Did you guys see the Amazon echo?
The Amazon echoes really something and there's been some really really great parodies and I want to play one of my favorite Amazon echo parodies
For you, it's pretty fantastic
What are you doing there? What is it? Is it for me? It's for everyone
Is it on? It's always on
Can it hear me right now? It can hear you from anywhere in the room. I've put wrapping paper on your shopping list
So what day is it?
Today is Thursday, November 13th eight minutes starting now. I
Can play music answer questions get the news and weather create to do this
Much more
Wow introducing Amazon echo she's listening. I wonder why they didn't just call it echo
creepy, yeah
Everyone's being harsh on it, but it's like it's kind of interesting. Yeah, I thought it I actually
Was kind of impressed like it doesn't look like it has a guy over ambitious feature set. No. Well, it's pretty
Pretty I mean it so who doesn't want Jarvis, right? Everybody wants everybody wants to be Tony Stark with Jarvis
Everybody wants the enterprise computer in their house
Obviously, I want to be in my studio and I want to say
Obviously, I want to be in my studio and I want to say, you know
Alexia or computer or Jarvis or whatever
Whatever it is, you know set the temperature in the other room to 75 degrees turn the TV to this channel and you know
Whatever and by the time I walk out there the TVs are ready to go and stuff like that
Obviously that would be amazing. But this thing what does this do the Google now can't do and it's always with you in every single
Great. No, it's not about that. It's about that being a device that does that
I don't know of any because I went around I looked yeah, as soon as I saw it
I thought I don't really want Amazon's thing. I'd rather have the Google one, but I looked around it's like wait a minute
There is none. Yeah, it's really about my device. It's a
culture phone
I
Understand where you're coming from, but there's no sit-in-house device that I can just sit down
Yeah, that's
Well a tablet
Yeah, but you know something you can plug in and use and kind of just have stand there as a little piece
I've got yeah, I've got a couple of couple of questions
The first is is this available in the US now and has anyone got one it is available. I believe I
Know I don't leave. Okay
I don't feel like buying one. So I didn't even bother
Yeah, you have to go and sign up on the list and then they'll let I think it was a hundred people of
Hundred or so. I can't remember
As anyone as anyone in here got an Amazon fire TV
Now that I will probably be getting for the studio in a little while. I have a few
Friends who told me they are pretty good, but I don't have that they're not just they're not just pretty good
They're damn storming amazing
Yeah, but I was gonna say one of the features on the Amazon TV is voice recognition and it makes it makes the Google voice
Recognition look like amateur hour. It is absolutely amazing. How can that be because what I don't know, but it's so good
Well, no, I mean think about what Google does to get their voice
Yeah, that is a shame if if Amazon
I mean, where would Amazon Amazon doesn't have millions of voice samples a day. Where's Amazon getting this from?
Alone is creepy because that means it's gotta be the fire tablets or no, maybe they're just licensing nuance
Maybe it's because so many people have the fire phone
But we've handed the remote around in the house between different people who've got different voice cadence
So different sexes and this thing just works every single time never misses a beat
It's absolutely brilliant daredevil and says he seems to know it though. What is it?
They have two things. First is they have actually very good machine learning algorithms, which they already use
to know what to buy and
They've been investing actually hiring on that department. Okay for a while. It's in-house
And the there's I'm not sure if it's totally in-house, but they hired people at least
And during these last year, they've been hiring all like a lot of people in this area machine learning algorithms and natural language processing
Okay, and they also have another service they do is something like
Actually persons go in surveying something. I'm not sure on the specifics, but it's some sort of service that it's to
Get people to audit sites and things like that
So I'm figuring that the process of getting some data from them and shouldn't be too hard. Hmm. Yeah
Actually, it's the problem with the actual natural language processing now isn't really getting samples anymore. It's actually
You know being able to
Have an algorithm that can understand. Yeah
I was just gonna say that the Amazon voice recognition is excellent
And whilst Amazon might understand
My buying habits and preferences because it's basically a narrow field of science fiction titles when I hand the remote to my wife
Who's into romantic comedies it picks up and understands everything she's asking for just fine
You know, I suppose in that sense if they know maybe the context is movie titles
Right that really narrows the scope
Because because it's it's movies television music apps and a whole load of other stuff
I'll tell you the only the only trick that Amazon have missed and this is the one thing about the Amazon fire TV that I
Really irritates is that they've that they've walled off this brilliant feature of voice search
from all of the other providers
So you
Yeah
Exactly, so you can
And you can install Netflix, but when you go and ask it to go and search for the walking dead
Yeah, it will only search Amazon
It won't go to any other places and that's that and that is just such a fail because you can see why Amazon are doing it
But they're doing it for all the wrong reasons. Oh, of course they are but they're gonna be very successful at it. Yeah, but
Everything else about it is is it's just brilliant. It's it's
Replaced our Roku in the front room. Yeah, that's what I was thinking too is it might be our Roku
And and it's actually a half decent gaming machine as well as you know, I'm not much of a gamer
So I'm probably not a good reference candidate here
But I play games on my Amazon fire TV now and as far as I'm concerned, it's the best thing I've ever had so
Wimpy once we get into the show a little bit
We got a little something we're gonna tell people about I don't don't say anything but a little something something. Yeah
All right. We'll do that a little bit in the show
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's loaded with protein and which is a very grateful
Happy Veterans Day to all the vets in the audience. My name is Chris and my name is Matt
Hey there Matt, happy Veterans Day to all the vets like we say and Matt. Happy Tuesday to yourself
And happy Tuesday
I know I feel like such a slacker on this this is like the day of the year that I feel like the biggest slacker
Ever doesn't matter how hard I work or how many hours I feel like today. I've been a slacker
So I went out and to celebrate I got I got one of those monster breakfasts
Where it's so much breakfast that you don't eat for pretty much until dinner and I'm still good. I got steak and eggs Matt. Oh
It was nice. Oh Matt. Oh, it was a really there's just there's Tuesdays have been good eat days
I guess so I'm ready to go
You know, hopefully
Hopefully we will avoid the flames in today's episode. We're gonna follow up on the Firefox challenge run through some of the
experiences and challenges that I had
We've got something really fun coming up towards the end of the show and we're also gonna discuss this whole gnome
Versus Groupon over the trademark where that's at right now what Groupon's been saying and how much damn money
The gnome foundation has raised a lot of stuff plus we've got a ton of great feedback
Going on in today's episode. So I think probably the best thing to do is arm ourselves with knowledge that knowledge supplied directly
Thanks to cranial implants that are connected to mumble time appropriate greetings mumble room
I
Thought let me eat at that amazing place nearby the studio. Yeah. Ellie's yeah. Oh gosh. I love that place
It's it's so good. It's so good and like all the people there and I'm like, I'm the only guy
We're not I don't know everybody's name. It's like cheers up in that joint and only it's breakfast
Yeah, it's great
Yeah. Alright, so let's start with let's start with some follow-up emails just a quick one
I'll leave the details in the show notes
But Ben wrote in with sort of one of the best write-ups on how to fix the NVIDIA
V-sync issue that we were seeing or that we had an email about last week
We had a few solutions a Ben had one where you just toss an export line into your dot profile
File and then that will take care of it and he says I love the show
I just wanted to chime in on the game v-sync issues that David from Alabama was experiencing in Linux on plug 65
Basically, he fixed his v-sync issues by forcing the unity compositor to v-sync for him
And he's looking for a way to do the same in gnome
this is not the way to go every time someone suggests using Compton or turning off unit directs full-screen or
Using another way to force the compositor during games. I scream in frustration
You're losing out on a ton of performance and you're increasing input latency in games
Which makes playing twitch games like counter-strike global offensive darn near impossible
So he's got a command in there. You can put in there that I should take care of it
If you're out there having some tearing issues
On video games. Yeah, so thank you Ben for we had a bunch of good responses to now
No, you're in here on your quote-unquote cheap
Podcasting Linux rig right now, right? I am. Okay. Well, I think we'll start this
I'll toss this question to you and then we'll get everybody's input. But here's the here's our first
sort of like I we're putting it actually in the show coverage of
USB headphones on Linux we get this question all the time. We talk about it on the pre-show live stream all the time in the
Mumble room, but now we're gonna get it right here wiggle waffles writes in says hi all I'm absolutely horrible
I have I've had a horrible time troubleshooting tech issues with my mom's c720 running Ubuntu gnome 1404
She now I do it over the phone and she needs a USB headset to make Skype calls while traveling searching the web for Linux compatible
Headphones has proved totally useless and of course manufacturers don't include any such info in their product descriptions
Matt mentioned some arcane sound controller name on last regarding this issue, but I have no idea what headphones they were
Or what type of controller headphones you wouldn't have in them. So any help would be appreciated
I'm looking for something low-cost and basic for Skype calling so no high-end suggestions, frankly
I've decided I'm never installing Linux on a family members computer again because once you install Linux
Your own you're the only tech support they have oh I see his point he says he goes on to say that there's also always
That one hardware feature that doesn't seem to work which is frustrating for him and that they need that has no Linux equivalent
The only success in this area though is he moved his dad to a Linux machine with email web and nothing else and it works
For him, so I suppose it depends on the use
So now he's in a spot where he hasn't been able to success. I think he needs to work on his Google foo
Because there is there are some threads out there for good headsets Matt. What are you wearing right now? Do you know?
It's a pellet
Yeah, I never pronounced this right but a platronics I have you know other Mike set up to the other computer
But on this one specifically now, I have a headset that I got a goodwill for $3. That'll work
I'll send him. I mean hell it's it's not hard to find if it's USB and it goes on your ears. It works
Yeah, that's why that's the big secret is it pretty much works. All right Colonel Linux. You've got your cheap rig there
Can you tell us a little bit about your setup and what kind of Linux any if any you compatibility issues you ran into right?
So my experience is the same essentially almost every USB audio interface. I've used recently
Works there was one exception. That was quite a while ago. I
Plantronics works really really well. In fact, that's what's used in the spaceship
So obviously they know something or two about making headsets, but I've also found that Logitech like the 8 390 for example
They're like 20 bucks Best Buy office max carries them
Amazon of course has them Amazon Prime and then my latest thing because this question keeps coming up is I want decent audio quality
what was the cheapest I could put together a
System that is totally Linux compatible. So you take it out of the box you plug it in no configuration. No, no compiling drivers
No downloading anything. I just wanted to work out of the box. How cheap could I do that and
Now mind you this is not meant for putting in your bag and traveling, right?
This would be if you want to get a little bit better audio quality than you get from USB headset
but I was able to whittle it down to
Just under 200 bucks and I have another microphone on order that's gonna come in and I'm gonna see if I can get it down
to about 150
But I think for for $200 and I'm talking on it right now
I think I think this sounds really good and that gets your USB interface that gets you a mixer get your microphones headphones and a microphone
That's a full Linux audio podcasting rig, which I think we should do a full segment on to be honest
I guess we should but a wimpy you sound pretty good today and you're on a new headset, right? What did you get?
I am well, I asked the question last week because I had a massive audio fail
And I went away and did a bit of research so this week I bought myself
Logitech h800 headset and it's not the cheapest and I'll explain why I used it
First of all in terms of Linux support
It's a wireless headset and mic all built-in with some buttons on the side for volume control and muting and track skipping and stuff
Like that all those all those media keys work
So it's wireless. It has a USB port plug that you put in your USB that shows up on your machine and you just go
So you're using Bluetooth Bluetooth?
It's both so it has two buttons on the headset one to use the USB dongle
Okay, which is how I'm using it now plugged into my Linux workstation to do mumble
And then you just go into your mixer and just say what your mic is and what your headsets are and all that works
But it also has Bluetooth. So you switch the headset to Bluetooth mode and then you compare it with your tablet and your phone
So this device now does all of my audio needs
So you can use it for your computer or to listen to a podcast from a phone or music or something exactly
Yeah, if I'm sitting downstairs and I want to watch a bit of BSG on my tablet
I just put the headset on pair it with the tablet and off I go. So what do you do for the mic?
What's the mic using? Is it the mics built-in? It's built into the headset support pull down integrated mic
Okay. Wow, that is a really cool. It says logic H 800 H 800
Yeah, and there's a there's slightly cheaper models as well, but I quite like this one because of the versatility
We've been able to use it with multiple devices. How do you charge it?
It's a micro USB charger and and so when you plug the receiver in just shows up to Linux as a USB sound card
It does sweet nice recommendation good fine wimpy
Okay, this is something I think about a lot and we're gonna we're gonna get into this discussion around Firefox and Chrome and
And you know, it's one of the things I've noticed a lot in my switch for the week is when something doesn't work, right
you know, there's a lot of different suggestions that come at come at a person and
I I feel like there's a lot of parallels between when we have people switch to Linux and things don't go right for them and
How we respond to that and how when I switched to Firefox and things didn't go right and how people have responded to that
I see a lot of parallels there
so I've been thinking a lot about how what I've just gone through reflects how we handle newcomers to Linux and
This first email or this next email that we're gonna get to sort of follows that that lat theme that we're gonna be talking about
Later today, so mount agent. I think is how you say it
Rodin or mount tangent. I'm not sure says on Sunday show Chris and Matt
We're reminiscing about the good old days of comp is and how the desktop cube and rad flame effects
We're pretty good at starting conversations and getting people to try out Linux
I'm wondering what features are beloved OS is you found to be the most pervasive or I'm sorry persuasive
to new Linux users
To be clear these would be outside the good well-reasoned arguments for switching
He says you can believe in the open source philosophy all day long
But willing to make the leap well sometimes a little shiny helps with that
That's what I'm asking about mine would largely be about Mac users looking at Linux since I work primarily with that user base
I'll second the desktop effects thing as an ongoing on and off again KDE user
I also find that Katie's incredible level of customization cuts both ways with this for some
It's a major draw for others
It's intimidating Mac users seem to have really enjoyed Cairo doc again with the flame effects before iOS and seven and eight
The ability to plug in iOS devices and read external storage was a big hit for them, too
Oh and hilariously for Mac users
Snapping the tiles of the windows, you know, so when you snap a window to the edges, they love that
I still can't understand why Apple doesn't do that in Mac OS
So he says what other shiny features of Linux say be at a desktop environment or otherwise
Do you show folks to start them down the road to switching the Linux?
Multiple desktops multiple desktops is a great one. Of course Windows 10 is getting that finally and Mac OS has spaces
Yeah, but it's it's not nowhere near as good as like, um, I run Cinnamon. I mean I have
10 desktops. Wow all hockey. Wow
Xerox, what do you show them a gnome that you really seems to grab their attention?
If somebody is watching me use my machine and I'm using gnome 3 the first thing they notice is when I
Mouse over to the top left hot corner and everything kind of backs out and I get a nice everything gets out of my way
That kind of thing activity overview, right? They get all over that stuff. Yeah
Yeah, well though when you go to activities overview all the windows you have
Yeah, that's a good one that's a good I also you know what one I find really sweet for Mac users
Which is just hilarious that the Mac doesn't have this. I know I just like when you click the when you click the
Clock in Mac OS it doesn't drop down a calendar like
This is 2014. How do you not? So anyways, so on gnome, you know when I drop down the calendar on gnome
Like I always show them like yeah, and it syncs with my own cloud server and puts all my appointments in there
So that's something that the gnomes got going for it. That's it's pretty nice for the shiny features, too
I it depends on who your audience is right because different people find different things to be shiny
Some people find the ability to boot off of a USB live
Thumb drive and recover your system a shiny feature. Some people think that's not so also the desktop cube. Yeah, you could always
Yeah, yeah, yeah
well
So if you have any ideas leave us some feedback
On what the shiny thing is go go put compass back on your rig or if you've got
A unity go turn on the compass settings manager and turn on the fire if you're writing plasma, you can it's native in Kadewin. Yeah
All right, RA writes in with our last email today says hey JB
With fedora 21 when it does finally come out in December
Probably you guys should review it
I know you will but there's just so much great stuff in there gnome 3.14 system D DNF butter a fart better butter butter
She's for easy for me to say Wayland and all of the new core apps and there's some extra dev tools in there, too
I was I was able to set up my C and C++ and Java environments with just five clicks and
Everything is butter smooth. So this is the first time I've got run and a gnome running under Wayland actually and it's quite good
All the apps I have run nicely probably though with X Wayland now that I think of it
I should look I would love to be in the mobile room when you guys review it would that be possible?
Yes, so stay tuned. We will win fedora 21 comes out have a review and we will probably do the whole comprehensive thing
Where we start the review in Linux action show and we're planning to do some pretty solid follow-up in that following weeks unplugged
The mumble rooms open
So RA you would always be welcome to join us
Yeah from time to time at least so
Haven't kicked you yet. Yeah. All right. So I want to talk about the Firefox switch
I think that's something we should probably get to plus. It's also the 10-year anniversary of Firefox before we get to that though
I'd like to thank digital ocean
They're our first sponsor this week head over to digital ocean comm right now and use our promo code
Unplugged in November when you check out to get a $10 credit now digital oceans only five dollars a month for their droplets
So that's gonna get you a droplet for two months for free to try them out now
Why would you go over to digital ocean my friends?
I will tell you because they rock it's simple cloud hosting and they're dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way to spin up
A cloud server. I got an email today from Jason who got started in 33 seconds
But they say on average probably get going about 55 seconds or so and pricing plans start at five dollars per month
Their pricing structure is very logical. It incrementally goes up you get all of the more of the things
It's very clearly laid out. They even have hourly pricing if you just need to do some testing
but for five dollars you're gonna get 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte of transfer connected to
Tier one bandwidth at some of the world's most amazing data centers you can see some of the awesome pictures on their Instagram feed
I'm super jelly. It's one thing
I really miss about working in IT is the really awesome data centers
And they have locations in New York San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam and London multiple data centers you can do private networking
It's really sophisticated stuff, and they manage it all with this dashboard. It is
Amazing the dashboard is super intuitive the control panel is
One of these things that I I wish I could just take it and like make it my idea because I would I would just take
This alone and make this the product and I would become super rich
That's how incredible is and this is just part of DigitalOcean
And they wrap up all of these great features like the ability to do one-click application deployments
Or if perhaps you want to do something like DNS management or a backup or a one-click install of GitLab
You can do all of that right from the dashboard
It's super slick and when you're over there use our promo code
Unplugged November to get a $10 credit and try it up for a couple of months for free and
DigitalOcean is also looking for folks to write tutorials will pay up to $200
So if there's something you're an expert on go write tutorial for me
You might get paid they have editors that will work with you in fact
They even have an open editor position right now for those tutorials
So you could you might be able to get a job over DigitalOcean too if you want to edit some tutorials
That'd be pretty cool. So go over to DigitalOcean.com and use the promo code Unplugged November when you check out try them out
It's pretty great. I've got I got cray-cray droplets. I got so many droplets now that Rekai has got droplets on my account
That's I got Rekai's got droplets now. How cool is that right?
And he's doing you better watch out though because I think he might be using it to develop Skynet
So you probably want to get on his good side
DigitalOcean.com use the promo code Unplugged November when you check out and a huge thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring Linux Unplugged
Okay, so let's start off by saying happy 10th anniversary of Firefox right version like 1.0 came out 10 years ago
They had a big old ad didn't they have it didn't isn't that am I right?
They bought a big ad in like the New York Times or something. I think so. Yeah
If I remember correctly it is pretty cool, and they as part of that
They've released a new developer version of the browser Aurora
They've taken the Aurora name and now it's sort of like it's a development release with a bunch of tools and a new theme
I download and tried it out last night
They also introduced a new feature in Firefox called forget since they've having to go into an entire
Private session you can just forget the last hour or 24 hours or whatever five minutes of your browsing sessions kind of neat
They're also launching project Polaris a privacy initiative and to kick that off
They're starting with a massive boost to the Tor relay network to give Tor more capacity
And they're pledging to make security management simpler and more straightforward in
Firefox so a pretty cool 10th anniversary
for Firefox
So last week well, I don't remember exactly even how it went down on the pre-show
We were like it somehow it came up that I run Chrome at chromium. I should say I don't actually run Chrome
Because it's just a little bit more of a pain in the ass to get on ours
So I run chromium and I'm I I like it a lot as far as a browser goes it has issues
I think it's too resource intensive
And I'm also not a huge fan of some of the some of the ways that Google seems to use it to push an agenda
This is super nitpicky, but like today on all my computers
I fired up Chrome for the first time in a week, and it's kind of like a welcome back
It's like all my computers are spamming me to donate to ebola now
It's a good cause
But like my browser should not be used as a platform for Google to deliver me messages like that right and I'm not super comfortable
With that kind of thing and that's happening in chromium
And the other thing about it is I don't like the ie
Factor that Chrome is starting to enjoy
You know you're seeing new services that launch that require Chrome
I think we probably at least all of us have seen that at least once Google's own inbox product that they just launched only works
in Chrome
So these these are some of the reasons. I also am a big fan of the Mozilla foundation
I like that they push forward an open web platform
And I think that they're you know and as far as their interest are more in line with end users interest than Google's probably are
So I'm a fan of Firefox all around. I mean I have used Firefox
Literally since the day the project was born right? I mean I I remember before there was a Firefox
I remember after Firefox. I mean I'm really a big fan of Firefox
I don't think you gave it enough never a chance
So I mean I literally I mean I remember I remember when 1.0 shipped. I clearly remember the day
And it was a really big deal because it took a very long time
It felt like to get there at least back then it was a huge it was a huge huge deal. Yeah
Yeah, yeah, and this is really it was a big deal
and this was really before people talked online like in like social in like a social way like there was message forms and and
BBS's and there was like there was discussion forums
But there wasn't like we don't have like this instant buzz about things like we have
Today where like the Gnome Foundation can raise like a ton of money in like 24 hours like we don't have that level of connectivity
But even back then we were all buzzing about Firefox 1.0. Oh, yeah, and it was like a horribly ugly
GTK application back then to super ugly really bad, but you know what rocked it loved it
It was the best browser ever it really was it was so much better in the Internet Explorer for a long time
Yeah, I know but at some point I I switched over to Chrome
You know just to try it out, I guess and I found myself pretty happy and I found extensions that work really well for me
On the pre show though people like Chris. Why are you using Chrome?
You should switch over to Firefox and everybody ganged up on me
And I finally caved right as the show started and said alright
I'll try Firefox out for a week and a few other folks joined me on the challenge
And we'd have some of them on the show here today and in fact
We also heard from just people in the audience that were taking the challenge now whom in the chat room Matt
Managed to go out and collect the moments
That throughout the whole week
I've been using Firefox and throughout the whole week different moments on air
My browser has crashed on me and left me stranded in the middle of the show
Whom was polite enough to go out and collect some of those for us
So I'll start with probably the one that was the most egregious. We're paying the bills
We're about to watch Kyra's app pick and Firefox crashes on us
Here's the clip that I get from the ladies who just want to hear my voice. Oh, yeah, let's find out here we go
No, you cannot speak to Kira Longfield
No, I don't need duck cleaning
I'm Kyra in this thing's app of the week
The app was so so awesome
It's not Kyra's fault. It's totally Firefox crashing on me. Hold on let's play it again. Go Kyra go!
Right so that okay. Alright, so there was a there was crash number one
Here it was crash number two in the same episode and he launched a user-friendly system based on arch
And I want to play a little bit of his Kickstarter video from that effort so that way for some of you who might
Oh, Firefox is killing me!
Seriously?
Theoretically, oh man, so the Firefox crashes right there as I'm trying to seek in the video again
You might notice a theme here. It was another flash video now. I actually haven't seen the rest of these clips yet
I don't remember these but here was another example of Firefox crashing on air
Hey Firefox!
How do you people use Firefox?
Look at how it's rendering my Google Plus page!
It's great as long as you're not doing anything with Google
Look at oh, yeah, that's right. That was when it totally that's when it totally mis-rendered the Google Plus page when I was trying to
Talk about system 76. Alright, so then finally somebody catches me. I show my extension. I have a lot of extensions
Oh my god
Dude, how is your browser even run?
Fucking far, far, far. But here's the thing!
Alright, so I did have a lot of extensions. Just a couple, just a couple.
But yeah, so there, so they could crash, they could also crash during Tech Talk today on me a couple of times
So it's been a pretty rough week. Not only did it, not only was stability an issue
But also just the same extension selection wasn't really available. Now, does that mean Firefox is horrible?
I don't think so, but I don't know like a lot of people said oh Chris, it's your extensions or Chris is this or that
And I was you know going through I just thought to myself well doesn't at the end of the day really matter how the browser
Handles a catastrophe? Like if even if an extension craps the bed, well bad on that extension
But even worse on the browser for totally dumping out, right? Because that's not what Chrome does, right?
So I don't know. So I don't want to get too far into it. First, I want to ask Popey. Popey, I know you've been working with it for a week
You're still in the Firefox challenge mode right now. How are you doing? Are you going to stick with it for another week?
So to be fair, it's worth noting that we've been shipping Firefox since Ubuntu 4.10 which was 10 years ago
And we shipped Firefox 0.99 in our first release of Ubuntu and it's been the default browser for every single release of Ubuntu since then
Okay. However, I have flipped between various browsers for years and I think we came to a mutual decision last week to
Both try a week of Firefox because we've both been using Chromium or Chrome mostly. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, I have everything installed even Midori
From time to time I use that for like a Gmail login or something. Right. And so and I've always had Firefox since I've never uninstalled
I'm not one of those people who are zealous and will like remove any apps that I don't use by default
But so I've been using Chromium and there's a couple of things that I liked about Chromium and Chrome that I've been using
So I switched to Firefox a week ago and actually whilst I've been bitching and moaning
Two things that have annoyed me most was the fact that it slowed down dramatically and ate all my CPUs and all my RAM
And I'm on a laptop with an i7 CPU and 16 gig of RAM and it ate it all up with and I wasn't I only have two extensions installed
And at the time when it ate all my RAM I had like half a dozen tabs open
So I'm not normally in Chrome or Chromium I will have 50 60 maybe 100 tabs open and if it starts eating my CPU
I'll be like, OK, I'm being a bit of a dick with my browser now and I'll close some of the tabs
But or Chromium will do that for me and it will start killing off tabs. Yeah. When it has a bad day. Did you have any crashing? Fair enough
Did you have any crashing? Firefox? Yeah. Nothing like you had. I had a couple of occasions this week where my entire laptop rebooted
And I've not had that for some time, but I can't pin that on Firefox. I think it's actually Intel video driver problem
And I have filed that and that's an upstream bug. Right. But the problems I've had is more slowness and eating all my resources
However, I think it's mostly down to the fact that I tend to leave my laptop running
I rarely restart the browser. I just shut the lid, suspend it, wake it up and carry on. And I think on my system
Firefox doesn't like being left running for a very long period of time, like days. All right. So Wimpy, what was I know you kind of had a similar path
What did you do exactly? Did you were you a Chromium user that tried Firefox for a while or vice versa?
The other way around. So actually, I adopted Chrome really early on. So very early on in sort of the alpha beta stage in around 2008
And that was because it had a really nifty JavaScript JIT compiler at the time, which we needed to test some prototype code on for work
So for work, I worked with aircraft and aircraft data and we wanted to plot thousands of samples of aircraft data in a browser
And you simply couldn't do that back then and suddenly Chrome turned up and it changed the game
So ever since then, I've been using Chrome because I started using it and I went through the growing pains and I sort of stuck with it
But about a year ago, I noticed Chrome rendering popular websites in strange ways
So I started using Firefox and then I just switched back to Firefox. So I've been using Firefox exclusively for about 12 months
And to be honest with you, other than the rendering problems that I'd had with Chrome previously, I couldn't really tell anything between the two browsers
But I thought I'd take a closer look as you were doing this this week and I've had a chat with Popey in the week
And running Firefox and Chrome side by side, what I definitely noticed is Chrome is significantly faster than Firefox
And I didn't believe Popey when he was telling me the subjective metrics about how much faster it was
So I went off and I did it properly. I know, right? I'm a big fat liar
Well, I just I'm just skeptical by nature, I suppose. But I went away and did some tests
And whilst you do these browser benchmarks that kind of mean something, if you actually run the two browsers side by side
You can see the difference. And it was when I could see the difference in the rendering time and the smoothness and the transition
And it was quicker and I just felt like I was in better control of the browser
Right. And I also feel like the UI responds faster, like tabs open and close faster
Like it's not struggling to to open that tab up if there's something else going on in the browser
Sometimes it's like Firefox is struggling with that and like there's only one or two worker threads
Yeah. Yeah. So well, you know, Chrome and Chromium have some tricks that they play that make it look faster than it really is
I think so, yeah. That's fine. I don't I don't care if they're tricks. They're tricks that fool my eyes
It's not just what you see when I ran the various browser benchmarks
Chrome, you know, on my system was was beating Firefox two times over every time
Really? Was that from a startup or after you had a bunch of stuff?
Sorry, there's a yes. So from startup go to the same benchmark site, run the benchmark and post the results
So the conditions were the same. OK, gotcha.
So here's a couple other things, just anecdotal, just my experiences
So day one didn't go super great. Firefox sync for some reason, just go figure, right?
Didn't actually sync on the I had a new install, set up the browser, logged into Firefox sync on the browser the night before
Went about, did some web reading, probably used the browser for about an hour, closed it
Came back, moved my laptop, brought my bonobo to the studio, opened it up, launched Firefox like around 8.30, then went on air around 9
So and then I go to start the show and realize that none of my bookmarks had synced, none of my extensions had synced
Yeah, and that was a little like, oh, man, day one I got burned by sync
But I was able to if I but then so to fix it, I had to delete my profile and then create a new profile and set up sync again
Same account, then sync just worked. Not a huge deal, but what I walked away from is when I would run into issues
So a couple of things would happen. People would, well actually, I guess I have a clip of it here
I might, I'm gonna play this clip from last, it might be a little ranty, but I'm gonna play it from the heat of the moment
And I'll see if this covers what I was just about to say
Oh, you need to be able to copy that as HTML? Just install
So how the conversation literally started was, Chris, just install an extension to have it have the same features as Chrome
You need that thing that Chrome can do? Just install
So the conversation starts, is Chris, just install an extension
And now, now the conversation is Chris, you got too many extensions, what do you expect to happen?
So I can't use the browser because I don't have an extension
And then once I have too many extensions, now the problem is I got too many extensions
And it's literally gone from Tuesday to Chris, install an extension
Literally, people are so determined that I install extensions that they literally, between Tuesday and today, developed extensions for me
Created extensions, I've installed those extensions, they're great, they make, they add
But now it's Chris, you got too many extensions
Now on the other side of that, Chrome is a big bloated turd biscuit
I mean, it's like, it literally, it just starts processes to piss me off
I hate Chrome, I hate it with a passion, I want to light it on fire and burn it
That's one of the things, I don't like Chrome, I don't like it
I literally, I use a little bit of Midori, I use some other browsers
But generally for just casual, I'm doing random stuff on the internet
I use Firefox because it's great for me
Alright, so I got to install GST
So what I found was, I found people were super willing to constantly volunteer things I should do
Like a lot of going to your about config and change this
Enable hardware acceleration, disable hardware acceleration, install this extension
Oh yeah, that extension that you needed, well that only goes in the status bar
Well the status bar doesn't actually exist anymore
So now you have to install an extension that brings back the status bar
And then once you bring back the status bar, you can customize the status bar
And take the button out of the status bar and move it up to the menu bar
And then uninstall that extension
And then go install this extension so that way, it's like it was ongoing
And then when I started having stability issues
Which were clearly related to the Adobe Flash plugin
Not related to the other extensions, clearly related to the Adobe Flash plugin
But immediately it's, well you have too many extensions, you need to do this
You're doing this wrong, and it sort of immediately went hostile
And what I started thinking about was, people that are switching to Linux
They have these problems in a much broader context
With all kinds of little pain points when they switch over to Linux
And I also see the same kind of, well what do you mean it's not working for you?
Well then you're doing it wrong
And I got emails where people critiqued my technical literacy
Because it's not that Firefox was having issues
It's not that it wasn't properly handling when the Flash plugin crashed or whatever was happening
What the problem was, is I wasn't technically literate to use the browser
And I didn't care enough about open source
I probably got nearly a hundred comments to that regard
And it's ridiculous
And not only is it ridiculous, it's antithetical to everything that I used to know about Fox
Anyways, I want people to just consider it
I think what we have to get better at, and I know this is maybe a soapbox of mine
But I think what we have to get better at is acknowledging that everything has strengths and attributes to it
Like I started this segment talking about what I like about Firefox
The history I have with it, and why the Mozilla Foundation is great
I also use Firefox on every computer I have
But my primary get work done browser has to remain, in my opinion, Chrome
And I think the bigger problem here is
Is that what we are really beginning to see
Is the division that Mozilla is actually up against
Which is not Firefox versus Internet Explorer
Or Firefox versus Chrome
It is Firefox versus every single other WebKit browser on the market
Because application developers are writing WebKit first
They're not necessarily even writing Chrome first
They're writing WebKit first
Then they might, specifically, maybe write Chrome first
And that's what Firefox's real challenge is
At their ten year mark going forward now
Is their lunch is getting eaten by WebKit
WebKit is the winning team right now
And Firefox needs to have an answer to that
And I understand Electrolysis is a thing that's coming
That's going to make Firefox super more amazing
And it's not going to crash as much
But honestly, to me, it feels too late
And it makes me sad a little bit
It doesn't mean it's going away
It doesn't mean it's a bad browser
It doesn't mean it's not going to get way more awesome
It doesn't mean that the Mozilla Foundation isn't incredible
It doesn't mean you're a bad person for wanting to use Firefox
And I'm a bad person for wanting to use Chromium though
To be fair, at Google they're actually removing the WebKit-centric stuff
Because they don't want people to do that
So that's why Blink has removed all of the WebKit CSS commands and stuff
That are specific to WebKit
Because people were doing that and breaking stuff in Opera and Firefox at the time
And Google didn't want to create breakage
They wanted standardization
So Blink has that stuff gone
Very good
By the way, I looked into
Actually, Rekai hooked me up with the info
But I read through the info on Chromium versus Chrome
And it seems like Wikipedia maybe has one of the best breakdowns
There's several
Google even has their own Wiki page on it
But Wikipedia
So here's a couple of things
By the way, I'm a Chromium user
Chromium is an open source project
It's BSD licensed
There's other components that have different licensing
It's got a lot of little asterisks at the end of that
So that was the other thing
People were kind of jumping on me for using another open source project
Either way
There is a couple of things that Chromium does not have
That I think people should consider if they were going to try
The print subsystem apparently is different in the final Chrome version
In Chromium, it'll hand it off to your operating system
But in Chrome, they're using the entire Google print subsystem
Which ties in with the Google Cloud Print and all of that
Of course, no ACC built-ins
It's going to have to rely on your operating system codecs
The tracking is opt-in in Chromium versus opt-on, I guess, in regular Chrome
I might have that wrong, but it's definitely opt-in in Chromium
And no auto-update features
So you're going to have to rely on your package manager
Which I prefer to have my package manager do that anyway
So that's fine with me
And of course, the integrated flash
Sorry, what's got no auto-update?
Chromium doesn't use the Google updater
It uses your operating system's package manager
Like it should
Okay
And no built-in flash
No AAC, no built-in flash, no Google updater, and no Google Cloud Print
So from the Ubuntu point of view, those are both the same
They both come as Debian packages from an archive
Yeah, yeah
One comes from the Ubuntu archive, one comes from a Debian Google archive somewhere
It doesn't have the multimedia extension either
Oh, that's a good point
Yes, that's a good one
And also, it's being pointed out that no remote desktop either
Which is a great point there, Dublin
Yeah, go ahead
Chris, the reason you're getting hate for using Chromium is because you keep accidentally calling it Chrome
Well, I kind of use both
So I kind of interchange them depending
I mean, I primarily use Chromium on the majority
Because it's a little bit quicker to install on an Archbox
Yeah, and people tend to get a little bit funny about
Whenever I've said I'm using Chromium
The question that always follows is, do you mean Chrome?
Or if I say I'm using Chrome, they ask, do you mean Chromium?
It's like, no, I'm 42, I've managed to differentiate between Chrome and Chromium
If I'm talking about Chrome, I'll say Chrome
If I'm talking about Chromium, I'll say Chromium
But sometimes, you want to talk about both together
Because collectively, Chrome and Chromium are very similar code bases
I find it, yeah, to be pretty similar
But to me, what this was really revealing to
Was just how freaking important the web browsers become in my workflow
Not only do I use it to show most of the visuals in all of our shows
But the research and the pipeline of a lot of our media management
And all of it is just browser based now
Thankfully, I felt like at the end of this
If Chrome or Chromium went away tomorrow, I would be okay
I would make do, especially since the community was pretty awesome
And there was a couple of user extensions that were
You know, use Greasemonkey and then add a user script to that
And they wrote a couple of those for me to do markdown stuff
So I mean, there would be ways around it
So the thing I've learned about this
Is that there are people who are exceedingly passionate about Firefox
And they want me to have a good experience on Firefox
So rather than dismiss this whole experiment
And go back to using Chromium as I did
I'm going to stick with Firefox, I've removed Flash from my system
So I'm doing everything I can to avoid Flash based websites
Or Flash streaming video, which means your website actually, Chris
You need to provide an easy way for me to be able to watch the live stream
Without Flash, right? That's on you, okay?
Well, why don't you just grab the RTSP
Okay, I'll do that
Yeah, because there's not really an embeddable open source live stream solution
No, no, I don't mind not having an embeddable thing
I'd like a URL somewhere that I could paste into
I actually used a nice tool that one of the other guys in the mumble mentioned earlier
Called Livestreamer
But that didn't find any embeddable streams to watch from your page
Grab the RTMP link, or RTSP, I don't remember which one it is
Okay, I'll try that
And then if you have MPV or a VLC, but MPV is really great
You just do MPV and then the URL and it'll fire up
You know what we should do is like a short, like we have jblive.fm for the audio stream
I should do something like that for the
That would be a great idea, because then you can just tell people to go to it
I'll think about it, yeah, that's a good idea
Yeah, because that is a problem, and we get that comment all the time
And of course the whole website is all HTML5 video except for the live stream
And it's really, you can thank HLS and H264 for that
It's kind of like, sickingly enough, Flash is one of the best assemblers of HLS video on the market
As disgusting as that is
And you can throw it on a new iPhone 6 or a Nexus 5
And they will struggle to do as well of a job as Flash can do for whatever reason
Alan could talk to you all day about it
But it really comes down to the fact that the standards we use for video streaming right now super suck
But we've just kind of moved ahead with it
There's also a Jupyter Broadcasting XBMC add-on that you could use
Yeah, and if you watch on a Roku, there's a Jupyter Broadcasting app and the live stream is on that
And I could watch on my tablet or something else like that
That's not a problem, so I'm going to try and stick with Firefox
And I'm going to take advice from various people in the Mumble channel
Who've suggested ways in which I can debug the issues and make sure that I follow up stream
And ensure the experience is better for everyone else as well
So my thoughts would be I would go the no flash route for sure
But I can't because of some of the media management I have for JB
But I was thinking, I've tried running in Terminal and stuff like that to get some output
But I didn't really get anything very beneficial
But my thought was to experiment around a little bit more
Because I know exactly what conditions caused it to crash because I could repeat it over and over again
See if I can get it to do it and then maybe as a 10th birthday present to Firefox
I'll send off a few bug reports over the weekend
You're such a nice man
Hey, happy birthday guys, here's some bugs
Alright, so we've got to talk about, boy, oh my gosh
We've really got to get going because we have some really exciting stuff to talk about
Wimpy's going to share something awesome
And we've also, you know what, I don't think the Gnome Groupon thing will take too long
But we've got to talk about it just real quick
But before we do that, I want to thank Ting
Go over to linux.ting.com right now everybody
linux.ting.com, that'll take $25 off your first Ting device
Or if you have a Ting compatible device, they'll give you $25 credit
linux.ting.com, you don't know what Ting is?
What is the matter with you?
Ting is mobile that makes sense, no contracts, no determination fees
You only pay for what you use, it's a flat $6 for your line
And then whatever your usage is, that's what you pay
You want another phone? It's $6
You want another phone? You could be a baller like me
I've got three phones and I'm up here and I'm paying like $45
But then when I go out and I show the ladies all my phones
They're like, that's so impressive with all your phones
Why do you have so many phones?
And I tell them I have Ting
linux.ting.com, go check them out
No old customer service? Yeah, that's another perk
You don't have to wait for a human
You just call them up and they answer
You don't have a phone tree, you don't have to leave a voicemail
You don't have to know some sort of secret zero-smashing sequence to get to an operator
They just answer the phone
If you call them between 8am or 8pm on the east coast
It's great, and then they match it all up with a fantastic dashboard
And an awesome online community
But this week, I wanted to do something a little different
You know in LAS, we'll often do an app pick video
But you know, app picks shmat picks
This is Linux Unplugged, let's go deep into the development world
They have a video up of talking with Kerry
The behind the scenes interview with their lead web developer
And I want to play a little bit of it
Because I'm playing it in Chromium
My name is Kerry and I am the interface developer at Ting
My role at Ting is to develop and maintain any customer-facing side of our website
Including WordPress and Facebook
Usually we'll start with a discussion
Product management will come over or ask us if what they want is feasible
Or how much time it'll take
And I will give them an answer, it'll take 10 minutes or it'll take 6 years
Sometimes it will take 6 years
And they go off on their own and come up with the designs
And then they finally, when they give them to me
I set to work on making them a reality
Earlier this year we went responsive with our design
What this means is that when users browse our website
On a smaller screen like a phone or an iPod
They're going to see a different design than if they see it on a big screen like a desktop
We're making sure that users get the best possible experience on all device sizes
It feels really good to be able to be part of something that even our senior citizens can browse comfortably
Because I mean, a lot of senior citizens aren't that comfortable with the internet
And then we get comments from them saying, thanks for making it so easy
And that is a really rewarding part of this job
Linux.ting.com, go over there and start saving right now
They also have a savings calculator
I've been, not quite yet, but I am nearing the 2 year mark
It is approaching and the final savings will be over $2000 for me
So why not get started right now?
Linux.ting.com and a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged Show
Okay guys, let's talk, let's do a brief update
Because maybe the real story might actually develop by the time the Linux Action Show comes around
But you probably saw the headline today
The Gnome Foundation is attempting to raise some funds
To help defend Gnome's trademark against Groupon
Yeah, Groupon, the coupon company
They have raised $68,000 as of, well, pretty much this morning
68? 68,000 bucks?
Groupon has also, yeah, yeah, yeah
And Groupon's already responded saying, hey dawg, look, we're sorry, we don't want to use anybody's name
And after additional conversations with the open source community and the Gnome Foundation
We've decided to abandon our pending trademark application for Gnome
We've chosen a new name for our product going forward
So Gnome was this retail box thing that they were going to, so you could go buy coupons
Kind of a neat idea for Groupon
But Pope, you and I were talking about this on the Tech Talk pre-show today
Or actually during the show
Am I missing any details at this point or is that kind of the summary of where we're at?
That seems to be it, it's all over, let's start bashing System D again
Yeah, we're back to, yeah, exactly, yeah, okay
War's over, but it was fascinating to see the troops mobilized last night
So before I went to bed or something, I saw a tweet
And then by the time I got up, the Google Pluses and the tweets and the subreddit
Every subreddit had it in there, like it was full on fire this morning
When you say troops, you know, on a day like today where we're remembering real sacrifice
The real people have done
You are taking my own point I made earlier and using it against me
You are a jerk, sir, you are a jerk
I would not call those troops
Yes, I know, and that's kind of my point
Again, we were just, we were ready to go to war
We were ready to go to war, and they raised a ton of money
I even, I threw in 55 bucks, I was like, well alright, I like Nome
I'm really surprised it's as low as that
I really thought they'd have double that
So what happens with the money now?
It goes to making Nome better
Yeah, they already said that it's going to go to Nome
Anything that's left over, and since all of it's left over, all of it goes to Nome
I think that's worthy
Well that's great because I know they've had some financial troubles, right?
Isn't that a thing?
Oh yeah, they ended last year in the red
Well, I guess they just got a little revenue boost then
But I'm glad, I mean, I think it's
I think it's also, what it really demonstrates, legitimately, is the serious brand loyalty
I don't know if that's the right term to call it
But the, I mean, people came to Nome's defense in mass
And people, I think things have turned around for Nome
I think the public opinion is turning on Nome
Because people really, really seem to come out in defense of it
And we're ready to fight Groupon and calling them names
And Groupon really responded
So not only did they have their official blog post
But their senior lead engineer, I think that's actually his title, senior lead engineer
Went to his blog trying to explain that it was a misunderstanding
That they had been in communication with the Nome Foundation
And that they're willing to be flexible
They really scrambled
I'm not really familiar with
I've seen comments from the Nome side saying
We've been in conversation with them for months and it's only today
Kind of justifying the whole public hatred of Groupon and people deleting their Groupon accounts
I'm not convinced
I'm not convinced that it was entirely down to the Reddit army
And the various armies leaving comments everywhere that got this done
But I'm sure it was a contributing factor
Yeah
I'd like to think that Groupon got a telephone call from Karen Sandler
Where she implied she was going to put the smack down on them
In no uncertain terms
That's what I was thinking too
And they realized what they were up against
Or maybe the people at Groupon grew a pair
And realized that actually they were being dicks
And what they really needed to do was just not do the thing that they were doing
Didn't someone who works at Groupon used to be someone who worked at GNOME?
Oh, now this is a good rumor
Ryan Cameron
Or even more interesting maybe
Using this as a way to show that they now have a new product
Marketing
And everyone kind of knows that they have a point of sale system
You think that
All the truthers are out there
Yeah, I would say that's a pretty obscure marketing strategy
Yeah
It will work though
Everyone now knows what they have
And might actually check it out
Yeah, and I'm actually thinking it's kind of a good idea
Because I don't want to go sign up at Groupon
But if they had a kiosk where I could just do a one-time transaction
Well, maybe I might do that
I mean, I'm a cheapskate after all
They might even look at
People might even look at the GNOME desktop environment now as well
Holy smokes
Maybe they were in on it from the first time
It's a false flag trademark dispute
Operation promotion
I know, right
We've got to
Boy, if we're not careful
We're going to have to bust out the conspiracy bacon on this edition
Yeah, that's funny because that's exactly what Blue Phoenix was saying in the chat room a little bit ago
That there was
It did smell a little bacon-y to him
And I don't think so
I don't think they'd be that dishonest
No, I don't think so either
No, it's a
If they're not though
Kind of you need to question
If they're in conversation in months
Why do you add applications?
Doesn't make sense
Because lawyers do stuff without being told
Yeah, I could see that
Or maybe the negotiations weren't necessarily going the GNOME Projects direction
So they went public to show their serious commitment
I mean there could be all kinds of scenarios
Who knows
Okay
You guys are lovely
And just in huge good faith
Yeah, I suppose
All right
I can't hold it any longer
We've got to talk about something super exciting
Really, really happy
But really quickly we're going to thank Linux Academy
I've got a note from Anthony who is one of the guys that runs Linux Academy
And he said that they've gotten a ton of new signups from the Linux Unplugged audience
And the feedback's been unanimously awesome
And when I went to Ohio Linux Fest
Shook a lot of hands from folks that are taking courses at Linux Academy
And they've been really impressed
And they say one of the things that's kind of hard to understand about Linux Academy
Is you really grok how great it is
And how it really is a solution tailored for Linux users
By Linux users
And that is so key because there's a lot of online learning resources
And you really see the difference if you're trying to go for something in this space
Something about Linux or AWS or OpenStack and DevOps and Android development
They've really nailed this
Because that's what these guys do
That's their area
And they can really get it right
They are these users
They're sysadmins
Linux users
And educators that came together to create Linux Academy
You can go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
And get our special 33% discount on your quarter
It's a great service
And once you sign up you get access to all of the courseware
You get the downloadable comprehensive study guides
You get to take those online or offline
You can do the learning plans
You can say I have just this amount of time available
Plug it in there
They'll generate you a learning courseware on that
With reminders about quizzes, checkups
When you log in you choose your course
And it lays it all out for you
It maps it all out and it's super easy to manage
They have a good active community that can keep you going when you're having a low moment
And they have live streams where you can ask questions to the educators
Their labs spin up on demand when the courseware requires it
And they're adding new courses every single week
They've got a whole bunch more they just put out
And that's why you want to just keep going there all the time
Because you can keep going back and learn something new
See what scratches that itch
Bring yourself a little bit further in something you've been working on
I use it honestly
Just to see if some of the same old technologies that used to be a problem for me
Still are a problem
To see if I have maybe a new interest
Something I want to build for JB
There's all kinds of things
They also have group plans
So we can have folks in the Jupiter Broadcasting community
That work here that have to do something
Maybe we have them go over there
They can log in under the group course
It's all part of one set under one organization
It's really neat
They're adding stuff too
You've got to go check it out
Because I can't say what it is
But I've been given a little hint
And it really underscores that this is a product that's made by Linux users
For Linux users
And when you're trying to learn some of these things
That is the differential that really closes the gap
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
Go check them out
PHP
Android development
Ruby, Python, Linux, DevOps
AWS with scenario based training
They've got it all
R-Sync even
You need to go learn how to do your backups with R-Sync
They've got a course on that
I'm telling you
It's worth checking them out
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
So I was noticing on Google Plus
That Wimpy, you posted that you guys are getting a little attention over in Germany
In one of their newspapers
Or I'm sorry, it's a magazine, isn't it?
That's right
Yeah
Congratulations
Yeah, thank you for that
So there's a quarterly Linux publication in Germany
Called Linux Velt
I think that's how it's pronounced
It's got a circulation of about 50 to 60,000
And they're including DVDs
Yeah, and they have DVD cover disks
And for the 2015.01 edition
Which I think is out next week
Ubuntu Mate is the feature story
And the cover disk
That is so cool
And so that's not just the announcement though
You've been working on a little something
We talked about it kind of recently
And so I know you're getting near
I'm teasing it off a lot, Wimpy
What process are we about to go through right now?
Right, okay
So everyone probably knows that's listening to this
That Ubuntu Mate 14.10 was released a couple of weeks ago
And we've been preparing an Ubuntu Mate 14.04 release
And I'm actually ready to go through the keystrokes
To release it live now
So we're going to release the latest version
Which is based on 14.04
Right here on air
That's right
Let's do it
Right here on air
This is fun
So I've got my Terminator sessions open
And I've logged into my two Digital Ocean build servers
This is where I prepare the ISO images
I've already prepared the images
And I'm going to run the release scripts
And the release scripts build the WebC torrents
Actually make the ISOs from the SquashFS
Add the assets from the official Ubuntu CD releases
And then R-Sync them to my distribution servers
And we'll do that now
So off we go
Right, so that's the power of Digital Ocean
That's just shunted six gigabytes of data
Really?
Wow
We'll now just edit the release flag on the article
Now we'll run the deploy script
This is so exciting
I know, right?
I know
This is actually the geekiest thing I think we've ever done on the show
And I love it
So the deploy script basically takes all the markdown
That the site is generated from and turns it into HTML
So that's done
So now I go to my CDN
And I prefetch all of those images into the CDN
And that's done
And now I purge the blocks
And now I purge the blog index from my Cloudflare
And that just makes sure that the updates go through
And I think we're done
So you just witnessed an operating system being released live
So you pushed the whole website and everything in that
Yeah, there you go
So if you go to UbuntuMate.org slash blog
The article that you'll see now is the release notes from the article
UbuntuMate.org slash download
Yes, that should redirect I think
Because there's two bits in there
You know what, Wimpy?
You just earned yourself
Very nice, sir
Very nice
Thank you very much
Awesome
Wow
So I would just like to rattle off this
There's a few people I'd like to say thank you to
Some bloke called Alan Pope
Santa Sweers, who's one of the Mate developers who worked really hard on fixing the accessibility stuff
Mike Gabriel, who's a Debian developer
He helped an awful lot in this release
Gerard Alders, who provided one of the new backdrop images
Some bloke called Michael Tunnel
I don't know how you pronounce your name, but Rotten Corpse
He's one of the guys here
He did the new icon theme
Luke Velvich, Kendall Clark, Kyle Bruard and Rob White
Who represent various distributions that are focused towards the blind off partially sighted
Who helped fix all of the screen reading stuff
Wow, great you guys
And one of the things that's interesting is you were mentioning before
It's based on Ubuntu 14.04
But yet it actually has some maybe what you might call improvements or feature enhancements
Over the one based on 14.10, right?
Indeed
So Rotten Corpse has tweaked the theme for us
Which looks nicer
We've got a new wallpaper
We've fixed the multicast DNS
We've fixed policy kit privileges
The big feature items are we've added indicator support
So now you can add indicators into the Mate desktop
And they sit side by side with traditional tray applets as well
Wow, that's a win
You like that, do you?
I like that a lot actually
I'm just interested in how fast that blog post went out
Now what you need to be impressed with is how fast we just pushed 18 gigabytes of data around the internet
Yeah, as well
And that's all down to DigitalOcean
You said it would take about five minutes
It took about two minutes
Yeah, I was hedging it on me
But bungling it enough into redo bits
A couple of other bits we've added is
The Mint menu I've forked as the Mate menu which is available in this release
Because lots of people are after that
And I've actually done that for the X2GO guys
Because they want a menu where they can disable logout and suspend features
Because of remote workstations that doesn't make sense
I've also forked the Mint desktop utility as Mate tweak or Mate tweak
To just access some of the behind the scenes bits and pieces
And then what else have we done?
Accessibility, that's where we've spent a lot of time, fixing up accessibility
Oh yeah, this is a good one
We've ditched Totem as the default media player and placed it with VLC
Nice, very nice
We ran a community poll for that and that was unanimously voted for
So we've made that change
So I think Eric, you've got probably a popular question
Yeah, since it's based on 14.04 is this going to be basically an LTS as far as you can do it?
Yes, so we obviously don't have to maintain the base OS
Pope can probably tell you more about what goes on with that
But in terms of the PPA, because this is an unofficial release
This is built outside of Canonical's infrastructure
So there's no official support there
But in terms of the Mate desktop
I'll be supporting that through the PPA that's embedded into this build
And how long?
For the duration of the LTS
So all 5 years, right?
Yeah, and for anyone that's running 14.10 already
They will have seen some of these features automatically turning up in the updates of their Ubuntu 14.10 releases
Oh man, that is smooth
I've got to give you a major tip of the hat
What's the long term goal here?
This is obviously going to start developing a pretty passionate following I'd think
I'm already thinking this is the distro of choice for the studio production machines
That'd be good
To me it just seems like a slam dunk
I'm going to give this a download and try it out
But what's the long term?
Because this could become a pretty big job
It could become a big job
So the short term is for 15.04 now we want to get it as an official flavor
So all of that drama of me releasing just then I don't have to do
Somewhere there are monkeys in canonicals infrastructure doing it automatically
That's handy
So that's the plan
I've met with some of the Debian developers a couple of weeks ago
And they've agreed to work to the same time frame that Ubuntu is working to for 15.04
So we're not going to introduce Mate 1.10 in 15.04
We're going to do the Mate 1.10 development work in Debian experimental
And then bring that through in the subsequent release later in the year
Interesting
But initially let's get official
Following on from that we've got some serious interest from some large organizations
Who want to use Ubuntu Mate with the X2Go remote terminal services platform
So the desire to get this into Ubuntu and have it as an official flavor
Is a request from some third parties who want to see this happen
Well I think you've got the basis here for a distribution that's going to get a lot of loyal followers
And the timing is pretty good I think too
It's obviously serving a niche
It's so funny too for some reason basing this on 14.04 feels really right
Like a really smart long term play
And so from end to end it just seems like it's firing on all cylinders
So congratulations you guys and to everybody who's worked super hard on it
Thanks very much
And it's been well being tested by my mum and my wife as well
So you can be rest assured it works
Okay good
That's so awesome
Now see there's some QA for you I've got to say
Alright well very good
I just want a couple of notes
We're still looking for your runs Linux
You guys send them in throughout the week and I appreciate that
If you have a runs Linux it's even more awesome
It's either your own thing it could be
Or something you find
It's total perks if it's got video or a picture
I'd love that
That usually puts it towards the top of the list
Because those are always fun to look at
Send those over to linuxactionshow at jupyterbroadcasting.com
Or like all content that you think might be great for either Linux Unplugged or Linux Action Show
Submit them to our subreddit at linuxactionshow.reddit.com
And don't forget you can join us live jblive.tv
We do this here on 2pm on a Tuesday
Go to jupyterbroadcasting.com.calendar to get that converted to your local timezone
And I'll have links to the Matei stuff in the show notes
So go grab that
Also links to the Gnome vs Groupon stuff in the show notes
And a full break out of the differences between Chrome and Chromium
So if you were a little confused by our conversation about that
Because I know some of you are kind of coming into this and saying
Wait, there's a difference? Yes, there is a difference
And instead of just sitting here and rattling through all of them
I broke it all out in the show notes for you
So you can check that out
And I would be interested to know if anybody has decided to take a Chromium challenge
I heard from like two people
Besides also Wimpy now
So Wimpy you're the third person that took a Chromium challenge
And you are the third person that's sticking with Chromium
So I wonder if anybody else tried it and if it didn't go well for you
And what problems you ran into
Send us an email and maybe we'll do a follow up on that next week
Could be kind of interesting maybe
You know what, I admit, maybe I just am a wild man with the browser
Alright Matt, well that's going to wrap us up
Now I'll tell you off air my super secret plans for the Linux Action Show on Sunday
Oh wait Matt, it's big, it's real big
So we'll talk about that in a little bit
So tune in on JBLive.tv Sunday
Also, right after the Linux Action Show on Sunday on the live stream
FoShow 200
We might have something going on
You can show up live for that if you'd like
FoShow 200 right after the Linux Action Show on Sunday
Don't forget we want your feedback because it's a huge part of our show
Go over to jubilabroadcasting.com
Slash contact or click the contact link
And choose unplugged from the drop down
Alright everybody, thank you so much for tuning in to this week's episode of Linux Unplugged
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday
Alright everybody, JBtitles.com
Let's pick our title and get out of here
So Popey, are you doing anything for the Ubuntu Summit that starts in a couple of days?
Oh my god, I am solidly busy
Shave?
For the next three days
So we won't be hearing you for a little while?
I need to have a shave
Popey's going to be AFK
Might have a shower as well
Actually, interestingly, the lunch break, in inverted commas, is at 5 o'clock my time
Which is the time when you do Tech Talk today
Oh, no kidding
So you're not, I mean really, don't tease, don't tease
No I'm not
That's pretty good
And what's crazy is you don't have to go anywhere
I'll be busy making burritos
Yeah, you're going to have to stay
You know what, if you wanted to stop by and you had a little burrito in your mouth, I would take it
Popey with burrito in the mouth is better than no Popey
Wow
Wimpy, we need to get together and have a beer at some point to celebrate this
Yeah, congratulations you guys
All those beers we drank at OddCat just clearly weren't enough
Well that was the investment
Oh god
Wow though, that's pretty neat
Yeah, I've just about dried out, so yeah, I think we should
Yeah, you know