Wes's adventures with IP tables. What happened? Oh, no, I just I just had a machine running some old monitoring software
I need to just it's just terrible. I'd love to kill it, but it's the thing receiving SNMP traps right now
But it doesn't use I mean like wraps net SNMP, but it doesn't use SNMP trap T
So it wasn't that I couldn't just have it stop listening or I couldn't set up my own proxy without having to take it down
for some times, but I was able to use IP tables with the dash dash T, which I'd never used before and
Then that sense it sends it over to a secondary host which then does a
pre-routing rule on it to change the
Where it's addressed to which then sends it off to my actual house where I'm going to capture all these so I know
You know, hey, what's actually hitting this machine?
But I was really it was like two commands. It was really yeah, I didn't have to oh, I know it
No, that's Wes. You had me at IP tables
This is Linux unplugged episode
190 for March 28th
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's converting file systems in real time. My name is Chris. My name is Wes
Hello, Wes. Keep your hands off my file system. Haha. I know I don't just there's actually a few file system things coming up today, but
First we're gonna get through some updates
There's a project that's been on the back of my mind for months that we haven't talked about
Saving it a big huge change up with free NAS this week
We're gonna talk about that kind of kind of fit in with some other topics that we have
Coming up down the road just some overall stuff really kind of like major changes for a few projects. We talked about then
I'm really looking forward to this. I'm very excited about this
towards the end of the show
We're gonna spend a little bit of Wes's money
Yeah, yeah, Wes Wes has entered that wallet at home. Haha, you know, we've all been there like I think it's time for a new laptop
Yeah, I gotta get a new computer and it this can be like a multi-month search
Sometimes it can be a couple of days search depending on your situation
And so this week Wes is on the search for the ultimate Linux machine
we're gonna find out what his requirements are and then our
Panel of Linux experts the virtual lug will chime in with their ideas on what might be a fitting machine
And there happens to be some new Linux hardware releases coming very soon that may fit
We'll talk about those we all of that to go through plus
kind of a
kind of an out there futurist kind of idea about how maybe we could
Sort of take Linux and mobile Linux to the next level and some really like taking some low-end machines and just giving them huge upgrades
So we'll talk about that in a little while too. So we got it
I'm got some good hardware stuff got some good file server stuff coming up
Got some huge project changes that people need to know about like stuff. That's like relevant to all of our interests
I think it's gonna be I think it's gonna be a great show West
So let's get started by bringing in that virtual log. Hello time appropriate greetings virtual log
Hello, holy that was that was that was I wake you up that was a moment right there
So Wes if we're gonna talk about hardware that might work for you this week
We got to start with the zero terminal a tiny Linux PC that you can build using a Raspberry Pi and a smartphone keyboard
Look at how cute that is. It is super cute called the zero terminal
It's an all-in-one handheld computer that features a 3.5 inch screen and it gives you remarkable portability with a Raspberry Pi
Yeah, you got HDMI out. You can put a big old battery in there to run this thing
I don't have a tab key. That's what I want to do. Does it have an escape key? That's what you really want
Yeah, and it's got a video. That's always a win
Yeah, you see that? Oh, yeah. Yeah, that's your massage. Yeah
This is the third iteration of the handheld Linux terminal project
I've been working on for a while now
Like the others the aim is to create a small all-in-one computer that is both portable and usable
One of the main problems with the last version was that it took way too long to make and some of the finishing
Wasn't as good as it could have been. I like this idea actually
Node plans to release the files for the 3d printed parts soon. So that's kind of neat but maybe
Maybe that's not really your style West. Maybe you want something more laptop style. So keep this in mind. I
Also saw this week. There is like a laptop like concept where you could snap something like that in
So you take a like a standard laptop?
Maybe in this case the Acer travel mate. Yeah, sure and you cut it open
and so you get it off eBay and you install a
Raspberry Pi into this thing and take advantage of its keyboard its screen you can use HDMI to drive the display
You can hook up keyboards and stuff like that and you put a Raspberry Pi inside a laptop
Okay, I'm just putting these out here as options. I know you're in the early that first one
That actually
Would be you like that because you can put it in the pocket. Yeah, you could put it in the pocket
I like that idea too. Okay, there's a few of these out there right now
There's one we covered on last recently too that's trying to build that in your pocket computer
That one was a more straight-up like we were gonna run Ubuntu and I don't I can't remember if it was arm or not
Yeah, a GPD pockets pretty cool. Yeah. Yeah, that's what it was. Do you remember William? Is that arm? It's just an atom
No, it's just like cheap low-end atoms like five watts or something. It's meant for like tablets and phones
Yeah, the GPD is atom and the Gemini is arm and these are all kicking around right now
They're both being crowdfunded at the moment. Yeah. Yeah, isn't that funny? Yeah, the GPD is like really funded like 2.5 million raised
Yeah, yeah. Yeah 1200 percent over their goal. Yeah
You have with these days
All right, so wait, okay, so it's been so funded man because at what point does it become a liability, you know
Like how how can they fulfill all those orders, you know, they were expecting to fulfill a few thousand now
They've got to fill a few tens of thousand. That's just a logistical nightmare
So that's what's kind of put me off the GPD. So here's it looks awesome. So that's a great point Joanne
So here's what I want to do because we have a unique opportunity Todd from purism is joining us right now
So I want to get to him because I think you could be our resident expert on crowdfunding
But at first before we go to Todd, I wanted I want to ask wimpy. Are you hedging your bets?
You're you're backing two different portable hardware devices. Like you sir are crazy. What you must really want this form factor
I do really want this form factor. And also as I've said before just recently
Bitcoin is
Trending really nicely
I'm making a few luxurious purchases around backing. Yeah, I've also bought something old and crusty as well
Which I can talk about later if you're really yeah, I am
So I saw the GPD and I thought that looks very interesting and I'm sort of 5050 as to whether or not we'll ever see it
Because there's a lot of renders and maybe they've now they've got you know, loads of backers there. Maybe it'll happen
Well, we'll we'll see what happens, but I'm not sure it's a little bit almost shady some of it. Yeah
the actual
prototypes now
Yeah, yeah, though they have shipped a product in the past that's very similar and it was on indiegogo and it did ship
Yeah, too many hackers. So they do at least have successful products in the past sure that were crowdfunded
It was it was when it was first announced that there was lots of renders and not much substance and it was just a little case
We're indiegogo. Yeah. Anyway, so that's that one's that looks interesting, but then the Gemini
Again, so this is an organization that really has sort of previous in in this area
They've worked in this space a lot before
And I bumped into them at MWC as well. So I had the had the opportunity to press the flesh
so
Yeah, I I've backed that because I think that that I think that will probably arrive later than they're hoping because they don't have all
of the manufacturing pipeline
Arranged yet unless they get you know, really good at that and that all comes together quickly
But I think when that one ships it will be the better device in terms of the way
It's designed and the ergonomics and things. Yeah, okay. It's interesting to hear how everybody now
I think we've all sort of we've shifted our expectations in what we get from crowdfunding here
Everybody's like well, this is kind of rolling the dice here
But Todd I wanted to toss to you first of all
Welcome to Linux unplugged and to Joe's point when you have phenomenal success
You have almost you've almost gone too far. You can't as a small company
Is it difficult to sort of now meet that demand which could start with what could possibly start a whole snowball effect of bad PR
Struggling for a new company. What are your reflections on this story Todd?
Yeah, well, thanks for having me on
So it obviously is a can be a challenge crowdfunding is you know?
Still really relatively new as a way to start a business and a lot of times
What will end up happening is, you know, especially if they're just you know
If we're talking about like a developer who says hey, I always want to do this or they get together with their buddies
And they're like, yeah, we think we think our cost is probably around, you know X dollars and what ends up happening is
To operate a business. Of course, it's you know, it's X times four usually
right, so it so that's one of the things that
Tends to to underfund you meaning on a per quantity basis. So they might know a lot of
Projects that
That they get overfunded and oversubscribed which of course is a great problem initially when you think hey, this is awesome
People are really excited what we're doing
but then I think to Wimpy's point was that when you're actually looking at a per
Cost per item that you need to start scaling your operations, right?
You have to start dealing with how you're managing inventory
Right the entire operational side of things which a lot of those types of campaigns don't end up having so it
you
know the sadly a crowdfunding track record is is not as good as
As we'd all like it to be because obviously it's such a great way to you know to get these things
Off the ground and you know see projects and it's sort of a new way to start businesses
really what they tend to do is
kind of stay in the hobby area or obviously, you know delivery is I think I think I could safely say that
99% of the projects are delivered late
Because that's just you know, the nature of the beast, especially when you're dealing with hardware
Yeah
especially it seems to when it's something that's pushing the edge a little bit where you might have to get manufacturers on board with
A new idea or a new way of doing something or shipping in a way
They've never shipped before it seems like the the the difficulty gets exponentially tougher
Do you agree with that assessment Todd? Yes, I think you're exactly right and and so like in our case
We actually I've had a previous company use the same exact supply chain
and
but that's that
You know just made it where I had the contacts to be able to do things that we were trying to do
But but you know, we obviously had a lot of learning curves along the way
Mostly it was around
You know delivery times or what products were actually available
And obviously even one of the things Chris that you might remember is that we were originally slated to get 4k screens
So we said yeah, we can do 4k screens because we heard from the supply chain
We can do 4k screens and then that ended up turning into
You know constant delays because the the actual source manufacturer of Samsung was getting bought up by
much larger suppliers
Or much larger buyers and so so we kept kind of falling to the back burner
and then at some point we just had to you know, cut our losses and say, you know
what we're gonna have to we're gonna have to ship what we can right now and then
and then
Basically place another order with a more reliable supply chain. So it really that supply chain management is an area that is
Really difficult to manage through
you know and now we ended up after we've just because we've grown to the point where we can have a really solid supply chain and
Through negotiation and really to some degrees trial and error
But a lot of the new new
Crowdfunded campaigns that that is I think wimpy's point is exactly right when you start to get
Oversubscribed then they introduce all sorts of new problems, right? It's not just like a hobby putting this together
They're trying to actually now start to form a business and if they didn't get their pricing, right?
It could end up being
That that they won't be able to actually fund the entire process, right if they don't have if they don't have
experience working with manufacturers and
Like to your point which I don't really think a lot of us think about
if they get to a certain size now all of a sudden they have to also have experience with managing inventory and
Tracking support issues and support staff that if you don't have the past experience standing those groups up and integrating those employees into your business
You know
It's gonna be a huge learning curve while you're also trying to ship the product that you just promised everybody
It's like zero to medium-sized business today
So I'm glad wimpy is risking the Bitcoin on it because I really want to see both of these be successful because I love the form
Factor idea totally. So thanks with me. Yeah
Yeah, and you know if I end up with two of these then one will be for my daughter. So that'll be fun. That's nice
Yeah, that's that's brilliant. Well Todd. Thanks for being here and I hope you stick with us
We got a whole bunch of stuff coming up
I just want to give a quick heads up to folks that may be using last pass
I've been looking at different password managers recently if that wasn't obvious and
And
It's that time again, and I keep coming back when it comes to mobile integration and stuff like that. I keep preferring last pass
So I this applies to me
I don't know if some of you are out there but over the weekend a Google security researcher reported a new client side vulnerability
So this is in the browser side, which could be potentially dangerous
There is an update now last pass is not giving us the details
Maybe those tech snap guys will keep an eye out for the details on what the actual vulnerability was
But right now as of yesterday
The the word from last passes is just update and we'll tell you all the details soon
Or maybe Google actually will because a lot of times that Google project zero blog. Yeah sure has that stuff
Speaking of tech snap we should mention more often that you can find more of mr.
Wes on the tech snap program was it last week you guys did a deep dive was it or is the week before last week?
Broke from the traditional format and did a deep dive into bacula, which is such a badass
Backup system that Dan knows very well. Yes, he does. Yeah, he's a bacula guy and I tell you what?
If you've ever been curious about a really rock-solid backup system, it can do bare metal restores
It can do individual file restores
It can it can really manage a lot of day sets of data
Bacula and check out the last week's episode tech snap about it, which is an open source. I
Used to use bacula. Oh, really? Yeah, I used to use it to back up a company that sold antivirus
Nice yeah, that makes sense and it works great for something like that. Yeah, and it was perfect
It really was so that's a different time. You don't know now I might use it with digital ocean
I could picture it digital ocean comm go over there
In fact do me a favor after you sign up
You can get a $10 credit and support the show by applying the promo code do on a plug to your account
I like the way that this works too because you can you fund the account?
Yeah, so this is just one of the funding methods you can find it with PayPal or credit card or probably pixie dust
But use the promo code. I'm not sure about that last one do unplugged one word you get a $10 credit
You can spin up a linux rig up on their infrastructure all SSDs for the storage
Wes it makes a difference. It sure does you know what also would help with that bacula thing
They're private networking dude you mean for like backing up your own droplet stuff
Yes, because also that's brilliant a because then your backup server isn't on the public net
But be the transfer all over the private networking doesn't count towards your total data transfer. Oh, that's money right there
That's a good idea yeah check that out
So one of the many great features of digital ocean go over there use our promo code do unplugged and spin up a rig you
Can try out bacula for just a few pennies on the dollar if you want to run it for a few hours?
Try out the $5 rig two months for free it's gonna be all SSD
So it's nice and fast and if you want to back up to digital ocean
They have block storage which you can add up and add up and add up and just keep growing as you need or even reduce
Or this is brilliant didn't realize this until recently move it to another droplet
Freaking mind-blown in the context of backups freaking mind-blown
It's and that's just the beginning to if you're into this kind of stuff
You might also fight you might also favor their new monitoring system coming soon
It's gonna be coming I little birdie tells me very soon
And you can sign up for early access when you go to digital ocean comm go there create an account big
Thank you digital ocean have a great interface for managing all of this an API that really works
Hell of a good service at digital ocean comm use our promo code do unplugged and thanks to them for sponsoring the unplugged program
okay, so I want to talk just briefly about
File servers, I know I know some people's eyes are gonna glaze over
But there's one that we don't talk about very much, and I want to give it a little love right now
And that's rock store. I've mentioned it once before but a couple of days ago. I missed it first
They had a new release and I think it's worth mentioning
Because they've put a ton of release a ton of effort into this they have now six contributors coming together
To work on bug fixes and performance improvements the code quality is from what people tell me has had a big jump in this one
They've had a lot of improvements to their Python back-end stack
They are still and this could be actually I think a feature to some of you all in on butter FS for the NAS file server
File system so if you're a big fan of butter fest which people remain fans
This is a great file server for you potentially they also seem to offer some some commercial products or offerings
I'm not totally familiar with support available as well. Yeah, maybe we'll make you feel a little more secure. Yeah
But if that's file system underneath so rock store
Just had a had a new release with which sounds like a lot of nice refinements and improvements
Which is pretty much exactly what you want from your NAS yeah now on the other end
there is
Free NAS coral, which is also known as free NAS 10. This is a
Massive release in my opinion for free NAS. It's it's big
It's it's sort of in some ways a total revisioning of the way the UI works. It's got a brand new slick UI
it's got a rewritten middleware architecture and
The big and probably one that has gotten the most discussion changes. There's they're transitioning from using jails for plugins to
Using Docker can say what Docker containers isn't that a Linux the Docker?
containers with full ZFS integration and a new command line and
There is some caveats if you're migrating from free NAS 9
Your plugins that you have installed via jails. They don't get deleted
They just get deactivated and you'll have to kind of come up with your own solution to maybe converting those into Docker containers
Now this is this is interesting because I think this is probably one of the biggest competitors in this sort of rock store sort of Linux
You know the household date. Yeah. Yeah friend free NAS is
Making huge changes and along those are also some of the changes on the back end team
Jordan Hubbard, who I've had the pleasure of meeting and watching a presentation on free NAS 10 at
meet BSD who seemed to me a big part of the project he's
He's moving on
Now he was the main dev. So he's also the CTO of IX systems. So that's a that's a big change
He's sounds like he's you know moving into something that he's gonna be super passionate about so
He's going into I think like that. Yeah, he says the nanotech biomedical field. It's a complete career change
Wow, yeah, yeah, which that's got to be nice from time to time. So really reinvigorate. Yeah
Good for him, but it's got to be a huge change also back in December. They had another long-time
Free NAS developer who was with free NAS since version 8 7 years
He's also moving on from free NAS
So some big changes Jonathan says that he will not be or Jordan not Jonathan. Sorry, Jordan Hubbard
Jordan says that I don't know Jonathan Jordan Hubbard says that he won't be a developer anymore, but he'll still be part of the community
So Jordan's still gonna be in the you know as a user, right says he'll be filing bugs and yelling at those devs
And some people have speculated. Well, is this because of all of the breakage from upgrading from free NAS 9 to 10, but I
Don't buy it. I don't buy it because free NAS free NAS
9.10 is still available for download still supported like you don't have to upgrade
Yeah, and you can roll back your upgrade if it goes wrong, so I don't really buy that like Jordan was pushed out
Which is what read it there right at the reddit conspiracy theories right now that the free NAS 10 was such a failure that it pushed
Jordan out which seems a little a little over the top, but if he was just pushed out
He'd probably go to a company with similar interests or do something in a similar vein not change careers completely
Yeah, I agree. I just I don't know
I think what it was is he what he worked on this until it was done
And he got you know something he sort of got it some stuff wrapped up, and now he's a natural type
It's like it's like a nice smooth transition. Yeah
and it I
The but all that is my way of saying there is there is some there is some
Some pushback on this new release this free NAS coral. I'm sure there is yeah
And I wonder if things like unraid or another Linux out-of-the-box file server could step up to fill the gap
I don't know a free NAS is got a pretty big lead at this point and
Like I said version 9 still perfectly good still perfectly usable still perfectly
But you do have to wonder I mean there was even a question to the Texas program about what's that support cycle gonna be which I?
Was I'm sure it's gonna be very reasonable. You know especially since there's a community around it
That's what it seems not that worried
But you do have to think like you know like you've been talking about like if you're planning in the next five years
I mean it would probably still work for that time frame, but ten years
What do you think about Docker? I mean that's an interesting
Interesting the doctor just win right there the doctor just win like I can't see it from their perspective of does that
Much easier like if it's packaged at Docker is it now pretty easy for them to make sure it works in their environment
Versus having to put together plugins with their own custom jail format that kind of thing
To me it seems to represent like sort of the industry even even the people on the BSD side of the fence coming to a
recognition that
Well, if you want to be able to distribute software that runs across multiple platforms
Dockers
Just the container technology we're gonna use and it's not so much that they're like betting on Docker so much as they want to
Make all of the stuff that's already in a container available to free nas so they instead of having reaches
Yeah, instead of having to have a plug-in author who creates something specifically for a free nas now
Just exactly Joe free nas using a container
Specifically for a free nas now just exactly Joe free nas user can pull down a Docker container
Do we know yet how they're doing it? Is it using it's probably still using jail. That's what I would others
It's just that the Docker format gives you this like universal format to package the thing up with and then she you know
I wonder I don't look controls that just work
I wonder because the way they say listen to the way they put this
Support for Docker containers its own built-in hypervisor that supports virtualization with full ZFS integration
So to me, it sounds like they're using a hypervisor to run this and they would have like a Linux kernel
It'd be you think they're able to run Linux Docker images. This is where they're going with this. They are Linux dockers
No, they are Linux dock because you're because they're making it available for you to pull down pre-created Docker containers
Then it's probably yeah beehive with Linux running on top of it. Yeah
That's to me is a huge statement. Yeah. Hmm. Don't you think?
That's pretty cool
That's sort of like when Microsoft started shipping Docker support and bash on Windows. It's just sort of like this
Linux is the runtime Linux is the runtime and however you get that runtime on your machine sure
Yeah, and the container technology is the is how you get the runtime right now
But it's really but those half of those containers are running Ubuntu, right?
So it's it's really Linux is the platform. Yeah, and in a lot of those cases, it's Ubuntu 70% There you go
Yeah
So it's that's that I think they came up with a way to run Ubuntu on free NAS
Let's look more into this
I'm very curious about it because I wonder if it'll create any pressure for their
Compact layer to implement those primitives, you know
Is they're just using beehive with a Linux kernel, right?
Didn't have to run a whole hypervisor
Support like OCI or other types of things that suddenly you could have like hey
I want to run for BSD as my you know base platform for Kubernetes or whatever most reliably
Using the hypervisor route is probably the best way
Yeah, don't yeah to start and maybe down the road they allow you to pick whether it's using the ABI or using a hypervisor
Yeah, and I think that's what Microsoft is doing up and at
230 the file system upgrade just finished on the phone
So in from to hot. Yes. There you go. The real the file system in real time is completed
Oh, geez, now I got to sign in. What is this crap just for one point release?
Does this mean if Ubuntu is running on freedom?
Yes, does that mean we can get snaps running as well? Well, if you I wouldn't you if you could run Docker containers on there
Couldn't you just run essentially like a small Ubuntu system?
And that's the stage. Yeah, you could and you could make snaps on it as well if you wanted to
Fascinating that is interesting. I really want to see what the web UI I've looked at the early betas
I would don't know they have supported this do you all right? So it would make sense that they might
Yeah, they have another built-in via they have a section called VMs, right? Exactly. Exactly
It's just that's what I would think it just another built-in VM
So it's something I think I'm gonna play around with now that I can get Linux on my free NAS
This is a game changer for me
But it's a big controversial feature in the free NAS community right now. Oh, I'm sure
All right. Well, there you go. I thought that was oh, oh and by the way, if you are going to upgrade
Let me see I have
Somewhere in this mess of show notes. Here we go. I have a migrating from free NAS 9 to free NAS coral
Entry on the free NAS wiki place that covers all of it and like issues you have
Especially for using encryption maybe just give this a read doesn't sound like it's gonna be too complicated
But probably stuff you should be aware of so check that out. I have all that go try the new version
I'd love to hear you think about it. Do you have a file server at home?
not anything
pre built like this
Hmm. I have a I have a box that has a container that runs my router and that it has a container that you know
Yeah, if you just if you just built a big desktop PC, you could put a bunch of disks in it
I sure could and you could just use that
Like a double duty. Hmm. All right, listen to that. We're gonna talk about your new machine
We're gonna go spend your money here. We're gonna go spend your money here just about now actually
So, uh, I think it's just about time. Let's so let's do that
Let's let's actually let's mention Linux Academy Linux Academy comm slash unplugged then we're gonna go home man
West see my favorite thing to do is to spend other people's money and I'm gonna get you set up much more fun
We're gonna get you hooked up
We're gonna get you hooked up with a good machine and then when you're ready to put that machine to use and you want to
Do more I want you to go to Linux Academy and learn more Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
You land there to support the show and sign up for a free seven-day trial
It's a platform to learn more about
The Linux with self-paced in-depth video courses hands-on real-world scenarios that help shake off that test anxiety because you've got actual
Expertise I love it
They spin up the lab server when you need it you SSH into that shenanigans
You get a real environment seven plus Linux distros you choose from the servers and the courseware. I'll snap
See what I did there to that distro. I'll snap to that distro
You can also take practice exams to like prepare for a cert test
You can get note cards have been forked by the community improved you get nuggets
Which are just tiny bits of wisdom you just do a little deep dive into a singular topic for five minutes or an hour depending
On the subject which is great when you've got a busy week speaking of busy weeks
They have course schedulers to work with you to help match content to your busy
Schedule a community stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members downloadable tools like guides and lesson audio that you can take with you
iOS and Android apps to study on the go damn
Damn, the list just keeps getting longer and longer, and they're always adding more courseware
You can just look at their Twitter feed to see that
It's just it's so awesome that something like this where you sign up once and then they just keep working their butts off to get
You more and more stuff Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and a big thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
Linux Academy comm slash unplugged so if we're not gonna do the Raspberry Pi with a keyboard for you Wes
It sounds like you are what can you tell people what you got right now give people a base?
So they know what you're coming from right now. I've got a
core i5
Was it second generation third what generation is this one? I think first that might be my first yeah first gen XPS
Yeah, with a I think that was the first gen i5 yeah 13 inch screen 13 inch screen
And what's the resolution of the screen 13 whatever yep? Yep, so that's the icing on this horrible cake
Oh my good, which at home. I have external monitors, so it's not that big of a deal
But has the monitor hookup display port yeah, okay, all right, so that'd probably still be the same. Yeah, so that's fine
I'm SSD SSD and four gigs eight gigs four gigs of room. Oh my god. Oh
My god, okay, wow yeah, we really got a talk
So 13 inch now. What do you like most about that form factor? I mean it is very convenient. It's not a heavy machine
It's easy to throw in a bag. I think I could do up to a 15-inch
As long as it wasn't you know crazy. I would like to like you don't be able to easily take it to a coffee shop
Or a bar to do some work, okay, okay?
All right, well see I was I was going to recommend. I was gonna recommend something a little bigger
I was gonna recommend you've ever seen this Acer here with the with the 20 inch curved screen
Okay, maybe not maybe not it looks like it has a nice keyboard though are those is that like a real keyboard yeah, man
Yeah, yeah, that's legit right there. Not the dumb pad not the dumb. No. It's the rest. It's like a mechanical keyboard
That's also the numpad actually comes out and can be a trackpad. Oh wow it flips over
Yeah, isn't that sweet so not that that's too big yeah, so what do you like least about the form factor?
Did you feel constrained on the screen and you must oh yes?
So it's not it's not that bad like I honestly spent a lot of the time
I have like you know a chat program or two
But once at a time a terminal and a web browser, so it's not that bad
But when I'm away from home, and I'm trying to do some development
Which I need you know like a couple terminals and a web browser then suddenly I'm all tabbing over the place
It's you see okay, so on not just because they're friends of the show
But it seems like something like the galago pro
Would be a pretty strong contender for you what you have to decide here is do you want to go bigger than 13 inch screen or
Not because I think that's that's the classifier
It sounds like you're leaning 15 inch I mean
The 13 inch I like 13 14 even I think I think I would be okay with a 15 inch
That's where it kind of forks the discussion. Maybe a little bit as well
Do I also want to consider building a new desktop rig right?
Okay, I haven't built a desktop and a desktop or or you know maybe not of the laptop
I guess there's both option. I would still like a new laptop
but if I have a nice desktop at home that beats I could have a you know a different yeah, I would probably want a
13 inch or
But how are these options with Thunderbolts e GPUs and I'm gonna be for your laptop
So here's what I think so I think we should I think we should do this
I think we should do this since people at home are probably thinking some of the same stuff
I think we should break that particular the desktop into a separate conversation because I think we can quickly get there because I think that might
Be the way to go. Although although there are some super nice laptops. Like is it called Kratos?
Is that how you pronounce it wimpy the Kratos Kratos? Yes, it's the entroware Kratos
That looks like a nice real. Yeah, if you're on this side of the Atlantic so in Europe
They've just released their new updated version of that which
Is an i7 and it goes up to 32 gigs of RAM and it's got an Nvidia
1050 in it GTX 1050
15 inch display that matters
Yeah, 15 inches kind of tasty. I think I think Wes you really deserve dedicated graphics if you can
There's something there's another route you could consider
This is something I know you've been looking at. That's why I bring this up
So audience behind the scenes Wes has been reading up a little bit about using
Say like a Thunderbolt cable to hook up an external GPU. You could also go this route
So if we go if we if we keep this in mind, this also opens up your your possibilities
I just don't know how well this kind of thing works with Linux
I'd love to know if anybody in the audience or in the Mamba room has any any information about external Thunderbolt
GPUs with Linux looks like WWS get something you do www. I got something on the windows side
Okay, so from I've only seen one person on YouTube actually test what Thunderbolting an external video card
What the performance is actually like and from that one series of like two videos?
It's a 30 to 40 percent decrease from desktop performance
For a 4 to 12 percent gain and that is if you're using the monitor hooked up to the external
Right right GPU unit. So I mean that's all windows your performance could vary wildly
Very you happen to know what what connection interface they're using if it was Thunderbolt 2 or 3 because I mean I think it was
Thunderbolt 3
Wow, I think most of the gear is Thunderbolt 3 driven
Thunderbolt 3 those 40 gigabits it is it what's cool is if you get a laptop that has the Thunderbolt 3
But it also has the reverse feed display port
So the graphics card can feed a display port back in and power the screen
Because like the Apple I want to say just the MacBook or the MacBook Pro can do that
And I know there are other laptops
I think like the razor blade and stuff can do that where you can plug in the external GPU and still use the laptop
Monitor with the external GPU feeding it instead a lot of people in the chat room have been suggesting razor blade
Have you looked at razor? I have done. I mean, I'm really aware of the price. Aren't they horrible with Linux though?
Are they are they so?
see this is this is this is the thing Wes is I I would I would encourage you to really get your head around what screen
size you want and
Really draw the line somewhere for me personally over the years having right next to me
I have my Librem right right now and I and I have the Apollo and one is a 13 inch and one is a 15 inch and
It if I want something that I take on the couch
I like the 13 inch if I want something that I'm gonna work from I like the 15 inch
It's just so it's really what you're gonna use it for. What are you gonna?
Is it more of a work machine or is it more of a browse the web have fun machine?
Honestly probably more of a work machine
I mean, I will use it in a casual capacity but portability do you take it with you to work?
Not to work, but I like to work out of the house a lot of my own personal projects show work that kind of thing
Yeah, that's where this really fails. How much time do you spend looking at the screen when you're doing that sort of stuff?
What do you mean?
When you're working on your own stuff and you want to use it, you know for working on your own projects
How much time might you be spending at the computer then those those moments?
Uh, I would say anywhere from two to six hours. Whoa
Depending okay. Jeez. I can't believe you've put up with that resolution for this long. I would not I would not man
That's gotta be rough. Well, that's how I find myself here today
Good for you. I'm really proud of you for taking so what?
So I've effectively got the same machine. I've got a 13 inch and a 15 inch variant
so it's the 13 inch XPS and the 15 inch XPS and the 13 inch XPS is what I take out when I'm going
Traveling that's the device. I sure because it's small. It's powerful
It's no compromise
But for extended periods working on that machine, it's not so great because 13 inch screen
You do find yourself, you know, you can't quite get close enough to it now
That's probably compounded by the fact that that's a high DPI screen
That's right. So I've actually been thinking about potentially selling that XPS 13 and getting the version with the
1080p screen
Because I think that would be better to work on
For longer periods. Oh, yeah, that's an interesting point
Yeah, and I'm not like I don't need a touchscreen. I don't have I mean, they're nice
I would maybe occasionally use it but not a deal breaker
I says it looks like razors working the razor core which is their external eGPU with a 970 in it hooked up to an XPS
13 running on arch looks like it's working to power an external monitor. That's in the XPI, you know interesting
I really like these most links for that somewhere. He put in the chat room. I
Really like I really like the XPS 13, but if it was my only computer
I would probably opt for the 15. Yeah, and wimpy
What was the battle like to put because this thing only ships with Windows
So what was the what was the process like to put Linux on?
Is it just a format nuke pave install Linux or is there some did you replace Wi-Fi and whatnot?
so I got my
machines both from Adele reseller and they were able to sell the
XPS 15 with a configuration that had the same Wi-Fi chip in it as the XPS 13 developer edition
So I didn't have to do any
Monkeying around it obviously arrived with Windows 10 on it, which was actually quite helpful because
Around the time I got mine sort of September last year
they were just working out the last of the firmware bugs in the BIOS and
So you did it anyway?
So yeah, I needed to do the updates anyway
So it was quite handy to have that do the updates and then it's just been running Ubuntu ever since hmm
Hmm. Yeah, I I wonder if even now if the latest model even would have if you'd have to replace the Wi-Fi
That may not be an issue anymore. Yeah, and I mean I'm comfortable doing that
It'd make me happier if it had a if it had a 10 series card. It has a GTX 960. It's not a hard swap
I've done it. You just take the bottom off and it's right there
It's not a hard swap at all and you can just get a replacement card on Amazon for like 35 bucks 60 bucks
But that seems like that seems like a decent way to go. Alright, so that is I so
You're so if you go if you go into like the 15 inch range that you know
There's some there's some nice machines there
but you said something that I think is probably the more exciting thing to consider because it's something I've gone through myself is
What if I do something like an ultrabook or even this is crazy, but even like a chromebook
Yeah
And then I get myself like a six core or more I seven machine
32 gigs of RAM lots of storage and you just go all out and plus it's kind of fun if you haven't done it for
A while to build a PC like when's the last time you built a PC?
Ages yeah ages. Yeah, it's like seven years or something. So if you've been on laptops for years now
Okay, so we got to talk about this because I did this
There's like a gaming rig kind of thing, but it's not like new has a nice graphics card, but older processor
So yeah, it's not where you're working. It's not where I'm working. No. Yeah. Hmm. Okay. All right, so
So I I I recently made this transition myself where I was on all laptops for years
Even the machines here at the table, right? Oh, yeah looking back at it seems
Really crazy. Yeah ludicrous. It seems ludicrous
Absolutely ludicrous and now cuz now you just it blows my mind
Yeah, so let's ludicrous. That could be your new handle Chris ludicrous
Like that
That's not bad. That's not bad. You know, what else is ludicrous ting go to linux.ting.com
You'll save twenty five dollars off your first device and support the show
If you already have a GSM or CDMA device that works check their BYOD page you get twenty five dollars in service credit
That's nice because it's six bucks for the line and then just your usage on top of that for minutes messages megabytes
I was having a telegram conversation today with I think it might have been it might have been Cory
I can't remember it on telegram. You see Chris is my mom does not want data on her phone
And he says can I use ting anyways?
I said actually thing would be perfect because you can just go in and completely turn data off
I guess I guess his mom like had a bad experience with data
Happens but and not Brent Spiner data, but what that one time you get that extra bill. Yeah
Hey, that's it. I just want phone calls. And so he goes in there can turn it right off boom
That's the thing team makes it so easy
And if you do want it, it's super easy to set like hey, let me know what I've crossed this boundary
Yeah, or if you just want to turn it back on just go check a box
They got apps for the phone to manage all of it
They've also got a great website and customer service that really sets the bar you get to talk to real human beings
So all of that combined with the fact that they're a really cool company with geeks that work there
They're really into this stuff and they follow stuff like on their blog all the time
They've got the moto g5 plus available now for pre-order that could be kind of quick
That could be kind of a cool device. It's got two. It's got a two gigahertz octa-core processor four gigabytes of RAM
It's like around what I think it's like what 300 bucks for a nice moto smartphone with
With damn four gigs of RAM. Damn. I think that's as much as the iPhone's got as much as my laptop
Oh, that's so horrible. Oh my god. We got out. We got a talk West. We got a talk
All right. Thank you to Ting for sponsoring the show Linux dot ting.com
Oh, yes, I tell you when I made that transition from I know what these are nice laptops, right?
Yeah, but no bo's XPS is you have been for laptops now. No, they're good. Yeah, I five I seven processors SSDs
This is why I thought and like the bonobos, you know for a while. They were dedicated GTX 510
And like the bonobos, you know for a while. They were dedicated GTX graphics cards
What could that in my mind?
I understand that some of these things are clock slightly slower and they run slightly slower for for for heat, right?
But in them not necessarily in the bonobo, I I don't I couldn't really conceptualize that there would be a
noticeable difference in my day-to-day usage couldn't really I even in my main workstation upstairs. I was using a laptop and
I'm not just doing that, you know and filter editing show editing. Yeah
Try and reviews and then when when it came time like I think I guess it was last year
I can't like was it last year the year before we built new rigs for the last week
Yeah, and I one of the things I can if I if it's possible whenever I can I'll buy two of everything
So that way we have a backup because we're live right?
I want to have a production machine and a backup machine. And so I bought and so you know what?
What if we're gonna build these anyways, I'll buy a third one because I mean I'm like I'm using Bitcoin, right?
It's not like I'm using actual cash here. It's not real money. So it's like
Yeah, looking back at it has it been money for ages
anyway, so we build a third one slightly nicer configuration because it's my personal workstation and
Put it in and I sit down to start working on it and now looking back at it
It is it's it's a it's a totally different computing experience. Wow. There is a just a it's something about the just the amount of
Sheer work. I can have this one system doing because not only am I doing like things like video encoding and editing and transferring large
Files around the network all at once
I've also got YouTube streams telegrams like all this regular desktop my email my web browser like all this huge
I've got all this regular desktop stuff going to and then in the back end. I've got usenet. I've got indexers
I've got downloaders extractors. I've got I've got sonar monitoring feeds
Like I've got all this other server stuff that this thing's doing that in the past would have been like on its own dedicated machine
And it's doing that all of it while I'm doing all this other stuff and it never misses a beat and it's just the sheer
Amount of productivity I get out of one machine. I for my main computer. I will never ever
Well, I shouldn't say that I cannot
Yeah, I cannot see me going back to laptop for my main work. That's a pretty that's a pretty strong opinion
Plus it takes the pressure off the laptop pick right which is so hard just right
Yeah, it doesn't have to be perfect anymore. Just has to yeah fill that niche
So that's anybody in the mumble room have a opposite or similar experience like, you know
You switch over to a desktop and it's just a totally different amount of work you get done for me personally
Especially working with video and stuff. I love the fact that I can start an encode job
I get I just gonna run for 15 minutes
I switch over to another desktop and it's like you start even worry about it don't not at all Wow
So as someone who's building a lot of software, it's invaluable to have like a dually five machine sitting in a closet somewhere
Sort of SSH and for my laptop to be able to build software on 32 threads. Yeah
My my bill I just have to change into everything
My build machine is my intro where Athena which is an absolute monster. So that's a laptop
And it's my gaming laptop
But when it's not being used for gaming which is infrequently it sits on the desk behind me during the day
And that's the machine that I do all of my builds and what have you on?
See that would be nice because
That's a big machine like the one I used to be able to get like a nice ultrabook with a huge battery say like
An x270 from Lenovo and be able to go 13 hours without plugging in and you're just SSH ing into your powerful box
So you can get a lot of work done, but still go forever on battery
It would be nice as well to have that kind of home base because I don't find this laptop
Especially like when I format it for the show or distro reviews or whatever like it's just not that consistent
So it ends up that I have to promote some like cloud server or droplet or other thing to be my kind of like
That's where I do ansible runs from that's where my main backups from my sink thing are taken or whatever
That might not be a bad strategy
Yeah
But it would be nice for some things to have like a home base that I could that's like me is like I just end up
There's some things. I just want to run on my local machine. Yeah. Yeah, I agree. I think you should
I think you should give the idea a serious consideration because if you've made it this long on this machine a
Fairly modest laptop would be a pretty big spec bump so you could do a modest laptop bump and really invest in the desktop
You know it's not it's not all fun though
You know I also I mean you you know we got a stack of dead motherboards right there that right there is a
It's not I don't feel like it's quite as good as it used to be I feel like I get a lot more
Dead-on-arrival parts when I when I custom build now than we used to but you know I guess
It doesn't seem like it's as big as an industry find to me
Yeah, so Wes how important is battery life to you um I don't need like
Crazy battery life. I would like you know like five plus
More would more would be nice
But I am usually in a position where I could find power or know of you know like my favorite
Establishments to work have a pretty readable power outlets that sort of it
Right so the reason I asked the question is when I got my
Entrower Apollo I suddenly walked into a new era of battery endurance that I'd not
Experienced before and I got used to having like seven hours plus battery life, and that was pretty great
When I got the XPS 13 I was looking for
Touchscreens and high DPI because I wanted to play with all the new toys
right and I I'm somewhat jaded because the the trade-off there that you make is
Battery endurance because those high DPI screens and the touchscreen
Just arriving in more power. Yeah, so I I will get comfortably four and a half hours on the XPS 13
Maybe five at a push, but nothing more than that and that's another reason why I've been considering for the
for the XPS 13 perhaps the 1080p model which
Doesn't have the touchscreen has a low res screen and the battery life is almost double. Yeah. Yeah, I think I could do
That's my observation as well also
You just there's more Linux software that works better at at right regular DPI
You cannot you can definitely make it work
Especially if you're working with cute five apps or GTK three apps you really you're gonna have a fine
You're gonna have a fine experience, but almost all of them will screw it up out of the box
So you're gonna you're gonna have to make some tweaks
But and I still I still I'm making small refinements to my plasma desktop on the XPS 13
I would I would also agree if you if you don't need it
I personally think it's you know, I don't know of any laptops that have the screen resolution, but 2k is perfect
Yeah, perfect. Yeah, perfect. It's perfect. Hmm. I really wish we had more 2k screens on laptop
The other thing to consider is on the high DPI
laptops most of the 13 inch laptops when you've pixel doubled them are like the equivalent of 1600 by 900 in terms of
You know, yeah usable, you know equivalent resolution. Yeah, so you actually have more screen space on a 1080p
hmm when we know it's
I'm just I'm just mentioning these things because these are things that I hadn't considered going into my purchasing decision
Yeah, I'm now aware of having having made it
I mean I wanted to I in fact, I still want I still want a machine
I can try out high DPI stuff on for review purposes. Yeah, no that makes sense
But if you're not doing that, I don't know
Depends like most of my time is at the terminal maybe some like photo editing
But if I had a desktop I could do that there too. Yeah, dude
You can also get a 2k screen for a reasonable price on the desktop
That's so I have the new x1 carbon is a 2k screen 14 is it? Oh in case you're curious lick
What now I might have to sell something
It's like the infinity display right it's got the thin bezel. Yeah, we were just talking about in the pre-show that pretty cool
Take a look at it. Excellent
See charging on the new ones. Oh, I love that. I'm that would be that would be awesome
That would feature the XPS 13 and this that way see charge. Did I take Bitcoin?
Seriously, cuz yeah that oh
70 I'm curious if that also type-c charges off the type-c port on it
So I'm so done with John to type-c me too
I was just having a conversation last night with Noah about how I just want everybody to go all in on USB C
Let's just do it. Yeah
That's why when I saw the Gallego ultra pro with the new one
See, I was like you guys you better fix this before you ship this
I would really love to see them have USB C on that. Maybe the next rev can do it
I'm not sure why they can't do it now, but it is time. It's time for cameras. It's time for everything
I want I want to charge my remotes with USB C my phone with USB C my camera my laptop
The thing that did it for me was I bought one of those battery packs
But it had one that you could use to jumpstart a car on it and it was chargeable and it used USB C
So I was like so in theory if I had my phone I could charge this battery from my phone and then start my car
Maybe yeah Wow drain your phone though. Yeah, but whatever I can go drive somewhere. Yeah, exactly
Okay, somebody at Chris Ellie asked me a Lenovo reseller that sells the x1 carbon with the end accepts Bitcoin
Okay. All right. So there's there's that now wimpy though. You were teasing earlier that you got new hardware
You got something a new device
Yes, I have I can't tell you much about it other than what it is, but I have bought a
an old computer
I have bought an IBM x200
But this x200 has Libre boot
It's an FSF approved laptop
Now this is a brand new purchase. Oh, you just got you got this old new device
This new old arrived it arrived today and other than getting it out of the box and the bubble wrap and turning it on
I haven't done anything with it
well hasn't that just isn't that just perfect because Todd's here and I just recently saw news from from purism about
Work on Libre boot Todd. Can you bring us up to speed what's going on over with with Libre boot?
Yeah, so
Well Libre boot of course is just the port from core boot that removes the binary blobs. So right, right
So so which which I guess to I guess can you back up and explain more binary blobs of what?
so
Anything that's built?
Pre 2008 you can actually have a core boot
Running without any binary blobs, which are of course
mystery code that runs at the BIOS level
And obviously this is getting more and more attention. Yeah, especially with vault 7 releases where about 90% of those
security based exploits were
EFI or UEFI
exploits so
And then obviously so one of the biggest ones and the biggest worry is called the Intel management engine
Then there's also something else called Intel AMT
That is that actually allows for remote access of your machine when it's even powered off
So those are a couple of things that are binaries at the lowest level
And the way that I like to describe that is basically from a security standpoint. It's kind of how deep do you go?
and so some people, you know, they'll just like install a
You know ad blocker and they think that they're you know happy as it can be
And then you know
Then you can go deeper down to the operating system where you you know
Do you have binaries that power your wireless card or your graphics, etc?
and then you can go deeper than that which of course gets you to the bootloader and then the
Lowest level is the firmware on the machine, which of course is the BIOS or EFI or in our case is core boot
so we actually just
ported core boot for the Purism Vibram laptops and
And and then we have also
What's called neutralized the management engine which means we've removed the network stack remove the kernel
So we have a very small bit of code to reverse engineer or actually just get to the point where we can disable the management
engine and at that point we'd actually qualify for
Respects your freedom certification on a brand new i7 6th gen
CPUs. Yeah
Yeah, that that's that's how I feel. I just disable the damn thing. Just turn it off. I don't
Yeah, that's exactly what's funny about it. Is that I mean, it's one of those things that
Initially, I don't think it was like really a nefarious reason why the management engine was initially started
It was part of this sort of business push to
To make it where sysadmins and you know remotely control a device at a lower level than the operating system to you know
To reinstall or repair etc
And then it turned into this, you know, wow, this can actually be this black box that does a tremendous amount
So that actually now has a separate its own separate core
It's an art core
But the thing at the end of the day is that it can be completely removed, right?
So we've actually proven it can be completely removed and the machine can operate
But it happens to operate for 30 minutes because there's a little watchdog timer that disables the CPU actually powers it off
so now we have
Ninety three percent removed the last seven percent is a this watchdog timer
So okay
So you're telling me just to just a pause there
In the process of trying to figure out how this damn thing works and how to how to disable it or just bypass it all
Together you're getting down the path. Oh my god. I think we got this working high fives all around everybody
We did it and then 30 minutes into it. It shuts the system down and it's like then you discover
There's a timer in there this that's yeah, that's exactly right. So there is a separate watchdog timer that basically
when the machine first powers on there's a signature check against one of the partitions within the
Management engines you can think of it like as like a zip file of partitions
so but the signature check is only on the very first file or partition of the
Management engine so the networking stack and the kernel are in other partitions
So we can actually zero out all the partitions except the one that has a signature check
And then if the signature check fails, then this watchdog timer triggers for 30 minutes
But because we manufacture the motherboard we actually have fusing capabilities that get us a little bit deeper than
Then what would otherwise be there?
So we can actually start to really debug and say we can put the CPU in a debug mode or the management engine in a disable
Mode, so we're starting to test those features out
And obviously the end goal for us is we want to have a device that can operate with completely free software throughout the entire stack
From the very first firmware loaded all the way through all the operating system and all the applications that run Todd my my
Capitalist sense would tell me that there would be some other
Market leader that would seem to want to jump to the call of organizations that want to have more secure
Laptops, especially in a post Snowden era
It seems like there could be even entire governments that would want computers that are rid of management engine
That's controlled by a US corporation. Why in your estimation? Is this something that's not being why is Lenovo not leading this charge?
It's yeah, it's such a great question and I don't happen to know the answer because obviously we're focusing on that
the the area that I think the only way I can really sort of answer that is that
for us
We need it. We we need to have the entire stack and it's really a game of depth
So if your operating system if you're gonna be running, you know Windows 10
well, then you're exploited at the operating system level, so it's right so it's
hmm, so the for us we look at it as
The game of security is a game of depth
And so we want to have all of our applications running free software the entire operating system itself the kernel
not running any binaries for wireless or for GPU and then of course the bootloader being freed and then the
firmware at the lowest level being freed so
And obviously the more these documents get leaked. It just really
It seems to me Todd like it's such a
Herculean effort to actually do this that by the time you get to completely done
there's there's the real honest potential that the market could shift out from underneath you and like
AMD's PSP system the system that you know a lot of people are talking about now that risins getting more attention
could all of a sudden start showing up in a lot of laptops and now the market demand might start leaning that direction right as
We finally get this problem checked off. Is it do you see what I'm saying?
Like it feels like as long as we're finding this uphill battle. It's we might never really be on time with the market demand
Do you think it's possible?
So I absolutely think it's possible and of course with AMD right now. It's a lot of potential
But we're not at the point where even if they were to say tomorrow. Yeah, well, let's go ahead and release this
You're talking about 2018 by the time they actually have something that's you know into a product
Yeah, and and I also think feel like right now
It's a lot more talk than it is actual product and the reason is because now is the time where they can talk about it
And have the you know, the theories start, you know spewing around and at the end of the day
It's going to be a business decision and you know and where in their triage list is it going to be to release the source
Code for the a Giza binary, right? It's going to be it's going to be way down their triage list
You know, but we but we're still we're pushing for AMD to to release it
And as well as pushing with Intel to say we want an emulous design
The you know the cryptographic bond and the goal for a lot of these corporations to you know
Really lock up a lot that you can start to see
especially with the CIA vault 7 release that
It's clear that at least the CIA as well as the tools that they were using
That they have the philosophy right if you were to ask me
Hey, you know, I want to I want to hack all the encrypted communication services on Android phones
How should I do that?
I would say go a level lower than the application right target the operating system and you own everything above it or the base
man goes more
Yeah, so the same way goes for
Management engine or obviously phones which with the baseband which were we're working on
We actually have all of our hardware specification ready for manufacturing a phone
That'll come out in 2018. So these are all things that that we're really concerned about
But to answer your question about you know, where's the market demand? Is it going to shift from underneath us?
I think where everything is trending right now is
That digital rights for users are getting stripped privacy is getting worse
and and the
Those who want to have access to your data or your devices is growing in number. Mm-hmm. Yeah, I think it's a market
I think it's a market that's gonna just get and more and more leaks
They're just gonna keep coming out Joe you had a question about working with Intel. Go ahead
Yes, so Todd when you originally launched your crowdfunding campaign and everything you were very positive and very optimistic about working with Intel
and trying to get the
You know the various binaries freed
Presumably you've come up against quite a lot of walls with Intel
You know, I just wanted to ask, you know, is your optimism still there?
I mean you've talked about what you want to happen. But I mean what you realistically think can happen and that's really what I'm getting at
here sure, that's a great question, so
One of the great things about buying product from Intel is that we're cutting checks to Intel
And so therefore we have account managers and we have therefore dollar leverage now
Our dollar leverage is obviously a whole lot smaller than Google
but the as we grow then our dollar leverage starts to increase where we can start making demands to Intel and they'll start to
Actually listen, so we have submitted, you know a petition. We've talked with Intel about you know, creating an MULS design
Actually, that's they came up with the name from us discussing it that there wasn't anybody talking with Intel about having an MULS design
So as an example Google once they had core boot running then they were perfectly fine with getting using the MRC bin that they
used from Intel's FSP binary, so
Google at that point was, you know, content with core boot running even though they're using that binary and we're just
digging levels deeper, so
for us we're looking at
Having our solution in parallel
There's actually three parallel paths
The first is communicating to Intel our intent and what we want and then they in turn actually share documentation
You know BIOS writing documentation so that we can start to find
Oh, you know, maybe there is something actually within the existing documentation that nobody's been able to really exploit
Such an example as the being able to disable the management engine from NVRAM
fuses on the CPU so those are
Some things that Intel is helping with
Oh, so the fusing tip came from Intel's documentation?
That's correct. Oh, okay. Yes. So that's one where by having an account manager and having access to
Documentation allows us to have more knowledge than let's say just you know
Someone else just trying to you know, plunk away and hack or reverse engineer
Yeah, try to trigger things out that way. So and their their documentation Intel's documentation is
immense, right so
So we have a lot that we can end up doing that way. That's the first Avenue
That's basically working with Intel saying hey, you know, you're not the enemy right? We we want to continue to use your hardware
We want to purchase from you
But these are the goals that we want then the second option is you know that that we by using the documentation?
Find our own way to you know, either modify code or disable the ME
one of the nice things here is that since it's not actually hostile towards Intel because we're not trying to reverse engineer and release like
A management injury and replacement, right? What we're trying to do is just not use it period so that's
Not a hostile relationship with Intel to go down that path
And then the third path of course is is looking at alternatives, right?
What do we end up wanting to use AMD or do we want to actually scrap it and go to something?
It's really low-powered. So with AMD's talk that ends up helping us with the leverage where we could possibly switch to AMD or
continue to talk with Intel about you know about switching so
So I am very optimistic because you know, I get to read through the documentation on you know
The me design for BIOS writing guide. It's a you know, 192 page document
So Intel has very deep knowledge and and documentation on on areas that you'd be really surprised about so
So that to answer your question is that Intel is I'm very optimistic because Intel has been helpful
In providing documentation and the long-term game
It might very well be that they don't put out an ME list design and we end up finding it something ourselves through their documentation
Or maybe in you know in a much later version that they say that there is a market demand for that and then they then
They offer that up. So I guess Todd. Here's what I here's here's the pessimist in me because I see it almost feels like two
scenarios
scenario one is a
triumphant
Arrival at some solution that
Essentially gives people the ability to use Libre boot to bypass and disable Intel management engine and and everybody's happy less blobs
Everybody's happy
but all of that work will just quickly be snapped up by vendors like system 76 and intro where and so
There won't be a there won't be a market advantage that lasts very long. So that's scenario one
Oh scenario two though, but scenario two would be that Intel just decides to do this and then everybody gets it and
Market advantages also lost there. So what's the what's the upside for purism long-term here, right?
So there's a couple pieces. So first of all, you have to be running core boot
So if your machines not ported to core boot, then you're then you have to do that port
So it's not like by us disabling the ME. Okay, and it's right that you still have that would be within the range of other
OEMs or especially those that are getting more serious about their own manufacturing. It seems like they could be within their capability
Oh, yeah, absolutely. They would just need to say I'm gonna invest and actually have that ported. So that's that's step one
But of course right now you're there. There isn't it. Everybody's using
EFI or UFI except except Chromebooks, right? So or you know
Pre 2008 machines right lever boot based machines. Yeah
So so that is obviously an advantage that we would end up having over others is that we're investing in that space
To have a really depth of credibility on the security side. That's true. Yeah, so okay then so that's you know point one. So but
Yes of system 76 or or even you know, let's say Dell decided. Hey, you know what?
We we don't like all these threats coming in from vault 7 where all of our machines are gutted because it's an EFI threat
That they could end up putting core boot on at that point then they would still be using the default installs from Intel
Then they would have to actually go through the fuses that we have and of course we'll publish what you know fuses word targeting
Because it actually helps users so
So then it would basically they'll be paying playing catch-up
But the question is are they gonna want to have the same depth of credibility that we have if they're installing Windows the depth of
Credibility is completely right. Yeah, it seems like you yeah
I guess your point there is by by dredging this journey
you'll establish the purism brand as sort of being like that not only one of the first on the scene with it, but also
Having expertise with it, which is obviously going to give it some credibility
So I I guess I guess that is a good point
But what about if Intel just decides to play ball? Do you feel like? That's still a net win for purism
I do and the reason is because then it actually allows the users to control it
Which would be that the ME is going to be on by default. That's just how it's going to be so
You know a manufacturer or reseller who has access to being able to fuse the CPU
Would be able to so our proposal to Intel is actually to opt to add one of the fuses that we have
One of the fuses that we get as a manufacturer because we get the CPUs in manufacturing mode
So then we have the capabilities to fuse the CPU and right now
we have 14 fuses that we can fuse and I were saying make a 15th fuse that allows us to actually disable the ME and
You can ship it where they'll be you know that it can be fused by default
But we can we can achieve it'll have the ME by default and then we can fuse the CPU during the fabrication process
To disable the ME and then that that's all we need so in that case then you know it it
Accomplishes a few things the first is that
We would then have a CPU that from Intel
It's Intel supported that would allow us to be able to disable at the lowest level a core that we don't need
The second piece is then it doesn't change that for any of their other
Buyers right because they would they would get what they had to be in and then they would likely would not be all that
Encouraged or motivated to make a change like going back to Lenovo or somebody because they are even pushing this if they were
Yeah, that's exactly right. Okay. That's a that makes sense all right Wow okay?
Well, I'm glad you guys are working on this because you know I go back going back to wimpy
I imagine wimpy your goal here is to have something that's sort of a unique fully open source stacked machine, right?
Are you gonna put like triskel on this thing, or what's what's your plan wimpy? It was shipped with triskel seven oh?
Really? Yeah, yeah, are you gonna get it or is this a mate test machine like what's going on here wimpy?
What's your what's your and why why this machine? It's it's a curiosity okay?
You know I as we said earlier. You know there's some Bitcoin
value at the moment
there are some unusual items floating around and this was one of them and
I was interested to have one of these and actually have a poke around with it and that yeah retrofitting
You know the the core boot Libre boot on these devices is not is non-trivial
Oh, so I wanted to have a play and see what it can do and what it's doing the first thing
I've noticed boots very fast that that initialization piece is I bet shockingly quick
It makes that old machine seem quite pokey. I've heard that yeah, I've heard that I've had the same curiosity as you
and so is this
Is that is the end goal here to experiment with just the just the process?
Yeah, it's just it's just another interesting bit of technology. I'd like to learn more about and I've had a helping hand in that
I haven't had to
Wrestle the laptop open and put it under my rather dodgy soldering skills somebody else has done that for me is an SSD
Yeah, so it's been refurbished. So they they've fitted it with a qualcomm atheros
wireless end card and a Samsung
850 256 gig and it's got eight make eight gigs of RAM in it as well. So it's like a full
Yeah, yeah, actually better not your laptop where's I could yeah, I bet you the performance is not that bad
It's actually very decent. It's actually very decent. Yeah, and I've got a I've got a
An X to a one which I've had for a while
So I I know how to compare the performance, you know, because the tour ones a little bit newer
And yeah
The thing that surprised me because it's obviously got the SSD in it is just how quick the machine comes on and actually starts
Booting so it comes up fast
But it's just not having to sit around and wait around for the BIOS and EFI to happen
It's very quick
But it's still a core to do isn't it?
Yeah, yeah
I mean I've not done much with it
Like I say, I've literally turned it on being impressed by the boot speed and done the updates on the box
I've not actually tried to use it for anything
Serious. Yeah, I'll get to that. Huh? I kind of want to check back in if I remember I won't be here next week
Oh, I won't be yeah, so I'm gonna be on the road next week. I think we're gonna I don't know who's gonna guest
I haven't we get to find out. Yeah, I so much going on
I haven't it might just be West so everybody show up in the Mamba room. Everybody everybody have a lot of fun
However, I do have this computer set up
So if we do have a guest they'll be able to call in and they'll be able to talk to mom
We'll be able to hear them. So we'll see we'll see what happens
We may have a surprise guest host next week, but maybe in a couple weeks
I'll check in wimpy and see what you think. I think that I think I think
I think we may talk about it on the Ubuntu podcast. So you can
Surprise go find wimpy over there surprise and also poppies on there so you can find poppy also, but he's not here today
Oh, yeah, the Ubuntu podcast a one of the one of the podcast
I am subscribed to you can also Joe Joe is on Linux late-night Linux
I almost call the Linux after dark again, because I keep thinking the screensaver
I know I'm sorry. I'm sorry and that's a great show too. So go subscribe to that as well
It turns out it turns out despite what might be going on with those guys over at Linux action
She can't trust him. Don't trust those guys. The unplugged show is sticking around here. So what will be here?
I might not be here, but we'll all be next week. It's a community. That's what makes it
You know, I thought about trying to join in mumble, but I was looking at the timing for next week. Yeah, and I
Just you'll be driving like a bad man. I think it's gonna be like peak driving
I think it's gonna be like an 11-hour day for me driving. Well Dylan's going along right just pop him up at the wheel
Yeah, well Hadid offered like oh I could drive for a bit. Oh, yeah, you know the thing is it's not just driving
It's like then you don't know where you're gonna be reception wise either because you're moving so much
So I just feel like I would be a board in the past
I'm sorry from a car man. That would be unbelievable, wouldn't it? Yeah, somebody no never that would never happen Joe
That would never happen. That's I'm heard of somebody joins from a car never crazy. Yeah
Hey, by the way mumbles on Android, so we'll see what happens
But I think well something something something will happen next week. Just got to tune and find out
We'll keep it fresh there will be sure there will be a show as long as these guys can figure out how to turn on
The studio which I think you've got I think you got it
I just stroked the beard the magic beard and everything comes up when I asked the beard about he said yeah
I mean, I think so. I mean the show might just be late. Yeah
That's fine, I suppose that really is fine
You tune in over JB live TV and you don't have to worry about it
You just get to watch the show go down and I know it won't be here to bail you guys out
Yeah, cuz he's gonna be flying right? Yeah, we're gonna be in Tejas
Meeting up with Dell. I wonder if they'll have any XPS 15s in the lab that I can check out go fine
If you see one of the hallway just snag it. Yeah, man. Totally. All right
Well that does bring us to the end of this week's episode of the unplugged program
Thank you for joining us. You can go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar to get our live time in your local
time of neck of the woods thing
Time zone thing also Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact for feedback
Linux action show at our reddit comm for potential updates and projects
Yeah, join us live in the mumble room to get information in our chat room. See you next week
Well, they will I'm out of here
See you guys
And we canonical a lesson
Bob it up that Bob it up. Alright, so JB titles calm. Let's go do our title thing now
I know that Nick lob who I almost want to call Nick Bob in the show had a question
Regarding the Intel management engine probably for Todd. So Nick go ahead
Are you I saw you asking you get first go?
Hello
Thoughts left actually just a second ago. Oh
He did. Oh, was it for him? Okay. Well, thanks Todd for joining us. Goodbye
Maybe it was our sick tunes drove them away
Jail that whale. What's that a reference to? Oh the docker stuff. That's pretty good. That's pretty good
Boot free or die trying that was my suggestion
Like it
Who should I have a guest co-host next week, who should I ask because obviously I can't make them do it, right? Who should I invite?
Takes we won't put my lap on right now
Chase just to throw it as a wild card. I feel like I feel like I could ask Joe
But I feel like it's a lot asking that's a lot of Joe
I mean, that's a lot asking a lot of Joe. But yeah, that would be good
That would be good for people to get to meet Joe. That's a good mix it up. Have my core
I'd have to not be in my car, but I could work something out
Yeah, that we don't want to impose too much on you. So I have Skype set up here and Joe could call it
All right. I like this Joe
The bus I'm gonna go with it Joe if you're down for it boy that shirt so that solves my problem right there and I
Actually probably is a good chance for the JB honest to get to meet you. Yeah
Digital ocean is like and honestly, there you go. Yeah, that helps
I heard the read in the plug for the affiliate in late night Linux in it. Yeah, it's legit
All right, awesome, well, that's awesome Joe, thank you
Alright, so I'll just you can just be able to Skype to Jupiter broadcasting it in West
You'll be able to just should I think I'll set it to automatically login
Cool well, that's awesome. Thank you guys. Well, that's that's excellent and wimpy. I'm glad I'm officially Joe's agent now. Yeah, right
financial attractions
transactions
Whoa, there's Skype there's Skype, you know, I'm gonna do I'm gonna log into Skype
I'm gonna turn off all of the notifications for you right now West. I'm gonna hook you up with those. Yeah, I hate those so much
And wimpy I owe you a beer or two. That's for sure
But yeah beers only redeemable at Linux fest Northwest
I'm gonna pull my finger out and sort my travel out this weekend at a boy. I'll be in touch