We have we have something kind of unusual for the unplugged show we have a
Well a real lug member. I guess not a virtual lug member Anthony is right here in the trailer with me. Hey Anthony
Hey, how y'all doing? I love your this so let me paint the picture for you guys Anthony is rocking a last jacket
It's a little warm, too. You're rocking a last jacket and then underneath it Linux fest Northwest 2015
That's how'd you get that jacket that shirt picked it up back in the spring mm-hmm when you were at?
Linux best North there you go
So did you make the drive did you drive all the way from here cuz I could now tell you officially
That's a long-ass drive. Oh, yeah to me. I don't know it's I go to Seattle a lot
So it's like to me is I guess that's nine hours, right? It's nine hours. Not too bad. Okay in ten hours
Yeah, nine ten hours. Not too bad. All right. Do you do it all in one drive? Oh, yeah, okay?
So you're crazy then I do you do it in your car. Yeah, all right you podcast the whole way
Yeah, now you do something right? I am a vlogger. Yeah, yeah, YouTube vlogger, so tell me about that
Um I vlog my life and my experiences with the Linux and computers. Are you oh really Linux isn't it mm-hmm?
Are you gonna vlog this you know what I'm gonna have to yeah
You got a camera over there, huh?
Yep, yep. Oh boy. Oh boy. Okay. You guys. I don't I don't know if I
Okay, now he's pulling out the camera right now. I'm painting a picture for you. Oh now. It's on me now
How did this have this supposed to be an audio show turn the tables on Chris last I love it
Now he's on video. Yeah now mom video right there. Hello everybody. Hey, it's a 4k camera here
Here's the JB rover in 4k everybody is that 4k. Yeah, wow I guess if you're doing YouTube right you should do 4k
Yeah, I just recently got into 4 take 4k. Yeah, how much was that? That's nice about 600 bucks. Oh, she's bad alright alright
No, I want another toy now. Yeah, I bet you know that you know there
Are there are a few things that come out a lot of times?
I think it's just marketing like when it comes to 4g or something like that
I'm like ah just a new way of marketing the same old thing, but when it comes to 4k
There are very clear defined advantages that nobody can deny
That make it really really really compelling to spend some money on something like a 4k camera, right?
It's it's beautiful when you actually even on a 1080 display
It still looks very very good right and you use it for do you do you like the super zoom effect you?
But you're releasing 4k, so you're probably not doing I see. I'm getting ready to release in 4k. I just recently upgraded to this
Because the new Lightworks beta is now supporting. Are you editing? Okay? Yes, I do everything on Linux
Yeah, he's doing you know he's doing everything under Linux. How about that awesome brother?
He's doing 4k. No you better step it up. I know I know well
Here's that here's the thing if I if if it give me this alright
Give me this the user interface like the layout of Lightworks is like it's horrible right like the workflow is pretty bad
I don't know
I actually it kind of grows on you because I've spent a lot of time in the program when I first first few months
Yeah, it was the worst thing in the planet to learn and now that I'm kind of learning
It's in and out somewhere everything's kind of hidden
I feel like it's it's just on the power level of like premiere. What do you use for encoding?
What do you what do you code out from Lightworks or using an FFmpeg once you get it out of it works?
I go straight from my camera load it up into the Lightworks
Yeah, and then just export it out of light
I'm just export it out and Lightworks handles all the encoding all that news and throw it right up on YouTube. Yep nice
That's not bad. All right. All right. I got to give that a shot the the thing about like so you've used premiere
So then you'll know what I'm talking about. I feel like every other
Audio product or a video production suite like I can even if I've never used it before if you just
Screw around with it a little bit. You can figure it out man
I bang my head against the desk for weeks trying to figure out Lightworks and I never did figure it out
and what I ended up doing was they have a
fantastic set of tutorials on
YouTube and you can go through and they teach you how to do all the stuff and like you said once you kind of get
Into their mindset and I almost and tell me if you agree with this. I almost treat Lightworks like an operating system
It feels very immersive because it just kind of takes over the entire machine and then you do all of the stuff
Inside of Lightworks itself, so you don't ever really leave the program
And if it turns your editing machine into like an appliance, right?
And if you do a monitor sport because your monitors are a mess
You need especially if you need research on the other side other monitor or doing other things like checking Twitter's and whatnot
You know, yeah
Yeah
But the one thing that I think that Lightworks has a leg up on pretty much every other video editor
I've ever used is the fact that when you do that
When you treat it like an operating system like it takes over all your monitors
The like the preview screen you can make it as big or as small as you want
You can place it anywhere on the quote-unquote workspace that you want
and
Mind you I haven't used some of the latter versions of Premiere some of the latter versions of Final Cut
So perhaps these features do exist now
But when I was previously when I was using them
It seemed like there was like kind of a stock layout how they wanted you to to kind of do things and where the toolbars
Were located and and that was kind of static. There was no real way to change that and with Lightworks
Everything is dynamic. Everything can be moved to wherever you best think it should be. Oh
Yeah, and did you know this shark actually eats some of the windows? I actually hate that
I didn't it was funny like I actually wrote into the form and I'm like
Is there a way to get rid of that shark and they go that's part of the sex appeal of Lightworks as we leave the shark
There and I'm like, right, but it literally destroys the corner of my screen and I can't get rid of it
And then it's like over all my windows and they're like, yeah, that's kind of the fun
But you can you can drag it up and then it like sinks back down. I'm like, right?
well, yeah, you can you can actually go over windows and it'll the shark will eat it Wow and then when you left-click the
Shark all your all your eating windows will pop back up. So we got a lot of things going on on the screen
So there is shark it almost some functionality there. Yeah, there's a function in there. Yeah, it's called shark. Okay. All right
I'll give them that then
Yeah, I I don't know. I just don't wish there was a way to turn it off. I can't say I'm a fan. I I
I the there there are there are I just saw actually actually for anyone that's interested
They're actually running a sale today. I
Just got I just got an email from the University
50% off Lightworks Pro
for for the for the editor so you can get access to all of the
Kodaks and the way that Lightworks structures or licensing is actually pretty cool
You can pay a one-time fee a large fee like you would for Adobe Premiere or Final Cut and then you buy that version of
Lightworks and it's yours forever
And so you download it and then you install it and then you're stuck on that version now the way that I do it is
I pay something like 89 bucks a year and I get the latest version as soon as it comes out
For you know indefinitely, but the trade-off is I'm paying a recurring fee and at first I was a little against that actually
I thought to myself. I don't like I feel like I'm just renting software
I don't feel like I actually own the software and it kind of bothers me and then a buddy of mine said
Let me ask you something. How much did you pay for at the time?
I think it was it was Final Cut that I was using and I said it was a couple, you know
High hundreds of dollars if I remember right at least back in the day. Yeah. Yeah seven
I think was the last one I bought it. I want to say Chris. Does this sound right seven or eight hundred bucks?
Hey, well, if you bought it at its peak Final Cut seven might have even been you got the full Final Cut suite
It could have been twelve hundred dollars. Yeah. Yeah, it was it was it was it was Final Cut and then it was motion
And then that's the twelve hundred dollar one. Yeah. Yeah, I think I got a bit of a discount cuz I remember
I think it was under a gram, but I remember being a significant amount of money and
When I and then then I was talking to him about and he goes how long did you use it?
I said, oh, you know three four years and he goes great
So it'd be half the cost man to just pay the 89 bucks a year
And if you you're never gonna keep the software for ten years, and I thought about it
I'm like, yeah, he's right. When would I use one version of software for ten years? I would that would never happen
That's true. Yeah, and you know so for some reason though that same logic doesn't come for me about Adobe Creative Cloud because we have
Adobe Creative Cloud because we have JB has a subscription to Creative Cloud for a couple of machines
none of the machines that I use well not frequently but
The it that burns me that for some reason paying for Creative Cloud burns me. I don't know why
If maybe maybe it's because it's it probably mainly actually I actually probably would have zero issue
Paying for it if they made Creative Cloud work on Linux then I yeah
Yeah, then I could do it and maybe if it was a little less irritating with constantly reminding you
Yeah, thank you. Yes that too. I think as free software people I think is open-source people
I think as Linux people I think that I think what it is is I think we have it ingrained in our head
That subscription leans leads to us getting burned because I have been burned so many times by a company who?
Existed and then the company goes away and so I can't renew my subscription or reactivate the software and let's take for example
Lightworks, let's just say here's here's what is a very realistic prospect
Seven years from now
Maybe edit share goes out of business and then my subscription thing goes down the tubes because I never bought it outright and so I
No longer have access to Lightworks. All I can do is start it up and I get to a login screen
I have all of my projects for the past ten years that right now I can open them back up and make any edits
I want change anything. I want
Re export them if if tomorrow a different Kodak comes out and everyone wants it in a different format and now Lightworks supports that I
Could open that project file up with my raw video and export back out into this new format. I could do all of that
Until I no longer have access to the software and then all of that that the all those options go away and essentially I have
been archiving all those project files for years for nothing and I think that as
As people that have been burned by that in the past
I think that people like you and I Chris I think we're and West I think that we are aware of that
And I think that I and I think that so then when it comes down to it
Even if we can't always put our finger on it
And even if it doesn't make sense on paper paying twelve hundred dollars as a one-time fee versus 89 bucks a year
I think it just makes it in our in our ethos and in and deep inside of us
I think we know that there is an inherent danger. There's inherent risk associated with that and so we shy away from it
I think anytime you've been around even for a few years
You realize that a lot of times commercial companies are more dictated by the whims of the market
Then they will try to present even companies like Adobe and other really big companies
They are very much driven by the next new shiny the next new thing that's going to generate profit and they're not
You know that doesn't and I'm not I'm not making a comment if that's bad or good because in some ways
That's what pushes things forward
But in another way it it also means abandoning previous ways of doing things and one of the things
I this is just me being you know
Maybe I've been looking at the hills of Montana for too long
but I really kind of look back at some of the stuff that we create in these proprietary formats these proprietary containers and
And I think this is stuff that is gonna be generationally lost
It's a generation is generational problem
It is an entire generation of people that are going to lose access to the content that they have created be it
Videos or photos or music?
I mean anything that's stored in a garage band file anything that's stored in a logic file
That's probably not gonna open in a hundred years and maybe maybe your crappy music doesn't need to open up in a hundred years
But wouldn't it be neat if a hundred years from now a family member or a historian or somebody could access a perfect digital
pristine copy of what you created a hundred years ago and be able to listen to it or watch it and the only thing preventing
Them from be able to do that is some proprietary codec or some a proprietary format or some lockdown application
And when you think about in that context, it's it's a real shame
It's a real shame actually if you think about it, too
Let you look at like when when my when my grandfather passed away him and I were very close
And so I was I was really interested in learning about his life before
Before me before I knew him as grandpa. I wanted to know, you know what the rest of his life was like and
We found pictures and documents and all this stuff that he had from back when he was in the military when he was 18 19
Years old and I found that I found that two days before he graduated high school
Was what I found his enlistment application and it was dated two days before
He he graduated high school and it was just interesting to look and see that was you know
That was him as he was an Air Force guy
I'm like, wow, I can't imagine like before I even get out of high school saying this is what I'm gonna commit the next
You know for sure at least eight years of my life
but then 30 years and the only reason I was able to go back and have that connection with him was because I found these
documents and I found the pictures and stuff like that and
Like you're talking about in in in 50 my grandkids. I don't have I haven't taken pictures of my kids that we print out
They're on Facebook and they're on Twitter. There's I have tons of them on a hard drive as I do video, right?
Yeah, who knows what is JPEG gonna open in a hundred years? I don't know. I mean, I hope so. I think so
So yeah, I think that I so I I think that there is I think there's a real concern of that
I think we have to be careful
This is Linux unplugged episode 111 for September 22nd 2015
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly tech
Talk show that's being brought to you from well
It kind of depends upon the hour and the current geographical location of JB rover
My name is Noah and joining me is
Wes
Hey, it's Wes guys. Wes is
joining me in
Seattle in the studio and then I'm actually in Grand Forks hosting the show and then Chris
The hair master Chris is actually in JB rover right now in the middle of Montana
Hello guys. Hi, how is Montana?
Well, I found a spot that has connectivity and it's actually quite pleasant here
And it's it there's time differences and all these kinds of things. It's a lot of fun
I get to struggle with time math. I get to find cellular connectivity and I get to be part of the virtual log
I'm pretty excited. That sounds amazing. And I heard that you found a I first heard that you found a straggler
That's right
Actually to be totally correct. He found me. Hey Anthony. Hey, what's going on? Not much
so Anthony I was tracking us over Jupiter broadcasting comm slash rover and
He saw us parked here. We're in a gravel lot. We were driving around literally Noah
We were driving around trying to find the best signal possible. We found like stop the vehicle stop the vehicle
We pulled over right here
Anthony was watching us in real time on the rover because he knew we were getting the best chicken in town
Oh, yeah, and then
That he when we got parked I started set up he came knocking on the door
No
I swear I started to almost panic because I thought it was the cops telling me to get the heck out of here
Well, you had you had that particular spot you would stopped because of a very specific technical reason, right?
It wasn't just like you were like, wow, this seems like a good place to park
That's true. Well, I had to get good signal. I had to have good connection. I had that. Hello music. Hi there
Go go go go. Yeah
I wanted to make sure that we were able to get a good spot solid spot
so that way we could get the prep the show prep necessary done and like there was like
Different sections of the city that would have no cellular coverage at all. Like that's a thing around here. Oh, yeah
Oh, yeah, it's just part of the challenge is part of the fun. Yeah, wait life is up here
You know you go one block you have no signal, right?
So we found this spot here we set up and now the only downside is we don't have any shore power here
So everything we're doing right now is completely running off of DC battery
So hopefully we'll last we got we got the my five plugged in to the DC outlet
We're running both laptops off of battery power and the mixer itself is as you know
Noah is able to run off of 9-volt batteries
So we're running the mixer off of batteries right now, too. Oh good. You had to change them though. I heard
Just when we were about to start the show
Literally right like everything's all dialed in Noah and it's like all these different challenges because I didn't I didn't quite plan to have two
People in the rover, but Anthony was totally prepared brought his own microphone. It's a gold mic too. Yeah. Yeah, it's a gold mic
That's awesome. But we didn't so we got everything wired and I'm like look at us
We managed to get two people set up right on and then all of a sudden no audio
Zoom and we're like what what's going on?
What is but it was it was enough power to still show power light on the mixer
But not enough power to send phantom power to the microphones
So the mics themselves were dead, but the mixer had enough power
So thankfully you included a nice box of 9-volt battery
So I just plugged another three in and we're good to go. Oh good the you know
It's funny is when I bought that mixer the guy specifically told me he's like it will run forever
without a battery change and being as you've been on the road for going on 72 hours and
You've done attempted one show and this is the first one. We're going all the way through. I'm gonna guess that's not the case
Unless you left it on the whole time. No, I did not leave it on. I didn't think so
Do you have to think though? It's if you think about it, so there are three nine volt batteries that are in there, right?
So yes three nine volts. So math tells us that's nine eighteen
Nineteen twenty four. Is that right?
Yes. Okay, so
48 volts is what's required for the phantom power
And so I guess that would kind of make sense that they would essentially what they're doing is they're getting half of the voltage and then
Probably doubling it to power the phantom power
But that's a lot that's twice the amount of voltage draw on on on each of those batteries
So it would make some I guess that 27. Yeah. Yeah, Matt and now we're also we're powering two microphones now
Yeah, well there are do you have dynamic mics or condenser mics?
There there one. What is your mic? I have the re20. What's yours? Yeah, it's a condenser mic
Yeah, it is condensers. You know what? I don't know. It was a cheap one on Amazon. I did it for game
I use phantom for the re20 because it powers the amp is powered by phantom
Huh?
So anyways, but you know
The the thing that's actually a little more interesting about about the rover is I'm actually I'm finding some challenges some challenges with DC
Power that I didn't expect so I'm not I'm hitting some speed bumps there
But other than that, we're all good and you have you have your you brought the the XPS 13 with you, right?
Yes, sir. Now, is that running enter goes?
Yes, sir. All right. So I saw that we are talking about enter goes today and
That is we are going to talk about supporting enter goes now
Here's the thing the first time I ever did arch
When you got when back when you and Matt actually did the Linux action show and talked about how we should switch to arch
I was game. I thought I'll give it a shot
I don't really think I'm gonna stick with it, but we'll see what it's like now
I'm too lazy to read the wiki which is what everyone which is what a good arch user should do and in fact
Oh, yeah, exactly. You can see where this is going, right?
So what I did was I did what I call the way of the future
Which is when your dishwasher breaks, you don't break out the manual anymore when your refrigerator breaks
You don't break out the manual. What do you do? You go to YouTube and type in the problem and see if somebody walks you
Through so that's what I did
By the way
That's also what you do when you can't remember if you put the sway bars on your hitch
When it's up a little bit or down all the way
It up if I remember right? Yeah, it works much better. You can get it. You can get a few more links in the chain
So I went to YouTube and I looked how to install arch and there was this guy
He pronounced a bunch of words wrong despite making claims that he was pronouncing them
Correct, and then and then went through it and and and went through the installation at March
And after I got done, I was like I could do that
It'll take me about an hour
but I could do that so I grab a spare computer and I installed arch and when I got done I was happy I
Was most I was 90% happy with the experience and I was 90% happy with the result
But my problem was I was afraid to go back and change anything
I was afraid to blow it away and do it all over again because there was no way I was gonna be able to reload
My laptop, you know in the 20 minutes that I've become accustomed to and so anytime I would travel
I would never take my laptop with me because I thought if anything ever happens
I have to have an internet connection and I have to have like an hour of time and not to mention my guide
Which I was keeping on an Evernote so I'd have it on my on my phone
So I'd have all the steps written down because I remember them
So it was just kind of problematic and I thought so it's a great operating system and I really like arch
But I don't think I could ever seriously commit to it because of some of those problems and answer goes
completely solve that for me and it did that in that I
Could now treat the Linux installation the at the arch Linux installation
I could have an arch Linux installation
but I could treat it just like every other distro in that I had a USB installer and I stuck it in and I just
clicked next and I waited for the bar to go from left to right made a couple couple of choices along the way and
I had a working Linux distro. Yeah, it's not even I mean you could stop right there
I mean, it's not even the fact that it's arch right this fact that it's just a nice setup usable distro with a good-looking theme
by default and you know, one of the things they're doing now to make arch more approachable is
They are giving you options at installation to do things like enable the long-term support kernel instead of the instead of the kernel gets updated
All the time use the LTS kernel. Do you want to have Samba work out of the box? Check a box
You want an arch user repository tool check a box you want Samba printer support check a box what LibreOffice check a box and all
Yeah, or simple a simple firewall check a box, right and these things all are just one check now
And they make for a very good distro
It doesn't matter if it's arch fedora or Ubuntu
You'd want that on anything and the fact that antergos is making this as part of their installation
It in my opinion takes and it takes arch not just approachable
But when you start talking LTS kernels and things like that
I think it opens up to a whole other realm of use cases and the fact that they're just building that right in there is
smart smart smart
So and well, I'm gonna get your take and I definitely want to get West's take on this too
But a lot of times I feel like when I'm trying a Linux distro out
Essentially what I'm really doing is evaluating the desktop
Having used fedora for so long and so having used gnome 3 for so long
it's not uncommon for me to sit down at my arch box and type yum and
Because of that and that's just because I'm so used to when I see gnome
I just have fedora pictured that's running in the background
And the reality is thus the differences between arch and fedora at least from a usability standpoint once it's set up
It's not much right if I'm primarily interacting with gnome now where antergo sets itself apart
And why I think it's it's a it's a really solid good operating system. In fact in some ways a lot better than fedora is
Well, really it begins and ends with the AUR
Right when I want to try software if I want to try a new piece of software
Especially if we're testing something for the show, I don't grab the Ubuntu box
I certainly don't sit down in my fedora box
I grab my arch laptop and or my antergos laptop and that's because with a single command I can go out and grab
How however the package is packaged whether it's available with source code or whether it's available in a deb or available in RPM
somebody has taken that and putting that into the arch AUR and then I can pull that down onto my laptop and
To me that is such a huge time-saver that feature alone almost trumps everything else
Every other advantage that every other distro could offer it is nice
It's nice to be able to just like install software on the fly while I'm on air
Like a lot of times when you and I are talking about an app on the show
If it's not if you if you convinced me to try it
I'll just install it right there on the show and try it. So I know Wes
I'm gonna jump to you for a second. But Anthony, what are you using for Linux? What's your main distro?
My main distro is arch. Oh really and Wes your main distros arch too, right?
Sure is has been for three years or so. Jeez. Listen to us. Oh my gosh. Well, it's funny. It's later in the show today
I might confess my love for fedora. I don't know. You know, there's a couple of things
I note where I'm offline and having to update a rolling distro on over a cellular connection is getting old
Super fast, so I don't know. I don't want to say we're all a bunch of arch bitch bigots
But it is now no and to be fair though. No, it's not your daily driver, right?
well
I'm not exactly sure how to answer that because I
For the purpose of not getting made fun of by all of my Jupiter broadcasting supportive teammates who constantly make fun of my fedora laptop
I installed on my ThinkPad
I have arch and so everything I do for Jupiter broadcasting all the show prep all of that stuff is being done on my ThinkPad and
Then somewhere along halfway through the year. I decided it was too inconvenient to do all the speed stuff on my Dell and
Jupiter broadcasting stuff on my ThinkPad
but at that point all of my stuff and all of my programs and everything was kind of set up on my ThinkPad so I
just kind of
unintentionally, I guess switch to it full-time and
so
My main laptop is running arch and that is the laptop that sits in front of my face
80% of the day. I have an Ubuntu box. That's that's downstairs at home, and I don't have any particular
I don't have any particular native love for Ubuntu if it was my choice
I'd probably be using fedora, but because Ubuntu is such a successful operating system
It's the one that I point other people to and therefore it becomes it becomes
Extremely important for me to know how to solve the problems on Ubuntu
So I forced myself to use it
So if I'm at home and I'm sitting at my desk
I'm using Ubuntu and I I kind of feel like I have forced myself to do that
It's not so much of a choice. I'm interested though. What got what got you started on on arch west?
you know I was in a bunch of user for a long time before that and
I kind of just wanted to dig in more get into I ran into a couple configuration problems after the initial unity switch
obviously things are a lot more polished now, but that had me digging around in configuration files and
And some forums I'd you know I heard some people using arch and they talked it up a lot
And I was like well is this really that cool and so far. I've been really happy with it
I think what you touched on with the AUR speaks kind of the way arch is built in general with the arch build system
You know you can download the package build for any of the repo files if you want you can modify them
It makes it really easy to add your own files as well
If you just want to make you know turn something that you can only get in a tar GZ
You can make that into a into a regular install
Yeah, speaking of software that speaking of software or solutions that you can get on the fly
over at reddit.com
Slash our slash Linux action show people submit projects that they think we'd be interested in or software
They think we might be interested in and Chris has been talking about how he's trying to move his life
from being connected online to being connected to seeming like he's connected online while simultaneously being offline and
One of the ways that he is going to do that or one of the things that he needs to accomplish that is he
Needs to minimize the amount of traffic that he's sending and so French AP 41 was kind enough to submit when proxy
to the subreddit and
Essentially what went when proxy is is a free portable TCP proxy which makes TCP connections send less data which improves TCP performance
and the throughput over lossy links now if you're sitting on a
Mobile hotspot and I don't care who is providing the mobile hotspot
Connection can be up and down particularly if you don't know within
500 miles where exactly you're gonna be then things really get interesting
And so the ability to limit the amount of traffic that you're sending back and forth becomes really really important
I'm interested Chris. Have you set this up and have you tried it? And if so, how is it working?
You know the other thing, you know, I haven't set it up yet
I just saw this today because he's he's submitted it six hours ago
But the other thing I thought about know is you nailed it right on the over the over the my fight connection anything you can
Do to reduce traffic is killer
But the thing that that struck me is it might also work really well when driving down the road just because it might help
Smooth out that spotting is that you have as you're just driving down the road and there's different, you know
Different you're moving between towers and things like that
And I he likes he warns us to he says don't be fooled or repelled
By its Spartan web page rent when proxy helps by compressing and duplicating data
So it makes things magically faster when you have slow links
He says that seems like that'd be super important if you're sitting in you know, you know trailer
I can't think of I was trying to think as I was reading over the show notes if there was a place that I could
Implement this honestly, you know Grand Forks back in 1997
We had a really bad flood like a super bad flood. And in fact when you come here Chris, I will show you
There's a landmark. It actually looks kind of like a giant penis but
Around the shaft of the statue is a ring and that shows how high the water was back in
1997 and it was it I mean people's houses were literally underwater when we got back into Grand Forks
There were like cars on the roof of garages and stuff like that Wow
Yeah, it was crazy
But here's the good thing that came out of it when they went through to redo the streets and essentially rebuild the city
Somebody somewhere had the brilliant idea of let's bury fiber everywhere in Grand Forks. I'm moving there. Yes. Yeah
Yeah, so we have fiber right up almost right up to our doorstep
There is a multiplexer that's out in the that is at this at the box out in the yard that and then they run copper
into the house, which I think is silly but
The that I have there is no place in in the city or any of the customers that I support where it would ever be
Where it ever be beneficial to me to limit my TCP traffic
So I can't say that this is something that I'm going to try
Simply because I wouldn't know how to really evaluate it
I wouldn't know if it was doing a good job or a bad job
But I think it would be super important if you were in a rover
the other thing that I think that is really helpful to minimize traffic is if you can get your
Certain parts of
Data that you want to send over the internet not coming from your hotspot and my understanding is that the rover live tracker
That isn't using
Your cell phone or a hotspot or anything thing like that?
It's actually updating Jupiter broadcasting comm slash rover that it's updating that live on its own, right?
Yeah, they it's using silver cloud and silver cloud has some
fee associated with it, but
In in all practical purposes, it's just using GPRS, which is like, you know old slow
Lots of coverage but not at all in Montana, right? Yeah, not in all Montana
Well, in fact, where was the dead spot you were noticing?
I'm just when I was watching you come across the border you disappeared until st. Regis. See that's a bummer
But yeah, it's but the nice thing about it is it's a self-contained unit. It has GPS in there
It gets our elevation in there. It does all of that on its own and it uses its own cellular connectivity
So I don't have to worry about any data usage
Now the cool thing about that is if if you were better at math than I am
You could actually figure out based on how far you're going from one place to the other what your speed is
And then you could do some more math and you could figure out even if the even if the device isn't updating you if it
Drops off the map for a little bit. You could figure out about where you are, but people can follow you all the way
From Seattle all the way to Grand Forks and when you get to Grand Forks
We're gonna have a meetup and we're gonna have there's gonna be a big party in Grand Forks. That's what's gonna happen
Yeah, we're gonna have a meetup. We are and and the thing is some people might be thinking
You know, I've gotten all sorts. You would not believe the questions. I've gotten Chris people are asking me things like
You guys have electricity up there. Do you guys it's amazing. You have internet there. How do you have running?
I mean like people there's a guy asked me about an outhouse like really no, we have plumbing. Come on
This I mean, it's not a third world country. It's we live in the United States. I mean, it's it's a city
It's just like Arlington. It just you know a little colder and a little further away and there's not much around
There's some cows and it's really flat, but it's a city
And so you're gonna find out exactly
What a party is when?
When Chris gets here to Grand Forks, I think tentatively it's scheduled for Sunday
The Sunday that Chris is gonna be here which this this coming Sunday at 7 o'clock p.m. Now that time is a little bit flexible
obviously
I didn't talk to Chris about it
Albert just asked me if if this would work and I'm like, yeah, sure when we can change it
so if if there are some people because I imagine it's gonna be a
Slightly smaller group than in some of the other larger cities if there's anyone out there that
Wants to come to the meetup and and Sunday is a bad day or Sunday at 7 is a bad time
Just get a hold of us go over to there's a form. There's no well, there's a forum thread there, too
So you think you can use the contact page, but there's also the forum thread at meetup, which Albert's monitoring
That's not that time should work for us and I think we're planning to do last Friday still so that she yeah
Yeah time, but yeah that the other thing too
By the way, I'll just mention is if there's other people along our route that want to meet up
You can use that forum there Albert's watch watching that. In fact, why don't we can we pull Odyssey down here?
I don't know if we can or not. But yeah, hello. Hello, mr. Westress. So
Did you want to mention anything about the meetup page?
I was just gonna say the meetup form you're monitoring that if people along the way want to meet up or if people need to make
Modifications that's a good way to get a hold of you, right?
In fact meetup comm slash Jupiter broadcasting. He just opened up the Grand Forks meetup page right now
So if anybody is gonna be in that area and would like to meet up with us
I go to meetup comm slash Jupiter broadcasting. We have two RSVP right now not enough
Not enough mana and those that link will be in the show notes, too. So if
Somehow that's not if meetup comm slash Jupiter broadcasting isn't easy enough to remember
Denny Milligan shown it. So one of the things is
Chris and I have been working back and forth on
Getting a mobile studio and and getting this, you know
The tracking thing set up and there there's all these different moving parts that make it possible for him to do shows from the road
but I think that I think one of the biggest things that he was worried about definitely the biggest thing I was worried about is
mobile connectivity and
The if you're looking for good mobile connectivity you want to look at something like ting if you go over to last dot tinged
I'm sorry is
We're at Linux dot ting.com, right? That's the that's the link for this show
We get Linux dot ting.com, which if you think about it is way better than last dot ting.com branding standpoint
It's like the coolest URL ever
But Linux dot ting.com you go over there and you can pick from a variety of devices now
I have had ting actually the first week that Chris ever
Announced that that ting was a supporter of the show. I was in bed
It was like 3 in the morning and I was I was watching
Linux action show on my laptop and he started talking about ting and as soon as I heard the ad read
I'm like, oh wow that that sounds like something I should be interested in so I
I get up and I go over to my desktop where I had all of my I have all my bills and I'm doing the
Little calculator and my wife looks up and she goes what on God's green earth are you doing at 3 in the morning?
And I'm like, I'm signing up for a new cell phone service. This is amazing
And so I sign up and I get there their cheap little phone
which is only like I think it was 40 40 50 bucks at the time and they still have cheaper phones like that and
But a couple weeks later I had gone to a Linux convention Linux fest Northwest and we were in
We were in
Bellingham and
Myself my regular cell phone died. And so all I was left with was my ting phone
And so ting kind of saved the day that day and ever since then I then then I switched to an actual smartphone and
Then I started buying more and more phones to add them onto the ting network. So I have my dad
I have my mother. I've got my sister. I've got my wife. I've even got a good friend of mine
That's that's all I'm on my my aunt is all of my ting account. And the reason is because it's so cost-effective
it's gonna be
my bill ranges from like $18 to
I'd say 35 40 at the absolute at the at the absolute most
Of course, I haven't looked as I've added as I keep adding people on that that number sure to climb a little bit
But the nice thing is you only pay for what you use
So if you're the kind of person that doesn't make any phone calls like my sister doesn't she texts and she used the Internet?
But she never actually makes any calls. She's not gonna pay for minutes
On the other hand if you're the kind of person that is really really really good at making at finding alternative ways to make calls
So for example, I use my phone on Wi-Fi all the time
So all of my calls are going over data because I'm using sip except it's that's actually being transmitted over Wi-Fi
So I'm not using minutes and I'm not using data and all of my text messages are being sent over Google Hangouts
So that's not using any data and ting is completely cool with that
So go over to go over to linux.ting.com and pick something out
You're gonna be really happy that you did Chris has I think you have you know, what you have three ting devices in your in your RV
To maybe he's got a hotspot and he's got a and he's got a phone
At least and probably a couple more
So the first story we want to talk about and I'm really interested to see what the mumble room thinks of this
we have
It as as some of you know Chris is coming here to look at my automated house
I have automated my house. And in fact, my automated house is actually just one on the market today
but there was a story about a gentleman who
Pioneered a smart home and then his smart home actually ended up with the denial of service. Oh, I love this story
Yeah, have you seen this the challenge of the futurist pioneer is being patent zero for a future day headaches in 2009 Paul Rouse
a computer science professor from the Free University of Berlin
Built Germany's first smart home
Everything in the home was connected to the internet so that the lights television heating and cooling could all be turned on and off from
Afar even the stove oven and microwave could be turned off in Rojas computer
Which prevented some potential panic attacks about leaving the appliances on after he exited the house. This sounds like you know
This sounds like you very much. So in fact, I have such a you know me
I have such an absent-minded memory that things like this
become huge to me the ability to walk into my house and go did I remember to turn that on or did I remember to
Turn that up and then you add to that my incessant laziness of doing repetitive tasks that I think are a waste of time
So for example when I walk into a room
I think the light should just come on because we have these things called motion sensors and it should know that I'm in the room
And if I'm in the room
I want light and I just I find the the concept that I should have to walk over to a specific area of the room
And hit the wall randomly numerous times until I find some sort of tactile device that I can then
Flip up to make the room illuminate and then the room illuminates at a hundred percent brightness
Which I think is total overkill it just it just seems antiquated and ridiculous to me
So yes, this is very me
But one of the last things that were connected to his house were the locks now
I do have my locks automated automated locks Rojas bought in 2009. We're still sitting in a drawer waiting to be installed
I was afraid of not being able to open the doors Rojas said in a phone interview
Now about two years ago Rojas Rojas house froze up and stopped responding to his commands. Nothing worked
I couldn't turn the lights on or off it got stuck
He says it was like a beach ball of death begins spinning on my computer, except it was my entire home
Now this is my wife's worst nightmare right now. So she's listening. I'm gonna get killed when I get home
Because this is what she's worried about
It wasn't quite it wasn't quite as bad as a nightmare on the connected home Street dream dreamt up by wired last year
But it was a fictional smart home's obsolete
Technology gets loaded with viruses and malware and starts misbehaving and uploading naked photos of its owner
Rojas a professor who specializes in artificial intelligence knows his way around the network well enough to cure his own home
And when he investigated it turned out that the culprit was a single connected light bulb
I connected my laptop to the network and looked at the traffic and saw that one unit was sending packets continuously said Rojas
He realized that the light fixture had been burnt out and was trying to tell the hub that it needed its attention
To do so it started sending continuous requests that had overloaded the networking and caused it to freeze
It was a continual denial of service attack. He says
the light was performing a
DDoS attack or a dos attack on my smart home to say change me Rojas change the light bulb and the problem was fixed
So a couple things come to mind first of all
I think that when people automate their house their houses
You have to be first of all aware that you are taking technology and you are putting fundamental
aspects of your life on
The line and so when you your ability to get up and shower in the morning your ability to turn
To turn on to turn at the television to watch things all of that
Is it becomes reliant on your computer system?
And if there's anything we know about computer systems working on computer systems, is that can we can we just stop right here?
Because this is exactly
Exactly my big hesitation even as a fan of technology and and and as somebody who wants to implement some of these things
I start to think to myself, you know, like for example, I mean I hate to be this guy right now
But here in in the JB rover, you know what I like
I like that every single light has its own individual power switch
I like that my water in my shower has a manual cutoff switch that I can hit
I like that every single thing has its own individual control point and they're all manually operated
You know what else I like for some reason I can't tell you why but for some reason I like the ability to turn
My water heater on and off with the flip of a switch in my kitchen or my water pump
Like I like knowing that my fridge can be turned on and off like with these switches here
like I like having manual control over all of this and then here's the other thing Noah is I like to be able to
visually look at the position of that physical switch and I like to know by physically confirming the way it looks what the state of
That object is and all of that's also taken away from you when all of this stuff is automated
So I'm not actually I'm not able to quantify with the advantage of the totally automated home is other than I can do crap
To it remotely, but that seems like a total
total
You know niche niche use case
So I'm hoping to change your mind on that and I think I'll be I think I'm on relatively solid ground to do that
Very very few things in my house are connected to the internet at the very most
They're connected to the LAN and some of them aren't even connected to that a lot of the system
I'd say the majority of the systems are tied together with
something known as normally closed normally open and basically the idea is you have a series of contacts a series of
screws and
dip and either a set of contacts are closed meaning there is a piece of metal that is going between them and
Electricity can flow or the contacts are open meaning there is no piece of electricity and and and electricity cannot flow
I'll give you an example your garage door opener is a normally open circuit
Normally the wires are separated when you push that little button to open your garage door
What you're doing is shorting those two contacts together and that tells the motor start the motor up open the garage door, right?
Now most of the systems in my house the door control system the security system
the
Even yeah, even the light system
most of those are powered by this by this idea of contacts and so
It's a very rudimentary way for one system to talk to the other and it's very very reliable
It's very very I think I can say it's efficient as long as it's all in one room
Obviously if you're gonna put control
Points all over the house that would you know that would limit its efficiency
But right now there's just wires that go from one system to another and the whole system works yet
It really can't be compromised unless you have physical access to it and I have made a I have made a
Strong point not to connect my stuff to the Internet and that's why I've shied away from things like the nest thermostat a lot
Of people have asked why don't you have a nest thermostat?
Well, the reason is I don't like the fact that it relies on a service
I don't like the fact that it talks out to the Internet
I don't like the fact that Google is going to start recording what temperature I like my house that I don't want any of that
I just want the ability for the thermostat to change the temperature depending on if we're in or out of the house and
There are certain things like the lights like the lights and stuff
Which is nice to be able to control from a smartphone, but really I don't need to control that from outside the house
I am a little worried about leaving an appliance on or something like that
But the security implications and the fact that it opens it up to basically the security implications
I guess that's what here's how you sell me on this and I and I am willing to admit that I would have to be
The biggest idiot in the world to be sitting here in Montana on the way to your house to see your automated house
And I would have to be the biggest moron in the world to say I'm not willing to change my mind on this because I'm driving
Halfway across the United States of America to see this
However, what I will tell you is where I sit now is the only way this seems feasible to me is if I could have
Like a one new rack mount style Linux powered rig that everything was wired in over
Ethernet or something into this thing and this was a central hub and I had to have a connection to that and then that
That orchestrated everything for me. I mean if it was like
if it was like as appliance level as installing an alarm system in your home or
Installing like a sprinkler system or an air conditioner. That's the level of appliance. The home automation has to be for me to buy off
how about when you're walking into your house and
You want to give your nanny a key to the house?
And so you give her a key to the house
but she could take that down to Walmart and she could duplicate it right and the other thing is your nanny really only needs to
be there between the hours of 8 and 6 p.m. Because that's when
Your that's when mom and dad are gone at work and that's when the kids need to be watched after it
There's no reason for her to come into your house at 2 in the morning, right?
and so my access control system allows me to
Authorize a key fob and I hand it to somebody and if they I can tell them that they can come in one time
Any hour they're choosing I can tell them that they will come in between these hours on these specific days
or I can tell them they have free access to the house until I decide that they don't and so if at some point I
Have no problem giving you a key to my house Chris
And if at some point we part ways and you think I'm gonna I'm gonna drive all the way back to Grand Forks, North Dakota
I'm gonna sabotage Noah's house. Guess what by the time you get here your key
I just I log in and I shut it back off and now you can't get back into the house
additionally because it's a proximity system I
Have a lanyard that hangs around my neck when I have my hands full of groceries or full of boxes
All I do is just swing the lanyard. It hits the side of the house and the door opens
Those are the kind of automation things that I think that there are very little detractions from I don't really see a downside to it
And I see a ton of advantages
So I'm leveraging the advantages of technology to make my life
easier as same thing with the lights coming on when you walk into my house or when you disarm the security system or when the
Little transponder in my car detects that I've my cars pulled up in the driveway
The entry lights come on and that is to me. There is no disadvantage to that happening
It just saves me that the hassle of having to walk into my house
well, I tell you I'll give you a scenario that does kind of that has crossed my mind is
JB one it would be nice to be able to have to somehow grant access for Wes to be able to say here Wes
Here's a token you can use Bluetooth on your smartphone and now the door will just automatically unlock for you when I'm not there
That sounds great
Yeah, that's the kind of thing that would be kind of nice
I don't know Wes
Have you have you thought at all about I know you kind of got a new place and when you're moving in have you thought?
Out all about home automation and like Hughes lights and any of this kind of stuff when you're moving in you're looking at setting things up
Definitely, you know a big one is I work kind of weird hours as does my wife and we have two dogs
So we've we've been looking at a system where the dogs could be let out and let back in and then maybe once they've come
Back in not let out again. So we're definitely interested in that kind of automation
That's yeah. Yeah that for pet owners and you're working that makes a lack
That's a that's a use case that makes a lot of sense to me
Wes have you seen these pet doors that have a little it's you know
A lot of people will put pet doors in their in their garage and so that the animal can get in and out by itself
But the problem is that creates a potential security hole pun intended for unauthorized people to crawl through the doggy door
Have you seen these little things that the dog wears a little RFID collar and then as the dog approaches the door it unlocks the doggy
Flap the dog can go out the dog can get in but other people can't those are exactly the kind of things
We're looking at we'd like to maybe experiment with making one, you know open source and easily hackable, but we haven't got that far yet
yeah, yeah, I the
Animal seem like anything that my line is I have a couple of hard lines in the sand one is I won't use something that
Requires a service or a company to stay in business to continue using it
totally agreed and
The other thing is I try and stay away from is things that require the internet to work if you turn the internet off in
My house all of my stuff would still work. My doors would unlock my lights would come on
Everything would work just fine with or without the internet
No, have you had any total failure problems like with this light bulb scenario?
the
closest I had to a total failure was we lost power for a couple days in a row and
During that time the the so there are electromagnetic
Locks that lock the doors and so if they're a fail what we would say a fail safe system
It's as opposed to a fail secure system
In other words if it loses power altogether the door defaults to unlock not locked, right?
And that's a safety concern because if I can't I want to be able to get out of my house, right? Yeah, it was definitely so
what I have done is there is a battery backup that will that will automatically kick in should the
Power die and it'll power the house up to 24 to 40 some hours. It was electromagnetic
yeah, so because the electromagnetic locks draw very very little power and so
But once I exhausted more than a day or so
the battery started to die and so what I ended up doing was I I used a
Junction box into the electrical panel so I could switch from the shore power of the city over to
Essentially what amounts to an extension cord that hangs off the side of my house, which was plugged into a generator. Awesome
Yeah
So I started the generator up and I just flipped those switches and then I was able to set
The I was able to switch over and run off of my off of my own
Off of my own power. Do you have any old-style keys at all? Or is it all completely digital?
No, there is the I we left the traditional locks simply for appearance sake Oh
Yeah, really? Yeah
Well when it's kind of weird if you come up to the house and there's there's just a plate over the deadbolt and you need
A handle to you know to open and shut the door so that you'll see locks. They're just they're keyed on both sides
So there's no way for somebody to lock me out of my house
That makes sense. Yeah, I'm really excited to see this Noah. Yeah. No, I think you'll be impressed
But before I move on is there anyone in the mumble room that has that has thoughts or feedback about the about the automated house
actually you
earlier you were talking about how the negatives about it and
I was already excited and you start talking about the negatives and you convince me I didn't want it and then you convince me
Again that I do want it. Oh good. Oh
good, so the mostly the stuff that you were talking about like the doors unlocking automatically, I've seen some some stuff like the
Africa I think it's called the YubiKey
It's like that you is it not the YubiKey
But it's Yubi and it's basically like a a deadbolt that you tap your phone to it and it works
But it requires the internet. So if you actually had something that already does that without any internet, that sounds awesome
Yeah. Yeah. Anyone else have any thoughts either positive or negative?
Yay or nay for home automation. Hey, no, how many how much research did you put into this because it sounds like you looked into
Ambitious nuts and bolts on this, you know, I really did and so what it comes down to is
I do research in a very strange way and probably
Probably not very well supported by a lot of I love it already
Yeah, you know what? I'm gonna say Chris. You know what I'm gonna say. I do research it. No, no, no
I buy it. I see if it works. Oh, yeah, you buy it
And here's what here's actually what you do know is you buy it you do you do some search?
Maybe that you do initial obsessive phase that involves YouTube and lots of googling forum readings
Reddit and then you get a very modest very average reasonable
Very very good starter edition and then you realize okay
This is either something bad or this is something good
And if it's something good
Then you have to buy the next better version because you can't have the crappy version you got to have the good version of it
Right and we're gonna go into the details of exactly what the system is and exactly how it works
I don't want to give any of that. I don't want to give too much of that away
But yeah, I basically I bought I bought a bunch of different systems. I tried a bunch of different things
I saw what works. I saw it didn't work. And the one thing I walked away with is
Mess tech mesh technology is garbage this idea that one thing is going to repeat a signal to another thing is gonna repeat a signal
to another thing is just a totally inefficient use of
Radio bandwidth and it's just a disaster and does not work reliably
Anyone who's used x10 knows exactly what I'm talking about and not that it's mesh, but it feels like a bad science project
It does not feel like yeah, it does not feel like like like an automated home
Anyone else have any thoughts?
Yeah, I think he's got some now
What do you do in the case of say like rodents getting into the wires or chewing them up?
You know what happens then just out of curiosity. Yeah, what do you do?
No, cuz if something or yeah or any kind of like degradation or something like that
That would be horrible because like I said, everything is interconnected via wire
So if wires get broken or cut or chewed or anything else bad things would happen
The wires control guy on speed down. Yeah
All of the wires were in the ceiling
So I guess there's a couple that are in the walls that go down to the various panels and stuff
But the most critical wiring is in the ceiling and then the things that go
From the security system and stuff like that. I won't go into too much detail, but they're not exposed
So it's not well, you can't just cut them, you know
No, it's not all the wiring can be replaced
What you really got to do if you're smart is you need to have that backed up and maybe you have it backed up
Off-site on your own droplet. Yeah. Yeah. Oh, no kidding that so I don't use I said all of my home automation stuff
Isn't connected to the internet
But you better believe that mice my home server and my file server and everything else that runs on my network is connected to the internet
And a big thing that I've been playing with lately is MB and you know how I'm running MB is on a digital ocean droplet
No kidding. Yeah. Yeah, that's that's how I set it up. And that's how I'm running
And of course, I'm running it on a sensible distro, which is sent us
If you if you head over to digital ocean comm and use the and use the promo code D
Oh unplugged all lowercase all one word
You'll get $10 credit and you can fire up your own digital ocean droplet now
$10 to some people might not seem like a lot of money
But when it comes to digital ocean, that's two whole droplets
You can have two servers for a month on that with with that $10 promo code. I
actually once I got hooked on digital ocean, I actually had to request that they expand my
My droplet limit because they limit you to 25 droplets and I have exceeded 25 droplets
No, actually you were in the Seattle area when you had to do that. It was hilarious. Yeah, I think so
Well, here's the thing digital ocean has won. They have made me a ton of money
I mean they have they have they have revolutionized my business because they essentially usually what happens in business is
You hire somebody that heads up a project and then they they take that project and then deliver a profit and loss statement
And figure out how they're gonna make money and all that stuff
Digital ocean essentially did that for my business what they do is they allow me to set up inside of their beautiful dashboard
The ability to spin up servers on the fly and I have clients all the time that call and say hey
This isn't working that isn't working just last week. I had a client called me up
She said our EMR system our electronic medical records
The thing that we use for our patients is not working
We need you to come fix this for so I go over there and their server is totally shot
Now a couple years ago, I would have had to tell her that we would have to order a server from Dell
It would take five the three to five business days
Unless they wanted to pay for expedited shipping and expedited processing in which case I could get it there in maybe a day or two
But they it would cost them an arm and a leg and then she tells me they're actually looking at switching software to something else
So I said hey, I got an idea. I got a great deal for you. We'll rent you a server for 20 bucks a month
And of course, it's only costing me five. So the my profit margin is built in there
yeah, and you know what honestly to like
There was a there was a time and a day where I worked for a company that did this and they would do it
For like three hundred dollars a month the same thing
And so really it's it's you know, the other thing that's really awesome about that Noah, and I know you know this
But of course you could then just once if like they ever wanted to move on or if they wanted to manage it themselves
You could just transfer it to them and we've done that and DigitalOcean is really really good about
About helping you move one server with no no downtime. No loss of no loss of no loss of uptime
They'll move it from one as they call it profile to another profile
And so if they want to take control of that server
They're more than welcome to do it and actually for the first time we went the other way where
We had a client that we had set them up with their own account and their own server the whole nine yards and eventually they
came back and said hey
We would actually really appreciate it if you could manage this because it's getting to be a lot for us to do and so they just
moved it over to our account and we just kind of took over and
We've been managing it ever since and it has worked awesome. So head over to DigitalOcean.com and use the promo code
Do unplugged all lowercase to get $10 and spin up your own Linux rig. I love it
I thank you digital anything to use DigitalOcean. Oh, yes. I love DigitalOcean. I use it a lot. Yeah
Mm-hmm. I usually mostly use it was for VPN work and tunneling around the internet
Oh, that's very good use for DigitalOcean. Awesome. Very nice
so
one of my all-time favorite distros
In fact, I'd say it still stays as my favorite distro is fedora and fedora released fedora 23 beta edition
And I have not had a chance to play with it myself
but reading through reading through this release from fedora magazine org seems like
They've got some pretty cool stuff that that's coming out now
One of the things I've noticed of the last couple releases of fedora is it seems like they are not making
They're not like plowing through making headway and sweeping changes
It seems like they're they're kind of trying to stabilize and try to polish things up
That's not so much the case with the with of course their their new installer package manager
So there's there's a couple things that have been new in the last couple releases
But it seems like 23 is shaping up to be a really really polished
Linux distro and the other thing I like and I've said this before and I'll say it again
I like the direction they're going with these with this workstation idea this idea that you can actually use
Fedora in production and I think that there's a big
Misconception about using fedora in production. I
I've obviously used it on my laptop and on my desktop
But I guess in the past I would have been hesitant to hand it to a client or somebody that wasn't overly familiar with Linux
To use yeah, you know has it have you is it just me or does it seem like the fedora project?
Also is changing in the way they message about asking for help with the betas
It seems to be that they're not what they're encouraging users to use beta more, but they're also at the same time
They're saying use our betas, but use it to help us find problems
So, you know, it's like be very aware of what you're using it for in a much more
They did a last release
But I really feel like they're doing it a lot in this release and now from a selfish standpoint
No, because I'm sitting right here in front of my XPS 13
I got to say the improvements that they say with Wayland and we've talked about this before on unplugged
Is the mixed high DPI support?
So those of you who don't have high DPI at the moment if you have a Linux rig that has a high DPI display and
You want to hook up a secondary display?
That secondary display also runs in a pixel doubled mode
So you get essentially half or more worse resolution
So the only way I've actually made this usable on my XPS 13 is I have a used Apple cinema 30-inch display that I use
As a second display and then I get a semi like reusable like the telegram app takes up half the screen. It's it's awful
Wow, it's super weak. Yeah, it's not usable. So having mixed high DPI support is a huge deal
Now you're gonna have to use Wayland to get that now, let's let's be let's be fair about this
This is a short-lived problem because eventually I my personal belief is my personal prediction is within
We'll say three years. Everything is gonna be high DPI. So I think that I think that this is a short-lived problem
I think that in a couple of years where every monitor that you buy will support this natively and we we won't even need to
It'll be it will seem like it will seem like complaining about not having a VGA port on a computer
And I know there's gonna be somebody out there that says I have to have my VGA port
But but until that time until we reach that point, I guess if you had a high DPI
Display on your laptop and you didn't have a high D and you don't have mixed high DPI support
That would be a real problem. Yeah, but you're right. That's like a limited time issue. I see what you're saying
Yeah, it's not gonna be a big deal
Okay here speaking of something that feels like something maybe more down the road and I'm sure it's not gonna work for a lot
Of hardware. I don't have a lot of high expectations for this particular bullet point in the feature list
But this is what they say the software application is smarter
And it now has the ability to update system firmware
We've talked about this before but system firmware updates through GNOME software to me
I seem like a big deal that to me is like that's like
MacBook
Level like, you know Apple sending you a UEFI firmware for your MacBook update and you get update through the software center now
With GNOME software. I'm sure the initial support is going to be limited but you're gonna be able to update system firmware through
GNOME software under Fedora that feels like a super integrated
2015 consumer experience to me and hopefully now if someone will and hopefully now if someone will you know
They're like taking the lead here. So if people do want, you know to better support firmware updates with Linux
They have a project they can go to and get it integrated right away. Yeah, good point
Yeah, what took him so long is what Anthony says what took him so long. Yes. How about exactly? What do you guys think?
Anyone's system the system firmware stuff like how like what exactly is it offering to update? Is it UEFI stuff?
I'm not exactly sure when they say on the bullet point here
They just say system firmware now when I we covered it before in the past
I looked into it and it was essentially like anything any hardware that can distribute a free open source firmware
Could potentially if they package it up correctly get updated through this
I don't think it has to be anything in particular the key there though
Right is if it it's if it has proprietary blobs if it if it if it's something that is, you know
Proprietary it's not gonna work through the system and if it's something where they don't I don't know exactly
But if they don't take the prep work, it won't work either
So I would imagine it's fairly limited
But then again if you want to be known as the best Linux Wi-Fi card or the best Linux
Video capture device or something like that
Then maybe you're the vendor that goes above and beyond and starts to support the system before somebody else does
Yeah
So, you know, it'll be interesting do we I didn't pull it up here
When is the when they usually do here we go. Here's a release schedule
Do we know when the actual when the at 123 will actually be out?
they just say October and
They say October in the list, you know
And I the reason why I hate to say more specific than that is because it doesn't and when's the last time a fedora release
Didn't get bumped a little bit. Never never it always does but you know what I support that
I support that decision because I would rather them take an extra month an extra two months and fix the stuff that they're holding
The release rather than just put it out there and say oh, we'll patch it there. We'll update it
No, just if it takes an extra month or two, that's fine
The way I do fedora releases and this is not a hit on fedora. This is I think this is just good practice
I have a machine that I use daily and then I have another machine that I use
You know kind of at night just to kind of you know, check my email and do stuff like that
I will usually install the latest version of fedora on that machine and then run it for a month or two and make sure that
All the kinks and all the bugs and and all my software works and on all that stuff on
It first before I actually move my daily driver over to it and I think that's a good way to do it
You know, what strikes me about the fedora project really is and I I mean
Maybe maybe he just successfully has his he batted his eyes at me and he impressed me
but I talked with Matthew Miller at Linux con and
You know, I really liked sort of and actually what I forget Noah who the other gentleman we were talking to from Red Hat
But he was he was talking about some of the things that fedora project and it may be even more so Red Hat have worked on
That they are unable to really advertise because it would actually expose them to greater risk
So I don't even want to go into too much detail here because this was a private conversation
But what they told me was essentially there has been major accomplishments. They have made
That they don't really advertise and I bet this is true for a lot of companies
I bet this is probably not a Red Hat specific thing
It's probably true for Intel and canonical and a lot of different companies that they make these legal battles or they they they resolve these
Issues, but the reason you can't talk about it is because if you say
Let's just say it's the ability to burn a CD under Linux
Let's just say it's like there was some code that had to be licensed to do that
And if you if you announce that you licensed it
Then you're essentially exposing yourself open to potential lawsuits down the road
so you don't say anything even though it was a major benefit to the desktop and
That's that is one of the things that when I look at Fedora
I like a lot about it is I like the people behind Fedora
I like the people leading Fedora and I like the company support supporting Fedora
That's one of the reasons I was at Ubuntu user for a really long time too. So
Fedora 23 coming out in October. That's sort of like
Interesting the major topic the takeaway for me is man
Fedora is looking really compelling and and you got to have some perspective when I say this because
You you do a snapshot of I don't know five six years ago
And I might have been one of the biggest Fedora haters around
I mean I even a year ago
I didn't really think it was that practical of a distro until until 21 started coming out
Then I started changing my tune and I guess for me what and I it's willful ignorance
I guess is what it was because I had started with Red Hat and
Then I had moved in for to Fedora and I'd have been using it since Fedora core 1
so I had just I had just learned to deal with some of the shortcomings of Fedora and I just I was like it for
Me it wasn't Oh Fedora doesn't do these things and those other distros do for me
It was just my computer doesn't do those things and and that's it's a good thing
And it's a bad thing on what it's a bad thing because I think I was I think I was unaware of how powerful Linux really
Was but I think it's a good thing because it allowed it allowed me to have an appreciation for
for to appreciate Fedora for what it was and
As you as you as you pointed out the company behind Fedora is so great
I have a large respect for Red Hat even more now after having visited with them
I mean, let me tell you the people at Red Hat. They are some really authentic live Linux loving folks and
I'm I'm trying to think it was it was it at the was it at the after-party?
Yeah, that you were talking to. Yep. Yep. Okay, and so I I think I know who that was
But yeah, but but yeah, you can tell from talking to him, right? He's a very authentic guy
He's he's he's he it's it's not just a show and it's not a tagline
Those are core beliefs to people like that
And yeah, and also I wouldn't just say that I would also say some serious like perspective on the community and on the landscape
And and not just like a lot of times when you talk to people they have a very very strong
Corporate bias, you know, they they see the world through a corporate lens
I'm sure that's the case for Red Hat employees too
But when we were having, you know with 20-minute casual conversation
it was really I got the sensation that he had a broader perspective and
And what was nice about that is two other Red Hat employees walked up and they also gave me that same impression
They have the corporate perspective and then they have the broader open source perspective
And that I found very refreshing. Yeah, and they're the first people, you know
I walked in there and I was talking about how how much I appreciated their training program and
They talked about and I asked them I said tell me what advantages Red Hat offers over its competitors
And none of them could answer the question all of them looked at me and they went
You mean like the other people in the community? We all kind of work together
I mean, I mean there's some things that canonical does that we use and we do a lot of stuff that canonical uses
but I don't I guess we don't really have a competitive thing as we
We just make what we need and we do the work and we support the project
It does help when you are standing on stacks of billions of dollars
It does but my point is they don't they don't say they don't say we're standing out
We have the the financial resources to make this project
Succeed and so that's what we leverage over these other companies. They don't view it that way
They just view it as a contribution that everyone can benefit from and the thing is I
Mean to some degree. I appreciate where they're coming from to some degree
I sometimes I think they're short-selling themselves because I when I went through the Red Hat training program
I was absolutely blown away
the fact that I was being tested on real hardware with real problems save the internet because I know we disagree on that point but
The way that they the way that the training was conducted the fact that the instructor was using a Red Hat machine the entire
Time all the notes were available to us in
Open office like it's it's the little things like that that just made it if you were a Linux user and you wanted to be
Immersed in Linux you could do the Linux training now these days
owning a full-time business
There's something that nobody ever tells you about owning a small business and that is when you go into business for yourself
You have the ability to you might be a really good electrical person that electrician and you can run electrical wires
But if you're gonna go into business for yourself you actually have to know the business side of it, too
And the thing they don't tell you about that is that business side of it takes a ton of time and so now I just I
Don't have the time to go for a week off to a Red Hat training course to get certified in in in the latest
In the latest Red Hat certification
But what I do have time for is late at night in two of the morning in my skippy sitting down with my laptop and going
To Linux Academy now Linux Academy if you use the if you use the URL Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
You'll get 33% off and let me tell you I actually paid full price
I think the first time I signed up because I didn't know about the program
I didn't know about the promo code and I thought that was a good deal. So 33% off. That's a huge deal
Now they are they're actually working to to help find you a job help get you into the career space and you
Linux Academy comm they'll be willing to help you with that. I
Actually am just getting ready to take my Red Hat 7 certification
And in the past the past couple versions of Red Hat what I've had to do is drive the nearest training center is Minneapolis
So that's a four-hour drive for me actually closer to five probably and when I get to Minneapolis
I have to rent a hotel that's money. I'm not working. So that's money. I'm paying to eat out every day
That's money plus I'm paying for the course and let me tell you while the courses are absolutely top-notch and I absolutely love them
They're expensive and so that's money and then I have to actually pay to take the test and then of course the gas to go
back and forth
With Linux Academy. I'm doing it for literally a fraction of that price and I can I can I can get certified
In the next version of Red Hat all I can't actually take the test
But I can do all of the prep work and learn all of the material right on their website now the other thing
I really like about
Linux Academy is the concept of the snippets
When I first got into when Ralph 7 first came out
The first thing I had to do was learn how to support it for clients. I didn't care about certification
I didn't care about what was gonna be on the test. What I wanted to know was the practical advice
How can I actually make this work and Linux Academy worked with me on that and said these are these are the five or six
things I need to know and
so they
And so they said here I told them these are the five or six things
I need to know and they said here's how much time you need to allocate and here are the things that modules that you need
To go through and and learn this stuff
Yeah
That helped me that when I when I saw like when I was trying to decide if I'm gonna take on Ruby or Python and being
Able to put both of them into a four hours or five hours or six hour perspective
I know I've mentioned this before Noah
But to me that is like goes from this big really weird like concept that I'm gonna learn a programming language
To I'm gonna spend five hours doing a thing and that made it much more approachable now
Think about that if I had told you Ruby is a really cool language and your your troll up in the upstairs
Your live-in troll says that you should learn Ruby
Would you have taken time out of your week and paid money to go to a course to learn programming or would you have?
Simply said hey, you know what? I'm not a programmer. I don't have time for this. I'm running a podcast network
I have three kids. I'm trying to launch new show. I have all these things going on
I don't have time for that
But then if you if then if you say well
Here's I want you to open your laptop and instead of watching TV
Click around through this right and you'll learn how to program right jeez anyone can get on board with that
And you know if you're somebody like me where sometimes your your version of playing gaming on your computer is actually like tinkering with your distro
Or messing around with your computer Linux Academy also scratches that same itch
Yeah
So so yeah Linux Academy dot-com slash unplugged Linux Academy comm slash unplug because then you'll get the automatic discount
Yeah, 33 percent. That's a heck of a discount. I know you know that number isn't accidentally picked. I don't think I think it had special meaning
hmm
Okay, so we were gonna talk this week about the the automatic like block backup system wimpy was trying that out
However, I don't see him in the room. You know he's on wireless connection, too
So I have to be gentle with him
I can't give him a hard time if he can't make it that's that seems legit
So I thought I would talk a little bit just for a moment then about the last couple of weeks
there's been a pretty important topic to me, and that's taking things offline and
Pretending like I'm online just sort of like that could be a lot of things like anything from search to
media content or things like that and
I've I've kind of have a couple of different ideas in mind, but
Since I'm on the road. I thought maybe specifically I'd talk about ideas
I had for the rover and Noah bad news some of it involves project time when I get to your place
Oh, that's what you're talking about. That's great news, dude. I know I'm excited
Listen anytime somebody's willing to let me drill holes and take parts off, and I'm just kidding, but I
I'm all over doing project. I think it'll be fun
Yeah, no, I think it'll be fun, and you know what the great thing is here's what Chris's answer every time
I I'm like oh, you know we have we have this problem where we have this here's his answer
It's become kind of a joke. It's all show content. That's right. That's you're gonna get to see it
That is very true. It does even even when my well my rings on the side of the road
It still ends up in being a show content, so
West have you continued to work with MB? I mean you still set it up
What are your thoughts couple day or I guess maybe a week and a half since we?
First talked about two weeks three weeks as we first talked about it and a week since we first recorded our segment any follow-up
thoughts
You know I'm still fairly impressed
I've been adding more content using you know file bots been working great the directory structure hasn't been too onerous at least for my personal
collection
And honestly I've been pretty impressed. You know a lot of that credit goes to f of M peg
But I built it on a rather
Let's say it's not generously spec'd it'll be upgraded at some point
But you know I'm loading it down pretty good transcoding 1080p streams and hardly hiccup
I will say sometimes when you need to jump around in the video that can be a little laggy
But once it picks up it seems to be continuous, so I'm having great time
Well, I think I'll be oh yeah
I was kind of that was kind of that's where I'm at too is I think I'm thinking about doing the donation once I get
Back from the road trip if I have the funds, but I was telling Anthony before we went on the air
Right where he's sitting right now or perhaps where I'm sitting
I'm not sure so one of the cool things about the current rover setup is the mobile studio all
Collapses down and it goes underneath the seat that's at the depth of like the dinner table
So I'm able to completely just get rid of all of this when we're driving and it's all safe
And it all fits under the seat, but there's another seat where we have that same storage area now. It's a very nice storage area
It's mostly filled with toilet paper at the moment
Truth be told the essentials exactly
But I was thinking there is a storage compartment in the side of the RV that is sort of lined up with where that seat is
At and if I were to fill that storage compartment with a bank of batteries
I could then put an inverter underneath that seat
I could then put a NUC and a NAS under that seat and a router and
Then when I wanted to charge that bank of batteries because it would be in that storage compartment
I would simply open up that storage compartment and then run the solar chargers to it charge over solar or whatever the source power would
Be and then have it come back into the inverter right here underneath your butt. Basically. Does that seem solid to you?
That seems very solid. Now. What do you think Noah? Is this an impossible task?
No, I don't think it's an impossible task
The only thing I want to add to that and I you I'll be completely honest
You kind of lost me in the middle of that when you're describing it
but the only thing I would add is I would want somehow your battery bank inside the camper to be connected to the battery bank on
The front of the camper and the reason I say that is because the front bank of the camper is what's tied into the charging
Inverter of the camper as well as the charging connector that goes into your truck
So anytime you're plugged into shore power or anytime you're plugged into your truck
I would think you'd want all the batteries available to charge as much as they can right that is true
Yeah, that is a good point. I was actually thinking about running as so I had two ideas
So I was thinking I could tie it into the main trailer power system and then I would have the advantages of shore power
Charging that battery bank. I would have the advantage of lighting up all of the AC outlets in here
And I would have the advantage of trickle charging while I'm driving
however
I
Could also use that as a separate isolated power system that just powers all of the computer gear essentially all of the studio gear all
Of the Linux server stuff and all of that that has its own separate source of power that is all completely off of the RV
System, so they mean there's two ways to go both have their downs and ups
Well, it sounds like you're you're developing quite the list. I know that when I did my RV
It took me a good two years
To flush out all of the things I wanted to do and and then I would do some of them and then I would go
Back and redo. I'm curious. Have you come up with that?
Have you have you done anything that you said that you've now after living in it?
You've said well actually if I had that to do that over again, I would do it this way instead
Yeah, I mean this this this battery bank that I'm talking about is probably the biggest thing actually is now that we're here doing shows
And I'm sitting here watching my both my both my laptops. I'm sitting in front of me are down to 40% battery and
Just you know this is
And I think okay this this power thing
Here's what we're doing to save money to be honest with you is we're boondocking a lot more is
We're kind of just we're finding places that have good cellular coverage and we're staying there and they don't necessarily have power hookups
Which means we're running off the battery a lot more
Do you?
You don't you have that thousand trails membership that gets you free camping at places
If there's one along us 90, but there's not
There's nothing along us. This is Montana. There's not much out there. Trust me. Yeah, that's really something
No, well a boondocking is kind of fun, and if you think about it really boondocking is the best way to test your your true
offline ability
Because you're you're literally reliant on nothing
Yeah, just for those of you who are not familiar with the term because before I knew anything about trailers and RVs
I didn't know what the hell boondocking was it is
Like it's basically a fancy term of dry camping
It's it's a trailer or an RV where you live off the grid you still have power because you have your furnace you have your water
Tanks you have your you have your your your your sewage tanks, and you have propane
So you can completely be self-contained and you can go anywhere and basically live off the grid
And you call that boondocking a lot of times
It's urban camping is another term people call like you know and and some places like Walmart's and yes
What cracker barrels and a lot of other places all you know they actually like it because they want you to be their customer
And so it's it's it's an interesting culture there
And we've been we've been meeting different people and they've all been really cool and every single one
Has a different technology implementation and we walk around sometimes some of the different parks
And we're checking out like the different antennas that they have hooked up and some people have like flat ones in their window
Some people have big ones they have out in their yard that are wired into their rigs and all of these people are coming with
Different technology solutions. It's it's not it's the it's not like these are technology dead spots
There's a there's a lot of different ingenuity going on here and a lot of maker stuff. I'm seeing that's really cool
That's awesome. The the the concept of see and in the thing is my next goal is to get you involved with ham radio because
It ties in so nicely with the concept
well from with the concept of open source with the concept of maker with the concept of
You know doing everything yourself
The one thing that you you are somewhat reliant on right now is connectivity to other places now
It's not ham radio isn't necessarily gonna help you with the broadcasting side
But it would definitely help you if you ever wanted to get a message from one person to the other and you didn't have cell phone
Service, you wouldn't need it. I don't know what what kind of like I'm gonna have to be honest, but I'm willing to try
And I and I think that as you I think that as you continue to move towards this idea of wanting control over your own
Every end of it like you were talking about controlling every individual like controlling when the water heater is on and when the water heaters
Off that kind of intense control intense flexibility and intense self-reliance
Just goes like just dovetails perfectly with ham radio
The only thing I'm you know
when I do all of this is my my default right now would be like use arch for all these different little machines to run these
Different things and the only thing is is I'm just not sure that's gonna work in an offline scenario
So that's one thing I'm revisiting
And there's some stuff that I have to kind of reevaluate when I think about some of this
It's like how would I really do this if I have to actually be offline could I take an arch box offline?
And if I go offline is it only offline for two three weeks at a time is maybe a week at most
But then if I go can I go somewhere I can get a lot of updates
There's little things like that when using Linux that are different than using some of the other commercial operating systems
But then the flip side is I have the main thing that I need and that is the ability to live offline on my own
No subscription necessary and like we were talking about the beginning
I'm not gonna also be victims of marketing whims of these different companies. Yeah. Oh, yeah, that's a big one
Right is it well, I guess that goes back to I guess that goes back to my thing of just anything that requires a company
or a service
Yeah, I know. I know you always make that point Wes. Are you so Wes?
Where do you fall on this?
So Noah's kind of coming down on the lines like he won't even get a Roku for his house because he doesn't want to be
Tied to the Roku service and this is one of the reasons he's a big Linux fan, too
Where do you where do you fall on like West stuff? That's like dependent on a third-party service to continue to function long-term
You know, I'm definitely skeptical as well
I I do use some of them, you know
My some of my family members have smart TVs and I've set up some streaming to those and that kind of thing
But you do, you know
You have to be very aware that
You're kind of just risking the time thing as soon as that platform decides to stop supporting the service you happen to use
You're you're out and it'll be an anachronism before
Your take on this too because I have a whole nother complaint when it comes to smart TVs
Smart TVs are these devices that even if LG stays in business
Which I think they will and even if they continue to support their platform, which I think they will
the fact that those apps constantly get updated, but the hardware is stuck and
Instead of replacing with the Roku we're talking about a 30 40 50 60 70 dollar box, right?
When it comes to the TV right now, we're talking about I mean
I've paid a couple hundred dollars for for free for any decent TV
And if you buy a real big one in your basement, and you're looking at twelve thirteen hundred dollars
you know how mad I'd be if in three years I
go to take that out and
Or I go to I go to update it and I realize I can no longer open Netflix on my smart TV
Yeah
Because the ARM processor in it is not capable of running the newest version of Netflix because they've literally quadrupled in speed in four years
That is definitely the stage that technology is at
Yeah, so I mean that and that's that's not specific the Roku where you gain some solid ground Chris and where I don't really have
a leg to stand on is
It principally I think I'm on safe ground
But the problem becomes that the Roku is such a cost-effective device that it literally becomes
Almost disposable, you know when you're talking about, you know
You've said this and I think you're right when you're looking at 50 or 60 bucks anything under 100
Really if it gets you a couple of years it served its purpose you what I mean
You got your use out of it and then you can go get some I think that's why the Chromecast is so successful because it
Is you know, it's so cheap. Even if you can't do everything with it. It does enough for it. So I know
Right. Yeah, the other thing about that but again, so and the Chromecast I come I become conflicted on I had we had a
meeting room
For a client and what they wanted to do was they wanted to obviously project from their laptop up on onto the screen
So we had run an HDMI cable in the wall while the room was being built and all that stuff
Do you know what turned out to be a way easier solution was putting a Chromecast in there and now every
Guest that sits down even if there's like six of them in a room
They can take turns who is sharing their screen up on up on the Chromecast and that was I mean
It was thirty freaking dollars. It required no actual
Wiring we didn't have to do anything in the walls or anything like that
It was brain-dead simple to set up and it's actually worked super well on the flip side of the coin if Google ever
decides not to support the Chromecast which
Could be next week for all we know
Not only not only are they out there there, you know 40 bucks for the Chromecast
But now they're out of solution now the thing that they were relying on to be able to get stuff up on this meeting room
TV is is host and I guess that's what kind of bothers me
Yeah, I have a personal example
We were looking to use a Groupon has some software where you can have like kind of point of sale displays where you can set
Up links for various Chromecasts and have a web interface where you can manage what each Chromecast is displaying
So you can kind of easily easily change them and we were looking to use that at work for looking at graphs and that kind
Of stuff but you know where you what you get with the convenience you lose in the custom
Ability, so we're looking to use at the new Ethernet adapters that they have but a lot of the security implications
We just couldn't you know, we have to use Raspberry Pi's because you can't lock down a Chromecast, you know
You just don't have the option if you if they lose power. They instantly come back as a wireless access point
Yeah, so what what what you've you've you've done that with a Raspberry Pi
We're implementing something that will be essentially the same but we don't get to take advantage of Groupon's awesome open-source project unfortunately
All right. Well, that's cool. There was I don't know if you caught in in Linux action show this week
There was a guy that was talking about the fruit party and how you can how everyone names their
Everyone names their mini little computer after some form of a fruit. That's awesome
So Chris any other final thoughts of of using Linux offline
No, I think I'm gonna something I'm gonna reflect on some more
Because we are about to go through unless I'm wrong Anthony pretty much
The most of the rest of the stretch in Montana is gonna be offline, right?
I don't know once you get past Billings. It's gonna be pretty rough. Yeah, and Billings is our next destination
So I think so we'll see
So I'll probably have some more thoughts after that and I'll say
Also this if you want to follow the destination as long as we have some level of connectivity should be able to over at Jupiter
Broadcasting comm slash rover and I don't know if I'll be able to post updates as often since we'll have limited connectivity
But you can also find a link to the playlist over on the rover webpage and we just posted one last night
We have now have seven seven of the rover logs go check those out and new patrons
Also some exclusive stuff over at patreon.com slash today some really cool personal touch just for you
All right
Well, that'll bring us to the end of this week's episode
Join us at Jupiter broadcasting comm
Or jblive.tv every week and we'll see you again next week
You
Well for flying by the seat of our pants I wasn't too bad no, I think that went pretty good good job sir
Good job. No, you're awesome. Yeah. Well, here's the thing you should I'm gonna take a picture when I get done
of what this room looks like I
It has been fun like I was literally walking why is it every every 15 seconds I'd look around and I'm like
Oh, I have to do this or I have to get that done
Yeah, I
You were quick on the quick on the telegram though. That works pretty well
Yeah. Yeah. Well, I have I have one computer that's dedicated to tell the past him. You've lost me. You've lost me
No, you haven't lost me. I'm here. Sorry. Okay, great. Sorry about that. I
Yeah, I have I have one computer that's just dedicated to to telegram
So that computer that had one laptop that was set up and I'm like, this is just the computer
I'm going to use to communicate with people. So
I hear that there was a Skype out yesterday and that has thrown a serious wrench into your plans of
Doing a mobile studio on Skype. Yeah, man. That was awful
We were all wired in sounded actually really good and I had good connection and then I was able to log in the studio
Thankfully after a little while I was able to get connecting the studio and talk to the live stream
But for a while, I thought it was like I thought it was an issue with the connectivity
I thought it was an I didn't know what was going on because I figured it was on my end because I'm in the mobile
Studio, so it must be my fault that I can't get logged into Skype
Yeah, but you you and so and so somewhere along the lines you were like this just isn't gonna work, huh?
Well about 50 minutes after the show was supposed to start we decided to bail
Yeah
So basically we kept trying to push it kept trying to push it and I just you know
And I had to vamp for 15 minutes on the live stream while I'm waiting for Mike to try to get connected
You know, I have to be honest with you. I have a new I started my newfound
appreciation for what you do for a living back when we were at the back when we were itself and it's like
I don't think I really don't think people get it
Like I think as as a viewer
I think I had like a general idea of kind of what I've kind of what you did
But you don't really get it until you're like you're gonna sit here and talk for six hours and come up with something
Something to say and it actually has to be something pseudo interesting to keep people listening
And then while you're doing all that you also have to handle the chat room and do all the auto stuff and then deal with
People complaining and people that need you for different things. And yeah, yeah, it's fun. It's good times. Yeah, it's good times
All right. Do we have a title? Everybody gotta go to JB titles calm?
Calm. Yeah, so what do you what? What do you do Skype goes out? Well, you switch to mumble
So this whole show was powered by mumble. It was yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Well, yeah, that's right. We nothing escaped anywhere
Everything is mumble. Yeah. Yeah
So the chair was complaining about audio a lot and hopefully it's better in the post edition, but hey
At least we used open source mumble for the whole thing