Did you see the Telegram was bragging about 500 million active users?
Oh boy.
Yeah, and they said 25 million new users in the last 72 hours.
It kind of seems like a great way to get a target right on their back.
Somebody's going to take notice.
Apparently it was a big wave from the riot on Capitol Hill.
A bunch of people were like, oh no, we need to communicate in top security.
Uh oh.
Oh yeah, Telegram, the maximum security chat program.
Nobody tell them about Matrix.
Hello friends and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello Wes.
Looking very dapper today.
I like the all silver outfit.
Well, I thought you'd like the bow tie especially.
Well, you know what really impresses me is those socks.
That is really going the extra mile.
This episode is brought to you by a cloud guru, the leader in hands on learning.
The only way to learn a new skill, you know it, is by doing it.
That's why ACG provides hands on labs, cloud Linux servers, and much more.
Get your hands cloudy at a cloud guru dot com.
So here we are gathered together for episode 388 and we're doing things a little differently.
So I want to first I want to say just to keep some tradition, some form, I want to say time
appropriate greetings to the mumble room.
Hello, virtual lug.
Hello.
Good evening.
Hey guys.
We're all kind of fired up today because we've been playing around with PeerTube 3.0, which
introduced live streaming support and it's peer to peer live streaming and it really
is now a full YouTube killer in a box.
You get everything you get with YouTube like from the good old days where a clean feed
of what people have recently posted, subscriptions, but unlike YouTube where it's spying on you
constantly to feed an ad algorithm, it's free open source software and it's peer to peer
and it can federate with other PeerTube instances.
You guys have heard us talk about it before.
We've had different experiments with it and recently we've been experimenting with a real
small instance over at Jupiter dot tube and playing around with its peer to peer live
streaming support.
So this episode and the last three days worth of live stream or tests that we've done have
all been on PeerTube and it's kind of crazy exciting because it is working and it has
allowed us with one Linode and some object storage to essentially create a worldwide
CDN where people are watching it and it still seems like it has a couple of kinks so we're
still testing it.
It's not like a production thing, but Wes, I mean, how long do you think the setup was
in total?
Well, I don't know, an hour or two maybe at most.
We built a test, a real test one, then we spun up our actual test instance.
So you know, there's some things getting everything configured, getting installed, but I mean,
it's all powered by Docker anyway.
And they've also got a very robust and nice guide if you just want to set things up traditionally,
use the stuff like Postgres and Redis and TypeScript.
So nothing weird or out of the box or hard to find anything like that.
So I mean, an afternoon, really an afternoon to get it set up, start playing with it.
And since then, it's been the same configuration.
They've got a lot of nice admin facilities.
They've got like a guide for, hey, you're the backend admin and you want to set everything
up by hand.
And they've also just got like a guide aimed at once you've got an instance, how do you
administer this?
How do you set it up?
How do you make it useful?
How do you set all the transcode options?
Honestly, I've been pretty impressed by the docs and all the configurability so far.
Yeah, and the options are really getting there.
I think customization, but not in an overwhelming way is a big part of what they're trying to
go with this.
As a content creator, I like a lot of the options they give me.
I can set system themes, I can install plugins fairly easily.
It's easy to create live streams and choose if the live stream is persistent and remains
available for playback afterwards.
But the other thing that's nice because of the architecture is we have 30 people or so
watching it right now and the load on the server itself still remains pretty low.
Yeah, early on we were looking at it and it was bouncing between 6% on the CPU and this
is a four core box to about 40% and at one point, just looking at the history, it looks
like it spiked up to around 60% CPU usage.
But this is, it's a YouTube instance in a box with 30 people watching a live stream
and you can configure how many are allowed to live stream and then the viewers themselves
become the CDN.
It's just so neat and I love where the project's going with it.
So we're all kind of fired up today because we've been talking about that.
But we're gathered here really to geek out on GPUs.
I think even if you're not a graphics head, you're going to get some valuable information
out of this episode.
I've been testing this new XPS 13 from Dell, the latest developer edition with the 11th
gen Intel processor.
I recently reviewed it in Coder 395.
I've been honestly trying to just wrap my noodle around the performance of this XE GPU
and the 11th gen CPU and I knew I needed to better understand it for the audience because
I could tell I was reaching the limits of my understanding and so I wanted to reach
out to somebody who had a deep understanding of this stuff and could communicate it really
well.
So I called up Wendell from Level One Techs and of course, Level One Linux.
He's a great resource for this kind of stuff and he's been covering a little bit of the
future of these XE GPUs and what it could mean for virtualization on his Level One Linux
channel.
I'll have a link to that in the show notes.
So he came on and he and I just started geeking out.
We started talking about the XE GPU.
We talked about Intel's new OneAPI initiative, which I won't spoil, it's a massive endeavor
that Intel's trying to leverage their position that they have right now.
And then later on in the interview, we also get into his current daily driver Linux setup,
which I think you might be surprised about his answer.
Ooh.
Yeah, I gotta ask, you know, I gotta ask.
Of course.
Of course, there's a few terms that get used in this episode that I wanted to define if
you're not a graphics head.
GVTG is virtualizing the GPU for multiple guest machines.
So it effectively gives you near native GPU performance in a virtual machine while still
also allowing the host to use that GPU.
So that's GVTG.
VFIO comes up that allows virtual machines direct access to PCI hardware resources like
the GPU or a network card or another PCI device.
I've actually passed through like a USB card to it and even a dock, a Thunderbolt dock.
That's using VFIO.
And then also another term that gets mentioned that you may or may not be familiar with in
this interview is IGPU.
In the context of our chat, it's the graphics card that comes built into Intel CPUs.
But don't worry, stick with it.
Even if you're not a graphics person, I think there's something that'll interest you that's
worth listening to in this chat with Wendell.
So the reason I wanted to chat with you today was I got my hands on a Dell XPS Developer
Edition that has an i5 11th Gen Intel CPU and the XELP graphics in it.
And this little laptop is blowing my X1 Carbon 10th Gen with an i7 CPU and GPU away.
I mean, it just is shredding it in machine learning benchmarks.
And I can play actual video games on it.
I can play Tomb Raider.
I can play Hotshot Racing.
I can play CSGO and nothing that's super demanding, but games I'm currently playing that I actually
enjoy playing, I can play them on this laptop with an integrated GPU.
And I thought to myself, something must be going on here more than I can appreciate.
And I thought, this is something I need to ask Wendell is like, what's going on with
these XE or Z graphics?
And I hear about a dedicated GPU and the whole thing.
So can you kind of just fill me in?
So Intel had their one API thing and a lot of details, I guess, about the Intel graphics
stuff came to light.
And they've got XE graphics now in their 11th Gen.
And to me, that's not quite, I mean, it's like, OK, it's impressive, but it's also not
super impressive because the integrated graphics sort of stagnated there for, I don't know,
like four generations.
And then so the XE graphics that's in the 11th Gen, yeah, it's OK.
But what Apple is able to do with their integrated graphics arguably is more impressive because
that would be something more on the level of what I would expect from Intel when they're
going to release XE graphics to begin with.
But maybe the second generation of that will be good.
And at Intel in their one API, they sort of revealed some of the DG1 dedicated graphics
stuff and like DG2 and what they have in mind for XE graphics, especially in the data center.
And packing 1,000 Dota sessions or whatever on a single card, which had four GPs on it.
But it's a single PCIe card.
And so that's kind of exciting because they're hitting power targets, not just throwing raw
watts at it to get the performance.
But also like maybe that will be good for laptop users having those kind of things integrated.
But in the bigger picture, how everything stacks up, it's like the Apple M1 and then
like Radeon integrated graphics.
And then way on down the list is the old iGPU.
And somewhere between the M1 and the really old iGPU is XE graphics.
It wins some against Radeon.
It loses some against Radeon.
It's a different architecture, and it is really interesting.
I suppose your point's well taken, though.
Ideally, we would have been where we're at right now about three generations ago.
So it's good, but not as good as it should be by now.
Yes.
Yeah.
I mean, if you want to take the anti-Apple spin on it, you can say, well, Apple was able
to do this with failed toaster parts and used rubber bands.
So the big people should have been able to at least be that good.
But the reality is that ARM and some other things are doing some magic for us.
But Apple did some genuinely good engineering with their processors and worked with some
smart and talented people to sort of bring it together.
And XE graphics is still sort of bolted on a legacy architecture, but I don't have a
feel for how different or how similar XE graphics is to things that have been tried in the past,
like Larbi.
And early on with Larbi, it looked like Larbi was going to be amazing because they're engineers
that are a deep dive on, I think, Quake, one of the id Software engines.
And there's 1,000 or 2,000 lightweight x86 cores on this GPU because, yeah, you can use
x86 for everything.
I mean, what could possibly be wrong with that idea?
And then you look at a game like Quake, and it turns out that that kind of a game, the
engine was basically from the mind of a genius or mind of several geniuses.
And nobody else built game engines that way.
But that wasn't really discovered until they went to port other game engines later.
And so it was like, oh, Larbi, maybe this isn't good for anything other than Quake.
But in terms of running hardware really quickly, it ran Quake really, really amazingly well.
And that's what Apple has done with M1 and M1 graphics is they've looked really closely.
They've done a lot of analysis on the software that they run and the instructions and also
the emulation layer, like the stuff that they added to make ARM better able to deal with
x86 instructions, which are variable length.
That's some really clever stuff, but it's from a deep dive at just looking at the sequence
of instructions that are run and looking at the insanity and saying, OK, what do we have
to do here?
Let's make this work.
It stands to reason they did the same thing with graphics.
And that's the difference here.
That's the difference for the IGPU.
They really looked at a whole ecosystem of games because Tomb Raider is fairly well optimized
and runs really good on the mobile embedded platform.
With Xe graphics for one API, what I'm starting to see from one API is Intel saying, OK, in
order for us to squeeze more performance out of Silicon, we're going to have to change
our software.
And so I think this is kind of long winded, but this is just a long winded way to preface
this by saying, I think Apple is taking a hardware assisted software optimization route.
And I think Intel is taking a software assisted hardware optimization path.
So on the one hand, you've got Apple, which is doing a pre pass on your software to make
it better fit the hardware.
And the hardware has stuff in it to run the instructions that are not necessarily ARM
instructions a little better.
Intel, on the other hand, is saying, we need to make adjustments in software and recompile.
And so this is happening at compile time.
And the other one's not happening at compile time, but it's not happening at runtime either.
It's sort of in the mix.
And I think there's pros and cons for both approaches.
Sure.
It seems to me, though, the advantage long term of Intel's approach is that that stuff
is baked into Linux.
And as longtime Linux users, I think you probably agree.
We can be patient with this kind of stuff.
And if it means in years down the road, we will have really reasonable laptop and desktop
graphics that are totally supported out of the box when I install Linux, I'm along for
the ride.
And it doesn't have to be absolutely, that's what I think excited me about the Xe graphics
is it doesn't have to be competitive with the latest Nvidia and AMD graphics.
That's not my work case.
My work case is mostly I want an accelerated desktop.
I want accelerated video encoding and decoding.
And I want to be able to play some games really well, but doesn't have to be like on absolutely
high settings.
And I think Intel could get us there and no driver fiddling required.
I just recently, in two different scenarios with two totally different distributions,
went down the rabbit hole of having to fix a system after a failed Nvidia driver install.
And it felt like I was back in the early 2000s all of a sudden.
And so for me, I just can't wait for this stuff to work out of the box.
And I think the other thing that you touched on in a video of yours that I'll link in the
show notes is it seems like Intel's baking in more shared GPU features for virtual machines.
And that could be really awesome for a lot of users.
Yeah, I think one API, their vision of one API is comprehensive from what I can tell.
And so imagine like, yes, it's all of those things, but it also reaches into other operating
systems even than just Linux like Android.
So their vision of it is to make it super easy for developers to not have to worry about
anything.
So I did the interview with Jeff McVeigh that'll probably be out maybe Monday or Tuesday.
And obviously, a lot of it is not there yet, but the vision is to make everybody not have
to worry about it.
And if you look at the language, like the problem that I have with it, if you look at
the language, it's a lot of really crazy stuff in terms of really high level abstraction.
And it's like, OK, but tell me how that's going to make my life easier.
And one thing that I have a personal experience with is just the linear algebra libraries.
And the linear algebra libraries, like you think it's like how many ways are there to
just let's compute the eigenvalues of this.
Let's do some matrix multiplication.
Turns out on a modern x86 processors, there's like a dozen ways to do that.
And some ways are faster than others.
Some ways are faster with a sparse data set.
Some ways are faster with a full data set.
Some ways are, you know, it's just it's crazy.
And so a lot with this open source like we do in the research thing, you actually need
to run some tests, not only in your data set, but also on the machines that you have available
to do the testing.
I can't just dive into the calculations and say to the library, here, go calculate this
for me.
Because you're not necessarily going to get the most efficient path to do the calculations
based on your hardware and the available data.
And so one API is supposed to take all of that away, but also supposed to make things
a little easier cross platform, like, you know, the new the new iPhone 12 has like this
lidar thing that's completely crazy.
And I was watching I think it was an Unreal Engine demo the other day or something.
No, it was it was a it was some third party company has trained a model that will produce
blender models from lidar and a camera.
And it is unbelievable.
Like, you just hold the camera up and slowly move it around as it as it indicates.
And it uses the lidar and the camera in the iPhone to produce a realistic blender model
of whatever it is that you were doing with your phone.
And it is truly incredible.
It's just it's just insane.
And so from the descriptions of one API, what's happening in my brain is saying, okay, if you're
going to build that, there's a phone component, there's a cloud component, there's a training
component, there's all these different software stacks, you think about developing an Android,
it's like, okay, I'm going to get out Eclipse or Android Studio, the JetBrains tools, whatever,
and start, you know, there's that whole tech stack and ODB and getting all that stuff ready.
And then in the cloud side of it, it's like, am I using Amazon lambda, and it's got all
the stuff that goes with that, or if I'm not using Amazon lambda, maybe I have to do my
own cloud infrastructure, maybe I'm going to need, you know, a whole tech stack there.
And then there's probably gonna be some middleware applications where I'm going to do, you know,
some special sauce or whatever, and it's gonna be a whole other product stack there.
And Intel is saying, look, this is too much to ask of developers and research scientists
and stuff like that.
We need to come up with a really high-level interface to all of this stuff and open it
as much as possible so that everybody will build it, because we're spending a lot of
our time, you know, figuring out which instruction set will do basic linear algebra the quickest,
and we don't need to do that.
And that is kind of, you know, to your point, that is kind of what Intel has in mind is
to take those optimizations away so that you don't have to do those optimizations yourself.
The library sort of knows that and figures that out.
How long do you think we'll be waiting around to see one API take off?
And what do you suppose the chances are of vendor adoption, like, say, AWS, for example,
or other vendors?
Are they on board?
Or is this gonna be something that Intel comes up with that's a really great idea that doesn't
really see much vendor adoption?
I don't know.
I mean, it's so large and so ambitious, it's probably gonna be both.
We're probably gonna see some vendors adopt it and for it to make sense in some places.
I would love nothing more than, like, you know, again, like, for one API and all of
its lofty goals, it's hard to talk about because it is so large and abstract, but, like, concrete
goals for me personally is I hope Intel's GVTG takes off.
This is kind of like Intel's answer to SRIOV, and it's been here a while.
It's not really new.
Actually, Intel's moving a lot of things that they've already had under one API.
So in some ways, yes, it's ambitious and we talked about it in lofty goals, but the reality
here is a lot of this stuff already existed somewhere else in some way, and they're just
kind of bringing it together.
But GVTG is an extension to the graphics subsystem, the iGPUs, like in Xeon E3s.
So I think Intel's had this discrete GPU plan for a while.
Now, you know, the iGPU and the Xeon E3, that is, like, when you say anemic GPU, like, there's
a picture there.
That's what it is.
So it's like, okay, I've taken, you know, an unsustainable amount of food and I've divided
it among four people or I've divided it, you know, I've divided this infinitesimal amount
of GPU horsepower among four virtual machines.
You can do that with GVTG.
You can slice and dice it where two virtual machines or three virtual machines, unlike
SRIOV, which tends to be more of a hard partition when we're talking about it in the graphics
space in terms of VRAM and some of the other components, GVTG is a little bit more flexible.
You get, you know, GPUs weren't designed for things like context switching, but you have
a little bit more of an ability to do context switching-like behavior with GVTG.
And so in the demonstrations that Jeff McVeigh did in the one API presentation and, you know,
in some of the stuff that Roger Koduri was talking about, it looked like their GPUs were
set up to do that.
So it's like, I want to run a thousand Dota clients across four GPUs.
Okay, you know, we can do that.
Now we've got a really, you know, a really heavy demanding simulation workload that we
need to run in this other virtual machine.
And it's like, okay, well, we can move the Dota clients over to these three GPUs and
give the heavy simulation, you know, one dedicated piece of silicon or whatever it takes to actually
run it.
And so those functions are the things that I'm looking out for.
I'm looking for that.
I want to be able to take the changes that they make to the Linux kernel and be able
to roll with that because one of the things they specifically talked about in the presentation
is being able to take the frame buffer from that GPU and shove it into another GPU directly
over the PCI bus without hitting main memory.
And for our Looking Glass project, that would be the Holy Grail.
Like if the plumbing is there in the Linux kernel to do that for the Intel GPUs, we know
Radeon GPUs are quasi capable of it.
What we need to do to move, we as a community, need to do to move the needle forward to be
able to do direct GPU frame buffer, frame buffer copies.
At that point, we're no longer constrained by main memory bandwidth.
We can literally copy that frame buffer directly into another GPU from a guest GPU to a host
GPU.
That's really the next step for speed and optimization in VFIO.
Not only for enterprise workloads where they're doing simulations or tons of streaming clients,
but I would love to see this land in consumer machines because it would make VM super fast,
obviously, but it also means we'd be a step closer to fully isolated applications where
the entire stack is completely isolated, but you're not taking a big performance penalty
for that.
Yeah.
I mean, having a hardware assist, I mean, that level of containerization, I don't really
call it containerization because I'd apply something else, but that level of containerization,
that can only be the future.
Or isolation.
Yeah.
I mean, we have to have this level of secure compute.
Like there's no, like the security threats and the stuff that we see with things like
solar wind, there is no reason today that we shouldn't be running all of our applications
in individual application sandboxes.
I mean, it's almost to the point where each individual application should have its own
encrypted memory space.
The thing that's preventing us from getting there is market segmentation.
We have the hardware, we have the technology, come on guys, let's dot the I's and cross
the T's.
Right.
Yes.
That sounds like another rant I heard recently from a well-known individual.
I want to take a moment and welcome a brand new sponsor to the network and to the show.
It's oh dear.
And the timing is perfect because I think a lot of us are looking for a better take
on how to do monitoring and looking for something that was designed to work with automation.
And that's where oh dear comes in.
Go to oh dear dot app and use the promo code Linux for a $10 discount on any plan.
Oh dear was co-founded by the author of cron dot weekly and a listener of the show.
So they're also from the community.
And I think that's really great.
But you know, as somebody who does run a lot of services, I know what it's like to be informed
by my listeners that something's out before I know it's out.
So be the first to know when your site is unavailable.
Oh dear has global uptime checking with servers that are worldwide that will report a problem
as soon as it happens from multiple different angles and they can go deep into your site.
They can crawl and index your entire website and detect a broken link and notify you about
that.
There's also the ability, of course, to monitor all kinds of aspects of the backend infrastructure.
So perhaps you have scheduled tasks or cron jobs and you want to find out if they've run
or not and look and get alerts if something doesn't execute.
Oh dear completely accommodates that.
Oh dear is always monitoring the performance and speed of your website over time so they
can detect if something happens immediately.
If you have a sudden performance impact, something gets really slow or get a historical snapshot.
See if performance is changing over time.
But the thing that really makes oh dear really special is the API.
It lets you configure everything about the application.
Everything you see in your dashboard can be controlled with an easy to use restful API.
And of course, any changes you make via the API are visible in the dashboard in real time.
It's the monitoring solution that embraces automation and gives you the tools to make
it possible.
And it's comprehensive API means there's tons of third party integrations already available.
There's of course a command line client, but there's other neat ways to interface with
like the notifications in the system to over the API like a telegram chat bot.
There's a JavaScript SDK, a terraform provider and a lot more.
So right now head over to oh dear dot app.
Oh dear dot app and start a 10 day no strings attached trial, no credit card required.
You can get set up in less than a minute.
And when you do sign up for any of the plans, use the promo code Linux for a $10 discount.
And if they ask, tell them the Linux unplug program sent you.
It's pretty neat.
And I think you probably agree.
It's time to relook at how we're doing monitoring, go with a fresher take on something that is
designed for automation with a comprehensive API and great documentation too.
So check them out.
It's oh dear, oh dear dot app promo code Linux for a $10 discount.
And thanks to oh dear for sponsoring the unplugged program.
So my conversation with Wendell continues and I asked him about his daily driver Linux
setup.
So before we go, I want to ask you one last question and that's just a snapshot of what
Wendell's daily Linux drivers look like today.
Are you still mostly a fedora guy?
What kind of hardware, et cetera?
My main machine is a threader for machine.
It's a 3970X.
It's got 128 gigabytes of memory in it right now.
It has a Tesla V100, a 2080Ti and a, I think it's a, no, no, it's the 6800, it's a 6800
non XT.
Whew.
And I'm about out of PCI-E.
Oh, wow.
Do you just run the whole OS at a RAM or what?
Well, I mean, that's the, that's the goal right now.
The V100 can, you can use the V100 as a Titan kind of sorta in a VFIO like type pass-through
type situation.
Oh, that's nice.
That works pretty well.
Yeah.
So you can, you run it as a V100 as pure compute or you can run it as, as whatever.
It's still, it's still a little sketchy sometimes binding and unbinding GPUs.
So that can, that can be a little, a little weird and it's not, it's definitely not an
ideal situation.
I'm not running Fedora right now.
I do have, I'm running 20.10 because I've been helping a lot of people on our forum
use 20.10.
I still have another machine that I do work on, which is still running Fedora, but the
Threadripper machine is running Ubuntu and it's, it doesn't have the same optimizations
for performance for virtual machines out of the box.
And so people on our forum and some, and some other people will have trouble with things
like, you know, sometimes it's crackling audio or sometimes like the virtual machine performance
is fine until you go to write to disk.
And I've found that I've had to do a lot more sort of hand tuning to get those things to
work well on the Ubuntu 20.10 kernel versus Fedora.
And I was going to try the low latency kernel, but then I ran into another problem, which
is you don't get ZFS out of the box necessarily.
And so like the newer kernel, it's like, okay, I'll download the, the, the devs for Ubuntu
from kernel.org.
I was like, oh yeah, ZFS is not a thing with those kernels.
Crap.
I did not realize that.
Yeah.
It's a, and then it's like, okay, let me get the DKMS thing and it's like, oh, this doesn't
work either.
Like, have I, have I painted myself into a corner here?
So I've been, I've been forcing myself to use this setup so that I can sort of learn
what those pitfalls are.
Cause I didn't expect that either.
Like I expected that when I download the Ubuntu kernel from kernel.org, you know, for 20, cause
it's like, okay, let's try 5.10 on 20.10.
But yeah, ZFS, the ZFS DKMS thing wouldn't, doesn't build and it's not in the kernel because
the canonical hasn't got a hold of it yet.
So you have to get the kernel that canonical got a hold of in order to get ZFS.
Oh, okay.
When you lay it out like that, I guess that makes sense.
I see it.
But that was a nice gotcha.
And it's interesting that there's enough people that are using 20.10 that you felt motivated
to switch over to it.
And do you think people are doing that instead of using the LTSs for graphics driver and
Mesa stack updates or?
Yeah, that's what led to all of that.
There was, there was a bit of a, a bit of a kerfuffle when the 6,000 series GPUs launched
and it was like, crap.
I'm going to have to figure this out.
And it really, for me, it wasn't really too bad, but you know, I might be a little bit
snow blind to it because I have so much experience with it, but it really wasn't a huge deal
to get it working on 20.10.
And so like, you know, AMD did a lot of work to get it working on 20.04, but 20.10 launched
like the week before the GPUs launched.
And so you could install the driver from AMD.com and there's, you can get the open driver or
the proprietary driver, but the open driver was basically Abhari with the, with the closed
driver.
And you could get Mesa, newer Mesa and Radvi and, and some other stuff.
I don't know if I'm saying that right, but the, all the accoutrement that goes like with
the stuff that's not in the kernel, but it's a little bit of a, you know, I could, I can
kind of relate because it's a little bit of a trap for newbies because it's like, oh,
I'm running the newest kernel.
And it's like, well, there's all this other stuff that's not in the kernel that you also
need in order to be able to run your games and do your stuff, or you need somebody to
backport those things into something that will run in your environment.
And so, and then, or some poor soul somewhere has to spend a ton of time backporting the
cool stuff in 5.10, which there's a ton of cool stuff in 5.10 and newer to like kernel
5.8 or 5.4 in the case of 20.04.
And so it's kind of an impossible situation because you want the people doing the development,
doing the development on branch master, I guess, for lack of a better way to describe
it, like on head, like you want them doing the work there because that's where it is,
or they know where the bodies are buried, you know, wherever it was.
And so they were doing their work all along when head was 5.4 and they know what's broken
in 5.4.
And so it seems like a crazy situation where, you know, somebody inside of AMD and somebody
inside of Valve or somebody on Valve's indirect payroll, because Valve is greasing the wheels
here very quietly with a lot of money and that is appreciated, but you know, it sort
of gets spoiled.
Like if it's like, oh, Valve is paying $3 million to, you know, developers all over
the world to advance this thing forward, then, you know, as the people tend to want to want
to want to pee in the Cheerios as it were, it's better to just keep it quiet and just
get the work done and, you know, not not do anything for the fanfare.
They're not necessarily in it for the glory anyways.
Yeah, yeah.
They just like, I just I just want a reasonable computing experience.
That's where I am with VFIO.
It's like the whole reason I do the VFIO stuff rather than trying to run a native is like,
I don't, you know, I don't have time for this.
I just want it to work.
And it's like, yes, I would love it if everything worked perfectly on Linux, but I don't have
time for that.
So I want Linux to do what Linux does well, because I can count on Linux to do that.
I don't want to bring the horrible ugliness into Linux because it's my nice, clean, pristine,
you know, thing.
But like the whole understanding in the community of like the whole driver thing with the 6000
series GPUs and all that, it's just it's like when the fabs were spinning up making those
GPUs, there were developers developing on what was then the head of development for
the Linux kernel, which is probably like five point four or five point six or something
in that, not five point ten or, you know, five point ten, you know, beta one or whatever.
And Ubuntu 2004 would have been sort of the big release.
It's what, you know, Canonical says the majority of their users are using the LTS releases.
Of course, the enthusiasts are using the latest releases and the enthusiasts are likely the
ones to buy new GPUs when they first come out.
But yeah, OK, we're using an LTS support, but long term support doesn't imply that it's
going to have the scaffolding and infrastructure to be able to support all of this stuff that
you get with graphics.
So like LTS support, it's like, OK, we're going to spin up our network driver.
We're going to spin up our mouse driver because our mouse has 37 buttons and the built in
driver doesn't handle that well or whatever.
That's going to be fine because that device isn't changing very often.
It's on the market.
It's set.
It's fixed, right?
Yeah, the interface in the kernel is not really changing.
But with GPUs, that's not really the case.
The interface within the kernel is changing dramatically.
And because of the work bringing the newer GPUs to the kernel, we see in what ways the
old interface is deficient.
So then it becomes a huge amount of work to backport those changes to the kernel to the
old kernel.
Effectively, you are, you know, just dressing up, cherry picking bits of kernel 5.10 and
shoving it into kernel 5.4.
And at that point, we're just deluding ourselves.
It's like, you might as well go to kernel 5.10.
I mean, you're probably going to introduce more bugs than you solve because you've, you
know, packaged and backported so much functionality in kernel 5.10 that you're running more kernel
5.10 than 5.4 at this point.
I mean, come on.
So what you're really saying, Wendell, is it would just be easier if the entire world
ran Arch and was rolling all the time.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
But you know, this is, I get like Linus saying, it's like, don't break user space.
I interpret to say, Linus is saying, you can trust to update your kernel and we probably
will not screw you.
And so the idea of, you know, okay, we're going to have an LTS distro, but I also need
to keep my kernel on whatever version of the kernel existed then.
I think I could see historically like how that was a thing because yeah, I mean, I was
guilty of that.
You know, kernel 2. something on Debian for like way longer than I should have.
Like guilty as charged.
But where we are now with the Linux kernel, it's so good.
And they are usually, not always, but usually so quick about being on top of problems that
for workstations, long-term support means something entirely different than servers,
I think.
And so I think my philosophy is like, let's just roll with the newest kernel that's reasonably
stable and we'll probably have a better experience for it, even on an LTS kernel.
And you can totally install a newer kernel on an LTS kernel and most of the time not
run into problems.
All right.
Well, thank you, Wendell.
It was great having Wendell on and check out Level One Tech and the link we have in the
show notes.
He knows so much about it.
I just like, I like to absorb the knowledge, but I do want to do a spot of housekeeping
before we go on.
Do join the Luplug if you get a chance on Sundays at noon Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern.
It's on our mumble server, just in the lobby.
You can get info at linuxunplug.com.
And also a special reminder about the accessibility tools on Linux on the January 4th edition
of the Luplug.
And I've updated the calendar to reflect that.
We're going to try to do that in the future.
And also I want to mention that you might have noticed we don't have a lot of time for
news this week.
Linux Action News continues on and we did get to a lot of stories in episode 171, which
came out yesterday.
And you can get that at linuxactionnews.com.
And a special plug for Self-Hosted 36 later this week, I review the new dedicated Home
Assistant hardware.
I think if you've been listening for the last few weeks, you know how much I love Home Assistant.
Well, I got one.
You got one?
What?
Oh, I'm excited already.
Well, it's here.
It's running.
You know, I'll show you.
I'll show it to you.
It's super cool.
And so there's just a couple of things you need to know about.
And I talk about all that in Self-Hosted episode 36 at selfhosted.show slash 36, which will
be out later this week.
Not out yet as we record this here episode.
So there you go.
That's the housekeeping.
I think that's all the housekeeping we got for this week, just nice and tidy right there.
I was listening to the PeerTube instance as we went along and I didn't have any drops
during the Wendell interview at all, nothing, no drops at all.
It was running super solid and I was getting it from 10 other peers, which was I think
there was something like 20 people watching it.
And then we had as we're going to hear something like 10 people that are seating in.
And it seems to be that when you have that many people, it really kind of smooths out
any of the hiccups.
Oh, that is so neat.
You know, we were playing around in the IRC room, too, and it looks like there is just
a regular HLS feed that you can find the playlist for and pop it in MPV or VLC or whatever client
you like.
I know I'll be trying it with a Chromecast later.
So that should work with anything.
Yeah, that's nice because if you do that, not only could you watch the video stream
in a native Linux client like MPV or VLC, but you're not seating.
Yeah, you wouldn't help us out with, you know, sharing with everyone else watching.
But sometimes that's what you need or you're on and you know, mobile connection or just
use what works.
Yeah, well, you know, if I was if I was on vacation, but I was watching the shows just
to make sure you guys didn't screw it up.
I mean, so I could still watch.
Quality control.
Mm hmm.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I'd totally do it that way.
So that way I wasn't burning through my LTE connection.
So and it seems like we maybe we figured out a way we could see it without having to watch
as well.
So you can watch it without having to see it and you can see it without having to watch.
This is the stuff I love about free software in this stack.
We can poke around with this and come up with solutions that we could never put together
with something like YouTube or even something like library, which for all effective intents
and purposes is a crypto scheme with a centralized control that can still be had pressure applied
to it by a federal government.
Where PeerTube, that's decentralized, it's peer to peer and it's federated.
You could take down Jupiter broadcasting, but who wouldn't take down the Federation
of PeerTube instances and their videos?
And it means that in the future, a project like Debian could have DebianTube where they
have their how tos, tutorials, and they have their community events and conferences all
hosted on PeerTube available for download.
And you know, if you hear, oh, there's a Debian event and it's live, you don't have to figure
out where or what platform or if it's on YouTube, you just know it's on DebianTube.
All of their video stuff is on DebianTube.
And now live streams are too.
And it's so cool because it's a lot like YouTube.
It's that simple as far as the user experience goes.
It's part of the publish process.
You publish and if your account's unable to go live, you have an option to just live stream.
And it gives you the URL and the key.
You plug that into OBS and you're live like if it was Twitch, it's just as easy to stream
to as Twitch or YouTube.
And it's incredible.
It's incredible because we're running it all on one instance.
And we experimented over the weekend with a Linode two core instance that was just two
cores and four gigs of RAM.
And we were hosting 20 people in that live stream.
And it was about 60 percent utilization.
We did totally max it out when we started two streams.
Well, I had to make trouble and stream myself.
I mean, you couldn't have all the streaming glory.
You were even sending some pretty high res stuff and it looked good and you were able
to play it back on the studio TV even.
Yeah, it plays the the peer to player even plays in Safari on the iPhone.
I mean, it passes that low bar.
So it's like really it works anywhere.
There's no flash required like it used to require back in the day when we first started
streaming.
I'm I'm pretty stoked about it.
I think it still has a few hiccups here and there, but some of that could be implementation.
So we're still testing it.
But I think it's pretty exciting not only because it could act as a canonical archive
for all of the past and current J.B. shows, but it could mean that if for whatever reason,
you know, maybe J.B. like I was I was speculating on the pre show, maybe J.B. one day defends
a an encryption activist who somebody who's who is publicly known for being anti backdoor
encryption and that becomes disallowed speech on YouTube will have a peer to platform.
Maybe it never happens.
Maybe it's just nice to just have multiple options.
But what's so great about it is we can just plug it into our existing infrastructure.
We can send an RTMP feed to it and we can stream to it just like every other endpoint
we streamed to.
And now it's just part of that mix.
And that's how we're starting to work with it.
And I think it has a lot of potential for open source projects, much like I think Matrix
does.
There's a lot of the same shared potential there.
Matrix for the chat and real time communication and then PeerTube for project archives and
live stream events.
I think the two things complement each other a lot.
Leno dot com slash unplugged Leno dot com slash unplugged.
That's where you go to get a one hundred dollar 60 day credit.
I was just checking.
There's just no way.
Right.
They're still giving us that deal.
Is this possible?
Don't tell them it's too good.
Did you did you check with Janice in the back office because it's just too good of a deal.
There's no way they're letting us still do this.
She was having a sandwich.
She gave me the thumbs up, though.
Got the thumbs up.
Leno dot com slash unplugged.
You go there to get a one hundred dollar 60 day credit towards your new account.
And of course, you support the show.
Leno is our cloud provider of this PeerTube instance that I can't stop going on about.
Yeah, you know it's hosted on Leno.
It's really neat, actually, because first we set up a test instance just like a proof
of concept in minutes.
And you know, we chose an Ubuntu LTS base 2004, then installed Docker on top of that
and then deployed the image.
And we're up and going and in just minutes, really.
And then once we validated it, we thought, how could we build it a little bit better?
Like we could carve off large chunks of block storage because it's super easy to just add
a bunch of block storage to a Leno host.
That's no problem at all.
And Leno's prices are really competitive, in fact, 30 to 50 percent less than major
cloud providers like AWS or Google Cloud or Azure.
So the pricing is great, but we thought we could probably do it better than that.
We were looking at the PeerTube documentation and they have a they have a deployment approach
where you use S3 compatible object storage.
Well guess what Leno has?
They have S3 compatible object storage, which means we can just use as little or as much
space as we need.
We don't have to carve off terabytes at a time so that way we can accommodate months
and months of growth.
We can just use as much or little.
And it also means that these files that PeerTube creates, like the different derivatives for
lower quality streaming, they're available to us via object storage for other automation
purposes.
Like perhaps we write some scripts that now publish those to archive.org.
It's so great.
Object storage is a lot of fun to play with.
And combining it with PeerTube, I think what we maybe have built here is a super easy reproducible
model for other open source projects out there.
Right now we have a four core VPS because we want to play around with live streaming,
but you could really get away with a two core VPS.
Right now we have 16 gigs of RAM because again we're experimenting, but initially we started
with four gigs of RAM.
This could be like somewhere in the $5 to $10 a month territory over at Linode.
You see what I'm saying?
Wow, this could be really accessible for projects.
You can one click deploy a system with Docker ready to go.
It's really simple for them to get going.
The entire stack is open source.
Linode is a participating member of the Linux community.
They've been contributing to projects and events forever.
They've been around forever.
They started in 2000 and I think it was actually, no, I think it was 1800s.
Yeah, I think they've been around for 200.
Oh no, I'm sorry.
No, that's not quite right.
But they've been around forever.
They're an independently owned company.
They started because they have a love for Linux and you just as a project now have access
to this.
It's like just, it became available, YouTube in a box, but it's YouTube of the good old
days under your control and it's not stealing your information and it's on the Linode stack.
It's with a company that's been around since 2003, so you know they're in it for the long
haul.
Also Linode makes it really easy to host game servers.
I was playing around with this for my kid.
They have multiple different types of game servers on there.
Of course they have things like Team Fortress and CSGO and Minecraft.
The Minecraft one, you should check that out.
They let you set all of the options you really are going to care about, like the in-game
server options in the Linode setup screen.
They've automated all of that for you too.
It's so cool.
So if you want a safe place for your friends, your kids, your community to play Minecraft
or one of the other many popular games like Arcs on there as well.
It's such a nice balance point though, right?
I mean, you get the one click, you get the easy configurability because you know how
to do it all.
You don't have to fuss with it this time, but if you ever need to go back in and actually
make more changes, I mean, you've got SSH access, you've got full control, it's all
right there.
Yep.
They give you the whole range, which of course appeals to Wes and I quite a bit.
They're just dedicated to offering the best virtualized cloud computing.
If it runs on Linux, it'll run on Linode and then however much you want, automation or
just build it from the ground up, you choose and they make it all really accessible with
a great dashboard.
So get that $100 credit and play around, linode.com slash unplugged.
You go there, you support the show, make it possible for us to give content away for free
and you help out a great company like Linode and become a customer.
It's a great ecosystem.
I love it, linode.com slash unplugged.
Let's get into some feedback, Mr. Payne.
Yes, let's.
We have a few emails.
Let's start with the openSUSE feedback because as you would expect, we got a lot of it.
We got a lot of it.
So last week on the show, we secretly ran openSUSE Tumbleweed for a week and then gave
you our thoughts, which in a super short summary version where there's parts of it we liked
a lot.
There were parts of it we were not big fans of, especially me.
I wasn't a big fan of the Yast experience.
I've never been a particularly big fan of Zipper.
I was using SUSE as an enterprise user when Zipper came along.
I wasn't a big fan of it then and I'm still not really a huge fan of it.
I think it's one of the slower package managers out there.
And I also think Yast is kind of slow and clunky.
But outside of that, I think SUSE and openSUSE have really stumbled on a nice relationship
between their enterprise products and their community products.
And in the community space specifically, I think one of the things that SUSE is doing
extremely well, I should say openSUSE to be clear here, is doing extremely well is they
have Leap for your server and Tumbleweed for your desktop or your laptop.
And they even have Micro for like a real minimal viable server install.
So they have this really nice suite where it's all very familiar.
If you learn one, it's totally transferable to the other.
And that really appealed.
And we were wondering, could it replace Arch for us?
But at the end of the day, it just felt like there was too much that was old school Linux
for us, specifically when it came to proprietary video card driver management and Yast.
But Caleb wrote in and said, I love the show, but I was disheartened with your experience
with openSUSE.
Obviously, you'd make a valid point.
The documentation is terrible, but they are working on it.
And they point us to t.me slash openSUSE underscore docs if anybody wants to help.
But Caleb suggests we try out OPI, I think OPI, you think that's OPI or OPUS?
I like OPI because it's just a cute name, but it stands for OBS Package Installer.
Search and install almost all packages available for openSUSE and SLE.
Hey, yeah, that sounds pretty handy.
I think that's interesting, and it's kind of like it's answering that AUR question and
tying in OBS, which seems like it really should be just more integrated in because it's such
a great service.
But they wrap up with, lastly, I'd like to make an argument about Yast.
OpenSUSE definitely should be clear about who it's intended for.
Although Linux-y ways of doing things are still there for experienced users, as a sysadmin,
I can tell you it really isn't for me.
Nowadays, even small companies like the one I work for have dozens of servers, bare metal,
containers, VMs, etc.
No one in their right mind manages those with Yast over SSH or whatever.
That's a great point.
Who I think Yast is great for is a power user or a sysadmin who is not familiar with Linux.
Yast does a great job of showing you what is possible in the OS and making it easy.
Yast, building a software RAID array, and Yast doesn't directly equate to the knowledge
of how to do that in RHEL.
The user does know that it's possible, though, and maybe what it should look like.
Interesting defense.
After we wrapped up the show last week, Neil pointed out that it's actually possible to
run OpenSUSE and remove Yast, which I figured would be like a package dependency bomb that
would just destroy your system.
Right.
It feels so integrated into everything.
I do like that defense, though, honestly.
I think there is a class of user where, especially maybe you're just trying out Linux, you're
an admin in your day job doing Windows or something, where you're used to this very
structured environment, lots of GUIs to click for, lots of that kind of deep system integration.
Maybe Yast is just what you're looking for.
And if Neil's right here, and he usually is, we can just rip that out for folks that are
more experienced or just want to do it on your own.
Okay, maybe I need to give that a try.
And then perpetuating the cycle that always puts us off from ever talking about OpenSUSE
and probably also makes it hard for us to enjoy it.
Of course, I had people that were berating me on Twitter, number one troll, of course,
being Richard Brown, who said that I've had people like him provide extensive, quote,
feedback on my, quote, misunderstandings and, quote, false assumptions, end quote, about
OpenSUSE over the years, yet I, quote, stubbornly beat the same false drum.
He is just bored of my rhetoric at this point, which I thought that was really, if that isn't
quintessentially just a perfect example.
You know, Richard Brown also publicly said I was in the pocket of big ZFS years ago when
I criticized ButterFS when it wasn't that great.
Do you remember that?
That was a cute one.
And of course, as he, even though he publicly said I was in the pocket of big ZFS, whatever
the hell that might be, he hasn't given me any credit for my Evolve stance on ButterFS
as the file system has improved.
Hmm, that's interesting.
And it's this kind of language, like when he says that me saying that I don't like to use
Yast or that I find Zipper slow, that that's rhetoric and false assumptions about Suse.
You know, he's saying he's using this language like rhetoric at a time when things are really
not great in the States.
And the words like rhetoric have a lot of meaning and a lot of power right now.
And it feels like it's a missed place kind of energy and anger that's coming at me.
And it's always kind of been this kind of arrogant stubbornness that has kind of radiated
out from the project by folks like Richard Brown, and even though he's less involved
now, he still seems to be kind of still creating that same persona around the project because,
you know, these words I'm speaking now are going to be heard by tens and tens and tens
of thousands of people.
His tweet is going to be seen by a couple of people.
So what does he think he's accomplishing with this kind of rhetoric and attack?
And using this kind of language, it only escalates the situation.
And it doesn't welcome anybody in to say your experiences are wrong.
He's denying me my own personal experiences in this tweet.
That's what stuck out to me, right?
Because I think we were legitimately trying, whether or not you liked our take or not,
to come at this with an open mind and sort of as a new people who had not used open Suse
for quite some time and just get the experience.
And many people have pointed out the things that we missed or, you know, as some people
have said, like, no one really uses yes, like, what are you talking about?
But that was our experience just getting into it.
And we don't have the inside community perspective.
I don't think we were trying to say, like, this is the truth.
This was just our experience.
Yeah.
And, and I think to say my experience is a misunderstanding or a false assumption is
unfair to me.
My experience is that zipper is slow.
And my experience is that Yas kind of adds a complicated layer to managing Linux that
makes it unique experience to Suse only, which presents non transferable skills to other
distributions.
And, I mean, maybe that's a false assumption, but it's, it's my experience.
It's the way I see the world.
And I don't like that he's shutting it down like that.
But Neil, I don't know if you want to wait in the middle of this before we wrap this
up.
And I don't really want to turn this into a big Suse bashing thing because I think it's
actually a pretty great project and they got a little, a lot of great tech and engineers
there.
Well, I don't want to bash open Suse either.
I mean, I'm heavily involved in the project, so it would be pretty bad if I did.
I think there is plenty of fair criticisms about how people have generally approached
open Suse over the years.
I mean, and I think it's, it's somewhat fair to say that Chris, a lot of your approach
to open Suse over the past five or so years has been influenced or colored by previous
experiences using it professionally, which I think is fine and fair.
But at the same time, it's also important to acknowledge that people who are longstanding
in the open Suse project who have been using open Suse for a very long time.
Like if you saw the end of the year survey, the majority of people who have been using
open Suse have been using it for a decade or longer and are like twice my age, which
is pretty insane when you think about it.
And that means that maybe the other part that's missing is just a lack of fresh perspective
on the project as a whole.
And that kind of dovetails into what you said about Zipper being, it felt slower to you.
This morning we actually, there was a mailing list post that empirically said on open Suse
itself in a CI environment for a specific test case, mind you, like it's not proven
across the board or whatever, but like for this specific test case, we found that Zipper
was twice as slow as DNF for the same workload, for the same installation transaction.
And I understand why that is.
Like I don't want to get into the details cause it's kind of mind numbing and boring
for most people, but it's important to recognize that you have to continue to figure out how
to evolve and to support a growing community over time.
And perhaps some of the issue here is that a lot of the folks in the open Suse community
feel super defensive about their choice in the same way that, you know, 10 years ago,
people used to be the same way about Arch and Suse and Mandriva and Magia users.
They're all in that boat now where people often criticize them for their choice rather
than embracing them and helping them turn into people that can help make their choice
of distributions better.
Yep.
I can totally, I could totally kind of see that.
I think that's a really fair point.
I hope that they are able to attract new blood cause it sounds like that may be an issue
for the project if that many people haven't have been using it for that long.
But we, uh, you know, I, we keep an eye on it.
It just, it seems like too, we, I think there has to be room for different distros for different
folks.
Yes, definitely.
And I think that's where Suse falls down for us.
It's like, it's not that it doesn't work.
It's not that it's some pile of garbage.
It's just not the distro for us and the way we've learned to work in the Linux ecosystem
over a long time because we, we, we now we've been doing this for a while.
Somebody coming in new and fresh, uh, like Kayla pointed out in the email that maybe
doesn't know how to do something in Linux, but just wants to know it can be done or maybe
needs to learn it's possible.
Yes.
Provides that functionality.
I mean, there was a period of time when I was using Yast to connect my, uh, Sles storage
servers to a, to a windows domain.
And I knew how to do it on the command line using all the tools.
But over time it just became a lot nicer and quicker to just go into Yast and if I install
that module, if I hadn't, if I didn't have it installed, put the credentials in and let
it just do its thing.
And I use the hell out of that.
And I told, so I can totally relate to somebody who maybe isn't particularly familiar with
the process, being able to rely on Yast and knowing it's getting done right.
That's just not where I'm at anymore.
And that's just my experience.
But anyways, let's move on because we had somebody write in that suggested that we try
out Alpine.
Jordan says, uh, I know you guys never really had a personal use case for it, but one that
I found for Alpine that nothing else can do is custom install media.
Just for fun.
Here's what I did.
I built a chroot on arch.
I use it to make a custom ISO.
Then I boot the ISO in a VM, configure the network, save the changes with Alpine LBU.
And then I boot that ISO with the LBU changes on real hardware.
Boom.
I have my own install image factory.
The biggest drawback is that it uses M U S L. Oh, instead of G lib C. Mm hmm.
He goes on to say the area where this is an issue is proprietary applications.
There is a compatibility layer for G lib C libraries, but I haven't tried steam yet.
Oh wow.
Alpine on the desktop.
All right.
What I like about this feedback was that Jordan clearly got some of our perspective, you know,
just that Alpine is conceptually similar to arch.
They write and that I like to think of it as a smaller, simpler arch.
What stuck with me there is that clearly they picked up on what we wanted from arch was
this sort of simple base, very lean and mean, and that we could actually just have an understanding
of everything that was going on, especially for the arch server.
He, I think, I think he's right though that, Hey, maybe we should try Alpine in a few more
places.
See where it fits.
Yeah.
That minimum viable server really is what appeals to us.
And you can kind of see why maybe SUSE doesn't necessarily appeal to us because what we want
is just the bare bare minimum where Wes and I can actually articulate to you the applications
that are installed because it's Samba and net data and everything else is in a container.
We can articulate to you the file system layout, everything because we built it with our own
hands and we only installed the packages we absolutely had to have.
And that's one of the ways we think maybe we've been a little more successful now with
arch on the server is switching to the LTS kernel and really keeping that base install
super, super minimal.
I also like it as a way for, you know, there's lots of stuff that arch or Alpine are similar.
They don't set up for you or maybe they give you documentation about how to set up.
And I, I like us having to either figure out how to do that or not do that and skip it
and live with the results because it also gives you a nice window into some of the stuff
you might get for free on a more fully featured distro like Fedora or Ubuntu.
Yeah.
And I think there's a, probably a future episode out there.
If we remember to wear our flame retardant pants, where we try out something like a micro
or some of the just enough OS stuff, maybe if it's possible to run on the raspberry PI
cause it seems like that'd be a great candidate for that kind of SUSE distro.
So I could see future content depending on what we get in feedback and the people are
interested in that kind of stuff.
I'm kind of thinking, Wes, we do a kind of a pick feedback special next week cause we've
got a lot of really good feedback that we haven't been able to get to, including some
follow up on mail spring, which I am now back again using since we heard the developer pop
his head up.
Yeah.
I'm using mail spring again for my email, but I want to follow up more on that later
cause we got some email to that.
We also got some people that got predictions in.
So I want to get those in while we can while we're still within January and a lot more.
So Wes, let's just jump to the pics and promise to do more feedback next week.
Now you may have noticed I've been thinking a lot about GPUs this week.
I don't know if that came across and while I was looking at what the hell's going on
between my X1 and the XPS 13 and of course my desktop, I wanted something that's like
that that utility that tells you everything about your processor that I forget what it's
called like X CPU or whatever.
Now there's GPU viewer and it's a front end to GLX info, Vulcan info, CLI info and ES2
info and it puts it all in a fairly decent way.
It's not beautiful.
I won't call it pretty.
Yeah.
That was my main takeaway here, but it's a lot simpler to navigate than having to know
all the commands and then figure out like paging in your terminal, especially if you're
new to this stuff and just want to figure out what's on your system and get to playing
games.
Yeah.
Is my Vulcan support working?
Am I using the accelerated GPU or am I using the open source driver?
These questions are immediately obvious to you with this tool and there's lots of ways
to get that info, but the nice thing about GPU viewer is you also get the nitty gritty
details like the specific driver version information and the exact video card that's detected and
the amount of hardware information that the thing can extract for your video card and
then all of the other kind of like supported 3D features in Vulcan and OpenGL and it's
just a nice tool for troubleshooting graphics in general and so it's called GPU-Viewer.
We'll have a link in the show notes at linuxunplugged.com.388 or you can probably find it on GitHub because
that's where it is.
It's on GitHub.
It's packaged in Ubuntu 2010 and a few other places or you can install it since it's just
a simple Python app.
So easy to get a shout out to our core contributors, unpluggedcore.com.
They really are the hawks of this show.
They really they held in there.
I announced last week that we had this bug where people who used the founder promo were
not getting renewed and so we had this renewal failure rate that was like 52% or it was getting
pretty bad.
It was getting worse by the day.
Well I'm happy to say that the bug's been fixed and like 97% of anyone who ever used
the founder code has got the discount reapplied.
You don't have to do a dang thing.
So if you sat back and didn't do anything, well your procrastinating paid off because
they fixed it for you.
But I am still, for anybody who may have slipped through the cracks because 97% is not 100%
and anybody else who wants to lock in a membership for this show and get access to the benefit
goodies, I'm keeping that promo code 2021 going for a bit and that will take two bucks
off.
Just doing that for a little while, kind of like a happy new year's deal.
Then you get access to our feeds, either the limited ad version of the show, the same full
production, the version that really sounds good in the car or the one that had the Joe
touch.
And then there's also the bootleg feed.
The full live version, all our screw ups, the stuff that never makes it into the show.
If you can't join live, that's the one you want.
Yeah, it has that live experience, man.
You can put it up on the TV and like, you know, be working in the kitchen and you would
feel like you're listening to a live show.
You get the full pre and post show.
It's basically like a whole other show.
It really is.
And we got a couple of shout outs from diehards that make it through the entire file because
it's much, much longer than the main show.
And that's all available to anybody who wants to support us at unpluggedcore.com.
Mr. Payne, also, I want to mention that our friends over at a Cloud Guru have a Red Hat
certified administrator exam prep course that you can take.
Oh, ho, ho.
Nice.
Yes.
And in this course, they cover like the concepts necessary to pass the Red Hat exam using a
mix of lessons and hands on labs.
And then at the end, you put it all together with a challenge lab.
And I know people have emailed into the show asking about certifications and which ones
on a Cloud Guru we recommend.
This is the one.
And so we'll put a link to that in the show notes because I guess a lot of people have
New Year's resolutions out there.
So check out the Red Hat certified system administrator exam prep.
That's the one we recommend for that particular path if that's where you're going.
And we'll have a link to that specific one in the show notes so you can get it at a cloudguru.com.
And then we'll hold, I think, the rest of the feedback, Wes, for next show because I
think we'll just do a feedback special.
So we got to some of it.
But I think that's what the plan is.
So do join us next week.
See you next week.
Same bad time, same bad station.
And now is a great time to get any feedback you might have Linux Unplugged dot com slash
contact and hey, maybe we'll include it in next week's show.
Good point.
Look at you.
That's the hack, right?
You got something you've been wanting to get in and now you know we're looking at the feedback
in particular.
Now's the time.
You can just get it in.
You can join us live at jblive.tv.
We do the show at noon Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern or get it on a download.
You can find the feeds for that at Linux Unplugged dot com slash subscribe.
And like I said, links to everything we talked about today at Linux Unplugged dot com slash
three eight eight.
Thanks for joining us and we'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
All right, JB titles dot com.
Let's go.
And I know we don't have a lot of time.
I wanted to kind of make this a slightly shorter episode because we've been going long.
But I did want to actually get this on air because it's something I've been meaning to
talk about and haven't had a place to like talk about it or troubleshoot with you guys.
So JB titles dot com.
Go boat.
Chris has some technical troubles.
Yeah, I'm having some fedora woes and it's nothing that's like it's not going to like
it's not a deal breaker.
But I have this weird problem where all of my flat pack apps have vanished from Plasma's
purview.
My launcher, my menu, K runner, what it cannot find them.
They don't exist.
I can still execute them on the command line.
And if I search for them and discover and then go to their entry, I can launch them.
So they still register.
They're there.
They're just not there.
But they're otherwise unknown.
And while they are running, I cannot right click and say pin to taskbar.
I cannot add them to the menu.
I cannot do it just the I can.
The option is it just you check it and nothing happens.
They just and then I close them and they are they are completely unfindable unless I do
the flat pack execute command or I launch discover again.
And here's and so I don't know what that's about, but and I don't know if this problem
is related.
I don't think so.
There's a separate kind of software discover issue where I will do a DNF upgrade, you know,
update whatever, and I'll update all my packages.
I'll get tons and tons and tons and tons of stuff installed because Fedora's always got
lots of goodies.
And then I'll reboot and I'll log in and I'll get the plasma notification that I have 14
updates available.
So I'll do a DNF update.
It'll say no packages available.
So then I do a I'll do a flat pack update.
It'll say no updates available.
I open up discover and there's like 14 packages in there, including like what looked like
to be just system packages.
And then I do the update.
So then so that happened one time.
Now the flip side has happened where I go and discover it says there's no updates.
I launched DNF.
It says there's updates and that they just don't agree like in none of them agree, but
they seem to be installing some of the same stuff.
And it's really strange.
So I'll do a DNF update on the command line, reboot and then get a notification.
Hey, you got more packages.
I go and discover.
I do an update.
And it's not just flat packs.
I know what you're talking about.
I know what's happening.
Different cache.
Yeah, there's two separate caches right now.
So one of the problems that we have right now and this is something I've been on the
on my spare time trying to figure out how to fix because I'm one of the by virtue of
happenstance.
I'm now one of the maintainers of package kit upstream.
I have been trying to figure out how to synchronize.
Basically the problem is because package kit and DNF don't expose APIs between each other
to lock the database while it is refreshing and pulling in stuff.
It can only do a lock when it's applying a transaction.
The fix quote unquote was to make it so that they fetch caches independently to avoid races
and all kinds of stupid stuff.
Like back in the days when we were using yum, everything was piped through the yum tool.
And what would happen occasionally is that when you ran the yum command, it would be
like waiting for package kit to quit waiting for package.
So can I ask you something?
So what happens when?
So I do a DNF update and I install all the upgrades and then I go and discover and I
install all the updates there.
Is it just reinstalling some of the same packages I just installed with DNF?
Yeah, what's going on actually happens on the file system?
Yeah, that's a good question.
I think what actually happens is that it silently does nothing.
Just chugs right along.
What are you supposed to going on with the flat pack thing?
Like all my flat pack desktop launchers are gone.
I'm guessing you updated the plasma 525.
Yeah, I always update like daily.
Can't keep plasma away from him.
I'm basically making that guess because like I've heard all kinds of random bonkers stuff
from different people about the plasma 525 update just today.
Like three different people have told me three different things that have gone wrong in 525
and now I'm scared.
It may be a little bit further back because I think this may have been going on.
This has probably been going on for three weeks, two weeks, two weeks.
Okay, so I wish I'd known this before because like I know I meant to bring it up to you
last week, but I forgot.
Okay, I think I know what's happening here.
So what goes on for the flat pack stuff is that flat pack in order for the desktop files
to show up in the desktop, what it does is it has a profile dot D snippet or environment
D helper or something.
I forget exactly what it is that tries to export a variable that adds the flat pack
desktop file path to the search path so that when plasma starts up or gnome starts up or
whatever, it'll read those additional desktop files because they're not installed in the
same place as everything else is.
I'm just saying if I wasn't using a flat pack, if I just installed a package from the AUR,
this would not have happened.
That's all I'm saying.