That whole like Firefox is fast thing I remember going to FOSDEM three years
ago and seeing two years ago maybe a demo of Servo their Rust rendering
engine and it was like ridiculously fast it was like I can't describe it was just
like an image appearing on the screen the rendering time it just looked like
they just opened a PNG like and it immediately appeared and there was an
flicking backwards and forwards through pages they were going through various
Wikipedia pages and because the renderer was very early on in its development
so it couldn't render every page they all used Wikipedia as the example
but they were skipping through Wikipedia pages and it was like they were all
cached locally and he made a point of clearing the cache and saying nope we're
loading each one and going to it new and they just look like flicking between
PNGs but when I ran Firefox locally it's nothing like that so in those three
years they've lost something from that or the webs got more complicated well
yeah maybe you know they just demo oh well there's that I do I don't this is
one of those things that I always feel like a bit of a dork for describing as
one of the things that I like about Firefox but because it's so like
intangible but one of the things I like about using unity over some other
desktop environments like these certain intangibles and for me on Firefox with
with the new rendering engine it's like I just prefer the way it loads the page
it's about I feel like Chrome and Firefox are about neck-and-neck maybe
Firefox has a bit of an edge right now but it and it definitely has an edge on
the the impact it puts on my system compared to Chrome but like I just the
way like the way my brain reads websites it feels like Firefox gives priority to
rendering those elements first interesting where Chrome seems to like
chug on the whole page and then dump it on the screen or something I don't I
can't even fold I'd almost have to like get a high frame rate camera and record
the two of them loading shit maybe I should do that actually unusual it
doesn't I do remember early browsers there was definitely a tendency to
render fields and stuff yeah it feels like we're back I feel I should take out
my phone and try the high frame rate slow-mo video recording and record
Chrome loading the page and then the record Firefox loading the same page
play it back and see if then I can figure out what it is well you could you
could just open the developer tools on the right hand side and it gives you a
timeline of what's loading so you can actually see it lists everything that's
loading and you couldn't you know you it will tell you what is it but I remember
one of the UDS is we had in Brussels many years ago like I think at 2010 this
would be there was a chromium developer who was giving a presentation about how
they sped up chromium and how they made it faster and he the demo that he gave I
may have said this before on the show sorry the demo that he gave he was just
launching chromium from from nothing and as a demonstration of a comparison he
opened known calculator next to it and he just kept opening them one after the
other and going chromium calculator chromium calculate and just showing and
you could see chromium would load faster than known calculator and if you watch
them calculate you could actually see it draw each of the buttons on the screen
and he said I'm not I'm not having a go at the known calculator devs and someone
shouted out that's a good job because he's in the audience right he said this
is an example like all this complication you've got with the GTK toolkit doing all
of that work and we've stripped that out and the browser which is way more
heavyweight than no calculator loads tons faster than just a simple
calculator and it's a lot of it is that perception of how how quick you watch it
draw exactly like you were saying you can kind of see where it's drawing the
page. This is Linux Unplugged episode 228 for December 19, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's all prepared,
battened down and our hatches are ready for the holidays. My name is Chris. My
name is Wes. Hello Wes and welcome to the last live Unplugged of the year. Boom!
Yeah we still have more shows in the can coming up in the feeds and on the site
and all the usual places but we are kind of excited because this is our last live
production of the year. Goodbye 2017. And we're going out with some great
community stories and we're gonna try something fun since we thought it is our
last show let's let's let's just do something that we've always kind of
wanted to do and it's the Linux commands you should never use. Like a few commands
that are guaranteed to wreck your box. Just don't do it. Don't do it. We're gonna
tell you about them. Maybe you're maybe a new Linux box came to you for the
holidays and you want to know how to destroy it immediately. We got you
covered in this week's episode but we also got a bunch of really great
community news and for the love of all that is Linux I really hope we're almost
in the homestretch for the Gentoo challenge but we will find out later
today. We will have to wait. Stay tuned and find out. So we have a lot to get to
and like I said it is our last live show of the year so it is at this moment we
must bring in the virtual lug. Time appropriate greetings mumble room. Hello.
Good evening. Oh I believe I heard a beard in that mix too and a poppy and a
wimpy. Good to see you guys. Mr. Veratunde is in there. CM. Hey citizen. Mini Mac.
You guys. You're my mumblers. I love you. I love you. Let's let's start out with
something you could be looking forward to in the summertime because it is the
thick of winter right now. In fact I think it's damn near winter solstice. You
know when is winter solstice? Do you know? Let's take a look. Hey Alexa. When is winter
solstice? I'm just I'm just kind of curious. Usually right around the 21st.
December 21st. We're pretty darn close and it's pretty darn
dark outside. So let's talk about the summer for a little bit. Oh dreams of the
summer. What can we look forward to in Linux in the summer of 2018? Well. Probably
some stupid drama. That's my that's my bet. Yeah yeah yeah I think you're
probably right. But Linus Claus has an answer for us. We could ask him. You
actually fully control and most likely can mathematically predict. This is
Linus at a recent Linux Foundation event the keynote where he's
being interviewed by Dirk and he says all right tell me about Linux kernel 5.0.
So when are we going to get Linux 5.0? Oh well I have I have been known to start
losing track of numbers when they go into the 20s and 30s. Fingers and toes?
Yeah no I yeah when I had to take off my shoes to count kernel releases. Can I
just say that I love that I love that this is how Linus decides when it's time
to rev the number. It's not like some like Phil Schiller marketing scheme or
Sanjay planning the next big phase of Azure and the version numbers got to
jump from 8 to 10 so that way they can pretend like 8 never happened. Nope it's
just I don't know that seems to be like the numbers are too high to me and I
can't really keep them all straight so I feel like I should change it. You know
it's it's psychological for me it turns out 13 and 14 they're easy to remember
but when you're looking back and you can't recall the difference between 23
and 24 or the the numbers smaller numbers stand out more so I suspect that
we'll hit 4.19 and and instead of 4.20 I might decide it's time to
5.0. The numbers don't mean anything at all they have not meant
anything in a long time. It was actually very stressful when back when they did
it was a horrible model for development. I remember I mean even back in the 1.0
days just trying to like draw the line in the water in the sand of this is 1.0
and this is when our internet code is actually working was really tough and
very stressful and then you never end up doing the right decision anyway so
jettisoning that entirely and saying no the numbers don't mean anything they do
keep incrementing but we just try to make them sound like easier to remember
than than any other kind of meaningfulness has made my life much
easier and I think pretty much everybody enjoys it now and there are still the
few people when I make 5.0 and they expect lots of new features they're
disappointed yes so if I get my math right that means next summer ish
probably I also did some numerology and decided that every 2 million get objects
is when when I need to do a new major release but since our development is
accelerating that actually might be sooner than next summer so it really
depends on I it's a random number and I want people to be aware that it's a
random number and has no meaning so there you go be arbitrarily excited for
no reason at all that we may get Linux kernel 5.0 in the summer hey yo are you
arbitrarily randomly excited for no reason very much so me too I can't help
it it's 5.0 it feels like then we get to have even though it's not true and it
makes no more sense you can shame people for being on older kernels like yeah
you're still three something we're on five now and your Android device is
running kernel 3.4 Wow exactly I have the whole talk it's about a
half-hour linked in the show notes if you'd like to watch it it's a wide
ranging discussion as well as a blog right up from its FOSS if you'd rather
read it now OMG Ubuntu put together one of those
traditional end-of-year posts the best of 2017 Linux I thought we just go we go
through with the mumble room see what they think this is mostly put together
by Joey's readers and then he voted then he I think added a few spices and dash
here and there the number one distro of 2017 is Ubuntu 1710 according to Joey
obvious reasons there because of a huge huge release but number two what do you
think a number two the number two Linux distribution of 2017 solace 3 solace
getting the nod here as an as like the number two competitor to the Ubuntu 1710
release that's that's pretty big news I would say yeah although thinking about
it I don't know who else I would give it to I mean it seems obvious that it
should be solace in fact it's a it's remarkable that solace is shot this far
up on these kinds of lists already right I do think it does speak to things that
we've noticed and maybe commented on throughout the year but it's sort of a
it's like a big win that it's deserved seems like huge I think what do you
think mumble room is do you agree with solace being the number two distro of
the year what about that what about that Ubuntu mate sorry I just I had to poke
wimpy a little bit love installed in a bunch of mostly way more than I've
installed solace that's what's up yeah yeah I have to get stuffed and put you
on a shelf that's brilliant I have to say I I'm surprised I personally I was
surprised at how much take up there's been of 1710 I mean I know it was my
like significantly different from previous releases that we've put out
over the last like three three to eight years but it we're seeing a ton more
people running 1710 than 1704 1704 is like probably proportionally what a
normal a normal interim release would be it's like not a huge amount of take up
most people stay on the LTS but we're seeing comparable numbers of people
running 1710 as run the LTS there's that many people who have jumped on it what
do you suppose that tells us I'm trying to interpret what that means people like
new stuff could it be actually that you know the people who left Ubuntu because
they went no unity and now they're doing no more flood back to it that's what I
was wondering definitely there's definitely I think anecdotally there's
some evidence that that's happened that people have come back to Ubuntu but I
think also there was a lot of interest around 1710 and there was a lot of good
communication from the desktop team about why people should care about 1710
and I think that piqued their interest for a long time you know that that that
hasn't been there and you know there was a lot of new stuff and a lot of things
that they knew that were coming and yeah people have have really flocked to it
the common wisdom though before the 1710 release was that you know we get some I
mean this is my interpretation was we get some pickup but for the most part
everybody will stick on the LTS now I wonder if as this development pace
continues if that trend will continue or if 1804 will become really sticky oh
that'll be Italian when that tells if it's gnome or if it's new stuff well we
tend to get two bumps when the LTS comes out because the people who are on the
interim release so people right now who are on 1710 will get offered 1604 the
moment it comes out as an upgrade option and sorry 1804 we'll get that as an
option when when it comes out but people who are on the previous LTS 1604 won't
get that offered to them by default until the point one release a couple of
months later so to iron out all the all the bugs so they don't we don't get
everyone from 1604 coming to 1804 on day one of the release they come a little
while later so we tend to get two bumps but I think we're gonna see two
similarly sized bumps for people coming from 1710 because there's a ton of
people on that and a ton of people coming from 1604 later so I think by
like middle of next year like August next year we're gonna see a huge number
of people on 1804 more than probably we expected yeah okay that's that makes a
lot of sense so I'm jumping ahead a little bit in Joey's list here the
number five event or Linux thing in 2017 was Ubuntu for Windows the subsystem
for the Linux subsystem for Windows and the arrival of Ubuntu on the actual
Windows Store in July and then it became available in the fall creators update
for anybody that wants Windows 10 and wants to go check that box and open
Sousa and Fedora I believe are in route still although I'm not positive might be
in there I thought they landed okay I think Sousa might be but I don't know if
Fedora is I checked kind of recently I a few weeks ago but I'm a little it's
been a few weeks yeah wow what do we think of that um do we agree is this has
this been a good thing I don't know if I agree it's been a good thing I think I
deviate I agree that it was a moment it's certainly noteworthy there I don't
think it's the sky falling everyone will just use Windows subsystem I don't
think that I think there are people plenty of developers plenty of
developers yeah and I'm sure Michael Dominic would speak to this who are either
forced or encouraged to use Windows at work but they want a typical Linux user
space somewhere on their machine and this is perfect for that and I we get a
fair amount of feedback from people telling us that is where they use it it's
just at work where they have to yeah that's what I've heard too but I've also
heard people say yeah I was thinking about switching but I'm not switching
now I have heard that yeah I so I think WSL is going to continue to evolve but
there's also a number of things that it just can't do right now so depending on
how exotic your requirements are you may run out of rope with WSL yes but but it
does a job to provide it does a far better job to provide a familiar Linux
work environment than you know SIGWIN and MinGW yes of that nature yes yes
very very very much so so it looks like beard just checked in here and yeah
Ubuntu is in the store right now leap 42 and SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 12 are
in the store but no centos or fedoras or nothing like that I'd love to see centos
I love the idea of the Windows store being taken over by loads of different
yeah I do love the idea of them being some of the most popular apps in that
store because let's be honest that stores filled with trash so it's could
be it could be possible arch Linux in there yeah he wraps it up with a few
other things like Adam IDE being one of the better desktop ID ease along with
all the packages and Geary as the best alternative to Thunderbird which I don't
know if I agree with Geary either I I may I may give the nod to mail spring
but perhaps I'll definitely give them not to mail spring for the best mail
client right now yeah yeah it's one of those it's one of those where Geary is
great in a world where there's not other platforms that have better mail clients
not to disparage Geary because it's one of my favorites mail spring is
competitive on all platforms Mac Windows or Linux it's a very competitive
application it's a very good-looking application a lot of thoughts gone into
the design it's a very responsive in terms like I can have it vertically
stacked in a small space on my desktop I can have it maxed out over a 2k display
a lot of work has gone into mail spring and an alias before it so I'm gonna talk
I think I've been I've been pinging back and forth with the developer he's a
busy guy it's the holidays and I've been pinging him last-minute every time but
in the future I think we might do a segment on it because I think it's a
very nice very very very nice mail client and it's in better shape than I
think it's ever been when it was the latest I've been using it I just wish
it support GPG but hello oh well I'm sure the future holds many great things
that you mail regularly that uses GPG okay all my family friends release
really so you're some some users of all of the people using GPG I haven't had I
used it on and off over the years but nobody else I email sticks to it so then
I always feel like the fool that's they almost feel like I'm fronting like I'm
like I'm showing off because nobody else sticks with it and then it's like okay
I'm that guy there's even there's even blogs from the GPG developers explaining
why they don't use GPG for mail because it's just a poor solution huh well we're
all doomed we're all doing it cause poor solution poor implementation
it's difference yeah the implementation is the issue yes yes yes good good
point because unless everyone's doing it it's irrelevant one of my favorite
projects to follow this year just on the back burner has been be cash FS if
William was here he'd tell you why but yeah I just really am excited about this
next-generation file system this may be eventually the one that I end up putting
on my workstations and Kent has taken a look he took recently a little time off
over the hot over the summer but he's been back since then and he's been
banging out a lot of different features and I just want to give us a quick
update he says the biggest thing he's been spending his time on lately has been
improving the test infrastructure which is awesome and chasing bugs he said
there's also been major and cool improvements on the core IO path the
recent change is that now whenever generating new checksums be cash FS
verifies it against the existing checksum by generating multiple
checksums that cover all existing data one of which covers just the data we're
keeping and then merging the checksums we calculated and verifying the equal to
the original checksum this means that even if you don't have ECC memory memory
corruption can't lead to silent corruption or bit rot of existing data
so this is in my opinion some nice stuff so a lot of times people are always
talking especially when you're talking about large ZFS implementations one of
the most common questions that comes into tech snap when they're talking
about setting up ZFS is do I need ECC memory and a lot of times the answer is
no but geez it sure helps and now with be cash FS you sort of have that safety
net which is way more economical on laptops and desktops and low-end arm
devices ECC memory has a big cost overhead and performance overhead to a
degree so and not that this checksum checking doesn't but be cash FS is so
damn fast it's just it's beautiful to see this happen in the file system and
it's gonna be one of those banner features once it ships and people ask
is this thing production ready this will be one of the things people cite I'm
very happy about that development also coming down the pipeline is quota
support which he says has been the cause of much wailing and gnashing of teeth for
now the less said about quotas the better I didn't follow I've not followed
the drama there but then here's the big thing he just slips in very very last
sentence of this rather long patreon post he says lastly be cash house be
cash FS has its first corporate sponsor a big thank you to elements TV and if
you need me to storage appliances you should definitely check them out so
apparently elements TV making a little long-term bet on B cash FS really cool
to see that it's really cool to see yeah and he I just don't feel like you know I
can't I can't be emotionally invested in butter FS and but there's just some
things that like as great as XFS is that just not what it has been designed to do
right if you're here you hope this is the new hope of Linux file systems and
I'm glad to see anything's are programmed if you're listening you're
like well what is what is so great about it do a site search and look on our back
catalog where we talk about it where William goes into some detail about it
and if you're excited like we are you can help out Kent at patreon.com slash
B cash FS before we move on anybody else in the mumble room want to wax
poetically about B cash FS or are we are we all actually I have I have I don't
know I don't know who I should ask cuz it's on the community hub but little
birdies around me it told me many little bits and details about this and I have
kind of a picture but I have a suspicion that poppy or wimpy may know a lot more
it's multi pass and it's it's not a password manager no no it's a totally
new project coming out of canonical that manages virtual machine instances that
are running up into it uses cloud images it's a QMU KVM on the back end and I
imagine it's it's gonna be hot stuff but I really don't know much more about it
than that I've I've seen I've seen little rumors and bits and pieces about
it I saw some murmurings at a boon to rally where people were behind closed
doors and I oversaw a lot of that but I haven't seen any concrete
pictures but I bet you somebody in our mumble room knows a little more about it
who wants to buy you spoke first okay so multi pass is to KVM what Lex D is to
containers so Lex D is a tool for provisioning thin containers and multi
passes away for standing up full-blooded virtual machines on a burn to really
quickly so you just snap install wait for not just on a bun to actually because
you can snap install multi pass in fact I was joking with I key about this the
other day that this is what all solace users have been crying out for now they
can snap install multi pass and then they can multi pass launch and it will
provision and fire up a 1604 funny VM on on solace very good so yeah it's just a
really fast way so it's designed as a developer tool so if you've used things
like vagrant in the past for example it's a much simpler way to actually
stand up a bunch of VMs running different supported releases of Ubuntu
so that you can flesh out your dev environment hmm and I think you'll see a
bit of noise about multi pass in 2018 it's definitely the one to watch yeah
since I got to I also noticed that what seems to be some rather banner features
again is a it can fetch and cache images from the cloud of like a what I presume
to be like a preset up virtual machine sort of like a la docker images and then
it can periodically refresh to make sure that the image is staying up-to-date
that seems like some pretty big features yeah yeah it's it's good stuff so they
use the what's called the cloud in it images which are updated frequently so
when when something in the archive changes that affects those images those
images get respun and then are available to you fresh and immediately hmm are
there any plans for API support or similar interesting question I'll
decline to comment for the time that's acceptable I will say you mentioned
vagrant I'm definitely excited vagrant could be so slow I already use LexD for
some similar things but having like a full virtual chase virtualization is
sometimes what you need mm-hmm I'm excited sometimes you need it yeah
sometimes you do yeah we have a couple use cases here in the studio where we're
still using virtualization we're on a very old Proxmox installation and when
multi pass came out I said to Wes he said this might be what I used to redo
some of these virtual machines because it's an early it's early days for the
project this post is made December 13th although it's been in the works for a
bit but it's it's sitting on top of KVM and other technologies that are tried
and true so there's not a lot of risk for me to try to spin up a virtual
machine based on this because Ubuntu is a known quality KVM is a known quality
snaps a known quality yeah like between like that and the tooling from like from
snap and LexD I've really I've really enjoyed what's come out of a bunty there
so I'm sure this will be an equally pleasant experience yeah what the bus
I'm not so sure on the name but I like the idea the name will become relevant
in the future I think so I've got a number of VMs stood up with a multi pass
different versions of Ubuntu and what I've been doing for fun is installing
inside those the Ubuntu Marte meta packages and then X to go yeah and then
connecting into them for running instances of Ubuntu Marte on different
releases of Ubuntu that's I don't do it for those purposes but I do something
similar with several Ubuntu Marte instances I do that exact thing but I
use it so I can test stuff across different versions of Ubuntu Marte you
know it's it's just really convenient much much simpler to get versions up
again then you know using virtual box or some other UI you can you can poke it
around it's nice and I'm looking forward how it's going to develop over at 2018 I
smile that it's a snap because it's it's just it's so funny that it's not just
boom it's everywhere it's everywhere that runs snaps it's there now that's
pretty great speaking of being there one of the things that freaks people out
about Thunderbolt 3 is you're on the PCI bus you're right there that direct
memory access too late you've seen everything and there is finally a
project in the works to tackle this problem I think this is probably Beards
favorite story of the week because I think he told me about this on Sunday it
was like early on on you remember what was it about the story that stuck out to
you Rekai because I was like okay well that sounds that sounds interesting why
do I care about this again I don't know it just it just seemed like it's nice to
have security on every part of your system yeah sure I suppose what I do
like about it is that it's like a full-fledged solution here this is
coming out of the skunk works at at Red Hat I believe and one of the things
that'll do is it'll even give you a prompt say in the gnome notification
area which is kind of awesome so you're sitting there you go hey hey yo homes
some rando just hooked up an unknown untrusted Thunderbolt device to your
system are you cool with this and that I think is a pretty great feature because
unlike USB Thunderbolt allows wide access to devices you could just read
the memory and you could in theory attach a malicious device to that thing
and just dump everything the system that's in the IO I mean yeah it's it's
it's pretty critical that this thing gets secured especially on a system that
might have randos sitting down at it the only the only thing that I wonder is
what happens for some of these use cases where some we have had issues where a
hard roller reconnect and disconnect and reconnect and disconnect and reconnect
and disconnect there could be kinds of problems where now you're where you have
another step where you have to say yes approve yes approve yeah I could see
some instances in troubleshooting of course this is probably just something
that people that don't live in a production environment don't have to
deal with very much but hopefully bolt just nails that right between a good way
to give a security without causing a bunch of inconvenience when troubles or
an easy you know like whatever I don't care just I know I'm on secure right now
I was reading up on it and I think if it recognizes a hardware device that's been
previously accepted it'll just write okay yeah it does look like that I
suppose that's true so I hope it's not going to ask me to authorize a device
using an on-screen prompt when my device is booting with an external I suppose
that is I'll explain now full disclosure with an eGPU attached when you boot your
system you get no output whatsoever until the display manager has loaded a
little little spooky yeah yeah I mean you know I do really like the UI
implementation like in the gnome drop-down menu it even gives you like
scanning peripherals like it's it's it's using a DBUS API to list the devices and
enroll them and then emit new signals to the desktop environment when a new
device is attached it so it does feel like it's very dependent on the desktop
interface but I just can't imagine they wouldn't have thought of that use case
scenario I do think that this is also good for there's devices that are
starting to count now that require these security levels so it's nice that Linux
is getting this early on before you know there's devices that you can't use yeah
yeah and there again not to make it all about us but there is a very serious use
case where we take devices that have USB C and Thunderbolt 3 specifically on them
to cons fest whatever you want to call them rallies and we take hardware there
and we set up and we record and we broadcast and our peripherals connect
over these buses so we really you could so easily have somebody walk up to the
booth and they could lean in while they're talking to you they could plug
in something to an open port and screw with you and do in we're live on the air
don't get any ideas people I shouldn't have said any of that forget all of that
gotta cut all that out it does it for us it really is that the the struggle is
real well as more and more laptops have these ports people are using them there's
more peripherals you want to use it could be vulnerable you macbook users
you all right that before we go any further let's take a moment and go to
linux.ting.com everybody now linux.ting.com sign up for a better way to do
mobile the way that if you're outside the States often seems like mobile
should just be done the way if somehow we had some sort of DeLorean and we
could go back and reset the whole cellular industry and they had to
compete on their own merits today this is what they would do you pay for what
you use it's I don't know it almost seems like it's too obvious but this is
this is the model it's six dollars for a phone and then you pay for your minutes
your messages and your megabytes and whatever you use that's what you pay
it's simple $23 is about the average bill once you've made some calls and
downloaded some stuffs and texted some peeps maybe done a few tinder hookups I
don't know whatever you're into West don't judge it's usually around 23 bucks
per month there's no contracts nor the termination fee nationwide coverage they
got the GSM and they got the CDMA you know about that that means if you got
one of them devices you could bring it over to ting and you can get $25 in
service credit now if your first bill is gonna be less than $23 you just paid for
more than your first month what now say your phone's busted it's old you need
something new they have a bunch of great devices you can buy directly and they'll
give you $25 off one of those in fact I think they got a big sale on the on like
the nice Motorola devices you'll go over there right now go to Linux dot ting
comm and then click on the shop page if you want a nice Android device that
doesn't break the bank yeah yeah they got the moto 2017 lineup on sale right
now so you can apply our discount at Linux dot ting comm you can get the
moto x4 unlocked no contract nor the termination fee no blocking updates for
their ting experience everything with a great Android experience nice
performance beautiful screen it expands expansive RAM or memory $324 I'm so
excited I my brain doesn't even comprehend how that's possible they've
also got the e4 plus for a hundred and forty four dollars under $200 for a
great Android experience and they have those physical home buttons which are
apparently going out of style these days couldn't they couldn't fit that in on
the latest iPhones no Linux dot ting comm go there sign up in a big thank you
to ting for sponsoring the unplug program Linux dot ting comm
Firefox quantum was a good release we were just talking about in the pre-show
how I've been using it more and more and then they went and did that thing with
the extension that we all know about you know the one where they injected the
mr. robot looking glass extension disabled it by default and then had a
whoopsie daisy said we're sorry and retracted it I've already covered this
in Linux action news I don't really have much more to say about this but I wanted
it I wanted to hear your thoughts Wes oh and then we gotta open up the gentoo
challenge but then I wanted to hear your thoughts what do you think about this
move Mozilla made to push down the add-on it's disabled by default if you
participated in the feedback program you got this installed and it looks like the
angle was going to be some sort of tie-in with mr. robot where people
watching the series could go unlock a game and they would discover oh my gosh
it's already in my browser oh my gosh Firefox and mr. robot work together on
this it's so cool I just love Firefox so much I'm gonna use it for the rest of my
life and so they pushed it down to everybody's computer because I was
obviously what was going to happen and it looks like Mozilla wasn't even paid
these rumors I have not confirmed this it looks like Mozilla wasn't even paid
a dime for this so this wasn't like they sold out to the mr. robot series it was
like we're gonna capitalize on the momentum of Firefox quantum we're gonna
capitalize on this somewhat popular geeky television show and blow everybody's
mind and it really backfired I think yeah I definitely I think I'm sad I'm
sad how much it has backfired and the you know the amount of negative press
personally I'm not I'm not thrilled about this I like like mr. robot
justified I don't necessarily need this add-on but being being shipped from
Mozilla I by using their browser I am in some ways implicitly just trusting the
software they ship if this seems like it would fall under the same domain so I
wasn't actively actively offended I also don't think it was a great move and I
was quantum had a really good release and so it's sad I can see why maybe they
would think that this could capitalize on that but it maybe also shows some
some wrong priorities or people who hadn't really thought this through at
Mozilla and it's really it's just sad that this this reaction maybe will make
people less ready to try out what really is quite a good browse yeah and it does
go geez what how did you not see how this wasn't gonna be received what what's
wrong with you guys does anybody in the mumble room have any thoughts that they
want on the story okay go ahead I wanted to give that I want to give you guys so
I I'm I'm kind of a little disappointed and companies make mistakes and people
can be very caught up in internally in their own thoughts and I know we've made
mistakes in the past that canonical where we've thought something would be a
good idea and there's been a gigantic backlash and we completely didn't expect
it because inside our own bubble the thing we did made sense but outside if
if you're if you're not an Amazon subscriber and you're not part of the
the culture that knows what mr. robot is this is just offensive it's it's
cultural arrogance on the part of Mozilla to think that anyone outside
that bubble gives a shit about mr. robot because they don't right it might well
be a popular program in the United States of America and a few other
countries but nobody else gives a damn and I think it's arrogant on their
behalf to think other people would yeah and insensitive to what it's probably a
large percentage of their user base like maybe that's not who they want to add
especially people who are fans of mr. robot they're gonna be the more
technically aware more privacy concerned group out of anyone watching any
television show either way it's not a great way yeah yeah it really shows a
lack of understanding and and the echo chamber effect I think is what poppy
sound like if they if they bundled like maybe if the extension was something
like hey we're gonna bundle tour in there or we're gonna buy yeah right yeah
as an option like things like that might have made more sense that might not been
used even I think tree I appreciate that the the extension that they did install
they only did it for English language install so but that still represents a
significant chunk of people who don't live on the continental u.s. you know
would have received this thing so yeah I think it was a little bit sad I think it
was a little bit overblown in the community that people went a bit nuts
about it but you know I can kind of see why it does seem to be there's building
momentum at getting angry at Mozilla that's really the core thing they've
got to figure out how to address is the mob is ready to get into justice mode at
a moment's notice these days and Mozilla's names ending up on that list
more and more but on the positive side of this whole thing unless anybody else
has anything they want to say I think the positive side of this has been
Vivaldi has received a lot of publicity a lot of people in our discord rooms and
our telegram group and on other places are so I'm trying out Vivaldi I'm
switching to Vivaldi when people say what should I try instead I'm seeing
Vivaldi linked a lot which you try brave brave is just awesome yeah yeah you
actually want a browser that is interested in your privacy then brave
is the way to go because that's just baked in that's their whole USP right
yeah and brave got a little news this week because they've launched now as a
snap you can snap install brave which is kind of awesome so it's a great chance
to try it out I believe they're adding some preliminary support for IPFS as
well and really so all kinds of interesting development activity can also
snap install IPFS oh geez let's keep it roll you know what else you can snap
installed now apparently VLC 30 RC one is available as a snap or the video is
the video land team looking at snapping is this is this happening yeah wow I've
been working with one of the VLC developers on this for a few weeks now
and we worked through some issues to make sure that hardware accelerated
video playback works out the box oh you know all of the platforms so it does the
right thing there are still some TV issues there's some theming issues those
are down to us in the snap world there's nothing VLC is our fault so we're
addressing those but it's um it's really nice because it's hooked up to their CI
so direct builds of VLC 3 goes straight to the snap store awesome get the
latest builds straight from there yeah that means it's really integrated in to
to the process which is great so odd to keep the to keep things rolling speaking
of Kota radio earlier Mike might be here happy to hear this that jet brains is
also getting on board with snaps and shipping 21 I think well I don't mean I
know they have 21 different tools I don't know how many are gonna be snapped
up but I know that the one that some of our audience might be interested in is
the pie charm stuff as well as the PHP storm webstorm go land oh cool very nice
so I've been working with one of the jet brains they they currently have 12 of
their products in the stable channel and they have two others that are in the
candidate and beta channels at the moment that they're hoping to push out
by the end of the year and then they'll be looking at other products in their
portfolio to see what they want to snap but yeah they've they've been working
very hard over the last six weeks or so bring in more and more of their
products to the store that's encouraging yeah yeah lots of done the jet brains
tools I wasn't super familiar with them and still I started working with them
and they're very very good I have to say yeah yeah Mike's been raving about them
for a little while I mean if you do if you do enterprise Java that's what you
use that's just that's just how it works so and a lot of those people do it on
Windows or I mean on a bunch of these days so that's you know that is a solid
ending for 2017 for snaps you know for an initiative that really was birthed
and really got into momentum this year that's a pretty that's a pretty
triumphant ending to that and a good positioning for 2018 we feel like I feel
like the the reasons for me to run arch are getting fewer and fewer if flat packs
and snaps and app images bear out I am really gonna get to that point where I
could have a solid stable Linux core with a LTS core and then fairly up-to-date
fluid user land application which has been the most achievable achievable for
me on arch but now it feels like it's almost going to be achievable anywhere
and then there's just gaps to close if we could get get the upgrades a little
smoother I'm oh man I'm I'm very excited about the future there's overhead there's
changes there's there's things to be worked out like Poby was just saying
with the theming but we have time to get there and we're making good time we're
making good progress yeah and that for the things that it works you know like
really well with it it's it's just amazing well I want to talk about one
more thing that caught my attention this week I don't know why I never noticed
this before but you know etcher right the the USB writing tool I actually
think it's pretty good we've covered it before is that electron it's electron
isn't it is yeah freaking a lecture on app to write USB thumb drives Wow welcome
to 2017 they have a command-line node app yeah 2017 indeed they have a little
piece of hardware they're working on have you seen at your pro no this thing
is it almost feels like a fantasy it's got one two three four five six seven
eight nine ten eleven twelve three four five six seven something like 17 or
some nonsense USB ports plus a master source port and an embedded touchscreen
that is etcher just running on the touchscreen it's like the electron app
just running on a dedicated screen in a hardware slab that could be best
described as a large USB hub and they they say it's they currently have this
thing able to write to dip 500,000 different SD and USB drives per month
are they etcher is already an etcher is already known for doing this so they're
like you know what we're gonna do we're gonna create a standalone hardware
device that allows you to write multiple cards or USB discs at once at the best
speeds we can possibly get to compared to any traditional method multiple writes
at the same time it does 60 megs per second it can do 750 megabytes megabytes
they're saying megabytes a second total you're gonna have a limiting factor of
just the total speed of the USB drives but 16 different cards you can hook up
to this thing with also there's I guess there's a whole bunch of SD card slots
that you can't see in the picture as well they say for the first the pricing
is gonna be competitive but I don't see an actual price on here but this thing's
I mean how would you do I'm trying to describe this to the audio audience like
this thing looks like almost like something out of Star Trek but like
retro star yeah like the original series it looks like Captain Kirk would like
something they would have where you could plug in a bunch of stuff you could
totally see how like hardware clinical or yeah very very just minimal interface
look at them go though so that's the etcher pro I don't really they just
have a subscription to find out about it it's interesting that this whole etcher
thing you know came out from from the resin that I owe people yeah and etcher
is just this you know thing to help them burn their software on USB Drive to get
you to install it which is why they you can see why they I mean they're like
well we'll make this for ourselves and then if we want a huge hit seemingly
it's yeah look at all these people that download right well now we'll make a
hard drive device that will make a hardware device to do and if a few
people want that and you can just see where their thought process on the from
beginning to end I have used some some products like that way back in the day
to you know to replicate a whole bunch of USB drives and a lot of them are not
you know their interfaces are not great they're pretty minimal so this is maybe
it's a maybe there's a target in the luxury USB mass writing market I'm not
sure that's a thing you know very tuned it points out that Noah could use
something like this when he's trying to switch people over to Linux I think
that's pretty good and Cody the dragon says maybe they should call it the
sketch so it'd be the etcher sketch boom yeah well but that's pretty good though
I think that's what I think they should actually do that just yeah yeah you know
what else is great digital ocean digital ocean comm go over there and spin up
some infrastructure I was reminded recently that there's so many great
features of digital ocean that I often go off in the woods and I'll talk about
spaces or I'll talk about this crazy modern stuff you know they say they say
Chris you really got to talk about that dashboard it's a dashboard for days is
what they say to me they say double down on the dashboard Chris is a dashboard
for days if you're a total noob or you're an expert server administrator
you're gonna find that dashboard wonderful they have an API to that
matches in fact I think the dashboard is a client of the API but I I digress
everything you want to deploy you're gonna be able to deploy within seconds
everything's backed by SSD drives and they have team support if you want to
work with a group and one of the features that probably gets a little
under talked about besides the dashboard is the snapshot and backup
functionality for just very little additional you can build in backups to
your digital ocean droplet which gives you a real peace of mind regardless of
what you're doing and you combine that with monitoring alerting that you can
collect metrics monitor performance and receive alerts to app optimize
performance or know if something's down and that's at no additional cost it's
just it's a really really good system and they've built in a way where you can
do work really fast you get an idea you go from idea to actually deploying a
system hey I want to try this thing out on github hey wouldn't it be cool if
next cloud could do this and you go from that moment to actually trying it within
just a couple of minutes it's really enabling digitalocean.com go there
create your account and then use our promo code do unplugged it's one word
you put it together you apply it after you create your account you get the $10
credit spin up that $5 rug rig run it for two months for free you know I'm
saying digitalocean.com it's just so much more pleasant to use than like any
of their competitors the APIs are simple and clean the UI is beautiful that
dashboard for days Oh days years even digitalocean.com use the promo code do
unplugged big thanks to digital ocean for sponsoring the show and thanks to
everybody out there for using the promo code do unplugged all right I gotta
admit it Steven got me Steven VN Steven over usually writing for ZD net but now
picking up a gig for HP Enterprise filling out their website he wrote the
Linux commands you should never use and I gotta admit he got me because this is
this is an idea we've kicked around for the show for a little while but never
really just put the list together we've actually even made jokes about it on the
show oh crap you know what I just realized Wes oh my god
fascinating we gotta start the gentoo challenge right we're over halfway into
the show what's going on all right we're gonna get to this in just a moment I'm
sorry that was not an intentional tease but I want to see this thing through I
got to get this over I was recently told by a listener that this might be the
worst audio the least compelling segment we've ever done the show yeah probably
true I feel good about that which reminded me of the satire piece that
swampy posted over at pseudo satirical and the headline was man loses will to
live after a gentoo install a man has been left hospitalized and his family
left distraught in the aftermath of a grueling install of gentoo the Linux
operating system the 32 year old man was admitted on Thursday and is currently
in stable but serious condition after he reportedly lost the will to live sources
say he was installing gentoo late on Monday evening and on his main computer
and this was his quote first serious attempt all right that's so how you
feeling right now good in all seriousness how many weeks I know it's
not weeks but how many episodes have you been doing this this is the third I
think the fourth third or fourth yeah so we're just doing it during the show
we're just doing it during about three you're about three or four hours in to
install about two and a half I'd say okay all right two and a half hours yeah
if I get a USB stick other than to in fact a blank USB stick and I have to
download the ISO yeah put the ISO on the USB stick sure and then install the
system I'm done in like 20 minutes tops right right so for all of the extra
performance you're gonna eek out of this install of gentoo do you think it's a
false economy oh you're asking that question before we've gotten there I
mean how can we answer really well because I think I think it's probably
the last gentoo challenge you're gonna do because you're gonna lose the will to
live as well a Christmas holiday I would say for most people probably not it is a
lot of fun I will say I really enjoy it's been it's fun to configure a
kernel it's just a lot of fun and there's a lot of neat options value
and visiting down this one you can do that in other distributions and upon
doing our it doesn't matter gentoo it's it's feels like it's it feels like it's
just part of the process a few of the houses I grew up in and Angela's house
they had this crawl space under the house and like you don't go there very
often but when you go under the crawl space of a house you kind of
reacquaint yourself with some of the mechanics of the of the plumbing the
electrical oh yeah that hack job we did a while ago and it's sort of good to
just have a real intimate understanding of actually how all these things connect
together in your home that you live in every day but at a certain point you go
above that crawl space and you just want to get you don't want to move on with
your life so I do feel like it is hmm in this day and age not particularly worth
it if I was on a system that was very old or 32-bit or maybe even arm if I
could use dis CC or something like that then maybe then maybe or if you're just
a you know a very skilled user who has a has an interest in maintaining all the
little bits and pieces of what goes on in their operating system you you will
enjoy it all right Wes well are you ready for the the official check and how
we doing over there in the agenda corner West well we're we're working on
emergent sway right now really yeah does that so when you do that does that oh
yeah oh I hear the build going now yeah that's it right there oh look at that
building away so that it does that is that pulling in Whelan and all that
stuff as a dependency how's that working yep we should be good to go after all
this is done so you are building not just what sway but also Whelan now do
you think that's gonna finish I installed that earlier but oh yeah do
you think that's gonna finish 51 of 120 right now that's where we're at we may
not get to a graphical environment this episode we're so close though all right
I will also say this has been slow partially because we've been doing it
uh you know in a virtual machine and and while doing the show and I had not
installed gentoo for years I did install gentoo on another system just play
around yeah me too second time is so much easier like oh yeah oh yeah you've
done arch one oh yeah it's like oh yeah it's simple it's really not that
complicated oh yeah I didn't if you don't go in the weeds probably in like
an hour I could have gentoo depending on build speed and as our friends in the
mumble room might say we're really just kind of taking a piss here at gentoo but
in the reality if we really wanted to buckle down and get this done it's it's
not that difficult it doesn't take that long but we want it if we're gonna do
this damn thing we're gonna have a little fun with it that's what we
figured all right Wes well before the show's over we'll we'll check back in
with you okay that sounds good all right all right so let's move on that that
that wraps up the gentoo well check-in I guess that doesn't wrap up the challenge
yet I'm doubtful we're gonna get to graphical environment this episode geez
though that'd be great for our last live episode to actually get to a graphical
boot so the systems booting at this point oh yeah well done sir you're doing
well you're doing well which kernel do you remember was it which version
probably not now you can't check well maniac all right so the Linux commands
you should never use we're gonna start with the obvious one right here at the
top RM dash RF slash the first one that I ever learned the hard way back when it
was much easier to actually delete your running system now it's a little more
difficult but I've just short version I've told the story thousands of times
probably but my favorite one of my favorite things I ever experienced about
Linux was the fact that I could delete my running system and then the fact that
components of it just continued to run as if I hadn't just deleted my entire
file system so I have the slow realization of what I had done this like
what is that doesn't seem like that's hmm well my my gnome session is still
going my terminal still working and then having this slow discovery as my system
completely fell down around me and more and more things stopped working and then
I said hey guys come over here cuz I'm in the middle of a school lab come over
here guys and I'm sure look at this thing I deleted my entire file system
and it's still running let's see what else I can do what else is in RAM and it
was like it was this massive fascination how powerful single-handedly that I could
delete my own because this would never happen on a Mac or Windows that I could
delete my own file system and then keep using it to a degree to debug the fact
that I just deleted my own file system so yeah maybe you should go RM RF your
system it's a lot of fun I mean if you're done anyways maybe do it to
someone else's system or a better yet a virtual machine oh well sure but I mean
like if you're on a system and you're gonna nuke and pave anyways after you got
all your stuff backed up right before you just go wipe the old disk anyways
want to have a little fun see how far you can get see which desktop
environments last the longest I bet you I bet you could get pretty far you'd be
surprised depending on how much is in memory the bashfork bomb of course which
is kind of hard to translate to audio but you'll go find you can find the link
in there then he points out how easy it is for noobs and I want to see what you
think he's probably right how easy it is for noobs to accidentally overwrite their
hard drive because you can basically pipe anything to Dev HD a accidentally
LS dash LA and then you go to pipe that to like a file you're being dumb you're
a noob you write in slash dev slash HD a and hit enter and the next thing you
know you've just overwritten the HD a device with the output of LS dash L what
do you think is that a destructive one there West is that like you think that
I've never heard anybody doing that I've never heard a single person doing that
I have not either not not to the actual to the device it is pretty easy to
overwrite a file especially if you're run into similar name files or like
versions that have like you know change just changed letters or numbers after
them I will say in general the command line is not a very forgiving environment
in a default configuration now if you have you know backup snapshots or even
there's even just you know helper helper things to make RM for instance more
friendly then it's not so bad but when you're coming to Linux or just Unix in
general really one of the things that is hard for longtime Windows users to
understand is nothing returned is generally a success a lot of times that
means failure in the Windows world like you run an application and nothing
happens that's a failure whereas in Linux you run a command line application
and and it just returns the command line it generally means it's success it
succeeded in what you wanted to do right and so it's this weird kind of like
mental like space you gotta get you got a bridge but the command that I would
bet more often screws not just noobs but experts is DD because that's really
where you could accidentally just put the wrong thing in there put the wrong
dev SDA device in there the right I mean it'll do what you tell it to do and see
here's a little more plausible because using DD you generally are working
working with a device of some kind so you're already mucking about here it's
pretty easy to just play oh well I typed a two but I meant a one there or an A
instead of a B and everything's okay right let's let's get this out to a
wider audience Chris your friend and my Joan Ressington has another podcast
called late night Linux yeah and one of his co-hosts is Jesse who's a very good
friend of mine but Jesse had made a bit of a faux pas earlier in the year where
he managed DD pop OS over his hard disk not onto the USB stick and this
caused all kinds of confusion because he accused pop OS of silently installing on
his hard disk whilst he was testing it on the live environment which actually
happened to be his hard drive now let's let's just say to everybody stop using
DD this is this is a recipe for disaster everyone has a ID deed over my hard disk
story we've already talked about Etcher and if you don't want a electron
applications then gnome disks has a facility to restore a disk image and you
just say restore disk image here's where my ISO file is point it at your USB
drive that you've plugged in and it will stick an ISO image on your USB stick
without any of the confusion of whether you've got the right device selected or
not so that's for 2018 let's all make a resolution that we're going to stop
using TV for putting ISO images on USB sticks very tune it sounds like you have
a horror story of overriding a drive recently but not drive but I was
actually building a open WRT image and it was a i386 image and I accidentally
did a make kind of install type thing and what it did it would basically
installed busy box i386 on my AMD c64 laptop and what that does is beat box
will replace all the kind of core binaries with sim links to busy box and
basically trash your system because you now cannot LS you cannot any of the
other crap scare us that we used to you do to try and pick the system and so I
had to spend time okay on the system copying across 64-bit binaries over the
sim links to restore the system enough that I can actually get the system
oh man yeah now Beardsley you have like a belt and suspenders approach to DD
rescue or I mean to DD it's DD rescue I kind of gave it yeah yeah the dash GUI
might be the the easier part there okay so I was just gonna say this I've
actually now I shouldn't say this cuz it's gonna happen to me because it's it
happens to everybody eventually I've never DD over the wrong drive before
I've never made that mistake but I have made the format the wrong drive mistake
mkfs extended 3 slash dev slash and I had I had several USB discs attached and
what I would do was this clunky manual system where I would I would edit and
edit and edit and then I would fill up my scratch drive and I would I would
fill up my output drive and then I would use our sync to kind of like collect the
entire project the project files and the output file and move them all onto these
large USB enclosures that were like four terabytes because it had two mir two
terabyte drives yeah it was like hard it was supposedly hardware mirror in this
enclosure the idea being I load this up with about a about three months worth of
content and then I put it on a shelf and I write a lay I put a label on the side
of it and say these date ranges of episodes okay yeah make sense so I had
this I was like I'm like pretty far into this just about have the whole drive
filled up pretty proud of myself for actually finally for one year getting my
crap together and saving I'm saving our source files until I went to go format
one of the discs in the computer and instead I immediately instantly
formatted that USB Drive just wiped it all out right then and there and and I
hit enter and then I reread it and I was like oh that doesn't look right I'm
like what I should probably don't check that and then I did like a quick mount
you know that's always my go-to to like what it where is everything at yeah so I
open up another tab do a quick mount okay then I tab back over oh my god
realization and then the command line returns right it just like and then of
course I'm like and this is you can probably find it in text app like I
tried some data recovery stuff and this is a long time ago now but it was it's
one of those moments so yeah make sure when you're formatting you're formatting
I've also probably I've probably done it with G parted too I just I don't have a
story for it oh so I have done that one so be wary of of that I think something
else and this is one that SJW or SJW no it's not something else it's SJN what he
points out is one of the other things that's pretty common is for noobs that
are trying to get tips online to do the whole grab like a command that W gets a
shell script and executes it and just paste it right in the terminal we've all
seen the websites really nice fancy websites you go there and they've got
like that syntax that you can just highlight right there and paste it into
your terminal and have a go and why should you care they're a pretty well
known name and that's pretty I think it's impossible to tell newbies not to
do that to be honest I think the risk to reward ratio is is too skewed and I
don't think there's any way you can properly tell a newbie not to do that
because at the end of the day they just want sublime text or whatever it is that
they're trying to install not to be a pessimist but that is such a dangerous
slippery slope right and I mean so there's like dangerous for multiple
reasons right one of them is some of those scripts are poorly written and so
if they are incomplete to download could execute something that is not is not
properly run but will still execute you can engineer scripts to not do that so
in that in that case in the best case situation it's about as secure because
they also don't expect any newbies to really verify that the script is
anything they probably don't know what it's doing they don't have the capacity
to audit it true but it's really just an unfortunate situation in general any
other like don't do this to kill your system tips for anybody that got a
Linux computer under the holiday pole this year does anybody have a going away
parting I'll add just at the start you find has the dash delete flag which can
be really useful but if it's you put it before any of the other arguments you
used to filter your find it will just delete everything my god that's one
thing to watch out for that's a good one with always that's like with special
with those things it's always best to like do one run just finding the files
yes leave that to a log file to put in the ticket for later and then run the
delete command and always always always double check when you're when you're
new to the command line before you execute anything is rude one of the
things that I do if I am like just double checking down before I format a
drive after I had that horrible circumstance where I deleted nearly 4
terabytes worth of source material what I do now is I write the command in
usually like g-edit but whatever you want whatever you have that's your
favorite scratch pad up and I I then I run the mount command I look at my mount
points like I make sure and I would have one of the things I will do I know this
is going really I'm being pandemic here but I will I will do I'll type mount
I'll see my output I'll highlight the output like the dev slash SDA one I'll
highlight that with my mouse cursor and then I'll use the X middle click paste
to paste that into my command syntax in g-edit so that way there's no typo it's
a one-for-one I know it's a copypasta and then I complete the whole command
out I type out the rest and then I copy that and paste that into my terminal
execute that when I'm doing it like a like a format just because I want to
like double triple check it right and it can be like you can accidentally get you
know returns in your in your copies or other things where things execute before
you've had a chance to completely review the command so I think that's great
right like yeah compose in a scratch pad and then you can run in a terminal yeah
yeah we have we have more in the post so you can go check out his SJV ends whole
post over at the HP Enterprise blog which I thought was interesting look at
HP Enterprise trying to trying to get in a little bit they have enterprise dot
next which is their insights and resources to help IT pros shape the
future of business it's the new enterprise blog for HP Hilly
Packard and I think it's very very interesting that they hired SJV in who
is a Linux writer and they want posts about Linux what does that tell you
Wes suppose they know their customers the people who they want to send emails
and get them to click and then maybe talk to their boss about buying HP
Enterprise speaking of talking to your boss about buying something why don't
you talk to your boss about buying a Linux Academy subscription this is I
think a great way to go if you have any kind of training budget because Linux
Academy is such an outstanding value this is a win-win it's a win-win for the
employer but even more so it's a win-win for you if you just want to advance your
career or just challenge yourself or just learn a new skill set Linux Academy
comm slash unplugged you go there you sign up for a free seven-day trial and
you can try out the whole dang platform they're downloadable comprehensive study
guides the virtual servers that spin up right away Linux Academy is such a great
platform to learn about every Linux cloud and DevOps topic or those major
big infrastructure things like Azure and AWS and OpenStack they have learning
paths which is series of content and courseware plans specifically for your
education and like I was saying at the beginning here they also have great
support for like team accounts and and you have these profile pages that you
can you can use for a lot of different reasons like a github public profile
where you can kind of bragvertize about some of the accomplishes that you've
completed but you can also use it as a way to say here's the things I've done
with the training budget so it's a great way for you to really turn around and
show this has been worth your time the reason I mentioned that is that's
something that can easily be hard to quantify in a corporate environment if
there's not a really clear rigid structure and you can avoid all of that
hassle of a super rigid structure which is the tools built in the Linux Academy
platform whether you're a single individual you're working at a business
or you have a whole group like Noah with his team there's so many great resources
and instructor mentoring real human beings hands-on scenario scenarios real
labs and core schedulers to fit with your busy time Wow Linux Academy comm
slash unplugged go there sign up for a free seven-day trial and you support the
show Linux Academy comm slash all right Wes how's the gen 2 corner over there
what's going on over there West 71 of 120 I thought so so yeah this is not the
fastest rig in the universe in fact far from it we have to well we can't always
we can't always just be talking about what it's like on like six core and 12
core systems like we do have to sometimes run it really part of this was
like what's it like for the casual Linux user who's never installed gentoo
before to just come over and you know they're not a newbie but they think we
need beard to act as official judge because he could be our impartial
decider here but I would agree with impartial but okay all right yeah
decide what do you think about for the sake of getting through the challenge
since it's quote the worst content of the show ever what what if what if we
let the build finish yeah like we don't boot we don't reboot like we let the
builds finish if they air out or finish we let them finish or air out and then
pause the virtual machine you really emphasize an error out there I saw look
on your face earlier and it was like oh shit the build just stopped kind of a
look I thought so I was a little worried oh no okay it's just slow but here's the
alternative or the alternative is when the theme music ends the Linux unplugged
outro music ends who s has to hit pause immediately on the virtual machine which
is more in line with the original spirit of this whole thing that is part of I
have not let anything finish I have right like so I think beards got to be
the decider if we let this one go through and then we pause it or if we
pause it during the outro music I say we let it go through okay all right judge
judges decided beardly so then hopefully that means next week we may be able to
boot up and get right into sway which would be the first time I've ever seen
sway I mean I have an idea of what it looks like but it'll be the first time
I've ever had to make sure then we can show it on air too so yes so that'll be
that we'll come up with a little way to do that too which will be maybe
impossible from Waylon now that I think about it I don't even I have seen one at
least screen recorder I'm doing some research in Oh Wayland you already bring
me I'll also have in the show notes if you want to read that satirical thing
about the man who became suicidal after installing gentoo that'll be linked to
the show notes but okay I feel good about that I feel good about that and
nobody you notice nobody in the Bumble room is participating in the gentoo
challenge anymore perhaps the worst idea ever but I submit it would have been
even worse video content people like this is just horrible audio content I'm
like yeah you know what have been worse if you are watching us do it that's
even that's even worse so you have spared us all of that now this is our
last live show of the year but we will be back at the beginning of next year
and we have releases coming out during the holidays and also just a little
plug skis right here for the new tech snap program tech snap dot systems new
program a reboot of the tech snap program on the Jupiter broadcasting
network so you can catch up on that if you'd like during the holiday break but
we will be back in the new year you will have the live times over Jupiter
broadcasting comm slash calendar we'd love it if you join us in our mumble
room which is mumble dot Jupiter broadcasting org but you can get all the
information you need when you go to that website and we have a dedicated Linux
unplugged community chat room at discord dot me slash Jupiter colony that's right
discord dot me slash Jupiter colony Linux unplugged in there as well as the
IRC room at IRC geek shed net Jupiter broadcasting wow that's a lot of stuff
you know and that you know that content you kind of underpoint it but it's not
like a lame clip show we know that's not what we're leaving you know we did all
new original content yeah mm-hmm turned out a lot of fun actually also let's
give a little plug skis for the wonderful and around 30-minute podcast
the Ubuntu podcast yeah go check out more wimpy and poppy over there please
do season break soon we strike for 30 minutes as long as we don't have
aikido yeah I was just gonna say that's some things you just can't control yeah
we're having season the last episode of this season will be out this Thursday
and then we'll have a break for a couple of months Wow so jealous so I have an
idea for a podcast where I'm gonna do seasons I'm gonna get all in on it oh
seasons thinking about it thinking about it West but that'll be a story for 2018
alright guys well have a great holiday we won't be we won't be gathering
together again until the new year so everybody there in that virtual
have yourself a holiday I really appreciate you guys being here
throughout the year and I don't know what else what other nice thing can we
say to them thanks for all the great content over the year here's to 2018 and
a lot lots more Linux yeah yeah and really same to all the audience as well
everybody out there hope you have a great holiday and I I hope you tune back
in and we have I think I think 2018 is going to be the best year for Linux
unplugged ever because we have so many cool things in store I'm super excited
it's I don't know it's just it feels like we have just the things that we've
even thought of for 2018 I think if we just pull those off it's gonna be a
great year for the show so yeah like Wes was saying don't miss the holiday
content that'll be out on the site the feeds the YouTube's all the regular
places you catch Linux unplugged so be sure to grab that check out the calendar
for more live again over at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar contact
page slash contact at Jupiter signal for the network he's at West Payne I'm at
Chris LAS the beard is at rekt.net hey look at that hey how about the subreddit
let's slip that in there too Linux unplugged dot reddit.com go there
submit content to the show all those good things all right I gotta go they're
playing me off producers are saying get out of here it's time to wrap up so
you're done let it go go enjoy the holidays okay thanks for being here see
you in 2018
All right, for one last time this year, we got to pick a title.
We got to pick a title.
You know, I resisted the urge to do like a predictions episode this year because that's
pretty common, but I did sneak a couple into Linux Action News, so we got some Linux Action
News.
Ooh.
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
Are we getting title suggestions?
What do you think, Wes?
Something about BcashFS being a hope.
Yeah, yeah.
Help us BcashFS.
Yeah.
That's not bad.
It does play on the Star Wars hype right now.
Etcher, because DeeDee is scary, says architect.
Multi-pass!
Yeah, if we did artwork, we could have What's-Her-Face from Fifth Element, who, yeah, yes, of course,
I bet you guys have been hearing that a lot recently.
Yep.
Yeah, I tried not to make the joke in the show too much because I figured that's one
that everybody-
No, we love it.
We love it.
Does multi-pass support custom images at the current point?
You can create, you can customize the cloud images and use those, yes.
Okay.
Oh, beautiful.
Okay, I figured, but yeah.
I love those cloud images.
Those images are great.
What about rm-rf?
Slash.
Yeah, that's the ultimate customization, but being really picky.
For the title?
No, use the bash fork bomb as the title.
Bash fork, just the word bash fork bomb?
No, the squiggly brackets and everything.
You know, that could actually break somebody's podcast catcher, I bet.
I will say that is like, if you're trying to find someone who's like, if they're familiar
with bash, it's a reasonable thing to make them explain to you.
What do you think?
Bash fork bomb is actually kind of funny.
But I also like rm-rf.
I can't believe we've never done that.
How about rm-rf 2017?
Yeah, there you go.
That's not bad either.
That's pretty catchy.
And mean something, sort of.
It's not bad.
So basically, I'm going to paste it in the Discord and tell me if you guys like the way
that looks.
Because I can't just, now that I actually see it, I don't know if I like it.
But I'll paste it here and see if I like it better on screen.
Doesn't that look weird to you?
That looks weird, right?
Sorry, give me five minutes to find where on Discord you posted that.
Well, you just look on the live stream if you know.
It's on the, it's in the, oh yeah, right, right, right.
What if I took out the slash, I think just slash.
I think, well.
No, I'd have a trailing slash.
2017 slash.
Yeah, there you go.
I like that.
Really?
That would make the difference?
Without the leading slash, maybe.
Oh, okay.
Because I kind of don't like the leading slash.
Because it's a directory beneath where you are.
Yeah.
Or even just plain 2017 is all right, as Rekai suggests.
Yeah, I kind of just like rm-rf though.
But I could, all right, so now if we do just without the slash at all.
Hmm, yeah.
Okay, oh, okay.
All right.
Hmm, I think I like it best without the slash.
I think you get it without the slash, right?
Yeah, I think you're right.
It's a bit nerdy with it.
Well.
Yeah, yeah, now it's not nerdy.