I don't know if we've talked about our clone before, Wes.
Maybe we have.
But I've been thinking about our clone again
in the context of getting my stuff out of Google Photos.
And I decided to give it a go.
And it has this nice, I guess you could call it a wizard.
It's a text-based thing that runs you
through connecting to the various services,
in this case, Google Photos.
And then it does this little, I don't know
if you'd call it a hack, but it does this little trick
where it runs a local web server.
It spins one up just to collect the Google authorization token
that gets returned from Google.
And then it immediately shuts down the web server,
configures your permissions,
and then you can just go in there
and start copying down your Google Photos.
It'll even do specific albums
or things like that if you want.
But I learned it's not exactly perfect.
No, no, it's not.
I mean, our clone is great.
The issue is more on Google's side.
So issue number one is right now,
downloads strips the exif location.
This is a known limitation of the API
and there's an open bug about it,
but who knows when that will get fixed.
That's kind of a bummer.
It sure is.
But number two might be even worse
because right now the API, which our clone uses,
does not allow photos to be downloaded
at their original resolution.
So they might still be useful.
You could still process them and post them on Instagram
or whatever you're trying to do.
But if you're trying to use this
as a way to have Google Photos be your backup
and then make a second copy of your backups,
that might not work.
And you might instead need to use something
like Google Takeout.
It's almost as if the best solution might be
just don't use Google Photos.
Hello friends and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello Wes.
It's good to be back from the Montana trip.
This episode is brought to you by aCloud Guru.
You know they are the leader in learning for Cloud Linux
and other modern tech skills.
Hundreds of courses and thousands of hands-on labs.
Get certified, get hired, get learning at aCloudGuru.com.
Coming up on the show today, are you, like me and Wes,
having a hard time kicking the Google Photos habit?
Maybe you're looking for a self-hostable alternative.
They did just recently make a few changes
to the Google Photos deal.
And let's be honest, there is that whole privacy thing
to consider.
So coming up on the show this week,
our buddies Brent, a professional photographer,
and Alex, my co-host on the Self-Hosted podcast,
and a home lab master, really, discuss new and old ways
to manage, organize, index, and search your photo collection,
sort of Google Photo style.
And if that wasn't enough, I spent the weekend,
a long weekend, started on Thursday,
with something special.
The new System76 Launch Keyboard.
They're built in Denver, created from scratch,
right there in Colorado, keyboard.
I rushed back from Montana to receive this package,
and I'm going to share my thoughts on the keyboard
that I say redefines what customizable even means.
But first, with the powers vested in me,
I declare a warm, time-appropriate greetings
to our virtual lug.
Hello, mama room.
Hello.
What do you think?
Hello, everybody.
Wow.
What a group we have today.
25 of you in there, just solid.
And it's nice to be back.
I missed everybody while I was in Montana.
But you know, it was a good family trip.
We had some adversities, and we had some triumphs,
and we got a lot of swimming.
And I got back to this Launch Keyboard from System76.
It's right here.
I have it plugged in over USB-C to my studio computer.
It is now my studio keyboard.
You haven't switched back, I was wondering.
I got it with the royal keycaps, I think it is,
the slightly quieter ones.
And I've swapped out a few of the keys
already, because it's pretty easy to do that.
It comes with a little keycap remover in the box,
and it comes with a couple alternative keys
that you might want to go with right away.
It's got a USB hub on the back, some A and some C.
It works on Linux.
It works on Windows, and it works on Mac OS.
The keyboard is 100% open source.
The hardware design and the software that runs on it
is all open source.
So of course, those right there check a lot of boxes.
For me, I've also recently gotten a little more
into mechanical keyboards, thanks to the bad,
I'd say, the bad influence for my co-host Mike on Koda Radio.
I've gotten a little more into them.
Let's just say it appears in the studio
that keyboards breed something like bunnies.
Or tribbles, in my case.
Yeah.
So I got it out of the box, and it immediately
had a very solid feel to it.
It looks deceivingly simple, but when you pick it up,
there's a lot of heft in a way that feels like quality.
The Royal keys are not quite as quiet as I expected.
That was my first impression when I started typing.
So maybe I should have just gone with the jades.
And it's set, by default, to a rotating space backlight theme,
which I like.
It circles through different colors
that you maybe would call, like, galaxy colors, I guess.
So I just kept it the default. But job one for me,
when I got this thing, was rearrange the Control, Alt,
and Super, and Function key layout.
By default, System76 ships it with Control key, Alt, Fn, Super.
And that's fine, but not how I like it, you know?
I like it more traditional.
So I quickly just swapped it to Control, Fn, Super, Alt,
swapped the keycaps, and then I went and grabbed their software
to configure the keyboard.
And I was curious what this experience was going to be like,
because I'm not on Pop!
OS, and I'm on Fedora, which is not even a Debian-based device.
Which is not even a Debian-based distro.
And so I'm like, am I going to be able to grab this, or what?
So I go over to their page, download it off their GitHub,
and it's an app image.
So you mark that sucker executable,
and you double-click on it.
It asks for your root password, because it's
going to scan your bus.
And then it comes up, and it gives you
a really clever layout.
It's a visualization of the keyboard, which works really
well for how my brain works.
And it makes it simple to click this, or hold this,
and map this function.
And within a couple of minutes, I
was mapping multiple keys to a single key press.
And I like that a lot.
Additionally, this thing supports four layers
of customizable keys.
In other words, you can essentially
have four different layouts in this one keyboard,
and you can toggle through them with different key combinations.
I have my right Fn key set to switch to layer two,
which is the default. But one of the things I've done in layer
two is where I have some of my combos.
I've set a different backlighting scheme
for layer two.
And you can do this with each layer.
You can do options like only light up
the keys that have a function assigned to them.
So when I hold down layer two, only half a dozen keys
light up.
And those are just the ones I've mapped something to.
And the rest all stay off.
Layer three switches to a vertical scan pattern
of LED lights.
So I know I'm on layer three, because the keyboard lights
switch pattern.
And then when I release, it goes back to the layer one
pattern of lights.
That simple little thing was the trick
I needed to keep all of this straight.
I was worried that I would get lost
in a sea of customization with this thing.
And I would not be able to map in my brain what's
on what layer, et cetera.
But being able to control the LED lights and colors
and patterns, or just do the single lightups for ones
that have function, gave me the visual trick
I needed combined with their software configurator
that gives you a visual on-screen layout of what
you're doing with a representation of the keyboard
up on screen.
It really actually clicked.
And I've been able to keep with it.
So the software really gives you a sense of how far you can
actually take this keyboard.
I mean, you can read the specs on their website.
But when you plug it in and then you open up the software,
it redefines what customizable is.
This thing is truly next level.
And then the beautiful thing is everything
is then saved back to the keyboard immediately.
So as soon as I change it, it's applied to the keyboard.
I can unplug it from this computer.
And I can go plug it into an entirely separate machine,
a different operating system.
It doesn't have any of the firmware or any keyboard
software on it.
And it will still all work because it's
saved locally on the keyboard.
That is huge for me because I don't
want to have to load the software on every single machine
that I want to use this thing on.
And it also is showed right up in the GNOME firmware
tool that uses LVFS.
So it's completely supported by LVFS for updates.
And I like seeing that.
And somehow, you haven't even mentioned
that their customization tool is powered by Rust.
Oh, I'm sorry.
What was that, Wes?
It was powered by Rust.
Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha.
And I wasn't really 100% sure, despite all of that,
if it was really worth $285 because that seems
like a lot of money for a keyboard.
So what I did is I went to Amazon
and I looked at some of their best, highest rated
mechanical keyboards.
And I went for the cheapest mechanical keyboard
I could find.
And I found one for $35.
So I thought, let's see how this $35 keyboard stacks up
against the $285 System76 keyboard.
And there's obvious things, like this one sort of
has a more muted sound.
It doesn't quite feel quite as good.
I mean, that's not a huge surprise.
It's also plasticky and light.
In fact, it even flexes a little bit when I twist it,
where I could win a knife fight with the launch as a weapon.
It's very solid.
And those things were kind of like, OK,
I went into a $30 keyboard expecting that.
That's not really where I'm going to judge this on.
I put them down side by side.
And Wes was here on Sunday and we
were doing Linux action news.
And I didn't even prompt Wes.
I didn't say anything to Wes.
You brought it up to me.
You said, you're typing faster than I've ever seen you type
on the launch.
That I did.
I mean, you seemed kind of naturally at home.
Admittedly, you had a different mechanical keyboard
currently in use at the studio for a while, which didn't
seem to be jiving with you.
But it was clear that this was a new keyboard
you were going to keep using.
Yeah, so that other keyboard we tried
that I hadn't here for a while was the Keytron K3.
And I really wanted to like it because it was a good size.
That was one that Keytron's a little bit smaller
than the $35 Amazon one.
The $35 Amazon one's a little wider.
But the Keytron and the launch are about the same desk size.
They're about the same size.
And I can type significantly faster on the launch.
And I think it is the layout a bit.
It is also the way the keys feel.
I think all of those, I think it's like three or four things
about the design of the keyboard that come together
to make it actually really fast.
But I noticed it too.
Even though I hadn't said anything to you about it,
that weekend, I used the keyboard
to write all of the notes for Linux Action News.
And I was flying.
I was like really enjoying the typing experience.
And I know that sounds kind of cliche.
But that matters a lot to me because I'm
touching this damn thing every day, all damn day.
And it matters to me that I smile when I look down at it.
And it matters to me that it feels good
every time I press on it.
That's what you're paying for, right?
If it works and with the durability
that it looks like this thing has,
it could be your keyboard for the next decade.
There's absolutely no question about it.
It's USB-C with its customizability.
I will use this keyboard forever.
It's going to last a very long time.
And keyboards do for me in general.
If it was $185 or $200, I would have already
ordered another one.
I absolutely would.
At $285, it's kind of a special treat.
And so it's going to be what we use in the studio.
That feels kind of appropriate because it's
kind of a specialty item.
And then that plays a role for me too, right?
This feels a bit like a bespoke item.
It feels like something that my friends hand-built in Denver,
you know, like people that are part of my community
hand-built something.
And I can buy it from them.
And that's special too.
And that's also the reason why I bought the Librem 15,
because it also had that unique kind of collector
almost feel to it.
And that's why I bought the Atari VCS as well,
even though I haven't received that one.
Because again, it's kind of a unique item
that comes from somebody that is working in the Linux community.
And this launch encompasses that even so much more.
I mean, they've been around now for well over 10 years now.
But this represents a new milestone
and a first for their business and a first for a Linux vendor.
And so I wanted to have it for that reason too.
And I mention that because those thoughts are invoked
every time I look down at it.
And that makes me happy as well.
And so for me, it is worth the $285.
And the $35 keyboard and the Keytron, which is $85,
are all good keyboards.
But they have things that are frustrating about them,
where the launch really doesn't have any compromises.
I didn't want a numpad.
I know for some people that is an issue.
But for me, this keyboard doesn't really
have the compromises that those other two have.
And a lot of times, when you get to the higher end gear,
and Wes and I talked about this over the weekend, when
it comes to our microphones, you start
to get to the $500, $600, $1,000 microphones,
they don't sound $500 better than a $200 microphone.
They don't sound $1,000 better than a $100 microphone.
They sound $50, $80 better, to be realistic about it.
The drop off is kind of dramatic when
it comes into high end professional audio gear.
Some of that is true when it comes to high end computer
gear.
I don't think that drop off is as dramatic here
with the keyboard.
But when I look at this $85 Keytron,
this launches another $200.
Is it $200 better?
I can't say.
But I can say it is much better.
I don't know if it's $200, but that's just
going to be a personal value call each person makes.
I, however, am very happy with it.
And we'll spend a very long time using the keyboard.
And I think in four or five years,
I'm not even going to be thinking about the $285 price.
I'm just going to be thinking about how
great this keyboard still is.
And I imagine it will remain my favorite keyboard
for a long time until I get another one.
There's also the aspect here that because it's open source,
all of the openness about it, you
can be a little less worried that support's going to drop
or somehow System76, god forbid, goes out of business
and you can no longer update or there's
no more updates to their configuration utility
or they somehow don't host the proprietary EXE download
anymore.
Seems like you can put your faith that A, this thing's
going to be around as long as you need it,
and B, I mean, you're helping System76 out
by giving them some cash.
And maybe there'll be some future keyboards
that are even nicer.
I talked to my buddy Mike in Coder Radio
this week about his experiences using it.
He tested it on a Mac, and it works there, too.
Spoiler alert.
So that's pretty impressive, the fact
that I got it working on a Neon install and a Fedora box,
and he has it working on a Mac.
And it seems to be fully functional there as well.
And it's really easy to swap the keys around to your liking
and then just go map them in the software.
And they're making the software available
for Windows and the Mac, too.
And all these things just kind of come together
to make it feel like it's a bit of a new milestone
for System76.
I mean, think about what they had to do to build this thing
and actually ship it to customers
from just like a project management
standpoint and a process development
standpoint for a business, right?
And then you think about where this leads.
Now that they've, this is their first shot.
And I'm sitting here telling you, I really like it.
It could have been junk.
It could have been crappy to type on.
It's not like they've built a lot of keyboards before.
So if they took something like this
and they put this something like this in a laptop,
that was like something they moved on to,
is building a laptop that just runs Linux
and has a keyboard like this on it,
I think that'd be an extremely compelling project.
And this is obviously the first step on a much longer journey.
And checking in on goalpost one, they nailed it.
And I think that's really the takeaway here, is wherever
they end up taking this, if this is step one,
well, they nailed step one.
So the way I look at this, when you first
mentioned this keyboard, I had a similar reaction of how much?
This is way too much.
There's no way anybody's going to spend $285 on a keyboard.
But then I started thinking about the equivalent
in different industries.
Cars is a perfect example.
I have a premium version of a Golf
sat on my driveway, a very average economy car that's
had a bigger engine and whatever put into it.
I don't need that bigger engine.
I don't need the four-wheel drive system.
But yet, I'm happy to pay extra because it gives me
those feels when I get into it.
I look down and I see the fact that it
has the flappy paddles on the steering wheel.
And I think to myself, yeah, this is nice.
This makes me feel good.
And if you're getting that same feeling from the keyboard,
something that you touch and see all day, every day for half
a decade, maybe longer, sure, I think it's worth it, don't you?
That is my math on it.
I know for some, though, I think maybe for Neil,
if it's not full-sized, it doesn't really work for you,
does it?
Yeah, I actually use my number pad quite a lot.
And I mean, I can obviously get away with it
without having it because my laptops don't have it.
I actually hate having the number pad on the laptops
because it makes them cramped.
But when I'm working on a desktop
and I'm going to have an external keyboard,
I really want a full-sized one because I take advantage
of the real estate.
And I like the more space in the keys
and a lot more even layout.
That said, I'm super excited about this.
And if they had a regular version of it with a full layout
and even maybe some multimedia keys
and some extra little quality of life additions,
I'd be down for it.
Maybe they will have multiple.
I've wondered.
Or like a volume knob that some of those fancy keyboards have.
I'd take that.
Yeah.
I love the volume.
I do, too.
It's my volume knob.
And so legit, I use my media keys a lot.
I have the volume control, the play, pause, back, forward,
and the mute button.
The mute button gets hit a lot.
I use those.
And so having those on a keyboard is important for me.
Right.
I am very, very, very fond of compact keyboards
here in the studio and in my recording setup
in my mobile setup in Lady Jupiter.
But at my desk, I agree with you there.
I like a full-sized keyboard.
And I think maybe that's one of the reasons I'm not
putting the launch at my office desk.
I'm putting it here in the studio.
And then also because it's a bit of a conversation
piece in the studio as well.
But yeah, that's very true.
And I would love to see one day multiple versions
of the launch.
That could be pretty cool.
What would you have on your keyboard, Wes,
on your custom launch keyboard?
Oh, yeah.
OK.
Well, I definitely want the volume knob and then
as many possible LEDs as they could pack.
And Pipe Dream here, what about something like a System76
Pure Open Source Powered Touch Bar?
Ha, ha, ha, ha.
Well, first, in the housekeeping,
I wanted to let you know that our buddies across the pond
have a bit of a party this Saturday.
Foss Talk Live starts at 7 PM their local time
on their YouTube channel.
You can go over there and get subscribed,
and then that will just go live.
So we are recording this on June 8.
So it is the Saturday we're recording,
which is June 12, 2021, Foss Talk Live,
7 PM their local time.
And it's a crossover event, too.
So Wes and I will have it up.
We'll have the popcorn going, and we'll
be cracking jokes at our friends' expense.
It should be a good time.
Oh, you know it.
Also, we'd love to hear from you.
Some ideas that we have on this show, some of the segments,
like today's episode, are inspired by our audience.
We get emails into the show, and then we pursue an answer.
So we'd love to get your questions, your feedback, all
of it, at linuxunplugged.com slash contact.
Of course, there is a whole network,
and the conversation is always rolling in our Telegram channel.
You can join that at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash
Telegram, and the conversation goes 24-7,
and many of us are popping in and out there
throughout the day.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 in credit for 60 days on your new account.
And of course, you support the show,
make it possible for us to release free content.
Linode is our hosting provider of choice.
You guys know that.
But I was reflecting on one of the things
that I really appreciate about Linode while I was traveling.
And as you can probably guess, that
was making it possible for us to keep services up,
even though I was mostly AFK.
So I'm traveling, and of course, as you would expect,
I get an alert.
That alert tells me that network traffic has gone crazy
on one of our boxes.
But the great thing about Linode,
and honestly, yeah, I could do this myself.
In fact, some of our Linodes, we do have our own software
and alerting on there.
And yeah, I can set up monitoring and alerting.
But it's table stakes with Linode.
That's the great thing, is there's a baseline.
And getting alerts on things like excessive network traffic
is almost always a tell that something is wrong on a box.
I mean, maybe you're just having a great day.
You know, that's good to know too, actually.
That's kind of like, yeah, hell yeah, we're doing great.
But no, not in this case.
But the thing that is really slick
is it's easy to work with a team.
And so Wes got the alert and was able to get logged in and fix
the issue before I even read the email.
He gave me a status update.
And I just sat there thinking to myself, man,
am I really grateful that these kinds of basics
are taken care of and that I pop into the dashboard,
I can see the history, I can see what's going on.
And even if you're not a pro, the cloud dashboard
Linode has built is so straightforward
that you're going to get access to this information right away.
And they kind of just abstract away
the fact that you get 11 data centers to choose from that
have crazy fast connections between them
and that you have everything from these $5 a month
rigs, which it's amazing how many things you
can run on one of those, to systems with AMD
epic processors that just crush all of the competition,
like the full range is in there, while still being 30% to 50%
cheaper than big cloud that has these complicated, horrible
UIs, often with some sort of funky secondary business
model behind them, where Linode, they're truly independent.
In fact, they are the largest independent cloud provider.
And I love that about them.
They've been around since 2003.
The Linode infrastructure is solid.
You can focus on your project and not
having to build and manage all of that stuff.
And you get alerts when something goes sideways, too.
And that's pretty great.
So head over to linode.com slash unplug.
Get that $100 credit for your new account
and try this stuff out.
Go build something, learn something, maybe deliver
something online.
There's a lot of ways to host things.
There's a lot of companies that offer
a lot of different options at crazy different price points.
But none of them, none of them are Linode.
None of them bring it all together.
None of them are the largest independent cloud provider.
And none of them have been involved in the Linux community
as long as Linode, because they've been doing it
before everybody else.
So go get $100 and support the show.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Dries from Belgium wrote in, I'm a long-term Mac user
dipping my toes in Linux with a second-hand ThinkPad running
Pop OS, that sounds like a nice setup.
I also have an iPhone and a Canon M50.
I'm wondering what photo managing solution
do you all recommend?
I think privacy is very important.
I want to add right here.
And I'd also like a local copy, as well as, ideally,
a cloud backup.
I've also got a Raspberry Pi laying around,
which I could use if I was going to self-host something.
What are your photo managing and backup workflows?
Local, cloud, both?
Uh-oh, I have to admit something on the episode now.
Right here, I got to say, I have slipped back
into using Google Photos as my backup backup.
You kind of have that second backup.
And truthfully, I have found part of the reason
that I've been drawn back to it is the front-end client
features of being able to search for objects like dog
and Christmas tree or pictures of my son in Idaho
has just drawn me back to using Google Photos,
because the front-end makes it easy to find photos
that I can then pull and send to a family member really quick.
And that practical functionality brought me back.
And so I use, on my phone, the Google Photo backup app
to send my photos off site.
Yeah, I have to admit, I'm in the same boat.
I used to have a sort of custom sync thing solution going,
which worked pretty well.
But honestly, the network effect kind of pulled me back
into Google Photos.
I mean, one, I had bought a Pixel,
and so it was kind of opted in anyway.
And then I went on some vacations.
This was a few years ago.
But my friends, they were on there too.
They were starting an album.
I had to upload some things to Google Photos regardless.
And once I was there, it was just so easy to stay.
That's the trick.
Yep, yep, yep, yep, yep.
So the problem actually is, we're
going to admit, Google Photos is a good product.
But recently, Google has made change to the pricing structure
and taken away some of the incentives that they
used to actually get us using it in the first place.
And with any kind of Google thing,
it's kind of like, how long is this going to be around?
Is this really a long-term solution?
And what about the privacy aspects of it
and the ongoing cost?
And I don't know, do you agree, Alex?
Is part of the problem Google Photos is just kind of, well,
it's damn good.
I do, absolutely.
Yes, hello, everybody.
They've done the old bait and switch there, haven't they?
The first hit is free.
Exactly.
They drew me in.
And then because I was already paying for Google Storage
for my backups, it wasn't like this, oh no, now I have to pay.
It was like, oh, well, I'm already paying,
so I guess I can just keep using it.
Now, for those that aren't familiar,
what's actually changing is that as of June 1, 2021,
the account storage is shared across Drive, Gmail,
and Photos.
But any new photos and videos you upload
will now count towards the free 15 gigabytes of storage that
comes with every Google account.
Now, the reason that's changed is
before they had this kind of compressed high quality
in air quotes that didn't count towards that quota,
but now everything does, no matter what.
Yeah.
And I wasn't using all 10 terabytes,
so it wasn't a huge hit to me.
But it woke me up and reminded me
how precarious the situation is when I'm using a hosted service
like this, and how they always, so far, Alex,
have inevitably bit me in the butt,
and a lot of times have done so in such a way that
inspired us to start the self-hosted podcast.
So that, I know, is well-covered ground for us.
But yet, here I am, knowing better,
knowing the privacy implications of Google, all of that.
The transparent background uploads,
the sharing features that Wes touched on,
and then the searching features are very good.
And you could make the argument that now that Google
is making you pay for this, it actually
makes Google Photos sustainable.
So it'll be around for a long time.
So I think it remains a very viable option.
But I know I should be probably looking into other things.
Well, when we look at the whole picture here,
you've got to take into consideration who owns the data,
what are they going to do with it, how much is it
going to cost, not just in terms of it's
going to cost me a couple of dollars every month,
but in terms of the cost to humanity,
I suppose, in not having a fully open solution.
And what I've come to find writing this piece
is that there isn't one size fits
all self-hosted photo management solution.
There are several very good options,
but all of them check different boxes
and miss other really basic stuff.
Libre Photos, for example, is one of the apps
we'll come on to later.
It doesn't let you delete a photo from an album.
It just boggles my mind that such a basic thing
gets missed from some of this stuff.
But the other angle of self-hosting
is that you have to have a server.
You have to pay either Linode, or build one
and stick it in your basement, or a closet, or whatever it is.
And so there's a cost not only in terms of financial stuff
upfront for self-hosting, but also in terms of my time
to research and set these things up as well.
And if Google Photos ends up being around for 10, 15 years,
is it likely that you're going to build and self-host
something that will also be around for 10 or 15 years?
That's what I was thinking.
I'm OK running some of my infrastructure,
but photos are some things I'd like to not lose.
And if I make a mistake, as a novice admin, say.
I always find it useful, whenever
we talk in such large timescales,
to just remind you, 10 years ago was 2011.
What were you doing then with your photos?
Just picture how far the industry's come in that decade
and think about how far it might go in the next.
It seems like what really is the killer next generation
feature is object recognition, face recognition, location
recognition, and then an interface that
allows you to manage all of that.
And that's what Google nailed early with Google Photos.
It isn't necessarily impossible to get in something
you could run yourself.
And I know you've looked at several of them.
Well, if I was reviewing Google Photos,
one of the things I would probably put in the negative
column is that it doesn't have an awful lot in the way
of organizational features.
It has basic album support, and that's pretty much it.
Compare that to a lot of the other options
that we'll talk about today.
And Google managed to sidestep a lot of that
by having awesome machine learning.
And when you have an interface that is literally,
like you said in the beginning, search
for photos of Dylan in Idaho, you
don't need a directory structure that organizes everything.
You don't need to spend hours tagging things.
Their algorithms have done all that work for you.
And machine learning, it's a bit of a buzzword in the industry,
but if we think about it in its simplest form,
it's just pattern matching.
So all the algorithms are looking
for are certain groupings of pixels
that it think, well, maybe that's a tree.
Maybe that's a face.
Maybe that's a monkey.
Or a hot dog.
Or a hot dog, yes.
Have you seen that Silicon Valley episode?
And machine learning really is everywhere these days.
And I was watching, I think it was a Marques Brownlee video,
MKBHD on YouTube, talking about how farmers
are using machine learning to identify weeds in their crops
so that they use 90% less pesticides.
So interesting.
There are some significant use cases for machine learning
outside of photos.
But of course, where it gets interesting is it reduces
your overhead of organization.
Right, because you don't have to go through and tag,
this is a Dylan picture.
This is a Chris picture.
This is an Idaho picture.
It just does all that for you and then
makes it available as search criteria.
Absolutely.
Now, when we're thinking about this space,
we've got to think about the workflow.
And I think we've got Brent on the line as well.
And as a professional photographer,
I'm sure he can add something into the conversation
about workflows.
But what I'm primarily looking to back up here
are the images I take on my smartphone.
I do take a lot of images with my SLR when I'm traveling.
But for most of the rest of the time,
I will dump those at the end of a trip.
And it's two weeks worth of images, bang.
And I'm done.
What I'm more interested in is that kind of daily minutia
kind of automation and getting those images
off my mobile device in a never compressed format.
Now, I use Nextcloud to do this.
What do you use?
Actually, Alex, I'm using Nextcloud as well.
And in the beginning, it was a little clumsy.
But these days, I'm finding it just very seamless.
Is that your experience as well?
It just works.
Yeah, and that's the best kind of works.
Does it run automatically in the background?
Yeah, it has this nice feature where
it's just called auto upload.
And you can add any folder that detects media on your phone.
So it could be even just like downloads and things like that,
not just the photos from your camera, which
I found really helpful to back up things like backups
of my signal database that happens automatically,
things like that.
Oh, that's a good idea.
There you go.
But for photographs, it's great.
Because as a professional photographer,
I have this sort of constant fear
of losing any photographs that's been baked into my mind
for a really long time.
And so I call it the sort of run over by a dump truck situation.
If your phone gets run over by a dump truck
while you're out on some experience
that you want to remember forever,
well, it uploads your photos as you take them.
And I think that's a really nice feature.
And Nextcloud has been really seamless doing that.
So in terms of at least that auto backup feature,
it's really solid, really, really solid,
not to mention solving a bunch of other neat things for us
outside of photos.
So there's several ways to get the photos off the phone.
Like Alex and I recently talked about FolderSync,
which is another Android application that does this.
Of course, I guess the obvious other one would be Dropbox.
They offer to do this.
Indeed.
And they'll get it on a file system for you, right?
So it seems like there are several ways
to solve that with various pluses and minuses.
But that's not really what my problem isn't getting
the photo off the device.
I don't even mind like you, Alex.
I'll sit down after a trip, and I'll dump the photos off
of the SD card for the drone.
I'll manually do that.
There's nothing automated about that.
But there's kind of a ritual about it.
And I'm pretty good about doing that one thing.
That I got down.
It is honestly, it's the organization.
I guess I don't want to say I'm lazy.
Young Chris kept everything in folders on his file system
and managed his music and his pictures that way and loved it.
And it was a system that really worked for him.
But now President Chris looks back at that guy
and goes, boy, what a waste of my time.
I'm not doing that.
But yet, I consider these photos extremely important.
It's this weird dichotomy that I find myself in.
And so it's not so much the uploading of the photos.
It is the managing of the photos.
And I'm trying to find something that
isn't a proprietary system, that isn't locked to Apple or Google.
It's really easy to do that kind of organization
when you have a trip to aim at.
You know, 2015 road trip, Southwest USA, for example.
Or like family reunion 2021.
Uh-huh.
But if it's just a random Tuesday
where you've snapped to your kid being cute,
it's a bit harder to get that into some kind of folder
other than misc, right?
Yeah, or just even spend the time
to do it in the daily flow like that.
And one of those things that slips, right?
Maybe you try to do it on Sundays,
but then something came up and someone came over
and then you missed it.
How important do we think open source
versus closed source is in this space?
Boy, that's tough.
That's tough.
That is tricky because I often consider
the essential applications to be the most important
open source free software applications.
Like that's generally my default.
But I'm worried, to be honest with you, Alex,
that the machine learning stuff
or whatever GPU acceleration stuff
that's going to be necessary to get what I want
is all going to be proprietary.
Well, good news there.
Most of the apps that we'll talk about today
use TensorFlow,
which is a Google machine learning algorithm.
There's another one that we'll talk about
called PhotoStruxure, which has a closed source
and it's also a paid product as well.
But the developer has committed,
if anything happens to him or his company,
to open source the product.
Does that count for you?
It's definitely a plus anyway.
I mean, I'm not,
I guess I can handle proprietary software,
but I'd like to understand some of the motivations
and think that there's something long-term
that I can depend on at the very least.
I mean, there's clear advantages to an open source project
if it has a sizable user base
and a sustainable development model.
You get visibility into the direction of the project
and photos is a pretty important possession.
And so having that kind of forward-looking guidance
on a project gives me peace of mind.
But we talked about Beersmith in episode 400.
That's a proprietary application,
but it is built by a developer
who's dedicating his life to that.
And it's got a good user base and he's not going away.
Or, I mean, we're recording this right now in Reaper,
which is also a proprietary application,
but one that we love and absolutely depend on.
Yeah, so if the tool's clever enough
and it looks sustainable, I'd consider it.
It's the age-old question
of how do you monetize open source?
Right.
I think it's a problem that will bother us
for many years yet.
Well, and Alex, it's also pragmatism versus idealism.
It's that question too.
And you're coming to something
like your precious life photos.
And you're like in this war of like,
well, do I want something that's only free software?
Or am I willing to settle?
And it's like, where do you fall
on that whole pragmatism versus idealism line?
Well, I think if you're going full pragmatist,
you'll just use Google Photos, right?
Yeah, and I think that's what's been gnawing
at both Wes and I is full pragmatist
also means you're fully vulnerable
to whatever that service provider does.
And that's uncomfortable.
We were looking a little bit before the show
and playing around with Google Photos sync
like a Python daemon that'll sync stuff down from Google.
So I wonder if there's maybe some happy mediums there
where you still might want a backup.
Maybe you even want sort of a read-only view
of a local web interface of those backed up files,
but you use Google Photos for sharing with family.
Right, and so you have local copies
and then you have the copies on Google Photos.
Or maybe it goes the other way
and you sync it locally
and then upload them to Google Photos on the site.
I'm not sure.
It seems like there's a lot of options though.
Or maybe something else entirely.
You could argue, right, that Google Photos
being a completely proprietary service is irrelevant
as long as the export tools are good enough.
And Google love to promote this Google Takeout tool.
But when I was writing this piece,
you know, it's taken me a week or so.
On the first night I was writing,
I went to Google Takeout
and pressed the give me my photos button.
We are about eight or nine days now
and I still haven't gotten the download link.
Really? Wow.
That doesn't give you confidence.
Not really.
Although I have to say,
I think if Google Photos was gonna shut down,
they would probably give people a pretty good grace period
to get their data out of there.
I don't think Google will just turn it off.
I think what is actually more likely, Alex,
is that something happens to my Google account
and I lose access to my Google account, thus my photos.
Now I know that Brent,
you have a fully open sourced workflow.
So you must have some opinions on this, right?
Well, I started tackling this problem
much before we had mobile phones.
And so I will say my solutions are a bit archaic,
but they are solid.
Stay a while and listen.
And so one thing, one criteria I had
that's still very strong for me
is to always have the ability to put my photos
somewhere on a file system without dependency on anything.
So anything includes a company, a web service, a database,
if I can have access to them always,
then that's really super important.
And so Chris, when you said,
oh, if I lose access to my Google account,
I started cringing and my palms are sweating
and that makes me super uncomfortable
because that's something I've seen happen a lot
to very well-meaning people.
And I've tried to help people get in
and sometimes it's impossible.
And so actually that's even worse
than having your phone run over by a dump truck
because it's all of the photos spanning across
several generations of phones that you've had
and not to mention other things you've uploaded there.
So I think having that in mind,
being able to export your photos meaningfully,
which Alex, it sounds like they failed there for you,
that's extremely important.
So for me, that's the top one
and that's the one that's kept me from using Google Photos
all these years is that it just makes me really uncomfortable.
And so some of the tools I've relied on
have been a little bit more offline tools for that reason.
And like I said, I've developed my pipeline
to have longevity to it.
And so it's worked up till this point.
Cause you're even allergic to stuff like Lightroom, right?
You really don't wanna even go as far as paying Adobe any,
I don't know, what's the word I'm looking for?
You don't wanna give Adobe credit
for going to a subscription model or whatever it is.
You use a dark table if I'm not mistaken, right?
I do, yeah.
And you know, Alex, you touch on a little piece
of my past there.
So Lightroom was sort of the defacto
and where I learned doing a lot
of really efficient photo manipulation.
And I got bit by early versions of Lightroom
because their libraries weren't compatible
between different versions sometimes depending,
but also they would get corrupted.
And so that was where both this desire
to get away from a dependency
on some of those functions came from,
but also where I got introduced to open software
in the first place, to open source software.
And so it's funny that you mentioned Lightroom
because it's the reason that I have these philosophies now
and that I looked for alternatives
that didn't tie all my metadata into, you know,
a neat little database that could get corrupted or lost.
I think it's better these days,
but back then it just sort of informed my decisions.
So all right, Alex, give us a rundown
of some of the apps you've come across.
One of the first apps I picked out was Photonics.
Now this one, its headline feature
is machine learning object detection.
There's currently no face detection with this one,
but there is active development in this area.
And I ended up really liking this app for a while.
And then the more I used it, the more I disliked it.
I just found the interface kind of really cluttered.
Now, the way I like to describe this
is kind of designed by developer.
It's one of those interfaces
where clearly the people working on the project
know every little bell and whistle,
every little knob and dial to turn,
but as a user coming to it fresh,
I don't need to be presented with everything all at once.
With a photo app in particular,
the content should be front and center
and then everything else should be available if I want it.
There is a demo of Photonics at demo.photonics.org.
Now the next one was actually a really interesting project.
So it used to be called OwnPhotos
and recently it was forked into the new project
called LibrePhotos.
This was probably,
it was certainly in my top three of the apps I looked at.
And there's a lot to like here.
It's got all the important stuff like face recognition,
geo lookups, object detection,
and the developer recently added video support as well.
And having just had a kid,
I have totally changed my tune on video.
Yeah, take as much video as you can, that's my advice.
And particularly if it displays,
just like Google Photos does,
in the feed, in the timeline view,
just like a photo would do.
Also, and this one Brent might be of interest for you,
it has a direct integration with Nextcloud via WebDAV,
which enables a seamless import of images
between those two applications.
See, I like that because it starts to combine
some applications to solve the whole solution space
that Google Photos is offering,
where it seems like so far,
some of these are little bits and pieces.
Is that what I'm getting?
Right, whereas this is a sync and the photo library.
And I like, I also like in here,
they have a data visualization section
that shows you timeline and word clouds and places tree.
Oh, wow.
That stuff's fun.
Actually really do like the timeline stuff
because I can go through there and look at,
just discover a whole time period.
And then pretty soon I'm starting to send pictures
to my wife, oh, remember this?
All of that kind of little thing,
things that just kind of built into Google Photos
and other software.
It's nice to see that here in Libre photos.
That's cool.
Those data visualizations are cool,
but ultimately, particularly the word cloud,
I found it just to be a bit pointless.
Like maybe if in the word cloud that's generated,
so what happens is Libre photos will go through
and scan your images and tag it
with all the different objects it's found,
you know, tree, monkey, dog.
Hot dog.
And it will generate a word cloud.
And obviously the more times it finds the same word,
the bigger the word becomes in the word cloud, right?
Just like you'd expect.
What I would expect when that happens
is that I would then be able to click on that word
in the web interface.
And it would take me to that category of images.
Yeah.
Unfortunately, it doesn't do that right now.
Ooh, you gotta be kidding.
What's the point?
That's no good.
It's a small thing.
But again, it's just another example
of how it's designed by a developer
as opposed to someone who's more focused
perhaps on the user experience.
Yeah, okay.
All right.
So Libre photos could be a contender,
especially if you're in the next cloud space,
but I have a sense there's something else out there.
Honestly, man.
There are so many.
I started off trying to write
a couple of thousand word article.
And over a week later, I'm tearing my hair out thinking,
oh, there's so many options.
So if I miss your favorite option,
or we don't talk about it today,
please, it's not a slight against you.
Just let us know, linuxunplugged.com slash contact.
All right.
So the next one I'm gonna talk about is photo structure.
Now this is the one that's got the really interesting
kind of open source dilemma going on.
So the application itself is closed source.
There are several features that the developer
has open sourced and upstreamed
to various different projects.
So it's kind of a, it's closed source,
but it's aware of the open source ecosystem.
So it's not on Adobe.
It's not like an Oracle kind of level
of closed source evilness,
but it's also not full on freedom hippie open source either.
Somewhere in the middle, interesting.
Yeah, bear that in mind.
The killer features of this app
are based around photo organization.
So Chris, this might be one for you.
There are zero machine learning features, unfortunately,
but what this one really excels at
is image ingestion and management.
So if you point this at a directory,
it will support either existing file systems,
or it will ingest and import images
into its own file structure, which is still readable.
It's not a database.
It's just a bunch of files organized properly.
It will also de-duplicate images
and run on any major OS as a kind of a web app,
but as a service, if that makes sense.
So I run everything in a container
that we're talking about here.
And if you're saying that's the way you'll go to,
but this one runs on any major OS that you'd like.
Oh, okay.
And it says it's been designed to handle
a lifetime of photos and videos.
Like all the best software,
this one scratches an itch for the developer.
And so it is closed source, but you can self-host it.
You can run it on your own system.
So it's a sustainable project, right?
The developer can eat, and I think that's important.
A lot of these projects are kind of
one or two man operations,
and PhotoStruxure is a one man operation,
but it's his full-time job,
and he can pay the bills and his mortgage with it.
So he's motivated to keep working on it and add new features.
And as a paid customer for PhotoStruxure,
you get the ability to vote on the next features
coming along and it's a meritocracy.
So obviously the features with the most votes
are the ones that he will work on
because the people paying the bills have asked him to do so.
I like that.
Always nice to see software that runs and targets Linux
and they've mentioned Docker right there
pretty prominently, wonderful.
I can live with that.
All right, so PhotoStruxure looks like a serious contender,
as long as I don't want the machine learning
like base tagging stuff.
Yeah, that is a shame.
And I think obviously with time,
those features will get added to it.
But the thing I picked up most talking to Matthew
was just how much care and attention and craftsmanship
has gone into the backend of what's already there.
By far and away, it's the most performant
of any of the products that we're talking about today
or any of the projects we're talking about.
And I think the project has a bright future.
Nice one, that had not been on my radar before.
What else do we got?
Well, we're moving into the kind of gallery apps,
actually, no, before we do,
I'll just talk about PhotoPrism.
This one is open source,
and there's a link to the demo in the show notes.
Much like Libre Photos and Photonics,
it also uses Google TensorFlow to do machine learning.
It can automatically classify objects,
but as of today, there's no face detection.
Okay, now like our emailer,
he only had a Raspberry Pi 3,
so I don't think he can do TensorFlow.
And what kind of requirements do I need?
Do I need to have a Nvidia Tesla GPU
to be able to use TensorFlow?
I mean, you certainly could.
You could use CUDA, I think is the Nvidia library
that does that kind of stuff.
But I'm just running this on an i5 eighth gen CPU.
So it's only got six cores.
It's not a super powerhouse or anything.
Maybe it is compared to a Raspberry Pi,
but it's not a data center.
All right, that sounds pretty reasonable.
So PhotoPrism uses TensorFlow to do all of that.
And it also gives you a gallery
to sort through all of that.
I would imagine exposing the metadata
and all that kind of stuff.
I remember the UI.
I remember checking it out for self-hosted,
and it felt like it was really clean
and simple and straightforward.
I actually end up growing to hate it this week.
Again, it's a design by developer problem.
So if you look at the interface that I've got here,
it's got eight pictures of airplanes.
Actually, some of those were taken at the studio,
by the way, do you remember when there was those planes
flying around at the sprint?
Yeah.
A couple of those are from then.
If you look at the pictures,
if you click on an image, what would you expect to happen?
I would expect the image to open.
Nope, wrong, guess again.
Oh no, what happens?
What happens here is it begins
a multi-image selection process.
No.
That's unacceptable.
To open the image, you have to click on the tiny,
tiny little translucent camera icon up in the top left.
Yeah, that does seem kind of like a really simple thing,
yet very frustrating thing.
Which is also sometimes a magnifying glass
with a plus in the middle of it.
Right, right, right.
And also sometimes a play button.
And because it's a web app,
God only knows what could be going on
with your web browser at that moment,
where the first click isn't even registered.
Right, so there are little things with PhotoPrism
that could use work, and again,
it's mostly user interface and experience stuff.
They do have really great documentation
on a WebDAV feature, so much like Libre Photos,
you can integrate this with Nextcloud,
but also you can mount this via WebDAV
from your desktop computer.
So Brent, maybe this could be one for you.
I'm thinking with DigiCam or Darktable or something.
Yeah, it does sound really interesting
because it seems to blend the internet world
with my here at home in my cave world.
And here's what I'm trying to wrap my head around, Brent.
So you take all these photos, you know,
you got a whole, I would imagine,
a nice library of faces and objects.
Have you ever considered how nice it would be
to be able to just expose like every picture
of this particular face or person
or every photo that has this plant in it?
Like that seems like that would be extremely useful
for a professional.
It's a feature I've dreamt of for decades.
And so I will say, I will admit to absolutely everyone
that my methods are deprecated
and only because they've worked
and I haven't really needed a better way,
although you guys are all making me realize
that I'm suffering a little bit
without some of these features.
So I am all ears.
Hey Alex, I'm thinking we do
a total self-hosted makeover for the photos
for Brent in a future episode of self-hosted, you know?
It's an intervention.
Yeah, we'll show up.
We'll have like this whole server set up for you.
We'll show you the whole workflow
and get the Brent stamp of approval and then deploy it
and get all of your images recognized.
And it'll be a full photo makeover.
I'll expect a link to the gallery of that event.
Okay, so that's PhotoPrism and it is open source.
So that checks a box, it supports web dev.
So that makes it pretty flexible.
Is there any other ones we should mention?
Cause you know, look, I wanted to mention,
I think it was at Leachy, we've used that before.
I think we still have that somewhere running actually.
We do gallery.selfhosted.show.
There's a few of my own personal images in there.
And this one's really interesting
cause it kind of somewhat blurs the line
between a straightforward gallery app
and a photo management app.
And the reason I say that is because
you can organize images into albums,
but you can also edit the metadata of these images.
Now, a lot of these programs that we've talked about
have next to no image editing features.
We're talking not a single one on this list
allows you to crop an image.
A couple of them allow you to rotate,
Leachy's one of those.
But I mean, I can't crop an image in any of these.
I was, I couldn't believe that.
Yeah, I think I'm kind of coming to the conclusion
that my strategy for that would be local editing.
So something like Shotwell or Darktable for local edits,
which I think that's what you're doing now, Wes.
And so that's why the ones that support WebDAV
are kind of appealing to me
because I could see using both tools.
One is a viewing and searching tool and discovery tool
that I can, oh, look at this great pic.
I can quickly copy it and paste it into Telegram, right?
That's one tool.
And then the other tool is that one
where I've gone a little bit in
and I maybe crop something to make it a nicer shot
or something like that.
And I can save it back to the same source location.
During one of those editing sessions,
maybe when you have the itch
or you're getting back from a trip
and you're kind of going through things.
Right, right.
What would be a really nice feature
is if you could use some of these apps we're talking about
as your sort of photo organization method
and then have this, let me dream here for a moment,
have this method to just sort of,
I don't know, you can't right click in here,
but right click and go open in Darktable
or open in Glimpse or something like that
and then do your cropping and your photo adjusting.
And that way they don't have to sort of rely on that stuff.
Yeah, I think you've just described
the mobile experience now.
Mm-hmm, exactly.
Dang it.
Well, and the reality is whenever you wanna share stuff
with family, oftentimes you're on the go
or you've got five minutes while you're waiting
on somebody else to do something or in a lineup at the bank.
I say the bank, who goes to the bank anymore?
But you know what I mean?
Hey, I went and deposited a check in person this week
for the first time in a long time.
Where did you go?
Caveman, welcome back.
But I found even for me, like I'm sharing most of my stuff
from mobile, not to clients, but to everybody else.
And so that's an essential feature.
I'll tell you what Brent, sharing images via link
is actually a surprisingly difficult thing to get right
apparently in this space.
Lychee does this best in my opinion.
It allows you to generate different URLs for social media,
but also, and this is a really cool feature,
Lychee will let you generate images automatically scaled
to certain resolutions.
That's directly in its sharing pane.
That's Lychee, L-Y-C-H-E-E.
And if you wanna see an example of it,
you can go to gallery.selfhosted.show.
And it's pretty straightforward.
Do you think maybe this is the most straightforward
of all of them to get up and running
and just share photos with somebody?
Yeah, I think it's probably my favorite app overall
in this entire rundown.
The downside is it has no machine learning features.
So if you want that kind of search organization,
it doesn't have that.
Like you say in your article,
it's a great front end to whatever else you're using
to make your photos look great and organize them well.
That's where it shines.
So I have a link to some of these projects
that we've mentioned here on the show.
So that way you don't have to worry about the weird names
at linuxunplug.com slash 409.
Now, if I could just do one final little honorable mention.
I came across an app called File Run on Self Hosted
a few months ago,
and I actually ended up using it quite a bit for photos
because it has a bunch of image processing stuff
in the background.
And all File Run does is it's a web app
that presents an underlying file system in the web browser.
And it supports full text and has metadata search as well,
which if you think about it,
apart from the machine learning stuff it's missing,
is actually half the battle.
So this is at filerun.com,
and this would totally be one of our tools
in the total photo makeover for Brent, Alex.
And the UI is surprisingly nice.
For something that I've wanted for so long,
just your files available in mobile
or in a full web version in a really nice UI.
And, although I don't really think
you probably use this much,
but it has plugins too for things like Google Apps
and Office 365 and Autodesk and a lot of those things.
Autodesk, what?
Yeah, so you can pull in CAD files, isn't that funny?
Why not, man?
And if all you have lying around is a Raspberry Pi,
this might be the way to go.
Yeah, throw File Run on there,
do your file uploads right there,
and then maybe leechy on top of that
to do some of the display and sharing.
That could be a nice way to go.
Absolutely, and I think it just highlights clearly
that none of these apps check all of these boxes.
You're gonna have to have probably NextCloud
to get the images off your device,
and then something else to organize and edit them.
Well, actually something else to organize them,
something else to edit them,
like a DigiCam or whatever it might be.
And then something else maybe to display them as well.
So very quickly you've got a stack
of three or four apps here.
And I ended up coming to the conclusion
that unless some of these apps
are able to kind of pool together their resources,
we're not gonna see a true Google Photos alternative
that ticks all the boxes for some time.
Yeah, and then it just has to, I suppose,
be that question of pragmatism versus idealism,
and how much work are you willing to put in for your photos?
Right, here you get to and have to build your own pipeline
with Google Photos, they've done it for you,
but you don't get any input on how it works.
And maybe for something like your photos
that you wanna have a 25-year grasp on
or something like that at a time,
maybe that's worth getting out the old, you know,
artisan, craftsman kind of mindset and building something.
I think it might be for me.
I've always been teetering on this.
And I also sometimes wonder if perhaps
it isn't maybe the perfect sweet spot
to build something locally that's like this,
and maybe still loop in some service to do backups,
because that's how important the photos are to me.
Well, Google Photos, I think, is still an excellent choice
for your offsite backup.
If you're following the 3-2-1 principle for your backups,
Google Photos is a fantastic choice.
I should also mention at this point that Amazon,
if you're a Prime subscriber,
has free unlimited photo storage for now.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
Yep, that's just it.
And it may be in some weird, twisted way,
Google's transition to actually making you pay
for the storage that you use for Google Photos
may actually be the thing that makes it sustainable
and stick around for a long time.
And maybe that is in some weird ways a good thing.
It doesn't mean they're not mining your data,
but at least they're not just gonna randomly
shut down the service on you.
So if you wanna add it to your arsenal of photo options,
that's a great way to go.
I think it works best as a complimentary offsite backup
and not the primary.
And I think that's where having a local cache
that I can then throw into these tools
that we've just covered
is gonna make me feel a lot more comfortable.
So thanks for the rundown, Alex.
Absolutely, you're very welcome.
I mean, there's, like I say,
there's loads and loads of other options
we didn't get time to talk about today.
You know, PyWeGo, PyGallery2, Pixel Fed,
PhotoView, Thumbs Up, Koken.
I mean, the list goes on and on.
Let's UNLOCK and we'll get started.
jupitrgarage.com is getting restocked
with some brand new items.
They're not in yet, but for the first time,
we've reached that goal of clearing out a lot of the old,
not everything, not everything,
but we have made enough room to bring in some of the new,
which was always, always the goal.
We are beginning that process right now.
I am gonna keep it simple and humble like we have been,
you know, baby steps here,
can grab the seasoned tux tee on sale right now.
That's a shirt that I created.
It's a new item.
It is a all black t-shirt with a gray and dark gray bearded version of the tux
holding the Jupiter broadcasting rocket.
The, uh, the, the seasoned tux, as I call it.
And, uh, it's on sale right now at Jupiter garage.com.
If you'd like to grab one.
And now for some feedback, Mark from Lenovo writes in.
Hello, Chris and Wes.
I'm the technical lead for the Linux PC team at Lenovo.
Hello, Mark.
I was listening to episode 405 and you mentioned the battery life on the X1 Carbon.
I figured it would be interesting to reach out to the firmware slash hardware team
here for their input.
I've now got a bunch of battery related ACPI APIs that I need to go through and
see how they fit into what the kernel has.
Although most of them are there already, but I also got some feedback on battery
charging thresholds looking through the docs.
One of the things I noted is that charging thresholds really depend on typical usage.
So here's the scenario.
If you regularly fully discharge the battery, then actually the default setting
of starting to charge at 95% and going up to 100% is apparently fine.
But in a different scenario, if you regularly somewhat discharge the battery, but not all
the way, say operating between 50% and a hundred percent, then the techs recommend
starting charging at 75% and stopping at 80%.
And for a final scenario, if you're connected to power the majority of the time, in that
case, you want to start at 45 stop at 50.
I was surprised, frankly, at how small the windows were.
I expected to see something more like 30% to 80%.
And I've also got some questions in to better understand typical degradation, like is
dropping to 96% in the first six months actually normal?
No idea what the curve looks like in most cases.
Holler if you have any questions.
Happy to forward those on to the hardware team to Mark.
Well, thanks, Mark.
I think the the the bit that stands out and that's from the Lenovo team that stands out
to me is if you're connected to power the majority of the time with your ThinkPad, you
should try to keep your battery charge in the 45 to 50% range.
I wish I knew that earlier.
Yeah. And Mark's right.
That is a really that's a 5% range that is really small.
I am achieving that with TLP right now.
And it bit me once because, of course, I was I was off grid, open up the laptop.
It only had 50% battery.
Oh, right.
I need to take action beforehand.
But we got a bunch of feedback in about how people are extending battery life or managing
TLP on Linux.
So if you've already sent an email to that regard, we received it.
But if you haven't yet and you have some battery management tips or the ways that you've
used TLP or things that you found that have extended your Linux battery life, please get
those in now at Linux unplugged dot com slash contact, because I think we're going to do
a batch of feedback next week and kind of put a cap on this battery discussion because
I have received a few cool tricks from the audience that I want to relay to everybody.
And I went on this trip the entire time using TLP, have some regrets, but also I think
there was some positives to it.
So we'll follow up next episode on that.
And thank you to Mark for reaching out from Lenovo and getting some info straight from
the team. I really appreciate the ability to pass on that to the community because, you
know, that's straight from, as they say, the horse's mouth.
So Linux unplugged dot com slash contact for your feedback and whatnot.
We are back to our regular live time.
So if you'd like to join us for a live episode, we do them on Tuesdays at noon Pacific, 3
p.m. Eastern over at J.B.
Live TV. Thank you to our members.
Those of you who have become members, you get access to the limited ad version of the
show and the full live stream.
So thank you very much to our unplugged core members.
You all are the very best.
See you next week. Same bad time, same bad station.
That's right. Either way, it comes out every week over at Linux unplugged dot com.
You can go to Linux unplugged dot com slash subscribe to get the feeds for all different
players that you like, and you can follow the show on the Twitter at Linux unplugged.
You can follow the West at West Paine can follow me at Chris Lass.
But you know what? It's really if you want to get something to show, it's probably best to
use the contact page that works probably the best.
But, you know, I haven't mentioned the matrix in a while and the major community continues
to grow. Despite that, shout out to them.
Info at Linux unplugged dot com slash matrix.
We're in there. We're hanging out. It's a great spot.
So thanks so much for joining us and we'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
So has anybody given the old Google take out a try to get their photos out, Alex?
I know you were experimenting with that.
We talked about it in the show briefly, didn't we?
And my link came in today, funnily enough, and I have I'm now the proud owner of a hundred
and forty four two gigabyte files.
That's how they gave me the takeout stuff.
Holy. And then how do you download that?
What's the UI to download?
Is it a URL? Like it's an email with one hundred and forty four individual links in it.
There's no download all button.
You just have to go through them one by one.
That's interesting because with Google Play Music, you had the option of downloading
everything as a large zip file.
That doesn't really seem like that great of an option, Alex.
I got to say. But, yeah, I mean, come on.
I've I've got 10, 15 years worth of images in there and every SLR image I've ever taken,
every mobile image. So there's a lot of data in there.
So one massive zip file wouldn't really be very feasible, I don't think.