The case for open source in all of the things researchers have found the code in Volkswagens
that was used to cheat emissions tests and it's pretty sophisticated stuff.
They would monitor all kinds of conditions like the position of the tire, how fast the
engine was having, how hard the engine was having to work to move the tires, how fast
they would spin and it was all tucked away under something very innocuous, just something
really simple called acoustic condition.
Yeah, a little specific piece of code that was just labeled acoustic condition which
was originally started as just a way to control the sounds that the engine makes but it later
became a euphemism for conditions occurring during the emissions test and the code allowed
for as many 10 different profiles, as many as 10 different profiles for different potential
tests.
When the computer would determine the car was undergoing a test, it activated the emissions
curbing system which reduced the amount of nitrogen oxide that was emitted.
I found that kind of interesting because there was, it turns out, also a less sophisticated
version that Fiat was implementing and this one didn't have to worry about like the position
of the tire or how hard it was to spin the wheel, the car's onboard computer just simply
turned on emission curbing software for the first 26 minutes and 40 seconds of the engine
start.
Nice, yeah.
So every time you started your engine, it just ran a little worse for the first 26 minutes
and 40 seconds.
If you were driving somewhere far, then you know.
Yeah, and then that would cover most emissions tests by that point.
Most of them don't run longer than that and so you're out.
Researchers noted that for both Volkswagen and for Fiat, the vehicle's engine control
unit is manufactured by an automotive component giant, Robert Bosch.
Oh, of course.
Yeah, Bosch and car manufacturers are then under their own choice, they can then enable
the code by entering certain parameters into the emissions control unit.
This is why we need open source for all of the things because, you know, our buddy Chase
got bit by this directly.
Did he?
Yeah.
I didn't realize that.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
He had to give back his Volkswagen diesel and he's now driving a Ford.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 198 from May 23rd, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that might just be planning a barbecue
for its birthday.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes and I'm hungry for burgers.
Hello, Wes.
Oh, I know.
I know.
You're the one that dropped the word ribs.
Just saying.
You might have to own that one, Wes.
You might have to own those barbecue ribs.
Coming up though on this week's episode, we're not there yet.
We're not yet to episode 200.
No, we're going to talk about some of our favorite open source projects, one that I
bet you have been looking for.
If you've ever considered getting a Chromecast and want to integrate it with your Linux box,
we'll talk about that, which I am particularly excited about because I have a Chromecast
sitting around needing to get a little more useful.
If you want to update some Logitech hardware under Linux, which I do, we have some good
news for you.
Big updates from Solus, a new version of Nextcloud is in the house and Joss will be here to talk
about it with us.
And then the magic device tool, I mentioned it a little bit last week.
It promises to make my Nexus 5 usable.
We'll talk with Marius, the gentleman who created the magic device tool, a simple and
feature rich tool to install or replace operating systems on a lot of common phones.
It's really slick.
And then also, we'll tell you a little bit about our barbecue plans, a little bit of
news that's going on, and of course, all of the wonderful discussions.
But one of the things I need to do right off the top because I neglected to do it last
week right now, prepare yourselves.
We're going to bring in that Mumble Room.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Dear friends.
Hey, you know what?
That intro right there, that whole show, powered by the new open source caster soundboard,
how great was that?
Hey, you know what?
That ding right there, also powered by the open source soundboard.
100% digital ding.
It is so awesome.
If you haven't checked it out yet, you should go to github.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting
and check out caster soundboard.
Now with new art graphics, like look at that icon right there.
You see that duck?
Yeah.
Look at that cute little duck.
Albert made us that.
That tells, that's the system-wide ducking.
You hit that and it ducks all the audio.
Awesome.
Brings it down to 33%.
Such a cool piece of software.
A legitimately competitive piece of software that was created by our community and it's
just so awesome.
And it's come so far so fast.
Yeah.
And we're using it in production now on all the shows.
It's pretty neat.
And you guys can go check it out if you want.
Now we'll talk about, we've got a bunch of stuff to talk about today.
That's not really it.
But why don't we talk about something else that's up on github?
MK, so Mik maybe, Chromecast, MK Chromecast, which allows Mac and Linux machines to send
audio and video to Google Cast devices and also Sonos devices.
Which not particularly appealing to me but I bet is to some people.
You can find more at MKChromecast.com.
And it's a program that lets you cast your audio or your Linux audio, whichever, it's
Mac or Linux, I don't think it works on Windows.
And it can also send video files.
Nice.
Super nice, over the land.
If you've ever had like, in fact it was like a, it must have been like Christmas or Thanksgiving
or Halloween, some recent major holiday event.
We had all these videos on my computer and I wanted to play it for the family on the
television.
And I ended up installing all these crazy Chrome extensions to try to make it work and
they were super rickety.
You have to pay a bunch.
Yeah, yeah.
This is just using FFmpeg and AVConf on the back end.
I think it's spinning up a Node.js instance and then it's using some MP3 codec encoding
to send it to this thing.
But at the end of the day, it doesn't really matter because it's allowing you to stream
high end audio.
You can do 24 bit, 96 kilohertz, high resolution audio using this thing.
And the other thing that's really nice about it is it integrates in on either the Mac OS
menu bar or if you're on Gnome or the Plasma desktop, it can also integrate with the desktop
there too.
So you get a little like a little Chromecast icon.
Look at that.
That is slick.
Yeah.
How fantastic would this be, right?
Now Sweetlo, you were going to mention CastNow.
Yeah I'm assuming that this MK Chromecast program works similar to how CastNow works.
I've ran CastNow a couple of times before and it did the job in that, mostly during
times when I was having issues with something like YouTube or something.
One thing CastNow can do that this can't, I'm not positive, is I think CastNow supports
torrents directly, but CastNow is command line only, whereas this integrates with the
menu bar on your desktop and stuff, which some people would prefer.
And it looks like CastNow isn't super, I mean there are some people making commits to it,
but on the read me there it talks about how the guy's kind of moved on, he's using DLNA.
So I know I'd use CastNow in the past too, so it's interesting to see another contender.
Yeah.
You know like Sweetlo says, I know I've run into times where certain content providers
are like, why are you not working?
I could just download the file, play it on the TV, so hey, there you go.
Well and there is some legitimate use for Chromecast like in the workspace too.
So if you could throw a Chromecast on a television in a conference room and now you can send
stuff to it from your Linux box, that could be some money.
So it's MK Chromecast, it's only $100.
So you just go there, you give them your username, if you don't have an account, create one,
give them your shipping address, make sure you have a U.S. credit card, they only take
U.S. credit card.
Yeah, maybe you're social, and then it's only $100, what, I'm sorry, what?
Oh, this is not the Mac Action Show, uh-huh, okay, oh it's free, okay, uh-huh, okay.
I'm sorry, it uses something called the open source, and it's free, it's totally free,
100%, who knew?
Can we trust that?
Who knew?
I wouldn't, but you know what, I guess if you want to take your own risk.
You come back next week with a paid version and maybe we'll talk.
I'm just telling you, man, I'm just telling you.
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
That is not us.
So I like to mess with my hardware peripherals.
I have a bunch, right now in front of me, I have a bunch of Logitech hardware, and one
of the things that's great about Logitech is they have these unifying receivers.
You put one USB, little itty bitty USB receiver, and you can have your mouse and your keyboard
using one receiver.
Well, guess what?
There is a vulnerability, in fact a whole suite of vulnerabilities, and when you put
them all together, it even has a great name called MouseJack.
It uses a whole bunch of different stuff, vulnerabilities that are targeted, the low
level wireless protocol that's used by the unifying devices, they can do things like
pair new devices without prompting the user, they can inject keystrokes, they can inject
raw HID commands with about $15 of hardware.
You could be 50 meters away in doing this.
So that typical imagine sitting in a cafe scenario is, of course, it's very scary.
I have a little mouse I take with me everywhere.
Yeah, me too.
That's what I'm all about.
These Logitech MX Anywheres are the best little laptop meese on the market, and so I have
these unifying receivers everywhere.
So Logitech Bastille Security worked with them, and Logitech acknowledged they had a
problem, and it took them a couple of releases, but after a couple of releases, they have
some updates that fix it.
It took them a few weeks, but they got it.
They fixed it.
The issue is solved, unless you're running Linux.
So they call up Logitech, and they're like, okay, here's what we're thinking about doing.
The cat's out of the bag on this whole mouse jack thing.
So we now know how we can randomly flash firmware onto your proprietary hardware.
If you gave us a little bit of official documentation, I bet you we could flash that secure firmware
onto these receivers using FW upload, which is a standard Linux utility.
It took a couple of weeks, and they rewrote the previously reverse-engineered plug-in
for FW upload.
The new documentation from Logitech came in, so they knew exactly what they were supposed
to do, how everything was supposed to match up, byte by byte.
They compared it with the Windows update version, and they were able to push this new firmware.
You could actually test it, too, right now.
If you'd like to test it, you need to get the new version of FW upload, because you
have to be able to talk to the hardware, so you need version 0.9.2-2, which is in Fedora
26 right now, and you can get it from Koji or for Fedora.
If you scroll just down a little bit there, doesn't it sure look nice in that GNOME software
that you just have that little update?
This is the idea, right?
They can then use this down the road via GNOME software update to update firmware like this.
That's brilliant, I think.
It shows you how everything... You've got to be thinking about the update life cycle
on everything now.
We're so used to talking about... We're about to talk about an update to Nextcloud.
We're used to talking about an update to our GNOME desktop, but there's even bootloader
code on these little receivers that the documentation-
Turtles all the way down, and the turtles run horrible, ancient software.
Yes, very well put.
It is turtles all the way down.
That's why we always are looking for a little refreshing cup of tea, or maybe a nice, relaxing
bowl of soup.
We got a little plasma in the soup this time.
Yeah, so Ikea has a rare blog post over at the Solus site, and it looks like, ladies
and gentlemen, prepare yourselves for the shocker of a lifetime, but it's early days,
but the plasma desktop is coming to Solus, and I actually think this is a great combination.
That's why I wanted to put it in here, because I think Solus is a great distribution, and
I think this could be one of the great plasma distributions if they work on it.
So right now, it's not officially supported, but they have Peter.
He's working on the project.
He's been maintaining plasma packages and KDE dependencies for a while, because it turns
out things like KDE and Live, Corita, K3b are pretty popular among Solus users, so they're
already packing in all of the dependencies for that anyways, and they're packaging...
So it wasn't that much further to just...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So the way Ikea writes this is, he says, Peter's ambition is to eventually support a full plasma
stack on Solus, and if you want to help him get there, you can help him evolve it, so
you can get involved, work with Peter, help Peter report bugs, things like that.
So do you think this would be something that you're interested in?
Are you doing it over here now?
Is this Solus here?
No, I just wanted you to...
Yeah.
Okay.
Maybe.
I would consider it.
I would definitely kick the tires, and Ikea here has laid out to who's now working on
the different desktops.
Josh is working on GnomeShell, Ikea's working on Budgie, Peter on KDE Plasma, Justin on
Mate.
It's a nice insight into how the projects...
Yeah.
What they're each kind of focusing on.
Good for them.
Yeah.
So if you asked about it, I'm excited to see where they take Budgie.
I think it's great to have another distribution where Plasma could eventually become a tier
one citizen.
Patreon.com slash Solus if you want to help them.
I think this would be a great way, even if you're not running Solus, but you like what
they're doing.
I really like the idea that there's a project out there that's making a really modern distro,
and they're not being religious about what desktop you have to use, and they're playing
well with others too.
Patreon.com slash Solus, and keep up the great work, guys.
I'll probably be checking it out.
I'll probably check it out.
I bet you will.
So NextCloud12 is out, and Joss is here to chat with us about it.
So before we go there, before we get any further, let's take a moment and thank our first sponsor
this week, Linux Academy.
Oh, yeah.
LinuxAcademy.com slash Unplugged, a platform where you can learn more about Linux and all
of the technology around Linux.
I think this is a resource that if you would have told Chris from 10 years ago existed,
he would have been delighted.
When I first started working with Linux, I actually just went and got a bunch of books,
and then I tried to find community college courses, and it was always hit and miss on
how good the instructor was going to be, and I would try to figure out what courseware
would be the best investment of my time, and there was really no oversight or way to figure
it all out, especially for somebody who's busy and had a lot going on.
Linux Academy checks all those boxes and more.
So it's built by people that are incredibly passionate about Linux.
They have full-time instructors available when you need them.
They're continually investing in content to make Linux Academy more valuable.
They have hands-on labs and exercises.
They have in-depth cert training if that's the route you want to go.
You get unlimited access to the courses.
They spin up the servers on demand when you need them.
They're even doing deep dives into things like AWS and Azure and all that kind of stuff.
Man, it is a new world, and Linux Academy is going to help you meet it head on.
LinuxAcademy.com slash Unplugged.
You go there, you sign up for a free seven-day trial, try them all out, get a little idea
of how it works, wrap your head around it a bit, enjoy, and if you have any questions,
take advantage of that instructor mentoring.
LinuxAcademy.com slash Unplugged.
Sign up for a free seven-day trial and support the show, and a big thank you to Linux Academy
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
See, I think at that point, you'd have to work hard to not learn something.
Ah, man, you would really have to not want to learn, which would sort of defeat the purpose.
Why are you doing that?
So Joss joins us again.
Hey Joss, welcome back to the show, sir.
Good to have you.
Hey guys, nice to be here again.
Thanks for inviting me.
Now we have a new Nextcloud on our hands, and it looks like it's going global scale
this time.
Congrats.
Yeah, you like that, huh?
I do, I do, I do like that.
There's also a couple other features in there that are actually more applicable directly
to me, like writable public links, improvements to the audio video chat.
But Joss, you're the expert.
Where do you think we should start on the new release?
Well, let's start, indeed, about the smaller features.
Well, I mean, next to global scale, everything looks small.
That's kind of the point of it.
But yeah, I think the collaboration features that you mentioned, like that you can send
a public link to someone with like a Collabora file, you know, a docx or something, and then
they can add it together with you.
They don't need an account.
That's really nice.
Very nice.
So it's essentially a very easy drop in replacement for Google Docs, because the end user you're
just sending a link to, they just click it and they're in.
They don't have to worry about what the software is.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
Our Office 365.
I mean, that's kind of officially what we're going after.
I mean, a lot of the other features, you see the same thing.
I mean, obviously, on top of that, you have all the control things, you know, that you
can say, okay, file access control, you can only you can limit, you know, access to files
from certain IP ranges or certain file types, you can say like, yeah, people in the HR department
when they share an Excel sheet via public link, you know, that is not accessible from
outside of the company, internal network, stuff like that.
You know, so you can put these these policies on top of it, which you can't really do with
most of the other solutions, because it just, well, they're not self hosted, they they're
not built to give you that kind of control as an administrator.
Sure.
And what what are the what are the when you say the big changes for like the global scale,
what does that really translate to what is what are the real technical changes happening
behind the scenes?
Yeah, so global scale, let me introduce it quickly for those who haven't seen it or seen
our video.
So the idea behind global scale is to transform the architecture of Nextcloud.
So Nextcloud, when Frank started this seven, eight years ago, it started as a standard
web app.
So in a web application, you can scale by just throwing more hardware at it at least
to a certain degree.
So with Nextcloud, you can you have an application server, Nextcloud itself, and then you have
database and storage and user directory like LDAP, and you connect it to those three.
And Nextcloud itself scales almost without limits.
If you want twice as many users, you just put down two Nextcloud servers.
But the thing is, they both need to connect to the same database and same storage and
the same user directory.
So at a certain scale, and I mean, you're talking about 10, 20, 30,000 users is all
quite doable, but if you get above 50,000, you really need to buy very expensive enterprise
storage, very expensive enterprise databases, it gets very pricey and slow at some point.
So that's what we want to fix.
So that's also what makes it more than interesting for really big solutions.
So global scale, the goal was to scale beyond 100 million users, like seriously huge installation
should be possible.
And the second goal was to lower the costs.
As I said, you get really high storage and database costs at the high end at large installations.
And the third was actually something a lot of people have been asking for, which is to
be able to say about the data that's on your Nextcloud, to be able to kind of split it
up and to say, look, I want this data to physically stay in San Francisco and this data to physically
stay in Germany.
Now you kind of could do that with Nextcloud 11 and 10 and other older releases by using
federation and you would simply have two servers and then the users would have to log in to
one or the other and then they could share with each other because they were connected
via federation.
That's kind of nice.
We still have multiple places to log in and what if an employee moves from the US to Europe?
You know, like you have to close their account and then create a new account, move their
data, all their shares will be gone.
That's kind of uncool.
So it wouldn't act like one instance, a little bit, but not really.
So this is what global scale is about, to make these three things different.
And it does that by splitting up indeed what federation did, except that it adds a couple
of components on top of that to make it act like a single instance.
So, you get the global site selector.
It's simply a server that when you log in, you go to cloud.nextcloud.com.
It's what I do every day, right?
That's our internal cloud.
And from there it automatically redirects you to the node where your data is.
So in my case it would be in Germany.
And what is doing that?
What's doing that redirection?
Is there some global master login database that knows where to send people?
Yeah.
So that's the global site selector itself.
It knows where you are.
The global site selector, is this a new piece of server software that Nextcloud is publishing?
Yes.
Correct.
It's a new separate, we actually implemented it, I have to see how it was implemented.
Give me a second.
Interesting though.
Because a number of things was done as an app and I would have to look up the details
there.
But it's a separate server component.
It's a separate thing that you have to run.
And that's where the users log in and then it redirects them.
And the user sets a cookie so that they don't have to go over this server every single time,
right?
Because your client logs in every 30 seconds and that would mean with 100 million users
you got 300 million connections every 30 seconds.
That's a little crazy.
So they remember what the node was, but as a user you don't notice that.
It's not that your URL changes.
You just go to cloud.nextcloud.com.
So you're in one place, but in the underlying there you're actually connected to a local
data center.
If local data switch fast, it's under control of the local sys admins.
They can say this data has to stay here or there and you know, it's all transparent for
you.
So that's one component.
And there are two more.
So the second component, that would be the lookup server.
So the lookup server, it knows where you are.
It's actually the global site selector that keeps a database with the node.
But the lookup server knows where you physically are.
It also knows your user sharing ID.
And when you migrate between nodes and your sharing ID changes too, then the lookup server
will keep a list of those so that if somebody connects is looking for an old share ID, then
the lookup server will redirect that to the new one.
So the lookup server is all about sharing.
Even if you would switch between, for example, providers, but I'll get to that a little bit
later, but lookup server is really important also for normal users.
Like this is not only relevant for a hundred million user deployment, but also for smaller
ones.
I'll get to that.
So it also stores information about you, like the quality of service metrics, like your
storage and quota settings, your reliability class.
Maybe you want your data replicated at least three times.
Maybe you're a VIP and you need always to be on SSD, stuff like that.
That's all in the lookup server.
Interesting.
And then the third part is the balancer.
And the balancer also runs on a dedicated machine and it monitors all the nodes.
So in Nextcloud 10 you might remember we introduced the monitoring app, which gives you either
via the web interface or via an API information about the CPU load, the memory load, the number
of shares, the number of users, all this kind of information.
Now this actually fits with the balancer because it takes that data and it keeps track of it.
And when it sees that the node is overloaded, it can actually initiate a migration of user
accounts from one node to another.
Or if it asks the lookup server where a user is, then it says, oh, this user just moved
from the US to Europe, let's migrate the user from the US data center to the Europe data
center and bang, the balancer makes that happen.
Or maybe you need to be moved on SSD because you bought an upgrade from your server provider
and you need faster data transfer.
So the balancer will make sure that you get on SSDs.
So this is the kind of stuff that the balancer does.
That is, that sounds super high end and fancy for enterprises, sounds like it's probably
be amazing for a lot of...
Flexible too, yeah.
Yeah.
And probably very useful for a lot of state installations.
Is there benefits that the home user or smaller, you know, small office user will also glean
from any of this?
Yeah, so that's a cool thing.
There are a number of elements where this helps normal users.
Now first of all, of course, the ability to migrate between servers, imagine you're at
one service provider and you don't like them.
You can migrate to another with all your data, with everything.
I mean, that's really cool.
This is something we're working on, by the way, I have to give a little caveat here.
So global scale isn't done yet.
We have a couple of pieces.
We have, for example, the lookup server, we have the global site selector, the lookup
server still needs more work, but it's already up and running.
We're using this already.
The balancer still needs to be done.
We've started working on the migration, but at the moment this is only doing the data
of the users.
So it's not doing a lot yet.
Josh, speaking of the global server, if I'm, you know, I'm Justin Trudeau and I want to
move the entire Canadian government over to Nextcloud, can I run my own global server?
Or is that something that's only hosted by Nextcloud?
How does that particular part work?
No, this is part of your own installation.
So all these pieces are fully open source.
They're in our GitHub.
And the idea is that, well, we would probably need to help a customer to set all this stuff
up, especially if you're big like the Canadian government, but you would run all these components
as part of your infrastructure and that would then be one massive Nextcloud system that
consists of nodes in every major city, for example.
So everybody has fast access, but at the same time, you know, it's cheap because you're
on all these small, you know, like two machines or something, you know, we're thinking that
nodes would have two to maybe six machines and that's all commodity hardware.
So that's way cheaper than this really high end storage stuff that you currently need.
So are you guys going to put feelers out with companies to see if they want to become like
a Nextcloud provider?
So there is already like a few dozen Nextcloud providers and some of the bigger ones will
definitely be interested in this.
And this is also something that might be interesting for service providers, like for telephone
providers, for example, telecom, mobile, photo phone, those guys might be interested in this
as well to provide this to their customers.
Because until now, you know, with own cloud and now Nextcloud, you couldn't really do
this because you couldn't get 50 million, 10 million users on a single system, right?
I mean, that wouldn't really work well.
And with global scale, you can actually do this now.
So that's really a nice step forward.
Another nice thing, because you were asking about what this does for home users, another
nice thing is this lookup server, because we already had a lookup server, a more limited
lookup server.
And the idea of the lookup server was always to allow you to store your federated cloud
ID and maybe some personal data that you choose, for example, your Twitter account, so that
people could look up what your federated cloud ID is, so they can share with you, it's like
an email address, they could look it up on the lookup server.
They say, oh, I know this guy's, you know, I know Chris Lust, that's his Twitter account,
you know, you look it up, and then you get your federated cloud sharing ID, and then
they can share files with you.
That's cool.
Yeah.
Huh.
So this is all in beta right now, yes?
It's all still kind of...
Yeah, beta is a good term for it.
I mean, we're putting all the pieces together now.
But we want the people to talk about this, to help us test it, you know, to get involved
with this, to give feedback on it.
And the core Nextcloud 12 release is out and solid, sounds like a lot of folks are already
jumping on and doing the upgrade.
Oh, yeah, it's totally, it's really cool, actually.
I tweeted earlier today, you know, it's so nice to see so many people say, like, yeah,
you know, we're upgraded, and it was totally smooth, as I've gotten used to.
That's great.
Now, you might remember in the old days, it wasn't always like that.
And I haven't seen a single person complain about upgrades yet, except one person was
really angry on the forums because an upgrade from beta 1 to beta 2 didn't work well.
Now, I personally take it as a compliment that the only fault you can find is in a pre-release
version.
You know, so yeah, this is really nice to see that we really managed to get the update
and upgrade issues under control.
I gotta say, I really like seeing, as far as security goes, I like seeing rate limiting
in there, which is kind of nice for developers to be able to specify, like, yeah, certain
rate limits based on IP range and time periods.
And looks like some improvements to two-factor authentication, support for other authentication
mechanisms like OpenID and OAuth 2 and Kerberos.
That's all pretty solid stuff, Joss.
Yeah, it's full of really cool features.
I mean, you have a lot of functions, like the guest app, you know, you can create a
temporary restricted account to a customer or a friend or a partner to share data with.
You have an app that can, well, we're working on a backup app now.
A lot of users will probably be very happy to hear that.
It's Frank himself who started to code that together at the last Hack Week.
Awesome.
So that's really, really cool.
And then we have the Circles app, which is, it's like user defined groups, you know, you
can create your own groups of people that you share with a lot.
And one thing that its developer is already working on is to make it then possible to
also just share your mood, you know, like a status update.
And at that point, then people who would follow you as part of a circle, because people can
join circles and leave circles, they can see status updates.
I mean, you all know where this is going, right?
That's really cool stuff.
Huh.
Interesting.
That'll be something to watch for.
See where that develops.
Boy, I mean, you guys don't have enough things you're taking on?
No kidding.
Yeah, the thing is, we have all the pieces already, right?
We have this federation.
This just kind of piggies back on it.
Like with Nexlot 12, one of the little changes to federation that comes together with other
stuff is that we are now federating activities.
So if you federate a file, you share a file from one Nexlot server to another server,
and then on the other server it gets changed by the recipient, then you will see that in
your activity feed now.
Oh yeah.
Wow, that's cool.
Yeah.
And once we have this like metadata sharing between servers in place, well, it's completely
trivial.
It's just a small number of lines of code to also share non-file related events, which
would be like Moot, right?
It's actually quite a simple thing to just inject something else in there.
So we're building this infrastructure and we're just using it.
Yeah.
And actually, as you were talking, I was thinking that very thing, and it just seems to all
make sense.
It seems like a good direction to go.
And it seems like functionality that will make sharing between Nexcloud servers even
easier.
Yeah, I mean, Nexcloud is like a core part of the lifeblood of my system.
It could be like the utility of file sharing and collaboration that now different vendors
could provide and you as a user could move between, it sounds like, with pretty...
Yeah.
So vendor lock-in, right?
We just kind of kill vendor lock-in with this stuff.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Provider lock-in.
That's really interesting.
Well...
Yeah, yeah.
This is really quite awesome.
Another thing that I don't want to...
Yeah, I want to make sure we don't miss it, is the audio and video calls, right?
We introduced this as kind of a tech preview in 11, and in 12, it's becoming really solid.
We use it now internally for our company calls every week, and it's working really, really
well.
And you can now share your screen, so screen sharing is built in.
That's kind of the one big feature.
But there's one other feature that we're working on, which is already part of the server side,
but it's not yet published in the client, it's coming.
This is push notifications.
So on your cloud, you can call somebody, and then they'll actually get that call on their
phone real time as a push notification, so you can actually really use it to replace
WhatsApp or Signal or whatever you're using to call people, right?
It's peer-to-peer, private, yeah, that's all there.
So we're working on integrating that in the clients.
And one of the things that we want to do in time is also to federate these calls.
So you have one server, and you can call a user on another server.
Combine it with a lookup server, and suddenly you have a completely decentralized audio-video
call system from Nextcloud servers all over the world.
So we've gone from documents and simple files all the way to a full, crazy, enterprise-ready
VoIP system.
This is a wild ride.
Yeah, and screen sharing, too.
That's pretty cool.
Yeah, the cool thing is people ask for this, right?
I mean, in 2005, 2010, you know, you would share files and have them on multiple servers
or multiple devices, you know, your phone, your desktop.
That was awesome.
But, you know, if you receive a file from someone, it's shared by them, what's missing
is context.
You know, normally you would have sent an email and you would say, hey, I need you to
review this.
But if you share it via Dropbox or Nextcloud, you miss context, so we added commands.
But then, you know, you see in a command that somebody says, well, this file, this is completely
stupid.
And then you want to call, right?
You don't want to have a whole yelling session in the chat.
That doesn't work.
So we need to be able to call.
And then, you know, you say, okay, let's just make this document right together.
You want to have a collaborative editing solution.
We got that, too.
So this is kind of a natural progression that you start to need all these pieces coming
together.
Yeah.
Yeah, and you can see some of the areas that we're using other tools, maybe commercial
tools at that, that are getting really popular right now that can do some of this stuff.
But there's not a big gap where if you just add a few more of these things to Nextcloud,
it can do all of the stuff those can do and a lot more.
And it's much, much, much more under user's control.
You could obviously take advantage of the fact that it's open source.
I mean, it's all the stuff with monitoring and the management options.
Yeah.
With the recent features, too.
I mean, what really, really exciting stuff.
Yes.
Thank you for coming on the show.
And hey, my pleasure, guys.
It's always nice to present what we're doing to you guys.
I mean, it's exciting stuff.
And I'm always glad that you guys see it for what it's worth and like it.
So I got to tell you, too, it's obvious you guys are hustling over there, too.
So really, a lot of respect, too, for how hard you guys are working.
If I'm picking up just even half of what you're putting down, it seems like you guys have
got a real vision on something you can go after and something that you're actually already
executing on.
Yeah.
I mean, they started seven years, seven and a half years ago.
And on one hand, it's the same vision, and on the other hand, it has evolved since then.
Right?
I mean, it started just to give people a way to control their data.
Well, OK, now we add collaboration and communication to it, but it's still the key is the same.
And the approach is the same, right?
Super easy to use, super like try to make it reliable first before you add the whole
kitchen sink to it.
I mean, these things have always been what we did, and then we keep doing that.
And it's working.
People love it.
It is essentially a visioning of how this technology could be used if it worked out
the way we all wanted it to work out.
Instead of having these things locked off with vendor lock-in and cloud lock-in, it's
the opposite of that.
It's the ideal version of how we could have done this, and it's really nice to see.
Not only, by the way, is all this technical stuff impressive, but the UI is looking great,
performance is looking great, security is getting better all the time, too.
So it's really kind of just firing on all cylinders.
And guys, check out all of the info about the new release.
We have it all in the show notes, Nextcloud 12.
There's links to blog posts and all of that stuff.
Yos, is there anything else you want to toss in before we roll?
Yeah, somebody on the chat is just pointing out that I should really say something, not
an incur image I just shared.
So one big annoyance of a lot of sys admins that would upgrade Nextcloud and before, obviously,
is that you have to re-enable the apps always.
We fixed it.
So if you have PHP 7 and you upgrade your Nextcloud, you don't need to re-enable apps.
Nextcloud will automatically check if they are compatible.
If not, it will try to update them from the app store, and after that, re-enable them
again.
Hallelujah.
Brilliant.
Very nice.
That's great.
Yeah.
That's those little things that make a big difference.
On the other hand, the fact that this was kind of one of the major issues that people
still had with Nextcloud does tell you how far we've come.
That's true.
It's a good problem.
If that's your problem, it's a good one to have.
All right, thank you.
Thank you, Yos.
Thank you very, very much.
Thank you for having me.
Bye, guys.
Have a good show.
Thank you, sir.
We're going to talk a little bit about the magic device tool here in just a moment, and
I couldn't think of a better time to mention Ting.
Two things that would go great together, like peanut butter and jelly, or peanut butter
and chocolate.
Ting is a smarter way to do mobile.
It's how we'd have to do mobile today if we just all of a sudden had mobile service.
If everything was equal and the carriers had to compete fairly.
You're dreaming.
I know.
But this is how it would work.
It would be $6 for your line.
You just pay for your line, and then it would just be your usage.
Just whatever you use.
That's how the market would work.
There'd be no contracts or agreements, no early termination fees.
You just buy the device, you choose if you want CDMA or GSM, and you'd pay for what you
use.
That's Ting.
That's how Ting does it.
It's a smarter way to do mobile.
One of the things I love about it is there are months where I am antisocial, and I really
do not pay much.
There's some months, maybe like Linux Fest Northwest month.
I might have a $45 bill that month, and then the month after that, because I am so done
talking to people, I might have a $20 bill.
It's really nice.
At the end of the year, I end up saving like $2,000 compared to my other service plans
I had before I switched.
It's incredible.
Linux.ting.com is where you go to save $25 off a device, or if you have a device that
works with Ting, $25 in service credit.
What?
The average bill is just $23 per line, so if you get $25 in service credit, it's going
to pay for more than your first month of service.
That's crazy, because not only do they have nationwide coverage, no contracts, it's paid
for what you use, and they have a great dashboard, but they also have fantastic customer service
and a great range of devices.
From ones you can bring yourself, pick up from the Play Store, or buy, they even will
help you find one if you contact their customer service.
I got to say, probably the best ever customer service experience I've ever had was when
I've called Ting.
They also have a little giveaway going on right now.
If you describe your home screen in a haiku, the home screen of your phone, they're doing
a giveaway.
Ting credit, maybe a Moto G5, things like that, you can find out details at the Ting
blog.
Just do me a favor.
First, go to linux.ting.com, and then head out from there.
Check it out.
See how much you might save.
That's such a better way to do mobile.
It's really, really, really fantastic for $6 a month to have a couple of GSM or CDMA
lines that you can activate devices for testing.
It's a great way to test devices.
It's a handy way to keep something connected, like say a tablet that you use with your drone
or something like that.
I just love it.
It's so handy, all the different ways.
Linux.ting.com, and a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Now, Marius joins us from way over across the world, where he is way, way... Let me
look.
I thought I had the clock up here, but I think it's like 11 o'clock, 11 PM.
Yikes.
Thanks for staying up.
Yeah.
Marius, welcome.
Is it Marius?
Am I saying your name right?
Make sure I don't mess it up too long.
You can say Marius or Marius.
That's fine.
Thank you for having me.
All right.
I'm sure they couldn't make it last week.
No problem.
It gave me a chance to mess around with Magic Device Tool, which I was pleasantly surprised
to see that all of the dependencies are in the AUR, and it's also a very easy snap to
install.
And if you have Ubuntu, it's just a couple of app commands away to get all the essential
files and dependencies you need to be able to flash any of the more recent BQ Aquarius
devices we've talked about, like the E5 or the M10, the Nexus 4, Nexus 5, Nexus 7 2013,
Samsung Nexus 10, the OnePlus One, the Fairphone 2, any of these devices.
Of course, I have the Nexus 5.
You have made a tool that essentially makes these devices relevant again.
I mean, it really does.
And I just I wanted to bring you on just for a little bit to talk about how the hell are
you doing this and how can we help you do it more?
So let's start with the first one.
How are you doing this Blackmagic?
How are you hacking my phone and replacing the very secure and safe image on there with
Cyanogen or Lineage or Maroo or even that there Ubuntu Touch?
What Blackmagic are you using, sir?
So I have to tell you a bit of a story back then from the history of Magic Device Tool.
When we started it back in or when I started it back in July 2016, I had like all of this,
all of the Ubuntu Touch devices that were out there back in the time.
And yeah, I wanted to make it easy to flash Ubuntu on it.
And but I also was one of the guys who got really annoyed by Ubuntu after a short time
and wanted to get back on the Synergy Mod or on Lineage, no Lineage came later, but still.
And yeah, I was tired of doing all the fastboot and ADB commands and I was like, okay, you're
going to write a script which is going to do all of this automatically.
And then I added a few other devices and then it kind of exploded.
And now I'm sitting here with, let me count, I think over 10 devices sitting on my desk
at the moment.
All of them are charging.
And I basically after every new release of whatever ROM I have to check if the update
is still working and if it's still compatible with magic device to it.
So it's a constant process.
So I imagine you probably have a few micro USB cables around your house.
Yeah, I would say too many.
Well, it's pretty cool tool.
And I kind of wanted to pick your brain a little bit about how people are using it today.
Because it seems to me that I found out about it because I was reading a thread on Lineage
OS.
I had heard of it obviously before, but it came back up on my radar when I was reading
a thread about Lineage OS.
Seems to me there's a lot of folks that want to use this to flash Lineage OS on their device.
So how is it being used today versus how it was originally envisioned?
Well back when we started it, it was obviously mostly used for flashing Ubuntu on it or
making backups or some of the other functions.
But yeah, thanks to the recent news by Canonical, many of the former Ubuntu people now got back
on the telegram chat and started asking questions about how they could get back on to Lineage
or to AOSP.
And yeah, unfortunately I can't really track how many of the watch functions are mostly
get used.
I can only see the current download numbers from the snap.
But I think it's mostly Lineage OS in the last few months.
So you know, what are the things that I would say if I had my critical hat on is I would
say things like there's only a very small fraction of the user base that's ever going
to want to install Lineage OS or Maru, which also looks very cool, or Ubuntu Touch.
This is just something that only nerds want to do.
Marius, what are your thoughts on that?
And what are your thoughts on sort of working on something that's sort of on the fringe
like this?
Do you think it's an uphill battle or do you find a purpose in it?
Well, it basically makes my life much easier because sometimes I'm just switching devices
because thanks to the Ubuntu Project I have so many things on my desk and sometime or
someday I just pick up the Nexus 4 or the Nexus 7 and decide that that's going to be
my daily phone or tablet for that week.
Yeah, it's still usable and relevant.
It absolutely is, yeah.
And we've also recently added other ROMs to it like Maru OS and what's it called, Phoenix
OS, which is a bit like Remix OS but for more devices.
And yeah, it's basically just, well, if other people wouldn't say that they're using it
and we just recently passed 10,000 downloads from the Snap Store from Edge Device to it
so people are clearly using it, I also would have just bought it for myself, which is basically
how it started.
Yeah, that's totally understandable.
So I really found it valuable because I'm like, I have this Nexus 5 here.
My kids would love to have another device to play around on.
Why not flash it with Lineage or Maru or just play around with Sailfish again?
Make the device totally relevant again and make it usable and the performance is surprisingly
good.
It's totally usable.
And a lot of these devices you have otherwise, I mean, my mom has a Nexus 5.
She bought it six months ago so it was otherwise brand new still and it works fine for her
but I want her to have some, I might even want to customize it more.
I think also, like you were talking about, sure, there's some niche aspect to this but
this tool really bridges the gap for like, if you were even considering trying it, suddenly
you have to become like kind of an Android expert.
Not so if you have something like this.
That's why I really liked it.
Yeah, it really didn't exist before.
I had no interest in like all the other stuff you'd have to learn but just to try it really
quick on an old Nexus 5 I had sitting around, it was the perfect level of resistance.
It was okay, I could manage to make this work, especially because all the stuff I needed
was in the AUR too.
Yes.
It made it pretty nice.
Marius, can we talk a little bit about the Snap process?
Is that something you were involved in and what's your impression been so far?
Well, I think we've moved, to have to start with, the magic device tool was a few months
before still adjust a batch script which we had to start manually and then I think it
was like four months ago, Canonical started promoting the Snapcraft tool.
So basically just this little one command line tool which makes it easy to create your
snaps and to upload them to the store and I was thinking with it for I think one evening
and the end result that I got was almost perfectly working and then we refined it and so it's
very easy.
Every change that we are pushing to the Git repository gets automatically picked up by
the Launchpad servers which are then going to build the Snap and then re-uploading them
to the store so I basically just have to commit to the Git repository and then everything
gets done automatically.
It all just happens after that.
That is the way of the future, I swear, that's so great.
If I could just interject, what Marius is using, if you go to build.snapcraft.io, you
can connect your GitHub repository to our build farm which in turn is connected to the
store.
So every time there's a commit in GitHub, the Snap is built on all of the architectures
in the build farm, so that's all of the ARM architectures and all of the Intel architectures
and some of the more exotic ones if you choose them and then gets published into the Edge
channel in the store and this is how Rekai hooked up Castor Soundboard to the Snap store.
That is great.
So Castor Soundboard is going to be a Snap.
That's good.
Beautiful.
That is really cool.
And you mentioned earlier, I was listening, you said AIF doesn't play when you were doing
things and you had to convert it in Sound Converter.
So I've updated the Snap to add the necessary codecs so AIF works in the Snap.
True gentleman.
A true gentleman.
This is pretty great.
I love seeing this stuff come together as these Snap packages.
There was another, oh yeah, Visual Studio Code was announced this week as a Snap package.
That's right.
Yes, it was.
So that's this.
It's a pretty interesting range from a very high-end GUI application to a command line
tool that will flash a smartphone to a Visual Studio Code editing tool.
Wow, that's a big range.
So Mariusz, where do you go next?
I know one of the top questions people always ask is, what do I got to do to get this XYZ
hardware supported?
Exactly.
So where do you guys go next in terms of the project and in terms of hardware support?
Well, as I said, most of the emails that I'm getting like 10 or 15 emails per day which
is like, please support device X and I have to reply, no, it's not meting the requirements
of our guidelines that we have set up.
But still, what we are going to do next is, I definitely have to mention this because
Max was also listening to this live, was just messaging me.
He basically rewrote the whole tool and he's a friend of mine, he's working on a community
project that I'm involved with and he basically completely rewrote the magic device tool and
the new release that will come out I hope next month will feature a completely QT GUI
so it will no longer be, well, it can still be a command line tool but it will also come
with a GUI soon and we will maybe refine the process of how to add new devices and make
it a bit more modular so that other people can contribute to it which is already happening
but I think we can do better on that front.
Yeah, it seems like there's more interest now than ever.
Yeah, absolutely.
There you go, and if you guys want to check it out, we have links in the show notes.
If you just Google magic device tool though, it's like the first thing that comes up.
Oh, Wimpy, you wanted to jump in.
Maybe let me plug one thing real quick.
We also have got a Telegram group which is basically an update and support channel and
where you can ask questions and it's magicdevice tool.com slash Telegram.
Oh, easy peasy.
So easy.
Yeah.
Yeah, magicdevice tool.com slash Telegram.
Exactly.
Now, Wimpy, you wanted to jump in on something, go ahead.
I was just looking at the store statistics and I was bowled over.
Do you realize how many installs you've had, Mariusz?
I know.
We've recently passed 10,000 downloads.
Yeah, over 10,000 snap installs.
That's awesome.
I'm one of them.
I have no idea who these people are but I'm glad to have found that the thing that I produce
is useful.
Well, you know, I really think it's just about anybody who's not on Ubuntu that wants magic
device tool.
That could be, yeah.
I think that's really what it is because the first thing I thought of was, well, I could
try getting these, I could try these things in the AUR or I'll just go grab the snap.
And that's what I did.
So I would imagine there's probably a lot of other people there too.
It's super handy.
It really is.
Yeah.
I love it.
Maybe let me add real quick to the point that Wimpy had before.
I'm definitely, I wouldn't consider myself to be a coder or a developer at all.
But still, with the batch scripts and the SnapCraft things that I did behind the scenes
and with the SnapCraft Builders tool that is also up on Git, it was really, really easy
for me to snap it in just one evening or two to make it completely run in like two days.
And definitely for the non-developer kind of you, it's really awesome.
Awesome.
That's a great field report.
Yeah, that is.
Thank you.
Thank you, Mariusz.
Thank you very much.
Mariusz, I was curious, what's your daily driver?
Is it a Linux desktop?
Is it Unity?
Is it an Ubuntu system?
I'm still on Unity.
Yeah.
I'm currently using 16.04.
Hashtag no judgment here.
This is a no judgment zone.
You're welcome to use...
At least today.
Yeah.
I wouldn't call him out, but Terz in the chat room is totally using Windows right now and
it's no judgment zone.
You're using Unity.
Wes over here is using...
What are you using?
Budgie?
I forgot what you're using.
It was Budgie for a while right now.
It's Gnome.
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
That's what I'm on too.
I'm on Gnome.
I'm on Gnome and I have some thoughts on that, but I want to let Minimac jump in with Mariusz
before we move on.
Minimac, go ahead.
Yeah, Mariusz.
And do you touch the partitions of the phone when you're flashing the images?
Do you change the partition tables or does it always stay the same?
Well, I'm technically not changing the partition tables or the formats itself, but sometimes
I have to...
If I have to flash, for example, Sailfish on it, then I have to preformat the system
image, but I'm not changing anything about the partition layouts.
I'm just formatting the partition itself.
Okay.
Thanks.
So it'll stay the same.
You're welcome.
Yeah, that's a great question, Minimac.
Thank you for asking it.
All right.
Well, so Mariusz, keep up the fantastic work.
Thank you for staying up late, and if there's other developments down the road that happened
that you want to share with the class, you are welcome to join our virtual Lug on a Tuesday
and share with us.
Or if you just can't sleep that night, we'll be here.
We'll keep a chair out for you.
Thanks for having me, guys.
All right.
Very good.
So I do want to talk a little bit about Gnome.
Not a lot.
I know.
I won't...
You know what?
I know.
Just a hint.
I'm just warning you.
I know not all of you are big Gnome fans, so first, let's talk about DigitalOcean.
Then if you don't want to talk about Gnome, you can leave.
But first, let me tell you about DigitalOcean, because I know that's really what you tuned
in for.
It's what I tuned in for.
DigitalOcean is my go-to platform now for when I need infrastructure.
Essentially, if I need a Linux rig and it doesn't need a screen hooked up directly to
it all the time, I'm pretty much just default DigitalOcean.
I'm default DO.
Oh!
Default DO.
DigitalOcean.com.
Go there.
Create an account.
So sign up.
I know I'm asking a lot, but trust me.
You're going to use it.
Create an account, and then apply our promo code.
It's like taking gasoline and putting it on top of your barbecue.
It makes everything taste better.
DO Unplugged.
One word, lowercase, and then it makes that fire go like crazy.
Plus, it's like a barbecue in the cloud.
Yeah.
Oh, shoot.
We've got to talk about our barbecue coming up.
Yeah, that's true.
I forgot about that, too.
It's not in the cloud.
Go back to it.
No, but first, before we get talking about barbecue, let's talk about cooking in the
cloud.
DigitalOcean.com.
Use the promo code DO Unplugged, SSDs throughout so you get really fast disk I.O., 40 gigabit
e-connections to the hypervisor so your network performance is great.
Linux is the host operating system, KVM for the virtualizer.
You can do huge rigs, super, super high-end rigs, crazy, crazy, monstrous, monstrous high-end
rigs, rigs that would make 64 kilobytes of RAM Bill Gates' mind explode with the insanity
in their size.
And they also have a CDN system built in, monitoring.
They have been integrating more and more features.
My favorite one is block storage, and then, like the cherry on top, they have the best
damn documentation on the web.
Check it out at DigitalOcean.com, create an account, use our promo code DO Unplugged,
get deployed in seconds, enjoy that SSD performance, work with teams, have a little block storage
when you need a little extra storage, and deploy a pre-built open source application.
DigitalOcean.com, use our promo code DO Unplugged, and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring
the shenanigans that is the Unplugged program.
So Mr. West, we're almost at 200 episodes of the Unplugged program.
That is crazy.
And I've been trying to think of what we should do.
What should we do?
Because I'd love to do something.
And one thing that turned out, oh, now iQIYI shows up.
Now iQIYI shows up.
See how that...
He heard us talking about him.
Yeah, that's true.
But I think there was some sort of transmission delay, because we were talking about his fantastic
blog post a while ago.
Anyways...
The iQIYI signal, it's on the fritz.
Come on.
I think there was some fog or something that delayed it.
So I don't know how long ago it was, but we did a barbecue, and Wes showed up.
And basically, we made out during the bar... No, oh geez, that was somebody else.
You weren't supposed to say it.
I know.
But anyways, Wes showed up for the barbecue, and things just went from there, and now here
he is doing a show.
And that was pretty fun.
I don't think that's going to happen this time, but I still thought we could kind of
have a tradition where, when the show has milestones, we have a community meetup.
I love that idea.
Like, you know, we have these extra chairs here in the studio.
It's perfect now.
So even if a couple of... Even if only a couple of people could make it, because it's
the middle of the weekday, but even if only a couple of people could make it up here in
Podunk Arlington, they could be sitting in these big, comfy, red chairs, and they could
be part of our lug right here in the studio doing the show with us.
That could be just a super awesome way to celebrate 200.
But I feel like we need to give people a few weeks more heads up.
Yeah, I think so too.
So we were thinking it's possible around the 4th of July, because we will have an Unplugged
program on the 4th of July.
And I was planning to go to Montana for the 4th of July, but Noah ruins everything.
That guy.
Totally Noah's fault.
So I think instead we could have a barbecue.
That might be a lot of fun.
It's going to be, well, it'll be a few weeks after our 200th episode, but it seems like
a pretty good opportunity.
Maybe that's more fair too, because what if 200, what if it goes terribly, or the internet
dies?
So it's better to have past 200, we've proved that we did it, and then we can all celebrate.
Yeah, that would be probably the best.
So that's sort of our tentative plan.
So there you go, Ike, you got your heads up and I travel out here now.
All the burgers you can eat.
No, that's true, yeah.
But if you do want to come out for our 200th birthday and celebrate on the 4th of July,
which will be weeks and weeks after, because we're only like two weeks away, it's going
to be literally a month after our 200th episode, but it'll be fun.
It seems like because it could be a good chance people might have the day off from work, and
it turns out my boss never lets me have the day off, so I'll be here, and might as well
be cooking.
Yeah, exactly.
And we could fit a couple people in here, plus we have the TV in the living room hooked
up, so you could watch from the living room, you could watch the show live, and so even
if you couldn't make, even if you can't fit in the studio, we'd have room for you in the
living room to watch the show, and you basically would get fed by us.
Seems like a pretty good deal.
It seems great.
So we'll have more details.
If you would be interested, contact me at ChrisLAS, and we're thinking on the 4th of
July to celebrate the 200th episode of the Unplugged program.
Yeah, my boss is a bozo.
That's true.
Yeah, he's a real jerk.
He's a real jerk.
So I wanted to discuss, just with anybody in the Mumble Room that maybe has a little
experience, and I thought maybe I'd start with Wimpy, because I suspect maybe he's played
around with this, maybe under Matei.
I'm not really an expert on the plumbing of Gnome.
My basic understanding is you have the Gnome shell, which then uses Mutter in the current
configuration to do essentially the compositing, and Mutter talks to X.
And in the Wayland setup, if I'm understanding this correctly, Mutter takes on more of the
X server roles.
It does the mouse tracking, all the stuff that the X server would traditionally do.
And I don't know where these problems lie, but I've been recently having... I'm going
to talk more about it on User Air, because I'm doing a deep dive right now.
So tune into User Air this week, where I'm chasing bug reports, and I'm doing all this
stuff.
So I'll have a full report later.
But I've been noticing.
I wanted to just check in with the virtual log, and I wanted to check in with you, Wes.
Is it just me, or if your system's been up for a couple of weeks, does Gnome 3 start
to slow down to a crawl over time?
Has anybody else noticed this?
I have not, but I don't have any systems that are up that long that have a desktop that
don't get rebooted or suspended.
So I don't know if I have that exact use case.
But I've seen it here happen at the studio, so I can definitely confirm that it's happening.
Yeah.
Actually, earlier in the show today, we just had Gnome 3 crash on us, and we had to stop
recording and start again, because we weren't sure if we lost part of the recording.
That's no good.
We could lose audio on the stream while Gnome 3 crashed for some reason.
Wimpy, have you played around at all with benchmarking Gnome or looked at the performance
of this stuff?
Not a great deal, no.
I have done some work to integrate MUTTA with MATE to see how that works.
And aside from key bindings not passing through, and what was the other?
The alt-tab and alt-grave implementation just doesn't work the same as you would expect.
So it works, but I've not done any serious profiling.
I am at the moment doing some power profiling on the different compositors to see what the
additional power draw is on the different compositors, but I have not concluded that
yet.
OK.
Yeah, that's a whole other aspect of it, too, is when you do have a system like this,
what kind of difference do the different compositors make on the CPU or GPU usage and the power
draw that they have?
That's a fascinating conversation, probably for a future show.
This is something I'm wondering about because I did not notice this under Plasma.
So just a little background for those of you who don't catch every episode is for weeks
and months, essentially since the last release of the Plasma desktop, I've been running the
Plasma desktop on my main workstation.
This is a machine that I leave on 24-7.
I've even recently started leaving the monitors on at lower brightness, so that way I can
literally just... I walk in the room, I sit down, I start working immediately, and...
The studio's always on.
The Plasma desktop never ran into this issue, at least not that I noticed.
I probably never made it more than two months without rebooting, because I usually just
decide, OK, it's time to get a new kernel.
But I definitely am noticing it within a couple of weeks, really, even a week on GNOME, and
on all of the machines in the studio that we've switched over to Linux that are running
GNOME are exhibiting these symptoms.
Really?
So it's something I'm trying to dig into.
It's not just a one-off on one machine.
I can't swap out mutter, right?
That's not something I can just... I can't just do that.
I can't swap out mutter for kwin or something.
Back in GNOME 2 days, you could do some crazy shit like that, but I don't think you can
do that with GNOME Shell.
So anyways, if anybody has any more information on it, I would like your help, tweet me at
chrislas or check out the new subreddit, linuxunplugged.reddit.com.
Sounds like Ikey's got a take on it, too.
I was reading his take in the chatroom, which is pretty interesting.
And that's what some of the bug reports that I've been digging into have been saying, too,
Ikey.
If you want to participate in our chatroom, we do this show live on Tuesdays at 2 p.m.
over at jblive.tv.
You can get it converted to your local time at jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendars.
Like Marius there, he has to sit there and do the time math.
We were chatting about it this morning.
I got you, Marius says, I hate time zones, and I'm like, I totally know what you mean.
We solved that already.
We have these robots on standby at jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
It will convert it to your local time.
If you think you could make the 4th of July work, which I know is a little crazy, but
if you think you could make it work, let me know.
I don't know for sure we're going to do it, but I think it's like a 90% lock.
And if we got a few people saying they'd be down, I mean, you and I are going to be here
anyways.
Yeah, we will.
We should probably, regardless if people show up or not, have that barbecue going on the
4th of July.
So I almost feel like it's all lined up perfectly, so we should just do it.
I think it's a lock.
I think I'm going to say it's a lock.
Yeah, if we don't barbecue on the 4th of July, then what are we doing?
I know.
I think I'm going to say it's a lock.
And basically, if you guys want to show up while Wes and I are cooking out and the beard's
here eating our burgers.
Then please do.
Yeah, yeah.
It's one of your few opportunities to see the beard in person doing his thing.
Yeah.
Now that means I'll have to tell people how to get here and all that.
We'll have all that information.
But yeah, okay.
All right.
I think we're going to call it a lock.
Wimpy, I'll expect you here, of course, obviously, I'm sure you'll fly out.
Marius, I'm sure you'll fly out.
Ike, I expect you guys all to make it here.
Should be no problem.
I'm sure everybody in the mumble room will just make it.
I mean, you know, it should be no problem at all.
What was the date?
The 4th of July, right?
America Day.
Don't you want to come out for America Day?
No, I might be in the area the week after that.
You know, Ike, if you make it, we'll have a wet t-shirt contest.
We might...
Oh, really, Wimpy?
Which is possible.
Hmm.
Well, yeah.
If you're in the area, let me know, I'd make a trip out to see you.
If you'd like to make a trip out to see us, go to jupitabroadcasting.com and grab a new
episode, usually Tuesday evenings, Wednesday morning, depending on your neck of the woods.
Don't forget we have the RSS feeds over there.
I did mention it, but I'll just say it again, linuxunplugged.reddit.com.
That's where you go to get involved in the conversation after the show and jupitabroadcasting.com
slash contact if you want to send us your feedback.
And Wes, are you ready for me to fire off the end of the show music with Caster Soundboard?
There it is.
That's it, right there.
That's so awesome, dude.
Now the show's ending.
You have such power.
That is incredible.
And I touched it right there.
It's a touch screen, and I'm watching it play across Caster Soundboard.
Now available as a Snap.
It's amazing.
So great.
Listen, we have a new show out, User Air.
Go check it out.
And Linux Action News, linuxactionnews.com and User Air at jupitabroadcasting.com.
Two great shows with more Linux content.
User Air, a little raunchier.
It's more for an adult audience.
Linux Action News, of course, is your hardcore take.
Super hardcore.
Really rough.
So hardcore.
It's OK.
No, it's not that at all.
All right.
Thank you for joining us.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
Say goodbye, Wes.
Goodbye.
Bye, everybody.
What are the chances that the week that you don't have to record TechSnap, we're done
super early?
How does this happen?
Yeah.
We got thrown off a little bit, I think, when Dome crashed.
So Ike, we really crapped on how ridiculous it is that you're shipping the plasma desktop
about how everybody in your project is going to burn out because of the diffusion of resources
and time and the chaotic state that the project must be finding itself in as a result of the
fragmentation of your desktop focus.
Did not say any of that.
Fair question.
Did not.
No.
I actually just think it's really cool.
And sounds like Peter's a cool dude.
Yeah.
That's pretty much what we said.
Accurate.
I will confirm.
I don't know, though.
I thought that was pretty good for coming off.
Let's see what kind of armchair bullshit internet criticism could I come up with if I just randomly
...
Let's troll as a service.
Thank you, Mumble Room.
You guys were great.
Marius, it was great to speak with you.
Yeah.
That was awesome.
Anytime, Chris.
Give me your phone, Chris.
It won't be bricked.
Just flash away.
Oh, I'm just kidding.
I got it.
See, I got him a little bit.
I got him a little bit.
That's good.
All right.
JBtitles.com.
JBtitles.
We covered your blog post about Plasma and all that.
Plasma.
Jeez.
Bitcoin is $2,200 right now.
$2,200.
That's crazy.
Did anybody else hear anything about Japan using Bitcoin or something about Japan making
it more official?
Yep.
We're going to talk a little bit about it in user error.
It's a good question.
Sweet.
Yes.
I can't buy things fast enough at the moment.
The rate that Bitcoin keeps going up in value.
It's gone up $400 in like six days or something.
Have you had any problem with the transaction fees being too low and your purchases not
getting verified in time?
I had a huge problem with that.
I thought I was crazy.
Yeah.
I had a problem with it too.
So I'd say half my transactions are Bitcoin transactions and half are transferring Bitcoin
to fiat currency and then using that to fund the purchase.
I had to do like a dollar something fee just to make sure it would go through.
I tried 50 cents.
I tried 60 cents.
I tried 70 cents.
I did them like, okay, a dollar?
What the hell?
It's just I think the network is super busy right now.
There you go, Ike.
There you go, boy.
Is this-
Yeah.
What is this?
Western Union?
Well, someone suggested in the Ubuntu podcast telegram group that how much an effect WannaCry
Bitcoin purchases are having on the price of Bitcoin at the moment, which was an interesting
point of view.
Ubuntupodcast.org.
They're still recording, so I'm going to put that in here right now.
After this show is over, what you should do is go get Ubuntupodcast.org.
Right away.
Then download Linux Action News and then download Ask Noah and then download User Air and then
if you're missing Ike, download Late Night Linux.