This can be one of those interesting episodes where we are gonna have people bailing from the mumble room and then joining back during the
Show because right now as we record red hat summit is happening and Carl you're manning a booth virtually right now
Yes, sir, the fedora in centOS chat room slash booth slash whatever you want to call it. That's awesome
And are you getting decent attendance? Oh, yeah on-demand created a fedora badge, which is like a little
little gamification thing that they do in the fedora community for attending and you just show up in there and let them know what
Your fedora account system username is and they'll give you the badge. Oh great. I was just about to ask, you know virtual booth
We need virtual swag. I was thinking the same thing. You know, this is like a different kind of summit, isn't it Neil?
I'm just glad it's happening at all because like I've been I've been kind of depressed with all the events that have been canceling throughout
The season and it's been nice to like at least get in listen to see what people are doing and and and chat with folks
In there and hey, this is the first summit where I technically maybe gave a talk. So that's cool
Yeah, and this year the concrete would be real bad and you're not gonna get that so that's a positive too. Oh, yeah
I'm gonna look forward to not being basically bedridden for a month again. Like I was last year. I gave it a go
I logged in I found it a little confusing but kind of like you I was just glad it was happening and I thought to myself
I really appreciate
The real Red Hat summit because when you go to the actual Red Hat summit
You really get an appreciation for how dialed in Red Hat has that game?
I've been to a lot of corporate events and they really have their summit game dialed in the virtual version. It's a little rough
Hello friends and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello, mr. Payne quite the show
We have for 351 packed too much. We never do it. Just right. We can't help ourselves because we have
So much to cover with a brand new fedora release and of course
There's things to follow up on the new Ubuntu 2004 releases
Well, we've had a little extra time with that
but as we said
We also gave the fedora 32 release a full try who could resist and I am happy to report that
Just after the show last week actually during the show. They attempted to deliver my system 76 limmer Pro
But they didn't really ring the doorbell
You I think they like dropped it off on the porch and like I don't want the kovat and ran off and didn't even try
But the next day I was like camped up by the door
There's a window in the studio living room where I can see the entryway. And so there I was with my phone in hand
Watching and they you know, sure enough knock knock on the door get the box
I open it up tried it out for a little bit and then the next day had to put fedora 32 on it
And I'll give you my impressions of what it's like in the next week
We'll have the review
But before we get into that before we get into the review of fedora 32 the follow-up of Ubuntu 2004 the community news
I have to say
Time appropriate greetings to that mumble room. Hello virtual lug whenever you guys do that
I always watch it from a waveform perspective and it's very impressive visually I have to say hello everybody
It's a great showing in there
I know some of you may have to come and go as the summits going but
Special hello to Matt DM Matt from fedora is back. Hello Matthews. Good to have you on the show
Good to be here. Very glad you're here on fedora release day. Your timing is perfect sir
And mr. Martin whimpers glad to have you back sir. Hello. Hello. Happy release to you as well
Thank you very much. Good to be here
Well, so why don't we start with you wimpy because there was a tweet from your fingers on April 24th saying there's new
Features in the Ubuntu desktop that no one is talking about and I thought well, let's talk about them
And the one that I thought maybe we could start with but I'd love to just go anywhere with you on this
but the one I'd like to start with is
It appears that with 2004 you can get a Ubuntu certified device right away
Like we're not there's not this typical leg of months before OEM is certifying it. Is that true? It's not quite that
So the way that it works now is that in the past the only way you could get a certified device experience
which means the correct power endurance profiles the correct firmware for
Auxiliary devices the right drivers by default all that sort of thing was via the factory image that came pre-loaded
So what we've changed now is that when you do an install of the GA release of Ubuntu
2004 it can identify if it's on a certified device and
Automatically pull in all of that stuff that would have been in the pre-loaded factory image into the standard install
So if you've got a certified device, maybe you bought it pre-installed with Windows
And you want to dual boot Ubuntu alongside it or maybe you've decided to make the switch to Ubuntu
You'll get the factory
experience
Just from the GA ISO. That is so cool
Now there's a bunch of other things in here
We should talk about because one of the areas we didn't jump into was like the fingerprint stuff and I'm curious if there's other
Areas you feel like need a little more attention too. There are I mean the fingerprint stuff is interesting
That was another OEM request and that's more around the support of new biometrics devices, which
Mostly proprietary these days because they don't want people having sight of how the internals of those devices work
So we needed a way to bring those devices into you know, the Ubuntu desktop and the wider Linux desktop ecosystem
So we did some work with the three
Largest suppliers of those biometric devices to find a way where those can be enabled on the Linux desktop
so that was done in collaboration with the
LibFprint project and
Then also with the upstream GNOME design team who've got a new design
To improve the way you enroll your fingerprints and then do fingerprint unlock
So we don't have those new designs implemented in 2004, but they will land before
2004.1. That is very exciting and also just impressive the amount of sort of backroom dealings
You know working out arrangements and has to go on to actually make these user visible features happen
So what we've done is we've created a LibFprint compatible protocol shim that sits in front of these
proprietary drivers and translates the proprietary driver
Implementation into a LibFprint compatible protocol clever
Before we get to the the Scuttlebot. I've already seen over 2010
What else was missed in the coverage of 2004?
So I think it was subtle stuff that was more like a distro level rather than you know
actual features of the desktop itself and some of this work was work that you know, I
Was interested in doing a community level and it's stuff that predated
You know me coming back to the Ubuntu desktop team
But it's things like making sure that FFmpeg is NVENC and VAPI and OpenCL
Accelerated in the distro so that things like
OBS studio and the video editors and all the rest of it can exploit all of those
Acceleration for scrubbing through timelines using acceleration and doing you know hardware accelerated video encode and all the rest of it
Oh, that sounds great for folks who are you know new
I mean, I know how to compile those things in but that's a big blocker if you're just trying to make some content
Yeah, indeed and it was there in 1804
albeit with the older way that NVENC was exposed via FFmpeg and then because of changes in the FFmpeg project it
Fell away in subsequent releases and we wanted to bring that back
So, you know, it's stuff like that and you know uplifting Steam
So that all of the current crop of VR devices and controllers all work out of the box when you install Steam
You know a whole raft of work around improving quality of life for people that want to make videos or want to
livestream or want to play games and
That also extends to
Including ferals game mode Daemon. Yeah, this is interesting
It's something that I don't recall being super easy to actually get running during the beta
So I was surprised to see it in
2004 final maybe I was wrong about that
But I seem to recall early on in the process having some trouble actually getting game mode for 2004, right? So this was
The last feature we landed in Ubuntu desktop 2004. Okay
It landed release week. I think it landed on the Monday and we released on the Thursday
So it was very late coming but it was something if you look at the bug
Report for it. I think I started that process as like I think it's the first thing
I did when I took over from Will was actually start that process and it sat and it sounds like a trivial thing
Well game modes just a bit of software and it's just a package so that you just include it in the distro
but for everything that is in the Ubuntu desktop, it has to be in the main archive and
the main archive is traditionally the archive that gets all of the security support and
You know proactive security maintenance
So in order to get into that archive the security team have to conduct a manual security review and audit all of the code
Of course, and we also have to do packaging checks to make sure that you know, the upstream is active
They have the appropriate security reporting mechanisms
The health of the packaging of the software is correct its standards compliant and a whole bunch of things. So
we've gone through that process and again, if you look at the bug there, you will see references to the
the work that the security team did and the upstream conversations they had in
Ferals github around the security review that we did so, you know
There was a number of you know changes and updates that happened in order for it to land in main
Which I think happened a week before release and then subsequently get included in the image
So yeah, it wasn't in the beta but it's in the final release. Well while we're talking about gaming
there is one new touch that I didn't and I still haven't regretfully had a chance to try yet and that is if
People out there have hybrid graphics or like myself. I have an external eGPU that I've talked about before on this show
Well now you can right-click on an icon in the launcher, you know
Where you normally have like new window or add to favorites what you know the options you normally have in gnome shell
There's an option in there to launch using the dedicated graphics card. How the hell does this work?
How is this possible and and do all I have to do is just plug in my eGPU and this just shows up in
Gnome shell. Well, first of all, let's start the very beginning. This is an upstream gnome feature
It was first introduced in gnome
334 but it only worked with Intel and AMD drivers and what was added in
336 was support for Nvidia. If you've got an Nvidia Intel hybrid system
you need to be running the Nvidia proprietary drivers and
The Nvidia proprietary drivers need to be in on-demand mode
So you're choosing that mode where the Intel IGP is in use and is rendering the desktop and the Nvidia
GPU is in this low power state waiting to be used and
Although this is a feature that I think it's integrated in
GLib, I may be wrong about that, but I think it's in GLib
But essentially in order to run a process on a dedicated GPU
It's just the case of setting a few environment variables prior to launching the process
So what's happening behind the scenes is a few environment variables get inserted into the execution context
for the application that you've chosen to run when you right-click and say launch on dedicated GPU and
it puts the appropriate environment variables in there for if you're using an AMD graphics card or an Nvidia graphics card and then
Subsequently that process is now running with the full capability of that GPU
I've been doing that manually, you know on the terminal now for a while, but this is just such a level of
Finesse that it feels it feels special
It feels like something maybe just you'd normally see on the commercial operating systems
I mean, I have to say that GNOME 3.36 has just just just been a load of stuff
That's landed all at once that just makes it an outstanding version of GNOME
You know
there was lots of design refinement that I think was originally scoped out by the GNOME design team in
2017 and they've been slowly working towards and then loads of it landed in this cycle
So it's perfect time for you know us to be releasing an LTS because without doubt
This is the best GNOME shell ever very well said and that is going to echo in my fedora 32 review as well
It is the culmination of years of work that are landing in this version. What a what a perfect release for an LTS
Yeah, it really is. I mean, yeah, it's a fantastic GNOME shell release, you know without question
I'm curious if you have any other bits or thoughts on like the ZFS stuff or any early information on how that's going
It's too early to look at the adoption rate on that just yet, but it's stronger than 1910
So it'll be interesting to see how many people are opting into ZFS
but the big change there is the introduction of
Zsys, which is our integration layer that sits between
ZFS and Vuntu and so that's responsible for doing event driven snapshots and that's
mostly around if you do
large package installs or upgrades
Then snapshots ZFS snapshots are taken prior to those transactions being committed
So if an update goes bad restore points are automatically exposed in the grub boot venue
So you can simply choose to you know, boot into the point before that upgrade took place
And it really does work. That's what's so great. Is it really works? I it saved my bacon a couple of times during the beta
Fantastic. I'm glad to hear that's working for you. And this this lays the foundations for
more backup restore capabilities that we're going to be building
On top of that as we work towards 2204 wire guard
obviously it has been back ported to the 5.4 kernel in 2004, but you were mentioning on the pre pre show that
1804 users if they're sticking with 1804 eventually, they're gonna get wire guard back ported as well. That's right. So
As you'll be familiar we do point releases for the LTS is and the next
1804 point release will have another or a newer
Hardware enablement stack which will include effectively. What is the 5.4 kernel from
2004 and therefore by way of that you will get wire guard in
1804 so for those people that are wanting to use 1804 for the long term
Then you'll soon have wire guard built straight into the kernel. No DKMS modules
In fact, that's an interesting point because we're not using DKMS modules for things like wire guard or the Nvidia drivers even these days
So the Nvidia drivers are
Distributors late-linked binaries that are signed so you can leave secure boot enabled
Without you know, even with Nvidia drivers and wire guard turned on
Oh, it's just so nice every time you update, you know not having to worry about DKMS
The one disappointing part there is now what am I gonna do to you know, pressure people to move on to 1804
I can't hold wire guard over their head
Yeah, this is that Gnome 3.6 goodness. Gnome 3.6. Well any other spots you wanted to mention or bits of attention?
You wanted to shine a light on that's a pretty good list. The thing that I
Love above all other things about this release is the Yuru theme. It was
Absolutely fantastic getting together with the the four guys
Who are the sort of the core Yuru team?
we had them in the canonical offices in London in January and we had members of the
Ubuntu design team and desktop team and then hangers-on like me and poppy, you know cheering from the sidelines
and we had this week-long sprint and
completely changed the face of Ubuntu for this LTS and I have to say I'm very proud of
Their accomplishments and I love the new bold look
Even though it's unmistakably Ubuntu. It's it's you know, quite a change of direction. I absolutely love it
I think it's my favorite default theme so far and we were having a conversation in the Jupiter broadcasting telegram group
That a lot of us are loading it on other distros, too
and it is fairly straightforward to do that and it just looks so great and
I like the combination with the appearance setting in gnome settings where I can just go and it's one click and everything's dark
And it looks really nice. The reason it's easy to install on other distros is no mistake
that was actually a product of the design sprint based on feedback that we had from
Gwadek and the Linux applications summit, which is there are obviously developers who are using
Distributions that are not Ubuntu and they want to make sure that their applications look correct on
You know other distributions and the criticism is well, I don't use Ubuntu
So how can I check to see if my apps work fine on Ubuntu?
So we've made sure that the Yuru theme is packaged and available everywhere
It needs to be available so you can you know use that theme elsewhere to make sure everything's working, right?
Well, it is great. Congratulations to you the team and of course all the upstream developers it all came together
It's a great LTS. Thank you very much. I shall pass those words on please
Pass on a thank you to whoever is making the Raspberry Pi 4 support
so rocking awesome because
I've been running
2004 on my Raspberry Pi for a couple of weeks since before release upgraded right?
No problem to the final version now and because of the version of kernel that's on 2004
I can boot now from USB devices and my Raspberry Pi 4 feels like a real computer and
I'm running an LTS on there at the same time and it's a distribution that I understand and trust
I'm going all-in. I think I'm even gonna enroll them in landscape
So that way I can just basically manage them without having to really think about it. That'd be a solid idea really Dave Jones
Who has been in and around the Raspberry Pi community for years?
Was hired by canonical about 18 months ago, and he's been leading that effort to really
Deliver a first-class experience on the Raspberry Pi and I'm delighted to say we're in the middle of our product strategy planning sprint
For this, you know this week for what will become
2010 which is going to be the groovy gorilla and
We had our talk about
Raspberry Pi and I'm looking forward to everything to come in 2010
For Raspberry Pi users. Oh, man, you're gonna get me upgrading now on my pie. Jeez Louise. Well, it's a good problem to have
Well, great. Thank you for coming on and and covering some of that stuff and I hope you get some downtime now
I hope you're gonna be able to catch your breath soon. Yeah, I'm gonna hang up my boots for a week and you know
Go and sit in the garden and drink some champagne. Maybe well-deserved before we go
Mini Mac has one question for you, and I'm kind of interested to hear it. So go ahead Mini Mac. Let's get that in
Yeah, thank you. Wimpy on my 1804 Ubuntu box
I have signed into the canonical life patch service to get the kernel patches live patched in
But from time to time I had to reboot now I read that you did some work on that
Can you be a little bit more specific on that?
So livepatch is actually built on an upstream kernel implementation. So it's not our own thing
It's just leveraging what's upstream and all we've done is contribute to that upstream effort to improve it
But yes, livepatch is available in you know, limited numbers. I think it's like three or five machines
I think if you're an Ubuntu member
It's for 50 machines an Ubuntu member being somebody who is in the Ubuntu community
And has been recognized as somebody making a sustained commitment to the Ubuntu project
Then you get 50 activations. So, you know you all your home servers and your laptops
But it's basically like high and critical
CVEs in the kernel that you will get patched via livepatch where you don't require a reboot in order for them to take
How lucky are we to have both Wimpy and and Matt here today incredible Matt?
Congratulations on the announcement that there were soon will be ThinkPads shipping with Fedora
This is huge and people have been talking about it since the moment this announcement landed and it looks like we're getting several models
Off the bat. Yeah, what the ThinkPad p1 p53 and x1. Oh, yeah the x1. Yes
Yes, now I think this isn't too surprising if everyone listening remembers
Not too long ago. We announced that Lenovo was joining the Linux vendor firmware service
And I think a lot of us went well, I know there's a lot of Linux users that use them already
But I wonder if this is going somewhere bigger and I think maybe we're here
So this is a big moment for the project Matt and it's fantastic that it's ThinkPads from Lenovo
I am super super excited and Lenovo has been amazing to work with
They're really interested in doing things the open source way being part of the community not, you know
Not stepping on things and they really were interested in shipping
Yeah, the stock Fedora image without any modifications
Which is very exciting for us as well because we obviously work so hard to make that image good
Talk to me about their comfort level with the cadence of Fedora because it sounds like maybe that that stock image aspect of it would
Make it maybe fairly straightforward to just keep current on whatever the latest
So in 33 ships, for example, yeah, exactly. That's exactly what they're planning to do
They're already on a six-month cadence for Windows updates
So it's basically the same thing with all of their processes. So they were not really concerned with that at all
I'm surprised to hear that actually that's that's I didn't know they would be on that frequent of a cadence with Windows
But you know, it is the Windows 10 era. Well as we've been talking about right now Red Hat Summit's going on and
Mark P from Lenovo was in the Fedora and Centos community area and he said that right now
They've got these three platforms as a pilot, but he says that if things were say to go well
He could see it expanding to other platforms including desktops
Although I won't say the numbers I talked to them about you know
The number of sales that they want to make to feel like this was a success and it wasn't a crazy number
So I'm very optimistic that they're going to hit those targets and see this as success and we'll see more
Well, let me ask you a question
I mean would it be possible that going forward when Red Hat employees?
Maybe they get hired or it's time to replace their rig and they just get issued a machine
Could it potentially be now one of these could that count towards that sale number? Yeah, I assume so
We've been talking to our IT people about that. We Red Hat already has standardized on Lenovo laptops for their models
So we are going to be ordering these particular SKUs in the future
There may need to be some other models because like you said there are
These three select models and there may be use cases that Red Hat has that doesn't fit those SKUs
So we may order some other ones as well
But yeah that that should be it and I guess they have some other large customers that were interested in Fedora
It's where they're gonna demand for this came from their side that I hopefully will fill out a lot more of them as well
But of course all of you and all of your listeners, you know, please help out next time you have a laptop to buy
This is definitely a choice that you can make that will help
Yeah
I mean
I think a lot of people have been waiting for a long time for current ThinkPads that would just be preloaded with Linux and there's
Been various ways to get them over the years
But the nice thing about the sort of focus channel approach is that it's much easier for people who are kind of just in that
Shopping mode to kind of identify what they're getting, you know
I've noted for years now and that's pretty impressive to be able to actually meet that but for years
I've noted that the upgrade cycles on Fedora have been very painless. In fact, I
think I had a machine that
Had been upgrading from 22 and I brought it all the way up to 31
Before I finally gave up and said alright, it's working. I don't need to keep trying this
Do you think that has started to set in in the user base of Linux are people starting to get that that?
That you don't necessarily have to have a long-term support. You don't necessarily have to have rolling
There's a spot right here in the middle. I hope so. We've been focusing on that for a while
We're kind of going to give the give the benefits of the newer software that people get with the rolling release
but with a little more
predictability and the ability for us to do solid QA on it to make sure that each release is something that we feel proud to
Put our name on right, you know, I had a couple people tell me. Oh, I upgraded over lunch
Think it's kind of a sweet spot and I think we're doing a good job of hitting it
That along with having our actual release cycles be more predictable and making sure that you know
We can have the the Mother's Day Halloween releases every year and you can basically
You know plan around that happening and it's such a kind of a different world now for software availability
Availability both from from video driver standpoint for both AMD and video and Intel
but also just from a lot of the
applications where you use these universal package formats and they just sort of stick around and work just between upgrades so it also kind of
Abstracts that layer out. Alright, so I I gotta go back to the laptop and I got to ask a question that I think everybody listening
Is wondering do you have any insight on when these things are actually going to be able to be purchased?
Well, as I said on reddit, I know but I can't tell you and it's not because of lawyers
It's because of the marketing people who would like to have their big splash and I would not like to ruin that sure
And there's always there's some last things that they're going through to make sure all their regulatory
Compliance and everything is all signed off on and so it's possible there'll be delays or something
So I don't want to promise a date that isn't doesn't come true
But it really shouldn't be that long now sounds reasonable sounds like we don't have to wait too much longer
And there'll be news on it in the near future. It sounds like yeah, exactly
I bet this is great news, you know made me think of folks who maybe not don't have a lot of laptop choice
They're working for a larger IT organization and that organization wants to see this support from the manufacturer
So sure you could get a bunch of on Dell's but now there's a whole new world of options
Yeah, I know definitely when we joined Linux Academy, you know
They were looking at just a couple laptop options like system 76 and the XPS 13
Because if they were gonna if they were going to issue Linux laptops to employees
They wanted it to be supported by the OEM exactly
even if it meant that IT actually provides all of the support it just from almost like a
Not a due diligence standpoint, but from like a responsibility of purchasing if you're gonna spend
$1,800 to two grand on a machine you want it to be a supported configuration and have someone to yell at if it doesn't work
That's always nice
A lot of these laptops I someone on hacker news. Their first complaint was well
I was promised they'd have Ubuntu available and I can't buy it
and the fact is
Lenovo does ship Ubuntu and certified rail configurations on a number of their workstation class systems already
But they're not available to you unless you go through a very complicated
Channel process and are buying a whole bunch of them and you know
There's a lot of paperwork involved. And so this is very exciting because this will just be like when you go to buy one of these
Laptops, it'll be a drop down in the OS configurator
You'll be able to you know pick through our workstation right next to whatever version of Windows you could choose instead
I mean, I'm sure it's still having some scuttlebutt in discussion
But I think if Red Hat summit was in person right now and this news had just dropped it would be
One of the points of conversation amongst the attendees is this is this deal?
Yeah, we were hoping to have the Lenovo people there at the fedora booth with us
Obviously, I think the whole news cycles been just kind of disrupted and even your Red Hat summit not just going virtual
But it's kind of the tone of announcements and news and press. It's like this is not the time
So things are a lot more subdued. Yeah, on the other hand we had this in the works and we weren't gonna hide it
So I think people have noticed though. I think at least in our circles people have noticed
It's been getting a lot of conversation in our community channels
I think job done is probably not the perfect time to make that kind of announcement, but I think you got pretty close
Well, thank you Matt stick around we're gonna talk about fedora 32 here in a little bit. But first
Little housekeeping to do is as we do
If you know that we're doing this live, but you don't know when did you know that we have a solution West?
Did you do thanks to the magic of the Internet? Yeah, this is something that was brand new
So I don't blame you for never knowing about it. We've never mentioned it before on the show ever
It's Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar. Oh wait, what was that? Oh, hold on West
I'm getting I'm getting a note here from the been there for almost eight years. Oh, yeah
Well Jupiter broadcast and maybe I I probably I probably don't need to mention it Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar
I just realized how fast I say that Jupiter broadcasting comm Jupiter broadcasting comm slash
Calendar. Yeah, there you go
RSS feed for this show is that Linux unplug comm slash subscribe where you can get the feeds and put it in any pod catcher
You'll like if you'd like to join us in the telegram community. It's Jupiter broadcasting comm slash telegram and please do yes
And if you are an ACG subscriber a cloud guru has launched the cloud playgrounds for business customers
In the in the biz that term is called B to B
B to C is business to customer and B to B is business to business
The more you know, yeah, well you think about it you get into a place you need to skill up
It's actually a very very handy thing. Yeah, having good, you know training right there available from your employer
Hey hard to beat I am
Thrilled to say that we had another luck log on Sunday
Wes and I made it and cheesy was there and a whole bunch of folks in the mumble room were there
Neil was neck deep in a v-bolt and
instance and
Just ready to go and we talked about as the pine devices a little bit
We really got into some really cool his history stuff, too
We were really kind of talking about old Linux and just a great chat
I hung out for a couple hours then I don't know how long did anybody know how long it went after I left
About three hours after you left. Yeah, so that's fantastic. It's noon Pacific
Which is the same time we do this show on Tuesdays?
So we just take the Tuesday time and we put it on a Sunday. You see what we did there
It's very clever wasn't my idea keep it simple because otherwise I don't think you would remember when to show up
No, and you know what's weird about it is
the
Timing because that was when I recorded land on Sundays
And then the weekend that I would have been doing land
But I no longer had land the mumble was meeting and it was like, I don't know
I just like step from one to the other it was really deep your groove and now you got more community
Yeah, it's pretty great
And so we hang out and I turn on the loudspeaker so my wife can listen in too and and have a chuckle
I'm sure Sheila it was pretty great. So if you want to join us, there's an IRC room
It's IRC geek shed net pound lup lug and then we just hang out on our mumble room
Which it's kind of great because it gives you maybe a chance to try out mumble
Try out your mic before Tuesdays and then you got everything set up. You could just join us the same spot
Yeah, low-pressure fun casual hangout. Yeah, it's pretty great. We'd love to see you. So
Join us on Sundays
Love plug actually went all the way to 10 p.m. Pacific
Holy, so just spend your whole Sunday there
Grab a pizza grab a couple of beverages
Put your feet up
All right, well today fedora 32 is
Officially released you may recall a few episodes ago episode
Dig a D. I put it lower down in the dog. He did 348
348 that was a really fun episode. So Linux unplug calm slash 348
we we took one of the big features of
fedora 32 and just sort of zoomed in on that and that is the early out of memory killer and
It's fascinating the difference it makes so check that out because that's a big part of what makes fedora 32 on the desktop experience
A little bit different but along with that is your standard updates to things like gnome
You have gnome 3.36 in here, which includes that new
beautiful
beautiful login and
Unlock screen. I mean, I've been using it for a while, but every time I like wake my computer up. It's just a treat
That's just such a great example. Like wimpy was intimating earlier that work was started in 2017
At a hack fest in London and now it's landed here in 2020
It's a special thing that is you got it. You got to actually use it to see it
It feels beautiful full stop. Yeah, it really it feels elegant
So along with early out of memory manager enabled by default
which helps improve the desktop experience and then the fixes that have landed in gnome 3.36 that have helped improve
experience in
IO load so that's something that a lot of work went into with this release of gnome where these bug fixes landed is
rooting out what caused gnome shell to stall during heavy IO load situations and
tons of those fixes have landed
Fedora 32 sort of doubles down on that by including that early out of memory killer
but also by doing things like enabling trim by default on the SSDs and
Twitching firewall D defaults to using NF tables fedora. You're so modern. So tell us about this West
This is kind of a neat little trick. Yeah, I mean NF tables has been around since 2013
I think and that's been a long time. But as usual no major distros
I've gotten around to really adopting it or adding it in places. Sure. You could use it yourself
It's been in the kernel and really that's sort of what you know
Folks upstream in the kernel have been working on been in the kernel since kernel 3.13
That's how long it feels like a long time ago, but you know, nobody's used it. Like you said
So this is this is kind of I guess the quote-unquote new packet filtering engine if you could call it that
But why why well as always when you upgrade things you just get you know
Get rid of some of the cruft from the past
There's a lot of code duplication and inconsistencies in the current IP tables world in particular
there's a lot of protocol specific extensions that are hacked in there to make it work for an individual protocol and
Nothing that would let you match on packet fields or do that in a more elegant way
So instead of having to add in all this custom work, that's just handled for you
There's also a lot better handling if you've got a dual stack set up
So IP v4 and IP v6 at the same time
If anyone's used IP tables for that and had to use both IP tables and IP 6 tables
It's just kind of a confusing mess and that's a lot better handled in NF tables
That's nice and something that I haven't yet played with but seems like one of those things would be worth just dorking around with
There's also the adoption of sysusers.d format, which I also don't really quite understand or even really appreciate what this is
Can you help me understand this one? Well, so if you think about it, a lot of packages are out there installing users, right?
Yeah, but that's not always super introspectable
Especially if it's just in some you know
Like post install script where they run the actual commands just install the user
So this change uses the sysusers.d format add some hooks into the packaging system so that you can do this in a declarative way
And there's kind of a theme and a lot of these changes around being more declarative
So yeah, you just look at the packaging and see like oh it needs this user
And then you'll know that that'll actually get handled in the right way
So instead of like hashing together some sort of bash script that like checks to see if that you ID and G ID exist and all
Of that it's just sort of like a handoff to say hey OS. I want this thing done. Yeah, exactly
There's also maybe some changes in the future to integrate with system D sysusers now that's not happening now
But this change makes a future switch like that easier. You can just stub it out
There's other small tweaks like DNF getting a little bit faster at counting a few things
Although I think we're about to realize the benefits of that in the next release
Also the ability to restart services at the end of an RPM transaction has been changed
So that's another one of those declarative changes where yeah, you could do that yourself
But you might have complicated dependencies between different services and you need to get that right
So now again, you can see what needs to be restarted
You can register that with the package system so that all those things get started at once and you avoid some of those nasty race
Conditions. This is what I love about a fedora release is
On the surface. It's like oh, it's it's a new gnome shell. Okay, right
but when you actually go below the surface and
You see what they're doing here
You see like there's so much stuff that we've been talking about for months now that is landing like kernel 5 6 which has wire guard
Python 3.8
LLVM 10 but also
GCC 10 which is a big deal and
system D
245 so the big deal about system D 245 version
245 if you can believe that is the first release that includes the new system D home D stuff. Oh
Change in the world once again, nothing's really being done with it at this time, but it's there now
Yeah, you've got home CTL right on your command line already after you install you can start setting things up
I tried it a little bit and didn't quite get it working before the show
But I've also never used it before and it will definitely be something I'm playing with. I just seems that seems like a big deal
I don't know. That's like a big one
And then the other thing that we've been watching for what feels like a hundred years
But has seen some significant improvements in this release is pipe wire
Some early work on I'm kind of making pipe wire sort of fit and finish stuff is now getting laid down
but more importantly this release they say has
Basically full-on jack compatibility and full jack support. So now pipe wire can fully integrate with jack on both ends and
They did something I can't remember because I just read this this morning
But essentially they've changed the way they do like a direct frame buffer copy
For for streaming the desktop and they've made it much more efficient now to like capture the desktop and put that into a video stream
And send that to an application. That's how to rework as well
Oh darn sounds like we're gonna have to reinstall the studio after the show. Yeah, right
Right, right. Hey also retiring Python 2. Uh-huh. That's another sign of those changes where they it has to happen
It's been a long time fedora isn't afraid to push ahead
There's some performance benchmarks if you like those kinds of things that we have linked in the show notes. Michael arable did the whole
fedora 32 versus 2004 with versus
x11 versus Wayland on and then also one that I always love is the cross desktop benchmarks
right gnome shell versus LX see versus
Plasma and all the others
That's all linked in there essentially the takeaway is it depends?
Which is what always happens with these reviews on like all these sort of similar releases
You know as I've been playing with the beta up till you know up till the release today
I will say if it order 32 has been a dream to virtualize even just you know using Wayland
No issues whatsoever. I kind of forgot I was using it in a virtual machine for a while
So I put this on the limo pro from system 76 it feels so wicked
Fast that it's been one of those where like I show it to people. I'm like try this try this
both 2004 and fedora 32 part of the boot experience now is so smooth because they're using the OEM
UEFI load yeah, right exactly hands-off from the bootloader very nicely and so
It boots about as long as it used to take a PC to just post
That's literally how long it takes a little more pro with fedora 32 to boot like wouldn't you know when you beep and then you?
Get a memory count and then it would flip over to the next screen and it's all your PCI devices
And then you would go to your bootloader, and then your OS boots
With this it's it's vendor logo, then there's a flash of the vendor logo, and then there's a flash in your on
It's not even really a flash. It's more of a transition and you're at GDM
I mean you almost can't tell like was this just hibernated or suspended or did I do a full boot yeah?
I'd say it's it's just a few shakes slower than waking from sleep if sleep
Waking wasn't so dang fast now like if it was like what used to be back when you stuff of like a disk spin up
Or something yeah, it's really really fast, and it's smooth the the theme is
clean very clean and
The gnome experience is also very clean because there's not a lot of tweaks some of the things I got to admit
I do like that canonical tweaks is like the appearance tab. I've learned to kind of like my
Favorites to a dock thing so there's just extensions
I go turn on but it's even easier to manage that now because there's a dedicated extensions app
That's like officially upstream supported
And so it's even easier now to manage your extensions and toggle ones that aren't working and toggle them on and off
And I love all that right. I don't know about you, but it's great experience
I had on 2004 I think fedora 32 is feeling faster the performance does seem a little bit a little bit
It's been super snappy. I did a clean install last night
of the ISO image and it was
Within seconds I had everything up-to-date the the software experience is really smooth for installing both firmware packages
But also the OS upgrades no kidding and then that you know that nice little pop-up asking if you want to
Turn on third-party repos is clean and just simple if you'd show me this like even let's say three three years ago
I don't know. I would believe it was desktop Linux. It really is pretty great. So what was the bacon take well?
I mean there were a few things again. I just looked at it with my bacon eyes. I suppose you're cheesy bacon eyes
I do like the wallpapers that they've put in there's some some pretty stylish ones that they've created for themselves
Especially the 3d printed one because I'm a nerd like that and I've been 3d printing everything as of late
I thought you might like that one and honestly it just looks really sharp
You know the nice depth of field in there exactly exactly and so that's my default wallpaper at the moment
And one thing that I really liked about your first initial
Impression of fedora was the fact that especially for new users you have the the help comes up right there
But they've also added these nice little video clips just to show you how to navigate
The genome system itself. So how to switch workspaces
How to quickly open up the applications menu and I think that those are nice little touches
especially for someone that you know might be getting a
Lenovo
Laptop preloaded with fedora and have never used Linux before so this might you know
Really help those types of users out and I thought another really interesting feature was
Once you initially installed the system
The updates were done in the background for you on that first boot and then applied for you on the reboot
So similar to how you would have a progress bar
With Windows or Mac OS or something like that letting you know that updates are being installed
I thought that that was a really clean way to handle that initial
First boot and I think that kind of goes back to you know
These additional little features like the videos and helping new users kind of get a feel for it and understand the system
There were a couple of dislikes
You know things that I think could be worked on. I think the partitioning is still a little awkward
Especially if you are a new user and you're coming over
It's it's definitely not as clean in my opinion as say Ubuntu is on
Partitioning and knowing what you're going to do a couple of things like telegram wasn't available for me in the default store
So I had to go to flat hub and pull that down
you know, you guys would probably know more about this, but I
Don't know if flat hub is integrated into the software store
The software store. Well when you go to flat hub and you do the quick setup
After that point it will be it's just added as one of the repositories flat pack itself is pre-installed. Yes
Yeah, just a flat hub repo is not added. But thankfully it's like a one-line command. You don't even have to pseudo for it
Again fractional scaling, you know while built in it wasn't in the UI
So not really a big deal for me on my on my test machine
But when I'm pushing, you know something on my 4k monitor, I would like to see that available there
And I thought it was kind of weird that there were two image viewers. So you had photos and then images as well
Photos I assume is a fedora project while images is a gnome project
well
I think it's photos is like to manage and organize a photo library similar to photos on Mac OS and iOS and then
Image viewer or viewer whatever it's called is for like viewing JPEGs in your downloads folder or PDFs and things like that
It doesn't have the same sort of like albums or favorites or that's right
So got you and that's and that's kind of what I thought would be the case, right?
It would be more for managing photos as opposed to images
You know, I noticed that you could crop and rotate and do a couple editing features in there as well
But I didn't take a deep dive into either one of those applications to be honest, but I think overall it's a great release
I mean, I enjoyed it. I liked the the little nuanced features that they added for the new user, you know the theming
I think you know, they've just used the stock gnome theme
I think that's something they could work toward in the future is maybe dialing that in a little bit and and maybe
Enabling the yard routine by default
Careful, you could be touching the third rail there on that one
Do you know how contentious that whole thing thing gets I think all of us
Are looking forward to maybe I'll bring Madden on this point is I believe in the next release of fedora
There is going to be a transition for DNF that will improve performance fairly considerably
Is that did I read that right Matt that that's being worked on for the next release. They're working on it
I don't know how much of it's going to land in the next release because
When you're looking at the update system
It's fairly sensitive. So you want to make sure any changes like that are
safe
Yeah, fair enough. Yeah, no kidding. Yeah better to take it slow and steady with that
so I was sitting here thinking fedora in a very special way represents the
collective works of so many upstream projects some of which Red Hat incubates and others outside of that and I
Wonder if you've noticed something that has stood out to Wes and I Matt and that is as we dug into this for research for the show
We realized there was significantly more in this release than what is in the written press right now
Not to like take away from what they've done because it's great that it's getting coverage
but it seems like fedora has a bit and I hate to be cliche, but it has a bit of an iceberg scenario where
Some of the big features like the new desktop release or out-of-memory killer or some package transition those are visible
But then below the surface
there's so many more things about this release of fedora that we didn't realize and still we started doing our research and I wonder if
You feel like that stuff isn't properly getting exposure if you've noticed this too. Oh, yeah
absolutely, and there are thousands of packages in fedora with a
huge rate of change and
We used to a couple years ago have a couple people on our docs team who are really dedicated to making sure we had release
notes that had a
Broad coverage of a lot of that change and that's kind of fallen off just as people moved on to other things
It would be awesome to have some people focusing on that again. So that's an area we could use some help
So this is maybe maybe a call to help join the fedora docs team and see what you can do around release notes
It's an easy way to make things better. What a great way to contribute and in the announcements
We kind of you know, try to pick a few highlights
But even there I kind of rely on people to tell me hey
This is an interesting thing I did and then I kind of talk together with our marketing people and a PR people and say okay
What are the things we should kind of put up the front here so that you know
They get get the attention this time around
I try to rotate those things a little bit so it's not always like new version of GCC every time or whatever
Whatever piece of software new GNOME new core OS things so there's a little bit of different attention
But yeah, there's just there's so much it can't all get the all get the attention
It deserves there really is and you would think you would think I was just it's a small release
But there's so much in there and then there's so many packages that have such
Huge things still changing and we just go along and upgrade and it all just works typically always
I think what we want is the nerd report all the all the nitty-gritty Colonel newbies, but for fedora. Yeah, really that'd be great
Somebody get on that get in contact with Matt. I don't know. I know Maddie
What's the best way for people to get ahold of you if they actually did want to maybe help out with that?
You can join our fedora mailing lists
Matt DM on Twitter Matt DM fedora and read it
Those are probably the best places you can email me. I am generally available IRC. I'm around
Well, I got to say
This release with the improvements to GNOME shell and whatnot feels wicked fast
it really is pretty impressive at being a longtime desktop Linux user and
Seeing this level of improvement
Continually over the years, you know, I think it's something that we take for granted
It could have gone very much the other way it could be getting slower and more and more
Right loaded and we've we've gotten the exact opposite
Is there anything that's in this 32 release that you don't think is getting a lot of attention right now that you want to?
Shed a little light on yeah, a couple of interesting things
One of them is finally the fedora core OS
We are getting to our different streams of having a next and updates and a stable stream and fedora core OS
Which is an important step of making that actually something
I really want to recommend people to use to install their compute clusters and things on top of
another neat thing the
computational neuroscience SIG in fedora special interest group put together a spin of
The desktop you basically install a live CD that has all this neuroscience stuff on it
So that people in the neuroscience community can get their brain imaging and all the software open source software that does that in one nice
easy slick place and I really love this because
You know, obviously that's a niche
But I really want fedora to be a place where people who have niche interests can come and you know
Make a solution for their particular users and groups another one that's in the works. We've had a fedora jam
audio
focused version of fedora for a while and
Someone has picked that up again. And I think especially with the pipewire stuff you're talking about really want to have fedora
Be a premier system for doing audio production. I think that'll be that'll be pretty neat
Yeah, yeah, definitely. I noticed that image. I'm like mental note gonna check that out in a bit. I also noticed a
Gaming ISO what's the gaming image that one hasn't been updated for a little while?
But it's kind of an idea about show sort of showcasing open source games
So it's not so focused on you can you know?
The big news of course now is you know proton and steam on Linux and kind of proprietary games
Yeah, but it is nice to remind ourselves like there's some really great free games, too
Yeah, and that's kind of what that is meant to show off in general
I would love for anybody who has you know, kind of a special interest and thinks that there would be a particular
You know focus they could put on the operating system that would would showcase something for their users
I mean another one I often give as an example is the Python classroom lab
Which is meant to you know for teachers teaching how to program in Python
It's gonna have an environment you can boot into and there you go. Everything's all ready for you that kind of thing
32 just continues this feeling that I've had for I think really since like 28 or 29 and that is
That fedora is such a great DevOps showcase Linux workstation OS
You know like the same thing I felt for 24
It's like we're so fortunate to have all this great work from all these different projects kind of coming together and land yes
and
I think it's pretty cool that you guys went ahead and pulled the trigger on the early out of memory killer stuff too like that's
Something else a lot of people aren't moving on
Were you involved in any of the conversations or they maybe pros and con debates on actually doing something?
That's kind of aggressive like that that one. I watched go by like the conversation was was was going okay
So, you know, there's there sometimes some of these development conversations feel like they are going off the rails or need some intervention
But I think a lot of times the process just kind of works
There was another example of that that I thought was pretty awesome in this distribution
If you're looking through those for Onyx performance results, you'll see that Python in particular is a lot faster
And this is because someone had a suggestion that
Python would be a lot faster if it were compiled statically rather than dynamic linking
For some technical reasons related to Python blah blah blah, which is cool
But there's a lot of downsides to static linking Python
So kind of the community discussing together came up with an idea of a particular compiler flag
Which gives a lot of the benefits with much smaller downsides
You actually can't LD preload things into Python anymore the way we're building it
But as a result, we get like a 20 percent performance increase on Python
Wow, that really does feel like a great developers workstation
I just always notice like Kexec already installed a ton of the tools that I have to install on other distributions
Fedora has them right out of the box
Also, I have to give honorable mention I didn't really do much with it this time around
But Fedora Toolbox, I believe, has been transitioned from like a bash project to a go project
And there's some story around that, too
Well, the bash was always kind of a prototype
And, you know, once as a sysadmin, you know, once your bash scripts gets to be more than, you know, fits in one screen of your text editor
It's probably time for it to stop being a bash script
Oh, I think Wimpy might disagree
You should see some of his bash scripts
It had exceeded that by quite a bit in complexity
So it was time for it to move on to something else
And just a lot of the tooling, you know, Podman and container tooling is written in Go
So Go is a natural ecosystem choice for that
We really should make our pick that bash, was that bash top? Is that what it was called?
That monstrosity bash script
There's a bonus app pick for everybody
Go check out bash top
Well, yeah, and, you know, Fedora Toolbox is very, very handy
So I've talked about it before on the show
But it's just such a quick way to get like an environment where it feels very much like you're on the same box
You're in the same, you can share resources
But you also are able to play in a way that's isolated from the rest of the operating system
And you can recreate them and spin them up very fast
And I just loved it
But I didn't really give it a go this time around because I got the concept
But I appreciate that the work's continuing and the investment's continuing there
It was designed for running on Core OS and on Silverblue where you have an immutable base OS
On those systems, it's basically vital because you kind of need to have some environment to mess with
So this gives you that
But it's also really useful just on a standard Fedora workstation desktop
To give you kind of that sandbox space where it's safe to mess it up
And then you can destroy it and create a new one or whatever
Well, especially if you're a bozo like me who's installing 30 different apps a week
So he can talk about them on his podcast
You know, eventually your system starts to pay for that
So that's what I, when I was running Fedora as my main workstation, I really found that pretty useful
I wonder if I can get Fedora Toolbox on Manjaro right now
I bet you can
Yeah, something tells me
Well, cool man
I mean, I just, I gotta say congratulations to you and the entire team
Another great release
And our team installed it and pretty much universally liked it
And we were, you know, messaging, telegramming each other back and forth
Like, did you see this? What about that? Yeah, it's very fast
And I'm running on this, I'm running on this
Okay, I have it in this VM
And I very much concur with Wes
It was pretty, pretty performant in all of those situations
It feels, it feels like this is the fastest Linux we've ever had
And I know there's some benchmarks that suggest otherwise
But I don't know man, when you put everything together
When you put the gnome shell improvements together
You put, even having trim on the SSDs
You put an early out of memory manager on there
Plus the improvements like with Python and whatnot
Like it all really comes together to a fantastic release of Fedora
Well, thank you
Well, thank you actually
Don't thank me, I'm thanking you guys
Please thank the whole team
I will
So, would it be outrageous for me to ask you
What the not so distant future might hold for Fedora
As far as you're concerned?
More of the same, I think
Continuous releases on a cadence
I'm excited about more of the IoT stuff
Hopefully we'll get some more devices
We've always had some trouble with, you know
Everybody's favorite Raspberry Pi
With, you know, upstream support and things like that
And, you know, Fedora really
We really like to keep everything
So that we have one operating system
That installs on all devices
Not a separate kernel
Not these kind of things
And so that's been a long road
I think that as the ARM device world matures
We'll have more things that Fedora will work out of the box on
And I think there's some neat stuff in Fedora IoT
That's coming up
I hope to see some cool stuff around that with Fedora 33
I agree on those points
I do hope to see some more maturing there
Maybe Wes and I will talk about our RockPro experiments
In the post show
Yeah, in particular, actually
The RockChip stuff has a lot of new support in Fedora 32
So hopefully that should go more smoothly for you
I'm hoping so
We'll find out
Wes Payne will be back with the results in a moment
But before we get there
I just wanted to say thanks
Thanks for coming by, Matt
You know, I know it's probably a super busy time
You know, probably if you have a little downtime
The last thing you really want to do is jump on the computer
And chat with people about it
You'd probably love to just be kicking back and relaxing
Having a beer right now
So I appreciate you making the time
I'm going to be back to the Red Hat Summit now
Right, of course
Enjoy
No downtime for you at Summit time
I forgot, of course
Well, thanks for making the time
I really appreciate it
Be glad to
Bye
And congratulations again
And Wimpy, congratulations again to your team on the release
Thank you for stopping by
And a big plug for the Ubuntu podcast
Go check out the Ubuntu podcast at UbuntuPodcast.org
Season 13 is in full swing
Thank you very much
No, thank you
And those look like some tasty potatoes
We do make good potatoes
You guys are making me hungry
Oh, yeah
I'm not done podcasting yet
We have a whole post-show still
Well, we will see about that actually
We're getting long
We'll see
Before we go, I want to mention that this show actually has a Twitter account
If you want to be following
I don't know
Maybe you want to be up to date on like new releases
Maybe you want to know when things are live
I don't know
I don't know what you want
It's Linux Unplugged, right?
Just at Linux Unplugged?
Is that what it is?
At Linux Unplugged
That's what it is
You say it like that so I believe you think that's what it is
But I know you're double checking just in case it's not that right now
You got to do your due diligence
And I'm right
All right
We'll be live again next Tuesday at noon Pacific
And links for everything we talked about at Linux Unplugged slash 351
See you next Tuesday
You and I were doing kind of concurrent projects before the show started
Because our mumble server was down
And so I was kind of keeping the live stream up to date
And chatting with the mumble admins who are wonderful people
Amazing
Volunteers that are truly just the best people on the earth
That took care of a little outage we had right before the show
Which clearly our virtual log is such a huge part of this podcast
So the fact that we were possibly going to be without mumble
I was slightly panicked so Mitt Fried jumped in on it
And got the system back up and running and we were able to keep going
Saved the show
While we were kind of doing all of that
You were out in the server room aka studio garage
And you were messing around with the Rock Pro 64 we have out there
And Fedora images
And the thing is I didn't get a chance to see if it actually ended up working or not
So how far did you get with Fedora 32 on the Rock Pro?
Not quite
We're still learning our way around that thing that's for sure
And it seems like occasionally when we reboot it
It needs a little cool down period before it's ready to try booting up again
Like fully unplugged
Yeah
And that's something that I'm not sure if other people experience
But we have to kind of leave it unplugged or else it won't post again properly it seems
Only after a failed boot
We can reboot it from the command line and it comes right back up
So that's not a problem
Yeah
So based on my limited knowledge and deciphering
While the Manjaro image that we used as a test booted up just fine
Neither of the two Fedora images I found were able to do so
Okay
And that's just from the SD card
Yeah and these are just the ones you know put out on the alternative downloads page from today
So I don't know that they've been optimized for anything but you know the processors
And so there may need to be some bootloader work etc done to actually get it loaded and working
As they say in your Zoom meetings we're going to circle back on that topic and put a pin in it
And see if we can't sink on a solution and then maybe bring some other stakeholders in and verify the results
Oh my God Chris