This is Linux Unplugged Episode 6 for September 17th, 2013.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, a weekly unscripted Linux podcast that's been taking RMS a little
more seriously. It's brought to you by our fine sponsor Ting.com. I'll tell you more
about how great Ting is as the show goes on. My name is Chris and my name is Matt. Welcome
back from the trip. Thank you. Thank you. Good times. How was the trip? It was unbelievable.
It was just what the doctor ordered. Oh, I bet. So I think I saw your waterfall picture.
That's what it was. Yeah, we went out to Lake Chelan here in Eastern Washington and it was
just amazing. Yeah, I showed that to the kids. They're like, I don't want to go there. So
that sounds like a must do. And you did it just at the right time. It wasn't probably
too hot, right? Oh, yes, it was. When we first got over the mountains, we were about 101,
I think it averaged in the mid nineties, the rest of the trip. Oh, wow. So I forget, you
know, like you were just saying on the pre show, uh, there is a whole nother side to
our state that is like a completely different state. It really is. Yeah. It's fascinating
when you go over those mountains, how warm it gets. Well, uh, we've got a big show. Guess
what? Big show. Uh, so this week I want to talk a little bit about losing the flame for
Android. Uh, if you've followed this week's Coderator, you probably know where I'm talking
about what we're going to get into it on this backing up a Linux server and a set it and
forget it way. I'd like to maybe pick the mumble server, uh, their brain folks on the
mumble server. And then of course we've got our feedback on our follow-up as always, but
nothing planned, nothing planned. I'm just saying, I'm just saying, so why don't we just,
why don't we bust through some quick F U that's what I'm labeling the follow-up is F U, the
F U segment, the F U segment. And, uh, the, probably the first thing, uh, oh, you know
what I need, I need like an F U a segment here. Let's see, maybe this could be our F
U segment bump. He's a jackass. What do you think that works? I, you know, I think it's
short sweetened. It's a, to the point. All right. Well, so I remember last week during
the news segment on the Linux action show, we were saying that a system D a number build
207 is coming to, to all of a distributions near you that run system D and that there
was that Etsy sys tl.com file that I was wondering if arch users were going to get bitten by.
Exactly. I specum allocated out loud in the, uh, in the show and we had a few people write
in and, uh, tell us what's up with that. And they pointed us to the source of all knowledge
in arch and that is the arch Wiki. And actually in this case is the news section. Uh, uh,
and it is, you will have a little bit of work to do if you've been using it, but however,
if you have a fairly recent installation, you probably don't have anything in there.
There is a Sim link you need to do if you do have config info in there. And if you don't
just go look at that file and if you really haven't said anything in there, you don't
have to worry. Good times. I love that. I love the fact that their Wiki really spells
it out in a real clean, easy to follow way. Yeah. Following the arch news and there's
also a mailing list you can follow is always a good step. I, um, I don't always check before
I, before I, before I run it. Uh, but I, I generally try to, and we're going to have
a, we're going to have an email, um, coming up a little bit later in the show about the
arch challenge again, King backup. And so I thought we'd cover that and let people know.
There's also another email. Actually, this was a bit message we got and they said in
last episode of last, you talked about note taking programs, which by the way, some people
loved Matt and then some people hated, some people were down with it. Well, you know,
some people take notes and other people have that mega memory thing going on. So yeah,
okay. Yeah, I guess so. Uh, but one that didn't get mentioned. And so our bit messenger wanted
to make sure I gave it a shout out is cherry tree. Cherry tree, I think has gotten some
love on the show. I want to say it might've been a pick at one point. Cherry tree notes
is great though. And it's got, it's got its own good, uh, like it supports rich text formatting.
It's got its own syntax. You can, uh, you can follow. And, uh, I have not actually, uh,
used it beyond like, you know, trying it out to see if it would do my, what I wanted for,
I don't remember what it was about if it didn't quite grab me. Maybe it was the way it implemented
X, Y, and Z or whatever it was. Sure. The UI actually, to be honest with you, it's sometimes
with note taking part of it is like, um, you know, you got to work in this space. You got
to live inside this application. So, well, I know UI is a big, it's an important part
of your space because it's, you know, you, you're very UI centric. And so for me, it's
a lot of times of, you know, can I, I don't know, ham fist through it. And a lot of times
I'll put up with a lot of that kind of stuff. I don't know. I'm looking at it now and it's
honestly, I don't, I doesn't look so bad, you know, it definitely kind of has a QT feel
to it. So yeah. So I thought, um, uh, one last bit of followup that I wanted to get
to, uh, because I wanted to spot to talk about this where people wouldn't be like, oh, you
guys are just saying this because they sponsor you. Right? Sure. And that is today the new
system 76 rig was launched. Now remember last week we said they're going to have a new leopard
extreme coming. They're calling it, I think they're calling it like the leopard X four,
the Leo X four. I'll pull it up here while we talk about it. Um, so system 76 sponsors
Linux action show, but they don't sponsor this show. Um, but we are both personally
fans of system 76. That's one of the reasons we were able to twist their arm to come on
board. Oh yeah. And so they updated today, their leopard extreme rig, man, have you had
a chance to look at this thing? I was looking through it and it's just like, I mean, first
of all, the first tip I would give anyone looking at the pictures is prior face off
the screen so you can actually take in the images because I was so busy trying to like
throw my money at the screen and get it, you know, like trying to like make it materialize
in front of me that I wasn't able to fully appreciate it till I pulled away a little
bit and I looking at it, it looks really powerful. I've already done a few builds. Yeah. They're
using a Corsair, um, um, water cooling solution. I've used the similar water cooling solution
and it's really cool because what it does is it's not very complicated. It just runs
to a radiator. I believe I'm guessing based cause I have a similar model. It runs to a
radiator that's connected to your 120 millimeter fan in the back of the case. And so it's,
it just uses the regular case cooling to cool it. So you don't have to have like a radiator
sitting on top of the rig. Um, and, and so this to me is one of those things where I
think the first reaction a lot of people are going to have is it's probably too expensive
because it is a, it's a highly priced machine. It's for, it's a high end machine for folks
that want high end performance and a high end experience without having to monkey with
something themselves. I think that's the real differential. This is a total pro level machine.
So like here, I thought I'd, so if I was going to build a machine, I would get the six core
fourth gen Intel I seven, which runs at 3.4 gigahertz. I would get 32 gigs of Ram. Uh,
probably because if I'm going to have a machine this nice, I also want to play video games
and I also use GPU accelerated functions. So they have an Nvidia graphics card here that
has a 5, uh, 1,500 CUDA cores. Uh, that would be the one I'm going to go with kind of expensive,
but I could use that. Um, I would probably not go rate. I'd go a 240 gigabyte SSD for
the primary hard drive and then maybe like, uh, I probably keep it as tight as I needed.
Three terabytes would probably be enough for my working space for my scratch. Oh yeah.
You know what'd be awesome with this too is if you're someone that does a lot of VMs like
simultaneously and you just don't care about, you don't want to have to think about do I
have too many running or whatever, that would be fantastic. Anything that's really performance
intensive. It actually clocked in less than I thought, uh, 30 at $3,059. Oh, that's actually
a lot. So now I would have figured for, I'm going to go to apple.com slash door. And the
reason why is because I'm comparing this leopard extreme to the Mac pro. I think this is for
content creators is for people who want, um, you know, like if I'm a plumber, I get myself
a real special kind of, this is not to compare the Mac mini to, uh, the extreme is to prepare.
I would go a slightly slower processor, but I would go two cores, uh, or, uh, this is
yeah. Six core. Now this is a Xeon 32 gigs of Ram. Um, let's go. We can't do, we'll do
a fire already without even going to step two at 61 99. No, and I'm at 7,500. Wow. Crap.
And the thing looks like a trashcan. So we'll know that we don't even know what the price
of that one's going to be. But my point is, is this leopard extreme is this is a professional's
computer. This is something that I, you know, if Chris Buysie writes off on his taxes, right?
This is, that's what this is now. I just even the next gen a Mac yet, or is this still the
old one? That's the old one. So this is the one that looks like a computer. But I think
this, because it's, it's got, it's a tower. So it has PCI express slots available to you
where the new trashcan doesn't like, I think as more people move to Linux for certain functionality,
I've been looking at a new generation of media production apps. Uh, one that just hit the
subreddit today. It's an audio editing application. It's in beta. I've been keeping an eye on
it. Um, and then another one that a video editing application that hit the subreddit
a couple of days ago that is yes, once again, another video editor, but I actually edited
a mock episode of Linux unplugged in that video editor last weekend. And I, it actually
wasn't perfect. It definitely wasn't as fast as my current workflow, but it was the closest
I've ever gotten to taking non-native Linux codecs. These were ProRes codecs, bringing
them into a Linux editor, assembling it the way I need it with the music cues and the
transition spots and, and then export it out to a file, a master file that I can then encode
on the distributed machines that produce all the different file formats. Um, it, it like
actually the whole process from end to end actually happened in this, in this environment
like on a Linux box. It was amazing. And so we're definitely very close to the point where
if I changed a few behaviors and if I changed a work, a few workflow things and I was willing
to live with maybe a little less quality, maybe, you know, silly things too, like night
is not, not as nice transitions, maybe a reduction in audio quality slightly because this didn't
have any audio processing. Um, we are at the point where I actually think this could all
be done on Linux. And that's pretty exciting because then it starts, you start looking
at this like the celebrity extreme and now it's actually like, you know, we're really,
really close. Um, and I think I could do 70% of it today on that. So I'm really excited
about it. I'm going to, you know, I'm not sure I'm ready because honestly the Bonobo,
uh, with its, I mean the thing has two hard drives, so my IO problem is solved. They're
both SSDs. It's a core I seven, it's got 16 gigs of Ram. So the Bonobo has done so well.
So I'm, I'm like, do I just run it on the Bonobo or do I maybe do this towards the end
of the year as like a, you know, 2013 taxes thing? I don't know, but I'm really excited
about it. I say hats off to system 76, that elaborate extreme. I think people can think
I'm, I think I'm crazy for saying this, but I think it looks like the best computer for
Linux for this year, maybe even 2014. Oh, that's not even a question. I mean, you just
look, I mean, as you just did the comparison with the Mac, there was no question there
at all. And then of course, as far as knowing the machine is going to be built to the specifications
you want and everything just works, it's got a solid warranty. The company's been around
for a long time. It's just a win-win. So yeah, it looks really good too. I like the look
of it too, the size and anyways, really excited. And, uh, I emailed them asking them for a
demo unit. So we'll see, I know that would be fantastic. Their inventory is tight and
they're building a lot of them in the U S now and that makes it even tighter. So I know
it's, it might not happen, but I thought I'd, I'd put it out there. Doesn't hurt. Yeah.
Yeah. All right, Matt. Well, before I get to what's been troubling me this week, deep
down on the inside and why I think maybe RMS has been right all along and we just haven't
been receiving his wisdom and now I'm rethinking everything. I want to talk about our sponsor
this week and that my friends is ting.com. Look, if you go to linux.ting.com, we've got
a landing page for you built just for you, customized just for you. Now ting is mobile.
That makes sense. They're a completely new way of doing mobile and they give me a lot
of hope for the future of this industry. First of all, probably the biggest differentiator,
no contracts, no early termination fees and you pay for what you use. So you get a line,
it's $6 a month. If you use a hundred minutes, you end up just going to that hundred minute
bucket and that's what you pay. Ting takes your minutes, your megabytes and your messages
and they add them all up at the, at the end of the month. And if you're like me and you're
a little bit savvy on your voice, some months I squeak away with hardly any voice minutes
at all. And my bill is about as low as it can get. It's usually in the $12 to $15 range.
Average price, average bill on ting for a ting customer is $22 or $21. I'm sorry. Uh,
so you know, it's a pretty reasonable price. It's not only that, but they have a good range
of phones from pre pre-owned phones that you can get at a great discount feature phones
and also high end phones like the HTC one, which is, which has fantastic speakers, which
is great for podcasts listening, but also has incredible screen, which is great for
watching content like our shows. So when you go over to ting, you might notice if you play
around that they've got some shots of their dashboard. That's actually what their dashboard
looks like. It is legitimately that beautiful. It is legitimately that easy to use and it
is very functional. You can do everything from porting a phone, deactivating a phone,
buying a phone, transferring a phone, anything for their website. Matt, what was your impression?
You know, you're on ting too. You got, you got the note too. What was that process like
setting that up on, on the ting website?
Setting it up was surprisingly simple. I was amazed that even though I had to release the
phone from its original owner, which was you, that only took like a couple seconds, uh,
just using their help file. And once that was done, the actual setup process, I think
was under like a two minutes, minute and a half. It was something crazy. I didn't have
to talk to anybody, even though you can get a real person if you do. But it was awesome.
It was so easy.
Yeah. Ting, uh, ting also has a great blog where they're actively posting the stuff that
they think people that are ting users might be interested in because the ting customer
base I think is a little savvier than your average bear. And so here's five things you
didn't know your smartphone could do. Matt, this is totally, totally up your alley. Remotely
control your electronics. They highlight these Belkin Wemo switches that integrate with an
app.
That's awesome.
Yeah. So you can control your different devices, scan high quality documents, play laser tag.
And here's one that I really like. Measure the speed of a moving object. They talk about
this app called speed gun that lets you, you take speed gun, you pointed at something that
moves across the frame and it tells you how fast that thing is moving. How cool is that?
Pick up a notch. And you said they have, you can do laser tag. They have an article telling
you this. This is cool.
Yeah. They got laser tag. They got laser tag. Yeah. It was called app tag and it's designed
to let you play. Yes. Ting blog is awesome. But one of the things that I caught on the
ting blog recently is they're doing early termination fee relief. So if you're in a
contract now and you really want to get out and you want to start saving money, you want
to move over to ting because you love that included hotspot. You love that included tethering.
You love the fact that they don't bundle anything along that you wouldn't expect. You love the
transparent nature of the company and you love what they're about. Maybe you want to
get out of that contract a little early. Now ting is going to help you with that. They're
going to take up to 75% off of that early termination fee. So all you have to do, get
your ting phone, you activate it and then you send them your ETF claim and they'll cut
you a check right there or actually maybe a credit. But think about that. Think about
how awesome that is. It helps not only relieve the blow of having to cancel that contract,
but then it just increases the amount of money you're going to save on the long run by switching
to ting. So go to linux.ting.com. Take $25 off your first device or $25 off your first
month of service if you're going to bring your own device. In fact, they even have a
concierge service to help find a used device for you so you can get a great deal on a device.
I love that. And if you've got somebody on maybe in your family that doesn't want a very
powerful phone, you can still bring them on, have a shared family pool of minutes with
unlimited lines and you can just give them a feature phone because ting has some great
feature phones. Yes, they're still a thing. They're out there. So awesome things got them
including some of the best android devices. So thanks to ting for sponsoring Linux unplugged
stuff. So one of the things that RMS warned us about, Matt, was that TiVo... It's negative
in the freedom dimension. Remember, he was quite concerned about the TiVoization of Linux.
And in fact, you could say that maybe that was a huge inspiration for a lot of the provisions
in the GPL3. I think so. I think that was definitely something that they forced them
to take a second look at that. And now we're looking back at it and it's like, oh my God,
he's right on a lot of stuff. I think the TiVoization... I think what TiVo has done
to Linux is quaint and adorable in comparison to what Android has done to Linux. I think
what has happened where you have an open source operating system where the core is open and
then there's layers of stuff on top of it that are Apache licensed and then there's
layers on top of that that are just commercially, you know, whatever their commercial proprietary
licenses and then Google takes this, all bundles it all up and hands it out to these OEMs that
then inject their proprietary code at the firmware level, at the radio level, at the
OS kernel level, at the user land space level, and even in the services level with the cloud
services these things connect to. Every single layer, we take this open source operated open
platform and we inject this proprietary code and lock down into it at all different levels.
We bastardize this thing. We make it an embarrassment of the original intent and then we ship it
as a product out to consumers and then to make matters worse, not only have we developed
one of the most incredible fast-moving open source projects that has thousands of intelligent
contributors making the thing better every single day, but we managed to figure out a
way to ship a product running that that doesn't receive updates.
That's right. And people are excited to get new ones, you know, that are literally oftentimes
running the same OS as the phone they just had.
So I'm at a point now and I think it's one part NSA inspired fear mongering because like
maybe it just has me thinking about cloud services in a different perspective, right?
I think it had, yeah, I think it, for you, it has a lot to do with that. I think it has
a lot to do with, I want to find devices and tools that compliment my desire to internalize
my own personal cloud in my own land, not outside of it.
Right. Yeah, exactly. Create your own cloud. Um, and I, so I, I think I'm not, I don't
want to start this off to, to slam Android because I think Android is a really great
solution for a lot of people that offers a lot of great features over the other alternatives.
Let's take the number one alternative iOS and let's just, you know, here's a great one
off the top of my head. Swabbing out the keyboard. We were talking about this on the pre-show.
The fact that the fact that iOS still has this, this ridiculous keyboard. I mean, it's
a, it's kind of an embarrassment, right? So I'm not, I don't mean to demean Android or
demean anyone who chooses it to use it as their mobile platform because I think there's
a lot of merit to the platform. However, I have to bring up issues with what, what Google,
I think Google has been a bad steward of this operating system.
I think they have left consumers in vulnerable positions. I think it is not an exaggeration
to call year old Android devices exploits in the pocket. I think that's exactly what
they are. But, and I acknowledge there are power user solutions to this, like replacing
ROMs and other things, but they're not a solution for the majority of people. So I want to couch
this by saying I'm about to get a little ranty on Android, but I don't, I don't want anyone
to take that as judgment because I, I'm not saying there's a perfect solution here, but
I'm looking at this now, Matt. So this last week in a Linux action show, I ended the,
the Android app picks. I didn't say anything to you because it was just something internally
to me that like, I just knew I was done doing this. And I said in the show, I don't want
to, you know, I don't want to make a big stink about it in the Linux podcast of record in
the big show, but I said in the show that I didn't feel like I need to evangelize this
platform anymore.
Yeah. I remember. And it was, it was for me, it was cause I knew nothing really any backstory
to it. It was very sudden and I figured it must have been okay. Maybe it's just burnout
on talking about apps. Okay. Yeah, that's cool.
So I feel like it's probably, it's, it's deeper than that. I think I've been rethinking cloud
services. I've been rethinking the treatment of this open platform by the carriers, by
the OEMs and by Google. In fact, I have a, I have a quote here from RMS that I, I, you
know, it's been interesting as some of this stuff has come out, either be the, either
be the NSA stuff or looking at the situation with Android. A lot of stuff that RMS said
a while ago actually rings true with me now. And he was just kind of ahead of us. And so
here, here's the point. So in an interview by the Guardian, Richard Stallman was asked
whether Android should be considered free or open, right?
Sure.
So RMS responds with Google has complied with the requirements of the GNU general public
license for Linux, but the, but the Apache license on the rest of Android does not require
source release. Google has said it will never publish the source code for Android 3.0 aside
from the Linux component. And even though executables have been released to the public,
Android 3.1 source code is also being withheld. Thus Android 3, apart from Linux, is non-free
software pure and simple. Android is a major step towards an ethical user controlled free
software portable phone, but there is a long way to go. Hackers are working on Replicant,
but it's a big job to support a phone model. Uh, I'm sorry, a new phone model and the remain
and then there remains the problem of the firmwares. Even though Android phones of today
are considerably less bad than Apple or windows smartphones, they cannot be said to respect
your freedom. And the part that I challenge there is I was, I think one of the things
that sort of started to shift my perspective on this is I watched and I watched it happen
in our community and I watched it happen on the internet in general. When the iPhone five
S was announced, everybody took to the web proclaiming that the fingerprint scanner was
an NSA mass collection device and that this would be used to track iPhone users fingerprints.
But I didn't see the same outcry when Android face detection launched or when the Moto X
launched with always listening capabilities. Well, let me ask you this, and I'm asking
this from someone that's not familiar with what's mandatory, what's not on the iPhone.
Is that a mandatory feature or an optional feature? Optional. Okay. And on the Android,
is that a mandatory feature or an optional feature? Uh, for the face unlock? Yeah. Optional.
Both are optional. From that perspective, I award Darwin awards to people that choose
to use them. Right. Well, yeah, there's that, right? And there's, there's a, there's a,
there's a whole series of issues like, uh, like wire point out, like pleading the fifth
when you use your fingerprint or your face to unlock. But well, I think my point was
as people, I feel like our community doesn't think critically about these things. Like
one's always good, one's always evil. I would say that by and large, that's true.
But I think it, I think it's, we look at the lesser two evils, like most people do politically,
I think at that, I think, and that's, and I don't, I don't support that idea, but I think
that's kind of where we're at. And so for each individual, one of us, the most powerful
thing we can do is to have the discussion we're having now talk about the good, the
bad, the ugly, and the choices that each one of us need to reflect on to make the decisions
that's right for us. I think, you know, I'll get some crap because I was particularly hard
in code or radio. Um, but really I think it's being just intellectually honest with yourself,
reanalyzing this stuff and, you know, making sure that it all, it all checks out, you know,
passes the sniff test. Absolutely. So I think you nailed it. I think it's picking the less
of two evils, right? And I think some of us sort of assume Google is less of two evils
because well, Google does summer of code and Google also often mentions things are open
and I love open and better marketing to geeks, quite frankly, right? Right. Yeah. And then
their slogan is don't be evil. I mean, so your first impression is okay, they probably
a good guys. Uh, but I, I just, I think that is not necessarily the case. I think there's
a case to be made that that is a misplaced amount of trust, but I want to back up a little
bit because way I open it. So there's not a great solution either way. And you've recently,
well not recently, but a little while ago you switched from the iPhone to Android. Absolutely.
Yep. And as far as a system functionality level goes, that's, I mean, to you, it must've
seemed like a pretty big upgrade. It was a, it was a huge upgrade. And my motivation,
honestly, I, for a long time, cause I've, you know, you want to go back far enough.
I was on very early versions of a windows mobile, then of course later on blackberry
and so on and so forth. And then I tried this whole iPhone thing and it was just a total
wake up call, especially with, from the browser and all this sort of stuff and being free
of a keyboard. It was a, it was a great experience for what it was. iPhone one, iPhone two, three
and 3G. And then at the, by the time 3G rolled around, I was kind of like, yeah, I'm kind
of done. And, you know, my wife went for, and I actually went with an Android phone
and it was just like someone pulled the, like pulled a kidnapper's hood off my face when
I tried the Android. It's like, oh my God, there's widgets and control and I can make
adult decisions with my phone. Holy crap. It's like, I felt like, there's a file system
in here. It appealed to someone that wanted to really play, you know, with the underpinnings
of their phone a little more as you want to, you know, root it or whatever to get that
functionality with an iPhone, I would have to actually jailbreak it. And I never wanted
to do that. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, exactly. Right. Yeah. Yeah. So, um, I've been looking at it
from the standpoint of a privacy aspect and I, I think, I think the iPhone has a better
argument here. Um, I, I feel like there and it comes down to kind of almost like a fundamental
corporate philosophy. I feel like Android is sold to, so the goal of selling Android
and this is why Google literally gives it away, right? Is because they really want to
eventually sell Google services. That is true. And, and arguably people would point out that
Apple is not motivated in doing that right now. I would counter with bull jobs. Steve
Jobs has passed on. Cook is absolutely going to keep that company competitive. And in order
to do that in the coming years, you damn well better believe they're going to mimic Google's
model. It will happen. I, but here's the difference, right? So here's the difference is they're
making the iPhone and as a checkbox on that, on that box or on that spec sheet, they have
this companion iCloud service, right? Google is the cloud and they make Android to connect
you to it. So Apple is making the iPhone to sell you a overpriced piece of hardware. Google
is making Android to sell you their cloud services. But the problem here is those cloud
services rely on extracting as much information about you as possible, logging that information.
And because they are a US held company, this is where the NSA paranoia comes in. Anything
they learn about you is subpoenable by the FBI, whoever needs to get it right. So arguably
Apple is not a threat in that regard yet. You know, I think even as they begin to roll,
ramp out more and more of those features, it still comes down to a, the basic alignment
of the priorities of the company. Apple is a hardware manufacturer. They live and die
on making that hardware. All of their margins are on hardware. They give away all of the
software because they don't make any money on it. We're talking about a company that
makes billions and billions and billions, hundreds of billions even on selling little
gadgets. Google makes its billions on selling advertising. That's a hundred percent accurate.
No, absolutely true. But I would also point to the evolution of, and I hate to keep bouncing
back to Apple, but it's part of the conversation. Apple computers wasn't always just Apple.
It used to be Apple computers. And they evolved. They had to change their model. They were
no longer just about selling, you know, selling an Apple computer. They were moving into complete
and more of a, I would argue, more of a services based experience, whether it be iTunes or
I this or I that or whatever. And I think the iCloud stuff, and I think that over time
we're going to see them, I would even say probably within, no later than two years from
now become on par with what Google's doing.
So, you know, I think you might be right.
So if you lock yourself into that ecosystem, yeah, you buy yourself a little time, but,
but are they truly going to, do you trust Jim, you know, do you trust Cook enough that
you're going to believe that he's going to tell you, Hey, by the way, we're changing
everything around and we're going to start doing this, this stuff behind the scenes?
Probably not.
I think, I think it might be a heretic in this room, but I think I trust Tim Cook more
than I trust the Google boys. I really do. And like, I'll give, I'll give you an example.
Let's just say all of this information that Google is collecting on us never is used against
us. It's never leaked. It's never, it's never given to the authorities. It's never used
to build a creepy database about knowing what you want before you notice. It's never anything
like that.
What happens when the next regime comes in and they have all of that data, they have
access to all of that information. They have all of that there. It's going to get twisted.
And you know, the other thing that I want to get, I want to just mention before it leaves
the chat log is you queue in the chair and GQ says Android is open source and iMessage
is backdoored. Well, how do we know that? Because what we actually have documented is
that iMessage creates an, it has a key on both ends and the messages are encrypted between
the two parties. That's what we know about iMessage. What we know about Hangouts with
the comparable on Android is we know everything on Hangouts goes through Google and is logged
by Google. That's what we know. Those are the things we know there. And you can't call
Google open because it's completely locked down by the carriers, right? And the other
thing is when you say the iPhone is more locked down, everybody's always talking about the
app store, right? Oh, well the iOS app store is super locked down. Well, you know what?
I'm the jackass that just got a crap ton of spyware on his Android device because I installed
a $5 Star Trek application, right? So maybe that is a little reasonable on a phone that's
meant so I can call my wife to see how the kids are doing. Maybe that is partially reasonable.
But also, if the measuring stick for what makes a platform open or closed is how you
load apps, if you can sideload apps or not, or who gets into the Android app store, then
let's talk about Ubuntu Touch and Firefox OS because those would also be considered
locked down because they don't even have an app store. There is open as Safari is on iOS
or Chrome is on Android, right? HTML5, baby. It's an HTML5 app. That's open. There's your
openness.
I think that's really where the focus needs to be is less about Apple, less about if Android
is a concern for folks. And believe me, I get it. I understand that. I just don't buy
into that Apple is going to be wholesome for two years down the road. I think that's crap.
I think at some point, just if they want to be competitive and get onto that whole database
tit that everybody's making all the money on, I think they're going to have to jump
on at some point. But for now, they're not. I get that. But I think the HTML5 stuff, I
think that's where people need to be looking. I think you're spot on with that.
Absolutely.
Again, I'm not throwing my HTC One in the garbage, but I just want to throw a few things
back to people and just get them to think about this a little more because I look at
like trying to move away from Google now and I think about, in a lot of ways, I'm kind
of locked in here. I've got my contacts syncing through Google. I've got my calendar syncing
through Google. All of these cloud services in a form are a type of data lock-in.
And even if you go to Data Liberation, whatever the hell it is that Google offers, they still
retain that information. So that's legitimate as well.
Well, then you think what? Then you get it in like some big old file and it's just a
pain in the butt.
Right. And you've got to deal with it. Yeah. I hear you.
I just wanted to put the brakes on everybody and say, okay, think about this a little bit
because I had an iPhone over the weekend playing with iOS 7 to talk about it on Koda Radio
on Monday. I actually thought it performed better than any Android device I've used.
I hadn't used iMessage before. I think iMessage is great. I actually thought it was a fantastic
user experience. I thought the battery life was way better than I expected. I couldn't
believe how good the battery life was. And to be honest with you, when I'm looking at
the two, I don't think you can really be mad at anybody for choosing one platform over
the other because I think they both have this long list of disadvantages.
Sure. And in my household, as in yours, we run all of them. So I totally get you. No,
I think for me, it's that I look at iOS 7 and it's like, oh, look, I should put on my
Stussy t-shirt and get my TNC surf shop gear because I'm looking at fricking this neon mess.
It kind of does have elements of iOS Vista. It's like they're Vista of iOS a little bit.
So if I wear sunglasses, I can enjoy the performance. I mean, it's just, it's, you know, we just
wait. That's going to make it everywhere else. You just wait. I know it is. And then, and
then all the Linux distros are going to start mimicking. I know. Oh man. That's going to
be awful. All right. I'm harsh on it. I'm harsh on it. I want to see a mumble room.
You guys have been quiet. I know this is something we kick around on the pre-show. What do you
guys think? Am I just off my rocker here? Am I, am I, am I losing it? That was to you
mumble room. Definitely not losing it at all. Like I said in a previous one, they do lock
you down with the ecosystem. Both sides though, right? You get locked into play area. I experienced
that now. It's a necessary evil in many ways. That's interesting. It's like using gasoline.
At the end of the day, you have to choose what's best for you and your condition, your
situation. You can't have ideology around very critical aspects of your life. Yes. If
you believe Android is better for certain reasons, you use that. But if iOS offers you
something that you absolutely need, you can't just abandon it. You can't just ignore it
because you believe in something. So I think you have to choose what's best for you at
the end of the day. At the end, you know. That's rational. Yeah. Very rational point.
I actually have a specific analogy that I use to describe an Apple product. It's akin
to having a steak in your front yard and your chain to the steak on your front yard. And
within this radius, you are happy. But if you ever want to get out of this radius, you
will never, ever get out of this bubble. But in it, it's pretty. As soon as you ever want
to go, you're screwed. Yeah. OK. I mean, I think but I feel like they both even like
Blackberry does that to an extent. But what about my what about my issues around as a
Linux user? I'm a little incensed that they're taking my baby and they're making it a whore,
a two dime whore at that a two bit whore. I mean, do you get my way off on that? What
do you guys think? Apache allows anything. But if we were going to get upset about what
Tivo did, how come we're not upset about what this what's happening here? Because I think
we're being I think Android and any any I won't even say Android, I think any passionate
mobile operating system experience that we're passionate about spoon feeds us B.S. and sunshine
to a point where we're fat, dumb and happy. And so regardless of what mobile platform
you're in, if it involves an app store and some level of vendor lock in, you're so into
that because you're enjoying the experience. You're really not interested or even that
concerned about the negative side of it. I know I fall into that category. I'm I'm aware
of it because I like to be educated. I just can't get myself to care enough to do anything
about it. That's a terrible thing to say, but it's true. That's why I'm I'm happy with
Android, despite knowing the fact that I've been indexed and doing decimal system by Google.
I don't know. I almost feel like the rational thing to do when I when I sort of weigh all
the pros and cons, I go into more depth on quarter radios, I kind of feel like jump off
Android and wait for a couple of years for Firefox OS to get rockin. And, you know, wait
for it to get a good messaging application, wait for it to get WebRTC integrated, wait
for, you know, some kind of ecosystem to build up around it and then get a Firefox OS phone
and then just be like, OK, I'm going to I'm going to live here. Or I'm going to. Yeah,
in the meantime, civilization is important because a lot of TVs and embedded devices
run Linux, whether we know or not, it's allowed the use of many like it to spread to many
factors of our life without us even knowing our cars. It would never be able to be put
in a what is that new electric awesome car there? Yeah, Tesla. Yeah, the Tesla. We'd
never have the Tesla running Linux if it wasn't too visible. Right. You see the Tivo
issue. Go ahead. Yeah, go ahead. The Tivo issue is also Tivo never acknowledges Linux
is there, whereas Google does actually acknowledge it, but just they don't market it. Yeah, but
remember, I mean, remember what just happened with the Chromecast. I mean, that that's disappointing.
That is not encouraging when it's just basically a bare Linux installation. I think it might
have been a Buntu based or Google to base with a binary named Chromecast running or
Gentoo. That's what it was Gentoo with a binary running. That's the Chromecast app.
It was a Linux box. It's a Linux device. Why not promote that to make? I mean, because
if they base their style, their stack on Linux, then doesn't it benefit them to show how Linux
can be used in like all of these different use cases? Like, it seems like it's not just
good for Linux, but it's good for them to not from a marketing perspective. If I'm not
mistaken, it's a yeah, it is a marketing thing, right? The Chrome, the Chrome ideology that's
easy to use. So if they call it a Chromecast, not like a Linux cast, it then sounds like
it's this easy to use thing that sort of relates to the web. And so it relates to the Chrome
streaming thing because a lot of what they do is they stream from the Chrome browser
to that device. So they want to make it sound like the two products are linked is sort of
my understanding.
Yeah, right. Okay. From like a, okay, okay. Yeah. From like a, oh, I know what that is
kind of standpoint.
Well, to give you an example, I work for a company that recently went through a name
change and of course the original name, no one ever heard of, but the brand name, people
are well aware of it. And you know, we don't, all the branding efforts go into the flagship
product name and the flagship brand name versus the tech, the underlying technology behind
it, because honestly no one cares. Geeks might care, but Joe user doesn't give a flying rip.
Yeah. I mean, a lot of windows users, you ask them, well, what version of windows you
have? I don't know. I got the one that came on my computer. They don't have a clue. I
have an HP or I have a Dell. You know, that's, that's the brand that they've been taught
to associate with. So I think that's the same thing with Google.
And there's still, there's still that, that, you know, mindset that, oh, it runs Linux.
Oh, it's, it's, you know, you know, just for hackers, it's just for command line and all
this other stuff. And which is obviously wrong, but yeah, you get a windows power user aware
of it and then they're start spreading thought everywhere. Absolutely.
Yeah.
Thing is, the thing about open source is that you don't actually have control over what
somebody else does with it. If Rome disagrees with what Cinnamon is doing, they can stop
it. If Ubuntu disagrees with what elementary OS is doing, they have no say in it. So similarly,
if somebody takes a Linux kernel under the, under legal licenses or whatever, and does
whatever to it, nobody else has a choice to, nobody else can stop it because it's open
source. They have the option to modify it and use it as they see fit, you know.
I agree.
Okay. Let me give you another aspect of, of Android that's bothering me. And I've mentioned
this before on previous shows, but it goes back to the original getting into the carriers.
So let's hit the, let's hit the way back machine. Back when Jobs was still kicking it at Apple
and in full evil Jobs force, he went around to every single carrier, starting with Verizon
and said, here's our product. We'd like to sell it on your wireless network. And then
as soon as the conversation got too great, we'd like to preload our applications and
do things like carrier IQ. Does everybody in the chat room who's giving me a hard time
about iOS being a spy device, does everybody remember carrier IQ? Because that got loaded
up on our free phones and that was a nightmare. If you don't know what carrier IQ is, go
Google that because your device probably still has it. So, so Apple said, no, go screw yourself.
And they walked and they ended up going to the smallest wireless carrier in America.
And that was singular. They were the small fry that everybody thought was a joke. And
they were the only ones willing to take Apple up on their offer. And then we all know what
happened to singular. They blew up and they became AT&T. And now to this day, Apple rolls
into Verizon store and it's not shitted up with a bunch of Verizon apps. And when they
roll into sprint, you don't get your sprint sports cast broadcasted to your iPhone, right?
They still to this day say, go, go F yourself. And even in China, they just blew off a deal
with the biggest manual with the biggest wireless carrier in China because they wanted to load
it up with some crap. And Google has never, never had the balls to do that. In fact, Google
sells it on the exact opposite, just like Ubuntu touch is going to. They sell it on
shit it up all you want. And in fact, shit it up so bad, you can never get an update
ever. You can have the top of the line number one Android phone, best built phone ever still
being sold as a top of line phone and it will never get an update. We don't care. And that
is a complete FU to the users. That is an FU that is disregarding every lesson we have
learned about internet security, about software update, about platform maintenance and about
being a good steward of a platform and pushing it forward so that way developers can take
advantage of new features. They forfeited all of it just for market share because they
want the information. And at the end of the day, that really upsets me. Oh yeah, no, I
can understand being upset by it, but I think you got to understand the motivation behind
it. Apple's motivation for doing that is not to benefit the user. It is because they're
purist and they want it to have it their way and that's how they've always been. Think
different. It's all about their approach. I agree, but doesn't that exactly line up
with a customer's needs? In this case, not always. I mean, it can lead them down routes.
No, it's definitely an important and it's an important thing that people need to know.
I think that's an important differential that when people are making the decision what phone
to get, they need to know this stuff. That's really important. I mean, basically, I feel
like every Android device sold in the store should have a big warning label on it that
says, warning in six months to a year. This will be a walking exploit in your pocket.
This will not get updates. This is a security flaw. If you want a good device that's updated,
please go to play.google.com and buy it there. Or check out CyanogenMod. I mean, every Android
box needs to have that disclaimer because when I bought my Android device, I assumed
I would at least get six months worth of updates. I got no idea. Maybe I will, maybe I won't,
but you know what? Tomorrow, every freaking iPhone user for the last three years is getting
iOS 7. And there's no reason Android can't do that.
Well, and I suspect that...
See, the thing about Apple is that they have the ability to tell the carriers to just bend
them to their will, unlike Google who has it the other way around.
That's crap. Google had that power. Google just didn't want to exercise it because they
wanted the market share. They could have stuck to it. But you know what the other thing was
is their product wasn't good enough. I mean, if we go back to the G1, let's be honest,
that was not good enough.
No, the G1 was garbage.
It wasn't really until the Droid, right, that Android really was usable. I mean, that's
when I switched.
I suppose so, yes.
So I mean, I feel like they torpedoed their users to compete with Apple.
Well, and I think part of the difference is too is that Google is interested in their
penetration into the market at all costs as much as possible. And that's their goal, market,
market, market, market, market, where Apple is ideology, ideology, ideology. And in this
particular case, it aligns with good user experience, and that's great. But I do agree
with the whole disclosure thing. I think that's important. But I think that we got lucky with
Apple in that it just happened to fall under our benefit. And maybe they're even smart
enough to realize that.
I don't know. I think what Apple, I think honestly what did it in a big part was Steve
Jobs wanted to be able to get everybody to push the latest features out. They wanted
essentially this update thing because when you look at it right now, it's something like
some ridiculous stat like distributor to the Android OS.
This is the problem, though. They could have. They could have in the light. They could have
structured the licensing the way Microsoft structures the Windows phone licensing where
they allow for some time. But it was within the contract that they have to meet a certain
window. And I think that would have been completely appropriate. And it's Microsoft learning from
twenty five plus years in the PC licensing business had to handle this. And the reason
why Apple wanted to have a pristine OS on there is that way they could push out the
updates. And the reason isn't just security because it probably isn't their primary motivator.
The reason is, is because they want developers to target the new features, which is a massive
train wreck on Android. And they're now beginning to fix it with the play API, which is, by
the way, completely closed source. So great. They're fixing this fragmentation problem
with more closed source software. Yay, Google, way to go.
So in the meantime, every every like it's like something like ninety five percent of
iPhones run the latest OS that gives developers this massive opportunity for creating brand
new feature rich applications that take advantage of everything these new OS is and phones can
do. That isn't that is not as optional on Android. And it is just yet another. It's
not so it's not just the security thing. It's the feature is the end user. And it's about
getting the investment out of my six hundred dollar device.
I would agree. I would even go so far as to say I suspect at some point you're going to
see toward individual hardware manufacturers a couple of class action lawsuits. I'd say
the odds are fairly reasonable in that regard, just because there's not there's a lot of
marketing promises that make it sound like this is going to constantly be updated when
in fact that's not the case. That's for a court to decide. I don't know. But I suspect
that it's probably going to end up taking care of itself at some point because eventually
people will have enough and will have to make that decision of, wow, not buying that. I'm
not buying HTC again or I'm not buying Motorola again or whatever it may be. They're going
to have to make those choices, you know, based on those experiences must have, you know,
an update repository. So then future phones will fill this void of like security void.
They will eventually have repositories that you can say update the kernel or operating
system. But right now it's a void. That's up to Google if they want to do that or not.
Well, here's an interesting idea that dream dream points out, like if HTC one sold me
like this overall not warranty, but like if I could pay HTC $35 or whatever, kind of like,
you know, you go buy a new, you know, a new OS. If I could buy the new OS for my HTC one,
like I would buy it for a computer. Sure. I would do that. I would totally do that.
And I think that would actually be not an ideal solution, but it's totally what I would.
It's at least a workable solution. When I think squeaky wheel gets the grease. I think
if P if we, if people continue to educate non aware folks of this situation to where
they can then become noisy about it, then I think we might begin seeing these changes,
but I think that's the thing. The best thing we can do right now is to make people aware
of it. Not to say you should go one direction or the other, but to be like, Hey, by the
way, when you're buying your phone, are you asking these questions on, are you implementing
that into your decision? Cause I think that's an important thing to do, but you can have
company company a company B company C and they're all going to have different business
models. Um, the way that they're successful is, um, either they have great marketing and
or, um, their, their, uh, business plan or their, their direction aligns with customers
needs and wants, um, or they just have a fantastic product.
Right. It'll be nice as if Google in their contract, like with HTC and Samsung said after
a year, you know, you have to release X to the community so that way they can maintain
or something because no, well, no, I mean, I think a Cyanogen mod and Google play devices
and nexus devices are not a good enough answer because they only apply to the people that
are in our IRC and on this mumble server and listening to this podcast. They don't apply
to our, you know, to the immediate group outside the tech circle.
There is a solution to that though. Like, like with, for example, neck nexus devices
could, if they, the reason people don't buy nexus devices is because they're too expensive
and they're not even that expensive. They're like an extra 150, 100 maybe. But if you,
if they had a plan where you could buy the, the nexus devices from Google on a monthly
basis, just kind of like the jump plans or something like that, then a lot of people
would see that as a much better option. And then people would have phones that are not,
that are not like mine where it took 18 months to get an update.
Yes. However, I don't think Google can actually do that because that would require them to
sell the phone through the carrier and the carrier is not going to want them to not put
the carrier software on there.
It all comes back to that original deal. It all hinges on that.
That is why Google sells the phone separately. I'm convinced. And I think all of this goes
back to the evolution of the smartphone market. Apple with Steve Jobs took a risk by not selling
it to these carriers that wanted to put their crapware on it. And I think because he was
the, they were the first ones to the market that they had the ability to say no and not
just, you know, install the crapware and go for market penetration because they were there
pretty much first. They were able to do that and as soon as they rose to power, now they
have the market by the balls and they can say, well, Verizon, they're selling, you know,
the iPhone in massive quantities over at AT&T. If you want to sell it, you can't put your
crapware on it. And they sort of have Verizon by the balls now because they don't want customers
to go to AT&T.
Yeah, it took them like two to three years to get them on Verizon.
And so I think that's how they had the handle, whereas Google came late to the party just
like Ubuntu phone is. And now they really need to cater to the carrier so that they
can push their phone everywhere and try and gain market capitalization. Whereas Apple
already had this.
I mean, we see what Google had to do reflected in what Ubuntu touch has to do only magnified,
right? I mean, they have this massive carrier advisory group and they're literally pitching
it as carrier custom as a carrier customizable platform where you slot in your own services.
In fact, one of the quote unquote features is that you can put your own app store in
there. You can put your own, you know, media back into it.
That sounds worse than Google.
Yeah, exactly. It does. It does. It does. And I guess the thing is I have to ask myself
is if, if we're getting to the point where, uh, for some of us, like, you know, we could
get the nexus devices, you know, and we can get the signage and mods and we can make buy,
we can make do we're fortunate like that, but what do we do for everybody else? Like,
I mean, this is a problem where I feel like, I don't know, because I see an opportunity
for a business and or a, or a nonprofit foundation, one of the other, and it sounds like they're
trying to go back and retroactively fix this by making all of their Google applications
a separate package from the OS now.
Right.
And it sounds like, you know, they acknowledge that they kind of screwed up on the deal where
they let carriers and let vendors customize the phone OS and now they want to distribute
their apps separately and that controls most of the software functionality on the phone.
So now you can get updates to most of the core applications. Yeah. You still can't get
complete core OS updates. You can't get kernel updates necessarily, but at least you get
the Google apps.
And you get some security updates, but not necessarily all security. Yeah. It's not a
good, it's not a good solution.
At least you get the Chrome browser updates, right? I mean, I think that's probably one
of the most important things that they're going to be giving out with that.
But I think if enough geeks get passionate about this enough to where they want to come
together and they want to look at the more open source, you know, centric solutions,
like what you're talking about in our community, if that gets to be loud and scary enough and
enough people care, I think eventually you're going to see some entity catering to that
at some level.
It's not going to appeal to Joe average, but to, you know, to people, to geeks that do
care about these things, you know, I think it'll take care of itself.
So then why do we have, so all of this sounds completely reasonable. So then why do we have
things in our community like Ubuntu shame, iPhone shame? Why do we, why is there this,
why is there this lack of critical analysis on Google and, and why is there this sort
of pre pretty, um, assumption that, uh, you know, somebody must be an idiot if they're
using the iPhone, they must be because we're it's honestly, and pardon my French, but we're
fart sniffers, uh, geeks as a whole, you know, especially Android geeks and, and they are,
it's like, well, you know, clearly I'm, I know what I'm doing. You're an idiot. Um,
well clearly I, I see the benefits and the, and the functionality benefits of using the
platform I'm using and I'm, I'm, I'm their king in that regard. Cause I look at Android
and then I look at iPhone and I'm like, yeah, right. I can understand that. Yeah. And so
that I get in that mindset. And so I will be your representative, you know, tool bag
here and pointing out that I walk around looking at iPhone, yours is going, Oh God, why the
hell would you use that? Not really stopping to consider there are in fact some advantages
to it. And I'm, I'm definitely guilty of that. So I think that as a whole, as a community,
a lot of Android folks do fall into that, you know, but I did use an iPhone for a long
time so I can back it up and not just say, I'm just talking to Android. I, you know,
I used to, you know, I, I, I've been, I walked that path. It had its preferences in your
needs and you're going to use what fits your needs. Not because it's popular. I mean, I
know people go out and buy new phones because the new hotness, but it's, it's, it's, it's
what, it's what you need. And, and people as us as a community or not, maybe not us,
but people in general should really just stop hating on other people just for the sake of
hating out other people because they're using something different or look down on instead
of the grass is always greener. The grass is always Browner on the other side.
I think for geeks and our people in our community, I think that's absolutely true. I think for
Joe average, I would absolutely say 120% people buy the latest idiot thing on the television.
Just average people. I see it all the time with the young, my nephews, poster child.
Oh my God, you see that one phone? I don't even know what the hell it does, but God,
it looks great. I got to get it. You know, you got those types of folks as well.
Yeah.
Non tech savvy people purchasing new hardware that they, they don't really know what's,
what's going on.
You don't even need it.
Yeah.
Things like that. Or here, here does, here's something that, that doesn't really help,
the case is you have the marketing, the commercials that's that, what was it? I think it was one
of the Samsung's commercials that was showing like the old folks in line waiting for the
iPhone.
That was awesome.
Yeah.
And that, and that's kids pay attention to that. Believe me, they really do. You ask
my nephew, he's 16 years old. Would you want a brand new iPhone or would you want my used
note too? There is not even a conversation there. He wants the note too, because that's
what he's been told is awesome. He's been told the iPhone is something dinosaurs use.
Well, all right.
And it sucks, but you know.
As far as the geek community goes, I think there's a stigma attached with something popular
because I mean, what I'm saying is Ubuntu is popular. Apple, iOS is popular. That's
why we must hate it. We must always root for Luke Skywalker, the underdog.
That's true. Yeah. That's an interesting perspective. I'm considering that.
Yeah, perhaps. I think, I think I want to, you know, I think maybe for a future conversation,
I want to talk about how a lot of these open platforms ended up saving their data back
to closed source programs and platforms that are really generally meant for tracking users.
But I think that could be a conversation for a future episode.
Yeah.
All right guys. Well, good on you. Thanks for kicking that around. And I, you know,
I leave it, I leave it kind of buttoned up with, you know, I'm left with, I try to find
the Zen of the situation and tell myself that honestly the HTC One, which is running 4.1.2
has everything I need. Really. I mean, there's nothing like in the new updates that I have
to have and I'm, I'm trying to be careful. Although I did just get recently bit with,
with spyware crap, but I try to be careful and studious. And so it's not really functionally,
it's you know, if there, if there was something really confidential and secret that I didn't
want logged by Google, I'd probably just not put it on my phone.
Well, and as someone as myself, who is, I would say I'm reasonably new to Android, so
I can still be kind of a newbie in this regard. What's your view on things like lookout and,
and anti, you know, security software? Is it crap?
No, I mean, no, I mean, I've tried it. I had a,
Cause I have no idea. I mean like, this is all new to me.
No, I, I used one of those programs actually to clean it up. I had a, I have a program
on here that scans it and it went through and found and cleaned it up for me. So I mean,
they don't seem to be totally, totally a waste of it. It seems so ridiculous. I guess.
It is. Yeah. And that's what puts all the overhead on my old phone. You know, you were
talking about how it was slow. That's, that's where a lot of the overhead comes from is
running lookout. And I, and it's, it's seemed to have kept my phone. It actually caught
me from keeping a few things off my phone. As a matter of fact, I remember when I switched
cause I, I, I followed the same path that you followed. I even tried windows phone,
you know, like the old, I had an old HTC windows phone that was just like this ridiculous joke.
And so when the iPhone came, I was impressed and I got like the, I didn't buy the first
one cause I was like, no way I'm going to buy first gen Apple, anything. And I think
I got like the, the three GS. I can't remember. I got somewhere around in there and I remember
thinking it was pretty good and I waited until the droid came out on Verizon. And then when
the droid came out, I remember switching and thinking, God, this feels like an actual computer.
Like this is, this is like, you know, and that was my feeling. So I, Android fits my
user style. My, the style, I'm a, I'm a power user. Android fits that better. And I have
options out there like Cyanogen mod, you know, just like I can use encryption to, and I can
use bid message or whatever. Right? Like I have all these options. I just, I wish that
when we just stop at the end of the day, I wish we would just think more critically about
some of it. Well, and I'm holding out a lot of hope more and more for Firefox OS. I really
want to see this be the solution with a company behind it. That's going to keep the value.
Even if Firefox OS is great. You've got, you've got a couple of years of, oh, it's going to
be a little bit. Yeah. Yeah. You got a couple of years. But I'm holding out hope longterm.
I'm thinking long game here. Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, I want to read a couple of emails
before we run. Peter wrote into the show. He says, hi Matt and Chris. I just backed
a zero AD on Indiegogo and then later had my credit card compromised by a payment made
to Samsung telecom in the US. That's pretty strange since I'm based out of the UK and
I've had no other US transactions except for Indiegogo. Who knows? He says, but by the
way, I also moved to mint 15 and the Chrome browser on all my machines. Steam was the
last thing holding me back from Linux. I don't think Linux games are cheap or gamers are
cheap going back to our conversation from a few episodes ago. In my case, I already
own most of the games. Yeah. And then of course when he moved over, he just downloaded them
on the Linux version. And what we kind of sussed out, I don't remember how we got to
the bottom of this. I think somebody wrote into the show. Steam, it's not just the survey.
So steam collects usage stats via that survey, but then also after you've played a game on
a certain operating system, after a certain amount of time, it also then logs you on that
operating system. So if you have a bunch of games that you bought on the Windows side,
all of those purchases are counted for Windows. And then when you move over to Linux, which
probably some people are doing, and you redownload them, it's not until you've played each one
of those games for a certain amount of time that they're still counted as a Linux user.
Oh, so that's a double whammy then. Okay. And then he had a question after being bit
by that credit card problem they had. He said, can you guys recommend what internet security
software I should be using on the now sinking windows platform? I used a combination of
McAfee and spy bot surgeon destroy. Thanks in advance, Peter. So is he asking about security
software for Linux or Linux? Uh, well, I would, I mean, not a good firewall. Yeah. So here's
what I would say. Don't run his route, which you, which you're not probably on a mint 15
and um, use really good passwords everywhere. Maybe use something like key pass or last
pass. My personal favorite don't execute random commands or random binaries or things
of that sort. I would say the most important security precaution you could take on Linux
is don't run random binaries, like Matt just said, and used a different password for every
website. Yeah. Yeah. That's really, Oh, and uh, don't, don't install Java. That would
be another, you know what? Yeah. Don't, don't, don't use Java unless you need to. Yeah. And
don't bother with the browser plugin if you don't need to. Right. Don't. Yeah. That's
a good one. Why not? Um, and, and then like in the chat, in the chat, keep your updates,
keep your, you know, stay current with the OS updates. And when mint 15 stops getting
updates, you know, just remember that on mint, you're going to do a full reload and you're
going to upgrade. You're not, there's not an upgrade path. You're going to load the
next version. But I mean, let's be honest. Sometimes it's good to start clean. If you're
really, really concerned about, you know, that's the elephant in the room of course
is people surf about content. If you're going to be one of those guys and really, I, as
a guy, yeah, I dealt with a lot of men, a lot of married men that came in begging for
help and I actually had a special program for them. It's called the live CD or the live
USB without writeable options. I'm telling you, what about like a porn VM? I never thought
about this. I just thought of a great business. Like totally just go all QVC with it. Right?
Like a porn VM that lives inside a true Crip volume, right? Okay. So I've come into, Oh,
are you busted again? He's all, Oh, now you can have another, here's the pitch. Now you
can have another computer in your computer and it's encrypted, right? Call it the porn
box and it's based on virtual box.
Oh my God. I'm on this. This is going to happen. This is the next moneymaker. I have no ethics.
Yeah, let's do it. All right. Distributed via bit torrent, right? Um, all right. Uh,
so I had it, let's see, I think I didn't, I have another one. I just accidentally closed
it. Um, Oh man, I'm a bad person. I'm a bad person. I just closed the other email. Sorry
about that. But I'll look for it. Okay. And I got off on a tangent. I got all excited,
talking about Peron. It gets me going. I didn't have a big message. It's here. So here's the
arch challenge. Follow up. This came from Carl and he says, hi Chris and Matt. I started
to watch the show about three months ago and I've been a fan ever since. I know I'm a bit
late to the arch challenge, but I wanted to mention it anyways. First, I should say that
the first Linux I installed was Slackware 2.0. Hmm. Okay. So that's, that's, that's
quite a while ago, but, Oh, this is where it takes this work. There's always a, but,
but after moving to Apple for a good 10 years, I forgot most of it. Uh, anyway, I saw the
episode with the arch challenge and I thought, yeah, I should give it a go. So I did install
of arch and when I first came out and got it started, I was a little disappointed when
I found out there wasn't an installer. Okay. Yeah. So I'm kind of, well, there isn't, there
isn't, I'll get into that. Should we have not, I mean, there isn't a separate ISO, but
yeah, not officially. I just, I didn't, when we did the arch challenge, I didn't mean for
somebody that to take the arch challenge that was at that level. Yeah, right. Because like,
if you didn't know that about arch, I didn't whether it was intended for you. So I'm impressed
that he went for it, especially after living on the Mac for 10 years. So good on, good
on you, Carl. So he goes on to say, I did the arch install and, um, after, after three
tries I succeeded and now I'm running arch. Uh, and he's sticking with it. The bad point
about this, and here's the downside he says to arch and, and actually I have found this
to be the major disadvantage to arch too. And I'm wondering if you agree, Matt, uh,
he says the bad point is now he can't go back to any of the distro because there's no match
for arch.
Uh, you know, I would say that for, it depends on the person. For me, I dual booted arch
and Manjaro for a long time. And just because I wanted to really understand what that was
going to be like. Yeah. From a meta standpoint, I consider arch, Manjaro, Linux, all that
to kind of be the, yeah, I did, I did found some distinct, there's definitely some differences.
There's definitely some differences. I would absolutely say Manjaro is totally not arch.
It just happens to share some similarities. Is that bit you now? Did that bite you in
the butt?
Um, honestly, no. I, you know, I, you know, with arch I just kind of, it's, I think it's
actually stolen the partition. It's hardly ever used it. But with Manjaro, it's like
all the stuff that I was reading that was negative or they screwed this up or screwed
that up. As long as you're on the mailing list and you pay attention, you know, I mean,
and they, and, and yes, it is officially they say it's arch, but there's some, they use
their own repos. There's a lot of things that they do do completely differently. Age software,
that sort of thing. But it's kind of like for it's, you know, like it's arch for people
don't care, care about security. I would say it's for people that don't really aren't paranoid
about security. I'd say it's a more accurate statement. Yes, it's, it's often a month or
two older, but I've probably still fresher than a lot of distros. And on all these horror
stories I've read are generally, there's never anything to really back up an actual use case
scenario. So based on my own usage, I would say that arch is awesome. And if you want
to go that route, go that. But as far as men, Gerald being scary, a bullshit, I'm sorry.
It's just that I, you know, I look at it, I have a single problem with it. Oh, neither
with arch either.
So you and I have been, um, um, you and I off, off, uh, off camera and talked a little
bit recently about preparing for the Ubuntu 1310 review. Yeah. And the problem I have
with it is, uh, now I got a good way to do this because I've got on the bonobos, I've
got USB three and I got a, um, I got a USB three, a one terabyte drive. And it's one
of those hybrid drives that has SSD and, and, and then the, so it's, it's pretty fast and
I'll load Ubuntu on that. And you know, I'll, I'll be fine. I'm not looking forward to it
at all. And not because, I mean, honestly, I remember I used to run it. That was my previous
distro, but what it really is for me. And I know I've said this a lot and it's so funny
because it's what I was like, what's a, you are, that's what I was like, you are no dude.
It's all about the AUR. It's all about it because at the end of the day, Katie is Katie.
Gnome is gnome. It doesn't matter what, you know, you put, you put your theme on it. You
set your background, you load your favorite apps. They're all the same. Yeah. But the
AUR buddy, I mean like, you know, that was, that was it for it for me. And that's what,
you know, let's say Majuro disappears tomorrow. That's not a big deal. I still got the arch
installs roll back to it. No biggie that for me, it was the AUR experience that I cared
about. I, the, the arch way is awesome. I just don't care. Um, you know, what I cared
about was the, you know, the arch user repository. That's what sold me on the experience in general,
whether it be whatever it is, you know, what, whatever the distro is that happens to embrace
that as seamlessly. Hey Matt. Yeah. Uh, president Obama's here. He, hello everybody. Uh, he
wanted me to make a point that, uh, he wanted me to mention that Gentoo is awesome and the
Gentoo is incredible. Um, there we have fulfilled our duty. If our president says that it's
awesome and clearly, you know, I guess Obama's, I guess Obama's a big Gentoo user. Who knew
you'd think he'd be busier than that. You thought he was an apple guy, but you know,
this is good to know. Uh, he also says, by the way, he's loving the new show. And, uh,
he also just wanted to point out that he liked the Star Trek segment. Oh, no kidding. Oh,
he's a Star Trek fan. We got a Star Trek fan. We got a Star Trek fan. And he said that in
Carl, something to be a bit message. Uh, and we have the bit message address in the Linux
action show show notes. Um, I'm going to just, uh, mumble room, just one quick, uh, shout
to you guys. If there's anything you guys want to touch on, if anybody had last thing
on the tip of their tongue before we run, uh, now is your chance. I wanted to say was,
uh, why can't system 76 just make phones and put whatever we want on it. I'm saying, I'm
thinking more like a tablet. I think a tablet, it would be awesome. Tablet. Yeah. You know,
I'm kind of, there would be a use for Nome three and Ubuntu and unity and all that. I,
I, you know, one of the things, one of the things we got a little, a little, a little
S for last week, Matt was, we talked about that. Remember that block phone where like
each thing, that's where I'm, that's where that with Firefox OS. Oh yeah. I mean, I
have to be honest. I mean, I, I acknowledge that's pretty unpractical that that thing's
going to ship. And even when it did ship, like it might not really work out really that
well, but I love to just think about that in a different way. And when you think about
a hardware platform like that, I mean, one of the things that really makes me sad about
is apparently a self fulfilling prophecy of the post PC era because PC manufacturers can't
figure out how to make computers. People want to actually spend their money on. I love the
idea that we all pretend like we haven't just had this global economic meltdown and that
nobody's got as much money as they used to have. And that everybody in the, in, at least
in the middle class that is the, is the bulk of people who buy these machines is struggling.
But let's all pretend like instead it's tablets that's causing the sales to drop down right
now. It's the fact that everybody's money is a little more precious and I'm not going
to spend it unless you give me something to pay for that I really, really want. It's more
about value. So instead they make these cheap tablets. That's fine. Whatever. I'm not going
to get all worked up about it. But what, what pains me about the loss of the PC is this
build it yourself if you want option and load any OS you want option. And I want that same
and that's what I loved about the block phone, right? I mean, even if it doesn't happen,
I love that it was just making us think about a future where that kind of possibility existed
where you have the choice of deciding not only what hardware is going to go into it,
but also what operating system and what software you're going to plug into it to where you,
if you, if something screws up, it was your fault because you did it. Right? That's awesome.
Democracy of a phone. Yeah, exactly. Right. Exactly. Yeah. I have a question. How is it
going to be different than how is it now? Because you still, I mean, if it's a lot easier
to install cyanogen or whatever on it, you still have a 95% users being windows and you
know, just like that, you still have a certain percentage being Android, certain percentage
being iOS. If you want to load another OS, you still have to do a lot of work. You have
to install it yourself. So we'd be back in the same position. If that's where other third
party companies will come in. That's what I'm thinking. Those little stores down the
road that would unlock your phone. It would say, do you want to try something else? We'll
do it for you overnight if you like, or in the next, whatever. Exactly. Well, I mean,
think about going back to system 76, you could have vendors like system 76 that take the
hardware and do the custom builder, do they take an OEM product and they create a solution
around it. And then they, they put the OS that that market wants, right? And then they
support it and they back it up and they build a whole business around it. You could have
that. So yes, I mean, so are you taking this to Danica then? There's a, here's a new business
idea. Yeah, I like that. Why would that, why hasn't that happened? I mean, that hasn't
happened on PCs yet. Why would that be more possible on the phone? Isn't, isn't aren't
companies like system 76 and za reason, um, examples of that happening? Yes. Right. But
they're not as popular. They're nowhere near as popular as they should be or could be.
Windows still controls the market. Linux is still 1%. I mean, windows Vista has more market
share. Well, I mean, it would shut us all up though, wouldn't it? We're going to have
to be moaning about this. We just move over to a system 76 or there's actually something
out now called the open moco device. Yeah, I remember that. Yeah, I, I, I think some
of this, I mean, we got to scratch our Gabe beards here for a second and look at his conference
keynote that he just gave that we're going to talk about more on Sunday. Uh, you know,
he says the Linux is the future of gaming. I don't, I mean, who knows if he's right,
but I've been saying now for a while that as Microsoft just continues to screw it up
real bad and they're going to just keep screwing it up because they have to, because that's
the direction they got to move in. And you just wait for Apple, man. They are going to
bone the Mac desktop like nobody's business. You just wait till the iOS, that thing put
arm in it, in, in their machines. Everybody's going to need everybody who needs a truck
is going to have to bail and good old Linux is going to be there with system D and Wayland
and great video drivers and steam and hopefully a desktop that is usable. And I really think
that while these are today's problems, these might be solved in 2015, 2016 and beginning
to be solved in 2014. Are they already starting to be so exactly how I said that everything
is going to be, you know, thin client remote that like remote processing of everything
and only thin clients will eventually do that and screw us. And that's what Chrome and OS
is going to be. And that's what Android is going to be. That's their, that's their value
card. Yes. Yeah. I think everyone should have a little nasi in the corner. All cryptography's
math is correct. The implementations, sometimes buggy, but the math of crypto is correct.
Don't worry about being tin foil hatty about it.
So I leave us on that point. I mean, like, uh, we have some today problems with Android
that really bother me. Um, and, and I'm not actually sure that we've even scratched the
surface of this conversation around Google, Android, cloud services, monitoring and all
of that. But I think what we do see is solutions that are being created, right? We see solutions
in the PC industry that might actually end up being a lot of people's salvation. And
we might eventually with things like sailfish and fire Fox OS, I think we'll see solutions
there too. And you know, we'll just talk about them as they come up. But as of right now,
I don't begrudge anybody for going out on Friday and buying themselves an iPhone. I
say good on you. I'll be happy with my HTC one. I'm going to stick with it for at least
now. I don't know. I could see you hanging out in a, hanging out in a car somewhere with
a hoodie and sunglasses and a baseball bat watching for folks at the Verizon store. Yeah,
yeah, yeah. I could see that too. All right. Mumble room. Well, thanks you guys for joining
us. Hey, uh, you guys in the download audience, if you want to join us live, you can, uh,
we do this on, uh, Tuesdays over at jblive.tv at, uh, 2 p.m. Pacific, which, uh, I believe
clocks in at like 9 p.m. UTC. If you want to join us over at jblive.tv or jblive.info,
we have a mumble server, which you can participate in, or we have an IRC chat room and, uh, we
watch that too. And then we also have a little, a pre and post show that, uh, is pretty great.
And don't forget to tune into this Sunday's Linux action show. We've got a big show coming
up. I am going to talk a little bit about, uh, there's a topic that's been coming up
and up and up and over and over again is this building the personal cloud, right? Building
your own cloud on your land because that's really the most secure, but it's not just
about security. It's also about reliability, performance, and it's about being able to,
for example, my house could be a, my house is a big Netflix house, but Netflix doesn't
run so good on the Linux. So we've been moving that in the house. If there's a series of
the family likes rip it and I put it on the server for them. There's a lot of things you
can bring into the internal cloud, but how do you protect that home cloud? Well, one
of the oldest standing popular topics on Linux action show goes back to the very first couple
of episodes is firewalls. This Sunday, we're going to retackle that topic. Also bring back
some of the things we've talked about, cover Gabe's speech at the Linux con, Linux con
and a whole bunch of other stuff, Matt. So I think we're going to have ourselves a great
show. Oh, I'm excited about it. There's some great topics in there and you're fresh back
from a little trip. That's awesome. And I had Saturday and Sunday off. That was, that
was actually quite nice. And you know, I was even able to play our pre show from Friday
on Sunday's live show. So people who showed up on Sunday still got to see a little bit
of that's awesome. Yeah, that was good for them. Yeah. All right, everyone. Don't forget,
you can contact the show. You can go over to Jupiter broadcasting.com pop that contact
link at the top of our show and choose unplugged from the dropdown box or even better start
a thread in our subreddit over at Linux action show.reddit.com. We check that out. All right,
Matt. Well, I'll see you on Sunday. I will see you on Sunday. Yeah, thanks. Thanks to
you, man. All right, everyone. Well, thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of
Linux Unplugged. See you right back here next Tuesday.