Running Linux on a toaster, sure, that's cool.
But what about a computer mouse that's a computer mouse?
No, I mean it.
Hey guys, how's it going?
So what you're looking at is something
I ingeniously named the computer mouse.
This is a completely functional computer
inside of a totally 100% completely normal sized mouse.
Basically, I designed a mouse in Fusion 360, printed it out,
and then added a Raspberry Pi Zero, a 1.5 inch screen,
a battery, and a keyboard.
Yeah, he said a screen, Wes.
This mouse has a fold-out screen,
and this thing runs Linux.
How cool is this?
I really think what you're gonna really use this for?
Winning nerd battles.
Sure, you're having a great LAN party.
No one else has a computer inside their computer mouse.
Right, you show up and they're like,
hey, where's your computer?
I'm like, this is my computer.
It runs Linux.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 284, for January 15th, 2019.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, it's currently freezing,
it's you-know-what off down in the heart of Tejas.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Mr. Payne.
Now, we have a heck of a show.
It's good to be back.
After getting all married up and traveling down to Texas,
we put together a show packed full of community news,
including some really surprising stories this week.
Dalton will stop by from the Ubuntu Touch Project
to tell us about their new release,
and then Neil joins us to explain
and really put into context all of the hubbub going on
around ZFS on Linux,
how the BSDs are rebasing their implementations
on the Linux version,
and the changes the kernel maintainers made this week
to block the ZFS module from working with Linux 5.0.
It's amazing, and there's a lot going on,
and there's a ton to get into.
We'll play that for you in a little bit in the show,
and then, if we don't go too long,
we have a big batch of pics.
I'm gonna tell you about my trip down here a little bit,
and then we'll put it all, wrap it up in a bow,
and send it off to the internet,
but the only thing missing
from what would otherwise be a perfect recipe
would be participation from the audience,
some crazy idea,
where a group of Linux-loving people
could just join an open Mumble server
and participate in our show.
In fact, why don't we even do that?
Time-appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello. Hello.
Hello, everybody. Hello.
Hello, hello.
Thank you for making it, even on Brexit Day over there,
on Brexit vote day.
Oh, it's always Brexit Day over there.
We promise this is the last time we'll talk about it today.
I don't know about, oh yeah, today, yes.
Oh, Wes, so thank you to you and Joe
for covering the show last week
and talking about Fischel, my favorite shell ever,
as I made clear in the interview.
You sure did.
You guys did great.
I got a lot of good, positive feedback on that,
and I appreciate it because it gave me a chance to,
well, I head down to Texas, you know,
as I said two weeks ago in the RV,
and on day two, we hit some mechanical troubles.
Oh no, of course you did.
Yeah, it was a couple of different issues,
but it all kind of came together
to really cause a series of unfortunate events.
I guess I'll put it that way,
including a popped water heater and all kinds of things.
But we persevered and got to our spot
where we had our marriage ceremony,
and it turned out really, really nice.
We had a great marriage ceremony under the stars,
and then it completed just as the sun rose
in the Tucson desert, and it was right between storms.
Couple of days ahead of time, it had snowed,
and then a couple days after we left,
it was windy and rainy, and we nailed it.
Just perfect weather.
It was wonderful.
Had great cellular connectivity too in the desert.
I had 30 megabits down and like-
Only you would mention that in the same sentences.
Oh yeah, you know, I drove through this desert
on an amazing trip, got married,
and the connectivity was great.
These things matter.
That puts it back on the we'll return to list.
You know what I mean?
Like, if it's got good connectivity,
all right, now it's a contender.
It's a candidate now.
You're right though.
I am such a nerd.
But it meant really good connectivity,
which meant we could keep up to date
with what was going on in the world,
and we could put together a great show today.
So made it down to Texas,
and it's been in the low 20s every night
since I've been here.
So it's been nice and cold.
That's why you go to Texas, right?
For that refreshing winter coldness.
Yes, yeah, it's my luck.
It's my luck.
I was down here earlier this year
when it was the hottest day of the year,
117 degrees in Dallas.
And now it's in the 20s.
During the day, it gets up to the 40s.
But what's fun is there's a huge crew here.
We're doing live streams for a bunch of content releases.
So a bunch of people are in,
and it's just, it's a good atmosphere down here right now.
Lots of, there's lots of temporary desks set up,
and I get to check out everybody's rigs,
which is always a lot of fun.
So I've really enjoyed my time down here so far.
And I'll be down here for a couple of weeks
doing the shows and whatnot.
And so far, enjoying the heck out of it.
It's really cool to have the RV parked
right next to the office,
because I can just, in 30 seconds, I'm working from home.
That is such an easy commute.
Right, and like I need to go to a meeting
or do something in the office,
30 seconds later, I'm in the office.
It's phenomenal.
You've got your own private conference room.
People kill for that kind of space.
I do.
People actually, a couple of times now,
have stopped by the RV just to chill for a bit.
So Lady Jeef is getting a rep for the place to chill.
And anyways, just really loving it and enjoying it a bunch.
So I really appreciate you guys covering the show
while I was gone.
I think it made it just,
gave me just enough time to pull it all off,
especially since we were compressed
with that one lost day due to mechanical issues.
Well, congratulations and welcome back.
Thank you, sir.
But that's not what we're here to talk about today.
Let's get into the community news,
and we're gonna start off the news
with a story about Apple,
which might be the first time we've ever done that
in the history of this show.
But they're releasing a pretty significant
open source project this week
that's caught a lot of attention.
Now, Apple originally acquired a project
called FoundationDB in 2015.
And last April, it announced that it was making
the cloud database open source.
But that's not what we're talking about today.
That was sort of done and, you know,
it's, everybody's moved on.
But things are taking a big leap forward this week
as FoundationDB has announced it's open sourcing
the FoundationDB record layer.
And along with this, Apple is outlining
how they are using their backend services
with this open source software,
which is something they've never done before.
It's the first public confirmation
that Apple is using this open source database
to power file storage on iCloud.
So we're talking about an open source project here
that's being battle tested by millions of iOS
and Mac users that's, the core part of it
was released for free originally.
But now we have this record layer.
And Wes, can you help explain what this record layer is
and maybe even how Apple might be using it?
Yeah, well, okay, so they call their whole,
their backend here cloud kit because,
well, of course they do.
Everything's a kit, Wes.
Everything is a kit.
And well, I mean, you want one for the cloud.
Sure, that makes sense.
The record layer, it's basically their own version
of a traditional record oriented database.
Things like the standard relational SQL databases
you're probably used to,
but built on top of FoundationDB.
And one of the things that's kind of unique to FoundationDB
is it provides something of a low level key value store.
And then they've made it easy to extend.
So FoundationDB is totally separate.
They've added this record layer,
which is actually a Java program
that interfaces with FoundationDB
and adds all these extra features.
So they only have to concentrate on running
all the complicated distributed system part of that.
That's the base FoundationDB.
And now they can add stuff like,
something like a MongoDB
or adding in this case, something like SQL.
Now, the other part of this that is
sort of the elephant in the room is MongoDB and AWS
are at odds right now as Amazon has announced AWS DocumentDB,
which is their own proprietary software
that implements a MongoDB compatible API.
The reason why this matters
is what Amazon can essentially now do
is offer MongoDB as a service,
but it's not MongoDB under the hood,
but it can talk MongoDB,
the version right before they relicensed.
And this is a huge,
huge blow to the MongoDB project
because they sell their own hosted service
with very few customers, unfortunately.
And so then a few days later after that,
Apple makes this announcement.
The timing is pretty coincidental, I guess.
It's interesting too.
I think it kind of compares and contrasts
the different types of open source out there, right?
Mongo has a venture backed company behind it.
They're trying to make open source software.
Yes, which is great,
but also running and making that software
is the core of their business.
Not so with FoundationDB.
Sure, it started that way,
but now it's just an open source thing Apple's using.
Downsides is you don't know,
maybe Apple could pivot databases at any time.
The upside, they're not really relying on it.
This is not how they're making money,
except as an implementation detail.
Really, so in summary, what we have here
is Apple releasing two more open source projects in total.
You have the original FoundationDB
and now this layer on top of it,
which makes it more like a relational database,
which people are very familiar with,
but has the file extensibility and the state support
everything they need for remote mobile apps.
And I wonder if this isn't gonna be pretty successful
because A, it's being used by millions of users already.
B, when you're trying to justify it to the CEO
or whoever you can say, Apple uses it.
And C, it's addressing a real need
that application developers have.
Yeah, I mean, it's got a nice license
and they've clearly learned.
It's a more modern database.
If you go back and look at when it was first,
after they acquired the company and open sourced it,
people are raving about it being open source
just because it has such a new, modern, sophisticated take
on concurrency and transactions.
So you get a lot of nice guarantees
and it's easy to administer.
Yeah, yeah.
That's really all I have.
I don't feel like I need to talk about Apple anymore
in the show, I think that's probably good.
Let's move on, what do you say?
And let's talk about the future of GNOME MPV,
which is my favorite, favorite,
favorite by a mile video player for desktop Linux.
I mean, LVLC, you're great, I love you,
but nothing beats MPV and GNOME MPV was a way
to wrap it up in a nice minimal GUI.
But I'm not so sure about this new name.
Yeah, well, okay, so do you agree with this?
Good app names should really be a single noun
that's related to the app's domain.
Something like fragments for a torrent app
or peak for a screen recorder.
Cause if you do, you're gonna like this new name.
No, I mean, I still agree with all that.
Don't really like the name.
Okay, I'm gonna try to pronounce it, you ready?
What do you, do you think I should,
let's see, we should all take bets.
Everybody bet if I'm gonna get this right.
Celluloid.
Yeah.
I got it?
Yep, I think that's good enough.
You're telling me I got it?
Yeah, it's celluloid.
Oh, I got it, I can't believe it, I can't believe it.
I don't know, man, I guess for some reason
it makes me think of cellulite,
which is not what I wanna think of
when I'm thinking of watching a video.
But, NomeMPV is clunky AF.
And I do like the one word thing.
And at least I can pronounce it,
so it's got that going for it.
Yeah, right.
And it's also the name of the transparent flammable
plastic made in sheets from camera four
and nitrocellulose and formerly used in filmmaking.
Yeah, right, so if you were,
if we were making a video podcast in the film era,
we would know all about celluloid.
Yeah, yeah, I've heard of like celluloid cylinders
and I've heard the term used before.
So this is gonna happen, it's like the switch-o,
will happen around the time of Nome 3.32's release in March.
So if you just got the most recent version,
or I should say the latest version, which was 0.15,
then it's still using NomeMPV,
you're not gonna see this yet.
What do you think?
So they also, they've got a new icon too,
and that does sort of fit with the name
because it looks like a piece of film.
I say we go to the mumble room.
What do you guys think of this name, celluloid?
Is it ditch it or keep it?
It's a keep it for me.
Yeah, how come?
It's a somewhat memorable name
and it's pretty easy to identify.
And the new icon is pretty stand out
from video player icons.
Yes, the new icon is the bee's knees.
That is really nice, you're right.
They should get credit for a great icon.
Okay, the mumble room in its entirety.
No, I'm kidding, actually we've got a good show
and we've got Conan in there,
we've got MiniMech, Sean, TechMav, Tyler,
Universal Super Box, AKA Dalton,
all hanging out in there today.
And I'm gonna roll with it.
I bet you it'll grow on me.
I thought iPad was the dumbest name I'd ever heard
when they first, and now people drop out,
it doesn't even affect me.
It's funny how that, you know, it has to,
it's kinda like music, once it sinks in,
you have a different perspective on it.
Yeah, yeah.
So Joe and I have been grousing
on Linux Action News recently
that Chrome OS is going to become the de facto desktop Linux.
Like the one that average consumers use,
the one that's gonna be used by millions of users,
the one that's sold in Best Buy and electronic stores,
it's Chrome OS, right, it's Chrome OS.
And we all probably should sit with that for a bit
and come to our own conclusions.
I waffle constantly if that's a good thing or a bad thing.
But I am really happy to report on the steady progress
of Linux application integration into Chrome OS.
And this week, thanks to some sleuthing,
based on a code commit uncovered by Chrome Story,
users of the Linux beta for Chromebooks
will soon be able to search and install Linux apps
from the Chrome OS launcher itself.
That's a big deal.
Yeah, right, I mean, it reads, add app search
into the Chrome OS app launcher
so that uninstalled Linux packages and apps
can be searched for and installed via the app launcher.
I mean, that's a pretty plain purpose.
And it's a nice workflow, too.
Yeah, not only is it convenient,
but it actually is going to put it in front of the face
of actual real users.
That's, to me, the biggest thing
is because it's in the launcher,
they don't have to go to a command prompt,
they don't have to go through all these different
less-treaded paths.
They are just using something they use all the time.
And we may even get to a point
where on some Chromebooks down the road,
Linux supports turn on by default,
that basic stuff's already installed.
I mean, this could legitimately one day
lead to the adoption of more open source desktop applications
which could, hopefully,
mean an increase in bug reports,
an increase in development time, an increase in funding,
it could mean an increase in quality,
but these are all maybes.
But with a broader market share, right?
Exposure in a way where you don't have to go
install your own distribution of Linux
or even know what that is, but you can still run GIMP.
Yeah, and people have asked me, like, why do you care, Chris?
Why do you care if Adobe Premier comes to Linux?
And it's like this, it may not be something I would use,
maybe it would be, I'd have to evaluate it.
And it's not that I want all this commercial software
coming to Linux, I think we need it all.
And I think we need all of it here
because we need more users.
We simply need more users
because we need more representation
and we need better software.
And the only way we're gonna get there
is if there's software to consume by users
and if there's not users to consume that software,
we won't get there.
So we've been stuck in this chicken or the egg situation
now for years and years, it just hasn't gone anywhere.
And now, maybe,
maybe Google is shifting that a bit.
And they're gonna take a platform
that has a ton of users and they're gonna turn this on
and now all of a sudden there'll be a whole new audience
for these applications.
So, Minimac, I wanna get your take on this.
Good news, this Linux adoption,
and now this continued integration
further and further of Linux applications?
Very good news, but the problem is
they don't support older Chromebooks.
That's the major problem.
I have this Intel Acer C720,
which is perfectly capable of running Linux and everything.
But on Chromebook, they have not yet opened
these new features like Android apps, Linux apps,
and Chromebook, the hardware is perfectly capable
of doing that, of handling that.
Good point.
Yeah, it's not like these applications,
you know what, in probably almost all cases,
most of these applications that users would be using
are lighter weight than its equivalent web app
running in a big old browser like Chrome.
Probably, yeah, definitely.
That's interesting.
So Dalton, do you think we're seeing a beginning
of a path here of Fuchsia for the mobile
and Chrome OS for the desktop?
So what I think back to here is Google's gVisor
that we talked about, oh, that was a while ago,
which is their container runtime
that re-implements all of the Linux kernel's interfaces.
If they had that running on top of Fuchsia,
then they could use their Apache-licensed kernel
and they wouldn't even need Linux at that point.
Jeez, Dalton, way to bring it down, man.
Good point, though.
You would end up with the core that they can have
and with gVisor too, right, they only will implement
the stuff that they know they can contain
and actually run so they don't have to be exposed
to that whole API surface.
Right, it's a safe user experience, they'll say.
And kind of just really quickly,
just to tangentially mention this,
we did cover this in more detail on Linux Action News.
I think 88.
But Chrome OS is also going to start letting
managed company Chromebooks choose their own Linux distro
for this layer.
Right now, I think we've talked about it before,
it's like a Debian derivative, essentially it's Debian.
But now, you get to specify a URL
of where your ISO image is at.
And when the user chooses the option to enable Linux support,
it'll pull it down from that customly specified URL
and install the version or the image of Linux
that you've set up.
Well, that's the rub, right Chris?
Because maybe it's you, but really,
it's the device administrators, whoever they might be.
Yeah, the IT department.
Because I don't even, I think people are digging around
in the source code and they didn't see a way
for individuals to turn this on yet.
Yeah, it really seems targeted at the enterprise use case,
which does make sense, Chrome OS has made
huge inroads there.
Yeah, and I could definitely see certain enterprises
that would want their own customer environment
so that way, maybe their own internal development team
could be developing on that environment,
which then gets uploaded to their production servers.
So, I think it could be a hit.
I don't know if I buy the premise,
but if the premise is true, I think it could be a hit.
And you've got to assume that once the underlying tech
is there, someone somewhere is gonna release a tool
so you can do it yourself.
That's what I'm counting on.
When that tool comes out, I'll probably grab a Chromebook.
I think I'm gonna do it, I think I'm gonna do it.
Unless, unless those chaps over at UbiPorts
can get me a tablet run in Ubuntu Touch that just sings
and they're getting closer and closer
with every dang release.
And Dalton's there in the Mumble Room
to talk about OTA 6, which is now shipping.
Oh, wait, I'm sorry.
No, I'm sorry, OTA 7.
OTA 6 was the one that came out last month.
Holy smokes, Dalton.
You guys are really hitting that monthly stride now.
We did.
That's one of the big stories for this release
where we finally got our release cadence down.
So, we've got proper testing and a lot of work done
in between the two releases,
but we're still hitting that one month cycle.
Congratulations.
That probably took a lot of work as a project
to get your heads around that and get that actually working.
So, that's a big accomplishment in itself.
But what are some of the new goodies in OTA 7
that you're the most excited about?
OTA 7's big headline feature for the users
is keyboard theming.
So, that might sound like a small deal,
but someone in our community contributed the support.
So, now you can change the colors of your keyboard.
So, instead of being blinded
by this really bright white keyboard,
you can have a darker experience.
And there are screenshots of this in our blog post,
which you can find at u reports.com slash blog.
Excellent, yeah, nice.
So, when you're using the phone late at night,
you don't get that blast of light in the face.
It looks like Morph has gotten some nice improvements too.
It's a steady improvement from now that Morph is in.
It is.
The Morph browser is our cute web engine based browser,
which is based on Chromium Blink.
And it's been getting more stable with every release.
So, in this release,
we've got fixes for multiple browser windows,
which is always an interesting experience
when you have a five inch screen,
as well as fixes to tab switching
and a bunch of other things that everyone will find nice.
And we've heard some really great feedback on.
Good, that's really nice.
The other thing I learned
when I was reading through your release notes,
and I hadn't thought about it.
And then when I saw this,
I was surprised that the project is still active.
I thought maybe it was a canonical project.
But Libhybris, which is that magic translation layer
that lives between the Android drivers
and the libc based user space, right?
So, Libhybris does this really, really important translation
that lets you use all kinds of different hardware.
And that's still an active project getting updated, yeah?
Yes, Libhybris was originally maintained by the Mamo team
when Nokia originally brought out their Linux.
And that has moved into the Mer project,
which is the base of Sailfish OS,
which is supported by Sailfish.
It's turtles all the way down,
but it means that there's a great well supported project
that other mobile platforms are also using.
So, it kind of works out perfect, doesn't it?
It is perfect.
And it's nice to have that upstream there.
Yeah, well, seriously congratulations
on another great release.
Good to see that new cadence,
that new keyboard does look sharp.
I'm looking at the screenshots in your blog post right now.
And for the new Nexus 4 and Nexus 7 users
with the Wi-Fi only version,
also a release that I think you're gonna be
particularly excited about.
So, go check it out.
We will have a link in the show notes
to linuxunplug.com slash 284, yes.
Dalton, thanks for stopping by to tell us
anything else you wanna mention about this release
or maybe the next release?
People to keep a lookout for?
Well, with this release,
we brought in a bunch of changes to help with porting.
So, I think people are going to be seeing
some new devices pretty soon.
In fact, I think that there might be
one of those devices from that company
that starts with X that Americans can't seem to pronounce,
about to hit our devices page at devices.ubuntu-touch.io.
It's in testing right now.
Very cool, that is awesome to hear.
Well, good work to you and the whole team.
Tell everybody to keep it up and we'll keep watching.
Keep watching.
Dalton, I don't suppose there's any chance
you're gonna make it out to Linux Fest this year?
I'm not sure.
I just booked all my tickets for FOSDEM,
so I might need to be recovering at that point yet.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, good, I'm glad you're going to FOSDEM.
So, let's just do a bit of housekeeping here for a moment.
I don't really have a lot to cover,
but Linux Fest Northwest is our next big public event.
We're also gonna be at scale.
So, that's now, we're locking that in.
I think I'll be there, Wes is gonna be there,
and a new member of our team,
which we haven't had a chance yet to introduce y'all to,
is gonna be there as well.
Ooh, I'm so excited already.
Just all the good ways to hang out
with our wonderful audience.
Yeah, but Linux Fest is gonna be the party.
I have a list of people showing up I'm so thrilled about.
I'm looking forward to hanging out with everybody.
Linux Fest Northwest, if you can make it,
please go April 26th through the 28th, 2019.
That's all I really had for the housekeeping section though,
because there is some stuff,
there is some stuff that we have to talk about.
You heard me mention it during the intro segment,
ZFS on Linux is going to be the new upstream project
that FreeBSD and Lumos and other operating systems
that ship ZFS will base their implementation on.
So, the FreeBSD project will likely still have
their own project repository
for their implementation of ZFS,
but it will be downstream of the ZFS on Linux project now.
This is a huge shift.
This is a massive shift.
And this was announced a few weeks ago,
we covered it when it happened.
Today, I came across what I thought
was the end of days at first.
Like, at first, my first pass of this story,
I was really kind of in panic mode.
And I PMed Wes, I'm like, Wes, talk me down.
Tell me what this is about, because the headline
and the ramifications are pretty big.
ZFS on Linux has run into a snag with version 5.0.
ZFS on Linux currently fails to build
against Linux 5.0 kernel sources.
This isn't due to just some trivial API change.
In fact, actually, it's just because
there are some kernel symbols,
kernel FPU begin and end respectively.
The kernel module for ZFS on Linux relied on those
in part to basically have faster performance
while doing some file system checksums.
Those are no longer exported and the module can't build.
Right, so these FPU symbols that allowed ZFS on Linux
to do fancy fast checksums just disappeared in 5.0.
And there doesn't seem to be a simple solution
for this immediately, especially one that doesn't involve
using GPL symbols due to license compatibility issues
that, I mean, we talk about this with ZFS
all the time with Linux.
And Greg KH chimed in on the mailing list
that's read about this on the kernel mailing list.
He doesn't seem to be too inspired to make any concessions.
Quote, Greg writes, my tolerance for ZFS
is pretty non-existent.
Sun explicitly did not want their code to work on Linux.
So why would we do extra work
to get their code to work properly?
It's unfortunate, this one might not be the biggest.
It looks like they'll probably just not have
vectorized floating point implementations
for these checksums in the future,
at least for the short term.
But at a time when suddenly the ZOL tree
is the place where new development is happening,
it just kind of seems like a downturn
or not a great relationship between the Linux community
and the large and the ZOL project in particular.
And it wasn't, I mean, obviously those weren't great, right?
I mean, it's an out of tree driver.
And we should also note that those symbols begin
with a double underscore.
And so really they weren't super officially supported.
They could have been removed really at any time.
So here they are, they're gone.
But just knowing that people as high up as great gay age
have no interest in bending even a little bit to help
our favorite little file system is pretty disappointing.
Yeah, do you think Wes, it's a power play a little bit?
Like they're looking at the situation, they're going,
ZFS needs Linux more than Linux needs ZFS.
And now you all just admitted that the ZFS on Linux
is the best implementation,
the one with the encryption you want.
So why don't you just come play ball?
Why don't you just come play ball?
Is that the message they're trying to send here?
That's one reading, I would assume that Greg in particular
is probably a little more pragmatic than that
and just can't be bothered to impose future support burdens,
even if they might be minimal or seem to be minimal now
on an out of tree incompatibly licensed module.
Yeah, in fact, I think I agree with you
because reading into it didn't look like there was
sort of iffy support for these symbols for quite a while now
and they've kind of been on the chopping block.
Yeah, I think what we're really gonna have to try
to pay attention to is the longer term story.
How many more symbols disappear?
How many symbols that we just can't rely on
are hard coded into the currency well implementation
and how big of a deal will these be?
Because if it's just sort of like,
this was gonna be deprecated anyway,
now's the time where we have to go do the back porting
and the updates, so be it.
If it signals a real degradation in the relationship,
that'll be disappointing.
Well, and it also seems like 5.0
is where you make some breaking changes.
Like if this is something you've been thinking about
and it's been on the chopping block
and you know it's gonna break a couple of things
because ZFS on Linux probably isn't the only
software project to use this vectorized checksum support.
It's probably other ones out there.
But at the same time, like if you decided as a team,
we're kind of done with this and it doesn't really fit
with our overall licensing scheme anyways
and what our intentions are and what the spirit of it all is.
5.0 would be the time to make that change,
it would be time to just rip that bandaid off, I would think.
We've got some good questions too in the IRC
just asking about, what about NVIDIA, right?
Because that's the elephant in the room,
it's the other really popular driver.
That's why I was freaking out earlier.
Now, it doesn't seem like this,
obviously when you have a GPU,
you probably don't need these particular symbols,
but the same practices could be applied
and does it mean there's a different relationship?
Does the kernel value the NVIDIA driver
more than say the relationship to the ZFS project?
Yeah, yeah. I don't know,
but it doesn't seem fair.
I'm glad that question came up
because depending on where you read this story,
particularly on Reddit, if you read the comments,
people are equating this to mean
that the NVIDIA driver won't work anymore
and that's not the case.
That's not what's happening here.
It's really just this one vectorized GP,
I can't remember what it's called.
Yeah, the vectorized floating point operation.
And Conan Kudo in the IRC has a great point.
It was removed basically
because they did a bunch of changes in the kernel
and entry modules no longer needed these symbols.
So they were unwilling to support stuff
that their code base wasn't using.
I mean, there you go, there you go.
So I thought what we would do here
is we had an opportunity to sit down
with an individual who contributes
to the Fedora project, Mangia, OpenSUSE,
and he's on the ZFS leadership council
as part of his day job at Datto.
And I've known Neil for a long time.
And so when this story came up a couple of weeks ago,
he was the first guy I thought about calling up
and chatting and he gives us some great context
about the situation.
Well, with all this news recently
about all the major projects that use ZFS,
rebasing upstream on ZFS for Linux,
I had to bring somebody on to process this.
So Neil's joining us and Neil,
you and I have chatted in the past
and I always manage to mess up the last name.
So help me with the pronunciation
so that way on the record, I don't get it wrong.
Neil Gompa.
All right, so there you go.
Hey Neil, thanks for joining us on Linux Unplugged.
And why don't we start a little bit with your background
because I know you're involved with the Fedora project,
OpenSUSE, you have a day job at Datto
and obviously work there with storage.
Tell me a little bit about your background.
Sure, currently I am a DevOps engineer at Datto,
which is a disaster recovery,
business continuity services company
that's focused on managed service providers
and people in that and all that kind of space.
And we use ZFS or ZFS, however you'd like to pronounce it
for a lot of our infrastructure
and of course our backup appliances
and stuff like that on Linux.
And part of that has also made it so that I'm involved
with the ZFS on Linux project upstream.
What kind of amounts of storage roughly,
you don't have to give me specifics,
but just kind of roughly are you working with?
I think the last time we talked about this publicly
as a company, I think we were at almost 200 or so petabytes
of data.
Now, it's not like it's a enormous cluster of ZFS
because for one, that's not a good idea,
but it is 200 petabytes of computers that run ZFS
as the data backing file system.
And the model that our company uses is that basically
we map a person, a customer's equipment
to what we call a cloud storage node.
And that node receives all of that customer's data.
So it's not like you have this massive fabric or something
that like along the lines of say like Ceph or Gluster,
it doesn't work that way.
It's more like we have a large set of computers
that runs ZFS to store data.
And so like the servers may have,
they'll have, I think on average somewhere
like 200 terabytes or so, maybe more per server.
So it pushes the limits of a lot of things.
And the workloads that we're doing on it are quite varied.
So this Datto's use of ZFS so extensively,
how does this work?
So I know you were involved in the ZFS leadership
and you were in the leadership meeting
when they were discussing rebasing,
like free BSDs implementation on ZFS for Linux
instead of the Lumos version.
How does that part of it work?
So is it a lot of companies that have some sort
of financial interest in the future of ZFS?
Is it based on their contributions?
How does the leadership team aspect of all of this work?
Cause I think that's an interesting element
to the ZFS project that, I mean,
I don't think ButterFS has anything like that.
So historically the leadership is more or less
the companies that worked on the Lumos tree.
And those were considered the people
that kind of led the open ZFS umbrella.
And would it be fair to say that a common conception
was that the Lumos version was the...
Mainline?
Yeah, that was pretty much the historical basis.
But a number of things have changed
over the past three, four years.
Like Datto as a company has contributed
the ZFS native encryption to ZOL.
And that has not been fully ported
to other operating systems.
Oh, I see.
So that's sort of a big differentiator
that the Linux version has
that the other projects probably want.
The library interfaces for ZFS are different
across all three operating systems.
Even the ZFS command works differently
between the different operating systems,
excluding the fact that native encryption
only exists on ZOL right now.
It's just the implementations are not the same.
They are not at the same level.
They don't exactly have the same feature sets.
And in some cases their compatibility
is a little bit wonky.
So there has been this open question for a while
of what we would consider the mainline.
And historically it has been the Lumos tree.
But with the changes that have happened
over the last couple of years,
that came into question again.
And now it's the Linux tree is the one
that's actually moving ahead and doing more.
And the other trees are not doing as much.
Like I think the most notable exception I am aware of
is the Zstandard support that came to FreeBSD first
because Alan Jude wrote it.
It's not because it was,
it didn't go to Lumos first and then go to FreeBSD.
There wasn't already a single mainline.
It was sort of just following where development
is naturally taking place.
It sounds like it was starting to get worse too,
potentially.
Yeah, and so nowadays,
if we wanted to follow in terms of like,
okay, where's the features going,
then we have to consider ZOL as the mainline
because that's where a lot of the feature development
is happening.
That's where the bulk of the usage
of the ZFS file system is now happening,
even though it is the redheaded ugly stepchild
of the open ZFS family.
Well, that's what I was gonna ask you.
That seems like a really awkward contentious position.
If the version of ZFS that perhaps has the largest
user deployment is the Linux version,
but a large portion of the ZFS community themselves
considers the Linux version to be sort of second class,
that's a bad position to be in because then in theory,
the projects most passionate members
aren't putting their best foot forward to the marketplace.
And that is definitely,
that has definitely been the case until very recently.
What changed is that Delphix is moving from Illumos
to Linux for their platform.
And so that means that all the members of the,
the main members of the leadership,
like Matt Aarons and company are moving
from the Solaris tree to the Linux tree.
And so that means that for all intents and purposes,
the majority is now Linux developers.
What distributions are they using?
Is it all Ubuntu?
No.
So, well, Delphix, I think will be using Ubuntu,
which, eh, sure.
Oh, wow.
I thought, you know, I mean,
at least they're shipping it, man.
That's true.
And Datto does as well,
but the ZOL primary developers,
which are the Lawrence Livermore National Institute,
use, they use RHEL.
And actually Red Hat Enterprise Linux
and CentOS and Fedora are the primary test engines
and the things that we test against
because Fedora gives us the latest kernels
and easy to test against along with the newer ABIs
and stuff like that to make sure
we're following the future well.
That just feels like there's a bit of tasty irony in there,
don't you think?
Like, it's, in fact, right now,
the leaders of those projects
are actively working on Stratus to compete with ZFS.
Ah, so Stratus is not about competing with ZFS.
That is the- You don't think so?
No, it's definitely not, look.
So just a quick recap to the audience,
Stratus is sort of a collection of existing tools
as well as new APIs to use existing Linux management tools
along with XFS to create a ZFS-like competitor
is what, you know, a lot of people consider it,
like myself and the people I've talked to.
But what do you think?
You think it's more of a stopgap
for a ButterFS competitor?
I don't consider it a competitor to ButterFS or ZFS
in any reasonable way because the problem with it
is that the layers don't know anything about each other.
So there's going to be weaknesses
and lack of optimization on certain parts of it.
There's a lot you can do to make,
like, this is more about making the user experience simpler
rather than anything else, like-
Right, I mean, it almost seems like that's the,
that's where it's competing, right?
It's not about the technical competition,
it's about their customers want to do this X
and if the performance is good enough,
even if there are limitations,
well, that's the same thing.
The main impetches for the development of Stratus
is that they want to have boot to Snapshot,
the stuff that SUSE did.
And boot to Snapshot is only functional on Linux
properly with BTRFS.
And if you try to use the other file systems
or the other technologies,
there's a whole lot of gotchas and quirks and problems.
And even to be fair with BTRFS,
you can't even do this with mainline grub
because the grub people are bad about reviewing patches
for this stuff.
Uh, yeah.
It is, I laugh, but it's frustrating.
Yeah, no, SUSE has, I think, seven or eight patches
to BTRFS that they wrote four or five years ago
to make this work.
I integrated them into Fedora with Peter Jones's help,
Peter Jones and Dusty Maeb who are,
Peter Jones is the guy at Red Hat
who works on the boot stuff
and Dusty Maeb is currently the guy
that works on the Red Hat Atomic and CoreOS stuff.
And back then he was just kind of the guy
who just worked on all kinds of stuff related to whatever.
The guy with the tie.
Yeah, yeah, that's more accurate.
But Dusty had been doing this for a while on his own,
just like integrating the patches
and then putting them into,
and then writing up instructions
on how to set up the SUSE style boot to Snapshot on Fedora.
I wanted, I've been doing it myself,
but like one of the downsides
is if you're building grub yourself and all this stuff,
you lose a lot of secure boot support.
So I worked with Peter Jones and Dusty Maeb
to integrate the SUSE patches into Fedora's grub.
And so now the boot to Snapshot stuff can work
if you like actually set it up on Fedora,
it's just not set up by default.
There's some work to be done,
but like my main annoyance at this point
is that grub is so bad about integrating grub
and integrating these things.
I have no idea what the hell happened
the first time around when it came to,
when they submitted the patches, assuming they did.
I mean, again, I can't even prove that
because navigating the grub patches mailing list
is horrible because it's that horrible mailing interface
that the GNU project uses for everything.
So it's just terrible to search.
Thank you, thank you.
I always felt like the jerk for thinking that.
It does seem a little bit like,
we have such better technology.
Like the Fedora mailing list with HyperKitty
and Mailman 3 has a bloody search engine
that can actually search properly across all the topics.
You can tag things, you can favorite threads.
That is pretty legit.
Let's bring this back to ZFS.
So now moving forward,
we've got certain features that are only available
on the ZFS for Linux implementation
that the market wants, like encryption.
You've got Delphix, which is switching their product
from a Lumos over to Linux.
But what seems to be the elephant in the room now
is looking over at FreeBSD and the BSD projects
that ship ZFS and thinking after, you know,
kind of a couple of years of really, really hounding,
you've got to ship BSD if you want the best ZFS,
they're now shipping or will be shipping
the Linux version of ZFS.
Is that an awkward position for them, do you think?
Or is that just in the eyes and minds
of the internet commentators?
So ironically, I think they're gonna have an easier time
once they complete their rebase to ZOL.
So one of the differences between the ZOL tree
and the Lumos tree is that the ZOL tree
is actually separated from the rest
of the operating system.
So it's easier for them to pick it out
and plug in the BSD to Linux compatibility interfaces
and plug the ZFS driver in.
I think that from a community point of view,
like the broader Linux community,
ZFS on Linux will remain an ugly stepchild.
And it's probably a very fair remark
to consider it that way, given how antagonistic
both sides have been to each other for various reasons.
It's not worth getting into right now,
but like that is not going to change anytime soon,
unless Oracle waves a magic wand,
which I don't think they'll ever do,
but you know, they could,
and then the problems will start going away.
And then maybe ZFS would be integrated into Linux tree
and you know, everything will kind of get better
in ponies and unicorns.
But while it might be an ugly stepchild
in the broader Linux community,
within the open ZFS community has gradually gotten
a bigger sphere of influence.
The current major developers of the ZFS file system,
as in like the features and stuff like that,
have increasingly been on the Linux side
rather than the other sides.
And for FreeBSD, they're going to find
that it's actually going to be easier
for them to integrate, once they've rebased
from the Illumos version to the Linux version,
I suspect they'll find that it will be much easier
to integrate new versions faster.
Now that being said, the FreeBSD development process
doesn't allow them to move very fast, very easily.
They have a lot of problems in terms of their,
in terms of their development process,
the size of the number of people contributing
to the FreeBSD operating system,
in terms of the kernel and the integration
across the different layers.
But I think that this will improve their ability
to integrate things from ZFS overall.
I think that's a different take than I've heard,
but I think that syncs up.
Knowing what I know from chatting with Alan
about this too, behind the scenes,
asking him what he thought of it,
and I think his views kind of sync up with yours.
And I wonder if then we can move beyond
sort of who has the best ZFS implementation,
and we just sort of achieve, finally,
which I think has been one of the project's goals,
maybe from the beginning, you can correct me
if I'm wrong, Neil, but we finally kind of achieve
one common upstream across all operating systems.
That's the holy grail, right?
Is it possible?
Is that possible?
The main thing that hampers it is that ZFS,
each ZFS implementation is too tightly wound
into the kernel that it is associated with.
So today it is not, we don't have
a modern open ZFS implementation
that can operate entirely in user space, for example.
If you remember from like five or six years ago,
or even seven years ago, even,
like there was the ZFS Fuse project,
and that was one of the first implementations of it.
And while it didn't last for very long,
it was a fairly complete implementation, if not a bit slow.
These days, Fuse is much faster and much more efficient,
and if we did it again,
it would probably be actually pretty good.
But the problem today is that without a way
to operate the ZFS file system entirely in user space
with an agnostic API that can be used
across different operating systems,
there is no way we can have a unified file system tree,
because we can't have an implementation that we can say,
okay, this is the behavior that we expect
and test all the kernel integrations against it.
That's just not a thing we can do right now.
How would you pull something like that off?
Would there be additions?
Would there, I mean, would it be something
like a set of super feature flags?
Is there a way to have a master branch
and then have all of these considerations or compromises
or whatever you want to call them
for the different platforms this thing gonna run on?
So sure, I mean, most modern file systems
are actually built in a relatively self-contained way
because they have to be able to understand
their full context and state.
ZFS is no exception to this.
The only difference is because of the way
that ZFS on Linux has been developed
and all the other variants,
it's been, they took out the common code
and re-implemented everything inside the common code
outwards into the kernel.
So ZFS on Linux, for example, operates in like,
I think it's like eight or nine kernel modules.
Like it's a bunch of different kernel modules
that make up ZFS, zfs.ko, ICP, Z comments,
there's a whole bunch.
And while we're talking about those kernel modules,
let's talk to Neo live in real time.
So we recorded that a couple of weeks ago
and he's joining us in the mumble room.
Neo, welcome to Linux Unplugged again.
And what do you think of this latest news with Linux 5.0?
Hey Chris, it's nice to be back again, this time live.
It's really not that surprising.
I mean, we actually kind of knew it was coming
to some extent because as I mentioned to you
the last time we talked, it was more about having the,
we often test against with Fedora.
We even test against Fedora-Raw height.
So as snapshots are coming in of Linux kernel releases,
we are actively testing in that.
And we detect these kinds of problems basically like that.
And because of that, it was no surprise
to most of us in ZOL, the real,
the kind of the kick in the teeth was that
there were no other consumers left
in the Linux kernel itself and they re-architected things.
So it burned us in that regard.
But you know, this is not all that different
from what happens every other like seventh
or eighth kernel release or something like that.
I mean, it's just gonna make it so that configuring ZFS
when you're building it from source is just gonna take
two or three more minutes longer than it did before.
I mean, at this point, I think we have 10 minutes worth
of configure steps for detecting which functions we can use
going all the way back to 2632.
Oh wow.
God, I'm looking forward to when RHEL 6 goes away
because when RHEL 6 drops off,
we can move the bar up to 310
and that lets us drop a huge chunk of checks.
I bet.
Holy smokes.
So is there going to be, as far as you know,
like a checksum performance impact
if it can't use this vectorized checksum methodology?
I don't know this for certain
because like I haven't dug too much into it,
but I suspect that this is really only going to impact
encryption really, because the FPU stuff,
I think is more about accelerating floating.
FPU is a floating point unit.
So it's accelerating floating point calculations
and that's primarily used in cryptography.
So I suspect that's the only thing
that's really gonna harm it.
There's not a lot of accelerated code paths in ZFS.
That's part of the reason why it's kind of
a heavy file system compared to most.
And the other part of it is just that it has a lot of stuff
and it has to re-implement large aspects
of what the kernel normally does
because of the licensing and compat.
So, I mean, it is what it is.
It'll move on.
Like there's already a little bit of,
if you look at the CFS on Linux repository right now
and look at the GitHub issues,
they've already got the issues filed
for like the different functions that have been,
basically they're blocked off from starting with 5.0.
And, you know, they're just,
we'll just poke at and prod it and fix it as we go.
I feel like we should maybe just
more explicitly assuage Chris's fears.
Are there changes to symbols or, you know,
other upstream changes that would seem likely
that could really endanger the future of ZFS on Linux?
Look, the only way that ZFS on Linux
will have a guaranteed future
is if it was mainlined into the Linux kernel tree.
That is not gonna happen until Oracle waves its magic wand.
So, nothing in this life is certain
when it comes to ZFS on Linux or ZFS on any platform.
Just take it as it can come.
And for now, I don't foresee a reason for it to disappear.
Yeah, it does seem like,
and I think I even put that in my episode
where we all had our magic wands and we had our wishlist.
If they dual licensed it even,
or just, let's just say they win GPL,
just for a hot second, let's just fantasize.
It would enshrine that file system
in the world's largest free operating system.
It would essentially make ZFS a file system
that could live on forever.
Not that it can't on these other platforms,
but as we've all seen with the GPL,
it has that viral nature
and that has worked out very good for Linux.
And if ZFS could be included into that,
it would be part of something larger.
I mean, not to get all like meta about this,
but being inside the Linux kernel
is sort of like being in a time capsule.
And the other thing about this
that a lot of people don't realize
is that we, in the ZOL implementation of ZFS,
we re-implement quite a bit of what the kernel does.
If we were actually allowed to be part of the kernel,
that would probably simplify quite a bit
of ZFS's implementation on Linux.
And the magic wand here would be something,
an arrangement similar to what we have
for the GPU stack, the graphics stack in Linux.
In the kernel side graphics stack,
most of the code is dual licensed,
ex-pat MITx11 and GPLv2.
And so that allows large swaths of that code
to be imported into operating systems like FreeBSD
that prefer to have a more permissive
pushover set of license terms
versus the copyleft terms that the Linux kernel has.
The thing to consider though is that
if such an arrangement were to occur,
like there's a whole lot of extra considerations
around like how ZFS is going to be maintained,
how will people make sure that the licensing providence
remains, you know, sane, stuff like that.
These are things that have been worked out as arrangements
before it's been done with the Linux graphics drivers.
It can be done for ZFS as well
if we could get Oracle to wave its magic wand
because if they make, like say for example,
a new version of the CDDL,
that new version could basically allow you
to have the terms that would be compatible with it.
That could be a way to do it via the CDDL.
Cause there's no restriction currently
in the CDDL license that specifically says,
the way that it's termed inside of the ZFS tree
that says that newer versions of that license
cannot be used.
And the license steward, which was Sun Microsystems,
now Oracle Corporation, is allowed to make a new version
and we are allowed to use that as our, if we want to.
Just put that out there.
Just going to put that out there, right?
Just maybe send that out in waves out in the universe.
Maybe something will come back.
It's the same path that Fedora, Red Hat,
Fedora and SGI did to fix the Xorg licensing problem
back in the early 2000s.
So it's not the, and the free software foundation
did the same thing for the GFDL so that Wikipedia
could move to Creative Commons licensing
instead of remaining on the GNU free documentation license.
It's not without precedent.
It can be done.
It's just a matter of getting the right ear
at the, with the right people to make it happen.
And if there's enough people who want it and there's,
and somebody knows the right person, then it can happen.
I'm holding out my hope.
I like that.
I think that's a, you know what, that's going to be the,
that'll be like the little, little string of hope
that I hold on to, Neil.
Thanks for coming on and sharing your thoughts
on this story as it developed today.
I appreciate you stopping by.
That was great timing.
And I have a feeling we'll be talking more in the future.
Yeah, I enjoy chatting with you, Chris.
So happy to be on whenever you'd like me to.
Thank you, sir.
Well, before we scoot out of here,
I wanted to just mention a couple of quick picks.
Both are really neat.
We've talked about dot file managers before on the show.
And I thought what I'd do, instead of me pronounce this,
I'm going to make Wes pronounce it, because he went and looked
up the pronunciation.
And I say there's a 50-50 shot.
You remember how to actually say it, Wes.
Betrayal.
I see how it goes, sir.
Shea moi.
OK, all right.
All right.
Good job.
It's not that I didn't have faith.
It's just that it was a while ago.
It was a while ago.
Shea moi?
Is it shea moi?
This is on you now.
You got the one reading, and that was it.
So when you first linked this to me,
I was a little skeptical.
There's a ton of different ways to manage dot files,
from a simple git directory to a ton of custom tools
that exist there.
Thankfully, this guy, they've got a great README.
And a big section there, I already
have a system to manage my dot files.
Why should I use this?
And there's actually some solid answers.
If you haven't ever tried one, or you're not
happy with what you got, this should be a serious contender.
Yeah.
I heard good things.
That's why I tossed it in here, because I
heard a lot of good things.
And I'm thinking about it.
There's also a bunch of other ones.
Probably the most famous is gnu-stow, or stow,
however you want to pronounce it.
Yeah, I've used that for a long time.
Yeah, that's, I think, probably the most common one.
I think this is a little easier to start with myself,
so I'll have a link to that in the show notes.
And then our last pick this week is a new web
browser called Ephemeral.
And I think this is a really cool idea.
It's the always incognito web browser.
And it's by our buddy Cassidy, over at the elementary project.
And he writes, it's an interesting idea,
Firefox focus, just making privacy a habit by default,
instead of a separate mode you manually enable.
And from that, he was kind of inspired
to make a really straightforward, nice looking,
as you would expect, I suppose, web browser
for elementary OS.
And it's a Linux app, so there's probably other ways
you can get your hands on it.
But if you are on elementary OS, go in the App Center
and check out Ephemeral.
I hope this maybe gets around a little bit.
I think this would be good publicity for elementary
as a project.
Yeah, and as you said, it's beautiful.
It's streamlined.
It's simple.
And I think Cassidy hit it on the head
with privacy as a default. Sure, you
might need sessions for some stuff,
for your work account, whatever.
But if you're just trying to buy something on Amazon
or look up plates, this seems perfect.
Yeah, I actually just like it just
for the idea of having an extra browser that's sort of like,
just go log into this for a little bit.
I do this all the time.
I'll fire up an incognito window to maybe open up
a Google account that's for one of the shows
that I don't log into too often, and I just want a one off.
And I just could always use this browser.
But speaking of publicity for elementary OS,
our buddy Jason, who was on the show last week,
I think when I was gone, and talked about Adobe Premiere
coming, possibly or possibly not coming to Linux,
and also about their plans with Rush.
Well, Jason has launched an elementary OS community
challenge.
And the gist of it is his challenge
is use elementary OS for a certain period of time.
It's not super, super long.
The whole idea is, especially if you're on Mac or Windows
today, so if you're listening to the show
and you've been Linux curious for a while,
this is perfect for you.
And I would like you to consider this.
The basic premise of the elementary OS challenge
is simple.
You ditch Windows or Mac OS for maybe elementary OS.
Maybe choose your own.
You know, elementary OS would be a great choice.
Oh, come on.
Come on.
It's not called choose whatever you want, Chris.
I know.
But I just want anybody to switch Linux.
But his suggestion, I think is a good one,
is you all are going to go in on elementary OS for two weeks.
Think about that.
You'll have a community of people
that are all trying this out.
There could be some really good results from that,
especially if Jason is able to stay
in contact with that community.
And he says, since we'll be on this road together,
he has a piece over on Forbes about this.
He says, since we'll be on this road together,
I'll be posting a bunch of content
here to capture my ongoing experiences with the challenge.
One day, may see a stream of consciousness journal.
Other days, I'll be publishing short guides, software
spotlights, interviews with elementary OS app developers
and team members, and my own discoveries and hurdles,
if any.
I think it's a great idea.
He's also at killyourfm on Twitter
if you want to follow him there, because he'll probably be
posting about it there as well.
And I'll have a link to their challenge, his piece on Forbes,
if you want to maybe get into that.
I know a lot of people listening, Wes,
that are probably on their own distro of choice.
But you know, because you see the stats, actually.
So you actually do know.
We have a very large Mac and Windows audience
that are likely listening because they're Linux curious.
This could be great for them.
It really could.
And elementary, I mean, it just keeps making leaps and bounds.
So maybe you're like me, and you hadn't used it
since the last time around.
It's really worth it.
Two weeks is nothing.
I mean, just give it a shot.
Yeah, give it a shot.
And if you do it, let us know too.
I'd love to know your progress too.
You could at Chris LAS me.
He's at Wes Payne.
Or you could just send us a contact form
if you go to linuxunplug.com slash contact.
It'll go right into our inbox there.
Or wherever you like to do that.
We would love to know how that journey goes too.
And I encourage you, if you've been thinking about it,
with Jason doing this, he has a pretty decent following.
This is going to be a little community that crops up
that can support each other.
And you can follow him along as he goes through it too
and writes about it.
It just seems like a real, if I was getting into Linux,
I'll stop talking about it.
But I just think this is such a cool idea.
If I was getting into Linux today,
that would be the thing that pushes me over.
And it's just really exciting.
And I'm just fired up about getting some new users.
And I think elementary is a great distro
for that potential audience too.
So with that, we're going to wrap up this week's episode.
TechSnap has some great stuff in the works.
Jim Salter from Ars Technica is joining Wes
as the new co-host.
And a new episode will be coming out soon.
So go subscribe.
Go to techsnap.systems slash subscribe and get that.
It's going to be incredible.
He's at Wes Payne.
Thank you to the mumble room for joining us.
I'm at Chris LAS.
And from a very chilly Texas, thank you for joining us.
And consider joining us live next Tuesday.
You can get it at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar
for your time zone and jblive.tv for that stream.
We'll see you next Tuesday.
Well, thank you everybody.
Really enjoyed it.
Mumble room, you were great.
Neil, thank you so much for making it.
Man, that worked out perfect.
I'll tell you what.
It really did.
Thank you.
Sometimes it just comes together.
Even when I'm doing live shows and oh man,
we had a great live show today, but there was a moment.
You know, and I don't, I mean, I guess I am a professional.
You are, yeah.
I don't consider myself one.
What do you, what was the last 10 years?
I know.
That's funny.
But you know, I totally, if I, if I was a professional,
I'm not anymore because I embarrassed myself so bad on the live stream.
I don't know if I should say it or if I should just make people go watch it.
But there was a moment where maybe because I wasn't directly on camera,
something happened and I lost it.
I laughed so hard.
Like you ever see those outtakes when a cast just loses it
and they can't keep it together anymore?
That was me.
Yeah.
Normally that's like multiple people.
And you know, you were definitely the loudest.
I was the only one laughing.
There was like one other ha.
But I was crying off camera, crying off camera.
Just because of one simple mistake.