So I have a DJI Phantom and it has it has zone restriction that you know so
that way they don't get in trouble as a company with like the FAA and there is
an airport near the studio and so I send the drone up and it takes it takes a few
beats before it gets GPS lock and so I send it about 35 40 50 feet up in the
air and by the time it gets to about 60 feet in the air it has very clear GPS
signal and it realizes that it's in a region lock zone and enforces the drone
down on me and there's really no way to get through it until I just let it get
GPS lock and the other day it almost came down in traffic and I'm sitting
there trying to abort the abort the landing abort the landing there's a car
coming and and it I was able to hold it up for a few seconds got the car to pass
like three feet from the car's roof and then as the car passed it landed then I
just have to I have to just agree to be safe and then I can send the drone back
up again but of course you then have to have your device that's connected to the
controller it has to be on some sort of data connection so it can ping the
servers that you've been authorized that you've agreed to the terms of use and I
had my I had my phone in airplane mode because like always whenever I'm doing
something I'm getting a ton of messages coming into my phone and I didn't want
them coming in over the over the UI of the drone so I turned my phone into
airplane mode so I can't I can't out I can't authorize it because part of the
authorization process is receiving a text message so there I am in the middle
of the road trying to get my phone out of airplane mode trying to get a text
message authorizing this drone so I can set it back up in the air out of the
road it's it's oh god is not annoying is there a way on iOS to get rid of the
drop-down notifications so they don't overlay on top you know well what I
realized I did what I should be doing later and I was just being dumb is put
it in do not disturb mode no but even if you have the do not disturb thing on
like the switch or whatever it doesn't actually do anything for the on-screen
notification I oh really well now I'm screwed now I'm I always have mine and
do not disturb mode always good man good man I have a solution though I'm you
know what I should do this is the really the the long-term solution here is get a
drone that doesn't have this control software on it because you know come on
I mean this is the problem is there's somebody else that's controlling what my
drone can do if Richard Stallman was here he'd be shaking his head at me he'd
be very disappointed good no good so look at this project it's a drone built
with a Raspberry Pi that's capable of streaming live to YouTube now this is
more my speed it's a quadcopter it's a quadcopter and it goes right either the
Raspberry Pi goes right on the top of it and it works it's legit the camera
could use a gimbal that's for sure I mean it's a work in progress and there
and then they're live streaming I there's no real like official control
software but they put a LG LTE card in it a SIM card it's got Wi-Fi antenna
it's got the camera for the right now the Raspberry Pi kit camera it's kind of
ingenious so maybe future vlogs will be powered by a Raspberry Pi drone this is
Linux unplugged episode 181 for January 24th 2017
Oh welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show with a host that's
flying solo this week well that's never really true my name is Chris and I can't
really be true when I got a virtual lug a packed virtual lug this week coming up
we're gonna talk about some big news that's breaking right now as we go on
the air that could affect the Unix landscape overall we'll talk about scale
15x and ubicon there's some really big project updates we're gonna get to this
week including those sly foxes over at Solus adopting flatback what yeah I
that's what I said when I literally did a war what when I saw the headline come
across my screen then a certain insider in the Ubuntu Mate project is gonna
leak some of the upcoming details and fanciness that'll be rolling out and
then Kali Linux yeah Kali Linux they're taking it up a notch you know they've
been around for ten years now ten years kind of makes me feel old to be honest
with you I think I've been using it for ten years anyways they have some big
news on their tenth anniversary that I'll tell you guys about and then we'll
touch a little bit on a future install a future rig build get some input from our
mumble room read some feedback and all of that goodness there's a lot to cover
in today's show mr. West couldn't make it this week he sends his apologies he
wanted to be here but there was just I'll just put it as this there was work
circumstances that came up you guys know how this how this industry goes sometimes
things just come up and you can't get away for the afternoon to podcast so we
we miss you Wes and you're here in spirit well I'll channel you from time
to time West but never fear we have a great team in our virtual log time
appropriate greetings mumble room
right now and you're plugging that doesn't matter you know there's a great
back catalog yeah I'll be fair late night Linux there you go there you go
you know what's gonna happen is they're gonna listen to that back catalog and
they're all gonna say I miss Laura so I don't really yeah that's a common
message that we hear yeah speaking of late night Linux mr. Ike is here hello
Ike it's good to have you here yeah and also returning to the show and I don't
know how I think it's almost been a year mr. Michael Hall hello mr. Hall well I
am looking forward to talking to all of you the course we all have a whole cast
of regulars in there too and so even though Wes isn't here we have a great
crew and everybody will be jumping in as we go along but I I don't like doing the
bad news stuff if we can avoid it so let's do like a quick breaking news kind
of thing yeah this is Linux unplugged breaking news and it's it's unfortunate
when this kind of story comes out but we kind of had a little bit of a sniff of
this story earlier Oracle is laying off more than a thousand employees according
to Mercury News Oracle's laying off approximately 450 employees in its Santa
Clara hardware systems division now that matters because that's the division that
was responsible for spark hardware which it appears to be where the majority of
these layoffs are coming from it looks like cloud is what Oracle cares about
now because software licensing Solaris and whatnot the revenue from that
plummeted by 20% last quarter and at the same time Oracle's hardware revenue also
fell 13% so there's just starting to essentially probably realign the
business with where they're actually making revenue from but it's kind of
sad because I think it's it's probably at least gonna signal a massive slowing
down for solaris at least that's that's my read of this story and that's kind of
why I thought it was worth covering today is because that overall affects the
Unix ecosystem I mean no entire in the entirety it's good it looks like it's
gonna be about 1,800 employees company-wide that will be pink-slipped
whoo there was already a story about this on the software side right like
they were talking about how they're canning the new major version it was
rumor at that point so that's kind of I think more recently though not only was
there the rumor that was like two or three months ago but there was a newer
story to back that oh yeah I was talking about the rumor we covered previously
yeah yeah I know I think there were two stories on the same thing yeah and this
is later yeah this has sort of been it's been there's been smoke signals really
since also pretty strong smoke signals since December it's not surprising
because like as someone who worked with solaris boxes at one point and saw the
transition to Red Hat next 86 I'm not surprised they're gonna have to close up
yeah especially since everyone wants more open infrastructure and they're
offering the most closed proprietary infrastructure it's just becoming more
of a commodity now where you need open infrastructure so this is just not
appealing yeah yeah and when I worked at Sun Microsystems we used to say solaris
for a pro Linux for show yeah I've heard that saying before and that's changing
yeah more now well yeah I mean especially with the lack of dedicated
resources right like I'm sure there are more dedicated resources in the Linux
community now than there are in this hilarious community oh for sure the
community it's not really a community and businesses and software services
around Linux and you know all the all of that when you go to a trade show you see
all of these middleware businesses that are selling Linux based solutions and
they're not none of them are selling anything that runs on solaris that's
that mean what I'm what I'm getting at there is the workloads we're becoming
more and more specific for solaris stations too yeah let's okay so let's
talk about something fun let's talk about something that I'm looking
forward to March 2nd through the 5th coming up at Pasadena convention center
is scale 15x the 15th annual Southern California Linux Expo we went last
year I think we've gone a few years past and I'll probably be going this year too
I'm gonna decide after today's show that's that's my plan and they just like
I believe last year too there will be an Ubicon summit to take place March 2nd
through the 3rd so sort of tucked up right next to scale and it looks like
it's gonna take place also in Pasadena so you just go to this location and you
can attend both events essentially am I getting it right mr. Hull yes actually
we're gonna be using two of the scale conference rooms for those two days
really I think this is such a good way to do it oh yeah we've got several
Ubicons that happen all over the world some of them are standalone some of them
co-host with another big conference like scale and it really helps the logistics
to be able to do that so what do I kind of expect if I'm gonna go to Ubicon is
it something that an Ubuntu desktop user would be interested is it something for
developers administrators who's the target and what should I expect it's a
little bit of both last year we had two tracks one for users and the other one
targeting developers and we're gonna do something similar again this year with a
little bit more workshop kind of sessions on the second day than we had
last year and then in the morning of both days we've got keynotes and
presentations going on that are generally relevant to anybody hmm well
see this feels like if I'm gonna go to scale I should plan to be down there a
few days earlier so that way I could be there for at least at least you know get
down there by the third but maybe even the second hmm I like that and so what
do you what is your overall goal is it to is it to inform community is it to
get more Ubuntu users what is the sort of strategy and why is canonical willing
to spend the resources on it well Ubicons are held by the community so the
Ubicon summit is being organized by the California community we're helping them
with logistics and we help you know as much as we can financially also you know
Michael I think it kind of feels like yeah oh for sure I think it kind of
feels like an official canonical event because last year you know the pretty
big canonical crew is there including mark shuttleworth so it feels like it's
a like in a big Ubuntu official event in a big official canonical event in some
sense but I forget that it's really community driven itself yeah last year
was kind of an oddball out because usually there's not that many people
from canonical being flown into Ubicons what is what is the rumor on on
shallow worth making it to Ubicon this year I don't think he's going to because
it actually overlaps a little bit with mobile world convert conference
happening oh wow yeah and we always have a big presence there and he's at that so
yeah I'm not sure if he's gonna get over I think he might try and get to scale
but I don't think he's gonna make it for Ubicon you know you know who I'd be
going to see would be Martin mr. wimpy down there but wimpy you're not gonna
make it this year either are you I don't think so no it's okay it's okay wimpy
it's all right I was just gonna buy you still I'm still buying Linux fest
Northwest though I think I owe you like a dozen beers so I'll make sure I'll get
I'll get them taken care of at Linux that's even better things mutual so
that's gonna be a fun night oh boy well you know what I tend I this I think this
year I'm gonna park at Linux fest in the parking lot so if we get if we get too
irresponsible we won't have to go very far because we'll just walk back to me
well Michael I'm gonna try it I think I'm gonna try to make it down there I'm
not sure what my whole approach is gonna be this year but I think I'll try to
make it down to Ubicon so how do I sign up do I need to pre-register can you
give me those details so we're still working that out I think we're gonna use
eventbrite for the Ubicon registration itself we just put out a call for papers
for the presentations that happened those two mornings and those are
actually going through the scale CFP system even though scales not taking
talk proposals anymore they still have it open so that people can submit them
for Ubicon you just use the Ubicon tag and they'll send all of those lists over
to Nathan Haynes and Richard Gaskin or the California team organizing all of
this the one thing I think I had some confusion on last year but from the
audience was I think some people thought you sign up for only one or do you have
to sign up for one and then sign up for the other signing up you don't get both
right you have to go you register for scale and then you register for Ubicon
is that what the how the format is gonna work yeah so the book cons
traditionally have been free to come and participate in you haven't had to
register you don't have to pay or anything to get in and what we've worked
out with the scale guys is that people can come into Ubicon without paying to
get into scale but we really encourage people to register to be at scale and to
go to all the scale talks in the conference or the expo floor and
everything because you know it's a huge conference it's totally worth going to
if you're gonna be there already for Ubicon anyway just pay the little bit
extra get into scale also yeah I second that for sure absolutely even if you
just walk the floor for a few minutes and you know say hi to a few people well
that that sounds pretty good yeah and compared compared to other huge shows
you know it's not expensive to get into scale at all what does it cost is it
free or is it it's not much no I want to say it was like $45 or something oh is
it so I always go in as media so I've never actually never had to pay for it
because they let media in for free but I think it's so reasonable that whatever
it is that it's it's I know it depends if you just want to go for the expo
floor it's kind of cheap it's like 20 bucks okay if you want I think the con
or the this the talks and things it's almost a hundred it's like 80 bucks yeah
and the reason why that kind of makes sense to me is because the talks are
gonna be more focused for people who are there probably because it's their
profession and and they would maybe even get work paying for that kind of but
that's really really cheap compared to other conference yes it's still under a
hundred bucks yeah yeah yeah very much so so pay to go to scale come to ubu con
for free if you're there the first day and I know Chris you weren't sure about
this but if you can get there the first day we've got Carl Rochelle from system
76 giving our keynote oh cool and I have been teased by Ryan that he has some new
announcements to make during that keynote well that is really neat Carl is
a super bright guy and really fascinating speaker so that will be a
really good keynote yeah I think I'm gonna try to make it I think I'm gonna
try to make it maybe I'll see if I can't ping the scale folks and maybe they can
get us a coupon because there are coupons out there floating around for
scale and that was yeah they just ended their special pricing I think that was a
couple days ago hmm but they had that going for and they still have student
discounts 50% off oh nice well mr. mr. Hall is there anything else you want to
add about ubi con before we chug along no just want to reiterate you know if
you want to give a presentation there we've got slots open go to the scale
call for papers and submit that with the ubi con tag we're also gonna have a
snappy workshop happening there that second day so if you want to learn how
to make snaps and go through the walkthrough of that yes I'll be there
hosting it also nice nice nice let's make sure I key attends haha I can't I
poke I poke I don't know if I believe that well I think it's gonna be a pretty
good show yeah and if you can make it to both come say hi because I'm gonna try
to make it down there I'm I try to make it down there for the whole thing with
Carl doing the keynote so maybe I'll end up doing some live shows from down there
too and doing a meetup we'll see we'll see I'll get my plans figured out I kind
of feel like this might be the year I fly down instead of drive down so I can
get down there cover it and get back up here quick because they might have
something coming up in the near future which would be a much longer drive and
probably save the wear and tear on the vehicle for that hey before we get into
like some seriously big feedback and some good updates and other things and
also big news for a cyanogen users I wanted to give mention to a project that
recently launched a refreshed website and it was it was really producer Michael
who threw it in my face because I don't I don't generally follow the cinnamon
desktop mod scene I guess you could call it but cinnamon spices which is
cinnamon-spices.linuxmint.com has been refreshed and relaunched make it easy to
modify your cinnamon desktop environment you know with things like themes
applets desktop desklets and of course extensions I don't really know if this
is something that appeals to most of you out there but I think it's worth
giving the the guys and gals working on this project to shout for the really
nice work they've done to showcase some of the stuff I mean it's dang it really
makes these themes it really makes this stuff look good so thank you to producer
Michael for throwing that in my face so if you are a cinnamon desktop user you
might want to go check that out I'll have a link to the cinnamon spices site
in the show notes lineage OS which was the continuation I suppose of the
cyanogen open source project I guess the cyanogen forked lineage OS we could say
for now have started surfacing we actually have real legit builds now that
will work on Nexus devices like the 6p and 5x now if you're already running
cyanogen mod there's an important note so pay attention to this you need to
first install the experimental ROM which has a big old ugly watermark on it
before you can start installing regular lineage OS builds otherwise lineage OS
is not gonna work at all you're also gonna have to be prepared to get a new
version of the G apps because that'll also require an update but you can get
experimental lineage OS nightly builds now on a bunch of devices but the ones
that jumped out at me where the 6p and 5x is anybody in the anybody in the
mumble room a cyanogen user or even an alternative ROM user on Android anybody
using different ones yeah I have it a space for selfish OS no okay so okay so
let's I think both Minnie and William was that who I heard just let's go
someone else okay me okay let's start okay let's start with producer Michael
and then we'll go Minnie so go ahead I used to use cyanogen mod before
cyanogen company was created but that was like my late my late phones I
haven't bothered yeah that's that's that's basically been my sub now Minnie
you said you were using cyanogen currently yeah we have it a space for
selfish OS for the ports for the Nexus 5 oh you have a port for us it's cyanogen
11 and 12 and there is one user he's working on cm13 even now and will that
eventually become lineage I don't know yeah I'll see now we now we are looking
for cm13 we got the base and we have some little struggles to go but if that
is working why not go further yeah I guess so I think it's I think it's good
that the projects continuing I don't I don't I don't feel good about the future
of the ROM market I feel like it's gonna get more constricted than ever I'm not
saying is dying I don't want to be dramatic about it but it doesn't seem
like it's it's particularly good wimpy are you still rockin Ubuntu touch is
your daily driver no oh done done done no hold on hold on now this we got to
stop the show we got to talk about this what happened tell me what happened I
got a Christmas present the holidays what did you get what did you one plus
3t oh and and it's now running Android it's probably running Cyanogen of a
type isn't it well it runs oxygen OS which is their their version of it yes
but I've set things up a little bit differently this time so I'm using the
f-droid store and almost none of the Google services very nice and how do you
like it is a good compared to what do you think compared to Ubuntu touch you
are you kind of glad to be back do you miss some features give me a sense of
that I miss the navigation of Ubuntu touch I think the way that the user
interface is moved around in Ubuntu is light years ahead of anything else it's
similar but different to sailfish so if you like sailfish there's some
similarities but I feel the Ubuntu interactions are more intuitive than
selfish selfish is kind of you have to know yeah that this thing does this
thing where with Ubuntu it's it's much more natural it's curious so I was
obviously using things that were like wraps of web applications on Ubuntu
touch and now I've come back to Android I'm actually using a lot of those rather
than native apps because in many cases now the web application version of
things is far better than the the native app version so for example Facebook is
one example of that yeah and the old reader is another two things that I
well one Facebook is for staying in touch with my family and the old reader
is where I get all my news from I think Facebook the perfect example I feel like
Facebook is safer as a web app than it is to have the Facebook app installed
on Android because yeah you never really know what it's doing and also with the
web app you get access to messaging and all of the other stuff that all separate
apps on Android you know as native native app so you know that's good in my
opinion yeah there's a there's a there's a slight thing where if you have if you
use a browser to do that that it tries to like it detect that you're using a
browser and it says oh you need to install the app but if you use a web app
wrapper it'll break that and make it think that it said not it's it's like a
desktop thing but it'll still show it as a mobile what a pain in the butt
mr. Hall I noticed that you said you kind of agreed that it looks like it
might be a dim future for alternative ROMs did you want to expand on that at
all oh I think you might have gone away yeah yeah I noticed you said you kind
of agreed that it looks like it might be a dim future for alternative ROMs on
Android did you want to expand on that a bit I don't think I agreed to that so
you think okay well I will second Martin though I've been on a galaxy s7 for
five months or so now and I totally missed the navigation of the phone yeah
that was the Nokia stuff right it's not what that was powered by on the boon to
phone I can't remember the mic was referring to the touch gestures not the
oh okay really that's interesting really honestly guys really honestly because I
got to tell you one of my biggest concerns about a boon to touch was that
the gestures were sort of opaque you didn't really you didn't have any idea
they were there so it seemed like it'd be hard to internalize them but that's
not the case no it only took like an hour to really get used to them and
within a week you're so addicted to it that whenever you go back to something
else you instinctively try and do those gestures that's good to hear how about I
guess I'm still I'm not convinced about discovery because you guys are kind of
bad examples because not only are you canonical employees but you're around
other people using a boon to touch and you were there during the UI creation so
if you came into a cold do you still have a sense that it would be
discoverable and usable it just seems so hard to find them I think so I mean the
the tuition the tutorial that runs on you know first startup that explains
what the four directions of movement are oh yeah that's right like 60 seconds to
complete and it basically introduces you to it's a pull down it's a pull up yep
and pulling in from the left and the right and that's the extent of it
completing the same tutorial on sailfish and for anyone that's got sailfish yet
they can maybe back me up to prove I'm not making up their tutorial takes about
five minutes to complete yeah and you can't skip through it you have to you
know do all of the steps yeah there's some Android like that too yeah and I I
always feel lost in sailfish when I want to swipe around it feels like you're
moving through one of these text dungeons you know go south go south by
southeast go go west go north and you're not to agree with you I mean I used an
N9 Nokia N9 before and the gestures were pretty much the same and on
sailfish you get used as with a boon to touch you get used pretty quick you use
ten minutes and you get used to it all right yeah I've not I've just not I
always feel lost when I use so I've got two selfish friends I've got the
original yolo phone and I've got the in tech aquafish yeah three gestures yeah
yeah and as soon as you master three gestures then you know you've got it
that does seem actually that does seem pretty reasonable especially combined
with the tutorial alright so let's let's cap off this conversation with the
obligatory web OS mention go ahead Michael go ahead yeah okay so I like
webOS yeah I was a huge fan back in the day their gesture structure was this
very similar to the how I want to touch works except instead of this from a side
interest it was the bottom entrance so like you had the same kind of really
pull the launcher from the side you had to pull the launcher from the bottom you
had the same like swipe away things except in a different direction it's
they're actually very similar so someone who was a webOS person would pretty much
just jump right into a bunch of touch well that's encouraging all right okay
now I want to run it on in my 6p that's that's official that's official hey
let's let's stop talking about mobile but before we go too much for the let's
talk about ting this seems like a great time to mention it well here's how you
get started with ting you go to the linux.ting.com linux.ting.com will get
you $25 off a device or $25 in service credit and think about this $25 in
service credit might pay for more than your first month because average ting
bill $23 after all you're sitting done here's how it works no contract nor
the termination fee and you only pay for what you use minutes messages megabytes
you pay for what you use linux.ting.com I love this system I was just talking
about in the pre-show how I have a couple of different my fives one on
ting's GSM network one on ting CDMA network and I use apps like open signal
to determine which one's gonna be stronger in whichever area I'm taking
the RV and that's the my fi I choose to use it's six dollars a month for the
line and if I don't use any data on that my fight for a month I'm paying six
dollars I could also just go in the control panel and turn it off it's
amazing it's great for when you're traveling it's great if you're an IT
worker and you need to have connectivity at a moment's notice and you want to
have two networks to choose from I love this functionality of course you can get
a phone that's on either network to doesn't really I mean I'm talking about
my files but you could use it as a phone I've got three phones on the ting
network and I think it's a fantastic service usually and if I'm not using
like my my advice a bunch which I use actually just lightly this weekend it's
it's so fantastic because I think maybe even with the holidays the phone bills
gonna be like around 45 bucks this month three lines when I'm at work and I'm at
home I'm using Wi-Fi all the time and so I might be making a few extra calls for
the holidays you on the average my phone bills around 35 dollars a month for all
three lines so it really averages out to be it's just an unbelievable price you
can get a little idea by going over to Ting's website and see kind of what it
would cost for you it's a really nice service because I also back it with
fantastic customer service an awesome control panel an active blog full of
good information tons of devices including ones you can just bring
yourself like one from the play store just hint hint nudge nudge check them
out linux.ting.com and a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring the unplugged
program and a happy customer for a long time now linux.ting.com this is an
interesting post and I just will touch on it really quickly I don't think we
have to have a lot of conversation about it excuse me Chrome 56 is going to
aggressively throttle background tabs hallelujah this is just kind of all you
really need to really know but they can they're coming up with like a timer and
a budget system and each tab and is gonna get a timer and then it's gonna
get a budget and the budget regenerates with a certain amount of activity and
all this it's they got a very very Google sophisticated system and they're
talking about how it'll affect applications like slack and discord or
bit mix or a Bitcoin trading site and there could be some major effects so you
might want to go check it out if you are heavily dependent on one of those
applications or a developer on one of those projects because it's gonna be big
eventually Chrome 56 is gonna be a big deal but it probably will help a lot of
us with like two core laptops on battery and you're running Chrome this is
probably gonna make life a lot better for you yeah all that budget gets
submitted to Google that is an interesting thought Altera wouldn't it
be in wouldn't that be a fascinating because they you know they do ask if you
want to opt into like diagnostics and air reporting I wonder if that time
budget and things like that would be diagnostic data
whoo that sense chills down my spine I mean for the first release I'm sure it
probably will be right because it's not gonna be a perfect system right away the
amount of data that gives googs about the what I mean it makes Google
Analytics look like child's play that is a that is a striking thought but not
just what sites you go to but how you engage with them how actively you engage
with them how long they said idle on your website they could tell you we can
go ahead we can just we can see if it's total if it's going to be in chromium
and Chrome or just in Chrome whether they're gonna be collecting data or not
yeah hmm that's a well we'll see we'll see where that goes maybe none of that's
gonna happen too so I want to talk about some feedback that I've gotten on
Sunday's Linux action show and I shouldn't really cross the streams like
this but I kind of want to take advantage of the mumble room so this
seems like the perfect opportunity I've been considering building something that
I'm gonna just called because we all understand what I say when I mean this
when I read what I mean when I say this I'm just gonna say it's like a
bulletproof Linux installation something that isn't like a fun Linux installation
isn't isn't like something I'm gonna run on all my systems but one of my
workstations maybe two would be set up in a way that is it's meant to be like a
five-year installation with absolute minimum failure maybe with a I would
love to say even a tolerance of one failure failure a year so that probably
includes maybe a hard a hard drive mirror maybe it also includes a UPS
power so there's some physical aspects of this too but right now what I wanted
to focus on because it's more germane to our show would be the Linux
configuration that would actually make this possible and I've been I've been
toying with the idea of installing solace as the base operating system and
relying on the fine folks over at solace to package up some of the core desktop
applications that I want like no pressure I key yeah like Telegram like
Google Chrome you know those types of the general desktop environment hoping
and maybe it maybe I should wait till after budget 11 but hoping that there
would be sort of a a consistency and stability there and then a lot of the
more esoteric applications many of which being web-based like sab NZB couch
potato sonar those would run in containers like Docker containers and
other other applications that maybe I would just sort of concoct one day and
maybe I would also sort of also supplement this with an arch virtual
machine that has access to the AUR or something for command line or maybe even
graphical applications so I've been this has been something that I've been
kicking around but I think mangas is how I'm gonna say it three days ago on a one
day ago in the Linux action show sub wrote it subreddit wrote I have the
feeling that container ization is not the solution for you Chris last I think
that you have to accept the three M's that Noah pointed out in last you go a
boon to LTS and you really should use something like snap packages also set up
a clone and whatnot but he he argues that because predominantly what I'm
going to want on this machine is of is a wide selection of desktop applications I
should probably go with an LTS snap flat pack approach for the container and
container izing contain the specific applications and use a boon to LTS for
the base operating system and just go something with much more generic and
maybe says yeah I could go fancy with CFS or something like that but and this
has been sort of a common thread that's come in is don't go as far as
container ization just go a boon to LTS or a you know maybe it's a bit of a tail
test or whatever it is but you go with a tried-and-true Ubuntu install and you
don't you skip the Docker container ization and you go with snaps and flat
packs and when I every time I look at this idea which doesn't seem to be too
too insane that kind of kind of look at and go why why does this not appeal to me because it
feels like the path of least resistance I could get a 1604 based install in 15
minutes I could go get a few snap packages 10 minutes after that and I may
theoretically be pretty close to done at that point I'm sure there's a few things
I still have to work out so it does have definitely has the appeal of being the
path of less resistance but with what I what I feel like it I feel like it's not
really ready yet like it seems like it's the easy path but in reality I love snap
packages I love everything getting snapped up but some of the things I want
don't get updated as frequently as I want because they're not being the
package itself is not being maintained upstream it's being maintained by a
volunteer some applications I want may may not be available things like steam
compatibility are still a big a big priority for me and making steam work
really easily and not break is a big priority for me and I don't really see
like a flat pack snap solution to that specifically either it feels like to me
if I'm building a five-year system today in terms of application availability
docker probably blows away just about every linux distros repo out there in
terms of current modern applications being developed that I would want to try
to talk about in reviews and whatnot docker is a massive distribution
platform already I would argue larger than snap packages and so if you were
building a system for today it actually seems like docker would be the one to
use today and then in five years put your head up and go okay all right all
right so let's take a look around where how what's gotten snapped up what's
gotten flat packed and when it's time to rebuild that would be the time to
evaluate that so I I've been getting a lot of that feedback and I've been
reflecting on I think I actually think the snaps and flat packs would be more
down the road should I pause here does anybody want to jump into the mumble room
before I continue on my question was is there a possibility to use LXC LXD
containers for GUI applications I mean I'm not really you know I I'm not
really sold on any particular containerization or necessarily even
containerization over virtualization or even a fancy cheroot really to be honest
I don't really have any strong leaning my one preference towards docker would
be it's pretty simple to set up on solace and it's got a huge application
availability on docker hub and there was actually some subset of those
applications up on docker hub that are being properly maintained by projects
that really care and you can you can suss that out eventually and there
there's still enough of those that it's a pretty wide set of applications to pick
from so kind of leaning docker that reason okay I wanted to so let's talk about let's
let's take all of this conversation and let's shift over to solace they
announced this week that they're adopting flat packs they've also they've
also been an update recently about some big changes coming in q1 to the to the
desktop including including something called why was it here don't have it
here bulletproofing we're gonna talk about all of this we're really gonna
talk let's talk about this so let's take a moment if we're talking about
containers we're talking about virtualization and you want to know more
go to Linux Academy Linux Academy comm slash unplug sign up take advantage of a
seven-day free trial support the show and learn more about all of these
technologies they have really dedicated professionals that follow this stuff
like legit people in the industry that have come to Linux Academy now we're
working with them consulting with them they have full-time instructors I think
this is where you get the knowledge directly from the people that know
what's up and I love it because the people behind the company started
because they're Linux enthusiasts and somebody who runs their company because
they water a Linux and started my company because I'm a Linux enthusiast
yeah I really dig that and it really kind of is the perfect essence behind
what they're all going for Linux Academy comm slash unplug that's where you go
find out about their self-paced in-depth video courses and just about every Linux
topic out there they got labs to give you hands-on real-world experience you
build the confidence you need when you go do the job which I've learned makes
all the difference instructor mentoring when you do need it a community that's
stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members courses specifically for cert
training if that's where you're going and course schedulers for those of us
that are cray cray busy and you need to have something custom built out for you
to match that schedule Linux Academy comm slash unplug they also have public
profiles if you need to let management know what you've been doing that's been
really nice for me in the past when I had I what I used to do is I had these
little systems these little papers that I would track my stuff in in a
spreadsheet and I would hand it in because I would go to community
colleges to get my course updating to get my training updating that work
thankfully paid for but you know with a public profile like this such a genius
system makes it work so it's just all automated plus if you're you know talking
to a client or looking for a gig very useful there too Linux Academy comm
slash unplugged whoo go there to support the show sign up for a seven-day free
trial and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged
program so I don't really know where to start Aiki because I am so excited about
all of this but I feel like let's start with flat packs and then I'd like to
talk about some of the other stuff you guys are doing sort of in q1 so what the
hell flat packs what this is this is huge because I thought we had this big
discussion on this show about how you weren't really a big fan of snaps or
flat packs you wanted to you wanted to be in control of the software that gets
bundled for your district what's what's changed in that respect actually nothing
so remember the most of the people are having this discussion based on
universal apps the problem that we have in solace as you've probably seen
yourself is we have a very very weird mechanism for deploying third-party
software like Google Chrome mm-hmm mm-hmm and it just doesn't work very well I
mean it's flaky I'm a big challenge are you mentioned a couple times in your
post the Google the Google Chrome problem solving the Chrome problem the
only thing I really if from my experience was I went to a third-party
section and it seemed like it took a significantly long time to install Chrome
I could I had the sense something was going on behind the scenes but I don't
really understand what is the Chrome problem okay so I mean you're not
allowed to distribute Chrome full stop only Google can do that which you know I
mean that's fair enough so the way that we get around that is behind the scenes
it's actually downloading the Devon repackaging it is an EO package then
installing that locally but I mean to do things like that I mean there's things
like exit compression involved and all this stuff which is why it takes
horrifically long amount of it's not viable there is no update mechanism for
it so we had to reevaluate it because at the end of the day anyone's personal
views aside it's leading to a poor user experience so one of the developments I
saw recently in Flatpak I say recently recently ish is it can it supports
downloading extra files at installation time now the first place I saw this was
over on Endless how to dig around there and I could install Chrome straight from
the software center so the more I dug into it it turns out that they're making
use of the same thing that I'm gonna be making use of and it's essentially still
pulling the debt but it's doing it in a way that's efficient quick supports
updates and it's transparently integrated and in the end I mean I put
the poll up on Google Plus but that itself wasn't a deciding factor but it
was definitely one of the things that enabled it as an option for me so the
other thing that probably comes to most people's mind is why say snaps why not
say snaps or app image or one of the other competitors oh well I mean app
images again it's the same distribution problem so it's immediately out I mean
an app image contains a file system which means it would contain Google
Chrome so it's in the out of the races mm-hmm and then again it's you know it's
now but snaps include snaps do have the ability to pull files down and sort of
essentially work around that problem right and don't get me wrong there was
there's a lot of hype and love around snap but it may if I'm gonna integrate
something into solos it's got to be done properly it's got to be done fully so we
don't have app armor and solos now you can yes you can run snaps without app
armor but again they don't get properly and I exactly a sandwich fully and
properly you've got a enable app armor now that's an obstacle in terms of
integration so there was a lazy aspect to it because it would be there's a
large integration challenge or something like snap but the main thing that
actually won me over in the end I mean everything else aside integration
problems distribution all that side of it was being engaged on a technical
level consistently by the flat back camp and every time I brought this up online
every time I've ranted about it discussed it bitched about it whatever
that fact has always remained true they've always engaged with me now fair
play it to snaps as well because Michael Hall actually contacted me offline after
and you know I've got a lot of respect for that but I was being engaged on a
technical level consistently by the flat back team and they've always answered my
responses and it's more aligned with what works in solos and for me it's kind
of what won in the end I had to be on technical merit only it couldn't be on
the hype it couldn't be around marketability and the universal apps part
of it at this point in time is currently not interesting to me I'm talking about
distributing some third-party applications now does this also solve any
problems around packaging steam for solace so what we're doing with steam at
the moment I mean at the moment we have this steam runtime compatibility if you
like within our repos works really well now but give it a couple of years
something like that would eventually fall apart at the seams because you know
they're gonna be using older have a an ABI problem so large you wouldn't be
able to solve it anymore so while it works for now it's not a long-term
solution match you spoke about this on late night Lennox last night I know
plug so so so so but yeah I mean it's kind of soulless only which is kind of
not fair so what I've done is I proposed to
upstream I opened up a github issue and it'll basically like here's the cards on
the table I would like to take everything we've learned about building
the same runtime because we're actually pretty good at that and offer one in the
form of a flat pack runtime which is optimized which has all the things that
we want then anyone flat back would be able to use it on any distro not just
solace so it makes it a lot easier than for distributions to have steam because
they're kind of hmm an omen an hour in about the whole lib 32 crap it would be
a lot easier for them they don't need to have like a 32-bit driver so this would
be though kind of all back-end plumbing right if I'm if I'm a user of solace I
would just basically hit an install button in the oh yeah definitely yeah
you don't want to complicate it it's got to be natively what it mean though as a
solace user I could run other flat packs that I found yes so the one thing I
didn't want to do is say like this is only for third-party and that's all
you're gonna use it for yeah if we're gonna do it we're gonna do it properly
yeah and that again that was the thing when was looking to snap it would have
been hard to integrate that properly into solace for a flat pack it's very
very simple for us to integrate producer Michael you had a question about can or
sandboxing yeah same as in categorization whatever the flat packs
originally we're doing via Wayland so how did they approach the issue this
like if they have it right now sorry I didn't quite get I don't know if they're
I actually just saw a blog post about this I think this is sort of in the work
still isn't it I didn't I didn't read the post yet I had tagged it for reading
but I haven't if one of the issues of is is app app armor is not available to be
to install and solace but the flat pack is covering this issue for security but
last time I checked they they don't have sandboxing for that yeah oh they do have
a sandboxing mechanism in place it's called bubble wrap and it effectively
creates a kernel level it's effectively a container you know okay to avoid they
don't call it a container because it has all the connotations of Docker and
things like that but effectively it's like a it's a kernel level namespace and
container containerization yeah and then you have there's a there's basically a
debossed proxy that sits in the middle that filters all out the cold you've got
a sec comp which is involved as well so we can actually filter system calls
going through so in terms of integrating into solace I had to update lib sec comp
and I made one patch which has now been merged upstream already and that was to
actually support a stateless configuration in solace so it was very
very easy to integrate for a Google Chrome itself we wouldn't be sandboxing
it here's the difference so we'd still be using the native file system stuff
there it's just effectively a way to distribute and update it so the
sandboxing for that part isn't important but for future and applications that are
being distributed as these things start to get more popular obviously we do want
that fully integrated that makes sense so I want how will I see this and when
will I see this as a solace user is my am I gonna be waiting for a while oh no
no no no no that wouldn't be fair at all so at the moment we are doing a very
very large stack upgrade we're going from normal 3.20 to norm 3.22 you will
see me ranting and raving about it on Google Plus at the moment I'm not in a
good mood with some parts of it but anyway so while we're doing that we also
try and bring up some of the reverse dependency so flat back has already gone
in there at the moment okay that's part of the next update series that will go
into the main repos but it's gonna be a colossal update like when I got as far
as packaging I think it was Nautilus which was the first gnome app that I'd
updated there was already 200 updates to solace by that time yeah so it's I'll be
nice I'm gonna issue some Delta updates as well but yeah so the next set of
updates that will all come through flat pack is already in the repos and
enabled now we just need to plummet into the software center to make it all work
nicely so that's that's kind of huge that's kind of a huge thing and you
talked about something else in a recent post talking about budgie 11 and you
talked about bulletproofing I think was the verbiage was like bulletproofing the
upgrade process yeah bulletproof boot is what it is oh yeah that was the name I
gave it so the kernel update mechanism in solace isn't great effectively you're
having the carpet ripped out from under your feet every time you read every time
you upgrade now there is a variety ways to do it in some different distributions
and that usually involves having a meta package which will then depend on a new
package that comes in and then you end up with multiple parallel kernels
installed the way that I'm doing it I'm actually adopting something that I
developed at work which is clear boot manager from clear Linux which is an
Intel project what I'm doing is make adapting that to actually support solace
fully and more importantly be generic enough that would work for over
distributions so the way that this effectively works is you take the
control of the kernel away from the package manager now that's probably
gonna sound a little bit weird mm-hmm so if you upgrade a package on your disk it
takes away any files are left there the difference is with this approach you
have this package once you upgrade it leaves the old files on the disk they
are no longer within its domain then clear boot manager is fired up the first
thing that does is make sure that the new your running kernel has to stay
there that's like rule one it has to stay that you're not allowed to remove
the running kernel this is a very bad thing to do it will then install the
latest kernel and the last running kernel so when it goes to install them
also make sure they're repaired so they're fully present on the disk if
anything's happened to them it will actually repair them and fully restore
the EFI system how does it accomplish this through the code that I wrote
basically I mean it's like pulling code down and patch like what it what's
happening no no no so like if you upgraded now like in solace you'll be
automatically shipped to this new package it's called Linux LTS and that
will be on the 4.9 branch so when you update the old files stay there and so
are the new files they're specifically namespaced versions with release
everything is encoded in the name of these files so when you upgrade it
automatically knows which one is the next new kernel because we'll have a
symlink which is default LTS shipped as part of the packaging so it knows who
the new guy is when it looked at the you name output that is also encoded to
carry the version release and type information of a kernel so it knows
which one needs to stay which one needs to be repaired and which ones need to be
garbage collected and so this is how it's able to this is how the package
managers able to just not even worry about it and it's able to exactly that's
really so the package manager it comes along so say we went from 4.9 point 4 it
then deposits all the 4.9 point 5 files on there the difference is now that
default LTS link is changed from the old 4.9 point 4 to the 4.9 point 5 one and it
doesn't have to be a version update it can just literally be like bumping a
release to fix something your current kernel will stay on there the one you
booted before will stay on there because we run a systemd unit at boot and once
it's got past the multi user target it records that information to a file so it
knows that that kernel successfully boots anything that doesn't meet those
parameters is then garbage collected from the disk including the initial RAM
disks which are now shipped as part of the package instead of being generated
at install time which is risky so everything is now pre-shipped ready to
go so you're never gonna have a situation where you upgrade and kernel
modules go missing and things disappear and you can't roll back so does this
clear root manager land install list as as well I mean at the same time that
Linux 4.9 does so I'm actually on the 4.9 now but yeah they will come
together so basically you'll have one last derpy upgrade which is going from
the 4.8 stuff because that part of it is unavoidable because it was broken to
start with once that's happened should be upgraded to the 4.9 and from then on
you can just keep upgrading and if there is ever a problem you can just roll back
to the old kernel now the difference between this approach and you know the
typical pseudo update grub kind of crap you have to record bits of those
information around for it to keep working properly so if you've ever had
encrypted installs you've got to keep hold of like the resume parameter
parameters the locks uuid parameters the root equals all of that stuff and it's
even harder for UEFI clever manager is is picking up all this information
automatically and recording it so it's entirely stateless it can completely
restore a boot partition for you so I put a video up on my Google Plus if you
want to go and have a look at it okay I basically RM RF everything on my ESP
which is something you probably shouldn't do but then just to kind of
demonstrate the confidence in that I ran the command and BAM my ESP was
restored including the bootloader itself because it manages the updates
that as well I will have a link to iQIYI's G plus page in the show notes as
well as to the clear boot manager that's that's a pretty nice upgrade that'll be
that that does sound like if it's everything works as intended that it
should make that update process much more bulletproof that's kind of going
for that's what I'm going for yeah I mean it's been used in clear Linux now
for a long time obviously here I'm not speaking on behalf of Intel while I'm
here now I'm speaking on behalf of Solus but it's a project I work on at work and
we've been using it there for a long time and it does work it's you know it's
field proven if you like and the the original thing that basically bugged me
was dual booting on an EFI system partition nobody really does that nicely
I mean if you look at some systems you'll get like a slash init RD zero dot
image and things like this who does it belong to you know where's the domain
ownership and then you have these subfolders it's kind of nasty so I
wanted to basically implement standards and have a way that things can cohabit
peacefully on an ESP without conflicting so the Solus kernel now is like a con
dot Solus project and then it'll have like the version everything coded into
the file names so you don't have to worry about things conflicting or
fighting over the ESP so I'm also making it very agnostic so if anyone else does
want to integrate it into their projects they're more than welcome to and so does
this make it possible to say run multiple branches of the kernel so say
if I wanted to have yes yeah yeah I mean that was one of the motivations
because in Solus there is a kernel package it's just called kernel like
you're kind of limited on new choices there which is kind of sucky because we
have to run the kernel that's gonna be safe for everyone but sometimes there's
hardware enablement differences or we need experience with that new branch of
the kernel before it becomes a new kernel so this one is becoming the Linux
LTS kernel so you'll upgrade and that's what you're going to okay it that'll be
handled automatically then the default on the LTS yeah just to make sure
everyone's safe you're you're gonna go to the LTS branch and then that's where
you're gonna be by default are you tracking Greg cage is that where the LTS
moniker comes from or yeah basically so that would be the 4.9 branch for now and
once 4.10 is stable then we can start like a Linux mainline package to kind
of you know have a bit of symmetry between holes and kernel dot org just so
you know where you stand I like that a lot I think that's a good idea well okay
well that's a hell of that's a hell of a lot of awesome stuff that's making me
really want to continue to use solace so that's good that's yeah there's a lot of
things that are coming we've just started up budget desktop to org as well
you know we say I do want to talk about a little bit about budget if we could
yeah I mean you know yourself I mean budget Evans kind of achieved a meme
status by now yeah you know like after budget 11 this thing and that but it's
actually nine now now I'm nervous because I'm like I feel like things are
just getting stable for me and then my desktops gonna get swat just pulled
right out from underneath me and no no budget is going nowhere I mean you have
my full assurances now so I'm worried about big changes it sounds like 11 is a
pretty big rewrite well the thing is well I'm gonna be explaining more of this
in the blog post later there's I don't want to spill the beans but it will be a
significant blog post but effectively it's we're taking measures that will
limit our creative freedom which will make budget a lot better because we've
got some long-standing bugs that we just haven't been able to fix so those will
be coming and cue boy oh boy it's big stuff but yeah sounds like all of this
is basically focused on one singular topic it's about giving users the
experience they deserve right now with budget we are not there you know we are
not there there are some annoyances some bugs that are there and the user
shouldn't have to put up with this shit so that's what all of this quarter is
about it's getting everything in place so the users can actually have that
experience that they deserve from their computer that they bought that computer
you know they shouldn't have to suffer these stupid bugs so we will have that
up there and it's going fully fully distro agnostic like it's up on its own
namespace and get hope has its own domain it has its own blog so it's gonna
be very some people you know are gonna be how people are when they see
something about new stuff and this is how we do things but it's believe me
it's for the best I will say I say from the blog post keep an open mind and
we'll wait for updates maybe you come back you tell us a little bit about it
don't care all right well I want to also I've never installed oh hey I'm
doing a show excuse me I wanted to also mention some big updates that are coming
to our friends over at Ubuntu Mate as well as Kali which I am super super
excited about so we should keep moving so we can make room for tech snap you
know I would be a miss if I didn't mention DigitalOcean that's the secret
sauce guys that's the secret sauce it's a super simple straightforward cloud
hosting provider that'll get you up and going in no time if you're a one-man
team up to a multi-million dollar company DigitalOcean is gonna work
great for you because it's it's super intuitive it's super reliable super fast
I'm trying to think of another super super SSDs I'm losing it I got I don't got
any more supers but it is a great service and it deserves all the supers I
can come up with they've paired an amazing user interface that really is
accomplished it accomplishes it's simple to use while also being very advanced
and letting people that know what the heck they're doing just to go at it like
I'm automatically attaching your SSH keys spinning up multiple VMs from
templates snapshots and backups but the best part is all of its exposed by a
very simple straightforward gotta love it API and you know my day-to-day usage
I talk about the UI so much because I was born in the fire of a time when
virtual machine management only ran under Windows and it was the worst
slowest MMC UI knockoff you'd ever seen so now in 2017 to sit here and look at
this DigitalOcean interface it just blows me away so that's what I always
focus on but the reality is their API is really where it's at on it as a daily
driver of DigitalOcean for spinning things up and down for our
infrastructure all day long up and down up and down all day long I'm using the
API I'm using bot commands that trigger the API to be honest that's how I'm
doing it and it makes it so easy to integrate DigitalOcean infrastructure
that's in San Francisco for me and in New York and it's just like one single
bot command and in the background these systems spin up online these sites go
active these streams turn up it is so incredible making multiple systems is a
snap as well you can do it from a snapshot but it is super simple and the
other thing that's really nice is not only can you transfer droplets to other
folks so say you're gonna build something for a client or for a friend
or a family member etc etc it also is really great working with teams for your
personal you say you want to do a mumble server a Minecraft server an IRC server
a sync thing bit torrent sync all of that they have 40 gigabit connections
SSDs for all of the machines and data centers all over the world check it out
at DigitalOcean.com just do me a favor when you sign up apply our promo code
DOUNPLUGGED DOUNPLUGGED to your account you get a $10 credit you can try out that
$5 rig two months for free DigitalOcean.com use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED
so there has been a massive leak Edward Snowden size leak about the progress on
Ubuntu Mate there's an insider I'm not familiar with this person I think his
name is Martin I'm not sure who he is but Wimpy is here to help us make sense
of all of this so Wimpy there's some really nice things coming down the road
and there's also some stuff that we talked about previously on the show from
Ikey Brisk in there so where do you want to start with the update for the Mate
project okay well let's start with Brisk we've just heard from Ikey I don't know
if you noticed he's quite a clever chap isn't he lots of technical detail there
that said he does need help from an older wiser gentleman with bitwise
operators from time to time but aside from that he's a smart cookie yeah so
let's start with Brisk because there's there's some news there that I've not
announced that dovetails with that Ikey released Brisk menu 0.3.0
yesterday evening and that's being developed as a an efficient menu for the
Mate desktop and we created a PPA for Ubuntu for that so if you're running
16.10 or 17.04 you were able to get 0.2.0 release and that PPA is now up to
date with the 0.3.0 release so if you're already using that PPA you'd
have got your updates today and there's a bunch of bug fixes for Brisk in there
and that's cooking along nicely I've gone through Ikey's issue tracker and
sort of highlighted the bits that I'm interested in seeing and Ubuntu Mate
we're in our second month now Ikey we're up into the crowdfunding from
Ubuntu Mate some of that money's being funneled into Solus so that Ikey can
work on Brisk for the Mate desktop as a whole which is really cool to see that
is cross distro collaboration yes and I also heard that mr. producer Michael
there in the in the mobile room was involved in updating high DPI and low DPI
for what what icon themes I think it was that's right yeah so yeah Michael in the
chat room here producer Michael he retouched all of the assets in the not
the icon theme but the the GTK theme itself so things like sliders switches
radio buttons and all of that sort of thing and all of the outlines for those
in the shading they've all been retouched so that there are two versions
there's a low DPI and a high DPI version available for those now yes so that's
all good stuff and yet he was another fund that was another funded contribution
in the same way that the work from Daniel for a elementary he he contacted
me just before the Christmas holidays and he was saying you know would we be
interested in adopting some of his updated folder icons and things of that
nature in Ubuntu mate because those of you that don't know Daniel years ago
used to work I think is on a contract basis but worked with or for Ubuntu on
the humanity icon themes so that all of those icons that you're using in a bun
to originated from his work and he's refined and improved those over time and
he was saying you know did I want to adopt the new the new version of that so
he did a bunch of work and we've adopted those icons and then they are a few that
looked a bit rough because they were the old style and he's now touching up a few
of the others there so we've got a whole new icon theme for all of the common
actions and folders and stuff like that and that's all come from Daniela
elementary and again funded through the Ubuntu mate crowdfunding that is slick
I really that sounds like some really nice updates it's great that the
crowdfunding is making that possible too that's I love it's really so it's made
quite a difference you might remember me saying I think it was a few months ago
we got sponsorship from bite mark to cover all of our hosting and bandwidth
now and that took a few months to fully kick in all of the advantage of that
because although we moved to them as soon as they made that available to us
we'd got some longer term hosting agreements with some other providers
that we've had to sort of be paying for well that all ended at the end of
December so this January is the first month where we're completely free of any
legacy hosting payments and already for January the amount of funding that
Ubuntu Marte is paying out to other projects and independent open source
developers is sitting around two and a half thousand dollars of money going to
other developers to work on either Marte or Ubuntu Marte related projects so if
we're able to keep that up over the next 12 months that will mean that we get
good quality consistent contributions coming into the projects that we care
about but some of those cross distro collaborations that's money going back
into those projects that they can use to fund their own work and for the the
part-time collaborators you know some of them are students and some of this money
is meaning that they don't have to flip burgers at the weekend they can actually
work on open source and get get a decent amount of money in return so that's
really hoping that that will that will continue to escalate over the next year
so you know what I really want to talk about though is I'm guessing the Mate
desktop 2.0 I mean you got you put 2.0 on there and I want to know I want to know
more details yeah so internally within the the Marte team there's there's sort
of four of us that make up the core team and there's two of us that want to go
with Marte 2.0 and the other two are like no let's call it 1.18 so I'm kind of
forcing the agenda here by putting it out there that it could be a Marte 2.0
and it might it might still be well we'll have to have some polite
conversations and agree agree that this is what we're going to do but the reason
for for this distinction in my mind is that with the next stable release which
at this point could be 2.0 or it could be 1.18 it's the first version which is
you can only build against GTK 3 all of the legacy GTK 2 code has been removed
from the entire project so that's all gone now and there's been some other
incremental improvements there but really that I feel that 2.0 is worthy
because GTK 2 is gone yeah and it would be nice to know that the one series was
the one that you could build against GTK 2 and the two series is the one that
meant went to GTK 3 that yeah and then you know we've had on our roadmap you
know this gentle progression to GTK 3 has always been more so from some of the
other distributions they've got an eye on adopting Wayland so another step
towards Wayland is this current so we have the development snapshots they're
currently 1.17 those development snapshots now have support for lib input
which is a modern library for handling input devices including you know mice
and trackpads and trackballs and touchscreens and what-have-you which
supports both Wayland and X11 so that's in there now so we're looking for some
testing and feedback on that but that gives if you've ever used lib input on
say GNOME 3 which has had it for a little while now you'll notice that the
the sensation of especially on trackpads you feel like your finger is really
moving the mouse rather than there's sort of your dragging your your finger
movement is disconnected from you know what you see on the screen with lib
input those things very sort of glued together and you can feel that that
that relationship is very strong so that's good and it opens up some
compatibility so improves things like disabling taps when you're typing and
stuff like that is much better palm detection oh yeah that's great stuff
oh and then that also puts you closer to Wayland right it does and then with
fedora 25 going to Wayland by default the fedora maintainer for Marte he's now
had a series of bug reports where some people are installing pieces of Marte on
top of fedora 25 running GNOME 3 and then those applications don't work
under Wayland so this is things like Kaja the file manager I have Marte the
image viewer the terminal you know various other bits and pieces the text
editor and what have you so we've now got this to the point where the
applications will run as applications on top of Wayland now that doesn't mean you
can bring up the whole of the Marte desktop in a Wayland session that's a
little way off but the individual applications when they're running on
Wayland will now run on one of them and that's plume of the text editor can run
natively on top of Wayland so baby steps but we're getting there we're getting
there yeah sounds like the way yeah the way this supports integrated I'm hopeful
that this will also mean that Mia will will work as well but I shall be testing
that later in the year hmm so Ryan types in the chat room there is asking if
you've heard any little bird or birdies tweeting about perhaps live input ending
up in unity and Ubuntu because that seems like that'd be a nice feature
upgrade for Ubuntu desktop to have you heard any discussions mmm I may have
done but I'm foggy on this so what I'll have to do it Ryan I will check some
things and get back to you on that I think I think it's in unity 8 already
I'm pretty sure about that it's not in unity 7 and I wonder if one window
digging around a launchpad if you might just get the answer yeah well I will
need to go off and have a little look in there in the code repositories but I'm
not but I'm aware of but that doesn't stand for anything because some of the
people are working on this sort of disconnected from from what I'm doing at
the moment so for end users what am I gonna what kind of new stuff is landing
for that we've just discussed as landing in the in the next release
everything we've just discussed is in the next release already it's already in
the development snapshots you are crazy sir remember how remember how one of
these releases you're just gonna kind of back off and just have like a really
boring release remember how that's gonna happen this is this is this is that one
yeah everything I've just discussed is what's happening in Marte itself rather
than Ubuntu Marte oh so Ubuntu Marte is is going to move to the next version of
the Marte desktop that's nice release we've already uploaded Marte 1.1 7
development snapshots to the Zesty archive so if you install a Zesty daily
image for Ubuntu Marte now you get all of this stuff I've just been talking
about if you download the alpha which is coming out in a week or so then you know
you'll get all of this stuff but in terms of what Ubuntu Marte is doing all
of that high-level you know headline-grabbing stuff we've just spoken
about is only part of it there was a load of rough edges in Marte 1.1 6
because that was the one where we sort of really jumped to GTK 3 and it was
available everywhere although it's still a build time option for some of the
components and I've been going through the issue trackers on launchpad and on
github for Marte and joining up all of this stuff and sponsoring the upstream
Marte developers to fix all of the sort of the real serious papercut issues
with with that transition to GTK 3 so there's a lot of refinement going on in
Marte in this release and consequently that will filter into Ubuntu Marte so
they it's just going to be boring and fixes is very true for Ubuntu Marte
we've got some shiny new artwork from from Daniel I really wanted to bring the
brisk menu into the Ubuntu archive now but for those of you that don't know
Debian stretch what will be Debian 9 they're in final freeze in a few days so
consequently they're not allowing new packages into Debian and if they don't
go to Debian then they don't automatically sync to Ubuntu and I
prefer when I'm working on Marte to do everything in Debian so these packages
have been so brisk has been uploaded to Debian it's in the new queue and it
won't get out of the new queue until Debian 9 is released so maybe I'll
upload it just as an Ubuntu version at some point but I'm I just want to see
what happens see does Debian 9 materialize in this cycle in this window
but I've done a bit of work with brisk so that you can have the brisk menu with
its search capability and you can still have the places and system menu along it
so instead of applications places and system you can now have the brisk menu
and you get menu places and system so you still have the three-tiered menu you
still have places and system as you used to brisk is very much like the
applications menu as was but has fast search and some additional session
management capabilities in there so I I'm thinking brisk might become the
default if not in this release then the next release sitting alongside the
traditional three-tier menu I think I did I did I hear you mention I think I
think in the post you said alpha 2 is scheduled for release in like three days
so yeah it's very it's very soon yeah I forget exactly but it's it's this week
maybe maybe this week there's a couple of releases coming up and I can't
remember which way around there we've got the 1604.2 release coming up on
February the something or other and we've got the alpha 2 of 1704 coming up
as well so it's all releases at the moment yeah boy that's I'm sure that's
not not a not a stressful time at all that seems seems very low-key sounds all
very good all good fun you're a good sport wimpy you're a good sport all
right so before we get out of here I just wanted to give a mention to Kali
Linux who celebrates their 10th anniversary this year and they have
announced today a new Kali Linux certified professional course which will
debut at blackhat 2017 the KLCP is the first and only official certification
program that validates one's proficiency with Kali Linux which I think is
interesting perhaps if you're in penetration testing business I used Kali
when I did that and the Kali Linux also announced that there will be on June
5th a Kali Linux revealed mastering the penetration testing distribution the
first official book on the Kali Linux platform and keeping in Kali Linux
spirit they're also gonna make the online version free for download so you
can get it if you want for free that actually is gonna be also a big refresh
in the documentation area too so you combine that with the book documentation
and a certification it's kind of big movements for Kali that's that's kind
of a big deal I don't I oh and also I should say cute 5.8 was released
yesterday that's that's the news right there oh yeah okay all right we're
gonna call it there we got to go because we got to make room for the for the new
tax net program which if you ever want to tune in live is on Tuesdays now but
yeah I just thought that was really cool to mention mention for Kali I mumbled
room you guys thank you very much for making it it was great having you here I
think we got lots of good info on everyone everybody's working on the
planes are overhead now flying the banners to celebrate our excellent job I
think that means job well done when the when they launched the planes that means
that means we did a good job so we can get out of here we'll end on a high note
thank you for tuning in this week we miss us I'm sending love to West right
now he he misses you too so don't worry if you miss West he'll be back next week
if you'd like to join us live next week perhaps participate in our mumble room
anyone is welcome we just like to do a mic check go to jblive.tv sign into our
chat room bang mom will get the information when go to Jupiter
broadcasting comm slash calendar to get that converted to your local time zone
Oh feedback and stories Linux action show dot reddit.com I'm on Twitter at
Chris Elias the network at Jupiter signal thanks for being here we'll see
you right back here next Tuesday
all right that brings us to the end we have a couple of minutes to pick our
title so everybody in the chat room go to JB titles that is watching live guys
thanks so much there was tons of good info from everybody in there also thanks
to mr. Hall who had to move on because he had other he had another call to
jump on but he he had to jump to that was good stuff now I key I had a
question you said something in there about a new icon theme is this a fork of
mocha or what is that nope nope you got the author right oh really yeah so what
we've deliberately done and this is gonna sound like me being a complete
knob but we deliberately done it on a private get for now because it's
something that's gonna be important to the visual identity of solos now it
might sound like a minor thing but solos was the first one to ship with arc
thing you know we've worked with horse the the offer of arc and getting budgie
to look good and be integrated it's it was effectively the official solace
thing everywhere you look now I see that bastard thing oh yeah it's good luck so
so what we're doing is we're doing it behind closed doors third first I can't
speak today doing it behind closed doors first just because I don't want to say
turn up in the AUR tomorrow and already been warned by half the country before
we even get to release the solar cell but it will be coming in time and it's
gonna be nice and they'll help you know define the look of solos that little
bit more so you know I was just pinged during the show that there is a there is
an event that I've been wanting to go to for a few years it's happening in the
back in my backyard during scale man I really want to go to this plus there's
something else that's happening with some friends on that weekend and now I'm
considering I'm considering maybe seeing if I can get I think Noah would go
regardless but now I'm now I'm wondering if I really need to go I in the show I
said I was gonna go to scale and now by the end of the show I'm like Noah's
gonna be there I'm forcing him to go yeah I think yeah I think he'd be
regardless so we get coverage so yeah I don't know the question is is do I
because it's not that the thing it's a it's a hot air balloon event it's this
massive huge hot air balloon event in this in in a town that looks like it's
from 1805 it's a it's a it's like a western town like wooden sidewalks dirt
roads it's a really cool little place and they have an RV park that is within
walking distance and you take a wooden stairway down into the town and they're
gonna have this massive hot air balloon event and it would be so cool to go I've
always wanted to go and it's only like two hours of three two and a half hours
away from where I live
I like going to that town too so I don't know so do I but I live in the city if I
have a big one every summer and it gets a bit boring I bet towards the end I bet
I would only go for like one day but yeah I don't know I don't know what to
do now it's always so hard scale comes at the
worst time possible I actually don't like that they moved it up this year so
it's closer to LFNW itself yeah I wish I wish it was still be in January like it
was because it would have been happening you know this past weekend I wish it was
happening actually like later in the year even that would be fun like
November some well that might be a little too late interesting somewhere in
that range might be not bad though October like yeah August might be a
little August is bad because there's a lot of security conferences honestly like
yeah I'm going on I don't want to make it right to scale yeah although I
wonder if they could if they did if they if they nosed it up to something like
that if they could get some more attendance although they get plenty
attendance scale timber Wimpy do you mind if I ask what did you consider
going and why you decided not to go just because I'm considering if I should go
or not um well I was either going to go under my own steam or go with work and
there are people from work going I can't afford to go to scale and Linux fest
Northwest so and it's a bit a bit awkward timing for scale so yeah unless I
was going with work I decided I'm not gonna go individually that's the thing
with with Noah going I don't it's not like mandatory that I go I don't know I
gotta think about it some more I wish I hadn't said I was going in the show
because literally during the last half of the show I got those I got the
message there's also we have a we have a close friend who has a concert once a
year and we've missed the the concert because of scale and and so like six
months ago she's like well guess what they we moved that we moved the date of
the of the concert well guess what they what they moved it to the weekend of
scale March 3rd yeah great thanks guys what you could do Chris you see is you
could do this you could save your money not go to scale and you could come to
UbuCon Paris in November whoa whoa whoa whoa that would be an amazing goal