Okay, here's my question before you go on a trip
Do you have like a gadget regime that you follow like you gotta charge the laptop gotta charge the tablet gotta charge the phone
Gotta charge the watch now like there's this whole series of crap gotta sync over
My audiobooks and my podcast any files I want to watch like there's this process you have to go the prospect of being unplugged
From the internet for more than you know an accidental 10 minutes. It's just foreign now, right?
Well, like, you know, I like flew to Hawaii reasons like okay six hours. No internet. What do I do for this?
I can't read the blogs. I read I can't listen to podcasts unless I plan ahead. Yeah, I feel like an animal exactly
Yeah, now I know poppy. I know you just made the the trip though a road trip
Did you do any pre road trip gadget planning? Did you like go through and charge all the devices?
Did you sync up podcast? What what was your pre road trip in resume regime? I I did
Yeah, say Martin trumped any preparation I did because when I got into his car
There was a wireless access point in his
And there were like USB cables all over the place
There were sweets in every door pocket and drinks for every passenger
So it doesn't matter what I say. He's done ten times more than I did
Now now, okay wimpy, please now
Is this normally how your vehicle is set up?
Or did you know there's gonna be a bunch of nerds sitting in my vehicle. I better give them some connections
I made I made two changes to the usual regime. So there is always Wi-Fi in the car
So it is a mobile hotspot
But the change I did make is and there's always a thinkpad
Power adapter in the car as well
Of course, hope he did hope he did contact me beforehand and say is your power adapter compatible with my laptop?
Which it was it was kind of fun watching Popey SSH ing into things as we were bombing up and down the motor
One of those cars that when you get to a junction that the engine cuts and then starts itself when you put away no
Every time it did that because the power right?
So my laptop's going dude
Every time he pulls away like yes thinkpad. I'm charging. No, I'm not yes
I am noise. Yeah, that was fun
So yeah, the only changes I made is I added extra USB charging points
So the passengers in the back had I think three USB charging points and us in the front we had
Five and a laptop charger and that was different from usual and then luxury drinks the sweets and drinks
That was that was new but that's because we were doing a five-hour journey
And I knew that will get cranky if I didn't you know fill them up with chocolate. This is very true
This is very true the console of my vehicle from the road trip still has chocolate in there
Steak bites like it's an emergency go-to bag and you know one of the vehicle one of the reasons
I got the current vehicle was because it has a C plugs in it. Oh nice
Yeah, so actual power plugs is fair as well
Yeah, there was there was a point during the road trip where Noah and I were working on the power in the rover
So we have the power off in the rover
And I literally pulled the truck up next to the rover turned it on and plugged in his soldering iron to the truck
With the AC plug, so it's very valuable. Yeah, it's a mess though of cables
It just makes for a mess of cables when you're traveling around
Your US power sockets, they're not
Real not not man-sized
No, they're definitely not there no plug with plugs
You would definitely not want to stay no and then and do you now do you over there?
Do you have like did you have plugs that are called like cute things like pigtail and things like that?
Cuz we have pigtails over here when we need like 30 amps and things like that
And so we have really cute names for all of our plugs. Do you guys have those?
I think that's very much an American thing. We do we do have names. We do have names for the plug
Shapes, but not for the capacities. So we've got the cloverleaf connectors all plugs. Yeah, yeah
They don't carry a different capacity they're all 13 amp plugs, yeah, they're all man-sized
13 amps
I need 30, please. I need 30. I got I got stuff to plug in here
I got oh, well, you can you can get big ones the standard is 13 amps and 240 volts. Oh, okay
Oh, yeah. Yeah that 240 volts. That's no joke. That's legit. No, it's not that's legit
This is Linux unplugged episode 118 for November 10th 2015
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's hoping to avoid that hands-on TSA experience. My name is Chris. And my name is Wes. Don't touch me, Chris. Don't touch me. There are rules.
You know, the only reason I say that really is because I'm about to jump on a plane
I'm about to fly over and see system 76 in Denver. Oh boy, is that exciting? Colorado
I know we don't know exactly yet about like meetup details, but I'm hoping we have a meetup
But the thing is I have like weird things like I have like stabilizer poles in my bag. I have cameras
I have wires. So we should expect a lot out of this trip. That's what you're telling us. No, I'm telling you
I think I'm gonna get groped by the security. Yeah, that's what I'm telling you
All right. Well coming up on this week's episode of the Linux action show. Oh, but who's that?
42.1 is out. We're gonna talk about the new leap release and of course Wes and I have had a chance to use Ubuntu
Mate 15.10 in the real world. We'll give you our follow-ups on that. We're gonna wrap up on Fedora 23 this week
There's been some interesting things developing there and then later on in the show
We'll talk about new ransomware that targets Linux systems
It's kind of ridiculous, but there's already a fix out in the works. We got details on that and then
There's some drama in
In the Debian world again. I know it's not about systemd this time
Okay, and actually this one is maybe it matters more to end-users than even the systemd debate did
We'll talk about that coming up on this week's episode of Linux unplugged Wes
We have so much to cover. We have so much to get into
So why don't we immediately without any further delay bring in our virtual lug time appropriate greens mumble room
All right, well, I'm I am really pumped about episode 118 today because we have a ton of topics to cover a lot of
Distro things to discuss so let's kick off the distro things with one Richard Brown
Open Susa's or I believe Sousa's chairman. I forget it was a very it was a very very cool title the chairman of open Sousa
Mr. Richard Brown, which are tell us more our Brown welcome to the show
Thank you very much. Yeah, and it's it's chairman of open Sousa
But Sousa paid for me my salary, so okay, okay, so technically the Sousa company pays your paycheck
But you're the chairman of the open Sousa distribution, which honestly is way cooler than the CEO or any other
Definitely chairman is awesome. So I
Richard welcome to Linux unplugged and today is a pretty cool week because open Sousa 42.1
Leap shipped and it's like Linux, but not like we've seen it before
Are you guys totally pumped over there at open Sousa right now?
Yeah, and the the feedback's been amazing. I mean we were trying something really different here for people who don't know
you know, we've got the effectively the code base from Susan it's enterprise so the enterprise distribution and
We started with that but then rather than just copy and paste
We started with that but then rather than just copying it and you know shipping that as our own
We've built a whole new platform on top of it
and and this and this is something that we've almost have as Linux users have
fantasized about and it almost seems impossible and it is this idea that you take a core you take the core Linux OS and
You make it stable you make it you make it secure you make it predictable
But then as an end user you get you get all of the trappings of nice updated end-user applications and things like that
You can get the latest things that are important to you. Yeah, you know, you know the small things like that
Colonel or x-breaking. Yeah, you look things like Thunderbird Chrome your steam packages things like that and
now
that is one thing to say is actually gonna happen, but
How how what is the long-term plan to actually deliver on
That how did how does openSUSE elite plan to actually?
Make that happen
Well part of it's all thanks to the the tooling we already have so things like the build service
Which make it really easy for us to do this kind of heavy
tricky engineering
So that the trick going forward is we're gonna do leap minor releases aligned with the the SLE service pack
so as they move forward will move forward and
And for each of those minor releases, which are expected about once per year
I expect to see most of that user space stuff kind of jumping up catching up with what's
common standard there
With suzer taking care of the base system underneath as part of the enterprise stuff
Now Richard what happens when something comes along that says this is
This is the new standard. This is something we want to do and it requires
XYZ be updated. Is there a process in which a maintainer can step up and say I'm going to make sure that these
Libraries and this this end-user package are the latest version even though it doesn't quite track what what's less is doing
Exactly. I mean that that's happened a few times already with this version of leap. We actually did it with the kernel as well
So we had a real big bit of community feedback that you know
They wanted the 4.1 kernel in there something newer than what SLE has. So yeah, we've done that already. I
expected probably hit a few more things again with 42.2, but
Also, we're seeing on the enterprise side because we're doing this they're a little bit braver about some other stuff
They're talking about for service back to so that's awesome. We we know they might be moving a little bit faster
We might have a little bit less of that kind of thing to hit them
We were expecting when we started this a year ago. So I mean so far I've mostly talked about this in the context of the
desktop and why it seems compelling to me as a desktop distribution, but
is there also a bit of a
Server answer here. Could this be maybe somebody who wants to have some fairly modern up-to-date?
Front-end packages of things like maybe sync thing
Plex, MB, stuff like that, but also then also have something that doesn't have a ton of kernel changes and whatnot. Is there
Do you see a role for openSUSE leap in the server position or is that clearly still defined for SLES?
What's your thoughts there?
If definitely totally yes, I mean as part of this release
We actually tied it up all of the server patterns and installation options
We have in leap so that they're a lot more straightforward and easy to get done
And yeah, I mean there's there's a big server
Market out there that that doesn't really fit leap doesn't really fit sleep
So, you know that there's not really too much concern from the SUSE business side, you know
We're going a different direction. We're gonna appeal to a different audience. So it's yeah, we're looking forward to seeing how that works out
One of the things that I think I've noticed that Ubuntu has had to figure out with their LTS releases
and I think they've done it pretty gracefully is
the the updates to the kernel to do hardware enablements as they call them and
one of the things that I I hear
consistent
consistently Richard is
And it happens about right now and Wes knows I'm about to say is
Ubuntu 1404 is starting to feel real old and he and I know of a couple of examples of people who wanted to go
with the LTS release but bailed because it's just simply it's too out of date now and
I it seems like the LTS updates are and to Ubuntu and the slash service packs are on about the same schedule
So what what how can leap avoid this problem where some of the base system starts to become?
Honestly a little stale and so things like, you know steam games start to suffer or new hardware support or
Honestly, even things like installing the latest versions of Java and flash to play Minecraft and what and do hangouts become complicated
What's what's leap solution to that?
well
The sleet service pack thing is moving up to about an annual release schedule now and and
Hardware enablement is a big part of what suzer do in those service packs
So we'll be benefiting from that plus, you know
Probably doing some of our own as well for the specific hardware that our community is interested in
So yeah
We we did with that that that should kind of be the bread and butter that every year when we do a minor release of leap
Hardware enablement should be there every time keeping this whole thing fresh
And would that be when I get say a new version of GTK or would that come at a different point in update in the update?
cycle
We're really expecting kind of the big things like a new num release in UK
Do you release to be sort of synchronized all around those annual service packs?
We're going to be doing so releases as we're saying so essentially I get one new version of GTK a year
One new version of QT a year and those kinds of things
Yeah, the open suzer packaging policy isn't necessarily that strict
So if there's like a nice compelling reason for us to push that out to the maintenance update during the life cycle of 42.1
We can we might but there has to be a reason because the last thing we want to do is break things now
how do you know down the road in all intents and purposes is there going to be a
A 42.2 and a 42.3 or is this essentially a continuously updating?
Installation that I'm going to have that will never
It's always just going to like 42.1 is always going to be the latest and whatever you install is just going to continually be updated
How does this work? And what is my upgrade path long term? I?
Don't know if you want a nice rolling release. That's what we have tumbleweed for. So that's your single installation that you can upgrade
So if 42.1 will have 42.2 next year
the upgrade path will be as simple as a zippered up so our equivalent of a
apt distribution upgrade and
So, you know, we're expecting that to be nice and simple
You can also do it offline if you feel like doing it the old-fashioned way over USB stick or a DVD
That's good
Yeah, and so yeah, we're expecting these to do one of these service packs every year
Then when Slee do sleep 13 a few years from now, that's when we're expecting 43.0
Which will be sort of a big
huge
Change everything
Probably based on wherever tumbleweed is around about that time. Okay
So that'll be in line with what the sues are doing with the the big enterprise really send as well
This sounds like it's the way you describe it. It's kind of a unique little space in the Linux
Yeah, it does seem different and I and I look at this and I ask so I guess Richard my next question would be if
I'm if I'm Frank
from own cloud or if I'm somebody who's making say a telegram server replacement or
You know, maybe plaques or whatever if I'm creating software for the Linux server or the Linux desktop
How do I as a software vendor say we are compatible with XYZ version of open?
Sousa leap, how can I how can I clearly?
Differentiate for the end user so that way they know it's gonna work on leap or not
What's what is so because of the reason I ask you is because it seems like one two years down the road there could be
Some installations of leap or something does work and some installations with leap or things don't work
So what's kind of the thoughts there to make it clear to end users if you know
Something's gonna work on your version of open Sousa say nine months from now
The cleanest simplest way would be I'd recommend that all of these vendors like we're already in discussion
for example with own cloud about doing this of
of either put your stuff in our distribution or use the build service where
Building it for all for whatever variation someone might have is just a button click away
Nice because we're not expecting any major heavy architectural stuff
So if you want to be extra sure that the thing is built for you know
Every variation of leap that should just be nice and simply done in the OBS
Wouldn't that be wouldn't that be great if we could get just everybody using that that seems that would be really something
So if you don't mind Richard, I would love to shift gears and for just a second and talk about
Well for a few seconds and talk about tumbleweed. So what is
If I'm looking at really today, you know and and really and let's talk about 2016, too
I'm looking at my options as an open Sousa user and I'm looking at tumbleweed it seems like and I'm looking at leap
I got two different things in front of me. I
Feel like maybe because I'm an arch user today if I was gonna make a switch to Sousa
Maybe I want to go tumbleweed and I actually kind of want to ask you straight up
What why would I not go tumbleweed?
And why would I go leap? Like what's the downside to going tumbleweed if there's two different versions of Sousa?
What is what is leap giving me that say tumbleweed isn't?
It leaps giving you a slower pace of change. It's really down to like what Linux is comfortable for you
You know, the thing we find is tumbleweed is you know, we've tackled those technical problems. It's stable. It works
You can rely on it
But it's changing at whatever the pace upstreams are and we have feedback from my users saying like ah
I didn't want to relearn my entire workflow this week
So, you know tumbleweed if you're if you're one of these guys who likes whatever upstreams are doing
Tumbleweed is fine great use it
But at the same time in certain use cases or just depending on how you are you want something that changes less often
That's what leaps going for
That's a kind of you know, the two complementary approaches really? Yeah
So if and and and also maybe if I was a if I was the administrator of a couple of Sousa Enterprise Linux servers
Or even more than a couple. Yeah leap would probably be a pretty good desktop for me
Seems like yes
Yeah, I mean I'm actually running tumbleweed and leap on my servers and kind of comparing at the moment and yeah, so um
I think was like three weeks ago
We did a review of open Sousa leap 42.1 release candidate in the Linux action show
And now I want to put a call out to the Linux unplugged audience and their virtual lug
If you would like to talk more about open Sousa leap
Let us know in the comments at linuxactionshow.reddit.com for episode 118 of Linux unplugged show
Would you like to have a dedicated segment where we discuss leap?
I would I would like to see how you guys are actually experiencing using it
Setting things up like telegram and her upad and steam and chrome and how is all of this going?
You know the everyday livability elements. Yes, and and what is what exactly what has been your experience?
So we've got a we've got a bond. We got a couple volunteers from the mumble room today West
You're gonna give it a go thing and let's next week Richard
Would you mind joining us again next week at this time and we'll kind of do a roundtable discussion of actually using leap for the last
couple weeks
Sounds awesome
Whoa, whoa, whoa. Whoa. Yeah outside of this. Yeah. All right, so I would love to hear it and kids and kitty
You had something you want to chime in with?
Yeah, I was actually gonna ask the question about the inclusion of gnome
316 in leap versus 318
Why go with 316 if 318 is going to be supported for a longer time?
318 came at a weird time during our development process. So we were like, okay, we could accept it
But there's an element of risk of you know, maybe we're not gonna get all the patches in in time, you know
318 2 isn't quite out yet
So so we wanted to make sure that you know what we shipped as leap
We're happy maintaining for a year
Is there a possibility that?
318 might come as a service pack update. I
Can I can be pretty sure that I expect 320 next year? Oh
Okay. Yeah
So 316 is what ships today, which you know as far as that goes that's also what 1510 is shipping with right?
So not not horrible like as far as wider adoption
But it does feel like a year is a long time to wait
But then again, I guess if you're gonna wait 320 is the one to wait for and at least it's kind of a consistent
You know, all right, once a year you get the new upgrades. I can wrap my head around that I can plan around that
Yeah, I I like that a lot actually
So and then last but not least Richard, I know that there was a big event that just wrapped up for Sousa
Do you want to mention anything about that? Oh, yes
Yeah, the big company party in Amsterdam. Sorry conference
Look like a party
It's Amsterdam. I mean what what kind of conference has beer served during the last keynote?
I mean that was just awesome. If you watch the YouTube videos, they had beer as a service and and they had yeah
That's amazing. You know just an aside really quick. Yeah, I got to say the open Sousa booth
When we had Linux con here in Seattle was given out free not only given out free beers, but beer koozies open Sousa beer koozies
Respect. So how did Sousa conga or how was the event overall?
The biggest we've seen by far way more customers than we used to having lots more partners lots of really interesting
It's mainly an enterprise conference. I mean the fact that open Sousa was there and we were launching leap was a little bit
weirder than usual
so
Yeah, it was it was not but it was really nice actually seeing that that collaboration between the two and like having a whole
Bunch of people come up to me and say like hey, we're we're running people ready. We're running tumbleweed
We want to know what you're doing with open QA. So it's like it's
You quite often see in other communities like there's a big
Bridge but a big divide between the enterprise guys and the community guys and and it was really nice to see that kind of just
completely disappearing last week
and of course
major props to you guys
Again, you've done another music video this year and it has been massively successful online
This is kind of ridiculous. But should I play a little bit of it? Should we as we wrap up?
Should I play a little bit of this? Let's see it. Alright, so we'll play a little bit of this
This is uptime funk, which interview sis admins are gonna love
My manager's mad it ain't pretty I need caffeine a big screen gotta fix the server and it's it's too hot
Cartouro boys and core hard man, it's too hot
Make a sis admin retire man. It's too hot
Holy cow, am I in the gym? It's too hot
Hot patch tell me get now it ain't funny service bad live patching. Hallelujah live patching. Hallelujah. Ooh, that's not a
Louie, yeah
Uptime funk. I'll give it to you cuz uptime funk. I'll give it to you cuz uptime funk. I'll give it to you
Don't reboot it just patch
Yeah, that was a huge hit so you guys can check that out online
So it sounds like it was a good event and good on you guys too for doing
For spending the time and the effort on that music video. That was really funny. Yeah. Yeah, and the money too
Yeah, that was a lot of fun. So alright. Well, I Richard we look forward to talking to you next week
be sure to join us and
Linux action show to reddit.com if you want to give us your thoughts on leap and then
Really if you want to double down on that and you're serious if you want to advocate this Gabriel 3
I'm talking to you if you really want to talk about this
Come join our mumble room. We have a virtual log. It's open to you. You can participate think of it like this
Back in the day before the internet was a thing if you are a Linux user and you wanted to advocate one distro to another
You would go to what these things were called Linux user groups. You had to go outside. It was horrible. Yeah
You had to go to like this place. There was probably like a school or something library. Who knows?
Yeah, yes, and then you had to go in there and you had to convince other people
well, that's what our mumble room is if you go to jblive.tv you do bang mumble and you'll be able to get our address and
Yeah, this there is an outside kids and kitty. There is an outside and I'd love you have a come in here tomorrow
Or I'm sorry tomorrow. Yeah, come in here tomorrow. No, that's next week. Come here next week and tell us about your thoughts on
OpenSUSE elite. I'd love to really hear how it's going for you
All right
So before we go any further and we have so much show to get into I want to talk about digital
ocean digital ocean is a simple cloud host provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you to spin up your
Own Linux reg or freeBSD and here's the thing. I
Need you to use the promo code do unplugged. I need it. I need it. Like I need a chicken pot pie
Have you ever had the KFC chicken pot pies? Oh, no, I have not. Are you serious?
I haven't I know what I'm doing after the show
Well, so when you leave the studio here, there is a KFC on the corner there
Here's what I want you to do. What's the setup now?
Here's what they do is they put an amazing pie crust on the top and then it's a tin bottom, right?
And so it's not too much carbs and it's tons of good chicken, but you get that right? Yes
You can still get a little crisp in there and a lot of good protein and there's some good veggies in there, too
And what I just described also applies to digital ocean. It's exactly the same. It is the same thing
It's a high protein content use the promo code do unplugged do
Unplugged one word lowercase because everything's lowercase like a boost and you'll get a $10 credit over a digital ocean calm
You can start in less than 55 seconds because their system is cray and pricing plans start only five dollars a month
five dollars a month
which is a 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte a
freaking terabyte of
Transfer and digital has data some locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore Amsterdam, London, Germany and a brand new one
Because f the NSA in Toronto, I mean they didn't say that I am saying that they're not saying that it's not digital ocean thing
f the NSA and
They yeah, you know what? You know what? That's right
F the NSA and the value of this is negative so they got new data centers in Toronto
You go over there use the promo code do unplugged one word lowercase you get a $10 credit
You can try it all over their rigs. They run Linux. They're on top of KVM
They have SSD drives everywhere everywhere. It's nice
They got 40 gigabit e connections and their newest data centers is so sweet and their interface is like
The bestest of all of the interfaces. It is really good when I started in
Virtualization West. Okay. Now you probably use VMware or something right in the past. I have yes
Have you ever used VMware server where it was in the web page? No, I have not
Oh god, this is such a travesty of humanity. It is the worst. Okay. All right, it is now boxes, man
I'm tight with boxes
Yeah, I can get down with that if you want to do some local emulation like an animal man boxes is awesome
But when you want something up in the cloud, I mean, yeah, honestly
Honestly digital oceans UI is better than boxes. Oh, yeah hashtag just saying
It's one of the best you eyes. I don't know. Yeah, every should I say it ever?
I think you should because I'll tell you why you get HTML 5 console, right?
You get all this stuff. You can you can choose between your data centers. You can transfer you get the snapshots
You get the one-click deployments. You can use Docker like a pro even though you don't know what I'm talking about
You don't have to know you don't cuz there's tutorials for that man
They have some tutorials use the promo code do unplug check out the interface check out that API
Which makes a bunch of open source apps possible and by the way speaking of their community because I didn't speak of their community
But I am now it is tight. They have some really good tutorials, you know, because they're willing to pay for them
It turns out that if something's valuable you should pay for it
I know right anyways talk to Linus. So anyways, they pay for the tutorials, right?
And this is really something they've hired multiple editors and you know a
Little background you ready for this? I don't know a little exclusive info just between you and me
Don't tell the audience help anyone. I don't think do wants us getting out
So this was the first podcast they started talking about their tutorials online and how you could write and make some money
Yep, this was the right here, right here and they got such a like crazy response
That they ended up having to hire two extra people after running the spot on the show
That's awesome. Isn't that cool? Because they have work guys
Yeah
I know the JB community
Freaking rocks and they're writing really good tutorials like this one right here how to run nginx on the docker container
Using a boon to 1404 right there use the promo code deal unplugged you support the show you get a $10 credit boom
It's magic digital ocean comm big. Thanks digital ocean for sponsoring Linux unplugged. It's awesome
All right, Wes, so you and I had a chance to try out a boon to matei 1510
Now you ran it for yourself. Yes, I did. Okay, I installed it for my girlfriend Hadia
Oh for her first Linux computer and I got her a new machine cuz her computer
She had an HP and it totally this is actually kind of a funny story
I should probably just a real
Detail Chris her her HP had like these metal metal trimmings on it. And whenever you touched the metal the computer would shut off. Oh my god
So I was like
And she uses this computer to run her business, right?
And so like I mean I'm talking like booking because she runs her own practice
Booking, you know all the accounting stuff messaging and of course any kind of like notes and anything like that
She have to take on her patients goes into this computer and this computer when you touch the metal turns off
I'm like go to Best Buy go get the yoga 3 because you had to get a computer that day, right and
You know have a business
Exactly. So day one I get the computer. We don't even put into Windows
I install integrals and I'm like boom. Look at this. This is the gnome 3 desktop. It's awesome. It's wonderful
Except for the Broadcom wireless didn't work. Oh, and I could have got it working because we got it working for Angie's machine
I mean, I could have done it but I
I let it sit for a while and I went on the road trip and all this kind of stuff and then I got
back and I realized
There were 384 updates like I just this wasn't something I wanted to manage
Yep, and so and you didn't want to be at fault. It was literally
Yes, yeah, and it was literally like
Two days after we talked about the episode where it was like that what's new mate
You know that where wimpy basically just sold the shit out of me on on using the food to protect good job wimpy
And so I was like, all right. Yeah. Yeah. All right. I'm installing this right now
This is gonna solve my problems and I deployed Ubuntu mate on her you deployed it. Yeah, I did. Well, that's how I talk
Yeah, cuz cuz I'm enterprise. Yeah
So I deployed Ubuntu mate following my standard deployment procedure that I thought which is a which is the installation
But with all of the stuff on the bottom of the screen
So I got the menu on the bottom of the screen. I got all the apps on the bottom of the screen
I forget which config that was called in the leap. That's Redmond. Yes. I think it was Redmond. Yeah, it's very good
I chose the Redmond config and mate tweak. Thank you wimpy for including that and then I went to town welcome
And it really you know that really got me started fast and I'd like to the advanced menu is there too
So I could use that if I wanted but I opted not to
Here's the thing Wes
There was three apps out of the gate. I had to install
Spotify, okay
Telegram yep
Scrivner cuz it's it's
Namo ramo or whatever. It's called. What's that called? I don't know. What's that in that nine more ammo? What's that?
Come on guys. What's that right? It's this the writing month right now and Scrivner is the big. Oh, I see what you're saying
Yeah, Scrivner is the big app everybody got it. So I I
In each single freaking app. I had to go bend over backwards to get it working really so for Telegram
I don't it was a bit of a process, but it wasn't that bad
Spotify though was the real SOB
Spotify I if I recall I had to go get an encryption library from a Debian repo pull it down and install and I wouldn't I
What I do wrong
Yes, which which version of Ubuntu Marte did you 1510?
I went through the welcome screen and I installed minecraft using the welcome screen and then and then yeah
But then telegram didn't you didn't fancy installing telegram or Spotify through the welcome screen. Was that in there? Yeah
Yes, they are. That would have saved me some time
and and
Navigates all of those hurdles you're about to describe. Oh
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Are you serious? How did I not see that?
There's a lot of options in the welcome screen. So yeah in a good way
Now that the other one you mentioned Scrivner, I've not heard of so that's new Scrivner is like it's like a it's like a book
writing screen writing program and
It's for people who want to write they have a beta out for Linux. There's I don't think there's a repo or anything like that
I think there's just some deb files you can download or a tar. GZ, right?
And so that that did also require some libraries, but you know apt cache search and all that and I got it pretty quick
but
For me that was that all that all took, you know, what 30 minutes? Yes top
So it wasn't that big of a deal. You've done it before. Yeah, not a big deal
I
What has been what has what what has been to beach what has turned out to be challenging?
Has been the small things that you wouldn't really think of really and today today while I'm driving
That's why this one jumps out at me was
So I got Chrome installed and then when Chrome launches
About about eight seconds after Chrome launches the you know
The the prompt that comes up that says enter your key ring password enter the master key ring password a default application
Requires access to the key ring and enter your master password and then in the title bar says key ring or something like that
Okay, like I I in fact, hold on West standby one
Let's pull this up because this act of this this matters here. So we go here. I got the screenshot this morning
Boom, it says enter password for key ring
The key ring default key ring quote to unlock an application wants to access the key ring default key ring, but it's locked enter
Password and the title bar says unlock key ring. Yep. I got it now
I got this on telegram because the question was is the hell is this and is this okay?
and is this why I can't save my files in Scrivner and
It is just these weird
wordings of applications like that enter password for key ring default key ring to unlock doesn't make any sense
And so any user who's actually painted the screen that you're describing. What's that?
Well, you know and recognize the screen you're describing what it is in the application that uses the gnome key ring or the gt
Whatever the so it's chrome chrome has saved usernames and passwords and it stores them in the key ring
And so when you launch chrome the key ring prompt comes up now
That to me is normal because I know I'm unlocking the key ring where the passwords are stored, but to Hadeah
This was like I went to a website and I and all of a sudden now it's asking me enter a password
This feels like fishing now props to her for being cognizant enough to be like this feels like fishing. What's happening Chris?
Why is it doing this right? I'm like, okay. Thank you for asking me that at the same time
Just enter your frickin password for God's sakes. All right, type it in hit enter. It's fine
So I'm doing a show right now
Yeah, so it is like it is slightly there were there's been a few bumps along the road where there's stuff
I didn't expect like another one was
The screen dimming like describing the process of going into the settings and changing screen
Do you mean was much more complicated than I thought at first? I need to change that study myself
I haven't tried it yet. So what have you been your thoughts? Well, I've been using it in a very different use case
I'm I've been playing with a NUC that I've got one of the new Broadwell ones
Or Braswell, excuse me. And so right well, well, no, it's probably well. Well, Braswell is the new one
It's like the oh Adam Pentium. Oh, but it has a h.265 h.264. It's got a pretty nice graphics
It's not a that of a BP CPU, but the NUC was just dirt cheap
So I'm picking it up to give to my parents as a way to oh cool
It's like a VPN node to connect to my network. They can see some of the media files
I have we can do you know backups with you know, that sort of thing
Yeah, so before I had been configuring it with arch just because that's kind of my default
But this gave me a great opportunity to install, you know, I'm going to 1510 Monta, you know
I should say like arch was my default too, and I actually
Removed arch to put this on
Wiped out the whole hard drive. Yeah, so I've been really impressed
My main use case here is as a VPN node and as a as a Kodi front-end basically and Kodi through MB
Mmm to connect to my media share
So you're using the MB database and you're using Kodi to display the metadata on top of Monta
but but I didn't you know
I didn't want to use open a lack or any of those kind of alternatives because I want it I wanted to be
Easy to you know kind of augment I was gonna use it to kind of do check-ins, you know
If I need to fix anything on that network, etc, etc
So I've been really impressed. It was super fast to install once it once it was installed
I mean at first I was like, oh, what's the is it gonna show me the boot animation? Oh, wait. No, it's already booted
Never mind. Yeah, it's asking me for my password to login. So I've had a really good positive experiences
It also it kind of rekindled, you know back before
Ubuntu switch to unity that was my main operating system
and you know, there's like that love there's this fondness and using mate 1510 it brought back all that like
I'm familiar with a bunch of I've used on servers. I know my way around it, but it feels modern. It's super snappy
I I tried out the Cupertino. Yeah arrangement. Yeah, and it has it has the you know plank panel right on the bottom
Which is really easy. Everybody loves plank. Yeah, I think I'm gonna use it like that because it's really clear
You know, it's like someone who's not familiar wants to like how do I start Firefox?
Oh, there's the icon right there at the bottom of the screen
So it's been rocks rocks all yeah, and I know that it's like I'm happy to have another arch box that I just you know
Administer because it's not that big of a problem. But this might be a perfect solution of it has relatively recent packages
I won't have a problem if I want to update to 1604 later and
It'll be rock-solid and I know I'll always have it sitting right there. So I think it'll keep on there
Yeah, the thing I like about it too is like it's it's pretty performant. So I feel like hey
I'm giving you a nice fast computer. I feel like the battery life is pretty great and
I like that. It seems like a pretty obvious upgrade path to 1604. I was also super impressed with the welcome screen
I mean just all the number of apps that you can install
A lot of the default apps that are installed as well
Like I love that you have that easy option for deja-dupe backups that impressed me a lot just like oh, yeah
I just stick this up to I can you know, I could set up for my parents. I could set up a I
Actually, I actually think you could remove every single
application and package from that welcome screen and
just have Minecraft and if it if it if it became known that you could install Ubuntu Mate and then one-click install Minecraft
It could become like a Minecraft appliance. I mean, I don't know
So if you have you know anybody out there who's listening who has kids, you know for it for or above
You know what a big deal minecraft is
It's literally their life and the fact that I could deploy at Ubuntu Mate machine with one-click installation of Minecraft
Is a huge huge deal and if you could tell you know, my son Dylan that this would become
I mean this would be his obvious choice
It is it just making that accessible even though it is as simple as installing Jerry and getting the Minecraft jar
Like making it one button installation is a transfer more. It is how can I put this?
It is it's like closing that 10% gap that makes all of the difference
It's the uncanny valley that makes Minecraft and easy gaming
Completely accessible and if you're looking at somebody who has an older machine
They don't need Windows 10 and you can say Ubuntu Mate low resources one-click installation of Minecraft mind blown. Yep
So Wimby now that we're a few weeks into it. What's been some of the what's been some of the feedback?
What's been some of the consistent response?
Um, yeah, it's been positive. I've not heard anything, you know negative or worrying about it
So I'm pleased in that regard. I think the one thing I need to do is try and position because you've you've borne this out
I need to position that software feature from welcome a bit more clearly
Mmm, because people are used to these
Welcome screens being a bit anemic. Yeah, I'm probably don't realize this one actually does stuff for you
So yeah, you should have poked around in there a little bit because you could have installed Chrome and Chromium and
Telegram and Spotify not even telegram to oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah
I thought that was great. She's maybe maybe calling it welcome screen is what's making people think it's gonna be anemic
Because welcome screen in Windows NT was a thing you just press close to. Yes, exactly. You check the box you never see it again
right, so what I'm working on is some of the
applications in Ubuntu
Have multiple icons and when you launch the different icons
They actually launch the same app but open it at a particular tab or section of the application
I've noticed that. So I'm thinking of making one just called software which basically just opens welcome at that software page
Hmm and drop that in there to sort of you know, kick-start that process, but then again with
The recent announcements about Ubuntu 16.04 and GNOME software. I'm very interested in you know
Including that in Ubuntu Marte providing there's no
Compatibility issues. So I've got all sorts of options and things to consider. No kidding. For the next cycle. Yeah
Yeah, I suppose the you know, the standout feature the thing that's really
Being popular is the Raspberry Pi 2 version for Ubuntu Marte. That has really so that's really good
That's seen some traction
Yeah, yeah, well and it has done for the 15.04. It's the most popular platform by far
So yeah and that in the 15.10 version
That makes 100% sense
With Minecraft, so you have you you have an inherent advantage of the Mate desktop being known for being low resources
So it makes it obvious for some of those use cases
Yeah, but and then you have the whole advantage of being on Ubuntu
So you have the home advantage of being known for being a low resources desktop on the Ubuntu on the Ubuntu platform, man
You know could no doubt that's popular in the Raspberry Pi
Yeah, but you know in making
Ubuntu Marte for the Raspberry Pi 2 it then became obvious that I was only two lines away from actually making any
Ubuntu version for the Raspberry Pi so I have ported every Ubuntu version to the Raspberry Pi 2 now
And I kicked off a little project a couple of weeks ago called the Ubuntu Pi flavor maker
And I presented that at OggCamp and at UOS. Brilliant. So all the Ubuntu's are now available for the Pi 2
and the one that I'm enjoying the most is the
Ubuntu minimal server image because you've got a proper Ubuntu server or traditional Ubuntu server
On the Raspberry Pi that you can now turn into anything you want
But it's got all the hardware unlocked for the you know, the video call. Talk about the perfect sync thing appliance or something like that
Yeah, I think the Raspberry Pi 2 with a with a sort of a minimal
Base OS. Yeah, like the Ubuntu minimal image. It makes that a really, you know flexible device
I mean, it's a flexible device anyway, but having a a trim a trim. Yes. Yeah
Kits and Kitty you wanted to ask would be a question about
Customizations and then maybe other distros kind of taking that and running with it. Go ahead
Yeah, one thing I've noticed there with mate is with well mate Ubuntu is it is a model mate distribution
And it provides a lot of stuff that I don't see open Susie. I don't see fedora
Implementing in their versions of mate in the future
Do you think that's going to change and we're gonna see distributions adopt more of your tools around that or do you think that other?
Distributions just don't care about and are you okay with that?
Yeah, I'm completely fine with that. I mean the thing that the tools in Ubuntu Marte that make it Ubuntu Marte are
not
wholly original
You know
Bits of software right two of the utilities. I forked from software from within Linux Mint
Ubuntu Marte welcome was forked from
And man now it was forked from and Turgos welcome, which was forked from Manjaro world
I really just walked from Karora. I love them. So this is now a fourth generation fork
So, you know those those utilities
You know if anyone wants to fork it and turn it into
Zubuntu welcome or the bun to welcome or whatever then, you know, go for it
I mean the end the day it's more Linux users, right?
Yeah, yeah, that's fine. That's the whole point of open source
Yeah, I wouldn't have been able to make these tools as quickly had there not been existing code out there under an appropriate license
For me to work from last but not least wimpy
Nobody likes to talk about this I have a feeling
This is probably something I shouldn't even say
But I mean, is there a is there a point say it's 2020
Is there a point where you could make a full-time living doing this because it seems like something that's being pretty well received by
The community and it feels like once it's that well-received. There's obviously value to it. There's obviously something there that people need
I mean, I know you have a great job. I know you love it. But is there yes, that's curious because I'm unemployed at the moment
Trying to make you sound like a hero
So, I mean
So actually that underscores my question even more than I mean because this is obviously a critical distribution
A lot of people find very valuable a lot of good utilities here something innovative and different on the market just like leap is
You know that we today we're talking about two very different distributions that are bringing something unique to the market. Do you do you?
Wish there was a way to make this a full-time gig. Do you want something like that to develop? What are your thoughts there?
Certainly if there was the opportunity for me to work on a plinthu Marte on a full-time basis
That would be terrific. That would be a lot of fun
And to be honest with you as generous as the community of being with their donations in order to sort of pay for the bandwidth
Which is mostly consumed by serving up the Raspberry Pi 2 downloads
I don't know that there are enough users out there to you know
Sustain, you know a team of people working on it on a full-time basis
and
You know, it's a it's a desktop Linux operating system. So
It's a niche of a niche. So, you know, you've already got a small audience of people
so and there's there's room enough in the Linux community for you know distributions like a bun to Marte and Zubin to an
Ubuntu to have
significant user bases
But I don't know that they can they can support
I mean linux mint have been hugely successful with what they've done what they've been able to generate in their community where they've that their
Community is funding the full-time development of mint
and
this has always been a bit of fun for me and it's been a learning experience as well in some respects and
Maybe it's better if it continues to be that
hmm, but sure, you know if there's somebody out there who wants to deploy this to you know, a
thousand people or something and they
Want to offer me a job to look after it and make bespoke changes then it'd be perfect come and find me
Yeah, well, you know what honestly a wimpy I would not be surprised if you keep it up if it doesn't eventually happen
But anyways in the meantime patreon.com slash Ubuntu underscore mate
That would be a good place for people to go wouldn't it?
That'd be lovely. Yes, the bandwidth bandwidth bills are getting quite scary now
I'm a backer and if you are if you are a if you're a tech talk today patreon patreon.com slash today
You support the Jupiter broadcasting network
Then really pretty much everything you need is all set up on patreon and you just go click the button and make sure that even
If you're not a user of this distro
Something very approachable in the traditional desktop paradigm is available to everybody 88 patrons. That doesn't seem like enough to me
Yeah, come on guys. Yeah, if you can't pay his bandwidth bills
then how is he gonna show up here if you could back in all of us if you can even if you can't back JB go give
Them two bucks a month and if you can if you can afford to back two projects
Then I'd say patreon.com slash today and then patreon.com slash Ubuntu underscore mate
But if you can't afford to back us go black go back them 88 patrons
I feel like that's not enough for something that literally is making Linux
Accessible to an entirely new generation of people who do not want the Windows 8 slash Windows 10 paradigm
I think that's a pretty cool effort and and not that there's not other distros out there
But I think we've all I think you know watching this from the incarnation up to now
I think it's pretty obvious is a good one to support. Yep
It has that spirit you mentioned the one-click installer for
Minecraft which I got the tip from kids actually using it and saying yeah. Well if it doesn't do minecraft, it's irrelevant
So I sorted that one and then the other thing I learned from my in-laws
Is well, if hasn't got solitaire, it's irrelevant. So you'll find directly after minecraft is yes. I did actually
Solitaire when I get home, which is free free to install on Ubuntu Marte, but I believe is a paid up on Windows 10 now
That's worth the patreon backing right there
All right, so very nice and wimpy
I'll I'll continue to give you my bits and tids and pits and pieces here and and and Wes
Continue to use it yourself
Let you know wimpy
But I actually so far and feedback is greatly received because it'll only get better if people tell me what's not working
right, I can already tell you I
I
Love I love them. I love the integration of compass and mate tweak because that just got me like oh, yeah
Matt mate tweak is very helpful. I got me like 70% of the way there right then and there it was really sweet
It really was sweet. I liked a lot and you know what super fast boot Oh super fast just the whole thing
I mean, it seems like the go-to testro for yeah visual appliance. Yeah
I was very very very impressed and I hope I hope it continues to be impressive
You know what else is impressive my mobile service provider. It could be yours to ting go to linux.ting.com
Now here's why I want you to go there. It supports the show keeps us on the air and you get to put Linux in your
browser bar
Really walk away right there Linux
You mean do you have how many URLs have Linux in your in your recent history? Not enough linux.ting.com
You also I mean this kind of is nice too. You get a $25 discount on your first ting device or if you got a ting
Compatible device and you probably you probably do you probably do. Yeah, you probably do you get $25 on service
Which is paid for more than my first month. Here's why I say you're probably doing this is really kind of a nice thing
Ting has a CDMA and GSM Network
So you get to be a baller you get to pick because you know what the difference between GSM and CDMA and CDMA is so
Check box there. You actually know what GSM is and you know, it's CDMA is not good CDMA. Good job
I don't know what it is. I don't know. I can't even say it
I can't even say because I just like to blur it. Apparently ting is so helpful. You don't you don't need to know
Yeah, I suppose you don't I mean what I like what I like about ting is
It's obvious because it's no contract it's pay for what you use. It's six dollars for the line
All right, so that's the baseline but we're like why I really like it is
if you just like
If you just like a little bit smarter than the average bear like you don't even have to be like super smart
But like if you've heard of the word Linux before or you know
What a bios is you probably can figure out ting and like everybody else who can't not judging because you know what?
I love them. They're basically my entire family deals
Yeah, we have we we have the advantage to game the system and we can game the system nicely with ting
Go to linux.ting.com use your Wi-Fi pay for what you use. No contract. No early termination fee
It freaking rocks. They got every single device from like a bare-bones GSM
You can just go get the GSM or CDMA sim and put them in your thing. You got a thing
You can put in a thing. That's fine. Just pay six dollars a month for the thing
Or get like, you know a feature phone because you know
You need to make calls and just need a speaker and a microphone
it's funny how these feature phones have really good speakers and microphones to and like
Ridiculous seven-day battery life. How is that not a thing anymore?
How did we let that go you could you charge your phone every night every night every night Wes without fail?
And don't forget you got to charge the watch. Yeah
Yeah, because of course the watch uses the power on the phone because you got Bluetooth turned on all the time now, right?
Okay, so you can go get yeah, you can go get your iPhone 6s or your you know your s6
Yeah, I got both those you can go get your Nexus's. They got the Nexus I
directly from ting
It's really cool. Go to linux.ting.com. Go check them out. Actually what kicks ass about ting is their
customer service and their dashboard
They treat these things as like features for their platform. So they're respectable
Go check them out linux.ting.com and they'll get a device now. They don't have these very often the Novotel mi-fi
Very frequently goes out of sale. This is a small
crazy long life battery life mi-fi device pay for what you use six dollars a month data in your pocket when you don't use it you
Turn it off because they have a crazy cool dashboard
Linux docking comm you go get this you get $25 of service credit
For all I would guess if you get $25 of service credit
I would bet you can use this mi-fi app because you buy it no contract, right?
You buy this Novotel mi-fi 5580. They don't have it on sale very often
So that's a great price to literally they like I only talk about this when they have it on sale
I haven't talked about this for six months you get this thing
$6 a month when you're using it. You can literally turn it off read their control panel when you don't need it
Okay, and then last but not least what I love about it
$6 so if you just want to accidentally leave it on right whoops
So you have it in your bag or whatever like it's $6
They're like that's less than that frickin burger you got from the fast-food restaurant in your couch. You'll find it in chain
I know like and then when you need data on the go. It's ready for you
I freaking love it and a hundred bucks no contract
No early termination fee pay for what you use and if you go to linux.com you get the $25 credit
You'll probably get about three months
That's crazy, right
Three months of data hundred bucks out of your pocket and you've got data on the go that if you do if you do any kind
Of remote administration, or you need to be available all the time
Man for an insurance policy six dollars a month is nothing you don't have to you don't worry about tethering your phone
Or any of that you just turn it on and you're ready to go you'd be like Noah to Noah got one of these recently and
He just has it in his Jeep. Oh, that's that's and they just yeah, it's his Jeep. This is Jeep connection
They got all the great phones. They got the motos they got that they got the Apple phones
Now the netgear zing is what I have in the rover and the nice thing about the zing is you got the touch interface
So you can be pretty much do all the config right there on the device
That's what I have in the rover. They got all the good stuff and and I think probably right now the best value. I
Mean besides the Nexus devices, which would be my first choice, right would be the LG G flex, too
It's got that nice curve to it. Nice version of Android
$237 no contract you own it
Linux.com and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring Linux unplugged
Man, I just want to go get phones. What's up? Hey, I wanted to do like some quick follow-up on fedora
I don't know how many people in the mumble room were using it
But a couple of things for fedora before we move on some of the spins are out the cinnamon desktop spin
That's right that one. Yeah. Yeah thoughts
It's not quite as nicely integrated as let's say mint, right? Hmm, but it was familiar
And it has all the fedora pluses, you know modern kernels lots of new packages all those wonderful fedora tweaks
Yeah, but not quite as nice as the gnome version. Well, or maybe it would just you can kind of see it in this little image
Here it's a little brown. It's a little you know, like gnome but without the gnome flashiness and modern
I don't know
I was less impressed than I hope to be but I think with like a few minutes of configuration
It could be a pretty it could be really it's all now that you say it
It kind of looks like a well, you're not running gnome. So here you go, right?
Right, you know and it's like that the icons aren't blue which is fedoras thing whereas in mint they're green
They're just you know, it's a little more and it's kind of a weirder blend between
Yeah, the gnome look and the cinnamon look but yes
But that said like for a fedora base with with a really good cinnamon on top is something I would be interested and the theme
Is something you can quickly change right exactly. Yeah first impressions do count though
also for fedora 23 of course the KDE plasma desktop spin is out featuring KDE plasma 5.4.0 and
KD frameworks 5.15 of course and because it makes sense. The application stack is 1508
So just because KD is really easy understand don't call it KDE though
You got you got plasma desktop 540. You got the framework of
5.1 5 and you got the application stack of 1508
I don't understand what you guys don't understand this
What can't you follow about this by the way plasma 5.4 includes because it's 5.4.0 includes a new audio applet
application dashboard and an updated breeze icon theme and
With some controversy Firefox as default
There you go. And then last but not least on our fedora 23
Something kind of neat a new fedora community blog. I'm actually kind of excited about this today
Yeah, it's kind of neat right the fedora project is pleased to announce the launch of a new publication platform for different fedora
Contributors the fedora community blog the community blog intends to better connect the different projects groups and efforts going on in the community
Every single frickin day
Which is great because fedora is already kind of that, you know Linux next pushing the boundaries
Yes, Lauren things right nice to hear more about what I agree
I agree and then last but not least in our fedora 23 follow-up category fedora ra hide
If you're already done with 23, you're bored with that s fedora ra hide enables Wayland by default when it is
Supported. Oh, I am so ready for this Chris. Are you I mean X is great. It works really well
It's stable and you know everything I want but X is X is
Suitable. Yeah, I wouldn't know it's not great in any way. Yeah, it is sufficient for now
Yeah, I am I am I am so ready for the Wayland future and I'm excited to explore it
I'm sure that a million things will break and I'll be very inconvenienced and I'll complain on air to everyone but
It's gonna be fun
Anybody the mumble room had a chance to try out fedora 23 anybody have any follow-up thoughts on our review for fedora 23?
The floor is open. I am running it right now. Tell me about it
so I think the only criticism that I have is that
RPM fusion took like a week to update that is really annoying and by the way
Couple us to two points about that. They got the they got the repository online much faster than they got the website updated
So it actually was possible to get working under 23 much earlier than those sites said it was but that aside the hell
One of the things that I didn't talk about in my review in Linux action show
But the hell is why are all of the third part third-party repositories and all the third-party flavors like a week at
Best and in some cases Korora a month behind
Fedora like when Ubuntu releases 1510 every single frickin spin is ready to go
You got PPA is good to go. Everybody's everybody's got tutorials talking about the new 1510 how to install crap when it's fedora
It's like oh
Wait a minute
Hold on. I'm sorry. Uh
Is there a new fedora release I guess we better update our repository I
Guess we should wait. It's been four months
I guess we should write a tutorial on how to do something in fedora
It literally feels like you're in a vacuum
When you install a new version of fedora like in the first like I would just say two three weeks
It feels like you live in a universe where no other person in the entire universe runs your app
Or your operating system and then and then here's the great thing five six months in
Everybody's got repos. Everybody's got tutorials
Everybody's got forum threads on how to do s in your version of fedora six months into it
But good news everybody that version is about to be replaced before you're even before you can even get settled and use a version of fedora
There is a new version out and nobody and and I'm looking at you RPM fusion. I'm looking at you how to Linux
I'm looking at all of you people out there. I'm everybody out there source Forge sure. I'm looking at you
I don't care
I got I just I want to see how you all the Ubuntu users do it when a new version of Ubuntu ships all the
Flavors are out all the tutorials are out all the PPAs are out web update omg, Ubuntu
All those people have articles on how to do crap under the new version
The top ten things to do with the new version of Ubuntu Google search that right now go go Google search
Top ten things to do with Ubuntu 1510 and go look at all of the crappy blog
Articles about the top ten things to do after you install Ubuntu 10 and 1510 and you know what they all have they have PPAs
They have themes they have tutorials all of which are relevant to the current version of Ubuntu now
I invite you top ten things to do fedora 23 go search that nothing shows up
literally nothing shows up and it is what fundamentally makes the difference between a usable desktop environment and that
Actual people use and other users can recommend to other people and what now stuff shows up. Well 21 and 22. Yeah. Oh, yeah
That's what shows up after the release and this is consistently the problem with fedora and and and how do you quantify this in a review?
and how and as literally as somebody and I'm just telling you this as somebody who has reviewed every single release of fedora
Since they literally called it fedora. Okay, since they called it fedora
I have been reviewing every single version of fedora and this is every single time been a problem
We are 23 releases in it will never change apparently and it's not fedoras problem
It's the community's problem the community apparently takes a week to get off their ass and the RPM fusion site
You know should just even update the wiki take some four or five days and it takes them three days just to get the repo
Online and you go on reddit and you see the number one thing about fedora 23 years
Oh, I can't get RPM fusion working
It is embarrassing and it is literally the difference between a distribution that is usable by end-users and approachable and recommendable to their
average person and
Something that makes it only approachable to the elite and on top of that it makes it a huge pain in the ass to review
I'm sorry about the rant
Done Wow, actually I was able to pull up some top 10 articles on a fedora
But they don't give specifics because everything is yeah
To cuz well, yes. So first of all, you can on on Tuesday, November 10th
Find some things for the fedora 23 a week literally after it's been released
You can find some stuff
But the majority of the stuff you will find is for the previous version of fedora that only a clown show would be using at
this point, yep, it's just it's
So what makes a successful version of desktop Linux isn't just that you release and ship
It is that there are people out there that want to use it
It is that there are people out there that want to support it
It is people out there that want to write tutorials for it
It is sites out there like OMG Ubuntu they'll want to have an entire blog about it, right?
It is all of these people that make the ecosystem around distribution that are fundamentally
Required to make it approachable to the end-user you need to have a good chance when somebody goes to search
how do I install steam on Linux there needs to be a a
a
At least a decent chance that a tutorial on your distribution shows up, and you know what if you're a boon to today
That's probably the second maybe even the first link right. How do I install steam on Linux probably?
I don't know
I've never searched that cuz I'm not a moron, but probably this it's up there, right
I would be willing to bet you right actually do the search. Let's do it. Are you are you on Bing?
Well, of course, I'm on Bing. We're running Windows 10 in the studio here folks. Yeah, the Windows 10 test continues
All right, I think he just wants to torture me. Okay. Go ahead search it right now. I do actually every week
Okay, so install steam on Linux
Now here we go. Here we go. And our first result is steam. Of course links. There you go and developer valve software comm
Debian Ubuntu boom right there Ubuntu right there even on Bing. It's Ubuntu. Where's fedora in that list? I
Don't see it. There's arch. Yep. Yeah, go to the next page
Okay
arch Ubuntu mint
Uh-huh open suit. Hey, there's open sues
Uh-huh
Okay, we're on copy Linux. Oh fedora 18. That's that's good on which page of Bing
I'm sorry, go which page you go down to the page. We're on three. Okay on page three
There is an article on how to install steam on
fedora 18 fedora 18
That is my point right there that proves my point right there this
Ecosystem this ecosystem that makes it possible for average people to approach your distribution is lacking for fedora
It is good steams page does have a fedora subsection. Yes, but that's just and and if you look at it
Let's see fedora fedora to do to do to do. Yeah, uh-huh. Okay. Yeah
Nothing on there about 23. Nope, but you do have to rely again on RPM fusion here
Which is the unspoken thing about many users using fedora is it's it's not just fedora. So what how does fedora fix this problem? I
Have a solution. Yeah
so
every distribution regardless if it's
Ubuntu
Open to see or fedora has a development version which tracks the latest versions of software and everything and as
It gets closer and closer to stable. Of course, it becomes more stable
now
when I was on
the
RPM fusion website I noticed this that they had releases for rawhide which is the rolling
unstable for fedora and
Yet they didn't have 23. Why weren't they able to just freeze rawhide?
Because they already knew it was coming out. So there was a point at which they could have said hey
We're you know, this is coming up a week from now. Let's go ahead. Yeah and freeze that so the biggest issue for me
Oh, sorry, you know what the biggest issue for me is this the communication right? It's like if it takes you a week
Okay, yeah, thank you for doing what you're doing, but if you just put out something that says we run hit a snake
No, it's super cool to be known as the distro. That's great to install a week or two after it's out
That's what you want to be known as the distro you install two weeks after it's released and and and nothing nothing
You know really nothing the fedora project can do here other than continue to kick ass, right?
They have to continue to kick ass to motivate their community
I call on the fedora community to step up a little more though
I think but I you know
I've watched it with 22 and now I just watched it with 23 and it seems like the rest of the crowd is a little bit
Behind the scenes like oh, there's a new release. We didn't see this coming
Like that needs to stop happening and I I feel like that is the fundamental
fundamental downside to installing fedora on release day is I
The one thing I left out of my last review is just wait a month
That would be the one like to make fedora the perfect desktop for you. Wait a month and then it's great
Don't get caught up in the excitement. Yeah, don't increase the download kept just wait a month
Anyways before we move on anybody in the mobile room have any thoughts
Yeah, I've actually spoken to a few fedora guys about stuff around this and we've seen the same thing in openSUSE of way back
when in the past that the really tricky part is
Like having build systems that can keep up keep this all stuff in sync
Yeah, you know, you know, it's part of it's a bit of a technical problem as well as a community one
Yes, I don't know what RPM fusion are using in the back end their stuff
Really? I mean honestly in a way. This is something the build service could fix, right?
Well, it's something that Pac-man our equivalent of RPM fusion
They're using their own build service for this exact reason because it means they don't have to worry about it anymore
Yeah, yeah that you can link actual build services to each other so they know there's two hours
Yeah, figure out what the heck we're doing and then it just builds and actually they got our one done a week before
So is it is it just that there's a different class of user using fedora?
Who are less inclined to want?
Vast I mean all the things you've talked about are pretty much all proprietary products so Skype steam
telegram while telegrams not but yeah, like hosted externally third-party probably binary only stuff, right and
every distro has a profile of users and is the profile of a fedora user the kind of person who
Values their freedom, you know fedora doesn't ship with any non-free stuff
but therefore is the kind of person who isn't inclined to want to
Fill up their lovely free software desktop with a load of non-free stuff. I
Think you could be onto something there. Yeah, I I do actually completely agree with you
Yeah, I I do actually completely agree and I I actually think that is a a pretty legitimate market right now
I mean it, you know, I think there was I think ten years ago. I think that was sort of a tiny tiny tiny niche, but
Honestly, I think that's tens of thousands of people now and I think that's a legitimate people to it to right and that's tens of
Thousands, but that's not that's not
Enough that can sustain a vast community of users who can maintain build servers who can yeah maintain
right up-to-date blog packages and right tutorials and all that or
Honestly blogs that drive enough traffic to make advertisers interested right right even break even on right?
Yeah, is it worthwhile me doing that kind of thing? Yeah, that is the huge part that you have to break through to make a complete
ecosystem and
And leap has got an interesting approach fedoras got an interesting approach approach
Especially if you haven't seen our review from Linux action show go check it out
The DNF upgrade might make it easier to move between releases. I talked about that a little bit. We'll see right
I'm gonna do an experiment for the next few releases and see how it goes Kitson. You have our last thought ticket, sir
Yeah, the counter on poppy on that one
There's actually quite a few titles of free software that is hard to get on fedora her root pad is near impossible
Yeah, it's free software and it's just not packaged. I
Know it drives me crazy. It makes me it makes me the sad it really does but I
Guess nobody else has taken the time to make her pad work. I don't know either as
Richard said I don't know what fedora or opium fusion used behind the scenes
I mean, we're very lucky in that we have
PPAs in any member of the community can just yes create a PPA for nothing for free
Yeah, two gig of space. Yeah, and it will be built on any supportive release including the development release
Which isn't even out yet?
So people can be building stuff before the release comes out and we're we're lucky and our users are lucky that they have that
I don't know what's stopping opium fusion from being able to do that
But that might resolve one of the issues you're you're talking about. I would imagine the RP infusion folks are probably just resource limited
You know volunteers
it's a migrate it's a it's a combination of several projects and
It's it's easy to sit here and take you know our you know be judgmental
But it does feel like the community needs to I guess here's here's my closing thoughts and then we're gonna move on
And it is this with the fedora dot next initiative. I
feel like the fedora project
stepped up their game and
23 is really the long-term realization of a lot of that 22 was interesting 23 is really that and
I feel like the rest of the community that does the support stuff around fedor
Hmm a lot of them the majority hasn't stepped up at the same way
Fedora project stepped up their game community didn't necessarily step up the game to match it
And now I call on them to step up their game a little bit. We could have something really excellent here
Yeah, it just takes a little bit more. Let's make 24 the one where everybody's on page at the same time
And it really is something you could say to an average person go try fedora 24 and all of the support infrastructure around it
Ready to go at that time. It'd be really sweet. Hey, you know what else?
It's really sweet Linux Academy another sponsor of Linux unplugged show Linux Academy comm go there right now
In fact pro tip West you ready for this Linux Academy comm slash unplugged. Boom
Unplugged special discount for the Linux unplugged are you fine folks? I need you to go there now
I need you passionately to go there because here's why you think there is you think it's just random chance
They've been advertising on the unplugged show for a little while new. Oh, it's not no turns out
It's because it's the perfect fit for our audience. It is a resource built defined created born
By people who are passionate about Linux, you know, there's other sites out there Linda other sites out there
I won't even name them
They just put like Linux and open source stuff on there as like a feature
Oh, I hear it all the time, you know on advertisements on online
There are
There are other podcasts out there today. They may run a you know a lynda.com ad
It's for people who like to mess with computers
But see they will list something like Linux or nginx or Apache or Ruby or Python or RPM or IP tables or our sink
or SSH
Exactly those are buzzwords. Those are those are bullet points on their website. They couldn't really give a shit about them
They really couldn't Linux Academy is more like Jupiter broadcasting
It was created because man this thing Linux is really freaking awesome
Now, how can we get more people to use it?
And then from there they partnered with educators and developers and they created the Linux Academy platform
They have over 1900 self-paced courses with instructor help on demand, which is a big deal
They got scenario based labs you go in they actually use something before you go do it in production and I love this
7-plus distros to choose from
You choose your distro and then the courseware and the virtual servers match that up
Everything matches. Oh, yeah comprehensive study guides ready to go audio video download them
Listen in the shower while you're naked you can do that. You can listen in the commute
Oh that might make sense. It's incredible. Plus they got live streams
Instructor help did I mention that? Yeah, it's pretty nice
and then of course in the month of October every single month, it seems like really
They got new features a new CDN all Linux powered new HTML 5 players throughout. Oh, those are slick
I love that and of course
Now better than like anything before when you go through and do a system
They can give you real-time feedback on how you're doing
Plus they have new systems to prep you for the big certifications. And by the way, the community
Stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members. It's pretty nice. Very friendly. Yes, go check them out
Linux Academy comm slash unplugged support the show just by visiting that website and get yourself a special
Discount just visiting. I mean you'll see something you're right. I want to know more about the new nuggets
Maybe you can learn more there just help the show out and learn a little bit more about Linux Academy visiting Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
There's a very special discount for you Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and a big
Thank you Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux unplugged program
All right, Wes. Well, we're gonna move right along now. And did you hear about this?
Well, oh actually, you know, I gotta give a special mention before we move on a friend of the show Benjamin Krencia or
I always get that wrong. What's what it's you know, you say it like Krenza Krenza. Thank you
Anyways, it is a he has an app called glucosio for I I guess he's working on iPhone
But it's it's out there for Android right now. It's diabetes month. This is a special thing for me and
It's not like other stuff. It's not like you don't have to go. You don't have to go donate money
Really? They just want people to spread the word. So it's like a crowdfunding campaign only it's sharing it socially
So you can share on Facebook Twitter tumblr
And I'm gonna do it right now. I got a link in the show notes
If you have anybody in your life who's affected by diabetes, this is extremely interesting
So glucosio is his application for Android and iOS and other platforms. We talked about it on tech talk today and
He is doing basically open source crowd sourcing of
Glucose and diabetes information to do some interesting crowd research and he's got a great app available for Android right now glucosio
To track that and to track blood sugar what you've eaten to do some some really nice data
And so if this is something if you have diabetes and something you manage you might want to check out glucosio
It's an open source app
That also is contributing anonymous data for research
It's expanding to multiple platforms and right now that they simply want to spread the word about their open source free application
There's no money involved
it is an open source app from a friend of the show friend of the network and I got a link in the show notes and
they just want to spread the word for diabetes month and
Honestly, if you have somebody with diabetes an open source application is a great way for them to manage it
I think this is also important because I think it can be a good wedge into the the medical
Industry in that I think having these open source apps like if you have if you have diabetes
Shouldn't there be you know just in common humanities infrastructure a way for you to you know
Open source something auditable something you can trust a way to keep track of your health issues, right?
We need those as a you know as a free society. I agree and we need more of that in the medical community
So to see something like this, I think we should all support it. Even if it affects you or not
Yeah link on the show notes if you want to tweet about it or something like that
So did you guys hear about this new Linux ransomware that's targeting the Linux system?
We thought we were safe. It was a Windows admin problem, right?
Right
It's called Linux encoder or Linux dot encoder dot one and it targets personal website files and demands
$500 in bitcoins the antivirus company. Dr. Webb has issued an alert about a new form of crypto ransomware
Stroke your beard. Oh, these terms are so fun. I know you see me stroking the beard. Oh, it's beautiful
Thank you, sir. Can I maybe next time I'll know? Yeah, never mind. Keep it growing. I'll keep your own beard growing
You got it going right now. I targets Linux users. It's designated as a Linux dot encoder one and
the malware largely targets web services encrypting the contents and demanding a ransom of
bitcoins of value about five hundred dollars many of the systems have been affected by malware and
Is
Primarily, I believe at this point targeting the magneto CMS. So if you don't run that you don't really get a you know
I'm back to you know, this doesn't apply to you, but it's a critical vulnerability for magneto CMS
Which has already been patched, but of course people are lazy
And so this thing is attacking those CMS is with the low-hanging fruit
And another point here is that you know since this has been
Productized or whatever it forms a good, you know, there are still servers out there available the shell shock or you know
You just kind of take this you change that one thing. Yeah
Yeah, like this week there was a there was a story that WordPress now is like running 25% of the web
That's that's frightening. Yeah, which basically means it's gonna take forever for security updates to go out
In order to run the malware has to be executed with administrative level privileges
Using 128-bit AES crypto the malware encrypts the contents of the user's home directories. Hey, oh
Yeah, your home directories gone and any of files associated with the websites running on the system. It goes scanning for those
Yeah, oh, yeah. Oh, it does dude. Check this out. It goes through the whole directory structure of mounted volumes like
shares it's gonna check those right and and it encrypts a variety of files in each directory it encrypts things like text files and
Then it leaves a file behind called readme
underscore for underscore decrypt dot txt all uppercase because it's boss that's cruel. Yes boss level clearly
Influenced by the windows pedigree here. Yes. Yes very much
So a very much so edit demands payments and provides the links to the hidden tor site
The malware specifically looks for a patching engine engine X installations as well as my SQL installs in the director structure of the targeted
Systems you got that database. It's gone. That's right
It's gone and it's gone and it also seeks directories log files
Locations of web pages contents port ultimately going after a variety of file types including Windows executables. Hey, oh
Program program libraries and actor server pages. Yes, those ASP files and SQL files Java JavaScript and document files
The victim makes a payment the malware itself will then initiate decryption of the file
Otherwise it remains encrypted. They don't mention Python. That's what I usually end up writing my servers in so
You know, it's funny actually about that. The fix is a Python script. Oh perfect. Yeah
I love it. Yeah, this has been a whirlwind story and by the time we got on air
There's already a fix out and you can decrypt your files
The tool was created by malware researchers from antivirus firm bit defender who found a major flaw in the linux dot encoder one
Ransomware turns out uses really shitty random number prediction
The researchers discovered that when it generates as keys
The most program uses a weak source for random data and the time and date at the moment of encryption
So it can be figured. Yeah, they just they just seed it with the current date. Yeah, and there you go and they
Encrypt it with an RSA
Private key here, but you don't even need it because you can just guess it
Yeah, the timestamp is easy to determine by looking at when the ASP files were created on the disk
Therefore researchers were able to reverse the process and recover the AS keys without needing to decrypt them
Making the RSA public key and private keys essentially pointless the tool is created and released by bit defender. It's a script written in
Python
That determines the initialization vectors NES encryption keys by analyzing the files encrypted by ransomware program
And the decrypts the files and fixes the permissions even fixes your permissions guys
It mods your files for you. If you can boot your compromised operating system download script and run under the root user
You're okay to go. Okay, if you can put any Linux live CD, yeah, you know how to mount a drive exactly exactly
The first little is hard guys, you know, I wanted to come on the show
I want to talk about the first Linux ransomware
I wanted to tell you that it was a it was a it was a real scary thing you guys
I mean, I'm not saying I wanted to come on this show and I wanted to be all like Alex Jones up in this space
What's driving me crazy is that photo right there zoom in on that
It's one of those cops in a black uniform with a mustache and you just look like an absolute clown freak
That works for murdering terrorists the jack our food and water. I think you're a big joke
But no, it turns out your Linux boxes are completely safe
completely safe
But mustaches are not
All right. So I wanted to talk about one more thing before I wrap up today this, you know Linux unplugged show
It's a community show. It sure is. We got our virtual lug here
Bunch of handsome assholes beautiful, you know, we need some ladies to come in here to represent. Absolutely. Yeah. Yeah go to jblive.tv
We do this show to a 2 a.m. Oh my god 2 p.m
Pacific over on likely that's like, you know in the best time zone ever
But if you go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar will convert that to your time zone for you automatically all sentient beings are welcome
If you're sentient, yeah, you know, you can think for yourself. You run Linux. Can I come hang out? Can I make an asterisk?
Yes, and your microphone. Yes. Okay, you need a microphone. You need it to be interference free
You need to not listen to the live stream while you try to talk to us
That's all of these things and then you can please please join us
All right, so anyways before we moved on I
Wanted to talk a little about a little bit of community drama
Because this seems like the show to do it. It's the unplugged show. We got to talk a little bit about things
But here is something that I don't know what to process and maybe something the moment room can chime in
but it appears to be that there is a bit of
Controversy in the Debian community and this is coming from the developer of the Debian live releases is
And it is permanently halting. He says that Debian live is dead
Hi jacked by the Debian CD and the Debian installer teams. The Debian live server will shut down at the end of the month
Get repositories will go read only as of now and are mirrored to a github for archival
So long and thanks for all the fish. Now Debian live is the basis of a lot of distributions live CDs
And it seems to be pretty upsetting and it appears to be with the result of a bit of an in-project
Controversy where there was things that were not happening. Like oh, I don't know you EFI support
What not that Chris right and so Debian live CD and G was created
Which sort of added some of these features
but the original developer of the Debian live CD project wasn't notified and
When he found out it was based on a pull request that referenced the new project
Not a great way to find out no upstream patches or you know, nothing submitted to him. Yeah. Yeah
This is a you know
Debian seems to get these where there's many sides and it's kind of just a complex human problem, you know
It's very much is open source community and it can be hard to do these, you know, some things need to happen
But it's it's hard. Yeah. Yeah, like they have to move on right?
But at the same time like they have the same difficulties that all of us who have difficulty to having difficult social interactions
I'm exactly yes
And so I don't anybody the moment before we open this up anybody the moment of have immediate thoughts on today's story about Debian
live being dead
It just sounds like a lot of overreaction
How so
Well, I think that
You know the Debian live maintainer could have been a bit more diplomatic about it, you know, if I was in issues
Yes, I would be a little bit upset that I wasn't notified about it, but I'm not gonna
Reject somebody else's work
And it does sound like he has had some
Diplomatic issues in the past. Yeah, that is all honestly something that I've picked up on to
And it seems like some basic communication stuff might have been missed both ways perhaps
Yes, exactly. And now we have this and unfortunately though
Who's really affected our end users and specifically Debian stable users who don't really stay up to date on the day-to-day stuff like this
They're depending on it to be stable. Yeah, and it is an interesting development. Any other thoughts in the moment before we wrap up? I
Think it's kind of unfortunate
But I don't really think it's a big deal if you have an owner who doesn't want to play nice with people who submit patches
Then they're going to fork your project. That's just kind of inevitable. I mean, that's sort of the point really. Yeah
Cognizant of it. I feel like he should have been aware. They were doing this. It probably wasn't you know, completely behind his back
I'm sure there was talk about it. And
And so I'm sure it wasn't just all of a sudden. Oh one day. Here's this project that no one knew about it
Has all these patches contributed to it?
Right, right
There is some sort of pressure in the open source world
If you don't make yours your branch the best then you get what else's will be very much
So it isn't that in some ways?
Exactly. Exactly. That's just what I was gonna say. Isn't that in the long term exactly what we want? Yeah
Yeah, go ahead and his response is actually kind of Braddish, you know, he could have just said oh, well
Maybe I shouldn't be the owner anymore and I can hit it off to all these guys who clink they know
You know what the correct direction for this project is
Shutting it all down and for them to go with the fork instead of allowing them to take over this original name and continue on
Yeah, the lineage. Yeah, although I do wish there could have been more communication up front
Yeah, just a notch of waste labor to you know, help. Yeah and avoid really the story. Yeah
Yeah, I have a theory as to why these problems keep happening though
Go ahead
So I think a lot of it is and I've noticed that it's personality conflicts
And I really have to wonder if these people have any experience in jobs where they work with people
maybe they don't have that experience like working with customers and whatnot and just dealing with angry upset people and how to
Yeah, calm them down. You know saying everyone should have to perform a customer service job in their life
Then I would agree with that. I will tell you the people the sys admins that have at one point in their life as they
Worked the chain up that worked in the help desk position or the knock or the whatever
They are absolutely the best admins like because they they have spent a year or two
Understanding the end-users perspective and no matter how intellectually you are know how good you are
Visualizing and tell you've actually worked that role you don't understand and it really does make a difference. That's a good point, too
All right. Well, I'd like to hear your points linuxactionshow.reddit.com. Go find the next unplugged episode
118 and leave us your feedback. Maybe you have another viewpoint, you know
You could also join us live and give us your view your viewpoint
We mentioned yeah Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar to get that in your local time zone
And don't forget we want to get your opinions on open Sousa leap. Have you been trying it out?
Let us know. In fact, you can even join us live next week
I should be back from system 76 in Denver, Colorado, and you can join our mumble room and let us know
Or you can go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact or even better Linux action show dot reddit
Comm West is anywhere you want to point you buddy this week. Not this week. Come on, man
Come on something Twitter account something. I do have a Twitter account. I'm also noble pain in the IRC
Oh, I got some more content coming your way. Nice noble pain in there
I like it for that next week. Very nice jblive.tv for live shows Linux action show dot reddit.com for content
Thanks everybody. See you right back here next week
I've never installed you know slash looks
It's for people who like
If you and you know who you are if you're somebody doesn't want to mess with I just want to surf
I just want to buy something on Amazon send an email to my kids look at some websites
That's you you don't want to mess with it
Probably
I
Think the Chromebooks are a good choice
I think a new version of Windows would be fine Windows 8 if you can afford it a Macintosh if you've got even more money
That's a good choice
It's only for the enthusiasts that I'd recommend
Ubuntu
There you go. All right. All right, Jimmy titles calm. Let's name this sucker a great turnout in the mobile room
Thanks everybody really appreciate it. Yeah, you guys make the show
Definitely definitely
I feel like we could basically turn them on and then if we just gave them a couple ideas and walked away, right?
We can you and I go get some tacos and we be fine. You come back you rant a little yeah
Charged up again, and then and then it's good
Usually when that happens it turns into a text editor action show
Yeah, nice. Yeah, that's fine. Yeah. Yeah, Jimmy titles calm. Jim. Tell calm everybody boat
Taking a leap mate
Sport no
So Chris you mentioned installing Spotify on Ubuntu and you had to grab an old
Yeah, like live
G-crypt one one. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. Look, I'm just gonna paste the link
This is probably the website that you read on the Spotify Linux download page. Yeah
That was where I started which kind of sent me down the wrong direction really
Yeah, so here's the thing that the the little bit of text in there is the word currently 1404
Yes information is relative to 1404 but in those instructions
They say at this repository and there is the word stable
if you change stable for testing you get a secret source
Not only that but it's the it's the 1.0 release and it's got the 32-bit and 64-bit
Packages in there the whole thing and good to know
Yeah, and that's what that's what welcome does behind the scene is turn that repository on very nice. Thank you. Good to know
I will I will I will keep that in mind for future deployments, but it's worth knowing for check-in
I haven't looked in the AUR packages, but if there's Spotify packages in the AUR if they're not grabbing them from
The testing repository grabbing the devs from the testing repository
Then they're probably also pulling in, you know G-crypt one one, but that means you're getting like naught point nine something of Spotify
But I'm running like one point fifteen or something at the moment
So, okay, and it's nice. The new version is sort of like feature parity. Yes
I did I did notice that on my arch desktops. The new version is much better
Oh, well, it looks like someone in arch has already figured this out in which case yes
Yes, but good to know very very much. So actually thank you
Well, you can pull pull in. Hey citizen kids and kitty and North Ranger. They've all been I know that they all have good mics
Well, actually, I don't know about hey citizen. Oh, hey citizen has the annoyingly best mic here. Oh, really?
That's really nice. Oh, I want to hear I haven't heard it yet. Yeah, so do I cuz yeah, it's telling me about yeah
Yeah, yeah drag him down in here. Let's see. Yeah. Hey citizen. Let me hear it. Let me hear it. Hey, okay
Hello, hey citizen. Hey
Now hey citizen, are you a podcaster yourself?
No, you're shitting me the why do you have such a good mic just to make you feel bad
Well, you should host a podcast you're hired
What what equipment do you have
You know just a cheap sound card and this mic. I bought like ten years ago when I was in a band
Until recently. Yeah, it was an old old mic from a stage
There's like also though. There is a like a five percent reverb that gives you a little tiny bit of God voice
So you sound like very authoritative like you could just you chime in with a teensy-teensy
Bit to echo and it really works for you. We're all intimidated courtesy of Jack
So you're using Jack to do your EQ and stuff. Oh, yes. Yeah, that's my it's working so good. Yeah
Yeah, I might be why you sound so good. It's almost worth tinkering with Jack, isn't it?
Yeah, it almost really is I should yeah, it's really rock-solid
Hmm. So what what what distro you're using and how did you persuade Jack to work with mumble?
Um, well on arch there's actually a package in the AUR, which is a mumble git
Of course and mumble jack. Yes. Of course. There is yeah
So that's for a current that's for a current version of mumble because I've heard people talk about this adapted
Version, but it's usually like one dot two zero or something quite old, but you must be running a current version
Yeah, one point three point. Oh
There we go. So
Well, it's all lies everything I've heard about the jack version not being available for a current version of mumble then that's just lies
Yeah, it's it's it's in the arch user repository as a god dash voice and you just go ahead and
What's the what's the difference between uh jack and lapsta plugins or whatever they're called
Are they the same thing at all?
Well, those plugins are are what you use in jack to uh, oh, yeah effects
Hmm
Okay, I need to spend some time with jack. Yep, me too. Oh, okay. So they are the same system
Well, yeah ladspa, which I think now has been replaced with uh, lv2
Um, those are like a protocol. It's kind of like vst you have instruments and effects
Hmm actually, um citizen, I think you've lost a bit of the base that you had
You know when we told you to turn it into an am radio the other day to make us feel better
I think you didn't turn it back to exactly how it was before you've lost some of your low end
A bit. Oh, really?
This just won't do
Hmm this just won't do yeah. Yeah, is this a bit better? Oh, there you go. Whoa. Whoa. Oh no
Okay, so apparently I should throw away thousands of dollars worth of gear and just use jack audio
Yeah, hashtag puppy wants it deeper