This was a fun tweet that was sent my way if you're stranded in a weird shell and you're only allowed to bring three commands
Which ones do you choose boy? There's a lot of good choices out there
You see tons of folks answering with you know, you need an editor of some type or maybe I'll just bring see
My favorite answer it was just give me common lisp. Okay. All right. What about you cheese?
What would your if you had you could bring up to three commands with you? Which one did you bring?
probably
pseudo
Less and
LS sure, come on. Where's the netcat?
What about you drew which three commands would you bring
Probably cat echo and LS our case. He says I'd bring Hollywood. That'd be good. You know that that
You're not gonna get much work done, but you'll be entertained. How come no one has said apt
It feels like that's the obvious choice or whatever your package manager of choice is DNF
Well, if you have a netcat you can just you know bring the archives across and I see you need to live archiver untar
Or whatever isn't the real answer Emacs. It's got a package manager built
Hello friends and welcome into your friendly Linux weekly talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hi Wes Payne. Hello
Welcome into 353 sir. Oh, I like that number. I know feel so official. Well, we have a really great episode
It's something we've wanted to touch on for weeks and that is your feedback
We got a whole batch of listener feedback this week also have our thoughts on the new pop OS
2004 we've been kicking that around and we'll give you our take on that and we have a new machine that just arrived in the
Studio still in the box. We'll take that out and tell you what laptop we're reviewing next
Plus we have a bunch of community news and so much more to get into so first
Let's start by saying hello to the gentleman on the over the internet mic line. Hello cheesy and drew
Good to have you guys on board. Hello guys. Hello. Hello. Hello and hello to our
Virtual lug time appropriate greetings mumble room. Hello. Hello
So, let's start with some community news
there's a story that I wanted to bring up to the top of the show sort of flag it to everyone's attention if you have
recently installed Ubuntu 20.04 server and chose the encrypted storage option it is possible that that
password you chose for encryption was
Stored in plain text in a log file. Oh
so the fix is out fixes in Wes and
If you grab the most recent
20.05.2 dash 1 8 7 4 of this sub equity. I think it's what it's called package
It will fix the problem. It's an installer issue. Just a bit of an oversight. I guess oopsie doodles
Yeah, one of those rather big oopsie doodles actually and it wasn't an intentional thing
It wasn't like some breach or anything about you back door and there's as far as we know
No examples of this information being used in the wild
It was caught during a check and then submitted as a bug and then of course canonical jumped on it
I might have the timing wrong, but I think they went from discovery to fix took them 17 hours or so
I'm not be able to you might be able to check Wes in the launchpad bug. Oh, yeah
It looks like it was reported here 18 hours ago 19 hours ago and the fix was in five hours ago
So that's some 14-ish hours Wow, even better than what I was told clearly something they're taking seriously
Yeah, you know so very good. But just so you know, that is pretty critical. You should probably get that updated
now
Go check if you've already got your system installed
Maybe just go and see if those log files are hanging around and remove them. Hello to Alan Jude
It's good to have you back on the show, sir. Hello
Hello
Was just saying on the pre show before we actually hit the record button that I've been really enjoying two and a half admins
Which is a new podcast with Alan Jim Salter and Joe Resington at two dot five admins comm is that what it is?
Yep, that's that's our clever domain hack
So clever really good show. It's great to have you and Jim on the same show
And I've been enjoying the first two episodes. Let's go check that out. Definitely don't mention ZFS at all. No that never comes up. I
Love it
you know like always Alan you do a great job of explaining the stuff that people are the most interested to know and sort of
Deliver it in a great in the way
You've always done a great job of delivering it since early days of tech snap clear clear breakdown
I love it
And so you then you add that with Jim in there and then Joe has the perspective that maybe a lot of people in the audience
Have which is they haven't yet learned about this. You need someone to ask the questions
Yeah, he's the dot five and the two admins right there. If you didn't catch it. I craves EFS. There you go
So go check that out. It's good to have you here
We have a whole bunch of a whole bunch of people in the virtual leg over 30 people in there today
Which is really cool. Maybe the best one yet. If you'd like to join us, it's at Tuesday
It's on Tuesday at noon Pacific over JB life TV and then there's instructions if you just google search
Jupiter colony mumble mumble Jupiter broadcasting. Okay. Okay. Thank you
So it's mumble dot Jupiter broadcasting org and that has the setup guide the trickiest thing about our mumble server is
It's using the old default port not the new default port and if you aren't going to join
Maybe just show up a little bit early make sure you can get your mic checked out get through all of our staging
It's great to see not a guy at work back in there because that's one of my favorite nicks of all
Not a guy at work totally innocent
One of the things that got us chatting in our back channels just between Wes I and cheese and drew and everybody else on the team
Was this sort of bold statement made by fedora?
I guess I guess you could attribute it to a statement on fedora's part
This kind of came out. Well not kind of it did come out of a fedora AMA that was conducted on
Telegram and ask me anything where a question was asked
Why is gnome shell the default for fedora workstation?
And then I guess after some reflection they realized, you know
We didn't really challenge that underlying assumption and so then a post was created saying that gnome is not the default for fedora workstation
No, it's not the default Wes. Whoa, that's news to me
But let's dig into what they're actually trying to say here
I get it, but I think it will provoke a conversation that I'd like us to get into what they're essentially
Asserting is that fedora workstation isn't a box of parts where you choose default options and then blast it onto the hard drive
They say no instead. It's a carefully procured
Assemblement of an operating system aimed at developers sysadmins and makers in general if you replace one or more parts of it
Then it stops being fedora workstation
It's not the thing they've created anymore and it starts being a build your own operating system and that's okay
But it's not fedora workstation, right? Then they say this is an important distinction to make
It's not that they have some specific goal of creating this exact gnome experience so much as it is an entire
Workstation product that is tightly integrated that they test as a whole and it's developed as a whole
It's a mindset of how they create the distribution how they test the distribution how they verify the distribution
Yeah, this post is over on Christian Schaller's blog and you know
He writes having been in the game of trying to provide a high quality desktop experience both
Commercially in the form of rel and through the community efforts around fedora workstation
I have seen and experienced firsthand the problems that the mindset of interchangeable desktop creates
For instance before we switch to the fedora workstation branding and it was all just fedora
I experienced reviewers complaining about missing features
Features that we'd actually spent serious effort implementing because the reviewer decided to review a different spin of fedora that can know
Mmm other cases. I remember our customers trying to fix a problem by switching desktops
Only to discover that while the initial issue they wanted fixed got resolved now that they've switched
Well, they have a whole bunch of problems and never saw the fix to the first one
yeah, and so for now rel only offers gnome as the default desktop and the same is true in fedora workstation and that's not because
They don't understand that people enjoy experimenting with other desktops
but because it allows them to work with their customers and users and
And hardware partners on fixing the issues they have with their entire operating system
Because it's a clearly defined entity and adding features
Needed going forward and properly supporting hardware and vendors going forward as opposed to spreading themselves thin
They say this is their take on it and just run around putting band-aids on problems that have been reported
Yeah
And maybe in the long run this is actually beneficial for people who do want to end up
Customizing their operating system because the team is just focused on you know
A narrow set of things like high TPI support getting wayland ready for the desktop
That's what we talk about all the time or making Thunderbolt work properly on Linux
And when you do have this giant mass of things to focus on it's not just not the same as having a you know
A precise goal that you're trying to polish and get ready to ship as fedora workstation
Yeah, and you see this manifest in fedora almost in every release in some way like a recent example
I think has been how they use a system D for the terminal sessions in gnome terminal
No, yeah, which is that's a that's a clear from the GUI all the way down to the low levels of the OS
Integration and there's been other things they when they rolled out like the example
He makes Christian makes here is Thunderbolt support when bolt and Thunderbolt D and all of the security stuff rolled out for fedora
There was a user facing GUI component in gnome system settings. There was a user daemon
In the lower levels of Linux and there was even some hardware firmware changes for some vendors
It was literally like he's speaking to here hardware vendor
assistance lower-level Linux cooperation and GUI implementation and it was executed as a whole
Singular product right and without that. I mean, it's kind of the Linux curse in many ways because we have all these interchangeable parts
Yeah, sure
You know the bolt daemon gets created but you're left on the own for the desktops and well
Maybe eventually plasma does it and who knows who spares the effort on the gnome side to do it?
But when you think of it as a shippable product in this big vertical stack
You're like, well, no
We need to we need to make this work from the bottom on up seems obvious
But it's not generally how we assemble something of a bunch of different parts
And so I guess I can see their point that if you go with this spin of fedora, it's not so much this default
It's that's how that spin is developed. I guess I can get that and it's not like they're not making the plasma spin or other
Spins available. Those are still perfectly easily valid options
But there was something that came up and this is really hard to quantify and I almost debated not even saying it on air
Because it's so silly but in our love plug. We were talking about how when you use
fedora
You can kind of perceive that it's one cohesive product if there's something about it that makes it
Feel like gnome is part of the whole system where most the time when I use gnome or any other desktop on any other distribution
It's like I can perceive there's a separation between gooey and lower level, right?
I mean compared to like a fedora install to just installing, you know an arch. It's not the same
It's not the same. You could put the same theme on there
You can have the same version of gnome shell
You can have the same version of the kernel and the same version of system D
And it still somehow doesn't feel like it's all a single product
that's why I debated not even mentioning it because I
I can't really even describe what that experience is but I bring it up because others also felt like they noticed it in the in the
Lug hangout and I thought okay, so it's not just me
It's not crazy Chris right and we talked so much about all the great work that fedora does sort of you know
Shepherding changes in from upstream and taking them together. I think it'd be easy to forget that there is this holistic approach that's going on
Fedora 32 it's so good. Just if you haven't tried it yet
I'll give that a spin because it's a great release
maybe you can tell what we're talking about here that that sort of full cohesive product experience now something that was going to be a
Cohesive product that is completely dissolved is ton or ton. I think it's ton
Which was the whole crypto?
Currency experiment the telegram was hurtling towards for the last two and a half years
They write on their blog our best engineers have been working on the next generation blockchain
platform
Called ton right? It was telegram open network, right?
Yeah, a cryptocurrency that they were also going to go with that was going to be grand
so you have the blockchain component ton and then you had Graham the coin and
That grand plan for telegram is now over and I think this is really noteworthy because the Linux community is pretty large on
telegram and
For the last two and a half years the best engineers as they put it on their very own blog
Have been focused on a cryptocurrency that by all outside accounts was never going to go anywhere
anyways, why do so many of the messaging apps seem to want to have a cryptocurrency like I remember was it keybase has been working on
one and
Making pop-ups in the app and annoying people that didn't care about cryptocurrencies about it. Although they just got bought by zoom. So who knows? Oh
That hurts so bad I know yeah
um, the other one that gets me and it's also widely embraced by our community is
Library or Libri or whatever library their whole system is really it comes down to a coin and when you cash out that coin it
Impacts negatively your search results on library
Look this one up go look up how you exchange the library coin. It's cute. You basically have to sell it to a completely
Other cryptocurrency something like aetherium or something something that's more widely traded that you can actually then trade elsewhere and it bitcoins too expensive
So go screw yourself. You better go with one of the lower tier priced
Cryptocurrencies then if you're if you're lucky you can either sell that directly into your currency
But more likely what you'll have to do is then sell that
cryptocurrency to buy Bitcoin and then you will have to sell the Bitcoin to actually cash out from library and
This was the same direction Telegram was going down
But unfortunately for them, but maybe fortunately for the users the US court decided that grams couldn't be distributed
not only in the US but
globally
Because they said it's possible US citizens would just find another way of accessing the platform after it launched
so to prevent that grams will not be allowed to be distributed anywhere in the world and
And while it seems like an excessive extreme overreach that the US law could somehow block
free cryptocurrency trade in other countries
There is a pretty established network of interest that is going to enforce that ruling
Yeah
It turns out the dollar is still pretty important as are all the financial institutions here in the States and the way they write about this
Kind of I think betrays where they were going with this
They write about it like
Yeah, like we found a gold mine and
We were gonna start letting people into our gold mine
He says this is a quote from the blog if this doesn't make sense to you
You're not alone, but this is exactly what's happened with ton the mine, which is ton the blockchain
It's investors and grams, which is the gold a judge used this reason
He'd tell people that they should not be allowed to buy or sell grams like they can buy or sell Bitcoin
They look at this as a gold mine
He writes many people invested in the gold mine because they were looking for profits
They didn't want that gold for the gold themselves. They wanted to sell it to other people because of this
You're not allowed to give them the gold
That's how he's thinking about this. That's that's from him interesting this cryptocurrency thing, which is kind of cool
But there was the peak hype when this launched
Was maybe seen as this path to monetization that so many projects seem to be struggling to look for clearly is not gonna happen for Telegram
We're writing this post to officially announce that telegrams active involvement with ton is over
You may see or may have already seen sites using the name or the telegram brand or the ton abbreviation to promote their projects
Don't trust them with your money or data course, of course
There's a sketchy
Stealing your money angle to this whole thing to block chain, man
Is there any cryptocurrency that doesn't have a sketchy angle truth that might just be true of currencies
I think about it. Hey when we when you put money on the line, I mean, there's a lot of incentives
Mm-hmm. That's how you know that Bitcoin is like real money because there's just as many scams around
That's very true
Yeah, it is very true. We got to get to the unboxing here in a moment
But I wanted to talk about a little discovery
I had over the weekend
Thanks to mini Mac and Jill in the love plug this Sunday and also a news item that we thought we could cover here
So you remember the Enlightenment desktop right everyone enlightenment, of course. Oh, yeah, it is still going and
Just this week. They launched a new set of their frameworks
EFL think of it as like their version perhaps of GTK
But they would argue quicker better faster and better looking and they've released a new set of their core libraries
We thought well, what a great opportunity to kind of just take a look at
At enlightenment and I was chatting with a love plug like I was saying and I was I was kind of praising
how the things I love about plasma are some of the Kaywin window rules and telling windows to go exactly at this desktop exactly in
this space every time I open it and
Mini Mac and Jill were nodding. Yep
enlightenment can do that enlightenment can do that and then Jill you shared with me one of the features that you found enlightenment to be
Just maybe tops as far as Linux desktops go for all of them is the monitor management
Oh, yeah, they they've been far ahead in that in that area
They have a wonderful screen utility your monitors come up out of the box
And this was like ten years ago before distros multi monitor worked really well on distros
Right now I have three monitors one
43 inch ultra HD and then two 30 inch monitors on the side in portrait mode and
Enlightenment I've got it all configured in enlightenment and it works just beautifully out of the box
Hmm. I think you mean you need a little more screen real estate there Jill
That's great. Next up. She'll be full VR. That sounds like a brilliant setup
But it must get tricky when doing gaming and stuff, you know, I'm a big gamer
I like to game spanning the three monitors. So it's it's a it's a big deal for that to work because most window managers
that does not work out of the box and
With with enlightenment it does that's so cool and mini Mac
There's a performance aspect to it too. That seems to be super palatable even in a VM. I lose enlightenment as Jill
I lose it on all my multi screen environments, but also on computers that have low specs
So enlightenment comes handy because not only does it use quite?
a small amount of one so my system now on that Toshiba has about a hundred megs of ROM
It's using and enlightenment is so scalable. You can use it on that
1024 to 600 pixel laptop and you can use it on a huge machine with like four screens a
Little tidbit you shared with me is there's a reason why themes are slightly trickier on enlightenment
But the net result is much better performance. There is a very very special thing that the themes are in fact binary
So that has a very positive aspect. So the whole thing is really
Really bleeding fast, but it also has a negative aspect that you don't have so
Much themes available for now. You have a an official arc theme that I use that is pretty good
Pretty stable. Yeah arcs great. I love arc, but you have you don't have all these fancy teams that you can use without a desktop
But these themes that you have are binary and they are bleeding fast and you can use them and it's a breeze to use
It it's really a breeze
Computer could you have a question that I bet is on the mind of a lot of people there?
They're a little skeptical of enlightenment. How would it stack up speed wise to something like i3?
As I never use some tiling window managers. I can't really tell you what I can tell you
It's bleeding fast
and when we talk about tiling managers you have a module in enlightenment where you can
Use a tiling options and the coolest cutest thing is you can in fact define
Virtual desktop to use tiling functions and others use not so we can say
My left monitor using tiling functions and my right monitor does not use tiling functions
Oh snap, that's awesome. So you can see my virtual desktop on screen one
Uses tiling functions and my my right screen doesn't so you have
Possibilities you can't even imagine you can choose for every application you use you can choose if yes or no you want the window
Decoration then you can use stacking so you can have like an RC
IRC terminal open remove the window decoration and put it just on always low
So you have like a living background and you have all the other windows
That you can over your living background and you can roll in windows
So you don't have to minimize them you go into Windows title and you roll up your window mouse and you just see the title
Bar or window shading as it is on plasma. Do you have so many options?
You really have to discover and you have to be ready to really crawl to through all the settings
but there's a lot of it and
some of the
Possibilities you have are rather cryptic you get you really have to work
Yourself through the settings, but once you have your setting you will never change it and you will love it
So this is where e live came in
It was recommended to me by you and Jill and you can find it at e live CD org
It is a Debian based preset up enlightenment environment
There's a stable version which I believe uses enlightenment 17 and a beta version which uses enlightenment 16 think and
You can throw it on a VM or on a box and try it out immediately and it's a pre-configured
with a nice theme some default options and it walks you through the basics of using the environment with a
with a help walkthrough and it is a
a blast to try this distribution out and I say this in the
Like the most affectionate way it in some ways reminds me of an older era of Linux setups
Yes
That where they really kind of they let you sort of set a lot of options at install
But then nailed the experience when you do it just right so I'm I'm installing it right now
I have it up right here on this computer
And it's asking if I'd like the compositor if I'd like conky for the for the resources embedded in the desktop
If I'd like a dock and you walk through these kinds of questions about package sets, would you like chrome chromium Firefox?
Hey, I've detected that this thing supports open GL
Would you like me to turn that on some of these things are just killer for new users?
Yeah, I would have never known how to go figure that out
But I used to love that stuff and now Linux distributions
They just they just do it all for you without even asking really but when I install this I was like, you know
Maybe maybe I will try pale moon this time
I will try and I just checked that box instead of Firefox and it was a really fun
experience because it reminded of the way it used to be installed distributions and at the end you end up with something kind of a
little bit unique for you and
It was so fast. So Wes and I were playing with this. You got a chance to try it
I did. Yeah, Wes and I were very impressed by it and I thought for myself
I know immediately where I would use this on a daily basis if they made an arm image for the raspberry
I knew that's what you were
Really would be I mean it makes you
Reconsider like how what you can get out of a machine because like it feels
Pretty modern right and it has a lot of features. It's got the nice dock right on the bottom tons of configurability
Yeah, like this thing right here low resource
Yeah
This thing right here with I have a web browser open in a PDF viewer and it's using 300 megabytes of RAM with the entire
Thing the whole whole thing loaded. That's not bad because it's and it's been sitting there for I don't know a couple hours
So it's not bad and it can scale down below that if you look at some of the screenshots
They've got yeah, and it's one of those. It's one of those desktops that works
Brilliantly, it sounds like if you have multiple monitors, but I've been really impressed a single screen on a laptop, too
So we reached out to the developer of e live thaner to mesas
I think is how you say it. I get that right nicely done thana termesis not easy for me
I had to write it down right here
But I wanted to get it right because this is an individual who is working on this distribution by themselves since 2005
I believe and it really showcases what is I think such a classic story in open source where there is
Really really great software out there that does amazing things, but there's no marketing team
There's nobody that's pushing it in any particular channel and it just goes undiscovered
That's the enlightenment desktop and the enlightenment libraries which are used by people in the industry who know like
You know embedded markets, but outside of that it doesn't have a lot of general user adoption or knowledge
And so something like e live comes along and it showcases this brilliant work, which in itself is also a brilliant work
So I thought maybe I'd share a little bit of the email exchange
he wrote back to us and gave us some inside information about the project and
Than it to mesas writes
It is developed by a single person me and it sometimes receives a bit of help from volunteers in the past
I was able to pay someone, you know a little extra for some development help
But at the moment I'm alone and donations are not enough to pay anyone extra help
and it's the reasons why donations are so
Crucial for the survival of the project and you'll notice that when you go to the download page is it's almost like an elementary OS
Style approach that really asks you to download they have some free options or maybe wait a little while to get the ISO if you
Don't can't donate. Yeah, that's one. That's an interesting approach is
Donate to get the ISO now or give us your email and you'll get an link in an hour and on the beta side
32 bits are free, but the 64 bits version is a donation
But I think this is actually better right then the more insidious ways
The distributions could try to make money with tracking built-in advertising god forbid some sort of cockamamie crypto scheme
This I think is a more direct user supported approach
But I think he's gotten a lot of pushback on this and people don't really seem to care a lot when you look at the numbers
Of donations that he's getting it's really kind of too bad because I think this is close to his full-time job
It's just trying to keep this thing going. It takes quite a bit of work
It's hard to position a specific role for you life to since it it aims to be better every single release. He writes
This of course doesn't mean that it is the distro to pick for use for maybe developing no JS or to use to deploy
Kubernetes, but since it's based on Debian with good customization and compatibility
You can still use it for any purpose or transform it in to other things. Yeah, and I think that's true
There's actually a Linux insider review just recently in May to quote them
Elive is one of the most multi-purpose and different Linux distributions
You are likely to encounter and it does seem you know, there's all kinds of interesting things out there
He mentioned specifically the very powerful customizations to the terminal, which I've not had a chance to try yet
But definitely piqued my interest if you type el underscore and press tab
You'll see a ton of functions that can turn your shell into a powerful framework for development
And I think he uses that to actually develop the operating system itself
And also neat of him is customized right out of the box to be a full IDE suite
As it should be and then like like I was saying sort of more in the era of classic distributions
But in a good way when you're doing the installation towards the end you get asked
You want to install extra drivers and stuff, you know?
You're kind of familiar with some of these some districts still ask you that stuff
And when specific hardware is detected check this out
It will automatically configure the font sizes based on your screen
resolution a dynamic installer of the distro that optimizes for lightness and low-end computers oral enable extra features if it detects the other more
powerful computer and its own persistent system that saves different desktop settings per each different computer detected and
And there's some default customizations for apps and ad blockers
included by default in the browser with tools to automatically fix things like
running out of space and watching for that a possible stuck process and
Detectors for hard disk errors and strong shakings of the computer
There's a good multimedia support optimized video playback based on your graphics card as well
He says I'm sure there's more stuff, but that's some of the highlights. That's a lot of stuff
At
The moment we have the stable and beta versions. They're really different in many senses
For example, the stable version is very old but offers the best user experience intuitiveness beautiful and features
Included in the enlightenment 17 desktop. Yeah, that's where it got a little confusing for me
Is the stable version actually has enlightenment 17 and the beta version I guess trying to work on all the underpinnings that's using
enlightenment 16 for now. Yeah
Enlightenment 16 is loved by many people and deserves a good try for those who've never tried it before
You could see there's so much pride in this work
Absolutely a little bit of defenseness about the donations which seems to be very common in open source projects
but the end result is something that's brilliant and beautiful to use and feels like a
Desktop that is different and modern and the funny thing is it's been that way for quite a while, right Jill
Yeah, enlightenment was the first kind of eye candy OS
It was the most beautiful desktop ever created at the time
Yeah, like you were saying, you know
it lives in that world between a lighter X window manager like flexbox and window maker and
Xfce so it lives in that space between memory wise but it's so
Fast and beautiful even though it's not one of the heavier desktop environments
I mean if you've been running genome and you can't stand that there's JavaScript involved at all
Yeah, go for your binary themes and I remember talking about
Enlightenment back during Linux action show and I think I had a bias set in and I'm gonna admit it right here
it was simply I
Figured by now that stuff would have broken like it was really good with the software
Compositor and the monitor support back when I was doing Linux action show with Brian
Like that's the last time I probably really looked at it. Seriously, and I thought to myself
Well, I'm sure it's just bit rot over time and that stuff still can't be good turns out
Like they kept with it. That's kind of the amazing thing is I mean
Not many other communities. Would you see this sort of its own little ecosystem that can just continue to flourish?
I mean doesn't matter if any anyone's talking about it on podcasts or folks know about it
If it has a dedicated set of users who care about it and get great use out of it. That's enough
Yeah
You got users like mini Mac and Jill who become advocates for because they know it's like there's this really great thing over here
That happened so often open source when you got to think too that they also offer for free the 32-bit version
Which if you have an older machine, you know an old netbook or something like that
This would be perfect for it as well. Whereas a lot of distros are dropping that 32-bit support
So it made me want to fire up man Jaro on a pi 4 like a minimal man
Jaro install and then just build my way up to enlightenment
but I know I wouldn't be able to create an experience as good as I witnessed with e live because
Thanatomysus has been working at that for very long time and
Really knows how to work the back-end configuration of enlightenment
but I really want it on a Raspberry Pi because it is in that sweet spot of
like Jill was saying of sort of where XFCE is
Including sort of a slower release cadence, but it's a slow but steady improvement cycle
Do you end up using predominantly GTK?
Applications you mix it mix it all up. Is there is there one?
Desktop tool get like cute apps or GTK apps that work better or look better under enlightenment
I've had it installed alongside Gnome and KDE as well and haven't really noticed a difference
I mean I run Kdenlive in it without any issues
Theming's not weird or anything?
No
The only thing that happens is when you boot into it like I have it installed on Ubuntu
Mate too and when you you boot into it, you know all your icons from Gnome come in
but other than that
No, it, you know kind of exists on its own same experience for you essentially MiniMac
I on my laptops normally I use Gnome. So I'm pretty used to the GTK environment
a cool thing about at least the latest versions of enlightenment is that you don't have a problem with a
Double title bar. So enlightenment can very good adopt right now to the new inline
Decorations of the GTK applications fancy you don't face a problem that some QT users
complain that you have to title boys and then you have to work through the problems to
Eliminate one of them. We're all a bunch of filthy multiple desktop users
So ridiculous
well
Thank you to the Thanatomysus for taking the time to respond to my questions and if this is all piqued your interest go check out
Elive, elivecd.org and if you like what he's doing there kick him a few bucks
I think it's a great example of an open source project showcasing other great open source work
And it really is on the users to make that thing possible. Exactly. So that's pretty great
All right, Wes. What do you say we do a little housekeeping housekeeping? All right, bring it in bring it in. Oh
Yes
You heard us mention that we're live. You heard us mention the lup lug
Let's just kind of explain what those are because we're just tossing them around like maniacs
We are live on Tuesdays mentioned that earlier noon Pacific
but you can get it converted at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar you go to jblive.tv to watch it and
That's the that's the gist of it. Although
More and more people are really figuring it out
We have a quiet listening section in our mumble room
Which is pretty good audio quality and like the lowest latency you're gonna get it's like you're sitting right here in the studio with us
It's true. So that's another way you can tune in live and it's low bandwidth as well. So that's nice
There's so many ways
But we just love to have you here
We have a great chat room going to a bunch of people in there IRC that geek shed net pound at Jupiter broadcasting. Okay
That's the live stream. Now. Let's talk about that lup lug lup lug that's happening on Sundays same bat time
We do this show on Tuesday. So noon Pacific in the same mumble room just up in the lobby
We get together we hang out for a few hours
We get Chris to try enlightenment and it's it's a rather good time. We really enjoy it
So we'd love to have you join us. It's just a way for people to hang out and actually
Chat with other Linux users can be refreshing if you don't get an opportunity to do that very much
So that's the lup lug and you just got to get in that mumble room to join us and there is an IRC room as well
We can get details IRC that geek shed net and that is pound
Love lug, it's just nice to have a casual chat, you know, it's no pressure
It's not live or anything, but you'll be surrounded by people who also want to talk about Linux. That's right
That's right. And then Drew's here with the news on the infinite escape room for Linux. What's this? What is this?
What is this?
This is a podcast that
Reached out to us on Twitter and they asked for some help getting up and running with Reaper on Linux for their editing
So I talked with them a little bit over Twitter DMS and got them up and running with you know
some Lin VST and some wine and
Really just getting them where they needed to be to do their audio editing on Linux and it sounds like they're there
They've got it running and everything is good. So I just wanted to give them a shout out and say hey
Congrats guys for moving to Linux
That's amazing. Super cool. I did see that Twitter thread go by and that's super cool that you helped them and I
I presume since it's you they were speaking to they're now using Reaper. That is correct. Yes
That is our recording tool of choice for the Linux platform
I mean big props though
It's not easy to go, you know
Especially when you're focused on the content to go change up all the tooling that you're using and I know from experience they get into
Working on Linux while it works. Great can be a bit of an adventure
So especially if a few of your favorite plugins are Windows based plugin, right now we have a bit of it's a change
But not really one that will really affect the show very much, but I'm excited to announce that mr
Wes Payne ladies and gentlemen has a new day gig
West congratulations
But not much is changing for the show really is it no not at all
I'm going back to the world of software development full-time
So I'll be leaving a cloud guru as an employee
But I'm certainly not leaving the Jupiter broadcasting community and definitely not the show now
I'm really glad that you were able to continue staying here for the show because
Since episode 100 it's kind of become a thing with I know I can't quit it. No, you can't I noticed you got these shackles installed
Yeah, if you just sit right there forever just so I can make sure you won't go anywhere
No, no, no, it's we we've chatted about it. I think it's gonna work out pretty good. I'm very happy for you
I'm glad you're able to get a new gig that's back in the software development field
And I think you're gonna enjoy it quite a bit
but it does bring up a rather particular challenge and
That is you got to give back that laptop
So let's talk about that, but that right there. We'll leave that for the housekeeping
That's officially the housekeeping this week
but let's talk about what we're gonna do about this think pad because that is a work machine and
That's got to go back. I miss it already. But wouldn't you know it?
We got something new that just came into the studio this week
So sent in by Dell go ahead and take it out of the box there Wes and tell me tell me what we got there
There you go. Oh, yeah open it up here. Oh, it's very silver. It is very silver
Mm-hmm. This looks like the latest new model of the XPS. Oh, it is indeed Wes. It is the new XPS 13
It's got one finger open kind of sort of
And look at that screen so that's got the new edge to edge screen and the edge to edge keyboard
So it's just nothing but laptop and the new fingerprint reader up in the top corner
Which looks really nice same carbon fiber feel to it, but even more metal now
I mean, they've got these fancy chamfered edges. Yeah, isn't that looking super? Wow. Yeah
It looks like a really high-end product now with those shiny edges
So Wes Payne
What good timing for you to review a new laptop and tell us what it's like to set it up for a software development job
And maybe a little casual gaming. What do you say? I think that sounds like a challenge. I'm ready to take on there
You have it. So we'll either have it next week or shortly thereafter the West Payne take on the new XPS
13 so that should be really cool coming with me buddy getting used and abused Wow
Look how much put that next to the ThinkPad there. Look how much thinner that is
Holy smokes that XPS is almost just the size of the top of the ThinkPad
It's that's wild and it's like 75% in the just in the area of the thing
So the ThinkPad is a 14 inch. Yeah, so it's a slightly slightly bigger screen, but no question about it
Just even from across the table here. I can tell you that XPS 13 screen is way better. Hey better
Yeah, we'll find out about onboard sound and things like that. You know, that'll be in the testing
Yeah, I'll be curious on the whole West Payne tank take because that's got the 10th gen
Intel processor which people are claiming has a decent as far as decent in integrated graphics goes has decent performance
You've been playing on the ThinkPad with seventh generation, right? Is that what it is? Yeah, so this should be a big GPU
I'm excited to give it a try. Mm-hmm curious to know how all the setup goes for the new gig and all that
Of course, eventually we'll have to send it back, but we'll wipe it. We'll wipe it
Just a great opportunity to do really give that. Yeah
I mean I keep watching these things evolve and of course I had XPS way back when yep
So I know it's been a good line
I'm seeing you know what it work is my day today. Was it the first model XPS?
It was yeah the first model says this is gonna be really interesting to get your take on this one stuff
Cool, so we'll have that in a future show, but now
What do you say? We talk a little pop OS 2004. Oh, it's beyond time for that now
I was a little spoiled because I got to play with it on the new lemur pro
So I really got to see it in its prime when it's on system 76 hardware
But I think that's worth talking about for a moment
So there's a couple of standout features that I think you guys will probably also echo
But I'd like to just give a little attention to here off the top and that is the new pop shell tiling tool
you heard us talk about it we were the first to interview system 76 and get information out there about it and
Turns out it's totally rad. It's rad and how it's been created to they're using typescript to write this thing
Which means in theory, I think a lot tighter safer JavaScript on the end. Yeah, right
I mean in a nice first-class development experience
Absolutely, and that feature alone is implemented in a really slick way that just makes it worth trying out
even if you just get a the latest version of gnome shell and install this extension, it's it's really neat because it's
Integrated in the top menu. Yeah, click that little sucker and then there's just one button toggle on one button toggle off
Yeah, just says tile windows. And there you go that one simple obvious
Fantastic feature is what makes this a totally actual
Usable feature for me that I will really use because there's certain workflows where I want free-floating windows
And I want control over everything where it's positioned and there's other times where it's just a keyboard day
My hands not coming off the keyboard go ahead and tile it for me. So I've got it right here
I've been using it while we're doing the show and I was using a note-taking application that had a little sub menu that just was
Not playing nicely with tiling super simple to go pop that off get my work done when I'm done with that app pop tiling back
On and I'm set up in show mode that feature alone is worth trying even if you're familiar with tiling window managers and whatnot
It's just fun to see how they implemented that and I think they're gonna just add more to it
It's got absolutely plus you can configure the spacing around the windows and especially with some of the just as a contrast to some
Of the more, you know low-level tiling window managers where you're customizing it in Lua or you know
Something that takes a lot more learning. This is just an easy mouse click away to configure about how you like
Yeah, and you're still a num shell too
So there's that's a lot more appealing to a lot of people other things in there are really nice to have
I feel like 2004 Ubuntu 2004 is just a really great release, but there's still some differentiation there with pop pop shop
I think stands out as
What seems to be maybe another round of thought and pass that went into the default selection of apps?
When I open up pop shop
Literally, probably three out of the five top apps
I have to install immediately to make this a work machine are right there
And then after I have those installed what it replaces them with completes the picture
it's pretty rare and it includes proprietary stuff and open source stuff and
They've really gone all-in on flat packs, but the way it's implemented the user never really has to be concerned with it
You know, honestly so far, you know
We've just been doing just stock 24 and fedora like the pump shop. It's been the best experience by far
No, it doesn't feel slow. There's no random sluggishness things queue up in a very natural way and all the software
You want is right there
Normally I give up and just use that back on the command line
But I didn't have to and just flat hub being installed by default is a nice touch
It makes it a little bit quicker to get running the other thing
I really appreciate that I implement on every desktop environment today except for plasma and gnome
now is they included a pretty great launcher super key plus forward slash and
It launches a quick responsive launcher that is definitely faster than stuff built into gnome
I think I'm probably just gonna stick with gnome at this point
I've built that muscle memory, but that's the kind of little stuff
They're adding that I think really shows you system 76 is thinking a little bit deeper about a particular niche
Jack Wallen has a take that will link in the show notes and in there he writes system 76
Understands that their target audience wants to keep their fingers and hands at the keyboard
Why it's more efficient instead of shifting from the keyboard to the mouse and back again
Things go much more smoothly when you can keep those digits pounding and he's right
You're seeing features like the tiling like the launcher
Not everyone likes that but they're kind of being bold here in a way
They're going particularly add a certain demo of users in an aggressive way that I like to see and I think adds genuine
differentiation between stock Ubuntu and
Long-term I think could potentially be great for main
Ubuntu mainline Ubuntu because they could Sherlock the crap out of this stuff
They can sit here and watch system 76 essentially market test this stuff in a particular niche
That's tolerant to these types of tests and watch what does well
And then just nab that feature and roll it into mainline Ubuntu that's called Sherlocking
Which is a term that's been coined because Apple does that with Mac OS and iOS they watch what independent developers create
They take the most successful ideas and then they just incorporate into their own OS and they make it part of the platform
Canonical has that opportunity here with the innovations that are happening in pop and pop shell etc
They can watch that and say, you know what things like game remote. Maybe we should ship that by default
Yeah, very true. I've also just been impressed with how accessible it is for tiling in general
It doesn't feel like some obscure super user type thing. It's just another way to interface with your desktop
That's a really good way to put it. It doesn't feel like you're all of a sudden becoming an elite hacker. Exactly cheesy
I know you've spent a lot of time with pop. I'd like to hear your thoughts on the 2004 release
I spent a considerable amount of time with it
Been living with it on the ThinkPad now for a couple of weeks to two and a half weeks something like that
Also living with it on the Thalia that I was gifted from system 76. So that upgrade process was painless
Tiling extension the pop shell is great. And I think it's a great
Entry level for someone who doesn't know if they want a tiling window manager doesn't want to necessarily go full i3
Maybe just wants to experience it first all the keyboard shortcuts are sane
And there's nothing just super crazy in the keyboard shortcuts. The terminal is added to your favorites by default. Thank you
Nice, the dot matrix wallpaper is super cool
I love it one of the cool things that I really like about pop and it makes sense to me
Because of the market that they're delivering these machines to is that it's an opt-in
Kind of disk encryption on the installer
You can opt out of it by hitting a checkbox, but by default
Disk encryption is turned on. This is where you need to be people
you need to be encrypting your your drives and obviously if they're selling to
People that are developing equipment for space or whatever that you know
You would want to have that disk encrypted in case that machine was ever lost for some reason a couple things
It didn't really care about and you know, it's just personal preference sort of thing
It doesn't default to detailed view. It's still icon view in
Gnome files. Oh, I hate that. That's where it always goes first right whenever I open up gnome files
There are still a few issues, you know with pop shell and I expected it to be that way if you're resizing windows splitting windows
And those sorts of things you'll run into issues where certain applications don't tile properly
So you'll kind of have to you know mess around with it a little bit to find that happy medium for you
Obviously if you've got a large 4k screen, it does help out with the screen real estate. So you're not crunching down
Gnome files to a you know, super small tile and the you know
Making it basically impossible to navigate through files, but overall it's it's really a solid
Distribution it makes sense that they would
Do what they've done with pop shell
For the for the audience that they're targeting with their hardware
So I think they've done a great job and it's built on top of 2004
Which as you mentioned has been a rock-solid release
So I've been thrilled with it and it's gonna remain on my Thalia and it's gonna remain on my laptop for quite a while
That's the ultimate testament is if you stick with it
And I don't I don't know for me because where pop sort of seems to be
Landing in my spectrum of distros is right where I have Manjaro right now. That makes sense
I think pop has a better out-of-box experience
but in
Three months. I know I'll be happier on Manjaro just because all the little things hooked on rolling and
You know with with an AUR wrapper. You can really just install anything under the Sun. I I
Was spending 10 minutes like a dope over the weekend
Googling for a Cups PPD file for my brother laser printer when it dawned on me that of course
It's in the AUR
Everything's in the AUR and I just installed it and I was ready to go and I got right to printing which was like the first
Time I'd print it in two years. I think you animal
Well, it should be said too that on the other drive in the ThinkPad there is Manjaro
You know, it's like West always says it's not the distro. It's how you use it. I
Do think you're right about the pop out-of-box experience
I was especially impressed with the installation. It just felt super friendly streamlined
Honestly, I think it's like my favorite install experience on any OS so far fair point
It has the best installer the best art. It looks the best it has the most consistent look and feel
You can really tell that they have talented people on their team and they're pointing some of them at this thing and saying or them
And saying make it consistent make it a product and it feels like it much like fedora does
I just in a different kind of branded way, right?
I think we were a little skeptical at first pop was announced like what where's the value add white?
But it's exactly that sort of focusing on it as a product combined with some of their hardware
Yeah, it's there and then lastly I'll just add with the the lemur Pro the most direct experience
I had being benefit that it was a pop OS install on system 76 hardware with the lemur was
The firmware update they needed to issue
Early into the review cycle of the machine that changed the fan curve
That was a very cohesive experience. It felt top-grade
I mean it felt just as good as anything you would experience from any vendor that has been doing this for 15 years already
During the flashing process that came up with a graphical system 76 screen with a console output
It wasn't just like some UEFI output on this on the command line. We had
Jeremy on last week
talking about the the lemur and we kind of briefly
Touched on the the keyboard and a lot of these keyboard shortcuts for pop shell
Kind of play into this new keyboard that they're manufacturing as well
So I'll be interested to see you know
how that all
Turns out and I'm sure I'll be the proud owner of one of those keyboards whenever they do start to ship too
So I think if you you know, if it works for you, it's a great one
I think for me, I'll probably stick on Manjaro
But keep a close eye on what pops doing to now. I really have like just have all the choices
So I'm doing good. We got a feedback in you want to switch to feedback West. It's
It's apropos as they say indeed says hello guys. I was just listening to episode
343 what Linux is best at the pop OS tiling window manager extension chapter made me wonder if you'd come across to paper
WM or paper whim it's a gnome extension that provides a decent tiling window manager experience
I've been using it daily for a few weeks
It works well on pretty much stock Ubuntu 1910 installation in my case and looks like it's under heavy development
Richard also wrote in on gnome and tiling says I just wanted to say that I was listening to the one-click trap episode and you
Mentioned a tiling window manager for gnome shell. I think we've been talking about this
I'm getting the sense. So this is a topic system 76 isn't the only one out there and some of them are really polished such as
paper WM and
Mosaic a new contender enters the ring West mosaic. You should check them out and review the gnome shell extensions
You know when we got these feedback actually did go and install paper WM because why not, you know
You just go clone their repository run the install script and it'll install for you. And yeah, it looks pretty nice
Maybe a little less user friendly than than the pop shell is but if you want perhaps a little more full featured tiling
Definitely worth a try. Ah
So if you are even hardcore on the tiling side of things, but don't want to step away from you know
That's a weird use case. Who is that user? Yeah, I took it. These people are
Richard and Chris are so then we have gammas dot file tool
Which I thought would be a cool one to kind of cap us off today. You ready for this one?
Yeah, if you're like me and use git for version control and sharing your dots you probably have a few things you want to keep
Private nearly everyone has an SSH config and a lot of people here need their mumble.com
Great point. Oh boy
We just always delete it but that's not the right
It's not which is one of the reasons it has your private cert in there
Which was what all of the permissions for mumble once you've been verified and like voice or you know
A mic check and all of that your certificate says you're good and then when you delete that config you lose that
He uses get crypt it uses gets filter attribute to encrypt
Transparently so you can host all of your dot files in one public repo without worrying about people stealing your sensitive data
if someone checks out the repo the encrypted files are simply checked out and
Encrypted unless they have the key and the git crypt unlock and then git crypt unlock the repo
Do you have you looked at this? No, you know, I've seen it floating around there
But I've never actually used it in any of my workflows and it does seem like a nice way to do it
You know if you don't have ways to separate that stuff fully out there or you have to compose them together when you you know
Reinstall stuff just leave it right there and then get handle it
I wonder if I was going to use get say to back up my configs and my dot files
I think that might be where I drew the line and just did a little self hosted git lab and
And I suppose I'd still care about security, but I just don't know if I want to put that stuff on a public
Yeah, I suppose it depends on the line two of which configs do you need secrets in and which do you really feel value and sharing?
You know if you've got a lot of
Customizations or nice hacks to your VM RC that you want to share with folks out there
Versus something maybe like mumble comp where it really is just one of your personal details
I think if I was doing a general dot file backup like that
I would be concerned that eventually something would end up in there sort of like we started the show with that
Installer error that wrote by mistake the encryption password in plain text like you just sometimes it's easy to have happened to even experienced users
You don't know what's going in there like sometimes applications. Just put something dumb in there
I think I'd want it encrypted, too
So I think this is a great a great tip by a gamma so gamma
Thank you for saying that along and again
It's git crypt this seems like another opportunity for folks to give some feedback to us to you know
This is a common problem if you're not using git crypt. What are you using? Yeah?
How are you doing this and is it necessary to use git for this or would our sync?
Just do the job and to like say a sync thing directory is that crazy
That just seems like maybe a simpler approach
Yeah, I mean, I think there's a forget users folks who already work with git every day
There is sort of a you know when you have this hammer
Then probably what you just said is it because I probably use our sync more than I use git right and git has you know
Versioning baked into it right yeah, that seems like the big advantage
Yeah, for sure interesting Linux unplug calm slash contact for how you do it or anything else
We've talked about recently that you'd like to chime in on including any questions you have for that XPS 13 that vessel
Oh, please do let me know yeah, putting it through the ringer probably another way to let you know is on Twitter
Yeah, that's right at Westpain, and I'm at Chris las you can go check me out over there
Let me know what's up check out my website Chris last calm. That's happening, too. I don't know maybe there's something going on
There you didn't know about I don't know there's only one way to find out. I'm not the boss of you not yet
That's right. That's right
Well congratulations again to you sir. Thank you. I am looking forward to hearing your takes on that XPS 13 as well as more feedback
I love doing that so please get all that sent in we have links to just about every dang thing
We talked about today at Linux unplug calm slash
353 that's this episode and of course I encourage you to subscribe at Linux unplug calm slash subscribe
Where we have a feed for every type of variety and player out there as well as just a straight-up RSS feed
It's new. I think you're really gonna like it check it out Linux unplug calm subscribe. There's only a little bit of XML
I
Thought it was gonna be an Oprah moment there whenever you let Wes unbox the XPS
I thought you're gonna be like, you know, you get a laptop you get a laptop, you know
If I could afford I'd get him a laptop
But now the West's you know, I think the rule goes Jesus whoever has the new gig buys the laptops, right?
I think that is how it works, right? I think he owes us all lunch and around the laptops. So I'll be taking orders