Google box. And it's basically cameras pointing at people in
the lounge watching the TV. So you watch people watching TV is
quite entertaining, mindless bullshit TV. But it's, it's the
characters. It's like people sat around in their lounge watching
some TV program, and the way they react to it. It's, it's
crap. But I love it.
John Greenewald People, wait a minute, you're watching people
watching TV?
Jason Valee Yeah, they know they're being watched. They're
they're, they're
John Greenewald Are they at home? Are they and they have
like webcams?
Jason Valee They're in their homes. No, it's proper cameras.
John Greenewald Where do I see this? Where do I see this?
Jason Valee You can probably find it on the YouTube.
John Greenewald Tell me what it's called. Tell me what it's
called.
Jason Valee Google, Google.
Jason Valee This thing called the internet, Chris, everything's
on the internet.
Jason Valee Oh my god, it's not it's not that good. You don't
need to go and find it. It's on channel four in the UK.
John Greenewald I feel like I need to find it.
Jason Valee Google box. Yeah. So anyway, um,
John Greenewald Oh my gosh.
Jason Valee You just reminded me that these two old ladies were
sat there. And they were using a Remington fuzz away just last
week to get all the bubbles on a jumper. Thanks. Was was the
innovation, technological technological innovation of 1986
that thing? It was and then one of them was going to get all the
bubbles off. And the other one was like, Oh, in that marvelous
John Greenewald series 11. Episode nine is literally a
couple of old ladies sitting around watching Britain's Got
Talent antique roadshow, the Queen's Green Planet, buy it
now, and Yorkshire vet. And so you're watching these old ladies
watch those shows.
Jason Valee It's not just those two ladies between lots of
different families. There's like big families, there's an Asian
family, there's a group who live up north. And so there's all
different accents in there and different like characters. And
maybe they're there's a there's a woman and her best mate who
live in a caravan like a mobile home somewhere. And those two
sitting next to each other quite is just quite entertaining the
kind of characters.
John Greenewald If anybody ever wondered if there was a market
for people watching people play video games, this shows you
they're totally if there's people. Can you hear the TV
show? Can you hear what they're watching? Or do you just cut to
they cut to it. So you know what they're watching you get the
clips of whatever it is they're watching and then it cuts to
them. Okay, as if you're cutting to the audience of a TV. So
you're watching the reaction. I see. I can't I can't believe I've
outed myself as watching this program because you'll never
live it down. Not for a day. Brilliant. I love it. My guilty
pleasure. Good. Oh, wow. I can hear the guilt just peeling off
you. Goggles box. Well, guess what I'm adding to use that I
just I gotta see it. I just gotta see it.
And it's and it's actually current because they record them
like that weekend. And so it's about the programs that you will
have watched the previous week. Oh, that is handy. Yeah. This is
Linux Unplugged episode 247 for May 1 2018. Welcome to Linux
Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's still smack dab in
the middle of the Linux fest hangover. My name is Chris. My
name is Wes. Hello, Mr. Payne. Hello there. Are you well fed,
sir? Oh, I am stuffed. Yeah, I I supplied the burgers and West
supplied the caffeine. So this should be a good show coming up
on this week's episode. Not one but two, two major distribution
releases for door 28 is out today. Ubuntu 1804 came out just
the other day. And we're going to give you our initial
impressions on both of them loaded them up kick the tires.
And man is there some cool stuff in both of them. I cannot wait
to tell you about that. So it's a packed distro episode. Plus,
Mr. Daniel foray is here from elementary OS to give us a
little taste of what's just around the corner in Juneau. And
some of those features speak deep to my soul. You guys will
totally understand once we get there. And then later on, did
you hear that Google just forked a popular GTK theme? What?
And you know how NFS tables is the new hotness to replace IP
tables? Yep, that's out something news coming in. And
the one the only Mr. Alan Jude will stop by the show live from
Linux fest Northwest and tell us all about BP F plus a new
release of dark tables out and listener Brent stopping by the
show to give us a walkthrough of that. And then we will do our
Ubuntu 1804 roundup with a look at the flavors, the new features
in Ubuntu itself, our thoughts on some of the server stuff
they're introducing and much, much more. But before I go any
further, before I even get to the virtual log, a special in
studio log member, Mr. Brent, the very, very, we're gonna call
him dark table expert now for the show is actually joining us
right now. Hello, Brent. Hey, how's it going, guys? It's
going good. How are you doing? I'm doing good. Barbecue is
good. A couple of nights on the couch. Good here at the studio
Brent stopped by for Linux fest Northwest took some great
pictures. He's been talking to me about dark table. We've got a
new release of dark table to to sort of button it all up. So
we'll be getting to that a little bit in the show. So stay
tuned for that. And now, without any further ado, we got to
bring in that virtual log time appropriate greetings, Mumble
Room. Hello. I heard that random UbiKon. I heard that. Yeah,
actually, that looked like an amazing venue Wimpy. I saw your
mate roundup of the new features and it looked like you're in a
church of Ubuntu. It was impressive. We were in an
historic building and it was rather wonderful. Yeah. Well, I
would love to chat about that in a moment. So let's get there
too. But why don't we start out with the huge news of the day
just to get things rolling here on the old podcast. And that is
the release of Fedora 28 Fedora 28 landed today as we record and
it's available as an atomic workstation image too. Yes, it
is, which is the first time that's officially happening.
It's not all out. They haven't really talked about it a lot
yet. But if you go on the atomic development list, which I troll
all the time every damn day, and you'll see that they have a
release announcement over there, which is a pretty freaking big
deal. But let's talk about the workstation version. I can't
believe I'm about to tell you this. Let me double check. Is
this? Is this actually fedora? It's real. You sure? Oh, yeah,
100%. Sure. Okay, verified. Well, a new feature,
apparently, I don't believe it a fedora 28 is the inclusion of
popular third party software repositories that you can just
turn on in gnome 328. They include applications. Nvidia
proprietary graphics driver, Google Chrome, the steam client.
Yes, and more like a pie charm are now all available with just
a few clicks in gnome software under fedora 28. That's what I
did not think I would see this day. But hey, this is this
isn't anything I just I can't even right now I'm still
processing this. And I think what it's got to be is fedora
trying to appeal to developers who use these tools. That's got
to be what it is. I don't know anybody in the Mamba room want
to before we move on to the other features want to just take
a moment and reflect on the fact that fedora is making it a
couple clicks now to install Google Chrome or the Nvidia
driver. Anybody think that's remarkable besides me? That's I
mean, I think it's definitely a change from you know, the
behavior we've seen in the past, but it's probably can't be the
only one somebody in that mom rooms got to think that's
remarkable. Somebody does they just don't want to say I
understand. It's remarkable. There you go. Isn't this
something that Ubuntu mate has done for a while? Oh, sure.
They're definitely by no means the first. Absolutely. I just
they're doing it would be the very, very last mini Mac. Did
you want to throw something in there? Yeah, I tried to install
Chrome into chromium browser last time and it told me that
it needed 600 megabytes to install all the packages. I was
pretty much surprised. So I kind of test how much the normal
Google Chrome uses. This is going to be something I'll be
testing to. I'll be testing all of this a lot more soon, but I
want to take a spoiler alert. I'm going to round up some of
the new features and new things people are talking about what
initially seems really great to me. I'm not giving you my
review for either Ubuntu 1804 or Fedora 28 yet. I've got
initial impressions. I'm going to share those with you, but I
want to run both of these for a while because I have been
living in Kubuntu so deeply that I just need to take time to
give them a proper quote unquote review, but I'll give you
something else in Fedora 28 that seems initially pretty
appealing to me. They've really sort of tuned down some of the
things that suck battery life with various different hardware
power saving features that they're turning on by default.
Now, these are all things that scripts will turn on or some
people, other distributions turn on automatically, but I think
in totality, this is actually pretty impressive. So we now
have a new default saddling power management policy on all
the Intel mobile chip sets that is way more disk friendly low
power. So like when it's idle, it'll save approximately one to
one and a half watts of power on idle, which when you have like
a 50 watt battery or a 36 watt battery, I will take anything I
can get. Additionally, the Intel in HDA audio codec power saving
is now enabled by default with a one second timeout, which I
think that's pretty pretty good. One second means if there's
nothing going out over the sound card for over a second, if you
think about it, that's a pretty long time in computer land. And
then that saves about point four watts of power on idle. Now
finally, USB auto suspend for USB Bluetooth receivers has been
enabled by default, which saves an additional point four watts
of power. You combine all that together and it's pretty
noteworthy. And again, not the only distro to do it, but I
think it's pretty nice to see Fedora including this stuff by
default. I think everybody would agree with that. And then of
course, the headline feature, the biggest deal is that it's
shipping with GNOME 3.28, which includes the new Thunderbolt
Bolt D support, which is that system daemon for security
connecting for the security of Thunderbolt devices when they
connect and allows gnome shell to interact and alert you about
that. And then finally, for RMS sake, they're including virtual
box guest additions by default now, and they're shipped in the
Fedora workstation install. Any installation of Fedora
workstation as a guest on virtual box will have the guest
edition features working out of the box.
I think that really that just plays to your case that this is
these are the developer aimed improvements, right? But nice.
I mean, really, really, really nice. I will say they have a
little blurb in here about the streamed on installation. I was
skeptical. I've been something of an Anaconda hater in the
past, but it's better. It's getting better. I'm glad to see
it. Yeah, it's pretty painless.
Yeah, it was I went through an installation on a laptop earlier
today, and I let it do the auto disk partitioning for the first
time. And it you know, it uses LVM and it makes some it makes
some sane judgments. And the other thing I've noticed is I
feel like it's faster now to when it's actually throwing
files on the disk. I agree. Yeah. Did you like it felt like
it was already copying files before? Well, part of it is
because it does like a post install to where it runs you
through creating the wizard for users, and like setting a few
other small details about the system. So it takes that out of
the installation process. So you're really in the
installation, you're setting your disk configuration, you're
adding a user account, and you're setting your time zone.
And then there's final details that'll ask you after the system
boots. And in fact, you don't even have to add a user account
necessarily. Oh, that's perfect. Yeah. And you just get to you
get to blasting files on the system. It's, it's a really,
it's a really good version of Fedora 28. And since Ubuntu is
shipping the same version of Gnome, I'll just say this now.
And maybe if anybody in the Mumble Room wants to chime in
with their thoughts. This is by far the best version of Gnome
I've ever used. It is cleaner, simpler, and more efficient than
macOS. I think it is if Apple were to have to hit the reset
button today. If macOS wasn't nearly a 14 year old operating
system, but say it was nine months old. I really think this
is, this is what they would have as a goal. The new system
settings is just it's so good. Like the Adaptia theme now is
good. Ubuntu's theme is, it feels a little old to me. But in
actuality, Gnome still looks great. It still looks good. So
it's such a good version of Gnome. It's not one that's
pulling me back to Gnome. But if you are a Gnome user, Gnome
328 really nails it. And of course Fedora's always got a
great implementation. Does anybody in the Mumble Room have
any thoughts on the Gnome aspect, either for Ubuntu or
Fedora?
So this begs the question, has it crashed for you yet?
Well, I've only used it a little bit. You know, I've only, I
have not, and I'm not using it in production. I don't have any
intention to. So I'll see, you know, in the review after I've
used it for a couple of weeks, we'll see. At least get a week
into it. But if you are a Gnome fan, it definitely feels pretty
fast. You know, it always feels good on a clean install, but it
just is so great. It's definitely worth it.
I really appreciate that. Because you know, when I'm
running Gnome on Arch or something else, I'm really fine
with Gnome defaults. I don't do a ton of tuning to it. They do
a little bit more than even I'm willing to do on most
installations. So it's just pleasant.
Yeah, and Gnome Photos also is now the default in Fedora 28.
That's finally coming along. It's been a long time coming.
Just small things, lots of small things in there. Check it
out. We'll have links in the show notes if you guys would
like. But last chance if you, if you guys out there have any
thoughts before I get to my review, let me know. Go to
linuxunplug.com slash contact and send them in your thoughts
and I'll let or something like should try on Fedora. Because
since it's not my daily driver, love to know. Also, linuxunplug.com
slash contact. Last chance to get in before the review comes.
Because I, you know, always be down for trying something or
your experiences. Also really good. Yeah. I'll share an
experience with you, Wes. How about that?
Please do.
linux.ting.com
Linux.ting.com. It's mobile. It's better than unlimited. If
you just use less, you pay less. You don't have to pay for a
whole bunch of minutes or a ton of SMS messages. I don't, I
don't know if I used a single SMS message last month. I don't
actually think I did. The only thing I might have done to
trigger an SMS message would be to log into a Twitter account
from like a new installation. And then it does like that SMS
verify thing that I hate so much. That might have been it.
And I could, there's other ways to get to that. So why pay for
messages? There's no need. There's no reason. I don't even
need 100 messages, let alone 1000 or whatever. It's not 2001
anymore. Yeah, it's not. It's not. And you've got Wi Fi at
work. So why are you paying for data when you're not using it?
Or if you got Wi Fi at home, it doesn't make any sense. And you
might have better signal on GSM networks in your area or maybe
on CDMA. So why can't you choose? See, that's all just
normal with Ting. You, you pick and choose what works best for
you. There's no contract, there's no determination fee.
It's really mobile the way it should be. If the whole market
had to start over today, this is what they would have to do. I
get messages all the time from people outside the country.
They're like, you know, that's how it kind of works here.
That's how, you know, the way Ting works. That's kind of how
it works here. And I'm like, yeah, that's not how it works
here in the States. And that's what makes Ting so great. It's
pay for what you use, six minutes for the line. And then
just whatever you use, minutes, messages and megabytes, boom,
you're done. You don't want it. You don't want the phone
anymore. You turn it off. You're done. You want to bring over a
new phone, you can activate the whole freaking thing through
their webpage. They got a BYOD page where you can double check
everything. You put in the ESIN or whatever it is through the
website, boom, activate, you're done. You never even had to talk
to a human being. But here's the crazy thing. If you need to,
they've got really nice ones. Friendly support people that
are actually phone geeks. Crazy concept. Control panel to manage
everything and then great support to back it up. You can
buy a device directly. It's not loaded with like the Ting
experience. They're not going to prevent updates because they
need to get their new Ting video store on your phone. They
don't do any of that stuff. You just want to use them for simple
services or you want to use them as your main internet
connection. Ting don't care. And you can get started at
linux.ting.com. Take $25 off a device or get $25 in service
credit if you bring one. That's linux.ting.com. And a big thank
you to Ting for sponsoring this here program, linux.ting.com.
Now, did you hear the story that we covered in Linux Action News
this week? Google has just forked a popular GTK theme. And
what are they doing? What are they doing?
I really want to know.
It's like Adaptia, but it's Googlified, paperized and
blued. And it's a new GTK theme that's got a material design
and it looks pretty good. It's called Cross Adaptia right now
and it's up on Google's Codehub. And commits show that their
designers are already busy making changes and adjustments
to the theme. And it looks like it's something that'll be used
on Chrome OS as part of their new Linux application
containers, which starts to suggest that we're not just
going to be seeing a terminal for SSH, but perhaps the
ability to run things like Eclipse or other GTK
applications inside Chrome OS. And you got to figure Google's
designing this for end users if they're going in to the trouble
of creating their own theme that looks like other Google
properties.
This is a lot of specific work for something else, right? It's
not just a whim. There's people being paid to work on this.
So why does Chrome OS have its own theme now, Wes? What do you
think's going on here? We're gonna start seeing Linux desktop
apps on Chrome OS?
I'm kind of concerned. I'm kind of excited. What does it do to
their, you know, their sort of mantra of these are like simple
machines that you, you know, can't mess up that aren't
complicated for people to use. I know they're implemented, you
know, with containers and other technologies to sort of keep
things isolated and controlled, but it's still, it might seem
like a different sell to, you know, a simple user.
Yeah, yeah, I wonder if it's not just, it could just be about
adding additional value to Chromebooks to make them more
appealing to businesses or system administrators and
developers could totally be all of that. But I do also have some
conspiracy bacon.
Fry it up, fry it up for me.
We do have, we've been eating a lot of meat these last few days
here at the studio. So why not fry up a little bacon and I'll
tell you what I think it is. And I hope I hope I'm wrong. But I
think Fuchsia OS is going to replace the underpinnings of
Android as the core operating system. They're going to boot
Linux out of Android and it could be semi devastating for
Linux. I'm not the only person that thinks this obviously, but
some people I really respect recently have been talking more
and more about it. And it seems like Fuchsia OS could be the
perfect little wedge to get Linux out to take care, to just
get rid of all of that pain in the arse LTS issue, pain in the
arse GPL stuff, have their own OS in there that's been
purpose-built to power mobile devices. And they essentially
would dump Linux for their Android platform. And at the
same time, double down on Linux on the Chrome OS platform. So
Chrome OS will stay Linux, Chrome OS will have the ability
to run Linux applications. Chrome OS will have the ability
to run the terminal. You know, you'll have complete Linux
environments in these containers. They may even go the
direction of Windows 10 and start offering different distro
environments that are similar to like the Windows subsystem
where you can pull down Ubuntu or you can pull down SUSE.
They're going to have probably, you know, the same thing, CentOS,
Ubuntu containers, maybe not initially.
Right. This has reminded me also kind of got like a like a Mac
feel. They've got their separate phone controlled
environment and then maybe something a little more
developer, power user friendly on the desktop.
Yeah. Yeah. You could see how that would be appealing to them,
right? And I don't know about that because I feel like if
Android switched away from Linux, Linux development could
lose quite a bit of momentum. But it does seem like this was
this is where this is going. Anybody in the Mumble Room have
any thoughts on my bacon?
Well, we're just about a week away from Google I know. So we
could hear some stuff next week.
Yep. Yeah, we may have answers sooner than later. I'm planning
to cover bits of IO that are interesting in Tech Talk today.
And I'll probably if there's anything very Linux specific,
I'll cover here in this show. Well, regardless of my bacon
and regardless of Android, I think this is great for Chrome
OS, because it means more desktop Linux apps in way, way
more users hands at a lower point of entry for cost. And in
some cases, like my kids, they get these books via school, the
Chromebooks, they just boom, here you go, here kid, here's a
here's an entire laptop with the Google Chrome browser on it
have at it.
That makes me a lot more excited, right? There's a
terminal there they can actually play with and learn from.
That's great.
I think you are a session everybody now is paying for
laptops that are made to seduce for selling services, not for
you to own them.
That's a fair point. Yeah, their goal here is to get more people
locked into Google services. And they're going to use Linux apps
as the way to sweeten that pot.
That makes me feel horrible now. Not even that, not even not
even just the Google services is the apps will be services.
Yeah, and I see what you're saying too, because in real,
realistically, you may have to have like, certain Google
account to get these things or you may be controlled through
the admin control panel of the community or the industry of
the business administrator. So yeah, okay. Well, I want to
change topics now, because that's really that's the
question. Yeah. We had an interesting chat at Linux fest
Northwest with one Mr. Alan Jude about BPF. Now you may have
heard and there's an article that I'll link to that was
posted just a couple of days ago, why is the kernel
community replacing IB tables with BPF? And this is a pretty
complicated little system that will be living inside the
kernel. There's a great talk that just came out recently that
really explains that this is essentially an entire virtual
machine that will be running inside the Linux kernel. Now I
know that sounds like a really bad idea. But there's other
virtual machines that already exist that we just don't really
talk about very much. It's, it's already happened that damage
has been done. This will be one of many and they really on the
right track. They look like they're securing this thing
well. And Jed, Wes and Alan Jude were sitting down at the
booth at Linux fest Northwest. And the topic came up and I
thought it'd be great to get the clarification on what BPF is
right here on the show. Successor to IP tables is NF
tables, right? Okay. So there's a successor to that now too. I
was reading a little bit about that. Yeah. Is that EBF
tables? EBPF is the tracing framework. I think this is just
a BPF based firewall thing. So do you know what BPF stands
for? Berkeley packet filter. So, you know, you're like, oh,
look, if we compile the firewall rules down to a BPF, we can
match them fast. Like TCP dump does. You know what firewalls
been doing that for 20 years? Yeah. It turns out there's a
fast way to do a firewall. It's because, oh, look, this machine
language is specifically designed to match packets is
really good at matching packets. Yeah, totally. Well,
writing the writing rules can be difficult. Just the syntax
between TCP dump and Wireshark, they don't use the same syntax
and I find it continually confusing. I'll jump from one to
the other. I have to go back to the web page and look up more
examples because I can't remember them all. Yeah. Back in
school, for our firewall class, we learned three firewalls, IP
tables, IPF, which is the predecessor to PF on FreeBSD and
OpenBSD, and Cisco PIC. The Cisco we had was literally like a
486 based appliance. Like the old one. Before they made it a
dedicated, it was like a regular 486 with some firewall cards in
it or something. But the Cisco PIC, that's been dead for a
decade. Or it should have been. Yes. So it was pretty much dead
when we were learning it. But the syntax is pretty similar to
what you would get on a newer Cisco like an ASA or whatever.
Even ASAs are out of fashion. In particular, we had one client
who was doing some streaming video. It was TV Ontario had
this system called Homework Help, where after school, they
would pay some teachers to be available via like an internet
chat thing to help you with your math homework. And every
student in like grade 7 through 10 got it for free if they were
enrolled in a public school. But they would have a streaming
video part, too. And they were pushing up to like 600 megabits
out of the network. And their Cisco ASA couldn't handle that.
Couldn't keep up. Yeah. So we replaced that with, we turned
their dev server into a PF sense. And now we can push a gigabit
with no problem. Yeah, that's Alan's way of saying it's
because of performance. It's because you can compile it down
to this machine language and the rules can be executed wicked
fast. He goes into some bottleneck troubleshooting that
he did for a 40 gigabit. I think it was actually two. So it was
in total 80 gigabits worth of transfer bottleneck
troubleshooting he did on a free BSD system in this week's
episode of tech snap. Yeah, go check that out. Yeah, tech snap
dot systems. But BPF is coming IP tables is out. And speaking
of other things that are just coming down the pipe, not too
far away is the next version of elementary OS. And I am getting
a little hyped. I got to be honest and not might be because
Mr. Daniel for a keep stopping by and tell me about all the
great stuff. And this one speaks to me, Dan, deeply, deeply
speaks to me. I love this stuff in the new update you guys
posted about notifications. And I didn't realize how much
frickin work you guys have put into it, like the heuristics
that you had in place. But now we're coming out. Can you kind
of recap what's going on here? Yeah, so kind of historically,
what happened was last cycle, we introduced this notifications
indicator, right? So that when an app sends a notification, and
you miss it, the notifications indicator will catch it and you
can review it later, same as you have on like notifications that
are on your phone. The problem is that only some applications
are actually sending their ID with the notification. So some
notifications come through, we didn't really know which app
it's from. So we had this heuristic in place to try to
guess. And it sometimes was wrong. And so we get people
saying, hey, you're a notification, notifications
indicators broken, it doesn't work, it, you know, it does it
wrong. And we're saying, well, you know, the problem was that
these applications never sent an ID. And so it was kind of hard
to say, you know, hey, this is not really our fault. While we
still had this heuristic it. So now we're pulling the heuristic
out. And any application that doesn't send its ID is just
going to be categorized as other. But at the same time, we
went and we submitted patches upstream to electron into
Firefox and into lib notify to make sure that application
developers had an easy way to make sure their applications are
reporting their ID correctly and didn't have to use like the raw
D bus API. And I would imagine electron apps are probably the
most frequent offender of this missing ID. Yeah. And the
electron patch has actually been committed upstream as well.
Oh, great. Yeah, that's hopefully that that'll fix it
for all electron apps. And this isn't just specific to
elementary OS and Pantheon. This is actually how I did
notifications identifying gnome shell as well. Oh, that's
awesome. So that'll be great for gnome users. Everybody wins.
Now, what's the lib notify part for time? It sounds like it's
involved with notifications. But what specifically is lib
notify responsible for? So we have a problem because way back
in the day, there was a specification proposed that was
the free desktop notification specification. But it only kind
of lived on the gnome wiki. And it was kind of adopted de facto
by a bunch of different desktops, but it never really
made it into free desktop. And lib notify kind of represents
that spec. Well, gnome added G notification to their stack. And
this is kind of a new version of the spec. But it is not really
compatible with the old lib notify version. And all of the
gnome apps use G notification. And so it's like different
libraries that kind of do the same thing, but don't all kind
of respect each other. So there's a bigger story. And
we're trying to work closer with upstreams to make sure that we
all kind of agree, like, what should the spec be? And what
should it support and try to make sure that things work good
across desktops. But this is kind of a first step, right on.
And also just honorable mention here, files is looking so good.
And it sounds like so clean. Yeah, look at that. I mean,
beautiful. We're looking at a picture of it here in the
studio. We'll have a link at linuxonplug.com slash 247. If
you guys want to read dancehall post and see the picture of it.
It is great looking, Dan. And I gotta say, it sounds like a lot
of the back end is sort of getting retooled to match the
more modern development processes on elementary OS.
Yeah, absolutely. I think that some people might know that
files is our oldest app. And we started way back in the very
beginning with a Nautilus fork. And then we eventually kind of
outgrew that and then wrote this file manager Marlin in the
modern day elementary files comes from that background. So
it was a C app. It was before we adopted Vala. So we're kind of
still migrating that code base. And this cycle, we were able to
do way more of that and a lot of cleanup and migrating to better
versions of utilities from upstream libraries like GTK and
GIO instead of using our own internal libraries. So that's,
you know, performance improvements, stability
improvements, more maintainable code, it's just getting way
better all around.
That does sound really good. Well, I will definitely kick the
tires when it comes to any other honorable mentions you want to
toss out from the post before we leave the rest to the listener
at home to read.
One thing actually I'm really excited about is improvements
going into elementary code. Oh, yeah. And, and we, so we landed
support for editor config by default in elementary code last
month. And this month, we have it turned on and enabled out of
the box. And now the guys over at elementary code drew a nice
little icon for us somewhere on their homepage. Now,
that looks so good. We're seeing, we're seeing some steady
updates to code this cycle. Like this has gotten a lot of
attention.
Yeah, I'm pretty excited about it. We're definitely trying to
get more feedback from developers about the tooling on
our platform and documentation and find out like how we can
meet their needs and make it really easy to write
applications for App Center and elementary OS.
I love the focus, you know, there's so much focus on on
application developers, you're actually curating this really
great environment for people to do that. So all these
improvements, people are just going to be happier to be
there.
That's how we got up to 87 new.
87. That is really good. That's that's gonna be a that'll be a
strong amount in the App Center when Juno releases. That's
really cool. Yeah, how how close are we getting to a beta
release here? Because I know there's just what under 10 bugs
left to get squashed.
We are so super close. So we're kind of we're kind of looking at
like if we can maybe punt a couple of those issues to the
second beta so we can get a public beta out sooner and like
what are the kind of the other release tasks we have to do with
the website and things like that. So I'm trying to get it
pushed out ASAP and I'm working with our teams to make that
happen. But as it stands right now, we just have the seven
issues left on our tracker.
Seven. Okay, I'm excited. That's I like that that's it's not a
date. It's it's when the issues are closed or when the issues
can be at least punted to the next beta. That's great. Well,
Dan, keep us posted because it's it's a fascinating case
study to watch this for the show. And it's it's fun to see
how you guys work the thought you put into all of this how it
all is kind of been coming together over the last year. And
we're so close now that you got to keep us posted because we're
almost to the goal, which is the release. All right. Well, we
have much much more to talk about as the show goes on. I'm
really looking forward to covering some important news and
and and then talking a little dark table because this is I
think going to be one of my new tools in my bag. But before we
get there, I got to mention the tool that I've had for years
now. And that's the tools over DigitalOcean. And you can be one
to do dot co wait, hold on. Let me get that prop out. Sorry,
Russell. There we go. Oh, yeah, it's so fresh. It's not to
really know. I've done a lot of wrestling at do dot co slash
unplug to go there to get a $100 credit when you sign up with
a new account. Yeah, I said $100. Yeah, I know we usually
say $10. I said $100. And with the three cents an hour, my
favorite rig. I mean, you're going to go nuts. Do dot co
slash unplug DigitalOcean is simple infrastructure that you
can deploy and use it in production, use it for testing,
use it for learning in less than 55 seconds. And everything
is SSDs. Every single machine, they have 12 data centers
around the world. They got 40 gigabit connections coming into
those hypervisors. The whole stack runs Linux KVM for the
virtualizer that they put an amazing interface that no one
else in the industry can touch on top of all of it. They call
it the dashboard. It's a dashboard for days. And then to
make things better, they've got an API that's well documented,
clear, easy to read. And I'm pretty sure that dashboard is a
client of that API, because everything the dashboard
supports, you can do in the API. That's great, because that
means there's a ton of open source code that's already
written that you can take advantage of good to go just
have added Haas or build something yourself from the
ground up do.co slash unplugged, but it gets even
better. Even now, what is 1804 been out, but just just a few
days. They are rapidly updating their documentation. I just
today read a guide on how to configure Apache with this with
an SSL cert on 1804 in just a few minutes. Easy to read,
clear documentation. They're updating everything for the new
releases. You can spin up whichever version of Linux you
like, or you can even deploy that free BSD. I know, I know.
And they also recently announced flexible droplets
where you can mix and match the different things that you
need. So maybe you need a lot of CPU for your application,
more CPU. You don't need much disk. Yeah, just put it all in
CPU. Or you want a ton of disk because you're doing some
logging and you don't need a ton of RAM or CPU or whatever
you need, you mix and match flexible droplets $15 a month
with that $100 credit, you can get pretty far. Just go to
do.co.plugged. That's do.co.plugged. And a big
thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Unplugged
program. Random excessive paper flopping and oops, just tore a
little more. Look at that. I don't know how much longer
that's holding up. Do.co.plugged. I think once that
paper is ripped, they're going to end the $100 deal. I think
that's because you better go soon. Okay, let's just talk
about a little serious news before we get to the dark table
stuff because this is just a heads up. If you are a void
Linux user, you need to be paying really close attention
to a situation that's been going on for a while and isn't
really moving anywhere and you could end up getting
misinformation. So I want you to just kind of track this in
the show. We'll keep links in the show notes. I may even try
to retroactively update the show notes for 247 down the road
if anything changes. So linuxunplugged.com slash 247 for
those, but right now the void Linux maintainers have lost
contact with the guy that used to be the head manager of
void. I don't know how to put this. It's really awkward.
Basically, the project leader has disappeared and they have
no contact with him since the end of January. They've had no
meaningful contact really for over a year with him and he's
he's got you know the keys to several things like the GitHub
page, the IRCs, the domains. They've tried to contact
GitHub and GitHub told them to go f a duck that they
weren't interested in this dramatic situation. They've
contacted free note support, but they really haven't gotten
very far with that yet and they've gotten partial control
over voidlinux.com, but they don't have control over the one
that people use the most, which is voidlinux.eu, which is the
one they really want and they're in limbo. They say
trying to get back on track and they don't see any possibility
of regaining access to the GitHub organization. So they're
gonna have to move to a new GitHub organization. They feel
like it may be the same for domains and for the IRC
channels, they're still trying to get in contact with free
note. Now this has been going on since January and I didn't
really know what to what to do with this because I thought is
somebody sick is somebody you know are they missing. I didn't
know what was going on with the project leader, but I've heard
from a few folks who say that they just kind of went AWOL and
that it might be like he's fine health wise, but no longer
interested in doing the project or something like that.
You know, and isn't this always the concern about these mom
and pop small distros?
Yeah, absolutely. I think, you know, and if you're going to
make it, if you're going to involve the community and you're
going to have other people that feel responsible for the
project, then it's probably essential to set up some sort
of minimal governance process or at least, you know, make it
so that one one bus accident can't take out the whole
project.
Yeah, and you don't want to undermine the Linux community's
faith in small distros because if nobody's going to be willing
to give a small distro a try, they'll never become a big
distro. And then we have a chicken and the egg problem.
And the only solution I really see for this is something
similar to Canonical's Ubuntu Flavors, where, you know, you
kind of you kind of graduate into an official member of the
Ubuntu community.
And, you know, there's some governance.
I believe you have to hear, too.
Obviously, Wimpy or Popi could speak much more coherently to
this.
And, you know, there's at least some assurance of a structure
as an end user.
Like, it feels like some some test must have been passed.
Maybe, Wimpy, why don't you start with you have so much
experience with MATE.
Is my read on that right?
Like, is that is there some sort of assurance?
If it's becoming of an official flavor that it's not just going
to go away one day?
Yeah.
So the first thing is, in order to become an official flavor
of Ubuntu, you have to demonstrate that you have some
sort of long term maintainership of the packages that are
specific to the flavor that you want to create.
So in the case of Ubuntu MATE, back in the day, I had to
demonstrate that I had been maintaining those packages in
Debian for six months before we were granted flavor status.
And that's for the flavor itself.
Following that, then you can become an Ubuntu member, which
also is a demonstration of a long term commitment to the
Ubuntu project.
And that buys you some additional rights within the
Ubuntu project, such as voting powers for the councils and
what have you.
So there is some process there to ensure that people coming
into the project have already got a track record of being
long term contributors to the thing that they want to work
on.
OK, that makes sense.
So I want to bounce around here a bit.
I want to go to Dan.
He has a point about open governance, and then I want to
go to Eric after that.
So Dan, why don't you bring up your point about open
governance, and not just even for open source, but just
in general?
Yeah, there's a point that was made earlier about bus factor,
right?
And so it's not just necessarily if someone
voluntarily steps down, but you never know what's going to
happen in their life.
But I remember there's a thing in the canonical code of
conduct or Ubuntu code of conduct about gracefully
stepping down, right?
And I think everybody should kind of have this idea built
into their governance of what happens when someone needs
to step down.
Yeah, OK.
And Eric, you've had some familiar you've had some
experience with this with Ubuntu Studio recently.
That's correct.
It's been a whirlwind.
Basically, what's happened is set Hallstrom.
He's the project leader for Ubuntu Studio.
He just completely ran out of physical time in his life to be
able to be dedicated to the project.
So about six months ago, they were kicking around the idea of
making an Ubuntu Studio Council.
Well, there were a handful of people that got into it, but
nothing really ever came of it.
So in February, they reassessed and said, hey, we want to try
to make this go forward.
But nobody was really stepping up.
So I finally like, hey, I'll step up.
I'll join the council.
I'll help to lead this thing.
I became the council chair since I was the one running
the meetings already.
And then Ross Gammon, who is the release manager, he had to
step out due to timing reasons as well.
So then I stepped in to be the release manager.
So it's been a real whirlwind.
But this is one of those things where if you can open it up
to like a council type idea where you have a bunch of
people helping to lead the project, the bus factor gets
significantly lower.
I believe there's another better strategy that nobody
really mentioned.
Go ahead.
Money.
You know, if you buy something, there's a contract there.
And if you're actually willing to pay for the development of
the distro you use, you incentivize the person.
And if something else fails, like you lost control of the
well, the person just disappeared.
There's no control of the website.
You can actually prove legal ties to that project.
You can actually, as a collective ownership, get that.
And that actually is a better, I believe, better business
model for the creator to have an incentive to stay for the
people using the software to have actually demonstration of
possession of the product.
And ultimately, that should simplify the whole thing.
And why does Canonical Flavors work?
Because Canonical has money to maintain it.
No, no, it's not about money.
The project when it first started off, it's about people.
It's about community.
It's about the fact that there are people willing to step up
and look after things.
And as Dan said, the community came together and made a code
of conduct that said, look, if you can't do this anymore,
everyone has real life.
People have children, get married, take a sabbatical,
change direction, buy a Mac, whatever it is, it might move
away from your open source project.
And if they do, as long as they hand over gracefully,
then it's fine.
And one of the things we've done in Ubuntu, which I know a
lot of other projects do as well, is when you create
something, you create it in a way that it's not just you
that looks after it.
So for example, if you create an IRC channel on Freenode,
just as a simple example, if you create an official Ubuntu
channel, so that means it starts with hash Ubuntu dash
something, right?
So you create a new IRC channel, we recommend that you give
rights to that channel to the Ubuntu IRC council.
So that in the event that you got hit by a bus or your IRC
account was compromised, or you had a baby or bought a Mac
or whatever it is, someone else could take over and then
hand that on to the next person.
It's not that you're a bad person for moving on.
It's not that any money changed hands in any way, shape or
form.
There was nothing about money.
It's just about people and process and having a simple
process in place which allows things to move from one person
to the next person down the line.
I do kind of agree about if you have this as your primary
form of income, though there is kind of more of an obligation,
right?
Like if you depend on this open source project to put food
on your table, you're much less likely to buy a Mac.
Yeah, and not only that, actually, there's the other
part, which is when you are stepping down, I'm talking
about, let's say you get hit by a bus and you really wanted
to control things on your own.
You didn't really trust anybody at the time you started
the project because this counseling thing is very pretty,
but it requires trust.
Like you're talking to other people that you may have seen
or not.
And this takes time to build that trust.
Until then, you're really not assigning things you paid for
where your name lies on to other people.
So ultimately, it's a process.
And until that time, if the monetary incentive is there,
it facilitates the number one, you being incentivized to
actually be responsible to the stuff you're putting out.
And secondly, there's legal ways for people to get to you
if you're not putting it out, if there's a commitment to it.
And ultimately, even if you disappear, it is easier to
prove because there's transaction records and to get
something done.
While if nothing exists, you really don't.
That might be true, but that's not how it worked in Ubuntu.
Now, this is also really kind of a benefit of an organization
like the Software Freedom Conservancy.
Now, you don't really see a lot of distributions underneath
it, although I don't know if that's entirely true, but you
do see a lot of large projects underneath it.
And the Conservancy provides a infrastructure to open source
and free software to focus on what they do.
They do the code and they do all of the legal stuff and the
operational stuff and take care of the getting, make sure your
donations are legal and stuff and documentation for certain
aspects of the business.
And that's sort of what some of the services that the
Conservancy offers.
And I don't know, maybe one day the Conservancy would extend
that to more and more distros.
I don't know.
I don't think the solution is really easily attainable for
how to make sure these small distros don't go away because
you're still dealing with, you know, perhaps potentially tens
of thousands of end users that just kind of get caught in
whatever drama is going on behind the scenes.
But additionally, I think it does an untold amount of damage
to the reputation of Linux, of open source development, and
I heard a term the other day that I just really got me mad.
And it was a derogatory term for the reliability of open
source developers.
And the podcaster said, well, you know, he's just really
open sourcey.
He's just open sourcey.
I don't like the sounds of that.
And I'm like, what does that mean?
You know, like, he just doesn't do a good job.
He just sort of flaked out.
He's open sourcey.
I was like, I don't know.
It really got me upset.
Were you going to say something wimpy?
I was about to.
I was saying what open sourcey like Linus Torvalds, who's
been doing what he's doing for 26 years.
Yeah.
Oh, I'm actually angry right now.
My heart rate is up.
Just even remembering, recalling it, I got so upset by it.
So, all right.
Let's change gears to something that makes me happy.
There is a new release of Darktable this week.
Version 2.4.3 comes out and it's perfect timing because I'm
just kind of getting my Darktable on.
And Brent, your timing was really good.
Brent is a professional photographer by trade.
We're going to have some of his photos linked in the show notes.
And you've been using Darktable for how long?
I've been using Darktable since about, I believe it's 2012,
maybe even 2011.
So you've been watching the development for a while.
Yeah.
And you use it for a professional workflow, like you
were working here today at the studio and you were touching
up photos all day in Darktable.
I would say for me professionally, it's 80%, maybe
even 90% of where I do all my work.
Really?
Okay.
Well, see, this makes me pretty excited because I always
thought Darktable was for only individuals like yourself,
but Brent stopped by the booth at Linux Fest Northwest.
That's where we met him.
And he told me an anecdote that made me realize that even
I could probably figure out Darktable.
Maybe I think it was about actually a week ago, I was
invited to do a workshop at a Makers Fest, which was a first
thing for me and really great.
And I thought, okay, how do I introduce some sort of Linux
or open source into this?
Because I actually didn't see very much of that in there.
So I thought, okay, I'm going to do a workshop based on
using Darktable because people get easily attracted to
photography and that's my specialty.
But I'm going to introduce it in a way that applies to
any user.
So I ended up with a class full of people that were ranging
from enthusiasts all the way to kids.
And actually the kids were the ones that picked up on it
the fastest.
And so there's the beauty about Darktable, I think, is that
it can be extremely powerful and extremely flexible, but it
can also be very, very simple.
So if you just determine a workflow that is one, two, three
steps, then your adjustments and your cropping is just
slider bars.
So that's the way to go.
It's super simple.
Start like that.
Oh, yeah.
Ignore like Photoshop and GIMPs and stuff like that for
regular, everyday stuff.
What would you say are three things that you should touch on
every photo you take?
So I can tell you that easily.
So every single photo, I would say, A, cropping in camera.
You know, sometimes you don't always do it well, or you get
a different idea once you see it on the large screen.
So cropping is number one.
And in a cropping tool in Darktable, there's some like
skewing of angles, which kind of comes into play as well.
And they make it super, super easy.
You just right click and go, this should be straight.
And it fixes everything for you.
So that's one.
Two would be exposure.
They have an exposure slide bar with blacks level.
And so that can get you pretty darn far.
And then color is the third one, I would say.
Boost it a bit or what?
Like, what do you mean when you say color?
Like white balance kind of a thing.
Right.
So if you shot in various environments, sometimes your
camera can't, it's not as good as our eyes at adjusting to
color differences, right?
So anyone who starts to be able to learn to see color can then
determine that, oh, wait, this photo would actually be a lot
more dynamic if the colors were actually corrected to true.
So for instance, behind you, you have this crazy green light
that keeps changing.
I noticed.
Yeah, it makes it impossible to set our camera.
Right.
So then necessarily, and that's the beauty of raw is that you
can adjust that later on.
So every 30 seconds, you have a different color going on and
you can just correct that later.
Yeah, that would be nice.
Yeah.
All right.
You did.
You convinced me to try it.
So I'll install.
Actually, we installed it on one of the machines here in the
studio already to give it a go.
And Chris, tell me how easy it was to do that.
We were talking about that.
That actually, I think, was a big takeaway for me when I was
looking at it.
And it must be something you appreciate, too, is we didn't
have to go log into some proprietary vendor's website
and authorize anything.
Find your license key.
Yeah.
Brent was like, before I go, I could just take care of these
right here.
Do you want me to just do that now?
And I'm like, OK.
Apt install darktable.
And he was off and working.
But then you have an extra step that you take.
Do you want to share that secret?
Absolutely.
So yeah, I'm not even using the same distribution as you.
I'm on Arch.
But that doesn't seem to be a problem anywhere.
It seems to be a little bit everywhere.
But what I've done for myself, because I was thinking
something like this may happen in the future, and just
for my own, to make things easier in my own system, I
actually keep my favorite darktable, like a settings
database.
It's like a whole profile?
Yeah, the entire profile that you find under.config.
And that includes your common colors that you change things
to, like your common presets for photo editing?
Yeah, I've got a bunch of presets.
So every single module in darktable can have its own
presets or multiple presets.
And you can also define defaults for when you import
images, what gets applied.
So I was able to, despite never having used the laptop that I
was on, in five minutes, I had my own home
environment right there.
That is slick.
It's so great.
And it kind of means you're not married to anything.
You're not married to any one hardware vendor.
You're not married to any one particular OS or even
distribution.
And darktable's free software.
So you don't even, that's great.
And they just recently had an update to GIMP that we covered
in Linux Action News.
Oh gosh, yeah.
And GIMP is now working with darktable, so you can send
from darktable to GIMP, and they're going to understand
each other.
And it's like a big kumbaya now between the two.
And it's a new version of GIMP that looks pretty great.
It does look really nice.
First big update in six years.
You can't see that, but I have this giant smile on my face.
Oh yeah?
You like it?
Are you a GIMP fan?
So the other 20% is I'm doing in GIMP.
And I haven't quite launched into credit yet.
But GIMP, for me, for many, many years,
has been doing the simple, offering the simple features
that I really need when I need that extra 20% of doing some
really specialty photography-specific adjustments that
need to be done that darktable just isn't designed for
and I don't think should include anyways.
We have a bunch of great photos that have been tweaked by,
and taken, too, by Brent in darktable from Linux Fest
Northwest, 158 of them.
And they're great.
And the cutest pictures of Levi ever.
Yeah, ever.
So cute in there.
It's ridiculous.
If you like puppies, you've got to go check out the link
in linuxunplugged.com slash 247.
I'll drop a link to the album in the IRC, too,
if you're watching live.
Some really great photos of our party at Lady Joops
that we had out in the parking lot.
So Saturday evening of Linux Fest Northwest,
we decided to have a tailgate-style party.
System76 brought a ton of meat.
I brought two barbecues, and a table, and some camping chairs.
I stuffed them all into the bays of Lady Joops.
The advantages of having a class A
is you have some big storage bays.
And brought two bags of charcoal and a chimney starter.
And we put the awning out and started cooking.
And we cooked for hours in the parking lot.
And Brent was there snapping photos the whole time.
It was a lot of fun.
We were flying drones and geeking out
in the parking lot.
And oh, geez, some good pictures right there.
And there's a good time.
Yeah, we had a really good time.
And I just thought that was maybe
the highlight of the whole thing.
So thanks for taking those pictures.
And thanks for making them available to the whole audience
to check them out, too.
That's really nice of you.
Yeah, I'm happy to.
And give people a little info maybe
if they want to know more about your photography services
and whatnot.
Because I got to tell you, I'd like to bring you
out to future events.
Absolutely.
Especially keep taking these cute pictures of Levi.
Where should they find you?
Levi's an easy win, right?
So website BrentGervais.com.
So I'll spell that out, B-R-E-N-T-G-E-R-V-A-I-S.com.
That's just where you can see a little bit of my work.
And I'm not super active on social,
but you can find me on Twitter, Brent, at Brent Gervais.
And I guess around the network.
Cool.
Yeah, you may hear from him some more in the future.
And check out the link in the show notes
if you want to see the cutest puppy pictures ever.
I mean, that's just indisputable.
It's just a fact.
Yeah, it is not even my bias.
It's just purely indisputable.
All right.
Well, we do have a roundup to get to of Ubuntu 18.04,
the flavors, the new features, the server stuff,
and maybe even a pretty cool feature
that I didn't even think about until I heard about it from Ian at System76.
And I went, why is nobody else doing that?
So we'll play a clip from Ian from System76 about something that Pop!
OS is adding that blew my mind, really made me just really impressed.
So we'll get there, but let's talk about Linux Academy, linuxacademy.com.
That's where you go to sign up for a free seven-day trial.
And coincidentally, just surprise, surprise, support this show.
Yeah, keep us on the air, maybe even get us to 300 freaking episodes.
Linux, maybe this show will have even more episodes than last.
That would be amazing.
Well, people go to linuxacademy.com slash unplug.
They'll help us get there, and you'll get a free seven-day trial.
It's a platform to learn more about Linux, a full-featured training library
with everything you want to get new skills and advance your career.
Now, I love the self-paced video courses.
This is the sweet stuff.
And Linux Academy, I happen to have first-hand experience,
is investing in great recording hardware.
They've really put a lot of effort into this.
They also offer hands-on scenario-based labs.
They spin up the system on whatever infrastructure you need.
So if it's AWSs, or if it's an OpenStack system, or if it's just a Debian box.
They spin that up for you, you log in over SSH, you get to work,
you get a real scenario, something you can take and do in production.
And if you ever get stuck, they have full-time human instructors that are happy
to help and answer your questions.
So you get actual hands-on experience, and you got the humans.
That's pretty much as good as it's gonna get, because that's all they do is Linux.
So they build features in that help you get there, like Learning Pass,
which are a series of content and courses planned for instructors that get you into
specific career tracks.
Or if you're ready to take some big tests,
they have courses created specifically to prepare you for certifications.
And practice exams too, which I gotta tell you, if you don't practice,
you probably won't pass, so that's a great feature.
And they have a community stacked full of Jupyter Broadcasting members who are
surprisingly supportive.
It's ridiculous, it's like an educational support group.
And they do it all on their own, they're just great people.
Try it out, seven days for free, linuxacademy.com.
Oh, and a big thank you, Linux Academy, linuxacademy.com.
So this 1804 release is big, I think it's gonna be a big release.
I don't know if you've heard about Ubuntu, but
it's a pretty big distribution, and they got all kinds of different flavors.
We never talked about it before on the show, so
I can understand if you'd be unfamiliar with this, but there's a bunch of them.
And let's talk about some of the main changes that are coming in Ubuntu 1804
itself, cuz we're gonna talk about the flavors here, but
you're gonna get Linux kernel 4.15, it's pretty nice.
You're gonna get five years of support, of course,
this is also the first LTS to support and ship GNOME.
Where you get X11, you get the new minimal installation feature,
which is a little different across the flavors, but
it is the best thing that has come to Ubuntu in a really long time.
And Ubuntu's live kernel patch service,
which I don't think is getting enough play in this release, is now front and center.
It's part of the welcome screen when you log in for the first time,
there's a GUI to turn it on, live kernel patching is here, it's available.
And I think it's kind of a big deal, and the fact that they've now wrapped
a GUI around the whole thing to make it accessible to workstations,
I think deserves a little more credit than it's getting.
Files is getting a revamped user, or has now,
a revamped user interface as well that looks really compact.
There's also other things that are just nice to have,
because it just makes it back to normal.
Close, minimize, and maximize buttons are back on the right side of the window.
And I do prefer GDM over LightDM, and
1804 has shipped GDM as the display manager.
It's big, it's bulky, it's weird, but I just happen to like it better than LightDM.
It does work.
Well, I just, I find it to be smoother.
I don't know what it is, it's like my lock screen and all of it.
I just, I find LightDM to be clunky, and I find GDM to, I don't know,
just suits my needs better.
So those are some of the core big things that are coming in Ubuntu 1804.
And that's what I would look forward to.
Also, you've got the other things like the Thunderbolt 3 support.
You've got Gnome 328.
There's other really nice things.
LibreOffice 6.0 is in there, but that's the main things I'd be looking for.
And then you have a brand new LTS flavor.
For the first time, Ubuntu Budgie 1804 LTS.
This is the first LTS,
first official time they've been a flavor during an LTS release.
It's gonna be supported until April 2021.
And it ships with the latest Budgie desktop, 10.4 Irish Summer.
And it's accompanied with the Gnome 328 application.
So that's kind of a big deal for them.
Kind of a big deal, yeah.
Congratulations.
It's real now, that's awesome.
Friend of the show, Dustin, and teamwork on that.
And then, of course, you've got all of the flavors that are available for
download, Zubuntu, Kobuntu, Ubuntu Mate, Ubuntu Proper itself, Kylin.
And the flavors come in at three years of support instead of the five years that
the main line gets.
Kobuntu, as I've mentioned many times, is shipping Plasma 512 LTS.
So you've got a whole LTS stack there.
Producer Michael has contributed several tweaks like Plasma Dark by default,
or I'm sorry, Breeze Dark.
Nice.
Yeah, it's actually really, really well done.
VLC is the default video player, which I know a lot of people like.
Latte Dock is in the archives and KDE Connect is pre-installed.
Excellent.
Yeah, also one of the other things it does is double click is the default
behavior to open files and stuff.
So Ubuntu 18.04 comes out now with a mostly high DPI support theme,
which is good for them.
And Studio has an 18.04 release, but it's only gonna be supported for nine months.
But they do have a new release.
It's there.
It's just not an LTS at this time.
And then look at that Ubuntu Kylin release coming in at three years,
ideal for Chinese users.
But damn, if that doesn't look like Windows 7.
It sure does.
I'd say anybody that just prefers the Windows 7 UI and layout,
you might just check out Kylin or Chillin.
Wonderful Ubuntu user.
Is it Chillin Wimpy or is it Kylin?
It's Chillin and it's based on Mate.
Yeah, yeah, it really, it looks, what do you think of this?
Is this, this is...
Well, it's delightful, right?
Because it's really nice to see what we're making being used elsewhere
in a very different way.
I mean, they've layered their own tools and utilities on top of it
to give it a very distinctive look.
And yeah, well, they're making what their users want and it's good to see.
It does look pretty sharp.
Do they share the size of the user base?
Do we have, I mean, they must be large enough to have gotten flavor status.
I have no idea how big their user penetration is.
I think it's considerable.
Yeah, I imagine.
Be interesting to talk to someone.
Yeah, that would be.
And then, of course, our friends over at Mate, Ubuntu Mate 1804,
which ships Mate Desktop 120.
It's got that new keyboard-friendly HUD.
Global menu if you want that mutiny desktop layout.
High DPI support that we know Wimpy's been working towards for about two years now.
Hardware acceleration in Marco.
Just like Wes always wants, color emoji support.
Heck yes.
Got the brisk menu in there.
You got the improved Mate tweak tool, the new software boutique updates.
I mean, I might be a little biased here, but this is one of the strongest flavors by far.
1804 Ubuntu Mate looks like some of your best work, Wimpy.
Thank you.
That's very kind of you to say so.
And my own assessment is it's the best release we've put out by some margin.
I was really pleased with 1710.
And when we released that, I felt like that was good enough to be the 1804 LTS.
But it's amazing how much we've got done in the six months.
Because in 1710, there was no high DPI, and there is now.
So it just goes to show how much of a hustle we've had on in those last six months
to really, really make this LTS something for the next three years.
It is really impressive.
It's fantastic.
I think a congratulations to the whole team is in order for that, because it's really nice.
I want to also talk about, in Ubuntu proper, the new welcome screen.
Because I might be wrong, I haven't dug deep into this.
But when you're all kind of done with the new walkthrough,
it brings up a new screen that says, install some new apps.
And you got Spotify on there.
You got a lot of really well-known apps like Skype and Slack and more.
So is this, maybe you should answer this.
I don't know.
Is this a Snap screen?
Are these all Snaps?
Are these all Snap apps if I click one of those?
They are.
Every single one of them is a Snap.
They're a selection of applications that we thought
people who are coming from other platforms might like the familiarity of.
So people who are coming from Windows or Mac or anywhere else
might like to see, oh, I can get Spotify on here.
I can get Slack.
Or I could chat to my friends on Discord.
Or my kids can play Minecraft on here.
Or if I'm a developer, I can easily get Android Studio.
So there's a whole set of applications, plus your favorite open source
things like Brave Browser and GIMP and all kinds of other stuff in there.
Well, I just noticed that I recently seemed
to be able to tell the installation spread across the different versions
of Ubuntu.
I don't know if that's something that's recently
being published in the Snap Store.
All of a sudden, I'm seeing comparatively how many 1804 users over 1604.
And it seems like this must be having subtraction
because the 1804 numbers are skyrocketing right now.
The view you're seeing there in the Snap Store
is a logarithmic scale of which platform those Snaps are being installed on.
And it's to represent that you can install these Snaps in lots
of different places.
And here are some of the places that you might find users
who are using those things.
OK.
That's a nice stat to have.
I really do appreciate having that.
And when I saw the 1804 numbers, I mean,
it's already like the number one on some of those Snaps.
It's really.
Oh, it's gone mad.
Yes.
I think it's all, if it hasn't already, it's
probably close to overtaking the 1710 numbers already.
Yeah.
Yeah, I looked a couple of hours ago.
And yeah, it's just nudging the 1710 numbers.
Yeah, I'm looking at VLC right now and exactly, exactly that.
And then after that, it'll be on to 1604, which is remarkable.
And it tells you that I think that welcome screen is a great idea.
I'm glad that was added.
I think we'll see those numbers move a bit more soon
because we haven't turned on the prompts for 1710 users
to get the prompt to upgrade to 1804.
So that will be later this week.
And then, of course, around June, July time,
the 1604 users will get the prompt when we release 1804.1.
So the ramp up of 1804 at the moment
is all people clean installing or deliberately
choosing to do the upgrade.
So we'll see that rock on a bit more
as the upgrade prompts kick in.
I wonder, does anybody have a guess?
If you take out 1804, 1710, and 1604,
the next top distro is not an Ubuntu distro for the Slack snap.
Does anybody have a guess what distro it is?
It's not an Ubuntu distro.
Arch Linux.
That's a good guess.
I see Neon on here.
I see Linux, Mint, Zorin.
Arch is a little bit further down the road.
No, elementary 0.41 is the next distro after Ubuntu 1804
right now for the Slack snap.
Those elementary users, they love their Slack.
Yeah, they certainly do.
They're getting their work done.
That's why they need to get their notifications done right.
It's a good thing you're getting that done, Dan.
That's pretty cool.
It's pretty neat to see that.
Debian 9's doing pretty good.
Neon 1604 is doing good.
Fedora 27 on the list.
Pretty cool.
I like that you guys are releasing that.
I'm going to keep an eye on that from now on.
It's interesting to compare the different apps
and see what different distros shake out.
Same with MailSpring.
It's the same kind of spread on MailSpring.
Yeah, people on elementary OS are just
getting some damn work done, apparently.
What it's there for.
Now, we can't really have an 1804 release discussion
without getting to some of the cloud stuff,
because that's just a huge part of what Ubuntu does now.
But I know that Wimpy might have a story that someone
like myself could appreciate.
Yeah, so we've inherited a couple of features
from Debian's current developments
that I think might be up your alley.
The first is if you install FFmpeg
and you've got an NVIDIA card, when
you install the NVIDIA proprietary drivers,
that will automatically enable NVENC capability
on the FFmpeg on the host.
And also, if you install OBS, that
will automatically pick up the fact
that you have NVENC-enabled FFmpeg
and turn on the hardware acceleration for you.
Wow, I was literally just talking to Wes
about this before the show, about how we were reviewing
if we really needed to have the NVIDIA card
during this last Linux fast rebuild.
And we landed on firmly, yep, we still
have to have the NVIDIA card.
We still got to have that acceleration.
So that is so great that you just made that easier.
Yeah, so no more building from source.
Just install those two things, and you're off to the races.
Yeah, boy, it's getting good there.
Because this new GIMP release I just mentioned earlier,
one of the things they're including now
is GPU acceleration, too.
So having a good working GPU setup on an Ubuntu desktop,
I think, is going to become more and more important.
And I don't need to tell you guys that,
because I'm sure machine learning and all kinds
of workloads like that are a big part of why
that's been done, right?
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, these contributions come from being
based on top of Ubuntu, but Canonical
have done a heap of work with NVIDIA
to unlock compute performance for deep learning and AI
and all that sort of stuff.
Oh, right, you said it came from Debian, right.
So let's talk about the new multi-cloud reality
that Canonical finds themselves in.
And this seems to be a point that Mark
wants to hit in his interviews about Ubuntu 18.04.
He says that they've done boot time and performance
optimized images of Ubuntu 18.04 on every major public cloud.
And they made sure to be the fastest and most efficient
OS for cloud computing.
I would hope he thinks that way.
He says, having an OS tuned for far advanced workloads,
such as AI and machine learning, is
critical to a high velocity team.
And that's from, actually, the product manager
at Cloud at Google, who says that they're looking forward
to deploying 18.04 on the Google Cloud infrastructure.
And Microsoft came in with their quote saying,
this was Craig, their program manager, says,
we're going to have Hyper-V optimized images
that we've developed in collaboration with Canonical.
These will be enhanced experiences
of Ubuntu and Windows.
In our upcoming release this spring,
Hyper-V's Quick Create VM Gallery
will now include an image for the latest Ubuntu 18.04 LTS
release, officially stamped straight from Canonical.
And I read this because it kind of underscores a theme I'm
noticing in this 18.04 release is Canonical
is working with AWS and other large partners,
like Microsoft, with Azure and Microsoft Hyper-V,
and I presume many others, to say,
well, what do you need us to custom build into these images
for you?
And it's something that they seem
to be taking to a much larger scale with this release.
I mean, that matters a lot, right?
Not every shop and everyone doing this has time
or even makes sense for them to do that sort of tuning.
So if you can get that out of the box,
it makes Ubuntu a natural choice.
Yeah, it's definitely an incentive.
So in Ubuntu podcast, season 11, episode 8,
we interviewed David Britton, who's
the lead for the Ubuntu server team.
And he talked about the customizations and performance
optimizations that Canonical do for the major cloud providers.
So for each of their clouds, they
get tailored images that are Ubuntu,
but specific to their environment
and their boot processes and their hardware.
Which episode again?
As we're recording this, the current episode.
So it's season 11, episode 8.
Oh, very good.
I look forward to listening to that.
Now, that seems like all of that is all good and fine,
but we haven't talked about Pop!
OS, which isn't a flavor, not an official flavor,
but it is one of the more well-known Ubuntu
derivatives at this point.
And Ian sat down with us at the Linux Fest Northwest booth,
and he told me about a feature they're adding in there
that I think is pretty clever.
And I wonder if we're going to see it
in other places pretty soon.
The new installer sets up a recovery partition.
Oh, OK.
So that's something new that I haven't seen in Linux.
I might have missed it.
I was just thinking about that today, actually.
Yeah, so basically there's an extra partition on the drive.
It's about 4 gigabytes, enough to hold two ISOs conveniently.
And it basically just holds the latest ISO
so that you have media to reinstall your OS,
even if you don't have a flash drive or a CD drive available.
Wow.
Love that.
Yeah.
So can you do a fresh install, configure install,
or does it give you a, when you install a machine,
does it come, does Pop!
OS itself come pre-configured with all of the System76
repositories, assuming that you're using System76 hardware?
Or is it come just as like a stock distro,
and then you further customize Pop! OS?
You have to add like a PPA later and stuff like that.
Right.
For the hardware that's specific to System76.
How does that work?
So the new installer should be automatically installing
the System76 package for all of the hardware support stuff.
That's in the main Pop! OS repository now,
in addition to being in the System76 repository
for other OSs.
OK.
So it should be installing that.
That may not be set up yet, though.
I'd have to double check on that.
But I can message Jeremy on Slack at some point
and figure that out.
Yeah, because we are talking like down the road here.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But yeah, it's pretty well set up.
And it's a whole entire distro.
And it will be doing the hardware integration
for System76, but it will work great on everything.
It doesn't require a System76 computer.
It's not lost on me that when you say the installer,
that is something that most System76 customers won't even
see.
Actually, no, because another thing the installer does
is full disk encryption.
Oh.
And so now.
There's like a user interaction process.
Right.
So the first run for a new System76 computer,
it's actually going to run the installer.
And it's going to do a couple steps in the installer.
And it's going to ask you if you want to encrypt.
And if you choose you don't want to encrypt,
it'll just say, cool, we're done, and it'll.
Now, it'll say you're done, and then it
goes to the user creation.
I got cut there because there's a lot of noise
in the background, and somebody jumped on the mic.
Because there were people having a really good time
at Linux Fest.
They sure were.
But, Pobie, you were noting in the chat room
that there's other ways this can happen, maybe
other companies that do this.
Yeah, Dell have been doing this for a few years.
They ship their systems with a little Dell utility
that when you first install it, it
says, do you want to create recovery media, basically?
Stick a USB key in, and it'll make that.
But if you don't, that's OK.
Because they've done the same kind of thing,
where they've got a recovery area, a partition,
and you can just reboot and make it nuke the system back
to clean.
And when I reviewed the Dell laptop that they sent us,
I just did that and reverted it back to factory defaults,
and then put it back in the box and sent it back to them.
Right.
That is really nice.
I think I've always traditionally just nuke
and paved the entire drive when I get a new machine.
And I've always kind of regretted it in the end,
because it's a nice convenience.
So I like that they're essentially bringing that
to everybody with Pop!
OS.
Yeah, more people should do this.
And I wish we could do that more easily in Ubuntu,
so that the default Ubuntu install had a recovery
partition and could do all of this magic voodoo.
But we'd get a bit of pushback, I think, from some people.
It's a lot of work to do.
And it's easier for System76 to bake this in,
and for Dell to bake this in at the factory
when they're putting the images on the hard drives.
It's a little less easier for us to do it as a USB stick.
But it could be done.
But it's a lot of engineering work.
Yeah, right.
And you know in that case that it's
going on a laptop, whereas Ubuntu goes lots of places.
So I've been pretty impressed.
My initial impressions, this is all they are at this point
with 1804, is that it's shipping just such a great version
of Gnome.
And it iterated on top of 1710 in a lot of great ways.
The choice to go with X11, I think, was a safe one.
And I can see where maybe a few things are going.
I can see perhaps a new theme that I think it's called.
People have talked about it.
It might be coming on the horizon.
But I could also see interesting directions
that new Ubuntu welcome screen goes, perhaps more
in the direction of Ubuntu MATE's welcome.
That could be really interesting.
I would love to see that develop more in 1810.
And I would like to see just more of what they're doing.
So far, my initial impressions have been pretty solid.
We'll see what the stability story is.
We'll see what third party application integration
and support is.
But right now, I can see where things are going.
And I'm liking it.
It seems like 1710, they pulled it off.
And the 1804, they would have had to really blown it
to mess up 1804.
And they didn't.
They didn't blow it.
They just iterated on top of it.
So both Fedora 28 and Ubuntu 1804
might be, so far, my initial impression,
some of their best releases I've ever seen out of either group.
It's a super exciting time to be a Linux user.
I mean, there's so much going on.
And 1604, I felt like it really shook up the landscape.
It was kind of a monumental release.
And 1804, it's like, now we're on that first just strictly
better polish LTS.
I'm so excited.
Yeah, and I'm really, I guess, I can't even
remember how long it's been since I've
been tracking an Ubuntu release and a Fedora release
around the same time, where they're
shipping at the same time.
And they're both shipping the latest and greatest GNOME.
And so we're back to, well, who kind of has the cooler GNOME
implementation?
It's been a long time since we've been there.
And it feels kind of nostalgic.
I love it.
I'm really excited about the whole release cycle.
So I think just a couple of solid releases.
I got Fedora 28 on the machine.
I got Ubuntu 1804 proper on a machine.
And then I have a mess of systems on Kubuntu 1804.
And I would be negligent if I didn't just say, hot damn.
We put it in the belly of the beast,
a trial by the greatest fire.
There is one thing we can do at Jupyter Broadcasting
to break a machine every single year.
Every year, we've broken a machine.
And we sometimes had to run out and grab parts
in the middle of the fest and rebuild our system right there
on the table at our booth.
We've had to reload operating systems,
reinstall OBS, set up NVIDIA drivers,
reimport all of our scenes.
This year, we decided if Kubuntu 1804 could survive Linux
Fest Northwest without crashing, it
would become our de facto production operating
system at Jupyter Broadcasting.
Because there is literally no better way to break a system.
And we built one really great OBS system.
We Frankensteined a couple of systems together.
But they're all really solid parts.
Six cores really fast, 32 gigs of RAM, MV&E drives,
multiple MV&E drives, brand new fresh power supply,
cleaned it all out, everything.
It's just a gorgeous system.
And we installed Kubuntu 1804 Minimal Install on it.
Minimal Install is so perfect for the studio.
It's so perfect.
Nothing's missing.
Nothing extra.
They nailed it.
It's so great.
And so we loaded that on this new OBS Frankenstein machine.
And Noah and I sat around for hours.
Because last year didn't go so well.
We had a lot of crashes.
Every episode of Linux Unplugged would suffer a crash.
And both Noah and I just felt super bad about that.
And he's like, Polar Bear, I don't
want to leave and have that thing crash on you the next day.
And I said, Brown Bear, I don't want to have to go buy a Mac.
So we've got to make sure this works.
We're getting real talk here.
If this fails on us, what am I going to do?
Because I'm at a point where I've tried Unity.
I've tried Arch.
I've tried Gnome.
I've tried Zubuntu.
We tried Zubuntu during this whole transition.
I've tried it all.
Fuchsia, that's probably it.
Like, what am I going to do?
So we have to know this works.
We have to be 100% solid on this.
We'll build it.
We'll set it up.
We'll do some testing.
We'll run through every single show.
And we had Alan by this time.
Alan had joined us.
So it's me, Noah, and Alan all working this problem.
And then we got the new Kubuntu rig set up.
We went through every single show.
We did a mock version of every show on the network, the three
of us.
It was a lot of fun.
That's amazing.
And we were able to be ridiculous because we
weren't streaming any of it.
So we didn't.
I hope you recorded this.
No.
I mean, I did.
But I don't know if I kept the files.
We did an unfilter.
We did a Linux unplug.
We did a BSD now.
We did all of them.
And made sure everything worked.
We certified it as good and said, OK, now we're going to
take it up to Linux Fest.
If it survives that weekend, we'll put it back in the
studio, and we'll lock everything
down to Kubuntu 18.04.
And it performed so well that Chase Nunes, who was running
the board, ended up loading up a pinball application on his
laptop and playing pinball while the machine just ran and
did its thing.
Just ran and did its thing.
That says so much.
He played pinball.
And afterwards, he went up to Angela and said, this was the
smoothest, easiest year we've ever had.
It's never ran better.
Did not crash once on us.
Beautiful.
Did not have a single issue.
Now we've recorded three shows through it since we've been
back from Linux Fest running Kubuntu.
We have it installed on five systems in the immediate room
that we're sitting in right now.
It's on another system outside.
And it's just been rock solid.
So I really can't say enough good things
about Kubuntu 18.04.
And I've really started to just take to plasma.
I tweak my defaults.
Takes me about a day of just sort of putzing here and
there, like the first time I open up Dolphin, I change a
few settings.
The first time I log in, I open up settings, and I change
a few things.
But after the first day or two of just doing that on and off,
I'm pretty much done.
And it's set.
You've got it dialed in now.
Yeah.
And loving it.
The performance overhead is less than it was on some of
the other desktop environments.
And I was surprised every time I saw that.
We have an active monitor right here as I'm watching.
I'm still watching the system.
CPU and memory usage is lower by quite a bit than it was on
some GTK desktops.
You were mentioning earlier, it feels like a professional
workstation.
Yeah.
I was teetering on what am I going to do.
I need a professional grade workstation environment that I
can put on powerful hardware that feels like it's designed
for people to get worked on as professional.
And that's how Plasma feels for me.
It just feels professional grade.
It's just really well done.
Kubuntu is a really great release.
I wasn't the biggest fan of the one that was
based on Plasma 5.5.
This one, they nailed it.
So my most experience, because I've been installing it on
systems for two weeks now, is with Kubuntu 18.04.
God knows I've tried it in every which way, different
configuration.
And I even got to see how it performed with failing
hardware, which was pretty entertaining.
It was, we had a disk that was going bad in a system, and
KWin disappeared.
Goodbye.
Just completely disappeared from the system.
And then after we got that fixed, VLC disappeared, just
completely gone.
I closed the window, and it was gone.
The entire application.
Never to be seen again.
So it was funny to see how Plasma handled it.
And we telegrammed producer Michael, and we're like,
Rotten, is there any way that KWin could disappear while
we're using the system?
No, that's impossible, he writes back.
We're like, um.
It just happened.
That's when we knew we had some trouble.
But it even did fine there.
You almost wouldn't have even known, except for KWin
disappeared, and then VLC disappeared.
But it actually did pretty well for quite a while.
I've been really, really thrilled with it.
I think it's maybe my favorite Linux release maybe ever.
Maybe.
We'll see.
I mean, we'll see.
Maybe a blow up in my face, and I'll change my tune.
But right now.
I mean, it's early days, right?
But that's the most exciting part, is you have so much more
to go, and it'll be with you for a long time, I expect.
Yeah, it is one of those releases where I'm excited
again to spread the word.
I got it installed on Hedia's computer.
I'm excited to play with it.
But I'm not getting distracted by tweaking it too much.
It's just, it's so good.
It's so good.
And there's little things it does, like remembering the
right spots for my windows to open up.
So when we're in the studio and we have to launch things
really quickly, they all go in the right place.
And little things like that that make it efficient to use
that I just really super appreciate.
And I still got Neon on a couple of systems.
Still pretty great.
I'm really enjoying KDE Neon on my workstation upstairs.
And I have it on a laptop.
But everything else is KWin2H04.
It just matches my production systems.
And then on both, you're still in Ubuntu, right?
It's mostly the same.
Just a little difference on the skin.
Yeah, I was tempted by Arch a little bit over Linux Fest,
just because I love that AUR.
I'm Brent's an Arch user, so I know he understands.
But that idea of the whole stack, the whole stack being
LTS, and my machines just become appliance-like as close
as possible.
And then you've got Livepatch in there too.
So I can even reduce having to reboot there.
It seems like it's just the right time for you
to have this be stable.
Yeah, because it's really come to a point
where we were considering, do we hire an IT person?
Because we've got a lot of systems.
Rekai used to help pick some of that up.
But we've decided, if we can just get these systems
manageable to a point where I can manage them,
and folks can help me out here and there
when they're at the studio, that's perfect.
And that's where we kind of moved away from Arch.
We'd look at something getting 300 packages behind on updates
before we could get to it.
And that's where you start rolling the dice,
with Arch, in a pretty big way.
Arch will run great as long as you stay on top of it.
But when you spread that across six systems,
and those six systems are there to serve
the purpose of doing work, not to do anything else,
it's hard to stay on top of that.
So we'll see.
Very happy with it.
Very, very happy with Kubuntu 18.04.
I really recommend people give it a try.
But go get more of our friends over at the Ubuntu podcast.
Sounds like they have a doozy that just came out.
I'm looking forward to hearing that.
And our friends over at Late Night Linux
just did their review of 18.04 as well.
And I thought that was pretty great.
So you can go catch out more of that.
And also, you may have heard recently
that Ubuntu 18.04 got loaded on the Nintendo Switch, which
is pretty cool.
The touch screen works.
Well, Wes and I did a technical breakdown
of how that's done at a hardware level, the exploit,
some of the ways that people are going to make it easier,
and the software in the Tegra that was actually vulnerable.
All that's covered in our TechSnap program,
TechSnap.systems, that would be it.
It's 365.
Thank you, sir.
Episode 365, which, how can you forget that?
Now, if you're watching live, which is, I mean, come on,
right?
You should join.
It's too much fun.
Everybody's doing that, right?
It's so obvious.
Well, then you stick around, because the Ask Noah program's
coming up.
And you've got your Linux sandwich.
You start out with the unplugged program.
We've got our live show.
That's where things really start.
Then you've got the main show.
We've got our post show.
And then that Noah Choliah guy comes in.
Messes everything up.
Takes a whole other round.
Woo.
Yeah, I was on his program just a couple of episodes ago.
And we talked about encryption and how
some of the different laws that could affect encryption
could affect open source.
I thought it was a pretty good chat.
So look for that.
But we'll be back here pretty soon.
Thank you so much, Linux Unplugged, slash 247 for links.
See you next Tuesday.
See ya.
So many good distro choices this week.
This is really, it's a good week to be a Linux user.
It's almost like it's the year of the Linux desktop, isn't it?
It's feeling like it.
It is in a lot of ways.
Not as we foresaw it, but...
You mean because it's Chromebooks?
You look at Chromebooks adding Linux application support, you look at Microsoft adding the
Linux subsystem to Windows, you look at these really solid releases from Ubuntu and Fedora,
and we've never been in better shape.
It is looking really good.
Although the doubters are still going to doubt.
Yeah.
Well, yeah.
That's true.
Yeah.
But what do they know, right?
All right.
We got to name this thing before we get out of here.
Yeah.
Banks and Jess.
JBtitles.com.
JBtitles.
Oh, God.
Did you guys see this?
Facebook dating was announced just recently.
Yeah.
Oh my God.
Just for you, Dan.
Yeah.
I'm off Facebook these days.
Oh.
I've been thinking about it a lot.
Yeah.
I saw that and I nearly included it as a news item for the Ubuntu podcast.
Smooth.
I've been thinking about doing the Facebook account delete thing.
I'm not sure.
It's just a few family members that I would lose touch with.
No.
I just unfriended all of the randos that I'd collected.
OCD shone through.
And it was like, where are all of the people I knew when I was at primary school and connected
with people that I haven't seen since I was 10.
And then some years later, I realized I'd got hundreds of friends that I didn't really
know.
And I just unfriended all the randoms and just coalesced around the people that I actually
So Facebook is just me now.
I actually know.
It's basically you and my wife, Poppy.
Yeah.
Are you not worried about the data tracking aspects of it, the monitoring you on other
sites via the Facebook like buttons and whatnot?
I am, but if I am not on Facebook and like everything my wife posts within a maximum
of a 37 minute time frame, then she thinks you're mad at her or something.
Yeah, exactly.
So I have to be on Facebook to sort of, you know, have a harmonious, you know, marriage.
So that's why I'm on Facebook.
Yeah, I do for family.
I need I need to create a bot that every time Louise posts something, it likes what she's
posted within 37 minutes.
And if I could do that, then I wouldn't have to be saying, yeah, that's worth every cost.
Do you have a Facebook brand?
Do you have a Facebook?
I do.
And I've been having this exact conversation.
It's like you're repeating what has been happening in my mind wondering if it's time.
Well, yeah.
And I've, you know, maybe one of the solutions to some of these problems is that new Firefox
plug in that came out to isolate the containers.
Yeah.
Oh, here we go.
I can I can w w up on this.
So I'm using the Facebook.
Well, I'm using Firefox containers generally, but I use the Facebook one.
Now on my phone, I've removed all of the actual Facebook app.
So I've removed Facebook Messenger and Facebook itself.
Yes.
And and the pages administrator, whatever it's called.
And I have installed there's a there's an application called I forget the exact name.
I think it's just called notifications or notifications FB or something, but it's called
notifications.
I can't find the exact name in a moment.
I have that installed, which polls the web service to see if you've been sent a message
or if somebody's liked something or whatever.
And then I have another app installed called Slim Social, which is a web wrapper around
the Facebook website and the notifications thingy integrates with the Slim Social.
So now everything on my phone to do with Facebook is constrained to this web app that is in
its own little sandbox.
So I I still get the notifications so I can still like everything Louise posts within
37 minutes, but I don't get all of that invasive shit that the Facebook applications have hooked
up to the rest of your system.
Wow.
I'm going to totally look into that.
That is so neat.
I just installed the sorry, go ahead.
I was just I was going to say I'll get the actual names of those apps that are available
in F-Droid and they're also available in the Android app store.
Neat.
What were you going to say Brent?
I'm just going to give a thumbs up there.
I just installed Slim Social for Linux Fest Northwest to get my Twitter up and going,
but I'm kind of anti or trying to be anti Google store.
So yeah, F-Droid it's in there and it actually works really well.
Super responsive.
Double plug.
Hey Dan.
Hey.
So what's going to be the recommended retail price for the next version of elementary?
Are you going to like, you know, what would you say would be a reasonable amount for someone
to pay when they download the ISO?
The default is currently at $10.
Are you going to keep that or change that or what are you going to do?
I don't think we're going to change it.
We always talk about, oh, we should, you know, run some kind of A-B test or some crap or
whatever.
Right.
Make it $10 equals Alan, then make it $50 or something.
There you go.
That's a good idea.
Actually, that'd be a good feature.
I mean, really what it is, is it's like what you can afford is the appropriate price to
pay.
So if you're, you know, destitute, like don't pay, but if you're Bill Gates, like pay a
lot.
Pay a lot.
Yeah.
That'd be nice actually.
I look forward to that.
Well, Brent, thank you for being on the show, man.
Yes.
Yeah, this is awesome.
A lot of fun.
How long, how many hours you guesstimate for that drive back?
Well, I have luckily planned ahead, so I've cut it up.
Oh yeah.
Good.
So I'm meeting a friend almost halfway, so taking a ferry going to Victoria for a little
bit.
Good for you.
That's a great ferry ride.
I've never taken it.
Yeah.
Are you doing a walk on or are you going to drive on?
I'm going to walk on.
That's the way to go.
The price is just.
Good for you.
And then I'm hitting up my brother in BC as well.
And then are you flying from BC to Ontario?
Yeah.
Good.
That's not too bad.
Good for you.
That's a good way to do it.
Well, thank you for being here today.
Thanks for having me this week.
It's been awesome.
Yeah, trekking to our side of the world.