So before we start the show can we talk about this really great project that the pirate Bay co-founder has built
He says based on the pirate Bay's own number or based on the music industry's own numbers
He could be costing them ten million dollars a day
The pirate co-founder Peter Sunday
I think that's how you say his name has created a device that he believes is costing that music industry ten million dollars a day
And it's a pretty sophisticated device
You see what it does is it makes a hundred copies of a song and then sends those songs to dev know
Because the whole point of this device is just underscore how ludicrous the RAAA's model is
To try to generate revenue off of copies of a digital item and also go after people and sue them for copies of a digital
item eight million copies of the song have been made and
the machine just
Constantly deletes them. It's I think built around a Raspberry Pi and it just downloads the tracks and immediately deletes them because it's the downloading
That the music industry says cost them the dollars and if you base it on their figures for how much each track cost
That's a lot of money. Yeah, it's it's better than just deleting though because it actually copies them to dev know yeah
Yeah, yeah, that is good of the name to copy machine
Good for them delightfully foreign, but perfect what a nice
Yeah, so the it's built on using a Raspberry Pi and then has an LCD LCD display and you know some quote-unquote Python code, right?
This is Linux unplugged episode
125 for December 29th
Welcome to Linux unplugged
Officially my last broadcast of 2015. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hey there Wes
Technically your last broadcast as well. What fun
Yeah, it is actually kind of it is when you do as many shows as we do it is
It's like whoa wait a minute. This is the last one. I'm doing for the year. That's that's uh, that's a mind job
So coming up on today's episode of the unplugged program
We're gonna follow up on solo s
one dot O's
Release and then the computer chaos club had a conference and they went some presenters went deep into red star OS
You know North Korea's custom Linux operating system the best operating. Yeah, in fact Wes you were compelled to install in your own V
I sure was so we got some clips from the conference and an hour-long presentation
I've boiled it down to just a couple of minutes of some interesting things and interesting ways the red star OS
Surveils its users locks them down to just certain parts of the internet and watermarks all of the media files that pass
through the system and has
Processes that are unkillable by root is a fascinating look into a way free software has been used to cripple free speech
It's a little disturbing, but it's also technically fascinating
We'll talk about that in today's episode on the unplugged program and then later on in the show
We're gonna follow up on that Raspberry Pi kit the canoe or the can or whatever
We still don't know what it's called
But it is an out-of-the-box turn your Raspberry Pi 2 into a full-fledged computer with a slick keyboard
Nice case speakers a hookup the whole thing. It's really cool plus
We have some interesting follow-up for scale towards the end of the show if we have time left
But West before all of that there's a little story
We've followed here on the unplugged program for the year and that is the Linux foundations core infrastructure infrastructure project
You've probably heard about that, right? I sure have and there's different people that have stepped up as of as of
As of like things like heart bleed have come out and things like that to support important open source projects, so
Our first bit of follow-up this week is a little thick so we better bring in our mama room
We need them to get a full take on this time appropriate greetings virtual lug
Oh hello
apologies if
50% of the hosts this week are dying I
Apparently have like a sinus infection or something that's killing me
So I'm gonna I'm gonna hand this first story over to you guys and see what you think, but did you hear this?
Facebook is apparently pulling out on their commitment of donating
$50,000
to canoe PGP and
And they say they initially announced they would provide $50,000 per year
They have since rescinded since rescinded West
Your initial reaction
Well, that's unfortunate. Yeah, you know I did see on Twitter that there are some people maybe associated with Facebook who are saying that it's a
Miscommunication, so I don't know if it's clear yet, but clearly you know the canoe PG folks are you know think they're not getting the money
And it's kind of the best
Privacy you know it's the best privacy guard open source that we have so good which is my go-to one
I'm I'm wondering virtual lug if anybody has any of the scuttlebutt on on this because it seems like a pretty d-bag move from Facebook
But whenever something like this happens you generally figure
There's more to the story
But if canoe PG is willing to go publicly in their news updates to shame there must have been some kind of communication
Yeah, so I'm thinking there must have been a back-and-forth before they made this post. There's something interesting happening there
but I who I just don't know and
One of the things this made me one of the things that's made me kind of
Zoom out and think about a little bit is what happens when critical infrastructure projects like this sort of get guaranteed funding from somebody and then
That somebody pulls out
Is that the open sources community to step up because how what is it?
What is what does an open source project do when they've sort of committed to having that fun?
So maybe I think plans yeah, what do we do then do we just cripple an important project?
Do we step up with some sort of funding? What are your thoughts? You?
Know it would be nice to kind of step up
Canoe PG is one of those tough ones that it's it's used a lot, but it's
Kind of a niche product still unfortunately. Yeah. Yeah
I mean it's gonna take a certain technical user to even know what it is so crowdfunding could be hard crowdfunding could be hard
And that's why it was so nice to see I mean
You know they're still getting the sixty thousand a year from the Linux Foundation
Which is great, but the Facebook's contribution would have nearly doubled that yeah
The other thing I don't quite understand is I guess stripe was also going to contribute, but they were gonna contribute along with Facebook
Or something like that, so I'm not sure how this is affected now either
But obviously these companies make a ton of money off of some of this technology
Winby do you have any reactions to this news and overall like funding of open source projects when in ways the community could step up
Well, I've heard it's been a hard winter for Facebook, and you know money's tight
And this is a lot of money, and they simply can't stretch stretch to it right yeah
No, whilst whilst you were just discussing that with Wes
I was thinking you know we've obviously got the Linux Foundation who are doing their sponsorship of critical infrastructure projects, but the
GPG
Funding wasn't through that was it these were
Organizations that just chose to sponsor the project directly. I think rather than through through the Linux Foundation
Right the Linux Foundation part of step, but yeah, but perhaps what we need is some
community
organization body foundation that people can contribute to directly and then they
Support other critical projects that are not encompassed by what the Linux Foundation is doing because obviously a lot of what the Linux Foundation is
focused on is to
Represent the interests of its members not necessarily you know the
Open source community large that might diverge from the community's interest yeah, yeah exactly yeah
So maybe we need a more community focused grassroots type you know
Some kind of proxy organization that you can yeah that you can put your money into and they then you know fund these projects
That's a really interesting idea
So how is that how do you do something like that without some sort of bias or corruption sneaking in eventually?
And you have to have a lot of people to handle that money, which is always a touchy. Yeah
Well, you'd need some tried and tested
names
Behind this you know the immediate name. I think of is you know Karen Sandler. She's got good standing in the open-source community
She's got the legal chops to deal with this. She's also horribly busy, so yeah
I think the conservancy itself is struggling to raise funds right now
Yeah, exactly exactly so but you know you'd need you'd need people like that with a proven history
Yeah with a track record, so here's here's where I'm taking this discussion is
This is our last episode of 2015 looking at 2016 and part of me
Part of me has I'm a little worried about about this particular problem. I feel like
The problem we've always worried about as Linux grows is starting to happen to us today
And that is when there's enough new users coming in that don't give a crap about the open-source
Ideology about software freedom
They don't give a crap about spreading software around the world and making a general technology platform available to all of humanity what they care
About is replacing their Mac or their Windows desktop more than anything else
And so you get people who are coming in who do not value the open-source software, and I look at it
You know there is a vocal aggressive and
Trolling isn't the right way to put it because it's worse than that because it's it's actually
harmful
there is a subset of the last audience who's still attacking us on a daily basis because
We tried to switch the Linux action show over to being produced fully under Linux and in doing so we had to reduce the full
video production scale and
We are we still are being attacked daily because of that
They don't care if it uses open source and Linux they just want to be able to see my hair in high definition
Well, we all want that I mean I understand, but it is
You know it is it's interesting to see more and more people come into this community
Some of them are coming in because of Steam some of them coming in because Windows 10 is stealing all of their privacy and backing
Up their encryption keys some of them are coming in because Mac Macs are coming with a single USB port now
There's a lot of reasons why people are coming to Linux and a lot of them are not coming because of open source
Idealism or or free software and so I don't know if we can rely on these people so the software conservancy project
Isn't being funded open SSL wasn't properly being funded until the Linux foundation steps up our own shows are being constantly pressured to be
Produced under a software that is not Linux compatible
That is not free software because the there is a larger group of people now who just don't give a shit about those things and so
I look at GNU PG which is an absolutely critical project, and I think maybe the problem is most the users couldn't give a crap
Maybe we need some 1990s Linux
Approaches you know something akin to the box sets that you used to buy for
4050 quid which had all the CDs DVDs and manuals in it
Yeah, you know what's some really good documentation. I could see that working
Yeah, but also, you know a percentage of that going back into community
projects projects that are critical to
Those operating systems and the community at large and you know Red Hat a great ambassadors for the open source community
They employ a large number of developers on different open source projects
so for all of the money that you know Red Hat are making they are channeling a lot of
resources back into open source projects
But of course, it's never going to be enough. There's always going to be something like GNU PG. Yeah, it's true
Yeah needs that needs some funding and I I don't mean to say that these new users they come over aren't potential users to
Sort of over time train them and sort of teach them
Through blog posts and mediums like podcasts with the values of open source of why it's important that that is free
So that's a possibility that they are potential
Converts of the ideology we can teach them our philosophy, but as they come in they're they're sort of the pragmatists at this point
They just want to get their job. Whatever their pragmatists are kits and you think maybe it's a consumerism thing
Yeah, I think so
It's the same reason that people go to Abercrombie and Fitch to get a t-shirt or whatever rather than you know
Go to Goodwill
Now how do you relate that to desktop Linux I
Think that people see the idea of like a Macintosh or Windows box is somehow crafted
Especially for them, even though it's not it's that kind of thing. Hmm. Hmm
I wonder in all of this if we also are suffering a little bit from our
More, you know our stark division between kernel and user space where they're like we have the Linux Foundation
I feel like a lot of you know, we talk a lot about the kernel. We talk a lot about the kernel community
But less so about the wider GNU ecosystem and a lot of you know core utils
We have celebrity projects right and whereas there's a lot of stuff that isn't sexy that you know
Makes let's let's use our wonderful kernel that maybe doesn't get that much attention
It's a good point. And so this sort of brings us to the next story
That's sort of trying to tackle this specially crafted desktop. Give it something nice
New version of solace 1.0 is out the big one. Oh is here
We've been covering it all year long on the show
We just recently did our review of the early version and I'm pretty excited about it. I key just joined us
Thanks for coming in the last minute. I think he's here now, right?
Good. I keep welcome to unplugged in that nice timing sir
Thank you very much. Yes, so come on. Don't just sit there and be quiet brag about the new release
Tell us what's awesome and tell me how the reception's been. I was to be honest with you
We didn't expect it to go the way it's gone. And I don't mean that in a bad way. I really don't so
Apart from the fact that my host is being completely derpy and I can't find out the stats myself
We've had something like 12,000 downloads already. I would imagine I've seen coverage all over the place about the release. I
Mean, I was really surprised to be honest
I mean and on the one hand they shouldn't be surprised because you know, that's kind of why you're doing it
You kind of want to spam it everywhere and get everyone to use it
It actually works though
Yeah
Well, there's a tiny bug and some people can but you know, it's the end of the year we pretend that didn't happen, right?
So I see a lot of different people posting on g-plus using it a lot of people talking about
What they like about it
So anything major change since we reviewed it on the show any other any any adaptations or improvements. Oh
Yeah, basically everything. Yeah
So we completely rewrote budget because to be fair the old one it's now technically two years old and
But the old version, I mean it was full of full of bugs and we had work around there since like early GTK version
So we took all that out
Budgie now has multiple panel support at the moment. You can have a top and a bottom panel
But we'll add left and right later on and we got a new notification
Center, which is called Raven and so your notifications get archived there at the moment. They're not interactive, but they will become that
You can configure everything there from there. So the old derpy settings dialog is completely gone
It's kind of your one-stop shop now to configure budgie. So it's kind of cool
So how has the coverage been release wise I have the blog posts and then stories that have been written up about it been pretty
Accurate on the coverage. I'm sure a lot of people must be talking about built from scratch. How a hit-and-miss. What's that like?
So we won't mention read it
I'm now the Antichrist on reddit. I feel great about it
It's an uplifting feeling sorry to God
better than being a
Yeah, I mean most of them have been really really good to be honest with you. Um, there are inaccuracies in some places
But to be fair, I was lazy about updating the site
You know, we were supposed to release on the 25th and we managed it the early hours of the 27th
Which is a lot better than our last release dates been three months late
So we did all right there two days, you know, you can you can take that. Yeah, and
some places
It just clearly not doing the research which is gonna happen. So, you know, you take the coverage first over the accuracy
That's kind of all you can do
But I mean on the whole people have been positive about it. Some people
Focuses on the wrong parts like oh you're using a different package manager. It's like it doesn't matter
You still have software in the desktop can install them. You can run them it. Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, I mean if you've really I felt like saying there is IPM in a repo if you want to install it
I didn't go that far. I'm not gonna subject anybody to that. Come on
Well, congratulations and it's been fun to watch the projects arc and I you know
You kind of had hinted there might be a present from Santa
It was a little late, but nonetheless it's still really it's still landed in the rough time timeline
So I think I kind of had a bit too much beer. I think and was maybe a little bit late
But we made it hangover or not. We got there, you know, very good. Well, congratulations and
so
What wins the next version? Come on now? Come on now, you know once shit. Well, I always shit. Yeah
Will be we will be putting out minor releases. Yeah, and the first minor release is going to be in January. Okay, that's pretty soon
Yeah, yeah. Yeah
Very cool guys. Well, congratulations. I think we're all looking forward to seeing this. Yeah, you know a new member of the ecosystem
Yeah, yeah. Well done. I key. Yeah, keep us posted. Thank you very much. It's always fun to see a new one
Oh born exactly
Yeah
And you guys have been you guys been doing a great job spreading the word on gplus and all that and the blog
Post looks really good. So yeah, great stuff
All right. Well, then let's take a minute to tell you something else. That's extremely great. That's my friends over digital ocean
Did you know about my friends over digital ocean? Oh
you go check out do yo cuz I got the droplets and
You can use our promo code do unplugged to get a $10 credit do unplugged one word lowercase over digital ocean a simple cloud hosting
Provider dedicated giving you the best Linux rig all on SSDs using KVM. Whoo
That's what makes up a droplet because they take super great hardware tier 1 bandwidth
Data centers all over the world and they let you do it all in less than 55 seconds
The pricing plans you get a whole server spun up less than 55 seconds pricing plans start up five dollars a month
Get your 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD cuz
One CPU and a terabyte transfer. I'm not even playing Wes a terabyte and you know, we say that we say terabyte of transfer
We say to your one bandwidth, but it it's really there. Yeah, it is a it makes a big difference over the holidays
I wanted to you know, watch some stuff. We weren't with some friends of mine. We weren't in the same location
I wanted to watch a synchronized stream. I spun up a do droplet stalled engine X
Installed the RTMP module nice to send an RTMP stream up there and bam
Yeah, we actually do that pretty often when we're on location. It's great
It's amazing and you know, or I use it all the time. Is it just a proxy?
You know, I don't have a good link to somewhere. Yeah spin up a droplet download it there. Oh, yeah, absolutely
I use that all the time for the rover all the time
There's some and when you use the promo code deal unplugged you get the $10 credit
You can run that $5 rig two months for free
Speaking of engine X they have a recent tutorial. I was posted on the 17th how to secure engine X with let's encrypt
Yeah, so your favorite. Yeah, exactly
So if you want to use let's encrypt on a boon to 1404, they've got a really great guide up a digital
I have tons of good guides tons of stuff
So they have one-click deployment of apps like entire stacks of applications in some cases and then for the stuff where they don't just have
A one button they have really good tutorials because they pay people to write these and then they have full-time editors to edit them
It's really good stuff and it really takes it's like it takes the best of the arch wiki and brings it to your service provider
But it's even better than it shows how much they care about the community, you know
Like they're not just here to make money. They do obviously and they should yeah
But they really give a lot back and they don't lock these down to be do specific either, right?
She's pretty cool. There's quickly becoming some of the top hits on Google a lot of these questions
Yeah, I think that's probably their strategy and then why you the way you do that is by making really good content
Exactly digital ocean comm use the promo code do unplug to go spin up a rig
There's lots of cool stuff you can do with it and a big thank you digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged program for all
of 2015
Do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do-do thanks guys and thanks you guys out there listening for using that promo code do unplug
Cuz well, that's what keeps them coming back
Keep spinning up those droplets and that's how we're able to show up and buy beer for this show. Let's be honest
Digital ocean comm use the promo code d a one plugged. Thanks digital ocean
Okay. So have you heard of North Korea's?
Operating system called red star OS before today had you heard of it before today?
I had but I never used it before today. We talked about a little bit a long time ago
Yeah, you actually used it.
What was that process like?
Actually, it was surprisingly easy.
Did you have to torrent it?
And then, or did they have direct downloads, or like?
Actually, I found there was a direct download
in one of the links,
and actually downloaded very quickly,
faster than some Linux distributions, actually.
Nice.
It's just an ISO file, loaded it up in a virtual machine,
and it's kind of the, you know,
the similar Ubuntu installer that they've copied over.
Yeah, okay.
But I was able to, even though it was entirely in Korean,
I was able to click through it,
get it installed, and boot it up.
It does have an English mode
if you can find it in the installer.
So it's based on, I believe, Fedora.
But they've taken so much stuff
from so many different operating systems,
it's really kind of remarkable.
It's a science experiment.
There's clearly a lot of engineering work
that went into it. Yes.
They've built their own quote unquote virus scanner,
which runs all the time,
but it's not actually even a virus scanner,
it's a pattern matching scanner.
So if you put documents on your system
that have certain phrases in them,
it immediately deletes them, instantly.
I gotta try that.
There's a lot of really interesting things
in this operating system.
And so two German researchers, Florian and Nicholas,
I think is how you say his name,
pulled apart the North Korean operating system,
which closely resembles Mac OS X in far as its look.
Very much like an older version of Mac OS X
when the brushed metal thing was really popular.
This was at the Chaos Communications Club in Hamburg.
They say, we found that the features implemented
in Red Star OS were the wet dream
of a surveillance state dictator.
How about that?
So, because it is a traditional Linux OS,
I figured we probably, just as Linux users,
would be kind of curious what's under the hood.
So I grabbed a few clips,
and this first clip tells us what is just the core use,
what's at the core just from a standard
Linux desktop perspective of Red Star.
If you look into the operating system,
it's basically a fully featured general desktop system,
you might imagine.
It's based on KDE and Fedora, as I already said,
and it tries to mimic the look and feel of Mac OS X.
You have an email client, a calendar, a word processor,
you've got QuickTime and all of that stuff.
You even have a disk encryption utility
that Will Scott has shown last year.
They implemented additional kernel modules,
and they touched a lot of kernel modules, so.
Oh, hi.
The kernel modules is kind of an interesting thing
in particular.
I might circle back to that in a moment.
They went through and dug through a lot of this stuff,
and what you have is you have a whole system
that has a whole series of protected files
that can't be touched,
and some of these protected files are backend daemons,
some of them are other strange things like.
I sure did a PS real quick,
and there's a lot of stuff running on your default install.
Yeah, and some of that stuff you can't stop
because of this protection system,
and there's some stuff that kind of makes sense
like some of these system files you can't change,
and there's other things that are protected,
like a WAV file that are really strange.
Quite interesting is that
when we were looking through all of this stuff,
there was a bunch of files that have a certain protection,
and they seem to be pretty important for the system,
and then there is a WAV file,
an audio WAV file that actually is protected.
It's userLibWarning.wav.
I don't know if we can hear this.
I hope that your ears are not going to explode right now.
I'll just try it.
Ah!
Do you recognize it?
I'll try it again.
Ah!
You hear that?
Can you tell what it is?
Sounds like a pig.
Yeah.
Ah!
Does anybody know what this is?
Pardon me?
A pig, exactly, and where is it coming from?
Does anybody know?
Do you have any guess where this pig noise is coming from?
I have no idea.
I don't think you'd ever guess it.
Anybody in the Mamba Room
have a guess where the pig noise came from?
It's actually kind of funny.
I've watched the videos, so I'm cheating.
Oh, okay, okay, okay.
Well, don't say it.
I'll play it, and then we'll say it.
That's stolen from Kaspersky Antivirus,
because in the older version of Kaspersky Antivirus,
if you find a virus, it actually will play this sound,
and it's exactly the WAV file from Kaspersky.
We verified this by doing checksums, okay?
So we have a copyright violation right here.
Ha ha!
I don't think anybody's going to stop that.
So yeah, it was a pig from Kaspersky Antivirus.
They have reached into every nook and cranny
of the ecosystem.
This desktop even has a QuickTime player.
They call it QuickTime player,
and didn't you say it's like located in slash applications?
Yeah, it looks like an OS X package,
but it's a Linux binary in there.
Yeah, yeah, so back to the virtual log.
Somebody was going to say something
about the pig noise, I think.
Yeah, it sounded a lot like a pig noise from Warcraft 2.
Oh yeah, that too, yeah.
I thought it was going to be like some slam
against American pigs, is what I thought it was,
and maybe it is. Unclean.
The warning comes up when you're doing something
from the West.
So then there's two processes on a Red Star OS installation
that are all about the quote unquote integrity
of the system.
They watch your system, and if you alter certain files,
there's a primary daemon, and then there's a backup daemon,
and they take dramatic action if you alter a specific file.
They're supposed to prevent tampering,
and they called it Security D.
Security D is kind of interesting
because Security D is also a process
that is known to run on the Mac OS X,
and I think that I'm not a Mac user,
and I think that Mac OS X with Security D
is kind of keeping track of certificates
and stuff like that.
So what they did is they re-implemented Security D for Linux,
and they included various plugins,
and one interesting issue with Security D
is that it comes with a library
that provides a function called Validate OS,
and what this function does is it has a hard-coded list
of files, you can see like our WAV file right here,
you can see configuration files and autostart files
for SCNPRC is the antivirus scanner,
so it checks if these files are untouched,
and if these files have been tampered with,
it initiates a reboot instantly.
So if you touch one of these files,
your machine will reboot instantly.
The same library is also used from KDM,
so during the startup process when KDM is starting,
it is also doing an integrity check,
and if it finds that one of these files
has been tampered with,
it actually immediately issues a reboot,
and the problem is that if you start tampering
with the system, you will end up in reboot loops
all of the time if you're doing your research,
because once KDM is saying reboot the system,
it's going to check it again if it's rebooted
and sees like it's still tampered with
and it's rebooting again and again and again,
and then your system is basically dead.
Super annoying.
Wow.
Yeah, and so they kind of went through in the video,
they talk about what you would have to do
to de-weaponize this thing,
and it's like this whole process of peeling an onion,
and then one of the last things is you go clean up KDM
so it stops checking to see if files have been modified too.
And you could see like if you're distributing
an operating system, integrity would be pretty important,
I suppose, of that operating system.
I'm also just imagining a free software advocate
going to a dictator in a country and telling them about
all the great things you can do with free software
and how you can customize it for exactly your use case,
be that spying on your citizens or not.
Yeah, so our next one really kind of fits in perfectly
with that whole spying on your citizens theme.
They, and this is something we covered I think a year ago,
but now we have details on how it works,
and they go into further detail in the video,
which I have embedded in the show notes.
Media files that you put on Red Star OS get watermarked
with a ID that is generated based on hardware
in your computer, so it is unique to each PC,
and then every PC that media file goes to
gets that PC's identifier appended to it.
So you could actually track it down back to the original PC
where the media file was created
and each person it was shared with.
But the most interesting thing this service is doing
is it watermarks files.
And now we are going to look deeper
into what this watermarking means.
So actually, as soon as this system will be started,
it reads your hard disk serial and then scrambles it
a little bit, and as soon as you are plugging in,
for example, a USB stick in your system,
then it will trigger a watermarking process
where it takes the serial, takes and hardcodes a death key
from the binary itself, and then encrypts it
and puts it into your file.
When you're converting this hex key
into a decimal representation,
then you see that it's actually two dates.
We actually cannot confirm what those dates mean,
but one of those matches Madonna's birthday.
Madonna's birthday?
There are rumors that some people in North Korea
might really like Madonna, but this is just speculations.
But if you have a better conspiracy theory,
then just let us know.
Because we found some pretty interesting stuff,
but we actually cannot confirm this.
So technically, the watermarks,
they have an ASCII EOF appended,
which is most likely used by the code itself
to parse the files and see if there's already
a watermark in there.
And for JPEG and RV files, for example,
it just appends this watermark to the end of the file.
And when you have a docx, for example,
then it appends it near the header
where a bunch of null bytes,
and then it just puts it in there.
So it's aware of the type of media file it's altering.
See what I mean?
This is a lot of work to make this system.
It really is.
So the watermarking itself is like,
as soon as you open a document file with the office,
then it will be watermarked.
And actually, they have code which watermarks files
even if you don't open those files.
But as soon as we saw this, it's pretty buggy.
It doesn't work every time.
But they have code for this implemented.
And mostly it works, but sometimes it just fails.
The supported types that we can confirm are docx files,
image files like JPEG and PNG and RV video files.
But the code indicates that there are several more file types
available for watermarking,
but we most likely didn't look into this.
But the most interesting thing here
is that only media files are affected.
So they don't watermark any binaries or something like that.
They're just, they're reducing their surface to files
which could be used to carry information,
which is actually, which could be used to put information
for your free speech purposes.
And actually what we think is that
this is not a security feature,
so they're actually trying to watermark
free speech in general.
So that every time you might have a document file,
an image or a video file,
then they want to know who had this file
and they watermark it so they can track
the origin of the file.
And they show a visualization of a program
they were able to put it into
and generate essentially a social connections graph
of all of the computers that this had visited.
And they say it's entirely possible
that these files would have visited.
They say it's entirely possible that Red Star OS
could send that ID back to some central server
so they would know which machine ID is tied to which IP.
They wouldn't even have to come hunt down the machine,
they'd just know what house it's at.
And they use an internal IP scheme, 10.1.something.
Right, yeah, at least they're using a private subnet,
that's nice.
The whole country.
That's crazy.
The whole country's behind an app.
And the web browser is a Firefox fork
and it's like a Firefox 3.0 fork,
the one they looked at.
They have a newer version out now
but the researchers didn't get a chance to look at it.
The only SSL root servers it has support for
are North Korean ones.
And it's just set to use all North Korean URLs
and I couldn't even quite get a DHCP provided address
on my network so maybe I'll have to change that
and see if it's in 10 slash eight, maybe it'll work.
Isn't that interesting that it seems like the DHCP client
didn't even fire up when you tried it.
And then they don't let you have root, so.
You know, here's the reality,
is you are giving the distro maker root access
when you set up a Linux box.
And anything they do, so like this thing,
it automatically detects when thumb drives are connected,
immediately mounts them, immediately scans all of the files.
I mean it is very aggressive.
Couple of things though that I thought were interesting
that you might jump out at you
as something you might not expect.
IP tables is installed, turned on, and configured by default
to be protected, to protect the machine.
Wow.
There was a couple other things
that I thought was kind of interesting.
Snort, the intrusion detection system,
installed by default, configured
with some really reasonable defaults,
not actually turned on, but just ready to be flipped on,
and you have an IDS on your rig.
They also included a well-known open source
desktop encryption app.
I'm blanking on the name, it's a GTK app,
I believe it starts with a B.
And I'm messing up with Becerra right now.
And it is legitimately a encryption tool
that allows users to encrypt their files on RedStar OS,
and they can't even find a back,
like they don't see any indication there's a back door.
It's a really useful actual application.
Yeah, their summarization was,
even the North Korean government realizes
that forcing back doors into software is futile
and just gonna make you vulnerable,
so they don't even, even North Korea doesn't bother
trying to inject back doors,
which I thought was a little slam at North Korea.
It sounds like maybe, I'm sure they're using it
for their regular citizens, but these kind of things
make it sound like they're probably also gearing it
for their military use, state use.
Definitely, in fact, they said there's very, very few
web-facing North Korean web servers
that are publicly web-facing,
but one that they did find publicly facing
was running RedStar OS.
Wow. Yeah.
So, I guess the most recent version
hasn't been publicly posted,
so there is one version newer that's in North Korea
that's based on newer stuff,
like it's not based on the 2.6 kernel or something like that.
So, Chris, any chance that Noah and Chris
review RedStar OS?
That would be funny.
That would be, oh boy, what an idea, actually.
That would be a good April Fools episode.
It sure would.
Save that one in the bank, that's not bad.
I like that.
So, Aiki, I didn't happen to be implying
that maybe you're not the trustworthy sort,
but it's true, right?
You distro makers, you really have root access to my box.
Yep.
Yeah.
And I don't know, there's a lot of people out there
that may not really think about that
when they're trying these one-off distributions.
Why should I trust a guy like you, Aiki?
What's going on?
Is it just because Josh hangs out with you?
I like Josh.
No, I mean, mostly I've got a really awesome hat
and I do look pretty good in jeans,
so I mean, those stand for my character more than anything.
I agree.
Your logic has convinced me.
The truth is, no matter what operating system you're using,
if you're downloading from a repository
and you're not the maintainer,
then you're inherently trusting someone
with root access, typically, so.
Yeah, and you know, some of the tools they use
to see if their operating system was spying on them,
for example, was they would just really,
like one of the first things that tipped them off,
it's really simple and straightforward,
they put a thumb drive with a text document
in a Red Star OS machine and never opened it,
and when they ejected it and put it back in another machine,
the file size was slightly larger.
And they're like, well, we never even opened the file.
And so then they realized after analyzing it that it was,
so there's just some basic tools they're using
to determine if the system's spying on them.
So the nice thing is, is while they were capable
of using free software to do this,
to surveil their public and to sort of monitor speech,
also free tools were used to discover it and reveal it.
So that's sort of the positive side of it, too.
It really is.
Any other thought, oh yeah, Aiki, go ahead.
Yeah, so on the serious side of it,
there's a few things that we can do.
Now, in terms of delivery from us to the users,
I mean, I know the problem is that we could be evil
ourselves, but from us to the users,
every single package has a hash in the index,
and we only use SSL on the repo, so I mean,
that's one part, they know it'll only be us who compromises.
But on the other side of it, we are open source,
and all of our infrastructure is completely transparent.
We've got build instructions out there,
so anyone can take a package from the Solace repo,
they can build it exactly the same way that we do it,
and they can see every individual comment
that went into making an update that they got.
So that would be one thing that would kind of mitigate
the concerns for people.
They can actually see what we're doing in real time.
Yeah, yeah, Red Star's being developed behind closed doors.
That's a pretty big difference, isn't it?
Yeah, good points.
All right, anyone else in the moment room
have any closing thoughts?
Yes, I do on this.
Yeah, yeah.
So not only do the distro makers have root access,
really anybody that makes a RPM or a deb package,
because those things have setup scripts inside them too.
Yeah, they do. Yes, they do.
Yeah, that's one of the reasons why you have folks
that are trying to work on installing applications
inside sandboxes.
That's part of the reason sandboxing brings some security,
not just when the application's running
in case the application has a vulnerability,
but installation time as well.
It's probably something that'll come up in 2016.
I think it will.
Speaking of things that might happen in 2016,
I bet that's one we'll actually see
somebody working a lot more on.
All right, well, I want to follow up on the canoe,
and I also want to talk about scale,
because scale's getting crazy.
I can't believe it.
So before we do that, I'm going to mention Linux Academy.
Talk about something else you could do in 2016.
Bring your skill level up a little bit,
and Linux Academy's the place to go.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
They've been sponsors of the unplugged program now
for a while, and all of a sudden,
they're also now on those jerks over at Linux Action Show.
I don't know who those guys are,
but Linux Academy is a platform created by Linux
and open source enthusiasts.
In fact, I think it's a pretty brilliant idea,
because I've definitely noticed over the years
that you can suss out somebody who's not really
a genuine open source enthusiast or Linux user,
somebody who's more of like getting into it
to make money off of it.
You definitely notice this when you go to the cons.
You really see like there's companies out there
that make money off the open source ecosystem.
And then there's companies out there
that are part of the open source ecosystem.
They work in there, they follow it,
it's their day-to-day stuff, they live and breathe it,
they advocate it.
Those are the kind of people that make really great content
for other people like that.
And that's where Linux Academy stands.
They are crazy passionate about Linux and open source,
and they wanted to do something
to spread the word about Linux,
and to do something in the content space,
and they just happened to figure out
a pretty good revenue model.
Not like I have.
I think they did a better job than I did.
They might be smarter than you.
They might be, they might be.
You can get smart too by going to
linuxacademy.com slash unplug.
Scenario-based labs, almost 2,000 comprehensive
study guides with videos, instructor help on demand,
seven plus distros you choose from.
It automatically adjusts the courseware
and the virtual servers.
Did I mention that instructor help?
Because that's actually a huge deal.
So it's not just like, okay, go punch some buttons,
and then good luck with everything.
It's like, here's some genuinely good content
by people who really care.
Oh, and if you get stuck, instructor help is available.
That's what makes the difference for me,
because I feel like there's a lot of us,
and we kind of feel like, well, we're smart,
we know computers, I should be able to read
the man pages and figure it out,
but sometimes you want to learn stuff,
and you want to learn it quick,
and you want to learn it well,
and they have real experts to help you.
And that is really a competitive advantage
that a lot of online learning services
cannot compete with, and I think what's genuinely great
about that is the specific type of subject material
is even more challenging for most of these places
to deal with, and this is their bread and butter.
And it's the entire technology stack around Linux
and open source, including AWS,
all of the Red Hat certifications
if you want to get out and work in that space,
OpenStack, Ubuntu, your basic Linux stuff,
your advanced Linux stuff, all of it,
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
They've been improving it all throughout 2015,
and they continue to improve.
Check them out and support the show
by going to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Thanks, Linux Academy, for the year of support.
Man, you guys rock it, you rock it.
All right, so I want to just take a moment
before we get into all the other stuff.
We'll do the Canoe follow-up here in a second, too,
but another little bit of follow-up
from a discussion we had a couple of weeks ago.
You see this rumor that Mozilla is working on a tablet,
a stick, and a keyboard, oh, and also a router.
Oh, boy.
Yeah, Firefox OS is far from dead.
It's not dead yet at all.
They have a tablet that's gonna be just a web browser,
it's total focus on simplicity, called the Firefox Pad.
It's like just a web browser tablet.
Then they're gonna have like a Chromecast thing,
and they're gonna have a Firefox OS router.
And, and a keyboard, which I believe
may have a Raspberry Pi in it.
So it's like a keyboard with a built-in Raspberry Pi
running Firefox OS.
So you could just plug that keyboard
into a screen or whatever and there you go?
Yeah, this is coming from FirefoxCentral.com.
They say this is an exclusive.
So an Apple TV Chromecast competitor, a router,
a keyboard with a built-in Raspberry Pi,
a tablet that does nothing but run a web browser,
no app store, no telephony, automatic updates.
What do you think?
Is this a scary wandering Mozilla,
or is this maybe the thing to double down on?
Well, I think it's already a scary wandering Mozilla,
but I have mixed views.
I feel like some of these are better than others.
I don't know about the tablet.
I think the tablet space is already kind of difficult
and hard to compete in, and people have a lot of tablets.
What if they get like around 99 bucks?
It's just, here's your web browser tablet.
That might be a great tool for kids who don't do a lot,
but they just wanna check Facebook or whatever.
It's just a flesh wound.
The Chromecast competitor and the router,
I'm definitely interested in.
The router is kind of interesting, isn't it, actually?
And you know what?
The Chromecast thing is what I would totally be down for.
Because I love the Chromecast model, but it's so hard
to shoe hone your own media in there,
and it's such a closed ecosystem.
Firefox would present a much more open playground.
I would buy one.
If they shipped a Firefox stick.
Yep, I would buy two.
Yeah, they could charge me probably 60, 80 bucks, maybe.
99 bucks, maybe.
I'd say 50, but you're a big spender, Chris.
No, I'm thinking, I wouldn't.
But I would support Mozilla, I guess.
Yeah, exactly.
I bought a backpack from them and a shirt before
because I wanted to support them.
So I could kind of see maybe spending
a little extra to support the project
if they would let me.
But yeah, 50 bucks would be great.
25 bucks would be nailin' it.
Yes, it would.
Yeah, all right, NorthRanger.
What are your thoughts on this?
Well, you know, I really appreciate Mozilla
for their efforts to keep the web open.
But it's kind of a funny point in their history
where they didn't succeed in getting embedded
with other software projects that needed a browser.
They kind of defaulted or seeded that market to WebKit.
So are they trying to kind of do one up on WebKit
and say, well, we're not just gonna give you
the browser engine to build your products around.
We're gonna give you whole OS
to build your project around?
I think it's more of a direct-to-consumer thing.
I think it's more of, well, we tried working with LG
and all these other folks.
Now we're gonna just make a few devices and ship them.
I think it feels, I don't know.
So they say it also does include Panasonic TV.
So that's not totally true actually.
But yeah, I wonder if that's true.
I don't think it is that.
I don't think this is, I think this is a new approach.
I think that brings up the larger question too
of how they tie it into the rest of the Firefox experience
or ecosystem or, you know,
if they do have a success with this,
how do they ensure that that helps
the rest of their brand?
I'll tell you, if they had a really good handoff
between the Firefox web browser on the desktop
or your mobile and the Firefox web browser tablet.
So if this thing's 99 bucks, let's say.
And let's say it's got like a 10-inch
or larger widescreen display.
And it's got maybe an all-day battery.
And this thing is a touch of a button
and your web browser's ready to go
and everything you were just looking at on your desktop
is now available on your tablet or vice versa.
You could go from tablet to desktop.
If they nailed that using Firefox or Mozilla Sync, whatever,
and this thing's running Firefox OS,
I think there's some people in this audience right now
that go, well, you know what, I don't need the iPad.
I don't need the Android tablets
that constantly disappoint me
because number one thing I do on that Android tablet,
I run Chrome.
And so I'm not speaking for me.
I'm just saying this sounds like somebody,
this sounds like a likely scenario.
And if the number one thing you're using your browser for,
your tablet for right now is Chrome or Safari,
well, maybe this works really well for you,
especially if you're already a Firefox user.
They gotta do something because I keep seeing stories
about how Firefox's browser share
has been shrinking for years now.
And I don't wanna live in a world without Mozilla.
I don't think I'm ready for that.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
Anybody else, WWE, do you have any thoughts?
Anybody else have thoughts before we wrap up?
I'm thinking that maybe they learned something crucial
from the Firefox OS phone
and maybe they figured out, okay,
maybe we should go desktop and get more users
but make it so it could be mobile
so people could take it with them somewhere else
and use someone else's keyboard and mouse or whatever.
Maybe they're trying something different
that will work out for them in the long run, I hope.
Well, this is what I find interesting.
Maybe out of all of this is the Firefox Pie.
And if you would have talked to me a couple of weeks ago,
I would have found this to be maybe the least interesting.
But now since we've talked to Wimpy and he says,
the version of Ubuntu Mate for Raspberry Pi is super popular.
We got this canoe in that it makes the Raspberry Pi
like a ready to go computer kit
that really just means you don't plug a few things together
like building Legos and you have a full computer.
I look at this Firefox Pie and the bullet points are,
the target market is education and emerging markets.
Education is brilliant.
For creation, not just consumption of the web.
Keyboard, computer form factor
with built-in keyboard and trackpad.
Can plug into spare TV or monitor.
E.g. millions of obsolete analog TVs in India.
Mozilla web maker built-in.
Harnesses the maker movement, which is a funny bullet point.
Yes, it is.
And partnership with Raspberry Foundation
and or the canoe?
Question mark.
So let's shift over and talk about that first.
Oh, I don't have my webcam working.
That's too bad.
I don't have, oh, hello, hello.
So anyways, right here in studio, we have the canoe,
which we talked about on the episode
right before the holidays of Linux Unplugged.
It is a very cool piece of kit
that makes the Raspberry Pi a ready to go computer
and listener FilesCopied said this
because he thought this might pique my interest.
FilesCopied, how did you hear about the canoe
and what made you decide to send it in?
Oh, the main way I found it,
I had a friend that was trying to get someone interested
in learning about computers
and all the toys that she was looking at,
I was like, they're just toys.
I wanted to find like a real Linux kit.
I knew something had to exist.
And so you started your search and you came across this
and it's an actual ready shipping to go product.
And so you sent it into the studio,
you sent us a heads up,
but I got the box like the day we went on air
and the email I didn't read till like the day
after we went on air.
I didn't know who sent it in, so it was great.
We tracked him down, we got FilesCopied here.
I played with it a little bit
and my impressions were this is really slick.
It's still more work though than the Firefox Pi,
but what it made me realize is this is ready for my kids.
The Raspberry Pi, once you get this,
like they could assemble this,
my six-year-old I think could put this together
and he would have a Linux Raspberry Pi
and the idea of the Firefox Pi is like maybe the solution
for Chromebooks in education, possibly.
You know, you get something that's ready to go,
20, 30 bucks with a keyboard and everything,
that could be pretty portable.
Yeah, we'll see.
I mean, there's still a lot of other factors
like marketing and deals and all that kind of stuff
to make something like that,
but I don't know if I like the idea
of the Mozilla Foundation being people behind it,
but I still want to see where it goes.
Right, and I wonder how much Mozilla can manage
a transformation, because I just think
about the days before Chrome existed
and I remember being a little surprised
how Google's making web browsers.
I mean, it made sense given their agenda,
but they've managed to kind of transform themselves
from what they were into owning Android and Chrome
and so much and I wonder if there's any chance Mozilla can,
maybe there's a future where Mozilla makes a great router
and I trust them with my internet infrastructure.
That would be really great.
And you want a cheap computer that doesn't have
like an advertising monster behind it.
And it's a first class web client.
And it comes with web creation software.
Right.
Mumble, have any closing thoughts?
Go on, once. I do.
Yeah, go ahead.
I think they're spreading themselves too thin.
That's my concern, too.
You think that's a valid concern?
Yeah, it's just like the most recent upgrade
to the Mozilla browser, for whatever reason,
just decided to not work with Google.
Is that their fault though or is that Google's fault?
I don't know.
Yeah.
I know that like I'll be on Google Plus
or YouTube or whatever and either the page won't load
or the page will just stop loading.
And then I'll close the browser, open it back up.
Sometimes it works, sometimes it doesn't.
Don't know what's going on there.
Yeah, I hope, so here's my, I'm very conflicted.
And I hope people aren't getting tired of this
because I'm actually, my stance on this is starting to change
as we do these episodes.
I initially would have taken the hard line.
They need to focus on the browser
and focus on Thunderbird even.
Right.
But now, when you look at the undeniable trend,
I think it's, Wes, I don't know if you remember the number.
I think definitely 2011,
but I think maybe even possibly since 2009,
Firefox browser market share has been on a decline.
Yeah.
And that's the reality of the market.
And the thing is, is what's pushing that too
is also mobile to a degree
which they have very little foothold in.
And so they are just literally now dealing
with a new market reality.
And they have to make some adjustments at some point
to stay a viable company.
Not that they're about to die and go away,
but you need to get ahead of the puck.
You gotta have the momentum to keep going.
Exactly, and you gotta start early
in some of these new emerging marketplaces
and in a lot of things, done right,
there is demand for that
because right now these things
like these Internet of Things devices are just a mess
and they're a hot mess at that.
So if you could have a trusted name
that has a trusted brand come in and offer some devices,
they could have a foothold.
And I wonder if they can play up the foundation aspect.
I'm sure there are competitors to Google
that are worried about having too much investment
in this other company.
Mozilla might be a more neutral party
where you can be like, well, we use their stuff
because they don't have an agenda against this.
Or even if they just shipped a couple of these things
and they were good.
Let's just say they shipped the Stick and the Raspberry Pi
because that Firefox Pi just,
Raspberry Pi is just complicated.
It's like you could make that today.
Yeah, and the Raspberry Pi is being built for you.
If they could ship those
and they were really well received,
then maybe your Panasonic's and your LG's
would be willing to sort of have a more serious conversation
about shipping a good product.
A proven record.
Yeah, but we'll see.
We'll see where it goes with that.
All right, so I got a little more to cover.
We've got some big stuff coming up in just,
well, January, which is just around the corner.
Like literally around the corner.
Sure is.
Holy smokes, Wes.
Holy smokes.
What are you doing in January?
Got anything big coming up in January, Wes?
No, I don't.
But I think that means that I have some exciting projects
I need to finish.
Well, well, we got some exciting stuff
coming up in January.
So you will be probably involved in some way or another
with some of these shenanigans.
I hope so.
Yeah, yeah.
And I'll tell you about that.
But first, I'm gonna tell you about our friends over at Ting.
You know, I was talking to Kyra over the holidays,
as I do.
Well, you guys are besties.
Yeah.
Well, she's an Overcast fan.
And I was, so I called her and I said,
Kyra, I noticed you had some podcasts
and your Overcast subscription,
but I didn't see Linux Action Show,
didn't see Linux Unplugged, so I had to talk to her
about that.
You know, I squared her away.
Just a little, you know, slap on the wrist.
Don't worry, don't worry, it's not a big deal.
But you know what, Kyra works over at Ting,
and I love Ting.
Let me tell you about Ting.
Ting is mobile that makes sense.
It's a flat rate, it's really simple.
Six dollars for the phone every month.
That's all you pay.
And then it's just your usage on top of that.
So if you don't use a line, then you don't pay anything.
And if you use a little more data one month,
or a couple of months,
then the other 10 or 11 months of the year,
you'll use less and you pay way less.
So it sort of adapts to your actual usage.
So for me, that usually means in April I have a spike,
and around the holidays I sometimes have a spike.
But for the majority of the year,
my cell bill for three lines is around 40 bucks.
That's amazing.
Hard to beat.
That is really hard to beat.
And the thing I love about Ting is they have
two networks to choose from.
So you can just be a little savvy.
They got the GSM and CDMA networks.
So if you have a phone that's compatible
with one of those networks,
you can get a $25 service credit
by going to linux.ting.com.
You also support the show.
And if you don't have a Ting device yet,
you can get $25 off a device by going to linux.ting.com.
Unlocked devices, great devices.
I love that they now have the brand new Nexus 6P
and the Nexus 6, the first Nexus 6,
because check this out.
Now it's $350.
Boy, that is like half off.
Yeah, on Ting, unlocked, direct updates from Google,
Android M, pay for what you use, right?
And then they also, if you want a great value Android phone,
the LG Volt 2, lollipop 5.1, tri-band LTE,
five inch display, $183, no contract,
unlocked, pay for what you use.
That's crazy.
Ting!
Linux.ting.com, linux.ting.com, go check them out.
Also, they have an early termination relief program.
If you got stuck in one of those duopoly contracts,
you can find out more about that on their website.
Just get started by going to linux.ting.com.
And a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring
the Unplugged program.
Thank you Ting, thank you Ting, thank you very much.
Okay, Wes, so it was like last week or two
I got talked into trying to go to scale this year.
You just couldn't resist.
Frickin' scale 14, January 21st through the 24th
in Pasadena Convention Center.
And Mr. P4, P3R, in the Linux Action Show subreddit
started a semi-official scale 14 thread.
And if you're going, I invite you to check out this thread
and give us the details.
So is it official now?
Does that make it official?
Well, we're workin' on it.
So, you know, budget-wise it's extremely tight
because in April Linux Fest Northwest is a big deal for us
and that's where we spend pretty much all the money
we make in a year.
That's a first class production.
Yeah, so this being in January is super tight,
but we're, and oh, oh, oh, oh, and to make matters worse,
right during Noah's wife's birthday.
Ooh.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
But we really, it seems like it's becoming
a pretty big event.
And so we're gonna try to make it down there,
one way or another.
I don't know yet.
Still trying to work out the details
on how I'm gonna do that.
But I'm trying to get a sense of how big the audience
is gonna be, presence-wise, down there.
And so that thread's there.
And we might move that into a meetup thread at some time
if we get a lot of interest.
So I'll have it linked in the show notes.
I should probably put it in the chatroom, too.
Wes, do you mind dropping that in the chatroom
when you get a chance?
I would be happy to.
Thank you, sir.
Is anybody in the Mamba Room going to scale?
Nobody?
I know Poby's gonna go, but he's not here today.
I'm wondering, I'm curious to see,
because we don't, for a bit we were considering not going,
just because of the cost,
because we go to so many other shows.
But I think it's a big enough event,
and with UbiKon happening a little bit beforehand.
So we have the official scale thread started.
It's over there.
You can go check that out.
Go show your support.
See if you'll be there.
Sure.
Make it a good event.
So a couple other things that I want to talk about,
just sort of, now it's just towards the end of the show.
I got the fire going.
It's just you.
So warm and cozy.
You, the Mamba Room,
couple hundred of our closest friends listening now.
I'm sure most people downloading
probably are gonna tune out here in a couple of minutes.
So I'm just gonna have a little chit chat with you guys.
A little fireside chat.
So we're gonna make some changes
on the Linux Action Show coming up pretty soon.
Whoa.
Yeah.
And we're gonna tell you about it
on Sunday's Linux Action Show.
We're doing the Linux Action Show on Sunday this week,
because of New Year's.
So that will be on January 3rd.
And I invite you to tune in.
I'm excited already.
We can talk about that kind of stuff.
Get your feedback live in the chat room.
And we're gonna make that pretty integral
with the show experience.
So I'd love to have you there live, if you can,
on January 3rd.
We're gonna do it at 10 a.m. Pacific time.
You can go to jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar.
But I'll just give you a hint.
Just give you a hint.
You're gonna be seeing a lot more of us.
That's all I'm gonna say.
I'm just gonna say that.
Oh.
I don't want you to take that for what it is.
Mystery.
Yeah, yeah.
So there you go.
Wes, I hope you have a good New Year's.
Oh, I sure will.
Yeah?
You got any big plans?
I'm thinking about seeing some friends in Portland.
Really?
Yeah.
That's a good, that'll be a good drive.
A little New Year's road trip.
Yeah.
It's gonna be like a fun time.
So I'm thinking, going back to scale real quick,
I'm thinking while I'm at scale,
depending on, so here's the thing.
It goes from the 21st to the 24th, right?
In January.
Okay.
And UbiCon's like on the 20th or something like that.
I would love to take the rover down.
I just don't know how it works out timing-wise
because I got so much going on in the month of January.
I got family stuff, I got my daughter's birthday,
I got my birthday, I also got some business stuff
going on.
Oh, it's your birthday.
That's good to know.
And it scales right in the middle of all of it.
So it's just really crazy.
But if I go down there,
I would probably be doing Linux Unplugged from the road.
So it'd be one of those where you could be in studio.
Hey, hey, hey.
I like, those are fun.
Those are fun.
Yeah.
And then Kernel Linux will be making out there midweek
and we'll probably record a Linux action show from there too.
Maybe, maybe not, depending on the timing.
Now looking at the calendar, we actually might not.
So yeah, we're not gonna do a booth.
Okay, so you'll be free floating.
Yeah, oh man, that's my favorite.
I don't know, we might not ever do a booth again
except for at Linux Fest Northwest.
Yeah.
It is-
Well, you're a staple there.
I mean, you have to.
Well, and it's fun to do the two-day broadcast.
I suppose that would be sort of the line
is if we're gonna do a multi-day broadcast,
then you kind of have to have a booth.
But if you're going there to get clips and do interviews,
it's all much better to be walking around.
Right, you get the real experience
of what someone else at the conference would be.
Yeah, yeah.
All right, so anyways, join that.
We'll have that thread over there.
And I hope you guys, if you're gonna make it,
can leave a comment in there.
And I also hope you have a great holiday.
Happy New Year's to everybody in the bubble room.
As we wrap up here, does anybody have
one big prediction for Linux in 2016?
Anybody have one they wanna, if you do,
ping me in the IRC with the mum prefix.
Do you have any big predictions for 2016, Wes?
You have anything you've been kicking around?
Big predictions.
Yeah, I know, it's hard when you actually go to get it,
when you actually go to just do it on the spot.
It's one of those, like,
and they come to me while I'm driving around,
and I'm like, oh, that's totally gonna happen.
And I write it down.
I think Ubuntu 16.04 is gonna be a powerful release.
I think that's gonna be one of the releases
that shapes the Linux ecosystem for the next,
you know, three or four years.
It looks like Wimpy and the gang did theirs
in Ubuntu podcast season eight, episode 42.
We did.
So I'll have to have a listen.
I will, I will, I'll have to have a listen.
And then Ham Radio, you have a big prediction for 2016.
He says that you're the Linux desktop.
I thought he was in the moment room.
But yeah, oh, well, look at Ikey dropping some,
look at that, wow, look at that.
He's trying to get, he has a,
Ikey, you have a challenge with Mark Shuttleworth?
Now we've completely gone off rails.
Let's hear it, let's hear it.
This'll be a good ending note.
You saw it on G+, right?
No, I don't think I did see it.
You can drop us a link, though.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, did you do a throw down publicly with,
because I'm sure he'll respond, because, you know.
Well, I mean, it was more in humor,
but the way it started out is somebody was saying
about 32-bit UEFI and all that crap.
And I was like, okay, I'll try and get it working.
So I went down to the shop and got a tablet
and it had Windows 10 on it.
No, it didn't, it had Windows 8.
Jesus, it's bad.
Like, I don't know how you're supposed to do it.
Like, you'd need a seal to coordinate your actions
for you to use the screen.
So I had to think about it and I thought within five minutes,
well, GNOME can already do half the things
you need to do on a tablet.
So after I'd bitched about it publicly,
I put a comment there underneath,
and I said, well, during 2016,
we'll get to the end of 2016
and see who's got a better tablet-based operating system,
Solus or Ubuntu, and I didn't get a reply.
So, I mean, it was friendly,
but yeah, the challenge is still there.
All right, so maybe we'll see a tablet out of there.
If you guys have any other predictions,
if you think about it, we could cover them in the post-show,
but otherwise, that's one of the things
we will be doing on Sunday's Linux Action Show.
Wow, look at me bring it all back.
On Sunday's Linux Action Show,
we're gonna do our 2016 predictions,
an annual tradition, an annual tradition,
which means at some point,
we have to own up to past predictions,
which I guess would probably be with Matt,
I can't remember, which I haven't contacted him about,
so I'm not sure.
So we might just have to start fresh,
because I can't really hold Matt accountable
if he's not there to attest.
But I wonder how I did.
I'll have to go back,
because that's always the hard thing,
is go back and see how I did.
And you know what always really stings,
is when I go back and look at the predictions
that didn't come true, but totally should have, right?
Those are the ones that. Then you just get sad.
Yeah, like why did that happen?
Why did that happen?
All right, well that brings us to the end
of this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
Thank you very much for tuning in.
Hope you will have a fantastic New Year's.
Hope you had a great holiday.
Make sure to join us for all the Linux excitement in 2016.
No kidding.
Kick it off.
Keep it at broadcast.com slash calendar
to get it converted to your local time zone
over at jblive.tv.
Don't forget we've got that mumble room,
which you are welcome to hang out in our virtual mug.
Linux Action Show on our reddit.com
is where you go to submit topics or feedback
for episode 125.
You can also go to jupyterbroadcasting.com slash contact
and choose Unplugged from the dropdown.
And yes, I know I sound like I'm sick.
So don't have to write that in.
I'm probably gonna get like a dozen of those.
I don't want that.
I know that.
All right.
Thanks so much for tuning into this week's episode
of Linux Unplugged.
Hope you had a great 2015.
See you in 2016.
Okay.
All right.
There we go.
That is the last show of mine in 2015.
My last show.
Boom!
Done right there.
I want to give Wimpy some credit for his excellent suggestion of a hot toddy right about now.
I know, right?
What is it?
So it's Bailey's?
What else?
No, no.
They vary, they vary sort of region to region and family to family.
But the way we make ours is, we use Ribena, I don't know if you have that in the US, but
it's a blackcurrant squash.
So you put some blackcurrant squash in a mug, you add to that some freshly squeezed lemon,
a large spoon of honey, a generous measure of brandy, and then boiling water.
And then you stir all that up together and you drink it as hot as it can be.
Wow, I've never heard of that recipe.
It's a cold remedy.
You know, when you're feeling a bit bunged up, you know, it's got all the things in it,
you know, the honey to soothe your throat, the lemon for the vitamin C, the brandy to
sort of, you know, help with the chest.
For the spirit.
So, have one of those before you go to bed to help you get to sleep at night.
Sounds like a great excuse.
It does.
Or in my case, two or three, because...
And if you drink enough, you'll forget you're even sick at all.
Right, yeah.
Except for I actually have so much like sinus pressure right now that it's making me a little
dizzy as it is.
So like I had one beer that I sipped this whole episode because like I already feel
a little intoxicated.
Like I had a day quill earlier today, but I think it's worn off by now.
So I think that's why all of a sudden the sinus pressure's like boom hitting me so hard
because it's like wearing off during the show, which is like so stupid.
But I only had one thing at day quill, so there you go.
Day quill also makes me sleepy.
All right, so let me go dig out this link.
So where did you...
Oh, I slacked it to you.
Oh, you slacked it.
You slacked it.
I couldn't paste it elsewhere.
You want it right in the iris?
Yeah, if you would.
I want to go...
So let's get to the bottom of this.
Let's see if this tells me where...
Oh, shipping status.
Okay, so we'll go over to the Purism blog.
We'll check the shipping status.
Let's see, updated December 21st.
I believe I have the Rev 2 coming to me of the Librem 15.
Says it's shipping now.
I thought it was going to say never, project canceled.
We should set up a fake website.
Rev 1 shipped June 2015, sold out.
So I must not have gotten that one.
It must be Librem 15 Rev.
Then there's...
So what's going on here?
What's the difference between there is a Rev 2...
There's two Rev 2s, and one ships in January, and one is shipping now.
Do you have the hinge clutch cover?
I don't know anything about that.
All I know is I was one of the very first people to back it, and a lot of things have
changed since then.
I didn't even know they had multiple Revs, let alone different hinges.
Or whatever the HKS location is.
There's a 4K version, which is shipping February.
As much as 4K is awesome, I sincerely hope that's not the one I get, because I specifically
bought this laptop, because I need 1080p out, I need to build a mere 1080 from the machine
here to the capture machine.
And honestly, high DPI just needs another year for Linux, maybe, I don't know.
So yeah, I hope I...
I might.
We'll see.
Wimpy, what do you know?
You're the one that pointed us to this.
I know what you know now, because you've read the same blog that I have.
Not so helpful.
And I also saw a tweet earlier saying that if you'd chosen an international keyboard,
so anything other than a US or UK keyboard layout, your devices would be delayed further
still.
And if you didn't want to have those delays, then to come and change your keyboard selection.
I see.
Okay, I see a lot of the difference in the Rev2 is all about the hardware kill switch
location.
I do like kill switches.
Yeah.
So either you'll get it soon...
They don't work.
They don't work?
Do they not work?
You want to see the blog from December the 10th, where they explain they don't work.
Oh boy.
Damn it.
In the meantime, I should have just bought an Oryx Pro.
How many games do people buy in the Steam sales?
I bought a couple.
But I only...
No.
Yeah, I only bought...
I literally bought two.
How many did you get?
About 30.
Really?
Yeah, I think I only got two or three.
I had a lot of games already.
Yeah, I had about 30 games and I've got about 70 now.
Now have you tried any of them?
Yes.
I'm big into Trine at the moment.
Oh my God.
Yeah, Trine is great.
Trine is...
I've never played Trine before, so I'm on the first Trine at the moment.
Oh, I'm so excited for you.
Yeah, Trine's gorgeous.
Also playing Coffee and Dodgers as well.
I'm enjoying that a lot.
Yeah.
Did you get all the Trines?
I know Trine and...
I did.
I had a deal to get all of them for like $6 or something.
Wow.
No way.
That's a great deal.
Yeah, that's super cheap.
I need three.
I only have one and two.
Yeah, three is a little different.
It's got more of a 3D camera.
Oh.
I didn't buy it.
I was totally in awe of that.
When I started...
Because I'm not a huge gamer.
The last time I was seriously into games was sort of like PlayStation 2 era.
So when it started up, it's just like, oh, this is so pretty.
I just want to play it because it's pretty.
Yeah, it's gorgeous.
It's gorgeous.
It's so packed with things and the subtlety of motion was just like, oh, this is too nice.
Yeah.
And the mechanic of switching between different player characters is a fun one.
That's a fun mechanic.
I see here that distance is on sale if anyone wants to...
Oh, yeah.
I've got that too.
Yeah.
Yes.
Yes, very nice.
He had a jump on the top of his head, Chris.
Yeah, I figured.
I just...
I just sucked.
I need to get the controller out is what I need to do.
I ended up getting GTA 5 and The Long Dark from Hinterland, which I'm more excited about
playing because it's pretty good.
Wimpy, how's the performance been for you?
For what?
Trying.
Yeah, are you playing on the NUC?
I am.
I'm playing it on that new NUC.
So far, I've played everything on the new NUC and not had any issues.
And I'm playing it at Quad HD as well because I've got a new Quad HD.
No kidding.
Really?
Yeah.
Well, that is really cool.
I was going to say, I wonder how it would do at higher resolution, but it sounds like
it's pretty good.
Okay.
Yeah.
Well, good enough for me.
I mean, I've not actually looked to see how many frames per second it's producing because
I didn't want to sort of find that it wasn't very high and I was then annoyed by that.
So I haven't looked, but I haven't noticed anything that makes me think this isn't fast
enough or responsive enough.
But I've been using an Xbox 360 controller and I was like, hmm.
And so I've ordered a Steam controller as well now.
Look at you.
You're going all in.
That's funny.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
My daughter's getting a bit older, so I've decided I need to up my gaming skills.
It is a fun thing to do with the kids.
They really need...
Yeah.
I've got a couple of kids' games for her as well to have a play on.