This is Linux Unplugged Episode 44 for June 10th, 2014.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's yabba-dabba excited to talk
about Bedrock Linux. My name is Chris. And my name is Matt. Hey Matt, episode 44 and we've got
the founder of Bedrock Linux on the line waiting for us just to get to him. He's been patiently
here all pre-show. We've had a fun pre-show today and I'm excited to kind of uncover Bedrock Linux
a little more. It's a pretty interesting distro that we reviewed on Sunday's Linux action show.
I believe it was episode 316, if you haven't seen that one. It's not required reading but
highly suggested reading if you want to be well-rounded. And then we'll also get to some
feedback and if we've got some time. Matt, something's got me upset all day. Alienware
has slapped Linux users in the face. They've taken a trout that's like two days old and they
just slapped us all in the face with it. And I can't believe it so we're gonna get to that as
well. Plus we've got some Steam updates and a couple of other things. So good show today. I'm
excited about all this stuff. So I figured maybe if we were so inclined we'd start with our feedback
and our first email this week and we'll get to just a couple of emails and then we're gonna get
right to the Bedrock Linux stuff. But I had a couple of things I wanted to start with and the
first one came from John. John wrote in to kind of rib us Arch users. He says, hey Chris and Matt,
I just have to tease you for beginning your show by talking about Arch regressions and then go on
to worry about Mint having potential to break. Currently Linux Mint works and there are a few
problems I have with it. Yeah I might not work right on other distros but I, and I think he's
talking about Cinnamon, I honestly doubt if Clem even cares about that. A quick look at the Linux
Mint website will tell you they are self-sustaining distro then they are self-financed too. Maybe this
is Mint's way of pushing back at the ultra accelerated pace that distros like Arch rev up.
What is wrong with Debian style of a revenue distro? Maybe it's an issue of two different
worlds. One world that's building a future of Linux and then there's the world that uses Linux
to do things unrelated to the development of Linux. Those who want something that works because
it's been rigorously tested. Cheers John. So Matt do you think maybe this is the Linux Mint's push
back at these crazy rolling distro world that we seem to be moving towards? I think maybe
inadvertently. I don't think it's done on purpose or with any type of real direct push back but I
definitely think that they're going for, you know, they're going for some stability and they're also
catering to a different audience of people. Yeah and I think there is a bit of like two worlds at
play here too and I also think it's a good point that Linux Mint doesn't really need Cinnamon or
Mate to be used anywhere. It's anywhere else. I mean it's in their benefit and best interest if
it does and I'm sure they want to see it used elsewhere but they are self-funded by their users
and so that allows them the flexibility to really focus on just building what they think is best
for them and if that means creating their own desktop that only they have, if that's what Clem
believes is the way to accomplish that mission it makes sense that's what he's gonna do. So yeah,
I think it's interesting. We'll see. We'll keep watching it. I actually am really glad they're
doing it. I think it's a grand experiment because I've always, you know, I've always speculated
like if you know if I had a perfect Linux distro it would be something kind of like what Linux Mint
is doing or like elementary does where only would be more user land updates really fresh user land
but really stable base stuff as much as possible and that's essentially what we're gonna see for
Mint so it's an experiment that I've been rattling around the back of my brain for a long time and
now we're gonna see it come to life. So my cookie wrote in, my cookie, he says, hi Chris and we got
this a lot and this is just a nice concise question so I wanted to get to this. On a previous
Unplugged you hinted that Chase might end up on Linux Mint after thinking on what to choose. Yet
once I watched the episode he ended up on Ubuntu. Why did Chase choose Ubuntu over Linux Mint? Now
I wanted to get to this here because we've talked a lot about how to Linux here in the show and the
current format of how to Linux is really the representation of months and months of thinking
like and then Chase you know thinking about swishing and so we've come to a lot of we've
had a lot of discussions and conclusions outside the show and then what you see in the show is the
manifestation of all that work and the essential reason was we figured a lot of people watching
will be starting there we're not sticking with any one particular distribution and Chase kind of
felt like because the choice is so overwhelming he was he was willing to hold off on making full
gone conclusions and try out Ubuntu see what he thought and then also be willing to try the thing
so you have to stay tuned to find out what happens there my cookie but we one of the biggest biggest
pieces of feedback was why didn't you put the explanation in the show it's because we'd already
decided before the show and it is just a process and we wanted to make it quick because we feel a
lot that's where a lot of people are gonna start so thanks for asking my cookie Matt before we get
on before we get onto the rest of the show and we got one more email I want to stop right here
and think ting that's right go over to Linux dot ting comm that'll save $25 off your first device
or $25 off your first month of service and we got an email came in from Brad he says dear Chris and
Brad I've switched to ting I've been saving for I've been saving up for a phone so I could make
the switch and I finally accumulated the scratch and bought a Nexus 5 booyah I've been getting
boned by t-mobile for years now and now I'm free free I say I mean it was like walking in McDonald's
and paying for nine hamburgers and only eating one every month what the who does that I activated my
phone entirely online in like ten minutes and like Chris likes to say Bob indeed was made my uncle
with ting I'm totally only paying for what I use which isn't much and currently with the last
discount I get the first month for free I actually end up only oh I'm sorry I only ended up owing
them a buck seriously a buck a friggin dollar so thanks gentlemen if you're ever in LA I owe you a
cupious amounts of beer sincerely Brad and his last name is pronounced kale oh like the healthy
snack so go over to Linux dot ting comm to check it out ting why is ting different because there's
no contracts there's no early termination fee and like Brad said you only pay for what you use it's a
flat six dollars plus whatever the man's gonna put on top of that he's got to get his cut he or
she the man's really not an actual person and then it's just your usage so your megabytes your
messages your minutes whatever buckets you fall into after all that's added up that's what you pay
and be like Brad I recommend go get the Nexus 5 $349 that's you own it price that's not you
spreading the cost out over two years that's what you own and just like when you buy yourself a
computer you'll want to own it it's your device that's what's great about ting you get this Nexus
5 one of the best Android phones out there even still today $350 when you go to Linux dot ting
comm then it's six dollars a month after that that's all you pay your usage plus ting has an
awesome dashboard that lets you manage it and best of all if you ever get stuck or if you want
to have multiple people on your account you'll appreciate this one they have rockin good customer
service you can call anytime between 8 a.m. or 8 p.m. Eastern at 1 8 5 5 ting FTW and a real
person answers the phone and that person it's not like a oh hi thanks for calling ting please hold
or what's your problem and that person's like hi thanks for calling ting how can I help you I'm
actually the person that's gonna help you and yes a real person just answered the phone when you
call the company support number that's that's it's incredible and like Brad said their control
panel so awesome Matt and I have both activated and deactivated multiple devices all through the
online control panel with zero problems it's awesome and if we ever did get stuck we know
we have that customer service really nice Linux dot ting comm that'll tell them hey thanks for
supporting Linux unplug I really appreciate you guys keeping them on the air that also gives you
a chance to try out their savings calculator just plug your current bill in now think about this too
when you're plugging your bill into their savings calculator put the numbers in that you actually
use not what you pay into because that's a gimmick that your cell carrier has tricked you into thinking
is the way to pay for things when you're doing their savings calculator put your actual usage
in there and then be it's astonished at the difference Linux dot ting comm and a big thank
you to ting for sponsoring Linux unplugged you guys rock and go over to their blog too they've
got another behind the scenes video they just posted up that you guys might want to check out
so Matt join us on the mumble line is the founder of bedrock Linux paradigm hey paradigm welcome to
the show thanks for being here man we really appreciate it so tell us so when did you start
working on paradigm so I started there isn't really a good firm starting date I didn't realize
what it became when I started playing around with it yeah so I'm guessing around 2008 to 2010 was
when the ideas started for me waiting for it got me where and then the first public release was 2012
and I gather like a lot of projects it was really like this is just something I want like I'm sick
of having to pick between Debian and arch or whatever you just looked out of all and said
I want all but at once right yes exactly that's bold and how has the response been to this because
I know I mean I've seen presentations far back as 2012 but yet I still don't see a lot of talk
about it I am seeing more these days so I do you think response is improving are people starting
to grok the idea I think the main concern the main thing keeping people away is that it's still
labeled alpha it there's still a lot of work that has to be done I expect that when that's when we're
past that it's a stable release if there's gonna be more tension that's what's gonna happen I'm
okay with the slow development sure it's actually kind of a good thing in a way isn't it because it
sort of slowly brings in more people and and and sort of doesn't make it an insane base that's all
of a sudden using your code so would you mind in your own words summarizing what bedrock Linux
is and what makes it different for maybe folks who didn't watch the Sunday's Linux action show
sure I'll try to use different phrasing than I did when you quoted me earlier on the show Sunday
so when you use a Linux distribution what they actually do for you is provide a lot of software
that they've packaged it's all out there so the question is whose package you put together to make
sure it all works but you have to pick which group of packages from which distribution if you want
something stable you know like rel or Debian if you want something cutting edge just like arch and
so on and so on every just rises its own advantages and disadvantages maybe been better like Linux is
that you can install software from any of those distributions so that it runs natively just like
it was needed for the distro no VM overhead no containers restricting what you can do just if
you if you want parts from different distros at the same time that rocks how you there's one way
to go about it now if you were starting bedrock today 2014 of June would you start with something
that was more Docker based or do you still think that this is perhaps a different approach or a
better approach than just straight-up container ization so I actually just added today a new
frequently asked questions thing on Docker since that that's coming quite a bit right
Docker is doing something different Docker is purposefully containing things so that they can't
interact with each other there's a lot of benefits to this I'm not saying it's a bad idea but it's a
very different goal if you're using Docker you can't for example say install some program then
Ron man to get the man page for it you have to actually go into the the Docker container for it
so no I would not switch the techniques I still think that the technique I'm currently using is
about the best way to go about it given the resources I have at hand and I think the thing
to underscore here is this isn't virtual ization and so it is native metal performance and I could
have an application running from an arch client and an application running from a Firefox client
and they could interact they could pass data amongst each other yes exactly for the most part
it all feels native like if you don't realize if you don't do anything to point out data usage it
feels like any other distro so does this get massive like that on the disk am I do I end up
essentially with the equivalent of an arch a full arch installation a Debian installation an Ubuntu
you know a fedora whatever I decide to install as a client do I do I need to have just a ton of disk
space that is definitely an issue with the techniques we're currently using we have some
ideas and how to fix that in the long term but we're not gonna get them done anytime soon yeah
I mean how would you even go about that the main concern with that is actually telling me package
managers that certain dependencies have been met elsewhere and you have to go do a lot of work
specific to each package manager to get that done in automated fashion it's also not entirely clear
that a given library will meet the needs from like a different distro so what ends up happening on
bedrock right now is that you'll have multiple versions of any given dependency if multiple
things need them they're not shared but there are some theoretical things that could be done
if it's a high enough priority could I run multiple versions of the same distribution so
could I have 1204 and and 1404 as clients and and mix and match match between those two sure
yeah I just I think I look at I look at bedrock Linux as as maybe a power desktop Linux users
perfect scenario is that who you're targeting in your mind when you're developing this so the the
key target audience for bedrock Linux is myself if other people want to use it great I'm just
trying to make it for me and it's for your desktop or server you run it on a server laptop I do I'm
not convinced it's the best option I think something like Coral West will give you advantageous
what bedrock does isn't as helpful on a server because things aren't just like they don't need
to interact quite as much as they wouldn't have desktop but it works fine okay well I've got some
some functionality and usage questions for you so I'm gonna and also I'll move us up into the main
mumble room too so they can jump in and ask questions so I guess where I wanted to start with
is are there already tools in place to do client all client updates so I could execute a yum upgrade
and an app git dash upgrade and a pac-man upgrade from one for one bedrock command so we had one that
did that but I decided I wanted the name of that utility used elsewhere we end up dropping it
temporarily in the long term we want to have we have a project that we're calling the package
manager manager or PMM and in theory you could run some PMM commands that would do that okay and I
kind of also had a question I noticed how do you choose the kernel so my bedrock installation was
using an arch kernel is that something that installation you just pick the distros kernel
you want originally I think I mean the first alpha I recommended compiling your own kernel
which kept a lot of people away but after some experimentation I realized that for the most part
any one external works and just about any distro you might lose some features like system tap but
yeah you can just use whatever so my recommendation is that you install kernel from a client and just
use that and so how about how many people are working on the bedrock Linux team now I'm the
majority of it I think well over 90% of the lines of code currently in their mind but there are a
good number of other people who contribute what they can when they have time I'm trying to give
an estimate depending on where you draw the line it's maybe five total wouldn't be go ahead ask
your question I was just curious what problem were you setting out to solve when you first created
bedrock Linux so there's a famous story with RMS having trouble with a printer which is why you
started the canoe projects I had a similar issue I had to I was using Debian stable at the time
my printer broke I got a new one and the drivers didn't work and I did spend a lot of time making
that work when I realized if I could just get this one package from Debian state or arch that
would that would solve that completely and so I did that I set that up and I just kept iterating
over it from there until there's it's its own distro I also like the story you shared where
there was a bug with comp is and one distribution had one part of the solution the other distribution
of the other part of the solution you're able to bring those two together and I've been in that
scenario myself especially though see the reason why I asked you about the desktop question is
because I have very very much been in the server space where we were just on the pre show talking
about Red Hat Enterprise 7 and so many times I've been on a CentOS box or Red Hat Enterprise box and
I've just thought if I could just manage this one set of applications through apt or if I could just
get this PPA or whatever it would make so much of my work easier and bedrock sort of seems to me to
have the promise if I could base the core bedrock kernel on a CentOS kernel so essentially I'm CentOS
on the whole stack but bedrocks actually managing the user land I could essentially accomplish that
couldn't I paradise yes and in fact that's what I'm doing on the server it's exactly the reason
it's mostly diving stable but I do have occasional occasions from elsewhere go ahead crossroads so I
was wondering how you'll handle the image system will you use system D or will you write your will
you write your own in it the custom in its system for bedrock that's that's actually a really good
question currently one of the main areas that better our clinics has issues isn't it most
things just work as long as they're not closely tied to in it when better started there was no
system D most things were system 5 or similar and that ended up working quite nicely system D I have
to be here with my phrasing here say it's really picky about how it does certain things and it
doesn't want to play with bedrock very well so we have to come up with some new solutions that
particular issue currently bedrock Linux uses its own busybox based in it which is super duper
limited but in the long term we're going to try to make other in its systems options just like you
can have for the main user lane whatever packages you want I'm going to try to make it so that you
can use whatever neat system you want Wow Riley go ahead yes I was wondering like have you had
any issues with the bigger disk shows getting mad at you pulling down their packages and installing
it on bedrock when it's not really that dish show like I remember a while back that canonical got
mad at MIT for accessing their repos the servers sorry it's just that's that's misrepresenting what
happened but go on but the broader question is have you heard have you heard any put have you
got any pushback from upstream distros I've I've not had anyone be upset by that yet I think we
may not be big enough yet to get that attention if that's something that's coming later off the
handle it however that the question is really what is the distro that you're using is bedrock
when it's just acting like a hypervisor you're really using some other distro in which case
you're using the software they're providing and the repos they're providing for that purpose so
there's some arguments can be made right it is their user land yes yeah it's just not their
kernel which what's the difference if you downloaded Ubuntu and swapped out the kernel
it's almost the same the same from the distribution standpoint go ahead blue Phoenix I know you had a
question we wanted to get in what about switching in its system like gentoo does some applications
I mean gentoo uses open RC but like if you're gonna use gnome then you can switch to system D
so the the trouble with unit stuff is it gets really complicated specifically things like
upstart and system D the way they're designed is really inflexible given what bedrock clinics is
trying to do and some of the tools we're using like system D will actually check when it's
starting if you're using some of the techniques that bedrock clinics it does do and then refuse
to operate so it's not as simple as just switching it out there's me a bit more work I see heavens
revenge has a question go ahead heavens okay well there is a situation in which I can't quite
wrap my head around let's say you start from a base system and of course you know you usually
start with installing X at least before you used to go distro or desktop environment first you'd
go X first then maybe the toolkit and then maybe the desktop environment what happens when you go
a stable X pull something bleeding edge like a bleeding edge KDE or GTK from arch and then go
back and switch to a stable desktop environment where that is trying to find updated API calls
in the stable version of the toolkit that you're using so if I if I followed that correctly your
concern has to is going to be met by the fact that if something has a dependency that will be
provided by the same distro which is one of the reasons we have to take so much disk space is we
have multiple copies a lot of dependencies so something is using a given toolkit and they're
sad it's it's missing they'll end up having their own so that that doesn't happen very good all
right look static no literally there'll be multiple copies of something like GTK so something
wants one specific version of GTK and something else wants a different version they'll both be
installed on disk that seems I mean I know some people are gonna scoff at the disk space usually
there but that seems like if you're if you want to do this kind of thing and disks are cheap that
seems like a fair trade-off for what you're actually getting and so when you install KDE
do you actually install a KDE and all of its complete dependency tree from that specific
repo or distribution and then have little kind of hierarchies within their own roots yes if you
install something like KDE you'll get the entire if you're installing it using that given distros
package manager and it does its own dependency resolution the way it typically would natively
you'll get all of those dependencies it's like if you were running that distribution and you just
installed KDE it will do all of the actions it would do when you perform that action so if it
if you if there's a meta KDE package that installs 300 dependencies it would do that okay I was
thinking of excess shared containers which they share a little bit more interdependencies between
them but I guess they're very very inter independent of each other okay so I wonder how oh go ahead
yeah how closely independent they are or how how much they're interacting with each other is
configurable given the way they're using it so if you want to try to do something like that you can
by default I'm trying to find a same compromise between things not conflicting with each other
and things just working interacting we'd expect all right I want to get a couple more questions
in before we go so I wanted to have crossroads that kind of finish this up with his last two
questions here go ahead crossroads okay so my first question is how does bedrock handle GUI
so when it's when you have a GUI running how does that work how does one particular client display
a GUI it's talks to Xorg or Wayland the same way it would natively like it doesn't they're not
contained it doesn't know that it's not there it doesn't know that the version of Xorg is talking
to happens to be different from what it's used to and my last question was oh if you could take
a time machine five years in the future where would you want to see bedrock or where do you
see it being in five years I see it being roughly where you see something like slackware who's a
popularity like people notes they're not everyone uses it however it's you know I obviously be very
different from slackware in terms of what the projects doing I expect I'd like to have a niche
number of people who are using in a community but I don't expect it to take over everything I like
that and so I think we have a lot of people that want to know how they can help contribute where
should they go to get involved or see if there's a way they could help so on our website I have I
think a quick question item on that but basically you can look our issue tracker there's something
you think you can take go ahead and let me know and go at it if you see some other issues that
are missing from there you can add them I think that the biggest thing though that that can be
done is to actually install it and use it and let me know what issues you find because I can't fix
issues that come up and workflow is different from mine like I don't actually use many desktop
environments so if there's some issue with those I wouldn't be aware of them so yeah just use it
and let me know how it goes very good well you are welcome to stick around and join us any time
to the mumble room is always open when we're doing the unplug show and I'd like to get your
guys's thoughts on on this next topic we have coming up to and we'll discuss more in the post
show so it's been great and guys go over go over to the show notes we've got links for bedrock
Linux and I think about you Matt but bedrock Linux to me is like one of the most interesting
distributions in ten years oh easily I think it could actually set the pace for the way things
are done in the future maybe not exactly the way it's being done currently but I think it does set
a pace and a different set of expectations that we could watch expand over time I like that I like
that that sort of you know slack where it has sort of a really soft spot in the community's heart
there's a lot of passionate slackers out there and you know I think it's it's still a distribution
that carries some weight every time we talk about on the show we end up hearing from somebody that's
that's not a bad goal at all I would I'd be very happy to have a distribution at that level and I
think it's possible bedrock Linux offers something that I think will really appeal to a certain set
of Linux users so you heard the man go out there and try it out go to bedrock Linux a site and
download it and deploy it and bang on it for him it's not not necessarily for those of you who are
maybe not a little more gray in the beard it takes some Linux skills but if you've got some or if you
want to challenge him you can go do it and you go always try it out in virtualization too so you
could always snapshot and whatnot speaking of which man I want to thank our next sponsor on the Linux
unplugged show and that is digital ocean go over to digital ocean calm and guess what we've got a
nice June promo code unplugged June to get you a $10 credit over at digital ocean digital ocean
is simple cloud hosting and they're dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way to spin
up a cloud server users can create a cloud server in about 55 seconds maybe less if you're a pro
like our audience and pricing plan started only five dollars a month for 512 megabytes of RAM a
20 gigabyte SSD a blazing fast CPU and 1 terabyte of transfer in digital ocean has data center
locations in New York San Francisco Singapore and Amsterdam man I'd love to be the IT guy that gets
sent to work at the Amsterdam data center and of course their interface is simple their control
panel is intuitive and power use can replicate on a much larger scale with their API and you're
seeing people take advantage of that in really cool ways there's so many great things I could
talk about with digital ocean I think what I'd like to focus on is how much I really appreciate
how they've rocked so many aspects of this it made it they've it is a combination of their
dashboard that I talk a lot about it's a combination of those SSD drives which is an early
investment I think they really saw the light on that it's the really great utilization of KVM to
get the density on these things so incredibly high and one of the other things that's really
fantastic about digital ocean is they have been on the cutting edge of Docker support Docker 1.0
came out yesterday digital oceans already down with it man and a great thing about digital ocean
is they're making it really easy to deploy some really great open source tools and things like
GitLab you can deploy GitLab to dot to a droplet on digital ocean in no time it's it's things like
this where you can make a template image and then redeploy it when you need and they have hourly
pricing so you can take this template get it up and running bang on it for a few hours and shut
it down and with our toned up with our $10 credit when you use unplug June that's gonna last forever
I mean it's this value combined with this technology and it's the technology that we all
support it's the technology that we all love combined with their investment SSDs these data
centers all over the world they really are a really cool company and they're doing something
different they have a different recipe than everybody else and that's why developers and
Linux users and power users and people that just want to learn alike are all responding so strongly
to digital ocean go to digital ocean comm and use the promo code unplugged June go get a $10
credit trap that $5 rig for two months you'll just get it for for two months for free that's
a terabyte of transfer you can use and just put bit torrent sync up there put own cloud up there
just begin to take back and control a little part put subsonic up there shoot I don't know put plex
up don't know I don't know about that maybe maybe I put a VPN then you could do it well here's how
what I did and I and I wouldn't necessarily go with that direction in the media but I think so
we have some folks that do have plex up there you know it could work right it could work but
I would want to make it secure yeah you wanted to make it secure I mean for myself I'm actually
looking at doing an own cloud because I really want to make sure I have access to my documents
number one going I'm also looking to drop Dropbox so this is a project I've taken up and I was
originally just doing it just a bit torrent sync part of my house but was soon as soon as I started
putting stuff up on my digital ocean droplet then I was like oh wait a minute now I can get
to it from my Android phone when I'm on the road without having to mess with any firewall stuff on
my home router and it it just and then it's like oh and then I have another sync point it's up in
the cloud and it's like essentially off-site backup for me it just all these things started
to click into place so check it out you guys all right so I'm a little upset I'm a little I don't
want to I don't want to be all ranty and ravey I hate what I hate when I'm grumpy I know you guys
do too so let's just jump in real quick we're just gonna do our valve update so Alienware got
on my ass list today they had a little e3 announcement guess what ladies and gentlemen
Alienware will be shipping their first steam machine in December despite the fact that valve
has supposedly delayed them because they're taking a little shortcut Alienware's first steam machine
will be shipping with Windows of course it will it's a it's a it's Dell jr. I mean what do you
expect yeah they did it again Matt they did it again they did it again they switched to Windows
they're they're shipping what they're calling the alpha version of the steam machine running
Windows and the alien will develop Alienware developers has to have and this is a quote
scripted up a new UI that makes the Windows interface more usable from a tent and from
ten feet away and will make it easy to launch Steam big picture mode there you go hell you
know it's Alienware I mean nothing they do really surprises me especially once that once
uh Dell kind of took them under their wing they really went a totally different direction at that
point it's really disappointing and I I mean like not only is it it's negative in the freedom
dimension that's a given but also like I I can in a way understand like maybe like they were
working hand-in-hand with valve and I was like yeah Alienware we're gonna do this you be our
partner and then then all of a sudden I was like actually you know what just kidding we're gonna
bump it to 2015 that's that's I mean that happened right valve so we're gonna bump steam machines
and maybe Alienware was like well that's great Gabe but here I am with my with my wiener out
and nothing's happening and now I'm kind of stuck to deliver I've got all these R&D guys we've paid
for we've developed a product we've got all the shipping and marketing oh and by the way we've
been working on a Windows one just in case your product sucked anyway so we're just gonna go with
our plan B I feel like that's what happened well and it honestly makes me wonder how much which is
really the plan B you know I mean really think about that if they were able to roll it out that
easily but well I think they've been working on this from the beginning oh yeah that's kind of
what I'm saying yeah I mean maybe or maybe they hacked it together I don't know maybe they did
hack it together but I to me it feels like how do you just go well yeah but we've had these we've
had some of our developers hacking together UI for this so we'll just go with that and you know
got big picture mode this is yeah I don't know this is really disappointing and this is this
is typical crap and I don't know I just I'm a little worried I don't like this is not a good
start for the whole steam machine thing this is not this is not how I wanted it to begin but just
sounds like still how passing things all over again with yeah I say that's all they've ever
done well and but now the headline is is Alienware refit steam machine with Windows you're seeing
that adventure beat it's on and gadget it's everywhere now that's the headline that's the
headline now and it sets the tone and so that's gonna challenge valve to have to step up their
game when they are ready to release and absolutely just really blow people away and that means
getting in the headlines quick and early if the Reese they're scripting a new UI or whatever why
are they doing that on Windows when that would be easier to do on a Linux system yeah I think it
has Dell I think valve blew it I think I think what valve valve blew it by engaging with other
companies valve should have just nutted up and just shipped a machine themselves and and not
shipped it until it was ready and they should have it should have been the steam machine from
valve and not worked with guys like the cube guys that blew it back at CES last year and these guys
that are blowing it now this is not the first partner that's blowing it and this this is a
big deal if they screw this up this is a big deal well I treat these guys just don't care what
operating system they're shipping with they care whether they can supply the games that people want
to put to their to the people who will buy steam boxes and the truth is that if you are going to
ship a steam box today you have to have more triple a I agree and Linux just doesn't deliver
there so they either have to wait and possibly another company could sweep in and ship with
Windows and everything that valve supplies with Steam OS is actually available for for Windows
already probably no one will stop you if you want to ship a set the box with that boot straight to
this steam big picture a steam box running Windows is a failed product on launch you know why because
we already have those those those already exist and they haven't gone anywhere it needs to be a
differentiator it needs the steam box applies to somebody who wants to have a more appliance
console like experience they don't want something that's running Windows that's just been lacquered
over like media center was or what's what big picture mode is they want something it's a
dedicated appliance box that's been blessed by valve the people who are maybe Mac users who
can't play very many video games or people who are Xbox users who maybe don't really even mess
with their PC very much maybe they have like a laptop you know like they don't even game on the
PC that's who I see a steam box running Linux appealing to is somebody who wants a different
solution because we already we've had big picture for over two years now I don't know a year at
least yeah and it's gone nowhere right and we already have that and so now Alienware is gonna
bundle up and package something with a too expensive price point because they are charging
more for this because of the Windows license they said it in the press release they're gonna
ship something that's more expensive that will play mediocre game graphics based on the specs
of this thing and what there and it has this it has the steam box name it's a stinker all around
I think it has to do with support no it doesn't I had Alienware that they sold with Ubuntu on it
and then I had an issue with the CD drive when I called in the tech support uh when they found
out I was using Ubuntu the first thing they said is we don't support Linux and I end up getting
the escalated and it was a hardware problem because of the case design but their their
first response is we don't support Linux yeah even though they sold it with Ubuntu on it right so
go ahead run no go ahead run uh doesn't I could be wrong but doesn't Valve have a rule like a
guidelines that you have to agree to in order to call it a steam machine or a steam box I don't
know Google has AOSP I know I know that the press is calling it a steam machine that's what I was
saying is uh they need to draw the line and saying and saying if you're gonna call this a steam box
you need to make sure it runs Linux and not Windows you know if you look at the headline
it says steam machine but I did I think that's I think that's a that's a very it doesn't matter
that what matters is the perception that headline creates steam box steam machine it could be that's
interchangeable for the for the impression it's going to create and despite how much I dislike
companies doing this can't uh steam contact the the uh companies who are putting that headline
out there uh or the media organizations and tell them that's not what this is please remove that
you're insinuating you know you're you're talking about our product the steam machine that's not
that yeah I don't know I don't know I mean maybe I mean I can answer that question so
go ahead man well I I can answer that question um I I receive those all the time and usually after
I'm done laughing at them and sending them to my inbox um yeah the point is is that send me a cease
and desist until it's legal they can bite me um that that's that's the most of the philosophy
of most editors unless there's a real compelling legal concern from the legal department no one
cares it's an interpretive statement so the title being the steam machine well it's running steam
and it is a machine that can be interpreted they can then fight it out in court or they
can accept the fact that there really isn't much right and and the thing too is like valve is not
going to want the bad pr but I want also the thing is is what the way alienware is positioning this
is they're even calling it alpha this is rev one we're shipping our first version with windows
and then later potentially maybe possibly kind of we might put linux on them in future versions that
we won't be calling alpha anymore we just want to see if the concept works even though it won't be
anything like the final product we want to see if the concept works and so that's why they're
calling it a steam machine because eventually maybe it kind of could possibly run steam os
you gotta wonder does anyone else here smell microsoft stink on this because they do have a
real tight relationship this is what i've been saying um microsoft and dell are known to be
like very simpatico together um what's that i would agree with heavens this is not the
microsoft thing at all it's just better currently if you are going to ship like i said before if
you're going to ship a steam box it's easier to do it with windows because of bigger library to
games you'll appeal to wider uh i think people who do it don't care absolutely at all um about
what operating systems they're shipping with and we care too much um the truth is probably
yeah yeah we care too much about linux to have a kind of a clear perspective on this
all right vr mac vr mac you want to give us a dose of reality go ahead i think the uh the thing
that this all boils down to is the fact that dell's a business and regardless of if they
have any sort of alliance with microsoft or whatever conspiracy you may think they're
they're a business and all they really care about is making money and they see this as
an opportunity to get a profit this is a really good opportunity for them too because as we know
of x for playstation 4 and xbox one guess what they're using x86 chips yeah i just this is the
future of gaming tell isn't very good at making money in the consumer space anymore i mean they're
kind of laughed at or converging this is this is this has now become the ultimate dell product
where they half ass it they they start ambitious and then they cut it and cut it down this isn't
going to be a successful product this is already a product that nobody wants i mean it's like okay
fine they want to go with windows great give me specs that i actually give a rat's butt about
then i might at least acknowledge that they're actually trying the problem the problem is is
when it runs windows you fundamentally have a complicated windows pc that you have to manage
that's why windows the old traditional windows mobile failed it was too complicated for that
type of device you you have to have a device that is dumb stupid i just want to effing play
some video game simple i press a stupid little alien glowing button and it boots up this this
shiny valve os and it boots right into this big picture mode and that's all it is it's nothing
else it's not windows that's been scripted to have a 10 foot interface that you can launch
big picture people don't want that it's going to be a failed product when they plug in their
controller they're going to have to install some drivers yeah it ships with the xbox 360 wireless
controller too that's what they're going with anyways it doesn't stink with microsoft at all
yeah it's not even a little bit i said i i know some things about dell and microsoft that most
people probably don't and i'm saying yes it does stick at microsoft of course you know what uh imicon
points out in the chat room you never know maybe it will be successful and the steam machine name
gets a good name and yeah right i don't think so uh yeah how about some uh how about some some good
linux gaming news right so let's talk about linux taking over the gaming universe again uh i didn't
really see this one coming today at least uh civilization 5 the strategy game is now native
on linux it's an aspire port but it's a native aspire port the steam os release includes all
civilization 5 dlc too and the expansion pack including gods and kings and brave new world this
is over on gaming on linux.com uh and it was posted by uh liam who joined us a couple weeks
ago on the show pretty big release for linux civilite this is one of the benchmark games and
it's out it's out there right now you can go get it and download it i actually think i bought it
like a while ago when it was on crazy sale sometimes i hedged my bets and so there you go
that's a big game coming to linux and uh so that's a good that's some good news and i also
wanted to share a little love with the krita product project krita am i saying that krita
krita krita the uh the kde or the qt based uh digital painting software is doing a kick starter
to sort of supercharge development and the main reason i wanted to give them a mention is because
this is one of the most badass apps we have on desktop linux and i i i'm i'm very hopeful that
crowdfunding can be a way for the open source community to fund these really standout applications
and when you have a desktop linux application that not only has a good history but it has an
ambitious target and has been delivering on a consistent basis i'm all about that so i wanted
to give them a plug you can find a link to their kickstarter project or you can just go to kickstart.com
and search for the krita project it's from the krita foundation they're trying to get to uh 15
000 and they're at 2148 right now 73 backers with 29 days to go and they got all their goals
outlined out there and stuff like that so good luck to them it's a really really good app um
it's one of these apps that i kind of wish we had spent more time with on the linux action show
demoing uh but i'm just so not skilled at this kind of stuff that it would be embarrassing right
but if i was i would i would be showing this kind of stuff off so just give it a mention for one of
our great desktop linux apps that's out there that you know this is this is one of the applications
that any desktop environment proprietary or not would be proud to have definitely so there you go
good work guys and good luck on the fundraiser they got a they got a video too that you can go
catch with some catchy like uh you know kickstarter music and they got some green screen action going
it's nice look at this green screen action they got going good work kickstarter videos is that you
always want to like curl up with a cup of tea as you watch you know the whole thing i mean the
whole kickstarter video thing you know that's like an industry now there's like people with their
full-time business is uh recording kickstarter videos and indiegogo videos and stuff like that
like the whole that's like their whole thing man that's what they do for a living that's crazy i
mean if only we knew more people had that kind of equipment instead of thought of that i should have
thought of that dang it all right well you guys can find links to all that stuff in the show notes
also just a shout out uh two new shows over on jupiter broadcasting how to linux launched
and episode one is out and uh tech talk today is daily monday through thursday episode six is out
today we talked about netflix and verizon round two it's a pretty interesting spat that is directly
related to all of the net neutrality stuff going on right now and has the potential to bust that
stuff open so we've been covering that on tech talk today we've also covered the best from e3
that's happened so far and you guys probably heard about that turing uh test that was supposedly
beaten but not so much we bust that in today's episode of tech talk today and you can join us
every day monday through thursday at jblive.tv 9 a.m pacific noon eastern and uh you know we
have uh also we have the mumble room involved too so if you didn't get it if you don't get a chance
to join us for linux unplugged we take calls and your opinion from the mumble room and tech talk
today and tomorrow we'll be rounding up not just the tech headlines but we'll also be covering some
of the stuff that happened in e3 so it's e3 going on right now matt did you know i've heard this
yeah well there's the rumors are true matt it is true it is going on right now so anyways we'll end
it right there so head over to linuxactionshow.reddit.com to get involved you can help
massage the content if you will you know to cup the content and give it a nice gentle boost over
at linuxactionshow.reddit.com it's also a good way to give us your feedback i've noticed we'll
see if anybody's still listening because i've noticed that the linux unplugged show gets very
little love these days in the subreddit and i understand it's because you guys are jerks and
you don't like us and you hate that's right that's fine we don't mind right matt i mean
as long as i'm getting abuse i mean being uh attention not abuse what am i saying i don't
want to be abused no at all i think it's just give us a little love guys come on and the value
of this is negative let's go along i kid i kid you can also go to jupyterbroadcasting.com hit
the contact link and send in some email to the linux unplugged show and join us live on tuesdays
2 pm pacific or go to jupyterbroadcasting.com calendar to get that converted by robots
in your local time jblive.tv is where the live happens where you can hang out with us in the
mumble room or in the chat room and help name our show hey matt i'll see you on sunday okay
all right see you then all right have a great week and have a great week everyone thanks so
much for tuning this week's episode of linux unplugged we'll see you right back here next tuesday
so
you