Wes, you're not still using that filthy top, are you?
Oh gosh, no.
Basic top?
Age top, come on, at least.
Maybe back in the 80s.
Well, Wes, I wanna introduce you to Vtop.
Vtop.
Yeah, it's got all the top.
It looks so good.
Now, it's a little heavy,
but it's probably in your local package manager,
or you can install with npm.
It's a graphical activity monitor for the command line.
It's pretty slick, dude.
If you have npm, you can just do npm install-g vtop,
but I installed it right here on my machine.
Yeah, you did.
I don't got a lot going on right now,
but you can go through the different processes.
You can look at your memory usage.
You get a real-time graphical representation of your CPU.
It's pretty cool.
Not bad.
Yeah, look at this.
Things are, jeez, Chrome, man.
Chrome's got 34 threads going right now.
It's using 33.9% of my system's RAM.
You know how all a computer is as a web browser these days.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 203, for July 11th, 2017.
Oh, welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's installing and upgrading distributions
like some kind of maniac.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Hello, sir.
Very excited about today's show.
Any day that we get to cover a new big distribution release
is a good day.
Fedora 26, coming to Linux Unplugged.
I'm Chris.
I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Hello, sir.
Very excited about today's show.
Any day that we get to cover a new big distribution release
is a good day, Fedora 26 is here.
It was released this morning, and we've
been installing it on systems all day long.
Not even our own systems, whoops.
I know.
Wait, whoops, uh-oh.
And Matt from the Fedora Project will join us
to cover the new release and explain why we maybe
accidentally installed it on his laptop.
Sorry, sorry about that.
It's our bad.
Sorry about that.
Also, we've got a bunch of great community news,
everything from some Ubuntu shenanigans
to new software projects that we think are super cool.
And updates coming for you Steam users that are,
I don't know, you might say many, many years overdue.
Yeah, it's kind of ridiculous to talk about that.
Then we're also gonna get geeky with NF tables.
Oh, sorry.
Not to confuse you with NFS.
I'm talking about NF tables, the replacement for IP tables.
It's been billed as a performant alternative,
the next generation IP tables.
But has that really been tested?
It looks like a Red Hat engineer took it to the benchmark.
We're gonna talk about some testing that he did
to really throw both NF tables and IP tables
through the wrenches and see how the performance
were different, see where one may perform better.
It's actually very fascinating.
There's a lot of details in there.
Yeah, you found a good one this week, Wes,
so we'll talk about that too.
But we sort of have to get to something
right off the top here.
We've gotta bring in the Mumble Room.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Greetings.
Hello.
Good to see you.
Greetings.
Hello, hello, hello, and a special hello
to Matt from Fedora.
Hey, Matt.
Hi there, glad to be here.
Sir, it is always good to welcome you back to the show.
I always love talking to you.
So Matthew Miller is the Fedora project leader.
He's been on the show for the last couple of releases
of Fedora just about here or there.
And today is Fedora 26's release day
with lots of things that are obviously coming
into Fedora 26 from upstream.
The new development tools like GCC 7, Golang 1.8, Python 3.6,
new partitioning tool in Anaconda, the installer.
Also, there is the new LX cute version of the spin.
It's got Kernel 4.11.8, ships with Gnome 3.24,
and all of its new fancy features.
LibreOffice 5.3, Fedora MediaWriter
has gained ARM support.
So if you want to write the Raspberry Pi versions,
Builder now supports things like Flatpak and Rust.
And the cute Odwadia theme has gotten lots of improvements
to make it match the GTK version, including
support for dark mode.
I mean, this is sounding like a great release, Matt.
Have I missed anything that's your favorite new feature?
So one thing I think is pretty neat
is we have a new Python classroom spin.
So one of the things we do, it's actually a lab.
We've divided things up into spins and labs now.
Spins are desktop environments, and the labs
are kind of use-focused things.
So the Python lab, it's basically a classroom
environment in a vagrant box or a Docker container
or a life USB stick that is basically pre-set up
to get your classroom ready to go to teach Python
or a bunch of scientific computing things
based around Python.
Oh, wow.
That's really, I could definitely
see that in a classroom somewhere.
Yeah, and I really like this because as a project,
we've been looking a little bit at our mission
and what we want to do, what makes Fedora unique and special.
And we came up with a new mission statement, which I
cannot say off the top of my head, although it is, yeah.
But the basic idea is we build a platform that
enables our contributors and other software
to make solutions for users.
And so this is a great example of here's
some things that some contributors did.
This wasn't a top-down, let's make a Python thing.
But some people who are involved in Fedora wanted to do this.
And we provide the tooling and stuff to make a kit like that.
And I'd like to see a lot more of those kind of things
for special use cases.
So there's a few things that have
sort of been on the ancillary edges of this release that
have also gotten my attention.
And so what I thought we would do
is maybe talk about a couple of things
that the Fedora project is working on.
And then sort of the second half of this would be our take
on the release, because both Wes and I have had a chance
to kick the tires.
And I've had this long-running Digital Ocean Droplet
instance since either Fedora 24 or 23
that I've been upgrading every single release.
And I run a couple of Docker containers on here,
and I manage it with Cockpit.
And it's sort of been my, how long can you run a Fedora server
and not have it break?
And so I completed that upgrade before the show.
And did my testing on it.
So I'll give you my report on that as well.
But not to take away attention from the release of Fedora 26,
but I always love to do this to you.
I noticed something about future releases
that really got my attention.
And I don't really even know how to put this right.
But it looks like Rawhide is seeing a shift as of about
right now, where essentially it sounds like Rawhide will be more
like a rolling release that you intend people
to use as a daily driver.
I quote directly from the wiki, it
will be generally useful to people
to use as a daily driver and a development platform
and means we no longer need to go
through the process of building, testing, and shipping
alpha releases.
And the entry on the wiki is no more alpha
for the Fedora project.
What's going on here, Matt?
Yeah, that's the plan.
I mean, this is part of an overall push
we have for more automated testing.
This is more validation testing rather than continuous
integration testing, which happens kind of more
the developer side.
But basically, Adam Williamson, who's one of our top QA people,
has been working with the SUSE thing, the open QA tool,
to set up a lot of automated tests.
Basically, all of the basic tests
that we've previously always done by hand
to make sure the alpha was ready,
those are basically imported as automated tests already.
So basically, there's the changes to make those gating
and so that automatic raw hide basically happens.
Something like an alpha happens every night,
assuming all the tests pass.
And so essentially, the raw hide system
is running through open SUSE QA?
Yeah, through the open QA thing that open SUSE made, yeah.
And so yeah, there's kind of two advantages.
The one advantage is that we can get more people using it.
I think it might be a little bit ambitious to say
this is like our rolling release because it's
still going to change a lot.
And I think that if you want to use this,
you've got to be willing to be like, well,
my system broke this afternoon.
I wonder what wasn't getting tested.
This should have been getting tested.
Very good to know.
Yeah, definitely.
But if you enjoy that kind of thing, I think it will be good.
And we do have a number of people
who are running raw hide already, as it is right now.
And generally, that kind of thing
happens maybe once a season or so.
So it's not that bad of a risk.
But if we can reduce that so you can maybe roll back or have
something a little bit better.
So that's one benefit.
And the other benefit is basically
that every time we put out a release, that is a lot of work.
And that's one of the reasons distributions
like rolling releases because it's like,
what else could we do if we skipped all that trouble
we were doing making releases and just did stuff?
So removing alphas is a way of removing some amount of work.
And with the automated testing, we're
feeling pretty confident that we can do that
without negative impact on the project.
Right, and it would seem to me that if raw hide is getting
continuously ran through automated QA,
that it would probably raise the average quality of it,
which would probably make average releases quality
better.
Exactly, exactly.
And yeah, one of the problems we ran into in this last release
is that some of the things came down
to tests that hadn't been done for a while
and they were just done on the last day before the release.
Then we're like, oh, look, virtualization on AMD
is broken.
So then we had to trace down that bug
like all at the last minute.
And so if we have automated tests running all those things
all the time, we can catch them long before they become
a crisis.
Sure, yeah, that makes sense.
I guess so, oh, hi there.
So my little playback there, a little echo back,
but now it's gone.
My follow-up question to that would
be, could you share any of the background
on how the Fedora project began working with the open QA
project from OpenSUSE?
I'm just curious, was there an event and you guys shook hands?
They're like, hey, let me show you what we're doing.
And you guys went, hmm, we could really use that.
How did that process initiate?
I'm not quite sure for this one, but a lot of stuff
happens at conferences like FOSADEM and things
where people get together in the distro dev room
and people show off their stuff.
I think that actually may be the genesis
of this particular thing, but I'm not quite sure.
It might just be us looking around.
A lot of people in the project like
to look and see what cool things other distros are doing.
And it's all open source, so we take advantage of it
where we can.
I think it's actually pretty cool.
It shows an open-mindedness.
Definitely, and we've talked a lot about open QA
here on this show, but haven't necessarily
seen the kind of adoption that we thought might make sense.
So this really bolsters, I think, both projects.
So Rawhide is going in an interesting direction
if things continue.
Is there a trend line here, or is this
just sort of the next evolution and what's
going to stay here for a bit?
And the question, really, what I'm asking is,
are we trending towards a Fedora rolling,
or is this not really likely the end goal of what Rawhide's
to become?
Yeah, so I think I said this on here before.
I've got strong opinions about rolling releases,
and that is there's sort of two people that rolling releases
benefit, and one is enthusiast people
who want the latest of everything
and just don't mind waking up to a surprise,
and now all of the buttons on my screen have moved around,
and hey, it's innovation.
That's one demographic, and that's probably
a lot of your listeners, right?
I don't know.
I can also sympathize with that to some degree.
It can be kind of fun.
I'm getting some new stuff for its own sake.
And the other one is basically the distro themselves,
because it's a lot less work.
But from a user point of view, I think having real releases
is actually a lot better, because in any distribution,
there's just a whole bunch of change,
and you can test to make sure things aren't awful
and don't crash, but you can't test for that thing easily
for the UI changed in this, or now that program's gone.
And so with a rolling release, you need something to target.
Right.
And with a rolling release, you get that basically
whenever the distro developers put it in there,
and then you get it, or else.
And if you decide to not, you then don't get security updates,
because that's the idea, basically.
You take it or you don't.
Yeah, makes sense.
So I think releases are better, because it
lets you have a window when you can decide, OK, this Thursday,
I'm going to maybe have to relearn how my menus work,
because I'm going to the new version.
So I think there's always a bunch of pain as change happens.
Change is pain.
That's one of those life-truth things.
And I think our model of releases
helps users manage that.
So I think we probably always want
to keep that to some degree.
Makes sense.
So let me ask you about another forward-looking thing
that I saw during this release.
And I don't know if I'm saying the name right,
because I've never heard anybody say it out loud before.
Fedora 26 Boltron server?
Or Boltron?
Boltron.
It's like Voltron bolted together, right?
I don't know.
I was thinking that.
There's a nerd joke in there somewhere.
Yeah, so this is actually very related to that.
Because the basic problem people have in an operating system
and a distribution overall is stuff
moving too fast or too slow.
And the rolling release basically
says everything's going to move fast.
And a LTS says everything's going to move slow.
And generally, nobody's happy with either one of those things
and you want something else.
So this basically lets us separate the hardware
enablement in the operating system from your applications
and have different streams where those things can actually
move at different speeds.
So you could, say, have basically a Ruby version
that you keep at the same version
even as you upgrade the base underneath it
and that kind of thing.
How is that accomplished?
There's a crazy thing called module build service.
You basically define a module, which
is a collection of packages, and then say, OK,
build this against this build root.
And then that's built against basically every new base
operating systems out.
We're making this stuff up right now.
So check out Boltron and see a little bit how
it's going to be accomplished.
But if it's successful, it's going
to be a big shift in how we make the distribution.
Right now, we're focused on I'm making
this package for Fedora 26, this package for Fedora 25.
In the future, if this works out, you'll focus on,
I'm making, say, the latest stream of this package
or the stable stream of this package or the version 1
stream and the version 2 stream.
And then you build that stream across all
of the underlying base OSes that we produce.
This sounds like a feature that must
have come from application developer feedback
or enterprise customer somewhere.
What's the background there?
Yeah, well, honestly, it's something
I've been thinking about.
I've been working on Linux distributions
for like 17 years now.
So it's kind of been the thing I've been hearing from users
all the time.
This is the pain I have.
So we wanted to try and address that pain.
So this is one stab at doing that, basically.
It really got my attention.
It sounds like a really cool idea.
And there's been a background debate recently
about new distributions that are coming up
by hardware manufacturers, both Tuxedo and System76.
And one of the arguments that both of them
has put forward is the LTS is too slow for us.
And we have customers that have problems.
And the solution to these problems
is to replace maybe its NGINX, or its PHP,
or it's the SQL server, or it's even the DHCP client
on that server to fix this problem.
And we end up getting in this weird position of trying
to decide if we package that up ourselves
and slip it in as a PPA, or how to evenly manage this.
And it gets to a point where it's, well, screw it.
Let's just ship our own OS, where
we can manage the package releases ourselves.
And this could sort of solve that problem.
Yeah, that's exactly the idea.
And the problem with the screw it,
or we're going to do it ourselves approach,
is that now you've created something that's
yet another thing that fits only one use case, right?
And then some of your customers are
going to have a different use case, and they're out of luck.
Yeah, that's a good point.
So my kind of last question is just really self-serving.
But we're sort of at an interesting point
here in studio about what we're considering using
for our production distro.
And Fedora is on my mind.
To be honest with you, my only question
is, what would be the right spin for somebody
who wants an extremely, or spin, or whatever
their terminology is, for somebody who wants,
essentially, a bulletproof workstation that's
Fedora-based, though?
See, when I think of Fedora, I think of a great workstation,
except for these are five, six-year systems
that I'd like to have running.
But CentOS moves too slow for me.
What is the solution in the Fedora world for this problem?
Well, so our main solution is that we've
tried to work on making upgrades less painful for you,
so that we don't have a five, six-year solution.
But basically, they've put a lot of engineering
into making sure that every upgrade goes smoothly,
and so that you go from one release to the next,
and your pain is minimized in doing that.
This is, again, like I often get the,
you should make a roll-on release, or an LTS,
and since those things are opposite ends of the spectrum,
when I dig into it, I often hear,
well, I don't wanna do that upgrade, it's so painful.
So, we've worked on making the upgrades less painful.
So, yeah, upgrades to Fedora 25, 26,
both on all of my systems, have been half-hour affairs.
I started it, went and got some coffee, came back,
and then I was like, oh, there we go.
And I think, especially for a workstation,
as GNOME has kind of settled down with GNOME 3
into a nice, comfortable environment,
they've got a lot of the rough edges
from the initial release sort of polished.
And basically, it's kind of increasing polish
instead of disruptive change every release.
Like, back in the first couple of GNOME 3 releases,
not only was GNOME 3 itself kind of shocking,
every point release was also, oh my goodness,
everything's new again.
Or there was GDK breakage.
Right.
Yeah.
Yeah, that makes a lot of sense.
And I feel like that's a really solid answer for the server.
I'll just cover really, really briefly to just cover it.
My Fedora 26 server right now running on DigitalOcean is,
I think it's either from Fedora 23 or Fedora 24.
And it's a Fedora server install
that I then installed, or cockpit was installed,
and I installed several droplets,
one of them a Nextcloud instance,
one of them a Plex server and an MB instance.
So I have both those running different containers.
And I've been chugging along with the upgrade releases
on day one of Fedora releases, which, you know,
I'm gonna say is-
That's kind of unheard of for you.
Well, I mean, you know, if you're not in a rush,
go ahead, give it a couple days, let it sit, you know?
But I, nope, because I've been wanting to talk about it.
And sure enough, if not a single thing's broken yet,
the thing is still running today.
I mean, there's nothing really to report.
The upgrade went totally smooth.
It's actually, the process is,
it's actually pretty good.
And Matt, are you the one that writes up
the upgrade posts every release?
Cause these are always easy to find and straight forward.
No, I think Justin Flory wrote those, they're very nice.
Oh yeah, Justin, yeah, I see that, yeah.
And it's just a simple process.
It goes through, it's really easy to do it through the GUI,
but of course I'm doing it on a server.
So I always use the different DNF commands.
And I'm always pleasantly surprised at how clear DNF is
and how safe it is.
It does all the downloads, it does all the checks.
Then you tell it to do a DNF system dash upgrade reboot.
It reboots into the kernel of the current,
of the, you know, the release you're upgrading from,
installs all the packages, verifies everything,
does another reboot now into the new kernel, and you're done.
Bob's your uncle.
Everything's, your cockpit's running again,
your containers are back up and running.
That's the one thing that really stood out to me.
It's like, with that DNF in general,
it seems like it's very, it's been thought out,
it's well-founded, I can trust it a little bit more
than maybe some of the competing package managers.
Yeah, so it's funny, you know, people don't,
I don't think can, you know,
normally think of maybe Fedora on their VPS,
but I'll tell you, it's been working solid for me.
But I don't know if that's gonna hold true, Matt,
if you're somebody who has maybe RPM fusion set up,
or you have, I don't know,
something outside the Fedora repos,
or maybe you have the Nvidia graphics driver.
Isn't it then not exactly as smooth?
Yeah, I mean, that's always hard,
because we're dependent on other people
for those kind of things.
And, you know, some of those third-party repos
package things that we can't even talk about,
so that makes the situation difficult.
Oh, yeah.
So, yeah, so that can definitely be a problem.
I know that some of them had problems in the past
that they are doing better with.
We're also, the workstation team is working
on building some relationships with Nvidia
and with some of the third-party repo providers,
where we can't point to, for legal reasons,
basically to a third-party repository
that has arbitrary things,
but we might be able to point to a repository
that has just a specific thing
that we know is okay for us to point to,
something that we wouldn't include in Fedora
for, you know, it's not free software.
We're never gonna include not free software
in Fedora directly,
but we know people need to make their hardware work,
so we would like to make it easy
to enable those kind of things,
or something that, whatever other reason,
isn't packaged in Fedora,
but we wanna make it available to people.
You know, so there was a post recently
about some future projects that Fedora's working.
In fact, even in the release notes,
or the release post on Fedora Magazine for 26,
there's sort of an inference in there
about some things that are coming down the pipe wire,
if you will, the pipe wire.
Can we, if you have just a minute,
I'm gonna take a minute and I'm gonna mention
our first sponsor, and then that'll be
pretty much my last question for you for the day,
and then we'll let you get out of here.
Everybody head over to linux.ting.com,
support the show, and get a great deal on mobile
the way it should work.
They'll give you a $25 service credit
if you bring a device,
and they have CDMA and GSM network,
so the compatibility factor is high,
check their BYOD page,
or if you need a new one,
they'll give you $25 off the device.
I mention this because it's really
a smarter way to do mobile.
It's so simple, it's how things would go
if the wireless industry had to reboot today
and be competitive.
It's $6 for a line,
you choose whether you want CDMA or GSM,
which is super nice,
you can bring an unlocked device
or buy one directly from them,
and then you just pay for what you use.
And with that, you get every feature you would expect,
I mean, really great stuff,
including hotspot and tethering.
Ting doesn't have any agendas for you to be
only using streaming at certain times of day
when you use these certain providers,
or else they're gonna, none of that,
no re-encoding garbage.
In fact, they're a pretty big supporter of net neutrality.
They have no contracts, no determination fees,
nationwide coverage, you just pay for what you use
with a great dashboard.
And they just recently posted a video
about Ting's privacy policy,
which, you know, I think is actually worth playing.
I'll just play a brief moment of it here on the show
because it might be something you're wondering
if you're gonna become a Ting customer.
It's kind of a legit question.
Does Ting sell personal information?
Ting does not sell personal information.
Ting's parent company, Two Cows,
has long been committed to protecting consumer privacy.
We do not aggregate information, we do not sell it.
And in fact, we actively advocate
for consumer privacy protections
at the legislative and regulatory levels.
Can your wireless carrier say that?
I don't know about that.
Linux.ting.com, a big thank you to Ting
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Linux.ting.com.
So I think Matt might have a roast in the oven
after Run Soon, so I just, really kind of my,
sort of my last question to you is,
can we talk a little bit about the stuff
in the incubator, like PipeWire?
That has got my interest piqued,
and I've seen a lot of people in our audience
that are excited about PipeWire.
These are like some crazy projects
that are coming from you guys.
Yeah, PipeWire is something from the desktop team
and can own people.
I'm not actually sure of all the details of that.
You might wanna get Kristen Schaller on here sometime.
He wrote that blog post.
I can talk to him for you guys and get him
to talk about some of those things.
That would be awesome.
I would really, I would love to.
I'm sure he, I'm sure he would,
I won't completely speak for him,
but I'm pretty sure he'd love to do it as well.
So I'll talk to him.
Cool.
Yeah, my thoughts are a lot more on
how we put together the distro
and what we're doing to make it
rather than what's going into it.
His thoughts are a lot more on what's going into it.
Here's my meta question about it though.
So why Fedora?
I mean, like, there's so many things to be working on.
Why are some of these things incubated in Fedora first?
I guess I don't, I don't, I mean,
I understand that everybody wants
to make the experience better,
but there's some mountains that some distributions
don't ever seem to wanna take on.
And then Fedora comes along and just sort of nonchalantly
says, yeah, well, we're gonna replace
the entire audio video pipeline on Linux,
or we're gonna rework the way network management is handled,
or, hey, you know what would be great
is if we had this unified init system
across all distributions, like there's this crazy,
like nobody can do that kind of projects
that get started over in your camp.
And I don't, what is it?
I mean, what is it, why?
Yeah, it's foundational to what Fedora is.
It's basically, it's one of our, you know,
Fedora, we have these Fedora foundations,
which are like the project values.
So features is one of those things
where we try and get all these things
that are going to be the next generation of the operating
system and get the new version of the software there.
And we want to experiment with it first.
So it's part of what we're here for.
So it makes it a natural place for people
who are interested in that kind of thing.
So then it's sort of self-fulfilling
because it attracts people
who want to do those kinds of things.
And also, you know, we've got a slant towards saying,
yes, we're going to do that.
Why the hell not?
All right, well, you know, Matt,
is there anything else you wanna add to all of this
before we wrap it up with you?
I don't think so.
I think this has been great.
I'm glad your upgrade went well.
I was a little bit prepared for,
and then everything horribly exploded.
But no, in fact, I've heard just a lot of good things today.
So that's, it's been a very successful,
nice release day with very few fires.
I mean, it seems like a release
that's just got a lot of improvements
and a lot of refinements.
It's not anything that's dramatic, right?
Yeah, I do have to say that the wallpaper
is like the most beautiful Fedora wallpaper
I've ever seen.
And I'm lobbying to keep it for a couple of releases.
It's so nice.
It's surprising too, like how well it looks,
like when you bring up like the applications menu,
when you log, I logged into the Plasma desktop
and it had that background on there
and just the colors matched the menu bar so well, ugh.
And also the shape there of the tree line
is actually based on the wave form
of somebody saying Fedora.
So it's also super, super geeky.
That's awesome.
I have to endorse.
I'm really, I really appreciate you saying that
because the first time I saw it, I thought,
oh, that's a wave, oh no, those are trees.
So that's awesome.
I've seen a few wave forms in my day.
And it was a nice example of collaborative design too,
where the design group, which is, you know,
a bunch of community people from all over the world
kind of started with this idea of a wave form
and then iterated on it till we came out with this.
So I really love it.
That is great.
Yeah, so if you guys want to see that,
either install Fedora or you can go check out
the Fedora Magazine post where Matt went through
the new release.
Matt, thank you so much for coming on the show.
It looks like a great release
and I hope to hear from you soon.
Yeah, thanks again.
I'll love to talk to you again later.
And I will talk to Christian,
see if I can get him on your show for you.
That would be awesome.
Thank you.
Love to chat with him.
Have a good one.
Cool, yep, bye.
So I had a chance to also, like I was saying,
kick the tires on the Plasma Edition,
which is the first time I've ever done that.
I've always, always gone gnome.
Always have because, you know,
it's just such an obvious solid gnome.
It's Fedora.
So I've just, just got started.
But, you know, out of the box, it does look really,
it looks really nice.
It's definitely, it's got me thinking
about some of the woes we've had here in the studio.
And right now I have been leaning Ubuntu LTS
with maybe like a OBS PPA or something like that.
But now I'm just kind of wondering
if I installed an OBS rig or Fedora 26 rig
and tried to put OBS on there.
What would that look like?
Yeah.
Hmm, I don't know.
I think it might be worth trying.
Because with all this stuff,
like you've been playing a lot with Docker
and we covered some of the stuff about running
even X apps and system D containers.
Like it seems like there's a lot of,
maybe the application relative unavailability of Fedora
that we sometimes talk about.
Maybe that's less of a thing in this modern Linux world.
Speaking of that, Minimac,
you were saying that it's actually much better
as far as like the community goes
with keeping up with Fedora releases now.
Yeah, it is definitely.
For example, OBS Studio is available now
on Fedora 26 on release day.
The third party repositories are really available.
Most of them, most of them.
And it's always, I always surprise.
You see, Chris, you're talking about a Fedora 26 server
with Docker and everything.
And I'm running that on the Chromebook
with two gigs of RAM.
And I have OBS Studio running here with my webcam
and everything.
I'm really surprised.
That's a really good distribution.
Really cool.
Wow.
I'm thinking about quitting another distribution
that shall not be named.
Oh, yeah.
It does seem to be, it's always nice to look.
I mean, I'm gonna be honest.
I've always been a bit of a hopper.
I stayed on Arch for quite a while,
but my hopper tendencies have been coming back recently,
if I'm gonna be honest with you.
You know, Mr. Wes, did you get a chance to try,
before we go on?
I didn't want to say anything else,
but before we go on, are you running it right there?
Oh, yeah.
And you're running the GNOME version?
I am.
I would be, I'd be really interested
to hear your thoughts,
because I have not tried the GNOME one.
You know, it's actually pretty slick.
I hate the default theme a lot less than I normally do.
Honestly, I just installed it.
I've done no customization.
It's pretty usable.
I could use this for a while.
Eventually, I would probably want ArcDark or whatever
installed with a few little tweaks here and there,
dash to dock, whatever.
All the normal things, but right here, it's pretty nice.
And I was very impressed with,
they have a nice little welcome screen,
kind of gets things set up.
The GNOME software's improved a lot over the years,
so that's like a decent experience,
and I've almost always had some kind of problem
with Anaconda.
It's always been my least favorite of the common installers.
This time, okay, first time, it crashed on me,
and I just rebooted it and did it again,
but that time, it worked perfectly.
I have kind of a weird partitioning scheme,
because there's already a couple OSs on here,
and in the past, that's really caused problems.
This time, nope, easy peasy.
Yeah, yeah, and that's the new,
Matt, are you still by the mic by chance?
Because that's one thing we didn't mention,
is there's a new partitioner in Anaconda
if you do the custom partitioning setup.
I am still here, yeah.
Is there anything more to add to that?
So what is, it's got a new name, or, I can't remember.
Yeah, it's called Blivit GUI, which is, I don't know,
another, some sort of in-joke of some sort.
I actually would like it to be something
a little more polished in the UI,
but we'll get to that eventually.
The basic thing is, when there's a big Anaconda rewrite,
like in Fedora 17 or 18 or something like that,
and it was based on a lot of the user studies
on how people install systems,
and the idea basically is, instead of telling it,
I've got this disk and this disk,
and I wanna make a partition on it in the logical volume,
and then this and this and this, and building it up,
you would say, I've got these disks,
I would like redundancy,
I would like a journaling file system, give it to me,
and then it would determine your configuration from that,
so it's kind of a top-down thing,
and I think that's good, especially for people who,
whom, when I say partitions and logical volumes,
they kind of get a panic look, it's really great for that,
but a lot of people have special cases
that didn't feel that covered,
or they definitely want to have partition,
the first partition be home,
because that's important to them,
or they are just more comfortable
doing the buildup kind of thing,
and so those people have, for a long time,
felt like the installer, Fedora installer,
doesn't suit their needs,
so this basically adds a third option
that's kind of a true partition manager thing
that can do a lot of very sophisticated things
for a buildup from the bottom environment.
On the other hand, you can,
and I did several times in testing,
make systems that will not boot that way,
so it really is for, if you know what you're doing,
this lets you do it.
Yeah, I did play around with it a little bit,
that definitely echoes,
it seems, there's not a lot of hand-holding,
but it is a lot more reminiscent of what you get
in a lot of other installers,
or even just something like, you know,
gnome disks or gparted.
And if you're going off in that neck of the woods,
you probably, that's probably the tool you want.
Yeah, it's like a power user escape hatch,
which I think is actually pretty nice.
I didn't use it ultimately to install my system,
I went back to the standard custom solution,
but it really, I think as it evolves,
I'll be happy to use it.
Yeah, and one of the UI problems we have a lot with that
is our installer people discovered that
if you have an advanced option,
people will always pick it,
even if it's going to make their life miserable.
So we wanted to try and figure out
how to freight it properly to get people steered,
not to choose it if they didn't know what it was.
So I'm possibly leaving it named blivet-gui
is the right thing for that for now,
but we'll figure that out.
I, it's a pretty, like I said,
it's a nice solid release
with tons of new stuff from upstream,
cause I mean, just bringing in that new gnome release
and then, and now also the new plasma release
and then when Anaconda gets some nice improvements,
it's just check, it's worth checking out for door 26.
And if you're crazy like me,
it's also very deployable on your digital ocean droplet.
If you go to digital ocean right now,
create an account and use our promo code DOUNPLUGED,
apply that to your account and you'll get a $10 credit.
Now at the moment it's fedora 25
is what's deployable on digital ocean.
However, I just did it a little bit during the show.
I spun up a 25 instance and I upgraded it to fedora 26,
just clean install, worked flawlessly.
So if you want to run that, you can also do that too.
It's all, I'll link to, in the show notes,
I have a link to how to upgrade
from fedora 25 to fedora 26.
I've been, I have a droplet now on this, on digital ocean.
It's four years old.
Wow.
I did not realize I've been using digital ocean that long.
Four years, it's an arch box.
It's an arch zone.
Good work, you've been doing your updates.
I've been keeping on, I've been keeping on.
And I have now also been running a fedora droplet for ages
and then I've got a bunch of Ubuntu droplets
and it's, you know, they also, they offer free BSD
and a bunch of other distributions.
It's a really easy way to spin up infrastructure on demand,
whether you want something personally for yourself
or hosting for your business.
Everything's SSDs from the low priced rigs
all the way up to the high priced rigs.
They have stuff with like 512 megs of RAM
for a nice slim system with things up like
over 200 gigs of RAM, tons of CPU cords, terabytes
and terabytes of transfer.
You can have team accounts, highly available block storage.
They're beta testing object storage right now.
They have loads of pre-built open source apps
that you can just one click deploy
and they're not like magic script setups.
It's legitimate.
Like if an expert system administrator built a system
to host next cloud, that's how it looks.
And like one of my favorite ones to do
is just a quick test.
I can deploy a base LTS system with Docker on it,
try something and then destroy it and spend like three cents.
It's amazing.
So great.
Digitalocean.com use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED
and yes, yes, you can run Fedora there as a matter of fact.
You crazy cats, just like I have been.
And you know what I do is I set up Fedora on there
and then I just manage my Fedora box
through cockpit all the time.
It's a super solid way.
Yeah, it's a super solid way to keep a Fedora system running.
And then in cockpit, there is a really simple
straightforward system to search for new Docker images,
click on them, pull them down.
And then when the first time you set them up,
you can set up all of the port forwarding,
you can set up paths and there's a UI
to just set all of that stuff and you hit save
and boom, everything just works.
That seems perfect for the casual admin.
You're not doing it every day, but you know the concepts,
maybe you forgot that command line switch.
Cockpit makes it just right there.
It's nice, it's really nice.
And the other thing that's really cool about it
is we've covered the security architecture of it
a couple of weeks ago, if you recall,
and it's really soundly built too.
So I actually feel pretty safe running it.
It's a pretty solid innovation.
You know, this is sort of tangentially related to Fedora
because they've been shipping Wayland by default now
since the last release and it looks like,
according to Will Cook, who's the head of the desktop team
over at Canonical, they're considering backing off
of their decision to ship Wayland in Ubuntu 17.10,
which could then ultimately impact the LTS in 2018.
Now, I think this announcement has been,
it's not really an announcement.
It's a discussion at this point, so keep that in mind.
This is not like this is being announced officially.
This is them discussing their gut feelings
about maybe Wayland not being ready yet.
And I think that's actually the fascinating thing about it
is that is a conversation to be had.
Is it stable enough?
They said they've taken some input from their users
that have been in testing and seen stability issues
with both Wayland and Ex-Wayland.
My gut feeling, Will Cook said,
is that Wayland isn't ready yet.
That's a tough thing because you wanna skate,
obviously, to where the puck is going,
and you wanna get this thing tested in the 17.10 release
before 18.04 hits, and you've got, obviously,
the Fedora distribution has been shipping it for a while.
But they had some legitimate use case problems
that they've had people writing in to them
in their testing that have come up.
So it's, I don't know.
The flip side of that is that we need this kind of,
we want Wayland to be really good.
We want it to be rock solid for the future.
We need these kinds of, sometimes it takes
another big distribution, being like,
okay, can we really use this?
What would that look like to make sure
that we do iron out all those bugs and make it stable?
Because we don't want another thing
where the pulse audio rollout or whatever,
where now no one trusts Wayland,
it's not gonna get good rep,
maybe less developers want to work on it.
Well, it's just the hard truth of default rules supreme.
So you could even include Wayland as a session option,
you know, GNOME parenthesis Wayland,
and then you could have GNOME X11 as the default.
But you're just gonna have a dramatic volume difference
between the amount of users testing it
and submitting bug reports if you do that.
It's just gonna, it's gonna be a tiny, tiny, tiny fraction
of the Ubuntu user base would use that.
Pretty much people who probably could,
might install it anyway.
I mean, I can tell you all of my Arch systems right now
that are running in this studio all have an option
to log into GNOME on Wayland, and I never do it.
I've had problems, especially I've had problems with Chrome
and I just don't, I guess I'm waiting it out.
But at some point you're right,
you gotta rip the bandaid off.
And Wayland is really at this point becoming a joke
if we can't get this thing out the door.
It's been years in development.
Now I guess, you know, if you look at it
in the grand scheme of things,
I think X has been around since Reagan was president,
so I don't know if that's true,
but it feels like it probably is true actually.
We just have long timelines.
So I guess if you consider in the grand scheme of things,
Wayland is still just a young pup.
And I guess maybe this is just the long haul,
but this stuff isn't easy.
And it sounds like the Ubuntu devs
are just uncertain about which way to go.
So we'll just have to stay tuned.
I'm gonna keep watching it.
There's also, there's a little follow-up news
to something we covered before, GR security.
Remember when we mentioned GR security
was sort of branching off and doing their own thing
and closing up their patch set against the Linux kernel,
which promises to make the Linux kernel super secure.
And now they're releasing it in this stable patch access
agreement license that says that you can take this GPL code,
but you're not allowed to share it.
And if you do, we're gonna revoke your access.
And they kind of have people really sort of
by the elbow here because these are oftentimes
business customers that have systems out on the web
that are doing e-commerce that are being audited.
And this is how they say they're secure
is because they have this, oh yeah, we have hardened Linux.
We've hardened our Linux with GR security.
We've hardened it.
It's used a lot by like multi-tenant hosts
or people running like open VZ containers
or other things like that.
And so what are they gonna do?
You know, they've been using this thing for years.
And then one day these guys decide to go,
ah, no, we're going commercial product and you gotta pay.
Huh, what's that?
No, you pay, you pay.
You can take it and you can use that GPL software,
but you gotta pay and you can't do anything with it.
If you distribute that, if you make modifications to it
and you share that GPL code with anybody,
we're gonna come after you, kind of crazy.
And it's got a few people's attention.
It got our attention a few weeks ago.
We talked about it here on the show.
And Linus about a week ago really ripped him a new one
saying that their code quality was just garbage.
Not really even concerning,
not even really mentioning the license issues,
but just saying that, you know,
they're a bunch of basically dweebs is what he said.
I mean, he said it in harsher terms.
Well, there is a gentleman, Bruce Perns,
who is an advisor to lawyers.
So wrap your head around that for a second.
And what does he advise those lawyers about?
GPL compliance.
You see where we're going here.
Now that GR security has taken their patch set
that they claim makes Linux better
and they've wrapped it behind
the stable patch access agreement,
customers are warned that if they redistribute
any of this GPL code, there's gonna be a penalty.
Well, here's the problem.
You can't deny this one fact.
GR security is a patch for the Linux kernel.
It's inseparable from Linux.
It, GR security does not work without Linux.
So this would fail a fair use test.
Because it's strongly derivative nature of the kernel,
it must be under GPL version two license
or a license compatible with GPL
and with terms no more restrictive than the GPL.
And there is a pretty clear clause of the GPL.
It's GPL section six, which specifically prohibits
any additions of terms as well.
So they're also violating it
by wrapping these additional terms.
They really got themselves in a pickle here.
And I think these guys are ripe for the picking.
I mean, I think this is gonna be one juicy, juicy pickle
that somebody is gonna come along
and decide to take a bite out of.
Nobody has yet, there's no lawsuits yet.
But there seems to be some pretty solid
GPL violation issues here.
And then this Bruce guy here at the bottom of his pose
is like, by the way, if you want to consult with me
and see these guys, it's essentially what he says.
He doesn't say it like that.
Give me a callskies and we'll work something out here.
So it's open hunting season for GR.
You got Linus coming after him.
You got obvious GPL compliance questions.
Well, there's been a lot of, let's say drama back and forth
between the projects.
I mean, for a long time, but even more recently
with they had some threats of lawsuits
against people like Kees Cook
and the Linux self-protection project
for using their work without proper attribution.
And it's just this whole culture of like,
they've certainly had some innovations.
They've done a lot of good research,
but it's been a long history of not using
the kernel standard, not making patches
that have any hope of doing it.
And they just, you know, there's a very,
almost in a similar style to OpenBSD.
It's a security first, but of course,
Linus is never gonna ship a broken kernel
even if it is more secure.
Well, stop right there.
I mean, like what a, that is a huge red flag
is if GR security is based intrinsically on upstream
and they have a hostile relationship with upstream.
Well, that doesn't lead to a good product.
You know, like that's not how you set up a winner.
So it's, this is a difficult situation for them for sure.
And I don't know if it really has direct impact on us
unless any of you out there are working in businesses
that use this, but it's sort of a fascinating one
to sit back from the rafters and watch a bit.
You know, we have a little NF tables stuff to get to,
but I also have a couple of cool apps
that I've been itching to talk about.
Wonder, let's do this.
Let's talk about this,
just this quick little open source app
that we found this week.
Cause this is just a real quickie.
It's called I want, and it's a decentralized
peer-to-peer file sharing command line application.
And this came across both Wes's radar and mine.
And it's just a, it's a CLI tool for searching
and downloading files on your land network
without any central server,
which I think that's kind of cool.
It includes easy discovery of files.
So it's sort of like a search type syntax.
You can download it from multiple,
multiple machines on your network.
This could be handy for us because we have large media files
that we're distributing.
You can do entire directory downloads.
And obviously, as you would hope,
it does support a resumption of file transfers.
It is, it is very careful about getting consistent data.
Any changes made to files inside a shared folder
are instantly reflected on the network.
It works on Linux.
It works on Windows and it works on the Mac.
Although I think this guy even admits like,
Mac version, I wouldn't use it to quite yet.
And if you, if you, if you want to give it a go,
just pip install, I want, it might also be in the AUR.
And I think it's kind of, it sounds like a really cool way
to just toss files around your network.
One of the questions that consistently has come in
over the years is what's the best way to share files
that's not Samba.
And a lot of times what our answer is,
well, if you have, if you have one machine that's always on,
you could consider setting up some NFS mounts.
But a lot of times what we tell people
is just use SCP.
Just toss it around on your network using SSH.
Kind of not super intuitive for people
that are coming from different operating systems.
Yep, and if you don't have keys set up,
there's maybe a lot of passwords and things.
Yeah, yeah, or if you have different passwords
on different machines.
Yeah, exactly.
So this could be a nice way,
if you have a nice, safe, trusted LAN,
like here at the network, here at the JB studios,
you know, we have, we have like large files
that we want to toss around between our machines.
And sometimes just being lazy,
we'll just throw it on Dropbox.
Yeah, exactly.
And it's like, why go all the way up to the cloud,
sync it to all my machines, bring it all the way down.
Why not just toss that one gig file
directly to somebody's machine using something like I want.
And I've played around before with graphical ones,
and I think command line is the way to go.
Yeah, especially if you're listening to this show.
What?
You do say, you do say.
You know, I won't be here.
I won't be here next week.
Are you?
How do you feel about that?
Are you okay?
You gonna be good?
Well, I mean, I'll miss you.
Yeah, yeah.
But I think you're gonna have a great time.
Yeah, yeah, I am heading off to.
You're gonna come back refreshed, ready to podcast?
Hmm, yeah, hopefully.
I'm going to Montana.
I would like to have seen Montana.
And it's gonna be hot.
It's gonna be, it's gonna be really hot.
So hopefully, like when we get there,
it's gonna be like 100 degrees.
There's some sweaty vlogs coming up.
I don't know, I don't know.
The cameras maybe will have to go away from that sweaty.
But yeah, I'm gonna be there with Noah.
He's gonna be doing Ask Noah live from there.
Is that right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I don't think.
That rascal.
No, I think, but I think we have a very special guest,
somebody from one of our other shows will be joining us.
We'll be joining Wes.
Yes, that's right.
We'll be joining Wes, because I won't be here.
But you guys, I think, will have a great show.
So if you out there in the audience
want to help the boys out while I'm gone,
head over to jblive.tv next Tuesday and join the Mumble Room.
You can get in the IRC there and just do Bang Mumble,
or exclamation mark, and get the server information.
And then you can hang out with Wes
and his special guest next week.
It'll be a lot of fun.
So there's a particularly cool little bit
of benchmarking and engineering work that was done.
And kind of a nice bit of research
that I would have loved to have done if had I had the time.
Because I've always wondered, what
is the difference between NF tables and IP tables?
And how is this new world, and does it scale
if you want to set up, say, maybe a Linux firewall?
And is it too much overhead if you just want to have it
on your workstation?
These are all questions I've pondered, but never really
sat down to iron out.
And so this next piece was a really solid bit
of research and write-up.
But I want to mention Linux Academy briefly,
because I think this is a great opportunity when you
get into this kind of stuff.
If anything we're talking about goes over your head,
consider going over to Linux Academy.
Or if you just want to just step your skill level up a bit,
stay competitive, maybe get a new job,
or just look good in a review, Linux Academy.
Start by going to LinuxAcademy.com slash unplug.
Sign up for a free seven-day trial of the Linux Academy
platform.
It's a place to learn everything about Linux.
They have self-paced, in-depth video courses,
hands-on labs that give you real experience with this stuff.
And I think probably one of my favorite features
that really makes Linux Academy stand out.
And this is really possible because they're really
all in on Linux.
It's not just something they do.
It's not just something they cover,
along with the Cisco stuff and the Microsoft stuff.
This is what they do.
Everything from the nitty-itty bitties
all the way up to the big stuff, like OpenStack and AWS
and Azure, they have the entire Linux pipeline.
And that's why they can offer instructor mentoring, full time
human instructors who know this material top to bottom
because this is what they focus on.
That's a huge differentiator for Linux Academy.
They have these virtual servers that they spin up
simultaneously with your courseware,
which is a really cool thing because you're going along
and it's like, OK, now SSH into this and try this out.
Boom.
My mind was blown the first time I did that because it's like,
I can sit there with the material on my screen
and then in my favorite console, I'm SSHed in just
like it would be any other system I'm working on.
It's just a brilliant way to learn.
It's especially great for things like AWS
where you're like, how much is this going to cost me?
I don't really understand.
I'm just trying to learn.
You don't even have to worry about it.
Let them take care of it.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
Big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring
the unplugged program.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
Sign up for a free seven day trial
at LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
So this is Benchmarking NF Tables
over at the developers.redhat.com blog.
And it was posted by Phil.
It was a little bit ago, but it was something that kind of,
I think, came across as Wes's radar.
And he passed it on to me, and I was pretty fascinated by it.
For starters, it's just interesting to see
how he decided to do this.
He wanted to figure out how different firewall setups
affected performance.
And so he messed around with a simple test framework, which
he could feed a bunch of different setup snippets
and then cycle through them.
And then he could test scalability with these snippets
by adding a number and a scale ranger from 0 to 100.
And then the test script would go off,
and it would run each possible value to that scale.
And then each value equals a multiple of five benchmarks.
And those are then performed, repeated nine more times.
The results are all plotted out with nice beautiful graphs.
And we end up in this post.
And what we get here is some rather interesting revelations,
including the fact that it seems to be that there
is a bit of a performance difference that
is fairly noticeable between IP tables and NF tables
on really small setups, like 20 or fewer rules,
or even like 100 or fewer rules.
IP tables may actually be more performant than NF tables.
But IP tables, if I read this correctly, there is,
and same to a degree with NF tables,
but I'll talk about that more in a second, with IP tables,
there is some suffering of performance
as the number of rules increases.
Not too surprising.
So the overhead introduced with adding rules
becomes less and less significant
the more rules there are with NF tables,
because NF tables handles this in a little bit different way.
It sort of does some of the logic ahead of time.
And it eats that cost initially, and then that cost
is essentially spent, that time is spent.
And then it is able to scale up more rules much, much faster
and performant than IP tables, which
has to go through the chain and consider
every single rule every time.
And so it's interesting, because at the smaller scale,
that might actually be advantageous with IP tables,
depending on your setup.
But if you consider that NF tables are still early days,
and they're still working on it, that
seems like a performance gap they're
going to probably close as well.
Right.
Really been focused on functionality, not
optimization yet.
What was your take from some of this stuff?
Was there anything that jumped out at you
as sort of an interesting result?
There's just so many tests between these systems.
There's a lot to dig into to this one.
For me, I think that one of the bigger things is, yes,
there's still early days around NF tables.
Some of the command line stuff needs to be worked out,
some of how that works.
There's some unintuitive bits, especially
if you're already familiar with IP tables and kind
of the defaults, the default chains, and tables,
and things that already exist.
But I'm really excited.
What struck me is it looks like NF tables and the NFT command.
There's going to be a lot of things that we can do with this
in more intuitive ways than we can now.
In particular, I think this article highlights
that if you want to do kind of traffic control things,
there's the TC application, which is part of IP route 2.
But it is one of the least intuitive command line
applications I've ever used.
If you actually need to do things with it,
I would definitely recommend something
like Fire QoS that can help automate that in a sane way.
But not only is the way NF tables
uses Netfilter to accomplish some of the same things easier
to do, it looks like it's actually
a little more performant.
So that story on Linux might be getting a little bit better,
which I think is great.
Did you see the part here?
And I just sort of read the highlight of this section
because I thought I'd pass it on to the audience.
He also performed DDoS protection testing
to see how NF tables stood up versus IP tables
and get a bunch of different ways to see how they handled it.
And I took away that essentially NF tables probably
would handle this better in an actual situation.
But I thought I'd list all that in there
because part of what he tested to see was, like you were saying,
is TC and blacklisting IP addresses in real time
and stuff like that and cycling through 100,000 packets
per second using package gen and just all kinds of cool stuff
the way he set this up.
So it's a fascinating read if you guys
want to read through the whole thing.
The TLDR might be the most prominent information
to draw from the experiment is that similar IP tables and NF
table setups are comparable in performance.
NF tables is usually a bit behind,
but given that the development focus at this point
is still on functionality, like you were saying,
it's going to be changing.
IP set is a blessing to any IP table setup.
NF tables follows their path with their native implementation
and their concepts.
Then NF tables could be in a great spot too.
He says he's not still convinced of his test results.
He still thinks there's probably no point
in breaking a leg over implementing something in TC
if the same thing is possible in net filter.
Yeah, that's a good summary.
It's a good post.
And it looks like, I don't know, if you're considering setting
up a Linux firewall, you might want to read it
and just decide, depending on what your scale is,
what would work for you.
Yeah, definitely.
Yeah.
And you might be surprised.
And it might be we're getting close enough maybe now
in a similar vein to Wayland, perhaps,
where, especially maybe for home use,
I don't have crazy performance concerns for my house.
Exactly.
I might be the time where I could convert over to NFT
and see what happens.
Yeah, and start just sort of learning now.
And then, because that's kind of where things are going.
Yeah, right.
I mean, it'll be years yet, I'm sure,
before I want it on the production server.
But someday.
Yeah.
One little story before we go.
Oh, I know that sound.
Your buddies over at Gabe's office
are working on some big updates to the Steam client.
I saw this over on gamingonlinux.com.
And I'll just cover a moment of what they are planning to do,
because it's from them.
Another thing we're working on is a major redesign
of the Steam client, which is probably far overdue.
So that includes a redesign of the whole Chrome
of the Steam desktop client.
But I think probably the most relevant and interesting thing
for you guys is going to be the redesigns
that we're working on for the Steam library
section in particular.
So once a customer owns your game,
what is that experience like in Steam?
Talking to developers, obviously.
So let's get forward a couple there.
So there's kind of two big parts of that update
in the library.
One is going to be a new library home screen.
If you've used big picture mode at all
and you go into your library, there's
kind of a similar thing that's in Steam big picture
mode, which surfaces games that your friends are playing right
now, surfaces things that you've recently played,
surfaces recently updated games.
We're taking that and we're building on that
so that when a customer comes and logs into Steam,
if they really just want to go back and play
the last game they were playing, it's super easy
to launch it right from there.
We're not making that any harder.
I'm going to leave the rest of the video for you guys.
It's 42 minutes long, so I'm not going
to play all that in the show.
But good to hear that update's coming.
And yes, it includes one to Linux.
That's kind of nice.
It's good to see that, too.
Are you much of a gamer, Wes?
Have we ever talked about that?
I don't think we've really done a gaming episode
since you've been a host.
No, we haven't really.
You know, I don't get very much time to play games these days.
But I do really enjoy it.
I try to find time here and there on the weekend to do it.
I've not yet set up my new place.
I've not yet set up my gaming tower.
But it's on the list of things to do.
So maybe we can do that here shortly.
Yeah, I would be, you know, maybe one day.
Maybe.
People don't love it, so we'll just do it experimentally.
But we would love it.
Yeah, right, exactly.
Hey, that sounds like great fun.
Before we go, I want to mention that we're
doing a little sweepstakes for a Dell XPS 13 developer
edition, which means one of the Linux machines.
You've heard Chris talk about it.
Now you can have it in your hands.
Yeah, spic and span, brand new one shipped directly from Dell.
Now, this is US residents only.
This is just sort of the way that this particular one
has to be.
And you have to be 18 years or older.
But if you're in the US and are perhaps
interested in getting a Dell XPS 13,
you can enter the sweepstakes to win.
Go to jupyterbroadcasting.com, click on the Shows menu option,
and choose the User Airdropdown.
And then you can enter to win there.
And we'll be announcing it here soon,
before I think it's coming up.
Now, since I won't be here, you probably
won't hear much about it next week.
So I just wanted to mention it now,
because it's a great opportunity.
And then stay tuned to the User Air program for the winner.
Yeah.
We'll be announcing it in there.
Last week, User Air went out a little late.
So episode 16, Desktop as a Surface, went out.
User Air 16 includes things from more discussion about LTS
overrolling, particularly in certain production
environments, the East slash West divide of Linux
that seems to keep coming up, two different types of cultures
that are clashing there.
We talk more about the Linux Laptop Survey.
And actually, we really dug into that for a bit.
And then end up with Microsoft's Desktop as a Service
announcement, and sort of how that affects Linux users,
maybe helps good and bad.
So it's a pretty great episode of User Air.
It's episode 16.
I know what I'm doing after the show.
You know what I'm doing after the show?
I actually have two ribeyes from the barbecue last week,
cooking in the sous vide machine right now.
So when you're doing TechSnap, I'm
going to be finishing those up.
I am still eating off of the extra food.
That's amazing.
Of course, I'm fasting, too, here and there.
It stretches it out.
But yeah, there was just so much good stuff here, really great.
Great people, great time.
It was such a good time.
So if you missed last week, go check out
last week's episode of the Unplugged program.
It was a lot of fun hanging out with them, folks.
Well, Mr. West, I just mentioned it there.
People can find more of you on the TechSnap program.
Oh, yeah.
Stay tuned.
You and Dan doing that.
They do it live right after this show.
So if you want to come next week in to hang out
with Wes and his special guest and then just stay tuned,
keep it up.
And you just get to watch the TechSnap program.
Yeah, it's awesome.
Back to back.
You are a busy man.
You know it.
Back to back right there.
You can also participate in the Mumble room.
Bang Mumble when you're in our IRC room, which is, again,
at jblive.tv.
And the live times are all posted at the calendar
at jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar.
You can also go to our subreddit,
linuxunplugged.reddit.com.
You can leave us feedback at jupitabroadcasting.com
slash contact.
You can tweet me at chrislas.
Follow the network at jupitersignal.
I won't be here next week.
I'll miss you.
But the show will go on.
That's right, it will.
And I think it's going to be a really good one.
Oh, yeah.
First time special guest on this show.
So that's going to be really cool, too.
It's a first time special guest.
We'll put them through their paces.
That's for sure.
I'm sure we will.
OK, everybody, thanks so much for tuning
into this week's episode of the Unplugged program.
And we'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
Goodbye, everybody.
Oh, boy, the chat room was punny today.
Look at these titles.
A fitting fedora.
The new fedora fits well.
Fedora's new hat trick.
Oh, man, most of these bad ones are WW's fault. No, I'm kidding.
Ouch.
JamieTitles.com, now we've got to go pick our title.
Hey, hey, at least I didn't, I'm not the one that came up
with Boltron.
You can't blame me for that.
That Boltron title, though, I kind of liked it.
I got it, because it's like bolt on.
But it's Boltron, which is even cooler.
Those fedora guys are working on some good stuff over there.
I'll tell you what, that really is impressive.
I cannot believe that I have pushed a fedora server
install that far, running Nextcloud and all that stuff.
Maybe it's the new way.
Maybe it's the new normal.
I don't know.
Or maybe I'm lucky.
The hipster BSD.
It was easy.
I will say, while you're doing that,
I installed OBS on the fedora.
No.
Super easy.
They actually have instructions that just add the RPS.
Which version?
Can you see which version it is?
I just rebooted back to R, because I can't.
But I'll check later.
That's cool.
This on our production one here is 19.02.
OK.
19.02-1.
JamieTitles.com, the tree speaks fedora.
The tree speak fedora.
What is that a reference to?
I don't know.
I'm not sure either.
Five people seem to think they get it, though,
because it's got five upvotes.
It's like the number one title.
It's the wallpaper.
It's the wallpaper that means fedora.
Right.
It is a nice wallpaper, I will say.
That title, though, is such a head scratcher
when you see that.
You know what's funny?
I honestly 100% thought that was a word.
It's like, oh, wait, oh, no, trees.
Yep.
That was interesting.
Yeah, I get it now, XM.
I get it now.
OK.
Remember how I have rib eyes cooking?
Oh.
Rolling pain, that's not bad.
Rolling pains, atomic fedora, fedora's tree line,
fedora incubator, there's boltron bend, the fedora fiasco,
fedora, fedora, adora, ah, jbtitles.com, jbtitles.com.
There's a lot of titles, a lot of titles.
I'm just going to put it, there's a lot of titles over there.
There's a lot of titles.
Not saying that much more than that, though.
It's crazy.
Crazy.
Yippee, yay.
So here, I also appreciated this.
Fedora handles UEFI very nicely.
Let me just say that.
I like that a lot because it did not
screw up my Arch UEFI install.
And gone are the horrible days of overwriting different boot
loaders and things.
It's like, I just picked the one, boom.
Yep.
That does feel like the future a little bit, doesn't it?
Yeah.
Finally.