This round of applause is dedicated to one and only Carl George right there. Mr. Carl,
I have to thank you. I don't think I've eaten better this year. I ate so well while I was
visiting Texas Cyber Summit.
Incredible.
Right?
Yeah.
You were very welcome, sir.
Highlight of the trip.
Yeah. Thank you very much, Carl. Also, thank you for driving us around.
You created a lasting good impression of San Antonio, I've got to say. I mean, I want
to go back.
I agree.
I like food a lot, and driving is just kind of a way of life in Texas. Everything's so
spread out.
We are so, so thankful, though, because we travel to these places that we have never
been before. That was my first time in San Antonio.
Same.
Jesus, I'm sure you've been in San Antonio plenty of times.
Yeah, as a kid, but not as of recent, so.
So you wouldn't necessarily know all the great spots.
No.
Yeah. And you go there, you don't know where you're at, you have no way of getting around.
Especially in a big place like Texas, right?
And thankfully we do these shows, and so we have listeners in those areas, and they sort
of are our tour guides in a way. It's so awesome. And the great thing about Carl is if he suggests
we go to a place, we don't even debate.
No, no question.
Which, in a group of people, Carl, you've seen this, in a large group of people, right?
You could spend like a half hour trying to figure out where to go eat.
And you end up with something not so great.
Oh man, we ate so good.
My main concern was, I just didn't want y'all to come to town, and then just go, you know,
walk around the Riverwalk, and then get back home and say, yeah, well, San Antonio was
fine. I wanted y'all to have a better experience than that.
No, and you have that local experience, so you know that hole in the wall. Well, except
for in San Antonio, it's more like that hole outside that has outside seating, but great
food.
Right, like the carnitas place that had one menu item.
Yeah, when the guy asked if what else was on the menu, and the lady just looked at him
like, uh, there is no other item on the menu.
Hello friends, and welcome into Linux Unplugged, episode 323. I'm Chris.
I'm Wes.
323?
Nicely done.
Is that even a thing anymore?
It is now.
You've been here since episode 100, so nicely done to you too.
Well, Mr. Payne, we have a great show. We're going to have our first look at Ubuntu 19.10,
which is likely releasing just as a, well, maybe when you listen, it kind of depends
on your schedule, but just about as you listen to this, Ubuntu 19.10 is releasing. We've
got some big community news, including a new KDE Plasma, and even more changes for Gnome
Shell, which, oh boy, it just got a new Gnome Shell, yeah, it's wild. Plus, not just myself,
not just Wes, but Mr. Cheese and Mr. Drew are here to give you their takes on 19.10.
Hello gentlemen.
Hello.
Hi. Nice to have you here. We all ended up trying out 19.10 for various reasons and all
walked away with different notes, so I think this is going to be a really good one. And
of course, we've got our virtual lug. Hello there, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Oh, hi.
Howdy.
Hey there.
Look at that, a healthy showing.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room. Good to have you here. So let's start
out with the community news this week, because we're going to be talking a lot in Gnome Shell
and Maté later today, so I thought we'd kick things off with some Plasma news. Version
5.17 is out today as we record. The big thing here for me is I'm all about, I like that
color grading, and Night Color is built in. It's a color grading system that helps your
eyes relax as the sun sets, as they put it, and it is now in X11. It also recognizes when
you're giving a presentation.
I love that.
It turns on D&D on that screen. That is straight up brilliant. That's next level D&D.
I mean, if you're like me, you have friends who send you embarrassing messages right when
they know you're giving a presentation.
That's actually a great prank. That is really great. But also, just sort of as a meta feature
for 5.17, things are thriftier than ever with Plasma.
Oh, yeah. It starts so fast. I'm actually running 5.17 right now. I updated it before
doing the show. Pleased to say my Neon install is doing just great, honestly. They finally
ditched Bash for some of the scripts that run as you're starting up Plasma, right? So
you get past the login screen, you've entered your password, you have work to get done.
Before it was totally synchronous. It runs Bash, it waits for the script to complete,
and then you get a desktop.
I mean, I love Bash, but it's not the fastest thing on the planet.
So now they've rewritten it in C++, and it's totally asynchronous. So login can just start
right once you're authenticated.
That's nice. That is very nice. As well as many, many, many, many other features that
are in Plasma, including some system settings, improvements for Thunderbolt support. In fact,
overall, there's just been general improvements to system settings.
Oh, yeah. Tons of improvements to system settings. And there's more stuff for like ksysguard,
which can talk about cgroup limits, which you probably have if you're running a whole
bunch of containers or doing fancy system D stuff.
Yeah, I also like that they put some stuff in there for visualization of the NVIDIA GPU
stats.
Sexy.
That's really nice for Ubuntu users, since the NVIDIA binary driver is now on the ISO.
But one of the main new features of Plasma 5.17 display manager kwin is fractional scaling
on Wayland.
That's a fancy term. What does it mean? Well, it means you can scale your desktop to suit
your high DPI monitor perfectly, right? You might not need like, a two time scaling that
might be too much. You can dial it down now with fractional support. So you won't have
tiny or gigantic fonts and icons on those 4k screens.
I like it on a 4k screen because I can get a little more real estate without having to
be too tiny.
And also, I mean, kwin's Wayland support has come a long way, right? I mean, we've been
covering it on this show for years. This was one feature that it's kind of it's kind of
been missing. It's been a standout missing feature that's finally corrected.
Yeah. Also, something that's coming back. If you're an old desktop KDE user and you
miss the ability to close windows with the middle click, it's back, baby. It's back.
Is that just going to confuse some people?
Here's why it's nice. It's a great way when you've got a couple of windows up, you can
close a window without changing focus.
I will say three mouse buttons strictly better than two.
Way better, right? Who doesn't want three mouse buttons? What am I in the 80s? Also,
here's a funny one. You can now on X 11, which wasn't really super easy before, properly
map the super key, you know, the little windows can. Yeah, that must have taken some work
in the back end, you know, deep engineering, I think on that one.
It did take some work in the back end. Having done that in Marte over like 18 months. It's
hard work that
What is it? What is it that's so dang hard? Because it has been a very top requested feature
of plasma desktop.
I mean, is it just that X is old and broken?
No, it's it's the fact that anything could have a key bound to super. So when that gets
picked up, you need to pass that event along all through the chain of windows so that any
window that's got that in their key bindings can respond when they have focus and it has
to touch lots and lots of parts of the system.
Yeah. All right. So I've waffled on this last item here. But let's talk about it. Discover
plasma software manager lets you install, remove and update applications. It's been
improved in this release. It includes better progress bars for the first time. And different
like UI feedback indicators that tell you it's working. And they've added icons to properly
demonstrate snap applications to help to help you get just some more information. And they've
helped with better feedback on connection issues. However, maybe we'll get to this in
a little bit. But having gone through a few different desktop environments in the last
couple of days to try out 1910 boy does discover feel like the absolute least favorite part
of the worst. And I hate to say that about free software that people are working really
hard on.
It's not that it's necessarily terrible. It is usable. I do use it from time to time.
It's just that the competition has gotten a lot better, frankly. Yeah, I don't I don't
know what the solution here is, because they have diligently worked to make this better
for a while. And it still seems like it's behind everything else. And I don't know what
would be better. And I obviously couldn't write something better myself. But boy, does
it feel like the weaker spot of the desktop right now. But it is nice to see some of these
improvements, some of these informational feedback things will go a long way and at
least making it much, much, much more usable than it has in the past. So they do seem to
be taking in the right direction. Yeah, I mean, continue to work is always appreciated.
You do wonder though, it's like, well, when you just start over, yeah, need to figure
out quite what's wrong with the core there. Well, speaking of core core boot is coming
to Comet Lake chips on system 76 laptops, at least two of them, the new 14 inch galgo
pro and the new 15.6 inch starter pro laptops will ship with core boot firmware, rather
than a proprietary BIOS. Now, as you probably know, and has been pointed out by Mr. Michael
liable over at for Onyx, these laptops still have Intel proprietary blobs because of course
they do. So it's probably best to think of them as more open than most laptops rather
than being completely open. Yeah, yeah. But still, system 76 is just one of a handful
of PC vendors shipping computers with core boot. purism comes to mind as another but
frankly, system 76 has more compelling and more options for laptops. Yeah, honestly,
this is great to see. I mean, I've I've played with core boot a little and for me the biggest
the biggest blockers, but I just didn't have hardware that was, you know, supported by
it. I think it's a great option. And we need people in this space working on it keeping
it modern. I think it lost a lot of momentum after you know, EFI support sort of went mainstream.
If system 76 can keep things working nicely on modern hardware, that should help everyone.
I just thought of this now. I should have thought of it before the show. If anyone at
system 76 wants to let me know, is this guaranteed to now be a thing for all future galgos and
darters? Like will all future darters and galgos just guaranteed have this or is this
just this current line? What do you think of this wimpy? Well, I think it's a great
step towards you know, freeing firmware in computers from proprietary bits and pieces
that we can't really know what they're poking around at. And coincidentally, while I was
at ubu con last week, I was reacquainted with an organization that I've worked with in the
past who are also doing some interesting things with core boot. That's a tease. All right.
There's this outfit in Portugal called LibreTrend. Wimpy. You're such a tease sometimes. I know.
And we did some work with them having Ubuntu Mate pre-installed on one of their devices
few years ago, which was a core boot device. And it was like a NUC equivalent type device.
Anyway, they sort of went dark for a couple of years and they went away back to the drawing
board and they've come back last year with a new desktop machine, which kind of looks
like a Mac Mini. And that is a fully core boot enabled device. And they're very proud
of that. But more importantly, they're doing work with the LVFS project to deliver core
boot firmware updates via LVFS. So that is coming soon. And they also have two laptops,
the Wildebeest and the Wildebeest Pro, neither of which are core boot at the moment. But
what they're doing is they're gauging interest in those two devices to see which of the strongest
sellers in order to determine which device they invest the time and effort into getting
core boot on. And again, this LVFS work. So they spent about two years doing the engineering
upfront for this LibreTrend LibreBox, they call it, which was fully engineered from the
very beginning to be core boot. And it's also got TPM2 modules for full disk encryption
and stuff like that, all in hardware. But for the laptops, they've decided they can't
afford that kind of investment each time they do a device. So they're testing the waters
as to which is the more popular unit in order to determine where they put the engineering
effort in.
What do you suppose the long term benefit for the user is?
There's a growing trend, isn't there, to sort of create these devices that do have unencumbered
firmware. And there's clearly a large enough niche of users that desire that to support
the, well, first of all, the R&D and the expense of working on this. But there's several companies
around the world doing this now. So I think they're really looking out for that niche
of users that really cares about their privacy.
What a thing. We're becoming a market that actually needs to be addressed. What a hell
of a thing.
That's a nice feeling.
It really is. Gnome Shell's getting better. And we're going to talk a lot about Gnome
Shell, or Gnome Shell as I call it, in a little bit. But what you're about to get on your
latest version of your favorite distro is already out of date. But don't worry, it's
mostly fixes.
Yeah, Gnome Shell 3.34.1 is heavy on those fixes. I mean, you've got stuff like allowing
the editing of app folder names, making menu animations more consistent, improving performance
when enabling and disabling extensions, which, hey, I sometimes have to do that, fixing screen
dimming on idle, crash fixes, and a variety of animation fixes, which all that doesn't
sound like a lot, but I think it adds up to something noticeable.
Yeah. Plus, there's also code for Wayland full screen compositing bypass, which is a
big deal for full screen video and games. But the other thing to watch with these future
gnome developments, sorry, Gnome developments is what happens with Mutter.
Oh, yeah. Okay, so they've got some fixes for Java applications, which I know, I know,
but it's still nice to have. Plus fixing the startup of X11 session services on Wayland,
better screenshot and window animation support when scaled, optimizing the booting of untransformed
off screen stage views, various other scaling fixes, and fixing the num lock state for the
native backend. Plus a whole bunch of crash fixes, which, hey, as someone who's complained
about that before, it's really nice to see.
Yeah. It does feel like each release is a big deal.
Yeah. And I think that's what matters here is this is a point release with a lot of usability
and just like, day of, you know, everyday use improvements. And you don't have to wait
for something like gnome 3.36 coming in March.
Yeah, right. Or four or whatever. It really feels like a remarkably different time than
when canonical announced that they were ditching unity seven, doesn't it wimpy?
Yeah, I suppose so. I mean, it's sort of really growing with momentum now. I mean, it's, you
know, it's got all of the mainstream distros shipping it as the default desktop experience
now.
Right. I mean, hearken back to that era. I was one of the individuals that was pretty
outspokenly concerned about performance and stability issues. I don't know if you noticed.
And we switched out our whole studio off of gnome shell because of it. I don't feel like
that would be an issue today.
Yeah, well, hopefully not. I mean, you know, there's a lot of people that have put a considerable
amount of effort into improving that situation. And in fact, as we talk, there is a gnome
hack fest taking place in the Netherlands this week. And there are two members of the
Ubuntu desktop team, Marco and Seb, who are both present there working on, you know, crushing
precisely these kinds of issues. I know that closing the gap between x11 and Wayland is
one of the objectives of this week's hack fest.
Oh, that's great. It really seems like there's been enough back end work done in the past
few years that now some momentum can actually happen. Right. And some of the user facing
features things that we notice, well, those are improving.
I think very much so. We'll get to it here in the review in a moment. But I was really
worried we weren't going to be able to even begin to solve the gnome shell problems that
we had.
We had an episode here where we debated, like, is this whole thing junk? Should we even continue
to building on it?
Well, I had a real crisis of faith because here's all these top distributions shipping
it as the default shell, and it just didn't meet my my muster. Like, too slow, too many
different issues, crashes all the time.
Takes down my whole environment.
Right. And I was extremely worried that so many of the problems were fundamentally at
the core of gnome shell that they were not solvable. But really smart people have looked
at this and they've been solving a lot of problems. And it really has become a example
of how different companies with different goals and different priorities can come together
and improve a common piece of free software. It's a pretty good example. It's not perfect
yet. It's not all solved yet. But it has it has become
we have a fantastic desktop environment as a result, right? Much more, much more better,
much more improved, much more usable, much, much faster. All of the bunches you can really
give it. So I think it's really kind of time we kind of get into some of that because he
can't really keep talking about some of these without getting into the review itself. Before
we do that, we should probably do a little housekeeping because there's recently been
a batch of brunches. Oh, my. So many. A batch of brunches, Wes.
A batch. Maybe batches. I don't know. So for those of you that are not familiar
with this phenomenon, Brent here, who joins us on the mumble. Hello, Brent.
Oh, hey. Hey, there. Turns out great interviewer. And he really
gets down. You know, I think he does this thing called listening. It's it's new. You've
never tried it. Wow. Wow. Cuts deep. See, I listen to that. And Brent just is. He's
a great conversationalist. And so we created this concept Brunch with Brent with Brent
because he also, by the way, makes great brunch. He sits down with somebody and he has a conversation
and it just is great podcasting. And so recently, a batch of brunches has been released, including
a chat with Angela Fisher and Alan Jude. Both. You got to go check out extras dot show.
You know, I guess one really neat thing to say about the chat with Alan is that you were
able to visit him in person. Did you go to his house? Yeah, I happened to be about an
hour away. Alan lives in the same province as I do. So he's near Toronto. And I got to
I basically said, Hey, Alan, I'm I'm near you. Is there any way I can come crash your
place? And he said, Yeah, yeah, come by. It happened to work out perfectly. It was his
normal podcasting day, but they had recorded some in advance. So he had the whole day off.
So he and I just kind of hung out for a long time and had a great conversation. And I think
that just got released today. So it's a great chat. I listen back and it was a lot of fun
listening back. So I think everybody's gonna enjoy it. What I've just learned is be careful
letting Brent stay at your house. He will interview you as someone who has been interviewed.
You end up telling Brent things you didn't expect. That's right. There's a brunch with
Wes, a brunch with cheese. I believe you're on the docket sometime, huh? Perhaps I'm coming
for you. Yeah, I wanted our brunch to be in person, though. You know, you're just hungry.
I felt like first of all, I did want to eat. And second of all, I felt like if I'm going
to expose all, it needs to be in person. So extras dot shows where you catch that we also
just released a reverse proxy basics, and we have a container basics coming out. Alex
and I sit down with Wes on the reverse proxy basics, talk about nginx traffic, or traffic
as they like to call it. And then in the next one, we get down into the dirties of containers.
Oh, there's a lot of good detail there. And I talked a little bit more about my setup
and my kind of realization that it's more than just hype. There's a practical like even
if you're an old school sys admin, there's a real practical angle to using this technology.
Yeah, right. I mean, Alex is working with containers every day. So good advice. There's
other shows we haven't even talked about yet that are on extras dot show like office hours
with Chris operation safe escape with Wes L and a guest production meetings chats with
people from Linux Academy. And we're going to also do a summary of our visit to Texas
cyber summit extras dot show slash subscribe. Just grab that. Yeah, you know, it's a place
where can do a little experimentation. Yeah, if you like what we're doing, you want to
see things we're trying follow extras, a batch of brunches and more at extras dot show. Also
now up on the Linux Academy community section. That's a free section of the Linux Academy
platform where you can sign up without subscribing. We've released a new batch of courses L's
in charge of this and she has some great ones cloud formation, deep dive, database administration
and SQL language basics. And that's never getting old. I mean, you gotta you gotta learn
to Google Cloud functions, helm deep dive, and the one that I'm going to be taking the
ansible playbook deep dive. Finally. Wow. It's a little aggressive, Wes. I'm right here.
Check those out. We'll have a link in the show notes. You can sign up without having
to pay and get access to all that stuff. And L's always curating that releasing new stuff
over there. So check that out. And extras dot show. Wow. That's a lot of stuff. Are
we good? You good, Wes? You go with? Oh, yeah. Can I? Can I move up? Please do. Okay. All
right. Again, kind of aggressive. You know, I don't think we mentioned to the chat room
that they should be bang suggesting as we go along. Yeah, well, it sounds like J. Bob
might be having some issues. Oh, really? Well, that's what chat room. Thanks. Thanks. I don't
know. I haven't. I did some just suggesting earlier. We got to move that J. But so that
J. But is Yeah, no, it's down. Yeah. Well, yeah, we're getting a bad gateway. Oh, start
up the West bot. What do you think? memory? It does do that. Yeah. I mean, how much memories
on that box? Yeah, like eight gigs. So you know, it's on the RAM for that for that J.
But Dang it. It happens. I think what we're gonna do is we're gonna I mean, not to be
that guy, but I think we're gonna containerize it. And then we're just gonna put it on a
supported system. Because that's on an arch box from like 2013. So it's insane. We really
should probably move on. And it kind of works sometimes. Yeah, I mean, you just got to go
in there and then restart it and then get in the console and then get the TCP IP stack
back online and then get the thing all running again and then get its custom web server up
and go. And then once you've done all of that, and you've forwarded the DNS, you're good
to go. So I don't know, you know, we're probably gonna have to make some changes. That's I
mean, it's only perfect that we talk about this though, because 1910 is it's kind of
like one of those releases that you're not going to want to install on a system like
JBOD because you want that running for years. This is this is not the long term support
version of Ubuntu. Right? It's a it's a place to try out new things and maybe preview some
of the features you will enjoy in a long term support in the future. Right. So how do you
say the name the code name? Eon? I don't know. Eon? Yeah, let's go with that. How we doing
wimpy? Is it Eon? You pronounce it 1910. Yes, you do. Yes, you do. Actually, yes. Confirmed.
We did try to look it up. Right? I mean, you wouldn't try to define what it is. Did you
Yeah, I thought maybe we should have some definitions. I'd like to know. Yeah. Yeah,
I know. I've been really appreciating. It's just it's a silly thing. But Popeye's been
doing these live streams. Oh, they're great. And so I learned a little insights recently.
You see, the they canonical referred to it as the code name during the development cycle
West, but as it nears release, one of the final changes is switching over to 19.10.
That sounds small, but it's probably a big deal. And then once it's released, it's referred
to as 1910. So get it right. Well, it's not out yet. No. Although if you think by the
time people listen to this, it probably is so don't screw him up. Right. But we I mean,
this is kind of our first look, right? Because it hasn't been officially released. We've
been playing with it though. And really, the whole crew has I think our intention is to
continue to run it for the rest of this week, and then give you a report on some extended
experience with some specific things next week. But we did want to give it a first look
this week because we have been running it. Even on our trip to Texas Cyber Summit, West
got Ubuntu Monte installed on his ThinkPad T480. And I have been running the main line
Ubuntu with GNOME Shell on my system. Mr. Bacon, what have you been running?
I was running the beta for a couple of days and then switched over to the latest daily
of Monte.
Ah, okay. And then Mr. Drew, are you on GNOME Shell? Are you on what? What desktop?
I started on the official Ubuntu desktop, which is, you know, they're rebranded GNOME
Shell. But then I switched over to the more bland GNOME session, just because, you know,
more comfortable there.
You're a Fedora guy. I know. Okay. But all right. So mainline. All right, very good.
So these are a collection of experiences. I'm going to try to sneak in some other flavors
over the next week and give you a more comprehensive review in the following episode, as well as
some performance testing and other things with the whole ZFS stack. But as far as our
first looks go, I thought, let's talk about some of the headline features. So we'll get
to GNOME Shell here in a moment, because it's really, it really, really shines in this release.
But I think the one that's going to get a lot of news attention is the ZFS support.
In this version of Ubuntu 19.10, ZFS version 0.8.1 is shipping with features like native
encryption, trimming support, checkpoints, raw encrypted ZFS transmissions, project accounting
and quota, and some back ports from 8.2 that did rocks, and I assume others determined
were appropriate. So we have a pretty solid ZFS implementation. But on top of that, there's
a lot of work that went into making the rest of the stack ZFS ready. What I'm thinking
of Wes is things like grub.
Oh, yeah, right. So there's this project called ZSYS. And the goal really is to make a lot
of the ZFS advanced in basic concepts easily accessible and transparent to anyone because
maybe you're a sys admin, and you're familiar with ZFS, you're like, Oh, yeah, I mean, it
makes sense for my big, my big pool of information, but you have the time and need to go study
up, review, understand how the system works. ZFS still has a number of great features.
If the software between the user and the system can help the user take advantage of those
right stuff like automated snapshots, rollbacks, offline instant updates, easy backup support
with ZFS replication, right? I mean, come on, those are all amazing features. Unfortunately,
desktop Linux hasn't really integrated those. Yeah, I mean, because this is an awkward spot,
right? Unless you're running the latest Ubuntu, they're all there, but nothing's really fully
incorporating them. Yeah. So that's why Canonical has been developing a new user space demon
called ZSYS. And it's going to cooperate with things like grub and it's got some patches
and better support for grub. And it's also going to interact with the standard ZFS tooling
to sort of smooth all the little gaps and make sure all those advanced features can
actually be enabled. And it's not necessarily grub dependent. However, this does mean that
they're shipping now a patched version of grub that lets you boot right on ZFS on root,
as well as support other functions. Yeah, I mean, well, as long as the installer gets
the system ready, you've been playing with it, Chris. Yeah. So this obviously was the
thing we wanted to really try because this is a bigger commitment than just including
ZFS in the main installation. There is software that's being patched. There's this ZSYS layer
here. And there is a lot of thought being put into pre configured data sets, if you
understand what ZFS is a bit. So I thought, well, let's give it a go. Because you've got
two things here. You've got the core ZFS support of Ubuntu 1910. And then you've got the installer
support. These are two separate things. And what's really brand new in 1910 is the installer
support in Ubiquiti. And that's what I really wanted to give that a go. And there's a couple
of limitations you need to be aware about right here right now. Number one, it's automatic
mode only. Number two, it's going to take over the entire disk. So everything on that
disk is going to be rewritten. Yeah, you can't install with ZFS on an existing installer
next to existing installs. And if you need to make customizations, well, you're going
to have to do that after the install is finished. The custom partitioner does not support ZFS.
So that is an after install thing. So be aware of that. Number three, and it's not a big
deal. But the installer is going to make it look like it's doing extended for so you just
need to be aware of that too. And that's actually because under the hood, it is using extended
for for some stuff and then moving it over to ZFS later. And so it just requires a lot
of patchwork to Ubiquiti to display it. And it just didn't make it in time for 1910. So
these are the caveats you need to be aware about if you want to use it. I was comfortable
with all of these things. My workstation here at the studio, we talked about this recently,
it's a pretty old install. It started life as neon 1604 ran really great, which was then
upgraded to neon 1804, which is kind of around the point I decided to try out X F C E. And
then I converted it to as Ubuntu 1804 install that also had no show installed. So I could
check things out on Whalen a little bit here and there. And this is gross kind of kind
of began to fall apart. But it was a it was a solid install from like 2016. So I wrote
it as long as I could. I thought it's at a point now where I need to reinstall. I don't
have to, but I need to. And 1910 is here. Let's do this shit. So I wipe out the whole
system after backing everything up. ZFS on route using the big, bold, all caps, experimental
option in the Ubiquiti installer. Hit that next button, rock that install option. And
I get everything installed and my goodness, it is glorious. I mean, it's fast. It's beautiful.
It is the fastest my computer has ever felt. And the software centers packed full of snaps
and other apps ready to go. Slack, Telegram, Chrome, slam it on my system. And I've got
an AMD GPU. So not a single proprietary driver is loaded. I am rocking this thing. Three
screens, two of them vertical. It's good to go. I love this. Oh, what's this, Gary? Oh,
this has really gotten pretty great. Look at this. It picked up my GNOME online account
stuff automatically. Wow, this is such an amazing experience. Well, time to go home.
Shut the computer down, go home, spend the night with the wife and kids, come back to
work in the morning, hit the power button, system fails to boot. Dead. This is when I
realized I was in a bit of a situation. So if I go into grub and I reload the previous
kernel, the one that came on the daily ISO, I could boot pretty good. Couldn't get a home
directory, couldn't get a VAR, but I could get the system up. If I boot on the new kernel,
I could get to a busy box shell and that was it. And that's when I realized that I had
hit a bit of a situation. You really didn't take the experimental thing seriously, did
you? I mean, I was on fire, Wes. I was on fire. And this was a hard, hard right turn
and I was not expecting it. And I sat with it. I thought about, you know, troubleshooting
here and there. But what I realized is I'm going to take advantage of the super solid
ZFS support that is in 1910. And I'm going to go ahead and bypass the installer support.
Root on ZFS, for me, has a lot of potential in a little while, but not a lot of potential
today. Do you know what I mean? Like, you could kind of visualize how that would be
handy. Right. I mean, we've seen other systems, things like FreeBSD, other other systems with
with longer ZFS support, or maybe things like OpenSUSE, right? With with ButterFS, like
you can get a lot of benefits with ZFS on Root, with snapshots, rollback, integration,
perhaps with the package manager to make sure the system stays in a consistent state. Right.
Could you see like a grub entry, last snapshot. So when my system fails, I just load that
and boom, I'm right back to where I was right before I did that update. Right. But you don't
really get that right now. Yeah. And you're risking a little bit of complexity. Right.
So the ZFS support in Ubuntu 1910 is top notch. The Ubiquiti installer is limited today.
So what I did on my next reload after I gave it a thought is I went get ready for this
extended for for my root XFS for my home and ZFS from my data partitions, which I just
set up later after the install was done with G parted and you know, just put them just
toss them an SFS tab and a big deal. Right. So basically, you've decided that on 1910,
at least, maybe just skip that setup, unless you specifically want to play with it and
enjoy the, you know, the consistent ZFS support we've enjoyed for a while on Ubuntu. I'm going
to give it I'm going to give the ZFS on Root a go again. But I really do he did rocks warning,
you know, he says this is this is legitimately an experimental thing we're doing in so much
that the format of the way we lay out the disk may change and it it may not be compatible
with what we decide to go with in the end. This is what I loved back in the day about
these interim releases of Ubuntu. They were really the try something out, try something
new, deploy the new desktop environment, deploy the new compositing back end, deploy the new
frickin file system, right? I mean, that's the only way to get some of this stuff ironed
out, right? I mean, you can test all you want behind closed doors, you can play with a limited
number of systems you have available. But until the people who are actually going to
use it use it, you can't fix all those books, you've got to put it in production. And that's,
that's what these interim releases have been about in the past. But it really feels like
the good old days. If you love living on the edge a little 1910 really makes you feel right
at home in that regard. So that's, that's where I stand with the ZFS support for my
production systems. For systems that I'm going to depend on from a day to day basis. I will
not use the ZFS on route experimental installer feature, but I am going to use the hell out
of the ZFS support that is there. I'm just going to use it a more traditional manner.
Yeah, I mean, that's still fantastic. And I expect by 2020, it'll probably be a different
story.
Yeah. Wimpy sounds like you perhaps had some feedback here.
Yeah, the the way that the ZFS on route is implemented changed quite a bit literally
in the last few days. And it sounds like some of you early adopters there with the daily
images got bitten.
I suspected as much.
As of yesterday, it's all fine again. It's still carrying an experimental flag for the,
for the reasons that you highlight, Chris, which is the implementation may change slightly
between 1910 and 2004 based on, you know, feedback and such and how people get on with
things. But if you know, when the final release is out, if you want to test ZFS, you shouldn't
run into the issues that you've just described.
Yeah, I would expect so. I still think maybe for my day to day production systems, I would
avoid it on route. But unlike my, my computers that are not like the end of the world, if
I do an update, and there's an issue, I think I'm going to give it a go again. And I obviously
am using it on the data partitions.
It's just making me excited. I'm looking forward to when this improves.
Yeah, I mean, this is how you get there, right? So let's talk about desktop environments for
a moment. So you spent most of your time with Matei. I spent most of my time in GNOME Shell.
From the GNOME Shell side, I would say it feels like a supercar now. Man, I am so hooked
on the GNOME Shell setup. I mean, I've been riding pretty happily with Fedora recently.
But whoa, I mean, I got to see what Fedora's setup is. But I mean, everything is so smooth.
It's so fast. But more than that, and this is something that Ubuntu has always done really
well with, but good God, the fonts look great. I've been I've been working with XFCE for
quite a while. And to sit down on this computer, I get a sense of peace when I look at the
fonts on my screen. I know that sounds so stupid, but there's something about when they
nail it, and my mind isn't distracted by what's wrong with it. It's just perfect. That's how
looking at the screen feels with Ubuntu 19.10. I can't go back. And I don't know what I'm
going to do now about my laptop. I don't know what I'm going to do because I actually hate
being in this position because I don't want to base all my setup on a frickin 19.10 because
I got LTSs everywhere and I'm pretty happy with Fedora on the laptop. But I can't remember
the last time I've come on the air and been this enthusiastic about how something performs
and looks on my screen. The fonts are so perfect. The performance is so butter smooth. The Yaru
theme is perfect now. It just looks like a professional grade desktop theme. I like both
the light version and the dark version of it. I'm not going to change it. I'm not changing
the defaults. And that doesn't happen. I always mess with the defaults. So for me, this is
the release that brings me back to GNOME. After two years of jumping from Plasma and
then XFCE, I can't go back. I really like it. So for me, and maybe it's the time I've
spent in XFCE that makes it such a strong contrast for me, but the animations are no
longer a detraction. They are an improvement to the experience where as before I found
them distracting and aggravating. They now give the desktop a sense of direction. Things
are smooth. It's just, what about stability? Because that's been one of your problems in
the past. Yeah, I can't fully speak to that because I had to kind of nuke and pave halfway
through this for the ZFS stuff. So I will have to give you maybe more on that next week.
Initially pretty good. However, I do have this issue that plagues I think just DisplayPort
on Linux, because it's been an issue on Plasma. It's been an issue on XFCE. And now it's an
issue on GNOME Shell, where when my screens go to sleep, they just completely get crazy
because I've got two verticals and then one horizontal in the middle. Windows move around.
Sometimes one screen doesn't even turn on. Orientations just go crazy. And that's still
an issue.
See, the problem is you're getting up from your computer. And if you just didn't do that,
then you wouldn't hit this button.
Well, I do have a workaround. And I thought this was because I had this dirty Nvidia graphics
card. So then I switched over to an AMD graphics card. And I was hoping that because it was
a fresh install with no other previous drivers, just always the free AMD driver, maybe it
would... No, no, no. So my workaround is I have Caffeine installed as the extension.
So I use that during the day. So the screens just stay on during the day. And then when
the computer goes to sleep at night, I have a XRender script that I run because I'm back
on X with Ubuntu, which has been fine. So yeah, I'd love to hear your impressions of
Amate. And then we'll go around the horn. And I know Drew ran into a few issues, so
I definitely want to cover those. But I'd love to get your Amate experiences.
I feel like I've been on the opposite journey in some ways because I've been sticking with
KDE neon and plasma for the for the past year or so. And it's been great. It's making me
think about some of those animations because playing with Monte for the past week or so,
it's been nice. And I will say I frequently just feel like it's so snappy and quick. There's
a few areas where it's almost too quick. And, you know, it feels like there could be a little
animation there. So I'm not sure exactly what I want out of a desktop. It's making me question
a lot of things. I'm not sure I get the most benefits from all of the fixes in in Monte
because there's a ton of work going on for for better support of high DPI in particular,
and better support for Nvidia graphics and gamers. And of course, you're on Intel with
low DPI. Yeah, and I haven't tried gaming on it yet either. Right. So life pretty decent,
but battery life has been great. And even then, as someone who's deployed Monte mostly
for family members, you know, people with either like a need an appliance type application
or just are used to a more traditional desktop. It's the best Monte experience I've had in
a long time. And kind of the first time in a while I might consider using it every day.
When we recently talked a lot about the improvements in this 1910 release this paper cut release,
but kind of what kind of now getting to this point. When you look back at this 1910 release,
what's the feature for you that I think will stick with you the most? Well, there's not
one, but so I think the notification center is a big deal for me personally. And I actually
made use of it at UbuCon last week with great success. I was able to put it into do not
disturb mode. And I gave my presentation and nobody saw the telegram messages from my wife.
So that was a massive win. You know, it's that's a simple thing. And I've I've been
wanting that for ages. So Jason, who implemented all of that stuff, I can't thank you enough.
You know, I really like that notification center. I think the I've got a laptop that
does well two laptops that support high DPI. So the high DPI improvements are hugely obvious
to me. And anyone that's got a high DPI machine and has used Marte in the past, you will immediately
see the improvements. And we've not finished all of those yet. We're very, very close.
We've got some more visual quality improvements to come in the next release, which will land
in time for 2004. I particularly like the fact that now we've got invisible window corners.
So you don't have to have pixel perfect, you know, grabbing on the window corners to you
know, seems like a simple thing turns out to be actually incredibly difficult to implement
properly. Yeah. And then the Ubuntu Marte has adopted indicators, you know, app indicators
from Ubuntu for several releases now. And this release is the first time it's really
all nailed, you know, they don't scale weirdly, they all work, the date time indicator and,
you know, interacting with evolution and everything, you know, it's just it's just lots of those
improvements. And then there's a ton of fixes, you know, it's just it's just, it's not perfect,
but we're really getting close to where we want to be now. So I'm very, very happy with
this release. Looking over Wes's shoulder, it does seem like it's been it's been really
solid. And I noticed that when we install Chromium, if you do like a pseudo apt install
Chromium, what is it? What's the package Chromium desktop or I can't remember the exact
package name. It kicks off a script that then installs the snap version of the package.
And seamlessly, very seamlessly. And I'm, I'm pretty impressed because that makes Chrome
and Chromium probably make some of the most sense for an application. But I did a little
digging. And I, I think this now makes it possible to install Chromium on versions of
Ubuntu that basically would no longer be able to run Chromium. And that must be applicable
to other districts to like 1404, for example. Yeah, the tricky thing here is he's not so
much running Chromium on 1404. It's actually getting the tool chain required to build Chromium
for 1404. Yeah, there's a chicken in the egg. Yeah, yeah. So you know, when, you know, if
you if you say 1404 is now in its extended security maintenance, and we've got 1604 and
1804 and 2004 just around the corner. So let's take 1910. For each of those four versions.
That's a separate build of Chromium that we have to build one on 1404 one on 1604 one
on 1804 one on 1910. And of course, it's 1904 as well. So there's actually five different
builds. And because the tool chains have changed tool chain has changed significantly between
1404 and where we are today, there's several different build configurations that you have
to manage along the way there. So by just building the snap, which runs a single build,
runs on all five of those versions of Ubuntu, plus 50 other Linux distributions, we cut
our investment in time to maintain Chromium considerably, you know, four or five times.
So that's the motivation for doing this with Chromium, because there's a new release every
six weeks, it's fast moving. And now we have a mechanism to continue to deliver it across
the entire family of supported Ubuntu.
And the the shim had been done before, right? Like things like LexD already, if you installed
the package just gave you the snap? Yes. So LexD, I think was probably the first first
package where we did the same thing. And for similar reasons, you know, it means you can
maintain one version of the thing rather than, you know, half a dozen. You know, when you
do something like this, which to Wes and I makes a lot of sense, especially with something
like Chromium, you're going to get people that react in the extreme, they're going to
extrapolate this to mean everything's going to snaps. And the the really sinister thing
about it is when I pseudo apt install, it's still installing a goshdarn snap. I didn't
do a snap install. I didn't apt install. Why didn't I get a DEP? And they're going to construe
that to mean everything's going to snaps.
Yeah. You know, obviously, there are people who will react in that way. I pasted a link
in IRC you can include in the show notes, a blog post on the Ubuntu blog that Popey
wrote that details this in some detail to explain what I've said and a few other things
in much more detail. But the plan is not to replace everything in Ubuntu with snaps. We've
done this with Chromium because we have to choose wisely how we invest our time and for
the desktop team, which is relatively small, this represents a big labor saving. And it
means we can invest our time in other improvements in in the desktop, such as you know, improving
the fluidity and performance of you know, gnome shell and other things.
Sure. Well, we tried it out on the Ubuntu mate install here. And I was happy to report
that we had native open and save dialog boxes. We had access to the webcam, we had WebGL.
So I mean, it was a perfectly usable, perfectly functional show from it right now. Yeah, you
really wouldn't know. And I think that's the type of application where they have a custom
toolkit like that, that is also kind of funky that sometimes you can't guarantee will look
right. And whereas this snap actually gets the right GTK theme and everything. It was
a great experience. I'm impressed. So I think it's not bad. And I wanted to now move over
to cheese and drew because I know they both had very different experiences. So cheese,
why don't we start with yours? I know you spent some time with both of them. So start
wherever you think is probably best.
Well, let me start with saying the bare metal that I was testing it on is a potato. So it's
a Dell and spirit on 3147. Not much better than some of the older atom chips. So it's
not a very good machine. It's one of these two in ones. Initially, I tried pulling down
the GNOME version, the stock version. And for whatever reason, GNOME likes to default
with the hid gyro and hit accelerometer kernel modules and stuff like that. So again, I was
faced with a rotated 180 degrees and flipped 90 degrees login screen. So quickly ditch
that, jumped over to the mate beta, found a couple of little bugs in the installer,
which were just like VLC and Google+, which have since been fixed in the daily. They were
fixed, I think, well before I'd noticed them. Another little bug that I noticed when switching
to the Redmond theme in mate was that some of the mounted icons were pretty large. I
don't know why anyone would necessarily want to switch to the Redmond theme, but it's there
if you do. But that was really the only kind of graphical glitch that I saw. I did also
have, whenever I tried to use the experimental ZFS install from the installer, the installer
did crash on me, which I wasn't expecting much. And it's on this little laptop.
And it's also still in the development cycle. So when we do this phase of the first look,
like that kind of stuff is expected. We'll do our follow up thoughts next week.
We went through several days with the ZFS install not functioning on the dailies. So
we know that's fixed now.
Yeah. And when you do like a regular like extended four or whatever, it's totally fine.
But my overall experience was really great. And mate works great on that older hardware.
You know, I haven't had any real issues with it. I love that I'm given the choice now between
the full install and the minimal installs. So immediately, you know, I picked up on that.
I love how mate gives me a welcome screen. Just a nerd like that, because I think anyone
that's going to be new to a system coming from Windows or Mac or something like that,
that's going to give them kind of that little extra help.
Nothing beats the boutique.
Yeah, dude, it's great. So I've had overall a really good experience with it. You know,
I will likely keep running it. And then once the final version comes out, I'll switch to
the final, played some installed steam, played some steam games, ran great. I have also heard
issues with people that have had their audio inputs or output switch from HDMI to their
USB headset. And I'm guessing that's just something on enumerating. I loved watching
Popeys live stream the other day where he installed to live. I noticed what was really
cool about that. And thanks, Popey, because now I'm in the land of looking for ThinkPads.
Oh, my God, you got him going on ThinkPads for like a solid few minutes. It was I never
I mean, you see you want to see Popey light up asking about things.
I know I'm waiting on him to like one day just lay them all out around him and just
go through each one and talk about it. That'd be a great video.
I know. I know. I actually think it's a problem.
I think the Linux and ThinkPads, it's like hand in hand. I mean, it's not a problem.
Cheesha, not alone. The number of people that are in the Ubuntu podcast telegram channel
exchanging notes about ThinkPads, they're buying on eBay. You know, Popey needs to be
on commission. I think there's going to be no ThinkPads left on eBay as a result of these
live streams.
Absolutely. All the off lease ThinkPads have been bought up now in the last two weeks.
But I did notice I think he was on the 220, the X220 or the X240. I don't remember which
one he was using.
It was the 220.
Okay, the fingerprint scanner works out of the box now.
Oh, yeah. I've got news about fingerprint scanners. Yeah. Go on. Go on. Yes. Yeah. So
that was something that happened in the 1904 cycle and has been improved in the 1910 cycle.
And it's still the case that the more modern biometric chips used in fingerprint scanners
are not supported by fprintd because they have, you know, a proprietary driver effectively.
And fprintd will only talk to an open driver. So I don't know when we're going to conclude
this work. But I was talking to my colleague Marco about this over the weekend. And he
was saying that he's got the fingerprint reader working on I think it's the T480 or something
like that. And he's written a shim that wraps around the proprietary driver. So fprintd
can talk to it. And he was showing me this because I was saying, oh, yeah, problem isn't
none of the new ones work. And then he unlocked his laptop with his fingerprint reader. So
I'm not quite sure what the scheduling is around that. But I know it's something we're
working towards. Is there a you don't have to say who, but is there a is there an enterprise
client that's driving this need? Because this seems this seems like, ah, yes, it seems like
that's one of those things. Well, good. That's what I love about open source. One particular
really important enterprise client can drive something that the rest of us benefit from.
And my final note would be, you know, big congrats to the whole team over there, what
they've managed to do, especially with 15 year anniversary. You know, right, right here
on us last week, makes me feel super old. But I know I'm proud to be, you know, a user
of Ubuntu and have been for a long time. And I really appreciate all the hard work you
guys do. Yeah, I think you're you're really nailing it with the 15 years like this is
this is amazing. And here we are back on GNOME two. All right, so Drew had had a go. And
what I love about Drew's perspective on this is he had a chance to really kind of look
at it from a production grade workstation desktop. And some things were great, and some
things weren't so great. So what did you run into? And what was good? And what wasn't good,
right? So the standard desktop experience was phenomenal. As you saw, the speed improvements
and all of the animation improvements and everything that's gone into both the GNOME
version and the Ubuntu desktop, you know, skin of the GNOME version are great. They
are doing wonderful work there. Everything is smooth and just buttery and really, really
a joy to use. And as far as stability, you know, I've been using it a little longer than
you have. I've been running it for about a week on the beta. And I haven't had any crashes
or really any issues under normal workstation use cases. The only time that I've had issues
is when I start to go into pro audio land. And there I did have some problems on my laptop
specifically when I would load up Jack and start using my audio interface, which is connected
via USB. Every now and then, and I never figured out what triggered it, it would just drop
the USB connection and switch over to the internal sound card. So not great. And I did,
just because this is a production machine for me, go back to Fedora on this one, and
I haven't had it happen again. So I don't think it's a hardware issue. I don't think
it's an issue with the interface, but something either in Ubuntu studio controls or something
in the USB subsystem is causing some interrupt on that. Other than that, that's really, I
mean, that's the only issue that I've really had. I will say that I tried a bunch of snaps
as well, just to see how that's coming along. And I do think that snap support is getting
a lot better every time I look at it. They are still launching a little slower than I'd
like, but I know that's still being worked on. And realistically for application support,
I think snaps and Flatpak are both really great ways to deliver standard desktop applications.
I'm not sold on it for low-level stuff yet, but I'm getting there.
Yeah. I completely agree with your assessment. They're really solid now, including the open
and save dialog boxes, looking right, getting access to your individual devices without
making it a battle. But it's really down to the launch time. It's still not quite where
I'd like it to be. Now, the nice thing with something like Chromium is I launch it pretty
much once a day, and then it's open all day long. But I can kind of see the groundwork
for 2004, you know what I mean?
Yeah, absolutely. And this looks so much like an interim release between 1904 and 2004.
It's just crazy. You see all of the work that went into 1904, polished up, made better,
and some other iterative improvements on top of that. Going into the 2004 stretch, it really
looks like it's shaping up to make just a real killer LTS when that comes around. I'm
really excited about that.
Yeah, that's my take too. And I look at it, I mean, this is a stupid, bad, horrible analogy
that I shouldn't make, but I kind of look at 1910 as a bit of, you know, it's a fun
mod car. It's a race car, it's super fast, but sometimes the turbo's a little too powerful
and you blow a bolt. And the LTS is like, it's your commuter car. It's your safe, predictable,
it's going to turn every time you...
It's your Volvo.
Yeah, it really is just like a really predictable, reliable car. And that's where the LTS is.
And it depends on which type of driver you are. Do you like to have a little fun? And
maybe sometimes drive a little too fast? Then maybe 1910s for you. Do you want to know that
every single day you're going to get to your destination? Then the LTS is for you. That's
kind of standard advice, but it is more applicable with the 1910 release than I think it's been
for a few years. And it's really something to see where we're at now with Gnome Shell
and where we're at now with Snaps. These have all been these concepts that we've been building
to and we've been seeing get implemented over time. And 1910 is a representation of what
I think Canonical had as a long-term vision. It's really close in 1910. We're not a hundred
percent yet, but we're really close. And so if you're interested in that at all, it's
worth checking out. Now, which flavors for you? Is ZFS slower? Is there other kind of
overhead costs with ZFS like memory usage compared to XFS and extended for? That I can't
tell you fully yet. That's something we're going to spend the next week investigating,
benchmarking, and we'll follow up. Now that 1910 is going to be officially released, we'll
follow up with some of that stuff. Give some of those things a try.
I'm thinking I might give Kubuntu a try.
Yeah. Kubuntu 1910 looks particularly good as well. I think I'm tempted to also try that.
And then before you know it, the new Fedora is going to be out. It's too much, Wes.
And then you're looking at like when 2024 makes it, it's going to be a nice supported
release too. So it's just a great time to be a desktop Linux user.
It's true. Oh, hold on. A production note here from the back office. They're telling
us to move on. It's time to mention the picks. Should we do that?
Let's do it. We got some great picks today.
Well, I moved over to a Gnome shell and I realized there wasn't a great menu editor
built in. Like basically all of the other desktops, you just right click on the menu
and you can edit it. Gnome's like, no, no, we don't got that for you. So I have two different
picks for you. I have this problem with my monitors that I gripe about on occasion. And
you can install an application called, what is it, A-Rander, which just gives you like
these really...
X-Rander.
Well, A-Rander uses X-Rander to create scripts for X-Rander.
Just like a nice little desktop. You lay out the screens how you want. It gives you the
script.
But then you have this problem where like you want to be able to launch super easy because
your screens are all screwed up and you'd like a single click or a command you can execute.
Well, that's where making a desktop file comes in and adding it to your menu. And my friends,
if you have ever wanted to add something to your menu, to your launcher, this is where
menu Libre comes in from Sean M. Davis. It's a menu editor, straightforward basic menu
editor that works on anything that follows the standard. Also a shout out to app editor.
If you are on elementary OS, this is a nice looking menu editor that I'd love to have
on every other desktop, but that's in the App Center. And either one of these two applications
depending on what fits your needs, allow you to add things that you can then search by
hitting the super key either on Plasma or Mate or Gnome Shell or Xfce, anything that
follows this free desktop standard for the.desktop file.
That's great because otherwise it's kind of like black magic to me and I don't want to
go messing with those files.
Yeah.
I can just...
How do you get stuff in that launcher? How do you make it searchable? How does this work?
I got a shell script, I want to be able to search for it and execute it. This pick will
help you do that. So check the show notes for that, linuxunplug.com slash 323. But then
Mr. Bacon coming in with the last minute sneaky pick.
He did sneak in there.
He's got a sneaky pick. So tell us about Wavemon.
So Wavemon is one of those curses apps that I previously used to use all the time. I found
myself using it at Texas Linux Fest just to kind of check it out. But basically it'll
allow you to monitor your wireless networking via Inker. This gives you a nice little output,
letting you know what your signal is, letting you know your throughput, what your rate is,
what your drop rate is, letting you know what channels you're on, all those sorts of things,
all those little details that you might need to know, especially if you're doing any other
sort of wireless work. So I would highly recommend checking out Wavemon. Beemon is also another,
which is a bandwidth monitor, another tool that I quite frequently used to use all the
time. But Wavemon's a great one.
Are we throwing in Kismet too? Who just literally threw in Kismet here in the last second?
Did somebody throw in Kismet?
Drew, did you do that?
Yes.
Nice.
All right, let's do Kismet.
I just wanted to point out that there's Kismet as well. Kismet is also for monitoring wireless
interfaces, but it's more along the lines of long-term monitoring. So you can set up
like little nodes in various spots. I used to use them for businesses where we'd have
to make sure that Wi-Fi was solid every single square inch of the place. So throw little
sensors around and then monitor them with Kismet and make sure that everything was up
and running properly. So if you need something with a little more power and a little more
long-term monitoring in mind, Kismet's a good choice too.
Sounds like my house could use that.
Yeah. Four picks, the quad picks. How about that? Also, I got to take a moment. I got
to take a minute. Well, not really, but I got to take a moment and I got to say...
Maybe like 40 seconds? I don't know.
How great has Drew done on Choose Linux? We hired Drew as an editor and then when the
situation arrived, he stepped up to Choose Linux and between him, Elle, and Joe, it has
turned out so great. Drew, you have done so well.
I love it.
I just want to take a moment here because I don't know how many people listen to this
show have checked you out on Choose Linux, but if you enjoy Drew on this show, he's really
at home on the Choose Linux show now. So go check out Choose Linux as well.
It often brings the much-needed voice of reason, I would say. I mean, Joe's sat in his ways
sometimes and Elle's a very passionate person. Drew, you just get it right. That's my personal
take.
I'll take it and I appreciate it. Yeah. Anybody who has any interest in Linux, I highly encourage
you to take a listen. We've got a new episode coming out soon.
I always do. Also, go check out Wimpy over at the Ubuntu podcast, the ubuntupodcast.org.
That is a staple of my week. I love every single episode. It's like hanging out with
friends, Wimpy.
Aw, thank you very much.
Thank you. Thank you for doing it. It's really nice to have you all back together now for
a few episodes. It feels like we're back at home now. Everything's good.
Yeah, it does, doesn't it?
It's nice and solid. Yeah. Something's going to change now, I know it. I just know it.
It is.
Dang it. I totally call it. All right. Well, I think that wraps us up, though. We'll move
on to getting to testing, benchmarking, and just living with Ubuntu 19.10 on a day-to-day
basis. We'd love to hear your experiences as we conclude our review next week. So tweet
me. I'm at chrisles. The show is at Linux Unplugged?
I don't know. The network is at Jupyter Signal.
You can also tweet Wes. He's at Wes Payne. And Cheese, what are you at? Cheese Bacon,
for God's sake?
At Cheese Bacon.
That's like a contact page, right? LinuxUnplugged.com slash contact.
You're kidding me.
Yeah, for real.
No. No. And then that would be a way to have a long-form response?
Oh, yeah. If you want to ramble in an email, don't go on too long, just for our sake, because
Chris isn't going to read it.
Wow. You hostile Wes. Are you noticing this? All right. Well, that's true. You're right
about that.
All right. One more thing before we get out of here. A little news flash.
Oh, wait, wait. Do you want? Hold on.
Do you have a news flash soundboard clip?
Of course you do.
Yeah. I mean, if you're coming at me with that, we're going to do it properly. Are you
ready?
I'm ready.
This is CNN breaking news.
It's cheese breaking news.
So, at the beginning of the show, we were talking about Core Boot, and I reached out
to Emma and I asked her about the plans for Core Boot on future machines. And she has
sent back to me that there are no plans to go backwards on their open hardware software
mission. So, it's safe to assume that they will be building 100% Core Boot, Daughters,
and Galagos in the foreseeable future.
That is great news.
Wow.
That is great news. Thank you for the real time follow up right there. I appreciate that.
That is so, so cool to hear. Let's end it right there on that good news. We can't top
it. Join us live, won't you? We'd love to hear your thoughts. You can always get right
in our ear holes by getting in the mumble room. All the details are in our IRC room
at IRC.geekshed.net pound hashtag Jupiter broadcasting. And then once you're in there,
you can just do bang, that's exclamation mark, mumble and it will give you all of the
info you need to jump in our mumble room and share your thoughts or you can share them
in the IRC room. Don't worry.
Every Tuesday. So, just set that aside.
If you can't make it next Tuesday, don't worry. We'll be back every single Tuesday
over at jblive.tv and then your RSS feed at linuxunplug.com slash subscribe. We'll see
you back here next Tuesday.
Well, there you have it. JBtitles.com. Let's go title. You guys remember that archive.org
has them emulators? They added a whole bunch of more games, eh Cheesy?
Yeah, so they added 2500 more games.
What?
That's too many.
That's too many games in your browser. So super cool. I thought, you know, poppy and
wimpy also might appreciate that since they're retro gamers. And then doing a little more
digging.
Wait, did you just call them old?
Old school gamers. Old school gamers.
It doesn't matter which way you dice it, it's kind of accurate, right?
It is. Well, and this is coming from a dude who's old too, so. But I also ran across Exodos,
which you can pull down their torrent and they're 7000 DOS games. I'm assuming a lot
of these 2500 that were pushed up to archive.org are there if you wanted to play them in your
own DOS box. But they've already been configured to work under DOS box. So they're freeware
shareware games that I've guessed just have eventually gone free. So take a look at those
if you want to get your old school gaming on for sure.
You guys are good for the rest of the show, right? Because I know what I'm doing with
the rest of my day.
Can I admit something? I have gotten into something that is shameful. And it's I blame
the algorithm. I blame YouTube. So back in the day, I back in the early I don't know
whatever it was 90s or whatever I played this game. It was my it was the it was the game
that really drew me in. And it was called Star Trek the 25th anniversary. It's one of
those games I started playing at 8pm. And then I looked up at the clock the next time
and it was 3am. And I'd been playing all night. And I found this dude who has been playing
them online in 35 minute increments. And I'm like on part 12 of his journey of playing
this game at 35 minutes at a time.
Do the multiplication there.
It's so bad was so I maybe I'll take a break and I'll go check out archive.org. Cuz I think
I think I don't know it feels like after a while it's like what am I doing with myself?
But what I do is I put it up while I'm working. You know, so I'm working away. Got myself
a little extension for Firefox so I can do video picture and picture for YouTube and
I just go to work.
I will admit I'm browsing the list right now.
What I like to that they all fire up within the browser. So it's all emulated within the
browser. I'm not sure what they're doing there to do that. But this might also be the moment
you want to set up an emergency hotkey. So when your boss walks in, my boss, my boss
Yeah, I think you gotta worry about your boss.