Winter may be coming to an end for us, but it's just beginning for the Mars Linux copter
You know that things made 27 flights
Unbelievable, but recently the little Linux copter on Mars has been struggling dust has settled on its solar panels
And it's having a hard time recharging its six lithium-ion batteries. You know I just had this problem Brent
I had to get up on the roof and clean off my solar panels
Are they gonna hire you to clean off the the wings of this little copter too?
Yeah, I don't know what the big deal is just get out there and dust it off. Yeah, just blow it off
Hello friends and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show my name is Chris and my name is Brent
Hello Brent Wes is out on assignment this week
I think he's actually at the airport as we record right now well coming up
We still have a heck of a show Nvidia has done it
They have kicked off the process of open sourcing their compute and GPU driver, so let's chat about that
Let's chat about what you can expect
Let's chat about what's happening first and break it down for you
And then later on in the show one of the co-founders of tail scale is going to join us
Let's see if we can get a sense of maybe what makes tail scale so different by chatting with him
And then we'll round out the show with some boosts some pics and a lot more so before we go any further
Let's say time appropriate greetings to our virtual lug hello. Mumble room
Hello guys, thank you for joining us today. I
Might sound a little different. I am remote on location
I am down in Southern Oregon getting the very last bits of damage from the Denver Road trip fixed on lady tube
She her suspension took a beating on the way into Denver, and there's just one bit of repair needed still before
We're ready for our summer road trip because we are working on another JB road trip
And we'll have details on that soon, so I'm down here
And of course it's right after my star link died on me if you heard last week's episode my star link is out
So I'm doing this an older school way low bandwidth, so if I sound weird that might be why?
But and Brent you're back at home now all done traveling
I am it feels funny that we kind of switch spots you're traveling now, and I'm home so
It feels good for my end. This is funny for me though because I traveled over 400 miles
it was like nearly nine hours of driving yesterday, and I get down to Southern, Oregon and
I park and
Everything's where I've left it. It's the weirdest thing. It's like I'm in a different climate because it's much nicer down here
But all my stuff is in the same drawers
It's almost like when you when you close all the windows blinds and stuff. It's like I'm I really never left
I feel like I'm still in Washington, but then I step outside of course. I'm in a totally different different spot
But I love it jubes did great on the drive down
We hit some traffic, but other than other than that she did so good, and you know the cellular system
I have now just so seamlessly switches between different networks that we remain connected the entire drive these days
Which is so awesome, so we're you know streaming podcasts and stuff and listening to him on the way down
We towed the car
And so it's just the wife and I the kids are at home because just a quick trip and I'll be down here for a couple
Of episodes that I'm recording one linux unplugged and one coda radio, and then we'll be heading home
But it's nice. It's nice to be on the road again
It's nice to be getting ready for the road trip that we're gonna do later this summer
So we'll be sharing details on that road trip and office hours if you're curious, but let's let's talk about the big news
Let's just get right into this
because I
Don't know if I ever thought this would happen every now
And then there have been these just ginormous Everest sized mountains
for the linux desktop that we had to climb and
Once we're on the other side looks like life has changed for linux users forever
This was definitely the case with Wi-Fi a long time ago
Automatic X configuration, I think maybe could even get this treatment. There's been certain milestones
milestones that we have hit that have just changed life for all future linux users where us old-timers look back and go
If you only knew what we had to do back in my day
This is one of those weeks
Nvidia has announced that they are releasing the GPU kernel modules as open source
It's starting with compute with so a focus on CUDA and that kind of stuff with an eventual
Solution for desktop graphics as well, and I think there's already some example code on their github
this is going to change the game for distributing the Nvidia driver on
Linux and
We have a couple of really great links in the show notes for you to read up if you're curious about the details and then
also, I want to mention that Christian Schaller joined us for Linux action news 240 and we dedicated the entire episode to our
conversation with him to get some of the details and
Christian is here now as well live in our mumble room Christian. Welcome back to the show. Thank you
Thanks a lot for having me
this
Must have been the hardest secret to keep there must have been a point where you realized this was really going to happen and that
Must have been thrilling
Yeah, no for sure. It's it's one of those things where I you know, even it was even top secret inside Red Hat
So I mean I had even conversations with all the Red Hatters. They're like you're saying oh we realize you can do something
Yeah, that would be nice
Because I couldn't confirm or this what you call it not affirm it until it was public
So yeah, definitely a hard secret to keep for a long time
I bet I I mean it wasn't too long ago that Matthew Miller was on Twitter saying, you know
This is something we've really got to address as a community getting the sense
Yeah, a lot of people didn't know it was coming in in part
I have to imagine this is something that they have to manage carefully because it is as a company
It's kind of an indefinite commitment to now supporting something on an engineering level, isn't it? Yeah. No, I mentioned Matthews
Twitter thing. Yeah, we ended up reading me into the news after that think like yeah, maybe you need to let Matthew know
So he knows that maybe this isn't exactly the best time to stir the boat
That's fair enough probably a good idea I suppose so I'm curious I know I got I got a couple of questions for you
Since we chatted I suppose as you'd expect there has been some skepticism around the announcement
But I think probably the most prominent
Skepticism has been around this sort of line of thinking. Well sure they released the stuff
That's gonna touch the kernel is open source
But they just moved all this stuff to the firmware and now there's a 34 megabyte firmware blob required
And I've heard this from a couple of different people
I'm curious to know what your take is on that not like, you know
What the official position is but just your opinion on on this method of driver development
Okay, so from a purely sort of ideal stand, but I would love for everything to be open including firmware that that said
I mean
I I guess the one reason felt it was little unfair when people started going off that was that
Everyone is doing this model of having a binary firmware and then you know the driver being
Mostly sort of connecting that up. So I mean it's it's yes, it's a little unfortunate, but it's it's what everyone does
So this is not I don't feel it's right to single out in media
Then you have to basically go after more or less every vendor out there
I mean the Linux firmware file is you know growing for every release due to more and more people putting more more functionality into the firmware
So that's that's just the way it is. And it's sort of something we as a community has accepted it gets for a long time
No, yeah, a lot of vendors are doing it this way
and I think the only thing that's a little unfair about the criticism is
The file size is being used as like like a negative, you know, 34 megabytes of firmware
But if you actually look at the firmware
There are just a ton of architectures that that 34 megabytes supports
In fact Longhorn on Twitter did just that he says the 30 megabytes supports multiple GPU
generations as well as a bunch of other ELF sections and
things specifically for ampere and Turing and all kinds of little bits in there that aren't necessarily like
Control mechanisms and stuff like that. So you can't really derive
Anything from that 34 megabyte file size. That's that's a bit of a red herring
additionally
It seems to me that that means the problem solved on the Linux side
So now as a consumer, this is just a different set of pros and cons that you have to weigh
But it's clearly a benefit because it's gonna make it easier for manufacturers like system 76. They're shipping Nvidia hardware
It's gonna make it easier for folks that have existing Nvidia hardware
But it's also going to be a benefit for the Nuvoo driver too, which I think is sort of been missed in all of this
And I don't can you share any details there Christian about what what's kind of maybe the next steps for the Nuvoo driver?
Yeah, I mean it opens up
opportunities for us right to so as I mentioned in my blog and this is that so historically what happened was that
When then we just switched to sign firmware. It basically meant that the wall couldn't use that firmware
So so we had we reached out and you know Nvidia was kind enough to work with us to say, okay
Let's let's make a firmware that make let's know what keep working that of course end up being a big effort for it for Nvidia
Because they had maintained an extra firmware and it took time to get features in
I mean one big feature people kept of course missing was the ability to reclock the GPU
Because Nvidia GPUs and I assume others by default the fault is sort of like almost like a power saving level of GPU
So so if you are less stuck in that, you know, don't get a lot of performance out of your GPU. So
So they were in talks with them what like how do we fix this and then you know when this thing became a thing
We said like, okay, maybe the solution is that we can then you know
Tie things together with your new release and then we have a shared firmware between you know
Then we just back in MSS stack, right? That is exciting. That seems like massively
Simplification of engineering efforts and just way easier to maintain long-term. Yeah, exactly
Exactly Casey points out in in the IRC to that, you know for 30 for a 34 megabyte firmware
You get a massively parallel computer with 12 gigs of RAM
Anyways continue Christian. I know you had another point there. Yeah, I was just gonna save it firmer
I think also I sort of
Came to terms it firmer in general when we launched LVFS
I felt that after that I couldn't really go out there and you know scream murder every time I saw
Former firmware out there being available close source. I bet being involved with LVFS does give you a pretty good perspective on that
I feel like this is one of those stories that after we were done recording LAN
I just wanted to take the rest of the week off like I was so excited
It's like what else could happen in Linux that would even matter this week. It's such a big deal
But now really in a in a weird way
Now a lot of the hard work starts, right?
Like I look at the github and I see all these issues that are being opened up by the community and people that are jumping
In and right now we're really just looking at a solution for compute as well
And so we should probably set our expectations. I mean, maybe it's not even unreasonable to
Expect maybe summer of next year before there's something people are gonna want to install on their machine
What do you think you think that's reasonable?
Well, I mean I think if you really want something to just run compute like, you know
We need the I want the driver and you want to sign it
Yourself for the time being to run on let's say your blade machines to use you for compute and you're definitely ready to use it
But you you need to wait until the graphics comes in for one before able to run to the desktop
and of course at the same time we in the distro world are of course making figuring out how we got to deal with signing and
Packaging this thing and you know, it's not an upstream drive yet. That's another thing people need to remember
I did still an auto tree driver. So that has you know
Like any other tree driver
It's only set of challenges for us in the distro world to deal with but you know
I think the pieces will fall in place and and it will make make things easier as we had
Going forward. Well, this was you know
Really the result of years of investment in a relationship and those details and more are in Linux action news 240
Where Christian covers all of that, but I think this is a obvious win. I know some people are very skeptical but to me
This means that people can now buy laptops or desktops within video hardware and you know within a year's time
It's gonna work out of a out of the box like your AMD or Intel graphics does
That's just indisputably a win if that means some some of the functions are in a blob. Yeah, it's maybe it's not ideal
But it seems to be the compromise
We have decided to live with and it does mean we deliver on the best end-user experience that we can right now
and it is such a
Tectonic shift from where we were a week ago
That I think people just haven't really even processed what this means so extremely excited and Christian
Thank you for giving us the scoop on all of that and so we can help people understand what's going on and set their
Expectations accordingly and again, I will link to your blog post in the show notes
Which I think everyone should give a read over as well because you put a lot of great info in there
Thanks for joining us again. Yeah, my pleasure and just maybe one last item
I mean I would ask everyone to try to be patient with Nvidia here too because you mean this is a big change for them
Too right and they have to come up with how they deal with the community around the driver
And I mean and we'd have done open source before and various things. It's not like they're completely new to it
But this is like, you know the heart of the hardware, which is not the heart of their business
So, you know if things doesn't all go super smooth from day one
You know give them have some patience and I'm trying to work with them
I say, you know iron out their own interaction with the community that will spring out and spring up around the driver
Linode.com slash unplug go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account, and it's a great way to support the show
Linode's been doing this for nearly 19 years and their mission has remained unchanged since that begun make cloud computing simple
Affordable and accessible to everyone. It's led to the best-in-class experience, and it's why we host everything on Linode
We look at the options. I hear from some of you sometimes tell me about some great bargain-based
deal you got and then usually about six months to a year later. I hear about why you switched to Linode
So take advantage of the hundred dollars
It's just a great way to go try something and Linode has a lot of one-click deployment applications as well
Some of the apps that we've talked about here on the show one-click to get going zoom replacements. Yeah, they got Jitsi up there
You want to try GitLab? Yeah, they got that fact some of the services. I'm gonna deploy soon for
Some back-end stuff that I'll probably talk about in the future. I'm just gonna use one of their one-click deployments
They've also got a great one for WordPress and they're always adding new ones like just constantly
So I check in there from time to time and I'll just deploy a project and try it out
And it's a great way to try out that hundred dollars, too
So from development tools to game servers to the back-end infrastructure for your business
So I'm talking like scaling from a personal project to something for millions of users
Linode is a great way to go try something and Linode is a great way to go try something
Linode has you covered and then they back it by the best support in the business and they've got a bunch of nice features like
s3 compatible object storage cloud firewalls DDoS protection a
Powerful DNS manager and of course your info management to kubernetes terraform ansible
They've got support for all of that with pricing 30 to 50% cheaper than those duopoly
Hyperscalers that want to lock into their crazy esoteric platform
Go use the real internet and go build a system either from the ground up or with one-click deployment
Linode makes it easy and their community support runs deep go get $100 support the show and try something out Linode calm
unplugged
Tail scale is a mesh VPN powered by wire guard
We've talked about it on the show before and I should disclose they are a sponsor on coda radio and self-hosted
They don't sponsor this show but you can go to tail scale comm slash coder or tail scale comm slash self-hosted if you want to
Sign up and it's a tool that we all use as a team and there's a lot of great tools out there
We've mentioned nebula in the past. We've also talked about s shuttle or shuttle in the past
We've covered all kinds of mesh VPN solutions like tink and others. It's always a problem
We've been trying to solve but tail scale really has seemed to solve it the best for us
And I have an opportunity to sit down with Avery pen around who is one of the co-founders of tail scale
He spent the previous eight years at Google where he launched some of their first p2p payment systems for Google wallet
He was involved with Google fiber and working out the Google fiber mesh Wi-Fi strategy
He's been involved in other high-profile alphabet projects
so it was just a great chance doing these podcasts sometimes just gives me a chance to talk to people I normally would not get to
Talk to and I wanted to get kind of an insight into tail scale because it just almost seemed too good to be true
And I was hoping maybe to get some insights and I walked away from this conversation
With some of those I think so I wanted to share it with you
Avery sat down with me just recently and we were chatting just before we got started about some of his previous projects that I was
familiar with I
have been looking to solve my
Desperate network problems for years and I've been rolling my own crazy solutions
I had tried a few different things with wire guard
but I actually started with shuttle and
We talked about it a long time ago on the show and I believe you were the original creator of shuttle VPN, correct that I was
2009 I think so you've been thinking about VPN stuff for a while
I take it was wire guard like the missing piece for you wire guard was definitely a missing piece
I've actually been thinking about VPNs all the way back to 1997 when I wrote my first one
for my the first startup that me and my roommate started in our dorm room in university and
That particular one made some you know major structural mistakes that you should not make when designing a VPN
We we we didn't exactly roll our own crypto
But we took the crypto primitives and we put them together in ways you probably shouldn't do
I learned a few lessons from that we did TCP over TCP which you should not do in a VPN
But it was it was educational and in fact this this carried our product forward
We had a company we it was the thing that actually launched us this VPN because it was on a network appliance server
You could install in small businesses. It was quite easy to configure compared to other VPNs at the time
But it had these other flaws, you know fast forward to the shuttle days. I'm like, okay
I learned a lot of lessons
I know what a few things not to do and I'm a little frustrated that you know
Our product got acquired by IBM IBM sort of dismantled it and killed it
No more VPN that I liked alternatives are like PBDP and IPSec which are pretty terrible or open VPN
So shuttle the motivation was like I don't want to do the encryption myself and I don't want to do TCP over TCP
So SSH has good encryption. Let me just like piggyback on top of SSH
You know rather than sending the packets over SSH
I'm going to disassemble the TCP sessions and then reassemble them on the other side which bypasses this TCP over TCP problem
That actually worked quite well. It was an open source project
I didn't try to commercialize it, but I used it for all kinds of things
It helped you know any any server that supports SSH can be your VPN server, which is quite handy
The performance wasn't the greatest but it was perfectly good for like transferring some files around and doing some remote terminals
With tail scale when when WireGuard showed up
I was really excited because it is like look I don't have to do my own encryption
But I can understand the encryption that these people are doing which means I can take this like a simple
Primitive for encryption and plug it into a bigger picture of the way I want the world to work
Right a really simple VPN that I control everything about the way the experience happens
But I'm not sacrificing security. It is deceptively simple on the front end as a customer experience
It's a very simple application to install. It's very simple to authenticate. It uses my existing single sign-on provider
It really couldn't be smoother
And so I'm not surprised to hear that you've been thinking about this since 97 because when I first tried tail scale
I thought they must be pulling some real magic off on the back end to make this feel so simple
So what are some of the more complicated things that are being solved on the back end to make it?
Just such a seamless thing for me to have a flat network of all my devices
There's quite a bit of magic in there. The first step is just this key management
So in shuttle we got out of key management by just saying like look it's your job to do SSH key management
You already know how to do that
We'll just piggyback on top of that which is great except that in fact
Many people do not know how to do SSH key management. And so there's a bit of a limited market
It's only people who can figure out how to manage their SSH keys effectively
Which at least is most developers if you wanted to deploy that company-wide for example
most of the people in your company are not developers and so they don't know how to set up SSH keys and so shuttle was
Never a you know a useful product for the general community even if even if pushed by an IT team
So tail skills key management instead of using SSH keys, we used what is now, you know, 12 years later
13 years later
Keep losing count 13 years later really common which is the single sign-on system that people are using on web apps, right?
The click click here to logging with Google click here to signing with github
This stuff in the intervening years has become like the standard thing to do. Everything is turned into a web app
All the web apps have a button for like login with Google
So we make tail scale look like a web app for the purposes of authentication, right?
You load up the tail scale app
Which is a native app on your phone or your PC or your Linux machine and it gives you a URL which sends you
To a web browser which then acts like a SAS app which can use your single sign-on
So that's that's the first trick we piggyback again on somebody else's authentication just like shuttle did but this time we're piggyback on
authentication that everybody knows how to use
The second thing we did is what we call NAT traversal
So this is especially magical other VPNs I've built myself and have used
Require one end of the VPN connection to be on a public facing open firewall port
Which is not that shocking the whole internet kind of runs on this principle
The client can be behind a NAT or a firewall, but the server has to be outside waiting for your connection
Otherwise, how is it going to work? The problem is
People setting up a VPN or trying to make a connection between two devices
This is really limiting to what kind of connections you can make it essentially turns the whole internet into the centralized system
Where nowadays the only people that get a public IP address
Are cloud providers and then you have to rent one from a cloud provider and now everything is like
The hub is the cloud provider and the spokes are everybody else, right?
You're paying rent to these cloud providers to do anything you want to do on the internet
So tail scale the magic involves like you could literally have you in a cafe
With your laptop and your co-worker in a cafe with their laptop
They log into tail scale on the same domain. Those two devices will find each other
They will not go through an intermediate server. They'll actually make a direct peer-to-peer connection
Between those two devices and now they're connected you can go to a service that your co-worker is running on their laptop and try
Out that web service or you can ssh into their device or do file sharing or whatever
Well, this is sort of what i've discovered using tail scale is that
It is essentially allowing me to create my own decentralized internet and it's kind of a sneaky way to do it
It's not really like tail scale selling itself as build your own decentralized internet, but that's kind of the end result, isn't it?
Well, I mean the word the word decentralized has become a bit dirty now because every time someone says decentralized they assume
We're talking about blockchains and bitcoins and stuff. Sure. Yeah. Yeah or any kind of weird crypto
Yeah, and that's that's not what tail scale does
The way I like to think of it is like look we actually did decentralization in a way that's actually decentralized
Therefore like achieves engineering goals, right? We're not we're not doing decentralizations for like religious reasons
We're doing decentralization because it's the most efficient way to solve your problem
Well, and it really is about connecting my devices, isn't it?
That's the issue is I don't have a great way to connect all of these disparate devices double nat different cloud providers vps
Some of them are locked behind vms or containers it flattens all of that
So the neat thing about tail scale is that it's sort of what I call a hybrid centralized decentralized system
The control plane the part that decides which devices can talk to which other devices the part that sends your public keys around
In the same way that you would send a public key to an ssh server and put it in your authorized keys file
That part is centralized you go to the tail scale sass product
We run a little tiny thing that we call the control server that is basically just a collector for public keys
But also connects to your identity system, right? That is where everybody else goes to rendezvous
So me with my laptop in this cafe you with your laptop in the other cafe both of our laptops
Contact the control server and say like hey
Where are my friends? Right and you find out the ip address in the public key
Go back to that and then those two laptops do the data plane
Actually sending packets back and forth initiating connections with each other in a purely decentralized way
This ends up being a really elegant algorithm because it's extremely inexpensive to run a centralized control plane where they only use it occasionally
And there's no latency sensitivity
But it's extremely inexpensive to run a data plane where we don't have to transfer any of the bytes for you
Right keeps the infrastructure cost down. In fact, you have to pay a lot of money to run a centralized control plane
You had a blog post that I really liked. It's titled how our free plans stay free and you write in there
All this is to say our costs are carefully managed like other sas companies. We don't build physical infrastructure
We avoid touching your packets for privacy, but also to reduce our costs
We fix bugs and docs instead of answering the same questions over and over again
Our control plane is lightweight and our dep network is cost controlled
This allows us to maintain a healthy operating margin so that a free tier isn't competing for resources with our paying customers
And I think there's a lot of insights just in that paragraph right there that I felt like I got about the company
And about you, I mean first of all
It's very clearly plainly written. It's very easy to understand
You don't really mince any words there and it makes a lot of sense as a customer
My first concern was well, is this thing going to stick around and is that a problem that you have discovered?
Are customers worried that this thing is too good to actually stick around that happens pretty often
One of the most common bits of feedback we get is like, please please don't cancel the free plan
Please please don't get acquired by you know list of competitors
Please don't add any more features to the product because I like it just the way it is
And I know what happens when companies add features to their products
I feel like the whole industry at this point has kind of been scarred by a bunch of software companies that have been
I guess kind of selfish they care more about
Their business model than they care about their users
It feels like the VC model in particular is tricky
And so I wonder if we could speak to that for a moment because also a congratulations
I know you recently raised a Series B round of funding and it looks like you have a blog post that addresses that as well
And in here, you know, you kind of address that issue is like some people are concerned after they hear about some series funding
That there's going to be a whole bunch of feature creep that all of a sudden it becomes this giant platform that
Like a chat system has to be built on top of what are your thoughts around that?
The biggest concern that people and even me when I see announcements like this have is
If you had to raise money, does that mean you were going to go to business if you hadn't raised money?
Because if that's the case then you're on what we call the VC treadmill
where
You have to keep running faster and faster just to not fly off the treadmill and smack into the back wall
Most startups find themselves in that situation and when that happens the desperation level rises and rises
And so you'll see a product that starts off really good, but they didn't quite find their footing couldn't figure out quite the right business model
Didn't make quite enough money to pay their expenses and they had this tough decision. Am I going to lay people off?
Or am I going to raise more money and keep trying?
And most of the time the companies go and try to raise more money and keep trying but that you know
They keep trying and it may not ever find their way, right?
That's where you get these more and more desperate weird things where like I'm going to add a chat system
Or a chat bot to my unrelated product. Tailscale is a little different and I tried to get that across in this blog post
So we announced a Series B funding of a hundred million dollars, right? Which is pretty big for a Series B
We're not raising that money
Just to stay in business. We actually had a bunch of money still left over from our Series A
We were on track to be profitable by the end of 2022
Kind of inefficiently because in fact, it's it's all you know, if you're going to raise this much money
You should actually spend it. Otherwise, you've kind of wasted your equity
Selling it to investors. So we we intend to spend a hundred million dollars, but we want to do this in a way
That we never end up at that desperation level. Like we want to be the ones in control. We're tracking our spending rate
Related to our revenues and because we've got extra money
We're trying to sort of clear out this buffer of extra money by spending a little faster than our revenues
But the revenues we look carefully at how fast we're growing so we could become profitable at any time we want
And that's a really important attribute to maintain in a company where you don't want to end up with this level of desperation
So we believe we can do it. I mean, you know, there's famous last words. We could always make mistakes
But we really really put a high premium on
Not screwing this stuff up because all three co-founders we're we're getting a little older now. We're into our 40s
We've seen this before we don't need to make a million dollars tomorrow
We don't need to make a million dollars tomorrow, but we are really tired of spending five or seven years building something
And then it fails and gets canceled out from underneath us or acquired and then somebody, you know tears it apart
Right. I don't want that to be my legacy as a person
When I retire is every project I've ever done has been ripped out from under me and torn apart
I've noticed what seems to be a consistent long-term thinking in a lot of this and a lot of what you communicate
You're currently thinking about like what we're doing today, but you're also thinking about
Where things are going long term and I wonder if is there something particular in your past experience that has
Has really drilled this into we have to be careful when it comes to vc funding and we have to think in a certain way
Is there something that you went through an experience you went through that really codified that?
I mean my first startup of course was was in this category
We absolutely got ourselves into this trouble where we built some really cool technology including that vpn. I mentioned the pre-shuttle one
It also had a bunch of other stuff. We found the traction users were getting excited
We never quite figured out our go-to-market model
So we could sell the product but the expense of having salespeople calling people
To try to find the ones who were willing to buy it
Was always a little bit higher than the actual revenue we got
From selling the product, right? And this is in the pre-software as a service days
So it was kind of weird back then you would you would sell something once and not a monthly subscription
And that you know the whole mathematical model of that is very different from the monthly sales, right?
So if you have a sales team today each salesperson say can add 50k of arr per month, right?
Then that's great. You you just have this one salesperson and they keep going and the arr keeps going up
And of course, you're going to have churn and so on so sooner or later it maxes out
But you have this really nice model when you have people selling one shot each time
Then your revenue doesn't keep going up over time, right?
The salesperson that you have selling a certain amount per month means you get that much revenue per month
Not that much additional revenue per month. So the models are very different
But back then, you know, we were selling appliances you bought appliances
The device was you know, there was no subscription element to it. And so we got ourselves into this treadmill of
The long-term value of a customer was slightly less than the cost of acquisition of a customer
And eventually we ran out of money related to the dot-com crash and everything else
Or we ran I shouldn't say we ran out
We never actually ran out of money we ran low on money and eventually we had to look for an exit strategy
The exit strategy we find was through acquisition, right? So our investors made their money back
But none of us got super rich from it, right?
And then I worked at google for a while
I don't want to say too much about google because everybody talks about google all the time
But I saw many many projects inside google succeeding and failing for many many different kinds of reasons and I'm extra curious about that stuff
So I talked to a lot of people while I was there to understand what was working in their project and not working in their project
Like there's definitely patterns to the things that work and don't work and a lot of it involves just sort of like
I think i'm not i'm not a real sports person, but some people call it like getting ahead of your skis, right when you over invest
money
And start spending faster than you understand the business model
That's when you get yourself on this treadmill and it happens just as much in startups as it does in teams and large companies
Do you feel like larger teams are more susceptible to that problem than smaller teams and smaller companies?
It's not so much about team size about money, right? So the the curse is having too much money
And not having the self-control to know that it's too much money
Back in the old dot-com days people used to say this about amazon losing money on every sale, but making up in volume
Right a lot of startups to this day still try to do that and it still doesn't work
Amazon was not actually doing that amazon was doing something else which is why amazon's so successful
But it kind of looked like that and there were a lot of startups that were doing that at the time
But they still do it now if you have a business model that you can't make money per unit
At small scale, you're definitely not going to make money per unit
At 10 or 100 times that scale
I want to shift gears but kind of in the whole business model arena tail scale is open source
And most of the times when I talk to ceos
They tell me that they can't open source their software because somebody would just copy it
Stand up a clone and take all of their profits and that doesn't seem to be a concern of yours
I mean, it's a concern it is it's also a backup plan
So like I said, one of my number one concerns is like when I retire I want my stuff to still exist
And one of my favorite things about shuttle, which is actually one of our competitors
Is that no matter how much I lose attention in it, no matter how much money it doesn't make
Shuttle is still around, right?
There's no company that can just disappear and vaporize the software that was attached to it
And I really like that about open source
I think there's a lot of people out there who open source things and that's like at least half the reason they do it
Is so that when the company they're working for goes away or when they leave the company they're working for
They can still have access to all that source code that they wrote is not destroyed, right?
So I have to admit I have an element of that
Like I personally want to make sure this thing can never die and this is one way to do it
That said, it's also beneficial to our customers
First of all, you can get bug fixes and contributions
Secondly, people don't like installing proprietary VPN clients in their Linux machines
Just generally speaking, you've got almost the whole stack you're using in your cloud servers is open source
If you have this one proprietary VPN server, it very much slows down the adoption
And thirdly, we do, there is a component of Tailscale called the control server that we operate that is not open source
Now there is an open source control server called HeadScale
It's not maintained by us, but we contribute to the HeadScale development
We work with the developer and so on
It doesn't have as many features as Tailscale
It doesn't integrate in exactly the same way, but it works with the same Tailscale clients
So people who are really concerned, they want to have a 100% open source system can do that
Yeah, I was going to ask you about HeadScale, so I'm glad you touched on that. Thank you
Looking at Tailscale, I think a lot of people identify it as one of those quintessential
This is how I get my work done now tools and there's others out there
Slack and Dropbox come to mind
Do you watch some of those companies or are there companies that you watch and go, okay, we're not going to do that
What are you looking for not doing?
I'm curious as a customer, what are you not going to do?
That's an interesting question
In the case of Slack, I really like the way they've done their business model
The way they did their authentication was a series of missteps that I think they're finally getting to
Correcting many years into their existence
So we're probably not going to copy the way Slack did authentication
But I really love their business model, the way that individuals in a company can adopt Slack
They don't even need to necessarily know that other individuals in the same company are adopting Slack
In different Slack instances
And then at some point, you can group all those instances together and say, okay, we're all using Slack here at this company
Why don't we get by a company subscription and get a discount?
That is a really nice business model
That's something that in the security world and infrastructure, which is where Tailscale finds itself
You almost never see that
There's almost no such thing as a security product that is adopted in this bottom up way
And the reason for that is pretty simple
It's that security products almost never solve the problem you have right now
If you're a software developer, you're trying to get something done
The only thing a security product tends to do is stop you from getting that thing done
That's the job of a security product
So it tends to be enforced top down by the CISO saying, look, I know you guys have a lot of work to do
But could you please not do these five things that are horrific security holes that are going to get us in trouble?
And then they slow you down
Tailscale has this nice model where it comes in as an infrastructure tool, a problem solving tool
And then coincidentally on the side, it's also really secure
So the default thing you do with Tailscale is way better than the default thing you would have done otherwise
So the security people who are in charge find out you're using Tailscale
And instead of saying, oh, no, no, please stop doing that
They're like, oh, thank goodness you stopped doing that thing you were doing before
Let's maybe formalize this Tailscale thing a bit
It makes sense
It does definitely feel like a bottom up tool that people are discovering and just falling in love with
I'd like to kind of wrap it up by just kind of getting your thoughts on sort of the state of the tech ecosystem
You know, you look out there, we have some major, major tech companies
And it feels like eventually if you're playing on their platforms, you get their attention
And I'm wondering if that's on your radar at all as far as maybe Apple goes or Microsoft or Google goes
Have you shown up on their radar yet? Have you had conversations with them?
Are you concerned at all about them influencing or trying to influence the direction of features on the mobile app or something to that regard?
I mean, we've had interactions with pretty much all of them
I would say that in general, they're all pretty happy that we exist
We're not hurting anybody's platform by creating this functionality
There's no like embrace and extend model for them
Because I mean, if you imagine Apple, for example, there actually was a Tailscale like product that Apple launched quite a few years ago now
Quite a few years ago now called Back to my Mac, right?
It did almost that exact same thing, except it only worked on Apple products, right?
Which sounds neat, but almost never solves your problem, right?
And similarly, Microsoft, I just found out yesterday there was a product called Windows Mesh, I think
Came out apparently with Windows 7 or near the time of Windows 7 that did similar things to Tailscale
But it only worked on Windows
Tailscale has a feature called Taildrop, which is a lot like AirDrop that Apple has that lets you move files between your devices
Except Tailscale's one works on all your kinds of devices and it doesn't care about physical proximity
Apple's AirDrop only works on Apple devices and even then only sometimes and nobody's quite sure why it doesn't always work, right?
And AWS, for example, they've got an AWS VPN, they've got VPCs, they've got IPSec connections, but it only works inside AWS
So if AWS was going to try to make a Tailscale, it might not make it easy to connect to other kinds of clouds
Because they really have no incentive to make it easy to connect to other kinds of clouds, right?
But if Tailscale is sitting out here independently making all these things work
Then it actually makes it easier for you to use AWS, easier for you to use Windows, easier for you to use Linux
And easier for you to use Apple, it connects all these things together, it makes all these platforms better, right?
So we don't see a lot of interference from the platform owners because we're not really hurting their business at all
We're just making it so that their thing works better with everybody else's things
Yeah, really, it makes it so I can get more work done on their devices, it's what it does
Exactly
Well, Avery, I'm just a huge fan, so thank you very much for all of the hard work
And of course for everyone there at the team and thanks so much for coming on and chatting with us
Yeah, thank you
I really enjoyed that chat with Avery, it's not many founders I can sit down and talk everything from TCPIP to big tech economics
So that was really great, and again if you want to sign up, that wasn't sponsored, that wasn't paid for
But if you want to support one of our shows, tailscale.com slash self-hosted or tailscale.com slash coder
The whole idea of mesh VPNs that can defeat double NAT, carrier grade networking has been a topic on this show for a long time
And when we were in Raleigh, I was kind of leaning over to Brent and I was saying, you know, you got to try this tailscale thing out
I think you would really like it specifically because you do kind of travel around and you've kind of got places you visit frequently now
Tailscale feels like it could be a good solution for you, and I know you didn't get a chance to try it out while I was there
But I think you have since then, so what is like the, I don't know, let's say the Brent review of tailscale, what are your thoughts?
Well I got to say I'm relatively new to it, it's been maybe a week that I've been into it, and maybe a day since I've really dove into it on my own systems here
But whenever you nudge me towards something I know I need to be listening, and so thank you for that
I have in the past, you know, with travel in mind, set up a WireGuard exit node
So I have a little VPS somewhere that just purely accepts my connections wherever I happen to be, that makes me feel a little bit better
Because there are certain places that I go with my laptop that I don't feel like open traffic is necessarily a good thing
But that being said, now I have access to a VM that Alex set up for me where I've been doing some Ansible playing with
And I guess I also have a Bitcoin node sitting over there that I can access from here now, and so the more I dive into it, the more I realize it's solving a lot of my various issues that I have had in the past
And have found solutions that were a bit annoying, but also solutions for problems that I've had that I haven't had a solution for yet
So I know, Chris, you use it a whole bunch, but I'm like tingling with excitement now of diving into Tailscale and really getting a sense of how it can just make things easy and seamless for me
For me, the progression was, at first, for like a month or two, I set it up and I was like, oh yeah, finally I can connect my RV server systems and the studio systems all on one flat network
That was a huge thing for me, because until Tailscale, I never opened up the RV's network to the internet, and there's a ton of dashboards and control panels and statistics and data that the system in the RV is collecting all the time
And sometimes I'm at the studio and I want to check in on that stuff
So that was the first problem I solved, because it takes 30 seconds to get it installed on a Linux box, if that, and they have Raspberry Pi packages and stuff
So I was like, all right, this is great, yeah, okay, sweet, I got a VPN, all right
I didn't really get hyped about it
I don't know why it took me like three months, so you're way ahead of me, dude, until I realized I could install it in a VM
And I had several VMs and projects, like a lot of the Nix stuff, the Nix challenge stuff I was doing in VMs
And it dawned on me that, wait a minute, I could set up a Nix VM, install Tailscale, which is awesome on Nix, and then I could access this VM from literally all my machines, like it's right here
And I could continue the Nix challenge from anywhere, which was great because we were traveling to North Carolina and all of that
And that's when I realized, oh, wait a minute, I actually could run it in this container
Oh, and look at this, Umbral has a Tailscale app that runs in Docker, and now I can get access to my Bitcoin, and it just
That is cool
Yeah, that's when it clicked, when I was like, oh, I could do it in VMs, I can do it in containers, and I can do it on my physical devices, including my mobile devices
And so I just sort of built out a bigger and bigger network, and then it kind of clicked, oh, I can also, you know, support my kids' computers this way
So I really like it, I've probably crossed over where I have more systems using Tailscale than Nebula
Nebula is great because there's like no centralized service, there's nobody getting involved, but it's a lot more of a bring up
So it just didn't quite hit the sweet spot for my, like my laptop and my phone and my Raspberry Pi
But it was, it seemed like a really sweet spot for the VPS and the servers on the studio LAN
But now Tailscale I think has kind of eclipsed some of that too, and it has some really nice DNS stuff, you can actually, if you wanted to, do an easy mode
You can put a Pi-hole in your Tailscale network, and it will start resolving DNS for all of your machines on Tailscale
So you can start referring to all your machines by machine name
That is very cool
Yeah, I like it, it's also been really handy while I'm on the road again, every freaking time I'm on the road
That's how I, a lot of the boosts and feedback, I do all of that through a VPN
It's really nice to be able to just have that right there
So it's a, it's a hell of a thing
I'm really impressed with the service and that's why I was hoping to get some insights into how the heck they're going to keep it running
And the thing that he touched on in there that I liked is they've set it up in a way where the free accounts don't compete with the paid pro users
Which is always like this collision that it seems like all of these services that offer a free version are always heading towards this iceberg
Where inevitably the sales team feels like the free accounts are competing with their benchmarks
And you know, we end up, you always see like the free stuff getting cut back
And the idea that they've kind of designed it in a way where that doesn't happen
I feel like that shows some really good long-time thinking, long-term thinking
So it was nice to see that
Like I said, I'm relatively new so I've been diving into some of their documentation
Just to get a sense of how it all works and what I could possibly do with it
And I found their documentation to actually be really, really great and also fascinating
Which I don't say very often about documentation
It's, it's slightly, I'll say it's ever so slightly confusing
They have a section for documentation which I think is a little bit more on the technical
It's a simple explainer of the technical side of things which I found very, very helpful
So getting DNS set up for your whole network and those kind of useful tips
But they also have sections that I would encourage people to just go browse
One of them is called the Tailscale Guides and the other is Tailscale Solutions
I don't quite know the difference between them
They seem very similar but there's some amazingly fascinating stuff in there
So they have a guide on like accessing a Pi Hole or Raspberry Pi from anywhere
Which I think is a really nice place to start maybe if you are trying to play with this
But they also have, you know, a guide on Tailscale and NixOS
A new Minecraft server in 10 minutes which sounds really fun
Tailscale in LXC containers
I know we talked about that a little bit last week
So that might be a place to go if people are interested
And the last one that really caught my eye was setting up a dog cam
With Tailscale Raspberry Pi in motion
Bitwarden.com slash Linux
Get started with a free trial of Teams or Enterprise
Or for an individual when you go to bitwarden.com slash Linux
Simply put, it's the easiest way for individuals or businesses to store, share, and sync sensitive data
Bitwarden is fully customizable
You can turn certain features off that you don't want
And of course it's what I use for my password and secret information storing
And I'll also add my two-factor authentication token
I put it all in one package
And man is that handy when I'm traveling
Oh my gosh, you guys
I won't name names
But some of my friends out there, they don't use Bitwarden
And I have been on a campaign to convert them
Because it is painful when I sit down and watch them try to log in on some service
When they don't have a password manager
Like maybe they set up a new box
Or maybe they're using a system in the studio temporarily
Oh my god, it's painful
Bitwarden makes it so much simpler
They make it easy and safe to store sensitive data
For yourself or when you're working with a team
Wes and I use it to manage our passwords and two-factor codes
And other sensitive data all the time
I use it to work with team members
And I really think it'd be great for open source projects too
And one of the things they've just recently added which is brilliant is a username generator
Stop using the same username at every site you go to
I never really thought about it
But that's crazy
Anything you can do to improve your security online is going to be good, right?
But like I'd say number one is passwords
And number two, I never really thought about it
But of course it's usernames
Because if a service is compromised and their database leaks
Then that username is going to be the same username across multiple sites
At least it is for me, I'm embarrassed to say it's true
So having a different username for each website you use
That's going to make it difficult
I'd say impossible for a hacker and attacker to track you across sites
And of course their generator supports your email service
If it has like the plus addition for an email
So like Gmail for example
User plus your actual like fake thing at gmail.com or whatever
It's really nice
And it's so intuitive the way they do it
Because it all just stores in Bitwarden
Then when I try to log into a service on my phone
I have a nice secure password for that too
And I'll admit before they got really good password management on the phones
This just wasn't a great option
And Bitwarden nails it
And then on the iPhone it ties in with face ID
So it's scanning my face
It's importing the password I mean it just happens so smooth so flawlessly
I love it
And like I say when I'm traveling tools like this
I don't know I don't know how I got work done without them
Something like Bitwarden it's the only way I'm going to go
And I love that it's open source
And I love that they have a self-hosted option
And I love that they got a giant community
Go try it out for yourself
Or maybe recommend it to a friend and family member like I've been doing recently
Or maybe it's time for your workplace to kind of get their act together in this regard
No shame in that game
It's just you know the way things have been in the past
But now Bitwarden is changing it and they've got great team plans too
Individual or team go try it out right now
Bitwarden.com slash Linux
Go to Bitwarden.com slash Linux to support the show
And to get started with the best password management
And I'll say it my personal way to keep all my secrets
What's in there?
Bitwarden.com slash Linux
We got some great feedback again this week
Thank you everyone
Lyndon wrote in
I was just listening to episode 457
I'm a heavy user of Ansible and LXD
And thought I'd share a couple of useful tips
One is the ability to use LXD to manage hosts with Ansible
No SSH required
If you configure a local LXD client to connect to a remote LXD server
You can specify the name of the host and containers in your inventory
And configure the Ansible host variable as follows
He gives an example we'll include
I think that's kind of neat
I know Alex got real excited about that
So that's sort of fun
They continue
I know you folks are also Bitwarden users
Rather than store secrets in multiple places and use Ansible vaults
I found a plugin that lets you use the Bitwarden command line client
To retrieve Ansible secrets
So we'll leave a link to that
That is awesome
I didn't really even think of that
It's so great
Why not use Bitwarden for the secrets?
You know what he touches on here
About being able to deploy a LXD container or a server
With just like a couple of things that you specify
And then Ansible does the rest
I do really appreciate that when we did the NixOS challenge
We did a bit of a comparison between Ansible and Nix
And that's sort of what's brought up all this Ansible feedback
And it wasn't really a fair comparison
Because the Nix system lets you manage the Nix package and the NixOS possibly
But you could run the Nix package manager on just about any distro
And it lets you manage that world, right?
Where Ansible is like multi OS, multi distro, multi container platforms, right?
And so that's the big difference
Now, I think there is a totally valid argument for only needing to learn a Nix system
If that's the scope of your work
But I think it's also really valid to say, you know, there's a lot more I want to get done
And so Ansible is the way for me
And I totally appreciate that
And I feel like I've gotten a whole new set of insights on how people use these tools accidentally
Like we just stumbled into this
And I'm learning a lot
So I guess that's a good thing, right?
So yeah, and I think that's the really the beauty of some of the feedback we keep getting
We're in a position where people just giving us
Keep giving us some great tips on things we didn't know we needed
And turns out we do
And now it is time for Le Boost
As always, we get some great boosts as well
SirLurksalot is back
1337SATS seems oddly specific
Feather for the tinfoil hat, if you will
Starlink knows where you are
Even if you bug out in the middle of nowhere
Considering how Elon's car company collects an enormous amount of data about its customers
You have to at least wonder how that data is being used
Or sold
Or in what form
Who actually has access
And how securely it really is in the hands of yet another tech company that dabbles in hardware
Are your internet habits and travels valuable to hacker loot?
Hmm, maybe some bacon here, Chris
Oh, man
Yeah, I hadn't really thought about the fact that now there's one more company that's tracking my exact location
And they do, you know, they have to know where the dish is in order for it to connect to the satellites up in space
And the dish is always aware of its longitude and latitude
And I must have GPS in there too
You know, it's such a trade-off
I don't know why, but I probably am more comfortable with Starlink than I am
Verizon or AT&T or T-Mobile
I feel like Verizon, AT&T, T-Mobile probably have like an automated system
That law enforcement can just check a box and get your location info for like the last year
Maybe Starlink will do the same
But it's the trade-off of getting connected to the worldwide community, right?
How else can you get connected to an internet like that
Without some trace unless you use someone else's system
And JOOPS does have, on the roof, I have a 7-in-1 antenna array
And a couple of those antennas are dedicated to 2.4 and 5 gigahertz Wi-Fi
I can pick up Wi-Fi from quite a range
So every now and then there is, I do have the capability of doing like some sneaky network joining
Careful of what you admit to here
I know, I'm sort of realizing right now
But, you know, when you're out in the middle of nowhere and you have to bring your own internet
Yeah, that would be a problem
Boost to graph
Marcel wrote in with a thousand sats
So when does the Star Trek podcast come out?
I'm kidding, of course, but I would definitely listen to that
You seem very passionate about it
I just finished Enterprise and I have mixed feelings
On the pre-show for the member feed, I think we got into Star Trek again, didn't we?
I think it was all Coder Radio's fault
It happens from time to time, we get up
With age does come some wisdom
And I have realized that there are some hobbies and passions that I have
That I shouldn't make content out of
And I should keep them for myself to enjoy
And I've decided that Star Trek is one of those things
And I have dabbled in the past with Star Trek related content
And I have found that Jupiter broadcasting is its strongest when we really stay on mission and focused
And so that gives me an opportunity
That is an excuse to just keep Star Trek for something I personally enjoy
However, I do love a good Star Trek conversation
And I will always jump in if something's going down on stream related to Star Trek
And I would love to, like, if one of my friends out there starts a Star Trek podcast
I'd love to join them for an episode sometime
Because, yeah, I'm a bit of a fiend when it comes to Star Trek
But I don't plan to launch a Star Trek show
I think I'll leave that out for all the other folks out there that want to make podcasts around it
We got several just like thanks for doing a show, Boose
These are great too
We got a couple from Crashmaster18 and Winebearer in a total of about 6,000 SATs
They just sent in some thank yous
So I just want to say thank you guys for boosting
We also got some folks that are doing the SAT streaming
So you can set an amount and while you listen, it'll stream a SAT every now and then back to us
And the great news is that with the price of Bitcoin down, SATs are on sale
They're the same SATs, one SAT still equals one SAT
So get them cheap while you can right now
I'll probably be on sale for a little while as the market's going to just be in the tank
So go get some cheap SATs and load up a podcasting 2.0 app
You can get them at newpodcastapps.com
Podcasting 2.0 has a lot going on
Including they're working right now very diligently on incorporating live audio streaming into the app
So you just open up your podcast app
And if Linux Unplugged is live, it'll just show as in your feed list, it's live on air
And you can tap it and you can listen to our live stream in your podcasting 2.0 compatible app
Not all apps support it yet
Like I don't think Fountain or Castamatic do
But some of the web apps, there's some really good web podcasting apps, by the way
Who knew?
Podverse is great because it's a web app that syncs to a mobile client as well
All of these are listed at newpodcastapps.com
But I can't wait for live streaming and transcription and a whole bunch of other stuff
That's all part of the podcasting 2.0 spec along with the value block
You can check out a lot of all that info in Office Hours
We covered a bunch of it last week at officehours.hair for that
And go try out a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com
And if you don't want a new podcast app, because I know a lot of you love AntennaPod
That's very popular in our community
So is Overcast on the iOS side
And actually Apple Podcast app is always a strong contender
And Pocket Cast, of course
I know you guys love those apps and you don't want to change
Go try Breeze
You can send in some boosts via the Breeze app and you don't have to switch podcast apps
That's pretty, pretty nice
Guess what?
We got a pick
And it's on theme
Like, I likes it
Brandon, how do you think you pronounce this one?
Oh, I think I got this one
You do?
Oh yeah, go for it
I think it's called We're On
Ah, yeah, yeah, like we are on
Right, you see that?
Yeah, we're on
I think you nailed it
So this is a secure overlay network based on WebRTC
That is interesting
Yeah, this is weird
But it's on theme for this episode
Wes found this actually
So it's a shame he can't be here
So maybe if we ever give this a go with him, we'll bring it up again
Because I think he actually wanted to talk about it
But the idea is with We're On is that it gives you access to nodes behind a firewall, behind an ad
Using WebRC to establish the connection between the nodes
And actually this stuff has been built into WebRTC all the time
And nobody ever built the tooling around it
And it always drove me crazy because we basically use WebRTC now for video calls and audio calls
And that's really where we stopped
But it could, you know, you can actually build a freaking CDN on top of WebRTC
So they're using the underlying suite of tools that are available for this
And the project claims it's pretty low overhead and it's pretty surprisingly good performance
That's ridiculous
If you use it between nodes on a LAN, they say, you may not even notice a performance overhead
Which is just wild
I don't know, man
I don't know
But it's actually pretty easy to get up and going on a Linux box
You basically can just pull down a binary and get it up and going
So we'll put a link in the show notes to We're On
And I could see someone who wants a temporary mesh network
You know, maybe it's up for the day or maybe it's up for an event
I could totally see that
Oh, yeah
Right
You're doing a corporate event or a Linux event and you want to build a temporary mesh network
You don't necessarily want to assign to anyone's particular account or anything like that
You could use We're On to stand that thing up in five minutes
And now you got yourself an overlay network
All running off of WebRTC, which everybody has support for on their box
Not really something we need because we're pretty much set
But gosh, you could see that
You never know
That's it
We're wrapping it up
I just want to make a mention that we do this show live on Sunday
Even if that means I got to set up some sort of hack together
Set up run over cellular from Southern Oregon
We're doing it live
And that means that we get great folks like Christian from Red Hat that stopped by
And if you're in our if you're in our Mumble Room
And you got a question about this Nvidia open source driver
You can ask one of the guys that has the most knowledge about the situation directly
That's a unique opportunity
And it happens right here on Linux Unplugged
But also hanging out live just lets you listen in real time
Give us feedback in the chat room
And if you get Mumble, you can actually just hang out in the quiet listening room
Then you get an Opus codec quality of the show
With probably lower latency than Brent and I have between each other right now
It's great and it's a totally free software stack
And then you got it
You can join us and you can do things like office hours
Which we also do on Mumble and other network shows that use Mumble from time to time
And if you're in the tech industry or you're just curious about what's going on in the world
Of free software and open source
Don't miss an episode of Linux Action News
LinuxActionNews.com
Christian worked with us to make sure that we had the most accurate information possible
So literally the moment the Nvidia news dropped
Linux Action News dropped
So that way you could have the context and the information first
And you could make sure that you were commenting
Or if you were saying something online, it was accurate, right?
I mean, you see a lot of people just popping off with their opinion
But JB listeners got the facts
Just by being subscribed to Linux Action News
So it's something to consider because when something goes down
We're going to try to cover it there as accurately and as fast as possible
So LinuxActionNews.com
Big plug for that, I guess
Hope to see you next week
Join us, we'll be live on a Sunday
But of course, you is always, always welcome to subscribe
Enjoy the show any way you want
Live is just one of the options
And of course, we appreciate any value you can return to the show
Maybe it's a membership at Linux Unplugged Core
Maybe it's jupyter.party for the whole network
Maybe it's a boost
Or maybe it's just telling someone about the show
That matters a lot too
Maybe it's a review, I don't know
I don't know you
I can't tell you what
But we appreciate you listening
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode
And we'll see you right back here next week
So obviously to make it clear
Because I was not sure that no Nvidia driver for the future
Is only possible with the right current version of the Nvidia GPUs
And the future GPU cards
And it is not possible to use that one with the 1060 for example, right?
No, not with 1060
Wow, is the 1060 that old?
Wow, yeah, it looks like
Yeah, but in fact, so it could be that
If for the 1060 a working row driver is running
Then somehow we could profit from that new initiative, right?
Maybe
Yeah, maybe
I'm not sure
Because I mean, once again, right
The driver consists of multiple parts, right?
This is a current driver and then there's a user space with Mesa
And then there's also the firmware
And we need all three of them to be able to work together
And I don't think the firmware can work with the such old cards
The other thing I had just because it comes in my mind now
And the firmware, if I understood it well
Before, all right, the firmware actually has some shared code
That is also used on Windows, right?
So the Linux and Windows driver with the firmware share some code, right?
I usually get someone from NVIDIA to go on details there
I mean, another driver in general is shared between Windows and Linux
And if there is exactly the same firmware, I think it is
But I don't know, between Windows and Linux systems
I mean, they try to, I mean, of course
For ease of maintenance to keep things as aligned as possible between the two
Here's what I'm wondering
And this is, we'll just see and it's gonna depend on developer resources
But imagine we're four or five years into this, right?
So we've all been using an open source NVIDIA driver for a while
We've got the open source AMD driver
We've got the open source Intel driver
Do we start to see one common interface to start to change some of these settings
Or whatever is maybe gets exposed that in the past required an AMD control panel
And an NVIDIA control panel
Like, do we start to see maybe some basic settings
Just get baked into the plasma desktop or GNOME desktop
And on the back end, they're figuring out if that's for an NVIDIA card or an AMD card
Like, it feels like the integration and control that could eventually come to the desktop
Is going to be at a whole new level
When all of the major video card drivers are open source
Yeah, I think my thoughts around there is that, you know
They are continuously expanding, you know, what Wokid can do
So, I mean, you know, I mentioned this to you afterwards over interview
But I'm really excited by the fact that, you know
There is Vulkan extensions coming out to do H.264, H.265 and VC1 encoding and decoding now
Which means that instead of, you know, up to this point having to deal with like, you know
Special encoding library for NVIDIA
Special encoding library for Intel and so on
We can now, as application writers, right
Have one API we target and we will get GPU accelerated encoding and decoding
So this is something I'm really excited about
And I think, you know, I think we'll see a lot more things moving into Vulkan over time
Because I think they're definitely going to go on beyond maybe, you know
Well, as we see with the video, just doing 3D graphics
Christian, as a last question, I'm curious about
What was your personal favorite part about working on this initiative for you personally?
Well, the main thing, of course, is that I know that for Fedora users
And RAL users too, of course
But it's been a pain point for years to have to then deal with going out
Or first realizing, oh, okay, I need a driver for my hardware
Because I think on Linux people sort of assume everything is just there
And then maybe not finding it or maybe they found the wrong version
Or they found a version that was harder to set up
I mean, I know a lot of people, of course
Ended up getting the upstream NVIDIA driver, which they then have to build themselves
And, of course, I did that myself back in the day
And it was, you know, a great learning experience
But, you know, it would have been a lot easier for people to, for instance,
Have found the repository of RPN Fusion to just get it pre-set up for them very easily
So I think just being able to get beyond that and sort of say, yep, graphics is not going to be
Something where I, you know, have to read a review for a new Fedora release
And people saying, oh, this broke
That's the big thing for me
Oh, I can't wait