I feel like we should probably warn everybody that next week is the daylight savings monster in the US and it's gonna mess with everybody's
Lifetime it's already happening. That's one of the reasons why we don't have any folks here today is it's already happened across the pond
They're all screwed up
Yes, yes, we are. I still blame George W Bush for this
It was really Bush's fault and now it's all it's totally ever since he did that
It's screwed with my live shows around this time of year. So next Sunday the 5th at 2 a.m. In the US
We switch so now it's gonna mess with land, but since land isn't live no big deal. Yeah
Yeah, see if we just had that one Linux based world government. Yeah, right. It could all just be Unix time
Would that be the Linux Foundation? Yeah, I guess so
You know change from a sort of foundation to government agency, but let's let's let's put a pin in that idea Wes
This is Linux unplugged episode
221 for October 31st. Whoo 2017
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's still in a reinstall fugue state. My name is Chris
My name is Wes. Hello beard. Mmm burgers. Yeah
We all have a little we have some burger pleasantry going on right now, but that's not what we're here to talk about
I'm not here talking about burgers at least at least not yet
No, we have a really great show lined up for you today. Very excited about today's program for a couple of reasons
We have two guests coming on did rocks who posted all of the Ubuntu gnome journey posts for the 1710 release cycle shares
some insights including an anecdote that
That occurred just before just before 1710 went live that hasn't been posted anywhere because they're all too exhausted
And if you think that those final ISOs are final, maybe not maybe maybe not
Yeah, so it's an interesting anecdote. We'll get to that and then we'll cook the Ubuntu desktop manager joins us
And I got a couple of hard questions for him
specifically, I want to know if them dropping unity sort of takes away some of their strategic advantage of controlling their own desktop and
I
Ask him if canonicals goals with snaps are going to impact the relationship with gnome
Which obviously they are very dependent on now and I'm just curious how he sees that relationship
So those those amongst other questions will cook answers and just a little bit in the show
but of course we have a whole bunch of community news to get into and we have a
I'll say a humble virtual look today. Hello mumble room. Thank you for joining us. Hello
Hello robot arms, so we have a couple of guys which actually the best guys we have the best people
I'm told people tell me these are the best so we have much to get into today
But I wanted to take a moment and share my fugue state of reinstalling computers with you. Just for a moment
I've gone full maniac. I haven't been on a tear like this in years and
And it's really morphed into something perverted. That's gonna give me people are gonna give me crap
I'm gonna tell you guys something in this in in just because it's content
Yeah, sit down if you need to be prepared, please go gentle on me when I tell you this, please
But I have to I have to be honest with you. I have been installing
Ubuntu 1604
Like crazy did no one make you do this. No, it's happening. He and I have almost swapped positions again
It's kind of funny. It's kind of funny and totally unrelated. He and I just had a conversation about this
I had a you know
I just had a I had a kind of I had a come-to-linus moment where I was
sitting here in the studio getting ready to reload the next machine and
You'll understand more after my interview with will cook by the way
This this will give you some of the insights as to why I've made my decision
but I decided after evaluating gnome plasma Mate or Mate and
unity 7
For the studio where we have some high DPI requirements non. We have some touchscreen requirements and don't I?
Evaluated those desktops to see if they could who would be the best one in fact
I didn't even intend to evaluate unity it just sort of happened by mistake
I never even gave any considerations just one of the systems happen to have it on there and
After trying all these desktops for production
I know you guys get sick of hearing this, but I'm just I decided that don't don't give me shit, but it's actually unity 7
it's
Ironically unity 7 it's the most stable it seems to perform the best under load and
It has polish in areas that that matter to me. I'm not saying it's better than gnome
But I am saying that for areas that matter to me. It's better than known and so I'll give you a couple examples
Multi-monitor support is is still better in unity would guess what we use a lot here in the studio
I I still prefer the way that they handle the launcher
I still prefer that's that system that that that super key system and instead of the way that gnome implements
It's not a big difference, but I do prefer it
There's others
There's other things though that are like
Rough edges that have been rounded off by unity where you can tell that a lot of thought it's it's ironically in some ways a lot
like when I use
elementary OS you car you are struck with
And you and maybe Dan could talk about this a bit, but you are struck with
Shit somebody thought of that
Somebody somebody actually thought of that and solve that problem for me and when you hit when that hits you a few times you're like
Oh, man, this is there is that there is something else going on here that I've missed
And I don't know Dan if you want to expand upon the point of where sometimes some projects are willing to spend I would assume
You tell me if I'm wrong a hell of a lot of time on something a lot of other people might not even consider important
Yeah, I mean, I think it just comes from just dogfooding and obsessive perfectionism
Just hating yourself enough to sit through it
You know good way to put it and I mean grinding your way through it and punishing yourself as you just keep working away at it
Yeah, I mean, I don't know if you remember the first versions of unity were awful, you know
Oh, yeah. Yeah, right and it the same thing for any software
I think the first versions are like this is what we assume is gonna be good and then they're terrible and then it's you know
You you grind through it and you iterate on it you go
Okay, this is what we learned and changed and you know
That's really you know
That's been happening to the plasma desktop and know them too
Like they've all been going through iterative releases where they've been getting better and better. I I switched over full-time to gnome 3
when
3.12
Was sort of the main release and I think every release since then has been getting progressively better
And I was very excited about gnome 3 for a long time and I never switched away from unity
Because of gnome 3 I didn't switch away because of right because of that I switched away from unity because I switched to arch and
With that I switched to gnome and I was excited by the idea of a polished desktop for all distributions
That's really what fired me up about gnome coming back to it now
Now I have a different mindset in the studio. These are not machines that I use to enjoy
I don't use these to play like I don't really play a lot of video games
But I do play with my computer alone and these are not computers I play with so it doesn't matter if they're appliances
And so when I sat down to load 1710 with the new gnome 3 desktop, I said well, okay
what what what is 1710 giving me that 1604 doesn't because we've already got a 1604 machine in production that has been rock-solid and
Beard and I looked up the packages that we need and we didn't see any all the software we needed is available
Wow. Yeah, and it struck me. This is not the same
Path it was back when you in 1404 or 1204 before especially
Yeah, the LTS as your desktop now is much more doable every single package
I wanted was available for 1604 without I used to come on air and say
Ubuntu LTS desktops are the hardest distro to install software on because after about a year and a half
Nobody makes offer for it anymore and all your PPAs break
Everybody's making software for it now every every single app that I've installed via a dead was all available for 1604
or snaps and
Including OBS and ffmpeg versions that we used to not be able to get. Yeah, it's it's just a different
It's just a different landscape now
and so I I just kind of made like this business decision that I was going to deploy 1604 and
Just I got six months until the next LTS comes out if I want and then I made then once I made that decision
I made the part that I've actually been building to because I know we've been talking a lot about Ubuntu
This is kind of the last big episode on it
For a while and I decided if I'm going to be practical and be all business-like with my machines and go 1604
Why not also experiment with deploying Ubuntu's product or canonicals product called landscape?
Now landscape is sort of a central management
Platform where you can also do inventory package management user management script management
performance monitoring
all of these things across all your machines from one central place and
You get like a hundred credits for free
For the first 60 days or something like that
And I think it works out depending on which
Tier you get it works out to be about five dollars a month
And if you're watching the video version right now, I have got my landscape account up on the screen
I've got five machines registered these this is the tear I've been on recently as these five and
You can see just by a quick glance that I have two outstanding alerts over these five machines
One computer has upgrade packages available and one computer has been upgraded but needs to be rebooted
Yeah, that's not too bad
But there's some things that are actually really quite neat about it
One thing is the performance monitoring so I can pull up graphs across all of our studio systems
And I can see if one system is under a quite a bit more load than the other system
I can see at what times that is like if it's show times or if it's non show times memory usage swap usage
temperatures for the storage and for the
hardware and
Any of this can be downloaded as a CSV and I can I can zoom in and just look at one machine for any of this
Information or I can get all of the machines, which is the which is the screen
We're looking at right now if you're watching the video version
Additionally, like I said, it also kind of has like an inventory management aspect to it
So I can click in and get the hardware information so you can see here is the precision
7720 that I'm using at the lady dupes office quote-unquote, which is a chair and
It has a boon to 1604 3 on it. It's got the xeon e3
1535 m6 processors in it 64 gigabytes of RAM
You know gives you the whole hardware spec any kind of technician notes that are on it
You can change its power state or schedule a reboot change which groups it or it is in you can go in even further and get
more detailed things like serial numbers and bio states and
Mac addresses and all the things you would get from an inventory management system as well as monitoring and alerting if there's an outage
Which is great
And of course the thing that I really signed up for is and this this has just been really nice for me is
Package management and they break it out in a way that is easy to read
So like here's the crack lib dash runtime and instead of some complicated CVE thing
It's just runtime support for a password checker library
It gives it gives me real English descriptions of what these vulnerabilities are
And so I I and then if I expand it I get all the CVEs I get everything
But I am able to make a like an educated decision if that's worth me interrupting one of our production systems
And I've been using this. I don't know if I'm gonna keep it once
You know, I'm gonna keep I don't know
I don't fuck you
But once my hundred credits runs out if it if I find it makes it easier for us to do IT in the studio
Which is kind of always a time suck for either the beard or myself. I think I do it
You also get alerts so you can see I've got one computer that has the packages
One computer that needs to be rebooted and I could issue that reboot from here, of course
So I I'll go ahead and I'll issue the reboot command to the precision. That's nice
Yeah, and I can just say restart as soon as possible and machines that need to be restarted
Also get a little icon next to their name a little like a weird
Yeah, and so that's what I've been playing with since our last episode
I know it's sort of I've explained it before this show is sort of like the deep space nine of
Linux podcasts where sometimes we have continuing story arcs that we keep going back on and this has been one of them and
I think my takeaway from it is I
Forgot I forgot how much I liked unity and I've never been a unity hater
So it's not like I'm reversing some position I've taken but I haven't been a unity user and I've been a baby a unity denier
Like I just pretend like it doesn't exist
Like I did like when we were first evaluating desktops, I didn't even consider unity
Like it didn't even come because it's that thing that only a boon to has right? Yeah
So you don't really think of it as the first class? No, and then all of a sudden
I'm like well, but I'm gonna install boon to oh
And stay tuned for the interview with will cook because you'll see why it may actually work out to be a really great long-term bet here
In a little bit. Did you have anything you look like you had something you were pontificating on over there?
Are you just dreading us formatting the last of these machines? I'm dreading having to support unity grace
Hopefully you won't have to well you'll love that comp is window effects. Let me tell you let me tell you well in the meantime
The media is continuing their freakout. Yes. I said the media is continuing their freakout about Cody
I don't know why it's Cody
That's that's the thing they hate and I do have a theory but I am really worried here because if you read this story
And this is this is unfortunate Brian Barrett over at wired and I generally like wired stuff
Just did a real hit piece against Cody
but it's actually it's an indictment of open source and that's what it concerns me is you could remove Cody and you could put a
Lot of other project names in the spaces and have the same damn problems even just desktop distros
So here's its start. I mean it starts with a vengeance
The Cody box pitch is hard to resist a little black plastic square
Not much different than a Roku or at Apple TV and similar in function as well this streamer though
Offers something those others never will free access to practically any show or movie you can dream of no rental fees
No subscriptions, just type in the name of a blockbuster and start watching in high-definition streams in seconds
What are we doing here? Let's just we don't need to do this whole thing damn
And of course if I'm if I'm an industry executive reading that and wired I just poop myself a little bit
Oh, yeah that I'm the one writing this but I won't I won't despair the author here
He goes on he makes he does write some interesting history about Cody and the XP MC connection if you're curious and does mention
A few things here and there but gets a few stingers in that really is the part that I go
Oh god, this could be any open source project
Like any open source ecosystem Cody contains multitudes. There are the Cody media player itself
There's the TV add-ons and other developer communities and there are the plugins that scraped the internet for pirated material
Those are what transformed Cody into the modern-day pirates favorite ship
It's a bit of a Wild West
Cody's open source anyone can take that software and put any piece and put it on any hardware and
The industry has thrived too because it's managed to stay relatively underground at least in the u.s
Which is funny because if you look at statistics for torrent downloads
They've gone from like damn near 30% of internet traffic to like 5% of internet traffic
So torrent piracy is way down and that's what these plugins do is they're torrent plugins that are capable of
Ordering the torrent in a way that lets them stream in real time. That's what these plugins are doing
and if you you have to do it that way because if you just did HTTP streams you get shut down immediately and
You could say that Ubuntu mate is a enabler of
Terrorist activities because maybe they used Ubuntu mate to plan a terrorist attack
this this is a really really slippery slope and
The Kodi project has had at least here in the US has had to make a really interesting response to cover their own asses
Because they're becoming the poster child the the context here is this story
I'm covering for you is is damn near a weekly story
If not, at least a twice a month story and I covered it a long time ago on the show and I decided to cover it
Again to illustrate to you that it's a problem that is not going away and I'm I am a bit concerned about this to tell you
the truth and
the Kodi project has had to respond in a way that I don't like and I can't see how they could have handled this any
Other way and the the thing that sucks is I could see other open source projects having to do the same thing
Well, first of all, they got to get all business-like then they have to lawyer up and then they have to go sue the shit
And anybody that sells anything that says Kodi that isn't just straight vanilla build from the project's website
Because that then they can tell the courts but look we're trying to fight this
We're trying to go after these guys because our pure Kodi project doesn't have these plugins
So we're going after them. But of course all if this is this is a short-term play because they're just stopped putting coding the name
Here's a quote from the Kodi project or I guess the Kodi company
We're basically taking the stance that if you use the word Kodi to mean something other than the vanilla software
We release if you pre-install add-ons or something like that
That means you're no longer shipping Kodi and we consider it a trademark violation
That's he goes on to comment that's sort of worked. We've been able to get a bunch of sellers off eBay and Amazon that way
Man I mean you could legitimately w get could be put in this position
this is bad and
I what it feels like to me when I read Brian's post here and I'm sure Brian Barrett is not a tool of the
Copyright industrial complex, but when I read this post
It feels like media executives that are super worried about their fiefdoms being torn down by this internet thing
And so they've got to start casting shade as much as possible and delegitimizing these things
And getting people to go into the grooves that are Roku Apple TV
And the things that are built to sell you content that is DRM and licensed
And this is part of the strategy. Oh, yeah
The reason why it's in Wired is because it's appealing to the geek audience with this one and that's also why you have the back
History of XBMC, you know, it's just it's appealing to the geeks. You got to get all the demos
You got to get the executives. You got to get the geeks. You got to get all the demos
Make sure you really get this this whole thing locked down and I worry about the Kodi project
So I have a link in the show notes if you want to read the whole thing because I did just give you some of the
highlights
I hate to see it happen to Kodi
And I hate to see them have to become super litigious because of it. This is a uh, yeah
It's a bad culture for everyone who's involved instead of just being like hey Kodi's awesome
And it's a great useful open source project. You want to talk about something positive to oh, please just sort of
If you have any I don't have any new flat pack. Oh new flat pack. Does it come itself in a flat pack?
How does that work? Well, the flat pack may be getting a little flatter and easier for people to understand or stable
So this is uh, we're going to be talking about a little bit more about that in a little bit
Um, so this is uh, we got we got two things actually. It's kind of neat
You're going to have flat pack 0.10
Which is going to be like a we won't call it LTS, but it's going to be the stable series of flat pack
The 0.10. Okay, and then you're going to have the fancy
0.11 which will get all the new features all the new
Yeah, so 0.10
The first one is going to be the first in a release of new
In a series of new releases that are stable new features will all be added to the 0.11
Branch and bug fixes will be back ported to the 0.10 branch
Which seems like a great way to put something in production but keep improving on it
And then maybe all those accumulate to like a 0.12 and you start having like a kernel versioning system
It's kind of impressive that they're already doing this sort of like a lot of projects takes a long time for them to get like a
Real development release workflow, but they're still at the you know
They're not even at like a real full release yet and yet they're they're doing this well. Yeah
Yeah, and um, we saw recently that the mint project is going in with uh
Uh flat packs because they kind of like the more ppa run your own repo
Uh solution than the centralized store solution and you can see how there could be different advantages to both
And and meanwhile the folks over at elementary os have put published an update on the state of the app center
So we had dan on the show dan
I mean was it how long ago?
Did you guys did you come on the show to talk about the app center was?
We did a special ages ago. Oh, I think I think it was maybe six months. I can't remember. Yeah six months and um
Uh now you guys have got over 50 apps and they're looking good. So what's going on with the app center? How are things?
Yeah, it's going pretty well
Um, like you said it's been about six months and we have uh over 50 apps now actually as of this morning
We have 58 apps. Oh, yeah in there
So yeah, i'm pretty excited about it
There's there's all kinds of cool stuff in there
I mean things that I never expected people to write and it's been really awesome to see like an explosion of native apps
Like they're not web apps or or cross-platform ports or anything like that. They're all gtk high dpi ready and
It's pretty sweet looking good on the desktop on the desktop, too
Um, so are you uh, are you are you talking all talking at all about any kind of the uh, money?
That's been made or if it's profitable at all or anything like that
Um, I mean I could I could give you some like little stats here and there. Um, I I
I want to be careful because there's people's privacy in question, right? And I don't want to everything's still new
Bust somebody out on how much money they make but um, I can tell you that
Um, nobody's making a living right now. It's still in the realm of like beer money
Um, one of the developers told me uh, it's enough that I could take my wife out to dinner. That's nice
I mean, that's really great. That's going from zero to that is really great
Yeah, so, you know it like you said it's going from zero to to something is you know, it's an improvement
But we you know, we still have a long way to go like our eventual goal
Is that we do want people to make a living so we've been talking to different people about um, you know
The kind of the problems that they have or what would encourage them to pay more
Uh, I know a lot of people want a flow for them to be able to pay later
So they want to be able to download free at first and then come back and pay
And the store isn't really good at handling that right now. You'd have to like uninstall and re-download
Okay. Yeah, that seems though. It seems like sort of that seems like a sort of a problem that other app stores struggle with
Yeah, definitely
Yeah, so that's something that we can be better at. You know, I was wondering as an end user. Um,
What are my expectations for when like, uh, like uh changes come to the app center?
Is it is that a release based thing like new releases of elementary os will have new app center
Updates with features or is it something's updated separately of the main os release?
And we're releasing updates all the time. We don't freeze application updates at all
Um, even for all our apps even like we we post a blog post every month where we talk about the updates we've made
And um our our average right now is that um,
The average app center app has received around five updates in the last six months. Gosh. You guys are doing great
Wow, these are some good stuff here. So I also noticed that it seemed like there was some interest in the app center, uh, by uh,
system 76
Yeah, so one of the things that um, we kind of set out to do when we built app center is making sure that we were
using all of open standards
And so that's awesome for system 76 because since we use package kit and we use app stream for our metadata
They can use our client in pop os and just do some branding work and they really like the way that it works
So they can really benefit as a downstream from this work
Cool, so they're essentially able to I guess white label it in in other words and uh, make it system 76 or pop os branded
Yeah, so they've got a couple of little tweaks in there and we've been talking to them about uh,
How we can upstream some of their changes maybe cool. Um, but I I guess the major difference between their they're calling it pop shop
um, the major difference between pop shop and app center is that um,
They aren't using our app center repository. So it's kind of just um a front end for the ubuntu repositories
Instead of uh our app center repository
I'm going to be really curious to see I want to play with that because it's probably a better experience than gnome software
I'll love to gnome software. You guys are doing great. Uh, but uh, you know
I've also played with app center and I found it to be a I don't know a better experience. I would put it
Um good for them and I wonder if we might see other distributions take that on too. I think that's a great idea
So i'm looking at the post i'll have a link in the show notes
Uh anything else you want to call out about the six month anniversary?
Um, just definitely that if you have an idea for an app, uh, you know
Or you want to get involved with either the front end of app center or the back end of the app center dashboard
It's written in node.js. It's all open source
Like we'd love for you to be part of this ecosystem and and there's you know
Tons of different ways that you can fit into it. Definitely and um,
I'm glad to see progress in like the right directions on some of several fronts on this. Uh, you're right
And just to reiterate you said it but it's awesome
I mean, it's not just like 50 more than 50 apps hitting an app center. It's 50 apps
Written for linux gtk plus high dpi ready fully native. Wow
Yeah, you know
I think one of my favorite things that they've done that a lot of the other app stores don't do is they have links
Directly to issue trackers. Oh, yeah
That's yeah, that's a great idea. That's really handy. Wow. Yeah, you know, that's been a big one because i've definitely watched people
Having that direct link i've been able to go file issues and developers are able to fix them really quickly and push out the updates
Like whenever they want we have a super tight feedback loop between users reporting issues and developers taking out updates to fix them
Yeah, if you guys are looking for an app to check out, uh, I suggest torrential, uh, which is a torrent app that I checked out
Awesome, just nice simple clean fast a good performance really liked it torrential and it fits right in on the desktop
It's it's a great experience and you know what when you guys launch it
I said it then i'll say it now i'm really glad somebody's doing this because I think if we can even just say
There's there's uh, even if elementary os proves out that there is interest in a linux consumer market. I think that's beneficial
So awesome guys. Well
Uh dan and i'll also say to cassidy because he was the one that wrote the or at least made the post over at medium a great
Work gentleman and great work for the whole team and great work to all the software developers, too
Thanks. Yeah, that's really good stuff now
Everybody knows that there's one threat to the human race that goes beyond nukes goes beyond rocks from space
I mean i'm not the one saying this it's elon musk saying it it's ai ai is going to doom us all
Ai is a fundamental risk to the existence of human civilization
um
in a way that
car accidents
airplane crashes
Faulty drugs
Or bad food were not they were not they were harmful to
A set of individuals within society, of course, but they were not harmful to society as a whole
um ai is
A fundamental existential risk for human civilization
Whoa, that is not mincing words at all
And so that is the context in which we view this next story at&t is working on an open-sourced ai project with
the linux foundation
Yeah
And it's going to be called the oh, I just the first time I realized I had to say it out loud akumas
akumas
A cu mos akumas akumas
Yeah, the akumas project which aims to be a marketplace of artificial intelligent apps and services
So linux foundation today announced that it's working on an open-source ai project at&t is one of the founding organizations
In my past experience this usually means that at&t is going to be the predominant contributor and therefore the driving force
Uh, we'll see something like hey, we have this stuff
We don't know how to shepherd or steward it. But uh, if you guys do we'll give you this big chunk of code
Well, it's sort of that definitely. Yeah. Um also hey, can you help us with a community aspect?
But it's it's even more than that
It's we don't think we can make a buck off the core technology, but we know we can make a buck off of ancillary services
and
services
So if we could get this thing to be a market winner
Then we would make a ton of bank, but we're not going to make bank actually selling it itself
So why don't we hand this over to linux foundation?
Because then people are willing to take it as a standard because it's not coming from at&t
And I would assume at&t is probably a company that could cook something up like this
Might actually be able to give google or amazon a run for its money
They certainly have a lot of yeah a lot of money resources that sort of thing
Yeah
But I think instead of like a core ai its goal is more like a platform is to enable a free exchange of ideas as they
Say and machine learning solutions, which is an interesting that would be interesting a marketplace and a platform for machine learning solutions
Using artificial intelligent frameworks you guys got your buzz bingo. Yeah, right
They want like tools for casual users not just data scientists
So maybe something that like we could actually go play with hey, you never know sticking apps
And microservices. There we go. I had to make sure we got the whole bingo. Oh, yeah, that's important
Oh that was this interesting development now
Here's the reality of it and they say this in the gadget post that we'll have linked
The project code will be available near to the platform's launch in early 2018
So maybe we might follow up on the story when that happens if there's some uh, yeah
They got like a real minimal landing page. You can go check out at uh, acumos.org
But the fact that they're even talking about this means that there's probably I bet you a pretty
Significant chunk of this thing developed if I if I were to wager how these companies work
They generally have almost the whole damn thing lined up and now it's really a matter of licensing partners
Branding marketing the new logos for the new name because there might be a name change now that they're making it a public project
And so they have all these old names in there and all that has to be done
Before they can actually hand it over to linux foundation and that's all the shit that's happening now
So the code's written
But all this other stupid bureaucratic crap is what's gonna take until then it can finally make its way to github or wherever
It's going to live right? Yeah. Yeah, and then either it will go nowhere
Or it may be successful, you know
I'm still watching the edge x foundry stuff that del contributed the linux foundation for iot and I actually think it's a great solution because
quick recap
it's like an iot firewall and it it it takes all your iot devices and
Manages them locally on your LAN and then of course can enable remote connections and stuff like that
But it's um, it's it's it's way more. It's way more privacy inclined. It's way more local
It's it allows you to build your own custom iot network using a set of apis and frameworks
They created that can enable alerting and automatic response and all of this and none of it's connected to the internet or cloud
it absolutely can be and you can even use remote services including the echo stuff, but um,
You can all run on the LAN and uh, that seems like that would be a thing
But uh so far I haven't heard a lot of buzz. They've had an update. They've had a big software update
it also seems like uh, these are the sorts of things that
They kind of go without buzz maybe because the people who end up getting adopted are right
Like I mean think there's part of a solution there. They are an implementation detail
They are not the product like think about uh open daylight when we went and checked that out
Like I hadn't heard a bunch about it, but then here's all these different people from different big companies using it
Yep, yeah
Because it's like it's how linus sees linux in a lot of ways linus says that linux is often just in implementation detail
Uh, it reminds me of the anecdote that when steve jobs, uh was still alive
He tried very aggressively to buy dropbox years and years ago and his pitch to them was
You should come work for us because you are a feature not a product and you will get replaced by the platform eventually
And uh to some extent he's right. You now have you have google drive. You have microsoft one drive. You have apple's icloud thing
But dropbox is competing
But just like that edgex foundry
And uh now this project. What was it akumas project akumas. There we go beards saying that he's the official pronunciation
It may just be an implement implementation detail for a marketplace or something
Just like linux is often an implementation detail for a mobile device for a phone
Did they say anything about what license is going to be? No, I don't know if you saw
Did you see anything on their holding page? It's definitely not in the news. No
No, and I don't know if I don't probably may not know until I get it up on github
Well, i'm just saying ant is popular with the bsd licenses
i'm, just wondering if we can connect the mycroft project with this with this project and have some sort of like
Like sped up sped up collaboration here where maybe solutions and and tricks could be built over in one spot
And they can be deployed to i'm just saying mycroft, please for the love of god mycroft
I don't know if I want a mycroft overlord
I'd take it more than an echo or a google or a any other one. That's for damn sure
I want it on all the things
You know what else is good for all the things linux academy if you want something for your linux box if you want to learn
about some of these cloud services
Cloud service eye is that yep, that's it when you're talking about multiple cloud services cloud service eye
Is that a thing or cloud survey?
Well linux academy can help you sort it all out. They got the right terms. I'm sure
I like that linuxacademy.com
Unplugged that's where you go to support this show and sign up for a free seven day trial
And a seven-day trial is going to
Pretty much let you get a good sense of their self-paced in-depth video courses their hands-on labs
Their learning paths if you want to go for a set course in your career
Their practice exams to get you ready for quizzes their certification training if that's your goal. You'll get a sense for some of that
They've also got virtual servers. They'll spin up on demand that matches your courseware
So say you chose debian, right then the virtual machine's also debian. I just love that feature
Not only do I love the feature, but uh, I that's when they were building that that's when we were really talking a lot
Uh before about them becoming a sponsor and oh man, they were so proud of that system because you got real linux geeks
At the core of this company real linux geeks
And then they worked with some of the best educators and developers to create this platform
And now they've got full-time human instructors when you need help
They got a community stacked full of jupyter broadcasting members that are vibrant and active and they can participate in the content to a degree
To like the flashcard systems forkable by the community
They have ios and android apps to let you study on the go and speaking of studying on the go
They also have lesson audio and notebooks and study guides you can download and well, you know
If you're doing that offline thing, it'll work just fine turns out paper has a great battery life
Who knew it's crazy and it's got a pretty good contrast ratio last millennium's technology
Linux academy.com slash unplugged linux academy.com slash unplugged you go there you get the seven day free trial and you support the show
Thanks to linux academy for sponsoring the unplugged program program program
Um, let's talk about uh, the intel me stuff just really quick. This is the management engine stuff
That's actually like an edison system. If you're not familiar with edison, that's like a x86 system on a chip
thing
It's actually fascinating because it originates from the 486 and then they've like modernized the 486
And this is what makes up the edison
So it's like a it's like the it's like the best things about the intel 486 with some of the best things about modern processors
Um for uh for crazy cheap price and a crazy even cheaper for intel
So of course intel has now built their management engine on more recent intel boxes off this x86 system
And this is a huge problem
Because that means your basic bitch hacker is now going to be able to poke at this thing
I mean i'm i'm i'm being a little generous but it's it goes from this weird esoteric architecture
Where there aren't very many debugging tools to rip this thing apart
And it requires these crazy hardware bridges to connect to it to now it's x86 code running on a pc
And it just fundamentally changes the game and I think i'm speculating here
But I think this is why google is now getting in the game of getting out of intel me
We recently talked about purism doing it now google's going even further. They've started the nerf project
It's short for the non-extensible reduced firmware and it's their effort to replace most of the uefi
Firmware with a small linux kernel and init ram fs and a custom portion of code written in the go programming language
That's right. Everyone you liked linux. We're putting linux in your linux. So double linux boot
Yeah, this is uh from one of from ron one of google's core boot developers. Uh, he was in munich. No minnick
Talk i'm horrible. I'm the worst person ever talking about their nerf project at this week's embedded european linux conference
So look that shit up nerf delivers linux performance and reliability in its firmware
Oh
Don't show that to alan jude. Oh my god. Don't show that to anyways as well
It also emulates all post boot activity of the uefi and more importantly the management engine
Rather than allowing it to run concurrently in the background, which that creepy son of a bitch is doing
Yeah, while your os is running. It's really awful. I really hate it currently
The nerf effort is focused on intel hardware hardware while the core boot developers acknowledge that the latest amd chips
Are closed up too and don't believe all you read about ryzen they say
Well, that's a bit of a bomb at the end. What does that mean?
I gotta say the slides for this they're they're posted here. They're definitely worth checking out
There's no video yet, but it's it's really easy to read through i'm very intrigued with this project
Yeah nerf also great name great name and it's fun to say. Yeah, it's it's really great
So he says that uh, he says it also has a 32 32x speed up and boot time
Oh because you can probably skip a whole bunch of shit
Because you can go from one linux kernel to the next
And just and kexec is already a thing that they're using. I wonder so and all the use
So all of the user lands written in go you eliminate all uefi uefi and all management engine post boot activity
yeah, they basically did a bunch of work and they kind of talk about it here to like identify every piece of uefi that
They could do without including like uefi has an ip tcp ip stack sometimes, right?
And a whole bunch of other stuff and it's like well, we already have this open source kernel that we use are using
All the time. Why not use this too and they're looking at it from the
Attack vector and and and control vector and not so much from the freedom vector
Which is interesting because they're still ending up with the same results to a degree
So here's they say the core problem. Yeah, according to the google developer linux
No longer controls the x86 platform between linux and the hardware. There are at least two and a half kernels
I'm gonna read that again because just wrap your head around that for a second
Isn't this reminding you of the baseband problem with your cell phone between linux and the hardware?
There are at least two and a half kernels. They are completely proprietary
And exploit friendly and the exploits can persist i.e
Be written to flash and you can't fix them. That's the core problem that google's trying to solve and
You know, they're really concerned about server security because they're looking at this not for desktops and laptops
They're looking at this for servers. Exactly. Uh, and then you're right. Jeez west. This is a super awesome
Uh, i'm looking at this, uh this presentation. Um
We can you toss a link to that in this section of the show because that is
That is worth reading. Okay, so we have just a couple more community updates before we can get into the interviews
And this story today's a breaking news story. I should have gotten like some sort of soundboard clip. The appeals court is uh, surprising us
Get ready for the story that has literally spun my in spawn span my entire podcasting career
It's this is unbelievable
Sco's back
Sco is back. No is back suing ibm in the appeals court. It's it's back on the sco versus ibm case
lives it's
Just done. So, okay. Let's recap last year us district judge david nuffers. God damn it chris
This is not your i'm gonna stop saying names for the rest of the episode has ruled against ruled against sco
um
In two summary judgment orders and the court refused to allow sco to amend its initial complaint about against ibm
We all said okay story's done sco's done this story. This is like a year ago where it said it's all done
But then sco soon appealed which didn't surprise too many of us, of course
But it happened and we've been kind of waiting around to see where this appeal is going to go
Well on monday the 10th u.s
Circuit court of appeals found that sco's claim of misappropriation
Could go forward while also upholding the judge's previous other two orders
so this is i'll get to it in a second is because it's kind of complicated but
If you haven't been following this story since march of 2003, I can understand. Um, I don't know why I have to be honest with you
So anyways sco then named then named caldera systems filed a suit against ibm in march of 2003
For allegedly contributing sections of commercial unix code that they thought they owned from the unix system 5
I think it was which the scope group was pissed and said you contributed that to the linux code base
There by sort of forcibly open sourcing it they argued that ibm essentially stole or misappropriated
Its proprietary code known as unix where system release 4
in the may 4 2001 release of the
Monterey operating system a new version of unix designed for ibm's power processors. It was incomplete didn't have a compiler
It wasn't like a complete
Um os and so sco claims that it was ibm
Uh, basically dumping to get the code out there on the on when ibm released that that same day, uh,
Sco argues that ibm released a sham version of the system in order to legitimize its own general distribution of the ax power product
Which contained sco's code?
They say that they what ibm basically did was did a sham release of an os that had their code in it
So that way when they later then released another os they could say but there's precedent
There's other operating systems out there. They're already shipping the code
We're not the first ones to do this, huh? And sco saying yeah, but you did that on purpose
Just so you could make that claim
And that's why we're still coming after you after all of these years
They're like, okay, well the judge can be right about all that stuff, but you still did a double dog trick
Back in 2001
Do we know if uh any of this any of this code still exists in its original form in the kernel
I would be curious. Well, no, no
There was like a serious like come to hasus moment where they went through and like cleaned out anything that might have been left
Who knows maybe that might have been some of the momentum behind system d2
The whole thing though is is like this zombie threat against linux
That is just sort of like it's one of those zombies that comes up at you, but doesn't have any teeth now
So it's just sort of gummy at your neck. It's not actually I don't know
It's actually but you're like, oh, it's a new accessory. Come on take with you. Just go just go zombie go terrible
Yeah
It's the zombies go and it's back zombies go is back
And they're saying that ibm double dog tricked them years ago by doing a sham release of an os
That way they could then do another release of another os that had their code in it that then ended up in ganu slash linux
Which was the original sin?
Everybody follow that good. So I want to talk a little bit about
our
Guests will cook is the ubuntu desktop manager and mr. Didrocks is I would say probably most publicly famous for his?
artfuls
Transition to gnome post he did 16 blog posts, which I will have linked in the show notes
I'll have at least the 16 and it was he was ubuntu gnome shell in artful
Every single sort of major decision was documented and we covered
Some of these in the show probably a dozen not that half a I don't know five of them
But there were some big moments we covered in the show
And we were currently going back to them and I really liked these posts because uh, there was something that microsoft did during
I don't when's the last time I complimented microsoft everybody microsoft did something really smart during the release cycle of windows 7
I wonder if you guys remember remember. She's sorry remember this
there was this like a insider windows development blog where they
documented every major decision towards the development of windows 7 and
Including like some big changes that would impact enterprise deployments and end users and gamers and they did this long
complicated technical series and even though I wasn't a windows user
I loved reading it because I really got an insight in the development of windows 7
And I think it really got the whole damn windows community for what it was excited about this release
And I still to this day believe was one of the things that contributed to its success windows 7 its success
In the enterprise because sys admins like me were reading that and we knew what was coming group policy wise
We knew it was coming with the smb signing. We knew what was changing with how the shares enacted all this stuff
Really kind of was just explained to us and it made it an easy adoption and I feel like to a degree
That's what didrocks post did for ubuntu 1710 in this transition from unity 7 to gnome and their idea to do with their
Their reasoning for their doc and how they did it the gnome mode. So I talked with didrocks about some of this
And uh, I think it's great and we get a great anecdote for him
And then after that i'll bring on will he he had to join us separately
They were going to come on together, but will got stuck at the office
And so after I wrapped up with didrocks will was getting home
So then will and I chatted for a bit
So we got two separate interviews that we're going to play and wills is really great because as the ubuntu desktop manager
He's in a position to answer some, you know
Rather poignant questions. And so I asked them and so i'm really looking forward to playing that for you guys as well
So let's take a moment
And let's thank digital ocean digital ocean is a sponsor right here on the unplugged program and they've rolled out so much great stuff
So I guess hacktober has wrapped up now as people are listening to this
Lots of good code went to open source
If you if you want to just go look at some of the projects that digital ocean
Helped code roll into go look at the hacktober fest page
They also provide a lot of back-end infrastructure for a lot of our favorite open source projects
They really do they do sort of quietly every now and then some of the projects might put like a logo on the page
Or something, uh digital ocean is just a great way to spin up really fast really powerful infrastructure in less than 55 seconds
And the pricing is just phenomenal. And if you use our promo code, you'll get a ten dollar credit. So go to digital ocean.com
Create the account and then use our promo code do unplugged one word
Put it all together do unplugged and that'll give you a ten dollar credit
My favorite rig is the one I use for my remote desktop system is three cents an hour
So that's just amazing and then I've attached 100 gigabytes of block storage which I use to hold what I call my work volume
Which is all the big like clips and stuff. I'm working on for work and uh, I i've
I've been really really impressed with how well that's worked because obviously these things aren't like built to be desktop systems
But hell if it's not super fast because everything's ssd. Oh, yeah, they got crazy great internet connection
Crazy great internet. So I always have the that transit man
I have the best doing like always when I'm wrote in I always know that the digital ocean
Droplet has the best possible connection and that really makes a difference for that
Um, the object storage is great for generating links to download stuff
Of course, I could I can only scratch the surface there and and all of it really kind of comes together with a dashboard
That's so great. I say it's a dashboard for days. It's you can you can choose from ubuntu freebsd fedora debian
Um centos and they have uh core os in there as well. You can choose data centers all over the world
Work with teams if you want and if you've never ever installed a server before it's easy
And if you've installed servers for the last 15 years
You're gonna love how they've managed to strike that balance and it's still easy
Like the thing that makes me smile every damn time I do it is the dns management in digital ocean
It's just or or actually really what really is tops is the ssh ssh key management. Oh, yeah
Oh, man, nobody doesn't like that. Nobody doesn't like that. And they're also uh rolling out their new spaces product
They're offering a couple of months for free right now and they have a great
Write up on what the hell object storage is how it works why you might want to use spaces
And how it could probably make your website faster to digital ocean.com
And then just use our promo code do unplugged one word you get a ten dollar credit
And you support the show and we much we much much appreciate it. Um, so there was a post recently
Talking about the canonical goals for 1804, which i'll have linked in the show notes
But we're going to get into that a little bit. Let's let's start with. Uh, mr
Didrocks, uh, I assume when I started talking to because he wrote all the blog posts that of course
He must be the man with the master plan. There was no even master plan
Yeah, actually in my conversation with him
It turns out that they weren't even really quite sure what they were going to do up until the point. They went to guadec
Like how far in are we going to go? Like how many changes are we going to make?
They knew they had some data like the they'd surveyed users and everybody wanted to dock
Everybody wanted thunderbird and firefox. So they had like an idea of what the users expected
But there was a moment
That we talked about on the show is one of the times we covered with this blog post where things really clicked for them
And that was they went to go to guadec. They they build up some contacts
But didrocks ends up having a conversation with a friend of his they just spitballing and and the guy goes hey, you know
There's this there's this gnome shell mode thing and you guys could implement all your modifications in this mode
And then people could just choose between them and that was sort of like the pivotal moment where I think development
For 1710 kicked up and he shares all insights here. Oh, yeah. Yeah, it's all based like we didn't, you know change anything in the core
You know like gnome shell, uh idea about theming or about, you know, adding extension
Like for the for the way we implement our session like adding the dock what you don't have by default on the gnome one
Uh, it's using what we call a gnome shell, uh mode
And so as part of the mode you can say this is the css. So this is a theme basically
This uh, those are the default extensions that we want to enable. Um,
And basically it was even you know, like based on a conversation with some friends, uh in the gnome community
Who told us oh you should do it that way
Yeah, that seems like a significant decision point for this entire project. Like it seems like when when the decision was made to implement
A gnome mode a session
Uh, it sort of was like a turning point in a way like how this was all going to be done. Is that true?
Yeah, exactly. Like, uh, yeah, so it was a little bit before even we decided
You know what we are going to do it was in july and I was just you know
Doing my daily exercise with a friend who is working on gnome and flat back
So we can see that we don't hate each other
And uh, and basically we just you know, like discuss about how how well in case you know, we are going to ship a doc
Or you know, what do you think because we are talking about tech, you know every time and say oh, you know
That there is this mode thing. Uh,
And this is how gnome classic is implemented and maybe you can look at you know
This and see if it works for you. And yeah, it did work. It did work even, you know
Way better than I was expecting
We we only have two or three distro patch in gnome shell changing the behavior like the alt-tab one that I explained on my blog
And two or three things on the sound notifications
But we made that depending on the session. So it means that if you are in the ubuntu session, it has this behavior
If you are on another session, it has a default upstream behavior
So the conversation meanders a bit and I get to 1804 with him and
There's a clear message from both will and didrocks here and it's the 1804
They really want it to be a rock. And so it's about polishing. So practically speaking
How do you go from that statement to actually making it happen?
And so didrocks says well, we're really going to have our qa
Focus on banging on gnome 3 the way we used to bang on unity 7. We're regearing our qa department now for gnome 3
We want as well with our qa team
To bring back, you know, the kind of quality expertise that we have
with unity in particular like
Running a lot of integration tests
So that each new uploads, you know are very work-solid
And so that we don't have to stress, you know as much as we did for 1710
They have a lot of automated testing
I'll be interesting to see if they can apply that to gnome, you know
Because then gnome could start seeing a bunch of great bugs and they can apply that to gnome
You know because then gnome could start seeing a bunch of great bug fixes
I was looking on the community page where will cook's starting to post our weekly roundup
They're working already practically on quite a bit of stuff. This made me think, you know, we were talking earlier about
Elementary and unity that there's something you know
Not to say that that like gnome or plasma don't have releases or anything like that
But there's something a little different when it's a distribution release, you know
There's a certain amount of like they understand that this is going to be the gateway
It's not just that it's to the whole experience and if they're going to get adopted or not
And so maybe there's a little bit different of an attitude and that's going to go up. Yeah interesting
Uh, so I got this anecdote from dinrocks
I really appreciate him sharing with us because I love this kind of stuff because it's nothing that's been posted on a blog or twitter
And um, it's kind of a significant development that came up 24 hours before the 1710 release
But the day before the release we found you know for first one guy telling oh, I don't have any more ui
Okay, and then we saw a second person, you know complaining as well. Yeah, they had ati cards
A third one a fourth one having nvidia cards and we started, you know, like to say oh
There is really something like a lot of people complaining no gnome shell crash
You know like before they had a ui and on that day, you know the update broke
and
Thanks to the very awesome french community. Uh, i'm i'm looking a lot on you know, the french forum being very involved with that community
And over the forum, we were debugging that
And I was asking, you know, uh, one of the impacting persons to revert, you know a lot of packages
And it was 24 hours before the release so you can imagine, you know the level of stress
Wow, uh and we found that it was the gnome shell update from 3.26.1
So from 3.26.0 to 3.26.1
This issue started to appear
So looking at you know all the commits and we saw that new features entered gnome and we saw that this
You know, oh potentially those commits are going to break
So preparing special packages, you know trying to revert some commits and asking over the forum to the guy, you know
To test it and the guy even was working and he went back home just to test this
So it's really awesome, you know dedication
Yeah, like I I can't thank you enough
And and once we found, you know the commits we were able at least, you know to ping upstream and they fix it, you know
very very, you know
Uh quickly, uh seeing what the issue, you know started to be but basically, you know
It's a lot of stress and and we just had a respin, you know on the day of the release
So people telling all this, you know, the isos are ready for a week already and you can download that it should be the final
No, it's not
Those are not final isos. So to this take this anecdote in for a moment, uh, 24 hours before the 1710 release
gnome
3.26.1 comes out and gnome 3.26.1
for some users starts breaking the graphical environment and this is the this is the
So they really gnome 3.26.1 didn't come out 24 hours release but 24 hours before release. They realized this problem has developed
Right. They've already got it on their iso, right?
So they've already got gnome 3.26.1 on the iso and they realized 24 hours before release shit. This is starting to wow
And it was thanks to a french community forum member
That didrocks was chatting with via the forum not a canonical employee
But this forum member who left his job and went home to help debug the problem
That they managed to find the issue
Get a fix written get the patch upstream to gnome gnome
Adopted the fix and they got that fix then repackaged up and pushed back down to 1710 in that day
So not only is it fixed but it was like fixed the right way and upstream. Yeah. Wow
I just couldn't even believe that when I heard that that's like the best because that forum member was willing to go home for the day
This is like a open source success story on steroids. I feel like canonical should like call that guy's
Office and give him like a doctor's note or something
Well, he's yeah, I mean I I say thanks to whoever that individual was
Yeah, I mean that really helps and it's it really does also show you in a weird weird like real way
How much of a community effort it still is at the end of the day?
You can talk about mark shuttleworth and canonical and and you can talk about the employees at canonical
But at the end of the day, thanks to a forum member in a french linux community. I just can't even believe it
It's it's just sort of
Uh, but it's so great because it is having worked in project releases like that the exact kind of thing that happens
It's those real human stories. Um
So I also asked him if he's going to continue to blog during the 1804 cycle because like I said, I've really enjoyed them
And he says he is he says that he'll be continuing to post updates
Um, and uh, he doesn't expect there'll be as many because there's really not going to be as many radical changes
It's going to be more like bug fixes and stuff. You know, they're trying to make 1804 solid not uh, not totally new but
um both
When I talked to will and didrocks, I got I got I got a sense that there's there is a um
Willingness to implement new features in 1804. So there could be new stuff that ends up showing up in 1804
Even though right now they're all talking bug fixes
uh, so
Now I want to talk I want to chat with will it's a we have these are a bit longer
Um, and um, I will uh, you know what? Let's do this. Let's take a moment
We'll uh, we'll we'll say we'll thank ting and then we'll get to will because uh will was a we don't want any
Chat and yeah, I just want to do the whole thing. So go go over to linux.ting.com. Yeah, that's right
Linux.ting.com you go there and you sign up for a smarter way to do mobile. It's it's it's
It's how they'd have to do it to be honest
If they had to compete today if the big duopoly's had to compete today, uh, it's how they'd have to do it
It's you just pay for what you use you don't prepay
for like 300 minutes and 300 text messages and a gigabyte of data or
Or a thousand, you know, you don't you don't just guess how much you're going to use
You just pay for what you do use. It's 23 for the average
Ting bill per line 23 bucks you pay for what you use
It's six dollars a month for each line if you want 10 lines at six dollars
Now I stop and think about that if you're a small business or even a kind of a moderately large family
Who else has those prices six dollars a line and then you pay for what you use? That's
I mean that's super competitive for a small business. It's a game changer
It lets us it lets us have mobility and coverage in a way that would cost us an inconceivable amount of money
Otherwise you go to linux.ting.com and you get 25 in service credit if you bring a gsm or a cdma device
Yeah, they support both just check their byod page or if you want to buy a phone, they'll take 25 off
They have great devices the whole range from budget phones flip phones sim cards only to uh, you know
The latest and greatest cadillacs and they really are just super simple to work with
It's uh, in fact, I really like their new strategy when when the beard over there was at twitch con
As uh, sort of like a twitch con swag item. They were handing out ting sim cards
And I think that just sort of perfectly encapsulates ting
It's like you just get the sim card and then when you need it you put it in something
And then uh, they'll let you use their mobile network, however you want and you just pay for what you do use
It's a really great way to do it. You go to linux.ting.com
It's it's my mobile service provider now for over two years linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring
linux unplugged
Yeah, so will is the ubuntu desktop manager and he just recently restarted the desktop weekly newsletter
Over at community.ubuntu.com where they covered some of the upstream fixes that they've been working with
And he has all kinds of things to talk about
I've been wanting to chat with will for a long time and he and I had a had a good chance to sort of
Chat on and off at the ubuntu rally
But I wanted to get him on the show because he's one of those guys where he has been around at canonical
And been following ubuntu well since forever and i've been using ubuntu for oh, I don't know
Well since the beginning stewart langridge of all people put me onto it
Um, I was playing around with debbie and and he said oh you should try this ubuntu thing. It's a whole lot less bother
And yeah, he's got like 11 year old uh an account over their launchpad account or something like that
and uh
He's now the guy that sort of manages the whole damn ubuntu desktop effort
And so I wanted to ask him sort of a question that's been kicking around in my mind
And that is did they just sort of screw the pooch by dropping unity because it was essentially theirs
Nobody upstream could tell them no they had a certain amount of difference
That was that made them stand out because they had this unique product and gave them certain leverage to implement
Goals that the company might have so if you want to integrate snap packs throughout the whole damn thing
Nobody would stop them from doing it to unity. So I asked will I said will
Is are you concerned that ubuntu has lost some of its leverage by dropping unity and switching to gnome?
I'm not concerned about it. Uh, I mean
there will need to be uh, these discussions about I don't know some of the
the usability that we think is suboptimal, uh, but upstream
Have a very clear vision about the way that they want to do it
So, you know, we need to we need to have those discussions in the open with upstream
And you know, we need evidence to back this up
Um, we do have a certain amount of research that was done in the unity seven days
Uh, and indeed the unity eight days to say, you know
This works and this doesn't so we can make all of that research available to to gnome designers and the gnome community and say
We think this is a good idea and here's why we think it's a good idea. Let's talk about it
Um, and you know
We're coming with with evidence showing one way or the other if it is ultimately against the the wishes of upstream then you know
That's that's the way we have to go because we are now working upstream
He actually reiterated that point later on he later on said yeah, if they do something that we're not on board with
Then uh, we'll just defer to their wisdom. We believe in this case and that's uh, that's a fascinating statement
Essentially, they're planning not to fight the current. That's a big that's a big move decision
Uh direction for you know a company to go that's a lot of trust in their upstream
And I also asked him kind of related. I said well, how have some of the hardware vendors responded to this?
You know what? I mean? And uh, his answer was essentially well for the most case they're shipping ltss, but
Uh for the second thing, uh in a way for them
It's it's less risk because now canonical is not solely responsible for the desktop product
And so the oems in a way
Uh don't really have that worry that it's canonical
You're not gonna get off the pot and uh ship something new or or we've got to start now. It's
They're they're not solely responsible for it defers the risk a bit for the oems in the long run
Was sort of his argument now I had I had a question that sort of been percolating from our discord chat room discord.me
Jupiter colony. We have a linux unplugged chat room over there linux unplugs chat room a reason why channel I guess they call it
Here's why I think this is a good idea you guys i'm mentioning this because if you're ever watching the video version
And you see a link go by or if you're listening and you want to hear what the discord room's response was
Now that we're breaking linux, we're gonna break all the shows off into their own channels
There's not going to be a ton of activity between this episode and the next one
So if you're here if you're listening to this in playback either in video or audio
You can go into that linux unplugged channel and see what the discord conversation was because there's not really going to be much else in there
And including links if you see something go by
So discord.me slash Jupiter colony and then linux unplugged as a channel for this show
And so one of the questions that's been coming through our discord a lot has been are they going to replace all the devs with uh,
with with snaps, um
Will said recently that they were are considering replacing the leaf quote-unquote applications with snaps in 1804
So, uh, I asked him, you know, what is a leaf application to deal with that?
And what role are snaps going to play in uh, 1804?
So we have the dev archive and that is not going to go away because there are flavors that are using it
Uh, a lot of the snaps are built on from from those devs
Um in that source, so, you know that it's not going to go anywhere
But we do want the to have the ability to to push out new and updated
Applications much quicker to our end users. We're not going to be a rolling release. You know, that's that's not going to happen
So the snaps give us the the freedom to push out updates quickly and it gives us the whole
Um ability to have various tracks and various channels so we can put something into testing
And people can very easily switch over test it and then switch back again if it doesn't work
so it gives us an element of freedom to
to move more quickly on a very
solid foundation of 1804 that the underlying os can
Can stay the same and all of the um, you know
The processes that we go through to make sure that only good quality packages get into that release. Um,
I see. So yeah the idea with snaps and the leaf applications. These are the ones sort of uh, the
The very tip of the tree if you like, um, these are going to be user applications, which are
perhaps less
Entwined in the in the underlying os so the likes of the gnome apps they depend on the gnome libraries
But they don't necessarily need to sort of dig into deep into the file system
Yeah, and so it seems like if it's a user space application that uh isn't necessarily overly integrated with the overall os
It could be a candidate to be snappified and then
Sort of like how android delivers stuff through the play store in a way. This is a rough equivalent
Uh canonical could deliver updates to applications
While not altering the lts base
Seems like a I mean it seems like a pretty good goal and that would be a good way to test it
But I my comment back to will was essentially that's huge
I mean, that's a huge objective for canonical that obviously makes snaps pretty critical to the future of the desktop into canonical
Um, aren't you a bit worried that this is going to frustrate?
Your upstream developers gnome that are creating your desktop now
Like you are now in a very precarious situation where the ubuntu distribution is pretty much married to gnome
And they're all in on flat pack and you're you guys are creating a competitor that could ruffle some feathers
Are you concerned about that? Yeah, I mean that that is definitely a very real risk
And we do need to be careful the way that we we navigate that
um
But ultimately, you know, we're not we're not blocking flat pack from being developed and distributing their apps in that way
Um, you know, you can get all the game apps as flat packs and you can get them all as snaps
So, you know, there should be a problem here
I thought that was a decent answer really because that's true at the end of the day. They're both
uh, essentially first class citizens on the ubuntu desktop
So you could if you want to run you want to flat pack it you can flat pack it
And uh, let let the market decide is essentially their approach there fair enough fair enough
So there's been some rumors go on afoot that unity 7 is not quite dead yet
That in fact, there may be a small
But not not insignificant effort
To continue unity 7 and to make it shippable for 1804
Yeah, and I want to know what the heck's going on here. Is this a canonical driven effort?
Is this a community driven ever? What is the story here?
A community driven thing. Uh, I mean we're obviously very welcome of people that want to step up and help maintain that
Uh during the 1710 cycle
We did take an interest in making sure that unity 7 still worked and and you know
wasn't completely broken and that
Is a is a statement that we will stand by in 1804
We will make sure that it doesn't just break horrifically and and then suddenly it is unusable
Um, what we won't be able to do is is any sort of significant feature development. It's in it's on 1604
So things like security updates and critical crashes these sort of kind of things
We are still on the hook to to make sure that those updates happen. So, you know if we're if we're in there
Um working on the code base anyway to to fix up things then
um
You know the the that will benefit 1804 users as well
You know if we upload I don't know let's say a new version of um xorg and suddenly it breaks
Um unity 7 the more people that are out there testing it the sooner
We know then the easier it will be to fix that or you know
Rather than six months later try and try and find what commit it was that that broke it in the first place
So yeah, i'm very i'm very keen to see people get involved in that
Yeah, there's a community organizing effort over on the community page and i'll have a link to that in the show notes
It's it's not insane actually because they already have to support it as you heard will say for 1604
so that the the security back porting bug fixing is
Not maybe not so much bug fixing unless it's something like a regression
Uh is still happening for 1604 because they have to support that for years
So why not also then make it available for 180 if that works being done totally, you know
like microsoft like makes security patches for xp but then
Hold on to them unless you pay
Yeah, it's essentially the opposite of that and um, I I kind of I kind of think it works great too because
Comp is itself
We've had wimpy talking to us a little bit about how compass itself is also still being maintained
And in in quote unquote not active development, but not also neglected. It's like still being worked on
It's still a product that gets tested and
It's getting better still. Um, so you have basically a vintage comp is compositor
Which has been pretty well worked out now over the years by a very intelligent very talented developer who uh, just blows me away
some of the some of the um video acceleration stuff I think is due to the compass the guy that also maintains compass and um,
Just incredibly talented individual
And so I really I guess I have a lot of I now that I now I know who he is
And i've met him. I have some faith in uh,
Uh that product and it seems like it's obvious that if unity is going to be maintained for 1604 that it's
It's probably a safe bet for 1804
And it's pretty damn reliable and it works pretty damn well
And so to me it was that that conversation there after I walked away i'm like why the hell don't I just use that?
Like I didn't switch away from ubuntu because of unity. I switched away because of arch
And uh, if I hadn't switched away, I would have still been using unity
So why not and it's going to be maintained for it for I mean
The l that 1804 is going to be maintained for five years. Yeah, totally
That's a ton of long time and I could switch back to gnome or plasma at any moment
And I have a ton of runway to let them work it out
That is where it's nice to be on a monkey right? Like not only do you get unity?
But yeah, you can switch to know just about anytime you want. I know you can get unity on arch
I tried I tried it's just it's not the same. Um, so there's there's there's sort of a bigger story here
And that is if you're I I hear this from the audience too if you're like, I I never really develop anything
I I don't do any translations. I I don't even submit bugs
uh
But I feel like I should do something and uh, maybe this is your time
Maybe this is your time 1710 is not bad to kick the tires even load it up in a vm as will says
And uh help file bugs if everybody could spend, you know an hour
In a vm testing something in 1710 and just log a bug report for everything they find then it means the 1804 is going to be
Just an excellent high quality solid reliable release
Um, we we can't do that on our own. We're you know, relatively small team
We can find the bump and fix the bugs that we know about so people can can tell us about these things
Then they will get fixed don't just hang out on um
comments on on forum posts and um
You know social media and that kind of thing moaning that something's broken. Please help us to to fix it
Yeah
And it's really not hard to file a bug for ubuntu and uh, it is sort of an opportunity to sort of contribute
Towards the next lts that could be more stable even if you're not a main daily ubuntu user
It's a nice way to help out open source and the gnome project and maybe wayland
Uh, so check that out. We'll have links to ways to help out and the community stuff in the page
It really seems to be in the show notes. It really seems to be their focus is making 1804 great again. Oh, I did it
Oh god, sorry. I'm sorry
Anyways, I really appreciate both didrocks and will coming on the show. It was great to chat with them
Yeah, that's great. And it was it was nice to sort of mark. Um a really um, I mean
Damn, uh, uh, what do you call it? Uh, hercules effort. What is that herculean? Thank you
That really was what seemed like 1710 was especially when you consider
They started out they didn't quite know going into it how far they were going to go
Like where was the line? Where do we draw the line from? This is unity now to stock gnome 3
They didn't know where that line was. They didn't know what their doc solution was. They they ended with a
A great anecdote where a community member saves the day by helping troubleshoot
And then upstream kicks ass by cooperating in record speed. Wow
Did you see this week that the gnome project had a little gnome loves, uh, ubuntu on their front page
I don't know. Yeah, I don't know if it's still up there, but they were they were welcoming 1710 users
That was pretty I did not expect to see that
Didn't I don't know if it's still up there or not, but oh it is still up there. Look at that
Yeah ubuntu plus gnome equals love. Oh at gnome.org
How far we have come well what happened to the big red hat conspiracy
Anyways, it's great to see it and um now i'm all now I now i'm
Now i'm some sort of unity hipster and I I hate it. I hate it because I know people are going to give me shit
Um, but i'm all in and i'll link you if you're if you are too if you want to stay here
Uh, you know what unity 7 is the new xfce i'm calling it right now. And I also am going to predict here on this show
episode
221 that there will be a unity 7 respin of at least 1804 if not 1710 eventually
That if this takes off and you even get a few people contributing
And the fact that canonical employees are going to be contributing as part of their maintenance of 1604
Why wouldn't you create a respin? Everybody loves making a respin. Yeah, totally
Maybe and maybe even it'll have first class support someday call it pop. Oh, no, i'm kidding. Um, oh, oh ouch
But I really think somebody could come up with something like this like a respin and uh, it might have some love
Yeah, maybe they're uh, maybe unity 7 refugees will end up on unity
We should name it. That would be really if anybody in the room anybody in the room good coming up with names
Because that'd be a really good one. Hello. Mr. Wimper. It's nice to see you pop in
Hello, i'm good at names. What do you think if somebody i'm calling a prediction that somebody
At least with 1804 maybe during 1710 cycle
But I think with 1804 is going to release a unity respin of ubuntu unity 7
Let's call it unity 8
like ate or like what like
No unity. No unity 10 unity 10, dude. You gotta go. What do you think wimpy? What are they gonna call that distro?
It's a unity 7 ubuntu
Well, I mean it's funny you should mention this because i've just sort of pitched in on their thread on the ubuntu community
hub to say
If they're seeking to make a there are a group of people that are gearing up to do this
You know if they're seeking to make an official flavor, I will help guide them through that process
And i've been thinking about names. I've not mentioned this to anybody but they could go for
For the ubuntu unity remix whilst they're, you know working through that process and then it would become ubuntu unity
But I thought to myself I quite like ubuntu united
That's good, too
I think uh, well, I think it's going to be ubuntu unity probably just for clarity clarity. I bet I bet you
Yeah, so the new naming scheme is sort of ubuntu and you know desktop environment or application
So, uh, my prediction is pretty on point then it would seem
uh
Wow, I would really I would really like it if they took you up on that offer
You have the bandwidth for that because uh, that's very generous. I don't know
I just not to repeat myself in the show
But um i'm going all in on unity 7 on the studio machines
And so i'm really i'm really glad to hear that
We just played a clip from will where he said that they're gonna there's be some level of support into 1804
Which really kind of sealed the deal for me?
Yeah, and you know, I I contacted will earlier and said, you know, I was gonna
Offer my assistance and i've found out that other people at canonical are already
also offering their assistance to sort of coach and guide this group of
um
Uh would be distro maintainers to get them orientated
So I think there's a good chance that this could happen because all the right people seem to be prepared to
You know lend extend a hand to to help them get started. So it'd be great to see it's a genuinely good product
Just it's it's a good product. Um, it's in the sense that you can appreciate that
It's well thought out it performs. Well, it does its job and it stays the hell out of your way
And then it does other things that I appreciate as somebody who gets impatient as it the there seems to be
Uh, and I have not confirmed this but noah's told me a subtle transition in the animation speeds as you continue to use the desktop
The animation speeds at a certain point speed up
Once they figure okay, you've gotten the idea
Yeah, that is some brilliance right there. That is some damn brilliance
There's a lot of thought and design that's gone into unity. And the other thing is is that it is still current
So, you know high dpi and all of those good things are all taken account for and when I when I wrote my email
I introduced on my my post on the community hub
I introduced myself for those those who weren't familiar and sort of basically said, you know, I have some experience in preserving a desktop
For the users that love it
And I did want to go on a bit further and and you know talk about that
But I decided to keep things brief, but you know, I wanted to say, you know, unity 7 is a great project to
Preserve because it's up to date right now
there's only one thing I can think of that they might want to consider doing to
um, you know bring unity 7 up to date with sort of contemporary stuff and that's to use lib input as opposed to the
Synaptics driver and other than that, you know, it's pretty much there
um, so yeah, it's a great project to to
Build a new flavor around or it continue a flavor around
I think it's going to happen and I hope it does because I hope so too
Have you seen that there's some nice iso spins from a couple of projects on source forge? No, I didn't know
That's a thing already. It's all yeah, so there's there's a 1710 abuntu unity iso and it's it's a proper job
It's been really well done. So I believe would you be able to toss a link to that in the unplugged discord channel?
A bit later. I will i'll have to go hunting and find it. Sure. I would love to see that that's fascinating
That's happening fast. Wow. Yeah, we should dig out the old um
the old docs that the design team did because they did some
They had a whole lot of extra features that were planned for unity, but never got done for various reasons like resourcing mostly
but there were
Some really nice stuff that they came up with that. We just never got around to doing. Hello. Maybe they could um, hello
Use inspiration. Yeah, uh, yeah
Will was talking too about maybe sharing some of the unity 7 usability research with uh with the gnome group, too
Um, cool
I uh
I'm really glad you guys are here because this is going to be the episode where I get flamed for being a unity 7
Hipster for like this i'm going to get labeled after this. So i'm glad you guys are here as a support group for me because
Uh, well, it's it's good that you're in at the ground level chris. Yeah. Yeah, I am apparently dude. I'm using it right now
It's my main desktop. Me too. Me too
Me too. I've reloaded five systems since last week's episode with ubuntu 1604
1604 and unity 7
And I put them all in landscape
It's been going great
I really like it. It's the it's so far i'm only i'm obviously only one week into it
I don't know if unity gets to be called hipster anymore. I think it's I think you're a unity oldster chris
Yeah, you know the uh, i'm a big proponent of cockpit as well. I think that's a great product for fedora. Uh, but um,
The landscape product is nice because you got a couple of tiered options here
You get yourself hosted which costs a little more but then you run the server yourself
Or you can go with the service version, which is like five dollars a month or whatever and it does everything I need
You know, I just go to I go to landscape page. I log in I get a quick overview of all the systems
I mean
That's that's it. Basically give it takes it from uh, kind of a mishmash
Everything's sort of before we had solace. We had ubuntu we had two arches
um
We had a couple of ubuntu 1710s
Uh, you know just kind of just a boy that sounds like madness
Even even though like linux is the whole thing that we're doing right? Like what show is this?
But like just that's that's a lot of administrative overhead for one studio for no real reason. Yeah, it's just sort of all over the place
and um
You know mostly was driven by application availability, right?
Like a year ago, um, which is just not the same issue today. It's so nice
Um, and so yeah, it was a great time to purge
It takes time going through and resetting up all these systems
There's so many little fiddly things you got to do and you have to be able to like
It's not like you can leave it off at any one stage you need to get far enough that you can like
Still do the next show that you have to do. Yeah, i'm gonna also say
Since i'm just since i'm already all in I think the unity launcher is still superior to any other doc implementation
That i've used first of all, it doesn't take a shit, which is nice a lot of a lot of linux docs out there do
uh, but it it has
Good progress indication, but I really like the wiggle bounce thing because that really is a nice subtle, but then it stops
It's just it's just a solid and then you hold down the super key and you get like the numbered execution
There's a there's oh, yeah, that is nice. There's just a crap ton of keyboard navigation possible in unity 7, which uh
Makes it really quick for me to do it on air. So if I wanted to uh
Uh launch spotify to play music like during the post show
I hold down super and I super 8 and spotify launches
And uh, then I hit fn play and it just starts playing
And then I get playback control in a drop down menu that I can use from the other virtual desktop that i'm on
Super right. That's great. It is. Um, there is many things about it that I I really appreciate the like control alt
numpad to uh, kind of quick tile windows
I use that all the time to work and also I do feel like speaking of that. I do feel like the uh,
Uh the desktop the the virtual desktop whatever you want to call this this this this this
This expose out or whatever you want to call it and then move windows around is is butter smooth
It's the it's the smoothest the zoom in zoom out move around
The way it works is butter smooth and then there's other things about this that I that gnome 3 has just gotten
Um with the with the new 3.26 release
That unity 7 had the entire time like the fact that you can snap a window to the edge
But then resize and drag it. Oh, yes, and yes, and I don't know what they're doing differently than other desktops. But um,
My windows
Just I don't know
It's like things are fitting better
Like I snap something and there's like still space for telegram to fit on the screen and telegrams fits proportionally
And it's just it's just like it just it just works and I don't have to screw with it
And it's all done beautifully and smooth and I should really stop now because i'm probably driving people crazy
But I I haven't used unity regularly as my main driver for what how long did I go? Did I switch to arch?
Uh three years now three four years. Yeah, and so I have not used I mean i've used it as an appliance
We have a machine over here
I poke at it
I set software up
But I don't sit down for a six hour work period and just use it right and that's where I had started having these
Holy shit moments where i'm like, oh, yeah
I
And you know what? I started members like oh, yeah
I used to I used to do a lot of work under unity 7 like this was the desktop I took to my clients
On my system and I sat down and I used this one. This is the one I got all my work done
This is the one where i'd work on dozens of servers at once like oh, yeah, that's right
This is a super kick-ass productive desktop environment
And it's smooth as hell
So to be fair
It's smooth as hell in 2017 with 2017 hardware when it first came out in like 2010
It was
It was when it first came out. It was built for netbooks. So right. Yeah, it was like really not not a competitive product
But it got it really it really got there
And you know, I took three years off from using it
um
When I kind of stopped using it was when the search stuff was all kind of like getting everybody all worked up about the ads
and the results and all the amazon results and all that and how it was proxied or if it was hdbs and
That whole thing was around the time
I just sort of switched to gnome anyways, and I haven't really gone back since then for any significant amount of time
And um, that stuff's all gone now. It's off by default. It's clean, you know, it's
Not a problem. It feels like you could have played a richard stallman sample at that point
I know you know what if my soundboard machine hadn't crashed earlier today. I would have that
I think he's finishing our burgers from earlier
We did have a little five guys earlier today and he does love those fries richard stallman loves those cajun fries
I won't speak for him otherwise though. Yeah. Anyways, so I guess i've waxed poetically enough about a desktop
That's eventually going to die and that nobody really wants to use anymore and has caused much political grief
In the linux ecosystem. It sounds like something that people really love listening to so I should probably stop
But uh, I would love to have you join us come over to jblive.tv next week
This is the week that next week the next episode
222 is the one where we where we here in the states make the daylight savings transition daylight savings. We're slow now
Yeah, so we're a week behind wimpy and poppy and uh, we will catch up to them next week
So check jupiter broadcasting.com slash calendar if you're a live attendee remember now, we have that linux unplugged channel
Yeah in discord
So if there's a link that gets tossed in there during the show or somebody says something you can go back after the fact
And look at it, but we'll generally try to put everything in the show notes, too
So you don't even have to worry about it go to jupiter broadcasting.com and look for episode 222
Something else I haven't mentioned in a little while is we have a telegram group for the community
I think you can just go to jupiter broadcasting.com slash telegram. Will you double check that for me?
You go there and it'll forward you to our telegram group
So i've been mentioning discord a lot recently
I should give a plug for that and then last but not least we have good old classic reddit linux unplugged dot
Reddit yep, that works just perfectly jupiter broadcasting.com slash telegram. Thank you, sir
Thank you very much. Check out more of wimpy and poppy over on the ubuntu podcast
Uh, they have always a great release at about around 30 minutes, which is great. I love that's my new favorite podcast length
These days because I get a few in there. Mm-hmm, and they always have something good going on
I think you know some command line love or uh, they did their ubuntu 1710 review recently so you can catch all that over
podcast
Halloween special coming up in two days
Oh spooky
You can get more west pain over at the dex net program
Yeah, please do check out him and uh dan breaking it down every single week on tech snap
And you can get more beard at what rec.net. Yep. I love that. Me too. Is it rekd?
Damn, dude
That feels like it's impressive. That's that's almost as good as star trek sexy
Which is the domain I own and i'm the most proud of star trek. Wow. I ever launched a star trek show
It'll be an easter egg. Does it just forward to jb for now? I don't
I you damn it really should I don't think I am an idiot. I should do that. Maybe i'm just too busy podcasting
I hope you join us for the next one
After that, maybe i'll get to that star trek show one day in the meantime
I'm, just gonna watch some star trek i've been enjoying that i've been enjoying that star trek, you know
We'd love to see you live next week
But if you can't we have rss feeds where you can subscribe to every single damn episode
You can find all of that in the show notes. Also check out me on the twitters. I'm at chris las
You can check out my vlog where we got a new solution for our power
Oh, yeah youtube.com slash chris fisher and the network at jupiter signal on the twitters where you get announcements news updates
And things like that. Thank you very much for joining us. We'll see you right back here next tuesday
So
All right, let's see if we can't title the son of a gun
Let's see if we can't title this. Mr. Chris. Yes, sir that uh, that gen 2 compiling you were doing. Oh shoot
I forgot all about that. We ran out of time. Well, it also scrolled up your discord chat. So you're behind. Oh, you're right
It did you're right that gentoo. That's what I can't ever tell what's happening. That's what happened
Damn, that's so the whole chat didn't move for the whole show
Look at that because I was busy building gentoo i'm beginning to come to the conclusion that the gentoo challenge is still on
But eight weeks later, you're still compiling the software that is so you've got something to talk about this week
We've never done compiling that software legitimately. This is that is true for this week
Every time we finish compiling this updates the things. Yeah new version the chromium comes out back at it. Damn it
It's been hard to fit it in, you know, uh, uh, I I feel bad about the chat room because uh, I had tabbed off
Yeah, you know, that's what should we interrupt you in case because you usually only
No, it's not really great to have because it sort of breaks the flow of the show for me to do that
So there's not a really great answer other than me just staying on top of it better
Really the best answer is is to take advantage of obs and discord that can you know?
Do some sort of api magic a little shake a dake and uh, so I can bring it up and do it
Yeah, well, well, yeah, so we don't need to be window capturing really we could do it other means
It's just you know, that's our old system and we just quickly switched
Um, so what do you think guys? How do we name this bish?
You can do bang suggest in either and I will check bang suggest in the irc
We'll put it up on the titles page. Otherwise, i'll just search for bang suggest
Um, and we're gonna have to get that fixed. Yeah, you know, we're just kind of waiting
You know because searching for bang suggesting the chat room works too because the search is pretty damn good in discord. That's a good point
I installed the discord maybe a few days ago. It's interesting so far. I've never used it before other than
This oh, yeah, you can also use the web app if you don't want to install an app
And it's just basically about as functional. Yeah, that's what i'm using right now. Yeah
As I right click I definitely see it's html5 ish. Yeah
Yeah, i'm using a fancy snap pack mutiny os. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Well, there's also a snap of it
Uh, if you just want to keep it all
All put away. So is it going to be a
Irc replacement as I saw the stream. I was trying to find the stream chat
I don't know if it's a replacement i'd say it's an alternative which seems to be better suited for live production
So we still have the irc room too because uh, you know
There's still like you can still hang out there and chat with people
The discord though is kind of great because we can break it out into particular shows and categories
We can do voice and chat it supports like images and previews
Which is gives some people something to look at when they're watching the video version
That is really sponsor are easier and clearer nice patreon integration patreon integration all that shit
So it's nice for from a live production, but if you know, you just want a basic chat the irc still works
Um mutiny times man
So something that talks is there a way to talk? Is there a way to put the fact that we have two great guests?
In the show in the title. I mean that seems like that what we should lead with because we have to oh, yeah, that's true
Um ubuntu double header
Double fisting ubuntu. No will was great will was great because uh, I could ask him did you have willow?
Yeah, because we we weren't around because we were recording ours because of time zones. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah will came on and um,
I think I got some really good questions that I think it's a pre-record with will and did that wasn't it? Yep
Yep, and uh, it was and I did that. Um
A lot too. I don't remember. I did that actually friday. I can't remember now
um, and uh, so I asked will about um, you know, like snap stuff and
You know pissing off upstream gnome and things like that and he had great answers
He just didn't he just and the good you just really did a great job and didrocks had some great stories and shared an anecdote
That's really great. It was just really fun to talk to those guys because they're they're um, what about hard workers inside?
ubuntu inside
Ubuntu a team ubuntu a team. I like that. It's not bad. That's not bad
Ubuntu a team also talk. Does that also apply to unity? Can we can we derive two meanings from that?
Maybe i'm really going to get some shit for this episode, especially from all the people that are running arch
And they're really going to hate this aren't they?
It's a little switch to open to now
The dda team dda team
That's how you say his name dda. Yeah
I just stuck with didrocks. I didn't fuck that up because i'm sick of that
I had enough of that this episode everyone calls him didrocks to his face. Yeah. Yeah, I was cursed this
This was the episode from hell for me. You