Did I miss all the media server discussions the last couple of weeks completely?
We have had some on and off.
It's sort of like a project I have been working on because I want to do a review for the Linux
action show and I've been kind of going through Open Media Vault, Rock Filer, of course FreeNAS
I'm familiar with, so I kind of just, I'm bringing some of that into it without actually
currently, I mean I currently use FreeNAS but I'm not currently installing it, and Open
Filer I believe.
Did I say Open Filer?
That's what we agreed you weren't going to look at.
Which has all been whittled down to Open Media Vault just simply based on looking at either
the fact that what their technology stack is or how long they've been since they've
been updated or what Wimpy's been poking me about that's gotten me excited, you know all
those things factoring.
But actually legitimately looking at it all it seems like Open Media Vault has the best
trajectory and long term sustainability for a project like this which is exactly what
I want for my file server and I like the folks behind it and I like the whole stack and I
like the community so Open Media Vault is the winner so now that's the one I'm going
to focus on for the review.
And I have a basic, basic setup on a NUC right now, an i7 older generation NUC but
it does have USB 3 attached to a 3TB RAID 1 disk setup over USB 3.0 and that's also
connected to a, what are those called, a UPS which I'm hoping to test like Open Media Vault
support for that which I haven't gotten to yet, I haven't actually hooked it all up.
It supports that, that's how I run it.
Yeah and I want to just test that all and then I also plan to test how much power it
draws and all of that stuff.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 159 for August 23rd, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux podcast that's broadcasting from all over
the world right here, right now.
My name is Chris.
And I'm Angela.
Hello Angela.
Hello.
It's great to have you in studio.
A couple of people will be joining us this week to keep us grounded, to give us the new
user's perspective but fear not, Mr. Payne's reporting in from the field on location.
Hello Wes.
Hello everyone, it's good to be here.
Hello hello.
So we have a great show lined up today.
We got some big open source project updates to give you, of course, Linux cons going on,
there's a bit of interesting tidbits that came out of that.
A couple of gentlemen from the elementary OS project have stopped by to tell us what
they've got cooking.
Later on in the show, I'll tell you about some of my woes.
I know I love myself the rolling release, but I think I finally got bit this morning
in the worst way possible.
I'll tell you about that coming up in the show.
Then later on, LibreVault, it promises to replace BitTorrent Sync and Syncthing, bring
the best of both of them to one GPL3 based project.
What is it and why do we keep talking about it and is it actually feasible?
LibreVault gets a little test today and will give you our report.
And then later on in the show, the new version of Android is out, Marshmallow?
No more.
It's all about that nougat now.
I've got it loaded.
I'll give you my first thoughts and why I think it's damn near time I switch to Ubuntu
Touch.
That's right.
I'm actually, you know, the thing is every now and then you got to reassess and that's
the phase I'm at.
So I'll share that with you guys.
But first, we got to bring in our virtual lug.
Some appropriate greetings, MumbleRoom.
Oh my gosh.
Powerful stuff today.
Oh, I feel kind of violated almost.
You all right, Ange?
That is a room.
All right.
So you guys have all heard the big news today.
Microsoft's got you scratching your heads with the announcement of PowerShell coming
to Linux.
GNU slash Linux is now the home of PowerShell.
First it started with.NET and then of course the next domino to fall was the.NET base.
PowerShell.
Microsoft obviously reaching out to system administrators that have to manage Windows
boxes from Linux boxes and as your enthusiast, but I have to tell you, every time Microsoft
makes a move like this, I kind of sit here and go, what's next?
What is next?
It started really with.NET and then Visual Studio Code and now this.
And I thought for a second here and I thought, holy, holy crap.
Did Microsoft just become one of the biggest proprietary companies in the world to figure
out how to make money on open source?
Oh, that's a thought.
Kind of.
Right.
We always talk about how do you make money on open source.
Meanwhile, Microsoft comes along and they figure out how to actually sell software as
a service via Azure and then how to use open source as sort of its backup dancers to bring
people into its platform and generate revenue.
Who would have thought?
Microsoft.
It's fascinating to watch them do this.
Wes, have you messed at all with PowerShell?
I've written some things back in the dark days when I had Windows machines to support.
Thankfully not anymore.
It's kind of an interesting environment.
You get all the.NET goodness.
A lot of people talk about how cool it is to pass objects around in the pipeline.
It's kind of got a neat, you get class-based things.
You have all the access to the.NET stuff and at the same time, you have what you might
call function composition where you can pass things to each other.
You don't have to parse text.
You can just get properties of objects.
That's neat, but personally, I'm kind of more interested in Python or other things like
that.
I don't see that much of a need, but for interoperability and working with Windows tools, definitely
it's far better than the Windows command line.
Mr. Tonell there has to…
I totally agree with Wes.
What's the point?
Python exists.
Bash exists.
As a system admin, I don't need PowerShell.
I think Ange could tell you.
So Ange, picture this.
Here it's me.
We were just talking on the pre-show back in the bad old days when I had to use Outlook
under Crossover Office.
I would do whatever it took to be able to manage the Windows systems I was responsible
for from a Linux desktop.
And for me, if I could have had a Linux-compatible Windows automation tool where I could have
wrote scripts for Windows systems from my Linux box, I totally would have jumped on
that.
And so I think that's who it's for.
I kind of agree.
Go ahead.
Ansible?
Yeah, I know.
Right.
And I think that's where, I think that's why this move is necessary for them to keep
this tool relevant.
Great.
So it's doing what Microsoft have always done, it's reacting.
It's not being this trailblazer that you make them out to be, it's reacting.
I don't know if I mean to make them out to be a trailblazer so much as I am sort of
in awe of the fact that they keep doing this and I just don't know where it's going
to end.
That's fair.
That's the story that fascinates me about it.
I think you have to acknowledge that this is without a doubt about revenue for them
and they wouldn't be doing it without it, without that motivation.
They're not doing it for – they're not doing it for RMS purposes, right Mr. Tunnell?
Yeah, they're selectively listening to RMS.
So like showing that you could give away the software and use the services to make money
like RMS has said for years but then you know, also proprietary and everything else.
Yeah.
So – but you know what?
In some weird kind of way, I think it's actually better for a company like Microsoft
that it's the bottom line that's forcing them to do this and not some moral rationale
because leadership as we've seen at Microsoft changes.
Board members can make things move around.
There's corporate restructuring that's happened.
There's many layoffs that happen at Microsoft.
CEOs even come and go over time at Microsoft.
If it's a moral sort of community imperative that's driving them, that could easily change
with the next CEO or the next board or –
You can't argue with the bottom line though.
Exactly.
Very well said.
Yeah, it keeps a company like Microsoft in the game because their livelihood depends
on it.
It's also a good example of showing how the open source system – like the open source
software works in a way that a lot of people say it doesn't because you can't make
money off giving away stuff and like when –
A lot of people – you mean like Microsoft has said, like Microsoft has said for a long
time.
Right.
That's true.
Yeah.
Well, I was referencing like people who were like regurgitating what Microsoft says but
the fact that Microsoft is changing their tune is maybe a way to show that everybody
else that – there is a reason why open source works.
I don't know –
Chris, I kind of think this relates to my prediction that I made a long ago about Microsoft
and Canonical and that because if you think about it –
Are you foreseeing a merger here, a marriage of two companies?
Yeah, especially after the release of Ubuntu 17.04 which will be the last in alphabetical
order and that will be Z.
And then after that, because Mark's run out of letters, he's going to call it good?
Yeah, pretty much.
You know what?
It's just a double A.
Yeah.
You're right, Mr. Lou.
Maybe you're right.
I've heard crazier theories.
There's still A and C which haven't been filmed yet so there's a couple more releases
to go.
This week is the 25th birthday of Linux.
Happy birthday, Linux.
I'd play the jingle but it would get us pulled down.
I know the Linux Foundation as they do likes to note the occasion and they've noted a
couple of things that are interesting, 13,500 developers from more than 1300 companies have
contributed to the Linux kernel since the adoption of Git made detailed tracking possible.
Now that is something else.
5,000 developers from 400 companies have contributed to the kernel.
Nearly half these developers contributed for the first time.
The top 10 organizations sponsoring Linux kernel development since the last report include
Intel, Red Hat, Lenoir, Samsung, SUSE, IBM, Google, AMD, Texas Instruments, and you guessed
it, ARM.
Oh, I didn't hear Microsoft in there.
You know they actually did show up on the radar for one year.
Really?
Yeah, they did.
They were contributing to making the drivers for Hyper-V. The rate of Linux development
continues to increase as does the number of developers and companies involved in the process.
The average number of changes except in the Linux kernel per hour is point or 7.8 which
is up from 7.71 in the last report.
What is kind of not really said here but is fascinating is and I guess I'd kind of be
curious to get the Mumble Room's take on this, predominantly the contribution to Linux
kernel is corporate sponsors, companies.
Does anybody have any qualms about the fact that predominantly all of Linux is developed
by commercial companies trying to make money off Linux?
Chris, this is kind of not really but in order to say happy birthday to Linux, I only have
one thing to say and I say it in the chat room a lot whenever he's brought up.
All hail King Linus!
And the value of this is negative.
So okay, go ahead Mr. Bitton.
And to celebrate the Sphinx Linux Foundation told on their keynotes on Thursday people
are going to have a black tie or a penguin or a Linux related shirt.
I wish we could have gone.
Toronto though kind of made it unfeasible for us to go but yeah, they've been doing
the keynotes.
There is a live stream and you've been watching it.
Yeah, at least one or two hours.
I've been busy with work but I watched the first ones at least.
And anything jump out at you?
Any kind of impressions you took away?
I haven't really think that much about it.
Yeah, I guess that's what struck you, huh?
I only had time to watch an hour, I was too busy and stuff.
Yeah it was just a little expensive for us to go but I would have liked to have attended.
It's always fun to be able to go to those events.
I did make it last year when they had it in Seattle.
That was good.
It wasn't just too long ago.
All right, so we are going to chat with the gentleman from Elementary OS here in just
a moment.
They've got something pretty cool they're working on and you may have seen it go by
if you've been watching the Twitters or the Reddits and we're going to talk to him about
it.
But first, I want to talk to you about my mobile service provider and that's Ting.
Go to linux.ting.com to get a $25 discount off your first device or if you bring a device,
you'll get $25 in service credit.
Now you could probably scrounge up a device because they support CDMA and GSM.
You just go to their BYOD page and find out which ones are supported.
They're on a mission to really make mobile simple.
It's just your minutes, your messages and your megabytes.
You just pay for them individually.
What you use is what you pay for at $6 for the line plus Uncle Sam's dirty take like
he always does.
He's got his hand in your pocket, that Uncle Sam and it's really straightforward.
Your customer service is amazing.
They've got regular human beings that are geeks that you get to talk to.
You've got an incredible control panel and Ange, did you hear about the big news for
Ting?
There's big news afoot, Ange.
They've dropped their data prices on Ting.
Did you hear about this?
Oh, that's great.
Yeah, check it out.
It's kind of a big deal.
So they've now gotten competitive across the board with just about damn near anybody.
Pay for what you use wireless is a great model.
No gimmicks, no leather jackets required.
Data is now cheaper on Ting.
From now on, prices look like this.
Need more?
It's just $10 a gig.
That's what new customers pay, that's what current customers pay.
It's simple.
We like simple.
See for yourself at ting.com slash rates.
So they're doing $10 per gigabyte beyond the one gigabyte level.
Really simple to understand.
Ting's data pricing is obvious and if you want to know more, they have a great blog
post about it.
Start by going to linux.ting.com, check out any of their devices.
Feature phones all the way up to real nice Cadillac devices.
In fact, if I recall, they're doing a giveaway of, yeah, the Galaxy S7 Edge.
Oh man.
Oh man, 3600 milliamp battery, Arduino 430 GPU, four gigabytes of RAM, 5.5 inch quad
HD display, and they're giving it away for free.
You just got to subscribe.
Making me drool, Chris.
I know.
Making me drool.
Wes, it's like the Cadillac.
It's the Cadillac, Wes.
You got to subscribe to their Ting account on YouTube.
Simple, simple, simple.
And then comment on their unboxing video and do that in the next three days.
So think about that.
You subscribe to their channel, you comment on the video, and by the 26th, you could get
a free S7.
They do this a lot too, so it's worth doing if you want a free phone because that's not
going to be a huge group.
And this is going out to a lot of folks that could act on that, so I would jump in.
See if you could get that free phone and then let me know.
I would, oh man, I'd be so jelly.
Free S7 on Ting, there's nothing better.
You take some of the best phones, you put them on the Ting network, it's a match made
in heaven.
Pay for what you use.
They don't get in the way of the updates.
I've got the Nexus 6P and guess what?
I'm already running Android N. Ting doesn't play that game where they get in the way of
your updates.
They get you basically a dumb pipe.
If you want to use it for data, go ahead.
You want to use it to make calls, Ting don't care.
They're Honey Badger and that's what I love about it.
They just get you connected.
Linux.Ting.com and a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring your unplugged program and
thanks to all of you guys out there for visiting.
That's what keeps us on the air.
Linux.Ting.com and then maybe go get yourself an S7 and then make me totes jelly.
I would love that.
So Lewis and Fabian are joining us today from Elementary OS and they're going to talk
to us about a little hack fest they're trying to put together in Paris.
In fact they've raised an IndieGoGo page to try to get some funding going to make this
thing possible.
So gentlemen, welcome to the show and I don't know if you guys want to fight it out between
you maybe to the death Kirk and Spock style and tell me which one of you wants to start
with why an IndieGoGo page for a hack fest.
Yeah I think I'll take that one.
Go ahead.
We currently raise funds on our website and that mainly goes to the elementary employees
and those funds are pretty tied up with paying the employees.
So we thought it would be a good idea to raise the money for the hack fest separately.
So we don't cut into the money we need for the employees.
And Fabian you're located in Paris right?
No I'm actually located in Switzerland but because the event is in Paris we put that
as a place there.
And so what's going to take place at a hack fest like this?
Is this sort of the kick off for the next version of elementary OS sort of get everybody
together in one room and brainstorm and begin writing code?
Yeah that's the idea here.
We want to brainstorm what we want to do for the next release but also look at a few things
we already have on our bug tracker maybe and maybe do a little bit of finishing work on
Loki.
Okay.
It depends.
We have to see.
Do you plan to have any kind of like report or summary or anything interesting for people
who do support you to see what awesome things come out of this hack fest?
Yeah we are planning to do a blog post on it at least.
Not sure what will be in it yet but.
Well right.
Great.
So you're raising funds for this hack fest but is attendance free?
Or will there be a sign up page where a fee is paid?
Actually I think that's a clear point to make to kind of for people to understand it's not
necessarily for people to attend.
It's not like a like a fest or an event is it?
It's not necessarily something that's closed but it's something where currently there's
just a gist that people are commenting on and it's just sort of getting people organized
who are going to pop in.
But this is a four day thing so the people that are staying over are just elementary
people who have been pre-organized.
So you're right that it's not totally open as such.
It is sort of you need to ask to attend.
Man I wish we had somebody we could send.
So I know maybe if we want to give Lewis a chance to jump in.
You know I've read some of the comments guys and like on some subreddits and things like
that and people just don't seem to grok the value in you guys doing this.
Why not do a Google hangout?
I guess you know and I'm looking at it right now.
You guys launched it yesterday and you're already doing pretty good.
You've got 26 backers.
That's $493 U.S. have been raised and you have a real reasonable goal of $1800.
I'm almost surprised to see you haven't popped it yet and I kind of wanted to give you guys
a chance to sort of explain why sort of a in-person meeting is actually important to
the process.
Lewis do you want to jump on that one?
Sure.
Well historically we haven't sort of had much of meetings going on in the European community.
I think there was some things that have been attended in Germany but that was a case of
people who are actually employees of elementary being flown over from America.
So this will be the first time that that sort of group of people have actually met each
other.
Obviously we think that when the sort of American siblings of that community have got together
they've got a ridiculous amount of work and some very long-standing stuff sorted out over
the course of a few days just because it's so much faster to be talking in person and
you can just show someone your screen instead of needing to screenshot it and upload it
somewhere and post it and have a discussion about that.
It's so much quicker to do that in person than it is to do that online as you do normally.
Even when there's only two or three people meeting up we've seen just there'll just
be a flood of stuff suddenly get fixed and you can just tell it's all just coming off
of them typically.
And there's that.
There's like the actual code that gets created or the documentation or the project outline
but Wimby I kind of want to throw it to you just for a moment because I think you'll
agree with me.
There's also an energy or an enthusiasm that sort of gets created and then shared amongst
the team when you have an in-person meeting that translates to actual productive work.
Do you agree?
Yeah I do.
So I haven't met Fabian or Lewis but I did meet three of their colleagues at the Snappy
Sprint a few weeks ago and that was Daniel, Kortan and Cody.
And prior to that I'd got a passing sort of more or less developer acquaintance with Cody
and I kind of knew of Daniel but didn't really know him and through the course of that week
although we were focused on Snappy stuff during the day out of the Sprint you develop some
personal relationships and some friendships and some understanding as to who these people
are that you're trying to communicate with that outlives that brief period of you being
in the same room together and now means that we have a much easier way of communicating
with each other over the internet having spent some time in person.
Yeah it makes those text chats easier to parse because you have a personality model to apply
it to.
Yeah and I absolutely see the value in elementary crowdfunding a get together like this because
actually getting people in the same place together isn't only productive but it builds
those relationships those working relationships and those personal understandings that really
bind a project together so I'm all in favor of what elementary are doing here and I think
that crowdfunding not just these kind of activities but crowdfunding in general is the financing
model for independent open source projects for the 21st century.
Why do you think that?
Because it works you don't have to ask for lots of down payment and investment from individuals
what you're looking for is small affordable amounts of money from lots of people and and
you can do an awful lot with that and I think that that model works very well there's certainly
a place for corporate sponsorship and corporate led you know projects and governance and things
like that but for the independent projects I think crowdsourcing is you know it's still
fairly new and in its infancy and I think people are still finding their way with the
blend and how to do things but different people need to explore the options and find out where
it works where it's unsuccessful and then refine that and reproduce it in the future.
So and perhaps Fabian or Lewis if you guys I'm noticing something you're doing and Wimpy
just totally touched on it perfectly that blending of funding for open source projects
so the best model I have is Jupiter broadcast and we have sponsors like you just heard from
and we have Patreon and we blend the two to sort of balance out not only multiple revenue
streams so if one dies we don't die as a company but two so we can sort of leverage one to
build projects up like for example we have something coming soon that we're relying on
the crowd funding to actually finance the creation of this thing to make it viable so
that and which is really great because there's no outside influence on creating this new
thing but it's not it's not just one or the other and I think it was Fabian who said one
of the things they're doing here ooh a little ambiance there I like that one of the things
Fabian said they're doing here is we use the traditional funding model we have to pay full
time employees and because this is something sort of above and beyond what we normally
do we're going back to our user base and saying please help us here do you guys want to touch
on at all why why break it out like this is it is it is it mainly down to things are pretty
tight and it's hard to raise funds so when you want to do something big like this are
you going to the user base hoping that they'll do the same people who may already be funding
it will go above and beyond or are you hoping that new folks will come into the fold Fabian
do you want to take that yeah the reasons for this are probably both and we do want
new users to contribute who maybe didn't complete contribute when they first got elementary
hours they've been impressed by now yeah or also get the users that are using it and liking
it to directly impact changes now because getting together like that will certainly
help push the next release out faster so I just want to vote I guess vote with my own
wallet here by the way Ange I backed it today I threw in some just a little bit of money
this this they so they have the indiegogo indiegogo campaign which we will link in the
show notes the elementary hack fest in Paris I threw some money just because on my own
professional experience I can tell you absolutely that first of all eight hundred dollars is
a ridiculously low amount for what you guys are doing and and what the value of what you're
doing is is easily ten thousand twenty thousand dollars because it's not just about getting
there if you guys if you guys literally did nothing but bullshit and hang out the entire
time and didn't write a line of code the value for the end users of having a tighter knit
team that likes each other more that has more passion compassion for each other and understanding
of each other will translate to a distribution that is supported by that team for longer
that has a higher level of passion that goes into creating the software that has better
communication understanding amongst the team members that is likely easier to resolve issues
amongst the team members it is so super fundamentally value for valuable for the long term viability
of this distribution that it just I don't personally run it but our son runs elementary
OS and for me it was a no brainer to back this because he's gotten more than a year
of use out of the last version of elementary OS I can't wait to upgrade into the next version
of elementary OS and for it for that for that alone it's worth investing in that team to
just keep making great stuff and even if I only use it on one of the many computers in
all of the computers that I take care of it's absolutely valuable and if you're an elementary
OS user where you kind of grok what they're going it's maybe worth throwing a few bucks
because they have a flexible goal and they've reached 27 percent and I got I would love
to see them get five thousand dollars because eighteen hundred dollars is not enough for
what they're doing you know and it's kind of our way some of the people you know elementary
has got got a great desktop experience that's something Linux you know we're really fighting
for and the other companies out there that are you know making these competing products
you're they're absolutely paying for team lunches and outings and going to conferences
so if this is a small way the open source community can contribute back and get the
same kind of experience I think that's great mm-hmm so guys anything else you want to touch
on before we wrap up and you know best of luck to you we'll have a link in the show
notes people want to lazy web it not really but thanks for your contribution yeah yes
no problem I'm I'm glad to back and I hope you guys can pull it off and if I if anything
if anything I would love to hear an update from you folks down the road because you're
always welcome to join us in the mumble room and let us know how it's going especially
because one of the things we try to do here on the unplugged show is give every major
viewpoint a good chance and platform to voice it and I don't think elementary OS is the
distro for everyone but for the folks that love it I think they are super happy to have
it and I think it's incredibly important that there is a team out there that is looking
with such a critical eye at how to build a great desktop environment for Linux users
and how to really make a product that is that is whole from beginning to end and that's
something that's desperately needed in the open source community and so that alone I
think makes the project valuable even if I'm not a daily driver of it and so best of luck
to you guys and I hope people out there even if they're not a daily driver of it see some
of the value there so good luck and hopefully we'll hear a report of how it went in Paris
if all goes well okay I got to talk about something if you if you're a patron you might
already know about this but if if you're a Linux user if you like Linux unplugged and
Linux action show that I may have something that pertains to your interests tomorrow actually
as you listen to this it should be available I was just gonna say we have a new show that's
launching on the Jupiter Broadcasting Network what I know I know I'm super excited about
it I'm really really stoked we're trying out a bunch of new technology on the back end
so it's incredibly fun from that standpoint it is really something that we have been kind
of percolating for I don't know two years and it just sort of is all kind of finally
come together in a really really really slick I really enjoyed it and the response has been
super super good and by response he means from the patrons that have subscribed and
got to see it and know about it what a week ago yeah I released it early last late last
week to the patrons and so yeah the show is gonna be called are you ready for this I'm
gonna reveal it for the first time music soundboard something something okay no wow no not that
one no was that the wrong one sorry okay how about this breaking news on the Jupiter Broadcasting
Network we are about to reveal the new show sources familiar with the matter tell us it's
gonna be called get ready dun dun dun dun dun dun user air user air and it is something
that is near and dear to my heart think of it like this everyone makes mistakes we're
just gonna make great show content out of them insightful it's gonna be a little bit
it's not gonna take itself too seriously so I'll be a little relevant irreverent I guess
and we'll take sort of the weekly issues from the community as Linux users ourselves mistakes
we've made and also just things we're doing throughout the week it is a relaxed enjoyable
talk show the first episode is out it is Noah myself and making his network debut the beer
Mr. Rekai as their host yep yeah it's true and it's great and it starts out good and
it stays strong the entire episode and I really enjoyed recording it we're using a bunch of
new technology to do it not only on the on the recording aspect of it but also on the
publishing end of it and it's all Linux based and so episode one you can go check it out
at Jupiter broadcasting.com user air one we talk about kind of a smattering of things
my experience with Linux on the MacBook and getting no man's sky working but also we talk
quite a bit about tiling window managers and Noah's attempt to get into that whole space
and sort of my issues about it we finally give you a tiling window manager review which
I think turned out really great new features that are coming to JBOT and some of the code
that we've been writing to make that possible and Noah has recently got into development
and we talk about that we talk about developing Python and Ruby so the whole show it's about
an hour long and it just was turned out great so you can check it out at Jupiter broadcasting.com
brand new show for you Linux users it's called user air and I'm really happy with the way
it turned out so on last are we going to be expecting to see exponent yeah right actually
I think you have to watch you have to listen to the episode or watch it but I think he
ended up going with awesome and he's very nice yeah yeah it is review was really interesting
kind of got me my interest peaked so yeah there you go I'm excited and yeah the patrons
the patrons have got it and we've gotten a hundred percent positive feedback on it so
far what an exciting thing it's like you know once in a every few years thing a new JB show
yeah yeah and it's super fun for us to do a whole new tech to do it there if there was
no Mac no Mac touch the entire process which is really fun and we used some some back end
scripts that we're hoping we can work with the folks they really great team over at pod
publish to integrate some of the cool things that we're working on with we'll see so yeah
it is it is slick and if you're a commuter or if you if you consume this via YouTube
it's out right now there's RSS feeds you can subscribe to it if all of its published it's
an iTunes is in the Google Play Store it's all ready to go we got everything ready and
loaded to go although we do need to get Aaron to update the drop down menu and the show
menu thing okay but yeah so I'm very excited I listened to the pilot episode let me I was
actually there for it yeah yeah you the secret life the secret yeah the sneaky live stream
yeah I do have a suggestion no considering it's more of a you know a loose conversation
may show why don't you include the mumble room in honor maybe one day maybe one day
I'll tell you what the audio quality of the show is like nothing else we've ever done
I mean it is it is far and beyond anything we've ever recorded before it like I said
like I was saying earlier the new audio the new one some new technology we're using is
also a technology stack that automates double-ended recording which for if you if you know what
that means that's kind of a big deal for us and that kind of makes it harder to do mumble
but we do appreciate a good technical challenge so it's it's not with it's not outside the
realm of possibility I don't know if this would work to give you a sample in the show
that might be kind of weird but I will give you and I'll give you a little sample of the
audit quality is here ideas if you take a more skeptical approach then when in a couple
months you end up running a tiling window manager I'll just have more fun saying I was
right so as somebody that's a run a tiling window manager in the past I'm gonna say that's
not true that I want more fun no that that Chris is not going to end up liking it it
just doesn't suit the the style of desktop that he is used to tell tell me okay let's
start with this in the same way that I both gave you both credit for being able to evaluate
an operating system from a completely neutral no bias standpoint let's try and do that with
with desktop environments and for everyone out there that's there I can I'll stop it
there I'll tell you one of the things that also I really like about this show is I'll
just say now I don't know if I've all really ever mentioned in the show so you only really
know if you ever listen to 159 of Linux unplugged probably but a secret of this show is I'm
going to edit it a bit so with most of our shows they're all live to tape if you can
call it that lives disk and what you get is what you get but we don't generally edit these
at all and that's how I've done it for a decade now that's going to change with with user
error from time to time I will cut it down I will make it more refined I will take the
more insightful and intelligent things we say and focus on those and sort of cut out
some of the extra I haven't done it's not heavy-handed so the original episode of user
error episode one was an hour and 14 minutes long the raw recording the published versions
like an hour and three minutes it is that is that right yeah there you go so it kind
of gives you a sense of I took some stuff I just tightened it up I made it I made it
so that way hopefully we keep your intention your attention and everything we say in there
has a good intention behind it and so that's the that's the idea with user error is it's
got a little different feel it's a little more relaxed a little bit more intentional
and it's it's definitely one of those shows where we're going to sometimes go down a rabbit
hole we're going to sort of let give ourselves license to just let people who are passionate
about Linux and technology have the floor from time to time and and I'm really excited
about we're going to go with that because the combination of that freedom but yet tightening
it up and making what the end product is really something that's solid I think is going to
be incredible so that's user error episode one it's out right now you can subscribe to
it and I'm very excited about it it's gotten 100% positive feedback so far you can be the
first person to crap in my punch bowl if you like and a big thank you to Rekai for finally
after all of these I know it is how many it's been at least six or seven no more than that
more than that it's got a bit I think eight years now yeah and you know what he's brilliant
so I've been why I you know what I thought from the day we set up the studio I thought
one day I'll get that guy on Mike eventually I get everybody on Mike eventually everybody
that's in my daily life ends up on microphone or on camera it just seems to be the way it
goes so that's out now and thank you to our patrons who funded it to make it possible
for us to create a show and the first question that didn't come to our mind is how do we
make it sponsor but how do I sell this the question was what's the audience gonna want
to listen to I think that's huge what is it ang breaking news here yeah what do we all
mr. wimpy go ahead um so I just hit play and I noticed that you've got audio spectrum analysis
running yes against a still image is that produced using ffmpeg or something else so
yes and yes it is there's a and Rekai probably the guy to talk to about this but what we
what we found was there was a a python GTK application that uses fm ffmpeg and I think
AV convert or something on the back end it needed some updates because it was built for
like Ubuntu three four years ago and it uses like a boon to his old hello hello who is
that who is that mr. Mike yeah thank you it uses a boon to his old ffmpeg libraries and
stuff like that but Rekai made some changes to one of the main Python scripts and fired
right up and it gives me a GUI to input the file and the background and the text and then
generates the video file and what we want to do is integrate that eventually into pod
published I believe so they yeah so there you go wimpy Rekai just linked you the plug
in yep perfect and in Python that's just perfect isn't it that's and I that's I guess that's
the other thing to kind of touch on here is if everything goes swimmingly user air will
be hopefully helping make podcasting on Linux easier even more automated and a little visually
richer and that's one of our goals too so it's super fun to be working on a project
like that that also has some wider community and some yeah just pioneering it basically
yeah I mean I I was so happy when I found pod published and and then the fact that it's
a snap wimpy really was sort of the the final nail if you will because it meant that I could
produce the entire thing for my Apollo under arch so thank you for snapping that up and
and continuing that project now did you talk about how often it will be released so our
plan is Wednesday morning over at Jupiter broadcasting we'll see if that goes because
again it's since it's kind of experimental technology things could break but you know
we kind of have a hole as far as technical content on Wednesdays right now on filter
comes out Wednesday evenings BSD now gets recorded during the day but it doesn't get
released so we kind of have a hole there in the schedule if you are a Linux user wanting
some tech content and not politics there's nothing really there for you on Wednesdays
and so our plan is to release it Wednesday mornings if all works to to make it available
so that way on Sunday you'll have Linux action show Monday you have Kota radio and tech talk
today Tuesday you have Linux unplugged Wednesday you have user air Thursday you'll have text
now okay and so then for those that like joining live like the entire Linux unplugged audience
isn't listening right now and participating in the mumble room will it be ever recorded
live or is it all I think so it's you know it's interesting because there are two totally
different shows right oh absolutely yeah so I think so I we recorded the first one live
but don't count on it I guess if you're thinking oh I'm gonna catch a live one I think we'll
always do it live but I'm just you know it just I don't know if always do at the same
time because the whole concept behind the show is I really want all of us to be in a
chill mood when we record it sure I just want us to be able to sit back and talk about stuff
and not be stressed out and that might not be possible for three people but and I hope
in the future to have West join us and bring on yeah yeah and bring on different JB hosts
from time to time and so you'll be able to hear like your hosts from other shows sort
of get in on this show which with I'm hoping super high fidelity audio quality everybody
will have local recordings using Zen caster for that which automates and wimpy if you
guys I don't wimpy what are you what are you using for the Ubuntu podcast for local recordings
there's a utility called audio recorder which is available in a PPA and then mumble for
the real-time chat yes use mumble for the real-time chat and then the the sneaky feature
of audio recorder is that you can set a time at which the recording starts so because all
of our machines are NTP synced we agree we're going to start recording at 2032 and 04 seconds
and all of our local recordings start at the same time so I've been I've been talking to
Josh and he's the gentleman behind Zen caster with I think it's missing an e so it's sort
of web web 2.0 name yeah and I don't think I've had a chance to look at Zen caster it's
like a web RTC front end that does all it one of the things interesting in user error
is Noah was slightly delayed from Rekind I Rekind are sitting here in the studio talking
live Noah was in Grand Forks and he had about a half a second delay so the other thing we
do is we start the recording so audio recorder starts recording and then traditionally Mark
counts us in with a three two one and then when it would be zero all of us say biscuits
because of course because and and then when they do when we do the edit you just line
up everyone saying biscuits together and that accounts for those you know few hundred milliseconds
of of jitter and it's Mark that does the editing right it's either Mark or I I'd say Mark does
about 60 percent and I do about 40 percent well it varies week to week depending on who's
busiest if you ever get a wild hair doing the lamination now I think that was poppy
I think it was poppy that'll happen if poppy is chief laminator yeah if you ever get the
wild hair and you want to try Zen caster it will put you out of business because it manages
the time sync up and it handles all of it also does the VoIP aspects you don't have
to use mumble if you don't want but you can just toggle that and then it will post process
and level and gate all the individual tracks and produce one file for you at the oh it
does the gating as well it does yeah yeah so I it's not you know I so me because we
do all that in post that's what I do too and I'm still doing it that way but I'm beginning
to run two versions and I I ended up for the final published version of user error I went
with Zen casters version of the mix okay I still tweaked it a little bit marked and we'll
have a production also known as going out for a curry at the end of the year and we'll
discuss a a change in production methodology it's fun yeah I'll have the I'll have the
creator on a future show he's working on a big release right now and after he's done
I plan to have him on unplugged or last to talk about what he's doing so mr. Wes you
found that there was an update to a project we have covered in the past and we just touched
on it a little bit it's good I think it's it's good new GUIX is a package manager I
believe oh geeks is that okay thank you good new geeks a package manager that I think promises
reproducible builds with everything am I right can you remind me about what this is and why
it's important yeah good new geeks is kind of an issue they're they they're similar to
the Nix package manager slash distribution and both of them kind of promise a functional
programming like approach to package management and like so today we see a lot of stuff you
know with chef puppet ansible you want systems that are reproducible you want to have configuration
management where you have some sort of you know declarative style so that you can specify
I want these packages I want these sys controls changed you know I want to be able to rebuild
a host on on-command or spin up a new host in the cloud if you need one but they kind
of do it from a top-down approach where you know I can configure whatever on my Ubuntu
machine and then have chef run and if I don't have chef you know know about or specifically
managing resources then those may not get managed and they may be in a state that I
don't know it's very easy for kind of unknown things or weird state to creep in that way
so these programs at geeks in particular they kind of go from the ground up where you have
to specify in basically one config file all of the packages you want all the settings
you want and they provide it in a way where it's it's reproducible oh I like that it doesn't
have a lot of side effects doesn't store a lot of state so that you you basically it
runs it processes to this one file and end up with a configuration of a system and is
the advantage to that then it's super easy to replicate that to other systems yes and
so you get you know they have a lot of dependency management they pretty much for the way they
do it is kind of clever they use a lot of symlinks so that you can have one of the things
this enables is you can have multiple versions of you know what might cause conflicts and
other systems you can have multiple versions of the same package because when it builds
it it has a lot of temporary directories there are not temporary but they're based on a hash
of the file so that they're unique per build and if you've changed you know the dependencies
or you've changed the compiler flags and that will be in a different folder and so you you
really have to manually or not manually but you really have to specify all your dependencies
to get this right but once you do it means that you can have multiple versions it makes
it very easy to reproduce and it lets you know that you know once you've got it configured
you can move it wherever nothing will change it will always be in that state huh you know
so I got bit just this morning it was rough West I said I woke up early and I thought
I'm gonna sneak out it's it's it's it's a technique you learn when you have young children
and you wake up before them rarely and you're like I've got I've got an hour before they
wake up I used to do this all the time and so same thing happened this morning I woke
up an hour earlier than I expected I thought I just got a free hour so I walked out to
the living room fired up the laptop went to launch no man's sky bubkiss didn't start wouldn't
run and I thought to myself oh my what did I update yesterday that broke my game and
this is where I thought to myself gosh you know I'd really love to be able to just pin
the version of wine and just oh just or have have this version of wine installed just for
this application and I know there's exactly there are tools to manage that specifically
with wine but this is something at a package level I could achieve right yes and you know
because of the way it works you can even install it on top of your a lot of people use it just
you know you want the latest version of Emacs and you know now we have some things like
you know snap packages that sort of stuff but this kind of has a different approach
and you can install this whole kind of like a package source you can install this on top
of your existing Linux implementation I think even just all from user land without root
permissions and then come you know get all the packages that you might need built just
for your user oh wow wow so they've just updated here now they're working on getting you can
you can compile it from source that's where you get a lot of the power but they also have
binary packages available so they've been working now on one reproducible builds which
you know we've talked about before a lot of projects are working on you know too they're
working on their own because of the way it's because of the unique properties of this distribution
security updates are kind of hard so they've been working on the technique they call grafting
to keep this functional approach but allow you to have security updates easily applied
without having to rebuild all of your programs well I love that and just super quick reproducible
builds remind me why that's super important even though I know I'm asking for the audience
you know mostly you just want to make sure that the program that you're end up running
as a binary really was compiled from the sources that you can inspect right so if you're running
some eventually unless you're using something totally interpreted you're running a binary
at some point and it's all well and good to have access to the source code but if you
can't actually confirm that that source code would produce a bit for bit identical binary
then you really can't be sure that you're getting those advantages so it's all about
verifying that what you built on your system matches what the source code available for
that upstream project is or or whatever it is you're installing and that seems almost
vitally important like it almost seems like half the information you have to know in this
day and age and it certainly would be you know it's one of the benefits of having access
to the source and and free software and all the right talk about so why not leverage it
because we have we with an advantage we have built in exactly even though it you know it's
not app image it's not snaps but it's still technically extremely interesting and that's
why I think it's fun to talk about here on the show and they have a new release and it's
great because West has been kind of following it so I thank you West for bringing it to
our attention again and we have a link to the LWN post that go check it out and let
us know what you think and also like I was just saying a heads up to those of you that
are running on the development quote unquote branch of wine and you may be running on that
branch of wine and not even knowing it because for some distributions it's just the default
branch of wine they install the new version of wine 1.9.17 breaks No Man's Sky which
is in my opinion and I apparently the entire internet disagrees with me the best game in
the universe but it does work fine on versions 1.9.16 and 1.9.15 I've confirmed myself so
heads up if you are playing No Man's Sky under wine don't update like I did because
that ruined my morning I spent my entire morning fixing that the entire morning I thought you
know and it was West it's funny because my first thought was well maybe it's this MacBook
kernel AUR package maybe it updated you know no it wasn't that it wasn't the Nvidia driver
it was just damn wine and it wasn't until I was looking for news for this show that
I noticed that there was a new version of wine out that I went oh wait a minute that's
what it was it was in preparation for the show I discovered the problem just a quick
super quick update on the MacBook Linux thing I talked about it more in user error West
I've done a couple of kernel updates in the meantime flawless my friend that is awesome
I have I actually I actually clocked it three second boot time it's oh yeah it's it's about
seven seconds total because x11 and the Nvidia driver at about another three to four seconds
to it depending on the day but I don't know could you just could you just super quickly
could you talk about how it's not it's not using grub it's not using lilo we're not using
refine to boot on this MacBook we're using the firmware bootloader and frickin system
D can you talk about that at all yeah you know we just used to be called gummy boot
and then it got eaten up by system DS so many things do for better for worse you can talk
about that later but it's just a really simple bootloader for EFI systems and so the max
for a long time to kind of work on some of the first machines to have EFI enabled bios
is if you want to call them that firmwares and so because they already use that to boot
the Mac OS X operating system if you don't need a fancy menu to pick for them and if
you want Linux to be the default and then have the option to hold the option key to
boot into Mac OS X when you need to say for firmware updates exactly exactly what I want
yep then you can just install it right to the fact partition that already exists that
holds the EFI bootloaders or executables and then it just writes a simple configuration
file that sets it up for you and then the firmware will just hit that default boot file
it will load the kernel and in at RAMFS and away you go just a couple of other notes because
I've always been a huge doubter of Linux on the MacBook and I've always encouraged
the audience not to do it even though they constantly emailing about it I found two packages
in the AUR that were great one was like fan control D or I can't remember what Mac Mac
fan control D or anyways it's a background process yes it's a demon that runs in the
background and actually manages the thermal management on the MacBook so I'm not cooking
the MacBook into hell which was a problem yeah hugely nice West two other packages one
that manages the keyboard backlighting just uses the ambient light sensor in the MacBook
and automatically adjust the keyboard backlighting just as Mac OS X does and then the last one
that has been also great is the same thing using the ambient light sensor to manage the
brightness on the display just like Mac OS does and I a lot of usability wins right there
it really is and I I have to say if you have an old enough MacBook I don't know about a
new model I couldn't afford to people are like people said I cheated because I tried
on a 2013 MacBook instead of a the subreddit and I saw you did they wanted me to buy a
new MacBook to try this I gotta talk folks if I was gonna buy a new computer today I
would not be buying a MacBook I would be I would buy in a machine that just runs Linux
out of the box however buying a new MacBook which is actually a three-year-old MacBook
right yeah exactly and that's why yeah that's actually why I thought it was a valid experiment
was I think that MacBook the one that I have the 2013 is gonna come down to sub easily
sub thousand dollar prices in a month and I think when that happens you're gonna have
a lot more people looking at it for Linux when you can buy the machine that I have which
is honestly a very nice computer it is I've been really impressed with the trackpad with
the keyboard backlighting with the performance but honestly what what what shocks me every
time I open up the screen is that 15-inch retina display with gnome 3 beautiful I've
never seen a I've never ever in my life seen a GUI that looks that good even the XPS 13
which is my one of my favorite computers which has a high dpi display doesn't look as good
it really is amazing too small yeah it's exactly it yeah it looks great on 15 inch so there's
some reasons to run it but I would say if I was buying today I would probably buy a
computer from entryware or system 76 where it was preloaded designed with to run Linux
or even the Sputnik edition from Dell which is also you know meant to run Linux but if
you are in the position of coming across a pre-owned or you have an existing MacBook
and you've been thinking about it you've been on the fence and a gross with the Linux
MacBook kernel which is in the AUR which you have to build every time it updates and a
couple of those packages just search for MacBook and the AUR it really it really is a great
experience it's yeah I would totally I'll just add that the enter grows installer even
it will do the system D boot stuff for you so it'll handle it right there you just need
to make sure you have as we talked about you need to make sure you have the Wi-Fi drivers
or yes USB Ethernet adapter and for more details on that just listen to episode 158 of your
unplugged program.
All right well enough about that I want to talk to Wimpy about LibreVault which promises
to bring what I love about SyncThing and what I love about BitTorrent Sync to a GPL3 licensed
open source project and we've talked about a little bit Wes has done some kicking of
the tires and like a gentleman he even did a screencast of it so we could talk about
it recently and I chewed on it I debated it and then Wimpy convinced me I've installed
on my machines and we're going to talk about LibreVault why it actually matters why it
could fundamentally I think change distribution of open source projects and how it could enhance
the Jupiter Broadcasting Network and how it could replace Dropbox or insert name of sync
application for you it's really cool it's really competitive and in fact it worked perfect
on a DigitalOcean Droplet DigitalOcean.com use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED all one word
lowercase you know I've really boiled the pitch the pitch for DigitalOcean down to one
thing if you need a computer that doesn't have a monitor most of the time DigitalOcean.com
really if you want to just accomplish something on a computer that is super fast has really
great disk I O because it's all SSD and it's connected to the best internet connection
possible DigitalOcean.com they use KVM for the virtualizer running on top of Linux they
got SSD drives for the disk I O and use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED you get a $10 credit
you can start in less than 55 seconds and pricing plans $5 a month for 512 megabytes
of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU but actually yeah they break it down hourly if you want
to just experiment with something you can spin up I like like West for the show notes
is like here's Chris's wiki Chris's wiki Chris's wiki now that reminded me of the fact that
for just one day I wanted Chris's wiki you remember that and instead of installing all
of that crud and pulling down all of those dependencies on my laptop and and honestly
doing it over on my vi connection I just spun up a DigitalOcean droplet and within about
two minutes I decided no good destroyed the droplet I don't even know how I don't even
know what I paid for that because they charge at an incredible price when you do it hourly
if you've got something you want to host for yourself to be fast that is really not like
something you want to share with the world DigitalOcean has private networking where
your DigitalOcean droplets can talk amongst each other that isn't over the internet which
is a really nice feature they have data centers in New York San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam
London Toronto Germany and India their interface though oh man back in the day when Angela
and I one of the things for the consulting company that we worked for was they did VMware
hosted machines remember like remember how we sold hosted solutions yes to manage that
I had to run a virtual machine that ran Windows that then ran the VMware ESX management consoles
just so I could manage the Linux machines inside our VMware infrastructure and it was
god-awful slow yeah very convoluted DigitalOcean changes all of it I mean it's not just a good
UI for a desktop application it's a freaking good UI period for a web app for a for a native
app don't matter DigitalOcean's got the best UI I've seen to manage this ever then you
combine that with a great straightforward API you can build applications around it or
you can take advantage of cool open source code already committed check it out it's really
straightforward DigitalOcean.com just use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED big thank you DigitalOcean
for sponsoring the unplug program and by the way check out their block storage that's the
hotness right now they've got the ability now to add storage as you need it at the block
level up to 16 terabytes all backed by SSDs wow yeah isn't that nice DigitalOcean.com
use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED it's one word lowercase you apply that to your account you
get a ten dollar dollar dollar credit over at DigitalOcean.com thanks for sponsoring
the unplug program so LibreVault is promising to fill a very necessary hole in the open
source sync ecosystem and I kind of wanted to open it up to Wimpy to tell me about his
experiments with LibreVault because honestly you're the one that's really got me looking
at this again and again Wimpy okay well it's early days it is so in fact it's so early
days that I think it's only packaged for Arch and Ubuntu at this point right possibly it's
definitely packaged for Ubuntu I've seen it in the AUR I've seen some discussion about
the developer making static builds at some point so that we can run it wherever yeah
if you want to install from the AUR you first have to have qt5-tools installed and then
it'll build properly but yes it is an AUR so leave a comment in the AUR for the package
maintain this they can fix that that's that's what needs to be done there and the project
the project been cooking for about a year now but I only became aware of it about two
weeks or so ago and like you Chris I was really smitten with the bit sync workflow that key
exchange mechanism worked really well for what I wanted to do and I've never really
been satisfied with anything else that I've tried to replace bit sync with until this
so what I've got running at the moment is a very small setup but on one of my desktop
machines I have LibreVault with the GUI version running and I have a folder of stuff in a
synchronized folder and then I've got two Ubuntu servers that are in two different geographic
locations and I just have the LibreVault daemon installed on those and that comes with a system
D unit which you can run either at the global system level or you can allocate to an individual
user or many users so I'm using it on a per user basis oh nice and so and that's a so
you start the system D service as that specific user yes so in this case you just sudo system
CTL enable user at oh yeah yeah yeah and that was the business and then from the command
line there's a couple of utilities you can run LibreVault daemon gen config which builds
the boilerplate configuration file and pulls some details from your specific system like
hostname to give it the identifier for that node you can derive the C type key so those
read only keys or the shareable read write keys rather than just the master key using
gen key and then it just has a JSON file for the folder configuration so you can just copy
paste your JSON folders.json from one box to the other and when you then start the daemon
running it just synchronizes and I've got those three machines running now and I've
just been poking at it and lobbing large files in and making lots of rapid changes to text
files in three locations at the same time to see how it handles conflicts and things
like that and so far so good.
I want to address a couple of things and maybe somebody in the audience might be listening
and thinking why does something like this matter so I want to touch on two things first
of all and I want to come back to this one with wimpy I think it could be the next open
source CDN but first of all when you have something like this working what you accomplish
is almost it's like a transparent network file system and once it's all set up and it's
in that set it and forget it mode you have any arbitrary folder that you choose on your
system synced across all your devices and that's huge you make a change in one directory
and it immediately is available on all your other machines and to give you this is a very
maybe off example but the current example for me is no man's sky the configuration folder
I just want that configuration folder synced across many machines in the Dropbox world
to accomplish that I do a sim link and I move the actual folder into my Dropbox and then
I sim link in the in the configuration folder that folder and then I had that I kind of
trick I trick no man's sky into thinking it's accessing the folder when in reality it's
hitting a sim link and going to my Dropbox but with things like LibreVault I could choose
any arbitrary directory on my file system to sync and that becomes to be that gets huge
that's just great for just one to one users you don't have to share it with them with
many people super handy and and also one of the other things before we get to the open
source CDN is one of the advantages has over something like Dropbox and I think this will
resonate with you Angela is there's no centralized storage it's just whatever space you have
on your hard drive so you don't have to worry about getting 20 gigs and 30 gigs or buying
the one terabyte package like we do with Dropbox you just everybody syncs and it's just synced
amongst your computers and whatever space you have that's the space you get there's
no limits that's extremely compelling especially for something like unfiltered which is ridiculous
but lastly it kind of and I don't know about LibreVault maybe wimpy you know better but
it sort of has it's sort of the bit torrent sync philosophy brought to a GPL 3 application
that's not going to get shut down it's not going to get put behind a paywall and it allows
the distribution of files in a way that is truly truly unique because like a torrent
everybody who participates in the sync also becomes part of the distribution network and
it is therefore its own built-in CDN and I'm wondering are you thinking about how to use
this in a way that because it's a GPL because that means a lot of Linux users might eventually
one day just have it in their damn repo could this be a way to distribute to distribute
project images or a large files to a user base what do you think absolutely and that's
one of the reasons why I'm looking at it so looking out into the future what I would like
to do is list LibreVault in the Ubuntu mate software boutique so it's a one-click install
yes and then provide so a new feature in the current build of LibreVault is links so it
understands that this URI construct is a link to a LibreVault key you can click on that
it will embed it in the application and that way you can then or I can then make available
images for Ubuntu mate for the various architectures available oh yeah people can just click on
those and sync them when a new version is available they automatically get the new version
and all of the people that are carrying that LibreVault key are part of the collective
that are synchronizing and sharing and part of the peer-to-peer network that is making
those images available and it is torrent under the hood if you actually go and look at the
LibreVault config file you will see well-known torrent trackers as the trackers that are
used to actually broker the connections between your installations very good you and because
it's torrent trackers of course you could run your own torrent tracker and just change
your config to point your own tracker and you could keep all of your tracking off the
public trackers as well you know you could just use your own torrent tracker.
So Wes you kind of been kicking the tires for us you've been our guinea pig I've also
installed on my machine and Rekai was the guy that had to fall on the sword and even
try installing on Windows Wes what were your take away from it?
You know I mean it is definitely early days but I was I was also impressed I do think
this you know the just be able to give it a link of a key and then especially having
the built-in you know write only read only that kind of access control yeah really easy
right there I'm excited to play more with it you know I haven't replaced my sync thing
needs yet but I'm thinking it's on the list of projects to see it's just so it seems so
easy to configure and it seems like a good scale very nicely.
I'll tell you a story that made me realize how important something like sync thing or
LibreVault is and I'm I'll be honest I'm a little more excited about LibreVault and
Janai you know we've got three kids and there's there's new movies that we discover individually
that the kids just absolutely love and if I wanted to back up one of those movies and
share it with her so that way when they're at home they could watch that same movie there's
no or I could yeah right don't forget about me yeah up there was there was actually recently
like when Zootopia came out that was exactly the situation and I had it I had backed it
up I had a copy of it but I had it sitting on a hard drive and when the kids went home
they couldn't watch Zootopia and it would be really really nice if there was a piece
of software I could use to just send you that file and didn't go through some corporate
server because a friend of ours you and I both know them you know there was a file they
wanted and so their friend put it up on a Dropbox account and sent them the link it's
it here go grab it and Dropbox shut down their whole account just completely terminated the
account shut it down you're banned wow wow yeah and and it's that's ridiculous that you
know if I go out and I buy Zootopia for 40 freaking bucks or 30 bucks or 20 bucks from
Costco and I use make MKV to back it up and I and I that's my copy and I want my children
to be able to watch it I should have it there should be a way for me to be able to easily
share those files with you and that's what Lee I think even if you're just an individual
Lee Bravevault promises that but you know in the term for Jupiter broadcasting we distribute
the unfiltered show notes and all of the clips that we play via BitTorrent Sync right now
and this is I think absolutely where we're going to migrate to Lee Bravevault looks like
the perfect replacement for BitTorrent Sync for us and if you're not familiar with BitTorrent
Sync it's kind of it needs to be replaced it's it's kind of things have gone south
let's just put it that way both Wimby and I are we're done we're done so like for
your for your issue is Zootopia with something like a Plex or MB work yeah you know that's
generally what we use but of course on my end I'm connected to a MiFi yeah yeah so it's
not like the kids are gonna very easily stream it from from my hard drive so it'd really
be best for them to have a local copy that just showed up in the kids movie folder if
I could just have a if we just had on both our servers we had two kids movie directories
and every time I put a file in there it showed up on both our servers it's the perfect solution
so that's that's my hope eventually but that all of course Ionic Badger and I were talking
about it before the show all pulls into kind of pulls into like this ultimate multimedia
server setup Ionic I know you and I are both excited about a media service have you solved
this moving files between multiple houses problem by chance he's oh Ionic left ironic
oh ironic that's why probably because I called him wrong I called him by the wrong name that's
fine yeah our sink is also how we actually do it now so it's just manual and it's painful
and LibreSync I think eventually will replace Dropbox Pro for us as a company we have made
the financial decision to buy a Dropbox Pro every year and go ahead and do that again
okay fine turn the camera on she won't do it and we're not happy so so you've talked
about you know wanting to sort of fund open source I'm I'm putting you on the spot a little
bit here by the way I don't mind so good man you know look at look at what you're spending
on Dropbox Pro and turn that into monthly payments and consider contacting the author
of LibreVault and for a year making donations to the project and marking the issues because
he's right sort of the issues on his github are kind of a roadmap of improvements and
sort of direct him at the things you would most like to see implemented and see if you
can you know encourage the developer to focus his his efforts I think the first thing would
be to not limit it to five users you know at the base oh they don't have the LibreVault
doesn't have that yeah yeah that's huge that's an automatic yeah that by the way is a Dropbox
limitation so I think it's seven hundred eighty dollars a year to pay for Dropbox Pro is that
right yeah and so and from like an expensive standpoint how would we do that as a business
could we could we instead of paying for a service so when we pay for a service is that
a is that a type of write-off that's different than buying a physical good no so when we
pay eight hundred dollars for an internet service that's like buying eight hundred dollars
of something physical well well okay so if it's a if it's a physical thing there are
there's like an amortization right down process but right but they just raised it to like
fifteen hundred so no in the case of eight hundred it doesn't matter doesn't matter so
could we as a business could we easily structure paying an open source project so it'd be about
sixty five seventy bucks a month it'd be exactly sixty five dollars yeah I would rather pay
monthly than get hit with this eight hundred dollars because we we we already have so many
subscription services mm-hmm and it's just much easier to manage that especially like
with cards that expire but so here's what I did is this is like what three weeks ago
we renewed it and I think we we just we draw a line in the sand and say never again let
me just let me just point out to that because yeah it's Dropbox professional we have five
licenses I don't have access to my own company's Dropbox no it's because we need the producers
in there dad I know so I am keeping all my all the artwork like for example I made the
artwork for user error but just all the artwork for all the shows is stored in my Dropbox
on my laptop right so all the assets all the assets and what we need to do is sort of reorganize
all of it in some sort of Libre vault folder structure but the problem really has been
in the past is own cloud and and sync thing have not been reliable we've tried them yeah
we did I still have on cloud I need to get that off yeah well it's it's like it's there
but it's only for a couple of things and the problem is is in a media production business
you just end up with this crazy amount of data I tried I was gonna get a I was gonna
get an estimate for the show again but the last time I checked we have over 600 gigabytes
of files just for one show wow that we sync around so you know like you really got to
have a bulletproof product to move all that stuff around and the one thing I will give
Dropbox is in combination with their selective sync and their web client it has been very
very very bulletproof and there are literally times where I make a change and then I walk
downstairs and I need to put it on the air within 35 seconds and if it's not there it's
that doesn't work for me that's just the reality of a live production and Dropbox always always
meets that deadline so LibreVault is not going to testing yeah yeah it will need testing
but of course the advantage of LibreVault is it's based on bit torrent technology so
it's syncing blocks not files yeah it doesn't care about files it's just hashes and blocks
and and that's important because because it handles all of the integrity checking for
you and small changes at the block level could be synced instead of the entire file exactly
so yeah yeah that's that is a great point Wimpy so you know I am really I'm really excited
to see LibreVault when do you do you feel Wimpy it's worth addressing that the primary
authors I almost even don't want to say this but I know I know some people listening will
be concerned that the primary author is Russian do you does that concern you at all that your
file syncing solution okay that doesn't bother me doesn't bother doesn't doesn't bother me
in the slightest no some of the smartest people I've worked with in the past were from Russia
so yep exactly the same for me and it's a good reason to have a you know open source
encrypted supported file sharing great point great point and the the LibreVault blog is
very instructional there's a couple of posts there about the detailed makeup of the config
file so the skeleton config files it makes are really bare bones don't expose all of
the configuration options but there are blog posts to describe all of that in great detail
and there are also some blog posts there that talk about the the crypto libraries that are
used and the other alternatives that might exist and you know talking about maybe changing
some of the underlying technologies because they're more optimized so along with the code
being open and you can go and look at it and inspect it there's also some open dialogue
through the blog as well I like that a lot and I I feel at the end of the day I feel
a little reassured this gpl3 it's not well we might one day open source it like bit torrent
sync kind of insinuated at the beginning this is just legitimately at the very beginning
gpl3 here it all is here's the goal yeah yeah and I think that is also very and there's
about half a dozen other libraries that it's built on top of as well that are all open
source and they're all linked in the github now repository um wimpy yeah if it blows
up in your face and ruins everything will you come back and tell us about it I will
at the moment I'm not moving anything around that's critical but what I'm working towards
I've spoken about it before so I'll be brief I have this roaming profile that I have synchronized
everywhere and I'm working to building up confidence in libre vault so it can take over
that and that is critical to everything I do so when I build up enough confidence to
make that switch it's passed some sort of credibility testing and then if it doesn't
screw those things up then as far as I'm concerned it's good to go wow you know I'll let you
know but I can't wait to hear that that's my dream that is my that is my dream that
I I work on a machine here and I go home and everything's the same so that's yeah whoa
and I have I have that now and I've had to change the sync solutions along the ways the
best solution I had was bit sync and this is really a workflow drop in replacement for
bit sync wow yeah exactly that's really oh boy I you know what after you've been running
a libre vault I say I don't know I don't know what that I don't know what the threshold
is wimpy but after you feel like it's like it's it's meet they this is working for me
threshold I would love to hear I would love to hear your full setup on that okay all right
well give me a few weeks because it's going to take a while for me to stress test it a
bit and build up enough confidence that I want to make the switch to something I oh
boy do I understand I think pretty soon you'll see us experimenting probably with the unfilter
show on just because the unfilter audience it's a great it's a great platform because
we have a backup copy of all the clips so if there was any huge data corruption we can
recover and it's a huge amount of data and it's a bunch of people to sync so it's like
this perfect scenario for testing so I bet yeah I bet you'll hear more so my plan is
to switch over to handling my profile exclusively but then have a job on my main machine which
makes an r-sync snapshot of my profile like every hour so if it totally screws it up I've
got a recovery point you know so that's my that's my sort of harness that I've planned
for this so I'm not going to just chuck all of my stuff at it and hope it works I do have
a a recovery point as well yeah it's in my my plan is also to do a phased approach of
more and more critical things starting with things that I absolutely have multiple copies
of and then over time I will slowly move to that really precious data whatever that is
so great I'm all in you convince me yeah really this little process of shaving revolution I
would love to hear it not even a gradual let's just all in you know what mr. tunnel you are
bold and I hope you come back and report to us because honestly I think it's going to
be if we get there and it gets wide enough adoption it could be a real fantastic way
for enthusiasts to get latest versions of ISO images or packages or whatever because
it's not only not only are you the CDN by participating in LibreSync or LibreVault sorry
but you are also you are also fundamentally part of the RSS feed part of the distribution
swarm part of the notification network it's all of that built into one thing and I love
it so LibreVault it's super early days you can hear from all of us here we're not really
quite ready to trust our most important data to it but it's definitely something we're
checking out and we'll be following up on future editions of the show now I got to tell
you about my experiences with Android N I believe it's pronounced new gay new gar do
get new get Android N and I'll tell you how that's gone and why I think I need to switch
to Ubuntu touch as soon as possible but first I'm gonna tell you about our friends at Linux
Academy go to LinuxAcademy.com slash unplug take advantage of the Linux Academy shows
continuing sponsorship by the Linux Academy LinuxAcademy.com slash unplug go there to
register your vote for one more episode you want 160 you hear it's a big number LinuxAcademy.com
slash unplug is one way to do it but also it's a great opportunity for you to learn
more about the Linux Academy platform the place to go really if you have any kind of
little rough spots around Linux the technology stack that's based around it or you want to
just put yourself in front of current technologies we were talking in fact speaking of user error
with Noah about learning Python and Ruby it's a great example of where Linux Academy can
help you bring you up to speed anything that might make you more money get the attention
of your employer make that client a little more inclined to go with you or just challenge
yourself they have courseware on the entire Linux platform and all of the cool technologies
built on top of it self-paced in-depth video courses on every Linux topic or really DevOps
topic to like this they really rest in there they got Azure OpenStack AWS as well learning
paths which are a series of courses and content planned by instructors for specific types
of career tasks which I find to be particularly valuable the hands-on experience if you're
a little test anxious like I am I mean I got to tell you I've never been a good cert passer
because I just get all worked up about these fake scenarios that's why hands-on experience
with the Linux Academy labs really gives me the experience to move forward like I'm ready
I've done it I've actually pushed the buttons that's super nice they have practice exams
and quizzes they have availability planners you can plug in how much time you have even
if you're super busy you got three kids in a podcast network trust me you can find time
at Linux Academy Linux Academy.com slash unplug with nuggets you can go into just deep dives
in specific areas they got search too if you want to go in for the search you just going
all in you got to get that on your resume they got great courseware for you downloadable
comprehensive study guides instructor help whenever you need it iOS and Android apps
to help you whenever you need that mobile experience lab service that spin up on-demand
and cert training that is above and beyond anything you've ever possibly thought of
I really have to recommend Linux Academy at Linux Academy.com slash unplug go check them
out it's a pretty cool platform backed by the Linux enthusiasts developers and educators
that came together to create something unique in the industry Linux isn't just a checkbox
on their feature list it's what they're all about Linux Academy.com slash unplugged and
a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring go check them out go try them go log in go
see what I love about it too stuff that in the past seemed like impossible I could never
actually achieve it I can never spend the time I can break it down individually into
chunks of time that I can wrap my head around and actually accomplish and that's what I
love about it Linux Academy thanks for sponsoring alright so this week is the big week Android
N hit our faces and of course everybody's got the write-up Android Authority Android
police ours Technica everybody's got their write-up on Android N it's good everybody
loves the new Doze features have been improved of course the multi window tasking all that
stuff the notifications all good we talked about some of it on tech talk today and I've
been running on the 6p I think it's it's it's definitely an improvement over and
Marshmallow but I some of my primary issues that plagued me with Marshmallow continue
to plague me with Android N and that is Doze kills Bluetooth audio I'm sitting there I'm
driving I'm 30 I'm 20 minutes into my drive say all of a sudden I start get cut every
podcast what's that yeah Doze is the new Android feature they launched in Marshmallow and then
doubled down in Nougat and that is depending on like if the phone's upside down face down
or if you're walking or if it's like midnight there's all these conditions that Android
is taking into account and if it thinks it's you're very unlikely to be using your phone
at this time it goes down yeah yeah wow which has really improved the battery life you'd
think they would have fine-tuned that for podcasting and audio and Pandora like if it
sucks it just sucks because I'm sitting there listening actually you know it's funny it's
it you know who it you know who it affects the most of everybody I know wimpy wimpy sitting
there making a great point on the Ubuntu podcast and all of a sudden every other word he says
starts getting dropped out and I'm not because because you know he speaks at a gentleman's
pace like I don't like is he like abbreviating his speech like at first I'm like I start
losing track of the conversation and then I realize it's dropping every few words from
the Ubuntu podcast this is just as I'm driving in today and I'm like what the hell is this
and this is the same problem I have with marshmallows ever since does was introduced and I you know
marshmallow seems to be good Nougat seems to be even better but I think it's just it's
just time the Chris gets off of Android and so is there no way to disable it yeah I don't
know like I think I could go in and say like whenever this application is running don't
save battery life but Android has such crappy battery life I was gonna say is it even saving
you that much battery no it does okay it is effective yeah yeah it does it mean I can
I can now go like two days without charging my phone if I push it which is oh that's big
whoa I heard of an Android I know but it kills the Bluetooth audio and so I have been from
a distance looking at different options I won't lie iOS feels very attractive because
I've been there before and I know that I get what I get and I don't complain you know you
just get what you get let me ask you're saying you're specifically saying Bluetooth yeah
if you had headphones plugged in that's what I do but then I lose all the controls well
no I don't have that problem with headphone jack when I that's what I use I got a little
like retractable headphone cable and I use the aux in but then I lose all of the controls
on my steering wheel so I don't get like skip ahead like or any or skip back or falling
I like I lose all of the controls on my steering wheel it which you know not a big deal so
I just do the headphone jack and that's what I've been doing for months and months actually
but it has kind of got me going through my head like I think I'm just I don't like the
way it performs I don't really enjoy some of the interface elements and I don't really
like the fact that they are tracking me like it is like a sensor in my pocket what about
turning on like isn't there a way to make the screen not turn off there are a few apps
I could use like force it to stay yeah I think I could actually like I think I could exclude
pocket casts from all those power management but then at the same time I'm while I'm driving
I'll be burning through my battery right I know yeah so it's not like does it does it
happen when you charge in the car as well yeah the the the dropouts do yeah in fact
West it almost seems like it happens faster which is oh wow yeah yeah so I'm not gonna
lie I've been looking I've been looking at the MX4 I've been looking I've been looking
at the one plus and there's this guy out there who's been giving me a hard time about it
for weeks and weeks and I I won't name names but wimpy you've recently switched you've
recently switched to Ubuntu touch I think you've been on for a couple of weeks and I
know that podcasts are a big part of your workflow and and all that I'd be I would really
love to hear thoughts because I know you and I have reflected on how Android doesn't quite
fit for us and we Ubuntu touch is sort of the perfect solution because every now and
then we just want something a little extra we like the flexibility of the platform we
know some of the folks behind it and it's an alternative to Android that is functional
and I and you've been actually living in it for a couple of weeks you've got multiple
devices I'd love to pick your head just go in there sort of like mind-meld style and
tell me what's it like to live as wimpy with an Ubuntu touch device okay um it took some
weeks of research to figure out what the apps on Ubuntu for devices were that could replace
or be alternatives or equivalents to what I was used to on Android yeah I bet and by
and large I've been able to find replacements for that and where it gets a little bit icky
is things like there are four or five different versions of Google Plus for example for Ubuntu
touch and are they all kind of repackaged versions of the web app and sort of kind of
there that so what you're starting to see now is people that are starting to use more
of the facilities of QML around the web wrapper to introduce more features into what is essentially
a web wrapped version but also doing clever things like using different agent strings
in that web wrapper to expose modern versions of the Google Plus UI right so what I've what
I've been doing is as I've been trying out the several different versions of Google Plus
for example is rating each of them based on my personal requirements so that the one that
I think is best gets the most stars and the others get diminishing star levels with my
rationale as to why they're not as good as the other option so I've gone through that
process and for things like Twitter and Facebook and Gmail and Google Plus and you know all
of the stuff you need to do obviously I don't have a WhatsApp problem because all of my
family are on Telegram so I don't have that big you know stopping block that is in front
of many people I have a completely functional experience I've got a few gaps in what I need
and I've I've decided at the outset I would find the apps that best met my requirements
and for example where there where there's an app that isn't quite good enough instead
of publishing a duplicate app I would reach out to the developer and work with them to
improve the existing app that's in the store rather than create even more versions of the
same thing because I don't think that's very helpful right so I've reached out to the author
of the Pocket Casts app and we're going to work together to make a slightly refined refined
version of Pocket Casts for Ubuntu Touch now how how much is it actually targeted for Ubuntu
Touch versus a modified repackage of the web version so the current version of Pocket Casts
is just a wrapped version of the website which is not bad actually which is very good and
the only drawback to that is that it was created about a year ago so it doesn't have the keep
the screen on keep the player moving so as the screen blanks the podcast stops so I've
contacted the author and said these are the improvements I would like to make and we're
going to work on that and produce a refined version that you know works properly and because
I'm a Pocket Casts user at the moment it's easier for me to use that than try and move
to Podbird which is a native podcasting app for Ubuntu for Devices and what I need to
do there is send some feedback to the developers of Podbird to say these are the features that
I feel need adding refining or improving in order for the native you know Podbird application
to be you know viable because listening to podcasts on my phone is very important to
me so full disclosure right now all of those things I said I can do on my MX4 the one thing
I don't do is listen to podcasts I still have an Android phone which I keep in the car and
I'm driving to and from work it is that device that is connecting over Bluetooth to the car
audio system to play the podcasts and that's for two reasons one I've got a podcast player
that works and two it's got Bluetooth that compare with the car and I've only got one
out of the many Ubuntu touch devices I've got there is only one that compare with the
car and what's curious about that is a few months ago they could all pair with the car
and now only one of them can so there's been some sort of regression there and I haven't
had the opportunity to dig around and identify what's going on but you know there are rough
edges but I don't have Android running anymore about my person on a day to day basis that's
very cool and I'm able to do all of the things that I could do before with a few caveats
so I'm going to one of the little projects I want to work on is write an app for buffer
because that's something I used to use quite extensively on Android and I think that that
can be neatly created using the Ubuntu framework it shouldn't be too complicated and it should
provide a totally analog experience cool you know I I think this is this is the perfect
moment because and she's here and she has without equivocation it rejected basically
everything iCloud she still plugs her phone in over a USB cable to sync all the stuff
over her photos her music and it's a huge part of her workflow and it's she doesn't
you know she doesn't want to auto update or auto upload her photos to iCloud she doesn't
want to sync her music through Apple music nope and and you're looking at this and you're
like I be honest do you feel like you're like on borrowed time with that platform to do
you yeah and and when when I hear wimpy talk about it I what I think about for somebody
like you is even if like everything else doesn't apply about the freedom or the or the platform
or or how they design it the fact that you could maybe find a workflow that you feel
comfortable with when the other platforms are kind of forcing yeah it's kind of appealing
right yeah and it's early days still but uh you know I'll uh I'll uh I'll let you know
when when it's ready to switch yeah there's some fixes coming in OTA 13 that I think are
really really interesting so there seems to be a lot of focus on refining what's there
at the moment and the last since OTA 10 it's really come on a long way so OTA 9 I still
wasn't convinced I could actually use it as a day-to-day device from OTA 10 I could because
in OTA 10 I could copy and paste between applications for example so you know that was three or
four months ago not being able to do that prior to then was really a I can't use this
day-to-day so that was that was what you might call a game changer yeah so you know I've
got two apps in the Ubuntu touch store at the moment and one of which is um last pass
mobile it's by no means as comprehensive as the last pass application on android but it
does mean that when I need to log into things I can open up last pass bring up the password
highlight it copy it and then paste it into the thing that I want to authenticate with
right which I couldn't do four months ago so you know the fact that that's possible
it is just that that was really that was the moment where I thought right I really need
to investigate this more seriously because I could make this work for me now I've I've
always felt like the place that would be the most successful for me would be on the tablet
first and then the phone so I want to get to that I also want to mention mini max he
has a question for you wimpy all of that but first before we go any further I got to say
thank you to Ange for stopping by she's got to run to go pick up the kiddos but Ange thank
you for stopping by yeah thanks for having me keeping us grounded wonderful to have you
and all the love I know and you can hear more from Ange in tech talk today go listen to
this week's episode or boy this week we had a Kickstarter of the week that is gonna sit
with me for a while it's gonna sit with me I get it get it yeah yeah all right wow thank
you for being here Ange yep all right so wimpy it's it's not just the phone I mean I know
the MX4 is your daily driver correct but you're also trying the tablet experience have you
noticed be honest wimpy does it work better as a tablet um does it work better as a tablet
it feels like the it feels like that interface that the whole unity 8 interface is begging
for a tablet UI it just it you know a little extra real estate but still mobile seems like
the perfect combo like maybe something on the BQ no I don't know I mean I I use I have
used you know when I was using Android I used the phone and the tablets differently and
I continue to use the phone and the tablet differently so I've got a BQM 10 tablet and
I also have a Nexus 7 that's also running ok Ubuntu touch the BQM 10 I'm mostly experimenting
with that as I could this be a laptop replacement yeah exactly and the recent advancements with
Libertine make that very plausible now because it's now possible if you've got a little bit
of knowledge about how to you know exercise come up the command line utilities you can
create containers of your favorite legacy X application and run them containers on my
tablet yeah so and there's a there's a nice guide that somebody wrote recently I'll get
a link in a moment that explains how Libertine is used to create containers of your app so
for example creating a container of mumble is very straightforward or audacity or gimp
or whatever it might be that you want to run on your tablet so that you can have a more
desktop like productivity experience actually create something on on your tablet oh yeah
it will it will effectively make the container that runs that app with a launcher so you
can just start gimp or audacity or mumble or whatever with icons you know that so that's
that's really very interesting the Nexus 7 is kind of my device that I use just for sort
of browsing and looking at stuff casually in the evenings so you know when I'm sitting
in the front room or cooking sure that's that's the device that I have to hand because it's
more convenient to use than a phone and it's easier to you know look at and yeah for for
that sort of stuff you know looking at YouTube catching up on podcasts dealing with email
and telegrams and all of the rest of it it all works just fine on the tablet and and
phone it certainly works better the MX4 is a slightly bigger screen than the Nexus 4
which I was using before and the bqe5 and certainly having a bigger screen is favorable
it's certainly much easier to use with a larger screen sure huh you know I I know it's just
I can't help but think of myself but I picture a day when I could actually publish something
like user error completely from the tablet that would be awesome right now Wes what would
it take for you to be able to use something for work like something that could actually
get your day-to-day job done what do you need from a tablet and do you have a tablet today
you know not really there there is a iPad I think it's like a couple generations old
by now that kind of floats around the house purely for consumption but it really doesn't
see very much use I think for work you know that that Liberty and stuff that would go
a long way sure I think also that you know last week we're talking about the improvements
to the terminal I think that would also go a long way if I could have a reasonable you
know a reasonable experience using thumb desktop apps and having you know SSH and just a friendly
Linux environment right by my side I'd be willing to cut it some slack in other yeah
me too me too exactly and I and I don't think that is it is I mean we can't deny this that's
a niche that's an that is absolutely but it is an industry now and there is a lot of us
men and women and in the hundreds of thousands that need to do that you think about every
small business that has more than a hundred employees they have somebody that could qualify
think of every large corporation I mean that is a massive massive amount of users that
is absolutely worth targeting and it could just grow from there I you know I tried to
buy the the BQ m10 when it went for sale I couldn't get it that the page was all kinds
of errors and it was just impossible and today I sit here with the Android and sick or I'm
sorry the 6p and I think to myself I would love to be able to take what I would love
to have the maybe it's maybe this is a 2018 thing but what I would love to have happen
is sort of like I can download ISOs now for general PC hardware I would love for Ubuntu
touch for a large range of great Android devices to be available and I and I realize that would
take a bunch of community commitment and interaction and work but God dang it would it be cool
if I could just go get the greatest and latest Nexus device and have a have a good solid
you know bet that within two to three months of the next Nexus 2016 device coming out I
could probably get an Ubuntu touch image for it and for the life of that device I could
run it right and then that's all I really think it would take for me or and wimpy I
know how you feel about this if I could get my hands on that MX5 hardware something that's
a real flagship device how's performance Chris is stringent stand because I am a bit of a
performance bigot wimpy so and you're on the MX4 I don't really know but my my rough understanding
is it's somewhat equivalent to the Nexus 4 and that seems like it would be ancient no
no no so I've got a Nexus 4 and the bqe5 okay this this MX4 is head and shoulders above
those in terms of performance when that is running Ubuntu touch but yeah is that is that
Ubuntu touch or is that is that the hardware because I might be basing my hardware requirements
on potentially bloated and Android requirements okay so definitely so it's the hardware basically
that makes it better there there are definitely improvements that could be made to Ubuntu
touch to improve the performance and perceived responsiveness of some of the UI and I think
talking to poppy you know there are some wet well understood things that need to happen
and there are some technical challenges as to why they have been addressed yet so I think
that will come in due course but the better the hardware gets the better the experience
get and the MX4 is significantly better than the Nexus 4 and the e5 and my understanding
is that that this pales in comparison to the pro 5 which is rarer than hen's teeth now
yeah and I I I really I was wanting to get and went on holiday around the time they were
released and thought I'll get one when I get back and they were all sold out yeah and now
you can't find them for that no money yeah yeah and if you want to load Android on that
I mean if you want to get the one that has Android loaded on it it looks like that probably
works for loading the initial image but there could be over-the-air update issues potentially
so as best as I've been able to determine reading some of the guides that are available
for that you can buy a pro 5 with the international firmware version of Android which is required
because the Chinese versions you can't unlock the bootloader but the international versions
you can so you have to have one with the international firmware you can then flash Ubuntu onto that
pro 5 but so far what I've read and I have haven't researched it very carefully there
seems to be some difficulty in flashing the Ubuntu recovery image onto that device which
then means that the over-the-air updates right won't apply automatically you have to go
into the recovery and extract those manually that kind of kills the fun so that's why you
haven't gone that route at the moment unless because it's they're quite expensive and I'm
not prepared to risk that unless I'm fairly sure of some success yeah it's kind of how
I feel too I just want to buy with Ubuntu pre-loaded and you were talking about you
know other devices there's a website called ubports.com yeah it's one of the community
members runs that site and that's crowdfunded and there's a list of devices there that can
run Ubuntu touch at various stages of completion and if you want to see Ubuntu come to one
of those devices then you come back the development effort for those devices and that's where
he will focus his attention and most of the nexus I think all of the nexus devices are
in there and some LG devices and the one plus one plus x one plus two so there's all sorts
in there oh I should talk to that guy because that sounds exactly like what I just got to
figure out which nexus device is well supported like the 5x would make a great great Ubuntu
touch device I would think yeah so it's in that it's in on the list hasn't actually started
yet but it's at priority three and the nexus 6p is also in the list as well hasn't hasn't
actually started yet so you know but there's someone there who's and he's been sponsored
by digital ocean I see as well there you go you know I will mention too just as we kind
of wrap up here I guess ZTE made the mistake of asking people what they want oof never
do that and now they've heard it and they've even suspected that there was some sort of
fraud involved so I encourage you not to do yeah I encourage you not to fraudulate this
but there is a poll going right now over on ZTE which if you've ever looked at new egg
for example some really nice ZTE devices are out there and and they're asking for input
from their community about maybe what can next generation projects they should work
on etc etc and OMG Ubuntu has generated some attention towards this initiative and I think
that's why they got so many votes and they're looking for possible ideas for 2017 that are
quote-unquote reasonable and I just want to give a shout out to this community effort
here because holy smoking crap did this write-up not only is it totally rocking the ZTE voting
right now with 88 upvotes but I two thousands who created this post did a true legitimate
like fortune 500 level proposal on why ZTE should create an Ubuntu touch device it's
really impressive yeah yeah you saw this I mean he goes to the breakdown different scenarios
different options for them to consider it's yeah yeah yeah and it I would I would I would
buy the shit out of this device if ZTE to this because I've looked at some of their
devices on new egg that are unlocked and been kind of tempted by them because they got front-facing
speakers they've seemed to have reasonable packaging for the price ZTE has consistently
caught my eye but not quite crossed that threshold for something that actually willing to spend
my money on but if they shipped a Ubuntu touch device a hands-down would buy one and if you
want to kind of just vote in that general direction I'll have a link in the show notes
for you to go voice your opinion I just think this is super important he says a brief summary
of the idea is ZTE should provide the following options people to choose when selling a phone
model pre-installed Ubuntu touch is the primary OS pre-installed Ubuntu touch is a secondary
OS alongside maybe something like Android or new Ubuntu or no Ubuntu touch installed
and only something like Android installed he talks about also including something like
a USB type-c connector and the advantages and the advantages of conversions and all
of it and I think it's a it's a brilliant post and ZTE would be a fantastic manufacturer
and I've heard I don't know wimpy if you've heard these things but I've heard some rumors
that perhaps BQ might not be doing another Ubuntu touch device have you heard that wimpy
I've seen it on Twitter I don't know what the authenticity of those claims are so I
don't either and it seems like it seems like they've sold as many as they can manufacture
of the Ubuntu devices so I don't I don't know about that either but maybe we'll see yeah
it's a bummer because at the moment you can't buy an Ubuntu phone anywhere no in fact unless
unless you go to eBay if if if today the MX5 Pro were available for purchase I think just
for Linux unplugged Linux action show alone it'd be worth me picking one up just to try
it but every time I go to their site they're sold out yeah yeah they they had a run and
I my understanding was they had an allotted production run and once they were sold out
they were gone so sounds like I see one of those experiment type things I mean Mac you
had a question go ahead yeah my question to wimpy would be what about multitasking do
they face the problems they had before for example when I was listening to music on the
Ubuntu touch I tested it on a Nexus 5 and then wanted to open the browser music stopped
so multitasking at the time I tested this but not really at a good level so that specific
example of audio playing there are facilities in the SDK now to continue playing in the
background good and I know pod bird the podcasting client supports that and there's another app
called cloud player they both continue to play audio when you switch away from them
and go and do other things so so long as the app has been updated to support those facilities
yes it can be done and my second question would be are the Ubuntu touch images all based
on the same Android base or does it depend on the different devices they run on I'm a
little bit not sure but my understanding is each device has got a slightly different Android
base origin so this is why some of the devices can support the Miracast wireless display
and some can't for example and why some can do fingerprint authentication and some can't
so I believe there is a correlation between the device and the Android version that it
can support and therefore what the functionality that it can expose is but next time Popeys
I'll ask him that question I know he's much more up to speed on that than me I've noticed
that I can say sorry what I can say Chris the Nexus 5 and I think you've got one of
these the Nexus 5 is normally a good device to test some of these images I run Sailfish
OS for example for the Nexus 5 and now it's based on Lollipop and this was a huge advantage
for Sailfish OS and so I guess if they port if they have a Lollipop base now for Ubuntu
touch it would run rather good you know I think this is more poignant than ever we started
this segment with the release of Android N and it's a pretty solid release you know
if you like Android it's just Android even better but if you don't like Android it's
everything you don't like even worse but at also at the same time if you're a Nexus
5 user Wes then you just you just got dropped from support where Ubuntu touch has come along
and they're kind of you know just picking up momentum how do you feel about that yeah
you know I can understand it but it is a little disappointing I mean there's lots of ROMs
to try I am kind of just holding out on this phone until the next Nexus line drops we'll
see when that is but yeah it does make me way more incentivized to try something else
and I played with Ubuntu touch on here probably like a year ago and I haven't visited back
so maybe I'll give that a flash here as soon and see what it's like so I just posted a
link in the chat room which is to the UB ports Nexus 5 build they've got green ticks in everything
except for Bluetooth support so the Nexus 5 version can support everything except for
Bluetooth so it is very close and when I got my first Ubuntu touch device it was about
14-15 months ago and things have improved massively since then yeah you know isn't it
when you come from Android wimpy isn't it kind of novel all of a sudden just see constant
improvements to your OS like on a reoccurring schedule it is and you know that's that's
kind of tainted because you you look at Ubuntu touch having and I've been using Android since
2010 2011 so you know that's a lot you know Google have got massive resources they've
been able to throw an Android and make it this dominant platform so you look at Ubuntu
and you think oh you know there is there is these little paper cut type issues but then
when you go and look what the upcoming releases are in the next OTA you see so many of these
paper cuts being addressed now that's exhilarating in a sense it is and you know part of me wanting
to do this wasn't so much about running Ubuntu touch but it was to really capture some of
that spirit and enthusiasm I had for Linux way way back when I first discovered Linux
in the in the mid to late 1990s and that sort of pioneering spirit and it's not perfect
yet but it could be and you can be part of the solution even if all you do is run it
and tell the developers yeah it could be better if you did this right that's part of the reason
why I'm doing doesn't it doesn't it and I okay I want to say two things first of all
before we go much further here it's not like I'm all of a sudden drinking the Kool-Aid
but as I have become more comfortable with Antigros and Ubuntu Mate and Fedora as as
my go-to desktops I'm it is freeing me up conceptually to just let go of the Ubuntu
default desktop and let them focus on mobile because it doesn't affect me anymore and I
don't have a horse in this race and so I can now look at the Ubuntu touch project from
a more dispassionate perspective because in the past I carried my baggage I carried the
baggage of you sons of bitches are working on this mobile project instead of my desktop
how dare you and I came with that bias towards Ubuntu touch but now and and wimpy I'm not
just saying this to blow smoke up your proper butthole it is generally because of projects
like Ubuntu Mate and honestly the gnome desktop that I just don't give a shit what happens
to unity really personally that I have been able to step back and just watch this new
effort of theirs from a completely new perspective and I look at this and it is totally exciting
for me and so that is number one I just want to I just want to mention that's kind of
my perspective on on this overall but number two we all we all have concerns I think to
some degree about the privacy of using an Android device or an Apple device we all have
concerns to some degree about how to install applications on our device outside the channels
that are pushed by the platform and we all have concerns about being able to modify our
device in a way that suits us and so in that regard as a technology enthusiast Ubuntu touch
has always managed to check those boxes for me and I now I sit back and I really think
it's boy it's a matter of hardware for sure and I'm still waiting for the perfect
hardware but once that comes along for me be it the 5x or you know I'm looking right
now over at UBports and it appears that if if I were to donate Bitcoin in the equivalent
of five hundred and ten dollars which for me would be less than one Bitcoin right now
it would all of a sudden the Nexus 6p would become a priority for them that's less than
the next smartphone if I were to buy it unlocked for me if I could take my Nexus 6p and donate
five hundred ten dollars equivalent of Bitcoin to this project and have a and maybe one day
have a have a version for the Nexus 6p then I could just continue to use my current hardware
until that comes out but yeah but aside from from all of that I think the point that you
made wimpy is what excites me the most and that is it feels like the early two thousands
the late late nineties where it's not ready for everybody but if you're willing to sort
of get in and get in the mud a little bit you can make this a viable platform one day
for everybody else by banging on the rough edges commenting giving feedback maybe even
making bug fixes is sort of what drew me to Linux a decade ago and do you find that to
be sort of the position you find yourself in now with Ubuntu touch wimpy absolutely
and I'm by no means a pioneer here because there are people that have been running these
devices as their main phones for 18 months or more now who are far more advanced in how
they're putting apps together and there's some quite sophisticated apps available now
so there's one called rockworks which is available from the open store and I have complete support
for both my pebble watches with Ubuntu touch using and the experience on my pebble watch
is exactly as I had it on Android with no no shortcomings whatsoever so you know there
are there are not many but they're the ones that exist the native apps are getting very
very good now and are solving real problems and it feels like it's really got momentum
and there's there's some talented people behind it and but yeah there's still some good work
to be done that you can have maybe yeah some influence in right absolutely I mean like
I said even if it's just commenting on the apps in the App Store to say this Twitter
app is better than that Twitter app because you know and up rate the ones that are good
so that other people don't have this dilemma as to well which of the several Twitter apps
should I install but also I think there are a few proprietary applications for Ubuntu
touch but most are open source so there are issue trackers that you can go and find and
you can actually have dialogue with the developers directly which of course is difficult to do
on some of the other platforms so just just by sharing your ideas you can have some involvement
in shaping individual apps and and the device as a whole that is you know for those of us
who are enthusiasts that's sort of a delightful era for a new platform and it's rare because
once the platform becomes established and lots of users it sort of passes and you know
it's your chance to be sort of a hipster before it's famous but in a way that is empowering
for those of us that want to move away from the Google platform and you know privacy concerns
and you know pioneering spirit aside obviously the main reason I've done this is because
I want to be an Ubuntu touch hipster I don't believe you for a second but the other two
reasons I do believe yeah and I really am thankful that you've joined us again and give
us an update and it kind of makes me wimpy I tell you if there's a way to make it possible
if the MX5 becomes available again I think I'm gonna jump on it is or or wait for a Nexus
5 image to really kind of get Bluetooth ironed out and then jump on that and at least try
it for a bit because it really is for me the perfect time to jump in I love this phase
of a new platform as long as it has just enough stuff yeah just enough stuff that I can get
by day to day I I'll tell you I'll tell you something I I you know using Android N and
iOS 9 shit ton of problems still tons of problems totally unbelievable the shit that doesn't
work on these platforms this long into it I sit there and I think to myself how could
they not have caught this and if I'm gonna feel that way anyways you know if I'm gonna
if I'm gonna say Aaron shake man go damn it Google why didn't you think of this problem
I might as well be using something where I can submit bugs I can have some kind of discourse
in the evolution of the platform and I can at least be there when when there's a rational
explanation why some of these things don't work and I know that seems like a weird cognitive
disconnect from but it generally it drives me crazy to use these more modern platforms
or feature complete platforms or whatever you want to call them and they still have
some of these fundamental usability issues at the end of the day I just need certain
base functionality and the rest is all gravy and so I just am waiting for the perfect hardware
device to come along and and maybe maybe I need to reassess my requirements because I'm
looking at it from a perspective an Android user but I don't know wimpy you tell me do
I is there a one-to-one performance ratio between Ubuntu touch and Android or can I
get away with maybe a little less hardware using Ubuntu touch because maybe I'm not running
Java etc no not really like I said there are some interactions with Ubuntu touch the user
interface that are slower than the hardware is capable of so you want the best hardware
if you if you if your Nexus 5 is spare definitely put the current image for the Nexus 5 on it
it's a community port so it's not as robust as the officially blessed versions yeah but
it does give you a flavor of where things are now and you know how your Nexus 5 performs
with Android so you can make that comparison and some of the how do you characterize it
it's it's just the way Ubuntu works at the moment and I'm sure this is going to get ironed
out in the not too distant future but when it does you can so there are some apps that
are just C and they bypass some of the framework and those applications when you start them
they launch instantly like there's your fingers not off the screen and they're running but
a lot of the apps that are using the framework they have the little spinner that gets them
going when they get started up so you have to sort of go into it knowing you're not going
to have this immediate snap snap snap type experience yeah I think on the pro 5 it's
much better because that's a super fast much beef beefier machine yeah yeah the hardware
that's doing that yeah have you just kind of tangently related have you seen the announcement
from the cute project of cute light I have only in passing not really in detail that
might that might help with some of that because you know let's be honest if you're if you're
using cute based applications there's a lot there and if there's something like cute
light that could come along and sort of they're kind of they're focusing cute light more
of the Internet of Things type devices but you could also see it working on something
like Ubuntu touch and perhaps think of think of cutie light as more of a minimal build
from base up of cute functions whereas the traditional cute environment is huge it's
got everything you need to do everything you could possibly want including touch support
which is extremely useful but it also means that when you load the applicant when you
load I would think I'm totally speculating here but when you load a cute application
for the first time there's a lot of other things in the background you have to load
to support that where cute light could sort of tighten that up a bit I don't know a lot
about it but I was just reading about it today and it seems like it could be the perfect
thing for Ubuntu touch and then you combine that with the fact that canonical has recently
become a backer of KDE EV which is the commercial entity behind KDE yeah yeah and and you know
Ubuntu has also got support for Cordova yes react something or other another Java that's
the one yeah JavaScript you know libraries for making native apps so that word needs
to get propagated because there are lots of people that have created their apps using
those frameworks that could come over directly without any any messing about you know it's
interesting we've talked about LibreVault and Ubuntu touch and they both have the big
huge you know marquee scrolling or HTML flashing tag warning that this is early days on both
of these Ubuntu touch and LibreVault at the same time I think for our audience they're
both getting to the point where if you kind of have a pioneering spirit for this particular
thing be it your file sync or your mobile device and fully acknowledging that both of
these things for some people are critical day-to-day devices that must be completely
flawless but if if some of you out there have that pioneering spirit for either one of these
types of technologies it's for both of them getting to be time for that type of person
to jump in and that is super exciting for somebody like me because that's exactly the
type of person that I am and I think of a lot of our audience is to watch this stuff
from this part and go boy you know I'm really like for me wimpy I'll be completely honest
I am thrilled that for the last couple of weeks you've been running Ubuntu touch because
I get updates from you on how it's going and I can I can kind of project how would how
that would translate for my experience and you're making you're giving me baited breath
you're making my mouth water you're making me want to switch and I think it's super exciting
and it's funny because I don't know if either one of you you or myself would recommend or
probably West would recommend that people go deploy LibreVault or Ubuntu touch for their
daily driver today but it definitely is ready for a certain class of us or a certain type
of user and wimpy just to kind of wrap it all up would you kind of give us an idea of
the range of devices you're trying it just that we kind of a full picture of your experience
that way when it does blow up and I mean if it ever does blow up in your face we have
an idea of what you test on because I was kind of impressed when you can share it with
me. Okay I've got a Nexus 4, a Nexus 7 tablet, a BQE5 HD phone, the Meizu MX4 and the BQM
10 tablet. Damn son! Whoa! Yeah that's quite a lot of devices. You know if you if you do
have that pioneering spirit and you want to experiment then consider getting yourself
a Nexus 7 2013 or a Nexus 4 off eBay because they go quite cheap now and they are officially
supported devices for Ubuntu touch so they come direct from the canonical channels and
you can be involved in actually testing these things and trying them out you know that you
don't have to make it your daily device you know I didn't for over a year I had a you
know one pound SIM in my Nexus 4 for months and months and months experimenting with it
before I determined it was time to make the move but you know you can participate at that
level. Yeah well shoot you're making me want to try it especially on a tablet I know right
I'm excited. Have you tried on any of your devices? Just the Nexus 5 but oh yeah that's
right it was a while ago yeah yeah it was it'll probably be a much better experience.
Yeah maybe when the next Nexus device comes out and you got the 5 sitting around you could
try it out and give us the unplugged take. I think I will. I like it. Well there you
go that sort of brings us to the end of this week's discussion we have lots of links to
all the stuff we talked about. Don't forget if you're like me and you'd love to see a
Ubuntu touch on the Nexus 6P the ubports.com a devices.ubports.com specifically has a funding
page on it that'd be pretty damn cool and if you're getting finally to the end of this
extremely long episode of the unplugged program and you want more go check out user air episode
one is over at jupitabroadcasting.com right now as we record this very episode. Wes thank
you for making it despite real life diversity. Hey thank you for I love being here. Absolutely
absolutely and you know what if the folks at home wanted to join us it turns out we
have a diabolical plan you could join us over at jblive.tv on a Tuesday. Oh what time
you ask. Clever of you. Go to jupitabroadcasting.com slash calendar where we have robots that automatically
adjust it to your time zone in real time before the page even loads. Thank you robots. Thank
you right. They don't and I think they probably run Ubuntu touch too. I haven't confirmed
it yet. Definitely. I just got them on eBay. Also litxactionshow.reddit.com if you want
to give us some feedback for episode 159 or submit a topic and don't forget you can join
us on our virtual lug get more information in our chatroom at jblive.tv and we'll see
you right back here next week.
All Wimpy's Vault. That's a good title. That's pretty good. That's good though. Oh yeah yeah
yeah boy look at that look at that text highlighting yeah thanks to Ange for stopping by she had
to go because we went so long but that was great that was a lot of fun sorry sorry about
that no no it was a bit of an epic no no you know I love it you know I love it so now we
just we just have to name this thing over JBtitles.com with the new suggest with the
new fancy updated website thanks to Rekai and team the JBot has gotten some recent refreshes
actually and I can actually say this now we go into some quite some detail about the changes
to JBot and how we do that and the code and the community members involved in user error
episode one it was really fun so I employ you you have multiple disks that you're going
to be pulling in and out and mismatched sizes and all that kind of stuff right I don't know
I probably just because the necessity of budget over time that'll have to be how it works
but I would like to start with a base and I think storage I think that's overlooked
with ZFS sorry British ZFS because if there's like a hidden cost to an upgrade when you
think right I've run out of storage you need to add a whole new pool or replace three four
five drives all at once and you know I don't know about you but when I fill up a disk I
just want to buy another three terabyte drive whack it in there and call it good and to
do that I use something called merger FS which presents all of the drives in my system under
a single mount point using a fuse files them and I'm running in it on a see you 750 as
rock board yeah so it's a union file system that sort of brings them all in under one
mount point huh yeah and all you do is you modify your mount point in FS tab sorry whoever
I talked over your mount point you modify your mount point with one line or you just
do a mount command and it will add the drive that you've just plugged in into the the fuse
where that is just a mount and I've been using it for I mean I tried MHDFS or whatever it's
called I tried another union file system and then after about 18 months of lots of ghost
files and messing about I settled on merger FS about a year ago yeah and since then Chris
it's been absolutely perfect no performance penalties really or there must be some right
because this is a fuse it uses a bit of CPU yeah it uses a bit of CPU but I have a atom
cause and when I'm transcoding a couple of Plex streams around my house I don't notice
any difference whatsoever absolutely oh and to dovetail with that there are two plugins
for open media vault that support those technologies so that you can grow your file system without
having to employ a traditional raid and you don't have to have matched size disks for
growth I forgot the best bit merger FS doesn't stripe file systems across the drives yes
this drive has its own individually readable file system so even if you exceed your redundancy
level you only lose the data on the drives that failed in excess of that level and you
can still read you plug that drive into any other Linux box and just read the data you
know that'd be a perfect way to like have some drives for TV shows that I don't really
care about on this disk that's not as redundant too because I've thought about doing like
these are my cheaper disks these are my more important keepsakes on on open media vault
the plugins you want to look at our gray hole and snap raid they provide those facilities
that plus one I just just separate huh well this is good stuff yeah you need to set up
you need to set up a cron job for the sink of the parity to run every night or something
like that otherwise you're effectively running the data that day doesn't have any parity
protection or you can force a sink if you like but I spent probably the best part of
three years getting down to this final docker snap raid and merger FS on top of Debian which
in my case I chose to roll myself but you know it will work on top of open media vault
just perfectly with plugins with a gooey I don't need any of that because I can just
SSH from my phone into my server and it just don't you know I remember now that I'm looking
at the gray hole website I have also looked at gray hole as potentially doing a segment
on last about it and I never even thought about setting it up for storage that is slick
so snap it raid or snap raid or snap raid dot IT if you want to go to the site and gray
hole dot net for gray hole which is an application that uses Samba to create a storage pool of
all your available hard drives and allows you to create redundant copies of the files
you store in order to prevent data loss when part of your hardware fails have you had any
inclination at all to try out the not sure how you say it in LA s and one email client
that has the hosted component and is electron ish I did try it when it was first announced
I created a gash Google account to hook it up to so I could but basically so I could
just see what the UI was like and use it and all the rest of it and every so often I kind
of update it and I haven't I haven't done what Wes has done which is host my own middleware
for want of a better description you know that piece that does the brokering between
the client and your back end servers I've just used their hosted platform because it
was a disposable account I'll tell you what I what I found what I what always draws me
to Thunderbird is how how how much I like the enigma GPG plug-in and whenever I want
to have a good secure emails setup it's such an attractive easy to use simple straightforward
system that works well with my workflow and I think it's finally been beat by n1 simply
also because it's been easier for the audience to find me on Keybase and so that tends to
be what they sign against and and one has one one check integration with Keybase and
it hit it is it has taken that ease of use to the next level and from what I can tell
appears to be a pretty secure implementation and all that's being done locally in the composer
so so the the advantage of Keybase being easy discoverability of your keys yeah so you can
have seamless email exchanges well and you know I kind of like there they have an interesting
approach to verifying who you are you know because one of the things that's really kind
of the weak spot of GPG in reality is the web of trust works best when you can go to
a con or a fest or a or a live event and you know everybody there can do a little key exchange
and hi I'm so-and-so it's really me here's my key that works well but it doesn't work
at scale and what Keybase allows you to do is connect to other online presence that are
well established and trusted and then by building up several of them and also in some cases
I think in mine I'm using something Bitcoin related to like there's something there that's
it's pretty concrete it's like three or four for me different these are obviously really
Chris Lass's account so it gives the audience some confidence now you have to have certain
faith in Keybase IO and assume they're setting it up right but those implementation details
to me seem to be interesting concepts mm-hmm okay yeah I it's just finding the time I'm
interested in Nihilus because I think it looks like a nice user in base yeah and I like their
ability to tag emails for follow-up so I can I can technically have read them and process
them but I don't have to take action on it immediately I can come back another time and
that's also nice and then it has it has interesting and I didn't even realize it was because I
just I guess it's just turned on by default and some male clients support it is it does
read receipts by default and what's interesting about that is it's it's also integrated with
the desktop environment notification so I'm off doing something else and I just get a
quick gnome notification that so-and-so has read the email I sent them and then it slides
away and I you would think that's it's actually kind of neat it makes email feel a little
more 2016 first of all the fact I'm getting a gnome notification about it but also just
how seamless that was I didn't really have to do anything yeah that's a good point because
yeah I I always I emails that have got read receipts with deep suspicion yeah I agree
I didn't realize it was on by default they also by default put a little a promo for the
email client and the signature and it's a little tricky to get rid of it because when
you go to the signatures configuration it has nothing listed if you've never created
one and the only way to get rid of the default one that puts in there is by creating one
yeah I like okay very nice guys