This is Linux Unplugged Episode 13 for November 5th, 2013.
Hi everyone and welcome to Linux Unplugged, the Linux talk show that just can't wait to build
email 3.0 on top of an open source system. My name is Chris. My name is Matt. Hey there Matt.
Hey man. 13 weeks buddy, 13 weeks in a row and you know this week, this week I feel like we're
going to talk about one of my all-time like soapboxes that I always get on. We need to
replace email. We need to just we need to get rid of it and there's been a lot of there's been a
lot of you know alternatives. BitMessage is one that I've talked a lot about but it just hasn't
really gotten traction. It's got a lot of issues around it but the Dark Mail Alliance, the Kickstarter
has officially kicked off. I want to explain what it is, what they're trying to accomplish,
talk about it technically, how they're going to pull it off and then hopefully at the end of it
some people will go over and contribute to the Kickstarter project if they think it's worth it
and we'll see a new open source email alternative emerge in 2014. Good stuff. Yeah yeah and you know
it's funny because I'll tell you what I really wanted to talk about this week. I don't know if
you saw this but the Verge got their well Verge and others got their hands on Steam Box, Steam
Machine prototypes. I saw that. Oh my god. I know and I thought you know I can make a whole episode
about this but I I'm gonna we'll do a round up in the Linux Action Show on Sunday but uh I'm so
excited and you know what you know what I'm a little jealous they went down to Bellevue right
that's like that's that's like 40 minutes from my house oh my god Val's office is like 40 minutes
from my house we gotta get in there Matt we gotta get in there get some get our hands on some of
this stuff I'm marching through the door with cameras in hand you know excuse me Gabian excuse
me uh the Linux Action Show and Linux Unplugged and uh we need to see this device right now
exactly uh but we'll have a whole round up in uh this week's episode of the Linux Action Show
so however I'll tell you I was like oh we gotta talk about this day we gotta talk about this day
but then then something of serious consequence happened uh we thought it might happen mentioned
it in the Linux Action Show this Sunday uh uh Ladar Levinson announced uh his Dark Mail Alliance
Kickstarter so we're gonna dig into the nitty gritty of that and I pulled a few clips they kind
of had the most unique Kickstarter video I've ever seen um where they took essentially what it was
it was like a walk at a um uh I guess a meeting of people who run mail servers I'm not even sure
what it was it was definitely the most unconventional Kickstarter video I've ever seen
and it maybe wasn't the greatest however uh since I recorded a few clips from this video they've
raised seven thousand dollars in like two hours whoa so they're definitely on the right track so
the video didn't really matter but so instead of making you watch the whole uh 23-minute video
quick clips about what they're trying to do and I think what's even more interesting is the
technology behind it it's uh it's it's it's definitely an SMTP replacement it's not fully
compatible with SMTP but I think maybe in light of what's happened recently people might be they
might be ready for it interesting yeah I wanted to give a shout out not to the man on the line here
but to uh listener Matt who is in Seattle right now and he has been a listener of the Linux Action
Show since episode one and uh he uh he emailed us and said hey Chris uh I'd like to take you
out and buy you a beer and uh you know wine and dine me probably wanted to sleep with me to be
honest with you man it's the hair it's the hair Matt it's clearly the hair it's always the hair
we're all drawn to you I don't know I can't help it it's like a big magnet I don't know what to
tell you man it's uh anyways he emailed me and he said uh hey I'd like to take you out and I said
you know what can't sorry because we're doing Linux unplugged right we're doing Linux unplugged
we can't do it so I want you to know I just passed up free beer and food for this show
that's a big thing well so um last week we talked about systemd we talked about systemd and we
talked about upstart and we talked about Debian's upcoming choice and the ramifications it might
have in the broader Linux ecosystem a lot of good a lot of good responses to that uh episode
so we're gonna do more like that in the future um you know as these big topics come up that there's
a lot of ambiguity around I think the show can kind of stand out by helping cut through some of
that and and discuss the real issues without all of the drama around it and things like that yeah
so the bulk of our email this week our our follow-up so the beginning of the unplugged
show we like to do a lot of f you that's our follow-up and uh sometimes it meets its name
and sometimes it doesn't but uh so we're gonna cover some of that uh but uh we have uh two
sponsors in this week's episode of Linux unplugged both Ting and DigitalOcean so I thought I'd tell
you about one of our sponsors up front before we get into it and that first sponsor of course
is my mobile service provider and Matt's Ting.com now Ting is mobile that makes sense and you can go
to linux.ting.com to get started and one of the great things about Ting is there's no contracts
no early termination fees that's that's huge that's huge on its own that tells you a little
bit about Ting right there also you only pay for what you use if you only use 30 minutes of talk
time then that's what you pay for if you only use 200 megabytes then that's what you pay for if you
need a gigabyte you get that included in your plan as hotspot and tethering Ting often sees themselves
as an ISP not so much as a phone company but as just mobile data and that's that's brilliant
that's exactly what I need because I'm one of the people who likes to buck the system I want to try
to get the most out of my cell phone bill by using VoIP services and things like that and Ting is
is a company built from enthusiasts by enthusiasts and you can see it through and throughout their
culture in fact if you go over to the Ting help center I got an email from a listener today who
said hey Chris I switched my family over to Ting and we're loving it it's been great and I noticed
in some of your ads you've mentioned that you have a couple of tricks to skirt around using your
cellular data now in the holidays this is hard for me to avoid because family members just call my
traditional phone but I'll tell you yeah and that's what honestly Matt like you know what
that's what's great about paying for what I need because in in November and December and in January
too when my when my phone minutes go way up I just pay for what I needed that month it's it's not a
huge deal right but here here's a little glimpse into the Ting corporate culture on the community
forums they have a post that I've referenced several times when just setting up a new android
device called reducing my bill via free texting and calls over wi-fi where they have outlined
how you can use different apps in the android play store to use wi-fi whenever possible to
make a phone call now think about that this is a phone company that has in their community forms
a document that is instructing you on how to avoid using minutes that's crazy I mean you'll never see
that with any other carrier never see that with any other carrier no and when you combine that
with ting's pay for what you use no contract and they have excellent devices and they're always
adding new devices they're adding new deals in fact the phone that matt has the note 2 is on sale
currently you can save 31 on top of what you're going to save if you go over to linux.ting.com
you can take 25 off your first device or if you got your own device you're going to bring
you can take 25 off your first month of service you end up paying for what you use you're not
locked into a contract it's on your terms and then you combine that with their amazing dashboard
man you're really cooking with gas it's really awesome not only that not only that but ting's
going to help you get rid of a used device they've got the they've partnered with glide so if you're
going to switch to ting and get a new device they'll help you sell your old device they'll
help you buy a used device if you want to save some cash like i started they got right now for
example the evo 4g with y max 123 bones off contract all yours you can pick up the nexus s
245 bones off contract all yours they've even got feature phones i mean there's all kinds of options
from ting and now is really time to get started because the sooner you switch the sooner you'll
start savings and speaking of savings they have a savings calculator they've got it linked over
at linux.ting.com you click that you put in your bill information your minutes your text message
your megabytes and then you can really see what ting offers you combine that with the early
termination relief program will give you up to 75 per device you have to get cancelled from your
current contract and now you're really cooking with gas so go over to linux.ting.com and thanks
to ting for sponsoring linux unplugged thank you i love my ting phones i've got a couple of them
oh and i'm just in love in the fact that i'm not married to any one particular plan depending on
how i'm using it that that's really awesome i totally agree our first email this week comes
in from jim and he's says hi christen matt thanks for the great show on systemd versus upstart
adoption and debian i wanted to weigh in regarding matt's comment on that upstart was the obvious
choice for debian i agree with his logic that it seems the most conservative way to go in the near
term but i think he missed the importance of canonical cla i never use debian myself except
for as a foundation for other districts of course i've considered it and even burned to a cd with
iso about a year ago but never installed it when i read when i read that time was part of debian's
mission statement was that it would be free forever i'm paraphrasing here of course consequently i
think matt's otherwise logical assumption that debian would go with a tired and true upstart
over perhaps less than well-tested systemd in the short term may not happen so he's saying the cla
might be a bigger blocker now you you were pretty confident i i am and i think that's a that's a big
consideration and it's one they're going to have to wrestle with i mean keeping in mind these are
folks that actually had a fit about the whole firefox trademark stuff and actually adopt you
know and and went to ice weasel because of it you know and i'm not saying that's bad or good it's
just their opinion so i mean it's a factor but i'm still not convinced yeah what would happen if
they forked it and like and like then they maybe like that's like a compatibility pact like hey
canonical that's kind of what i'm thinking yeah i i think that's what's going to happen i think
upstart at some point at some level is going to either they're going to use it as it is or they're
going to find a way around any uh issues as far as licensing and whatnot you know i i don't know
if you saw the headline and i'm trying not to read too much into it i wasn't even going to mention it
but this just fits right in uh today we saw that debian is considering switching to x or i think
they have decided to switch to xfce for their default desktop now one of the reasons i would
imagine doing that is because gnome 3 has a dependency on systemd and by switching to xfce
they remove that dependency and i can't remember what episode it was but i actually mentioned that
at one point i bet that they would i can't and it makes sense for debian too i think
it's just it's what that's their whole approach is to not get in the middle of these of these
linux wars basically just to step back and say what's the most neutral logical place for us to
be and i think that's kind of what they're doing i agree i agree i agree and uh i mean this if
anything prevents them i mean i'd love to see them choose systemd on it from a technical standpoint
but i really think gosh i mean after i saw this move to xfc i thought oh i think matt might be
right i think matt might be right now that's not to say they're going to outwardly directly just
automatically adopt it without any hassle or drama or whatever i think that they're going to
find a way to maneuver around it through it over it it won't be a direct thing but it will be
through upstart interesting interesting all right uh so you know now the big question is when we
find out what they're going to do uh mt wrote in and uh he said that in the subject line the feature
of linux should be independent hello chris and matt love the show but i wanted to go out on a
little rant here uh because i hate how we the linux community are always supposed to be held
back because of the bsds one major point in your systemd versus upstart discussion was that systemd
doesn't support the bsds however i i disagree this is a problem we as the linux community should
strive to push linux forward to make it the best contender for our needs the bsds do not like us
they don't need our help with any project like katie gnome etc but then demand that we consider
them they bash us they hate us on their mailing list but then when linux wants programs but then
they want their linux programs to run on bsd they rely for years on gcc but as soon as they switch
to something else they bash gcc as if it was not providing them with a faithful service for years
i just think that we are so worried about the bsds while they're clearly not giving a crap about us
so why should we cripple the progress of linux platforms because of the bsd i'd love to hear
your opinion on this mt boy you know i think first and foremost we're talking about a vocal minority
much as we see in the linux community where there's a vocal minority that tend to be the
loudest and proudest and you know most vocal i think it's the same thing in the bsd community
i think most bsd people honestly don't care i think the vocal people probably the ones that
are being affected by the various things you know certainly i can see i can see where it's
point but i wouldn't go say the entire community as a whole i would say that's basically affecting
a vocal group and as far as what we should be doing with linux and whether we should be ignoring
them or not honestly you know i agree with the linux going forward stuff and you know i agree
with that i say look at it like this um bsd isn't asking how they can make beehive their new
virtualization layer run on top of linux they're just going ahead and making the best virtualizer
possible for bsd and i i actually want to take what mt is saying and maybe flip it a bit and say
i think sometimes when we i think sometimes it's justified to say what you know what kind of
decision the gnome project or kd project are doing is going to impact kd because it is the goal of
those projects to be available for those distros and so as debbie as a platform they want to help
support the goals of the software that sits on top of their platform so i wouldn't discount
debbie's concern and consideration for the bsds but i would zoom out and say
we shouldn't discount our bsd cousins it's almost kind of like insulting in the sense to say well
if we don't provide them with this they'll have nothing because they can't do it on their own
right and i think sometimes like developers fall into that trap a little bit like the bsd community
is fully capable of creating their own awesomeness that they need for to suit their own needs just
fine and that's why the linux community should feel free to go off on their own direction and
create their awesomeness because the bsd community is going to do it too and i think it's kind of a
little demeaning to sit here and go well if if we don't provide gnome just right then the bsds will
be left out you know what the bsds can solve it themselves and this is true you know yeah so i
agree i think mt raises an interesting point uh but he does seem a little a little upset about it
yeah i i mean obviously this is something he's probably read about or maybe even come in direct
contact with but at the same time let you know you're dealing with a vocal minority of people
that feel that way and that's that's their opinion you know don't no need to get sucked into it yeah
yeah uh so james writes in james writes in he says um i've listened to last linux unplugged show a
couple of times over now it was a very good show in my opinion i do have a minor complaint though
once again the size of ubuntu's user base was brought up in an attempt to give their side more
legitimacy namely as a reaction to the charge that ubuntu is the only distro using upstart
sadly everyone bought right into it as usual and didn't even bring up some very major caveats that
go with that number one ubuntu does not have a huge user base or i'm sorry ubuntu does have a
huge user base that's absolutely true however they have a huge user base of highly non-technical
desktop users with little to no actual linux experience they don't know their desktop gets
from they don't know how it gets from grub to light dm nor do they care you know that's kind
of true but it's like yeah yeah that's stereotyping because i think there's lots of technical users
that use ubuntu i would agree in that a growing the the growth is coming from new from newbies
no question the growth of numbers is coming from newbies however actual numbers i would say that
it's pretty well balanced that's not to say that people aren't migrating to other distros but i
would say that the growth is coming from the newbies but the sustained base is coming from a
mix he says on the other hand you got fedora reddit enterprise linux open sucess less enterprise and
of course you got arch all currently using are going to systemd that's a seriously massive user
base of a bunch more more technical users in every area desktop workstation service clusters cloud
deployments etc i'm not really sure where or when the current trend of dismissing the actual linux
power users or professionals began but i think it's past time it stopped unfortunately i'm almost
positive dab you know end up going with upstart canonical seems to have their claws sunk in pretty
deep with that community if they do it's going to be a very detrimental to the future of their
project in my opinion and i and i kind of grow tired of saying this over and over but honestly
these things take care of themselves the market will in fact in this particular case the community
as a whole will decide which option is best for them and it very well may be a mixture so do you
think though i get tired of the victim crap with the markets okay well so with the market approach
what we sometimes end up with is like a half implemented solution right we get um i mean so
if debian bought in with systemd essentially there would be one standard to rule them all
right there would be one interface to c groups there'd be all this kind of api's that systemd
would provide if debian doesn't buy into systemd because the market decides they should go with
upstart then there will be a more pronounced division in the underlying internals of linux
right and that's true that's true i guess my big gripe of the the big underlying gripe i have is
that rather than concentrating on promoting talking up sharing yeah you know the things
that you're into the distros that you are into why do we spend you know why does the community
spend so much time hand wringing over something that news flash kids you have zero control over
you don't you can pretend like you do all day but you don't so we we have to decide let's you know
how do we take the stance i agree that we need to you know be mindful of what we use on our individual
systems but the but you got to be careful not to fall into the victim trap and i don't mean
that in a derogatory sense i mean that factually you you come out you come out on the losing end
of it really yeah yeah the victim camp yeah you got to avoid that you got to avoid that
this doesn't work yeah and it's hard when you get really you get wrapped up into it you know and you
see you know anytime anytime an issue becomes clear from beginning to end to you and you can
see an injustice or you can see a logical it's very hard not to get upset by it and the only
reason why other stuff doesn't upset people is because they just don't get as invested in it but
if you got invested in politics or sports you get just as upset right this is true i mean good example
earlier we had a big skype crash i mean it was a pain in the butt and boy how do you know i could
sit there and shake my fist oh microsoft you how dare you crash that application that i chose to
install and use and we could have a debate should we drop skype switch the mumble yeah like all
these technical discussions or do i suck it up and either continue to use it or use something else i
mean really it's really what it comes down to so yeah anyway that's my take on it uh i wanted to
say um i'm sorry i i made a little uh i made a little boo boo last week get it out of here uh oh
yeah uh so oh my god matt so after last week's linux unplugged i lost all access to my google
account oh no full on couldn't get to docs couldn't get to youtube couldn't get to my email
and of course i couldn't get to the jupyter broadcasting youtube account well this happened
while i was posting linux unplugged so normally if if you notice what happens on the jupyter
broadcasting website is right when a show comes out i i post on the website and i use the youtube
embed and that's because webm is horrible technology and takes way too long to encode
literally like if if the hd version of linux unplugged it might take 25 minutes to encode
and the webm version not exaggerating at all will probably take two and a half hours to encode
it is that kind of half hour two and a half hours so youtube's down because i can't get to my google
account so i say screw it i'll just go straight to the html5 version and i posted it on our website
linux unplugged html5 version and because the webm wasn't ready yet i just didn't link it well
on a ton of linux desktops if you don't have the webm well anyone using chromium or chrome on the
linux desktop if you don't have webm uh embedded it won't play it just sits there and spins for a
while so a bunch of people couldn't play last week's episode on the html5 player i apologize
i did get the web web version up later but because it took so long to encode it it was like a couple
of days later so my apologies to those of you who had problems we got a lot of people emailed and
said i couldn't play the episode the direct download links by the way folks uh so where the
so you have the video embed then where the show description is you scroll down a little bit direct
download links you just download them right there we got torrent feeds and everything uh but that
was my bad that was my bad well and i think that's an important piece to to really realize is that
sometimes those things happen and that is so frustrating for the end user i totally get that
but the cool thing is that we do have that alternative option so if you run into a problem
just remember we probably got you covered no worries and then also i try to link the youtube
version which you can go watch and all of that um so this week uh i wanted to uh i oh god did i
get yeah here we go this is our speculator tron you like that the speculator tron and we're gonna
look into the future the the the distant year 2000 future and we're gonna talk about replacing email
lava bits darkmail initiative uh launched on kickstarter this week and our community's been
talking about it in our subreddit i actually already became a backer 35 bucks worth nothing
outrageous but i became a backer and i want to talk about this today because this is a
as a former sysadmin but also now as a business owner these are placing email is kind of a big
topic for me uh because i gotta i gotta replace it with something that solves the needs of a small
business i want something secure and safe because i i get hundreds of emails from people outside the
country in a week and you know so i i never know who i'm getting emails from and i also want
something that's easy enough that uh is just sort of doesn't have a cognitive burden as they put it
and so i want to talk about the darkmail initiative i want to break it down and the fact that it's
open sourced it's going to run on linux all of that is going to be a point of our conversation
today uh but before we get into that i want to thank a new sponsor on linux unplugged and that
is digital ocean now if you're not familiar with digital ocean they've cracked it they've solved
a digital ocean is simple cloud hosting dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy to spin up
cloud servers and the this is i'll tell you a little bit about the the digital ocean cloud
server i spun up last night by the way check this out matt users can create a cloud server in less
than 55 seconds pricing plans start at only five dollars per month which gets you 512 megs of ram
20 gigabytes of ssd storage a cpu and a terabyte of transfer a terabyte of transfer for five dollars
a month the interface is so simple so if you're watching our video version here i've got my
personal digital ocean control panel up and so you go you go to create and then you select your size
so here i have a 512 megabyte cloud server one cpu 220 gigs of ssd and a terabyte of transfer five
bucks a month now that's crazy that's a great deal that's a great deal if you use the code linux 13
this is episode 13 linux 13 they'll give you a 10 credit that's basically two months you can get a
digital ocean server for free for two months so what i did is i went in here and i said i want
the 512 box and then you select your region they got new york amsterdam san francisco and another
new york location so i went i decided to go east coast i'll tell you why here in a second
then you go down and select your image now they've got everything from ubuntu 1310 through ubuntu
1004 they got centos from version 6.4 to 5.8 they've got debian from version 70 to 60 but matt
then they got fedora too but matt they have the arch they've got arch believe that it's like oh
my god it's like all those times you're wondering i wonder how arch would handle this well there you
go right so so that's what i did i i spun up an arch an arch server they've got the uh they've got
the may snapshot so you you know that's the so you click that image you get the minimal arch system
just image to your box so it's totally set up you generate the root password you log and you've got
root access at this point you can set up and even any encryption you want anything like that you know
what i decided to do what did you do one of the things i've been trying to figure out a way to
utilize and but also make a good experience is bit torrent sync bit torrent sync it offers just
incredible possibilities for content distribution and i've been experimenting with distributing the
unfilter supporters show and and clips catalog using bit torrent sync so i spun up an arch
linux box on the east coast running bit torrent sync this got a copy of all of the unfilter
supporters stuff on there so when new members join the unfilter supporters club they get seated from
a new york server and from my server here on the west coast so i've got now i've got servers on
both coasts of the united states seating the unfilter supporters club so it just makes it
super crazy fast and matt i brought my arch box up to total current the first thing i did matt
when i when i logged in right i just brought that sucker up to date i was pulling down packages from
the arch repo at 9 10 megabytes a second whoa yeah and that all goes on those ssd hard drives
so when you when you combine that crazy speed with those ssd hard drives it is absolutely
mind-blowing digital ocean also offers a vast collection of tutorials in their community
section this is awesome matt users can submit articles to the community and get paid fifty
dollars per published piece so if you feel like you have an article you could write that would help
the digital ocean community if if digital ocean selects it they'll give you 50 bones i know so
i'll put a link to that in the show notes if you guys want to check that out and if you want to go
check out digital ocean use the code linux 13 when you check out that'll get you a ten dollar credit
so if you get the five dollar box that's going to get you two months of digital ocean for free not
only not only can you select like base images but under the applications tab you can just say well
i just want a lamp stack on ubuntu 1204 just spin that up or i want ruby on rails on ubuntu 1204
or i want ghost on ubuntu 1204 like you can just push those out right then and there uh you have
you can have stored images so once you have something you can snapshot it and then redeploy
that later on you can back things up you can destroy images if you don't like them they
support docker containers so you can create something locally and ship it up to them using
docker and then on the back end they're using linux and kvm to make it all possible and i love
the interface i love as you're bouncing from tab to tab it's it's physically impossible to get lost
confused as to what you're doing you don't even have to know what any of this means it's so awesome
it's so awesome it's like awesome uh and uh we were just talking on the pre-show with some of
our mumble uh folks and uh they were mentioning it was a jbviewer66 he was mentioning that uh
he's uh he's had he's been digital ocean customer for a long time and support questions get answered
super quick super fast right i i couldn't believe like their claim you spin up a server 55 seconds
is totally legit i spun up an arch box in 55 seconds and i owned it and then i got geeky matt
i got super geeky like i sshed into it with x11 forwarding so then and then i installed firefox
and only the x11 dependencies i had to have and then i'm forwarding my firefox session and
configuring my bit torrent sync through localhost that way i don't have to open up a remote listening
port it was awesome it's so cool good deal you feel that ssd speed too so uh go over to digital
ocean.com and use the promo code linux13 to get a ten dollar digital ocean credit and thanks very
much to digital ocean for sponsoring this episode of linux unplugged we'll have a link in our show
notes as well i'm gonna be checking that out after the show that is fantastic oh yeah buddy it was
so i was like i walked over to my wife and i'm like okay i gotta apologize i'm really geeking
out tonight i just did the coolest thing did you get the geek twitch you know when you're about
to do something really i absolutely did uh so uh switching gears to uh to the lava bit dark male
initiative uh i thought let's back up a little bit and then we'll open up to the mumble room too but
let's start with uh ladar's introduction of the goals around darkmail and what it is um i've been
working with mike jenke and his team at silent circle phil zimmerman and john callous um and
we've been working on a little project we're calling darkmail we thought blackmail kind of
gave the wrong connotation and what we're doing is we're setting up a little non-profit called the
darkmail alliance um that would be the group that we're using to maintain and control the
intellectual property related to this new protocol i think if i had come to you guys two
three years ago and said hey it's time to toss out all the mail protocols and replace them with ones
that integrate security all of you would have laughed at me you would have said you want to
throw out how many man hours of work all for this hypothetical threat that we don't know exists
well i think after the summer of snowden hopefully you guys have a slightly different attitude about
how important security is and how insecure many of the protocols that we use every day
so uh that's ladar uh the uh owner i guess of lava bit which was shut down uh as uh
big as it became public that edward snowden had used uh lava bed as his mail server and then they
wanted right carb launch access to all of the mail records there and he makes a very good point is
in the past and i think this is very legitimate to the conversation in the past if if somebody
come along and said we want to replace email but we don't want to use smtp people would have laughed
them right out of the room oh they really would have too yeah and and it's it's now to the point
where it's like okay well i'm willing to seriously consider this in fact i was reading some of the
comments in our subreddit and uh uh josh uh struggle wrote i personally threw in 35 bucks
i look forward to love that code being open source the darkmail alliance making the protocol open and
the fact that they are tailoring this to everyone ranging from service providers to your grandmother
and end encryption is absolutely needed um somebody else wrote uh uh that he says uh this
was uh buffus brie 66 he says i'm gonna throw in 100 when i get paid this is the first smtp killer
i really believe in and smtp really needs to die a painful death i think it i think this will also
be a great time for companies like google and yahoo have been leaking bits and pieces of
conversations starting how they hate the nsa and gchq uh so i thought you know these are i'm too
like these guys are ready i'm ready yes but it's it's not only has how we needed the right time
but we've needed the right team and i think that's the other thing that the darkmail alliance has
is the right team basically what you've got is you've got uh a real interesting mix going on here
you've got the phil zerman who john and i is the co-founder silent circle along with john and i
uh creator of pgp you got john callous who's the creator of pgp universal server and apple's whole
disk encryption and you got ladar who if you haven't figured it out is one hell of an engineer
i mean it's kind of the dream team it really is and i think that was the missing piece as you
pointed out these are the people needed to come together to actually make this come to fruition
and come to reality and what one of the things that's i think probably important to understand
so this is what this kickstarter is funding is uh developers it is not necessarily funding the
product directly itself but funding hiring the developers to work on cleaning up lava bit source
code and open sourcing it and at the end the end product will be was essentially a series of
protocols this is really a set of protocols and it's a set of protocols that has as the goal you
start out with security and for those who need to dial the security down you can dial the security
down the problem right now is that email has no security and you're forced to dial it up and you
can only dial it up to a certain point there's lots of metadata in every email that absolutely
cannot be protected at all such a great point right email starts insecure by default and then
you can try to force all of these security layers on top of it but at the end of the day the metadata
is still exposed right well it's just a band-aid solution i mean that's the bigger picture is that
no matter how much how much wrapping you put around it that metadata being exposed is going to be
the downfall of anything you're trying to protect i mean it really doesn't work there's so much you
can draw from the metadata i talked to this person at this time over this time period right after i
dropped off the backpack in front of the trash can right exactly and that's really all they need
they don't even need the contents of it but what also inspires me about this darkmail initiative
isn't so much what they're saying now and the fact that it's going to be open source but the
fact that it's probably going to be based on a technology that they've already got working
what we're thinking about doing is basically building a new messaging protocol based around
json that like he said includes security by default i would say we already have it we already
have a working prototype of it that our our texting system silent text basically works this way that
that if i send you the equivalent of an mms you know i text you a picture what happens is that
you get an encrypted mms an encrypted xmpp message that tells you where to go get the picture and the
picture is end-to-end encrypted between me and you and nobody else can decrypt it at all so what
they're going to do is uh the system will use xmpp for the communications between clients it will go
to a client and say hey so when i send matt an email it'll say or uh i guess a darkmail it'll
say you'll get essentially a notification that hey matt there is a goodies waiting for you on
this server now that could be chris's server that could be some that could be gmail that's
implemented this protocol that could be anything that kind of cloud storage and then your client
will go out and get this encrypted bundle and pull it down that'll be the actual message contents
now that gets encrypted on my end using a key that it gets generated on the client not from
the cloud and then you could only decrypt it using the key generated on your client and then you pull
that package down and you can decrypt it you get the contents and it's it's sort of um kind of more
like how a lot of messaging systems are going on mobile where you have a message and then the asset
gets stored on the cloud and this in this case the cloud is whatever you want it to be uh and i think
you know you when you've already got okay so you got you got people who spent 10 years in the
industry ladar creating what was the most secure email option of our time then he gets shut down
by by fighting back against the um um i don't know national security state i guess yeah yeah
and then you've got silent circle who also shut down in in spite of the national security state
who already have a war a working messaging protocol right they've already got it working
and they've teamed up and they're saying hey we want to do this and we want to open source it
and we want it the way we want to make this happen is by giving money money to developers
and then you know i think this is really chocolate and peanut butter coming together
i really feel like it is you know i feel like we're sitting here on the edge of like
the first honest to goodness serious email replacement like we've got the motivations
we've got the technology and we've got the people right and it's all but it's all going
to be open source and it's all going to run on linux i'm excited to see it come to fruition i
really am so uh i so i was curious i thought i'd i'd toss it here to the mumble room and ask you
guys uh is anybody not on board with the dark mail is anybody anybody have any issues concerns
or doubts in this room i just say it's about time yeah yeah why do you think we needed this years
ago i agreed actually that was going to be my question to you guys is so their best effort here
is they hire up a developer i mean we're best case scenario you're going to see something mid 2014
probably beta status right i mean is that too long you guys is that too far away because i feel like
i need something right now i wanted to deploy zimbra and move everything like this year and
i'm now i'm sitting here i'm seeing this i'm like maybe i should wait for for lava bit 2.0 dark mail
1.0 what do you guys think mumble room is it is it too far out i think it's too late because i mean
if you think about it this snowden thing that happened i mean if we had something like this
before the summer of snowden as he put it then we wouldn't have as much issue with oh well let's
just switch everything over to this now we've got to wait too long to have that happen and
and quite frankly everybody knows that email is already completely insecure so get the dark
mail going it needs to happen quickly we got a big message yeah i mean bit message is here today
but see here's where here's where the dark mail system is superior is dark mail is is it's mail
and then if you want you can dial it down theoretically and it can also do smtp and
communicate with older mail systems so it gives you that it gives you that transition whereas where
bit message is off on an island of its own you got to use bit message to take advantage of bit
message the sender has to be on bit message they've got to find it they got to find you
whereas this in theory could be integrated to existing mail products today and it could even
downgrade so it starts at the highest level everything is encrypted from the email to the
metadata from top to bottom everything's encrypted and it's encrypted exactly you also might bit
message is its own island it's its own ecosystem whereas this integrates with everything yeah and
also because it's worked on xmpp you can even use it as a dark mail for instant messaging right yeah
okay so uh that's a great point is mail is just going to be one aspect of what the system could
deliver whereas bit message is pretty much just for messaging and you'll probably you'll be able
to see more people willing to adopt something like dark mail than just than that message i think so
i think so i think the fact that it could support pictures and video is kind of a big deal because
if you're going to replace email don't you want to replace it with something that has more
capabilities exactly my two senses is that if you're going to replace an email then you're
going to need a bit of time for some of the companies such as google and microsoft to work
with these guys uh to develop a standard in a way that it suits businesses going forwards i don't
i don't see them being on board though especially microsoft and google i mean there's at least right
now the nsa is probably so integrated within those corporations right now that it'd be hard
to have them even be interested in it this is a crazy idea but i think the way that uh the first
person the first company who's going to jump on and actually provide a good service using darkmail
is yahoo that'd be interesting they have oh i see what you're saying because they're kind of the
underdog right right they need something to give entice people that would that would be a pretty
nice feature i kind of wonder if we aren't fighting the business model here uh and it sucks because
what all of these cloud providers uh base their business model around is mining every bit of
information about you even if it's just their robots doing it's for to display ads they have
to be able to read the contents of the message and it's not even like oh well that's gonna suck
if we couldn't do it no it is like fundamentally key to their business model it's how they analyze
and sell you things and so it is a massive it is why they did mail it's literally why they created
an email service that's why they did it and so to take that context away from them essentially
makes them run the mail service at a total loss and so i don't see the commercial incentive for
them to have their customers contents encrypted on the drive right i mean they're happy all day
long to let you connect over an ssl connection whoop-de-do what they don't want is that data
sitting in rest encrypted because then they can't mine it and i think that might be the
biggest thing they have to fight against well they could tell you now is this darkmail is it mostly
the protocol that they're focusing on yeah the back end yeah so i wonder if it could be paired
up with something like the mail pile for a good client well lava bit is talking what they're
talking about doing is re-releasing lava bit as the as a software package that integrates in the
darkmail initiative so you'd have the lava bit mail server i don't know what web front end would
sit on i don't know if i'd never used lava but maybe it had its own web front end uh they want
to repack okay they want to repackage that as an open source project that to be quote unquote a
first class darkmail initiative citizen but they feel like that those protocols could be used by
anyone but they're gonna it's like their nexus device in a sense i think the biggest issue is
going to be red hat if red hat can uh introduce this as their uh server operating system and
include it in their package along with updating gnomes evolution to include it and it's going to
be a big step forward well here's a here's a thought i mean the reason i'm saying yahoo would
would be an option for it is because the the fact that they're an underdog right now but also the
commercialized part of it is they could pay they could chart they could do a darkmail service that
is kind of like google apps for business so they can provide a darkmail that's completely secure
but so they could immediately be uh like hippocompliant so here's what i like about it
yeah because it does provide a certain like um regulation compliance and i like that if encryption
happens this is why i like last pass too because encryption happens on my end and on my client
device and so then it is a little less risk in using a public service because they can't decrypt
the data but you as a backend service provider not only do you lose the mining aspects of it
but you also lose like a lot of nice things like reducing multiple copies of files and and all of
that kind of stuff that you get when you can just look at the data so i wonder if if we're i mean
i'm not saying that it's not going to be successful but it seems like it might be a little more indie
now they say they've already got like 32 companies they'll want to launch with lava bit or i'm sorry
darkmail support right just built in does it have a list of those companies on the page no they don't
they don't have anything up on that 20 bucks says half of them are vpn providers yeah maybe
because they're already in the privacy business why not right probably yeah yeah that that is
interesting is you could do that well i was thinking you know to go back to our to go back
to our digital ocean sponsor i was thinking like this would be there you go so you take a you take
a five dollar a month server you throw your did your darkmail initiative project on there and
you've got a mail server no kidding and it's just i want to see this happen but i feel like
i i guess like the the primary issue is there's email has been consolidated down to four or five
big companies now to really do it and so it seems like you got to get one or two of those big
companies on board and yeah and i and really for one of those companies it has to be a company that
isn't wanting to try to get government contracts for their service because otherwise they the
government could hang that over their heads for them to get the data well yahoo's pretty good at
like uh fighting request for the data as well so that's another reason why i suggest i thought
they might be my thing with it is as long as they keep it open source that's the bigger picture here
that's always been my one issue with bit message is this uh closed source and proprietary you never
know what they're doing in the back no i thought bit message was open source he's thinking btsink
he's thinking btsink yeah that one like as long as they keep it open like i'm fine with it because
that's like you can see the best encryption ever as long as it's closed source i still don't trust
it yeah and you know we've seen like with true crypt like when the when the project is important
enough certain groups will you know sit down do an official audit of the code and that's why i think
that is key just for a trust standpoint not even not even from everything else but just from his
trust standpoint i think that's pretty key all right any other thoughts on the darkmail before
we move on guys was that mail not was that mail not audited on tor at one point so you know let's
talk about that name yeah because that name does like it it brings up darknet right uh
yeah now what do you think is do they make a do they make a mistake with the name um i think as
they pointed out it's probably better than other names they could have gone with but i do i don't
think it's gonna it was definitely sounds like something that was developed developed by
developers it sounds like something that is not really hitting the mark as far as the
consumer is concerned they said their uh their their inspiration was the dark empire right but
at the same time i i applaud the name simply because it's going to attract the people that
need to get a hold of it the people that are going to roll it out on their own service that are going
to actually work with it and then provide it in more of a uh to start out with probably in a very
niche or niche uh point of view maybe i should have called it ninja mail well after the summer
of snowden maybe we need something that snapped us awake right no mail right yeah that's why i
think red hat's a good contender for that because uh if they already established it and have it in
the repositories and businesses might see it and think hey we'll include this and maybe not they
don't know what it is but once they start offering that service then they'll get users to like them
well no go ahead also go back to the open sourcing did he say what he was wanting to licenses that
no no i haven't seen any license no i haven't seen any license i hate it when they say open
source i thought he said gpl oh did he because i haven't seen that okay okay this would be good for
bsd licenses where anybody could just take with take it and run with it so there'll be a million
different versions of it like you said before i can't stop them all yeah yeah sure well here's
what daniel said daniel wrote into the show and he said why people will not use darkmail or at
least why many people will be discouraged is because of its name seriously why can't they just
call it smail or secure mail or bmail or better mail this has of course nothing to do with the
technical functionality but with the average user's perception darkmail sounds well dark it
sounds dubious just not right here in germany isp's cooperation with the state try to promote
something called dmail any links to the dmail wikipedia page it says for quote unquote secure
communication the whole concept is not secure but offering interception possibilities for law
enforcement but if i would have to explain some average computer user to why to use darkmail
from the darkmail alliance instead of the d email from german tcom they'll look at me like i want
them to commit a crime we geeks are used to funny ironic names and technical names like xmp rfc 25
353 whatever but the average user is not maybe we should keep in mind from time to time greetings
from germany and great shows daniel so i email 3.0 yeah email 3.0 is almost catchier yeah so i
think the thing to remember too is as this email pointed out i agree with this latter part as far
as the naming scheme and stuff and linux is just atrocious but because i can't pronounce half of it
but at least it's not your mail like yet another mail client yeah no kidding right but i think
that the the intro point of it is that we need to remember that this is not a product that's
going to be successful going straight to consumers it's going to be targeted at some it department
at various companies people that aren't going to read into the name other than oh hey this
is doing what i wanted to do they can then rebrand it into something like you know grandma's good
time cookie mail or whatever the hell they want to call it and you know what the the name smtp
never really seemed to held hold smtp yeah yeah exactly when's the last time you logged into your
you know i mean yeah users don't care about that or pop or imap yeah yeah right i i guess where i'm
at is i'm left still not knowing what to do like i i feel like i need to probably get off gmail
honestly just because like last week when i lost access for a little bit that was enough to freak
me out and then because i now i'm at a point where i have to pay for like every mailbox for a year
when i want to create a new mailbox that's annoying because i know you know it's they're not used that
much that i need to do that and so i would prefer to just roll my own have my own system but at the
same time i don't want to roll something out and then have this come out six months later and be
like oh i really wish i would have switched i really wish i had that and then switch all over
again right so i'm just kind of in this holding pattern now well i think the main advantage to
rolling your own is that if you control the domain whatever's running in the back that's true that's
true i can just point at something else but this is the time of it you know it is the time yeah
you're right and going back to our previous linux action show if we just get one of those robots i
know right now i need it now i need it now you know take care of it yeah you know it'd be awesome
with this is somebody would make a susa studio version on this like the own cloud thing right
just deploy uh just deploy a darkmail alliance compatible mail server and seriously a few minutes
yeah that would be really cool yeah i gotta say as far as branding oh dark cloud with that yeah
that's i mean it sounds like underground or it sounds like black market you know you're
you might as well call it like hacker cloud or ominous cloud silk mail so are you guys
take a charge with that because they offer cloud solutions and that just seems like the best key
are you guys going to contribute to their kickstarter which will have links in the
show notes absolutely yeah i mean there's that i mean i i threw in 35 they kind of have a funky
so they i mean honestly this seems like the loosest kickstarter project i've ever seen
because i thought kickstarters were supposed to have like a seriously hard like complete goal and
really the goal here is like well we'll hire some guys and they're going to work on it so it's kind
of the loosest kickstarter ending i've ever seen but they've got a 25 spot oh i could have sworn
that was a 35 spot when i threw in a 25 spot a hundred dollar spot and then it goes to thousand
five thousand ten thousand wow yeah i bet they dropped it to 25 just to make it more accessible
um yeah and you know um they're they're now at 27 000 of 196 000 22 days to go they just launched
it but when i threw in they were like at 16 000 so they've really it's going up pretty quick
yeah it seems loose but because it gets backed by the by uh ladar it makes it okay for me to do it
for the 25 at least i agree i feel like i feel like it's totally fine i i think just a reflection
on how kickstarter seems to be a little loose if if it's good pr they'll kind of allow a looser
def that's fine i mean it's their it's their prerogative well at the same time if you got
that loose of a uh of an ending for it it's not like yeah that just gives them some freedom to
work on it how they need to mm-hmm that's true that's true i wouldn't want to box them in too
much i want to cover a little bit of two things before we before we run this week uh first of all
i'd love to hear your thoughts audience out there on the dark male alliance and replacing email with
email 3.0 so email us you can go to jupiter broadcasting.com and click the contact link
and choose linux unplug from the drop down we'll cover your thoughts in our follow-up next week
last week uh we asked the audience to vote on uh what they thought which direction debian would go
you remember this mm-hmm and uh we didn't get a ton of votes because i screwed up on how i linked
and embedded the poll but we still got enough votes i think it's pretty telling we got oh yeah
208 votes total uh 19 of the votes went to upstart 81 of the votes went to system d 81 of the people
think it's gonna go system d uh that's probably wishful thinking though i think so right well and
what i want to know is because you have half you probably i'd say you know you have a large group
of people that are doing this based on logic you know there's logical reasons why they're throwing
their hat to system d no question that but there's also a fair handful of people that i
firmly believe are throwing it in based on emotion and same thing with upstart i think people throw
into upstart for emotion too i'd be interested in a poll that shows whether you're basing this on
you know your emotional dislike for one of them or the fact that you really feel one is superior
i would love to see that yeah here's the here's the options to vote and now give it why yeah right
exactly yeah i would i wanted to keep it simple to see what people which way people go people are
voting people are voting right now and it's still going to system d and that's totally expected i
mean i i don't know that direction overall it uh it's gonna be interesting to see the drama fall
out and then uh either way right either way you think we're gonna get we're gonna get some
interesting drama so kind of crazy and and the numbers increase yeah yeah they're going up the
system d is still going oh upstart just got a vote well there you go it's it's fast and crazy
oh my gosh well uh all right so um maybe we'll do another poll again in the future yeah so next week
on the linux action show so on sunday uh we'll be talking if everything works out with joss
from open sussa and he is the community manager over there and he's going to be at the fedora sus
fedora at the florida suscon right is that what it's called suscon suscon suscon yeah and uh i
was i was just kind of thinking maybe we'd brainstorm real quick here with the mumble room
on what we should ask the open sussa community manager when he's on the show so mumble room is
there any burning questions that we think we should kick the open sussa community manager's way don't
forget 13.1 is coming out soon so that's in there and of course uh i've got a list of questions but
i i wanted to open the floor and also to the audience um listening on the download just go
over to jupyter broadcasting click that contact link you have a chance to send in choose the
linux action show though and send in your questions for the or start a thread in the
subreddit linuxactionshow.rat.com send in your questions for joss i i have a question but it's
not very it's not like a broad it's more specific but it seems to be that open sussa is the only
distro that you netbootin doesn't work with that is pretty broad okay i don't know if the community
guys yeah i thought there's a couple other ones to do i thought uh manjaro doesn't work with it
either if i'm not mistaken yeah right he doesn't i i'd be curious about uh open susa's plans for
maybe implementing wayland in the next couple years that's interesting yeah yep yep okay that's
a good one he might have the scuttlebutt on that maybe we can what do you have to because um uh
katie e wouldn't they oh yeah they're gonna have to yeah they're gonna have to right keep in mind
also this is gonna be an evergreen release oh yeah true yeah so maybe they're gonna be a little more
conservative but that's usually that's a good point so maybe this is probably anything we ask
us would be then considered or pondering into future releases going down maybe a year or two
rotten did you see that uh big c just linked in the chat room a open susa live usb stick creator
that might help you that might help you get going dd uh ben ben digs in the chat room asked maybe i
should ask about my sound issues and kde there we go oh wow well they are tied in so tightly with
katie it would be interesting and i did experience those same sound issues with an open susa you know
with an open system so this is i was saying on the pre-show i was going to uh it's been so long
since i've tried it on another distro but uh just a little background because i know a lot of people
don't watch the linux action show live right before last starts and we're trying to stay on
a schedule because we had uh frank from the own cloud project coming on and we didn't want to make
them wait so yeah right and and and the runs linux pick was that now robot and it had a video so i
knew i wanted to i knew the first thing out of the gate as soon as we got into the show i want to
play a video and i want to make sure that works because i hate you know to have it like right
there in the show the beginning to have some sort of problem so uh i just do a little test run i set
my sound outputs i get all the sound effects i even like people i even did like the little bark
sound through the sound effects control panel and the viewers at home were like oh you're making my
dog go crazy right we know it's working it goes out over the live stream everything's solid we
tested it we saw it on the vu meter i i launch up chromium i load up the tab i click play on the
video and the sound comes out my laptop speakers and where it gets weird is that everybody's
immediately going to go oh well you just you just run the pulse audio uh volume manager normally
that would be true but in chris's particular case different tabs did different outputs yeah
no that's where it got weird that was so strange that's where it's like okay you lost me it's got
to be a flash issue it's got to be a flash issue but it's like at the same time uh how do you
explain that i i just don't yeah i don't know i don't and then what can i fix it because i had to
play the video um and then like later on in that episode you know 30 minutes later we did a skype
call with frank and it was just fine there was no sound problems at all right so that's what i
felt about support for kernel 312 with 312 they're going to have full optimist support even
switching graphics cards right yeah that is a big thing for laptop users also like what about the
installer because i want if they're ever going to update their installer because that thing is still
beautiful you mean i've had issues with it like the partitioning part really i i haven't i never
have i've had issues what file systems are you guys using for when you're having problems
okay here's something i'd be interested in asking my laptop is currently running open
susa 12 3 i wonder how would an in-place upgrade to 13 one work compared to doing a clean install
okay good question that's what i was so i was wondering uh what you guys thought like should
i during the review i guess certainly if you all do the 13 one and then maybe after the review
maybe i can try going for a week on tumbleweed or something that's what i've been doing for a while
yeah yeah my issue with tumbleweed is somebody uh the build service packages don't work with it
yeah oh that could be a pain in the butt that's an excellent point yeah good point yeah there's
quite a bit in the build service that don't work with tumbleweed yeah yeah okay there's a there's
an option in the obs to make it work with tumbleweed but you have to do extra steps for it
make it show so maybe they should just have a check box or uh you know something be nice
well guys uh that does bring us to the end of this week's linux unplugged you know uh we have
gotten i i have stopped i've stopped reading them on air because we get so many emails from folks
talking about their switch to arch and i and i think that's so cool that some people are trying
it out and the only reason i haven't covered it is because i didn't want to make this these shows
like some sort of arch and you know promotion platform but at the same time i think it's so
cool that people are trying it after they saw us try it and a lot of people are having really good
success i think it's just fun to step outside the box and see what is happening in other
distributions as well and uh so one of the things i want to do in the near nearish term
what i mean before january uh i'd like to talk to integrals and mangero developers as well so
if we have mangero developers out there listening uh go over to jupiter broadcasting.com and click
the contact link and choose linux unplugged from the drop down i'd love to get you guys on mumble
and chat with you about what you're working on because i have a feeling we're sending a lot of
people your way and i'd like to ask you a few questions about how your system works how it
differentiates itself from arch and where you're going in the long run so that's a that's another
invite i want to put out there but thanks to the mumble room for hanging out with us this week and
chewing on all of this s and you guys will have a link to the kickstarter project for the darkmail
initiative if you want to go in and maybe help them out the wrong show if you want to go in
and maybe help them uh get to their goal well then we'll have a link so you can do that and
we'll keep you posted on their progress matt i think we're gonna have a really good show on
sunday we'll be talking to joss while he's in florida oh right on i know that'll be fun and
don't forget everyone you can join us live go over to jblive.tv at 2 pm pacific on a tuesday
we've also got jupiter broadcasting.com slash calendar where you can find out what time the
show is live in your neck of the woods what's great about joining us live is not only can you
participate in the mumble but you can participate in our irc chat you can help us name the show
and we've got a lot of fun in the pre and post shows after we're all done with linux unplugged
linux unplugged is out every tuesday and linux action show is live on every sunday
all right everyone thanks so much for hanging out with us on this week's episode of linux
unplugged matt i'll see you on sunday all right i'll see you sunday
i have them we'll see you right back here next tuesday