I present to you over at github the fastest website ever ultra fast single TCP packet
audio-visual experience yeah that's right it's a web server and website that
just sends you one packet you can try it at HTTP packet city all right
apparently it's an actual audio-visual experience yeah well they did say yeah
they even have room for 120 bytes of ad space and a single packet that's pretty
impressive that's just some high-quality music yeah I'm gonna mute that right now
because we do not need that let's look at the source though no to be fair that
that music is probably copyrighted and we'll get us pulled down that will
probably get us pulled down yeah not again beard yeah okay this is a pretty
small yeah that's a tiny amount of source code with no formatting with no
formatting whatsoever yeah so you can go you can go check it out they got a
client here index dot HTML just a tiny little thing and I think they just have
a tiny little C web server that sends this to you so if you know your clients
don't want a bloated website who does these days just send them to the fastest
website ever see what they should do is they should figure out how to also send
you a copy of the thing to run it yourself in that same packet oh yeah
yeah that would be like a quine type thing but for a single packet web server
you know getting all meta up in here I like that beard this is Linux unplugged
episode 216 for September 26 2017
welcome to the Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's definitely
not jealous of Chris's awesome New York City adventure my name is Wes and I have
a beard you sure do have a beard we have a great show coming up today we spent
some time with our friends over at Microsoft we catch up with some of our
favorite projects discuss some of the hard details of being a free and open
source software maintainer and get a little quantum with the latest Firefox
quantum beta but before we do all that I think we have at least one friend to
join us we should say hello to and time appropriate screening to our wonderful
mumble room time appropriate greetings oh wonderful to have you mr. mech oh how
are you doing beard thanks for joining me Chris is away he's out in NYC I am
stuffed full of five guys oh yes I am a fan of five guys in my mouth five guys
all up in that mouth yep with a side of fries yeah excellent well we can't be
having as much as fun as Chris but we sure can make a show happen so I guess
we pop over here talk about our first story today which is okay so on the
previous episode we had quite the kerfuffle we were talking about mr. Jim
Zemlin of the Linux Foundation and his his choice of computing hardware device
that was a little contentious right because he was caught not using Linux
how could that be how could that be so I just thought and you know maybe it's a
little fun we poked some fun at the other side Bill Gates now uses an
Android phone at least according to the verge I mean to be fair to him he has
more an excuse because nobody makes Windows phones anymore yeah really yeah
it starts out but you know Windows phone has been dead for a good year now and
Microsoft co-founder Bill Gates has decided it's also time to move on in the
interview with Fox News Sunday Gates reveals he's now using an Android phone
well Gates doesn't reveal the exact model he does note that it has a lot of
Microsoft software on it which could suggest it's the special Microsoft
edition Samsung Galaxy s8 but who knows I guess he's still not interested in
iPhone though he famously banned iPhones and iPods at home in the past that's
kind of funny I wonder too like is it just because do you think you'd use
Android just because there's probably is it easier to get Microsoft software on
there versus iOS yeah probably but it would you know I don't know who's a
bigger competitor to Microsoft these days Apple or Google I mean Google's
going after their cloud business a lot more yeah but of course Apple has been
there a long time I mean not arrival almost feels wrong clearly they're
beating them in the you know in the mobile world but for a long time Apple
was the underdog does Bill Gates even care anymore no I don't think he does
right that's a lot of it too it's like it just doesn't matter and that's really
what I was trying to get he's just a dude now that happens to also be a
billionaire that people write articles about yeah you know still owns a bunch
of Microsoft but hey that's just what happens okay so moving on then to our
next story today which is an update to lineage OS change lock number 14 brings
burn in protection and changes to privacy guard audio effects and more so
lineage is this something you would ever be interested in mr. beard not really
yeah what do you run on your phone is it just stock yeah it's whatever Samsung
sends me yeah just trust into the old same song well that's fine well I mean
with the Samsung phones if you if you root them breaks the the knocks
protection yeah right yeah so that's no good anyway the lineage OS team has just
released a new change like summarize the most important changes made to the
popular third-party custom ROM in recent weeks originally made every two weeks
change logs now being you know only only when the team teams necessary so I
thought hey this might mean something interesting has changed so there's now
the lineage updater app has been rewritten from the ground up to fix
some long-standing issues doesn't seem very exciting but I think that's one
thing that like if you're gonna have a successful long-running ROM you actually
need to be able to get updates because I can't like the number of times I've had
to install something and then like a few months later been like I just have to
like reflash this phone I don't want to lose everything what what is the
procedure here so if you have like a really official good non buggy simple to
use updating tool I think that goes a long way so is the the update you're
like a utility that you're on your PC or is it an app on the phone you know I'm
not actually sure I imagine it's something you run on your your computer
but let's see let's find out I'm not actually sure cuz uh if we're on the
phone that'd be that would be nice yeah that would be here we go at your change
devices yeah okay it looks like it's a flask app here so that would suggest to
me that you run it on your on your device and then interact with it and then
you know it will then flash your phone or provide the update interesting yeah
you're right if it was right on the phone that would be like first party
level of yep just boom this is official just open the app it's like you got an
update and it downloads it and you reboot and flashes that'd be great so
also they now have burnin protection so if you have an AMOLED screen that you
know a fancy AMOLED screen that you would prefer not to get ruined they now
have burnin protection which shifts the position of the status bar and
navigation bar icons every few minutes you may think you're going crazy if you
haven't read about this you know you just like is my phone my phone changing
on me I didn't do that but hopefully that prevents burnin in those areas so I
guess they actually move at 3 DP horizontally 1 DP vertically subtle
little change and really what was highlighted here is September security
patches have been included and fixes that blue born vulnerability we were
talking about last week as well so that's another good point if you do have
one of these ROMs boom update yourself you've got these patches you don't have
to wait for Google to roll them up into some update that takes however long or
Samsung to do so which will clearly take forever yeah that's really I mean it's
beginning to a point where I don't I'm not that interested I have not even
unlocked my pixel so I which is weird for me I only got Android 7 a month or
two ago hmm which is like many months behind yeah so you're not gonna get Oreo
until 2019 yeah 2019 yikes well then maybe for your next phone consider
something that can run lineage maybe yeah I know somehow I don't see that
happening but you can think about it okay so if you aren't going to do that
you are probably still concerned about security turns out Google is concerned
along with you Google has extending security support for Nexus 6p and Nexus
5x devices until November 2018 this has been one of the more maligned things
about Google's devices I was seeing a you know comparison thread that the
iPhone 5s is still supported and how long that's been compared to the the
support that that Google generally has for their devices so it's nice to see
that maybe maybe you're getting a little more than you expected or a little more
than they've actually promised so since Android is the most used operating
system in the world it also stands to reason that it's also the most attacked
the only way to prevent security problems on mobile devices is to keep
them updated amen see the text that program and this is exactly what Google
is doing up until now the support for both the Nexus 6p and Nexus 5x was until
September 2018 but has been extended until November 2018 adding two more
months this can only be a good thing for Nexus users who can hold on to their
devices a little bit longer fancy scroll in there that's my mistake
don't mistake but you should not mistake security support with software support
it's important to keep in mind that security support only refers to patches
and nothing else software support ended in September 2017 so it's ending right
now which means that no new version of the OS will be provided after this date
that definitely limits the usability but there's a lot of people I think of like
my mom as an example where she doesn't need the latest and greatest you know
like software updates necessarily she just needs a phone that will just keep
working run the same apps that she's had for the past however many months but I
would worry if she was on a phone that was no longer getting updates so that's
nice to see yeah it doesn't really change the like haphazard path haphazard
pace of change hardware change deprecation ending lifespans of phones
after like two years but maybe there's a happy medium somewhere in here well
isn't that um that one project that they announced supposed to help with a lot of
that yes it is man I'm blanking on that come on beard what's it called hey I
covered the project part you get the other part yeah you remember that it's a
project yeah that's true though it does sound like there are some you know
upstream changes going on in Android that will help refine some of that make
it easier for people to have those have all the weirdness of the actual system
on a chip confined at one software layer and then be able to build on top of that
so hopefully this will not be a problem that we see indefinitely in the future
still though I was a little I'm glad to see this I know a lot of people who
still have the 6p several people who have gotten the pixel and kind of missed
their 6p we'll see pixel 2 I guess will be coming out before too long but it's
nice to see Google at least kind of makes you wonder if they're extending it
because of that that new stuff maybe has made it easier for them to extend it oh
that's an interesting idea yeah maybe now it's yeah provides less less you
know lack of momentum less breaking to their bill yeah because you can update
the the OS without also having to update the the baseband and the firmwares and
all that yeah yeah as they end here also we have to remember that Google launched
the Nexus 6p and Nexus 5x back in September 2015 wow that seems like that
ain't a long time ago this means that support for them will end three years
later that's not too bad at all I've done the the math West that is two years
ago yeah I suppose that's not that long but that's a long time in the world yeah
exactly okay so speaking of phones let's just jump right on over to our first
sponsor today and that is our friends over at ting what is ting ting is
mobile that makes sense it's I mean it really it's a smarter way to do mobile
so go to linux.ting.com that will get you a $25 service credit and is my
mobile service provider is it yeah yeah you know what it's mine too I don't
believe it it's true and my parents mobile service provider and just about
anyone I can convince to switch it's a little weird right because you're like
hey can I talk to you about your cell phone plan I don't work for a phone
company but this can save you money but I yeah exactly it's like to that point
where it's like I'm not trying to pressure you I'm just letting you know
that there is a company that does things differently it really is smarter because
okay so it just starts at six dollars a month right so each line six dollars a
month one line two lines but the studio has like three or four lines something
like that yeah even if you have another another phone plan just pick up a sim
and screw around with it on the side for a bit to see if you like it yeah right
that's like one one hamburger a month less and then you have a you have a
phone line you can use as much data as you want yeah sure you pay for it but
you're free to do so which is awesome so head on over to the rates page they'll
make it super easy for you to figure out what you might be paying per month as I
said lines are just six dollars each then you just add up whatever bucket
you fall in so let's say you don't use any minutes because hey why would you no
one wants to call me and so I don't have that problem and you probably don't use
text messages because SMS is really just the worst thing ever so don't use those
either we're still at a whopping six dollars but now you get to data this is
one of the best things about Ting because data is just data tethering yeah
you can tether that's included you want to use a whole bunch of data that's fine
Ting doesn't try to like nickel and dime you with these complicated plans
overage charges none of that just pay for what you use so you know if you just
use a gig a month now we're at $22 maybe use two gigs a month $26 how reasonable
is that seriously $26 a month two gigs of data one phone that's perfect that's
affordable that's why I love Ting plus okay CDMA and GSM you can bring your own
device so maybe you all have got up you know got one of those supported lineage
phones Ting is a perfect place to bring it whether CDMA is better GSM is better
maybe you have a fancy one with like dual sims or you want to switch them out
depending on where you go all kinds of options plus they have an incredible
dashboard great apps and real live human customer service so Linux dot ting
dot-com there you can save a bunch of money on your cell phone plan and thank
Ting for sponsoring the Linux unplugged program thanks Ting okay so moving on
more Linux to talk about always more Linux can we just like skip the Linux
yeah okay what are you uh I don't know I guess we're going back on I guess we're
okay we're just gonna fall back to Linux anyone else doesn't want to talk about
Linux then I guess I'll be outnumbered I don't have Chris here to back me up
today yeah that's okay though okay so here's something we've talked about
more than a few times on the show and that is the top icons plus extension you
mean the one that the gnome project recently recommended that people use if
they want that stuff yes that that is the one looks like according to an issue
over on their github page development might be pausing or stopping so hey y'all
I'm sorry but I'm gonna have to take some distance with the development of
this extension it's motivated by a couple things one I have not used the
extension myself recently I use less and less extensions that use it and among
them none of them breaks or loses functionality without this to the gnome
project does not give a shit about it and made it public they don't even point
to this extension but to an outdated unmaintained one besides Ubuntu after
making a survey also moves on with its own extension all right we're getting
dramatic here anyway the API is dying it won't be dropped in future GTK updates
documentation is sparse and the development requires considerable effort
also the API is buggy and incomplete so it's impossible to make a reliable
extension or really enhance it of course it will never be fixed for top icons plus
then became a magnet for claims that would be better to be addressed by the
gnome project people fail to understand that the extension depends on an API and
is not capable slash intended to fix the gnome shell service it's extremely
exhausting and five the gnome extension website is awful as there is almost no
maintainer there and validation takes sometimes weeks
meanwhile I get issues from disgruntled users so I came to the conclusion being
also very busy with my job and my life that the hassle is no longer worth it
especially when it requires considerable effort because of the sparse
documentation status icons are dead with gnome shell move on and enjoy gnome
shell or switch your desktop environment oh okay those are some strong words over
there oh I kind of agree with them though like that's kind of what gnome
said that is kind of what gnome said yeah you're right I mean it is and that's
just one of those you know like love it or hate it that's kind of the way gnome
has been going these days right like they stick to their guns they have a set of
principles and philosophy whether or not you agree with it or not or even think
it's consistent they that's that's the way it's a benevolent or not so
benevolent dictator project yes dictator framework Adam I don't know what to call
it but so do you know much I usually use made okay yeah so this was not an
extension that you yourself was we're availing of no Chris uses it though I
think yeah definitely so I wonder what he's going to think about this no no
well right now he's on budget so it doesn't matter yeah right now he's on
budget the budget craze is sweeping the studio and I think the world mmm
probably yeah probably that's that's what seems to happen when those solace
guys get ahold of something and enough enough that I key went full-time yeah
full-time which is incredible it's nice to see that having listened to some of
that coverage do it does seem like you know it could be pain if you if your
development has diverged from what GTK intends it becomes increasingly it
becomes increasingly and increasingly difficult so I definitely have sympathy
with that you know that line of reasoning and you got it especially in
the open source world you just got to do what you can do don't stress out too
much about it and if he's not using it it'd be really hard to maintain
something that much work if you were not actually using it yourself any longer
and the fact that they that he said that the buggy or the API is a buggy and
incomplete kind of probably speaks to how much gnome cares about things that
aren't things they care about exactly yes exactly okay well I don't know if
anyone in the mumbroom wants to chime in but now is the time before we move on to
our next story unless you have something else to add mr. beard no well it's but
she considered to be a lightweight to desktop because I have a rest free
pipeline here around and I would try I would like to try some different
decimal budgie is more lightweight than gnome as far as I can tell at least I
would that seems to be easy yeah well true but I'm not sure where it where it
fits in relevance to the other ones I'd say probably somewhere on the level of
main yeah okay so it would be worth a try and is it it's fully compatible with
weight on the cast I think so yeah I believe so I don't know that I don't
think I've actually run it under Wayland yet on any of my systems but if not I'm
sure that I key guy will come yell at us about it yeah that's the fastest way to
find out or everybody else will go yelling at him oh yeah you're right oh
even better okay that's just fine then by the way I would have a last comment
on the lineage discussion you had a selfish has taken the first steps to do
to to base to have a base on lineage OS until now they had Cyanogen always for
the community ports and so they started to have the first steps to port to port
it to lineage which would be a great improvement because right now the
newest Android base for selfish always is Cyanogen modes 13 so probably there
is a way to go further now and take the energy space yeah I mean it seems like
there's a lot of momentum there so that makes like that seems like it might be a
good choice as something to base yourself on you well it seems to be the
only option now it does kind of seem to be the only option now yeah very true
excellent okay so moving on talking about only options in a way that's not
the button here we go announcing the X free kwin project no it's not X free 86
as you might be thinking but it is kwin running without X support so Martin
writes over the last few weeks I've contradicted concentrated my work on
kwin on what I call the X free kwin project the idea is to be able to start
kwin wayland without X Wayland support well most of the changes required for
it are already in plasma 511 not everything got ready in time but now
everything is under review on fabricator so it's a good point in time to talk
about the project so why an X free kwin you might ask you might wonder why we'd
spend time on this after all we need to provide support for X Wayland anyway to
be able to support legacy applications which are not yet on Wayland yeah I'm
sure a ton of us who are using Wayland are using a lot of X Wayland under the
hood so what's the advantage of a normal
session one needs to start X Wayland anyway well one aspect is that it shows
that our porting efforts to Wayland are finished over the last few years I've
tried to start kwin without X Wayland support for a few times just to find
areas which are not yet ported by being able to run kwin without X 11 support we
know that everything's ported or at least does not hard depend on X 11
anymore hey okay that kind of makes sense yeah we can actually run it all
without this stuff running so hey guys it's good another aspect is obviously
plasma mobile does not really need X Wayland and so it doesn't make much
sense to have a build that includes it and especially like lib hybrid systems
they won't have open GL there so it just it just doesn't make sense so by not
requiring X Wayland we can reduce our runtime and memory costs speaking of
runtime cost not requiring X 11 means that we don't have to wait for X Wayland
during kwin startup instead X Wayland can be started in parallel this means k
win and the complete plasma session starts just a little bit faster and most
important this is an important prerequisite to be able to handle a
crashing X Wayland so far when X Wayland crashed kwin terminated gracefully as k
win depends on X 11 the hope is that when X Wayland crashes we can just
restart it and keep the session running yeah okay that seems like a totally
legit reason to do that I don't want X buggy old X Wayland bringing down my
beautiful pristine new Wayland session makes sense yeah definitely so how it
was done the general idea behind getting here is that the code that isn't loaded
can't interfere kwin uses platform plugins for the various platforms kwin
can run on there's also a platform plug-in for kwin slash X 11 so code
which is only required in that case can be moved into the platform plug-in as
kwin slash Wayland does not load this plug-in we're certain that the code will
not be loaded and thus cannot interfere interesting but how do you find all that
code after all kwin's code base is about a hundred and fifty thousand lines of
code yeah I would just ctrl F and search for X just search for X yeah that'll do
it right X and then separately search for just 11 that will help too or org
or yeah definitely won't find that X 11 is the really really old code really old
code X 12 that's where it's at yeah good help is I guess they have a they have a
pretty good CI system which performs code coverage so kwin's tests mostly are
based on kwin slash Wayland so an area which just does not have any test
coverage is a good candidate for being X 11 specific boy doesn't that say a lot
right there that's why they want to protect it from the bugginess because
it's not tested I mean I'm sure that that's that's totally possible so
anyway like they kind of looked at those things by looking at these areas it was
possible to find patterns which also helped to find more usages so you know
kind of profile oh here's where we have to keep adding X 11 support that's
probably refactored in the same way in other parts of the code base there's
also kwin's internal X 11 API so they were able to find a bunch of those
patterns root those out and then exercise it so now they're able to you
know control it exercise I like that yeah right I mean it's all about it's all
about violence mostly that's how it works when you work with these old code
bases just got them got them got them right out put them back together we have
the technology beard like we just totally do okay so being able to start
and run X kwin slash Wayland without X 11 support is of course only the start
more changes will be required for example the delay loading X Wayland
until an app elation tries to connect to it another area to try to get X win
compiled without excellent support and to move everything required for X Wayland
into a plug-in so be a larger project as it will require much more code movement
and added further abstractions to some areas of kwin but this could be a nice
Google summer of code project as a fast step for especially plus mobile and the
purism Libra and phone which we've talked about there's an if-def now
around the X 11 code so that might be another path forward but the his motive
Martin's real motivation here is handling a crashing X Wayland so I think that
makes sense and it's cool to see I really appreciate these blog posts just
because well I don't always run kwin like I don't have a plasma system going
at the moment it really is a heck of a I mean compositor everything that it is
now right I mean a Wayland desktop yeah so it's cool to get to see this sort of
stuff that's one of the things that's so wonderful about open source is like sure
I remember the old days like Microsoft would have like a tech post about
something they were doing but you didn't get to go look at it whereas we can go
like look at the commits that have changed this I'm probably not going to
on this one because it sounds like it's kind of gross but the fact that we can
that we can learn from it and we get to see the motivation I think that's pretty
awesome what about you are you a plasma plasma fan I actually prefer plasma over
any other desktop I just don't run it because I still find the the settings to
be too over complicated yeah you know I've had that problem myself I actually
I like it a lot and I just but it just had a couple years ago I had it tuned
really nicely it was just perfect I loved it but I that time I did not do a
great job of like remembering what those settings were so the last couple of
times I've used it for like a week or two here and there but I've been in the
same boat where it's like I just don't have the time right now to sit down and
make this perfect when you have to go to three completely separate sections of
your settings to to theme your your your stuff then I think it's a little over
complicated yeah what is this Windows 10 especially since some of them like to
override other ones so you end up going circles you'll never win yeah circular
dependencies that's that's what we need here well okay so maybe that makes you
pretty frustrated beard maybe frustrated enough to just leave this whole planet
behind and join a new spaceborne Linux supercomputer it's now started running
in space achieves one teraflop I'm sure it's pretty warm I can just like lay on
it yeah you can just snuggle up with the supercomputer out there and you won't die
at all yeah it'll be fine okay so we'd heard about this a little bit before I
you were mentioning that that yeah I think this is the same HP supercomputers
that was launched on a SpaceX rocket that recovered a couple weeks ago yes
about one month ago the HPE their new name of course come on it's HPE now they
split Rekai HP Enterprise yeah uh-huh it's serious stuff anyway their
spaceborne computer was launched into the space using the SpaceX Dragon
spacecraft this beast was launched as a result of a partnership between HPE and
NASA to find out how high-performance computers perform in space now the
supercomputer is fully installed and operational on the International Space
Station the performance experiment will be carried out for about a year which is
roughly the time will take for spacecraft to travel to Mars at the
moment lots of calculations for space research projects are carried out on
earth but this brings in an unavoidable factor of latency yeah I imagine your SSH
sessions aren't great when you're going from space to the earth and back huh
yeah we've got some photos here I'm sure it's better than like the the
SSH session to like the satellites we got way out far out looking at planets
enter a keystroke wait six minutes and then check that's when you use a mosh
that's when you use moss yeah okay finally a situation that makes sense
that's great actually I do kind of like mosh so here's a cool picture it looks
like it's getting installed here the hardware which is being talked about
here is an Apollo 40 server with a high-speed HPC interconnect running you
guessed it Windows ME no it's Linux it's a Linux beard come on now it has a
water-cooled enclosure and additional software to take care of the
environmental constraints yeah sounds like this is also a closet gaming box
for the astronauts on onboard that's what I'm picking up here it must have
upgraded from their solaris supercomputer that's great can you
imagine putting together a computer in space though it's hard enough are it's
hard enough yeah your screws are floating all over the place oh that
could be good in some ways yeah you just kind of like set it there over the screw
in the sky yeah maybe you have to I guess I guess magnets would be even more
helpful but be careful don't let the magnet float too close to the computer
now the magnetic screw trays is pretty good too on earth that's true yeah so I
guess it's not so different yeah I will take that challenge though so if anyone
wants to send me pay for a new computer and send me to space to assemble it
sounds like it would make great content just gonna just leaving that there you
should pitch to what's his name Richard Branson yeah okay ask if you can build a
computer on the first version of galactic flight I'm gonna just write
this down right now following up on that after the show anyway this is devices
the first high-performance commercial off-the-shelf computer to run one
teraflop at the ISS for those who don't know one teraflop is 1 trillion
calculations per second which is 30 times faster than a laptop okay that
really doesn't sound that impressive now that I mean like 30 they could have just
taken 30 laptops up there I probably already have like yeah it's really hard
to do like Beowulf cluster yeah that's true and then what if one person's
playing steam and it's really tying up the whole cluster all them Ethernet
cables in space oh yeah that's true you'll get caught up in them that makes
sense okay so according to their technology officer engineers are ready
to launch the multi node high-performance linpack benchmark test
this test will determine the number of multiplication system can produce per
second so now that it's all been doing over the coming months the engineers
will study this installation and its performance so that's kind of cool not
that often you get to hear about Linux in space like we all know it's there
obviously but it's just like do you remember seeing all those pictures from
years ago of you know we still had the space shuttle and seeing astronauts on
there when they got like their ex Windows XP thinkpads running on the
space station yeah so hopefully now they'll have some it does seem like it
would be pretty handy if you're doing it you know they do so much science up
there that just to have your own little supercomputer that you have right there
to go do your workloads on so I guess the supercomputer is inside the the
pressurized area of the place that's what it looked like yeah or at least the
front the way they talked about I thought they were gonna do something
crazy like just have it sit in the vacuum of space to keep it cool yeah I
thought that too like it was just you know it would just be floating maybe
alongside or in a similar orbit I guess they didn't have a way to deal with
potential like any amounts of condensation at all oh yeah okay
interesting and then I guess you have to devise the right kind of like would you
use like a like laser beam or infrared or other type of like line-of-sight
communication to it now you just poke a hole for Ethernet cable and then you
tether it on to that yeah mm-hmm maybe like and then a couple extra ones just
for security sake and then one that's actually the data line yep hmm no that
is an interesting idea there Beardsley how'd you get so smart mm-hmm
who knows okay so I know I've heard that you like video games fact or fiction
hmm well the video games are fiction true that I like them as fact okay how
do you feel about Atari and how do you feel about a new gaming system from
Atari called you've guessed it the Atari box so it's an Atari branded PC I'm
guessing yeah take a look that seems completely pointless yeah doesn't it but
guess what it's Linux based hmm so it will use an AMD customized processor
with the Radeon graphics technology this means a proper CPU so not like an arm
chip that's nice it will run Linux but the they will be providing a customized
interface as it's mainly aimed at using it like a console on a TV even so they
say it will give a full PC experience for the TV so we're back to like
whatever web web TV is that what it was what I'm hearing is that Atari couldn't
make a deal with Steam to make another steam is exactly what it sounds like but
you will apparently get full access to the underlying Linux system so it might
be possible to have you know buy this and then put your favorite OS on it why
you would do that I don't really know maybe it'll be maybe that's subsidized
somehow so it'll be cheap like Xboxes of old I'm not sure I wonder if the the
modules for the the custom PC chip are publicly available I wonder that too
yeah it sounds like it's going to remain quite open as they say you will be able
to access game purchased from other content platforms as long as it's Linux
compatible so it sounds like installing Steam might just be possible so this
really is like a weird side loaded steam you're gonna get it's just gonna be like
Ubuntu with an Atari wallpaper yeah Ubuntu Atari wallpaper and Steam
pre-installed and then Steam pre-installed yes and then maybe a
couple other game platforms oh we'll come preloaded with classic Atari games
and even some current titles from a range of different studios it'll be
interesting to see if these current titles are games already on Linux or are
they gonna have some actually ported games especially for this I'm gonna
guess they're already on Linux I would bet so I don't know how much they're
actually gonna try to outlay on this yeah so it will launch on IndieGoGo soon
they say this fall it might seem strange for a bigger company to go with
crowdfunding yeah it is kind of strange I didn't know Atari is broke yeah but
they say this because they want the community to be part of the launch
Rekind not because they're broke yeah they want part of the community's money
to be part of the launch yeah you're probably right though honestly though
it's mainly so there's less risk involved for them but because Atari is
broke because Atari is broke but maybe it's a good way for them to gauge real
interest I don't know as for the proper launch it'll be late spring 2018 with a
price aimed between 250 and 300 dollars depending on the addition and
configuration Atari is still reeling from the the whole ET cartridge fiasco
back in the 80s yeah you're right about that okay but what do you think about it
this is apparently not a render it's a real unit with real wood involved the
wood edition it just seems like another steam machine with less everything yeah
and I haven't heard like this hasn't talked much about like what is the
controller gonna look like will there be controller are people putting keyboard
and mouse hooking up to this is it just USB ports on the back like it doesn't
really excite me because it's a it's just a slightly more proprietary PC that
happens to support Linux but so don't all non proprietary PCs yeah okay that's
fair that's fair yeah no that's about now if they announce that it's some
absurdly cheap price and it has good performance maybe I'll change your mind
but I doubt it yeah I'm with you okay well I guess I do have something that
you might get excited about and that's our next sponsor today which is our
friends over a digital ocean it's hard not to get excited but yeah exactly
have you heard about their new spaces a beautifully simple and scalable object
storage service hmm yeah so if you listen to if you listen to tech stamp
you hear about all kinds of people always getting hacked because they leave
their s3 buckets open to the public don't make that mistake just hop on over
digital ocean they've just launched basis you can get in on it I think
you'll find the price is very competitive and kick your bucket get a
space get a space yeah exactly and I mean digital ocean makes it so simple
you don't have to fight through the always confusing AWS API's you can use
digital oceans amazing super simple API the well not to mention the the web
interface for AWS is so confusing convoluted especially compared to
digital ocean where you just click click and you're done or like have you ever
tried to like find out what you might expect to pay for your your AWS oh no
you find out what you expect to pay when you get the bill for what you pay yeah
so head on over to digital oceans pricing page and you'll see the
difference because like look at this oh look oh yeah it's just the prices per
month or per hour whatever you want and you can switch between them you can
switch between them yeah which is also like a huge feature so I like this
$10 a month one because you get one gig of memory one CPU 30 gigs of SSD disk
and it's all SSD des over digital ocean and two terabytes of transfer and this
transfer is not this is not your grandma's transfer this is not 56k it's
not some single bod modem this is like 40 gigabit e straight to that KVM
hypervisor go run like a couple apt-get updates go pull down some files you will
see that this is real transfer I use it all the time when I'm like trying to
connect to a server in Europe and my ISP just doesn't seem to have great peering
across the Atlantic but digital ocean sure does that's because they have data
centers all over places like London and Frankfurt and then a bunch here NYC San
Fran and they keep expanding so there's almost certainly one near you if you
have two droplets in the same data center you can get private networking
between them you can use our promo code do unplugged that will get you a $10
credit so that will pay for your first month or you know you probably don't
really need that whopping droplet so just just downsize just downsize five
dollars a month or seven tenths of a cent per hour isn't that insane it's
insane so it's so cheap run an IRC bouncer run a server of any kind start
hosting your own website you can use their attachable block storage so if you
need to do some backups up there plus they've got stuff like monitoring load
balancing cloud firewalls all the all the bells and whistles you've come to
expect from those big-name competitors for way better prices way simpler
interface and way better API go to digital digital ocean comm our promo
code do unplugged go get yourself a droplet and join the cool kids club so
easy to remember that we forgot it that is exactly how easy do unplugged okay so
talking about talking about do and therefore we had to talk about AWS
because they're just you know AWS some yeah they're just exactly up exactly
mm-hmm you're just trying to get them to sponsor you aren't you beard yeah right
so they're a big competitor another big competitor in that space is our friends
over at Microsoft I don't know if this is relevant or not but Microsoft and
Facebook have just teamed up and laid a hundred and sixty terabit per second
cable four thousand one hundred miles across the Atlantic I love that the
verge feels it's necessary to tell you how many videos you can stream on that
but that's 71 million HD videos at the same time so that's HD that's only 1080p
yeah 1080p man I mean yeah might even be 720 if they're like skimping on you why
aren't they telling us like 4k Netflix streaming I don't know yeah that's
what's relevant for the future anyway Microsoft Facebook and the telecoms
infrastructure company tell Telxius have announced the completion of the highest
capacity subsea cable to ever cross the Atlantic Ocean the cables type of wolf
transmitting 160 terabits of data per second that's terabits so that's an
important important point there and is 16 million times faster than an average
home internet connection ouch it's trying to make us feel bad now Microsoft
we all get it you have gigabit apparently the cable be operational by
early 2018 called the Maria which is Spanish for tide the 4,000 mile long
subsea cable lies 17,000 feet below the ocean surface and extends between
Virginia Beach Virginia and the city of Bilbo in Spain it also stretches
route south of most existing transatlantic cables because of this
Microsoft says the cable provide resiliency for those living in the u.s.
and Europe by safeguarding against natural disasters or other major events
that might cause disruptions that's nice but where's our Pacific cable yeah where
is that I want to have high-speed transfer to Singapore I'm trying to
download some sushi right direct from Japan and it just doesn't fit over these
low bandwidth pipes we've got I like my sushi okay don't judge me I guess it
comes at a pretty critical time submarine cables in the Atlantic already
carry 55% more data than trans-pacific routes ouch gosh well maybe that's
okay you're not putting down the cables yeah we need more cables and 40% more
data than between the US and Latin America there is no question that the
demand for data flows across the Atlantic will continue to decrease I
suppose there's a lot probably a lot of financial transactions and others oh yeah
I wonder why it's so different in the Pacific for most of the route the cable
made up of eight pairs of fiber optic cables enclosed by copper lays on the
ocean floor some parts are buried to protect from shipping traffic usually in
areas closer to the shore in a blog post Microsoft said the project was
completed nearly three times faster than usual in under two years maybe it was
even under budget who knows they are an open design which allow it to evolve as
technology does and as the population of internet users around the world
continues to increase so anyway I don't know what their exact like why they
Facebook and them had to be involved are they going to get some sort of are they
gonna get a bunch of this lease here are they immediately buying transit across
this cable or ownership are getting data collection rights or they're just
kidding yeah so if your connection goes across this cable it instantly has ads
so just watch out for that but it is just really cool that this is something
that we can do you know you like you don't we don't really get to talk much
about these undersea cables but turns out a lot of the internet and backbone
of it needs them and it boggles my mind like 17,000 feet and somehow from the
surface we can just like lay giant cable on the on the bottom of the ocean I
couldn't do that it's probably like titanium reinforced or something you're
right probably probably titanium reinforced beard you just know
everything well that way the the lobsters can't cut the cable I can't
even with you I can't even with you we're moving on and I know this will
make you upset so Microsoft ignite sequel server 2017 for Linux goes live
you know or Windows if you want and then get this the preview Docker image has
already been fetched two million times Microsoft's just like full-on hipster
DevOps up in here I didn't realize that not only is sequel server popular what
it's popular in the Linux not yet popular under Linux and despite everyone
who likes to say you should never run a database and a container that you can
have the Docker container obviously that's not for production I'm just
kidding but it's interesting I mean I know Microsoft's on like a ton of work
with Docker to make Docker on Windows work clearly they embrace it on the
Linux side too so I guess yeah sequel server 2017 is now generally available
today's release is a remarkable step in sequel service history because it's not
just a release for Windows today makes the general availability of the sequel
server for the Linux there's also a containerized version for deployment
using Docker it was announced March of last year to widespread surprise yeah
amen sequel server as they say here at ours
technico sequel server is the kind of software that shifts Windows licenses
people buy Windows Server for the express purpose of running sequel server
supported to the Linux world is really forfeiting a huge amount of Windows
server potential revenue Scott Guthrie executive vice president for cloud
enterprise acknowledged that risk but felt that it was offset by the
opportunity sequel server for Linux presented sequel server has a rich
feature set and potential customers were telling Microsoft that they'd love to
use it but they were Linux shops or were dependent on Docker and
containerization as such being Windows only prevented sales to these customers
so it really does kind of to me it feels like the organization of Microsoft is
like really realizing that they have to like they can't just compete at this OS
level anymore they can't let the OS drag back their other products so they have
to they just have to make it available and you know sequel server is great I
haven't used it a ton but I know a lot of people who really like it and find it
sometimes the only acceptable alternative to Oracle database Postgres
obviously has come a long way but sequel server has been like a dominant force in
the industry for a long time and I'm sure there's a lot of people are like
yes I can run it on Linux now and you wonder too is it just good for them to
have more people familiar with it so that you know there's more devs who can
use it there's more devs trained to use it well it might not mean that they have
to buy Windows it might make it easier if they're already into the sequel
server enterprise if Microsoft can be like hey here's your cheap Windows
license or here's why it runs better under Windows I don't know that it does
in fact in the early builds we'd seen some articles stating that it was
running better under Linux than it did under Windows but maybe that's part of
their play here bringing the Windows dependent software to Linux made use of
a Microsoft research project named drawbridge that investigated new
approaches to virtualization and software isolation it happened that
this research work already aligned neatly with the way sequel server itself
was was engineered so they were able to just kind of stack those two
technologies together abstract away the host OS levels and make this work on
Linux it's kind of wild like Microsoft's they might be better at Linux than
Linux is now I don't know about how you feel about that
well aren't they one of the top kernel contributors they're not I don't think
they are in the current cycles they were for a while I think that was at a time
when they were doing a lot of work to get like better hyper-v support and
stuff for Azure but they certainly have you know they've certainly contributed
to it so we'll see I'm not gonna use it but it does seem like it further cements
Linux dominance in the server world
okay so one more little Microsoft update here just our little Microsoft check-in
in today's show because you know Microsoft loves Linux they love it so
much canonical Microsoft have now teamed up to make an Azure tailored Linux
kernel yeah that's right custom kernel customized by Microsoft actually this
isn't too surprising Microsoft runs Gentoo Microsoft runs Gentoo yeah baby
emerge world it kind of makes sense like there's already extensions you can do it
for better you know better virtualization support pair of
virtualization stuff on AWS so this basically adds a bunch of those options
to the Azure world so canonical has announced that it is joining forces with
the Microsoft Azure team to build an Azure tailored Linux curl for Ubuntu
cloud images of Ubuntu 1604 the new kernel will receive the same level of
support and security maintenance offered to supported kernels but is not yet
compatible with the canonical live patch service if that doesn't matter to you
then you'll be able to enjoy the improvements right along the kernel is
provided by the Linux as your kernel package and here are the highlights from
right from canonical infinite band and RDMA capability so you'll have more high
performance networking options available to you full support for accelerated
networking and Azure this is a huge one direct access to the PCI device provides
gains and overall network performance offering the highest throughput and
lowest latency for guests in Azure they have basically basically it's all of
these sorts of things right to make your virtualization less expensive 18%
reduction in kernel size hyper V socket capability and the very latest hyper V
device drivers and feature support available so it will now be used by
default if you spin up any Ubuntu 1604 LTS images on Azure but if you you can
check just you name dash are that will show that has a dash Azure in the name
if you don't want to use it you can install the regular stock kernel just
fine you just won't get those performance increases so you can also
still get support from canonical so really just business as usual but a
little bit more better tailored for Azure so that makes sense to you got to
be competitive it is interesting though like canonicals done they've been
working a lot with Microsoft between running on Azure the Windows
subsystem for Linux all that I'm sure they're not doing out of the kindness of
their heart a little bit of money a little bit of money on the sides here
yeah I know I see some speculation that maybe a bunch of wants to get wants to
get bought by Microsoft I don't know if that's the case or not but is there a
reason Microsoft wouldn't buy canonical I don't know all their stuff is Linux
focus so yeah unless Microsoft really really loves Microsoft loves Linux and I
think the real thing is Microsoft loves developers and Ubuntu has a lot of
developers how many of those tutorials you know you see by default that are
just boom right here right now okay so that's it for our Microsoft coverage
today but so we do have a little update just in the world of like Microsoft
loves next links is open source open source can be difficult so Rika are you
familiar with caddy no okay so caddy every site on HTTPS caddy is the HTTP
slash 2 which is the new version of HTTP it's a HTTP HTTP slash 2 web server with
automatic HTTPS so it's like a modern modern open source web server
lightweight recommended by experts it has secure defaults so unlike a lot of
you know you can install engine X even or like old Apache and have to do a lot
of work to get from like web 1.0 open everywhere port 82 I'm running a secure
modern patch web server caddy aims to make that just like you start it up it'll
serve your files it can integrate with let's encrypt to automatically get it
HTTPS enabled it has secure ciphers enabled by default all that stuff and so
it's been you know it's been praised by experts at usenix and NYU lug ACM all
kinds of stuff it's free for personal use there's commercial licenses available
and there's open source so you can go to their site caddy server comm you want to
find out more about actually using it but we are here to talk about a recent
blog post by Matt so this is titled the realities of being a FOSS maintainer
authors note here this is a more intimate look into what it's like to be
a maintainer of a popular open source software it's written by me personally
and not as a representative of the company I'm going down on a limb here so
try to be nice okay we'll try Matt don't worry so over the past few days I've
been inundated with well over 1,000 comments tweets emails messages and even
phone calls about Wednesday's announcement so what he's hearing is
that they've announced caddy commercial licenses so they were pleased to unveil
that we've been working digitally on fast past few months on caddy commercial
licenses the change has decided to accommodate the needs of the growing
caddy community and user base with commercial licenses were able to offer
exclusive features and services that parts key to our business users that we
couldn't do before while sustaining caddies open source
development we're even starting today with one new service for our customers
and more plan so you can read more about that if you want they have some like you
know if you use caddy for personal academic or nonprofit purposes not much
is different just a new response header that gives tribute to our sponsors it's
one part that was contentious if you use or distribute official caddy binaries
at work or as part of a product service you will need to a commercial license
based on how many instances you want to run concurrently official binaries are
produced by our build server I this website and get caddy comm with a commercial
license you can use this website to seamlessly download official caddy
builds blah blah blah if you automate installations or use direct download
links the URL syntax is changing slightly so that's like it right they
are now trying to like paywall basically there'll be a commercial license for
some features and services and their limitations for how you can use the
official binaries freemium freemium yeah totally so that's one you know that's a
model we've seen before so anyway lots of feedback interestingly most of the
positive reactions came from individuals who have met met me in person who are at
least somewhat acquainted with me online whereas every one of the negative
reactions stem from someone who has never met me or interacted with me in
other words there was not a single person who responded negatively or
unreasonably whom I knew or who could recall prior interactions with so if you
ever find yourself in a similar situation look at this statistic it
might give you some relief not everyone you know hates you okay so right after
right after this announcement he went on a research lab to retreat the mountains
had no internet connections so got some nice time away from the internet which
is always nice Matt's back now I want to take a few minutes to respond personally
and candidly about everything that's going on what he's learned what the
reactions have been like and just kind of a reflection so announcement day he
posted it on hacker news within nine minutes after someone had they posted on
Twitter after it was tweeted it was right on hacker news right at the top
the at that kind of that kind of makes sense right so it became very popular
he talks about forks here too so forking is a normal part of open source it's
allowed by the Apache license which is the license as long as you give
attribution and state all changes when one fork started a spinoff project on
Wednesday my co-founder Cory reminded me reminded them to remove the caddy name
and logo from the repo to avoid confusion with the caddy brand that's
also an important part of that spinoff was quick to change the name and leave
attribution and within minutes the issue was resolved and closed
unfortunately the response to this by spectators has largely been less than
professional and I think is along with some other reactions I discussed below
exposes a glaring community flaw in our open source community there was no
hostility in Cory's comments nor those of the projects maintainer both Cory and
the maintainer did the right things as has been seen so many times before
toxicity festers in open source because it's all too common for forks to ground
their motivation and enmity towards other projects this obviously isn't
healthy and we hope that the open source community will figure out a better way
to deal with negative sentiment than by creating new communities rooted in it so
they also removed the header basically had a header that would send back
thanking the sponsors of the server a lot of people just were like I don't
want these weird headers on every response that I send out of my web
server they say that although they did ask their sponsors about it before this
is implemented they didn't get any response so add this to the list of
things we're learning we'll do better over communicating with our sponsors in
the future sorry I don't know what else to say about this I guess there was a
lot of confusion as well around the EULA and the caddy binaries so really what at
the end is the open source code of the software's
licensed under Apache 2 and not under the end-user agreement so caddy is
still open source we go to extra effort to provide you with convenient binaries
customized just for you so the official binaries are licensed either for
personal or commercial use under this EULA so you get like the commercial ones
have like private plugin hosting and the future maybe some other features this is
really something we've seen before the build server is also not going to be
open source because it's just it only works for caddy and that's what they're
using to produce these binaries so some reflections one phone call I received
was from a friendly company it had associates associations with offering
their support and congratulations for the bold move it was much appreciated
I also have received dozens of tweets and DMs mostly from friends to those who
took a side were supportive thank you you didn't have to and it helped us
weather the storm from one human being struggling with the daily realities of
life to another thank you yeah I can I can that's nice sentiment there well if
you had criticisms of the change all of those were reasonable but none of them
could quite been down what it was that made the changes wrong to quote one but
the whole affair has made me extremely uneasy for a variety of reasons that are
really hard to put a finger on the crux of the opposition even according the
most well reasoned arguments was missing the best we could find is that was that
a commercial license out of reach of small startups that are bootstrapping or
don't have revenue yet we agree Cory and I are looking to a good way to handle
this so for now we encourage some startups to simply contact us with their
needs and ask about special pricing okay that's somewhat reasonable now we get to
the bad some feedback read opinions and advice we received had good intentions
but wasn't very well thought out or didn't have the necessary perspective of
project owner or maintainer to hold any water here I address some of them
candidly so why not offer a comprehensive support package instead we
tried this nobody bought it why not offer an enterprise solution or
consulting service we're two resource-constrained we could probably do it
but that would stifle almost all caddy development as well as my graduate
schooling and research so I have to pay to remove ads from my web server no your
company is required to pay for commercial use of official pre-compiled
pad caddy binaries not further removal of the caddy sponsors header you could
do that on your own anyway because the source is still Apache licensed further
our sponsors don't pay us for advertising the pay us for its ongoing development
to make the web better to support our customers who benefit from good web
servers and to keep caddy free for you to use the license frankly had nothing
to do with the header limit the free features instead and things like but
then I have to build from source to get what I want and yes that's the point
welcome to open source I do find it ironic that the open source community is
so irate about having to compile software from source to customize it the
way they want so he kind of just goes through talks about a bunch of the you
know a bunch of the problems just take donations then it really comes back to
how do we support how do you want to support open source this is how he
touches on this a little bit with the ugly I really don't want to focus on
this but now it must be talked about I've been balling these things up for
years I think the worst thing I saw this week was twofold the overwhelming
illusion of entitlement and subtle emotional manipulation based on a
misconception so there's like there's a lot more here it's a pretty long article
of his really is just mapping very candid they kind of talk about more the
pain here the emotional manipulation the entitlement that we're talking about
but they end with it with one final note here just want to emphasize how great so
many people have been several dozen individuals reached out over many
mediums to express their appreciation and even congratulations thank you thank
you for showing me the human side of an industry that is often dehumanized by
long distances screens and texting we expected some pushback as usual but the
extreme controversy this created was unforeseen sorry about that thank you to
all who responded quickly but at least reasoned out their comments before
writing them here's looking forward to what's next and we hope you'll be a
part of it with me so that was that was heartfelt whether you agree or disagree
whether you think that it's a good business model or not I think we should
talk about that but it's interesting to see such a candid response we could talk
about that a little bit before I do I just wanted to pop on over to the Linux
subreddit where there's also a discussion going along that sounds like
Synergy 2.0 is going closed source Synergy was one of those projects maybe
you've used it beard I don't know yeah a lot of people have you know especially
if you have a Windows or a Mac and you also have a Linux you want to share your
mouse and keyboard between those systems really works pretty great or even just
multiple Linux boxes or just multiple Linux boxes yeah I think for a long time
now not forever but for the past couple years Synergy kind of had the same thing
where you could pay and they would give you pre-compiled binaries but if you
didn't you know you had to build it from source yourself some distributions still
have it I think arch has it there's a couple other ones Debian maybe but you
know and I don't I've actually built it as well not a big deal I think what was
harder is like I don't know how to build that for Windows so it's a little more
difficult I don't have a Windows build build chain installed that sort of thing
it sounds like now for Synergy 2.0 they're removing some things from the
open source and the GUI will no longer be open source so if you want to pay and
support Synergy which if you use it I mean you definitely should consider
doing it sounds like the core will remain open source so you can still use
it it would probably be command line only you'll have to like write your
Synergy configuration file yourself I don't know I imagine this will still be
the same setup where you're gonna have to compile it yourself get Synergy core
check it out from github build it and then run it so there's definitely I
mean you can go check that out on reddit as well or the hacker news discussion
thread I'm sure we'll see some of the same elements that we just talked about
in the caddy post about entitlement about about changes there's one little
note though that there is a program called x2x which is apparently a pretty
decent alternative for X sessions who knows about Wayland though so I don't
know what are your what are your thoughts on this how do you stand are you the
type of person that doesn't want to ever pay for software do you do you know I
think currently pay for software I think if software is good it's worth paying
for yeah that's nice and simple yeah no I mean and it's like I can feel that too
because I think a lot of times things start open source check I'm scratching
my own itch or an itch I see in the community you start doing it things take
off like crazy like that's kind of what happened to caddy and then just like it
makes so much sense to me that you'll want to go like I want to go make that
my life like if you get so into this project you're spending so much time on
that you really want that to be the thing that you can work on day in and day
out or at least a part of that time you end up needing to have some sort of
revenue model and it's great when you can make that in a way that people seem
to like like support packages donations patreon's it seems like are pretty
popular in the open source community yeah but at the end of the day if you
like use and value this software it has to be whatever whatever is gonna work
both for you the users you the potential population that's going to be buying it
and for the actual maintainers and developers of it because they're gonna
have to spend all their time doing support and not be able to just you know
make the project better that might not be what's in everyone's best interest
and it depends on you know it's not everyone's red hat so may I jump in
absolutely so if I had a project that needs some of these premium features of
caddy I would probably jump on the caddy wedding as you said I'm ready to pay for
software if it's good otherwise if I have a basic project and all of a sudden
my project grows and I'm confronted to the situation that I have to pay for
per instance and so on maybe I would try to avoid this kind of software and it
would start with a software I know or because you're working as you said
you're working for a long time with a web server for example and if all of a
sudden you come to a point where you have to pay for instances if you launch
your server then maybe it's not a good choice for me oh yeah no that's that's
fair but I appreciate that attitude of you know you're happy to pay for what
you use if you can but it may depend on what that you know what the distribution
model what the use of it how that looks in terms of like your actual
application workflows so that make that that makes a lot of sense
anything else you'd like to chime in there Mr. Minimac thank you for joining
us today we certainly appreciate you thanks okay so if you are now super
thrilled by all the possibilities of open source software and not so open
source but you know between Microsoft support between all the great projects
that exist for Linux Linux is a better platform than other to use so if you
want to become a part of it our last sponsor tonight is probably the best
possible way that is our friends over at Linux Academy head on over to Linux
Academy comm slash unplugged there and you will find just about the best
resource possible on the web to learn about Linux so you can just you'll go
there just sign up what are you gonna get when you sign up well you're gonna
find this is not one of those sites that will teach you just about anything right
that's crazy now this is a site that will teach you about Linux and related
technologies you don't have to worry about hey am I gonna learn how to do
underwater basket weaving crochet any of that no they don't do that because
they're Linux experts and that's why all the features that they have show so like
one thing I use all the time nuggets I love those nuggets not only are they
delicious fried golden and tasty but they're like little tiny morsels of easy
to plan around time that just teaches you like one I mean some of them are
kind of big some of them are pretty small but you just get like one solid
new skill or command-line tool or you know whatever that concept is and the
way Linux Academy does it it makes it like they have they make it super easy
just but you know schedule and budget your time they tell you right up front
how long these things are gonna take and it's all customized to the OS that you
need so whether you're trying to learn CentOS for some reason maybe you've been
listening to Noah way too much or you're using Ubuntu like a sane person it
doesn't matter they're gonna customize the courseware automatically for you
which is awesome you have unlimited access to the courses they've got six
different cloud servers hands-on labs and exercises in-depth certification
training that's one of the best parts right there is like if you need to go
get a certificate sign up for Linux Academy they have great courses to help
prepare you for it they have real mentors and stuff that you can talk to
like humans and get help on your projects plus it's stacked full of JB
community members and they've got like team options too so you know if you have
a training budget at work Linux Academy is a great option managers can sign up
for it sign up whole teams it makes it really easy to track people you know
make sure that people are doing their courses see how far they've gone verify
that they are learning the skills that you're you know paying for that to be
used so whether you're big or small next Academy is a great option check out
their courses because they have like a ton of stuff AWS Google Cloud they've
got a ton of the Red Hat tests Linux professional Institute exams on here
maybe you want to learn OpenStack turns out it's super complicated maybe you
want to learn about Azure because you've just been so hyped up about our awesome
Microsoft coverage here on the Linux unplugged show or you just want to learn
all about DevOps so you can become a certified Jenkins engineer a Nagios
certified professional or take puppet 204 system administration using puppet it
really has become one of the go-to trusted places on the internet something
you can put on your resume they even have you know an easy way for you to have a
personal page that will show your accomplishments so if you are looking
for a job Linux Academy can be one of your best partners so head on over to
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and they can get started join us over in the
awesome Linux Academy community it sure is a lot of fun and you can learn a lot
of things about Linux I know Chris talks about a lot but when you will teach
yourself Linux sometimes you miss like random commands there's just so many in
core utils and others that like it's nice to sometimes go through like a
really structured course and you're like oh nice refresher that's how I do that
yeah exactly ah so talking about oldies and goodies here
introducing Firefox quantum it's now two times faster on the speedometer 2.0
benchmark I don't know what that benchmark is but that sounds really
freaking fast I don't know about you beard sounds like a JavaScript benchmark
maybe yeah it does so start your engines Firefox quantum lands in beta developer
edition engines are important both in cars and in browsers I don't know if you
know about that but that's why we're so revved up Mozilla writes because we're
releasing the beta of a whole new Firefox the version number 57 can't
really convey the magnitude of the changes we've made not since they copied
Chrome's crazy version in any way and how much faster this new Firefox is
that's why we're calling it Firefox quantum last October they announced
project quantum an effort to create a next-generation engine for modern
computers by leveraging technology from the servo research project which is the
project that partially helped create rust it has uses rust and is there a
next-generation browser so now we're finally seeing some developments of that
the R&D arm pays off since then the engineering team has been relentless in
their focus on making Firefox incredibly fast so there's already been
a ton of you know Firefox improvements we've talked about that a little bit
things like those containers speed improvements I remember Chris and I both
installing Firefox 55 and being pretty impressed with how much faster it was so
you know they're trying to run for example we've transformed Firefox to run
using multiple processes trying to strike just the right balance between
speed and memory usage plus they've got new things like web VR and web assembly
trying to make you know games other heavy what should be desktop apps but
now run in the web browser which I can only assume is good for Linux in the
long run Firefox quantum is also a big leap forward in that it's much faster on
many top websites so just like browsing your favorites I can think probably like
heavy fit websites like Facebook and other things is a way that you can
notice that and it turns out you can measure Firefox quantum speed too so
they're kind of obsessed with this data driven approach maybe you've heard of it
but you can go check out speedometer 2.0 which is a still in development
benchmark that simulates modern web application results vary based on the
computer and the apps that you're actively using but one thing that's
relatively consistent is that Firefox quantum is about two times faster than
Firefox of a year ago wow all right that's actually that's that's pretty
actually significant I think so take your own we can make your own
comparisons go try it out this is just the beta release but if you care about
this if you want Firefox to be better or you just are a big Firefox user you can
go check it out they even have a little video here oh come on Chrome that's so
slow happy Firefox quantum music
yeah all right so uh it's not like a it's not a blowout but I would say it
certainly seems pretty competitive with Chrome these days so there you go
Firefox quantum I don't know about that name I mean quantum is a fun words and
all I don't know that I mean quantum doesn't really mean fast I don't really
know well well when they speed it up enough they can call it a Firefox
quantum leap oh that's definitely where they're going and I think Scott Bakula
will be there up on stage to help announce that when it happens so we can
look forward to that anyway we have a couple more links about Firefox I
figured we'd round out the show today with Firefox coverage honestly I've been
using a lot of Firefox at work Chrome has all of my personal stuff and I
didn't really feel like making a separate profile profile just for like
work stuff so I was like I'll just have a separate browser for a long time you
know it's just like stock Firefox from up on 216 that wasn't really cutting it
I was used to a lot of niceties from Chrome but once I installed it's actually
really easy I just downloaded the tar from Firefox extracted it under slash
opt now it self updates super easy to sideload it's kind of it's kind of
awesome there's a lot of nice features I've definitely noticed the process the
multiple process improvement there's still some like UX changes between
Chrome and Firefox that get me like I really like that Chrome has the
duplicate tab functionality that comes up helpful way more often than I would
have ever thought there's probably a Firefox add-on that gives you that I
don't know I haven't looked at anyway we have a few more links just to round it
out so like they do a deep dive here over at e rom org Eric roms blog
Firefox memory usage in the quantum era so as a continuation of the are they
slim yet series Firefox release 57 has a huge focus on performance as we've just
heard so we've quantum all the things but we haven't really talked about
memory usage which is something that often falls by the wayside in the
pursuit of performance but honestly like especially these days like when I'm on
not that nice of a laptop or frequently on smaller devices memory usage is one
of the things I actually care about a lot and I know you were kind of like me
beard and we have quite a few tabs open at one time do we not true yeah so
Firefox actually does a pretty good job of suspending them I use the great
suspender in Chrome to do that too so it's but it's like I would almost I
would almost rather have better memory usage sometimes then speed because half
the time I load one page and I'm gonna be on that page for a couple minutes
yeah and so it doesn't I appreciate speed but I would definitely take
memory usage first so it's interesting to see them talking about it so this is
kind of a it's like a little bit technical blog post they've got some
nice nice styling here to show you what's going on
so I'm really excited to see these changes in Firefox I mean if you see the
last changes you see in 40 54 55 really exciting and they continue to do that
it's really cool I'm an all-time Firefox user I mean my first five books really
was called firebirds if you're yes I do if I remember it was a one-man
development at the start and then they took over and then Firefox has become
their browser and I really love it and I won't change I have chromium aside but
my all-time browser is Firefox oh yeah nice yeah it's nice to it's nice to see
that I you know I remember back in the day convincing people that like
Firefox was something they should check out hey get away from that evil
Internet Explorer and it definitely felt like you know Chrome's a great browser
they've done a lot of they've done a lot of great things I was recently reading
about some like fuzzing of the Dom Chrome with their new with their web kit
for blink has added a lot of security but Firefox you know there was a time
where it really felt pretty stagnant and that kind of upset me and I had really
sort of started preparing for a time where Firefox wasn't gonna be brought
up that much but yeah it's true it became heavy at the time and then and
now they have made some changes and and the last month you see the development
and it's going in a good direction yeah exactly but I couldn't say that better
so now I see some hope some momentum and hey I don't have to be ashamed to be a
Firefox user I don't think I mean I'm also a crime user right who you don't
have to limit yourself to one browser these days it's just nice to have
competition so looks like they've done some good work here they've got some
stats you can check out on various platforms memory usage tests but boy
looks pretty great especially on Linux apparently edge has the highest memory
usage on Windows which is a little bit strange because you think that would be
exclusively what they could optimize for and Safari also doesn't doesn't look
like it's doing so great in memory usage on Mac either that kind of surprises me
Chrome is a hog we kind of all know that but it looks like on Firefox on a bunch
of 16 is doing pretty great so overall they're pretty happy with other at but
now our big performance pushes over they'd like to spend some more time
focusing on dropping memory usage so we can start pushing up the number of
content processes they'd also like to see like Mac OS was kind of a big
regression for them in this so they're gonna spend some time investigating that
as well which is always nice while I'm not a Mac user it's nice to see the true
multi OS first class kind of support for this open source project one more I
guess two more and then we'll get out of here today looks like there's a little
sneak peek here client-side decorations will be coming to Firefox yeah so I
don't know how you feel about client-side decorations but maybe
Firefox is getting hip now meh yeah man okay fine beard I was trying to get you
all riled up okay well then this last one this one's just for you oh there's
two more things what am I doing there's just too much news today anyway Mozilla
adds tracking protection to Firefox for iOS and focus gets multitasking focus is
that new browser of theirs that's supposed to be lean and trim fast and
just simple for focused reading while you're on your your device so yeah
Firefox for iOS version 9.0 now available iPhone iPad etc they'll also
have an automatic add and content blocking with private browsing mode as
well as tracking protection in regular so that's great at the fees feature uses
the same ad blocking technology and as Firefox focus for Android and iOS
Firefox desktop and Firefox for Android so it's nice to see that they've really
like kind of pulled up the stops here there's also better sync functionality
and a bunch of other fixes and maybe the bigger thing Firefox focus now has
multitask so multitasking capabilities that allow users to browse multiple
websites simultaneously using tabs it seems silly that this is how we're now
at and I think focus what a big focuses big thing was like didn't really have
that you were focused on it I don't know if that like does this break kind of
what they were doing or is it just a simple and pragmatic change that keeps
things light and minimal but gives power users like a little bit more of what
they're used to I'm not sure but it should not interfere with your private
browsing experience nothing else should really change you just get tabs now so
hey you one thing I was I don't actually use it right now because I just use
Chrome but when I was on my Nexus 5 still I was using Firefox I was really
pleased I like the Firefox for Android it's pretty snappy it was a lot faster
than Chrome at the time I liked the way it did tabs I was kind of surprised
because I hadn't really never really considered it as a real option as a for
a mobile browser before what about you are you just Chrome through and through
I'm Chrome everywhere all the Chrome desktop mobile everywhere yeah well so
you're what you're telling me is that you're not even going to consider our
final story for the day which is a new release of pale moon this is a major
update further in general development of the pale moon browser so you can head on
over to pale moon org slash release notes release notes dot s HTML go check
those out for yourself maybe you're not familiar with pale moon pale moon is an
open source go on a based web browser available for Microsoft Windows and
Linux with other operating systems in development focusing on efficiency and
ease of use pale moon offers you a browsing experience in a browser
completely built from its own independently developed source that has
been forked off from Mozilla Firefox code a number of years ago with carefully
selected features and optimizations to improve the browser stability and user
experience while offering full customization and a growing collection
of extensions and themes to make the browser truly your own so I wonder if
that mean they probably won't be getting those EME extensions we're all worried
I'm so worried about I guess not yeah have you ever used pale moon nope yeah
so you're probably not gonna be yeah I'm not gonna be checking out this new
new release mmm probably not I don't know 2750 it's almost feels like old
style Firefox versions there's got got a nice stuff improved MPE MP3 metadata
parsing change window stuff bunch of user interface fixes a bunch of DOM
improvements so I don't use it either but it's kind of nice to see that their
development is proceeding according to plans it sounds like it's a big release
I'm not gonna use it but it's just a testament I think today's theme might be
hey open source is hard we all need encouragement so yeah here's to you pale
moon I think with that that's that's it for
Linux unplugged today beard thank you so much for joining me I've had like a ton
of fun today and thank you to all of our viewers our wonderful bumble room come
join us there you can head on over to Jupiter broadcasting comm you can find a
whole bunch more of Linux unplugged you can find a whole bunch of other shows
there's also Linux unplugged dot reddit comm that's the wonderful subreddit
beard if they want to see more of you where they should they go oh they can go
to twitter comm slash for Kyle P or rec net if they want to see my stream
wrecked on net and I am at West Payne or you can check me out on the tech snap
program thank you very much for joining us and we'll see you next week
all right what time for the potion post show all right where's all my screens up
in here you got us some titles yeah we got to find some titles Jimmy titles
calm everybody I saw thirty titles that's awesome I would hope that you can
disable this client-side decorations in the browser because I in my desktop
manager I can roll up roll on the the browser window and with client-side
decorations I can't do that oh yeah yeah that's like a lot of people were
hoping that it would be you know set by a preference so yeah yeah just a
preference settings and I'm good oh yeah okay here it looks like in looks like
you need to set widget dot allow dash client-side decoration to true in about
config we'll have the tweet linked about that so in the show notes you can say
this is perfect it's very sad we had three people who wanted to join the show
but there was no one who was capable to care push them in yeah well we
unfortunately we can't stage people while you're in the show so I see the
problem I see the problem so today it was a problem you know well we
certainly appreciate you mr. mini Mac for joining us that was it that was good
fun it was my pleasure I try to give some comments if I have some that is
awesome okay so everyone else we can go vote at
JBtitles.com and we can pick ourselves a title for today's here the example of
program I kind of like open source is hard yeah I do too that's not bad I'm
just gonna just give that a vote here a little votey vote voting all the votes I
say we just go with open source is hard it's right at the top right at the top
okay thank you a kick much appreciated and thank you for everyone for joining
us here on the Linux unproductive program Chris was away but he'll be back
in time for next week's show I do believe so we'll have the hair master
back in here regaliness of stories of Ubuntu the East Coast and I'm sure how
scary and confusing New York City is we actually recorded an episode of user
error today at the end of the week that will cover some of that as well awesome
man there's just so much good JB content coming out so and I'm sure Chris
will also talk about it on next Linux action news I think anywhere that will
give him he's back in time if he's not I might oh cool so everyone stay tuned
Linux action news 21 will be exciting no matter what happens indeed here's
Poland for beard thank you all very much for joining us and sticking around for
today's fun day of broadcasting we'll see you next week and JB reruns coming
right up think the the next live show we should be bs now oh yeah that makes
sense and there might be a whole crap load of coder at the end of the week
whole crap load of coder so get ready for that apparently I just didn't do our
post show here but whatever that's fine chromium will let you browse the web in
VR with the daydream view headset so that's something I don't even know what
that means really but I guess it just means that you can take your daydream
headset hook it up to chromium and then a big wall of a browser a big browser
wall yeah I think there was a new 3d file system a relatively new actively
developed like that old Unix II one from Jurassic Park so that just feels like
that I find it really amusing that they they they they hype the stuff when it's
it's trying to put something that's inherently 2d in a 3d space yeah oh man I
can see the corners of your website bro your website is basically a poster in a
virtual world yeah right exactly