All right, so here's what here's essentially what my the last like week and a half has been like so
Starting last week. I was out at a clients, and I was working and
My kids every time they get sick it kind of like passes around
It's like we're gonna rather Rosie, and then we all die right and around Sunday
I started to get sick the Sunday that I arrived there now
That's a Sunday that feeling prior with starting this is Sunday prior to election day, right?
so Sunday and Monday, I kind of stick it out not too bad and
Around Monday Tuesday it starts to kind of sink in right after the election start to lose my voice start to get super stick start
Throwing up start coughing. Yeah, it's bad and
Go basically the rest of the week like that get home Friday late late Friday
and I thought well, I'm gonna take the weekend and just
hyper hyper rest
Lots and lots of rest lots and lots of water lots and lots of good food try to fix yourself
Yeah, I'm gonna kick myself back into gear so that I can be here ready to roll on Monday
So that's what I do Friday that what I little time I have on Friday
Saturday and Sunday
Monday get a super important call, and I decide I have to go into a client to take care of something before I leave town
So I look at the seats available, and I find out that there aren't a lot of flights to Seattle anyway
So I go take care of the client and I get to the airport fly over to Minneapolis
Which is the only place you can fly out of Grand Forks?
And I spend nine and a half hours in the airport trying to get flights to Seattle
We get to 1045 at night, and it turns out we're not going to get to Seattle
There's just no way flights are not gonna happen so I
Call Rekind I'm like dude. I am exhausted. I have had four or five hours of sleep
I have been here for nine and a half hours
I don't know how to get to Seattle and
I just I don't know what I'm gonna be able to do and Rekind says well
We got to find something so him, and I spend like an hour
looking at every possible flight between Minneapolis st. Paul Airport and
Seattle Airport where did those two intersect well turns out Boise, Idaho is
A city that nobody wants to go to or from from either
Minneapolis or Seattle and so they have 68 seats available, and so I'm all right
I'm gonna go I'm gonna go get on that flight
So I go hop on on the flight to Boise the problem is the flight to Boise
Doesn't leave until 1045 at night, so now I'm at the airport going on 12 hours, and I
Fly to Boise, and I land in Boise at midnight flight back out of Boise into Seattle isn't till 645 the next morning
so I go like lay down to try and get some sleep and
Airport security guy comes and he's like excuse me sir you you can't sleep here you have to be outside of security well
Inside a security they have nice soft little benches outside of security
They have the anti-bum metal benches that have big bumps on them, so you can't actually sleep right
So I'm I try it can't sleep can't sleep can't sleep about an hour in I get some sort of sinus
plug infection something and
It just makes my entire jaw and my face
Just like this crippling pain that I can't I can't even I can't talk I can't breathe
I can't do anything all I can do is concentrate about how much my face hurts
So I look to see if there's like a little shop or something I can go get some some decongestant
Well there is on the other frequent side of security, right?
So I'm telegramming Rekai, and I'm like I need to get something you know arm
I I don't know how I'm going to continue living like this because I really cannot take this
So finally after four and a half hours or five and a half hours the security checkpoint opens back up
I'm able to get through before I actually get through this the security line the
Crippling pain goes away, so I'm well
I mean yeah
This is this is looking up so but I still go spend seventeen dollars on some decongestant stuff just to have on hand
I just considered a mantis suicide pills because it was gonna be and I didn't take my own life from pain right seemed like a good
Investment so I get those I get on the plane, and I'm like and thank God they had first-class available
so I was I was like well, I'm actually gonna get to sleep well apparently everyone in first class on a
645 a.m.. Flight wants to like have a social hour with the flight attendant right that's crazy
So every 30 seconds the flight attendants is coming up, and she's like
Hey there
How do I?
You know do you want anything to drink? Would you like a banana? Would you like toast?
Would you like to add a bread like really what I'd like is for you to GTFO and just let me sleep right you know
So I so I you know it's a it's a hour or something actually I entered the space-time continuum
It took off at 645 and landed at 6 o'clock, which is kind of cool. That's great. Yeah, so
So I land and and
Or maybe it was I took off at 6 and we let I don't remember anymore
but I land and all I want to do is get my just get a rental car and get to the studio and sleep and
I pull on to i5 and it is
Standstill traffic, and I'm like what is going on and so I'm flipping through the radio stations turns out
There's this huge car accident takes me three and a half hours to drive from the airport to the studio
And I finally get to the studio like I don't know 10 10 30 and I just crash right onto the couch
No sooner does my face hit the the the cushion do I hear the deep rumbling voice of a beard going?
Hey, Noah. It's you might want to get up because you got to be on air in 20 minutes. I'm like
So I drag myself back up go into the shower
And I have been trying not to use my voice
for the past couple days for two reasons one is because it hurts and two is
because I need to save what little of my voice I have left to do these two shows so
all
That to say that big long rant to say
I
Hear it's gonna be a fun. Yeah, it's gonna be a fun show and you get you know late-night jazz announcer Noah
That's that's what it's gonna be and the thing is like I was talking to my mother and we're going back and forth and
I'm like this is this is why my clients hire me though and
Because when Noah says Noah's gonna get something done
I will either get something done, or I will die in the process of trying to get something done
But one way or another yeah, it's happening. It's very stressful for your family, but it works out great
Yeah, yeah, well shit with you know we knew about the the JB trip
Well, we didn't know a family perspective was we weren't aware that I was gonna be gone the week prior in Wisconsin
I didn't find that out until late in the week. Yeah, that's rough
so beard was kind enough to share his orange juice with me, so I
Have I have I have orange juice and vitamin C that I'm gonna be sucking down on the whole show
This is Linux Unplugged episode 171 for November 15th 2016
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show where the current hosts have taken off and been replaced by the walking dead
My name is Noah and joining me for the first time both of us here in the studio is Wes
How's it going man, I think I'm doing better than you are I think so you know it's great to finally be here in studio
I don't think we've ever done a show just you and I in the studio. I don't think so
We've done it remote yeah, we've done remotely you and I well those are a lot of fun
So this must be even more I agree I agree and hopefully if all goes well and according to plan
I won't kill you by the end of the episode and Chris won't tell us when he gets back exactly yeah
I didn't wipe out JB. That'll work out
We have a super fun and exciting show, but no show is complete
No show can even begin without first saying hello to our mumble room. Hello mumble room. How are you guys?
Holy cow
Full house well
Thank you mumble room and yeah
If if you didn't catch if this doesn't if it if my rent didn't make it into the pre-show this week
Noah is doing jazz voice Noah because Noah is
Practically dead, but I'm still here so
The first thing we're gonna talk about today is something near and dear to my heart anyone that has known me for more than 10 minutes
If you if you meet me on the street, or we're having a conversation in a restaurant the first thing
I'm going to do is switch you to Linux and
After that happens after you've been converted and after you are letting you that's going to know it's gonna happen. Yeah, I just did it happens
After that happens though the next thing I'm gonna do is I'm going to give you direct communication like to me
So that I can continue to troubleshoot your problems and so that you can communicate not like an animal
And so I put people on telegram. Mm-hmm. I
have so many telegram conversations that it it would take me a
year to
Just get through. I mean I'm scrolling right now right scrolling. I'm continuing to scroll. I'm continuing to scroll
Continuing to scroll. I'm just I have telegram conversations with everyone so if he doesn't respond
That's why yeah, that's why and here's a great way to get me to not respond if you send me like
Seven messages in a row. It's not I'm not trying to be rude
I just I literally like my brain does this weird thing where I'm like I'll just ought to get back to him like I can't
I can't process that much information when the tech star goes off the screen. I just I can't keep up with you
And then and then a lot of times I just forget so it's not me being rude
I just I literally don't know
Yeah, I have I have I have the memory fish of a I have the memory of a goldfish anyway
So besides you don't need to do that. That's what the great feature of editing your messages are for
Right exactly or maybe just you know composing a message one time and then sending it. You know, there's that
so when signal messenger first came out I
I was super excited because I saw this is possibly the only replacement for telegram
I would have ever considered I am I've been very happy with
Telegram and I've had no reason to want to leave telegram, but
At the end of the day all of the security audits of telegram have come back and said
We haven't found any problems with it per se
But the way that they tell us that they want us to audit their security leads us to think that
There may be some security holes that were unable to discover
so introducing
signal signal messenger is a
encrypted
Chat program that not only does chat but also does voice
communication SMS that whole the whole nine yards and it went through a
Crypto analysis and the results are in you can trust it
Signal is secure
So the article from the register.co.uk says encrypted SMS and voice app signal has passed a security audit with flying colors as
Explained in a paper titled a formal security analysis of the signal message protocol published by the International Association of Cryptologic Research
signal has no disc no discernible flaws and offers a well-designed and
Compromise resistant architecture signal uses a double ratchet algorithm that employs in
ephemeral key exchanges
Continually during each session minimizing the amount of text that can be decrypted at any point should the key be compromised
Signal was examined by a team of five researchers at the UK Australia and Canada namely Oxford University
information security professor Cass Kramer and his PhDs
catril cone garden and Luke Garrett
Queensland University of Technology PhD Benjamin Dowling and McMaster University assistant professor Douglas Stabila
so basically they went through and they looked at
the
this particular messenger
And they said yeah
It it's it's actually pretty secure
Providing a security analysis for the signal protocol is a challenging for several reasons first signal employs a novel and
Unstudied design of involving over ten different types of keys and a complex update process which leads to various chains of related keys
It therefore does not directly fit into existing analysis models second
Some of its claim properties have only recently been formalized
Finally as a more mundane obstacle the protocol is substantially documented beyond its there is not
Substantially documented beyond its source code now. That's an important point
signal messenger the
protocol of the server
The entire thing from top to bottom
Open source open code. Yep, you can look at it look at it modify it run it right so that makes me
It makes it a very compelling product now. I tried it a couple weeks ago, and you know my experience was not great
I had a crash a lot
You know that was back when I was on a boat too, but I
I the experience was definitely not as polished as telegram
Did you try it on the phone no because I think you know that's kind of like where they started like they had
Tech secure on Android for a long time
and then they they had a different iOS app and then they kind of made signal and merge them together and finally it's merged and
Then eventually got the the desktop app which I think is a Chrome app right isn't it really these days
So like all electron. Yeah, yeah, it's electron app
So they've come a long long way so that I can definitely see the desktop not being their primary focus at least hasn't yeah
Yeah, and to be fair most of the time. I'm on telegram. I'm using it on my phone
But you know on the other side of the coin
Telegram has made the Linux desktop client a huge priority for them really is it's a very good client
I mean honestly I use it more because I like it as a chat program than it has a security chat program exactly
How about you the desktop version of telegram doesn't even have security at all anyway?
Well, it's still encrypted. It's just like yeah, it's encrypted from this. It's not encrypted
It's it's from server to server like everything on the server is not encrypted
Say what no if on their server when you use the secure chat feature in telegram
That's encrypted when you're not using that it's not encrypted
I was under the impression that the difference within the secure chat and the regular chats were the secure chat the private key is on
your device only
whereas the
Regular chat it's still encrypted, but they hold the key on their server so that it can do synchronization
What'd you but the fact that you can edit it on on both parties means that it's not really secured
Okay, because it's on their server editable
So it's not yeah secure and so that's just like it comes back like telegrams the thing that I try to get my family
On because you know end of the day if we're spied on that's alright
But for people you know that have more real concerns are more concerned about that lead different lives sure cool enough
You know we could have even more trust in open whisper systems and signal in particular. Yeah, yeah
They have a choice anyone in the mumble room actually used whisper. What do you think of it?
Yeah, I use it. I used it when it was tech secure then it became signal, and then it combined red phone
Right into signal. Thank you, and it's uh. It's all it's really good and
It also could do tell on text messages for SMS on signal on the the phone version
So it's it's really cool because it also gives you like a notification whether this this particular conversation is encrypted or not
So like if someone else is using signal
But you're you there or you're using the SMS feature, and they're also using signal as their SMS
It will just automatically convert it into a signal thing so that's really cool
But what can yeah?
What confuses me is more like how do they have the keys shared between devices for conversations that are encrypted?
From phone to phone and then move to the desktop right it's an electron app
It's like I don't I don't even see how it works. That's a good question, but
Just to be one more thing is really interesting to know that that signal protocol is also used by Facebook really
Yeah, they're messenger
Yeah, and what's that? Yeah, it's too bad
They won't let that messenger be like it's the thing is when Facebook started forcing you to install messenger
That's when I stopped using messenger second. I just I don't play that game. Yeah anyone else in the mobile room use signal
What do you think of it?
Nobody when I installed it I installed it, but I have no friends using it so
Very difficult to to really convert them the canonical chat platform
That's the problem if you don't have anybody to get on there
It's a little point in having it right I have I have telegram
But that that got started pretty slowly, and I just met new people there right
Mm-hmm yeah, and you know if you think about it any social networking platform any chat platform any communication platform
Really what it amounts to is you're gonna be where your friends are right? Yeah, and I think that's why
things like g-plus and Facebook have reason to such prominence and in Twitter because
So many people are already there. It just becomes natural. I mean I remember back when I was in high school
MSN messenger was the way that everyone communicated right and
Nobody used it when MSN messenger started to die was when Facebook took off
Yeah, because they had an integrated messenger, and so why would you why would you have friends on MSN?
When you could just chat through Facebook, it just doesn't make a lot of sense
So well what's up? I remember the same thing I used to be on Yahoo messenger and MSN messenger
Isn't it funny how we just kind of go rotate through chat platforms. Yep. I just have everyone on aim
Yeah, I'm not died. Yeah, I see Q like j-core says and IRC
IRC is still around and we're still using yes. Yeah. Yeah, there's a guy never got on IRC until like three years ago
You know I think that's actually kind of it seems like the PRC has kind of had a resurgence at least in the
Tech crowd oh for sure yeah, I was I was on the original ICQ
You know why IRC has got a resurgence because slack has an IRC. Oh, yeah, there you go. Oh, yeah
Yeah, that's that's a big thing and if you think about it really slack is just IRC for 2016
What is right I'm a huge fan of riot and matrix tell me about it um so
Matrix is a way to do federated chat so you can it's sort of similar to diaspora
But for just a chat protocol and so you have all these disparate home servers
And you have usernames at the home servers hosted on a domain
And so it's kind of federated in the same way email is
So if I'm at one server with my name I can send to another server with that name and they connect to each other and start
Sending messages back and forth got the server store the seat and then you log into the servers using some client like riot
That's really the biggest one actually you may have heard of it. I don't know of many others before they used to be
Okay, yeah, yeah, but one of the neat things about it is like
I think they kind of build themselves as the the missing signaling layer for web RTC
So they support web RTC kind of you know yes as a first-party platform and the same time
It's really the signaling part really shines through so it really is good at like they have a lot of different bridges
IRC bridges slack bridges sure rocket ship bridges and so like it's a it seems and the nice thing is you can host your own
Without having to deal with someone else's server directly you always just talk to your own local instance
And then it goes out and federates with other people
And on top of that it also has bridges for slack and IRC
All of your conversations in there like you know like a modern web
HTTP json focused yeah bridge that can just take glue that you can take between I actually like it more than using quassel for IRC
I have all my IRC pumped through a matrix Helm server really that's which is super nice
Yeah, and then I just use riot on like my phone or in my browser. I will have to try that
It's pretty cool. There's a lot of infrastructure you to set up, but it's pretty nice once you get it running
So now how do you have a setup on your phone? Oh the phone?
There's an app so iOS and Android have a riot app right now. You can talk to your own home server
So ham radio you were saying that they're going to be discontinuing along a lot of the Google apps
Yeah, I heard that Google next year is going to be disabling the Google apps on Chrome
And so that means that the desktop client for signal is going to be going away
Huh, okay, and that does not know doesn't mean that
Okay, what does mean then?
Anything running on electron can run on electron because that's a completely different framework
It's Google is room is eliminating the apps that are inside of the chrome store
So like they're like you won't be able to be able to install apps from there. Why are they removing it?
I thought that was a big thing part of the whole Chrome OS thing Chromebook
they're saying that the whole point of those ass was to be able to use offline and
They're saying that the majority of people who use those apps do not use them offline
So it doesn't really benefit them to even have that infrastructure available
That makes sense, but if I go to open whisper systems website, there's no
Download our look on app. It's you have to download it through the Google Chrome store
So, yeah, but they could convert it more than likely like it's mainly that the bit there what they're
Just they're removing is the offline features and because signal is a online only thing
Well as far as like is sending the conversations back and forth right it makes sense they could just switch it but
They're not that's good. It's gonna be for at least another year. I guess we'll have to wait and see
They're actually doing it they're just gradually doing it most of the rest you'll be doing it for like a year
They're just gradually doing it most of the rest you had a comment about why IRC is coming making a research
Actually wasn't really that it was speaking of research. It's just that I can remember using it before the internet became big and
as
Things went on a lot of people that were on like, you know
The old-school BBS is and all that kind of stuff if they wanted to keep in touch with each other
They ended up just sliding over to IRC because it gave them the same kind of setup as well
I RC unlike let me see if I can get the theme here
MSN messenger Yahoo messenger
AIM if you're not getting the theme the theme is that they're all branded IRC is not branded
It's just kind of there. It's sort of like hey, it's a library. It's called a library. It's not Roger's library or
Verizon's library, it's a library you go to the library, right?
Sure, so it was the same thing with IRC just anyone had it and he would access it
The servers were all over the place. You just kind of went there. So it wasn't
Attached to any one particular company. So it wasn't a matter of hey
I don't like this company or hey this company how it now has you know
These flashy little ball things that wink at you and stuff like that. It was just kind of there
All right. Anyone else any thoughts on signal messenger? So
They conclude that it's impossible to say if signal if signal meets its goals as there are none stated
but what their analysis did say is approves that it's it it satisfies security standards and
They add that we have found no major flaws
So it's not definitive but it's a kind of the first the first ratchet if you along the way towards it being trusted
All right. Now this next story as you can imagine it has me super excited and that is that the new MacBook
doesn't run Linux
So there was a gentleman that did a very comprehensive write-up in the Ubuntu
subreddit and basically he took his brand new 2015 MacBook and
Went through and said here's what I tried to do
Here's I tried to get Linux to work and here's why it doesn't work. Basically
It the
The first problem is that you can't even get past the grub screen. So you can't even actually get Linux to boot
Secondly if you can actually get into Linux the built-in keyboard and mouse don't work
Only the power only the power key works to force
The the reboot and he tried this on the non touch bar version
He says that there's a patch for the 2015 MacBook that may work for it, but he's not obviously entirely sure
Any links to the driver and we'll have that in the show notes and the biggest problem is that the NVMe drive?
has the wrong PCI class ID so
Linux doesn't actually see it as a bootable device. So you can't boot off the built-in hard drive
Which by the way, if you look at Louis Rossman's breakdown of it, they used like some
fancy special connector that is
You know only available to them and that particular computer so you can't just replace the drive
The thing is a walking disaster
Another thing is like the input devices. He was saying they don't work
That's because they're over the SPI bus and said right USB bus, right?
It really is quite a different machine than we've seen before
This thing is a disaster. Yeah, I was glad to see that at least some of the people in the reddit thread world, you know
Thank like being like well at least thank you for sharing right?
I know some people turn to the like
You know like you should have checked and like yeah
Probably if you weren't willing to spend that that money check to see if it's Linux compatible right given like the history of Macs
But it is it is a nice donation to the field of maybe we can eventually get something work sure
You know and the thing is is there's oh, there's a lot of chat in this in the subreddit about well actually
There's a lot of chat in general the community of we need to be ready to accept Mac users when they come over to us
I think a certain amount of time should be spent on that and then I think we should start focusing on
the manufacturers that aren't actively working on these like
One-off models that are just freaking crazy. You know, it's one thing to you know
Take a Lenovo machine and swap a wireless card in it
It's one thing to open a you know, the Adele and and you know
Put a different wireless card in it or put a different sound card or something like that
It's something entirely different when the manufacturer makes a totally separate hard drive that is barely related to
What we know as computers everything
Exactly
exactly, it's just
The amount of time that I would like to see the the Linux community doing that
For a couple of reasons one is I don't know that I even necessarily agree that there are droves of people that are buying
a 2015 MacBook and then wanting to put Linux on it
Think of you're in the market for a to think of you're on the market and you're willing to make a compromise
For a laptop that's limited to 16 gigs of RAM and doesn't have an escape key
You're probably buying that computer because you wanted macOS to begin with
so I
Don't know that that's a really valuable use of our time
But secondly if we really want to take people over and we really want to be there for Mac users
Then they can sell their Macbooks and buy something like a system 76. It's gonna work right out of the box with Linux, you know
I'd be interested what you guys in the mumble room think I
Think it's crazy that you have that 16 gig limitation on something so expensive
I mean I have 16 gigs on a T for 20 from 2011 so but it's he 420 has so much more space on the motherboard
And the chassis you have to kind of understand what Apple's constraints are for their motherboard and layout of devices and such things
Well, they're only getting one dim in there effectively
Even though I think it's actually soldered on but it's the capacity of one dim in one controller, right?
So it's until they make 32 gig dims. They're not gonna have 32 gigs available
Yeah, but you know the answer that I've seen for that is that they wanted they wanted to keep it smaller because they wanted
More room for the battery exactly, but hold on
That stands up to reason until they say well until we reach 100 watt hours
And then we don't want to go over that
Because the airline the airlines wouldn't let you take a laptop on on a plane and I looked into this that's total BS
The airline restricts external batteries over a certain
Oh and I don't remember off the top of my head what it is X external batteries are restricted
So you can't separate on your big pack of right now separate batteries
You can't take on and only that you can take that on carry-on. It just can't be checked in luggage
Internal batteries things that are inside of a device. There is no limit
So you could have if you can find a way to get a five thousand, you know
What our battery attached to a laptop as long as it's in case the in the laptop generator in that whatever day
Yeah, exactly. You can take that puppy put it in a laptop bag. Check it in the baggage compartment
No problem from the FAA. So that's BS
Now they might be limited to it to a single dim and I guess I can understand that the problem is
It seems like they had two lines
the MacBook Air seemed to target the
Daily desktop user and the people who wanted light and thin exactly there were their focus exactly. I want a thin
Daily driver laptop exactly exactly that seems like the appropriate place to put in
You know 16 gigs of RAM and integrated graphics and stuff like that. The pro line has always been set aside for
People that are doing more demanding tasks media tasks
You know, well, what else do they have? I guess just media tasks, but people
How much yeah, yeah, I guess you're running VMs so I don't understand Apple's decision to handy
well, I guess I shouldn't say that I
I understand their decision from this standpoint
Even with as many MacBooks as you see at a conference
They still don't really hold any significant share of the PC marketplace, right? I'm still under 10% Maybe 15, right?
They're the outliers in the enterprise, right?
So by and large
Majority dominated by Windows right with Windows 10 no longer having a I mean as far as they say no longer having a newer and newer
version of Windows
They've lost the advantage of well buy this machine in the last two ten years or whatever and we'll just keep giving you updates
No, Microsoft can make that claim at least for the time being right at the same time
You look at tablets and smartphones and they are surging right a lot of people even die-hard Linux users
Make compromises and go buy an iPhone or an iPad. Yeah, definitely
So if you're the if you're a executive at Apple and you're sitting in your office and your primary
Task is to make a lot of money and you look over here and you say
We're selling iPhones out the wazoo and making bank on them and over here on this department
We're still struggling to get a real grasp on the marketplace
Where are you gonna spend your R&D? Where are you gonna spend your time?
Where are you gonna spend pushing all of the stuff together?
If you look at the latest version of Mac OS it resembles now more than ever
iOS right, so I think that there is a I think there's a real chance
That I think there's a real chance that what they're looking to do is
Migrate iOS into Mac OS make them all one platform
Let the people that are doing media production and all that stuff
Port all their tools over to iOS and use all that stuff and
Then just then they all they have to do is sell what they would call like an iPad Pro with it
Oh wait, we already have that. You know what I mean? So it's just like at every turn
It seems like they're continually doing that. I'd be interested if anyone has any feedback
I think it plays into their history as well of just like, you know, but before they went Intel they had their own
I mean not that their own architecture, but they you know, they used these power chips and they used Motorola chips and
I think we just see what was almost more of a convenience or coincidence for them when it was like a large overlap with
Our x86 based PC marketplace and I think we see iOS as sort of its own ecosystem its own architecture
They're making their own processors or at least, you know having them fabulous
Right, so I think that they've always viewed their desktops or Mac OS X in the same way
It just doesn't look like it from the outside
But now like with more with their touch bar and with their you know
The arm chip sitting on their system on a chip right?
Well, it really is like they see it as a whole platform as one thing and probably yeah
It will form more into with iOS into their Mac ecosystem
Mamoru, what are your thoughts?
Honestly, I'm saying
IOS is going to be better than Mac OS for professionals is I didn't say that
Well, I don't think IOS would ever be for professionals if anything any professional that I know from
Outside of Chris or Rekai or professionals. I know personally
They don't use Mac anymore because of their hardware choices and their software choices. Yeah
They're like they're done. They they've had it if if Matt doesn't you know cater to them and go look
We have these awesome machines for editing. We got this rock solid OS, you know
We're still working on Final Cut. If you don't grab those people you're gonna lose them and I don't see them doing that with their offerings
Yeah, I agree. Yeah, we actually we had a we have a small production house in Grand Forks
They're an offshoot of a local news agency and they have switched to Adobe
Premiere on Windows boxes and the university. Yeah, and the university first they dumped. They originally dumped Final Cut Pro for
For Premiere and and the new machines the new desktop machines are Windows boxes because they support all of their PCI capture stuff
And they have repurposed the they had like a learning lab and those had a lot of IMAX and those have been repurposed for up with
Adobe
Premiere on on those IMAX so that when those students get up into the the later years and they're they're doing because then
In your third and fourth year when you're doing journalism school, then you actually go do assignments, right?
And so they're teaching them to do it on these IMAX in
On Premiere because they already had these IMAX and then they're moving off onto these Windows machines where they're using Adobe
So I've seen the exact same trend. However, I of course being the Linux guy that I am I
Contacted a couple of guys that were teaching that particular video course at UND
Switched them to Linux
Got them editing all of their stuff under Linux and now this year is the first year that they are teaching in tandem with
Premiere Lightworks, so it's gonna be done. Yeah, unfortunately, it's gonna be done on IMAX because that's where the that's where the lab is
But the advantage of those students is they can take those they can take that software those things that they have learned
Inside of that class and take it home and then they can edit there. So
I actually haven't checked in with those guys to see how that's going. But um, you know at the end of last year
That was my that was my understanding that that you know, they they saw that as being a really competitive advantage
So I I have seen that I I have I have seen that trend as well with people moving off of OSX
But I think what you have to consider is that there are a lot of people
That change the definition of what a professional is right 15 years ago 20 years ago
a video professional was somebody that showed up with a $65,000 camera and had either you had a studio camera
You're recording inside of a studio or you had an electronic news gathering crew. So you had an ENG camera
And you filmed and then you brought that back into an actual edit bay and you had and you know
And you had you had a you had an actual hardware mixer where you took your audio
Where you know everything was recording you could tweak all that stuff in you know live right there and you do all of your editing
And then you produce it you take it to your editor and then that would go out and then that would get produced onto
Some sort of published media like a DVD or VHS or whatever master sent and get stamped out exactly and we can send out, right?
today
The definition of a professional has changed Apple sees a professional as somebody who films on their iPhone
Edits edits on iMovie and publishes on iTunes the New York Times fired the majority of their photographers
And gave all of the reporters iPhones and said here they all have 64 gigs of RAM start clicking away
I'm sure you'll get something that's usable
Does that quote post? Huh? Well, you know, yes, but I mean, you know, there was a there was actually I was looking
I was watching a um
Thing on still photography and they bought a bunch of Canon rebels put them all on auto mode
Handed them to 50 people and said go take pictures of the sport events
They had you know
150,000 photos 148,000 of which were useless and then they found like six that they actually wanted to use
But the cost to buy those cameras give them to people have them shoot was still cheaper than hiring like 10 real professional photographers
So I think the definition of a professional is is rapidly changing. I think people on YouTube broadcasting themselves
Are professionals, right?
And Apple does a good job of hitting that like we have a pipeline and it's good enough for what you want to do
I completely agree. They
Put all of those tools in place. So my my question back to you, sir, is
Is is it possible that Apple says they take all of the stuff in iOS and they just say all right. Here you go
Let's make
Let's make these tools available on iOS and push those out to people
Just redefining what a professional is
Or you're still not seeing it
Maybe i'm totally off
I I can say that they the fact that they're more switching to the prosumer grade. I don't think professional is really changing
I think more
More areas and industries are developing to become professional
But I think the vast majority of people who are like professional youtubers are using professional gear
Yeah, I I think that statement is true like you like you can use
low-end
prosumer stuff or consumer stuff, but eventually you will be going to
Cannons and other rigs and you know professional XLR mics. It's just the road to get there pretty much
so eventually
I think any kind of prosumer that's not hardcore
A studio or news journalists or anything like that from the past
Will eventually want to demand tools from Apple and I think they're just going to have to give it to them eventually
Andy Akers, you're saying that that you still define a professional photographer as somebody who can operate a camera in manual mode
And it's essentially second nature to them
Andy Akers
He's going once going twice
Thanks for the call. So, uh, basically I
I believe I truly believe that Apple is uh, is
Is sucking it up on I think they're sucking on the desktop and on the laptop
And I think that's a good thing for their business model because I don't think that was where they're going to see
Huge profits anyway, right? And I think that the cost to continue to develop macos to make it a competitive platform
Was going to be high and I don't know that they would see the returns that they're getting
So I think that's a good thing
for them as a Linux desktop user. I have never been more excited because
Windows despite the changes that they have made
still suck and they will forever hold a
A bad taste in everyone's mouth for being Windows. What do you what do you think though about the that new subsystem of theirs for Linux?
And and the potential there for at least like a new version of Windows
What do you what do you think though about the that new subsystem of theirs for Linux and and the potential there for at least
Like the developer side or the content creator, right? Because they have the Adobe apps. Yeah, and there you can have both
I I it did it does scare me a little bit
um
I think maybe what we're counting on in some ways is there is that distaste distaste of Windows and the want for a real
You know POSIX style system, which you get with OS X at least a little and and obviously with Linux
Huh?
I I I I I guess I can see that I I can see that being a threat at the same time
I think that eventually the people that like to dig down and get dirty with the system
Are eventually going to want more so I think they'll come over to us eventually
And I think they're also going to just be honest with you
I think they're just going to get tired of their computer crashing all the time
I like it. So uh
So this brings a lot of hope to me because I think that you're going to have people
I don't think Windows is a great place to be on the desktop
I think macOS is becoming a less great place to be on the desktop. And so
Microsoft continues to focus on and in transition to cloud-based services
Exactly and Apple is transitioning and focusing on mobile. So who's left to really concentrate on the traditional desktop?
Linux now
If if if the answer to that is while the majority of people are just going to have an iPhone
They won't have a computer. I can totally live with that
if my job revolves around supporting Linux desktops for people that work in in CEO positions
Or tech level positions or something like that and in the traditional desktop keyboard mouse laptop
If that paradigm is is relegated to Linux
Even if the even if the amount of people in that paradigm shrinks and those people have and the majority of the society
Has moved over to mobile devices. I can live with that compromise. I can happily live with that compromise
I think I think there's some nuance there at least in terms of where
We're expected to do things but along as long as things are currently shifted towards the
Obviously you can do content creation in some domains on your mobile device
but I think as long as it's like, you know, there's professionals in the back rooms creating things and then you know
We have all these other devices we use for consuming and interacting with them. Sure. Yeah, that's where I could I could live with it that way, too
so a couple of uh, so a couple of weeks ago we talked about the
Super Nintendo on
or the uh, the new Nintendo Entertainment System that is going to be running on Linux
And apparently there is an exploit compromising Linux desktop
Wes, can you tell me about this? Yeah, so it doesn't actually relate to that fun device. It's just kind of similar
There's a lot going on with the NES these days
So this is a zero day exploit right now, though
At least the one that was released it really only affects like a specific version of Ubuntu 12.04
So it's not something you necessarily need to have
But basically there's a Gstreamer plugin that plays these NSF files, which are music files from the from the NES
Um, and when you're using something like Nautilus
Yeah
It it tries to part like when you open it
these files gets parsed by Gstreamer and there is a
There's a vulnerability in in one of these it's in the bad set of plugins for Gstreamer and it only is in the 0.10
Distribution not the newer 1.0 Gstreamer package
But basically when that happens then
Then you get pwned, but it's kind of interesting because these files they're not like a regular music file, you know broken down into samples
Yeah
It actually emulates a processor like it takes less space and the way they're encoded it emulates a processor to then
Tell and then it tells the processor
Do these instructions to produce these tones and then it captures those tones and plays them which I thought was kind of interesting
It is interesting
So not to not to totally so first, I guess I'll open it up to the moment room. What do you guys think of this?
You guys are so quiet today
You guys come in the the technology of the the emulating the the processing of it to create the sound is it's kind of amazing
because it more like one of the biggest problems with most emulators is like they're trying to
reverse engineer it instead of trying to
Try to create a hardware emulation
Uh-huh, like one of the the biggest things is like a lot of games that are impossible to play as an emulator because the the hardware
Emulation that they're trying to compensate is more like slowing down the current process the current hardware we have
whereas this is more super interesting, but the
the the the problem with the zero day doesn't really sound like it's a big problem, but it's
You know, it's going to get a ton of attention, especially like ars technica and stuff, right?
And it just to me it was more interesting really to highlight these files and the way they work and of course to be just
To just to realize like, you know, um, obviously this just doesn't affect newer distributions
But it's always good to be aware of parts of your systems that are
Taking vulnerable inputs which are you know file system files and auto loading them or that kind of thing
Just just something to think about
Anyone else? I'm only using 12
1204 should yeah gtfo great from what I saw it was
Is recommended to use a raspberry pi and put retro pi. I mean, how does that compare?
I mean, this is not really right. It's
This is a difference between being an official product versus um, you know creating yourself. It's like you you technically aren't
Legally allowed to download roms unless you own the game itself
so um
They're not losing any money from it. So they're not gonna like
technically attack anyone for those doing those things but
This is more like if you want to have like a set top box kind of thing that's built for you
And you don't have to build it yourself, but there's also certain games that can't run
without proper emulation
So like if you're getting retro pi that retro pi is just like a distro that pulls all these different emulators in
So you're not really going to get the exact kind of experience
So maybe some games like for example, this is not what nes classic does because it's just the nes
but if they ever come out with like n64 classic or something like that, that would be amazing because games like banjo kazooie were
taking
Flaws that were in the hardware of the n64 and making that a feature of the game
So they're impossible to emulate. So if they figure out a way to emulate the the
Processor for the n64 that would be amazing
I mean i've been waiting on that a long time as well. Uh, super nintendo, I think would be more exciting to me or n64
I I i'm really hoping for the n64
In fact when uh, I was I was joking with rikai a couple of weeks ago
I said when we talked about that little portable nes system. I said I wish nintendo would make a portable n64 system
Right, I would take that everywhere. I would if I had a portable game boy like device that I could play
golden ion that would be ideal, right and what uh rikai's answer was
He said you have one. It's called your s6 and I said
They they have that and he goes. Yeah, so sure enough went to the google play store
And uh, and I was able to download an emulator on my phone and you know, the great thing about
My phone is it's on ting, right?
And so I have I don't pay to download any of the any use any of my data because i'm on wi-fi
In fact, we have a special wi-fi network that is at every location that we work at and it we call it the tech network
The tech network and it's oh that's clever. I like it. Yes. It's there's no speed restriction anything like that
So basically any client I go to I have internet. I have network coverage
Unrestricted unrestricted network coverage and so I can walk into to any of these places and and just my phone automatically connects
So basically what I need my mobile carrier to do is to provide me with
Basically gap coverage, right? So right when you're on your way between sites exactly. So I had a nine and a half hard drive between
uh, wisconsin and grand forks and then
Today, uh, well over the past two days. I actually I had to
I was in an airport for well what ended up being like 17 hours 18 hours, right?
And the great thing was I don't usually
Tether on my on my laptop. Usually I just have a dedicated little card that that connects there
Card wasn't connecting and so I was like i'll just tell it right now
This is something I haven't used in a long time on my phone
My phone had a great signal laptop didn't I take my phone?
Climb up the airport and set it on like the edge of the window. Nice. Yeah enable hotspot
Ting doesn't charge me any extra for the hotspot. It's just pay for what you use
So you use 100 minutes you fall into that bucket
They charge you for 100 minutes you use one gig of data you use one gig of data and they don't care if you're using
That giga data on your phone or if you're using that giga data through tethering on your laptop cell phone plans for adults
Exactly. Yeah cell phone plans for adults. Now. There was a gentleman in the chat room that asked me if I would send him
A ting sim. So if you send an email to know at jupiter broadcasting.com with your address
I will throw a ting sim in there and get that out to you. No problem ting sims as a service
I am. Yeah, I am. This is not an offer for everyone
I said one person that like reached out to me and specifically asked i'm going to accommodate him
I am not going to send ting sims to everyone but that particular guy it's i'm feeling generous
So, uh, you send me your address and I will ship you out of ting sim free of cost at my expense
And if you want to get a ting sim, you can go to linux.ting.com
It'll get you 25 off your first device your first month of service or
You can get 25 sim cards
You didn't think about that. Did you no I didn't no you didn't but if you wait for the dollar
That's your whole business right there. Exactly exactly if you wait for the dollar sim sale
You could get 25 sims
for free
with your first month of service
I don't know if that's really a necessary or good thing to do but you could totally do it
The other thing you could do is you could get uh, 25 off your first phone which for me
Paid for the majority of the phone because I buy cheap phones exactly or you could get 25 off your first month of service now
Between my wife my son my mother and I I think our average ting bill is like
Oh, and I have a couple office phones and I think our average ting bill is 45 bucks
That's all right. Let me look i'll tell you what not only does ting have an amazing dashboard. They have an amazing app
We don't talk about the app nearly enough, but I can pull this app up in about 30 seconds 27
Wes, will you verify please? Yep, 27. All in the nose now. Look at how many minutes i've used
Zero zero minutes. You know why because all of my calls are funneled over sip
So I use a I use a program data and then and then you're just you have the one bucket system to worry about
Exactly not only do I have the one bucket system to worry about that particular bucket doesn't apply to me
Basically anytime i'm not in in transit, right when I got here as soon as I got here stop not using minutes anymore
So linux.ting.com get yourself something nice and thank you
To ting for sponsoring the linux unplugged program
All right guys, so let's take a look I want to dive back into
This uh
Linux fest northwest founder honored with uh, the community builder west. Can you tell me a little bit about this?
uh, yeah, so there's just uh, there's a an award called the cascadia community builder award and it's you know, it's meant to
to recognize people in the the cascadia region the pacific northwest who
Have done good work building community building things that people can feel a part of building organizations that last you know
Over time that bring people to get diverse groups together
and so this is kind of it's just a nice article over on open source.com talking about uh,
Bill who has been the the main founder and person running linux fest northwest. Obviously the home show here of the jb network
Yeah, um, so kind of tells the story back in 1968 the great northern railroad hired bill then a student at western washington university my alma mater
Uh because of his computer experience
Uh bill became interested in linux and open source community in the late 1990s as things were ramping up
With another few other computer nerds
He helped start the bellingham linux users group and then from then started its linux fest and since then he's been he's been doing it uh,
You know, he's he's seen a lot at other festivals around the area. He's known in the community. He's recognized by people all around
So this is just a great little thank you bill. Thank you for all you've done and some nice community recognition. That's super cool
Momo room, how many of you guys are coming out to linux fest northwest?
I'm, hoping to be there. Awesome. Anyone else?
No idea if i'll make it all right. All right. Well, it's in april. So start thinking about it now
early may
Money money issues. Yeah, that's that's a real thing, right if we could come up with some way
To have some sort of like sponsorship to get people to uh different linux fest. That'd be a be the real way to go
Uh, you know, the other thing is too is I wish they would split these uh linux fest linux cons up a little bit
Because it would be nice they all hit like in the first couple months. Yeah march to june
You know scale the linux fest northwest itself. Yeah, it's just like immediately all in a row exactly
Yeah, it just it just it just it drains the pocketbooks of those of us that have to uh,
Have to be at all those it's unbelievable. I'll be at scale. I don't know about lfnw. All right
Uh, so kde neon users are requested to perform a full
Reinstall, uh west. What can you tell me about this?
Uh west, what can you tell me about this? Uh, well, so it looks like it was just that some of their uh package distribution servers
Uh, it was possible for people to push things to them, right?
So here's a package archive used by katie neon was incorrectly configured so that anyone could upload packages to it
They have no reason to think that anyone actually did so or that there was any, you know
Intentional compromise or that any of these packages are bad, but they do ask that for your own protection
They've they've updated packages. Everything has a newer version in the repo now
So if you if you do a reinstall you'll get all the new packages and they fix that configuration
And restore the server. So it's just something to be aware of if you're on neon
That's crazy
uh
What else do we have mumble room? How are you guys doing? I haven't heard much from you
This would be a great episode for you guys to to chat because my voice is just uh, it's not great
Take it easy on poor newick. Well, I mean, I don't know you're chatting at all
I just don't want to be rude when people are talking. Oh, no, no
Um, we we're we're following your lead though. All right
For so for the about the uh, the katie neon thing
um
There it's not necessary to
To do a reinstall
They're they're suggesting that
If you're worried about it
Like for extra security to be absolutely sure you could do a reinstall
But they're saying that if you just do an upgrade once the packages are rebuilt that it's it should be fine
Do they not sign their packages?
they they do sign the packages but it's more like
if someone had access like the configuration issue is that someone could just push the packages and
They would be on the server
kind of
with like
Already allowed to be in so they would be signed by this process kind of yeah
So unfortunately that doesn't solve the problem
but uh
They wouldn't be able to like replace the other packages. They would be able to replace like add their own
extra package they could kind of like so it wouldn't be like
Like having to rehash anything or anything like that
It's just more they could put something on the server and then they could kind of like
Trick a mega mega meta package to pull something down. It's it's a really
Uh, it's it's a really scary sounding issue that is not as bad as it is but could potentially be terrible
So it's more like just let's be aware of it. Yeah
It's more like let's get it and get in front of it. So it doesn't actually make any problems
I'll tell you what else is terrible is the internet of things this article comes to us from hackerboards.com
Despite growing security threats the internet of things hype shows no signs of abating
Feeling the fomo companies are busily rearranging the robots for iot
The transition to iot runs deeper and broader than ever before
Iot runs deeper and broader than the mobile revolution everything gets swallowed into the iot including smartphones
Which are often our windows on the iot world and sometimes our hubs and sets are and endpoints now I have
Said once or twice on this show and on lass
That I don't like the internet of things. I don't like the concept. I don't like the name
I don't like the branding. I don't like anything about it
and yet there the answer now is
from what I understand
looking at containers
To solve a lot of the problems that we face in the iot world. So canonicals iot oriented snappy abuntu core
Version of abuntu is built around a container like snap package management mechanism and offers app store support
The snap technology was recently released on its own for linux distributions on november 3rd canonical released abuntu core 16
Which improves the white label app store and and update service control some update serve update control services, excuse me
So basically their idea is let's take this really crappy
World that we live in and try to use containers to leverage updates and security patches
and I think on one one on one side that sounds ridiculous because
Obviously from the world of our you know in the you go from the iot world to the server world and containers are the new
Thing that's kind of viewed skeptically from the security angle where vms are trusted or you know bare metal even
Uh, but but I think here the the idea really is, you know
You're using you know using a bunch of like this the snap stuff or you're using resin.io
Which is like a platform trying to use docker containers on embedded devices. Yeah, um, I think really what you're getting
Is better, you know a better understanding of what you of the build structure and a lot of these embedded devices, right?
Like they're you know, they're using build root. They're they're forking from existing open source packages
But they're maybe not upgrading things. They may not have great build pipelines or anything approaching that so I think this is just trying to take
Some some modern development practice modern, you know understanding what your dependencies are understanding what you're built from in ways where you can then
Improve on that rapidly, uh to to hopefully at least compartmentalize and then establish right because with a container system you need to then
Rather, you know
If you have a telnet system, you know
You have telnet running because you have to export the port for the telnet and you have to configure the daemon
Uh more so than if you're just taking a fork of open wrt and sticking it on your light bulb bow chicken. Wow. Wow, you nailed it
Yeah, no, uh mama room. What do you guys think?
I don't know how that fixes the problem. I mean most of the problem is people aren't doing their jobs in
Setting the systems up securely
right, so I think I think and not not that this is the answer but more like it's it's one place they're exploring I think the
their their idea then is to is to
And make that easier to do have better systems to produce those artifacts to produce, you know
And things without having to do things from scratch where you might not have the incentive to actually update things or configure them securely
But personally I still like the separate offline network of things. That's my favorite. Yeah. No, that's fair
Yeah
But you're just complicating the the design of the solution to make it simpler and more secure kind of oxymoron there, you know
Well, I I mean, I I think I think basically what they're doing is they're trying to say if you're going to have something insecure
First of all, let's try to make it so that the people that develop the iot stuff don't have to
Think about the security per se that can be handled for them on a different level and be pushed out, right?
And the second they're not thinking about it now
I agree, but that but so I mean if my choice is between
An insecure internet of things any more secure internet of things. I don't like internet of things either way
But i'll take more secure internet of things every time right and it may be that you have less of a service area that you
You know if you're if you're responsible for the entire os stack and securing it versus if you're grabbing a base, you know
Almost container hypervisor type thing and then you're responsible just for your app and what it exposes. It may be a different incentive structure
And also it's more even more specific that it's not just a containerization system like docker
snaps are
Are are secured in a more of a mount a mount point that is its own
Separate thing that it's but it's also connected to other pieces so that you have benefits of basically both worlds
Hurricane uh herndes
Hey, how's it going on
Correct me if i'm wrong
But most of the iot in devices that have been insecure has been because people haven't followed
Best practices right and we're talking at the base level of the operating system
So I don't see how docker is going to stop people deploying these
devices with operating systems that have
Um, you know, I mean the same password on all the systems or I mean the same security certificate
You know, I mean these guys are not following best practices and I think that's the biggest issue here. Yeah, absolutely
It's it's it's because it's not docker and it's more it's the same thing of you want to upgrade your system
You do snap upgrade you're done
Well, I think what he's saying is that if you if you take a company
That doesn't it's we have a human problem not a security problem, right?
We have companies that aren't taking security seriously
And if you think that technology can solve security concerns and you don't understand the technology and you don't understand the security concerns
That's the famous quote, right?
Right. It's the issue of them being lazy and not updating it sure, but that's the same thing with all software of any kind
Okay, fair enough mini mac
Yeah, I more and more see that
Internet of things has become a marketing
Argument for products. I don't see the reason that a coffee machine has to be on the internet
So the real need and use it to secondary and these are in fact the machines
They're in fact used for spamming other machines afterwards, right?
Right, and that happens a lot actually you find that
You find that you you you run into a lot of these machines that like I saw a meme
A couple days ago and it was talking about you know things like the the the internet connected broom and stuff like that
When you get to I mean there becomes a point where it becomes ridiculous, right?
There are certain things that make sense to be connected to the internet, you know from my perspective
But even people like my grand my grandparents would have not understood internet connected light switches to them
That would have been ridiculous that you'd want to put your light switch on the internet
So I I have a hard time deciding where exactly to draw that line because what seems ridiculous to me
May may not seem really ridiculous to the next generation and what seems perfectly logical to me probably seems ridiculous to the previous generation
but I this idea that this idea that
This idea that everything is is going to just happen in the cloud for us and talk out to the internet
Is kind of ridiculous, you know, I think it was william that brought up
There is a you don't have to be on the internet to have a connected lifestyle
I have ip based cameras. They are connected
Three through their own dedicated switch. They have their own dedicated dhcp server
Uh, and they are on an entirely separate wiring system than the rest of the house
They are technically networked. Yes, but there is absolutely no tie-in to my normal household
Network and certainly no tie-in to the internet
So the chances of those cameras getting hacked some even if they they could be the most insecure thing in the world
The chances of those getting hacked slim to none slim to none unless you're physically inside of my house
And you manage to plug into that switch. There's no wi-fi access. There's no outside internet access
In a weird way. I kind of wonder if we haven't jumped a little too far with containers too fast
I kind of wonder if we haven't rushed it a little bit
I remember when containers first came out
I barely had a chance to start trying them before I started to hear people rolling them out into production
And in fact, I myself have rolled a couple of them out in production
And the only reason I was comfortable doing that is because we have services like digital ocean that
You that I can go ahead and try those things on before I actually have to go to a client's network
You know or someplace that where it really matters and you can set up a production ready
Emulation suite, you know, there was a time
When I was going through networking where I had to rent a cisco stack
So I rented, you know, you know a cisco switch and a cisco router and a cisco this and you know
It's very expensive. It's a couple hundred dollars
For the week to access that what they call the cisco lab, right?
and I I did when I was first setting up containers I did the same thing by going over to digital ocean and using the
uh the promo code do unplugged
And basically I was able to get a ten dollar credit and I was able to spin up
My first two droplets my first two five dollar droplets for free using their private networking
I was then able to build a virtual data center that I could test all of this stuff on
And I mean it was it was a total game changer
So come five six months down the road being able to walk into a client's
Facility and say yeah, I can do this with confidence. Yeah, we can go ahead and set this up
It was no problem for me because I had already tried it
I had already had a chance to play with this stuff
And if it didn't work out, I just blew it away and I started all over again
And i'll tell you the real key though, and no pun intended pun intended
The real key is when you pair this stuff with a ubi key
Because now you're not getting root passwords emailed to you and they're always like some obtusely long thing that you have to like copy
And paste and then you forget that you have to use shift when you paste into the terminal
So it doesn't really paste and then it closes something else. Oh my gosh, it's ridiculous
And then the other thing is too is I have this weird paranoid sense about me
I'm, like oh the nsa is spying on me that they've captured my yeah. Yeah, they've captured my email now
None of that with the ubi key
I literally add my ssh key and then when I spin up all my digital ocean droplets
I just checked that little box that says, you know, noah's ubi key around his neck or whatever and boom digital ocean spins up
Do makes it so easy to do that they do and if you use our code do unplugged again
You're gonna get ten dollars
Which will give you the you can get a five dollar rig for free for the first two months
Or you can get two rigs or you could get a ten dollar rig if you wanted to try something
You know with a little bit more oof to it. We actually spun up
We were testing uh saccom one and saccom two
uh, we actually
We spun up like super super powerful ones just to kind of get the hang of it
Just to kind of see what it would be like to to work on a super powerful linux rig
I think we did it more out of novelty than any real production requirement
so linux, uh, uh
Digital ocean.com and use the promo code do
Unplugged is crystal with us or did he he drop out?
He's still there. Yeah, you gotta did is your uh, is your connection any better, sir?
It's not his connection more like he's trying to set up push to talk and he's currently on voice activation
Got it. Okay. All right. Well, we'll let him sort that out. I uh, yeah
Kind of nice to have him here because uh, you guys are super quiet today
Uh, so west tell me about the the end of the general purpose operating system
Uh, yeah, so this was just an article
I saw that I thought was kind of interesting uh over at the blog more than seven dot net
Uh, and it was just talking about kind of and it's probably is focusing maybe on the opposite end
Spectrum of the iot. I threw that article in there just to kind of get this this topic started. Um, but what we're seeing at the
I don't know when I when I started doing things on the internet, you know
Kind of in the early days of linux not super early, but the early days of like web scale linux
You know you were getting your vps or maybe a shared host and you were configuring things on the you had an ftp account
Or you had a you know, you had a whole open vz server that you were then configuring you had a whole
That you were then configuring you installed apache with mod php and you got your mysql going
Oh boy, now you got your web app running. Uh, but these days there's a lot of things
That's that's not necessarily the level of abstraction that people are going for these days
We're seeing a lot more, you know, you have infrastructure. It's a service
You have all kinds of different intermediate service platform service layers
Uh, you have things like aws lambda where you know, you're not concerned at all or you know
The the whole no ops thing where you're not concerned about what operating system is. Is it rel?
Is it ubuntu it all runs on linux sure, but but for you, you know, you you write your java application
It gets executed in your container or wherever and then it runs. I want the candy
I don't care how I get the candy, right?
And I understand that I mean I even may support that that worldview when you're trying to build large scale distributed systems
I just wonder what it is that a success for linux. What does that mean?
Also, like what does that mean in terms of new developers who you know, maybe they start from the code side
But they want to start deploying things
I think in the past some of those people would then be pulled into the linux ecosystem
Where you're suddenly running linux at home and you're converting your media center and you know
You get in the linux culture and if you're just using these cloud scale platforms where yes linux is there
But that's not really never, you know, you make a docker container where you you know
You might your import python and then you build your python thing. Never is it even say the word ubuntu?
Or linux on it. What does that mean for the linux ecosystem and new developers new people in that ecosystem who are coming to this?
Well, let's tie that back to our original discussion about free nas and bst, right?
right, I think if you start to look at things in it from the from the from the perspective of I just want to
Put yeah, I want to push the button take the banana
If you know if we look at things in that sense
I like free nas because I can drop an enterprise ready solution if linux becomes
So effective at doing its job that I don't have to know it exists for me to get the banana
I'm okay with that. That actually doesn't bother me and if amazon can make a buck by customizing that operating system
And delivering delivering an end of banana to a to a user without them having to understand
How how the banana got there to begin with I guess i'm okay with that too. And so then to to to go on from there
How do you feel about the uh, how do you want to call it patriotism or you know to the to the kernel level?
Do you care mostly about?
You know the experience is it posix like is it or is it a license issue?
Like could you could amazon then replace their ec2 service with free bsd hosts or even a luminous host?
And would that change things for you? Would you is there a community loss there? Does it matter?
Well, I think first of all, I don't I i'm usually not aware if they're going to change something like that out
Right, I wouldn't know is again. I'm it's it's a black box. I don't know how it's working
I like I don't see that happening for a couple of reasons. First of all
I think that a lot of these systems have gotten built up
On the backbone of linux and they have ridden that train up and you get a lot of people that are very very comfortable
Uh administrating in in what they already know and i'll give you a great example of that
It's been 15 years since I first sat down and was required
To use a given server a server operating system, right when I first started out
They said you will use rel because that's what we use here and that's you know, whatever
And you know, I was formally trained on rel and whatnot and and I got and I and I got my start in rel
Partly because I sought out jobs in that in you know in that area
but
I ever since then I have formal training on rel I have worked with rel i've worked with redhat the company extensively
So when I go to set up a server, it is second nature to me
I just naturally want to use rel and you see in the military a lot of the guys that that go in and
They become very proficient with with a given firearm
They own a very similar firearm when they get home because it's what they like to shoot because they're very comfortable with it
And I I think that we have gotten as an industry
so entrenched in the linux ecosystem in the linux system
I think it's going to be very difficult if not impossible to ever back our way back out
And and and and so if you're going to go to something like bsd
Bsd would not just have to equal linux in in a competitive advantage
It would have to far exceed it because you would have to have something so compelling
That it's worth people to fundamentally relearn the system that they know. What do you guys think in the mumbo room?
In general, I don't think the general use os is going to go away for a long time because I mean
These cloud solutions are great and all but even the average user is going to have to be on the technological level
And understanding to be able to use these and have them work
And people who really want a general use os to do whatever they want with as a playground
I think most of us in here and most people who work in it and devs who like to tinker will probably always use one
rotten corpse, what do you think?
Going once we'll always use um
I'll always use a, you know, general operating system. I mean, yeah, totally. I'll add stuff like um
A cody box or something. Sure, you know, there's definitely there's definitely places where it makes sense, but it's not a fundamentally going to change
How I use majority of what I do like I guess and I think that applies to most people because they're they're even if you have
Uh, like even if people switch like earlier we were talking about how maybe the mass majority of people will switch to something like a phone or a tablet as their main system
That's a general operating system. Sure. So I don't really think that this really has much
You know ground to stand on sure
so I guess I just wonder from the new user perspective and
And and maybe maybe it's like the the difference like you were talking about like learning rel
And like even learning rel like even though it's an enterprise distribution. It's kind of locked away in its own little tower
You know, you're on the command line. You're using these gnu tools. It's it feels more part of the community versus like
These days maybe you could have come up and like what you got you got certified in aws, right?
You know how to administer the acls for network access as you know
All about ec2 sure and that doesn't I guess that doesn't feel the same in terms of
You're maybe even accomplishing the same things, but it doesn't have the same heart to me
You know, it doesn't and you know
The thing is it's we're in a drastically different landscape today than we were 15 years ago
You know these days when I started out
I spent I and I spent it out of my own money too. Uh, no, no actually I didn't that's not true
That's not true. I I got a company to pay for but I I I contacted a company and had them pay
I think it was like three grand
To send me to official training to get trained on on rel because I was doing this stuff for them
And I said, you know, I just I really need some some actual training and it wasn't so much that I needed
To learn how to do things. I think I knew how to do the tasks
I needed to do really what it gave me was the confidence to know I was doing things correctly
These days you don't have to spend twenty five hundred three thousand dollars to get that sort of training
You know, you don't you you can go to linuxacademy.com
Unplugged and we will give you a great deal
Uh to be able to use linux academy and the thing about linux academy is they take everything in bite-sized pieces
So they work with your schedule
They take everything that you'd need to know and and you can do it on anything
You can do it on rel you can do it on abuntu. You can do it on aws
You pick the area of expertise that you need to know and then you go through those snippets now for me personally
I went through when I when rel7 came out. I didn't need to go through
You know the basics of the red hat operating system
I'd been using it for 10 years, but I needed to know it was different between six and seven
Wow, linux academy had a course for me. They had a course from transitioning from six to seven and I was able to in just
A week or so get myself up to what I would have had to spend
Five days plus hotel plus food plus taking time off work. A lot of people don't
Constantly, you know if you're self-employed
The cost to come here to do a show the cost to fly out here the cost to stay here that
That's not where the money is
The money is in the fact that i'm not working when i'm back in grand forks
How much money could you have made exactly the cost in going to a training session is not the 2500 three thousand dollars
Really? That's peanuts
It's not the couple thousand dollars i'm going to spend on a hotel for a week or the food i'm going to spend
It's the time away from it's the time away from my business and and I see that dropping well with linux academy
I'm able to keep doing my work keep serving my clients and at the same time
Stay up to uh, stay up to date on the leading edge of technology
You can get a professional grade education right there in your office
You can and these people are dedicated linux professionals. They're not just people that show up, you know
You know just just to collect a paycheck. These people are dedicated linux professionals that that you know
Really have a passion for teaching linux. So head over to linux academy dot com slash unplugged and a huge. Thank you
To linux academy for sponsoring the linux unplug program
So one of my passions in fact it one of the focus of uh, the show that we are working on uh, the call-in show
Called ask noah that we're working on is uh going to be small business. Small business is near and dear to my heart
And one of the things that fits in tandem with small business is of course
Linux because in small business, it's all about that roi
How can I get the most return on my investment for the least amount of money invested? So this article comes to us from zdnet
Many small businesses with tight budgets are facing a tough choice stick with an obsolete operating system and remain vulnerable to hackers or spend a lot
to install new gear
David gerwitz shows how linux can help preserve your investment while still staying safe and secure
Earlier this week my phone rang. I looked at the caller id and it was from a neighbor in the community since I was writing
I ignored it. Next week. I'm going to show you how to do it
I ignored it next came a text from the same guy. Please call me. Like I said, I was working so I ignored it
God, we've all been there, right?
Then came a succession of text alerts on my phone. I turned my phone off and finished my article
When I finally looked at my phone there were a scroll of alerts all from fred
I don't know fred all that well, but we often bump into each other around town and events
He normally seems like a cheerful calm sort but not today
I listened to his voicemail message where he sounded like he'd been crying
We're done. Dave. Don't know what to do expletive computers
It was a busy week and it sounded like it'd been generally desperate. I I reluctantly decided to get involved
I called him back and said hey fred what's going on? You sound upset dave. Can you come over?
I think I might be done for if there's if there's a chance fixing computers is not her. Sorry. This is back to him
Fixing computers is not my favorite thing, but i'd been inside all day and so it would be nice to get out
So I headed over to his office
What I walked into seemed like a war zone more than an office a cluster of workers
Were staring at a clunky old lcd monitor that looked like they'd seen a ghost. Here's what I discovered fred's service business
Has 20 pcs all more than a decade old and still running you got it windows xp. Where's abel?
This time it was ransomware this time. He wasn't going to recover quickly or cheaply
Fred was running windows xp for a few reasons his hardware was running solidly and he didn't want to pay for a windows upgrade
Remember that free windows upgrade to windows 10 didn't include xp, but he couldn't afford to buy new machines
Now here's the thing
I see this
This is this is not a this is not a an isolated incident
I see this on a daily basis this right here
And if you're wondering why I dove so far deep into this article
It's because I first of all, I think the writer just did a fantastic job
really drawing you into his narrative, but the second thing is
this story is
Probably 95 of our customers really rings true. They have reached the end of their rope. They don't have a
Necessarily large budget they have a budget
Yeah, you know, we're not america worker, right?
But they have a budget just not a large budget and they don't want to spend, uh, you know
60 000. Well actually more than that. We we just did a bid for a business that is getting all new machines
Uh whole nine yards and that's I think it was 85 grand and of course that includes all the network
Infrastructure and installation stuff like that and they're doing you know, so we're pulling new wire and stuff for them
Yeah, but uh, but and that doesn't even include I mean i'm sure it would be more expensive
We are buying those computers with windows right because these are no operating system. We're gonna put linux on them
This kind of client exists out there. So if you are a that there are two
People that this story should speak volumes to the first story is if you want a small business and you're running computers with windows
Xp you need to stop today
You need to go download up on to mate and you need to make it work for you
The first thing you're going to say is well noah
There are some applications that I just have to run on windows xp or that i'm just very used to this
Not saying it's going to be a perfect experience. You might have some hiccups along the way
But I promise you a hundred percent
You are going to have hiccups if you continue down this path of using a 15 year old operating system and expecting it to continue
To work for you
Microsoft isn't doing any favors in that regard, right?
The second group of people that should really take light note of this story
Is if you have it in you to start a local it service
This is your client right here. You go find this person and you say for you know, $50 an hour $75 an hour
You know $50 an hour $75 an hour $90 an hour whatever you think you can get
I will come in here and I will clean all these machines up
I will reinstall them with the latest version of an operating system for you and i'll work with you until we get your business operating
With acceptable solutions if you are willing to do that and you're willing to stick with it, you know
And I sat just last week
sat in a boardroom across from a uh, you know a very demanding client
And he looked right at me and when I told him we're gonna wipe these machines gonna wipe windows off
I'm gonna put linux. We're gonna do this. We're gonna do that. You know, it was not I was not met with uh,
You know, oh that sounds great, right? He wasn't very happy about it
Um, but you just you stick on your guns and you say this is why we're doing it
And I have a I have a proven track record in the last 10 years of doing this and we have successfully served clients
We can successfully serve you but you need to trust us on this
You need to let us go forward. You need to let us do this and this is why and here are the competitive advantages
You will make so much money off of doing stuff like this. It's not even funny
I'm a room. What do you guys think about this?
I definitely think that's a good service to have and people should be jumping up on that because they really do need to move
away from xp
It seems to be like a a good value add that the community, you know
Like where maybe open source plays well where a commercial solution wants to wrap it all up
They want to sell you the support but where open source solutions open up is a good business opportunity for people who like open
Source who contribute who support it who can then go out in the agency and one evangelize and then two
Maybe provide support sell support that can then you know foster the community
What do you guys think it'd be it'd be a great option for
If there was like a community project that would do a service but provide like you still had to pay for it
but you're paying for support and
The people who are committing to the project are getting paid from that in certain ways. So it's more like
You're you're contributing to help the community help people come to the community
And that would be awesome. Um
but there was actually there's people who are still using xp and
continue to use xp regardless of having
Dealing with stuff all day. Like there is one. This is just an anecdotal story
But there was someone I was talking to a company that was potentially becoming was going to become a client for mine
But they decided that um, they didn't they didn't realize they didn't think that they were a big risk
So they're going to keep using xp
um
And I refuse to let them keep using xp as everywhere because they wanted to do it where every
Every system was xp and their server was xp and everything absolutely. Everything's xp
I wanted to get like give them uh, linux everywhere
But an xp vm for the people who are going to use it so I could keep them off the internet and
Since the xp is not online. It's not a big deal
Uh, but they refuse to do that
So I have uh one person who works there who sends me messages at least three times a week or so
Uh complaining about something going wrong where their their computer completely crashes or
You know the server getting infected even though supposedly that's impossible as they say
but
if we could actually provide them a
community or a service or something that would give them, you know a semblance of
support and they
Weren't they're not going into like oh, we're switching completely and it's up to us to figure it out
Right. How many business owners would spend hours on google trying to figure that out when they really just need to get it done?
And if they have a resource that they can maybe support financially or you know
Whatever you need to do to make that work where it feels like, you know, they're doing it as part of community
Maybe it helps put uh, you know businesses together against the virus
Uh, you know businesses together who have done that so that they have people to talk to talk about how the transitions went
Problems with training all that stuff
That's a good idea
More as a part of a
Good good. No good
I was a part of a local it business, uh that that totally missed this vote
Um, I had been railing on them to begin supporting
linux in any form
Um from day one that I arrived there and I spoke to several clients about you know, oper oper
Switching their operations over to linux and and finding solutions that worked and this was five six years ago
um
and now the local it business is dead and those clients are
Looking around I guess they they have nothing to fall back on
Uh, because this was this was a business that developed when doing hardware repairs was easy money
And you could actually make you know a fair living at just repairing the boxes
And I could not get this business to look bigger to look smarter
at what was going to happen in the next five years with the hardware becoming essentially unrepairable because
Joe consumer was buying tablet related machines more so than laptop or desktop related machines
And they weren't looking at the commercial market. So there's my sob story of of an it business that totally missed the boat
uh, yeah, just give me a second here. I got the link for you
It is a company called three
Sorry, there's a company that is inside of toronto where i'm located called free geek toronto
What they do is they take old machines and they convert them over
Get them back up and running and they always throw linux on it. Sometimes they give them out for free
Sometimes you can buy them. Here's the link here
Now the reason why i'm bringing them up is because there's a lot of people that are
out there right now that are in the hey, we're just going to remake this machine business now if more of them actually provided
Setups with linux on it, which would mean that they wouldn't be paying as much towards the um, the operating system
They could always you know, donate that to the people that are making the operating system
You know more people would be actually willing to try it out because a lot of people
Who are you know making the decisions about the computers at the work place?
You know making the decisions about the computers at the workplace. They're going to have windows at home
Or they're gonna have mac at home
So if they start off with linux at home say linux and windows like what I have all of a sudden
You're no longer as afraid to sit there and try out linux at the workplace because you already know
Hey, this is what it can do. This is what I can't do so on and so forth
And i've actually converted businesses doing exactly that rotten corpse
I like the idea of providing machines to people so that they have the transition
From work to home
And I also like the idea of giving them
Uh, you know a service that provides them with the free equipment to make it easier for that transition
But I don't like the idea of these free equipment. There's been there's multiple plate companies that do this
I know of one
One that mosenrath mentioned in toronto. I know of one in the uk
And they all do the same thing
They take these really terrible hardware that well linux can run on this old hardware. Yes, it can
But that doesn't mean it's going to be a good experience
Right, it's probably going to be an awful experience because it's awful hardware linux deserves good hardware
You'll get even more value. Exactly that like when when they use something that's good
That's fantastic when they use them. They're giving something that's terrible
They're just going to blame linux and not the hardware because they have no idea
Exactly. Well, thank you so much for the mumble room for joining us today. We really appreciate it as always
Special thanks to michael tonel our producer and show screener mit free the man who keeps our mumble room up and running
Rekai our chief editor and all-around in-house genius and the entire team here at jupiter broadcasting
Linux unplugged airs live on tuesdays 2 p.m. Pacific time
You can keep an eye on the schedule of this show and every other show at jupiter broadcasting.com
We look forward to seeing you right back here next week
So
So, uh
There's an article here from mod zero on modzero.github.io
Github.io
And it is with the release of microsoft windows 10 operating system several innovations have been introduced into the market regarding privacy settings
What is normal?
What is a normality with apple since long apparently has been accepted by osx user now has finally become a reality for microsoft users
The analysis of the user data and behavior of the us american creator of software
Over time more users published instructions on how to break microsoft's habits of spying on the users including
Private users whose computers are not part of a company or enterprise domain
I was annoyed that this
That this leads to manually clicking check marks on a graphical user interface
Or running confusing powershell scripts that merge with several several single rule sets
So I don't know if you guys have seen this article or not
Um, but it it basically
Uh it my understanding is that there is a it is a it is basically a how-to guide
On how to fix windows 10 to be more privacy respecting. Is that right?
Well, even better than that. It's uh, like uh something you can install that will do it for you
Took a bunch of other guides tips on how to do it best practices that have emerged and then made a tool that will just
Apply that for you, you know
So if you don't really want to get into powershell scripts or find the registry or who knows what?
Uh, here's something that will purportedly do it for you. I haven't tested this myself. I don't have
Windows 10 at home, but I know a lot of people do, you know
Maybe you have it for gaming or something else or your spouse is using it and this might be something just to
Help make it more like you're used to. Oh, that's awesome