Starting the show off with an amazing discovery, ArchiveOS,
the Archive of Operating Systems.
Its mission is to save great free operating systems,
Linux, of course, the BSDs, the free DOSs, Solaris,
and many other independent operating systems,
and make it bootable.
Look at this thing, Wes.
How beautiful is this?
It's like the Internet Archive in an ISO.
A testament to the ages.
So you can go check it out at ArchiveOS.org.
And I'm going to look into this more.
I got to try this.
They say it's important to save systems
and let the next generation of users find them, try them,
and learn as much as possible.
This has been rattling around in my head.
I haven't tried this, obviously.
But what's been rattling around in my head
is trying to set up some old VMs,
or I should say set up new VMs of old versions of Linux,
just to like, what was it like to use KDE 2?
What was it like to use GNOME 2?
Like, what was it really like?
Because we refer to it all the time.
I've been really tempted to set up some VMs to do this,
just to have them sitting around when I want to try it.
Oh, yeah, right.
And I think that's where this site is maybe useful.
A lot of times, maybe you have a disk image or a tarball,
but it's a long way from actually making things bootable.
So if you have some of this set up already to go,
you might actually use it.
That would be the perfect part, like one ISO you download,
you load it on your machine, and it boots the whole thing up.
That would be the holy grail.
Maybe they'll get there one day.
Maybe they'll get there.
But right now, they're just archiving
these old, great operating systems.
If you do want to try this, it's a great resource for that,
so you can build your own system.
One day, we may get to that ISO.
Somebody should build it and call it
the Linux Unplugged Booter.
No, don't do that.
Call it something else.
Yeah, definitely something else.
As I look at the pile of ThinkPads stacked up
in the corner of the room.
You are building an archive.
Different operating systems.
How many do you have there?
How many ThinkPads is it?
Do you want to reveal the number?
Well, from what I can see in front of me,
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
Seven, I think, as I can see.
You could just have various different states of Linux
on each one of them, like a cross-section.
Yeah.
I kind of like them to be usable,
like actual usable machines, not just something
that you put in a cupboard and never think about again.
So there's actually two on my desk right now.
One of them is a machine that we use for audio production.
I don't actually use it.
Samantha uses it for audio production on the podcast.
But the other one that is on right now,
I'm running offline IMAP to synchronize all my email down
from Gmail, because I quite like having
an offline copy of all my email.
Just in case anything goes wrong,
I can open this laptop up, and it's
got a local copy of all my email.
And I've got MUT installed on there, so add a pinch.
It's got no GUI.
I've got no graphical interface on this thing at all.
It's only command line applications.
And offline IMAP sync my mail, and then MUT
if I need to actually write an email.
So now I can visualize you during the zombie apocalypse,
hunched over this old laptop, reading your email on MUT.
It's beautiful.
And I have a lot of email to read.
So once the zombies come, I'll be
quite busy reading all my old archives.
Right, of course.
But on that old laptop, only seven minutes to read it all.
Yeah, right.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 249 from May 15, 2018.
Oh, welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that undoubtedly should have gone to that English class
more often.
And my name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
I'm just saying, it might have helped out
in this whole podcasting crew.
It probably would.
Went into IET, ended up podcasting.
You know, Wes, we'll muddle through.
We have a great show.
We're going to talk about Gnome removing the ability
to launch binary apps.
That's been the hot topic in our community this week.
Hot, hot, hot.
Yeah.
We'll do a deep dive into the new bookmark sync
stuff that's coming to Firefox, talk about System 76 and LVFS
back and forth, and some new features
that look like they could be coming to Gnome if Will Cook
gets his way.
Wimpy's here with a new trick.
And malware may have been found in the Snap Store.
Is everything ruined?
We'll get all worked up and super upset.
Plus, the folks from Plasma, well, some of them at least,
went to Berlin and came back with some code.
We'll talk about data collection in 1804
and some of the attempts to generate
controversy for ad clicks.
And purism gets busted by Intel.
We alluded to this on a recent Linux action news,
but now we have a lot more details.
And then we'll ask if Docker is dangerous
and if it's time to just drop that all GTK or all cute
mentality.
Is it still relevant today, Wes?
We'll find out.
Don't answer.
We're going to get into that.
But before we go any further, we've
got to bring in that mumble room.
Time appropriate greetings, mumble room.
Hey-oh, hey-oh.
Hello, good evening.
I like that.
That was a good mix this week.
Didn't expect that one coming.
So I want to start with the elephant in the room,
and that is the story about Gnome removing the ability
to launch binary apps from Nautilus.
So we got the big news from last Gnome release
really was the removal of the desktop application icons,
the desktop icons from Nautilus.
And now it looks like this is sort of a continuation
of that cleanup is really launching
binary applications when you double click on them in Nautilus.
So like.bin and.run files, perhaps app images as well,
.desktop shortcuts, or a shell script that you might execute.
You know, like the dumb arse that I am apparently
doing things the old way.
I just downloaded a new game off of a good old games, GOG,
and was assuming I would just be able to double click
and run it.
I don't know what I was thinking.
I should have definitely considered opening the terminal
and running it that way.
Of course you should.
You should be running all your programs that way, Chris.
Now, it's pretty easy to poke fun at this decision.
And it, of course, plays into that whole narrative of Gnome
always removing functionality.
I think the common reaction I've seen on the various internet
outlets is just when you thought Gnome couldn't
take any more functionality, they're
taking away the ability to run apps.
But that's a little hype.
It's not really that.
It's more really about how apps should
be launched from the app launcher,
and the files app should be managing files.
And they think removing the ability
to launch binaries from Nautilus will improve its security.
And, of course, there will still be other ways to launch apps.
So what do you think?
Initial impressions, when you hear this kind of thing, Wes,
are you so tired from drama that you're just sort of numb to it?
Or do you have a strong response to this?
OK, I will admit to being at least a little bit numb.
I also have some sympathies.
I feel like Gnome gets viewed as so many different things
and a lot of different roles.
Some of that might be valid, especially now
on so many desktops by default. But that's really
the distribution's choice.
I can see why Gnome wants to craft things
into a more elegant desktop for the future.
Maybe not all users are ready for that.
I can see why people want to keep a lot of standard paradigms
around.
I personally don't need them.
I'm OK with Gnome developing into whatever
it is that they want.
I understand why it upsets people, though, because, hey,
this is a lot of people's workflows.
You can't do it anymore.
You're not allergic to bees, are you?
Because there is a wasp.
Oh, look at that.
Wow.
Here, maybe you could put this on top of him.
There you go, Wes.
Maybe you could trap that wasp that's walking around
by your hand there, Wes.
Just a little Pacific Northwest summer.
There you go.
That surely won't piss him off.
Now he's trapped in the bell.
Now let's ring it.
All right, well, I agree.
I think that people often lump Gnome into one singular
category when it's a bunch of individual developers and people
that are doing a lot of different work,
and it often encompasses many projects.
And all of those disclosures aside,
I can't imagine something like this ever landing in, like,
Kaja, for example.
What do you think, Wimpy?
Would you see it?
Could you see a rationale for something
like this landing in a Maté desktop environment?
Well, probably not, because we choose not to remove features,
if at all possible.
So the only time features go away
is when they can't technically be supported anymore.
But then I was thinking about this.
How often do people actually launch binaries
with the file manager?
I think it's more common to a group of people
that this is going to most negatively impact,
and that's new users that get switched to Linux,
or people that are buying commercial software.
I've definitely noticed the folks
that I've helped move to Linux, they
have this habit of Google searching,
and then going and downloading the deb,
or downloading a binary file, or like when
you buy something from GOG.
Right, I can see that.
Or I use this program, oh, they have Linux,
I'm finally on Linux, they gave me a tarball,
what do I do with this?
Yeah.
So a deb isn't executable though, right?
You double click a deb, and it launches something else
that handles the installation, or you double click an image.
I'm just commenting on the behavior.
That's just the behavior.
I think the instinct for Windows users
is to download things off of the vendor's website,
whoever that vendor might be.
Right, but even those crazy lunatic third-party app
developers create desktop files, and launchers,
and if you download, let's say for example,
a simple example like Telegram.
If you go and get Telegram from their website,
there's a simple executable, you run it once,
and then you've got an icon forevermore
in your launcher, your menu.
Right, same with the GOG game.
I bought that new fancy looking space game,
I can't remember what it's called.
Space game.
But it looks really good.
And it's a bin file that downloads,
and then when you double click it, it then launches a GTK
installer, and that does create a.desktop file,
and all that kind of stuff.
But you've got to double click that bin file
to get that GTK installer to create the desktop file.
But is the ultimate goal of this in the GNOME project
to break the habit of these bad patterns of downloading
something from the internet, and then just double clicking it,
and expecting it to work, and it not be full of malware?
Maybe, yeah.
I mean, I think you could make a pretty solid security
argument from that standpoint, and you could argue
if they feel the code isn't up to snuff
that they shouldn't be maintaining it.
You could just base the argument off of that.
It does kind of remind me, too, of some of the,
you know, maybe like a Chrome OS type environment,
or iOS, where these newer environments that were designed
in the world we have now don't have some of these legacy
things, but people who are familiar enough
with the file system, familiar enough with, yeah,
just like running binaries, feels like a big loss.
I don't really ever do this.
I guess the one area, it kind of sucks for app images, maybe.
Yeah, yeah.
Other than that, it doesn't really affect me.
I guess I just don't agree that you can change user behavior
this way.
I don't think this ever works.
I think you just piss off users.
And I think what you're going to have is.
Or filter your base then, right?
And you're going to have distros that are just going
to ship another extension, just like they're shipping
extensions now to restore desktop icons,
or they're shipping extensions now to restore tray icons.
Now they're going to be shipping an extension
to execute binary files.
That's likely the biggest impact,
is that it'll just be now the work of the distribution
maintainers.
Or they'll hold back the version of Nautilus
that has this patched out and patch it back in again.
Yeah, yeah, maybe.
I have a link to the mailing list discussion.
Let's say give it a read.
And give the team some slack to just figure this stuff out.
Like, the world hasn't fallen apart
with the removal of desktop icons from GNOME 3.2.8.
True.
We're still here.
We're still holding good.
And people that really need it have extensions.
I think also there's like, yeah, people have extensions.
And if you're listening to this program,
you probably know that there's a bunch of other fine desktop.
So if we're having this debate in the context of like,
what should the new user experience be, or the standard,
that's one thing.
But for a lot of us, we just don't have to care,
because there's lots of choice.
Poby, are you still rocking Firefox as your daily driver
if you cave to Chrome?
Yep.
All right.
Yep, yep.
No, the only reason I use Chrome is
to talk to Wimpy on a daily basis,
because the video chat thing we use only works in Chrome.
Yeah, I have similar.
I've made an Electron app of the video conferencing tool
we make, so I don't have to have Chrome or Chromium installed
anymore.
How do you make an Electron app of any Rando website?
I would love to know that.
I will send you a link in IRC to the Ubuntu tutorial guide
that explains how to do it.
Thank you, because I have a similar situation.
I have one app that I have to use Chrome for.
Yeah, that's a great app.
We should do that.
I know.
You know exactly what I'm talking about.
So Firefox is just getting better and better.
And Beta 61 and the Nightly 62 have a new sync system
that is going to address some of all of the complaints,
actually, I've really ever had with Firefox Bookmarks.
This is something, their sync system with Firefox Bookmarks
has always sort of been a retrofitted solution,
where Chrome was sort of engineered from the beginning.
And now, Firefox, the team over at Mozilla
that creates Firefox for iOS, has quite a bit
of experience with this, because when they created Firefox for OS,
they created it with syncing in mind.
And they created this whole JSON system,
and they created this dual database system
of your active bookmarks and the synced bookmarks,
and even a third database for conflict resolution.
And then they had a really great system
for keeping it all straight and keeping track of everything.
And when they engineered this, they
looked back at their Firefox desktop sync engine
and said, well, how could we apply lessons learned to the iOS
sync engine to the desktop?
And that's now essentially what they're doing.
They're going to have a mirror and a merger database.
They're going to have more of an iOS inspired.
It's not a direct three database,
like one for one re-implementation
of the iOS system, because there is just historical legacy
things they have to support.
But in a sense, they're going to be building into Firefox
a shadow bookmarking system that will be kept syncing separately
from your primary bookmarks.
And that's where it will work out,
like merging of conflicts or other issues
that crop up when you're syncing bookmarks
or adding new items or editing existing items.
And that'll be happening much faster in the background.
And it has a graceful way to get out
when there's a conflict that it can't figure out.
So then this is just sort of a new system being
added, bolted on, that will take the same data
and do better things with it.
Yeah, exactly.
And they're starting to roll it out in 61 and 62
in different phases.
I have those details linked in the show notes
if you want to read the whole post.
If you're a big Firefox fan and you're
curious about this battle and why it's sort of been
a little clunky, they even identify some of the issues
that I thought I was just crazy.
I thought these were just problems that I had.
And now I'm seeing Mozilla just say,
the list is pretty damning there, right?
Like, yeah, it doesn't make you confident.
No, bookmarks will be duplicated, lost, or reordered.
I have absolutely experienced the reordered thing.
And folders with different contents
would get smushed together.
New bookmarks wouldn't make their way to all devices,
causing them to gradually fall out of sync.
And moves would be partially or completely undone at times.
There you go.
Yeah, right?
Wow.
And I thought I was just using it wrong.
And I thought Chrome did it a lot better.
And that was one of the things that first drew me to Chrome.
I went back.
I feel like it's been pretty solid.
But I've also kind of reduced how much I use bookmarks.
Same, yeah.
And I'm looking forward to these changes.
Definitely you should check the article out.
I thought it was a great level of there's
a lot of technical details without too much.
There's not a ton of code, but they
talk about the advanced designs of the system.
And it's also worth mentioning, recently I've
gotten a little more critical about the way Mozilla
communicates.
It's very corporate heavy.
And it's sort of a turnoff to, I think,
a lot of members of the open source and free software
communities.
And so reading that, I'd say it was very clear.
It was technical.
Felt like it was written to us.
I liked that a lot.
I liked that.
And if you want to go read that whole thing,
go to linuxunplug.com slash 249, and we'll
have a link in there.
I've talked a lot on this show about LVFS
and the whole firmware update mechanism
that I first experienced on an XPS 13 running Fedora,
and then later different distributions, including Arch.
And it was just so exciting.
Yeah, you're in the software updates.
And you go to the updates, and it's like, what?
There's a new firmware update?
Crazy.
And then we really saw the value
of having that system when Spectre and Meltdown were
announced.
And this system, LVFS, it's a Red Hat project
that is attempting to be distro and vendor neutral.
We've covered a lot in the past.
Richard Hughes is the primary developer behind it.
I think he's done some great work.
And I love the idea of something that's cross-vendor,
so Lenovo or Dell could participate in it.
And you can be on Arch, Fedora, or Ubuntu,
and you're getting these firmware updates.
Doesn't matter, yeah, right?
Yeah, that's great.
So I've always been a fan of, well,
let's get LVFS in all of the places.
And so that's why I think other people have felt that way too.
And there was some interest in what was
System76 going to be doing.
Now that they have Pop!
OS and that they'll be building their own hardware soon,
what is their intention to participate in the LVFS
program?
And then it came out that in the background,
there had been some communication between System76
and the project.
It's not like they weren't aware of it, right?
Right.
But nothing of major substance that
had really progressed anything beyond like, hey,
can we do this?
How does this work?
Things like that.
And it seems like things just sort of faded out.
There was some rumors that, yeah, they started talking
to us from the LVFS camp, but we haven't heard anything.
And then about a year went by, and Richard Hughes
posted a blog post where the crux of it
is this isn't going anywhere.
They're not going to use our project.
They're going to do their own update mechanism
that they've created.
And if you want somebody who supports LVFS,
go get an XPS 13.
And Carl took to the System76 blog
and wrote a kind of line-by-line response where he says,
we reached out to Richard over a year ago.
We were enthusiastic about LVFS and interested in whether
or not it would work for us.
Once we described how we needed to deliver our firmware,
we were told that it would not work well
and would likely not be acceptable to Red Hat Legal.
And they kind of post a snippet of the issue.
Richard Hughes says, I don't think
this will work for us because there's
no way to reference a flashing tool in the XML
or sign an executable on LVFS.
I don't think Red Hat Legal will like the idea of shipping
the flashing program.
We've only ever talked about the firmware files themselves,
although I can see the images in the.cap file
probably contain firmware executable code wrapped up
in layers.
Yeah, fair enough.
He says, I also know the Red Hat security team would
do more than just blink when we tell them
that we want to ship an untrusted, non-free binary,
which would run as root on RHEL customer's machines.
So that's the snippet of the conversation
that way Richard Hughes says, I don't think
this is going to work for you.
It's kind of, I believe, at that point in the conversation,
things just died off.
System76 is like, well, obviously, this
isn't going to work for us.
We'll focus on what we need to focus on.
They were also launching Pop OS around this time,
and they have plenty of things that they're doing.
And so he also, Carl mentions in his blog post
that the update capital mechanism that LVFS uses
wouldn't work for over a decade of machines
that System76 has in the field.
And without update capsule, and with update capsule as well,
it wraps everything into binary blobs.
You can't really pull it apart and reverse engineer firmwares,
and they don't like that aspect of it as well.
Carl outlines a few other concerns in his blog post,
but I kind of wanted to reach out to Carl
and ask him a couple of direct questions,
because there's been some that I think
have been rattling around the internet that we'd
like answers to.
So I sent Carl an email, and he got back to me this morning,
pretty promptly, actually.
And I asked him, I said, is one of the core problems
with System76 using LVFS is that it's not really compatible
with its upstream OEM agreements that System76 has in place,
with say, Clevo or whoever that might be upselling the parts.
Carl responds to that, System76 has no upstream agreements
limiting anything we can do to deliver firmware
to our customers.
This is made up.
We were told in the email we posted
that LVFS would technically be incompatible
and would likely not be acceptable to Red Hat legal.
We needed to still provide the functionality,
so we built our own tool, which I, OK.
Fair enough.
So he says that there isn't an agreement.
There is no agreement in place that
limits how they redistribute firmware, is what he said.
And I said, just to clarify, if customers
choose to buy a stock Ubuntu machine from System76, not one
running Pop!
OS, will they still get updated?
He said, correct, any Ubuntu-based distro
will work, of course.
We also had customers use the update tool on Arch.
Nice, yeah, OK.
And I said, in the future, when you're
building your own systems, like your own desktops,
do you intend to use LVFS at that point?
And he said that their first in-house design
and manufactured desktop will feature
open source firmware components.
So they don't need to be reverse engineered,
so the update capsule thing isn't.
But they'll still use their existing infrastructure
and tools to distribute the firmwares
when they're building their own systems.
And so I think it's pretty clear in here.
This is just simply a matter of, this is what works for us.
It wasn't really a statement on the LVFS project.
It's just not a solution that's necessarily
going to work for us right now.
And he would have, I think, I got from my back and forth
with him, he would have preferred
to just leave it at that.
Yeah, I mean.
I wish there was a mechanism for these different groups
to communicate better.
It's funny, we have all these different platforms, Twitter,
and email, and IRC, and Slack, and Telegram,
that everybody in our community uses pretty regularly.
And yet, like, these like.
It feels like we end up talking past each other in blog posts.
In blog posts, right?
And I really respect Richard, too.
I think what Richard is working on
is really important for a first class Linux user experience,
where you don't have to sit there and do the distro math
and wonder if there's a PPA for that system.
And you just know that if you get a modern system,
when you go to get all your updates,
you get your firmware update.
I like that.
I like that, too.
And there's probably a lot of different ways
System76 could crack that particular egg.
And maybe they could deliver it that way as well.
It's sort of unfortunate, though,
that we end up getting these lobs thrown back and forth
at each other.
In another world, I almost would like to give people a.
Maybe this is something we could do.
I almost would like to give people a space
to just talk it out.
Because you get people talking, and it just is everything's
fine.
Let's hash it out now, and then not
have to keep talking about it.
And we can stop covering it on the show,
and everyone will be happier.
Yeah, it just seems like that would be a lot nicer.
Do you think there's any, was there any in the reaction,
any sort of open source community frustration
just with Pop!
OS, or feelings about that System76
may be motivated to do this for some of their not
appreciating forking when they don't need you?
That's an interesting question.
Yeah, I think that is a bit of it.
I think where Richard Hughes comes in is,
I saw some of his follow up comments on Google+.
He's a little disappointed, because the idea here
is this is sort of like the community thing to do.
This is the Linux, this is like a good Linux hardware citizen
thing to do, I think is the thinking.
And so there was a level of disappointment on his part
that System76 wasn't interested in participating
in that larger ecosystem, even if it meant sort of reinventing
the wheel a bit.
Because some other manufacturers are redoing the way
that they do all of this process too.
And I think that is a point you could argue.
Maybe that's not necessarily true.
Because perhaps you could argue that LVFS
is not as independent as it would need
to be for that to actually happen.
It also strikes me that it's great that System76 is taking
this seriously.
And maybe if a lot of other vendors had been doing this,
yes, it would be a worse world where we had a whole bunch
of independent Linux flashing programs.
But imagine that, if for years you'd
be able to easily flash firmware from whatever big name vendor,
that just wasn't the world that we lived in.
It's cool that it's changing now.
But I can understand why they're like,
guys, we've been shipping this for like 10 years.
We just have to support our machines.
Yeah, the machines we already have in the field.
Let's take a moment and thank Linux Academy,
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Go there and sign up for a free seven-day trial of a platform
that's built to teach you more about Linux,
with full-time human beings that can help you whenever you
get stuck.
And when you're not asking them questions,
they're always improving, adding, and updating content.
They have a course scheduler that
works with your busy schedule and helps set learning goals
and then helps you stick to those time frames.
They have cloud servers that they spin up on demand
when you need them as part of the courseware.
You can SSH into those systems, and they're really cool.
You can set the distro, and the courseware matches that.
And they also have practice exams and quizzes
to help prepare you for certifications and tests
to make sure you really have learned what you think you've
learned before you go take the big test.
Yeah.
They also have iOS and Android apps
so you can study while you're going.
They have lesson audio and study guides
that you can download and take with you.
And they have rolled out a big batch of content
in the last month, and it's still coming, too.
It's impressive.
There's so much to cover that they've
been doing live streams and just trying to bring everybody
up to date on all of this stuff, because it's so much,
it's hard to keep track of how much.
You don't even want to read all the stuff
that they have just offered, let alone all the actual material.
Yes, and they're updating old stuff as well,
so the old material is staying current.
It's a great, great service.
And you can try it seven days for free.
But when you go to linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged, go sign up for a free seven-day trial
and support the show, linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged.
Bubba-dubba, bubba-dubba, bubba-dubba, bubba-dubba.
I like that sound effect.
I like that, too.
You should keep it going.
So if I say GS Connect, does it ring a bell?
Does that ring a bell at all, GS Connect?
Well, it does make me think of KDE Connect.
You got it, Wes.
That's right.
It is the gnome shell implementation of KDE Connect.
Yeah, without the Qt.
I'm interested.
No Qt or KDE dependencies.
And KDE Connect, of course, is that awesome, awesome tool
that allows you to basically make your Android phone
a companion to your Plasma desktop
and now your gnome desktop with GS Connect.
You can share clipboards.
You can get notifications moved between them.
You can use it as a remote control.
I mean, you could transfer files.
There's a lot of stuff.
And you've got to figure, it's a feature
that Microsoft is eyeing.
They've talked a little bit at Build
about the new timeline feature in Windows 10
that requires a special launcher on Android
to make it all work, where none of this
is required with GS Connect.
And so this guy, this random guy, Will Cook,
some guy on the internet, he has proposed
that Ubuntu should integrate GS Connect as part of 18.10.
I think it's a great idea.
That's awesome.
And so he's put out there for conversation
on the Ubuntu community portal hub.
What do we call it, Popey?
Is it hub?
Hub.
And asked for folks to give input
and has even named people that are volunteering
to do some of the work.
I think this would be a great and useful tool.
And it'd be a nice feature on the side of the box
like they used to say.
That sounds awesome.
Yeah, I mean, I would certainly use it.
So if you want to get in on the conversation around that,
I'll have a link in the show notes.
And then a little birdie dropped off, a new snap.
New snap?
Right on the doorstep of the show this morning.
What is it?
I'm dying to know.
Well, you know how we're big fans of the FFmpeg project.
Oh, love it.
And you know what FFmpeg could always
use a little more of?
Hardware acceleration.
Always.
But you can't do that in a snap, right, Wimpy?
That's not possible.
It is now.
Oh, boy.
Dish.
You got a dish.
So this is something we've had brewing for a little while.
You will have heard Poppy and I talking about the fact
that OBS is able to use an accelerated FFmpeg that's
in the Ubuntu 18.04 archive, which is terrific.
So people who want NVENC and HEVC and what have you,
that's all available.
But as is common, the 18.04 release comes out.
We're shipping the latest stable release of FFmpeg
and then days later, FFmpeg 4 drops.
And we've now got an 18.04 release,
which is never going to see that new version of FFmpeg.
So what we've been working on is a snap of FFmpeg,
which is FFmpeg 4 with the NVENC and HEVC pieces enabled.
So you have the hardware acceleration.
We've also done the work to build in the VA API stuff.
So there's a hardware accelerated encoding and decoding
for Intel and AMD as well.
And all of the bits that FFmpeg relies on
are all built from the current versions of source parts.
So the whole stack of FFmpeg is all the latest stuff
inside the snap.
That snap is currently classic because it's FFmpeg itself.
And it sort of makes sense that maybe FFmpeg, the tool,
should remain a classic snap because there's
many different ways people would want to use it.
But that snaps only 20 meg.
So it's very small.
Wow.
Yeah.
I'm really excited to try it.
I could take that anyway.
Yeah.
And what we've been doing is we've figured out
how to confine FFmpeg and open up access to the NVENC socket.
And what this will enable us to do is, in snaps like OBS
and Kdenlive, embed the bleeding edge versions of FFmpeg
with all of the acceleration turned on inside those
applications.
So they don't have to go looking at the host, which
may have an old version.
They can have the current latest versions
with all of the acceleration features.
Right.
Boy, that's going to be great for them.
This is incredible.
And they'll know exactly that everywhere that it ships
will have that version of FFmpeg, which is going
to be great for Kdenlive.
Maybe that's one of the biggest challenges
for doing video editing on Linux is
that people have different parts underneath
of different versions.
And so you can say, my Kdenlive crashes.
And it comes back with, OK, what version of this
and what version of that do you have?
And this solves that.
That's available now in the stable channel.
In the future, we'll be doing a bit more
with the Intel and AMD acceleration.
And a little project I'm interested in looking at
is we've now got the capability within snaps
when they're being built to make architecture decisions
in the build process.
So you can say, when I'm on an AMD 64 machine,
do these things differently than when I'm on a ARM device.
And what I'm planning to do is bring some work
I did on the Raspberry Pi last year,
where I made an FFmpeg that was specifically
tuned for hardware accelerated encoding and decoding
on the Raspberry Pi, bring that into the same snap
so that when you're building on ARM HF,
it automatically turns on all of those Raspberry Pi
optimizations.
So the same snap will be the accelerated version
for the different devices.
You are doing the work of many editors out there.
They are going to appreciate that very, very much.
They're going to save so many folks time
that would have had to figure out
how to get that working individually
on each one of their systems.
Right.
Can you mention the different, like just a couple of years
ago, trying to put that all together.
Maybe you're manually compiling things or with sketchy PPAs,
and now it's just a couple of snaps.
Yep.
OK, so while we're on this subject of snaps,
there's a big story floating around, huge story,
massive controversy, shaking everything to its core.
So big.
There was malware found in the Snap Store.
And as a response, there has been a post up on the blog.abuntu.com
talking about future steps that will
be taken to secure, to a degree, the Snap Store.
And there was one bit in here that really jumped out at me.
And Will Cook talked a little bit
about this on the recent Late Night Linux, too.
They say, on the roadmap, they have an interesting security
feature in the works that will improve
the safety of the system and also
the experience of people handling
software deployments in servers and desktops.
A simple but fairly effective feature that we are working on
is the ability to flag specific publishers as verified.
OK.
The details of that will be announced soon.
But the basic idea is that it's easy for users
to identify that the person or organization publishing
that Snap are who they claim to be.
And so, though, would that have solved this?
So what happened?
So let me back up a little bit.
Yeah, lay it down.
There was a video game in the Snap Store,
I think it claimed to be a version of that 2048 game
everybody loves.
And when you get that there game,
it was actually doing a little crypto mining
in the background, surprise, surprise.
Well, of course, that's what you got to do these days.
So it's an interesting use of, I guess,
what you could call malware.
It was really more like crypto ware.
Because it's in this confined Snap,
but it can still use your CPU resources and do mining.
Just raises your power bill.
Yeah, so it's behaving in a way that
was unexpected to the user.
But they could have been a verified publisher.
Right.
And with the verification, does that speak at all
to the procedures?
How do they keep their keys?
All those sorts of things that would actually also impact.
Yeah, maybe we'll get details on that.
But that's about as much as I know.
I'm sure our friends Popeye or Wimpy
would have more insights on this particular topic.
It's been kind of interesting, but it all
could have been more of a shitstorm.
It's been kind of a mild shitstorm, but not that bad.
So what's been the piece that people have missed?
What is the definition of a mild shitstorm?
Well, I don't know.
From where I've sat, I could have
seen it could have been a lot worse.
But you were more at the heart of the storm.
So I'm curious if you have the same impression.
So whenever something like this happens,
and I'm not talking about whenever we regularly
get malware arriving.
I'm talking about whenever there's
a problem in Ubuntu, and we see the community reacting
in some way, we all jump to it.
And there are people, you could think of the Avengers
around the world, all coming together in order
to resolve this problem.
And I know that a whole bunch of people in Canonical
care very deeply about this problem,
wanted to get it solved.
So someone alerted us to the fact
that there was an application in the store,
and the application did something
other than what it said it did in the description.
That's effectively what it was.
It's as simple as that.
Someone said, this is a game.
It's 2048 or Hextris.
There was actually half a dozen, four or five applications
from the same author, and they all did the same thing.
They were, in inverted commas, masquerading as one thing,
but doing something else.
They weren't stealing data.
They weren't grabbing data off your machine
and sending it off to some third party.
They were basically using your CPU in order
to mine some kind of cryptocurrency.
And at the point when we found out about this,
I think it was early on a Saturday morning,
the weekend just gone, and I was standing in a field
watching my son play football.
I know Martin was in the middle of a forest with his family.
Other people were spending time with their families
on a Saturday morning, and everyone jumped to it.
Telegram lit up, IRC channels lit up.
We all jumped on it.
We all pinged all the right people,
phoned the emergency numbers, and made sure
that those applications were yanked from the store
as soon as possible.
So we did exactly the right thing as soon as we were alerted
or as soon as we figured out that there was something wrong.
We pulled these apps from the stores,
and then started a plan of investigation
and debugging what the applications were actually
doing to make sure that this doesn't happen again.
And we can plan for the future to make sure
that people are more aware of what's going on.
Yeah, and so do you think this verified program would
have fixed this particular problem,
since he did have a few other apps in the store?
He may have been considered verified at that point, no?
Well, the verified, there is no verified program at the moment.
So I couldn't possibly say if it would or wouldn't fix it,
because I don't know what form that verified program will
take.
We've discussed this a number of times at Canonical,
and it was most recently raised a couple of weeks ago.
The Snap team were at a sprint recently.
And it's a hard problem to solve.
It's not straightforward.
Even if you have someone who is, whether they are verified
or they're not, it's not a magic bullet
that stops someone from doing something nefarious.
You have to be able to keep an eye on these things,
monitor what's going on, and react fast
when things do go wrong.
If you look at any of the other app stores, Windows Mobile App
Store, iOS App Store, Mac App Store, Windows Desktop App
Store, Android App Store, they've all
had some kind of occasion that something
has been put in the store that users might feel aggrieved at,
in one way or another.
Whether it's too many pop-up adverts or crypto
mining or something else, everyone's
had this with a rite of passage for any app store.
We've hit that now.
And yeah, we're going to have to come up
with ways in which we can ensure that users have confidence
that the applications that are coming from the developers,
they can have some level of confidence
that that's a valid application.
One thing that we're trying to do with the Snap Store
is not that you should trust us, Canonical or Ubuntu,
is that you should trust the developer.
It's the developer who's pushing their stuff in the store.
The code is coming from their GitHub repository.
You should be able to go and have a look at their GitHub
repository.
You should be able to interrogate the Snap
and figure out where did this come from, who made it,
what's inside it.
You should be confident that the thing you're
installing on your computer is what it says it is.
And we've got some work to do there,
because right now, we don't make it obvious where
the source of the Snap came from.
So there's certainly some things we can do to improve.
Maybe verification will help as well.
Yeah, it obviously will be a process.
I'm curious to see when the details come out.
Congrats on being a real software store now.
Yeah, it is a challenge, especially
if you're going to allow submissions
from the general public, which you can kind of offset
to a degree by the fact that they are contained or confined,
I guess I should say.
Right.
And the other thing is, it's worth
noting that when we reacted, we reacted really fast,
like faster than most stores react.
So when we were told, within a couple of hours,
it's yanked from the store, so no new users
could download that application, what we also did
was made sure that any users who currently had the application,
we pushed out an update to those users
that removed the component.
That's still in progress, that removes the component
that does the nefarious stuff.
So they end up with the game and not the malware
that came along with it.
So we didn't just leave that software on people's computers,
but equally, we didn't reach out to everyone's computers
and delete the software from their computers.
It's a fine line to walk between saying,
well, you made the choice to install this software tough,
and the Amazon way, which was to reach out to people's Kindles
and delete a book from your Kindle.
We didn't want to do that.
We wanted to leave the software, but remove
the bit that was bad.
So it was a very delicate line and balance to walk.
Yeah, I hadn't thought about that.
I'm glad you mentioned that.
So now, we wait for the details down the road.
I appreciate that little tidbit about verify.
I think that is a good idea.
I mean, it shows that these are concerns that
take it seriously, and that goes a long way.
Some of the developers that have applications in the store,
we have one-to-one relationships with.
So some of the applications, like those
which are classic snaps, like many of the popular code
editors and things like Skype, people
are a little bit concerned they're classic snaps.
Being a classic snap, it means it has full access
to your system, very much like a dev does
when it's being installed.
And so people have a little concern there.
And we go through a vetting process for classic snaps,
where we vet the developer who has access to the snap
and make sure it correlates to the upstream developer who
owns the application.
So there's additional scrutiny applied to classic snaps?
We already do that scrutiny for classic snaps.
And perhaps that will be part of what
we do for our further verification process.
But like I say, we haven't figured out
the details of any of it.
Well, thank you for sharing that insight.
It's very interesting here for the behind-the-scenes aspect
of watching it from the outside.
Of course, people jumped on the bandwagon, but you're right.
It is almost a rite of passage to a degree.
And it's not necessarily even a new type of threat vector.
We've had rando repositories that people
have been adding to their sources list for years,
PPAs that you plug into a system.
I think there's always just going to be this conflict,
right?
It's either you have a super-lockdown store
where you don't have all the apps you want,
or it's easy to publish new software, and it's great,
and there are just more risks.
Yeah.
And the verified step, and perhaps others, will help.
All right.
Well, I want to move on to our friends
over at the Plasma Camp, who were doing a little get-together
in Berlin, Germany.
And some of the folks there gathered to discuss the
forthcoming 5.13 release, and of course, the future of Plasma
and Wayland itself.
But this time, with a twist, one of the members of the Sway
Window Manager team joined them to talk Wayland input methods
and a bunch of other things.
It looks like there was some really fruitful stuff coming
out of this.
Drew Devault, the lead developer of the Sway Window Manager,
joined the Plasma Sprint to discuss where Wayland
protocols could be shared between the projects.
Wow.
Right?
Brilliant.
The team looked at their layer protocol,
which covers much of the work of the current plasma shell
protocol.
We found that this protocol contained some nice ideas
and suggested some improvements for the Sway Window Manager
developers as well.
The plasma output management protocol was also discussed.
Now, get this thing.
This protocol defines how external monitors are used.
And Sway currently just reloads config files.
So the Sway team is going to consider using the plasma
output management protocol so the two projects are using the
same thing for external monitors.
That would be nice.
This alleviates some of my big concerns I have about the path
to Wayland.
And I'm really glad to see this.
There was also some talks about remote access
and using pipewire, because that's
the route the plasma's taking.
Right.
This is exactly the thing that we were like, well,
probably we'll need this in Wayland.
And it's happening.
So that's good.
It's really good.
They also had some new work on the new input stack for Qt,
because there was a bunch of other developers
there as well.
And Sean, I think I'm going to butcher this.
Rutledge, going to go for that.
What do you think?
Yeah, I think this time you got it right.
Yeah, well, he's the lead developer of Qt's new input
stack, and he joined the sprint for a few days
to work on and review the new API.
And this is really all about putting Wayland first.
And they said they got some nice parts in that were improved,
and things went surprisingly smooth.
And the plasma browser integration got final touches
for 5.13, which will be released next month.
Now, the plasma browser integration
means that Firefox and Chrome and Chromium browsers
will use Plasma's file transfer widget for downloads
and the native plasma notifications
for browser notifications.
And more importantly for me, the media controls in your task
manager will work for browser tabs and stuff,
so you can mute.
Oh, love that plasma manager.
It's nice.
So lots of stuff there.
Translations as well getting fixed up, other kinds of things,
and some work on the Falcon web browser
and getting it feature parity in terms of plasma integration
like the other browsers.
So some good stuff coming out of the plasma sprint in Berlin.
It's nice to see that.
Huge, huge fan now these days.
I'm all about it.
I've just really become quite the plasma fan.
You're biased, we know.
I really am.
It's been working so rock solid for me.
I appreciate your restraint.
You only put in this one story here.
That takes a lot of self-control.
I'm going to get you to switch eventually.
Popi and I, we're still rocking it.
We're still rocking it, right?
Yeah, Popi, you're still there, yes?
Yeah, totally.
Totally.
All day, every day.
Really?
Yeah.
It's an almost believable yeah.
OK, so I have two computers.
My main computer runs Unity on 1804,
but the laptop that I go walking around with, my T450,
that runs KDE Neon.
I have to point out, still the same install I did just
after I came back from your place, and it's still rocking.
I love it.
I don't want to steal his story because he might share it
on air, but Noah has a hilarious story
that is a true tribute to how stable KDE Neon was for him.
Long story short, he never rebooted
since the initial install.
He'd just been using it and sleeping his laptop, which
bit him in the arse in a major way, but I'll leave it to him.
What?
It's too funny of a story for me to share for him.
I won't take it from him, but it's a good one.
And it's been the same thing for him.
Super rock solid.
We're still running on all of the studio systems here,
so it's great just to see the team getting together in person
to put that final polish on 5.13.
I think that really makes a big difference for some
of these teams, so it's nice to see them have a chance
to be able to do that.
We have much, much, much, much, much more to get into.
Still lots to discuss, so let's take a moment
and thank DigitalOcean.
Go to do.co slash unplugged, where you will get a $100
credit at DigitalOcean when you sign up with a new account.
That lasts for 60 days and gives you a chance
to try out DigitalOcean.
Everything's based on super fast enterprise grade SSDs.
It's designed for developers, but it works for human beings.
They have a dashboard that's so good,
you might call it a dashboard for days.
And now they have new flexible droplets
where you can mix and match resources
that are the most appropriate for your application.
do.co slash unplugged.
They have private networking if you
want to have something in the back end,
like a database or a cache.
They have block storage that you can add to your system
as you need it.
I just put 250 gigs on it.
Oh, big spender, but not really.
Not that bad.
It's pretty reasonably priced for what you get.
Yeah, so for an example, my favorite rig, $0.03 an hour.
What?
Yeah, and that's a significantly fast rig, too.
It's probably more resources than I really
need most of the time.
And you can get a $100 credit when
you go to do.co slash unplugged.
They have a great API that's clearly documented,
easy to follow, and because of that,
there's tons of really good open source code already written.
You can integrate it into your Linux desktop,
like control your droplets.
You can get apps for your phone.
You can get command line scripts.
You can get libraries for your favorite programming language.
I mean, the whole spectrum is covered for DigitalOcean.
Plus, they have a ton of great distributions,
all of the real distributions you'd probably
want to put on a server to begin with, plus that free BSD.
Really?
Yeah.
Wow.
So go check it out, do.co slash unplugged.
Get the $100 credit, and a big thank you
to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the unplugged program,
do.co slash unplugged.
So with the release of 18.04, we've
seen a disappointing trend of clickbait
to try to make or manufacture, you might say,
some drama around the, quote, data collection
services in Ubuntu 18.04.
And even the name is sort of overdramatizing what this is.
If you install Ubuntu 18.04, at the end,
there's a screen that comes up that says what's new in Ubuntu.
And at the end of that screen, it talks about data collection.
And it shows you an example of the data collection.
We're going to go over one of those reports in a moment.
But I've noticed a trend, particularly with YouTube.
And I hate to come on here and be like,
Chris yells at YouTube once again.
Oh, then Chris is back.
But it's pretty disappointing, because it
plays to a well-trained sort of knee-jerk response
that's in the audience to respond badly to anything
about data collection.
Because of all of the Facebook stuff, all of the Google stuff
that we all know, NSA collection,
since Edward Snowden, we've had it drilled into us
that everybody's spying on us.
Windows 10 launched with all these metrics.
It's just been drilled into us that spying equals bad,
data equals bad.
But the reality is, if you're deploying a large-scale
operating system, you have to have some insights
into your customer base.
You have to.
You want that feedback cycle, yeah.
And so there's a line to be walked here.
And I think Canonical has walked it really well,
because they could have gone further than they did.
Essentially, what happens when you opt into this data
collection is you generate a report about your system.
And I'll have an example report linked in the show notes.
And what it does is it collects things
like the version of Ubuntu that you just installed,
the type of processor that you have, the type of GPU,
the vendor and model number, just
like they would be in an Xorg report, nothing fancy.
It's not like it's a super in-depth thing here.
Your screen resolution, if you have live patch or auto log
on, turned on, the desktop environment,
and if you're using Wayland or X, then your time zone,
the media that you use to install, like the ISO,
if you use the minimal install.
And that's essentially it.
There's a couple of other basics in here,
like did you download updates during the install?
That's the data that gets sent.
It's really quite harmless.
And also, if you choose not to participate in the data
collection, there is a one-time ping.
All of this is just a JSON file in clear text
that you can read yourself.
You can just open it up and read it, and it's clear.
And there's a one-time ping that's
sent to Canonical that says user did not
opt into data collection.
There's no IP, no identifiable information.
Will Cook stated they don't even store the IP address
of the HTTP connection in the Apache logs.
On the server side, yeah.
Right.
It's just that they opted out.
So that way, they have a metric to know
how many people are choosing not to use this program,
so they can have idea how unpopular.
Yeah, exactly.
So you know how many total installs are happening.
But that doesn't stop people from attempting
to generate controversy, because that generates clicks
and views and ad dollars.
And if you look at the comments on a couple
of these different YouTube videos,
people are all in on this stuff.
They're all in on it, because they are just
looking at that word data collection,
and they're freaking out.
And the problem is that it actually
handicaps Canonical's ability to really figure out
what's popular.
Like for example, 64-bit versus 32-bit.
How many of their users are actually
using 32-bit processors?
Or how many of them are installing a 32-bit version
of the OS on 64-bit capable hardware?
That simple plain text data file tells them that.
That's a pretty valuable piece of information
that could save them tons of engineering time.
Well, and also it can be very difficult
to get that feedback other ways.
You often see that minority communities are
going to communicate a lot more.
And it's hard to get a sense of just what
a lot of bland default users who don't care
to give feedback to Canonical, this
is a way that they can be sampled in that user base.
Producer Michael responded on one of the videos.
He said, I completely disagree with this video being made,
because none of the collection is a negative thing.
The initial data collection of Ubuntu report of,
it's Ubuntu Dash report by the way,
when you choose not to send info only
sends that you chose not to send info.
The removal of the package merely to not tell them actually
skews the data, because it lowers
the amount of people who will be continued and counted
as not participating.
So these videos are advising uninstall this package,
so that way you don't have anything ever sent to them.
Never even a ping.
Wow.
But the problem is, is then Canonical has no metric
to know how unpopular this is.
So producer Michael goes on.
If you wanted them to know you dislike it,
then you have to send them the info that you opted out.
They have to have that information.
The reason it was made automatic and opt out
is because most people dismiss the pop ups
and close it anyways.
The other aspect is there's some bug data collection
that will automatically get sent to the background that
does contain more information.
But again, that's critical information
that every commercial desktop operating system is collecting.
And that's really my piece on this,
is I think this is actually an example of how
open source media can be, or free software coverage,
or whatever label you want to apply to it,
can actually be destructive to the movement.
Because it creates fear and uncertainty and doubt
about something that is very vanilla and very clear.
You actually, when you finish the first time run wizard
of 1804, you can click a button, and it will show you
what it's going to send.
So you can review all of it.
We also kind of waste an opportunity
to interact with the developers, with the organizations
in the community.
I mean, Ubuntu, I think, has been very clear about what
their purposes were.
There was a long period of assessment
before this feature got included.
So you don't have to pretend it's
some monolithic corporation.
It's not Oracle we're talking about,
where you have to assume the worst.
Why can't we have a good faith discussion about this?
Maybe people don't like it for legitimate reasons.
Let's not start it from a bunch of posturing videos
that haven't bothered to have a conversation.
And Gambus, do you think it's also something
that software developers have more appreciation
for than, say, an average user?
Yeah, I mean, I've been developing some applications
for the Linux desktop, and they are quite specific.
And many times it happened that people just reported,
oh, this thing doesn't work, and I don't know what's going on.
And I just tried troubleshooting and spent many hours
trying to get the information about the hardware.
When if I just add in some user profiling,
well, not user profiling, but some information
that's useful for developers, just like an Oracle is doing,
I would have had a much easier life trying
to troubleshoot all these issues.
And I think this is the same thing for Ubuntu.
I mean, they have to make a distribution that
works on such a great variety of hardware.
And I can only imagine how difficult
it can be to fix so many possible and potential bugs
without knowing anything about the systems
that those bugs are on.
I mean, the typical problem that works on my machine
and nobody else's.
Yeah, it's hard to fully appreciate it
from the support standpoint, and how do you make decisions,
and how do you design your software
when you have zero visibility into your user base.
And if you want to see what the information actually is,
if you're on 18.04 right now, you
can run Ubuntu-report show, and it will generate
the report that gets sent.
So you can review it and see how benign this is.
Wimpy, were you going to jump in with something there?
I was.
There's a couple of issues I have with this particular video.
The first is everything about it is technically inaccurate.
So it's got a wonderful click-baity title.
But the first thing it explains to do
is remove the Ubuntu-report package, which is actually
the wrong package to remove, because that
isn't the package that the GNOME first run wizard interacts
with.
And you actually see this in the video that he clicks no,
and it generates the opt-out report,
and he sort of skips over it a little bit.
So it's removing the wrong package.
He also suggests that you remove popularity contest, which
is also known as PopCon.
Now, that's installed by default,
but it's not enabled by default. And sending a telemetry report
doesn't enable PopCon.
PopCon is installed by default, not enabled,
and we have no plans to turn it on.
So in suggesting that you remove Ubuntu-report and popularity
content because these are the things that collect data,
that also removes the Ubuntu standard meta package.
And what that does is breaks your upgrade path from 18.04
to any subsequent version of Ubuntu.
So if you follow the instructions in this video,
one, it doesn't actually change the behavior
of the first run wizard, and two,
it breaks your ability to upgrade in the future.
Wow.
That is really damaging in a way that I hadn't even
touched on before is that a lot of times
these videos are poorly researched and kind of thrown
together because you need to capitalize on something
while it's very popular in order to generate.
There's no time for research, Chris.
YouTube has this term that they tell
you to score for called VPH, which
stands for views per hour.
And you want to optimize your VPH so that way it
juices the algorithm and puts you in front of subscribers.
And the way you do that is by producing a video on something
that's trending at the moment, that's
popular amongst your audience at the moment.
And so that is a long way of saying
you are incentivized to rush content on YouTube.
And that's damaging as well, right?
Because YouTubers are being incentivized
to produce content quickly, which
could be fine in some respects.
But the 17 pence extra a month that this particular video
is going to generate, which is trading off besmirching
Ubuntu's reputation with a technically inaccurate bit
of video tutorial, that is poisoning the world.
It doesn't help anybody.
You see all of these comments.
They see data collection.
They assume this is like the kind of invasive stuff
that's in Windows 10.
Literally, that's in the comments several times, yeah.
And they make all the wrong assumptions.
And there is nothing in the words
that are used in the video or the title to suggest otherwise.
And the source code's available.
I mean, if you want to research this,
you just go and look at the source code and see how it works.
What I find frustrating is that Martin alluded to the fact
that if you do something, there are some things
that it's possible to do to Ubuntu
that many new users follow blindly a tutorial that
breaks their experience six months down the line.
When they come to upgrade to the next point release,
or if they're more conservative, they
upgrade to the next LTS release.
And the problem is people don't remember.
In six months' time, they won't remember
that a thing they did six months ago
is the reason why they can no longer upgrade.
We get it in the neck.
And people say Ubuntu upgrades don't work.
They do if you don't screw your system in the first place.
But the problem is you screwed your system six months ago,
and you've long forgotten any terminal command
that some random dude on YouTube told you to put in.
You thought it was a good idea at the time,
because that's what he told you.
Six months later, you're in our IRC channel
or on our support network asking us, why is my system broken?
I've upgraded and I've got a black screen,
or it won't upgrade, or it crashes, or whatever.
And we're like, well, that thing you did six months ago,
no, no, no, it's you.
You're the reason all this stuff is broken.
It's Ubuntu's fault.
And that's really bitter pill to swallow,
because we try really hard to make these upgrades work.
But if people actively shoot themselves in the foot,
it's really hard to undo that.
And that's really painful six months, two years down the line.
So behind the scenes, if you do remove
the Ubuntu standard package, which people have done
for different reasons in error, there
are some heuristics in the upgrade manager
that try to figure out, what version of Ubuntu
did you have installed before it got
gutted to try and piece together what it should
do to repair the situation?
But it's a best guess, because you
can do so much to your system to mess with it.
And this kind of thing, removing the base meta package,
is just a recipe for disaster.
Yeah, I'm really glad you brought that up,
because I hadn't watched more than a few minutes
into the video where I started to read the comments.
And I got really frustrated, because two things.
It plays on the paranoia of a technically savvy audience
about metrics.
And it builds, perhaps, momentum against future projects
that might want to do something similar.
And I would argue that is a bad thing,
because I would make an argument that these metrics are benign
and that they are beneficial.
And then they are much more beneficial
than they are in any way benign in a sense
that they could track you or that they
would be identifiable.
The thing is you really have to appreciate
how much insight they're able to gain just
out of knowing the types of processors, the Windows
server, and desktop environments.
That can significantly give a company
like Canonical important information
so they know where to focus development resources.
And they're competing against commercial operating systems
that are doing 10 times the level of data collection.
Right, and then on the other side,
you end up with complaints about, why don't we have this?
Why don't we have that?
How come we can't compete?
And it's just a no-win game in that world.
At the beginning of this episode,
we talked about the Gnome project removing the ability
to run binary files.
Imagine, and I'm not suggesting that this
would be a good world, but let's imagine
that the Gnome project did have telemetry
on how people used Gnome Shell.
And let's say they had telemetry that showed that 75%
of their users, at least once a day,
launched a binary file from their file manager.
They may not be considering removing that functionality.
But they have no data.
They have no insights other than their gut intuition
and what they grok from the drive-by feedback
that they get.
I have no, and I think most people in Ubuntu
have no problem with the fact that people
might want to tick the no box and say, no, I
don't want to do this, right?
Yeah, have at it.
It's an individual decision that someone might say,
you know what?
I don't care.
And I actually value my own personal privacy
so much that I don't want to even tell you
what resolution display I had when
I installed the software product that I got for you
for free, right?
I don't want to tell you that.
OK, fine.
But that's another step to then make a video
to tell the whole world not to do that as well.
That's what gets me.
Because when you socialize that whole don't allow Canonical
to have any kind of data in order
to plan what they're doing in the future,
and then we plan things.
And you say, well, what the fuck were Canonical thinking?
Why were they doing those things?
Why did they focus on laptops with 1366 by 768 displays?
Well, because that's the only data we have, right?
That's all we know.
And if we don't know what type of displays there are out there,
what types of CPUs out there, we can't make educated decisions.
And if everyone is told to turn this shit off,
what the fuck are we going to do?
I agree.
And it's going to scare other projects away
from something similar.
And the thing that is unfortunate
is this was pretty well implemented,
I really have to say.
The real cherry on the top was at the end
where you could see the report or the fact
that you could show yourself the report at any time.
You can see in a plain text file what's being said.
Simple, transparent.
And it's all clearly documented about what from the bug reports
get sent and all of that telemetry.
So even when it was done, I think,
probably the most open and transparent way possible,
including the very source code, the powers, all of this
is open.
I just don't know.
It's obvious that the core issue here
is that there is a financial incentive or a even ego
incentive for different outlets to try to make hay on this.
There's a lot of stories that just get blown out
of proportion.
And this is just another one of them.
So I've made this point before.
I won't make it again.
But thanks, you guys, for your thoughts on that.
And just be aware of it, even if you don't want
to opt into data collection.
Just be aware of the impact this kind of stuff
has because I think you're completely, like Popi said,
you're 100% within your right to not send any data.
I do think it's pretty nice, though, to send them
the I'm opting out.
So that way, they get a signal.
So you can essentially have a vote still.
I think that's something to consider.
All right, I want to just also talk about really briefly
a little follow-up on the reverse engineering
at Purism for some of Intel's FSP stuff that disappeared
off the internet all of a sudden.
Whoa.
Yeah, there was a blog post that went up
describing the in-depth technical process
that they went through recently to reverse engineer
some of this Intel crap.
And we noticed on LAN that it disappeared.
And so we made a comment on Linux Action News
that perhaps they had been contacted by Intel.
Yeah, it looks like that was the case.
It looks like Intel politely asked Purism
to remove their document because they thought it might conflict
with licensing terms, i.e., if you want to buy processors
from us in the future, you'll be taking that down.
That's a pretty big fist to say no to.
Yeah, and so they complied.
However, the internet never forgets, as you well know.
And Chris somehow found a copy in archive.org.
You demon, you.
So if you want to read this extremely in-depth technical
document, I'll have a link in the show notes,
linuxunplug.com, slash 249 to archive.org.
Wes, I almost think we should save this Docker story
for another day.
It deserves probably a better discussion.
Yeah.
I'll just quickly, last week I made a comment
at the end of the show.
I think nobody's going to like this episode
because we talked about containers too much.
Wah, wah, wah.
And I got a couple of emails that were like,
I actually really enjoyed that because nobody else is really
talking about that.
And it's a huge part of my life these days.
And it's a huge part of where software is going.
So I feel like people have their heads in the sand.
And then other emails were like, it's new to me.
And I'm learning.
So it was interesting to hear what you could do with it.
Nobody really emailed and saying they hated it.
But I assume some people do get tired of us
talking about magical ponies and container technologies.
So I'm going to save why Docker is dangerous.
And it's a gamble that you will regret for a future episode.
But it's out there.
We'll be talking more about it in the future.
Because there is still that question
that I want to get to before we wrap up.
I want to ask the Mumba Room and Wes if it's
time to move on from the all GTK, our all cute mentality.
So let's start first by thanking Ting.
I'm taking them to Texas with me.
This show is going to be broadcasted over Ting all
the way down to Tejas.
And it's perfect.
It's pay for what you use wireless.
So I've got a little MiFi for CDMA.
And I've got a little MiFi for GSM.
Because Ting has both networks.
And I let them sit around for a little bit, boss level.
It's $6 for the line.
So you don't care.
That's funny badger.
And you could just deactivate the device
if you weren't going to use it for six months
and then just order up a SIM and pop it in and good to go again.
That's actually what I've done.
And it's great.
Because then I've got CDMA and GSM with me as I go.
And I just pay for the usage.
So whenever I'm parked somewhere that has Wi-Fi, which I always shoot for,
then I'm not paying anything for data.
It's like I'm just getting by for free.
It's nationwide coverage with no contracts.
It's just $6 for the line.
And you pay for what you use, your minutes, your messages,
and your megabytes.
There's a control panel you can log into to always check
your minutes and your messages and your data usage.
And you can always take total control, turn stuff on and off,
activate and deactivate devices.
You can set usage alerts.
If I ever get talked into giving my kids a phone,
I'm going to start using those usage alerts.
Dylan, stop it.
Too much.
Get off them internets.
And they've got lots of devices, including the new Moto devices.
It's got the modules.
Have you seen that where you can snap on a new camera or battery and stuff?
They're selling that now.
Or you can bring your device, and they'll give you a $25 service credit.
Love it.
Might just pay for more than your first month.
So go check it out.
Linux.ting.com.
That's linux.ting.com.
I just noticed there's a TechSnap logo there.
Yeah, I noticed that, too.
That threw me off a little bit.
Am I doing the TechSnap show?
But don't worry.
You still get to type linux.ting.com.
And maybe go see the old TechSnap logo.
It's kind of retro.
Woo.
I made that logo.
Look at you.
Yeah, you can tell, too.
Professional.
You can tell I made that logo.
And then we have a new one.
Yeah.
The new logo is done by a pro.
OK, so this was a question that popped up on the dumpster fire known as RLinux.
And it was asking, is this mentality still relevant today, the all GTK or all Qt mentality?
I ask this because I've seen people arguing about this online.
He says, nowadays, there's a lot of disk space.
So usually having two GUI frameworks installed really doesn't make a big
difference on disk usage.
And he says, there's also people who use GTK apps when using a GTK desktop and Qt
apps when using a Qt desktop, and they only use those apps.
And I actually will admit to when I switched back to Plasma again, I tried to just try
to do Qt everything.
And when I couldn't find a good Qt Twitter client, I just didn't even bother getting
it.
I just use the website now.
Yeah, sure.
Or I was using Corebird on GNOME.
Or some Curses UI you found.
It would be great.
So I admit I actually do kind of try to skew all Qt now.
Wow.
Backing QO notes and stuff like that.
Yeah, I admit I've done this a little bit.
What do you think you get out of it?
Do you like it?
Do you feel clean?
There's small things that I appreciate.
Small consistency things like in my open and save dialogues, like my favorites and my
bookmarks are different between my GTK and Qt dialogue open and close boxes.
And that's always frustrating because I'll be working in Qt apps all day, and so I'll
have a new bookmark in there.
And then I go into a GTK app, and I've got to browse the file system like an animal.
It's so slow.
And that stuff is kind of frustrating.
So that makes me kind of prefer that.
And then you get other bennies usually, like the plasma notification integration or KIO
slave stuff.
And there's just things that are with the Qt apps that I just like to have.
Better integration, sort of a first class feel.
Yeah.
You're on the gnome side of things.
You don't seem to shy away from a Qt app, though.
No, that's fine.
I don't have a ton of Qt apps.
You kind of have a mixed family desktop, don't you?
A little bit, yeah.
But yeah, I guess I can see why you might want to do it.
I can appreciate a little of the software purism, but I'm not.
The theme looks a little better.
Oh, that's gotten a lot better these days.
I guess it depends on if it's a program that's easily replaced, then sure.
Maybe you'll find a new program that you love.
That's one of the great things about being a Linux open source enthusiast, right?
Is you have so many choices.
I'll tell you, I've taken this far enough that I've given Kmail several goes.
OK, yeah.
And I like Kmail in its own way.
I like it.
It's in its own esoteric, unique way.
But Snap installed MailSpring.
That's just what I ended up going back to MailSpring.
Yeah, I did.
And it's the Snap, too.
I Snap installed MailSpring.
And it's just better.
But it's like this hybrid app.
It's not a Qt app, either.
Clearly, you've been thinking about it, though.
And that bugs me.
Yeah, it is something that crosses my mind.
What about you guys in the Mumble Room?
Anybody want to admit if they're a Qt or GTK purist?
I'm not a purist, no.
So I use what is the best tool for the job.
So for example, I use QoNotes as well.
That's a Qt application.
But it's the best that's available.
I use the Shotcut Video Editor and ABS.
And they're both Qt applications.
And I use VLC, video player.
And that's a Qt application.
Same.
So yeah, I use what's best.
Yeah, when you install MailSpring, by the way, little pro tip.
If you Snap install MailSpring on the Plasma desktop,
you also have to install Gnome Keyring in the background.
Because it will not run without that.
I have two machines.
One is mostly with the approach of let's try to use everything Gnome.
And the other machine, it's the one I develop in.
That one, of course, is full of everything.
Yeah, interesting.
So why do you have the one that's all pure?
Is that, in an ideal world, your preferred setup?
Just generally, I would like to see the project.
I started with Gnome, essentially.
And I'd like to see the project to be able to be self-sufficient in all
of its toolings.
There's no better way to try the flow.
I also am a very big fan of default.
So I don't tend to use things that, by default, are not the way
I tend to like them most.
I really don't like fiddling around.
In the beginning, that was exciting.
No longer.
There's no time for that.
Yeah, I understand.
That's how I kind of see it.
Let's try to reduce the foreign aspects and have the experience.
And if the experience is not it, try find something else.
Generally, that's how I go.
And something else might mean the whole new package.
I don't care what toolkit an application has.
Looking down my launcher, things that I'm running right now,
Firefox, Telegram, Gnome Terminal, Steam, Slack, IRC, Cloud,
Visual Studio, Zenkit, VirtualBox, Discord, Signal, and Mumble.
Don't care.
So if I want to talk to you, I use Mumble on this show right now.
I'm not going to go out there and say, I can't use Mumble because it's cute.
And I've got a GTK desktop.
That's just lunacy, right?
I'm using the application that I need to get the job done.
And so I installed the right application for the job.
But that's not what I'm advocating.
I'm just saying that there's a preferential path that I have.
And then, of course, you do one or other exception.
But I think that for having that cohesive experience,
you do in the beginning go through, oh, maybe there's a lack of this.
And again, I have two machines, and I develop stuff.
And it's also one way of seeing, oh, there's a potential target here to develop.
And I can see how someone might want to dive fully into the elementary experience
and only use elementary applications designed, written in Valor,
delivered in the elementary app store, and designed specifically
for that environment.
And I can see why you might do that.
But I'd be pretty sure after a short while,
you'd feel like you're missing out on something.
And there's a couple of applications you really need,
and there's someone you need to talk to, or there's some application you need
access to, or some data you need access to,
that you need to install something that breaks outside of that amazing,
though it is, Valor boundary and into Qt or GTK or whatever.
It does seem inevitable from that perspective.
I might want a new user to start out in a consistent world,
and then you sort of eventually learn about the realities of the world
that we live in.
And OK, it's a little more complicated than the real world.
Got to get the work done.
Yeah.
I do admit to one unique constraint I do usually tend to put myself,
is to not install apps I cannot maintain myself, in case doomsday.
That is actually also part of how I decide.
Some apps I really like, but for example, they're in Go.
So I'm never going to use them, because I really
hate that language as an example.
And so I'm not going to be willing to maintain it in Go.
I try to find alternatives or just put the effort in,
so that it happens in another language that I feel it's the best way.
I love your doomsday scenario is not, I need to find food and drink,
but I need to be able to code applications I'm using on my laptop.
Well, you have to maintain, right?
What's the point of having source code if one day things shut down
and you can't fix it?
The bunker is going to have computers, obviously.
They got to keep running.
Yeah, I think I kind of agree with all of that.
But mostly, you got to have the best tool for the job.
And that's always the way I'll land.
Even if it's a GDI application running via wine,
I'll use it if that's what I have to use.
But if there is any kind of thing that sort of tilts the preference dial,
it would be if I could also get it in whatever
the native toolkit of my desktop is.
Well, I think that's what Architect in the IRC sums it up perfectly.
Use the least offensive tool for the job.
Yeah, that's very well put.
Yeah, OK.
I'd love to know your thoughts, too.
Knowlinuxunplugged.com slash contact where you can send in questions
to the show or if you are acute or GTK purist.
There have been times, especially when using Gnome 3 Shell,
I'm like, yeah, yeah, I am tempted.
Client-side decorations all the places.
Forever.
Yeah.
Let us know.
Let us know how you feel about it.
If you want to join our Mumble Room, we do have a setup guide
that you can follow.
Yay.
If you just go Google Jupiter Colony Mumble Setup Guide,
guess what?
You'll pretty much find it.
It's pretty much all it takes right there.
You can follow Wes on the Twitter.
He's at wespain.
You can go get more poppy and wimpy
in the Fantastic Ubuntu Podcast.
New episode just came out.
And you can find out how many laptops each of them have.
Oh, boy.
Also, Wes and I just did a breakdown
of eFail on TechSnap, all of the technical details,
all of those goodies in this week's episode of TechSnap.
If you want to know more about eFail, what's
going on with GNU PG and OpenPGP, and what the real details are,
what the real deets are, it's all in that episode.
All them deets.
All right, thanks so much for tuning
this week's episode of the Unplugged program.
And guess what?
We're going to see you right back here next Tuesday.
I've never installed Linux slash Linux.
Roof, roof, roof.
Guard dogs on the Unplugged job.
They don't want the show to end.
No.
Keep it going.
They love the Unplugged program.
Mumba Room, thanks, you guys.
That was a great conversation and a bunch of stories
that you had some good insights on.
So I really appreciate you making it today.
You're wonderful.
You're gosh darn wonderful.
Now we've got to name this thing.
And the J-bot's still down because, long story short, it was-
J-bot's down again?
Yeah.
Well, you know that arch box is falling apart, right?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
So I got TCP IP up.
No way.
I know.
Well, it didn't get updated for a couple of years.
So I got the TCP stack working again, and I got SSH up
and running again.
Well, those are luxuries.
But I still can't get J-bot to properly function.
Oh.
But the OS is actually standing again.
I don't know how I did it.
Okay.
Good.
Like a miner through the DigitalOcean console chipping
away at all of the cruft.
Literally.
So what happened was-
Praise be to that console.
The system hadn't been updated for a couple of years.
Because it's been a while since DigitalOcean let you deploy arch.
Yes, it has.
And so-
Years.
Yeah.
And it got locked to an old kernel and all that.
Anyways, long story short, they had to reboot for Meltdown Inspector.
And when it rebooted, it didn't really ever come back up quite right.
And so I went in there and sort of salvaged the system and got it standing again.
We figured out we had to SU to Rekai's account.
Yeah.
So we got the little esoteric, like what weird user situation we had to be in, where the
scripts were to start everything.
Fired all that out.
And it connects up and it just generates errors.
So we don't have it long.
That's my long way of saying we don't have JBOT to do title suggestions.
We have to just come up with it on our own.
So much pressure.
You can throw it in the chat room though.
I saw Fudbuntu.
I kind of don't like that though.
Because it sounds like a-
Oh, guard dog.
It sounds like a flavor.
So I kind of don't like that.
So other title suggestions would be appreciated.
I also wanted to point out a documentary by DW, which somebody remind me, DW, are they
out of Germany, I believe, but I'm drawing a blank.
They just did a video called the Microsoft Cyber Attack.
And it's, you know, the premise is a little, but they go to Munich.
And during all the transition stuff and they talk about how Microsoft lobbied to make some
of this transition from LibreOffice back to Microsoft software.
And they cover also a French government transition to Linux.
There is some rando shots of consultants using Unity, like at the 27 minute mark, there's
a consultant that they're doing an interview with and she's using Unity on a, it looks
like an XPS.
And she's using the touchscreen to scroll a document that she's showing the journalist.
So I'll have a link to that in the show notes if you want to check it out.
The Microsoft Cyber Attack though, if you just go Google it on YouTube.
And it's in English.
They've done translations.
Oh, nice.
Great.
Yeah.
It was a really cool documentary.
I didn't think the premise started a little like too newbie, you know, I was like, ah,
this is thick.
But then they got into like the Linux and Limux stuff and then I was all in, which happens
about halfway into it.
All right.
We got to name this thing, Wes.
We do.
What did we talk about?
Oh, all the things.
Let's make it easy.