This is KOTORadio, episode 480 for August 22nd, 2022.
Hey good buddy, welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and the business, the software development, and the world of technology.
I, a man trapped in time, my name is Chris, and I am joined by my time lord, Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike.
So now I have to ask you which doctor you think I would be, so you're going to do this?
We're turning into a Facebook quiz now.
No, I think you're actually the time traveler in TNG that shows up and like puts his hands
on the equipment and then makes the machines like go crazy, and then the machine has super
warp speeds and all that.
I think you're that guy.
At least you didn't say I'm hardcore Fenton Mudd, so I'll take it.
No, but I would like to know what you did to Wesley, so there is that.
He's fine.
He's hanging out with the Klingons, he's having a great time.
My homie Takuvma is taking good care of him, it's all good.
Oh good, good, good, good, hanging out, hanging out.
But not hanging out with you, because you're going to be at TCGCon Tampa.
I am.
That mana tapping monkey is back on my back, known as Magic the Gathering.
It's uh, oh did I fall off the wagon hard.
You know what, I like it.
It's properly nerdy.
I think it's good for you, you know.
I've already done a commander event, and I'm going this week again to, I think it's commander
again.
Which as someone who hasn't really played Magic in like 10 years other than Arena, that's
some crazy diabolical politicking stuff for folks who don't know.
It's a weird multiplayer format, but it's both competitive and cray cray.
So yeah, a lot of fun TCGCon.
I will be there at least Saturday, I might go Sunday, depending on how fast I get my
ass kicked.
Pretty good.
If you're in the area, come say hi.
I will be wearing something super nerdy.
Really this is the first one they're doing in Tampa, and the ticket prices reflect that.
It's very affordable, surprisingly so.
So yeah, I figured why not.
I live literally like it's like a 30 minute drive or less, so.
Oh, that's great.
That's great.
I'm jealous.
I have been like in an event drought, and the events that I have been like that have
been made possible, like that I have been invited to, I guess, the words are hard today.
Just haven't really worked out, haven't been practical, so good for you.
Get out there.
Go say hi to Mike in Tampa, if you're in the Tampa area.
I'm jelly.
I'd love to go.
I bet the weather is going to be great.
I bet you'll get your butt kicked.
That'd be great to watch.
I'm sure.
I was going to say for you, it's watching me get stomped, but yeah, did you ever play
magic?
No, I never got sucked in.
I don't know.
Maybe I was just maybe I got sucked into other stuff, but magic I somehow managed to avoid
that in Pokemon.
I managed to avoid both of those somehow.
Yeah, that's probably for the best.
I even got my kid into it.
Yeah, I would.
I would.
I mean, let's be honest.
I would too, right?
Because that's fun.
He also helps me sort the cards because, you know, child labor is the best kind of labor.
That is.
Yeah, they can.
You know what?
I know.
I know about it for a fact.
They can be good at card sorting.
No, I won't tell you how I know, but I know for a fact.
Nick knows for a fact that he ain't kidding around no more.
He's got S to do.
Things have changed around.
He says, Hey, Chris and Michael, I want to say cheers to Chris.
I don't remember exactly when I started listening to JB, but it was somewhere in 2012 or so.
So it's been 10 years for sure.
So thanks for all the shows.
Well, thank you for listening.
Now onto the main topic.
I was doing some catching up on Coder Radio recently, and I stumbled on your discussion
about Mac OS and Windows stealing Linux desktop users.
Well, I'm a recent six months or so Windows convert after 10 years of exclusive Linux
desktop use.
So I wanted to chime in.
I guess I'm older now.
And while in 2012 I was a student, nowadays I have a day job with responsibilities.
So I really like my machines to just sort of be appliances.
You turn it on, runs, does what I want.
That's it.
And honestly, desktop Linux become too much of a hassle for me.
As stupid as this might sound to some, Windows is the ultimate LTS.
If you apply some basic best practices like having a backup and not running from sites
with pictures of naked ladies, it just runs.
Everything works because everything is written with Windows in mind.
Further, besides WSL, I think Redmond has got two more things that might snare some
Linux users.
One is this new Windows terminal.
Well, things good.
Also, did you know SSH is installed and on by default now?
You fire it up and you can SSH into Windows like it was a Linux box.
The other thing I hear nobody mentioning is Hyper-V. Nowadays, we all have pretty beefy
machines, so why not run VMs?
Hyper-V is no problem for anybody that ever had to run Vert Manager.
Its ultimate killer feature, though, is dynamic memory management that just works, meaning
VMs do not use all the memory you allocate to them, but just what they need right now.
I could run two, three, four Linux VMs daily and not even worry about memory at all.
I know it's possible to do these kinds of things with KVM, but I just never managed
to get it right.
Here, it's just a checkbox.
Do I find all of this problematic?
No.
Now that I don't run Linux, I run way more Linux.
I have various Linux machines where I can tinker when time permits and I use VMs daily
for critical things like backups.
And yeah, I am eyeing those damn MacBooks.
It might just be a matter of time.
Best regards.
Of course you are.
You know, the only thing that strikes me about this, Nick, but otherwise I totally feel where
you're coming from, is you might still be in the honeymoon period.
You know, six months with Windows usually takes about a year, I find, with a Windows
Insta.
For your registry to be completely polluted, yes.
Well, and just to start getting a little tired, you know, of the way Microsoft does things.
Just that.
But I do remember when we tried Windows 10 for the show, which feels like ages ago, though,
I do remember very much having what he said in here where, like, everything's just built
for Windows.
It's like, you just, you can get anything.
There's every application, even like the esoteric free software stuff, is built for Windows.
So like, and it's, there's only one Windows, really.
So it's not like you, you know, you don't have to worry about devs and RPMs.
There's just the Windows build and everything supports Windows.
It's so nice.
That's so nice.
As a Linux user, that, you don't always have that experience.
It's pretty common these days.
Sure.
I mean, it's, I don't know, I sort of feel like the Linux app compatibility stuff is
kind of better than Mac at this point.
Hmm.
Because if you care about like games, I guess, because still no viable proton for Mac.
I know people have sent me the link every time I say that, but that is a hell of a lot
of work.
All right.
Our next email comes in from Christopher and he's dropping some Glad Whale bombs.
He says, hi guys.
I've been a show member since you returned and I'm glad I have the opportunity to support
you.
Well, thank you, sir.
Hmm.
Just thinking about how damn thankful I am for our members this morning, so thank you.
He goes on to say your take on Malcolm Gladwell is spot on in Coder 478.
I see him as a bit of a bomb thrower who enjoys intellectually tossing incendiary statements
and watching the carnage of sociopaths abandoning their own thoughts and beliefs without critically
analyzing what he's actually saying.
What Gladwell is really saying against remote work is that work is a cult and you must stay
in the compound.
I like that he's like, he says Gladwell is playing like 40 chess here.
I like that he just went for it.
That's pretty, pretty hardcore.
Yeah.
I mean, I don't know.
I, I can't say that I'm super aligned with how colorful this opinion is, but I definitely
agree with the facts.
I love it.
I don't know if I do agree.
I think Gladwell does believe what he was saying.
So quick recap for those that didn't hear it.
We played a clip of Malcolm Gladwell, author, podcaster who said, you know, don't you want
to be a part of something?
Don't you want to be your best you?
Don't you want to do your best work of your life?
Well, then you have to come into the office.
That was basically his position.
I don't know.
I mean, I, I guess I, I guess I don't agree with you that I sort of feel like he, he says
things like most people that align to his incentives and to his fear group.
And uh, I mean, I have read all his things in favor of working in a cafe or in a, I think
it was like a pub that played some kind of cool rock music that he liked.
Right.
So I don't know, you know, it's people tend to just pitch their own book, right?
I, well, here's my thought and I hate to be this guy, but maybe he's not a digital native,
right?
Maybe he's not fully aware of all the tooling available to remote workers these days because
really the best stuff is not used by most, by most organizations.
They're sort of like during the pandemic, we got to this new minimum quality bar, which
was way better than it was before the pandemic.
Like before the pandemic, most people didn't have cameras.
Their wifi couldn't handle video conferencing.
It was horrible.
Right.
And we got to this new bar, but that bar is basically zoom, right?
And you know, a Mac book camera and uh, air pod microphones.
I don't know, I mean, I think for tech workers in particular and developers, I mean, some
of the, the, uh, joint coding stuff or whatever we call that pair programming stuff in VS
code is really in a very short amount of time has become incredibly impressive.
See, I think that's just it.
I think that's the difference between a successful remote work culture and the picture that Malcolm
Gladwell was painting.
Malcolm Gladwell, I think is painting the picture of the organization that doesn't take
advantages of things like pair programming.
But organizations like yours that are nimbler, uh, more up to speed on the tooling, more
adaptable, more accommodating because of your size, you can employ things like VS code pair
programming extensions that would take years to make their way into an enterprise, right?
And that's, I think Malcolm's insight is the older school way of doing things.
This zoom level of quality for remote work, not your version, which is, is much more dynamic.
It's just much more collaborative.
Well, it's also asynchronous by default, right?
That, that, I mean, for me, you know, cause I've gone back and forth on the remote thing,
having to just give up on the idea that things are going to happen at the same time every
day.
Once I made that sort of mental shift, a lot of my, let's say irritation as you know, the
guy who wants the company went away, not expecting like, okay, it's 10 o'clock.
Where the hell is he?
Right?
Like that kind of thing.
There's a downside, right?
And the downside of that is people do get used to it.
And occasionally you're going to have to literally not aggressively, but you're going to have
to do the old fashioned thing of just like call someone on their phone, even though they're
not online, which I don't know why that feels super rude, but I feel like the culture has
changed so much that just out of like calling someone about saying, Hey, you have a minute
for a call feels like super intrusive, but that's, that's like the, the, the, you know,
the emergency move.
Right.
That's right.
Yeah.
That's like a text ahead of time, like, Hey man, you got a second, like that's like, there
must be something wrong.
What is it?
What's wrong?
Right.
Yeah.
That's, that's, I don't know.
I mean, I would also add, and I don't want to hit this too hard, that I think a lot of
this, uh, particularly for one, I think there's probably a generational component here too,
right?
You know, older generations like that are at the top of these large enterprises, basically
boomers, probably it's just a lot of change for them, right?
They've been in, think about this, if you're in your sixties or even early seventies and
these kids today are asked kids today in their forties and thirties are asking you to change
what you've been doing.
It was good for you.
Good for your dad.
I think you'd fight and let's not leave, let's not ignore the Larry Ellison thing here of
ego.
A lot of these guys are, see themselves as like Kings and there's, and it's true that
it certainly is appealing to walk into a place and like, it's your domain, right?
I would, uh, these are all my people everywhere.
These fluorescent lights touch is my kingdom.
I would point you to what does look quite a bit like a penis, the Salesforce tower.
I think I could just leave that one where it is, right?
It's literally their castle.
Yeah.
It's literally something else too, but it's a very phallic castle.
All right.
So Jacob writes in kind of like with the context of, Oh, I think everybody's, everybody's feeling
a little subscription exhausted, but, uh, he says this is probably one of the most thoughtfully
written reason explanations for a transition to subscription model.
He says, I'm also super glad I bought the app early because I'm grandfathered in.
This is a big transition we've been seeing in the Apple ecosystem.
This move to subscription.
And now I think one of the most famous independent apps, one of the most famous modern independent
apps on the Apple platforms is pixel mater.
I don't know if you've ever tried it, but it Photoshop wishes it was this good.
I don't believe that I have, I use something called acorn for that.
And honestly, uh, the GIMP, so, you know, they took a lot of what makes Photoshop great
and they just, they worked on that and then, but they built it in the era of metal and
modern Apple APIs.
So they built something kind of for the Apple Silicon era and it's accelerated throughout.
It's just, it's one of those apps I'd love to have on Linux, but they, they really point
out and you know, this is true.
The core issue is, and they have a great visual they'll have linked in the show notes with
the traditional type of model, your sales are really when you have a big new version
and then you have a massive sales drop off, which will be the length of the development
window and then you have a smaller but noticeable spike in sales when it's when it's time for
an upgrade.
But the revenue is never quite what the original sales was because for most people they're
just buying the upgrade price.
Meanwhile, the baseline cost to run your business, especially these days are always going up.
So the revenue kind of Peters off over time as people buy discounted upgrades.
Meanwhile, base costs going up.
The other thing they point out, and I'm curious to know your thoughts on this specifically.
One of the other issues with the upfront development paid model is they are essentially incentivized
to hold features back to make releases big enough to get people to pay for them.
So they'll sit, they'll hold a feature for a couple of months just to make it, you know,
a good a good set of features that encourage you to upgrade.
They have no way to do discounts via the app store.
This is a classic one, so they have that problem as well.
There's no way to do proper trial on the IOS devices, so, you know, a lot of these typical
issues combined with low price pressure on mobile devices for an app that is now, I don't
know, 10 years old with a team of independent developers working on it full time and they've
been living on one time payments.
They actually make a really solid case for subscriptions.
I have to give it a think, though, because I'm an occasional user when I'm on an iPad.
I do use it on an iPad from time to time.
If I'm on a Mac for more than a couple of days, I generally install it because one of
the things I love about it is the damn thing opens up Photoshop files like a champ.
So it's like, oh, great.
This is an opportunity for me to get, you know, some of my old graphics and get them
out of a Photoshop format, and that's a huge opportunity, and it has a really slick web
support, you know, where you can export files like PNGs and WebPs and JPEGs specifically
encoded for web pages, like it's got a great tool for that.
I just I think it's a really nice tool, but honestly, I use it sparingly once every few
months and the pricing, albeit seeming fair, is five dollars per month or twenty four dollars
per year or fifty five dollars for a lifetime license.
Paging paid users will be grandfathered in for free.
It's pretty good.
It's pretty generous.
I'd like to know what you think.
You know, I think we've been talking about independent app pricing and just generally
making money off software products for 13, 12 years, something like that.
It's been a while.
And unfortunately, this is where we've landed, right?
The predictions we made have come true in weird ways.
I think maybe the aspect of this is they need to make enough money to be sustainable.
And people are not, how can I say, acculturated to spending a hundred, two hundred dollars
on a piece of software once a year anymore.
So you get nickel and dimed with subscriptions, which sometimes cost more, ironically.
I can't see myself launching a product now that wasn't a type of either renewable or
subscription or like an annual license that somehow didn't work once you didn't pay the
license.
Part of that is because a modern piece of software that's going to command any decent
amount of revenue these days almost certainly has some sort of server component, which is
an ongoing cost that you have to maintain.
It probably has integrations with things like Google Work or I guess in this case they must
maintain Photoshop compatibility, right?
Well every time Photoshop in this case changes, I'm sure the Pixelmator folks have to go ahead
and fix it, right?
They got to change their software.
And dozens of other formats, no doubt.
Right.
And if they integrate, I don't know this piece of software, but I know like Alice, for instance,
if when Google decides they're going to pretend like they give a crap about privacy and just
make it ever so slightly harder to refresh auth tokens, they did this like a year ago.
That's just a cost I have to absorb and then like the redeployment for every single instance.
So I get it.
I don't...
I mean, I agree with Jacob that this kind of sucks, but part of a little bit of a devil's
advocate here is the user expectations of everything just kind of working together and
all your stuff being in the cloud, it just makes it more expensive.
I mean, think about...
I always come back to this because I just think it's really funny.
Facebook's bad day where they pissed off Tim Cook, right?
And he just shut down all the internal Facebook iOS apps with the stroke of a key.
That's what's up, right?
That's another form of dependency, another form of maintenance cost.
You have to keep your stuff in compliance with all these third party things now.
Pixelmator, if it's a Mac app, I would bet my hat that it's at least notarized.
If it's on the App Store, it certainly is, right?
So that's, again, got to keep in compliance, got to keep updating to the new OS, if Apple
changes their mind because it's Tuesday and they say it's privacy, but they want to be
the only one to sell ads on iOS, you have to change something potentially.
So I mean, it's tough.
It's tough out there these days.
Yeah.
And it makes me think the subscriptions aren't going away, right?
Because this is a clear advantage for them in a development model.
It's going to make it sustainable and predictable from a revenue standpoint for them.
And so then I start thinking, all right, well, in arguably, the subscription model does make
sense for some types of services and apps and media and whatnot.
So it's like, well, then it seems like the job really falls on me now to just be more
vigilant than I have in any other point in my lifetime about managing my subscriptions
and my family's subscriptions.
Because like Circus Freak points out in our Matrix chat room, you can have family members
like my kids or my mom, I've looked at their subscriptions, thankfully, iOS makes it pretty
easy to review.
And I've seen $99 a year for a video editor that they wanted to use one time for a family
video that they haven't used for six months.
And all kinds of just absolutely outrageous, totally scam subscriptions that I can't believe
Apple lets in.
So they need to be better about that to make the market feel more comfortable about this.
I need to be more vigilant about it because it's easy to get subscription creep.
And then those of us who have a subscription like the QA membership and Jupiter party,
like I've got to always be working to make that subscription more valuable.
You can't just create it and then leave it there.
And that's the lesson I'm internalizing right now.
And it's like, okay, so now we've got a whole other list of projects to just bring more
features to our member feeds because if I'm going to ask for a subscription revenue, I
got to keep it competitive.
I got to keep adding stuff to it.
I got to keep creating value.
And I think that's something that's going to make the difference between the successful
programs and failures and successful developers and failed developers.
One other model that I meant to mention a couple of weeks ago, but I forgot.
So I use OmniGraffle quite a bit, which is like a really pretty Mac, what would you call
it?
A diagramming tool?
Yeah.
Sort of like the Visio Kin, but maybe a little bit easier and not quite as hardcore, maybe.
Not quite as hardcore.
So if you download some of the extensions, it gets wild.
And there's an iPad app, but I generally use it on the Mac because big screen complicated
systems.
Yay.
And they will sell this piece of software to you in one of two ways.
One way is a annual or monthly subscription.
The other way is straight up.
And I've never bought the regular version, I use the pro versions, 250 bucks.
But if you buy the straight up, what happens is to use their kind of cloud syncing system,
you have to subscribe to that.
So what they've effectively done, and I think this is actually...
I was annoyed when I first saw it, but then I'm thinking about it and having a little
empathy as a fellow kind of independent developer.
The cloud service is an ongoing maintenance cost and potential, I guess, they have to
maintain security servers, whatever.
So they're just breaking that out and charging for that.
That's not the craziest thing.
The other thing I should add, if you do the subscription, which they definitely want you
to do, you also get the iOS version.
If you do the traditional, you only get the Mac OS version.
Yeah, I guess I see what you're saying.
Yeah, I also, but I look at those kinds of things and I go, could they have just used
iCloud and then not charged me?
But all right, I'm sure they want to do more things than what iCloud will allow.
And you're right, it is a reasonable revenue stream.
Clearly though, this is a topic that people are still adjusting to.
I'd like to hear your thoughts out there, coder.show slash contact, or boost it in with
a new podcast app, or tell me in person.
The meetups cometh, meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting the West Coast road tour made
possible by Linode.
It is another Linode on the road event.
I just had a call with Linode last week, I think it was Thursday.
There's some new swag that they're going to be including that they haven't really got
out there much because there hasn't been many events.
We have a new shirt design that we're working on for the trip that we'll be giving out.
And then we're also going to do geocaches and we'll stash some of that stuff along the
way.
So even if you can't make it to a meetup but you're in the area, you might be able to find
the geocache.
So we got some fun stuff as well as a matrix room to help coordinate it all.
We'll have links to all of that in the show notes, meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting.
For that, it's coming up real soon now.
Linode.com slash Coder, go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and go there
to support the show.
I love Linode, it's fast, reliable cloud hosting with the best support in the business.
Right there, real humans every day, all day when you need them.
Linode's how we run everything we've built for the last few years.
It's how we are building our new website right now.
Yeah, it's on Linode.
We walk what we talk here.
We really do love hosting everything on Linode.
They are super fast.
They have 11 data centers around the world and they're 30 to 50% cheaper than the hyperscalers
who just want to upsell you and lock you in all the time.
It just is a no brainer.
And on top of all of that, with all of the data centers to choose from, with object storage,
with all of their great features like VLAN support, the ability to provision things using
things like Ansible and Kubernetes, we can deploy infrastructure as we need.
And it has been something to watch this team go.
Our community with Brent and Alex building this website has been incredible.
And the infrastructure they deploy in one day would have taken me a month or two to
deploy just, you know, a few years ago.
You really have to try it out because it just takes your flexibility, your agility, your
reach to a whole other level.
You can play at a level that you would think would cost you thousands of dollars a month
and they have systems that start at $5 a month.
You go to linode.com slash coder and you get a hundred dollar credit on top of that.
I just think it's such a great opportunity to try something, build something, put it
in production for a bit, see how it does.
A hundred dollars, you can really kick the tires.
Go support the show.
Try it out for yourself, linode.com slash coder.
One more time, it's linode.com slash coder.
Oh, it's almost here and I'm not talking about fall.
I'm talking about dot net seven.
And you know, Mr. Dominic, I remember a time when dot net was just brand new.
I really do too.
It's so sad.
When our ASP was like her Coca-Cola classic.
Oh man.
Remember how everything was active for a while?
Active everything.
Yes.
I have wild security holes.
We move forward a little bit, just a little bit forward in time to a dot net seven preview
seven, which came out just a few days ago as we record this here podcast.
Yeah, there's some, there's some good stuff in here.
Couple things of note.
If you are a Xamarin slash Maui developer, you can be really excited to wait.
No dot net seven for you yet because Maui is the project curse in time to constantly
be behind.
I think it's Xamarin.
No, Xamarin is, so it's weird.
So Maui is based on Xamarin.
I think it's Mooey.
Mooey?
I'm sorry.
I don't even, you totally made me lose track.
All right.
Yeah.
So, but there are some good features at dot net seven.
The usual crowing about performance and portability.
Great work, Microsoft.
Nicely done.
Simplified rate limiting.
Rate limiting is, so this is obviously for like the server side stuff, right?
Like ASP.
Rate limiting is a pain in the butt on all platforms.
So simplifying it sounds good.
I looked at the codes and the samples they put up.
Very magical.
We'll see.
I like it.
The one that really got me was this minimal API enhancement section and I put it in quotes
in the doc.
Yeah.
Because basically I guess they have listened to people making fun of C sharp for being
somewhat verbose compared to say your, you know, your pythons of the world.
And they're effectively making the API calls just a lot cleaner and simpler for your API's,
right?
So again, this would be like you're writing a rest service or something like that.
On the back end.
It's boring.
Like if you think about it, it's okay, you have the type of, but I, I found the examples
they gave versus the the old style of doing it very readable and oddly pythonic.
Yes, I'm, I'm using that cause I coined it last week.
I'll take it.
I think this is a great use.
And I don't know.
It made me not want to install windows 11, but Hey, you could.NET's cross platform.
You can open VS code on any platform and do this.
So this is just a preview.
I'm not gonna spend a lot of time on it still, still the thorn in the lion's paw of Microsoft
is God damn Maui.
It's just this thing has been taking so long and it's a crazy ambitious plan, right?
It's a, it's another flavor of right once run everywhere.
But if they actually pull that off and they can actually hit these performance metrics
across platforms with, you know, reasonable variances, that is going to be pretty substantial.
There's a bunch of stuff about blazer too, and this, I don't care about blazer.
I very skeptical of blazer cause you know, anytime you try to avoid JavaScript and HTML
and CSS, you just make more pain for yourself.
Just embrace our JavaScript overlords and move on.
Now don't send any pictures to your kid's pediatrician though.
Oh boy.
Um, that's a little tease.
So before we get there, do you agree with the statement, the areas of Microsoft that
really seem to be executing just continuously for years is this.NET and I would include
just sort of the Linux area in general, the people that are creating some of the tools
that they're releasing as free software, those projects, they're consistently performing
on them, right?
Just for years now, I feel like there is some aspects of Microsoft that are waning and teetering
a bit.
Office.
Yeah.
But this feels like an area that has just remained, just solid performers just executing
nonstop.
You know, I know this isn't the most pro Microsoft audience in the world, but a couple of years
ago they had the goal of we will make.NET platform agnostic and it will be one.NET
and they certainly had some, they had a journey there, right?
We had.NET Core, we had all that crap.
It's basically, if you're using all the modern stuff, it is the.NET standard, which is now
just.NET.
It's, they got it.
The, with the one crazy hook hiccup of Maui, but-
We'll see how 7.0 final goes, but doesn't it feel like they've really hit their stride?
I think if they pull this off, and the reason I keep harping on Maui is because the missing
piece has always been the front end, but at this juncture, I mean, some of the performance
benchmarks that they're claiming, so who knows, in this.NET 7 preview, it's significantly,
it's vast and even compared to like.NET 6.
So if, I don't know, our dark matter devs out there, in five to six years, when you
guys can upgrade to.NET 7, will you be happy?
I mean, I would bet.
I'd like to know.
It feels to me like if these teams continue to execute, the Azure teams continue to execute,
this is Microsoft's game to lose right here.
Google is just really falling apart.
They just don't execute anymore.
We're about to get there, so I'll give more context.
You know, Apple is focused on Swift and their platform, right?
It's a different game they're playing.
Microsoft is playing the entire market game, enterprise, individual developers, independent
open source developers, you know, they have moments where they do things like they suspend
the account of a free software developer who created TornadoCache and everybody goes, ooh,
maybe that's a sign, but that's not really blowing it, right?
Most people said, ah, that's for criminals anyways, who cares, and they moved on without
giving it another thought, unfortunately.
It really feels like this is Microsoft's game to lose at this point.
.NET is just a part of that, but one of their strongest parts of that strategy.
I'm impressed to see it.
Okay, let's talk about this Google thing, because it's what our chat room is talking
about right now as we record, because last night, I think it was, an article came out
in the New York Times about a dad who sent photos from his Android device of his baby's
groin to a doctor, you know, doing like telemedicine, which is becoming super common, and then Google
disabled his account and reported him to the police because their CSAM scanner flagged
him for child porn.
It took about two days after he took the pictures, and then Mark's phone made a notification
noise.
His account had been disabled due to harmful content that was in, quote, a severe violation
of Google's policies and might be illegal.
Then he had a, quote, learn more link that led to a possible list of reasons, you've
seen these Google help pages, I'm sure, and one of the many reasons on the page was, quote,
sexual abuse and exploitation.
It took the dad, Mark, a little bit to even figure it out, because he didn't think of
this right at first, but then he realized, oh God, a couple of days ago, I did take those
pictures and Google probably thinks that was porn.
This led to an investigation into the dad, and I'm not sure, probably by the time this
episode comes out, we'll have some resolution, but as we record, he still doesn't have access
to his Google account, even though he's been cleared by the police, and all he did was
take pictures of his kid with his own device, but because he uses Google Photos and they're
scanning your photos, they detected this, and consider this, too, right?
In this situation, this wasn't a picture that matched a preexisting model out there, right?
These photos were unique.
There was no hash in any law enforcement database for these pictures of his kids growing, and
Google still found them, so they're looking at everyone's stuff, and they're not just
looking for preexisting images, they're looking at each individual picture, all of your stuff,
and they're throwing their various models at it, which appear to be very accurate.
I would say classified as intended, but context matters in these situations, and it just happened
automatically.
All he did wrong was use an Android device, and let's be honest, we know it won't be very
long until this is the same situation on iOS.
It almost was.
It wasn't in this last OS release, and they postponed it.
You and I are both dads, but this just drives me crazy.
Oh, this one, I just a few months ago had a conversation with a friend who, she just
had a child not so long ago, and she's like, oh, I sent a cute picture of him on the bathtub
to my mom.
I said, just do not do that again.
Don't.
And yeah, this is literally the reason why I told her not to do that, right?
I said, you don't understand everything, which then she thought I was a tinfoil maniac, but
yeah, I would say, I mean, I read some of the responses to this, which I thought were
chilling, to be honest with you, that, well, the classifier worked, and there was a human
review, and the human review referred it to the police, who, without saying anything,
started an investigation, pulled all his account information, including apparently some, I
guess, intimate photos of some woman or something, and yeah, that's fine.
He didn't get charged.
So that worked, right?
The system worked.
But think about that.
His entire life was now just on a bunch of San Francisco detectives' desks, or San Diego
detectives.
Well, and this also, these pictures got forwarded to a team internally at Google, and so the
police are looking at his kid's crotch, a team of people at Google are looking at his
kid's crotch, and all he did was telemedicine.
Well, not only that, but they pulled not just the stuff off his phone, they pulled his entire
Google account, emails, possibly text arguments, because the police got a warrant.
By the way, the fact that an automated flag can be used to trigger probable cause for
a hyperinvasive warrant is just...
That then gives them your entire Google account, your search history, all of his location history,
all of his messages, all of his Google Docs were all given over to law enforcement because
of this process, automatically.
And these were not...
So the CSAM promise was that there would be hashed photos that are known to the authorities
to be child pornography.
This was not that, right?
This was using machine learning to basically...
Just like hot dog, not hot dog, right, Silicon Valley from the HBO show.
So there are more...
Now it's hard because you can't say, well, don't police this, but this kind of seems
like a wild overreach.
It's chilling the more we talk about it.
It's just absolutely chilling because an accidental triggering of this process then invokes a
discovery process which could find all kinds of things potentially that you never thought
would be public.
And I don't know, it's just, this is super chilling.
This feels like a deal breaker for me, I have to be honest with you.
Google Photos is such a remarkable product, but my God, and there's so much other metadata
in those photos, including the faces of your family.
Like I have a family member who's never been on social media ever.
He's just, his late 60s never has ever created...
I don't even know if he has a Google account.
I know he has a Microsoft account, but I don't know if he has a Google account.
And so in theory, he would have no social media footprint except for family members
have taken pictures of him and put them on social media and we've uploaded them to our
Google Photos and tagged his name and we, on the backend, Google can build a network
of all of the different people who have that person's face in their photo library.
Well, the interesting thing was in this case, just to bring it just particularly, well,
the police cleared him and said it was a misunderstanding.
So good on the police for not just like, I mean, I'm sure this guy was horrified, right?
Because you've got the full weight of the government and you're accused of something
heinous.
So it's...
Could you imagine, could you imagine how wrecked his life was for a period of time?
Oh yeah.
Persona and Agrata, right?
But Google still wouldn't give him his account back.
Right.
It just destroyed all his data.
Yeah.
So what do you do?
Because the other problem is, is like, what happens if your kid does this?
You know, that your kids are screwing around.
I had a situation, I can't remember if I'd mentioned it on the show or not, but my daughter
recently was looped in because her watch has a phone number and she was looped in to a
text message thread with other kids in her school during summer break about causing harm
to another student.
My red alert alarm goes off immediately, like now she's involved in a text message thread
where kids are joking about causing harm to another student and all my daughter did was
just get automatically looped in and they just won't stop and they won't stop and you
know, of course it gets reported.
And that kind of stuff could also just automatically get scanned and flagged.
And it just feels like there's so many ways to accidentally get drawn in to where now
your entire account contents get handed over.
And the only way to really kind of prevent this sort of thing is to opt out of the legitimately
nice to have features like Google Maps, because they also gave us the entire location history
and Google Photos and your photos are for some of us the most precious thing we own.
So there's another version of this.
Oddly enough, I think it was the Wall Street Journal that published this story.
The IRS in that new wonderful bill that everybody's so excited about is putting aside a ton of
money for machine learning and social media analysis to try to catch tax cheats.
But what is a tax sheet?
What if let's say your grandma dies or you know, you inherit some money and you like
buy a car.
Same thing.
Well, this is an anomalous thing.
You said you only made, you know, $30,000.
How did you buy that, whatever, right, just Chevy, who cares?
That's where we're going with this.
Everything is going to be analyzed against some model.
I mean, I could think about how to write this model right now.
Okay, I have a single dad who makes, you know, say $100,000 or claims to make 50.
He lives in this zip code, average cost of living plus incidentals.
He should have this type of profile on let's say, Insta, Facebook, whatever.
Oh, this dude looks like he's more in that hundred, 105, 110 bracket than 50.
Look at this picture of a Tesla.
You know, we've identified a Tesla in this guy's photo feed.
And you could automate this.
Let's trigger, because if you've ever been audited, they start with a paper audit, right?
They just say, show us documentation.
And then they escalate up to a real audit and then a potentially criminal charge.
That seems real scary.
I'm just saying.
And we've privatized it.
We've privatized it.
It's going to be contracted out, right?
This is the most beautiful thing about it is all this information.
It's all packaged up and beautifully delivered to the state automatically through this process.
But it wasn't the state that collected the information, right?
It's so beautiful.
It's just both parties get to wipe their hands of any responsibility there.
I did my part.
Oh, I'm doing my part.
So the same law and the reason I'm dunking on this law is because I'm not trying to be
political, I'm just saying there's a lot of bad in this law.
Welcome to unfiltered.
Someone in Congress decided maybe it would be a good idea if the Defense Department,
who isn't supposed to spy on American citizens, certainly not in the country, would have to
disclose when they purchased the data from data brokers of American citizens.
What an idea.
The fact that they're routinely doing that, we didn't break the Fourth Amendment.
I don't know how the hell they got the data, but we didn't break the Fourth Amendment.
Right.
They got the product from a private organization.
Hey, they're a contractor.
They went through the whole vetting process.
They're in the, they have an, what is it, the NIA, I forgot the code, but the government
classification code.
So that's fine, right?
It's totally cool.
What Fourth Amendment?
By the way, you know who was already doing that?
The IRS.
Now they want to automate it further and do it themselves with machine learning.
Can I just say that this is what happens when people learn about this crap that Google's
doing and Apple will be doing soon and Microsoft too, I'm sure, if not already.
This is, this is, this is like you're two steps away from like this conversation we're
having now.
This is what happens because you start to realize, holy crap, this entire system is
just designed to really take advantage of me if I make one mistake and I can't help
but think the only thing one can do, and yet I'm not doing it, even though I try, the only
thing you can do is not participate.
Go listen to self-hosted.
I just, just one last point on this and then we probably should move off the unfiltered
stuff.
They, they justified all of this crap, all of this crap that it's now evolved into with
two main things.
The classic, but think of the children, which I'm sympathetic to, but they didn't stop at,
you know, protecting children and goddamn 9 11.
If you, if you were to take a guy from, let's say the seventies, even at the height of protest
and tell him how much surveillance is just routinely done in a mass way on American citizens,
they probably wouldn't believe you because that sounds a lot like, ah, the Soviet Union.
My last thing on this is really shame on Google because yet another tool they've built that
is hostile to the user and pro establishment and I, what I mean by that is they could have
built this thing where maybe the offender is presumed innocent and maybe there is a
little bit more of a check and balances before like the kid's crotch is showed to a team
of people at different agencies.
Maybe the per maybe the person could be presumed innocent, but they never do that.
Same with YouTube, right?
This episode will get flagged.
Every single live stream does.
I didn't play anything copyrighted, but it will get, I've had my own voice.
I've literally had my voice in the intros get flagged.
They assume I'm guilty by default.
All their tooling always does.
They assume I'm in the wrong.
They're minimizing their legal liability.
It gets to the core of these giant mega rich corporations that have dumped on the market
to get incredible market share have never built out the support department that even
comes even just a tiny percentage, a tiny fraction of the size of their actual user
base.
They're trying to become Kings without having any support.
And so you get a situation where this guy, this guy might get his account back now that
the New York fricking times wrote about it, but otherwise he'd be SOL.
He's not.
So Google, it's just their policy.
There've been, according to the reporter in the times there is have, she was on Twitter
elaborating.
They're having other cases, it almost exactly like this.
And Google's policy is once you're flagged, you're flagged.
Well, of course this isn't the first one.
Of course this isn't my God.
I wonder how many other lives they've completely destroyed with this.
What if it was his Google work account, just like take his whole business offline.
What if the guy was in the process of a divorce, right?
And his ex wife tried to leverage this against him during the divorce proceedings.
Like, what if this, I mean, imagine if this kind of investigation leaked public for somebody
who's, you know, in a, in a public position or something like just, it could destroy someone's
life or career.
It would destroy his life.
And we're just not even hearing about it.
And they, all of these, all these systems just assume that the person is guilty by default
because it's the least amount of work.
It's the least amount of cost.
It's the least amount of friction with law enforcement policy.
And it doesn't require a support department.
We're the product, right?
We are the product, not the customer.
But I sure can't wait for that new pixel.
All right, and, and by the way, if you don't, we've been pretty harshing on Google.
If you don't think Apple and Microsoft do stuff like this, Apple to a lesser degree,
but they're going to, Google's probably just the best at it.
And Facebook, Facebook's already doing this at large scale.
Yeah.
But if you pay in rubles, you're fine.
Tailscale.com slash coder.
Tailscale is a zero config VPN and installs on any device in minutes and it manages your
firewall rules, it'll take care of your double nets and your devices connect directly to
each other using a mesh network protected by a WireGuard's noise protocol.
That's it right there.
That's the concept, but it is a game changer.
And I, I don't know, I don't think, uh, I don't think I know the term cause I was never
really into like a band before they got popular, but that's how I feel with Tailscale right
now.
So I think you know what I mean, right?
Like I feel like I was into Tailscale just a little bit before it got popular and now
I see folks talking about the way Tailscale changes the way they work all the time.
And I'm like, yeah, I know, I know, I've been telling people about it.
I hope they went to tailscale.com slash coder.
I don't know, but you can, you can support the show and you can try it out.
Tailscale allows you to build a flat network protected by WireGuard's noise protocol.
And it even supports DNS.
So if you want to throw a DNS server in that flat network, you can start resolving machines
by their name.
They've also recently introduced Tailscale SSH, which allows you to establish an SSH
connection between your devices on the Tailscale network and you can control access with the
built in ACL controls in Tailscale.
You don't have to manage SSH keys and you can authenticate the SSH connection using
WireGuard.
The whole thing is mind blowing.
I'm going to play with it this weekend, get everything all ready for the road trip coming
up because I've already got all my devices in Tailscale.
So yeah, I'm going to take advantage of this.
I use Tailscale to maintain my kids computers, my friends, my family and my work systems.
It's so great because you can also share a single node with somebody and I find that
really useful, really super useful.
And I've just no longer have any inbound ports on my firewalls.
I've just turned them all off.
They're all off now, guys, guys, no inbound traffic at all.
That's the way it should be.
Tailscale made that possible.
Just a game changer, game changer.
You want your, you want your game changed?
You want to know what that actually means?
People say it all the time.
What does it actually mean?
Go find out.
Tailscale.com slash coder.
I mean it.
I love it.
Tailscale.com slash coder.
Well let's talk about a little development.
I don't know, maybe some programming, something related to coding because I need to change
the subject.
Okay.
So are we coding a bunker?
No.
So, so I have been for a while now using Ionic again, which for folks who don't know, Ionic
is a cross-platform mobile webby framework, I want to say.
It's really more of a collection of stuff, but that focuses on web-based mobile development.
There's three flavors of it, React, Vue, and the good one, Angular.
So I'm of course using Angular because I am not a heathen nor a Facebook fan.
And I'd just like to talk about it a little bit because it's pretty cool.
It is totally TypeScript-y, a lot of really cool native plugins.
If you've ever done PhoneGap development, God rest its soul.
Oh yeah.
You know that PhoneGap became Cordova and the folks at Ionic have come out with an open
source project called Capacitor, which is compatible with Cordova, but in many ways
better, mostly in the ways of performance.
It is really neat.
This kind of development methodology of doing basically web views, but having hooks into
native APIs and into native hardware functionality is so much better.
If you did this like five years ago, it was pretty jank, but today it is so good.
I mean, I was surprised I was able to get Bluetooth connections working easily.
I was able to write a small custom thing for a scanner.
So low level stuff.
Low level stuff, as long as the lords of Cupertino actually allow it natively.
Yeah, of course.
And then you have to write a TypeScript wrapper, or it could be JavaScript, right, and hook
it in and register the component.
If you've done Angular before, same kind of idea, just Capacitor.
If you've ever done like extension development or even like a mod for a game or like Minecraft,
it's the same idea of you write your little thing, you put it in, you got to register
it with the application, rebuild the whole thing so it builds it in and huzzah.
So they're taking this a step further.
And I think they have two things that are interesting, AppFlow, which I'm currently
doing a trial of.
It's kind of a build in the cloud solution for all your horrific code signing needs.
I have some feelings about it.
One thing that I do like is if you have a very small, only HTML, JavaScript, CSS change,
you can actually deploy that without going through the App Store.
Are they creating build environments for you?
Yeah, that's what they're doing.
Yeah.
You still have to upload like a signing key.
But once you upload it, you know, the keys expire, I think like once a year, something
like that.
Wow, the infrastructure to do that must be super impressive.
Well, they're also charging for it, right?
Of course, I bet.
The bill is not that bad, actually.
But it was big enough that it's something I actually had to think about right before
I like, ah, sure.
So the deal with this is if it's just a web change, you can basically deploy it.
Now, you have to comply with Apple's rules.
So there's some gray area of like, how big of a change is it?
But for all, like, if it's a, oh, my God, we had a typo on our about page, something
like that, right in our app, you can change it.
Anything that needs a native integration, unfortunately, has to go through the App Store.
They also support, which I thought was really interesting, using this AppFlow system as
basically your own little private test flight, but like the old test flight, where you just
have like your client or your small internal team.
And you're sending bills or just updating the build for the tester silently on the app.
That is super cool.
I can't tell you how many Trello tickets or back in the bad old days, Jira tickets, I've
had open.
And after like an hour of walking through on the phone with the dude, it was like, hey,
man, did you get the build from like three days ago?
Oh, no, I'm on the old build.
Sorry, man.
Yeah, dude.
Well, we changed the API.
So you got to, you know, whatever, whatever, whatever, right?
So that's just freaking peachy.
The other thing I'm just starting to evaluate that I have kind of, I have some fee-fees
about portals.
They call it portals.
So I'm just going to read their little press clipping.
Micro front ends for mobile portals.
Micro front ends allow multiple teams to build, test and ship in parallel with hyper focused
embedded web experience in your React native Android or iOS apps.
So basically, let's say you have an iOS team, an Android team, you have a basically native
app, right, more or less, but you just want some stupid like checkout views or, you know,
some kind of registration view and you want it to be uniform and you want to spend a lot
of time developing it twice.
You could just develop it in one of these portal web views, install this portal SDK
and it would be taken by either platform and intelligently remapped to the default type
of controls.
Oh, man, that sounds like the promised land.
Well, it reminds me of those, what did Google call them?
Like the little applets?
I know it wasn't applets, but you didn't have to download the whole app kind of thing.
Yeah.
Like this, like the snap apps.
Snap app.
Yeah.
Is that what it was?
I know both Apple and Google were experimenting with this, but Google was first.
I can't remember.
I never really, I've seen like a couple of them, but like they're app sheets essentially.
App sheets.
No, I think it was sheets.
I think it was called sheets.
So the interesting thing about this is you can apparently, and I've done some testing,
it seems to work, use capacitor plugins in the portal view, even if the Xcode project
is not built for capacitor.
So even if you're golden Mac book, drinking tea out of a bowl, Swift developers have no
idea and will not add that filthy, filthy capacitor dot framework to their project.
Of course.
You don't need their permission anymore.
Tell them, put your feet off the desk, stop it hippie, we'll do this on the web.
I like that.
I still firmly believe that the web technologies are going to consume everything much like
the Borg.
What I don't buy right now is that Apple is not going to stop this because it seems in
theory that you could tie these two things together and implement functionality after
you've passed app review that would have not been reviewed.
And I guess if it's significant enough would technically violate the terms.
I could totally see what you're saying, but it feels like that ship has sailed.
There are so many apps now where even the settings pane, they're all web views, but
you don't even really know.
In fact, like the whole Uber UI, both for eats and the app, they can add and remove
elements from the UI on the backend.
I think Marco does this with overcast as well, as well as other apps, obviously here's a
couple of web views.
So it kind of feels like that ship has sailed already.
Like there's no going back now, but this has taken it to whole other levels.
I could see what you're saying, but well, one ionic is not super huge, right?
So will Apple notice and my impression of kind of chatting with the community on their
forums is ionic is really, really loved by like people like me, right?
People who develop internal line of business apps for other companies.
I am very tempted because I need an app that can scan my magic, the gathering cards and
put them in an inventory for me, of course, which obviously needs to be updated all the
time and it needs deep native integration, right?
And it needs to be highly secure.
I'm talking end to end encryption here.
Oh my God.
You don't get to know how many, how many dark rituals I did today and they were dark, Chris.
Google knows and the FBI is on their way, but yeah, you took a photo with your Android
phone so they know.
I took a photo of a hot dog and Google made a horrible, horrible mistake.
That model needed a little more training.
You know what?
That's not funny.
That poor bastard has, I'm sorry.
I went backwards with that poor bastard.
Wow.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I think this kind of thing is the future.
Like you asked me about Maui.
Every time someone wants to bet against the web, they basically just get B slapped.
Yeah.
Why wouldn't it be the web?
Didn't NASA just send up something that was, you know, like rust and C plus plus under
the hood, but the front end was basically react JS.
And when does the absolutely best technology win?
You know, when does that happen?
Like I'm not saying this web stuff isn't the best technology, but you might argue like
the native applications using native controls.
That's the best.
It's okay for iOS users, but you know, when does that ever win?
The general computing platform always wins.
It always does because that's the one everybody can write to.
It's the one everybody gets access to.
It's the most accessible.
It's the great, it's the great neutralizer.
Well also like, you know, VHS beat beta, right?
It's a little skewed and I'd be curious for people who are doing more consumer facing
applications because in my little corner of the world, like double native, are you doing
a Kotlin app or Java app and a, you know, I guess Swift could be Objective-C though
app isn't going to happen.
No one's paying.
No, no project manager or product manager is going to authorize, you know, a six figure
budget for their internal one app.
They may authorize stuff like that for like an entire suite of apps with a backing, you
know, backend service and databases and blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
I don't know.
Like all of my customers are, you know, the non-Alice ones, right?
The ones who are doing like mobile projects.
It's all this web stuff, either that or it's like Xamarin.
And I, and God damn it, Chris, just, you know, I'm already sad because, you know, I started
the morning on Twitter, morning sun yet again.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
You thought we'd get away with not mentioning the death of our dearly departed son, Sun
Microsystems.
I felt the need to correct that before I got the email or to be, Oh my God, your son died.
No, not my son, the son, son, Java Duke.
So I don't know.
I'd be, I'd be curious to hear from you, those of you who are riding that Marco train and
trying to do like a very tasteful, thoughtful direct to consumer apps.
Does it have to be Swift?
Does it have to be Kotlin?
Although I've seen Android apps and you guys are not doing great.
Can it be a web app?
Am I wrong?
Am I too deep in the dark matter developer, enterprising crap?
I'd like to know.
Coder dot show slash contact or boosted in with a new podcasting app.
So let's get through a couple of these cause it's just about the end of the show.
And so something that we're doing on the other shows, we'll eventually be doing it here on
Coder too, as we've set a 2000 sat limit to get on the show.
And then going forward, we may make further adjustments, but I wanted to say something
really briefly, even though I know we're going kind of long, the boosts represent a fundamental
paradigm shift for podcasting super quickly.
If you're a YouTuber and you make content on YouTube that the algorithm likes and promotes,
there's a built in path to revenue.
It's a captured path where you're dancing for the algorithm, but there's a built in
way to monetize.
There's a model for YouTube.
There's no model.
There's no built in path for podcasting.
So every podcaster comes up with their own bespoke approach to try to monetize and make
revenue so that way they can do their passion.
And whenever you get serious about something, you need to do it full time because of the
amount of focus and attention it requires.
And what you're seeing right now is podcasters are flocking to dynamically inserted ads.
I got a note from Optimus Gray who said he was listening to an English spoken podcast
and he got a dynamically inserted ad in Spanish and they're just never really a great fit
for the show.
We're also seeing a massive consolidation with Spotify, Apple, Google, and Libsyn who
are trying to centralize podcast advertising and drive their rates way down, which is also
going to starve the podcast industry.
And podcasters are acquiescing to these pressures because there is no model to follow.
There is no real light at the end of the tunnel.
You have to create your business from whole cloth.
And so the issue with all of these platforms, Libsyn, Spotify, Apple, Google, is the incentive
is to please the platform provider and operator, their algorithm or whatever they have, not
the audience.
The audience isn't the customer.
Boosts represent a fundamental shift for podcasting because it is a truly, and I mean truly on
the technical sense, a truly decentralized no middleman network that's all based on free
software that's built into the podcast app that specifically rewards the creator when
they create something of value that the audience enjoys.
So it's a fundamentally structured incentive system tilted towards the audience because
the creator gets rewarded when the audience creates good content for them.
Not for the algorithm, not for Spotify's front page, but for the audience.
And Boosts represent the first time in 15 years of podcasting that there could actually
be a built-in path to revenue for podcast that rewards content creators based on the
quality of their content with no middlemen taking a skiff, tilting the wheels of content.
It's a massive fundamental shift.
So we are trying to figure out how to incorporate them in a way that doesn't like, you know,
add 20 minutes to the show.
But at the same time, they represent possibly a savior to the medium that is undergoing
right now extreme centralization pressures that I don't go on about as much as I probably
should because of the existential threat, but I know how much it drives everybody crazy
and I just try to contain that in office hours.
But that is the context in which we find ourselves in the Boost era.
And so your support via memberships and your support via Boosts are building a pathway
that I'm not even exaggerating, this is not overstating the situation, could literally
save independent podcasting.
So with that, let's read a couple of these before we get out of here.
And I want to start with our over 9,000 Boost from Bronzewig.
With 9001 sats Chris and Mike, I wonder what you guys think about this Android initiative
and I took a look at it.
And Google is going all in on green versus blue bubbles, they've produced a video to
shame Apple even the green bubble versus the blue bubble.
Why is this a thing?
See, Apple uses SMS and MMS.
You remember that technology from the 90s?
Anytime their customers want to communicate with someone outside Apple sphere, limiting
them to low res video, no encryption and no red receipts.
You know that that old tech from the 90s and the whole thing.
It's this whole this whole pitch to shame to have the the public shame Apple to fix
their texting.
Ironically, though, it seems to be backfiring a bit because people don't like RCS that have
gotten it.
This is dumb.
I mean, you know, it's a competitive market.
I message is really, really good.
I know people don't like it when I say that.
You know what I like about it?
I message bypasses the carriers.
Yep, that's what's good about it.
That's why it's better.
RCS is dependent on the carriers.
And I'm sorry, I that's just not a solution.
I think that's better for the market.
Yeah, they're not the most innovative fast moving lot over there at the carriers.
Yeah.
So I don't know.
I think this is sour grapes.
I get why they're doing it.
I message lock in and we've gotten the emails I don't want to jump into the whole blue green
bubbles thing again.
Yeah, you know, I message lock in a strong it's a problem because like I will be buying
an iPhone every two years for the rest of my life now.
I agree.
And can I be ignorant now this next boost is to educate myself user 77 nine probably
need to set your username and fountain they boosted in with 2022 sats and this is me being
completely ignorant.
I've never I've never used a computer sold out of the EU I've never used you know I don't
know this but he says the EU is glorious.
You get four spaces in Python two in JavaScript.
Is there some is spacing done differently in the EU than it is in the States?
Is this is this a thing?
What is he talking about?
I think he's just saying the EU is glorious because we kept dunking on it last week.
You're right.
They're two separate things.
Two separate things.
Okay.
So you're Yeah, well you have to use Yeah.
All right.
Good on you.
You should post your VM RC.
I wasn't even gonna read the part about them.
I'm so sick of hearing about them.
So let's see Chris Chris is an e-max user.
That's all that tells you one thing that hasn't come up and the whole VIM discussion.
I don't think oh maybe it did but I'm just reiterating because I think this is the most
important point.
Don't do it.
The value in learning VIM is those key bindings are everywhere.
You know like our even our hedge doc our collaborative markdown.
You can put it in you can put it in VIM mode and you can use the I key bindings to move
around the dock.
It's just everywhere.
Right.
It's like the M1 Mac.
It's the obvious better product.
Yeah.
Okay.
Oh Kyron aka lower third boosted in with a row of ducks.
And he says following up on the we asked him remember he said it's a real Mario and Luigi
situation which I forgot that I wanted to steal that and use that so this was a nice
reminder.
Nice.
He says to try and describe what a Mario and Luigi situation would actually really put
me in a real Mario and Luigi situation.
It's not nefarious but it sure is something.
Keep up the good work.
And here is an honorable mention for Sun Microsystems and Java Duke gone but never forgotten.
Certainly not on this show.
Every week.
We're we're more.
Yeah.
We're keeping it alive man.
We're keeping it alive.
All right.
And then a baller here in our parts CB boosted in on like a boosting rampage that I'm a big
fan of with forty three thousand seven hundred and seventy sats because I'm a back home baller
if I want something I just holler.
He says several months ago the company I've worked for had completely stalled out.
There was no sales no money coming in and no paycheck.
I've worked at this job for nearly a decade as a senior lead developer for the last five
years.
In that time I managed to exercise everything Microsoft from the company.
The previous senior dev had written a good portion of the software in C sharp targeting
Windows which is crazy when you realize we make computer vision based software.
So I got rid of everything Microsoft 100 percent Linux after I was done.
He continues with another five thousand seven hundred and fourteen sats.
So I'm now out of a job been firing off my CV like mad with zero replies.
I took Mike's advice for a few months and I kind of took a grassroots approach contacted
local companies.
I got me a few interviews but no job.
All right.
Well that's that's some good progress right there.
I like that that's the Mike recommendation.
I completely agree with that.
Go go with the local companies.
Start there.
Yeah.
He says the only company that gave me an offer is a pure Microsoft shop.
I'm talking Windows, Teams, Outlook, Visual Studio, Sharp, Azure, Azure DevOps.
I had a minor extensional crisis when I found all this out.
Did I commit some sort of genocide in a past life to deserve this?
I'm also surprised I didn't get any other offers.
I feel as though there's only a few senior roles available but I'm quote overqualified
for most regular dev roles.
We just had our boy.
My wife is out on maternity leave so it's the worst possible time to be without income.
I have a job now but with a huge Microsoft catch.
I guess this is a challenge to my ideals.
Do you stand your ground or do you feed your family?
Well I'm feeding my family but at least I use Linux at home.
You know I think CB, God I know this is easy for me to say but if I was in your position
I think I would try to take this as an opportunity to just live the Microsoft life for a while.
When I was acquired by Linux Academy, can you imagine that change from going from like
a small team of four or five in a tiny little small LLC to then joining a company of hundreds
of people that had VC funding that was growing like crazy and so I had to just have a mind
shift.
I went this isn't what I envisioned but this is also an opportunity for me to get reacquainted
with this world and I learned so much with that mindset and I think I'm better at the
independent thing now because of it just like I think you might be better at the Linux thing
after you've really lived the other way for a while so you truly understand what it's
good and bad at and then you can approach it from a real honest angle which is really
what's going to be valuable in the market.
For sure yeah and congrats on the baby boy.
The other thing is if you actually do this for a couple years you can now pitch yourself
to whatever your next gig is your next job is as I'm a Microsoft expert I'm a Linux expert
and you can basically be the guy who can bridge those two worlds and there are a lot of places
because Microsoft is just giving you those Azure credits man they're just the first 20
hits are free.
I have a feeling if you can just meditate on you know the glory that is vBasic I know
you're doing C sharp but I thought it was funny for a couple years you're probably going
to be in a super strong position and you're plus your little boy is going to need a lot
of food.
Yeah they get they just eat more they just eat more and more.
And my understanding of as a divorce man I can tell you wives do not like it when there's
no money.
That's true too that is that is also true CB had to also come in with 2000 sats just
to kind of.
This is where it loses me.
Yeah.
I want to give my thoughts on Orville I think it does well because it is a TNG clone every
other new show nowadays is always trying to be like the big reveal a big twist generate
social media buzz drive engagement etc.
The Orville is predictable straightforward cookie cutter based stories and I love it.
It's bright it's colorful the characters the characters are passionate and positive and
look out for each other.
They get excited about things like first contact.
I agree with some of that I saw this boost last night when I was preparing the show and
I thought all right honey let's watch some Orville.
And so I watched the episode where their federation is trying to strike an alliance with a patriarchal
arcal society that hates men.
And so they have the captain and all of the men pretend like they just do grunt work.
And so for 45 minutes of the show they lie to this other species about the role of men
in there in the human society and the entire time you're just smacking your forehead going
why are they lying to them.
How is this treaty treaty going to work if they sign the treaty and then there's a big
reveal that surprise actually men have a role in society.
How is this going to work.
And I'm just the entire time like this doesn't make any sense.
This is clearly not going to work.
And now that episode still has really good moments in it.
But every single time I watch the Orville I go to my I'm saying out loud like this doesn't
make any sense or like they do things that are really kind of dark like the doctor pressures
the robot into changing himself and it's twisted.
And it's like if you take yourself out of the character it's it's a twisted dark thing
to watch.
I'm just constantly I have that experience when I watch the Orville.
I have yet to watch it.
I did watch I started to watch the first episode seemed OK but I will put this on my list.
I mean I'm watching it slowly.
It is there are I say also good moments in the show and as the seasons go on it gets
better.
Every time with the Orville the first few episodes of the season I'm a little shaky
on and by the end of the season I'm like oh I'd like some more of that.
That's how it goes every single time we're discovery it's the opposite first couple episodes
of the season.
I'm like OK you got me midway or by the end I'm like this damn show.
These were who the hell writes this thing right.
They lose me.
So at least it has that he goes on to CB goes on to say with another 2001 sets the Orville
isn't perfect but it was the best until strange new worlds came along.
I like both shows and that's allowed right.
Yeah I think that is allowed.
And then our last boost just came in from George or banks with four thousand four hundred
and forty four sets.
Here's how it goes.
Hey hey hey you've got to pay more stats if you're going to infringe on my copyright.
I know right.
Hey I know.
Actually George or is pretty funny too is pretty good though I like it.
Star Wars then the Orville then Star Trek.
Fight me Trekkies.
Yeah.
I like that.
I would reverse that.
What are you doing.
You got a minute.
I'm going to take this guy Mr. Quackers boosted with a row of ducks saying thanks.
Cospe and also boosted in and asked if we've tried to Google's GitHub alternative which
I have to admit I have no because they're going to kill my next show bother or like
to.
Yeah.
Or they'll have me arrested for writing some book.
I don't know.
Oh yeah.
That's the dark twist now.
There's always that you're you know you take the wrong picture and oh God I would get so
screwed if my business account got actually because I know you put this on YouTube.
It was totally the right decision to kill ways and reader and I apologize for ever criticizing
Google.
Oh no.
Oh God.
I hope they don't kill ways.
Don't say that.
They already killed ways.
No.
Oh I'm thinking wave.
It's so dead.
I can't remember the name anymore.
Yeah.
The traumas inflicted on us by a company that pretends to be a kindergarten but is really
a billion multi-billion dollar behemoth.
But they've got rainbow colors in their logo.
And there'll be really nice to you if they invite you to their Chelsea office and let
you play with Legos and give you lots and lots of coffee.
They put socially accurate and I'd say prescient art on their website.
So they've got to be good.
By the way my new TV is a Google TV and I'm very aware that it is definitely listening
to my son be extremely aggressive in Mario Tennis.
All right.
If you'd like to send us a boost go get a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com.
I like Fountain.
They're building in Podverse into our website.
It's great.
Castamatic is fantastic as well.
They all work.
You just need one.
You can also just grab Breeze and not even not even switch podcast apps.
It's all listed newpodcastapps.com.
Mr. Dominic is there anywhere you'd like to send the good people before it gets?
Of course.
I'd like to send everyone to at Duminico on Twitter and for George Roribinx may the light
of Kalish sends you on a better path.
Yeah.
You know what.
I like invoking the name of Kalish on people upon people right.
It works really well at the bank too.
They love it.
Well the wrath of Kalish be upon your head and your family.
Sir this is a Wendy's.
All right.
Links to what we talked about today are at coder.show slash 4 8 0.
We do the show live on Jupiter dot tube on Mondays.
We're doing it now at 9 a.m.
Pacific noon Eastern New Time.
Come see how it fits.
Try it.
Try it on.
It fits.
Also you can join our matrix coder dot show slash matrix that'll take you to our room
and of course our contact form coder dot show slash contact.
Your feedback is a big part of the show.
We'd love to hear from you and a big huge thank you to our coder QA team and our Jupiter
party members for keeping us independent.
We appreciate you.
Thanks for joining us on this week's episode of Coder Radio.
Be right back here next week.