This is KOTOR Radio, episode 435 for October 11th, 2021.
Hello friends, welcome to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
This episode is brought to you by a cloud guru.
You know, they have that cloud playground, Azure, AWS, or Google cloud sandboxes on ACG's
credit card, not yours.
Get certified, get hired, get learning at a cloud guru.com.
My name is Chris and joining us every single week is the man who's been burning the midnight
oil, but taking a nap before the show.
It's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello, Mike.
Hello, Mr. Fisher.
I like this employment of the nap strategy.
So you know, you know, you got to be fresh for the show.
I mean, that's like pro move.
It's pro.
I'm impressed.
You know, I just came out of the woods this morning, I went in for my reading weekend,
and I only got through a book and a half didn't really work out the way I wanted.
But it was still really enjoyable.
I was I was actually looking forward to hearing about that.
I enjoyed it a lot.
And I think the concept is sound.
I just need to clear my schedule a little bit more, I guess, because I ended up having
to drive in and you know, the whole thing.
But I still really enjoyed the time I did get out there.
Oh, the other thing that was kind of funny is I'm used to going out there and it just
being no one around for like miles.
But I guess it's like salmon season right now in the Pacific Northwest.
So all the fishermen were out in the woods, like finding the good fishing spots along
the riverbed and and then, you know, they drink while they fish all day.
And then when the sun sets, they load up in their trucks and they go bombing through the
woods, running into crap and driving 35 miles per hour, having a good old time, blasting
their music in the dark.
And it was quite the experience.
So I learned pretty quickly, like when when the sun sets, I'm going to get inside for
a bit, let the fishermen clear out, let them have their time.
But I came out of the woods and I saw a pretty big announcement from you.
It's like it's here.
It's real.
And we're going to talk about it today.
I don't know how much you want to say now, but it seems like a pretty big congratulations
is in order.
Thank you.
Yes.
So finally, finally, after 5000 years, Alice is at a one point state launched to do.
If you've noticed the Python content, she's in Python.
Yeah, I mean, I know we have some more stuff on it, but yeah, basically it's a Rosetta
stone for data.
So it's like, you know, I've been trying to do these automation things for a while.
I found that dealing with people's proprietary data from like whatever insane system that
somebody built for them and, you know, the odds, the early odds was always like the problem.
So what she does, I call it universal data fluency, which it's really catchy for like
the PM types.
So if you're a PM and you like it, thank you.
Where she can analyze data, compare it to known data types and try to understand it
based on what she already knows.
Obviously the idea is as I introduce more integrations, more types of data, she learns
more stuff, more, learns more stuff, right?
Yeah.
So we'll probably talk more about that in a little bit.
Thank you.
Well, congratulations again.
Yes, we will.
We're definitely going to talk more about that, but we had a couple of emails come in
that we felt like, ah, we got to answer these.
So we're going to, we're going to stick to the format for a bit and there's also some
hoopla, but then we're, we're going to dive in.
So stick around for that.
First, let's start with Ethan.
Ethan kind of feels, I think like he's run out of time.
He says, Hey guys, I'm riding in because I'm facing a bit of a dilemma.
I'm a computer science student trying to get a job before I graduate.
However, I don't have any on the job experience.
I've been trying for internships, but in this last year of school, it looks like all of
them are booked out until summer of 2022.
I feel like my skills are diverse, but I'm trying to find a job for either positions
that I could possibly work in, which would be an embedded systems programmer or perhaps
an OS developer.
I just don't necessarily have all the skills yet.
I have been working on a operating system as a side project and I have tried applying
for some dev ops internships.
However, nothing's really clicked.
I've had some projects stall because of various bugs involving something that come up or maybe
something just doesn't work out.
I know a few different programming languages, including C++, Python, Go and Rust.
I have some sys admin experience for both Linux and windows, and I have a bit of database
experience, but I don't really understand what the majority of the jobs I find.
Seem to require like automation skill sets like SaltStack or Kubernetes or Ansible.
At this point, I'm just not really sure where to start looking or even if I'm looking in
the right place.
Overall, I'm wondering if my skills are the right skills for the kind of jobs I want,
if I'm looking in the right place, if I should just go for internships in 2022, if there's
something I'm overlooking, any advice you guys could offer, I'd appreciate.
And the email is kind of all over the place, Mike, and I read through it and before the
show and the vibe I got from this was he's sort of a jack of all trades, master of none
kind of guy, and he's also not really following through like he's got two projects that he's
put on the shelf because like a roadblock was encountered and he kind of just ran out
of steam on them.
And it kind of seems like he's just all over the place with the skill sets.
And I think maybe that's his core issue.
What are your thoughts?
Yeah, I mean, a little bit of focus on that might make it a little easier to, I hate the
word marketable when it comes to people, but I think that's the right word here, right?
To be a little more marketable.
This is almost worthless advice, but you got to stick to it, right?
Yeah.
I mean, I might even have different versions of my resume that like paint me, not lying,
right, but slightly.
Different focuses.
Different focuses, right?
Featuring like the DevOps stuff in one and something else in another.
Or the embedded stuff in another and really kind of sell yourself as somebody who focuses
in on that and then tailor it for that particular job that you're applying for.
That's exactly what he's got to do, huh?
Well, just like, you know, anybody, anybody selling a product or anything like they kind
of have different pitches based on who they're talking to.
And I think to Ethan's young enough that he may find that if he does find a job or an
internship or an open source project that he wants to work with, he may either discover
he really enjoys that kind of work or he doesn't yet enjoy that kind of work.
And so I don't, I don't, you know, reading through his email, he feels like he's in a
bit of a rush, like he's looking at summer 2022 and that's not soon enough.
And I don't think he's actually in the position he thinks he's in.
I would encourage him to follow Mike's advice to the letter is maybe even if you're not
ready to focus yourself, focus your resumes, focus your tactic.
Don't come in as just somebody who's capable of doing everything, whatever you need me
to do, because that just says that just screams project to a hiring manager.
Just makes you sound like a project.
Yeah.
All right.
Solve that one.
Tyler writes in, he's got two situations he wants to run past us.
Tyler's also a high school student.
I should point out.
So, uh, this is, that's interesting today.
Both emails.
Hmm.
Tyler writes, I feel like the attacks on large corporations generally have good underlying
intentions and he's referring to like, uh, the employees, you know, like there's like
this Apple to hashtag now on Twitter where people are sharing their, their Apple stories
about, you know, employment issues and stuff like that.
Uh, but Tyler says, I think that many people fail to grasp that the arguments only have
validity when someone else is creating a platform for others to build on.
Competition is essential to a functioning economy and therefore to function as a society.
If you create a platform and you call it fair, but then cunningly deceive your clients, that's
uncool and that should be banned.
However, if you try to create these anti-monopoly laws in the wrong way, we could very well
end up in a position to dastardly to recover from.
I feel bad that Tyler has to worry about these kinds of things.
I think what he's trying to say is, wow, when they do something wrong that has to be stopped,
we could very well go too far.
In fact, you might argue that Microsoft was a good example of this for a while.
They really seem to have their hands tied behind their backs and got lapped by the rest
of the market and the kind of missed out on the mobile situation that kind of missed out
on the beginning of the internet situation.
And when Satya Nadella came on board, the other thing that happened around that timeframe
and maybe it played a role, maybe it didn't is some of the overseeing structure that was
in place by the government was removed that time it expired.
And so the monopoly watchdog that was like, you know, installed at Microsoft left, they
were done.
And Microsoft figured out how to play game, play ball with the federal government and
buddy up and make contracts and accommodate special national security needs.
And they did all the right things.
And now they're, you know, they're doing better than ever.
So I don't know, I think what Tyler's trying to say is we could screw it up too much if
we try to overmanage it.
But he has another note and he wants to get your opinion on Mike.
He says, as a high school student, I love programming and I pretty much love doing nothing
else but maybe some gaming.
I'm curious, this is a programmer, how high in a company can I reasonably expect to rise?
He's asking as a developer.
I mean, I don't really want to end up as a server administrator, but I also want to progress,
grow and make some money in the process.
I'd love to hear your takes on what avenues I should pursue to find a job where he could
reasonably rise up in the ranks and make good money.
So he wants a good day job, something he could raise up in the ranks, huh?
Probably means you're gonna look for a company of a certain size.
I don't know, what else would you look for?
Well, you want to look at the history of the company, right?
So one, when you say rise up in the ranks, there's rank and there's money.
There are companies that don't promote developers into necessarily upper management, but they
have like steps on the developer track where you end up just making a ton of money, right?
It's possible.
There are companies like Microsoft that a good way, unless you're Balmer, which I don't
think they want to repeat that, a good way to get to the upper C-suite is to be technical,
right?
Especially if you get on the right projects at the right time.
That's often what happens in these companies is you're working in one group, that group
does really well, so they kind of tap you for the next big project.
And if that project takes off, your career tends to go along with it.
I just want to say, by all accounts, Satya Nadella is a lovely dude, super nice, great
to work with, but he's probably CEO today because he was the boss of Azure, which just
prints money.
Right?
I mean, it helps to be like in the right place.
Well, it also was a very strong message to Wall Street that this is the future direction
of Microsoft by putting Satya there.
Yeah.
I mean, we don't have it in the show, but this is a bit of a diversion, but you know,
Windows 11, not a huge upgrade, unless you want like WSL, then it is, right?
Then it's really nice.
That's like the best feature of it from what I can tell.
It's like the best feature.
That, and it looks a little more like Plasma, the Plasma desktop.
I like that too.
I mean, everything has to steal from KDE there.
I said one nice thing about KDE, that's it for the next year.
Oh, I said, you know, look at the company's organization, you know, a company that its
business is technical or engineering focused is probably going to be more open to, you
know, a good promotion track for that kind of role.
My point being like, if you work at like a law firm as like the guy who runs their website,
that's probably not the best choice for you.
Yeah.
That's my point.
Having said that you're super young, you're probably going to switch organizations a bunch
of times.
So I wouldn't even worry necessarily about it just yet.
He's probably not even going to make it until the crash.
Let's be honest.
He's going to be a, wait, what?
The dot com bubble 2.0?
What?
Please don't say that now.
Linode.com slash coder.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and you go there to support the
show.
I host everything on Linode these days.
They've got servers all over the world, 11 different data centers, and to make things
really sing, they became their own ISP.
So they control the links between their own data centers.
They've recently reinvested in their MVME storage.
So it's faster than ever.
And their high end CPU systems have AMD epic processors.
It screams with 40 gigabit connections coming into their hypervisors, a beautiful dashboard
to manage it all and tons of one click applications.
Maybe for example, you'd like to deploy VS code server.
Why not have your own VS code editor in the cloud?
But under your control on your own box, they have a one click deployment for VS code web
server.
It's great.
Also like next cloud, Jitsi, tons of projects.
Maybe you just want to get started on and don't want to spend time setting up.
They've got one click deployments for that.
But if you're a DIY kind of person, they got you covered and it's easy to use their S3
compatible object storage, managed cloud firewalls, they have DDoS protection, a powerful DNS
manager, and so much more.
Linode is all about the community too.
Their community support runs deep.
They've invested in projects that make what we do possible, distributions that I use every
single day, and they made our road trip possible.
And I bring this up because it's like being a good environmental citizen.
They're taking care of their neighborhood.
They're taking care of their community.
They invest in all the important aspects of their business.
They've been doing this since 2003.
They know how to do it right.
But I think you got to go check it out for yourself because there's a lot of places you
can host stuff, but nobody checks all the boxes like Linode.
So go over there and take advantage of our $100 credit and support the show.
It's linode.com slash coder.
Get $100 for 60 days on a new account and support the show linode.com slash coder.
Well speaking of antitrust and just weird things that don't feel quite right when it
comes to these large tech giants, of course, as absolutely 100% expected, Apple is appealing
the Epic Games ruling, you know, the one in which it pretty much won every single claim
except for a single claim.
It is appealing that single claim.
Obviously a 99.9% victory is unacceptable.
But there was just that one problem, you know, is that was that one little finding that said
that Apple violated California's anti-steering rules and demanded that Apple let developers
linked outside payments.
So it's kind of why they're fighting that one.
It's kind of the one they care about the most too.
And then they're using the excuse, which I suppose is legit, of ongoing litigations against
Epic to not allow them back into the app store.
They're like, you wanted to bring this against us?
Well guess what?
You're not getting back in now.
And Epic's asked to be back in and Apple said, nope.
I don't understand why Epic thought that we're going to get back in.
No, this is just beginning.
So like Apple has asked to have this appeal.
The court has not yet granted the appeal.
And if they do, then they will grant a stay.
That stay will push out this this change that Apple have to implement to at least until
December.
Apple's plan is to argue.
Remember that chicken compromise that they announced a few weeks ago before the epic
trial finished?
Yeah, yeah.
They're going to argue it's moot because they already offered a compromise.
Yes, they're going to go into court and they're going to point to that announcement.
This is their plan.
And they're going to say, look, we've already agreed to some of this stuff.
So we not only not only do we think this is bogus, but we don't even think it's necessary.
It's a bunch of ticks.
I think the judge is going to buy it.
I think so, too.
That's so bad.
Oh, man.
And Apple is just going to laugh all the way to the bank and Epic's going to be screwed
in the meantime.
I bet Apple lets them in after all this is done, but it could be a long time.
Well, I mean, Epic is, quote, screwed.
I mean, I don't know.
Even you know, the court documents, iOS is not that huge for market for real time feedback
is bite bitten points out in the chat room.
The Netherlands is getting nudged or the Netherlands is nudging Apple for their app store payment
options.
And then today, as you and I were going on the air, the Wall Street Journal published
a report that the U.S. Justice Department is quietly hush hush putting together antitrust
enforcement against Apple.
I guess like they're working with the Biden administration, the White House would go for
it and I'll have a link in the show notes.
But they're basically putting together a low key antitrust case against Apple right now
in the Justice Department.
And that should be interesting.
This all feels super weird to me because like Apple's got to know they're not going to get
away with this forever.
Remind me again how they're a monopoly.
With 20 percent of the phone market.
Remind me again.
It seems pretty clear that they're going to have to give something on the app store payments.
I guess so.
I'm trying to I'm trying to think about it.
I mean, I agree they should.
But are they truly the monopoly of the market?
That just seems like we've completely lost focus on how large Android is as a platform.
It just doesn't seem well, I mean, as many sad lawyers have made the argument, right?
The problem with Android is it is the share monopoly, but not the revenue monopoly.
I'm sorry.
It is the share majority, but not the revenue majority.
Like I wouldn't write a native Android app anytime soon unless somebody paid me to do
it.
Yeah.
From from a revenue standpoint.
Yeah, you're right.
Yeah.
I mean, that's kind of crazy.
So although I don't think that's a valid argument, I'm not a lawyer, but I can't imagine going
into court.
But yes, Your Honor.
But that 80 percent of the market won't buy my smurf berries.
It just kind of feels like saying that Disneyland has a monopoly on, you know, event parks.
Well, that's true.
Like they are the biggest and they're the most expensive.
And when you go in, it is all Disney from top to bottom.
But there's six flags.
There's, you know, Splash Mountain.
There's there's other stuff out there.
There's Silverwoods in Idaho.
There's all there's other Universal Studios.
They will.
If you live in Florida, they will send you a letter every month until you sign up for
their pass, reminding you that they're there.
I'm guessing wildly, but I bet you if you looked up at the overall percentage of different
types of fairgrounds in parks like that, Disney was probably the minority.
If you look around the world, you know, it's like claiming that Disney is has a monopoly
on this market.
And I, I agree that if you go into Disney's Park, Disney has a monopoly.
But you chose to go into Disney's Park.
And I know this is an old argument, but I'm just trying to I'm just trying to grasp quite
how serious this is, because this is a really weird angle to take on it.
But like if you take if we screw this up, like just thinking about Tyler's email and
we say we take Apple down, what has been changed?
What's been accomplished is now on 20 to 30 percent of the mobile market.
There's more flexible payment options.
That's what we're going to accomplish.
I mean, that's a good thing, I guess.
But I don't know.
Seems like you give Apple five to 12 years and they're going to be there themselves anyways.
I mean, maybe not, but it just doesn't seem like it doesn't solve the overall problem.
That's like these five tech companies control our entire lives and you literally cannot
go through modern life without touching one of them.
That's the real problem we have now.
Not that, you know, that 20 percent of the market can't use Stripe to pay for an app.
I mean, it's an issue, but is it really the issue that the Justice Department?
I don't know.
Well, that's what I was going to say.
The real problem is that to solve the problem, you just stated that these five monoliths
are basically a presence of everyone's life that they cannot realistically avoid.
You would need functioning government, which we don't have.
So that people are just trying to like use the courts as a way to, you know, conjure
litigation and to do that, the only route, because honestly, if you want to like dunk
on Android people, sorry, most of the audience who has Android.
Another way to look at it is why don't Android users spend more money?
Right.
And you can you actually market to them differently?
I think that's a very complicated, very complicated problem.
It's a complicated thing.
And there's a strong case that if you're on the Apple side of life, you just say, it is
not my problem.
It is not my job to make your software successful if you don't like our platform, go to the
other platform.
Yeah.
I don't know.
I like I sort of want that not to be true because like my issue is more all the restrictions
on what developers can do less than 30 percent, even though it is ridiculous.
You know, and maybe I'm wrong, Gus 77 in the chat room linked me to counterpoint market
share data that was published on August 16th of 2021.
And it shows that for the last this just goes back to Q1 2020.
But basically, it just shows a steady growth of iPhone for the last year, really kind of
since the pandemic began going to today.
The iPhone has just gobbled up market share and according to these stats that now has
a 53 percent market.
Now this I don't know if this is true, because they also at one point claimed at a 65 percent
market share and then it dropped down to 55 and now it's 53.
So I don't know, maybe it's going back down.
But according to these stats, it's at it's at over 50 percent of the market.
So I guess you could start considering a monopoly at that point.
However, it seems pretty tenuous if if just three quarters ago is at 65 percent and now
it's at 53 percent.
Seems pretty tenuous monopoly to me.
Oh, well, this will be another three years.
Chrissy wrote in.
He wants to learn.
He says, I know this is not always topical, but it's a bit of an evergreen question, something
I thought you guys might have some thoughts on.
I'm an RN by employment, but I self identify as a general purpose nerd, really.
And I've always been more of a hardware guy.
I like to solder and, you know, I like to do my own custom sensors and hook them up
to home assistant.
Ha ha.
Atta boy, Chrissy.
He goes on to say, for example, I like to wire up the various configurations and always
make sure I get the best speed bump.
I'd like to learn some basic coding, though, to fill in the gaps of my knowledge.
I've got no formal training anything aside from one credit of VB I took in high school.
That's the most important class.
So also dating himself slightly.
I'm not trying to write standalone software or anything.
So any thoughts on like maybe what I could do?
Remember, I'm somebody with a negative amount of free time or really hardly disposable income.
But I can learn some basic coding and programming.
But what can I do with zero prior knowledge?
And that just sounds like a fun challenge.
I thought maybe since Chris was working with Home Assistant.
I thought this could be an excellent opportunity to learn Python because the Home Assistant
project is written in Python.
No, that's exactly what I was going to suggest.
Do some of your your home automation stuff in Python.
I mean, talk about a great language to jump into.
There's so many, so many resources to learn Python to you found a really, a really good
one that it's a type of resource that completely clicks with the way I learn.
I like this.
It's called understanding all of Python through its built ins.
So this is an idea of just learning quite a lot about what Python is capable of and
its various features by just learning what all of the built in options are and what they
do.
Yeah.
Basically telling you what features obviously is not, you know, comprehensive, but what
features the designers of language think were so important that they had to have like special
built in functionality for I have to say, it's a pretty novel way.
I've never thought of it this way, but you know what?
For someone, someone like the writer coming in kind of technical, but doesn't, you know,
not really a programmer, that's probably a good good blog post to look over.
Oh, man.
It's so extensive.
It's so well done too and formatted really, really well too.
So it's very easy to read the actual code and understand what it's doing.
It's top notch.
The other thing, and this might be a, maybe he's too advanced for this now, but a spark
fun, they sell like boards and stuff, but they have a whole like burn section where
they do, they have like videos on how to, you know, you buy the lighter sensor.
How do you program it?
How do you set it together?
How do you do the soldering?
I know for him, he already can do the soldering it sounds like, but that might be a route
for folks trying to learn how to do this kind of thing.
That could be a really fun way to do it.
If you're more of a hands-on visual style learner, that could be a great resource.
I'll mention that our friends over at a cloud guru have an entry-level Python programmer
course that'll help you get a certification as well.
The certified entry-level Python programmer certification is what it's called.
And it's a great place to start when getting started with Python, or if you even want to
consider getting a Python certification.
Go check it out.
They'll go over Python data types, control flow structures, data collections, functions
and generators.
By the time you complete the course, you should be more than comfortable with Python.
I'll have a link to that in the sponsored section of the show notes, or you can go over
to a cloud guru and search for certified entry-level Python programmer certification, quite the
mouthful link in the show notes at a cloud guru.com.
And that could be a great way to get started perhaps.
What do you think, Mr. Dominic?
Are you ready?
Should we, should we talk about the big news?
Do you feel like we've, we've done our duty for the people?
I feel like we've done our duty.
We've dutied.
So tell us about Alice and, and what Alice is and I don't know, I personally love to
hear the backstory stuff.
So maybe any of that kind of you want stuff you want to share too.
Yeah.
So it's a, it's a conversational UI, right?
So that's probably a big part.
It lives in Slack and MS teams.
So you interact with it via speech or not speech, but typing.
People might notice a couple of weeks ago, I was talking about and tweeting my NLT key
NLT kit using that fast API, async IO rust via a very, very cool library called Pio three,
which lets you take a rust.
I always, I always mix up how they say this, but basically, you know, a rust module and
make it into a Python module that you call and it feels and looks like Python from, you
know, from the consumer's perspective, right?
The consuming developer's perspective.
So that's kind of the technical underpinnings, a lot of WebSockety stuff, particularly for
Slack because Slack is amazing and has a great WebSocket API that actually works unlike others.
Just on top of that too, it's, it's a tool that so many people already have.
So it's just, it's like just plugging into something that's already part of their workflow.
Exactly.
So the whole idea here is to, let's say you're a midsize business, right?
You have some system, some contractor probably wrote in VB6 and it's sitting there holding
you back, right?
You want to move on to more, you know, more modern technologies.
A big need that I kept seeing people kind of calling and reaching out was because of
COVID, they're trying to do like more either hybrid working or just straight remote working.
And these systems that are like behind the firewall, weird VB application are causing
all kinds of problems.
So Alice can also live behind the firewall.
That's kind of the key.
This is not like a SAS that you subscribe to.
This is something where there's an installation implementation.
And from there, basically we take a look at what kind of weird psychedelic data is your
proprietary system coming out with.
She'll compare it to what she already understands and we'll get a close approximation.
We call it universal data fluency.
If we have to tweak it, we will, and we'll go from there.
And the key is once she understands the data, we can then convert it into all the other
formats she knows.
I love this.
So this is universal data fluency is this concept that your business application may
spit out something that really no other application can do anything with, but Alice can understand
it and then translate it into something that is usable.
Am I following you so far?
Right.
So she tries to figure it out, right?
She gets it and then she keeps comparing it.
We have to have a couple of expected outputs, but we go from there and piece by piece she
puts together the structure.
But then let's say, so the value that you add as a company is if it's something so esoteric,
Alice doesn't really recognize what to do with it.
You provide the ability to customize Alice in a way to help her work specifically with
that format.
So the business could reach out to you, contract you to do that bit of work, and then they
have that forever.
Correct.
Right.
If you have some like really insane thing that is unlike anything else we've ever seen,
we can just do that as part of the implementation.
That's awesome.
That's great for you because it means that from time to time you're going to get a contract
to do some work and make some revenue that, you know, makes it worth reinvesting back
into Alice.
And for Pete, for businesses, you know, like the business I've worked with, they'd absolutely,
that's a, it's a great concept for them because it's like a, it's like we, we just have to
hire this chunk of work.
It's not like this ongoing thing that they'll have to do forever.
So it's not going to be like this endless pit of money.
It's you get the software, you hire them for some, from our, some hours of time to do this
for us.
It's, it's pretty straightforward.
Yeah.
That's, that's the whole idea.
I mean, the, the other advantage is once we have an understanding, a comprehension of
your, your, you know, proprietary data format, well then we can do all the automation stuff
that you would expect from any automation tool, right?
Like a Zapier or something like that, where it's like, Oh, I want to automatically, you
know, get this data out of my system and create tickets and Trello, or I want to create, you
know, a report or I want to write an Excel document, stuff like that, or remind a message
in Slack or send a message in Slack.
Yeah.
Save a file and drive, right?
All that stuff.
The key is that first step though, right?
Of deciphering the actual crazy format.
That's why I, that's why I liked the Rosetta Stone analogy because that's, this is a weird
history nerd thing.
But when the Rosetta Stone was found, there was a, I think I believe a French archeologists,
they were able to start translating Egyptian hieroglyphics, which they never could do because
the other languages on the Rosetta Stone were known to them.
So that's the whole, that's the whole point, right?
So that's, yeah.
And this seems like a, it seems like it's gotta be a pretty common business problem
because I don't think I've been in a single business that doesn't have a problem just
like this, where it's either some old app they've purchased, some old application I
should say, or it's something they've built or something like that.
And it's just time to move, time to migrate or time to integrate.
And it's just like this roadblock they always hit.
Yeah.
It was kind of how this idea came about.
I would constantly be in these sales conversations for projects that went something like this.
We have this insane proprietary database we bought from some company.
That company is now out of business.
We don't know how to work with this.
So we're stuck on this old application.
We want you to write a new one.
What's that going to cost?
And the answer was always, well, we can't get your data out or the cost was just most
likely too much for them to want to pursue.
This solves that second problem, right?
Well, it solves both.
This is a cheaper solution because it's, you're just licensing it.
And voila here, but welcome to the modern world.
Yeah.
Well, and for you as a development shop, it means you don't have to build the customer
a GUI that sits on top of this data translation tool that you're one off building for them.
Correct.
That's great.
I mean, it helps you scale across multiple problems without having to invent some sort
of graphical interface every single time.
And oh man, I think that's really clever.
I like it.
Do you have an idea of what kind of size, like, is this like a small business tool?
Is this like a government tool?
Like what do you, what's your idea on that kind of like ideal customer?
Yeah.
I think it's more than the medium to smaller enterprise, not small business, but like you
got 50 to like a hundred people ish, right.
Where you're, you're big enough that you have custom systems already that are probably kind
of older.
And you could probably use some workflow automation, but you're not like, you don't have that giant
enterprise contracts with like, you know, Microsoft or or Oracle or whoever, right.
And they're probably using some sort of team communication tool and cloud storage and all
that.
Yeah.
That's pretty good.
So, uh, we should, we should mention if people want to check it out for themselves, alice.dev
and we'll have a link in the show notes.
It looks so slick.
I, whoever's doing your, uh, your Alice artwork, you got to hook me up because that's not a
problem.
You know what I'm saying?
I want some of that work always comes out good.
So there was a little, a little hiccup though.
Oh, so somehow my domain got flagged as malware.
Yes.
Right.
As you're like about to launch to this weekend.
Yeah.
Right.
Oh man.
So I ran around with like a chicken with his head cut off all weekend.
So I've been like Dick Tracy and the underbelly of these cyber security companies that, ah,
so that's why you got a new Apple watch.
I did not get a new Apple watch.
I learned something very disturbing and that is one of the ways these companies decide if
your site is malicious is they just look at each other and say, did the other one say
it's malicious, which creates a cascading false positive, which is exactly what happened
here.
Yeah.
So you're, in other words, not only did you have like issues with one, but you had issues
with multiple social media sites like Facebook and Twitter were blocking you at the same
time, right?
Uh, yes.
I will give Facebook some credit though.
They're their tool to like put in the URL and like ask them to manually check it.
They were, they were very fast.
They did it.
You were fine.
And I guess the Genesis is, is that at one point there was like something wonky on the
site, something, something flagged it, but then it just, you just get passed around on
these lists even after it's fixed.
I think what happened is at one point last year I had to have an XE for someone to download
and I just put it on the server.
Oh, that's right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right.
I think that's like a no, no, you can't really, you're not supposed to do that.
Yeah, yeah.
The demo XE.
Yep.
That, that's right.
And then you got flagged and now it's in a database and it takes months for these databases
to propagate is the other thing.
Oh man, you know, uh, you should use Linode object storage for that.
I really should.
That's like the best, the solution to this problem.
Amazing.
Well, um, so that's like super last minute stress.
I mean, think about everybody, put yourself in Mike's shoes for a second.
You've been pushing for weeks, you've been building towards something.
It's now finally time to release it to the world, to go public, to launch it and your
site gets blacklisted by social media, which when there's no events going on is like the
primary platform to promote something like this.
I mean, you must have been extremely pissed.
Uh, I was more pissed when I realized that Twitter, um, their support option is you tweet
at them and they ignore you.
Yeah.
That's also the problem.
It's much like the Google Python script of go pounce and yeah.
Yeah, they arbitrarily decide to censor you for whatever reason.
And then there's really no, there's no like repercussions.
You can take these.
Okay.
Well at the same time, emailing me, emailing me to see if I'm ready to run the ads, which
I thought was hilarious.
Oh yeah.
That's great.
Yeah.
They'll happily take your ad money.
Right.
I was like, uh, let's just wait.
So that the only thing not resolved.
So the Alice site never had a problem.
The mad botter site now doesn't, but Twitter has not caught up yet.
So unless it has, you know, in the last couple of hours, but yeah.
All right.
So I know optimus gray, there was no malware on the site.
It's just crap forever.
Now here's my question.
When you started this, this, this project, you must have expected that by now trade shows
would be a thing and that you'd be out there shucking and jive and shaking hands.
I have a box of coasters.
Yes, I, I did in the stickers and stuff like that.
I was, uh, yeah, I was thinking, all right, we'll be going to like, like, you know, South
East Linux or somewhere in Denver, right?
We'll be doing something.
No, no, we're not.
So do you feel like that's going to be a, uh, an impedance?
Like it's going to be a softer launch because of that?
Um, I, I don't know.
Right.
This is where I, I'm a little out of my depth.
So I, I hired a kind of like PR consultant lady.
And when I told her that you couldn't tweet the link to the company site, I could hear
her head explode on the phone.
She's like, I quit.
She's like, I hate it.
What did you do?
She's like, I was like, nothing.
So the, the marketing strategy is going to be a social media targeting, giving the big
bad blue app money.
Both big bad blue apps actually.
Yeah.
I historically do not believe in this.
So this is kind of a maiden voyage for me.
Hmm.
You know, I'm, I'm, I've got like savvy cow running.
I'm, I'm all hip now.
Chris, I'm, it's gone or the martini bar, you know, side deals at the trade show days.
Now you're schlepping it with the rest of us on the internet.
I'm, I'm like thinking about CPM and I'm like, I don't, I don't like how this works.
It sounds like I'm going to spend a lot of money.
Yeah.
You said you started thinking like, well, okay, so then, okay, how much is each person
worth to me?
And I don't know about that line of thinking, you know,
And I'm like, do I want to like advertise this on like tech podcasts or is everybody
be like, ah, we could do this in a weekend as developers will.
That's a good question.
Huh?
So I'm, I'm trying, actually, I got to talk to you about that too, but I'm probably going
to hold my horses until the end of the month, see what happens organically.
And I have some existing customers I'm reaching out to, you know, I feel icky giving Facebook
money.
Yeah.
That's the one I've been advised and it's just like disturbing how granular you can
get.
I mean, it must work or else CBS and the wall street journal and the New York times wouldn't
be going after Facebook on a daily basis anymore.
You know, it must work.
It's, it seems kind of like, okay, so, you know, we're, we're a, we're a small business.
So we want to target people we can reasonably kind of access, right?
So okay, let's just say the Southeast United States and like the New York, New Jersey metropolitan
area where I have, you know, existing relationships, stuff like that.
And the company, like company size, you can target the title of the person or what type
of work they do.
Do they have a dog?
I mean, it's, it's really, it's pretty impressive, huh?
It's disturbing.
Yeah.
But I'm going to try it because it's, you know, I would much rather go to like Linux
Fest Northwest, even though I wouldn't be presenting there and just like bump into somebody
who might want something, right?
Or you know, one of the kind of more business oriented chambers of commerce shows I used,
I used to do down here.
If you came to Linux Fest Northwest, you could just sit at the JB table and you would have
a line of people who want to talk to you.
That's yeah.
Yeah.
It's true.
You know, I think, you know, you're, you're right in a sense, like I could see you trying
to pitch us at a tech audience and then be like, Oh, I could, I could build a shell script
that would take that data file and convert, but the reality is the value that you're really
offering is the ability to here's a done thing.
And for a set fixed amount of cost, we can customize said thing and then we can provide
support for that if there needs to be a change for future applications compatibility down
the road, that bulk of work ain't nobody in it got time for nobody with a job today has
time for that.
And the people who would be willing to go home and spend their evenings building that
for their company, I hope they're getting paid a lot because they're very, very, very
dedicated and valuable to that company.
But your real value there is you're, you've solved, if not the entire problem, 90% of
the problem and then you, because you're not slack, because you're not some huge company,
because you are a development shop that is, you know, approachable by a hundred to 200
person company, you can, you can interface with them and have a business relationship
that they can't have with a larger solution or a, you know, a guy named Ted who spent
the night building a bash script.
That's the real value, right?
And we're also not coming in with some platform that's going to like, you know, you don't
have, you don't have to go full Oracle.
I pick an Oracle because it's Oracle, right?
You don't, you don't, you don't have to like replace everything you have, including your
coffee machine.
It's like, no, just Alice kind of just sits there and helps you out.
You want to stick with whatever weird, by the way, the amount of huge businesses that
I have spoken to in my very, very lame sales attempts that are just running on access and
they're ashamed.
You can hear it.
Well, actually that's a, that's, that's, that's access.
Like the IT guy knows what he's doing as well.
You know what the sad thing is?
They're a notch above the folks that are running it all out of a spreadsheet.
That's the sad reality.
Yeah.
I have people in my family, uh, ma who are, I don't know what I would call this, but it's
Excel sorcery.
Sure.
Yeah.
Like I have seen spreadsheets do things that I did not think were possible.
They like have their whole, a whole environment in there.
Yeah.
They're running VB six.
Of course they just don't know it.
This is a, this is exciting because it's a project that you're shipping that is like
the realization of a lot of the technologies we've been covering over the last six months
on the show.
And so now it's like, we're going to see how they actually do in practice.
Yes, we are.
And of course it's done, but obviously I'm adding more integrations, which means more
data formats and we're just going to keep on trucking.
This.dev if people want to go check it out.
Datadog.com slash Coder Radio.
Get a free trial and see why so many listeners of Coder Radio have been trying out Datadog.
They're the monitoring and security platform for developers, security analysts, and operational
teams in the cloud age.
You can unify your metrics, your traces, and your logs all in one place.
That means you troubleshoot issues faster and you break down silos between teams and
communicate better, and you can create beautiful real time dashboards for over 450 technologies
that you're going to want to integrate with in just minutes.
And you can easily pivot from like a high level overview of your entire environment
right down to a granular visualizations of specific events and specific metrics.
Datadog offers infrastructure monitoring, application performance monitoring, security
monitoring, log monitoring, user monitoring.
It's all in one place.
So go get started today with their free trial at Datadog.com slash Coder Radio.
See why you can and why thousands of other companies trust their monitoring to Datadog.
Coder Radio listeners love it and you will too.
And if you start a free trial and you create one dashboard, well, guess what?
Datadog is going to send you a free t-shirt, free t-shirt and a free trial and you support
the show.
It doesn't get better than that Datadog.com slash Coder Radio.
Well before we get out of here, I wanted to pontificate something at you, okay?
You heard about this big old Twitch leak that happened where they got the source code and
did you see the commit notes?
Oh man.
No, I didn't.
Glorious.
Oh yeah.
One guy committed, I don't know why this works.
Awesome.
Way to go Amazon, goodbye.
So what I thought was interesting is when I read through some numbers that the Wall
Street Journal went through, they did some math.
I was getting a lot of App Store vibes from this and the situation that we've been talking
about with developers I think is happening at an even faster rate with even less oversight
to content creators.
Now check this out, okay?
The top 1% of Twitch streamers made over half of all the money paid out in 2021 so far.
Doesn't that sound like exactly how it works with the App Store?
Are they also selling Smurf Berries?
189 million so far this year, up from 517 million over the same period last year.
Three quarters of the users making any money this year have made less than $120.
Three quarters of the users have made less than $120.
Wow, that sounds like the Android App Store.
And here's what's even wild is the Wall Street Journal's analysis excluded 896,000 accounts
that have either made less than $120 or actually owe Twitch money for some reason.
There's 890 accounts, 890,000 accounts that they basically are excluding from this analysis.
The best paid streamer on Twitch made more than $5 million this year so far.
This is just into September.
Only 0.06% of Twitch streamers received over the US median house income of $67,000.
A quarter of all revenue was earned by the top 1,000 accounts.
The top 1% of Twitch streamers made over half of all money paid out in 2021.
These might be worse than the App Store numbers.
That's what I'm saying.
And it's happening at a faster pace, too.
Amazon's only owned Twitch for a few years.
I'm frantically trying to look up the App Store numbers, but I'm not gonna be able to
do it fast enough.
And let me tell you, my friend, the situation's not great with Spotify and podcasts either.
They're trying to do the same exact thing.
I was just gonna say, Marco Arment was just on Twitter going off about Gimlet, Glimlet,
something like that.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Doesn't Spotify own them now?
And it's apparently he was like an investor and they're doing this kind of lockdown stuff
or paywall, whatever.
Yeah, that's right.
He got a payout when Spotify bought them.
Oh, good for him.
I mean, that's right.
Yeah.
Isn't that nice?
It's happening to content at a pretty rapid pace.
I mean, I just want to say, Mr. Fisher, build that wall.
I know.
Well, Spotify did hit me up with a proposal.
It was like super low ad rates, but it was like guaranteed three ads a show and you get
access to our music library.
And I went, what?
Let me think about that.
But no, I'm not.
No.
Wait, wait.
To like do a DJ show?
No.
But you could.
But yeah, like if you use their...
So you have to switch your publishing platform.
You have to switch to their feed servers and all that kind of stuff.
But if you publish through, I'm not sure about this.
I think you can still have a public RSS feed, but you have to publish through their system.
But if you do that, they give you license like a radio station to their music library.
So you could do a DJ show or we could have like your favorite song as our intro music,
that kind of thing.
But you have to sell your soul.
They own you.
They own the content and they own all the ad deals and they give you a very small cut,
but they give you a lot of small cuts.
I mean, have you ever read the Apple developer agreement?
The soul's already got a couple of markers on it.
I know.
And Twitch is doing the same thing.
YouTube is going down its dark route.
I tell you, the only thing that's really going to save podcasting is if listeners continue
to use and insist they use their own podcast apps, their favorite podcast app.
If they use these, you know, and I, we have people listening on Spotify and I am grateful
they listen, especially if it's the best way or only way for you to listen.
But the best thing you could do is subscribe to the show at coder.show slash subscribe
in an independent podcast app.
That isn't owned by Apple or Amazon or Spotify.
I love overcast.
Right?
It's great.
You'll pry it from my cold dead hands.
Hey, whatever happened to pocket cast?
Are they still around?
Yeah.
They were bought by like a group that NPR was part of and now they're selling it.
They're selling it again.
So that group is selling it off.
They used to be Indie, right?
They were like a couple of folks, I could have sworn, wasn't it shifty jelly was the
name of the corporation.
Good memory.
Yeah.
And then they got bought by NPR and this group of like public radio stations and other folks.
And then NPR pushed hard for tracking in app tracking that would basically ping an HTTP
address when you pause, rewind, fast forward, skip, you know, that kind of stuff to try
to create metrics of where people are listening and not listening.
And they wanted to create an industry standard of tracking in the podcast apps and they wanted
to deploy that in pocket cast first and have pocket cast sort of roll it out and everybody
followed suit.
And thankfully we have enough independent podcast app creators that said no, and they
have enough market share that they could say no.
And so it never took off and the tracking standard never was adopted.
And so I think NPR got kind of frustrated and their group and they've just decided to
sell it.
This sounds a little awful lot like streaming video content where if you want to watch a
Star Trek discovery, God damn it, CBS.
That's exactly what they want to do.
And if you, if you listen in the Spotify app, they have metrics of where you listen, what
you, what you rewind, what you skip.
They know everything.
That's a bit creepy.
Let's see.
Just let me have my pot.
I mean, podcast ads used to be, at least on me, the most, one of the most effective ways
to advertise.
Like, yeah, I buy stuff off pocket ads even today all the time.
I think it's the kind we do though, right?
Like when you hear, like when you, when you turn on a planet money or something and they
blast you with two pre-produced ads that aren't even from the hosts that do the show, like
they don't stick at all for me.
They, they don't register at all.
But if somebody comes on and you know, like, you know, at the beginning of the year I bought
some Warby Parker pants.
I think it's Warby Parker, right?
No, no.
They make pants?
I thought they make glasses.
No, no, no, no, no.
I'm getting them mixed up.
But that's the advertising.
It works.
Warby Parker is the glasses.
Exactly.
But that was an ad.
But no, I'm thinking of Mack Weldon.
I bid on a Mack Weldon deal in a podcast ad, you know, but I don't normally buy it on those
ads that are just pre-rolls and pre-produced and all of that.
I mean, I buy stuff off JB ads all the time, as should you.
That's right.
Absolutely.
That's how you do it.
That's how you pay for the tea.
Links in the show notes.
I'm just worried about this and where it's going because really it's just sort of the
trend of everything to get centralized like this.
And I don't know, I guess thankfully we have a very geeky audience, so they're likely to
continue to want things like open RSS feeds and web pages with show notes and stuff like
that.
But maybe not, maybe the average listener won't or maybe it'll change how people consume
the media.
Well, you know, all those Linux guys buying the M1s, that's the gateway drug right there,
Chris.
I have a confession to make.
Yes.
Oh my God, this would be the best show ever.
You bought an M1.
I ordered an M1 last night.
Which one?
I got the Mac Mini fully decked.
Fully decked.
Yes.
Because I've gotten words from the developers of, I'm trying to say it right, Asahi Linux.
They've put the word out that they are very, very close, that they've got a functional
usable desktop right now.
I saw that too.
Yeah.
And they're working on an image and an installer.
It'll probably be out soon.
So I did it.
I did it.
I'm going to, I want to get it in time to try it out when they release it.
So because there's a bit of a delay right now, it's like the end of the month is when
it's going to ship.
If I got it all stock with the crappy amount of storage that they include and the crappy
amount of RAM.
Yeah.
Apple doesn't believe in Photoshop files or audio files or video.
No.
I know.
Right?
And it's like the way it's going to work right now is you have to dual boot.
There isn't like get rid of macOS.
And you'd want to keep macOS for firmware updates and whatnot.
So you need enough disk space to have enough room for both operating systems to live happily.
So you got to upgrade it.
You know?
So I have a confession.
Oh.
I have a problem that I don't know how to solve without selling and replacing my air.
Oh, I have run out of storage.
Yeah.
And when I say I've run out, I had to update macOS there and I had to delete stuff to update
macOS.
Have you tried cloud storage?
Yeah.
No.
I really don't understand Apple's just like ridiculous markup on hard drives.
It's so bad still.
And memory.
It's so bad.
It's so, so bad.
I mean, I bought the M1 because if it can run Linux effectively, and I think it will,
I may transition it eventually to my home server in my RV, which is currently a couple
of Raspberry Pis.
Right.
And you know, the Mac mini has a pretty good power draw even at full load.
It's like 33 watts and it has pretty low noise and it has really good thermals.
And I could easily pull my two or three Raspberry Pis and put one M1 Mac mini running arch
and let it just, you know, be my powerhouse.
So I think that might be the ultimate trajectory.
So my bet on Asahi Linux is that I just can run it as a headless Linux box.
I mean, I think they'll get the graphical environment accelerated, but even if they
don't, it's still a win for me.
So I decided to pull the trigger.
I don't think the M1 as they are today could function as a desktop for me because absolutely,
especially if I was using a Mac, I would, I would need a lot of virtualization capacity.
So yeah, that we're talking a minimum 32 gigs of RAM, cause you know, I'm probably legitimately,
I often have two or three different VMs going on depending on what I'm working on for, you
know, a show or something like that.
It can be a lot.
So I got, yeah, that'd have to be a factor, but you know, it's coming soon.
I suspect you could always, uh, could always gift this, the air to the kid or to the girlfriend
and then get yourself an M1 X or something.
Why would you ever encourage my podcast ads to buy?
I know I'm the worst.
I'm the worst.
Oh boy.
But yeah, um, I'm excited to try it out.
Although if it comes in a different color or shape, I'll have to, I'll have to give
it a go with macOS for a couple of days just to get a feel for it.
But I suspect by the time I'm receiving it, the Linux project will be ready with their
installers.
I am going to tell you macOS, why did Apple break Safari on iOS?
Oh, you having a hard time?
Well, if I have a field such as the Google for work or whatever they call it now, G suite,
whatever sign in page, and I don't want to be on that page, but somehow the password
field got focus, the keyboard blocks my ability because they've put the URL bar in the bottom
to actually get out of that without having to do a very unintuitive top of the screen,
like slap swipe thing.
There's way too much going on down there now.
It's very non-intuitive.
I don't understand.
I feel like it's something I would do to people as a prank at like a cocktail party.
It does seem like a prank.
I turn on like colorblind mode on people's phones when they leave them unlocked.
Like I honestly thought someone was screwing with me.
I'm like, Reese, you're five.
You're amazing.
Did you just like break my phone?
They put the window selection down there, the URL, URL bar selection down there.
If you're on the iPad with a keyboard, there's a little keyboard thing that's down there
and the task switchers down there.
Oh, they did it to the iPad too.
I didn't update my iPad yet.
Oh God.
It's like, I tweeted a couple of weeks ago about Safari on Mac being just what the hell?
Like a psychedelic nightmare of tabs changing colors.
I think it's great.
I'm just letting you know, you are, you are coming from the sublime world of KDE.
Yeah.
It's true.
You're going to, you're going to hate it.
I tell you, I, I, I use Safari very sparingly, so it doesn't really, it doesn't hit me very
hard.
Like I had a dream.
I'm like, maybe Apple should just buy elementary, like seriously, just huh.
Like elementary.
I know they don't love this comparison, but it's like a good version of Mac OS.
Yeah.
Back when it was good.
Right.
It's like, it's prettier snow leopard, right?
They, I mean, they've done modern improvements.
Of course, snow leopard's super old now, but.
It's like back when Mac OS was designed to be a good interface and not trying to keep
up with yearly trends of design themes that the design department comes up with.
I don't think anybody, like, and I mean literally anybody was like, you know what would be great
in my web browser?
The inability to see that I have other tabs open unless I magically remember.
And also why don't we change my screen's color to neon orange and then black and then blue
and then red because the branding and the best is, so then I of course had to check
the Alice site.
Cause I'm like, is this obnoxiously blue?
It is not.
I don't know why it's not.
I went to the Mad Botter site.
Is it going to be like crazy purple?
It is not.
But somehow my GitLab instance is the most aggressive form of fire orange that I have
ever seen in my life.
Yeah.
It's great.
It's just great.
I'm Safari and I claim Safari and I GitLab.
Johnny I would never let this ship.
He would be like, what are you doing?
Make it Chrome and you put the Adobe program down.
Sorry.
I miss Johnny.
I want to say thank you to our Coder QA team out there.
The new Coderly has been recorded and it will be edited as soon as Drew is available.
He's a busy guy and we just sort of slipped that in on him, but it'll be out in the feeds
sooner than later.
So if you haven't signed up yet, head over to CoderQA.co, you become a member, you support
the show.
You also get a limited ad feed and you get access to that Coderly report, CoderQA.co.
Mr. Dominic, where do you want to send people this week?
Go to Alice.dev and if you all could do me a favor, any little bit of help in this scary
new world of social media helps or retweet, whatever, I appreciate it a lot.
Yeah.
Help celebrate by helping spread the word.
Seems like we need it more than ever these days between getting blocked by social media
and there being no events, definitely could use the help.
You can also find them on Twitter at Dumanuco, his company's at the Mad Botter Inc.
I'm there too at Chris LAS, podcastnetworks at Jupiter Signal, the show's at Coder Radio
Show, at Coder Radio Show.
Links to what we talked about today are coder.show slash 435.
Our open and free RSS feed, that's there, coder.show slash subscribe.
You're also going to find our contact form, your emails, they're a big part of our conversation.
Send them in your thoughts, your suggestions, your ideas, your upsets, coder.show slash
contact.
And you can also join us live Mondays at noon Pacific, 3pm Eastern over at jblive.tv.
Thanks so much for joining us.
We'll see you right back here next week.