This is KOTORadio, episode 408 for April 5th, 2021.
Hey there, handsome.
Welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look at the
art and business of software development and the world of technology.
This episode is brought to you by a Cloud Guru.
A Cloud Guru has that cloud playground, Azure, AWS, and Google Sandboxes, boom.
But on their credit card, not yours.
Get certified, get hired, get learning, a CloudGuru.com.
My name is Chris, but really, I'm here to make our host shine.
It's Mr. Dominic.
Hello, Mike.
Hello, Chris.
And can I say happy Victory Oracle Day?
Oh, yeah, right.
Big congratulations, right, to the folks over at Oracle.
Wait, what?
Wait, wait, wait.
Hold on.
Updated news item here.
Hold on, Mr. Dominic.
Hold on.
Oh, no, no, no, no.
Oh, no, no.
I got this.
F*** you, Larry Ellison.
Yeah.
It is definitely a victory day for the folks over at Google.
We kid that it's a boy.
This is a story that has been like 10 years in the making, right?
Just about.
And finally came to a conclusion today, but I'm left with questions.
God.
Oh, can we just take the win for once?
Can we just take the God damn win?
I didn't think it was going to happen, but we'll get there first.
I want to know if it's true or not.
Did you buy another HomePod?
No, because I couldn't goddamn find one.
What made you decide to buy a third HomePod?
Two, I get.
Three, well, might as well get four at that point and have another stereo pair.
You know what?
The HomePod is just significantly better than the Sonos.
It is, isn't it?
If you have iOS devices.
Yeah, that is true.
All right.
Well, I just thought I'd have to find out.
I had to because I'm trying to now the trouble is, like, I'm at the point where I don't
they make the HomePod anymore and maybe lower the price to a more, you know, sane level
because I would totally buy I mean, honestly, if I had a multilevel residence or like a
place with a basement, I could be good for five or six HomePods.
All right, now listen, stay a while and listen.
Oh, Decker game.
There you are.
I know.
It's nice, isn't it?
You got to work him in every now and then.
I have a robe update.
I have a very exciting robe update.
So I thought maybe I'd talk a little bit about this because this was an area that I think
is interesting from a small business standpoint and managing your small business.
So I'll come back to that.
But quickly, the update is domestic and US orders should start arriving around May 19th,
May 20th.
We didn't quite make the window and the materials got used and had to be reordered because of
some of the issues that held up the order, which are related to international troubles.
Now, international orders stand by.
I'll have more news for you next week.
We're still trying our best to work that out.
I may have bad news, but either way, we'll get in touch with you as we try to sort that
boy.
A lot of lessons learned.
I have rethought a lot of things and I'm also very excited that we actually have a like
a ship date or an arrival date, perhaps for the robes.
But I feel like as a business, I'm rethinking my entire strategy around swag.
And I think what, when I look back at this as sort of like a post-mortem, I think one
of the primary problems I had was I was attempting to do something that was really, really outside
the norm for like my first thing.
And additionally, I couldn't work with a shop that like shipping internationally was like
the thing they did because of how unique this particular thing was.
And so they were a domestic operation who generally would like just send like a hundred
or 200 units to me.
And then I would ship them out to everybody around the world.
That's generally the type of customer they have.
And instead I was trying to get them to send it everywhere in the world, which they can
do, but it's not their core competency.
And as a result of that, I didn't appreciate how much that would matter.
But now I understand that it seems like for the kind of thing I want to do and to ship
internationally at reasonable rates, because some of these rates to like anybody who lived
in Germany, the original pricing we were working with was $150 of shipping per robe.
Holy crap.
Yeah.
The cheapest international shipping we had was $95.
So it was a range between $95 and almost $200 with the exception of Canada, which is like
$85.
So now we're trying to sort that out.
And it was clear to me what would really work a lot better for an operation like JB who
operates out of the States, but has a worldwide audience that represents a significant portion
of its audience.
I have to build up some sort of operation where we're printing the shipping labels and
slapping them on boxes and boxing them up here and then dropping them off at the post
office and they're shipping them off.
And I'm just not there yet.
So I try to get another company to do that part for me.
And the way they operate it is the way the type of drop shipping they do is they need
all the shipping information and get every robe's destination and then come back with
a quote.
And then of course there's tons of back and forth and trying to find alternative fulfillment
places and all that kind of stuff, which is where we're at right now for the international.
But the domestic orders, what we decided to do was break those off into their own original
order set from the original supplier and just get those out and going while we sort out
the rest of it.
I mean, I learned a lot and I think I've internalized a new strategy for the company and how we're
going to learn how to do this.
I can't just start selling swag.
I can't just turn on a switch and all of a sudden I'm like, you know, stocking swag
and boxing swag and shipping swag.
First of all, it sounds like hell.
And second of all, I have no idea what I'm doing.
And third of all, I have no inventory.
I have to figure out how to get that skill set while not bankrupting the company because
things could go really simple where like I pre-order a hundred robes for a second patch,
stock them here at the studio and then never get them shipped out or never get, you know,
like I could just so many ways I could screw this up.
So I have to build institutional knowledge while not screwing the pooch and keeping the
train on the tracks while we try to build up this new aspect of the business.
But I feel like my lessons learned here are if I want to be serious about how to do this,
I'm going to have to be kind of responsible for at least, at least like, like maybe what
I would do, I guess I'll say it, put it this way.
If I were going to do this again, I would take pre-orders and I would like make, I would
just order 200 robes.
And then once 200 robes were sold, that's as many as we had.
We could do a second batch if we wanted, but I would, and then I would box them up and
ship them out myself with like a label printer and like, you know, on a specific day, a couple
of us are here at the studio boxing things up, loading the car and sending it out a couple
of times a week.
And that's what I would do this time around.
And then, you know, and then maybe open up another 200 orders or something, but I'm just
not there yet.
Or don't do it at all.
Right.
Robes were a stupid idea.
Yep.
You shouldn't have done them.
Nope.
I warned you.
I was, I felt like a good challenge would, would force me to dive deep into this and
like I'd have to solve it in route.
And that might be true.
Unless we got Reese and Dylan and Abigail, right?
Their daughter, are you talking about, you're talking about a ham slice in the channel?
No, yeah.
We just enslaved the kids and make them box all the ropes.
Oh yeah.
I'm totally going to enlist the kids.
For sure.
Like, I mean, I have a 14 year old brother.
He just turned 14.
Um, I'm totally cool with child labor.
I just make it fun somehow.
I'd figure out a way, you know, play some music, make a game out of it.
We need to learn.
No, no, no, no, no, no, listen.
My first job was a janitor when I was in high school.
And uh, for all my young men in the audience, you think girls are neat and clean, clean
a ladies room.
It will change your life.
Should have done something much simpler.
Like a t-shirt.
That'd have been easy.
Could have done a lot of t-shirts.
T-shirts suck.
They do suck.
That was what it was.
I'm so bored of typical swag.
Let me just fix your problem for you.
Do the coder radio beer glass.
Like a Stein kind of thing.
That's an internet.
Yeah.
Okay.
I was even being like lazier than that, but if we can pull off a Stein, that's even better.
Yeah.
That's kind of love 400 thing, you know?
I mean, I'm just saying.
They're hippies anyway.
What are they going to care?
That's true.
What do they even know over there?
Nothing.
I have been actually legitimately looking for like a supplier of, of mugs or cups that
have like a ring around the bottom that prevent tipping.
I mean, if you could get an actual Stein with a hinge on it, that'd be pretty cool.
That would be cool.
But I feel like that's going to have the same problem as the ropes.
I don't know.
Yeah.
And plus, plus shipping something breakable like that probably isn't a good first, uh,
yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Fine.
I don't want to dare.
I dare.
I touch the luck monks of feudal Linux observance.
Right.
How about this quarter radio martini glass?
That's right.
On brand.
That's actually very on brand.
I'm just going to say.
Yeah.
That sounds great.
And I can tell you, I do mad butter or martini glasses and that is not very hard.
So.
Hmm.
All right.
I'm filing that one away.
Okay.
I could see it.
I could see the glass too, like a stir or something.
I don't know.
But anyway, so thank you everybody.
I am going to get these robes figured out and then I'm going to make some like lessons
learned plans that they'll share with everybody.
I went from a business standpoint, I'm going to do in the future, but that's the robe update
for now.
It's just, it's been way more than I expected, although, uh, I did, I do totally acknowledge
I brought it all on myself.
I do this to myself.
It is completely my fault.
I acknowledge that.
I am excited to say robe, Rose in the U S you'll be receiving, you'll be receiving your
robe soon.
Those of you internationally, you'll be hearing from us either with bad news or, uh, an alternative
source or perhaps, perhaps we will be just absolutely forced to do a round two.
I don't know.
I mean, maybe, maybe more robes will be demanded.
You know, we get a lot of emails in.
I feel like you're just making an excuse to do more robes.
I think this whole, like you just saying you're going to do more robes.
Personally, I kind of want to be done with the robe.
It's been a lot.
I don't believe you.
And here's what's going to happen in June.
I'm going to start selling mad botter swag on here because you know what I deliver, you
know why I deliver?
I only sell glass and t-shirts.
Yep.
I know.
You know, a shot glass would be easier to, would have been a lot easier shot glass would
have been a lot easier.
Look at Java jacks, the coder radio sippy cup.
I have been looking, I've been looking something spill proof, but you know what?
A lot of the things that they sell as like a rebrandable swag seem like they're targeted
adults for some reason and not children.
I mean, I feel there was no need for hate speech, but maybe we should just move on to
the actual show.
I think what we need is an artist and sippy cup created by the audience that we could
mass produce or maybe only make a couple limited.
You know what?
The only person qualified to create a sippy cup in the world is me because I will find
every flaw.
There you go.
You could be a good product tester.
Oh, and then I think the other thing I'm going to do in the future, although I haven't worked
out the details on this yet either, is I think I'm going to figure out a way that members
of our shows can get discounts when they buy any of the merch that we do.
Why the hell don't we have new stickers?
Yeah.
And stickers too.
I think stickers are, I think if I'm going to be able to ship robes, I could ship stickers
too.
Dude, I can ship stickers and I'm usually like depressed or hungover or like wiping
somebody's butt.
I mean, come on.
Well, stay tuned because stickers have been a topic of conversation recently.
Before we move on, because we have lots of email to get to, I want to mention that our
friends at a Cloud Guru have a PowerShell core for Linux admins course that I thought
would be particularly useful for our audience.
Now this is an intermediate level course, so you might need to know a little bit of
basics around Linux, but it's really about the concepts of using PowerShell core with
Linux, everything from like getting it installed on a Linux box to using commandlets and using
Visual Studio code, and then you get into some of the more advanced components as well.
And by the end of it, you've got a like working Docker install and SQL server running in there
and you're managing Azure resources with PowerShell.
If you're curious about their PowerShell core for Linux admins course, we will have a link
in the show notes at coder.show slash four zero eight.
Now let's get into the email.
We got a lot.
We had a spicy inbox this week.
Not all of them made it onto the air, but James S. writes in with an idea that I have
a feeling you're going to think is terrific.
He says, Hey guys, I love the show.
The talk about the new Apple Silicon performance in the context of development though has triggered
me slightly.
I've long felt that developers should be working deliberately on low to mid range hardware
because otherwise it's just too easy to hide bad code behind a fast CPU.
The majority of end users don't run the latest and greatest.
They have older hardware.
What do you think of this idea that if a developer has tons of RAM and a fast CPU, they almost
always write code that feels fine on their system, but crawls on hardware that the typical
end user actually has?
James, I'm sure you're a lovely person and I think you're great.
Thank you for listening to the show.
Your idea is stupid.
What a developer should do is have a good computer with a gimped VMs for testing.
So the VMs should be intentionally weak to test.
For instance, on my Mac, my Mac pro, I have good windows VM for dev and a very crappy
windows VM for testing.
And it's like a third of the RAM and a third of the GPU, you know, allocate, you know,
it's VMware, something the allocation, I'm sorry, it's parallels.
I actually keep saying VMware.
I don't use VMware.
Okay.
I think I like VMware better on the Mac.
I agree with your point, James, that for testing, you should use a slightly weaker hardware
or significantly weaker hardware.
I honestly think a good workstation with different virtual machines for different use cases is
the best way.
So again, Chris, I agree with this point that like when I'm testing windows software or
any other kind of software, like Linux, whatever, my VMs for testing have like the minimal specs.
I don't want to have like five machines because that would be great.
I like your answer a little bit better than yours.
My answer was I think most developers keep a lot of their older hardware around.
Not me.
I pour marketing.
Well, yeah.
Yeah, for sure.
But I think some developers have like probably a couple of iterations of machines around
so they can use that for this thing called Q&A where they could actually test it on the
older hardware directly.
I am not a fan of limiting any developer's productivity.
Like if you get in the flow and you are having one of those beautiful moments, I feel like
the machine should be as fricking fast as possible to let you rip.
Like I buy my guys the best machines we can afford.
Amen.
It's the only area where I don't economize in the business.
I don't.
You know what?
Like what?
What's the stupidly dumb expensive machine that the asshole who works for me tricked
me into buying for him from System76, the Oryx.
Oh, that big laptop.
You got the big one.
Yeah.
He's got three monitors.
So I'm like, this is not what was intended.
He's like, I know, but I have two.
I have a giant GPU.
Like you don't need a GPU.
He's like, I know, but you're part of it anyway, you stupid bastard.
Hey, man, you want smooth window manager animations.
Let's be honest.
That stuff matters.
It still crashes if he runs an extension.
That's too soon.
It's too soon.
I actually have big news on that front later in the show.
You're pregnant.
No.
In the genome shell related world that I want to get your take on.
But I think I think VMs are a good answer to the trolling aside, right?
Like the question is, if you're a company, right?
If you're like someone like me where you have you employ devs, it makes sense to buy them
a higher spec machine than have them test in virtual machines that are intentionally
slow.
If you're like one guy, though, obviously keep your old machines back and just test
on those.
Right.
You don't need to buy a crazy iMac Pro that will be obsolete by your MacBook Air within
two years because Apple's evil.
What was I talking about?
Ron writes in, he says, hey, talking about Apple's gross, Dear Coder Radio, there are
two kinds of people who use Apple.
Number one, the technologically illiterate and number two, the insecure.
Group one is terrified of computers and group two is terrified of coffee shop laptop shaming.
Let's debunk some Apple fanboy myths.
Now, I don't know if Ron's trolling us because he spelled fanboy with an I, which I think
I don't know if he's trying to be.
Yeah, he writes the last time I spent 20 hours away from a power source was never so implying
you don't need long battery life.
Well, I have I've definitely done that, but keep going.
Yeah, I know.
And it's like if you've ever gone to an event.
Do you speak at conferences ever?
Yeah, a conference like the battery life, especially when you get to that stupid moment
where you realize you didn't charge, you left your laptop in your bag overnight.
You get there to do the talk.
You didn't plug it in.
And because Apple only lets you have a couple of USB-C ports, you're really in a tight spot.
But battery life matters a lot for me, too, because I spend a lot of weekends completely
off grid where I am only generating power that comes from the sun.
Sometimes in the Pacific Northwest, there's not a lot of sun.
And I'm usually on a Coke bender.
So, yeah, right.
Of course.
And who's going to bother plugging in when you're on a bender?
He says syncing digital content across devices has never been easier.
I cloud isn't needed.
He set up next cloud in ten minutes.
Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no,
no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no.
Ten minutes.
He had next cloud going in ten minutes.
You were wrong when you said next cloud, but keep going.
I mean, this is this is a common thing that I think is hard for our community to understand.
A lot of people have no interest in doing that, even if they have the technical capability
of doing it.
They don't care.
Yeah.
He says staying productive during renders is not about hoping things get faster on the
M1.
It's about organizing your workflow.
My custom PC used for content creation will scorch any Mac in existence.
Wrong.
Stop.
Custom PC.
Yeah.
Wrong.
Right.
Because most people are not buying custom.
They're not customizing their PCs.
Yeah.
So what I think guys like Ron kind of they don't look at the actual market and go, oh,
like there must be a reason why a guy like Marques Brownlee buys the Mac Pro.
Right.
Because, I mean, I'm sure he doesn't like burning money.
He'd rather probably buy that.
He'd rather spend that money on the next Tesla.
He's you know, why?
So why are they buying that Mac Pro?
And the reality is Final Cut.
It's Final Cut.
It's if you ask them, they will tell you.
It's because of Final Cut Pro 10.
Well, this is a developer show.
The reason I buy only System 76 and Macs for my guys is because I know out of the box with
either of those machines, they can get up and running.
Right.
My biggest expense is pay.
And then additionally, like if one of those guys leaves and you want to move that machine
to somebody else, do you want to move them some weird custom built PC or do you?
No, I want to wipe it and put Pop OS whatever or Mac OS whatever.
And then you scale that up for like any company that has like an IT department with a bunch
of employees.
It's just not scalable to do custom PCs.
The custom PCs are, I mean, bully for you.
No, that's great.
Seriously for you.
But when you have like if I was just a solo shop, honestly, I probably would have a custom
PC.
There's still a group of individuals out there who think that what's selling Apple and why
Apple is one of the most valuable companies in the world is because of marketing and fan
boys.
And I don't really need to dwell on it.
I don't think it's, I mean, but I think it's worth realizing that sometimes we can have
real blinders on to what seems to drive the market.
What seems to really drive the market seems to be battery life and performance and I would
say visual appeal.
And then it's something that we don't quite grok as a community is the entire package,
right?
It's a product.
The cloud services and the fancy Apple sales, everything is part of an entire product.
When you roll your own next cloud, that's awesome.
And I have two, I have two next cloud servers.
It's great.
The reality is though, that's not a whole product.
You built a custom PC, you loaded your own Linux on there and built it up just the way
you like it.
And then you set up next cloud to do your syncing and you did it all on your own.
And that's fantastic.
I host a show with Alex called Self Hosted because I love that stuff.
But I have to be aware that the vast, vast majority of the market, like the significant
total vast majority of the market doesn't do that kind of stuff.
And so they need a solution that works well for them.
And the better and faster that solution is, the overall more people are, their technology
experience is improved.
It's easy to dismiss this stuff, but I think it actually, it deserves important consideration.
And then the next questions start to become like, well, how do I make money on this reality?
Like if I want to have a business in software development and this is the reality of the
market, how do I make money on it?
I think that's a fair question to ask too, but maybe it's not.
Maybe your question is, and I'm not saying it is for everybody, but I'm saying often
in the context of the show, that's how we talk about it.
Maybe it's just, how can I have fun with it?
And Ron, that might be the area you're in and you can be wired to a wall and you never
have to go anywhere mobile and you can spend the time to set up Nextcloud and configure
your Android client to sync with your KDE desktop and man, more power to you.
I wish I had more time to do that stuff because I love doing that stuff too.
But you and I, my friend, we are a rare breed and we may be even fewer and fewer in some
ways, at least compared to the overall growth of the mobile and technology market.
Next one comes in from Alex.
Now for him, the Linux desktop just isn't worth the hassle.
He says, first of all, love the show.
You guys are great.
He goes on to compliment us for a bit, but I'm going to skip over that, but I really
appreciate it.
Thank you, Alex.
It's not you.
It's me.
Yes, I got it.
He says, you're great.
And I just don't want to talk about it.
You know, like we focus on it too much.
Geez.
No.
He says, some time ago you asked people to tell you about their work setups.
Remember when we came back, we did that for a little bit.
He says he proudly wrote in about his high end Dell 7 series, 7000 series laptop running
Ubuntu 1804 and i3.
The thing is I really wanted this setup to work.
My employer insists on using some commercial VPN software as well as some other office
software that only runs on windows, but I had it working for a bit.
I felt kind of like the hacker movie version of a developer spitting up new borderless
terminals and i3 and switching workspaces all while never really leaving the keyboard.
I felt productive, but then one day when going to our support desk, trying to get some Linux
corner case fixed, the staff member most knowledgeable on Linux was out and I had a full day of work
ahead of me.
So the solution they provided me was a used Mac.
What I got was a late 2020 Mac Pro fully decked out, i7, 32 gigs of RAM, one terabyte SSD.
And the amazing thing is it doesn't really seem to get all that hot and I don't really
hear the fans to the point where they're audible, even when running Docker or VMs.
I did disable turbo boost, but here's the kicker, Docker for Mac works amazing on this
Intel Mac.
And I just brew install all the GNU core utilities and just eat the annoyance of some of the
brew limitations.
And I'm not really looking back, the setups working really well for me.
And he goes on to mention how he had some problems with gaming, but he decided, you
know, really for that, maybe I should just set up a windows 10 box.
In conclusion, I'm kind of embarrassed to say that I've ended up leaving desktop Linux
behind.
It of course is the only answer for server side work, but my dumb terminal interface
to it is, well, a shiny, expensive, but effective gray slab from the guys in Cupertino, Alex.
That's hard for me to hear, I have to say, as somebody who's been using desktop Linux
for a very long time.
I know you have a religious objection to computers that actually work, but yeah, this is why
Max, this is why there will be no year of Linux desktop, right?
You don't see a lot of people doing blog posts and YouTube videos about switching away from
Linux, right?
There's a lot of blog posts and hacker news stories about switching to Linux.
Let me tell you, how many of them do the blog posts about switching back?
I mean, I'm on an iMac Pro right now.
Sometimes you see it, but you don't see a lot, but I've done several of those blog posts
and I'm on an iMac Pro, right?
Just, I just hate, I hate hearing this.
I really do.
I hate hearing this.
So I mean, I can tell you, I also have hated hearing a lot of things over the last, let's
say six months and it doesn't get better.
So the M1 Pro is coming out in June.
Oh, geez.
Too soon?
Yeah.
If they had a, if they had a 16 core, if they had a 16 core M1 with 32 gigs of RAM and two
terabyte SSD and 27 inch plus screen, that'd be pretty tempting.
The only other like shoe or whatever the term is I'd need to kind of drop would be if I
even got like a whiff that like the Linux M1 support was getting dialed in and it was
like, you know, within the next year it's going to be working for sure.
I think I'd probably pull the trigger, but I, it doesn't mean I, there'd be, I just have,
that'd be one of many machines that I have.
Oh, let's backpedal.
Yes, of course.
No, no.
It's just the reality is the reality is I'd need something mobile and I still need lots
of Linux and it's not going to do those things for me cause I'm not going to get a Mac book
from them.
All right.
There's many, but I'm not, we'll see.
We'll see.
I think Apple is going to stick with the M1 for the remainder of the year and I'm not
really interested in the M1 now.
Now I feel like I got to hold out for something better too.
So that's what I'm hunkering down for.
The Fisher doth protest too much.
Maybe it, I am in a weird place with it.
I'll tell you that.
I can feel it.
It feels weird.
I don't like it.
I'm uncomfortable with it.
And then the other thing that's hard is the lines between GNOME Shell and Mac OS are even
blurrier than ever because now GNOME Shell has gone to horizontal workspace layouts and
they have the same gesture as Mac OS to get to it.
It's just one less finger.
It's a three finger gesture instead of a four finger and they move the dock down to the
bottom now and the whole thing's feeling a lot like the two, the two interfaces are colliding.
It's we've been here before, Sam.
Yeah.
It's a weird overlap.
Scott writes in though.
He says, Hey, I changed my mind for JavaScript on the server.
I once like Mike was just not having JavaScript on the server.
I thought I should always stay in the browser on the client side.
Just use it minimally.
But my mind changed once I learned about server side rendering and it all clicked.
This allows the server to build the fundamentals of a webpage and then just send the browser.
Oh, this is not new Scott, this is not new at all.
Well he says it's nice cause in the browser gets this nice little thing that it can just
display really super quick.
Any additional logic can be, any minimal logic can be done on the client, but the server
does the bulk of the work.
He says it doesn't necessarily negate the idea of flask having an API for jazz code
and then load additional resources, but he thinks it might be worth considering when
you consider server side rendering.
You're not having it though.
It's not that I'm not having it, it's that this has existed for a very long time.
It's not a new idea and this is how everything like ERB and flask and ginger or I guess ginger
would be the flask version of ERB.
It's how it all works.
The server side builds the page and puts it down to the shithole that is the web.
I mean, JavaScript is a language that should not exist.
I have written large things in JavaScript.
I have had to just delete them and I've lost tens of thousands of dollars.
You need a better language.
Well, I can't argue with you.
I'm not going to be, I'm not, I'm not going to die on this hill for this one.
It's I get what you're saying, man, like it's convenient for what you're doing, but it's,
it's not good.
Like it's, it's just, geez, you know, I'm not even going to go into the history of server
side rendering, but it's not a new idea and it doesn't need to be JavaScript.
JavaScript is deeply compromised language we could say.
It's not a pure language that has a fundamental philosophy, elegance, purity.
We could say, you know, say qua machismo, even I'm just off the top of my head.
I'm thinking of a language, your, my criteria, and that might be objective C obviously be
a good language.
JavaScript is a bad language.
I think the fat cat proposes we ban JavaScript from the chat, promise you can't ban JavaScript
just like you can't cure herpes.
It just won't go away.
He said, and then Java Jack says JavaScript is what happens when there's no competition
in browser languages, spicy chat room tonight.
Coder radio happy hour.
I am sorry.
I did start it tonight, but my moaning before the show, yes.
You know, that's why you got to show up live so that way you can catch the moaning at jblive.tv
on a Monday, lino.com slash coder, receive a $100 safety day credit towards your new
account.
Yeah, a hundred dollars, a hundred dollars.
And you support the show.
Linode is awesome.
It's powerful.
And you can simplify your cloud infrastructure with Linode's great prices and modern Linux
virtual machines and tools to develop, deploy and scale applications faster and easier than
ever.
And what I love about Linode is they are independent.
We've been around since 2003 and they are in full control.
They set their own ISP up.
They run their data centers.
They have 11 of them around the world.
Super fast connections, super fast native SSDs, and of course, 40 gigabit connections
coming into each one of those machines.
Linode can really help your ideas come to life on the web too.
If you want to set up a personal portfolio, maybe you want to put a resume online that
looks nice or a status pager.
Maybe you want to host the backend infrastructure for your community's chat platform or something
even else that, heck, I don't really know because I'm not you, but I know Linode can
do it.
They have a full range of systems, dedicated CPUs, dedicated GPUs, $5 a month systems.
They're great and they're 30 to 50% cheaper than the big shops like Azure or that AWS
you may have heard of.
And they have features similar like S3 compatible object storage, cloud firewalls, simple one-click
application deployment, and a lot more.
So you should probably just go check it out for yourself and see why they are our cloud
hosting provider of choice.
Everything we've built and all of the things we have continued to build, it's just really
gotten pretty, pretty awesome.
I should do a machine count at some point.
We run it all on Linode and you can too, linode.com slash coder.
I found them a few years ago, started as just something I was doing on my own as a personal
thing and now I use them for everything and you can too and you can support the show while
getting that $100 credit at linode.com slash coder.
All right, now it's time to talk about it.
The Supreme Court has ruled in Google's favor in the copyright dispute with Oracle over
the use of the, I think it was like 11,000 lines of code or something.
Yeah, it takes back to 2010 when Oracle bought the Java, well bought Sun, and then Java came
along with it.
I looked back at our archives.
This is the story that we've been covering for.
Oh yeah, remember Oracle claimed that Google owed them $8.8 billion and $475 million in
lost potential licensing revenue and then in 2016 a jury found that Google's use of
that structure and sequence and organization of Java APIs was fair use but then the Court
of Appeals and the Federal Circuit overturned that decision into Oracle's favor and it just
went back and forth what felt like forever.
And to be fair, I was initially on Oracle's side because Google literally copy pasted
some of the headers and everything.
But not that they couldn't use the API but that they should pay some damages for literally
copy pasta.
Right.
Come on.
Yeah, it was and the thing I think that we thought was pretty damning was the emails
from the executives that kind of just said we're going to do this and we're either going
to have to license it or fight them in court one day.
If you remember and I did my research today, I actually did my job today, Chris, you should
pat me on the back.
Thank you.
Just for you.
I rang the bell.
They could have used C sharp for free, but because they hated Microsoft, they wouldn't
do it.
Right?
Yeah.
And there was the sense back then.
I mean, you remember back then when they were first starting Android, like the sense was
that the whole world of these devices were going to run on Java.
Well, hang on.
If we're going back, there's only one gentleman that can help us.
Perfect.
I was thinking Deckard Cain, but you went a different direction.
Oh, oh, you mean you like you want to go.
You want to share.
So that's that's that's story time.
Stay a while and listen.
Back in the day, Microsoft was actually a scary company, but now they're a little hippie
company that runs Azure, but they used to put companies out of business.
Yeah, kids, Microsoft was actually scary at one point.
Yeah.
And I guess there was also this feeling at Google that like Microsoft was the big bad
guy.
The world was going to run all these like I remember Blu-ray players back then were
running Java.
Like everything was going to be Java based.
Everything that Microsoft did was bad.
And I think that they figured, well, we'll we'll we'll swoop up a huge amount of developers
who can already target our platform.
That'll get us in the race against Apple as fast as possible.
From India that are cheap, yes.
But yeah, you and I both thought, boy, Oracle could win this, but it would be bad if they
did.
And I actually thought there was a good shot that Oracle was going to win.
I couldn't really comprehend what the knock on effects of that would be.
But so it's on tape, right?
Like I was pretty pissed about this because I felt like just stealing Java.
The problem was Google was kind of right, but I didn't like what they were doing because
this is going to sound super old managed, but Objective C at the time requiring memory
management allowed me just to charge a lot of money that made me very happy.
It seemed like they knew there was some questionable activity to it.
Like they kind of had a sense that maybe they were in a gray area.
Well, in their emails, they knew.
What we have here is kind of like a half decision, though, because the question is are APIs copyrightable?
That's been skirted by the court here.
They focused on fair use and they didn't really establish the copyright precedent.
It's like the case establishes a precedent that if you're copying an API and its primary
purpose is matching interface so the developers can re-implement it, you're in fair use territory,
which it doesn't really answer the primary question of the copyright violation.
So I have a service that copies the API for AWS S3.
I have not talked about this on the show because.
Oh, you mean you really do?
I really do.
For real.
Oh, okay.
That's theoretical.
I've seen Bezos' pecker, let's say.
Thank you, Reddit.
And I'm pretty sure he would slam that right up my bum.
No, you can, I mean, you can.
I run an object storage.
Right now, right?
I could have the exact same programmable interface and my whole thing I do with this is go to
people that are spending a lot of money on S3 so we can set you up in our data center.
Literally, you change the API keys, you change the endpoint, the secret key, all that nonsense
and bam, you're saving thousands of dollars a year.
Yeah, and it can also, like in some cases, yeah, you work with a smaller business that
can be more hands-on, that can be more attentive.
And we can offer you added custom benefits, like whatever crazy stuff you need.
So like I'm spiritually on the side of Oracle with this, but I felt like Google was so brazen
in how they did it.
I mean, we listened to the back catalog, folks.
I was pretty rough on Google.
And Chris was, I mean, Chris said Microsoft was great and we should all run Windows Vista
at the time.
So I don't know.
I mean, like, and I did that like every episode, it was weird.
I just want to say YouTube, Google, I'm sorry, Windows Action Show.
Yeah, joking aside, I feel like I sort of, this is anti-climactic in a way, right?
It doesn't matter.
Nothing happened.
Yeah, I mean, well, it matters.
I think it matters in that if it had gone the other way, then it meant that implementing
an identical API could have set precedent that that is a copyrightable court case that
you could pursue.
What are you talking about?
When I was 19, I tried to open Mercury Broadcasting.
But you know what I mean, like if Oracle had won, it would have set a precedent that other
companies could have sued other individuals who have re-implemented their APIs.
Well, hang on.
If Oracle had won, then Minio as an open source project would fail, and as a company.
Oracle database, which was a clone of IBM database right from the interface layer, would
itself be invalid.
Because let's Deckard Cain style go back here.
Oracle's original business was being a clone of IBM's proprietary databases, but a little
cheaper.
Yeah, I hadn't thought it.
You're right.
I hadn't thought about that in a while.
This is the courtesan calling the prostitute a whore.
I mean, this is not right.
Yeah, it is kind of, you know, but I guess companies change, I suppose.
But there is some irony in that.
It's very simple.
When you're small, you have to work outside the law because you have nothing to lose.
When you're big, like by the way, we don't talk about this on this show because Unfilter
exists.
But Facebook suggesting internet regulations is like the Nazis suggesting housing regulations.
It's just not good.
You don't want it.
Yeah, they have lobbyists.
So that's something they can shape.
When I think about my feelings over the last nearly a decade of this thing, I think a piece
of me wanted Google to have to pay some penance for the stunt they pulled with Android.
I can't ever forgive them for Android.
It is a bastardization of Linux that is horrible.
And they made so many decisions in the name of adoption.
It just doesn't work.
Well, you go back to, remember, they were going with something that was cursor driven
until they saw the iPhone event and then they switched to their Moonshot project, which
was touch driven.
But Android, when it first shipped, you could still dig out the cursor.
It was very much still very touch focused.
How about Project Butter?
Right.
All the time, all the times they had to address the performance.
They slapped together this system that was horribly unoptimized.
I mean, the early versions of Android were really bad because it was not native code
running on these.
So folks who are younger won't remember these ARM processors on mobile were back in the
day.
They were terrible.
Really bad.
Yeah.
The reason iPhone programming was hard and I got to make lots of money doing it is because
you had no memory.
It was terrible.
Loading images in a list view or UI scroll view, if you will, was actually like you.
People had different strategies and I'm sure you can find them on Reddit.
There were blog posts debating what is the right way to load images on iOS because you
didn't have the memory to do it.
Come on.
You know this is true.
Oh yeah.
And it was so much worse on Android.
And then you'll recall, I don't need to recap history, but the incredible compromises they
made with carriers to get great sweetheart deals with the carriers to compete with the
iPhone, like allowing carriers to bastardize up the firmwares with their crappy apps and
tracking that they crossed all these lines in the name of adoption that I felt like created
a product that didn't learn anything from the Windows PC OEM era that makes shipping
updates easy and fast and secure.
And we ended up with an OS that's now in reality in the pockets of millions of consumers with
out of date Linux kernels, out of date Bluetooth stacks, tons of vulnerabilities, vendors who
stopped patching because they didn't have some driver licensing deal that went beyond
two years so they couldn't supply updates past that.
And so now it just gets no fixes and it just sits there open on the internet every single
day.
And there are millions of them.
And then you bring in all of the crap around this that this Oracle suit, which was another
example of Google cutting corners to try to get fast, quick adoption to slam something
into the market.
So then that way they could get all of these hardware manufacturers to switch over to their
crappy platform and have a horrible fight race to the bottom.
LG, by the way, just announced this week they're out of the smartphone business entirely.
That's all Google had.
Google dumped an operating system on the market that drove the value down, that created a
race to the bottom, that created manufacturers to make these horrible deals, these totally
unsupported phones, and now the market is awash in them.
And what makes me sick about it is it's all on the back of Linux.
Linux is at the core of all of these and it's a bastardization of what is a beautiful operating
system that could deliver a secure, free user experience and instead has been perverted
by Google for this use, all while getting their backs patted by the open source community,
loving them every step of the way for their open source stance and their open source support
and their summer of code.
And so we never questioned the almighty Google, even though they've taken the beautiful platform
that is Linux and they've weaponized it as a tracking platform as, and now not intentionally,
an exploit paradise.
But it's all on the back of Linux and I hate it.
They've turned it into slow, the fact that they spent years trying to perfect a goddamn
scroll view.
I'm sorry, but no, I know it seems like I'm being mean, but that is a stupid problem to
have.
Yeah, it's just been a bad product.
And you know what, by the time they finally get it fairly decent, which it's in a pretty
good state now, I enjoy my Pixel, but it's still not as good as iOS.
You know what, if somebody comes to me with a business ID and they have an Android, I
just ignore them.
You just decide right there.
Oh, they got an Android wear watch.
I won't let them in the door.
And I'm not even joking.
I've read VC posts.
People say if a founder comes to me as an Android, no, I don't know how I feel about
that.
It's about taste and you can look that up.
I feel like they've done a better job with Chrome OS that was just brought up by the
chat room.
I feel like that's been better managed by Google from OS, you know what the good mobile
OS was?
Yeah.
Web OS.
Web OS was never going to happen.
Windows Phone 8.
No, it had a registry, dude.
It's out right there.
If it has a registry, it's not on my, it's not going in my pocket.
This is not happening.
Yeah, but web OS was actually the good one and come on.
It was from HP.
It was never going to happen.
For some reason, the Google YouTube algorithm thingy decided to show me commercials of the
Compaq iPack from that era.
So the late nineties, I guess, in my feed and for whatever reason it was right and I
watched it and man, I had one of those.
I actually really liked it.
If you were in that ecosystem and you had like the exchange integration, it was, it
was pretty cool.
I just want to say I was a Windows 95 power user.
Oh yeah.
Did you actually, you know, you gotta get the plus pack then so that way you get the
themes and stuff.
Oh no, I upgraded from 3.1.
And then, and then you had to get the Windows 95 like OSR 2 or whatever it was where they
added USB support.
I couldn't do it.
I was on Windows 95.
But then I got a gateway.
Oh yeah.
Cowbox.
Yep.
Fuckin' the CAS bar.
But then I upgraded to Windows 98.
What's wrong?
Maybe it was great.
Didn't work?
It was slow.
Oh yeah.
You definitely felt it back then.
Felt it.
Especially on low end systems.
You, you and my systems were low.
Yeah.
You felt the pain.
Yeah, you really felt it.
Mm hmm.
Yeah.
It was one of those things where like we were, you know, reminds me of the email we got earlier
in the show.
It's like you have no idea back then.
I mean, it sold new machines.
People would just buy it back then when a new Windows would come out.
That's when people just buy entirely new PCs with Windows preloaded on it.
Then I sort of skipped Vista because I wasn't crazy.
Then I went to seven.
Then I went to Mac and Linux.
And I'm not going to talk about the machine I'm on now because people will send me hate
mail.
Well, besides, you got to replace that thing anyway.
It's got those dirty x86 processors in it, right?
I've done some benchmarks on my MacBook Air.
It's not great.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
Oh good.
Let's do a little anti-M1 for a moment.
So the iMac Pro crushed it, huh?
No, no, no.
Oh, no, that's not what happened.
Oh, damn it.
It's the iMac Pro has a beautiful screen.
Uh-huh.
Yeah.
But did it beat it on the CPU test?
Tell me it beat the M1.
It's my special little computer and I love it very much.
You're not answering the question, which I think means that it didn't.
Oh, I didn't need to hear that.
Unless the GPU becomes involved.
Ah, yeah, sure.
The air is faster.
Number one out for the x86.
Honestly if I was Intel CEO right now, I would not be making snarky commercials with Justin
Long.
I would be at the bar crying.
That might be my character flaw.
Maybe you can do both, you know, but he is the CEO of Intel.
You can probably do both.
But do you need Justin Long?
I mean.
No.
No, it does.
It's bad too, right?
I mean, the funny thing is, is like you're so he's he's essentially getting on products
that still are shipping with Intel processors and like they still I mean the whole thing's
like they're making funny.
They're making fun of MacBooks, but they're still MacBooks selling with Intel processors.
It was an awkward moment.
Like I just want to say making an advertising campaign campaign dunking on one of your biggest
customers seems super stupid to me.
I don't know.
Yeah.
What do we know?
Datadog.com slash coder radio.
You know what?
Get your code level performance, get it across your entire environment, the whole stack and
troubleshoot issues faster with Datadog.
Datadog's continuous profiler does something amazing.
It automatically collects profiles from your production servers and your applications all
the time so you can analyze any data from any source at any point in time quickly with
minimal overhead and then pop, get it a whole unified picture with their beautiful dashboards
correlated with code performance metrics and other monitoring data from your servers in
these real time beautiful dashboards.
You got to go to datadog.com slash coder radio to see these dashboards and when you're there,
you sign up for a 14 day free trial and you will get a free t-shirt after you create one
of those beautiful dashboards.
You get the dashboard beauty and the t-shirt, but you got to go to datadog.com slash coder
radio for that.
See the log management, the tracing, that continuous profiler in action and see how
great it is to bring it all into one platform.
Datadog enables you to pinpoint the root cause of issues faster than ever and it's a tool
to help you communicate.
Go try Datadog's products for free.
Get that 14 day trial by visiting datadog.com slash coder radio and for a limited time,
if you start a trial and you create that one dashboard, you'll get that free Datadog t-shirt
free swag.
Are you going over to the WWDC website right now to make your plans because it's been announced.
We now know it's going to be virtual again this year.
They are leaning in hard on the Craig Federighi staring at his laptop in a weird way and they've
announced it'll be June 7th to the 11th for the all online program open to everybody free
at no cost and even if you're not a Apple developer or even interested in any particular
thing from Apple, it's kind of fascinating to watch this from a production standpoint
because boy howdy, if these aren't just the peak of virtual conference production, like
nobody does it like these guys do.
They also this year are doing a Swift student challenge and they're going to have additional
details on that.
So teaching the young ones the Swift, it's a big focus at WWDC.
Gotta get the young ones learned up.
I guess if you hate children, that might be a thing you would do.
No, but I mean, I obviously would love someone to look at me like Craig Federighi looks at
the MacBook Air.
I mean, who doesn't want that?
And yes, I'm going to WWDC and no, I don't think there's going to be AR glasses because
battery life.
This is the shit about the Apple community that is so annoying.
The incessant yammering on about like VR goggles or AR or will Apple build a car?
Like get over yourselves.
Like who just wait and see what they ship.
Like this is like the community.
There's so much palace intrigue type stories and rumor mill and they have a giant processor
transition they're doing.
Yeah, they are not shipping.
And first of all, the glasses have a particular problem of the boundaries of physics with
battery life.
And unless they have some amazing battery technology, which honestly, if they have it,
they should license it to everybody because that would change humanity.
Really?
Yeah.
Let's share it.
Share it with the world, right?
Seriously.
No, no, no.
I'm not being a dick to get such battery capacity in such a small package would be a significant
leap in like actual battery physics, right?
Actual like the science of storing energy that would be different, like they would be
dunking on Elon Musk like he was the, you know, junior university basketball team in
their shack.
But if we return to reality, they don't have that.
There's not going to be air glasses.
So it's so annoying.
If you think if this isn't just the way they shouldn't just do this, because I'll tell
you what, man, you get a lot more information this way because you don't have to pay a thousand
dollars to go.
It makes it way more accessible to people that are considering getting in development.
It makes it way more accessible to children specifically who could never get access to
this stuff because they sometimes, you know, they're not old enough to have credit cards
and whatnot.
I think like there is a big net benefit to make this open to all.
And instead of this, like this, like exclusive, only like two thousand people to four thousand
people can make it there.
And it's a thousand dollar ticket and the price is only going to go up because there's
less and less space available.
I appreciate the value of those in-person events.
You know me, I really understand the value.
But this seems like a net improvement for everyone because even a casual like me can
attend these and I can feel more informed and I like to have the technical details of
things.
I am conflicted.
As a dev, I feel like the online format is better.
But as a sales guy or like a business owner, I guess, which is really a glorified sales
guy, right?
There's something about the conference, like pub scene, you know, the hall track, right?
Having said that, WWDC, I mean, I don't want to be too negative.
If there's a good API that I think I could build a cool app on, I'm going to do it.
Absolutely.
Right.
And I'm going to walk this whole thing and I'm going to be on the hunt for something
like that.
But my entire problem, like I'm a, you know, you know this, Chris, I'm a huge iPad believer.
But the problems are Apple's policies, not the technology.
I mean, I don't want to say I'm not going to build something on iOS because obviously
you know me, I get excited and I do something and then I don't ship it because I'm crazy.
Coder bytes is not coming because of trademark reasons, by the way.
So it will be something else.
Oh, man.
We'll get another.
I'm sure there'll be another name out there that'll work.
It's going to be a coder balls inappropriate.
Past Mike was wise, you know, past Mike was much calmer.
No, but I mean, are you excited for WWDC?
I mean, I kind of don't give a crap.
No, I actually am.
I am.
It's the home pods.
It's the it's the it's the cumulative radiation from all those home pods.
OK, no, it's not the home pods.
But I think they I think they're delivering.
I think the iOS platform is looking better than ever.
I find it fascinating.
The last couple of WWDCs we've seen them allow some major changes to iOS we hadn't seen in
the past.
I think the M1 platform is going to get iterated on.
That'll be interesting.
And then I think they'll probably send me into some sort of existential crisis and panic
when I worry that Linux users will leave us all.
But you know, I've I've calmed down.
I've calmed down.
I think I think there is a good a good portion of Linux users out there who will never be
swayed by the shinies of Apple, regardless of what they do.
And I have good news for those of us on the platform, Mike.
This has been sorely needed, a library that essentially plays a role in just defining
the visual language of a GNOME application.
You want to make a GNOME application.
You can use Lib Adwaitia to now do that, sort of like elementary OS's Granite.
This is going to be something that's available to all GTK developers.
It'll track specific releases with GNOME.
So you can target like a GNOME 40 look or a GNOME 42 look, and they'll include guidelines
as well as code.
And the idea will be a library that kind of grows over time that gives developers an ability
to get some of the basics of a standard GNOME application without having to lay out every
single button themselves and decide where it all goes.
It's like the missing library that the desktop environment needed to get application developers
started quicker.
Yay.
Here I come.
I bring my nice little thing and I say, look, Daddy, they finally did it.
They fixed the complaint of yours.
And you give me nothing.
You you smack it out of my hand and you just tell me to piss off.
Well, let me ask you, how many users are going to pay for that software you built with that
library?
Oh, well, OK.
I mean, there's, you know.
Yeah.
OK.
All right.
I admit I acknowledge the payment.
Things a little tricky.
I grant.
Tricky.
It's tricky.
I would call it the battle.
Hmm.
Look, battle.
Hang on.
The six day now.
Hmm.
Hang on.
What was the complete route?
Oh, the Alamo.
Oh, yeah.
Actually, the Alamo, they held up for a while.
Hang on.
Well, a lot of apps do and then they finally fall.
That does happen.
Oh, it's France in World War Two.
Right down.
Sorry, French people.
I'm not sorry.
My stepfather is French.
So you know what we need is we need somebody, somebody to help me prove Mike wrong.
If you're if you're writing Linux applications for the desktop right now and you're making
profits off from it.
I bought a Linux developers company for less than a month of my current rep.
So.
So tell me.
I want to.
We're talking desktop Linux here.
Yeah.
Somebody making a desktop Linux app.
Remail it and tell us.
I'm a desktop Linux developer and you are making more than seventy five thousand dollars
a year selling exclusive only selling exclusive desktop Linux apps.
Only.
Why would you limit yourself?
Why not make yourself?
I mean, what if I think Linux has to represent a significant portion of revenue, but to limit
it to only seems.
No, no, no, no.
You got to make at least seventy five thousand on desktop Linux apps.
I will.
And I'm doing this publicly on tape to challenge right now.
I and the Mad about our ink will sell you or not sell you, give you a Thalia from system
seventy six brand new for you and a quarter radio robe if Chris can get off his ass and
actually ship them.
And if you can't do that, we'll give you stickers and a poster because I guarantee that no one
exists.
And when I say developer, I mean, an independent developer, a small team, not you.
You can't say, hey, I work at Red Hat and I listen to the show and ha ha ha or, you
know, my sister brothers.
I want an indie indie developer selling an app.
I don't care what it is.
And then if OK, so if you win, you essentially don't have to give away Thalia.
But if you lose, you got to ship somebody a computer.
But if I if I lose, what are you going to give them, Chris?
J.B. should support the Linux developer community.
Right.
The Mad Vodder is already in maybe like a swag box of like retro swag or something.
Maybe in the Mad Vodder partner, I'll I'll buy you the very expensive computer and he'll
give you some stickers.
That sounds about right.
No, no, no.
It'll be a high value.
It'll be is the highest value I can fit in the box.
I just don't know which size box it is yet.
Highest value thing he has is the rope.
Those ropes are.
Yes.
Basically, they should be sewn in gold at this point.
I just I know we did this at the beginning of the show.
What were you thinking?
And I thought I thought it was a challenge to myself and also saying, come on, right
into the show.
You know that this can't be done.
I think it's.
Yeah, I think it is.
I I God, I would love to.
I would.
What?
OK, if I recall, I actually hired a desktop Linux developer for less than my current rent.
You know, we need to do is we've got to like set like a limit because what if like three
dudes right in?
No, just one.
The first one who does it?
No, no, no.
It's first to the finish.
But you're not even worried about that.
That's not going to be a problem.
It's not going to happen.
And I want to see receipts where to sell them.
And it can't be like steam, right?
It has to be verifiable Linux desktop sales.
So Ubuntu Software Center, hang on, I'm going to go laugh my ass off on you.
Elementary what about the Elementary App Center?
I'm a big fan of Cassidy and Daniel, but nobody's making seventy five thousand dollars.
OK, you can also not be Cassidy and Daniel because I'm sure they have.
But all right.
You may not be the platform vendor yourself.
Coder dot show slash contact for that.
Last Mike's mess hall Christmas.
I got I mean, I got you know, I got I got a lot of gear.
I should just start throwing that stuff in boxes.
So if you'd like to help support whatever this is, you can become a Coder QA team member.
Coder QA dot go.
You support the show.
You get a limited ad feed and we have a Coderly that will be coming soon.
So if you haven't signed up yet, you can get it when it releases, go to Coder QA dot co.
And then when the Coderly is recorded and posted, you'll automatically get it in your
feed along with the limited ad feed.
Or you can download it manually to we also post available for manuals downloads there
for them.
Coder QA because we love our members.
So thank you, everybody over there.
Boy, if you want to win a Thalia and you make five thousand dollars or more by selling software
on the Linux desktop, go to Coder dot show slash contact or you just like to give us
feedback.
We're seventy five thousand, not five thousand.
OK, yeah, right.
It's a big difference, like a big difference.
It's a real bit.
So like it's rogue Amoeba versus some assholes selling a counting thing that he sold, if
I recall, five hundred dollars worth of licenses.
Yeah, you can find Mike.
He's at Dumanuco on the Twitters.
His company is at the Mad Botter Inc.
I'm there to Chris LAS.
I don't tweet much, but I try to respond.
The network is that Jupiter signal where you can get announcements and news and same with
the show at Coder Radio show.
How about that?
Links to what we talked about today are Coder dot show slash four oh eight over there.
You're going to find that contact form as well as our RSS feed links, really kind of
all the resources, all the resources.
And then you go to Jupiter Broadcasting Dotcom and holy smokes, there's like a whole bunch
of other shows, including Linux Unplugged 400, which landed this week.
That's pretty great, too.
You could join us live.
That's Coder Happy Hour at five p.m. Pacific, eight p.m. Eastern at JBLive.TV, and we'd
love to have you join us in the chat room or watch live and chat right along.
It makes a lot of fun for us.
Thanks so much for tuning in to this week's episode of the Coder Radio program, and we'll
see you right back here next week.