This is KOTOR Radio, episode 469 for June 6, 2022.
Hello friend, welcome back to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and the business, the software development, and the world of technology.
Positioned right up here from the sunny Pacific Northwest, we're joined as always by our
host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike.
Hello Chris, and your brother in good hair was spending some time with us earlier.
He's sort of the hair king really, isn't he?
Really the lord of the hair.
The hair force one, you could say.
Something else, I tell you what.
Yeah, I also am wearing my uniform.
You like my new, look at that, huh?
Pretty snazzy Star Trek uniform I got here.
I decided now you can just call me Captain Pike.
Well, I have to tell you, I have seen all but the most recent episode of Strange New
Worlds, and with apologies to President Roslin.
I'm in love again.
Oh, really?
Number one, if you will.
If number one, yeah.
Of course.
I know you.
For me, I'm kind of a nurse chapel guy myself.
I could see that, because you're a little more quirky over there.
I'm like, no, I want some command presence.
But you know, to tell you the truth, I am pretty impressed with this new Star Trek series.
You and I recently got on here, and we were yelling at the clouds about the new Star Trek
and the kids that write it, and then Strange New Worlds comes along, and they haven't screwed
it up so far.
Yeah, it's really good.
Isn't it the same writers?
It's mostly the same team, but you know, I've been thinking about this.
Why is it so much better, right?
Why is it better?
And I think I've got a few reasons.
I think number one, they had to break out of their mystery box formula, because it isn't
one overarching story where they build and make more and more intense as the season goes
on.
The problem there, that I always have with Picard and Discovery, is they don't deliver
when they build and they build and they build, and then they just don't deliver.
The ending, like the season finale, it's always such a mediocre delivery.
But with the episodic nature of Strange New Worlds, they can't do that.
They can't just keep opening mystery box after mystery box.
They kind of have to keep it tidy per episode, and they're doing character arc stuff.
But that, I think, has been a big limiter, and I think it's forced them to solve a big
issue that a lot of us had with it.
I think number two, they're working with legitimate source material, right?
This is a 50-year-old pilot they're working with here.
The source material was created by the original team.
It isn't a whole cloth creation like Discovery and Picard are.
Yeah, I mean, they can't have that much source material, can they, though?
They've got to be doing something.
I mean, you've got Spock, you've got Ohura, you've got the Enterprise, you've got Pike,
you've got the Era, you've got all of the stuff that we know about that Era, like the
Klingons, the Romulans, right?
It really provides them, yet it's like a framework.
But because it's so vague, like you kind of just said, there's also a lot they can... It's
sort of like the perfect balance for this new writing team, I think.
This is my theory, at least.
This is... Because you want to look at it almost from a product development standpoint,
because the first couple of versions, Picard and Discovery they launched, I think don't
hold up as products.
I think they had systemic problems.
But then they got this one so far, they've got it right.
Now, they could still screw it up.
But what changed, right?
And was it an institutional thing?
Was it a leadership change?
Was it a team change?
Was it new constraints that just forced a better outcome?
Sometimes it's that.
But I can't help but think, what changed?
What made it a better product?
That I think there's a lesson in there for anybody.
I wonder if it's that we all know how the story with Captain Pike goes.
I think the fans would have an uproar if they did some alternate universe BS and saved him,
right?
I don't know, 40-year-old spoilers, I guess?
Yeah, actually I think it's near 50, actually.
Near 50-year-old spoilers?
Maybe.
Dude doesn't do well.
I mean, he does... Well, it ends badly.
I don't know.
I like it.
I will say, I loved the first couple episodes of Picard, and then I was just like, this
is very... There's just a lot of nothing happening here.
There is that.
So they are right at the point where sometimes New Trek loses me.
I don't know.
It was really good.
And I know this episode I haven't seen yet, Shoreleaf, and I just want to hope that they
have those statues on Ryza.
Oh, is that the next episode?
Huh.
Okay, I haven't seen that.
Oh, maybe I'm not behind.
They come out on Thursdays, don't they?
Yeah.
So it'll be the day after this episode comes out.
So we're recording on Monday.
Today was WWDC 2022.
Yes, we all returned to the mothership.
I am totally discombobulated because I didn't get in until right before the stream starts.
So this is going to be a focus show is what I like to call it.
And I think, you know what you and I need to figure out, which we could have talked
about earlier.
But we got to figure out when we're going to do a double because you're traveling and
I'm traveling soon.
So I was thinking maybe like the next thing we record is a feedback special.
I was thinking that or or we shouldn't be doing this on the air.
I don't think.
But why not?
Production meeting time.
I do have that dev one.
Oh, I think we should talk about that today, possibly today.
First impression.
All right.
Yeah.
First impressions today.
But we'll chat more.
We might actually need to prerecord two episodes.
I don't know.
But you and I'll sync up.
So I don't have much feedback for today's episode.
But I thought we'd start with a couple of WWDC highlights and what kind of just work
through what you and I found interesting.
Apple mentioned right at the top they have thirty four million developers.
That's a lot.
A hundred dollar a year subscriptions.
I'm sure some of those are free, but thirty four million devs is their biggest number
ever.
They really went all in on Craig Federici this year.
They have like glorious Mission Impossible meets Air Force One.
I actually loved all of them.
They were so on the on the edge of being too much.
But I loved him, especially that one where he super ran like speed and put his hair back.
I might have a man crush on Craig Federici.
The only problem is when he tries to be earnest and he tries to be earnest about your privacy
and stuff like that.
I don't buy it anymore.
I also don't buy his epic basketball shot.
I don't think he made it across town.
OK.
That's where they went too far.
Is the the Swift a track suit?
Yeah.
It was too far.
It was too much.
I feel like that conference where I watched Craig Federici try to claim that, you know,
any kind of sideloading at all would hurt mom and grandma.
It changed forever how I see that guy now.
Like when I see him get all earnest about safety, I just don't really buy it.
It seems like he's acting.
I also thought the Tim Cook stuff seemed a little rushed.
It was just boom Tim Cook.
He was kind of going like he needed another couple of takes.
This was like his first or second take of the read and he was rushing through it.
They didn't treat the audio.
So there's because I'm listening on my studio headphones.
There's a crazy echo on Tim's audio.
They did and they've shot in those locations before without that problem.
And Tim Cook just kind of he just he blazes through the beginning and he blazes through
the end.
They were both clearly shot at the same location at the same exact time of day.
They got like 20 minutes with Tim this time and they just rushed it.
And I find that wild considering this is their most public thing they do now.
I feel like Craig Federighi is just kind of better at the kind of silly, you know, showman
stuff.
Oh, no doubt about it.
Craig's the better showman.
But Tim's previous introductions were much more produced like they were the camera shots
were better.
The audio was better.
Tim's reads were better.
You know, when you're working with somebody who's not familiar with any of that stuff,
they generally need a couple of passes at it before they get a real natural on camera
read.
I didn't really bother with that with the intro or the outro.
And he didn't show up at all in the rest of the video.
Just an interesting observation, I thought.
Probably fine.
I felt like there was an overall theme to this WWDC.
And not to be cliche, but I really felt this WWDC theme was finally like we're finally
getting this stuff.
Some of it it's like I'm kind of angry.
It's only now arriving and some of it's you know, it's great to see it here.
Like they made a big start with the new lock screen.
It looks great.
It reminds me of watch customizations.
But I can't believe we're 10 years into this thing.
We're finally getting this.
Yes.
And the whole profiles thing, which is directly related to the to the lock screen is I looked
it up was a feature of WebOS way back in the day.
Yeah.
And different Android vendors took cracks at this, too.
Generally, Apple does a better implementation when they do.
And they one thing I liked is right off the top.
They're like API for this API for this.
Like the new lock screen, there's a live activities API, the new focus mode.
There's now a focus filter API that extends into apps.
You know, that kind of stuff.
Right.
There's now a new shared with you API for messages so you can reach into their new APIs
for dictation, new APIs for maps.
They just boom, boom, boom, boom.
Every time in the beginning, it didn't keep going like this, but at the very beginning
of the keynote, everything they announced, they said, and there's an API for it.
That's good to see.
That feels right.
Like that's how they should be at a developer conference.
And the one thing that I noticed and I'm curious your thoughts on this.
They are really clever with their messages strategy.
And I think most of the chat room that was watching live didn't get it.
Messages has been this steady iteration of improvements.
A lot of times it's like features other stuff have had like marker group thread as unread.
They just got that.
But it works, doesn't it?
Because you don't want to move the gas pedal on the average user.
And this is an average user app.
Yeah.
I mean, we've been schooled by the younger folks that listen or about the whole green
bubble thing, right?
So I mean, I, you know, I'm notorious for typos and it was funny when he did the one
that said, babe and Gabe, I've done something very similar and you just want to change that,
right?
You just want to like have that not be like something that can come back, you know, 10
years.
Well, I had an embarrassing type.
One of my dad that was one of those things, you know, I was like, oh my God, sorry dad.
Yeah.
It's good to see that stuff.
I suppose.
I think in general, Apple has pretty good family stuff, but I think they finally address
the shared photo album.
We've gotten questions into the show about this and this isn't too revolutionary, but
the idea is that it looks like it's going to use some like face ID.
Yeah.
I mean like identifying the faces in the photo albums, it's going to use location information.
It's going to use your family sharing settings and a feature that I think is clever when
you're in the camera app taking the picture, there'll be a little indication if this is
a photo that's going to your private library or your family library and you can tap to
toggle that.
Nothing really, no developer story here, but I actually really like this from an end user's
perspective because I've got devices I'm taking pictures with, my wife does, now my kids do
and Angela does.
We're all in one family sharing group.
We are constantly trying to figure out best ways to share photos.
And of course, it's all synced to iCloud and backed up.
I mean, for average users, these are table stakes features that again, finally-
Yep.
I mean, I feel the parental control stuff I think was good.
Maybe not super interesting for the show, but it goes into your family sharing thing
right easily.
Oh, you know, every couple of years, kid has to get a new iPad because weirdly enough,
schools use them now, right?
But you want to lock that stuff down if it is not school issued.
Yeah.
And it looks like you're going to be able to set that up up front now, right?
Up front and be able to control it from your device rather than have to be like, give me
the thing.
I got to go into settings, blah, blah, blah.
Yeah.
And a little NFC setup too, so you can bring your phone to their iPad and start just setting
it up automatically.
Yep.
Love it.
I like the kind of just when we jumped over the new shared with you API, depending on
how robust that is, that could be really cool when you tie it to shortcuts, right?
Or even just like automation workflows.
You know, oh, get me all the pictures that grandma sent, right?
I'm in a very family oriented boat apparently right now, but you could see how that could
really just ease a lot of the like, ah, copy, paste, blah, blah, blah, go back, get another
one, copy, paste.
Yeah.
And it'd be a great way to just make sure you're always grabbing the photos and backing
them up and you're not accidentally letting them expire and lose them.
And yeah, especially when you pair with automation, I can see that really nice.
There was one that our chat room was like, I think the most universally against one of
the announcements.
And this was the full CarPlay takeover, your, all your dash, your whole dashboard, everything.
How often does it, I can tell you from my experience, my phone dies all the time, right?
If I'm running around going from place to place.
And also that seems really distracting to me.
I have no doubt they would build in some sort of can't edit while you're moving feature,
you know, accelerometer detects movement.
They just disable editing.
Ford's going to have to build their own UI.
I guess I have to be like, you don't have your iPhone with you fall back to something
sane.
Oh man, that means this is going to suck, right?
I hadn't.
Of course.
So that was like 20 manufacturers are claiming they're going to support this.
I'll play devil's advocate and just say, you know, I, I agree that CarPlay is a mandatory
feature or Android auto if I'm using the Android because ultimately it is a much better experience
than anything that the vendors provide.
And like one of the reasons why I don't really want a Tesla is because I can't do CarPlay
on it.
And I know that sounds crazy and I'd probably get over it, but I love having my podcasts
and my nav and everything can be on my phone.
I can look a route up on my phone.
I can download podcasts on a phone, all that stuff you can do on your phone and then I
can just go plug it into my dash and I have all of it on the screen of my car.
I love that.
Uh, I could see it being a better experience than what any manufacturer is going to make,
but you're right.
They could never depend on it.
So of course it's going to be like an application that's running on the vendor's platform.
I don't know.
It does make you think maybe Apple does have some like division internally that's doing
car stuff.
Even if it's just for these kinds of products and not ever going to result in an actual
car.
Could be.
Yeah.
I personally super excited to see them spend so much time talking about matter up on stage.
Matter is a multi-vendor home automation protocol basically, and it includes Amazon and Google
and Microsoft and the Zigbee foundation and a whole bunch of vendors.
And the great thing about it is it requires to be compliant with the matter standard.
Vendors must implement a local control API so you can control devices over your land.
It's a requirement to be compliant with the spec, no cloud services dependencies.
Now you can use cloud services and you can offer additional services, but the minimum
spec requires that you have a local control protocol.
That's a big deal.
And so to see Apple up on stage pushing it when it's been sort of lagging, I felt was
a big moment for the matter protocol.
I think this WWDC just changed the game for matter.
So for us in like the self-hosting community, this is a big deal.
Yeah.
It would be great if a standard kind of became de facto and we could get.
I don't do a bunch of the home automation stuff, but from what I hear from self-hosted
and just a weird guy I know who complains about it all the time, not Chris, is that
none of this stuff is really compatible.
So like HomeKit's its own little dimension and yeah.
Before we get into like OS and APIs and all that kind of stuff, I just wanted to get your
opinion on the heart stuff they talked about.
They have new tools now to monitor for stroke.
They have AFib history.
They've updated the health app to like display all your AFib information and to export it
as a PDF for your doctor to review.
They seem to have a real focus on heart health.
Yeah.
I think it's all good.
I mean, I use the current stuff.
So when iOS 9 comes out in production mode for Apple Watch, I'll use that too.
I think it's good.
It's a watch is perfectly placed to also get that information.
If you're not wearing it in some weird way, like up your arm.
I like it.
I think they do a good job.
They're pretty accurate if you wear your watch with the proper tightness.
I mean, I kind of like all the fitness stuff as I'm trying to get in better shape.
They seem to, you know, they seem to be really focused on progressing your fitness rather
than just saying hit your steps.
In particular, the heart zone rate monitor is interesting because you could say, I don't
for someone who has a heart problem, you maybe don't want to go above a certain zone, right?
Maybe you want to stay, the goal is to stay low, not to go high unless you have to.
Linode.com slash coder.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and you go to support this here
show.
Keep the coder program going by going over to Linode.com slash coder.
Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting.
You got to try it for your next project.
That's how I've deployed everything for the last couple and a half years, but I am so
impressed by the project that we did this last weekend.
We set up PeerTube again on Linode, using its object storage as our backend for our
video storage.
And during WWDC, we had several hundred people live streaming from our Linode PeerTube instance
and it worked fantastic.
And now those videos are up there available for playback, streamed straight from Linode's
object storage.
And they got 11 data centers around the world.
So if you want to deploy something for yourself, they got something close to you or your customers.
If you want something with extremely high throughput, they have AMD epic processors.
They have MVME storage.
They even have 40 gigabit connections coming into the hypervisors, but the best part, they
are their own ISP.
So they just have fantastic connectivity.
And then you combine that with the best support in the business.
The massive hyperscalers that want to lock you into their esoteric platforms can't afford
to do the level of support that Linode can.
And as far as features go and the UI, well, Linode has been refining that for 19 years,
steadily making it better and better.
And now it's the best place to run an application on Linux.
They recently introduced managed databases as well.
I've told you I love their object storage, their cloud firewalls, their alerts that you
can simply configure, their dashboard that makes it simple to see what your machine is
up to, and of course, the support and the performance.
Go build something, go learn something, try something and support the show.
Just go to linode.com slash coder, get that $100 and try it out, linode.com slash coder.
I think the biggest item that got your attention and my attention is the M2 was announced,
and there's a lot here.
50% more memory bandwidth, up to 24 gigabytes of RAM on the base M model, eight core CPU,
that's four high performance, four efficiency cores.
They're saying on average it's about 18% faster than the M1, about 1.9X, that's 1.9 times
the performance of an Intel chip at the same power level, so nearly twice the performance.
And they have a now 10 core next gen GPU, that's two more cores than the M1.
They're claiming 25% better GPU performance at the same power level as the M1.
They have a new next generation neural processor unit in there, a new next generation secure
enclave in there.
The media encoding engine has been greatly improved, multiple 4K and 8K streams, ProRes
encode and decode, et cetera, et cetera.
The new M2 chip, I don't think it's an exaggeration to say they're lapping Intel again, they're
looping them now, it's a loop.
It's a pretty impressive display.
Did you also notice that they had to compare them to old Intel Macs too, just to?
Yeah, that's where it's brutal.
That was really brutal.
So you see it all come together in the M2 MacBook Air.
They touted that the MacBook Air is the world's best selling laptop and it's got a new square
design.
It's 20% thinner, they've popped the screen edge to edge basically, they've brought the
ports back, they brought MagSafe back, it's fanless, oh man, it looks like a killer machine.
It looks like a good machine.
It's got the notch, but I think the notch isn't as big a deal as some people would say.
It's a good machine.
It's like the M1, it's interesting too, the pricing's pretty competitive.
The M1 is now 999 and this one is, what, 1099?
Yeah, 1199, yeah, 1200 bucks.
For a laptop, it's pretty well specced at 1200 bucks.
You could buy the base model and use it for six, seven years pretty easily.
Yep, and then there's the 13 inch Pro.
Well, no, I would destroy it in three days, or when the next model comes out.
Right, of course, accidentally.
Accidentally.
But the MacBook Pro, 13 inch, another respectable choice for those of us who sometimes do air
travel and can't open large laptops because we're chunky.
I like it.
I like how they can't say fans though, they have to say active cooling system.
It's like the most Apple thing possible.
Fans are beneath us, so we say active cooling.
We have an active cooling system to sustain performance, but then they're not really clear
like what the difference is between fanless and active cooling, other than just more performance.
So if you want more performance, you gotta get the Pro, but then you're also getting
fans.
Well, you know how, I mean, you know what it is, right?
They use the low energy cores more in the air and blah, blah, blah.
Yeah, yeah.
No, yeah, they do a good job of managing the fans.
I still have yet to hear the fans in my 16 as far as I can remember.
I think maybe once in the Mac Mini M1, I've heard the fans kick up when I was doing like
a trillion things on it.
They're claiming that it's 39% faster in some photo filter work than the M1, 40% faster
in gaming performance, 20 hours of video playback on the MacBook Pro.
P3 wide color gamut display, $1,300.
It's expensive, but I would argue that if you were to spec an Intel equivalent at $1,300,
I bet you that MacBook comes out on top.
Probably the thing that, I don't know, I'm going to guess you probably care the most
about, maybe not, is Mac OS Ace Ventura.
You know, it kind of blows to be the Alfred app, I guess, because Spotlight's getting
a lot of the features that power users use.
Safari changes, I didn't have time before the show to really read into them.
I'm hoping that Apple is like, although I honestly care more about mobile Safari than
I do Safari.
So let's just like keep embracing standards and not being jerks about things.
No, passkey looks interesting for your password, you know, management needs.
You know, the stuff that I was like, blah, like I never give a crap about mail.
Stage manager, I don't really think that, I use magnet, right?
I like tiled windows, so.
Is this Apple attempting to bring some sort of window management system?
What is this?
So stage manager is this new way to auto arrange windows.
You can group windows together.
It brings one to center focus and slides the other off to like a new kind of dock on the
side.
It remembers window layouts for you.
I'd be interested to see how that works with multi window.
They didn't cover multi window or multi monitor at all with this.
It gathers them together.
Like, so if you have an app that has four or five windows, it'll bundle them all up
for you.
This is not the direction I expected for the Mac.
Um, you know, I think, I think with stage manager, you see Mac and iPad kind of coming
together and I, we have another section about iPad OS.
But that is it, right?
That's, that's the punchline is now stage managers on iPad OS.
Now that feels like a revolution.
This feels like another mission control on the Mac, but on the iPad it feels like a fundamental
feature that's been missing.
Yeah.
I mean, I, I guess, you know, I keep wanting them to just like unleash the iPad and they
did talk.
And this is again where I'm gonna have to look at the dev sessions about new pro app
API.
So I don't know what makes an API a pro API or like a regular API.
Um, so I'm gonna have to look at that.
Things I didn't buy their whole little bragging about gaming.
It's just, no, right.
It's not going to happen on Mac.
Well, wait, before you go onto that, going back to the iPad, they said that apps will
get 16 gigabytes of virtual memory that they added a virtual memory manager to iPad OS.
That seems kind of like a big deal.
Yeah.
Good for Photoshop.
It's going to be great for Photoshop.
Also they introduced real grownup display support.
Like you plug in an external display, you get the full resolution and you can drag windows
between the screens.
You know, I, I've been burned by this so many times where I get like get off a WWC or one
of their events.
I'm like, yes, finally I can do those pro tablet app Star Trek style that I want to
do.
And it's like, well actually these are just basically iPhone apps blown up.
Isn't the issue, honestly, that they could do anything to make iPad OS multitasking more
powerful and at the end of the day, if you don't know if your app's going to make it
through the app store, what's the point?
What's the fundamental issue?
They don't even touch on that.
Well, there's, there's, it's really a two step, right?
One, does the API exist to do what you want to do?
Two, is it somehow skirting or coming close to a perceived edge for maple and you don't
really know what those edges are.
Now I'm still willing to bet now that they've had to do the Epic lawsuit and you know, there's
going to be more of this app store or scrutiny that they're going to be a little less jerk
like about this stuff, but obviously like anything that tries to skirt in app purchase
is always going to, going to be looked down upon, shall we say.
I do wonder about things like why can't we have like a really, really good text editor
that actually can like compile code or like do a debugger on the iPad.
And the answer is because they just don't believe in that.
They want the code that always runs no matter what environment to be downloaded and vetted
via the app store, which is a security thing, but it also severely limits some of the cool
things you might be able to do with an iPad app, right?
I will double check on this.
I hope to be wrong, but I have a feeling these are more impressive demos than, you know,
than actual leaps forward and making the iPad.
You know, when I say a pro app, like I don't know what pro API means.
Like I said, when I say a prop, I mean something like charging significant money for, right?
Significant in the iOS world, I guess is like 14 cents, but you know, like 50 bucks, right?
A yearly subscription, 50 bucks, a hundred bucks.
I don't know that you can provide that full feature stuff.
Now there are some areas you can write apps for DJs, app for podcasters.
Those are people who, although again, you have Spotify and they're Sherlocking the crap
out of you.
So it's true.
Yeah.
You'll see, I've been burned before.
So maybe I hope I'm wrong.
I also wonder how much of this is limited to the M1 iPads.
Some of this new multitasking, multi-monitor.
A lot of it is.
Yeah.
They finally introduced weather kit for iOS.
They bought dark sky.
I can't even remember how long ago.
And they just finally introduced a weather kit API.
I don't know what that means for developers like carrot weather that, you know, they're
an independent weather app.
I don't know.
I don't know who's going to be able to bang out a weather app.
We'll see how that goes.
They also on the iPads, they announced display scaling.
So you don't necessarily have to run in pixel doubled mode.
You could scale it back and get more screen resolution on your iPad.
You combine that with what are they called stage manager and the multi-monitor stuff.
And then maybe you have that $300 magic keyboard with that thing and maybe a hundred dollar
pencil with that thing.
What you have is something that's damn close to a laptop, but it's iOS.
And for some people, I think that actually is a, I don't know.
I still use my 2018 iPad pro and I still like it a lot.
I still find it to be a really good device just for really focused communication.
It's such a big investment that I would only be willing to do it very rarely, you know,
but they're getting there slowly.
Maybe they move so slowly because people upgrade so slowly.
People like you and I, you know, we don't get new iPads that often.
So maybe they just figure they can go at it nice and slow.
Could be something like that.
They also jumping around a bit, talked a little bit more about continuity.
You're going to get FaceTime handoff.
That's actually a pretty good feature.
I think Apple automatically just now has like, if a contact supports FaceTime or something,
when my, anyone in my immediate family calls me now, they're always calling me as a FaceTime
audio call.
So getting FaceTime handoff is nice.
And then in the finally category, iPhone is a webcam available later this year, paired
with a MagSafe clip that mounted on the top of your monitor or your laptop.
You attach the MagSafe clip.
You don't even have to wake the screen of the iPhone.
It immediately wirelessly connects to the Mac as a full res camera.
And then they spent God knows how much time developing this crazy ass niche feature that
uses the wide angle lens of the iPhone to actually capture your desk, your keyboard
and your mouse.
So you can show people your workspace if you want without having to change cameras.
That might be cool for like a VR situation, virtual workspaces.
Maybe, maybe.
Maybe.
I mean, I doubt it.
But yeah.
This is a nice little thing though.
You know, cause you've got good optics on that iPhone and it's got a good image signal
processor and it supports center stage using that wide angle.
So I don't know.
I look at that kind of stuff and I put that all in the nice to have category.
But it seemed like some years are like this more than others, but it seemed like this
was a year where everything was about the Apple ecosystem with the exception of matter.
Everything requires that you are all in as a developer, you're all in as an end user.
It is nothing really new to bring you into the ecosystem.
There wasn't like a new category or something like that.
It was very, very much a deepening that trench.
You know, and I, what I got out of this, when you look at all of the share stuff, the family
integration stuff, the handoff stuff, what I got is Apple is creating an ecosystem out
of your friends and family with the iMessage improvements, with the auto share API, they
are creating.
So now they're extending their ecosystem beyond their like before the ecosystem was watch
phone, Apple TV, Mac, HomePod, right?
Now it's all of those things, but now it's all your family and friends are interconnected
with all those things too.
And now they all are creating a collective dependence on Apple services and Apple messaging
and et cetera.
And making it a pain in the butt to leave the ecosystem, which is we know is their goal
because one of the emails revealed in the Epic trial was on the hardware side, one of
their big concerns is we need a cheap iPhone and we need messages to make sure that parents
don't just give their teeny bopper, you know, a cheap Android device.
This is the WWDC where I think that master strategy becomes kind of obvious on its face.
And now looking back at it, it's clear this is where they were going.
This is why they've always made such great, great family sharing options.
That was always their incentive.
But with this WWDC, it really felt like, Hey, look at the stuff we have and look how it
gets even better when you use these new collaboration features.
Like they talked about sending a link over messages to somebody and instantly kicks off
a collaboration session in an app, FaceTime sharing, where you can be on FaceTime and
you can start a collaboration session and start working on something.
Everybody's name who's working on the doc, good features, good stuff.
But all of it is to reinforce the ecosystem effect when you're working with multiple people.
I thought that was fascinating.
TailScale.com slash coder, this is a secret weapon of mine, it's not so secret, but I
love tail scale.
I think, Mike, you use tail scale.
I think everybody on the network is using tail scale now.
It's so great.
It's so handy.
You create a super quick VPN.
It is a peer to peer connection from your machine to your other machines, all on a mesh
network.
They have a backplane that handles all of the negotiations and connections.
It works with your single sign on vendor.
So that means if you have like an organization that use a single sign on with two factor,
you can integrate it with that.
It supports magic DNS.
So if you put something like a pie hole in your mesh network, then you can start resolving
all of your machines by name.
All of it's protected by WireGuard's noise protocol, which I think is the absolute best
VPN encryption out there.
And I think they're a really clever company.
I think if you go read their blog, you'll get some real insights into the long term
thinking that tail scale has about all of this.
So if you go to tail scale dot com slash coder, you can sign up for free for 20 devices.
And it is so quick to get started.
You can get it running on just about any device.
I bet you you could probably do it in one minute per device on my next OS systems in
probably 30 seconds.
I can get tail scale up and running.
Raspberry Pi's same thing on my phone.
It's in the app store.
You get it installed.
You get connected.
You have the authentication process.
It's so smooth.
I want to put this on blast.
You got to go try it.
It's going to change the way you do networking.
It's going to change the way you do VPN.
That's so obvious.
But I think I'm just making that connection for the first time.
That's the power of tail scale.
Go try it out.
Tail scale dot com slash coder.
So you got yourself one of the new HP dev ones.
I have a review unit in route.
You actually bought one.
I bought one and I do apparently have a review unit in route, but you got one anyways.
And you got it quicker that way.
So perhaps that's good.
What do you think?
Do you want to do a first impressions on HP's laptop built for developers that ships with
Pop OS?
Yeah.
So just a quick first impression.
It's only been a few days.
So overall, I like it.
It's I would say it's on par with most Linux laptops you can buy now.
There's some interesting choices in it.
For instance, the glossy screen is super bright, but still glossy.
So I found myself turning up the brightness to fight glare.
Out of the box, the setup experience is great.
It's Pop OS, right?
Which is like Ubuntu under the covers, basically.
So if you know how to do your apt glory, you can set up a dual chain pretty quickly.
The remote encryption.
See, it's difficult not to just be reviewing Pop OS, right?
Yeah.
So, you know, I'm just going to focus on the hardware.
We've talked about Pop a lot and I think it's the hardware.
That's kind of the difference here.
Build quality is pretty good.
It is plastic, which I was slightly disappointed.
I thought it would be metal, but it's a pretty nice, firm plastic, but it doesn't feel flimsy
at all.
It has actual ports, which is which is nice.
No USB-C charging, though.
Barrel.
It's got a barrel charger.
Yeah.
The webcam is OK.
You know, it's what you get on most laptops.
It's got a nice shield on it where you can close the webcam via hardware.
Speakers I would say of the Linux laptops I've used, these speakers are better.
Ah, OK.
Performance is great.
The AMD Ryzen 7 is is doing, you know, doing just fine.
It does come when you buy it with 16 gigs of RAM.
You can configure it after the fact.
I haven't popped it open yet to upgrade RAM.
That's definitely something I think I'm going to do because I work when I'm on the Linux
machines.
I usually have a Windows VM open, too.
But you have to do that after the fact, right?
Because unless I'm missing something here on their order page, I went to go order it
and there's no there's no tweaking of the build.
I found the same thing.
There's no tweaking of the build.
It's you order it.
They ship it.
Huzzah.
Then you upgrade it after the fact if you want or can.
I don't know.
OK.
And they do say you can.
They explicitly say that.
So that's going to be something I'm going to be trying out.
I did not buy the I have a launch keyboard.
I don't you know, I didn't buy the HP creator mouse, but I think we're getting one anyway.
So I like that they're offering to include a system 76 launch.
That's pretty neat.
I mean, it's a really interesting deal from a Linux ecosystem perspective, right?
Yeah.
I definitely hope that there are future versions of this product because I could see, you know,
some some kind of obvious upgrades, like one USB charging.
Right.
What year is it?
Yeah.
I wonder if maybe somebody could send it in over a booster email.
Is this something about the rising platform?
Is that it?
Is that the limitation?
Because my son has a rising laptop and it also has a barrel charger.
Maybe that's it.
Yeah.
Performance rise.
It runs fine out of the box.
Of course, I hit a steam issue because that's what you do when you comment on Linux laptops.
And when I had a weird issue where the terminal kept suspending, but then I just blew out
a couple of dependencies and reinstalled them and it was fine.
Hasn't done it in a day.
So I'm not sure.
No biometrics that I saw.
I'm curious about fan noise, you know, with the rising system, how's temperature and performance
and and that stuff.
So I haven't got it to be loud yet.
Okay.
So hopefully my plan for tonight is to install XCOM and see how we do.
You know, that is where I'd be really curious to hear your opinion, because like I mentioned,
my kid has a rising laptop and for the most part, I just don't even have him turn on his
NVIDIA GPU.
I have him just use the built in rising graphics and it looks pretty damn good.
So the idea that you could have pretty acceptable gaming performance on a laptop with the integrated
GPU is a serious seller for me, because if I'm going to blow, you know, eleven hundred
bucks on a laptop or something, a thousand bucks on a laptop, and it's going to be a
Linux laptop, I really want to play some games because there's so many great games for Linux
now.
Yeah, well, that's and that's one of the big things Linux has for Mac OS, right?
It's just leaps and bounds above it in gaming.
Real time follow up from the chat room.
They have a Dell with a Ryzen that has a USB charger, so it's probably not something specific
to the Ryzen platform.
OK, and I'm sure if we looked deeply that there must be some very similar Windows HP,
right?
Like SKU could be a next generation thing, too, like if they started working on this
a year ago or something to, you know, QA and everything like that.
The only thing I haven't just real quick tested yet is I want to see how much pressure it
can take without getting super loud.
Yeah, it's so far it hasn't gotten loud at all, but I'm always skeptical of that.
I'm curious about your your first impressions of the keyboard and trackpad quality.
You know, the trackpad, it's a little old fashioned.
First of all, it has a nubbin.
The little the little, you know, the old thing pads have like nub in the middle of the keyboard.
The track point.
Thank you.
I could not use one in the early aughts and I still can't use them now, so I'm not the
best person to ask about that.
Trackpad's fine.
It's got two dedicated mouse clickers.
You can change that in the settings to do some more gesture stuff.
They do have some interesting gesture stuff enabled.
It's for a Windows trackpad.
It's not bad.
It's good.
You know, non Mac trackpad.
It's pretty good.
I would say it's probably on par with I mean, I have an older XPS.
It's pretty much on par with that, right?
That's I'd say an acceptable performance.
It's not stand out, but it's acceptable.
The keyboard is nice.
I actually like it.
You know, they cut like a circle, like a half circle, and the keys were the track point.
That's what we said.
Where the track point is, which I thought I would find very annoying, but it was fine.
The battery life.
Well, I don't think Pop OS tells you the truth about your battery life because it jumps wildly
all the time.
This is my usage.
It's actually been better than I thought it would be.
Oh, okay.
I'm going to take it on the road and see, you know, a more true test, right?
Getting out of the house, not being plugged in or, you know, what?
What is it really?
What's it like in a realistic usage, right?
Like streaming Spotify and working in VS code with Slack open?
I'd love to hear the results of that test.
Yeah, because this is a machine you need to take with you sometimes.
So, okay, at this stage, where you're at, would you buy something like this for a new
hire?
You got it.
Somebody coming on.
I mean, one of the things you got to give these guys is they got this thing to you fast.
Would you buy something like this for a new hire?
If it holds up and I'm doing kind of a month-long test of it, this could be the easy, like,
you know, mad bot or standard issue.
You're a new random Python or Ruby guy.
Here you go.
I mean, we're mostly buying Linux machines now anyway.
So another nice thing about this machine is right now we have like a bunch of different
S76 and a few Dells running around.
It would be nice to standardize for kind of like lots of reasons, right?
I could maybe get a better deal on buying RAM chips if I could order just like...
It would be great if I could buy it with more than 16 gigs of RAM and not have to deal with
that problem.
Yeah.
But as it stands, you know, the processes I buy the machines, I try to install the dependencies
that I think the person is going to need for the role on them.
I give them the password, blah, blah, blah.
And then I send it back out, which is, you know, very inefficient, but it saves usually
like half a day of I can't get my tool chain up.
And I guess if you were going to deploy Pop OS already, it's getting you just that much
further down that process.
Yeah.
It tends a lot easier.
Right.
And then I know that, like, there's someone for me to yell at if somebody's Wi-Fi card
dies.
So it's got two USB ports to USB-C and HDMI out and of course, a headphone port and then
the barrel connector.
Not bad on the connectivity side.
No, not it.
It's it's I got to say, like for a web dev laptop, I think this is a very viable choice
if you want Linux.
I know that's a lot of caveats, but I feel like the Linux machines are somewhat have
to be judged both against the Macs and the higher end Windows machines.
And but also, if you're like if you're coming to the table saying, I will only buy a pre
installed Linux machine, that's kind of a different category, right?
Right.
This is a tool to do a job.
Yeah.
I need a Linux development environment.
And the pricing is not bad.
All right.
So, you know, I've got a whole battery of tests I want to throw at it.
But I, of course, want to really kind of dissect it, try different distributions on there,
see how Wayland works on there.
You know, I want to throw it through all of the various paces, but I'm content to wait
because your first look here has has answered some of my questions.
Now to be clear, it looks like a glossy display, but they have notes on here that make it look
like they've tried to make it usable in a bright environment.
Did you try using this thing outside?
I did.
So I was able to overcome the glare by turning the brightness all the way up.
Whoa.
That, of course, hammers your battery life.
It gets bright, though.
It gets bright.
I think they said it was like a thousand nits or something crazy like that.
You know, as a Linux user, what I love about this laptop is the idea that with a rise in
GPU and a rise in CPU, I do nothing beyond just install my distro and I've got full
3D acceleration.
I've got full freaking open source graphics.
To me, that's a very compelling starting place.
And it's why I bought my ThinkPad and I went all Intel and the performance has been inadequate.
I have never really been that happy with my ThinkPad.
I still use it.
And I feel like I've learned certain optimizations that I can do that have helped with its performance.
But I feel like it suffers from having a really good GPU and I kind of just missed the latest
gen of Intel CPUs that kind of made up some of this distance.
And I got a generation before that.
And so I've never been really that thrilled.
And now with the Apple M2 generation launching, I know this sounds silly, but I'm kind of
disincentive to buy an Intel based machine.
And I feel like at least when I get a rise in, I'm getting something that feels modern,
even though I understand it's maybe not equivalent like that.
But in my mind, it feels like Intel represents old computing and AMD and Ryzen don't represent
that to me.
I know that's just a pure branding thing.
But when you're trying to decide what you're going to buy, I feel like that stuff kind
of plays a factor.
And then you combine the fact that you get open source graphics stack, I think it kind
of puts it ahead of the pack.
So I am looking forward to getting my review unit.
Yeah, I'm very curious as to your thoughts because I'm just never going to care to install
different disk rows on it.
So for me, it's kind of like just first impressions, right?
Is this a viable machine for a Python dev or an Angular dev?
And the answer is yes, right?
Obviously, yes.
There's I do feel that the target customer here, even though the marketing is very like
devs, devs, devs, I think it's IT manager or guy who owns dev shop buying for their
devs.
Yeah.
Linux enthusiast that wants a nice out of the box experience.
Linux enthusiasts.
Yep.
System 76 is market.
Yeah, which is why I find this to be kind of a surprising.
Not yet, I think, delightful partnership.
Oh, you won't remember my bacon.
Yeah, I do.
I do remember your bacon.
Your tasty, tasty, you know, acquisition bacon.
My M&A bacon.
Yes.
I feel like in six months to a year, I want to sit down with Carl, have a drink and just
ask him like, what are your thoughts on this from like a, you know, 50,000 foot strategic
level the next five years?
Like what are your thoughts here?
Is this a new area of business?
Chris, at Stanford, you can do better than a drink.
Well, there you go.
Thanks for giving us that first impressions.
What do you say we do a couple of boosts and then we get out of here?
Sure.
Boost it out.
Four score and seven boosts to go.
All right.
Well, the golden dragon boosted in and he loves giving us the row of ducks.
That's four twos.
You put it in a calculator.
Yeah, I know.
So the golden dragon boosted in.
I'm a duck.
D-U-K duck.
Loaded with talent.
He says, not technically sure if this is cloud, but at my job, we log into a remote server
that runs Microsoft Dynamics AX and it's terrible.
I wish that we would go FOSS and get over with it.
The version we use hasn't been supported for a decade, literally, and has connection issues
all the time amongst other remote issues.
We were talking about remote desktops and working environments.
We did get some feedback on that that I think we'll read soon.
I actually used to support a Microsoft remote desktop session for Dynamics AX and I can
attest that it is an absolute horrible pig.
And when you combine that with limitations of remote sessions and then running multiple
copies on one box and the fact that it's not supported, that's remote sessions done the
worst way possible.
So I feel you golden dragon.
Vine Hummingbird boosted in with a thousand sats four days ago.
B-O-O-S-T.
You folks beat on Windows all the time.
Meanwhile, the entire financial world runs on it and it employs legions of devs.
I think Hummingbird might work for Microsoft.
He's right though, or they are right.
One of us once said Windows 11, or I'm sorry, Windows 10 was the best Linux desktop distro.
You did say that, didn't you?
Then I did the WSL and the WSL 2 challenge and I had the Penguin guys when I did the
interview show and I did a lot of Windows love, mostly sub Linux love, but come on.
It's because it's been a while.
You know what?
We do on average go hard on Windows because we don't like it as a desktop experience,
but there has been several times where we've got to come on the show and been like, no,
Microsoft nailed this.
They've done a good job with this.
It's just far and few, mostly because I think you're bitter over the whole Metro stuff and
Windows stuff.
I shouldn't have said anything.
All right, moving on.
Never forget.
Nix are boosted in five days ago with a row of ducks.
Thank you very much.
And here's something for your trouble.
He says just giving love for the best podcast for developers out there.
What do you think of that?
He must be drunk.
Fuck on that ATP.
Hey, I know you're right.
You're right.
I accept you as you are.
Nixer actually came back in with a double boost boost that I caught the part about the
cloud work and I wanted to send this in.
I work for an MSP remotely.
They actually have a box set up in the office in Texas that I use for support to do remote
into that box from New York.
Any tools that we have uses the web and I just have my local browser on my machine.
Anything else is done on that box in Texas.
They've mailed me a phone.
So all my calls come from that office to our customers like I just work out of the office
in Texas.
I suppose either way, it works OK, though, until someone takes out your power cord in
Texas backs.
Yes.
So because, you know, as a worker, that's just a that's just a free license to take
the day off.
No, no guilt.
No shame.
You know, as a boss, it sucks.
As an owner.
It's horrible.
Yeah.
If it works, I mean, whatever.
I know you don't like it.
You're always and you're always looking at it as a boss.
We also got some thank you boosts, a double thank you boost from Cospe Land and from Elty
Guy O5.
Thank you, everybody.
If you'd like to send us a boost, you can get a new podcast app over at new podcast
apps dot com and you load up with some stats or if you don't want to switch apps.
You can grab Breeze at B R E E Z dot technology for iOS or Android and then you can boost
without switching apps.
Also thank you to our members.
You get something very special.
That is a Coderly once a quarter.
You also get the members feed that has no ads.
I am also working on a live version, which I got to figure out not only some of the tech
details but like what's going to be in that live feed version.
But I am formulating that for the members.
I know probably just a lot of cussing, you know, a lot of cussing, lots of cussing.
Drew cuts it out of the show, but they start the show being like, hey, did you see this
new Metro UI?
Oh, my God.
Mike was logged in.
Yeah.
It's awful.
It's also just a great way to support the show.
Keep us independent.
Working with the sponsors.
We should be.
You know, all that kind of stuff.
Coder QA dot co.
Thanks to our members over there.
Mr. Dominic, is there anywhere you want to send folks this week here on the Coder program?
Sure.
You know what?
Go to Alice dot dev and maybe the end of the week I'll have something on the one on Dominic
M dot com.
The dev one.
I mean.
Oh, further thoughts on the laptop, perhaps.
Very, very nice.
I wonder if my next episode I'll have my review unit.
Wouldn't that be cool?
I think you probably will.
It seems like you should.
I might tweet it out when I get it.
At Chris Alias.
The podcast is at Coder Radio Show and the network is at Jupiter Signal.
There's a whole network of shows.
You might like Linux action news.
Perhaps you'd like to try self-hosted or Linux Upload.
They're all over there.
And of course, the new show Office Hours, where we talk about the back end projects
for the network and more at Office Hours dot here.
Yep.
It's Office Hours dot here.
Thanks to what we talked about today, Coder dot show slash 469 over there you'll find
our contact form.
That's a big part of the show.
We'd love to hear from you and our subscribe page.
Also, we always appreciate you sharing the show or showing up live Mondays at noon Pacific
three p.m.
Eastern at jblive.tv.
Thanks so much for being here on this week's episode of Coder Radio.
See you right back here next week.