This is Koto Radio, episode 312 for June 4th, 2018.
Hi everyone and welcome to Koto Radio, Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a
pragmatic look at the art and business of software development and its related technologies.
This episode is brought to you by our two great sponsors, DigitalOcean and Linux Academy.
I'll tell you more about those great sponsors as this here show goes on.
My name is Chris and joining us every single week is our host, Mr. Michael Dominic.
Hello, Mike.
Hello, Mr. Chris.
How are you doing?
Are you up all hours of the morning watching keynotes and reading tech news today?
I have been so deep in the tech news.
This is like a gift from the tech gods.
It has been a big day, as they say, because it was officially announced today.
It's been rumored for a little bit, but officially announced today that Microsoft is acquiring
GitHub.
That process has now started.
It is public.
We're going to be talking about that.
And of course, it's also Apple's WWDC 2018 kickoff keynote day.
So a lot to talk about today.
Everything we took notes and we came prepared, like you got a beer and I took notes.
So I think we're pretty much set.
So let's do that to go.
Let's save feedback for next week, because we've got so much to get into that I think
we should probably just start here.
And let's save the GitHub stuff for a little bit.
And let's kick off with the news of the day, which is WWDC.
We both just got done watching and streaming.
And it really came down to a few sections, iOS 12, watchOS 5, the Mac, and that really
was kind of it.
There wasn't really...
There was no HomePod mentioned.
So I'm sorry.
I know that disappointed you.
No HomePod.
I cried.
And Apple TV, I suppose, was in the mix too, but I didn't take many notes for Apple TV.
So let's start with iOS 12.
What do you say?
Yeah.
You know, I think just right up front, we need to remind the listenership that WWDC
stands for Worldwide Developer Conference.
That's something that may have been easy to forget during this presentation.
I was not pleased.
So iOS 12.
I mean, maybe we should get your impressions first, because I'm going to come down pretty
hard.
Nothing major.
The newest stuff, they really sort of started off with performance, particularly performance
for oldest devices, which that's going to sell.
They announced a new cross-device VR file format that Adobe's working with too to create
content creation tools called.USDZ.
And they announced a new AR app called Measure, as well as some updates to Photos to try to
get more competitive with Google Photos.
But I think the big stuff, which I can save if you want, was the Siri stuff.
Yeah, the Siri shortcut is interesting.
It looks pretty limited.
I don't, you know, I would like less Siri in my life in general.
I don't see a whole ton of people running out and writing apps specifically to take
advantage of the Siri shortcuts.
So the Siri shortcuts is also, well, it's really more of a user thing too, because you
can assign your own phrases and then essentially like using workflow style macros, create little
functions like I'm going home and then it gets you directions, set your home kit settings
to 70 degrees, sends a text to a significant other, and then begins to play the NPR radio,
whatever you may have set in your macro.
So that way Apple doesn't have to try to invent every possible esoteric use case for Siri.
They're just going to let users create it.
They just basically punt it.
Let the apps do the work.
Yeah.
And a bunch of core apps got iPad versions, app limits, which give you now reminders to
take a break.
Collectivity reports, based on what you see too, you can give your kids allowances based
on how they use their device, i.e. if they use their devices less, you can reward them.
They announced Apple Books, which is replacing iBooks, and some changes to notifications
like group notifications by topic, thread, and app, and group FaceTime.
That's really the things that stood out to me for iOS 12.
Now you seem like you got a different impression.
Yeah.
I, you know, I would almost rather take the conference as a whole.
Okay.
I only saw maybe, or the conference, the keynote as a whole, I only saw maybe three, maybe
four things that really were interesting to developers, and I'm not going to count dark
mode for Xcode or Mac OS.
One because Xcode finally getting dark mode is not something they should be bragging about.
Just throwing it out there.
Some of the ML stuff around Core ML 2 and their machine kit stuff with Swift looks interesting,
but that is a major departure from how that domain space typically works.
And I'm not convinced that it's going to be attractive for a lot of people to basically
train their models, their machine learning models, using a GUI app on a Mac in Swift,
especially when a lot of machine learning algorithms work really well with Nvidia CUDA
cards and Apple does not offer that.
So that felt odd to me.
I guess the desired use case is one might want to add some sort of machine learning
element to an existing application or into a Mac or iOS app, and this is just an easy
way to do that coming from the position of an iOS developer.
It's certainly interesting, certainly accelerating with Metal may give Metal a reason to exist.
That's not games.
I felt a little bit like, honestly, the big plan for this keynote was going to be Marzipan,
the cross-platform iOS and Mac thing they mentioned at the end, but it just wasn't ready.
Yeah, so let's talk about that.
Let's talk about Marzipan just for a second, because that is maybe the biggest news, ironically,
which is not even going to be until next year.
They said-
Until next year.
Yeah.
It's going to be something that they'll ship their new apps like Home and News and Stocks
apps that's going on Mac OS.
That's built with Marzipan or whatever they're calling it.
They didn't give it a name.
They're going to try that for a year, and then however that goes, then they'll incorporate
changes and improvements, and then they'll release it to developers in 2019.
The more I hear about this, though, is this Electron that they're creating?
Are they creating a new Electron?
But with their own technologies, so it's Electron for the Apple ecosystem?
No, it's adding from the very little that's leaked and the very little they showed on
stage today, it's adding basically UI kit hooks into app kit.
I was actually pretty hopeful for it, because I could see a world where you run an iOS app,
and then just theoretically, I was doing a little architecture in my head during the
keynote.
Let's say you had an iOS app that gathered a bunch of data or did a bunch of AR tagging.
Then you brought it back to your Mac, let's say your iMac Pro, and did a bunch of machine
learning on that data.
That would be a good place to take advantage of something like Marzipan to share the code
between both sides of the application.
Now the reality is someone can do that much easier in a number of other technologies,
including C-Sharp.
You can just do a Xamarin app and do a – you can just write a desktop app in C-Sharp or
pal whatever you want.
I don't know.
I don't have a lot positive to say about this keynote.
I was hoping – when it kept dragging on and they kept showing ridiculous stuff for
the watch, I was thinking, okay, so they're dragging this out.
There's going to be something.
Is there going to be a Macbook Pro?
Is there going to be – is Marzipan maybe actually coming out?
I was thinking they really should update the Macbook Pro, even if it's just a quick update
with a new keyboard.
It's like a swap out the keyboard.
Although I think it's underwhelming.
I think the whole thing was underwhelming.
It was very consumer focused, but there were – I don't know.
It's unusual for Apple to talk about something that you're not even going to get your hands
on for a year and kind of sneak that little information out there.
I thought that was interesting.
So Marzipan may not be shipping, but they're at least talking about it.
They're just like, you know what?
Everybody's been rumored about it.
Or what about the fact that they just addressed the whole, are you going to integrate MacOS
and iOS head on?
There's just a big nope slide up on screen.
Well, that's what makes me think that the original plan was they were just going to
announce and release Marzipan, and when it wasn't ready, they had to back off of it.
Just one other point I want to throw in here, ARKit, adding additional functionality to
ARKit is really interesting, but then Apple immediately – Sherlock's one of the more
interesting things you could do with ARKit in terms of the measurements.
In particular, it almost felt like Apple was really excited to be their own app developer
instead of a platform vendor, which was weird to me.
A lot of this presentation was – I mean, seriously, walk down this road with me.
In an alternate universe, their presentation makes a lot more sense when at the end of
the day, you're like, oh, and Marzipan is available now, developer.apple.com, the beta
– we're releasing in a week, right?
And by the way, you've already seen it in stocks, home, blah, blah, blah, here, all
these apps.
Instead, it was like, yeah, we're not done yet, and we don't have anything.
Okay, I just – devil's advocate, right?
I came into this, Chris.
I have my MacBook set up.
I set up a whole tool chain.
I was ready to go.
My plan was, whatever new API, if it was Marzipan or if it was something else, I was going to
pound out an app within the next month and get it out the door as kind of a marketing
thing.
That gave me nothing, right?
There was no app that I could write today that I couldn't have written yesterday.
I guess it depends on the lens you're looking at because they did add new features to watch
OS, which you say we're all kind of screwing around, but the stuff they added to watch
OS seemed sort of relevant.
You get third-party apps that can play background audio now.
There's some vague improvements to what complications and access third-party apps get to that, and
podcasts on the watch are huge for me.
I think that's going to be great for our audience that have Apple Watch.
So there's some stuff in there that I think is decent.
It just depends on where you look.
I grant you there is hardly nothing brought to the Mac that's of any interest to developers
at all.
I grant you that.
But iOS 12, I think maybe you might be underselling some of that, and same with watch OS, but
I think you've nailed it with the Mac.
Well, the watch OS is they're just removing self-imposed restrictions, right?
I mean, the only reason they didn't want background audio before was presumably battery life concerns,
or they just didn't have the ability to hook it into the API.
I mean, be the HomePod Apple defender.
Tell me, what did I miss?
No, I think it's a very...
Okay, I'll tell you, you want to know my big theory about it, and it's...
Yeah, fry me some bacon.
I have already mentioned it once, but after watching the recent keynote and other actions
recently, I think I'm right, and I have a theory as to how something could possibly
be at a company as rich as Apple that the people running it don't know how to use computers.
Now stick with me, because I know that sounds like a controversial thing to say, and, oh,
Chris is just taking shots, but I think we have a serious problem here, and I think it
starts at the top, and I'll explain my logic, because I think it explains why you're disappointed
from a pro user standpoint.
They're up on stage, and they're constantly saying, this was designed, in fact, I grabbed
one of the quotes, and I don't know if I...
Yeah, inspired by pro users, designed for everyone, and then they kept saying, this
is something pro users really want.
They said that several times on stage, and yet everything seems very, very consumer focused.
Very little new stuff was opened up for developers.
No major new kits were announced.
It was more like a cleaning up, which is good, but I have a theory as to why this is happening.
So first let's talk about Linux Academy, because that's why I'm on the road right now.
I'm in Cortez, Colorado, and I'm on my way down to see Linux Academy to help them get
their broadcast system on Linux.
They brought in some new folks, the new folks knew how to use it on the Mac, and we're gonna
go down and help them get it working on Linux, and go to Texas Linux Fest, and Linux Academy
is committed to Linux.
They're enthusiasts about Linux, developers, educators, they got together and they said,
let's create a platform to teach people more about Linux.
It's a full-featured training library with everything you need to learn new skills and
advance your career.
They have self-paced, in-depth video courses on every cloud, Linux, and DevOps topic.
If it can run Linux or Linux runs on it, you can find a course about it at Linux Academy.
They have hands-on scenario-based labs that give you experience on real servers, full-time
humans that can help you whenever you get stuck, and if you're busy, no problemo.
They have a course scheduler, you can set a time frame, set learning goals, stick to
it.
It's pretty great.
Now if you go to linuxacademy.com slash coders, it's got an S on the end of it, linuxacademy.com
slash coders, you can sign up for a free seven-day trial, and you can support the show.
They also have training for particular types of certification, if you wanna go and get
your certs.
They've got learning paths if you wanna get down to a particular career track, maybe you
wanna move tracks.
They have a series of courses and content planned by their instructors to get on specific
career tracks.
And of course, they've got iOS and Android apps too, linuxacademy.com slash coders.
And a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Coder Radio program, linuxacademy.com
slash coders.
So I think what's happening at Apple, and this is a wild speculation just based on years
of observation now, and I think Steve Jobs built that company in a way to be run from
the top.
And it is architecturally designed in such a way that you've got your chiefs, you've
got your Phil Schillers, and you've got your Craig Federighis, and others, and then you've
got what used to be Steve at the top is now Tim at the top.
But Tim is an old Compaq guy who ran operations before he came to Apple.
He was never in the nuts and bolts of Compaq, and he's not a big computer user.
I mean, he's even said it himself, he's more of an iPad user.
And then you look at Craig Federighi, he seems to be perhaps the most technically competent
of all of them, but he's a man, a middle-aged man who has a family, he has a very big career,
he has a lot of things going on, lots of people to manage.
He's probably not going home on the weekends and trying to build a Hackintosh or trying
to try something brand new in machine learning on his Macbook with an eGPU.
There's a chance he's tried it, but it's probably not something he's passionate about.
And so the people...
And Phil Schiller, again, he's a marketing guy, a marketing genius really, but he's not
a technical expert.
So you don't have an executive at the top now who is a PC user, a computer user, or
even just enthusiastic about technology in a fundamental way, like willing to risk everything
and build a company in his garage so they could sell some wood boxes with computer parts
in them with his esoteric buddy.
Like you gotta be really into it to do that, and there's nobody at the company at the top
anymore.
Of course, you've got tons of developers, thousands of developers and computer experts
throughout the company that are incredibly passionate about this stuff, and they're the
ones that are writing the good code, right?
They're really just super passionate, but they don't run the company.
And I think the DNA of Apple from the day Steve Jobs started it is such that it is a
top-run company.
It has an executive that sits at the top, and now it's a team of executives, and this
team of executives decides based on customer stat data, what the customer stat data is,
on what the cost for manufacturing is, what the marketing message is, and they sit there
and have these conversations and they decide on what's gonna ship.
And it is to abstract from the actual people.
And so that's why they actually do the work.
And so that's why they've had to go assemble a pro team that could do pro work and advise
them on the new features that should be in Mac OS, because they don't know.
They don't use them.
They don't use Final Cut.
They don't use Logic.
They don't use Xcode.
They don't know.
And so they need to hire people, which are essentially yes-men, to tell them what to
do.
And what we've got is just a little bit more of the same now with dark mode.
And it's disappointing because it's like the Mac App Store is all well and good, and it
looks like a decent update, and there's some new apps like BBEdit that have never been
in there that are long-standing pro Mac apps that are coming.
But there was no mention about upgrade pricing.
There was no mention about any of that kind of stuff that's gonna solve real issues for
large-scale applications that cost tens of thousands of dollars to create.
Why?
Why after all this time has that not been addressed?
They just don't know.
They're disconnected.
So they're kind of just going around by what all of their crew tell them, and then they
make decisions based on factors that probably are different than the factors you and I would
make decisions on.
I'm thinking if I agree with you or not.
I don't think I agree with you, actually.
Or maybe...
How could it be any other way?
I mean, just look what they're producing year after year.
Look at the MacBook Pro.
Right.
So there's two categories of complaint I have.
One is the hardware is not for me, right?
Which I think your theory works there.
So I'm not...
Let's just table that, right?
I will concede that point.
They're obviously trying to keep the Mac as a high-end development platform.
And they...
That little Swift tool they have to do machine learning in Swift is something I'm going to
check out.
Because if that actually works, right, with that nice little easy GUI, that's pretty good.
It's weird that it's not following the industry standards.
You know, devil's advocate, your Apple, therefore you must use Swift, I guess.
You see what I'm saying?
The standard's Python, right?
Not an Apple.
I'm just...
Right.
I get it.
But like Microsoft, you can do it in F sharp.
You're fine.
What I don't get is almost like an argument mismatch here in terms of I tune into a developer
keynote from the richest company in the world, ready, willing, and able to develop some sort
of new software on their platform.
I don't get a whole lot new.
Now, it may be also the case that because of what you said, because of your theory,
the people presenting the information just failed to present it in a light that would
have been attractive to me.
So I'm certainly going to watch the session videos and look through the private...
Yeah, and the State of the Union and all that.
It may actually be true that there is something...
My expectation was at minimum, there was going to be some amazing new ARKit APIs.
And I have an idea of something I want to do if ARKit was just incrementally improved.
But that's not what they told me, right?
I mean, you're asking me to make a...
Well, I guess you're not.
You're saying it just doesn't exist because they don't care to do it.
Is that basically your point?
Well, I think it's a little...
So let's stick with ARKit for a second.
It's very possible that they're at the developer level, there's new stuff they've put in there
that just goes up in a word cloud for 25 seconds or if that, maybe five seconds in the background.
But then if you were to go to the actual sessions at WWDC or go to the State of the Union, you
may find out about a new set of APIs because there is a new version of ARKit.
So there's likely new functionality for developers to take advantage of.
But the people that are presenting the information, not only are they trying to target it for
a general audience in the press, but they also genuinely don't understand and know how
to distinguish between something that is really applicable to developers versus something
that is just a nice new feature.
I think they don't know...
Probably Craig Federighi is in the unique position to understand that.
And I think that's the issue, is you've got one really strong, technically competent player
in that executive team.
Okay.
But I don't even know if I'm arguing against you now, I'm just frankly complaining.
If you're serious about machine learning and you want Swift to be a good machine learning
language, fine.
You know what?
I would be okay with that, right?
I am not religious.
I love my System76 stuff, I love POP, I would totally work on a Mac if it was easier.
Then you need to ship CUDAs, you need to ship NVIDIA CUDA graphics cards, right?
The fact that a company with 30 people or however big they are now just released a laptop
that will do a better job than a MacBook Pro that cost a thousand dollars more at a task
that Apple just highlighted in their keynote is ridiculous to me.
The company I'm talking about is System76, but it is a fact, Chris, that if you are doing
machine learning and you are, for whatever odd reason, trying to train your models on
your own laptop, you definitely want at least a CUDA card, right?
The guy said that unless what Apple thinks is that you are not going to do any high-end
machine learning.
What you are going to do is you are going to add a little bit of machine learning to
an app and then I'm going to – then you are in this weird argument of what is like
scripting and just like statistical analysis and what is machine learning because that
seems weird.
I agree with you.
It sounds like Craig Federighi was deadly serious on stage about that, right?
He very much seems to know what he is talking about.
I just don't understand.
Why would you not put your best foot forward and say, this is ARKit 2 and here is the ten
new things you can do with it and this is CoreML 2 and what is it, MachineKit was the
other one?
I don't think I grabbed it.
Oh, Metal for Machine Learning.
Okay.
Metal for Machine Learning.
And this is why you want to do that.
Instead, we had to have this very long explanation about exercise during a developer keynote.
Have you met developers?
I know.
That was – the whole on the bike thing was – that was weird.
And Animoji is just wrong and I don't mean wrong as in for developer conference which
it is.
I mean morally wrong.
My kids love it.
It creeps me out.
My kids just love it.
They love it.
It reminds me of those old like late 80s horror movies when everybody was worried about Satanists
and stuff where like the kid wears a go-tet or something.
Terrifying to me.
I am horrified by Animoji.
This may be more of a Mike issue than an Apple issue but I don't know.
I mean to me, I don't even know if I agree with you or I don't agree with you because
I feel like we're across purposes but I feel like they're just not taking their
developer community serious at all.
They want – and that video with people's moms talking about – oh, no.
I'm sorry.
David Attenborough talking about developers like they are animals in a jungle somewhere.
Did you see that intro?
Yes.
Yes, I did.
Replace developer with any other group of people and you're on the front page of
the New York Times.
That's unbelievably terrible.
That's insulting.
Here's what – so I am more optimistic about the software improvements.
The integration of workflow into iOS could be the biggest standout feature for iOS 12
for power users and I'm glad that they finally revamped the Mac App Store.
But the things that jumped out at me was no new MacBook Pro at all, even if it was just
going to be now you can do 32 gigs of RAM and a new keyboard for God sakes.
No iPad software OS level improvements.
Just a few new apps that are coming to iPad from the iPhone so they're not even really
new apps.
So it's sort of hit and miss for me.
I think the hardware area is the weakest story for Apple in terms of no Mac updates at all,
no Mac Mini update either.
Again, I think if you were looking for what developers need –
Mac Mini.
I mean if you're looking for a Mac Mini.
Actually if you – so imagine if they had the Mac Mini and it was just basically a rebranded
Intel NUC.
A NUC?
Yeah.
That would be a great little machine to just try something out, especially if you're an
iOS developer and you want to experiment with the Mac.
Right now your entry point is a laptop or an all-in-one iMac.
It's just ridiculous.
I know it's just – yeah, anyways, I just – that's what – those would have been
signals to me that they kind of grokked with some of the more wider developer –
Yeah, it's like certainly not fixing the damn keyboards and all their computers is
super crazy to me.
And I got to be honest, I know I'm coming in pretty hard and I can already see the YouTube
comments coming, although it's not up on YouTube.
I hope you're right, Chris, right?
I hope Chris is right.
I hope it's not – like I hope there is some cool stuff and it's just like Tim Cook
is just not the right person to run this company and the message – because the messaging
comes off as weirdly infantilizing and it's kind of like oh, you guys are so cute, little
boy, here's a Matchbox car.
And now the grown-ups are going to go work out and you know, I don't know, it – yeah,
it felt bad.
I mean, Chris, do you agree or do you think I'm just crazy?
It felt off-tone.
It felt – I don't know how to put – I've been trying to think of how to put this into
words but all but one of the female presenters they brought up on stage felt like they were
bringing females up on stage to check boxes.
And that – and I think some people in the chatroom felt that way too and it's unfortunate
when you see that because that almost feels like the reverse of what they're trying to
accomplish.
I'm not saying that for all of the presenters but there was definitely some.
You know, they've all been very, very heavily coached.
The Apple Keynote is almost a parody of itself now and it's such a –
It could have been an episode of Silicon Valley, right?
Yeah.
It could have been the guy from Hooli up there.
It's such a ripped off format now too.
Like everybody uses that format.
And so it feels really done and I think the pent-up need – what's going on here is the
crossroads that we're approaching now.
We're dancing around this GitHub story but look at the message from Microsoft, the continuous
say last 25-year message about how they feel about developers versus the story we just
got from Apple.
And you and I both watched Build.
You compare and contrast Build to WWDC and it's clear Microsoft deeply, deeply understands
developers.
It feels like when they're up on stage they are developers themselves that are making
things for other developers.
When Apple's on stage it feels like the candy company is making a new magical toy and there's
a way for you developers to play along too.
And that –
That can make it so much worse.
And so I just – I think it's just it wasn't enough and it didn't solve enough problems
to address the crossroads that they're at right now.
It's not – see, to me, I mean, I'll get off of it because I think we're just going
to come close to a flame war here but it wasn't just that it wasn't enough.
The actual tone to me was – I felt like I was in 10th grade and some girl's mom was
trying to convince her to go out with me because the nerds, he'll make a lot of money, right?
It felt weird like the – especially the first video with the developers in the wild
treating them like some sort of weird creature you would find, an animal.
And the thing with the moms and the relatives was just unbelievably bad.
If you contrast it to Microsoft and to Google, Microsoft and Google treat this like a real
profession, a real skill.
Apple treats it like some sort of –
Lifestyle choice.
I don't even know.
It's a lifestyle choice.
But for like children, like honestly, it felt like they were talking to children.
I don't know, we can move on.
It just felt super – the only word I can think of is infantilizing.
I mean it really felt like they were trying to say we're the adults, we understand you
have these feelings and you want these things but you do have a curfew and you can't drink,
right?
Like it just – ah, terrible.
Yeah.
I don't know if I get that strong of a read but I do feel like it was off the mark.
And I myself am just pleased to see that they're adding a workout mode for hiking because jeez,
I always feel like I was getting ripped off on that.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, why don't we take a break and we'll change gears and we'll talk about GitHub,
Microsoft and the big story and all of that that isn't really getting very much discussion,
at least not today on Monday as it's all broke.
But first, let's talk about DigitalOcean and how you can get $100 credit when you go
to dio.co slash coder.
No S on this one.
Dio.co slash coder.
$100 of DigitalOcean credit for 60 days when you sign up with a new account.
And you can do a lot in 60 days.
Try something new or maybe improve an existing app, test something you've been wanting to
try for a while.
They have optimized compute types where you can deploy droplets that have been optimized
for specific types of compute workloads.
They have customizable drops where you can mix and match the resources.
My favorite system though is three cents an hour.
Three cents an hour and I get four gigs of RAM, two CPUs, 80 gigabytes of SSD disk space
and three terabytes of transfer for three cents an hour.
Everything is SSDs.
If you get the $5 a month system or you get one of those systems with hundreds of gigs
of RAMs and lots of Xeon CPUs, everything is SSDs.
Even the block storage.
And then they have easy, simple, straightforward DNS management.
Cloud firewalls which block traffic at their network level instead of letting the traffic
hit your box, monitoring and alerting so that way you can deliver pro-level services and
keep track of how things are trending.
Global data centers, data centers all over the world and 40 gigabit connections coming
into the hypervisors.
And then they wrap it all up with a great dashboard and a super straightforward API.
Try it out.
60 days with a $100 credit, do.co slash coder.
Now if you're thinking about trying GitLab, they have a one click deployment for GitLab.
One click and it's all set up and ready to go and you can get to work, do.co slash coder
and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Coder radio program.
Yeah, so it started, you started probably seeing this over the weekend I think based
on the telegram and Slack chats that I saw.
But for $7.5 billion today-
I'm sorry, put your pinkie up.
Billion.
So they officially announced it today that they are going to acquire GitHub and Nat Friedman,
the founder of Xamarin is going to be, or Xamarin or however you say it.
Still called Xamarin every time.
Because it's going to be, I can't stop now, it's going to be the new CEO of GitHub once
all this closes in about a year, or at the end of the year they think.
So it's huge.
This is huge because it's also, it's also Microsoft buying Electron basically.
And that to me seems like the big story that's not getting a lot of discussion right now.
Yeah.
And Atom, which I think is going to be good night to Saigon for Atom pretty soon.
Oh, right now we've got-
VS Code.
Yeah.
We've got some redundancies.
And under the hood they're effectively the same.
So.
Hmm.
Yeah, I mean, so let's start with GitHub.
A lot of people have been talking like this is the end of the world on Twitter.
You know, lots of announcements about being at the end of the world.
I think it's a little too early to tell, but I think it is a, it's a good, as they say,
leeching moment about centralization.
And especially when that comes to open source projects and it's a great opportunity for
GitLab.
So that, that, those are my thoughts on, on everybody freaking out about switching.
But what have you, what, just before we move on, what do you think about the reaction so
far?
Surprised?
Not surprised?
Over the top?
What do you think?
Am I surprised that it happened or am I surprised at the reaction?
Well, I was thinking the reaction, but I'm actually curious of the first one too.
So start with the reaction and then let's talk about it.
Yeah.
So I made a mistake of when I first saw the leak, posting it to the Reddit programming
subreddit and just watching the comments come in and my little notification panel there.
Oh boy.
People are not happy.
Right?
I wrote a quick blog post on dominicm.com.
I wrote it when I noticed that the GitLab import tool actually crashed because so many
people were trying to pull their repos off of GitHub.
Oh man.
I myself up until recently was a Bitbucket user, but for basically compliance reasons,
I'm using a self-hosted GitLab now.
I had evaluated GitHub, but I'm a little old man-ish and I kind of think it's important
to control your own infrastructure provided you have good backups.
Yeah.
I wasn't surprised by the reaction either.
So what do you think?
Were you surprised about this purchase?
No.
I think Microsoft is one, the logical purchaser for GitHub and honestly, someone had to buy
GitHub, right?
Like they weren't going to IPO on good terms.
I don't know.
I mean, the one argument I've heard a lot is one of the features of GitHub, one of the
biggest features of GitHub was the fact that it was an independent operator.
It could sit between AWS or Azure or DigitalOcean.
Like it was just this independent operator that didn't have any skin in that aspect of
the game.
So I would prefer to have seen it stay solo, right?
But the answer to that was they probably needed to generate more revenue and therefore raise
prices.
Yeah.
Okay.
I can see that.
The other thing is one thing that I'm not seeing enough of is people are like, oh my
God, GitHub, how am I going to use Git?
If you are using GitHub as a central repository, you're just like doing Git wrong, right?
Your real problem is that GitHub created a bunch of proprietary tools to help you with
deployments and continuous integration and you got totally locked into them.
So I don't know, like I moved to GitLab from Bitbucket in a day because I pulled the repo,
added an origin, pushed the new origin, right?
It's really easy if you're doing everything by open standards and open tools and not using
any proprietary integrations.
It's really hard if you're using these one click deployment things.
And that's where I think a little bit of the FUD makes sense around like the Microsoft
acquisition because I could totally see an Azure button on like every repo, right?
Like deploy to Azure now.
Oh, 100%.
Yeah, absolutely.
Those things already exist.
Right.
And of course, Heroku has one, Microsoft has one, but the only way this really makes sense
is as yet another play to funnel people into Azure in my mind.
Yeah.
I mean, yeah, I think so.
Seems like this could also be just, hey, we're the developer company now.
You want to write software on Linux and deploy it on AWS, as long as you're doing it with
Visual Studio Code and pumping it through GitHub, we're good.
You know?
Like they don't care.
I think that might be the, this is, we're the company for developers and you look at
the contrast we just saw from Apple and then you look at Microsoft, Microsoft really has
been making a lot of moves,.NET Core, Visual Studio Code, and many other things on their
GitHub page, which we'll have a link to the show notes.
A lot of stuff is open source, including throwing windows on GitHub.
They may be the largest code contributor on GitHub.
I think that is actually a...
They are.
Yeah.
That's the truth.
So I wonder if this is even bigger than Azure in a way, like I absolutely fundamentally
has a very important, maybe the most important component is the Azure component and the future
potential there.
Yeah.
But I wonder if it isn't bigger than Azure.
Because look at Electron.
I think GitHub is, yeah.
Consider Electron too, right?
Electron.
Yeah.
And so it's a bigger purchase.
They have Electron now, they have GitHub and GitHub can, GitHub is like this middleware
between so many different endpoints.
It's so many things are tied into GitHub.
So many things are tied, like my Linux box sitting next to me right here is, it pulls
down updates from GitHub.
It's like, there's so many things that are tied into GitHub.
Oh, sure.
GitHub now has all of that.
Plus they have now easy tie-ins to Azure and they've got Electron.
So I think it's bigger than just one thing.
But okay, so the bigger message you think is that Microsoft is basically the anti-Apple
now.
They're saying, you know, we are the developer company, we're engineers, we understand you.
We're not doing weird documentaries on you.
Sorry.
Can I help it?
Yeah.
And also, I think it also means that a lot of Microsoft's products are going to probably
shift over to Electron.
Skype was just the beginning.
Yeah, I think that would have happened anyway, though.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, that's why they probably made the purchase.
This actually ties into both WWDC and the GitHub Microsoft purchase.
And I'm going to make a bold prediction here and I can't wait to see Telegram later tonight.
I think Microsoft is actually ahead of the game in a lot of ways.
They understand that the future is open standards.
I would argue the present is open standards, too, and progressive web apps, Electron, just
frankly not being crazy and proprietary about stuff where Apple's like, we're going to re-implement
machine learning in Swift because that makes sense.
It's weird.
I don't know.
I feel like there's something here, Chris, that both of these things happen on the same
day and the dichotomy between them is huge.
It's like night and day, help Mojave and Snow Leopard O.
Oh, yeah, I agree.
I think it is.
It's a massive A-B contrast between the two.
We couldn't be getting a bigger disparity because I really think Microsoft has shifted
towards this development platform focus and Apple is shifting towards this enrich our
ecosystem focus.
They've shifted.
They've been there for a while.
This enrich our ecosystem focus, make things better for the iPhone.
If you're on an iPhone, now you can scan using your iPhone camera and it goes directly into
the doc you're working on on the Mac.
That's where they're focusing, which is great for that ecosystem, but everyone's-
Or that type of user.
Right, but the thing is, if this continues, if these trend lines continue, everyone's
going to be writing software for those iPhones and especially the backend software for all
those Macs.
They're going to be writing it on Microsoft's tools.
They're going to be hosting the code on Microsoft's tools and the services are going to be running
on Microsoft servers.
Microsoft's going to own all of the stuff that's getting sold on those devices.
If Apple had played their cards better, they could have owned the entire stack better.
I agree with you 100%, but let's run it out five years.
In five years, it's not going to be writing your native iOS app using Xamarin.
It's going to be everything is a web standard, thank you, WebAssembly.
Check off your bingo card for Coderadio.
Microsoft is providing the best tooling, the easiest deployments from GitHub to Azure or
frankly from GitHub to wherever the hell you want.
I really hope they don't go too crazy with the Azure thing.
Apple is still trying to convince you to redo your whole workflow in Swift.
Apple had nothing future-leaning today other than the marzipan, which really, you know
what marzipan is?
It's rejiggering your iPad apps and your iOS apps to go work on the Mac, where Microsoft
is saying we are going to make best practices for frankly large-scale engineering projects
such as continuous integration, continuous deployment.
We're going to make those practices more attainable for even junior developers.
I'm talking kids right out of trade school or junior college rather.
You know what?
I take it back.
I welcome the click to deploy to Azure button on everything, if only to explain to junior
developers that you really have to automate your deployment, right?
Or maybe like some sort of Docker generation tool, like Docker file generation tool, which
by the way, Microsoft is a huge supporter of Docker and containerization in general.
Where Apple's, I don't know, trying to get me to run.
It's not even on the map.
Yeah, it's not even on the map.
Right.
I don't know how to do some crunches, I don't know.
But what about the FUD?
I mean, you are the host of the Linux action show, Chris.
Are you feeling-
Wow.
Retired.
It's the retired host of the Linux action show.
Wow.
You know what?
I just listened to the old episodes.
You're always my host, baby.
What particularly do you ask of me?
What do you want to know of me?
So, I mean, I'm sure you've seen some of the comments in Reddit, right?
Some of the, you know, M dollar sign, blah, blah, blah, yeah, yeah.
Does that have any weight to you, or is that kind of just, yeah?
Oh, yeah.
So, I asked some folks on Twitter that follow me, and it seems like everybody's pretty middle
of the ground.
It seems like, you know, people should have cared when Microsoft joined the Linux Foundation,
has come up a few times.
A lot of people feel like eventually it's going to not work out.
It's almost just guaranteed to eventually kind of devolve into something people don't
like from when it was independent.
So, a lot of people are just sort of hedging their bets.
But another, a fair amount of folks are pretty much sit back and wait and see.
See what happens.
Maybe things will work out okay.
I think that's sort of my position as well, is there's so much FUD going around right
now that you got to give time.
You got to calm down.
I mean, this deal isn't even going to be done for another six months or something.
So, we've got a lot of time before anything really changes.
And then once the deal does go through, I think it's at least worth sitting back and
seeing where this all goes.
And the fact that Nat Friedman is going to be running it is encouraging because he's
been in open source and working with Linux for a very long time.
I forget how I'm supposed to mispronounce his company, Zemarion.
When Microsoft acquired Zemarion, he became a Microsoft employee along with Miguel Itacaza.
And I got to say, like, if you're going to put somebody in charge of GitHub, it has needed
a new leadership for a long time.
That's kind of why they're in this position to begin with.
And he's been toying around with Linux since the 90s.
So it's like, who else are you going to put in charge that's not in a better position
at Microsoft to run this thing?
So I say it's at least we deserve, they deserve at least a wait and see approach.
That's my take on it.
It's not like you can't move to GitLab in 10 months.
Or, you know, a day or less.
He stresses in his blog post that we'll have linked in the show notes, coder.show slash
312.
He says GitHub will operate independently as a community platform and business.
They're going to retain its developer first values, distinct spirit, and open extensibility.
So it seems like maybe it's going to be more like a Zappos run business than it's going
to be a Skype run business for Microsoft.
It's going to be like LinkedIn, right?
When they bought LinkedIn, LinkedIn's basically still LinkedIn.
Which I mean, in that case, maybe not a good thing.
So what's everybody freaking out about exactly?
You know, I'm seeing a lot of stuff about like, well, all these, and it is true, right?
A lot of projects are moving off of GitHub.
It seems like there's just a lot of bad feelings in the community from like the 90s almost.
Like one argument that does make sense to me, although I am the one who originally made
it on Twitter was, you know, if I had proprietary software and I was in some way, even tangentially
competing with Microsoft, it might give me pause now that they have access to all of
my repos, right?
Like that, that might be a reason to be afraid, but those aren't the people who seem to be
screaming.
It seems to be the FOSS community, which Microsoft is already very much in bed with you.
Well, I don't think people acknowledge that as much as it's because it's more happening
at the business level and people don't see like all the behind the scenes code contributions
and stuff like that.
It's not apparent, you know, a gnome release is something that's in the user's face.
Microsoft contributing 200,000 lines of code to the kernel is not in the user face.
So I think that's part of it.
And I think, yeah, it's history.
You know, somebody on Twitter, again, I go back to, cause I've just been watching reactions
to this cause it's just been something.
Somebody on Twitter said that people just sometimes want to hate and they need something
to hate.
And it's a personality trait and we tell ourselves, oh, it's because they're Microsoft, it's because
of technical reasons, it's because of things that they've done.
But sometimes we just, that's just how we're wired up.
That could be a part of it.
You know, people have picked their tribe and now they're fighting it and they're going
to stay.
That's part of their identity is that.
I also have to leave a little space in here to acknowledge this could go wrong.
So not all of them may be wrong.
Microsoft could screw this up and it could really screw over a bunch of open source projects
somehow.
Right now it doesn't seem likely, but it could happen.
So right now, how is somehow, so what exactly could they do?
Well, you know, I couldn't tell you, but I will say this, um, and this has been a common
argument is I am really disappointed in Skype since Microsoft has bought it.
They destroyed its P2P inherent nature.
They've essentially tried to chase every particular type of tech trend since they bought it, including
right now, make it a Slack killer.
They've awkwardly integrated it in with other products.
It's gotten, it's gotten more love and I can see they've got a longterm vision with it,
but I really am just, I miss old Skype, old P2P, simple app, clean little tiny app that
just made calls Skype.
I don't want a Slack killer big electron app that uses web RTC, which in my opinion doesn't
sound as good as the old Skype and is now all server based.
So it's, it's also not as great for all those edge cases where P2P is, is a better solution.
I'm really unhappy with the way Skype's gone since Microsoft acquired them.
LinkedIn, I feel like has gotten pushier and a little more aggressive since Microsoft's
acquired them.
It's like they've gotten more runway to be dicks and I don't like that either.
So I'm not a hundred percent solid on Microsoft's longterm strategy here, but I'm willing to
give them the benefit of the doubt.
And it seems to be their particular strength.
They have a huge reputation for putting developers first.
I mean, Steve Ballmer has made that famous.
They have been making obvious inroads into the open source community for years now.
And I, it does seem like a natural fit and they have a good person to lead it.
So I'm not saying it's going to be a failure, but I think, I think we do a disservice a
little bit intellectually if we say it's not possible, what do you think of that?
I guess, I mean, I would say the better argument is more, once again, one of the five big tech
companies is eating what could have theoretically been a contender.
Now GitHub had weird harassment issues that kind of screwed them up.
But you can definitely think of an alternate universe where GitHub actually became a top
tier company.
Right?
Like I could see a mud.
Now it's weird though, cause what would GitHub have had to do to become equal to the Microsofts
and Facebooks and Amazons of the world?
I don't think it's possible.
Would they still have been GitHub?
No.
Just because of the resources they're giving away to the open source community?
No, no.
Because these corporations have 20 years of customer base, plus they have huge, massive
lucrative contracts with governments all over the world, and they've got major brand recognition
amongst average consumers, so they're able to introduce products that get big traction
much easier.
GitHub doesn't have, doesn't have those things going for itself.
I think it was probably destined to get purchased, if you think, if you think in those terms.
Doesn't you know, but it doesn't have to be a top five, it could have been a top hundred.
I mean, if it has to be purchased, I can't think of a better purchaser.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think so.
Right?
Like the, the thing about the alternate universe where Google purchased GitHub, that would
be some serious cause for alarm.
I bet you wouldn't be getting the same reaction though.
It might spook you and I more.
Oh, it would be, really?
You think, you think people would be more okay with it?
I do, yeah.
I see that would scare the shit out of me.
Like that.
Me too.
But I think, I think the people that are reacting strongly about Microsoft purchasing GitHub
are the people that would probably, not all of them, but a lot of them would probably
react better about Google.
I wouldn't.
Why?
Uh, because Google is an open source company and uses Linux.
That's the brand, right?
That's the, that's the, that's the community.
Every time I get, I get, I, every time I criticize Google on the show, people get upset at me
because I'm criticizing a company that uses open source.
Okay.
So every time I've ever been to a Google campus, it's a fricking sea of Mac books.
I just want to throw that out there.
I understand they use Linux on the server and this is not me trying to be a jerk, but
you know, uh, uh, laughing, the chat room points out, it says now that Microsoft owns
LinkedIn and GitHub, do they even need to bother interviewing new hires anymore?
Well, that's actually, you know what?
That's a fair point.
Can you imagine you get something in your GitHub email?
It's like, Hey, uh, want to come to Redmond?
Yeah.
Right.
They're going to have really interesting, they're going to have so many interesting
insights now.
That's the creepy part that we may learn more about as time goes on.
We may not.
I mean, this just broke today.
So we're still processing it.
It seems like there's still a lot to figure out and learn.
I'm sure they'll share.
Yeah.
And the reality is, I think for the first year, they're going to be very hands off,
right?
Nate, Nate, we'll go over and go ahead and take over, but then it's, I would be surprised
if we see aggressive moves because they, you know, it is true that people are, a lot of
folks have left to get lab.
Like I'm sure it is a very, very vocal minority, but I wouldn't be surprised if they just do
nothing for a year just to calm the community down and say, nothing's changed.
Your paychecks just say Microsoft now, right?
Yeah.
And they can afford to be a patient, slow moving company when it comes to this kind
of stuff.
Well, and get help makes money, right?
Get help does have revenue.
So it's not like they bought some little app startup that the app like never even launched.
Right.
And now their services costs probably just got removed.
So now it's going to be much more of a moneymaker.
Migrate that baby to Azure.
Yep.
All right, Mr. Dominic, is there anything else we want to touch on this week?
I know I'm going to go ahead and throw this Mac out the window and we'll be back on Pop
by the morning.
Wow.
All right.
Well, hey, there's a sale on Pixelbooks.
Tell the good folks where they can find you in the meantime, like somewhere else online.
Follow at Dumanuco on Twitter.
I'm sure it's going to be entertaining.
And follow me at Chris LAS.
And the show may float.
Recording days and stuff are changing as I'm on the road and Mike's going to be traveling.
So grab every single new episode at coder.show slash subscribe.
Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Coder Radio.
We'll see you right back here next week.