This is KOTOR Radio, episode 396 for January 11th, 2021.
Well hi there and welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and business of software development and the world of technology.
This episode is brought to you by a cloud guru.
So many career possibilities in the cloud, so little time.
ACG's learning paths help you take the right course to prepare for architect developer
security and many more high paying jobs.
Get hired, get certified, get learning at cloudguru.com.
My name is Chris and joining us every single week is our hostess with the Mac, it's Mr.
Dominic.
Hello Mike.
Wait, hostess?
Did I have a surgery I'm not aware of?
Do you still have the M1 by any chance?
Yes, I do.
I just thought maybe it got sent back since we talked last.
No, well, you know what?
This time the love has stuck.
Oh, oh, okay.
Well, we're going to talk about that in the show today.
Yeah, I do have some axes to grind first.
Oh my gosh.
Here we go.
First of all, why do we not have a shaman?
Yeah, I know.
You know what?
We've been around way longer than the Q conspiracy theory.
I want a dude in a Viking helmet with like objective C brackets, like tattooed on his
chest.
Wearing a robe.
Oh, goddammit.
You know it's going to be a robe, bro, man.
Come on.
The robe rows were out in force this week.
Hey, don't you besmirch the robe rows.
No, I think it's a coup, frankly, by the robe.
They're overthrowing the power of the Coderadio program and we're pushing the robe agenda
forward.
There's no doubt about it.
We're just going to become a show exclusively about robes.
That's all it's going to be every week.
We're going to go to a hotel, get a robe.
This is a little more chintzy than last week.
Fat cat in the chat room says he's going to get a robe tattooed onto his entire body.
That seems like the way to go, to be honest with you.
I don't know how it works.
Let us know, fat cat.
I moved office spaces this week.
So the studio has two upstairs office spaces and I moved to the other one.
But it was a nice chance to just redo everything.
So I got myself a standing desk forever ago, to be honest with you.
It's embarrassing how long ago I bought that, but never put it together.
So I finally got that put together and had the help of the wife and family over, helping
me just move stuff and clean stuff up.
Angela came over and helped grab a few things and wrangle kids.
We just kind of got a big chunk of work done and I got myself a whole new workspace set
up.
It's really nice.
It's like coming into a whole new work experience now.
It's changing my game.
I'm feeling the vibe, the new office vibe.
I actually ordered a replacement standing desk and every second that I'm on this very,
not strong enough to hold my computer, Amazon Day6 desk.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
Autonomous, I think is the brand, Autonomous IO.
That's the one that I bought too.
That's what I got.
And so it's got four memory positions and I mean really everything's working pretty
well except for now I have to kind of redo my wiring setup because I need to get longer
cables and stuff like that for the all the way up mode.
I think I want to mount the power adapt to the power brick for all the plugs.
I want to mount that to the wall possibly.
So I got to do things a little differently now, but for the first time, I'm investing
in me.
I'm even getting myself, get ready for this, a desk stand for my MagSafe adapter so I have
an actual spot and I can tidy the cord up.
I mean that's how fancy I'm getting.
That is pretty fancy.
I'm going to have like a metal pedestal for my phone, just set it down and it charges.
I'm done with the wires all over the place and the pucks all over the place, looking
like Doc Brown's desk or something.
I'm done with that.
You know?
I feel like I'm a gentleman now.
I got a gentleman desk.
I got one of them big mouse pads too, so like the whole thing's down, you know?
I have to tell you, working on this little desk, I understand what Dark Matter developers
must feel like.
It's like I have literally, this is the worst thing ever.
If I move my hand to slightly the wrong way, something is spilling into this iMac Pro,
which frankly is what it deserves because it's just trounced by the M1, but it was still
$5,000.
How are you getting the angle of the spillage because the iMac's not like, I see a laptop,
that's a target because the most vulnerable components are laying just right there on
the table.
You could easily knock something into the keyboard, which spills into the main board
and it's dead.
But an iMac, that's like up on a foot, you know?
It's way harder to get the beverages to the really important components.
You really got to aim.
You doubt my ability to destroy Apple equipment.
No.
It seems like a bet.
I think what it is, is I'm just trying to fantasize how you're going to pull it off.
Like a ricochet or you were stacking shelves and maybe there was like a beverage up there
that the kid set that you didn't even know was there and the shelf falls and it falls
inside.
The drink comes off the shelf and pours into the iMac.
Just do a little flair bartending and like miss.
Which is probably happening all the time at your place.
I'm sure.
Yeah.
Well, not anymore, but those were the days.
Okay.
Well, so we got a lot of feedback.
I mean, a lot of feedback.
And so if your email doesn't make it into this show, it may make it into the next one.
But we did ask people a little bit about their setups.
And now I'm really curious because they just redid mine and it really came down to like,
man, if I'm going to redo my desk and I have to pull everything out of here anyways, maybe
I should just move rooms where it's got a better view.
It's got airflow.
You know, it was a, it was a big setup.
So then people are starting to write in and tell me about their steps.
I'm like, oh, that's a good idea.
Maybe I'll do that.
So Eric wrote in with his setup for a, he's a suspicion and a software developer by day.
I think he dabbles with R and he said for work, I use a 2018 MacBook Pro and he does
sometimes have a choice.
He has a choice between that or severely locked down windows.
So you know, might as well go with the Mac.
He does some day work with MacBook and Docker containers and VS code.
They mostly use office 365.
He has a persistent team up session going on all the time, logged into some of their
nodes with a web based IDE called R studio server.
But he's been starting to use VS code a lot more with a remote extension for personal
projects at home.
And I love this.
It allows him to, you know, like modify Docker and stuff like that remotely.
But then he took it to the next level, Mike, and you may already know about this, but I
wanted to mention it for the audience in case you didn't know is what Eric is kind of migrating
to and I have set up at home and love it is VS code in a web browser and it's code server.
It's open source and it's essentially VS code in a tab.
And it's just so handy to like throw that up on a Linode or on like a local server that
I have in the RV where I don't use it super often because I prefer to have VS code local.
But every now and then I'm on a machine and it's just nice to have a centralized editor
and you can even edit local files on your server if you set it up particularly the way
I have it.
So are there, I guess there would be performance implications because it's literally an electron
app, right?
So yeah, it's really kind of cool.
I keep wanting this to be a thing and someone's going to have to correct me, but I think it
was cloud nine.
Yeah, years ago we talked like way when we were first talking about Docker with this
whole idea that like you are, you know, you'd go back to the eighties, right?
Your terminal would be just like a really, you know, that eight hundred dollar laptop
from Best Buy and your ID would live in the cloud.
This is kind of that dream, only it's now it's VS code.
Yeah, because I guess all my extensions would actually just work, right?
Because it's just running on another Ubuntu box or if you're, you know, have taste, SUSE.
By the way, I happened to be listening to a certain unplugged podcast of the Linux variety.
Anything you'd like to share?
Well, yeah, I was running SUSE in secret for a week.
I got to admit I was doing that.
I felt like it would derail the show, so I didn't mention it.
And then afterwards I thought, you know, maybe, you know, once I probably should have just
brought it up.
But, you know, I got to say it was all right.
It wasn't it wasn't great.
I unlike probably you, I find you asked to be a vestige of years gone past.
But you really want to use Zipper, though.
Yeah, I mean, I know.
I know.
But I'm just talking about for configuring the system in general.
I actually am not a huge fan of Zipper either.
I definitely like it more than something like RPM or apt RPM or or something like that.
But I think these days it's probably of like, say, Archdebian Red Hat varieties.
It's probably my and then you throw SUSE and it's probably my least favorite package manager
of that group.
OK, I mean, I will say there are niceties in apt that I miss.
It just seems slow to really slow to do any zipper.
It just really seems like I'm really waiting for the package manager.
There's a lot of steps in Zipper that I think, you know, I kind of started to kind of hone
in on the aspect I could really see liking about SUSE and that would be leap on my server,
tumbleweed on my laptop and desktop.
That kind of that kind of idea does resonate with me a lot.
And you know, long term, I think they've made some some clever choices in some areas.
So it's like all things with Linux, it's kind of pick your set of compromises and your sets
of wins.
Really.
Is that another way to say half broken?
Oh, see, well, I think what I prioritize is simple, minimal and whenever possible, built
in.
So if there's a way to just do a way to do something that system D just does it already
or like I prefer to go that route like one of the reasons it's silly, but we we talk
about it on plug.
We actually chose to run Arch Linux on our server here in the studio, and it's actually
kind of an important server to us.
But everything, with the exception of net data and Samba, everything runs in a container.
And so we keep arch on an LTS kernel and we update it semi frequently.
And really everything that we need is taking place in Docker.
And what I love about the setup is it is a minimum viable server.
It doesn't have anything extra.
It doesn't have any additional packages.
It literally has just what you need to get that environment functional.
And so it has a really low maintenance surface because of that.
And it has it's just kind of secure by default.
And it feels like with SUSE, it's kind of the kitchen sink distro, you know, even the
way you download it, they've got like the four point two gig DVD image or do you want
the net install or do you want the five I five eighty six optimize or the X 64 optimized
images and all of that just sort of feels kind of like the old school baked in approach
of Linux and there are advantages to it.
I prefer the minimum distro kind of thing myself for servers.
If you're playing the code radio drinking game, we've had Robros, SUSE, lizards, arch
and rust and R. And by the way, Eric, I believe, is the host of the R podcast.
Very good.
You should go listen to it.
You are probably suffering from alcohol poisoning right now.
So sorry.
All right.
If you're taking shots, the code radio drinking game, you're getting wrecked.
Oh, and objective C.
All right.
Go throw that in.
And the M1.
Did you say that?
Because if you didn't, I did.
Two shots for the M1.
Oh, and I said something insulting about Linux.
So that there we go.
So let's talk about a dev living the M1 lifestyle right now.
Kent writes in, says, hey, guys, responding to your question on last week's show, I work
at an education company and currently I'm building a new website to replace the in-person
training they used to do well because of Covid, obviously.
My dev machine of choice is the M1 MacBook Air with 16 gigabytes of RAM and a 35 inch
external monitor.
It's ultra wide 3440 by 1440 resolution because the company wants to integrate with their
WordPress and WooCommerce site.
I'm working in PHP for the back end, but building out a front end for a section of the WordPress
site with Flutter web.
Eventually this code will be reused to also launch mobile apps for Android and iOS.
And he says, by the way, sign me up for two robes, one for me and one for the lady.
I love it, Kent.
You got it.
Two robes, bros.
So good.
It's like I just, you know, I had an intuitive moment with the audience.
I just struck a chord with them.
Morgan writes in with a quick rundown of their setup.
You mentioned wanting to know a little bit about our setups.
Well, my main programming language is Go Bash and I work with Terraform and Ansible.
A little bit of Podman and K8s is in there, too, with WireGuard connecting everything
using Fedora and CentOS Stream now working good.
And then we use SystemD with a bit of Bash glue to tie it all together.
I'm split between maintaining our Linux distribution, managing the cloud component of our product,
and then of course, keeping our infrastructure for our factory working and hacking on the
code bases for these different projects and sending it upstream when possible.
He's working at a place, or they're working at a place called Holopot.com, H-O-L-O-P-L-O-T.com
in case I'm ready to replace my HomePods with something more pro.
And I checked out their site and holy shit, Holopot Plot, sorry, I keep messing that up.
It's H-O-L-O-P-L-O-T.com.
Looks incredible.
Like incredible speakers.
Yeah, you got to go look.
We had a few people write in, somebody wrote in with a solution on how to use Homebrew
on ARM and Intel, depending on which version you want with only one terminal, using different
environment variables or something.
I'll put a link to that in the show notes if people are interested.
Yeah, that was an interesting approach.
I think your approach is just simpler and easier to...
The only thing that's annoying with my approach is I wish I could set a different visual profile
for like Rosetta Terminal and...
Why aren't you using iTerm?
I mean, you've had a week, give it a go, come on.
It's a better terminal than the Mac OS Terminal, I tell you what.
Okay, why is it better?
First of all, it just looks a little bit better.
It has a lot more configuration options and it has the themes that you're looking for.
What I like about it now, you don't have to do it this way, but you can even set it as
sort of like that drop down Quake Terminal style terminal.
You can actually...
There's lots of guides to configure iTerm like that, so you can hit a key on your keyboard
and it just drops down from the top of your screen.
All right, well, I'll tell you what, as we do the rest of the feedback, I will live install
it.
How about that?
I really like the iTerm layout that I have, so you might like it.
I think it is pretty good.
I mean, in theory, that would solve my problem because then iTerm could just be like...
Because the little dirty secret is I'm almost always in Rosetta Terminal because...
The dirty secret is I'm always angry.
The dirty secret is I use a lot of Ruby gems and Python packages that are not compiled
for ARM.
We also got a tip that you can switch to the Visual Studio Code Insider builds, which I
guess are starting to support the M1.
It wasn't super clear from the feedback, but I guess if you get the Insider builds, you
get M1 support.
That might be something to think about too.
So of course, some setups aren't as swanky as the M1.
Josh writes in, he says, I work as a system admin, primarily in a Windows environment.
I've been doing a lot of PowerShell scripting and PowerShell Linux is a different bag than
in Windows.
Things like AD integration, registry edits, etc.
When I'm not in the office on my Windows machine, I have a ThinkPad T440P running for
door 33 and I have Windows 10 and I have server VMs.
I'm guessing he probably means Windows Server VMs with VS Code for development.
One thing that I noticed is that I really end up spending more time in the VMs than
on my host machine.
So he said I felt like my environment was just kind of unique and janky enough that
I wanted to share it all.
And then, devastatingly adds, I also want to throw some shade on the robe bros.
I just perked right up.
The only people I know who wear robes are my 60 plus year old parents.
Inappropriate.
Well actually, if you live in the south, there are some other people who wear robes but you
definitely don't want to hang out with them.
I feel like our feedback speaks for itself.
There are robe bros out there.
We are proud.
Robe bros also includes ladies, I will mention.
And we are uniting and we are going to change the agenda.
And it's not just men, it's not just women, it's even those tiny humans.
Reece writes in, very short and simple, I'm 13 years old and I want a robe, hashtag robe
bros.
So thank you, Reece.
All right, all right.
Stop corrupting the youth.
This has gone way too far.
I'm telling you, it speaks to the people.
It speaks.
It speaks to the people.
You're going to have a riot on your head if you don't come up with robes.
You know, I think robes are going to bring peace because you know what?
When you're wearing a robe, you're comfortable.
And who wants to riot when they're comfortable?
So last week, that's what we needed.
Come into JB Studios, we got robes, cannabis, and scotch and you just sit back and listen
to a podcast.
Yeah, I feel like the robes are not the operative functioning things there.
So I appreciate Reece lodging their vote and I love that we have 13 year old listeners
too.
So we have a few more setups.
I just want to blast through really quick.
Like I said, there's a whole bunch sent in and if you don't hear yours here, I may cover
it next week or I may just reply directly back to you.
Before I do that, I want to mention that a cloud guru has the Red Hat certified system
administrator exam prep.
In this course, they cover the skills and concepts necessary to pass the Red Hat R-H-C-S-A
exam using a mix of lessons and hands-on labs.
They tie it all together with a challenge lab that really helps you test your skills.
So if you're looking at getting Red Hat certified, check out the link in the show notes and get
started at the cloudguru.com or go specifically to this course with the link that we'll have
in our show notes.
It's a cloud guru's Red Hat certified system administrator exam prep.
The best way to learn is by doing.
For more feedback, this one is an AWS stack from Paul.
Hey there, just writing it with my typical dev stack by day I specialize in AWS and serverless
technologies.
All of our APIs are deployed to AWS Lambda and written in Express.js.
We use a combination of DynamoDB and Aurora Serverless for our databases.
Our front ends are written in Vue.js or Angular depending on the developer and for mobile,
we leverage the Merian forms.
Outside of the day job, I write my games in either straight C or minimal C++ and open
GL and SDL and sometimes I'll pair it with a little good old C sharp and mono game.
That's Paul on the AWS Lambda stack.
In fact, you know, Mr. Dominic, we've got a handful of people using AWS.
So I kind of condensed them down into Paul's email, but that set up, you know, some sort
of JavaScript framework, AWS serverless, probably mentioned three or four times by
people that sent in emails, which that's kind of interesting.
I think.
Yeah, last year I briefly did a project on a Lambda using F sharp, believe it or not.
It was, it's one of those things that was so straightforward in terms of getting it
set up that it's almost, we didn't really cover it too much, but I mean, it's exactly
what it says on the tin, right?
It's a serverless thing.
It turns on, runs your functions, you know, data in, all I was doing is data in data out.
You know what it is about iterm I just realized not to jump around like a maniac, the developers
wear robes when they code.
How did you know?
You're a little predictable.
It feels like a Linux terminal on Mac OS.
It feels like the configuration you get with a Linux terminal emulator.
So Susan wrote in with a really solid arch set up, Susan from Nepal.
They said that they've been listening to the show for quite some time and really love it.
In regards to the question we asked about people's work setups and their stack, their
development machine is a six year old ASUS laptop, but it's held up really well.
It has a fourth gen i7, 16 gigs of RAM, an NVIDIA 950M in there, and it just keeps working.
The dedicated graphics was a total waste of money as I haven't played a single game on
this machine in about 12 years, she says, yeah, I know, right?
The project we're working on our company is large and takes some time to build around
five minutes.
So instead of buying a new powerful machine, we refactor the entire application into modules
and leverage that to reduce the build time significantly.
Now the build time is in, for the different modules, between five to 40 seconds in general.
The OSs that they've hopped through are Linux Mint and Kali and Ubuntu, but in the last
few years have settled on Arch.
It's only broken once, that was for Kernel 5.9 and an Intel video driver, but they quickly
found the solution on the forum.
And other than that, it's really simple, lightweight, that combined with, he says, or they say,
they were a GNOME fanboy, but they were having annoying problems where the display would
stutter from time to time and just got little issues, little paper cuts on GNOME, switched
over to Plasma, never looked back since then.
So the Arch Plasma setup has been totally rocking for them and rock solid, super smooth,
uses less resources without compromising features and makes for a great workstation.
And I just love that, to get Susan's take from Nepal and the idea of these, sometimes
we talk about these absolute latest machines.
This is a 12-year-old laptop running Arch and she's getting perfectly good performance
from it and working, getting the day job done.
And the approach, instead of throwing more hardware at it, was to break the application
up into modules and then build the modules as needed, which go much faster, totally a
valid approach.
Yeah, that's not that crazy at all.
Probably easier for maintenance long-term as well.
So that's also a win when doing that.
Okay.
So the last one, the last one we have for this episode, we have a batch for next week
too, but Mike wrote in and after selling his company and sticking around for a while and
kind of getting the bonus for sticking around, they kicked off what they thought would be
a four-month project, they're now 14 months into it.
They're using AWS, Lambda, DynamoDB, Elasticsearch, S3 of course, CloudWatch.
For the CICD, they're using CodePipeline and CodeBuild.
Their infrastructure as code is Terraform running in the Terraform cloud.
Go on the server side with some JavaScript and Java where there's existing third-party
libraries that are superior and available.
They use, and this is something I wanted to ask, but they use Go's built-in unit testing
capabilities.
Side note, I think that's the question for next week's episode.
How do you test?
Is it old school?
Is it manual?
You're not testing.
You have very specific methodology for building and testing.
Coder.show slash contact.
How do you test?
I'd love to know that.
But here's the interesting thing that Mike says.
My development machine is the XPS 13, the 9380 version.
Usually docked to a Dell UltraSharp 27 4K monitor, JetBrains for the IDE, and SmartGit
for Git interactions.
Serverless has been great.
Switching to serverless has zero regrets for doing so, and follows the latest best practices
and uses the right CI and CD tools for each deployed environment.
And they love it.
He says, I'd love to hear what people are doing for unit testing.
I've grown increasingly dependent on my unit tests to confidently make changes in my platform.
I'm approaching 4,000 unit tests across my code bases.
I recently upgraded from Angular 9 to 11.
It took me about an hour, and that included patching a few issues I discovered thanks
to my tests.
I couldn't imagine doing it without the tests.
I think it's a great question that Mike brings up.
Mike, listener Mike, how do you test?
Let us know.
Coder.show slash contact.
Yeah, testing is one of those things, you're never going to be where you need to be on
it.
You know, and it bites you in all forms, too, because there's also not just, there's not
just, this is the one that bit me, is my environment.
I updated my environment, and that broke.
And so then production, and a production application broke, and I didn't realize it because I forgot
to test the underlying platform stuff.
I just tested the application.
So that, you know, you're always learning.
It feels, that has to be, I think, I think the mindset is, I'm just going to keep evolving
this all the time.
It's like a checklist that I have for the RV.
I've been driving that RV now for like five years, and I still, from time to time, add
up, I need to start checking this.
In fact, I'm not kidding you, last night I had a nightmare that I forgot to check something
and I was driving down the road with my awning sticking out.
That's when I woke up, I woke up like, crap, did I?
Okay, it was just a dream.
See, if you were wearing a robe, you never would have made that mistake.
No, right, because you have one robe for when you're lounging and one robe for when you're
road ready, obviously.
Oh my god.
Yeah, well, there is room for a multi-robe lifestyle, no doubt about it.
You have your winter robe, your evening robe, and your combat robe.
Well, you clearly have to.
I mean, you don't want to wear your winter robe in the summer.
You wouldn't be comfortable, and the robe's all about being comfortable.
You can't wear a white robe after Labor Day, so.
And not be a gentleman.
And you know, sometimes it's special night with the ladies, you want to have a nice red
velvet robe.
I mean, you might.
I don't know.
Maybe you don't.
It's more black velvet.
I'm with you so far.
Linode.com slash coder.
Go there and receive a $100 60 day credit towards your new account.
Linode is the largest independent cloud for developers.
They're our cloud hosting provider for Jupiter broadcasting right now as we are doing this
show.
We're streaming on a brand new Jupiter.tube PeerTube instance hosted on Linode.
And here's what's great about it is on the back end, I'm using Linode's object storage
to store the videos.
So when we post a video on there, it goes through all the various different coding styles
that you need for like mobile and low resolution and HD, and then it stores them on object
storage in Linode.
And the reason why that is fantastic is not only are those files now available via URL
if we want to link to them directly and it means they download super quick and they load
up in the player super quick, but it means we don't have to like carve off like a terabyte
of block storage and then use like 300 gigs and know that OK, well maybe in like six months
we might be using 700 gigs, so we better go for a terrible like you don't have to do any
of that with object storage.
You just use it as you need it and it's super easy to get access to it because it's all
S3 compatible and Linode costs 30 to 50% less than major cloud providers like AWS, Google
Cloud and Azure.
You get a nice balance of technology and price and you can get something like $5 a month.
What I did for our PeerTube instance is I first we tried it just like a two core machine,
four gigs of RAM and did a proof of concept.
We ran that for about 24 hours.
We got an idea of what we wanted and maybe what we might change and then we just nuked
that one and we just set up a new one in the production data center we want to deploy on
and this time I went for something with four CPU cores so that way we can render video
that gets uploaded and leave a couple of cores available for live streaming and it's all
set up and it's ready to go in seconds.
And if you want to get a gaming server going, they have all of the options right in there
to set up a lot of popular game servers like a like a Minecraft server for example or or
an arc server or many others and they have a lot of the options you might want for the
game server, but like maybe it's a creative world versus survival or any kind of mod settings
you might want, they're all in the setup for you right there and an easy to click use interface
and then you hit deploy and you got your own custom server.
So if you want to use it for your business like we do or you just want to use it for
a personal site or service, get started by going to lano.com slash coder.
Get that $100 60 day credit towards a new account and you support the show.
Helps this humble podcast stay free lano.com slash coder.
So there's some hoopla this week I'm a little worried that we're touching the third rail
on this one because there's there is just so much going on right now where world news
is getting into tech and one kind of hit close to home since we were on the air jet brains
really went under the magnet magnifying scope thing what do you call it microscope microscope
thank you jet brains got kind of called out in a way for potentially being like a back
door for Russian hackers and really got a lot of fun throwing at it.
Yeah well that was brought to us by the little bull so and the New York Times actually yes
yeah yeah they said there that Russian hackers may have piggybacked on a tool developed by
jet brains which is based in the Czech Republic to gain access to federal government and private
sector systems you know all the solar winds they say American intelligence agencies and
private cyber security investigators are examining the role of the widely used company jet brains
in a far reaching Russian hacking officials are investigating whether the company founded
by three Russian engineers in the Czech Republic with research labs in Russia were breached
and used as a pathway for hackers to insert back doors into the software jet brains said
on Wednesday that it was not aware of any investigation at all nor is aware of any compromise
and that the team is trying to get more information from the FBI does everything to Russia yeah
I know right and you know it's it's unnamed U.S. officials it's unnamed cyber security
experts and they say things like security experts warn that months long intrusion could
be the biggest breach of the United States network in history but that's like well yeah
okay if all this is true and they compromise systems and they were in for a month or three
then yeah it'd be a really big deal but they throw that in there as if it's already true
as if it's already happened it's it's bull so gather around children when you are hosting
software yourself that you buy from a vendor such as I don't know team cities a popular
solution that jet brain sells and you do not update said software or you are not managing
your hosting right that can be a problem I have a huge issue here because the way the
story was reported it makes it sound like like the jet brains like they're updating
tool or whatever was completely compromised all the solar winds right not the case what
it looks like and you know no one's gonna confirm this yet but I'm hoping that at some
point they do is that there were at least one potentially more unpatched out-of-date
improperly configured team city instances that were being self-hosted by various customers
and that is a vector for compromise just like if you have an unpatched out-of-date WordPress
instance on a server somewhere right so this is nonsense it's nuanced because
it involves understanding that software can be created by a company and deployed by a
user incorrectly and then be used as a vector of attack and if you don't understand that
nuance it just looks like well jet brain sells a bad product right you have to understand
that if a customer is hosting a vendor software and managing it themselves that they are ultimately
responsible for the security of said software yeah and I actually think that's the biggest
disservice by kind of labeling all of this as nation state attacks it sort of reduces
the responsibility of the sys admins that set that up in the first place like that's
on them they set that up incorrectly and it didn't really take somebody with sophistication
it took somebody who was willing to crawl the web and I when I saw this what my first
thought was is how does this impact a guy like Mike who maybe has clients who know he
uses these tools do you worry about it hurting your reputation by association I actually
took to Twitter as one does these days because I was pretty concerned right because we use
Ruby bind we use pie charm it's we're basically a jeopardy shop we actually don't use team
city though so there's that yeah it's it's not great right I don't you know is it going
to make us dramatically change our tooling no VS code is slowly but surely making us
do that yeah I mean if I was using team city I think I might be more concerned having said
that now that they're you know publicly in caps and red letters with the hammer and sickle
next to it publicly known to like non people in the industry as a Russian company which
they are not from the Czech Republic different country that maybe isn't great having said
that a lot of my clients particularly those in like regulated industries also are JetBrains
customers so you know if you're doing Java you're probably wanting you're at least looking
at IntelliJ it may be that their brand and reputation withstands this but yeah I think
they had they're gonna get some crap from like people like honestly stupid congressmen
who are gonna want to like grandstand right yeah I hope I hope there's nothing to be concerned
about I I guess I'd be lying if I didn't say now I kind of have like a bit of doubt about
the company like just a little bit of hmm you know okay like I'm gonna kind of keep
my eye on them now and I think that's super unfortunate because they don't deserve that
before that their action so far had had really you know what they've done is they've made
a good product and they've charged for that product and that seems like it's been a pretty
good business model so maybe this will blow over I hope I don't think it's gonna really
affect them I mean it might I could see it may be affecting like the team city line which
I sure I don't mean to downplay that I know that's a big product for them but just not
the way I run my process so not something I'm interested in I mean I just just like
from my own experience switching the entire IDE infrastructure and the plugins and all
the custom crap you've probably written for them for your entire company based on one
very shoddily reported New York Times article that sounds expensive and bad so okay now
the other thing that's obviously going on right now that has huge ramifications for
our industry is parlor as we recorded now is offline I'm not really familiar with it
but I know it's a social network that's like an alternative to Twitter that has gotten
famous for a lot of well-known people on the right to switch to it after Twitter had started
fact-checking or whatever and you know this whole thing is all kind of been going down
for the last couple weeks if you want more context you can always check out unfiltered
unfiltered.show but there's been a lot of changes a lot of things have been happening
very fast and sometimes you know I think for the better and some I think have have been
sort of like oh boy now the genie's out of the bottle on that one and an AWS pulling
the plug on parlor that was a moment where I went oh whoa well that feels like a whole
other level did you get that sense?
So I gotta be honest with you I don't know what the hell parlor was until this week.
Yeah they went from being famous to offline in about a week.
And I just want to like make sure I understand it's effectively Twitter right but like with
no rules?
Right right well I don't know I really don't know about that but I know that it's been
like promoted as like the free speech social media or whatever which of course attracts
all kinds right.
The question that I had after this happened is it's one thing right if Twitter says okay
we're gonna close your account because that's their service well AWS that's really kind
of become like the infrastructure of the internet that's a whole other level and a lot of dominoes
fall after that.
So but it wasn't AWS first right it was the App Store I think right?
Right Google Play and then the App Store.
And then like Dio preemptively came out and said they wouldn't host them.
So like there's a lot of weirdness here right there's a lot of reporting that like maybe
the guy who founded parlor's wife is a Russian spy.
Oh Russian?
A Russian and this makes me want to talk about honey traps for a minute.
You have Unfilter we have this I have my company where are these Russian women for us Chris?
Where were they when we needed them?
Where is our honey trap money is what you're saying?
Right you want the you want the girl and the investment in rubles.
I mean Jupiter Broadcasting is a podcast network has a reach that far exceeds many very popular
magazines.
You know somebody ought to be in here you know getting some propaganda in this we got
a platform but no none of that Putin money.
Just like a little gas prof cash.
Yeah they got tons of oil money man come on they got so much oil money that they used
to build nuclear powered lighthouses have you looked that up have you seen that on YouTube?
No that's nuts.
One of these days you should look up nuclear powered lighthouses blow your mind what they
were doing.
So come on just a little bit our way would you but I agree what I find to be interesting
is the details that have come out now that parlor is suing Amazon it kind of because
in the lawsuit it sheds a little bit of light on Amazon's rationale for banning parlor they
say this is according to Amazon the team said that it was troubled by repeated policy violations
the email cited 98 posts that incited violence it included screenshots of a call to hang
traders as well as exoneration to start systematically assassinating liberal leaders and supporters
of the black lives movement matter and others in January.
Amazon said publicly they cannot provide services to a customer that is unable to effectively
identify and remove content that encourages or incites violence.
I mean if that you know that kind of that kind of stuff like OK well where does Amazon
draw the line.
Maybe that is where they should be drawing the line but it was just still kind of surprising.
I mean obviously all that stuff is gross right.
Yeah.
I have no defense for it but I do wonder like if you're if you're a small startup and you're
doing some kind of platform does that mean like if you just like fail to moderate your
platform because you're like three guys in a dorm room AWS is going to kick you off if
you get big enough.
I think it definitely means that now because I feel like I mean I don't think any of that
stuff is good and this climate will make it such that any service that is centralized is
vulnerable like that.
Well that's problematic.
I mean we think of Twitter as like the strongly you know kind of like woke moderated platform.
Back in the day Twitter was a garbage pit.
Good point.
Remember Twitter porn which is still a thing but it was like people were doing revenge
porn and like harassment of girlfriends and boyfriends.
If you actually look at the whole history of Twitter it may have been more of a garbage
platform for longer than it's been a woke politically correct platform.
Right.
And then it just you need money to like moderate this crap right like that's one and they want
to sell ads.
Well but like you at some point moderation requires actual moderators and humans are
expensive.
That's my point.
So like I wonder if this is the standard which I kind of am coming dangerously close to saying
this shouldn't have happened which I kind of don't agree with because if you're calling
for political assassinations that's obviously not good and potentially a crime.
But could you make a new Twitter in a dorm room or a new Facebook in a dorm room and
actually satisfy these requirements in a realistic way.
The reason why I say no is because this isn't where it ends.
OK where does it go.
It's an evolving issue.
Not only is a loud speech an evolving and usually narrowing issue but I really kind
of am concerned about other issues that don't seem that impossible.
I could see even within 2021 it comes up a pretty big debate about the US law requiring
back doors and encryption.
It was something that the Obama administration fought for really hard.
It was something that I mean you can find tons of James Comey on YouTube talking about
it and I could see the issue too if radicalization in the US is becoming a bigger and bigger
problem then the need to get access to these private communications is going to become
a bigger and bigger issue.
And so what happens when a service refuses to do that and what is going to be sort of
the system's response to that.
And so just like you may have to moderate or else you're going to be held liable you're
also likely going to have to meet legal requirements when it comes to encryption to operate in
the US.
That's also going to tighten the noose a little bit.
I mean so that's just that's just one example of how the goalpost will always be moved because
society is always always moving.
So you kind of get down to the argument of things change whatever you have to change
with them.
But do you let the market decide that and like you just fail if your platform sucks.
Well I mean you feel you figure if this is if this becomes the new normal it will create
demand for something that's not censored.
It will create demand for something not if you can't host it anymore.
Well yeah.
Or you have to use the tools like you have to build your own system you have to build
your own email server you have to host that yourself you have to build your own e-commerce
platform.
Yeah but that's that's such a lift.
I mean but it is easier than ever.
You know.
True.
There's a lot of packages out there or Docker images or you know I mean there's a lot of
options out there.
See I'm very of two minds on this.
I don't like obviously what I've seen of Parler is probably the worst of it right.
Because it's right when it got taken down.
Yeah.
But I have no problem with like a private business saying hey because I think you guys
are you know unacceptable.
I would use a different word but we're not going to serve you anymore.
You know we're not a public utility and you like if I just like fired a client because
whatever or I refuse to take a client because of whatever it's I think when you get into
cases like it's all it's less the AWS when it's more the app store one that kind of bothers
me a little bit because it's like there is no other way to develop on that platform.
Yeah well the web but yeah yeah but you're you're gimped in a lot of ways right.
And history has shown us specifically with social media platforms people want a native
local app.
Well because they want to do photos want to do filters and it's possible but it's never
going to be as good of an experience.
But again like I wish it wasn't parlor do you know what I mean it would be easier to
kind of get on my heels and be like you know like when hey.com got like pushed around by
Apple that that was easy right right.
This is like well you guys actually did like a way way over any reasonable line you know.
So I don't know I I sort of miss and this is where we're going to be a little you and
I are going to pour one out for Sun I sort of miss the ideal of like the 90s when like
the Internet was becoming a thing and people are just going to develop their software man
and you download the member shareware and it'd be great and we'd be happy and you'd
have like a million little dev shops doing all these crazy things.
And they'd be like news groups that would specifically be like for these types of people
in software that really geek out about this particular thing and computers and that was
great.
I actually still have a very active Usenet connection to you really.
I do I do although I don't quite use it for the same thing anymore but I do follow what
you mean.
And also I guess this is me being an old man but I yearn for a time before Twitter.
Yeah.
Like things were so much better in a lot of ways.
Just slowing the pace of conversation and allowing time for thought and deliberation
and not creating a discourse where your goal is to get as many likes and retweets as possible
so you're always turning the dial up so that we always are getting people engaged.
I think it just brings out the worst in people.
It's negative incentives right.
You're always like I look at my own stats because I'm a I see I'm an attention enthusiast
I was going to say something else there and it's just true.
Like if I can say something mean about Linux that like triples engagement if I say something
nice about Linux it doubles it if I say something negative about Apple forget about it I can't
even keep up with the notifications.
That's so true.
It's like yes for sure yes yes and if we really wanted to play the game we'd intentionally
say something incendiary about Linux or Apple and then we'd cut it and we'd clip it and
then we'd post that as a standalone bite on Twitter and blast it out off to the races.
Right.
Yeah.
And that's what people do.
It's just all right.
Well so let's let's shift gears to a little bit of tech because in your M1 endeavors one
of the things we were talking about last week specifically was the state of Docker and not
being ready for the M1 platform.
I guess have you had any more experiences with trying to get Docker working on that
sucker is the situation improved.
So there is a development release of a Docker version for the M1.
OK.
It's still in dev mode.
It's it's not there yet but you know like we talked about when this M1 first came out
this is going to be a problem that Docker is going to solve pretty quickly.
Yes sure.
I would bet my hat in 60 days we're not talking about this anymore.
That seems pretty aggressive but.
So do you know like they must be doing some sort of VM right.
They must be doing some sort of.
They have to move over to Apple's new hypervisor is the problem which you know to be honest
with you I mean maybe it's totally flushed out but you kind of wonder like what's this
how complete of a product how solid is just that because it seems like those are that's
new plumbing for the OS to begin with and it may be one of those things that needs a
little bit iteration itself but it is interesting to see that they're just plugging away at
it.
I'm just I was just going through it.
Yeah it looks and it looks like they're getting a pretty good amount of engagement too.
So it's going to it'll get there won't it.
You're probably right.
I don't know.
You.
The only thing I think your prediction is just a little optimistic if that new set of
virtualization APIs and Mac OS ends up being kind of half baked then there's really not
it's a kind of out of Docker's hands there's nothing they can do.
I would be very surprised if that's the case because remember people want to run Windows
on Mac too in VMS and that's like a core feature for them data dog dot com slash coder radio
data dog is the unified monitoring and analytics platform that gives you comprehensive visibility
into cloud hybrid and multi cloud environments.
The key is you can really quickly analyze the performance of your Linux servers and
applications in real time you get customizable dashboards that are beautiful.
You should go to data dog dot com slash coder radio just to kind of get an idea of what
the UI is like.
But the nice thing is is these dashboards give you the ability to do all kinds of things
like troubleshoot issues in seconds get a unified view of your metrics your traces your
logs all in one place and they have just turnkey integrations for over 400 different technologies
and you can use data dog as a monitor your Linux boxes the containers and the applications
inside them and then pull in metrics and other data from the rest of your entire stack across
multiple clouds to get visibility and health into the performance of your entire infrastructure
and applications.
So do this get started by going to data dog dot com slash coder radio start a free trial
create a dashboard and data dog will send you a T-shirt.
Yep that's awesome.
It's a nice looking T-shirt too you see when you go to the data dog dot com slash coder
radio URL and that's a great way to get started experience the UI and how you can lay it out.
It's so slick data dog dot com slash coder radio go there start a free trial get one
dashboard set up and then you get yourself a free T-shirt.
Thanks to data dog for sponsoring the coder radio program and thanks to everybody who
supports our show by going to data dog dot com slash coder radio.
So let's do a little M1 update.
You must have a little bit better sense of the battery life at this point.
Days.
It's out of control.
I actually forgot where I put the charger.
You know I gosh I got I am thinking maybe I I'm trying not to talk myself into buying
one and then you.
You need to do it.
Yeah.
Just get the air get.
I don't.
So I did bump it to 16.
If I should if I was going to do it I should have done it as like a Christmas gift for
my wife or something you know you should have done it at the end of the year for the
write off.
I just missed the taxi window too.
I wonder if those business now I shouldn't even I shouldn't even do a business.
I just I am kind of curious about what it's generally like and you know people been telling
me that it's something you really got to experience to fully understand.
All right.
I am going to tell you right now.
Giving having given it a second chance and less of like a whatever kind of I snarky I.
Yeah it is my favorite computer that I have ever owned ever ever even like the nostalgia
days of of years past.
I wish it ran Snow Leopard.
By the way if you're not blacked out by now you're going to be in trouble.
Yeah that's got to be on somebody's drinking game.
I mean yeah Big Sur is no snow leopard.
Big Sur is the worst part of it.
But just like not having to think about plugging in and this thing goes from asleep to I'm
in my works workspace in like almost instantaneously that is nice and somebody saying but Linux
in the chat Gavin is I'm hoping that system 76 or Dell or one of those guys can somehow
match this because the hardware benefits the speed the no fan no fan it's it's awesome
like it I literally I like maybe I could see a world where I just work on a MacBook Air
for a while because that's the for those who don't listen every week that's the model I
have the MacBook Air it's I mean it's fast enough even in Rosetta I don't notice any
noticeable slowdowns I mean obviously the iMac Pro and the Thaleo have like more RAM
and dedicated GPU so that's a little like certain things are a little unfair right like
the Thaleo runs the flight simulator the air doesn't for obvious reasons but as a day-to-day
computer if the apocalypse ever ends and I can go on trips again having a laptop that
one has no fan and two barely ever needs to be charged is gonna be a game changer for
me yeah the battery life seems just like it would be it would fundamentally change the
way I would use the computer oh and as more people have it particularly like them the
Super Mac community a lot of the like pain points I experienced the first go-around have
just either been people know workarounds or have been resolved and honestly when stuff
starts getting ported to ARM I think I'm gonna see additional performance increases from
where I'm at now yeah that's kind of the funny thing huh it's not even as fast as it's gonna
be in a year right this machine like if I can manage not to pour a goddamn martini into
it or Earl Gray depending on the week it might actually last me more than six months yeah
which is you know that's a lot of commitment for me you know I'm a little good little shy
you know I mean you just miss it but that is that Linux thing is the major blocker for
me that's why I ended up going the route of the x1 and then tried out the XPS 13 and now
I was I was fantasy specking myself a galago pro they don't have the dedicated Nvidia graphics
until February though we all know I'm a shell for system 76 I'm joking by the way people
have read it I am not in fact a show I can't unhear the galago's fan now yeah no fan is
such a big deal too I love that for recording especially recording when I'm on the go like
even the iMac Pro oh gosh oh no oh no don't stop it stop it I can't think about it but
that no fan deal no fan that no fan is a big deal because when I'm on the go my mic is
often right next to my laptop I am super tempted to just take because I've I mean this is way
inside how Mike setting up his new workstation but I have two workstations once the Thalia
because it does specific things and once the iMac because I stupidly bought an iMac Pro
I sort of think the iMac Pro is just gonna become the MacBook Air workstation and that's
it what do you mean you're not even gonna use it I keep going back and forth but like
every time the fan kicks in a part of my soul dies you're like what what is this the 90s
what is this spin and rest in this thing yeah it's like it's like my dog's hair like just
caking in this piece of crap like you know I don't want to tempt you because you are
like super Linux guy but it's the it's the damn console vacation of computers and it's
so frustrating you know don't don't don't buy one because the fan you you will you won't
go back right fanlessness yeah it really is it is frustrating because a lot of the performance
it really appeals to me the battery life the no fan really appeals to me I also I am I'm
pretty convinced that it's just a great chip like Apple probably really knows what they're
doing and it's sort of the ultimate expression of their idea of a computer where that's an
all-in-one that they build from the ground up the hardware OS all of it it's an interesting
idea but without that escape hatch you've been able to load Linux on there I'm just
like it just wouldn't be as useful for me it would be a slam dunk if I was still in
a corporate environment and I had a lot of meetings and calendar invites and all that
kind of you know just stuff that you want to stay up to date with and all that and ran
slack a lot and did all that like I could see it for sure but right now like my main
production tools they haven't been ported to m1 so there's that as well so I'd be running
a lot of stuff under Rosetta well I will say like one of the more interesting effects that
it's had on me I'm weirdly getting used to like native Mac apps again and I'm getting
like you mentioned slack I'm getting increasingly frustrated with slack because it's such an
obvious electron app and doesn't like follow the conventions the right way of for those
who have been listening for a long time I was an iOS developer back when you sort of
like that was like full-time what I did so I lived in the Mac for like ever before I
even really did much with Linux other than college which you know everybody fools around
with Linux in college the like poorly done electron apps really stand out on Mac OS where
they don't on Linux to me I think part of that is just like there's such conventions
on Mac for like how the keyboard shortcuts are supposed to work yep yep we're on Linux
everything is kind of like written in its own weird way and you just have to know the
application but like airmail fantastical and no fan yeah I'm just gonna keep saying it
Chris yeah I do hear that imagine sitting in your rope with no fan yeah you know you
know my my x1 and the XPS 13 I really don't they do have a fan but it's very minimal don't
hear it much so it's my it's getting much better on the Intel side too with the later
processors but you know I think for me my I would I mean the battery life does sound
really good I don't know I'd be tempted I'd be really tempted if they had if some of my
production applications were ported I mean I already am tempted I'm just always tempted
from a technological like tinkering standpoint my one concern is how can they ladder this
up to like a MacBook Pro 16 because if they can actually do that with with like a similar
performance increase that you would have gotten from the errors of Intel age and the sixteens
of you know the last whatever with the I nines I think right if they have the same delta
of performance those machines why would you not get one yeah I just I will right I mean
yeah if anything where like especially for the unfiltered show because I do I do that
all the processing myself there's no editor anything you know an hour and a half show
takes forever to process it really is a pain in the butt don't even don't even get me started
on trying to encode that much video it just is a time it just takes forever it's like
you work all day on something and then it's the evening and you just want to go home and
you're sitting here waiting while your laptop just maxes out and anything that may be dramatically
improved that time would would be pretty hard for me to say no to I've actually thought
about to like well you know the nice thing about the PC architecture is it is possible
to build a just all out powerhouse PC system that outflanks anything an M1 machine could
do you know you could you could really get like a thread ripper going 128 gigs of RAM
four terabytes of PCIe SSD storage you know you could really put a nice GPU in there and
get something that really cranks maybe like an AMD 6800 series GPU and that thing and
it would blast the doors off the M1 I suspect but you know I'd be looking at three thirty
five hundred you know four or five thousand dollars if it's a pre-built you know maybe
even more of it you know six seven depending on the on the manufacturer and it just feels
like give it a year and a half and there and Apple's gonna lap it but it is it has crossed
my mind and it's what drew you know if drew was on the show right now what he'd be telling
me I bet you is build a really powerful Linux system and do all the production tools under
Linux and with a combination of wine and native tools and get 90% of the benefit with without
having to switch platforms because that's the one thing that's still nice about x86
right is if your work case demands it you can really build a system that's really specific
to you and what I struggle with Apple now is the console vacation of these machines
it's like yeah okay I could I could get the same exact thing in various varieties either
with active cooling or without and I can run one operating system and it's not even one
I particularly want to run I don't want to run Big Sur like I probably wouldn't buy a
PC that only ran Windows 10 and it's just that is enough friction that I haven't pulled
the trigger yet but in reality I'm not going to build that rise and thread ripper system
I don't have time to do that I don't have the funds I'm not going to do it but I like
that it's still possible and that's not an option with the M1 I mean your best bet is
adding compute via Thunderbolt but you can't even do an eGPU at this point at some point
we need to talk about eGPUs again because that that was the dream that never came yeah
so this is the thing right I and by the way the MacBook Air that I keep salivating about
was only $1,200 so I would argue that like every other you just buy a better one yeah
which and they like god damn it I hate to admit it but dang it it's true the price points
pretty good right it's yeah I have been thinking about selling the X1 Carbon and maybe getting
an XPS 13 but it's 20 the XPS 13 I'd want to be $2,200 right $1,400 and it's a better
performance and multi-day battery life and a platform that's only getting faster and
has a lot of interesting features and excitement and it's hard to justify that $2,200 even
if I could sell the the X1 Carbon for $1,200 well your justification would be like Linux
is a must-have right yeah you can't hot platforms like I do all the time really I guess you
can obviously but you wouldn't make a lot of sense for other reasons yeah but I worry
a little bit because like the reason they limit to 16 gigs of RAM is because the Apple
Silicon cannot handle more than that I hope this isn't like and it seems silly that it
even could be but like some sort of weird technical limitation they haven't been able
to overcome because that although I take it back because this machine has never felt slow
the MacBook Air for me yeah so what do I care if it has 16 gigs of RAM or 24 or 32 right
right maybe if more things start using virtualization if you know having to use virtualization for
more tasks because because it is ARM and not x86 maybe that starts to become a thing but
so far that doesn't seem to be the case huh yeah huh well I'm gonna I I like following
along I tell you what I don't know if I'm gonna I was the other when I after because
after the show I kept messing around with that XPS 13 and I loaded more things on there
and I just like oh my gosh this is I think I like a lot better than the ThinkPad I like
the ThinkPad keyboard and I like the weight of the ThinkPad X1 better but the XPS 13 that
11th gen CPU and that screen and that build quality whoof it's just hard to beat that
even as even at an i5 it's just a great config so I legitimately I've just I hate that I'm
always in this zone I'm it's like I can never just get the right setup I think for me the
perfect maybe the perfect world is some sort of remote desktop solution I don't I don't
know I feel like I'm perpetually spinning between machines but the last thing I probably
should do is introduce an M1 in there but sometimes it feels a little tempting I mean
it will be the last machine you introduce I can guarantee that and then the next thing
you know I'd be putting an M1 at my desk and it's just welcome to the M1 action show and
I'm on the other I'm using Mac mini colo Marco warmants coming on yes I don't think so no
I do want to mention we have a new coderly out so if you would like to grab that just
go to coder qa.co and become a member or if you already are a member it's in the RSS feed
or it's also available as a dedicated download in your members area we do these every quarter
and they're a special thank you to our members for helping keep the show on the road and
you also get a limited ad feed when you become a coder qa member and that's a coder qa.co
go follow Mike on Twitter he's at Dumanuco his company is at the mad botter Inc I'm at
Chris last in the podcast network is that Jupiter signal and the show is that coda radio
show is there anything else you want to mention mr. Donald before we scoot I know everybody
should get an M1 MacBook Air you get in a cut you gotta work you gotta work that out
email Tim you know he lowered my App Store Commission ha ha there you go also links to
some of the stuff we talked about today is a coder dot show slash 396 you also find our
contact form there which is a big part of our show or you can email us directly coder
at Jupiter broadcasting comm also you can join our happy hour we do this show Monday
at 5 p.m. Pacific's 8 p.m. Eastern and then kicks off a little bit of that and we have
a good time you can join us over at jblive.tv thanks for joining us see you next week.