This is KOTORadio, episode 426 for August 9th, 2021.
Hello friends and welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and the business of software development and the world of technology.
This episode is brought to you by Cloud Guru.
You know, Cloud Guru has got that cloud playground, Azure, AWS, and Google Cloud Sandboxes on
ACG's credit card.
Not yours.
Get certified, get hired, get learning at a CloudGuru.com.
My name is Chris and joining us, ready to podcast like the pro he is, with tea in hand,
it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello Mike.
Happy tea time, Chris, although it's way too early.
Happy tea time.
It's kind of.
It's our unofficial KOTOR tea time, one o'clock.
Oh, what a mess, dude.
It's such a mess because we just got the new, the new show time and then I hit the road.
So now it's a, it's a totally different time for me because I'm in mountain time.
It's a totally different time for you.
You're in Eastern time.
The whole thing I thought was going to come crashing down because I thought we turned
into a bus of super spreaders about five days ago, four days ago.
I thought the whole crew was going to come down with the Rona.
Oh crap.
So we're getting, we're getting into Idaho and my son comes down with a fever and it's
not looking good.
He's down for the count and we're thinking, what else could this be?
And if he's got it, then maybe other other people in on board have it.
Like we're going to have to cancel the meetup and we start strategizing.
We get to, we get to Idaho and we start thinking, well, maybe we turn around and or maybe we
wait here and we isolate and see if we're sick and cancel the first meetup in Salt Lake
city.
You know, we're trying to strategize the entire thing because like now we've got Corona on
board, right?
And a couple of days go by and uh, we haven't seen anybody.
We're not sure like what to do.
So we just kind of had, oh, there was a windstorm too, so we had to stay put anyways.
So that worked out and we wake up the next morning and my son's feeling different.
Like if the fever has broken, he's, he's not really feeling so exhausted anymore, but he's
got this big lump on his face.
I'm looking at this lump and I'm going, wait a minute here.
And we start replaying like history, you know, you start going back through your brain archive
and I realized like four or five days ago, whenever we left, he chipped his tooth on a,
on a sucker on a hard candy and I bet he cracked it and got an infection.
So we took him into urgent care and sure enough, it was an infected tooth that had caused the
fever and him not feeling well and we got him on some antibiotics and he's just doing
great now, but it wasn't, it wasn't the Rona at all, but I had a total COVID panic because
I thought, what if, you know, what if we go to the meetup and we've got COVID or something
because we're trying to be careful, obviously we're all taking extra precautions and we
thought, you know, something had gotten us either anyways, but it turned out just to
be a cracked tooth and he's on the mend.
That's been my week, not to mention driving and working.
And you remain in Florida.
So I remain in the sunshine state.
Well, Mr. Dominic, with all that aside, what do you say, should we get in some feedback?
Let's hear what the screaming gnome users have to say.
Oh, too soon.
Actually, I think we, I think we made it clear this week, David writes in and he really just,
he has the key to using Linux, he says is boring old hardware.
He says, Linux hardware is a lot better years after it's come out.
It seems a vendor sell Linux with some initial options, but in my experience, the support
doesn't tend to be that great.
It isn't refined yet.
It seems much better to install something like an LTS Ubuntu or some other reliable
distro on hardware that's frankly had some time to simmer.
I haven't purchased Linux as an option from a vendor since I prefer to install Linux on
my own.
More recently, I purchased a brand new T-series ThinkPad.
At release, Kubuntu's install was broken and Mate just wasn't stable.
I switched things up and let things sit for a while and after revisiting it a little while
later, I was pleasantly surprised how refined it was.
The deciding factor of Linux desktop quality seems to be the open source projects familiarity
with the hardware.
The oldest popular machines always enjoy the best support, while the latest models typically
have bugs, bad defaults, and or drivers that just don't work well.
I know Mike doesn't like to touch his workstations and just wants to order a product from the
manufacturer, but with the way support actually happens on Linux, it seems like he'd be better
served reinstalling his own OS from the downloaded ISO after the hardware has gotten a bit older.
This has always been the mainstream way desktop Linux is deployed and it's a first class citizen
there.
And while regulations from the vendor is new and not nearly as popular, at least today
it seems you get a second class experience when it comes to Linux hardware support.
But the older devices work great, love the show, keep it up, David.
So he's saying stop buying new hardware and buy a used machine and put Linux on it.
But I love new hardware.
I know I thought that too.
It's like, well, that sounds kind of boring, right?
Yeah.
Plus, like, I mean, you got a job to do, you want something fast and powerful, right?
Yes.
And with no fan.
That hurts right now because my laptop is working hard and you know it.
You know it.
Hey, so I went to the Salt Lake City meetup and it went great.
And guess what?
A lot of Koda Radio love there.
Several people mentioned it was their favorite podcast.
There was some serious Salt Lake City love and so everybody says hi and they missed you.
And I think there were more iPhones and Mac users there than Linux and Android devices.
Yeah, I think JB is really a Mac network now, just saying.
But that meetup, there was a lot there.
It was a good mix, though.
We had some engineers, we had some security analysts, but it was pretty cool.
It was a great chance to just reconnect with folks and hear what they like about the shows,
how they found the shows, all that kind of stuff.
And Koda Radio was well-repped.
The next meetup is going to be in Denver on August 20th.
That's all linked up at meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
It's going to be a big event there.
So go check out the meetup page and see if you can make it.
It's going to be like a big deal.
It's going to be fun.
We're going to have giveaways, Raspberry Pi's, swag.
It's going to be huge.
Linode's going to have people there that are like spoiling everybody.
So meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
Linode.com slash Koder.
Go there to get $100 and 60 day credit on a new account.
And of course, you support the show.
I host all of my servers on Linode and I think you'd like them to Linode is independently
owned and they've been redefining how great cloud computing can be for 18 years.
You'll learn a few things in that time.
This road trip I'm on right now to reunite with the audience and with the JB team.
It's being powered by Linode in every sense of the word and my business runs on Linode.
That's how much I trust them and that's why I can recommend them.
They have 11 data centers around the world, award winning customer support and a dashboard
to manage everything that sets the bar in the industry.
But let's be real, I also love them because they're fast.
I mean, that matters.
Performance is a big factor in my choice here and their servers, their network connections,
even just deploying a server, creating a snapshot, upgrading the memory in one of my boxes.
It all happens really fast and with clear status and feedback as to what is happening
while you're doing the action so you know exactly what's going on.
Recently we deployed our live tracker so you can see the progress of our road trip at colonytracker.live.
And yeah, all of that runs on top of Linode.
It was straightforward to set it up and start using and they loved it.
In fact, Linode got so on board.
They helped make some artwork for the page and all of it.
So go check out colonytracker.live if you haven't seen that yet.
That website is running on Linode and then that embedded map is running on own tracks,
which we have running on a Linode all on open source software.
How great is that?
Anytime we're deploying something for ourselves and production behind the scenes that the
audience never sees or stuff that is going to be facing to the audience, we always deploy
that on Linode.
Now we have for over two years now and it's really the best choice out there when you
combine the support, the performance, the dashboard, the data center locations, the
fact that they're independently owned and not getting jerked around by different VC
funding.
It's really nice to know my business is with somebody who's been around for 18 years and
knows what they're doing.
I could go on and on about Linode and why I think it's so fantastic and why I think
it's so great.
But the thing that they've done to make it easier for our audience to try it out for
yourselves and just get some experience is they've created that $100 credit.
So you can go to linode.com slash coder.
You get $100 in credit on a new account for 60 days and you can go experiment with stuff.
Go see why we use them, why we choose them over and over again for yourselves.
Plus it's an opportunity to learn something, an opportunity to test something and an opportunity
to support independent content like the Coder radio program.
How great is that?
It's a check in the box all the way down kind of thing.
So go to linode.com slash coder, get $100 support the show and kick the tires.
It's linode.com slash coder.
The internet is freaking out this week because Apple has announced it plans to scan images
in children's iMessage and in iCloud.
Kind of two separate functions, but they were announced at the same time.
And everybody says this is an era of censorship and monitoring that Apple is just rolling
out.
So it seems the slippery slope argument here is once you build a technology that can identify
types of images, it doesn't take long until governments come knocking on your door like
China or Russia and say, add these hashes to your mix.
Well, we were briefly talking about this in our Slack and what was my first reaction?
Wait till Beijing gets their little paws on this one, right?
Like this is, remember the old DRM arguments from the nineties, Chris, let's take the time
machine.
Sure.
It seems so reasonable, right?
Like these small indie developers were making their little games, their shareware, whatever,
productivity software, whatever, whatever have you.
And it just seems like a little bit of protection, right?
So like, let's get some keys.
Oh, but you know, you own the disc, man.
You got the disc, you got the game.
That's it.
You just need the product key.
And it activates once.
Well now we have, most things are basically always online.
In fact, I just got an Xbox series S, the little one, the digital only one.
And this slapped me in the face, literally the night I got it.
My router happened to decide to poop the bed and all the games I had spent all day downloading,
I wanted to try Assassin's Creed, whatever the current one is.
And sure enough, after like 30, 40 minutes, whatever it was with no internet connection,
bam, no, you're done.
My point being, you know, the intentions were good, right?
Right in the beginning, we'll have these product keys, you know, help developers.
The intentions are obviously good with this, right?
Child abuse is bad.
Should not be a thing.
Anything that can be done to stop it is good, but you have to understand that once you enable
this kind of surveillance functionality, have you ever heard of, I don't know, Prism, right?
Any of these Snowden S things where it was like, oh, we're just gonna stop terrorists
and now we're sort of listening in on everybody's phone calls.
Yeah, the way this is gonna work is there's an organization called CSAM that is essentially
set up to prevent child exploitation and they are generating a series of fingerprints and
hashes that Apple will subscribe to and then try to match and ID those.
And there's two different systems in place and one I don't really have actually much
problem with, and I think it's been completely misrepresented online, and that's the iMessage
functionality.
This has kind of been blown way out of proportion.
The iMessage scanning only happens on iCloud accounts and iPhone accounts that are part
of a family plan and 12 years of age.
Above 12 years of age and still part of a family plan, there is some functionality,
but it's different.
12 years of age and below, it's looking for those fingerprints in the iMessage pictures,
it could be SMS or iMessage, and then it sends a push notification to the parent.
It doesn't notify Apple when something is found.
And that actually seems like kind of a reasonable implementation because my kids have got iOS
devices, and I absolutely don't want them doing anything like that, and as long as I'm
notified and it doesn't report it to anybody, I think that's actually a pretty reasonable
system.
It's also opt-in.
It's not on by default.
If you're above 12 years old and you're part of a family plan, I don't know if maybe it's
like it drops the notification to the parents, but it still blocks the image or something.
I can't remember because I didn't look into that part of it.
Then there's the iCloud part where it's scanning it, and if you opt into iCloud photo library,
they're going to be looking for these fingerprints throughout your iCloud photo library.
If they find something that matches a fingerprint, it notifies a person, like somebody in the
department at Apple who then has to review a low-resolution image to verify if it's child
porn or not and then alert the authorities after that.
And I guess there's even like a threshold because there could be some possible false
IDs, so it's like if you get triggered a few times, like nothing happens.
It takes several triggerings of this algorithm before it actually alerts somebody.
And I think if you look at what Apple has planned here, it's totally fine, really.
That implementation is pretty reasonable.
It is 100% the slippery slope argument.
And I think the more... I can kind of believe Apple if they say that we are going to refuse
government demands to expand the photo scanning beyond the CSAM.
We will refuse that, they've said that a couple of times.
I could believe that if one of these two scenarios is true.
If this is Apple's Hail Mary move to prevent having to build in back doors to all of their
software for law enforcement, if they can say, look, your argument that you need encryption
back doors into everything we do to save the children is null and void now because we've
built this technology.
And we're going to scan these images just like Facebook does in Facebook Messenger.
And we're going to participate in that same program.
So now you don't need a back door key.
If that's why they're doing this, I can kind of believe them that they won't have scope
creep.
But perhaps another alternative reason they could be doing this is because some sort of
optimistic woke culture has told them they can save the children in the world by doing
this and it is with full unbridled optimism and cooperation with CSAM that they're going
to save the children.
And if they actually think that's the reason they're doing this, if there isn't some devious
other motivation that they're not talking about being like, we want to prevent the FBI
from getting back doors.
If it's instead this unbridled optimism that they're presenting publicly, then it's totally
going to get fucked with.
No doubt about it.
It's totally going to get screwed with.
If it's the first one and they're trying to do a ninja move to prevent back doors, I'm
on board.
But we will never know.
We'll never know.
And so you just wish it never had come up.
You just wish they'd never opened this Pandora's box and they're not going to be able to put
this away.
I guess I don't understand how you think that little judo move would work because every
time, you know, let's say since, I don't know, the early aughts, right, we've had an encroachment
on privacy by any government, it's always been, okay, we're going to do this, but nothing
more.
Right?
Remember kids, it's just metadata.
Well, it turns out not so much.
All right.
I'm just.
I agree.
I think that's most likely what's going to happen.
I think if you look at the history of Apple and their battle over the San Bernardino iPhone,
the little pivot they had to do back in 2008 around encrypting backups because the FBI asked
them not to have a link about that in the show notes, they've been very strategic in
how they're dealing with law enforcement and the access they get.
And that encroachment on privacy is often done at the rally call of save the children.
And the director of the FBI, the last couple of directors of the FBI have been tested,
have been testifying saying, we have to get access to encrypted chat to save the children.
We have to save the children or else pornography will spread through encrypted chat.
And if that is the lever that they are trying to use to open Apple's back door, this could
be their cover up for their ass and well, you don't need that now because we've we've
solved that problem for you using technology and algorithms.
So don't worry about it.
The algorithm is on it now.
And they'll tell the FBI to, you know, sod off now because they've got this built in
and that they're now they're their reason for needing backdoor encryption is null and
void.
Oh, I wouldn't.
The FBI in this case or whatever law enforcement entity just say, OK, let me wait a year until
there's some weird exception that Apple screwed up on.
And then I'm going to go, you know, on Fox News, CNN, MSNBC and be, you know, banging
the drum again.
I mean, I know that's and also they're going to yell terrorism.
They have to stop, you know, to stop the terrorism.
It's interesting that Apple has kept this very focused on law enforcement when the more
interesting question is like intelligence services, which I understand some countries,
well, probably this one, too, is a little bit of a thin line, right?
Because they're saying what someone who intends to take you and put you on trial can do.
What about someone who has no intention of ever putting you on trial?
Right.
It's just like literally, I don't know, spying on every phone call.
That could never happen, though, Mike.
We've never seen examples of that.
Come on, Mike.
You've read too many Tom Clancy novels.
What do you do?
Oh, no, I think you're right.
And I think Apple, I think Apple loses their privacy crown with this, because the way average
people will see this is, well, for Apple to do this, they have to be looking at my photos.
They're not going to understand the difference of like hashing things.
And they're losing that argument now.
Apple's privacy argument is now it's private, except for we're looking at it.
So you have your your judo theory.
I have my China's the biggest market in the world.
It's going to be the big smart in the world for certainly our lifetime.
Apple needs to probably appease Beijing.
I don't know if anybody listening follows the news, but Hong Kong protests, they just
got slapped down pretty, pretty hard using things like digital surveillance and just
a ton of tear gas.
So I can't see this not having wider implications other than CSAM, right?
I understand like that's the main thing, and that's the thing they're talking about.
But you know, if you can, if you can do images of child abuse, which again, no one should
condone that, right?
Like, go after those guys as hard as you can.
But, you know, you can go to jail for like, posting a Winnie the Pooh meme in China, because
like somebody said, the president of China looks like Winnie the Pooh.
Why wouldn't Winnie the Pooh be part of this in China?
Well, there goes Koder in China, they were screwed.
Now we're done in that market.
Yeah, I agree with you, man.
I think that's exactly what will happen.
The only kind of real world use case we have here is Apple does not make FaceTime available
in Saudi Arabia, because Saudi Arabia demands that all audio and video calls be unencrypted.
And so Apple just opted to make Fight FaceTime unavailable in Saudi Arabia, Saudi Arabia,
though.
I mean, it like, it's not China.
Yeah, right.
It's not the biggest market in the world.
Yeah.
Right.
And that really is and and you you see Apple and their drive for that stock price and that
drive for revenue.
There's just no way Tim Cook can say no to the Chinese market and keep his job.
Uncle Tim is chasing that dragon hard.
Yeah, I wonder I really it's really hard to know the motivation here.
And this is going to be one of those problems where if this begins to slide, because here's
the other thing is we're assuming that CSAM organization is untouchable, and that they
couldn't be corrupted and that images couldn't be or hashes couldn't be injected from that
side.
Right?
It's not only are we being asked to have faith that Apple won't have scope creep with this
feature set, but we're being asked to have faith in this CSAM organization who is organizing
all of this.
And then there's also the man, how do they say it's like the neck Mac, that's NC MEC
database, which is where a lot of this actually lives, these fingerprints actually live.
So there's actually two other organizations outside of Apple that are involved with all
of this.
And then we have to trust that the governments that Apple operates in won't be constantly
putting pressure on them.
So you have CSAM, which stands for child sexual abuse material, which is, you know, awful,
no doubt about it.
And then you have Nick Mac, NC MEC, the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children.
It's both of those organizations.
They are both founded and funded by the US government.
So it is possible that organizations that are founded and funded by the US government
could then be influenced by the White House and you could get a president, maybe it's
another president in a few years that gets in there, that puts pressure, political pressure
on this group to add new types of imagery that society now considers to be offensive
and dangerous.
And that goalpost is constantly shifting.
And so you could see just over time how something like this, even if Apple never, ever wavered
on their commitments, you could see how maybe the other groups might over time because things
change.
So this is my whole bottom line on all this security stuff.
Like you're saying, you could have a different guy in charge or gal in charge later.
It's not enough for these companies to say that they won't.
They have to be saying, and it has to be in fact true, that they can't.
Not that I won't do it because you can trust me, it's I cannot do it even if I wanted to.
Even if I woke up and had just like the burning desire out of the best of intentions, I literally
can't do it.
That's the only way you have any kind of digital privacy.
And there are serious downsides to that.
That's why there are legitimate cases where it would be a lot easier for law enforcement
and other entities to just have nothing be encrypted.
It will cost lives if everything's end to end encrypted.
But this is going to be problematic too.
And where I think this is going to go in five years is going to be weirdly some sort of
pseudo corporate slash government marriage surveillance state.
This is the tinfoil hat edition of Coder Radio.
You know, there's other cloud providers that are already doing this exact scanning right
now.
I mentioned Facebook and there are others.
That's why it kind of sucks that this has been not properly explained.
Like I think out of all of this, the most reasonable thing that Apple is doing is that
iMessage filtering that happens on device for children's accounts that just notifies
parents.
That's sensible.
I think a lot of people could get on board with that and it's pretty minimal impact.
It's the cloud based scanning that really sucks.
The people are conflating this and saying that it's anyone who uses iMessage, they're
saying it's on by default, that it's going to be checking everybody.
Like the coverage of this has really been unusually inaccurate and unusually bad.
And that sucks because this is such a nuanced issue here.
And there's really two or three things Apple is announcing at once that's all getting conflated
together.
And generally they're a lot better at messaging this kind of stuff.
They really kind of blew it.
And you wonder if they're going to have to go up on stage and try to spin this in the
most Apple way possible when they announce the next hardware or whatever.
You mean like with the Sarah McLachlan song?
Yeah.
And slow like slow fades of children that have been saved from like try from trafficking,
you know, just really hit those emotional buttons.
And then then Tim Cook comes up on stage with hands folded together and like the in like
that triangle shape that he does and shaking them up and down, you know, at Apple, we care.
You can see it now.
The thoughtful triangle.
Yes.
Oh, somebody title suggests that that is that is it.
Oh, man.
OK, well, I mean, all we can do is wait.
It's going to happen.
It's landing in iOS 15.
The stakes here are incredibly high.
Apple could blow this so bad.
And going back to that, the misreporting, I think the really unfortunate side effect
of that is Apple will lean on what people are misinformed.
They don't understand the nuances and Apple will be right about that.
And that will be their go to defense over and over and over again.
And you look at things like the Washington Post.
They just blew this story so, so bad.
Their opening paragraph is just complete and total crap, complete crap.
And it's it just gets worse from there.
And that's that's that's a damn shame, because this is a fundamental shift in privacy and
hyperbole isn't going to help us get to the pros and cons of this.
And ultimately, I don't think it's going to move the needle for anybody.
I don't think it's going to stop anybody from using iOS.
I don't think it's going to stop anybody from using iMessage or iCloud photo library.
I think the only thing this will ultimately do is take a little pressure off Apple to
build in backdoors, which is why I go back to that one possible explanation, because
if you look at the outcome of this is when Apple turns this sucker on, they're probably
going to find a bunch of kiddie porn in people's iPhone library.
And all of a sudden, they're going to have a whole group of people in their offices looking
at naked kids.
That's the reality of this change, which is in itself illegal.
But now they're going to point to this in antitrust hearings in encryption, backdoor
hearings, and they're going to say, look at Apple, we care, we're doing this.
And that, I think, is ultimately going to be the biggest result of this is there some
staff are going to look at more naked pictures of kids.
Some people are going to get in trouble, a couple of people, because let's be honest,
who's dumb enough to put that crap in my photo library to begin with.
And they're going to have now an argument to use to push back against the government
of various countries.
That's the net result of this.
Oh, oh, and of course, they lose part of their branding as the as a privacy first company
who designs things in a way that you can't be snooped on.
They've just losing that now.
And they're going to lose it anyway.
It was coming, wasn't it?
You could feel it coming with their push towards services.
I don't know, I in in some way, I feel like I'm tilting at windmills a little bit here,
because I don't know that we're ever going back.
But everything's a service now.
Everything's a subscription, which means that you need data on your users.
You know, even in the most innocent cases, it's built in now.
It's built in.
It's part of them.
These aren't really devices with software.
These are portals to an ecosystem of services.
And honestly, basically a lifestyle, right?
I think about I have home pods now.
Thanks a lot, Chris.
No, it would be so painful for me to extricate myself from the I life.
Because it's all tied together.
And how is it tied together?
All the services to have all the data on my account and my purchases and my preferences.
It realized like where I live when I moved to this house from a couple towns over.
And I did not have to tell iOS that they just figured it out.
When I was at the Salt Lake City meetup, it the conversation went like this, I'm always,
you know, asking and trying to get a feel and the conversation goes just like this.
It goes, I know I'm actually I'm on a Mac now.
And they always hang their head in shame.
Yeah, I got a Mac, you know, I mean, my servers are still all Linux, my servers, my servers
are all still Linux.
But
my servers to SUSE.
Well, that's actually Ubuntu.
Yeah.
Oh, man.
Ah, yes.
And and I think it's it in every conversation.
It's the stuff you and I touched on weeks ago in the show is, you know, the late 30s,
early 40s, to late 40s, for just about most of the people that were there, with a few
exceptions, kids, for a lot of them, and a full time job.
And they just felt like life got busy.
And I just kind of fell into this.
And it's just working for me.
And they I guess, you know, they feel like they've lost a bit of their geek cred.
And I, I feel like we should, we should try to push back against I don't feel like anybody
should feel ashamed of what tool they choose to do their job, you know, and I, I feel bad
that they felt a little shame admitting it to me.
But you know, I'm trying to be cool about it, because I understand.
If you've ever used SSH, compared to the general population of the world, you are a geek.
Don't worry.
Even if you've used it in something weird on Windows, like putty or whatever, right,
you're fine.
I love it.
Apologies to Windows users.
I think I may have said the wrong application name because I don't use Windows because you
know, obviously, that's not real.
DataDog.com slash Coderadio Try DataDog's products for free for 14 days by visiting
DataDog.com slash Coderadio.
For a limited time, if you start a free trial, and you create one dashboard, you'll get a
free DataDog t shirt.
We all love some swag.
So what is DataDog?
Well, picture it, imagine a system that allows you to analyze code level performance across
your entire environment and troubleshoot issues faster than ever with beautiful visuals.
That's DataDog, and DataDog has a continuous profile that automatically collects information
from your production servers, your applications, everything all the time, so you can analyze
that data quickly with minimal overhead.
Are you getting how valuable this could be?
Get a unified picture of your environment by correlating code performance metrics with
all of your other data from your stack in real time with beautiful dashboards.
I love it.
And with 450 integrations and more, you have tracing, log management, you plug right into
your enterprise applications you already have, and you combine that continuous profiler,
it brings everything, finally everything in one platform, and it enables you to pinpoint
the root cause of issues faster than ever.
That's DataDog.
So go try DataDog for free for 14 days.
Go to DataDog.com slash Coderadio.
Go get that free t shirt after you create a dashboard, you support the show, and you
start troubleshooting faster and communicating more efficiently.
That's it.
DataDog.com slash Coderadio, and a big thanks to DataDog for sponsoring the Coderadio program.
DataDog.com slash Coderadio.
So Zoom, your favorite video conferencing company in the world, has to pay out $85 million
for lying about end-to-end encryption and sending user data to Facebook and Google.
So this is like a claim that happened because essentially Zoom has like all this language
around we don't share your data, and the calls are end-to-end encrypted, and Zoom takes privacy
seriously and adequately protects users' personal information.
These are quotes from like their privacy policy and their EULA and stuff like that.
And then it turned out that because Zoom had implemented the Facebook SDK and Google's
Firebase SDK, they were sending everything off to Facebook and Google.
Quite a bit of data, it seems, even before the user had accepted the EULA and privacy
statement.
Oh, that's brutal.
So there is a real dev story here about maybe you want to check out what your dependencies
are actually doing.
You know, when you install a CocoaPod or whatever, a PIP package or RubyGem, you want to maybe
just check out what's going on there.
I wonder, like, do you think they even knew everybody that was just like sitting there
implementing that SDK?
Do you think?
I mean, they must have known, right?
They must have known that it was sending off analytics to both Facebook and Google.
Well, like did the developers who just like needed the Facebook SDK to hit whatever, you
know, Jira card they were working on know anything about what the legal department was
doing, right?
They had a KPI, right, a key performance indicator of integrating like Facebook and like once
you get Facebook integrated, we've reached one of our goals for our OKR.
Oh, man, that's exactly why.
And of course, you got to get Firebase in there, too, because you need all the data.
You can't just have Facebook stuff.
Oh, what is this, like a corporate conferencing tool?
But of course, the lawyers are going to get their cut.
You know, they're going to get their cut.
The lawyers, they're going to get 25 to 15 bucks per person.
They're basically it works out like the lawyers get millions of dollars, like up to 25 percent
of the 85 million.
That's what the lawyers will take.
And then they also have two hundred thousand dollars of expenses that get reimbursed on
top of that.
So the lawyers are really working this case and they're going to make out great and users
are going to get like maybe five, eight bucks if if you were a user during this time.
I just like that, you know, the sword that they fell on was importing the Facebook SDK.
I know that is hilarious.
The judge also ordered Google and Facebook to delete any of the data they collected.
But there's no enforcement mechanism there.
And does it matter if they've already sold ads based on that data?
Right.
If they've already used it to identify things about you.
And if they've used it to feed their their ever growing algorithmic engines, does it?
I mean, I'm sure they never want to delete data, but do they care that much at this point?
Right.
But at this point, the machine has probably learned.
So it's like, OK, the beast has consumed your data.
And I mean, if I was Facebook and I was and we see story after story about just how voraciously
data hungry they are and about how how far they're willing to go to get data, you know,
there's no way they're letting that that that kind of analytics come in from Zoom and they're
not doing something with it.
They're absolutely consuming it and taking action on that.
And same with Google, they'd be negligent not to.
So this whole thing feels so slap on the wrist.
Eighty five million bucks.
Sure, that sucks.
But I bet Zoom would pay that again in the heartbeat to have the kind of user growth
they did during the peak of the pandemic.
It was worth it.
It's a speeding ticket.
It is a speeding ticket.
It really, really is.
And we'll just keep all plugging away at using Zoom.
I have a hot tip for you, though.
If you use Zoom on Linux, use the flat pack version and then they can't monitor all the
processes on your PC and what active windows you're using, which is a creepy thing that
Zoom can report to those that are running the meeting if they have a pro Zoom account
or enterprise Zoom account or whatever.
They can get analytics on how long the window was active versus how long the meeting was.
And they can get analytics on all of the other processes running on your Mac or Windows machine.
So creepy and gross.
That's ridiculous.
Yeah.
And then there was just a story that one of the call centers that Apple works with, which
is like this large call center that handles a ton of companies, but because one of them
is Apple, it made a headline.
They're based out of, I think it was Chicago, I can't remember.
But they now have cameras on all the time policy while you're at work.
Even if you're working from home, your webcam must be on so that way they can watch what
you're doing and monitor for odd activity, I guess.
So it just gets weirder and weirder.
So is this our surveillance edition?
I mean, we've really got a theme.
I guess.
It's like there's a...
Corporate America is sliding.
Well, if you want to work from home, then we're going to up the monitoring.
And it's like they're freaking out.
We have to have butts in chairs.
And if we can't physically monitor butts in chairs, we'll virtually monitor butts in seats.
So you better get your employee monitoring set up.
No.
You're falling behind.
You need like a heads up display, maybe like a butt sensor so you know literally when butts
are in seats.
What if they have a standing desk?
Could you imagine?
Well, then you get a pressure pad.
Obviously.
Well, she's definitely working, but it appears she's doing jumping jacks, too.
I don't understand.
Maybe I could train the dog to stand on the pressure plate, you know.
I just want to take a moment and mention for all of you out there that are ready to get
certified and you're looking at the Linux Engineer Exam 201, our friends at a Cloud
Guru have a course for you.
This course has been designed to cover all of the objectives for the LPIC-2 201 exam.
We will have a link in the show notes or you can go to cloudguru.com.
It begins with capacity planning and includes utilities and concepts for measuring resource
usage, predicting future resource needs, all of the kind of thinking you're going to need
for the exam.
Once you've completed that course, you'll be prepared to sit and pass LPIC-2 201 exam.
So go try it out, see what you can learn and maybe even get certified.
It's all at a cloudguru.com and we'll have a link in the show notes.
Wow, this has been another depressing episode of Coder Radio.
Maybe next week we'll go back to the internet of the 90s.
That'd be fun.
We should do some nostalgia soon.
You know, we do have a new Coderly report posted for our Coder QA members.
And if you're not a Coder QA member yet and you want to support the show, keep us going,
keep us independent and you get access to the Coderly report every quarter.
There's a new Coderly.
So go grab that.
It's a bit germane to part of our topics today and that's at coderqa.co.
Mr. Dominic, is there anything you want to mention or plug or tell the people to go check
out before we get out of here?
Nope.
Just follow me at Timon Nugent on Twitter.
That's really easy.
You could also follow me.
I'm at Chris LAS, the podcast network.
Well, I'm glad you asked.
That's at Jupiter Signal and the show is at Coder Radio Show.
And that's handy for announcements and stuff.
You never know.
I guess things could be, you know, shifting or whatever while I'm on the road.
I think the next Coder Radio, I'm not positive, but I think the next one will either be in
Denver or just outside of the Denver area.
And then it is meet up time.
Awesome.
I know.
Pretty stoked.
I'm going to go to System 76, see if I can I spy how they build that launch keyboard.
Maybe walk out of there with a couple of Thaleos under my arms.
I'll never notice.
I'll bring my big jacket.
Links to what we talked about today.
They're over at coder.show slash four to six.
You also find our contact form over there.
We need your feedback.
It's a big part of the show.
Go send us your feedback.
And our RSS feed is there as well.
You can subscribe and you can send the show to somebody.
That's always real nice.
And then join us for Coder Radio live on Mondays at 10 a.m. Pacific, noon, Eastern.
Time math is hard right now.
I'm in the mountains, but I'd love to have you join us live at jblife.tv.
Thanks for being here.
We'll be right back here next week.