This is Coda Radio, episode 432 for September 20th, 2021.
Hello there and welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a pragmatic look
at the art and the business, the software development, and the world of technology.
This episode is brought to you by Accloud Guru, the leader in learning for cloud, Linux,
and other modern tech skills.
We have hundreds of certification courses and thousands of hands-on labs, free cloud
sandboxes where you can develop your own skills and more, all at AccloudGuru.com.
Right now, everyone can go learn, get in on it, AccloudGuru.com.
My name is Chris and joining us every single week, it's our host, Mr. Dominic.
Hello, Mike.
Hey, I'm happy to be on the Blaze.
Thank you so much, Chris.
Yeah.
This is our new exclusive right-wing streaming service where we unintentionally upset people.
Can we call it the no spin zone or is Papa Bear or Riley going to sue the shit out of
us?
Yeah, sure.
You know, he's still going.
Is he really?
You know, that old coot is still, he's got like, he talked some YouTuber into helping
him out with some setup and the production quality, like the lighting and the cameras
are not...
It's got to be bad.
They're not good.
Well, it's weird because like Glenn Beck faced the same problem, but he's like, yo,
I got my whole network.
Now I'm good.
I feel like Bill Wright is just like a little too old, I hate to say it, but...
It is wild how many different streaming platforms and services and et cetera are out there today.
Like, I was thinking about this last night as we were watching a Star Trek Lower Decks
with the kids.
Nice.
And you know, that's a CBS all access show.
Yeah, it is.
And we're sitting there watching it and we can just pull this up whenever we want it.
There's no commercials.
There's no like waiting around until Thursday night when it airs.
And then we, you know, or like when I was a kid, if I wanted to see a cartoon, I'd have
to watch it Saturday morning.
That was when I was going to watch cartoons.
Like they don't have to do any of that now.
I literally had this conversation with my son and he looked at me in a state of, I can
only describe it as confounded horror, that there was a time when one could not just simply
watch whatever, you know, insert your kid's favorite cartoon here, right?
Right.
At On Demand.
He's like, but Dad, Netflix.
I'm like, okay, there was no Netflix.
Brace yourself for this.
There was no YouTube either.
You know, like...
He is not allowed on YouTube.
But yes.
Good call.
But you know, it's a funny reaction.
Like when I stay in a hotel room with the kids and the TV comes on and we're watching
something and then it breaks for commercial and the kids are just like, what the hell
is this?
I've also had to have the conversation explaining the concept of a commercial.
Yeah.
Pretty funny.
But I enjoy it.
We love our sponsors.
That's true.
And I just started watching the Ted Lasso because everybody's been going on about the
Ted Lasso.
Oh, how is it?
I haven't seen it yet.
It's good.
Is it really?
So frustratingly good.
Yes.
I really don't want to pay for Apple TV Plus.
I know.
Because you know, it's getting out of hand.
And I don't need another damn show.
Yeah.
But like, I have to pay for Picard because the world hates me, which is I think, is that
the CBS one too?
Yeah.
I pay for Peacock because I must have been drunk and just paid for Peacock.
I wanted all of the law and order apparently.
I honestly don't know why I have Peacock when I have Hulu.
And I pay for like the super Cadillac Hulu because I like soccer.
And apparently if you're in the US, you need to pay more money to like soccer.
Oh, geez.
Then you'd really like the Ted Lasso show.
He's a soccer coach, right?
Isn't that the whole?
That's why I resisted it.
Because it was sports.
Yeah.
Yep.
Well, if you ever notice, I'm a little wild on Twitter on Saturdays talking about how
much Manchester United sucks because it's all about Chelsea.
I'll leave it there.
Sports ball.
Man, sports, huh?
It gets me so riled up.
I know.
Chris is like, let me tell you something.
Linux Mint is going to win the NHL Stanley Cup.
Man, I'd love to see that.
Then they're going to pitch a perfect game while dunking on Shaq.
Boom.
I'm just waiting for a NASCAR, a NASCAR car to come racing by with a Linux logo on there,
like a distro logo.
You know what?
I'm going to throw it down here.
System 76.
It's time to get into the NASCAR game.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
They seem like big NASCAR folks.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, they definitely do.
You want to know something adorable?
That's the last thing I'll say about my kids.
But you know, we took the kids with us on the Denver road trip to see everybody.
And we brought them to the meetup.
That was great.
And we had a listener, Mike, show up and really great guy, like, you know, the kind of listener,
like it's just it's so cool to meet people like listener Mike.
And he turned out to be a Cessna pilot.
And he also offered to take a bunch of us up for a couple of hours on a scenic tour
of Denver in his Cessna.
And I got to bring Dylan with me.
And you know, it was a great experience.
But I'm not kidding you if the bigger impression for Dylan might not have been when Carl from
system 76 took Dylan around in his Tesla.
Dylan's mind was blown by the Tesla and he got to turn on the fart whoopee cushion settings
and he got to see it in the rainbow road mode.
And I mean, Carl was such a sport.
He took he took both Dylan and Abby out for a spin in his Model 3.
And I think that was probably the highlight of Dylan's road trip.
That was awesome and also I did not know there was a rainbow road mode.
Yeah, just like, yeah, from like Mario Kart.
No, that's awesome.
Yeah.
So last week we set a small part of the Internet on fire unintentionally.
And you know, this is a tricky one for us because I know I blew it in one way and a
big way is I get really caught up in the practical aspect of the situation.
Like we were talking about fair pay and we were talking about that slack channel that
Apple shut down.
And I just sort of had this natural reaction of like, yeah, of course Apple did that.
Right.
And of course, Apple doesn't want you using a company slack channel to talk about pay.
I don't think I did a good job of articulating it from the worker standpoint.
So I know I can totally understand why people who are dealing with this issue right now
at their workplace would get super upset.
But I kind of feel like some people when they got so upset, missed an opportunity to hear
this from a business owner's standpoint, which is a valuable perspective, I think, for people
who are negotiating better pay to understand it, like when we talked about it last week,
I think we were very much thinking about it in the way an Apple executive would think
about it.
It's a business owner mentality versus a worker mentality.
And I think that is actually the core of the conflict.
Yeah, it's a hassle and you kind of don't want to deal with it.
Right.
Yeah.
For the business owner.
Right.
Yeah.
So let me just on this subject, some were constructive, others were less.
And this is what I'm saying.
Like, I think maybe an opportunity was missed here.
Like Chris B wrote that he fired a podcast to hear a usually interesting code of radio.
But what he heard instead was some bizarre far right extreme political triad sounding
like a radio broadcast from the dying days of the Weimar Republic.
Employees are actually fully purchased property of their own employer.
Anyone who doesn't want to work to the death of the industry is a traitor to the fatherland.
Seriously, off the rails, guys.
OK, so one, no one mentioned slavery.
Like I just like if some Chris, I'm sure you're sincere, but I obviously don't think slavery
is good.
Right.
No, I would not be surprised to hear that.
Nor am I a fan of fascist German governments.
So my point was like and actually there was another email that you didn't highlight in
the doc here that actually sort of changed my mind.
Right.
And I think I kind of pissed off the folks more.
It's funny because like what I preach is not what I practice, right?
People who work, you know, at TMB can talk about their salary.
It's kind of lame because we all have basically the same salary, but just do it by your experience.
So I do that because I don't want to be accused of like prejudice or whatever.
I realized like for years I've been talking about how folks I won't name names, but large
consulting companies that you have definitely heard of abuse the H1B system to the detriment
of the H1B recipients, right?
To lower wages on all people.
This is something we covered a lot back in the day on the show when it was happening.
Years ago when Disney, yeah.
And I realized that and someone sent me a nice message pointing out that there is an
internal kind of logical inconsistency in my arguments.
Basically like you and I have what, like, I mean, whatever less, I think we both have
less than like 10 employees, right?
Yeah.
So it's not like we're robber barons with like 400 people digging, you know, laying
railroad track.
We're closer to the worker side of life, particularly me, right?
Because I sell development services effectively.
Yeah, for sure.
I do think it's bad when people like when Apple and Adobe and Microsoft or I can't,
I don't know if it was Microsoft, but it would definitely Apple and Adobe have a secret agreement
to collude to lower wages, right?
I think it's bad when companies, I won't say the name, but you can Google it.
There was a story about this, hire H1B visas explicitly to make them work unpaid overtime.
And then basically knowing that if they don't do what they want, they'll fire them.
And that is effectively deporting them.
I think that's bad.
I think it's bad for the folks getting the visas.
It's bad for small companies like mine that have to compete for these consulting jobs,
but need to pay like reasonable wages.
It's bad for Americans, British, Indians, anybody trying to get these jobs.
If these large firms know that they, I mean, excuse the crude language, but they effectively
have these folks by the balls because if they lose their job, they get deported.
That was my point.
Not that we, like we should not allow immigration, that it's abusive.
Let's be honest too about what does getting deported mean?
It means losing out.
It destroys their life.
They ruin your entire life.
Everything you've built up.
Imagine you have, you know, your kids are in school here.
That's horrible.
Yeah.
My point is if we're going to have the H1B system, and I've been saying this for years,
you can go back to 2014, 2015.
The recipients of the H1B visas must have, and not just in writing, but like actual in
practice, the same protections as domestic workers.
And it just isn't the case, right?
I mean, you could Google it.
There's horror stories.
I mean, we'll name one name, right?
Because we covered it years ago when Disney just laid off all their IT people saying that
they were redundant.
And then a month later outsourced everything to H1Bs and to one of these large consulting
companies that isn't notorious for treating their folks like crap.
Another example is the verge has the H1B folks and the contracting folks, not all of them
are H1Bs, but that that company for the, they hire another consulting firm to do their moderation.
These people themselves are being mistreated.
My point is if you're going to have employees, you should treat them well, right?
That's basically it.
Yeah.
And I think that is an ongoing conversation that if you haven't heard the back catalog,
you know, they didn't have all of the context for your position in the last episode.
And again, I should have been more eloquent, right?
Well, I mean, neither of us were at our best because it was at a different show time.
I was in a hell state called Tucson.
Dude, you're going to get ripped apart by Tucson folks now.
I don't know what you're doing.
I hope.
Bring it.
They can bring it.
They live in a failed hell state.
And I'll say it right now.
All right.
Can someone suggest Tucson is a failed hellscape, please?
The rest of Arizona seemed great though.
Anyways, Drew, our editor, put it really well.
He said, you guys are wrong about this in the most Florida way possible.
Fair pay is a huge issue in the country right now.
It's less of an issue in Europe because they have actual laws to protect workers.
In contrast to this, the dystopian nightmare we call workers rights in air quotes, he says
with a wink and a nod, heavily implies that the right is that you can work, not that you
have rights while being a laborer.
He writes case in point, Colorado passed a law recently requiring companies to post a
real legitimate pay scale on job postings.
Some companies decided they would rather not have employees in Colorado rather than let
people know what others are paid.
Some tried to skirt around it by posting something like a dollar to one million.
And then, of course, they got smacked down with fines.
That's amazing.
I have a story about that I'll share in a second.
He finishes though with the employees at Apple should have known better than to have a chat
room within a company property.
Apple had every right to shut that down.
But when they start telling the employees that they can't have those conversations inside
or even outside the company, they're becoming thought police.
You don't pay these people while they're off the clock and off property.
Get the out of here trying to tell them what they can and can't talk about on their own
time.
Sincerely, your editor.
P.S.
Don't fire me.
No, you nailed it.
No.
Yeah.
I mean, so the pay scale thing is so I worked at a bank forever ago, lifetime ago, and every
position in the company in the H.R. book had a pay scale that was posted like, you know,
I.T. was probably thirty five to sixty thousand or so or maybe forty thousand to sixty thousand.
And you knew that if you had the I.T. position one, you would get something in that range
and you knew everyone else in that position was making that pay.
And that was true for many, many years until it wasn't when they wanted to promote me to
sort of incentivize me, but it was above what was public in the pay scale.
So the the one time they just paid me more and didn't say anything about it.
But then when it came time the next year to do something else again, they just created
a whole new position and decided that had a new pay scale and they just created it spontaneously
and said, well, now you're a server technician level three.
OK, where did one and two go?
And they just sort of invented new pay scales.
But I thought when the system was working properly, it was kind of nice to know that
if I wanted to jump over to, say, working in the branch side of the bank, these were
the salary ranges I could expect.
And if I shot for top tier, I could expect to make as much as this.
And that worked.
But that's something that company chose to implement.
And I wish we could utilize technology in a way to create something like Glassdoor,
but better and decentralized that also helps us discuss pay in a way that would actually
be appealing to Americans who are culturally awkward about this.
And it's a real hard spot for me.
This whole thing, and I think it affected the way I talked about it last week.
Honestly, at this point, it's a joke.
But let's say somehow I ended up making three hundred thousand dollars a year doing this
job, which I can't imagine how that would ever happen.
But let's just say like that would be my high end of what I could ever expect for success
is three hundred thousand.
It's not, you know, it's not in the grand scheme of things.
It's not a ton of money for media.
But I'd be I'd be over the moon to make that much money a year.
And if that ever went public, it would significantly damage my brand.
Back in the day when I worked in I.T. and I was making a good chunk of change because
I was charging one hundred and twenty an hour for my clients, and I also had podcast revenue
coming in from sponsors.
It became scandalous in the community when I bought an Oryx, like Chris, Chris just spent
three thousand dollars on a laptop.
He must be making so much money.
Well, I'm not going to listen anymore.
You know, like there is a big part of the Linux community that responds extremely negatively
to financial success.
And it's not all of them.
And I don't even think it's the majority, but in a weird way for me, if I were ever
public with how much money I make, because ultimately it's probably going to be more
than somebody in the audience, even if it's not very much, they it creates this brand
problem for me.
And it's the craziest thing.
And I think I don't think this is true, like in other communities, you know, you have YouTubers
who kind of flaunt giving away money.
You got you got like ATP, the accidental tech podcast where they literally brag about the
thousands of dollars they spend on monitors and stands and they each make over five grand
a month per episode, apparently.
Right.
Like they've mentioned it on the air.
Probably more since that membership of theirs, because they have a ton of members.
Like it's it's like, you know, our members are like essential to keeping the show on
there.
Their members are helping them buy Apple Watches.
It's a whole other scale of money they're making and Tesla's right.
And actually, all kinds of crazy stuff.
I mean, if you listen to the show, it's clear that money isn't a problem.
And they also have other alternative revenue.
I mean, they're making good money and it's not considered a bad thing.
And I think it's because the Apple community, you know, it's sort of a high, high spend
bar to even get in.
And so it's just normal.
But in in the audience that I serve, there is a portion that would be very it would be
very upset to hear he makes 300,000, which, by the way, I got to be clear, I make nowhere
near that.
Not even close.
But it would even though for me, it would be like the success of my career of this particular
trajectory to make that much, you'd be like, it'd be like a life goal for me to achieve
that.
And I, you know, I would imagine life would be great.
For a good portion of the audience, they would be angered.
And I think they'd probably tune out.
And so when I think about wage transparency and talking about how much I make, it's a
scary topic for me, because it has so many negative, negative ramifications for me.
So I that also influences how I think about this.
Because not only do I own a business, and not only have I done a lot of hiring, where
depending on when I hire somebody, and what's going on in the market, and what the needs
of the business are, if they come in at the right time with the right ask, they're going
to make more than somebody that came in a couple of years ago when the market dynamics
weren't the same.
And it's an unfortunate reality, and I've seen it play out in multiple companies.
But it's like, there's a lot of things that influence how much a business is willing to
pay for somebody at what time.
And every now and then, like, you're the right person with the right skill set, with the
right ask, and the business says yes.
And it doesn't necessarily mean they're a better coder than somebody else already on
staff or a better tech or a better podcast or whatever it is.
But it means that they bought at the right time, essentially, you know.
And that also can, when employees find out about that disparity, it can create a lot
of issues inside the team.
I don't necessarily know what the answer is there.
And I do feel like workers should have access to as many tools as possible to negotiate
with these large, especially these monstrously large companies.
Because the employers and the businesses have all the tools in the world, from all kinds
of tactics to literal tools to personnel to lawyers, they have all the tools in the world.
So I do think workers need access to more information and more resources, but I just
don't know what the answer is.
And I think it's a more complicated problem than we really give credit for.
Yeah, I think it gets messy too, the smaller, like it's very easy to say that like Apple
should not quote, interfere with organizing or whatever.
But you know, if you have a company of like five people, and everybody's making roughly
the same amount of money, and the company, like all small companies, is always on the
edge of life and death.
There's just not like enough fat there to have this massive drain of like constantly
fighting with the employer.
I don't know.
I mean, one, I don't know about other places.
I know in Florida, if you're small enough, a lot of these things don't really apply.
But I feel like there's just a fundamental difference between the huge tech companies
and like, JB and TMB, right?
It just seems oh, yeah, like you and I are not making 300 times more than our employees,
right?
It just.
And you know, think about it in terms of employee disparity.
I thought about this when we were getting those emails, and we you know, we didn't talk
about with Apple is imagine being an employee there, right?
Maybe you're like responsible for some subsystem and iOS or some component of the desktop or
whatever.
You now work for a company that's willing to pay like 30 million dollars to do Ted Lasso
and pay those to pay the staff of the Apple TV arm.
Millions of dollars in payroll, millions, right?
Like the difference now between what a developer makes and what Jennifer Aniston makes, who
are both now employees for Apple, is gross.
And that is a whole new level of disparity.
And I don't I know it's different markets and all that, but like at the end of the day,
if you're an employee at Apple, that's a reality for you now.
And that doesn't sit well with me.
Like I'm thinking about it, like in my exact case, the difference between me and my current
lowest paid like employee, like full time employee is, I think, like four or five dollars
an hour.
It's a lot narrower in our in our area.
Yeah, I don't know.
I think it's kind of crazy.
lino.com slash coder go there to get one hundred dollars and 60 day credit on a new account
and you go there to support the show.
Of course, Linode started in 2003 is one of the very first companies in cloud computing.
I got hip to them about two years ago.
And what I realized is for 18 years, they have been focused on being the best in this
area.
They haven't been led astray and done a million different little strange things.
Instead, they have focused on making cloud computing accessible, simple and affordable
to all.
And if you are starting a project, Linode is a fantastic way to go.
And they have systems in place that help take care of your box, like with snapshots and
backups if you ever need them.
And they make it really easy to get started.
I frequently deploy a Debian box with Docker preinstalled.
But for example, you could just one click deploy next cloud or maybe Jitsi if you want
to replace Zoom.
They have a lot of just hit a button, deploy the app and get started type stuff.
But they also make it really simple for you to go the DIY route if that's what you prefer.
That's why that one hundred dollar credit is so great.
Plus, you get access to their S3 compatible object storage, cloud firewalls, VLAN support,
a powerful DNS manager and really great 24-7 customer support.
Linode is always making an investment in their infrastructure.
Their high end CPU boxes have AMD epic processors.
They have super fast SSDs.
They are their own ISP.
So their network connection is fantastic.
And they have 11 data centers around the world.
I mean, it really just doesn't get any better than that.
While I was on our Jupiter Colony reunion road trip, it was Linode that kept the lights
on here.
My on-premises server went down and I ended up having to shift all of my workload to the
Linode instances that I had set up before the trip.
And that kind of stuff is so great too because you can use Linode as part of like a multi
cloud strategy.
Maybe you have multiple cloud providers.
You want to spread out some risk.
Maybe you have on-premises and you want to augment that with a cloud option like I did.
Linode is super flexible in that way and you can run your entire infrastructure up there
because their pricing is 30 to 50 percent cheaper than the major duopoly cloud providers
out there.
So go get started and get a hundred dollar 60 day credit by going to linode.com slash
coder.
You get that one hundred dollars and you support the CoderRadio program and make it possible
for us to keep going.
That's linode.com slash coder.
Apple today, as we record, so probably two days as you're listening to this, has released
iOS 15 and iPad OS 15 along with the watch stuff and I assume the Apple TV stuff.
I wanted to note it since it's happening today on the show and there is actually one real
significant feature in here that I think is decent.
But you have any off the top of your head thoughts about the iOS 15 release?
None.
I'm actually curious what the feature you think is important is.
Well you know what I'll say this.
I've been using the beta the entire summer on the iPad.
Really?
Mm-hmm.
Way better on the iPad.
They just did one thing and it was really simple is they just made the multitasking discoverable.
They put little tabs in stuff and gave you clues of how to use it.
It's relatively the same but it's so so much better now.
There's a feature in there that I haven't played a lot with because I've really been
waiting for it to land on the phone.
And I think it's a great example of A, the kind of area where Apple was really really
behind for essentially all of iOS and then just sort of leapfrogs with a feature set
that it looks really really competitive.
And then the other thing about it, so B, is it sort of really checks that sync across
all your boxes and I cloudify this for everything in the ecosystem the way only Apple really
does these days.
So I'm talking about here is the focus feature.
So at a high level the idea behind the focus feature is it's like do not disturb but way
more turned up to 11.
So when you want to focus on a particular task like say maybe you're recording a podcast
or you're flying a damn drone or you're trying to sleep or read a book or play a game on
your device.
You can enable that particular focus to silence notifications from specific apps or people.
You can also at the same time trigger automations and shortcuts and rearrange your home screen
for that particular focus.
So it's do not disturb on steroids where it touches all this other stuff.
And then you can sync those different focuses so like I'll have one for podcasting, I'll
have one for driving.
You can sync these different focuses across all your devices.
Everything that's either on the latest version of the latest Apple OS.
But for me the biggest thing is as you're using it you can start to add people or notifications
to the focus mode or remove them.
It gives you a surprising amount of customizations where I could say allow notifications from
Mike and Wes but nobody else and it will actually recognize you assuming that the developers
are using the new APIs.
It'll recognize you across chat services so iMessage, Slack, Telegram, WhatsApp.
If it's using the new API it'll know it's you regardless of the chat application they're
using.
So I can just put you in there as a contact and that means any app you want to use you
can break through and I can specifically allow or deny apps.
So I can say in the case of like when I'm flying the drone this has actually been, this
has been a really frustrating problem is because the universe hates me just like when I'm podcasting
when I put my drone up in the air that's when I start getting all the push notifications
you know motion notifications, Slack notifications, everything.
And the horrible thing about iOS is you can be in do not disturb mode but if you allow
banner notifications and you have your screen on you will get those notifications and if
you have an iPhone mini and you're flying a drone those banner notifications cover up
a significant part of the screen you're using to fly the thing.
So I can literally be in mid-flight and not able to see where I'm flying because of these
damn notifications or I can be recording a podcast and they break through.
So with these focus modes I choose the task that I'm doing and I will have only certain
allowed applications through and I will have custom home screens so I don't even have to
see the badges of the other apps.
And then they're going to do some things we'll see how it works like some contextual suggestions
based on you know things that it's observed which they seem to get right about 30% of
the time but the 30% they get right is pretty clever and in terms of iMessage which is what
my family uses for better or for worse it'll let them know I'm in a focus mode and not
seeing their notifications and then there's also some way for them to say this is urgent
break through the focus mode and let him know I need him to see this notification sort of
like slack can do and I think that is going to be a feature that genuinely changes how
I use my devices and how I'm interrupted which is a rough interruptions are rough for me
and it also is one of those stupid it's a small stupid little thing but it makes me
go huh you know if I had a M1X Mac with Monterey it would get silenced when I silence my phone
or my watch like they all the iPad the Mac the theoretical Mac that doesn't exist they
all would get it and that is extremely appealing to me it's a small stupid thing but yet huge
for me personally.
Really I didn't sell you I thought that was a pretty good explanation.
No because I because I can already hear the complaints like you monster well I can already
hear like the family tech support I'm gonna have to do when someone mistakenly puts some
app on a block thinking you know like oh come on you know this Chris you get all kinds of
crazy calls from relatives right like yeah you're the tech guy in the family like I've
seen all right my love you and also I understand you love collective bargaining and I'm very
sorry but like the woman can destroy an Apple TV in ways that I didn't know were possible
really an Apple that does seem like the impossible.
So like giving more settings to my relatives it's just there's a reason I make them pile
life it was to avoid this.
Yeah like you know what I want them to do nothing.
I don't even again sorry ma but like she discovered how to turn her phone off.
She's a very smart person but she thought off was silent.
This is years ago when like smartphones were new and that was just a problem right now
granted we're talking the iPhone.
Oh God what was the first one of horizon was it the four or the three G.S.
It must have been the I want to say four but I don't know I felt like it took forever for
Verizon to get it.
Yeah well there was a setting you could like change what the button did from like off to
silent or something sleep silent.
Yeah OK it was sleep to silent you could change it and she changed it and she just kept turning
her phone on silent and then being mad that her phone wouldn't ring and like my opinion
is that setting should not exist.
Right.
I'm just like no.
So I don't love that what you just described it took you at least two and a half minutes
to describe on a technical podcast.
Yeah OK.
All right.
OK.
You're right.
It does seem a little complicated.
Yeah it does.
But it's like it is the new do not disturb and I think they've just taken do not disturb
and they've made it a focus now.
I think it's way better than it was the notification system seems uniquely improved in fact it's
got other things in there too now like silently collecting notifications and just tucking
them away in a tray until you want them instead of like blasting them in your face a lot of
things like that that I think are a nice step up but you're right it is complicated.
You know they're not doing a lot this year.
I think Apple is paying the covid tax this year because let's be honest the iPhone event
was kind of a snoozer.
It was a dud.
Yeah but they're not doing a lot but they're doing more than their nearest peer competitors
for sure.
Unless you care about folding phones and I just want to say at the rate I destroy hardware
can you imagine a folding phone.
Would I even get it out of the box if I could do it right.
I wouldn't.
I kind of liked the clamshell phones but I don't think I want something that thick in
my pocket.
I'm talking the tools you know the same way.
What do they call the Samsung.
Yeah the fact the things that unfold into a tablet basically.
Yeah I can't remember the name but someone will will have it in the comments.
What are your thoughts though on on on the 13.
Did you order one.
Did I ask you last week.
No but you and I are iPad mini brothers apparently.
No I don't have one.
I thought you ordered one.
No I got a 13 Max Pro.
Really.
Yeah I do like the mini.
I think that's a good iPad but no I don't have one.
I had the I what you're thinking of is I had the iPhone mini with the iPhone mini.
That's what it was.
OK.
Yeah and it's been a disaster for me.
It's just been a dumpster.
So I like to read.
In fact we're going to have a review of it if I ever finish it like you know Manning
presses like technical books.
Oh yeah.
And I find that on the regular Kindle they're kind of garbage because you know you don't
get the syntax outlining or whatever.
I cannot express how painful dropping an iPad pro on my face is with the keyboard attached.
Oh yeah.
When you're sitting there reading in bed and yeah you start falling asleep and you just
like knock your own ass out.
So the mini and also my son has discovered cut the rope.
He's a little late.
Stop being mean to the five year old and fruit ninja.
So he is enjoying the best of 2014 mobile games.
Hey you know what you have to do next is get him on Angry Birds.
I mean you know what the classics are the classics.
How much money those those rovio guys made on Angry Birds.
Seriously it's not anymore dude.
You know it's it they got a version in the arcade now and it's all just like you know
all built in.
No no in-app purchases or anything.
Yeah that's that's it's a while.
They're all going for that subscription revenue now.
Hey get down to 15 percent Apple tax after a year.
Yeah so we'll see.
Yeah I got that.
I've got the big one.
It's problem problem.
I'm also I also think live text is a decent feature where you can select the text in photos
in like a screenshot or in Safari or I've actually already used that a couple of times
on the iPad.
So we'll see.
Anyways I just wanted to note that it's here and we're aware of it and I think focus was
probably the only thing that's really going to change my productivity with these devices
and I think it is a nice little note of of system wide setting sinking that Apple could
do.
They could do a lot more of that if you think about it there's a lot more things they could
sink across all these devices and if they got it right and didn't screw it up.
That's pretty compelling feature set for me.
I just want to remind all I was developers of the cloud API you know and sinking and
if they got it right OK Datadog.com slash Coder radio go there and see why Datadog is
the top monitoring platform and Datadog is the monitoring and security platform for developers
security professionals and ops teams in the cloud age.
You can unify your metrics your traces and your logs all in one place and you troubleshoot
issues faster and break down silos between teams and communicate better than ever.
Datadog lets you create real time dashboards for over 450 integrations in minutes and you
can easily pivot from like a high level overview of your entire environment to just a granular
visualization of metrics and events.
You see Datadog offers infrastructure monitoring security monitoring real time user monitoring
application performance monitoring and more all in one place with beautiful dashboards
that you just got to go see for yourself.
That's why I recommend you get started today with a free trial at Datadog.com slash Coder
radio.
You can see why thousands of companies trust Datadog with their monitoring solution and
so many Coder radio listeners are now using Datadog to go to Datadog.com slash Coder radio
start a free trial and if you create one dashboard Datadog is going to send you a free T-shirt
to free swag to try out Datadog and see their beautiful dashboards and unify your entire
platform and communicate between teams.
It's a great tool and you got to check it out Datadog.com slash Coder radio.
Let me tell you about an experimental operating system that Microsoft has developed.
It's called Singularity and it's designed to eliminate some of the shortcomings of existing
operating systems such as the general security vulnerabilities failures and crashes due to
drivers extensions add ons and of course crashes due to unexpected interaction between apps
and an overall lack of performance and robustness.
So they are aiming big here.
Their strategy is to utilize a safe programming language no more of C's shenanigans as Microsoft
says they will use verification tools impose constraints that will make verification easier
and they have a new architecture and design that they think is tops.
Do I have your attention are you impressed?
No of course not.
Yes I should know better.
It's a very fascinating theoretical study that they did.
There's just one little catch.
The last release was in November of 2008 just an old it was an experiment about 18 years
ago they thought would make for a better platform for the long run kind of like Google's fuchsia
today that's the first thing I thought of when I saw this is this makes me think of
what Google is doing right now with fuchsia.
Okay I mean first of all what does it say for programming language are they just saying
they're doing rust because you know that's great for the hashtags on Twitter.
Well there was no rust 18 years ago was there.
So it's C sharp.
It's Longhorn 2.0.
Yeah maybe they actually do have it up on GitHub now so one could go sniff around.
I wonder if this kind of thing like these rich companies you know they do this kind
of stuff these skunkworks projects whole new operating system and then the business
sort of just says that knock it off we got a good thing going over here we're not going
to reinvest in all this because like what ultimately is going to happen to fuchsia is
either Google will slowly replace Android and roll it out to first all its IOT devices
and then its mobile devices and then put it on Chromebooks eventually or in a few years
they're just going to they're just going to give up it's just going to kind of wind down
a little bit because the Linux kernel or whatever that is that they need changed will adopt
what they're doing and the business will say ah good enough I mean it just seems to happen
over and over.
It is C sharp.
Oh you know of course it is oh yes well I wouldn't expect anything else from you know
this is like this is their dream and I have a similar dream or I have a dream I think
it's not similar but I have a dream that like I keep going back to that keeps like not working
and I respect them for not giving up is that a dot VBS file get out oh it's got to be right
I mean come on get out a VB all right you know this repo we're going to we need to put
this in the chat room this repo is worth a look there's some stuff happening here okay
yeah and I'll put in the show notes too there's also a PDF paper they wrote which I'll put
that in the show notes as well it's pretty great singularity how about that and you know
it's the new Microsoft so of course they put it up on GitHub wait what's iron hang on did
the PowerShell there it is all right wait wait no way really oh yeah there's a lot but
it's mostly C sharp sure of course using common system collections and link you man this is
wild because this is what they were saying back in 2008 this is long software runs on
a platform that has evolved over the past 40 years and is increasingly showing its age
the platform is a vast collection of code operating systems programming languages compilers
libraries runtimes middleware etc and they're calling that as super old and this is 18 years
ago I just want to say I'm looking at some of this code granted this is my cursory but
like this is actually pretty good like if you want to learn C sharp and like hardcore
C sharp not like you know you're just doing Xamarin or whatever I would check this out
there's some like they're doing a lot of like bitwise opera they're doing some good stuff
here like yeah yeah yeah well their whole idea was if we were going to start today and
learn and use everything we've learned how could we use that to create the basis for
quote more dependable system and application software singularity exploits advances in
programming languages and tools that create an environment which software is more likely
to be built correctly program behavior is easier to verify and runtime failures can
be contained this is fascinating I would actually suggest that like especially our newer developers
or folks wanting to get into it who write us all the time if you are at all interested
in the dotnet world or even you know now even just like programming patterns this repo is
actually this is this is beefy I was gonna make fun of it but and then in the show notes
I'll have a link to a story from a developer who decided to start taking phone support
after never doing it he only opened up in Japanese because he's primarily Japanese and
he had a Japanese phone number I would hope he speaks Japanese if he's only doing Japanese
phone support but of course you know it's kind of an interesting experiment because
he says most of them were polite he says probably mostly because Japanese culture I was yeah
I was just yeah but he did get a few upset calls and this was the key insight that I
thought it almost it almost made me go like maybe I should like have a phone line for
like a week the people could call he says you can detect critical parts of your product
there are times when there's large problems that's obvious but there's small little things
that the phone calls would expose to him that he realized everybody must be hitting and
that he should probably fix and he says of course there's also an opportunity to improve
listening skills and get a better understanding of what clients explain they want and what
they actually want but the insight that he essentially was getting bug reports even though
they didn't realize that's what they were gave him critical feedback of a data point
he was missing when the application was in the field without phone support and I thought
isn't that interesting you know and he didn't make a big deal about it I think he just put
it like in the about page or something like that but sure enough he'd get calls the other
thing he said is that if he went a while in between updates in the past people would just
kind of assume the project was dead yes but now people would call him and say hey are
you still maintaining this and he could say yes and then he'd have a sale I don't love
the fact that most business communications have moved to like slack or email or like
you know Trello in my case because we're TMB uses Trello enterprise it's horrible sorry
you guys I can just say like if there is a problem which software always has bugs there's
always a problem people are much much much nicer on the phone than they are on oh yeah
sure in fact it it's easier to get a detailed bug report when you're actually on the phone
with someone or better yet in person with them not only are they nicer usually but they're
more generous they'll be they'd be willing to check test more things and do more steps
for you over the phone right to walk you through it yeah I mean I I've definitely found that
like I mean I mean I've been on both sides of this equation right but like DMS or emails
you get at like 2 a.m. or probably like you need to take them with some charity because
they're not going to be good you know customers get frustrated I guess my thing is if I had
a consumer facing app like I used to a code journal if I opened like just like I guess
the phone line can't be my phone line it has to be like some kind of view view over IP
solution because don't you think you just get too much like random questions this seemed
like his situations best case scenario where he put it in the about version for the Japanese
version of the application so it's very specific I'd be willing to release code journal in
Japan only and have phone support I know they sound great over I mean I can't translate
the text into Japanese because I don't know if you have Google Assistant answer and I'm
pretty sure I can't compile it anymore but whatever right yeah there is that problem
I've always liked the idea of hearing from the audience that's why I went on that road
trip for me I know implicitly with with without any doubt that going out there and meeting
the audience gives me a much better understanding of who these people actually are than what
I get through social media and chat rooms and I say that all the time so not a big surprise
there but it's like I have to drill the point home because if people aren't frequently experiencing
that difference it's I think our our brains sort of normalize it out and we sort of forget
how low bandwidth these relationships truly are and we we don't really have a brain that's
adapted for a low bandwidth style of communication so we put a lot into that communication that
isn't there because that's how our brains are built that when you're talking to somebody
you see their facial expressions and you see how they're holding themselves and you also
just sort of humanize them more like those emails we got a lot of times if you respond
to them and say you know hey so and so and such and such and I'm sorry or this like they
realize oh yeah right no man I'm sorry I forgot I forgot actually you're a person right you're
not in facts and a Nazi robot for instance right and I probably I've probably heard that
a thousand times in emails when I respond but I but I will tell you a little bit like
remember way back in the day gather around children in 2012 when I used to respond to
YouTube comments now I don't yeah because there are people who are just trolls right
who are just gonna like yes you know and I feel back I've been on both sides of this
especially like I'd like to say when I was younger but not that much younger it's very
easy when you're like staring at a slack channel you're staring at a telegram or whatever to
forget that whatever thing the person did that annoyed you they are a person who probably
has their own stuff going on right how do you know right like you can use me maybe they're
going through like an awful divorce right and it's just like whatever they're a little
messed up maybe yeah hell maybe they got an offender bender right or some health issue
or some health issue yeah and we both had pretty severe health issues over the course
of the show yeah I don't know it's something I try to do I would recommend especially as
more of these communications become these asynchronous messaging services right is it
clear the direction we're going better or worse you got to remember that like the person
might just have like especially in the age of COVID right everybody's kids are home like
people are tired you know people are just run down you got to give a little bit of charity
and I'm trying to do it I'm not perfect as at it as Chris knows but you got to you got
to try yeah well said unless unless they are the maintainers of the GNOME project then
just wild out at them I'm joking I love you guys sorry they have been getting it this
week tough week was huh yeah yeah boy I tell you but you know what I'm more appreciative
than ever for our members there our coder QA team out there is amazing and we are grateful
for your support you can join us and get access to all the previous coderlies and the future
coderlies and of course you get a limited ad feed which will have some upgrades soon
you're going to get the also warm and fuzzies of supporting the show over at coder QA dot
co coder QA dot co mr. Dominic is there anywhere you'd like to send folks this week follow
me at Twitter at to Manuco I am two weeks away from shipping and I haven't slept much
remember what I said take charity you never know what somebody's going through they could
be about to ship you're gonna have to have a lot of charity with me in the next couple
weeks yeah yeah the hell I was going through I realized I shouldn't have done shows that
last week like the last two weeks you could argue but that last week where I was like
trapped in Tucson and it was a hundred and something degrees every day in the RV and
I mean like I just shouldn't have done the shows but I I didn't plan to get stranded
somewhere so I didn't have any backup plans you know the other thing about the behind
the scenes about last week's episode to which people don't know is if you listen to a drew
does such a great job but we had all kinds of like crazy strange drifting latency and
yeah it like oh god it was so brutal and so awful I shouldn't have done the shows but
I think my kid Mike's son was whiling out in the other room right like I think we should
have just said sorry but yeah yeah you know what you know what like you know what big
podcast networks do like you know that Roman Mars guy he just he features another show
and says I would love to feature stoked this week yeah this week we're featuring something
from our catalog and you know then they just roll it and that's that's how they get away
with it I just want to say stoked email him hey you know what stoked was great it was
fun I like stoked I don't know why stoked went away well I do know why but well cuz
Star Trek online got a little weird for those of you don't know which would be everybody
I used to do a podcast way back in the day it was a video podcast with some decent production
values I'll add it was awesome yeah and cuz I'm such a big Star Trek guy and we we got
early access to this Star Trek online game which is still going to this day but we got
I call that Fisher privilege we were very early we got very early access so they were
here in the event in Seattle and the guy that ended up later on running the project for
a while but the guy that was working there let us film for a bit before he shut us down
like he was supposed to and so we had solid few minutes worth of gameplay footage on YouTube
and from there we just sort of took off because we became like this rumor house for the game
before it launched and we started a podcast and there's a lot of fun for a long time until
until it wasn't the game got bought also my co-host got acquired by the company that we
were covering because you really knew his stuff so then you know we had to shut it down
and focus on other things and that probably was for the best you know isn't it gone down
though the game yeah no it's still going I don't know how many get out yeah yeah really
yeah it's still going it's free to play now too of course Star Trek online all right well
I think we need to end the show because I know where I'm going oh Windows only never
mind it does work under wine it does also on GeForce Now streaming I'm on Twitter at
Chris Elias the show is at Coder Radio Show and the whole podcast network is at Jupiter
Signal you know what links to what we talked about today can all be found on our website
we have a web page with links at coder.show slash 432 432 how about that you'll also find
our contact form over there our RSS feed where you can subscribe all of that your feedback
is a big part of the show so please do use that contact form usually makes up a good
bulk of the show so we appreciate it and you can always join us live on a Monday at noon
Pacific 3 p.m. Eastern thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the Coder Radio
program we'll see you right back here next week.