This is Koto Radio, episode 331 for October 29th, 2018.
Hi everybody and welcome to Koto Radio, Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show,
taking a pragmatic look at the art and business of software development and its related technologies.
I'm over here in the now forever grey Pacific Northwest. My name is Chris and joining us
is our host, established in the always sunny, always temperate conditions of the beautiful
Florida, it's our host, the one and only, Mr. Dominic. Hello, Mike!
How's it you, sir? Oh, it's been a while, Jar Jar. Oh, it's been a while, Jar Jar. Oh,
I've missed you so much, Jar Jar, so much. Why don't you get the hell out of here and get Mike
on because we've got a show to do, all right? Bye, sir. Yeah, yeah. What an attention seeker.
I tell you what, I was going to say something worse, but I'll just keep it PG here at the
intro. You know what I mean? But that Jar Jar, I don't trust him. A bit of an attention seeker.
Don't trust him. Yeah, you know, he's just a bad guy doing bad things. I agree. You got to get him
out of there. Get out of here. You got to get him out of there. Hey, you know, since I didn't want
to curse for Jar Jar's sake at the top of the show, how about right here at the top of the show,
I just give a real quick fuck you to the Twitters. I am so sick of Twitter. You just casually say
something the other day and now I've got three days worth of crap in my feed. That's my bad.
I ended up deleting the original tweet because I was like, OK, I don't know how we got here,
but it's not what I like. Bail, bail, bail. Yeah, I'm just like, you know, I can't reason with you
guys. You know, it's funny how like a just slightly incorrectly stated tweet, which is easy to do in
a super short format or like somebody who's just not even familiar with a certain knowledge domain
asks a question because they've just discovered this domain exists and the and the crap storm
that it will generate four days on Twitter. Whoo. I got to tell you, that was that was like Mike
stepped in it. So, you know, we know we have to retreat to the show. That's all I was going to
say. That's what we do. We retreat to the show. We got a good batch of feedback up in here.
Got some cute follow up. This little company, this little upstart called IBM just purchased
this other little upstart you may have heard of called Red Hat. Let's pour one out for Red Hat.
Yeah, we got some GitHub news. And then if we have time, I'm going to take one more crack
at a golden topic here in the Coder Radio show, the remote workers. New study out showing remote
workers are outperforming office workers. And I know we've talked about this over the whole
history of this show, but now here I am finding myself an employee of a company based out of Texas
and I am now a remote employee and no longer. See, when we've talked about this before on the show,
I've been the boss and everybody's been working remotely for me. Now I'm working remotely for
somebody else. Whole other side of the coin, my friend. Totally different set of experiences,
let me tell you. So if we have a chance, I'll get to that in the show, too. Now we probably should
know that I know that I set it up so much. I'm sorry about that. I just got carried away.
Let's start with Jacob's feedback. He's the Marine that wrote in a while ago on the show.
He says, hey, guys, I'm the Marine that asked for advice with zero experience
after listening to up hold on hamburger menus in the way after listening to your advice.
I put myself out there and I applied. I'm currently relocating to Florida to a government
contracting company as a C sharp and Russ developer. Thank you again. Well, now that's
a success story. Congratulations, Jacob. It's great to hear that. Maybe maybe go look up.
Mike, I hear Florida is just all one really small. Everybody down there knows each other.
It's really we all just know each other. Yeah, I didn't. You know, we all have alligators.
It's a good time. But yeah, I think we need a bell for this one. It's code radio success.
I agree. Yeah, everybody under 40 and code radio has to in Florida has to stick together. I believe
otherwise. You know what? There's so few of us. Oh, I know. I know. Hey, wait a minute now. Hold
on. My this pastebin link says no good. This one from Robin about setting you straight on WPF.
Did this go away? It says no good. Did it go away? Well, I can give you the gist. So I last week I
had stated that dotnet core did not work with WPF on windows, which it turns out is not true. It
works with WPF only on windows. So the deal is basically this. And this is kind of what Robin
wrote in to tell us. WPF does not work on other platforms, but it does work on windows. But you
can have dotnet core in a WPF app. Oh, okay. So nuance. There's like a lot of nuance. So
basically, that's how things like Avalonia work. Avalonia UI, which is a cross platform framework.
It will under the hood use WPF controls on windows, but still use dotnet core or it can
still use dotnet core. And Robin shared some good links that I will throw in the show notes
about kind of where Microsoft says dotnet core is going. All in all, it is going to be the future,
or that is their stated goal. The area of error in this case on my part was
stating that dotnet core could not be used with WPF on windows. That's not the case. It can,
but it can only be used with WPF on windows, which I still think is ridiculously confusing, but
it is a little, you know, basically the UI framework of WPF does not exist on any of the
platforms. Right. That's okay. That's what I'm rocking. All right. Well, so it's good to get
the clarification, I suppose. Boy, that seems sort of limited, but I actually kind of make sense.
That's how it would be. So thank you, Robin, for writing. And if you want to give us some feedback,
there's a couple of ways. The most official channel is the contact page at coder.show
slash contact. There's also the subreddit, which I try to check before each show. And I know Mike's
in there several times during the week too. And of course, when Twitter isn't blowing up,
you can also add Domenico and I'm at Chris LAS if you want to tag us on there. So I wasn't going
to bring this up, but you put this in the show and I didn't want to trigger you, but we do have
a new release from the cute folks. It's Design Studio 1.0. Big release. And they're hyping it,
man. They're hyping it hard. And to me, the cute outsider, it does look pretty good for building
some effective workflows for Qt and QML. I mean, it looks good, but obviously I haven't tried it.
Yeah. It looks interesting. Basically, it's a design tool that runs on Windows and I believe
Mac. I mean, they have a lot of talk about taking Photoshop files and generating QML.
Yeah. It's pretty interesting. Basically,
you have designers who might design your interface and you want to kind of create a,
I don't even know what to call it, not an asset pipeline, but kind of like a UX pipeline for them
to generate some layouts for you. Right.
For you to kind of use as a baseline. And then it does live previews and it'll do like,
it'll frame rate counter to give you an idea of how it's actually going to perform. It'll zoom in.
Yeah. Yeah. I have not gotten my hands on it yet, but certainly if this works,
this would be pretty cool. Anything that makes the development process faster,
particularly when somebody hands you a giant Photoshop file with a million layers
and you just like want to get a baseline layout template to work with.
The other aspect that's interesting is the timeline-based animations,
which is a timeline or a keyframe-based editor that lets designers create animations without
having to write any code. That's pretty nice because you could see how if you want just even
a basic proof of concept animation, this would be a useful tool. It might not be super sophisticated,
but relaying an idea before you start spending tons of time building something is extremely
valuable. And this thing has a lot of new features they're adding to the timeline-based animations.
Yeah. I think at worst, this is going to be a pretty good prototyping tool to say,
well, this is something like we could do. And then maybe you have to go back and
Yeah.
do the animations for real.
But in the meantime, you're building Qt and QML. I don't know about this Photoshop bridge. That's
the part that seems the most dicey to me. They label it as import your graphics designs from
Photoshop, create reusable components directly from Photoshop. Okay. Maybe if they're providing
very specific templates that you start with in Photoshop, I could buy that. I could see that
working. Maybe it's a pretty cool feature. If it does work kind of makes me wish like I could have
like a research team that I would be like, Hey, go try this. Come back, report back to the show.
But if anybody out there has a chance to let us know, do contact us because the Photoshop bridge
and the time-based animations and the Qt live preview stuff really seems pretty slick. Is there
anything else that jumped out at you about it? You know, not really. I mean, there's a level
of magicalness going on here that we've seen lots of these tools over the years. We've been doing
these shows for different platforms. I would be very curious to see how it actually performs.
But certainly I think there's particularly in the Qt space an opportunity for this to be
very useful. Yeah. Yeah. And for prototyping could be particularly invaluable. All right.
Well, moving on to a little breaking news here. This is a release on the Swift announcements
forms. We at Apple are making it a priority to support high quality tooling for all Swift
developers, including those working on non-Apple platforms. We want to collaborate with the open
source community and focus our efforts on building common infrastructure that can be
shared by Xcode and other editors and other platforms. To that end, I am excited to announce
that we are going to start a new open source project for Swift and C family language services
based on the language server protocol. We have chosen to adopt Lisp so we can benefit
from its active community and wide adoption across other editors and platforms. This means
that Visual Studio Code, Atom, Sublime Text or whatever your favorite editor happens to be
can use the same service as Xcode and any improvements we make to the service will
benefit them all. Wow. That's great. That happened. This announcement came out,
I think because of the delay, about 10 days ago or so, 14 days ago when we were recording this.
Have you had a chance to sit with this? Have you sat with this monumental announcement?
I've been trying to get more context for it and it seems pretty straightforward. They are trying
to make sure that Swift and basically the Apple development ecosystem are not completely locked
down, which feels weird and shocking. There are lots of people, if you read around about this,
who have been trying to implement their own LSP language service because they just can't,
whatever, they want to work in Vim, they want to work in some other tool. Whatever the tool is,
everybody can teach his own. I find this weirdly surprising, but good in a happy way.
Like certain other surprises we'll talk about. You're getting ahead of yourself there.
To be super clear, if you just develop an Xcode, this will actually end up benefiting
you in the long term as well, but the immediate benefits are probably going to be for folks who
are trying to write Swift in Vim. If that sounds weird to you, keep in mind that there's things
like Vapor and even IBM, I forgot the name of their solution, but IBM has a Swift, don't call
it Rails, but Swift-like backend solution that you can run on Linux. It's completely possible.
So a couple of points of clarification. The LSP service will use source kit D to get Swift-specific
highlighting support or code completion support, those kinds of things.
There was a question asked in the forum if the developers would be using lib syntax
X to implement highlighting, but that would be, it looks like probably not. It looks like what
they're going to do is they'll essentially be a library that you can grab. The intention is for
part of this to replace the existing library they're using today and really make it available
to all editors. Really, truly make something that's available to all editors so you could
have syntax highlighting in Visual Studio Code or Atom or like Mike uses Emacs all the time.
I'm like, yeah, they could be making, oh yeah.
There's some Google developers that are jumping in on this too and they look like they're pretty
pumped about this. They say, Google is also very interested in contributing.
We have a fair amount of work in this area to meet some of our internal needs.
We're excited to see this moving forward. Isn't that interesting? Well, I'll be one to watch,
but if it pales in comparison to what feels like maybe one of the largest stories
of the year, not just an open source, but of the year, some breaking news on Sunday.
Got all the breaking news in the Coder Radio program today. IBM announces they're going to
acquire Red Hat for just a small amount of money. Nothing that much, just a few billions, like 34
of them, which works out to be about $190 per share, which is a 60% premium over their Friday
closing price before the announcement. Red Hat will become part of IBM's hybrid cloud division,
with Jim Whitehurst, the CEO of Red Hat, reporting directly to IBM's CEO.
I don't know. You kind of went through the gamut of reactions through Twitter,
and I think one of your reactions was I really didn't think it would be Red Hat first. In fact,
I think the implication was you thought it'd be Canonical that sold first.
Yeah, I sort of did. Yeah.
Isn't this something? And you got to wonder if it does mean that maybe Canonical is going to be
more likely to be an interesting purchase for maybe companies like Microsoft or Amazon.
Amazon, yeah. So what was your initial take on this? Like your first raw reaction when you saw
this? Well, you know, I mean, full disclosure, I think this is pretty common, but it was a little
bit of dread. It was a little bit of, oh no, this is, I mean, and I got to be clear, I do not have
that reaction to all acquisitions. Like the GitHub Microsoft acquisition, I was more like, well,
this is interesting because there's a lot of rumors that GitHub was falling apart at the top
and they needed new leadership. They weren't like making enough money.
Right. But when the Red Hat one gets announced, I try to, here's the game I've tried to play.
There's two things I've asked myself. Number one, who else would I rather it be? And number two,
is the new owner better than the old owner for some of their various things that they have?
And my sense to the second question is no, but my sense to the first question is,
I'm not sure who else I'd rather have buy them. Let's say, I mean,
who else would have the money to buy Red Hat? I guess, you know, 30-
They had Amazon, Microsoft, I mean, all the big boys, but who would want to would be an interesting,
maybe Amazon, but you know, the canonical Amazon marriage would make a lot more sense.
Right.
I think.
And still be terrible, but-
Although Red Hat's pretty big on there. I think, you know, I think Ubuntu may have it
beat, but they don't release specifics. So it's hard to say.
Red Hat's already public too. Right, Red Hat was already a public company on like GitHub. It was,
yeah.
You know, there's one thing, because I know, I know a handful of people who work at Red Hat.
And there's one thing that I would say is consistent about a lot of people who work there
is they went to go work at Red Hat because it was Red Hat and they wanted to contribute to
open source in a way that would actually make a difference. Because working at Red Hat,
you were working on projects that would ship. And I just, I know a lot of people who are
working there because it's Red Hat, not because it's IBM. And I don't know what that means for
those engineers, what they're going to do. And I feel for them, put yourself in their shoes just
for a moment. A lot of them, the majority of them found out about this via Twitter, the news,
Linux action news, a couple of them found out via Linux action news. It was not well communicated.
And so when you have a bunch of employees there that are super passionate about your unique company
culture, which they're very proud of, Jim Whitehurst has written a book about it.
And they're working there because of open source and wanting to be a player in open
source and make a difference and contribute to open source in a way that will actually go out
and ship. You got to figure there's going to be a certain amount of talent train after an acquisition
like this. You got to figure that's something given IBM's aggressive history of, you know,
domestic layoffs and like aggressive offshoring with their consulting work, which is like,
I read somewhere 70% of their business now. I don't even know if they'd see that as a problem.
Yeah. So TechCrunch has an interesting take on this. Jonathan Schieber over there says that
what the latest $34 billion acquisition of Red Hat really tells us is that IBM needs a way to
save its failing Watson business. And this is an interesting take here. Watson, which is the
business division focused on artificial intelligence, whose public claims were always
really more marketing than actually market driven, has not performed as well as IBM had hoped. And
investors are losing their patience. There's also some critics, including analysts at the
investment bank, Jeffries, that have been skeptical about Watson's ability to deliver
what IBM claims for over a year. And earlier this year, the online medical journal Stat reported
that the Watson was giving clinicians recommendations for cancer treatments that
were unsafe and incorrect based on the training data had received from the company's own engineers
and doctors. All of those woes were reflected in the company's latest earning calls where it
reported falling revenues primarily from the cognitive solutions business, which includes
Watson's artificial intelligence supercomputing services. So there's a few folks out there that
have their take on this is IBM made a big marketing bet on artificial intelligence and Watson. They
did a whole blitz about Watson and it's not actually delivering real financial results.
And so they need to get back to basics. They need to get back to the cloud. They need to
get back to selling services. And of course, a lot of those services in the cloud are powered by
Red Hat. What do you think of that? I mean, I think it's hard to say that this isn't a,
you know, this is anything but a shot at the cloud business. I hadn't heard that Watson
was struggling so much revenue wise. That's at least according to TechCrunch. I'll have a link
in the show notes. I think there's a lot of areas that they've invested over the years. I am no
expert on IBM, but having watched them just sort of tangentially since the PS2 was being sold by IBM
since then, they've had my interest. I believe that they have lost their way. They became a sales
and consulting company and they went too far. They got too hooked on that sauce and they didn't.
What has IBM done recently? What have they done? You know, you can point to things that Amazon's
done and Google's doing and Microsoft and Apple and even Oracle and the companies in that,
even that outer tier of large tech companies, but IBM, they've sold a lot of services.
But what else have they done? What comes to mind when you think of what IBM's done? All that comes
to my mind is stuff they used to do. I mean, they're effectively a giant consultancy now.
Right. My point is, and I'm not trying to take anything away from other than saying
in that light, it seems obvious that this is a desperation play, a 60% premium.
Huge mark. Yeah, that's crazy though. That's-
34 billion. Now mind you, Red Hat is on track to make 3 billion this year.
So they got 34 bill for the sale. The way this was rushed out and the fact that the
employees weren't informed when the culture management issues are massive with IBM,
this is a huge issue for, I mean, Red Hat and now IBM. The fact that they weren't properly warned,
the fact that this is a $34 billion acquisition, it kind of makes me wonder if there wasn't another
interested party. And announced on a weekend, by the way.
A Sunday when I think they were planning-
Sunday.
They were planning to have a corporate meeting on Monday and then this came out on Sunday.
And it started out as rumors. So then Red Hat just jumped on it on their Twitter account and
confirmed it and posted the blog post. Seemed pretty rushed to me.
Strange. So maybe there's other bidders.
So do you see this as another step towards consolidation? Meaning,
do you think that other dominoes are now going to fall?
It does make me wonder what's next for Canonical as they're trying to go public,
as they're trying to raise funding, maybe even look at selling. It makes me wonder,
it makes me wonder what's the next move. And you have to figure that some of the platform
providers that compete with IBM, but have Red Hat VMs on their platform are a little nervous
right now. And you have to figure that Microsoft's looking around going, God, look at Azure.
We've got like 30% of these things. I mean, who knows what it is. They don't really often say,
but we've got like 30% of these things running Ubuntu. Especially if you count the containers.
If you look at the containers we're running, they're like 70% Ubuntu. This is a platform
that's obviously critical to Azure making money. And it's obvious they will spend money
to make Azure a success. So you got to figure, somebody over there is talking about this right
now. Okay. If Microsoft buys Canonical, all I am going to do is hang out in Telegram and on
r slash Linux for about a week and just watch. Well, what's worse? IBM buying Red Hat or Microsoft
buying Canonical. I would argue that Microsoft buying Canonical would be less of a threat to
Linux in general. Red Hat is responsible for the gnome shell. They are the primary stewards of GTK,
SystemD, PulseAudio, Fedora. Oh, who uses Fedora? Not that Canonical doesn't make genuine
contributions, but I actually have more faith that Microsoft would run them properly and the
contributions they do make would continue. In fact, perhaps Microsoft would even resource them
better. But in the case of IBM, what's the argument for IBM to continue developing Pipewire to create
a unified audio and video pipeline for the Linux desktop? What's the point? Why does IBM care about
that if this is part of their hybrid cloud division? See Red Hat did, and that's something
Red Hat is working on. I don't really see IBM being too fired up about that.
Yeah, I mean, maybe it's a little unfair to characterize IBM this way, but they really do
feel like they've been focused on basically pumping up their consulting business and not
developing products or projects in quite the same way as, since we're comparing apples to apples,
a Microsoft who every week there's a new major Microsoft product or announcement or open source
thing or, I mean, not that this is the Microsoft action show, but they're really doing a lot in
the space right now. Yeah, IBM, yeah. I mean, they've ran some commercials, they've contributed
code for sure, but yeah. And the other thing about it, about this whole, about this whole,
like Microsoft or whoever would buy Canonical, you have to figure with Canonical, with Canonical,
with Canonical, their business really is selling that server support and the server side.
The desktop is almost kind of, the desktop components on a bit are, I don't want to say
autopilot because that sells short the work that they do put into it, but they're based on upstream
projects for the most part, right? So there's not a same required, like they don't have to have a
huge desktop division. They can have a sustainable desktop division. So Canonical, you could acquire
Canonical and it would still make financial sense to run the desktop side of the shop.
Red Hat has all of these really long-term investments that are like foundational
technologies. Like I said, GTK, but also others like Stratus storage is something they're working
on right now. There's these big ones in there that, I don't know, we'll see. The claim is that
they're going to run as an independent operator for a while at least. Yeah, that always happens.
So is this just how, this is how it always was going to go? Is this it? I mean, is this what
this was all about? Like in the 90s, what Red Hat represented and what Microsoft represented
were so cornerstone to how I experienced technology. Microsoft was the bad guy and Red Hat
was the rebels and now Microsoft is an open source citizen and Red Hat is going to be owned by
the original establishment in technology. It's just really, it's really, it's kind of a,
it's kind of a whomp whomp into a story. I mean, I realize the story's not over yet, but
I don't know, all this fuss and then this is what we end up with. Is Red Hat's gone?
Marc Andreessen had a good post that came out this morning about how Red Hat was really one of the
only successful truly open source companies. And with them basically going, I mean, not basically,
they are in fact being acquired by IBM, right? The only one other than them was Sun. And honestly,
my initial reaction to this news was to pour one out for Javaduke because it's the same thing.
I mean, I'm not going to say if like IBM is worse than Oracle, but it's not good. I mean,
we already see some of the shenanigans with the Java SDK agreement on the Oracle side.
I can imagine Red Hat's contributions after a couple of years, eventually starting to be much
more focused on cloud, whatever that cloud, but whatever it is that would actually like generate
revenue for IBM. No, I don't know. They are consulting, you know, who knows what their
actual plan is, but I'm trying to think of another major company that is, you know,
of that late nineties, mid nineties, actually kind of open sourcey generation that is still around
and independent. Yeah. Hmm. I bet you, I bet you there's a couple, but I just, I'm not,
I'm not, they're not coming to mind. Like not as much as blender blend. Yeah. Blender is not.
Not at the scale. Yeah. Yeah. I, I, I really, the more I think about it, the sadder I get,
and I don't want to be, I keep trying to remind myself that IBM does have a great sales team
and IBM is going to bring enterprise credibility to Red Hat's offerings even more.
And the bill to sell it is parts of huge packages. Red Hat believes that they are sitting on top of
a $1 trillion market that they just can't address and that they need the resources of IBM to fully
address that market. This is, this is what they think. So Jim Whitehurst thinks at least.
Yeah, that's a very convenient thing to think.
So in other news, get hubs now officially part of Microsoft, Chris. Yeah. Yeah. Ooh. Yeah. Good.
Yeah. With government approvals received, the acquisition announced in June is officially
complete and get hub is now part of Microsoft. How do you, you know, how do you even follow any
of this up? Like we're just at a place now where this consolidation. Yeah. We're in a phase of
consolidation. Maybe, maybe it'll leave fertile ground for new upstarts. I don't think so though.
I don't think so. Yeah. I think we're, I think what's happening is an entire business cycle is
basically coming to its end. Right? Yeah. Yeah. And I feel a bit of mourning. I don't know what it is,
but there's a bit, there's a touch of sadness for it, which doesn't feel like an appropriate
response. It feels like this doesn't really affect me. I shouldn't feel sad, but at the same time,
it's, I feel like there, it's an era that's passing and a special company that was unique
is getting absorbed into a larger organization that, that quite frankly has failed to impress
for the last few years. I think their Watson stuff has smelled like bullshit from afar.
A lot of us have kind of thought that, I mean, I think you and I've talked about it, how it just,
it's marketing hype. I think we've talked about that on this show and so I just, they kind of,
you know, I kind of lost faith in IBM. And now to see this, we'll see, we'll see where it goes.
Just, just don't know. And you know, time will tell, as they say on these things could take
years before anything major changes, to be honest. Oh, I would hope that they would be,
you know, respectful of the community and, and red and indeed red hat was making money.
Right. So it's not like, it's not like this is a ship that's on fire.
Right. 30, $34 billion though, that, that took some serious effort on their part. That's IBM's
very serious about this move. You know, you want to make sure you get a return on investment on
34 billion. Can I make, can I make, can I make a coder prediction? Yeah. I say canonical Amazon.
If canonical gets acquired, it'll be Amazon. If they try, if they treated them like a Zappos,
that would be okay by me. That's not going to happen. No, it wouldn't. No, no, it wouldn't.
They might let them work remote though. Yeah. So, uh, remote workers, according to an article over
at inc.com are outperforming office workers and research shows that, uh, the real issue comes
down to employees being able to, unable to concentrate at their desk, uh, which is, uh,
that's an interesting reason. I'll tell you, um, that I'll go through their reasons and then I'll,
I'll, I'll give you my thoughts here. They say productivity, uh, with no office distractions
and greater autonomy, remote workers have the freedom to get more done. In fact, according to
a nationwide survey, 65% of workers said the remote work would give their productivity a
boost. Another 86% said that working alone allows them to hit maximum productivity. Despite the
distance though, remote workers are actually sometimes the best teammates. This is another
reason why productivity goes up. This is because the distance demands more communication and
without being able to lean on physical proximity, remote workers must reach out to another frequently
and with purpose leads to stronger collaboration. And then there's presence. Often office life is
littered with absences, workers who are calling six, sneaking out early to run an errand or even
go to an event on time. But remote workers don't really need to make excuses since they're not tied
to any office. They can design their workday to meet the demands of their lives. If they have a
cold, they can work from home without spreading the germs to the office too. There's just a,
these are just a few reasons. No beard taps or hammocks are necessary. You're right in the
article. But I'll tell you. So my experience is sort of a mixed bag with remote work.
So the first part is when I do go down to the Keller office, I can not work in a cubicle there.
I can't, like they have a few like open desks with like keyboard stands and second monitors
and phones and all that kind of stuff. And I was like, oh, I got a power cord, USB-C,
I'll just sit down and hook up. I just can't work like that. People be talking. Like they're all
talking. They're just talking, talk, talk, talk, bitching, mostly bitching. Sometimes you'll hear
somebody on the phone bitching, they're bitching. I don't want to hear any of that when I'm trying
to work. They're talking and I need to focus. So I had to go lock myself in a sound booth to go
work. But here remotely, there are certain things that you just don't get to participate in like a
group lunch in the office. You're kind of left out of that kind of stuff. Or another example that
drives me crazy right now is they have a small packet loss about every 10 seconds on their
network that mostly doesn't affect anything except for VoIP calls. Like web browsing,
even watching video doesn't impact it because everything buffers, everything pretty much sorts
it out, TCP retransmits. But VoIP calls, which are not only UDP, so they don't retransmit,
but also highly susceptible to packet loss. So remote workers, things get cut out. You can't
hear every 10 seconds or so what people at the office are saying, but they don't hear it because
they're not on the side of the call against the dropout, so it doesn't get fixed. It's not a
concern. So there's small things to it. But then on the plus side, I today decided I'm going to
start working at 5 AM. I came in, I started working at 5 AM today, and I just have the office to
myself. Nobody's here to steal that perfect morning productivity that I managed to achieve,
which is rare and prescient. And I was able to come in and have the morning to myself
and sip on my caffeinated beverage and get some work done with no interruptions for hours,
which just wouldn't be possible in an office. So there's definitely those kinds of mixes and
minuses, but the tools today, Zoom meetings, Slack, Dropbox paper, Google Docs, they are so common
and effective that everybody's using those same core tools, rather you're on the land at the
land at the office or you're remote working in Alaska. Everybody's on the same tool set now.
Everybody's using the same exact tools and applications to do everything. And that
consistency has made a huge difference, especially when you're dealing with applications that don't
require a VPN or don't require special crazy network security, because these are services
like Slack and Google Docs. And removing those barriers has made remote work as a remote employee
much simpler, much easier. And I think it makes a big difference if you have a large percentage of
your work base that's remote. If you're one person who's remote, or there's two or three people that
are remote and everybody else is local, you're really the odd person out. And so if you have
a large percentage that are remote, then there are certain accommodations that the company makes,
like putting HR files online in a secured location instead of paperwork that you have to go in and
fill out and then hand to them. There's little accommodations that can be made for employers
for employees to make that stuff smoother, to give them resources through a web portals or whatnot
that don't require physically going to somebody's office or doing an inner office mail. Anyways,
so I'd say on the flip side of remote work now, I think my overall takeaway is as an employee,
I am definitely more effective remote, definitely considerably more effective. When I go into the
office, I'm effective in a different way. So what I do is I batch. So when I go down into Texas,
I batch meetings or certain types of conversations that I'd rather have in person or something that
needed like a group of people at a table, I'll batch that stuff up. So it's a good kind of
hybrid approach, I think, to remote work. And when I kind of came to that conclusion and making it
really easy by following some of the travel hacks that have been sent into the show and by keeping
a go bag down at the Linux Academy office, I can jump on a plane, it's a four-hour flight max,
and if I leave here in the morning, I can get down there mid-afternoon and actually get
worked on that day. And that works pretty effectively. And that kind of flexibility
is really nice to have. But it's still not a perfect arrangement, I'd say, just because of
things like VoIP calls sometimes can be a little crappy. If you have a room full of people that are
having a meeting and you're the one remote worker who's joining that meeting, you kind of have to
sit there and wait till they remember to connect to you and that kind of stuff. But overall,
it's nice to have the flexibility. Yeah, I'm still not sure what I think about it.
Really? This article didn't change your mind at all or anything?
It didn't change it. I think it's what I'm doing because it's the best of all bad solutions,
but I think remote work can... I'm not sure. I'm not sure if it either creates new issues or it
can exacerbate issues that are already there. Well, let me tell you what I was struggling
with. And I wonder if you've tried this when you're doing remote work. The biggest struggle
for me was a drop in my energy level because I'm sitting around this place all day long in my office
chair, going upstairs, going downstairs, just in this building all day. It's quiet. There's nobody
I'm interacting with. And by the afternoon, or sometimes even in the morning, if I start really
early, my energy starts to drop off. And one of the things I've been experimenting with is going
to these various locations to work that are more public. This sounds very basic of me, but to be
honest, I've found it's working really well. I got the Starbucks app, which I've never done this
before. I got the Starbucks app on my phone and I order up some egg bites and some caffeine,
and I walk into the Starbucks, I grab it, and I sit there and I work on their Google
wifi for like 45 minutes in a public space, like a regular person. It's weird. You ever tried this?
It is weird. It keeps the energy level up though, is what I'm trying to get. Like changing it up.
I'll have to try it. Yeah. I find that if I do the right kind of work there, I can't be like
super focused. It has to be kind of light work, but I do a certain amount of light work there.
And just the change of vibe and location and all of that. And just really the ability that I can
actually legitimately work at a Starbucks is, I don't know, it just feels cool. And it doesn't
have to be a Starbucks. It could be Joe's Coffee. Wes likes to go to a local brew pub and he just
hangs out. That's more my- I know, right? And it's down on the waterfront, the Seattle waterfront,
too. So he gets a table where he can look out at the water. They got wifi. I mean, the guy's got it
and he can walk there from his place. That's the setup. I mean, that Wes Payne, he knows what he's
doing. Now me, I'm just going to basic Starbucks here, but it's worked for me for a little bit now.
And when I added this semi-recently to my remote work regime, when I sat here, I'm thinking to
myself, why am I at this desk? I'm getting sleepy. And I could take the same exact laptop and I could
go work somewhere else. And the thing about that app on the Starbucks thing, and there's probably
other places that do this, is there's no waiting. There's no lines. There's none of that fuss that
I'm not a big fan of. Like when you order food with this app, you walk in and it's just right
there on a hot plate waiting for you. And you just grab it, you say, thank you. And they say,
thank you. And you go sit down and you leave. It's the best thing ever. Yeah. Isn't that great?
So it's, I have found that tweaking my remote work by about every other day or so, I'll go
do this. And I've been doing it for about two weeks. I found that working outside can sometimes
help going on if you have a backyard or a porch. Sure. Sure. I'm also one last thing I'm trying
to do. And then I'm also trying to leverage a few more of the Google tools, which I've resisted
because it, you know, it's, you know what the thing is, is like, I'm already in on Google
apps because Linux Academy and Jupiter broadcasting use Google apps and we use Google docs to do this
show. Right. And the other thing is, is it's getting ubiquitous. Everybody has a Google account,
family members. Like when I go to a family thing or, you know, for Hadia, my fiance,
she has a, everybody has a Google account, everybody. So if I want to share something with
them, it's almost guaranteed I can share a doc or a photo or whatever. So yeah, I have,
I have bit the bullet and I ordered myself one of those Google home hubs.
Going to try that out. It's got the little calendar on there, you know? Now, will that and your home
pods could have like a battle royale to death? I hope so. I hope that would be so amazing if
when I'm not around, they're like, they're like fighting it out, like packet wars,
the sending, trying to send like ping of death to each other. Yeah. I'm going to give it a go.
We'll see how it works, you know, and I'm going to use the integration with Todoist,
which is my to do app of choice. So can we talk about our least favorite topic again? Sure.
I am, as you know, in the market for a workstation. Oh my goodness. This again. Yes. This again,
there is an Apple event tomorrow and system 76 is doing some very pretty videos while telling
you nothing about the product they're going to ship, which is a interesting marketing strategy.
Classic. Classic. I don't even want to know what these videos cost.
So tomorrow, supposedly there may be new iMacs and the new quote unquote pro Mac mini.
And I have been seeing a lot of excitement about the pro Mac mini and I just want to maybe lower
some expectations. Okay. Because if this computer indeed is, you know, announced and like released
within a reasonable timeframe after tomorrow, all it's going to probably be is a MacBook Pro
high end 13 low end 15 in a little box. Right. So it's really not, I, my guess is that it's just
given history and that they're coming out with a Mac pro and that the iMac pro exists. It's not
going to hit that sweet spot for most people, I think listening to the show.
Why not? I mean, you know, you put an I seven in that thing. You put a MVME SSE,
SSD in there. I think you want a GPU, right? Cause I think otherwise you may as well just go with
the laptop. Although I will say that I have come to the conclusion that laptops make terrible
desktop replacements for the most part for me, I don't know that it's a big enough Delta to,
to have that make sense. I don't know. I mean, I could almost see what you're saying.
I guess I could see what you're saying on the GPU, but it seems like with, with Thunderbolt
and all of that stuff, there's other methods now to get the USBC stuff. The USBC, the whole
ecosystem is so flaky and crappy right now. Like what's the point? So then you have the idea of a
bumped iMac, right? Which I think is maybe the more viable option. Cause you can get like an
NVIDIA card, hopefully. And it's, you know, a very nice 27 inch monitor. What if that doesn't
exist, right? Apple has been super stingy with their hardware upgrades, unless you're willing
to spend like $5,000. Sure. Am I, am I overly pessimistic because I've been responding to
people with, I don't think the event is going to be what you want it to be.
I thought this was going to be an iPad event. And I would say it is an iPad event, but they also have
Macs. Yeah. I'd say it's a safe bet to keep lowered expectations. If they don't update the Mac mini,
that is a tragedy. That's a tragedy. It's a travesty and a tragedy. And I wouldn't expect
a lot on the iMac. For me, I feel like the iMac is fairly competitive. You just recently got the
iMac pro. We had the iMac pro ship recently and the iMac 5k isn't really that competitive. So you
could see some updates there. You're not going to see any teasing for the Mac pro. I disagree on the
Mac mini. I don't think they need to make that much of an update to it. I think if they just
basically ripped off the Intel NUC, people would be happy. The mini is a glue machine. It's not a,
not a performance desktop. You stick it all together with the mini. You know what I mean?
And yeah, it's, well, it's a media server from a lot of people, right? And you know,
the iPad pros, I'll be curious to see what they do there. Be curious to see. Again.
Well, those have already leaked completely. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. USB-C they say, but that really could
just be a USB-C dongle in the box for all we know. We don't really know. We'll have to wait
and see tomorrow. You know, all will be revealed, right? Because like we can speculate now, but
really it's like literally tomorrow. This show will be already stale. Yeah. In two days, whatever
the hell Thelio is probably would know to probably be today when the show's coming out. Well,
anyways, that has been, that has been, I was good. I liked that. You know, we should, we should,
we should actually make this an official segment. Don't you think? Like we could call this,
we could call this a lowered expectations with Mike. Yeah. Is that going to be the, I like it.
You know what? I love it. There's all kinds of things I can. That'd be great dude. Next week, Rust.
Yeah. All right. Well, anything else you want to fire bomb before we get out of here? You good?
I hope Twitter goes bankrupt. I don't know. Oh, oh. In the meantime,
where can people find you on Twitter? We are the worst. I'm at Chris LAS.
The whole show and all its links is over at coder.show. Everything we talked about today,
news items, things like that. Coder.show slash 331. You can also go to coder.show slash subscribe
for all the links to subscribe. You're catching the theme here, right? It's all over on our site.
Like say you want to send us some contact. Guess what? Coder.show slash contact. It's pretty fancy
how that works, huh? Anyways, thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of the show. We'd love
to see you live next time. Check the calendar. We may be recording next week's episode later
this week. How does that work? I don't know. See you then.