This is KOTORadio, episode 476 for July 25th, 2022.
Hey there good buddy, welcome back to Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking
a pragmatic look at the art and the business of software development in the world of technology.
My name is Chris and sitting there with a very, very special hat, it's our host, Mr.
Dominic.
Hello, Mike.
Hello.
Hello, sir.
I like the whole vibe today.
You feel like, I don't know, in my ears, you just feel closer.
It's intimate.
It's like you're right here whispering into my ear.
Love it.
I think it's this new audio pipeline.
Anyways, I saw the news that you got yourself one of them little baby launches.
Yeah, it's a review unit.
I'm using it right now.
So I don't know if you could hear that.
It's quieter, isn't it?
It's quieter.
It's smaller.
Is it much smaller?
Yeah, I'm going to live in it a little longer.
It's not that much.
It's weirdly smaller.
Okay.
I definitely could see who the user for this is, though for my money, I think I prefer
the classic launch, particularly because you know that USB hub is super helpful.
So when it's smaller, what did they sacrifice?
Does it not have the F keys and like, does it not have the home and page up buttons along
the side?
What was, what was?
It has the home and page up.
The arrows are aligned like, so the right arrow is aligned with the end key and there's
no space between them.
The number and function row is one combination row.
I'm looking at mine right now as you talk.
So I'm like, I'm like visualizing it as you.
Okay.
Hmm.
Good experience.
I got, I got the pink switches, the quiet switches, which I, you know, I'm usually more
of a middle of the road kind of clicky guys, but this isn't bad.
I mean, I do type a one L I think I have enough muscle memory for the bigger one.
One that it is something of a change, but I could see people who maybe are just ever
so slightly more desks and strains wanting this.
The only additional thing I think I would want that might make me like this model better
than the classic launch is for its small size.
It really should be wireless.
Oh, wireless would be killer.
Cause then it'd be like a fancy like magic keyboard replacement.
Now I can understand when it's a USB hub, USB hub and whatnot, why you couldn't have
one wireless.
But interesting, maybe that's a launch three, you know, you never know, you never know.
You got to figure too, they got to make it smaller if they're ever going to get it built
into a laptop.
So if they're ever going to get it into a laptop, they got to keep working that down.
Chunky pie wrote into the show and he's feeling the call of the M says, I love listening to
you guys talk about programming in four 75.
Uh, he says your conversation over declarative UI was interesting.
I hate programming UIs and dealing with all the text boxes, buttons and screen sizes.
Now here's the thing, Mike, he says, I love Linux and I love supporting made for Linux
laptops, but guys, those new M one and M two Mac books are sexy.
I can't wait till Asahi Linux is 100% baked.
I think I'm going to have to get an M two or an M three at that point.
Love what you're doing.
Now I think you'll recall that your humble co-host here proclaimed that he was concerned
that over the years, and I think it's been about a year since he made this concern public,
he was concerned that we would see a drainage to the Mac from the Linux community, much
like we did when the whole genome three unity situation happened.
We saw a big exodus to the Intel Mac platform and then that happened to be right around
when Apple did a processor transition.
Here we are again, Apple's doing a processor transition and I feel like we're going to
see a big exodus to the Mac and I think we have, I kind of actually think my prediction
has bared out just based on a lot of anecdotal data.
Yeah, I think it's, it's, uh, in fact we have something to show from a John Grouper, which
I know is super Apple fan person, but you can't, you can't fight the numbers and the
power efficiency on these M1 chips and M2 chips, but more of the M1s.
That's something the industry just needs to catch up to.
I mean, there's really no two ways about it.
The situation with multi monitors and high DPI and high refresh rate, while it's not
like amazing on the Mac, it's so much better than Linux.
Our buddy Brent is down at Alex's house and Alex has a bunch of nice screens and Brent's
kind of experiencing for the first time what it's like when you have an NVIDIA GPU and
you got some high DPI, high refresh rate screens and using the plasma desktop and things sometimes
just don't work, they get rearranged, the monitors get weird refresh issues.
Like there's, he's running into all these problems and I have to tell you, I have heard
from a lot of people in the audience that like, yeah, I got a Mac book, it's just worked
so good with my external monitors, you know, the battery lasts all day.
Funix enough, right, I don't really hear about a lot of people defecting to Windows.
You hear about the WSL stories and how it's great, but those are existing Windows users,
right?
But I hear a lot of Linux users converting to the Mac.
You and I both know a former Linux podcaster who's no longer a Linux podcaster who switched
to the Mac.
I don't know, I think it'll ebb and flow, to be honest with you.
I think the Linux desktop is in kind of this vulnerable transition point right now where
we don't have open source NVIDIA drivers, but in a year or two, that's going to be really
solid.
We're really on, like we're seeing good momentum on the transition to Wayland, but not really
fully there yet.
It doesn't work for everybody.
There's a lot of things like that right now.
We'll see.
Stone writes in, he says, hello, long time listener, first time caller.
I was listening to the latest Coder episode and wanted to drop my two cents on the declarative
UI portion of the show.
For background, I'm a Flutter developer and I have been working in Flutter since sometime
during the V1 release.
I also work in ReactJS and I've tried my hand at Xamarin or I think it's maybe Xamarin,
React Native and even a little bit of UW Piskis.
To the point of write once and it looks great everywhere, I have to say Flutter is the closest
to this dream of all of the alternatives that have been discussed.
Unlike other cross-platform frameworks, Flutter uses its own rendering engine, allowing for
custom UI elements that really do look like the same thing no matter what platform it's
running on.
This is opposed to the way other cross-platform libraries work in which essentially just a
library that translates to a native UI and makes it harder to have consistent look and
feel across platforms like iOS, Android or the desktop.
Now, I'm not saying it's perfect by any stretch of the imagination.
Productive development, while technically officially supported, still runs rather horribly
on mobile browsers and he goes on to say there is still an amount of work needed to make
the UI adaptive based on device size.
However, the overall polish, performance and ease of development outweighs the cons in
my opinion.
I've brought multiple production applications to market using Flutter and I think we'll
only see more examples of this as the platform matures.
One thing though, to warn anyone considering Flutter, at some point you will have to gain
some basic knowledge in Swift and Kotlin.
This is if you want to actually hook into the platform's native function, think like
local authentication, where plugins are not available or you're just going to have to
do something where you write it yourself.
He says, looking forward to the upcoming meetups too.
Yeah, you probably agree with this take.
Yeah, for sure.
This is, I mean, we keep hearing about the Flutter, what we call them, the Flutter birds
keep chirping at us.
I will say, Chris is right, like every other cross-platform framework, you're eventually
going to have to drop under the hood.
It might take a while, you might have to ship a few apps without doing it, but one day you're
going to have to and just be prepared.
Good input and feedback though.
Thank you, Stone.
I like hearing about that.
I just, I got a tingle about Flutter recently.
Just seeing more and more like just things in the community and whatnot of projects people
are working on.
Who knows?
Maybe you can come tell me at some of our upcoming meetups, because holy smokes do we
have some meetups.
Meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting, Friday, August 5th, 6pm local time.
There is a meetup in London and I'm trying to think if there's anything else I need to
relate to you about that, but the details are at the meetup.com page.
And then we have all of the dates for our West Coast tour.
Those are also at meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting.
Start signing up for that.
And then last but not least, this is the big one, the tour lottery form.
If you are in the Pasadena area and would like to get a tour of JPL, you can join the
lottery at linuxunplug.com slash JPL.
Really quick little form we have on Nextcloud.
You fill that out and then we're going to run a little script to pick 15 names and probably
five or so backups just in case somebody can't make it.
We just ask that if you sign up that you can definitely be in the area when it is time,
which is September 29th around 12.30pm in the Pasadena area at the JPL offices.
So that's going to be pretty awesome, but it's such a limited availability.
We had to do it as a lottery, so it's linuxunplug.com slash JPL for that.
Linode.com slash coder.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account, and of course it's a great way
to support the show.
Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting.
You really got to go try it.
That's why they're giving you a hundred bucks to see what I'm talking about, because they
do it so much better than everyone else.
The best way to understand that is to experience it.
And speaking of experience, if you're brand new to deploying a server, they've got a marketplace
where you can deploy all kinds of useful things, like a system ready to go with Docker or Git
lab instance.
Perhaps you want Drupal or one that I just was looking at and I thought, geez, I should
mention this on the show.
They have Easy Panel, which is, well, as it says, it's an easy panel based on Docker that
lets you deploy Node.js, Ruby, Python, PHP, Go, and Java applications in their intuitive
control panel.
It manages the SSL certs.
You can even run commands on the command line through the browser interface.
And of course it integrates with GitHub, so you can push and pull your code down to it.
And that's just a one click deployment on Linode.
And if you're a pro, they got options for you too, including guides that let you build
systems up from the ground up.
They even have bare metal rigs.
And one of the back end features I love on Linode is their S3 compatible object storage.
It's so handy.
We use it for all kinds of storage for systems that are kind of always accumulating data,
like our Nextcloud instance or our PeerTube instance, but it's also just a great way to
distribute certain high availability files, like XML files for an RSS feed and things
like that.
And they've been doing this for nearly 19 years, so they've managed to build the best
way to run applications on Linux in the cloud.
With 11 data centers around the world, they are their own ISP, so their connection is
super fast.
And they're always investing back into the hardware.
They just recently added MVMe PCI storage.
Before that, they upgraded AMD EPYC processors.
They've just launched a database as a service, service.
There's probably a better way I could say that.
But I think you know what I mean.
I mean, I could just go on and on, but I think probably the best thing to do would be to
get that $100 and try it.
Why not get that $100?
Leave it on the table and go support the show.
Go to linode.com slash coder.
Once again, that's linode.com slash coder.
Well, John Gruber was feeling spicy this week.
He's got Apple Silicon is an inconvenient truth as opposed to one of his, I guess, links.
I don't know what he calls them.
But he's calling out a trend that I've noticed and you may have noticed, but recently, certain
review outlets like the Wirecutter and Ars Technica are excluding the MacBooks, the M
series MacBooks from comparison.
So they'll compare, say, the Surface Go 2 and they'll compare it against other X86 laptops,
but they won't put the M series machines in there.
And what's a little sticky about that, when they reviewed the Surface Go 1, they absolutely
compared it against MacBooks.
They were just Intel MacBooks at the time.
But when they made the transition to the M series, they kind of quietly just stopped
comparing the Intel laptops to the MacBooks.
And Gruber writes that he's quite certain that the reviewers are just essentially leaving
it out because they don't want to piss off the PC fans in their audience.
And that he says, quote, Apple Silicon is profoundly an inconvenient truth for many
computer enthusiasts who do not like Macs, so they've gone into denial.
And to appease them, he postulates, Wirecutter, Ars and others are just taking the Macs out
of the comparison altogether.
Is that what's going on, do you think?
Or is there maybe something less dramatic?
I think there's a couple things going on, right?
On the flame side, I would even add that, you know, people like to get review units,
right?
But pissing off the people is usually not done, right?
You're right.
Like if they make the surface book to look like a clown in the battery life department
and in the temperature department, then there might not they might not get access to another
one.
Right.
I mean, the reality is, if you're not, for some reason, bound to Windows, and you're
just like, oh, you know, a regular non, let's say non Linux enthusiast.
There's not a real good reason not to buy a Mac other than maybe price.
But even then, those errors are pretty affordable, the M1 errors.
So yeah, I kind of think this is Intel and AMD have to get their shit together.
And the lead is pretty significant for Apple Silicon right now.
I'll play devil's advocate just for fun.
I'll say that perhaps what's going on now is just a realization in the marketplace that
if you're buying a Windows laptop, there is probably a motivator that's putting you into
the Windows ecosystem.
And so you're not really in the market for a Mac.
So it's probably more fair to compare the Macs against Macs and the X86 boxes against
other Wintel systems.
I mean, because you see, you could take this as far as, well, why isn't there an Ubuntu
system in the mix?
And right.
Like, where do you draw the line?
So they have to look at the actual consumer market and go, well, if you're shopping for
a surface go, you're in the Windows ecosystem.
So therefore we'll compare it to other comparable Windows ecosystem laptops.
It's not a complete picture.
It's like a slicing of the market.
But maybe that's what's at play here.
I mean, that does make sense.
I would also say that price range stuff, particularly with the M2s and MacBook Pros, they could
argue that, well, we're looking at a price budget and these are just way out of it.
Yeah.
Although the go, you know, I mean, the goes like the price of an air, right?
I don't, I don't know for sure.
But I so I think the point that Gruber makes in there because he makes this kind of ham
fisted comparison to climate change deniers.
And I think what I take from that comparison is.
If he if they were demonstrating the benchmarks and the comparisons against the MacBook, it
would put pressure on the PC OEMs to do better, to produce computers that consume less power,
that produce less heat, that have faster disk drives.
You know, he would put pressure on them to produce better machines.
And so it'd be long term better for the entire market.
I don't I don't think that's actually how things work.
Right.
Like what is Intel?
OK, well, Intel will just, you know, crank the knob to faster and less power.
Yeah, they're not going to do that.
Right.
Like Intel.
I say AMD has something more of a chance.
But even then, it's Apple really has a winner here with with this Apple.
And I know people aren't going to like to hear that, but it's just the truth.
Yeah, especially when you consider they've been able to scale it from watches to set
top boxes, phones, tablets and something like the Mac Studio.
Yeah, that's pretty impressive.
I have to give it to them.
OK, but let's talk about where they're not so impressive.
This is both the most ridiculous small change ever and a monumental moment that took a decade
to actually make happen.
Netflix is rolling out an external subscription button for iOS users.
Just to kind of give you some history here.
This has been a back and forth for a long time.
And back in 2018, Netflix just removed the ability to subscribe within Apple's ecosystem
altogether because of Apple's 30 percent cut.
So now there's a button in the app to subscribe.
We hit that a message comes up that says, quote, you're about to leave the app and go
to an external website.
And then it also tells you that the transaction will have Apple have no responsibility if
things go sideways and that subscription management will have to be done independently.
You're not going to get that.
You got to do that on Netflix's site.
And once they once you clear that message, their page comes up and it's a pretty big
message, too.
It's like a full screen modal dialog that comes up with big, bold text that tells you
you're going somewhere dangerous, basically.
But you get to do it and then you get to subscribe outside of the Apple ecosystem via the Web
browser.
Right.
And the app developer in this case, Netflix gets to basically have that customer relationship,
which is what they always wanted.
Netflix just wants to be in a relationship with you, Chris.
Yeah, directly.
They don't want they don't want it to be a three way.
They just want it to be a one on one thing.
Nomination to.
Yeah.
This, though.
It's so funny.
Right.
What we're talking about is ostensibly Netflix is now allowed to put a link that opens up
the Web browser and shows a page where you can subscribe.
That's all that's happened.
And it's taken almost quite literally the run of this entire show to materialize.
Yeah.
So far.
That's where we're at right now.
That's where things are at these days.
But there's small little things like I've noticed, too, that Google, I think it's in
the EU.
I could be wrong.
I apologize.
I didn't grab this before the show.
But Google is now also allowing another payment processor in a rather large Western market
that isn't Google.
They're allowing a third party payment system.
And now Apple is expected to do the same.
But we don't have details on that yet.
After a dozen years, I don't know how long the app store has been around 10 years more.
And this we've gotten this far.
Apple held the line.
The other watches on the wall.
Yeah, I think Apple rightly recognized several years ago that the app store is a 20 year
moneymaker for them.
Right.
You can buy a device once every couple of years, but you hopefully are going to get
to the point where you're subscribed to Apple Arcade and you're buying an app every couple
apps a month.
You got a couple of subscriptions going right.
They don't need it to be a lot.
Right.
And if they could get 15 bucks, 20 bucks out of you a month, they're happy, right?
And the app store is a huge player in that.
And I think that's why they just fight it so relentlessly, because long term, I think
they see it as kind of how they're going to get rent.
Sweet, sweet recurring revenue.
Everybody loves it, man.
Talescale.com slash coder.
Go there to get a free personal account for up to 20 devices.
And of course, it's a great way to support the show.
Tale is my favorite VPN solution by a mile.
It's a zero config VPN that installs on any device in minutes, manages your firewall rules
and it works from anywhere, even in double carrier net situations.
I can attest to that.
Devices connect directly to each other using wire guards, noise protocol, building you
a mesh network with the best VPN security in the business.
And you'd be surprised how quickly and easily you can create a network between your servers,
your computers and your cloud instances and create one flat network where everything has
a static IP.
And yeah, you could even put a pie hole system in that network or any DNS server and you
can start doing name resolution in your Talescale network.
I use it to keep all of my family computers connected, all of the studios computers connected.
It's how I do tech support.
It's how I do work.
It's a major component to be able to get to.
Well, they're not even like super secure resources.
Actually the resources that are just not secure enough.
And so I don't want to put them on the public web.
I don't even want to open up ports on my firewall.
And now with Talescale, I don't have any inbound ports on any of my firewalls.
That's huge for me.
And I have it running on x86 arch servers, Raspberry Pi is running open, suits a tumbleweed.
I have it on my iPhone, my iPad, my next box.
I mean, everything you get up and running in just minutes, they have it for Windows
and Mac, of course.
I should probably make that statement, but it's obvious.
And they even have like binaries available for a Linux system.
Say you're on silver blue like I was and just want the binary.
They got that to devices.
Keep going.
And you know, the work with your existing identity provider as well.
So you can easily enforce multi-factor authentication.
Say if you're in a business and the fact that Talescale VPN is always on on every OS I use
and has a slick little GUI, including there's even a really nice gnome extension out there
to get the GUI in the gnome menu.
It's just dead simple.
It works every time.
It's super reliable and you're protected by WireGuard to go try it yourself for free and
support the show.
Go to talescale.com slash coder again.
That's talescale.com slash coder.
Well, I hate to say it, and I truly do mean this.
I really hate to say it, but it does seem like the tech hiring slowdown is starting.
Big tech layoffs and hiring freezes are prompting recession fears that are actually trickling
into other parts of the industry, according to an article at the Washington Post that
was I think it went live like on Friday or something of that extent.
And it captures a lot of the moves by the big tech industry.
Last week we found out that Microsoft has laid off a thousand staff.
Microsoft has also halted hiring in the Windows team and the office divisions for May at least
and perhaps beyond.
We just don't know.
This is old information that just came out.
Intel has told employees it would not hire more staff in the PC chip division and it's
reevaluating company priorities.
Google has announced it is hiring more cautiously, saying, quote, it is time to be prudent.
Apple has announced that it is doing a hiring pause amongst, quote, economic uncertainty,
saying it's tapping the brakes.
Google is switching from a hiring slowdown to a complete hiring halt for at least two
weeks with a reevaluation how they're going to proceed for the rest of the year.
It's kind of all happening and I hate it.
I hate to see this and it's not it's not an emergency.
It's not like everything's crumbling.
But I think the analogy that people are hitting the brakes now, they're tapping the brakes
are still on the freeway.
We're still going down the freeway, but they're tapping the brakes and we're starting to see
a backup.
That's a bad analogy.
But you know what I mean?
So I think there's a couple of things going on here.
I apologize.
I forgot the name of the podcast I was listening to, but they had a pretty prominent VC on
there.
I think it was something and it was hilarious listening to this guy, Chris.
He could barely like withhold his glee because really the valuations were too high.
The salaries were too high, especially.
I'm talking your startups, right?
And you know, a lot of these companies don't make money, not even just the big boys, but
I think we're going to feel this first in the startups.
We're going to see a lot of calling there.
We're going to see far less generous compensation offers.
And I wouldn't be surprised if some of the bigger firms use these where you have to come
into the office as a way to get people to self basically sell fire right to quit.
And then they'll start reevaluating salaries, basically pulling them down at the higher
end, which is an interesting kind of dichotomy we have.
We have like service industry workers, hospitality workers, their salaries are generally going
up.
And I just saw, you know, my buddy owns a pub and 17 bucks an hour for a dishwasher,
which was like crazy.
God, I almost want to do that.
Right.
But the high end is going to go down because honestly it was overheated, right?
These startups were throwing money like they're like it's going out of style and I can't get
over it.
Stress it enough.
They don't make money and they're not as honorable as Sun Microsystems.
So you know, we can't tolerate them not making money.
They have to fail.
I agree with your thesis to a degree.
I think if we were to continue to see an economic tightening, we were continued to see a hawkish
fed policy.
Yes, I think you're right.
You would see kind of this reckoning, a return to the mean, an actual return to values and
fundamentals that, you know, drive profits and revenue.
And I have worked for a couple of VC funded companies, you know, in the mid hundreds to
few hundred to 700 employee range.
I bet anybody listening that has to knows exactly what I'm about to say is 100% true.
I saw so much money wasted, like it like stuff that when I ran my business, we would never
even consider because, you know, everything we bought was really carefully calculated.
But I mean, I just saw unbelievable expenses on all kinds of stuff, travel stuff and office
stuff and just things that they had groups of people working on that would never produced
a penny.
They just were complete 100% cost center and that kind of stuff.
We've just seen that.
We've seen that as like a like a sickness spread throughout American business culture.
I think anybody listening who works at a company with more than 100 people probably has something
that goes on at their business that is a 100% total cost center that doesn't produce anything
beneficial for the company, the kind of stuff that if you are life and death, you know,
just survive by every paycheck kind of thing you would never allow.
But when you've got money coming in, it sort of makes it easy to just kind of ignore that
stuff like the saying is that, you know, when the when the when the when the tide is in
and everybody's out swimming and having a great time, everybody looks like they're having
a party.
But when the tide goes out, when the when the money slows down, when the tide goes out,
you see who's been swimming without their shorts on.
And so I would agree with your thesis if we got that far.
I don't think we'll get that far.
I think the money printer will turn back on probably in November, somewhere between now
and November, but probably not right yet.
And when that happens, the money will get dumped back into the tech sector just like
it always has.
Oh, oh, I hope not.
It'll be mega bubble time, buddy.
We've been printing money.
We have been on a financial bender since 2008 with maybe one or two moments of clarity in
there.
And fortunately, right, if you're an addict, you eventually have to go through the withdrawals.
It's it's time to go through the withdrawals.
It's time to I mean, come on, look at these dumb businesses that were being started.
Look at how these companies that make no money have effectively D I would argue they devalue
actual like modestly profitable, you know, what could grow into from small to like medium
sized firms, because it's all growth, growth, growth, you know, IPO, whatever, turning a
profit.
What's the product?
Remember Silicon Valley action, Jack Barker talking to Richard Hendricks, I will never
compromise the product, Richard.
And he's like, Oh, the algorithm?
No, you idiot.
The stock.
It's like, it's crazy.
It's all effectively.
And I know you love crypto, but it's all effectively like a securities.
It's a casino.
Basically.
Oh, crypto securities?
Yeah, absolutely.
Well, not just crypto.
The stock in these startups.
What's is what's the difference?
Why not call it?
You know,
well, the two are related, right?
The reason why you've seen crypto and NFTs just go crazy is because they're securities
that Wall Street guys are playing around with that.
The money that's been pouring into crypto isn't coming from Wall Street bets, a sub
Reddit, right?
Like, yeah, a handful of it is.
But they're a drop in the bucket compared to the billions on Wall Street that are screwing
around with off the book securities.
I completely agree.
Have you ever hang out at Wall Street bets?
Yeah, I've been in there a couple of times.
I mean, like literally twice.
Have you noticed over the last month?
I read my some my Reddit feed now and I tend to read.
I don't know.
I've somehow been drawn to read it again.
But I never comment because Oh my god.
Yeah, good call.
A lot of it is like less, you know, diamond hands to the moon, bake this, you know, we're
the apes, whatever the hell that means.
And now it's like, I just lost $20,000 and my wife is divorcing me.
Yeah.
There's a lot of that right now.
A lot of that going on.
It's like, yeah, well, do you like you were only doing well, because, again, I'm gonna
say it.
The Fed had everybody on a frickin bender.
And I think right now people just haven't really fully realized it yet, because it's
been so normalized, because it's been happening in the background for so long.
I don't think it's totally clicked yet.
I don't think people have made the connection to the state of employment, the state of the
tech industry and the money printer.
I think they're just too distant for most people.
See, this is the problem.
The tech industry, I feel like in a lot of ways is going through some sort of transition.
I know this is welcome to old man radio.
When we started the show, it was all about like, crazy ideas, you know, mobile, mobile,
mobile, rapid product of rapid, you know, MVP is we talked a lot quick break things
a lot about agile, right in different forms of that.
And now it seems like tech and media are like in this weird or serpentine, polyamorous orgy
with politics.
Well, all of the tech companies wanted to become media stars and media platforms.
All the media companies want to become tech companies.
It's great.
Yeah, everybody.
They all want to be streaming platforms, or they all want to be media.
Nobody realized that the only reason they're at this crazy college party at the scrap party
is because, you know, Pledgemaster Fed was just bringing the kegs in.
Let's go.
Let me tell you something.
As a man, I think you can.
I think Chris will go with this, Chris.
If you had to ask me to identify a bender, if you had to pick of all the hosts, who could
identify a bender when he sees one?
It's got to be me.
Oh, I think so.
Yeah, I would.
I would agree.
I think we've been on a what is it, 14 year bender.
It's time to stop.
It's time to you know, there's going to be some vomiting.
There's definitely going to be some tragic cases of startup founders losing everything,
but you never had it.
It was a lie.
So yeah, but it's a yeah, but it's a little bit different when it's like, say, you and
me.
Right.
If like, if this thing, if this thing gets really rolling, it's probably going to wipe
out the advertising market and it may wipe out people's appetite for development projects
as well.
Well, it's going to yeah, everybody's going to get hit.
It's but what's the alternative?
We just keep going.
That's exactly what they're going to do.
Yeah.
I mean, you can't do this forever.
Nope.
But, you know, he could probably do it for another cycle.
Our sons will get to fix it, right?
Our kids will get.
Oh, I think it's going to bite us.
Oh, I think we'll be around for it.
There's a lot of moving pieces to something like this.
But at the end of the day, the Fed policy is to make changes to their policy that increase
unemployment.
The idea being that if you increase unemployment, you'll reduce demand.
You'll cool the market.
That should have a lowering effect on inflation.
I know this is this is this is a long way removed from development.
And you're probably wondering how it all kind of connects together.
The way it all connects together, what Mike and I are trying to tell you with this entire
discussion has been about is this is directly connected to the health of the tech industry.
It is directly connected to the employment market.
It is directly connected to the indie business market.
It is a one for one thing.
Whatever the Fed policy changes, it directly impacts the tech market directly because this
tech market has thrived during a period of loose economic policy, loose money, easy money,
better than free money, really.
So that's changed for now.
And as long as it stays in this state, the tech industry will take more and more hits.
The health will deteriorate.
I imagine it's not forever, though.
But that's how this all kind of comes back together is it is directly correlated.
When you hear about the Fed hiking rates, that makes money more expensive for these
companies that operate off of loans.
I mean, you hear about how Apple has so much money in the bank, right?
They just sitting on tons of money, like two trillion dollars.
They legit they decided to become a credit card company because they didn't know what
to do with it.
And now they're a buy now pay later.
How did Apple manage to run operating expenses while putting all of their money in an offshore
savings account?
How do they do that?
They take loans because they have a guaranteed collateral.
They have that balance.
They can take out loans like crazy against it.
They get access to loans in a way that average people like us just can't even comprehend.
You know, you want a few bill.
Here you go.
Here's a line of credit.
Apple, here's a few billion line of credit.
No problem at all.
And when the interest rates are lower than inflation, it tends to work out better for
a company like Apple to take a loan out.
And that's what they've been doing.
They've been getting access to easy money like that.
And that easy money is going away.
That's just it right there.
The loans cost more now because the base rates are going up.
Yeah.
But on a positive note, if you are a you know, someone looking to be an entrepreneur, I hate
to say it, but particularly if you're young and don't have things like kids, dogs and
mortgages, this type of environment, a crash is always a great time to start up.
Not like in the VC way, but it's it still will be possible, of course.
But there will be opportunities coming from don't forget, we are still experiencing changing
dynamics of remote work.
Covid apparently decides it wants to visit again.
And something about somebody slept with a monkey.
I don't know what the hell happened there, but probably a BSD user.
So if you want to create, you know, the next.
Just please don't create Uber for something right, but some interesting technology product
that maybe works with these trends that you can bootstrap.
This is still a pretty good time.
If you focus on where things are transitioning to, because I don't I don't know what Chris
thinks, but I don't think we're done with our Covid hangover.
Yeah, seemingly not.
At least we have the Provo lax or whatever it is that the plies are elected.
At least we have that now.
So hopefully that's helping people.
But I think you're totes right.
Like these types of markets are a time to build and invest.
And then when the market turns around, you want to be in a position to catch that wave.
And the only way you're going to be ready is if you've been building something, creating
a bit of credibility, creating a bit of network effect around it.
And then when things pick back up and there's market demand again and people are looking
for the solution that you've created, you're there for it.
These types of downturns that we're in right now can be beneficially life changing for
a career trajectory or for somebody that wants to start an independent business and has the
ability to hunker down, survive and weather the storm.
The next wave.
Yeah.
Right.
And also when these things tend to happen, there's still markets amazingly that do all
right and are still hiring.
And so it's just a matter about finding those places and even some regions still end up
doing better than other regions as well.
So it's not all a bad thing.
And I think maybe that's the part we could focus on a bit more is these are actually
great valleys of opportunity.
And when you start to look at it as a moment of opportunity.
You start to think, God, I hope I hope the down market lasts long enough.
I hope I have enough time.
Right.
You start to.
It changes your mindset about it instead of like, oh, God, here we go.
How long is this going to take?
Oh, I'm bracing myself instead of that.
It's a oh, I hope it's a down market the last while.
I hope I hope I have enough time to build this thing.
Right.
That's actually, you know, a nice mindset shift.
It helps you get through it.
But Chris is probably right because we live in a cynical world and there's an election
coming up.
So the Fed will probably start putting money again here.
Just not what your podcast can boost for you.
But what you can boost for your podcast.
Boostagray.
All right.
Well, we got some boost this week.
Optimus Gray boosted in with a big one.
He is coming in with a big row of ducks.
Twenty two thousand two hundred and twenty two sets.
Now, he was listening live and was just enjoying the show.
We stream over at Jupiter Dot Tube on Mondays at noon, Pacific three p.m.
Eastern.
We're not yet live in the podcast apps, but that is part of the podcasting to do spec
is the ability to actually live stream in the podcast app.
So you just subscribe to Kota Radio and when we're live, it'll just show up in your podcast
player as a live item that you could just listen to, tap it and just tune into the stream.
And then when the stream is over, it goes away and then the actual edited version takes
over and replaces it.
It's a pretty neat system.
So we'll be there one day.
But we're not there yet because step one is getting to the point where we're satisfied
with creating and generating our own RSS feeds, which we're just kind of at the beginning
of that.
Next boost comes in from Yukon Cornelius with two thousand sets.
I'm curious to know if the GitHub Copilot models make their way individual studios,
A.I. autocomplete, what do they call that, Intellisense?
I've used V.S. one at work.
It supposedly scans my code base to provide the recommendations.
No mention of scanning GitHub, though it seems to be true.
The Visual Studio recommendations often seem like they were coded by me.
I found the feature actually saves me a ton of time.
Visual Studio offers a custom version of Copilot that scans your own code for the training
model.
Saves him a ton of time, he says.
The Copilot and V.S. code also does that in addition to whatever external sources it scans.
Have you found that useful?
As a form of autocomplete?
Yeah.
I mean, I tend to use the same patterns over and over again because I'm old and you will
pry my delegate pattern out of my cold dead hands.
I use what works.
Me and Deckard Cain were there.
No, it's useful.
I mean, the thing about Copilot is it's basically better Intellisense, but when it's wrong,
it's freaking hilarious.
The Golden Dragon boosted in with a gigabyte of sats, 1024.
Holy crap, that's too much sats.
He says, Mike, you need to go grab yourself some Microsoft tactical wear.
I don't know if you saw this.
Tactical?
Yeah, they've launched the hardware division designed by one of Microsoft's creative directors,
and it's like super retro cheesy Microsoft swag, including pants that cost like $150
cargo pants.
No, that's not going to happen.
I mean, they've got a little Microsoft logo on there, man.
Don't you want it?
Come on.
Actually, they look really comfortable.
I'm not going to lie.
They're not like standard CACULA, like a different material.
They're $150 pants, Chris.
I know.
But they're tactical pants, man.
They're tactical pants.
Don't you go spending our rope budget.
All right.
You're right.
No, you're right.
All right.
I'll simmer down.
We got a double boost from the Golden Dragon.
He sent us in a little small row of ducks saying that things had him feel a little awkward
at episode 475, like maybe we were getting a little Linux betrayal-y when we were talking
about how you could use Windows, Mac, or Linux these days.
He didn't like it too much.
So to make up for it, he sent us a triple boost with another row of small ducks.
Honestly and truly, I am Robin Hood.
Now he's bringing up the whole east and north and south, the Carolina thing.
I hate to get into the Carolina barbecue thing again, but he's doing it, so we're going in
there.
I feel like we don't have a choice.
It's vinegar-based sauce, guys.
It's a kind of waste nothing but the squeal type approach.
It was trendy.
Oh, when you add it to your meat, it can make it super tender and juicy.
All right.
I don't know, man.
If I'm going to rely on a sauce, I feel like it's maybe not great barbecue.
That's just my thing.
Like the barbecue, you should be able to eat it without sauce, and then if you add sauce,
it makes it better.
You're just throwing down like that?
Dude, send your feedback to chris at jupiterbroadcasting.com.
I'm just saying.
If you disagree, boost in.
We'll make it work out.
We'll figure it out.
You're a bad man.
That's some bold stuff you've got going there.
I know.
It offends people.
Oh, a guy sent us in a multi-part boost, 444 cents.
I think you guys should check this out.
It's an article by the New Yorker, Mario not so super at 40.
It's probably, he says in the second part boost, best read in Mario's voice.
It's a me, a Mario.
And the whole thing is an article written in Mario's voice.
And it hits a little close to home about how life's harder for Mario at 40.
Like things like, so basically I wake up and it's like, I can't move my back, like at all.
So I go to Dr. Mario, no relation, and he's like, Mario, when's the last time you had
a physical?
And I'm like, can't you just look at my back like a normal?
And he's like, no, no.
I'm starting to think there might be an underlying problem.
And it just, the whole thing goes on.
It's about life at 40.
And I'll leave it for you to read.
I'll have it linked in the show notes, thanks OA guy.
Nothing like that to make me feel old.
He did send us a double boost though.
Another row of duckos, boost.
He says, still prefers Vim over TextMate and BB Edit.
Very good.
We got 3,737 stats from TrevDev, and he says, in regards to comments last week we made about
using Windows, Mac and Linux being fairly interchangeable, he says, I'd like to gently
remind you both that the three distros, Windows, Mac and Linux, are not really on equal footing.
Linux is clearly superior, and it doesn't come with the bloat of Windows.
Embrace, extend, and extinguish.
We are currently at the extend phase.
WSL is the extend phase.
Does that mean extinguish is like the next phase that Linux is gonna die?
Is that what you mean?
I'm pretty sure Linode is like, eh, I don't think so.
Yeah, TrevDev, I'm curious if you think that Windows could actually extinguish Linux, because
it just doesn't seem possible.
As long as you're gonna have any kind of substantial server market, it's gonna be beneficial to
have the desktop around in some capacity, right?
I mean, you gotta have a dev platform, you gotta have a test platform, so I think as
long as you have a substantial server deployment, I think you're always gonna have a Linux desktop
of some form.
I don't know if it'll be the king desktop, but I think it'll always be around, but I'm
curious to know, TrevDev, if you think they actually could extinguish Linux altogether.
LRAI 7.41 boosted in with 2,245 SATs.
Boost!
He actually has a correction on my comment about how JB is using Cloudflare.
He says, I only know because I've been helping with the new website that's under development,
and he says, you're not really using any of the fancy features of Cloudflare like Mike
was actually talking about.
You're just using it for DNS.
Yeah, I know, but we could turn that stuff on.
But it's a hell of a DNS provider.
It sure is.
I actually have liked it.
I didn't want to.
I was very resistive.
Why?
What's your beef with Cloudflare?
I think they want to be like the Walmart of network services.
I mean, I don't mean that in a bad way, but I just mean that like in a huge market dominator
way.
Well, yeah, we need to get to where there's only one company named Mom, right?
That's exactly it.
Isn't that what we're doing here?
We are.
That is exactly what's happening.
That was my only hesitation.
I think you get it, right?
It's just a little concerning.
I feel like I've seen this before.
Yeah, you're probably right.
That's a future rival reference for for the Gen Z-ers in the crowd.
It's good.
We watch holds up.
It does hold up.
It's a little too close to home on certain episodes, though.
No kidding.
You should.
You should watch it with a post covid eye.
Double boost from Ellery 741.
Just checking out Podverse.
Thanks for the awesome show.
So Podverse, just a quick tangent here, Podverse is one of these new apps, these new podcasting
apps that are pretty great.
They've got an iOS, an Android and a Web version, and it's all open source.
But here's what's really cool.
So I interviewed the developer, one of the developers, the co-founder for office hours.
And then after he came on office hours, he agreed to help us out with the new website
that we're working on.
And so now our embedded player on our new website is the Podverse MP3 player.
We've gotten they worked with us to make their web player that they have embeddable and that
it can point at our own files.
And so when the new website launches, we're going to have a Podverse player that has like
chapter support and playback speed support, boost support all right there built into the
web player, open source, GPL, baby.
And Mitch at Podverse has been helping us out with a new website to make it all possible.
And he loves Coderio so much.
He included it twice in his directory.
There you go.
You know what?
Let's get it in there a third time.
Oh, you know what that is?
I know that beautiful old artwork.
What is it?
What did you find?
That's the old member.
We have changed feeds way back when.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
That's what that is.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Because it is.
Yeah.
2017 feed update.
That's what that is.
Good old days.
The old feed.
The old logo.
You know, I don't mind the old logo.
I like the old logo.
We never did new coasters for the new logo.
We should.
We should do it, too, but I just, you know, the old logo I remember thinking when we were
trying to figure out looks like how the hell do you even the show had launched yet?
Like, how the hell do you even visualize the show like we can't just have like HTML code
or something.
And now if we did a logo, it would just be a MacBook with a bottle of gin poured into
it.
Amazing.
If you want to check out Podverse, it's like Podverse dot FM.
It's one of the apps at new podcast apps dot com.
And it's neat because it's because it's GPL, it's also an asteroid if that's how you roll.
And then we did get a series of thank you boosts.
Five thousand sats from L.T.
Guy for episode four seventy five and then an additional five thousand sats from L.T.
Guy of double five for episode four seventy four.
We got some lead sats from A.V.
Parker and we got some future sats for seventy six from K.P.
Vuck.
Thank you, K.P. for boosting the future.
If you'd like to send us a boost, you could try out Fountain FM.
I'll have a link in the show notes, which is like my link.
I think it connects you to my account so you can see my clips and that kind of stuff.
But you can just also grab any any of the new podcast apps that look interesting to
you at new podcast apps dot com.
And one more note.
I was on the podcasting two dot o podcast.
I think it's episode ninety four.
And we talked about the podcast biz.
We talked about advertising.
We talked about memberships.
We talked about standards and Spotify and all kinds of things.
Those are actually a really fun chat.
So if you're interested in that kind of stuff, go check out the podcasting two dot o podcast.
I think it's episode ninety four titled Bell's out is the episode I'm on.
I got good news for our members.
The new Coderly report is out to do to do to do.
It took me a little bit longer than normal because I was slammed recently, but it turned
out really good.
This is one I think it's worth becoming a member for if you're not already.
We did a little look back at like twenty fourteen, twenty fifteen early days of the show and
replayed some moments where we kind of talked about issues at the time and then we reflect
on them now or some predictions we made, one that I got massively wrong and a couple that
we got right.
But we it was just it was more fun than I was expecting.
Thanks to Alex, too, for for clipping a lot of those and tweeting them at us.
So we had a good batch to go through from the past because he's been going through the
back archive.
So the timing just worked out good and I thought it turned out really well.
So it's a new Coderly.
It is live now in your members feed.
Or if you're subscribed to the public feed, you can also just go to your member full dashboard
and you can download it directly and just play it if you like.
And if you want to become a member and you're not one yet, Coder QA dot co become one of
our QA members.
You get access to every every Coderly so you get all the previous ones to you support the
show and you get an ad free version of the feed so you get all the Drew's nice hard work
but without the advertisements in it, you know, for your preferences.
So go check that out.
Or you can keep the public feed and just download the specials when they're available.
Coder QA dot co.
Mr. Dominic, is there anywhere you want to send the peeps this week?
Follow me at to go on Twitter and why don't you check out Alice Dot Dev for your automation
needs?
I don't believe you.
No, I believe you.
I think that's a great tip right there.
You can follow the podcast on Twitter at Coder Radio Show.
The network is at Jupiter Signal.
Links to what we talked about today.
That's on our website.
Coder dot show slash four seven six.
If you'd like to check out the in development website, Jupiter broadcasting dot net, and
then you can report an issue on our JB GitHub.
Love to have your eye on it.
Let us know what you think.
It's going to be live pretty soon.
You can also send us some feedback at Coder dot show slash contact.
That's a big part of the show as well as a boost.
We appreciate that.
And you can subscribe.
We've got our RSS feeds over there as well.
And of course, we're live Monday at noon, Pacific three p.m. Eastern.
Thanks for joining us.
We'll be back here next week.