This is Kota Radio, episode 384 for October 19th, 2020.
Hello friends and welcome in to Kota Radio, Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show,
taking a pragmatic look at the art and business of software development
and the world of technology. This episode is brought to you by the all-new Cloud Guru,
the leader in learning for cloud, Linux, and other modern tech skills. Hundreds of courses,
thousands of hands-on labs. Get certified, get hired, get learning at cloudguru.com.
My name is Chris, and joining us, like the soldier here he is, is our podcast buddy,
it is Mr. Dominic. Hello, Mike. Hello, Chris. That was my Oprah, and I just don't,
will never do that again. Oh, so do I get a car?
You get a Matchbox car. You know, she's always going to be known for that,
regardless of what else she does. Did it like once, yeah. Oprah's known
for giving away cars, and you're known for spilling stuff on laptops.
Well, I see we're starting classy here today. I just cannot believe it. You know, sometimes I
check your Twitter feed before the show. Yeah, so here's the thing. I have a deep-seated hatred
of MacBooks, apparently. Whether it be gin, beer, or in this case, herbal tea, I cannot somehow
keep them dry. What you got to figure is perhaps you suspend the laptop in air and use a Bluetooth
keyboard, then you're only out a Bluetooth keyboard. See, I got a strategy for you.
Well, a not insignificant number of people on Twitter recommended a ThinkPad that actually has
holes in it for just this purpose. Yes, some ThinkPads have drain holes that actually drain.
Now, if it's an entire glass of liquid, you're still kind of pushing the limits of the gutter
system in the ThinkPad. I also saw some people tweeted at you like a water bottle that has a
suction bottom that sticks to your table. Yes, I believe Emma from System76 recommended a sippy cup.
I mean, that could be another solution. Maybe you already have some around the house, too.
However, other than the trackpad, it is fine. Oh, really? That's good. I want to picture the
moment. Did you spring into some kind of action? Do you have a protocol at this point you follow,
like a standard operating procedure for this situation? I actually do. We have a dedicated
giant bag of rice for this. There you go. The bag of rice, man. It does wonders.
Well, I'm glad you're able to save it. And, you know, it's like being home again. I keep saying
it's like we're in 2017 all over again. And I thought, you know, this would be the last episode
where we'd talk about SUSE. I don't think we got very much email about it. But the lizards brought
a gift for Mr. Dominic, an actual gift. So Kevin, who started this all. Thank you, Kevin. Sent me
two rather large SUSE pillows, lizard pillows. Oh, yeah. And roughly 30 Linux. I think it's
Linux user and developer. But the issue where they featured SUSE, of course, of the same issue. So
30 copies. Now, the lady where I still have a small office space who got the mail was deeply
confused. I mean, she's like, did you order like all of the same magazine? I said, what's on that
magazine? Some lizard. I'm like, oh, I still have some boxes of of SUSE around here in the studio.
Well, so for Halloween this year, every kid is getting a SUSE DVD. I thought you were kidding.
But then then I saw you tweeting something ridiculous like you don't know Linux until
you. Yes. And then I thought, wait a minute. Now, what is going on? What is happening to
to my co-host? I think he's being sucked into the dark side. You know this already, but I am working
on an initiative that should be done by Christmas if you believe people that give estimates that I
don't believe. But let's say the New Year and it does involve SUSE and it involves something that
requires permitting. Is this karma coming back here? So SUSE is a requirement of an application,
I take it? Yes. But I'm going a bit beyond that. Oh, oh, oh. You mean you're enjoying it?
Let's just say in a hypothetical world, you are a biologist, a professor at NYU. Your student's
name is Peter Parker. You lost your arm in an awful accident and you're thinking what animal
can regenerate limbs? Right. Of course. Of course. And if you notice, if eagle eyed Twitter users
will notice that your Coder radio announcement, I responded with the most beloved Spider-Man.
I would say hero, not villain. The lizard. I mean, he's just misunderstood, right? I think
also a SUSE user. It's the random German in his notes that sort of throws people off. But really,
I mean, so I am not kidding at all. I am doing some a lot of SUSE stuff and it's going to and
Kevin in particular is going to be excited. So is Johan. That is legitimately the other guy's name
because of course it is. And I'm assuming a number of Hans and maybe a few Gretels. But
yeah. So get ready for the SUSE action show. And how is the experience? I know it's early days
and all, but have you lost any limbs or is it actually going OK? It has gone surprisingly
smooth. Now, that is scaring me. Right. This is something I greenlit like last week, literally
on Thursday. And, you know, I had some preliminary conversations over like the last month and
everything that was supposed to be an impediment didn't impede. Now, I don't know if it's like
because covid people are being more reasonable or if it's something bad is going to happen and
delay this whole thing. You know what I mean? But it hasn't happened yet. So I don't know. You know
how I am, Chris. I'm a little skeptical when things look too easy. But yeah, like why is it
going so good? Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait a minute. I can't get like a pizza delivered
correctly. And I'm in Florida, so there is no pizza. So like why is this working? Yep.
Or or is the answer the superior technology that I'm using now? Of course. Right.
Hashtag lizard people. Wow. So I thought we were all done with it. Just took a hard turn.
And now you're turning into a SUSE user. And I'm struggling to do what to do with that.
You know, it's just well, here's what you do. Give me six months. Then you have me on Linux
unplugged and we just listen to the groaning of your regular host. I like them just who's in the
IRC. He says Mike has committed suicide. Wow. That's good. Good stuff. I am actually legally
required to only drink German beer now, though. So there's that. Well, you could find worse,
I suppose. Well, we did get a bunch of feedback from the dark matter developers that we pleaded
with. So I picked a couple of them because a lot of them are long and detailed, like somebody who
would be a good employee would. So a non writes in, he says, Greetings from the dark matter side.
I work in the darkest of dark matter environments. It's large, very, very large U.S. company. And the
code is mostly in Java and TypeScript. Oh, interesting. And is part of an entire ecosystem
of software that exists within our part of the organization. None of that software ecosystem is
exposed to the outside world, and most things are internal to just this division of the company.
This does not mean that it is boring, though. The software has many users that need to get their
job done, and it contributes to a good experience to our end users. And I think in the end, that's
what counts. If you have any other questions about life in the dark world, though, I'd be happy to
answer them. Of course, I do have health benefits because I'm not living in the crazy U.S. So
everyone has access to health care they need here in Sweden. God damn Germans. Sorry. I know he's
a Sweden working for a large U.S. company. How about that? We get in Sweden health care.
I got to figure that out, man. I got to move to Canada or something. I got to get it. You know,
Munich is looking better every day. Also, he he wrote about Sousa. OK, so there was some Sousa
follow up. Yes. I forgot. He says the value of open Sousa is not that it's the most polished
distro out there. I'll give that a ding. Neither does it boast a especially well thought out and
opinionated user experience. These things together mean that I generally recommend open Sousa to
people that I just want to use their computer like an appliance. I set up the family and I
support it with Mint. And lately I've started moving some of them to Manjaro. I do love open
Sousa, though, because I used it quite heavily and was influenced by its governing model. And
I think it's one of the better things it has. Yeah, you know, the distro governance is like a
whole other thing about this. Talk about a lizard's nest. He says the lizards just never give up.
You'll never hear the end of the feedback to the open Sousa bashing. Oh, my God.
What have I done to myself? You know, I was between Darwin, BSD and Sousa. I was between
BSD and Sousa. What can I say? Yeah. Yeah. I guess it could have been worse. I could have gone
after the Mac. God only knows what I probably would have somebody show up at my house. Oh,
well, hang on. So he's dark matter. And didn't the TypeScript thing seem weird to you? Oh, yeah.
Thanks for remembering that. Yeah. Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's awfully modern. I wonder if you
could chime in on that. He said if we had any follow up questions, like, did you get to choose
that? That's the part I think we're really curious about is how much of the tool chain do you get to
pick versus like you're told, use this ID or use this language. So I do wonder if like DarkScript
was forced on them because of like the type checking and maybe they have some sort of way to,
I don't know, they feel the enterprise feels safer. I don't know. You know, I'm grasping
at straws for that one. Well, yeah. Boy, are you right? I mean, TypeScript, I think is it's a very
that's not conservative choice, but it's a safe choice. It is a safe choice. Runs great on SUSE.
So another Anon writes in, nobody wanted their name used. Hey, Chris and Mike,
I'm definitely on the dark matter side of the spectrum, but I've got some unique perspective.
So I figured I'd give you an insight on my job. I won't mention the company I work for,
but it is a large corporation you have definitely heard of and maybe even own products from,
but they no longer make consumer products. All right. He says my department is relatively small
in, you know, comparison to the rest of the company on the order of a few hundred employees.
And we do a small-scale TD. So you know how many employees I have? One.
So his small department, which is a couple hundred, I'm sorry, a few hundred employees,
and they do small scale government contracting, building hardware and software for them.
For the most part, the job is very corporate. I get decent insurance, average pay and great
retirement benefits and my very own cubicle all in exchange for a sane number of hours.
You may think doing development work, I spend 40 hours a week writing Java 8,
but I actually get to play with a spectrum of tools, including C and C++, Python,
TensorFlow, Docker, and JavaScript. Okay. It is not bad. He goes on to say,
as for the actual tools, read computers, it's complicated because we have many different
networks and computers for different security levels. In general, the business machines
run Windows and development machines run Ubuntu. Our Windows machines were just upgraded from
Windows 7 to Windows 10 in January. And our Ubuntu machines run the LTSs from 1404 to the latest.
Sounds like government contracted to me.
We are fully integrated with G Suite. Oh, interesting. So they use Gmail and Drive
and they use Meet and all of that stuff. Machines without internet access, we're
just upgraded from Office 2007 to 2016. That's interesting. Coronavirus changes,
he says, were also a bit of a mixed bag. Corporate didn't lay anyone off, which is awesome.
But benefits were temporarily reduced, which that's weird during a pandemic, huh?
To reduce the benefits. It's like extra mean, right? Come on.
I guess it's better than getting laid off, though. He goes on to say most of the company is still
working from home to this day, but due to the nature of our work, about 90 percent of my
department is back in the office. Personally, I'm kind of somewhere in between. Most of my work can
be done from home. But honestly, I find it so much easier to focus in my gray walled cube than at
home. Hope this gives you some valuable insights. Huh? It's that transition to working at home was
difficult for him, it sounds like. Had to go back to the office. Yeah, there's probably a bunch of
security concerns like equipment or systems that can never touch a network. I was really lucky
during the peak of the lockdown because, you know, there was a point where Washington locked down
pretty significantly and I'm the only one in the studio right now. So and I still to this day,
I mostly just go from home to the studio because I don't I don't want to get sick. I do. I do go
out more now than I used to, but it's still pretty limited. I'm still being careful and I'd never
really had to worry about staying at home per se because I just get in one box and then drive to
the next box. So I've been pretty lucky in that regard. I didn't really have to do much remote
work as it were. Yeah, I I miss an office like a lot. Yeah. You know what? Four year olds, man.
Yes. Yes. Very much so. Very much. That's you know, when I when I had kids is when I moved out
of the house and and got the studio going because I didn't want to be I didn't want to be chasing
after them to quiet down all the time because they're kids. You know, it's natural. Get off my
lawn. OK, we have one more dark matter dev that I'm going to cover today, but they all just kind
of came into the light. Well, we kind of remember what we did, right? Is we gave him a bag. Yeah,
we gave him a hard time last week. Yeah. And I actually would like it. I'm not necessarily
done with the topic. So if you have thoughts on this, if you're listening to this and want to
share your insights, please do go to Coder dot show slash contact. We'll keep it anonymous.
Don't have to say your name or the company. Speaking of that, totally anon wrote in and he's
a dark matter developer at a company that does it as a service. I'm writing him because you asked
about your nine to five guys. I work at an I.T. service company that does everything from the
help desk to outsourcing all the back end I.T. and development for our customers. That said,
I am on the sys admin side with some dev ops. I get handed what I get to use depending on the
customer I support. So I have a few laptops on my desk for each customer, along with my company
laptop that I have remote desktop applications, VMware, Horizon and Citrix to remote into the
customers who don't give me a laptop. That said, I don't really get to choose what tools I use
because everything's on the customer and in their environment. However, with some of our customers,
we have been pushing new tech like Kubernetes, but most of them only really accept OpenShift
because of Red Hat's backing. And my job is currently to manage those hosted clusters.
As for the final parts, well, we do work from home for full time now unless we need to go into
an office till the end of the year. That said, before COVID, we got to pick two days a week that
we worked from home. And because so many of the clients that we support their entire back end
networks, which is not really a lot of them, we get to use flex time. And that means when I have
to go there on off hours, I can apply that. So it's nice to have some insurance, especially when
the pandemic is going on during trying times. And it sounds like, this is me now, sounds like totally
a non-company was pretty well set up for work from home because they were letting you pick
two days a week. Yeah, I wonder what the transition would probably nothing, right?
Must have been much simpler, right? It had to have been. He goes on to say that they're kind
of just slowly going back to work at the office. And then our last bit of feedback, Mr. Dominic,
was from Oded and he wanted to follow up on a kind of a point of clarification on our Google
versus Oracle coverage last week. So he takes issue with the claim that we said where it appeared
that Google had copied some stuff line for line. What it was actually what they had copied was
something that was put in there by a different group and was just basic licensing stuff.
The version that was released publicly had all the comments and stuff removed. So it wasn't so
much that it was more of like language wording that they had copied word for word, which Google
would normally do, which kind of actually makes that Oracle argument. Well, a little flaccid.
It's one of their better claims. And it's kind of that is one that isn't particularly going to hold
up. He doesn't think he wrote in with all the details. But essentially what happened was Apache
Harmony added some stuff to the to the top of the file. Google copied that stuff. And that's what
Oracle's pointing to. So this is super weird. No, it's and it's so nuanced to really first that we
got to see him. I'm like, this guy's crazy. Let me just, you know, find the New York Times article
and look, bam, you're wrong. He is right in that it is something from Apache. What Oracle is
claiming is that by apparently, quote unquote, decompiling it and copying the comments on the
top of the file, that the comments would be copywritten because they compiled it. I mean,
it's it's like wacky. Yeah. Like, so it's weird. I mean, I have you know what? It's been a decade.
I know. Can't mom and dad stop fighting now, right? Like, oh, no. And I have to get now has
to go all the way to the Supreme Court. It's just so ridiculous. Dang it. Thank you, though,
everyone, for the feedback. Lots of good feedback. We'd like to get yours. It's a big part of our
show and helps us get going every episode. So coder dot show slash contact to send yours in
Lino dot com slash coder. Go there to get a one hundred dollars, sixty day credit towards a new
account. Linode is our cloud hosting provider of choice. I started using Linode two years ago for
J.B. and I love it. I first really started for myself personally. And then as J.B. was going to
go independent, I just began spinning up new infrastructure on Linode. Linode actually started
in 2003 as one of the very first companies in cloud computing three years before AWS,
because their Linux users and they saw the features and capabilities that were coming
to the Linux kernel and realized they could leverage that and create what we call today
the cloud. And Linode has really, really innovated over the years. Their cloud dashboard nails it.
It makes it so simple for me to spin up a machine. I think the moment, though, I was most impressed
with the cloud dashboard was when I had an existing system and I added a new disk. Not
only was that just crazy simple, if I didn't even know what these device names were or anything
like that, they had me covered. And when you do know, it's even better because there's one
click away and they give you all the advanced options that you would want as an advanced user.
And then after you create the disk, it comes up with a screen that gives you all the commands
you might want to use in the host operating system to actually attach that disk now.
Like, how do you do that, actually? Well, here are the commands and they're independently owned.
And I like that a lot. Well, you know, some companies will get VC backing and they'll go real strong
and real hard for a while. But when it's your infrastructure, when it's your systems, you want
to know what happens after that funding train runs out. Since Linode's been around since 2003
and independently owned and operated, that's not a concern with them. They're dedicated to
offering the best virtualized cloud computing. If it runs on Linux, it runs on Linode. So go to
linode.com slash coder and see what I've been talking about. Get a $100 credit for 60 days on
a new account and support this show. They have 11 data centers worldwide, enterprise grade hardware
and next generation screaming fast network connections. It's really something you can
simplify your cloud and save at the same time while supporting Coder Radio. It's a great way
to deploy your own website, maybe a portfolio and learn to. Linode.com slash coder. And a big thank
you Linode for sponsoring the Coder Radio program. And thank you to everybody who supports this show
by taking advantage of our sponsor's offer. Linode.com slash coder.
Quick recommendation on using your $100 at Linode. Chris, you know what you can do with that?
What's that?
Spend a bunch of SUSE leap servers.
They do have it on there. That's true.
They have open SUSE.
That's right. That's right. Linode.com slash coder.
All right, Mr. Dominic, you ready to move into the hoopla? Because of course.
I have been pining for this.
I you know, this is what happened, man, is they had the big event the day after our show and it
ends up there's a couple of things in there that are worth talking about. And then we got to wait
a week. So we're going to just get this out of our systems right now. Last week, Apple announced
the iPhone 12, which is a whole bunch of them, a whole zany lineup.
Who cares about that? HomePod mini go.
HomePod mini. Yeah, that's really all that matters. I am legitimately excited about this.
I will be buying at least a few of these.
Of course you will.
Now, I mean, I think this is a sleeper product that people don't appreciate. And I think the
reason is, is the price. And this is significantly cheaper. It's ninety nine dollars versus like,
what, three hundred dollars for the other HomePod, which is a total barrier.
Wait, is that still three hundred bucks?
Crazy Apple just doesn't drop their prices, dude. They never drop their prices.
That's a lot of money.
Every now and then they put them on sale through third party sellers like Best Buy.
And that's how I bought mine.
Well, then you spent twelve hundred dollars on HomePods.
No, I got one hundred dollars off on a couple of my HomePods. So.
OK.
Yeah, but these are ninety nine dollars. And I think what people fail to understand
about the HomePod is that it can execute any shortcut you create on your iPhone or your iPad.
That is tremendously powerful because they integrate with all of the apps,
all you know, all of the automations that Apple's built into iOS
can be executed from the HomePod. And that's massive.
And it has HomeKit. So in theory, and I find this hard to believe, but
you're kind of the expert on this one. If I had a shortcut that integrated with some HomeKit
devices. Right. Could I just like tell the HomePod to, you know, do that? No. Right.
All day long.
Seriously.
So if you have those like fancy Philips lights or whatever.
Oh, yeah. Yeah. And HomeKit ties in really great with the open source home assistant
software that I use. So Siri has become my voice assistant for my own locally self-hosted
home assistant instance through HomeKit. And I can automate things using HomeKit.
And it's fast because it's all on the LAN. And the other thing about the HomePod specifically is
it, I believe, has the best microphones of the bunch. And a lot of times these smart
assistants kind of fall down when you have a fan going and it creates white noise,
or maybe your TV is too loud. Out of all of the home assistants that I have tested,
HomePod breaks through the noise the most often. And she understands you well. Like it's cliche
to give Siri a hard time. But when you're using her in a HomeKit capacity, it's just,
hey phone, hey slow mo, turn on lamp, turn on heater. And it just it does it immediately.
Plus, it sounds the best. So if you're in the iOS ecosystem, which is the big caveat,
I think why it doesn't get as much love as it should. It just is brilliant. It shows
up in your AirPlay list of devices. You can manage it as an AirPlay device. That brings
it into the realm of home theater. Because if you have an Apple TV, the Apple TV and the HomePods
are aware of their general locations. And they will treat the HomePods, if like they're behind
you, as rear speakers. And so the way it automatically works at my place is the sound bar
becomes our vocals, our center channel. And then the HomePods become the surround sound system.
Automatically, without me ever telling it to, I just, in the AirPlay menu, checked the HomePods
and their pairs, right? And they automatically figure out which side's left and which side's
right. Well, you tell them that. But once you tell them that, they automatically figure out who's
supposed to do what load. And so you get terrific sound. You get a surround sound environment that
is completely wireless, which is fantastic for me because I can't run wires in my current condition
certain situation. And on top of that, you get all of the power of any shortcut you can
fancy and any device that supports HomeKit. And oh, if you're crazy enough to go all the way into
open source Home Assistant, it's also the best voice assistant with that as well. And it's a
good speaker just to listen to podcasts or music on. And these minis come in now at $99. Well,
think about how you could use that in a surround sound environment. How easily it would be to maybe
put one near your couch and fill out a little bit of the sound there. Or maybe, you know, put one on
the counter where I'm at and I hear a little bit of sound coming from that. So I'm really excited
about how not only could I get more voice automation in places where I couldn't afford to
put a Home Assistant before, but also I can fill out my existing system a little bit better, which
I also think is going to be great because they just work together so easily. Damn, I might have
to get one. I mean, they sound great, too. And I don't know about the minis. Well, at $99, it's
like even if it doesn't work out right. Yeah. Yeah, I get that it's funny at, you know, $300.
And of course, you have to have an iPhone or an iPad or an Apple TV to make it worth it. So I get
it right, especially for Android users or people that are deep into the Google ecosystem. It's
silly. But man, there's a lot of iPhone users out there. I'm not trying to shill for Apple here.
I would love for this to be made by anybody. Anybody who made a product like this sounds good,
easy to pair, excellent home automation assistant that ties in with my self-hosted local home
automation system. And it all works over the land. So when I'm off grid in my RV, I still can use
the home pods. I don't have to have Google intermediary and a proxy connection to send
audio or video. It's all over the land. I mean, it's just there's a lot of advantages there that
people don't consider because, you know, really, I think I think Amazon has stolen the mindspace
here. They've really kind of nailed it because they've executed just consistently on the Alexa
product. But, you know, I literally try these things side by side. And I think you can you
could confidently say you can do more with an echo. But the core things I care about the home
pod is just focused on like three things. And it does those really well. It's very Apple style,
I suppose. So would you recommend for like a home pod version just to go with the fancy one?
Or I don't know. You know, I'm not sure. I kind of think maybe not. I think I would buy two of the
minis than one. Oh, they can do the thing where they talk to each other and like, oh, it's not
quite as sophisticated yet as the big pods. Right. But there is they can at least stereo pair up.
So you still you get two home pod minis and you're still not even at the price of one home pod.
And the only thing that I noticed that Apple did is they called this the home pod family.
Now, which I don't know. It might suggest there's some more coming. And I find it fascinating that
they're cramming decent CPUs into these tiny little things like this thing has the S5 chip.
What do you make of yourself? I mean, yeah, but I think it makes it. I think it matters
having a faster CPU in the system. I think it I think it matters. Do you have any thoughts on the
on the other stuff that they announced? Like the I mean, they've got like a whole smattering
of iPhones now. Buckle up. Let's talk about 5G for a moment. All right. I was a little surprised.
I have the blatant Verizon commercial at the beginning of the I guess, you know, we still
call them Kinos, I guess. Yeah, I sort of don't understand why they're pushing the 5G thing so
hard, given that unless you live in like literally New York and San Francisco and some other
metropolitan areas, you probably don't even have good LTE. Yeah. And you're not going to have a
good 5G. And it's not like you're not going to have it for like six months. Yeah. I mean, let's say
I know people like the first cash is saying like a year, I would say, especially if you're like out
down here in Florida, it's like five years. And also, you may not always want 5G, right?
Because you know, more power drain. That's why they had to make a point to say that John's 5G
and Jim's 5G might not be the same, which I think is always amazing that the telcos get away with
that. I mean, maybe it's just me, but did it strike you as weird that they were talking so much
about a network that basically doesn't exist? Yeah. And and especially in the United States,
and especially given in the past, they've never really made much fuss except for the iPhone 3G,
which is going quite a ways back to see Apple make a fuss about the radio technology.
I think there's a couple of things at play here. I think it's good to signal that
Apple is leading here from their position, from a strategic position.
They're often not the first to market in a compelling form factor with stuff.
Usually it's Samsung, right? If you're gonna look at the mobile market, they're pretty aggressive.
But in this case, Apple feels like they're really right there with the rest of the industry,
maybe even a little bit on the leading edge when you look at the Qualcomm modem that they're
shipping and the form factor and battery life that they're claiming you'll get.
I think another factor in the focus is that they worked out a deal with the carriers to take 30
bucks off the phone. And additionally, they appeared to work out a deal with Verizon to
actually hold the announcement of the launch of their nationwide 5G network until Apple's keynote.
Imagine the business arrangement there, man. Think about that. Think about what a product
launch that is for Verizon. Somehow Apple talked them into waiting to make the announcement until
their keynote. I mean, that's quite the deal. So that had to play a factor too.
From a technology standpoint, I actually am kind of excited about it,
even though it's not widely deployed yet. Number one, mobile data is a big deal for me. It's one
of the number one expenses in my monthly expenses. Seriously, it's mobile data. I have multiple
carriers, and I don't mean to, and I really follow this industry very, very closely.
I can say with some surprise that the iPhone 12 has one of the most advanced cellular modems
we've ever seen in the market. It literally supports almost every LTE band in existence
today, which is extremely rare. And it means really good LTE support. Additionally, it has
a four by four antenna so it can make four simultaneous connections to the cell tower,
which is incredible. And then additionally, it happens to have 5G and it currently supports
every standard of 5G that exists today. So one iPhone for all carriers. It's just one iPhone now.
And they've got that screaming Qualcomm chip in there. So from a purely cellular data and band
support standpoint, for mobile workers, this is a killer phone. And the mobile router support,
the tethering support, the Wi-Fi tethering support in the iPhone, it's pretty good.
It makes a pretty damn good little mobile router. And so I will likely pick one up
just for its LTE band support and then use the 5G when I happen to be in an area that has it.
And I'm not even expecting that 5G to be significantly fast. I think this is
the biggest misread about 5G and maybe the thing that kind of annoys me the most. I could get 100
megabits on LTE if I have the right modem and a good signal. I can get 100 megabits. I've got
I got a spot out in the woods where I get 90 megabits on LTE. It's crazy. It's like utopia.
Now, 5G probably not going to get me any better than that. But what it will get me that really
matters for my industry is lower latency. And that's what Apple really focused on. They focused
on gaming. They focused on medical record transfer and and video applications where latency is
extremely important. And the goal with 5G is to eventually get the latency as good as it could be
for a home connection. And I don't care what you say, but that's going to make a transformational
difference on the Internet, just like bringing up bandwidth to the home, brought in streaming video
and all of that. Improved latency will get us real time video communication. So what you and I are
doing will get as good as a phone call or even better, better actually. And maybe if they get
there and if they get if they never get the speeds up beyond what you could get in a good LTE
situation now, but get the latency down, I would happily use that. And this phone is going to get
me the closest to that that anything possibly can on the market today in a form factor that I'm
actually going to want to use. That all makes sense. Actually, I spoiler alert. I, of course,
ordered one because I mean you did. So you must have gotten the 12 pro or 12 then because the
other ones aren't even available yet. I think I got the blue one. Yeah. OK, good. That's what I
think I would get to. I like that. I guess like you have painted a world where like we're all
dancing with Taylor Swift and things are great and we're streaming it right. But I see a world
where every time I, you know, in the before time, somebody used to travel all the time within three
days of being on a trip, rising like Haza, you're on the limited plan. It is unlimited. Enjoy the
fifty six K. Oh yeah. So like if like I could give them virtually any amount of money and they
would like give me real unlimited help, even for even LTE, like you're saying, right? I think that
would be awesome. Yeah, but I'm pretty sure based on decades of history here that they're not going
to do that. Right. Even for like a stupid amount of money that they're going to be like, it's
really fast. You have low latency, very little ping, Haza. And as soon as you finish streaming
one one episode of The Simpsons or whatever the hell you're watching or stream one episode of
the next action show, you are done. Yes. Yeah. So I guess like, do you do you see like a cultural
shift on the telcos where they might like not do that? I hope. I mean, they have to. Right. They're
like Verizon is talking about when you get their millimeter wave connection, they're talking about
a gigabit connection. But the plan allows for 20 gigabytes total. Well, right. So like, literally,
you're not going to make it. No, it's it's ridiculous on its face. And this is one of the
reasons why I have multiple cellular connections in Lady Jupes. I was on a trip just recently,
and AT&T cut me off. I have I had a grandfathered iPad plan that was supposed to be truly unlimited,
but I used 500 gigs on the road and they cut me off. I had one of those. They don't like it when
you tether the items. They just shut it down completely. No, nothing. Just boom, you're you're
you're done, man. You're you're that you're over. And so, yeah, I end up paying for multiple so I
can spread it out. I have different carriers from in different areas. And it's such a shit show. I
hope I look back at this in 10 years and go, oh, man, that was sure the bad old days of mobile
connectivity. All right. If I could even pay like three X what I pay for the businesses wireless.
Right. But it was like truly unlimited. You just can't do it. No, they will. They will not sell you
that. Yeah. If you're like in the CIA or the FBI, they have a special plan they'll give you. Right.
But yeah, you're out. And I know people listening and think this is crazy. When the world is not
ending, go to your local Verizon store and ask for the business rep. Tell him you would or her
you would like to buy the highest enterprise plan that they can sell you. But you want
truly unlimited data with no throttling. You will be asked to leave. One of the carriers is working
has a plan now for quote unquote business users. It's prohibitively expensive. It's quote unquote
unlimited. But you're only allowed to do things like Zoom, email and VPN. Yes. No tethering.
That's my favorite trick. Yeah. And if you do anything outside of that, they reserve the right
to immediately shut down your account. Now, of course, you could VPN it up and maybe, you know,
they'd never know what you're using this line for. But you're always skirting around the policies
and rules. And if they ever did get insights into what you're doing, they could immediately shut
your account down. And that's how you get quote unquote unlimited. But even that is got some,
you know, asterix next to it. So that has to shift. I don't know if you know one thing that
could actually happen is Starlink could come along. Elon could offer something on the market
that is competitive and then the carriers have to respond. Is it bad that I kind of believe in Elon
more than, you know, the government regulating this or fixing it? That's how I feel. That's really
that's truly how I feel. And they've just the carriers have made such a mess of this that it
does make it hard to be enthusiastic. They want us to be excited about the 5G. And I think that's why
it stood out to you so much. I think there's technical advantages by having a modem capable
of it. Oh, I love the tech. Just the policy doesn't work. So funny story, because I'm not
really in a position just to be dropping a lot of cash. But before the pandemic lockdowns hit,
I ordered a super high grade industrial grade cellular modem router kit for my RV that is used
on trains and buses. It's professional gear that you just can't buy. You have to buy it from a
special reseller and all that kind of stuff. And it includes a seven in one antenna that you mount
on the roof and you wire it into this thing. And it's really cool. And it has four SIM slots,
two modems active at the same time. And then it can use a special VPN technology to bond the
carriers together into a single stable connection. And then you run a hosted component on the other
end or use their service. And that's where your traffic comes out. And so like I would run one
on Linode. I ordered that and it's like $1,200, right? But I ordered it back in March when I was
still employed. And so the pandemic lockdowns came and all the shipments from China shut down.
And I got an email saying, hey, your thing's going to be delayed. They told me if I order now
and they'll just include the shipping for free and all that and go ahead and charge it. And I
thought, this is a bad idea, but I'm going to do it. And so I said, go ahead, place the order because
I really want this equipment. My kids are doing school from home and the connection is not reliable
enough when they're all three on school calls and whatnot. And so this is the year I'm going to
invest in this for real. So go ahead and charge it. And then, of course, the lockdowns come and
it doesn't ship and it doesn't ship and it doesn't ship. So in August, I emailed the guy and I'm
like, so did I just get scammed here? What's going on? And he tells me, no, no, it's all due to the
lockdown. It should be shipping in September. It'll be fine. And so I'm sitting there pontificating
on if I should just cancel this thing because I just been scammed and go to my credit card and ask
them if they can reverse the charge. But I found another seller. And so I emailed him. I said,
what's the status? And he gave me the same exact story that it's all shut down, but they should be
shipping in September. And so if you'd like to place your order now, you can. I thought, well,
OK, so maybe that's really what's going on. So I don't cancel the original order. September goes
by. I never get it. October comes. I get an update. It should be shipping any day now.
October 15th comes. Nothing. October 16th arrives and I get an email saying that the the entire
setup with all of its modems and its antennas and it's all this stuff is all going to arrive
on the 20th. Oh, wow. And this whole thing, you know, is all based on LTE. None of it is 5G because
I just I'm not investing in 5G right now. It's ridiculous. It's all going to be LTE for years.
And what I hope is that people will move off the LTE network and move over to 5G. So everybody go
buy your iPhone 12s and get off my LTE network. Just free it up for me. I want all the spectrum
I can get. So I'm you know, I've got this industrial grade LTE kit now that's coming.
I've got to drill holes in my ceiling and all kinds of stuff. My God, I know it's going to be
massive, but when I'm done, I should have the most reliable LTE connection humanly possible.
You know, you could do like a testing rig, you know, just like drive around the country. All
right. Well, I'm locking the bandwidth here. Yeah. And so it's got four SIM slots, but only
two of the modems are active. So I'm going to have an AT&T and a Verizon and then a Google
Fi and a Ting as my backups. And yeah, I mean, I'm serious about it. It is it's a it's a massive
issue for me because my entire job is online. Everything I do is online. The way I communicate
with everybody in the team, everything is online. And so I'm going to have to do a lot of
online. And so and then you have the kids with their schooling and then my wife, any client she
does have, most of them are virtual and those are video calls. She can she can switch over to
LTE on her phone, but it'd be nice if the Wi-Fi was reliable. So, yeah, that's a thing. Sounds
awesome. Should make working from home a little bit better, although maybe maybe if you're a
Dropbox employee, you'll want some of these tips because it looks like Dropbox is letting all
employees work from home permanently with like kind of a we work style where some folks will
come in during the week and they'll work together and they'll have like a collab space where they
can give each other the Rona and then they go back home and infect their families.
I am relatively sure that the group email that announced this, that was not the pitch.
I feel like, you know, the head of engineering or whatever, the CEO was like,
here's the plan, folks, you're going to work from home. Everybody's like, yay.
Then once a month you come in, you get COVID, you spread it to all your family. Wait, what?
It's like what we talked about, though, what they're trying to get to is the best of both worlds,
where you still get the in-person collaboration and sustain the company culture. Because I have
witnessed that working for clients in various capacities. I've noticed that all remote companies,
they they front like they have a culture, but it doesn't actually exist. All the people behind the
other ends of the screens are all kind of lonely and disgruntled. And I say this totally just on
observation. It's not any kind of... Are you talking about me specifically now?
No, I've noticed this with several companies I've worked with. And you quickly get in a situation
where you have the like the management layer is preaching to you what the culture is constantly
and they're constantly telling you what the culture is, but it's not real. It's just...
It's a fancy blog post. Yeah. Where you actually come into an office space and you're working with
multiple people and the kind of ideology and culture of the office is generally represented
in the workspace. And you see that, you get that human connection, that high bandwidth exchange,
and you get your feels out, all that kind of stuff. And I think you then send people off and
they go be productive for a few days from home. Sort of like one of our dark matter developers who
got to work a couple of days at home and then come into the office. That's, I think, the perfect
balance. I think it's very funny that you put this in the show notes. I am reopening our space
in Plant City. Yeah, right. I thought I heard you mention that. I think you mentioned it to me on
Slack maybe. Yeah, in Slack. It is related to my magical SUSE thing I'm doing. Don't want to say
much about it now, but yeah, instead of having a large space, this is exactly what we're doing,
right? Like, you know, kicking off projects. We have a lot of weird hardware integration work
that came in, so that stuff you kind of have to do there. But not trying to really do this
until the Rona's over, which, God willing, will be soon. May never. Well, geez. Listen,
every time I listen to Unfilter, I cry a little bit. So let's just move right along. But hopefully
it ends. And yeah, this is the idea. Small spaces, you know, we operate in two states,
so maybe one in New Jersey soon. But yeah, it's, I don't even know what to say.
I, it's weird. I love remote work for like heads down coding. Right. But when it's stuff like,
oh, I have to ups you this custom board back and forth. And oh, the kid at the UPS store,
like spilled his tea in it. Let's be honest. It wasn't the kid at the UPS store, but moving right
along. It's kind of inefficient. So can I fry some bacon? Oh, you know, I've always got a little
right here. You want me to throw it on the old griddle? Go ahead. So this is bacon from Japan.
Curtis, courtesy of that rich guy who invested in WeWork, whose name just literally evacuated my
brain. I really don't remember anymore. It's Wagyu bacon. Wagyu bacon. I'm pretty sure this is going
to bail WeWork out. Well, I think you'll have a lot of corporations just convert their offices
into WeWork like spaces, but then you'll have others that are looking to fill in gaps and
whatnot in like areas. Yeah. I mean, obviously, like if you want WeWork, but for adults, there's
Regis, which I use. But yeah, I, I, I'm a little mixed on this whole concept because then you're
taking a lease. Like, to be clear, our space plan city is like a traditional lease. That's why I
still have it. And you're not using it all the time. Doesn't that feel kind of wasteful, Chris,
as like an entrepreneur? Oh, yeah. 100%. It's, I mean, the studio is, it makes the production
of these shows so much more consistent and straightforward, but yet I still look at that
expense and go, hmm, could always just do it from home. But what I have right now is kind of a
balance. Some days I work from home, the days I'm not on air, I might, I might come to the studio.
I might not. I kind of break it up depending on the project work that I'm doing. And I like having
that flexibility. I basically have kind of cemented my idea that it's worth the business having the
space. But when times are tough, you look at it and you go, gosh, you know, I could, I could make
that back because it's not just the rent, it's the services and the utilities you have running here
too. And maybe insurance and you know, it ends up, it ends up being a pretty decent expense.
Yeah. Let's see, let's see how long I last for doing this. Although the peace and quiet,
especially for recording has to be just, yeah. Well, except for sometimes I have airplanes going
overhead. So you never know. It's never, sometimes I'm in Florida and there's like lightning
everywhere. So yeah, I think it's a good mix though. I think maybe wouldn't that be interesting
if we had a bunch of companies that didn't land on everybody works from home, but what they land
on. And I think what we're kind of seeing happen is a lot more flexibility because now the
infrastructure had been put in place, the tooling has been put in place, except for the companies
that really screwed it up. They're going to be in a position now where they could, where they
could do that. Plus he thinks like it wouldn't save them money. Having people not in the office
saves money. It makes it harder to watch what they're doing every single day, but there's tools
to compensate for that. Well, I think you need less space, right? Isn't that kind of the. Yeah.
And less power, less snacks, less things in the fridge, you know, like seriously,
the only downside is I have seen some companies that are getting a little Snoopy. Like they want
to up the surveillance software that runs on your company machines. So they have more confidence
that you're being productive during the day. I don't think that's a good trend. I don't like
that. And, um, there is a company out there that shopping to tech podcasters right now about, uh,
selling a service that helps you monitor your employees that are working from home.
Do their checks clear? I mean, no, no, of course not. Yeah. Yeah. Well now let me tell you about
now actually, you know what? Let me thank, uh, the coder QA folks. Uh, if you'd like to be a member,
uh, coder QA helps us stay independent. It helps us be choosy about the sponsors,
coder QA.com. Uh, the first coderly report is out as well for our members. You can get that
in the feed or as an individual download, you support the show and you also get a limited ad
feed of the show. Plus that coder quarterly report coder QA.co that's coder QA.co to sign up and
support the show. Why not? Uh, why not buy your buddies here at coder radio, a holiday gift that
revenue goes towards paying for editing, producing all of that. That is a, it's a business cost and
we'd like to make it sustainable. So that way we have a varying load of sponsors from time to time,
but the basics of the show are still covered at coder QA.co and thanks to everybody who does
support the show over there. Now, Mike, last week we teased about this a little bit, but I think we
got a few more minutes. We could get this in. Uh, and you recently had an adventure in Vinland
and I also had a new editor that I've been trying out that I wanted to mention, but
what's going on? What's going on with you and Vim? So because I am picky and the fonts were not
rendering at what I perceived as the right size in gnome three, thank you gnome. Um, I decided to
try out Vim again. I then like all Vim users spent way too long configuring my Vim IRC. Yes. You gotta
get the colors just right. I have been doing this for two weeks. I think this is going to be my last
week. So this is a very brief segment. Okay. Here's the good on Linux. Nothing renders that
better than the terminal. Visually it's beautiful. It's a great flex. You know, it looks nice. Um,
I probably will actually turn on Vim key bindings and Ruby mine then pie charm now,
but damn, is it a pain in the butt? For instance, I had to open my Mac and I'm like, ah, let me just,
you know, pull down my Vim RC, which is in a gist. Well, for some reason that I don't understand,
it simply does not work on Mac terminal. There's the plugins are not installing, right?
And it's very annoying. I really wanted to love this. I do not. So how's your editor?
That's not what I expected at all. I was all sitting here. Oh my God. I was expecting this
whole love letter. Okay. All right. Well, let me introduce you to something simpler.
It's called micro a modern and intuitive terminal based text editor. That's simple. Lightweight
has easy to use features compatibility with key bindings from Vim or nano highly customizable.
If you want to go down that route, even a plugin system, if you want support 75 languages,
seven default color schemes to choose from. It supports true color schemes as well.
And of course, syntax color schemes are very simple to make if you want to make your own.
And if you want an editor on the console that can also do the multi pain thing where you can have
side pains and two pains and all the quad pains, it'll do all of that. I'm not talking about the
West pains. I'm talking about the view pains. And, um, it, um, what did I say? Mouth support
has mouth support. So, you know, if that's your thing too on the terminal, it has that.
Now you're just rubbing it in. It's like a nano alternative that's a little more powerful. It was
recommended to me on Linux unplugged by a listener and, uh, I installed it and I love it. I mean,
I still love my nano. You know, it's, I kind of joke a little bit, but I'm, I'm serious too in
that, um, I want, I want easy and wait, hang on. You actually like nano. Yeah. You know, I mean,
I, I can use Vim. I taught myself Vim because it's on literally every system. And that,
that was a concept that actually mattered back in the day when you had to install everything with
RPMs like an animal. But today it's so easy to install software and most systems ship with
multiple editors installed. I think it's a little bit of dogma that maybe is more myth than it is
truth. And everything is, has nano. It's easy to get nano or Pico on just about anything. And it's
such a nice, simple, everything is there. All the commands are at the bottom. It's just, uh, no
surprises, no complexity. I'm into the file. I'm out of the file. There's just a simplicity and
quickness to it that I really appreciate. And if I'm looking for something that's more advanced,
like I'm, I'm editing the sudoers file, I might use Vim or visudo. But if I'm just editing my
Samba config or something like, you know, a basic file on my file system, I just use nano. If I'm
not using VS code to begin with, I'll just use nano. In, out, easy, quick, simple keybinds.
And now I've started using micro more and more. And I get that I'm not leet and I feel bad that,
you know, I'm not leet when I say that and that I'm not, you know, cool hacker, bro. But
I just don't care. I just like the simplicity of it. That's my confession to you. And, uh,
I leave myself open to your judgment. I bet it works great on Azusa.
Oh, all right. Okay. Okay. All right. Well, I'll put a link to micro in the show notes.
If anybody's interested, go check out Mike on Twitter. So that way you're first to know when
something is spilled on a machine or how the lizard adventures are going. He's at Dumanoku on
Twitter. I'm at Chris last. Anything else you want to mention, Mr. Dominic, before we get out of
here? No, no. Uh, get ready for more Susan news. I think I'm going to have a drink before the next
episode. We also would love your feedback, especially from you dark matter developers.
Anybody else that wants to get a thought into the show that's coder.show slash contact links
for the things we talked about today. Coder.show slash three eight four. It's really simple.
And I encourage you to subscribe to the show. That's Coder.show slash subscribe. You get the
RSS feed or just get the Jupiter broadcasting all shows feed. Thanks for joining us on this
episode of the Coder Radio program, and we'll see you right back here next week.