This is KOTOR Radio, episode 475 for July 18th, 2022.
Oh, hey there, good buddy. Welcome into Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show, taking a
pragmatic look at the art and the business, the software development, and the world of
technology.
My name is Chris, and joining us right there from his tactical podcasting station, it's
our host, Mr. Dominic. Hello, Mike.
Mama Mia. There's a put in a lean on the castle because I keep losing the princess.
You know, eventually, you gotta take some responsibility there. Like, you just put some
security in.
Who do I got to help me? An imaginary mushroom in my brother who says he sees ghosts everywhere.
I'm all alone, and Bowser breathes the fire. Like a pepper.
Just to mention, not to mention, you're constantly out there breaking bricks with your bare hands,
so I can imagine.
Yes, like Apollo, like my Madam Vin Diesel.
I've had a really good week, you know, and I think it's all thanks to your Twitter feed.
I have no recollection. Madam Senator, I don't know.
No, it's really, it's positive. You know, so here I am the other day. In fact, I just
sort of, I captured this and I thought, let's share it on the show because it's just so
great. So a tweet comes out from Mr. Dominic on July 15th at 10 a.m. and it just says simply,
living more or less purely in desktop Linux these days. I'm finding a lot to love, but
do wish the community didn't have to rely so heavily on electron.
And you know, you mentioned elementary OS a little bit there. I thought, oh, this is
great. He's having a great time with Linux.
So I thought, I'll just check in now this morning just to see how things are going.
So I'm sure you've tweeted later. Oh yeah. In fact, the very next tweet on July 15th
at 6 p.m. in the evening, it looks like you're buying a MacBook Pro the very same day. The
day you tweet about how great desktop Linux is, a mere half a day later, you buy a MacBook
Pro.
On the advice of my attorney, I respectfully decline to answer this question as it may
very obviously incriminate me.
So you're supposed to get it tomorrow too.
I already got it. In fact, they screwed up my weekend plans because FedEx was like, yo
dawg, you need to be here to sign for this and we'll be there in three hours. Ding, ding.
There was less than eight hours between the two tweets. What happened in that eight hours?
Well, we can blame Nilay Patel for this one.
Oh, I always do. Was it the beard or what was it?
It was the Verge's posting about a sale on that specific MacBook Pro. And me, I don't
want to dunk too hard on the good folks at Ionic, but their deployment tools, their cloud
deployment solution is not very good. And I had to hand me down my MacBook Air. So I
was like, hmm, now I won't use the iMac out of Pure. Just you're disgusting.
Oh, you're so shameful.
Intel. Oh, oh, yeah, but this is an M1. You didn't go for the M2.
Well, if you look at it, so that's a great point. But if you look at the M2, the M1,
it's really not worth it for what I'm doing. I did, however, this is actually the largest
laptop I've ever purchased for myself.
Yeah, it's 16 inches, it's a big lunch tray.
It's a big boy. It's big and dark and speaking for a pre-show topic.
Beautiful. It's just beautiful.
You know what? Space gray is beautiful.
I have the 16 inch as well with the max CPU in there. And I still don't feel like I've
ever put that thing to its maximum. So I'm sure as far as workload goes, the M1 is fine.
I'm just surprised you weren't drawn, tempted by the maybe the new M2 Air or something like
that.
I was tempted, but I was dissuaded by the price and the 250 bucks off of this was tempting.
Also the screen, I wanted to hear what the hype was about this whatever blah, blah, blah
fancy fancy screen.
Yeah, right. It's got that XDR or whatever laptop display.
It's pretty. It's very nice. So I have not completely betrayed Linux, but doing a little
havesy havesies here.
Yeah. You spend some time with your Linux family, then you sneak off on the weekends
and go spend time with your Mac family.
Well, like every good Republican congressman, I get to the airport, I tap my foot a couple
of times. If you get that joke, you've been listening to a lot of unfiltered several years
ago, like a lot. Or you happen to be a Republican congressman who goes to the airport quite
a bit.
Deep ref. So Richard writes in because he's struggling to with a similar problem only
on the other side of the fence. He says, I recently bought a gaming laptop with a GeForce
RTX 3080 TI to do machine and deep learnings. It came with Windows 11, which means I also
have WSLG. That's WSL with graphical apps. And it was really simple, I got to say, to
get Ubuntu 2204 set up a couple of commands. And I have Firefox and Chrome with audio.
NVIDIA has special instructions for CUDA pass through back to Windows. And I have TensorFlow
set up with the Jupyter Notebooks and the JupyterLab working.
I'm thinking of all of this as I hear you review the HP Dev1 laptop running Linux.
And I wonder if a Windows 11 machine would be a sufficient, if not even better Linux
machine for most people. Not for a Chris type that uses specialized avian podcasting software,
but maybe for like Mike's hypothetical web developer type running Git, Node, Python and
other software in WSL and not ever having to worry about driver issues. Even more so
for a developer at large, maybe a developer in the enterprise where everyone runs the
Microsoft suite of Office and Team Software. I'm even writing this in Linux and Chrome
running under WSL.
So do you think a Windows 11 machine is a viable alternative for devs that need Linux
software?
Yeah, right. I mean, I think we've talked about this before. You know, we're in such
a state with the three major, the three families of the, you know, the major families of desktop
operating systems that they're all good now, right? Mac is good. Mac, if you never want
to charge it and it has infinite battery life and it's beautiful, it's good. Linux, if you
want customability and to have your dev machine very much match your servers in a very likely
way, great. Windows, if you have to do some.NET and do a booting, it's a pain in the
ass.
And I, you know, we could do a couple of shows on WSL and WSL too. It's really good. Like
I know everybody likes to make fun of Windows and the fact that the registry still exists
is terrible, but Windows 11 is fine. Not my cup of tea, but that's purely down to reference.
That's what it's getting to. It's getting to what environment works better for you?
What tooling works better with your workflow? And undoubtedly, probably should have said
this first, what do you have the most experience with? What are you the most comfortable with?
What it means is whatever your answer is to those things, there's just less and less downside
now to whichever one you choose. And it also kind of means all the silly religious wars
that were fought over desktop operating systems in the past have essentially been made irrelevant
as they've all just sort of normalized. Thanks web technology and Linux. And you know, for
some of us, that experience is Linux desktop. Some of it's the Mac, some of it's Windows
and sometimes it's all of them.
Some of us, you know, we swing based on who's the highest bidder that night.
Yeah. Neo Vim's got a big buddy in Aden. He writes in, I don't think Neo Vim gets enough
love. I don't think Vim would be making the changes it is today if Neo Vim hadn't come
along. Why Neo Vim? Well, they cleaned up the code base. It's larger and more distributed
development team is definitely better and it has better defaults and abilities for modern
systems. And now that Vim script nine is out, I'd be interested in your take on the rewriting
of the Vim script engine versus just using Lua await, which is the direction Neo Vim
took. I prefer the Lua choice as it's more widely applicable than Vim script and is going
to have a wider development base in the longterm for the language itself. He's getting deep
into the Vim ecosystem here.
Yeah, that's that's good. I mean, I have not personally ever used Neo Vim in any significant
way. I think I installed it like twice, but yeah, you're probably right that competition,
right? The thing we don't have in American, the telco, for example, makes everybody better.
So Neo Vim comes out, Vim gets better.
Yeah. Yeah. That sort of was my take too. It's like, yeah, it makes sense. I'm not super
passionate about this topic. Don't have many thoughts on it, but the logic checks out.
Can I take a side, but related tangent here?
You know, those are my favorite.
You know, I decided to tweet that I was interested in looking at Zed. And thank you guys for
all the invite codes, but I only needed one. Still, thank you. And you know what? I feel
like I was concerned that VSCode was going to just butcher the editor field for a while.
I don't know. Zed's pretty cool. I've been trying it out for a couple of days. It's a,
it's definite. One, it feels snappy as hell, probably because it's written in Rust. And
it reminds me a lot of maybe a potential Tex-Mate successor, which I'm not sure if that's what
they're really going for or not. But I'm sorry, I mean Tex-Mate 2. Yes. Don't yell at me.
I don't know. Does anybody who listens to the show actually know what Tex-Mate was?
No? I'm old? Okay, great. In the eight days of the leopard and the snow leopard, it was
the de facto developer editor on Mac. In fact, I'm pretty sure most editors were using Tex-Mate
themes. They just write in packages for a very long time. Yeah. Yeah, Monodevelop used
to. That's a whole different era, man. That was a different time. And you paid 70 bucks
for that, baby. Yeah, you did. And you did it happily. Gary's got a lead that will take
no questions, as my lead only knows one set of rules, and those are the US Air Force rules.
I like to ask why a project of ours was denied or maybe why I'm filling out a spreadsheet
that's listing our commits for the third time. He hates questions. He's a no questions kind
of guy. Just do what I say. Any tips or resources for working with a no questions allowed development
lead? Ooh, that's rough. Yeah, that just sucks, dude. Also, why do you have a spreadsheet
of your commits? Because that's maybe how the lead likes to review them. I don't know.
I mean, git log, it's right. There's nothing worse than when you're taking information
out of one system and just transposing it to another system just so a lead can review
it. Frustrating. Also, if you just like Gary, go on my GitHub. It's just Dominic M like
everything else is except for my Twitter, which is weird. But I have a little terminal
script. It's called Get Pretty Print. Your manager might love it. He may be happy, but
your lead might love it. I don't know. I mean, I've met guys like this. I don't tend to love
working with them because in kind of cray cray, I used to know a guy who would count
the number of commits. So you every and the developers learned real quick. Here's what
you do. One file, one commit every time. Oh, God. Yep. So yeah, that's uh, I don't know,
Gary, you gotta you gotta roll with the punches and maybe see if you can, you know, maybe
it's time for a change. Yeah, I was thinking that he said Air Force and I thought maybe
he can't just easily change. That could be tricky. Right. He might be in. Yeah. Mm hmm.
Mm hmm. I wonder. Keep us posted. Let us know how that goes and what your choices are. And
if anybody has any tips, feel free to boost them in or email them into coder dot show
slash contact. Gosh, that's a bad situation where you got a bad lead and you're kind of
stuck there. I feel for you. Now, speaking of being stuck somewhere, if you're stuck
in London, what I did there, the London meetup is nigh six p.m. local time, August 5th, Jupiter
broadcasting dot com slash meetup for details on that. Alex from self hosted will be there.
There's already one hundred and four attendees on the meetup. It's going to be outdoors.
So that way there's fresh air. That's going to be a hell of an event. I hear Boris Johnson
is coming. So that's going to be a freaking rager. Yeah, he's got a little more free time
now. So he's going to show up. But still, just as much vodka as you'd expect. Now we
do have the initial dates up for our West Coast tour that's coming up. Linode is making
it possible for JB to go down and do a West Coast road tour and get a very special tour
of the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena. And we'll do a series of meetups in southern
Oregon, in Sacramento, in southern California and in Portland. And those will be although
I don't see the Portland one on there yet. Those meetups are all getting listed at meetup
dot com slash Jupiter broadcasting. And we'd love to we'd love to meet up with you. There
it is. There's the Portland meetup. So we'll have them all there just so you know the dates
just in case you're in the area. We're going to be in southern Oregon on the 20th of September.
These are all September. We'll be in Sacramento on the 23rd and we'll be in the Pasadena area
on the 30th and then we'll be in Portland on October 7th on our way back up. So if you
are on anywhere near those places, do come out and say hi to us. It's it's it's a who
knows who knows how many opportunities we'll have like this. And so it's a great chance.
We also have a matrix group, a West Coast crew matrix group set up where you can chat
with us, get details, coordinate with other people in your area. I'll have a link to the
matrix room for that in the show notes, as well as a link to the meetup page in the show
notes. But if you're in the West Coast area, come out and say holler, come say hi to us.
Maybe we'll have like a cardboard cut out of you, Mike. You know, you're just like standing
there next to me with a big smile or maybe like in your robe with a cigar and a martini,
just like a cardboard cut out version of you. Yeah, that would work. I mean, why don't we
all put our oculus is on and I can just be there. I think that's probably a good plan.
Although I'm not sure the martini glass and the oculus are going to work well together.
Smack, smack, clink, clink. There's only one way to find out above an open laptop, of course.
Too soon, man. Too soon. Linode dot com slash coder. Go there to get one hundred dollars
and 60 day credit on a new account. And it's a great way to support the show while you
get to try something great out. Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting. Should try it
for your next project, maybe the next thing you're building or the next thing you want
to learn about, especially now that Linode has Kali Linux as a deployment option in their
marketplace. It makes it super quick to try something like Kali out and learn a little
bit about cybersecurity, but also test your own systems. It's a real legitimate tool.
I love the upgrades that I have seen land over at Linode over the last couple of years.
The rollout of their MVME storage, the rollout of the AMD epic processors, more features
like database as a service. They started with one database and now they've added multiple
databases. Hello, Postgres. Thank you very much, Linode. If you're a performance hound,
you're going to love Linode. If you're a budget hound, you're going to love Linode. If you're
a hound, you probably don't know what Linode is, but you get what I'm saying. Linode has
been doing this for nearly 19 years. And over that time, they have had to refine it to stay
competitive. They've really built something special here. So that's why they want to give
you one hundred dollars. I think they know that if you try it and compare it to what
else is out there, not only will you see that it's a great service with a beautiful interface,
but it's also a better value than the hyperscalers that want to lock you into their crazy esoteric
platform. And we live in this world now where they're constantly trying to abstract away
all these services into individual things that they can charge you for. Linode is how
we've built everything in the last couple of years because we can go there, we can build
our infrastructure and it runs great. And if we ever need it, and I hear this from the
audience all the time, if you ever need it, Linode has the absolute best service in the
business. Their model is different than the hyperscalers, so they can offer you actual
human support. That really matters. Go try it. Go see why we've been talking about it
and go see why they're still sponsoring because Coder Radio listeners like you are still trying
it out and discovering it's the best out there. It's really great. We've got a whole crew
of Linode users out there now. Go become one of them and get that $100 and support the
show. Linode.com slash Coder.
Let's talk about declarative UIs because I love it when you get declarative and I have
been hearing some buzz around Flutter recently. Brand new app just dropped that I want to
try out. I got declarative on the mind and I think you do too.
I do, I do. I do declare. What's the new app?
Of course you're going to put me on the spot. It was a Bitcoin app, of course.
Of course it was. All right. We should just talk about what declarative UIs are. Basically,
it's back in the olden days of I guess the 90s and early aughts. Actually, I don't know,
for a while. UIs were basically object oriented. You had a button. The whole thing was like
... The metaphor was like, it's an actual button in your car or whatever. Yay. If you're
familiar with skeuomorphism at all, that was a design language that was supposed to make
things look like actual things. We had a lot of leather iOS apps for a long time. It's
very... Wachowski Brothers, Keanu Reeves in 1999, we were having a good time in black
leather.
Yeah.
Now, because the world is in a fallen state, we have multiple screen sizes. If you've ever
done old school iOS development, that becomes increasingly hard. We have declarative UI.
What does that mean? I do declare what my content is and what the data is and how I
expect it to be broadly structured. A lot of this declarative UI stuff will look very
like XML-y, kind of like a document adjacent. Chris, if you'll read us how Flutter explains
because the wizards at Google are like the techno mages. They know.
Yeah, they do. They say that this... They have an introduction, which we will link in
the show notes. They say, frameworks from Win32 to the web to Android and iOS typically
use an imperative style of UI programming. This must be the style you're most familiar
with where you manually construct a full functional UI entity, such as a UI view or equivalent,
and later mutate it using methods and setters when the UI changes. I think I just understood
it less by reading that.
Well, no. That's the old way, right? Let's just say... I'm going to just iOS it up to
torture everybody. All right. Let's say I have Jar Jar view, and then on Jar Jar view,
I have... I think it's... What is it? ViewDidLoad? That might be a view controller, but I'm going
to call it ViewDidLoad. Then I would go Jar Jar view.background equals blah, blah, blah,
color hash. Jar Jar view.title equals blah, blah, blah, my title. Literally, imperatively,
line by line by line, I'm telling the view based on the loading trigger what it should
look like manually.
Then that view is my class Jar Jar view. I go into a view controller or some other type
of container, and I'm like, okay, put the Jar Jar view on view controller did load,
which is actually also called ViewDidLoad because I think I got the view one wrong.
It's been a long time. Back in the day, we would literally denote the pixels, right?
Like 20 pixels from the top, 10 from the left, 10 from the right, and whatever below it.
That's the imperative style. That's... Back in my day, me and Decker Cain were doing that,
but Google, the heroes, they are... I'm going to continue the quote. In order to lighten
the burden on developers from having to program how to transition between various UI states,
it's a me and Mario, but I slipped a little bit there. I turned into a Boo from the quickie
bar. That was not good. By contrast, less developers crowd the current UI state and
leaves the transitioning to the framework. Okay. We basically have... Think of SwiftUI.
I know it's super popular with Ionit audience. Let's just genericize it, right? You have
a view. You lay out roughly what you want. I want a table view. I have this item. Map
it to the properties of this data structure, which could be some sort of object or it could
just be like a hash, whatever. Lay it out. You're not telling it pixels. You're not imperatively
saying do this, this, this, then this. You're giving it the structure and the data that
you want, and it's basically Voltroning itself up. The advantage of this, wide declarative
UI, is that in theory, in theory, it's less manual crappy imperative coding work. Arguable,
but okay. You get something called two-way data binding in most platforms that do this,
which if you're familiar with Angular is like the magical thing where you don't have to
do... Because remember, let's go back to my old iOS app. If we have a text field in
that Jar Jar view and someone types fork you Jar Jar, well, to actually get that back into
the backing data model, I have to go Jar Jar.message equals fork you Jar Jar. With this kind of
thing, it just automatically will do the two-way binding, assuming you know what you're doing
and you're in a platform that does that, which most of them do now.
The problem is the same problem we always have with this kind of stuff. That little
like promise it'll basically look good on all your devices is basically not true. Having
said that, I don't think this is bad at all, but this is like the Java dream that me and
Duke cry every night over as we cuddle in our sun t-shirts, blankets.
There it is.
Write once, run everywhere just doesn't really work. Granted, now that a lot of front-end
development has transitioned to like HTML5, which I don't even think is a term we should
use anymore because that's old. That's 2012 talking. Let's just call it modern web. It's
less about the actual platform you're on and more about the screen size and the screen
aspect ratio and resolution, which I mean, I will say like I'm doing a bit of Angular
backed by Ionic or Ionic or however you want to say that. It's sane. If I put it on an
iPad versus a phone, it looks okay for the most part, but it is a little things you end
up wanting to change it anyway. That's my long winded explanation of why you should
look into declarative UI, but it's partially a lie.
I feel like there's an elephant in the room with this stuff too, and that is you've seen
a lot of apps that come out where the developer, maybe rightfully so, just doesn't want to
invest time or money or resources into UI development. This can be a way where you can
essentially ship minimum viable UI that actually survives platform updates frequently as well,
but not all of them.
So okay, let's get crazy. Let's talk about Swift UI. So for about a year, I've wanted
this little prototype news reading app because I used to be an extremely heavy pocket user
as anybody who's followed me on Twitter for longer than two years will know, but I'm just
less and less inclined to use it. I kind of prototyped something up in Swift UI, just
the UI side and like basic internal data, no server backend yet. And as long as I kept
it to Apple's controls, it was really, really nice. I mean, I kind of get why Marco always
uses Apple's controls now, because you know what? I could like magically implement dark
mode. As long as I followed the HIG. The beautiful thing is I'm the customer for this app, so
there's no one who's like, we need our special branding, special kind of like, God forbid
whatever drawer they want made that doesn't exist in iOS.
Users are the worst part about writing software.
I really think every user who complains about the color blue, and I'm carrying the spoon
from roughly 10 years ago now, should have to work in the God damn terminal.
That's right.
Not warp and not tabby. You know, we're installing Ubuntu 910. I'll give them 910.
No fish shell.
No fish. And I'm going to bust the auto complete on you. I'm going to mess with your Bash RC.
There you go. That'll show them. That'll show them. No, it's really, it's really nice. It's
definitely opinionated. It's got some fee fees. But if you're willing to tolerate its
fee fees, it's a lot like my six year old, honestly. Like he, we play Mario soccer or
Mario strikers, which is, should be called Mario soccer, but it's not. And he believes
the way to win is to nuke me with red shells. And unfortunately that seems to be working.
I hate the shells. I hate the shell. I wish I could turn it off and make it like FIFA
and be like, all right buddy, let's go. I know the challenge with Swift UI in particular
is the minute you have to import UI kit, which I actually have an old blog post when I was
trying this out last year, it works, but Oh baby, you got to wrap that in some Swift UI
goodness. And some of your old school delegate callbacks might be mad at you. Oh, and of
course the biggest problem with Swift UI is the Swift part. Cause it's not objective C.
Yes, I had to get it in. Um, but I would encourage you, I mean, I would suggest, and this really
hurts me every time I do that. If you are a young budding, you know, glamorous or strapping
or whatever wannabe iOS developer, leave the objective seat to the old guys and just pay
us a lot of money to do like the three hours you need to fix your stuff. Go ahead and go
straight into Swift UI. Oh, and it works across Mac OS and, uh, iOS. Oh, and it works on the
watch now, which is super interesting. What's super bad about it is that you're, you need
a beastly laptop because it reloads constantly. They'll solve that for you for a price. Yeah.
$2,500 or 2250. If you listen to me, I Patel, you know, with your kid, you might be able
to get an educational discount, right? Can't, can't you as a parent, I've actually never
tried this myself, but there's educational discounts too. I mean, not to give even more
excuses to buy max, but something to look into. So, you know, the small business discount
used to be really good, but that I think that's the same as the education. It's not like 7%.
Ah, I do know the educational discount has gotten less. The, the literal best buy. We
hate Amazon. We're competing with them. Prime day sale was more than both my business discount
and, uh, yeah, my fiance is actually taking some classes so she could, she has it through
her school. It was about a hundred bucks cheaper just to go at best buys. Like, you know, we
hate Amazon sale, which I'm pretty sure is why they did that. Hey man, works for me.
Yeah. Competition again, here's looking at you Comcast. So you know what I'm surprised
hasn't really come up at all is react. I mean, where does this fit? Because I hate it. Oh,
thank you for life. Yeah. I mean, okay. All right. Well, there you go. No, react native
react native is actually, I would say the pure flood. Okay. So we should, we should
compare the three, the three we put in the doc flutter, Swift UI and react native Swift
UI. I would say it's the most bastard eyes of these declarative UI frameworks right now.
That's partially because they just have a huge transition they've got to make, right?
And you've got to be able to mix your UI kit code in there and UI kits as imperative as
they come. It's view did load bam dot background color. Let's do it. React native. I mean,
comes from react.js, right? It's its own thing. Same with flutter and they're, they're real
deep in this declarative UI stuff where their whole pitch, both them and flutter is to write
your code. You can have some rules for different device sizes, but you know what your data
driven your functionality driven everything. We, we used to call this reactive programming,
which is kind of a different thing too, but most people doing reactive programming, we're
also doing declarative UIs as kind of a byproduct. And they, they kind of go together really
hand in hand, right? Cause it's less about, you know, you manually typing the code and
it's more, um, you know, the object backing your view changes. The view automatically
changes. So yeah, I mean if I would say if you just like have never heard of this concept
before you had to pick one unless you're just that aspiring, you know, iOS developer, I
would say take a peek at flutter or react native first. There are the, the purest implementations
of this.
All right. We have links in the show notes and of course you can always check the back
catalog using tags, keywords. In fact, if you go to notes.jupiterbroadcasting.com,
you can search for our previous coverage on react on Swift and on flutter all there. So
good stuff, especially as I think flutter is, um, I think I'm beginning to change my
mind on flutter. I think we're going to see outside of Google adoption more and more.
You've got several projects happening at canonical. They're really close to their flutter based
installer and there's this Bitcoin lightning wallet that is using flutter specifically
because they want to target iOS, Android, and the desktop.
Yeah. I think from where when we first covered flutter, um, and when actually a couple of
years ago I interviewed the guy at the time who I think like ran flutter or something.
He goes big shot and flutter. It's a, it's become really impressive. I don't know. I'm
still clinging to my angular, which maybe we'll talk about the current state of angular
slash ionic next week or a week after. But that's, uh, partially because I'm doing more
pure webby stuff and dart scares me.
In
multiple different providers that could be across physical systems, virtual systems,
mobile devices.
It's fantastic.
And you'll be impressed with how quick it is to get started.
If you're a business, it'll work with your single sign on provider that includes two
factor.
And for me, the best part is, is every device now is accessible to me when I'm at work,
when I'm on the road, when I'm at a friend's house, like anywhere I can get either with
my mobile device or my laptops.
They all just have tail scale and it's really intelligent about how it routes the traffic.
So you're not just like dumping all your internet traffic into your tail scale network.
It's intelligent about that.
It works with DNS too.
So if you want to throw a DNS machine in your tail scale network, you can start resolving
names.
It has ACL support.
It has sharing support.
If you want to share one node or maybe just one port on a node with a friend, I do that
with my buddy Alex devices connect so quickly and transparently.
Once it's up, it's always on.
That means it's always available and then you can start building around that.
They're always on VPNs that get up and going in just minutes.
So go try it for yourself for free for up to 20 machines.
Go to tailscale.com slash coder.
You go there, you support the show, you try out one of the best things that's come around
in years and you get it for free up to 20 devices.
That's tailscale.com slash coder.
I wanted to document something that I thought was interesting happening in the tech industry.
Do you remember it was a bit ago, it seems like 10 years ago, thanks to the last couple
of years, but it actually wasn't.
It was 2020 and 2021 when America's greatest cyber hack occurred, SolarWinds software was
compromised and then all of the different government and large institution and enterprises
that use the SolarWinds software, a lot of them got compromised as a result and it turned
out it was some really poor practices.
I believe with the way software updates were being distributed and checked and it was just
this devastating attack and SolarWinds as a brand was essentially nuked from the sky
and just drilled into the ground.
Do you recall all of this?
Oh yeah.
So it's interesting to watch as the tech media begins the process of repairing the brand
and I wanted to capture this so that way our audience could be aware of how this cycle
works.
Here's the general cycle.
Large company and institution in the tech industry becomes well known, well established,
brand equity is high, has a very embarrassing event, goes quiet for a year to two years
and then begins working on a sustained campaign to bring its brand back.
It generally starts with smaller media outlets, local if it's in the business tech cross section
and then it kind of grows out from there.
The headline reads, why SolarWinds just may be one of the most secure software companies
in the tech universe by Jill at SC Media.
I'm guessing SC Media looks like they focus on cyber security and other things.
Yeah, of course.
And she writes her opening sentence, a house gets burglarized, the owners buy a fancy alarm
system, a hurricane knocks a house down, it gets rebuilt, bigger and stronger.
Indeed there are a slew of analogies that could be applied to SolarWinds which just
might now be among the most secure software companies in the tech universe.
And you can kind of probably get a vibe for where it goes from here.
But I'm closing the door on a few business opportunities because SolarWinds is actually
a surprisingly large company and they actually own quite a few sub-brands that are interested
in buying podcast advertising, but it shouldn't be able to work like this.
They screwed up fundamentally.
As a brand they should be dead, it should be sold off, it should be done.
Instead this industry pleasing media is going to write these soft pieces about them because
you know it's just tech, who cares, it doesn't hurt anybody.
And they'll pump the brand and they'll pump the brand until they're back and they're bigger
than ever and they're making billions of dollars again like they didn't make some sort of massive
fundamental mistake that exposed millions of people's private information.
And I find the process frustrating and so I just kind of wanted to document it here
so we could see the cycle in the show so we could all be aware of how they do this and
how their coverage isn't like regular media coverage.
Oh they don't take it seriously.
Right they don't, but I don't think the journalists, if you can call them that, they don't take
it seriously either because it's not life and death stuff, it's not political scandals,
it's tech stuff.
We can even look at some of our, or my, more beloved tech sites and they've all weirdly
turned into like navel-gazing pseudo reporting on the media itself site, which I get, you
know Facebook decided to do crazy crap, but sometimes you just want a good old-fashioned
hey man there's a new laptop out, you know, or like there's this weird gadget.
You know where this is going to take us, right?
My pet peeve.
Large accounting consultancies realizing there's a bunch of little companies in a small metro,
let's call it Tampa, and deciding that they are going to systematically rip that like
basically just cut prices and go into every mid to somewhat large business to put those
companies out of business.
By hiring just massive offshore teams or a couple good coaches and in the past a lot
of H1Bs, but I don't, somehow that seems less and less a thing, or at least maybe in Florida
it's less of a thing.
I don't know.
In New York I used to see it all the time, but it's really like I'm not going to name
names because I used to have a relative that worked at one of these, but these guys need
to see more growth and they can't handle little ratatouille over here having even a piece
of the bread.
Right?
No baguette for you.
Can I fry a little bacon?
It has felt like the last few years there has been decision after decision and policy
after policy or strategy after strategy that is just absolutely crushing the small business.
Like it started with the lockdowns which universally advantaged large companies like your box stores
and disadvantaged small businesses, but we're also seeing it with the supply chain shortages
now.
Large businesses like Amazon and Walmart can actually afford to just fly their own jet
planes and their own boats, but small businesses like the mom and pop hardware store near where
I live can't get access to the same things.
That's not one person or decision disadvantaging them, it's just a series.
It's a structural disadvantage.
On top of that, you have things like Blackwater that's going out and buying up real estate
that's not only taking it from homeowners, but they're also buying up commercial real
estate and offices that now drive the price.
Yes, they're my landlord.
Oh yeah, that's right.
Yes, that's right.
But you get my point.
It seems like this is getting gnawed at from several different directions.
Maybe it's just that there's all of these giant institutions now and because these giant
institutions are so big, they just suck up all of the resources around them.
Well, this is the thing.
This is what the Chinese have right.
It turns out mercantilism was flawed, but fundamentally correct.
There is just a limited amount of resources in a given area, and there is no such thing.
I'll give you an example.
COVID is definitely a part of this too, and I think they were able to use COVID to their
advantage.
There used to be five or six, and let's call it the Tampa Hillsborough County area, moderately
small to medium size, bigger than the Mad Botter, or around that small, businessy, indie
sized dev shops doing dev or dev-adjacent things.
A couple of them put on their hipster glasses and plaid and said they were design shops,
whatever.
Same thing.
Now there's, to my knowledge, three of us left.
That barely counts because one of them just decided to offshore a bunch of their stuff.
Wow, wow, wow, wow.
It's me, and I'll plug them source though.
They're good, but they're also half in Australia, I think.
The way the survivors survived was by niching down super hard.
We do the automation stuff with Alice, and we do software for basically enterprise, line
of business, run your business, get your analytics for your internal, whether it's your farm
or you're repairing jet engines, those are basically our two big areas right now.
Or you're a small business, want to automate some of your stuff, integrate multiple services,
go to alice.dev, we can do that for you, very affordably.
The other guys, they focus on cruise ships.
SourceTode, they just all in on cruise ships.
If you are a Russian oligarch and your yacht has not been seized, go talk to Greg over
at SourceTode.
He can hook you up, although I don't think he will, but he could.
This is the thing.
See, this is the thing.
You have them sucking up the resources, right?
You're making it harder and harder for these niche businesses to exist, which means... I
think that's a whole other conversation, actually, but going back to the SolarWinds piece, this
is why I think SolarWinds should just go away.
It should be broken up into all its subsidiaries, all of its individual pieces, and it should
be a dozen small little businesses, and we should be hitting the reset button from time
to time to help keep this ecosystem healthy.
But instead, we have this press coverage and this brand repair that they engage in, and
I'm not even claiming that SC Media or SC Magazine was paid for this or that it's a
native advertisement.
It could be, but I actually think the way the incentive system works, because getting
access to these CEOs and getting connections is what keeps these types of outlets going,
they have to kind of do this stuff.
It's the incentive structure.
In order for them to get somebody at SolarWinds in the future to pick up the phone, they got
to kind of engage in this sort of stuff.
It's not even a malicious thing.
I occasionally write book reviews, and I used to do the Manning Press, the early access
books.
They'd send to Dev, and they'd be like, hey, free book if you want to write a review.
But they're always like PDFs.
I used to get those too back in the old days.
Back in the day, they don't do that anymore.
And I would occasionally review them.
Well, that was a mistake.
It's like every Monday, my email box is deluged with, and it's always like a random crap.
I know.
I was willing to do a few like Linux on topic ones, and then all of a sudden it was just
unbelievable.
It's because, again, the incentive structure.
Okay, so going back to this, and this is why I really think this matters, is the SC media
doesn't even have to be doing anything malicious.
The incentive structure of advertised based media is such that the reader is just not
the customer.
So it's not in their interest to get you the most accurate information.
It's not a malicious thing.
The tech industry and the advertisers in that tech ecosystem are the customer.
You guys have heard it a million times.
If you're not paying for the product, you are the product.
It's true in media too.
And side note, this is why memberships are a big deal for our show.
This is why the boosts are a big deal for our show, because it means our largest customer,
our most important customer as a business, is our audience.
You're our customer that gives us the leeway to work with other advertisers and pick the
right ones.
But it doesn't mean we have to, right?
We have choice in the matter.
That's the difference.
You are the customer.
But in the case of SC media, you're not the customer.
I want to read this email that came into the show a couple hours before the show.
Hello, my name is Monica, and I'm an outreach assistant at ZZB Agency, a small company representing
a handful of real money gambling and betting related clients.
While looking for potential partners for a content marketing campaign, I stumbled upon
Jupiter Broadcasting and found that it would probably be of interest to our partners.
So allow me to ask you, are you open to publishing paid articles with do follow real money gambling
or betting related links in their text on their website?
I think she's saying links that go to the gambling website.
I'm well aware that the fact that this business is in general pretty sensitive and that any
collaboration in this area would involve higher rates than usual if you're open to working
with my partners of this type.
Please let us know.
You're asking price for a paid article with one live link in its body.
Please include the price of creating the article as well.
If you have any questions, feel free to ask.
Best regards, Monica came in this morning.
Comes in all the time.
I actually got three this morning to office hours.
It's a brand new show.
I got three like this.
That's like extra shady.
I know.
I just need to pay you a little more and you know, keep it a secret.
Don't say anything.
The implication is don't put like a sponsored content thing under it.
Yeah.
That kind of stuff comes into shows like ours all the time.
And if you weren't the customer, eventually a business has to survive, right?
And eventually you just the right kind of offer, maybe it's not that one, but the right
kind of offer comes in.
It's a little shady, but you're willing to do it because the money's good.
And pretty soon it just becomes a standard practice of business.
It's not even considered immoral anymore.
It's just the business you're doing.
And that is what happens in the tech press.
All of the tech press is like this.
It's bad.
It's all like this.
Right.
And I mean, there's exceptions for sure.
When I say all, I guess I'm really talking about all the big ones, like Mike's favorite,
The Verge, a few others.
Hey, OK, you know what, though?
The Verge at least says when they're doing it, they put that they put that big sponsored
banner.
Right.
And then I just don't click on it.
But that's still there's still that problem.
And I think it's one of the things that our show does not suffer from in some shows that
you and I listen to do suffer from.
There is that problem where if you want to maintain a relationship with individuals in
a company, sources and whatnot, there's just certain things you won't say or there's just
certain things you'll interpret a certain way because.
You're incentivized to do it that way, right?
It's just human nature.
You know what I mean?
And that just, I think, is a really rampant problem in tech because it's it's a close
community and because it's not high stakes compared to other types of news coverage.
I think it allows for those kinds of relationships to form more.
I don't know for sure, but based on my 15 years of kind of watching all of it, I sure
seem to observe observe that kind of behavior in that practice an awful lot to think it's
just at this point pretty widespread.
And so you see it in things like this brand repair campaign.
If you go search SolarWinds on Google News, you would think the largest cyber attack in
US history, which is what it was called over and over and over again, it even has its own.
They gave it a name.
You would think that if you looked on news.google.com for SolarWinds, maybe the largest cyber compromise
that's ever happened in US history might show up.
Instead what you will see is 20 or 30 spin articles that are part of a sustained campaign
that's been going on right up until their earnings are announced in just a few days.
To spin the brand as this recovery brand and Google News just surfaces what everybody's
reporting and that's what you know, all these different little no name outlets are all publishing
and it begins to create this noise and it just all the surfaces now in the feeds and
I thought to be an interesting for us to be able to watch it happen in real time.
That's really all.
We're a little sad.
Yeah, or perhaps could be a little sad.
But at least it's good to know that's how these things go down so we can invent new
thought technologies to process the information like that sounds great.
Ask not what your podcast can boost for you, but what you can boost for your podcast.
All right, we got some boosts.
Trev dev boosted in with some leet sats 1337 five days ago, Mike, you can use ZSH and a
completion plug in, by the way, like you could spell PG SQL correctly once and then if you
use control E, it'll complete repetitive queries for you automatically.
I mean, sure, these fangled new terminals offer a lots of stuff, but very little for
a dude just trying to write some Python and also please don't feed the animals while visiting
the zoo.
That's right.
Not sure why you would ZSH plug in at love, I guess.
So yeah, probably shouldn't do that.
Tim Apple boosted in with a row of ducks, two thousand two hundred and twenty two sats.
I'm a duck.
The UK duck loaded with talent when you read that letter from Lenart and you said 2014.
I couldn't believe it.
It seemed just like it was the other day.
What a ride.
Also, people are still bitching about system D all these years later.
Microsoft has one thing right, though.
Oh, wait.
Forgot what it was.
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh,
oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh, oh,
regarding V.S.
Code and Microsoft spying on you.
You can just turn off the telemetry.
That's what we do.
Fair.
I actually like I was saying last week and I'm surprised nobody said anything about this.
I leave it on on purposeful.
So you want to rep Linux.
Yeah, that's right.
I want to rep the Linux.
I'm curious if anybody else does that.
But nobody else boosted in.
I do it for edge, actually, but I turn it off on Mac because they don't need to see
that.
There's enough Macs out there.
I'm a closeted Mac.
Bros and Wing boosted in with LeetSats.
Mike and Chris, I have a dream.
I want to be in my car on my hour long commute listening to Jupiter broadcasting when something
interesting is talked about on the show and I have a thought.
I just want to pause the podcast and say into the air, Siri, boost in Dakota Radio, save
blah, blah, blah with X amount of sats without ever having to leave Apple CarPlay.
What do you think?
Is that going to be possible in the future?
I wonder.
No, because aren't sats a proxy for money?
Yes, but Fountain App is an iOS app that already lets you boost in and Castamatic, too.
So there's there's there's podcast apps that let you do it so you don't buy the sats in
the app.
That's, I think.
Oh, OK.
So it's like if you buy like e-bucks or v-bucks, whatever it was, right.
So you like to use something like Strike or Blue Wallet to buy the sats, which are in
iOS, but they've been approved as like Strike is like a legit.
Payments app.
Well, then, yeah, you could probably do it, then.
Yeah, I would think so, because Fountain is working on a CarPlay app.
If the boost features in there, I'm not sure, but that could be pretty neat.
You can mine Bitcoin on the road as one does.
I've thought about that when I'm going down the road in the RV, I've got solar.
I've got a really big generator or alternator in that thing.
I have got more power than I know what to do with when I'm going down the road.
So why not?
Why not?
Sir, license registration officer, I'm so close to a fiftieth of a Bitcoin right now.
Yeah, I don't want to stop now.
I might get some Bitcoin dust.
I don't want to stop.
Oh, man.
All right.
So the Golden Dragon boosted in with another row of ducks.
Thank you very much.
And here's something for your trouble.
So the great show, guys.
How would I go about learning how to set up a hosted service for my own that I can use
outside my home and attach a domain name to it?
You listen to self-hosted.
That's a good start.
I think Golden Dragon probably does.
I was thinking, too, there's some good Leno guides on this.
And what you really want is you get a DNS name, you register your domain name, and then
you get like a guide for Leno that tells you how to point that domain name to your Leno.
There's several ways to do that, including just changing the name servers, actually moving
them and all that.
You'll have to do some reading on that.
Golden Dragon.
And you probably want to put Cloudflare in front of that.
Yeah, absolutely.
That's what I'm doing these days.
I'm putting Cloud.
I'm.
Yep.
So that's those Russian bots.
Don't care.
They're going to keep hitting every port they can find.
Golden Dragon kept it going with a triple boost, one thousand one hundred and eleven
sats.
He says, which version of Carolina barbecue are you guys into?
I went several years ago and had eastern northern Carolina style was very impressed.
Hold on.
Yes, there's more than one version.
Oh, my God.
You got to be kidding me.
So them or Emacs or Golden Dragon go, you know, can I say something controversial here?
I don't know for sure.
I'd be willing to try this somehow.
I think the Carolinans go on about their barbecue because they're just far enough away from
Austin to eat real barbecue.
And so they think they've got great barbecue because they've got good sauces.
Right.
But but great Texas barbecue starts with meat that is incredible.
And then they custom design a sauce that complements the specific flavor attributes of that meat.
And the two when they go together, change your life.
And I've been hanging out with the Linux Academy and tell people too much.
I'm telling you, Carolina barbecue is amazing.
No, no, I'm telling you, it might be good.
Right.
I mean, it might be like really good.
But if you get the right barbecue in Austin, Texas, it will change your life.
It'll change your life.
You will not.
You will leave the barbecue place.
Not.
Why can't we love them both?
Life changing.
That's right.
Maybe I'm wrong.
I'm willing to I'm willing to try it.
I'm willing to experiment.
I'm willing to sacrifice that if I have to travel to Texas and the Carolinas to put this
to rest.
By God, I will.
You know what I had for dinner yesterday?
Did you have barbecue?
Mango habanero ribs homemade.
They were fantastic.
All off the bone.
Oh, I didn't make them, but they were great.
All right.
Splurk boosts in with seven hundred and seventy seven sets.
Great podcast.
I really appreciate your perspectives on the industry.
I just wanted to comment on the software conservancy issue we talked about last week, how they're
raising a big stink about GitHub.
It seems to me that the SFC and the FSF are actually anti freedom.
They simply just don't have patience for devs or companies who want to make a living off
GPL code.
They feel more like a religious cult than an altruistic organization.
Microsoft might not be the best open source player, but they are putting money and time
into open source and in my humble opinion, that's way more valuable than naming and shaming.
Wow.
Now, I feel like he's not giving the FSC and the Free Software Foundation credit for everything
they have accomplished, the projects they've supported, the infrastructure they provide.
But I think what Splurk does touch on is the overall vibe that the broader community who
doesn't follow all the nuances and developments is getting.
And I think it's a problem for those organizations because I think it makes them less effective
in messaging.
I don't know.
I'd give them a little more credit that I keep seeing this get back in my day, an easy
way to get a laugh out of really any dev conference or especially Linux oriented ones was to dunk
on Microsoft.
And I feel like just because of how age and time work, many of the people who now run
these organizations have a lot of that old like Microsoft is evil bias.
And I'm kind of like, well, they're all evil, right?
Look at what happened to our beautiful son.
It's dead.
And Red Hat is now joined IBM.
So I, you know, I would rather a little bit of a little bit of demon blood and they survive.
I think what you're touching on there, I could expand on just a bit by saying with IBM buying
Red Hat and the changes we've seen in the tech industry and honestly also listening
to some of those older clips.
So we just recorded the Coderly for our members and we played some old clips, predictions
and whatnot that we made from like 2014 and 15.
And after hearing that, after doing that episode and then reflecting on stuff, I'm like, none
of these companies really hold up over the long time.
Like if anybody gets too brand loyal or really anything that's too centralized eventually
will disappoint you.
That's essentially what it is.
And Linux was a great thing because it's such a decentralized spread out thing that it's
not like one company, there's no Linux CEO, there's no like one company that is running
Linux.
I mean, there's the Linux Foundation now.
Perhaps that'll be a problem at some point as it gets more and more centralized.
But thank you, Slurk, that's some interesting stuff to ponder.
I love the boosts that make us think.
I love all the boosts.
Thank you everybody who does that.
Again, we, of course, we've done this for forever.
We're always, we do this because we enjoy doing the show, we want to make something
for you guys.
So you guys really are our customer.
And what's great about the boosts, what's great about the memberships is it aligns the
business that way too.
So we also, just to wrap it up, we've got a couple of thank you boosts.
200 SATs were streamed from user 6594.
We got an additional 222 SATs from Golden Dragon with an early thanks for the show and
saying that his Python journey has been quite the trip.
Golden Dragon on fire, on fire this week with the boost.
Some of, really a big bulk of the support this week's episode came from Golden Dragon
and he's in the live stream right now too.
So like fist bump Golden Dragon.
He's a coder completist.
He probably has a robe.
You're right.
If he doesn't, he should be first on the list.
He is officially a coder completist.
There we go.
Egon's going to have to share some of the wine.
We also got 475 thank you SATs for a next episode boost coming from KPOVAC in also in
the chat room right now.
And we got a thousand SATs from X thumbs X who says plus one on the coder cocktail swag
idea.
Cocktail glass for the win.
We got to get on that.
We got to get a swag.
We got to get on the other side of it, have a laptop just like sparking out a complete
set.
If you'd like to be a member, we would appreciate it.
It's a great way to support the show.
You get the coderly report that we release once a quarter, a little extra episode and
you get an ad free version of the show and in the future, probably towards the end of
the year or so you'll get a live version if you'd like a totally unedited, unscripted,
whatever, whatever they call it behind the scenes.
That's what I'm looking for.
You can, I advise you though, the drew edited version, much better sound, much better pacing.
Drew does magic really.
So we'll always keep the ad free feed around too so that way members can benefit from that
work he does.
You can sign up at coder QA dot co for that.
Keep an eye out members for the coderly report.
It'll be coming out soon.
We don't have a specific date yet, but cause we just sort of slip it into the work queue
as we have it, but it'll be out soon.
Mr. Dominic, is there anywhere you'd like to send the people this week?
Go to Alice.dev if you want some automation goodness.
Who doesn't?
That's right.
Alice.dev for that.
You can find the show on Twitter at Coder Radio Show and the whole network where announcements
for all the shows come out and stuffs.
That's at Jupiter signal.
And if you've made it this far, a little pro tip.
We're working on a brand new website.
You've got a designer eye or if you're a Hugo expert, go check out Jupiter broadcasting.net.
It's an MVP right now, but we're working on a static site that's generated by GitHub actions
and then auto publishes.
It's going to be awesome.
We have a matrix room where we're discussing that and we have issues on our GitHub if you'd
like to peruse that.
We'd love your input.
This is nice.
Thank you.
Links to what we talked about today are coder dot show slash four seven five to find our
contact form there, also our RSS feed so you can subscribe and get the show automatically.
And don't forget, you can join us live over at Jupiter Dot Tube on Mondays at noon Pacific
3 p.m. Eastern.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of the Coder Radio program.
See you back here next week.