This is KOTORadio, episode 333 for November 26th, 2018.
Oh hi you and welcome to KOTORadio, Jupiter Broadcasting's weekly talk show taking a pragmatic
look at the art and the business of software development and its related technologies.
This episode is maybe the last one for a while, recorded in the rainy and gray Pacific Northwest.
My name is Chris, and joining me, like a soldier always at his post, even when we're not doing an
episode, is our host, Mr. Dominic. Hello, Mike. I'm sorry, when I was at a bar, what happened?
No, I think you were stuck in traffic, actually. Yeah, that's true.
You know, I guess the two things are related. You go to a bar, you have a work meeting at lunch,
and then you get stuck in traffic. I haven't actually had that problem where I can't make
it to a show, because like a gentleman, I schedule my travel during non-KOTOR days.
I see what you did there. But man, the most recent travel, I have been stuck in traffic
in a way I have never been stuck before. And that comes from a professional former commuter.
It has been bad, so I do understand. And to make up for it, we're just going to have a
great episode, right? Yeah. I mean, easy, right? No problem. I actually, I think I feel like this
episode is jinxed, if I can be honest with you, because 15 minutes before we started, I just
learned that I'm leaving Washington on Sunday. And I sound like I'm still processing, like,
how does that impact my life and my show production? I'm still trying to figure that out.
It's one of those things. Well, I thought we knew that, because the live audience will get
a little treat at the end of this show. Yeah, yeah. One of us, oh shit, I'm leaving too.
Yeah, exactly. I know, we're prerecording for you, but it turns out we need to be
prerecording for me. Also prerecording. You and I have to stop this whole-
I know. So can we take a tangent about my recent travels?
Yeah, let's do it. So, you know, if there was to be a Bible written by laptops
about angels and devils, I think I might be Satan. Yeah, I agree. I had two casualties
on this. Now, this was a three-legged trip. We went to Tejas. No, you did.
Then, yes, I did. San Antonio. Then to New Jersey, also known as Military City, for those who don't
know. I'm not kidding. Oh, right, for your new clientele for the app.
Yes. And then to New Jersey, and then a quick detour into New York City. By New York,
I had no more laptops. Wait a minute. Okay, so you start the trip
with two laptops, and by the time you get to New York, you got no laptops?
No laptops, and I did not get mugged. So, okay, so I'm packing, right?
Yeah. And I throw in the Mac cable, the USB-C
brick thing. I throw in the Galego cable. Wait, wait, your Galego cable? Your Galego
doesn't charge over USB-C? It does not.
I'm sorry, what? Is this the old Galego, or is this a current Galego?
This is the Gen 2, or 3, whatever the Gen before the one you would buy today is.
Okay. Yeah. For the laptops I buy,
it actually has been a little while. So, okay. Turns out the Galego cable I bought,
brought, was not in fact a Galego cable. Oh, man.
Sucks. And that's the machine I needed for Tejas. So I, in my infinite wisdom,
buy a cable in the airport. Sure. It's kind of fun. Did you do it from
a vending machine, or did you go into one of the actual stores?
You know, they have those vending machines that are super tempting.
That was a weird experience. And yes, I did.
Oh, you did. You used the vending machine. I've always wanted to do that.
You know what? I was so sure my credit card was going to be stolen by the end of that whole
process. I know, right? Yeah.
But I had no choice. I mean, I got to do this demo. There's no way out of this.
So this was a brand that I've never heard of before. And I honestly don't know the name,
because it came in a little plastic pouch, like a Ziploc bag that one would, you know...
Not a box?
It was the only one. It was one of those universal ones with like 10 different
attachments. And you're like, one of these has got to work.
And it turns out it did. So I'll give them that. So whatever, I throw it in my bag,
because I got in, I got a ride to the hotel. Are you Ubering? What are you getting to the
hotel with? I lifted it, but same difference.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. It sent me a notification that it was
some percentage off. I don't know why. You're like, yes, please.
I'm like, sure. Sounds like a deal. You know what? I got in like 9.45,
and I hadn't eaten, right? Like, this is one of those situations where, you know...
Oh, man. So you're exhausted.
A whole bit. Flight delayed. So I'm like, you know what? I'm starving. I go to the hotel
bar and order a salad. But the first thing I do is check into my room, plug in the computer
to this cable. But I turn it on and I let it run updates. It seems fine.
I guess what I should have noticed was an error message saying that the cable was no good.
What error message? What error message?
I don't know, some kind of like pop up that said like not charging.
No. This isn't a thing.
Well, all right. Well, let me tell you, this is what I've heard digging through forums.
So, but anyway, I didn't check, right? So I just turned it on.
Right. You're hungry. It's nine o'clock at night.
I had a little my fi puck, because I don't use hotel Wi-Fi, because I'm not crazy.
Atta boy, you really got this down.
Right. Well, I, you know how much I travel. I mean, yeah, you do. You have to have it down.
It's just worth the, you know, 20 bucks a month to Verizon for the Wi-Fi puck.
Whatever. I do the updates and I, you know what? I want it to download,
like make sure the demo ran, whatever, whatever. But I was tired and I was hungry. So I get
downstairs and I do chicken wings. You do a salad, really? You do a salad.
I do chicken wings. Cause who can screw up chicken wings?
Well, here's my thing. Well, I could not get a salad because they had no salad.
So I ended up having to wait for what they call the quesadilla. And you would think in Texas,
it would be good, but it was weird. Oh, you're in Texas. Yeah. They don't have salad in Texas.
Yeah. No. The young lady just looked at me like I was on drugs. So then, you know,
I'm sitting there waiting for my food. They were very busy. Remember, this is election night we're
talking about. So this is back a while. And you know, I'm sitting, there's a convention there.
I'm talking to people from the convention doing my salesy thing. Yeah. To be honest,
the convention doing my salesy thing, get upstairs and I'm beat. It's gotta be 1130.
And I have to meet the customer in the morning. And you're out of your time zone too.
I'm out of my time. 1130 local time. Right. Right. So my time, what is that? 2 30. So I get
upstairs, go to sleep, wake up, turn on my laptop, a strange fan noise and beeping.
Oh no. Yeah. So I go, I do the first meeting. Fine. I whip out the Mac book,
install a windows bootcamp partition. I'm sorry. Wait, wait, wait. So was the Galago at this point
just unusable? It wouldn't turn on. Ah, okay. So you brought two machines. Second machine's the
Mac book. Mac book. Is this a USB-C Mac book or is this amazing? It is USB-C. Okay. All right.
And I had the correct adapter that came with it. Right. So I partitioned the drive bootcamp,
whole thing. I let it run all day cause Griffin runs on Linux and windows, right? It doesn't
run on Mac. So fine. We run the windows version. No big deal. Most, you know, the Linux version
is, it doesn't matter. Right. For the, for the end of, for the purposes of a demo,
it doesn't matter. Right. So if you've got windows 10 on there and Griffin runs fine,
good to go. Runs fine. Good to go. So that's how I did my whole Tejas trip.
Fly to New Jersey. Now I'm still thinking it's just a bad cable and there's nothing
wrong with the Gallico, right? Like, you know what? My mistake. I didn't take the
cable that they sent with it. Get to New Jersey and a relative of mine who runs a small business
has a problem. She had left her computers plugged in and it destroyed her only computer.
No. Like from a power issue? Yeah. So I try to recover it. It's toast.
What kind of machine is this? It's a desktop? This is like a cheapo. Windows box? Yeah. Best
fights. This is nothing. So I'm thinking, you know what? Gallico is fine. I'm sure if I plug
it into the right cable, whatever. I have Mac build servers in the cloud. Now I'll just give
her the Mac book or Mac book pro cause she's in a bind. Yeah. Oh man. Wow. So I wipe all my stuff
off. I give it to her. No, you formatted it. Everything's backed up. I didn't lose any data.
Oh man. Okay. Okay. So, so I fly to, you gave her a Mac book while you're in the state of unknown
hardware at that particular point. So I had the iPad pro we ordered on the live show for the
Apple event. I had shipped there to New Jersey. So you acquire the iPad pro at this point?
Acquired the iPad pro and I spent the rest of my entire trip solely working on the iPad pro.
No shit. No. Yeah. That's exactly what had to happen. And, and wait a minute. So you're telling
me you never got the Gallico working again? Ah, so I get back to the sunshine state.
I thought I had it at first. I thought I couldn't get it to turn on. Then I got it to turn on
about two hours ago. I thought I had it working and now it doesn't hold the charge.
So it will work on AC power. It will not work, which is useless to me. Right? Right. Cause it's,
you're traveling. I'm traveling. So I might just send it and see what they charge me.
System 76 to repair it, which is fine. Or I might do something else. I don't know. I,
I have to say that I'm thinking of going back to punch cards.
Yeah. Right. Just pack them all up. Put them in a bag. I am like, I am like the,
the apocalypse of laptops here. Yeah. That's why I was asking you guys in the, in the JV Slack.
So how's that Dell XPS 13 look? Yeah. Well, I mean, the nice thing about the iPad pro I gotta
say is the USB-C charging. So I recently went, I just got back from Texas actually.
And the thing that was really nice for me is I brought one charging cable with me. Funny enough,
I bought a, I, I not, not because I have a Mac book, but I brought the Mac book pro charging
cable. And then I took with me my Lenovo T four 80 and an iPad pro and my pixel three. And I was
able to charge all of my devices with one cable. It was glorious. It was, I can't, for somebody
who's like frequently quickly traveling right now, it was, it was liberating to bring one.
USB-C's gotta be a requirement for whatever I do here. Cause this all started because I mistook
my wife's old Dell XPS cable, which then I got yelled at for taking her charger
for my Gallego cable that wasn't paying attention. Interestingly, I also got the iPad pro,
as you know, I got like the cheapest one I could with LTE on a pencil and the keyboard,
which is still a ridiculous amount of money to spend for a device, but unrelated. I also just
kind of have started waking up at 4 am for, for months now I've been waking up at 4 am. And
what I do is I, I go generally eat like breakfast and I watch something on YouTube and then I try
to go back to bed and maybe I sleep for 30 minutes. And so instead of what I've started
doing about a month ago is it just got up. Like if I wake up at 4 am without an alarm clock,
let's just get up. But then like, seriously, what the frick do you do with yourself? You're up at
4 am like not 5 am not 6 am. Like, what do you do with yourself? Because you go on Twitter and
fight with Kara Swisher. That's what you do. That's what you do. What I did. And I know this makes me
sound like a total douchebag, but it, it fricking works for me is I took the iPad pro and I started
going out to like coffee shops and stuff. And I just started working from there before I even
come into the studio. So I have like, I have this, I have this period of time that is around other
people that keeps me awake. It keeps me alive. It, it, it prevents me from falling back asleep.
And then I come into the studio and I do my real work. But during this period of time,
you know, two hours, an hour and a half, whatever it is, I am exclusively using the iPad pro right
now. I feel like a d-bag, but so it's really working for me. I ended up writing scripts on
the iPad pro using ISH to, and oh my God, it actually worked. Yeah. So you and I are both
using ISH then. This is great. This is, this is a, you have to, you have to get on like the test
pilot program, but it is an entire Linux environment, an Alpine Linux environment
on the iPad. It is even emulating x86 hardware, which is disgusting, but it's, it works.
Well, no, you know what's more disgusting? The iPad pro was more powerful than every device
I've destroyed on this trip. Oh man. Let me tell you the speed and performance that,
so here's the other reason. So the iPad pro it doesn't work for anyone out there who's
never used iOS before. If you're not a happy existing iOS user, do not waste your money
buying one of these things. It's not for you. If you use the Linux desktop and you don't have
an iOS device or you love Android, don't get the iPad pro. It's not a device for you. If
you are an existing and established iOS user and you understand the limitations of iOS,
and you can excel within those limitations for certain types of workflows, I think you
should consider it because I'll give you an example. I get a lot of emails that I have
to convert to PDF and then save the Dropbox. That is a two second process on the iPad pro.
I have to do a lot of Slack and other apps that would be electron on my Linux desktop
that are native applications on the iPad pro and it's fast. It feels better, right?
I do all my go to meetings, Zoom meetings, and all that stuff on the iPad pro. It's so much
better than the Linux or Windows experience. It's way better. It's just way, it's way better.
I shared Google drive and walked them through a doc. I had a meeting this morning and walked
the folks through a document on an iPad pro and I don't think that any idea was on an iPad.
Yeah. And then if you want to participate in the expensive Apple ecosystem, then things
like the AirPods work really well with the iPad pro so you can be somewhere and you can
just open the AirPod case and put the AirPods in and you're doing a, you're doing a virtual meeting
right there from a, from a fricking tablet. And to see how far I could push this, I just recently
got a USB-C to USB-B cable from Amazon. And I hooked up a production grade Zoom U22 audio
interface to my iPad pro with an XLR microphone, like a professional studio microphone, a microphone
that costs $300. And then you have to buy the $60 XLR cable and the audio interface and then plug
all of that into the iPad pro. But I, you know, I have all that stuff. So I just got this like
$9 cable, hooked it up and I'm able to input high grade studio quality microphone audio into the
iPad pro over USB-C.
So when I got my hands on mine, before I decided to give the MacBook away, I did some testing on
the USB-C interface, that's accessible via Swift or theoretically Objective-C on the iOS SDK,
but I did my tests in Swift. It's not locked down. I mean, they don't make certain things easy. So
you have to write your own, like file, like there's a lot of stuff. If you want to do something,
you have to do it, right? But well, storage sucks, but everything else, audio devices,
interface devices, video devices, monitors, HDMI, ethernet, or even using a tablet in a factory,
let's say to flash IOT devices or IOT boards. If you have USB-C to USB-C and you have a custom app
on iOS, technically that's just like an opening up. I mean, this isn't gross oversimplification,
but opening a port and just flash it onto the board. Well, this could be a real,
it could be basically do anything you want. Maybe. I mean, you got to keep in mind it's Apple and
they're going to lock this shit down as much as they can. No, it's not locked down. I literally
did it. It's not locked down. Yeah. I mean, it's, yes, but at the same time-
Going outbound, right? I'm talking outbound. So I'm talking your code on iOS goes over USB-C
and interacts with another device. I'm not talking about modifying the system.
Yes. Okay. All right. Absolutely. Yeah. Yeah, there, I agree. I have had, and you too, it's funny,
really super condensed amount of travel. Oh man, I wish I had my, um,
I don't have the app with me, but I've done something like 60,000 miles in the last like
four months. Um, it's just, it's unbelievable. I'm like, I get like access to clubs and stuff.
Like I can go in the Alaskan lounge now and just-
Nice. Yeah, it's great. But I tell you what, I, I, I totally spend all of that time surveying
everyone in the lounge and not really, really, I mean, there's some, but I mean, really almost
everyone is using a tablet of some form in the lounges and at the airports and on the plane.
And yeah, I'm a dick bag, but I'm buying the premium seating or once or twice, maybe first
class, but every now and then too, like- Naughty boy.
Yeah. Well, I haven't submitted those expenses yet. We'll see how that goes.
But, um, I, I also am, I'm coaching it up, you know, 95% of the time and-
Yeah, I'm, I'm, I'm coach plus usually, but that's about it.
Coach plus my, yeah. Coach plus is my average with some coach and the rare first class only
when it's like the only seat available.
Although I, I did treat myself to business class this time and I was like,
you can call me Mr. Dominic. Thank you.
And you get, you get the free booze. You get the free booze.
Free booze. Well, you know what's funny? I have flown so many Southwest United flights
now in the last few months. Yeah. I get free booze tickets anyway.
Oh, really? That's nice. Yeah. Well, have you ever been on a Southwest flight?
Oh, I mean, yeah, but not recently. Nobody wants you sober. Nobody wants to be sober.
Well, so, uh, if you want the commuter flight between Washington and Texas,
you go with Alaska airlines. It's a nonstop three hour, 50 minute flight. So,
I signed up for their lounges and I'm at the bar and I'm there with probably, I don't know,
15 other people and all of us are on tablets. Now, the great thing is, is it's all, you can drink
just part of the membership. So, if you fly better after having a few drinks,
I do everything better. Which airline is this? Alaska you said?
Yeah, it's Alaska. Yeah. Delta. I'm also looking at Delta now because I'm flying enough on Delta
that I might, I might be able to fly better. I'm not sure. I'm not sure.
I'm flying enough on Delta that I might, I might be able to get into the Delta lounge.
Same thing. Yeah. United is a respectable two drinks. Oh, really? They limit you.
Well, you can, they free to, uh, you pay for the rest.
I will tell you, I mean, I don't get, I don't get sloshed cause I think they're making them
a little on the light side, but, uh, I've never walked out of an,
I've never walked out of an Alaska lounge without at least three drinks for free.
Well that, and I don't know about you. Oh, the other thing is I was carrying,
I didn't tell you about the TSA. This is going to be a weird show folks. Sorry,
but this is hilarious. So I was carrying 3d light scanners in my luggage.
Wait, what? Yeah. Go to peel 3d. I was carrying one of those. Just peel 3d. Google it. If you
people are interested. Um, the TSA was very, very unhappy. Really?
Well, they look like, uh, weird guns. Are you doing regular animal style PS TSA? Like
I did not. I did not get my pre-check approved yet because I didn't go do the, uh, I still have to
go do that. What's the matter with you? What is it? Two laptops, two skaters.
It's 10 times easier than getting your passport and getting your passport. Isn't that hard?
You, you, uh, you, you just do a quick interview and you're done. And I know,
I know I gotta go do it. Everybody's got TSA pre-checked. So there are lines. So don't think
it's going to save you a ton of time, but it means you don't have to empty your bag.
You don't have to take off your shoes. I mean, I'm telling you, man, I have gotten through with
stuff that is not legal. And I mean, I shouldn't say that because they're probably listening,
but the TSA pre-check is the way to go. That's for sure. Because when you look at my audio
recording equipment, it looks like it's like a bomb. Like it just looks like I'm carrying a
legal contraband, like custom motherboards. Right. I have, I have circuit boards. I have
coiled cables. I have tubular devices that have modules in them. I mean, it looks like I am
carrying like a weapon of mass destruction. And so TSA constantly would be like, what is this? What
is this? So I got the pre-check and now they still scan the bag, but they've never stopped me.
So you got to get the pre-check or clear. Okay. I got to try that. I don't, I don't know what clear
is. Anyway. Well, clear is another, it's like a, it's a commercial competitor to TSA that, that a
lot of airports contract. So if you haven't seen clear, then it's not one for you to sign up.
All the airports I go through have clear. Yeah. So you're, so you, you traveling with two bags is
super heavy. Are you checking luggage every time? I had to check one. So what I figured out, so I
was depositing some of this hardware in Texas. So the trip, as soon as I got to Texas, everything
was a lot simpler because then I didn't need to check a bag because it was one of those situations
where it's like a luggage set. So one bag was just equipment protected by clothing, which was checked,
which I did get a lovely note from the TSA that it was searched. And the other bag was the rest of
the crap and some clothes. So you get the iPad pro, you get some time to play with it before you
hand over the Mac book back book. Did you set it up new? Did you transfer from an iCloud image? What
I never transfer. I always set it up. Do you, I did this time. I went new this time. Yeah. Yeah.
I just don't trust the iCloud. Did you get the pencil with it? I did. I spent way too much on a
tablet. Yeah. Yeah. What are your impressions though of the pencil? I'll, I'll, I'll tell you
mine just to put them out there. So you know what my bias is. I also got the Apple pencil because I
thought, you know, if I'm going to get an iPad, I haven't bought one for three or four years.
If I'm getting an iPad, I'm going to get an iPad. I'm going to get one with LTE. I'm going to get
one with the keyboard. I'm going to get one with the pencil. And I, I knew that since I bought my
last iPad. In fact, it's the reason I did not buy the last iPad pro because I knew I was going to
spend a lot of money and I just wasn't ready to spend that money. So I want everybody to understand
that like, you know, this is something I calculated three years out, but it was still a painful
purchase for me. And when I got the, when I got the pencil, I was very worried that it would be a
total fucking waste of money because it's way too expensive. And it only works with this iPad,
doesn't work with my phone, doesn't work with any of the kids I have. It doesn't work with my
iPad. It doesn't work with any of the kids iPads, doesn't work with a Dia's iPhone. It only works
with my super nice iPad pro. So, and I don't draw. I stick figures. CPG gray makes me look like a
child. So I was really concerned that I wouldn't get any use out of the pencil. But what I realize
now after using it for a few weeks is the pencil is the new mouse in a lot of ways. Has your
thought changed? Not exactly, but I think you should keep going before I jump in. Well, I'm
using it for tech selection, cursor, cursor, like positioning. And I mean, part of that is because
the fricking iPad doesn't have the ability like you have on the iPhone where you can press down
on the keyboard and you get a mouse cursor, which you basically can convert the iPhone keyboard
into a trackpad, which is great for editing text. But you know what's way better at working with
text is a larger screen like the iPad, but you don't fricking get that push down on the keyboard
functionality. So I use the pencil for that quite a bit. A big part of my show prep is highlighting
sections of articles for news. The pencil works great for that. And just kind of finessing the
interface. I use the pencil quite a bit for that as well. So I have found it to be kind of like
mouse 2.0 in a lot of ways. So I like the pencil a lot as well. My issue was that apps we still
don't take advantage of the pencil. And I kept wanting it to be able to do things that I felt
were very intuitive, that it just doesn't do. Right. If the app support of the pencil was as
good of support as they have for the keyboard, it would be great. Like the keyboard is surprisingly
well supported. You can hold down the- Yeah, it's really good. Yeah, you see all the available
commands. Well, and a weird collection of Mac, like if you've used a Mac for a long time,
Mac keyboard shortcuts just work. Which I find- Yeah, yeah. Like Alt-Tab and copy and paste and
all those kinds of things. As Varitunda points out, in a way, we're rediscovering the stylus.
And it is that. Going back to our travel theme here, what works really, really well for my lady
and I is to do a Google image search of a high resolution calendar. So like January or December,
like a basic business calendar. And then she takes that image from Google images-
Wait, wait, a basic picture. Does it come with a pumpkin spice latte? I can't let that one go.
No, you know what I'm saying? Like it's just like the most clear grid calendar for like January 2019.
Oh yeah, sure. Okay. It's just really plain, just a high resolution. Like somebody just created this
and then posted online. So what she'll do on the iPad Pro is she'll go Google images for like
February, January. She'll get a great looking calendar that has basically nothing on it.
She saves that to the photos or actually no, I'm wrong. What she does is she imports that photo
into a new note. And then she brings that into Apple notes and she illustrates our entire month
on these calendars. Like she can pinch to zoom to get like a lot of working room in a particular day.
And she can illustrate an entire like road trip or I'm planning to go to Fosdam, which is
in Brussels. Like that's a massive trip because I'm leaving from Texas, not Washington because
I have to go to Brussels mid trip. So it's one of those, okay, we're going to travel to here,
then we're going to fly to here, then we're going to drive to here, then we're going to
fly to Brussels, then we're going to fly back and then we're going to drive to here.
And I'm a visual person. And so being able to actually draw all that out on a calendar,
goes from like nebulous concept that I can't wrap my head around to, oh, okay, well now I'm going to
prep the team to expect when I'm going to be gone. It really makes a difference.
And it's the pencil, it's not a mouse. You know what I mean? Drawing.
Yeah, no, I get it. Right. Drawing makes, well, it's because it's like I take notes by hand still.
And it's just because like I can just quickly draw up like a simple UML diagram, right? I get
people who have worked with me will know that like, I'm a big fan of just walking up to the
whiteboard. Let's just like draw it with the system. What didn't broad strokes look like, right?
Do you agree though, that no one should buy this? And it is an extremely limited platform
where the operating system is one of the biggest constraints and that it is a total waste of money?
Well, I don't like absolutes, right?
I feel like it is both one of the best computers I have ever owned in my entire life going back
to the 80s. And it's also one of the biggest wastes of money because a lot of that power is
just completely untapped. So it's weird for me. Like, you know, I had to draft my flight simulation
rigging to be my desktop. That's what I'm talking about. I'm in the elementary partition right now
because I've destroyed all my laptops. And the iPad Pro is not quite as powerful as this machine
because yay, graphics card. Right. But it's not that far off either, right? Like this is...
I mean, if you deal with a machine that's all Intel parts, the iPad Pro probably kicks its ass.
It is in a weird way, the best portable computer. And I'm going to use the word computer here
that I have ever owned or I think seen. That's not like just a giant thing that dies in 45 minutes.
But because of Apple's weird hangups about software distribution and like how you can
access and use the system and frankly, file access, which I never thought in 2018,
going on 2019 very shortly, that I would be complaining about like, you know, file access.
Yeah, kind of. I mean, in a way, though, the integration with cloud services is pretty slick.
Like if it's in iCloud or everything on the cloud or in Dropbox. Yeah, you're set. Yeah, exactly.
I don't know about that. Right. Oh, totally. It's I want it on a USB thumb drive, to be honest with
you. And I'd like to then copy it to the local iPad storage, which is crazy fast.
I am hoping that like, like, you know, the USB port being relatively open
gives me a lot of hope that like, you know what, they're going to make this a true utilitarian
device. And I know it's not going to happen because it's Apple and whatever, but they're
going to come close enough that it doesn't that it's OK. Yeah, right now you're still very like
like I watched the announcement live and I bought the NBA 2K game.
It's awesome, right? Like, you know what? I haven't really done console gaming in a while.
I don't do a lot of PC gaming, but for like games like Civilization and, you know,
like Rogue Legacy, indie games. But even then, I barely get to play anymore.
To me, if you just showed me like a video of someone playing that game,
like without showing me the device, I would assume they were on like an Xbox 360,
right? Even like a low budget Xbox. I know it's phenomenal. It's right.
I mean, have you tried the NBA game? It's the graphics on this thing are they're
literally console level graphics. It's it's unbelievable what Apple's doing. So that's why
it strikes me as funny that you think the big problem is the file system. Like, I agree with
Wes and I don't think that's the big problem. I think that's a problem. I think the big problem is
Apple's general philosophy of not letting app developers basically treat it like a PC,
which is what it is. Yeah. Okay. All right. I mean, I guess and maybe this is a mistake on my
part, but I'm giving them a pass until WWDC and iOS 13. If they don't fucking make good in June
with iOS 13, then it's on like Donkey Kong. I'm going to be so good. What do you what do you mean?
What do you what do you mean? What's good? iOS 13 needs to be an iPad focused release. It needs
to make the iPad a real machine like it needs to be all about all of these little rough edges.
And the file system is not it. Like, I don't think it's not the OS. It's even like forget about like
the OS being like kind of mobile focus and a little bit of a pain in the ass. And it's built
for a phone. Right. Yeah. Well, yeah. I mean, certainly there's quality of life things, but I
feel like we're talking about two different things where I'm talking about the fact that
Apple will reject apps that do things that are like interesting with the device. Ah, okay. Like,
if I believed all right, let's let's let's back it out there. And thank you for to our new owners,
Linux Academy. They're going to hate this. If I believed that I could write an iOS app,
just like I could like submitted elementary app or even a Mac OS app today.
I would not even look at replacing my dead laptops with anything but a Mac.
Because this is the see what annoys me is this is the tablet device that could fulfill my long
standing or Windows RT tablet dream. But I have no faith that they're going to actually allow
developers to do what needs to be done. Right. Right. And this is where I think the iPad Pro
is not an appealing purchase to most people. This is what I was getting at. It's the apps
aren't powerful. Well, I mean, they're they are very powerful within the limitations that Apple
allows them. I have been very I mean, they're beautiful and they're fast. I mean, powerful as
an they're getting they're getting legitimately, though they're getting way the fuck better than
they used to be. And I don't swear a lot on this show. Usually that's that's your domain.
My department. Right. I have had a couple of come to Jesus moments with the iPad Pro
where I have I kid you not on two different occasions. This is my thought process.
Oh, OK, so I will never do this again on any other OS other than iOS.
For two different major video mother effing editing and audio mother effing editing,
I have I have seen a lot. Yeah. Oh, my. Oh, oh, oh, my goodness. Oh, my goodness. Basically,
there is a Final Cut equivalent for iOS that is. Yes, there is. Fantastic. And it is efficient.
It is clean. It is fast. It totally takes advantage of the iPad hardware. And then
there is a multitrack audio editor called Fairight that is available for iOS. And it is
perfect at exactly the type of workflow that I now have with audio editing, because I now have
Joe and Ham that edit these shows for us. I'm not doing the show editing. But anytime you hear
real time audio, anytime you hear a clip or a sound effect, that's from me. And I make those edits.
And Fairight is a multitrack audio editing system that is perfect on the iPad Pro. It is perfect
with the keyboard. And it is exceptionally perfect with the pencil. And I can bang out audio in
seconds with this thing. I have now successfully edited six different audio projects using Fairight,
including audio that I have captured over the USB interface into the iPad Pro directly into Fairight
and MP4s that I have downloaded from YouTube using shortcuts to download them from YouTube
and automatically import them into Fairight. Like I hear a great clip. I can then create just by the
share menu an action that downloads that video and then extracts the audio from it and then imports
that audio into Fairight. And I can be editing as fast as the internet connection allows. And it is
10 times faster than I could ever do on the desktop. I'm not going back. I'm always doing that
via iOS from now on. My mind is actually blown. My brain is scattered across the back of the wall
here. Chris, you're seducing me. I mean, the apps are getting way more powerful. They are
way more powerful. No, I agree with you. I've played with the USB interface. So for a show
called Coder Radio, there was no code reason why I can't do like the literal 75 field notebooks
full of app ideas I have. Well, except for there's no Xcode for iPad. No, no, no. I mean,
I mean, I don't care. I'll do it on a Mac, right? Two or Windows if I'm using Xamarin, or hell,
I could do Xamarin on Linux now because yay, JetBrains Rider. How do I see everything you
just told me makes me think that I'm a little dated on my view of the app review team here.
That I'm still fighting a battle from like 2013 2014. Well, I think it's not your fault. I blame
Apple because Apple since the beginning has made this iPad versus laptop comparison. I mean, there
was quotes from Steve Jobs about how the iPad was going to be the real computer and that laptops
are going to be trucks. And then even in the most recent Apple event, they had a comparison of iPad
sales where they were just blowing away laptop sales. And they were making the comparison right
there on their gigantic projector saying how much more iPad sales there are than laptop sales.
So Apple is themselves stoking this conversation of comparing tablets to laptops, which then makes
everyone compare tablets to real computers that can do real work. That it's not a fair comparison
yet. But if you look at this as a new device that supplements the work and does not replace the work
of the x86 type computer or the desktop computer or the laptop computer, but maybe except for
but maybe accelerates at certain limited types of workflows, your slack, your emails, your audio
editing, your video editing, maybe your photo workflows. Because think about how this thing is
built. It's built with CPU cores that are hyper accelerated at specific kinds of tasks,
photo manipulation, processing. No doubt. Right. So it's not a replacement, is it? It is a
supplement, isn't it? It is a supplement and not a replacement. And so if you think about how you
work, like for me in the morning, I prefer to do more conceptual work. I'll write out show docs.
I'll make big plans for the for the department for the week. I'll email people that are on the
East Coast. Like I'll do these things that are more mental and I'll do that in the morning
from an iPad because it's slack, it's air mail, it's telegram, it's Zoom. Exactly how I do it.
Yeah. Well, and and and with that in mind, then it just really comes down to is it worth the money
when you combine the performance? It's a little rough, though. It's rough, isn't it? It's like,
are you willing to buy a phone, a laptop, a desktop and a tablet?
Like, I got to be I got to be honest with you. If I had known like the day I was watching
Lana Del Rey and drooling on myself that for those who didn't see the Apple event,
Lana Del Rey was the singer. I I almost certainly would have ordered the iPad with
with the Apple branded case and the Apple branded pencil. You know what I mean? Like,
yeah, because that was I mean, it was a thousand dollars. Mine was mine was, I think,
a little over tax. It was like thirteen hundred. Yeah, that's a laptop. I mean, seriously, that's
your. Yeah, it is. It is. Now, for me, I'm in a situation where my laptop has now been purchased
by my employer. So I no longer have to finance the lab. And Chris rub that salt. So this is really
my computer. This is this is the first computer I've ever bought since I've gone full time working
for someone else that is paying for my equipment. And legitimately, I don't expect to buy another
computer. And when I travel and I was trying to get to this point earlier, what what seems to
validate what you and I are talking about and the reason why I'm really kind of willing to go all in
on this subject is when I when I'm in the airport, when I'm traveling, I I almost exclusively see
tablets. Now, I have I have seen a couple of laptops. I recently told a story on Linux Unplugged
about a Microsoft employee who was trying to make a convertible laptop work. But the reality is they
just they crush your available space and they make they make it so that even the space that a
12 inch laptop takes up is not enough. Plus, you got crappy power that you can maybe plug into.
So if you have something that charges over USB, you're way better off. But secondarily,
kind of just the like the just the nuts and bolts of it is when you're traveling. So you're in an
airplane. The the media experience where you can watch videos and the TV shows that are on a local
server, sure, it's just way better on mobile devices. It it really effing sucks on Windows.
I watched a passenger just recently spend nearly an entire four hour flight trying to get Windows 10
to stream the videos because you got no Internet. Right. So if you need to go get a flash update or
something like that, your S.O.L. You're done. Right. But if you're on a iOS or Android device,
you've got the app installed and you're good to go. It's HTML5 because there's no flash.
So I just want to throw one point here as someone who spent a lot of money and time trying to make
WinRT work. I hate two in one devices. I want them to die. Yeah, because each side is sort of
two minutes compromised. Yeah, right. It sounds like a good idea, but it's just not. It's an
awkward tablet. The software you have the right to make that work is actually really shitty and
complicated. What most people do is just like take the desktop version and just like blow up the
buttons a little bit. It could you know, I could see it working if we had 10 years of iteration
on software design to make it work right. But it is so rough right now that it is supremely
frustrating to use. Yeah, and I don't I don't think that's the direction things are going.
I mean, for all my skepticism about the iPad Pro, I have a feeling next time Chris and I are done
taking planes. I'm like, so let's talk about Mac OS Mojave because that's what I'm all kidding
aside. Do you think so? I actually think in a way it makes me a better Linux user to have an iPad.
So, again, I'm thinking about developer opportunities, though.
Yeah, I think there this is see my vision of the of the tablet revolution was going to be that
there would be pro level applications for tablets that really made a lot of sense.
Ah, see my pro on my computer and my consumer like basic bitch apps are on my tablet.
But you're like a hyper pro, right? I'm talking pro apps like write some company
who has like a hangar or a factory, some custom tablet app for their format or quality control
people or something like that. Right. Yeah. And then that makes a lot of sense for them.
Yeah, I. I'm very conflicted, Chris. You know, you've really hurt me here. This is.
I feel like it is a it's a rich person's toy and not that I am rich. I am not rich,
but it is. Oh, I'm sorry, Mr. Vice, Mr. Gore, Mr. Gore. Nobody. Nobody in my situation
after years and years and years and years and years of grinding it out to make a podcast network work
is is rich. Nobody. I don't know about a podcast network, but tell me more about
grinding it out for 10 years. Oh, yeah. It just leaves you devastated. Right. So I mean, at best,
at best, I'm back to not even, you know. Oh, I had. Oh, what was it? Oh, just something just
recently just crossed my. Oh, garbage bags. So, yeah, garbage bags. This is how my life has changed.
I'm not rich, but. So my garbage really stinks right now in my house, you know, my RV, it's
full of garlic. I roasted a I roasted a bunch of garlic and then I like I threw out like the husks
and everything and the and the garbage just frickin reeks in a delicious way. But it makes
because the RV is only 47 feet long, it makes the whole RV smell like garlic. And we're going into
two days of this whole RV smelling like garlic. And I'm sitting there in the RV finally by myself
for the first time in weeks. And I'm thinking to myself. Why haven't because the garbage is only
half full because I haven't been home much and neither has the idea and neither of the kids.
So, like, why is the garbage only half full? And yet I'm still putting up with the smell,
like, why haven't I taken it out yet? And I'm like, am I that lazy that I haven't just collected
the garbage and taken it out in the last couple of days? And then I realized, oh, no, what it was
is I didn't want to waste the money. The negative space in the garbage bag. I only have so much room,
right? I mean, I only have so much money. I can only buy so many garbage bags. And if we run out
of garbage bags before my next paycheck, I can't buy any more garbage bags. So we need to make
every garbage bag last and therefore everything must smell like garlic for the next three days,
because God forbid that I throw out a garbage bag that is half full. And I'm sat there and I realized,
you know what? I can now afford more garbage bags. I can take that out.
Do you know what the worst part of this conversation is? That's exactly what I do with
garbage bags. Till they're full to the brim, baby. It doesn't matter if they reek, right?
Yeah. Hey, listen, let me burn some candles.
I mean, that's why, like, I say all this stuff about the iPad Pro with, like, a lot of couching,
because to me, like, I understand how much that money means. $1,200. And I didn't even get enough
storage. But, because I got the 256 gig unit. But here's how I feel about the iPad Pro now.
I'm not shitting you when I say, when I look back at the last 20 plus years of me building
and buying computers, this is one of the best computers I have ever bought. And with that said,
if I were to fill this iPad up, I will buy another iPad Pro. Because, in fact, I can already envision
how multiple iPad Pros would make me more productive. I have never had a computer that
has been so universally successful in how I use it for work, how I use it for pleasure,
how my little daughter wants to use a computer, and how my fiance wants to use a computer.
I have never had a machine that has been that successful across that range of work demands,
while having outstanding battery life, mind-blowing performance, and USB-C universal charging. It,
to me, is one of the best computers I have owned in the last 25 plus, maybe 30 years.
I actually agree with everything you just said.
Really? Even with all the limitations of iOS and Apple's ecosystem?
I still don't think the limitations are really iOS. I mean, my file system complaint,
I think you correctly shut down as being petty. That's my word that Chris did not call me petty.
Please don't tweet.
What about, okay, but what about the limitations of iOS? It's a thing like XMM points out. What
about multiple fricking user accounts? iOS is-
We're going to get there though, right? That's iOS 13. That's going back to your argument.
The limitation that, the only thing that stops me from just calling up the Apple
business rep like, yo, ship me a MacBook, is has app review found Jesus?
If I come up with something really cool for iOS, and I spend the next
N months developing it, and being a variable, of course, am I just going to get rejected?
You know what I mean? Am I going to have another winter of no product launches?
Yes. Unless they really figure it out. And I don't, I mean,
Fairight, to be honest, really is impressive. It's an amazing, it's one of those unassuming
applications when you launch it, it seems simple. It gets, I mean, it even says,
it says, I recognize that you've hooked up the Zoom U22 USB audio interface. It has the full
name of the device and everything. So that's, I mean, that's getting close.
I am trying to figure out like Photoshop's coming to iPad,
that app you're discussing for editing video and audio.
What is it that Apple sees this device as? Because right now I see it as a case by case basis.
They like Photoshop, so Photoshop goes in. They like media production,
so media production is okay. But what if you want to do something a little crazier,
right? Or not, I don't like the word crazy, but if you want to do something a little more
engineering-y. Because this is the Windows RT dream, the trademark pending, come true.
It really is. Like from the device, you know what, that A whatever processor is amazing.
I mean, if you want, if you're really nerdy, go look at the Geekbench scores.
I could buy a new MacBook Pro today and it would not be as powerful in most cases as this iPad Pro,
unless I just spend like $3,000. It could do more though.
It could do more. But as a software developer who has a lot of experience in Coco,
I should really be able to capitalize on this, not to be a dirty capitalist.
I know, I agree. But the fact that if I spend all hundreds of man hours working on this,
my dogs are raging Android fans and they're really upset. I don't know if you can hear
them in the background. If I spend months developing a iOS-specific pro-level engineering
product, what assurance would I have that Apple doesn't turn around and just say, no?
Let's say they say yes. What assurance do I have they don't just feature some competitor one day,
or at the same time? The whole gatekeeper thing still rubs me.
Yeah. Yeah. If it's a pro machine, we need to be able to load our own pro applications.
I would think I should be able to write custom... Like Riffin is a product I sell
that is not on any app store. You have to call me and you buy it.
Or Jupyter Broadcasting is developing this automation system to encode, upload, publish,
and distribute podcasts. That is a very custom piece of software. It's never going to be approved
in the app store, but it would be great to be able to execute that stuff from the tablet,
especially one that could encode audio and video super fast, like the iPad Pro.
And they're never going to say okay to that. That's never going to get accepted.
So it's not really pro. I would challenge, why do you need the app store?
For these type of customers, why do you need the app?
Right. They should have called it the iPad Plus, not the iPad Pro.
It's not a professional machine. It is a pro consumer machine that is really, really kick ass
at doing consumer workflows or basic, you know, mid-level management and up workflows.
People that are making things and creating things, we have to use crazy shims like ISH,
which is emulating an entire x86 stack and then running Alpine Linux on top of that.
You know what? You know what? That's my tool of the week, ISH.
That's my tool of the week, ISH, but it is insane the way that works.
It's so good, man.
But it's so messed up what those folks have to do to get that app to work.
Yeah. It's one developer as far as I understand.
It's one guy. Yeah, that's my understanding.
One guy, and he's got a lot of plans. And I'm using it right now.
And it's got a package manager. It's great.
Well, you know what? They let ISH in. So again, you said no, but maybe I am dated.
It's not from the app store. You got to get the test pilot.
Oh, that's right. You got to be on test flight.
Yeah, test flight. That's what it is. Test flight.
Yeah. So we'll see. I think that's actually a bellwether.
If ISH-
Like if ISH is in the app store, then I think I'm just wrong.
And, you know, I'm not even asserting that Apple's the problem here actually.
I don't know. That's my concern.
We'll see. Maybe people haven't tried. I doubt it. I doubt it. We'll see.
Command lines, ISH, or God forbid, God forbid, Apple ship the BSD user subsystem for iOS
that actually gives you access.
Wait, wait, wait. Can we just summon Alan? Alan, let's go.
I know, right? I mean, Apple could ship this. It doesn't need a whole x86 emulator.
Apple could expose the user land, even in a contained environment.
They could expose some of the user land utilities that are there on the iPad running natively in iOS.
It's all there.
The fact that you have to construct a virtual machine and then build a user land on top of it
with a distribution that's built for containers is ridiculous and shouldn't exist.
And Apple could just flick their fingers and create a subsystem for iOS,
like Microsoft has for Windows and like Google is doing for Chrome right now.
And if Apple wants to keep up with what their competitors are doing,
they better take a look at this and they better take a look at ISH.
And in their best interest, they better let this thing in the app store
because otherwise they're going to get left behind.
People want access to Bash. They want the command line.
And it's there. Apple just doesn't give it to you right now.
I'm going to abstract that out a little bit.
You and I want Bash, right? And in some cases when I'm drunk, Z shell.
Developers want, but developers want Bash.
But people in general just want to get their job done.
And they, you know, I got to be honest with you.
Like we get some criticism on Reddit that I'm always talking about hardware.
I am so tired of paving laptops.
Hmm.
Like this is a dumb problem to have.
It is right. It's so exhausting.
Like, you know, who's working for me?
My very boring, very ugly Dell Optiplex tower that's sitting here, right?
I hooked up a throttle and a trigger to it to make it a, uh,
and put in a beefier graphics card. And it was my flight sim machine.
Now I needed it as a desktop. So it has an L I booted it in its elementary partition.
I needed more storage. I'm sorry.
And people call me an old man on Twitter for this.
You know what I did, Chris? I bought a terabyte, 720 RPM drive or 7,200 RPM drive.
And I, and one of the many open days when I opened the case, by the way,
Wait, wait, what you have, you have a physical drive that you're putting in your desktop.
A physical drive that you're putting inside a machine.
And it took me, and I had my two year old sitting next to me.
I let him help me with that. I let him do one of the latches.
It took like 10 minutes and it's shared between the Linux partition and the windows one.
Yeah.
And it just, it's like not, not to like troll Apple. It just works.
And otherwise the hard drive was a hundred percent full.
I was going to have to buy a new machine or do a crazy external thing, which I think is crazy.
It doesn't have Thunderbolt. So like, I don't know, man. I'm tired of this crap.
I'm tired of being like, I got a new laptop. Here's for a few,
which is weird because next episode we have a laptop review.
Yeah. I was just going to, so at the beginning of this, I was going to ask you
if you had imaged or if you had started a new, but either way you go, it's pretty freaking
easy for me to say it's really painless because you have all of the app store
or restores. So you can restore any app you've ever bought. And if you're a LastPass user,
the integration of LastPass and Face ID means that you can just pop into the app,
go to the login screen, Face ID checks your face and it logs you into the application and Bob's
your uncle, you're signed into the app. My point is the process to set up an iPad is 10 times faster
than the process to set up a PC. In some of, in some respects is because I can do about 10 times
less stuff, you know, but the stuff I can do, holy shit, man. I got that set up. So I got that iPad
set up and good to go in two hours. It takes two days for a laptop for me. I got to fiddle through
everything. Well, that's the thing. So let's say like, I want to jump on this iPad per opportunity
and then we should wrap up because we have another recording. He's going to take, let's just say like,
I got up tomorrow morning and like drove to the app store and bought a MacBook pro, right? It will
take me because I have other things that I need to do at least, at least until the weekend to actually
be up and running. Yeah. And yes, I'm finicky. And I got to spend at least an evening to get the
basic stuff going though. Right. And evening, I got to get Dropbox, got to get all that stuff set up.
You still run Dropbox. Yeah. Doesn't that eat your CPU on Linux? It's a long story. Don't get me
going. Okay. We can save it for next week if you want. Yeah. Because I had it on my elementary
partition here and then I was like, Oh, this is terrible. I just installed a library this morning.
In fact, had to build it myself and then do the whole install process to trick Dropbox on a couple
of my systems to use XFS because Dropbox has dropped support for everything, but extended
for on Linux. And I use XFS because it's a better file system. So that's what I spent my morning
doing that and being told I'm flying to Texas on Sunday night. So, all right, Mr. Dominic,
well, I know we have much more to get into, including some cute follow-up and correction,
some community feedback and some new laptop news. So tell people in the meantime where they can find
you throughout the week and what you're doing. They can find me on Twitter at Dumanuco and at
themadbotter.com. Clever, clever. I'm at Chris LAS. The whole network is at Jupiter Signal and our
show coder.show. Go over there to get links to subscribe, all of that. If you want the link
specific to this episode, there's not much, but you can find it at coder.show slash three, three,
three. We'll be back next week with another episode of the Coder Radio Show.
Get every single episode at coder.show slash subscribe. Thanks for joining us
and see you right back here then.