Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News.
Episode 213, recorded on October 31st, 2021.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Let's do the news.
We start this week with some cheap hardware, well, if you can manage to get your hands
on it.
It's been nearly six years now since the Raspberry Pi Zero was first announced, and
combined, the Zero and its wireless-enabled big brother, the Zero W, have sold almost 4
million units.
And this week, the Raspberry Pi Zero 2W was announced.
Priced at just $15, the Raspberry Pi Zero 2W uses the same SoC as the launch version
of the Pi 3, but it has its ARM cores slightly clocked down to 1 GHz to reduce thermal load,
alongside 512MB of LPDDR2 SDRAM.
The Zero 2W is equipped with a mini HDMI port, microSD card slot, hardware encode and decode
of H.264, and nice to see this, a hack-compatible 40-pin I.O. header.
But what might be the most impressive thing here, and really great for those of you who've
already invested in a previous Pi Zero, Simon Martin, who designed both that original Zero
and Zero 2W, has been able to squeeze all this extra performance into the original Zero
form factor.
So that means almost all cases and accessories designed for Zero should work just fine with
this new board.
People are loving that online, and this makes me think there's two things about this.
One of them is thermal, but before I get to that, I also want to note that this also brings
the entire lineup to 64-bit now.
That's maybe a small step for one product, but it's a giant leap for Pi kind.
And this Pi 2Zero shows us that they are really working on their thermal game.
Thermals are always a challenge when you're trying to package more performance into the
same small package you had before.
It's an age-old problem.
You want to up the performance, but you want to cram it into the same space.
So how do you dissipate that heat?
Well, similar to what we've seen in other recent Pi products, like my Pi 400, the Zero
2W doubles down on some of their lessons learned recently and uses thick internal copper layers
to conduct heat away from the processor.
Yeah, they mean business.
Apparently, if you hold them both in your hands, you can actually feel that difference
in weight.
Now, sadly, actually getting your hands on one is going to be a challenge for a while.
Zero 2W is not immune to the current global semiconductor shortage, so as a result, they
expect to ship roughly 200,000 units this calendar year and a further 250,000 to follow
in the first half of 2022.
But they do say, quote, we aim to keep Zero 2W in production until at least January 2028.
In news that I just quite never get used to saying, Microsoft's Edge browser on Linux
has finally reached official stable status.
As reported by Sophos, and now covered in several other outlets as we record, a stable
version of Microsoft Edge for Linux is now available in the official Microsoft Edge Linux
repositories.
Now, it is version 95, just like the latest stable release on Windows.
There's been no official announcement by Microsoft as we record this.
It's possible this news cycle just got ahead of them, maybe hit the repo and people started
reporting about it, or it's possible they just don't intend to make a very big deal
out of it.
But if you've been using the development builds of Edge, it should just auto update with the
rest of your system when you do an update again with the repo you already have set up
in most cases.
And you can actually visually tell when Edge has been updated, because that little beta
badge on the icon will finally go away.
Now if I recall, Chris, you started trying out Edge right after it was released.
I did too.
Did you manage to stick with it though?
Not at first.
It was definitely an on and off thing, but as Chrome or Firefox would give me a fit about
something I was trying to do.
For example, this typically would happen was, as you know, we'd be using some WebRTC VoIP
app to do a show and Chrome would be spinning up my CPU and causing my fans to go crazy
and Firefox would have some issue with the screen sharing or some weird Google policy
had been applied to my Chrome browser.
And so just different things would come up and I would try Edge.
Yeah, you need a spare browser sometimes.
And I would find that Edge handled those workloads better.
And so over time, Edge has kind of picked up more and more things I use it for because
in my use, I've just found that it seems to use fewer resources doing the same job.
And it has that Chrome compatibility that I need in some of those WebRTC apps.
So that's kind of been a winner for me.
Plus, I have issues with Chrome where it's constantly nagging me to sign into a profile
when I log into a Gmail inbox for like one of the shows and I just don't get that garbage
with Edge.
So overall, I've, you know, I found the experience to be above average, I'd say, and I find myself
on most systems now installing it alongside Chrome and Firefox.
Have you used it much after you gave it that initial go?
No, I'll be honest, I kind of got installed, played around with it, seemed like Chrome
but with a Microsoft stamp and so I didn't keep using it.
But I can definitely appreciate how, yeah, having an extra browser lying around.
And I'll be honest, I've not really been impressed with Chrome lately.
Some of those same things you mentioned, they're definitely bugging me.
So maybe a less Google version might be what I need.
Yeah, I don't think you're going to see Linux users in mass switch, though.
You might see some enterprise adoption, some educational space adoption where people need
compatibility.
But you know, I mean, I don't think this is going to be like a revolution at the regular
Linux user level.
No, I don't think so.
I mean, I'm going to keep using Firefox.
But hey, don't we want a little browser diversity?
Unfortunately, Edge doesn't quite count there.
Well, transitioning from open source web browsers to open source messaging systems and clients,
we noticed EMS the folks behind the element matrix chat client and the matrix hosting
service have announced element one this week, which promises to bring matrix WhatsApp signal
and telegram chats all into one place.
The service is priced at just $5 a month, and they're offering quote, a fully managed
consumer experience with the bridging and hosting managed by the experienced EMS team.
They say it's also basically unlimited usage with some reasonable fair use limits to protect
against bots.
Yeah, that's pretty understandable.
You see, the fundamental value pitch here is that you have a lot of chats online, potentially.
I sure do.
Yeah.
And you'd like all of it in one place.
And for some of us, that is a very tempting product.
And you could even see them expanding this beyond just what I've listed and even maybe
going to things like Discord, Slack, Mattermost and lots of other services that can just kind
of layer them on top of this.
But there are some trade offs.
Bridges support conversations, invites, images and attachments, but they don't support voice
or video calls between platforms, although your voice and video attachments should be
supported just fine.
And the big caveat that right now, end to end encryption is broken in order to make
the bridges work.
But the EMS team do say they've taken some efforts to reduce that risk, noting, quote,
the bridges operate in Elements trusted EMS environment with no content scanning or data
mining.
And of course, element to element or any other matrix app supporting end to end encryption,
those conversations are still end to end encrypted by default.
They also support voice and video calls.
If you're someone who manages a lot of online communities or just participates in them,
and you've been thinking about getting into the world of matrix, this might really be
a no brainer.
I can't really think of an easier way to get started with this kind of stuff and have a
nice hosted, curated experience.
Yeah, in fact, setting a matrix can be one of the barriers to adoption and they've really
packaged it all together here.
I also think that you're right, Chris, when you say expect more bridges coming soon.
This might be a nice funding method where EMS gets the money and some of that gets directed
to developing better or future bridges.
I see the hint quite strongly at this on their blog saying, we'll be listening carefully
to all feedback to see how to develop element one in the future.
It could be the people want more bridges added, or perhaps end to end encryption for existing
bridges might be deemed more important, or something else entirely, either way, or all
ears.
I like what you're saying there about this being a way for users to fund EMS and element
development and that reminds me a little bit of the Nebuchadnezzar setup for Home Assistant.
That's the commercial organization above Home Assistant and they offer a Home Assistant
remote access service that's very reasonably priced.
It's full of features and it gives Home Assistant great functionality that you're going to kind
of want anyways, which is the check of a few boxes and a monthly subscription.
But what you're really doing with that subscription is you're financing future development of Home
Assistant.
And so by subscribing to this element one, you'd be helping the element organization
continue as just a, you know, a matrix fan.
So I think this isn't quite ready for me, but I am definitely on the fence.
I'd love to see a Slack bridge set up.
Ooh, that would be nice.
Yeah, yeah.
Or just a one click Discord bridge.
Then I could close a few more Electron apps.
That's one of the main goals here.
One Electron app to rule them all, Wes.
And while we're talking about the element chat app, the chat client added export support
this week in version 1.91.
So with this latest release, you now have the ability to export chat from all rooms
and DMs on the element web and desktop apps.
And this new export ability was definitely one of the development team's most upvoted
features and the implementation looks pretty solid.
Not only are you able to choose what you want to export, the current timeline, the entire
timeline, or just a specific number of messages, but you're also able to choose how to export
them HTML, plain text, or my favorite, JSON.
As we record on a Sunday evening, Linux 5.15 is scheduled to be released just momentarily.
This merge window opened back in September and there's some particularly interesting
new features and changes in this release, including one that I've been dreading for
weeks.
Oh, we're going to touch on that.
But first, one of the most talked about new features is the new NTFS3 file system driver,
originally developed by Paragon Software.
It feels like we've been reading about this one forever, but now it's finally shipping.
Something else we've been following closely, the Apple M1 IOMMU driver was added, among
a whole bunch of other ongoing work, adding support for Apple's new SoC in the kernel.
But the feature I know you've been dreading, this release merges in KSMBD.
So good up, Wes.
I know you're loving this.
This is just crazy to me, an in kernel Samba file server.
You know, SMB, the Windows file sharing protocol that accepts remote connections over the network
is now built into the kernel.
And we're trying to figure how this is even going to work.
Is the kernel going to open up an interface and accept Samba connections over a new interface
like Wirecard does, or is it going to actually open up the remote port somehow on your machine?
Like, we don't know, but I have a suspicion we'll find out.
And the overall message is this isn't a replacement for traditional Samba for most workloads.
But KSMBD does promise a high performance and more lightweight option for those of you
who might need it.
Hey, nothing better for my local network.
And really, I suppose that shouldn't be too hard to do when your service is built right
into the kernel.
But that's definitely something we're going to test.
Interestingly, Samsung's use case for this is lightweight file sharing on Android devices
and other embedded applications.
But we just think it might be fun to try a Raspberry Pi file server.
I do have to admit, I am looking forward to that.
Another big thing that lands in 5.15 is the preempt RT locking code.
This represents the bulk of the previously outstanding real time patches for the Linux
kernel.
So the mainline kernel is getting close to holding all of the needed real time functionality.
And while real time functionality isn't needed by most of us, this is going to be huge for
the workloads that do require it.
We know that our friends at SpaceX and JPL, for example, maintain their own patch sets
to Linux just to enable real time functionality on the devices they deploy Linux on.
And this has been a long time coming.
The preempt RT patch has been available for every long term stable version of the kernel
since kernel version 2.6.11.
AMD users also get a lot of nice to haves, including future AMD users of the Steam Deck.
The AMD Van Gogh APU audio driver was merged in 5.15, and the Steam Deck will be among
the first hardware to actually benefit from it.
Really, there is just a lot going on in 5.15.
And as always, Michael Haribol has a great write up at Ferronix, which we'll have a
link to in the show notes.
And of course, the kernel never sleeps.
With the release of 5.15, the merge window for 5.16 will open up pretty much immediately.
And there are already many exciting things in the works.
You know why I use Linode?
Because I'm not my own ISP.
I don't have 11 data centers around the world.
And I haven't been deploying servers in the cloud for 18 years.
I have been deploying servers for more than 18 years.
And that's also another reason why I use Linode.
Because I'm really blown away by what they have here.
First of all, the pricing is just fantastic.
It's 30% to 50% less than the major duopoly hypervisors out there.
They've made a really great dashboard.
I think they revved it like a couple of years ago, and now they've just been really kind
of iterating on something really great because it's definitely a refined product.
It manages to strike the balance between simple but give you advanced functionality when you
need it.
On top of that, they have a really flushed out API and a command line client you can
use on your OS of choice to interact with Linode and do things like upload files or
manage a box, create a snapshot before you make a change.
What I actually do on my machines is usually I have a dropdown terminal on whatever desktop
I'm using.
And almost always, that's where I have the Linode command line tool.
So if I'm working on something, I can have that just ready to go.
Drop that down, execute a command like a snapshot or something real quick, and I'm good to go.
Linode is really focused on giving you a simple but powerful setup.
And you can go with one of their pre-built stacks, just one click deploy kind of thing,
and they got a lot of good ones for that.
That's a great way to learn too.
Or you can go the DIY route.
I've actually found guides in Linode tutorials on how to replace their images with my own
custom Linux image, which I use for this VPN monster that I run for my LTE connections.
But I was just blown away that they were like, not only did they allow it, but they were
showing me how to do it.
That's what's so cool about Linode.
They're in it for the tech.
Like I mentioned, they are their own ISP.
When they did that years ago, it was like kind of like a controversial thing that Linode
was using Linux as firewall and routers.
Like what are they doing?
They can't do that.
And now it's just as commonplace.
You see Linux in so many places in our network infrastructure now.
So many people now do infrastructure as code.
Linode was all about that early on.
When things really got cooking in the cloud age, it was really when virtualization became
available.
And that was something Linode saw coming before anybody else.
They saw what you could do with that before anybody did because they're geeks and they
played around with this stuff.
And now their service has a bunch of great features.
I love their S3 compatible object storage.
They have cloud firewalls, DDoS protection, VLAN support.
Of course, they've got a powerful DNS manager because you're going to need that.
Kubernetes support, super fast networking, and a lot more.
So go get that $100 and really get an opportunity to try it.
Linode.com slash LAN.
Go there, get $100 on a new account for 60 days, and you support the show.
It's real easy to support the show and try out something great.
Linode.com slash LAN.
And Linux Action News is made possible by Ting.
Linux.ting.com.
Ting's my mobile service provider.
They are a mobile virtual network operator.
That means they focus on the customer support and a great value.
Go find a plan that fits at linux.ting.com.
They have a special deal going on right now as I record this.
So if you're listening around release time, they have very special rates up to 35% off
on some of their plans.
You go to linux.ting.com and get $25 in credit so you could really start working here.
Ting has fantastic plans and rates.
Whatever you need, a little bit of data, a lot of data, unlimited talk, unlimited text,
they've got plans for you.
And they've got simple to understand terms and no contracts.
It's simple to switch to Ting.
You go to linux.ting.com.
Pretty much any phone's going to work with Ting because they support multiple networks.
They have coast to coast network coverage, and they know.
They know the math.
They know what works best in your area.
So you go to linux.ting.com.
You check out your current phone.
You create an account.
You pick a plan that fits you just right.
And seriously right now, if you're listening around release time, they've always got great
pricing.
But if you're listening around release time, go to linux.ting.com.
Check out these prices.
If you fit everything, everything looks good, they're going to send you a SIM card.
You get that right away.
You pop that in your phone, and you get activated online in minutes.
You can pretty much do this entire process without having to talk to customer support
because they've got a great dashboard.
But if you do need customer support, they've got the best in the business.
That's something Ting is really focused on, so they've got you covered there.
They send you that SIM card.
You pop it in.
You get going.
But if you ever have any trouble, they're there for you.
The next generation of Ting Mobile is incredible.
And right now, the pricing is record breaking.
So get started.
Try it out and see why I've been using it forever.
Go to linux.ting.com.
Big change for network administrators is under development in Red Hat land.
It appears the Fedora project, and further downstream, Red Hat Enterprise 9, is considering
removing support for the Network Information Service, or NIS.
NIS solved a problem in the early days of Unix networking as the number of systems grew,
became quite a chore to copy around your Etsy password file and keep those UIDs in sync.
NIS was one of the first forms of any sort of single sign-on on a local network.
Not to date myself, but I'm sure some of you out there already know this.
But when I was entering the industry, some folks still called it Yellow Pages.
And I always liked that name better.
But as you can probably guess, trademark issues ensued.
And the entire Unix community was just exhausted by trademark fights by this point.
So the name was just changed to NIS, and then later NIS Plus in 1992.
However, you'll still end up using functions and commands that start with YP.
Now these days, Linux systems still carry NIS support, and the PAM Unix authentication
module supports it as well.
And distributions still package the various NIS utilities.
At the beginning of October though, Bjorn Esser suggested that Fedora, at least, might
stop doing so soon.
Esser is working on a project to replace PAM Unix, which also receives unfortunately little
attention these days, with a more straightforward alternative.
One of the things that would make this work a little simpler would be to just drop support
for NIS.
So he wanted to know if anyone was still actually using it.
Well, and they did hear from some of those users, didn't they?
They seem to exist, surprise, surprise.
LWN notes they were perhaps most aptly described by Stefan John Smogen, who said, quote, the
places I've seen it still being used are in universities run by people who learned sysadmin
in the 90s and early 2000s.
Ouch.
That burns a little less.
He goes on to say, it's a lightweight system that is simple to set up and tends to be the
go to stick for a lot of we put this together in 1999 with rail six, and we've upgraded
it ever since type places.
Another commenter was quick to ask whether any simple alternatives might exist.
Unfortunately, the answer would appear to be no.
Smogen responded, there is LDAP, but that isn't light.
And there is Kerberos, but that isn't easy.
He added that an awful lot of the quote, cool kids just defer to one of the large service
providers for authentication services these days, a solution that doesn't seem likely
to appeal to anybody who's been making the effort to keep NIS running all these years.
That's really the no win scenario part of this because you could you could kind of mitigate
this with modern infrastructure management tools.
Of course, you could you could deploy free IPA and essentially replicate a lot of Active
Directory type functionality.
But none of that is as easy or quick to set up as NIS.
In my opinion, it's a bit of a shame that some universal distro agnostic and universally
supported Active Directory alternative hasn't been built and adopted by the wider community.
From my days in both the industry of enterprise and banking and my days in education and
IT support there, I think I can make a pretty solid argument that a lack of a drop in replacement
for Active Directory.
In other words, something that's practically built into every distro, not having that has
slowed adoption in the enterprise and in the education desktop market easily.
And I think it's left the low end market open for Chromebooks to just dominate.
And of course, Windows continues to dominate in the higher end market.
I think I have to agree.
We do see more and more Linux desktops in the enterprise over time, but they tend to
be rolling their own solutions for user management if you're lucky enough to have user management
at all.
But given that it seems round nine will not support NIS, and even if Fedora punts this
change for maybe a cycle or two, the final days are nigh.
Well, support still remains for now.
I mean, what an incredible run over the decades from the very early days of network Unix to
2021, no matter how you slice that, that is an extremely impressive run.
And I feel nostalgic for something that may be fading away just a little bit.
Maybe that's why it made it in today's episode.
And while we're speaking of Fedora on Tuesday's Linux Unplugged project, lead Matthew Miller
will join us for our exit interview with Fedora 34 and our review of Fedora 35, which is scheduled
to release Tuesday, November 4th.
Yeah, that'll be episode 430 of Linux Unplugged, and I think that's going to be a really good
conversation.
But we'll keep an eye on everything going on in the world of Linux and open source.
So be sure you go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to keep in touch.
And don't forget links to everything we cover today at linuxactionnews.com slash 213.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
Thanks for joining us.
And that's all the news for this week.