Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open-source world.
This is episode 15, recorded on August 20th, 2017. I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe, and my podcast-tuned ears tell me that sounds a bit like a hotel room. Are
you still at Ogg Camp over there?
I am still at Ogg Camp, yes. I've been there all day yesterday and all day today.
How's it been going?
Yeah, it's been going great. And I'm going to be going out for the social event tonight
as well, Sunday night as we record this in the UK. But it's been really good. I've seen
a bunch of talks about loads of random stuff. But I think one of the good ones for me was
Richard Brown from OpenSUSE. He gave a really comprehensive overview of how the project
works and how it ties in with SLE, the enterprise version and stuff. And that was really good.
And also, he did one today, a shorter talk about OpenQA and how that relates to Tumbleweed
and why they think that's the best way to do a distro, which is a little bit controversial
to say that a rolling release is better than the snapshot releases that Ubuntu do.
That does sound pretty interesting. And it sounds like also a few shows got produced
while you're there. So there's some content out of OggCamp people can look forward to
if they go check out late night Linux. So overall, pretty productive, Joe.
Yeah, so far so good.
Of course, there's another group of folks that are having a party this week. And that's
Gnome. Gnome has officially turned 20, Joe.
Yeah, can you believe it's that old as a project?
It kind of makes me feel old. I know that's a selfish take on it. But that was my first
thought is, whoa, wait, what? 20 years? Oh, no.
Yeah. And Debian has turned 24.
1993. That was the first release of Debian. Unbelievable. 24 years of Debian, 20 years
of Gnome, two projects that have had a huge role in my Linux usage. Debian Day. What do
you think of that, Joe? We should start celebrating Debian Day.
Yeah, we should definitely. Maybe we can convert a few people, maybe.
Speaking of Debian, there's a bit of a remix for the Raspberry Pi that's got an update.
Yeah, the previous version of Raspberry Pi was based on Jessie. And now they have updated
it to Stretch. So it's kind of up to date now. And there's not anything massively different
in there. You've got new versions of things, new PHP. And some of the kind of core apps
have been updated, like Sonic Pi has been updated to version three now.
Yeah.
Which is a major update for that. That's got a lot of new features on there. But in this
blog post about it, Simon Long was talking about how he's fixed some issues with passwordless
pseudo and the fact that the default user is Pi. And if you change that, then some applications
don't like it. And he's kind of fixed that. But to me, that just highlights that I just
don't think that it's put together very well, that distro. I think that having a default
username and password, and you can change it, but it doesn't prompt you to do that,
or at least not in very overt terms. And then to have pseudo with no password, it just seems
like it's security and usability are always a balance, right? But in this case, I just
feel that they've got that balance wrong for me. And that's why I would always use Ubuntu
Mate on the Pi.
One thing that was a red flag to me, and it's absolutely their choice to go this route,
but they've ripped PulseAudio out. And that to me was a bit of a red flag. When you roll
backwards, that's generally not something that's sustainable. I remember a time in Linux
where only one application could use your audio interface at a time. And if you had
something playing sound, that's all you could listen to. So when we start to slide backwards
in audio, it does make me a little concerned. I'm not saying PulseAudio is the best thing
ever, but just completely ripping it out and then saying, oh, if you need that, just install
it yourself, seems a little bit of a backwards approach. Maybe, I don't know. Maybe I don't
have extensive use with it on the Raspberry Pi. So maybe this is the right move. But that
was a red flag to your point.
Yeah. And another regression is, well, I suppose a change. Do you remember when they made a
theme for LXDE and started calling it a desktop environment and called it Pixel?
Yeah.
And I pointed out to them that that was probably not such a good idea because of the Google
Pixel.
Sure.
And that they might have trademark issues. And they said, oh, it's fine. Don't worry.
It's totally different. Well, now they have silently rebranded it as Raspberry Pi Desktop
and not a single mention of Pixel on their website anymore, apart from the old article.
That's a good move, though. We don't know why, although I think your reason might be
it. But that is a good move on their part.
Well, I asked Ben Nuttall, the community manager. He did a lightning talk at OggCamp yesterday.
And I asked him that very question. And he just took his phone out of his pocket and
held it up as to why they've rebranded away from Pixel.
Was it a Pixel?
I believe so, yeah.
That's I think you nailed it then.
I suspect they got a letter from Google, but he wouldn't say for definite.
Yeah. So here's something then that's good. Let's end on a positive note with our coverage
of this. They have a fix for that Broadcom 43 wireless chipset that ships on the Raspberry
Pi 3 and Pi 0. It potentially allowed an attacker to take over the chip and execute code on
it. And this stretch release includes a patch to address that vulnerability. That's a pretty
important fix and a good reason to update.
Yeah. And to be fair, one thing that is quite impressive about this distro is that it will
work on any Raspberry Pi, from the very first one on the zeros, on the two, the three. And
it'll just work regardless of which Pi you have, which is not something that can be said
for any other OS. So fair play to them on that one.
Yeah, I agree. Just because Debian's 24 years old doesn't mean they're sitting still and
enjoying the architectures and systems they already run great on. Work continues for Debian
on mobile devices.
Yeah, it's easy to forget that you can actually run a proper GNU slash Linux distro on some
of these portable devices, including the Pocket Chip, which is a pretty cool little computer.
And even a phone, Zero phone, which is based on the Raspberry Pi Zero.
Very geeky phone.
Yeah, yeah. The thing is that with the death of Ubuntu phone and Firefox OS, you kind of
think that all hope is lost and Android is the only way if you want Linux on a kind of
embedded small device. But it's good to see that Debian is actually working on this stuff
and hasn't forgotten about it.
I agree. And there's actually a device shipping soon that looks really compelling that'll
ship with Debian. The Pandora folks are getting ready to ship the Pyra. I think I'm saying
that right. P-Y-R-A. It's a 5-inch LCD touchscreen. It has gaming controls on it, but it also
has a full QWERTY little mini keyboard. It looks about the size of a older Nintendo 3DS.
It has a 1.5 gigahertz dual-core ARM CPU, which you could upgrade and get up to 4 gigs
of RAM, backlit keyboard. And yeah, Debian pre-installed on these. And these guys have
a history of shipping. It's a pretty compelling little device. And if you want something super
mobile, I like it. And Joe, you'll like this too, at least in the screenshots. It's run
on XFCE.
Well, it's the only desktop that makes sense.
So there's actually a few. When you stop thinking about the consumer handhelds like the Galaxy
phones and the Nexus phones, and you start thinking about these really awesome geeky
devices that, honestly, only a niche is going to want to buy, but that's fine. Debian starts
to make a lot of sense here. The Xero phone was an interesting one, but also they're working
on the Samsung Galaxy S Relay 4G. Now, I just said don't target consumer phones, but if
you do need something that can make calls for some reason, and you want something running
Debian, that's also going to be an option. But the pirate in me had the most compelling
feature set, a really nice modular handheld computer with gaming controls, Wi-Fi, multiple
SD card slots, USB ports. You can get it in Europe or the US, and it's going to be pre-loaded
with Debian. The only downside, when I started to get a little bit more interested in it
and looked at the pre-orders, the one I would want with four gigs of RAM is about $670 US.
A little too expensive for me. Yeah. Well, it's funny, kind of related. While I've been
here at Oddcamp, I got my hands on the GPD Pocket briefly. What do you think? Its build
quality is brilliant. It's milled aluminum. It feels like a MacBook Pro type, but software-wise,
it doesn't really work with certainly the LTS version of Ubuntu that was on there. Also,
when I put it down on the table, it turned itself off and on again because of a loose
connector in there. There's some quality control issues by the looks of things, but I really
want one. If they weren't so expensive, I kind of wish I'd backed it now, but you see
it all at Oddcamp. It's brilliant. There's another device coming out soon that is sort
of making me also interested. This space is really starting to get interesting. My better
sense says, wait another generation. That's what my better sense tells me, but my early
adopter sense says, jump in now. It's obviously getting more and more interesting. We'll have
some links in the show notes if you guys want to check it out, but in the meantime, those
of us that have existing devices and nothing's really compelling to us, that's the situation
I find myself in with my Nexus 6P. Lineage is starting to look more and more attractive,
and they've recently launched a summer survey that I have to be honest with you, Joe. After
I started taking the survey, even though I'm not a recent lineage user, it actually made
me want to use lineage more and more. I hadn't realized how great it's gotten, and just looking
at some of the questions in the survey, it's really standing out.
I haven't used anything else apart from it. Well, I used Android Ice Cold, which is based
on it, for a while, but as soon as I bought my OnePlus 3T a couple of weeks ago, literally
the first thing I did was flash lineage on it.
Yeah, you did. That is the fact I remember. It was basically, hey, I got this, and it's
already running lineage, which is pretty funny. There was no gap. For me, I've just got the
Nexus line of devices because I wanted to just get it directly from Google, and I thought
if I'm going to be on an Android device, I should just run as close to what Google envisions
for Android as possible.
What I've discovered by that is it's not good enough, and it's boring, and I don't use my
Nexus 6P as much. Lineage seems like a great way to sort of inject a little bit of life
back into the device and make it a little more compelling again.
The survey is linked in the show notes. If you're a lineage user and you want to give
them your thoughts, they're calling it their summer survey, and they have divided it into
five areas, apps, wallpapers, features, infrastructure, and how they handle public relations. So it's
worth checking out lineageos.org slash summer dash survey, or go over to linuxactionnews.com
slash 15 and find the link in the show notes.
Yeah, and the thing is that you have no right to complain about a project if you don't take
part in these surveys. I will always do a survey if I can because that's the best way
to give them direct feedback, crowdsourced info and opinions. So if you do use Lineage,
then I urge you do go and fill this out and help them out. It's a very simple way to give
them a couple of minutes of your time to really help the project out.
DigitalOcean.com. Go over there, create your account, and then apply our promo code, here's
the thing. All one word, smush it together like you're slurring it, and get a $10 credit
at DigitalOcean.com.
DigitalOcean is simple cloud hosting that you can get deployed in less than 55 seconds.
I'm talking from getting the machine created to being logged in as root and creating and
working on your project. DigitalOcean.com promo code, here's the thing. Everything uses
SSDs, they have a simple API, they have highly available block storage, lightning fast networking
with private networking that doesn't count against your transfer, which is really brilliant.
If you have a front end proxy server connecting to back end web servers or doing backups on
their back end, that private networking is over their data center land too, so it's crazy
fast. They have load balancing as a service, team support if you want to work with a group,
and monitoring and alerting to make you look like a boss. DigitalOcean.com, use our promo
code, here's the thing. Get started in seconds and see how great that interface is, how simple
it is. DigitalOcean.com promo code, here's the thing.
One of the projects that I've been watching closely for a few years now is Solus, and
this week they've come out with Solus 3. Now, full disclosure, Aiki, the founder and lead
developer of Solus, is on my other podcast, Late Night Linux, so I'm pretty much bound
to say good things about it, but this is a really solid release.
Yeah, this is the third iteration of Solus since they've moved to a rolling release,
and I wanted to watch this kind of come out a couple of times after that transition, and
it was this one that made me install it on the machine I'm sitting in front of right
now, which is one of my most important machines in the studio. They've moved from a regular
snapshot model that a lot of traditional distributions take, and they've now gone with sort of a
hybrid curated rolling release model, and that works perfect for me because it keeps
the applications fresh. I've opted to use the LTS kernel and the LTS video drivers,
so those remain constant and stable, and I think it's a really good balance for me. This
is also the first release of Solus to ship with an LSM by default. The Linux security
models like SE Linux or App Armor that are essentially a control list or a control system
that prevent applications from going outside certain boundaries, and Solus hadn't really
picked a horse in that race, and now they've chosen App Armor, and by shipping App Armor
by default, they've also brought in a bunch of the support they need to ship really good
Snap support, like great, essentially Ubuntu-level Snap support with full confinement using the
Linux security module within their own kernel, which this module happens to be App Armor
to use Snap. So now we have complete Flatpak with confinement support and Snaps with confinement
support on Solus, which is great for users of the operating system that might want to
install something that isn't in their curated repository.
Well that was one of the biggest criticisms to date of Solus, that the repo is relatively
small compared to Debian or Ubuntu, for example, and now this basically takes care of that,
or it certainly will in the future.
Yeah I am looking forward to adding support for a couple of applications I don't think
they would ever want to package, maybe things that run more as a server with NGINX, and
I'm thinking of certain Usenet clients and whatnot that I just don't think would ever
end up in the user repository for Solus. So this is pretty cool, it also represents some
pretty great cross-platform collaboration between the canonical Snapcraft folks and Solus, which
we got a little bit of the backstory on last week's Linux Unplugged from Wimpy and iKey,
which sounded like essentially they just had to kind of point him in the right direction
and he was able to roll all this in, but fascinating nonetheless.
Not to focus too much on Snaps because there's a ton of other pretty great features in their
custom desktop budgie 10.4, which has new animations, a new alt tab, a new nightlight
feature that changes the color tones at night, all other kinds of really nice things including
modifications to the menu that I really appreciate as a new adopter of the budgie desktop.
Not to mention the most important thing, to put the panel in the correct place at last
on the bottom.
You know I read somebody say on the internet recently that Solus is one of the most newsworthy
Linux distributions, and I have to agree. There's a lot happening here, and it's been
fascinating to watch it for a little while myself.
Yeah, it seems like we were right when we said that once iKey goes full time, development's
going to accelerate, and it's just gone at an amazing speed. It was already going pretty
quickly and it was already quite newsworthy, but it seems like iKey's going to be providing
us with news for weeks and months and years to come.
I totally agree. In fact, I'm looking forward to it. It's one of the reasons I installed
it. I'm also always following news around the ZFS file system and getting better support
for ZFS on Linux, and finally it looks like we might be getting decent encryption support.
Which I would have thought for certain enterprise use cases is absolutely essential.
I wonder how many people encrypt their NASs or their SANs in an enterprise. People listening,
I'd like to know. Tweet us at Linux Action News or at ChrisLAS and let me know. Do you
encrypt your data center storage? I could definitely picture encrypting any mediums
that leave the data center, like backup drives or tapes or absolutely laptops, but large,
large storage volumes. Do people actively encrypt those? I'm not sure.
I would have thought so with certain areas like banking and where it's really critical
security.
Yeah, you definitely have controls around the data and restrictions and lots of protection,
but encryption at rest comes with a pretty big considerable overhead when you have high
usage applications hitting that drive a lot. So there's a big cost to doing that. I don't
know. Maybe I'm a little old school on this, but to me it seems like you definitely encrypt
the network during transit. You definitely encrypt any data leaving the data center,
absolutely. But often on the LAN itself, you just manage it with access control lists and
file permissions.
So I wonder if it hasn't been a big concern for Linux. But they have been working on it
for months. The patches go back for months and months, and it was just really until this
last week that they felt like it was matured enough for merging into the upstream code.
So you're going to have to wait for these updates to come downstream to you, but there's
16,000 new lines of code. There's a fun fact along with this new Linux encryption support
on ZFS.
Yeah, so I wonder if this is one more small nail in B-tree FS's coffin. What do you think?
I'm going to take the other side on that now. I think ButterFS is essentially untouchable.
All of the shots that it can be, it's not dead yet, Joe. It's just a flesh wound and
it's still going. Because where it's useful, there's certain NAS devices that ship it by
default on the NAS hard drives. There is certain large Linux distributions out there that insist
on shipping it. And there's certain crazy data mining corporations that run it on their
edge network. They'll probably continue to do that for years.
Yeah, well, SUSE are all in on it. Their whole basically update strategy relies on it because
you need to have the rollback and they're not going to ship ZFS. They've made that very
clear. So I think, yeah, even if it's only SUSE using it, it's going to stick around.
Yeah, I'm glad because then we can really have a good turf war. Now we can have ZFS
folks against ButterFS folks. And meanwhile, us Stratus hipsters over here will really
have the high and mighty attitudes.
Well, I'm just sitting here using XT4, what can I say?
There's also a little upset in the Bitcoin community. Another fork is coming. Yes, we
know there was just another fork. Bitcoin Cash just happened. On Wednesday, a group
of Bitcoiners scheduled yet another split for the network in November, which would create
a third version of Bitcoin. Now the date's not set yet because it's based on the number
of blocks. So once they reach a certain block number, the split happens.
And so this all comes down to Segregated Witness, doesn't it? Which is a feature that was being
debated as to whether they were going to implement it and it was going to help with this block
size problem. And so it was implemented into the main Bitcoin, but that wasn't enough to
stop the fork of Bitcoin Cash where they just said, we don't care about Segregated Witness.
We just want a bigger block size. And now this other fork is people want both. They
want a bigger block size and Segregated Witness to basically optimize the block size as much
as possible.
It's going by two names, SigWit2x and BTC1, I believe. And its two main differences would
be a two megabyte block size versus OG Bitcoin's one megabyte. And it would also include the
new Segregated Witness. But that's not the interesting part about any of this. The interesting
part about this is how fired up the Bitcoin community is. This appears to be a much bigger
deal than the last split. And it's potentially going to be much more noticeable. There is
a bunch of Bitcoin Core developers and Bitcoin Core community members who are very vocal.
Henry Braid is one of these. A vocal person that's been promoting Bitcoin since 2011.
He's a frequent speaker at events. He's very knowledgeable about Bitcoin and the blockchain.
And he tweeted this morning, the SigWit2x hard fork scheduled for November is an attempted
hostile corporate takeover of the Bitcoin protocol. Fight it and educate people.
They're saying that New York business interests are coming out and it may even be a state
takeover. And meanwhile, the SigWit2x folks are saying we have 80% of the hashing power.
We have these former core developers on our side. Let's give this a go and let's see just
where the cards lie. And it's getting really volatile back and forth. This is the interesting
fork.
Yeah, because Bitcoin Cash, it's not done massively well. It's done better than I expected,
I must say, but people have just kept using Bitcoin basically. So you think that now this
might be serious, that people might actually start using this other fork?
I think it could be the combination effect of Bitcoin Cash and SigWit2x. Bitcoin Cash,
if you mine, is more profitable right now than original Bitcoin. So if you're in the
mining game, you can actually make more money with Bitcoin Cash. So that's going to eat
away a bit of Bitcoin. And then SigWit2x comes along with their two megabyte blocks and segregated
witness and big professional slick industry backing, quote unquote, the corporate people
that are trying to take it over. It could be really appealing. And if you get companies
like Coinbase and Bitpay, who is Bitpay is one of the big companies behind this, this
could by default just become the elephant in the room, could suck all of the oxygen.
I can't think of another metaphor. Could snuff, no, got nothing, Joe. But there's a lot of
metaphors you could throw at this. Like there's this the metaphor, the metaphor potential
is high.
Yeah, it's we live in fascinating times with the whole Bitcoin thing. I'm just waiting
for it to crash so I can invest again, because it seems to go up, crash right and then go
up and go even higher than it was before.
Those of us that follow Bitcoin call that a sale. Yeah, there's a you're waiting for
the Bitcoin sale. Hopefully it'll come. As we record right now, it's somewhere north
of $4000, which is just absolutely insane. It's mind blowing, isn't it? I've been I've
been following Bitcoin since it was below $1. So sometimes it makes me want to break
out the old plan B. But I tell you what, I'm too busy doing this here show, which you can
find future versions over at linuxactionnews.com go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe
for all the ways to get new episodes and go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways
to get in touch. Yeah, and you can support the entire network at our Patreon page over
at patreon.com slash Jupiter signal. We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on
the latest Linux and open source news. I'm at Chris LAS. I'm at Joe Ressington. Thank
you for joining us. And we'll see you next week. See you later.