Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open source world.
This is episode 67, recorded on August 19th, 2018.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe.
It is really great to be connected to you while you are live down at OggCamp 2018.
And we're kicking things off with a story that I bet you heard some buzz about at OggCamp
because people are talking about it all over the internet.
It's these rumors that Valve is working to make Windows games work on SteamOS.
Yeah, unfortunately, all it is is rumors.
So we don't know whether it's them using wine or whether they've written something themselves,
or exactly how it's going to work.
But it seems like a pretty logical step for them to do this in order to boost SteamOS
as a platform.
Like a few stories recently, this started by people digging on Reddit through Steam
TB.
And they found a string named string settings compat info, where the description reads,
quote, steam will automatically install compatibility tools that allow you to play games from your
library that were built for other operating systems, end quote.
Yeah, and by other operating systems, they mean Windows.
Absolutely.
And there's a there's also another string in there they found the steam settings compat
advanced info, which has a warning in there, which reads, quote, you may select a compatibility
tool to use with games that have not been tested or verified to work on this platform.
This may not work as expected and can cause issues with your games, including crashes
and breaking saved games.
That last warning there about crashes and breaking save games has most of the internet
speculating this is some sort of wine compatibility layer.
I don't know, Joe.
I'm more inclined to think it's more like something like DX VK, which is that DirectX
to Vulkan compatibility layer that would only work with Windows Vulkan games.
Well, maybe it's both.
Maybe the Vulkan games are going to work better than the others, but they're going to at least
attempt to support the non Vulkan stuff just to widen the number of titles that they've
got available for Steam OS.
Well, something tells me we'll be learning more in the near future.
These things have a way of just keep coming and leaking and then they grow and then eventually
we see the complete story.
So we'll just keep tracking it.
Well, one project that we've been keeping an eye on is Endless OS and last time we were
talking about it, things weren't going too well for them, but now things seem to be looking
up because they are going to be shipping it on some Asus hardware.
This is an interesting partnership indeed.
You remember Endless, the GNOME focused Endless OS, which is based on Debian.
It is shipping already on the Asus VivoBook 15 X540NA.
That's one of the few products that you can get Endless on.
It also has an option for Windows 10, but it sounds like this may be expanding a bit.
I did some digging around too and there's already some support documents up on Asus's
website as well as an introduction to Endless on Asus's website.
So it seems really early days, but it could pan out to additional hardware.
This seems like a pretty great partnership for them.
Oh, definitely.
It's pretty modest hardware, isn't it?
Two gigabytes of RAM and we're not talking about i3s and i5s here.
We're talking about the low cost, low end machines, but that's kind of what Endless
is aimed at anyway, isn't it?
So it sort of makes sense to start with that kind of hardware.
I could see that.
I would be curious to see how GNOME 3 shell performs on that.
And keep in mind too, Endless has been heavily tailored to have pretty good functionality
offline as well.
That's kind of neat in a laptop of this size you might have in your bag.
You want to break it out while you're on the commute and get some work done.
And to have a bunch of stuff like Wikipedia and whatnot available offline might be a really
nice combination with lightweight, cheap hardware.
But we have been burned by Asus before, haven't we?
Remember Xandros with the netbooks and they kind of made this whole market.
And then when that didn't pan out, they just got rid of Linux completely and started saying
it's better with Windows and stuff.
They're saying that still right now on their website.
And it's very heavily marketed as a Windows 10 home machine.
They do seem to fail to go all in, like they don't quite grok that they need to completely
go all in.
Even if it's just one product, go all in like Dell did with the XPS 13.
Instead they sort of have this back burner hidden down on their website that they don't
really talk about, but you can go get support from Endless solution.
Maybe that grows into something bigger, but when you sort of tend to repeat the mistakes
of the past, you tend to get the same results.
Well, to be fair, with the XPS 13, they do also do them with Windows.
It's not going quite all in, is it, with the Linux, but at least they are making a proper
effort and you get people like Barton coming along and really promoting it and engaging
with the community.
Whereas, yeah, not so much with Asus, unfortunately.
Yeah.
I mean, really to clarify the going all in statement, I just mean a website that I can
go to where this product has been end to end tested running Linux and I can see a whole
website about the information.
Like it's a real product from the company, not something hidden away.
That's all they really have to do is keep selling the Windows 10 version, keep making
a website that talks about all the great features of Windows 10.
Also make a website that highlights and features the Ubuntu version or whatever it might be
and do the same thing.
That's all I'm saying is go all in in a way that's a full product.
Yeah.
Well, it is early days.
They're just testing the water.
If they sell well, then maybe they will do that and all we can do is hope really.
I think so.
And wouldn't it be really interesting to see if those could get some traction and education,
the price point combined with Endless, that could be a really nice document editing machine
in high schools or or even middle school.
So there could be some real potential in education.
Well, another potential option for that kind of low end hardware would be the Trinity desktop.
TDE, a continuation originally of KDE 3.
Now it's really it's its own project and they just had a big update.
They just shipped version R1 14.05.
It's their fifth maintenance release of the series and they've made some nice maintenance
improvements, fixed things like Ogg playback and some sound server issues and did some
major code base refactoring, they say, and fixed a few memory leaks as well and added
a few features.
But that's not really the headline feature here.
The headline feature is that a desktop environment that harkens back to KDE 3, the 90s is still
getting updates and seeing releases.
I love open source.
Well, yeah.
The real headline for me is that I thought that they were pretty much dead because we
haven't had a release for nearly two years.
And here we are with a new release.
So just open source refuses to die, especially people's favorite desktop environments.
I am seriously tempted to give it a go.
I did make an attempt before the show, but their live CDs haven't been updated yet.
So I might kick the tires in a few days once they've updated their live CDs.
I just I got to try it out for nostalgia purposes.
Well, I haven't had much time because I've been at odd camp, obviously, as we mentioned,
hence my echoing audio, sorry about that.
But I did have a quick chance to spin up slacks in a VM last night.
And after I did app get dist upgrade on it, because it is Debian based, it did show as
being 14.0.5.
But it said that it was from April of this year.
So it's all a bit confusing, really.
But I don't think it's changed massively in terms of features and stuff.
It's quite a lot of bug fixes.
And there are a few features, but the overall aesthetic of it hasn't changed.
And it did give me kind of fond memories of my early Linux days, funny enough with slacks
being this really light distro.
And I don't know as much as I do really appreciate what the KDE team has done with plasma five
looking back at KDE three, okay, it looks a little bit dated, okay, it looks a lot dated,
but functionally, it is a great desktop.
Yeah, you hate to give Microsoft credit, but that start menu, launcher bar, quick icons
setup that they kind of refined after Windows 95 over the years, and then lost the trail
after Windows Vista, it is a functional launcher.
And if you add that, and you put a decent file manager on there, and you have good performance
in a terminal, you're pretty close to having most people's bases covered.
Yeah, and if you look at KDE four, I think they just added too much bloat to that.
And it took people a long time to get used to it.
And I never got used to it.
And it was only really when five came out that I reevaluated that situation as an it's
almost like four is that Vista type release, probably kill me for saying that.
But three was great, but a bit dated for not so much.
But now with five, that just keeps getting better and better.
And I don't know, it's good to see Trinity.
It's a little bit like Marte, isn't it?
In a sense, Marte is more modern, of course.
But it just goes to show that if you make major changes, some people just will not like
those changes.
And they'll just hang around with the old version and fork it and still maintain it.
It gives me a lot of hope, actually, for XFCE that maybe I can just keep using that forever.
It will never die.
I mean, imagine, could you imagine if KDE 3 is still getting some love today, then XFCE
is probably good for the rest of your life.
Well, with the amount I drink, that won't be too long.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
It's a platform to learn more about Linux and all the things that runs Linux, advanced
training tools that increase your skills and encourage critical thinking, full featured
training library with servers that you spin up on demand, interactive guides as you dig
in, real human being instructors ready to help you, topic experts on the subject, practice
exams and quizzes.
There's so much to the platform that I encourage you to take advantage of that seven day free
trial.
And don't worry if you're busy.
They have a course scheduler where you can pick a course in a time frame and it'll help
you stick to it.
They have a vibrant community that keeps you going.
They have a flashcard system that gets forked by that community.
So there's a lot happening there.
And if you're just trying out Linux Academy, you're not sure yet, check out their YouTube
channel Linux Academy com on YouTube.
They're posting stuff every week now, like several things.
Their CEO, Anthony, just posted a new video as well as another edition of Google Cloud
Weekly just went up and they're doing some Docker beginner training sessions over on
their channel to all for free.
They're just passionate about this kind of stuff.
So try them out.
Go try out the course scheduler, maybe the learning pass.
See a series of course and content that's been planned by an instructor for your specific
career track.
Try out one of those hands on labs.
It's all available at linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
So let's talk about Richard Hughes again and the LVFS project, Linux Vendor Firmware Service.
We've talked about Lenovo joining the project and how great that is, especially for you
wanting to buy a ThinkPad soon.
But now Richard wants to broaden the scope a little bit and his next target is NVME drives,
SSDs.
And he wants people to submit some data about what SSDs are out there so that he knows what
to work on.
And he's got a post on the GNOME blog with instructions of how to do that.
So if you do have an NVME drive in your machine, then do check out linuxactionnews.com slash
67 and there'll be a link there.
You can click through to his blog, run a couple of commands, send him off the data and help
with getting some firmware updates for SSDs.
I ran the command.
It's pretty straightforward on Ubuntu and Fedora systems.
The package you need to install is NVME dash CLI.
And then once you install NVME dash CLI, you run the commands that Richard outlines and
you basically get back like the manufacturer identification and a model number, at least
on my Samsung drives, and I'll send those off to him.
That's pretty nice.
And he has all the information you'd need on the blog post there.
Yeah, and I think this kind of opt in approach is not going to offend anyone, is it?
Because if you don't want to share your data, you just don't run the commands.
This isn't something baked into any distro or desktop environment, but that does mean
he's going to get less data as a result of possibly doing something like putting it into
GNOME software or whatever.
Yeah, hopefully if he just gets an idea, you know, a snapshot of what the more popular
drives out there, it'll at least tell him where to start working.
The Linux kernel developers have been up to some hard work.
We've got not one, but two kernel updates in the last week.
Yeah, 4.18 and then a few point releases.
We've got the 4.18.3, which is already out within a week.
But this 4.18 kernel is a big one, isn't it?
There's a lot of new features in there.
Yeah, not only do you get support for the AMD Radeon RX Vega M chips, complete support
for the Raspberry Pi 3B and 3B+.
We're also getting support for the Qualcomm Snapdragon 845 ARM chip, which is what's found
in those new Windows 10 ARM systems.
And that's just the tip of the iceberg.
There's all kinds of great things in 4.18, even some improvements to USB Type-C and Thunderbolt.
But what do you make of this inclusion of the spec file system encryption support?
Yeah, the spec cipher, which has gotten some buzz around it online because the NSA was
involved with its creation.
This is something that I have to dig more into.
You know, I do understand why people have a strong reaction, but I think it might be
a future deep dive topic.
Yeah, there's a lot of speculation, isn't there, that the NSA have got the means to
crack this cipher, and that's why they're so keen to push it out into the mainstream.
I suppose we don't have to use it, do we, just because it's in the kernel, but I think
it's upset quite a lot of people.
Yeah, I think that's why it's worthy of the deep dive.
Yeah, well, we'll have to get Wes on the case for a TechSnap episode.
Well, speaking of TechSnap, we did a complete breakdown of Foreshadow, or that L1 data cache
bug, whichever one you like to call it, the terminal fault.
That also got patched this week.
Now, just a quick high level, it was discovered that memory present in the L1 cache of an
Intel CPU core may be exposed to malicious processes that are executing on the CPU core.
This vulnerability is known as L1 terminal fault, or L1 TF.
A local attacker in a guest VM could use this to expose sensitive information from other
guest hosts.
So it was a big deal for the cloud providers.
There's a new kernel update as well that mitigates this.
Yet more speculative execution vulnerabilities.
I remember when Spectre and Meltdown, the news of that broke, and we said at the time,
this is just the tip of the iceberg here.
We know there's going to be a lot more of this.
And sure enough, here we are.
I think this is the third or fourth one that has a name.
Yeah, if you're on a supported distribution, it is worth upgrading because one of the things
we've also discovered is sometimes the initial headline comes out and then people work away
at it for a few weeks and they discover other clever ways to exploit those flaws to go after
desktop users.
So it starts really impacting cloud providers because you have this ability for the guest
VM to read data from other guest VMs.
That's bad.
But given time, researchers and others tend to find ways to go after desktop users.
So if you're on a distribution that's getting an update, the Ubuntu, the Debian, the CentOS,
the Red Hats, go apply your update.
And one of the emails that you definitely don't want to wake up to when you are away
at a conference like OggCamp is an unattended upgrades reboot required email because, okay,
it's normally fine when you reboot.
It almost always is, but there's always that feeling in your stomach like, please come
back up.
Please.
And so I did it and thankfully I was able to go to OggCamp and not spend all day trying
to fix it.
Well, good on you.
You stayed current, Joe.
I'm proud of you.
Some people might say, oh, that Joe, he never installs his updates, but that right there
proves otherwise.
You can find out what other things Joe is up to and all the other news and headlines
in Linux free software and the open source world.
Visit our show every single week by going to LinuxActionNews.com slash subscribe for
all the ways to get our new episodes and go to LinuxActionNews.com slash contact for ways
to get in touch with us and maybe consider supporting our whole effort over here at Jupiter
Broadcasting.
Head over to Patreon.com slash Jupiter Signal.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I'm at Chris LAS.
I'm at Joe Ressington.
Thank you for joining us and we will see you next week.
See you later.