Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 178, recorded on February 28, 2021. I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes. Let's do the news.
This week, Red Hat announced yet another way to get no-cost access to Red Hat Enterprise
Linux, but it's only for those who qualify.
No, you're not experiencing déjà vu. This is an additional program from the one they
expanded in January, where they brought the production count up to 16 for developers.
This is seemingly perhaps an olive branch to people who use RHEL in production of open
source software or for infrastructure that supports open source software. But there's
a couple of hoops you got to jump through to qualify.
Hoop number one is you have to email Red Hat to be approved. You've got to actually tell
them you're interested in this program and then, in theory, go through the process, sign
up, make an account until you get access to all those goodies.
I think Red Hat's Jason Brooks made their intention clear with this quote.
We want to make sure that those organizations engaged with open source have access to RHEL
as they build and test the future of open source software.
And I think this point is kind of important. To me, it kind of sounds like you have to
email them and kind of ask and justify why you should deserve access to this. And then
they will review it and then decide if you qualify.
They do say who gets it when they're kind of talking, trying to set expectations on
their site. They say the program is available exclusively to open source projects and other
organizations that support the production of open source software. They go on to say
generally all software distributed under a Fedora approved license is considered open
source for the purpose of this program. Projects sponsored by for-profit companies can also
be eligible for RHEL for open source infrastructure subscriptions with the caveat that subscriptions
obtained through the program must be used solely for independent project infrastructure.
So there's a couple of gotchas in there and I have a few additional questions on top of
that, Wes. Like what happens if my company is sponsoring open source software today and
we develop open source software for a couple of years and then we stop? Maybe the developers
leave or the project's over. Do we then have to email Red Hat and get a quote to pay for
our licenses? Do we get to keep those licenses that were issued to us even though we no longer
support open source software? And how do I format this email when I write in asking,
please, sir, can I have some free Linux? How do I format that email?
You can tell there are definitely going to be those questions. They even note way down
at the bottom of their blog post, we realize this program doesn't cover situations where
open source projects are using public CI infrastructure provided by third parties. This and other
programs are still being worked on. That's a pretty big hole here.
Yeah, it is. That hole is big enough that it's an entire market or two of users. And
then you combine the hassle of having to email in and beg for your Linux. I think this is
enough of a barrier that people will just use Rocky Linux or they'll use cloud Linux.
They're not going to bother with these games because if you're thinking about it, you're
spending up some VMs for some infrastructure. Are you really going to mess with this sort
of loan to you Linux where it's sort of vague and not really clear what happens down the
road long term?
And yes, you get access to things like the forums, but you don't actually get support
with this. It's self-serve support. Well, I can get that with every other Linux distribution
as well.
Well, they did sort of dangle support for some organizations. We may also be able to
offer no cost support depending on the scope and nature of the organization, which that's
kind of just more questions to my mind. This might be useful for people and organizations
and projects that are in the Red Hat ecosystem pretty closely already. They had a quote from
folks at GNOME who appreciate having this access. And maybe if you're already administrating
a lot of Red Hat boxes, you're using those tools all the time. And now you can just do
that for the open source you're involved with. Okay. I mean, that's probably a good thing,
but I agree with you. The value proposition, if you don't need, you're not insistent on
having access to real RHEL, I'm not sure I get it.
I think your point's well taken that if you're producing software that's going to run on
RHEL, that's just made your life easier. And that's totally worth acknowledging. And it
is good to see because this is going to cover those areas a little bit more completely where
the developer program didn't really make sense. And so I do want to commend them for that
because my criticism of the developer program was it meant a lot of use cases were going
to kind of be shoehorned as a developer, like infrastructure. But now this is going to make
that a little more clear. But they also say this isn't going to work for a large list
of organizational types, academic institutions. This doesn't really solve their problem. Healthcare
organizations does not solve their problem. There's a lot of categories of firms like
that that are not going to qualify for this. And I think Red Hat's answer there is pretty
clear. You should just buy commercial RHEL. You have a use case for commercial RHEL in
those cases. And I don't know if I completely agree, at least in the academic sense. What
is your thought?
Well, yeah. So they do say Red Hat is continuing to explore new programs for traditional nonprofits
and academic institutions and government entities. So I think they acknowledge that maybe in
some of those cases it might make sense. You know, there's a lot of folks who are on CentOS
or people involved with scientific Linux perhaps for a while that are already in that ecosystem
probably could use some free RHEL to support scientific research, say.
Yeah. You know, actually, it's funny you mentioned scientific Linux. There are signs of life
again with that project post CentOS news. And that's interesting to develop. And it
is good that they kind of acknowledge that government was one that I didn't mention.
And it's clearly a huge one for them. Government and academic could use a solution here. And
I think then it would be a little more complete. But they're going to need support packages.
It's going to be tricky.
I think it's hard to blur that line of which organizations do or don't. I think that's
part of the reason they're trying to set some clear or not so clear guidance from the start
with this new program.
It does make a little more sense than the developer program. I'll give them that. And
this is it's almost cliche to say at this point, but it is the elephant in the room.
So I'm going to just say it. This totally should have been flushed out before the CentOS
announcement. I grok that the intention was to get the news out to CentOS users as fast
as possible so they could start planning. And that is an honorable intention. But man
oh man, if the left and the right hand couldn't have worked a little bit more together on
this one to kind of package this up. Imagine this now in its full context. You've got the
expanded 16 production system developer program. You've got this where it's not really limited
to any amount of systems. It's more about the type of industry or job function and type
of system. Yeah. But it's opened up to a lot more people. Yeah. Now then you also still
have CentOS stream, right? It's not like CentOS is gone. And so if the announcement was, hey,
you've got all these ways where you can actually just run RHEL how you used to run CentOS.
And by the way, CentOS is transitioning in a year. Plus that would have been a totally
different story than CentOS is going away as you love it. And then months of really
nothing while projects sprung up to replace what they took away before the complete picture
was out in the public. Meanwhile, behind the scenes, all knowing that this was going to
happen, the Red Hat staff knew this was the direction they were going in with these RHEL
programs, but just simply failed to execute in a way that communicated it properly. And
instead they just took one on the chin and lost reputation and lost the faith of the
open source community. Yeah. You know, here they even explicitly say that this is something
they are, they were already doing with organizations. They knew they needed to clean this up. Yeah.
But it's here now. And by the end of 2021, once CentOS has gone to stream, it's, there's
going to be a clear delineations now. It's still kind of fuzzy between all of them. Well,
you know, Alma Linux just put out an RC1. Tracking the CentOS clones as they land here
on the show. Well, while we're talking about Red Hat, OpenShift 4.7 landed this week. And
the notable thing here really is Red Hat is attempting to simplify the migration of virtual
machines to containers and also just migrating from your maybe quote unquote legacy VM stack
into OpenShift. Well, those virtual machines, they might not even be running Linux because
according to Red Hat's Peter Lauterbach, the OpenShift team has been working closely with
Microsoft on this one too. One other thing I want to talk about is that we've done virtualization
validation with Microsoft. This has actually been the case since we actually GA'd the product
several releases ago. So anything that's supported from Windows 2012 R2 onwards all the way up
to Windows 10 is a supported validated configuration, not only from Red Hat, but from Microsoft
as well.
I'll take anything that makes managing Windows a little easier.
Leno dot com slash land. Go there to get a one hundred dollars 60 day credit towards
a new account. Yeah, I said one hundred dollars. I know it's great. Leno provides virtual servers
to make it easy and affordable to host anything you want in the cloud. We use them for all
of the new infrastructure as JB 3.0. I started a couple of years ago personally using them.
And then when the opportunity to go independent came and I knew I'd need a whole new generation
of infrastructure, Leno was the obvious choice. 30 to 50 percent cheaper than places like
AWS or Google. But they've been around since 2003. So they've honed this machine. They
know what they're doing. SSD storage, 40 gigabit connections, a super easy to use UI to manage
everything. Wes and I were messing with things over the weekend and I knew Wes was up to
something because I started seeing the emails come in with some of their built in monitoring
tools. You get alerts when certain events happen, which is always a great way to kind
of get an indication that something's going on on your box. But of course, it was just
Wes being awesome. But, you know, I was thinking we talk a lot about how we use it for hosting.
But something I don't mention a lot is it's a great way to learn. And with our one hundred
dollar credit, when you go to Leno.com slash LAN, you can build a configuration of performance
and distribution and server location that's perfect for you. So you get great performance
and a platform to learn on. Think about maybe cybersecurity. This is something you could
really, really use hands on experience with. And not everyone has a dozen different rigs
of different compute power and software stacks that they can mess around with. But with our
one hundred dollar credit, you could really get a lot of runway there and learn something
fundamental about cybersecurity. There's so many great opportunities to learn there.
But perhaps, perhaps it's worth seeing if you could extend your existing infrastructure
with Linode. Maybe cloud monitoring that you roll yourself with something like Zabbix.
They have a one click app deployment for enterprise class open source monitoring. Zabbix is an
all in one monitoring solution that you can deploy on Linode and then monitor your systems
from the cloud. Try it out with our one hundred dollar credit and see how far you can get.
Leno.com slash LAN. Go there, support the show and get that one hundred dollar credit.
And a big thank you to Leno for sponsoring independent content like this here show. Leno.com
slash LAN.
Well I know you don't need yet another laptop, Chris. But what if I told you about a new
modular repairable laptop that doesn't look too bad either? This week, the framework team
unveiled their first product, the framework laptop, a thin, lightweight, high performance
13.5 inch notebook that can be upgraded, customized and repaired.
Modular, repairable, upgradable, customizable. These are not usually the terms you hear thrown
around for a modern laptop anymore, so it definitely caught our attention. Let's talk
a little bit about the specs. 11th gen Intel core processors in there. Optional Wi-Fi 6E,
up to 64 gigabytes of DDR4 RAM, four terabytes of storage. It can go up to four terabytes
of storage, which is Gen 4 NVME storage. And then, of course, like Wes said, it's thin,
lightweight, got that 13.5 inch screen, which is running at a three by two screen ratio.
But the standout item here, like the feature, the headline feature of the framework laptop
supposedly is going to be this expansion card system, which is one of these things that
could be both brilliant and also disastrous, depending on how it's implemented. The idea
is you have these modules that have ports that can be interplaced with each other. USB-C
is the back end connectivity, so you can get DisplayPort in there, micro SD, fast storage,
a high end headphone, amp, or just a USB-C port itself. Like you mix and match the modules
as you want. And that's going to be one of its strongest features, differentiators, you
could say.
So that is providing these modules get built and are there third parties that are interested
in. In theory, this is all open and anyone could build a module. Question is, will they?
Now for upgrades, both storage and Wi-Fi are socketed and there's two slots of upgradable
memory. Even the entire main board can be swapped if you want to support a new CPU gen.
That's forward looking, I like it. High use parts like the battery, screen, keyboard and
color customizable magnetic attach bezels are also easy to replace. There's even QR
codes on each item that take you directly to guides on their site.
That's all pretty nice. And I'm starting to get a picture here of this laptop that I buy
once and then I upgrade for two or three cycles perhaps, and I can get different modules.
The Linux support story in here is a little tricky. It's there, there is Linux support,
but it's it's not like a headline feature of this thing. It was mentioned once in their
post. Yeah. In the DIY edition of the laptop, which should honestly probably be what I'd
want to get anyways, but see, they know. Yeah. Yeah. Otherwise it's like windows 10 home
or windows 10 pro depending on who you are, but they're going to have the DIY DIY edition
for those of you who do prefer to install your own Linux. I don't even think it's going
to come preloaded, but all the parts, if you look at this thing, Intel processor, Intel
wifi, it's, it's all going to be supported by Linux. That's like, they don't have to
do much. And because the interconnect is likely using USB-C for all the different modules,
that's also going to work with Linux. We'll be fine. But it does remind me of my, one
of my all time favorite laptops was the Apple power book, Pismo and wall street generations.
They were, they were pretty cool laptops because they had these interchangeable modular base,
two of them, and you could change out the DVD drive for a battery. You could put a hard
disk in the slot, or if you were like me and we're a baller, you took two batteries and
you put them both in the module bay and you got all day battery life out of this laptop.
It was awesome. Rocking like Mac OS classic nine or something really old. I mean, this
is a long time ago, but back then I grok the benefit of a modular laptop. It was like,
great to have. And so you're right. This would speak to me if you could do things like pop
in a graphics card, right? That's the kind of stuff. I appreciate that the CPU is socketed.
I'd love to see that more in modern laptops in the memory and all that, and the storage
is all socketed and even the motherboard is replaceable, but that's only as long as it
fits within those thermal envelopes and that power profile. And there will be a point one
or two CPU generations down the road where that's likely no longer going to be the case.
And you'll only get so much runway out of that replacing the motherboard CPU set up.
Yeah, but it's better than what we've got now, right? Yeah. I mean, even if you could
buy one generation of motherboard CPU after your generation, that'd be great. That really,
cause that really would be, I mean, yeah, I'd like to see them do this. You know, they're
not really taking orders yet. It's still in the pre-order stage, but I looked at the crew
behind this and I thought, because that's what's going to make or break some fantasy
like this.
Who's actually trying to make this thing? It's a nice vision, but.
Yeah, well it is. And they acknowledge that they're making big claims. They say that consumer
electronics is littered with the graves of companies with grand ideas and failed executions.
The proof is going to be in the products. And they then go on to talk about what a great
team they have, which right now seems to be around 13 officially with about nine open
positions. Some of them rather critical, but I looked at their founder and I looked at
their system software engineer and they have some serious credentials, Wes. They have been
around. The founder spent years at Oculus and then even spent some years at Facebook
after the acquisition working on both software and hardware teams. Same with the main software
engineer. Seemed like they were both directly responsible for essentially every Oculus product
we've ever seen. And the other people on the team have experience from ASUS, Google, Dell.
There's others that they come from some decent pedigree.
And organizations that are building and shipping products, right? I think that's what stands
out here is it does seem like a team of people who've done this before have been through
successful releases of products and have clearly learned a lot. I think my main question is,
what's the market for this going to be? They're shooting pretty high here. I don't know what
kind of funding they have or what that runways look like and how much success do they need
to really make it here is going to be a question. Now, I think there has been more interest
in the general public and right to repair laws, repairability in general. Maybe this
stands out. I think what might make it or break it though is how thin does it really
end up being and are the aesthetics up to par?
Yeah. And then you got the nice things like how good is the keyboard? How's the screen
look? How's the track bad? How's the Wi-Fi reception? There's a lot that goes into a
good laptop.
Yeah. Does Bluetooth actually connect?
Yeah. It's a harder job than we could probably even imagine, but they do seem to have those
credentials. I'm very skeptical. I'd love to see something like this and even if it
just sort of pushed the industry or if it gave the folks over at System76 some ideas
they could do with a laptop, I'd be happy, right? I'm probably never going to buy this
laptop, but I'd love to see them push the market a little bit.
Right. At least hopefully this signals to other companies out that there might be some
interest here.
Well, something Google's been showing some interest in is funding Linux Kernel Security
Development. Google and the Linux Foundation have announced plans to fund two full-time
maintainers to exclusively focus on Linux Kernel Security Development, Gustavo Silva
and Nathan Chancellor.
Chancellor, who's been working on the Kernel for four and a half years, will be focused
on triaging and fixing bugs in Clang and LLVM while working on establishing continuous integration
systems to support that work. Now, this doesn't really sound like working on the Kernel, but
once those compiler aims are well established, Chancellor plans to begin adding features
and polish to the Kernel using those compiler technologies. He was quoted in the announcement
as saying, I hope that more and more people will start to use the LLVM compiler infrastructure
project and contribute fixes to it and the Kernel. It will go a long way towards improving
Linux security for everyone.
As for Gustavo, he'll be focused full-time on eliminating several classes of buffer overflows
by transforming all instances of zero-length and one-element arrays into flexible array
members, which is the preferred and least error-prone mechanism to declare those variables.
Additionally, he is actively focusing on fixing bugs before they hit mainline, while also
proactively developing defense mechanisms that cut off whole classes of vulnerabilities.
He's well qualified for this work, he sent his first Kernel patch in 2010, and today
is an active member of the Kernel Self-Protection Project. He's consistently one of the top
five most active Kernel developers since 2017, with more than 2,000 commits in mainline.
He's also one of the top five most active Kernel developers since 2017, with more than
2,000 commits in mainline.
There's a shiny new version of Firefox out this week, and while we don't cover every
release, this one seemed pretty special.
Version 86 is out, and one of their headline features is Total Cookie Protection, which
they say is a major privacy advance in Firefox. It's essentially creating a cookie jar for
each website, and I love that term.
I know, there are consequences to this, but that's one of those features that made me
think, why haven't we always been doing this?
86 also has simultaneous picture-in-picture mode for multiple videos, which is going to
be fantastic for me because my security cameras on LadyJupes are all RTSP video feeds that
I can pop out now into multiple independent players. Very excited about that. I actually
have switched back to Firefox recently, and I've seen notable performance improvements
even from the last time I tried it out.
One of the performance improvements you might notice this time around is they've moved Canvas
Drawing and WebGL to the GPU process. That makes sense.
That's going to be really nice. Some improvements to reader mode and also printing land in this
version. But really, for me, it's all about the picture-in-picture mode, the cookie protection,
and taking those rendering processes and moving them to the GPU. You bring all of that together,
and I think it's one of these releases of Firefox where if you haven't tried it out
for a while, it is definitely worth checking in because it's going to be noticeable.
You know, I gave that multiple picture-in-picture mode a shot, and it works pretty well. I'm
kind of impressed with that functionality in general. It feels pretty seamless, and
honestly, regardless of the Linux desktop that I use it on, it just works, and that's
impressive.
Yeah. You know, in this release, they consolidated the way they do video decoding in Firefox
and not only improved performance, but actually managed to improve security and how they do
it as well.
You know, I've been using Firefox a lot more myself, and you mentioned those reader mode
improvements. Honestly, that's one of the reasons. It's been built in forever now, and
it just keeps working. I try to use it on basically every site.
And on that theme of being back on Firefox for a bit, I really don't have any extensions
anymore that are not available for Firefox, and the ones that I have used in Chrome and
I am now using in Firefox, I find small little things that seem like they are either better
integrated with Firefox or just the way it's all handled seems to work better in Firefox
than it does for the same exact extension. There's a handful of them in Chrome.
You know, I have the same experience.
I don't know what they're doing there, Wes, but I like it, and I've been really impressed
it's nice to make it theme and make it look like my desktop. It feels more like a native
Linux desktop web browser to me than Chrome does now.
Chrome will always be a bit alien, I think.
You know, I'd be interested to know if the audience has noticed what we're talking about.
Go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact for all the ways to get in touch.
And linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
If you're curious about the tricks and tips we have for sticking with Linux after all
these years, check out Linux Unplugged 394 at linuxunplug.com slash 394.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
Thanks for joining us, and we will see you next week.