Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 253, recorded on August 10th, 2022.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Let's do the news.
We start this week with a question we know is on the minds of all of you out there.
What's the latest with Microsoft's Linux distribution?
It was just over a year ago that the world was shocked to learn Microsoft had been working
on CBL Mariner.
And not only have they been issuing steady updates, but they've also been extending its
capabilities.
And Microsoft has been issuing one or sometimes even more updates per month.
And this week, it marked the release of CBL Mariner 2.0, the July 2022 update too.
So I take that to mean they had two updates in one month.
And it seems that the release itself, well, there's a lot in there.
But one of the things that caught our attention is more and more packages are being added
that make the distribution at least somewhat practical to run on bare metal now.
Now we should note that this all still appears to be very use case specific.
So no, don't expect a desktop spin anytime soon.
They've also added some other useful packages though, like FIO and SysBench for performance
testing, KubeVert, libXF, kernel tools, and a bunch of other ones I definitely do use.
This newest revision to CBL Mariner 2.0 also adds a few more packages to its subset of
Fedora RPMs, network configuration support for unattended ISO installs, that's handy.
And it brings Linux 5.15 LTS to the mix among a bunch of other fixes and improvements.
Any adventurist among you out there can actually go find an ISO link from the GitHub Readme
page which we will have in the notes.
But I can't help wonder, how far does this go?
It starts to get bare metal support over time, starts to get more and more package support,
more and more scripting for unattended installations.
How far does this go?
And I think the second question that I feel in all of this is, and I'd love to hear the
audience's input on this.
So dear listener, how do you think the Linux community is going to process this information
about CBL Mariner and process the information around its continued growth as they push it
forward?
Go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact to let me know or send a boost into the show
with a new podcast app.
Security issues around the free software supply chain have become a popular topic of discussion
lately.
At the core of the concern is how we verify the many different free libraries and components
that modern application stacks depend on.
The Microsoft-owned GitHub announced on Monday that it plans to support code signing for
npm software packages using the code signing platform Sigstore.
That tool grew out of a collaboration with multiple tech companies to make it much easier
for open source maintainers to verify that the source code they create is the same code
that ends up in the software packages actually being downloaded and used by end users worldwide.
Those multiple tech companies include the likes of the Linux Foundation, Google, Red
Hat, Purdue University, and Chain Guard.
There's also been some significant adoption of Sigstore by the likes of Kubernetes, and
there's even an official tool for signing Python packages using Sigstore these days.
Of course, with any tool like this that requires additional work, Sigstore relies on being
free and easy to use to spur adoption and to get people to actually use it.
GitHub says it's starting with a proposal on how Sigstore will be implemented for npm,
and then also having an open comment period to get feedback from the community on exactly
how the tool will be deployed.
And on the topic of GitHub, also on Monday, the source code for an open source Ethereum
privacy mixer called Tornado Cache was completely removed from GitHub, prompting outcry from
privacy and free speech advocates alike.
This all happened after the US Treasury Department added the Tornado Cache website and a long
list of Ethereum addresses to its specially designated nationals list, banning American
citizens from using the tool or transacting with those addresses.
If you're not familiar, Tornado Cache is an app that lets users make private transactions
on the Ethereum network.
It does this by pooling together Ethereum deposited by many different users and mixing
them together so those transactions are obscured.
Within hours of the announcement by the Treasury Department, reports started to emerge that
GitHub had taken action, shutting down both the Tornado Cache project page, but also the
developer's entire GitHub account.
The developer then took to Twitter, asking, is it now illegal to write open source code?
For their part, GitHub says they had no choice but to act, though that response certainly
has provoked a general outcry from several industry leaders, who cited the 1996 federal
court case Bernstein v. U.S., which established source code as speech, protected by the First
Amendment.
And Matthew Green, a cryptography professor at Johns Hopkins University, said, quote,
30 years of hard legal work to establish First Amendment protections around software distribution,
blown up in a day by GitHub and Microsoft.
In response to clarification on the situation, a GitHub spokesperson said, quote, trade laws
require GitHub to restrict users and customers identified as specially designated nationals
or other denied or blocked parties.
Or that may be using GitHub on behalf of blocked parties.
It's an understandable tough position for Microsoft and GitHub.
Notable though, the U.S. Treasury sanctions on Tornado Cache do not name the Tornado Cache
developer or anyone involved with the project.
In fact, the only identifying information in there is Tornado Cache, the project, the
name, and some Ethereum addresses.
There is no individuals listed at all.
A tricky situation to be sure.
We're just glad there are still viable self-hosting alternatives that are out there.
But sticking with GitHub for one last story, many of us became aware of a privacy policy
reversal after a staffer tweeted about the issue.
Yeah, on December 17th, GitHub published a blog post promising not to use non-essential
cookies out of concern for user privacy.
But a week ago, that blog post got an update with an asterisk signifying that the privacy
policy had changed.
It seems that for GitHub enterprise marketing subdomains, non-essential cookies are back
on the menu with the reason being just quite simply, quote, better reach and to improve
the web experience for enterprise users.
If you're not comfortable with that change, well, there is a 30-day comment period.
You can find it at linuxactionnews.com slash 253.
Well after all of that, we kind of feel like covering something like good news from the
decentralization file on the show.
And that's IPFS, the Interplanetary File System, which is a protocol for peer-to-peer decentralized
file sharing, has now been baked into FFmpeg starting with version 5.1.
And it appears the effort is not stopping with FFmpeg.
That IPFS support actually landed in FFmpeg back in July.
But Mark Geiser, an OpenGrant participant turned Protocol Labs contractor recently blogged
about the FFmpeg IPFS implementation, sharing some more juicy details that we could really
sink our teeth into.
The utility of having a fully decentralized file protocol built right into FFmpeg, that
just seems pretty obvious to me.
And it seems like the inspiration for the idea actually came from a failed drive in
Mark's home server.
He wrote in the blog post, quote, after days of debugging, I just couldn't resolve the
issue which sparked a simple idea.
I already use IPFS, why can't I use that to play my media?
Good idea Mark, in multiple ways, because by building that support into FFmpeg, not
only does anyone using FFmpeg directly benefit, but so do a huge amount of downstream projects
that also make use of FFmpeg.
But oh no, Mark did not stop there.
He's also begun adding support to VLC, MPV, and Kodi.
That MPV support in particular, looks like it could be finished up by the next release.
For details on how to play around with this new support in FFmpeg, and the grants that
are making all of this possible, well you should check out Mark's full post, we will
have a link to that as well.
Ubuntu 22.04.1 LTS was scheduled for release earlier this week, but that's been pushed
back by an additional week, after a bug was found that led to Snaps like Firefox failing
to launch.
Now, if you've already upgraded to Ubuntu 22.04.1 via apt upgrades, don't worry, this
bug actually only affects new OEM installs.
As for the bug itself, well that was found in the final hours before release.
Thankfully though, as we record right now, the fix has been completed and it's on track
for that new release window.
That's Linode, right there, with real humans that are available to help you 365 days a
year.
Linode is how we run everything we've built in the last few years in the cloud, and like
us, Linode loves Linux, and that stuff matters to me.
As a business owner, I want to patronize other businesses that support the Linux ecosystem,
and Linode does.
They provide support for projects, they invest in open source, and they also invest in the
community.
Linode is sending us down to California in September to meet up with a whole bunch of
you and get to take a tour of JPL, and Linode doesn't do that because they're going to make
a ton of money on it, although hopefully they'll get some of you to sign up as a show of support,
but they do it as an investment in the community because they're long-term thinkers.
I mean, they've been doing this for nearly 19 years, so they've really figured out how
to do this right, and because they are Linux enthusiasts themselves, they get that connection
to the community like no other provider does.
And of course, it doesn't hurt that they're 30 to 50% cheaper than the hyperscalers that
want to lock into their esoteric crazy platforms with their own unique languages and names
for everything where they forked a bunch of projects and call them something completely
different now.
You know what I'm talking about.
That's not Linode's game.
Linode's game is simple, affordable, accessible cloud hosting.
Their game is the best place to run applications on Linux.
They've recently rolled out MVME storage, AMD EPYC processors.
They are their own ISP, and with 11 data centers around the world, you'll find something close
to you that's nice and fast.
It's so nice.
It really is, because honestly, I wouldn't want to host my stuff anywhere else.
I'm really happy to say that we are proud Linode users, and I think you're going to
love it too.
And you know, they just recently updated their Kali Linux support, so they added Kali Linux
support, and then a new version of Kali came out, and they've already updated the version
of Kali that they now let you run.
It's pretty convenient, and it's a great way to remotely audit your network.
So go try Linode, learn something, support the show, maybe deploy something.
Try it for yourself, try it for your business.
Just go to linode.com slash lan.
One more time, that's linode.com slash lan for that 60 days, $100 credit on your new
account.
Linode.com slash L-A-N.
And a big thank you to Kaliide.
Kaliide.com slash lan.
Kaliide is an endpoint security solution that uses the most powerful, untapped resource
in IT.
And users.
And when you're trying to achieve security goals, maybe it's for yourself or a third
party audit, maybe it's just for the boss, the wisdom of yesterday was to treat every
device like it's Fort Knox, with old school device management tools and MDMs that force
disruptive agents onto employees' devices, slow down performance, and gunk them up.
I never wanted that stuff on my machine.
It really turns IT admins and end users into enemies.
And not to mention those tools often create their own security problems.
So it was time for something different.
And that's why it's great to introduce you to Kaliide.
They do things better.
Instead of forcing changes on users, Kaliide sends them security recommendations via Slack.
And Kaliide will automatically notify your team when the device becomes insecure.
And it'll give that person step-by-step instructions on how to solve the problem.
And by reaching out to employees via a friendly Slack DM, and then educating them about policies,
well, Kaliide helps you build a culture in which everyone contributes to security.
Because everyone understands how and why to do it.
And for IT admins, Kaliide provides a single dashboard that lets you monitor the security
of your entire fleet.
Maybe they're on a Mac, maybe they're on Windows, and even when they're on Linux.
You can see at a glance which employees have their disks encrypted, their OS up to date,
and a password manager installed, making it easy to prove compliance with your auditors,
your customers, and leadership.
So that's Kaliide.
User-centered, cross-platform, endpoint security for teams that Slack.
You can meet your compliance goals by putting users first.
Visit Kaliide.com slash LAN to find out how.
If you follow that link, go there, they'll hook you up with a goody bag, including a
free t-shirt just for activating a free trial.
You know I love that free swag.
So go get it, it's Kaliide.com slash LAN, that's K-O-L-I-D-E dot com slash L-A-N.
You'd be forgiven for thinking you missed the announcement this week of the next Linux
kernel officially getting the 6.0 major version number.
After all, there seems to even be some confusion about that on the Linux kernel mailing list
right now.
You might just say that excitement is building for this next release, but we don't actually
know yet.
There's no official announcement.
Probably only Linus really knows if we're going to get 6.0 or 5.20 for the next kernel
release.
Historically, Linus has bumped the major number around the dot 19 release, but he sometimes
does it for the dot 20 release.
For example, Linux 4.0 came after Linux 3.19.
But just to send us a little bit of a curveball or keep things inconsistent, we did see Linux
4.20 before we got Linux 5.
So you never really know.
Why does it matter?
Well, simply put, Linux is probably the most important operating system in the world.
And at least I think there's something remarkable about how unremarkable a major decision like
this is being made.
I think to the outside observer, it probably seems a little haphazard.
Yeah, I can understand that position.
I mean, version numbers mean different things to different people, different projects, and
maybe whether something is considered a library or an application or in this case, an operating
system.
Don't know quite where that falls.
But I think you should read this and take some hints from both Linus's policies around
not making breaking changes, at least for user space.
And then also as you say it, the sort of haphazard nature.
A Linux kernel version, it just doesn't really mean much.
I've started to think of them kind of like the arbitrary release numbers that seem to
be popular with browsers these days.
I totally see that comparison.
I agree for all of the minor releases, and I think most people don't even think about
what version of the kernel they have on their distribution.
The version that the distribution ships with is probably very rarely a deciding factor
on what distro they're going to use.
I mean, it is for me, but I doubt for most people, I don't think it's something users
care about much.
However, 6.0, right, those big point releases, that's going to get coverage.
That's going to get attention.
That's going to get buzz.
And you know, I think strategically, it might be a good idea to do it because there is a
lot of great features in this release that probably should get some attention.
I mean, just super quick.
Some of my personal favorites, again, we're going to see real time kernel support possibly
land.
One of my favorite file systems, XFS, is getting improvements from multi-core CPU systems,
which is like all my systems.
ButterFS, my other favorite file system, it's getting version two of stream support, major
new features in IOU ring, which people are excited about.
And finally, the Raspberry Pi 4 GPU kernel driver is landing.
Love all of that.
Yeah, I like those too, but that's just scratching the surface with whatever this new kernel
is going to get called.
I mean, we've mentioned that Rust support is expected to land.
There are also a ton of improvements and new hardware support for both AMD and Intel, and
even some good news for Clevo hardware users out there.
Enterprise users will also benefit from some plumbing being done for Compute Express Link,
and there are some changes that should greatly improve NFS.
I just can't see them not trying to get some attention on this release, and I think people
listening will say, oh, Linus doesn't care about that stuff.
Wrong you are, I say.
I've observed this man for a long time, and I think he does think about this stuff a little
bit.
They have pride in the Linux kernel, and they have pride in their work, and they like to
go after narratives about the kernel getting too old or slow or too big.
That's all part of this, and either way, we're just super happy to see this continue to get
work done.
I mean, there's so many things landing in this next release that we could dedicate a
week's worth of shows to it.
Even our favorite feature, the new Samba server that's built into the kernel, even that is
going to see some improvements.
Long live KSMBD, I say.
How dare you.
As for when we might actually get our hands on that new kernel, well, there is a process
to follow.
The merge window, which is the time during which contributors can send in requests for
their new code to be integrated, that's currently open.
Once that closes will come a period of testing and integration work marked by a series of
release candidates.
Then, if all that goes well, we'll finally get to find out what new version we're working
with.
And either way, we'll be happy.
I went back just kind of historically to the archives in preparation for this segment,
and I read all of the release announcements between major version bumps, you know, 3.19
to 4, 4 to 5, and just read all of them and really is a capture.
It's like a time capsule of what's going on in the community at that time.
And some releases, you could tell things were kind of stressful.
And in fact, one of them, Greg even writes in there in part four line, it's just everybody
take a week off after this release, go have a week off, walk away from the computer.
That's not the sense.
I get with this release.
There's a lot of new stuff in here and a lot of excitement.
And the Colonel really seems to be firing on all cylinders this release cycle.
And every single day, Wes and I are seeing a new story, a new announcement about something
landing in the Colonel about some work being done about some improvement.
There is just a level of development, I think, looking back at those archives that we didn't
know where we'd be at back then.
We weren't sure if it would be able to continue.
There was a lot of talk if the development was sustainable in the Colonel.
And here we are.
And it's firing all cylinders are doing great.
We'll have a link to some good resources in the show notes for all of that stuff, including
a really good write up about the new user space block driver that's going to work with
IOU ring over on lwn.net.
So if you're into that stuff, that's definitely worth a read.
But either way, we're going to follow the development and all this stuff pretty closely
and we'll report back to you what ships, when it ships, what you need to know about.
So to find out what's going to happen to your Linux install before it happens, go subscribe
to the show over at LinuxActionNews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get those new
episodes and LinuxActionNews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch.
Would you like to get an ad free version of this show?
You can support this show and the entire network by becoming a member over at Jupiter.party.
Whichever version you choose will be back next week with our take on the latest Linux
and open source news.
Thanks for joining us.
And that's all the news for this week.