Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 229, recorded on February 23rd, 2022.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Let's do the news.
We start with the next generation of the TrueNAS platform, TrueNAS Scale 2202 has been released.
Unlike FreeNAS and TrueNAS 13, though, Scale is based on Linux, Debian Linux, to be specific.
When IX Systems announced that back in the summer of 2020, it's kind of a big deal, right?
Because they were really seen as a BSD shop.
And I remember them explaining some of the motivations and then mentioning KVM virtualization
was in there, Docker container support and Kubernetes support, those things were all
mentioned, but it just seemed like, wow, what a radical idea.
But as time has gone on and the team has worked on this project, it's just made more and more
sense and they've hit their milestones now.
It's great to see this release.
You know, we certainly like the BSDs here at Linux Action News, but there's no arguing
that if you want to do more than just storage, you know, run some applications, well, the
industry kind of expects things like Docker and Kubernetes these days.
And for Scale, well, IX Systems had to put in some work to migrate all their old app
capabilities that were using FreeBSD's jails over to their new Kubernetes infrastructure
that's powered by their own version of Helm charts called TrueCharts.
It's not all just taking of Linux goodies, though.
They're pretty proud that they added NFS v4 Windows style ACLs to open ZFS on Linux.
By default, Linux only has sort of more limited POSIX ACLs, but if you're going to use this
thing as a robust storage solution for primarily Windows hosts, as many do, well, you're going
to want fancy ACLs.
That's actually really great.
I have done crazy things like run RiserFS on top of SUSE to get ACL support.
I ran Gen2 for a while to get extended attribute support for Windows clients.
I moved mountains, Wes, I moved mountains.
It's also noteworthy that IX Systems is still keeping TrueNAS 13, which is based on FreeBSD.
It's still in production, and they still have it in their product lineup.
In fact, they've got some terms to help customers pick which TrueNAS is best for them.
They have the TrueNAS 13 scale up storage product, and now they have TrueNAS Scale 2202,
which they say is a scale out hyper converged product.
I think one is build storage up and one is scale out the actual application platform
horizontally is how I read that.
Yeah, with scale, they're actually integrating the Gluster file system on top of OpenZFS
to sort of let you do exactly that kind of scaling out, which we haven't really seen
before in the TrueNAS product line.
All of this is a really compelling grouping of stuff, and so we are absolutely going to
spend some time with this in studio and give it a full test on the future Linux unplugs.
Keep an eye out for that, but I'm impressed, and I can clearly see this addressing the
scale part.
I mean, TrueNAS is a wide product range, but the scale aspect now based on Linux, I would
really love to deploy this at previous clients of mine that have 20 to 200 people.
They maybe buy one small business server that runs at their operation, and it's maybe their
directory.
It is their file server.
This is less and less common these days, but there's still millions of them out there,
millions of them, and now you could put something in there that's modern.
It's easily supportable.
It's easy to expand it.
It can run all the different applications you need, and then also on the on the enthusiast
side of the market, I could see this slowly eating away at the QNAP and Synology markets
out there, at least on their high end, because the capabilities of this unit are going to
be way more than the capabilities of those appliance units, and they've also just invested
a ton in the UI, which is available on some of their other products, so they've got like
a lot of R&D going into all aspects of this, and as a Linux user, I'm really excited now
that they have a Linux based offering.
I've been a FreeNAS fan before, but I ultimately migrated away because it was BSD based, and
my skill set is in Linux.
Although that might just mean you feel a little too confident about getting into that low
level system shell and messing things up.
Often when we talk to developers building tools out in the real world, or sometimes
on the surface of Mars, they almost always tell us the same thing.
They're actually running their gear that's based on Linux with the pre-amped RT real-time
kernel patches.
Well, the group behind that patch that has recently been acquired by Intel.
In a statement on that acquisition, Intel said, quote,
Linutronics is comprised of a team of highly qualified and motivated employees with a wealth
of experience and involvement in the ongoing development of Linux.
Led by CEO Heinz Eiger and CTO Thomas Kleiksner, Linutronics is the architect of pre-amped
RT and the leading technology provider for industrial Linux.
Particularly noteworthy is that Kleiksner has been the principal maintainer of the x86
architecture in the kernel all the way back since 2008.
Intel went on to say that, quote,
By acquiring Linutronics, we're deepening our longstanding relationship with a highly
respected team of globally recognized Linux experts, adding to the remarkable breadth
and depth of Intel's hardware and software talent.
Linutronics will continue to operate as an independent business within our software division,
led by Eiger and Kleiksner.
There's no way around it.
This is a huge get for Intel.
And it's noteworthy that they're specifically calling out that it's going to remain an independent
business unit within the software division.
So it's a department inside a department that likely reports to a lead.
But nonetheless, I think this is actually a good move.
Intel has been a good steward of the kernel.
There has been some rough patches.
There has been a few issues.
But that's pretty normal when you look at the scope and depth of what Intel's involved
in.
And they participated with the kernel team for a long time.
And it's also noteworthy that back in June of 2021, the team was seeing some funding
issues, right?
And so it's conceivable that they got to a point where they needed to get some kind
of acquisition.
So it may mean that now they get paid to do this full time.
And this could be a good benefit for them as well.
So overall, I can see a lot of positive upshot to this.
And then I think the other thing that gives me some peace of mind is I don't see any kernel
developers freaking out about it right now.
They all seem pretty pleased.
No, hopefully this just means more robust preempt RT support for a long time in the
future.
Podman 4.0 came out this week and the new version supports a new network stack while
keeping compatibility with the old stack.
So don't worry.
It uses Netivark.
It's a Rust based network stack for containers.
Now don't worry if you're not ready.
Only new installs of Podman will be getting Netivark by default.
You'll still be using OCI networking if you previously were using Podman.
Another big focus for Podman 4.0 was improving the Podman experience on non Linux operating
systems.
Yes, yes, I know we try not to mention them, but Windows and Mac OS do exist.
Support for Podman on those platforms is enabled by Podman Machine, which somewhat like how
Docker Desktop does it, basically creates and manages a virtual machine under the hood
that actually runs all your containers.
Now Podman Machine is not new in this release, but it has seen some really nice improvements.
Particularly that Podman Machine now automatically mounts the Podman API socket to your host
system.
So if you're using the regular Docker CLI or, important for our use cases, Docker Compose,
you can just point that at the Podman socket, forget about Docker, perhaps entirely.
Another nice improvement is WSL2 support on Windows.
This means that instead of creating a QEMU based virtual machine, Podman can hook into
the Windows subsystem for Linux directly and get all the nice features that Microsoft's
been baking in there.
Now it's not all quite good news.
One thing I was hoping to see in 4.0 was support for volume mounts from the host.
I want my containers to be able to interact with the files I might have on my Mac or Windows
desktop.
We didn't get that with 4.0, but sounds like that's coming in version 4.1.
This week, the executive director of the GNOME Foundation gave us a heads up that his term
is coming to an end.
Neil McGovern has been there nearly five years and he's decided the timing is right to step
back from GNOME and start looking for its next leader.
It's been an interesting five years though.
As a foundation, they've gone from a small team of just about three to now employing
people to work on marketing, investment in technical frameworks, conference organization,
and really a lot more.
And of course, during this time, GNOME has become the default on many major Linux distributions.
And something I've watched blossom while Neil has been the executive director is Flathub.
Even if they just as a project just help them, encourage them, it's been great to see this
flourish and now it gives developers a way to publish applications directly to their
users and for users like me to discover applications on a daily basis.
All powered by free software.
Of course, it hasn't all been fun and games.
During his tenure, Neil also helped the foundation deal with patent suits, trademark disputes,
and by-law changes.
He also helped oversee the move of the entire GNOME development platform to GitLab, while
at the same time seeing 10 new GNOME releases, the development of GTK4, and of course a monumental
release itself in GNOME 40.
If you're curious to hear a little bit about his perspective, well, this here show did
an interview with Neil back in Linux Action News 182, which we'll have linked in the show
notes.
It's also noteworthy that GNOME 42 beta landed this week.
This is a feature freeze release.
This is a great one to help the team track down last minute bugs.
A lot of big core components have been ported to GTK4.
Dark theme support, like real dark theme support has been added to several applications now.
GNOME Shell and Mudder also see a lot of changes and improvements.
What I'm saying is big things have landed.
It's definitely worth testing and this is going to be a very special version of GNOME.
Well, we've been following this next story for a little while and it actually looks like
the hardware side of all of the rumors is getting really close.
So back in January of 2020, Google said it would bring Steam to Chromebooks.
And now it seems like that plan is really starting to get close.
Yeah, it appears that HP, Lenovo, Acer, and Asus are going to be releasing some gaming
focused Chromebooks using Project Borealis, which is Google's code name for bringing
Steam support to Chrome OS.
9to5Google has been doing some excellent work sleuthing around in the code base and according
to a developer comment from January, Google now has firm timelines for when this stuff
actually needs to ship and we maybe have some requirements for what your Chromebook would
need, which include an 11th gen Intel Core i5 or i7 and a minimum of 7 gigs of RAM, which
kind of eliminates all but those Chromebooks that are really in the upper mid or high end
range.
Another interesting little tidbit about this is that Nvidia appears to be directly involved
with the development of Steam support on Chrome OS with some of the code changes actually
being developed and submitted by Nvidia employees.
I can't say I really understand what's going on, but it'll certainly be interesting to
see how Google's plans for Chrome OS continue to play out.
Linode.com slash LAN.
Linode makes cloud computing simple, affordable, and accessible and when you go to Linode.com
slash LAN, you'll get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and you can go there to support
the show.
Linode is fast and reliable.
Put simply, it's the only place we host user facing content machines like our systems that
are designed to serve you up stuff.
Anything we build, we put it up on Linode and now that Linode has upgraded to MVME storage,
your systems can fly on there.
I mean, you'll get performance like you've never seen before.
You can get massive parallelism with MVME drives and so if you've got a database, something
that helps maybe like, I don't know, keep track of user information or backend stuff
that has a lot of IOPS, you might want to look at that.
In fact, Linode's support, which is excellent, can also help you work through these kinds
of things.
They've got a range of systems that you can pick depending on what your needs are.
And don't worry, it's all simple and easy to sort through.
They've been doing this for 19 years and they just keep getting better and better.
And now they're powered by Akamai, so it's going to get taken to the next level.
Go try it for yourself.
It's real, it's here, and you can get $100 in credit while you support the show.
Linode.com slash LAN.
And a big thank you to Ting, linux.ting.com.
Go there and take $25 off.
This is my cell phone provider.
I've been a customer since 2013.
It's just a simpler way to do mobile.
Ting is an MVNO or a mobile virtual network operator.
They run on top of the carrier networks.
They interface with those awful duopolies and create a meta company that is great to
work with, that is customer focused and has fantastic support.
And I can say that because again, I've been a customer since 2013 and their plans are
simple.
Go to linux.ting.com, review them.
They got one that's going to work for everybody.
Really it's a great option for small businesses and family too.
Often I talk about the individual possibility to save, but if you've got like five or more
lines, the savings could really add up with Ting.
It's tremendous and every plan gets access to Ting's award-winning customer service with
nationwide LTE and 5G.
And of course, Ting just recently was named the number one carrier by Consumer Reports
in 2021.
So it's simple to switch to Ting and there's no contracts ever.
And pretty much any phone's going to work because of Ting's multi-network support.
So just go to linux.ting.com, check your current phone, create an account and pick the plan
that's right for you.
Ting will send you a SIM card, you pop that in your phone and you're going to get activated
in minutes.
It happened so quick, you won't believe you weren't saving money earlier than this.
You can thank me later.
Go to linux.ting.com.
We bring you back to reality just for a moment to tell you about a new Linux-powered virtual
reality device.
It's called the Simula One and it's a full portable Linux computer built right into a
VR headset.
Powered by WL Roots and the open source Godot game engine with NixOS under the hood.
And best of all, it's not made by Meta.
No it is not.
In fact, the team behind it has been working on this for about four years.
And one of the things that really makes this headset stand out from all of the other VR
headsets on the market, besides the fact that it has a Linux box strapped to it, is the
super high resolution screen, 35.5 pixel per degree, with a real focus on making your VR
terminals look good.
Yeah, I'm talking your text terminal in VR because the team stresses they are focused
on work and productivity, not gaming.
Now this thing also features a detachable computer so you can actually take that Linux
box off and then dock it on a desktop unit at some point in the future.
And I have to say it is actually kind of nice to see some Linux action in this VR space
because so far this has really been felt like it's been dominated by commercial players.
Which speaking of, I tried one this weekend for the first time.
So if I would have seen this news story last week, I would have been Mr. Skeptical pants
on here.
I would have told you the price is outrageous, the idea is silly, I can just get monitors,
all that kind of stuff.
But I just happened to actually try a virtual work environment this weekend.
And I have changed my tune a little bit.
Having unlimited monitors at any size is like a utopia for me.
Sitting here right now recording this, I have one, two, three, four, five physical screens.
And that's not even counting like meters and stuff like that, spectrum analyzers, I'm just
talking computer screens.
And I mean, we definitely want a few more in the studio if we had anywhere to put them.
I really would.
And like when I'm recording shows with remote hosts, I'd love to do that in a virtual studio
environment.
And this is where it really started to click for me, is when I realized at home, I have
a tiny home, a very small space, it's not a private space to work.
I can put on this VR headset.
And I'm in a gigantic studio log cabin with a wood ceiling, panoramic windows that look
down on a lake with fog, with rain that drips down those windows, and I've got a big blue
couch.
And I have got six ginormous, you know, 110 inch screens in front of me are running all
kinds of stuff.
And that's when I realized, man, I could take this virtual environment.
And I could go to the studio or I could, I could go to a hotel room, I can put on this
headset, and I am working right back in my infinite office, I can take my infinite office
with me everywhere.
But the missing piece was it needed to connect to a computer, I had to bring a laptop with
me, which just isn't super portable.
I mean, when I'm traveling, I'll just bring the laptop and that's good enough.
But with Simula, they put the Linux box in the headset.
That's the game changer.
Having everything self contained, not being tethered to a full computer, but having the
headset itself be a full computer.
That's a game changer when it comes to VR.
Now there's so much that's going to it's like the smartphone West, it's like you got to
have an ecosystem, it can't really just be a single purpose device.
So I'm still a bit skeptical here.
But man, it looks like the team has really worked hard on a really good software hardware
combination.
Everything checks the boxes I was looking at, it's got an i7 under the hood, it's going
to have 16 gigabytes of RAM, it'll have Intel Xe graphics.
So you know, you're going to have a really good desktop Linux experience with this thing.
But I fear, West, this is one of those things you got to try to really appreciate.
And at this price point, I don't think enough people will be convinced on the premise to
go all in.
What do you think?
You know, I do share some of your concerns a lot about VR right now has has social aspects.
And as you say, many are not convinced about the possibilities here.
I can see what they're getting at though, you know, longer term, we may have multiple
VR systems, you might have one thing that your gaming setup, whereas you want a slightly
tweaked setup to get your sys admin or development job done during the day.
But yeah, it's pricey.
So it's probably worth pointing out that you don't actually need this fancy new hardware
if you don't want it.
The underlying window manager and operating stuff, I mean, it's all out in the open and
Simula, that customized environment built on top of Godot, well, it's officially compatible
with Steam VR headsets like the Valve Index.
There's experimental support for some open XR headsets.
And while this being Linux, some enterprising hackers have gotten it kind of working with
the Oculus Rift S. But that hardware does look really nice.
And if you'd like to see these initial takes at Linux VR continue, you may want to consider
supporting it.
They're working on a Kickstarter, hoping to raise 2.5 million.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
I mean, that's not an impossible goal.
We'll see where it goes.
But be it in the real world or the virtual world, if it involves Linux or open source,
we are going to cover it right here.
Go check out linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes every
single week.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact if you can't find us in the metaverse.
And don't miss the upcoming episode 447 of Linux Unplugged for additional coverage of
True NAS.
As for this show, well, we'll be back next week, of course, with our take on the latest
Linux and open source news.
Thanks for joining us.
And that's all the news for this week.