Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 238, recorded on April 7th, 2022. I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes. Let's do the news.
We start this week, in the midst of the spring release season, with the new 22.04 LTS version
of Pop!OS hitting the mirrors.
That's on top of the well-received Ubuntu 22.04 core, System76's release is putting an emphasis
on workflow customization, auto-tiling, and a heavy focus on a ready-to-go development
environment.
And 22.04 features their GNOME-based Cosmic Desktop, which is really pretty close in terms
of overall look and theme from what you saw in 21.10, but of course now with improvements
throughout some of those that you get just by now being based on GNOME 42, and all of
the goodies that has, including GTK4, which means you're going to see some improvements
in performance likely as well.
And one thing that I wanted to mention that just sort of jumped out at me was Pop!OS 22.04
now introduces this updated support panel in the GNOME Settings app. And in there, this
page tells you what your computer and OS model and version are. It provides links to documentation
and the Pop! community chat, and the ability to archive your recent logs up and send them
off to support.
Pop! Shop also received some nice updates, now highlights recently updated apps, and
features improved package management operations. But with those more, let's say, mundane
changes out of the way, one of the bigger changes as far as we're personally concerned,
Pop! now defaults to Pipewire.
This feels like a big step because this is an LTS release, let's keep in mind. And so
this is something maybe we wouldn't have expected traditionally, but I love it. And I think
that personally, you take some decisions like that, and you combine them with System76's
commitment to ship newer kernels as they release. That to me is going to be an interesting recipe
for a new kind of LTS that I want to keep my eyes on.
And speaking of those updates, Pop! 2204 has automatic update options now in the GNOME
panel that you can set like a time of day and week to automatically do the updates for
the system. And in there, there is now an option for not just Debian packages, not just
Flatpacks, but for Nix packages as well.
Wait, Nix? Really?
Isn't that something? I did not expect this. I haven't followed the beta super closely
for this. And so I was really surprised when I saw this. We dug into this a bit. We'll
have some links in the show notes, and we've emailed System76 for more information. But
it seems that there's like a backend service called the Pop! System Updater. And this has
facilities for these different types of packages that you might have installed, Debs, Flatpacks,
and Nix packages.
And of course, it's written in Rust. It's not all good news just yet, though. It's
probably worth mentioning that the Raspberry Pi 4 images for 2204 with Pop! Well, they're
not quite ready yet. So the ones available are still based on 2110. But it does sound
like work is underway. We'll just have to be a little bit patient.
While speaking of Ubuntu 2204, one of the new features Canonical drew attention to during
the release was the support for a real time kernel beta. But now we're learning some
more details on how that's exactly going to work.
Now most of us never actually need a quote real time kernel day to day. But for some
industrial applications, a guaranteed window of execution is absolutely critical. You know,
for industries like telecom, manufacturing, and of course, space robots. And while real
time patches, known as preempt RT, have been out there for years now, there was never really
an official way to get that kernel built on Ubuntu and supported by Canonical.
Well, 2204, that's changing. Well, as long as you're willing to sign up for Ubuntu
Advantage. If you're interested, there is the free tier of Canonical's Linux enterprise
subscription plan with extended security maintenance, kernel line patching support, landscape, and
a few other offerings. Now, that comes with the Ubuntu real time kernel access as well.
I suppose this isn't super surprising. This is a kind of a continuation of Canonical's
enterprise OS as a service. You can get the free Ubuntu, you can even run it for five
years for free. But if you want to pay for Ubuntu Advantage, you get all of these enterprise
capabilities that make it appealing. And it sells itself to a lot of customers. And now
they're adding another perk to that program, another feature set to that program. I was
actually surprised by the real time kernel support itself, because didn't really see
it come up much during the beta. It wasn't in the repos. So you know, we didn't see it
like at one point, I did look at all the available kernels. But now we know why because it's
been rolled into this Ubuntu Advantage program. And so it's going to be coming from there.
And I wouldn't be surprised going forward, if we see other enterprise specific features
may be similar to this or in the same vein, show up as Ubuntu Advantage only over time,
maybe with some time, a free PPA becomes available or something like this. But this does seem
to be a continuation of this idea they have to monetize Ubuntu on the server. And when
their goal is to IPO next year, it makes sense that they would be wanting to add competitive
features like this.
What feels like a million years ago, back in 2020, we covered the new NTFS file system
driver that Paragon software was contributing to the kernel. This driver was previously
a proprietary commercial offering from Paragon, who after years of selling that commercial
driver decided to contribute that code upstream. It features full read write support and a
ton of other features that were not found in the old NTFS driver.
Right, this was seen as a bit of a moment because finally, we would have a real true
safe NTFS driver in Linux. And then when we covered the actual deployment in Linux 515,
we thought, well, okay, we can wipe our hands of this. It's a start of a new era. We have
full NTFS support in Linux. It was time to format your drives, boys.
Oh, it was a sweet, sweet feeling. But seems not destined to last because unfortunately,
less than one year later, concerns are being raised that the driver is already orphaned
and not being actively maintained. Paragon software did pledge to keep the driver maintained
as part of the process of getting it upstreamed into the kernel. But since 515 landed, there
haven't been any major updates, despite there even being a few fixes already queued up.
Man, that is unfortunate. And you know, the kernel team tried to get that pledge. Yeah,
hey, all right, we'll do this. But don't leave us high and dry. And props to Michael Larbel
over at Feronix, who kind of put all this together. And he notes that one of the developers
that contributed a number of patches to that NTFS3 code during the review process, Cary
Oligrander, well, they raised concerns over the state of the Paragon driver to several
people. They've also noted that they've been unable to get any response from Paragon's
maintainer. It's been virtual radio silence.
Yeah, Cary raised those concerns on the mailing list and kind of classified the driver as
this point being effectively orphaned at the same time making an offer to co maintain the
driver. Although that offer is complicated because so far, there's been no response yet
from the currently recognized maintainer.
Oh, what a mess, Wes. What a what a stinking mess. You hate to see this happen. And now
it's naturally raised questions if this driver should be removed from the mainline, or at
least what action should be taken now. We'll definitely be keeping our eyes on this one,
but maybe don't rely too much on that NTFS support on Linux for now.
Checking in on the slow rollout of the Steam Deck for a moment, it seems sales have remained
strong. The Deck has held the number two top grossing product on Steam for five weeks in
a row, according to SteamDB. And this week, the Steam Deck grossed more sales than even
the massively popular new game Elden Ring.
And probably all this success likely means delays the our Steam Deck community estimates
that Valve is still working through the first 15 minutes of pre orders from July 16 2021.
Now it depends on the model you ordered. Some queues have been moving faster, but the US
only just made it past hour one, and only with the 64 gigabyte model. Now this is changing
all the time. So we'll put a link to that thread so you can get the most up to date
community estimates.
And while most of us sit here and wait, the Decks client software keeps getting better
and better. From pushing firmware updates, OS fixes, and just some nice to have features,
it seems like Valve is pushing development ahead at a pretty rapid pace. Though it does
leave us wondering a bit if it might still be some time before we see a standalone release
of SteamOS 3.
Oh, come on, Valve. We want it already. Although I could see what you're saying there. If they're
still doing a bunch of updates, they're probably not likely to drop it over the fence for the
public yet.
Let us test it for you, Valve. We'll give it a go. There's also good news in Deckland,
the compatibility layer that makes those Windows games go on Steam and on the Deck. That got
a solid update this week. Proton 7.0-2 is out now, and it is considered the new main
stable version of Proton going forward. And it has an impressive new list of games that
are now playable via Proton. And that Elden Ring we just mentioned is one of them, as
well as many others.
As you may have noticed, Matrix is one of our favorite up and coming platforms. And
in some exciting news, the leading chat client Element has rolled out threads in beta.
Threads help you separate conversations from the main timeline. Starting a new thread opens
a thread view where you can continue your conversation without interruption or interrupting
any other conversations or topics that are going on in the main timeline. It's really
quite great to see this feature roll out as more and more free software projects and fans
adopt Matrix as sort of their main place to communicate. But it's also been nice to
see because Element the client, well, it just keeps getting better with improvement after
improvement and more layers of polish. If you haven't checked it out in a while, maybe
go create an account on Matrix.org and then join us in the Linux Action News Feedback
channel that we'll have linked in the show notes.
Linode.com slash LAN. Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and you
go there to support the show. Linode is the Linux geeks cloud with 11 data centers worldwide.
They've been hard at work for almost 19 years, creating the best experience for running applications
on Linux. If you need a personal small site or you need something that's going to possibly
entertain millions of visitors, they have systems that scale to that. I was just thinking
of the large box that we deployed for our Matrix installation just recently. That's
a great example. I think we started at a $10 a month Linode and then over time we just
resized it as we needed. As the user base grew, we resized the system to meet our needs
and it's worked so great. Now we have a system with 48 cores and 96 gigs of RAM. You know,
it's pretty screaming fast and also you can get them now with NVMe PCIe storage. So it
can just be unbelievably fast on disk IO as well. And they have the best customer support,
super fast rigs and networking, and a Linux culture that runs deep in that company. There's
so many great reasons to choose Linode. After you've been using it for a minute, you'll
come up with a list of your own. And if you're like me, you'll really appreciate that you
can tell where the Linux love is baked into the product. So go put it over the top and
get $100 in credit. Try it for yourself. See why I've been talking about it and support
the show. What a great opportunity. So it's linode.com slash LAN. You go there, you get
that $100, you create the new account, you build something, you learn something. Linode.com
slash LAN. Linux.ting.com. And a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring this episode of
Linux Action News. Ting has been my cell phone provider since 2013. So go to linux.ting.com
and see how much you could save and then take $25 off by using our URL. Ting is an MVNO
or a mobile virtual network operator. That means they don't focus on digging holes in
the grounds and working with all the different local regulations. They work as a meta network
on top of the big nationwide carriers. So they get access to the same LTE and 5G networks.
But you deal with Ting who has to focus on customer support and value to survive. It's
like their whole bread and butter is customer service. Right? Where the duopolies, they
just they get you locked in and you know what that service is like. And Ting was recently
named number one by Consumer Reports in 2021. And I think what I love about Ting is their
plans are always simple and straightforward. They've changed them over the years a bit
as the industry has evolved, but they've always remained simple and easy to understand. And
one thing that's always stayed true. No contracts ever. It's simple to switch to Ting. And pretty
much any phone will work. You'll be blown away by the prices. They have cell phone plans
that are as cheap as 30 bucks a month, 15 bucks a month, depending on what you need.
You know, maybe you don't use your phone a lot. Maybe you use it a ton. Maybe you need
a data device. They also will sell you a device and you can take 25 bucks off that when you
go to linux.ting.com. Go check your current phone, create an account and pick the plan
that's right for you. It's linux.ting.com.
The folks behind the modular laptop, the framework have now made the laptops mainboard available
as a standalone component in the framework marketplace. They write in their announcement
quote, we designed the mainboard from the start as a standalone module to make upgrades
easy in the framework laptop. All you need to do is insert some memory, plug in a USB-C
power adapter and hit the tiny power button on board and you've got a powered up computer.
I love this idea and it's so great that they designed this mainboard from the beginning
to be standalone like this. What a cool idea. And not only just that Wes, but they've also
released a GitHub repository with 80 different CAD drawings. They've got electrical documentation
on there for the mainboard and they're putting it all under a creative commons license. And
in addition to that, they've got some 2D drawings of the mainboard so that you can get the exact
dimensions and they've released two 3D printable reference designs with the hope that the community
starts creating cases and accessories to house the mainboard. You could actually see like
a Raspberry Pi style case for a framework laptop mainboard, giving those of us who self-host
or maybe you just need a small headless machine, a low cost, low power, easy to repair, easy
to upgrade headless x86 system.
Maybe I can finally get you off that Pi habit. Maybe. But speaking of pricing, there are
three main options and price points here. It starts at $399 that's in USD and that gets
you a i5 11th Gen Intel, $549 for the base i7 mainboard and $799 for the i7-1185G7 board
if you want to get fancy. Then of course, add whatever memory and storage your use case
requires.
Yeah, and those are introductory prices too. So these prices will likely go up at some
point in the near future. And that is sort of the killer for the casual play around with
a little computer and learn Linux user. But it still doesn't necessarily put it out of
the price range of an enthusiast necessarily.
Yeah, and you know, that's obviously one use case here folks who like assembling hardware
who like building their own systems and now have a new modular sort of base that they
can build from. I get that. It also makes me wonder though, you know, with this being
so out in the open, is some of this research, some of this, you know, the hard work that
the framework team have done here, could any of it be used by other vendors looking to
maybe build off or build similar products?
Hmm, right. Like this is almost like a base platform. And you could take this main board
and you could put it in a whole different chassis or something like that. And maybe
you could see other vendors create products around this. I wonder, you know, you could
see it. I think clearly the major use case, which we haven't even really mentioned yet,
but is the obvious primary use case for this and these, all these standalone main boards
is for framework laptop owners that either need to do a replacement or maybe, maybe they
bought like a low end i5 model a year ago. And maybe in a year or two, they want to pop
in a high end i7 model and essentially get an entirely new PC.
It's a whole new era of laptops, or at least maybe if things like this continue to go well,
we'll see. For now, the framework folks are also giving away 100 of the i5 main boards.
But you do need to live in an area that they currently shipped to. And you have to apply
via a special form. But don't worry, we'll have that linked in the notes.
Indeed, that's pretty cool. The notes are always at linuxactionshow.com slash episode
number. So for this episode, it is linuxactionnews.com slash 238. But we'll keep an eye on all these
stories and so be sure you go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe. So that way you can get updates
on everything we talked about and new stories as they develop.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch, at least if you didn't
take our hint and join us on matrix.
And just a heads up, Linux action news will be out one day late next week. Brace yourself.
Don't worry, we will be back next week, though just just a little bit late. But still with
our take on the latest Linux and open source news.
Thanks for joining us. And that's all the news for this week.