Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News Episode 195, recorded on June 27, 2021.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Let's do the news.
We start with the release of Rocky Linux 8.4.
As you may recall, Rocky Linux was one of the first traditional CentOS alternatives
announced, and this week the gold master of their first release shipped.
Rocky Linux 8.4 is binary compatible, of course, with Red Hat Enterprise Linux 8.4, making
it possible to run apps built for Red Hat Enterprise Linux on Rocky Linux, in theory,
without too much trouble.
Developers love that.
The Green Obsidian was its code name, also known as Rocky 8.4.
And it's pretty great to see this milestone.
This was one of the first we saw crop up, and now we've seen them reach this very important
moment.
The team has a gift as part of this milestone.
There is a migration script that existing RHEL 8.4 users can install and migrate to
Rocky Linux.
Now, beware, any distribution that's had its core repositories altered, removed, duplicated,
maybe overwritten, you're going to have a bad time.
You may just totally have a broke system, so be careful and back up.
And another gotcha could be that Secure Boot is yet to be supported in Rocky 8.4, but the
good news is there is the team is working on that.
Clearly, still early days overall for Rocky Linux, and yeah, the team acknowledges that.
But it does seem like a pretty good start and some momentum in community being built
here.
Looking back, 8.4 took seven months to go from a newly formed community all the way
till today, where we've got a release available, not only for x86, but also ARM 64.
For its users, free community support is available through the Rocky Linux Mattermost, IRC, and
the forums.
And if you need something a little bit beyond that, paid commercial support is currently
available through CIQ.
Sticking with our theme of commercial support, Ubuntu maker Canonical has announced they'll
support open source Blender on Windows, Mac, and Linux.
This really all starts, though, back in May of 2020 with the release of Blender 2.83.
And with that release, the Blender Foundation announced the start of their long term support
pilot program.
That's a program aimed at ensuring that long lasting Blender projects can still be executed
using a stable version of Blender that doesn't change out from under them, but still have
that Blender version get some of those critical fixes and patches throughout a two year support
lifespan.
You can see how handy that could be for a Hollywood production that might be taking
three or four years to actually create some of the visual effects.
That's not uncommon.
Well, just recently, on June 2nd, Blender 2.93 was released.
This is the second release to enter this long term support program by the Blender Foundation.
And then this week, Canonical announced that they've partnered up with the Blender Foundation
to offer paid enterprise support around the long term support versions of Blender.
Canonical says the support offering will include Blender LTS releases across Linux distributions,
Microsoft Windows and Mac OS.
Canonical's engineers will engage directly with customers to provide comprehensive technical
support to users and they go on to say Canonical will manage the entire support process, including
integration with Blender support infrastructure.
And if you're already an Ubuntu Advantage customer, well, this is just one more support
offering baked right in.
As for what this new offering might cost, well, the standard 24 by 5 support package
starts at $500 USD per year.
Or if you need advanced coverage, 24x7 support, that's $1000.
Yeah, that's for those really demanding directors that need immediate support when something
isn't wrong with VFX.
But honestly, in terms of enterprise price points, well, those really aren't too bad.
Five hundred for the standard, a thousand a year for the high touch plan.
That's actually a pretty good deal.
And it seems like a clever move on Canonical's part.
I could see Blender being really popular with Ubuntu workstations and Ubuntu based workstations.
So what Canonical is doing here is tying all of this together.
And they're also saying at the same time, our engineers are going to handle your cross
platform support issues as well.
Does this mean there are now folks working at Canonical who get paid to just play around
with Blender in between those support calls?
Maybe.
We'll have to watch the job postings and see what comes out.
But in the meantime, Canonical is making a move to be one of the best supported Linux
distributions on the RISC-V platform.
Ubuntu now supports two RISC-V boards from Sci-Fi, the Hi-Fi Unleashed and the Hi-Fi
Unmatched.
Now, of course, we've covered Sci-Fi pretty extensively on the show in the past.
And just recently, they were in the news with rumors that Intel was looking to acquire the
company.
But in a blog post this week, Canonical wrote, Canonical's team is engaged in an ongoing
process of porting Ubuntu to Hi-Fi boards backed by the Sci-Fi engineering team as part
of a long term collaboration between the two companies.
Canonical goes on to say that RISC-V has a lot of potential and is becoming a competitive
ISA in multiple markets.
And that meant porting Ubuntu to RISC-V to become a reference OS for early adopters was
kind of a no brainer.
Yeah, at least according to Canonical.
And I see this here, and I think there's a couple of notable words in that quote of theirs,
ongoing process.
So this is a long term thing.
And they're collaborating.
The two companies are working together.
So you would think that potentially suggests future boards.
There may be some collaboration there.
So right now, practically speaking, there's essentially three Ubuntu images available
for Sci-Fi users.
The unleashed supports Ubuntu 21.04 and 20.04, and the unmatched can run 21.04.
Well, just maybe sometime soon, we'll have more RISC-V boards laying around next to our
Raspberry Pis or running in a server somewhere.
And if you're developing for that, seems like at least right now, Ubuntu is probably the
logical choice.
In just a horrifying story that we wanted you to be aware of, Western Digital is recommending
that customers unplug their MyBook Live storage devices from the internet until further notice,
while the company investigates unexplained compromises that may have entirely wiped data
from devices worldwide.
Mass incidents of disk wiping came to light in a thread on Western Digital support forum.
To make matters worse, so far, there are no reports of that deleted data later being restored.
The affected model known as MyBook Live uses an ethernet cable to connect to your local
network.
And then from there, users can remotely access their files and make configuration changes
and maybe a whole lot more through Western Digital's cloud infrastructure.
Yeah, and there's a wrinkle in this story, and that is that Western Digital stopped supporting
the MyBook Live in 2015.
Multiple users reported that the data loss coincided with a factory reset that had been
performed on their devices, and one person posted a log that showed some unexplained
behavior occurring on Wednesday.
This is just unacceptable, and unfortunately, as we record right now, there's just limited
information available, so it makes it really hard for us to make any kind of determination
we can relay to you about what is causing this mass destruction.
Western Digital's statement, well, it kind of implies that maybe customer accounts were
compromised individually, and so it's a onesie-twosie thing, but then the support forums would seem
to indicate otherwise.
I don't know.
I mean, if this event was triggered by some server-side process on their infrastructure,
I'd have a lot of questions about why that is even possible.
I mean, the stories of people losing their insurance policies or budgets, personal pictures,
business data, that's just rough to read.
If you know anyone that this has happened to, maybe a good moment to try and help if
you can get some sort of self-hosted or Linux-powered solution that they actually have complete
control over, maybe with your help, and one that can't be wiped remotely.
Lino.com.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit towards a new account and support the show.
Our friends at Lino make this possible, and when you go there, it's letting them know
you heard it right here.
You thank them for supporting us.
And you can try out Linode with $100 for real and see why they are our cloud hosting provider
of choice.
They're fast.
They have a great UI, and they have a ton of features that we love, and 11 data centers
around the world.
Linode has been doing this since 2003, and over the years, they've slowly built it into
the best place to run virtualized Linux, and they have impressive support for various technologies
you can use to manage your cloud at scale.
You know, like Terraform?
Terraform's well-known and widely used to manage infrastructure as code, and Linode
is making an eBook available that will help you understand the underlying concepts of
how it could be significant for you to leverage your infrastructure.
A free eBook will have that linked in the show notes, but go try them out.
And if you ever run into any trouble, they're fancy, super great, totally the best support
ever.
And I mean it.
They really are great.
With 24-7 support, by phone or ticket, and along with hundreds of guides and tutorials,
they're going to help you get started.
I love all of the guides, because they inspire me to build things, too.
And often, it's just one click away, with several applications you can deploy with very
little effort, or build it up from the ground up and learn something.
And remember, without $100 credit, it's never been a better time to learn.
Linode.com slash LAN.
Go there and find out why we think they're just the best.
Check out their S3 compatible object storage, which could up your backup game, or maybe
just be a great way to run a static website.
Super fast networking, and machines that are blazing fast.
Go see why we use them for everything.
Linode.com slash LAN.
And thank you to our long time supporters over at Ting.
Go to linux.ting.com and get $25 off a great plan or a great phone.
Ting just makes mobile so much simpler.
Stop banging your head against all of these confusing plans with these weird small print
items.
Just go to linux.ting.com.
Check out their Set 12 plan.
It gives you 12 gigs of data with unlimited talk and text for $35 a month.
And they have plans that are perfect for families, or plans that are great for individuals that
don't use data or need all the data.
Ting's got every plan covered with their award winning customer service, Nationwide
LTE and 5G coverage.
I'm impressed as a Ting customer how real the 5G promise has been after years of hype.
It's in my neighborhood, and it's mind blowing, 100 megabits on Ting 5G.
It's so great.
And I have the freedom of no contract.
No contract ever with Ting.
So go pick Ting right now and choose from one of their great networks.
It's simple to switch to Ting, pretty much any phone will work because they've got lots
of compatibility, and you can just get started by going to linux.ting.com.
Check your current phone, create the account, get the plan that's just right for you, and
then Ting will send you a SIM card.
Cutting your phone bill in half has never been easier with Ting's new plans.
The next generation of Ting mobile, it's here, and it's better than ever.
Go see how much you can save and then take $25 off at linux.ting.com.
Windows 11 is making a lot of news this week, but one of the issues that has caught the
attention of Linux users is Microsoft's requirement that computers running Windows 11 must have
a TPM chip and it must be enabled.
The TPM is a chip connected to your main motherboard, and what makes it special is a collection
of registers called platform configuration registers or PCRs.
When the system is reset, these registers are initialized and then during the boot process,
the system will generate cryptographic hashes of the various boot components and then pass
those hashes back to the old TPM.
Any modifications to the boot components thereafter will then change the value of all those hashes
and then change the values recorded in the TPM.
This is basically called measured boot because you're measuring all the different components
going on and then down the line that lets you detect changes or do things like restrict
access if you're not in the right measured state.
BitLocker, for example, leverages the TPM to ensure that volumes can only be decrypted
if the system booted as expected by all those measurements in the TPM.
Now why this is a concern to Linux users is many systems built to run Linux don't bother
putting TPM in because it's not something currently used by Linux and so these machines,
which might otherwise be great dual booters, will just simply be left out.
And not all Windows PCs have TPM necessarily turned on either and that can be tricky for
average users but the primary concern here is creating a generation of PCs that might
leave Linux out or I guess, Wes, it wouldn't be all Linux, it would just be any Linux that
hasn't been signed by Microsoft.
Yeah, because in conjunction with the TPM is our old friend Secure Boot and the goal
here is kind of partially to combine these two technologies together because Secure Boot
allows the firmware to validate your boot loader before executing it, right?
It's the bit that has your computer say, well, is this new OS you want to boot signed by
Microsoft or well, technically signed by whatever keys I am happened to be told to trust, otherwise
I won't boot it.
Now that works pretty well but if you're also worried about firmware attacks and Microsoft
says they are, well, the firmware itself could be backdoored and you would have no way to
really verify that Secure Boot function correctly and that's where some of these boot attacks
come from and that's where the TPM comes into play because it turns out you can use that
TPM to measure the Secure Boot state and detect if that changes and just further add boot
security.
Yeah, that's why they work well together and that's why some Linux vendors have been open
to implementing this and obviously making sure that your boot environment is secure
and verified is critical and that is a real world use case, especially one appealing to
enterprise.
However, all of that said, because I just want to play devil's advocate for those who
are concerned here, all of what I've just said aside, I think the reality is Microsoft
has been pushing this particular technology stack for over a decade and the fact that
it's taken this long for all of the pieces to be turned on because they had some requirements
in Windows 10 but it didn't have to be on by default, they've slowly been turning the
temperature up on this particular issue for about a decade now.
And that makes me think it's not a customer driven issue because if it was enterprise
customers knocking on Satya Nadella's door saying we need more security, Microsoft would
have flipped these bits on immediately, maybe even enterprise versions would have it on
by default.
This would have already been a solved problem.
The very fact that they've drugged this out for so long and have done this very slow incremental
approach actually makes me think this is a Microsoft driven feature for Microsoft motivations,
which I just can't help but think perhaps some might be to leave some systems in a state
where they're more like ARM systems, where they come with an x86 OS, perhaps that's been
subsidized by a vendor relationship and it's always going to run that particular x86 OS.
Maybe it's a Linux, maybe it's something like Chrome OS, more than likely it's something
like Windows 10.
And that has to be part of the motivation here.
So I do understand the Linux users who are concerned about this.
The flip side, I think Wes, and I wonder if you agree with this, is it feels like the
Linux vendor ecosystem is healthy enough at this point that even if some Windows vendors
make the decision either via laziness or intentionally to lock out other operating systems, it's
almost a non-issue to me because of these other vendors.
Yeah, you're right.
I mean, we've got a lot more options in the Linux space than we once did, including some
bigger vendors that themselves are happy to ship Linux.
So I don't see them shutting it out anytime soon.
But it is a little bit worrying that we're seeing more of a closed walled off garden
approach on the regular PC side of the fence as well.
I mean, as Apple's been arguing in court lately, yes, it is more secure if you restrict what
you can run on your computer, but I don't think that's a trade-off we've all agreed
to make on some of these more traditional platforms.
Yeah, I couldn't have said it better myself.
We have seen so much of mobile UI and mobile use paradigm infect the desktop.
And then we've kind of now, within the last couple of years, rounded the corner and found
the right balance there.
And I just don't want to see that same mobile creep happen when it comes to locking down
boot environments, locking down our machines.
That's been a mistake, I think, in the mobile universe, at least for some phones and some
types of devices.
And I just hate to see backward steps taken in the PC industry, making that aspect more
like mobile.
Now, I should note that even in the worst case here, where you can only boot Microsoft
software, for the moment, they are signing some distributions, bootloaders, right?
You'll be able to boot Ubuntu on one of these machines in theory, no problem, at least if
booting from USB is enabled in the firmware.
Yeah, and it seems like they've been a good faith player in that space for a while.
They have a good track record there.
So it's not alarm bells, but maybe slightly concerning to see a trend going in this direction.
And good luck getting your Arch install booting up on there.
And our last story is one that we've been watching develop for a long time.
TrueNAS Scale 2106 Beta is now available.
TrueNAS Scale is something kind of special.
It's like FreeNAS, but not based on BSD.
In fact, it's based on Debian Linux.
There's kind of a range of these products now, Wes.
Maybe we can help break them down.
All right.
Well, at the base, you've got TrueNAS, the free public base version, TrueNAS Core.
Now, this was previously known as FreeNAS, and that's probably what you know it as best.
Then there was sort of the traditional TrueNAS, which is like the commercial big brother of
traditional FreeNAS.
That's TrueNAS Enterprise.
Both of those are based on FreeBSD as usual.
And then as of January 2021, when we learned about this, there's TrueNAS Scale providing
open source hyper converged infrastructure, including Linux containers and virtual machines.
And yeah, that one is powered by Debian.
That caught my attention because I liked FreeNAS and by extension, TrueNAS quite a bit, but
honestly felt a little bit lost.
Many times something went a little sideways and I needed to actually go down to the command
line.
But now, with something based on Debian, using tools that I'm familiar with, it's kind of
marrying the best of both worlds.
So we gave it a go before the show, popped it on a machine and demoed it for a bit, and
I'm really impressed with the interface.
It's using their new slick UI that they've been developing for a little while, and it
makes it outrageously simple to set up a ZFS pool and then start installing applications
via Docker, which opens them up to a huge, huge, huge community of applications.
Yeah, I think the flexibility of this is pretty key.
I mean, they've had a lot of experience as a company making these UIs, managing your
basic simple NAS devices, but they really stress here that TrueNAS Scale is all about
the scale.
You can take just a single node and it's still super simple for you as a home user to get
set up.
But if your needs start growing, maybe you're a small business and you get some additional
locations, you can actually scale these systems out both individually on the compute side
and individually on the storage side.
And I think maybe part of what makes that quote-unquote scale happen is I think there's
some Kubernetes happening in the background because I noticed when I was deploying an
image, there was some Kubernetes commands executing on the console.
Yeah, I mean, it's got all the Linux hits, Docker, Kubernetes, and KVM.
Yeah, I was going to say.
And of course, a little bit of ZFS on the side with a nice UI and then their support
from IX Systems.
I think it's a pretty compelling product.
I think it's everything I ever wanted from TrueNAS and FreeNAS, but now it's based on
Linux and this is really worth taking a look.
Check out TrueNAS Scale.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
It's a pretty solid product and it's really, I could see the ideal small business server.
You put this on there.
We started talking about the Western Digital Livebook.
This is such a great example of an appliance you could build out of an x86 computer with
a couple of hard drives.
Our test rig had three hard drives and it just saw all the disk and made a nice pool
that we could use and start taking advantage of right away.
It probably took 15 minutes to set up.
Now, this is still beta, of course, but if you're interested in another contender in
the space, maybe give it a go and provide IX Systems some feedback.
Yeah, they would love that.
And we'll keep an eye on things and keep testing it as they finish it up.
In the meantime, go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new
episodes.
You can visit linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch, but please no TrueNAS
scale bug reports.
Meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
We have two meetups coming up in early August in Salt Lake City and in Denver.
And if you can go, we'd love to know.
So join us at meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting and sign up for one of those two meetups.
And just to note, there'll be a slightly delayed episode next week, but you should still have
your weekly Linux news on Monday with our take on everything that happened in Linux
and open source.
Thanks for joining us and we'll see you next week.