Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open source world.
This is episode 20, recorded on September 24th, 2017.
I'm Joe.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Thank you for joining me this week.
The boss is away, driving to New York.
He's almost there.
I saw his Rover log.
Yeah, sounds like a great trip.
I'm a little bit jealous, that's for sure.
Thank you for having me.
It looks like we have an excellent show today.
Yeah, well, let's get straight into it then.
So the Librem 5 is a device that we've been talking about on this show for two weeks already,
and now it's going to get a third outing.
And this time it's because the Gnome Foundation have officially partnered with Purism.
They've given it their official backing.
So I don't know whether to think that this is just good publicity or what, but either
way, it seems to have bumped up their crowdfunded total that little bit more.
Hey, that's definitely what counts in the end.
And from my perspective, I've definitely had a little bit of Purism skepticism in the past.
So having more of the technologies they rely on, having the sort of official endorsement,
that plus a lot of other changes that I've seen, some of the momentum they've been building
recently, and I think their improved transparency of late, all of those have kind of come together
and I'm feeling a lot better about them, you know, as a company and a project.
Yeah.
So the Gnome Foundation say they're committed to partnering with Purism to create Hackfest
tools, emulators, and build awareness that surround moving Gnome and GTK onto the Librem
5 phone.
A little bit nebulous, not any kind of concrete promises there, but it's still good that they've
got Gnome and KDE, and I spoke to Jonathan Riddle about it, and he said that it's almost
like the early noughties KDE Gnome wars all over again.
Hey, that's got to be good, you know, some competition.
Maybe they'll both be able to compete here, we'll end up with two awesome stacks on a
largely free phone.
Yeah, I'm just wondering which way they're going to go in the end.
That's actually if it meets its crowdfunding total, when it's still like a million dollars
away from that, so let's not forget that.
Ooh, yeah, that's a very good note.
Here's hoping, but that is a lofty goal.
Yeah, well, it's still a fair way off, and the trajectory looks good, but I don't want
to get too excited yet, and I just, I'm not willing to take the risk, so good luck to
him, and I keep saying that.
I hope it happens, and then maybe I can buy one afterwards.
Amen.
So, speaking of phones, let's talk about Replicant.
So Replicant is the totally free software version of Android, and they've had another
release this week.
6.0.
Well, they did have a 6.0 out before, so this is just another 6.0 release that's got some
security fixes, but most importantly, some new devices, when I say new devices, they're
all pretty old devices, unfortunately, and that kind of reflects the situation that you
have with Android, that the newer devices are just basically impossible to run totally
free software on.
Yeah, it's a little disappointing when you read, I mean, I'm glad that this exists.
We sort of need that, right?
It helps the ecosystem, I think, at least in some ways, even if only in theory, but
reading through it, it's a little hard to get excited about when I don't have any of
those devices.
I'm not about to go get one, so I just, I'm not going to play with Replicant anytime soon,
unfortunately.
Yeah, the device that seems most attractive to me is the Galaxy S3, because that is still
a reasonably good phone.
Yeah, and especially if you're running some open-source software, you're not loading the
latest giant proprietary app, you could still get some real use out of it.
Yeah, so even with lineage and no Google apps, you could still get pretty decent performance
out of that phone, I think.
Oh, that's a great point.
With just F-Droid, so this is, basically, that on steroids, if you want free software,
they do their very best to make all the drivers free.
So yeah, I thought it was worth giving them a shout out anyway, it would be great to see
more development and more money go into this, because there's just so little free software
when it comes to phones, we've just accepted that you're going to have all these blobs
going on, even if you're running lineage, like I am, there's still going to be a load
of proprietary software blobs running in the background.
You just can't escape it.
So yeah, it's nice to see a little bit more momentum here.
Good luck to Replicant.
And yet more mobile news, UbiPorts have released OTA2, and there's more devices there as well.
So UbiPorts is, well, they're still calling it Ubuntu Touch, it's a bit confusing, they
don't seem to have their branding quite sorted out yet, because as we know, Shuttleworth
pulled the plug on Convergence and Ubuntu Touch and Unity 8 and all that kind of stuff.
But the mobile stuff was forked, well, I suppose just carried on really by the UbiPorts team.
Yeah, in the grand tradition of open source.
Yeah.
And I was a bit skeptical that they would have enough resources to do it.
But here we are, they've released two proper releases now.
And this one is pretty solid, I tried it out today on a Nexus 5, which is one of the officially
supported devices.
And it works quite well.
I mean, it's basically Ubuntu Touch, it's a little bit more polished than it was when
Ubuntu and well, Canonical killed it.
But it's still not ready for mainstream use.
But that's the thing that my whole attitude to it changed.
I don't know if that was the same for you, when it stopped being this consumer product
and started to be just a community project again, suddenly, my expectations for it were
kind of lowered.
And I just accepted that, hey, it's a good project.
It's got potential.
Right.
And it has the potential where it needs to be to be successful kind of changes, right?
Like, if it supports some phones, if people can get some use out of it, that's totally
successful in the open source world, not as a like mainstream consumer product, though.
So I think you're right, mine has to and I've tried it on a Nexus 5.
Unfortunately, my Nexus 5 is really on its last leg.
So I'm in another situation here where I don't have a phone that I can run this on today.
But I would love to see it.
I've enjoyed using Ubuntu Touch in the past.
And certainly, I might not use it on my main mobile device.
But for projects, for embedded devices, anything that I maybe have an old tablet laying around,
I would love that to be able to run Ubuntu Touch.
Yeah.
And so they say with this release, we're officially supporting the Nexus 4 and Nexus 7 2013 Wi-Fi
version.
And users of this device will find that they can install Ubuntu Touch 15.04 using the UbiPorts
installer, which I tried the app image of today.
And that worked absolutely brilliantly.
Oh, great.
So yeah, I recommend that.
They've got an AXE and a DMG if you're on a evil proprietary operating system.
And they've got a dev as well.
So there's plenty of ways to install it.
And it just makes it so much easier than messing around with the command line.
It's just you run this nice, simple GUI, and it gets it sorted out.
No fastboot, no ADB, just boom, done.
Yeah, well, all that stuff's embedded in that, I assume, because it needs to be.
Right, it has to be.
And that's one of those little things adds a lot of polish and makes it seem like a successful
project with momentum.
And hey, maybe you could even get your only a little technical friend to play with it.
Yeah.
And I was actually speaking to Marius Gripsgard, I think it is, in the Late Night Linux Telegram
channel yesterday about this.
And he basically admitted, if that's the word, that he is testing a 16.04 version with Halliam
on a OnePlus 3.
Wow.
So that is coming.
It's not anywhere near official at this point.
It's very much internally developed and tested.
But this latest release isn't based on Halliam, which, is it Halliam?
I never know how to say that one.
I don't know either.
Yeah, which is a project that's kind of bringing together a lot of the Linux based mobile OSs.
So that's still in the future.
But it's on the horizon, which is good to see.
Yes, I would love 16.04 on my phone.
Oh, man.
Yeah, it would be good.
It's kind of strange that it's all based on 15.04, which is...
Right, that's a weird base.
It's not a standard LTS or anything like that.
Yeah, yeah, strange.
Not supported anymore.
And just, you know, it must be a bit of a hack.
So there we go.
All right, well, let's move on and talk about PipeWire.
So PipeWire is the latest creation from one of the co-creators of Gstreamer called VimTamans
or WimTamans.
I've butchered that, sorry.
And it is basically the pulse audio for video.
Is that fair to say?
You know, it's something like that.
What I found really interesting was it's not only going to be for video.
This first release is for video, but there's plans to include audio as well.
So it's pulse audio plus video.
Yeah, which kind of makes sense, doesn't it?
Because one of the major multimedia issues that you have with Linux is syncing of audio
and video together.
Yes, definitely.
And I think that speaks well of the development here, too.
It seems like they understand, you know, they're not just trying to develop the tool that scratches
their itch.
They look holistically at the problem space and they want to build, you know, the next
foundation of audio visual tools on Linux.
And that's definitely something we need, especially if we want more developers to be able to target
the platform.
Yeah, but the thing is that this is not just for audio visual stuff like video editing
and streaming and OBS stuff like JB does all the time.
It's also got wider implications, hasn't it, for remote desktops and stuff.
Yes, definitely.
It sounds like they've done some great work trying to put in some, you know, put in some
new shims, some build some foundations for the Wayland era that we are fast approaching
so that we have remote desktop capabilities, screenshot capabilities, but in a, you know,
at a foundational level that doesn't have to be hack implemented in each window manager.
The fact is we are moving to Wayland.
There are no two ways about it.
It's happening.
And you can't expect to have things that are based on working with X that are going to
work long term.
So we need to rethink stuff.
Now is the time as we're moving to Wayland to do this, I think.
And calling it pulse audio, I don't know.
People have had a lot of bad experiences because that was introduced too early into Fedora.
And this is going to be in the next version of Fedora.
So the question is, is it going to be ready?
Is it going to be another pulse audio gate, as it were?
Here's hoping that it's going to be more ready than Pulse was.
Yeah.
I think it seems like people have learned a little bit from that mistake and are trying
to avoid it.
This first release looks like it just has video and audio will be added later partially
because they are worried about that problem.
But it does, you know, we had Wim on Linux Unplugged 2.15.
Based on that, I had a lot of trust for the development models that they're doing, that
they really know the problem space well and that they're not trying to just rush in and
be the next big hyped thing in the Linux platform.
Yeah, do check out Linux Unplugged episode 2.15 and you can hear more from Wes.
Exactly.
And it looks like, you know, if you're an Arch user, or PipeWire has already packaged
an Arch and a few other distributions, so you might be able to just try it at home yourself.
DigitalOcean.com.
Sign up with the promo code, here's the thing, to get $10 credit.
DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and
easy way to spin up a cloud server.
And you can do so in 55 seconds, and with prices starting at only $5 per month, that
means you can get two months free if you use the promo code, here's the thing.
They've got data centers all over the world and they've got a great simple interface for
dealing with your droplets, as they call them, and they've got a great API as well if you
want to script it.
Loads of the JB infrastructure runs on DigitalOcean, and I've been using it for years personally.
And now, as well as block storage, you can also use object storage with DigitalOcean
with their new product, Spaces.
From just $5 a month with very reasonable rates on storage and transfer, you can scale
the storage that your project needs as desired.
And best of all, you get two months free trial with that as well.
So whether you want just a small next cloud server or a hugely powerful Linux rig out
in the cloud, go to DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code, here's the thing, and get
$10 in credit to get you started.
Well Joe, I know how much you love proprietary software running on your machine outside of
your control.
We've got some new developments over on the EFF's website.
They've got a new open letter about the recent W3C decisions around encrypted media extensions.
And for people who might not know, could you explain encrypted media extensions?
Well, to massively oversimplify it, it's a standard in HTML which allows encrypted media,
as it would suggest.
DRM is what we're talking about here.
So the likes of Netflix can stream stuff to you without you being able to dump it and
save it.
And this was proposed a few years ago to be added to the W3C standards.
And to say there was a bit of a controversy here is a bit of an understatement.
There's been an argument going on for years.
And this week it was officially voted into the standards.
Now at some point there was a suggestion of compromise whereby it would be brought in,
but security researchers could still hack on it and try and find vulnerabilities and
responsibly disclose them, but that was shot down and is not happening now.
So there was a vote of 108 in favor and 57 against with quite a lot of people abstaining.
And the thing is that the W3C is supposed to be about consensus.
And that is not exactly a consensus, is it?
That's democracy, but it's not a consensus.
Decidedly not a consensus.
And especially when we have, you know, this will have far-ranging implications and this
is about the only real kind of somewhat governance we have for the Wild West of the World Wide
Web.
Yeah.
And so the EFF, the Electronic Frontier Foundation, were members of the W3C for quite some time,
but that's it.
Cory Doctorow has said, we're leaving, I'm resigning, and you can just get on with it,
which is really sad because the EFF are a really important organization.
And for them to basically be forced into leaving over this is not good.
I wonder if they had to, I suppose they kind of did, but I think that maybe there was a
way to work through this and vocally, very publicly voice their concerns about it and
their distaste about it, but still be within the organization because we need that voice
of reason.
So it's a real disappointment here.
Yeah, it's like at one hand it makes a big fuss.
We're obviously talking about it here because of that, but what do we lose in the future
by their voice not being on the council?
Yeah.
So where do you stand on encrypted media extensions anyway, and DRM as an HTML standard?
The idea is that we get away from these plugins and Flash and Silverlight and everything.
And do you accept, are you pragmatic enough to realize that you're going to have DRM one
way or another?
I think at the end of the day I am, and I do want to be able to watch Netflix or other
services or still be able to pitch Linux and open source operating systems to friends and
family and they're going to want to do those things, even if I might not want to.
I thought that the compromise that was ultimately rejected was fairly reasonable because we
are going to have to interact with these proprietary blobs that are running, managing the DRM.
The least thing that we can be allowed to do is still introspect, still poke at our
system, still have the ownership and control.
Otherwise, what was ultimately accepted here, it really does start to take away from this
open web feeling and, yeah, sure, I downloaded Chrome, I'm running it on my laptop.
It's different now.
It's going to be farther away from Chromium and I feel less free to use and it's either
my control or their control.
I don't feel as in control.
You're starting to sound like Stallman there.
I know.
And so that's, I definitely have those feelings at the end of the day, this is going to happen
and I'm certainly going to use it.
It's definitely sad though.
Yeah, it's not ideal, but I think it was inevitable and we just have to deal with it, unfortunately.
Find other ways that we can continue to be free on the web.
Yeah.
So let's talk about Facebook.
What?
Why are we talking about Facebook?
Well, we're talking about ReactJS.
So this is another controversy that has been brewing for a while.
So React and Jest and Flow and Immutable, loads of the modern web developer type frameworks
were licensed by Facebook as the BSD plus patents license, which basically meant that
if you use the software, you can't sue Facebook even if they infringe on your patents, which
is questionable at best.
And so Apache a few weeks ago, the Apache Foundation, actually back in July, it feels
like a few weeks ago.
It sure does.
Where did some go?
But anyway, they said that no new projects can use it, any software that has this license.
And then more recently, Automatic, who are the developers of WordPress, announced that
they are not going to use React in their next major update, which is called Gutenberg.
And also, they were going to rewrite the last one called Calypso to not include it.
And shortly after that announcement, here we are, Facebook have caved in and they have
relicensed it as just plain old MIT.
It's big news.
But I think on one hand, it's kind of also not big news.
The real takeaway I saw from a lot of this discussion is just software patents are a
huge existential crisis that the software world is not really dealing with.
And what Facebook did with this kind of nonstandard license is make everyone have to start thinking
about patents.
Because right now, now we're in a situation where under MIT, there's some legal opinions
that MIT includes an implicit patent grant, but it doesn't specify that.
So before you had an actual grant of the patents.
With MIT, it's somewhat less clear.
While you don't have this other clause that takes away some of your rights, you're not
sure about the actual patents.
The other part that just shows how messed up this whole situation is, is in all the
discussions no one's even sure if there were like patents on some of these things.
Do they have patents on what the technology underneath React?
Nobody knows.
It's too hard to tell.
There's too many bad patents that exist.
I can also somewhat understand Facebook's motivations originally because they put out
a lot of open source software.
And because of the patent situation, I'm sure they must get all kinds of frivolous lawsuits.
And so this was their somewhat heavy handed attempt to try to put a stop to that.
And while that's not ideal, I do value the amount of open source work that they do.
They have a large number of developers, and they've given the world a lot of really good
software.
That's a very pragmatic view.
And I haven't really heard that.
All I've heard is, for the last few months, just ragging on Facebook saying that they're
a terrible company and why they're taking advantage of people like this.
So it's interesting to hear the other side of it and a more reasonable approach.
Yeah, I'm hopeful that after this change, even if it's not really changed, it doesn't
solve a giant problem.
Even for WordPress, it sounds like WordPress's decision wasn't even that they were that concerned
about the patent part, but that switching to the nonstandard license was causing other
people to have concerns and they were worried that that would hurt WordPress adoption.
So if we can just get back to a, you know, all right, well, no one's thinking about patents
anymore and people can continue to use React, which I personally, that's my framework of
choice for UI work.
I think it's a great technology.
I'd like to see it continue to succeed.
Yeah, and Matt Mullenweg, I think that's how you say it, who is the founder of WordPress,
has written a blog post a few hours ago that hasn't quite cleared up whether or not they
are going to go with it, you know, to change their mind basically back to going with it.
But they've certainly left the door open with his blog post there.
So we'll have to see because my understanding is it is a very popular framework.
Yes, very much so.
It sort of changed the way people looked at frameworks because it operates on this diffing
mechanism.
So instead of having to, you know, manually update various things, add a new div or something,
you just describe what you want it to look like.
React handles all the automatic diffing and figures that out for you.
So it makes it really simple to work with, very clean UI architectures that you can build.
There are some like drop-in compatible, Preact is one, basically API compatible with React,
but by going there, you lose out.
Like Facebook just has such, not only dominance, but just they have such infrastructure and,
you know, just sheer number of developer hours, plus with the React ecosystem, you get things
like React Native.
So if you already have, you know, you're a web developer, maybe you don't know how to
write Objective-C, but with React Native, maybe you don't have to.
That seems like it'd be really lucrative, especially if you work on a small startup
or a small team.
Well, hopefully people will be less reluctant to use it now.
I know people were worried about it and hopefully this has put that fire out.
Exactly.
So speaking of patents, then Red Hat have announced a broad expansion to their open
patents promise.
And that promise is to not sue you for using any of their patents as long as the software
is open source.
Now what has been expanded here is that it's now going to cover permissive licenses.
So pretty much anything that is OSI or FSF approved is covered.
So the Open Source Initiative and the Free Software Foundation have got these lists of
approved licenses and it pretty much means any open source license is covered.
And they have got over 2,000 software patents, it seems, Red Hat.
So it's good to see them extend this promise and people can sleep that little bit easier
at night now, hopefully.
Yeah, and it's, you know, it's one of those interesting, we live in such a business dominated
world.
It's kind of nice we have good actors like Red Hat here who really, I mean, obviously
they make their money, it's good for their business model to support open source.
But you know, when you're a small open source developer, maybe you want to launch your new
product or you're just trying to, you know, help and support people in the United States.
Trying to interact with the patent system, trying to understand that, trying to even
just begin, that's a nightmare.
You don't have a budget for a lawyer.
Red Hat certainly does.
So if they can be this bridge between the open source community and the legal community
and just make sure that, yes, we are not going to do this, we're setting the standard that
if you're doing open source software, we realize you're not like a, you're not a business competitor,
you're not trying to take advantage of our patents.
I imagine there's a lot of people at Red Hat who don't even like all these software patents,
but to be defensive in the industry, they have to have them.
Here they're just on the open source side, which is great.
So how much of this is actually going to be a practical benefit to people and how much
is it just a publicity grab by them, you know, trying to improve their image that little
bit further?
That is a good question.
You definitely want to be seen as this open source friendly company.
There is a lot of details here reading through their actual patent promise, you know, covered
free and open source software.
So it seems a lot more clear now whether or not projects are actually even considering
this.
I think there is kind of a put your head in the sand approach to patents a lot of the
time where we're just not going to look, we're not going to investigate, just do it.
If someone sees us down the road, then I guess we deal with it then.
I don't know how practical this is, but if you happen to be using some Red Hat technology,
I guess you're in the clear.
You can check out linuxactionnews.com subscribe for all the ways to get the new episodes every
week and linuxactionnews.com contact for ways to get in touch.
And you can support the entire network at the Patreon page patreon.com Jupiter signal.
We'll be back next Monday when it will be either me and Chris or me and another guest
will just have to see whether he gets back from New York in time.
And we'll have our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I'm at Joe Ressington.
I'm at Wes Payne.
Thanks for joining us and we'll see you next week.
Thanks for having me.
I'm Joe Ressington.