Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News. Episode 256, recorded on August 31st, 2022. I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes. Let's do the news.
And we start with a project that is as universally loved in the Linux community as just about
any project can be. FWPD.
This week, Richard Hughes, the lead developer of FWPD, as well as its backend infrastructure,
the Linux Vendor Firmware Service, announced the release of FWPD 1.8.4.
A significant update, FWPD 1.8.4 not only includes bug fixes and support for some new
hardware, but it notably also lays the groundwork for the ability to make changes to the system's
BIOS from within Linux.
Yeah, let that sink in for a minute. FWPD can now read your system BIOS settings and
has the ability to actually change them if the user desires, and has the authorization
to do so, I should say.
And this ability is not only useful for some obvious reasons out there, but should also
go towards this new Device Security Control Center page in future versions of GNOME, which
is planned to expose important hardware information, like a security issue, should they exist.
And according to Hughes, support is going to be limited, at least for now, to certain
hardware, writing, quote, we currently support this on modern Lenovo and Dell platforms via
the Firmware Attributes kernel interface. Other vendors just have to add that kernel
WMI bridge, and it should mostly start magically working.
You ThinkPad users out there will especially want to keep your eyes out for this update,
since it includes support for the ThinkPad Thunderbolt 4 dock, as well as the ThinkPad
Universal Smart Dock. Additional details on FWPD 1.8.4 can also be found via the link
in our notes to Richard Hughes' blog.
Well an update on Canonical's effort to make Ubuntu more appealing to gamers. They
are continuing to make improvements to their Steam Snap, like resolving some graphics drivers
issues, and now seem to be expanding out to other components for gaming.
Now you might guess that Canonical had snapped up another game library, or maybe created
a free interface to GOG. But you'd be wrong. The latest Linux gaming component to receive
Snap treatment is now Feral Interactive's Game Mode.
Yeah, you might remember Game Mode. That's their demon for automatically setting the
CPU governor to performance mode, and then dynamically adjusting other system settings
when a game is launched. And then it restores those settings back when you exit the game.
And it looks like Canonical here just wants to snap up more of the gaming ecosystem.
Reception in the Linux community seems to be a bit confused and hesitant. For their
part though, Canonical has been making it pretty clear they want to invest in gaming
on Ubuntu. They held a talk at the Libre Application Summit earlier this year, and opened two positions
within the company focused on gaming.
But I think it's safe to say that many of us sort of expected those efforts would be
going into system optimizations, enabling newer drivers on Ubuntu, or maybe reaching
out to developers and other partners.
Yeah, I suppose we can hope that's kind of part of the plan. Maybe what we're seeing
right now is a bit of a phase one, some basic groundwork that the team can then build on
later. I guess we'll have to see, time will tell.
Just a few days ago, Pine64 announced the Star64 single board computer prototype. And
yeah, it's powered by a RISC-V based Star5 JH7110 64-bit processor.
Alright, bring it on I say. Let's get more of these on the market. The Star64 will be
available with four gigabytes and eight gigabytes of LPDDR4 RAM. And the Star64 will also feature
an eMMC slot, a PCIe slot, and a microSD slot.
The Star64 also features dual gigabit ports, Wi-Fi 6, an HDMI and MIPI display interface.
And of course, the board also includes a 40-pin GPIO header, three USB 2.0 ports, one USB 3.0
port, a 3.5 millimeter audio jack, and a power button.
Well how about that, a power button. These small board computers are getting fancy indeed.
Now we're still missing some, I would say, essential launch details. So in my opinion,
it's a bit of a mini red flag. I have no doubt that ultimately Pine will ship this.
My main question is how finished will it ever get? But that we'll have to wait and see.
It does sound like interested developers might be able to receive their boards as early as
in a few weeks. So we'll keep you posted.
And a quick update on one of those apps that's always working for you in the background.
Network Manager 1.40 has been released with Multi-Path TCP support. Multi-Path TCP has
really come together in the kernel over the past two years, and it allows TCP connections
to use multiple paths for greater performance, efficiency, and added redundancy.
With recent kernels, the Multi-Path TCP functionality is in great shape, so it's really nice to
see the Network Manager configuration side finally adding support.
In addition to that, though, there's also been some generous cleanup around the Network
Manager DHCP client code, support for configuring the IPv6 MTU, and improved carrier detection
for you mobile users out there.
Linode.com slash LAN. Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account, and it's
a great way to support the show.
Big thank you to Linode for their continued support of Linux Action News. Keeping us going,
keeping us on the air, Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting. I think it's the best in the
business, and they have the best support in the business, and the best performance in
the business.
I know, big talk, but independent study after independent study has shown it over the years,
and I've seen it with my own eyes, too. We just launched the new website, brand new website.
It's up. If you haven't been to jupyterbroadcasting.com in a little while, go check it out.
And yeah, it's running on Linode. We build it on Linode. We deploy it on Linode. All
the infrastructure on Linode is part of our toolbag. It's how we get jobs done, and Linode's
been around for nearly 19 years, building the absolute best way for you to run applications
on Linux in the cloud, and they're 30 to 50% cheaper than those hyperscalers that just
want to lock you into their cray-cray platform, and they're always trying to upsell you. They're
always coming up with some new rebranded open source project and selling it to you for a
few bucks, you know? It's always their game. That's not the game Linode plays, and they've
structured themselves in a way where they are their own ISP. They can have a dedicated
365 support staff. They got 11 data centers around the world, and then they have great
complimentary features, stuff that makes sense, like S3 compatible object storage, cloud firewalls,
bare metal boxes if you need them, and Kubernetes, Ansible, and Terraform support, so that way
you can just snap this right into your existing infrastructure and potentially make it part
of your multi-cloud strategy. So go try it out. Go build something. Go learn something.
Go kick the tires. Go put that $100 to work and support the show. Linode.com slash LAN.
One more time, for good luck, go there and keep us going. Linode.com slash LAN.
And a big thank you to Kalyde. Kalyde.com slash LAN. Kalyde is an endpoint security
solution that uses the most powerful untapped resource in IT. Your end users. When you're
trying to achieve security goals, whether it's for a third party audit or your own
compliance standards, I think the conventional wisdom is to treat every device like it's
Fort Knox or something. You know, with old school device management tools like MDMs that
just force disruptive agents onto employees' devices, slow them down, treat privacy as
an afterthought, and often have their own set of security drawbacks. You know what I'm
talking about. It also has a way of turning end users against the IT admins and kind of
creates this baseline hostility between the two groups. Kalyde does things differently.
Instead of forcing changes on users, Kalyde sends them security recommendations via Slack.
Kalyde will automatically notify your team when their devices are insecure and give them
step-by-step instructions on how to solve the problem. By reaching out to employees
via a friendly Slack DM and educating them about company policies, Kalyde can help you
build a culture in which everyone contributes to security, because everyone understands
how and why to do it. And for IT admins, Kalyde provides a single dashboard that lets you
monitor the security of your entire fleet. Maybe they're on a Mac, Windows, or Linux,
you got it. You can see at a glance which employees have their disencrypted or OS up
to date and a password manager installed, making it easy to prove compliance to your
auditors, your customers, or even leadership or yourself. So that, that's Kalyde. User-centered,
cross-platform, endpoint security for teams that Slack. You can meet your compliance goals
by putting users first. Visit Kalyde.com slash LAN to find out how. Now when you go there,
they're going to also hook you up with a goodie bag, including a free t-shirt, just for activating
a free trial. You got to love that free swag. So it's K-O-L-I-D-E dot com slash L-A-N, Kalyde
dot com slash LAN.
And we end this week with Debian's problem with non-free firmware. The basic issue is
that the use of downloadable firmware and computer hardware is on the rise, and most
of that firmware is just not free software. The official Debian installer, however, only
incorporates free software and thus free firmware, which leads to serious problems for many users
attempting to get Debian up and running on a modern system.
Right. You got a new piece of hardware. It's got some fancy stuff in there that, well,
only has binary blobs. This has always been a gray area for Debian, and a lot of us who've
used it for a long time know that installer image only has packages from the official
main repository, which is software that's only conforming to the Debian free software
guidelines. So it's going to be a more limited set. It's generally a pretty healthy set of
software, but this is an area, hardware blobs, where it's just traditionally been a little
weak. And the same team that's responsible for creating the official installer images
that don't have that firmware, but they also create the unofficial images, which do have
the firmware in there. And honestly, most of us are going to end up just going and getting
those images to get Debian up and running on modern hardware.
But as you might imagine, the status of unofficial adds a little confusion to things. So an internal
discussion on how Debian should be handling this started earlier this year. Now that discussion
is moving forward into the Debian general resolution process.
Yeah, indeed, something can only be unofficially unofficial for so long. So discussions on
how Debian should be handling this have been going on for a really long time. This is really
being driven by a longtime contributor, Steve McIntyre, and recently he proposed a general
resolution on how Debian is going to just handle this non-free firmware situation. Now
there's a discussion period that's kicked off that'll last until September 3rd. And
this resolution that he's proposed has three main options.
First there's option A. Include non-free firmware packages on the official installation
media. In this version of the proposal, firmware binaries would be normally enabled by default
where needed for hardware support. But it would also suggest that Debian explore ways
to let users disable that support at boot time if desired. Under option A, the Debian
installer or live system would also have a means of informing the user about what firmware
is loaded, whether that firmware be free or non-free. Finally, option A specifies that
these new versions of the media would replace Debian's current official installation media,
which as we noted, does not include non-free firmware packages as it stands right now.
Then there's option B. Include non-free firmware onto the official installation media along
similar lines to option A. The main difference with option B is that these new images would
not replace the current Debian official installation media. Instead, these new images would be
separate and complimentary non-free firmware images.
Finally, there's proposal C, which is really just a simplified statement that supports
the inclusion of non-free firmware for the installer, but leaves out all the fine details
present in options A and B.
In my opinion, anything other than option A seems like bending over backwards to suit
the idealists, but that's not to be dismissive about the difficulty of that choice because
Debian is a very principled distribution and they are frequently in this struggle of ideals
over ease for end users. And this is one of those tricky problems because this probably
affects new users to Linux more than the more experienced users that are going to be making
this decision.
And so this is a kind of representative of how Debian wants to be perceived by that class
of user. And that's probably what I find the most fascinating about this decision. Ultimately,
whatever they choose to do, I can obviously roll with. But I think it's really saying
something about who Debian is targeting, who the people that are making these decisions
feel that the project is targeting at least.
Yeah, that does have some logic to it, right? I mean, most new users, well, they're still
kind of figuring out all of our principles and ideals around free and open source software
and some of the consequences that that can imply. And I agree with you, right? Like if
you are concerned about that, which there's many legitimate reasons to be concerned about
these binary blobs, having some kind of escape hatch, like a command line option to disable
that at boot, that might just work. I do want to add here though, you know, I think sometimes
when we discuss binary blobs, we think of fancy high end hardware. But another reason
for wanting non free firmware, by default, might be accessibility. Say a blind user is
running the installer in text to speech mode, but also needs audio firmware loaded to be
able to actually drive the installer at all.
Absolutely. And if they can't get the hardware activated, they can't even get the operating
system installed. And you know, option A seems like the most straightforward, you just include
the non free packages on the official installation media. The challenge seems to be that it requires
changes to the installer to actually fully execute this. So that way the user can be
properly notified. And in there, it seems like it's honestly pretty easy to add a check
box. And if for legality reasons, they needed to have it download at the time when you check
the box, that seems totally reasonable too. There is definitely a way to make this work
for the end user. You know, in the case of assisted access, perhaps the project could
make an effort if they choose not to bake it into the main image, perhaps the project
could make an effort to try to put an information campaign out there that it does tell users
that need that stuff. We do have an image for you, but you'll have to go get it here.
I don't think that's a particularly great strategy, but maybe that's something they'll
like to do if they don't choose option A. We'll see, we're going to be watching this
story and if more information is shared publicly, we'll capture it and we'll share it with you
and everything else going on in the world of Linux and open source. So don't miss an
episode, go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe to stay up to date. And head over to linuxactionnews.com
slash contact for all the ways to get in touch. I am so excited to say our new website has
launched. Check it out and then get the entire behind the scenes story on how our community
built our new website, office hours dot hair slash eleven. We'll be back next week with
our take on the latest Linux and open source news. Thanks for joining us. That's all the
news for this week.