Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 121, recorded on September 1st, 2019.
I'm Joe.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Thank you for joining me while the boss is on the road.
We've got tons to talk about, so let's get straight into it.
The big news of the week is that exFAT might be going into the Linux kernel sometime soon.
As they say, it's important to us that the Linux community can make use of exFAT included
in the Linux kernel with confidence.
To this end, we'll be making Microsoft's technical specification for exFAT publicly
available to facilitate development of conformant, interoperable implementations.
Yeah, they've opened up the technical specification for exFAT.
They haven't made it open source necessarily.
Right.
They're not providing any code at this time, just a spec of how the file system works.
And well, of course, there's already a little controversy.
Some developers say the spec is not even complete.
Yeah, but the missing parts from the spec aren't really relevant anymore, are they?
It's for Windows CE, something that's long dead.
Nothing I want to use.
Yeah, yeah.
But the key factor here is that Microsoft is adding the patents for exFAT to the Open
Invention Network's Linux system definition.
They joined the Open Invention Network last year, and there were a lot of questions at
the time.
Well, what about your fat patents?
Well, they've answered those questions now by adding them.
So now anyone who's a member, which is pretty much everyone in the industry, can use exFAT
without worry of any patent litigation.
Right.
There's even some code that's been floating around.
But before this clarity around the patent issues, well, kernel developers were obviously
a little wary about merging it.
Yeah, and Microsoft have made it clear that they are not going to add it to the kernel
themselves.
It is up to the community, as they say.
And it looks like that code is going to be added to the kernel, but in staging.
There's been some questions about the quality of the code, so having it live in staging
for a while, get brought up to the kernel's high coding standards, and just, you know,
get some more testing before it ships to any of our machines seems like a good idea.
There's also still a debate.
Some developers have talked about trying to build the exFAT driver on top of the existing
FAT driver, although that's been tried before and proved difficult.
Yeah, it doesn't look like that's the route that it's going to go, but it does seem a
little up in the air at this stage.
It seems more likely that it is going to go into staging and just be sort of cleaned up
and eventually make its way into the main branch.
Really to me, this story is interesting, not so much because of technology, honestly, I
try to avoid exFAT, but just as a continuing spotlight on Microsoft's changing attitudes
towards open source.
Well, yeah, Microsoft loves Linux.
They said that again in the post about this.
And it really is getting more evidence of the change that has happened over there.
And it's clearly of no benefit to them to make these patterns available because they're
going to make less money from that.
But I suppose the goodwill is probably worth it to them.
Right.
They want to be seen as part of the open source community.
And exFAT has been one of the longest holdouts of their patent arsenal.
The thing is exFAT is still fairly widely used in SD cards for cameras and stuff, right?
Right.
Crucially, it gets over the four gigabyte limit in FAT32.
And if you're recording, you know, 4k video files, you reach four gigs pretty quick.
I've seen people saying that it's kind of dead and not used anymore, but I don't know.
I think my camera, although it's fairly old, I think that formats it as exFAT.
So it's very annoying at the moment, you plug it into a new installation, and it doesn't
work.
Oh, yes, of course, I need to install Fuse and exFAT utils, which is just really annoying.
So ultimately, once this does go into the kernel, it'll make a few people's lives a
little bit better, I think.
I'd call that an open source win.
Yep.
Well, somewhat sad news this week, and that is that Chris Beard is stepping down as Mozilla's
CEO.
He'd been there since 2014 and has overseen a number of large organizational changes.
He's overseen Firefox kind of making a bit of a comeback, certainly in terms of technical
quality and coming up to maybe not quite feature parity with Chrome, but certainly getting
there.
Because for a while there, it was really lagging behind and it was starting to get really slow
compared to Chrome and just was not the choice of anyone.
Whereas now, I think people are certainly in the open source community going back to
it.
I've heard at least anecdotal evidence of a lot of people doing that.
I know, I certainly switched back during his tenure.
Yeah, and there's no doubt that it has improved.
It really did feel stagnant for a time, but now it's constantly changing.
Some of those changes, like the move to web extensions, has been a bit controversial,
but I think it shows a healthy and actively developed Firefox.
Yeah.
It does seem a little bit strange though that he's chosen to step down now, and he said
that he's not going to step down right away.
He's going to be at the end of the year, but that's still not a huge amount of time.
And there's not really a great explanation as to why he's decided to move on.
It is an odd time as Mozilla has launched a number of new campaigns to expand some of
their product base and explore other revenue sources.
Maybe that's just a bigger problem than he feels like handling.
Possibly because it does feel inevitable.
How long have we been talking about this though, that Google are going to pull the advertising
deal and then they're going to be very much struggling to make any money, and that's why
they've been going for these extra revenue streams?
It could be to do with that, but it's just all speculation really, because it's kind
of just the usual, I want to step back and spend more time with family and stuff.
It just all seems a bit strange timing wise.
It's also a reminder of the corporate structure that exists within Mozilla.
They've hired someone to help them search for a new CEO.
We'll see who they find.
Yeah, they've retained the services of Tuck Richards from the recruiting firm Russell
Reynolds to find a replacement.
But in the meantime, if they can't find someone by the end of the year, Mitchell Baker is
going to step in as interim CEO.
She's currently the executive chairwoman of the foundation and Mozilla Corporation.
Yeah, so she seems well suited.
I wonder if she will end up just getting the job.
It doesn't look like it from what she said, but you never know.
And it should also be said, Mozilla is a very different company, and while they feel that
the search committee knows what they're looking for, I can't imagine finding a new CEO who
understands Mozilla's unique mission would be an easy task.
Yeah, it's not your typical tech giant, is it?
No, they're trying to build for an open and better internet and not necessarily just profits
and returns.
Well, more news from Mozilla this week, Thunderbird 68 is being released, and this is a huge release
for them.
I know you, Joe, and you must be excited about the new app menu.
It's a hamburger menu, oh yes.
But it's more than just small changes like that and the ability to mark all folders of
an account as read and time zone, data improvements, spellcheck improvements.
It's the huge under the hood changes that have taken place, which mean that now only
web extension dictionaries and themes are supported, and the add-ons are only supported
if they've been adapted to work with it.
Because of this, the latest version, 68, is not a direct upgrade at this time.
You're going to have to go download it manually if you want to try it out.
Yeah, but 68.1 will come out fairly soon, and you will be able to update to that.
With all these big changes, it makes sense that they're playing it safe this time.
Yeah, it does.
They've clearly thought about this because if you try and transfer your profile data
to a machine that has an older version of Thunderbird, then it will warn you and won't
open up unless you specifically tell it to allow the downgrade to that older version.
And don't forget, they've included a little something for Chris here too, and that's improved
dark theme support.
Yeah, they're definitely getting with the times and making his prediction come true.
So yeah, that's no good, is it?
It is nice to see some of these UI and UX improvements.
I think one thing that's held Thunderbird back over the years is it's just not that
pretty.
Yeah, it has definitely felt neglected, but it feels like they care more about it.
I mean, they hired Ryan Sipes to be their community manager, and he's been really getting
the word out there and really promoting it.
And so it feels like Mozilla is starting to realize that, hang on, a standalone email
client isn't something that's totally dead.
Yes, a lot of people use webmail, but it's important to have a decent standalone email
client as well.
And they are the organization to do it.
Right, to take advantage of the open and federated standard that is email, well, we need a great
open source client.
Yeah, we can't all just rely on Gmail, can we?
Well, if you do rely on Gmail, you may be interested in Google's new Chromebook Enterprise
devices.
There are two new machines from Dell, the Latitude 5300 and 5400, kind of convertible
all in one and just a regular laptop, which I checked and Dell are selling with Windows
10 at the moment, but they're soon going to be selling them with the Enterprise version
of Chrome OS.
Now, that Enterprise version has been around for a while, but these are the first devices
that come preloaded with that.
And they've got a few enterprise friendly features, you know, the ability to remotely
disable a device.
You can delete all user data at an end of a session and well, you can integrate with
the always popular Active Directory.
Google also says it's massively revamped its admin console with performance and design
improvements in mind.
Yeah, this is Google really trying to have a go at Microsoft in the enterprise space
because how long has Microsoft dominated that space?
It's been decades, whereas now the needs of users in enterprise have changed really.
And you're seeing the rise of iPad Pros and that tablet end of things, which Google hasn't
really been able to compete in that area.
Whereas Chrome OS now is very much established, very mature, and with these enterprise features
could potentially take on Windows in the enterprise.
And if that does happen, it means that we're basically going to have desktop Linux.
Okay, you've got to put the asterisk there, but it is essentially desktop Linux in the
enterprise.
They've even emphasized in the release the ability to enable what they call managed Linux
environments on Chromebooks.
It's interesting how they've managed to target both simple end user workflows and more complicated
developer focused tasks.
Yeah, that's certainly the aim.
But what do you think?
Do you think they actually have a chance of competing with Microsoft in the enterprise?
Because the enterprise moves very slowly, doesn't it?
Yes, it does.
And Microsoft has a long history of knowing how to work those relationships.
Google a little bit less so, although I think it does make sense as they try to build their
cloud business.
Well, that's true.
I don't know though, it's such an embedded thing.
How many business people do you see on, well, in my case, on the tube with their ThinkPads
and they're all running Windows and the fact that, okay, you can run local applications
to some extent now with Chrome OS is still very much a kind of always connected operating
system.
And just little things like that, I don't know, for me, it feels like they will probably
take some of the market, but I can't see them dominating to the extent that Microsoft have
with Windows.
Maybe some new organizations, people contemplating a change or upgrading their machines might
consider this, but it's going to take a long time, if ever, to penetrate some of those
entrenched markets.
It is interesting though, these are decently specked machines, up to 32 gigs of RAM and
a terabyte SSD drive.
This is a long way from the first Chromebooks we saw.
But it's not the very latest hardware in these.
It's not like the 10th generation CPUs that we've seen in the XPSs that were announced
recently.
So Dell's not quite going all in on this.
And it's interesting that Google have said that it's not an exclusive deal and that we
might well see other OEMs shipping these enterprise Chromebooks soon.
Hey, maybe that means better Linux drivers for everyone.
Well, that was my thought as well.
Does it mean that a Latitude 5300 or 5400 are going to be decent Linux machines?
Probably right?
Because they must have picked something that had reasonable Linux support in the first
place and maybe they changed out the wireless card or whatever, but that's easy enough to
do generally.
So yeah, the more Chromebooks we see, probably the more Linux support we're going to see.
Somehow Joe, I don't see you running one anytime soon.
Not an enterprise one.
I do have an old Chromebook and I've been thinking about getting a new one to kind of
see where Chrome OS is because I've just been running proper Linux on it, gallium OS on
my Chromebook for a long time now because it's so underpowered, but it would be interesting
to see where they are with it.
Maybe that's a good excuse to buy a new toy.
That's how I'll sell it to my wife.
Good thinking.
That's a good idea.
Well, soon I might be able to check and update the firmware on my huge stack of existing
laptops though.
Yeah, Dell has reached out to Red Hat's Richard Hughes to work with an intern and build a
power user GTK app for managing firmware.
Now this would be independent of the existing GNOME software tool that can already do some
of those things.
Yeah, the main difference seems to be that in GNOME software, that's all about just updating
to the latest firmware, checking is there a new version available and then giving you
that update, whereas this is more nuanced than that.
This is more looking at the different versions of firmware that have been available in the
past and you can potentially downgrade if an older update has given you some issues
or whatever.
So this seems like it's going to be a very useful tool.
Of course, you can already do those things on the command line with thwupd, but having
a GUI client, well, that would be great and it kind of speaks a lot to how far we've come
in the world of Linux and firmware.
It used to be that you had to go burn some sort of ancient free DOS application and reboot
into it and hope that you didn't break your machine and now you just click a few buttons
in a UI.
Well, when I read about this this week, the first thing I thought was, hang on, System
76 have just announced their firmware manager, which I talked with Chris about last week
and how that can use either the System 76-firmware tool or thwupd.
And so the timing of this seems a bit bad for System 76.
It's kind of hogged their limelight almost.
I suppose for us, it's still good that we've got a plethora of tools available, but you're
right.
There's sort of independent organizations working at the same task right now.
Yeah, which could be a bit of wasted effort, but also competition is good, right?
So maybe they will kind of push each other forward and we'll end up with two excellent
firmware updaters.
It's a bit like video editors, eh?
It is.
It's interesting to note too that it seems to be Del further recognizing the value of
working upstream in the open source community instead of having to roll something themselves.
Yeah, that's true.
Yeah.
Well, also from Grom this week, they have been working with Endless on what they're
calling the Coding Education Challenge, a competition aimed to attract projects that
offer educators and students new and innovative ideas to teach coding with free and open source
software.
Endless has given them $500,000 in funding to support the prizes, and hey, that's a good
chunk of change.
It is a good chunk of change.
And so there's going to be 20 teams selected from the applicants, and there's going to
be various rounds where you can win various amounts of money, but ultimately the winner
is going to get $100,000, and the second prize is $25,000.
So it's quite a lot of money, seems to be well worth getting involved with this.
Anyone is encouraged to submit a proposal.
And I like the way they've structured this, you know, they sort of pick some of the better
ideas, move on to a prototyping phase, and if you make it to the final round, well, you
turn your prototype into a real product.
You know, I was reading this thinking this is exactly the kind of thing the Grom Foundation
should be doing, getting involved with other companies who can put up the money for competitions
like this and endeavors that will generally further free and open source software, especially
in education, because get them young and then get them hooked.
But then I thought, Endless, didn't they lay off a bunch of people not that long ago, and
don't they seem to just be constantly pivoting their business model?
And so where did they get half a million dollars to put into this?
Right, I mean, it makes sense that they'd want to support it, but that's a lot of money.
They're obviously doing better than I thought.
So fair play to them.
If you'd like more details or to submit a proposal, well, you'll have to go check out
the Gnome Foundation website.
Of course, we'll have that linked linuxactionnews.com slash one to one.
All right.
Well, I always like to end if possible with a cryptocurrency story mostly to troll Chris,
but I'm afraid you're getting trolled this time.
And this week is that Telegram is actually going to launch his gram cryptocurrency.
And it's got to do it by Halloween.
Otherwise, they're in deep trouble.
Back in 2018, they raised $1.7 billion.
Yes, that's right.
But they promised they would have this stuff launched by October 31.
And well, it's getting to be crunch time.
There were reports back in May that they'd canceled this initial coin offering.
So it was a bit of a surprise this week when the New York Times reported that it was going
ahead and that pretty much all 300 million users of Telegram are going to be offered
the gram wallet.
It's been a bit confusing too, because while Telegram has maintained a decent level of
secrecy around this project, a lot of the work is being done by Ton Labs, which is a
separate company founded to build developer tools for Telegram and well, they're kind
of vocal.
But this Telegram Open Networks, it is a little bit strange and it feels like it's just a
hype that has died down and now they have to kind of deliver on hype that was sort of
yesterday's news or last year's news.
But according to Coindesk, the code for this was due to be released today.
Now having to dig around and it does take a deep dig around, you can find a client available,
but there seem to be some aspects of it that aren't readily available yet.
Right.
That client was leaked back in the spring and has seen some regular updates, one that
was just published on the 31st, but no signs yet of things like their sharding implementation
or the consensus mechanism used for the chain.
Yeah, presumably that will be forthcoming probably by the time this gets edited and
released.
So maybe this is bad timing by us.
Of course.
But what's interesting is that this is going to be compatible with Ethereum.
Right.
And the tools we're expecting should allow apps built for the Ethereum chain to run on
TUN.
Now we should note a lot of this information is not officially confirmed and all the interesting
developers are kind of just hoping that the leaked information has so far been accurate.
You basically just have to go find the tarball and inspect the provided files and hope that
this is somehow official.
What are you telling me that something blockchain related is sketchy and not to be trusted necessarily?
Who would have thought?
Well, we'll keep an eye on that and of course all the other Linux and open source news and
report back on future shows.
And the easiest way to get those future shows is to go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe
for all the ways to get new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I'm at Joe Ressington.
I'm at Wes Payne.
Thanks for joining us and we'll see you next week.