Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 185, recorded on April 18th, 2021. I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes. Let's do the news.
And we start with news from Dell, who've announced they'll spin out their stake in
VMware, with the two companies agreeing to continue to operate without major changes
for the next five years.
On a conference call for investors, Dell founder and CEO Michael Dell emphasized the short
term benefits to shareholders, saying, as much as we grew the revenues of VMware, the
market does not appear to appreciate a hardware-software combination.
It's interesting to see Michael Dell flip his position from a total 180 in August of
2019, when he was asked about why Dell EMC and VMware were good together. His explanation
was companies like that combination of hardware and software.
Yeah, look, I think customers have told us very clearly, they don't want to be systems
integrators anymore. And they're looking for fewer partners and bringing together, you
know, a broad set of capabilities across the infrastructure, security, client devices,
the cloud, digital transformation, enabling all those capabilities for customers. They'd
much rather work with one leading company than 20 or 30.
Perhaps what Dell learned was that industries don't really like lock into hardware and
software vendors at the same time. And maybe they want some flexibility there. But either
way, we'll save that for the analysis. Back to the story details here. Like Wes said,
this deal includes a five year agreement on the two businesses essentially just carrying
on as they do today, followed by an automatic annual extension to the deal unless one of
the companies says no more, we're calling it off. Dell, which is an important aspect
of their revenue will continue to resell VMware products, makes up about 35% ish of their
revenue right now. So you can imagine the sales department was pretty relieved to see
that deal would stay in place.
It's also worth noting that Michael Dell will keep his seat on VMware's board and retains
the right to appoint another director. And while the announcement was made after markets
closed, Dell shares popped 8% in after hours trading. VMware rose 1.5%. The deal is expected
to close sometime in the fourth quarter of this year, but could still be called off if
it isn't done by early 2022. If either of the companies backs out or if something goes
pear shaped in any other way.
I guess initially, the market seems to like this. Little birdies have been hinting to
Wes and I behind the scenes that this was coming for a while. Our buddy Drew actually
predicted this on Linux Unplugs annual predictions episode and VMware's leader, like they're
what is now going to be their CEO, was hinting back in September of 2019 that maybe things
would be just fine if the two companies spun off from each other. You could see that there
was a need for some breathing room by VMware. The market's getting competitive for them.
They do a lot today. They still have a very strong market share and a very good market
position. However, companies like IBM and Red Hat and many others are coming for their
lunch, their core bread and butter. And my read of this situation is they just needed
more flexibility. They needed to divorce themselves from a particular hardware vendor and make
themselves more universally available. I imagine that's exactly what they're going to achieve
with this.
They're a legacy company in many ways, or at least from an older era, who've been trying
to establish themselves in the new world of cloud and the marketplaces there, and I think
have made some good inroads. But being tied to other legacy companies like Dell that really
are invested in non-cloud areas or EMC before that, maybe it's just holding them back. What's
interesting is this announcement coming from Dell because it doesn't seem as advantageous
for them.
When they purchased EMC, when Dell purchased EMC, which included VMware, it was a 67 billion
dollar transaction, the largest in tech history, just a ginormous acquisition. And VMware makes
up a pretty big part of that EMC acquisition. It was like clearly a big part of why they
bought it. And the idea was is Dell had now the hardware to do the storage, the compute
and the software to do the virtualization. And if you want to go big centralized storage,
they've got all this EMC tech as well. But it just didn't quite bloom into what I think
they were expecting. And I do think that a big part of their core business today is on
premises data centers, small business data centers, large businesses who want to run
their own infrastructure. That's still their bread and butter. But obviously, as the world
changes and a lot of these shops go to a hybrid setup, they have to have some sort of solution
there. And they've got like three or four irons in that fire right now trying to solve
that problem. And none of them really have anything to do with Dell. And so when you
look at it from like what's VMware doing today and how is VMware positioning themselves?
They were already kind of leaving Dell behind before this even happened. I'll be interested
to see if anything changes with VMware's role at the Linux Foundation. You know, they do
contribute a lot of things to open source and are involved in standards bodies and different
organizations as an independent company. Are they going to be able to keep doing that?
System 76, makers of Linux hardware, has announced they are developing Cosmic, the computer operating
system main interface components, a set of in-house extensions developed for GNOME Shell.
The initial release of Cosmic is due in June alongside with Pop! West 2104 and will be
based on GNOME 3.38. Cosmic itself is not a fork of GNOME, which it has been described
by as some.
System 76 said it studied user behavior and sought to refine key elements of the desktop
accordingly. Say, for example, the activities overview, the core navigation tool in the
GNOME desktop. It's now been split under Cosmic into two views, one just for workspaces, open
windows and virtual desktops, and one for launching applications. Cosmic is also adding
a dock by default because, at least according to System 76, over 56% of Pop! West users
already use Dash to Dock or Dash to Panel.
We asked Karl if they consider Cosmic to be ultimately a fork of GNOME or just a set of
super extensions.
Cosmic is an extension that creates a unique user interface while maintaining compatibility
with GNOME, GNOME extensions, and the GNOME app ecosystem. We haven't found anything that
we want to do yet that requires a fork, and we hope doing so is not required. Avoiding
forking makes our work useful to people in other distributions.
I like hearing that. When asked if they just considered basing the whole thing on the Plasma
desktop, which would let them customize some of this, Karl said,
Most of our work over the years has been in GTK. It would be a much larger decision to
port that work over. We spent some time investigating writing larger portions of the desktop from
scratch and did look at Plasma, but we haven't been persuaded that we'd had a lot of value
in either of those directions.
Fair enough if your team is more of a GTK team. That just makes sense. So we gave it
a go before the show today, and I'd say individually, the components that make up Cosmic on their
own are subtle. They subtly change the GNOME shell experience. It still feels like core
GNOME, but when you bring all of the Cosmic components together, it begins to feel still
like GNOME, but a unique GNOME, differentiated from all of the other desktop experiences
out there. And of course, it requires this new Cosmic experience, this extension that
breaks out workspaces and applications into two individual windows. The whole experience
that requires everything they've built, all of the extensions from tiling, window management,
and now this Cosmic stuff, along with their theme, kind of really make it all shine and
a unique experience.
It takes a lot to make a GNOME experience that's out of this world.
I guess that's true. And they've done a pretty good job. I'm not 100% sure that I like breaking
out the overview of your windows and your applications. I actually think one of the
nice things the GNOME team did was brought all of that into one interface. I don't know,
we'll see.
System 76 seems to be implying that they're using data and user surveys to drive some
of these design decisions. So they may have somewhere that they're aiming for. We'll have
to really wait till June and they release ISO images for that complete experience, though.
I know there's been a lot of speculation about how System 76 would continue to have developed
the GNOME desktop after all the work they've been putting in Pop OS and Pop Shell and adding
these changes. And I think that's why there's so much conversation and confusion about,
is this a fork? Because it seems like folks are worried that there might be a fork in
the future here. But so far, it's kind of impressive how much they've been able to do
just with extensions.
Yeah, it makes you wonder if that isn't going to be a challenge for them as the GNOME team
starts to address some of their extension shortcomings, but also begins to address other
technological shortcomings in the GNOME Shell. Will System 76 have a hard time keeping up?
And I guess, will Ubuntu? Because they are already basing this on GNOME 3.3.8. Well,
my laptop over here is running GNOME 40. So that means to use this, I have to go back
a version of GNOME, which all said, I probably wouldn't really lose much, you know, because
they've got a nice experience here, but it already kind of puts them behind the ball.
And it's not really their fault. That's just what Ubuntu, which they're based on, is doing.
But what I see here is maybe the first signs that highly customizing GNOME like this does
kind of put you behind a little bit. And with so much coming down the pipe to make the GNOME
experience better, I'm kind of of the opinion that I want to be on the latest and greatest
GNOME all the time. And maybe they can get it there, especially if Ubuntu gets it there.
Maybe they just inherit all of that work. But right now, I'm wondering if we're just
kind of seeing some of the early signs of when you go in heavy on customizations, you
end up behind. I guess we'll have to wait till 2110 to find out. If you're curious,
though, and you'd like to give the Cosmic components a try before the beta is out, you'll
find the packages in the System76 POP PPA. Otherwise, the sources are on GitHub and in
our show notes. But do keep in mind, this is far from the final product. System76 also
says they're looking for Windows and Mac users to experience Cosmic firsthand. If that might
be you or someone you know, you can help out by contacting UX at System76.com.
Linode.com slash LAN. Go there to get a $100 60 day credit towards a new account. And of
course, you go there to support the show. Did you know Linode is the largest independent
cloud provider out there? They started in 2003 as one of the first companies in cloud
computing three years, three years before AWS or other enterprise providers, and they
are still independently owned and doing it right. They have refined it to an art and
no matter what skill you're at, or whatever technology stack you use, Linode can help
your ideas come to life on the web. If you run into any kind of trouble or any kind of
problems, Linode comes with amazing, fantastic customer service 24 seven by phone or by ticket.
They're going to help you if you've got one Linode or you got 100. They're going to make
sure you get it taken care of. There's also hundreds of guides and tutorials to help you
make sure you're getting things set up just right and have the confidence to actually
put those things into production. That's what I love about their guides. Sometimes I just
want to make sure I'm doing it right. And they got lots of good guides to help you do
that and Linode is easy to use with a powerful cloud dashboard. And you can tell there's
little hints in there that the people that build this stuff love Linux. And one of the
features outside of just server hosting that I think is fantastic, even though they got
11 data centers around the world, super fast 40 gigabit connections, crazy fast native
SSDs, AMD epic processors for their dedicated CPU rigs. They also have s3 compatible object
storage. Chew on that for a second. Just marinate that in your brain on what you could do with
Linode s3 compatible object storage. And yeah, they got cloud firewalls. And of course, they
got simple one click application deployments, and so much more. That's why you got to check
it out yourself. So go to linode.com slash LAN, get that $100 60 day credit on your new
account and kick the tires. See what I've been talking about and help make this show
possible all at the same time. That's linode.com slash LAN.
It should come as little surprise, especially given the recent news of Google allowing rust
to be used for Android system level code, that engineers at the search giant are in
support of rust being used in the Linux kernel. In addition to that this week, there was a
rust RFC for the Linux kernel and that discussion is still taking place in the Linux kernel
mailing list. We'll get back to that. But Google engineers, they wanted to optimize the
moments and express their support on the Google security blog stating that we feel that rust
is now ready to join C as a practical language for implementing the kernel. It can help us
reduce the number of potential bugs and security vulnerabilities in privileged code while playing
nicely with the core kernel and preserving its performance characteristics.
Holy moly guacamole, Wes. This seems like this is actually happening. Linus's reaction
to the RFC seems fairly positive, inquisitive, you might say. He definitely has some questions
he wants answered. But he said, quote, on the whole, I don't hate it. But he also said
that the runtime failure panic is a fundamental issue. So, Wes, I was hoping you kind of explain
to us what this runtime failure panic is that Linus is referring to.
I thought you might ask, but I'm going to punt to Steve Klabnik, Rust core team member
who said on Hacker News that the short explanation, this code wasn't in its final form yet, but
good enough to ask for a high level review. The review came back said, hey, this looks
OK overall, but I have some questions. So really, the RFC never claimed to be in a shape
to be immediately mergeable into the kernel. Part of the problem is about the way Rust
panics. And this is kind of a big moment for Rust because up to now, yes, it has been used
for some kernel development. Look at the Zircon kernel over in Fuchsia or Redux OS, but nothing
quite as big in production as the Linux kernel. Of course, there are a lot of Rust applications.
And in those, most of the time, those applications don't really handle the situation of running
out of memory well. And you want something like a panic where you just kill that thread,
give up, something's gone wrong, you don't have memory, try again or just crash the system.
That's bad in the kernel. You don't want the kernel to die. The kernel is the one in charge
of memory allocation. So you need it to get a reasonable result back and then be able
to do something else to try to free up memory, whatever has to happen.
Yeah, you definitely don't want it panicking while it's in the kernel.
Definitely. But the nuance that got lost here was really the use of alloc, just the call
in Rust to allocate memory, the normal one. That was just a temporary measure to speed
up development. And that's why the RFC really wasn't meant to be merged as is. The point
of this discussion is to say, yes, there's some work to do, we need to make the memory
allocation do some fine tuning there as long as the rest of this looks good. And if it
does look good, which at least sounds like to Linus and many other folks, it does in
kernel Rust support is to the point that prototyping modules can start now. We can work out some
more of that binding code, figure that out, get that, you know, up to Linus's satisfaction,
but go start trying to use it.
Well, and what Linus has identified as an issue here sounds like they also already think
is an issue and are working towards solving. So that's pretty positive. Android is taking
this a step further, right? They're doing like their Bluetooth stack in Rust. And you
look at things that are inherently low hanging fruit, like the wireless driver support stack
in the Linux kernel. And you wonder if maybe that wouldn't be better rewritten in a more
memory safe language. But additionally, on top of all this, besides the what could be
some nice technical advantages supporting Rust, there's the human advantage. It allows
the kernel team, which skews a little older Wes to tap into new hype around Rust and maybe
appeal to new developers that are willing to contribute to the kernel, but just don't
like contributing in C, they want to contribute in Rust.
Yeah, I think that despite Rust obviously having its own learning curve, you know, C
is an old language, you might not know what resources to use. And just beyond all of that,
Rust is modern. It's got a linter, it's got a package manager built right in. Now, you're
not going to use all those things in the kernel world, it's definitely going to be different.
But just as a language to learn and try to bridge to get someone who might just be doing,
you know, web development on the side, but wants to start playing with the kernel, Rust
seems like a good fit.
Well, speaking of the kernel, if all goes as planned, we will have a brand new Linux
5.12 next weekend. It was supposed to land this weekend, but after looking at everything,
the team decided to put out one more release candidate and hold off on the release until
next week, which all in all is probably a pretty good decision because the 5.12 release
cycle has been kind of bumpy, slightly.
Caution is good in a project like Linux kernel, but you can't fool me, Chris. I know you were
just waiting for that N64 support, but you'll have to wait one more week. Don't worry, though.
We'll have all the details about 5.12 in the next Linux Action News.
Linux.ting.com. Ting is my mobile service provider, and it has never been a better time
to try out Ting in all of the years I have ever used Ting. Linux.ting.com will get you
$25 off. And I know it's hard to get a good family plan, too, and I want to mention this
for everyone. Ting has solved this particular pain point. As many lines as you need on your
account, it's just $10 per line. Every single line has unlimited texts and calls, and every
line shares that same pool of data so you can budget and plan accordingly. And if you
use two or 20 gigabytes or even more of data, there's a perfect Ting plan for you. Every
plan gets access to Ting's award-winning customer service. Award-winning customer service.
Not just like regular customer service, but like the extra good kind of customer service.
And that matters. You'll notice that if they got good customer service, I'm going to tell
you about it, and Ting does. Something else I love from a technical side, though, is they
have nationwide LTE and 5G networks to choose from. I'm presently on the Verizon network,
but there may be something in your area that has great signal, and they have all of the
maps to help you figure it out. One thing about Ting to keep in mind is they keep things
simple. It's really easy to switch to Ting, and it's really easy to get your new phone
or an old phone set up. Pretty much any phone's going to work on Ting because they got so
many dang networks. So just head to linux.ting.com to check your current phone, create an account,
and pick up the plan that's just right for you. Right for you could be something very
different than what I use, but that's the beautiful thing about Ting. You get what's
right, they send you a SIM card, you pop it in, you go to their website, within minutes
you're going. Really, that's it. Like the time it takes you to hear this, you could
be up and running on Ting. Cut your phone bill in half in minutes and get started with
Ting. Just go to linux.ting.com.
The team behind Matrix, Element Matrix Services, also known as EMS, have announced they're
launching a hosted bridge for Microsoft Teams. A single Microsoft Teams bridge supports unlimited
users across unlimited channels. And the pricing is actually based on the number of active
users that are using the bridge from Microsoft Teams at a cost of 50 cents per user per month.
And then all of the other traffic and stuff related to that is free. But what's notable
about this release, at least if you're not a Microsoft Teams user anyway, is that when
they were asked if the bridge would be open source, they said no. The bridge itself is
not going to drop into the open source matrix code anytime soon. This is an entirely new
bridge that we've built exclusively for Element Matrix Services, which is the SaaS hosting
platform we provide in order to keep the lights on for Matrix development and for Element
in general.
Yeah, they kind of make a joke about how if you're rich enough to pay for Teams, you're
rich enough to pay for our bridge.
You know, I have to give them some credit there. Matrix is pretty neat. It's definitely
a useful product and you have to fund it somehow. I think this just caught some of us by surprise.
Yeah, not going open source. Yeah, I agree. But I think when you look at the client for
this, these are clients that use Teams that are trying to get to platforms maybe that
Teams isn't on. Or another use case that I think they mentioned in their press announcement,
but I know companies I've worked for would be all over this, is DR, disaster recovery,
is it like maybe Teams is down option or a backup in searchable index of Teams. That's
super valuable there too. And you don't even have to do it for all your users necessarily.
So there's really, when you look at the customer base here, Wes, I think I see their logic.
It would be nice if you could self-host this, right? Like if you could just run this on
your own VPS or your own on-premises box, that would be ideal.
And to that point, I suppose I should note that there's nothing stopping a willing developer
out there for making an open source Teams bridge if they want. Although it's not going
to be me.
This is why friends just don't let friends use Teams.
Speaking of Microsoft, Microsoft's WSL team has just shipped the latest Linux 5.10 series
kernel to Windows Insiders. And the new update brings some nice to see improvements.
The way Microsoft works on the Linux kernel is fascinating. They have a Linux system group
that is responsible for creating the WSL2 kernel, as well as the ones that run on Azure
and a lot of their other devices. They have like a department at Microsoft that is dedicated
to Linux kernel development. And once they say they have a new version ready, they pass
it on to the WSL team. The WSL team runs it through a series of tests. They test it internally
extensively. And then once it's passed those tests, they ship it off to the Windows Insiders.
Those crazy batch of living on the edge Windows users then pull down the latest Microsoft
updates and in this one, they're going to get a Linux kernel update that will add Lux
disk encryption. And with some nice WSL fancy command line love, you will be able to mount
those Lux disks inside of a Windows host.
This shiny new kernel also fixes a clock sync issue that caused WSL2 instances to have a
different time than the actual time on the host machine. Not what you'd expect. Windows
Insiders out there just need to run Windows update and they'll be upgraded to the latest
kernel version. Microsoft shipping Linux kernels in Windows update. I'm still not used to
it.
And one last story in the Microsoft and Windows world. Thank you to Michael over at Ferronix
for noting that Hangover had a new release. Hangover 0.65 is now available. Forgetting
wine up and running with cross architecture support so you can enjoy the likes of Windows
games and Windows applications under 64 bit arm and even IBM power hardware that's running
Linux.
Yeah, that's right. Hangover, of course, is the project that crafts wine with a modified
QEMU and other bits, allowing x86 32 bit and 64 bit Windows programs to run on alternative
architectures under Linux. But hey, who you call an alternative? As for Wednesday's release
of Hangover 0.65, it now supports starting QEMU automatically if needed amongst a variety
of other improvements.
Well, if those massively powerful arm or even IBM power workstations ever do develop, we'll
tell you about it and everything else that happens in the world of Linux. So just go
to LinuxActionNews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And LinuxActionNews.com slash contact for ways to keep in touch.
And a special heads up for you Coder Radio fans. Just for this week, the live time has
moved to Tuesday. Tuesday at 5pm Pacific, 8pm Eastern. It's a special live event. Come
for Linux Unplugged and stay for Coder. That's one huge Tuesday.
And we'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
Thanks for joining us and we will see you next week.