Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 131, recorded on November 10, 2019. I'm Joe.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes. Thank you very much for stepping in while the boss is away.
Thanks for having me.
Google have been up to quite a lot this week. So let's start with them giving quite a few
Chromebooks a fair bit of extra support.
It's definitely good news, but a bit of a mixed bag. Depending on what particular model
you happen to have, most models received another year of support, but others got only another
six months, and some lucky ones received two more years.
There were some models that had already been abandoned, which have been resurrected. Unfortunately,
not my C720, which remains abandoned, and so will live on with gallium OS.
Right, that kind of highlights why this matters, Joe. Chromebooks, unlike perhaps other devices
that you may be familiar with, have a strange fixed lifecycle, right? I mean, Google, after
they've certified a new platform for Chromebooks, they set an end date, and that's when your
security updates are no more.
Well, it's a little bit like smartphone style updates that you get that fixed window that
is generally much shorter than, say, a Windows or Mac device. And I think that's the crux
of this here. They're really looking to push further into the enterprise and education
markets, and those markets won't stomach these short support cycles.
Right, you've got to include whatever refresh rate they've got internally for the hardware,
otherwise they probably won't choose your platform.
And you would imagine that's the kind of feedback their sales reps would have been getting,
and so this is the result of that.
Probably matters, too, if you've bought one of the more high-end Chromebooks. I mean,
Chrome OS has gained a lot of features. It's now very usable as a sort of high-end workstation.
And while you might be okay with your budget model expiring after four years, I'd like
longer life and a significant investment.
Yeah, they have been adding a lot of features, and this week they announced a couple more.
The big one for me is virtual desktops that they're calling virtual desks, something we've
had for a long time in Linux, but something that Chrome OS has really lacked.
Yeah, Linux has had this feature for quite a long time, but we've seen most other major
operating systems playing catch-up, so it's nice to see Chrome OS join the club. All you
have to do is open the overview and tap New Desk in the top right-hand corner, so it's
a fairly accessible feature, and it works just as you might expect. I'm also very pleased
to see they've added some keyboard shortcuts if you're not a big fan of the mouse.
They've also added a bit of a convergence feature where you can now make phone calls
on your Android phone originating with phone numbers on the Chrome OS device.
Makes me think of some of the slick integrations on that other platform we won't name.
Yeah, they've also added some improvements to printing. Now, I've never tried to do that
on a Chromebook before, but I've heard that it wasn't the easiest.
As someone who tries to avoid printing whenever possible, anything that makes it easier is
very much welcome. They say that compatible printers will just automatically show up,
no setup needed, although I'm not quite sure where that list of compatible printers is.
Yeah, they call it print without hassle. That just doesn't exist in my mind.
No.
Yeah, I'll believe it when I see it. But on the mobile side of things, Google have seemingly
put their hands up to the fact that Android has a bit of a malware problem.
Yeah, this week they've announced a partnership with three antivirus firms, ESET, Lookout
and Zimperium, to create what they're calling the App Defense Alliance.
Now, they already have a thing called Play Protect, which is something of a black box
to me. I don't know exactly how it works. I don't think anyone does, really, apart from
Google.
You just got to wave your hands and say, machine learning.
Yeah, machine learning. But that is obviously not enough because I keep reading almost on
a weekly basis about an app that was downloaded 25,000 times, 100,000 times, that was some
sort of malware. And so these three companies all have competing products for Android security.
And all three of them have a different approach. And so it's kind of typical Google, isn't
it? Instead of just having one solution, let's have three competing solutions and somehow
that will work well.
That does sound like Google, although some diversity can go a long way. You're right,
all of these companies already do this sort of scanning. But before this agreement, they
were doing it after the fact, right? They were trying to identify malware out in the
wild. With this partnership, before apps actually get to the Play Store, they'll have to go
through all four different protection engines.
So in theory, this will stop the malware before even gets into the Play Store. But it's funny
that the VP of Android security and privacy, Dave Kleidermacher, said, when you're at the
massive scale we have in these platforms, when you can even get 1% incremental improvement,
it matters. So they're not necessarily looking to catch all the malware, but even a 1% improvement
would be massive for them.
With 2.5 billion Android devices out there, they do have a point.
Yeah, and Tony Anscombe from ESET said that they're likely to be scanning many thousands
of apps per day. So it really does go to show the scale of the whole Android ecosystem.
Yeah, there's a lot of investment here. And they started working on this two years ago.
We don't know anything about the finances of this. Presumably, the companies are making
a fair bit, but they're also getting access to a lot of data, which is always valuable.
Right, the more apps they scan, the better they can improve their own databases, which
makes their products better too. And hopefully, makes the Play Store a bit better at the same
time.
Hopefully, but realistically, this is an arms race. And okay, this is really stepping up
Google side of the arms race, but people will always find new ways to sneak crafty malware
into the Play Store.
Yeah, there's no getting around that. Even if it is a semi curated environment, think
twice before installing just any app.
Yeah, good advice. And think twice before getting into VR, I would say, as we had a
bit more evidence this week that VR is not really panning out to be the success a lot
of people hoped it would be.
Oh, Joe, you must be talking about the open sourcing of Google's cardboard VR headset,
which I'll note comes just a month after they dropped Daydream.
Yeah, Daydream was they're quite fancy VR headset, which is not supported by the new
Pixel 4 phones. And now they're open sourcing cardboard, the libraries and SDK for that.
And it feels to me that although they say they're going to continue to contribute to
it, or they may continue to contribute to it, realistically, this is one of those cases
where things are sort of put out to pasture by being open sourced. And realistically,
I can't see many people wanting to necessarily work on it, because it's almost an admission
that it's just a dead platform at this stage.
That's one way to look at it. Certainly. I am pleased that at least some remnants will
remain even if they never invest again, right? We've got the bones of the project here open
source, and perhaps some artists or enthusiasts, people just looking to play around can make
use of that. And I think having it open source is just better than having it die closed.
Oh, definitely. Yeah, I wish more people would do that.
You are right. It seems like maybe it was time for cardboard to die. You know, it was
launched five years ago. And while VR has certainly not taken off, as many may have
thought it might, cardboard was very early in this whole timeline and presented a device
that you could play around with, try to get an idea at the base stages of what might work
in the VR world. These days, the price has come down on much better VR tech. And I think
there's just less reason for cardboard to exist.
Yeah, but that said, we still don't have a truly wireless and truly portable VR solution.
Whereas we all have these phones in our pockets with relatively high resolution displays that
are totally wireless and can just slide into this cheap, like $20 or less cardboard headset.
And you can have very, very cheap VR, it might not be the best. But I've played with it and
it was pretty fun. It's a novelty. It's not something I'm going to do all the time. But
I think there is still a huge gap between cardboard and even the cheapest proper VR
solutions.
Yeah, you're right. It had a unique place in the market. And I played with it a bit
too. I've even got one of those plastic headset models you can find on eBay or Amazon. And
it's not amazing. But it was fun to play with. I hope we'll see more releases from Google.
They mentioned perhaps a Unity SDK package in the future. And really, the only thing
that will continue to make cardboard relevant is the community wanting to use it.
Yeah, well, we can hope and like you said, it's much better that they abandon it by open
sourcing it than not. And with the Apache 2 license that it's under, it could potentially
live on as some commercial products, although they are going to be quite restrictive about
the Google Cardboard trademark. You have to be a bit careful that you can use the term
Google Cardboard, but not implying that it's official. But I think that's fairly standard
for this sort of thing.
Well, something that hasn't been abandoned is Ubuntu 14.04. It ran out of support in
April, but thanks to Canonical's ESM program, which is extended security maintenance, you
can get support for it up to 2022. Up to now, you've had to pay for that. But this week,
Canonical announced that you can now get free access to that for up to three machines.
Or up to 50 machines if you're an official Ubuntu member. With that, you're going to
get fixes for high and critical severity CVEs for the most commonly used server packages.
And you'll have access to Canonical's live patch technology, which permits users to apply
critical kernel patches without rebooting.
And they've got a new client for this, which is just called UA for Ubuntu Advantage. And
so I tried this out, I installed 14.04.
Something tells me you already had an installation lying around, Joe.
I haven't actually, I recently updated one to 16.04. But I'm not telling you where that
is. But I installed a fresh 14.04.6 and fully updated it, rebooted, checked for updates
again, it said there weren't any, but if you're part of this Ubuntu Advantage, you can get
them. And so I signed up for that and put in my key, which was really easy. And then
suddenly I had a bunch more updates, and I was completely up to date.
It does seem like they put in a lot of work to make this fairly seamless.
Yeah, definitely. It was really, really easy to do it. The only thing is, I wasn't sure
how I could get rid of that machine, how I could kind of uncouple it from my account.
Because having kind of deleted that VM, does that mean that it's there forever, and I've
kind of wasted one of my lives, as it were? I don't know, the documentation wasn't that
clear on that.
Yeah, this is an area of Ubuntu I'm not too familiar with, because unless you need these
updates or already have a support relationship with Canonical, you just didn't have access
to it before.
Yeah, we generally talk about the kind of new and shiny stuff. But I think the reality
is that there is a lot of infrastructure out there that is running on old versions of Ubuntu
and old versions of various other distros as well. And it's this extra long term support
that makes you a proper enterprise company. And that's why Canonical started offering
the paid tiers for this, I think is part of their plan to IPO. And I think that what we've
got here is them giving people a free taste of it to kind of hook them in and realize,
actually, this is good that we can rely on Ubuntu being updated for a seriously long
time. It's not clear whether 16.04 and 18.04 are going to get this free ESM arrangement.
So we'll have to wait and see on that one.
Nevertheless, it does seem like a goodwill and good PR move. I imagine from the perspective
of a small business or perhaps a nonprofit who still got a 14.04 machine running somewhere,
depending on it, this makes you pretty happy.
Well, there have been some significant changes since 14.04 came out. That was still using
upstart, no system D back then.
It really is a new era. And even with this support, I think these organizations will
still have to confront an update sometime.
Well 2022. So you know, a couple of years to get yourself sorted and get on to 16.04
and then face the same problem in another couple of years.
Yeah, there's no escaping updates.
Well, from the old to the very new, something that created a lot of buzz this week, something
that's really cool, Splitter. This is from the French music streaming service Deezer.
And it takes a music track and separates it into its constituent parts, for the most part,
actually very well.
Yeah, sounds like we both had a chance to give it a shot. It's really easy to get running.
It's a Python application using TensorFlow. And then they have access to some private
data sets that they've used to train all these models. So the tool basically downloads the
model and runs it against whatever input file you've got, which could be a wave or a flack
or MP3.
Yeah, they've got access to tons of data for this because well, they're a music streaming
service. And that made me wonder, does this only work with commercial music that they
had trained the engine on? And the reality is no, I tried some of my own tracks and some
more obscure stuff. And it really does work. I mean, the asterisk here is it's not studio
quality drums, studio quality guitar, studio quality vocals. But I think it's good enough
to do a remix or something.
Right. It seemed particularly effective at pulling the drum lines out. And while the
vocals were at times a bit eerie, which makes sense considering how well optimized our own
brains are at detecting human vocals, as a tool to pull the vocals out of a file, some
things I tried worked surprisingly well.
Well, I'm not sure about it being really easy to get going. It took me probably about 10
or 15 minutes of messing around to get conda to work something that I'd not used before.
It's not just a case of calling the git repository and run a binary or anything.
I will note and maybe this would have helped you there are Docker images available both
for the CPU optimized version and the GPU optimized version, which is even faster.
Of course, that's the route you went down. You're all over Docker. So yeah, okay, that
makes sense. Yeah, that would be very easy. But I wanted to do it the other way. For some
reason. I'm just awkward. You mentioned the GPU there. With the right graphics card and
the right drivers, you can get it to go 100 times as fast as on the CPU. And the CPU was
for me on a fairly old laptop, about real time ish.
Yeah, and even on the CPU, it really wasn't that slow. I ended up spending a couple hours
and throwing 20 or so tracks at it. And I had a great time. So even if you're not going
to use it to remix or as a sample somewhere, it's just a neat application of technology.
And somewhat unique in this space. And being open source, there's a lot of commercial tools
that can do some of these same things, but you don't often get access to how it works.
Now I mostly tried it with the splitting into five different stems, but you can just separate
the backing track and the vocals. Or you can do a four stem version. But I would highly
recommend the five stem because that gives you a piano, which more often than not is
not a piano. It's just really cool, really eerie sounds that have come from all sorts
of sources within the track.
One angle on this tool I hadn't considered before is somewhat interesting just to try
to analyze how these pieces are put together and what the model thinks they should be.
Well, yeah, as someone who at least used to mix quite a lot of music tracks, this could
be really handy to assess your mix and see how you've done it. It's not necessarily going
to dictate the decisions that you make, but it is a good extra data point with regards
how you've separated the various frequencies within your mix.
Now while most of us don't have access to the private data sets, Deezer does. They include
all the technology in the open source release to go train this model on your own data. And
I wonder if we'll see any interesting results there too.
Yeah, I suspect that this is only going to get better as more people train it and contribute
to the open source project. And it is great to see that we do have an open source implementation
of this rather than it all being locked away. So yeah, I think this is definitely one to
watch. Much like our last story is definitely one to watch. And that is that Microsoft's
Edge browser is going to be released for Linux. It's official. I know I'm looking forward
to it, Wes, are you?
Well, I'm looking forward to giving it a try. Anyway, I don't think it's going to replace
my main browser. But it seems like Microsoft is genuinely interested in making this a good
experience for all platforms.
Yeah, and this was announced in your neck of the woods, wasn't it at their Ignite conference
in Seattle?
Yeah, although unfortunately, I wasn't there to catch it in person. There is a video available
if you're curious. It's also not as surprising as it may seem because the new Microsoft Edge
is powered by chromium under the hood.
Yeah, it's using the blink engine. So it's not a huge stretch to get it onto Linux you
wouldn't have thought. But in that video, they announced it and kind of were expecting
a reaction that they didn't quite get, which is quite funny. But, you know, I could see
this being relatively successful. And a lot of people would scoff at that. And just the
idea of edge coming to Linux seems to be funny to most people. But when you really think
about it, yes, we've got Firefox and Chromium. But sometimes you need to use Chrome for things.
Source Connect, which we sometimes use, for example. Now, if that worked in edge, it would
make me stop and think, whose proprietary browser would I prefer to use? Evil Company
A, Google, or Evil Company B, Microsoft? Honestly, I don't know. There's not much in it really.
Yeah, you know, at that level, it's probably worth just giving it a shot. I was able to
test it out under wine, which worked surprisingly well. And I mean, it was a it was a fine browsing
experience. In particular, I noticed they had really easy access to get a voice narration
of the page. And it was surprisingly decent.
All right, that's a nice accessibility feature. How did it compare to Chrome then?
It felt like a slightly lighter, more optimized version of Chrome with a little bit of the
Microsoft Windows aesthetic put on top.
Now I am curious. I will have to try this once it comes out. We don't really have any
further details on when that's going to be. But yeah, I'll give it a go. It'd be interesting
if you could try Source Connect in there and some other web apps that seemingly require
Chrome and see if Microsoft have managed to crack that aspect of it.
Now you're thinking it's also already available to try on Mac or Windows or iOS or Android
basically everywhere but Linux.
But realistically, I'm staring at these show notes in Firefox and I think I will be for
quite some time to come.
Same here.
Well, we'll follow the progress of Edge on Linux along with all the other stories in
the open source world. So go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe so you don't miss any future
episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I'm at Westpane.
And I'm at Jyresington. Thanks for joining us and we'll see you next week.