Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 183, recorded on April 4th, 2021. I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes. Did you dodge all the pranks and fake releases for April Fools?
Well, I think we'll see today the proof is in the podcast pudding.
Alright, let's do the news.
And we start with something that's definitely not a prank, although it was announced around
April Fools, right on schedule, Alma Linux's initial release is here.
This first version is based on Red Hat Enterprise Linux 8.3 sources.
And as you probably remember, Alma Linux launched with the codename Project Linux when Red Hat
announced CentOS was shifting focus from CentOS Linux to CentOS Stream, which tracks just
ahead of the current RHEL release.
Now under a new name, Alma Linux OS is here with its very first release.
Yeah, congratulations to them and hitting it right on time to that's impressive to see
that makes them first to market with this.
Cloud Linux is the company behind Alma Linux, and they started in 2009 to provide a customized
version of RHEL, their own version of RHEL that was purpose built for their customers,
multi tenancy web and server hosting companies.
So they were essentially selling the shovels to the hosting companies that were doing the
mining.
And when the Red Hat news about the change in CentOS status came out, they were just
perfectly positioned to spring into action because their work pipeline was building this
already.
That's what they had been doing.
So they were first to market with this stable traditional CentOS clone because it was so
in line with their existing business practice.
As exciting as all that is, though, Chris, there's another piece of this announcement
that might be just as important.
You might be right, Wes, long term.
So what it is, is the company announced the formation of a nonprofit organization that
will go around the distribution, and it's aptly named the Alma Linux Open Source Foundation.
And it's this group that's going to take over managing the Alma Linux project going forward,
although Cloud Linux will still be involved and has even committed a one million dollar
annual endowment to support the project.
They've recently hired a former Red Hat employee and Fedora engineer to run the community.
And this governing board they're putting together, I'm mixed on it, Wes.
Yeah, it sounds like it'll be mostly made up of Cloud Linux staff, but there are going
to be two additional members that will be selected by the Alma Linux community itself.
Yeah, a couple of members just from outside of Alma Linux that are part of the nonprofit,
a couple of members of the staff from Cloud Linux, and then I guess down the road, these
other community members will join.
But to me, Wes, it seems like a clear attempt to appeal to the people that are still kind
of in shock by all of the CentOS changes and perhaps skeptical of a corporate entity running
this type of distribution now, and maybe are a little more inclined to go with something
backed by a community.
It feels like they're trying to say, well, we will now be all of those things.
We will have the one million dollar resources of Cloud Linux and some of the staff, and
we have a community governance board which will guide the distribution.
Yeah, or at least I think there's the sense that they want to do this the right way, that
they appreciate the open source model and the open source community, and they acknowledge
like, okay, well, we should probably have a foundation.
We should have a board.
We should have folks involved with the community.
It's definitely a positive thing, I think, to see that.
Yeah, I mean, the intention seems good here.
It does to me still feel there's been a lot of benefit from the corporate resources to
get this bootstrapped, and it's all happened very quickly, again, to their credit.
But I just, I think it takes time to build legitimate community and that interaction
and to see, you know, over a couple of releases maybe, or at least a few more months, is there
back and forth?
How does the development work?
What's the nature of this new community?
Right.
This is truly chapter one.
Everything that's been before this was just like the epilogue.
This is now what is living this distribution like going forward.
And it's ironic because the benchmark might actually be the least you can tell, like the
less and less you can tell you're on a different distribution, the better a job they're doing.
And they're trying to make it appealing to people to convert from RHEL or CentOS to them
and make scripts available.
But you got to think it's a job well done when you can't tell you've switched, which
is kind of funny.
You look at it, that's kind of funny.
But I think they recognize what this is.
This is a once in a lifetime opportunity.
This is like parallel universe kind of opportunity, like when and how else who could have seen
this giant opening coming in the super established enterprise grade Linux server distro market.
It was locked down tight.
And now all of a sudden this company we've never heard of until about a year ago, well,
a little bit not even that long ago, comes along and they have the first crack at what
could be one of the major Linux server distros.
When else do you see an opportunity like this open up?
And the fact that they executed in four months, it puts them I think at the front of the list
right now.
Yeah, I think it does.
And clearly they sense that this was an opportunity.
I mean, you weren't just going to go unseat the classic version of CentOS by yourself,
right?
No.
It took Red Hat deciding they wanted to change the focus for this to exist.
They should probably feel good about how quickly they've dived in here.
And how good they are positioned, because it was already kind of in line with their
existing business model.
So this was a process that they've already built and established.
And so just expanding on that wasn't a matter of spinning up everything from scratch like
it is for Rocky Linux.
It was just simply investing in what they've already done.
Right.
Build it out a little better in the public view, transition things out into the open
and make it a little more generic.
And they have the benefit of having the organizational aspects of a company to help just staff the
things that need done to get something like this going.
I mean, even getting a governance board established takes many, many hours of work behind the
scenes.
And they have people who get paid to do that work.
And so they're kind of giving you the promise or the kind of the guarantee you get by having
a company with a revenue model behind it and the advantage of having community governance.
But it's really going to be one of these things where we're going to have to be a year or
two down the road to see how all of these different CentOS clones are contending.
And if any of them have deviated much, if they try to add their own value or whatever
it might be that makes them different, because their core value is going to be as close to
RHEL as possible, which means there's not a lot of area in there for them to offer differentiated
value.
And of course, there's still also, you know, CentOS is around, Stream exists.
And how do you feel about this, you know, this new brand new community and foundation
versus something more established like Red Hat itself?
That's still up in the air.
Along with that is not just CentOS as a project, but also is this Stream model perhaps a better
model for servers today, especially servers where a lot of the workload is either virtualized
or containerized.
Maybe it makes a little more sense to go the core OS route and have a little bit more frequently
updated base OS.
And CentOS will provide just that, but still be a very enterprise focused distribution.
So it could actually end up being perfectly usable for most people.
And none of these CentOS clones ever ended up picking up that many users in mass because
of that.
Just wait and see.
Like a bad movie remake, this week, IBM and Red Hat were sued for copyright and antitrust
violations from a SCO group successor, Zinus.
They formed around the SCO group's zombie corpse about a decade ago.
And this week they thought, hey, let's reignite a decades old fight.
So they sued IBM and Red Hat for alleged copyright antitrust violations, claiming that, quote,
first, IBM stole Zinus's intellectual property and used that stolen property to build and
sell a product to compete with Zinus itself.
And second, stolen property in IBM's hand, IBM and Red Hat illegally agreed to divide
the relevant market and use their growing market powers to victimize consumers, innovative
competitors and innovation itself.
My goodness.
The complaint from the Virgin Islands based company further contends that after the two
companies conspired in their evil boardrooms to divide the market up, IBM then did their
master move and acquired Red Hat to really solidify its evil genius position.
Now, of course, the SCO group way back in 2003 made a similar intellectual property
claim at the time, arguing that the SCO group owned the rights to AT&T's Unix and Unixware
operating system source code, and that Linux versions 2.4 and 2.5 at the time were just
unauthorized derivatives of Unix.
And that IBM violated its contractual obligations by distributing Linux.
I can't help but just have a toot about this one, because I remember this from the days
gone by where this originally went down.
You know, back in 2001, SCO, which was this plucky little Unix company, joined forces
with a plucky little Linux company called Caldera to form what they thought was going
to be like this major, serious Unix approach to Linux that would compete with Red Hat.
Instead, it took them about two years or so to drive the thing into the ground.
And then SCO sued IBM in an all-out legal attack to essentially try to derive some
value from the IP they held.
And as I recall, and probably many of you do as well, that drug on for years.
And it got to a point where it got ridiculous.
I had clients who started to doubt the use of Linux because SCO actually made claims
that they would sue individual Linux users for infringement.
Despite those claims, things did not exactly go well.
SCO lost battle after battle, and was eventually forced to file for bankruptcy in 2007.
But what is notable is that while some of the claims have been dismissed, its case against
IBM remains essentially unresolved.
I always wondered if this would come back to bite us.
So let's fast forward to 2011.
They went bankrupt in 2007, we fast forward to 2011, and really the only thing left of
value in SCO is its Unix operating system, which they sold to Unixis, or Unisys?
The original name of Xenius.
Right.
That acquisition, which at the time seemed a little strange, kind of makes sense when
you figure that SCO's Unix products, like Open Server and Unixware, still had a small
but real market share.
But the ironic thing is, is at the time, the Xenius people said, we have no interest in
SCO's quote, worthless lawsuits, and in 2016, the CEO Sean Snyder said, we are not SCO.
We are investors who bought the products.
We did not buy the ability to pursue litigation against IBM, and we have absolutely no interest
in that.
Now, what changed?
You know, because that's a pretty bold statement.
Well, kind of like the old SCO Caldera situation fell apart.
They also have fallen upon hard times and now have officially released a statement that
says, well, this case is about Xenius and the theft of our intellectual property.
It is also about market manipulation that has harmed consumers, competitors, the open
source community, and innovation itself.
These copyright claims go back almost two decades now, and seem like they've lost time
after time.
But digging into this again, I was looking at it, it seems like the litigation is based
off of specific Unixware and open server operating systems and code that came into existence
after September 19th, 1995.
So not the earlier Unix code, but after that point.
So when an IBM spokesperson was reached for comment, Doug Shelton responded with the following.
Xenius's copyright allegations merely rehash the stale claims of its predecessor, whose
copyright Xenius purchased out of bankruptcy and have no merit.
Xenius's antitrust allegations brought against IBM and Red Hat, the world's largest open
source company, similarly defy logic.
IBM and Red Hat will aggressively defend the integrity of the open source development process
in the inherent choice and thus competition that open source fosters.
Not only does it defy logic, as IBM puts it, but Xenius provides really zero proof of this
claim that IBM and Red Hat conspired to divide up the Unix and Linux market between them
and then the grand finale was IBM's ninja move to buy Red Hat to consolidate its market
share.
No, it seems more like IBM's purchase of Red Hat was a desperate move to stay relevant.
And of course, Xenius's version of reality doesn't explain the rise of Debian, Ubuntu,
or all the other server distros.
Linode makes cloud computing simple, affordable, and accessible.
I realized the other day Linode is really part of our team.
They make what we do behind the scenes possible, and if it weren't really for these spots,
you'd never know that we use Linode because, like all great infrastructure, the users never
really notice it.
It's just fast, reliable, and it makes your experience great, and that's one of the many
reasons Linode is our favorite hosting provider.
Linode is also the largest independent cloud computing provider.
They've been in this since 2003, and they've got it right.
They make it easy for you to give your creations their own personal space on the internet.
No matter what skill level you're at or what technology stack you use, Linode can help
your ideas come to life on the web, and if you run into any trouble, they have the best
support.
Linode comes with whatever level account you have, one server, or a whole bunch of servers.
You get 24-7 customer support by phone, ticket, chat, along with hundreds of super high-quality
tutorials to help you get started, and Linode is easy to use while also having a powerful
cloud dashboard.
One of the features I love is their S3-compatible object storage.
It's great for all kinds of applications, so that's why you gotta go and check it out
for yourself and get that $100 credit and support the show.
Sign up today at linode.com slash LAN.
Get that $100 60-day credit towards your new account and support the show, of course.
That's linode.com slash LAN.
Canonical has released a community preview of Ubuntu on Windows as a sandbox for experimenting
with new features and functionality on Windows Subsystem for Linux 2, aka the Weasel.
Now, if you're not familiar, Ubuntu on Windows is normally installed via the Microsoft Store,
and only LTS releases are available.
Yeah, now this new preview that Canonical is cooking up is only available by a special
sneaky link, which of course we have in the show notes, and it's a frequently updated
build of Ubuntu that is based on 21.04, which is expected to release on April 22nd.
This setup is specifically more user-friendly for the WSL environment, and it uses a utility
called Ubuntu Weasel with many features that are experimental, and this allows Windows
users to tinker with settings such as how Windows drives are mounted and other kind
of text-based options to make life in Weasel more satisfying.
Now, Canonical said that the preview is important to match the speed of innovation in open source
and test new features with the community at a faster pace.
That's another way of saying we feel like this platform has a community that is large
enough that wants to build applications on Ubuntu, but they want the latest Ubuntu so
they can supposedly, in theory, I guess hypothetically, develop future Ubuntu applications from the
Windows desktop, because that's why they would need access to the development versions of
Ubuntu is if they're writing applications, but they're using it via Weasel on Windows,
so they're writing Linux applications on Windows for a version of Linux that hasn't been released
yet.
Now, maybe you're writing a server-side app that you're just trying to, you know, plan
ahead a little bit.
Hmm.
Okay.
Yeah, okay.
That does make more sense for the server side, although how many servers are going to be
based off of 2104?
But they'll be based on future LTSs, and maybe you want to make sure you're catching up with
libraries to get ahead of changes.
Right, you get the kinks worked out on this system before it's close to the LTS time,
and then by the time it's LTS time, you have this system kind of worked out and people
know how to use it, and you know, maybe these scripts to make it better under Weasel are
even more fleshed out.
Though to your point, one feature that is eagerly awaited right now is official support
for a GUI on Weasel 2.
Now, last year at Build 2020 in May, a Microsoft program manager did say that adding Linux
GUI app support is on the roadmap, and that their goal is for a user to be able to run
Linux GUI apps on the desktop seamlessly alongside Windows apps.
We've heard little sense, perhaps there will be more at this upcoming build, but what we
do know is Microsoft's implementation is going to communicate with an RDP client on the Windows
host.
Sadly, no sign of this yet in the new Windows community preview, but there is an intriguing
option to include legacy GUI integration, though we should note that requires a third
party X server.
Well, just in time, because it might be just one giant leap away from finally getting rid
of our X servers, Wes, because this week, NVIDIA proposed Mesa patches to support alternative
generic buffer manager backends, which I read as Wayland support is nigh.
Boy, oh boy, yeah, it looks like NVIDIA is finally taking the GBM route for supporting
Wayland compositors with their proprietary driver.
For years, NVIDIA was resisting using GBM, and instead proposed using an alternative
called EGL streams.
Now, some compositor, like Gnome's Mudder, did implement EGL streams, but it's been kind
of only a mild success, really hit and miss, and a lot of Wayland compositors were not
exactly keen to implement an NVIDIA specific solution.
Yeah, it was like this package deal that people didn't like because they were pushing this
new Unix device memory allocator interface to try to address some shortcomings of GBM
and they thought, well, maybe we could learn a few things from what we liked about EGL
and bring it forward.
But there really hasn't been much to report on that front, doesn't seem like they got
much traction and without much changing now, NVIDIA with the version 470 of their driver
series has Wayland improvements that are expected and will introduce DMA buffer passing support,
which is the clearest sign yet that they are actually going the GBM route, which is exciting
because that's where most of the community momentum is for this solution.
We got an update when NVIDIA's James Jones, longtime contributor to Linux drivers and
Wayland related efforts on their side, sent out a work in progress merge request that
would allow Mesa to discover and load alternative GBM back ends.
And it seems like the only reason NVIDIA would be working on this GBM back end discovery
and loading code was if they were planning to, perhaps already done internally, implement
GBM support for their proprietary Linux driver.
Yeah, this doesn't take away the need for the proprietary driver.
So it's still not as simple a solution as an Intel Linux box or an AMD Radeon style
system where you just boot up the system and it just works out of the box.
You still have to load the NVIDIA proprietary driver here.
But NVIDIA being willing to make this compromise actually, truly for realsies opens the door
to use Wayland on the proprietary NVIDIA driver, which means by summer, end of summer ish,
the classic age old problem that prevented Wayland adoption amongst a ginormous swath
of the Linux population could be resolved.
And it could be a problem of the past that just is no longer a problem.
With this contribution and that recent GPU pass-through contribution, does this mean
we have to hate NVIDIA less?
Linux.ting.com.
New year, new plans, same incredible service.
And you know, a good family plan is hard to find, but not at Ting.
Ting's newest flex plan addresses this particular pain point in a very customer friendly kind
of way.
Add as many lines on your account as you need, it's just $10 per line.
Every line has unlimited texting calls.
Every line shares the same pool of LTE or 5G, and you just pay $5 per gigabyte as you
need.
But if you need two gigs or 20 gigs, there's a perfect Ting plan for you.
And every plan gets access to Ting's award-winning customer service with nationwide LTE and 5G
coverage.
Plus, the thing I love the most, the freedom of no contracts ever.
And now Ting has three great networks to choose from.
It's simple to switch to Ting.
I've been on the Verizon network and it was easy to go to linux.ting.com, check my current
phone, I created an account, got the plan dialed in, and then Ting sent me a SIM card
that I just popped into my phone and it was active in minutes.
You can do it all through their beautiful website, but if you ever need support, they're
right there to help you.
Cutting your phone bill in half has never been easier with Ting's mobile plans.
Check out the Flex plan and much more.
It's the next generation of Ting mobile.
It's here.
So go see how much you could save and get $25 off at linux.ting.com.
Thanks to Ting for supporting Linux Action News and thanks to everyone who supports this
show by going to linux.ting.com.
Good news in GTK Town.
There's a new library in the works that should be a boon to anyone looking to create a modern
GNOME application.
But to understand why, we need a little bit of context.
For the past 20 years, GNOME has had Human Interface Guidelines, or HIG for short, but
implementing them has been a lot of manual work for application developers.
And it's tricky because developers have been told, yeah, just go create a GTK application.
How do you create a, quote unquote, GNOME looking GTK application?
Elementary OS has Granite.
And there are some things out there that GTK developers can use like Lib Handy and a few
others that have cropped up over the years like Lib Dazzle.
But it's not really a clear signal on this is how you go create a GNOME looking and GNOME
design following application.
It just really hasn't existed.
Developers have clearly needed some kind of blessed library that implements the HIG and
what a standard GNOME application should look like.
This new LibAdoita library intends to be that missing code.
It's going to be implemented as a direct GTK for continuation and replacement of Lib Handy.
And it's going to be developed by those same current developers.
Replacement of Lib Handy is a big deal.
And I don't think when Lib Handy first came along, they thought it would be this way to
create standard looking applications.
But it clearly has been something that the GTK ecosystem developers have needed.
Now the library not quite ready to be used yet.
There's still some fixes and remaining issues that have to be worked out.
They're going to write up a migration guide and then they'll start releasing an alpha
that people can target.
But what's key here is that this LibAdoita library is going to follow revisions of the
GNOME Shell Human Interface Guideline.
And it will have a release schedule that tracks with GNOME's release schedule.
And each version of the library will target a specific version of GNOME and the first
stable version being released alongside GNOME 41.
Dang it, Chris.
Just when you started learning Flutter.
Somehow I'm going to make due, Wes, because a well-known GNOME developer has been chipping
away at making OBS Studio work completely under Wayland that includes things like capturing
monitor and windows, even on the Wayland composite desktop.
It's here.
It's awesome.
It's a release candidate.
It's a major milestone for the Linux Wayland desktop.
Yeah, I think this is one of those checkboxes.
There's just a number of Linux users out there and they need to have before they're actually
ready for Wayland.
And it's nice to see all the hard work that's had to go in both to the OBS project itself,
but also all the plumbing underneath things like pipe wire and portals that are required
to make this not only work, but eventually be better and more secure than it could have
ever been on X11.
Well, they weren't April fooling around.
Arch actually has an installer now.
And you know us, we had to give it a go.
Yeah, you know we did.
We had to try it.
You download the standard Arch ISO image and then just run Arch install and get kind of
like a guided basic installation.
It's not going to do much fancy for you.
No, it's a Python application.
You can also install it with PIP or all the other ways to get Python apps if you like.
But I like they've included it by default, huh?
And no, there's not a lot of extensibility right now, at least not in the built in.
But because it's Python, they've got some documentation for scripting it yourself.
If you want to totally customize it, that has some interesting potential.
Yeah, because when you're kind of done answering all of its questions, it essentially just
generates a big JSON output of what's going to happen to your machine.
So I would think you could take that and pipe that back to the Arch installer on another
machine and just kind of replicate your setup.
Yeah, and you can use it as a library directly if you want to go fully custom, say, for your
fleet of Arch servers you're building.
Of course, obviously, who wouldn't be?
And I'll say this, it's not like going to blow you away.
But by the time you're done, you'll have a fully booting graphical Arch Linux desktop.
Pretty minimal, but there and it takes about 15 minutes.
There is one gotcha we ran into, though.
We were testing things out in a virtual machine, I'll admit.
Haven't tried it on bare metal yet.
It only seems to support EFI.
So watch out you BIOS booters out there.
It's legacy.
But of course, that's what we got by default in the virtual machine tells you things are
done and ready to reboot.
Oh, no, my friend, you don't come back from that.
Who would have thought it?
Arch with its own official installer and it's really, you know what, it's not bad.
We'll have a link to the project repository too.
There's always a lot going on those to go to LinuxActionNews.com slash subscribe for
all the ways to get new episodes and LinuxActionNews.com slash contact for ways to keep in touch.
Now don't miss Linux Unplugged 400 this week.
Wes and I have been brewing up something special.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
Thanks for joining us and we will see you next week.