Hello and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open source world.
This is episode 10 recorded on the 16th of July 2017.
I'm Joe.
And I'm Ryan.
And Chris isn't here, he's on holiday.
So we've asked Ryan to step in and thank you very much for doing that, Ryan.
No problem.
I'm housed here at the System76 headquarters.
And I've got everything set up my whole command center, three monitors, a mic, you know, it's
just I'm ready to go.
I'm ready and I'm willing.
Nice.
I was going to mention System76, but you just literally couldn't wait, could you?
No, no, of course.
Okay, well, let's start with Fedora 26, which has been released.
And there's kind of a few not that exciting things like GCC 7, Golang 1.8, Python 3.6,
and loads of under the hood stuff.
But there's also a new GUI for partition editing in the installer called Blivit GUI, which
isn't that new.
It's been in the repo since Fedora 21.
But now it's kind of in the default live image.
So have you given Fedora 26 a go?
I haven't given Fedora 26.
I was using Fedora 25 for a while, just playing around seeing what was available there.
But I have not yet tried this out, although I probably will.
We played with it here a few times, especially since kind of, this will be later, but since
we started working on Popover at System76, we've been looking across the entire Linux
distribution landscape to see where people are doing things well and trying to emulate
that.
I'm really curious to see the partition manager.
I can't find any pictures of that.
And I tried looking earlier, too.
I'm not sure if I'm just missing the link in this release or what, but have you played
with it yet?
Yeah, well, I always would do the advanced partitioning because it's usually on a test
machine that's got several partitions.
And it looks pretty good.
But in terms of functionality, it was a bit lacking because I've got a logical partition
and it wouldn't, well, at least I couldn't see a way to enlarge that to add another partition
for Fedora.
So I had to put in one more primary and then that was the maximum number of partitions
for the disk.
So that means I'll have to delete Fedora if I want to install anything else.
So that wasn't great, but it looks good at least, but I'm used to using GParted basically.
It's that I would always do that, or even the partition editing in Ubiquity as well.
Yeah.
I was kind of just looking through the release notes here.
I think I remember last week, was it, Matt was talking on Linux Unplugged?
Yeah, he spoke quite a lot about it.
And to me, there's nothing hugely exciting about it, but in a way that's good to me.
I don't think huge changes are good, really.
I think that it sounds like steady improvements and just progression with new packages, new
kernel, that kind of thing, and a few features here and there, but nothing massively exciting.
Right.
The thing I'd be most interested in seeing is if there are any changes to Wayland and
how it interacts with applications.
I know that I've talked to Alberto Ruiz and some of the guys over at Red Hat about the
work that they've been putting into that effort, and I don't know if any of that was scheduled
to be in this release, but I just know that they've been putting a lot of time and effort
into Wayland and how that interacts with applications.
Right now you can't really do screen sharing in a Wayland session, and other things like
that, just little things that I'm wondering what the progress of that on.
I bet Fedora is a great way to keep up with that Wayland development and see what the
new and shiny is.
I definitely will have to pull it down and at least play around with the Wayland session
and see if anything has changed, because right now I use Wayland every day on my POP system
and for the most part it's pretty stable and it's a good experience, but there are little
tiny things that I'm hoping that are getting addressed and I want to see how they're implementing
it in Fedora and if that's any different.
Yeah, well Fedora really blazed the trail when it comes to Wayland, so I think you should
definitely check it out.
But another story that developed shortly after this was that there is a proposal by Justin
Forbes who's one of the Fedora kernel maintainers to drop the 32-bit kernel because essentially
hardly anyone is using it, hardly anyone is testing it, and it's just time for it to go
basically.
I have been skeptical, shall we say, about dropping 32-bit support in Linux, but I think
the time is coming and we've seen it with Arch, we've seen it with Tails, we've seen
it with various other distros.
Do we really need 32-bit support anymore?
Frankly, I have not used a 32-bit system for probably a couple years now, maybe longer.
Even in systems that are rocking 30 gigs of RAM, which I know isn't the only difference,
but I still have been throwing 64-bit on them.
So I don't know between myself and my family and my friends of anybody who's using a 32-bit
system, although now that I said that, probably my friends who are listening to this will
probably ping me and let me know that they are.
But if it's just a lot of extra work for them and they don't have people who are doing this
regularly enough people who can test out and make sure everything's working properly, then
it's better to drop it than to offer something that hasn't been thoroughly tested.
And maybe that's not the case, but based on kind of what's in this article, it seems like
there might be some problems with QA and maybe not enough of that happening.
And so I think that it might just be time.
And if somebody is really, really passionate about it, maybe they can pick that up and
take on that project.
Yeah.
I mean, the thing is on the desktop, it doesn't really make any sense anymore.
The only thing I would say is the 32-bit Atom machines, but even they're pretty long in
the tooth at this point, but I would say that with Atomic, Fedora Atomic, that might possibly
make sense to have a 32-bit version because if you've got a lot of VMs running and you
want them to be as small and lean as possible, then it might, there are some circumstances
where it would make sense to be 32-bit, but yeah, I think really that that's a pretty
edge case.
So yeah, I think it is time to move on from 32-bit now.
But let's move on and talk about Unity, or is it Unit, Y-U-N-I-T.
It's the worst name I've heard since pop underscore OS.
And so that is the fork or the continuation, I suppose you'd say, of Unity 8, which Canonical
famously dropped earlier this year.
And it is now available as an overlay repository for Ubuntu 16.04 LTS, which I think is good
news for them because you need to start somewhere and the LTS seems like a very logical place
to start for me.
And I've tested it out and it didn't work very well at all, but you, as I say, you have
to start somewhere.
I don't have a great deal of faith in Unit or Unity as, well, as having a future put
it that way because without the great resources that Shotoworth brought to Canonical as a
community project, I just have to wonder who is really interested in Unity 8.
Yeah, I am patiently watching.
I'm in the Telegram channel as well.
I don't really have any feelings on it only because right now I'm not sure where this
project will end up.
Like when I think about people deciding on a distribution and on a desktop environment,
I don't know anyone beyond the people who are in that channel, you know, who are actively
contributing to it, who have told me just in, you know, little Linux user groups around
and some of my friends who I talked to online, none of them have said, yeah, I really want
to give Unit a try.
Maybe that'll change now that these packages are available for the LTS, maybe, you know,
someone who's running that will pull it down and I might throw it on one of the test machines
here at the office just to look at it, but I'm just going to reserve judgment until I
see where the project goes and what their big overarching goals are.
The main thing is the applications that are built for Unity 8, I'll call it Unity 8 because
Unit is weird to me.
I'm worried that there won't be that many native applications beyond the core ones that
already exist and maybe I'm wrong, I could probably spend some time like looking through
their documentation and see if anybody's creating new applications for it, but I think as far
as interest goes, I think maybe at least among the developers I know who are developing applications
for it, a lot of their interest for developing native applications died along with Canonical's
backing of the project, but you know, they seem to be chugging along so I could prove
wrong in this and in a few months we might be talking more and more about the project,
but I think my honest opinion is I think we're looking at a known world for the foreseeable
future.
You would, wouldn't you, but yeah, I think that this and UbiPorts, now their community
efforts, I really want them to succeed, I want convergence to happen, I always wanted
it to happen when Canonical were paying to develop it, now it's out in the community,
I think it's probably going to take a lot longer, but it would be great to have a phone
that is a serious competitor to Android and have convergence working and have one device
that can have all my Linux desktop and phone needs taken care of, but yeah, I think we'll
be waiting a while for that, so here's hoping.
Yeah, if I was going to bet the farm on an alternative to Android, I'd be much, right
now at this very moment, I'd be much more comfortable saying that Sailfish would be
that before I would say Unit, but I know some of the guys working on it and they are driven
and, you know, they have a lot of passion for the project, so that's why I have to reserve
judgment because they could prove me wrong.
Yeah, here's hoping.
Well let's move on and talk about Ubuntu being in the Windows Store.
We've been talking on various Linux shows about the Windows subsystem for Linux for
a while now, and now Ubuntu is a Windows app, what kind of topsy-turvy bizarro world are
we living in when I can say that, that, you know, okay, you have to be enrolled in the
Windows Insiders program and you have to be on the latest build of Windows, but Ubuntu
is in the Windows App Store.
What is going on?
Honestly, I've been thinking about how I feel about this for ever since it was released
and I still don't know how I feel about it.
I can't determine whether this is a good thing or a bad thing or it doesn't matter.
I'm really curious to hear your thoughts because, I mean, I know this story is specific to it
being in the App Store, which is interesting in and of itself, but I had a very hard time
formulating an opinion on this specific feature in Windows.
Well I feel ambivalent, I think, I think most of us do because on the one hand there's a
chance that it's going to expose Windows users to Ubuntu and therefore Linux and therefore
free software and open source and all the rest of that and they might be using this
instead of Cygwin and therefore they might realize, hey, this Ubuntu thing is actually
pretty good, but it's not desktop.
They've never said it was going to be desktop.
I saw some people complaining in the reviews that X11 doesn't work.
Well it was never supposed to work.
You can hack it and make it work just about, so I read, but yeah, I kind of feel ambivalent
because I'd like that to be true, but I think the reality is it's more a case of people
who are dual booting because they have their games or some other stuff they need and they
don't really use the Ubuntu partition that often now basically don't have any need to
use the Ubuntu partition and so they can just go Windows full time and I think that's what
Microsoft's game is here.
I think you're right.
I think that, well, I remember talking to one of the guys on this project at OSCON I
think last year and I remember he was an Ubuntu user.
I found that pretty interesting.
He was working inside Microsoft, but he was using Ubuntu full time and this is obviously
just an anecdotal story of me talking to a guy, but he just found it really interesting
work and thought it was good all around for Linux because it exposes more people to Linux,
but listening to you raise the point that, yeah, there are going to be people who use
Linux and they feel like they need to be able to use that bash environment on Windows that
are going to simply stop dual booting because, you know, or although in those cases they
might have a virtual machine, but the point is that there's a chance that they might stop
dual booting because, hey, I've got it right here.
I've got everything I need.
I've got apt, I've got git, I've got SSH, it's all right here and that's all I needed.
The other side of it that's exciting though is that Linux is popular enough among developers
that this is something that Windows and Microsoft felt like they needed.
I don't know how exactly that worked.
I think there was a blog post on it though from Justin Kirkland where it talked about
how they started talking about this, them being Microsoft and Canonical and ultimately
worked together on this.
If that came from Microsoft, that's really interesting.
That shows that they felt a distinct need to have a Linux user space in Windows for
certain types of customers and I think that would speak to what thinking is like inside
of Microsoft as far as courting those developer customers.
And so that is the more interesting side of the story I think, but I'm curious to see
if we have any people telling stories on their blog about using Ubuntu from the Windows store
and then becoming a full-time Ubuntu user, or if we see anything that's the opposite
of that.
I'm just really interested in seeing how this plays out.
DigitalOcean.com.
Sign up with the promo code, here's the thing, to get $10 credit.
DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and
easy way to spin up a cloud server and you can do so in 55 seconds and with prices starting
at only $5 per month, that means you can get two months free if you use the promo code,
here's the thing.
They've got data centers all over the world and they've got a great simple interface for
dealing with your droplets as they call them and they've got a great API as well if you
want to script it.
Loads of the JB infrastructure runs on DigitalOcean and I've been using it for years personally
and recently they've introduced high CPU droplets.
The thing is their standard CPUs are pretty powerful but now if you need that extra bit
of performance for your application then they've got Skylake and Broadwell Xeons for the absolute
maximum performance.
So whether you want just a small next cloud server or a hugely powerful Linux rig out
in the cloud, go to DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code, here's the thing, and get
$10 in credit to get you started.
As of July 13th, Aiki is working full time on Solus and that was his first day and he
posted to his Patreons thanking them for their support and frankly this is awesome.
Another person working on Linux full time is great and Aiki is such a smart dude that
I've been watching his stuff as well trying to see what's coming out of it that frankly
System76 can use and so I'm very proud that the community was able to come together and
do this for him.
Yeah we did talk about this I think four episodes ago on Linux Action News but Aiki's my friend
so I thought well Chris is the way I'll slip this one in again and as you say this is just
great news, he'd been pretty happy at Intel, well very happy actually and he'd learned
a lot but the time had come and now he's full time with it and Solus is a great distro and
the development has already just massively accelerated and so I think that this, he was
doing this as a part time job and now it's his full time job, it's going to mean great
things for Solus and as you say probably for the rest of the Linux community as well because
you've got Budgie and also there's a lot of the technicalities of the under the hood stuff
with Solus which I think a lot of the other distros could benefit from if they integrated
that stuff like the bulletproof boot and stuff like that.
So if you do want to help him out check out patreon.com slash solus and throw him a few
bucks a month.
Yeah and I wanted to add to that, I've heard some people say like oh you know another project
we don't need this blah blah blah but none of this happens in a bubble you know I just
from personal experience working in a Linux company, a Linux focused company, when these
projects are around we never knock them here because we're always looking at okay how is
this project doing this you know and if there's something great happening there then the rest
of the community can adopt that and you know contribute to that and it just makes Linux
as a whole better so if you're interested in seeing what they're what what Ike's up
to and what the project is up to you know check out its github and throw them a few
bucks if you can because it'll ultimately benefit everyone and I say that about Solus
I say that about elementary I say that about Abuja Mate you know we're we're all a rising
tide right raises all ships so yeah supporting these guys really does make the Linux desktop
as a whole better.
Yeah okay well let's talk about a Linux desktop with which you are intimately familiar there's
been an update this week from System76 who are they on pop exclamation mark underscore
OS now from the blog post it says of the GNOME work that you guys have been doing CalDAV
and CardDAV work continues but the deeper we've dug the more hard coding we've found
now that is something that concerns me concerns me and I've heard that concern from a lot
of people you guys have taken on a big big challenge here to create your own distro even
though it's based on Ubuntu and basically Ubuntu GNOME and it's not that different at
the moment but you have taken on a lot and it seems that you are slowly realizing that
fact.
I think we realized it from the get-go we talked to a lot of projects before we jumped
in for instance we're really close to the elementary guys and so we had conversations
about what we wanted to do especially with GNOME online accounts which is what we're
talking about here and so we already had set aside some resources for this specifically
with GNOME contacts and GNOME calendar and Geary and those applications that should be
using the evolution data server and sharing you know this information in many cases they've
implemented how they talk to GNOME online accounts slightly different and so I don't
think that it's really unexpected that we have to do a bit of work I guess it is kind
of surprising that there wasn't a single implementation for this type of stuff across these applications
but we have one of our engineers David working on this pretty essentially full-time right
now and so he's going through and doing a lot of plumbing on this we've also teamed
up with elementary they've been making a big push with Pantheon Mail to implement the evolution
data server in Pantheon Mail and so we're looking to see how they're doing that and
talking to them about where we can work together to kind of do some of this plumbing and in
shared applications okay and also this installer situation it seems that you guys are not a
fan of Ubiquity which is by far my favorite installer and you don't like one specific
bit of it which is the bit that I really like and that is that it's very linear you stick
all your information into it it finishes reboot done login start using it whereas the GNOME
way to do things by default is to do a little bit upfront and then once you boot it for
the first time then you put in things like your locale and username and passwords and
all that kind of stuff I don't know why you don't just use the OEM installer quite frankly
because that is it you know that does it for you yeah we do use the OEM installer the OEM
installer still prompts you to do some things in Ubiquity that we decided should be in GNOME
initial setup for instance I remember when we started this conversation it actually started
because of the Ubuntu mailing list and they were saying there are things in Ubiquity that
you do that you then end up doing in GNOME initial setup and that's really quite weird
and so because even the first time I did it I was like why am I filling out this information
twice so we were having conversations and at first we were actually on the opposite
side we were talking to the to Jeremy Beecher and we're saying why isn't this all in Ubiquity
and then over time as we played around with GNOME initial setup more we decided oh wait
okay so let's say that you create a new user you could run them through some of this GNOME
initial setup stuff so that they can set up things specifically on their account like
for instance if they do want a different keyboard layout or something they as a user can set
that up specifically and then as we went further down that path we realized well Ubiquity could
be paired back to where it's only handles things that are specific to an installation
of a machine and then on first boot a person can set up the rest of their stuff through
initial setup and it just seemed as we played around with it more it seemed like a better
user experience and so because you might have like in the case of me installing something
for someone else I might install do some complicated partitioning or whatever and then hand that
off to a friend or a family member and then when they go through a new GNOME initial setup
they're setting up the things that they understand and that they're ready to do and so I feel
like it had to go one way or another you know because inputting the same information twice
during setup being installation and setup seems strange and frankly I don't know doesn't
really make much sense because you're like oh you already have the information why don't
you just skip this and so it had to go one way or another and it seems like the proper
way is to have the installer handle installer specific stuff have the GNOME initial setup
handle the user configuration stuff and I think we found a fine line there and I think
that that's probably the best way to go.
Fair enough I disagree but I can see the arguments for it so yeah okay so let's wrap it up with
Beaker and reading from a motherboard article here the concept behind Beaker is similar
to torrent file sharing a user can create a site on their local machine by opening menu
and clicking a single button which creates a folder on the hard drive that can be shared
over the internet with other Beaker users via URL.
So this is a browser that aims to completely decentralize the web now you could say well
the web is supposed to be decentralized anyway isn't it it already is why do we need this
extra thing and the argument is that you've got things like AWS and as you're and you've
got centralization happening so I mean the technicalities of this I don't think we need
to get into it's pretty cool I've tried it out you do have to build it from you have
to clone the git repository and build it it's not too difficult to do it this is clearly
just for developers at this stage it's not for consumers but for me the what's interesting
is the concept here of a decentralized web do we need it more decentralized than it is
I don't know I'm struggling to see the argument really.
So on ironically on motherboard there's a documentary a short documentary I think it's
like 20 or 30 minutes long that features my friend Isaac he was working on at Occupy Wall
Street and it's covered pretty well there he talks about you know how the web is a lot
more centralized than it once was and how when it comes to things like things that companies
may not feel comfortable with being on the web it's very easy to shut them down even
if they're just a instance of free speech or whatever you know not necessarily anything
criminal and that got me thinking more about this back that was in 2012 that we started
talking about this and so I've used zero net I've used I can't remember the name of the
other one there's another popular one now that's you know part of this decentralized
web push I haven't used beaker but I have seen it before I've seen the project page
I think I think honestly this is moving the world in the positive direction I don't like
the idea of like any good Linux user I suppose I don't like the idea of losing out on on
my my freedom because some company says that this doesn't meet their content policy or
or you know you could have AWS say we don't want this hosted on our servers whatever and
it could be not necessarily like I said criminal or anything it's just something that they
don't want to have to to defend you know like when someone says like why do you host that
on your infrastructure so I think this is ultimately good and as a positive thing for
for free speech I as far as like which one of these projects will raise rise above the
rest this looks cool zero net looks cool they all look cool I don't like them being browser
specific though and I don't think zero net is but you have to run like a script and and
you have to I think you might have to use Firefox but I would rather just have it be
something that you can access well that's the thing there's a huge barrier to entry
at the moment and you have to be very technical to do it the idea of normal people using this
stuff is it feels a long way off and that to me is what we need to crack it's all one
and good to have it in a nice technical implementation that works well if you know what you're doing
but it needs to be as simple as open Chrome type in address or Google search the thing
that you're looking for an open up website right right I agree 100% I think that will
be the barrier I could see this being really helpful for journalists too and I say that
in a more broad sense you know people who are covering things that that a government
or company may not want out in the open and so I think ultimately it's a net good for
technology and society but yeah the barrier to entry is pretty high and some of the people
who would benefit most from this may be among those users who find it difficult to set this
up and get started that's something they'll have to be overcome before this really takes
off yeah well time gets away from us so we'd better wrap it up you can check out linuxactionnews.com
slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes and linuxactionnews.com slash contact
for ways to get in touch and don't forget you can support the network as a whole at
the patreon page which is patreon.com slash Jupiter signal I'll be back with Chris next
Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news I'm at Joe Rissington
and I'm at Ryan Lee Sipes thanks for joining us and thank you Ryan again and we'll see
you again next week