Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 117, recorded on August 4th, 2019. I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe. Good to be connected with you on a very busy news week. Let's start off
with Mangero's plans to ship Free Office.
Yeah, Free Office, which is free as in beer, but not free as in freedom. This is a proprietary
suite, which they had initially planned to ship by default in Mangero. But then after
a fair bit of backlash, shall we say, they've decided that they're not going to ship it
by default, but they'll give you the option to install it, or LibreOffice, or no Office
Suite.
A pretty common reaction online was negative. People thought it was a bad idea to shove
a proprietary Office product into a free Linux distribution when LibreOffice exists and it's
pretty functional. I had a chance to chat with Philip, one of the founders of Mangero
on Linux Unplugged 3.12. And what I took away from the conversation was that it was more
about trying to create a bit of differentiation for Mangero from the rest of the pack.
So there's something unique about the distribution, but also trying to improve compatibility for
users that treat their Office Suite like a tool. And they wanted perhaps improve compatibility
with the commercial products on the market, which SoftMaker's free Office is pretty well
known for. I think the project looked at it as a very practical move. There was no monetary
exchange to take it on. It was more of a let's just try to do something different and improve
compatibility for users. The reaction was strong. And so now it sounds like it'll be
an option during install.
Yeah, you're going to be faced with a screen that gives you the option of either free Office,
LibreOffice, or no Office Suite. And I think that's what they should have done in the first
place, really. I think that it was a bad idea to ship proprietary software by default. Fair
enough to give people the option to install it. But I think just having that on your default
ISO is just, it's not a great look really for a Linux distribution.
I think I agree. Making an option is best for everyone. Because myself, when I install
Mangero, I'll choose the no Office option. That's perfect for me. I don't really want
it. I don't use it that much. So that's what my dog in this hunt is, full disclosure. However,
so I could have an informed conversation with Philip, I downloaded free Office and gave
it a go. And after using it for about an hour and opened up a couple of different things,
compared it to LibreOffice and Google Docs, which is my, sorry to say, when I do need
a word processor or spreadsheet, I use Google Docs. So I compared it to that as well. And
I walked away with something. And that is good enough is not good enough for people
that are opening up business documents, where they need to properly be able to import proprietary
Office formats and then save as different proprietary Office formats and keep functionality,
make sure formatting is correct, and have a workflow that's really similar. Imagine
that mythical migrating user who's coming from Windows to Linux, free Office sort of
replicates that Office look and feel, combined with the compatibility. And in my experience,
it's also faster, a little faster, starts up a little bit quicker, feels a little lightweight
on the system. And you combine that with the look and feel and the compatibility. I think
it is a solid argument that it's better than LibreOffice for a certain type of worker.
So again, I think having the option to install is a good thing.
Yeah, by all means, make it easy to install this proprietary Office suite and point people
towards it and recommend it or whatever. But I just think shipping it by default, it's
just crossing a line. Some people talked about shipping graphics drivers by default, but
I think that's different. That is making the most of your hardware. Whereas this is just
different. This is productivity software that we're talking about that you don't actually
need to make your computer work properly.
Yeah, I agree. There's not an equivalence to a hardware enablement. But there could
be an equivalence to codecs or making Steam super simple to install. You don't need Steam
to make your computer work. You don't need H.264 playback and MP3 playback to make your
computer work. It's nice to have, just like opening up Office documents that you need
to interact with to do your job is nice to have.
Yeah, but there is no open source version of Steam. There's no open Steam or whatever.
There are different ways to get games that can be open source or whatever. But I don't
think that is a fair equivalent because LibreOffice is good enough for some people, at least for
me. And I use it actually quite a bit and I just have no need for a proprietary Office
suite. I think it comes down to make it easy to install, but don't ship it by default.
That's what I personally want to see.
That's reasonable and I can't really argue that. I want to sort of pivot for a second
and talk about the meta aspect of this story, which we in a way have touched on several
times this year already. And that is outrage driven development. Project announces intention
to do X, community reacts very strongly, and then project amends announcement to do Y instead,
which is generally a compromise in some way. And sometimes that truly is for the best,
like in the case of the 32-bit support for Ubuntu. I am reminded of that famous Steve
Job quote that's roughly, if you asked consumers before the automobile came out what they wanted,
they'd say a stronger, faster horse.
Yeah, I do get what you're saying there, but this is open source development we're talking
about and it's supposed to be a community effort. And okay, some people go about it
in the wrong way, being too strident and Twitter rants and all the rest of it, but isn't the
whole point of it that the community drives the direction of development?
Absolutely. You quantified it right there. That's why I'm worried because Twitter and
the forums don't represent the tens and tens of thousands of people that are running Manjaro.
Just as the people that got really upset on Twitter and the dozen or so news articles
were written and the outrage comments on Reddit don't represent the tens of millions of Ubuntu
desktop users. But yet what we talk about as community is just a hyper-representation
of the most outraged individuals who are taking the effort to go to different outlets, some
which are very low effort like Reddit and Twitter, and they're expressing their outrage.
I saw so many comments about people dropping Manjaro over this. This sort of, I want to
punish them attitude for doing this. It's not just that people are upset, they want
to punish them. And then the developers, who all of a sudden have this onslaught of very
loud feedback, cave because we all see this as this is the voice of the community when
it's just the representation of a small portion. You know this because our shows have a lot
more people downloading than we get comments from. And it's just the nature of doing business
on the internet. You get a lot of people that just enjoy content or will use a distribution,
faithfully upgrade from release to release of Manjaro and be perfectly happy with it
and not really care. You know most people probably just figure, right, well if they
install FreeOffice, I'll just uninstall it and then I'll install LibreOffice. Job done.
And that's it. End of story. And what we end up getting is this hyper-representation from
the outrage. And that's really what bothers me here is because that is driving decisions.
And it's not fully representative of the entire community.
There's not really a way to get representation from the entire community. You just have to
listen to the vocal people or ignore them or whatever. They are the people who are in
your community who are talking to you. And so you have to decide whether you think that
they are a true representation of the silent majority or whether they're just crackpots
or whatever. And that is a difficult thing to do.
I think it's a skill you have to build up. I think it's something that takes perhaps
years of exposure to calibrate correctly. And some personality types may be better or
worse at handling that kind of feedback as well. So there's a personal factor in there.
Yeah, but it's just part of running a project. You just have to be able to deal with this
stuff.
Add that to the list of required skills to run a large open source project. All right,
problem solved. Moving on to other large open source projects are coming together, perhaps
maybe to benefit end users.
Yeah, the Linux App Summit is going to be held in Barcelona in November from the 12th
to the 15th. And there's going to be representatives from both KDE and GNOME all working together
there.
Joe, I believe this is the artist formerly known as the Libre Application Summit. But
I think that was when it was more just the GNOME camp. And now that KDE and GNOME folks
are coming together to sort of talk about some future collaboration on the desktop,
they've renamed it. And it's, I think, a pretty positive sign of where the two projects could
be going in the future. And the headlines are going crazy. They're coming together to
create a new desktop era for Linux. I don't know about that. But it seems like it's a
good sign. And it's looking like this is the next generation or the next phase of this
conference.
But really, this isn't anything hugely new, because the different projects in open source
have generally worked together before. And this supposed rivalry between GNOME and KDE
is just not even really true. It's the users, if anything, might be starting this. But I
think that what actually stands out here is that they're going to actively start working
together, rather than just kind of playing nice with each other and occasionally interacting
or whatever. This is going to be some serious coming together to improve the Linux desktop.
I mean, is that pie in the sky? I don't think so. I think genuinely, this is a really good
move.
I think the truth lies somewhere there in the middle. Like you say, a lot of this has
already been happening for a long time. There have been common standards efforts for years.
I think what we're getting here is a bit of a sales pitch from a group that is trying
to grow a conference into something that's a serious contender in the industry. And so
they're using a lot of enthusiastic language. I'll give you an example. KDE and GNOME will
no longer be taking a passive role in the free desktop sector. That's just that sentence
right there. That reeks of sales bullshit. First of all, it's demeaning to the project's
years of efforts. And it implies that they have somehow been just sitting around observing
the free desktop market, but not actively participating in it, which is an insane sentence
because they are the free desktop market. So it's just ridiculous on its face. And they
then continue on with the joint influence of the two projects. The summit will shepherd
the growth of the free desktop by encouraging the creation of quality applications.
This is one of those fallacies that we run into a lot in open source development. We
have this great belief because we have seen it work a few times, a few times super successfully
too. If we build it, they will come. If we build the perfect framework, if we have the
ideal toolkit, if we use just the right language, they will come. That's not what drives the
desktop market. I think it should be obvious and painfully clear to this group in particular
that that's not the dynamics at play in the desktop market. It hasn't been for about 25
years.
So a lot of this to me reads as they're really excited about this event. They hope they can
lay some foundational groundwork here to really work towards something in the future. And
they need a lot of people to get on board. And so they've got to talk about it in a really
big way. And the way it's being represented in the rest of the community as this incredible
event of the two projects coming together, while that feels good, it's just a conference.
It's not like some joint declaration of cooperation that the foundations have issued with co-signatures
of all of the primary developers. It's some event organizers that are promoting something
that's happening in Barcelona in November.
I thought I was supposed to be the cynical one. That's a very cynical read of it. I'm
just much more positive. Maybe I've just swallowed the Kool-Aid on this one. But I think it's
got to be good for them to be getting together and working together like this.
You might be right. The way to really know would be to go. I won't be making it to Barcelona
this year. But if they ever made it to the US, like next year or something, I'd check
it out and see if I'm wrong. I'd sure love to see some information about how they plan
to entice third-party developers. I'd like to see some action plans on how to go after
the market that is creating applications that run on the cloud. That seems like such a perfect
market for the free desktop groups to target. A real type of power user that's comfortable
with change that needs to develop on the platform that they're targeting anyways. Oh, my gosh.
They practically could just give them an invite. So maybe that'll come out of this conference.
But that might just be too practical. Maybe I'm expecting too much.
Maybe. Well, Barcelona in November is lovely. So maybe I could try and go.
You could be our special correspondent, Joe.
Yeah, yeah. Sounds good to me.
You be careful. You might get held to that.
All right. Well, let's talk about Android. And we got a pretty big update this week regarding
search providers in Europe.
I guess I was naive. I did not see it going this way. So first, it's kind of what you
expect. A real basic screen in Android that will have Google and three other search providers
that you can choose from that have been randomized. Google writes, we'll introduce a new way for
Android users to select a search provider to power a search box on their home screen
and as the default in Chrome if it's installed. Not too surprising.
But if you want your search engine to be part of this, then you're pretty much going to
have to pay.
Now, this is the part I should have expected but hadn't really given the thought. It's
going to be an auction, Joe. To get your search engine on that list next to Google's name,
you have to participate in what Google calls a first price sealed bid auction to select
the other general search providers that appear on the choice screen.
Google will conduct auctions on a per country basis for a period from January 1st, 2020
to December 31st, 2020. Following the initial round of auctions, any subsequent rounds will
only occur once per year, which means these are high value spots. In each country's auction,
search providers will state the price that they are willing to pay each time a user selects
them from the choice screen in that given country.
Yeah, and then each search engine is just going to get an invoice every month from Google.
This is how many people wanted to use you, so you've got to pay us this much money. This
really is Google just doing the absolute bare minimum to comply with the European Commission.
And Google had previously argued that it needed that search revenue that was tied to results
in Chrome and on the Android platform to monetize what they said was, quote, a significant investment
in the system. However, the commission rejected that assessment, noting the billions Google
earns in the Play Store alone, as well as all of that very valuable data that Google
is collecting on Android users. But to monetize this, and to make it super exclusive once
a year, and there's only three other slots along with Google's own search results. So
it's going to be really expensive. And you have to get cracking because if you want your
search engine in that list, you need to apply to bid by September 13th of 2019.
But what's interesting is that if you are running a search engine, you don't necessarily
have to pay to be part of this. Because if three search engines aren't willing to pay,
then any of those extra slots will just be chosen at random from a list of search providers
that were interested in it but didn't want to pay. So I don't know whether that's actually
going to happen. It seems capitalism will probably mean that there won't be any free
slots. But it'll be interesting to see whether that actually happens. Although we won't probably
hear about it because this is all kind of sealed, confidential, and that no numbers
are going to be revealed to the public.
It does kind of make me giggle, though, picturing Bing and DuckDuckGo, like shell corporations,
being set up all around the world bidding on these. So that way DuckDuckGo and Bing
would be just a big conspiracy to screw with Google. That makes me laugh. Hey, let's do
a quick update on DNS over HTTPS, a.k.a. Doh.
Yes, I was looking to implement this by default in Firefox. But before they do that, they
are running some tests.
When we were talking about this a couple of weeks ago, I was kind of curious how this
would work for managed networks like enterprises that have centralized DNS that they use for
very specific reasons or parental controls. Well, it turns out Mozilla's thought of that,
or at least they are thinking about that right now. And they're running a test. They want
to understand how often users of Firefox are subjected to managed networks or parental
control software. Also, a really common way to do ad blocking, right, is by DNS blocking.
So they have to attempt to discover how common this is and how they can accommodate it.
Selina Duckelman writes on the Mozilla blog that they'll be capturing this information
locally, including when people are using safe versions of Google or YouTube. And they will
analyze that and then they'll send up the metrical information, if that's a word, to
the Mozilla servers, but not the actual URLs you're going to.
So this is sort of a safe way to participate in the study for them without them having
to actually look at all of your DNS queries and all of that garbage that would sort of
violate your privacy like crazy. And of course, they are offering a way for you to opt out
as well.
I don't really know what they're planning to do with the data that they collect here
because what are they going to find out? A certain percentage of users fall into these
categories. But then what?
I could see a couple of uses. If it's super low, if it's like one percent of our users
have managed DNS, which I doubt, but let's just say that's what it is, then that makes
just a great stat in the blog where we can just completely ignore this because only one
percent of our users have this problem. So it could be that. But I doubt it. I think
the more generous interpretation would be they'll use this to develop the different
features and support in DNS over HTTPS. So they will have to build in some types of accommodation
for safe search and for managed enterprise DNS. And perhaps this will give them some
insights into what areas they have to focus on.
Well, right now it's pretty easy to go into the settings and enable or disable DNS over
HTTPS. And I would imagine that once it is default, that's going to be similar. So I
think that administrators are not going to have a hugely bad time of it. And most users
will be fine. So it's going to be one more part of the setup process for people who have
specific uses. I don't think it's going to be a huge issue.
I started playing around with it just recently. I'm going to give it a go for a while. And
I noticed now there's just a field right in there to specify your own DNS over HTTPS server.
And to make that a little bit easier, there's a snap now. I think it's like it might be
called like a cloud, Cloudflare or something. It's a version of the Cloudflare DNS over
HTTPS proxy server that you can install on your own system and run it on your own box
and try it for a little bit. It can be kind of a neat way to just mess around with the
whole software stack. I'll try it for a bit, see where it goes. I think the biggest question
on all of our minds is, will we ever get used to saying doh?
I certainly won't. And DNS over HTTPS is a mouthful. We need something that's, I don't
know, easier to say.
We need a new contract, Joe. One for the web. And I think your good buddy, Tims Burners-Lee,
may have just the solution.
Yeah, the way he sees it, things are very different from 30 years ago when he invented
the web. And he thinks that it's gone into some pretty dodgy directions. And he thinks
that what we need is for everyone to sign up for this contract for the web. And suddenly,
that's going to make everything much better.
The idea is get major governments, major corporations, get everyone in between to literally sign
a contract that companies and governments should ensure everyone can connect to the
internet and keep all of the internet available, affordable, and accessible all the time, and
respect and protect people's fundamental online privacy and data rights. Clearly something
that's pretty easy to get behind. What company wouldn't want to be on that list? It looks
dead. Burners-Lee goes on to describe this as a journey from digital adolescence to a
more mature, responsible, and inclusive future.
Is anyone going to pay attention to this? It seems pretty unlikely to me.
I mean, maybe. I mean, a lot of my attention these days is really focused on Solid.
Yeah, whatever happened to that? That was his project to... I don't even know what it
was supposed to be, some sort of like next generation web or something.
Yeah, a new way to do linking of data.
Yeah. And if you look at the website, it says the apps are coming. The first wave of Solid
apps are being created now. So who knows? Maybe he's just working on a few things at
the same time. But it just feels like he's trying to stay relevant, maybe?
Maybe. I'm of two minds. I do see that. It feels like these initiatives go nowhere because
the internet and the web are just not a cohesive small thing that can be influenced like that
anymore. But then I also think about what people say about Richard Stallman. And I'm
somewhere in the middle on those particular things too. I feel like in a way, it's good
to have something to strive for. Like what is the bar? What should we as citizens of
the internet be pushing for? And that's a pretty good list.
I could get behind that list of ideals. I could say I'm pretty skeptical anything's
going to become of this. But maybe it's good to have that goalpost.
Yeah, I suppose you're right. Having one good force tugging in the positive direction can't
really be a bad thing. So maybe I should stop being cynical.
Well, and I suppose in that regard, it's good to have his name attached to it.
Yeah, I suppose. And if they can get some seriously big organizations signing up to
this, then maybe it can create some momentum.
Now our last story of the week. When I first saw the headline, I kind of snickered a little
bit and I thought this is kind of silly. And then it clicked in my head how I would personally
use this. And well, now I'm kind of excited about moving the Linux desktop into virtual
reality. This may actually be a genuinely decent use case for VR on Linux.
Right. Well, this I have to hear because I did not stop snickering, I'm afraid.
Well, Collabra has made this announcement and it was development that's sponsored by Valve.
And there's real functional code today. Those are all three, like, unusually great things
about an announcement. It's called XR Desktop, and it sits on top of either Plasma or Gnome
Shell and extends the window environment into virtual reality, into a 360 degree space where
you can manage windows in that space.
Now this is, for me, perhaps the only solution to what is otherwise an insatiable appetite
for monitors that I have. I want so many screens, Joe. It's ridiculous. I would like to have,
if I truly could, a screen per application. Really would. So this is actually potentially
a possibility because not only can you lay windows out, but because it's a full 3D space,
you can have them far away. You can move them closer. There's core elements to what they're
proposing, the workflow that I find super appealing. Essentially unlimited screen space
in a whole virtual world. When I'm sitting here doing these shows, I could be sitting
here with a VR headset on my face with hundreds of windows. It could be paradise, Joe. I could
be in ADD heaven.
It sounds like a nightmare to me. I can't think of anything worse. I suffer really badly
from motion sickness and it seems to be getting worse as I get older. So this, just no way
would I possibly want it. It's like something from an 80s movie. It just seems laughable
to me that you would want to do this.
That might be why I like it too. Well, I'll tell you what. Honestly, it is so early days.
This is really rough stuff. I'm very skeptical about the interface. They've done a good job
to map UI controls to the VR controllers. I got to give them credit for that. I'm not
on board with using my Oculus controllers to manage my desktop though. I want a keyboard
and mouse. There's a lot of rough stuff here, but here's what we do know so far. It integrates
with the existing desktop environment's compositors. In the case of Kaywin, it's sort of like a
Compiz plugin, if you will, and in the case of Gnome Shelts and Patches. So you can run
both the virtual space and your actual desktop environment at the same time if you want.
They've written a GLib wrapper to Vulkan, which they call Gulkan, which makes it easy
to use Vulkan rendering for this entire environment. And they have early support even for Wayland
on Gnome Shelts.
Now, I don't think this is going to be the future of the Linux desktop. In fact, I don't
even think this is going to be a mainstream thing. But I really appreciate the idea that
if you plug a VR headset into Linux in the future, there's actually something functional
you can do with it. It doesn't just show up as a second weird display that has the wrong
aspect ratio and Linux just looks like a dumpster fire trying to manage it. If you plug that
thing in and all of a sudden your desktop applications extended to it like a mirrored
environment and it was functional, that's pretty impressive. And if they just got to
there, I'd be a happy camper.
Yeah, fair enough. It's not something I'm going to use. But I suppose bringing more
functionality on Linux to existing hardware, that's always got to be good.
This is more likely going to get me to hook up my Oculus to a Linux desktop than gaming
would. I know that sounds silly. But like I said, I've just got a voracious appetite
for screens. I want all those screens. So then actually, I was thinking we should do
a challenge and try to get Wes to set this up for us during the sprint that we're doing
in a couple of weeks. Don't say anything. Don't tell anybody. We'll surprise them.
They'll get Linux action news every single week at linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe
for all the ways to get new episodes.
And you can go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch with us.
And go check out the new linuxacademy.com brand new website launch and it looks slick.
Yeah. Did you have anything to do with this dark mode thing?
It's taking over Joe. Oh man, I love it.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I'm at Chris LAS.
I am at Joe Rossington.
Thank you for joining us and we will see you next week.
See you later.