Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News.
Episode 232, recorded on March 16th, 2022.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Let's do the news.
This week, Arch Linux turned 20 years old.
And we thought we should start the show out this week by wishing Arch, the project, and
the many people behind it, a happy birthday.
No, it's not quite old enough to drink, but you really shouldn't use Pac-Man under the
influence anyway.
Arch has seen distros come and go, the rise of SystemD, the introduction of Wayland, and
PulseAudio for that matter, but it was first released way back on March 11th, 2002, a simpler
time for the Linux desktop, and Arch 0.1 had a nice simple codename at that, Homer.
Since then, they've managed to mostly keep things simple while also building out an incredible
user repository, a wiki that I still use even when I'm not using an Arch system, and an
amazing amount of community goodwill.
That's why, even though I get pretty excited about Fedora these days and still have some
Ubuntu machines laying around, of course, Arch, I think, will always remain one of my
go-to distros.
And I know you've had a few mean Arch desktops over the years, Chris.
Are you actually still using it, though?
I have.
I do.
I have, well, we have two boxes in the studio, a desktop machine of mine that's just been
a rock since like 2017.
I have just slowly upgraded Arch on that thing, and it's been totally great.
And then we have it on an old server here that it's still in transition, and it's running
on there in a server capacity.
Also quite stable.
We started it as, honestly, a year ago as a lark because the live audience was giving
me the hardest time for not trying out Arch Linux.
This is probably a decade ago.
And I was like, all right, fine.
You know, being a smart arch kid that I was, I was like, fine, I'll try a chat room.
I'll see what your Arch user repository is all about.
And I did a week-long challenge.
And we still have people that write into the show that say, hey, I started listening during
the Arch challenge.
And I did a total deep dive into Arch and came away extremely impressed.
I went from a skeptic to a true Arch believer.
I try not to tell you about it all the time, by the way, but sometimes I just can't help
myself.
And I still love it.
It might not be like my go-to distro for like a laptop these days.
That tends to be Fedora.
But for custom-built systems, maybe rigs that are going to have a really specific purpose,
or when I'm trying out cutting-edge hardware, I always still turn to Arch.
And I think part of that is because Arch hasn't changed much for the last 20 years.
I mean, it's changed technologically.
And it's changed with the Linux community in that way.
But I thought this is interesting in that first release there, that Homer release, the
0.1 release, really.
Arch was described as this.
Arch Linux is an i6-86 optimized Linux distribution based on ideas from Crux.
And then it goes on to say in the post, a default Arch install leaves you with a solid
base.
From there, you can add packages to create the custom installation you're looking for.
That 20 years later is still perfectly, it just perfectly describes Arch still.
And you've got to give the project credit for that.
That's a hard thing to really stick to over 20 years.
And by just nailing that basic promise, a lot of people have come to love the distribution.
So happy birthday, everybody.
After what has felt like years of rumors, on March 15th, Google announced that Steam
for Chrome OS is finally here, or, well, almost here.
It's a little confusing.
It is.
It seems maybe the right hand doesn't know what the left hand is doing in this case at
Google.
So we dug into this just a little bit for the show.
And I'm thinking they were planning to have everything lined up for this Google Game Developer
Summit.
And then the announcement and the slides and all that stuff kept going forward and the
bits that Chrome OS needed didn't.
So a Google PR person confirmed that the Steam for Chrome OS stuff isn't actually available
right now, like they said it was, but it should be in the near future.
OK, fair enough.
That stuff can take time.
And to no real surprise, they are initially targeting the higher end Chromebooks.
OK, also, fair enough.
Not a surprise at all, really.
But you're going to need something in there like a decent Intel or AMD x86 64 CPU, not
an ARM CPU.
Those will not get support for this.
Unfortunately, you're also probably going to have something that has somewhat of a graphics
card on there.
They have a list that we'll have linked in the show notes.
Steam on Chrome OS is also leveraging, like you probably expected, those Linux application
containers that Google built a little while ago.
That means that Valve gets to use a lot of the stuff, well, pretty much everything they've
already built for Steam on Linux.
They don't have to like make a Chrome OS specific version.
And actually, speaking of Steam, Valve has sent the developer of Lutris a Steam Deck
to help with development of Lutris.
I mean, I just think that's pretty notable here because Lutris could be a tool that lets
you bypass the Steam ecosystem if you chose to.
You can participate with it as well, but it is essentially a competing tool that lets
you use multiple different game stores.
Yeah, I guess the hope here is that having an actual Steam Deck in hand should help further
development on the Flatpak, as well as maybe hooking up anything special that's needed
to get Lutris to work specifically on the Steam Deck.
But yeah, I mean, as you say, like Lutris is not limited to the Steam ecosystem.
Yes, it does work in the Steam ecosystem, but it works with a whole lot of other things
too.
So good on Valve for kind of continuing to keep up this commitment of the Deck is just
a Linux device.
Yeah, they keep saying it's a PC.
If that doesn't underscore that philosophy, I don't know what else does.
And then just last bit of news on Steam.
The Steam survey results for February 2022 have been clackalated and we just have a couple
of notes.
Just a reminder, though, that this is kind of a notoriously unreliable metric because
the total Steam user base is always growing amongst all other kinds of things.
But here's the figures you're probably interested in.
In February of this year, Linux had a Steam market share of 1.02%.
Unfortunately that's down a little bit from 1.06% back in January.
But taking a longer term view, things look pretty healthy year over year.
Way back in February last year, if you can remember that, Steam on Linux sat at 0.81%.
Although again, as you noted there, Chris, Steam's overall market share has definitely
continued to increase significantly in that time.
So it's a little difficult to make complete sense of these numbers.
Yeah, I think we mostly just wanted to note it today because won't that number be pretty
interesting in about a year from now?
Not only has the Deck been sent out to people who pre-ordered it, but likely in a year from
now, hopefully, sales channels are loaded up, people have easy access to a Deck.
The number here could be pretty different.
That may also have the halo effect, as Apple used to call it, where perhaps people see
the Deck and decide, well, if I've got a Deck now, maybe I also will try Linux on this machine
and install Steam.
We may see this number go up, perhaps in a year.
The thing we don't know at this point is, how's Valve going to calculate those Deck
numbers?
Are they going to lump it in with the general Linux scene, are they going to break it out
as a distro, or is it going to be its own category altogether?
We just don't have that answer yet.
Michael Larable over at Feromics caught wind of a new Linux driver testing framework this
week called RoadTest.
What immediately stood out to us about RoadTest is it enables drivers to be tested under
user mode Linux, and makes it super simple to use mocked or modeled hardware.
Yeah, modeled hardware, isn't that interesting?
But here's the problem they say they're trying to solve, quote, most of the hardware is not
available in current CI systems, so most drivers can only, at best, be build tested there.
Even basic soundness, such as drivers successfully probing and binding to the devices it tries
to support, cannot be tested.
Drivers cannot be easily regression tested to ensure that bug-fixed code does not get
reintroduced again.
I think the key thing in there that they're talking about here is, testers can use this
modeled hardware to at least build some basic test coverage.
And when you have a setup, which a lot of these hardware vendors do now, when you have
a setup where you're building with a continuous integration system, anything more you can
do there is going to be great, even if it's just some really basic stuff, because I think
it's not particularly robust, Wes.
I think it's kind of basic.
Yeah, it's definitely focused on just simple tests.
Actually the tests and hardware models themselves are written in Python, taking advantage of
Python's built-in unit test framework.
So no, this isn't going to give you the full set of capabilities that real hardware has,
and of course testing on real hardware is still important, but that's really difficult
in CI systems, just given the huge nature of different types of hardware and parameters
and configurations that hardware can be in.
All of that makes development, modification, maintenance work, reviewing patches to these
drivers, all of that is way harder than it actually needs to be.
So RoadTest hopes to make some of those things just a little bit easier.
Linode.com slash LAN.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account, and you go there to support the
show.
You know everything we've deployed in the last, like, what, two and a half years?
That's been on Linode.
It's the Linux Geeks Cloud with 11 data centers around the world, and they've been hard at
work for almost 19 years, creating the best experience for running your applications up
there on the cloud.
And you know, they're rolling out this new database as a service, and they've done it
right.
It's a MySQL project.
They worked with the project there, and they have focused on getting it just right.
They're gonna expand upon it.
I actually haven't had a chance to try it yet, though.
It's in beta right now, but I know Linode is gonna nail it.
You're gonna have the expertise and the pros that know how to make Linode tick.
They're gonna be behind that, right?
They're gonna have that fast infrastructure, and of course, the great uptime.
So I'm planning to try it, but if you get a chance to try it, let me know what you think.
In fact, go sign up and try it out yourself and send me the feedback.
I'll incorporate it in a future read.
Linode.com slash LAN.
Go get that $100 to try it.
Linode has been rolling out screaming fast MVME-based block storage recently.
We use their super flexible S3-compatible object storage to power things like our Next
Cloud or the backend storage for services that are always growing.
If you want to deploy a matrix server like we have, Linode is great for that as well.
Maybe you just want to use Linode for a few minutes to try something out, or maybe you
want to run your business infrastructure on there for the next 10 years.
I know people that have been doing that, and I know that they've been loving it.
And one thing that I hear over and over again from our audience is the support is incredible.
When they need it, Linode support has been outstanding.
Great support, super fast rigs, crazy great networking, and 11 data centers to choose
from.
Yeah, there's a lot of reasons to like Linode.
So let's put it over the top.
Go grab that $100 in credit and support the show.
Linode.com slash LAN.
Do you hear that?
Good Savings is calling Linux.ting.com.
Thanks to Ting for sponsoring this episode.
I've been a Ting customer since 2013.
I love these guys.
I mean, really, it's the way mobile should be done here in the States.
They don't do it good enough.
They didn't have to.
They got in early.
But I've heard from friends outside the country that say, you know, over here in our country
and our fancy country, this is how mobile has to be done.
Ting is a mobile virtual network operator.
They're a lean mean fighting machine.
They focus on the customer experience, value, picking the plans that are simple and straightforward.
Great device selection, that kind of stuff.
Not greasing the wheels of politicians so that way they can dig a hole in the ground
and stand up a tower.
They don't bother with that.
Instead, they work at the meta level.
They rise above it.
And they pick multiple networks that they can work with nationwide coverage.
Great speeds, LTE and 5G.
And their customer support nails it when you need it.
In fact, Ting was recently named the number one carrier by Consumer Reports in 2021.
Ting's plans are simple and straightforward.
It's just the smarter way to do mobile.
And every single plan comes with that great support and no contracts ever.
It's pretty simple to switch to Ting.
Your phone's likely going to work.
So go to linux.ting.com.
Check your current phone, create an account and pick a plan that's just right for you.
Once everything's good to go, Ting will send you a SIM card.
You're going to pop that in your phone.
You'll get activated in minutes.
You'll kind of feel bad for not doing this sooner.
I went through that as well.
But you're going to be so glad you did it.
Start saving.
Same great wireless experience, just better value, linux.ting.com.
You'd be forgiven if you didn't happen to notice the release of GNOME 42 this week.
It was what you might call lacking in ceremony.
But after a bug update to rename the release from RC to final, GNOME 42 has finally landed.
However, before you get too excited about it, and there's a lot of reasons to get excited
here, we should remind you that it will probably be a few weeks before it lands in a distribution
near you, with the upcoming Fedora 36 and Ubuntu 22.04 likely shipping it first.
Now the fact that it's not technically available in a distro easily didn't stop us from giving
it a go just so we could get some impressions for you.
Heck no.
I got to start here with the visual look.
They really took it to the next level.
I wasn't sure what to expect because when GNOME 40 was announced, off in the far distance
was this big transition coming to GNOME 42 that involved Libidwaddy and a new way of
doing dark themes and themes on GNOME in general.
We just didn't know what that was going to materialize.
But this 42 release is just blow away in the terms of visual refinements.
Throughout the desktop and small little spots that I felt like didn't even need attention
have gotten attention, and the GNOME developers have made real efforts to implement a systemwide
dark mode that works here.
And they've also included a couple of pre-selected dark and light wallpapers that look really
great.
And so when you pick a dark mode or a light mode in the appearance selector, it now also
will adjust the wallpaper to be darker light, which just looks great.
And on top of all of that, they're doing this smooth onscreen transition.
They just nailed it.
It looks so good.
Like when they said they were going to do it, they committed to it and they did it right.
This is some impressive work to see, definitely.
But it's not all just shiny new shell work, no.
There's been a whole bunch of stuff behind the scenes to continue the efforts to port
things to GTK4, making a whole bunch of apps faster, and yes, also shinier.
One thing I have mixed feelings though about in this release is that our longtime reliable
text editor, GEdit, is being replaced.
GEdit at least is being replaced by a new text editor that also supports theming.
Oh, okay.
All right.
I'm picking up on a theme here, I think, Chris.
Yeah.
Yeah, I know.
But GEdit, too soon.
And of course, as with every GNOME release, there's also a whole bunch of bug fixes, a
last minute crash fix, nice catch guys, and performance improvements.
Yeah, I think we'll have more on that specifically on the performance part coming up soon.
I also wanted to mention, though, that what's nice about this release is it seemed to really
kind of motivate the general GNOME ecosystem, too.
So you see a lot of numerous third party projects have been making improvements to try to land
in time for GNOME 42.
So a lot of GTK apps are getting some nice improvements there.
So what we're going to keep doing is using it.
I'll keep running it.
Brendan West are going to give it a go and we'll give it a review in Sunday's Linux Unplugged.
We'll dig into some of the performance stuff and some of the areas they've improved, including
how they're doing remote windows and desktop applications with a full Wayland setup now.
Because I know a lot of people who use that on X11 have been wondering what the solution
is going to be for Wayland.
That is now baked in and we'll give that a try as well.
So don't miss our coverage in Sunday's Linux Unplugged.
And if you want to go get your hands on it, the Fedora 36 beta and Ubuntu 2204 betas are
out there.
Let us know what you think.
But that does bring us to the end of this week's Linux Action News.
If you would like to get this show every week ad free, support the entire network and become
a member at jupyter.party.
You get all the shows ad free with any of their bonus content.
And it's the only way to get Linux Action News ad free.
But as always, you can get the show for absolutely free at linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe,
where we have every single possible way in the universe to get the show.
And once you've got it, well, let us know linuxactionnews.com slash contact.
Yeah, yeah.
And don't forget our East Coast Meetup is coming up real soon, April 9th in Raleigh,
North Carolina.
We'd love to see you there meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting for the details.
We'll be back next week with our take on the latest Linux and open source news.
Thanks for joining us.
And that's all the news for this week.