Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News. Episode 252, recorded on August 3rd, 2022. I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes. Let's do the news.
There has been a lot of chatter as we record about a, quote, massive widespread malware
attack on GitHub. Steven Lacy on Twitter reported finding, quote, over 35,000 infected code
hits on GitHub.
But it turns out things might not be as bad as the internet seemed to initially think.
A false alarm of sorts. There is a problem, but maybe not as bad as originally thought.
The infected repositories were just simply forks and clones of projects. And GitHub seemed
to be really quick to clean it up, faster than I've ever seen any service provider clean
things up.
Yeah, they definitely deserve some props on this one. I saw the reporting tweet floating
around last night, but by the time I saw it and tried to click a few links, I was already
getting 404s.
We're not entirely sure of the motivation of these malware actors, but this attack vector
seems like it might be trying to target users who type in related code snippets into their
favorite search engine, and then happen to land on these malicious random GitHub repositories.
As discovered by Steven Lacy when accidentally browsing through one of these infected fake
clones himself.
The attacker amended the most recent commit and modified it with malicious code. It's
possible they planned to then inject that code into the original forked project, but
that's just an educated guess based on what the researchers have found.
This kind of confusion is possible by amending or committing changes in just the right manner,
letting attackers impersonate another GitHub user and make it look like the commit came
from them, at least in an attacker controlled repository. Behind the scenes, this is done
by locally changing certain environment variables to obtain the username and email address of
the user the attacker would like to impersonate, and then push those phony commits up to their
repo.
Yeah, actually a similar trick was used back in January to make it appear as though Linus
Torvalds was claiming to be Satoshi Nakamoto, the creator of Bitcoin. But the researchers
who dug into this say this is actually kind of becoming more and more of a problem. They
end their report with the following quote, we are seeing more and more large scale attacks
on the open source ecosystem. Those attacks can easily fool an unsuspecting developer.
It's time for a Steam Deck update. And there's plenty to talk about this week. Starting with
the release of SteamOS 3.3, which has your typical array of bug fixes and other minor
enhancements, but also solves user experience issues with the Deck.
Indeed, audio and Bluetooth fixes probably being the biggest quality of life improvements
for the Deck owners out there. But for me personally, it's tweaks to the virtual keyboard.
Bring it Valve, bring it. Firefox is also now available as a flat pack. And as always,
you'll love to see some nice updated Radeon graphics drivers making the update and 3.3
has that. But perhaps most importantly, it seems that Valve is just shipping more of
these things than ever.
Of course, we've also been keeping an eye on the Decks impacts to Linux's overall Steam
market share. Michael Harbel over at Ferronix reports that during June, Steam on Linux usage
hit a multi-year high point of 1.18%. And that growth continued in July, with Linux
gaming reaching a market share of 1.23%. That's an increase of 0.05% over just a month. Meanwhile,
Windows is at 97% and macOS at 1.74.
The reason why those relatively small numbers for Linux are actually impressive is you have
to take in account the rest of Steam's market share continues to grow. So that Linux growth
is in despite of the Windows growth. But also the speed at which we are seeing that number
tick up is increasing. And it seems in no small part thanks to the Deck.
And the software side of things that's coming together to meet that new demand. DXVK 1.10.3
has been released, which is part of the latest version of Proton, which of course, powers
Steam Play, letting you play those shiny Windows games under our beloved Linux.
I think the most notable thing though with the updates to DXVK for us, at least in our
opinion, is the implementation of shared fences, which is required for getting videos to work
within the Halo Infinite Windows game, which is very popular right now. But Halo isn't
the only game that's going to benefit from the updates. It is getting all of the attention
and the headlines right now because it's like the big title. But DXVK 1.10.3 also fixes
a regression that caused rendering issues in all Direct3D11 games, such as Wes's beloved
Ninja Blade and Need for Speed 3. You can find my review of the Steam Deck in episode
467 of Linux Unplugged. Yeah, we got them links in the notes.
Debconf 22 in Kosovo recently wrapped up and Lenovo's Mark Pearson, who leads the company's
Linux initiatives, talked in person about their 2022 platform support for Linux and
their progress over the past year.
And kind of right off the bat, Mark kind of makes it clear that 2021 was a rough year
for Lenovo's Linux team, with multiple problems hitting them kind of all at once. He said
Lenovo's Linux engineers were just challenged with one problem after another, like refresh
problems with the OLED displays, Wi-Fi changes, Intel networking driver issues, AMD power
problems that had to be sorted out, and of course, NVIDIA driver issues that caused the
laptops to fail, energy certifications, and then on top of all of that, the dreaded supply
chain shortages that hit everybody.
But it seems like their luck may be turning around in 2022. And Mark pointed out that
there are now over 36 Lenovo systems certified to run Linux in 2022.
I listen to quite a few Linux podcasts and talk to a lot of people and there was quite
a bit of sort of like Lenovo's giving up on Linux with some of the comments that I heard
last year that really isn't true. And if you're interested, I can explain what happened last
year and last year was rough. But yeah, we are still the Lenovo Linux team is very busy.
So I actually thought, I hope I'm not gonna get into trouble for this, but I thought I'd
actually put up some of what we do just so you can sit there and go, yeah, they do not.
So we actually have 36 plus platforms and I put them on the side there. They're roughly
so Intel ones, AMD and workstation, a mix of them, but I put them separately. Not in
the list is we also have ThinkCenter platforms. Previously, I've never really talked about
ThinkCenter because they were not doing Linux properly, but they are now. They are putting
firmware on LVFS, doing all the right things.
And that is excellent news indeed. He also told the conference attendees that Lenovo
continues building closer relationships with the OEM hardware vendors with aims to improve
Linux support and compatibility, which thankfully was one thing that did not seem to slow down
in 2021.
You know, I think the entire talk is worth a listen. It's about 45 ish minutes long
and in there it gives you insights into just how hard it is to make hardware. That's always
worth kind of reminding ourselves, but also I feel like you get insights into what is
really different about building hardware to run Linux versus building hardware to run
Windows and the different processes involved for drivers and hardware fixes. I found that
to be particularly fascinating and yes, we got a link in the show notes.
Recently we told you about a Fedora change proposal to officially support the Raspberry
Pi 4, including full accelerated graphics. Well, this week the Fedora Engineering and
Steering Committee signed off on this now official support for the Pi 4.
For a bit of background, up to now the Raspberry Pi 4 really hasn't been a significant focus
of the Fedora workstation due to various patches not being upstreamed. Most notably of course
waiting on the open source 3D graphics bits to make it upstream in the kernel. But now
that those bits are finally coming together, work begins on Fedora 37 to support the Raspberry
Pi 4 Model B, the Raspberry Pi 400 and the Raspberry Pi CM4 Compute Module.
Linode.com slash LAN. Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and you
go there to support the show. Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting with the best support
in the business. Real humans all day, every day that can help you. Linode is how we run
everything that we've built in the last few years in the cloud. And like us, Linode
loves Linux. They use it every day throughout the company, throughout their environment
and they build it into their tools. You can really tell as a Linux user, it's a company
that gets Linux. That was the base that they used to build Linode nearly 19 years ago and
today nobody has them matched. And the great thing is they're 30 to 50% cheaper than the
hyperscalers that just want to lock you into their platforms and are always trying to upsell
you on their next thing. They've always got a fancy name for all those crazy things
too.
But on top of all of that, Linode has the best performance and they've got 11 data
centers for you to choose from with great features like object storage, cloud firewall
backups, Kubernetes and Terraform support and a lot more. But really I think the best
way to see it is to try it yourself. As they used to say, go kick the tires, go build something,
go learn something, try it yourself and see what I've been talking about. So go to linode.com
slash lan, get that $100 for 60 days on a new account and really try it. That's linode.com
slash lan.
And a big thank you to Kalyde for making this episode possible. Kalyde.com slash lan. Kalyde
is an endpoint security solution that uses the most powerful untapped resource in IT
into users. When you're trying to achieve security goals, maybe for a third party audit
or your own compliance standards, the conventional wisdom has been to treat every device like
Fort Knox loaded up with software and policies. Old school device management tools like MDMs,
they force disruptive agents onto your machines, onto your devices. They slow down performance
and they treat privacy as a bolted on afterthought. And it really tends to drive users nuts. It
turns IT admins and users into enemies. Plus they really create their own security problems
often and you kind of almost have like shadow IT people in the organization trying to make
it all work. It's just a mess. Kalyde does things differently. Instead of forcing changes
on users, Kalyde sends them security recommendations via Slack. Kalyde will automatically notify
your team when their device might be insecure and it'll give them step-by-step instructions
on how to solve whatever the problem might be. And by reaching out to employees via friendly
Slack DM and then educating them about the company policies, well Kalyde can help you
build a culture where everyone is contributing to security because everyone understands how
and why to do it. They get the reasons for the policies. And for IT admins, well Kalyde
provides a single dashboard that lets you monitor the security of your entire fleet.
Whether they're running on a Mac, Windows, or you bet, Linux as well. You can see at
a glance which employees have their disks encrypted, their OS up to date, and a password
manager installed. That makes it easy to prove compliance to auditors, customers, or leadership.
So that's Kalyde, user-centered cross-platform endpoint security for teams that Slack. You
can meet your compliance goals by putting users first. Visit Kalyde.com slash LAN to
find out how. And if you go there, they'll hook you up with a goody bag which includes
a free t-shirt just for activating a free trial. So it's Kalyde.com slash LAN. That's
K-O-L-I-D-E.com slash L-A-N.
Linux 5.19 was released this week after a one-week delay to deal with the fallout from
the retbleed mitigations. Work on 5.19 was contributed to by 2,086 developers. That's
a new record, beating the 2,062 developers who contributed to the 5.13 cycle. Of those
developers, 278 made their very first kernel contribution, which is always wonderful to
see.
As for the release in its totality, Linus referred to it lovingly, we assume, as quote,
a mixed bag of various odds and ends.
An odds and sods release, it truly, truly was. But there's some interesting data in
here that LWN pulled out. We'll link to it. The top contributors for this release has
been changing over the last few releases, and AMD's growing Linux team is really coming
in at the top of the list now by a pretty big margin. AMD accounted for 37.9% of the
lines of code changed in this release of the Linux kernel, followed by Intel and then Lenovo
at 6.5% and 4.9% respectively, and then Meta coming in at third place with 4.3% of the
lines of code changed in Linux 5.19.
There is some odds and sods notable features in here. Z-standard compression for firmwares
here. That seems to be spreading everywhere throughout Linux these days, and it just offers
space savings when you're trying to get the most you can out of a firmware, perhaps on
an IoT device. Laptops equipped with Intel's Skylake through Comet Lake chips are going
to run cooler. You're going to have better battery life after this update. That's always
nice. And then the Apple M1 NVMe controller and Apple eFuses driver have also been merged
into 5.19.
And speaking of that shiny new Apple hardware, perhaps one of the more notable things about
this latest release is that Linus released it from an ARM MacBook, writing in the announcement
quote,
On a personal note, the most interesting part here is that I did the release and am writing
this on an ARM64 laptop.
It's something I've been waiting for for a long time, and it's finally reality, thanks
to the Asahi team. We've had ARM64 hardware around running Linux for a long time, but
none of it has really been usable as a development platform until now.
It's the third time I'm using Apple hardware for Linux development. I did it many years
ago for PowerPC development on a PPC970 machine, and then a decade plus ago when the MacBook
Air was the only real thin and light around.
And now, as an ARM64 platform.
Not that I've used it for any real work, I literally have only been doing test builds
and boots and now the actual release tagging.
But I'm trying to make sure the next time I travel, I can travel with this as a laptop,
and finally dogfooding the ARM64 side too.
And the ARM64 Linux community celebrated around the world with that news, and the Asahi project
on Twitter confirmed that Linus is using an M2 MacBook Air running the ARM64 build of
Fedora.
Linus, of course, uses his own kernel builds with the Asahi branch merged in. If you're
curious how he did that, the Asahi Linux documentation actually has a list of guides for most likely
your favorite distro. We'll have a link to that in the notes.
But I should probably make it clear, it's still not daily driver. It's at a stage where
it's totally worth investing your time and energy into make things work and make them
better. And if you are up for that, I say go for it. But just be aware, it's not quite
daily driver for the rest of us.
Don't worry though, we'll be keeping our eye on it, testing it, playing with it, and let
you know when it seems ready to use, at least to us.
Also interesting for those of us who follow these kinds of nerdy things, Linus stated
that 5.19 might be the end of the 5 series kernel, writing quote, I'll likely call it
6.0, since I'm starting to worry about getting confused by big numbers again.
He always does this. I swear from like the early Linux 2 years, he was he was just kind
of, I think, shocked by the big reaction to big changes. And I don't know, maybe I'm maybe
I'm making something out of nothing here. But it seems like he always does this. Oh,
it's no big deal. I'm just changing the version number because it's a big number. And I kind
of love that he always claims that because I bet it is partially true. I kind of believe
it to a degree.
But it also just happens that the next version of the Linux kernel, whatever version number
you give it, is going to be a whopper of a new release. I mean, we've got new IOU ring
features in there that the enterprise is clamoring for. There's more improvements to the Apple
SOC support that's going to make it even better for Linus himself. There's a really good chance
the real time preempt RT patches land in this next release. And there's been significant
plumbing for RISC-V improvements for Docker workloads, as well as those XFS improvements
we told you about recently are going to land. And then quite possibly the most notable thing
is that Rust support we've been talking about for what seems like 100 years might actually
land in this next release. So all of that might actually warrant a bigger than normal
version number bump. I don't know. Just my opinion, though. We'll see because he said
likely, and Linus gets to do whatever he wants. So as always, we'll keep an eye on that kernel
team and we'll keep you posted on what actually ships. So don't miss a single episode. Be
sure you go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact to let us know what nickname you think Linus should
give to this next release.
And don't miss this Friday's Office Hours. It's a spicy one that we want you to hear.
Or you can go catch it right now unedited on Jupiter.Tube.
As for this show, well, we'll be back next week with our take on the latest Linux and
open source news.
Thanks for joining us. That's all the news for this week.