Welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on the free and open source world. This is
episode one, recorded May 14th, 2017. I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hey Joe, happy Mother's Day.
Oh yeah, it's Mother's Day in America, not in England though.
No, but I just felt like I should just wish you a happy Mother's Day for our first episode.
Fair enough.
We have so many interesting stories this week, we couldn't have picked a better week to start.
And I think maybe what might be one of our largest stories for a while is what's happening
at Canonical. And this week, Mark Shuttleworth, in an interview at OpenStack Summit, talked
about Canonical's path to an IPO. And this could be a massive shift for Canonical, Joe.
Well, this already is that we've seen it over the last few weeks, haven't we? And as you
say, this is the perfect time to start the show because this is, I would say, probably
the biggest story in Linux for five years, maybe longer than that.
You know, Joe, I think people don't realize how big of a story this is yet because things
are still transitioning. There's some things that are still happening that haven't fully
clicked into place yet. And it's going to be a massive shift for this company, a massive
shift for the Linux desktop. And if Canonical goes for the IPO, that means a big shift in
what the company focuses on. It's going to be less altruistic type things and more does
this make a profit type things.
Well, yeah, this whole idea that they were this family, it wasn't a proper company, was
it? It was this kind of super happy fun time FOSS family that was, you know, made a few
pounds here and there, but wasn't too bothered about it and was interested in software freedom.
Whereas now, it seems like Shuttleworth has just realized that he's not going to make
money from the desktop. The desktop is not going to be a success financially. And he's
just decided to cash out by the sounds of things.
I don't I don't know if I don't know if that's true. I actually would I would actually disagree
with you just to a bit. I think it's ironically the desktops probably making Canonical more
revenue right now than it ever has. Based on my conversations with Mr. Barton George
at Dell, they're seeing 100% year over year growth on those desktops. And to the point
where in India and China, half the machines sold are running Ubuntu. It's and here's
the thing, Joe, I don't know any of the details. But according to Barton, every single one
of those machines has a support contract paid by Dell to Canonical.
Right. So there is revenue coming in there. So therefore, you have to ask yourself, why
are they abandoning Unity? Okay, you can see why they abandoned Unity 8 and convergence
because that wasn't making them any money. But Unity 7 on the desktop is making the money.
So why are they making the shift to GNOME?
I think it's pretty clear that there was a realization at the upper levels of Canonical
that they weren't going to change anyone's mind. I think that's an exasperation we're
seeing. It's an exasperation. All right, you know what we're going to do, we're just going
to disengage and just make let this make money. In fact, Joe, in some ways, it's it's parallel
to what Apple is doing with the Macs. They're just sitting there in milking an existing
market while they focus on the things that make money, iOS, iPhone, services, things
like that. Canonical is going to do the same thing. They're going to ship a desktop, and
they may even invest some time and engineering into it. But it's not going to be their own
whole creation like it was in the past. Instead, they're going to spend their time innovating
on things like snap packages, things that they can do to be more competitive in open
stack space, things that they can do to be more competitive in containers in the cloud,
they're going to double down on LXD, those areas where they're making money, IoT, that's
going to be what they focus on. And they're just going to sit here and bring revenue in
from the desktop, and they're going to ship a no just a vanilla gnome desktop. That's my
cynical view of it.
Well, yeah, basically, they're abandoning the desktop to the community. Meanwhile, they're
going to still make some revenue off it by the sounds of things. And why bother to spend
valuable resources on an engineering team for the desktop when Ubuntu gnome is doing
it for free for you when you can just co-opt them? That mean you talked about being cynical.
I mean, how is that for cynical?
Oh, geez. Yeah. Although, did you see that before all of this big news about dropping
unity and switching to gnome came down? Did you see that? I think it was Dustin Kirkland.
I might be wrong on the attribution, but I'm pretty sure it was Dustin that went on Hacker
News and started a thread asking the always interactive folks over at hackernews.com what
they wanted from the Ubuntu desktop. And on the top of the list is just ship us a standard
gnome desktop. Did you see that?
Yeah, that was interesting timing, wasn't it? That they basically just said ship Gnome
and Wayland. And that's exactly what canonical turnaround and did well announced they were
going to do about a week later.
It's almost like they were putting feelers out there to see how people would react.
They surely must have made the decision before that.
I completely agree. But I wouldn't be surprised if it wasn't just a let's double check the
temperature of the market before we make this announcement.
Yeah, yeah, maybe they were checking that people weren't saying, oh, we want unity eight
finish unity eight, get it out the door. Whereas it seems that at least with, okay, it's a
very specific part of the desktop users Hacker News, at least they want just standard gnome.
And well, that's what they're going to get.
Well, Joe, can I float another idea past you too? So when we look at that Hacker News discussion
thread, which got a ton of traction, and we look at who's buying Dell Sputnik laptops,
and we look at who's buying Galago Pros, I think a large selection of them are that quote
unquote, web developer, that developer who wants to run on their laptop the same environment
they run in production. And that's why bash on Windows doesn't work for them, because
it needs to be exactly what they run in production. It really does make a difference. It really
makes a difference for these people. And so for them, they're buying up these Sputnik
laptops like crazy. And they're buying they're looking at system, system 76 machines and
entryware machines with an entirely new set of interests now. And you have to wonder if
these if these manufacturers aren't coming to canonical and saying, I need to plan the
next year of products. And this Unity eight stuff you haven't you haven't shipped anything
mirror hasn't shipped. I mean, it's shipped, but it's just been in testing, like Unity
eight isn't ready yet. We need to plan our products we have, we have to plan things out
8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 18 months in advance. And right now, we're seeing demand for the gnome
desktop. The fedora distribution can deliver that open Sousa can deliver that canonical,
we want to work with you. But we're kind of we're a little hesitant about your path in
your future. What do you have for us? Because the reason why I say that Joe is I saw a lot
of machines at Dell running the gnome desktop, they weren't necessarily running Unity seven,
it seems to be that there is a lot of momentum there. And so you think that that's why they
have decided to finally kill unity then because they they've got this pressure from the OEM
saying to them, people don't like unity, they want just standard stuff like gnome that you
can get on all the other distros. Because one thing about Unity seven was, it wasn't
very portable, was it? You kind of could run it on arch if you really wanted to, but you
couldn't run it on any of the other distros. Whereas now, if you look at what's probably
going to be stock Ubuntu and stock fedora, and the grown version of open Sousa, you've
got a unified experience across those.
Yeah, and I think a really inconvenient thing happened along the way to mobile is the desktop
actually started getting some traction. Inconveniently, while canonical was focusing on building
a great mobile experience, the desktop actually started making the company a significant amount
of money. And so recently, what from what I can tell, it seems like they got really
serious about unity eight on the desktop, but it was just too little too late. The the
vendors, I believe, want something today. The the Linux end users that are developing
on Linux and deploying in the cloud, they want something today. And we're not we're
not really ready to wait around. In the meantime, it's not like MacBooks. And it's not like
Windows 10 is sitting around both of them are getting better. And they're adding features
that are more appealing to this to this particular developer market.
Well, you say that the desktop was starting to gain traction there. Could that be because
unity seven was mature, it was stable, it was working fine. And okay, I've never been
a fan of it. But I speak to people who are and they say, okay, early on, it was a bit
ropey, didn't work too well. Whereas towards the end now, in well, people who are using
1604 are happily using it. It's very, very stable. I mean, I saw poppy saying that gnome
shell is crashing on him. And it used to unity would crash maybe once a month, whereas he's
had like two or three crashes a day with gnome.
It's funny. It's gnome three has just started crashing on me on our OBS machine that we
have here in the studio in the last couple of days. I don't know why. But all of a sudden,
every few hours, it just reloads.
Why the hell would you use gnome on such critical infrastructure as the OBS machine surely should
be using XFC or LXD. So it's, you know, all the resources.
Well, because unlike you, I try to skate to where the pucks gonna be. So that way I have
very informed commentary right here on the show. So I live and breathe the gnome three
desktop because let's be honest, that's where that that's where everybody's going. And I
don't stay on XFC island like you do, Joe. I don't like XFC. I want the real desktop.
I want the current desktop. I want when I say people should try Linux, I want the experience
that they're going to get Joe.
Well, yeah, that's why you can maybe use that on your laptop. But on critical infrastructure,
man, I would not be using something as heavy as gnome.
To tell you the truth, Joe, I can't really argue with you right now, because you're right.
But I think it's sort of a deep irony, if you're also right about why, why maybe it's
just getting successful right now is because of unity seven, I disagree with that premise.
I don't think it's unity seven that's making the Linux desktop take off right now for these
particular web dev type customer base, or whatever. I don't mean to categorize it as
just web devs. But you have to understand that I've been talking to these companies,
and that's who they're focusing at. And that's where they're actually seeing a lot of sales.
And you know what they're doing, Joe, they're using the command line, they don't care what
the UI is, they don't care if it's unity, they don't care if it's gnome, as long as
they get a terminal, as long as they get Docker, as long as they get git and all of the same
tools, they're happy. And it sort of doesn't matter. It doesn't matter how much time and
effort canonical puts into unity eight, it doesn't matter if they keep unity seven going
for the next 15 years. And it doesn't really matter if they just ship stock, no, because
the reality is, everybody's just using the terminal, everybody's just using sublime text
or atom or Visual Studio code or them. And it doesn't matter. And imagine if you could
have all that stuff and your games as well. All the triple a title games on the same operating
system. Oh, that would be super tempting. In fact, that would be so tempting. If there
was something like that out there, Joe, I may never switch to another operating system.
Hmm, yeah. I wonder if Microsoft maybe have thought of that. Hey, yeah, this was some
big news from build conference this year. So last year, Microsoft announced the ability
to run the Ubuntu environment like a bath shell on Windows. Now this year at build 2017,
they have announced they're also bringing Sousa and Fedora. And along with that, they're
also putting Ubuntu Fedora and Sousa in the Windows Store. So it's just like an app you
install now from the Windows Store. And Bob's your uncle, you've got Linux right there on
your Windows box. This will be coming in the fall Creators Update. What do you think, Joe?
Well, I think what is key here is the fact that they're going to be in the Windows Store,
which means that it's going to be on Windows 10 S, which is the lockdown one they're trying
to sell to students because they realize that these students are going to need Linux. I
mean, Microsoft has long since accepted, Microsoft loves Linux and all that stuff. They've long
since accepted that in the cloud, Linux has won, but they don't want to lose the desktop
because that's basically what they're hanging on to. I mean, they've got Azure and everything,
but the desktop and Office and that's a big part of their business model. And so they
don't want to lose it. And this is their way of doing that. They're incorporating what
is effectively Linux, even though it's not Linux, is it? Because there's no Linux kernel,
it's everything, it's sort of all the GNU stuff and all that. And they just want to
keep people on Windows as much as possible. And you have to say it's a very smart play
by them.
Finally, finally, I can use proper NTFS with Linux, finally. I have to tell you, I have
to tell you if I was stuck on Windows, like say I worked at a company that required Windows
for some sort of network reason or for other reasons, I would be very thankful for this
feature. And I'm very impressed that Microsoft is willing to do this. It does sort of alarm
me a bit that it makes it less enticing to switch away. But I go back to, it truly makes
a difference that you run on your test and dev machine, which you run in production.
And so while it's cute and handy, and it makes Cygwin look like a product of the past, I
don't really fear this. I don't really fear this.
You hate it.
Yeah, I don't. I tell you why, Joe. The problem is Windows 10. It really is shit, Joe. And
I'm not just saying that because I like Linux. I recently tried it out again when I was testing
out different video editors, and I had it on a 4K display. It's a joke, Joe. It's a
real joke. It is laughable. When Apple ships a high DPI product, the entire operating system
and all of the applications are high DPI because they control it all. Okay, I grok that. When
Linux ships a high DPI product, some things that are GTK3 or QT5 look great in high DPI.
And I understand why some things that are maybe older like your XFCE desktop look like
total arse. But when Microsoft ships a high DPI desktop, their own stuff, like their own
management interface is mixed. They have multiple control panels. They have 10 different ways
to do things. They're bundling Cortana like it's going out of style. They have new ways
of invading your privacy. In fact, one of my favorite ones is you can turn off ad personalization,
but you cannot actually turn off ads in your start menu. And when you turn off ad personalization,
it warns you and it says, by the way, you will still see ads. They just won't be personalized.
That kind of stuff, Joe, the reason why I mentioned it is because it is the little things
that grate against people's nerves that does compel them to buy a machine running Linux
or to try installing Linux on their machine. And so while this stuff is great, and if I
was stuck in a Windows world, I absolutely would use this. And I'm impressed that Microsoft's
doing it. As a Linux user, I'm a little underwhelmed. First of all, is it SUSE? Is it open SUSE?
Is it version, is it LEAP? Is it, what is it? And which version of Fedora is it? Is
it Fedora 25? Is it Fedora 24? Is it Fedora Atomic? Is it Fedora Cloud based on version
24? There's no information here. And one other thing I'll just happen to say is the day that
Microsoft announced Ubuntu running on Windows, there were folks at Canonical that had the
entire blog post up on how all of it works, about how they packaged it up, about the testing
they did, about how the performance works. So as somebody who wanted to use this in production
potentially, I totally grokked how it worked, how it worked for me, and what the potential
limitations are. There has been nothing from SUSE or Fedora.
Why do you suppose that is then? Do they just not really care about it? If Microsoft said
to them, we want to use, you know, SUSE and we want to use Fedora with this Linux, Windows
subsystem for Linux, and they've just said, yeah, okay, whatever, use it. And just they
don't really give a shit about that.
To be honest, I can't tell because in one sense, it could be good. Maybe they've modified
the subsystem for Linux in such a way that any distro is possible, and so they just put
these distros on there. Or they did, they worked directly with these different distributions
and they're just choosing not to promote it because maybe some of them came out and shit
all over Canonical in the past when they announced this feature. I don't know if you recall that,
but there were folks that came out of the woodwork and shamed Canonical for doing this.
And now some of those same people helped enable it for their distribution.
Yeah, I mean, I would have thought that the licensing would mean that you'd have to kind
of do a deal, wouldn't you? I don't suppose they could just ship it in Windows.
The trademarking alone, right? You would think that the trademarking alone would be enough
that they'd have to work out some sort of deal. But they're saying SUSE, so maybe it's
SUSE Enterprise, which at that point, how many of you out there have SUSE Enterprise
on your VPS? Raise your hand. Oh, none of you. Oh, okay. Well, how many of you have
Fedora? Oh, okay. Yeah.
Fedora is available for digital ocean, isn't it? I'm sure some people are using it.
What do you think, though, of the joke I've seen passed around online now that it's truly
the year of the Linux desktop because you can now run Linux on Windows? Does that sting?
It's kind of true, isn't it? Yeah. You've got Chromebooks and these Windows S laptops
covering a Windows 10 S, which are both basically Chromebook type devices, both of them running,
well, one actually Linux and one everything but Linux. And so it kind of is really the
year of Linux on a desktop, but just not as we thought it would be.
I would put it differently. I would say it's the year of the Linux runtime. It's the year
of the Linux runtime. And I think that's actually part of why our show is important because
Linux now runs everywhere. As a developer, you can write for Linux now and you can run
it on BSD. You can run it, of course, on Linux servers, which are the predominant web servers
on the web. You can run it now on Windows. You can run it in virtualization. You can
run it in Docker. It's truly the universal platform that doesn't have some crazy runtime
around it.
Yeah, I think that's fair to say.
It's kind of amazing. Welcome to 2017, everybody, where Microsoft is shipping Fedora, SUSE, and
Ubuntu in the Windows store, in the Windows App Store.
Crazy.
I want to take a moment and thank Ting for sponsoring this episode, our first episode
of Linux Action News. Do me a favor and go to last.ting.com. It's a little retro and
it's a little awesome, las.ting.com. It's a smarter way to do mobile and if you go to
that URL, you'll save some money. What I love about Ting, I've been a customer for more
than two and a half years, it's just pay for what you use wireless. And when I say this,
it sounds like, oh, geez, Chris, that's a really neat idea. There must be a trick. And
to some people, those would be people that live in the United States. And then there's
a group of people like a lot of you outside the United States that go, well, isn't that
kind of how, that's how my mobile works, Chris.
You see, if the U.S. were to hit reset on the mobile market today, the Ting model would
be the dominant model because it truly empowers the customer. If you've got Wi-Fi, there's
no sense in paying for gigs and gigs and gigs and gigs of data. There's no reason to use
that if you only need your data when you're driving from home to work or something like
that. Same with calls. Now that Telegram has calling, I'm never making a phone call again.
Now that the Echo has calling, I'm never making a phone call again. So why pay for minutes?
You think I'm kidding. I'm not. Find out more by going to last.ting.com. They've got a brand
new website. It looks super slick. It's pay for what you use wireless. And one of the
other things that's cool, and I mentioned this because we kind of have, you'd be surprised,
we kind of have a geeky audience. I know. I know. I wouldn't have thought so either.
But it turns out we do. And so they understand that there's CDMA and GSM. At least here in
the States, we've got both of them. We're maniacs like that. And on the Ting network,
you can choose either one that's better in your area. Maybe one's better for calls. Maybe
one's better for data. Or maybe one just makes you feel like a baller. Find out more by going
to last.ting.com. They've got a bunch of great features, a great dashboard, and more. But
I want you to take this away. It's $6 for the line, and then just your usage on top
of that. last.ting.com. And a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Action News.
Just a quick headline for you guys this week. The OpenWRT and the LEED, our LEDE project,
have agreed on a peace plan. I didn't realize that there was a split happening here, but
I guess a set of core developers went off and started their own project from OpenWRT.
So you didn't know about this either. I kind of felt a bit stupid reading about this. I
should have known about it.
No, I did not. And I guess things have actually worked out for the better. Some of the core
developers are coming back. They're going to use the LEDE project as sort of the base,
but they're going to keep the OpenWRT branding. It's sort of a kumbaya, Joe. So look forward
to better firmwares on your edge devices soon. Speaking of edge devices, Google in Android
O is finally going to solve a major issue with Android. But I suppose, Joe, the question
is, does it go far enough?
No, in a word. It solves one of three problems, doesn't it? With the whole updating Android
situation where, first of all, you have to deal with the silicon manufacturers. So usually
Samsung or Qualcomm. So you have to deal with them first. Then you have to deal with the
actual phone manufacturers. And then you have to deal with the carriers. So you've got these
three steps that have to be dealt with before you can push out an over-the-air update. And
so Project Treble is going to make that a little bit easier because it's basically separating
the first layer of that off. So the code coming from the silicon manufacturers can stay the
same. And then everything on top of that can change.
Another way to frame that would be, now the silicon manufacturers don't have to be bothered
before everybody else in the stack can do an Android update.
Well, yeah, which is good. It's definitely a step forward. There's no doubt about it.
One of the things I didn't realize was such an issue, but apparently it's a big issue
in the Android ecosystem, is Qualcomm only certifies updating their chips, the drivers
for it and firmwares and whatnot for two years. Two years. And then, sorry, we're all done.
Well, that two-year cycle is basically the standard cycle in mobile, isn't it? Because
after two years, you've upgraded your phone, in theory.
In theory. Meanwhile, iOS devices, see, here's why I disagree with that. I disagree with
that because they get passed down. Like, especially in families, you pass your devices down, they
become gaming devices. They're still on the network. They still have your personal information
on them. In some cases, now they're used by children. So that's why iOS devices with a
five-year support cycle are much better for families where they want to do a pass down
thing.
Yeah. And if you just want to buy, I mean, buying an iPhone is an expensive endeavor
and buying a Pixel phone is an expensive endeavor if you buy it outright and not through your
carrier, right? And so you want to make that investment work. You want to be able to use
it for several years, not just like two years or even less than that if you've only bought
it like halfway through the cycle.
Right. And the Pixel is one of the first devices. In fact, if you already have the Android O
developer preview, you already have this, in theory. Also, I think it's worth mentioning,
this doesn't solve the carrier problem or the OEM problem, which I think is the core
problem. If the OEMs like Samsung or LG or HTC were truly motivated to support these
devices for longer, something tells me that that would be worked into their contract with
Qualcomm. They would be pressuring the devices manufacturers. They would be working on the
software stack. There's been no motivation at the hardware manufacturer layer for the
entire time of Android, which is a core problem because they want you to buy new devices.
Same at the carrier level. Here, at least in the States, it's within their best interest
for you to buy new devices. All the carriers now are offering plans where you just pay
a monthly price. Lease that phone, friend. Lease that phone and every 18 months you get
a brand new phone. Just keep upgrading, my friend, and then we can push you new services,
new network features, all kinds of upsell services that make them lots of money and
help them brand the device. So it's in everybody's interest to have you buy new devices.
Yeah. And can I point out a potential problem here? It's only a potential problem, but if
you are leaving the code from the silicon manufacturers there untouched, well that doesn't
necessarily help you in terms of security because what if there are zero days or whatever
found in that code? And if Qualcomm have decided that they're not supporting it anymore, then
yeah, okay, you can go and upgrade the Android stack and make that more secure. But if the
fundamental code run in the silicon has got vulnerabilities that are not being patched,
then this doesn't help that either.
I would say stay tuned. Another shoe could drop at Google IO on May 17th. May 17th through
the 19th is Google IO. So it's coming up very soon. This is sort of like a pre-announcement
and we could hear other parts that make it all click at Google IO. So that has to be
kept in mind. But right now, this is only step one in a three-step process. And in some
sense, Joe, it really doesn't make any sense unless you consider where Google may be going
with things like Project Fuchsia.
Yeah, exactly. So Project Fuchsia is their backup plan, I suppose, their mobile backup
plan, which is a completely different OS. It doesn't use Linux. It doesn't have the
Java virtual machine. It doesn't have all of the baggage of Android.
Right. It's licensed under BSD clause 3, MIT, and Apache 2.0. No GPL.
Exactly. Right. Which is something that Google, I mean, they've never been a huge fan of the
GPL. Let's face it. So the OS is called Fuchsia and the kernel is called Magenta and the kernel
is MIT licensed. And so this has been around for quite a while, but it's caused a bit of
a stir in the last week because of a demo that has surfaced with a UI called Armadillo,
which you can actually run on Android. And it's not complete at all, is it? I mean, it's
basically a skeleton of UI at this stage, but it does show that Google have not forgotten
about Fuchsia. Google are still working on it. And it's going to be open source, but
it's going to be that different kind of open source, isn't it, than Linux? It's going to
be the permissively licensed open source, which is better for, well, it's an easier
sell, isn't it, for big business.
It's corporate empire friendly. And when you look at this, it's really a landing spot for
some of their favorite projects. Dart is in on this thing to give you high-performance
graphics. They have Vulkan for the rendering. They have Escher, which is volumetric soft
shadows for some of their UI stuff. This is high-end GUI stuff. It's like their fantasy
project stuff. Now, all of this is neat and interesting. And with Google, some of this
stuff could go nowhere. They often launch products that compete with each other. Like
for years, the conversation is, well, Android and Chrome merge because they seem to be competing.
That's not unusual for Google. When you look at Project Treble and consider Fuchsia, it
could be that Treble would allow them to abstract away the hardware stuff, abstract away the
hardware drivers, and move over to Fuchsia without a whole bunch of device problems.
So at least Google's own devices, like the Pixel, maybe a Nexus device, could run Fuchsia.
But what about the problem of applications? I mean, that's always been the problem with
these new Linux-based operating systems, right, for the mobile. They don't have that wealth
of apps. I mean, there are millions and millions or a billion apps or whatever it is available
for Android. They're going to have to either convince everyone to rewrite their app to
work with Fuchsia, or they're going to have to write some sort of compatibility layer.
I hope it's the first one. I hope people...
So do I.
You know, wouldn't that be great if Android apps were all of a sudden 120 frames per second
just flying around and had great graphics and just loaded really smooth?
I mean, we have...
And didn't crash all the time.
Right. I mean, we have supercomputers in these phones, at least compared to when I was growing
up and now looking at these devices. I don't understand why they're so slow.
Yeah.
So Fuchsia, it feels like one of these fascinating Skunk Works projects, but we don't really...
At least I won't speak for you, Joe, but I don't really have any expectations it's going
to go anywhere.
I do. I do think it is going to go somewhere because that's how Google does things. They
always hedge their bets, don't they? They will never just have one product for things
or very, very seldom. And eventually one will win out and they'll kill the other one. But
I mean, just look at their messaging fiasco at the moment. How many ways have you got
to send someone a message through Google?
Oh, you're getting me worked up right now just thinking about it. Yeah. Allo, you have
Allo, Duo, Hangouts, of course. I mean, there's so many. Yeah. And then of course there's
Google Doc Chat. Yeah. Yeah. And you know, maybe, maybe something will be announced next
week, or this week, May 17th. Maybe something will be announced at Google IO Keynote. They'll
just be unbelievable. I don't really expect that you and I are going to talk a lot about
mobile and Android on this show. This is go figure as we're launching the show. This is
the big news right now. So we're talking about it now, but I don't know, Joe. I think down
the road you and I probably won't be talking about it much. That's my instinct. I could
be totally wrong. And of course this is going to be the week that will prove me wrong.
I don't know, man. I have to disagree with that. The way I see it, the desktop, okay,
it's never going to go away. Of course, you're always going to have people using it on the
desktop, be it Windows, Mac OS or Linux, hopefully. But we have seen the growth of mobile and
it's not going away. And hopefully Linux is going to continue to be a big part of that.
But I think that while people are primarily using Android devices or mobile devices at
least, we've got to talk about that. We can't ignore the reality that desktop Linux like
desktop computing generally is on the wane.
It hurts, but I think you're right. I have more and more people in my personal life that
when they go home, they don't have a computer. They just use their mobile device.
Well, you're talking to one of them now, Chris, I'm afraid. Yeah, seriously. Okay. I have
my desktop, I have a ton of laptops, but my primary device is my Android phone running
Lineage on this, because it's always with me.
You want to know something funny? My middle child, Abigail, this weekend said to us, how
come you guys don't have to pay for your home? And we said, what do you mean? We pay for
our home? No, no. When my mommy pays for home, she uses her computer, but you don't have
a computer here. So you don't pay for your home. And we said, no, trust us. We pay, we
just don't use a computer to do it. And that's when I realized, yeah, most of the time when
I'm at home, there's not even, there might be a laptop in a bag somewhere, but there's
no computer set up at home anymore on it on when I'm at home and I'm not working anymore
because I have, I have connectivity on my television. I have my phone, I have tablets.
So Joe, while I want to sit here and disagree with you, the reality, even in my own home
would say otherwise. Yep, exactly. Now I would love to hear your thoughts on anything we
talked about or that particular subject. You can go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact
to send us in your feedback or just email us directly news at jupiterbroadcasting.com
or you can tweet us at linuxactionnews.com with stories or feedback. Yeah. And also the
new Jupiter Broadcasting Telegram group. Bit dot L Y slash J B Telegram. Bit dot L Y slash
J B Telegram. We just launched it. We're only telling you guys it's a Linux action news
secret bit dot L Y slash J B Telegram. If you want to get on the official Jupiter Broadcasting
Telegram group and there is something you can do to help the show out, subscribing your
favorite podcast player. If you or even just a few of you do it this week, it'll help with
discovery because the way it works is they got these crazy python scripts. When you subscribe,
the numbers count up, boop, boop, boop, and even 10, 30, 40 of you do it and we'll move
way up in the charts and people will find this new show. You can actually help us out
this week by subscribing. We have links to all of them and all of the subscription services
at linuxactionnews.com. Maybe not all of them, but pretty close. And you know what, Chris?
The dirty secret of a lot of our listeners is that they use iTunes. What? Yeah. And you
know, even if, even if you don't want to admit it, we won't tell anybody, but there is another
dirty secret. You are our potential white knights. We need them here at the Linux action
news. Of course you can save us by reviewing or rating an iTunes. You actually don't only
juice iTunes for us, but you juice like a dozen other podcast directories who all just
scrape iTunes. That's why iTunes is the bosses. Many, many podcast players, websites and apps
are actually just scraping iTunes. And if you rate and review in there, you can help
us out a bunch and not a lot of you want to even admit to using iTunes. So if you're one
of them, please consider doing it right then. I suppose that'll do it for this episode.
So we'll see you again next Monday. Be sure to go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe
for all of our feed links and thanks for joining us guys. See you later.