Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 233, recorded on March 23, 2022. I'm Chris.
Wes has the week off, so we're just doing a flash update, and let's get into the news.
And we'll start with a follow up that might really be connected to the most important
story in my opinion we covered last year in Linux, and that was the University of Minnesota's
hypocrite commits to the Linux kernel. We initially covered that in Linux Action News
186, and now it seems we're having something of an official response from the kernel team.
The Kernels Technical Advisory Board, TAB for short, has put together a set of guidelines
for researchers who are studying how the kernel development community works or individual
projects. This document that's been created by the TAB has just actually been merged into
the main line of Linux 518, so it's actually going to be baked into the Linux kernel now.
And it's really good to see this, but here's my take on the overall document. I printed
it out, if you can hear it there. And I went through this thing, and you know, it seems
pretty reasonable. It really does kind of just sort of describe itself as a set of best
practices. There's no mechanism to enforce it necessarily. They're sort of appealing
to the researchers' goodwill, I suppose. And it calls these researchers to disclose
to a developer before a developer's project or that individual developer are targeted.
It also asserts that these developers cannot just be targeted without some sort of consent.
And the document outlines what is expected when a researcher submits a patch to the Linux
kernel to fix whatever they might have found. And it's an extensive set of requests and
asks, including in there is if you've never submitted to the Linux kernel before, maybe
have somebody who has look at this first before you send it to us and waste our time. I mean,
they don't say that part, but it's kind of implied.
They also take some effort to link and point to ethics and research papers that have been
published before. And overall, I get it. I like it. I think it's good to see this. And
I think it's great that this actually lives in the Linux kernel. So there really can be
no missing it. I think the linchpin of this is going to be if researchers actually follow
these guidelines. But clearly, if they do, then they could expect probably a more cordial
interaction with the Linux development team than if they don't.
Activists are targeting Russians with what's been dubbed as open source protestware. And
for better or for worse, this is getting some attention thanks to an MIT research review.
They've taken a brief look at what they've dubbed as protestware from open source. And
they have come to some questionable conclusions, I'd argue, but maybe they're not wrong.
This is a quote from from their review. They say, quote, no tech firm has gone this far,
but around two dozen open source software projects have, and they've been spotted adding
code protesting the war. According to observers tracking the protest where movement, the open
source software, or I'm sorry, they say open source software is software that anyone can
modify and inspect, making it more transparent. And in this case, at least, more open to sabotage.
Okay, they might not say it dramatically like that. But they, you know, hey, open source,
it's more open to sabotage. And then they cite a couple of examples that are frankly
hard to argue with. I think the one that they cite that is the most damning is the recent
node IPC update. Node IPC helps you build neural networks. It's downloaded more than
a million times in a week. And it had a quote unquote, a quote unquote, protest update slipped
in there, I guess you could say, one that sort of described itself as a message of peace.
But another that was supposedly hidden in there, watched for the user's IP. And when
it detected a Russian IP, it triggered a script that wiped the user's drives, whatever they
had permission to, it would wipe. And soon after that update was published, a GitHub
post went viral claiming that the code had hit several NGOs that were documenting Russian
war crimes with photos and videos. And this update designed to protest the war ended up
wiping out the NGOs documents. They say that 30,000 messages and files detailing war crimes
committed by Russia and the Ukrainian army and government officials were wiped out. And
it's not even the first time that open source developers have sabotaged software in their
own projects as a bit of a protest. In January, the author of the Colors JS, remember that?
They added that infinite loop to their code that rendered any server that was running
it useless until it was fixed. These are all things that the MIT research paper cites.
And my take on this is that they're not wrong. I don't think it's an issue at scale, but
it's enough of an issue that Pandora's box has now been opened. And there will be some
in business and in institutions that just don't trust open source the same way. And
while right now, today, it's being targeted against a group that we might disagree with,
open source, as you know, is a worldwide phenomenon. And so, by my math, it's just simply inevitable
that we'll find ourselves on the other side of some herd mentality one day. And these
kinds of things, if they become normalized, will likely strike us.
But some good news for at least you Risk 5 fans out there. Potentially great news, really.
Psy5, one of the most ambitious groups behind pushing for the Risk 5 platform, they just
begged another series of funding, $175 million in a series F round. That's a lot of rounds
of funding, but a couple of details came out in this process that overall kind of leave
me feeling pretty good. Psy5 was valued at $2.5 billion in this process. That's no joke.
We've seen companies like Linode recently sell for $900 million, right? So the fact
that Psy5 is valued at $2.5 billion shows you the industry thinks there's some real
potential here.
And overall, when you dig through it, at least the picture that Psy5 is painting, the funding
situation looks pretty good because between some recent money they've raised, some of
which hasn't even kicked in yet, and business revenue is actually doing pretty well too,
they seem to be in good shape. At least, again, according to Psy5.
My take is that it's about time. I mean, really, Psy5 has been around since 2015. They are
core to the RISC-V game, and they've built a growing business out of this thing just
day by day here. So it's really good to see them really getting some momentum now. They
say they need to hire to keep up with all of this, and this funding is going to let
them do this. Get this, though. Psy5 expects to double their 300-person staff in the next
12 to 18 months. That's how they're going to keep up with demand, and that's why they
need the funding. That's amazing. It's actually happening.
With Ubuntu 22.04 just around the corner, it is great to see one major change getting
finished up just before next month's Jellyfish release. So, Ubuntu 22.04 LTS will now default
to using GNOME on Wayland when running the NVIDIA proprietary driver. I can't believe
I just put all those words into a sentence. GNOME, Wayland, on NVIDIA, default. Now, this
is only going to work if you have a card that can take advantage of the NVIDIA 510 series
or newer driver. And if you're already on an AMD or Intel GPU, well, you're already
set. Ubuntu Linux has been defaulting to GNOME on Wayland since 2104 for those of you with
AMD graphics. But this is huge for NVIDIA users that use the proprietary driver, and
it's the result of months of work by Red Hat, Canonical, and of course, NVIDIA. And I'm
talking Zoom meetings or BlueJeans meetings, really, in reality, that went on and on forever
that we'll never really know the full details of how hard people worked behind the scenes
to make this happen. But we do know on NVIDIA's side, they've been working to address bugs
for some time, and really what's helped make all of this possible is their implementation
inside their proprietary driver of the generic buffer manager. Adding that support really
unlocked all this.
Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting. You gotta try it. It's what we've been using
for the last two and a half years to build anything that's audience facing. It's fast
when I say it, I mean it. They've got 40 gigabit connections coming to the hypervisors, MVME
storage for the disk, and AMD EPYC processors when you want something fast. They've been
doing this for nearly 19 years, and it just keeps getting better and better. In particular,
I have to say their object storage has been a lifesaver. Their cloud firewalls make managing
traffic simple, and their interface makes it possible for anyone on our team to deploy
a server. So go try it out for yourself, see why we use Linode for everything. Go to linode.com
slash land, get $100 in 60 day credit, and of course, you support the show.
Linux.ting.com. If you're sick of overpaying for cell service, go support the show and
see how much you could save by going to linux.ting.com. Ting's an MVNO, that means you get access
to the same networks as the big carriers, but with way better customer support at a
lot lower of a cost. They have very simple plans. It's one of the reasons why I've been
a customer since 2013. And their support is the best. That's what they get to focus on.
In fact, Ting was named number one by Consumer Reports in 2021. I mean, there really is no
smarter way to do mobile. You save money, you get better, simpler plans, and access
to the best customer support with no contracts ever. And pretty much any phone is going to
work with Ting because they support multiple networks. And it's super simple to switch.
You can do it all on their website. Just get started at linux.ting.com. But check your
current phone, create an account and pick the plan that's right for you. Ting will
get you going in minutes. Get started, support the show and save 25 bucks at linux.ting.com.
While it's actually happened, the first alpha to get Linux on the M1 Macs has shipped. The
Asahi Linux team and Hector Martin announced this week that they are very excited for the
public alpha to ship. It supports the current range of M1 machines with a few limitations
in there. As we talked about before and prepared you for, there is no accelerated GPU support
at this stage. Things like DisplayPort, Bluetooth, et cetera, they're not working. Some things
like HDMI are hit and miss depending on the machine you're using. And at present, there
is no support for the recently announced Mac Studio. None of that's too surprising. It's
kind of what we expected all across the board. But now that it's actually gotten in the hands
of end users, we're seeing a ton of positive reports. And for a lot of people, it seems
that performance might even be better than expected. Michael Larble over at Ferronix
noted this in his tests, which we'll have linked in the show notes. And he did pages
of tests. But one of the things that stood out to me was this. He says, quote, even with
there being power and performance work still ahead for being able to make the most out
of the M1, these benchmarks with the Mac Mini did genuinely exceed my expectations for this
early alpha state. Running Linux on the M1 MacBooks may be a bit less ideal due to also
having to worry about the battery life and cooling concerns. But at least in the case
of the Mac Mini, this was a great little platform for evaluating the early state of Linux on
Apple Silicon. Now, here's my take, guys. I think what they've done in here is really
clever. Asahi Linux has made it very simple to handle the Mac OS install on the Mac. It
is designed to dual boot that, which I think is very smart in this phase, not only because
Asahi Linux is not fully functional, but even long term, you're going to want that Mac install
to do, I would imagine, firmware updates and things like that that Apple will only make
available through their OS, of course. Right. And I think also I love the choice of fully
embracing the dual boot mindset, because for some people, that's going to be the utility
of these machines. A lot of people got a utility and still do get utility out of dual booting
Linux and Windows. It's the same scenario here. But they've also accounted for those
of us that are just going to want to run Linux full time. There's essentially a minimum viable
Mac option in here where the Asahi Linux installer shrinks the Mac install down and then you
can use the remainder, the bulk of the free space for the Linux install. Right now, Asahi
Linux is really just a brilliant installer that sits on top of a slightly modified version
of Arch. I tell you that so you know what you're getting into, but I also think that's
really smart. Right now, this is for the domain of power users that are probably already comfortable
using Arch Linux. And Arch Linux also means faster software update. So as the team upstreams
driver improvements, you know, when they when they do get when Alyssa gets GPU acceleration
working, or they get Bluetooth working, right, that's going to land upstream first. And that
means it's going to come to Arch first, sort of the same mentality, I think that Valve
had when they released the new deck with Arch, get those upstream improvements onto the hardware
as fast as possible, because it makes the whole system more usable. But I have seen
people out there that are actually doing NixOS, all kinds of different distros, because really
it's it's it's using upstream bits that Asahi Linux is doing here. There's nothing proprietary
to their installer. There does seem to be users discovering that some of Apple's tools
are brittle in all of this. We actually had this bite that bite us on Linux unplugged.
The project is getting reports and we saw it ourselves that the APFS resizers part is
failing, probably due to some other type of file system corruption, either something that
existed ahead of time, or something that the tool is introducing. There is a couple of
options that we found. But if you don't, if you don't know to expect this, it's kind of
a bummer because it breaks the whole installation process. And it leaves you with what appears
to be a corrupted file system. However, in our case, disk first aid managed to just fix
it when we put it off the recovery partition. And other users have reported that they just
had to do a nuke and pave reinstall Mac OS. Not ideal, I grant you. And then they could
proceed. I don't know, but we seem to have our file system problem solved on the MacBook
that we are trying it on. We're going to put Linux on a MacBook Max. And we're going to
give it another go on this coming Sunday's Linux unplugged. So join us live Sunday at
noon Pacific 3pm Eastern at jblive.tv. If you want to see how our Asahi Linux attempt
goes this time, I think it's going to go better now that we fix that file system problem.
It is early days, right? No doubt about it. You got to acknowledge it. The value isn't
there. There's absolutely no reason at this point to go buy a Mac with the intention of
running Linux. That would be a silly thing to do. Don't do what Chris did and some of
his friends. But I see a near future here where I'm going to have a headless, low power
home Linux box running on M1 hardware in my future. This could really bring my home hosting
game to a whole new level. I'm always going for the best performance per watt because
for large portions of the year, my home runs off of solar energy. I have no grid hookup
at all. And so it really makes a difference how much power something draws over the long
haul. And so the M1 hardware has just been extremely attractive to me from a home server,
low power, high performance standpoint. But there's just no way I was going to do with
Mac OS as a server. So to see a saw Linux working on this, I'm extremely excited. GPU
acceleration is still kind of far off in the distance, but that's clearly like the next
major milestone along with some of the other hardware enablement. But it feels like we're
on track here. And now that the public's getting their hands on it, it's going to accelerate
the involvement. It may even accelerate people joining the Patreon and supporting the project.
We'll have to see. We'll keep an eye on this and everything else in the world of free software
and open source. So don't miss a single episode. Go to LinuxActionNews.com slash subscribe for
all the ways to get new episodes. And we'd love your feedback. You can either send us
a boost on a new podcast app that supports boosts or go to the contact page. Old school
LinuxActionNews.com slash contact. And let's hang out. I wanted to let you know we do have
a live stream coming up on March 31st at 4 p.m. in Seattle, 7 p.m. in New York, 11 p.m.
London time. Again, that's March 31st. It's an ask me anything. If you've been having
questions, you got thoughts, concerns, ideas, I don't know. Let me know. Come to the live
stream and let's chat. I also have the mobile room going and I'm going to help people get
Matrix set up because I know the onboarding can be a bit rough, but our Matrix community
is awesome. Decentralized chat is the future and I want to help people get on board. And
speaking of decentralized futures, I'm also giving away some Bitcoin to help you get started
with boosts and value for value. So go get a new podcast app, newpodcastapps.com. I like
Fountain. You need something that has a lightning wallet and I'll be giving away some Bitcoin
to help you get started because I think it is the future of independent media and free
software. Again, that's live March 31st, 4 p.m. in Seattle, 7 p.m. in New York, 11 p.m.
London. I'd love to see you there. Of course, we'll be back next week with our take on the
latest Linux and open source news. Thanks so much for joining us. And that's all the
news for this week.