Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open source world.
This is episode 108, recorded on June 2nd, 2019. I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe. Good to be connected with you. I'm fresh off of Texas Linux Fest, and I think
I even managed to avoid the Fest hangover this time. I'm getting good at this, Joe.
What do you say we kick things off with hidden wasp, some Linux malware?
Yeah, this is quite an unusual bit of Linux malware in that it's not a crypto miner,
and it's not just a botnet that's designed to do DDoSs and stuff. It seems to be fairly
targeted and designed to take over machines completely.
Yeah, it's not really about mining crypto. It's more about command and control. And I
think one of the interesting things about this one, it's like three different projects
mashed together into one Frankenstein piece of malware. That's not something we've seen
a lot of. And some of it's from like open public code, and some of it's from some well-known
malware. And despite the fact that it's this Frankenstein based on known malware, most
detection systems haven't been catching it.
This is not really one of those stories where you have to worry about your box being vulnerable.
I mean, I suppose theoretically it's possible. But generally, according to initial research
so far, it seems that the systems are already compromised in some way. And then this is
left behind to use it, to manipulate it, to control it, and not necessarily used to like
steal CPU cycles or route mail or anything like that. And it's really kind of early days
right now, because we've only gotten a couple of files to look at, some bash scripts and
whatnot.
And they think that the main way that the malware is used is really just to kind of
keep control of the systems that have already been ransacked, which I think is fascinating.
And it doesn't seem very professional either, does it? Because they've just mashed all these
different things together to create this new hybrid beast.
Well, isn't that the spirit of open source? Take existing stuff and put it together to
make something better?
I agree. It's just the article that we've linked in ours sort of tries to really kind
of point the finger at China as a state-sponsored attack. But it doesn't really seem like it's
very sophisticated, like a state wouldn't necessarily just mash something like this
together. They'd probably create one unified piece of attack code.
At least traditionally, that's the case. Who knows? I mean, I'm just sitting here speculating
because it's just one of these fascinating stories where it's not a big threat, but it's
a weird beast that's going by undetected. And a lot of times that's the case with these
vulnerabilities is people are chaining a series of vulnerabilities together. So you get onto
the box, and you get what you need. But then how do you retain control, right? Each one
of those is an individual problem, getting into the box, executing what you need done,
and then retaining control, three separate problems. And this is solving just the latter
one.
Well, it wasn't the only security issue this week. There was also yet another vulnerability
in Docker.
In the show notes, we'll have a link to a great write up by Dennis Fisher, who breaks
down both sides of the argument here. You have the researchers case, and then you have
Docker responding, and I'll get to both of it too briefly. But from a high level, the
flaw is a weakness that results in a race condition in Docker. And there's already a
fix that's in the works, but there's also a workaround you could already take advantage
of. And like our previous story, you already have to be on the box to take advantage of
this flaw. And I think that's really key here, because with this particular flaw, and the
last one we just discussed with the malware, if somebody's already on your system and executing
that code and has access to these things, you're already messed up. A line has been
already crossed.
So it's funny too, because this is like the simplest thing to check this out. It's a bug
that's a result of the way Docker handles symbolic links. And it was discovered by security
researchers that in some situations, an attacker can insert their own symlink into a path during
a very short time window. I'm saying like in some cases, a millisecond or so of a time
window between the time that the path has been resolved, and then the time that it's
operated on. So this is a tiny, tiny fraction of time in there. An attacker could add that
link to something that's on the root file system of the host, and get out of containment
and get access to something on there. This happens when somebody executes Docker CP.
That's when this opportunity comes up. Because when you run Docker CP, it's giving you read
write access to the host file system. The obvious and super easy solution is, A, make
sure your containers are secure, and B, pause the container when you use Docker CP. And
that solves the problem.
But that's not always possible when those containers are in production.
Yeah, I suppose so. And that's definitely not ideal. I think Docker plans later on to
upstream this as the default behavior in future releases of Docker, even later this year.
And what they'll do is it'll just be a very, very brief pause. You execute the copy command,
it pauses for a few microseconds, and then it completes, or however long it takes, and
then it unpauses.
But Docker doesn't seem to think this is that serious, because it's such an edge case. And
that's why they were kind of willing to let this vulnerability go out there into the wild
before they had a fix ready for it.
Yeah, the Docker official said in a statement that the attack scenario needed to exploit
this vulnerability is quote, rare, slash unlikely. And that in the next monthly update, they'll
have the fix merged. In the meantime, use Docker pause, and in the future release, they'll
have Docker pause automatically.
Well this week saw a release of a bit of software that I have been using since the very beginning
of my Linux journey. And I can't believe that after 15 years, it is finally getting to a
1.0 release. And that is G parted.
Such great software. Really have so much appreciation for this team. And it is so cool to see this
happen after 15 years. And which, I don't know, at this point, it almost feels like
a meme. This release completes the migration to GTK 3.
Yeah.
There's a couple other things besides just switching to GTK 3, though, that jumped out
at me. I thought this was one of the features that was already in there. Maybe I was running
an early build, but they've added the ability to save your partition layout to an HTML file,
which is really nice for documentation purposes.
There's a couple of other noteworthy changes in here. Number one is they've improved the
refresh of NTFS file systems. They say it's a fix for slow refreshing of NTFS. And then
in the bug fix section of the release notes, they note, we've removed support for the ButterFS
Progues utilities to manage the ButterFS file system. So it appears that they've removed,
even if the underlying distribution has BTRFS Progues installed, they don't support it in
G parted 1.0 anymore. I think that's what I'm reading here, Joe.
Yeah, it certainly looks that way. But then again, who's using ButterFS these days? Oh
yeah. I'm Sousa.
Besides, everybody knows the future is BcacheFS. Everybody knows that. Actually, I think the
reality is, at least for future technologies, Unity is looking really strong. And they have
a brand new announcement for Linux users.
We're not talking about the desktop environment for Ubuntu here. We're talking about the game
engine. And they've announced that the Linux version of Unity editor has got official Linux
support now.
I struggle to be excited because I've been underwhelmed by more Unity based games that
I have been excited by them. But it's also one of those Electron style compromises. And
I don't mean to ascribe the performance comparisons there. I'm just talking about, it's a bit
of a, what do you call it? Common denominator? Is that the right term? A common denominator
where it's, you can't really go all in because you're not writing natively for that platform.
You're kind of targeting a common problem set. And that's sometimes good though, because
it means it opens up the door to a lot more games. And it means that people can actually
now do some of that game production on a Linux desktop, which means more desktop users. But
it also means these games might be just a little more refined under Linux now. It's
probably not going to take off like Wildfire, but it appears they're doing this based on
customer demand, which is a great sign, Joe.
It is a good sign. And they have offered experimental and unofficial builds for quite a long time.
But now it's good to see that because of commercial pressures, they're actually going official
with it and they're going to properly support it. But it's not just for games, is it? There
are other industries that can utilize the engine for various 3D stuff. Things like the
automotive industry and of course the movie industry and even some manufacturing and stuff.
And so it goes to show that even if gaming on Linux isn't massively big, those other
industries are adopting Linux across the board. And they've been using it on the server for
a long time, but maybe more and more so on the desktop.
So let's look at these desktop specs they have here. They want you to run either Ubuntu
16.04 or 18.04. So you need to be on one of the LTSs for the supported configuration.
Your mileage may vary. Or CentOS 7 is acceptable. It needs to be the x86-64 architecture. And
here's an interesting requirement. GNOME Desktop is a requirement running on X. No Wayland
for you and no plasma if you want, again, a supported configuration. And then they require
you to use either the NVIDIA official proprietary graphics or the AMD Mesa graphics driver.
And they recommend a full desktop form factor running on a device or slash hardware with
no emulation or compatibility layers. So my PCIe pass-through setup is out.
I'm sure that XFC would be fine with this. Of course.
But realistically, they have to set some standards here and say these are the supported configurations
and these are what we recommend for a best experience.
Yeah, it's kind of impressive. It's not just Ubuntu 16.04. End of sentence.
Yeah, that's true. And it sounds like it is going to work perfectly well on other systems,
but they just have to set some standards, don't they? They can't support every last
Linux distro and desktop environment and configuration.
Oh, you said standards, Joe. You know how that triggers me these days. The browser vendors
are applying more and more leverage over W3C, the folks that are supposed to be setting
the standards for the World Wide Web. But of course, without the browser vendors being
on board, they don't really have much leverage, do they? You can't really set a standard if
the people that would implement them aren't on board.
Well, yeah. And this goes back years, the Web Hypertext Application Technology Working
Group or how would you say the acronym?
Woodwig.
Woodwig, yeah. That's been around since 2004 and has almost been battling with the W3C.
You've got the browser vendors on one side trying to set the standards and W3C on the
other side. And it's kind of gone back and forth. And now it seems the W3C is just kind
of folded on this and just accepted the reality that they are going to be dictated to by the
browser manufacturers.
This has been a long time brewing, like you said. I mean, I don't know how else it could
have gone down because if you've got Apple, Mozilla, and Opera and generally Google working
outside of what the... I'll give you an example, actually. So this is one of the better examples.
The W3C really wanted to kind of convert the web over to XHTML so everything would have
an XML-like structure, which then the browsers would render for you. But they hated the idea.
The browser vendors hated the idea. And from that rebellion against that idea, this is
Chris paraphrasing here, we got the HTML5 standard, which then later on, the W3C later
formally approved as the next major iteration of the HTML web standard to sort of make nice
with the browser vendors because they were putting the support behind it and things were
going in the right direction.
But this week, things have taken a major shift. In a press release, the W3C and the Wodawig
announced that they were finally putting their differences aside and signed a new, quote,
memorandum of understanding.
That's certainly one way to put it, yeah.
Yeah. They say, per this new agreement, the W3C is officially giving up publishing of
future HTML and DOM standards in favor of Wodawig, again, that's W-H-A-T-W-G, that group
effectively giving them full control, which really means the browser vendors having full
control.
Which ultimately means Google having most of that control.
I do wonder about that. I do wonder if we'll look back in 2025 and look back at May 28th,
2019 is the day where something major shifted and the standards, but that body, that group
also, Microsoft sits on there, Apple sits on there, Mozilla's in there, Opera's in that
conversation. Really, isn't the solution now just to open that group up a little more?
Because at the end of the day, if they're the ones writing the software, they always
had ultimate control. The W3C has just sort of been a, I mean, it's a theater piece in
a way. They can make good suggestions, but if Firefox and Google alone decide not to
do it, it's like they're effectively powerless.
Well, yeah, and the market will just go to whatever the most popular browser is. Already
we're in a situation where some sites just don't work without Chrome. Source Connect,
for example, is a web app that we sometimes use in production that requires Chrome. It's
just got that hard requirement. And I don't really understand why all that underlying
technology ought to work in a standards compliant browser like Firefox, but it just doesn't.
There's some interesting parallels here with the free desktop standards and the conversations
going on around the desktop and theming for Linux. In fact, I bet you a listener out there
knows the perfect XKCD comic they could tweet me at Chris LAS that it's like we set these
standards and then we get all the support behind them and then everybody goes off and
does their own thing. And then we all decide the standards need to be redone completely
all over again. And I don't, it's almost like what's the effing point? I mean, not to curse
on your show, Joe, but what is the effing point of it all? At the end of the day, it's
like people just want to sit around and make stuff up and then people go off into their
own corners and do their own thing anyways. I find it frustrating.
Yeah. 927, by the way, is that XKCD you're thinking of.
Oh, okay.
How standards proliferate.
Yeah. Oh, that's a good one. But I feel like there's another one where we all go off and
make standards and then throw them out. And I'm not talking about a standard for our standards
either. That's not what we need here.
So tell me about Texas Linux Fest then. How's that been going?
Yeah, Texas Linux Fest was two days here in Irving, Texas, Irving, which is kind of nice
because it's only about 30 or 40 minutes from the Linux Academy office. So I was able to
shoot over here to do the show today. It was good. Friday was kind of slow. It is typically,
you know, when it's a work day, like that first day is usually a little slow going.
But by the second day, it's all the people you saw on Friday, plus a new batch of people.
And they kicked off with, I think it was Thomas Cameron is his name, I believe. He's a local
log number here and just gave a killer keynote. Both Elle and I just looked at each other
after the keynote and was like, that's one of the best talks we've ever attended at any
conference ever. It was really good. And we got the audio for it. So I'm going to see
if we can release it. And we got some video of it for them too. So we're going to try
to help them release it on their own channels as well.
And it was at the same time, you know, there was a few bumps here and there. But as far
as a community event goes, there's something kind of special around the 300 number because
you see the same faces five or six, seven times over a weekend. And by day two, everybody
kind of loosens up a little bit because you've been around each other. You've kind of gotten
all the social awkwardness out of the way. And so day two is really casual and it's sort
of a very friendly atmosphere. And so I just I really enjoyed the heck out of day two.
And we got a hell of a thunderstorm here. It was raining and lightning like, like only
Texas can provide. It was quite the show. And we had some great meetups, got to get
some good beers and good food, some good company. So all in all, I'm very, very glad I made
it down. And I hope they keep growing. I think they might try to go back to Austin possibly.
But I hope they keep it up because it's like, it's like that plucky little conference you
want to see keep going and grow.
And what was the kind of topic trend there then? Was it all about cloud and hybrid cloud
and corporate stuff? Or was it much more community desktop type stuff?
Hmm, good question. You know, I hadn't really I hadn't really kind of thought about it.
But as you're asking, I kind of went through it all. And I'd say my first my first hot
take on that question would be it was fairly container focused and cloud focused, but not
in like the buzzy, commercial cloud sense, but in the I'll give you an example, like
the first talk that was really well attended of the day was about going from a total noob
with ansible to going to brilliant. And it was a workshop talk. So about halfway through
the talk, the author takes a 10 minute break puts up the download URLs for virtual machines
and to get configuration files going. And then for the rest of the talk, you work along
with the presenter and get ansible working by the end of the talk. And so it was that
kind of stuff. And there was several of those workshops each day, which are very valuable.
And there was a there was a really good message underneath it all. And that is, you could
be a Linux admin today. And that's that's a really good living and you've probably got
like a good solid 10 years where that's going to be a great living. But at some point, the
Linux admin is going to go the way of the Unix admin. And that is to say not going away
completely but becoming much, much more of a niche job. And what is going to take over
is a cloud admin. Now, what does that mean? That's a lot of things. That's understanding
networking, that's understanding Linux basics, that's understanding storage and network storage,
that's understanding network fundamentals, that's understanding how data centers work,
that's understanding how these services work and how to interface with them. It's a very
complex job. But the awesome thing is, is if you're already a Linux admin, or you're
even if you have a basic understanding of Linux, you're in a really good position to
leverage that knowledge to pick up those other skill sets and have a really complete skill
set resume. And so you're in a good position for the next 10 years, you just have to act
on it and learn and train yourself up.
It sounds like a really cool conference, then I might have to try and make it over for
next year.
Especially if you like to eat, because there's always really good food in Texas Joe. As my
stomach will tell you, it's just a little bit bigger now.
So there's a bit of breaking news that we don't have much info on it's happening as
we record. This seems to happen every every Sunday when we record, doesn't it? And that's
the Google Cloud seems to be down.
Yeah, which is affecting things in weird ways on the internet right now. So of course, it's
a big topic of conversation. But at the moment, we just have Google status page, not a lot
of information about what's caused the outage or exactly how widespread it is. But what
we do know is I'm in Texas and Joe's in London, and we're both impacted by the outage right
now.
The document that we used to do this show has been kind of connecting and not working.
It's working right now, but it's been hit and miss. So yes, not sure how bad this is
yet. But if it does turn out to be a bad one, then maybe you can follow up on Linux Unplugged
on Tuesday.
Yeah, if we find out something interesting, I will do that. I will do that. You know,
Joe, sometimes it's just worth self hosting these kinds of things. Maybe this is our lesson.
I know Nextcloud is starting to look more and more attractive to me.
Well, we'll keep an eye on all kinds of things throughout the week and report them here for
you. Check out linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch with us.
And speaking of getting trained up, we've released the Don't Be Famous Learning Kubernetes
and Securing Your Cluster talk, which is up on our YouTube channel, youtube.com slash
Jupiter Broadcasting. A great introduction to getting Kubernetes secured away and an
information packed talk in general.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I'm at Chris LAS.
I'm at Joe Rissington.
Thanks for joining us. And we will see you next week.
See you later.