Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open source world.
This is episode 86, recorded on December 21st, 2018. I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe. It is finally here. Our annual predictions and, for the first time ever,
look back at our former predictions, which I think we should just skip right over and
not even talk about at all.
Well, I've left the Bitcoin stuff till the end. So, yeah.
Okay. All right. Well, then I think I can get through some of this. Maybe we should
start with your first quote unquote prediction, which I don't think really came true.
No, and listening back to this today, we were both dead certain that this was going to happen.
And this was that Ubuntu Unity 7 would become an official flavor. And we just thought, oh,
that's a dead cert. That's just a really easy one. But that hasn't really happened, has
it? We've seen a few images. We've seen some work towards it. But there just doesn't seem
to be enough momentum there to get even a project going properly, never mind an official
flavor. And we both agreed that by 1810, it would be. But apparently, people are happy
enough with GNOME.
Yeah, I actually thought you were cheating a little bit with this one. That was such
a gimme. Of course that's going to happen. I think in part because we were hearing from
canonical employees that were trying to make that a thing. So it seemed natural that that
would pan out. But I think the other thing that happened was they nailed the GNOME implementation.
It's good. And by 1810, it's really good. And 1904, by all accounts, is looking really
neat. So I think that was part of that whole Unity 7 will survive was some incorrect assumption
that the GNOME Shell implementation would be trash. Just didn't pan out. And so the
need just wasn't really there.
Yeah. And of course, in Marte, you can make a fairly good approximation of Unity 7. And
you can do it in Plasma as well. So if people were really wedded to that workflow, there
are ways to get more or less that workflow with other desktops. And maybe people were
just willing to do that. Or much more likely, as you say, just the GNOME implementation
in Ubuntu was good enough.
I missed the mark, though, on my prediction. I thought we'd have a massive botnet story.
Just a cyber attack type story that was facilitated by a bunch of insecure Linux-powered, unfortunately,
IoT devices. I thought it would at least be the largest area of attacks over 2018, mostly
due to bad defaults. And in some ways, that did pan out. We saw routers really get abused
this year. But the smart plugs, the toasters, we haven't really had that doomsday story
that I thought we would have. So I'm going to mark that one as a miss.
Well, you did also say Linux servers. And you were kind of half right in that we've
had a lot of crypto miner attacks on Linux servers. So you were kind of almost right.
But I think that's a bit of a stretch. So yeah, I think we're kind of both a bust on
those two there.
Well, OK. All right. How about your next one? I think you had a Microsoft prediction, I
recall.
Yeah, I said that Microsoft Linux, maybe called Azure Linux, would come out. And it would
be their own cloud distro with tight windows, desktop integration, and basically that Microsoft
would have a Linux distro. And I think I was more or less right. I wasn't quite right in
the details. But they did put out a Linux distro, didn't they?
Yeah. I mean, Azure Sphere OS is Linux-powered. And it's a cloud-connected Linux OS running
on devices being sold by Microsoft this year. I mean, I think that counts, Joe. I think
you get a win on that one. It's a close call, because I don't think it was exactly what
you had in mind. But I think you win on a technicality.
I think it was a bit more than a technicality. But either way, yeah, I'm claiming that as
a win.
I'm happy to report that my next one was also mostly a miss. In some ways, what I was watching
was a storm a-brewing. Winter was coming to the open source community, and I didn't expect
the best from us. But I think overall, mostly things turned out okay. I thought we'd see
a huge gap between the idealist and the pragmatist. And I thought we'd see that really widen as
you had people that were in that DevOps category or sysadmin category or web dev or whoever
it is that is buying Sputnik laptops and buying these different machines and installing Linux
on them and replicating production and development on their laptops. That stereotypical person
now that's driving the adoption of Linux.
My big fear was that there would become sort of a battle between those that were involved
in Linux for the freedom aspects and those that were involved in Linux for the work aspects.
And I thought as the people that were just using it as a work tool grew, that gap would
become more and more polarized. And that really didn't seem to happen. We do definitely see
more and more pragmatists using Linux as just a day to day work tool. And we see more and
more different implementations of Linux across commercial operating systems like Windows
and Chrome. But thankfully, there hasn't been that big community battle playing out in all
of the different aspects of online communication. Yeah, it's there. It's always been there.
But it didn't turn into the all full fledged holy war that I was expecting.
I think the reason for that is that all the pragmatic stuff is additions to Linux. If
you look at, for example, the Nvidia driver, you don't have to install that. I have got
a PC that's running the Nuvo driver, for example, and I don't need to do any 3D stuff with it.
And the card works perfectly well with Nuvo. And so it's running almost all free software.
And so those pragmatists who have definitely grown in number, we've seen that this year,
definitely, we've seen a big rise in that pragmatism. Take Fedora, for example, making
it easy to install those proprietary drivers. And we've seen more and more people coming
to Linux using it for things like gaming with Steam.
Sure. I would argue the accelerated use of snaps, flat packs, and app images is also
a bit of the pragmatists taking over.
Yeah, definitely. And so you were kind of half right there. We have definitely seen
more pragmatism and more pragmatists coming to the Linux world. But I think the people
who are running Triskill or Debian with no proprietary stuff, they don't really care
because that stuff still exists for them. And they just don't have these proprietary
additions on top of it.
Yeah, fair enough. Their territory didn't go away. It's just, like you said, all been
in addition. We've just made room for everybody.
Yeah, I think that it's ultimately better. I think that the free stuff does benefit from
the pragmatists coming along because it's no good having the NVIDIA driver be really,
really great if the rest of Wayland and whatever doesn't work very well. And so that kind of
feeds into the free software development, makes that better, and then the purists and
the free software people benefit as a result. So maybe that's also why there's not been
this big backlash.
Well, before we own up on the Bitcoin stuff, do you want to lay down a few 2019 predictions?
Okay, my first one. Now, you have to bear in mind that people have been saying this
for many years now. And I've been saying, no, it's not going to happen. And it hasn't
happened so far. But I'm convinced that this year it will happen. And that is that Microsoft
will buy at least a significant percentage share in Canonical. It just seems inevitable
to me that I don't think they will kind of buy them out right. And we might not even
hear about it because it is a private company. But I think they'd struggle to keep it quiet.
And Shotworth said he was looking for investors before the IPO. And so I think that Microsoft
is going to pony up and put some money into Canonical this year, a significant amount
of money.
So if you've been saying this isn't going to happen for years now, what is it about
now that's changed your mind? Is it the IBM Red Hat sale?
I think that has definitely played into it. And of course, SUSE was acquired this year.
Yeah, and last year and the year before.
Yeah, yeah. But it goes to show there is a market for these companies. And I think really
what has changed my mind here is that Shotworth has cleaned house over the last sort of 18
months and made Ubuntu and Canonical a profitable, leaner operation that is growing and making
some money and innovating. And is actually quite an attractive proposition now for someone
to buy. Whereas before, they had the phone stuff that was going nowhere in Unity 8. Whereas
now it's much more streamlined. And it just seems much more valuable.
Yeah. And with the Red Hat acquisition from IBM, there is less opportunity for Microsoft.
And so they need to strike while there's still opportunity. And we know that this year, Azure
crossed the 60% line for Linux. That's a massive number for Microsoft. And they seem to be
willing to do whatever it takes to keep more people getting into Azure. I got to imagine
they're looking at this at least. Maybe it won't happen. But I think it's a pretty solid
prediction. And I like the hedge that you've made this year. And that is, it's at least
a percentage. Because you're going to be right if they just invest. And you're going to be
right if they buy them. So that's a safe one.
Well, I'd say it's a significant percentage. I'm not talking 5%. I'm talking at least 20,
25.
Well, I've got one that I feel like is going to be a pain point for Linux users this year,
especially for those in the iOS ecosystem that have an iPhone or an iPad and have a
Linux box. I'm pretty positive that Apple will indeed launch a video streaming service.
Original content, much like Netflix does, that's not going to work with Linux at all.
And Linux users will be completely left out as if it was 1997 all over again. And the
richest company, or at least the richest tech company in the world, continues to underdeliver
for us Linux users.
You have got some front, my friend, to say this. This is so obviously going to happen
that I couldn't possibly have put it in. Apple are definitely going to launch a video streaming
service.
No, I think people listening to this show will be like, what? A Netflix competing streaming
service? These guys are crazy. I don't think it's a foregone conclusion. Not until Uncle
Tim's up on stage, Joe.
Come on. We've read how many stories this year that they're working on it and how they're
not going to have any swearing or nudity and it's going to struggle to compete.
It's already struggling to compete before it's launched. I love it.
Yeah, yeah. And the idea that this would possibly be available on Linux, well, OK, maybe via
the browser. But you would imagine, I mean, you can't even watch the Apple launches on
Linux, can you, in the browser? So yeah, I wouldn't be surprised at all. This, to me,
is the easiest, definite prediction that I've ever heard.
Easier than yours, huh? Hmm.
Well, the Microsoft buying canonical, that could definitely not. I mean, Shuttleworth
has said that he's looking to IPO. The official line is that they're not selling. And so no
way. This is definitely happening.
I wouldn't completely count Apple out. See, if you look at the divisions of Apple, they
have Apple Music for Android. They just launched Apple Music for Alexa. Cancel. Cancel. Cancel.
Stop. Thank you. So, you know, like they maybe there is it is it within the realm of possibility.
But also within the realm of possibility is they never launch a streaming service. That's
what I love about this prediction is it's it's got it's a full spectrum possibility
here.
They could, in theory, just make content and sell it on iTunes on demand that way without
a proper streaming service. But no, they're definitely going to do it. And it's probably
not going to work, at least very well on Linux.
The only thing I think crazier than my prediction would be like some sort of prediction that
like Linux gaming is going to take off or something.
Well, that's my next prediction. And that is that Steam Linux market share will crack
5%. It's under 1% right now.
Yeah, it's 0.8. 0.8. You think you're going to go to 5% in one year?
Yep.
That's you're giving me a hard time. I mean, I just don't even see it. What's the Mac at?
What is it? What is the Mac OS market share right now for Steam OS? Is it even above 10%?
This is a bold prediction, Joe. Do you think Proton is going to be what fuels this meteoric
rise in Linux gaming?
Well, that's certainly part of it. But the bigger part of it is not that there's going
to be loads more people running Steam on Linux. It's going to be fewer people running Steam
on Windows because of the competition that is brewing. And that is Epic and their games
store and also Discord and their game store, which are looking to undercut Steam. And so
you're going to have a lot more titles going over there, potentially exclusives. And I
think that Steam is going to lose its crown as the premium gaming platform. I think you're
going to have a much more distributed three-way race. And as a result, you're going to lose
the Windows users from Steam. And you'll also get more Linux users on Steam. I think that's
going to settle out to be about 5%.
Hmm, that's bold. I mean, right now I'm picturing a future where I'm sitting on my partially
Microsoft-owned Ubuntu desktop watching my Apple streaming video while I download a Steam
game where I'm nearly one of the five percenters on the platform. It seems nearly crazy, but
not any crazier than my next prediction. And I want to make sure I'm very clear about this.
I don't think this is going to be a final product. This may be only beta or even maybe
pre-release. I don't know what they're going to call it. But I believe this year, in some
form or another, maybe preview, maybe beta, Microsoft will launch Office as an Electron
app. Maybe just to like Office 365 subscribers. Maybe it's only a small preview or a beta.
But my thought process has really been over 2018, looking at what Microsoft has done.
When they acquired GitHub, they also acquired Electron. When they announced the transition
from Edge HTML to Chromium, they also announced making Windows a really, really first-class
Electron platform. And they own Electron and they can make contributions to Chromium.
They have the potential to build something really significant. And if you look at some
of their more recent products, like the new version of Skype and other things, VS Code,
etc., they're Electron based. I think we could see a truly cross-platform Office 365 desktop
style application, something along this line. Maybe it's just Word, but it's an Office style
application that is released as an Electron app by Microsoft. Maybe it's preview in 2019.
I can't disagree with any of that. That seems very likely to me. I think that we'll even
get to a point where we've got a snap of it as well. I think it'll run across basically
all Linux distributions or at least most of them. As soon as you said that, I thought,
yeah, I'm fully on board with that prediction. I can totally see that happening.
You can kind of look back at some of their recent moves over 2018 and see them lining
up behind Electron. And having a couple of conversations with a couple of different developers
down there, I've been told about a couple of different in-house projects that are Electron
based that we're like, what? You've got to be kidding me. You guys are working with Electron
on that? Yeah, we're doing these things. I don't want to say who or what. I know that's
very vague, but it sort of changed my perspective on what Microsoft would be willing to ship.
And when we look at Skype and VS Code, I think we see those things individually, and we don't
really take into account that they're essentially Electron applications. And we don't appreciate
how sometimes companies can test the waters and trial balloon things with some products
before they move their most treasured product to a new platform.
And I suspect, based on the conversations I've had, that that's what Microsoft's been
doing for the last couple of years. And this final drop of Internet Explorer and Edge,
which is a 20-year legacy and a move over to Chromium, is such a significant change
that the only thing that would make them truly willing to drop that 20-year heritage and
make a new shift like that would be to serve a bigger goal long term, like making Windows
one of the best platforms to run desktop Electron applications, which to us probably sounds
horrible, but to the business world is absolutely necessary.
Yeah, and just because they'll be the best experience on Windows doesn't mean that they
won't work on the other platforms. Yeah. So we should hopefully benefit. I hope so. We
should, well, if running Office can be considered a benefit.
Yeah, and Electron applications. At least we have them.
Yeah. Right. Well, you can't filibuster this anymore. We have to get into Bitcoin.
All right. All right.
So we had our predicted highs, lows, and the price on the 1st of December 2018. It's worth
mentioning that when we recorded this, it was before the crash, basically. It was...
We recorded a bit earlier than we are this time, didn't we? And it was riding high. It
was nearly at 20,000. And so we got a bit carried away is the bottom line.
Yeah. It wouldn't even be a topic of discussion this year. It's not, you know, like the hype
on Bitcoin is just totally dead now. Back at the end of last year, though, it was what
everybody was talking about.
Yeah. So for the highs, I said 120,000 and you said 100,000. And I was close because
it was actually 117,000. Oh, no, no. 17,000 was the actual high. And that was on January
6th. So it's just been downhill ever since. So yeah, we were kind of a little bit off
there.
Yeah. It was supposed to be over 100,000 for either one of us. You went a little higher.
I went 100,000. You went 120. But as we record right now, it's 3,800. 3,800. That's so bad.
Yeah. Well, the price on December the 1st, I had said it would be 100,000. You said it
would be 107,000, which was higher than you thought the high would be.
Yeah. I know. I know.
Yeah. I think you got a bit of a rush of blood to the head there. And yeah, the actual price
was about 4,000. So we were just slightly off there.
See, this is what happens. See, Joe, you made me do a prediction and this is what happens.
I blame you for all of this. Not only my wrong prediction, but for the crash itself is actually
your fault as far as I'm concerned.
Yeah. So the lows, we were kind of a little bit off there as well.
Oh, weird.
I said 15,000 and you said 10,000.
Yeah. I wish it hadn't gone below 10,000 to be honest with you. And then when it got to
5,000, I thought that'd be the floor. And then when it got to 4,000, I thought that'd
be the floor. Part of what's always factored into where I try to guess where Bitcoin is
going is the fact that there is a limited quantity. There's like 21 million or so that'll
ever be created. And you figure a lot of people are losing them. A lot of people are hoarding
them. So you either have a situation where over time Bitcoin will get more valuable or
it'll completely be worthless. And it'll be, you know, just, I mean, maybe a couple of
bucks at best. And I just, you just don't know which way it's going to go. But at this
point in time, towards the end of 2018, the general narrative is that the crypto market
has burst and that things are struggling. And that it's the end of Bitcoin. If that's
true or not, time will tell. Obviously you just have no way of knowing, right? In a year
it could be completely different.
Yeah. Yeah. There's all talk of now is a great time to get into gaming because the graphics
cards are cheap again because no one really wants them for mining the altcoins. But yeah,
so the, the actual low was 3,200 ish and that was in mid December.
Wow.
That's as we record. It may well be by the time this goes out that it's lower than that.
So although it does seem to have bounced back a bit, but there's just no way to know is
there.
No, no. And, and you know, anything could really influence from a scam, a exchange going
down or an economy collapsing somewhere. All these things play into the Bitcoin price.
It's a worldwide internet currency. And so things all around the world impacted, unlike,
you know, regional currencies where at least you could say here, the dollar in the States
is impacted mostly by things that are happening with dollar or with the oil price. But that's
pretty much it. But with Bitcoin, it could be politics in China that are influencing
the prices here in the States. It's just a totally new phenomenon.
Yeah. All right. Well, we have to do predictions, but there's just, take these with a pinch
of salt because
Oh no.
Who knows?
Oh no. You're making me do this again. Oh no.
Yep. So what's your prediction for the high in 2019?
Hmm. $12,000.
Interesting. So you think it is going to go back up significantly? My high, 6,000.
Really?
Yep.
Hmm. I wouldn't be surprised if it stabilizes around 10, maybe. I could also see it completely
collapsing though, to be honest with you. In even just a few months, I could see that
happening. So it's a tough call really.
Well, that's why I think the low is going to be 900.
All right. Okay. All right. Hmm. All right. So I'd say $300 for my low.
Right. So you think it's going to be a huge range then?
That is a massacre if that happens though. That's an absolute massacre if that happens.
Yeah. I can't help but feel if it goes as low as 300, although actually if it goes below
a thousand, then surely the bottom will just fall out of it and it'll just go to nothing
and it'll just be proved to be the Ponzi scheme that everyone said it was.
Or would everybody start buying like crazy? Because now it's below $1,000. So buy up like
crazy because there's only ever going to be 21 million. The people just, you never know
how they're going to react to that kind of thing.
Yeah. All right. Well, December 1st then, where do you think it's going to be?
I'm going to say $9,200.
Right. That's pretty high. I think it's going to be $2,000.
Yeah. I feel like I went too high, but I feel like it's either going to be high or it's
going to be completely low. And if it's going to be high, it's probably going to be higher
than what I predicted. So I don't think I like my number either way.
My numbers, let me justify my numbers to you.
All right. Okay.
I think that what we're going to see is a bit of a rally now up to $6,000 over the next
month or so.
I can feel that coming. Yeah.
And then I think we're going to see a crash down to $900. And then I think it's going
to struggle and it'll sort of inch its way up slowly, slowly, slowly. And then by the
end of the year, be around $2,000.
Yeah. The only way my predictions work out is if it finds a new floor and then it just
very slowly builds its way up towards $10,000. And I think if that doesn't happen, if that
stability doesn't happen, then Bitcoin is pretty much screwed as anything but just a
transfer mechanism. You know what I mean? You can't use it as a currency if it's moving
this much. By this point in its lifecycle, it needs to start stabilizing now. And that
might be what we're seeing because it has been hanging out in the $3,000 price range
now for a while. And it could slowly build up to $10,000 and just take the whole year
to get there. And I think that would actually be a healthy signal for Bitcoin that it's
slowing down. But I think it's the least likely. I think you're probably going to win that
one.
Watch it end up being $200,000.
Well, if it is, we'll own up to it. I mean, now we got to admit it. We're on the record.
We'll see what happens. This year couldn't have gotten any worse. So let's see. Check
out linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get future episodes, including
our regular weekly updates, as well as our special episodes.
And go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch with us and tell
us how wrong we are about our predictions.
Or your own predictions, too. I'd like to read those. And we'll be back next Monday
with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news. I am at Chris Ellis.
I'm at Joe Ressington.
Thank you for joining us. See you next week.
And we'll see you later.