Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 150, recorded on March 21st, 2020.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe.
Good to be connected with you.
What do you say we start out with the big news from NPM this week?
Yes, NPM has been acquired by GitHub, or is that Microsoft?
I think it's the more palatable way to say Microsoft.
Well, in the press releases from NPM and from GitHub, they did not mention Microsoft once,
which is quite telling.
And it seems that it is going to be under the management of GitHub, obviously with Microsoft
overseeing things and ultimately financing it.
But I think that Microsoft are going to be hands off.
They've been relatively hands off with GitHub, haven't they so far?
Or at least hands on in a way that people like.
And maybe this is ultimately a good thing for NPM.
I think that's the very goodwill they're cashing in on with this announcement.
And I think it's clear it will be managed by GitHub.
NPM makes more sense as a product of GitHub than it does of any other component of Microsoft's
offerings.
It's still probably a pretty big shock, though, to millions of developers who use that public
registry every day.
Now Nat Friedman on the GitHub blog post does say that they will keep the registry free
forever.
They've developed an infrastructure for that, that they will improve the core experience.
And he gives a couple of examples of that, specifically improving on the CLI tools, which
I think is awesome.
And they intend to engage more with the larger JavaScript community.
One thing that stuck out to me in some of the messaging, and it's here in Nat Friedman's
announcement, is this language around improving the security of, quote, the open source software
supply chain.
I think that's an interesting way to look at NPM.
But we have definitely talked about some of the security issues these software registries
have experienced in the past.
And I would credit Microsoft with managing their infrastructure pretty well so far.
Well, that's another reason why this may well be good news for NPM ultimately, is that apart
from the finances, it's the management of this.
It's the fact that we hopefully won't see these security issues, developers just pulling
their project out and messing up all the projects that depend on that.
Hopefully GitHub will be able to manage all that properly.
And so we'll see a kind of more professional NPM as a result of this.
Maybe they'd have to come up with some solutions for basic human nature.
Perhaps monetizations for projects that are struggling could help with that.
I'm skeptical.
Let's put NPM's footprint into context for a moment.
NPM serves over 1.3 million packages to roughly 12 million developers who download these things
75 billion times a month.
And if the trends continue in a few years, those numbers will seem tiny.
If the trajectory continues, I bring all that up to just kind of turn this around and say,
is it maybe not even just important, but is it maybe critical that something like NPM
remains independent in an open source free software ecosystem?
There's obviously, like we just mentioned, benefits to the pockets of Microsoft, especially
under the leadership of Nat Friedman, who seems to be doing a fantastic job.
Obvious benefits, but I just thought, let's play devil's advocate.
This seems like a pretty big, important piece of our open source software ecosystem.
If you'll take a term from their announcement, shouldn't it be independent?
Shouldn't it be something that is not owned by a single commercial entity?
Well, it was owned by a single commercial entity before, NPM Inc.
But they're a small independent company that when you read their side of the announcement,
sounds like things weren't always great, that they've had some struggles and that maybe
this needed to happen for them.
But I guess maybe let's fantasize in a world where a foundation of sorts steps in and it
becomes something that is maybe managed in that sense instead of managed by a holding
company, which then manages another company, which there's a lot of conflicting interests
there.
I do get where you're coming from here.
And maybe the foundation route could have been something they did.
But if you're going to try and compete in the commercial world, then consolidation is
just inevitable, isn't it?
The only way to survive is just by becoming part of a bigger and bigger entity.
And that entity, in this case, is Microsoft.
I think the reality of the market right now, especially here in the States, but really
around the world, is there are four significant, five-ish significant tech companies.
And if you want to get to millions and billions, you got to go through their gates.
And that, in a way, gets products into the hands of users that never would have had access
to that technology.
But it also limits the way it gate keeps, essentially, the way you can get to market.
But aside from that, I think the reality of the numbers here suggests that you would need
infrastructure experts running NPM within a year or two.
Not that they're not already, clearly.
But you need somebody who can really operate at scale.
And that's one of the big tech companies.
And Microsoft is clearly one of the ideal candidates if you're going to pick from the
top five.
I'm very glad this wasn't Facebook.
I'm pretty glad this wasn't Google or Apple, too.
And it's yet more evidence of Microsoft's shift towards open source.
Right.
And this fits in line with what we've kind of been saying recently with WSL, the new
terminal and GitHub's acquisition in general.
It seems Microsoft has realized during a gold rush, the way you're going to make money at
this point is by selling the axes and the pixes and the shovels and whatever, the tools,
to the gold miners.
And in this analogy, open source development is the gold mine.
Yeah.
And all that shiny new open source code is the gold.
Exactly.
And Microsoft's more than happy to help you get that gold because their tools and services,
a lot of them have a monthly price attached to them.
And now NPM is another set of those tools.
But more importantly, I think it will signal to the market that this is a safe bet.
It's in the hands of GitHub now and Microsoft.
You can depend on this.
Some in our community will have the exact opposite reaction.
To them, it's now going to be something that's suspicious.
It's something that probably needs a free replacement, something alternative to.
But to a larger segment of the market, and especially to the business types, this will
be a signal of stability and safety for NPM.
Yeah.
And exactly where that split is and how many people are on each side of it, we'll be telling.
I suspect there'll be far more people on the business side of things.
I'd like to know how much they paid.
NPM and GitHub are not sharing that detail right now.
I'm curious, how much does a world famous software repository go for?
How much is this all worth?
I'd really like to know, but nays the word on that one so far.
Well, it wasn't the only GitHub news this week.
The iOS and Android apps are now out of beta.
Had the NPM acquisition not happened.
This may have been a bigger story because neither one of these apps for Android or iOS
are open source.
And interestingly, GitHub wrote the apps separately for each platform.
They used Swift for iOS and Kotlin for Android.
I find that interesting.
They went for a native look for each one of them with a couple of shared components and
toolbar stuff in there.
And it has some essential basic functionality that you would come to expect.
It doesn't have everything.
That's one of the main complaints on Twitter right now is people grousing about what it
doesn't do.
But it lets you organize tasks very simply in a mobile UI.
It gives you the ability to respond to feedback and issues.
And obviously the big feature allows you to review and merge pull requests.
Yeah, you're right that there's been some negative feedback about the stuff that it
can't do.
But I've also seen some very positive feedback about stuff that it can do.
I've seen some devs tweeting about how they can get some of these tasks done while they're
waiting in line for groceries or whatever.
So I think mixed reaction is the fairest way to describe it.
Yeah.
And the thing to remember is these apps aren't done.
In fact, I believe it was implied by Ryan Nystrom that the apps may go open source.
He was asked and he said, well, they're not open source now, but maybe in the future.
And you could see possibly as they add new features and whatnot that perhaps one day
they'll also have a big announcement, GitHub's mobile apps are now open source.
One can dream, Joe.
Yeah, we can.
It's funny that he tweeted, it's not right now regarding the code being open source.
And that was from Twitter for iPhone.
Hey, that Twitter app launches real fast on iOS, Joe.
So I hear.
Well, something that has taken a while to launch is Linux Mint Debian Edition 4, Debian,
which has been released this week.
Yeah, I think it's been a few years, but it's here, LMDE 4, Debian Edition.
And this is their hedge on Ubuntu going away one day, keeping the project sustainable with
a different base.
But over the years, it's kind of turned into a semi unofficial slash official way to have
a slow release rolling Mint desktop.
But it has seen a bit of neglect over the years.
They'll kind of release it and then certain packages get updated and it gets a bit kind
of left behind while they concentrate on the main Linux Mint Edition.
So I'm really hoping that with LMDE 4, they can give it a bit more time and resources
now because I installed this yesterday and I was actually really impressed by it.
Recent versions of Cinnamon are pretty good.
And that's the primary experience you get with Linux Mint Debian Edition.
I like it.
For me, it's not quite the right fit.
So it's based on Debian 10 Buster and it has kernel 4.19, which feels like it's from a
hundred years ago at this point.
So there's things I like about it in that the concept of a semi rolling release, because
sometimes upgrades are challenging with Mint, that's based on Debian, which is a great foundation
with Cinnamon, which is turning into a top grade desktop environment that needs upgrades
every three to four years.
That kind of sounds almost like your perfect kind of thing.
It seems like it's right in your alley, but for me, it's just a little too old.
Well, yeah.
And also the fact that Cinnamon is very Windows-like, I can see why you don't like it because you
don't really like Windows, but I think as a UI, that's perfectly fine.
So I like it.
It's been ages since I've tried out Cinnamon or Mint of any description, but I think I
should maybe give it a bit more attention.
I think if I was going to switch to Mint, I'd probably want to go with the main edition
because if I were betting on the odds in Vegas, I would bet that between Ubuntu, Linux Mint
proper and Debian and Linux Mint Debian edition, if any one of those distros was ever going
to go away, first I would bet on Linux Mint Debian edition going away.
Then before I ever bet on Ubuntu going away, I'd bet on Debian going away because the project
is cratering right now anyways.
People are living in a fantasy land if they think Debian is in a sustainable point right
now.
I haven't been listening to enough of these shows, but this project is on the verge of
cratering.
And there may be a future where Ubuntu has to pull this up by its bootstraps and just
have their own repository that they build off and we have Ubuntu proper.
I would bet on that way more than I'd bet on this escape hatch ever needing to be pulled
for the Mint project.
And so I just look at this from a practical standpoint and go, I don't know if I see another
five years in this.
You might be right, but it never hurts to hedge your bets to some extent.
I suppose it depends how much in terms of resources and time is going into this.
If it's just a kind of side project for them, then why not keep it on the back burner?
That's what I think.
And that's why when we talk about their cadence and some of the packages being out of date,
I think that makes sense when you consider this is it's a plan B and I think it gets
the right amount of appropriate resources.
I'm reminded of the old tales that Apple used to keep x86 max in the bowels of Apple when
they were on power PC just in case.
And then one day, guess what?
That became the predominant platform and the reason they were able to make that transition
successfully was because they had kept x86 builds and x86 machines around essentially
as hackintoshes and that gave them the runway to actually make it successful.
And that's kind of the same exact theory that's being applied here for Linux Mint.
So I like it.
The idea, I mean, I get why they're doing it.
It even seems sort of practical.
I just would maybe dial down the rhetoric a little bit in the announcement paragraph
for this release.
Second sentence, quote, its goal is to ensure Linux Mint would be able to continue to deliver
the same user experiences and how much work would be involved if Ubuntu were ever to disappear.
And then it's actually restated a little bit later, too, in here.
That just seems almost a little disrespectful if you consider that Linux Mint was made possible
because it's able to piggyback on all of the work that goes into an LTS.
It's sort of been the mother's milk for this distribution that now pays a good amount of
money every single month.
It seems like you'd have some sort of reverence and respect for your parent distribution,
especially by my estimation, when it has a better shot than Debian at this point of surviving.
And yes, I understand Ubuntu is based on Debian.
Well, that leads us into the next story then, doesn't it?
And that is the Debian Project Leader Elections 2020.
And there are three candidates with quite different manifestos.
I think there's one candidate.
And that's why I am maybe hitting this as hard as I am in this episode, because I look
at these candidates in front of us, and I nearly panic for the future of my beloved
Debian distribution, a distribution that has been around for as long as I have been in
Linux and was key in me getting started.
It's a distribution that I have a deep respect for.
And the three candidates that are applying, well, at least two of the three are not ideal.
This project is in bad shape.
People are in denial about the state of this project.
And I don't really see anyone fully addressing any of it.
I don't think any of them fully solve the problems the project is facing right now.
Do you feel that way?
Yeah, I think that whoever wins, you're going to have problems.
You've got Jonathan Carter, whose platform is continue to do what Debian does well, among
some other things as well, but he concentrates on technical excellence and promoting free
software and things like that, basically more of the same.
And he kind of does address some of the other issues that are there, but he's very much
the continuity candidate.
Then you've got Sruti Chandran, whose platform is very much about diversity.
It's not quite a single issue, but it's very much concentrating on the diversity angle
and increasing diversity within Debian.
And she doesn't have as much experience as the other candidates.
And we know that diversity is a very divisive issue.
And then you've got Brian Gupta, who says, I'm running for DPL with a singular goal,
the creation of Debian US and EU foundations, I largely view my candidacy as a referendum
on this goal and its details.
So he's very much a single issue candidate.
And he describes in his platform about how he's going to achieve that.
And it's basically adding a lot of bureaucracy, which he sees is required for the project
to continue.
So you've got three very different approaches here, which are all kind of divisive in their
own way.
So it seems that no matter who wins, it's not going to solve any problems.
And we kind of talked about this a couple of episodes ago, that it needs someone to
come in and really take charge of this situation and bring everyone together, but maybe that's
just impossible.
Soterios Johnson Clearly, Carter and Gupta have the most experience
with Debian.
Gupta has been a Debian member for about seven years.
Carter has been in the development field for a long time, but also been in Debian the project
itself for quite a while.
And then Chandran is new, she's been a developer since May of 2019 and a maintainer of a package
on Debian since 2016.
My concern is all of these candidates, while good candidates for those singular issues,
are not addressing the spectrum of problems that's going to cause this distribution to
implode upon itself.
Debian is a platform, it's more than just a couple of packages, it's more than one architecture.
Debian itself is a platform.
It's an entire operating system that uses the Linux kernel, really, and the GPL land.
I don't feel like any of them are looking at it from that perspective.
And additionally, the only one that seems to actually have the experience and a somewhat
decent platform seems to be Carter.
So there only really seems to be one candidate here who has the goal for technical excellence
and making the community easier and more straightforward to contribute and participate in, and remove
bottlenecks for new contributors, and work on attending to some of the basic housekeeping
items of the Debian project that have been neglected.
Carter is the only one that's addressing all of those, and I don't normally hit this so
hard.
In fact, we've covered Debian elections twice now on this show before, and I've never hit
it this hard before.
But I cannot stress this fact enough.
If you are not paying attention to what's happening to the Debian project, you need
to wake up and pay attention to what's happening.
And this matters.
This election for the Debian project, it matters more than any of these we've ever covered
before in the 13 years that I've been on air covering Debian news.
Well, I wouldn't go that far as to say that the project's doomed or anything, but I think
it is in serious trouble, and whoever wins this does need to bring it together.
I think reading through the platforms, you're probably right.
I would probably vote for Jonathan Carter, but I do worry that he's going to kind of
leave behind the people who want to see more diversity and stuff.
And this system D situation that's been bubbling again, there's not really any mention of that
in any of these platforms here, so that's going to have to be dealt with.
It does seem like they're going to be testing times ahead, and I just don't have huge confidence
reading through these three that any of them are going to be able to manage it.
I foresee them not doing more than one term, put it that way.
This definitely comes from a place of passion for me.
I am oddly enough extremely passionate about the Debian project.
I think it's just an essential, essential part of the free software ecosystem.
And I think to play nice, everyone has sort of glossed over how bad this has gotten.
And to your earlier point, one of the reasons why I think they are quite doomed is it's
too late.
The conversations are too far along to just shut individuals out.
These people need and deserve representation because they are now officially parts of the
project, and their viewpoints have to be heard.
And if they're ignored, it's just going to irritate the problem that much worse, and
it's going to slow things down that much more.
I think we've probably hit this maybe even harder than we need to, but I think what I
am worried is, is that I'm going to spend the next two years on the air, or longer,
I don't know how long, documenting the collapse of this distribution.
And that, it literally chokes me up and makes me sick to my stomach to think about that.
I don't think it's going to collapse.
I think that it's going to change, and that change may well be for the worse, but I don't
think it's just going to go away after 20-odd years of being around.
Yeah, I suppose you're right.
After all, I think I have family members who still watch VHS.
I think my mom's still got some somewhere.
Well, from the free software end of Linux to completely the other end, this week we
saw the announcement of the Works with Chromebook stickers.
Well, it is Gen 2 after all, Joe, just not as we know it.
Not as we know it.
These are, much like other manufacturers that have Works with, it's a similar idea where
Google will actually test the accessories to ensure they comply with Chromebooks, and
then they put a badge on there.
And then you know that it's good to go with a Chromebook.
I do like this from the standpoint of Chromebooks are great for family members that don't need
a Windows or a Mac machine for their computer uses, and Chromebooks kind of work well for
that.
And now you can just point them at a category of chargers and keyboards and other accessories
like cables and adapters that are all tested by Google to work with the Chromebook.
It's kind of a nice idea.
Yeah, and my first thought was if it's going to work with a Chromebook, it's going to work
with basically any Linux distro.
That's what I was just going to say, and there's some nice stuff on here.
You know, Logitech has some devices like webcams and headsets that are supposedly going to be
certified to work with Chromebooks, which really means, and that's why I made the Gen 2 joke,
they're working with the Linux kernel because that's where these drivers are implemented.
Yeah, so this is ultimately something we've talked about for a long time, which is having
a Works with Linux sticker, which is effectively what we're talking about here.
It might be through the back door and, you know, there might be some proprietary stuff
on top of Linux that Google is controlling and capturing all your data, but ultimately
you will be able to walk into a bricks and mortar shop, look around at the accessories
and know what is going to actually work with Linux.
I mean, these days, most of it is just going to work anyway, but this way you'll actually
know.
Yep.
You can pay a little extra for the USB-C charger right next to the same exact thing that doesn't
have the sticker.
That'll be great.
Oh, what's this?
Oh, I see a sticker on their website for Works with Fuchsia.
No, I'm kidding.
That'll be in the future.
One day.
One of the things that family members have often needed is the ability to print and scan,
and that's where it gets a little weird with Chromebooks, but it appears Chrome OS will
soon get a print management app that just simply allows Chrome OS users to view and
manage native local print jobs.
And because why not, Google seems like they're also slamming in a scanner UI into the print
manager app so you can also interact and scan with a connected scanner.
Honestly, that's like the number one missing feature for family members that have Chromebooks.
So I would not be surprised if they are just slowly incorporating different user feedbacks
from schools and general user communities and just checking these features off in Chrome
OS over time.
Yeah, and eventually it's just going to become yet another full blown Linux distro.
It started out as just a browser and look how far they've come.
Yeah, it truly is a full blown desktop operating system now with window management, Linux apps,
a printer and scanner UI.
The only thing it's missing is a way for me to set up my modem.
Yeah, and I don't know how they're going to solve the problem of not being able to connect
to your printer because I don't think I've ever seen a Chromebook with a serial port
on it.
Oh, boy.
There you go.
There's no serial port.
No, it's fine.
I have an adapter so I can use my parallel port.
Right.
But in slightly more serious news, Chrome and Chrome OS updates are going to be paused
because of this virus situation.
They are going to continue to offer security updates.
That's kind of what they're concentrating on, which I think is quite a sensible approach
in these testing times.
So you're telling me that somehow the coronavirus is delaying Chrome OS releases?
I find this to be a fascinating limitation in the Google infrastructure.
I wonder if it's one that's a technical limitation.
Is it a security limitation?
What is it that prevents them from issuing Chrome OS updates when staff are not physically
in the office?
Well, I am assuming here, based on no evidence, that they are just planning here.
This is contingency planning because people might be taking time off and people might
be getting sick or whatever.
It just seems like if they put this out there now and just say, look, there's not going
to be any Chrome OS updates or any major updates to the Chrome browser, but we will prioritize
security updates, it means even if they end up with a skeleton staff, they'll still be
able to do that.
So I think it's quite a sensible approach, really.
I see what you're saying.
So it's not so much that they can't mission impossible into a central chamber that has
a button that has to be pressed with a retina ID authorization.
It's more like our staff are just dispersed, we're kind of unproductive, so we'll just
focus on security for now.
Yeah, I think so.
All right.
I like the mission impossible visual, but I think you're right.
In the meantime, I'm looking at installing Papel, Joe.
Papel.
I'm done with Cups.
Yeah, this seems to be what Michael Sweet has been working on since he left Apple where
he was working on Cups.
He was doing that weird label printer thing, but it seems that as part of that, that was
called Lprint, this P-A-P-P-L, Papel project, has come and it's an alternative to Cups.
A Cups alternative.
I didn't even know we needed it, but now I'm uninstalling it immediately and putting Papel
on there because it supports all the major imaging formats, it supports printers that
are connected via USB or like jet direct network connections and app sockets, and it's licensed
under the Apache 2.0 license.
It'll incorporate the label printer stuff.
It also leans heavily on the IPP everywhere standard, which is the internet print protocol
and which is part of Cups as well.
It seems like it'll be a nice modern version of Cups.
I don't know why we need it, but I'm actually, I kind of joke about the whole story because
it seems like printing and modems are such a solved problem right now.
However, I'm kind of curious to see where this goes and it's one of the things that
I love about Linux and free software is that sometimes to our detriment, nothing is done
necessarily.
Like how much innovation do you think has gone into the Windows Print Spooler in the
last five years?
Yeah, probably not much.
There's really very little incentive for a commercial company like Microsoft to throw
30, 40 developers, which would cost them tons of money because these are well-paid people
on a very expensive part of the United States to update the Print Spooler, like it's just
not a priority.
It doesn't sell more licenses.
It's silly.
But in the free software land, Michael Sweet had an itch to scratch and here we are looking
at modernizing a component that many of us assumed was done.
And the great thing is, once again, you don't have to choose to use it either.
Yeah, strange.
There's competition in the space where I thought there never would be any.
So that's probably good.
Well spin down your Bitcoin mining, Joe, and focus your GPU on fighting COVID-19.
Yeah, the Folding at Home project has seen a huge resurgence in the last couple of weeks.
And now you can use those unused GPU and CPU cycles to contribute to potentially fighting
this thing.
CoreWeave, which is one of the largest Ethereum miners, has made a decision to redirect 0.2%,
which actually represents 6,000 GPUs towards Folding at Home to help fight COVID, which
is a neat way for a company like this to kind of not only get some good PR, but generally
contribute some very powerful resources to solving a problem.
Yeah, and Intel and Nvidia are encouraging people to do this as well.
There's been a massive jump of like, I think it was 30,000 people were doing it before.
Now there's an extra 400,000 and counting.
And another related story, just a quick follow up from last week, we talked about Firefox
74 having been released, and they had disabled TLS 1.0 and 1.1.
And we were kind of joking about how surely there's no websites out there that are still
using it.
Well, it turns out there are some government sites still using the old standards.
So Firefox has temporarily re-enabled TLS 1.0 and 1.1, so people can actually still
access those sites.
You know, we should have a rule on the show when we're trying to figure out who could
possibly be using ancient technology.
We should just assume it's some government in somewhere in the world.
Somewhere.
Yeah.
That's so not surprising when we think about it.
So good on Mozilla, I suppose, to revert that change.
So that way, nobody has an issue during a global pandemic getting access to information.
One other item that slipped in here that they're kind of pitching as a privacy improvement.
I think it's actually kind of a bug fix for WebRTC in general, but you be the judge.
We're now providing better privacy for web voice and video calls when you're using WebRTC.
So depending on your WebRTC session scenario, you could be actually leaking your public
IP address.
It's one of the kind of downsides to using WebRTC.
However, now Firefox has added support for MD&S ICE, which cloaks your computer's IP
with a random ID in some of those WebRTC scenarios, improving your privacy.
I think you could probably argue that maybe it should have been designed this way from
the very beginning, or you could argue it's an implementation detail and so it's a feature.
Well, either way, it's good news.
And while the world's dealing with all of this, it's business as usual for us.
So go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get future episodes.
And we'd love to hear from you, linuxactionnews.com slash contact for all the ways to get in touch.
And if you'd like my analysis on the world events going on right now, check out Unfilter.
unfilter.show.
It's back, baby.
And just to say Foss Talk Live 2020, which I've mentioned on the show before, that has
now been canceled.
I won't be doing that for pretty obvious reasons.
You can read more about that at fostalk.com.
Maybe in 2021, eh?
Well, in the meantime, we'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest
Linux and open source news.
You can find me at chrislass.com.
And you can find me at joelrest.com.
Thanks for joining us and we'll see you next week.
See you later.