Hello and welcome to Linux Action News episode 128 recorded on October 20th, 2019.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Drew.
Hello, Drew.
Good to be connected with you.
Joe is away at Ogg Camp this week.
He'll be back next week and Drew's filling in.
And Drew, we start off with a huge new release from Canonical, Ubuntu 19.10 is out.
Yeah, and it's pretty great too.
I've been using it for the past week or so in the beta and really, this is just a super
solid release.
I am astounded by how polished everything is, even when it was in beta.
Gnome Shell has reached just a new level of performance and 19.10 is one of the first
distros out of the gate to showcase that.
But also, you have your official flavors this release that are really looking good.
One of my favorites, Ubuntu Mate 19.10 goes up to the Mate Desktop 1.22.2, Evolution replaces
Thunderbird, MPV comes in to replace VLC, and there's a new updated Brisk menu as well.
But Joe's favorites, Ubuntu also gets a great update, Budgie also, Kubuntu, all around,
it's looking really great for the flavors and for the main distro.
Because really, in a sense, it's getting everything positioned and ready for 2004, the next big
LTS.
Well, yeah, they're getting everything all polished up and ready for their long term
support release and is going to have at least five years of support.
So you want to make sure that everything that goes into it is going to be rock solid.
Because with the exception of adding in backport PPAs, that's going to be what they're going
to be running for at least five years.
Yeah, and perhaps even longer with extended support could be up to a decade in some cases.
The most notable new feature in 1910 is obviously support for ZFS on route.
It's a checkbox in the graphical installer.
It is heavily couched as experimental in all caps in the installer.
So they really want you to know that you are taking your data into your own hands when
you try it.
But under the hood, they're working on some really sophisticated layout options that as
you would expect, accommodate not just the desktop, but also different kinds of server
deployments, some that are automated that are clustered, as well as putting a layer
in there called ZSYS, which will take care of a few of the fundamentals and works with
things like a patched version of grub that allow you to boot directly from ZFS on your
root partition.
But even further from that down the road, you may be able to select snapshots of your
system like you currently select kernels after you do an update.
Something goes wrong, you reboot, select a two hour earlier snapshot, everything's right
back to where it was.
Right.
And this is a feature that they are trying to borrow from the BSD world, something called
boot environments, where you literally select the snapshot that ZFS took prior to you doing
some crazy system upgrade or really just anything that could be a breaking change and allows
you to just essentially roll back to the snapshot that you had before.
It's a really good technology and I'm really looking forward to them integrating that into
the system.
I think it's going to be a game changer for Ubuntu down the line.
Well, the idea would be that when 2004 ships, things like kernel updates and major system
updates are no longer going to take your system out.
It's going to make that much safer in an enterprise environment to deploy those updates.
So there's a lot of really important things there, but there's so many other benefits
like really good file system compression that can actually improve boot time and file read
access, incredible data management options.
I couldn't do it proper justice, but Jim Salter does in TechSnap 4.14.
Go to TechSnap.Systems slash 4.14 and listen to rooting for ZFS.
I think one of my favorite moments in that episode was when Jim explained how snapshots
work in a way that is so totally understandable and it really clicked in my head why it doesn't
consume tons and tons of disk space and why in some circumstances a snapshot can happen
so quickly and how you really could just make it part of a package update script.
So such a great episode TechSnap.Systems slash 4.14.
Once you get 1910 installed, it is important to go ahead and do a full upgrade because
there is an important kernel fix that was released after those images were spun.
Yeah, it's an embarrassing bug too because it reminds me of a bug on Windows way back
in the day where you could just blue screen a Windows system by sending it some packets
of data.
This is on that level and it took a little while for people to catch on to this bug because
initially it was reported as a WireGuard bug and then we came to realize it's actually
a kernel bug in the IPv6 stack and yeah, it's an issue.
It's worth upgrading because people can just crash your machine.
Yeah, definitely.
You want to keep those machines nice and safe.
We gave our first impressions in Linux Unplugged last week and since then we've been benchmarking
a ZFS 1910 system versus an Extended 4 1910 system and how it performs in low memory conditions
and just on like an average SSD, not like a super nice crazy MV&E, but we went and got
like an EvoDrive that we've had for a couple of years and in that batch of testing one
of the things I've discovered is that Canonical did spin an image for the Raspberry Pi 4,
the 32-bit and a 64-bit.
As we record the 64-bit version has an issue with, well, USB devices don't work, but it's
reported and it's in their bug tracker.
32-bit for my testing does not suffer, so the 32-bit image, you put that on Raspberry
Pi 4 and you've got 1910 running on this tiny little arm board and that's going to be a
really interesting story as well as 2004 comes out and we have a lot more types of arm devices
on the market including the Pi 4, but also including Amazon's new bare metal arm instances.
Yeah, this looks really cool.
They're calling it the A1 family and it is powered by Graviton processors.
I love these names, Drew.
I know, right?
I mean a Graviton processor?
That sounds like something that would be in Star Trek.
Yeah, it totally does.
Graviton is saying that it's a great fit for scale-out workloads including web front-ends,
containerized microservices or caching fleets.
Right, and in some workloads they say you'll get a 45% cost savings because they're running
these machines for less money and for the right applications it could make a lot of
sense, including developers who are starting development on ARM can now move that ARM code
up to machines running on EC2.
This is a pretty big deal when Amazon starts doing this because it's one thing when Joe's
hosting says, oh, by the way, I have ARM servers, but for Amazon to put this out in AWS where
you can spin it up in minutes, this is a big boost for ARM.
Right.
When you are on EC2 you're also part of their entire stack of their monitoring and their
messaging their entire ecosystem and the thing that's nice about having this on Metal is
you run your own distro and they write even in their announcement about it just run a
distribution like Ubuntu, Red Hat, Enterprise Linux, SUSE Linux, Enterprise Server or Debian
and of course Amazon's Linux 2 is available as well and you tie that in with their whole
orchestration and management platform and if you're a shop there's a lot of them out
there these days that has nearly their entire data center on Amazon.
This is just now one more system you can deploy and I think it's going to be a big boom for
ARM code on Linux as well which is really still not quite up to parity with the x86
counterpart.
That's true but changes are coming and Docker has announced support for ARM based architectures
with their Docker Enterprise Edition.
So while it feels like ARM support has been growing slowly it is really starting to get
there and I think the future holds of just a world of possibilities for ARM.
Yeah imagine like the edge network stuff a lot of enterprise-grade applications that
are just doing a couple of things here and there and they don't need an entire stack
but that hasn't necessarily translated to big profits for IBM in the enterprise in fact
IBM has missed their estimates even as Red Hat was added didn't really offset the declines
their total revenue was down 3.9% from a year earlier.
Analysts had forecast 18.2 billion dollars and IBM got close but just missed it and doesn't
really seem like Red Hat made a huge difference does it?
No it doesn't but I kind of have to wonder how quickly did they expect the Red Hat purchase
to really change things and turn it around at IBM.
These kinds of acquisitions are big business and they do take time to really start taking
effect.
Absolutely in fact in a way like they should be getting a pat on the back for it not being
worse during a merger like everything's crazy you know people are figuring out their stuff
I mean I can only imagine our merger had lots of little details we had to sort out and we
were a tiny little company and this is Red Hat.
There's so many things they have to sort there's so many additional meetings the cognitive
overhead of a merger at this scale is massive and so I mean in one way you could spin this
and say I'm surprised that they weren't much worse but I think it does also represent what
kind of a small impact Red Hat's revenues make to IBM's bottom line because this is
really the first time we've seen Red Hat included in the results since the 2018 purchase so
like we see the first results of this in this quarter and it's kind of well it's nothing
yet it really is nothing yet but I think you're right time will tell won't it?
It will and to be fair Red Hat's revenue was up from what it was projected at this year.
Realistically I think that the Red Hat merger is showing promise I think we just need to
give it a little more time yeah and in fact Chief Financial Officer Jim Cavanaugh said
in an interview that he expects IBM will be back to a sustained level of revenue growth
in 2020.
Yeah look we love to give IBM a hard time a little bit because they're sort of the suits
but there's other factors here that are maybe things that we don't track as clearly and
that's things like foreign currency and how the shifts in the foreign currency markets
can just affect IBM's overall results or their global IT company starts having poor performance
in Ireland for the last few quarters and it has impacted their results and none of it
has anything to do with Red Hat or what their success is in the cloud.
Really and you also have to take into account that IBM is massive they have all kinds of
departments doing all kinds of different things and if any one of them underperforms from
what they were projected that does affect the total company's bottom line.
You know Drew when you say all that global markets and currencies and all of this it
man it really strikes me how far open source software has come like it's powering massive
massive businesses now and time really does tell all stories so we'll see where this
goes and now we have an update with Samsung's grand attempt to put Linux on DeX and it's
not good.
Yeah bad news coming from Samsung they sent out an email to all of the Linux for DeX beta
participants saying that they are ending support for Linux on DeX.
Now if you're listening you're going what the heck is DeX guys well this debuted back
in 2017 with the Samsung Galaxy S8 it let you get a desktop mode UI when you put it
in their special DeX station which had connectors on the back of it and then later with the
launch of the Galaxy Note 9 they made it work with any HDMI to USB-C type cable which meant
you didn't need the dock anymore and they also started testing Linux on DeX which enabled
the user to get a full-fledged Linux desktop running on the smartphone in DeX mode specifically
Linux on DeX supported a modified Ubuntu 1604 LTS for ARM 64.
Yeah and it looks like that program is going away with Android 10 they have noted that
Linux on DeX will not be supported on Android 10 beta once you update your device to Android
OS 10 you will not be able to perform a version rollback to Android Pi if you decide to update
your device to Android 10 beta we recommend backing up before updating.
Yeah this is not going to be a thing anymore.
They decided not to graduate it to a product you know they tried it out as a beta and they
said now we're not going to do it to be honest I never really saw the appeal I mean if you
look at me I might be the perfect ideal candidate to buy something like this like I like getting
me a fancy smartphone I love the idea of a mobile usable workstation that's in my pocket
I'd be willing to invest in a dock I mean a hell I bought Thunderbolt docks I'll buy
a DeX dock even if I had to or a USB C to HDMI cable with a Bluetooth keyboard I do that
but I think just instinctively I knew it was never really going to be up to my expectations
and performance and I've come to a new a new place with how I use my mobile devices and
how I use my desktops and how I divvy up those tasks and I'm pretty comfortable with it.
I'm kind of of two minds here I think it's a really great idea the whole idea of convergence
of being able to walk around with your computer on your cell phone you plug it into a workstation
and all of a sudden you've got your desktop so you could travel from home to the office
and have the same computer without having to lug around a laptop or anything like that
it's a really cool idea but I think we also have to recognize that it's 2019 now and almost
2020 and more and more people are doing more stuff on mobile.
The mobile devices battery lives haven't significantly improved the OS is still aren't really quite
fast enough like you don't have enough horsepower to use it as a desktop apps that are designed
for mobile use like a banking app that's a mobile app that makes sense but hooking up
to a whole screen I just I don't think it's there I mean do you really think it's you
really think it is honestly I don't think it's there now but I think the potential to
make something great out of it really would be there if we hadn't seen such a global shift
towards mobile only computer over the last few years really I think that's what's killing
Linux on decks and things like Ubuntu touch which had a very similar idea but as we all
know that's one that we can say rest in peace to okay I see what you're saying you're saying
mobile has gotten competent enough that you don't need to snap it into a desktop mode
that's right I mean just look at the success of you know Chromebooks they're not running
full on Linux and granted you can get Linux apps running on them but for the most part
people are using them like bigger cell phones what's funny about this is we're both skeptics
but for totally opposite reasons see my argument is the desktop has stayed competitive has
gotten better and faster in fact in a lot of ways it's better than it's ever been when
you get a like a full rise in system and or even just a system with an AMD GPU and you
can run Wayland and you have to you didn't have to install a single driver and you get
full 3d acceleration it's really getting to be the next level now in the Linux desktop
it's it's better than it has been at any point in time that I've ever been doing this and
the hardware is getting good again as well and so are laptops they're getting really
competitive again Intel and AMD are back at each other's throats again like I feel like
the desktop and the laptop space is more competitive and has moved forward more in the last couple
of years than it has in the instance mobile became a thing and so in a sense it hasn't
stood still is just going slow for a little bit now it's in gear and so I think the gaps
getting wider again and I think you're right about that I just think that the train has
left the station as far as being able to really capture I don't want to say desktop usage
it's like that good enough usage though where it's like it's fast enough I can do everything
I need usage yeah absolutely and for most people mobile or mobile like experiences are
good enough what do most people want they want to check their email they want to browse
the web it's the people like us the people who like to mess with computers who really
love this stuff right yeah all right I agree and I I think that's why the Linux for decks
didn't quite click for me because it was clearly going after the more advanced user being Linux
and the fact that you had to go get this thing and install it on your phone and even know
that it had this capability to begin with all of those probably put you in a more advanced
category and then when you get to that category well we got a whole heck of requirements you
know we got a whole bunch of requirements the first thing is somebody's gonna want to
put i3 on that thing and the packages wouldn't be available they'd be out oh yeah absolutely
but you know all is not lost there is Maru OS still out there and they're still targeting
convergence so you know people who do still have that dream where you can walk around
with your computer in your pocket and just connect it up to something and get going it's
not completely dead yet well drew my dream is software distribution that's truly safe
we're not there yet it looks like a crypto jacking worm was found inside images on DockerHub
yeah this is bad news for DockerHub and the Docker project at large having this kind of
malware attack the system is not a good thing now to their credit I can't find any of these
Docker images on DockerHub anymore so it does look like they've been pulled but who knows
if they've uploaded some other malicious images under some other name so this graboid malware
works kind of interestingly and kind of wonky at the same time it carries out its worm spreading
and crypto jacking by randomly picking three targets on each run iteration it installs
the worm on the first target it stops the miner on the second target and it starts
the miner on a third target this procedure leads to a random kind of mining behavior
and if a host is compromised the malicious container doesn't necessarily start immediately
so you don't necessarily see anything at boot time that would draw your attention the container
runs for a little bit and then the other compromised hosts can randomly stop other mining processes
so essentially the miner on every infected host is randomly controlled by all the other
infected hosts and unit 42 the people who discovered the worm said that they really
can't determine why the miners are deployed and run and stopped so randomly is it just
bad design or do they have some other goal that we don't necessarily understand yet
palo alto networks has a great breakdown that we will have linked in the show notes at linuxactionnews.com
slash 128 when you look at the overall scale of docker hub this issue still kind of remains
to be a little more on the theoretical edge i know it's even like you know nearly 10,000
image downloads have happened so it's real and that's a lot of people but docker image
deployments are on the scale of millions in some cases even billions and just like in
the aur there is the theoretical risk which there has been bad stuff in the aur before
if you use the entire suite of tools around the software including looking at how many
other downloads or in this case polls or looking at the comments or all the other attributes
you can analyze like publishers etc you are able to build a more complete picture and
essentially get a better idea of if you can trust the author or not and you combine that
with industry best practices and it just doesn't really feel like a huge issue to me it's not
one that i worry about on my systems but i'm also willing to put a few minutes of research
into an image before i deploy it on a production system well yeah you absolutely have to if
you want to stay secure you can't just trust everything you see out there you want to make
sure that your images or software are coming from reputable sources at the very least well
let's talk about the hard time google's been giving free software projects that are attempting
to raise donations two fairly important projects were removed from the play store this week
we start with and otp and otp was pulled from the google play store by google after they
introduced a donation button and it cost a bit of a stir this is an open source project
that is not necessarily wanting to charge for itself but would like to allow people
to give money to it and google says that's not okay i also i kind of don't like this
because in both circumstances the one we're about to talk about and this one these applications
improve the android ecosystem security and otp is a fabulous two-factor authentication
app for android and it supports devices down to 4.4 which a lot of developers have abandoned
at this point and it's a solid implementation of a time-based one-time password or other
systems as well you got an hmac based one you can just scan the qr code it automatically
will get all of that set up it's a really nice user experience and the developer is
just trying to make it sustainable i completely agree i don't see anything wrong with having
some kind of donation service within an app that just lets people give back to a project
especially one as beneficial as and otp or wire guard which was also removed from the
google play store for the same thing this is really upsetting because again wire guard
is some really great software personally one of my favorite open source projects in the
last couple of years and a similar story here they added a link to wire guard dot com slash
donations which we should all go to now that google has forced them to remove it just adding
that link which would open the user's web browser to do a donation google so it was
in violation of their payment policy in the google play store yes and both projects are
back up on google play now that they've removed their donation links but really how bad is
it to have a donation button i mean they're not forcing people to pay for the software
they're not doing anything other than just routing people to a website that asks for
a little bit of money it's really unfortunate especially when you're just talking about
a link that opens the web browser i mean for goodness sakes the ios version has it it's
nice and prominent with a little heart emoji in the setting screen and you tap it and it
opens up a web browser to their donate page ios has it like it feels like this should
be a story about apple and here we're talking about google in my opinion these actions have
elevated f-droid to a whole nother level of prominence in the open source community thank
goodness we have another alternative and one that is friendly to open source because during
both of these pollings from the play store f-droid of course kept the apps with the donation
links absolutely and i personally think that it shows a lot of backwards thinking on the
part of google with more and more software going towards services like patreon to support
themselves we really need to be helping these businesses generate revenue in ways that are
friendly towards the open source community the lead wire guard developer jason donofield
commented quote we won't be making any similar changes unless we are certain that we won't
be delisted again yeah i couldn't see any way for them to survive if they're not in
the play store i mean granted the technology itself would survive in servers and desktops
and ios but if people aren't able to take advantage of it on android they're gonna go
somewhere else yeah they'll use something that's perhaps proprietary or it's a some
weird implementation that spies on them wire guard is good audited free software that implements
really good crypto and a great vpn technology and i think as we start to see really solid
commercial solutions wrapped around it it's going to be a no-brainer and eventually it'll
be just a detail you'll get an app that uses wire guard and you'll just have the peace
of mind of knowing that the underlying software is open source and has been reviewed and is
continued to be reviewed and i think that's the real long-term benefit that wire guard
offers even average users on android they may not even know they're using it but they'll
get something that's good reliable that supports a mobile connection way better than current
vpns do with its super easy handling of getting disconnected and reconnected it's just an
up and down of an interface and it it makes it so smooth i could go on and on obviously
i love it and i just think it's critically important that google supports things like
two-factor authentication and vpn technologies and pulling these two applications simply
because they had links to donations well it's it's a clear step beyond what even apple would
do and i i just don't know where that leaves us because of the prominence of the play store
it leaves me uncomfortable well when these types of stories break we cover them in linux
headlines like both of these stories you get the information and then you get the analysis
here linux headlines dot show every weekday a new episode in three minutes or less and
fridays with drew that's right quickly becoming one of my favorite shows yes and also check
out choose linux drew is one of three hosts on choose linux choose linux dot show you
guys just released an episode on small board computers which i have queued up for my drive
home featuring special guest cheese bacon yeah you gotta catch that of course get every
single episode of this here show check out linux action news dot com slash subscribe
for all the ways to get new episodes and if you want to get in touch with us head over
to linux action news dot com slash contact joe and i'll be back next monday with our
weekly take on the latest linux and open source news i am at chris las and i'm at drew of
doom thanks for joining us we'll see you next week