Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 151, recorded on March 29th, 2020. I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe. Good to be connected with you. Have you noticed the web just seems a little
better this week?
Well, it is, according to Mozilla. They've launched a new test pilot, Firefox for a better
web.
Yeah. I mean, I like a better web. Who doesn't want a better web? So, Scroll, if you recall,
is a $5 a month service that stops ads from loading on certain websites. But what's interesting
about it, it's not technically an ad blocker, but rather it lets publishers know that for
this user, they shouldn't serve ads in the first place when you visit.
Now, while they're rolling this up, by the way, I will mention just here on the side,
for right now, the price is actually $2.50. So, I guess it's a sale. It's an extension
we're talking about here that Mozilla's introducing, which would technically work in other browsers.
But the experience, they say, is best in Firefox. And the extension includes Scroll as well
as a, quote, customized enhanced tracking protection setting that will block third-party
trackers, fingerprinters, and crypto miners. You know, the kind of setting that should
be turned on by default, but that's according to Mozilla. It will work across different
desktop browsers, but that aspect might be Firefox only for now.
This deal with Mozilla should get Scroll, in theory, a much larger user base, but neither
company would actually disclose what the financial terms were.
Yeah, so it'll block all the tracking except for Scroll, who will be tracking which of
these websites you're visiting so they can divvy up the money that you're paying proportionally
among the websites that they support.
Yeah, at this point, it's not really clear what the extent of that data is. Obviously,
you need to know how long you spent reading an article to proportionally pay that publisher.
This whole thing kind of reminds me of like the Brave Rewards system, but there just hasn't
been a huge adoption of that where this, with Mozilla behind it, could see some adoption.
Like if you look right now, it's pretty light. The Verge, for example, is part of it, but
most websites aren't. And right now, that hasn't changed. There hasn't been a lot of
velocity there. Mozilla's stepping in, giving it their seal of approval. Maybe that changes
things.
Well, yeah, this is a huge vote of confidence in Scroll as a solution to the problem of
how to pay publishers without loads of tracking and advertising. And surely, that vote of
confidence is going to bring more publishers on board. That's if Mozilla still is relevant
and Firefox is relevant. Is it relevant enough still? I don't know.
Well, the problem seems to be very relevant. This is an issue that goes back as old as
the web. How do you monetize content that people expect to read for free? Some publishers
with a large audience, like the Wall Street Journal and the New York Times, have been
successful at a paywall, while most publishers are not. Without a good answer to this question,
the industry seems to have relied on very privacy invasive techniques to really track
you across all properties, to really properly monetize you. And it never really reflected
on the value of content. In fact, it sort of encouraged, well, not sort of, it absolutely
encouraged clickbait, because more views equals more ad dollars. Whereas a system like this
rewards quality content. The more time you actually spend reading and digesting an article,
the more they get paid.
I think the key to how this is different from Brave is that we're talking about actual
cash here, rather than Brave, which is tokens and, let's face it, magic internet beans.
Yeah. I think for this to really take traction with the publishers, they've got to return
real money. Maybe it's not as much as advertising, but in some cases, for some sites, maybe it
would be more. They've got to really deliver results. And then I think publishers would
be all in. This is a win-win. Publishers get rewarded for good content. They don't have
to cow-toe to advertisers. And users win out because pages load faster, they use less battery
life on mobile, they take less bandwidth, and they're less privacy invasive.
Or you could just use an ad blocker.
Yeah. No, I mean, you joke, but I think that's a fair point. And that's free, right? And
it's all publishers.
Yeah. I haven't seen an ad on a website for a long time.
Yeah. And I hope, man, I hope that publishers understand that's who they're really competing
with. There's some analogy here to when the iTunes MP3 store launched at 99 cents a track
when you could go on LimeWire and download them for free. They had to make it super easy,
they had to make it convenient, and they had to make it a reasonable price. And then users
switched to the actual commercial legitimate versions. Something like that could happen
here. But I think publishers need to remember their real competition is not things like
Brave or Scroll or whatever you want to call it. It is truly ad blockers.
Yeah, I think the iTunes analogy isn't quite right. I think Spotify is more spot on there
really because there's the free tier where you can, again, listen to adverts. And I think
that is what killed music piracy more than iTunes.
Streaming killed the download star, you're saying?
Yeah, pretty much.
Yeah, I could see it.
But the thing is that we already have this free, convenient way to not see adverts that
involves just installing an extension, which it seems not just tech savvy people are switched
on to. So how can they make this a thing? You've got this kind of problem here in that
you need to have all the publishers on board for it to really have value. Whereas if you've
only got a handful, then that $2.50 or $5 a month doesn't seem worth it. And I think
you've also got to convince people that they need to support good journalism and good content
generally and make the argument that using an ad blocker is ultimately going to lead
to clickbait and just lower the quality of the web. And this is something I suppose Mozilla
should be doing. This is within their remit. Whether it's going to work or not, I don't
know. But who else is going to drive this forward but Mozilla?
But taking a data approach to it as well. We'll have links in the show notes, but it appears
that Mozilla has been running pilots that indicate that 18% of the test users after
the free period opted to subscribe. Now, 18% doesn't sound like a lot, but when you consider
that the industry average is 3% and 5% is considered a massive success, 18% would suggest,
and Mozilla makes this assumption, that users reflect the value in paying for good journalism.
And if we give them an easy way to monetize good journalism, they'll take it.
But once again, this is only available in the USA for now, as is this way with all of
the new things that Mozilla seem to be coming out with for Firefox. And at the moment, it
is a test pilot, but that could change relatively soon. They seem to move fairly quickly with
these things.
Well, something that's available to anyone that has a Raspberry Pi 4 is Plasma Big Screen.
Now I know that all your Raspberry Pi 4s are velcroed down in your dinette, whatever that
is.
Quite literally, yes.
But I've got one kicking around, so I tested this. And what it is, is a big screen experience,
as the name suggests. It is the plasma shell, but it's not a plasma desktop. It's using
the same technologies that make the plasma desktop. And it's designed to be a 10-foot
UI for smart TVs, or give you that smart TV experience, so you could turn any TV into
it.
Well, my monitor has got HDMI in and some really terrible speakers, so I was able to
test it as if it was a TV. And they're calling this a beta. I think that's a bit generous,
to be honest. It felt alpha quality to me. But I like what they're doing, and I think
it's got potential, but it does need a lot of work.
Now what I didn't mention is the Mycroft integration, which is heavy. That integration is integral
to it. As soon as you turn it on, Mycroft starts talking at you, making you register
it as a Mycroft device. So I had to create an account, and I had to type this alphanumeric
thing in and register it. And that finally made it shut up.
Did you try any voice commands?
I did, but the Raspberry Pi doesn't have a microphone, right? So therefore, you need
to plug a microphone into it. So I plugged my audio interface that I'm talking to you
over now into it, went into the settings, selected it, and nothing. It just didn't seem
to be working with it. And I don't know. I tried everything, and I was like, hey, Mycroft,
hey, Mycroft. And it just would not listen to me. I even tried talking to it in an American
accent, and that didn't work. So maybe my accent was not good enough.
What does that sound like?
Hey, Mycroft. And it just wouldn't have it.
Yeah, that's totally it. Well, so the idea here is that Mycroft offers what are so-called
quote unquote skills. Each skill takes care of a particular voice interaction. They say
there's a large variety from weather to date and time and reminders to online service clients
and integrations with things like SoundCloud and YouTube. And they can display information
using QML inside this big picture, big screen environment. For people listening that want
to kind of conceptualize what it looks like, of course, you can just check out the links
in the show notes. But if you have an Android television, specifically of the Nvidia Shield
variety, this is like a really clean version of that. If you took out all of the trying
to push like game stream and different services and just focused on that UI, this is what
you would have a nice, clean implementation of it. But I'm not surprised to hear it's
early days. These TV interfaces are surprisingly fiddly and they take a lot of work. I feel
like they have a pretty good base, though. The Raspberry Pi 4 is a solid device to target.
I am so impressed, even months into using them for production servers. I am impressed
and I'm picky and I'm impressed. It's also using KDE neon for the base. So it's a great
way to get new cute and plasma libraries in there. And then Libre CEC or Lib CEC, which
allows you to control your big screen TV with remote control. And they've tried to bring
these things together along with their completely open UI stack to give you an open UI for your
television. Is it family ready? Does it have that spousal approval factor? I don't think
so. But I am really pleased to see something in this space that isn't Kodi. Not that Kodi
isn't fantastic, but it's one project.
Well, that's where I was going to go next with this. Do we need this? We have Kodi fully
open source. The brand might be a little tainted by piracy and stuff, but it is a very, very
functional open source, full screen, big screen TV experience. Do we really need something
from the KDE team for this space?
Yes, I'll tell you why. Kodi is so great. If I have a library that I want to point Kodi
at and I want to watch media, man, there's just no better TV video player on the planet
than Kodi. However, if your interest is more things like Netflix or Twitch or Plex or YouTube,
or if Kodi is just one of the many things you want to do with your set top box and you
don't want it to be the entire set top box experience, that's where this fits in. And
to be honest with you, Joe, it's why I still use an Nvidia Shield. I have Kodi as one of
the apps. And when the job calls for Kodi, I use Kodi. But on that same box, I also
have VLC. I also have an actual official Netflix app. I have an official YouTube app. I have
an official Plex app. These are for me, cornerstone pieces to the living room. And I know there's
plugins that would offer me that same basic functionality in Kodi, but it's not good enough
for me. And it's really not good enough for the family. Truth be told, it's probably good
enough for me. And that's where I could see this UI that you implement on a Raspberry
Pi 4 instead of something that's like an Nvidia Shield that's hundreds of dollars and not
even available in every country. Once it gets good enough, this could replace that kind
of functionality. I think my assessment's in line with yours based on what I've seen
so far. It's not there yet, but I am tempted to fire it up on a new Pi.
Yeah, it's something that I want to play with more, especially I want to try and get the
Minecraft stuff going, but I wonder whether they'll ever get official Netflix apps and
stuff like that for it. That seems a bit farfetched to me. If you can't even get Kodi working
properly and consistently and not breaking all the time with Netflix, then are you really
going to get an official app on a new open source TV interface? It seems unlikely.
Yeah, probably not. I suppose the best option might be a well-presented web UI.
Which is good enough. That's how I use Netflix. So if it was properly embedded, it would be
fine, I think. And it is basically just a Plasma desktop underneath, so there's no reason
they can't do that.
You make a good point, actually. And I think you're touching on something that as a community
we are not discussing because it's very uncomfortable. And that is a lot of the things we want to
watch are wrapped up in proprietary services and proprietary apps. And the web experience
is there, but it is not the same. Like if I'm just thinking about our home television
experience, I have Amazon Prime because I've had Prime forever. I have CBS All Access because
I'm going to pay for the development of Future Trek. That's just who I am. Even if I don't
watch it via that service, I'm going to pay for it. So I have the app, and when it's available
I like it. I like to watch the behind the scenes stuff and the little mini shows via
their app. Netflix, yep, I got that. YouTube TV, too much, but yep, I got it. These are
all proprietary streaming services that are wrapped up in proprietary apps that are available
for iOS and Android that have web versions that are OK, some of them not even optional.
And then there's even more services that have launched just this year. Disney Plus is an
example of one that my kids love. Peacock from NBC is about to launch. There's a Hulu
app. There's Spotify apps. All of these are available in some form or another via the
web, but it's a new experience. And it's just not what you're down for when you sit down,
you turn on the television, you just want to hit a button on your remote and start enjoying
content. And I think fundamentally the issue is these different service providers, if you'll
call them that, these, that's essentially what they are. They're content as a service.
They just can't be bothered to make desktop apps for Linux. And so it's hard for projects
like Plasma Big Screen to integrate them. And Kodi kind of gets around that with some
hacky plug-ins here and there, but it's not 100%. And as a community, we're just not really
talking about this. Maybe we don't have an answer. Well, I tend to use the web version
of everything. Like the Amazon one's fine. Netflix one's fine. I don't have many of the
other services, but I think they're good enough as a kind of stopgap, certainly for people
like me who don't mind the odd little glitch here and there. But I think for that kind
of spousal approval, family friendly thing, maybe it's not going to be good enough. Well,
even just the TV experience, because I would, I would bet you're probably what, doing that
on a laptop or a desktop? Yeah, this is on a desktop with a big monitor essentially,
like a TV. Yeah. It's different when you're on a couch and you're 10 feet away, like what
this is exactly positioned for. And you're doing it with a remote that has, you know,
a directional control and a select button. Yeah, which I didn't have one of those to
try this out. I was just using the wireless keyboard, which I always use. And you can
just use the arrow buttons and enter to kind of emulate that. But then you can also alt
tab and stuff to some extent on this. So you can see it's desktop routes in there. Ultimately,
these challenges that we've just highlighted won't be resolved unless there is a demand
for that content in that layout. And it's projects like this that will get us there.
And so I will probably give it a go at some point. I may wait a few months for development,
but I could see here at the studio where it's just me and Wes mostly. This would be perfect.
Well, you probably want to get off that Nvidia shell because it's running Android and Android
is terribly insecure, isn't it? Hey, apparently. Although thankfully, they haven't figured
out that you go after television apps yet. But two different malware detection vendors,
just as a broad category this week, are making a bunch of noise about apps in the Google
Play Store that are riddled with spyware, I guess, monitoring, monetization techniques,
what do you even call it anymore?
Yeah, adware spyware, there's various definitions of it. But either way, I suppose crapware
is probably the best way to put it.
Yeah, one of them was in 56 different apps that they checked. A lot of them were targeted
at children, surprise, surprise. And it seems like we're looking at a 1.7 million device
install base here. There's a cool aspect to this show, real cool guy developer trick that
they did to get clicks that looked organic on the ads they were serving up. Because of
course, users aren't necessarily going to just tap ads that show up on their device,
even if they can present them to the end user doesn't mean they're going to tap them. So
if you could come up with a cool guy way to still get some clicks, then you're really
making the money. And this round of malware used Androids motion event mechanism to simulate
clicks based on just moving around in your pocket or moving around in your hand, it would
translate that to rando clicks to make it look real to advertisers. So they were able
to fraud legitimate ad services like Google's AdMob. Another couple of interesting bits
that I suppose are somewhat noteworthy. They wrote these apps in native Android languages,
you know, use Java in the right spots, use other languages in the right spots to make
it look like legitimate background apps or games. And then there's the separate group
Dr. Webb, who found a whole other batch of infected apps not even related to this using
a whole nother branch of malware called Android Circle one.
Hang on a second. What happened to the App Defense Alliance? This is something we reported
on back in November last year, where Google partnered up with three antivirus firms, ESET,
Lookout and Zimperium. And the idea of that was that they kind of pool their resources
and make sure stuff like this did not happen. They'd be scanning applications that were
submitted to the Play Store and monitoring them and working with the technology that
Google already has and avoiding this from happening. And yet I keep reading about more
and more cases where researchers are finding these malicious apps in the Play Store.
In that something three different vendors, all of which would be using their technologies
to scan play submissions before they even went live. And yet here we are. And last time
on the show when something like this came up, I just said, hands up. Android is the
new windows for end users. Don't let friends and family use Android. Guys like you who
know about lineage or people who maybe aren't looking for background changers or pop the
bubble games that are going to install Android malware. They're fine. If that's not you,
you're fine. But friends and family that are not savvy, don't let them run Android. Not
only do they end up with crap phones from carriers that generally are loaded with carrier
crap and underspect, but even if they get a good Android device, there's still hundreds
of thousands of apps that make it into the Play Store that are riddled with crap that
will make their phone slow, steal their private information and drain their battery.
That's not a good situation where someone on a Linux podcast is saying essentially use
iOS, not the Linux based phone.
It's really so sad. It took me a while to get to this point, because I wanted to think
maybe with the pixel devices and this this Android malware alliance that we talked about
in November, I thought maybe finally Google will get this together.
It's funny. I don't think I would go so far as to say use an iPhone and Android is not
secure. But I think there was a time when I would have said, just stick to the Play
Store and you'll be fine. Whereas now I think it's just stick to well-known applications.
If you're installing Facebook, WhatsApp, all of the standard stuff, then yeah, you're going
to get all the tracking that goes along with that. But at least that's big billion dollar
business tracking.
You're selling me on this. I'm really not selling myself on this. Don't go for obscure
apps essentially and read reviews. But then I suppose they can be faked as well.
And the problem is, is that is great advice for people that are the type of user that
listen to a podcast like this. But for my family members, like my aunts and uncles,
it's just completely lost on them. If it's in the Play Store, they have the expectation
that it's completely safe to install. And I would bet you my family members have been
bitten by stuff like this because I've been handed their phones at family events and they
hand them to me and they're hot to hold. And they have like two hours of battery life.
And some of them are newish. They're like some big LG device with a ginormous screen
and 15 cameras on the back. And they just got it for a great deal from the Verizon store.
But then what is Google to do? We get up in arms when they kick open source apps out because
they don't follow the rules. But if they make the rules even stricter, then it's going to
be much harder for developers to get their apps in there. Like with iOS, my understanding
is that is not straightforward at all. It's not open in the slightest in terms of getting
your apps and you have to jump through hoops to get them into that app store. But then
we don't hear many stories about malware making it through the gates. No, it's mostly those
billion dollar companies. Like there was just some story about Zoom. Even if you didn't
have a Facebook ID, the Zoom iOS app was sending your information to Facebook and they just
fixed that. But that kind of stuff happens all the time on iOS. Yeah, it's tricky because
how often do you hear about Google having an issue around executing at scale and scope?
Like that's not generally their thing. They don't generally have issues executing at scale.
But with the Play Store, it seems like they are. Well, maybe they'll have an answer for
this at Google IO. Oh, hang on. No, that's not happening this year. Ah, too soon. Yeah,
to be fair to them, it was a sensible decision. And a quick update on something that we reported
on last week, and that is Chrome and Chrome OS releases, which were paused, but it seems
only for a week because instead of just security updates, they're going to continue on with
Chrome and Chrome OS updates. So what was the point of the pause? It's not like a week
is enough time. If somebody in their area was going to get sick, it could still happen.
It's not like Corona is gone. Maybe they just were pausing to do an assessment of what resources
they had. And maybe they did the math and worked out that if a certain number of people
go down, you know, they'll be all right. So yeah, a bit strange. Yeah, you know, given
the benefit of the doubt, maybe they were preemptively over communicating expectations
saying, Hey, as we go remote, we don't know as a team what we can deliver. Oh, by the
way, we're remote. Now. I think we've got our feet underneath us. Okay, we're resuming
normal operation. Interesting, though, that Microsoft are not going to be releasing Windows
preview releases in May because of all of this. So maybe Google's a little bit more
agile than Microsoft. Oh, Microsoft always slightly behind the trends. Well, a company
that tried to ride on the trends was Telegram. And they had this huge ICR $1.7 billion of
investment. And they've been struggling ever since to get their coins out there. They call
them grams, struggling with regulators. And this week, they were dealt a serious, serious
blow, which looks like it might be the end of this project. Not just the end of the project,
but spell serious long term trouble for telegram. This week, a federal court judge sided with
the US Securities and Exchange Commission against telegram and granted a preliminary
injunction against that 1.7 billion initial coin offering. In an opinion, an order filed
on Tuesday with the New York Southern District Court read a spot in the United States that
is very aggressive against cryptocurrencies. The SEC has shown substantial likelihood of
success in proving that telegrams plan to distribute grams is offering securities, and
they have a test called the Howie test, h o w e y. So Howie Howie, and essentially anything
that meets this test is considered a securities and the telegram gram in their quote unquote
emergency filing, they have an emergency filing jokes, it's an emergency. They say it clearly
meets this test. And so they're clearly essentially trading on the idea that if you bought in
now you could sell for a higher rate later to a bunch of people, which is true. That's
hard to argue.
Yeah, that's the whole point of an ICO, right? You sell a bunch of investment in your cryptocurrency
low. And then once it launches, the value goes up. And then you cash out and make a
bunch of money. It's basic investment. But they were trying to argue that it wasn't an
investment and they just have lost.
Yeah, and the SEC is arguing the telegram knew all along. They understood that purchasers
would not be willing to pay $1.7 billion to acquire grams merely as a means to just store
and transfer value. Telegram recognized and developed a scheme according to the SEC to
maximize the amount of initial purchasers and would be willing to pay by creating a
structure to allow these purchasers to maximize the value they receive upon resale to the
market. In other words, they knew all along, they built it this way. And that proves their
case. So telegram has been served an injunction that prevents them from issuing grams or doing
anything with the cryptocurrency until after their hearing. They could fight this, but
it is extremely unlikely that telegram is going to fight this. And it is very likely
the telegram will end up having to pay the money back, which they don't have. They don't
have 1.7 billion just sitting in a bank account. The guy behind telegram is rich, but he's
not that rich. And if telegram is ordered to pay it back, they're going to face a very
particular kind of painful situation.
Yeah, I'm thinking, do we move to signal, WhatsApp or what? We use telegram heavily.
I know. It would really be a shame to see telegram go away. But I think in the back
of our minds, we've always wondered what's the end game here? What's the monetization
strategy?
Yeah, I talk to everyone on that. Like all my friends basically are on there. So I'm
sure we'll all move to something pretty quickly if it does go away. But it just seems strange
to think that all our chat history and everything will just be gone. And surely not, but $1.7
billion is a lot of money.
Time to start a people's movement to open source all the telegram.
Yeah, there's been various open source bits of it. But maybe if the back end was somehow
open sourced and federalized, we could maybe keep it going peer to peer. It seems a long
shot though.
Yeah. Plus, you know, Vlad's got a really good internet connection in his basement.
So you got to go down to Putin, you got to convince him to get the server out of there
and put it up like on DigitalOcean. It's going to cost. Well, whatever happens with this
and everything else in the world of free software, be sure to check out linuxactionnews.com
slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch with us.
And if you haven't checked in on the user error show recently, check out user error
88 error.show slash 88. It's titled well, comma, actually, and I think that explains
everything you need to know. It's a great episode of the user error program.
Yeah, I think you need to do it in the proper voice. Well, actually.
Yeah, you guys know what we're talking about. And it made me smile from beginning to end.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
You can find me at chrislass.com
And you can find me at trs.com
Thanks for joining us. And we'll see you next week.
See you later.