Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 190, recorded on May 21st, 2021. I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes. Let's do the news.
Google I.O. was this week, and there were two announcements in particular we thought
you might be interested in. First up is Chrome OS's Linux app support finally leaving beta
with the release of Chrome OS 91. Google's been adding a lot of new features during the
beta, enabling things like GPU acceleration and better support for USB drives. We learned
about this exciting status change at the end of the Chrome OS keynote at Google I.O. this
week.
Now back to Emily for a quick update on Linux before we wrap up.
Thanks, Sanjay. Regarding developing on Chromebooks, I am really pleased to announce that the Linux
development environment is going to be out of beta in our next release. There have been
a lot of updates over the last year, including a new terminal app, better USB support, configurable
port forwarding, and a whole lot of work on performance and stability. One nice improvement
is that now, when you install a Chrome OS update, your Linux container is updated at
the same time. Before, you had to wait 3, 5, or up to 15 minutes for it to update independently
after an OS update. No longer.
This is a nice example of the increasing polish happening with Linux on Chrome OS. Linux and
developing right on a Chromebook is one of my favorite features, so I love that the integration
is getting better and better.
A deeper dive into many of the topics we have touched on today, including Linux, optimizing
Android apps, building PWAs, as well as many more all about developing for and on Chrome
OS, can be found at ChromeOS.dev. With that, I would like to thank you for your continued
enthusiasm for our awesome operating system over the last 10 years, and I hope you will
be right there with us for the next 10.
After that Linux support, Google also announced that it would bring Android 11 to Chromebooks.
Technically, that update has already started with Chrome OS 90 for some select Chromebooks,
and it will just come with a whole new host of features, including increased optimization
of Android apps and a new dark theme. In fact, a big focus of Google I.O. this week was getting
Android apps ready for bigger screens.
The second announcement out of I.O. we thought you should know about is some good news for
the likes of F-Droid. Android 12 will finally let alternative app stores update their apps
on their own.
We got the first hints of this back in September, but now we're seeing signs in code that actually
enable the support. Google has updated Android's package installer session params class with
a new method called setRequireUserAction. Now, that little bit of magic there indicates
whether or not the user action will be required before an app install is allowed.
And assuming the app in question meets Google's requirements, user action won't be needed
for an app installation or update. So when an app that has met the requirements tries
to initiate an installation and it uses this new API, it'll be able to update without the
user being involved. That's pretty slick.
Our next story makes you wonder what's in store for desktop Linux because Red Hat has
opened several job positions this week that are focused around the desktop graphics stack.
A couple of the positions are focusing on upstream drivers for open source code around
Intel, AMD and Nvidia. And outside of those two graphics engineer positions, Red Hat is
also hiring a software engineer for the graphics team to be based out of the Czech Republic.
And then rounding out all of that is another opening on their Linux automotive team. So
we'll have links to the job positions and Christian's blog post that goes through all
the details in the show notes.
At the end of 2019, the developer of CUPS, the common Unix printing service for Linux
and Mac OS, Mike Sweet, left Apple. Following that, it was very noticeable that public development
of the project seemed to have come to a halt. But now, there is a major development. Seemingly
confirming their intent to no longer develop the subsystem, Apple has effectively transferred
CUPS to the Open Printing Project. Sweet presented on this change at this month's Open Printing
Summit and acknowledged that Apple stopped actively developing CUPS when he left the
company. But now, he's been contracted by Apple to apply important bug fixes from the
Open Printing fork of CUPS back to the Apple CUPS code for Mac OS.
And it seems now Open Printing is working on a new CUPS 2.4 release with AirPrint compatibility,
OAuth authentication, Package Config support, Snap support, TLS improvements, and really
a variety of other feature improvements, making CUPS 2.4 effectively the new upstream of the
market. And it seems even early plans are in the works for CUPS 3.0, which will feature
a bit of re-architecting, amongst other things.
Everyone's favorite fox learned some new tricks this week. On Tuesday, Mozilla introduced
Firefox's new Site Isolation Security Architecture. In a blog post, they wrote,
Site isolation builds upon a new security architecture that extends current protection mechanisms
by separating web content and loading each site into its own operating system process.
This new security architecture allows Firefox to completely separate code originating from
different sites and, in turn, defend against malicious sites trying to access sensitive
information from other sites you are visiting.
Basically, here's the problem. Without site isolation, the browser will load embedded
pages, whatever they might be, whether that's a bank page or an advertisement, in the same
process as the top-level document. So, in a more dangerous scenario, a malicious site
could embed a legitimate site within a subframe and then try to trick you into entering your
sensitive information. And with the current architecture, if a page contains any subframes
from a different site, they will be generally in the same process as the outer tab.
Yeah, that doesn't sound very nice. Very clean, does it? That's where site isolation
comes in. Firefox will load each site into its own process, thereby isolating their memory
from each other. And it relies on the security guarantees of your hopefully up to date and
secure operating system. And on top of security, there, of course, are other benefits to site
isolation. Poorly performing tabs won't necessarily have an impact on each other. And then there's
the aspect of more cores, right? Using more processes to load websites allows Firefox
to spread that work across CPU cores and take better advantage of the underlying hardware.
One wonders if there'll be a battery impact, but I'm all for lighting up those cores.
Mozilla is currently testing site isolation on the nightly and beta versions of the desktop
browsers with a subset of users, but should be rolling out to more desktop users soon.
If you can't wait though, you can enable it now in the nightly with an about preferences
tweak. Of course, we'll have a link in the show notes with details.
Well, believe it or not, it's been a month since we learned about the University of Minnesota's
ban from the Linux kernel and the hypocrite commit research that they were conducting.
This week, the kernel developers completed their review of all of the UMN patches. Part
of that work was addressing some of the questionable and problematic patches instead of just outright
rejecting them.
And the work on those problematic patches should land in Linux 5.13. A rather packed
pull request sent out on Thursday by Greg Grohe-Hartman noted,
The majority here is the fallout of the UMN.edu review or re-review of all the prior
submissions that resulted in a bunch of reverts along with the correct changes made. And there
is no regression of any other potential fixes that were made by those individuals. I would
like to thank the over 80 different developers who helped with the review and fixes for this
mess.
Going by git activity from the UMN.edu address, it looks like the kernel developers pulled
37 patches from a diverse set of subsystems, stuff like ulsa, media, networking, and more
than a few others. But for a little context, that's 37 reverts out of 150 plus total patches
from UMN developers over the last few years. We'll link to Michael Harbel's post that
goes through the patch comments and a few choice explanations he found for some of the
problems with those patches.
Linode.com slash LAN go there to receive $100 in 60 day credit towards a new account. And
of course, you support the show. Linode is the largest independent cloud computing provider.
And no matter what skill level you're at, Linode is going to work for you. They're our
hosting provider. Linode is like our secret member of our team. We get the presence and
the performance and the reliability of a large enterprise company while still being a small
team. It's like I outsourced all my data center stuff to Linode. And it's perfect that way.
They let me focus on what JB does best. And they have a simple cloud infrastructure that's
crazy fast, and is built from the ground up around Linux. You know, they have been around
since 2003. So they picked each thing they've done, and they focused in on it since then
and they've just really gotten good. So performance, they've they've figured that out and they've
really got fast systems, native SSD storage, 40 gigabit connections to the hypervisor,
their dedicated CPU rigs have AMD epic processors that just crushed the competition. But their
dashboard is so straightforward that even if you're not an expert at this kind of stuff,
you're going to find it very approachable. And then on top of that, they have a bunch
of guides and tutorials, and then the best support in the business. Additionally, they
have services around that hosting like s3 compatible object storage, which could really
up your backup game or your config offsite game or just setting up a static website.
They have cloud firewalls and simple one click deployments of lots of common open source
application stacks, and so much more. So I really want to encourage you to go try out
that $100 because that's a legit amount of money that you can really do something with.
And I could sit here and go on and on and tell you about why I've chosen to use Linode.
But I'd like you to go see go to Linode.com slash land get that $100 credit. And then
feel free to move in because Linode is 30 to 50% less than the big cloud over there
at AWS or Google or Azure. Think about that better performance, an independent company
who supports the Linux community and manages to be 30 to 50% less. That's pretty great.
And they have 11 data centers worldwide. So you're going to find just the right spot to
deploy for you or your users. And you're going to rest easy knowing that Linode has built
in monitoring tools that keep an eye on your system. And they'll send you an email if anything
looks kind of funky. And that's often a heads up that something's going on. And you can
get to it before your users even notice a problem. Go try them out at Linode.com slash
land Linux dot ting.com. If you're sick of overpaying for cell service, go see how much
you could save and then take 25 bucks off of that by visiting Linux dot ting.com. Ting
has their set 12 plan, which is a power plan. You get unlimited talk, unlimited text and
12 gigs of data for just $35 a month. They have great family plans to where you can pool
data and you can obviously have unlimited calls and text there. And the other great
thing about Ting is they have three networks that you can choose from. And so there is
such a good chance that you can pick the one that's the best service in your area. It also
means they have just a massive compatibility with phones. If you use two gigs or use 20
gigs or whatever, there's a perfect Ting plan for you. And every single one of those plans
comes with access to Ting's award winning customer service and of course access to their
nationwide LTE and 5G coverage, which is so handy when I'm traveling. I'll sometimes carry
multiple devices because Ting's pricing is so simple and straightforward. I don't have
to invest the hundreds of dollars to have some of the other carriers, but I still get
access to their networks. And the beauty thing about Ting is their website. You guys know
I love a dashboard for days and they've got a great one. It's simple to manage just about
everything you're ever going to need to do. And I'm, I think I'm going on seven years
maybe as a Ting customer now. And I've called in twice like ever. And one of them was for
like an esoteric data issue on a dedicated data device. And they just hung on the line
forever. Well, like two and a half hours, which is like forever in support call time
and just worked it out with me, even though at the end it wasn't really a Ting problem.
I mean, I just like, I felt like I was tight with that rep by the time we were all done.
It's customer service at a next level when you need it, but the website really manages
everything with that dashboard. So just had the linux.ting.com to check your current phone
because it's likely with their multiple network, it's going to be supported. You create an
account, you pick the plan that's just right for you. And then Ting will send you a SIM
card and you just pop that in your phone. You go to the site and you finish up the activation
and you're good to go. And if you went to linux.ting.com, you're taking 25 bucks off
whatever great price Ting's already given you. Cutting your phone bill in half has never
been easier with Ting's plans. So go to linux.ting.com and see the next generation of Ting mobile.
It's here and it's fantastic. Linux.ting.com.
In our discussion story this week, we wanted to cover something you've likely already heard
about. The many resignations over at the long running IRC network, Freenode. Originally
started in 1995, Freenode grew to become the de facto communication and support tool for
free and open source projects of all shapes and sizes. And by 2013, had officially become
the largest and most active IRC network in the world. Over the last few weeks, an organizational
split has been brewing. And what's clear right now, both sides of the split are proclaiming
the other side was attempting a hostile takeover.
Boy, this story is is nearly impenetrable if you're coming at it from the outside. So
a way to help think about this and understand the situation is when you consider that there's
Freenode the network, the IRC network that's made up of volunteers, some of which are fairly
new in all of this and some of which have been around for a long time. And then there's
Freenode Limited, the company which owns the Freenode domain, trademark, has contributed
financially in some capacities and is owned by Andrew Lee. There are some paid people,
but the bulk of what we consider, quote, Freenode staff are really just their volunteers. And
my impression is not many of the two groups from the Freenode Limited team and the Freenode
volunteer team ever really mixed much. There was some interactions, but with just maybe
a few at the top of the volunteer team. Essentially, there were two communities within the Freenode
staff. Andrew Lee, of private internet access fame, purchased the domain and trademarks
and Freenode Limited company in 2017. But more recently, discussions over control of
the Freenode DNS escalated into a series of staff resignations, with many of the staff
leaving to join a recently established and competing IRC network known as LiberaChat.
And with each side of the split releasing statements, chat, transcripts, and even screenshots
of conversations, it's been more than a little complicated to sort through and figure out
just what happened here.
I think it hasn't helped that one side of the conversation has been a little overrepresented.
And that's the LiberaChat side. They were very organized in all of this. They had their
letters ready to go. They linked to each other's letters and kept that updated. And of course,
they had their new infrastructure waiting in the wings. And it seems there was a fight
over the DNS, they wanted control of the DNS of Freenode as well. And so they may have
just taken over the Freenode infrastructure had that not gotten shut down by Lee. I guess
it just reminds me of that old adage that there are two sides to every story. But you
know, it's clear, whatever the full story is, there was a large group of the staff that
were just unhappy, and they wanted some kind of change. And in my opinion, the situation
just got a bit explosive when lawyers started sending letters. I think open source volunteers
and this I'm including the Freenode volunteers in this, they, you know, they don't like it
when the lawyers get involved. Things get legally vague real quick. And just getting
lawyers involved could cause some volunteers to nope out and just resign right there.
Yeah, there's definitely that aspect to this where it's a weird intersection between private
companies and enterprise and a loose knit group of volunteers and open source contributors
on the other side. And those two systems, well, they don't always mesh.
And then there's the elephant in the room that this is a fight of personalities. When
you look into this, there's a lot of strong, unique personalities, and they're making boisterous
claims that seem really intense. And so I think there is a element of they said versus
they said here. And it's kind of like whatever team that people are jumping in on, they're
just going with that line. And I think not helping the situation is Andrew Lee himself
seems like kind of the type of character that people like to take shots at. He made some
money from Bitcoin. There's been some sort of tabloid style hit pieces on him. And so
it's really kind of low hanging fruit for those click baity, lazy writers or YouTubers
that just kind of want to get an opinion out there and grab some clicks and views. Andrew
Lee makes for a character that's easy to take shots at. And it's an underdog story with
the libera chat folks, you know, coming up and forking and starting their own server
from the ground up for open source projects. It's an underdog story that the community
just loves to latch on. And I think those elements have all come together to really
kind of just skew everyone's perspective on what's gone down here. Well, we're kind of
used to in the open source community being a little skeptical of private companies or
well resourced individuals getting in and at least being perceived to change projects
that we know and love. I mean, partly for good reason. But I think you're right here,
there's been a huge information gap. And that means both sides are sort of reasonably upset.
I mean, Andrew Lee sees himself as having been involved in Freenode for years. And yet
here's longtime staff members on the other side saying, we don't really know who you
are or think you're involved with Freenode. And I can understand both sides because it's
just confusing what's going on, who's been involved and owns what? Yeah, and then there's
the obvious sort of like, really, we're fighting for who wants to be IRC King in 2021. Because
we make no mistake about it. Freenode's got to be one of the largest public IRC networks
out there, right? This is a fight for IRC King in 2021 right now. It just seems ridiculous.
As unfortunate as all of this is, it also kind of seems to me that Freenode was in a
sort of precarious place from an organizational governance structure already. I mean, it appears
that this transaction with Freenode Limited happened way back in 2017. And yet a number
of staff claimed not to have any idea about it. And in 2021, seems like getting your open
source set up with a foundation or nonprofit or other organizational entity is just really
important if you want things to continue on in an organized fashion that is hopefully
less susceptible to personality disputes like this. Yeah, you think when you have competition
like Mattermost, Discord and like Slack, you kind of have to have your A game on already
if you're IRC and you want to stick around and just sort of keep your entrenched real
estate. But the reality is they didn't have that. I think maybe everybody thought things
were going just fine until there was this brouhaha that developed, this kerfuffle,
if you will. Well, and you know how it goes in open source organizations or volunteer
organizations. You maintain the little bits that you do. But unless you really want more
work, you don't ask about the problems over there. But you're right. I mean, IRC is kind
of yesterday's technology at this point. And there are things like Mattermost, there's
proprietary things like Slack, not to mention all the exciting work that's been happening
over in the matrix community. Yeah, I think a lot of projects will stop and use this moment
to consider some projects. I've already announced they're leaving free node some projects like Gen
two said, No, we're gonna wait for all the facts. But I think everyone's kind of taking
this moment to go. Well, matrix really seems like they're getting it together. And they announced
spaces recently, which put simply is a way to group rooms and people together. And it comes
in a few flavors depending on what size of organization you have. But to help us understand
how this could be beneficial to open source communities. And I think also help us understand
how this replaces matrixes previous community features. I want to play a clip of audio from
Matthew Hodgson. He presented at Fossum 2021. And he's about to describe how they're discontinuing
their current matrix communities feature and focusing on the new spaces. What we decided to do
is to burn it with fire, introducing spaces, matrix about change 1772. So how spaces work
is again, to group together your rooms and users, but we group them in a room. So you inherit all
the intrinsic capability and goodness that you get in a matrix room, you get power levels, access
control, invites membership, you can store any kind of room state in it as metadata, you get
third party invites, get decentralized rooms, they're shared between servers, you can even
bridge them into identity sources. So if you did have your big LDAP set of users, there probably
always in future, you could bridge that into the room in order to define the membership on the
matrix side. And so that's basically the whole thesis of spaces, we throw away the entire groups
and communities API and just use the one that we already have. It supports auto joining. So if you
join a space, you have the ability to join the rooms within it. And more interestingly, we
support nested hierarchies of rooms in spaces. Wes, I think you could see how that would be just
inherently beneficial to open source projects that could use a little bit of organization and
spots for public members and spots for private development members. Yeah, it sounds like matrix
was a little concerned that discord was becoming quite popular for open source projects because of
some of those features and functionality. And so on one level spaces is here to provide that
structure and compete against similar chat applications. But the other fascinating angle
to matrix is not to just view it as a platform for chat and instant messages. Because with spaces,
they're now providing a decentralized hierarchical namespace with decentralized access controls
for every room. And you can really think of a room as a pub sub topic like you might get
on Kafka or MQTT or in all kinds of technologies. And that's where it might be really interesting
to see what kinds of stuff will be built on top of matrix. I mean, you've already got things like
forums or blogging platforms that are built on matrix spaces will take that flexibility to the
next level, I think. And that would make the rooms that that would make them go across servers as
well, right? So you would you could you could participate in a room that essentially spans
multiple matrix servers. Yeah, that's one practical benefit of a decentralized hierarchical namespace
is you could have a space with rooms from different servers under that one same space.
Spaces could become the main backbone of the protocol with chat rooms being mere just leaf
nodes and a giant tree of collaboration was. And I kind of joke but matrix has serious potential
here. And they have a mobile game that IRC can't natively offer. And they have that bridge. So you
could bridge to your old IRC community and make the transition a little smoother. Although none
of these features really matter if free software projects keep picking discord for their collaboration.
Yeah, I think we've all been a little nervous about that, which is why it's so nice to see
spaces out in beta. But we should probably stress that beta part. We haven't yet upgraded the JB
matrix, but we'll be looking to do so soon. We look forward to seeing you. Indeed we do us and
we look forward to seeing you back here next week. So go to Linux action news.com slash subscribe for
all the ways to get every new episode. And if you're not on matrix yet, Linux action news.com
slash contact for ways to get in touch. Be sure to catch self hosted 45 this week, the founder of
Home Assistant joins us and we look at the project's future hardware devices, new standards
and more coming to the amazing Home Assistant project self hosted dot show slash 45. As for us,
we'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
Thanks for joining us and we will see you next week.