Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open source world.
This is episode 106, recorded on May 19th, 2019. I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe. Good to be connected with you again. This week, we're starting out with
a story that is maybe a theme of 2019. And that is the side channel attacks specifically
on the Intel processors. And another one has been discovered this week that also impacts
Linux.
Yet another side channel speculative execution bug in Intel hardware. This is starting to
get a bit old, isn't it? This time they're calling it zombie load.
Yeah, the idea is that like it gets zombie information, it resurrects information from
the dead. The technical name for it is MDS, micro architectural data sampling. I guess
zombies are way, way cooler than micro architectural data sampling. Fair enough.
It's actually a combination of three different vulnerabilities. And Red Hat have got a great
write up of this, and some videos, they've got a kind of high level video that explains
it with metaphors, and then a really deep dive video. So very impressed with Red Hat
for this. I suppose that's kind of their job. But either way, that's my go to on this if
you want to learn all about it.
It is actually kind of interesting that Red Hat has one of the best takes for different
levels of understanding. We'll link to a couple of different things in the show notes that
are worth checking out, including their breakdown of the differences of MDS, say versus Meltdown
or Spectre. But there's another aspect to the story that I think is fascinating to chat
about a little bit, Joe, and that is, number one, you're not really fully safe, even after
all the microcode updates and whatnot, unless you disable hyperthreading. And number two,
it's really something that shared hosting providers or cloud providers that have multi
tenant users on there need to worry about more so than people that are on premises or
on a desktop PC. Not that those systems aren't affected, but just simply, it's a lot more
of a risk when you have untrusted users on one box.
Yeah, and if you've got six physical cores and no hyperthreading like me on my i5, then
you're completely safe. But yeah, either way, it's not a huge deal if you're just using
a personal system and you're completely in control of it. But yeah, those shared cloud
hosting environments, that's where this is really going to cause a problem.
Yeah, and some of the numbers are pretty dramatic. When you apply the fixes and you disable hyperthreading,
you can get to nearly a 40% reduction in performance. And those are Intel's numbers. So those if
anything may be a little conservative.
And that's why Red Hat is saying that you really have to look at your specific use case,
your specific workload, and do the risk assessment. Is it worth that performance impact to mitigate
the risk? And in a lot of cases, it probably isn't.
This really does seem like a tricky one for multi-tenant systems. And you kind of wonder
like long term, maybe this is going to sell some AMD systems because they're immune to
the MDS vulnerabilities. And all rise in box is looking better and better for that desktop,
Joe. I got to say, they're making it really appealing these days.
Yeah, I mean, the value for money proposition is better. And now if the security proposition
is better, then it feels like a no brainer, really. I've always gone Intel because I don't
know really, it's the name you know, you know, you're not gonna have any problems with Linux
on it. But I hear great things about Ryzen. And really, the data center is where this
matters. And the Xeons are just absolutely dominating there. Maybe this is excellent
news for AMD. But that said, some of the older side channel attacks, you know, they're still
vulnerable to that. And it is conceivable that there will be future ones. I mean, it's
almost certain, isn't it that we're going to have future potential vulnerabilities for
both Intel and AMD. I remember talking about that at the time that Spectre and Meltdown
came out, you know, around Christmas, we knew that was going to be just the start of it.
Mm hmm. Yeah, sure. Yep. And we called it on TechSnap too. We said this is 2019 is going
to be the year of speculative execution and side channel attacks. It's, it's a pretty
handy feature that is right for the picking if you can get a process on the local box.
And it was part of Intel's secret sauce. Now AMD likes to boast that well, we designed
it with security in mind. You know, that'd be that'd be what it is. I'm sure future Intel
processors will work this out. But in the meantime, I just can't get over that 40% number.
I can't tell if that's if that's real or not. And I'd love to get some information from
the audience that has hands on with this and data centers. Just let me know at Chris LAS,
are you seeing performance impacts from these fixes? And are they as dramatic or worse even
than 40%? I'd love to just collect some anecdotal evidence from the audience from various sources
because that's that's a huge story if it's true. There's also another topic I'm really,
really interested in getting feedback. That's AMP. Now, I was a couple of months ago, we
talked about this new committee that was being set up to oversee AMP, you'll have to forgive
my brief summary of it. And we weren't sure what that would result in. But it seems like
maybe we're seeing some of the first fruits of that committee's work.
Yeah, AMP being accelerated mobile pages, which Google are very much in control of even
though they're trying to kind of spin it that they're not. And this makes websites load
really quickly on mobile, specifically on Chrome on Android.
Right. And from a publisher standpoint, you get featured in their carousel of search results
with a live preview. So you get essentially top tier placement, like what you would get
for a Google ad placement.
Yeah, and the performance is amazing. It's really, really fast for the user. But one
of the problems that publishers have is that the URL always shows as google.com slash whatever
slash AMP, and then the URL of the page. And that's a bit confusing for people, you know,
you think you read in TechCrunch or the register or whatever, but in fact, you read in something
that's on a Google URL.
Well, and publishers hate it because you're not sharing their URL, you're sharing a Google
URL. It doesn't have their brand. It doesn't link directly to them. It's hard to track
metrics. They hate it. Yeah. And fair enough. It's their content, I suppose. Fair enough.
Well, yeah. And so the solution to this is just obfuscate it, just hide the fact that
it's on Google servers and pretend that it's coming from the actual source.
Yep. This is a thing. It's called signed exchange. And it is another Google initiative to solve
a problem that was caused by Google AMP. So if you're not familiar, just a super brief
overview. The reason AMP is so dang fast is because it's all coming from Google server.
Google pre-renders the page, caches everything. It's all prefetched. And then they deliver
you a fully realized result immediately. Of course, the issue is, is then you're sending
around Google links instead of website links. You lose that idea and that branding. So Google
figured, well, what about this signed exchange idea that we have? It's a Google technology
that provides a way to prove the source and origin of a web document. You can use signed
exchange to determine a page's original publisher, no matter where that document is being hosted
at currently. A publisher can sign an HTTP request response pair with their domain certificate.
So it's their cert that's signed. Thus, it generates a signed exchange and it can be
served to browsers similar to the way a web page is now, but it's served from Google's
servers with your domain name, even though it's from their domain, but it's using your
SSL key to prove that it's legitimately from you, even though it's from Google.
This makes me feel very, very uncomfortable because at least those who are tech savvy
can know, all right, hang on. This is an AMP page that is hosted on Google servers because
you can technically host an AMP page on your own server and it will be fast and everything,
but obviously the Google cache is going to be amazingly fast. So that's what a lot of
the publishers go for.
Oh, it's a slippery slope, my friend, because it's not only fast, but it uses less data.
So it's cheaper for mobile users. It uses less CPU because the client isn't doing the
rendering so it saves battery life and you get that carousel placement. And now you take
it a step further. This is a Google technology. It's the signed exchange thing is something
they're proposing. I mean, they're proposing as a standard working with other people. So
it's something anybody could theoretically adopt except for Safari and Firefox have signaled
they have no intention of supporting it. So what you have is AMP content being served
up by Google servers that only works in Google Chrome.
I think the European commission might be having a word with them about this shortly if they're
not careful.
Man, this does not seem like the direction Google wants to go with this. I kind of get
it and I appreciate that signed exchange actually is pretty clever technology that they're trying
to establish as a standard and Firefox could change its position. That's a really tough
spot for Mozilla, though, because they lose either way. Because if they enable Google,
then they encourage more lock in. But if they don't support this, they're essentially left
out of a game that is a lot larger than they can ever hope to be. That's a rock in a hard
place for Firefox.
Well, except that if you're using Firefox as your primary browser, then you won't even
really know about this. And so you won't see the benefits of it. But you won't know what
you're missing.
Yeah. And I suppose it's possible to that Firefox could support this later on. It seems
that the publishers don't like this very much. And that was something that the committee
has also been very focused on. I'll put some supporting links in the show notes for that.
It's an interesting position. So Google is trying to drive this with a lot of energy.
And there's no real clear demand on end user side. And there's no real clear demand on
publisher side. So who is it that wants this?
Well, Google, obviously, they want to have more control. I mean, we both tweeted about
that purchase history thing this week, where you can see everything you've ever bought
online, as long as you got the receipt going into your Gmail. And it just backs up the
obvious fact that, of course, Google knows everything you're buying if your receipts
all go through Gmail.
Yeah, of course. Of course, they're indexing and categorizing that. We knew that. I actually
kind of appreciate that they're willing to tell me that. In a way, at least if they're
transparent, then I can make an informed decision. So in a way, I respect that. It was alarming
to go through that because I was thinking like they'd have anything I bought on a Google
account. No, no, no, no, no. Anything that's ever emailed my Gmail account a receipt, an
Uber ride, a DoorDash, buying something with Stripe out in the real world, Google has it
on a list.
Suddenly, you realized how many sandwiches you'd be buying.
Yeah, a lot of sandwiches, Joe. So maybe I should cut back and I could just use the Google
list to keep track of things.
But it really does just come down to Google wanting complete control over all the data
in the world so they can sell you stuff.
I don't know. I feel like that's a hard line you're taking. To me, it seems like there
is, there is a couple of things that it's doing that I like. Loading pages very, very
fast and pre-rendering them. So they're saving bandwidth on mobile and CPU cycles. I get
that. I think it would be better served from publishers directly. And the other thing that
I, the other reason why I think that'd be a lot better is you could be better than your
competition and get ranked higher in Google.
Like if you really invested on building a responsive, fast website, you invested in
designing things correctly, you did the right kind of images, you cashed everything correctly.
Like you really, as a business, made that part of your focus. And as a result, the Google
search results would reward you and you may show up above your competitors, which could
matter a lot.
All of that's gone now. It removes that pressure for publishers to really invest in their technology
because now Google can come around, suck it all up, pre-render it, and then deliver it
in a consumable way and your site can be dog crap slow. And that I don't like at all. So
there's the control aspect that we talk a lot about and that feels like it's going to
make the web experience for the rest of us, not in Chrome, a little less great. And control
or not, there's that element to it too that I think is part of why people care about the
AMP story.
Well, I really hope that this advisory committee can do some good here. And I'm not very impressed
with this first move that they've made, but it could be this amazing standard, this open
standard that Google has kind of talked about and is trying to make happen that individual
publishers could use and adopt and potentially have different variants of instead of just
having all of that centralized control and obfuscating URLs is just the complete opposite
of what I wanted to see with AMP.
Well, I guess we've said our piece. If this topic does interest you, I want to draw your
attention to a link in the show notes. We have a blog post by an individual who is a
self-admitted AMP critic, but I love where he took it. He decided to join the advisory
committee for AMP and they just recently had a meeting and he documents it on his blog.
I appreciate this level of transparency. He seems to have a rather rational take on it
and links and cites a lot of the stuff that he talks about. So it's a really good reference
and we'll have a link to that in the show notes.
Yeah, linuxactionnews.com slash 106.
But you won't be reading that blog post running Windows on a Chromebook. Not that you'd ever
want to, but it was almost, almost a real official bonafide thing.
Yeah, we talked about this last summer and the Windows aspect is not particularly interesting,
but if you can dual boot Chrome OS and Windows, then it's going to make dual booting Chrome
OS and Linux that little bit easier, at least you would assume. But unfortunately that project
went nowhere and so it's going to be just straight up Chrome OS with all the Android
apps and the Linux apps on top of it.
I love this story though, because first of all, it had a great codename, Project Campfire,
and it's one of those where just loose on Reddit find this stuff and they noticed recently
it was like a user cross frog or something like that on Reddit. Notice that there was
comments in the latest Chrome code bases that said that these features have been deprecated.
They were pulling them out. I think about a world where you kind of had a Chromebook
that was running Android apps, Linux applications and tribooting Chrome OS, Windows and Linux.
I don't know the use case for that, but that's a hell of a lot of different ways you could
use a $300, $400, $500 laptop. That straight up would have been impressive. I think they've
determined they've gotten there close enough with where Chrome OS has gone recently that
they thought, let's pull the plug on this for now. We don't need people running Windows
on these things.
And you know that Project Campfire, only a Mac user could have come up with that. That's
pretty close to boot camp for my money.
Oh, you know what? I guess I hadn't really put that together. I suppose I kind of see
it, Project Campfire. I was thinking because it was like a summer project.
Oh, maybe. Maybe I'm casting aspersions there, but that's the first thing I thought about
was boot camp.
Yeah. You could see where the logic had come though. I bet you the thought process was,
well the one thing that's preventing people from switching to Chrome OS is that one Windows
app. Because that's the same thing with Linux desktops. The one thing that prevents people
from switching is like the one or two applications on Windows that you can't get on Linux. Maybe
it's Premier or it's some game or whatever it might be. They had to have a similar conversation
at some Chrome OS development meeting and said, you know, if we made it possible for
people to run Windows 10, even if it was like in a tiny light VM or something, then they
could run that one application and switch to Chromebooks. That had to be it.
And then they sat back and looked at the way the market's going. And they said to themselves,
ah, we don't really need to bother, but maybe old Goog saw that Gardner market forecast
that was published in April. And they said, ah, I don't know. They read this report and
the report says something to the effect of only 75% of professional PCs will be running
Windows 10 by 2021. I mean, it's a good chunk, right? But it's maybe not where the future's
headed. And so they decided to invest in other places. That's got to be, that's got to be
like the whole logic process. If I were to guess.
Well, surely the other 25% is going to be Windows 7 because people are desperately clinging
onto it.
Yeah, actually can understand, right? If you just want to get something done and you need
something that's compatible with Windows, Windows 7 does a heck of a job. The only problem
is that pesky support that's expiring. And if you're say the South Korean government,
you got to make some plans and they are at least considering and testing migrating to
Linux instead of Windows 10. That's according to the Korean Herald.
Can I put my extremely cynical hat on for a second?
Of course. I thought you were always wearing that hat.
Oh yeah, that's true. Let me put my extra cynical hat on top of it then. I can't help
but think this is the South Korean government trying to shake down Microsoft for a bit of
extra free support, just threatening them that we're going to move over to Linux. Because
if you actually look at life in South Korea, you need Windows to do a lot of stuff. I remember
having a conversation with a listener, it must be a few years ago now, about how to
do any sort of interaction with the government, you need to have a Windows PC.
Yeah, ActiveX, I think specifically is what it is.
Yeah, and some other applications that are only available for it. So for them to move
over, it's not like switching out Office for LibreOffice.
I think there's also some character support issues that aren't as solid as they should
be.
Yeah. And so it's not really a realistic proposition that South Korea could do this.
Maybe. At a certain point, you have to move on from ActiveX, right? There's other factors
at play here. My understanding, I don't know, I've never actually been directly familiar
with it. But from conversations I've had, and from what I've read, that ActiveX requirement
comes about because the government has their own self-implemented form of encryption. Because
at the time that they built all those systems, it was illegal to export anything beyond 40
bit from the United States. And so they came up with their own solution that is implemented
with ActiveX. But if they own that, then they can move it to something newer. And it's high
time to do that. Let's be honest, Microsoft is deprecating Internet Explorer. They're
deprecating Windows 7. They're up against a couple of massive market forces. And yeah,
they could be trying to leverage a few more years of free support. But it looks like they're
doing the math. They say it would cost them about 780 billion won or I think that's 655
US greenbacks, 655 million US greenbacks. But it also anticipates long-term cost reductions
after the entire total cost of ownership has been calculated. So they've been looking into
that. They don't mention like specific plans or actions, but they do say one of their goals
is to avoid building reliance on a single operating system.
The most disappointing thing about this whole story is that they're going to build their
own custom distro based on Ubuntu instead of using Red Star OS.
Well, yeah, I agree. Red Star OS is best OS, no doubt about it. But I really hope this
doesn't go the route of Munich where they really like they fork off their own version
of Ubuntu. They fork off their own thing of LibreOffice. If they were smart, they would
do this in a very standardized enterprise rollout form. Get mainline Ubuntu, get a support
contract. It's $25 a desktop. Get a support contract with Canonical. Do it the proper
way. So that way these are supported machines. These things are performing a critical function.
To treat them otherwise is just asking for disaster. This is just, oh, just spend a little
bit of money here.
Yeah. Even if it ends up costing you a little bit more, at least you're not completely locked
in. At least Ubuntu does use all open source and open standards and you could hire a consulting
firm to carry on if Canonical goes away or stops supporting the desktop or whatever.
This is why I think it's really important in businesses and in enterprises and in governments,
you shouldn't go in talking about cost at all. In fact, let's say it's even a little
more expensive. Let's say that because I think the total overall win for the public is open
formats and avoiding vendor lock-in for the core operating system which powers your entire
infrastructure. The value of that long-term, especially when it's government money, so
it's citizens tax money, that's just critical. Having document formats that we can open for
the next 25 years, that matters. That matters a lot in these types of deployments. Having
something where different contract support companies or internal IT support can actually
build and extend your system and maintain it and avoid technical debt is so much more
valuable than the cost of the machine license or the support license. It's phenomenally
more valuable in these institutions because these are long-term institutions that get
10 plus years out of these machines if they can and they're creating documents that have
to be consumed for 30 plus 50 years. That's the value that we should be selling to these
institutions, not the cost of the software. We're going to lose if that's what we focus
on.
Yeah. You have to figure that changing from say Ubuntu to Red Hat, it's got to be a hell
of a lot easier and cheaper than moving from Windows to Linux or vice versa.
Absolutely. Yeah. No doubt about it. No doubt about it. Just from a file system standpoint,
it's easier to move your data from one Extended 4 file system to another Extended 4 file system.
It doesn't matter what the kernel is or what the user land is, but going from NTFS to Extended
4, that's a hell of a transition. Just simple things at that level or backing up your configuration
file for NGINX, you could use that on another box. There's direct one-to-one value, skill
set, et cetera. You make the migration once and then you reap those benefits for the life
of the systems. That's the real value there. We'll see where South Korea goes.
I hope they're not just leveraging. One would think that if they're at this stage, they've
still got a year and change of support from Microsoft Extended support for Windows 7,
so they're in a good position right now.
Well, if they do switch to open standards and open source, then surely they're going
to be taking full advantage of Microsoft open sourcing one of the algorithms behind the
Bing search engine.
I was going to come on here and be all like, womp, womp, Bing algorithm, open source, who
knows? I was wrong, man. I did some investigation into what this actually does, and it really
makes me appreciate that search is a way harder problem than I ever have appreciated.
Yeah, because if you think about doing just a find or grep or whatever, the time that
that takes, usually you're only dealing with a few hundred or a few thousand files and
if it takes a second, whatever. But if you're dealing with billions of files and it needs
to be instant, then that is a very tricky problem to solve.
Especially when you have the variability of human language. An example they give in the
documentation and in a video is a user sits down and wants to search for the Rocky 4 movie,
but Rocky 4, the proper spelling is in Roman numerals, but being just an average user,
they sit down, they type in Rocky and the number 4. The system has to be smart enough
to consider other factors and still return the right results.
Another example they gave is the word bank generally means like a financial institution,
but you can also bank things. You can have a bank side of a hill. There's a lot of different
uses for the word bank when you think about it and a computer has to know what the intention
is. That's the element they've open sourced here, a key piece of what makes that possible.
It seems Microsoft's intention by making this open source isn't to make Bing take off like
crazy, but to just give developers another tool to work with machine learning and AI.
Essentially what you have here is a Python library with AI models pre-built and it has,
I quote, a space partition tree and graph algorithm, speed tag. That's what's at the
core of the open source Python library that Microsoft is making available. It's not a
new idea of vector search, but it's really powerful and they are teaming vector search
up with machine learning here, buzz, buzz, buzz, and then releasing that as an MIT licensed
Python library.
That's it. I'll spin it up in Azure instance and run in this tomorrow.
To the cloud, Joe. It's time to do some vector based searches.
Do you think that's what it's about though, just driving people to Azure? I know that's
the kind of cliche go to, but I can't really see any other reason why they would open source
this.
I think so. I mean, machine learning is a big part of the platform's future plans and
it I think is very valuable from a brand standpoint, even if there's not a direct correlation to
Azure. I think it's pretty powerful from a brand standpoint to be a leader in this industry,
to have services that enable machine learning, to be releasing software that enables machine
learning.
I think it's pretty clever on Microsoft's part. They're trying to get legitimacy with
the developer community and giving them really good free open source software. Well, how
are developers not going to like that? People just have to keep looking for ways to hate
Microsoft, but this one isn't going to be one of them.
Oh, I'm sure people will find some way to hate them about it.
Yeah, there's a way to twist this, I'm sure. I mean, after all, it does have Bing in the
name.
Well, before we get out of here, there's a breaking story as we've been recording. Details
are a little bit light at this point, but it seems that Google have cut off Huawei,
and so there'll be no more GApps for them. And if they want to sell any Android phones,
then it's just AOSP all the way for them.
Boy, what a story. As we're recording, Reuters publishes that Alphabet Inc., Google's parent
company has suspended business with Huawei that requires any transfer of hardware, software
or technical services, except for those that are available in the open source project,
which Joe said. Here's the direct quote from a Google source, Huawei will only be able
to use the public versions of Android and will not be able to get access to proprietary
apps and services from Google. Google has clarified that includes the Play Store and
Play services, and has also clarified that existing Huawei users that currently have
access to the Play Store will still be able to update the apps that they have now from
Google. So your Gmail app and whatnot will still get updated, but what happens to your
operating system and telco updates and things like that, that's all up in the air right
now. This has got to be a massive blow for the company.
Well, it's fine for the users. They can just flash lineage and the Google apps and they'll
be fine. Oh wait, no, Huawei locked down the bootloaders so no one can do that.
Right, right. Yeah, this is a hell of a story. And there's some deep political sides to this
that we're not going to get into. On Thursday, the Trump administration added Huawei to a
trade blacklist. So I think this is likely Google responding to that. They probably don't
have much of a choice in this situation.
He does have the best blacklist. Tremendous.
People say Joe, people say. People tell him.
Not a lot of people know this.
Everybody knows.
I think you're going to have to follow up on Linux Unplugged on Tuesday with this because
this is going to be a big story this week, by the looks of things.
Yeah, I would imagine the next couple of days it'll develop. So if something interesting
does come out of this, you bet. We'll put it on there. And like always, we're going
to get the latest and greatest that's happening in the open source world every single week
right here on Linux Action News. Go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new
episodes.
And go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch with us.
Also, we have two events coming up at meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting. We've got a Kubernetes
study group coming up and a dinner at Texas Linux Fest. If you're going to Texas Linux
Fest, it'll be awesome to see you there. Meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting for those and future
events.
And we'll put a link in the show notes to the last study group that has been published
on YouTube, Command Line Threat Hunting. So do check that out.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I am at Chris LAS.
I am at Joe Ressington.
Thank you for joining us and we will see you next week.
Have a great night, y'all.