Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 146, recorded on February 23rd, 2020. I'm
Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe. Good to be connected with you. And I got to say, I just barely made it. I
was so busy installing the new Linux Defender from Microsoft.
Yeah, they've announced a public preview of Microsoft Defender Advanced Threat Protection
Antivirus for Linux. What?
Finally, finally, now I can finally browse the web on my Linux box. I've been waiting.
Okay, I might be joking a little bit. I actually have not installed this because it's not for
me. It's not for you, Joe. It's for the enterprise. They write, we are aiming to protect the modern
workplace environment across everything that is being Microsoft or non-Microsoft. We are
protecting endpoints across Mac. And today, we're extending this endpoint to protect Linux
and iOS and Android.
So the idea is they are selling the concept of end-to-end device protection, regardless
of its OS, all feeding sensor data, shared sensor data, back to this Microsoft protection
system, which is going to be part of Microsoft Threat Protection Suite, MTP, which is a bundle
of services.
Now, I know this is a lot, but how Microsoft is talking about this is like next level.
What makes Norton Antivirus look like your grandparents' antivirus? They write on the
Microsoft blog, this is artificially intelligence-powered sensors all over the place, designed to stop
attacks from spreading and auto-healing impacted assets. And they write one more that I just
loved, coordinated defense to uncover the full attack kill chain can help block nation-state
level attacks. So this is nation-state antivirus level here. That's pretty good, Joe.
Yeah and it all ties into Azure as well, obviously. The way Microsoft are talking about this,
they want to just control the whole antivirus security sector in enterprise. And they want
ATP to be that box that you check on your compliance form. And I think that it's genius.
I think that this really goes to show what a good CEO Satya Nadella is. This is a strategy
to stay relevant in the enterprise over the next 10 or 15 years, while Windows on the
desktop becomes less relevant and Windows Server becomes less relevant. And as the market
changes, they're going to still be in the enterprise. Their salespeople will use that
Microsoft name and they will stay relevant and stay making a ton of money.
As we talk about this, I am of two clear minds, which are very much in conflict with each
other. There's the version of me that wants to sit here and just yell how this is totally
unnecessary. It's going to be a major impact on your performance. It's likely invasive
in some way because of the amount of information it needs to collect to do this job properly.
But then there's the enterprise, Chris, that knows that this means more people can now
run Linux on their desktops because they can be compliant with corporate requirements.
And as you just alluded to, often audit policies that they're held to, which is a really big
deal to make a breaker. So it means no Linux for some companies. This change could now
mean employees have an option they didn't have before. On that hand, I'm like, wow,
that's great. And I can also see Microsoft's pitch here. If we have sensors on all of the
endpoints, iOS, Android, Windows, Linux, and on your servers and on your cloud servers,
then we're collecting all of that. We're using our training to analyze it and identify threats
and then automatically shutting down services or blocking access proactively while alerting
you. And only Microsoft can do it because only Microsoft has it across this entire range
of devices and services.
If I feel like software like that or a service like that is essential to my business, that's
a pretty compelling argument. I would be drawn to that. Now there's that other side of me
that's like screaming right now at how I would never want anything like this. But that's
often the case for things that are designed for the enterprise.
Well, yeah, I don't want anything to do with this, but I can see it being massively successful.
This bundling of security products that Microsoft has will be rolled out in various different
ways to existing subscribers to some of the Office 365 products, as well as others. But
speaking of services, we have an update on one of Mozilla's much talked about services.
Yeah, their VPN service, which is still invitation only and costs $4.99 per month, now has an
Android app.
As a reminder to everyone out there, the Firefox private network VPN is powered by Mulvad VPN.
And they make claims on their website, which I just went through again this morning, that
they do not log and monitor user data. And here's something else that's kind of interesting.
They're using WireGuard for the back end connectivity. So this may end up being one of the largest
commercial deployments of WireGuard to date. Now, be aware at this point, they do not have
as many WireGuard servers as they do open VPN servers. As of this recording, they have
169 WireGuard servers distributed throughout the world. So it's still a pretty good amount.
But the Android app for the Firefox private network is using WireGuard to connect back
to Mulvad. And they're wrapping it up in a pretty nice to use package that supports the
Mozilla Corporation. $4.99 per month isn't bad, because when I looked into Mulvad, they
seem like they check out like obviously, I don't have access to their logs and stuff.
So I can't make full claims. But a lot of what they use, they have contributed back
upstream and their own code that they've written, they've open sourced and posted on their GitHub.
And I went through a lot of it and it looks really good. They seem at least solid to me
like Mozilla has made a good choice as outwardly as you can judge these kinds of things.
And $4.99 doesn't seem outrageous, does it? That seems to be about the going rate for
a VPN service, at least a decent one.
Sure that and WireGuard may actually be a little more performant than OpenVPN. So you
may be able to argue this is one of the faster VPN services for Android. I wouldn't mind
if the industry as a whole, tap the old brakes on the whole VPN thing, because it's a product
that's sold in various different ways, often using scare tactics, sometimes proclaiming
ways to pirate content and bypass region restrictions, which all of that feels a little gray area
to me. But additionally, it's advocating for consolidating user traffic, which ultimately
makes it more vulnerable to attack than having it distributed all over the place from people's
local networks.
So I kind of just I want us to think really carefully and be sure that when people are
choosing VPN providers, they're really looking into them because there's a lot of flashy
ones out there that make it really easy to one click VPN. Now, maybe that's a good thing
for average users, but maybe we're running a risk of consolidating traffic and actually
making people more vulnerable in the long term. What do I know? We'll have to just wait
and see at least this one here seems legit. And it seems like they have a really easy
to use implementation. Those two combinations hopefully will be a success for them.
Did you see that video that Tom Scott made about VPNs about a month ago, maybe talking
about some of the claims that they make and how HTTPS really does solve a lot of the problems
that they claim they're solving with VPNs?
No, no, I'll have to look that up.
Yeah, it's a good video. I didn't learn a huge amount. But I think that he put it in
very simple terms that non techie people can understand. So it's worth a watch.
While we're still talking about VPNs, we should mention that private internet access is planning
to open source their Android app.
Yeah, the process has started. And they've also some of the dependencies and it's going
to be happening shortly, according to their blog. And it's part of an overall strategy
to open source everything we possibly can, which I think in this day and age of like
you say, some of the VPN providers seeming a bit shady. I think it's good PR for them
to have it all be open source.
Yeah, absolutely. And I suspect that's why IVPN got in on it as well. They're open sourcing
their applications for Android, Mac OS, iOS and Windows under the GPL three. And it does
give me more confidence. Now, I don't still fully have a view into how they handle logs.
And I'd be curious to see who's going to step forward on that. I don't even know how you
would do that, how you could be publicly responsible and publicly prove that you're not logging
out. Maybe somebody clever will think of it.
Well, private internet access talk about having random audits. So that's one solution, at
least for now.
Yeah, I can see that. And I suppose it's just a matter of how you communicate the results
and follow up if there's something found, I guess. Well, let's talk about turning it
up to 11. Joe, get ready for that joke to be made for about a year.
Yeah, this is the first developer preview of Android 11. And this is unusual for them
in that they're calling it Android 11. It used to be the letter of the dessert. But
since they've dropped that, I suppose they're not doing that anymore. So it's just Android
11 developer preview.
I think I like it now. I think I think I prefer this. It's just simpler and a little a little
more serious, I guess. Android 11 has a whole bunch of changes, as you would expect. There's
probably the most noticeable change in the notification area where they're going to have
a dedicated conversations section in the UI. So there'll be a top level of your notification
shade where you'll find ongoing conversations with quick ways to reply. Additionally, you're
gonna love this, Joe. They're making an OS wide API for message and chat bubbles. So
you can have chat bubbles all over your OS. I'm sure you'll love that.
It doesn't make sense on a small phone screen. But I suppose on some of the big foldables
that they're also now supporting. That kind of makes sense, maybe.
Yeah, yeah. And it felt like a tablet to back in the day when I had Android on a tablet
and a Samsung, it kind of worked. But I don't know, on a small, I want my phone smaller.
So I'm just those kinds of things. I'm not super stoked about I am really happy to see
improvements and notifications. And I'm happy to see the one time permission dialog box
come to Android. So if you've used iOS before, you know this one, you launch an app. For
the first time, it says, Hey, this app wants access to your location. Do you want to only
allow it this time? Do you want to allow it only when you're using the app or just totally
deny it? That's going to now be the modal dialog that comes up in Android 11. When you
launch an application, similar things for not just location, but also your microphone
and your camera. And with those, which is kind of a neat trick, you can now grant temporary
one time access, which didn't exist before in Android, which has existed in iOS. And
it's something that I think is the just right amount. I'm trying out an app one time. I
have no idea if this thing's bogus or not. Only allow it this once, and then proceed.
I think that's a great option. And it's nice to see that evolve over the last couple of
Android releases.
Yeah, that's the standout feature to me. I think it's needed that for quite some time.
And it may not be original, but who cares? It's a great feature.
I thought you were going to say scheduled dark theme.
That's pretty cool, but I just have a dark theme all the time anyway. So yeah, I don't
really want to schedule that.
No, I'm not surprised. I'm not surprised. Also some new UI stuff around setting options
for do not disturb and whatnot. It doesn't seem to me like it's a blow away release,
but it appears there's just enough security tweaks that they've had to provide some backwards
compatibility options for Android developers that aren't ready to totally modernize and
11 eyes their app that they can throw in their code to let Android 11 know that they haven't
gotten up to snuff yet and not abuse them as bad. I'll be curious to see if that works
out and I'll be curious to see if app developers even bother updating their apps with that
flag in there because a lot of times the new releases get neglected for so long that even
something as simple as that often gets overlooked or adding support for a notch or whatever.
But maybe, maybe those things are finally starting to shift on the old Android.
Maybe one thing I'm not sure if this is in iOS, but something that's going to be really
useful for me is when you put the phone into airplane mode, it doesn't disconnect Bluetooth
by default, which used to sting me a lot when I would go into the tube, the underground
trains here in London where we have no service down there, no signal. And so you either just
leave it not on airplane mode and drain your battery or you have to pause your podcast,
put it in airplane mode, re-enable Bluetooth, hear the ding and then start playing again.
And now you won't have to do that on the tube or on airplanes.
Fascinating. Interesting. So yeah, iOS did roll that out about the time the Apple watch
came out because guess what? People were buying their Apple watches, turn it off their Bluetooth
and then all of a sudden their watch that was totally dependent on a phone was dumb.
And their AirPods will quit working. You know, these Apple users were not happy about it.
So what iOS does is when you get to the control panel and you toggle off Bluetooth there,
it disconnects most devices, but not certain devices like your watch, your headphones,
things like that. If you go into the settings app, you go into the actual settings and go
into the Bluetooth settings where you'd see all your pairings and stuff like that. And
if you turn it off there, it actually completely turns off Bluetooth.
All right. I don't know how I feel about it not killing all the radios though. It is a
convenient feature, but I like the fact that with airplane mode you just toggle it and
that's it. It's totally disconnected in theory at least.
Yeah. Well this, when Apple made this change, I think it was probably one of the bigger
upsets about that release of the OS. People were shocked by it and it was, it was a story.
So I wouldn't be surprised if it isn't a little, although Android 11 will probably roll out
so slow that I doubt it'll be, it probably won't hit as hard.
Yeah. I mean, I'm still stuck on Android 9 with my old lineage release. So I'll probably
get 10 around the time that 11 comes out. But they have now enabled screen recording
from the kind of pull down menu. There's been a screen recorder built into lineage for quite
some time, but it's not as easy as it will be on Android 11. So that's quite nice I think.
Like to see more screen caps hitting Twitter in a feed near you. That's what I see people
using their iOS device for though, like write notes or you won't believe what just happened
and they'll screen record them recording or something. And then they posted on Twitter
and it's always such a funny way to like get a longer message across. So you might start
seeing that. It's a nice feature though when you're just trying to explain to somebody
like go here, tap this and then select this item. You can just now flip that down, hit
record, you do the action really quick and then in two seconds you can send it off to
somebody over a message. Yeah, and it's just what the world needs, more vertical videos
out there. Well, despite the JavaScript package repository, MPMs best efforts, they have yet
to find a way to fully fund open source development. The ambitions were high and so far the deliveries
have been low. Yeah, this is starting to irk people now because originally MPM had promised
to launch an open source funding platform by the end of 2019. Well, here we are in late
February and all they've managed to do is add the fund command. Yeah, they talked big.
The plan was to really create a platform to fund all of these dependencies and make it
worth people's time at least to contribute to the MPM repository. In fact, MPM Inc's
co-founder and CTO back when they announced it said, quote, the problem we're solving
is open source projects need funding and there are very few ways people can do that and get
that information in front of people using their code. But like so many great ambitions,
things can shift and change. I think you have to mention in this conversation that MPM went
through a major change recently. Their CEO left and that's kind of a big shift. There
was a leadership shuffle in general and the register contacted individuals at MPM like
Darcy Clark who suggested that this is just a reaction of company initiatives being reevaluated,
roadmaps getting adjusted and priorities changing. They had one plan, then new leadership comes
in and now their plans have changed. And it's not that they're abandoning this, but they're
obviously taking a lot slower approach. And I think you can kind of see that Joe in a
phone call that the CTO and co-founder had with the register. He says, ecosystems that
are sustainable won't happen overnight. A platform is a collection of features people
use. We're continuing to work on this. I don't think anything has changed, but we're making
steady progress and engaging with the community. I can appreciate that some folks, the progress
might seem a little lackluster. And then he continues, funding open source projects is
still a very big problem and it's still a very unsolved problem. And I wonder if they
haven't had a leadership change and they didn't come in and think, you know, this is a big
problem and we're not going to solve it. It's not our core competency. Let's scale this
initiative back a little bit.
Yeah, that seems to be exactly what they've done here.
It's a really hard position for NPM that is dependent on a vibrant community that they
really have to be careful how they interact with that community because they don't want
to upset them and demotivate people from participating in creating code that makes their platform
more valuable. At the same time, while they're making commitments, their leadership is changing.
And so they go out and say one thing and then things change after that. And now they're
kind of held to what they committed to, but held to the expectations of the new leadership.
It's a really difficult spot for the staff that have to interact with that community.
I hope leadership is able to appreciate that for them.
Well, as an aside, this story made me think about the Linux Foundation and Harvard Labs
report that came out that is attempting to quantify some of the most popular in terms
of usage open source software and maybe identify better practices they could follow. It's a
doozy, Joe.
This had a focus on JavaScript and frameworks and that side of open source and the most
popular and most widely used pieces of open source software are things that you wouldn't
necessarily have heard of.
Yeah, it's all the little bits that make the bigger things run. This is actually the second
census they have done. Census one looked at system packages specifically for Debian to
get a sense of how popular packages there are, assuming that other distros base off
Debian, you kind of get a baseline. This second census that was run by a different group in
the Linux Foundation wanted to look more at language level packages. The report discusses
some of the challenges in that things are not named consistently, so it's hard to talk
about them. And they also talk about how, like you just said, Joe, a lot of these little
pieces of interdependency packages that people create don't really have the same level of
eyes or auditing or even maybe even quality that you'd want in a production system.
This isn't necessarily new news, but the report is attempting to actually quantify what that
is. Like, what are they? What are the top 10 at least? And then this is just a first
pass, the intention being to get a baseline to figure out what they can't quite get a
hold of what they can't figure out and then take another pass at this again later.
This all comes back to Heartbleed, the open SSL bug that was discovered in April of 2014.
So nearly six years ago at this point. And shortly after that, the core infrastructure
initiative was established. And the aim was to stop something like that happening again.
Well, nearly six years later, we're not any closer really, it seems to avoiding the next
Heartbleed.
This doesn't really get us there. The Linux Foundation writes on their site, the report
begins to give us an inventory of the most important shared software and potential vulnerabilities
and is the first step to understand more about these projects so we can create tools and
standards that result in trust and transparency in software. The argument the report makes
is that free software now contributes to 80 90% of what runs the world even when you
look at large commercial applications and services underneath them is a bunch of little
individual open source components and free software components. And so their thinking
here is they want to make this something that businesses can rely on. Like all of a sudden,
it's become a big deal. It's really important that went from hobby software that people
are scratching an itch to something that people are seriously using in business. And according
to the census that they conducted, most of the people that contribute full time to open
source are doing so under a large corporation like Intel, or Microsoft, or Red Hat, or others.
This seems to be them establishing processes around this and realizing that you can't just
kind of randomly look at software and decide what you're going to put your efforts into.
You need to have a process of looking at what's most widely used and, and divert your resources
appropriately, which is the kind of standard big business way to do things, which is kind
of where the Linux Foundation fits into this whole ecosystem.
Because of just that, I think this is particularly vulnerable to Foundation scope creep here.
They're advocating in this consensus that all open source developers get on a big old
Zoom call, I'm being facetious, they don't actually advocate that part, and come to a
kumbaya on all naming schemes. And this is critical, Joe. The Linux Foundation believes
that until one exists, quote, strategies for software security, transparency, and more
will have a limited effect, organizations will remain categorically unable to communicate
with each other, because of all the silly names that silly open source developers choose.
Well, they do have something of a point, don't they?
Yeah, but there's something of a point of having some fun. It's kind of like coming
into a group that says, Hey, guys, you know, this entire open source software ecosystem
that you've built over the last 20 years that now even by our own report says you run 80
to 90% of the world's software, you've been doing it wrong. I agree. Could it be better?
Could it be simpler? And I grant you here, we're not talking about distribution names.
We're talking about names of libraries, names of MPM packages here.
Well, what they're trying to do is solve a fundamental problem here. And I think we all
agree that that problem is there. Heartbleed shows you that. So there has to be some way
of solving it. If you've got a fundamental problem, then you maybe need a fundamental
rethink of how it all works. And open source software may be successful, but it has this
flaw in it that a lot of that older code just never gets looked at.
So this is where I say foundation creep is very possible. Because when you start talking
about things like how people name their software, you really start having to come up with a
pretty big solution to that problem. And that's where the creep potential really comes in.
Yeah, I think that this is somewhat over ambitious, but I can't say that I have a better solution
for the problem.
You know, ultimately, I think the tone of the report, and then also ZDNet's take on
it, sort of has me upset. Because it seems like they're talking down to these developers
who have contributed their time and their energy and years of their life into building
software that Jeff Bezos and others can get super rich off. Here's a line from the ZDNet
article that really got me fired up. Quote, in short, open source developers must start
addressing the problems of legacy software. Maintaining code is never as much fun as developing
new code, but it's necessary work, says blogger who's never written a line of code. I think
it completely dismisses all of the hard work that so many open source developers do out
of a labor of love, not because they want to back port fixes and software, but because
their users need it. It is a huge part of what our distributions and upstream software
projects spend a significant amount of resources on is maintaining old software that people
don't want to leave. It's where a disproportionate amount of energy goes towards instead of creating
new software, and it completely dismisses all of the effort that they do. Could it be
better? Yes, especially in some of these NPM repos and things that are distributed amongst
many, many applications that end up, oops, big vulnerability in there. Obviously, we
have the data that shows it could be better. But this kind of whole tone throughout the
report and throughout ZDNet's article, it treats open source developers like they're
kids playing with their toys, and it's time for them to grow up and get serious. Meanwhile,
at the same time saying they're responsible for contributing to all of this ecosystem
that's made so much money. It's like they're complimenting and telling them they've changed
the world at the same time telling them that they're not serious, and that they're not
adults. I really just don't like the tone of it. And I think that's my core problem
with the way the Linux Foundation is approaching all of this. I encourage anyone to go look
at the link we'll have in the show notes for the Linux Foundation's official announcement
about this. Go ahead and have a read of that. And tell me about how that's going to inspire
more people to get into free software and open source. It's a boilerplate piece of PR.
I see where you're coming from here. It does feel as if it's coming from people who don't
necessarily have that experience of actually writing open source software. And maybe a
better approach would be to put together a panel maybe of developers who have got a proven
track record within the industry. Maybe that would be a better approach to this.
I think that would be a good way to go. Because ultimately what we want out of this is code
to be developed for free software and open source that patches security vulnerabilities
and leaves people confident in the software. That's the ultimate goal.
Well, at the complete other end of the spectrum from the Linux Foundation is the GNU project.
And it appears to be business as usual for them.
Yeah, and that's in light of the social contract we'd mentioned a couple of episodes ago that
was submitted by the community, reviewed and modified, and then presented for contributors
to agree upon. And they decided, no, we're going to just do business as usual. Thanks
for the idea, though, guys. I don't know if you remember, Joe, but we went through that
contract here on the air and it stated the four freedoms. It stated their goal of creating
free software and said that anyone was allowed to participate. That was the near totality
of the social contract.
Yeah, and the deadline for either accepting or rejecting that was Monday the 24th. It's
nearly Monday the 24th when we're recording this. And it seems that instead of accepting
or rejecting it, they've just ignored it. Stormin is just saying, I'm the chief nuisance
and I decide what happens. And it's just a reiteration, just writing down what has been
the almost unspoken hierarchy before that he just calls all the shots.
Well, this surely is resolved now. We can just file that one away as everyone has made
their statements and I'm sure it won't come up again. Yeah, we'll see about that. Well,
we keep track of that and all the other stories in Linux and open source. So why not get every
single episode? Go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get those.
And you can go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch with us.
Well, if you want something just a little extra, check out extras.show slash 57. Brent
has brunch with Heather Ellsworth from Canonical and it was a fascinating chat.
Yeah, well worth a listen. We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest
Linux and open source news. I'm at Chris LAS. I'm at Joe Ressington. Thanks for joining
us and we'll see you next week. See you later.