Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News. Episode 198, recorded on July 17th, 2021. I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes. Let's do the news.
And this is Steam Deck. It's a handheld, high-powered gaming device that lets you take your Steam
library with you wherever you are. It's got a beautiful seven-inch display, ergonomic
controls that are really built for long play sessions, and a new look for Steam designed
for Steam Deck. You can think about Steam Deck like a portable gaming PC with built-in
controllers.
And it runs Linux. Arch Linux, actually, with a Plasma desktop.
Yep, that's right. And it's available for reservation right now. The first units, Valvik
Specs, will ship in December 2021.
It comes in at three different price points. $399, $529, and $649. Each price brings more
storage with the top two tiers offering faster built-in storage, but all levels come with
an SD card slot for some expansion.
In an interview with IGN, Gabe Newell says they had to work aggressively to get the price
points down to where they are now. Note, this clip I'm about to play from IGN, it has music
baked in. I apologize for that. But we think that the information from the bearded horse's
mouth is worth it.
One of the things we're testing on this is that price performance is going to be one
of the critical factors in the mobile space. And so we've had to be very aggressive in
terms of pricing on the deck.
Because of its form factor, many people are comparing the deck to the Nintendo Switch.
Sure, that was one of my first thoughts as well. But when you look at the specs, Valve
has managed to cram into the deck. I think maybe the comparison becomes a little less
clear. The deck has an AMD Zen 2 processor with 4 cores and 8 threads. It's got 16 gigabytes
of RAM and has an 8 core GPU that bursts up to 1.6 GHz. So in a lot of ways, this is more
comparable to a modern Xbox, but just in a portable form factor. And Valve's actually
hoping that the combination of this hardware running at 720p on the display will produce
really good gameplay, even at rather high game settings. And their goal is to potentially
sell millions.
So our view is if we're doing this right, that we're going to be selling these millions
of units, and it's clearly going to be establishing a product category that ourselves and other
PC manufacturers are going to be able to participate in. And that's going to have long-term benefits
for us. So that's sort of the frame in which we're thinking about this.
Valve is talking about defining a whole new product category here. One that would be powered
by Linux.
And the reaction overall seems really positive. You can really see if you've been watching
Valve for a while, a lot of the lessons they've learned building hardware over the years are
baked into the deck.
Ultimately, it's an evolution of years of hardware and software design work. We've taken everything
we've learned from developing the Steam Controller, Steam Machine, Steam Link, and Valve Index,
along with the Steam Client, and applied all of that collective experience in designing
Steam Deck.
That's Eric from Valve, and a video they created for developers interested in supporting
the Deck.
One of those hardware lessons that set the Deck apart from devices like the Switch are
the built-in trackpads. And while definitely something we'll want to go hands-on with,
the way Valve describes them sounds promising.
The trackpads here are an evolution of the same technology that we've been working on
since the Steam Controller days and experimenting with internally. You also have seen some of
our trackpad work as part of the Index Controller, for example.
They can be used for many different things. We have a keyboard that lets you do dual thumb
typing. In-game, you can map them to areas of the screen for a mouse cursor to jump there
and be kind of a one-to-one region type input. You can create on-screen menus that pop up
on top of the game and have many customizable macro buttons or keyboard keys. And you can
just use it for mouse input, where it's really powerful and reliable for the people that
are comfortable with that sort of input.
And something that Valve stresses multiple times in their interviews is the Deck is just
a PC. An open PC at that, you could even load Windows on it. And users will be able to connect
just about any device compatible with Linux to the Deck, but Valve is also working on
a direct dock solution.
Yes, we're producing a dock. It'll be sold separately.
Is there a price on that yet?
We don't have a price for you today.
Will that be available at launch?
Don't have that answer for you yet today either.
There's plenty of existing off-the-shelf solutions. I don't think that it'll be, you know, providing
this nice experience, but a similar functionality.
Any USB-C dock that you can buy off the shelf will work with this, and it'll do USB, Ethernet,
and HDMI out, all of the things you would expect from a dock.
One thing we don't have a very clear picture of just yet is the battery life.
Well, there's a wide variety of experiences there. It's about two to eight hours, depending
on what you're doing. You can play Portal 2 for four hours on this thing. If you limit
to 30 FPS, you're going to be playing for five to six hours.
That's something we're going to want to test when we get our hands on the actual hardware.
One aspect that's caught the attention of some developers is the Deck's launch is really
focused on Proton for game compatibility. In fact, there's hardly a word about native
gameplay at all from Valve in the announcements or in their documentation for developers.
Steam Deck runs games using Proton. And if you aren't familiar with Proton, it was originally
released back in 2018, and it's a compatibility layer that allows Windows games to run on
Linux.
And it seems Valve is shooting for the moon when it comes to compatibility with Proton.
The team has been working on and improving Proton for a while now. Most APIs are already
supported by Proton, and most games already just work. And the team is building support
for more APIs and enabling more games by default.
Our goal is for every game to work by the time we ship Steam Deck. We are constantly
building on Proton, and there's a lot of work that has been done that doesn't yet affect
the public version of Proton, including testing of thousands of games, engaging with third
parties like anti-cheat providers, work targeting game compatibility, and more.
Yeah, Valve says they're actually going for 100% compatibility and that they'll be working
with anti-cheat vendors directly to try to get Proton compatibility. I have been contacted
by some developers in the Linux game space, however, that say that they've been nudged
or encouraged by Valve to focus on a Proton version of their game instead of a native
Linux port that they might have already had in the works. I don't know if that's true
or not, those are just the rumors going around on the internet that Valve seems to be really
pushing for Proton, but I could see in this early stage they really want the narrative
to be around compatibility. They don't want users or developers thinking games are all
going to have to be ported in order for them to work on the Deck. I can see Valve wanting
to focus a lot on that Proton compatibility right now.
Yeah, it seems clear that they want to have a narrative out there for developers. Listen,
this is new, it's different, you might not be experienced supporting a Linux-based platform.
We've got your back.
They definitely are getting developers hardware. It's just going to be a little bit and it
sounds like developer kits will be in very limited supply.
The answer is we're currently building dev kits and have earmarked some of those units
for partners like you to test your games. And these dev kits will be identical to the
same Steam Decks that we'll be shipping off to customers that they'll be playing later
this year, except for a few small cosmetic differences. And supplies are really limited
and so we're going to have a program where you're going to be able to request a dev kit
soon and we'll be sure to keep you posted and let you know the moment you can submit
a request.
Now I am a little concerned if they are pushing everyone towards Proton, if this is true or
not, and I could see that creating some incentives around the Steam platform, developers would
really be targeting the Proton environment, especially if something like the Deck really
took off and there were multiple versions by multiple hardware makers. I don't know
if you remember this, Wes, but Dell actually took a shot at creating a Switch-like machine
a little while ago too, but bailed on the project.
Oh really?
Yeah, so you could see maybe if this sells well, Dell picks a project like that up again
and of course they're going to use SteamOS, it's free, and Valve is going to want to guarantee
that those games work like a console. And so maybe that's why they'd be pushing something
like Proton. I don't love that though, because I think the dream about Steam coming to Linux
originally was availability for all Linux distributions, getting games just native on
Linux, but if this is the case, I still am compelled to get one.
I mean, at the end of the day, it's a Linux machine that plays your games, right?
I love the form factor, I love that they're going to include the Plasma desktop, and like
they stressed over and over and over again, it's an open PC so you could really throw
anything on there.
Are you locked into Steam or can you, because you mentioned this a minute ago, Pierre-Luc,
or can I log into the Microsoft Store with my Game Pass Ultimate account or my Epic Game
Store account?
Again, you can really do anything that you would expect a PC to be able to do, so the
answer to those things is yes.
Yes, excellent.
The switch to Arch as the base for SteamOS is, frankly, a little surprising, and Valve
has confirmed users will have full access to Pac-Man and the usual Arch package repos.
We're going to dig more into the DeX Linux implementation with our expanded coverage
in this week's Linux Unplugged.
Well speaking of handheld-powered Linux devices, Ubuntu Touch OTA 18 has introduced a new way
for Ubuntu Touch to scale down the wallpapers that you have set.
You know, your high-resolution wallpapers, guess what?
They take a fair amount of RAM, and that's really going to benefit some of the lower-end
devices running Ubuntu Touch, like phones with less than a gigabyte of RAM.
This release also comes with an updated MediaHub component, which is being used by Ubuntu Touch
apps for audio and video playback, so expect a smoother, more reliable experience there.
And of course, there is, as always, a batch of bug fixes that just make your experience
smoother and more stable, but there is a significant fix in here for Google Pixel 2 devices that
were having audio call quality problems.
You'll definitely want to check the notes for that.
We covered Amazon's announcement of their Elasticsearch fork back in episode 173 in
late January.
This week, Amazon announced the first production-ready version of that fork, named OpenSearch.
Amazon first released OpenSearch back in April, but it was in alpha then.
It just really wasn't ready for production use.
Amazon's making the statement now with version 1.0, which is available up on GitHub, that
OpenSearch is ready for production environments, and Amazon is eager to remind everyone it's
very much open source and they would like your contributions.
In a blog post, they wrote,
We encourage anyone to use, modify, extend, embed, monetize, resell, and offer OpenSearch
as part of their products and services.
They go on to say,
Broad adoption benefits the entire community.
This has been in the works, really, since AWS launched its Elasticsearch service in
October of 2015.
That kicked off a whole series of events that have led us to this announcement today.
We are now living in a post-server-side public license era.
Yeah.
Okay.
So back in March of 2019, AWS created its own distribution of Elasticsearch.
Now that's distribution and not fork.
Because at the time, while they were unhappy that Elastic, the upstream developer of Elasticsearch,
sort of keeping some of their more useful components out of the core open source project
and making you pay for those.
Amazon's new distro was called the Open Distro for Elasticsearch, and they were pretty clear
that they were not forking Elasticsearch and still intended to contribute back upstream.
Yeah, however, Elastic remained unhappy with the use of the Elasticsearch name by Amazon
and its trademarks, essentially.
And at the start of 2021, they changed the product to be dual license under their own
Elastic license and that SSPL or the server-side public license that was originally created
by MongoDB.
This relicensing had the effect of making it difficult for cloud providers to run Elasticsearch
as a service, since now they would have to publish all the proprietary magic in the backend
that actually makes that service work.
Elastic's move was also kind of unpopular with the open source community, especially
those who had contributed code, believing it would always be free to use under the Apache
2.0 license, but this time around with a new name and explicitly forked from Elasticsearch
just prior to those license changes.
The company also introduced open search dashboards, a fork of Kibana.
But now all of that is history, and the key question going forward is how successful was
the company be in actually building a community around open search?
Linode.com slash LAN.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account.
Linode started in 2003 as one of the very first companies in cloud computing.
And now, 18 years later, Linode is the largest independent open cloud provider in the world
with 11 global data centers serving nearly a million customers and businesses around
the globe.
Linode's mission, though, remains unchanged since the day it began, to accelerate innovation
by making cloud computing simple, affordable, and accessible to all.
That's led to one of the best experiences out there, and why we host everything on Linode.
Linode has an easy-to-use, powerful cloud dashboard, S3-compatible object storage, bare
metal service cloud firewalls, DDoS protection, VLAN support, a powerful DNS manager, block
storage, object storage, Kubernetes support, and even simple one-click applications, plus
super fast networking and so much more, with pricing that's 30% to 50% cheaper than other
major cloud providers out there.
I find a simple $5 a month Linode offers a surprising amount of performance, and we love
their dedicated CPU instances for our encoding jobs.
And if you ever run into any trouble, Linode's got the best customer support out there, with
hundreds of guides and tutorials to help you get started.
And their community support, it runs deep.
They're making our Colony Reunion trip possible, with meetups in Salt Lake City and Denver,
and more along the way, all powered by Linode.
So what do you gotta do?
Go use our $100 60-day credit to performance test your network, to build an application,
or to learn something.
You know, they do have a tutorial on IPperf.
You can use that to diagnose your network performance and see what's up.
Plus, Linode could just be part of a multi-cloud strategy.
That's why you gotta go check it out.
There's a ton you can do, and a ton you can learn.
So go take advantage of that $100.
Sign up today at linode.com slash LAN.
Get that $100 60-day credit on your new Linode account, and of course, support Linux Action
News at linode.com slash LAN.
Are you ready for mobile to get simple?
Linux.ting.com.
You see, Ting is an MVNO, a mobile virtual network operator.
That means they're not digging holes and putting towers in, but they're getting access to the
same towers.
They're getting access to the big networks, but at a lower cost.
And with Ting Mobile, you get the same coast-to-coast coverage as you would with, say, one of those
big carriers, but you just pay less, and you get Ting's fantastic customer service.
All of Ting's plans are simple and straightforward, like their new set 12 plan, 12 gigs of data,
35 bucks a month, unlimited talk, unlimited text.
It's pretty great for 35 bucks a month.
And of course, they have family plans that are flexible that let you add as many lines
as you need, and every line has unlimited text and calls.
You get a shared pool of LTE and 5G, and they have flexible pricing.
If you use 2 gigs, 20 gigs, or a lot more, there's a perfect Ting plan just for you.
And every plan is contract-free.
With their great interface, fantastic, straightforward UI, it's simple to switch to Ting.
And pretty much any phone works with Ting because they do support so many networks.
So to get started, just go to linux.ting.com, check your current phone, create an account,
and pick the plan that's right for you.
When everything lines up, Ting will send you a SIM card.
You pop that in your phone, and you get activated in minutes.
Cutting your phone bill in half has never been easier with Ting's brand new plans.
It truly is the next generation of Ting mobile.
I've been a longtime customer, and I can tell you they've never had plans this great.
So go see how much you could save and take $25 off of that at linux.ting.com.
On Wednesday, July 14, Microsoft announced Windows 365, a new service that makes it possible
for users to run a full version of Windows right in a web browser on a device of their
choice.
The new service is based on a similar Azure offering, but at first will only be available
for businesses.
Although given Microsoft's tone and the announcements, it seems pretty likely it will become available
for consumers pretty soon.
Today we are continuing this journey and creating a new category with Windows, the cloud PC.
I'm excited to announce Windows 365.
With Windows 365, we are making Windows available not just on Windows devices, but any device
harnessing the power of the cloud.
This has never been done before, and think about it.
Just like applications were brought to the cloud with SaaS, we are now bringing the operating
system to the cloud with Windows 365.
That was Satya Nadella during the introduction, and they really emphasized the fact that you
can run this on Linux and Android and iPads, because Windows 365 is creating a virtual
PC in the cloud that you get access to.
The cloud PC you set up with Windows 365 can be completely personalized.
You get to choose how much RAM you want, like up to 16 gigs at least, and how much storage
you want, at least up to 512 gigabytes.
Things you tweak and change about the PC remain persistent even after you disconnect.
Microsoft says they've built this thing around a zero trust architecture, and they're also
offering an instant on boot experience, and well, I have to say all that seems pretty
likely.
I would expect Microsoft to invest heavily in the security architecture of this thing
such as it is, so that way services like Windows 365 would be compliant with some of the more
rigorous regulatory requirements out there, at least eventually.
And really, instant on, that sounds like a natural evolution of what Microsoft has been
building with virtual machines for years.
Right.
There's a lot of things they've been working on here, including RDP, which is the back-end
protocol.
Now, Microsoft's been working on that since 1998 with Windows NT 4.0 Terminal Server Edition.
They've built numerous ways to deliver an RDP session, so it's not really a surprise
that they could get broad device compatibility that way.
What is new here is that this is a first-party offering right from Microsoft, and they're
strongly positioning it as a hybrid solution.
With Windows 365, the operating system itself becomes hybrid, accessible on the device as
well as the cloud.
Well, I guess in the aggregate, this might mean more Windows users.
You could especially see the use case scenario in the enterprise environment where you could
deploy cheap low-end hardware, maybe even Raspberry Pis, and just spin up a client that
connects to a Windows machine in the cloud that Microsoft is continually updating.
It's really going to be ideal, I hope, for potential and existing desktop Linux users.
You know, the ones that have that one Windows app that you just have to have for work or
whatever.
Now you'll be able to immediately and instantly load up a modern version of Windows that has
been built on a virtual server that is run by the OS vendor.
So not only does that mean more people are going to be able to use desktop Linux, Microsoft
says this is a long-term project, so it means they're going to be pushing the industry to
take this thing seriously and support Windows 365 like a full-fledged version of Windows
in a universal way.
That's huge for Linux users.
That means when they need Windows software, they're likely going to be able to run it
on Windows 365.
It's funny how this changes the framing a little bit.
I'm realizing that, okay, I don't love Windows in general, but I really don't like it running
on my device.
And if Microsoft makes it easy for me to just use Windows when I have to, that's honestly
pretty nice.
I've played with Azure virtual desktops a little bit and played with running VMs on
Azure, and none of it was as seamless as it sounds like Windows 365 is going to be.
And I'll say this too, Wes, I've always felt like the best way to run Windows is in the
safety of a virtual machine, and now they're just going to do it for you.
It is funny how long it took them to get here in a sense.
I mean, other providers like Amazon have had this for a while, but Microsoft being the
maker of the operating system, I think, does give them pretty good advantage as an example.
They've got some nice tie-ins with existing Microsoft admin tools built into this thing
already.
Yeah, I agree.
It does seem like this has been a long time in the works, a lot like the first story we
started with with the deck.
The Steam Deck also feels like it's something that Valve has been working towards for a
long time.
But where Microsoft is going to stand out from, say, like the Amazon Web Services workspace
service, is Microsoft is going to offer a flat rate fee instead of a consumption-based
fee structure like it does for Azure and AWS does.
So they may have something that people can just pay a flat rate, maybe consumers could
pay like $10 a month and they get access to Windows 365 and Office 365 and they get everybody
all nice and locked in.
You know, that seems like where this is going.
But I look at it as an opportunity to enable more desktop Linux and I prefer to look at
it that way.
But we'll keep an eye on it and we'll keep an eye on everything else going on in the
open source Linux world.
So go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get them new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch.
Hey, don't miss the latest self-hosted episode.
It's now available at selfhosted.show slash 49.
As for us, we'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux in open
source news.
Thanks for joining us and we will see you next week.