Hello and welcome to Linux Action News Episode 240 for May 11th, 2022.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Let's do the news.
This week we have a special edition of the show.
Sometimes a news event is just so extraordinary we have to focus the episode to just get you
the most valuable information possible.
Today's Linux Action News is one of those episodes.
As we publish, NVIDIA has just announced a new long-term effort to work upstream to release
an open source kernel driver and related code for their GPUs.
Let that sink in for a moment.
The historic nature of this announcement really cannot be overstated.
What we know at this time is that NVIDIA's plans start with a focus on CUDA and compute
the goal for 3D display by the end of the year.
This work is not only the result of a significant change in thinking at NVIDIA, but also years
of interfacing with internal Red Hat staff.
Christian Schaller is the director for desktop, graphics, infotainment, and more at Red Hat.
He's been there for nearly 10 years and has been directly involved in the nouveau project.
He joined us earlier to discuss the details of NVIDIA's announcement from the Red Hat
perspective.
We started by asking him how long Red Hat has been involved behind the scenes to make
this happen.
Yeah, we've been probably talking with NVIDIA, I mean, we have had the bigger discussion
with NVIDIA around this for literally for years, pushing them towards this.
But I mean, in terms of this concrete effort that is now coming to fruition, I would say
that we've been working more intensively on it for at least three months.
Is the upside for Red Hat that there is a good amount of RHEL systems out there doing
compute with NVIDIA GPUs?
I mean, the upside for RHEL is, A, there is a lot of those systems out there, and this
announcement will make it easier for us to support that.
I mean, one sort of growing customer request, of course, is that they want to enable secure
boot on their systems.
And the fact that NVIDIA driver hasn't been signed up to this point has been a major point
of contention for enabling secure boot.
So it sort of means that we can get to a point where it is possible to have a signed driver
for NVIDIA.
The other thing that we feel is hugely valuable is that as part of this, right, we can have
more shared infrastructure between the open source stack and NVIDIA's binary stack.
Because when you've been using Nuvo for the last few years or tested it, you probably
realize that the performance you get out of Nuvo is not particularly impressive.
And the reason for that is that we have never been able to reclock the GPU to make use of
the power.
So one thing maybe your listeners are not aware of is that ever since NVIDIA started
signing their firmware, the only reason Nuvo has been able to support anything has because
NVIDIA has been releasing a special firmware for Nuvo to enable us to initialize the hardware.
The problem with this firmware was that it didn't have all the knobs and whistles because
NVIDIA was slowly working to redo things.
So we couldn't reclock with that.
So a big thing coming out of this announcement will be that, you know, regardless of the
details of how things look out, we will be able to have a shared firmware eventually
between the open source stack, including Nuvo, and the binary stack, which means that we
can do the reclocking.
It certainly means that we will have a situation on the NVIDIA side looking, you know, pretty
close to, for instance, what you can see on the AMD side where there is a closed source
AMD driver.
But for most people, the open source AMD driver is more than good enough.
And that's what I'm abusing.
So if I'm understanding you, there will still be a role for the Nuvo driver and for the
NVIDIA driver, even if the NVIDIA components are open source.
Exactly.
I mean, the thing that is sort of unclear is, well, or what we know for sure is that
whatever ends up being the future, it's not going to be today's Nuvo.
It's going to probably be that we work with NVIDIA to sort of create some sort of new
shared kernel driver that, you know, will be based on what they're open sourcing.
But it probably won't be exactly that.
And that will then go upstream into the kernel and for Turing hardware newer, because this
thing only affects Turing on newer, that will then be eventually the new open source kernel
graphics driver for NVIDIA GPUs.
That sounds like a lot of ongoing collaboration with NVIDIA.
Yeah.
I know you can't read minds, but could you help me try to wrap my head around why the
change of heart and direction here?
Was it just pressure about things like Secure Boot and look, our customers want this.
And so NVIDIA is trying to make a partner happy or is this some bigger land shift?
I think it's a bigger mind shift.
I think they have sort of realized that, you know, sticking with their current model beyond
just, you know, the practical concerns about like, how do you do Secure Boot and so on,
generates a lot of extra work and effort for them to write.
I mean, and it creates sort of a constant source of conflict with the kernel community
around, you know, GPL only headers and all this kind of things.
So I think this is sort of been something they've been working on for quite a while
before they sort of publicly shared with us that they were working on it, because it will
make their life easier and our life easier.
And by basically, like, you know, not having to sort of fight with the Linux community
in some sense about this.
It still feels like there's a big shift there.
Do you know, have there been other vendors partnering with NVIDIA on this effort?
Is it just been primarily a Red Hat NVIDIA effort?
I would say it's primarily a Red Hat NVIDIA effort.
And the reason for that is pretty simple.
I mean, there is no other Linux company out there who has significant resources on the
graphics side.
I mean, of course, I assume the other distros will be packaging this stuff.
But in terms of actually contributing upstream, I mean, if you look at both the kernel graphics
subsystem and Mesa and so on, you will see that, you know, there's Red Hat engineers
involved and, of course, engineers from other companies, but not necessarily from other
Linux distributions.
Right.
Do we know license details?
Like, is it MIT?
Is it GPL, I guess?
It must be GPL.
Yes, it will be.
I think they do licensing it, GPL, MIT, I think was.
OK.
Yeah.
So the bits that touch the kernel will be GPL.
All right.
That makes sense.
So, of course, an added benefit here for NVIDIA in the long term is that they will be able
to take advantage of all those GPL-only kernel APIs that so far has been off-limits to them.
Hmm.
I hadn't even really considered it from that angle.
This will make their engineers' life easier, too.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
Uh-huh.
That makes a lot of sense.
I mean, I'm still kind of putting the picture, like, this just seems like a real commitment
here, because if they're working with the Nuvoo driver, too, down the road, or they're
willing to work with Red Hat to shape that into something new, it sounds like they're
willing to commit almost an undefined amount of engineering time to this, just sort of
ongoing engineering time.
Yeah.
No, I mean, definitely.
I mean, this is going to be their primary way of supporting Linux going forward, right?
I mean, the binary driver will continue living on, I mean, especially because for pre-turing
chipsets, that's the only driver that will be available from NVIDIA.
Ah, okay.
So there are certain chipsets that the new stuff won't work with.
Yeah.
So, I mean, you need a GPU from 2018 or newer to take advantage of this.
So I mean, it's definitely a big effort, and they have, you know, they are committed,
and they've been working very closely with us for quite some time now, not just on this,
right?
We have almost weekly meetings with them, for instance, on making sure that NVIDIA and
Valiant support is top-notch.
Is this the fruit of that?
Well, I think that the reason why they reached out to us maybe beforehand is because we have
sort of established a strong relationship with them over the last few years.
I mean, I think it's sort of the initial effort that we started working closely on was, you
know, the GLVND effort when we put in place infrastructure to allow Mesa and the binary
driver to coexist.
Right.
I feel like that was sort of like the proving ground, and it sort of set the tone in some
sense.
And then we have been working together on, you know, discussing these things, discussing
how we can improve Nuvo, and then how we work around Nuvo with them, and of course, a lot
of discussion about compute, too, right?
How do we package?
Getting bigger and bigger, right.
Yeah.
So, Christian, maybe you can refresh my memory because it feels like it's been ancient history
now.
Was NVIDIA's initial reaction, would you characterize it as unhappy with the Nuvo driver attempt?
I'm wondering, have we seen a complete arc from, we're skeptical of this thing all the
way to now we're contributing to it, or am I misremembering that a little bit?
I don't know that I can say that they were, you know, statedly skeptical.
I mean, I think maybe, and this is purely from, call it a subjective perspective, this
was not what NVIDIA said, but I think maybe they at times were a little bit concerned
that Nuvo made their business model a bit harder.
I mean, you know, they often offered their GPUs in different market segments, and historically
they even shut off certain features through the driver.
So I think that probably fueled some skepticism, but over the years they have sort of moved
away from limiting things through the driver.
So I don't think that's a current concern for them, but of course, it definitely was
something that maybe colored things in the early years.
Yeah.
You know, their approach and things change.
So can you describe from your understanding how this is going to roll out from like say
a Fedora user's perspective, just sort of a kind of basics of how they're going to see
this rollout?
Yeah.
So what you will probably see happen is that, I mean, I expect relatively quickly, you know,
after day's release today, they will, we will have it packaged in Fedora.
And of course, if you're using Fedora to run CUDA based stuff, then you can of course start
making use of that right away.
And then of course, you will see a sort of steady stream of updates coming out from NVIDIA
towards the end of the year, adding more features and then, you know, ramping up the graphics
side of it.
And we will keep packaging that in Fedora, although of course, it's still an auto tree
driver.
I mean, to be clear about that, right?
So it's not, so there will still be, you know, some challenges around that fact.
But then in parallel with that, of course, we will be working with them and I mean, it
will happen in public, because it's not about just Red Hat and NVIDIA, right?
It's also about making sure we work openly with the existing Novo community and Mesa
community in general.
To come up with like, how can this look in the long run?
And how can we make sure that we have something that is, you know, suits all of NVIDIA's
needs and that suits all of the Mesa open source community's needs.
Hmm.
Okay.
You know, I have noticed recently, and I think Michael, our beloved Pharaonix also noticed
recently, there has been some compute specific code being submitted to the Linux kernel.
So this is all going upstream, it's not Fedora specific.
No, it's all going upstream.
I mean, as you can see from reading their blog post about this, I mean, the driver from
day one is publishing it on GitHub.
And then of course, part of the work with us, right, is, I mean, part of the reason
why we also want to do this shared driver is to get this upstream.
I mean, that will make life so much easier for everyone if it becomes the actual upstream
driver eventually that we have here and that is worked on by us and by community members
in general and of course, by NVIDIA engineers.
This really feels like every now and then in Linux, we've had these things that were
just these mountains that would just seem like they were going to be this way forever
and would never change.
And then one day they change.
And then we look on, okay, what's the next thing?
And I think for a lot of people, the next thing has always been, well, we got to get
that NVIDIA driver open source.
That's got to be the next thing.
That would really make life a lot easier for folks.
And now what?
Now what are we going to complain about?
Yeah, no, exactly.
I mean, you know, one thing I put a lot of blood, sweat, and tears into ever since joining
Red Hat is of course trying to beef up what we do around Fedora workstation and dealing
with NVIDIA driver has sort of, I mean, you know, we've worked with NVIDIA around GLWD
and so on because that was a critical point in making things smoother, but this will eventually
allow us to make NVIDIA an equally easy solution to work with as today with Intel and AMD, right?
Because it's, you know, upstream drivers, everything should work out of the box.
Since we're using the same firmware that NVIDIA is using for their closed source drivers,
it means that you don't get these kinds of delays that we, for instance, had with Novo.
And for me, this is sort of a huge step forward just in making Linux install and set up a
lot easier.
I feel that often if people these days try out Linux and trip up, it's often about like
either, you know, don't even knowing that you need to get this separate driver from
NVIDIA and then like, hey, why is my graphics performance so slow?
Or just having trouble still with it.
I mean, I think things have gotten a lot better thanks to, you know, getting things packaged
up and then made available to NOMO Software for us and so on and other people have put
it under ISOs to make it easier, but this will sort of, you know, remove all the needs
for all these kind of weird special casing and relying on third-party repositories and
all these kinds of things.
Yeah.
I mean, it feels like it's going to be a true, once we kind of see the full fruits of the
labor down, sounds like towards the end of the year and maybe beyond, we're going to
see a smoother desktop Linux experience than we've ever seen before, it sounds like.
And Red Hat is, I feel like this is a great example of Red Hat really doing something
at the, doing the really hard long-term work, especially you and people over there, you
know, doing this long, hard-term work to make this possible for all Linux systems.
So I mean, I know everybody's super grateful and I want to say personally, thank you, because
I have some NVIDIA cards right here in the studio and this is going to make life easier
for us.
Is there anything we haven't touched on that you think might be relevant to the discussion?
I mean, there's so much up in the air right now, any more clarity we could give?
No, I think it takes just, of course, one bigger reminder is that, you know, this is
not going to be an overnight fix, as we talked about.
NVIDIA's driver leaves some time to start supporting all the graphics cases and of course,
it will take time to do this rewrite to get everything upstream.
So people should expect to be a little bit patient before this is available, but this
will allow us to resolve a lot of items.
And it also allows us in my team to spend our resources better, because at the moment
we have Ben Skaggs, who's been a Novo maintainer, more or less working full-time on Novo.
And a lot of that is sort of just, you know, in collaboration with NVIDIA, but still sort
of trying to figure out how things work and so on.
And I know we can maybe have him more help push Envelope forward as opposed to just sort
of trying to keep Novo alive.
Right.
Yeah, that could be.
That might be something that's, yeah, I appreciate you underscoring that.
Because that could be a long-term benefit of this as well.
And it seems like this is going to improve the situation for laptops too, that come with
NVIDIA cards in them.
And hopefully we'll be able to focus on things like, you know, maybe next year, the year
after that, we're really nailing energy usage or something like that and fixing sleep and
things.
Yeah, exactly.
I mean, and it means that, you know, we will all be sharing the same infrastructure and
then, you know, this will be a lot easier for the desktop environments, right?
Because eventually you can, for the most part, rely on the MESA stack for everything.
So you don't need to have a special case or deal with all that OpenGL implementation
behaves a bit differently in so many cases and all these kind of things that creates
pain.
I mean, I think overall, I'm also just excited because I think it will allow us to more quickly
move forward with new features like, you know, one other big effort for graphics that we
have at Reddit at the moment, right, is trying to get HDR support plumbed through the system.
And that's one of these things where, you know, we need kernel drivers updated to support
it.
We need GNOME Shell updated to support it.
We need the GTK and Qt updated to support it.
So it's sort of like, and we need MESA updated to support it, we need open source Vulkan
drivers to support it.
So I mean, it's sort of like you need touching everywhere and then, of course, having NVIDIA
being such a critical part of the graphic ecosystem not being something we can touch,
but instead we have to then constantly wait for NVIDIA themselves to do updates in the
binder driver means that we can, you know, push these things forward a lot easier.
Right.
And it's also just going to make that story better for the distributions, right?
Because end users, especially new ones that are adopting Linux, they don't really appreciate
where the delay is in the feature set.
They don't understand that there's another vendor that has to release code.
They got their desktop distro and they want that feature and they don't really care why
it doesn't work.
Yeah.
Well, that may be a thing of the past in the near future.
Christian, thanks for helping explain all of this.
This is really exciting.
Yeah, I'm really excited too.
So I hope to hope, of course, also people who are listening in, if you are interested
in helping out, I mean, you know, the Mesa community is always happy for any contributors
to come along and help out.
Like any open source project, there are a lot more tasks and people at any given time.
No kidding.
We'll put some links out to help people find all that.
Thank you, Christian.
Thank you.
And I want to take a moment and thank our sponsors for making this reporting possible.
Thank you to Linode.
Go to linode.com slash land to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account.
Linode offers just the best options for developers, businesses and Linux users that don't want
the complexity of hyperscalers and don't need their endless options.
Linode's how we run everything we've built for the last few years in the cloud.
And you can tell when you use the product.
They love Linux.
It's what got them going 19 years ago.
And now they have some of the best services, 11 data centers around the world, 30 to 50
percent cheaper than the hyperscalers that are trying to lock into their platform.
They got some of the best performance, the absolute best support, and I love great features
like their object storage, their clean, simple API, command line tools, cloud firewall, backups
and more.
So go build something.
Go learn something.
Try it and support the show.
Get $100 by going to linode.com slash land.
That's $100 for 60 days on a new account.
Linux.ting.com and a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring Linux Action News.
If you're sick of overpaying cell service like I was back in 2013, go to Linux.ting.com.
I've been a customer since then because it's the smarter way to do mobile.
Ting offers nationwide coverage, a great mix of plans and fast data on LTE and 5G on the
big nationwide carrier networks, but you're interfacing with Ting, who was recently named
number one by Consumer Reports in 2021.
And Ting has great customer service and no contracts ever.
They got a plan that works for just about anybody out there, and you're going to start
saving right away.
So when you go to Linux.ting.com, you check your current phone.
If it's compatible, they're going to give you $25 in service credit.
But if you're ready to pull the trigger and buy a new phone, they'll give you $25 towards
a new device as well.
You're going to be amazed how simple and quick it is to get started.
They have a fantastic dashboard, and the plans are so straightforward, you're going to grok
it right away.
Go try it out.
See why I've been using it since 2013 and why Consumer Reports says they're the best.
Linux.ting.com.
After we wrapped, Christian mentioned he believes this is also going to be a huge benefit for
Vulkan video encoding and decoding as well.
That's something I hadn't even considered or gotten excited about yet.
I can only imagine, right?
You got to figure that the improvements and innovation we're going to see as this code
begins to land upstream is just going to multiply.
Like we might not even have a full picture yet.
This might just be the biggest story in Linux for 2022 that might continue to evolve with
new developments all the time.
I think no doubt there is more to come.
So we'll keep an eye on this and everything else in the world of free and open source
software.
Also, be sure you go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new
episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to keep in touch.
Don't miss out on the new Office Hours show.
We have a summer of projects here at Jupiter Broadcasting and we're covering the details
in each episode, officehours.hair, to get it.
As for us, well, we'll be back next week with our take on the latest Linux and open source
news.
Thanks for joining us.
That's all the news for this week.