Hello and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 211, recorded on December 26, 2021.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
And this week, we're not doing the news.
Not this week.
No, we're going to start with an update about the show itself.
Starting next week, January 2nd, Linux Unplugged will be moving into LAN's current Sunday
time slot.
That means Linux Action News will be moving to a little later in the week to hopefully
better capture the news cycle.
Right, that and really kind of balance out the entire Jupiter broadcasting release schedule
as well.
So, starting in the new year, all going to plan, of course, the next episode of Linux
Action News will be out January 6th, and then every Thursday after that.
We'll monitor this adjustment and watch for your feedback at linuxactionnews.com contact.
But the underlying goal here is to better position both LUP and LAN to sort of play
to their relative strengths.
And don't worry, I know a lot of you out there are Monday LAN commuters.
Linux Unplugged will be in that time slot.
It'll be there for you.
And it'll be better than ever at linuxunplugged.com slash subscribe.
We're just kind of moving things around on the board a little bit for the new year.
But with that business of show out of the way, let's get to the predicting.
Well, first, we've got to own up for last year, and I guess I'll start.
I thought that by this time, Mozilla would probably have just killed Pocket.
But no, seems like Pocket is still alive and kicking.
I liked this prediction, not because I wanted to see Pocket die, but because I thought it
was both possible and a bit bold.
Because you know, this time last year, we weren't really sure what was going to happen
with Mozilla.
It seemed like this was going to be a make or break it year.
But overall, 2021 worked out to be a better year for Mozilla than I think either one of
us expected.
And I don't think they got to a position where they needed to make cutbacks like this.
Because I listened back to the episode, Wes, and it sounded like that was your angle on
this was, well, they're gonna have to make cuts because things are trending badly.
And this is where they're gonna cut.
Yeah, I think I've just been questioning how invested have they actually been in Pocket?
Now I'll admit, I do give it some clicks when I'm using Firefox, I do have some articles
that I think are interesting.
But it's just a small piece of the evolving story of how does Mozilla get money, right?
Like I mean, they're still at least in 2020, really dependent on their search revenue from
Google, something like 86% of their revenue came from that source.
So well, their services are growing, still seems like an open question.
Yeah, I agree there.
Their VPN service has seen some good growth there.
There's some good trends, better trends at the end at this point than when we did this
show last year.
All right, I'll own up to one of mine, which I think I got right.
But I'm going to preface this, listening to this right now, it's going to seem like this
was an obvious one.
But when I made this prediction, Alma Linux hadn't been announced yet.
We had just really learned about the end of the traditional CentOS release.
So I predicted that at least three CentOS clones would ship essentially a 1.0 or their
first stable release in 2021.
And that's exactly what happened Alma Linux, Rocky Linux, Springdale Linux, and a few other
clones did end up shipping.
Not I guess a huge surprise, although for a little bit there, some of us thought maybe
Rocky wasn't going to actually make it.
All right, I have a couple of thoughts here, but let's start with, what is Springdale again?
Because I don't think we've cited that previously on Linux Action News.
No, I had to go look because I knew Alma and Rocky had done it, right?
And I was like, well, okay, who else?
Because I don't think Scientific Linux is presently shipping.
So I had to go find another one.
And it's a thing and they've shipped an ISO.
So I guess it counts, I think.
Yeah, yeah, I guess so.
I mean, it does make me think one uncertainty we had was we didn't really know where they're
going to be one, where they're going to be two, three, or a whole bunch of clones.
Because I mean, once you've got some in the space that prove it out, you can just keep
copying.
It's open source after all.
Yeah, I almost am surprised we didn't end up with like 10 or 15.
You know, and of course, like nine of them are horrible.
But it does seem like it's just maybe a harder task than, oh, I just copy the source RPMs
and rebuild it.
I think it turned out to be a harder job than that.
So but we did get at least a handful of them out there.
And then I think the other thing that we didn't really know, but we have a much clearer picture
of now is there's a lot of folks that just seem to be happy with stream itself and are
just sticking with CentOS and streaming.
And then something we learned on Linux Unplugged last week, pretty sizable people said, screw
it, I'm going to Ubuntu.
And none of us predicted that because, you know, it just seemed like too much of a pain
in the butt.
Yeah, that definitely caught me by surprise as well.
But speaking of Ubuntu, it's my turn again.
I predicted, hoped even perhaps that Ubuntu would ship SystemD HomeD sometime in 2021.
And I'm sad to say that didn't happen.
Did anybody, did any of the major desktop distros, I should say, ship SystemD HomeD
by default?
I don't think they did.
And in that episode, we were like, well Fedora will probably do it.
I don't even think, I mean, the version of SystemD that has it may have shipped.
But you specifically put yourself into a corner when you said, not only will the bits ship,
but it will be configured and enabled by default.
And you said Fedora is too certain.
So I'm going to go for a risky pick and choose Ubuntu because you had like this, this really
nice optimistic dream that they were going to be pushing the desktop technology stack
forward very aggressively in 2021, which just didn't really pan out.
No.
Wow.
Yeah.
So naive.
I think kind of the story we've been talking about sadly is some desktop disappointment
with Ubuntu, with Canonical's efforts there.
I mean, a lot still happening on the server side, but it just has not been the space to
watch for exciting changes or innovation on the desktop.
You never know though, Wes, there is an LTS coming up, things could change.
My next one was pretty bad.
You know, this was one of those where I thought maybe I was onto something because I was reading
tea leaves, which in other words is mailing list posts.
You don't even drink tea.
I know.
You know, it hurts the tummy, but I thought BcashFS would make it into the Linux kernel
in 2021.
I didn't necessarily think any distributions would use it or do anything with it.
But I thought, you know, by the end of the year, a shipping stable version of the Linux
kernel would have BcashFS mainlined.
And the things that I was reading in the mailing list were that they had hired a dedicated
tester.
There was a bunch of things they'd already identified.
It looked like they were on track to have some major stuff dialed in by summer.
And that, you know, if they got those bugs fixed by summer, then I had expected by, you
know, winter to be mainlined.
And it just didn't, it just didn't happen.
And you know, it's funny because here we are now at the end of 2021.
And I'm seeing some of that same stuff that makes me think maybe 2022.
You know, cause I could almost make that prediction and say it's going to happen in 2022.
But I am not, I may save it for Linux Unplugged.
And I will own up to the fact that it did not ship in 2021.
I got that one wrong, unfortunately, despite how much I would have loved to see that.
I would have loved it.
It just would have been so great.
Yeah.
And you know, that definitely shouldn't take away from Kent Overstreet's hard work continuing
the development.
I mean, on one, on one hand, I'm a little disappointed.
I think we're all excited to see what BcashFS might offer.
But on the other side of that coin, this is a final system after all, and it's better
to get it right than fast.
Linode dot com slash LAN.
Linode loves Linux.
And I love Linux too, so I can tell, you know, you can't fake that kind of thing.
And it's how we run everything now.
Like we've built everything out on Linode for the last couple of years.
You should really try it out because I'm sitting here telling you it's great.
And that's after years of now actually using it in production, running my business infrastructure
and running my personal stuff, you know, the kind of stuff you never want to go down because
you don't want you don't want things to be down for for your customers or, in my case,
your audience.
And you don't want things to be down when you're just sitting down for a few minutes
with the kiddos to play a little game, you know, like maybe you maybe got like 15, 20
minutes to play a game.
Right.
You don't want to deal with crappy performance or outages.
That's just not the time for that kind of thing.
And I've never had that problem with Linode.
And you know, there's been opportunities for them to be tested, like this recent log for
Jay vulnerability, Linode really stepped up to the plate on that.
If you're curious about what I'm talking about, go check their blog, go check their Twitter
feed.
I mean, they were just following this stuff from day one, making sure everybody is solid
and taken care of.
And they just have the best support in the business phone ticket, email, whatever your
method is, they're there every day of the year.
They don't do that escalation thing where they try to like pawn you off on some some
like, you know, first layer tech thing.
No, they take care of you.
They handle it right there.
There's no there's none of that.
It's really nice to know that's there.
But here's the best part when you go to Linode.com slash land, you get $100 to work with.
That's Linode saying they have confidence that if you actually put this thing into production,
they know you're going to like it.
All right, cuz I mean, they could give you like 10 bucks, 15 bucks, then you could run
some of their rigs for like two, three months, right?
Because they got great prices, they're 30 to 50% less than the major hyperscalers out
there.
But with $100, you could build real infrastructure, or you could really learn an entirely new
system.
Instead of even wanting to build an environment from scratch using Ansible or Terraform.
This is your opportunity.
Go do it and support the show.
Have some fun, learn something and support the show Linode.com slash land.
And a big thank you to Ting Linux.ting.com stop overpaying for cell service.
Why not do it right now at the beginning of a new year just start saving from the very
beginning Linux.ting.com go there and take 25 bucks off whatever you end up going with
a new device or a new plan.
You see Ting is an MVNO, a mobile virtual network operator.
That means a couple of things.
That means they have several nationwide networks for you to choose from.
That also means that your device is likely already compatible because of that multi network
compatibility.
And then on top of it, it means that they're not digging holes.
They're not fighting with local authorities.
They're not trying to get new laws passed and lobbying the state to get new towers installed.
They don't have to manage any of that.
So their business focuses on the customer and creating value and they've nailed it.
That's why I've been a customer since 2013.
It's just a smarter way to do mobile.
It's probably how the industry would have to operate today if they were to like reset
everything from the ground up.
They have plans that start around ten dollars a month and they kind of go up from there
depending on what you need.
A lot of their stuff is just like so simple that you just go to the website and it's just
one of them is going to be obvious which one should work for you.
You know, they got plans with unlimited data, unlimited calls and every single plan has
the nationwide LTE and 5G coverage.
How great is that?
And maybe one of my favorite things is no contracts.
They stay flexible.
Over the years, I've dialed back my usage.
I've increased my usage.
I've gone on road trips.
I've been all over the place and Ting has remained flexible and awesome and a great
value.
So here's how you get started.
You go to Linux.ting.com.
You check your current phone, you create an account, you pick the plan that's right for
you.
Ting is going to send you a SIM card.
You're going to pop that SIM card into your phone and then you're going to get activated
in minutes because they have a really nice clean dashboard.
Boop, boop, boop.
You're ready to go.
You didn't have to talk to a human if you didn't want to.
If you do want to, they got great customer support.
Cutting your phone bill in half has never been easier.
Ting has great plans.
You got to go check them out.
Kick off a new year and save a little bit of money and take 25 bucks off whatever you
find at Linux.ting.com.
And now it's time for our 2022 predictions.
I'll start things off.
I think that sometime in 2022, SUSE will release a RHEL clone of their very own.
Now, this is something we've speculated a bit before, specifically in LAN 2.10, but
they already offer RHEL support and there were some clues from Apple and our friend
Carl George that maybe there's something more in the works.
I could see it happening and 2022 seems like the year that it might.
Yeah, I thought if it was going to happen, they would have tried to have shipped before
end of life for CentOS.
I suppose there's still a few more hours on that clock as we record right now.
I say you're still going to get it if they release it in 2021 because this is either
going to ship or they're going to just shut down the whole thing.
The rumor mill has it that once we started talking about it on the show and it started
showing up on Twitter, the word went out internally to shut off all like Apple repositories.
So we no longer have any external numbers to go on.
But what we did see for a short period was what seemed to be a SUSE designed and built
RHEL clone that was connecting to external repositories and checking in for updates.
Quote, Liberty Linux.
Right.
Liberty Linux was the tagline and there was multiple connections.
It wasn't just one or two or three, it was many.
And this could be kind of like a kind of really calculated move by SUSE to make it easy to
migrate from RHEL to a SUSE infrastructure.
They did something similar like this back in the NetWare days, where they made it really
easy to transition from NetWare to SUSE in part by emulating NetWare.
And it was a strategy that worked for them.
So I think it's a solid bet, Wes.
Yeah, you know, I mean, they've already got robust build tools out there.
So I don't think that's going to be too much of an issue.
They're familiar with the RPM ecosystem, and they already provide commercial enterprise
support.
I mean, if anyone's going to try this, seems like it might be them.
Right.
That's the other aspect of this that we forget is they do have like a cheaper than RHEL patch
service that you can get that will patch SUSE boxes and RHEL boxes today.
So you can actually purchase a SUSE tool to patch your RHEL boxes.
So they're already probably maintaining, I would imagine, their own RPM repositories.
They're already taking the source RPMs and building them, possibly.
So it could just be they're increasing that infrastructure and growing that out.
I hope we see it because I think it's going to shock people to see SUSE shipping a RHEL
clone.
And I think it's going to make for a fun story if it ever happens.
And if it doesn't happen, if we're sitting here this time next year and it hasn't shipped,
it's going to be like, what the hell happened?
Because we saw it showing up on the numbers.
Something was out there called Liberty Linux coming from SUSE IPs.
All right.
Now, mine, I feel like my next one is a pretty sure bet.
I think both of us just want at least one win is what I feel like these first ones are.
And that's mine.
This one, everybody's going to roll their eyes when I say it.
But, you know, might as well try to get an easy win.
Asahi is going to ship, Asahi Linux is going to ship an installer for getting their version
of Linux or like, you know, an installer that gets another version like Arch or Debian or
something like that on M1 hardware.
I imagine it won't be an entire standalone distro, but more of a tool to get an existing
distro on an M1 Mac.
But it could be its own distro too.
It's pretty broad.
But that's something that's like targeted at end users and not just potential developers
or people trying to contribute to the bootstrapping effort.
Something like you might use to run a real desktop day to day on an M1 machine.
It seems like you could you could see a scenario where a developer edition, which is already
kind of out there.
There are there's already docs on how to do it by hand.
And you could see maybe a little rougher version of an installer coming to market first.
That is really for like your first wave adopters.
And then by the end of the year, there's something that's really even before the end of the year,
you know, midway, there's something targeted for average users who average Linux users
who just, you know, maybe picked up an M1 and they want to try getting Linux on it.
Now that's maybe a year old or so.
I think that's going to become as you think about it in terms of M1 hardware age right
now.
You know, when even when the project, especially when the project first started, some of these
people they just got themselves a 12 to $2,000, $1,300, whatever it is, MacBook, it's precious.
You don't want to try slamming Linux on that thing right now.
But you know, a year, year and a half into it.
It's just you know, your old laptop at that point.
So yeah, once you take it for granted, you've already messed it up a couple of times and
had to reinstall.
What a great time for a new Linux installer to come out and for people to start slamming
Linux on them.
And I think that could also play well for a crowdfunded project.
So that's my prediction is that in 2021, you're going to see Asahi ship an installer for average
Linux users.
People are familiar with Linux and want to get it on an M1 machine.
I know it's kind of a it's probably a sure bet, but that also just speaks to the confidence
I have in the project.
Okay, well, my question then is, if that happens, is that what it takes for you to start trying
Asahi on your M1, Chris?
Oh, I think so.
You know, because I didn't even touch on like GPU accelerated graphics, because for me personally,
I don't even need it.
I would love to be able to run a headless M1 server in my RV off solar because, you
know, even under load, it's taken hardly any power compared to most systems.
I think it just make a great little headless server.
So yeah, I'm all about it as soon as they as soon as they're shipping, I'm installing.
Well speaking of neat things in small packages, my next prediction is that SteamOS will have
a community fork out there sometime in 2022.
You know, with the deck launching with people getting really excited, I could see the community
wanting to leverage some of Valve's hard work sort of stabilizing Arch and then shipping
something that kind of bridges the gap and makes it a little more useful for you know,
non strictly gaming uses something that makes the AUR easy to set up something just sort
of smooth the gap between regular Arch.
Something that says, Hey, you out there, you want a workstation that's gaming ready and
has a OS tree style file system?
Well, we've got a distro for you.
Something that strips away some of the branding, you know, sort of all that red hat to send
us where they make sure they don't have any custom logos or trademark stuff in there.
And then they, you know, they sell it as vapor Linux or I guess maybe not vapor that's already
out there.
You know, I don't know what what you call but something that's probably a play on valve
or steam, right?
And then you go download that thing coal powered Linux.
I'm not sure gasoline Linux, I don't know.
But you know, and maybe it's gotten maybe it's got like a script that installs steam.
I don't know how it works.
But I could totally see that happening.
I hope it does.
Actually, I'm gonna be really disappointed if this prediction doesn't come true, because
I want I want to try it.
Well, yeah, that's just it.
You know, I don't I don't know that I really I tried running the last steam OS kind of
as a day to day way back in the day, I could see playing with it briefly.
But you know, if there's not something that's really meant for that, I think I'll just
keep it for the gaming use cases.
But I am looking for another arch replacement.
I mean, who's not?
Well, I suppose step one will be just getting the deck to ship.
And then step two is going to be valve needs to release steam OS.
And hopefully they'll be good about it and release all the bits.
Oh, geez, now that you say that that's a lot that needs to happen.
But fingers crossed.
There's some milestones, though.
You know, we can watch those milestones, we'll find out.
Okay, here is my next prediction.
It's a bit of a long shot, but boy, do I really hope this is going to happen.
So I'm looking at the Raspberry Pi lineup, and I'm liking what I'm seeing with the compute
module a lot this year.
I think that's made the Raspberry Pi a totally new kind of interesting for me.
My Pi 400 is one of my best little pieces of hardware I've ever bought.
I keep it set up in my office ready to go for like basic business stuff, you know, for
when I have to be a businessman.
And I think that's really nice.
So I thought maybe I'd try to make a prediction in this realm.
And I was looking at the Raspberry Pi 4, which has been really solid for me, I've been using
it as a server.
And you know, they launched the Pi 4 Model B in June of 2019 towards the end of June
2019.
And they have a lot going on.
And there is a worldwide part shortage.
So this is, it's hard to say, but I feel like enough hedging already out with it.
I think maybe we're gonna see a Raspberry Pi 5 at least announced in 2022.
I don't know if it's gonna be able to ship though, because the supply chain woes.
In fact, what we could end up seeing is a Pi 4a, you know, because you've got something
that they've remarked on is that their engineering team hasn't had a very good collaborative
year with work from home.
It's been tough on their team.
They've had supply chain issues, parts costs are going up, the devices they're making right
now, they're making them as fast as they can.
So what we may end up only getting is a Pi 4a.
But my long shot would be a Raspberry Pi 5.
That would be, you know, and then if I could go all the way, Wes, Raspberry Pi 5, with
a 16 gig of RAM option, and eMMC, but that's just not gonna happen.
Well, okay, what comes in the 4a then?
The 4a, I think, is a yeah, it's a CPU bump, you know, eight gigs of RAM still, I don't
think the 4a is a big change, other than some maybe like board or, you know, PCI layout
changes, maybe something in that regard, something that makes me look at and go, hmm, you know,
I could use it for, you know, something new or something extra.
It's tough to say because the compute module actually brings so much to the table that
I'm not, I'm not totally sure, but I could always use more memory and I could always
use more CPU.
Well, I'm just curious to see, you know, I think with the 4, it got really close to sort
of using a Pi in the Chromebook territory of performance and like, you know, low end
Linux desktop, so maybe a 4a, but I think certainly a 5 could really take that to the
next level.
How do I make this?
How do I square this?
Because it's like, it's really two predictions.
We're gonna either, I just, I think they're gonna, they're gonna rev the current 4, right?
That's what I'm going for.
The Raspberry Pi 4 Model B is gonna get a rev of some kind.
It's gonna, I don't know how they're gonna do it.
It may replace it altogether with the Raspberry Pi 5, or they may be like the B+.
If they, if the, if the Pi 4 hasn't been replaced, you know, with like a next iteration at this
time next year, I think it's a, I think it's a loss because like if they update the Picos
or the Pi 400, that doesn't count.
It's gotta be the flagship big Pi.
Ah, the flagship Pi.
Okay.
Well, I think you're going to get this one.
I'll be surprised if not, but time will tell.
We will see.
Um, I read a couple of interviews that make me think it's not going to happen because
they were set in expectations low, so we'll see, but I'd love to see it.
And then we have, we have a Linux action news tradition here on the show.
I don't know why, but it started with Joe and I talking about Bitcoin and trying to
make our annual Bitcoin predictions.
And it just seems like an impossible thing to do, but we did want to do a little reflection.
Yeah, we like being wrong.
And what better way than to try to speculate about the price of cryptocurrency?
There's no better way.
There's no better way to be wrong faster either.
And 2021 was a wild year for cryptocurrency and Bitcoin in general.
At the beginning of the year, Bitcoin shot up to nearly $40,000 at the end of January.
April 3rd, it broke $63,000 and then it just ramped down and up for the rest of summer.
And then in early October, an all time high of $68,000 was hit and then crashed down about
40% for about four days and then has built up some of its losses.
And it's now, as we record sitting around 51,000, but here's some interesting numbers
for you, Wes, as of 2021, the entire crypto market, when you include like Ethereum and
a lot of the altcoins is now worth $2.4 trillion.
It's truly just become its own economy.
And to put that in perspective, crypto market is 2.4 trillion.
All of France's economy is 3 trillion.
India's economy, 2.8 trillion.
If you take out just Bitcoin, Bitcoin is a trillion on its own, over a trillion on its
own, which is larger than Italy's economy by a lot.
Just Bitcoin alone is barking at the size of India's economy.
I mean, you know, that's something, Wes, that is, those are huge, huge numbers.
Well, and it just seems to be far more present just in the culture, right?
I mean, many folks who are otherwise not interested in technology or speculating in stocks, well,
they know what crypto is, and maybe they have a small amount of it.
It's certainly become more popular in institutions.
Yeah, that's been, it's been a big trend this year, some large institutions, including JP
Morgan.
Their crypto strategy go all in El Salvador, the city of Miami.
These really interesting ones, Coinbase had their IPO, rocky year, but they're doing kind
of better now towards the end of the year.
Those all were big institutional moves that started to legitimize cryptocurrency for,
I think, another wave of adoption.
You still have tons and tons of critics and skeptics out there, but I think another wave
of adoption happened in 2021.
Like you're saying, getting really close to that near mainstream, and it's really interesting
how it sort of reminded me a lot of Linux's early uptake.
A lot of people thought, what does it do that Windows doesn't do or network isn't doing?
What is the critical app of Linux?
What is its critical function?
A lot of people were skeptical about the security model, about open source and free software
developers just donating their time, about IP issues, a lot of early skepticism.
And then some of us really saw some potential in it and really stuck with it, and then 30
years later and it dominates the world.
Bitcoin, it's been around since 2009, and if you look at its trajectory and you compare
it to previous adoptions, a lot of people will compare it to the internet and say that
it has a faster pace of adoption than the internet did in its early years.
But I don't know if it's an apt comparison because Bitcoin is more like a protocol.
It's more like the slow adoption of TCP IP.
When TCP IP was announced, there was dozens of competitors, NetBui, IPX, Appletalk, Token,
all these different network standards that all of these different vendors tried to push
and sort of pooh-poohed all over TCP IP.
But over time, it just became the great unifier, became the great nullifier, and it just took
over.
And it seems like we're seeing a similar trajectory that just has become obvious in 2021.
Coin Ring was obviously trying to hint at our crypto future.
The other thing that happened was a China ban on mining, which represented a ginormous
portion of the Bitcoin network.
They cracked down and the network hash rate dropped, and then the mining spun up mostly
in Western countries, and now the hash rate's higher than it was before China did the crackdown.
So it's hard to say like, what could 2022 possibly, what could happen, right?
You have world economies that are a mess.
Who knows?
It just feels more impossible than ever to make a prediction because there's so many
factors now.
Well, that's just it.
I think it's more in the front of everyone's mind.
We're waiting on decisions about regulation.
And I think we're waiting to see what 2022 brings for the overall market.
I'm kind of curious to see what bears out when we do have more of a bear market.
If people are forced to start to divest in some of their holdings, do they choose to
do that in stocks or gold or is crypto the thing that they sell first?
I don't know, but I'm curious to see what happens.
So here's my prediction, because I got a price prediction, but I actually think there's something
else that probably should be called out here.
So right now, like if you just look within the last week or two, you'll find several
accredited, intelligent people who say Bitcoin's going to collapse.
Carol Alexander, professor of finance over at Sussex University or Sussex University,
said that she expects Bitcoin to tank as low as $10,000 in 2022.
She says it's going to wipe out the gains of basically the last two years.
And if you're invested in Bitcoin, you should get out now.
It has no fundamental value.
And then you've got others that say it has intrinsic value because it's a digital currency
you can send anywhere around the world.
There's a fixed cost to mine it.
The utility of it gives it its worth.
And then, of course, like humans, it's worth whatever we say it is.
And these are two battles that have been playing out since 2009.
And I think in 2022, one side's going to have to shut up.
Either this thing's going to the moon side's going to win, or the people that say this
thing like your Peter Schiff's or your Carol Alexander's say this thing's going to crash.
They're going to have to shut up by the end of 2022, because it's going to get to a point
where it's just either going to be ludicrous to make those claims anymore, or it's going
to be they were right all along.
And so we will end that debate, and in the process of starting all of this out, it's
either going to be heralded as the moment right before the big crash, or the moment
right before it took off Bitcoin, at least momentarily in 2022, I predict will hit $70,000.
I see you're not stepping too far out, right?
If it was a 68 or so back in October, then just hitting 70 sometime in the year.
That doesn't seem too outlandish.
But I guess my question is, where do you think it's going to end up?
Right?
Okay, we might have another, you know, summer of crypto where everyone's excited, but December
next year, where are we going to be tough to say, huh?
Because it does, it does seem like more and more of the normals are learning about cryptocurrencies
and theorem included.
And here's something else I've noticed.
Linux appeals to a narrow band of people that are trying to get something done or have a
certain philosophy about the world.
But a lot of people like making money.
And so people who are not technically inclined, are interested in making money.
And I gave my son a little bit of Bitcoin for Christmas.
And he's 12 years old.
You know what, though, you know what, Wes, he got it immediately.
And the fact that it was digital, and not like tied to a physical metal or something,
is a complete non issue for my son who, you know, has lived in a Minecraft style metaverse
and just works with digital stuff.
He's done online schooling.
All of it is digital to him.
It's all digital.
And so to him, the fact that it's a digital asset is huge because he's 12 years old, right?
Now all of a sudden, he's basically got a bank on his phone.
And he's thinking about how to convert this cash that he's got into that.
So that way, maybe he'll grow that a little bit over time, just thinking like the way
he just got it made me realize the younger generation, like, you know, younger than you
and I are even more digitally inclined, they're even more just tuned into this kind of thing.
And so you got those people coming online.
They're gonna have some spendable money, you know, 18, 19, 20, 25 year olds, they're gonna
be coming online, they're gonna be able to get the cash app, they're gonna be able to,
you know, get the strike app.
Well, that's just it, right?
That it's so much easier now, you don't have to understand necessarily how to host your
own wallet or be running software on your system.
There's friendly apps that let you buy stocks and crypto at the same time.
Also you got the fact that as of 2021, 90% of all bitcoins have been mined.
Only 10% of the 21 million now remains.
That is going to create a supply crunch.
Also you mean just thinking of price pressure, the Bitcoin miners are holding, right?
The exchanges are at a three year inventory low for Bitcoin right now, because the Bitcoin
miners are holding waiting for the prices to come up.
But you've also got inflation in the US that's really bad right now, not just the US, right?
I mean, Bitcoin is a worldwide currency and inflation is going rampant in all kinds of
places and there's going to be a percentage right or wrong that see Bitcoin as an inflation
hedge.
So those things I think are going to drive the price up.
But then you have the fact that here in the States, interest rates are going up.
So cheap or free money is going away.
So the institutional investors are going to pull back.
So it really seems like it could be anyone's game, but when you factor in the limited supply,
the fact that inflation is a problem, mainstream adoption, easy technological innovations,
the fact that we really haven't seen the benefits from the lightning network coming online yet,
which is going to make transactions super fast and super cheap, and you have El Salvador
that's just kind of getting their stuff sorted out, I kind of feel like on the all it's going
to end up higher than lower.
And when I say 70,000, I hope I'm I hope it's going to be higher than 70,000.
But you know, if you've pinned your hopes on something like that, Bitcoin will disappoint.
Yeah, I think I'll be I'll be the bear today, then and not too much.
But I think we're just gonna see a flat 2020.
Probably this time next year, we'll be flirting around 50k just the same that we are now,
you know, maybe a little over maybe a little under, but nothing too far different from
50k.
I mean, that sounds boring, but reasonable with you know, especially with the altcoins
like Ethereum and others out there that are showing some interesting technical solutions.
I can see the money going from Bitcoin to things like Ethereum or salon and stuff like
that.
We'll see.
We don't know.
That's why we only talk about it once a year.
Otherwise, it's back to Linux and open source for us starting in January on Thursdays.
So go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe so that way you don't miss a single episode
in the transition.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to keep in touch.
And join us on a Sunday now Linux Unplugged will be live over at jblive.tv around 1230
Pacific and that would be 3pm Eastern at jblive.tv.
As for this show, well, we'll be back Thursday the 6th with our weekly take on the latest
Linux and open source news.
Thanks for joining us and Happy New Year.