Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 266, recorded on November 9th, 2022.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Let's do the news.
We start this week with an observation.
It was not a particularly busy news week in Linux, but there are a few things we wanted
you to know about.
Big Neomundu Summit, which is just wrapped up in Prague after a couple year hiatus.
Yeah, unfortunately, we could not attend this year just due to scheduling conflicts.
But the company did live stream the event.
And we will have a link to each day in the notes.
Sheldon Worth kicked off the three-day event with a bit of a keynote.
All right.
Hello, everybody.
How's this working?
Can you hear me at the back OK?
What a treat to be here in Prague with all of you.
Thank you for making the trip.
It is my greatest, greatest, greatest pleasure to host you here.
And I'm extremely excited for what we're going to be talking about, what we're going to achieve,
and what we're going to enable other people to do with open source.
The community-focused event followed multiple internal company get-togethers that took place
at the same venue, with Mark Shettleworth noting that they had over 500 canonical staffers
there during the Q&A portion of his talk.
Why this specific place?
Yes.
Because we were 500 people last week, and we needed at least 500 rooms, and this place
has 800.
Yeah, and as that Q&A rolled on, Mark proceeded to touch on the tension between the feeling
of being part of something larger and the tension of working from home, and how Canonical
had to adapt during the pandemic as well.
So at Canonical, I got to tell you, we work pretty darn hard, and we work from home, right,
which kind of means everybody gets a corner office, which is great.
But the times that we get together are critical to the health and sanity of a distributed
workforce.
So there's this tension, right, like I think you wouldn't work at Canonical if you didn't
want to be working at home, but then if you were only working at home, you wouldn't feel
part of something much, much bigger.
So for me, it's really, really important that everyone at Canonical makes a commitment twice
a year to get together, not just with their own team, but with lots of other teams.
And I love watching the kind of experiences that people have, because people who've just
joined the company are working inside one team for up to six months, working on one
problem, and then suddenly they realize, wow, I'm in the middle of all of these interesting,
potent, difficult, important threads, right?
And that's really important.
The pandemic, you'd think that the pandemic would be really easy for a remote first organization.
It wasn't.
It really wasn't, right?
And I can tell you, we really missed this feeling of getting together, right, and working
stuff out in person, reaffirming our commitments and our relationships in person, right?
So how do we make that work?
How do we make that work?
Well, what I think is fun is that we try to pick interesting places, right?
This is a very interesting place for lots of different reasons, right?
First, lots of James Bond movies have been shot here over the years.
And second, beer is cheaper than water.
And third, the non-alcoholic beer is very good.
So it seems like there are lots of great reasons to be here.
And when we're in a place, we need a venue where we can all be together.
This event might be the restart of the Ubuntu Summits.
And unlike the Ubuntu Dev Summits of the past, Canonical's intention this time around seems
to be aiming for a bigger tent, an opportunity for them to hear from the community and a
chance for Canonical to showcase their solutions and ideas.
Microsoft has a new version of.NET and one of its headline features is bigger, better,
badder Linux support.
Yes, dear audience member, you heard that right.
One of.NET 7's big new features is improved support and performance on Linux.
Now it even has native ARM64 support and yes, IBM Power as well.
Wow.
Okay.
I mean, there's a lot in.NET 7, no doubt.
That's really kind of a Coda radio story.
But I was just thinking in the Linux terms, if I could travel back in time to young Linux
using Chris in the late 90s, and I could tell him that one day Microsoft would have this
product called.NET, this development language called.NET, and they were releasing this
big new version and they were promoting its new Linux features, I could only imagine how
young me would respond.
I would guess his first question would probably be, how'd you get so damn fat?
And then his second question would be, why did Microsoft pick such a stupid name like
.NET?
Sadly, even in 2022, we don't have answers for those questions yet.
But sticking with Microsoft for just a moment longer, a surprising amount of you out there
were upset when the death of the team's desktop Linux app was announced.
Well, good news.
This week, Microsoft launched the team's progressive web app for desktop Linux.
And you know what?
This might actually be an upgrade for y'all.
I mean, typically, when we talk about a desktop app getting discontinued in favor of a web
app, that's a downgrade.
But teams was always just a web app in different clothing.
And now this PWA brings the Linux version at least closer to being feature parity with
the Windows teams version.
This is how Microsoft puts it in their announcement, they say, quote, a progressive web app enables
us to ship the latest Microsoft Teams feature faster to our Linux customers, and helps us
bridge the gaps between the team's desktop client on Linux and Windows.
The PWA experience is available for both edge and Chrome browsers running on Linux.
Now that's all well and good.
And I'm happy to see investment on Linux here.
But it kind of sounds like maybe Firefox is being left out of this little browser bunch.
If anyone out there has tried to let us know.
That's one bit of research we're happy to outsource.
The standards body behind OpenGL, OpenCL, Vulkan, and some of your other favorites out
there have announced their next graphics API.
And it's called Cameras.
Yes, the Kronos group is working on this new API with the European Machine Vision Association.
The work started back in March, and it's aiming to create a royalty free standard for controlling
camera system runtimes across embedded, mobile, industrial, extended reality, automotive and
scientific markets.
Yeah, you know, having messed around a little bit with embedded remote camera systems, I
can see the need for that.
It is tricky.
So this Cameras API would sit sort of between like software using say FFmpeg or whatever
it might be.
And then the hardware and transports that talk to the actual hardware, be it attached
directly or over the network.
They intend to also support multiple programming languages, and they're going to have a loadable
layer system just like Vulkan and some of the other standards do.
You can think of this layer feature as a command dispatch system that enables developers to
use installable layers for validation, profiling, debugging, things like that.
One question that's still in my mind at this point is what does the introduction of Cameras
mean for Lib Camera?
That's a good question.
We don't know.
I mean, Lib Camera, I think that's a Raspberry Pi project.
So it's potentially single vendor where this wants to sort of create a universal standard.
I mean, you know what you do when you have too many standards or in this case, too many
APIs.
You've got to do the right thing, Wes, and create a universal API that just covers everyone's
use cases.
That'll solve it.
A quick mention for the new FWUPd release this week, version 1.8.7.
The headline feature is more hardware support from Star Labs, including their upcoming Star
Fighter laptop, though we might be most excited about the experimental support for Intel's
discrete GPUs.
Also included is support for fingerprint lengthy devices, Anker's Thunderbolt 4 Mini Hub,
Elan Haptic hardware, and more than a few other devices.
Some new features this time around, well, they include the ability to measure system
integrity when you're installing UEFI updates, and support for XZ compressed metadata, which
should reduce the bandwidth used to download firmware files by approximately 25%.
We'll link to the release notes because we're really just scratching the surface on this
one.
Linode.com slash LAN.
That's where you go to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account.
It's a great way to support the show while you're checking out Linode.
They make cloud computing simple, affordable, and accessible.
It's how we run everything we've built in the last few years, including our new website,
or if we wanted to check out something that requires a GPU, or we wanted to build a matrix
community.
If you want to do anything from running something for your business, or hosting something for
yourself, Linode's the way to go.
30% to 50% cheaper than those big hyperscalers, and a machine that's going to fit your needs
perfectly.
And on top of that, great performance.
They've got 11 data centers for you to choose from today, and a dozen more coming on next
year.
And great features such as object storage, cloud firewall backups, and Kubernetes support,
and so much more.
So go build something, go learn something, and support the show.
Check out Linode by going to linode.com slash lan.
Get that $100, and support the show, linode.com slash lan.
And also, thank you to Kalyde.
Kalyde is an endpoint security solution that uses the most powerful, untapped resource
in IT, end users.
Instead of forcing old-school MDMs on your users, Kalyde sends them security recommendations
via Slack.
Kalyde will automatically notify your team when their devices are insecure, and give
them step-by-step instructions on how to solve the problem.
By reaching out to employees via a friendly Slack DM, and educating them about company
policies, Kalyde can help you build a culture in which everyone contributes to security,
because everyone understands how and why to do it.
For IT admins, Kalyde provides a single dashboard that lets you monitor the security of your
entire fleet for Mac, Windows, and of course, Linux.
So that's Kalyde, user-centered, cross-platform, endpoint security for teams that Slack.
You can meet your compliance goals by putting users first.
Visit Kalyde.com slash LAN to find out how.
If you follow that link, they'll hook you up with a goodie bag, including a t-shirt,
just for activating a free trial.
That's K-O-L-I-D-E dot com slash LAN.
We end this week with a nice fireside chat between Pat Gelsinger and Linus Torvalds.
The casual conversation was conducted at Intel's Innovation 2022 event, where Intel's CEO got
to sit down and have a wide range of topics to be discussed with Mr. Torvalds.
Intel Innovation is their developer-focused event that they say spotlights the tools,
training, and community to empower the world's developers to create what's next.
So the topics are more developer- and ecosystem-focused than you typically get in some of these fireside
chats with Linus.
One of my favorite moments is when Linus talks about what's most important about open source
to him personally.
And I think one of the most important parts to open source for me has been that everybody
needs to feel like they are in equal footing.
We've had a lot of companies who do dual licensing, and it's perfectly legally fine, but it tends
to result in politics and internal strife about the project when one company or one
entity has more rights than the other entities.
So I've personally tried to always keep all my projects that very clearly I'm not special,
I'm the top-level maintainer when it comes to the kernel, but if somebody else does a
better job and one day that will happen, they will take over because I don't have any special
rights except for the fact that people trust me because I've been doing it for 30 plus
years.
It does seem like open source trust, this idea of contributing to the community and
having the exposure of the community and then finally the trust of the community.
Yes.
But I mean, so you say, I don't actually like the notion of contributing to the community
because that implies a certain amount of altruism that I'm not a huge believer in.
So I really think it's more like you're not contributing to the community.
What you're doing is you're trying to make a project better for yourself and the rules
of the project end up then meaning that as you're making it better for yourself and trying
to improve your own situation, you kind of indirectly contribute to the community.
But you should always be motivated by your needs and that's actually how a lot of these
open source projects, including very much the kernel, have improved so much is because
I'm looking at all we've done in the last 25 years and none of it was stuff that I needed
or I wanted because as far as I was concerned, 25 years ago, the system pretty much did what
I needed.
There's also this moment when things get a bit real.
Linus tells Intel CEO Pat Gelsinger that people don't seem very happy at Intel anymore.
I think everybody knows that issue.
The problems on the execution side have been pretty painful for everybody and I don't see
any of the hardware and fab issues.
What I have seen are kind of the fallout from the Intel software development standpoint
where the last few years have not been quite as ebullient as they were before and people
have not been as happy with being inside of Intel because I don't think Intel has necessarily
been a very happy place for a few years and I'm hoping that's changing.
Well that's certainly my job to change it as well and we're getting on it as we rebuild
and obviously having events like this one are about rebuilding our commitment, our engagement
with the community, participating, driving standards as well.
Linus then goes on to stress how vital hardware documentation is and how Intel could lead
there, but another of my favorite moments was when Linus shared his thoughts on companies
like Intel using software to limit hardware features for marketing purposes.
And since I have your ear and this may be cut out, the thing I sometimes despise about
different companies and Intel has had that problem is when you do market segmentation
where certain features only exist in certain markets that aren't necessarily as available
as others and I'm thinking of things like the transactional memory.
I mean it's gone now, maybe it's never coming back, but that was very painful for us when
only certain server CPUs had it and the people who actually needed to develop for it couldn't
access it easily on their own desktops and that's I think an area where Intel can maybe
improve and not let the market segmentation drive these kind of technical issues that
make it hard for developers.
You tell them Linus and respect to Intel for leaving that bit in the interview, they could
have cut that criticism.
Overall though it's a friendly low key chat, it's about 29 minutes long and we recommend
it.
And in our show notes and while you're over there, check out linuxactionnews.com slash
subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact to let us know how that new Teams PWA is going for
you.
Yeah, and be sure to check out Office Hours.
We have a lot of projects going on and some new features for our audience are in development.
OfficeHours.hair and episode 16 comes out on Friday.
Don't worry though, we'll be back right here next week with our take on the latest Linux
and open source news.
Thanks for joining us and that's all the news for this week.