Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open source world.
This is episode 99, recorded on March 31st, 2019. I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe. Good to be connect with you on Lucky 99. And we start out with some new software
from Mozilla.
Yeah, Firefox Lockbox has come to Android. And that allows you to sync your passwords
over from the desktop. And I've tried it out and it works pretty well.
This is another one of those was a test pilot. And then they launched it on iOS. On iOS,
they recently updated it to be more iPad friendly, as they say. And now we have it on Android.
So I guess the value proposition here is, if you've already invested in saving all of
your passwords in Firefox, this now abstracts them out essentially from Firefox. So it utilizes
that same password database, synchronizes it to the lockbox, you log in with your Mozilla
account, and Bob's your uncle, there's all your passwords from Firefox. And on these
mobile platforms, you can opt to also turn on autofill. So it will autofill apps and
other websites from other browsers.
Yeah, I tried out that autofill feature. And that worked absolutely perfectly. I was very
impressed with this generally, I must say.
And much like LastPass and other password managers that are out there, although lockbox
is a little simpler than a lot of what's out there, that might actually be kind of appealing
because it's not like too much. But for me, it's definitely not enough. And they're pitching
this at complete newbies to password management. Like in their blog post, they write, say goodbye
to the password cheat sheet. Store it as a note or a contact in your phone or maybe written
on a sticky note on your desk. Like you're no longer doing the under the keyboard thing.
That's who they're pitching this at.
Oh, yeah, definitely. But I think one reason to switch to it from LastPass is the fact
that it is open source. Unfortunately, it's not on F-Droid yet. So you do need the Play
Store to install it. But I'd rather use something that I know is open source and comes from
a trusted organization like Mozilla than LastPass, which they've had some breaches in the past
and I don't know, I just don't trust them somehow. Whereas I'm very tempted to start
using this.
But I really can't disagree with any of that. I would say if you haven't been using a password
manager, this might be a decent place to start, especially if you're a heavy Firefox user.
For me, I've been using LastPass now for so long that I disabled the built in Firefox
password manager. And so I have like a total of five passwords saved in my Firefox password
database and everything else is in LastPass. So this service has not a lot of intrinsic
value to me because I've already been using LastPass for so long. And there's a lot of
other good alternatives out there as well, like key pass and many others that people
could tell us about at linuxactionnews.com contact that I really feel like this is aimed
at the new to password management market that are heavily invested in Firefox, which is
a pretty narrow niche. But going back to your point, I do really like that this is open
source.
Yeah, and I think this is something that Mozilla should be spending money on. Some of the stuff
they've done before is a bit questionable, but I think this is very useful. And the tight
integration with Firefox means that it is actually really useful for people. And it
means that you can use Firefox on the desktop. You don't necessarily even have to use Firefox
on Android to take advantage of this because most people use apps for everything. So it
seems like the kind of thing I want to see them doing.
So let's talk about something Google is doing that I'm not yet sure how I feel about this.
They're bringing AMP to email, of course, starting with Gmail.
Of course with Gmail. So AMP accelerated mobile pages, which was originally a way to make
websites that were really stripped down and worked really quickly on mobile. But the features
have crept in and crept in. And now they're putting this into email. It was announced
about a year ago, and it's taken this long to be fully rolled out. And it's just something
that I'm not interested in at all. I don't even like HTML emails really. Never mind rich
features like carousels and being able to vote in polls and interact with emails. I
want emails to be just a plain text document really. I want just some facts in that email
and maybe some links that I can then click through. But the whole point of it is to make
it simpler, make it so that you don't have to click through.
So I think some people will like it. But for me, it just seems like emails fine. Don't
mess with it.
Google pitches this as turning email into a surface to get things done, which is pretty
broad. Another way to say is it's a way to turn emails more into apps without using a
ton of JavaScript. So this is a reduced version of the AMP spec specifically for email. We'll
have a link in the show notes if you want more information. And there are a considerable
amount of security considerations that have been put into this.
So let's talk about what Google is trying to do here. The way Google frames this is
that there is a movement for interactive emails that is being driven by large corporations
that want to have more engaging emails. And there's all these different competing ideas.
And so this is their suggestion. And from a high level, the advantages it offers is
real time content in emails like you could have flight information that's updated in
real time or news stories or weather that is updated real time in an email thread. You
could bring in other components. Google has partners they brought on like Pinterest and
others that will have dynamic content that updates in the email. It sounds like a nightmare
to me personally. However, Google's version of future is this is coming whether you want
it or not.
That is a reasonable argument. I suppose that if it's going to happen, then at least make
it an open standard and have it all be open source and everything. But I'd rather that
they just said no, we're not going to stand for this. Gmail is one of the biggest if not
the biggest email platforms in the world. And they could just say we're going to block
all of this HTML and JavaScript stuff, rather than encouraging it like this. But I suppose
then, ultimately, people may start switching away. And that's probably what they're worried
about.
One of the things that I admittedly thought this would be for would be so that way Google
could guarantee a way to deliver rich ads in email because right, I mean, that seems
like one of the things you would want a more interactive email experience to have is advertising.
But when you look at the AMP for email spec, they specifically removed the advertising
portion of the AMP spec. It's not allowed in AMP for email. And on top of that, if you
want to send one of these emails to a Gmail user, you have to go ask permission from Google
directly. And they have a whole series of verifications you have to go through and steps
you have to take to send AMP emails to Gmail users.
How long is it going to be before adverts slip into this, though? Because originally
AMP didn't have any adverts. And then eventually, they added that feature. And they've made
a bit of a song and dance about the fact that this doesn't have adverts in it. But it's
surely a matter of time.
I should think so. And AMP still has the original issues that we have with AMP. And that is
that is controlled primarily by Google. I admit they set up that new council, but that
council is still pretty much controlled by Google. And I'm not comfortable with this
very heavy handed using the leverage of Gmail. And they've partnered up with outlook.com
and mail.ru to also support AMP emails. So they're using this very large market lever
to really essentially force a standard onto everybody. And email used to be the one last
remaining decentralized standard and protocol we have. Anybody could set up SMTP and IMAP
and POP3 or whatever the hell they want and have their own mail server. I don't recommend
it, but anybody could do it. But now we're beginning to see a shift where at least a
portion of the content of an email is going to be centrally controlled by one corporation.
Well, not necessarily, because they're not changing the way email works. They're adding
to it. And so this will be optional. And you can still send plain text emails to each other
without this. And I don't think they're ever going to stop that happening. And maybe you'll
just get a link to the content or whatever if your client doesn't support it. So I think
people will be able to just block this.
Yeah, they're going to have to have a fallback mode. You're right. Because a lot of people
just have plain text turned on on their mail client. And so there will have to be some
sort of fallback system. And I think what I'm getting at is Google's going to have,
they could if this takes off, have a very critical part of what becomes modern email.
They could really kind of own that. And maybe you could argue they already do with Gmail,
but I don't know, this just feels different. If you could just hit the reset button and
do AMP over again, it almost makes more sense in this context, especially in its more restricted
mode. You could kind of see like, start here, start with AMP for email and then over time
grow it to the web. Because I think undoubtedly part of it is my biases I have about AMP for
the web and how that's been bad for publishers, like ourselves, has influenced how I view
AMP for email. When it actually seems like it could be, especially when you watch some
of Google's videos, a pretty usable product, or at least one that you could see a lot of
companies would want to use. I don't know if I want it, but when you see their product
demonstrations, it's clear there's going to be market demand for something like this.
Well, I think you've almost hit the nail on the head there in that it's solving a problem
that doesn't exist. It's companies wanting to solve this problem.
Yes.
And it will appeal to them. But I don't think it's necessarily going to appeal to consumers,
because it's certainly not appealing to either of us.
I already hate my email. I don't want it doing more things. I don't need the weather updated
in my email. And I realized that was just a really cute example they had. But I'm perfectly
okay with just getting the link to go get the most relevant information. And I'm good
with that. And I'd like to keep email as clean and simple as possible. Then it's easier to
encrypt. It's easier. It's more standards compliant. But I doubt I'm going to get my
wish on that one, Joe.
Yeah. All right. Well, things have been happening in Ubuntu land this week.
Yeah. I have gotten my wish on one thing, and that is performance improvements and stability
improvements to the GNOME Shell Stack. And these are very apparent in the new Ubuntu
19.04. We wanted to give a quick rundown of a couple of these because there's some big
progress that's going to be trickling down to a lot of the new distribution releases
starting right here.
GNOME Shell 3.32, it's going to be shipping with Linux kernel 5.0, and a bunch of other
new things. I've been running it for two months now, I think. A month and a half at least.
And it's the fastest, most reliable GNOME experience I've ever had.
And now they've reached this beta milestone, beta one. It's really looking ready to ship,
isn't it?
Yeah. We don't normally talk about betas on this show. But with Linux 5.0 in there and
the new release of GNOME Shell, I think this is going to be a milestone release, like I
said, of all of the distributions of this next generation of 2019.
But it's not just the main version of Ubuntu, of course. All the other flavors have released
their beta one of 19.04. But Ubuntu Mate has released a beta of 18.04 for the Raspberry
Pi.
And I've been checking this out and it's pretty solid. It's got hardware accelerated VLC,
a proper Ubuntu kernel, so it's not sharing the Raspbian kernel like it used to. And that
old 16.04 image was pretty neglected at this point. It didn't really work properly. Firefox
wouldn't open and stuff. It was just broken. So it is good to see that that project hasn't
been abandoned. And it's great to see that we've got a good competitor to Raspbian, which
now is very mature and a really solid OS for the Raspberry Pi. But competition is always
good and choice is always good. So I would say if you've got a Pi, definitely check it
out. We'll have a link to it in the show notes, linuxactionnews.com slash 99. And stick it
on your Raspberry Pi and see what you think.
Yeah. I'd love to hear people's take on it. Also, ffmpeg got hardware assisted video decoding
and encoding, which is huge on a device like this. That's a big deal. And something else
that Martin included that I think is genius is Steam Link is available for install now
on 1804 running Ubuntu Monte. That's great. I mean, it kind of makes me want to hook one
up to my TV with VLC having hardware decoding and ffmpeg having hardware decoding and Steam
Link. I don't know. That actually starts to turn into a pretty competitive media system
too.
The only issue, though, is that there's no acceleration in the browser yet. That's something
he's been working on. But yeah, unfortunately, it's not there. So browsing is a bit of a
painful experience. But if you're only looking to the media stuff with it, then it's pretty
solid.
Well, speaking of media stuff, the Ubuntu Studio flavor also was recognized again officially
as a flavor. And two of the developers that applied for their upload rights to Ubuntu
Studio's core packages received permission to do so. So business continues as usual.
Yeah, there was some doubt about that because the team had changed and it just looked like
it may lose its official status. But good to see they've managed to sort that out and
it's going to continue.
Well, speaking of business as usual, Red Hat continues to make money. It looks like they
are finally crossing that three billion dollar revenue line. In fact, if you do the math,
it is looking like it might be three point four billion dollars.
Yeah, suddenly the IBM acquisition makes a lot more sense, doesn't it? I mean, as I said
at the time, they didn't buy them for a laugh. They bought them because they're a money making
machine.
Yep, I completely agree. And who says that open source can't make any money? This is
really something. And Jim Whitehurst, the CEO, attributes enterprise organizations as
a continued source of growth as they convert their environments to hybrid cloud environments.
Jim's favorite buzz term. And he also said their subscription service is up. It continues
to grow. OpenStack and OpenShift continues to be an area of growth for them, even though
the buzz is kind of those things are on their way out. And they're investing more into Kubernetes,
as everyone says. But the final bit of information here, Joe, is that the deal with IBM is due
to close in the second half of this year. So that means any time, I guess, between June
and December 31st, it could be anywhere in there.
Yeah, that's nice and vague. I wonder if it'll be before Thanksgiving or not.
We should bet. I'll bet before. Do you want to take after or do you want to take before?
Because I'm going to bet before Thanksgiving.
I will bet after. I think it'll be right at the end of the year.
Now I feel bad. Now I want the other bet. All right. Let's see. What should we bet?
We got to bet something.
I know what we can do. Whoever loses has to go first with the Bitcoin predictions.
Okay. All right. Fair enough. Okay. All right. That seems fair. Okay. Well, let's talk about
the big news out of LVFS. We love talking about the Linux vendor firmware service, think
it's great for new users and potentially for servers in the future. But they have a big
announcement this week.
Yeah, they've joined the Linux Foundation. So yet another project that's done that.
The way that the folks involved in the project that are talking about it, it sort of sounds
like this is a way to vendor neutralize this fairly important service that could potentially
in the future expand into updating the server space and become even more critical that it's
vendor neutral. I think the concern was that by some it was seen as a Red Hat project.
And I wouldn't also discount the long term Dell involvement with since the very beginning
of this project. Even till now, Richard considers one of the Dell engineers has been involved
Mario, like a co-creator of the project. He's been so involved. And they have a close relationship
with the Linux Foundation.
Well, there were two things that stood out about this to me. One is that the firmware
files are distributed as cab files, which is just funny. But the other thing is that
they have now reached 500,000 downloads per month from the LVFS project, which is a lot
of machines.
Yeah, that's in the last month. That's in the last month. And the other way to say that
is 500,000 modern Linux desktops with machines that have updatable firmwares connected and
updated. That's a decent chunk of people. Because not everybody's running the absolute
latest stuff or using GNOME software very much. And not everybody has a machine that
can be updated by LVFS yet. So I'm impressed with that number, especially for the last
30 days. It seems like Richard was talking about this. It seems like whenever the project
gets some news coverage, the downloads go up. And there's been a lot of news coverage
around joining the Linux Foundation.
Yeah, I suppose people start checking their software center and go, actually, I can update
my various firmwares here.
Yep. It's still open source. Richard's still at the helm. It's still a Python Flask project.
You can still go get involved. It's just they're trying to make it vendor neutral now. And
my reading of that is it's a positioning for a long term play.
I think you need to have a service like this to gain wide industry adoption and to be taken
seriously. And so joining the Linux Foundation kind of gives it that extra credibility as
well.
I don't know, Joe. Needs more blockchain, in my opinion. Joking, of course. I love LVFS.
But speaking of in it for the long term, Handshake has been making a lot of donations to open
source projects. And it appears kind of recently, rather quietly, they made a pretty significant
contribution to Debian.
Yeah, $300,000, which is an awful lot of money given that Debian usually gets an order of
magnitude less than that donated to it every year.
Yeah. And the project says, and I think this is very true, I'm very happy to see this,
they say it's going to help them continue to replace old failing hardware. They have
a whole migration plan that the Debian system administrators have written up, which includes
reloading and renewing servers, replacing components, just making the workflow a little
easier for their developers, which we've talked about recently on some of our shows. That
all sounds like very, very positive long term improvements to the project.
And because they've been contributing to all these different projects over the last year
or so, you hear about Handshake a lot, but you might not remember what it is. Just a
quick recap. It's a decentralized permissionless naming protocol that is, guess what, compatible
with DNS. And the idea is taking away root DNS servers that are centrally controlled
and moving it to a peer to peer system that is, as you also guessed, powered by blockchain.
However, it does seem to be a very cool project. And I do like the idea of decentralized root
DNS servers that is still completely compatible with the DNS protocol. That seems pretty clever
to me.
That wasn't clear to me whether these donations to the various free software projects had
been in actual cash, or whether it just been in cryptocurrencies. But doing a little bit
of digging, it seems that it is cash, they will be getting some cryptocurrency as well.
But this 300,000 is actual cash, by the looks of things.
Oh, huh. Yeah, we had tried to get that answered in the past by various projects that have
been involved with contributions. And they were a little reluctant to answer that before.
So it's a combo thing.
By the looks of things, I mean, it's not completely clear. But from digging around and watching
various YouTube videos and reading various articles, that's the conclusion I've come
to. But it would be good to get some clarification from the various projects.
That's true. They say USD, but they could just be saying in value of. Handshake writes
that they've gifted nearly $10.2 million to various floss projects. And they say it's
10.2 million in USD. They're not saying crypto. Although I think famously a lot of their initial
funding did come from various crypto sources. So I think that's where some of the speculation
comes from.
Yeah. It's funny that this money is essentially investment that they needed to enable them
to have a valuation that was true, but they didn't actually need that investment. So they
decided to re-gift it at $10 million. It's a lot of money. And I suppose who's to complain?
All these free software projects are benefiting from it. But it just seems all a bit strange,
doesn't it?
Mm-hmm. But they really picked some good projects. You can search the tags on our site. Just
search the site for Handshake. And there's lots of great projects they've been contributing
to now. So they keep picking good ones. And Debian absolutely could put that money to
good use. And that's nothing to sneeze at, 300,000 US greenbacks. So at this point, I
don't know if a blockchain-based DNS, a decentralized thing is ever going to take off, but hats
off to Handshake for their awesome contributions to the community.
Yeah, definitely. Well, before we get out of here, a quick mention for the UK Open Source
Awards 2019. And this is happening on the 12th of June in Edinburgh. And it's not just
the awards, it's kind of an afternoon into evening event where there'll be some speakers
and it's kind of a conference as well.
Right. And you can still nominate, they say categories are five and it's companies or
individuals which in the last year have shown exceptional innovation in free and open source
software. And they have different categories for like public, company, individual, etc.
Link as always in the show notes or in your podcast player of choice.
I'd like to go up there for this, but I'm not sure about scheduling yet. So fingers
crossed on that one.
Hmm. It probably depends if they're going to have an open bar or not.
Very good point.
Well, we're back every single week. Go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all
the various ways to get new episodes.
And go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch.
And if you're a Ruby on Rails developer, Linux Academy is hiring right now. Go to linuxacademy.com
slash careers. They'd like to talk to you.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I'm at Chris LAS.
I'm at Joe Rissington.
Thank you for joining us. And we will see you next week.
See you later.