Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open source world.
This is episode 91 recorded on February 3rd, 2019.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe.
It's good to be connected with you.
And it is a great week to be a Firefox user.
Yeah, Firefox 65 has come out.
And it is all about privacy.
Privacy really has turned into a bit of a buzzword, hasn't it, especially recently after
the proposed changes by Google and Chromium.
It seems like privacy for the web browser is the battlefield for 2019.
And Firefox isn't going to be left out of that fight, Joe.
Yeah, they've got a new set of redesigned controls to give you real granularity about
how you protect yourself when you're browsing.
This is a really sensible approach.
So the default is standard for anyone who wants to just set it and forget it.
It's the default right now, you're good to go.
And it really is the perfect setting for those of you who expect ultimate privacy when you
open up their private browsing mode.
But for the rest of us that want a little more, quote unquote, strict control.
That's for people who want a bit more protection and don't mind if a couple of sites here and
there break.
This setting blocks all known trackers by Firefox, regardless of the privacy mode or
not.
But then if you like to kind of get down to the weeds, they also have now a custom mode.
That's three different modes, Joe, for privacy.
Well, it's always been the browser for the power user with the about config options and
everything.
And now with the privacy settings, you've got real control as a power user if you want
it or if you want to just go for the defaults, then that's pretty much fine for most people.
So it kind of serves both types of users.
Yeah, it's really not bad, is it?
It's nice to see the three different options and to see them expand out this built in set
of options.
But it's pretty generic and basic and not enough.
It's really one of those feature sets.
It's good to see, but it's not enough to move the needle.
That said, some of the things that they are working on for future versions of Firefox,
I think that kind of stuff could move the needle.
Well, in the next version, 66, it looks like they're going to implement a feature that
warns users about man in the middle attacks.
So again, it's all about privacy and security.
Right.
This is a very, very useful feature, especially for those of you on Windows.
Starting with version 66, Firefox will let you know if, say, a rando antivirus product
or malware or maybe even your ISP is intercepting your HTTP and HTTPS traffic.
They're building in a new style of air page into Firefox when it detects this kind of
shenanigans.
And the way this feature works is to show that visual, hey, you user, your traffic is
being intercepted.
You need to look into the software on your computer or ask questions with your ISP.
That is the kind of feature set that I don't really see Google all that compelled to introduce.
Well, that's hopefully what's going to save Firefox and Mozilla here, because we all know
that Chrome has just been absolutely eating up all the market share and Firefox is way,
way down now, almost insignificant in terms of percentage.
But hopefully with features like this, they might be able to claw some of that market
share back and become more relevant as people wake up to the reality that their data is
actually worth something and they should be a bit more careful about who they give it
to.
With that said, I can't help but take a bit of a downer note on this story, because when
I look at what Firefox is attempting to do, I'll give you an example.
They've limited, the limit is remarkable, it's like four or five extensions.
When you consider all of the extensions available to Firefox, Mozilla has picked four or five
that they are occasionally recommending to a subset of users.
An example would be if you go to Facebook, Mozilla will recommend an extension to you
called the Facebook container.
This is one of the best things that has come out of Mozilla in the last five years.
It completely isolates everything about Facebook to an isolated Firefox container.
It can't track you across websites, it's contained to this specific environment.
And yet, users are reacting very negatively.
In fact, bug 1523701 has been filed in the last three days, essentially saying, you're
advertising to me, you're giving me advertisements and I think at the end of the day, what it
represents is Mozilla has lost the trust of their users.
And if they can't keep their existing user base happy, then how can they possibly hope
to grow?
That's a bit of a negative take on it, but I'm inclined to agree, unfortunately.
But I don't know, maybe people who are the hardcore Firefox users at this point actually
care about open source and software freedom and everything.
And they're the ones who are going to go on Reddit, ironically, and complain about this
stuff.
And maybe the people who read the mainstream headlines about Google doing evil things and
Facebook doing evil things might then do a little bit of digging and discover Firefox
and remember, oh, yeah, I used to use that before I switched to Chrome.
And maybe, oh, right, this recommendation, that looks cool.
So maybe the existing users might be a bit alienated, but the users that they will attract
might find this good, I don't know.
Maybe I'm being naive.
Yeah, that's very optimistic for you, Joe, I got to say.
Well, it's all good in the hood if you are an HP user, because I am extremely thrilled
this week to say that LVFS is welcoming HP to the fold.
Yeah, this is excellent news that I did somewhat see coming, but not this quickly.
Because we're seeing other major OEM sign ups with Linux vendor firmware service.
But now HP is like the other behemoth.
So almost all laptops now, potentially, are going to be updatable via the GUI when it
comes to firmware.
And that's got to be a good thing.
So you did see this coming, huh?
I got to be honest, I didn't.
I mean, after System76 said, nah, no, not for us, I wasn't sure what direction this
would go.
But since then, we saw a doubling down from Dell.
We saw AMI get in the game.
We've seen HP and even Lenovo get in the game.
To me, it's like every time one of these new vendors comes along, it's a total unique delight.
I am so thrilled, because I guess I just don't expect it.
Because when I think of Linux computers, I don't think of HP.
But they're looking at the Z2, Z6, Z8, Z440 line.
That's the kind of rigs they're targeting, maybe even the Z840 and more.
OK.
All right.
It's starting to click with me.
But I guess I just didn't see HP next.
If you were going to ask me to make a prediction, say, at the beginning of the year, I don't
know if HP would have been on that list.
Well, he likes to drop hints, usually, about the various companies that he's in negotiations
with and working with.
And it obviously takes quite a while to make these things happen.
And just the speculation of being that it would be HP.
So I was pleasantly surprised to see it.
It'd be good if they could support more models, but I suppose you have to start somewhere.
Reading his blog, though, for a while now, you get a real sense of pride in his work,
which is completely understandable.
And I hope he does feel a sense of pride because he's doing a huge service for Linux users.
But in that sense of pride, he kind of can't help but give a little indication of what's
coming next.
And in the blog post, it's not even vague.
It's pretty much in your face.
He says, even seemingly unlikely companies like Microsoft are still interested in shipping
firmware on LVFS in the future.
Does that mean we're about to get firmware updates for Surface Books on Linux?
What does that mean, Joe?
Well, surely we'd have to get actual, proper Linux support first before we got any firmware
updates.
When I read that, I'm thinking to myself, are we talking about Azure Sphere OS?
Yeah, you never know.
But something that people have actually been getting their hands on over the weekend at
Fosdom is new hardware from Pine64, including a tablet and an upgraded PineBook Pro.
Right.
But the real story here is the freaking prices.
I mean, if you want all your gadgets running pure Linux, then Pine64 has you covered.
But if you don't have a lot of money to spend, well, then Pine64 has you covered.
And the news coming out of Fosdom this year is really about the Pine Tab, a 10-inch tablet
with either Linux or BSD.
Inside the Pine Tab, you'll find a 64-bit system-on-a-chip ARM processor.
It's a Cortex A53 quad-core processor, a Mali 400 GPU, two gigabytes of DDR3 RAM, 16 gigabytes
of eMMC storage built in, and two megapixel front camera and a five megapixel rear shooter.
All of that is behind a 10-inch LCD touchscreen, which is running about 720p for 80 bucks.
Yeah, but you do have to take that price with a bit of a pinch of salt.
$79 might end up being more like $150 by the time you've paid for shipping and import duty
and stuff.
But it's still fairly cheap.
But then it's a fairly low-res screen and things, so it's probably a fair price for
it.
And it is worth keeping in mind that the demo model that they've got at Fosdom is running
Android at the moment.
But they have said that it is fairly similar specs-wise to the original PineBook.
And there's plenty of distros and ROMs available for that.
So in theory, they should work with minimal tweaking.
So the software support should be there pretty much from day one, and I'm very tempted to
get this.
Yeah, but what do you think about that $20 keyboard?
I think that looks pretty good, and the people I've spoken to at Fosdom say it's pretty
solid as well.
Really?
Oh, okay.
See, I was thinking $20 magnetic keyboard, there's no way they can deliver that.
That out of all of this was the thing I was the most skeptical about.
Well, yeah, I mean, for the price, obviously, it's not going to be the quality of a Surface
or whatever.
This is a budget device, and you have to go into it with that in mind.
But based on my PineBook, that for a budget device feels relatively high-end.
It's plastic and everything, but it's solid plastic and doesn't creak and bend and everything.
So I give them the benefit of the doubt on that.
But this PineBook Pro, now they're making some pretty hefty claims about that.
Yeah, the PineBook Pro is what I am actually excited about.
And it's just anecdotally what I've heard the most from the audience from this week.
I mean, the idea is a 14-inch 1080p IPS display with about 128GB of eMMC storage, 4GB of system
RAM, and maybe the option of adding your own MV&E SSD drive.
Plus, you get all the usual ports like USB-A, USB-C, and inside that sucker, a dual-core
ARM processor, maybe a quad-core, depending on the way the specs work out, and the whole
thing comes together for $200, that puts it below a Chromebook, Joe.
Yeah, and it is the same processor that's used in a fair few Chromebooks as well.
So in theory, you should get decent performance from it.
Now, what piqued my interest towards the end of this part of their announcement was where
they said that the PineBooks that people already have might well be upgradable to this.
Because it's very hackable, the PineBook that I've got.
You can open it up with like 10 screws or whatever, and they're just standard screws.
And you can see all the boards right there, and it wouldn't be difficult to change the
insides of this thing.
And you've got the screen, the keyboard, touchpad, battery, and all the ports.
And so in theory, you could put in the more powerful hardware and have an actual usable
laptop, because at the moment, it's not a daily driver, and they make no bones about
that.
But they're saying that this PineBook Pro would be daily driver-worthy.
In the Chromebook category, you're not going to be compiling kernels on it in 10 minutes.
It's a fairly lightweight browsing machine, but the claim is that it would be good enough
to do that.
And so I had been tempted to sell my PineBook and maybe get the tablet, but now I'm thinking
maybe hang on, and hopefully it'll be not that expensive to buy just the board to put
inside my PineBook, and I could be off to the races.
No kidding, right?
Like how cool would it be if the part of the Pine brand was upgradability?
I mean, it seems like such an obvious thing, but you can't name a single brand that's well
recognized that is known for the upgradability of its components and its laptops.
That just doesn't exist.
Yeah, well, these days you're lucky to get RAM slots rather than soldered RAM.
Or disk, yeah.
And so if you could change the entire system on a chip and the whole basically motherboard
of it very easily and relatively cheaply...
Swap it out, just the whole board.
I think that'd be pretty great.
And to say nothing about the other rumors coming out of FOSDEM, the one that I'm probably
the most looking forward to is a $20 open source IP camera.
I would be all about that.
And then there's the one that I'm the most skeptical about, which is the $150 Linux smartphone
with an unspecified screen size.
Well, they do actually have working dev kits of that phone, which is more than you can
say of Purism at this stage.
Oh, shots fired.
Shots fired indeed.
But, you know, and they're being very modest about it.
They're not making this big song and dance about the phone.
They're kind of saying that we're working on it and, you know, here's a prototype and,
you know, it's not this big grand product.
And that's kind of never been their style as it's always been.
We're aimed at hackers and tinkerers.
And you know, this is the phone that we're working on and it's going to be ready when
it's ready rather than making firm promises and then not keeping them.
It seems like a genuine, clear understanding of the actual marketplace.
And then you combine that with the same thing that I feel like other projects we've talked
about in the same space, sort of primarily Plasma Mobile, where they come at it with
a humbleness.
This is where we're at today.
You know, this is what we can offer today and we think it's something that is unique
to hackers and we're trying to offer it at a competitive price point.
We're not saying it's going to replace the iPhone or compete with the Pixel.
But if you are in this particular market and you even know what these things mean, we have
a product for you.
And God bless them, Joe.
Yeah, and they have the attitude of come and help us.
This is an open source project, come and help us hack on it.
Yeah.
And that is the right approach, because then it's not, oh, we're going to take over the
world.
We're going to fundamentally change the consumer landscape and alter cloud computing all in
one swoop.
It's, hey, we have something we think is appealing and we're going to iterate on it for years.
And eventually we're going to get to something that we think is super competitive.
In the meantime, help us make it better.
Yeah.
In the meantime, hackers are going to use it and have fun doing so.
But I suppose the elephant in the room whenever we're talking about any of these arm based
systems is the Raspberry Pi Foundation.
And you and I have some predictions in the works, in play, as you might say, that could
be affected by this next news story.
But we're here to report the news as it is.
It appears we will not see a Raspberry Pi 4 at least in 2019.
Yeah, this is very disappointing to me because I predicted this with great confidence that
we'd see it this year, but apparently not.
In an interview with Tom's Hardware, Evan Upton has said that, no, it's not happening
this year.
It will be called the Raspberry Pi 4.
It will be $35 and it will be more powerful and have more RAM.
So it's most of what we thought, but it's just not going to be this year, which is going
to disappoint quite a lot of people, I think.
Well, not just other people.
I mean, just you and me.
Like I was hoping that we would have a super cheap Raspberry Pi, a $35 Raspberry Pi, and
then like a $55 Raspberry Pi or so, because the reality is, Joe, is $35 today isn't necessarily
buying you what $35 bought you when the Raspberry Pi launched.
And I think there's room in there for a more feature, maybe more memory, more processor,
but more feature rich Raspberry Pi.
I've made this argument before and reading this over at Tom's Hardware, I can see that
Evan is totally in disagreement with me.
Well, he does seem to be very much sticking to that $35 price and has done from the very
beginning.
But if you consider with inflation, that $35 doesn't actually go as far as it once did.
It's roughly equivalent to about $38 in today's money.
So if they're only selling it for $35 now, then it makes it very tricky for them to squeeze
more and more performance out of a new model.
I really recommend that people read this article because it made something really click for
me.
And you just touched on it, Joe.
They're really sticking to this $35 price.
Now, who knows, maybe they'll have future products that are outside the core Raspberry
Pi product line that are of a completely different price like they did with the Xero.
But reading this article, it seems like he's pretty committed to that $35 price point.
And I think that's important for the market because at their scale, they are actually
applying downward pressure on the prices for the overall component ecosystem.
But it also, to me, resonates with something that the audience has been giving us as solid
feedback anytime we talk about the Raspberry Pi.
And that is simply summed up as there are really good competitive alternatives.
And it seems to me that those competitive alternatives just got even more competitive
with this.
So both the audience is right.
But at the same time, the Raspberry Pi is doing us an overall good by putting downward
pressure on the prices of the entire market.
Well, that's true, but we talked about Pine64 and it feels like if the Raspberry Pi Foundation
don't put out a new board this year, then Pine64 might well start eating their lunch.
I mean, there's a lot of other boards out there.
Most of them are like orange pie, banana pie, that sort of thing.
For my money, anything that has Pi in the name is a cheap rip off and is just to be
avoided.
Now, that's maybe the wrong attitude to have, but it just feels like just cheap and nasty
to me to put a pie in the name.
Whereas Pine64, what makes them sort of sets them apart is that they don't need to try
and cash in.
They just do what they're doing.
And that makes me take them more seriously.
I totally agree.
And on top of that, you also have to figure RISC-V is now a real player in the marketplace
and there are RISC-V boards being built.
And that is also competition for the Raspberry Pi.
That is true.
Yeah.
I mean, the photo of a RISC-V board running plasma mobile at FOSDEM, I mean, it's nowhere
near the size of a Raspberry Pi and it's going to be significantly more expensive at this
stage.
But that is coming and we saw Raspberry Pi join the RISC-V foundation.
So maybe we'll see a RISC-V Pi at some stage.
It seems very unlikely anytime soon.
But maybe in this hacker board space, the tide is turning and that crown is starting
to slip slightly from Raspberry Pi.
Raspberry Pi is a brand that is a that's a known quantity and it works in like the education
space and business and there is just it's so well recognized that they have carved out
a market for themselves now and it is really their game to lose.
But that's just an aside.
I want to take a moment and talk about some throwaway comments that Eben makes about USB-C
and maybe seeing future Raspberry Pi devices with USB-C.
And this is a quote.
He says, there's some awkward decisions in the pin choices on the USB-C connector in
a kind of fairly rugged environment that people use the Pi in.
If the connector gets twisted or if dust gets in it, you can end up exposing the high speed
differential pairs on that connector to rather high voltages.
Overall, it sounded like he wasn't very happy with USB-C and was fairly happy with the ports
they have on the Raspberry Pi devices right now.
Yeah, it seems like he's voting for micro USB still.
And he is an engineer with a lot of experience in this area, so you kind of have to trust
him on that.
He's obviously looked at it and we all have hailed USB-C as the next big thing and the
standard, but he's made me question that now he's doubted my faith in it.
Same with me.
I have been having doubts about USB-C for months now.
Behind the scenes, we've had just issues amongst the staff with different laptops that have
come in the house that have different features on the USB-C ports, and you really have no
idea of knowing what those ports can do unless you are intimately familiar with the entire
spec of the laptop.
And we've just been talking as a group, like, how is this going to work for average consumers?
Well, average consumers are going to buy that Meizu Zero phone that's got no ports at all.
So I don't think they'll be worried.
There you go.
Problem solved.
Meanwhile, back here on Earth, those of us who love a great media center fully under
our control and of course is open source are celebrating the release of Kodi 18.
I tried this out and it doesn't look much different from 17.
It's nowhere near the huge leap in skin that we had from 16 to 17, but there's quite a
lot under the hood that's changed.
You could probably easily be forgiven for missing the changes, to be honest, especially
if you're like me, you're on the Nvidia Shield, which I think is one of the best TV devices
ever.
And you have Kodi installed on it, which is one of the best media centers ever.
This update kind of came along and it was just more good stuff where the last one, like
you said, was like this huge change in the way it looked and everything.
But what you get under the hood is pretty noteworthy.
In fact, what they took out is kind of noteworthy.
Nearly half a million lines of code were removed and nearly half a million new lines of code
were added.
That's arbitrary to us.
Half of that stuff could be Hello World for all we know, but it's just kind of a big number.
And it represents 10,000 commits to the project, which is 36 different individual open source
contributors that are writing code to the main upstream Kodi project now.
And it also represents just a ton of beer and wine and retro gaming for us Kodi users.
This is something that I tried to try out, if that makes any sense, and didn't get very
far.
I didn't spend a huge amount of time on it.
I didn't do much reading.
I just tried to go in as the kind of new user.
And it wasn't immediately obvious to me how to get the emulators working and get my ROMs
loaded up and start playing Sonic.
So I think this is more aimed at people who get down and dirty with hacking it with extensions
and everything.
No, actually all that checks out, Joe.
I got to say what's great about Kodi and also kind of not great about Kodi is all add ons
are essentially created equal.
The Jupiter broadcasting add on that Rob Loach wrote for us like four or five years ago is
like on par with some of this new stuff that is headline features.
And that's cool and feels great from an independent content creator standpoint, but isn't really
serving the project the best it could.
That would be one criticism I might have.
But once you kind of live and learn Kodi, you kind of can figure things out.
But even that said, it took the audience writing into me personally saying, hey, Chris, by
the way, you can use Plex inside of Kodi, do XYZ and it all works.
It took like it took about 20 of them writing me before it clicked how to actually set all
of that up.
Well, also, they've added DRM to this release, and it's a similar situation is not straightforward
to get Netflix and Amazon working in it.
It's not out of the box support.
It requires you to install add ons and do a bit of hacking.
But that's kind of the beauty of it.
It can either be this fairly simple interface that, to be fair, actually adding media to
it can be a little bit confusing for new users I've found that I've set up for.
But once you've got all that set up, it's really straightforward.
Or if you want to get really hacky with it, you can.
And you can do all sorts of stuff, including getting Netflix and Amazon working and your
ROMs on emulators and everything.
And first and foremost, Kodi is the player that gives me the least screen tearing of
any video player on Linux.
So that's why I use it.
Everybody's got their Kodi reason, Joe.
Yeah, I say the least screen tearing.
It's not perfect.
It's Linux.
You know, got to get that X jab in there whenever you can.
Before we go all down the Linux hate hole here for a second, can I just say that Kodi
is a standout Android TV application and version 18 adds a couple of nice features that make
it feel like a full fledged Android TV application.
I don't actually use this, but if you are a fan of Google Assistant on say like the
Nvidia Shield TV, Kodi now has full feature support for voice search and voice typing
using the remote and all of that.
It's I mean, that's like a first class app kind of thing on that ecosystem.
It's it's a big deal for a lot of people.
It doesn't resonate with me, but it checks a box with the quote unquote market.
Well, hopefully they can ride this tide of positive publicity and get to a point where
they're releasing early and often with new features and kind of put the negative publicity
behind them.
I agree.
I hope I really hope so, because Kodi is one of these open source projects that makes a
daily positive impact on my life.
As we record this episode right now, I am in route from Texas to Washington and many,
many times in route, I don't have Internet connectivity and I use Kodi to stream media
around my local land.
And it is after everything I have tried over the years, the absolute best application for
the job.
It would negatively impact my life if it went away and it positively impacts my life when
they have a new release, just like so many other great open source projects.
So much free software now positively impacts my life because I use it on a daily basis
and it probably impacts you out there to go to Linux action news dot com slash subscribe
for all the ways to get new episodes.
So whenever something changes in the world of free software, open source, you find out
about it right here on this humble show and you can go to Linux action news dot com slash
contact for ways to get in touch with us.
Also just a quickie for those of you that are listening right around the publication
date, February 5th, 2019, right after this week's episode of Linux Unplugged, we're holding
an online study group for YAML, the basics of YAML.
More details at meet up dot com slash Jupiter Broadcasting will be back next Monday with
our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I'm at Chris LAS.
I'm at Joel Ressington.
Thank you for joining us and we will see you next week.
Until then, I'm Chris LAS and I'll see you later.