Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News. Episode 262, recorded on October 12, 2022. I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes. Let's do the news.
We start this week with the release of Plasma 5.26, which has benefited from a significant
focus on stability.
Yeah, stability, and there is also a lot new in this release, add-ons or plasmoids, widgets,
whatever you call them. They got a lot of work in this release, from some totally new
ones to just improving long-standing ones, like the calendar and the clock. And something
that jumped out at me that I think a lot of you are going to like, because I know it's
one of your favorites, Kate and K-Write have now been spruced up with a fancy new welcome
window that launches if you start the application without any files open.
Well, we always like to see some bug fixing in these releases, and 5.26 is no slouch in
that category. System settings no longer sometimes crashes when you navigate away from the Thunderbolt
page. In the Plasma X11 session in particular, if Kwin happens to crash and gets auto-restarted
or you manually restart it, it no longer loses its mappings of windows to activities, which
is a big pain to fix.
And the team also fixed an issue that could occasionally cause apps like VLC and Firefox
to stop refreshing after being used for a little while, plus a whole lot more that we'll
have linked in the show notes.
And it might surprise some of you, but there are folks out there that actually have plasma
hooked up to their TV. It can be pretty handy as a media home and a server all-in-one kind
of setup. And they've put some serious work in this release for their big screen experience
with two new apps landing, Aurora, which is a web browser designed for the big screen,
and Plank, an easy to use media player, you guessed it, for the big screen.
I've upgraded my Neon Station that I'm sitting at right now to do the show, and just like
so many of these later 5 series plasma releases, the upgrade went super smooth. I kept all
of my settings. It was really no big deal at all. In fact, if I hadn't intentionally
gone to do the update and seen all the packages upgrade, I might not even know I was on the
new version. When you go looking for things, you can find it, but the Neon betas have just
been really smooth for me recently. And I have a sense that when Plasma 526 lands in
distributions out there in the Linux world, people are really going to like this release.
Well, you better keep that apt update handy over there, Chris, or really PKCon, I suppose.
Either way, work is beginning right now on Plasma 527, which the project says will be
the final feature release in the Plasma 5 series.
Less than just two weeks after Google announced plans to shut down Stadia, its cloud gaming
platform, Google has announced plans for Chromebooks built for cloud gaming platforms.
Well, for as much sense as that makes, Google says the Acer Chromebook 516GE, the Asus Chromebook
Vive CX55 Flip, and Lenovo's IdeaPad gaming Chromebook all have refresh rates of at least
120Hz, displays with up to 1600p resolution, and WiFi 6.
These units, what we used to call laptops, are now called Chromebooks, and they don't
really have any dedicated graphics cards in them per se, and they don't really seem to
be related to the recent efforts we reported on to get Steam working locally on Chromebooks.
Instead, these units are equipped with modern Intel GPUs, so you could play some light gaming,
but clearly the focus is on cloud gaming.
They even emphasize WiFi 6 and quad phonic speakers for cloud gaming.
It's just someone else's cloud gaming.
But some of these might make a great little Linux machine.
That Lenovo IdeaPad in particular, well it starts under 600 bucks.
It has a 16 inch 120Hz display, a 12th gen Intel CPU, 512GB of SSD backed storage, 11
hours of battery life, at least under Chrome OS, and it's only 4 pounds.
So if the community could find a quick way to wipe off Chrome OS and load a nice shiny
Linux distribution, it might just be a cheap way to snap up a pretty nice rig.
Well speaking of mostly acceptable gaming performance, the Intel Arc A770 and the A750
have gone on actual official sale in various global markets this week, with price points
starting around $289 US greenbacks.
Gnir and Asrock have also announced their takes on the Arc graphics cards, though sadly
they're entirely out of stock as we record.
Linux users in particular are pretty excited about this release, because the driver for
this discrete GPU is built off Intel's existing open source integrated graphics driver stack.
And as we've been reporting over the recent years, well there's been a lot of refactoring
there to introduce the concept of discrete video memory and other features that you really
only have to think about with a discrete GPU.
Yeah, and Intel has been slowly but steadily building out the support at Linux for this,
and I love seeing that.
A free software driver stack for the video is just massive for Linux, but they're competing
on price here too.
The lower end RTX 4070 is still a couple hundred dollars more than the starting Intel Arc GPU.
And I can already hear you guys saying, yeah, they're not really comparable.
The RTX is still going to be a better gaming card and that kind of stuff.
And I think you're probably right, and it's going to be a little bit probably till they're
totally equivalent in that arena.
But when it comes to just workstation day-to-day desktop use and experience, I bet they are
a little bit more equivalent, and the benchmarks are starting to show that out.
Of course, our buddy Michael Larable over at Ferronix has been watching this story closely.
But I, as a longtime Linux user, I find this really compelling to have another open source
driver stack option for a Linux GPU.
This is something we'll keep an eye on and report back any interesting details that develop.
This week, Canonical launched a free tier of their Ubuntu Pro commercial offering.
Ubuntu Pro is a subscription security maintenance and compliance program initially designed
for enterprise customers who want long-term stability for their infrastructure and applications.
Ubuntu Pro is somewhat ideal for that use case since the more you pay, seemingly the
less you need to upgrade.
Now, however, Canonical decided to expand Ubuntu Pro for personal and small-scale commercial
use with a free tier for up to five machines.
And as Mark Shuttleworth points out, this program doesn't impose the restrictions on
types of users that other enterprise distribution providers do.
All of these programs cover the full distribution for up to 10 years with the option to extend
beyond that for industrial use cases.
And I'm very pleased to say that we are making all of that available free of charge to anybody
with a personal subscription.
It's not a student edition, it's not a developer-only edition, it is full commercial use for you
and any business you own on up to five machines.
You guys know me, it was kind of like one of the top reasons.
I first discovered Linode at a Linux fest and I could tell they were one of the few
vendors actually in it because they were geeking out about Linux.
Some of the other vendors were not taking it very seriously and you know, I was just
looking at their calendar, chatting with my buds over at Linode and they've got a lot
coming up in the fall.
They're going to be at a bunch of different events.
I'll put a link in the show notes so that way if you're going to be at one of these,
you can say hi, like Hashicomf in Los Angeles coming up right now.
Actually just finished, so scratch that one.
Sastok though, that's coming up, KubeCon, CompTIA, EMA, that's coming up at the end
of the month.
Web Summit next month, IT Nation Connect also coming up.
The Caribbean Developers Conference, how do I get it on that one?
I want to go to the Caribbean, that sounds great.
I mean, they're all over the place, they're always trying to engage and interact with
the community.
That's why they supported our road trip events because they get that Linux, it's made by
It's worth investing in that layer and then you build out a really great business on top
of that technology platform that the community builds for you.
They've always gotten that concept and so that's why they've invested in these areas
and areas like support and making the UI really work and of course, performance, so fast.
They've got 11 data centers to choose from.
They're adding a dozen, over a dozen next year as well.
They are their own ISP on top of all of that and they really have no reason to not work
with any kind of configuration management tool that you want, Chef, Puppet, Ansible,
whatever it is, the Terraforms, yeah, you got that.
They have no reason not to.
They want to be your alternative cloud if that's what you need.
They want to be your primary cloud if that's what you need.
They want to just run whatever simple application you might need.
They try to do all of it and they try to do it better than anybody else and I think they
nail it.
So that's truly what keeps me as a customer and why I keep building over there.
It's nice to know that support's available if you ever need it.
So if you go get that $100 at linode.com slash LAN, you can really try this stuff.
You can see the actual pricing and really get a sense of how it works and I think once
you start to do that, you'll start to see the competitive advantages for yourself.
So go build something, go learn something, go try something while you support the show.
Just go to linode.com slash LAN, get that $100 for the best place on the internet to
run your applications.
I mean the best place to host your services, your applications, and to get a full Linux
box, linode.com slash LAN.
And a big thank you to my friends over at Kalyde, Kalyde.com slash LAN.
Kalyde is an endpoint security solution that uses the most powerful untapped resource in
IT, the end users.
When you're trying to achieve security, maybe it's something you've set for yourself as
a goal, maybe it's a third party audit, maybe you have a new boss in town.
There's been so many ways that companies, businesses, organizations, schools, what have
you have tried this.
I've seen a lot of it over the years.
Conventional wisdom was just to treat every device like it's Fort Knox.
You just go all in on like just this really old school draconian device management, MDMs
that force disruptive agents onto employees' devices, slow down performance, and they often
treat privacy as an afterthought.
That was just an awful way of doing things because it makes a bad experience for the
end user which kind of pits them against IT and does not create the best atmosphere, sort
of makes them enemies.
And also creates its own security problems.
It often also results in sort of a shadow IT structure just so the employees can quote
do their jobs.
Kalyde does things differently.
Instead of forcing changes on users, Kalyde sends them security recommendations via Slack.
Kalyde will automatically notify your team when their devices are insecure and it'll
give them step-by-step instructions on how to solve the problem.
And by reaching out to employees just with a friendly Slack DM and educating them about
company policies, Kalyde can help you build a culture for which everyone is contributing
to security because, well, everyone understands how and why to do it.
For IT admins, Kalyde provides a single dashboard that lets you monitor the security of your
entire fleet.
It supports Mac, Windows, and of course, Linux desktops.
So you can see at a glance which employees have their disks encrypted, their OS up to
date, and a password manager installed.
Making it easy to prove compliance to your auditors, customers, and leadership.
So that's Kalyde, user-centered cross-platform endpoint security for teams that Slack.
You can meet your compliance goals by putting users first.
Just visit Kalyde.com slash LAN to find out how.
When you go there and you sign up for a free trial, they'll hook you up with a goody bag,
a real goody bag with a free t-shirt inside.
I do love me a free t-shirt.
That's just for activating a free trial and checking it out.
So it's K-O-L-I-D-E dot com slash LAN, Kalyde dot com slash LAN.
We wanted to wrap things up this week with a little heads up.
Mulvad VPN has discovered that Android leaks traffic every time the device connects to
a Wi-Fi network.
Imagine if the block connections without VPN or always-on VPN features are enabled.
The data that makes it outside your VPN tunnels includes source IP addresses, DNS lookups,
HTTPS traffic, and likely also some NTP traffic.
Yeah, Android does things like check for a captive portal every time you connect to a
new Wi-Fi AP.
It tries to determine if the user needs help to get fully connected.
This is by design, Android was built this way.
It is a choice by Google just to make things easier for users.
But I think anyone really familiar with Network Unity knows this, you're going to inevitably
reveal details about yourself and your machine if you go out and probe the state of the network
and try to find the edge devices.
And to make this worse, I think most developers and users probably had the wrong idea about
what block connections without VPN exactly meant here, especially compounded by poor
Android documentation that inaccurately describes the feature.
Yeah, that's where you could almost fry some conspiracy bacon with this story.
The wording around the feature in the Android OS sort of implies that everything gets blocked
if a VPN is turned on, it only goes through that tunnel.
And I've experienced this setting by accident when I first installed TailScale.
And I had it set to tunnel everything through VPN, and that's not how TailScale works.
And so nothing worked, at least that I knew of, I didn't realize it was leaking information
at the time.
But then we're like, you could see someone getting conspiratorial here is you go read
the documentation for Android developers.
And they also really make it sound like nothing gets out.
And maybe the people writing the documentation just didn't understand the nuances of what
was happening there.
Maybe it's a right hand not talking to the left hand kind of thing.
I mean, as an example, you can take Graphene OS, there's an option in there where the user
can toggle that check.
If they toggle it, so the check doesn't happen.
The researchers did not observe Graphene OS leaking this information that simple setting
that Graphene OS exposes that gives the user control seems to fix this issue.
Mulvad just simply discovered this because they were conducting their own audit of their
own apps, trying to figure out why it seemed like their app was leaking information when
it was on the network.
And it turned out it wasn't an issue with the Mulvad VPN at all.
It was an issue with Android.
Now of course, the core privacy concern here is that that connection check traffic, well,
it can be observed and analyzed both by the party controlling the connectivity check server,
but also anyone else on the network path between.
And even if the content of the message itself doesn't reveal anything more than some Android
devices connecting to this network, the metadata, which includes the source IP address, well,
that can be used to derive further information, especially if you combine that with other
data such as Wi-Fi access point locations.
Unfortunately, it seems iOS users, well, they're in the same boat, if not a boat that's a little
bit more leaky.
A security researcher back in August found a significant flaw in iOS VPN apps and a second
researcher has now demonstrated another major issue.
Details in the show notes for that one.
Yeah, a bit more leaky indeed, some of that second research shows that a lot of Apple's
core apps, they just bypass your VPN if things aren't working right, cause they want to talk
to the home server.
They don't care.
So you're leaking even more metadata in those circumstances.
That's definitely worth reading.
You know, the situation here is sort of unfixable by the VPN vendors.
There's nothing Mulvad can do to solve this problem.
It's a limitation of how these OSs are built, at least the stock OSs, which is what most
users are going to use.
Mulvad has submitted their suggestions to revise the documentation around the block
connections feature, just to make it more clear what data is still being sent outside
the VPN at least.
Yeah, they have a pretty nice write up, which we'll have linked in the docs.
And in that they end on a pretty simple recommendation, quote, as a closing note, we would like to
recommend Google adopt the ability to disable connectivity checks like on Graphene OS into
stock Android.
Yeah.
From their fingers to Google's ears, I guess it just seems like a relatively easy solution.
If they wanted to, they could even just probably get the code from Graphene OS.
And if they wanted to impress us with their development prowess, they could create it
from scratch.
I'd be happy with either one.
Just add a user controlled option to let us check for captive portals or not.
Just let us have control over that setting.
I have to say, if you have a pixel, Graphene OS has just really exceeded all my expectations.
I have kind of ended up using it in a somewhat compromised way because I do have the play
API and the play store on there, but Graphene OS allows you to use them in a sandbox way.
It's extremely clever and very effective.
Now the mainstream commercial operating systems, they're always likely to err on the side of
convenience over privacy.
You kind of have to pick one.
And I think if you'd prefer things to bend a bit more towards the privacy side, and you
can get your hands on some pixel hardware, I have to highly recommend giving Graphene
OS a try.
It might just exceed your expectations too.
But if the situation with the commercial OSes ever improves, well, of course we'll let you
know.
With all of that and everything else happening in the world of Linux and open source, go
to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact to let us know your source IP address so we don't
have to rely on the leaks.
If you haven't checked out our PeerTube instance, head over to jupyter.tube.
You can see how we make some of our podcasts.
Just not this year's show.
That's top secret.
Don't worry though.
We'll keep it secret in the back end.
But only until next week when we'll be back with our take on the latest Linux and open
source news.
Thanks for joining us and that's all the news for this week.