Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 111, recorded on June 23rd, 2019. I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe. We start out this week with a story that is getting a lot of discussion
online, and that is Ubuntu's plan to drop i386 support in 1910.
Yeah, this has been a long time coming. They've been discussing this for well over a year,
and now is the time to do it before the LTS. It's going to be dropped in 1910 in preparation
for the first LTS 2004 that will just have no i386 support at all.
Yeah, the post on the Canonical Discourse site reads, the Ubuntu engineering team has
reviewed the facts before us and concluded that we should not continue to carry the i386
support forward. Consequently, i386 will not be included as an architecture for 1910 release,
and will shortly begin the process of disabling it for the series across the Ubuntu infrastructure.
And they go on, and this is the part that really caught a lot of attention. While this
means we will not provide 32-bit builds of new upstream versions of libraries, there
are a number of ways that 32-bit applications can continue to be made available to users
in later Ubuntu releases.
Well, virtualization being the obvious one, and potentially Flatpak and Snaps.
Even a chroot of the 1804 libraries, because 1804, it has many years of support ahead of
it.
Yeah, another four years, which should be enough time, hopefully, to migrate away from
the various applications that are still using 32-bit components.
I mean, this is a thing that's happening. We've been talking about it for a year on
this show. OpenMandriva also announced this week their plans to drop the 32-bit release
in sort of a transitionary method. What are your thoughts on this, Joe? I mean, it kind
of feels like this is the future in a way. This story made me realize, I'm an old man,
by the way, because I have been here for the transition from 8-bit to 16-bit to 32-bit,
and now I'm watching the 64-bit transition. And this one seems like the sloppiest of all.
It does seem to be a very painful transition, definitely. It's been dragged out for many
years at this point. I think the way that Canonical have done this with Ubuntu has made
a lot of sense. They, first of all, dropped the ISO images, and they stopped automatically
upgrading people to 1904 in preparation, really, for an inevitable eventuality. And that is
that they can't just keep building that 32-bit i386 repo because of all the QA testing security
issues that come with it.
Well, and think about it from the Canonical developers' position. Once you make an announcement
like this, you still have to wait for all of the production-supported systems to work
their way out. So if you think about it, that would be 1404, 1604, and obviously 1804 all
have years of support left. So they will have to continue to maintain these libraries even
after this announcement and this release is final. So it's long-term planning.
Yeah, you might have to pay to get some of those, like 1404, but yeah, that will be supported
potentially for another few years still. So this is extremely long-term planning from
them. And they have to draw a line at some point, don't they?
It does seem inevitable as the steady progress of time marches on. And I would not be surprised
if other distributions start having this same conversation in the next year or so. It may
be the number one conversation over the next year. And oftentimes, Canonical and Ubuntu
are kind of at the forefront of these kinds of decisions. I think of Mir and Upstart.
They weren't really popular decisions, but let's be frank. When they decided to choose
Mir, development on Wayland was going nowhere. It wasn't until they committed to Mir that
Wayland picked up. And to be honest with you, Joe, the same is really true for Snaps. Flatpaks
weren't even called Flatpaks then. XGG Apps, I think is what they were called. And they
were going nowhere until Snaps were announced. I kind of think the reality is the same here
for this transition from i386 support.
Well, it took a few days, but the community did react to this. And it turns out that there
are quite a few, not even that niche cases, that still need some 32-bit libraries and
components to work properly, specifically Steam and Wine.
Yeah, you're right, Joe. 32-bit is alive and well in the gaming world. In fact, friend
of the show Popey, Canonical employee, did a little testing of his own and the results
were pretty much miss, not so much hit. A lot of things depend on those 32-bit libraries.
I'm not telling anybody anything they don't know that's ever attempted to get kind of
any sort of gaming setup on Linux. You really have to get all of those libraries installed
for it to work properly. But does that mean it should always be that way?
Well, hopefully not. Hopefully, this is going to be the impetus to push forward development
and move into the 21st century and stop using i386. And we do have to stress that this is
32-bit x86 we're talking about. It's nothing to do with ARM 32-bit, which is still going
strong and probably will be for a while.
Yeah, you're right. It's kind of funny we have to make that disclosure now. ARM 32-bit
is fine, guys. It's fine. It's fine. But really, I'm a little disappointed because there has
been a significant backlash to this announcement. It really kind of kicked off when that Valve
developer tweeted that they're dropping support for Ubuntu going forward. And then from there,
you had a change.org petition that people started signing.
Yeah.
I know. I don't know. I mean, I don't even think it's broke 200 people yet. But it really,
it started to stoke the internet outrage machine. And I'm a little disappointed because you
can see different Canonical employees immediately beginning to backtrack now. And now Canonical
is repositioning this as like a firm thing we're doing. And now it's a, hey, it's a proposal.
And it's not out yet. And we may change things. Guys, calm down.
Yeah, it's funny. There was a decision that had been made. And then now they're talking
about it as a proposal. And that is, well, you could say it's them listening to feedback
or dealing with the backlash. But this whole backlash has happened at the weekend. So we'll
have to see in this coming week how this is dealt with and whether they do officially
backtrack on it or whether they double down and say, look, if it means you moving off
to another distro, so be it. This is what we're doing. We've made a decision. And we're
going to stick with it.
Yeah, the timeline is not great here. So the announcement is made on Tuesday. And the language
is strong. You know, we're doing this thing. This is how it's going to be. And that happens
on Tuesday. The internet doesn't care. Nothing happens, apparently. But then on Friday, a
Valve developer tweets that they're dropping support. And the internet outrage machine
goes into overdrive while all of the Canonical employees are, you know, having themselves
a weekend. It's its worst case scenario in a PR event here.
Well, I really do hope they don't backtrack on this. It's been difficult for the Canonical
employees basically on their free time trying to deal with this. But presumably, on Monday
morning, when they actually get together and discuss this, there will be a decision made
and maybe some sort of public statement about it. And I really hope that they do just double
down it and say, look, we are pushing forward for once. We're not going to just cave into
this outrage culture.
That would be great. I don't think that's what's going to happen. They're going to come
up with some sort of solution that involves just moving the 1804 maintain libraries forward
to 1910. And yeah, that's great. I think at the end of the day, I'm pretty disappointed.
I think watching this entire discussion happen has made me realize that Canonical and Linux
project development in general, open source project development, really, in general, is
really subjective to outrage development. You start down a path, the internet freaks
out, and you turn to something that's less objectionable by the outraged Twitter groups.
And we all kind of suffer in the long term. We don't make the dramatic progress that we
really need. We make a compromised progress. And the rest of the end users, the silent
majority suffer. We don't get the real change we need. We get some sort of compromised end
product that satisfies the people that are upset over the weekend.
But isn't that kind of the point of open source development? Whereas, if you take something
like Mac OS dropping 32-bit support, that will have happened internally, the discussion.
Whereas, because this is open source, the discussion happens externally out in public.
And isn't that a good thing?
That's complicated. I think what you need is you need the public discussion because there
has been a lot of good points made online on Twitter and various different outlets that
are worth considering that Canonical should reflect on. At the same time, you have to
have people that are really committed to a vision that won't just cave to the outrage,
that are willing to see the big picture through. You got to have a balance there.
You do have to have a balance. And it's probably better for people to have the discussion in
the correct place. And just ranting on Twitter probably isn't the correct place for that.
In a calm discussion on the proper mailing list or on their discourse forum or whatever,
that would seem to me to be the correct place to do it.
I would love to see a rational, technological discussion around this. Imagine if all of
that energy had gone into coming up with a solution around this. Because every single
distribution is about to face this problem. So what if we came up with a way to solve
this? Maybe it's just the Steam runtime gets more libraries. Or maybe we double down on
a Flatpak or Snap solution. But what if, as a community, we took this opportunity to come
up with a cross-distribution solution to this problem? Solace has tried it. There's a Flatpak
that tries this. There's a Snap that tries to solve this problem. Everybody has a solution
to this. What if, just for a moment, we took all of this upset and outrage at Canonical
and we said, you know what? They're trying to solve a problem we all face. How can we
solve this? That would be such an appropriate focus and use of everyone's energy. Instead,
we get silly things like change.org partitions, and we get silly outrage on Twitter, and we
get silly hot takes here and there. People don't even give it three days to settle and
marinate.
Well, they have to get their outrage out in time to build another video editor, right?
Yeah, let's launch a crowd funder too, Jim.
A petition to make another great video editor for Linux. That's what we need.
That'll solve it. Well, in the meantime, the rest of the press is all writing about these
outrageous security vulnerabilities that affect both Linux and FreeBSD.
Yeah, this is something called SAC Panic, which has been dubbed the new ping of death.
What's really happening here is the way the OS handles these SACs. A SAC is a TCP Selective
Acknowledgement, and there's various different ways the kernel can respond to these. And
in this particular and the other vulnerability that's happening here, CVE-2019-11478, the
operating system does not handle that kind of traffic very well, both in the case of
FreeBSD and Linux. And what essentially happens is the operating system becomes completely
consumed handling these types of TCP packets and can't respond to other services like,
you know, a web request.
And this is not exactly a new issue, is it?
No, that might even be the part that really kind of makes this a story. This flaw goes
as far back, at least as far as Linux is concerned, it goes back to kernel 2.6.29. So that's a
lot of kernels, Joe.
Yeah, and never before has Alan Jude's advice of patch your system, I think that's what
he's saying.
Your stuff, your stuff.
Oh, your stuff. That's it, yeah. Never before has that advice been so relevant. The patches
are there, but you have to apply them. And if you're not using a live kernel patch, then
it means a reboot. But I think some of these kernel flaws, you know, take it or leave it,
it's not really that important to reboot immediately. But with this one, I was just on it, rebooting
everything immediately.
Yeah, yeah. I mean, in total, we're really talking three different flaws that could be
found in the Linux kernel's handling of TCP networking. That, to me, definitely registers
as a worth it. And the most severe vulnerability could allow a remote attacker to trigger a
kernel panic, and nobody wants their system to go down. So it's worth updating on this
one.
Well, this was the week that Slack did a very successful IPO. But I noticed that Mattermost,
which is the kind of open source alternative to Slack, raised quite a lot of VC funding.
This is the story that did not get very much reporting in the wake of Slack's big IPO,
but Mattermost raised $50 million. And that's not all, really. This is their latest round
of funding. It brings their total raised money to $70 million to build a Slack competitor.
Now, I've been aware of Mattermost for quite a long time, but I'd never actually tried
it out. But this inspired me to spin it up on a digital ocean droplet. And I must say,
I was very impressed with it. It seems very much like Slack, but missing a few of the
features. But I suppose you could say it's focused on the features that you need rather
than some of the bloat that Slack might have. And I could seriously see myself and a team
using it, self-hosted, open source. I mean, there are obviously the enterprise versions
that have some added features, mostly around compliance and stuff. But I could definitely
see running this self-hosted version, certainly with a smallish team.
Yeah, you and me and a few others gave it a go this weekend for this story so that we
could have some experience with Mattermost. And I think we all walked away fairly impressed.
If you're a Slack free user today, I really don't think there's any reason you couldn't
switch over to Mattermost immediately. Now, if you're not familiar, it's a startup that
characterizes itself as an open source messaging alternative to not just Slack, but also Microsoft
Teams or Atlassian HipChat, those kinds of enterprise chat softwares. And along with
the announcement of the money, there's also some changes in the Mattermost board. Most
significantly, the Twitter COO will join the Mattermost board as a director.
And there's also some good news that comes along with the fundraising. The project has
grown to 10,000 independent downloads a month and 1,000 unique contributors to the project.
Much of that in translation, admittedly. But it's kind of nice to see the project grow.
We tried it out and we both walked away with, huh, you know what? Better than I expected.
I thought you'd have to like set up a matrix system and get a riot IM on top of that and
really build something out to get something competitive with Slack. But with Mattermost,
you stand it up in a few minutes, I assume, and you're good to go. I'm kind of curious,
Joe, how long did it take you to get a Mattermost instance running?
Well, the documentation was really good. And yeah, it only took a few minutes to get the
initial system up. And then only a few more minutes really to get the NGINX proxy going.
And I got my let's encrypt sorted out. And so yeah, total, probably less than an hour
of working on it. But now I've done it once, I think I could spin it up on another instance
much more quickly.
Well, their CEO says that this is going to accelerate their growth and their community.
They plan to go from 65 employees to 110 employees by 2020. They're going to like go at Slack
like full on, full force now. And having seen it, I've not only tried it out with your instance,
but also the Pop OS community is using Mattermost. I honestly think it's better than Slack free.
And if we were starting today, I would just use this. And if I was an open source project,
creating a distribution or a project that was being consumed by open source enthusiasts,
the Mattermost just be 100% the way I go. I mean, IRC rooms are great. Absolutely. I'd
probably have one of those too. But I wouldn't do a forum anymore. I wouldn't do a free Slack,
I would just stand up a Mattermost instance. And I think it would be really successful.
They also have apps for Windows, Linux, the Mac, Android, iOS, as well as a web application.
Yeah, I tried out the Android app. And it was pretty much on a par with Slack. The only
issue I had was that the notifications don't actually tell you what the message is. It
just tells you that, you know, Chris has sent a message or whatever. So then you have to
open the app.
That's how I like it.
Like a bit of mystery.
Yeah, read my message. It's a mystery. Yeah, I tried out the Linux desktop app. It's you
know, it's a it's a wrapper around the web application. But you get, you know, system
trays, and you get notifications, and you can have multiple instances. So it's it's
not bad. But it's a web app. It's a web app in a desktop application. But you know, they're
making a Linux version available. And it does integrate. So I can't complain.
Yeah, it's definitely one to watch. But it seems that something that we won't be watching
is any more Google tablets.
As a longtime Android on tablets enthusiast, which I thought it did better at I got the
Samsung tab, I obviously got the Nexus seven, I thought it was great. I'm a little sad to
see this news. But if Google's going to focus on a singular OS, especially one around the
laptop form factor, Chrome OS is definitely the OS to just focus on I, I really, really
wanted a pixel slate, but the reviews were so bad. It seems so so early, it seemed like
a product that lacked focus from its developers from from the makers. I hate to see this at
the same time, they need to pick a horse and they just need to try to win a race. The iPad
Pro is so far ahead right now.
Well, that's the elephant in the room here, isn't it that the iPad Pro is very expensive,
but it is the class leader in that space. You could argue that maybe the surface devices
that Microsoft have got are competing there. That's kind of mostly an enterprise and stuff.
But
I kind of disagree there, Joe, with this change, I feel like Google is going more head to head
with the surface.
Well, yeah, I suppose. And they're basically just leaving that tablet market to Apple now,
and just accepting defeat there, really. Because initially, they dropped Android on their own
tablets and tried to go for Chrome OS, but it just it doesn't make sense on that form
factor. Whereas the pixel book form factor, which is essentially a convertible laptop
that you can fold all the way around into a tablet, kind of splits the difference gives
you the best of both worlds. But without the keyboard attachment, that pixel slate just
didn't make any sense at all. And because that keyboard wasn't really good enough. That's
probably why it didn't take off. So I'm not hugely surprised by this, really. But it's
just a bit sad that there will be OEMs like Samsung and stuff making tablets still.
Yeah, they'll keep going. They could go with the open source version of Android.
Well, yeah. And you know, Android, you can just run kind of phone Android on a slightly
bigger screen. But it just doesn't have that traction, the app ecosystem that Apple has.
That's the thing you need those applications, you got to have the app developers on board.
Yeah. Well, unless like me, I recently bought a Galaxy Tab S2, I think it's called and put
lineage on it. And that's the only a small, I think, an eight inch, four by three aspect
ratio one. And that I use for reading news and stuff.
It's a great size. I love the seven inch that my Nexus seven is my favorite tablet. I have
an iPad Pro now. It's a great, it's a great tablet. It's so fast. But my favorite tablet
was the Nexus seven, I could put it in my coat pocket.
Yeah, I can do that somewhat with this Galaxy Tab S2. But really, I just have it set up
very much like my phone. It's just a bigger, easier to read phone, really. I think when
you get into the 10 inch plus, that's when you really need to have a UI that's based
around it. And that's why we're going to see iPad OS shortly, which is really just iOS
with a few extra features. And you need to have the apps that can take advantage of that
bigger form factor. And I think that Android is just lost in this space, unfortunately,
and Chrome OS never really got started. So yeah, it's kind of sad.
I kind of agree. I think at least immediately, that's true. Long term, Google is making a
lot of wins with the Google Apps integration with companies. And I think that sells Chromebooks
right there. I think they have a good long term strategy. And if they can get behind
one product like this, which has often been a criticism of Google, they could be really
successful. I'd love to see them bring something that's Linux based as a competition to the
iPad because right now, I'm using the iPad Pro because it's the best product. But if
I could buy a Google Linux based device that would be better, hmm, I may consider it then
it would really come down to the privacy stuff. You know, that little detail that nobody has
to worry about with Libra coin, that rumor we talked about last week, Joe, turns out
it's a real thing.
Yeah, it turns out those rumors were completely true. And it was officially announced this
week. And we've got a link in the show notes to a Verge article that then has a bunch of
links to way more articles if you really want to get in depth with this. But I think because
those rumors were pretty much spot on, we didn't learn a huge amount.
Yeah, I agree. What we kind of learned, if anything was the rollout plan. At launch,
you'll be able to send Libra inside of Facebook Messenger and WhatsApp, surprise, surprise.
And then, for the most part, it'll be initially used as a way to take Facebook money and convert
it to real money. But eventually, like the long term plan that Facebook has, is they
hope that Libra will be accepted as a form of payment, and maybe other financial services
that they can build on top of some sort of service. They have, quote, plans long term
port to transform the global economy, end quote.
Well, global is the key issue here. This is not aimed at us in Europe and America. This
is aimed at developing nations where people are using these phone based payment systems,
and it's really looking to compete with those.
I agree. I completely agree. That's where the story is really going to get interesting
long term. Anyone who has followed the cryptocurrencies and blockchain for a while now has been just
kind of sitting back and waiting for some large corporation to take advantage of what
is essentially a gift of the riches. If you can really pull this off, you make your own
currency and you make it math based and you follow the right kind of protocols and procedures,
you can have a hit. And I think any of us cryptocurrency enthusiasts, yay Bitcoin, have
been just kind of waiting. Who's going to figure this out? I thought it would be Microsoft,
but apparently it's Facebook.
Yeah, so it would seem. And our speculation last week about the price of Bitcoin going
up seems to have been correct because it has. It's been somewhat volatile, shall we say,
but it has gone up. Good news.
It wouldn't be a Bitcoin story without a little bit of volatility in there, would it?
Even though this Libra is, people are saying, it's not even a proper cryptocurrency. It's
basically just a fiat currency. And there's been a lot of naysayers, but I think that
it potentially has some legs. I don't know. I still don't know where I stand, whether
it's the death battle of a dying company, very slowly dying company, or whether it's
going to really take off and make them a bunch of money in developing nations. I think really
we have to wait until it's launched next year.
Absolutely. I'm sitting here with a huge smile on my face right now because I love all of
the parallels to free software and open source that are happening in the financial sector.
It's amazing. It feels like it's 1979 for the financial institutions right now. And
they are about to witness a reckoning when an open source way of doing currency comes.
And it's math backed at that. I really enjoy this. And there's so many parallels for somebody
who has been watching the free software and open source communities for years when it
comes to cryptocurrency. And it is one of the grandest experiments that's going to happen
on the human stage when it comes to software and everyday life. I can't wait to see where
this goes because we have a very special position in history to watch this thing unfold.
Who's going to be the richest storm in a bit though? That's the big question.
Hey, at the end of the day, Joe, we're all Satoshi Nokamoto. Well, wherever it goes,
we'll follow it as we always do here on Linux Action News. Be sure you go to linuxactionnews.com
slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch with us.
And why don't you come work with us? Come hang with Joe and I over at Linux Academy.
They have lots of open positions right now, from training architects across the board
to general engineering, like development on Ruby on Rails, QA engineering, Node.js and
Angular development. All of it is open right now. They're growing and they want people
like you that are listening to these podcasts to apply. So go to linuxacademy.com slash
careers or go to the link in the show notes.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I am at Chris LAS.
I'm at Joe Rissington.
Thank you for joining us and we will see you next week.
Have a great day.