Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 205 recorded on September 4, 2021. I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes from an extremely hot Tucson, Arizona. Let's do the news.
And we start with a historic moment for SUSE, the release of SUSE Rancher 2.6. 2.6 is hot
on the heels of SUSE's Q2 numbers, the company's first earnings as a public company since their
Ranger Labs acquisition. Key takeaways from the investor briefing are the company's confirmation
of an annual run rate of 519 million, growth of 16% on the prior year, and perhaps most
interestingly, Rancher had an annual run rate of 50 million. That's up 91%.
Those are your numbers the market notices and those are numbers that matter to SUSE.
Rancher 2.6 is released is Rancher now under the SUSE umbrella. It is an evolution of that
brand now. And they've kept it with a minor point release. And I think that's actually
pretty clever by SUSE. We'll get into that in a moment. But their main goal here with
Rancher is to continue to position Rancher as a Kubernetes agnostic management offering.
To that end, this latest release supports any cloud native Computing Foundation certified
Kubernetes distribution. For on premises workloads, there's the Rancher Kubernetes engine, which
runs entirely within Docker containers. And of course, SUSE Rancher supports all the public
cloud distributions, doubling down on their efforts to remain cloud agnostic and vendor
neutral, the key selling point of Rancher.
So what's new in 2.6? Well, actually quite a bit. And it leads one to suspect when you
look at all these changes, they avoided bumping the version to 3.0 simply just to set expectations
with customers that, hey, this product you love this Rancher, it's not going to be radically
different under SUSE. But when you look at it, it has a whole new improved user experience
and a new UI at the top level. They've re-architected some key workflows that right there alone,
some companies would bump the version number over and under the hood, they've improved
security and they've also strengthened compliance capabilities. But it seems like a lot of engineering
work went into rebuilding the containers that Rancher deploys. Of course, when you set up
a Rancher deployment, it's going to spin up a lot of the services that you need inside
containers automatically. Previously, those containers were based on Alpine and Debian
predominantly, but now they've reworked it. So they're all based on SUSE Enterprise Linux.
And in addition to that, SUSE Rancher 2.6 also has added the SUSE Linux Enterprise base
container images. So think universal base images, a containerized subset of RHEL, but
for SUSE Linux Enterprise. And of course, because you got to have acronyms for all this
enterprise stuff. They're calling it the SLI BCI.
I'm not sure that name is really going to stick in my mind. But really, my question
is, what took them so long? At this point, Chris, I think you'd agree with so many management
platforms out there now. The real issue facing IT teams isn't really, can they find something
that works to manage Kubernetes? But really, it's determining the best way to manage a
multi cloud, maybe with some on premises components, and a whole bunch of solutions that you've
already deployed in production, you need something that's going to work with all of that. And
really, SUSE Rancher is known for solving that problem. With 2.6, they're investing
even more into that strategy.
Well, sticking in the container space for one more story, it seems that Docker Inc has
managed to piss off more of their commercial users this week, the company has announced
that their free plan is now a quote, personal plan and requires the businesses with 250
or more employees. Or if that business earns more than 10 million in annual revenue, it
must pay a subscription if they require the use of Docker desktop.
And they very well might if they're using Docker on a Mac or a Windows machine. Now,
there are no changes to the command line Docker engine, but that only runs on Linux. In addition
to that new personal plan, there's also a $5 per month pro plan, and a $7 per month
team subscription. Both of those are left unchanged. There's also a new $21 per month
business subscription that adds centralized management, single sign on and quote, enhanced
security. That's $21 per user. And I can see that adding up really quick. I mean, at that
price, you might as well start swapping people over to desktop Linux and save money. Sadly,
this is truly the forever story of Docker Inc. And I do mean sadly, how the hell are
they going to make money? It seems to be the perpetual question and watching the way they've
just jerked around Mac and Windows users over this last year alone, it, well, it's starting
to look pretty desperate over there at Docker.
And speaking of growing a company based on an open source product, MongoDB just had a
rather impressive quarter. In a recent interview, their CEO also shared some new details about
their customer base.
So we have all types of customers, we now have 29,000 customers, we have some of the
largest brands in the world, people like Toyota, AT&T, Morgan Stanley, Verizon, etc, as well
as cutting edge startups and new breed companies like UiPath and DataRobot, who are building
their business on top of MongoDB. And that's what you're seeing in our results. It was
the best quarter we've had to date.
And it appears the US government may be another potential source of growth for MongoDB. Their
database as a service product that we've talked about before called Atlas, just received a
new level of compliance approval for use in the US federal government. They already use
MongoDB on premises quite a bit. And it seems the US government is quite interested in the
hosted solution from the company.
As the clock ticks towards December 31st, we watch and wait to see how the CentOS community
will handle the upcoming transition to stream. We know Red Hat won't support CentOS 8 past
the end of the year. But now, someone has stepped up to provide updates and support
till the end of 2025. Cloud Linux has announced it will provide those updates and much needed
support for CentOS 8, giving users a new lifeline and more time to work out their plans.
This seems both good and bad to me, Wes. From a practical standpoint, it seems useful for
the market. No doubt many CentOS 8 users will want to take Cloud Linux up on this. That
just seems obvious to me. However, it also seems like it will slow adoption of both their
own Alma Linux alternative and CentOS stream, which ultimately, I suspect it just would
have been better for the industry at large to just accept, adapt, and then transition
to.
We've been keeping an eye on the framework laptop, the modular machine with a big nod
to the right to repair. This week, they've posted specifics for getting the best results
with Linux on the hardware. They note it mostly comes down to driver support in the kernel,
with the relative newness of their Wi-Fi card being a particular challenge. They also point
out that the Goodix-based fingerprint reader will require a newer kernel and at least version
1.92 of libfprint, which is the library for the fingerprint reader. Makes sense. But really,
you can just sum it all up by saying this. If you want to use Linux on a framework laptop,
come Linux kernel 512 or newer. Yeah, that's really it. They note just about everything
else works great with Linux out of the box, including those neat USB-C swappable hardware
modules. Check the link in the show notes for more information on the framework Linux
community.
Linode.com slash LAN. Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on your new account and you
go there to support the show, of course. Linode started in 2003 as one of the very first companies
in cloud computing. I mentioned that because I think one of the most common questions I
get, Wes and I got it this morning before we started recording the show. Hey, guys,
why should I choose Linode over XYZ provider? Because there are a lot of ways to host with
Linode and Wes responded with, well, I like the fact that Linode is independently owned.
You know, it's not some like crazy VC funded thing like they make money and they survive
on the merits of their product. And I was like, that's a good one. I like Linode because
they're fast. And then that other stuff I learned about later, and I really appreciated
that. But what really made Linode stick with me is their speed and their performance. They
are their own ISP. They've got 11 data centers around the world. They have a brilliant interface
to let you manage all of this. And then the systems themselves would really matter. Our
screamers, they're really fast. Linode has really just been focused on making cloud computing
accessible, affordable and high performance since 2003. That's 18 years of dialing this
thing in. So when you ask me, what's different about Linode? Well, it's everything that would
come from focus like that and from being independently owned and having a true love for the underlying
technology. That's what's different about Linode. That's why I stick with them. That's
why I'm comfortable running my business platform on Linode. And honestly, it's really the best
in class experience from the best customer support in the business to the interface to
the UI to everything down at a technical level. And then I really appreciate all of the little
extras that they have, like their S3 compatible object storage, cloud firewalls, VLAN support,
their powerful DNS manager, and ultimately their support for the community for projects
and open source. And of course, for things like this here humble podcast, there's so
much you could learn. There's so much you could try. So that's why they're giving you
$100 in 60 day credit. But you got to go to linode.com slash land that does a few things.
It lets them know you heard about it here. It says, Hey, it is worth your time and money
investing in the Linux action news. It also gives you that $100 credit. And it lets you
try things out like maybe go install Iperf on Linode and install it on another machine
on your end and do some performance testing there. Go try out a distribution you've never
played around with and take advantage of the fact that you got snapshots. Yeah, I mean,
I do. I'll spin up something on the node, just to avoid having to spin something up
in a VM on my laptop to make it warm. Because really, it's so quick. It's so simple. I can
deploy the entire base stack in like one click, or I can do a whole DIY setup if that's how
I prefer. You just got to get started. So go get that $100 credit today. Sign up at
linode.com slash lamb linux.ting.com. Have you heard the word? No, it's not the bird.
It's ting. Let's go see how much you could save right now and take 25 bucks off of that.
linux.ting.com. The trick is they're an MVNO or a mobile virtual network operator. That
means Ting customers get access to all the big carrier networks, the ones you heard of,
the nationwide coast to coast coverage that you look at on the coverage maps, you get
access to that. But you just pay less. That's why I've been a Ting customer since 2013.
They've stayed flexible with me when I'm on the road. They've got great plans. And I love
their new plans. They make it great for an individual, a family or a small business.
I like to mention the set 12 because I think that really hits the sweet spot. Go check
that one out. They got a whole bunch. Get started at linux.ting.com. But set 12 gives
you 12 gigs of data and unlimited talk and text for 35 bucks a month. How nice is that?
You just don't even have to worry about it. I mean, you sync your music and your podcast
while you're on Wi Fi and you're pretty much good to go. But if you use two gigs or you
use 20 gigs, there's a Ting plan for you. And every plan gets access to Ting's award
winning customer service with nationwide LTE and 5g coverage. It's simple to switch to
Ting. Pretty much any phone will work. So just head to linux.ting.com. Check your current
phone, create an account and pick the plan that's right for you. Once everything checks
out, Ting will just send you a SIM card in the mail. You pop that in your phone and you
get activated in minutes and they've got a nice clean process for all of it. And while
you're there, go check out the Ting blog. They often are doing giveaways or helping
with tips on battery life. There's a lot you can learn just from their blog. It's something
that I've read for years now. So cut your current phone bill in half. It's never been
easier with Ting's brand new plans. It is truly the next generation of Ting mobile.
It's here and go see how much you could save and then take 25 bucks off that. Linux.ting.com.
Just a couple of quick stories to round us out today. We've got to get Chris out of here
before he melts. It's actually over 100 degrees Fahrenheit in his recording spot right now.
So first, it seems the RISC-V platform might be getting a boost from a rather unlikely
source. Apple is exploring using the open source alternative to ARM CPUs in future devices,
at least according to a recent job posting. Yeah, the job posting is rather revealing
and I would expect to see Apple use this for IoT type devices, you know, dongles and their
home pod type gadgets. In fact, a few of Apple's cables like the lightning to headphone cable
actually have tiny, tiny ARM computers in them doing digital to analog conversions already.
Yeah, that makes sense. And maybe this way there'll be a few fewer ARM license fees to
pay. And while we're speaking of Apple hardware, the much anticipated IOMMU driver required
for PCIe, Wi-Fi, USB, display support and almost everything else on the M1 platform
has finally been merged upstream by Linus into the upcoming 5.15 kernel. This is a huge
milestone, Wes. This is huge. It's now being merged by Linus and this is a lot of what
it takes to get Linux running on an M1. And let's not forget how great it is to that this
is landing upstream. It's not like some crazy fork of Linux. Obviously, GPU support is still
a big, maybe the biggest hurdle, but we're already seeing progress steadily be made in
that direction, too. But speaking of things landing in Linux 5.15, one of the earliest
pull requests sent in for 5.15 was KSMBD, an in-kernel SMB3 file server developed by
Samsung. Now, KSMBD isn't designed to replace our beloved Samba. Instead, it's focusing
on delivering really fast SMB3 file server performance and also supporting some interesting
features that can be far more easily implemented in kernel space. Things like RDMA support
for SMB Direct, which can help offload some of the SMB workload to supported network cards.
Not just that, Wes, but also they said this is just going to work better for some Linux
workloads on smaller devices that need to host files. What I was mostly curious about
is will they integrate with the existing Samba user tools? And it appears they will, at least
they say, where appropriate. And the Samsung developers have worked with the Samba team
to make sure that some of the configuration files work right, things like extended attributes
are supported and compatible. And really, I never thought this was actually going to
get merged. I never thought Linus would merge a file server into the kernel. But when we
read through this in some workloads, I start thinking to myself, yeah, actually, I could
see myself using this. So maybe I'm actually glad to see it land.
You know, I didn't expect it either. But if you do use it, make sure you've got a firewall.
That's a great point, Wes, like how many Android devices is going to get installed on from
Samsung that are just connected to an LTE network all the time or a 5g network? I'll
tell you what, though, when 515 ships, I think we're going to be pretty tempted to try it
out. So check out linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes
and linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to keep in touch. And if you want to
hear more on the framework laptop, Cassidy joined us and gave us his take. He's had it
for a while. So check out linuxunplug.com slash 419.
As for us, we'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open
source news.
Thanks for joining us. And that's all the news for this week.