Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 217, recorded on November 28th, 2021.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Let's do the news.
And we start this week with what might just end up the first RISC-V powered phone you'll
be able to catch your hands on, and it could be just around the corner.
With Linux support nearly complete for several RISC-V chipsets, and an increasing quantity
of chips powering Linux single board computers with prices as low as $12, RISC-V seems to
be entering a new phase of maturation.
With this next phase comes the next major challenge, though, turning us all into an
ecosystem for both developers and product builders.
And Android support is finally getting in much better shape.
It was helped definitely by later versions of Android tracking much closer to the mainline
Linux kernel, which has improved its RISC-V support a lot in recent years.
Alibaba has also been one of the first to produce a working Android 10 port over to
the RISC-V architecture, complete even with GPU drivers.
But this week, leading RISC-V manufacturer SySpeed demoed a full Android 10 system on
a seven inch touchscreen.
This was building off some of their work last year when SySpeed produced the smartphone
like my ex amigo development kit as the first experiment for free hardware PDA.
One part development kit, one part learning kit, I guess you could say it was a fairly
robust looking device and not all that impressive spec wise, but an early RISC device nonetheless.
And you could easily see them putting something like that together, but maybe version two
is powered by a RISC-V chip in there.
And supply chain shortages, aside from what I'm reading, all of the bits are really there.
They just need to put it all together in a mobile dev kit now.
And according to SySpeed, a RISC-V device like this, like a little phone or learning
kit would be more powerful than like a quad core A73 ARM processor.
So possibly in line with Qualcomm Snapdragon 663 or 662 SoCs.
We'll keep our ears on the party line and give you a ring if a RISC-V Linux phone comes
a call on.
But while we're speaking of super cheap RISC-V devices, measuring just 46 by 25 millimeters
in the style of a Pi compute module, the all-winner D1 packs a one gigahertz CPU and 512 megs
of DDR3 RAM, all for just $17.
Just like a first glance looking at this thing, it looks like a stick of RAM.
Like a laptop, small size stick of RAM with just a few extra bits on it.
They're designed to slot right into a docking board that will have additional connectivity.
Maybe like HDMI, Ethernet, and GPIO pins, etc.
But I like to take these things to like an extreme version, maybe that's years down the
road.
And I picture a blade server with like 300 of these things.
And they're all installed inside this one larger box integrated into some sort of high
speed backplane, making it like a ginormous Beowulf cluster in a box.
I don't like where you're going with this, but they've actually got to ship these things
first.
Thankfully, though, the D1 is available now on AliExpress, and those docking boards are
supposed to start shipping within the next month or so.
It's a holiday week here in the States, and so there's not a lot of breaking news in the
Linux and open source community.
But there actually have been a few essential developments we wanted you to be aware of.
In the background, for years, the LLVM project has been working on a massive relicensing
effort for its code base.
And we wanted to bring it to your attention this week because a there's been some developments,
but be LLVM is a critical part of the open source ecosystem.
So we just wanted to keep you apprised.
No, it's not the latest and greatest virtual machine manager.
In fact, LLVM is not even an acronym.
It's just the name of the project, which is a collection of modular and reusable compiler
and tool chain technologies, been around now for 18 years, and started off as a research
project at the University of Illinois, created by Chris Latner, initially focused on C and
C++, but built the language agnostic design.
Yeah, that modular and language agnostic design turned out to be a huge asset for the project.
And today, it's just enormous.
And it's not just in the open source community.
LLVM has been an integral part of Apple's Xcode development tools for macOS and iOS
since Xcode four.
And this week, we got an update on their effort to relicense to what effectively will be an
Apache 2.0 license but with an LLVM exception.
That exception is just dealing with your code being compiled by LLVM as well as when pairing
LLVM code with the GPL version two.
Currently LLVM is published under the University of Illinois slash NCSA open source license,
which is based on the MIT or X11 and three clause BSD licenses.
Okay, got it.
But to make this transition to Apache to clean, they need to collect the contributor signatures,
the people that have contributed to the code over the years.
And surprise, surprise, that is the sticky point right now, the LLVM Foundation has managed
to get approval for more than 94% of the older code base and they're getting really close,
but they need 100% to legally relicense it to Apache to a Google spreadsheet is being
used to sort all this out and keep track of who they still need to communicate with so
far.
We'll have a link to that in the show notes.
The hope with this whole license change effort is to clear up the patent section of their
former license that led to some unfortunate confusion and organizations not contributing
to the project, as well as getting the runtime libraries and the rest of the code under the
same unified license and clearing up the wording on the patent rights.
In the land of farmers and fishermen in the northern German state of Schleswig-Holstein,
there is work afoot to switch 25,000 PCs to LibreOffice.
The state wants to reduce its dependence on proprietary software and eventually end it
all together.
Yeah, the goal is by the end of 2026 to have replaced Microsoft Office with LibreOffice
on all those 25,000 computers used by civil servants and other government employees, including
teachers.
Yeah, so that seems to kind of be like a phase one, and they're entertaining the idea of
a phase two if that goes well, which would be switch the OSs from Windows to Linux.
Now, I know some of us long timers are getting a solid sense of deja vu here, but I am encouraged
by a few lessons that they seem to be applying here.
One of the big ones is they're switching the applications first, getting the users familiar
with the very same applications they would end up using on Linux before switching out
the OS.
Change the apps, then the platform.
Yeah, I mean, that cuts the learning curve in half and is leveraging one of the great
things about LibreOffice, right?
It runs everywhere.
That seems like a good thing to me.
Another good sign that stood out is that they're not trying to do this just to save money.
They're doing this to break out of a dependent vendor relationship, not even trying to do
the transition on the cheap, which is good.
It means you're actually willing to spend the money to try to make something like this
effective.
Additionally, it seems to me in conjunction with broader thinking about the government's
use of open source and selecting services and software that support multiple operating
systems.
Yep.
These are some of the changes that they're implementing compared to how Munich did it
a decade ago that do make me want to be more positive.
So that's nice to see, but what's underneath a lot of this is a new motivator, which I
think is fascinating.
So it's like before it was let's save money by using free software, but now the motivator
seems to be more like we don't want to be locked into a vendor.
And we're seeing this time and time again now, this theme for businesses and for governments
is they don't want vendor lock-in.
And that is a difference.
I don't know.
I can't help but be slightly skeptical.
It was rough watching Munich over a decade just blow this thing where there were bad
choices.
You know, they rolled their own distro.
There were politics.
There were like Wolf of Wall Street style moves by Microsoft that really torpedoed this really
public Linux switch.
So it was really hard to watch that.
But yeah, I agree, Wes.
They seem to be taking a better, probably more practical strategy with it.
Well, here's hoping the fishermen and farmers will have a better go at it anyway.
And whenever government time and money is invested into free software, even if only
temporarily, users all around the world benefit together.
And that's great.
Linode.com slash LAN.
That's where we host everything up in the cloud.
And I started using Linode before they were a sponsor because they had the best price
to performance.
They had a great interface.
And I could tell after using it for a little bit, they were really Linux geeks and it was
influencing the product in an absolutely great way.
Now we're rounding into our second year of working with Linode.
And it's been absolutely enabling for us as an independent business to not only survive
because they are a fantastic client, but also they are where we run everything.
We still choose to deploy everything in Linode.
It gives us that fast performance.
It gives us locations near you because they have 11 data centers around the world.
They have the best API out there.
It truly is a developer owned company.
They have a 99.99% SLA.
They're ready to work in a multi cloud environment.
And when you compare Linode pricing, performance and features against the hypervisors that
want to lock you into their proprietary platforms, Linode crushes it.
The independent parties have verified it.
Linode is the fastest provider out there.
And especially when you look at price and performance.
But they have brand new AMD EPYC dedicated CPU rigs if you want to go that way.
They're rolling out new MVME storage to their systems.
And of course, they're $5 systems.
They're like budget focused systems are still incredibly powerful.
I use that now for game servers and sync thing and all that all running on one $5 Linode.
They really do stack up to the competition and I acknowledge there is a lot of ways to
host something.
But nobody does it like Linode, nobody.
And on top of all of that, they have the best customer support in the business.
By phone, ticket or social, they're gonna help you, they're gonna take care of any problem
you have.
And that means you can rest easy at night.
And I do knowing that because that's where my business infrastructure runs.
So go build something, go try something, go test something, push it to the limit, see
what you can get and really kick the tires because Linode is going to give you $100 when
you go to linode.com slash LAN.
Go there to get that $100 in CCD credit on a new account and you support the show.
It's a great deal.
It's a great opportunity.
Linode.com slash LAN.
Linux.ting.com and thanks to Ting for making this episode of Linux Action News possible.
Ting is my cell service of choice since 2013 and the trick is that Ting is an MVNO.
So they're a virtual operator that runs on top of multiple carriers and they can focus
on great deals and great customer service, not digging holes in the ground.
So you get great connectivity and speed on LTE or 5G networks across the nation.
And Ting has plans as low as $10 a month.
You can dial in the plan that works just for you.
A lot of data, a little data, unlimited calls, unlimited texts, you pick.
Every plan has access to Ting's award-winning customer service and nationwide LTE and 5G.
Plus the freedom of no contracts ever.
Boom.
Ting's been leading the industry on that.
And the nice thing is it's so simple to switch to Ting, which means you can start saving
money right away.
Pretty much any phone's going to work.
Just head to linux.ting.com, check out your current phone, create an account and pick
the plan that's right for you.
They're going to have one.
Once everything checks out and Ting figures out exactly where your best service is going
to be at, they'll send you a SIM card.
You pop that into your phone and you get activated in minutes.
It's a great way to get started.
And then from then on, you're going to find just about everything you want in the dashboard.
A customer since 2013, I've called customer service twice, both times because I was doing
something crazy on a road trip and they stuck with me.
They really did stick with me.
I had a great experience and you will too.
So get started and save $25 when you go to linux.ting.com that's right linux.ting.com
see how much you could save and then take 25 bucks off that linux.ting.com
Something rather big happened this week in the world of Linux and specifically Linux
distributions, but you'd be easily forgiven if you didn't happen to notice.
Amazon announced the release of Amazon Linux 2022 and well not typically a big event.
This time things are a bit different.
One of the major changes being that Amazon has rebased their Linux operating system on
Fedora.
That's a bit of a hybrid actually between select bits of Red Hat Enterprise Linux and
a whole lot of that Fedora goodness.
Now isn't that interesting thoughts on that in a moment.
But what I noticed is Amazon seems to casually refer to this as AL 2022 and in the release
notes they noticed that quote AL 2022 uses the Fedora project as its upstream to provide
customers with a wide variety of the latest software such as uploaded language runtimes
as part of quarterly releases.
In addition AL 2022 has SE Linux enabled and enforced by default.
Little round of a quiet applause there because I think that's really great on systems that
are built for cloud workloads.
Some other things that they're baking into their distribution include live kernel patching,
extra kernel hardening they have details about that on the GitHub and they're basing it all
on the 5.15 LTS kernel.
And then there's the support window.
Amazon is recommitting to major versions of the operating system every two years with
five years of long term support.
And much like Red Hat or Ubuntu but a bit abbreviated, there are two phases of support.
Each release consists of standard support for two years and then a further three years
of maintenance support.
Each release receives quarterly minor version updates to provide security updates, bug fixes
and perhaps new features.
Yeah, that new features thing is going to be interesting to see how customers react
to that long term.
Because that combined with a Fedora base seems to really position this thing as aggressively
close to upstream.
I mean, this is pretty fresh for an enterprise distro quote unquote.
And Amazon I think recognizes this in in their announcements and on their GitHub, they tout
repository locking as an option for those that want something maybe a little less aggressive,
writing on their GitHub quote, Amazon Linux 2022 gives customers control over how and
when they choose updates and provides the ability to lock major and minor versions,
as well as specific versions of your Amazon Linux repository.
This enables you to ensure consistency of package versions and updates across your environment.
I've got to be honest that when I'm choosing an OS to run on the cloud, it's not usually
Amazon Linux.
And of course, that's where you're going to see their distribution running on their cloud
and AC two instances in particular.
But it's so neat to see a new distribution come out that's based on Fedora.
We just don't see that very often.
I do agree that this seems perhaps aggressively upstream for the enterprise.
But that's kind of exciting, because a lot of these sort of server districts have felt
so stale for a long time that you maybe you chose something like a month or because it
felt like it changed a little bit more often, just a little more fresh flavor.
If you didn't need the years of support in a lockdown system.
In some ways, it feels like Amazon's kind of trying out a new approach and a new part
on the spectrum.
Yeah, yeah, it's, it's a little more aggressive than say, going with sent off stream, because
it's closer to that fedora base where stream is going to be a little more reserved, a little
more careful in those updates.
And so it's kind of sitting between that between fedora and between sent off stream.
That's interesting, and would normally not be enough.
But then you come in and say, Oh, by the way, five years of support to which has always
been the Achilles heel of running fedora in production, and no one wants to upgrade those
every nine months or so.
But the other thing that's just casually nice about having a fedora server is you understand
fedora 34 as a base or fedora 35, which is what they're ultimately shooting for.
That as a base means XYZ features as a developer to build on in perhaps a sign of the times.
It feels like they're almost leading this announcement with their arm release.
I mean, yeah, sure, there's x86 as well, of course, but they're being quite prominent
that those new processors running arm of theirs in their data centers.
Yeah, of course, al 22 is going to be great on there.
Yeah, it really is sort of the ultimate Amazon fantasy stack.
You get you get an Amazon instance with an Amazon ARM processor running Amazon Linux,
the whole thing.
It's, I could see it working really well for some people.
But this would be a lot more exciting to me if these eventually released as ISOs that
I could install on any x86 or ARM system.
No sign of that just yet.
But we'll keep an eye on it.
If it does happen, we'll let you know and we'll let you know about anything else that
happens in the world of Linux and open source.
So be sure you get every single episode by going to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe
for all the ways to get those new episodes and linuxactionnews.com slash contact for
ways to keep in touch swag bags are back for a little bit longer rando swag bags at Jupiter
garage.com now with a Jupiter Journal.
It's pretty great.
As for us, we'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open
source news.
Thanks for joining us.
And that's all the news for this week.