Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 206, recorded on September 12th, 2021. I'm
Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes, from Northern California. Let's do the news.
This week, kernel developers have been hard at work on the Linux 5.15 merge window, which
closes today. Now, 3,440 patches may seem like a slow start to some, but those patches
are packed with significant new features.
Actually, those numbers still continue to impress me. But a feature looking through
all of them that really caught our attention, well, was one that was 17 years in the making.
The real time preemption locking code has been merged. That work began back in 2004,
and it's ended up touching so many different parts of the kernel. So we will have more
on preemption locking in the future.
But for today, another fascinating feature in 5.15 is the idle scheduling class control
group. This new group will only run when there's nothing else for the CPU to do. But using
the control group architecture means you can control the relative allocation of those idle
resources within the group. It's really a nice use of a collection of existing kernel
technologies.
We're also seeing improvements to some of our favorite file systems, the block IO subsystem,
and of course, improved hardware support.
Yeah, we've been reviewing some of the development chatter and it seems like there's a lot going
on with this development cycle. And it hasn't all necessarily been good news, actually.
But at least in this case, the robots have our back. Intel's kernel test bot found a
noticeable performance regression that made it into Linux 5.15. The performance regression
came from the new memcg accounting support that was merged just last week. It turned
out to have a lot more overhead than anyone expected about a 33% performance impact, at
least according to Intel's tests. And well, when Linus saw that he quickly reverted the
patch and he noted, quote, it was completely broken, and I should have caught on to it
earlier, end quote.
And while we're speaking of errors in the kernel, there's another kernel-related story
we wanted to fill you in on. Landing this past weekend was the surprising move by Linus
to enable the werror compiler flag by default for all kernel builds. That flag makes all
warnings be treated as errors, which in turn stops the kernel build if it runs into those
new errors. And unfortunately, it turns out there are a few more warnings than one might
have thought. This change has led to quite a mess.
Oh, man, in particular, like test farms, like the Intel bot we were just talking about,
you know, they're set up sometimes to validate just recent or specific changes in the kernel
that they're interested in. Well, a lot of these farms were just stopped cold due to
warnings in the code base that aren't even related to what they're working on, sort of
rendering the farm semi-useless. And a Googler who has been involved with the LLVM Clang
building of the Linux kernel, ended up submitting a patch that reverted the change by Linus.
And he noted that, quote, while I can appreciate the intent of enabling WR, I don't think it's
the right tool to address the root cause of developers not testing certain tool chains
or configurations or taking existing reports seriously enough.
No one wants to see their CI system turn red. He went on to say that the WR flag might be
useful to prevent new warnings from creeping in, but doesn't seem like a good fit for the
current state of the kernel, unfortunately. Linus being Linus responded and basically
rejected the notion of disabling it by default outright, saying, no, it was merged in response
to years of pain. I'm not going to revert that change. Now, I will probably have to
limit it. But basically, any maintainer who has code that causes warnings should expect
that they will have to fix those warnings.
You could tell the tensions were getting high and Linus went on to say that he spent hours
recently getting rid of warnings. And he really shouldn't be the one fixing other people's
code. He also noted that they shouldn't really be shocked when he tells them it's time to
clean their own house. Marco Elver chimed in shortly after with the idea of maybe just
enabling WR when doing a compile test kernel build. That's really the type of build that
makes sure the kernel and all of its drivers can successfully compile. And that idea seems
to have taken hold with Linus calling it a reasonable change and merging the patch that
demotes it to compile test only by default. Really, it seems Linus just wants developers
to start dealing with their compiler warnings.
And while we're speaking of things Linus is trying to correct, you might have heard about
the merge of the new Paragon NTFS driver we've been telling you about. And Linus's subsequent
complaints regarding GitHub merges. Here's what he said.
That's another one of those things that I really don't want to see. GitHub creates absolutely
useless garbage merges. And you should never ever use the GitHub interface to merge anything.
Linus goes on to note that to him, GitHub creates totally worthless commit messages
as well, adding GitHub is a perfectly fine hosting site, and it does a number of other
things well too. But merges is not one of those things. For a little context around
that complaint, you've got to remember that the kernel is a pre GitHub, and even a pre
Git project. Modern, what you might call GitHub native projects tend to outsource some of
this bookkeeping to the pull request process. And that kind of workflow was never adopted
by the kernel team. Yeah, and after all, Linus created Git. So this is not a complaint about
Git, but really how GitHub creates merge commits. He kind of hits the nail on the head with
this point when he says, quote, the Linux kernel merges need to be done properly. That
means proper commit messages with information about what is being merged and why you are
merging something. But it also means proper authorship and committer information, etc.
All of which GitHub entirely screws up. And then Linus goes on to mention that they had
this same issue with the KSMB server request, which reminded me that we're putting a Samba
server in the kernel. But file servers built in the kernel aside, if you're an AMD user,
check the show notes. There's some nice to haves landing in 5.15 just for you.
One of the lesser known realities of large companies running enterprise Linux distributions
in production is the need for newer software mixed in with that tried and tested stable
base.
Absolutely. I don't know how much of a little known reality this is because we have heard
tales from Amazon employees who ripped out the TCP IP stack and wrote their own on Linux.
We have heard tales from Facebook developers rolling their own centos kernels and repositories
replacing entire large chunks of the traditional centos release. And just as an aside, this
is one of the reasons the Facebook server team is really super excited about centos
stream is they can now participate directly in the future development of the platform.
That's going to be something of a game changer, I expect. But back to this poorly kept industry
secret. Something needed to be done to address the needs of Red Hat Enterprise Linux and
CentOS users who might not have the resources of Facebook or Amazon and are just kind of
stuck in the position of needing newer components for their chosen operating system.
Yep. And long story short, Fedora team members realize, well, they had mostly what they needed
to solve the problem right there in front of them for their enterprise cousins. And
that's how the Apple project was born. It stands for extra packages for enterprise Linux.
Apple packages are typically based on their Fedora counterparts and Apple uses a large
part of the same infrastructure as Fedora, including the build system, the bugzilla instance,
the update manager, the mirror manager. And well, now the group has recently begun building
packages against centos stream as REL calling it Apple next. The initiative has gone through
various transformations over the years from a test project to now a full special interest
group responsible for over 3000 additional packages not included in REL.
And this week, Red Hat announced they will officially support the community based special
interest group. A new team is being formed and expected to start work sometime in October.
It's a part of the community platform engineering group or CPR for short. That's the Red Hat
team that unites it and release engineering from both Fedora and CentOS.
This is nice from the standpoint of seeing Red Hat acknowledge that this is a workflow
that their customers are dependent on. And I would expect that probably give some peace
of mind to users who are taking advantage of Apple. But overall, there's still major
parts of the centos story that are still coming together. We do not yet have a complete picture.
I mean, we still have the transition to stream. There are new rebuilds yet to be announced.
And there are large well resourced companies that are just getting started working upstream
with stream. And now you have this official Red Hat backing of Apple. Well, all of this
suggests to me that we could be about to witness some kind of centos revolution.
Good news everyone, Microsoft's first full Linux distribution has an update that might
just pique your interest. As you probably recall, CBL Mariner is a Linux distribution
maintained by Microsoft for their own internal usage, but it's publicly available for anyone
interested. CBL Mariner is used as part of WSL. It packs Azure Sphere OS, Sonic, and
a whole bunch of other Linux based efforts within Microsoft. And now that we are in September,
Microsoft has just published their August 2021 update. CBL Mariner continues using the
Linux 5.10 kernel, which makes sense given it's a long term support release. And they've
added many new packages this time around, including cockpit. But the biggest feature
as far as we're concerned, is that they're now shipping a public ISO image ready to download.
So of course, I had to give it a go. I mean, is Microsoft they've released a Linux distribution
and it's now available as an ISO? Yeah, yeah, that's that's gonna get a download. And it's
quaint and not in like a bad way. It's clearly a lean mean working machine. It has a similar
approach to other tiny distros like alpine and container Linux came to mind. But CBL
Mariner only has just like basic packages needed to basically run containers. I mean,
it's very minimum. You know, you have some common Linux tools in there, of course, like
PS and LS. And it's got bash and all of that. And it uses RPM for packages. So you can install
packages that way. It's about a 700 megabyte ISO image. When you boot it up. It starts
with a text to speech at the boot menu. It's not like grub either was it's like their own
boot menu, I think. And it starts talking to you immediately. I had other audio playing.
It was very disorienting. Clearly, that's a weird lesson they've learned from the Windows
side. I mean, I guess it's friendly. Yeah, and I could kind of see it being useful, obviously,
for visually impaired folks, but maybe for those that are installing it on a headless
system as well. It has three options. It has text installer with speech, the text installer
and then the graphical installer. And so of course, I was like, well, let's see what Microsoft's
graphical Linux installer is like. So I chose that and then it immediately and hilariously
crashed. And then this green reader ridiculously read the error message to me. But I didn't
expect much with that. So I rebooted and I did the CLI install. And it's a bare minimum
installer. I mean, very, very bare. But it gets the job done. It's kind of exactly what
you'd want and expect from something like CBL. And it installs quick, like quicker than
I even expected. I want to say maybe within two minutes, the entire distro was installed.
It was about two gigabytes on disk once everything was all said and done. You reboot, you got
a real minimal install. I mean, your your basic tools are there, you're going to have
bash when you log in at the shell, and you got system D. So you're pretty much good to
go and you could start running containers. I mean, all in all, I can see they clearly
have built something for their particular use case. And it is designed to a T for that.
Microsoft for their part has stated that they're committed to keeping CPL Mariner up to date,
noting that it actually enhances Microsoft's ability overall to stay current on Linux updates.
They also note that the stripped back nature of the OS makes for better security saying,
quote, by focusing the features in the core image to just what is needed for our internal
cloud customers. They're just fewer services to load and fewer attack vectors. Now, it
still strikes us as a little bit strange to watch Microsoft build and maintain their own
Linux distribution, which is now even available as an ISO. But they seem to have a clear vision
for CPL Mariner, crafting it for their own specific needs. And it's gonna be fascinating
to watch if anyone else chooses to adopt it. For my part, though, I'm just hoping they
ship a version with plasma baked in sometime soon.
The
big large hyperscaler cloud vendors, they're going to present themselves as a one stop
shop. They're going to invite you to just come on in, become wholly dependent on them
as a single source for everything you might ever need. But you know, that's that's not
a good thing. The problem with relying on a single source cloud provider is vendor lock
in, you get so deeply intertwined into the vendors ecosystem that it becomes impossible
or at least cost prohibitive, if nothing else to break away. And then if your business needs
to change, you're stuck. And beyond being stuck and trapped, it's a single source architecture
that well makes your business less adaptable, and less resilient. So little really can be
part of your multi cloud strategy. And you know, there is a significant shift happening
in the industry right now. Gardner recently estimated that two thirds of all cloud industry
customers are going to adopt a multi cloud strategy as a means for specifically avoiding
vendor lock in by the end of 2024. So it's something we all really should be thinking
about. And if you ever run into any trouble with Linode, they have the best customer support.
I mean, it's truly amazing. 24 seven customer support by phone ticket or social, they're
going to help you along with hundreds of guides and tutorials. And they're always reaching
out to content creators to help create an ecosystem of content that makes it easier
to use Linode. They also recently invested in our colony reunion road trip to make it
possible for our community to connect because they understand that it's important to invest
in those areas of the Linux community as well. And not a lot of companies get that there's
a lot of ways to host something. But Linode is one of the companies that truly gets it.
They're dedicated to offering the best virtualized cloud computing ever runs on Linux, it runs
on the node. So go see what you can build, go see what you can learn. Sign up today at
Linode comm slash LAN, get $100 in 60 day credit on your new account, and you support
the show, Linode comm slash LAN, Linux dot ting.com. If you're sick of overpaying for
cell service, go see how much you could save and then take 25 bucks off that at Linux dot
ting.com. This episode of Linux action news is also made possible by our friends at ting
and there's something special over there. They're making the big networks that you hear
about all the time the coast to coast networks, they're making them available to everybody
ting is a mobile virtual network operator. That means ting customers get access to the
big carrier networks, but with way better customer service, and at a lot lower cost.
So it's just a win win. I've been a ting customer since 2003. And they've stayed flexible with
me. They've worked with me over the years. And they're great for those of you who are
traveling as well. And their plans are simple and straightforward. They have ones that are
really easy to understand. They have ones that are flexible for families. It's great.
And ting is also doing a bit of a giveaway right now. If you go over to their Twitter
page, you'll see more about it. They're at ting FTW on Twitter. They're doing a Yeti
prize pack giveaway, you can get a Yeti cooler, a Rambler, a Tumblr, a backpack and more.
So I have information on their Twitter feed and you can sign up they have like, I think
it's like seven different ways you could sign up to win. You might as well get in on that
and then check out their plans to, you know, a good plan is hard to find and they're flexible.
And if you can be clever on how you use your technology, like download your podcast and
sync a little bit of music before you hit the road, you could be shocked at how much
you could save. And the great thing about ting is there's no contracts ever. And it's
super simple to switch to ting pretty much any phones going to work because they support
the major networks. So you get started by going to linux.ting.com. You check your current
phone, get all the information, they have a really easy, smooth process to do all of
that. And you get set within minutes, they'll send you a SIM card, you pop that in, you
go back to their website, once you got it, another couple of minutes, you're activated,
you're good to go. They have a great dashboard to manage all of it. If you do need to talk
to a human, you're going to be set. But if you don't, you're going to love the website.
But the key is to support the show and get 25 bucks off by visiting linux.ting.com. It's
never been a better time to be a ting customer. Their plans are more competitive than ever.
And they're needed in the industry more than ever. So go sign up and save 25 bucks at linux.ting.com.
We don't spend a lot of time going meta on this show, by which I mean talking about the
show in the show. But with the summer coming to a close, we wanted to touch base on an
editorial choice that we made during the summer lull of development and general free software
news. Really, we thought you should know that more than a dozen additional stories were
considered and rejected for this episode. Not because they were bad stories, but because
we know you're busy. We're trying to focus on the news that matters this week. That's
the Linux action news promise. And it often means we're going to pass on more stories
than we can include each week. Not as a judgment call on those stories, but out of respect
for your time. We know you're busy. And the value of this show is getting concise, accurate
information to help you do your job and stay informed. As a concrete example, we didn't
cover the latest point release of the OpenShot project. Not because we don't think it's
a valuable project or a worthwhile release, or even something we personally are excited
about. But because unless you're an OpenShot user, this release hasn't really changed
the value proposition of the project. And that means it doesn't really fit in Linux
action news. And that's true for a lot of stories, some of which might just be a better
fit for some of our other shows, like Linux Unplugged. And I think we also realize you
can read headlines in a million different places in a million different ways if you
want. So we have a job to do. And our job is to provide value and context and some selection
where it's helpful. And more often than not, it will mean the episodes are short and concise.
And it doesn't mean that we're not digging into every story and seeking comment and evaluating
all of the news in a broader context. In fact, ironically, a shorter show often takes more
work. As backwards as that might seem on the surface, it takes more work to make a show
shorter because it's a process of working through each story, identifying the ones that
have a larger impact and taking those lists of stories and whittling it down into something
more refined. It means after we've concluded our research, messaging our contacts and sleuthing
around the mailing list and reading through our RSS feeds, what makes it into the show
is the stuff that we think you should really know about. And I should probably add, it
does sometimes mean occasionally longer episodes too, usually not in the summer. But if that's
what the content calls for, well, we'll hope you stick around for the longer episodes when
it's a big show week as well.
And really, that's the kind of flexibility that we think new media productions like this
podcast should lean into, not getting trapped in the formats of the past that follow the
clock. Making Linux industry news more accessible to busy professionals is something we take
seriously because in a very real way, this is the new show I would want to listen to
if I wasn't already making it. Now, with all of this said, we are always interested in
your thoughts. Our inbox is open to you. LinuxActionNews.com slash contact. Indeed, we always like to hear
your ideas or story suggestions or leads or announcements. You can send those there as
well. You know, Linux Action News, if you haven't been around for a while, you might
not know this, but it started life off as just a news segment in the Linux Action show.
In that context, the news could be five minutes long, or it could be the entire episode. It
was just the news segment, and it was what it needed to be. And that general idea echoes
today in Linux Action News. In a way, I guess we are we're asking the audience to trust
us and disconnect episode length from quality of episode. In our view, our value to you,
our listener, is in creating a high quality episode that provides you the information
you need in the most concise and accurate delivery possible. And we're going to keep
trying to do that every single week. So make sure you get every episode by going to LinuxActionNews.com
slash subscribe. And of course, we'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest
Linux and open source news. Thanks for joining us. And that's all the news for this week.