Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open source world.
This is episode 59, recorded on June 24th, 2018.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Tom.
Hello, Joe.
It's good to be connected again from JB1 Studios in Seattle, Washington, and we kick things
off this week with an Ubuntu Touch story.
That's an interesting one to lead with.
Yeah, Ubuntu Touch OTA4 release candidate has been released.
Now yeah, this is just a release candidate, but it's pretty close to what is actually
going to be released, hopefully quite soon.
And it's a bit of a milestone for them, because it's based on Ubuntu 16.04 rather than 15.04.
15.04, of course, is not supported anymore by Canonical.
This is supported for a couple of years, so they've bought themselves a bit of runway.
Yeah, and the phone release has traditionally been an LTS behind.
That's normal for the phone release.
But I think the bigger thing too, beyond the years of support that you get with an LTS,
is it means today, currently, they'll be receiving core package updates directly from upstream,
from the larger Ubuntu community.
And I've actually tried this out on a Nexus 5, and I didn't have a huge amount of time
to play with it, but it is pretty stable.
Much better than the last time I checked out the 16.04 version of it.
It feels pretty much finished to me.
There are a couple of little bugs in it that they acknowledge, but otherwise, I think if
you are all in on the Ubuntu touch experience and don't require certain Android apps like
I do, I think you could use this as a daily driver already.
Yeah, the project says you should be able to get away with using it as a daily driver,
as long as you're, quote, able to endure a little suffering, which I think is a good
way to put it.
And the other thing I like about this release is all of the previously supported devices
are still supported.
And like Joe said, there are a few rough edges and bugs that you have to suffer through.
They're enumerated on their post.
Just go to linuxactionnews.com slash 59 for a link to that.
But sort of at a bigger, higher level, it's just sort of great to see this project still
going.
They're not going to use it as a daily driver, but it's amazing to see that this community
has picked this up and continued this effort, even after Canonical decided it was no longer
for them.
And it's not dead yet, Joe.
It's still kicking, and they've got a good, solid release here that appears existing users
of the project can update to over the air right to their device.
Yeah, you can't actually do that right now, because the 15.04 version on the Nexus 5 and
the RTA didn't actually come through, but that's because it's just release candidate.
Once the final release comes out, hopefully very soon, then it will just work as a normal
OTA, which is pretty handy for people, rather than having to manually flash it.
Although you can flash it without wiping your data at the moment.
I just wiped data because I didn't have much on there.
But the most important thing here is if you've been following their Q&A, which they do on
YouTube, but there's also an RSS feed for the audio version, which is what I catch every
couple of weeks.
Everything that they're planning to do depends on getting this 16.04 release done first.
The Andbox stuff, which is getting Android apps working as an option for people, that
requires 16.04.
All of their plans in the future depend on getting this release out first.
So it is not only is it getting onto an officially supported base of 16.04, it is a base from
which they can then build all of their plans and all of their cool stuff that they want
to do.
It's just massively important to them.
So I would urge people to, if you've got a compatible device, do test it for them.
Look at the bugs that they're already aware of, report any new ones.
And if you're a developer and you've got some time that you can spend on it, then I do urge
you to contribute to the project because this is potentially one of the only Linux-based
OSes for phones out there that's got any longevity to it.
We'll see what happens with Purism and whether they can deliver next year, but for now, we've
got Ubuntu Touch, it's here, let's try and make it the best that we can.
And on the opposite end of the spectrum, another project that we're seeing some life from is
Android x86.
They have an 8.1 RC1 release, yeah, it's an Oreo-based x86 release of the Android project.
And speaking of Purism, I gave this a go on my Librem 15.
How did you get on with that then?
Much better than in virtualization.
They do have support for VMware and QEMU to have Mesa 3D acceleration, but boy, is it
dog slow.
But when you load it on physical hardware with Intel HD graphics, you get full OpenGL
acceleration.
And so I downloaded the 64-bit ISO and I chose the Taskbar launcher, which gives you an alternative
Windows-like launch bar at the bottom, not quite like you see on Chrome OS.
It's kind of a mix between what you would see on, say, Windows 10 and Chrome OS.
And there's two launchers that it ships with, but I went with Taskbar because that's the
one they've added with this release.
And it worked pretty well.
It also has modal windows, so you can maximize and they go full screen, or you can un-maximize
and they're modal windows that you can drag around.
So I had the Play Store open and the Twitter client open at the same time.
And yes, if you're on 64-bit, the Google Play services comes pre-installed and it works
pretty good.
There's some bugs with the 32-bit version where it can crash.
It's installed, but it's a little crashy.
And I updated Chrome.
I updated several apps on it and I set up my Google account, so my emails were coming
in via Android notifications.
It actually wasn't a horrible experience.
It was a little tedious managing the Windows.
But if that Librem 15 had a touch screen, it might have been a little bit better.
Well, enter my VivoBook.
I've got a little, I think it's an 11-inch Asus VivoBook with a touch screen.
And it's almost made for Android X86.
It's just a great experience having a proper keyboard to type on when you need to.
And I tried out both launchers on it.
One of the launchers is just very standard Android.
But this Taskbar launcher, it's just great.
It's kind of a little bit crumbly.
It's a little bit like LXQ.
It's exactly what I like.
It looks very much like my XFCE desktop that I'm looking at right now, so I'm fully on
board with it.
Very simple, searchable menu that works exactly as it should.
I'm tempted to stick it on a partition on that VivoBook and use it regularly because
it's a great release.
And the reason I wanted to talk about this was we actually talked about the last release,
which was based on Android 7, came out in February, which was long delayed.
Whereas now, I looked it up, Android 8.1 came out six months ago, and now we are almost
at a final release of Android X86.
Okay, that's not great, but they're improving.
It shows that development is accelerating on this.
In my opinion, it's better than what you get on most Android handsets.
Well, exactly.
Yeah.
It's not too bad, a six-month window.
I mean, it would be nice for them to slim that down to be day one if they could, but
I can't see that happening anytime soon.
And Android P is going to be out fairly soon by the looks of things, so they will end up
being a release behind, but it shows that this project is not dead.
And it's really cool to have it, especially if you've got a touchscreen device like I
have.
Unfortunately, it doesn't work on my little tablet.
I don't think I've talked about this before, but a while ago, just as a kind of stupid
purchase, I bought a Link 7 tablet, it's a seven-inch Atom-based tablet that came with
Windows 8, and I bought it just to see if I could get Linux working on it.
And Fedora actually boots straight away on it and works perfectly, so that's pretty cool.
But unfortunately, it doesn't work with hardware acceleration with Android X86, so I could
have had a really cheap, really quite powerful Android tablet there, but unfortunately not.
Yeah, if you've got a touchscreen laptop, just boot it up live, check it out.
If anything else, it's just a bit of fun, really.
Yeah.
I mean, to be clear, it does fully support the mouse and keyboard.
So I was using it on my Librem 15 with just my trackpad and the keyboard.
There was a couple of times where the mouse became unresponsive as something grabbed attention,
so it wasn't a perfect experience.
But there's just a couple other things they've added that do almost put this in the legitimate
daily driver category.
First of all, it's kind of a no-brainer if there's a couple of Android apps you really
like, like the Twitter client, maybe the Evernote client.
If there's a couple of official Google Play apps that you just really like, it's kind
of nice to be able to just pop them into a window on your laptop.
The other thing they've added in this release is hardware acceleration for video codecs,
which means you can watch video on this thing and get decent battery life.
I think, although I didn't run it all the way down, I think I was getting five hours
on my Librem 15.
At least that's what it was projecting, and I spent at least two hours of that battery
life.
And then something else they added for this release, which I, again, think it kind of
almost makes it legitimate as a daily driver, is they've added Ethernet support.
So if you've got Ethernet on your laptop or your x86 machine and it's a common chipset,
it's going to work now because there's a Linux kernel powering this thing.
And then the last thing that just makes it a lot of fun if you just want to play around
is you can actually get this as an RPM.
And you can download it, install it on an existing system, and it'll set up QEMU for
you.
They also have a guide for using Alien to convert it to a deb to put it on Debian systems.
So you can get it as an ISO, obviously, but you can also grab it as an RPM.
Well, Android may well be on the path to becoming irrelevant anyway, because surely Fuchsia is
the future.
Oh, man.
You're raising my blood pressure just talking about it.
And there's some details in the future Fuchsia releases, that's fun to say, that make it
look like Linux apps could be coming to Fuchsia.
What?
Yeah, it's not just for mobile devices.
There is some proper software in this thing to make it a full desktop stack.
And one of the things they're adding is guest apps, which allow you to boot up a virtual
OS inside Fuchsia.
And there's support today for a Debian based environment.
And now support is being added for what looks like a Chrome OS environment.
And part of this is using that same Vert IO technology that so many other VMs use on Linux
as part of Linux's KVM stack.
Now part of the Vert IO standard is this new VSOC, the virtual socket stuff that we've
talked about recently, that's enabling Chromebooks to run Linux apps.
In fact, that's that VSOC kernel module is the thing that Google is backporting to older
kernels to enable Linux apps on older Chromebooks.
This VSOC stuff's kind of the key piece to make no mouse lag, automatic adjustment of
screen resolution, supporting a copy and paste and transferring of files of virtualized applications
really smooth and transparent on a desktop.
That's what Vert IO with this VSOC kernel hook can accomplish.
And it's the same technology in Fuchsia and Chrome OS.
And when you put it all together, it looks like they're making one singular runtime across
these operating systems to run Linux applications.
Yeah, and suddenly this is looking less like some abstract project for the future and more
like something that's coming around the corner.
And it's fairly obvious why Google wants to do this, at least to me, and that is because
they don't want to have the Linux kernel anywhere near it because of the GPL.
Fuchsia is all permissively licensed, and that's the way they want to go with it.
Yeah, that's why it raises my blood pressure when we talk about it on the show.
It gets me a little anxious because Linux powering all of these mobile handsets in everybody's
pockets has been a big part of the Linux success story for a long time now.
And it plays a huge role in the weight that Linux devices now carry with industry manufacturers.
If that were to transition to a non-GPL operating system, all of the advances in that operating
system would primarily be going to one single entity, Google.
See, the advantage of Android being powered by Linux today is everybody has to contribute
those improvements upstream.
So the general technology platform that powers things from digital ocean droplets to watches
is getting the same improvements.
If it's all controlled by Google, as long as the license is something where people don't
have to contribute back upstream or they don't have to make it available to everybody, we
all lose.
As a thought experiment, imagine for a moment if every singular improvement that Apple made
to the core of Mac OS had to be upstreamed to the FreeBSD project.
Now I grant you, it's not based on the FreeBSD kernel.
This isn't a good one-to-one comparison, but as a thought experiment, consider how much
further ahead FreeBSD may be on the desktop today if all of the desktop improvements Apple
had to submit back upstream.
A lot of that is essentially what's happened with Android and Linux.
So many improvements to power management, ARM compatibility, Wi-Fi and Bluetooth, those
improvements have been contributed by hundreds of different hardware manufacturers that are
involved in the Android ecosystem.
And it's not like Android would go away tomorrow, but if Google made a strong shift, you got
to imagine a lot of Google's ecosystem would eventually make the transition with them.
But the difference here is that with it being permissively licensed, Google could make it
proprietary, but they haven't yet.
And so that is surely the great hope here that they will keep it open source just with
the insurance policy of the permissive license.
But it still benefits so many less users.
When you improve Linux as a whole, you improve e-commerce, you improve the education sector,
you improve the life of people like me who are now broadcasting and making their living
using Linux.
It extends to so many areas of the ecosystem.
And even if Fuchsia is, you know, I don't care what it is, MIT license, I don't care
what it is, Berkeley license, I don't care if it's the, you know, the Sergey license.
If they're the only people using that stack, if their IoT devices and their Android devices
and maybe, you know, their laptops are the only devices using that stack, then it only
benefits that narrow spectrum of an ecosystem.
Yeah, but who's to say it will only be them using it?
Because if it's open source, people can take it and do what they want with it.
And if it's permissively licensed, then they can take it and do literally whatever they
want with it.
So you're going to potentially have loads of other OEMs and other companies making devices
that are based off Fuchsia, but I suppose then they won't necessarily have to contribute
back to it.
I suppose that's the point here.
Yeah, and really, I'm not expecting all of the industry to switch, you know, the server
market, there's so many things that are built on top of Linux, they're going to remain on
Linux.
Linux will be okay, but they won't necessarily be reaping all of that developer attention.
Last.ting.com, thank you to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Action News Show.
This is a way to do mobile that breaks the mold, the lock-in that the duopoly has here
in the States.
It's a smarter way to do mobile because if you use less, you just pay less.
If you're savvy enough to use Wi-Fi while you're at work and home, then you really don't
need to be paying for, I don't know what, 12 gigabytes of data or whatever you might
be paying for.
Like, you don't, you need to just pay for what you use.
If you use a messaging application of any of them, besides SMS, you don't really need
to pay for a thousand text messages, do you?
I get what, three or four a month, probably mostly from two-factor stupid login systems
that shouldn't even be using SMS.
Why do I need to pay for a thousand messages?
That'd be ridiculous.
It's pay for what you use, a fair price for how much you talk, text, and data you use.
So this last month, I used way more data than I'll use for the rest of the year.
So I'll pay more for that month.
But for the next 11 months, I'm gonna pay around 40-ish bucks a month for three lines.
I got a phone and I got two MiFi devices that I use.
One MiFi device is on the GSM network, and the other MiFi device is on their CDMA network
because Ting has both.
And I can pick and choose whichever one is stronger, and I just join my systems to that.
I've got a Microtech router in my RV that connects to the different Wi-Fi access points
and does a speed test.
And then it'll switch to whichever Wi-Fi access point has the faster speed.
And I don't have to do any of it.
And legitimately, this last month of shows were recorded over the Ting connection.
And often, Joe would remark, you know what?
Our latency is better than when you're in the studio in Seattle because I am able to
choose what works best in my area.
And then to make things even better, I've got a booster up on the roof of the RV that
really boosts the signal.
And I can sit and have great phone calls over Ting.
And I know that I'll just pay a little bit more that month.
And then I'm done.
It's simple.
It's easy.
It's pay for what you use with nationwide coverage.
No contracts.
last.ting.com.
Okay, so let's talk about how you are suddenly regretting backing the Atari VCS.
I don't know.
I feel like this is a real hit piece by the register.
They trolled Atari hard this week.
I do agree that their PR train went off the tracks a little bit last week.
Atari VCS posted a link to some register coverage on their Facebook page and added a little
commentary.
They said, we honestly can't explain this article.
Our executive sat with that reporter for a half an hour.
And he wrote what he wanted instead of what was discussed with him.
Sadly, there are even irresponsible trolls in quote, professional positions, I guess.
We clearly said that we were bringing engineering design models to GDC.
And lots of people clearly don't understand what that means.
Hunks of plastic?
Well, yeah.
Yeah, that's how you finalize the designs and confirm that you can get the look and
feel of what you want for the finished product.
Sad.
And so the register had written, you know, hey, they were just hunks of plastic that
didn't work yet.
They didn't have any working demos.
And then the register responds with a full copy of the interview with this executive,
this marketing executive at Atari.
And it's pretty bad.
The guy doesn't have any answers.
There was no product to show at the time.
They hadn't even finalized the chip design.
Only one of the two controllers was functional.
So I agree, it doesn't sound good, Joe.
Yeah, and this was back in February, when they'd already kind of missed their initial
goal to get the pre-orders in.
And now here we are in June, and people like you have backed this.
And it's only got a week left to go.
And you're thinking to yourself, well, if they had no clue what they were doing back
then, maybe they are not going to be able to deliver this after all.
And that original article had gone under the radar for most people.
I think I'd read it at the time, but I'd forgotten about it.
Whereas now they've just had the Streisand effect, haven't they, at the end of the day?
I think they should have just not said anything about it.
And now we're all talking about it again, and it's looking really bad for them.
But it's too late.
People have backed it.
I don't know.
Can you get a refund on these crowdfunding sites?
I've never tried.
See, I wouldn't expect anything but exactly this.
Because in the interview, I listened to the whole 30-minute interview, because The Register
kindly embeds it in their article.
And the guy says they're not worried about building the Linux system, because they already
have some early prototypes of that.
That's the easy part.
The hard part is going to be building the UI on top of the Linux system.
I agree with that.
I don't think they need to finalize any of the...
It's an x86 box with an AMD CPU, and that's what it is.
The design of the box, the ports, how the controllers connect, and how they interface
with the software is way, way, way, way more complicated.
And the deals with the different game publishing outlets, building a store around all of that,
that's the hard work that is going to be really tough to pull off.
And it sounds like in that interview, that stuff's already in the works.
He just couldn't talk about it, because they want to play the hype game, and they want
to do timed announcements with specific partners at specific times, so they just wouldn't tell
The Register anything.
That's where some of this is coming from.
And as a backer, I'm actually not really worried.
If you were to ask me, frankly, I'd say this is exactly what I'd expect.
I would think they probably have a few prototypes working outside of a case that are probably
not much more than a new high-end NUC at this point that they're trying out.
And then I would imagine they're going to try to find the best price to performance
ratio and thermal overhead, and put it in this case.
And then we'll just install some x86-based Linux system on there.
And they'll call it good.
Yeah, well, it's going to be based on Ubuntu, isn't it?
So that means that you've got all of the work that Canonical are doing there for free, essentially,
because it's open source.
And so then you've just got to build, well, say, just the UI and the stuff you talked
about there.
So not making it an ARM-based system means that you can just put more or less whatever
x86 chipset in there you want, and it's going to work with Ubuntu.
Right.
And if you get some sweet partnership with Netflix, where they're going to open up 4K
HDR streaming, then that might force you to use the most latest AMD chip.
But if that deal with Netflix doesn't work out, and you're not going to have any super
high-end thing pushing the machine at launch, you might go with the AMD chip that's already
out and a little bit cheaper.
So I could even understand not finalizing that design yet, because Linux itself is a
known quantity they can already work with.
The AMD hardware pipeline is pretty well-established at this point.
And the box seems like it's probably got the thermal capacity for whatever they want to
end up doing.
It's just going to really come down to the GPU.
So I'm actually thinking this is fine at this point.
Maybe I'm overly optimistic.
Maybe I'm going to be regretting that backing of the Atari VCS.
But as of right now, I'm only at yellow alert.
It's funny that you used the words, this is fine.
Suddenly I'm picturing that meme with the dog and the fire.
That's true.
Everything seems to be fine over at Fedora, at least I think.
I'm not quite sure exactly what's going on.
But it appears to be the next shoe dropping in this merger of Red Hat and Core OS.
Yeah, it turns out that Michael Tunnel's joke turned out to be true, calling it Fedora Core
OS.
It has a good ring to it.
Yeah, it does have a good ring to it.
Although there's a bit of baggage there with the old Fedora Core.
Oh, what you call baggage, I call nostalgia.
Fair enough.
But now we know that this is going to be the upstream community version of Red Hat Core
OS.
So going off of a post that Matthew Miller made at the fedoramagazine.org site, it sounds
like the new Fedora Core OS is going to be built from Fedora upstream, rather than from
Core OS upstream.
But the way it gets delivered will be more like the way Core OS is delivered today, containers
of clustered host OS that keep themselves up to date so you just don't have to worry
about it, as he puts it.
Now, the technical details of how all of this is going to work are still being flushed out.
So don't jump to any conclusions yet.
Fedora though really is a community driven project too.
So you could still get in on the conversation and help direct where this goes.
Now he writes, I expect that over the next year or so Fedora Atomic Host will be replaced
by a new thing combining the best of Container Linux and Project Atomic.
This new thing will be called Fedora Core OS and serve as the upstream to Red Hat Core
OS.
That's a lot to take in.
I've invited Matthew Miller to come on Linux Unplugged this week.
He's got a super busy schedule, as you can probably imagine.
But if it can work out, I'll try to get it from the horse's mouth, no offense Matthew,
to try to understand what's really going on here because it sounds like a major shift
for Fedora, but one that the project is kind of architected to take on so it has a chance
to work out.
And the key aspect you mentioned there was the community involvement.
It's early enough in this whole process that the community can get involved, can help shape
this thing, and potentially even shape the direction that Red Hat's going to take Red
Hat Core OS.
It seems like it's really early days, so it's all still in the works, but it could make
Fedora really stand out as a uniquely differentiated Linux distribution.
Not that it isn't already, but this is a clear differentiator, so I'm kind of excited to
see where they go with it.
In the meantime, we do have some data for you Ubuntu users.
You recall the new survey that was baked into Ubuntu 18.04.
Well Canonical has done the first round of publishing the results.
And very interesting results they are too.
Some of them are pretty kind of what you'd expect, like stuff like people only having
one GPU mostly and one display mostly.
But one thing I was quite surprised about was that 1080p is the most popular display
resolution.
Yeah, 1080p.
We finally reached above that low res netbook graphic size that we were hanging out for
so many years.
But the thing that you don't seem disappointed in, I kind of am, is one monitor?
Everybody knows the more monitors the better.
I'm a little disappointed in that.
Yeah, it's not a battle station if you've only got one monitor, right?
Yeah, it's just way better with at least two regular monitors and one vertical monitor
from personal experience.
So come on everybody, you got to jump in on that bandwagon so that way distro maintainers
are encouraged to support it more.
The thing that jumped out at me is 15% of people installing Ubuntu 18.04 already are
using the new minimal install option.
That's a pretty high adoption rate for a brand new feature.
75% did a fresh install while 25% did an upgrade.
I would bet you that number will climb after 18.04.01 comes out or 18.04.1 comes out because
that's when existing 16.04 users are going to get the prompt upgrade.
The 16.04 desktop users haven't even gotten that like, hey, it's time to go.
Also as a little disappointed, just going to say it right now, eight gigs of RAM is
the most common.
Really people?
Four gigs was more common than eight gig, just slightly, which that didn't surprise
me because most laptops, most cheaper laptops that you've bought in the last, I don't know,
four or five years have come with four gigabytes, but yeah, eight is actually slightly lower
than that.
But it's interesting that at least a couple of people had 128 gigs of RAM.
That must be some serious workstations.
Oh yeah, that's awesome.
Yeah, because remember these are all desktop installs.
Also speaking of the survey itself, a pretty strong 67% opt-in rate to take the survey.
That's pretty good.
And that's just within the last few weeks, 67% of people.
Yeah, although I do somewhat feel in the minority here because 90% of people download updates
during the installer.
I never do that because I had one bad experience one time.
Half the people use the restricted add-ons, I never bothered with that.
And only about, well, under a third of people use auto login, which I always do.
So I feel like I'm out in the cold here.
Except for the codecs, I'm on the same.
I had a one time bad experience with downloading updates that made the install take forever
and eventually hang.
So I filed my bug, I did, and then I've never used it since.
And I installed the codecs every time.
And on all of my studio systems, I set up auto logins, which is the majority of my installs.
But the one key bit of data that we don't have yet is how many of these installs are
there.
That's the one thing they didn't publish, and they haven't published the raw data yet.
Will talks about wanting to do that as soon as possible.
But with all this GDPR stuff and general data protection concerns, you can see why they've
just put some percentages out there for now.
And they must be being very, very careful about what data they're actually going to
release.
And they did tell us that the US has the biggest Ubuntu user base, followed by Brazil, India,
China, and Russia.
Well, that's kind of the populations of the world, really, isn't it?
It's not a massive surprise.
And if you look at the graph, I think you said every single country in the world, there
are Ubuntu users.
So that tells you something.
I wonder how many distros could say that.
Yeah, we have the data linked in the show notes, as well as It's Foss did an infographic
of all of this, which, hey, look at that.
We got an infographic about something, Joe, and we'll put a link to that in the show notes
as well.
Well, I look forward to quizzing Will a little bit more about this on Late Night Linux that
we record tomorrow night.
So yeah, check that out, and hopefully we'll get some more info.
And I do want to know when we're getting the raw data, because so many people want that.
Yeah, and we'll cover it when it happens, as well as all the other stories in Linux
and the open source world.
Go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch.
And you can support the entire network at our Patreon page, patreon.com slash Jupiter
Signal.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
I'm at Chris LAS.
I'm at Joe Rissington.
Thank you for joining us, and we will see you next week.
I'll talk to you later.