Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News Episode Zero, recorded May 5th, 2017.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Joe, we've got some really interesting stories this week, and the first one that piqued both
our interests is one that's coming out of GR Security, and I'm not sure if it's on very
many radars out there.
What's going on with our first story?
Yeah, so GR Security, they take the kernel, and they add some security patches to it,
and then sell it.
And up to now, you have been able to see these patches and use them even if you're not a
customer of theirs.
But now they've decided to pull the plug on that.
And so only if you pay them will you get these changes.
And that rings alarm bells, right?
Well, hang on, they're making changes to GPL software.
Shouldn't they have to release the changes?
So to give it some context, too, you could compare it somewhat to GR Security to SE Linux
or AppArmor.
In some cases, GR Security would say it's even more complete of a solution.
And so there are folks out there on Debian systems that are all hardened up with this
GR Security.
They're essentially hooked on the good sauce, the good security sauce.
And they base their audits off this stuff.
It's a very important tool for some people that have these installations, and it's been
free historically.
What I thought was interesting, too, Joe, is GR Security is put out by a corporation
that runs it, the Open Source Security Inc. company.
And they did some sort of big company reforming in 2015.
And this is sort of a big bombshell announcement.
And I got to wonder if when they reformed, if maybe something was in the works, a way
to try to get to profitability.
And they essentially say, if you don't want to pay, well, then you can use the one that's
based on Linux kernel 4.9.
It's an LTS kernel, and it'll last for quite a while, and you can just stay on that.
But if you want something new, you have to purchase a subscription.
Oh, what's the cost of that subscription?
Just ask us.
We're not putting it on the website.
Yeah.
It's funny.
You talk about corporate restructuring in open source projects.
That sounds familiar, doesn't it?
Trying to make a profit all of a sudden.
Yeah.
This is an interesting approach, though, because it's like you touched on.
It's taking GPLed software and saying you can't have access to it unless you pay a subscription.
And I don't think RMS would have a problem with that, necessarily.
But there is a contract agreement, I believe.
It's hard to get details, because there's only vague information online.
But it sounds like you have to agree that you will not redistribute GPLed software.
And if you do agree to that, and you still share the code with somebody, like you give
them some of the GR security software magic, they will terminate your contract.
So you can share it, because legally, they have to let you, since it's GPLed software,
but they'll punish you for it.
And it's really not in the spirit of open source and free software, this, is it?
Well, how is this different than what Red Hat does?
Well, Red Hat, the source is available.
You've got Centos.
You've got Scientific.
You've got Unbreakable.
The source is available, and it's just not the binaries.
Right.
Yes, that's true.
But in the same sense, though, they're distributing GPLed software that you pay for with the Red
Hat subscription.
And they are telling you not to redistribute that GPLed software, in some sense.
I agree.
It's not a good analogy.
And actually, Red Hat does make binaries available as well.
So the analogy doesn't quite hold up, but it's not, I would say, unprecedented that
there isn't some sort of contract that almost seems to override some inherent aspects of
the GPL.
Yeah, but even though it's legal what they're doing, probably, although there are some people
online who are kind of arguing that it's not.
But even if it is legal, which I think it is, it's just not in the spirit, is it?
The whole point of open source software is that you make your changes available to everyone.
They would argue that they're putting a lot of work into this, and they're seeing demand
to move over to ARM platforms.
They're seeing demand for Android protection and mobile in general.
And there's no funding to do that.
And there's demand.
People are deploying Linux on ARM systems.
They want GR security, and they want to deliver it.
I mean, what are they going to do?
They've got to make a buck.
Yeah, but that's the argument that kind of just falls down.
If you can't make money from it, then should you be in open source in the first place?
I don't know.
I mean, I can see why they want to charge money for it.
It's fine.
A lot of work goes into it.
But at the same time, they are taking something that has been contributed to by a lot of people
and is free to anyone.
And yeah, they're working on that.
And then they're not releasing their changes.
It's just not in the spirit of open source.
And I keep saying that because there's one thing to be within the rules and within the
law and the contracts and all the rest of it.
But to be in the spirit of open source, it just looks bad to me.
It feels too corporate.
And I suppose that's probably what they want.
They want to be corporate.
They want to make money, right?
Well, I mean, Richard Stallman doesn't have a problem with people making money off of
GPL software.
Here's where I'll give you something.
I don't know if I completely agree with you, but where I do kind of feel like they definitely
win against the whole spirit of the community is they've been around, they've been doing
this for like 16 years in one form or another.
They haven't been a corporation, I don't think, for that long.
But they've been a community, I think, for 16 years and doing this for free for 16 years.
And you got to ask yourself, at what point do you have to make some kind of change to
turn this thing around, to make it in from a hobby to a day job to make it sustainable,
to grow it?
But that, I think, is one conversation.
Then I think there's a second conversation, and this is where I'm going to give you some
ground here, is the second conversation, how they went about it.
How they went about this is rough.
It's brutal.
The change is effective the day of the post, April 26, 2017, that that post went online.
The change was immediate.
No more options, no warning, just done.
We're switching gears, enjoy your 4.9 based release, we're moving on.
And that, to me, that immediate kind of abruptness, no warning.
When you're talking enterprise installations, it's almost like they pulled the rug out from
underneath people and the only way to pick yourself back up is to subscribe.
In fact, they even talk about it in their frequently asked questions, where they say,
what do I do if I'm dependent on this?
They say, well, then you should probably subscribe.
You should probably.
Yeah.
At least what Canonical did with Ubuntu, changing to GNOME, if you want to stay on
community, at least you've got 16.04 for another four years, which you can make your plans.
Whereas this, exactly.
It just feels, it leaves a bad taste in my mouth, put it that way.
Yeah.
And it seems to be that there could have been a different route, there could have been a
different path to take here.
I didn't really follow GR security super closely before this because for myself, SE Linux or
AppArmor has always sort of done whatever I've needed.
But it is interesting to check it out.
You can go to grsecurity.net and if you want to know how it compares to SE Linux and AppArmor
and why I'm making that comparison, even though it's not exactly apt, you can find it at grsecurity.net
slash compare.php.
Everyone's favorite subject, secure boots in the news this week coming from Debian.
The final stretch of Debian 9 stretch is upon us.
And one of the revelations that's come out from that is secure boots been booted.
Yeah, Joe?
Well, it's considered no longer a blocker to release.
So it's not looking good for its inclusion straight away, put it that way.
So it's not that they're explicitly excluding it, it's that they're not going to let it
hold up the release.
So it could come after release then possibly, I would imagine.
Yeah, I would have thought so because yeah, it's kind of important, but they just don't
deem it important enough to stop the release.
And that's the question you have to ask yourself.
If you are capable of installing Debian and want to install Debian rather than one of
the more, well, I was going to say mainstream, but easier distros like Ubuntu, Fedora, that
kind of thing, are you really the kind of person who's going to worry about going into
your BIOS, well, your EFI and turning off secure boot?
I mean, it's not going to be an issue for someone like me.
I suppose it's dependent on who the target is because there are some servers that have
secure boot as well and enterprises potentially for security reasons would want to use secure
boot.
I don't really have the hate for secure boot that the entire Linux community apparently
has.
Having talked to some people that helped develop it, they seem to have very rational approaches
on it.
The Linux Foundation doesn't seem to have a big issue with it.
They don't even seem to have a big issue with Microsoft asking OEMs to include Microsoft
keys by default.
They say as long as it's consumer choice, they don't really seem to have a big issue
with it.
How do you feel?
Because to me, this seems like almost like a non-issue.
Secure boot, either it's on or off, almost doesn't seem like it matters to me.
Well, where it matters is with the kind of person who goes to their local electronics
store, buys a Windows laptop, uses it for a couple of years, it gets so slow that they
can't reliably use it anymore.
Then they start hearing about things like Linux Mint or Ubuntu, and they want to try
that out.
They follow some instructions, and then it won't boot because secure boot doesn't work.
That isn't going to be an issue with the more mainstream distributions.
Whereas with Debian, that's what I said at the beginning of this.
If you're the kind of person who's wanting to install Debian, then you're going to have
the technical skills to get into the EFI and turn off secure boot anyway.
For me, secure boot, I can't stand it.
It just gets in the way.
It makes it harder to boot Linux.
The first thing I do, I got a new laptop this week from entryware, and the first thing I
did was turn off secure boot, and then I've just never looked back, basically.
It's been working fine since then.
But the kind of person who isn't going to turn that off, that's why you need to have
support for it.
But for me, Debian, I don't think they need it.
It would be nice to have it, but I think it's justified to say it's not a blocker.
I agree, and I think you have a good point.
I do take your point.
And also, if you're the type of person that would probably be comfortable installing Debian
and turning on or off secure boot, you might also be someone who would be more inclined
to try dev1, the GNU slash Linux project that is Debian Jesse now without systemd, and they're
supporting new devices.
Are they going to get you, Joe?
Are they going to pull you in with their Chromebook support?
Well, not the Chromebook stuff, but the Raspberry Pi stuff, maybe, because dev1, to me, I didn't
think it would even get to a 1.0, and we're at release candidate two now, so we're almost
there.
Because to me, it just feels a bit irrelevant, because systemd, it's one.
There's no point trying to fight against it, and from my experience, I haven't really noticed
the difference.
I don't really get down and dirty with init scripts and stuff anyway, so as long as the
system boots, that's all I care about.
And in most cases, with systemd, it seems to boot faster.
Well, yeah, exactly.
So that's kind of a plus for me.
Yeah, although I started, you know, Joe, I started as a dev1 skeptic.
I made fun of the name a little bit, and I kind of thought it was a bunch of gray beards
that just wanted everybody off their lawn.
And I still don't quite grok all of the use cases for the project, but I'm starting to
see more of it, especially when it comes to lower-end devices with lower, maybe perhaps
some system memory.
But also, I think it could potentially be a really great distribution to base other
distributions off of that want to do very niche solutions, distros that are very targeted.
Dev1 could be a really great base distribution for those, too.
So as time goes on, I'm starting to respect the project a little more and more, and I
also got to respect the fact that they're nailing these releases.
You know, they're on their second release candidate just two weeks after the first release
candidate came out, and they're already talking about turning their attention to the ASCII
release, which is their current development branch, once Jessie's released.
So they really seem to have their t's crossed and their i's dotted.
Yeah, well, fair play to them, and choice is always good.
I don't think it's necessarily going to be something I'm going to choose on the desktop
or server, but what interests me is the fact that it's going to be available for a ton
of ARM devices, including the Raspberry Pi 1, 2, and 3.
And I have been pretty vocal in the past about not being a huge fan of Raspbian, the kind
of default Debian-based distro for the Raspberry Pi.
So maybe, dare I say it, a properly implemented Debian might be nice on the Pi.
And so it's something I'm keen to check out.
Only once we get a proper release, I'm going to check it out, and yeah, maybe I can report
back on it.
I have also been very, very interested in Google's SDK of Google Home, the whole Google
Assistant AI that you can now load on a Raspberry Pi.
And I'm not the only one that's kind of interested.
It looks like, is it MagPi that's putting together a kit, like a do-it-yourself kit
to create a really cheap Google Home?
Yeah, so the Raspberry Pi official magazine called the MagPi, which is funded and subsidized
by the Raspberry Pi Foundation, they have given away a few things in the past, including
the Raspberry Pi Zero, which was pretty amazing.
I mean, people were talking about, in my day, we used to get software disks given away with
magazines, and now we get a computer given away.
And now they've kind of upped it a little bit by giving away this kit, which is basically
a cardboard box, a speaker, and a button, and then the other necessary hardware to connect
to the Google SDK and get Google Assistant talking to you and interacting with you.
And the whole point of the Raspberry Pi Foundation is to get kids into computing.
And so on the one hand, I feel that this is a great thing, because you've got kids tinkering
with this stuff, and potentially Raspberry Pis that have been sitting in a drawer might
end up being brought out and actually used for this thing.
But then at the same time, I think, well, Google are kind of a big evil corporation,
and should the Raspberry Pi Foundation really be encouraging kids to get more enveloped
in that Google world, where everything's tempting because it's free and cool and shiny?
Yeah, but in the world, in the reality of Chromebooks, YouTube, and the Chrome browser,
I feel like that's probably the last worry.
In fact, one of the things I kind of thought was neat about it for the security-conscious
folks that are still curious, it doesn't have always-on listening.
You have to push the button.
So when you're not pushing the button, it can't hear you, which might be some folks'
preferred way to interact with a Google Assistant.
Well, that's what they tell you.
Yeah, maybe so.
I think the button press has to be used because that's what activates the microphones off
on the Raspberry Pi.
I don't remember the details.
Yeah, well, this kit comes with a microphone, and so, yeah, that makes sense.
But you can hook up any mic and speaker to any Raspberry Pi, and you can sort the software
out yourself.
So you're not limited to just this kit, but if you do get this kit, then it's free with
a magazine which is like four pounds or something, or five pounds, ridiculously cheap for what
you're getting.
And you wonder how much of that money is Google money and how much of it's Raspberry Pi money.
They've both got a few quid, I think.
Good point.
Also, you get at least a good project.
This is the thing with the Raspberry Pi for kids is I've always felt like it's great,
but you actually need something to accomplish that is desirable by the average person to
play with this.
Even if you and I might have concerns about the security implications of always listening
devices or assistance, to be able to say to a kid, you can assemble this box with this
little Linux computer in here, and then you can ask it questions and do Google searches,
that's actually an achievable thing that kids would want to get involved in, or actually,
let's be honest, even adults.
And so I do like that aspect of it.
I'm not totally sold.
I would love to say I would love to be doing a story that was a Mycroft box, and you came
with all the kit you needed, and it was just a really great, super responsive Mycroft box.
We're not there yet.
We're just not there.
The Google Assistant is a real product.
The SDK came out recently.
You can set up yourself, or you can get a kit like this.
And I think it's actually going to get people to get their hands on these things.
I think it's going to be a huge hit.
Man, Mycroft.
That was the word that I just kept thinking about, Mycroft.
And the next word was, why?
Why don't we have that yet?
Where are you?
I don't know, everyone had such good hopes for that, and here we are.
They still haven't delivered.
The opportunity's lost now, surely.
You've got Alexa.
I mean, the thing is, even the real hardcore open source people that I know, like you and
Wimpy and Poppy and those kind of people, you've all bought Echoes now.
You've kind of just given up on that whole Mycroft thing.
You know what else?
He'd probably kill me for saying this.
But if you ask him, he'd admit it.
Noah is looking at the Echo 2 now.
He can connect it to his offline home automation system and use it as the voice bridge.
And he was obviously a skeptic, but then working in the studio throughout the last week and
using it to-
He sold him on it.
To control the studio.
It did.
It sold him on it.
And you see the benefits of it, especially when you're moving stuff around and working
with equipment.
And so there is something to it.
And you could, the Google Assistant in the Raspberry Pi can connect all the same services
and APIs and control your lights and all of that in that little cardboard box.
And somehow, I don't know, I'd probably prefer Google than Amazon somehow.
I don't know why.
Really?
Yeah.
I don't know why that is.
I just don't really like Amazon.
I think the lack of taxpaying and stuff like that.
Yeah.
I have those concerns too.
I mean, they're the Walmart of the internet for sure, but I find their motivation understandable.
They want to put a storefront in my house and they want to sell me goods from their
website that I buy goods from.
But Google has a totally different motivation for putting an assistant in a Raspberry Pi
or in a tube.
And that is data collection.
And they're already experimenting with the advertisements.
So if you can ask these assistants, you can ask all these ladies in a tube, what's going
on?
What's new?
What's the report?
And they'll start kicking off your different news feeds and give you a verbal reading of
what's going on in whatever news feeds you follow.
And then now what they're just doing is they're slipping in an ad for a movie, also playing
today at a theater near you, and it's a paid ad that they're just slipping into the feed
now.
You can already see the trajectory that they're going with the Google assistant.
So for me, when I look at the motivations, it seems like Amazon's probably the most trustworthy.
I don't even want to say it.
I can't even say it.
Well, you can trust them to be a company that's selling things, whereas Google, what do they
sell in advertising?
It's kind of a little bit shadier, isn't it?
Yeah.
Amazon just wants to sell you shoes.
I want to take a moment and thank DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux Action News.
DigitalOcean.com.
Go there, sign up, and use our promo code.
Here's the thing.
Oh, Joe, we've got to come up with a new promo.
We'll think about that.
But for right now, go retro.
Here's the thing.
You create an account and you apply to DigitalOcean.
DigitalOcean is an easy way to spin up a server on their infrastructure.
They call them droplets.
I call them magic, and they have a great interface to manage it.
Really nice services.
And Joe, have you seen DigitalOcean's documentation?
It's like ArchWiki good.
Yeah.
I use it all the time for all kinds of stuff, yeah.
It's a really convenient way.
Once you get a system set up, they have one-click deployments of an entire application stack,
or you can just do a base system and then go read the documentation.
It's really top-notch.
They're also rolling out high CPU droplets, so if you just need a ton of CPU power, they're
rolling that out.
You can get early access right now.
They've recently rolled out monitoring.
They have block storage.
You can get a machine spun up in less than 55 seconds, and if you use our promo code,
here's the thing.
You can try out the $5 rig, two months for free, and you're voting for the new show,
which we really appreciate that.
Let our sponsors know that you're still listening.
Go over to DigitalOcean.com, use our promo code, here's the thing.
Spin up a droplet on their incredible infrastructure with 40 gigabit e-connections, SSDs for all
of the storage, and maybe some ponies.
DigitalOcean.com, promo code, here's the thing.
Okay, let's talk about Nexus phones and devices, shall we?
This is a story that I've seen floating around this week, and it wasn't really news to me,
but it seems that it is news to quite a lot of people, and that is that you basically
get about three years of support with a Nexus device for official ROMs from Google.
Well, three years if you're lucky, really, because if you buy a Nexus device, say, nine
months to a year into its release, which is not unusual because sometimes the Nexus devices
or Pixel devices are actually very hard to get your hands on because Google doesn't seem
to make enough of them.
And so if you buy them nine months, a year into release, the phone will stop receiving
updates before your carrier agreement is up.
Yeah, which isn't very good, is it?
As somebody who's bought just about every Nexus, just about, this is something I've
definitely noticed, and it does sting a little bit because I thought that was the point of
the Nexus program, was to keep getting updates directly from Google, and I was surprised
when little things like a contract with Broadcom expired, so they just stopped shipping updates.
That surprised me when that happened.
And I used to tell myself that this was fine because the Nexus devices, like the 5 and
the 5X, are reasonably cheap compared to other smartphones on the market.
And so if I have to replace them somewhat more frequently, in the end, it's probably
about the same cost.
However, now with the Pixel phones being $700, $800, that whole math has changed now.
Yeah, and we're talking about three years here, that is the security updates.
The major versions of Android are only two years for the 6P, the 5X, the 9, the 6, and
the 5 even.
Yeah, and let's be honest, I actually care more about that than I even do security.
I mean, I want my security updates too, but...
Yeah.
I mean, the thing is that the phones are not completely useless without the security updates,
and let's face it, billions of people or billions of devices out there running, you know, the
cheaper ones, Samsung and other OEMs, that basically you buy the device and never get
a single update.
People are happily using them, logging into their bank and all the rest of it.
So it's not like it gets bricked after three years, but yeah, you'd think that coming straight
from Google, and I mean, the thing is that if you buy a laptop running Windows, how many
years are you expecting to get in terms of security updates with that?
I don't know, seven maybe?
I mean, I would think.
Yeah.
I mean, XP got like 10, you know?
So in theory, you can buy a laptop or you used to be able to buy a laptop, a computing
device, which let's face it, phones and tablets are as well, and you could get at least five,
six, seven plus years of security updates, right?
Whereas now with these ARM devices, because it's so difficult to update them because they're
all unique and they all need their unique ROM and drivers and all rest of it, that you
get these situations where the kind of shining poster child for updates, the Nexus series,
are only getting three years.
I mean, thankfully you've got custom ROMs and that's something that I have been into
for a long time because I don't want all of the Google stuff.
I want some of the Google stuff, but Open GApps Pico for the win is all I would say
there.
You get the Play Store and that's it, and then you can build that up.
You can install whatever you want, and I'm hoping that my Nexus 9 and my Nexus 7 will
continue to be supported with security updates.
Right now they're basically up to date, but if you're the kind of person who's not into
doing that kind of stuff and flashing ROMs and just wants stock, then you're just out
of luck basically.
Well, and that's really, that's really not saying the majority of the market is an understatement
really.
That is the market.
It is such a niche to do this custom ROMs.
That's why I sort of wince when it even is brought up because it's so often an excuse
for what to me seems to be inadequate customer support.
The iPhone 5, I mean, I don't mean to make this comparison, but the iPhone 5 and the
iPad 4 released in 2012, still getting updates, still getting fixes.
Well my friend just upgraded from a 4S to a 7 and she was still getting security updates.
Yeah.
I'm not saying that should be for all Android phones, it just doesn't seem scalable with
the multi-vendor model, but for Pixel devices and Nexus devices, it seems like that would
be reasonable.
So if you're wondering, the Pixel phones that are on the market right now will stop getting
updates in October 2018.
Which is not very far off, is it?
Yeah.
And then I think you get like security for another year after that.
So you know, take it for what it is, I guess.
At least you know going in, I suppose now.
That was the other thing, Joe, really, is this wasn't really official official.
Like it was not really quite clear for many years with the Nexus program.
So at least now we have some numbers, we have some expectations to be said.
Well they kind of said two and three years, but it had always been from the last time
it was available.
Whereas now we've got some actual, as you say, in numbers.
September 2017, September 2018, that kind of stuff.
So at least people know where they are now.
But maybe it'll drive people to custom ROMs, and maybe even in a dream world, not installing
the Google stuff on there, but yeah, F-Droid and stuff, maybe a better dream on that one.
And maybe convergence will take off, and we'll all be running Ubuntu on our phones.
Oh wait.
Oh well, you never know with Maru, they've got proper conversions.
Maybe so, maybe so.
And at least we'll all be able to play and encode MP3s.
So that's good.
Yeah, so there's been quite a hoo-ha about this, the final MP3 patents running out.
And even Fedora now is adding full MP3 support.
So you could previously decode, so you can play back your MP3s, but now you can even
encode, or you will be able to on Fedora, which is kind of a sign to me that a legal
team as big as Red Hat have got, seem to think it's fine.
So therefore it must be, right?
Yeah.
Well, and to me, the big signal was that the folks that originally held some of the licensing
posted on their website, essentially saying, have at it.
And I thought, OK, that's a pretty clear communication.
It's still not free software fully.
I mean, it's free as in cost, and it's free as in speech, but it's not open source code.
But here's my question to you.
Is this enough?
And is this going to be the death of Ogg?
Could be.
Could be, because, yeah, I suppose now that you don't have to worry about MP3.
But then again, is this not a sign that MP3 is a defunct format?
I mean, it's basically ubiquitous at this point.
Yeah, that was actually what they implied when they posted it.
Was it Fraha?
How do you say their name, Joe?
Do you know?
The Fraunhofer?
Fraunhofer?
I would say Fraunhofer.
OK.
So they essentially said on their blog, yeah, we're done.
We're over MP3.
There's other things we're moving on to.
There's other better stuff out there.
And we have plenty of patents on those things.
But there's probably petabytes of MP3 sitting on various people's hard drives and NASes
and stuff.
Oh, for sure.
For sure.
And the reality is, when I asked you about the Ogg thing, the reason why I asked is we've
recently, for our new shows, been doing a whole new renovation on the back end.
And that includes moving to different hosting providers for our files and doing a lot of
market research.
And Joe, in my market research, what I found was that MP3 is the de facto supported format
everywhere.
And if a platform like Libsyn or another one has support, it's sort of like hacked on.
And if they do have a secondary format support, it's almost always M4A, AAC Audio.
And Joe, these companies, their entire business is hosting podcasts.
That's what they do.
And they don't have Ogg support.
And this is not one of these many companies.
They simply don't have Ogg support.
They maybe, maybe have AAC support.
And they definitely have MP3 support.
So in the podcasting world, it's getting harder.
It's getting harder to distribute Ogg files.
It's costing more because you have to build your own hosting solutions.
And if you have a lot of downloads, it gets expensive.
Yeah, well, hopefully this will mean that people will stop complaining, why don't you
have an Ogg?
Why don't you have an Ogg?
Because MP3 is relatively free now.
Yeah.
Can we all just move on to Opus?
I want everybody asking, where's the Opus?
Where's the Opus?
What about Speaks?
Yeah, where's Speaks?
I want Opus, Speaks.
I want it in VP9, too.
Just I want to take an image file and encode it in VP9 with a Theora audio track.
Why not?
I don't know.
I don't know if we're going there.
Let's face it, Chris.
We should be putting this out in FLAC.
Right.
That's the only format that matters.
I agree.
We can only do it for two minutes, though.
We have to make it a two-minute show.
That way it fits.
Yeah.
Well, that does bring us to the end of our first episode, episode zero of Linux Action
News.
You can find us online at linuxactionnews.com, where you'll find RSS feeds, links to add
it to your favorite podcast player.
And of course, you'll find it in our Jupyter broadcasting feeds.
You can go to linuxactionnews.com for all of that stuff.
Click also links to the things we talked about.
And you can follow me on Twitter.
I'm at Chris LAS.
And I'm at Joe Ressington.
Linux Action News is a weekly show, so be sure you get that RSS feed.
That's it for this week.
Thanks so much for joining us.
And we'll see you next time.
Goodbye.
See you later.