Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 227, recorded on February 9th, 2022.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Let's do the news.
And we start this week with the industry's biggest story.
That is, the collapse of the $66 billion sale of SoftBank's ARM business to NVIDIA.
The deal fell through after regulators around the world raised some serious concerns about
the effects on competition in the semiconductor industry.
Don't feel too bad for SoftBank, though.
They're going to receive a $1.25 billion breakup fee.
They also still appear to have some plans to perhaps take ARM public.
And there's some management upheaval in work.
So I'm sure we'll see some stories about that as well.
It seems a lot of people had concerns about this merger, as ARM was kind of viewed as
the Switzerland of the semiconductor industry, if you will, meaning that they dealt pretty
evenly with all of their 500 plus license holders, regardless of country or company.
I think a quote from Greg Rowe, head of research at Hyundai Motor Securities, really emphasizes
this with him saying, quote, there's a chip war going on around the world.
So many weren't very welcoming of such a key architecture firm going to the US.
Countries are competitively trying to build up their chip industries and will try to defend
against that chip technology moving to another country.
Well as the Steam Deck gets closer, we're watching the last minute developments closely.
And Ferronix has the details on a new deck driver that's landed for the Linux kernel.
It was posted last weekend and it's really a kitchen sink platform driver that adds support
for the Steam Deck specific embedded controller in there.
A controller is responsible for a whole swath of things like CPU fan control, battery temperature
measurements, display related settings, even USB-C event notifications.
As you might expect, this driver was developed by engineers over at Valve and specifically
Andrey Smirnov, who's an engineer hired back in 2018 to work specifically on kernel projects
for Valve.
So it's interesting seeing that hire pay some dues here.
Now given the timing of this patch, it's not expected to be merged until sometime in the
Linux 5.18 cycle, which doesn't kick off until late March.
But it's not actually critical functionality if you want to play around and use other Linux
distributions on the deck.
It's just nice to have.
And Valve's Arch Linux based Steam OS is expected to be relying on a patched kernel at least
initially.
So all the functionality should work for early Steam Deck holders.
Regardless of all those details, honestly, it's just kind of nice to see Valve getting
maybe not quite ahead of the ball, but keeping up and working with upstream.
I mean, that's what we expect, right?
So this week, we saw the announcement of the Open Source Firmware Foundation.
They're getting set up with the hopes of expanding open source firmware usage throughout the
entire industry.
Their founding members are Nine Element Cyber Security and Molvad VPN.
Yeah, that last one's interesting.
But hey, I'm a fan of open firmware, that's for sure.
Now, obviously, this was just announced, so it's early days.
But if you head over to osfw.foundation, you'll find that, quote, the foundation sets its
goals to research and to educate corporations and individuals alike about open source firmware,
through sharing intellectual resources, infrastructure, services, events, and training.
The OSFF is meant to be an umbrella organization for all parties interested in open source
firmware and acts as the first point of contact in the open source firmware ecosystem.
Yeah, so they're really about adoption throughout the industry, right?
Like, we don't see LVFS listed anywhere on here.
It's not necessarily about the software bits, it's more about getting the rest of the industry
to use open source firmware.
But if you like your foundations, well, I got good news for you.
Because FreeCAD also has a foundation.
That's right, the FreeCAD project has a legal nonprofit organization around it now, Long
Live FreeCAD.
Well, speaking of big organizations making big changes, Intel has announced that they're
joining the RISC-V international organization as a premier member.
And while they already have their RISC-V based Neos V processors, Intel isn't necessarily
planning anything as radical as replacing X86 with RISC-V in the short term.
But it is making this move to invest in the RISC-V ecosystem for the long term.
And of course, hopefully lure a few customers to the Intel Foundry services.
Yeah, those Foundry services is probably what this is really about, right?
But it seems like a pretty significant shift for them to double down on their investment
like this.
And in today's announcement, they also touch on funding some open source software development.
They write, quote, today Intel announced several immediate RISC-V community benefits led by
Intel's Foundry services or IFS for short, IFS will sponsor an open source software development
platform that allows for freedom and experimentation, including partners across the ecosystem, universities
and consortia.
So it seems that Intel is making a big push here.
Maybe one day we'll look at Intel as one of the premier manufacturers of RISC-V systems.
I don't know.
I'd love to see it.
If you haven't been paying attention lately, you might have missed a major new feature
that's in the works for ZFS and we happen to have an update for you this week.
We first mentioned RAID-Z expansion way back in June in Linux Action News 194, but since
then it seems that ZFS co-creator Matt Arends has been hard at work.
For those of you that might not have listened to episode 194, one major expensive pain point
of ZFS has always been its lack of support for expanding storage of an existing setup.
The unofficial answer has always kind of been that hey, ZFS was built to protect your data,
not do it on the cheap.
RAID-Z expansion though would change all that by allowing disks to be added one at a time
to an existing RAID-Z VDEV, expanding its capacity incrementally.
Now that might be especially useful for those of you out there with small pools that only
have one VDEV, where maybe there isn't sufficient hardware to add capacity by adding a whole
new VDEV when you want to upgrade, which might involve doubling the number of disks.
That's something I know we've run into while trying to plan out studio builds and either
not having the disks at hand or not really having the storage capacity available.
But with the new patch you'll finally be able to attach new disks to an existing RAID-Z
VDEV.
Whether or not that's the way you want to go, that we leave up to you.
We've both been looking forward to this, and I saw that there was an update recently on
the FreeBSD Foundation website, so where are we at now with this upgrade?
Yeah, we did get an update there this week, because well, they're a sponsor of this work,
which I'm very grateful for.
And I'm also grateful that it seems like things are going quite well.
All the planned capabilities have been implemented, and all the tests are passing.
Now there is still some code cleanup to do, verbose logging to remove, code documentation
to write, that sort of thing.
But even with those remaining tasks, the aim is to have this feature integrated sometime
in Q3.
If you're as excited as we are, we should also note that as with many open source projects,
the biggest need right now is for more help testing.
I've always had an uneasy sense of the big three hyperscalers out there.
I don't like all of the reasons they're in the market, I don't like how they can leverage
their position to change things in the market, and I don't like their interfaces, and the
sense of lock-in that I get when I try to use those big hyperscalers.
And I'm not the only one, in fact devops.com just published this, 20% of developers out
there believe that the big three hyperscalers are going to engage in behaviors that will
leverage their brands that will stifle competition.
That doesn't feel good, I don't like the way that sits.
There's a lot of reasons to choose cloud providers out there, and there's a lot of cloud providers,
but none of them are like Linode.
They've been around for nearly 19 years, they're independently funded, they have 11 data centers
around the world, and they have a real simple product.
They get value out of trying to make it really good.
Their whole thing is just to make a great product, back it up with the best support
in the business.
They're not trying to leverage their whole industrial shipping side of their business
to push a cloud computing thing and subsidize it in this weird way that just isn't really
a genuine product, is it?
Now, I know every platform has its place, but I think Linode is one that's worth your
consideration.
It's incredibly powerful, it has fantastic performance, and the pricing's 30 to 50% less
than some of the hyperscalers out there.
And if you're an individual that just wants to do a project, you want to run a blog, have
a gaming server, or maybe you're a small business, you want to do a little bit of collaboration,
I really personally believe there's nothing better than Linode.
So go try it out and get $100, you can really, truly kick the tires, linode.com slash lan.
And of course, linux.ting.com, a big thank you to Ting.
Hey, do you hear the phone ringing?
It's Common Sense calling, and it's time to check out Ting.
Seriously, if you live in the States, you've got to go to linux.ting.com, go see how much
you could save, and then take $25 off that when you visit linux.ting.com.
You see, Ting is a mobile virtual network operator.
That means Ting customers get access to the big carrier networks, the nation to nation,
coast to coast LTE 5G networks, but you're dealing with Ting, a reasonable company that's
a reasonable size with great support, and no contracts, and there's really no other
way to say it.
Ting plans that just make sense, it is smarter mobile for sure.
That's why I've been a customer since 2013.
And every single Ting plan gets access to their award-winning customer service, nationwide
LTE and 5G, and no contract ever.
How great is that?
Plus, I think the other thing that's really nice is you could switch to Ting in an evening.
It's really simple, and because of their multi-network support, pretty much any phone's gonna work
on Ting, so you might not even have to get a new phone.
Head to linux.ting.com, take a look, they do offer phones directly, or you can bring
your own.
You put your phone info into their system, they'll tell you if it's compatible or not,
likely gonna be, and when it is, they'll send you a SIM card, you pop that in, within a
few minutes after you get the SIM and you get it in your phone, you're gonna be activated.
Their dashboard is super straightforward, really easy, you can get everything going
in minutes.
When I signed up for Ting back in 2013, I think I did it at like 10.30 at night, in
my home office, when everybody else was in bed, and I wouldn't have done it if I had
to talk to a human, I just wanted to get it done online that night, and I got everything
done online with Ting, I was really impressed, and then the couple of times where I got kind
of stuck, both times when I was on a road trip actually, the Ting customer support really
came through.
They won't leave you stranded, they'll really take care of you, it's pretty great.
So go to linux.ting.com, support the show, and take 25 bucks off what Ting's got to offer
at linux.ting.com.
This week, the KDE community released Plasma 5.24, a long-term support release that will
receive updates and bug fixes until the final version of Plasma 5.
It's been just a short four months since the previous release, 5.23, which came out in
October 2021, but that shorter time frame has not stopped the project from packing this
release full of goodies.
Right off the top, let's mention KRunner, which is definitely one of my favorite parts
of the Plasma desktop.
Now, it's great and has plenty of updates in 5.24, but what really stood out to me is
a new feature that teaches you all the power that exists in KRunner, because now, you can
just click and explore the plugins that exist to get an idea of how you can actually use
them.
Also landing in 5.24 is support for fingerprint readers, well, assuming you've got all the
hardware enablement bits sorted out, now Plasma will play nicely too.
Discover has also gotten a bit smarter, especially around what packages it does, or crucially,
does not let you uninstall, hopefully preventing folks who don't quite know what they're doing
from breaking their system.
Also nice to see in Discover, while it has supported Flatpaks for a long time, that support
is improving in 5.24.
You can now install locally downloaded Flatpak packages, and Discover will figure things
out and sync up the backend repositories for those Flatpaks automatically.
That is nice to see.
A lot of feature improvements or tweaks are in that category of nice to see.
So many that we really couldn't touch on all of them, but I did want to touch on a couple
of the visual improvements, because these are equally as impressive.
To give you a couple of examples here, they've tweaked the way Plasma notifications look
now.
Critical notifications stand out with an orange strip on the side of them to visually
distinguish them from like a less urgent message.
Love that.
The breeze theme, always looking good, but looking absolutely great now with some nice
refinements.
You can now select custom accent colors, and it just looks great throughout.
They've implemented the free desktop spec for dark mode.
So if you have a third party application that also follows that spec, and you use dark mode,
everything's going to look great.
Widgets have received some nice new features, like how they get deployed and all of that.
And there's been some cleanup on how you navigate all of them.
On the desktop side of things, there is a nice new wallpaper in Plasma 5.24, but if
you happen to prefer something else, you can now set your wallpaper pretty easily just
by right clicking on any picture in Dolphin and hitting set as wallpaper.
Or if you want to get a little more creative, you can use the picture of the day wallpaper
plugin, which can now pull images from Simon Stollenhug's gallery, which you may recognize
as a whole bunch of cool and a little bit creepy sci-fi images as seen in Tales from
the Loop.
Another small, but I think important visual enhancement this time around is that video
notifications, that is notifications about video files, well, they now display a thumbnail
of the actual video, just like you'd expect for image files.
And just because maybe we have to a little bit about Wayland, the Wayland journey for
Plasma is definitely a long one, but the march continues.
This time around, something that stood out to me is that Spectacle, the KDE Screenshot
tool, well, it finally has access to that active window mode that's been missing.
And they're making good progress on catching up the keyboard shortcuts that only work in
X11 and getting those gradually implemented on the Wayland side.
The project obviously put a lot of care in making sure this was a really nice LTS release,
but something that didn't really get listed in any of the features, but I absolutely noticed
right away is this release has definitely felt faster in terms of performance on my
machine than the last few releases.
Like I feel like I kind of got an upgraded computer with this release, and I know I touched
on it earlier, but the breeze theme is so dang good now that I keep the default theme
with Plasma.
Like you go back like maybe a year and a half, and the first thing I was doing on a new Plasma
desktop was tweaking the theme and the way it looks and spending a couple of hours getting
that right.
And now, now I'm using the defaults.
It feels like the team has just put a ton of work into that kind of stuff.
And so all in all, this just feels like a release that is absolutely worth checking
out.
It is available via Plasma Neon right now, that's how I tried it out earlier, and it'll
be coming to a distro near you soon.
And we hope next week's episode is something you'll consider checking out too, so go to
linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact to let us know what we got wrong.
Are you ready for a new podcast app?
Check out newpodcastapps.com, grab one that supports value and help keep podcasting decentralized.
As for us, well, we'll be back next week with our take on the latest Linux and open source
news.
Thanks for joining us.
And that's all the news for this week.