Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 242, recorded on May 25th, 2022.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Let's do the news.
We start this week with an almost cliché kernel release from Linus Torvalds, announcing
Linux 5.18.
Linus wrote in the 5.18 announcement, no unexpected nasty surprises this last week.
So here we go with the 5.18 release right on schedule.
And that obviously means that the merge window for 5.19 will open tomorrow.
No surprises, perhaps, but there have been some controversial additions.
5.18 brings the first wave of support for Intel's software-defined silicon, or SDSI,
functionality.
The purpose of which is to disable access to specific processor capabilities in the
absence of a certificate from Intel saying otherwise.
Yeah, my brain almost has a hard time believing the words coming out of your mouth, Wes, but
it is all true, and it's all GPL.
So that's good, right?
No, it leaves us feeling uneasy.
But here's what we do know.
David Box, who submitted the patch set, he made at least one aspect of this clear.
The interface to the mechanism itself is relatively simple.
It's not like Intel's doing anything weird on your Linux box.
What happens is this system appears as a device on the bus that offers a couple of operations.
Install an authentication key certificate or a capability activation payload.
So the certificate is used to authenticate any request to enable a feature, while the
payload actually contains the requests themselves.
And unless this device has been used to store an acceptable certificate and payload, the
features that it governs will be unavailable to software that is running on this new Intel
CPU.
This new SDSI hardware also maintains a couple of counters that it uses to track how many
times you've tried and failed to load a certificate or enable a feature.
And well, if you exceed the threshold for those counters, the mechanism will be disabled
entirely.
No new shiny features for you, unless you power cycle your box.
Yep, and Intel says this is great because it's a system that enables shipping cheaper
CPUs with features that could be of interest to users down the road, but are just unavailable
until the additional payments are made.
Um, yeah, I mean, to be clear at this stage, we don't really know what those features
are going to be.
So that will be worth waiting for.
But we do know at this point, the Linux support should be ready.
And as for me, well, I'll be ready to vote with my wallet.
Looking ahead to Linux 5.19, butterFS users are in for a fresh treat.
David Sterba of SUSE has submitted almost 4000 lines of code with some exciting new
features from one of our favorite file systems.
Indeed, and surprise, surprise, performance has been the focus of a lot of this patch
set.
Probably the fruits of a lot of low level code optimizations by various groups at SUSE,
Facebook, and some other large supporters.
What are you getting for all that effort?
Well, starting in 5.19, butterFS will now avoid blocking on space reservation.
That's a change that should see about a 7% throughput improvement for both reads and
writes.
There's also been some improvements to locking code when you're using the no copy on write
option.
That's about a 3% throughput performance improvement.
And there's a nice to see improvement in the butterFS send code.
They've reduced pressure on the page cache there by dropping extent pages sooner.
The list just keeps going on here.
We're not going to go into all of them here on the show, but it's well worth checking
out in the notes.
And I've got to think, you add up all these small little pieces, it's going to be some
performance improvements you can feel.
Yeah, how often does that happen?
Everything gets created, and then each release, it just gets better and faster.
I mean, I feel like at this point, butterFS is becoming one of the better turnaround stories
in free software.
It's really gotten good.
And it's just great to see that the network effect of its adoption is really paying off.
If you haven't tried out butterFS for a laptop install, maybe a Raspberry Pi, it's worth
a go.
Alan's Christoph Steiner, aka ATAF, shared a noteworthy update this week on the F-Droid
infrastructure.
It included some nice improvements for developers submitting apps, and just for us end users.
Absolutely.
And for those of you out of the loop, F-Droid is a free alternative to Google Play.
It's something focused on free software.
You could perhaps load it on a device that has no Google services, and more and more
apps are co-publishing in F-Droid, or perhaps some apps are only publishing there.
As you can imagine, running something like this over time, it sort of gets built organically,
and it requires a big pile of automation to manage the process of building thousands of
apps from source.
Yeah.
I mean, think about that for a moment.
You got to check out the source repos for all of those apps, you got to check to see
if they've been updated, you got to actually go through and build them, make a new release,
securely sign them, that's pretty tricky as well.
And then, of course, make sure that they get put into your test infrastructure, spin up
a virtual machine, make sure that they still work.
And yeah, all of that has sort of been built over the many years F-Droid has existed, and
it's all running on Debian.
But no, not the latest release of Debian.
Of course not.
It's an old install of Debian, like five years old Debian Stretch, I think.
Yeah, is that old in Debian terms?
I think it's getting there.
You can understand, right?
Because upgrading to more recent releases, that's not like a simple app-get upgrade.
It's a lot more complicated, and the project says they also need to overhaul their build
process to get there.
And that's tricky, because they really need to provide a platform to build those thousands
of apps.
They can't just upgrade the base image as often as they might like.
Ain't that the truth?
But work is underway, even if it's going to take some time.
Thankfully though, this is nice to see.
Kallax Institute, who builds Kallax OS in F-Droid, they're sponsoring 42 hours a month
of time dedicated to improving the build infrastructure and improving automation more generally.
And you developers out there, well, you'll be happy to hear that the outcome of some
of this process should be faster application submission and improved signing automation.
That maybe opens up some possibilities for parallelizing the whole thing submission process.
Google has announced the Summer of Code 2022 project winners, and the list actually includes
more than a few names that you probably know.
Debug Point News has done a nice job of listing out the ones most folks would be interested
in, but there were a few that stood out to us, including FFmpeg, Google sponsoring some
work on a high-throughput JPEG 2000 decoder, as well as some work to enable CUDA C++ support.
Another lucky project this year is Debian, where the primary focus is going to be trying
to complete the Android SDK in Debian's packaging base.
Well, you got to have that.
There's also some summer fun coming to Tor, LibreOffice, the GNOME Desktop.
One that I thought was interesting is it looks like there's a project to sync GNOME Health
app with Apple Health, Nextcloud, and other apps.
I don't think I even knew there was a GNOME Health app, so that's interesting.
There's also a project to add Chromecast support to GNOME Network Display.
Yes, please.
I know, right?
Yeah, I think they have Miracast now, and really just several other nice-to-see things
for GNOME, some Nautilus stuff, but don't worry, Plasma's getting some summer fun too
if you're a desktop of the Plasma-variety user.
Nothing too exciting though, nothing that really jumped out at me, but we will have the full
breakdown and a link to the Debug Point news article in our show notes, because it's not
just those projects.
There's a bunch of others getting some love, like Xorg, GIMP, VLC, etc., so go to linuxactionnews.com
slash 242 for a link to that.
Well, we all knew it would happen eventually.
This week, Canonical announced that Ubuntu 22.10, which is shipping in the fall, will
switch to Pipewire by default as its audio server.
Now technically we should note here that Ubuntu already includes Pipewire, 2204 LTS for instance
ships with both Pipewire and PulseAudio installed.
But it's mainly included for Wayland compatibility, you know, all that fancy new stuff, and not
in use currently as the default server.
But starting with the next release, that finally changes.
Linode dot com slash LAN.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account, and that's where you go to support
the show.
Linode offers options for developers and businesses that don't want the complexities of hyperscalers
and don't need their endless options either.
You know they're always trying to lock you into their esoteric platform, and I feel like
Linode is the jetpack for my business.
Seriously, it lets me compete with the likes of Spotify.
I can deliver an on par experience with Linode's infrastructure at pricing that my business
can actually afford.
And their pricing is 30 to 50% cheaper than the major hyperscalers out there.
And they've been doing this for nearly 19 years, iterating on making the best platform
to run your applications.
Everything we've built in the last couple of years, we built it on Linode.
And we've learned that they have the best customer support in the business.
And this is the number one signal I hear from the audience.
Hey Chris, yeah they got me with the performance, but then I had this problem and the support
was unbelievable.
Tier one support, when you pick up the phone or you send them a message or a ticket, $3.65
a year they're working on it for you.
And on top of that, they just have some of the best performance with 11 data centers
around the world.
They are their own ISP, so they have just the fantastic, bestest internet ever.
It's so much fun to mess around with, I have to say.
And then they have great features that we use, like object storage, their cloud firewall,
their backups, and so much more.
And the dashboard makes managing all of this straightforward and simple.
So if you're just looking for a portfolio or a gaming server, they can do that.
But if you're looking to run the back end of your business and you want to scale up
to millions of users, yeah, they absolutely do that as well.
Go build something, go try something, go learn something, and support the show.
Go to linode.com slash LAN, get that $100 in 60 day credit, and go kick the tires for
yourself while you support the show, linode.com slash LAN.
And a tremendous thank you to Ting for their sponsorship of Linux Action News, linux.ting.com.
Are you sick of overpaying for your cell service?
Yeah, go see how much you could save and then take $25 off of that when you go to linux.ting.com.
Ting is a mobile virtual network operator.
That means they focus on the customer relationship, the value, and they ride on top of the existing
network built by the big mega nationwide carriers.
You know who I'm talking about, and Ting utilizes their networks, the same fast LTE and 5G,
but you interface with Ting, who was recently named the number one carrier by Consumer Reports,
and you save a bunch of money.
Their plans are simple and straightforward, and there's no contracts ever.
And Ting's customer service, of course, it's up there, and those little things all come
together, like simple plans, great pricing, network access, multiple network access I
might add, support, all of it just comes together to create a fantastic experience.
That's why I've been a Ting customer since 2013, for reals.
Go check them out.
The linux.ting.com plans that are really competitively priced and easy to understand, and if you
ever get stuck, they'll help you.
And you can do it all online, and pretty much any phone's going to work with Ting, so just
head to linux.ting.com, check your current phone, create an account, and pick the plan
that's right for you, linux.ting.com.
And we end this week on a rumor that could change the industry.
Bloomberg and others are reporting that within the next week, Rodcom could announce an agreement
to acquire VMware, at least according to people familiar with the matter.
Absolutely a big deal, and you'll recall in 2016 Dell acquired EMC, which owned VMware
at the time, for an historic $67 billion, still one of the largest acquisitions in tech
history.
And after five years of being part of Dell, VMware was then spun out in November of 2021
with an agreement to continue to work together with Dell for the next five years.
Now also along with that, Dell CEO Michael Dell owns approximately 41% of VMware.
He plays a critical role still at the company as chairman of the board of VMware, so he's
going to have a say in whatever happens here.
And VMware currently has a market valuation of around $50.3 billion.
The takeover discussions are ongoing, but there's also no guarantee that the talks actually
lead to an agreement.
Representatives for the two companies didn't immediately respond to requests for comment.
But the Wall Street Journal does note that the bid could be around $140 a share or totaling
$60 billion.
Wow.
I mean, $60 billion is a lot.
No getting around that, but it's interesting because it's not really what Dell originally
paid for VMware back in the day.
Dell's chief executive officer, Pat Gelsinger, told Bloomberg TV he has mixed feelings about
the potential acquisition.
And he does have some standing to comment.
Gelsinger was VMware CEO for eight years before recently returning to Intel.
First it's a rumor.
You know, I'm, you know, happily reading the newspapers like you on that.
But you know, for us, you know, I, you know, I'm excited about VMware being an innovative
partner for the future.
And any potential transaction for them, I'd want to make sure that innovation is alive
and well.
And while that's not a strong condemnation or really a strong endorsement, I would say
as far as CEO speak goes, it's rather bearish on the idea overall.
That's probably reflective of how we're all feeling right about now.
Of course, VMware is also a platinum member of the Linux Foundation.
So whatever happens here could impact that.
A platinum member pays around the tune of $500,000 a year for the title.
So we're going to keep an eye on this and everything else happening in the world of
Linux and open source news because there will be knock on effects.
So be sure you go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch.
And don't miss the new show Office Hours at officehours.hair.
It's a podcast made just for the Jupiter broadcasting community.
If you're not a J.B. listener, don't tune in.
It's not recommended for you.
OfficeHours.hair.
But hey, you can still find this show back every single week with the latest Linux and
open source news.
Thanks so much for joining us.
And that's all the news for this week.