Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, our weekly take on Linux and the open source world.
This is episode 33, recorded on December 19th, 2017.
I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe.
It's good to be with you.
We are recording out of time, ahead of time this week for the holidays, and we've put
together a holiday special.
Look back at some of the big stories from 2017, the things that really changed Linux
and open source.
Yeah, so let's start with 32-bit support, and a number of distros dropped it this year.
It seems that 2017 is at least the beginning of the end for 32-bit Linux.
Yeah, it kicked off really, to my recollection, on January 23rd when Arch announced that they
were beginning the process, they say due to decreasing popularity, which is what a lot
of the distributions recently cited, like Tails and others.
Yeah, Ubuntu 17.10, of course, there's no 32-bit desktop image for that, although there
are still 32-bit packages in the archive and will be probably for quite a while.
I think we've seen the tide turn in 2017 away from 32-bit.
Because of containerization and things like that, it's not going to completely go away.
But I think certainly in the desktop world, you have distros like Solus that never even
bothered with 32-bit support, because realistically, the only machines that are still working and
going to actually give you any sort of performance are netbooks, and even they are pretty old
hat now.
But everything else for the last 10 years-ish has been 64-bit capable.
So it's time for 32-bit to die on the desktop, I think.
I suppose so.
We did see some pushback.
In fact, I recall even you and I were talking about how I think you still have a 32-bit
system in production or so that you still find perfectly useful and functional.
So there's people out there that are still rocking 32-bit.
But if you look at just the date math, I don't think Intel has shipped a non-64-bit chip
in eight years, nine years for the desktop.
Yeah, it's time.
The system I had, I kind of remember why I had installed 32-bit.
I think I had some issue with some application, and I just stuck with it through sheer stubbornness.
But then I upgraded to a newer version of Ubuntu and just went 64-bit.
And now I don't have any 32-bit systems at all.
One of the other stories we watched unfold throughout the year was the slow and obvious
failure of Limux.
Yeah, in Munich in Germany, it was the poster child for open source and government, a project
that was around for about 10 years.
And this year, they voted to return to Windows and started to see that rollout happen now.
And it's just the end of a chapter, the end of an experiment that went horribly wrong,
unfortunately.
But you know, Joe, when Munich closes a door, Microsoft opens a window, and those users
that will be switching back to Windows 10 will at least be able to install Ubuntu or
maybe even Fedora because this was the year where Ubuntu arrived in the Windows Store
and SUSE and Fedora were announced to be there soon, the subsystem for Linux went out to
all Windows 10 users.
This was the year that this really took place, like it all clicked in and Microsoft delivered
on this run bash on top of Windows reality.
Yeah, it's kind of everything but Linux, isn't it?
The kernel, it's open SSH now as well, as we talked about recently.
It's Microsoft embracing open source, realizing where the market's going, and taking decisive
action to not be left behind, which I'd rather they didn't, because I'd rather they were
left behind and people moved over to Linux, but the market reality is they've decided
to embrace this stuff, and it's probably going to eat into the potential converts over to
Linux.
Perhaps there's nothing like seeing Ubuntu in the Windows Store, you go into the Microsoft
Windows Store, and you search for Ubuntu, and there's this big logo and screenshots,
it's really quite the experience.
But it's not the true Linux experience, so it may stop the bleeding, but I'm not super
worried about it.
In the meantime, I'm just too distracted by Bitcoin and all of the forks we saw this year.
Yeah, it's been a funny old year for Bitcoin.
Of course, now the value is about 20 times what it was at the beginning of the year.
We did say we were recording this earlier, it could crash in the next few days before
this is published, so let's hope that it is.
I suppose it's always possible, right?
But yeah, two hard forks appeared, and there was the threat of a third one.
The first one was Bitcoin Cash, and then the second one, Bitcoin Gold.
And to be honest, I haven't even really cashed in my Bitcoin Cash or Gold.
To me, it seems not even really worth doing.
What about you?
Have you managed to get hold of yours and sort it out?
I haven't really pursued it that far, because the whole Bitcoin fork fiascos just got me
more interested in some of the cooler cryptocurrencies, like Monero and Dash, that to me may have
longer-lasting usefulness on the internet than Bitcoin.
So I don't know, it's funny, these forks got me less interested in Bitcoin and more interested
in other cryptocurrencies, which I think is a good thing.
I'm not sure, Joe.
But at the same time, I was kind of expecting these forks to destabilize it and make the
price go down, and it's just had the complete opposite effect.
Whether or not that price would have gone up regardless, I don't know, but it's almost
legitimized it as the Coke or the Pepsi, whatever, the name you know in cryptocurrencies.
Yeah, I should save this rest for a predictions episode in the future.
But I really have been struck by everything that turns out initially to be negative news
for Bitcoin eventually just led to the rise of the price of Bitcoin, Joe.
So it's pretty nuts to watch all of this stuff.
And these forks still are going.
I see people talking about them online, so it's not like they're dead.
And it's a good space to trial and error different approaches to these technologies.
So it seems to have been a net positive, just like some people speculate there's too many
Linux distributions and other people say it's a natural evolutionary course where all these
different ideas get to be tried out.
I think it's a one-to-one comparison to cryptocurrencies.
Yeah, I think that's a reasonable way to look at it.
If you look at these two forks, they weren't just for a laugh, were they?
They were there to solve a particular technical problem, and that is there is not enough space
in each block.
There are not enough transactions per block, and that is eventually going to cause a huge
problem.
We've already got transaction fees through the roof unless you want to wait for a very
long time for your transaction to be processed.
And so there are very sound technical reasons why these forks happened, but it just seems
that unless Bitcoin itself adopts these changes, these changes are not going to actually be
implemented and it's not going to solve the problem.
Because Bitcoin is the name you know, and I suppose the people who made these forks
hoped that Bitcoin Cash would take over, but it hasn't happened yet and I just can't see
it happening.
Right.
The good news is all this stuff is open source, so it could be brought back in upstream if
there was some significant technological improvement.
I'm getting to the point though where I wonder if this stuff isn't going to be solved at
another layer.
Not to go too far into this, but you picture the blockchain and Bitcoin as like layer one
and two of the network stack, and there's application layers that could sit on top of
that, SQL databases that can process transactions instantly.
If you think about Coinbase, one of the largest, most popular ways to buy Bitcoin right now,
those transactions are happening off the blockchain, inside a SQL database instantly, and then
they sync up to the blockchain.
When you go to a store and you buy something with your credit card here in the States,
the Visa network isn't instantly verifying the transaction.
They have a 30 day lag, but they solve it at the application layer.
And I think that might be true with Bitcoin too.
You could build transaction software, your Stripe type services on top of Bitcoin that
use off-blockchain backends, like SQL databases, and then synchronize it to the blockchain
like Coinbase does or other large Bitcoin exchanges do already.
Yeah, I think that is pretty much going to happen, and that's why I think the value is
going to continue to rise, and we'll get into that next week when we put some hard numbers
on our predictions for Bitcoin.
DigitalOcean.com and use our promo code, here's the thing.
It's all one word, you create your account and then you apply it.
DigitalOcean is a way for you to spin up a Linux system in seconds on their super fast
infrastructure and they have data centers all over the world.
Everything, every machine is using SSD disk, and that means everything flies because between
all SSDs and 40 gigabit connections to the internet, these systems have unbelievable
performance.
For $5 a month, you could use our $10 credit and try out DigitalOcean two months for free.
They have block storage and object storage, a simple API with tons of really good open
source applications pre-built for you, and monitoring and alerting that it's built right
into the service.
With straightforward pricing and great documentation and an interface that will blow you away,
there's really no reason not to try it.
DigitalOcean.com and use our promo code, here's the thing.
DigitalOcean.com, promo code, here's the thing.
Okay, so by far the biggest news story in the Linux world this year was back in April
when Mark Shotworth dropped the bombshell that Ubuntu was abandoning Unity, abandoning
the phone, switching back to GNOME, and it was all changed for the Ubuntu project.
This is the story of the year that affected me the most personally because unless I was
a canonical employee, I couldn't have been more on the front lines.
I was sitting at a large conference table with the folks at Dell that all were responsible
for shipping Ubuntu machines.
The moment, in fact, I was the one that broke the news to them.
By the way, you're no longer going to be shipping Unity and you should have seen their faces.
I mean, I couldn't have been in a better room other than Mark Shotworth's office, I suppose,
and then I was in New York towards the completion of this journey, watching the team come together,
the remaining staff, and the final push towards 1710.
So I saw both ends of bewilderment and the homestretch completion, and it really caused
a lot of reflection in the whole community, I felt, Joe.
People were asking, where is this going?
What does this mean for GNOME?
What does this mean for the Plasma desktop now that all these companies are in on GNOME?
Is there going to be a huge fork?
Is there going to be controversy and fights?
There were so many questions, but so few answers.
Yeah, there was a lot of confusion early on in April and May, but then Canonical really
upped their communication game, didn't they, with DDA blogging, the desktop progress, and
of course the Ubuntu rally that you went to in New York.
And a lot of the questions were answered over the six months after the announcement, and
for me, I think they were answered in a very positive way.
If you look at Ubuntu 1710, it is a solid release.
It wasn't just stock GNOME.
It isn't just them abandoning the desktop.
They did work on it and refine it and make it their own.
So I think a lot of the doubters, myself included, were kind of silenced, really, by the work
that they actually did on it and the release that came out that wasn't what I had expected
when I read that announcement, put it that way.
And I think they've really set the table for the 1804 release next year, and I think it's
going to be, I hope, a pretty polished release of the Linux desktop and maybe the one I eventually
switch to.
I'm thinking the future is bright for all of us who have been looking for a great workstation
operating system to settle down on.
More and more really good options are coming along, and I think 1804 is going to be one
of the better ones.
Just wait for one of my predictions on the next episode, and you might end up using something
I'm going to predict.
Very good, sir.
In the meantime, there's been one story this year that you've kind of been my go-to guy
on, what does all of this mean?
And it's all of the hoopla around Cyanogenmod.
Yeah, so this was technically around this time last year that it started.
There had been problems with Cyanogenmod for a long time.
I'd noticed in, I think, September of last year that I hadn't had any snapshot updates
for Cyanogenmod for a few months, and the writing seemed to be on the wall for them.
And then it was right around Christmas that Cyanogenmod's servers got turned off, and
a fork appeared, and it became LineageOS.
And a lot of the original people who were involved with Cyanogenmod jumped ship over
to LineageOS, and I had really high hopes for it at the beginning of the year.
I was really hoping that they were going to deliver on a number of devices and keep supporting
them with OTAs, and they did.
My hopes came true.
It's been solid all year long.
They're now working on their next version based on Android 8, actually 8.1, and it's
been solid.
I've been using it all year long on various different Android devices.
It's really just a continuation of Cyanogenmod.
There have been a few little tweaks here and there, but fundamentally, you've got the same
open source ROM without all the Google bloat.
But if, like me, you want to add a bit of that Google bloat back in, you can.
But if not, you've got a mostly open source mobile operating system to use.
I knew it was going to happen like this.
I just know myself at this point, but when they announced LineageOS, I hated the name.
I just hated it.
And now here we are in December, I don't mind it at all.
No problem.
I've totally gotten used to the name.
In fact, I'm really excited about the project, very happy that, like you said, it's going
in the right direction.
But intellectually, I've been finding what's going on over at Yolo almost more interesting.
I'm going to end up using LineageOS, but I've been finding that I enjoy the Sailfish X saga
much more.
Yeah, so Sailfish wasn't looking too good at the beginning of the year, whereas it's
had a reasonable year actually with this Sailfish X project, as you mentioned, that is on the
Xperia X phone, which is a ROM you can buy from Yolo.
And financially, they're still not in great shape.
They still owe quite a lot of people for the tablets that they crowdfunded and never delivered.
But they have got a revenue stream now.
They are developing Sailfish and I want them to succeed.
I want them to be more open source, don't get me wrong, but I want there to be at least
another operating system for phones that is usable.
I heard that sentiment over and over again from the audience over the year, but probably
the most poignant moment was when I was in New York, I was talking to a couple of canonical
developers who really liked the idea of having a revenue stream to just fund this type of
development because they've been through that mobile process now.
And I think they ended up ordering the Sailfish X phone.
What was it, Joe, is it the Sony Xperia that you could install it on?
And I think they ended up pre-purchasing that phone in anticipation of all of this.
And you could see they have palatable excitement about something that's an alternative to Android.
Yeah, the Xperia X is the phone, yeah, and I have used Sailfish on various other devices
and I must say that of all of the Linux-based alternative mobile operating systems, it's
the best.
It sounds fairly good, but Sailfish is really solid from what I've seen of it.
I completely agree.
I really enjoyed it for the limited amount of time that I did run it.
The situation on Android could be improving in the near future, the next few years.
This year, Google announced Project Treble, the modular base for Android that may actually
allow updates to be sent out to consumers to keep them protected, to keep their operating
system up to date.
It essentially broke out the low-level system architecture of Android and the upper levels.
Yeah, so it means that there's a lot less work for the OEMs to put in to keep the ROMs
up to date and to keep the versions of Android up to date.
And so in theory, if they deploy this properly, it means that you won't have months and months
and months of lag between updates and often with some devices that you buy, there's just
no updates or you might get one maybe and then you get these huge security vulnerabilities
coming out and then they're just not patched against that.
So in theory, and I keep saying that because it takes work from the OEMs in the first place
to implement this, but in theory, this is really good news going forwards and not only
actually for people who want to use the official ROM that comes with the phone, it also makes
custom ROM development far easier because there's just less work involved importing
ROMs to the device.
But if this doesn't solve your Android woes, then maybe the Librem 5 will because this
year on October 11th, 14 days ahead of the deadline, the Librem 5 was fully funded.
They reached $1.5 million in crowdfunding for a fully free open source phone with hardware
kill switches.
Yeah, and I said at the time we need to hire their PR department because they did a brilliant
job of promoting this, didn't they?
I think they did the best I've ever seen in the open source community.
It should be a case study for other projects that want to do a hardware software combo.
If you recall, Joe, towards the end of it too, a couple of big whales came in, which
that's not necessarily reproducible.
Well, yeah, eventually it got pushed over 2 million, didn't it?
Thanks to those big whales, as you say, which we still don't know who that was, but maybe
we'll find out next year.
Yeah, we'll keep following the Librem 5.
I'm very interested in that development and I'm sure there'll be more news throughout
2018, but let's talk about Firefox OS for a moment.
The news wasn't so good in 2017 for Firefox OS.
Yeah, we kind of saw this one coming that there hadn't been any devices for a while
and there weren't any plans for any, but officially this year Mozilla shut down the Connected
Devices Group, which was the department within Mozilla responsible for Firefox OS.
So it officially died, but thankfully Mozilla had plenty of other things that they got up
to this year.
Yeah, it was a bit of a controversial year for them, kicking it off with acquiring Pocket.
Yeah, and this came off the back of installing Pocket by default, which ruffled a lot of
feathers.
I actually use Pocket all the time for this show and others.
It is a very useful service, but I don't know about bundling it by default.
But when they acquired Pocket, they promised to open source it and I was really excited
about that because an open source client, fantastic.
More importantly, an open source server so I can roll my own.
That would be exactly what I want because I don't want the adverts.
I want to be able to potentially have some bloat stripped out of it.
It'd be great to have it on a droplet running and have complete control over it.
So come on, Mozilla, what's happening with open sourcing that?
Get on with it, please.
See, I actually thought you and I were going to have a disagreement about this.
When the whole Pocket thing went down, I was a Chrome user.
I was all in on Chrome.
I was looking over from afar going, geez, these guys are really getting upset about
this.
So of course, I had Firefox installed, so I checked it out and I'm like, oh, Pocket,
this is a lot like Instapaper.
Well, I use the hell out of Instapaper.
It seems like a feature you'd want built into your browser.
And Apple has shipped it in Safari for a few years now.
I'm pretty sure Internet Explorer has something similar.
Really, I think Chrome's the only browser that doesn't have this functionality built
in.
So it got me thinking, well, if Mozilla had just built a Pocket competitor into Firefox,
would people have been as upset?
I don't think they would have.
It is a great app.
I think it's a pipe dream that the whole thing's going to be open sourced, especially the back
end.
Because one of the things that Mozilla touted when they purchased Pocket was this great
human recommendation engine on the back end that's curating the best content of Pocket.
And there's no way, there's no way they can ship that because that requires a staff.
So they're either going to give you some sort of pared down Node.js server application or
it's just never going to happen.
That's an early prediction.
That's a tease for our predictions episode, Joe.
Well I'd be happy with a pared down version of it.
I have no interest in any of the social stuff and the recommendation.
I just want to be able to save links and view them offline.
Thank you very much.
Fair enough.
I think one of their strategies that made a lot of sense to me personally this year
was the introduction of Firefox Focus.
This seems to be the way to go after mobile for Mozilla in my opinion.
Yeah, I remember trying this out when it first came out and really being impressed with how
fast it was.
It was definitely the fastest browser I'd ever used on Android, but I remember thinking
at the time that it could do with a few more features and those features have been forthcoming,
but I wonder does that somewhat defeat the purpose of it?
If you add too much in the way of features, does that make it not as fast and it's kind
of focused on privacy as well.
So I think it remains to be seen how this develops, but it's good that they have got
a different approach because it seems that Firefox itself, the main version of the browser
is not doing that well on Android compared with Chrome.
So they have to try something to stay relevant in the mobile market and it's something that
I'm definitely going to keep an eye on throughout 2018 I think.
I've always enjoyed the ad tracker counter as a cool little demo to show people how creepy
the internet is, but there is an area where Mozilla has had more success and that's Project
Common Voice.
What I love about Project Common Voice is it just feels like an initiative for the people
to make something better on the web in general without a direct benefit from Mozilla.
Yeah, this is them doing their public service, isn't it?
Collating all of these people's voices, reading the various things that you have to do and
also the data of people listening to the voices and confirming whether or not they've transcribed
it properly.
We need something like this if we're going to compete with what Amazon and Google and
Apple have got going with their lady in a tube, as you call them.
Yeah, and even just to offer basic speech recognition to websites and open source applications
that can't afford nuances, multi-million dollar licensing agreement and all of the data exchange
required.
That's why I think this is one of Mozilla's power spots, like they're in the power stroke
with this particular project.
They also really nailed the Firefox Quantum release this year.
Yeah, I've seen nothing but universal praise for this release and for me it's just something
that got upgraded on Ubuntu and I was just using it as a matter of course, and it's definitely
faster than the previous versions of Firefox.
I think some people have a little bit over-egg the pudding on how much faster and better
it is and they changed the layout a little bit, which I didn't like at first, but I've
got used to now, but it is definitely a huge step forward for them.
They need to stay competitive with Chrome if they've got any chance and I don't know,
do you think they really have got any chance of winning back market share from Chrome at
this point?
I mean, I'm not sure they've won back market share from me.
It's enough of a cumulative improvement that I find it launches faster, I find it loads
web pages at least as fast, if not maybe slightly faster, and I would say maybe what it actually
is is the order in which it loads the web page, I prefer.
That's what we're getting down to now, is how the web page is rendered on my screen.
I like the way Firefox is doing it better than the way Chrome is doing it now as it's
loading, but it also seems to do it without putting as much of a drag on my system, which
I also really like because it leaves resources available for other applications.
I'm pretty happy with it and I'm one of those fools who likes the new UI because I've heard
a lot of people complain about it, but I think it's pretty great.
That and all the other improvements they've baked into it, it's become my daily driver.
But they're not without their controversies this year too.
In fact, going into 2018, I think Mozilla might be one of the companies that's embroiled
in some of the biggest controversies.
Yeah, the lawsuit with Yahoo, which stems from a deal that they did to become the default
search provider, which would net them over a billion dollars, but had a clause in it
that said, if Yahoo is sold, then Mozilla can walk away from the deal, keep the money
and change the default search provider.
Well, Yahoo was sold, as we know, to Verizon.
They changed their default search back to Google and intend to keep the money.
And Yahoo, or Oath as they become, and Yahoo Holdings, are having none of it.
And they want their money back and they don't want to pay any more money.
And so they're trying to weasel out of this deal.
And neither of us are lawyers, but I'm fairly confident that Mozilla are going to get away
with this and get to keep the money and keep making it rain.
Yeah, if I was a betting man, I would bet this is going to work out OK for Mozilla.
I'm not so sure how this whole Mr. Robot looking glass add-on situation is going to go.
They're at least going to spend the first half of 2018 digging themselves out of this
hole.
Yeah, so much squandered goodwill.
Just when they were coming off the high of Firefox 57 Quantum, they go and do this at
the end of the year and push an extension to people's browsers without them even knowing
about it.
And it's some confusing thing about Mr. Robot that hardly anyone even knows about.
I can't believe they've made this mistake.
And I hope that people get fired over this.
It's not good when people lose their jobs, but it's also not good when they damage the
reputation of a major open source project.
Yeah, I hope there's some reflection in the upper levels of Mozilla.
It's been a good year overall for them, though, so hopefully they still have some goodwill
to cash in.
I debated dropping Firefox after the extension fiasco, but if I'm being honest, I think I
still trust Mozilla more than I trust Chrome.
And I like the advances in Firefox this last year, and I think they're on a good trajectory
for 2018 with Firefox specifically.
So I'm just going to keep an eye on it, and we'll keep reporting on what happens here
on the show.
In fact, you can get every single week's episode if you go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe
for all the ways to get this episode and, like we've been teasing a couple of times
this week, our predictions.
And not just predictions, but things we hope to see throughout 2018 in the world of Linux.
That'll be in next week's episode.
Yeah, and go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact if you want to get in touch with us.
You can support the whole network at our Patreon page, patreon.com slash jupitersignal.
We'll be back next Monday with our look forward to 2018.
I'm at Chris LAS.
I'm at Joe Ressington.
Happy holidays, everyone, and thank you for joining us.
We'll see you next week.
See you later.