Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 169, recorded on December 20th, 2020.
I'm Chris.
I'm Wes.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, gentlemen, and Joe, welcome back to the show.
Well, it's good to be here.
Now it is that time of year where we look back at what we said would happen in 2020,
and we predict what will happen in 2021.
And to help us go through those previous predictions, Joe's back.
And so since you're our guest of honor, Joe, we're going to start with you.
Last year, you predicted that in 2020, we'd be able to buy a RISC-V based single board
computer that's capable of running a full Linux desktop, maybe Debian and XFCE, perhaps,
and it will cost no more than the most expensive Raspberry Pi.
Unfortunately, this did not happen.
No, clearly, I was wrong about this, although I listened to it and I did predict an eight
gigabyte RAM Raspberry Pi, so maybe half a point for that.
Yeah.
Accidental half point there.
You could tell it's a true Joe prediction, too, because it's got XFCE.
Yeah.
Of course.
Well, that's what he would be running with it, right?
I mean, yeah.
But the eight gig Pi, that's interesting.
Was that just a casual mention?
Yeah, yeah.
Well, all right.
This one, I'm kind of curious to know what you guys think.
I'll do mine.
I said Richard Stallman would reemerge on the talk scene, not necessarily affiliated
with any particular group, but he'd be like a mercenary for free software out there and
about and we'd see him sort of pop up a little bit more.
Interesting.
Do you think I got that one?
Okay.
Well, this year, it's a little hard to tell because the scene is a bit different.
I don't know.
I don't know that he's at least anywhere near as prominent as he once was.
He has done some conferences like Emacs Conf 2020.
He was there and he did a couple of talks there.
One like AMA type thing, which is on YouTube, which I watched the other day.
So he's definitely not totally disappeared.
He definitely did come back.
And that was what we were talking about was the whole political angle of it, that it kind
of been canceled.
And now he's kind of come back and it hasn't been as much of a stink about it as I thought
there might be.
Yeah, that's true.
There really hasn't been.
I guess I did kind of, although I didn't predict that there would be, I did kind of assume
there would be.
I think we all did.
So I'm kind of getting this one, it sounds like then.
I think also maybe if you look at it as did Richard Stallman totally fade away, the answer
is no.
And I think in that spirit, yeah, you get a point.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, on to Joe's next prediction.
By this time next year, there'll be a license that solves the AWS problem.
Well, still being open source.
Now, this is interesting.
There's a lot of definitions here, particularly open source and the AWS problem.
And do you think you got this one, Joe?
Not quite.
Almost.
The AWS problem, of course, is that the likes of Amazon are taking open source software
and selling it as a service and not contributing financially or even code back to the original
projects.
And so we had various attempts last year at it.
And I think we had a pretty good one this year, which was the timescale license, which
is pretty close, but it's not quite open source.
So I don't think I can claim a full point here.
Yeah, timescale does get close, but I don't think it was quite the spirit of it.
So I tend to agree there.
There still is that overall AWS problem, not fully solved.
I guess this next year, we'll see what happens.
All right, Chris, I think you're up for now.
All right.
So this one, it seemed like everything was in place.
There are almost years of little hints leading up to this prediction.
And I thought it was going to pop this year.
But I don't think I can make that claim.
I said that NVIDIA would show various types of support.
Maybe it was code, documentation, developer time, et cetera, that would enable the nouveau
driver to become really functional, close to fully functional for basic daily driver
uses with the NVIDIA graphics card.
But it just did not materialize.
I even saw rumors and suggestions that certain NVIDIA developers were having conversations
with certain Red Hat developers to make some of this work, like on the DL.
But nothing I can point to officially and say, yeah, they stepped up and they really
enabled the project.
Yeah, weren't we expecting some sort of conference talk that ultimately got canceled?
But it seemed like this was in the works and I guess just never realized.
Yep.
There was a talk that was scheduled.
There was, if you go back to 2019, there were several announcements about how documentation
was going to get delivered.
There was a GitHub repo set up, and it just all went nowhere.
And you got to wonder what happened.
And in the meantime, AMD just seems to have refined their strategy on Linux.
We had Michael Arbel on recently, and he was talking about what a good year it was for
AMD on Linux.
And you look at launch day with the 6800 series, and it's pretty solid on Linux.
And then you look over at NVIDIA and they've just really done nothing to improve the experience.
They've continued to make their driver and they continue to refine that.
It does perform well if you're willing to jump through the proprietary hoops, of course.
Yep, but nothing to really address the fact that AMD and Intel just have it all baked
into the Linux kernel now.
And that's what I was really hoping to see, some kind of help and support there that would
make this thing more functional.
And it just didn't happen.
Linode.com slash LAN.
Go there to get a $100 60-day credit towards your new account and go there to support the
show.
Linode is our cloud hosting provider.
All of us here on the show, we use Linode for our personal stuff and all of our business
stuff.
And I like that they're independently owned.
That really makes a difference.
I trust that they're going to be around for a long time.
And they started forever ago in 2003 as one of the first companies in cloud computing.
There's so many little nice features that you don't even really have to worry about.
For example, I was setting up a new rig and I was just sending a ton of data because it
was going to be the central node in this mesh network that I was setting up.
And so I was just sending a bunch of data to get it all synced up.
So when I turned everything on, it would have all of the files.
And about 15 minutes into this process, maybe 20 minutes into the process, I get a message
from Alex.
He says, what is going on?
What are you doing?
Because I had these little threshold alerts set up that were just perfect little reminders
that, hey, something's worth checking in on here.
Your box is doing something a little unusual.
And the number one thing that I know from running servers in production is that is a
great way to tell that something is wrong, that somebody has owned your box, something's
going on, or you have a process gun haywire, or something's syncing that you didn't expect
to sync.
These thresholds let you check in on things like CPU or bandwidth transfer in my case.
It generates a nice email.
It says, hey, you're not in trouble.
It's no big deal.
But this just meets the threshold, which you set.
And so we're letting you know that you've exceeded that.
And it was really kind of cool because I thought if we got that on the matrix server, we'd
know something was wrong.
That would be a sign that we should go check in on that kind of thing.
Or something was going really, really right.
It's a party on the matrix server, which we also host on Linode, of course.
So go check them out.
Because with that $100 credit, you can really build some awesome infrastructure with some
great tools around it to really make it run solid for you.
So it's stable.
It's fast.
They have 11 data centers around the world.
You can choose whatever is close to you or maybe close to your clients.
And of course, that dashboard makes it easy to tie it all together.
And unlike entry level hosting services that lock you into their platform, Linode gives
you full back end access to customize and control your server to fit your needs.
And they support tools like Kubernetes and Terraform, which great opportunity to learn
or great opportunity to plug it into your existing management system.
So go to linode.com slash LAN.
You go there.
You get that $100, 60 day credit towards the new account.
And you support the show.
You make it possible for independent media to give away their content for free by going
to linode.com slash LAN.
OK.
So I'm not even officially on this show anymore.
So I'm not going to be making any predictions.
So that's a good excuse for me to just be the unofficial referee.
So you two have got to do two each, I reckon.
So who's going to go first?
Wes?
Yeah, all right.
I'll do that.
This first one doesn't necessarily make me happy to say, but that's not how this game
is played, right?
I'm going to predict that Mozilla kills Pocket.
Pocket, huh?
Yeah.
You know, it just never really felt like a great fit.
They never open sourced it.
And it doesn't really seem like they've done anything with it.
No, I'm not opposed.
They've used Pocket.
Having a nice read it later service is pretty handy.
It makes sense as a feature in a browser, really.
They just like so many other things.
It's rotting away.
And with the, you know, the downsizing, the new version of Mozilla, I just don't know
that there's a ton of effort that they would have anyway to go in there.
So we'll see.
The thing that makes me think this might not happen is that just the other day I had a
new installation of Linux and a new Firefox without my profile or anything.
And the first thing it said was, hey, try Pocket.
So they're still heavily promoting it to new users.
So I can see it, but I can also not see it.
I think we won't see it open sourced either way.
Isn't that just like the only exit strategy they have for Pocket that doesn't piss everyone
off?
Yeah, I think so.
If they just kill it and they fail to open source it, I think that's even worse PR for
them.
But I could totally see your resources argument here.
They don't really have the resources.
They haven't really got a solid way to monetize it in a way that's moving the needle for them
financially at all.
So they may have to focus in on what they can do well and what they can generate a profit
from.
I could see Pocket not being on that list.
But how they handle that, that's going to be critical.
And you're not saying they're going to open source it.
You're saying they kill it.
I say they kill it.
They wind it down.
There's some sort of timeline where it's going to be going away.
All right.
We're locking that one in.
So mine is a little safer of a bet than yours.
I predict that at least three traditional CentOS style clones will ship their quote
unquote 1.0 in 2021.
All right.
Well, I think that's where we'll first need the ref.
What are we counting as 1.0?
Is that just like a release that's ready for the general public to consume and deploy production
wise?
Yeah.
I don't know if they may call it they may call it 8.0 to make it clear what version
it is.
Right.
It'll be their first public release.
What do you think?
Yeah, I think that's fair enough.
We're saying three new clones here.
So we're not counting Oracle's one and stuff.
So that's the tricky thing is I'm wondering what qualifies or not.
And I'm thinking it's three rocky rocky Linux or what a rocky OS that would count.
But I'm like a restart of scientific Linux I think would count.
But I don't think cloud Linux counts or Oracle because they've already been shipping for
a while now.
So I'm saying three clones.
OK, so some at least seems like some new clones would need to be well one new clone by my
count at the moment.
But I'm not, you know, somewhere in the mix.
The thing is, the reason why I think this is a little tiny bit risky is these are supposed
to be enterprise distros.
And so going slow and getting it just right is sort of in their nature.
And so it may be too aggressive of a window to say maybe they don't actually ship something
until 2022.
Maybe they don't actually even ship something until I don't I don't know, December.
I mean, that would be my idea.
Here's where my background on this was is they got to get something shipped by December,
right?
Because in December, the end of December 2021, that's when traditional CentOS upgrades, updates
go away.
That's when support dies for CentOS as people knew it.
And people either need to switch to stream, which I think is what the majority of people
will need to do, or they'll have to come to some sort of decision where they do one of
these conversion scripts and convert to some fly-by-night distro.
But I think that's your target.
If you miss that December window, you're going to miss the majority of the market, right?
That's when you need to be ready with something that people could, in theory, actually switch
to.
And that's my prediction is that three of them will be at their production-ready state
by then.
By this time next year, basically.
Right now as we're recording.
Interesting.
All right.
What's your next one then, Wes?
Well, I suppose I'm keeping in the theme of maybe not that likely.
I'm doing it anyway.
Ubuntu ships Systemd HomeD.
Now not Fedora, but Ubuntu here?
Well, Fedora felt almost too certain.
That's just going to happen, right?
At some point, it's going to end up in a Fedora release.
Maybe not the default, but there.
So I think maybe by the next, what, the one in 2104, Systemd HomeD will be available.
You can try it out pretty easily on Ubuntu.
And then by the fall 2110, it'll be online by default.
That's what I'm predicting.
Now, it might not be that they've engaged all the features.
It doesn't have to use all of it or radically change, but just that it's there and it's
running by default in a regular Ubuntu desktop install.
So could we say the key qualifier is if the user account exists when the home folder exists,
that's using Systemd HomeD?
Yeah.
And you've got that part of the distribution of Systemd installed.
Okay.
Just installed?
Yeah.
Installed and configured on the system by default.
Okay.
Hmm.
Yeah.
So if I were canonical, maybe I'd want to claim a little recognition for being willing
to do a little more cutting edge.
And so maybe this is something they'd seriously look into and maybe try to figure out if it's
shippable before they do the LTS.
That's exactly right.
That would be the time.
Get it in there before the 2204 LTS that's coming up.
Yeah.
And they could always pull it.
They could put it in 2110 and then if it doesn't work out, pull it and go back to regular home
directory for 2204.
Yeah.
I like this one, actually.
I would like to see it.
It's neat and I'd like to do a little more playing with Systemd HomeD, honestly.
I'm going to save an Ubuntu prediction for Linux Unplugged.
I got one that I'm setting aside.
I feel like I'm going to save it because I want you to have that space in this.
So you'll be the one making the Ubuntu prediction in this episode.
So what's your other one then, Chris?
All right.
This next one, this one could screw me like the Nouveau driver did because this is one
where I'm reading all the tea leaves.
I'm seeing all of the activity leading up to this year.
And I think, I predict the BcashFS will be mainlined in 2021.
I would really like to see this, a nice high-performance file system, fantastic for NVMe drives and
workstations.
You know, when you don't need everything that ButterFS or ZFS can do, but you still want
a modern high-performance, really awesome, well-designed file system, BcashFS.
And it's getting there.
It's getting there.
But like so many things, that final getting it over the final hump to get it in the kernel
can just take forever, like we saw with WireGuard.
Yes.
I mean, there's a high bar of entry for the kernel and rightfully so.
Yeah.
And they've just did another round of reviews for inclusion in October.
And it's looking like it's on a good trajectory, but it's by far, it's not a sure thing yet.
It's not a sure bet yet.
I'm almost glad of that, honestly, because with file system development, we don't need
that to be rushed.
Like just take the time, get it right, because I think once it is in the kernel, assuming
it makes it there, that's when people will actually really start trying it out.
You're not going to compile a module of a file system that you might use that you don't
know and isn't trusted.
But once it's blessed and actually available by default, yeah, all right, I'm switching.
There are still, as Kent Overstreet puts it, the main developer, a few bugs remaining,
including, quote, kernel oopses with Zstandard compression, some of the erasure code not
being quite stable, but pretty much everything else, replication, compression, checksumming,
encryption, all looking really solid.
And another good sign that's helping get BcacheFS over the inclusion hump is a veteran file
system developer, Dave Chyner, has jumped in to help with testing Bcache.
And he's even found a couple of things by throwing it through a dual socket motherboard,
which looks at some of these checksums and does a little bit of different behavior than
everything on one chip.
And he actually uncovered some scalability issues where BcacheFS wasn't quite staying
up to snuff to say something like XFS is currently doing.
And they're working on those things.
And I think probably by summer, they're going to have all that stuff wrapped up.
So I don't know.
I don't know, Wes.
We'll see.
I don't know if it's going to get included then.
But I think by the time we're recording next year, this kind of episode, I really hope
to see BcacheFS in the mainline kernel.
It may not be shipping in distros yet, but it's going to be upstream.
It's going to be mainlined.
My next question then is how long after it gets mainlined before we've switched the studio?
Linux.ting.com is the next generation of Ting Mobile and it's here.
I've been a customer for over eight years and I can tell you there has never been a
better time to try out Ting.
And when you go to linux.ting.com, you get $25 off.
It's now the smarter choice for everybody.
They have unlimited data plans at $45 a month.
Whether you need two gigs or 20 gigs, whatever it might be, there's a perfect Ting plan for
you now.
And they've made some big improvements there.
But no need to worry because that's really it.
The only thing that's changed is just lower monthly phone bills.
You still get access to Ting's award-winning customer service and nationwide LT and 5G.
And you know what else?
No contracts.
No contracts ever.
And now Ting Mobile customers can choose from three different plans based on your data needs.
And you'd be impressed with how much you can get done through the Ting interface.
The dashboard takes care of just about everything you'd ever need.
I don't understand why the rest of the industry doesn't catch up to where Ting's at.
I mean I'm talking about even like porting over and bringing a new device.
You can do it all through the website.
And pretty much any phone will work with Ting.
So just head to linux.ting.com to check your current phone.
You create an account.
You pick the plan that's right for you.
And then like magic, Elves will send you a SIM card that you pop into your phone and
you can activate and you're going in just a few minutes.
And one of the brilliant things about Ting is there's multiple carriers you can choose
from depending on how it works best in your area.
And that also means that if you need to be mobile or you need multiple different carriers
or maybe you need to move, you can always pick and choose what's going to work best
for you.
So go see what it's like to cut your phone bill in half.
It's never been easier with Ting.
So get started by going to linux.ting.com.
This is the next generation of Ting mobile.
It's here and I'm really impressed with what they've managed to do.
And you can get $25 off when you go to linux.ting.com.
Well it wouldn't be a Linux action news predictions episode without some Bitcoin talk.
And boy howdy with all the news this week.
It's more relevant than ever.
Yeah, it's already dropped about $800 since we started recording.
Yeah, oh boy.
This is a tricky one.
So why don't we review what we said would happen and then we're going to talk about
if we can even predict the future because I think that's a conversation in itself.
Joe, you said that it would get to $19,000 as a high.
I said $22,000.
It actually got as high as $24,000.
And it's possible that it could go even higher by the end of the year after we've recorded
this.
That's absolutely true.
For the low end, you predicted it would go as low as $4k.
I predicted $5k.
And it looks like that's about where it was, was $5k, somewhere around there for the 2020
low.
Wow.
Yeah, around March time, it got to about there.
So you were pretty spot on there.
I was close though.
Boy, that, right now looking back at $5,000, that seems like quite a deal.
You know, because you don't have to buy a full Bitcoin.
You just buy however much you can afford.
Yeah, get like a couple hundred bucks worth of Bitcoin.
Back then it was $5,000 and that would have paid off right now at this point in time.
Not any kind of advice, of course.
I'm just looking at that thinking maybe I should have done something there.
Then we said, okay, here's what it's going to be on December 1st, 2020.
Joe, you said it'd be $7k.
I said it'd be $14k.
It actually turned out to be around $19k.
So much higher than either one of us were thinking.
And I thought I was going a little high because I thought if the low was $5k and I said it's
going to get all the way up to $14k, I was like, well, that's pretty big growth.
Right.
Is it big growth or is it more of a sustained?
Yeah.
Well, I listened back to that predictions episode and what I was talking about was wanting
stability.
I didn't want it to have this massive high.
I thought that if it dropped to about four or five and then crept its way up to seven,
seven and a half, that's what I would want to happen.
I want just slow and steady growth, not this crazy up and down.
But here we are talking about it at $23,000, $24,000, having beaten last year's record
and crucially that $20,000 barrier because it came close earlier in the year to $20,000
and just didn't quite make it.
And that's a psychological barrier to people.
And I kind of didn't want it to break that yet.
I wanted it to have a sustained period of being around about $20,000 and then for it
to break through and then start climbing.
The volatility is going to be its undoing and ultimately will be the undoing of its
value, I think.
It's hard to say because I don't really know how to really predict a currency that has
a limited supply and because people are losing their coins and their wallets.
There's always less and less bitcoins and there will only be a finite amount ever made.
So while new ones are getting mined, there's also ones that are getting lost and there's
a limit on that.
So I do wonder if that doesn't play strange things with the value as well.
Yeah.
I mean, it seems like it's ripe for speculation and people are happy to do that.
And what we noticed is it just took off again like a rocket.
It was bouncing around, bouncing around and then boom, $19,000, tipped to $20,000, came
down a bit and then bam, all the way up to $24,000 as of this morning.
And as we record, it's $23,799.80.
Not that I'm checking, but it's still, it's crazy.
It's still crazy.
But I have noticed a huge shift in how many normals know about Bitcoin.
Everyone in my family knows that Bitcoin is a thing.
They might not understand it.
But there was, I think, a large adoption of Coinbase and then the Cash App made it really
easy to buy Bitcoin.
Right.
It's in the hands of folks, so you might not understand anything about how digital wallets
work or blockchain, but hey, here's something you can buy.
I had the Cash App set up already so I could, you know, hey, here's my half a lunch or whatever.
Like I've used it, I've used it for all kinds of like quick little ways to send money.
So I had everything plumbed already.
And when they rolled out Bitcoin support, it was just a button on my phone now to buy
some Bitcoin.
I actually haven't used it, but I bet a lot of other people have and you're sitting there,
you're watching this thing go up, you buy a little bit of it.
And I think making it easier every step of the way has accelerated adoption and made
it understandable to some degree by the normals.
I told this story on air before, but I actually got a telegram from my mom about a month ago
asking me what I thought about investing in Bitcoin and talking to me about Bitcoin.
My mom, who I've never had a conversation with about Bitcoin before, she found it on
her own and I mean, that really to me was a sign that I kind of feel like I feel like
it's impossible to predict.
But I think it's I think this year it's stuck.
It's here now.
It's sticking around.
I think people who actually speculate on commodities like gold and silver are now keeping.
I mean, I hear this all the time on the economics YouTube channels I watch.
Oh, I have about five percent of my portfolio in crypto.
It's just a new way to diversify your account.
Doesn't seem like we're really using it to actually buy that many products or services
these days.
At least I haven't seen that much of it.
I mean, there's some, right?
It still exists.
But yeah, it seems now more it's a new investment vehicle side hustle.
So how do you predict something like this?
Can you predict something?
You make wild guesses and see what sticks.
Because if you look at the volatility we just saw in the last couple of months, we could
stay this exact price all year long and then in November it could jump up to forty thousand.
I mean, it's just it's wild.
But I do think once twenty thousand was crossed.
Because I think every time what you're doing is you're setting a new expectation of what
Bitcoin's value is because it's all made up anyway.
Right.
And once you get used to that idea, then you're more comfortable paying that for it.
And that's part of how that gets established.
And the longer it stays at these higher prices, the more that becomes the new floor.
Like it just never goes below a certain amount now.
And it ultimately ends up higher than where it, you know, so when it crashes, it usually
rebounds over time higher than when it originally crashed.
So I can't make a prediction here, but I feel like we're going to look back at twenty four
thousand.
I think it was quaint.
I guess you're telling us to buy.
I just think it's reached that point where it's not going away.
It's nature, the block chain, the fact that it's open source, the fact that there's all
these applications being built on top of it.
And now that it's so commonly known, it's becoming easier and more accessible for the
normals.
Yeah, I think it's unless unless a government like the size of the United States just decided
to try to shut it down as much as possible.
It's not going away.
You're right.
People aren't buying goods with it, but a lot of people are also storing silver.
And you think about when people buy gold and silver, some of them are not even actually
they don't actually own the metal, right?
They're buying rights to the metal that's stored somewhere else, right?
What's the difference?
At least one can be cryptographically proven.
Well, I started to get people asking me about this when it was approaching 20,000 again.
And should I buy or not?
And my advice to anyone would always be only invest what you can afford to lose.
And this is a long term investment if you are going to do it.
But I said to them, back in late November, early December, if it breaks the 20,000 barrier,
then it's going to go to the moon, essentially.
If we can break that psychological barrier, which we now have, and we're at 23, 24 ish,
I think it's going to go a lot higher over the next year.
So if you've got money to lose and to risk and to bet, essentially, then you could do
worse, I think.
Well, now that we're all just looking at the ticker, it's time to wrap this episode up.
Go to linuxactionnews.com slash subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch.
And check out my show, Late Night Linux, latenightlinux.com, if you want to hear more from me.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
Thanks for joining us, and we will see you next week.
Until then, have a great day, and I'll talk to you later.