Hello, and welcome to Linux Action News, episode 159, recorded on October 18th, 2020. I'm Chris.
And I'm Joe.
Hello, Joe. Good to be connected with you. And we start this week with the new and improved
Plasma 5.20.
The KDE developers say it's one absolutely massive release. More features, more fixes
for long-standing bugs, more improvements to the user interface. I think they might
be slightly over egging the pudding here. It is a good release, but it didn't seem like
a massive change from the last one to me.
Over egging the pudding. Yeah, from where I sit, it's a very small change. Because one
of the things that's fantastic about Plasma for a workstation is it just keeps the settings
that you've set. So if you deviate from the default and you do an upgrade, it almost always
keeps your deviation. And there's a lot of new things in Plasma 5.20. I think the biggest
one for example would be the task manager is now icon based and it's grouping windows
together. That's not how I use my task manager. And I did an update to 5.20 and everything
the way I like it is still just that way. And while it's really great to see these improvements
land and I think there are some really good ones in here, you might be right. Maybe they
are, as you say, over egging it just a bit. But I really appreciate as a workstation user,
I think I have gone through at least five or six fairly significant Plasma desktop updates
now on this desktop right here and it's all been really solid. It keeps working the way
I expect every single day. It just seems to get better. Well, I installed KDE neon because
I wanted to see it in its default state. And the icon only task manager so we're talking
about the panel or the taskbar as it would be in Windows. It's very Windows like now,
where you just have the icon. Now, to Linux users and people who are already used to a
different way of doing things, that's a bit alien. But I wonder if it is a good idea to
encourage new people who are used to this from not only Windows, but also Chrome OS.
And really kind of more like how mobile would work, I suppose, which has the most users.
Well, yeah, true. And the thing is that it's trivial to turn it back to what I would consider
normal, you just right click and then there's an option for alternatives. And then you can
just set it back. And it's just like, ah, okay, good, how we like because plasma is
just so configurable. But defaults are king and most people don't change them ultimately,
although maybe not with plasma because it is known for its configurability. So I don't
think it's a huge deal. I think that it could have upset people if it wasn't so easy to
change.
Yeah, the standard functionality is still there and working great. I think a lot of
the improvements that have gone into making plasma work on Wayland are easy to overlook
because Wayland is the story that just keeps on going. There's never really an end to the
Wayland improvements, it seems. And so it's easy to overlook those. But we're getting
to a really usable state now. There's some significant usability things that are now
baked into Kwin for the plasma desktop that X users that are transitioning to Wayland
would just expect like the ability for your screenshot tool to work or for the task manager
to preview the windows of their running applications, or K runner just showing up in the right place.
Those things didn't necessarily work right under Wayland. And the KDE community has really
been hitting this hard since 2019. And a lot of those efforts that have been just nonstop
every single release improvements are all kind of coming together and paying off in
520.
Yeah, and they're still looking at this from something of a legacy angle because one of
the bullet points under the Wayland improvements is the whole desktop session no longer crashes
if X Wayland crashes, which is important because this transition has been very, very slow.
And I don't think that we are anywhere near a full Wayland world yet. And so improving
aspects like X Wayland are going to be important probably for years to come still.
I do have to say with this release and with recent GNOME Shell releases, I think it is
possible to live daily life on Wayland in certain hardware combinations. I have several
machines and only one of them is full time Wayland because it just happens to be the
most stable combination, which is all Intel right now. And I think if you are on plasma
520, you're going to have pretty good results. There's other things in here though that are
nice because it just feels like it takes plasma closer to the metal. The system settings and
info center have gained a couple of new capabilities. Joey has a great article over at OMG Ubuntu
with screenshots of some of this that we'll have linked if you want to see it. But now
in there, you'll get smart monitoring for your hard drive so you get maybe a heads up
if you're going to have a hard drive issue, which seems really nice. And your touchpad
cursor speed can now be configured a little more accurately. And it's presented in a way
that's really easy to understand and use. It's just another example of bringing things
in a little bit closer, making it feel like plasma is fully integrated with the machine.
It's all one experience.
And there's some small areas of polish as well. Like they've redesigned the onscreen
display bubbles. Now they're much smaller and subtler. It's not a huge difference. I
had them side by side, the old one and the new one. And it does make a difference though.
Makes it feel slicker and just that little bit more polished, as I said.
I noted that you said you tried it with KD neon, which is what I'm using here as well.
And I think I've been running it since mid to late 2018 KD neon. And I've been upgrading
every single release of plasma as they've come out. And it has been a very rock solid
workstation. And like I started to mention at the top, it shows me how committed the
plasma desktop developers are to letting users create their own plasma desktop experience
and then trying to preserve it the best they can.
I feel like something's going on with neon. It's more than just a testbed for plasma developers.
I think they're making a sneaky workstation OS and they just don't want to admit it.
Well, that's something that Nate Graham talked about at Academy 2020 at the beginning of
October, how KD neon is kind of this halfway house. It's basically a distro, but it's
not officially. And maybe it should be a proper distro and the official showcase for KDE.
That's kind of how I've always seen it anyway, is it's the official showcase. It's the immediate
thought I go for. Okay, there's a new release of plasma. Well, let's download and install
KD neon because that's going to be the purest way to look at it.
Yeah, I've heard it implied that the existence of KD neon has deterred some distributions
from shipping plasma as their default desktop. And that's why we see so many of the enterprise
distributions and products that are focused at enterprise workstations using GNOME Shell.
That's the implication I've seen. I don't know if I buy that, but I do think that we
don't see enough enterprise workstation focused Linux desktops built on plasma. There's really
nothing out there right now. And I'd love to see KD neon just say, you know what, we're
gonna do it, we're gonna be the premier distribution for running plasma. And I guess maybe it would
take more resources, it would take a lot more than what the project probably currently has
scope for. I mean, they probably have their hands pretty busy just doing what they do.
So I wouldn't want to see it harm upstream plasma development. But I do feel like plasma
is pretty underrepresented in the workstation space, especially for how powerful it is and
what a great workstation desktop environment can be because it can really be suited to
match your environment's needs in a way that most desktops can't using really good sound
modern technology that has been clearly well maintained and has a good path forward. It
just seems like it just checks all the boxes. They even have an LTS release of plasma. And
yet we don't see it featured on any of these quote unquote enterprise distros. And maybe
neon needs to close that gap. I don't know. Maybe it's not possible. But it just seems
like such a shame because it's a great desktop environment that you really kind of have to
go find yourself. You have to go seek it out and you have to even know about it. And it
just sort of puts them on a disadvantage in that regard.
Yeah, I agree. I'd like to see it more widely used. Apart from anything else, it's more
familiar to people coming over from the Windows world. Even by default, it's pretty similar
to Windows in terms of the user experience compared to GNOME, which is just a complete
paradigm shift, which like it or not, whatever, it is very different from Windows, whereas
plasma, not so much.
System76.com. Let me reintroduce you to who they are. Go over there, check out System76
and see the combination of hardware and software. And if you get something, tell them the Linux
Action News sent you. Laptops are assembled in the US. You may have known that. But did
you know that the Thaleo workstation is designed and built in the US? The Thaleo even has a
flash sale right now. So if you're listening as this episode comes out, head over to System76
as soon as you can and take advantage of their flash sale because I don't know how long it's
going to last. You should jump in on that. What really makes System76 stand out now is
the special hardware combined with the excellent software. I've become a big fan of their auto
tiling extension recently released with Pop OS. It's built on modern tools, so it's sustainable,
a lot like their firmware tool, which is built on Rust. Also a sustainable, long term kind
of project. They measure twice and they cut once. It shows in their software and it shows
in their hardware. The current version of Pop OS just keeps getting better. Fractional
scaling has landed in Pop OS, hybrid graphics mode for external displays, and even more
is coming. So go over to System76.com. Reintroduce yourself to what they have to offer. It's
pretty great. System76.com. And when you're there, if you get something, tell them Linux
Action News sent you. System76.com. The integration of hardware and software has never been better.
System76.com. OpenOffice reaches the 20th anniversary mark and LibreOffice still seems
to be struggling to get out from underneath their shadow.
Yeah, the board of directors at the Document Foundation published an open letter this week
detailing how little development there's been of OpenOffice over the last six years and
showing the relatively frantic development of LibreOffice and basically saying to them,
look, give it up, guys. We should all be using LibreOffice now. Just let it die. Forward
all your users onto us. Now, I look at this and I think I understand why the Document
Foundation is doing this. They do have a much more actively developed office suite, which
is just better than OpenOffice, but they don't have the mindshare. And we've talked about
this before. Normal people still think of OpenOffice as the free alternative to Microsoft
Office. I suppose less so now with Google Docs and things, but if you want something
locally installed, oh, you don't need to pay for that Microsoft license, just go for OpenOffice.
So I do sympathize with them, but that's just not really how open source works. If you fork
something, you take the rough with the smooth. You are now in control of it, but you also
don't have the branding that the original product had.
Right. I'm sure people still refer to Nextcloud as own cloud very often.
I think that Nextcloud is a good example of this. I think they've done a better job of
marketing and getting their name out there. Maybe that's because we're in this Linux bubble
and maybe it's because it wasn't quite so established, own cloud as a brand. But to
me, that is a better example of how to do a fork and really push some marketing effort
with it. And LaborOffice have done to some extent, but here we are nearly 10 years after
they originally forked it. And still, they haven't got the mindshare that OpenOffice
has despite the lack of development with OpenOffice.
Well, I can go back even further. It's 20 years since Sun initially open sourced the
suite as OpenOffice. And then OpenOffice 1.0 didn't come out until two years later, 2002.
And then it wasn't until 2011 that Oracle transferred OpenOffice to the Apache Foundation.
And that's where we get 20 years from. So we have 20 years of OpenOffice. That's a long
time for a brand name. But when you look at the Nextcloud own cloud situation, there's
a key difference there. People are interested in file sync and hosted services that Nextcloud
offer. People are not interested in office software. What I think is really evident here
is the Document Foundation and the LibreOffice team have a complex around OpenOffice holding
them back. They look at that as that's what's limiting their success is the brand awareness
of OpenOffice instead of addressing the wider problem, which is making their product more
compelling. And yes, they've done things to make it nicer. But fundamentally, there's
just not a lot of room in this market. And there's not a lot of passion and interest.
And I think that's really what holds back LibreOffice, not that OpenOffice is beleaguered
out there just sort of around absorbing all these random downloads. So I decided this
morning to just take a crack at downloading OpenOffice to see what that experience is
like. If you're on a Debian system, it downloads 41 different devs in a tar gz file that expects
you to go through and figure out the dependency chain on your own to install. And then on
the Windows side, it's a super old installation process didn't bother going through because
I don't have a Windows machine handy, but I could tell it was archaic in nature. Additionally,
every modern Linux distribution for the most part, with some exceptions, ships with LibreOffice
already pre installed. And if you attempt to install OpenOffice when you have LibreOffice
on a system, that's not going to fly. So there's probably not really this ginormous amount
of drive by downloaders that are going and getting OpenOffice that would have otherwise
gotten LibreOffice if only there was a note on the OpenOffice website telling them where
to go. And what's even further evident when you dig in is this has become very much a
personality conflict between two projects that are more alike than they are different,
but yet they just can't seem to get along. And of course, there's a little bit of licensing
goodness in this mix that makes it so that LibreOffice can adopt changes in OpenOffice,
but OpenOffice cannot integrate changes from LibreOffice. So it's a one way improvement
window. And I don't really think the look of an open letter asking your competitor or
your former forked project to shut down and tell users to go somewhere else is a very
good one. It just comes across as, well, not very classy, and maybe a little combative.
That is true, but I don't think that your download experience there was typical. You
might say that the Windows experience is archaic or whatever, but isn't that the case with
most Windows applications? You just download the executable and then open it and next,
next, next, done, maybe reboot if you're unlucky.
Is that or is it the Windows store now? I don't know. I really don't.
I don't know. I haven't used Windows enough really in anger to know whether people are
using the store these days. I think most people who use Windows don't actually install much.
Doesn't an administrator do that for them? Whether that is a part of a corporate network
or whatever, or just someone's a technical friend or whatever sets things up for them.
But then if it's someone technical or a friend that's an enthusiast, they may already know
about LibreOffice.
Well, that's what I would argue that maybe not. Maybe not, you know.
It's possible.
And that's certainly what the Document Foundation are arguing.
That seems to be their main issue, is that people would know they exist if it wasn't
for that dang OpenOffice out there. And the OpenOffice folks responded in such. They said
we only wish that in addition to strongly encouraging a dual license contribution model,
the LibreOffice would also stop heavily campaigning for Apache OpenOffice's demise. And even if
somehow Apache OpenOffice died tomorrow, the idea that we would appoint LibreOffice or
any other singular project as OpenOffice's successor seems to indicate a lack of understanding
about nonprofit foundations and how they work. We must remain neutral. There are, after all,
other open source office suites available, each with their own audience and niche.
I was actually surprised that you didn't argue that an office suite doesn't need to be updated
that often. And the fact that it's been like six years since there's been any significant
update to OpenOffice is fine because the word processor is essentially done. I thought that
would be your argument.
Well, it's the compatibility argument that Microsoft keep changing the goal posts with
macros and stuff like that, that you do need to stay on top of it. Otherwise, you're going
to have cross compatibility issues. You're going to send people documents that just don't
look right. I mean, even now, I still send people PDFs. I just render it to a PDF and
then there's no chance of it not looking right. Even with basics like just Word documents
that are just like a basic invoice with a couple of different fonts or whatever. I've
had that show up with the bank details not working stuff. And you only have that once
when you have to send an invoice twice.
Yeah, that's a very good point. I think also we would be negligent if we didn't mention
that there's plenty of really good text editors available now if you just want to write. There's
purpose built text editors for all kinds of different writing. And then there is pretty
feature rich web based word processors like Google Docs and Office 365 that are available
to everybody that has an internet connection. And so I think when you combine the fact that
there is a very viable industry standard in Microsoft Office, when you add in a little
bit of open office brand recognition, combine that with the online word processors, and
it seems like there's probably not a very growing market for LibreOffice. It probably
much has a very established user base.
Yeah, I agree. It's sad, but I think it's true. I don't think we can kid ourselves that
people are looking to run something locally and natively when they can just fire up a
web browser and open a Google Doc for free. All you need is a Google account which is
free to get. And we in the open source world don't like that idea. A lot of people don't
trust Google or Microsoft or whatever and want to run things locally, but that does
seem like not exactly a growth market to me. You're right.
And I appreciate this is very much a dog bites man story in this regard, but it's painful
to see these two projects bicker publicly at each other in what seems like pandemic
and not really all of that meaningful differences, but they to them mean all of the world. And
you add in a little bit of license radicalization and it's just polar opposite opinions on certain
topics and they can't work together when clearly they each would benefit so much by collaborating
and they obviously share more in common than they have in actual technical differences,
but yet they just cannot see eye to eye. You add in the licensing differences between the
projects and it's oil and water and it makes me a little disappointed to see it still because
it's just it's such a waste of great resources, but yet they can't come to any kind of agreement
any kind of terms together and it seems like there's bad blood and I got to agree with
the folks at open office and the Apache Foundation. It does feel like LibreOffice is champion
a death watch for open office. I mean, let's face it now you and I are kind of watching
and thinking, okay, we'll see how long an open office sticks around now. It's on our
minds now.
Yeah, and I'm sure that people will write to us about the various online hosted versions
of LibreOffice that they're working towards, but it's just nowhere near Google Docs is
it or Microsoft. I've never actually used the Microsoft one, but even Dropbox has their
paper which is reasonably good and I just don't think that we are anywhere near there
with LibreOffice.
Yeah, and I think the other thing and this is I guess maybe my last thing on this is
I feel like teams, especially teams that are working from home are picking tools that work
for their jobs, you know, various kind of more specialized tools. An example here is
we very heavily use Kodi MD. So we have tons of documents we create at Jupiter broadcasting
lots and lots, but they're all in Kodi MD. We're not we're not using Google Docs or Office
365 because we want everything in markdown. We want real time collaboration. We want syntax
highlighting and we want to be able to render out real previews and share links with each
other over messaging platforms and whatnot. And so we just gravitated to mostly using
Kodi MD now and don't really consider writing anything else. So I don't even bother installing
an office suite.
You might want everything in markdown. Not everyone does.
Oh, they just don't yet.
Linode.com slash LAN. Go there to get a $100 60 day credit towards a new account. Linode
is the largest independent cloud computing provider. They started three years before
AWS because they saw the feature capabilities of Linux before just about anybody else. And
no matter what Linux skill you're at or what technology stack you use, Linode can help
your ideas come to life on the web. I was just going over my Linode dashboard. Their
cloud manager makes it really, really easy to use Linode. I currently have five running
rigs and four attached disks to those five running rigs. One of them is just using the
built in disk. But what's really nice about this is I wanted to create a reproducible
system so I could test something before I deployed it in production. And I discovered
Linode images which allow you to take a snapshot of your disk and then you can just deploy
them to any other Linode under your account. Man, is this super useful when you're trying
to bootstrap a master image for a large deployment or in my case, something I'm deploying over
and over and over again. You can upload that image to your cloud dashboard and just deploy
it when you need it. It's now available. There's no additional charge to store images
for Linode users. They're limited to six gigs, but that's it. That's your only limitation.
So now I'm rocking that preloaded with the stuff we need to do testing. It's also just
a great way to get a base install the way I want it. Linode has so many features that
make it just a default for me when I'm deploying something. I don't bother setting up a local
server anymore when I need something quick because they have $5 a month rigs. But on
top of that, what I really appreciate about Linode is they have access to infrastructure
and bandwidth. It's just not realistic for my small business or myself personally to
get access to. And unlike other entry level hosting services that lock you into their
platform, Linode gives you full back end access to customize and control your server to fit
your needs. I use their DNS manager to manage a couple of my domains right there inside
the Linode dashboard. It's really easy. They're independently owned and founded on a love
for Linux, which means they're in this for the long haul. They're not just a shoot to
the moon and see how big we can get. They have been building this over and over periods
of years independently. And you guys know I love that. They've been supporting Linux
and other open source initiatives like our favorite Kubuntu or our beloved Linux Fest
Northwest. So go see what I've been talking about. Go to linode.com slash LAN. You support
the show that lets them know you heard it here, but also it gets you that $100 credit
towards a new account for 60 days. If it runs on Linux, it runs on Linode. Linode.com slash
LAN.
Another week, another Bluetooth vulnerability. This time it caused a bit of drama though.
Yeah, it seems like there wasn't very much heads up given to the distributions or kernel
maintainers and at the same time that there wasn't a lot of heads up given Intel kind
of just started committing that the fix would land in certain versions of stuff without
actually talking to the projects and then had to walk it back. They said, for example,
the flaw we're about to talk about, the fix would be in kernel 5.9. And then they had
to walk that back and say, oh no, no, no, actually it's going to be in kernel 5.10.
And it's not like Intel doesn't know how to do this, right? They should know, especially
after meltdown, really how to nail this. And they blew it again. They dropped this on the
maintainers with no heads up. They got the announcement in the morning and the news was
public by the late afternoon.
You mentioned kernel 5.10. Well, at one point Intel said, oh, it's all fixed. It's available
in 5.10. And then people realized, hang on, that's not coming out until December. What
are you talking about Intel?
And you got to be thinking like Fedora 33 and Ubuntu 2010 that are just about to release.
They've got to be hustling now even after they've reached their relative freezes to
try to get this fix in. So here's the problem and what you need to worry about is it's a
flaw that resides in BlueZ, the software stack that by default implements all Bluetooth core
protocols and layers for Linux. Besides Linux laptops, it's used in a lot of consumer and
industrial Internet of Things devices. And it impacts any version of Linux after version
2.46 of the kernel. So it's been around for a while.
Well, that means most Internet of Things devices will be fine then.
Yeah, I'm sure. Yeah, because they're on 2.2.
Exactly.
It's known as Bleeding Tooth. It's a set of zero click vulnerabilities in the Linux
Bluetooth subsystem that can allow an unauthenticated remote attacker in a short distance, so they
have to be within range of your Bluetooth system, to execute arbitrary code with kernel
privileges on devices that are vulnerable.
But the reality is this is very specific. And if you were going to attack someone via
a Bluetooth vulnerability, you'd probably be using the older BlueBorn. So it's not quite
the huge catastrophe that some people are making it out to be. It still needs to be
patched.
Yeah.
And how Intel disclosed this appears to be not very responsibly or it certainly wasn't
managed very well. Either that or somehow everyone else was caught sleeping on this,
which seems less likely to me.
Ideally, Intel would have given the projects some heads up to start working on this because
once the information is out there, people will start working on tools to make it more
and more efficient to exploit it. This advisory is assigned a severity score of 8.3 out of
a possible 10. It's CVE-2020-1235-1 if you want to look it up. But I have to agree with
you, Joe. While technically it's an issue and it impacts many generations of Linux,
and I hate to see that, at the end of the day, it requires serious proximity to actually
exploit it. And it's only going to be able to do so much depending on the software hardware
stack combo. There's variations of success that they'll reach.
But it really just goes on the big pile of vulnerabilities for IoT devices that never
get updates, which is, let's face it, most of them.
Right. And without a doubt, it'll be all these vulnerabilities added up that the robots use
to exploit to take over and control everything and deploy their AI.
Sometimes I'm convinced that's already happened, man.
Pulled right out of the everyone saw this one coming file, the CUPS printing system
has essentially stopped development. It's seemingly dried up since the end of 2019.
Yeah, it was Michael Larabelle over at Phronix who brought this to everyone's attention.
And like he said, we all pretty much saw this coming when Michael Sweet left Apple at the
end of 2019. There's not many people left to work on it. So instead of there being 300-ish
commits per year, there's only been one in the whole of 2020. But the question is, does
this really matter anymore? Because printing seems to have moved on to driverless and more
of the functionality happening on the actual printers themselves rather than needing something
complex like CUPS.
Oh, I think very much. I'll get to that. So the background here, why is the Apple involved?
Well, they have to do with that Apple adopted CUPS, the common Unix printing system for
Mac OS in 2002. And they hired its author, Michael Sweet, in 2007. That's also when Apple
essentially acquired the CUPS source code. Sweet continued to work on printing at Apple,
using CUPS until December 2019 when he left to start a new company, which by the way,
I think it's actually working in the printing space, but more focused at receipt printers
and smaller printing labels and stuff.
Yeah. Asked at the time, though, by the register, what was going to happen with the future of
CUPS? He said, quote, CUPS is still owned and maintained by Apple. There are two other engineers
still in the printing team that are responsible for CUPS development, and it will continue
to have new bug fix releases, at least for the foreseeable future. So it's possible Apple
is working on an internal fork or branch that they're updating that they will then do a
code dump. Not ideal, but possible. But I'll tell you what, Joe, this is why CUPS matters.
CUPS changed my career. It was so massive for me. At the time, I worked at a bank that
had 40 branch locations. Every location had several tellers with the teller printers,
and they had big laser printers for the loans. And nothing could really handle this kind
of complex printing that they were doing, except for CUPS. I mean, it really, it saved
our bacon. And we had something at the time like 700 printers, or some, no, it was even
more than that. It was it was a ridiculous amount of printers. And you need something
that you can, you can go in there and you can tweak a little bit, you can customize,
you can load in a PPD and get support for a printer all of a sudden, you need something
that manages all of that and abstracts away the vendor implementations of protocols that
are always crap. And the thing that CUPS really was great at is they came out of the gate
with the internet print protocol support, and PPD support. So vendors could easily release
a file that made it possible to print on Linux, and it just changed the printing game for
Linux. The future projects that are out there, they're ambitious, I look forward to where
they're going. But for example, the one that's kind of more targeted for Linux from open
printing now, which is a fork of CUPS is removing PPD support. It's going to be great for home
users that go by a combo printer and put it on the network and Linux auto discovers it
like that is going to work better one day, which actually works pretty good today, but
it's going to work better one day. But what is going to take a major hit is the enterprise
side of things where you have central print servers that manage print queues, and people
have a total that they're allowed to actually print, there's print quotas, and things are
tracked to particular clients because it goes back to billing. Those kinds of systems need
something like CUPS. And I hate it when Linux has something and it's enterprise grade, and
you begin to depend on it, and then it fades. And we have to invent something new to replace
it, which is often better in some ways, but maybe is kind of lacking certain features
in other ways that make it not as great, not as one-to-one replacement. I feel like that's
the future we're going into is we won't have a good one-to-one replacement to CUPS. To
avoid going on though about printers forever, because I know not everybody cares, I just
put a few resources in the show notes. If you're curious about where printing is going,
what the Linux Foundation's open printing effort has in store, those links are in the
show notes at linuxactionnews.com. Linux.ting.com. It's mobile that makes sense. You just pay
for what you use. $6 for your line, and then you just pay for your minutes, your messages,
and your megabytes. I'm on Wi-Fi almost all the time, except for when I'm driving between
the studio and Lady Joops. It's Wi-Fi for me, and so it makes a lot of sense to only
pay for what I use. I maybe make two or three or four actual phone calls a week, tops, and
maybe it's even one actual phone call a week. The rest are all over VoIP. Why would I pay
for those cellular minutes that I'm not using? And rest assured, Ting has you covered with
three nationwide networks from coast to coast. There's a lot you can choose from. I've been
enjoying Verizon recently, and this is no-contracts mobile. There's no lock-in here. You just pay
for what you use, risk-free. You're in control the entire time, too. They have a fantastic
dashboard that lets you take complete control over your account. You can set usage alerts,
you can individually name different phones so you can check in on how little Susie's
doing on her new phone. And let's talk about devices. Of course, they're compatible with
the latest and greatest Galaxies or iPhones or Pixels or whatever you might want to throw
on there, but I would encourage you, if you don't have a phone already, go to Ting.com
slash shop. Well, do the show a solid. Go to Linux.ting.com. That way you get a $25
discount off the device, and it says, hey, I heard about it here on the show. I'm supporting
Linux Action News. They've got a bunch of really nice devices, like the Motorola Moto
E. Yeah, it's still a thing, and you can get it for $99 unlocked fully yours from Ting.
But if you have a device, that might be a great way to go. They have a compatibility
checker. Head over to Linux.ting.com and click on the Check Your Phone link. Then go in there,
put in your phone's IMEI, and it'll tell you if it's compatible with the Ting. If it is,
it's click, click, click. You don't even have to talk to a human. You're good to go, and
you'll get that $25 service credit. So then your first month, it's probably paid for.
That's how awesome Ting is. It's just that great. So go check it out. Get started. Linux.ting.com.
Well, my heart skipped a beat this week when I received an email from the AntennaPod team
telling me that a major new version had been released. I was panicking. Oh, no, they haven't
changed my favorite podcast player, have they? Well, they have, but only a little bit, and
I think ultimately they are improvements.
If you're on Android and you're like a power podcast listener, you should probably be looking
at AntennaPod. It has features that none of the other podcast catchers have, but they've
added a few things too that are new. An option to export your favorites to an HTML file.
They'll ask you if you prefer streaming over downloading when you just stream the podcast
very often, which is great if you don't have a lot of storage space or you're on Wi-Fi.
And they have feed settings to reduce volume or skip an episode's intro or ending if you
know kind of what the timing is. You can put them in there per feed and it'll just do that
for every episode for you. And then the one that I am super happy to see, even though
we don't take advantage of it today, support for chapter images is awesome because we do
chapters in almost all of our shows with some exceptions. And to be able to display something
up there is really nice in those rare times you need to show a visual. But there's just
a ton of other good stuff in AntennaPod, so it seems that version two is even better.
I'm assuming you got a chance to kick the tires?
Yeah, I immediately updated when I got this email and was immediately relieved. And then
I've just been discovering little changes since. It did kind of feel like it was due
for an update. It'd been a while. The last update, I didn't like it, changed it completely,
but I got used to it. And now they're adding these features like they've been able to set
a certain number of seconds that you skip at the beginning or end and you can sync with
G Podder and everything. It does feel like a proper modern podcast player now. And the
fact that it is, I mean, it's really the only game in town in terms of open source podcast
players on Android at least. I feel like I could recommend it before this update because
it's open source to Linux people. Whereas now with the additional features, I feel like
I can just recommend it just full stop. Like it is a great podcast player. They do mention
in the press release for this that they're going to soon add support for podcastindex.org,
which is the new database from Adam Curry, which is kind of his open competitor to Apple
podcast and Spotify. We'll have to see if that actually takes off. I'm a little bit
skeptical, but it's good that they're thinking about the future anyway and adding that in.
And also related to this release was a community led effort to redesign the logo. And Intendapod
put it out to a public vote. There was a ratings and analysis and they made their decision
and they have a new logo as part of this process too that was made by their own community.
Which does look more modern and seems to kind of fit in more with the other modern app icons
that I can see on my phone. But it's different and I don't like change. So I wish I could
just have the old one. But as much as I don't like change, a change is coming to this show.
Yeah, it's mixed news, really. It's good news in the sense that our buddy Drew has a new
job and it looks like a good job for him and we're excited for him. But it also means that
we have a gap in who will be editing Linux Unplugged. And ladies and gentlemen, Linux
Unplugged is a particularly challenging kind of show the way we do it. And there's really
only a few people that are qualified to edit. And with Drew stepping out to take on his
new gig, it leaves us with the need of an editor. And the only other qualified person
I know to edit that show is Joe, which is a big ask and it's a big time commitment.
Yeah. And we kind of talked about this and how to try and make it work. And ultimately,
I only really have time to either do that or this. And so Wes is going to step up and
take over from me on this show. I couldn't think of a better person to do it. Wes and
Drew would be the kind of toss up. Drew's way too busy with his new job. Wes is the
man for the job.
Yeah. And Wes has always been helping the show behind the scenes. He's often stepped
in when one of us needed a weekend off. And he's always been following the news very closely.
And so he's going to be able to step in and just hit the ground running. And that's going
to be great for the show production, but it's also going to be great to just get his take
on the news because he's got a really sharp eye. And he's thought a lot about these. And
while I know Wes will do a great job, I of course will miss doing this show with you.
So you'll have to come by Linux Unplugged from time to time and harass us. And of course,
I think you got to come back for the end of year predictions review.
Yeah, definitely. I'm going to come back and make sure that I beat you. I'll manage to
twist the facts so that I beat you on that. And you know, if you or Wes are away, then
I'll be around to step in. But it's just that weekly commitment that I don't have time for.
Yeah. And as part of bringing JB back to Indie, JB 3.0, is we want to try to keep everything
sustainable. We don't want to overdo it and burn ourselves out. We've learned our lessons.
We know what's sustainable and we know what's not. And so that's also at play here. It's
just in part for the longevity of the show because I don't want to burn either one of
us out. And it will be nice to have you come by and visit from time to time.
And who knows what might happen in the future if circumstances change and timings and schedules
work out better. I could end up coming back.
Yeah. Although I'm never talking to you again, obviously.
Yeah, obviously.
Also, you know, maybe go subscribe to the All Jupiter Broadcasting Shows feed. You never
know what could be in the future as things change. And the first place you'd see something
like a new show or something like that would be in the All Shows feed. So you can find
the All Jupiter Broadcasting Shows feed in your podcast catcher or at our website.
I will be back for one last episode next week, though. So go to linuxactionnews.com slash
subscribe for all the ways to get new episodes.
And go to linuxactionnews.com slash contact for ways to get in touch.
We'll be back next Monday with our weekly take on the latest Linux and open source news.
You can find me at chrislass.com.
And check out my shows, Late Night Linux and 2.5 Admins.
Thanks for joining us and we will see you next week.
Have a great night, son.