Hi, everyone, it's Joe here. And today I'm going to talk to you about what I've learned
over the last seven years of being a podcaster. And the last kind of 18 months of being professional
full time with it. Let me get this caveat out of the way. First of all, these are just
my opinions. And you may have differing opinions. If you do, I'd love to hear from you. I'm
always interested in a conversation about these things. There's as much art as there
is science in this. And everyone has their own way of doing things. This is just what
I think. So if you want to get in touch with me, then at Joe Rissington on Twitter, or
extras dot show slash contact. So with that out of the way, the first part of this is
the recording space, where you're going to actually be when you record. Now, most people
will be looking to do this in their home office, let's say. Now, the ideal office has got no
clutter in it, a lovely hardwood floor, minimalist decor, lots of hard surfaces everywhere. Well,
unsurprisingly, that is a terrible studio. It's a terrible studio, because all those
hard surfaces create echo. And that is what you don't want on your recordings. What you
ideally want is to have as dead a sound as possible. And by that, I mean, no echo, no
reverb, no anything else apart from your voice. And so there are a few ways of getting rid
of that echo. The first one is just with basic physics. If you surround yourself with soft,
fluffy things, then they will absorb the reverberations, the echo, and make it sound better. So just
generally lots of stuff and clutter is a good start. So not being tidy, not having perfect
hard surfaces everywhere, that can help. Having a carpet or a rug rather than a wooden floor,
that's a great start. Even getting things like cushions and pillows or duvets, comforters,
blankets, whatever, and just trying to cover up the surfaces and just trying to get as
much of that bulk into the room with you and towels and bedsheets, just anything soft.
Now if you want to spend some money on this, the first thing that you can do is get some
acoustic foam panels. They're usually around about a foot by a foot or 30 centimeters by
30 centimeters. And they come in various colors. Black is the most common. But you can either
get kind of a bobbly pattern on them or sometimes they have like a row of teeth like in a triangle
pattern. It doesn't really matter what you go for. It's just that same basic physics
principle that they are soft and foamy and will absorb sound and reverberations. So you
can stick them all over your walls. Obviously that doesn't look great. You can do it quite
artistically if you're not like me and then it can look okay but it's generally not going
to get spousal approval. What you can do if you're a little bit handy and practical is
build yourself some sort of room divider. That's something that Drew did and there's
a blog post that we can link to telling you how he did it. And that is basically the same
principle as sticking these foam panels on your wall but it's just on something that
can be folded away and looks a bit neater when you're not recording. Of course if you
want to get really serious then setting yourself up in a dedicated space for recording is the
best. Now if you're in America you might have a big enough closet to do that and thankfully
closets tend to be full of clothes which are soft and absorb sound and so that is a great
place to start. Now I hope Elle doesn't mind me saying this but that's where she records
in her closet and I think it sounds great on her recordings. Or you could build yourself
a little room like I have. My room isn't ideal because it's quite small and I've got bedsheets
hanging on the walls of it. I'm not very happy with it to be honest. I have ordered some
acoustic panels. I've got some up. They helped a little bit but I need to put some more up
so I need to get some more of them and I'm hoping that I'll be happier with the sound
after that. But it's kind of good enough for me and most importantly being in London it's
very loud around here. There's a lot of planes and just general noise and being in a dedicated
room kind of helps with that. Now the second topic is types of microphone. There are essentially
two main types of microphone that you can buy. One of them is a condenser and the other
is a dynamic. The main difference between a condenser microphone and a dynamic microphone
is that the condenser requires power and is more sensitive and in ideal situations and
a stress ideal it sounds better or can sound better than a dynamic mic. A dynamic mic doesn't
require power and it is less sensitive and in an ideal studio setting might not necessarily
sound as good as a good condenser. Some typical examples are the Blue Yeti and the Blue Snowball.
They are condenser mics and they are incredibly popular and they are a terrible microphone
for most people getting into podcasting. I have got the Rode NT1 which I'm talking to
you on now. Again I'm not massively happy with it but it's doing the job and I'm happy
enough. The most common dynamic mic is a Shure SM58. That is what you'll see stand-up comedians
and singers generally in a live situation using. They are great microphones and you
could do worse than that. I know some guys who do professional podcasting with them.
It's not necessarily my first choice but they are okay. The Rode Podcaster which is used
on BSD now, Benedict and Alan have both got one, that's an okay mic. That's USB and dynamic.
Most of the Jupiter broadcasting crew have got an Electro Voice RE320. That is basically
everyone apart from Chris. He has an RE20 which is basically a better version of that
because he's the boss. He has to have the best obviously. Some of the pros and cons
of these microphones. The condenser, the pros are that it sounds better in a perfect setup
in my opinion. Some people may disagree with that but I think it does. It's also more forgiving
of poor mic technique. By poor mic technique, if you drift away a little bit like this or
you're talking around the side of it, it doesn't sound great but it's not as bad as it can
be with a dynamic mic where you have to have really good mic technique because if you drift
away from it, even a little bit like this, I'm a few inches away, the drop-off in volume
is a lot more than with a condenser so it's more forgiving if you don't have a good technique.
The cons of a condenser mic are that it picks up everything in the room and beyond the room
and I mean everything. If I shuffle my feet around, that's just rubbing on the carpet,
you can hear that quite clearly. With a dynamic mic, you'll hear a lot less of that. Also
the echo factor, if you haven't got a perfect room then it's going to pick up a lot more
of that echo versus your voice which you want it to pick up. I tend to fiddle with things
while I'm recording as well. I've kind of got a bit better at that but if there's anything
like sweet wrappers, it picks up that really loudly or clicking pens or anything and anything
outside as well. I live fairly near Heathrow and so sometimes there's planes going over
that are really loud and my condenser mic picks that up quite loudly and I have to kind
of pause and edit it out which is very annoying and noisy neighbours and sirens and dogs and
just anything you can imagine that's outside, it will pick that up potentially. Whereas
with a dynamic mic, it picks up more of your voice compared with that other noise that
you don't want including echo from your room. One of the main disadvantages is that it requires
good mic technique. You have to stay in the sweet spot so I haven't got a dynamic mic
here to demonstrate that but if you drift away from it then it can give quite a different
sound and it just sounds a bit weird so you need to kind of be much better at working
the mic. Now whether you go for a condenser mic or a dynamic, you have two choices at
that point. Either you go for a USB microphone or you go for a microphone with an XLR connection
which you then need to plug into an interface which then plugs into the computer. Whereas
with a USB mic, it's much simpler. Just a mic, a USB cable and a computer. However,
if you buy a USB only microphone like the standard Yeti, you are limited in that it
has to be USB connection. You can't use it in any other situation. You can't upgrade
the mic and keep your interface. It's cheaper to buy a USB mic than a mic and an interface
but I think it's kind of like buy cheap, buy twice situation. If you buy an interface that's
good enough and even a fairly cheap one, less than $100, I think the one that a lot of the
crew uses is the Zoom U22. I think you can pick that up for 50 pounds sometimes on Amazon.
That will allow you to try out different microphones and upgrade microphones over time whereas
with a USB mic, you're just stuck with it. Another big disadvantage of using a USB mic
is that they tend to be quite noisy because if you're going to cram all of the electronics
that make it an audio interface into a microphone, then the electronics are kind of too close
to the capsule, the thing that picks up the sound. So often with Yetis, I get recordings
from people who have used Yeti and it's full of kind of ground noise, just buzz and hiss
and it's just not ideal really whereas you are less likely to suffer from that kind of
thing with a proper USB interface and XLR microphone.
One thing that's quite important regardless of what kind of microphone you use is a pop
shield or pop filter as they're sometimes called. That is to remove what we call plosives
or the puh-puh sound. Now if I come around and get out of the way of my pop shield and
I say Peter Piper, you'll hear how terrible that sounds whereas if in front of my pop
shield I say Peter Piper, you can hardly hear that plosive sound.
The two main types of those are the foam type which is kind of a round foam thing that you
push over the microphone and they are somewhat effective. They're definitely better than
nothing and they look better if you're doing video because they obscure your face less
than the other type which is kind of the arm type as I call it that clamps to the mic stand
and then it's a circle with a kind of thin layer of foam usually that you can move around
and put in front of the microphone. Now they're better if you're only doing audio but maybe
the foam round type that fits over the mic is better if you're doing video.
So once you've got your gear sorted you want to record your actual podcast. Now I'm assuming
that most people will be doing this remote. It's kind of a little bit different if you're
doing it in person but it's more likely that you're going to find compatible people online
and that's kind of how most Linux podcasts are done these days so let's assume you're
doing that. I'm not going to talk about any software specifically. I'm going to try and
talk about principles here because it doesn't matter whether you're using something like
Audacity or Ardour or Reaper or GarageBand or whatever it is you're using. The principles
are roughly the same. Now what we always do when we record a podcast is make sure that
we're all recording and then we record some absolute silence. If you've ever caught Linux
Unplugged live you will have listened to this. Now the reason that you record absolute silence
is it's not actually silent. When you stop talking you stop moving you stop breathing
what you record is hiss, hum, buzz, all the stuff that you want rid of. Now if you record
a bit of absolute silence for say five or ten seconds then you can use noise removal
software to get rid of all that hiss that you don't want. I use Audacity for this but
there are tons of other ways of doing it but the principle is always the same. You need
to train the algorithm on the silence the stuff that you want rid of and then apply
that to the whole recording. I cannot stress enough how important it is for this silence
to be absolute silence. If you're training an algorithm on what you want to remove and
you leave in scratching of neck beards or shuffling feet or breathing then it's going
to detract from the sound quality of what is left after you've removed that noise. That's
why whenever I come to do my noise removal I listen to the absolute silence and make
sure that it is just the hiss and buzz and everything we want rid of and that there is
no breathing or whatever. I do that by turning the volume up to the absolute max that I can
get it and then I listen out for just even little sounds and try and select a bit of
that audio that is just the silence that you want rid of. That's why it's very important
to capture that silence properly in the first place. Assuming that your recording all went
well and everyone has sent you their flack or wave file or whatever and you line them
up in Audacity or whatever software you're using one of the first things that you'll
probably want to do is EQ equalization. There are various different types of EQ plugin but
the type that I like the best is parametric EQ because that is a good visual representation
of all of the audio frequencies. Generally speaking on the left that's going to be the
lower frequencies and then on the right it's going to be the higher frequencies. So usually
they go way lower than humans can even hear to real sub bass on the left and then to really
high pitched frequencies which if you're a little bit older like me you can't hear anymore.
Now the basic EQ that I use is just cutting the low end the real low end boom as I call
it and we're talking about the real bassiness here of a person's voice. The reason that
I do that is because people who listen in a car to podcasts which is quite common their
car stereos tend to have a lot of bass in them and if there's too much rumbling bass
in someone's voice then it makes it very difficult to hear what they're actually saying because
it's just boom and rumble rather than the bits that you want to hear of their voice.
Once I've done that then it's a case of either boosting or cutting various frequencies depending
on the quality of the recording how that compares to other people's voices and I tend to be
quite sparing with EQ because it's quite easy to mess it up and make it sound terrible.
Drew tends to use more EQ than I do and this is something that is a real art rather than
science this is what you want it to sound like and the only real way to know what you
want it to sound like is to experiment and maybe there might be a particular frequency
that you want rid of or maybe someone's kind of muffled and you want to boost the high
end it's too individual for me to tell you exactly how to do it unfortunately.
The next thing is compression now we're not talking about compression like zip compression
or mp3 compression we're talking about dynamic compression that means that the parts where
it's really loud will become quieter and the parts where it's really quiet will become
louder and it makes everything roughly the same volume now much like with EQ the right
level of compression is very much subjective if you listen to the radio they tend to use
a lot of compression and I mean a lot to the point where someone yelling at the top of
their voice would be the same volume as if they're whispering into the microphone there's
real divided opinion on this I tend to use quite a lot of compression as I said because
I think about people driving in their cars again if there are too many dynamics in the
volume of the podcast then it makes it difficult to listen to because you're constantly having
to turn it up and then the next person speaks really loud and you have to turn that down
again or someone might have inconsistency in the level that they are talking and compression
is a quick and dirty fix for that but it does have a sound in of itself so again it's something
you have to experiment with the more you compress it the more it's going to sound like radio
some people like their mixes to breathe they like it to have a lot of dynamic in it but
personally I would rather use a little bit too much compression than not enough and so
the final thing is editing now some people record live to tape line it all up export
it job done that's not what I tend to do I tend to go through and edit it properly this
could be a whole episode in of itself how to actually do editing but I'll give you a
few tips that I always give people the first is leave a beat and by that I mean if you
get to the end of a sentence there's usually a cap between that sentence and the next sentence
if you listen to me now I'm leaving pauses there because that's how humans talk a very
common mistake that people make is doing the cut at the end of a sentence and then they
cut from the beginning of the next sentence and then they mash them together so there
is no gap between them I'll give you a very quick example of that now I'll now speak the
next sentence and then I'll speak the next sentence and then I'll speak the next sentence
as I recorded that I left a standard pause like you'd expect in any human conversation
but you hear how that sounded a bit weird well that is a mistake that a lot of people
make it's almost become a style on YouTube now there are huge YouTubers whose style is
like that and I cannot watch their videos because it's just too annoying it's too frantic
every time they edit they don't leave the beat in there and it's it's kind of younger
people maybe get off my lawn whatever I don't know maybe people like to listen to audio
that is edited like that I certainly don't another tip is don't cut off breaths I suppose
I will give you an example of that now if you cut off the breath there you hear that
sounds a bit weird the best way if you are doing a cut that involves a breath is to use
fades fading in and fading out but again that takes a bit of practice the final tip when
it comes to editing is listen back in full because things can go wrong you may get through
your edit and you think you've done everything perfectly and you export it and then you publish
it and then you go to bed and then you wake up to a bunch of comments saying well what
was that weird bit in there or how come there was no audio on the left channel for 20 minutes
or whatever I think that it is a disrespect to the audience to not listen back how do
you expect them to listen to your whole show if you can't even be bothered to do it yourself
yes it adds the length of the show to the process so if you're doing a two-hour show
then that's two hours of listen back but I think you've got to do it and I think that's
what sets apart people who care from people who don't and my final tip here is don't mess
with your recording machine we in the Linux world like to distro hop a lot and try out
different desktop environments and try new software all the time I do not recommend that
I recommend if at all possible whether it's a partition or a physical machine get it so
it's working and leave it that way get another laptop pick up a cheap think pad or something
if you want to mess around with different distros set yourself up with a machine that
works and just leave it that way because there is nothing more upsetting to the creative
process than technical difficulties you sit down to record something like I decided to
sit down and record this today if I had had technical issues it would have been very frustrating
and would have probably led to me not recording this whereas I have a setup that I know works
I plug in my various equipment start recording simple so don't mess with your recording machine
so well done if you made it this far with me rambling about all this stuff like I said
at the beginning these are just my opinions and there may be stuff that you can teach
me and if you can great get in touch let's start a conversation about this because I'm
always willing to learn and also let me know if you want more detail or specifics on any
of the topics that are covered here at Joe Rissington on Twitter or extras.show.com