Hi everyone, Joe here with another User Error Extra. This time it's a conversation that
I didn't want to put in the main show. It was a conversation that we kind of needed
to have and we're going to have regardless and I thought let's record it and see how
it works out and maybe release it as an extra. I didn't want to put current events in User
Error. That's not what the show is about. The show is supposed to be entertainment and
it's supposed to take your mind off things. But I knew that if we didn't have this conversation
before we recorded the main show then the current events would slip into the show somehow.
I didn't actually tell Dan and Poppy what my plan was. I just asked them the question
once we'd started recording and kind of had in the back of my mind that maybe it'd work
as an extra and so that's why at the beginning of a recent episode you heard Dan say that
they'd been tricked into recording an extra but I checked with them and they said it was
fine to put it out. So without further ado, let's hear it.
What do you think is going to change as a result of all of this virus business? Is working
from home going to become the norm? Is that going to be the answer to climate change or
are people just going to go back to normal when it gets back to normal?
I think a lot of people will go back to normal but I think people will have that realization
that actually is technically possible for a lot of people. Yes, I know some people can't
but a lot of people can actually technically work from home and also the fact that the
kids can be schooled from home. I know some people school from home already but my kids,
Sam has been sat there with iPad out and being set work and normally he'd be sat in the classroom
with a bunch of his mates but he's actually in his bedroom working.
But isn't school about interacting with other kids and learning life lessons rather than
learning the actual school work? Well, it's a bit of both really. I think what it might
end up being is people realize that a proportion of work can be done remotely. It doesn't have
to be 100% on site. Maybe one day a week they stop going to school and maybe they work from
home. There's 20% of your carbon footprint knocked on the head in one go.
Yeah, definitely would be interesting to see if more people are just straight up working
from home or if there's more of like a hybrid approach.
I think you're probably right that hybrid approach will be what it is and it might be
half and half maybe and you'll schedule days that you need to work together or whatever
and it'll be, I don't know, maybe it'll be the norm to mostly work from home because
what I'm wondering is who is going to be the first office to say, right, everyone come
back in then. No one's going to want to be that firm, are they?
No, I think they'll all do that.
Yeah, I think they will too. They won't give a shit.
But I do think there's the possibility that this is going to be beneficial for the employer
as well because those days that someone might stay at home when the gas man is coming or
when they need to have their boiler serviced or whatever it might be, rather than taking
a day off and not being able to do any work because they're at home, maybe they'll organise
it so actually you can work from home on the day when you have to be there, like whatever
the life thing is that you have to do and the employee benefits because they don't have
to take a day off to do it and the employer benefits because you're not losing a day's
productivity out of someone. Yeah, okay, it might be slightly different productivity and
they can't come into meetings and stuff but there will be proof that it manifestly is
possible because for months we'll have been doing it.
Yeah, I wonder how many people will not be taking sick time or PTO when they just don't
want to come into the office and be like, you know, I'm feeling a little bit under the
weather today, I'm just going to work from home today.
I think companies will certainly enact policies. I think it will be employee-led, there will
be employees pushing from the bottom and innovative companies will push from the top and say,
hey, it really works during coronavirus, we're going to do a sea change. I mean, they could
reduce their office size, they can reduce the infrastructure that they need inside those
offices and reduce their carbon footprint, all the things that people want to do, reduce
their costs, you know, if they've got an expensive office in a central city. There's so many
things about working remotely that even if you only do it half the time, everyone benefits.
How wild would it be if more offices just like rented a co-working space every once
in a while, you just kind of had a rotating schedule and one company shares, you know,
an office building with five other companies and they just each go in one different day?
Yeah, I don't doubt that those companies that run those type of places are going to be showing
research after all this calms down that, you know, co-working places are the best way to,
you know, optimize your homeworking, you know, strike that balance between someone working
at home and working in an office because you get the benefit of being in a room with other
people and you're not traveling a long distance into the office maybe. I don't know. I think
you're right.
What's that going to mean for the price of rents and property, commercial property in
central locations? If there are fewer people working in those locations, then each office
will scale down or be looking to scale down or share spaces or whatever. So there'll just
be less demand. So does that mean that the price will go down and therefore will housing
go down as well closer to the center?
Possibly.
I don't know because I feel like that there's so many places that are just vacant even before
all this, where the landlords didn't want to lower the rent and they were like, well,
we think we can get this much for it. And they're just vacant for like years. It's weird.
You'd think they would just lower the prices, but they just like hold out.
Not in the UK because they brought in a law that says that if you are the landlord of
a commercial premises and it's vacant, I think if it's vacant at all, you have to pay the
business rates, which is like one of the taxes you have to pay for a business. And so that's
normally paid for by the tenant. But if it's empty, then the landlord has to pay it. So
not only are they not getting income, it's actually actively costing them money. And
so that is the incentive to lower the rents and get businesses in there.
So one of the things Canonical did in London is we downsized the head office. We had like,
I don't know, a half of a floor in a building. And because some people work from home and
then some people left and maybe weren't replaced, then we had a lot of people quite spread out
in half a floor of a fairly sizable building. So they squished everyone up a little bit.
It's not like super compact, it's like reasonable space. But they squished everyone up a little
bit, got rid of a few meeting rooms and carved off a chunk. And that's I don't know, legally
how they've done it, whether it's sublet or they've given it back to the building. But
there's now an additional company now in that building in central London. So maybe that's
the way you do it. Because you downsize your company, move to another office or shrink
the office you're in and either sublet it out to somebody else or turn that into co-working
space. And other people could come and maybe your or some of your people could use that
as co-working space. But also you could have other people coming in and using it as co-working
space. So I don't necessarily think that the downsizing will necessarily be a bad thing
for rent because people will still want spaces to meet with people, I think.
And maybe people who otherwise couldn't afford big offices in town, they can afford a smaller
one. So maybe it'll work. I still think that there will be, instead of a premium on premises
and houses in town, I think the premium will start to shift towards decent internet and
infrastructure and house prices. I'm not saying it'll be the only factor, but I think that
going forward, people will be seriously looking at the potential internet speed of houses.
And before it was just, oh, it's got broadband, that's fine. If that was 20 megabit, now that
they'll be thinking, well, that's not good enough. I only want to live somewhere that's
like 50 or 100 plus. And maybe that will now be a factor on the cost of housing.
I don't know anyone who doesn't factor the speed of their broadband into-
Yeah, because you work in IT. But normal people just, you know, has it got internet? Has it
got broadband? Yeah. Okay. And then they, you know, they just deal with like six or
10 megabit DSL or whatever.
Yeah. I definitely think I agree with Joe that I don't think the majority of people
really understand how much bandwidth is or what things require or like, I don't even
really know anything about like, what does a reasonable latency? Like, I don't know.
So I think that that's not something that people really understand. And I don't know
if this will necessarily get them to understand. They'll just be like, well, it didn't work.
The internet's not good.
Maybe the internet providers, the broadband providers will have a work from home package
that like optimizes zoom and hangouts and, you know, video chat stuff, optimizes that
traffic. And, you know, during the during the day and Netflix during the evening or
something like that, you know, maybe, maybe they'll start marketing towards those people
who are looking to work from home and have their little office. Maybe people will start
advertising, you know, better office equipment for home, like tailored for home that has,
you know, a nice laptop desk and you know, that stuff that is already there, but they'll
be marketed directly towards people who want to work from home. I think we'll probably
see more of that as well.
You know, what I'm really interested to see is how many people just absolutely blow through
their data caps, like every month, because that's the thing that not so much here, but
in America, that's pretty standard to have a cap, isn't it?
Yeah. And luckily, the provider that I have doesn't have a cap. But when I had Comcast,
like we had, I don't know, three, four people using it, and we would be at or, or above
our data cap, like almost every month and had to start telling people like, hey, okay,
like we need to figure out how to not, you know, watch as many movies or whatever is
going on, because we're going to get charged pretty quick here.
Yeah, I have read that that is surely going to happen that they're going to have to lift
those caps, at least temporarily. It's interesting how all the things that you think are set
in stone in life have suddenly been changed. Like, I think yesterday, I saw a tweet from
the transport minister that the annual motor vehicle testing, because people can't leave
their house and can't take their car to a garage and have it tested, that's just going
to be extended for six months. So if your car after 30th of March is due for its MOT
test, then you just get extended for six months. Mine's due on the 28th of March. So I'm a
little bit salty about that.
I'm a little confused personally about what to do with my residential parking permit,
because the Department of Revenue is closed. So I can't go in to submit my documents to
get a new one. And it expires at the end of the month. So I have no idea who the hell's
going to come around and give you a ticket. There's like nobody working. It's not like,
I don't know, is a traffic enforcement officers out in the street? I don't know. I mean, that's
the question is like, there's been no statements. There's not even information. They didn't
even say on the website that we're going to be closed. It's weird. So it's like, I don't
know what's going to happen. Am I just going to get tickets all of a sudden and then have
to be like, Oh, okay. Well, you weren't even open. How am I supposed to get a pass? We're
living in weird times.
That's what I mean. It's like, everything's up for grabs. Everything can be changed. Suddenly
my wife gets furloughed from work. She just gets an email that says, Hey, you've been
furloughed. Stay at home. Don't come in. You'll be paid 80% of your salary up to two and a
half thousand, whatever, whichever, you know, and that's it. Like she's been knocking around
the house thinking, what the hell am I supposed to do? I, you know, I was working last week.
I was going to work and now I'm sat at home and the house is tidier than it's ever been.
I can tell you. So yeah, that's quite good.
It's really weird for me. Like I'm just stuck in the house all the time, just making podcasts
and sitting on my ass drinking and occasionally going out for a walk at night. It's my life
has just been turned upside down by this.