G's here and I've recently been falling in love with ThinkPads again. I've owned a few over the
years and specifically used ThinkPads and how you can get more value for your money out of a use
ThinkPads. And so the one and only person that I could think to bring on to talk about ThinkPads
is of course Alan Pope. Many of you know him as Popey. So how are you doing Mr. Popey?
I'm doing very well. Thanks for asking me on. I'm not the world's biggest expert on ThinkPads,
but I think you could class me as an enthusiast.
Yeah. So how did you originally get into ThinkPads? Like what was your first one?
Was it a hand-me-down or a work machine or what was it?
So I used to do IT support for companies years and years and years ago. And I think I came
across ThinkPads at some point. I worked for one of the big six accountancy firms and some of their
accountants had ThinkPads. And I liked them then because as an IT support person, you know, if you
had to do any maintenance, they were easy to work on. You could take them apart easily. You could
swap out the battery, the hard drive. They were just really easy machines to work on. And so that
set it in my mind that ThinkPads are always this high bar for laptops from a maintenance point of
view and reliability as well. And I never really owned one back then. That was in the mid to late
90s. I never had one until working through IBM. And obviously everyone who worked through IBM
got a ThinkPad. And so I got one given to me, well, you know, on loan while I'm working there.
And that's when I properly fell in love with it because I installed Ubuntu on it
and everything just worked. And it just felt super reliable and robust. And, you know,
I could lob it in my bag and it just felt like the perfect laptop for me for all of the reasons,
you know, robustness, ease of maintenance, everything worked. And so it just ticked all
the boxes as soon as I got that one workstation ThinkPad.
Aaron Alexander Excellent. So
do you remember what model it was or what the specs were on that first ThinkPad? Because this
would have been in the late 90s then?
Jason Vale No, this one would have been quite a bit later. So this would have been in the 2000s,
around about 2004, 2005. No, later than that, about 2006, something like that. And that would
have been a W series. So for those who don't know, the ThinkPads have like the first letter
defines the series of ThinkPad and the W's are the workstation ones. So it was a workstation
of some kind. I know it had an NVIDIA GPU. So it was it was quite chunky. And it was mostly
sat on my desk at work. But yeah, that was that was the first one. So I actually went in high.
I didn't get an entry level one. I got a really decent spec machine as my first one, which I think
probably helped.
Aaron Alexander Yeah, I would imagine that that would help. So
the workstation series, is that still the series that you kind of go along with? Do you is there
is there a series that you gravitate to more on your personal buys?
Jason Vale Yeah, it really depends. And I mean, I have
a number of ThinkPads and they're a mixture, but they're a mixture between the X series,
which are the kind of lightweight workstation, the one that's a little bit thinner, a little bit
narrower. So the keyboard generally goes right to the edge of the machine. There's not like a big
gap either side. Whereas the T series are more the corporate desk-bound laptops, and those are
slightly wider. And then the workstation ones are the higher end ones. So I mostly got X series
laptops and T series laptops, but some of them are so old that they predate that naming scheme.
So they're, you know, they're R90 or R something. And most of the ones I've got are that I actually
use are relatively modern, like within I say relatively modern, we're talking within the last
eight years. And but I've got a bunch that are much older than that. And those are kind of the
retro ones that don't fit that naming scheme. But currently, it's mostly X series and T series
machines.
Aaron Alexander Right. Yeah, I've actually got one that I
when I purchased a vinyl cutter from a friend of mine, they gave me an old ThinkPad that was running
I think Windows 95 or something that actually still has a parallel port because that's what
the printer needed. So I'd have to dig it out to see what it is. But it currently isn't in use.
I probably will never use it again, in fact. So how many ThinkPads do you own now?
Jason Vale That's a good question. Is it bad that I
don't know?
Aaron Alexander No, it's not.
Jason Vale So my main machine that I'm sat talking to
you on is a T450. And that's the one I use all the time. And that's the one I sit in a docking
station and I run it with three displays. And I've upgraded the drives in it and I've upgraded
the RAM. And that's my main workhorse. I've even replaced the display with a better display. So
it's like, that's the one I'm sat looking at all the time. The previous ThinkPad I had was an X220.
So that dates from around 2012. My general guide is, when you're looking at the X series and the
T series, the middle digit equates to the year of manufacture roughly. So if you're trying to
think how old a machine is, a 220 was made in 2012. And a 230 was made in 2013. So that gives
you an idea of how old it was. Mine dates from around 2012, my X220.
Aaron Alexander Okay, yeah, I was actually
looking at some of the X220s in the X series myself.
Jason Vale They're great. They're really great.
I mean, all of them have their flaws. None of them are perfect. But then no laptop is.
I've got a couple of X61s. And the X61s are even more compact. And they've got a four by three,
they're much older. They've got dual core CPUs. And they've got four by three aspect ratio display,
no webcam. But they're perfectly serviceable. I've got one running Ubuntu Mate. And the desktop,
once you get the desktop up and running, everything's fine. And I've got another one,
which is a command line only system has no GUI on it. Because you can.
And those both work really well. And they've both got six gig of RAM. So you know, it's not like
they're starving for memory or anything. They've got enough oomph to work.
Aaron Alexander So we're counting up to like,
six or so at least that you have in use?
Jason Vale Well, that's one, two, three, four. That's
four in use. There's an X1 Carbon, which is the Ultrabook style, which my wife uses as her
main machine. And the handy thing there is because my T450 and my wife's X1 Carbon have the same
charge port, this rectangular yellow port. It means that when we're sat on the sofa,
we just hand each other the cable. Like, so I don't have to have two chargers underneath the
sofa. I can just, she has the cable for a bit and I have the cable for a bit. And then the rest of
them are really somewhat older, crustier, kind of Windows 98, Windows 95, Windows XP era kind of
ThinkPad. So I've got a T43, which is the last model of ThinkPad that was made before IBM sold
off the laptop line to Lenovo. And I've got a super thick one that's got speak, front firing
speakers, like grills on the front of the laptop. It's really, really thick. And that's got Windows
98 on it. So yeah, I've got a range of them. But the main ones that are actually in use on a daily
basis are the X61, the X220 and the T450. Excellent. And the T450, you said you have
three displays hooked up to that. Are you running those out of the DisplayPort, Jack?
So I've got it sat in a docking station. I picked the docking station up on eBay.
And I just slammed the thing into the docking station. And there are two external displays
plugged in. One's via DisplayPort, one's via HDMI. And as soon as I slam the laptop in,
I use the internal panel as the main screen. And then the other two displays are sat above
and behind as I use the secondary and tertiary display. But thankfully, you know,
GNOME and KDE and all the modern desktops remember the layout. So when I yank the laptop out,
everything just reduces back to one screen. And then when I plug it back in again,
everything opens up to three screens and I can rearrange my windows a little bit
and carry on. So yeah, my day-to-day machine has three displays, the laptop and two externals.
That's pretty awesome, man. You know, talking about these and have you purchased any of these
new or do you mainly purchase them used? If someone was kind of looking to buy their first
ThinkPad, is there a suggestion you would give them to look for pre-owned or buy new?
What would you suggest?
Yeah, they're quite expensive, like relatively speaking. And one of the pitfalls you can fall
into is buying the, there's a consumer grade ThinkPads, which are the E-series and I would
avoid those. I mean, if you're on a budget and that's all you can afford, then, you know,
fair enough. But they're nothing like what I would call proper ThinkPads. The E-series ones are
consumer grade and it shows they're not as easy to upgrade. They just don't feel as robust and
they don't have the same components.
Yeah, I can attest to that because the first ThinkPad that I ever purchased outright was the
X120E, which was the AMD GPU or APU rather. It was not great. But I mean,
it did the job for what I was using it for.
So I think that's the thing is that if you've got the budget and you can buy one new,
that's great. But I personally have only ever had one from new, other than the one I had when
I worked at IBM. I personally bought the X220 myself from new and I was contracting at the
time. So it was a business expense, my own company. And I paid 45 pounds, I think it was,
on top of the cost of the laptop for on-site warranty. And I had to use it, I think three times
in the three years that that warranty was valid. And I had to have the motherboard replaced once
and I can't remember what else, but I had other components replaced and the guy just turns up to
my house and, you know, sits at my dining room table and repairs my laptop right there in front
of me. It's great. It's a lovely service, not having to return to base and be without your
laptop for, you know, who knows how long. It was really valuable. That 45 quid was the best 45
quid I ever spent on that laptop. But most of them I've bought secondhand, either through eBay,
or there are various resellers that, you know, refurbish laptops. And if you can find a reputable
one that's got good reputation through, you know, other people or has got good online scores or
whatever. But I bought them on eBay and they've been fine. I've not had any problem with buying
ThinkPads on eBay. And there's so many of them because, because ThinkPads are so popular as
business machines and then businesses churn and get rid of hundreds of them. The market is full
of them. So there's, there's tons of these X series laptops on the market and they don't
particularly hold their value. They're not like Apple laptops where they command a high price
secondhand. You can pick one up for a couple of hundred dollars pretty easily.
Well, and it seems like from just my research recently, whenever I purchased, my latest
purchase was, was a T440S that a lot of these machines are off lease machines. So you'll find
that the seller has 150 of these machines. They've sold, you know, 40 or so. So I can attest to,
you know, buying from eBay and, and so far I've had a good experience. But I think you're right.
I think you just need to do your research and kind of determine if the seller is reputable
enough to buy from them or not. When you're shopping for a pre-owned ThinkPad, is there
a particular model you would say that you should look for nowadays? Is, is there, you know, a
particular combo mill per se that you should look for? I know that on my 440S, the track pad is
probably the worst track pad I've ever used. So immediately I replaced that. But is, is there,
are there any tips or tricks that you would give people out there if they're looking to buy one?
Maybe which model?
So I would start, if you're looking for ones that are going to be a usable workstation,
it really depends on what your use case is. Do you want something for, you know, retro fun,
maybe installed DOS and Windows 98 and Windows XP and stuff like that to play old retro games and
have a bit of nostalgia as a like spare machine? Or do you want it as a, an active usable machine?
And if we, if we talk about the, the latter, then I would say the X220 is okay, but it's a bit long
in the tooth now. The CPU is Sandy Bridge. It's usable and you know, you can install a modern
desktop on it and it works perfectly reasonably. But you might, you might get a good deal on a
230 or 250. I would probably skip the 240, which has the dodgy keyboard as well.
So some of them have, Lenovo went through a weird phase where some of the models had a strange
keyboard, which had the function keys along the top were a little bit weird, like touch buttons
and generally nobody likes those, but it's down to personal taste. You know, what your personal,
some people prefer those keyboards. Most people don't, they prefer the traditional Lenovo keyboard
and the X220 has, I think is the last one that has the older generation of ThinkPad keyboard.
And then they went to the chiclet style and then they went downhill, I think with the 240
and the 440 and then they came back with the 450 and that's the one that's good.
So if you get a good deal on a 450, so a 2015 era machine or a 250, they're both the same age,
same kind of internals, or you want something a little bit cheaper and a little bit older,
probably the 230 would be a good one to have if you want something low price and they do show up.
One of the pitfalls with the X series is a lot of them have, because they've been
low cost corporate machines, they have 1366 by 768 resolution. For some people that's okay,
that's good enough if you're just going to be browsing the web a little bit, but if you want
it as a workstation, generally you probably want 1080p and the 450s come with 1080p screens and
more modern ones do, but it's hard to find older ones with a 1080p screen than mostly
the 768, which is a bit awful. It's usable, but it's not so good.
The other thing that's worth noting is some of the T series ones have an interchangeable battery.
In fact, most ThinkPads have an interchangeable battery. You can just like yank it out and put
a different one in, but the difference with the T series is they have an internal battery as well,
so you can actually take the external battery off while the system is running.
And for me, I love that. I have four spare batteries for my laptop in my laptop bag,
and when I'm out, if the battery runs low, I'll just pull the battery out while it's running
and put another battery in and it will just carry on working. I don't have to shut down,
I don't have to plug it into the mains, it just carries on working because it
keeps running on the internal battery while you pull the external one out.
And that's quite a selling point that not many laptops have. But if battery endurance isn't the
main factor for you, then that might not be interesting to you. You might want something
thinner, light, so you might go for the X series, which doesn't have that feature.
Yeah, and I've noticed with that 440 that I have, I think it's a three cell internal battery, and
it's great, man. I love that ability, just like you said, to be able to swap batteries. I've yet
to purchase additional batteries, but I'm sure that that will happen, you know, next pay period,
whenever I can offset that so that my wife doesn't get too mad that I've been purchasing all the
ThinkPad parts and pieces. Yeah, that's the downside. It can be a bit addictive. You can
find yourself, well, you know, I could just buy this docking station and I could buy this ThinkPad
branded mouse that goes along with it. And, you know, I could upgrade the keyboard and it's very
addictive. Exactly. And the one thing for me that I was looking for whenever I purchased the 440
was the 1080p IPS display, because one of the things I noticed with the earlier X120e that I
had was that it had the 1366 screen, but the viewing angles were horrible. Like you had to
get it just perfect to get that kind of, you know, best viewing angle possible. And with that IPS
display, it's been phenomenal. But I purchased that. And then after purchasing that, I purchased
because it came with the i5 4300, I believe it is, immediately bought another motherboard. I bought
the i7 motherboard, found that for like 40 bucks or so, bought the 450 trackpad, found that for 20.
And then there was also an available M2 slot where I guess normally a 3G or cellular modem
would go. So I purchased like a 120 gig M2 drive just to kind of work as my boot drive.
Are there any sort of upgrades that you commonly do to these machines or do you try to buy it
all loaded out as you see?
Yeah, that's a great question. So you can get a good deal on one that's got like only
four gig of RAM or something and spinning rust hard drive, and then you can just replace those.
Because you could be confident with certain models, anything other than the carbon,
the X1 carbon, you can change the RAM, change the hard drive. And the hard drive on most of them is
is on the X series, it's usually a case of undoing one screw and the drive just slides out the side.
With others like the T series, you have to take the whole backplate off, but it's like 12 screws
that get retained in the backplate so you don't lose them. And then you could just pop the drive
out. It's not it's not super hard. It's not difficult. So definitely storage. And yes,
the fact that some of them have an M2 slot, like some of my ThinkPads, I have dual boot.
So for example, I've got my X220, I've got Windows installed on the M2 drive for when I want to test
out stuff like WSL on Windows. But yeah, storage is an easy one to do. In the X220,
I've upgraded the hard drive in that, I don't know, five times in the eight years I've had it,
or seven years I've had it. So it's, it's very easy to do. And the fact that it's easy to do
means I don't, I have confidence that it doesn't matter if the if the drive goes bang, I'll just
put another one in there. Or if I want more storage, I'll just swap it. It's I feel confident
I can do that. The other thing that's a bit more tricky, but you can do is replace the screen.
And so my T450 came with a gloss screen. And it took me a while before I figured out actually,
I could just replace this. And there are companies that will sell the right screen for your laptop
that has the matte coating or a different resolution. You have to be a bit careful because
some of them have different connectors and different interfaces. But in general, it is
possible to replace the screen. So if you really, you know, you like the laptop, but the screen is
getting you down, it is possible to just upgrade that component.
Now are these third party screens?
Yeah.
Okay. So from my research, that's really what I found mostly is, you know, a third party seller
that's that's basically, you know, selling a display that will work with a ThinkPad,
but not necessarily the OEM replacement.
And that gave my my 450 my T450 a new lease of life because I was getting to the point where
the screen was starting to annoy me. And I thought, you know what, I should just go and
buy another laptop because this one's yeah, I'm resisting using it outside. Like sometimes I'll
go and watch my son play football. And I'll take a little chair and I'll sit while he's playing and
I'll get my laptop out tether to my phone and I'll start working on my laptop. But if it's a
bit sunny, the glare makes it almost impossible to use. Whereas now I can I've replaced the screen
and it's now suddenly more usable again. And the other thing to note on upgrades is sometimes
the manual is wrong about how much RAM a machine can take. So the spec for my T450 says that it
can take 16 gigs of RAM, but it's lying, it can actually take 32. And I know this because I bought
two 16 gig sticks and put them in and I've now got 32 gigs of RAM. So there are certain online
resources I'd recommend the the best one actually I found is this there's one website which is
this there's one website which is think wiki. And I think think wiki.org and it's got all the specs
of everything pad. And the other one is on Reddit, there's a subreddit called ThinkPad,
slash our ThinkPad. And in there, you'll find plenty of conversations of people just showing
off photos of the new ThinkPad. But people also having discussions about I want to do this hardware
upgrade or, you know, is this the right amount of RAM for this machine? Is there anyone else who's
got this particular model and has upgraded in this particular way? And it's a really friendly,
nice community. It's a nice bunch of people and most of the people in there seem to run Linux.
So that's also nice.
Well, yeah, and that's we were recently having a conversation about ThinkPads in the
Jupiter Telegram channel. And one of the things that we were talking about, you know, someone was
like, well, this machine only supports 16 gigs of RAM. And I was like, Are you sure? And so I just
looked up the specs for the CPU that was in it. And it can support up to 32. And, you know, I
couldn't see his eyes bulge wide open. But he was like, Oh, my God, dude, I never I never thought
that this would work. I was like, you might as well give it a try. I mean, at the price of
of RAM, I mean, it's it's a pretty inexpensive upgrade. And he now has RAM on order. So I'm
looking forward to whenever he pops back in and he says this ThinkPad now has 32 gigs of RAM.
I was really lucky this T450 takes RAM I couldn't swap out of any other machine because most of them
are older than this. But on eBay, there were two different vendors selling the same 16 gig
stick at the same time. And so I bought one from each of them. And they both arrived within a day
of each other and I put them both in the machine and they're basically a matched pair. They're
exactly the same. I put them both in and now 32 gigs. It's awesome.
Yeah. And with that 440 s a little disappointing, but four gigs was soldered on. So in theory,
you know, I could so I've got the four gigs that are soldered on and then an eight gig stick in
there. So in theory, I could upgrade and throw a 16 gig stick in there, but I'm likely only going
to get the 16 gigs, not the 16, not the full 18 gigs that would be in the machine. Wouldn't it go
to 20? Would you not get 20 with 16 plus four? Yeah, my math is horrible. Thank you. Thank you,
poppy for correcting my math. But yes, so I wouldn't I wouldn't be able to get, you know, the
full RAM that would be in the machine. So I'm kind of teetering on if that's an upgrade that I want to
do or not. And I have noticed too that like the gets the 440 p model actually has a socketed CPU.
So you can swap the entire CPU out without actually having to do a motherboard swap, which
I found to be, you know, pretty inexpensive way to upgrade a machine as well.
Yeah, the only thing to watch with CPUs on ThinkPads is their thermal design isn't perfect.
And my X220, I bought the i7. And a colleague at the same time bought the i5 version, identical
in every way, just different processor. And mine overheats quite a bit. And it overheats,
we think because the thermal design doesn't allow the ThinkPad to get the hot air out fast enough.
So you know, if you're going to be using it for like compiling code constantly, and you want it,
you never want the processor to scale back the frequency, then you might want to consider that.
The other problem is my 450 in a docking station, this is an official docking station from Lenovo.
The bit on the left hand side where there's a key lock and a button to power on and the eject button
to pop it out of the docking station actually obscures part of the vent. So it's the thermal
dynamics on this thing are worse when you put it in a docking station than when you don't.
So my laptop overheats more when I'm sat at my desk. Now part of that is going to be because
it's driving three screens. So there's more pixels to push around, for sure. And there's
more applications on and active at any one time. But still, it's a bit rubbish designed to have
half the vents blocked by the docking station that it's sat in. It's not great. I don't know
if the modern ones do that as well. But this is the most recent one I have.
I see. Well, not the best engineering design decision, it seems. So of all these machines,
and obviously you run Ubuntu and other variants of Linux on most of these machines,
BIOS updates. If your system doesn't have LVFS support, is there a way that you go about updating
the BIOS, flashing custom BIOS? Have you tried any of those?
So I haven't tried any custom BIOSes. I'm always wary of bricking machines with BIOSes. So I'm
pretty careful in that regard. I have seen that one of the downsides of Lenovo devices is they
sometimes have whitelists in the BIOS for things like the wireless card. So you can't always just
open it up and replace the wireless card with a better, faster one because there's a whitelist in
the BIOS that won't let you. And that also happens with the battery sometimes as well. If you
plug in a non-OEM battery, it can detect that and say your battery is dead, your service center or
whatever, which is not very pleasant. And I don't like that. But thankfully, I've got none where I
have wanted to do that. But I can understand if people have wanted to do that. And it's frustrating
that you're blocked by some flag in a BIOS somewhere. But there are guides that I've seen on
Reddit, on our ThinkPad, where people have talked about what they've done to overcome these issues.
And yeah, patching a BIOS is one thing. For the standard BIOS updates that come from Lenovo,
the two main machines, I mean, most of my machines, as I've said, are ancient. And so
they're never going to get BIOS updates ever. So I don't really care. But the main ones that I use,
I generally also don't care because I don't know, they currently work. It's only if there was some
issue that I discovered that I actually had to do a firmware update for. If I was experiencing,
then I'd go and look for one. But I'm a pretty BIOS cautious person. I'm not like an arch user
who always wants the latest version of everything and the latest number in the BIOS boot screen and
all that. However, that said, I do have Windows on both of them, both of my modern ones as dual boot
on the M2 drive. Now, one thing that can be useful to do, whenever I receive a Lenovo ThinkPad,
I always boot from Clonezilla on a USB stick, and I clone the hard drive before I touch it,
so that in the event that I ever do need to boot back the original operating system,
I can put it back on the drive. Or I might pull the drive out and put a different drive in. I'll
always replace a spinning rust with an SSD. And so having the old drive kicking around or an image,
you know, on a server somewhere or on a USB drive via Clonezilla, means if I really urgently wanted
to do it, I could restore the original image, do all the updates, and then do the firmware update,
and then take it out again. But other than that, I don't really care.
But I personally, I haven't been hit too badly with that.
Okay. Yeah. And that's, you know, the same for me. I'm very much one of those guys,
if it's not broken, you know, don't fix it. Right. So and I don't want to run the risk of,
you know, flashing the BIOS and having some unforeseen issue and breaking my machine.
I had considered flashing the BIOS or patching it, rather, to create a Hackintosh out of the 440s.
Because of that reason that you spoke about the the white listing of wireless cards,
you know, if you wanted to put a wireless card in that would be supported for
Mac OS, you would basically have to go in and patch the BIOS for that.
Which is not something that you have to do, because you can always just get a wireless
adapter that plugs into USB and you're off to the races. So not a huge problem there.
You know, that now that we've been talking about these ThinkPads, and, you know, I run Linux on
mine, obviously, you run Linux on yours and dual boot it with Windows. Are there any features
that we can expect to work or not work? I've noticed recently with the latest version of 1910.
And I don't know if that's just part of the GNOME 3.34 package or not, but the fingerprint reader
in mine works flawlessly, which is super awesome, something I didn't expect to work.
But is there is there anything that that, you know, doesn't work really on these ThinkPads?
So yeah, the fingerprint reader works for me as well on my 450 and my X220.
I think on more recent ThinkPads, I think from about a 470, 480 onwards, I think it might be
broken. And I believe it's broken because the the necessary driver for the fingerprint reader is
proprietary. And the people who do the fingerprint stuff on the Linux side, don't want to interface
with proprietary blobs. And so that's a bit of a blocker. However, I'm told there are people
working on some kind of magic voodoo shim or something that will enable that to work in the
future. So I would imagine in the next six to 12 months, the fingerprint readers on more modern
ThinkPads should start to work as well, where if they don't already, they should work. But yeah,
I've got 1910 on both of mine and the fingerprint reader works. But I think that's because
they're sufficiently ancient. I mean, my T450 dates from 2015. So it's not that ancient,
but it's still like a four year old laptop. And it works there. But no, I don't know. I don't
know of anything else that I've not had working. All the ports work as expected. One of my laptops
also has a GSM modem in and that works. So yeah, I suspend works and more importantly resume works
as well. The camera works. Yeah, I can't think of anything that doesn't work. All the media keys
work so you can, you know, turn the brightness up and down the volume up and down and all that kind
of stuff with the function keys. The only thing that might be interesting to look at on newer
models is Thunderbolt support. I've not looked at that because I just don't have a modern enough
ThinkPad that has Thunderbolt ports. But that might be worth a look to investigate if that's
something that's important to you plugging in external GPUs or other Thunderbolt devices. I
don't know how well supported that is. Yeah, and I've had great luck. You know, we talked about the
dual batteries, the onboard battery and the detachable battery. I've also noticed that both
of those report fine in Ubuntu. I haven't had any issues with those. I like to see that whenever I
am running low on the detachable battery that, you know, I can see the power level that I have left
in the onboard battery, which is super convenient so that you never really run the risk of being in
a position where you can't power down or save your work or swap another battery in. So, I mean,
overall, I've had a great experience with this recent purchase. One of the questions that Chris
wanted me to ask is he's talking about upgrading Dylan's laptop. Is there a particular ThinkPad
that you think is good for kids? Do you hand any of your ThinkPads down to your kids?
Oh, God, no. I guess, as always, it comes down to what do they want to do with it. And I know Sam
has used my X220 in the past and his primary use case back when he was using it was Minecraft.
And the GPU in the Sandy Bridge processor in the X220 is a bit gutless. And you have to
lower the render distance and drop the detail. And so for gaming, these older ThinkPads are not
really up to it. But something like a 230, 240, once you start getting a little bit newer, like
2015 era laptops, they can run some of the more basic games. I mean, Minecraft, I wouldn't
necessarily say is basic, but you know, it's not Skyrim and Fortnite. But yeah, I think
the robustness of a ThinkPad is helpful for a kid. Like, you know, kids are like,
they can, you know, drop them, have them on their lap and, you know, spill stuff on them.
I don't know if you've ever noticed, but there are drip holes on the bottom. If someone spills
a drink on the keyboard, the idea is that the liquid is routed around the motherboard rather
than onto it and through and should just drip straight out the bottom. There's a fun video I
think Lenovo made a few years ago where someone just dumps an entire litre of water over a running
ThinkPad and it just runs straight through and the laptop carries on running. It's not something I
would recommend anyone tries and I'm certainly never going to do it on my laptop, but it's nice
to know that that's a test they do. And so for kids, like my own son has dropped a cup of juice
over a laptop before my mother-in-law's MacBook Air and so it was ruined. Whereas you would like
to hope that the ThinkPad would survive that kind of abuse pretty well. So yeah, I think the other
nice thing about ThinkPads is, I mean, I go back to the repairability and the maintenance. If
something does break, if the plastics break, you'll always find someone on eBay selling
the plastic shell or the palm rest or the underside or something or the memory slot cover.
There's spare parts for these things all over the place. So even if something does break,
there's a chance to get it fixed.
Right, right. And that's one thing that I've noticed that they do have really good documentation
and repair manuals, you know, freely available. It's not like you have to go through some
loops to try and say that you're a dealer or a vendor or something to get these repair manuals.
So that's one thing that I really like about Lenovo. And it makes sense, in my opinion,
for them to have drain holes for drinks. I mean, if I'm thinking about this as a business class
machine, I'm sure several people have knocked over a cup of coffee or something into their
keyboard. So yeah, it's easily done. It seems like it's a wise decision on engineering's part
to try and help mitigate that. You know, thanks for coming on and thanks for talking to me about
all this. No worries. Are there any closing suggestions or some sort of advice that you
would give people if they're looking at picking up a ThinkPad? Yeah, so we've mostly talked about
like the modern era, like from year 2000 onwards. But there's still a whole bunch of older laptops
that, you know, predate year 2000 that would have come with DOS and Windows 98 and XP.
And they're tremendous fun to play with as well. Especially if you want to try, you know, playing
old DOS based games and stuff like that and live that retro life if that's something that's
appealing to you. But one warning I would give you is there are some models of ThinkPad which
have BIOS passwords in them that you absolutely can't remove. And if you're looking for second
hand older ThinkPads on eBay or Gumtree or whatever, do make sure that you've got assurance
from the vendor that you can actually boot directly to an operating system and that there's no password
lock. Because I made the mistake of buying a ThinkPad and it has a password on the BIOS and
I absolutely can't get into it. And I've had to buy a complete replacement motherboard for a 15
year old ThinkPad just so that I can get the thing to boot. So that's one thing to watch out for I
would say is make sure the thing boots. You know, get some good photos of what it looks like when
it's booted. But the nice thing is they're mostly super repairable and, you know, easy to maintain
and they're fun to use. And despite their, you know, 1980s industrial design that looks like
it came out of a, you know, Russian military, they're delightful machines. I love them.