Hey, Wes, hello, I thought you know what that's the most ridiculous thing I'd ever heard.
I mean I was bouncing in my seat.
It's got a great name name too.
It's called the eff up theme.
You know, the eff up theme.
Let's see.
It describes what we're doing here.
Yeah.
So we thought, let's get meta for a little bit.
And I would do a little Wes and Chris reacts.
This is something the YouTubers do.
Now we're bringing it to the podcast medium.
Well, what are we reacting to ourselves?
This is that's the thing, you know, like old clips of yourself and stuff.
But I hate me.
Oh, my God.
You should hear old me.
It's so bad.
So bad.
So I thought I thought we kick it off with like a really bad one of me.
So we go back in time to episode 100 of Linux Unplugged.
Far back.
Your first episode.
What is this like 2015?
Episode 100 right on the number like you just that's a pretty I mean, of course, it was
because of a special event that you were there.
That's pretty cool.
Anyways.
But this is me.
This is me back then doing the introduction.
You know, for episode 100, I wanted to do a meetup, but we have so much going on.
We've just done a bunch of meetups and we have a couple of coming up kind of didn't
really fit in the schedule.
So why not just have people over to the studio and do a little cookout?
We had six people RSVP and we had a pool going.
I said three would show up.
I nailed it.
That wasn't sped up.
That was going to be my question.
No, it wasn't.
You can tell because it's it's like a little brighter.
You've got a you've got this weird eagerness sort of going forward.
I was young, foolish.
We were having like a big day.
That was episode 100.
Yeah, we were doing the old barbecue for what started as like a just sort of a spinoff from
last.
Yeah.
In episode 99, which would only have been one week before I said anybody in the Pacific
Northwest that wants to come up and do a barbecue for episode 100, come on up.
And in the back of my mind, I was thinking this would be a great way to find a new co-host
for the show.
Like, wouldn't that just work out great?
And I thought, yeah, no, no, that's probably crazy.
So we eat.
Do you remember what you brought something good?
Can't remember now.
I don't know what I brought.
I know.
I mean, I know I brought beer.
Yeah.
You might have bought, you may have been beer brats too.
That would be my style.
Yeah.
Something that stuck out.
And so then after we ate, we all came into the studio and we did a show and it was pretty
clear like right there with no prep, you were sort of like a natch co-host, check out, like
we're just sitting here shucking and jiving and you jump right in.
I think that's one of the best things about Unplugged is you can connect developers with
the people who are actually using them.
Yeah.
They come into the room.
Right there.
Look at me go.
Right on point.
Your first time on air.
Like we had almost planned like that kind of thing.
Had you done a podcast before?
I had not.
Really?
No.
Well, you were quick on your feet.
Man.
So, okay.
So that was for episode 100 and we just finished recording.
314.
Yeah.
Wow.
I did some digging around.
There's like a big change from like from about 100 to 200.
I mean, I much prefer the way it sounds now.
We've changed quite a bit there.
It's come a long way.
So why don't we go back in time?
So that was a couple of clips I pulled.
You pulled a couple of clips and I don't know exactly what this one's about.
It just says Gnome crashes and we are back.
So Gnome just crashed on us.
That's kind of ironic.
I'm not joking.
Summary of the show, folks.
This is a bit of an awkward thing for me right now.
This is my love song to Gnome because I think it's such a great desktop and I think it has
such a strong future and yet I think I'm switching away.
And I'm going to be talking about that more.
But I just I want to continue being positive about Gnome, but I do have to acknowledge
that we just had to stop broadcast and we had to stop and re-edit here and all of that
because Gnome crashed on us again.
Oh, man.
I know that what I'm really struggling with is I am very upset, but I also am trying to
be more positive because I know people work really hard on this.
And the rest of the show, you're like, oh, man, it's getting there.
It's really come a long way.
Yeah.
And I'm trying to be positive because my new outlook on this kind of thing is it just doesn't
work for me, but it could be great for other people.
That's my outlook now.
It's a very accepting view.
And so here I am in the middle of a crash during a live show.
And what used to happen back then, and it's the most awkward thing for me, it's the thing
I hate the most, is when Gnome Shell would go, it would take out Pulse Audio, which would
leave dead air on the stream.
Just nothing.
Even for like 30 to 40 seconds, it's just dead air.
Or sometimes we'd switch to Barry White mode where it would shift us and we'd be in the
wrong phase.
And for me as a broadcaster doing a live event, like...
That's the whole thing you're focusing on.
It's just like the Achilles heel of a crash.
And nothing you did, right?
You set it all up perfectly.
It was rough.
And I was trying in this moment to stay very positive.
So we are going down a path, but...
And this is a system, by the way.
The one that crashes the most is the system with almost no extensions.
Just for the record.
The only extension it has is Dash to Dock and the ping extension.
Yikes.
There you have it.
Yeah.
It's good times.
Do any other machines suffer from this in the studio?
We have three Gnome desktops that crash every day.
They're all similar hardware, NVIDIA, Arch, Core i7, like a generation ago.
Yeah.
It's happening quite a bit.
That's kind of...
Wow.
I had forgotten how bad it got.
Oh, it was pretty bad towards the end.
Now, we have some issues right now.
So I thought it would just be interesting to sort of reflect on where we've been and
where we're going.
Boy, I'd say the issues we have now pale in comparison to that.
It's so much more stable.
And so these systems have been installed for a year and a half.
And the main issue we're really having probably results from switching from Plasma.
We jumped on the recording computer from Plasma to XFCE because we were having video artifact
issues that we thought might have just been a combination of NVIDIA Driver and Kaywin
or something.
However, weird video artifact issues have continued even on...
They remain.
Yeah.
So we think it's just time to do a reload and re-swap a video card out and just do a
general work.
But this system, actually, like the OBS machine, which was the one that was crashing, which
is not...
We're not really having problems with it as long as we restart about once a week.
Once we started using Jack, we had to restart once a week.
But that's acceptable.
We do some security updates.
We reboot.
Otherwise, you're right.
It just works.
You kind of set it, forget it, which is exactly how I want it.
That's acceptable to me.
You're right, though.
I had forgot about that.
Do you remember...
We've had a conversation in a couple of forums over the years, but do you remember the conversation
around submitting bugs when you're doing testing and all of that?
That's something we've talked about, like when we're reviewing a distro.
I mean, we all love to complain, right?
But we don't all often submit bugs about things we're complaining about.
Going back to Poby's argument about filing a bug, this is not one, I think...
And I don't know, maybe it's my bias.
I've been around for a while.
This is not one I think is worth my time, because it's...
Yeah.
That's what I heard for six months from the people complaining about wireless on 1604.
I disagree with that.
I didn't actually have that problem, but that would have been one that would have been.
But that's exactly the problem.
Not everyone had this problem.
There were people very close to you ranting about how wireless on 1604 was completely
busted and everyone should avoid it on 2604.
It turns out, no, it's not busted for everyone.
It's not busted for anyone in Canonical.
It's only busted for certain select people with certain chipsets in certain environments.
That's crazy.
Those f**kers wouldn't tell us what the details of that system was.
If you don't tell us, we can't f**king fix it.
I think this is a real problem.
I think the core problem that that issue...
The thing is, is I'm not going to spend my time.
I'm not going to spend...
I'm not going to...
Like I said, if I'm working 65 hours this week, I'm not going to work 67 hours so that
way I can report a bug and then watch them tell me it's an Nvidia problem.
I think the thing that I would articulate or attempt to articulate now that I wasn't
because I was so surprised by how fired up Popey got that I wasn't really articulating
very well is the core...
I was trying to play the part of this is how people feel.
We're not...
I, Chris, am not going to file a bug, but people who are working 65 hours a week aren't
going to work an extra two hours for Canonical, who maybe they barely even like to begin with,
to help out with something like this that should be caught in basic Q&A.
I wasn't trying to say I don't ever want to submit bugs, but I was just trying to...
I guess I was trying to have a conversation around, how do you solve that problem?
Because...
You're not arguing for that position.
It just...
It's a human problem.
It's how people feel.
Yeah, exactly.
I don't think I did a very good job there listening back to that.
And I don't know that too much has changed, right?
I mean, maybe it's a little easier.
GitHub is popular, PRs are okay, but it's still a lot of hoops.
I think we as a team are...
We participate more in funding open source projects, bug tracking, issues that...
Or we'll follow issues on GitHubs for projects that we are using actively in production.
So we have improved our skills there, mostly because we now have a team that has a culture
of doing it.
But I think if you don't have that, and you don't have a strong motivator to improve Canonical's
product, you're not likely to do it.
You're right.
I don't think it's changed.
Well, it's a culture issue.
You're right.
I mean, that's exactly it.
I think the only way you could change it would be, I don't know, a lot of evangelism and
tooling to make it as easy as possible.
So, you're right.
We are on the precipice tomorrow, we're reloading the studio machines.
But one machine stands alone now in the studio, and that's Westpain's ThinkPad.
So let's...
One more Plasma thing.
And I wanted to pick up from where we left off last week with you.
So during the show last week, you switched over to the Plasma desktop for a little bit.
Oh, that's right.
I also got the state of Plasma that was posted at Netrunner-Mag.com, which we'll have linked
in the show notes.
So I kind of wanted to go over your experience, cover his experience, because I've been so
impressed with the Plasma desktop, specifically 5.9, that I've had a hard time articulating
what's wrong with it.
People said, so what's not working still?
And I'm having a hard time articulating it because I'm not like in review mode, I'm just
like in use mode, I'm just like geek out mode.
And so I haven't really had to turn on that part of my brain until I started really getting
this question more and more.
And so now I've slipped into more review mode of the Plasma desktop, and so I've got some
observations of things that I think should be improved.
But they're still not major things.
And so I'm curious to hear what your experience has been so far.
I've been pretty impressed.
I think it's been a year or two since I really had like Plasma KD anything as my main desktop.
Some things I like, like I already use Quossel and other cute applications, so it was nice
to kind of have that be my native environment.
But I have been approaching it very much like what you said, just install and the defaults
work.
I was kind of interested in exploring with that, because that's really what I do a lot
of the time with GNOME, at least on like this laptop, which we refresh for the show a lot,
that kind of thing.
So I really just kind of installed KD or Plasma, started working with it.
It took me a while to get used to some of the trivial things, just like the mouse cursor
is a little bit different, plus some of the applications I use, like I have a lot of like
Telegram or Slack, they didn't integrate quite as nicely or look quite as nice with just
the default theme as I found that they did with GNOME.
But I have not customized that much.
So I'm kind of interested to hear.
So another part that I like, I've been using Unity at work, mostly just because I got my
desktop refreshed there.
Not taking the time to customize that either, because, you know, get work done.
But I have been thinking about either installing GNOME or Plasma.
So now Plasma is on the list.
But like one of the things I think Unity does well is imitate a tiling desktop or give me
some of those features.
A lot of times really what I want, and Cinnamon does this well, is just like quadrants, even
just splitting half their screens, but especially quadrants.
So now you're still on Plasma.
That was back in 2017.
Oh, boy.
Could you pull up like something there to tell you what version of Plasma you're on?
There's probably something in the system preferences.
So you're still on it.
You really stuck with it.
KDE Neon 5.16 at the moment.
Does that happen to say which version of Plasma desktop?
Because you were in that clip, it was 5.9.
Yeah, that's the same.
KDE Plasma version 5.16.4.
Hmm.
So 2017.
Wow.
That's like, you're like, that's the longest running, nobody else has been stuck to one
desktop that long.
Well, so it wasn't that long.
There was a long known period in between, I have to admit.
So that's what's funny about this, because this was kind of the, I said it had been like
one or two years, but that was just like trying a desktop that came with KDE as part of an
other OS review.
That is kind of the first time I did like a real, I'm going to use Plasma for a while,
at least the modern version of Plasma.
But it still feels just shallow in comparison to what I've been doing now.
So I feel like change is in the wind, you guys, you're just selling me on Fedora on
this ThinkPad.
And you're right, like I have an ancient kernel, we've been playing with Jack, like I'm not
too worried about compatibility issues.
So I'm loving Plasma, I still don't know that I take full advantage of the configurability.
And honestly, part of the reason it's lasted so well, and like, I don't have the same complaints
is because you tuned this for me when it got set up.
So it's not really the defaults.
Have you ever experimented with the tiling or the quadrant stuff?
Yeah, a little bit.
Kwin's great.
I could probably be doing a better job of taking advantage of it.
Yeah, Kwin is really great.
I mean, you do have wobbly windows.
I have wobbly windows and exploding windows are still in effect.
Yeah.
I mean, you just do this and you go, yeah, no, I totally understand.
I'm just looking over here at my Xfce desktop going, is it worth trying to retrofit this
thing with Compass?
No, no, leave it alone.
Leave it alone.
We don't need Compass.
I mean, unless Compass fixes our weird glitches, then okay.
No, you're right.
We don't.
It's just, wouldn't it be cool if the windows exploded?
It would be cool.
So one extra clip.
This isn't Linux Unplugged, but Wes and I, back in the day, did TextMap together.
And this is funny because it's a story arc that we did complete on Linux Unplugged later
on.
And we ended up replacing this install.
But we did it initially on the TextNet program and then finished the job by replacing it
with Fedora later on.
On Linux Unplugged, amazing.
After a few years of basically working seven days a week, the Jupyter Broadcasting Studio
has accumulated a bit of technical debt here and there.
And we've been kind of going through and cleaning it up, trying to address it.
But there's one that we've been putting off because it's just worked.
If it ain't broke, don't fix it.
It's always the same.
And this thing is essentially not broke.
But the reality is we have a very old FreeNAS mini.
When IX first started selling the product, I bought one.
And it's even running, or it was running, a beta version of FreeNAS.
And we just went to the races and never really went back and addressed it.
It's been in production all these years.
Yeah.
And really, it's one of those things that once it's in production, you have a hard time
stopping everything and taking this thing offline and interrupting everybody's workflow
and upgrading.
Right.
It's pretty essential to the day-to-day operations of, you can't put shows out.
We can't do anything.
No.
So it's kind of a key thing.
And the other issue is that it's growing so rapidly that we're having a hard time backing
it up because you can't really back it up online because we need the connection for
other things.
And it would just dominate our connection constantly.
And I haven't gotten, Dan almost convinced me, but I haven't yet gotten like a tape system,
which is kind of where I'm actually going with it.
Okay.
Before we get to the backup thing, I said something in that clip that I wanted to follow
up with you now that we have our new system, which is based on Fedora.
Everything's in containers, ZFS for the storage.
The one thing I said in there is you really don't want to have to take this thing down
for a long period of time and interrupt everybody's workflow.
And now the team more than ever is going to rely on services on these things, especially
the ones...
Ain't that true?
Do you feel like we solved that problem?
Maybe not completely, but I think we're a lot closer, if only because we understand
the system a lot better.
One thing that we definitely are doing differently is we won't be taking the Nextcloud system
down to upgrade the storage ever in its current configuration.
So in the past, we'd have limited sets of disks.
Yeah.
We have a lot more expandability.
We'd have to swap in a drive like animal.
We wanted new storage.
But this time around with our Team Nextcloud instance, we decided to use DigitalOcean Spaces
as the backend.
So in theory, it'll just grow...
Well, in theory, it grew 50 gigs in usage yesterday.
I guess I'll go check.
That would be interesting.
Now, it hasn't been super...
It's not completely smooth, I'll admit, but that's a huge advantage.
Yeah.
I mean, yeah, I guess it hasn't been super smooth, but it seems like the goal...
Actually, no.
I'm wrong.
It's been very smooth.
It's been a few...
Small things.
Yeah.
And the goal, theoretically, not having to swap in new disks every time we have like
a new project that we take on, boy, that could be a game changer.
You just don't have to care what anyone else does.
And then because the applications are all in containers, it does really reduce the downtime
of the application services because we're upgrading the OS, but the containers remain
up.
And when we upgrade the containers, we generally...
It's just a quick take them down.
Pull and stop and start the new one.
Yeah.
Should we continue?
Yes.
We need the connection for other things and it would just dominate our connection constantly.
And I haven't gotten...
Dan almost convinced me, but I haven't yet gotten like a tape system, which is kind of
where I'm actually going with this.
Oh, yeah.
But I haven't gotten there yet.
If I could find a good deal on eBay, I might get a tape system for it though.
But I haven't yet.
And so it's in production, we're using it seven days a week, and I don't have the best
backup.
It's not paid, but I'm working on that.
So it's time for some tender loving care.
We decided we needed to get this thing upgraded because the next step we have to do is address
our storage, get our pool back in the right shape, and get backups working.
We're going through the dependency tree to get this thing to a state where it needs to
be a reliable piece of enterprise equipment again, and digging it out of its hole.
And step one is getting it off of a beta release of FreeNAS, so that way we could get it on
a supported version of FreeNAS that was getting maintenance, that had full features, and then
we use that to readdress the storage.
But in the meantime, we got to get there and we thought, well, how would the audience do
it?
Would they make a leap?
Would they try to upgrade in between?
What would you do?
And so what we thought is, let's go out there, we'll go out into the Jupyter Broadcasting
Data Center, aka our garage, and we'll just record the whole process and share with you
how it went, so you can learn from our mistakes, or potentially our victory.
So we've been looking at this, we have two options.
We can either go straight to FreeNAS 11, or we can go to 9.3 and then try to go from 9.3
to 11.
What version are we on now?
9.1.
Okay.
Beta.
Right.
And so we thought the audience would be most likely to do the graphical update options,
so we're going to try that.
So we've downloaded the 9.3 image.
I'll go over to log in and give it a go.
Yep.
You ready?
I think we should have a break.
We'll be fine.
You can hear the old server.
It's so much smaller.
No kidding.
It's so much more low scale.
Yeah.
This was a fun upgrade because we really were kind of out.
Both of us have managed servers for a long time.
Basic storage server is not that complicated, but both of us just sort of felt out of our
element with FreeNAS.
Yeah.
I've used FreeBSD.
I've used ZFS.
I've used ZFS on FreeBSD, but never FreeNAS.
Yeah.
That's the other thing here, right?
This is a...
I mean, it's not like we're not going to break it, but it's not a test system, so we would
prefer to have the FreeNAS working at the end of the day.
Yeah.
I mean, it's so out of date because it was one of the very first FreeNAS minis, and it
was a beta build, and we just never...
It turns out you're running a podcast network.
It went to work, and we never revisited it.
It's a testament to the reliability.
Yeah.
But it's now, as we get to the point where we want to do a bunch of storage changes,
we got to get this thing updated.
Now we might want to do the save config option also.
Right.
Yes.
I did recommend that.
Yeah, we will.
Yeah.
So you can click here.
It'll download your configuration, which is good.
Perfect.
And so that's step one.
And then step two is you have to choose your upgrade image, which is different than their
regular ISO image if you're in the 9 series and you're upgrading.
So that's something to keep in mind.
They've got like an XZ packed tar that you can just do.
It doesn't have all the ISO stuff.
Yeah, exactly.
Okay.
So you can select it.
And hit upload.
A whopping 364 megs of FreeNAS goodness.
So I guess there's no step after this.
You just hit apply update.
All right.
Let's hit it.
It's uploading the firmware.
It's going pretty fast.
Okay.
Hey.
30%, 60%, 80%, 90%.
It's uploaded.
I think it's probably doing the checksum now.
And extracting the firmware.
The FreeNAS mini is in this.
We're in the garage of the studio, and it's out here.
So we're sitting next to it.
We can start to hear it, start thinking here in a second.
This is it.
Extracting firmware.
Do you feel like the 9.1 to 9.3?
That's not a significant jump.
I feel like if we can get the 9.3 pretty safely, we don't lose our configs, it should be a
pretty straightforward process.
And we're like a standard place.
I think a lot of people probably upgraded from 9.3 to 11.
And then it's storage time.
Then we're redoing the entire storage setup, adding a whole bunch more storage.
Excellent.
Yeah.
I think it needs it, right?
We're at, I shouldn't even say it, but we're at 94% capacity right now, which is, we've
got to change it.
Oh, file system loves that.
We've got to get that down to like 80% max, which is, that's a future goal, but that's
why we need more storage.
All right.
Well, the firmware updates, I'll get our Etcher backup.
Just in case this image based upgrade, they call it the graphical upgrade, doesn't work.
We have a backup plan, which is to go straight to FreeNAS 11 via the ISO image and just plug
in a USB port.
It's faster than the iDrive.
Yeah.
Although if we have to plug in a USB port, we're also going to have to get a monitor
and a keyboard.
Oh, system is rebooting.
Oh, here we go, Les.
Okay.
Fingers crossed.
Oh, boy.
Now you just wait, when you're doing these things remotely, you just wait for the system
to come back up online and you're like, you're always tempted to like bring up a terminal
window and start a ping.
Yeah.
Just run a ping.
Absolutely.
Why not?
Should I?
Okay.
Sure.
Yeah.
You just want to know, right?
Resist.
I can't help it.
You know what's interesting is that helped us get in the position to then move over
to that super micro box, which then it really set us up to swap out the whole thing again
to Fedora.
But like that was the crucial piece is we needed to get the OS normalized and we had
to get more storage.
Right.
But then we brought it over to a more general purpose system and eventually, yeah, added
more storage and eventually, I mean, a Linux upgrade.
That was one of those upgrades that took a really long time because it was when we were
still an independent company on a very, very small budget.
So I bought the drives on a Black Friday sale.
Right.
And they sat in storage here at the studio for a while.
Then when I finally got a great deal from Unix Surplus, I got a great machine.
I got that in here and then a listener of TechSnap very kindly donated some memory.
That was amazing.
And really put it over the top and then we were set.
And it was just it all kind of just eventually came together over like a six month period.
I love that that same data set just keeps chugging away.
Yeah, really, really.
It's really being put to the test right now because it's so freaking hot out there.
So if it survives the summer in that garage, I'll be really impressed.
It's the ultimate test.
It's a pressure cooker.