Dell has some new Linux PCs. It's August 21st, 2019. I'm Chris and here's the news
update. Dell is unveiling their new consumer PC portfolio and included in
the announcement is the ninth generation of the XPS 13 developer edition laptop.
That's the one that comes pre-loaded with Ubuntu. Dell will be blessing us
with two different models of the XPS 13. The 7390 is the new one and the 9380
will remain depending on your price comfort. Now that new developer edition,
the 7390, does still feature the same chassis which means the camera is in the
more flattering location. Both the 7390 and the 9380 XPS 13s will be available
for a period of time. The initial launch will be September 5th, 2019 in both the
US and Europe. Initially they'll be shipping with the tenth generation Intel
Core i5 processors, 6 megabytes of cache, up to 4.2 gigahertz for cores. Later on
though in October, both in US and in Europe, they will launch i7 base systems
that will be added to the developer lineup. These systems will feature Intel's
10th generation Core U series processor with an i7 hexa-core CPU and they will
update the Ubuntu systems at the same time that they update the Windows
systems. Now here's a little bit about the specs. The 7390 will be the first
Dell system to include 1804 SP1. It comes with the new killer AX1650 Wi-Fi 6
chipset like I mentioned Intel Core i5 or i7 based on your configuration and
the time of purchase. And I double-checked with Dell and they are
currently still not happy with the state of the fingerprint reader so that will
not be a supported configuration. But Dell really has refined this XPS 13
developer line into a really nice machine. Availability will be Australia,
Belgium, Switzerland, Germany, Denmark, Spain, France, Ireland, Italy, the
Netherlands, Norway, the United Kingdom, and of course the US and Canada. If you
enjoy these quick extra updates go to extras.show slash subscribe to get all
future updates.