Well, we got something special because elementary OS 6.1 landed yesterday and Danielle Fore is
joining us.
Danny, welcome to the show.
And it sounds like it's more than just a number.
There's a lot in 6.1.
Yeah, it's actually, you know, I think it's the most we've ever packed into a point release
in a short amount of time.
Like our release blog post for this point release is nearly exactly as long as our original
release post for like the 6.0 proper.
OK, help me.
How do I say the name?
Is it Jolner?
So that's the fun part is none of us know how to pronounce it correctly.
I think it's like Yulnir, like Yuletide, I think, maybe.
OK, I should have gone that you're right, right?
I should have gone that direction.
You're right.
That's obvious when I think about it.
OK, so what happened?
Why is dot one just loaded up with stuff?
Is it things that were kind of on track for dot o and just didn't quite make it?
Well, I mean, we've got a ton of feedback from people from the release of OS six.
And so one of the big things that we like to concentrate on is, you know, wrapping up
all that feedback and trying to address the things that people have told us like as soon
as possible.
But we've also, you know, been really revamping a lot of our processes like internally and
taking more of a project management approach to things.
So we've gotten like a really good system for kicking out new updates and just really
prioritizing things and just getting features hammered out.
Mm hmm.
That sounds great.
Like so some internal improvements that have just led to a more streamlined development
process.
And this is sort of the fruits of that labor.
Exactly.
Oh, that's great.
Congratulations.
That sounds like that's going to be an investment that'll, you know, pay dividends for a while.
I know a lot of people had mixed opinions on the available apps at launch of OS six,
but it sounds like now there's over 90 curated apps in the App Center, at least.
And things are coming along and now there's is there also a flat hub integration as well?
Yes.
So as of this morning, we have 97 apps approved in App Center with a few more in the queue.
And then kind of what we've done is we've worked really hard to make sure that people
know that sideloading is like expected and an important part of the flow and like show
them in our welcome map and on App Center if they like get a search result that doesn't
return anything, like let them know that, like, hey, you know, all these flat packs
on flat hub are compatible with elementary OS and you can easily just go download them
and double click and install like anything you want.
So even if something is even if somebody doesn't publish their app in our store, like you still
have the complete open availability to download these apps for Linux.
That's I mean, that's what people love to hear, right?
They want to know that's going to be the case.
This is sort of an odd one to talk to you about.
But it struck me like a lot of times when you get a new update to how something as fundamental
as alt tab behavior works, it's it's honestly like it's really glitzy, right?
It does a lot.
But you guys have almost kind of simplified the alt tab process now in a little bit.
Tell me about that, because it's kind of gone from a very visual swapping where you could
tell what the active application was by watching the doc.
And now it's something a lot simpler.
You know, when we first designed the alt tab switcher, we kind of had all these things
about like, you know, well, let's throw everything out the window and like come up with something
really unique and different and like what, you know, could we possibly do with like the
tools that we have?
And over the past several years, really, we've got a lot of feedback from different people
that they didn't really like the solution we came up with and that the animations were
too flashy and can be disruptive and didn't really fit into how most people actually use
those kind of switchers.
So we tried to gather up a lot of feedback.
We worked with a bunch of members from the community.
We even got design input from somebody who does some UX work for like Google services
that was just happened to be like in the community and wanted to give their thoughts.
And so we came back to this like really just simple switcher that was like, you know what,
this is this is what the people want.
You know, they don't want the flash.
They don't want the whiz bang.
They want just the thing that does the thing.
And so that's you know, that's what we did is give the people what they want.
I mean, it's not a common approach.
Usually it's more glitz, more glamour.
But this one, it's it's back to the basics.
But I think it works really well.
And is it accurate to say that six dot one is really the release where the dark style
is fully implemented and looking good now?
Yeah.
So, you know, when we first implemented the dark style as something that was very specific
to how it was working on elementary OS, but we've been working a lot with three desktop
and the gnome community in particular.
And so the version of the dark style they're shipping right now is compatible with the
new free desktop standard.
So apps that are built for gnome 42 will be compatible with it.
And I believe the upcoming KD version, I can't remember the version number of KD that's going
to be compatible with it.
But it's it's like something that's going to work for every app you get from everywhere.
And like right now, it doesn't necessarily support that because people are still updating.
But like we're there, we're ready for the next generation of, you know, that free desktop
spec.
I love that.
It means it works across gnome, it works across elementary apps and sounds like future plasma
apps, too.
That's that's good.
But now that it's, you know, a free desktop spec that we can get buying in from electron
and maybe from, you know, Google and Mozilla and stuff like that, too.
Yeah, right.
I mean, hopefully, you know, I'm looking through some of this stuff.
And it's like a lot of really nice stuff to see some stuff around display scaling.
And she's that that whole UI around that looks so great.
But the burning question really, when it comes to that area in our chat room is, what are
your thoughts about whaling down the road?
Because it's, it's, you know, near and near is the groundwork being laid for that?
Or are you looking at kind of what needs to happen to make that transition or things more
further along than I realize?
Yeah, absolutely.
Like we've had a whaling project up for a while and kind of just like picking issues
off it here and there.
But we really are trying to make whaling a big goal for OS seven.
And Cassidy actually has been doing a UI study recently related to some components that we
need to rewrite to work properly with Wayland.
So we're really like, aiming for first class Wayland support when the next release, that's
a huge goal for us.
And then this last kind of question I have that's an area I don't, I don't really understand
because honestly, some of the aspects of flash packs still kind of are complicated to me.
But is there now an elementary OS flat pack platform based on the six one release now
that that can be used as a flat pack platform for others to build and distribute apps on
now?
Yeah, yeah, that's great.
So when we redid our app center completely based around flat back for OS six, we had
a flat pack runtime, there are six versions, and now we have a 6.1 version out.
But yeah, developers can build their apps against the elementary runtime.
And that's what we use an app center.
And you know, it's built off of the free desktop SDK and the gnome SDK.
So it's compatible, you know, across other distros.
So if you write your app against the elementary runtime, you know, you could download the
flat pack and run it on whatever distribution.
Okay, so if I'm following you, it's sort of like when you do a major update, now, there's
going to be a update to the flat pack platform as well.
Yeah, that's right.
Because it contains, you know, all the libraries that we're building against and like the latest
versions of granite and our style sheet and like, you know, all the little utility functions
for the latest HP eyes and everything.
Okay, that's okay, then I got a random one for you.
Because I know that there are six 64 bit arm versions of a lot of the apps in the app center.
And I know you guys tested on like the pine book and stuff like that.
But now I've got I've got a generic arm 64 box, I just want to run elementary on is that
going to be something that's doable soon?
Like, will there just be an arm ISO that people will be able to download in the future?
Yeah, so right now, if you go to build stop elementary.io, we have arm images and early
access.
So you can download and test those out, we're still kind of ironing out a crude good kernel
that we can like know that it's well supported so that we can have like an officially well
supported release.
But that is available in early access for you to play around with the caveat that you
know that, you know, it's it's still kind of experimental.
Yeah, okay.
All right.
Good.
That's great, though.
Sounds like so it does sound like work is underway.
I know my Raspberry Pi 400 is gonna love that too.
There's so much we could talk about like just alone with the app center, we could fill a
we could fill a whole episode.
So is there anything else you wanted to draw attention to or mentioned before we wrap up?
Yeah, actually, you know, another huge focus for us has been making sure that we can get
elementary OS shipped on devices.
So we have, you know, our partners, our retailers.
So if you go to store dot elementary dot IO, you can see there if you're in the market
for a new computer, we have, you know, laptops and mini desktops from laptop with Linux.
We have the desktops, laptops and minis from slim book and all in ones also.
And then star labs makes some really, really slick computers, really cool notebooks.
Okay, I'll have to check that out.
Man, it just really impresses me this release.
There's so much in there.
So I'll put a link in the show notes to the release announcement.
This if you want to if you want to go to school on how to write a post that covers updates
to your OS, you can go to class with this post, we'll have a link to that in the show
notes.
Thank you so much for joining us.