Welcome to part two of my conversation with Peter Adams.
If you haven't had a chance yet,
take a moment and go listen to part one.
If you have already, here's side two.
So when I came back to photography,
full-time as a professional,
it was like one,
it was so high on my list of projects that I wanted to do
just because it had made such an impact
in my personal life and my professional life.
And I knew the story,
I knew the power of open source.
And I just couldn't believe that there was
effectively zero photography documenting
this amazing community of people doing this amazing work.
So that was where I dove into it.
Yeah, the story of open source
is so much told through code.
I guess as a medium of expression perhaps,
but having other media forms capturing that same essence
is I think a nice way to fill it out a little better.
Yeah, I mean, as much as it's code and projects,
I mean, open source is really all about the people
because without the people,
there would obviously there would be no code,
but without the personal stories
of why people invest their time and energy in open source,
it's that personal experience
that leads people to open source.
That's what I found in my travels and talking to people.
People don't go into open source,
like they go into a profession saying,
oh, well, I could be a lawyer, I could be a doctor,
I could do open source.
That's not how it goes, right?
People are somehow there's a personal experience
or something that has impacted them
that has led them to open source.
Whenever I discover that about somebody
and I hear their personal story,
that's one of the most exciting things about open source
to me is just seeing the community
through that collection of personal experiences.
I would echo that completely through every single one
of the discussions that I've had here on this show.
I've discovered that every person has a story
of how they came to open source
or how it came into their life.
And they're pretty varied.
For you, that was surrounded
by quite a bit of an important piece of history,
but lots of it's in a professional setting and all of that.
But for many people,
it's been sort of passed on by their brother in my case,
or a friend who just suggests that,
no, I think you'd like this, you should check it out, right?
It's that really kind of intimate story
that we all have connected to it that I agree
is quite a powerful force and never really leaves us, right?
It doesn't, it's so weird, right?
Because I mean, there's so few things that stick with you,
I think, kind of like this.
I mean, yeah, you're always into things
and you're into certain bands or you're into certain music
or certain art or certain lifestyle
or whatever it is over the years,
that kind of comes and goes and fades away.
The open source stuff doesn't,
I don't ever see anybody say,
I was really into open source in the early 2000s,
but not anymore, like that has never happened.
I've never heard that.
That has never once ever been something I've ever heard.
I meet these people and I photograph people,
they've been doing it for 20 years,
they've been doing it for a decade,
or they just discovered it and it's like all consuming
and they've oriented their life
where everything is open source now
and their whole careers is geared around open source
and they would never work for anything
other than open source company.
I mean, it's just, it grabs you.
It's, and I think really takes hold of you.
I think once you embrace the philosophy,
it makes a lot of sense on so many levels
that people have a hard time seeing the world
through another lens after that, right?
Yeah, and I'm sure everyone listening
can totally relate to that feeling.
And it's also true that many who come to open source
and invest their time into making open source better
and building things tend to keep with it
until quite a late age as well.
Like you don't ever really get out of it for any reason.
No way.
It becomes a part of your personality, really.
Yeah, I mean, a lot of,
look at the folks at Bell Labs that were developing Unix
in the 70s.
Many of them are still writing code.
A lot of them work at Google,
but many of them are, they're still writing code today.
And they've been writing code
and doing different projects throughout the decades.
That's so amazing.
And all open source.
I mean, some people have done commercial ventures
alongside of that,
but they've always contributed to a core open source project
or added to the open source corpus, if you will,
over the decades, right up till today.
It's amazing.
I hope to join that group, you know?
I think you and I are well on our way.
We're pretty big.
Right, we can only aspire to that.
Yeah.
Can I ask you some maybe a bit more challenging questions
because they're questions that I think
are around the open source philosophy
and how that integrates into our lives a little bit.
And certainly they are questions
that I've thought about lots and lots.
So you mentioned how you had
that pretty powerful experience around open source
and dedicated to always then building the future projects
around open source technologies.
And so I guess the question I have is,
was that a challenge for you
when you came back into photography, when you did,
considering that photography has been classically
such a sort of commercial software, you know,
it's sort of a mono crop of software out there
that almost every photographer uses.
Was that a challenge for you?
Oh my God, absolutely.
I mean, you know, I've been using Adobe Photoshop
since version 3.0.
And so I've kind of grown up with that.
And that's just been my way to wean myself
out of the dark room and off of analog tools
and into the digital world over the last decade.
I've never really been in a position with Photoshop
where I felt like I was hamstrung by it or locked into it.
But I would say like, that's maybe one of the only pieces
of software where I felt that way.
The other pieces of software, you know, oh man, absolutely.
I mean, don't get me talking about, you know,
digital asset management, you know,
like all the wasteland of software products
that I've used and I'm sure you've used over the years
trying to organize your catalog, maintain metadata,
publish stuff up to the internet,
you know, do specialty processing on files
or noise reduction, God, it's just,
I mean, I have a folder that's just like,
it's just a wasteland of stuff.
Like a graveyard almost.
It's a graveyard, it's a total graveyard.
And it's super frustrating.
And you know, it's like you're dealing with bugs
and there's no way, there's nothing you can do.
You're just, you're totally beholden
on the software company fixing it.
And I know there's, you know, now there's some good
open source tools out there, but I tend to, you know,
I think, you know, GIMP being the, you know,
probably the best one and the most well-known one,
I can't give up Photoshop for that.
And also I have the whole hardware lock-in problem.
I shoot with a phase one camera,
which is a digital medium format camera.
And I shoot tethered, you know, from the camera
into the computer, you know, for most of my, you know,
for all the portraits in this project
and most of my commercial work.
And you know, that goes into Capture One,
which is their software.
And you know, there's just, it produces the best results.
And now if there was an open source tool
that could seamlessly handle my phase one
and the, you know, the a hundred megapixel files
that come out of it and do it better than Capture One
in terms of image quality and workflow,
I would absolutely use that.
But because it's such specialty software,
no one has really, really taken that up as open source,
you know, at a level that, you know,
would work as a professional, you know, for professionals.
At least as far as I could tell, maybe it's out there
and I just don't know about it.
But that's been, yeah, that's been frustrating.
I, and I've run into tons of bugs with their software
and, you know, I know all the work arounds
and you know, it's, and I shake my head every time,
you know, thinking, oh God,
I just wish there was a community behind this
that could improve this faster, you know,
and God forbid that, God forbid they go out of business
or whatever, you know,
that's always in the back of my mind, absolutely.
I echo those thoughts completely because, you know,
the whole reason I got into open source so deeply
was a lot of the same sort of worries
that you were just mentioning.
You know, for a long time I started,
I guess I'm a slightly younger than you,
so I started, you know, I was doing the Photoshop 7,
which if anyone, you know, has had darkroom experience
and has used Photoshop around that time
or even earlier as you did, it's an amazing gift.
Like the things you can reproduce digitally
that you could accomplish previously in the darkroom,
just the ability to sort of repeat those steps digitally
so you can create, you know, the same effect
on a series of photographs is like a kind of mind blowing
for photographers who've started in the film industry
or the film era, I should say.
And so I don't disagree that Photoshop
is an absolutely amazing thing for sure.
And that's why, you know, not quite 90%,
but it feels like 90% of photographers
end up using it at some point.
But for me, so I had, you know, tons of experience
doing that on Windows and Mac as well,
and certainly used some phase one products
and Hasselblad stuff, and so you kind of realize
that it's quite a commercial industry
around the whole photography industry.
And that's great because it has really come a long way
very quickly if you look at all the technologies
that have had to come in place to make the images
that we can create now.
You know, you're talking 100 meg files like it's nothing,
but that was a big feat, right?
Oh, it's huge.
And the quality coming out of it is like really unbelievable,
you know, before you used to have to shoot 8x10
to get anything close to that.
And so I'm not suggesting at all that Photoshop
and the phase one products and all of the commercial stuff
is not great because it is.
But what worried me for a long time,
once I sat down and started thinking,
okay, if I'm gonna run my photography business
for a few decades, how are these things
gonna start affecting me?
And it was similar to the experiences
that you had early in the tech industry
was that anyone can change anything
and you have little control over it.
So that is the kind of the thought process
that threw me into open source
and gave me the challenge of trying to create
a photography workflow that's 100% open source
that would not compromise too much the end product
that I was trying to create, especially for clients.
And is Photoshop part of that workflow for you
or have you managed to wean yourself off of Photoshop
as well?
I've managed to create a 100% open source workflow,
which is no small thing, like you're saying wow,
because you know what?
That's super impressive.
You know what goes into it.
But it's not without its compromises, right?
Like software like the GIMP or Krita
are really impressive, you know,
the minds that have gone into making that.
I can't even imagine how many hours
went into creating that kind of stuff.
And yet, just because of the nature of it,
they're implementing features all the time,
but it's still not at the same place
that some of the commercial software is, right?
And you know that well,
you're using this stuff on a daily basis.
And so it has its compromises.
I would say the piece of software
that's made it all happen for me
is a piece of software called Darktable
that has come a long way in the last seven or so years.
And I would say now I end up spending 70% of my time there.
Interesting.
And for anyone who knows photography software,
it's much like Lightroom.
It's almost like a Lightroom analog or alternative,
but not all photographers can accomplish what they need to
in that one piece of software,
because it's designed to accomplish, you know,
a certain workflow and it'll get you so far.
I wonder if it, does it, do you know,
does it handle phase one files?
Do you know?
I don't know it, but I have a feeling
that you and I after this conversation
might dive in and go learn that.
Yes, I think I may.
I think on my wish list is to have a conversation
much like this with some of the people there
who are creating Darktable and have dedicated
to making that wonderful piece of software.
But yeah, maybe it is the next step for you
in sort of pushing those beliefs.
But I really don't know.
I mean, the phase one stuff is pretty specialized.
I know it's easy enough for people in open source
to sort of deconstruct, you know,
files from Canon cameras and Nikon cameras,
because there's a huge user base, right?
But I really don't know what it's like
for the phase products, for instance,
but hopefully there's some incentive.
Yeah, I mean, I'll take a look at it.
I mean, I think it's gonna happen for me
where I think the open source tools will at some point
have, you know, the critical mass of features
that I need and rely on, and I could start to use those.
Because I mean, Photoshop is adding features
at such a rate, you know, and features
that I just don't use.
Fair enough.
This is the whole like Microsoft Word thing all over again,
where, you know, you buy it because it's a word processor,
and then it's, you know, a to-do list,
and then it's a publishing, you know, platform,
and then it's a collaboration platform,
and it's all this stuff that is not a word processor anymore.
And that's when you just go to, you know,
an open source, you know, word processor,
because you only need 10 features to do, you know,
to write your manuscript, and you don't need, you know,
the monolith that the commercial product has become.
And I think the same thing is gonna happen
probably with Photoshop, maybe with Darktable as well.
Maybe that's the project that really, you know,
makes it happen on the digital side.
Actually, these days, I think about that a lot less
just because I find that the software, you know,
for me is working, and I don't have as many issues there.
I'm particularly excited about for, you know,
in the photography world, for open source to come in
and just completely devastate what's happening
are camera operating systems and lighting control.
Yes, absolutely.
I cannot wait for somebody to,
and I have seriously considered doing this myself,
starting a lighting comp, like a lighting company
around commodity lighting
with open source software running it.
Because there are so much
that I want out of my lighting, you know, equipment,
and to be able to do,
that I wanna be able to program my lighting equipment
to do certain things.
Because, you know, like this project is a great example.
You know, it's a six light setup.
It's not the same light for everybody
because you have to look at that,
but, you know, it's largely, you know,
the same distance from the backdrop.
And, you know, you're using a similar modifier
to make it consistent.
And, you know, it's just like just getting your lights
to respond in a consistent, repetitive way.
And you're, you know, with the radio slaves
and triggering and all of that stuff is super funky.
It's just so funky.
It always has its problems.
And I think the skill of being a photographer
is to always be dealing with those curve balls,
you know, in real time.
Totally.
And you have a catalog of things that could go wrong
at any one point.
You have a catalog of things that go wrong
and you have like three backups.
You know, like I have like three sets of radio slaves,
like from three different vendors, like.
Yeah.
And it's just like, and you have to,
because you could get into a position where like,
oh, well, you know, the Profoto Air is being blocked by,
you know, you're in a studio or you're in a stadium
and, you know, there's lots of other radio going on
and it's interfering.
So you gotta have a pocket wizard.
So you have to do that.
And it's just like getting all this shit to work.
And then like the rate of features
that are not coming out from these vendors is so painful
because you just see it and you're like, oh my God,
please, please let me control the lighting temperature
within the light.
Like, please make it possible
for me not to have to cart around gels.
Like, I know it exists on like the, you know,
hot light side, but like on the strobe side,
please let me have that.
So, and even the camera, like phase one is wonderful.
And they put out a lot of great features
and phase one is kind of a specialized platform.
But there's little things that I know
like would be really good ads.
And why can't I write that code
and put that in my camera, right?
And that's the area, camera and lighting,
to me that is the most frustrating right now, at least.
And I really hope, you know, if somebody came along,
if anybody's listening and they wanna start
an open source professional photographer strobe company,
you know, hit me up because I just think it would be,
it would be so impactful.
I know so many photographers that would be like,
oh yes, please, let's please do that.
Well, you know, I've got my hand up
and I know a few people who know a lot about technology
and are really passionate amateur photographers
and really good, my friend Alex,
who also hosts, self-hosted here
on the Jupiter Broadcasting Network.
He's a massive photographer and very interested
and I'm sure he would have his hand raised as well.
So I feel like, you know,
the beautiful thing about photography is,
at least I'll speak for myself,
is that it can be very technical
in a way that someone who easily latches
onto the computer worlds can also appreciate.
Like that for me was a really nice,
not transition, but those two exist at the same time,
but also a really nice way to be creative as well.
So I know a lot of people who do coding
or are involved in tech and IT somehow
who are also just in love with photography.
So I feel like you might be surprised
with how many people hit you up with that offer, you know?
It's so necessary.
I mean, also, and you look at like what's happening
in the smartphone photography world
with all the sort of algorithmic photography,
you know, that's starting to happen now.
All the algorithms that are at work,
every time you press the shutter button
on your iPhone or your Android,
you know, it's taking seven pictures
and averaging the exposure and applying a sharpening
and, you know, stitching things together
and doing a long exposure and blending and filtering.
You know, it's like the algorithms
that are at work there are amazing.
And Google and Apple have some of the best
software engineers in the world.
They have a little bit of a corner on that talent.
And I worry that some of these other camera companies,
you know, that may not be able to get,
you know, may not be able to access that talent,
how do they compete?
You know, like how do they stay abreast
and get access, you know, to the best tech
and the best programmers or the best innovations?
And to me, it's so obvious that it's open source.
It's out there.
So there's so many open source developers
that are also, you know, into photography
and could be contributing to these areas
that if any of these companies opened up their platforms,
even the slightest bit,
I mean, even if it wasn't just like a totally,
you know, open source OS,
although I think phase one,
I think when you start the camera,
you're actually booting a Linux kernel.
I wouldn't be surprised.
Yeah, and I think the same is on Hasselblad
and some of these other ones.
You know, if the startup time is more than like a second,
I think you're actually booting into Linux.
And that's not a dig on Linux.
That's just to say there's like a full blown OS.
Yeah, there's a whole operating system
booting in a few seconds, right?
Which is amazing, right?
And that's so cool.
So like, can we please open that up?
Like, because there'd be a flood of talent and innovation
that would go into the space
in a way that would be so phenomenal.
And I just think like, that may be more impactful
even than the sort of image processing and manipulation side
just because so much can happen in the camera
and between the lights these days.
That's my personal preference.
If somebody is listening out there is working on it,
please let us know because we're ready for that.
Absolutely.
And it feels like then it's a bit of a dream
that I've had as well to accomplish,
just to grow the dedication I've had
to creating an open source post-production process,
but to open that up into the entire pipeline, right?
From Capture to lighting to sort of printing as well.
So I would love to dedicate my life to making that happen.
I'm totally into that.
So it's gotta happen.
I mean, I'm a little afraid
that like there's this giant sucking sound into my iPhone
and that like 10 years from now everything may,
we may, you and I are gonna pack up our equipment
and go on a job and it's gonna be,
consist of six iPhones
and a whole bunch of lighting equipment.
But so I'm a little worried that photography,
there's this giant sucking sound into the mobile platforms.
But there are laws of physics that are at work that-
Thank goodness they're on our side.
That are on our side in terms of just,
you wanna have a certain amount of image quality
in a certain size, you've gotta have glass,
that's gotta have a sensor of a certain size
and you gotta have glass that's a certain size.
And so I think there's always gonna be camera companies
that are gonna be servicing videographers and photographers.
And I just wish that one of them would realize
that they can make it a competitive advantage
to be open source,
as opposed to keeping this whole proprietary arms race
that's been going since the beginning of time
and use open source as a competitive advantage,
be the open source camera company,
be the open source lighting company,
or at least have an open source component.
Because I just think like they'll run away with the market.
Everybody, nobody wants to be locked
into these proprietary systems
that are so slow in the photography world.
I mean, nobody I've ever met has been like,
you know what, I'm really, really happy
with the way the menuing system works on my Sony,
or I'm really, really happy with the way
my Profoto light works with this trigger or that trigger.
I mean, I've never heard that before.
Never, it hasn't happened, so.
Well, I think some people listening to this
will certainly point us towards
some of the open source firmware
that was able to be loaded onto certain camera,
certain Canon cameras.
I don't know if that's still true,
and I haven't really owned any Canon cameras.
I know, me neither.
But when I heard about that,
and I've certainly seen it in action,
and I've done some research around it,
it was really exciting for all of the reasons
that we're talking about here.
Oh, I remember that, and I was so, so excited about that.
And then I was like, I just don't own any Canon gear,
you know, so.
That's how I felt.
But it feels like, geez, that would be a nice place to go.
And this conversation is reminding me a little bit
about what's happening in the hardware sphere
around computers themselves, you know?
There are a few open hardware vendors
kind of trying their very best to make a difference
out there, but it's not an easy place, right?
It's dominated by lots of really big commercial giants.
Yeah, and also, I know you know this,
photographers don't have any time to really,
I mean, you and I, we would love to burn a weekend
on this problem and working around something on our own
and scratching our own itch.
But, you know, there's many months where we just don't,
we're not gonna have that time, right?
So the equipment has to work, it has to be bulletproof,
it has to be supported.
And I think, you know, every time I say that,
I just have these flashbacks to my son, Oracle,
you know, EMC storage days and thinking the same thing,
right?
Of course.
And I just know how that story ends.
And I know that this is, you know,
this is exactly the same, you know,
this is exactly the same issue, just with a completely
different technology domain.
So it's gonna happen here.
It's just a question of who's gonna do it and, you know,
and when, and if it's one of the existing manufacturers
that, you know, becomes enlightened and gets the religion
or whether a new manufacturer is gonna come along and-
And change the game.
Use open source and change the game, right?
And that'll be super exciting.
You know, either way, I'm good either way.
But I just hope somebody does it soon.
Well, yeah, I hope you and I are both around to see that.
For sure, we need it sooner than later, I feel like.
I know.
In terms of photography,
have you put any thought around the emergence
of some of this artificial intelligence stuff
in developing, you know, portraits and things like that?
Cause I've heard a few stories recently
of AI creating some really interesting,
at least I very much hesitate to call them portraits
for an obvious reason, which is that I don't want to equate
them to the craft that you and I spend all of our time on,
but there's some interesting stuff happening out there.
I mean, I haven't really.
I mean, you know, the closest I come is, you know,
on the iPhone with, you know,
all the portrait lighting effects that Apple introduced
and, you know, all the algorithms that are at work
and even, there's some good algorithms actually,
even on the phase one now for long exposures
and things like that, but in terms of AI,
in terms of stylistic preferences or things like that,
I haven't really delved into that.
What have you been seeing that has been intriguing you?
Well, yeah, I think where I'm going with this is,
you know, artificial intelligence has been really impressive
in many areas and digital photography,
if you look at it, is just, it's really just, you know,
you and I are taking real life and digitizing it
in some ways, if you look at it through that lens.
And so some might argue that you can create
that digital version from scratch using some intelligence
instead of real life.
And so the way I've been thinking about it is in terms
of what is the future of photographers and photography.
And I don't know that that's coming soon,
but if we're peering into the future,
maybe 20, 30 years or so, you know,
I'm just throwing a number out there, but what do I know?
It feels like crafted images coming out of some,
you know, a few algorithms, at least,
I see it kind of in the sphere of stock photography first.
You know, you have a lot of photographs
that are not necessarily tied to a specific person
or individual, but are really useful
for a bunch of other reasons.
And so I've been just seeing artificial intelligence
as a really interesting expansion
of who we are as photographers.
And it both intrigues me and scares me at the same time.
No, totally.
I mean, what was that project?
Was it the research group?
Was it Samsung or?
I forget which research lab came out with like the ability
to create portraits of like fake people
from photographs of real people?
Oh man, yeah, right.
Like, it was like these incredible like, you know, photos
that you weren't like, oh, that's like a Photoshopped photo.
It was like, no, that's like a real person,
but that person actually doesn't exist.
It's the eyes from one person and the hair from another
and the facial structure from a third.
And, you know, the algorithms are able
to produce these lifelike, you know, very real,
photorealistic, you know, images of people
from the source material.
I think that's fascinating.
And I think, you know, from an artistic standpoint,
I mean, there's tons of photographers today
that are doing so, you know, incredible photo manipulation.
And, you know, I think that there'll be a whole realm of art,
you know, much like the, I don't know how familiar you are
with the whole processing space, all the generative art
that's being generated using JavaScript and, you know, data
and using programs like P5.js and processing.js
that are doing all this sort of like algorithmic artwork
all from data, which is,
I'm personally super fascinated by that.
So I think it'll be, I think it's gonna happen.
How will it aid us as professionals?
You know, ego-wise, you know, I don't, you know,
I want to think, oh, well, you know,
damn algorithm's never gonna do better
than you and I are gonna be able to do it.
But I think that, you know, the AI will, you know,
be really helpful in automation.
I mean, I personally, I would like to just be able
to go into a shoot and open up a case,
have five drones pop out and, you know, the AI is like,
oh, you wanted Rembrandt lighting?
Great, let me get in position.
You know, like to me, that's what I want.
That's a, you know, I could see that being like
super impactful, but I'm still driving the boat, right?
I'm still saying, oh, Rembrandt lighting or, you know,
or, you know, put a flag over there and-
You're automating your photography assistants.
Yeah, exactly.
I may be more like a little bit more like machine learning
where the algorithm's like,
oh, Pete likes his flags on the right, not the left.
You know, like stuff like that, I could be,
I could see that being like really super helpful.
But, you know, maybe it gets to a place where, you know,
you and I are, you know, deploying the algorithms
and not much else.
I don't know, it'll be interesting to see.
Well, I think it's interesting to look at it
as a toolkit really, which is what you alluded to there
is, you know, the cameras in our hands
and the software that we throw those images into
and even, you know, the printers and all of that stuff,
they're just tools to allow us to be expressive.
And so as our tools evolve, so too do our expressions.
And so those of us who I think are keen to stay
with those leaps in technology kind of get to create
in a totally different way.
If we're willing to bring those things in,
some people unfortunately get caught up in, you know,
it's almost seen as a rivalry, you know,
when new innovative tools like that come into play.
But if you're open to them, man, can you create
some really different things or approach, you know,
typical problems in a really different way?
Yeah, I mean, I think you're totally right with that.
And I think maybe, you know, the place that that comes in
first is in post-processing, right?
Because I mean, if we had an AI that could go through,
you know, a thousand layered Photoshop files
and know all of the layered edits that I typically do
or you typically do on your portraits
or, you know, on certain types of events or whatever it is,
it's absolutely possible for an AI to learn, you know,
your style, learn Peter's style, learn Brent's style.
And welcomed, I would say.
Exactly, right?
Because so much of that is a, you know,
it's an iterative process, yes,
but there's a style that you have as a photographer
that comes out, there's a thread through your post-processing
of everything you do,
just like there's a thread through mine.
And so to have an AI be able to pick up that thread
and learn that thread so that it can apply it for you
without you having to do 60 edits over two days
because you gotta think about it more.
And if the AI is like, look,
I know tomorrow you're gonna wake up and think this is crap.
So, you know, I'm gonna delete these four layers
and I'm gonna add these six
because you really liked these in the last hundred edits.
I can see that, that can be kind of cool.
For those who don't know photography quite that much,
like capturing photographs with your camera
is definitely quite obviously a really important part of it,
but the editing after the fact is almost 50% of it,
I would say, you know, you need both to be great,
but there's such a creative expression
in that process as well.
Oh, totally, totally.
Yeah, if we continue with this imagination that you have
where that process can be captured and repeated easily,
maybe you'll agree with me, but I won't speak for you,
but I would totally welcome sitting at my computer less
and being out into the world capturing photographs more.
If I could be certain that the output was still
within the realms of the kind of things that I love,
I would totally welcome that.
You know, just as a professional photographer,
you're always managing your time
and so many of your shoots and your projects
and the way you schedule your time
is all around trying to find efficiencies, right?
So, you know, let's shoot a collection of subjects together.
Let's do the capture, you know, on the same day
in the same studio, bring everybody in
because we can just keep shooting
and we don't have to, you know, start and stop
and things like that.
And the same with post-processing,
like then let's have a week where we just go through
and do all the post-processing together
and make it consistent.
So it's a huge consideration, you know,
on what you're trying to do, you know,
to get this, you know, to manage your time
and apply your style and effectively batch up your work
so that you can get some kind of efficiency on it.
So yeah, an AI could change that game.
I mean, that could be, that would be super welcome.
You wouldn't be locked in your studio, you know,
for a week after a shoot, you know, just doing editing.
You could actually be shooting every day
and the computer could be applying your style for you.
That would be awesome.
And if you grow that a little bit
and see it as open-source AI, if we can build such a thing,
man, those, those kinds of things are awesome.
Man, those, those kinds of preferences and scripts
can be shared around and modified and combined
and all of that stuff.
It would be a really, quite a wonderful
creative exercise, really.
Yeah, no, I think so.
I mean, there's, you have like a hint of that right now
with the sort of like recipes and Lightroom.
I don't know if Darktable has a similar thing,
but like people sell, you know, like Lightroom presets
and Photoshop filters and, you know,
the sort of Instagram filter, you know, effect.
But, you know, that's just like, that's like a blunt
instrument, you know, I mean, we're, you know,
with an AI would come in and be like, you know,
being able to apply selective contrast to different parts
of a face because it just knows like,
you like more contrast over here.
That this specific person needs this specific, yeah.
Exactly.
So it's coming, I'm sure of it.
Oh man, you're getting me all excited.
I know.
I mean, we just hope, hopefully it'll be open-source
and not some proprietary black box.
Yeah, not a fan of black boxes.
No, black box is not so good.
I've been, I feel like I've been trying to rub, you know,
paint off the side of black boxes for a long time.
You mentioned that in the past,
you've been to a few conferences.
Do you have any lined up yet where you're hoping to be
capturing a few of these photographs?
This year, I'm just thinking the one that is closest out
is the Red Hat Summit,
which this year is actually gonna be in San Francisco.
I photographed, I had a great time two years ago.
I did a whole bunch of photography around that conference.
And so I hope to do that one again this year.
The folks at All Things Open are super supportive
and they've invited me.
I've shot there a couple of years ago.
They invited me last year
and they've kind of given me an invitation
for this year as well.
So, or hopefully I can do that conference again.
That's sort of at the end of the year.
The middle, I'm not sure yet.
That's, we'll see.
But those two are ones that I kind of have penciled in,
you know, my calendar as placeholders right now.
I was just speaking, I mentioned my friend Alex earlier.
He's a Red Hat employee.
And so he, I guess he does a little bit of everything.
He's kind of one of those amazing people.
But he was talking about Red Hat Summit
and how great it is.
But he was also in the same breath mentioning
All Things Open and how that's kind of in his backyard
and was mentioning how maybe I should join him there too.
So maybe if the stars align, you and I might get to meet.
Ooh, that would be awesome.
Perhaps at All Things Open, which would be a real treat.
That's I think in October, if I remember correctly.
Yeah, it's like, it's towards the end of the year now.
Yeah.
It's always a, I try to do like a New York,
you know, tack it onto a New York trip.
Since you're in the neighborhood, yeah.
It's just a question of, you know,
making the logistics happen.
It's all logistics, yeah.
It's all logistics.
Well, that would be really exciting.
I think it would be a real treat
for those who get to see some of your work
either exhibited at some of these,
if you get that opportunity or even just the chance
to photograph a few more pioneers in open source.
Can't wait to see those.
Yeah, I mean, that's the beautiful thing
about this project is there's so,
open source is such an evolving thing
and there's so many new projects,
new contributions, new applications.
So it's, there's always,
I'm always finding out about new people
and new contributions.
And I have, you know, I have a running, you know,
huge research list of hundreds of people on it
that I'm constantly, you know, reviewing
and trying to find people to photograph, so.
Great, yeah, it sounds like you won't soon run out
of great people to photograph.
No, no way, not with this community.
It's just a, it's a burgeoning community, so.
That's amazing to hear, great.
I wanted to ask you a question
that you might wanna send out to the communities
and to the listeners.
Is there something that you would like listeners
to think about or to try or go and see something
you'd like them to experience, anything at all?
I would say, you know, there's probably two things
that I've been, you know,
particularly interested in most recently.
You know, the first one I actually mentioned already,
which is the whole generative art category
where people are using these open source tools,
mostly around processing and JavaScript.
And there's a library written by Lauren McCarthy,
who's an artist out here in LA,
and she created this tool called p5.js.
And it's just so cool, and it just,
it's used to create all this like really cool
algorithmic art and visualization work.
And there's a whole community of artists,
and her artwork also is particularly,
and her projects are particularly cool.
So I would encourage everybody to check out Lauren's work,
Lauren McCarthy, and p5.js, and just that whole world.
You could just, you could burn an afternoon easily
just diving into that.
You might have just scheduled in an afternoon
for me this week.
Yeah, exactly.
It's just like, it's like open source art,
and you know, data visualization, JavaScript,
it's got a lot, there's a lot there, a lot there to like.
The other thing that I've been really interested in recently
is open access data, and sort of open data movement
in general, you know, and I photographed some folks
from Wikipedia, but you know, the work that Carl Malamud
is doing around making the law accessible is fascinating.
Like I never really knew this until I started digging
into his work, but there's a lot of state law,
and like, you know, and stuff as mundane as like
building codes, and fire codes, and stuff like that,
that is locked behind like paywalls.
That seems unbelievable because those are expected
to be followed by masses of people.
And they are, and because of that,
there's wonderful businesses out there
that are able to extract, you know, hundreds or thousands
of dollars for access to basically the law,
essentially to the law, and he has just, you know,
been a crusader on getting that all of this,
you know, legal documents and the law online,
freely accessible, you know, re-keyed in, typed in,
you know, he's like, he's got lawsuits and stuff before,
you know, the US Court of Appeals,
that people have tried to stop him.
His website is just fascinating.
And I mean, so I would encourage people to dig into him,
and his website, which is public.resource.org,
and just learn about kind of what he's doing
and support him because in this day and age
where institutions are, you know, especially in the US here,
but I think really around the world in general
are under a lot of pressure, and the rule of law
is under a lot of pressure, you know,
what can we do to help, you know, bolster democracy
and access to the law and strengthen our civic,
you know, institutions?
I think his work is more important now
maybe than ever before.
So I would encourage people to check him out too.
I think that's another Saturday you could easily burn
on digging into his work in that whole world.
Wow, that sounds like someone who's dedicating their time
to that kind of challenge, so worthwhile,
and sounds like such an important area
for all of us to benefit from.
Yeah, and it's even more impressive.
He's doing it around the world, so it's not just in the US.
He's also, he was just in India.
I think he's also doing it for the government there.
So it's a global crusade, if you will,
and I think he's really at the forefront of this.
So it's definitely worth taking a look at his work
and digging into that website.
Yeah, and it sounds like work that feels like we need more
now around the world than ever really
with things going digital and some of the unfortunate
directions that some governments have been going with,
the data and data hoarding and protection
and that kind of stuff.
So I really welcome that sharing.
If you're gonna have a democracy
and you certainly want the law to be accessible, right?
So it seems obvious, but it's, but it's not, it's crazy.
Carl knows that better than anybody, I think, so.
Oh man, I wonder what inspired him
to kind of dedicate his time to this.
That would be an equally great chat, I think.
He has a fascinating story and it goes back,
like I won't spoil it as you dig into it,
but it goes back to the early days of commercial internet,
the nineties getting the SEC Edgar filing database online.
And so it's, he's got a really rich history
doing this for a long time.
So it's cool stuff.
It reminds me of some of the work that's happening
like at the EFF and the Software Freedom Conservancy
and those kinds of organizations that I think often
we just take for granted that they exist.
And yet I think we shouldn't, like they're doing work
that probably a lot of us hold dear to our hearts
and really believe in, but just don't have the time
or the expertise to do ourselves, right?
So we gotta support these organizations
and these people as much as we possibly can.
Yeah, I mean, the two biggest ones
in the sort of open data world
and sort of open knowledge access,
Wikipedia is just incredible, obviously.
That's the one that everybody knows.
The Internet Archive also, I mean,
people have probably interacted with the Internet Archive
through the Wayback Machine and looking for,
you know, I was looking for a webpage
that no longer exists anymore maybe,
but, or your high school MySpace page
or whatever it is that you're trying to find from,
you know, make sure is or is not accessible.
But the Internet Archive also has all this amazing,
they have an entire scanning operation
and they're scanning in books,
they're scanning in recordings from,
lifted from 45, you know, vinyl.
I mean, it's just, it's incredible the archive,
you know, what's in that archive,
the classic computer games,
which is actually one of my favorite console games,
you know, that used to play in the arcades,
you know, those are all accessible in the Internet Archive.
And it's just, this stuff is, you know,
as wonderful as the web is the one thing,
you know, that is not built into it is archival.
So, you know, the web is constantly growing and dying
and parts of it are fading away.
And the Internet Archive is kind of, you know,
has stepped in and really is the mechanism
that is filling that gap.
But it's also the mechanism filling that gap
for the world's libraries with books that are out of print.
Public domain and all of that.
Yeah, and not just that, but also software as well,
old software.
So it's fascinating.
You could spend an entire, you know,
way more than a Saturday,
you could spend your whole weekend in the Internet Archive
or your whole month in the Internet Archive.
But I just think like those things are,
they're a little bit of the personification of open source,
like not just from the data,
but also a lot of the technology
that's used to operate all that stuff is, you know,
there's open source underneath all that too.
So it's an accessible thing for a lot of people
can really wrap their head around it.
Aren't we lucky?
That's cool.
That's cool stuff.
Have you considered doing a self-portrait of yourself
for this Faces of Open Source project?
Because it sounds like you're an important piece
of that as well.
That's a great question.
I have not considered doing that.
Would you?
I would consider it, but you know,
I would say I'm slightly uncomfortable
in terms of my contributions
compared to the contributions of the people
that are being photographed.
You know, so much of, you know,
I try hard as a photographer
not to insert myself into the story, right?
Just cause I think it changes the story.
And I realize in this case, you know,
there's some open source, you know,
nature to what's happening here.
But for the most part, it's a documentary project.
And, you know, just like a documentary filmmaker
wouldn't write themselves
into the script of a documentary necessarily,
unless you're Werner Herzog or, you know,
certain documentary filmmakers do do that.
And it works out.
Michael Moore and folks do a great job of doing that.
I haven't felt like I would add anything
to the project by being a part of it.
But I have to admit,
I've never really spent a lot of time considering it.
I appreciate your perspective there
because when you said inserting yourself into it
changes the project, I think you're completely right.
There is, I think as you know,
there are many photographers in the industry
who sort of lead with ego first
and that often is attractive and useful in many ways
and yet changes the work, right?
And if you are trying to be a bit more documentary in nature
and complimentary to the people in front of the camera,
instead of focusing on yourself,
I could see why that would change things.
So your answer is making me reflect
even more on my question, which is a good sign.
So yeah, I appreciate that answer for sure.
It just changes the dynamic a little bit.
Certainly.
You know, I'd have to think about it more,
but I've never considered doing that for other projects.
I think, you know, if it was, you know, if I was
a significant contributor to some massive open source thing
and, you know, or something like that
and the fact that I was included
made the project possible or something like that,
then maybe, but I don't think any of that
is happening here with this project.
Well, I think what's interesting
and really what the crux of my question was
is just to sort of nudge you
towards a little bit of self-reflection
and to acknowledge that the project you're doing here
is really important and it's a bit of a gift
to the open source community
and there's real personality in those photographs
and I think that's what really drew me to them.
You know, I've looked at a number of photographs in my day
and the thing that attracted me
to the series you've created is that
you can read the person's personality
in each of the photographs that you've done of them
and that is not always that straightforward
or that easy to accomplish
and so browsing through the photographs,
even if you don't recognize the people,
it's really fun to go through
and see sort of the different types of personalities
that are included in this wild and crazy thing
we call open source,
but also you get to sort of click on these faces
and learn about the people
and be surprised about where they've put their time
and how much history they may have
or how young they might be and are totally diving in.
So it felt to me, at least when I've been going through it,
and it takes a few sessions because there's a lot of them,
but it feels like a total ride and an education
in just everyone who's made what we're living possible.
So I found it really super fun, super entertaining.
So from that angle too, yeah.
Yeah, thank you.
I love hearing that
and so glad that you're digging it.
It is fun to learn about the people I try to include
and the captions that we do,
something also about the person's extracurricular activities,
if you will,
because what's also really interesting
about the people in the project
is that a good number of them
do way more than just open source, right?
Like they may have a whole nother superpower
that is not even, you would never think,
whether it's Ken Thompson invented Unix with Dennis Ritchie,
but Ken is also an accomplished pilot.
Yeah, one thing I've mentioned here before
is what I'm really fascinated in
and that you're discovering as well
is that juxtaposition between all of a person's experience
and the contributions they make
to a great number of areas in life, right?
And that's what makes us all quite unique
and I feel really fascinating.
Every single person has this quite interesting story to tell
and you're helping to tell that in a little way.
Peter, if people wanted to get connected with you
or I guess to see some of these photographs,
where would they go for that?
I mean, the best place to view the project is online
at facesofopensource.com and all the portraits,
I put all the portraits up there
and you can kind of click through the slideshow of them all
with the captions and there's links there
back to my professional photography website as well.
So if you wanna see more photography,
there've been some interesting sort of adjunct projects
that have come out of this that I have
on my peteradamsphoto.com website.
Yeah, I was digging into those a little earlier.
There's one on printed circuits,
which is really, it's like portraits of circuit boards,
which is really fabulous and really interesting.
Yeah, we can talk for another hour about that.
Well, Peter, thank you so much for connecting with me
and for chatting about some of your life's experience
in open source and this photography project.
It's been really fun.
Hey man, thank you for having me
and it's been an honor to spend some time talking to you.
Well, thank you.
Yeah, and hopefully maybe we get to meet
at some of these conferences at one point.
That would be a real treat.
Yes, let's make that happen.
Yeah, that'd be amazing.
Thanks, Peter.