Well, hello. Today, I'm joined by Jacob Rucker. Some may know you, he's been a long time JB
community member and listener for a long time. Jacob, how are you?
I'm doing great. Thanks for having me.
Thank you so much for reaching out to me. You've got a little bit of a pretty deep connection
to the JB community. So I am really looking forward to learning about that story and diving
into it. Tell me a little bit about where you are now.
So currently in Boise, Idaho, which is like, the people here are like Canada nice is a
good way to describe it.
I know what that's like.
Yep. And my wife's Canadian. So I think I can say that. Yes, yes.
The connections. We already have connections. We're like 10 seconds in.
Well, it works out pretty well. But she's from the other part of Canada. She's over
in Alberta. And I think you're in the East Coast area or East side of Canada.
I am north of Toronto. So I'm in Ontario. I'm north of Toronto in a place called Sudbury,
but I'm in Eastern time zone. So you reached out to me and which I really appreciated and
said, Hey, I've been listening to some of the conversations you've been having with
people on on Brunch with Brent. And I think I might have a little bit of a story to tell
that the community might appreciate. And we chatted a little bit about what that story
was. And I kind of stopped you and said, No, no, no, don't tell me anymore. I want to,
I want to have this be a really nice chat. That story, at least the parts that I heard
sort of really hit me as really meaningful for you. And I just wondered if you wanted
to start telling that story.
So I started listening to JB, it must have been 2008. I think I was still living in Utah
at the time. And found it because a friend of mine posted, I think, Linux action show
on Facebook or something like that. And it got me interested in it. And previous to that,
my experience with Linux was actually, so I was in the army for 20 years and I went
to Iraq twice and then Afghanistan once. And the second time we went to Iraq, one of the
things we were doing is there was, you know, your troop size changes. And so the footprint
for support changes. So we were taking some old servers out of system and I was repurposing
them to build a kind of a computer lab to train folks on, you know, how that technology
worked. And I couldn't get a Windows Server 2003 installation disk because they were very
controlled by our IT department, you know, licensing and whatnot. And Ubuntu had come
out at the time, right? And so it was like, okay, well, let's try this thing. And so I
ended up diving in and the internet was so slow.
How slow is slow?
Our backbone was no more than 768 K.
Oh man. Okay. That puts it into context.
Right. I mean, it was 2005, right? We downloaded Ubuntu at that bandwidth speed and then I
even downloaded SUSE at the time as well and started playing with, you know, what can I
do with these? How can I repurpose them to teach, you know, my soldiers some basic skills
on this stuff?
How had you heard about Linux in the first place?
There was a national guard unit that was there and one of the guys had said, hey, try this.
Okay.
You know, most of us have come to it that way. It's like someone else just like had
a quick conversation with us and said, you got to really like, this is going to work
for you. It's so thankful that those moments happen, right?
Right. And it was, it was cool. And then later on in college and this is how I started getting
back into Linux, I was really excited to get a new computer for myself for all my work
at college. And it was, you know, I love technology. Been online since like 93, 94 with prodigies
network originally and stuff. And so I love what technology empowers people to do.
And so at college I was really excited because I was going to get this machine that was built
for windows Vista and it was built for windows Vista and it didn't work. It was so frustrating.
I think many of us have been there, right?
So what I learned from that is I learned that you can't just accept somebody else's all
in one experience. You've got to kind of figure things out. So I knew Linux was a solution
back when I was in the army trying to repurpose servers and it's like, all right, let's throw
it on this. You know, it was a Lenovo R series thing. So I threw it on there and did a bunch
of my college work there and then we ran Linux for years, cut the cord, you know, in 2008
and just once I started listening to all the JB shows, it wasn't just listening to Chris
and the team as far as the shows they were producing. It was kind of that extra content
that they do on the side that this show or this channel, extras.show is really embodying
because Jupiter at night was a lot of fun and then kind of, you know, some of the outtakes
and things like that. And then, you know, I grew up kind of isolated in Connecticut
when I was in high school. And so there were like three nerds in the whole high school
that you could talk computers with, right? Yeah. And so being able to be in a space where
I could listen to and start hearing that conversation to learn more about it. And then thanks to
Chris, I've rewatched the entire back catalog of the computer Chronicles. Really? That's
great. I don't know if they still show that on the live stream, but they used to when
they didn't have a whole lot of self-generated content. So I've watched a lot of that stuff.
That's awesome. So I'm going to, I'm going to rewind you there for a second. So you were
telling the story of trying Ubuntu on those servers, but you mentioned something that
I want to ask you a little bit more about your, you mentioned that you wanted to teach
some of the soldiers, some basics and computer. Can you talk a little bit more about that?
Yeah. So when the army trains you, they train you or they trained us on what we call POTS
telephone systems now. So plain, plain old telephone, telephone systems. And they were
modernizing when we were in Iraq in 2005, 2006, they were going to a fiber backbone
in the country. They were going all data, everything was going to be over TCP IP and
they didn't teach us any of that. And so and they weren't going to either. And we were
going to be there for a year and have to implement this stuff without knowing what the heck it
was or how the technology worked. And so they put me on the night shift and, and left me
alone, which was good. And so what I would do is I would spend, you know, my 12 hour
shift at night researching as much as I could and building a training module. And then the
next morning, stay awake for another two or three hours and train my guys on, Hey, here's
how TCP IP works. Here's how you can test it. Here's some Cisco routers that we had,
you know, in switches that we had them program and learning VLANs and other things like that.
So it was really helpful. And when I was finished and I left Iraq early to go to college, finish
out my degree, which was really nice. But when I was finished doing that, one of the
things that they did is they awarded me with a bronze star medal because all those folks
that I trained by the time they got out and to different locations where they had to function
as smaller teams, they were a lot more effective. And so I was really proud of having earned
that award.
Yeah. And it's kind of, um, like self-motivated for sharing knowledge, right? Uh, it sounds
like you just sort of were inspired to, to share this knowledge and, and the effort that
you put into it is really impressive.
I I'm always been the sort of leader where I want to help other people be successful.
And so I w I could see where things were going and I wanted to help the team be successful
and I'd read enough or learned enough, um, that I could, I could start closing my knowledge
gap and then build it into some sort of training. Um, it wasn't perfect and I didn't know what
all, you know, what, what should be in the, the whole box, right? But I knew parts of
the box and I could at least train that.
Well, it sounds like in this case, even, even any parts is helpful, right? And they can
start to build those, those pieces together as they need.
Yeah. Um, and it was, it was cool. I mean, the equipment we had, I learned all kinds
of stuff about radio frequencies and, um, that national guard unit I mentioned, they
actually had a piece of equipment I have to nerd out with you about. It's called a tropospheric
antenna. So it shoots a, it's, it's pretty close to microwave frequency up at the troposphere.
The signal bounces off of different parts of the troposphere and then back down. So
you can actually do line of, it's kind of like line of sight, but it's, it does 300
miles.
But reflective.
Yeah.
Yeah. Wow. That's awesome.
Being a long time JB listener, when I, when I heard Noah and you hear him talk about nerding
out about ham radio and amateur radio, it's like, Oh, I get it. I know that stuff. You
know, it's like, it's a lot of fun.
Well, and a lot of those like technologies, um, the same style of interest or the same,
um, type of mindset that is required to have interest in it, like overlaps in those different
areas, right? So a lot of us have interest in that kind of stuff. That's great. You mentioned
that you got to leave Iraq a little bit early to go to college.
Fun story there. I'm the only person that ever graduated from Utah state university
without applying for their major.
That's awesome.
I was literally applying from Iraq and um, you know, my tour was supposed to leave, it
was supposed to be a 12 month tour and they had a program for a green to gold activity.
So they were going to make me an officer, but, and they were going to pay me while I
went to school. So I applied for this program, um, and very grateful that it existed. Uh,
and in doing so, and with the time zone difference, cause I was in Iraq while I was applying,
I didn't actually get to fill out all the paperwork the school required for picking
your major. And I wanted it to be something with, with computers and communicating. And
so they put me in the college of humanities with a degree in communication studies.
Not quite what you were looking for, right?
No, but I was so grateful to go and I learned so much. And, and when I became an officer,
the skills that I'd learned from that were great. And so, you know how you can always
ask a programmer, you know, uh, what do they use at work, right? What's their language
at work and what's their language at home, right? So, so work at soft skills, right?
And then at home, it's jumping behind a computer, building something with a network, making
cat five cable, which is one of the most relaxing things I do. It's like, it's, I'm just going
to build cat five cable for, for half a day, you know, type of thing.
It's what I need right now. Orange, white, orange, green, white, blue, blue, right, green,
brown, right, brown clips away. Yeah. Like I just, yeah, it's been there.
It's kind of meditative, right? Cause you got to focus just enough that you can't think
of anything else. And I don't try to be fast. I am not the fast
guy in the room. I'm just the guy that can get it done.
Slow is smooth, right? In the army, we say slow is smooth and smooth
is fast. So that was one of our things. Yeah. I was thinking about you and that the
other day when I was trying to rush to get somewhere and I was like packing my laptop
in my bag and things were flying all over the place. And I was like, okay, I know I'm
trying to go fast, but this has just taken way longer than how I usually systematically
like take my time to do it. Then I thought, I thought of you and I thought of that and
I was like, okay, I'm just going to slow down. And then everything just went really great.
So listening to JB from 2008, again, Jupiter at Night, some of those other shows that aren't
there anymore. SciByte was great. See, these were before my time or at least
before I got connected to them. So, uh, so I love hearing these little snippets about
them from, from long time listeners. So, and I've always wanted to contribute.
So for one episode of SciByte, um, I worked with my daughter's like third grade class
or something like that, or second grade class to submit a question to the show. And we did
that with video and it was fun. Chris is, Chris is so great. He takes out audience feedback
and content and to really tries to work it in. And that was, that was good.
That must be like a special connection to when you're a listener and you can, you can
actually like provide some content.
It feels really good cause you want to contribute back to this community. Cause as, as we'll
talk about this community has meant an awful lot over the years, um, for what they've,
what they've done for me. I don't, I don't think they've taken the time to realize it.
The army sent us to Georgia and then Germany. Georgia and Germany are two very different
places.
Right. So the next time I contributed to the show was in Germany. Um, and over there it
was hard to get Netflix, uh, working and the cell phone companies over there are a little
different than they have in the U S and so I ended up building a Linux server in my car,
which made it into an episode of last cause I sent in the video of how I did that. Um,
and it was totally not efficient, but it was, it was functional. It's like, all right, kids,
we're throwing you in the minivan and we're going to Prague, right? Like it was, you know,
they could, they were able to watch their shows off of that, you know, movie server
in the car thing. So when Chris is at his like peak stress level for content for a Linux
action show and they had a week where they just couldn't produce anything, they grabbed
that clip and they threw it as the episode of last and I was like, so, so essentially
I was a, I got to be a guest on last, which was fun. Nice. That's amazing. Yes. So that
was, that felt really good. I don't have that. And so, um, there's another gold star for
you. I'm trying to make my way around the shows every three to five years. You know,
that's basically what I'm doing here. Succeeding. Um, well, yeah. Uh, but this, this is a different
story than those other contributions and I don't think, uh, there's parts of this that
are going to be hard to talk about. So, so three deployments, three times being away
from family. Um, there's some challenges that come with that. So when I left, uh, so Iraq
the first time was interesting cause it was during the invasion and you end up with a
few cool war stories out of that. So war stories that nobody minds sharing or ones where nobody
gets hurt. And I've got a couple of those. Um, one of them was, uh, when we got there,
we had to take all of the ammunition like artillery rounds. So these things are 155
millimeters wide. Um, and they weigh about 90 pounds and it's explosives and, and whatnot.
And we'd had it and the rockets and the other things that Stomm had been stockpiling up
for years and they would put those in what we call an ammo holding area. And then we
had to destroy them. Right. So it wasn't me destroying them. I was the communications
team, you know, across the street from these guys, but that team would go over and they'd
grab a small stockpile and then put some more explosives on it and blow it up and it would
happen noon every day. Right. So you knew what time midday was because there'd be an
explosion. It's, it's kind of like a neat clock. And if you've ever been around an explosion,
the guys on the show or the guys who are listening will know what I'm talking about. You feel
your chest compress from the shockwave before you hear it. Um, which is cool. Wow. I haven't
experienced that. It really gets your, your blood going. It's kind of cool. Um, so, so
they were blowing this stuff up across the street from us. Uh, and then, um, something
happened that wasn't supposed to, instead of it just blowing up the small pile, it started
blowing up the entire ammo holding area. Oh no. The first thought I get is, is those videos
you see of like firework production facilities when they have fires and it's just kind of
like all over the place. Yeah. Okay. So you, you, you've got an image for this, right?
Right. This is, this is, this is good for us. We had, you know, kind of a sand barrier
or a berm, you know, between us and them. So we couldn't really see, um, but we could
start hearing like, Hey, that's a lot of explosions. They must really be aggressive. And then it
gets just kept going. And we were like, Oh, this is not good. So they tell us to just
leave our site, right? Leave the equipment on and just go. And I had two guys on guard
duty inside of our little area. So we've got this small Humvee that's only designed a seat
for, and we pulled up to the guard area and I jumped down into the bunker that these guys
were in and I grabbed them and I said, get out of here, jump in the car right now. So
I gave him one of my seats in the car and I'm in the back of this. Um, it would be like
the equivalent of a pickup with one of the covers on the back, right? And I'm looking
out the back as one of my dudes is just driving and he's flooring it. And I'm watching rockets
come to our left and our right. And they ended up not landing anywhere near the truck, but
there's, there's a real feeling where you can see a rocket that looks like it's headed
right your direction for, for a few seconds before it spins off and going somewhere else,
which is pretty cool. When we got to a safe location, um, I use some of my, uh, orienteering
land navigation skills and calculated out the base of the smoke, um, column that was
there. And it was over a kilometer wide. So that's how much stuff was exploding. And it
lasted until about one, two in the morning. So it's like 12 hours. It was, it was great.
Oh wow. Okay. That's a pretty good story. Nobody got hurt. So that's a fun story to
tell. Um, but it's surreal. And then, so, uh, the second deployment to Iraq was, again,
that was the 05, 06 one. And I got to leave a little early and go to college, but it was
so abrupt. Like I left, I left, you know, being in an environment where people wanted
to kill you, um, you know, and, and then being on a college campus. And so I always kept
my weapon on my, I'd strap it over my shoulder, right? And when I got to college, I would
always make sure that I had a backpack, you know, just kind of strapped over my, my shoulders
to kind of give me that it's, it's like my sense of security, right? Yeah, yeah, it is
that helped out. Um, and then Afghanistan was interesting, right? So Afghanistan was
a, a really hard deployment. Um, I bought the internet when I was down there, it costs
something like a hundred dollars a month and it was 15 kilobits a second. And, uh, I would,
I would still download the JB shows that were video cause there was a lot of torrenting
on those, uh, on those shows when they were released. And so I just set it up to download
and I'd loved using transmission, had a little, you know, uh, system 76 mirror cat. That was
my, you know, kind of download machine, um, and just prep those files. And I set up a
movie server for, uh, the team down there because again, there's no Netflix at 15 kilobits
a second, right? So you were the Netflix, right? So between JB shows and other shows
I'd keep us. So we all had someplace to escape to. Um, but the job there was really stressful.
We had to interface directly with the Afghan army a lot and try to help and train them.
And it was also at a time where we were leaving the country. And so from a system standpoint,
that's a really dangerous time period. And, and, uh, because if we're leaving the country,
um, then things are going to revert back to normal. And if these guys are seen as helping
the Americans, then it doesn't look good for them and their family, you know, puts their
family in jeopardy. And so we had, um, I think we had four interpreters when we started two
of them, uh, were caught trying to kill us, um, or sell information that would allow people
to kill us. Um, and so we had to fire them and things like that, but it was a very high
stress environment. It was very frustrating because it didn't feel like we were going
to win. You know, there was no victory defined by Congress and other things. And so it was
very hard. And, uh, immediately after that deployment, I had to, I came home and then
had to turn around and go back to, uh, some, some technical training. And so with, with
all of these deployment and except for the first one, I've never been able to kind of
just park my butt and reset and be around people that knew me before and after, uh,
these things happen. And, um, because of that change in transition, um, I've ended up with,
with PTSD and, uh, and there's a couple of different ways to get this. One of them is,
you know, the, the common classic you see it in the movies, people are faced with traumatic
events. Um, the other way to get it is to be in a traumatic stress environments, high
stress environments for a long duration of time with no opportunity to reset or escape.
So the high stress becomes your normal, I guess, right? It does. It very much does.
It's kind of like building a highway in your brain is the way I describe it. That hurts
already. Just even imagining what that might feel like. Right? I bring this up because
one of the stories I want to tell for, for the team that has been doing Jupiter broadcasting,
you know, and the alumni from Jupiter broadcasting is, you know, I've, I've had to, I've had
to reset a lot, um, and reframe a lot. And it's taken a lot of work. By the time I got
to Boise, I was so broken. This is only a couple of years ago. I was so broken that
I'd get in the lane that I could on ramp and off ramp, but I'd never change. And it didn't
matter if I was stuck. I couldn't change. I didn't feel confident changing lanes, you
know, driving on the freeway, I guess, cause there's a, an inherent risk that you might
miss your stop or that you gotta, yeah, there's a risk and that would throw off an expectation
and that would make life hard. Um, and, and so that's, that's how bad I, I was, but I
was very grateful that when I was dealing with that stress, I could escape and, you
know, enjoy the content from the JB shows. Like they were just, they were, it was nothing
to do with what I was dealing with. It was something cool and exciting and building something
that was going to be productive. And here I was trapped in an environment where even
if I were to help that army unit be as productive as possible, the system that they were surrounded
by was going to undo everything I was doing as soon as I left. And it, it just that hopelessly
frustrating situation. Um, and so, so part of this is, man, just, just thank you guys.
Like thank you for giving me that escape.
That thank you is so huge, right? Like I feel like for those of them who've been behind
the microphone and the camera, obviously for some of the video shows, um, you never really
know the audience you're reaching. Uh, you produce the material in studio, you know,
you imagine surely some people will listen to it and definitely a lot of people do. Um,
but you never really know on an individual level who you're reaching and what that impact
is delivering, right? And so to hear these stories come back, even like years later,
I would imagine for the team who was involved in that stuff, it's like a huge, massive boost
in the, the personal energy that you put into creating this content a because you're super
dedicated to it, but also because that dedication from the listeners is the connection that
we make between each other. Right. And that's really powerful stuff. I feel like that is
the reason that we are a huge community is like we all have some stuff in common and
help each other in ways that we don't even realize.
So I run a very unpopular blog right now. Right. Okay. And I've run a very unpopular
blog for like two years ish now. Right. There's 7 billion people on the planet. 15 of them
accidentally click one of my links a day. Right. Oh, that kind of unpopular. And so
I've had to reset how I look at that. And this, this applies to this as well as somebody
in India clicked on my blog, right? Like how cool is that? When I was growing up connecting
with somebody in India or China or any of these places would have been unheard of. Right.
But some computer in India or China. Okay. Yeah. You guys were technical and you're probably
going to tell me it's just some scam bot. I got that. Right. But, but it clicked on
my blog. Like that's, that's still cool that we're that connected. And, and to think of
what that means, I'm sure the guys who worked on warty warthog or whatever it was in 2005
never realized that we would, we would wait three days for that sucker to download so
we could throw it on a server just to see, you know, what's, what would stick. Right.
That obviously means that it's really valuable if you're willing to wait that long. Right.
So, so it feels like the code that people are writing in the same way that the JP shows
is like it's, it's affecting people in major ways. Exactly. Right. You can't discount the
one, you know, we look at the numbers in aggregate, right? And the numbers in aggregate don't
help us connect with the, the individuals or the individual use cases that are oftentimes
really powerful and, and what they do. I ended up inheriting an old system in Iraq or no
in Afghanistan and ended up giving it to one of the Afghan guys. Right. And guess which
operating system I threw on there? Let me see. Not Vista. No, not windows. No. And it
was, it was this old Lenovo somebody had given me with a cracked screen, but for those people
in that environment, it was a valuable tool that they could learn from. And so I threw
on 10 oh four, which to me was just the pinnacle of classic Ubuntu. 10 oh four was just, oh,
everything about it made sense and it was so good. And now my kids run a Ubuntu mate.
It gives them the versatility and it gives them that same sort of feel. But you know,
you kind of want to tell Martin Winpress, Martin, my kids are learning computers using
the code that you're, you know, working with your team to create. Like how cool is that?
Like that's their experience. Right. And, and why Ubuntu mate? Well, because I know
if I throw them in there, they can customize it 10 ways from Sunday without really breaking
it. And then when they get behind whatever system they end up using in the future, they're
kind of agnostic to the workflow, right? They can figure out any workflow on any system
that's out there. Um, because of that experience of, of working with, you know, Linux and Ubuntu
and those sorts of things and the way that the user interface is designed.
Yeah. That versatility is like priceless and reminds me of the gift that you gave to, to
some of your, um, partners. Uh, was it in Iraq when you were teaching them some of the
communications stuff with computers too? It's like you're doing the same thing with your
kids. That's powerful stuff. You're giving them tools for the future. And, and you know,
those are future Linux users, I would imagine.
So one thing working on my undergrad and that communications that wasn't really technical,
right, is, uh, I did have one teacher who was technically minded and she was actually
doing a study on how, um, the computer actually trains you, right? It is, is an interactive
part. People, um, interact with their operating systems the same way they do with people and
the brain, it has trouble noticing the difference. That's why we have to manage screen time these
days, right? Cause their brain has trouble noticing the difference between, am I interacting
with a person or am I interacting with, you know, a software or, you know, type of experience.
And, and so again, we measure screen time and I go back to Microsoft Bob because Microsoft
has, has misread the study that they commissioned on, on users. Um, because, because a user
treats the operating system like a person or like their regular environment, Microsoft
misread that.
And so they created their environment to look like what a person had in real life, hence
the bookshelves and the other things like that. And so it, it's one of those things
that, you know, when I, when I look lovingly back at Microsoft Bob and I smile because
what that shows is, is it's, it's so classic and showing us how powerful the tools we are,
um, as far as our interaction with them and, and what that means. Okay. I've been listening
to the JB shows, but I've been consuming and using operating systems and different parts
of Linux and different tools and, you know, Chris's, uh, you know, recommendations on,
on software for years. And, and, and I've chosen to, even after I knew this was going
to happen, I've chosen to let that be a part of, you know, how I'm wiring my brain to think
through problems and work through things. And this team does it, you know, on a bootstrap,
you know, budget and all those other stuff. It's like, it's what we have is amazing.
Well, and I feel like Linux in a way, uh, this is true for me is it allows you to take
older hardware or piecemeal hardware and make it useful up to today's standards, which is
an amazing gift. You know, a lot of that hardware with the software that came with it, generally
windows, um, is mostly useless. Uh, and so like for instance, you and I are talking on
my X two 20, which came out like eons ago, if you compare it to modern hardware, but
it still produces a whole bunch of magic and it's, I've got extremely modern software on
this and it's running amazingly, right? So it would otherwise end up in the landfill
and my plex server at home is running on an old Mac pro from 2008. Yeah, exactly. Right.
That's awesome. Because it has the four bays of, you know, for hard drive space that I
wanted. And it was, you know, it, it just works and it works like a champ, the transcoding
on that thing. And I've got friends and family for days on that, you know, banging at it.
And it's, it's holding up because it's running Linux and it's, it's able to add value to
all of their lives. Um, so that's, that's really cool. I'm also the sort of person that
doesn't, uh, I don't tend to sit still very well in, in what sense, like, like that you
always need to be solving a problem or that you always need to be doing something or I
have trouble sitting still physically and sitting still mentally. Um, so I've ended
up writing like three books at this point, um, which is fun just cause I had something
I wanted to share. Um, and I've done a lot of projects on the side and when I do something,
I do a lot of it. So it's like all or nothing. Right. So in college compared to what I was
dealing with my long days in Iraq, right. I, uh, I turned around, so this is for my
bachelors. So I decided to figure out how many credits I could do in one semester without
having to get the Dean's approval. Um, turns out at Utah state university, you can do 24
semester hours without having to get the Dean's approval. And I did all 24 and ran a 5k that
raised money for charity and had our third kid. So that was, that was pretty good. And
then the next semester it was, it was, Hey, this academia thing likes publishing. Um,
I'm going to write a paper that gets published. And I did that as an undergrad, which was
a lot of fun. Um, so, so that was cool. And then, uh, you know, coming back from Afghanistan,
I started working on my master's preparation for leaving military and that sort of stuff.
And, uh, sort of really, really, um, had a job in Germany that required a lot of my attention.
I was in command of 138 soldiers. We had, uh, we had a 34% turnover every year because
of rotations that they're just naturally scheduled and the Russians invaded the Ukraine. So I
was constantly sending communications teams out to Latvia, Lithuania, Spain, you know,
and all England, um, or some of the other places they went. They went to Israel, uh,
one time, uh, lots of things in Germany, lots of things in Poland. Um, and so I was sending
teams out all over the place and working on my master's on the side and my master's program
did not include, so it was distance education and did not include lectures. And it was,
I wanted to be an it project manager. So they had the program for that. Cool. Great. There's
some few it classes. There's a bunch of project management classes, put them all together
and Bob's your uncle. And without any lectures, understanding the context of the content,
cause I'm, I'm a self learner, but a lot of times when you Google something, you only
get the answer you need, right? For that specific problem, not the greater picture. Right. So
if we take something basic, like, you know, how does, how does TCP IP work, right? You
might find, uh, the instructions to configure it on windows, but that doesn't really explain,
you know, all of the parts of how it works and was designed and, and those sorts of,
you know, things. And so you miss that context. And it was about this time that, um, I, I
was struggling in my classes that I just started paying a little more attention to the tech
snap show. Um, back when Chris and Alan were doing that and Chris always, I think you have
the introduction memorize, you know, he would get on like his baseball announcer voice,
right? And he'd be like, and, and joining me or is Alan Jude, you know, the tech, the
admin and the teacher, you know, and Alan would break down, has just a snack to break
down complex concepts into ways that the audience can understand, right? You're not insulting
the technical folks in the audience and you're really allowing the folks who aren't quite
there yet to bring them in. And so Alan and Chris were essentially my teaching duo for,
they were the lectures I needed to get through my coursework for those it classes.
Wow. Oh, that's huge. And it sounds like a perfect timing too, right?
It was, Oh, and my goodness, the show notes, they do such a good, they did such a good
job on those show notes that what I would do is I would go through and be like, okay,
I can write that into a paper. I'm gonna, I'm gonna, you know, like I'm gonna write
that new paper, write that new paper. So I'd be on my little commute right now. Okay. All
right. So I'm listening to tech snap. This is what's going on. And then other stuff from
last would tie off with it. And you know, I'd, I'd pull all these things together. And
so by the time I'd sit down on the weekend, cause that was the only time I had time, I
was working 14 hour days on the job and come home on the weekend. And I don't think my
family really saw me much in Germany. And I'd sit there and lock myself in a room for
all of Saturday and most of Sunday and just start cranking out papers. But thanks to the
show notes, right? The research was basically done. I didn't have to go Google where to
find the sources. I had the list of the sources. I could go back and read the articles. I could
pull out the relevant material. I could put that together and submit it for my professors
and academia, at least for this university was not as cutting edge on tech, you know,
as, as I would have liked them to be. And I was, the teachers were writing me back and
really impressed with my sources and you know, kind of, kind of appreciative that I was helping
keep them current as opposed to just referencing something published in an academic journal,
you know, and I'd mix it up, right? I'd use academic journals as well, but you know, that
it totally reduced my research load to have all of that JB content and be able to, to
get my masters that way, which was just, just awesome to hear that one of the shows helped
you get through your masters. It's unbelievable. And like so valuable, like unbelievably valuable.
That's amazing. Well, let's put this into perspective. 15 people visited my blog in
the last 24 hours. One of them was from India, right? So Chris has been producing content
for over 10 years now, it feels like. So some, at some point it's going to stick with one
or more audience members and Hey, I'll be the one for today. And maybe there's another
one out there and two or three people and you can sleep well at night, right? There's
7 billion people in the world. It's about time you made a difference for one of them.
No, I'm totally kidding. It's it's, I really am appreciative of it. And I know there's
a bigger network than that. I just, I'd never get to see him cause I've never made it to
Linux Fest North to see that crew or any of the other conferences.
Did you ever get a chance to meet any of them? I did get a chance to meet Chris. So I'm working
on my masters. I'm working on my PTSD issues. I'm leaving the army and I have no job, right?
There's nobody that's jumping out. I've only lived in Boise at that point for like a year.
So I don't have a professional network of people that want to hire Jacob. I'm trying
to build that network and I'm working on my masters. And so I applied for a job just,
so I could get an interview, right? I was just throwing my resume out there just so
I could get an interview. And this guy ended up picking me up and wanting me to be an intern
at his entrepreneurial software development shop. You know, so, so I say, Hey, cool. Let
me do my army job in the morning. I'm done with that. I'll come over and work with you
guys. And Oh, by the way, I'm working on my masters. So, you know, I was taking two master's
classes at the same time and now working two jobs. It's great. It was just, it was awesome.
What I did is I was, I was working on that and he wanted to bring me on full time when
I left the service. And so dealing with the anxiety PTSD issues I had, Oh boy, that felt
really good to know that at least I had something to land on after I left the service instead
of just avoid, I suppose. Right. And so the show that helped me the most through that
process happened to not be on Netflix and it wasn't on ABC or NBC. It was also on Jupiter
broadcasting, right? And it was Coder radio because literally this entrepreneurial shop
was doing the exact same things that the Coder radio team was doing, you know, in their entrepreneurial
shop just on the other side of the country. So I'm sitting there and, and you can understand
cause I was a hardware implementation guy and then I was a leadership guy, right? So
you're going to develop software and I have no idea how to write a line of code, but I
had to at least not fake it, but understand the language and Coder radio really helped
close the gap on that. So I'm in this position where I'm leaving the service. So I've got
to turn in all my army gear at the end of this, right? And so they told me to turn in
my army gear in Fort Lewis, Washington, which is in Tacoma area, right? So it's a little
south of where Chris is at. And so I travel out there and on my way out there, I think
I messaged Chris like a month out like, Hey, I'm going to be in the area. I'd really love
to take you out to dinner or breakfast, something like that. And, and so we landed on breakfast
and, and Hideo helped coordinate that cause Chris was dealing with a lot and oh boy, she's
just so nice. And Angela, Angela in the background of all the shows. Oh, Angela is one of my
favorite people in the world. And I wish she had her own show again, cause there's something
about the way she sees tech that it's just, Oh, you made it approachable for me. So, so
Hideo was so nice and helping to set that up and, and Chris and had the kids that weekend.
And so I bought them all. I think we met at I hopper at Denny's. And so I bought breakfast
for him, brought coloring books for the kids. And, and I think Chris was uncaffeinated or
didn't have a good night's sleep. And I was extraordinarily nervous because here I'm meeting
a hero of mine, you know, and I remember one of the kids was like, dad, you're famous.
And Chris looks at him and he says, I'm internet famous, son. It's a little different. And
so it was not this like, Oh, we got to come to this moment where I got to give him a hug
and just tell him thank you and what it meant. I did get to tell him the story of, Hey, I've
got this job offer. I can land, but you know, with the kids there and everything else with
that, we kept the conversation pretty light. And I never got to tell that whole backstory
of, man, I've been, I've been, I've had issues building up with me for years. And those highways
in my head that I've got to try to, you know, disconnect and, and, and short, short circuit,
right. So I can be, be functional and how just having that offer available, you know,
meant so much to me and how his team has helped to produce that over the years. I mean, you're
making differences in people's lives and it's just awesome. Um, and I think he got it, right?
I'll have to find out later on, you know, right. We'll see what he says after this guys,
guys communicate differently, right? Um, sometimes you don't have to say things. And, and for
those of you guys that may know somebody, for those in the audience that may know somebody
who is dealing with PTSD or other issues, one of the best things you can do is just
sit next to them. It sounds really weird, but just sitting next to somebody when they're,
when they're having a moment where they're disconnected or they zone out, don't say anything
till you're asked, but just sitting there makes all the difference. It is so, so comfortable
to have that.
The power of presence, right?
Yeah. Uh, now as cool as that story is, I didn't end up taking that job.
This is a twist. I did not expect the shop was about to go through a really hard period
in order to make the transition in the shop that I would need to, to be functional. Um,
I didn't have the experience to be able to stand up to, I mean, it's a small 10 person,
15 person shop, right? Um, and I didn't have the experience to be able to, to confidently
say no to the boss when I needed to. And I knew that and I didn't want to be in that
position where he did hire me for three months and then have to let me go cause we had a
professional disagreement and I couldn't back up what I was saying. Um, but where I've landed
is absolutely great. Um, uh, so Idaho is known for I'm quizzing you. Idaho is known for what
Brent, do you know?
Well, the first thing that comes to my mind is potatoes.
That is absolutely correct. So in Pocatello, I believe, um, yeah, that's one of the areas.
There's quite a few actually. I get to work for the Jr Simplot company is one of their
project managers. Um, and I'm on a great team. Um, and, uh, the Jr Simplot company is known
for being the largest supplier of McDonald's French fries in the world. No way. And now
we do way more than that, right? We have way more going on than just McDonald's, but, um,
that's best what we're known for. Um, and so the team I get to work with is great. And
what's neat here is I've got that mentor gap is closed, right? I had a, I had a mentor
gap in a lot of my other experiences, whether it means learning it or me in that entrepreneurial
shop, you know, and I know by the way, I have such great memories of all of that, right?
That, that shop was so, so good at what they did. We helped reorganize their hiring process,
right? And they ended up making the ink 500 because they were able to hire people so quickly
and get the right talent in. It was like 69% improvement in a four week period or something
like that. When I sat down and looked at how we were, how the processes, once you, once
you do, once you do a process map on it, you know, you can, you can build things out from
there. Um, and one of the things I do at work here and one of the ways I got the job here,
so I came on as a contractor and then they picked me up full time at a moment where they
were getting rid of all their contractors and they didn't have a whole lot of open positions.
So I'm really lucky. But one of the reasons they picked me up here is because I'm the
sort of guy that, uh, I'm, I'm, I just want to help get the workflow done. And I know
a lot of tools to do it. And so I'm able to, to jump in and help people like get through
things. And again, that goes back to the shows and the content from, and the experience with
running Linux is you have to figure it out, right? You've learned, we've all learned,
if you're listening to the show, you have a gift that you may not realize you have learned
how to build your workflow and stuff where there may not be good documentation, right?
Where the software may be buggy and where nobody's going to spell it out for you. And
oh, by the way, if you find a YouTube video, it's probably going to be somebody's hobby
project with 300 views. It's so true. You and I have both done photography, right? If
I want to know how to create a mask in Photoshop, I have 600 videos to choose from, right? Yeah.
In all versions of Photoshop, whatever. Yeah, exactly. You get a dark table. We just don't
have the community there. So you had to learn it on your own. And that has made me a powerful
force for good at work with helping people be productive and get their content out there.
And then changing the culture is a part of it too. I'm at the point now where I'm influencing
culture. Our project team is about 200 right now, and it's going to be about 500 in the
next six months. And so the project culture is going to impact the broader culture of
this company that is globally known for producing really good food products, including good
french fries. That's amazing. So it must feel to you like you're making a massive difference
still in the work that you're doing and that I would imagine feels really good, especially
coming from some of the previous experiences you've had. Yeah. So you remember that frustration
I had about Afghanistan where it didn't feel like my effort was going to make a difference
at all. I can make a difference individually. And we did. One of our interpreters is now
living in the United States. He was able to come and move his family. And so he's safe.
His family's safe. And he's down in Texas and really doing well. And I've kept in touch
with him a couple of times a year. But now on the other side of it is I'm a part of the
company's mission statement is we help feed the world. And they've got a challenge statement
downstairs that says, can you think big enough to feed a billion people? Yes. Okay. That's
a challenge. Right. And, and so, and so that's, that's where we're going as a company and
what I feel like I'm contributing to. And then Carl Sagan once said that the advances
in science and agriculture have done more for creating world peace and lifting people
up out of poverty than any war has ever done or ever will do. And I'm totally paraphrasing.
Yeah. Fair enough. It's still had the impact. Wow. So now I'm on the other side of that
coin, right? I'm on the other side of the coin where it's like, Hey, I don't always
directly get to see who I impact, you know, at the, at the end of where people consume
our products, but I do get to see the impact of the people who are helping to do that.
And I, they like working with me and I like being around them and, and it's getting me
to the point where I can be human functional has been a, been an interesting road and getting
me to the point where I can be technical functional and all these things have kind of merged recently.
And then one of those arms is the JB audience. So I get to share that with you guys today.
Yeah, that's pretty amazing. The JB community, you know, I've been in it in a deep way only
for a few years now and it feels like just a massive family, right? Where some people
you're closer to and as time shifts, you get closer to other people for you. The shows
were that family for a long time and they were the, like the person sitting beside you
silently, you know, in your ear while you're doing those commutes in, in various situations
and places, right?
Chris has spent a lot of time on the quality over the years and, and part of it is to create
that intimacy between the audience and, and the hosts. And so literally like, look, I,
I can't tell any of these people apart, you know, you know, if I ever meet them, but it's
the, it's the it feels like there's a connection there and they, they spent the time to make
sure that things were good enough that that could exist. And then the difference that
it makes because it exists.
Somebody has got to say thank you around here because, you know, this is only the first
10 years of JB, you know, what is, what is the next 10 years, you know, look like, right?
Like
That's the challenge statement right there.
Can you think big enough to feed a billion people right on my end, right? And you guys
have this challenge statement of, you know, reaching more people and making more of a
difference.
That's massive. I feel in many ways, completely honored to help craft that challenge from
hearing your story. That's really unbelievable.
But the way you do these interviews and, and the way L talks and, and the cast now, you
guys and Wes and, and Chris has just always been solid on this is you guys are not in,
you're making the content approachable for people who are not technical. And that makes
such a big difference because not a whole lot of people have that gift. And the fact
that there's this many people that have that gift working at JB is just really cool. I
mean, Litix Academy, like snatching you guys up is just gotta be so happy and thrilled
because that's part of what they do too is helping to make content, you know, approachable,
you know, at different levels of knowledge.
Yeah, there are certainly these great synergies happening there for sure. And I think as listeners
here, you're seeing some of that benefit for sure. And for you, it feels like, you know,
what, what is JB going to be for you in the next few years? You know, what are you hoping
to get out of it?
Oh, yeah. If I get to choose my own adventure because it's been part of your life for the,
for the last little while there. So what do you need next? We'll give it an, I think extras
dot show. Um, if, if I had my, if I had all the time in the world, right, I would, I would
create a, um, content for extras, uh, for the, the extras feed on fonts. Oh man, that
is a rabbit hole, isn't it? Right. Um, but we so often overlook the systems in our lives
that make a difference, right? We don't notice. Um, there was a story of a guy who said thank
you when he picked up his coffee one morning and then his kids like, well, or the, the,
the barista was like, well, don't thank me. Thanks. So, and so who delivers the beans,
right? And he ended up having like a year, he wrote a book on this, right? About spending
like a year saying thank you to everybody that involved him getting his coffee and how
connected we are. Right. And, and, and so fonts are part of that system where we just don't
notice, right? Like it's, it's, I mean, you probably do cause you do photography and you're
graphically minded, right? But, but most of the people, when I walk around and I'll, I'll
gripe about, you know, Helvetica or Ariel or something like that, they'll be like, what
does it matter, Jacob? You know? And it's like, no, it matters. You know, uh, my Halloween
shirt was the word Helvetica written in Comic Sans, which is the only time Comic Sans should
ever touch my body. Yep. You get it. I think cheese is going to love hearing this. And
all my goodness, I haven't mentioned it. Those graphics that he's designed. Wow. Like way
to get the theming down. So it totally works in my podcast app guys. Like it makes it so
much more approachable. Oh, that usability stuff is like, just like what you mentioned.
If you don't like, obviously you're noticing it now, but there are some professions that
are, um, that have the challenge that if they're done well, nobody notices. Yes. Yes. And,
but, uh, and it, it just takes asking questions. Like, how did this happen? You know, why do
people care so passionately about X? Right. And then understanding the Y and, and you
can disagree with their solution or their, their, the end result of their thought process.
Right. But understanding the Y just makes it so it makes so much sense. Um, I was listening
to the Ubuntu podcast and they were talking about a flat earthers. I didn't even know
that was a topic, man. I didn't notice topic. So, so, and I'm like, I'm like, okay, well,
how did they get to this point? Like how, how did they get to, and I started listening
to, you know, some of the commentary, both sides and, and realizing that, Oh, Oh, okay.
They just reject any evidence that they can't see or touch. And then that leads them to
this conclusion. Oh, it totally makes sense. I can, I can get along with flat earthers
now. You know, like, like I don't agree with them.
Well, and you know what? I think that is the right approach to most problems is like, okay,
if I don't understand it, I shouldn't, um, resist it or, or be aggressive towards it.
I should ask questions to try to understand their perspective. I think you totally nailed
it. Uh, and that's hugely valuable.
So when you, you see the differences in how, like, I would really love to know why when
Ubuntu went back to gnome, right. Versus KDE. Cause KDE was in my mind from a user experience
was much more sure my mouse worked, right? Like, you know, you have those odd issues
on Linux. I've never had a conversation with Mark Shutterworth, but as his benevolent dictator
for life, you know, like, Hey man, can you walk me back a few steps and say how you got
there? Cause I see the results. And now though, like, Oh my goodness, they've done such a
good job in that space. You know, um, that it's really awesome. And one of the things
I wanted to share in this is there's a difference in how we compute like this audience, there's
a difference in how they compute. Most of the people I work with see their machines
as allowing them to be productive. And the Linux community sees a computer as allowing
them to be expressive.
Well said. That's such a big difference, right?
And so, so then we get to choose, right? Once you realize that you want to be expressive,
then you get to choose, how do I want to be expressive? And that's where all the options
come in. And so that, that, that some of that infighting that was a lot more prominent back
in the day where this is better than that, right? It's like, no, no, no, no, no, it's
not better. This is how I choose to be expressive, you know, and we need to recognize that. And
right now my choice is I'm guys, I hate to admit it to you. I'm running a Mac book pro.
Um, and I love it because I love final cut and a few of the other things. And that doesn't
discredit any of the work in the Linux community. You're still powering at least five systems
in my house or three systems in my house in various ways, you know, but it's how I choose
to be expressive with the tool. Um, and, and where, where's that road going to lead me?
You know, I don't know what that next phase of this looks like, but I feel like I can,
I can be more expressive in every aspect or every challenge I come up with in life because
of these experiences and learning how to use these tools and learning how to help people
through things.
Yeah, I feel like looking at our tools as means of expression is, is huge. Um, and you
helped me clarify for myself what I felt, but not been able to explain. And because
like many of us, I imagine the people surrounding me have far less interest in, in computers
and Linux than I do. Like most of them, when I mentioned Linux, they're like, huh, what
is that? Um, but the, the real gift is that this is a tool I've discovered for myself
that allows me to be expressive, especially that I tend to do creative work on it. Right.
Um, but even, even tinkering with software problems or hardware problems, like that's
a means of expression and building my own systems. And I don't mean computer system,
but I mean like systems that surround me and make me a more productive person or a better
person is an amazing way to be expressive. And the JB community for me, and I would assume
exactly for you as well, is a way of connecting with people who also get that. And so the
way you worded it, it was like, Oh, I know I'm sitting beside someone who totally gets
me for sure.
Yeah. And, but we may disagree, right? Like, like I, you and I both like dark table, but
after that I'm, I'm not jumping in to get man. Like I just, Nope, I'm good. I'll just,
whatever dark table can do, cause I'm not a professional photographer. I'll do in dark
table and then I'll walk away. And you know, for the purposes of capturing my family memories,
I'm good enough. And that works right. Whereas you're probably more comfortable in there,
um, than, than I am. So yeah, it's just, it's, it's different, but it's complimentary and
it's so cool when you see people that get it and can talk that way. You guys have Linux
Fest Northwest and it's a big hoo-ha and I think that's great. One of these days I'll
get there. It's like my pilgrimage to Mecca, but not quite as important as that. What we
have here is, uh, around, it's usually like the Friday after the 4th of July, we have
a free fry day where we give away French fries. And, and if you've never been to Boise, especially
downtown Boise, you've got to give it a shot. Right? So right across like the next building
to us has a six story slide. Okay. Got it. So, so you got to let that sink in for a second,
right? Like, like, remember the slide as a kid, right? Like it was cool and it felt really
tall when you were small. So it's like somebody around here decided let's do that on steroids.
Let's do that for adults, right? We have a six story slide. We give away free French
fries. How can you not have fun in that environment? Right? Exactly. Right. And then there's usually
a giant octopus that like starts eating the building next door as well, which is also
cool. You know, I don't think they've settled on the date for free Friday next year, but
if you Google it around June, July or around, uh, uh, we usually post that about May, June
timeframe, you will be able to find out when free Friday is in Boise and, and the team's
welcome to come. Sure. Yeah. I think you just hit on something too that I've been really
impressed with the more and more I learn about the Jupiter broadcasting community, which
is that, um, we're scattered a little bit everywhere, literally around the world. And
I'm, I'm planning a trip to go see Alex, uh, from self-hosted, uh, we've been meaning to
get connected and he and I have a similar trajectory into JP. So we were really, really
close friends now. And, uh, and so I'm planning the strip and I was thinking like, Oh geez,
well I'm, you know, I'm close to New York. I know there's some JP listeners there and
Oh yeah, I'm, I'm, I'm going to be in Raleigh and I'm close to like, maybe I might end up
in Savannah. I know some people there might go see Drew. And so it was like all of a sudden
my like daily life for at least these special trips that I do, which is almost daily, um,
end up being connected all the dots being connected by, uh, Jupiter broadcasting community
members. And that feels like, okay, I've got a family anywhere I go now, which is so powerful.
And I feel like you as a JB community member, you chose to go anywhere you can, you can
find someone. Right. And, uh, and that invitation you just gave gets given all the time. And
it's just like such a beautiful thing. So thank you for, for putting that out there.
It's massive.
Well, and, and we got to thank the folks who make the swag happen because one of the towns
in this Valley is Nampa, Idaho. And it's like what, 80,000 people, not a whole lot, but
it has a Costco and I'm walking in Costco one day with my wife and there's somebody
wearing a last t-shirt. And so it's like, Hey man, can I take a photo with you real
quick? And so we exchanged phone numbers afterwards and like, you know, every once in a while
we'll text back and forth. I'm like, Hey, how's it going? It's going fine. You know,
but there's, there's like, you know, three people I know of that are, that are huge fans
of the program in the Valley. And that'll, there's more. I just haven't met them or connected
with them. Um, cause for kids, I mean, we're running around with all kinds of activities.
So I could only imagine for sure. It's a lot of fun. And it's so cool when I see that my
kids don't struggle with technology because we've, they've had the experiences where something
didn't work and then it became a learning opportunity. Um, and that's why when L describes
learning, that's been resonating with me recently so much because it's like, Oh, this is really
uncomfortable for me right now. Oh, I must be having a learning experience. The reward
is at the end of this. This must be a positive thing. Yeah, exactly. For sure. Um, is there
a specific, um, place where L mentioned that kind of stuff that really hit you? Like one
of her talks or, or on one of the shows or something? I think it was something she tweeted
or retweeted where it was like, you know, typical programmer life where it's like, you
know, this sucks. I hate programming. This sucks. I hate programming. This sucks. I hate
programming. This sucks. It worked. I love programming. You know, like, like seven lines
down. I could totally relate to that. And you know, whoever wrote that, like had to
calculate out the 240 characters going backwards to figure out how many lines they could do
to make it, make it meaningful. And it's like, I really, if I could double heart that tweet,
that tweet, I totally would have because it's like, I understand the thought behind this.
You mentioned when we were chatting a few days ago, um, you mentioned something called
the theory of constraints and you got my ears up and I'm very curious about that and I know
nothing about it. So I was wondering, can you give us like a theory, theory of the constraints
one Oh one.
Yes. So the, Oh, I love this theory. It's so awesome. Um, so one of the things that's
great here is it labels itself as a theory. So if it doesn't work in your world, then
Hey, it was just a theory, right? Right. Um, but the theory of constraints says that for
any process that has several steps, right? One of those steps will be the constraint.
Okay. And this came out of manufacturing, right? So if you have five different work
centers, right? And the first work center can do five widgets an hour. The second one
can do four, the third one can do three, right? And then the last two can each do five, right?
Your constraint is the one that can do three. So you really don't need to worry about the
other ones because the only constraint in the system is the one that can do three. But
if you have local, um, measurements on each of those, um, work resources, right? You're
going to encourage the guys that can do five to do five. You're going to encourage the
guy that can do four to do four. And, and then the guy that does three is sitting there
and they've got a whole bunch of back, you know, back stock, right? Or backlog sitting
in front of them and they can't do anything about it. Um, because that's, that's their
capacity. So the theory of constraints is kind of like five steps on how to identify
that. Um, and then what you can do to protect the constraint and then what you can do to
improve the constraint and then how you can continue to repeat that system and go through
it. Um, and it was written by, uh, uh, a physicist, right? So, so, you know, take solutions from
one discipline and bring them into another, right? So physicists like to look for a common
denominator among things. And so when he was called to do some manufacturing consultant,
he tried to say, well, what's the common denominator in manufacturing? And this is what he came
up with. His name was Eliahu Goldrat. Um, and, uh, he's written several books after
that, and it's just been really great. And, and from the project management side, when
you can, when your brain's wired to see something as a system, right? When you can identify
the constraint and support the constraint and then be able to protect the constraint
and allows that system to be more productive, um, and is really, um, a very, very helpful
tool to use. I also wondered for you how that got applied in your personal life, even cause,
cause you know, you and I both have minds that are wired to see our lives as systems.
And so I imagine it carried over for you. So what happened by accident the first time
those 24 semester hours in college was B and I didn't know about the theory of constraints
in my, in my undergrad work, but, uh, it came about because I realized that I was spending
most of my time doing research. And so it was like, okay, well how can I, how can I
make my research, uh, I can, I can keep it the constraint, but I can maximize the output
of that constraint. And so what I did is I figured out that you can hack college by taking
complimentary classes. So you can do a full semester where you're doing, um, you know,
international business, uh, and learning the communication styles. You need to be successful
there and combine that with your English class. So you can take your English 201 or whatever
the case may be, and you can combine that with a public speaking class and you can combine
that with a rhetoric class, right? And then you can throw your math class in there for
good measure. So that way you're not, you know, falling behind on what you should be
working on. But, but when you, when you combined all of that stuff and then there were a few
other classes I took on the, on the side as well. But when you combine all that stuff,
what's beautiful about that is you can take the research from one discipline and one class
and bring that as a source into another one. So you're still writing five, six, seven different
papers, right?
But there's clearly an overlap between them, right?
Yes.
And it, it allows you to leverage that going forward. And so when we take a look at our
lives and we say, okay, well where's my constraint, right? So I don't like not being able to learn.
I'm a lifelong learner, right? My commute's a half hour. And so I listen to podcasts and
I listen to audio books because now that half hour is not constraining me from learning.
I'm learning, I've been learning so much recently I've had to turn it off and just have quiet
on the way home for about 10 minutes. Um, and it wasn't because of stress, it was because
I need to absorb and, and get that into my head. So there's different ways of doing that.
When you're, look at your system and your photography workflow and figure out, Hey,
where's my constraint and, and what does that look like? And you don't want to remove it.
You want to hack it. You want to make it more powerful. If it's really bad, yes, you can
absolutely re you know, like adjust it so it's no longer the constraint, but then you
have to go looking for it again. So sometimes it's valuable just to, Hey, let's leave this
be the constraint, but both the workflow around it and figure out how to, how to make things
better.
Yeah. I like how one of the aspects you mentioned in that process is to protect the constraint.
And that feels like, Oh wait, we always want to like break down the things that aren't
working or like get rid of them like you were saying, but, but that protection piece feels
really meaningful. So I'm going to have to dive into that.
Well in a lot of the audience will be familiar with Kanban boards and what you need to recognize
when you're using a Kanban board is you are protecting the constraint because you're letting
the constraint not be distracted by having to give a status update, right? And so because
somebody can walk up to the board, right? Whether it's digital or physical, it doesn't
matter. They can walk up to the board and they can see what is currently going on and
what the status is. So as long as your users are disciplined, as long as your resources
are disciplined to update the board, you know, and that becomes accurate, then you're protecting
the constraint. And, and one of the ways that you can use to explain that to them, cause
they'll grok it pretty quickly is if, cause some people are like, I just get worked on,
just leave me alone. I just get worked on. No, no, no. I need you to not only get the
work done, I need you to just do this little thing, little admin thing every, you know,
sometimes hourly, right? But more often, you know, once or twice a day to let people know
where things are at and reset yourself. And I do that with my boss right now. It's like
I showed up and I had a different tool set in mind than he did. And I said, look, dude,
I said, I'm going to put my tool set over here and you're going to have visibility to
it all the time. You're not going to have to wonder what I'm doing. It's going to be
right here. And, and he's been learning how to use the tool and be able to see what's
on my plate and be able to say, Hey, this has been sitting there for a while. You know,
we can have that dialogue now. So it's been helpful.
Wow. That's an amazing tool. I am very jazzed to integrate it into my own pieces. So thank
you for sharing that. It's awesome. Uh, I wondered, uh, Jacob, if you, if there's anything
that you wanted to share with the community, uh, kind of an ask something you maybe want
them to try or think about there's, there's two things here. One's selfless and one is
selfish or self-interested. Oh, I like this. Okay. So, so the first one is to, to tie off
with your interview with wimpy about poo pooing out other people and their projects. And,
and mine's, mine's just a little different twist is whether you're a user or a consumer
or producer in that space, uh, take the time to be grateful for what it is. Um, you know,
and maybe that means disconnecting first to really think through what that is. We're using
code, right? That's 20, 50, 30 years old, right? Have we ever bothered to say thank
you, right? The, the guy who invented bash, I heard an interview he did. I, what a totally
realistic story. He invented globbing before he invented quotes. And I'm, I don't know
if too many people under there's a part of the audience that gets that right off me saying
that, but, but what that means is that he sat there and he, as he was welding out bash,
he figured out how to do that. You know, asterisk, you know, delete asterisk, everything, right?
You know, type of thing, right? So he was, he was working. And so on, on making sure
you can use the asterisk and it would delete all the things. And as he was doing that,
he, he decided to delete all the working files that he had in a particular directory. So
we put that particular directory or a particular thing in quotes and ended up deleting everything
on the system and had to start over and rewrite bash. That's one way to learn. And I think,
I think bash is better because of it. But when you realize that there's a human story
behind it, oh my goodness, doesn't it make it easier to just say thank you for sticking
it out and finishing that, you know, thank you guys for sticking it out and finishing
that. Even if I may not be using it right now, cause it may not be how I want to express
myself. Pause, take a moment and say thank you to somebody, handwritten card, a post
on Twitter. So pick your favorite host, pick your favorite, you know, tool and, and find
a way to tell the person thank you in a way that, that just lets them know you, you cared.
And so that's the selfless task that's out there. And the other one is, is, you know,
I guess that my blog is really unpopular. I wonder what it would be like if it were
popular. So tell us a little bit what it's about, what you put down there, how you're
dedicated to it and what you'd like people to get out of it. So I've never been able
to run an agile project. The military runs waterfall. The projects have been on a worker
waterfall oriented and I wanted to try something that was completely agile. And so listening
again, the Ubuntu podcast was influential in this where I think it was a Popey was saying
that he would just do a Twitter kind of audio feed and then send that out or not Twitter.
It was over a telegram. He's just telegram feed. And I was like, wow, that's like podcast
MVP. Like I've got an iPhone. I'm just going to go ahead and start recording something
to call the podcast. And, and so I've been adding every week or every two weeks, I will
change the workflow cause I'll look at my constraint and I'll change the workflow one
or two steps. And I'm getting close now where it's like, okay, once I've got episode numbers,
this thing's legit and it's happening. And I think I'm about a week away. And that's
been another thing too, is like as first is just, I'm just going to talk, we'll figure
out what the topic is later. And where I've landed over the last couple of weeks is taking
curiosity and gratitude and taking a look at the people and systems in our lives that,
that make a difference. There are about five minutes and it sometimes gets real nerdy and
weird. Like, like there's, Oh my goodness. What was it yesterday? This might not make
it a family show. We'll find out. But, um, synonymous words don't equate to the same
thing. Okay. Okay. Um, and if you understand English as a system, right, then this becomes
really cool. So English is a system and I like exploring English. So, but dial, right?
Okay. It means that your phone made a call now, but, and booty are synonymous, right?
Your button, your booty are the same thing. I see where this is. All right. Continue.
And dial and call, right? Are synonymous words as well. But dial is not booty call. Right?
Right. One may lead to the other. Well, yeah. Yeah. I didn't take it that way in the episode
when I recorded it, but you're not wrong. Um, one of the things that does for us though,
and I like to point this out in the show is it means that even though you may be using
synonymous language, right? You may not be conveying the same message. And so let's stop
and take a look at what is the language we're using? When are we understood and when are
we not understood? So that way we can be more productive. And that's kind of the way I take
it is, you know, find something that I enjoy a little bit curious about and obscure and
then, and then pull that together and, and, uh, having fun. So, so I did my challenge
on this. I challenged the user error guys. What is the most useless job that you would
be willing to do? Oh, interesting. Right? So most useless job that you'd be willing
to do. And mine is absolutely really fun. So I'll tell you mine while you think of yours,
Brent. So most useless job that you'd be willing to do. And mine is, uh, you know, from having
worked for the government, I know they're pretty ineffective and ineffectual. And so
they, they create a lot of jobs that I consider useless or not value add. And, um, so you
have to find a position where one of those jobs that are created by requirement, you
know, there's not actually the requirement on the ground. And so what I came up with
was I would love to be a lifeguard at the Olympics, totally useless. And then as I was
talking on the show and recording and I was like, oh my goodness, this is the greatest
reality TV show ever. If the Olympics goes to Los Angeles and I think it might be scheduled
to, if the Olympics is going to Los Angeles, somebody should create a reality TV show where
they get people to compete for being lifeguards. Right. And then at the end of it, help them
realize that it's the most useless job ever. Right. Cause you'd be this great competition,
like these really buff, you know, strong guys. And then at the end of it, you'd be like,
Hey, by the way, you're just going to sit there for eight hours a day while you're watching
Michael Phelps. It could be worse. Oh yeah. That wasn't the question, right? The question
is the most useless job you'd be willing to do. So right. Do you have, do you have
a most useless job that you'd be willing to do in the same kind of vein as yours? I would
be willing to do something where I get to observe people. Uh, I think connecting with
people, uh, is super powerful. So maybe it would be like, I don't know, something like
greeting the greeters at Walmart or something like that, you know, uh, where I can just
like watch people and their behaviors and just kind of enjoy life and people's lives
for what they are. I think something like that would be pretty interesting.
So yours is actually trying to add value. You're so wired that way, Brent. That's, that,
that is awesome. No, it tells you something about your personality. You are wired to connect
with people and, and you really do a good job. And that is one of the reasons, um, for
those who, who aren't quite aware, this is the first time at this large of an audience
that I've ever really talked about some of the things I've dealt with in my past. And
one of the reasons for that is because of the way that the, the, the way that you, as
a host connect with the audience and connect with your, your guests. Um, and it's, this
has felt really comfortable and I really appreciate it.
Awesome. Well, I feel so completely honored to help you tell that story. Uh, I feel like
it has been obviously a super important story for you, uh, with massive growth in it and
vulnerability, of course. Uh, and to see where you are now, uh, you're still taking those
experiences you've had and giving gifts to the people around you, which is really powerful.
And so if I could have some way of helping you spread that message, I feel like, uh,
I feel like that's a total honor. So thank you for reaching out to me with it. That's,
that's huge. If people want to get connected with you to say thanks, since you put that,
that challenge out there, where, where do you think you would send them?
Well, the blog podcast YouTube channel thing is all parking thought.com, right? So the
idea is I take my drive out or I take my thoughts out for a bit of a drive and then I share
them with you when I park. Um, it's a one take sort of deal. It's going to stay a one
take sort of deal. Um, and it's honestly my morning coffee. Well, I don't drink coffee,
but it's kind of like my morning coffee because it gets me starting to practice communicating
before I go into work a lot of times. And so that, that helps me prepare for the day
and gives me a frame to think through. So, yeah, so you're welcome to find me there.
Twitter is on there as well.
Right. We'll find all the goods there. That's amazing. Uh, Jacob, thank you so much for
this chat. It's been a huge pleasure. Uh, thank you for your time connecting. And, uh,
I definitely hope that we get to connect in person at some point, uh, maybe for some fries
or something like that.