Welcome to the Dystopia. I just had my whole world
shaked. Just shook and ran underneath me. I'm still processing what I was just told.
You're also putting your money where your mouth is. You're planning to accept salary
in Bitcoin. It's rather interesting that the new mayor-elect here, Eric Adams, is...
So they're taking salary in Bitcoin in Miami, the mayor is, and now they've launched Miami
Coin.
First, we become friends, and we joke with each other and kid each other all the time.
And so maybe it's difficult for him to do it. It's very easy for me to do it. So I don't
know if there's a generational thing there or something that's going on.
He's an old mayor.
We use an app called Strike, and that allows us to convert it instantly. So it's like a
direct deposit feature. So it actually directly deposits the money into a digital wallet.
And so it's very easy for us to do. And I'm doing it with a variety of different cryptocurrencies
on my mayoral salary. And I think, you know, things like putting the Satoshi White Paper
on our website, we're the first city in the country to do that.
So he wants to make Miami competitive by going all in on crypto.
Paying our employees in Bitcoin. We've already paid multiple employees in Bitcoin, including
myself. Allowing our residents to pay for fees and taxes in Bitcoin. And then, of course,
the Miami coin, which now created a New York coin after the Miami coin.
The Miami coin. So you can get paid in Bitcoin. You can pay your taxes in Bitcoin and you
can buy and trade the Miami coin. How about this?
And then, of course, the Miami coin, which now created a New York coin after the Miami
coin, which has generated 30 million dollars in revenue in three months from the mining
revenue that gets put into our digital wallet.
30 million dollars in three months for the Miami coin. I want to know, would you buy
a coin for your city? Where the nearest city to you? Would you would you buy your local
coin?
Ours in revenue in three months from the mining revenue that gets put into our digital wallet.
We're staking that and we're going to give every one of our citizens a Bitcoin dividend
on a quarterly basis. So now they're going to have money in their pocket from innovation
of the city, but they're going to learn about Bitcoin as well.
They're going to give a Bitcoin dividend to the to Miami citizens. I'm having a hard time
even processing these words.
Mayor talk to me from a big picture perspective. A lot of critics would say, OK, the appeal
is cost of living. It's the good weather. It's low taxes. Right. But eventually with
the flock of people, you're going to need to get better housing, fix, get better schools,
fix the roads, fix the bridges. With that is going to eventually become higher taxes.
And it's just going to be this revolving circle. What is the case really that you can make
to stand out for the long term?
I'm laughing because I love when the sense begins to critics say, right, dot, dot, dot.
But for us, it's actually been a completely different story. We've reduced taxes to the
second lowest level since the 1960s. Obviously, we don't have a state income tax and our budget
has doubled in size. So the people who think that you have to raise taxes to increase the
size of your budget are completely wrong. The more you increase taxes, the more people
are going to flee, which is what we're seeing in some of these high tax states. And then
you're going to lose revenue, which is going to create a budget hole. It becomes sort of
a vicious cycle. So for us, we've seen the exact opposite scenario by having more revenue
in our coffers by reducing taxes. Now we've been able to increase policing while many
cities across America have defunded their police. And guess what happened? They know
it's going to shock you. Crime went down in the city. So while the murder rate is going
up across America, it's actually decreasing in the city of Miami. So we're starting to
see these counter narratives. And so they're in there. They're using the Bitcoin to fund
certain city initiatives. They're giving a dividend. They have a Miami coin that's gone
to 30 million dollars in three months. There's a lot to process. There's a lot. Optimus Gray
says his met his nearest city would be St. Louis. So not going to do it for him. A Seattle
coin. I'd have to see outperforms. What would you base it on? The entire thing is completely
new to me. I wonder if I could find anything else about it. The greatest investment, the
greatest newest investment, Miami coin, you've got to be shitting me. Miami coin. All right.
Here's the coverage of the launch. Let's see what we have.
That Miami coin will set the city up for that lofty long term goal. The cryptocurrency was
born out of a project with a nonprofit called City Coins. According to its founders, anyone
can download the software, hop on a computer to mint those new coins. The miner keeps 70
percent of the profits and the rest goes straight to the city's wallet. And like OK, OK, all
right. So a miner keeps 70 percent of the profits. All right. This is that's the key
details here. 70 percent of the profits and the rest goes straight to the city's wallet.
And like other crypto currencies, Miami coin also trades on an exchange so people can invest
in it. This one hit an all time high of just around five cents. It is the first and so
far the only test case of this idea. But since August, the cryptocurrency has brought in
just over 10 million dollars for Miami. That's more than three times what officials say.
This is this, by the way, is as of I should mention, because this was a recorded theater
mode without make it display better for you guys. My cat, my capture device is dying,
so I can't play real time video for you. It's a slow, pathetic death to 10 million as of
October 5th, and now he's saying 30 million. Hmm. So you get to keep 70 percent. The rest
goes to the city to essentially pay for city services or however they're going to spend
it. Some cities will probably not spend it very well. But that allows them to back off
on paying taxes, theoretically, of course, they'd probably just do both. It's an interesting
idea. OK, I guess the more I hear about it, the less I'm hating it, but I'm still feeling
like it's some sort of weird, dystopian future. They forecast it. The city's mayor and a Bitcoin
believer, Francis Suarez, says at the current pace it could bring in as much as 60 million
dollars for Miami and eventually subsidize or even replace taxes. But he says Miami's
still holding the coins in escrow for a couple months. He says they're doing more due diligence
before Miami can start spending these coins. We're going to hold them for a while to make
sure that there are no issues related to the technology, and then we can work on a variety
of different ideas that we have to make our city better, including educational ideas,
including affordable housing and including a lot of issues that, you know, we obviously
as cities across America would love to have more resources to help solve. The project
comes with its share of challenges. There are price fluctuations, regulatory questions
at the federal level and even money laundering concerns, to name a few. City coins are the
latest sign of growing competition to attract the fast growing digital industry and digital
asset industries. Suarez has billed Miami as the crypto capital of the country, but
Austin, Texas, and Cheyenne, Wyoming are among those also competing to attract crypto companies.
Sources tell me Austin and New York are on the shortlist for their own city coin. Well,
you're going to see a lot of different implementations possibly, and one of them inevitably, or many
of them will have corruption. And then you will have a currency that the city is creating
or an asset being created by the state or the local city that is involved with money
laundering and fraud. And these coins, what they'll do is they'll be pumped up in value
initially. This is going to be a thing. This is going to be bad for Bitcoin because these
coins will initially take off like rockets, like the Miami coin is and others. Miami coin
will probably be the strongest because there is a first mover's advantage here. Oh boy.
And then what's going to happen is all the other cities are going to start getting, well,
a lot of other cities will start getting involved, states and cities, it's going to be a mess.
And you're going to see this happen. As they go up in value, the city officials, the people
running, the managing their part of it will use that inflated temporary price to buy Bitcoin.
They're going to turn it around and convert that into Bitcoin and they'll buy Bitcoin
when their price is at a premium. And then when they start doing that and they start
selling and they start buying the Bitcoin to do it, they have to sell to buy the Bitcoin,
that's going to start to crash the price. So the cities will cash out and they'll move
this into Bitcoin, the price will drop and it'll artificially inflate the price of Bitcoin
while they do it. Then as the value of all these currencies tumbles, after a while they'll
all start to tumble. Then the very price that propped up Bitcoin will start to crumble and
it'll affect the price of Bitcoin as well. It's going to be a mess. And we do not have
a federal government that is capable of properly managing this because there are elements of
this I could get on board with. If my local county had a coin, I know this sounds crazy,
but I would, I would, if, if I could do something that would help raise revenue for my local
county and I could also maybe make a little money, that does seem like there's something
to that idea. Um, but I'm pretty skeptical of the implementation. And I suppose if I
lived in downtown Seattle and if they raised revenue via cryptocurrency to help with the
homeless population or something, that would be something that I think a lot of my citizens
would be compelled by. So that, that shared goal would add value. It would, that would
be value created by the Seattle coin. If, if the city of Seattle said, we're going to
use these funds to help build homeless camps and set up shelters for the homeless and feed
them, a lot of us would think that's a worthy cause. And I could see that adding intrinsic
value to something that would otherwise be valueless. If supporting your city is valuable
to you and you can achieve that through a cryptocurrency, I could see some people adopting
that and you could even see like local businesses that use the Seattle coin and they get a special
kickback, a special, special percentage from the city. I mean, you could see how far this
could go. I don't know if I think it's a good idea or not though. It feels like, it feels
like instead of having one true currency, we're going to have thousands and you'll have
some big cryptocurrencies that are essentially the primary stores of value that everybody's
going to move things in and out of. And you're going to have all these other cryptocurrencies
that are popping off and dying and popping off. It's going to be stocks times a hundred,
right? Because the volatility, the speed at which it moves and the global nature and the
24 seven aspect of it, right? Because who says a rich billionaire in Russia couldn't
go buy up a ton of Miami coin and start effing with the market. I bet you there's nothing
that says you have to be in Miami to own that coin, right? So you could start to see how
people could really manipulate this thing and how that would force some sort of federal
regulation. And then we get into a state versus federal rights thing. And that's also going
to be just a huge political mess. Political lines will be drawn and sides will be declared.
That's what I suspect will happen. Miami's kicking it off. Austin's next and New York's
on the list. So it's coming. Wonder how long until Portland or Seattle or San Francisco
around there. To make those new coins, the miner keeps
70 percent of the profits and the rest goes straight to the city's wallet. If you're just
joining us, we've been talking about Miami coin launching. It launched earlier this year.
Miami now has their own cryptocurrency that's around 30 million dollars. They're letting
citizens pay for taxes in Miami coin or Bitcoin. And some of the city staff, including the
mayor, are taking some or all of their paychecks in Bitcoin. Miami says that they can use some
of the funds raised to pay for things like police enforcement and other things that have
been defunded recently. So the question I've been asking the chat room is, would you buy
a local city coin? Now, Avath in here says that there's no such thing as fixing social
problems and using crypto at the same time. And I think he probably knows I kind of disagree
with that. My mindset is you have a technology which is amoral and then you have how people
use it. And this is a universal debate we have about all kinds of things, but it is
100 percent applicable to crypto currencies as well. You could look at Bitcoin as just
a volatile asset that can be a store of wealth and not a currency. And if I think if you
start looking at things like Ethereum or Miami coin or Bitcoin as an asset comparable to
gold and silver, but digital equivalents, you might start to see some of the shift like
the nice thing about Bitcoin for, say, people who are lower on the social tier or don't
have a lot of or no disposable income. You can Satoshi down these Bitcoins into teeny,
teeny, teeny, tiny amounts and you can buy tiny bits at a time. Ten dollars worth, twenty
five dollars worth. And you can stack that and stack that and stack that and stack that
over time. Now, Bitcoin just had a 20 percent value drop, right? But if you started getting
in at the beginning of the year, even with this 20 percent drop, Bitcoin has had one
hundred and sixty percent gain for the last year, even after the drop. And it's recovering
right now from the drop. But even at the bottom of the drop. Bitcoin had gained one hundred
and sixty percent in value from the beginning of the year. Now, if you've been stacking
like the beginning from the beginning of the year, that's pretty great. And I I just kind
of went through this. So I decided to just experiment with this about the beginning of
the year. And I started buying small amounts of Bitcoin every Friday, like twenty five
bucks here, maybe 50 bucks here, depending on what I could afford. And then by just dumb
luck, I decided right before the price crashed over the weekend to cash out some of that
Bitcoin for Christmas to buy Christmas gifts, because I think if you can convert that stuff
into physical goods like that, that's you know, it's not a good investment strategy,
but it's how I'm using it right now. I'd rather use that than credit. So I had put about almost
three hundred dollars worth of cash into Bitcoin since the beginning of the year, just buying
little bits at a time here and there. And I withdrew this weekend. Four hundred and
eighty dollars now after fees was four hundred and fifty dollars. But I put in almost three
hundred and I took out after fees four hundred and fifty dollars. And that's just been since
about April. And now I'm paying for Christmas with some of that stuff. I don't have another
way to build wealth. I can't buy real estate anymore. And even if I could buy real estate,
I don't have the personal bandwidth to maintain the real estate to even do the paperwork and
pay the taxes. I don't have the bandwidth for that. So and I don't have the I don't
have the money to and I don't really have anything to leverage for the loan. So I can't
do the real estate thing. I don't really understand the stock market well enough to feel like
I'm not going to screw myself. So I don't really do anything there. I don't have a company
retirement account because I'm an independent business person in a sole proprietorship.
So there's not a lot of tools. Plus, I've chosen a very minimal mobile lifestyle. So
I can't really like accumulate valuable things and store them in my RV. And I don't really
have any interest in paying for gold because to me, it's just a rock. It's a useful rock
that has a lot of good industrial applications. But there's a lot of it out there. And I don't
personally want to have a bunch of metals and rocks. I want to store my my wealth digitally.
And so Bitcoin is a is a form of mathematically provable property. That's what it is. It's
an asset that is mathematically proved and secured by a peer to peer network with a central
ledger that tracks who owns which coins and everyone can have a copy of that ledger.
How people use it? Well, I mean, we could talk about how the Biden family pays each
other off with diamonds, right? Or we could talk about how most drug sales are in cash
or how we give bags of cash to the Afghans. What are they using cash for? Who knows, right?
The cash cash is the ultimate crime. Currency. Caches. So we got to be realistic about that
by probably orders of magnitude more, right? So the technology does not necessarily equal
the use of it. And there is an opportunity for people that are lower on the social economical
ladder to actually build wealth if these things don't blow up in their face. But just like
playing in the stock market can blow up in your face times five that so can crypto currencies.
But there absolutely is a place for people lower on the wealth ladder. Now, when you
start taking it to things like city coins, like Miami coin. And then you times that to
an Austin coin. I mean, like, maybe I just I don't know, would you like say you say you
knew you were going to move to Austin in two years? Do you start by an Austin coin? It
just it starts to it does start to become a casino. And people's concerns about that
about the fraud and Ponzi scheme nature of it are legitimate because those aspects of
it are concerning. But they don't necessarily mean the technology is bad and there isn't
some fundamental use.
You know, my buddy Joe has been taking to calling cryptocurrency like our modern dot
com bubble. And I think that might be a good way to think about it. If you were buying
stocks back in 2000, and we had the dot com bubble, 95% of those stocks went bust. They
just blew up in your face and people went broke. But 5% of those stocks are Amazon,
Apple, Microsoft, Rackspace, all the companies that were involved in building the cloud era,
from hardware to software to services. Like they were around back then too. And some of
those paid off handsomely. But a lot of them didn't. That's where we're at with this whole
crypto idea. Like there's some fundamentals there like with the blockchain. Being able
being able to send money peer to peer with no middleman to anyone in the world a universal
currency that somebody in Russia and somebody in China and somebody in India and somebody
in Canada and somebody in Mexico like all over the world. They all have a common currency
they can work with. That's clearly fucking needed. Like that's just obvious, right? That's
just like, in the age of the internet, especially like you look at my kids, man, they're growing
up online. Especially these COVID years. You think they're you think they're going to find
value in physical crap that you got to move around or or like paperwork you got to deal
with now they want something they could buy on their iPhone in 15 minutes. And you know,
that often gets thrown around despairingly. But you know what the technology should actually
enable that that's not it's not an unrealistic expectation in 2021 and on. So we also have
to think about this from a younger generation who values things like avatar skins in roblox.
It's a huge market right now is these digital goods in app purchases, these tokens. And
they're I mean, that's how app stores make money now. And if they value that stuff, that
stuff is literally never going to gain in value. It's never going to do anything but
buy more crap in a game for them. Our crypto currencies really that much more of a leap.
Don't they actually make more sense because they're cryptographically verifiable. You
can trade them with anybody. They have value amongst a many areas of things and utility.
Cryptocurrency is the conversion of energy into wealth into a store value and it's very
expensive right now. But that's an area where people are going to invest a lot to is making
it greener and greener. And as people do that, that hype cycle is going to keep going. I
mean, we we are entering like this.com bubble mutant that's probably going to go for a while
it's going to build and it's going to get outrageous. And then one day it's likely going
to give and there will be a few left standing. And I think so it's it's not a bad analogy
to say it's like the dot com bubble, but just a global 2021 dystopian version of it. All
right. Well, Coder's coming up here in just a minute. Mike's going to be joining me shortly
and we got a good show plan.
Hey,