Well, hello, everyone. This is Brunch with Brent. I am so pleased to be joined today
by Alan Pope. Popey, how are you doing today?
I'm doing very well. It's Friday, so end of the week, getting ready for the weekend.
Of course. We're lucky to be recording on a Friday here. It's seeming very quiet this
Friday, so it's a good day to be doing this kind of stuff. And of course, we are on completely
different time zones for you. You're in the UK, right?
Yeah, we're on the time zone. Everyone should be on, you know, UTC. Everyone should just
switch to UTC.
The standard. Everybody else is lesser. So for me, it's midday. For you, it's a little
bit later. But yeah, great to be connected with you. Could you give us a little bit of
introduction? Some people already know you. I know that. But can you introduce yourself
for some of those who might not?
Yeah, so I'm some guy on the internet who uses Ubuntu. And I used it enough that I got
hired by Canonical to start working on Ubuntu. So since 2011, I've had a number of roles
at Canonical. I'm, as I said, based in the UK. And I'm an enthusiastic fan of computers
in general and IBM ThinkPads specifically. I also like cats.
You're starting to get known for that, right?
Yeah, just a bit.
You were mentioning cats. I heard a cat in there somewhere.
I live with my wife and two children. And we've had cats ever since we moved in together.
And yeah, a bit of a fan of cats. Even just laying in bed at night, I'll browse the cats
subreddit. And there's also a subreddit that Joe introduced me to called Chonkers. And
it's like large cats. And so I'll just sit and browse our Chonkers and just tap my wife
on the shoulder and show her my phone and it will just be a big fat cat waddling down
the street or something.
Perfect bedtime content, right?
Exactly.
That's pretty funny. Yeah, I did notice that you have a cat emoji in your Twitter handle
currently.
I put emojis in my Twitter handle intentionally. And I try and insert emojis in fields on websites.
Not to break them, but in order to uncover bugs, because there are some websites that
still don't support emojis. And this all came about years ago when Fedora Linux had a code
name called Schrodinger's cat. And the name Schrodinger has an apostrophe and an accented
character in it and it broke the bug tracker and it broke a few tools around the release
of Fedora. And someone in the Ubuntu project rather confidently claimed that it wouldn't
happen here. And I thought, hmm, I bet it would. So I started changing my launchpad
name to have emoji characters in and sure enough, I broke stuff. Most recently Thunderbird
email client, if people get emails from me, they'll see a list of email and then mine
will be in the middle at like 72 point text for some reason. There's some bug in Thunderbird,
but it's great because they're scrolling through their email and then suddenly mine jumps out
at them. So it was successful finding bugs by just putting emoji all over the place.
So yeah, there was method behind that madness.
I suppose you're getting a lot of replies to your emails as well.
Well, more angry ones saying, Oh God, another email from Alan, especially people who are
subscribed to bug trackers. Like if you subscribe to the launchpad bug tracker, it's mostly
people who work for Canonical. So people who work on NumShell or back in the day Unity
and I would file a bug and so they would get bug mail and it would say from Alan Pope and
it would, my bugs would stand out a lot more than anyone else's because giant emoji penguin
took up half their screen.
That's one way to get things at the top of the priority.
Exactly, exactly. But it uncovers, there's two things there. There's, I've got attention
for the bug that I actually filed, but then there's also clearly a bug in their email
client that we have now discovered that that also needs to be raised and that's probably
going to be fixed more quickly because it annoys more people whenever I send them an
email. So yeah, double win.
Two bugs in one. That's great. But that shows just the importance as well of testing fringe
cases, right? And you've kind of taken it upon yourself to test a whole bunch of services.
Have you found any bugs in other services that you're not so related to on a daily basis?
So sometimes, yeah, like I get frustrated when you sign up for something and they don't
allow certain characters in email addresses or, you know, it's often, nerds will often
tag their emails with a plus sign and some characters or a dash and some characters in
order to, if the email address spreads and is used for sending unsolicited spam, you
can tell where it originated, right? And there are a lot of websites that don't accept those
tagged email addresses. They don't accept a plus sign as a valid character in an email
and I kind of rant at those companies. But it's unfortunate because they probably just
bought an off-the-shelf web package or they just didn't realize that a plus sign is something
people use in email addresses and they're probably not going to fix it. But it still
makes me a bit cross. Yeah, but I like breaking stuff. I like discovering, pushing the boundaries
of software and doing stupid stuff with software in order to identify bugs. I did one a little
while ago where I have a tendency to hold down keys on the keyboard to see if that breaks
anything because people don't do that. And there's a couple I've found by doing this.
If you hold down the mute button on a ThinkPad, there's a hardware mute button, you know,
the media keys. Some years ago, I discovered that if you just hold that down, it mutes
and then un-mutes, so auto-repeats. But after a while, it gets out of sync with the mute
indicator on your desktop. So you get to the point where you press the mute key and the
light comes on to say it's muted, but the thing goes off on the desktop to say you're
not muted. And so they're completely out of sync. So I filed a bug and one of the guys
on the desktop, I filed a bug saying, if you hold down the mute key, it gets out of sync
with the indicator. And the reply from someone on the desktop team was, why would you do
that? I'm like, doesn't matter. I did do it.
Well, you know, I was, because I have a ThinkPad in front of me here in X220 with that mute
button, I was tempted when you first started explaining it to give it a try. And then I
thought, I better not.
That's the other flip side is sometimes you find bugs that if you tell someone to do it,
you have to give them a warning beforehand. So there was a similar bug where if you hold
down the print screen key, when you press print screen, it flashes the screen either
black or white to like a photo being taken and makes a photo sound and takes a screenshot.
And it's, it does this kind of fade effect. And I discovered that the print screen key
on one release of Ubuntu auto repeats. And so if you hold down the print screen key,
it will rapidly fire off multiple screenshots and it will keep trying to flash the screen
repeatedly causing your machine to eventually lock up because it's trying to do this 3D
composited fade effect. And so I, I dropped by the Ubuntu desktop team channel and said,
Hey, I think I've discovered a bug. Hold down the print screen key. One of the guys, Will
Cook held down the print screen key and that, as far as he concerned, locked up his machine.
And I, and he didn't see the very next line that I typed, which was by the way, this will
lock up your machine fair warning. Yeah, a bit too late. So yeah, I like doing that kind
of thing.
I've learned recently that in software development and even like web development, those kinds
of things, that's actually a surprisingly important part is having someone on the team
or a few people or someone in the public who is intentionally trying to break things, you
know, trying to push the boundaries of what the defined use cases perhaps. Is there a
word for that kind of, I think it's fuzzy, fuzzy testing. Okay. I think you're fuzzing.
Some people call it fuzzing. It's just like doing stuff that's outside the boundaries
of a fixed set of tests. I'm not a QA person. I just, you know, pretend to be one really
well. And it's not uncommon for people to re do a software release and then ping me
and say, Hey, I've made this thing. And then within minutes I'll tell them I found a bug
like very quickly. I'll find a bug because I'll just do stupid things with the software.
Just like resize the window as small as possible or make the window as big as all of my displays
just to see what the dialogue does. And, and that exploratory testing, you can't really
automate. You need human beings to do stupid stuff because unfortunately human beings do
stupid stuff.
We're very good at that. Yeah. One of my pet peeves, and it happened to me two days ago,
I was trying to sign up for a conference and I had to create an account and this happens
all the time. You can probably relate, you've probably run into it, but I use a password
manager, which everyone should, if you're not currently like get out of the nineties,
I guess. Um, and so I use long passwords cause why not? They're all unique and stuff and
I don't have to remember them. So, um, so my pet peeve is that on some registration
pages, when you put in a long password, it auto truncates the password without really
showing you or telling you or giving you any sort of warning. What? Yeah, I've run into
this a few times. That's insane. I know. And so I put in the password and it doesn't complain
and you hit okay. And then it immediately, you know, it should send you like a confirmation
email so that you can, uh, you can say, yep, I actually did that, which you have a story
about that, uh, which we might get into. Um, but upon clicking yes on that registration
email and coming back to log in, the password doesn't work and it's because it gets truncated
to some, I don't know, it, it's not an arbitrary number, but it's some kind of defined number
in their system. And then, uh, and then you can't get in, you have to do, so I had to
do a password reset immediately the first time I tried to log in, which is a pretty
bad user experience. So I, whenever I run into that kind of stuff, I try to give someone
some information, but, uh, yeah, it's surprising that we're still dealing with that kind of
stuff.
Yeah. I, I get frustrated with the web forms that don't let you copy and paste. I know
my email address. I, you know, it's pretty short. I'm not going to mistype it. And if
I just double click it and paste it in the next line, I'm pretty confident everything's
going to be all right. But there are some websites where they use funky JavaScript to
disable paste, um, which is just ridiculous. I mean, I guess, I guess, you know, you have
to protect against the archetypal idiot user who, you know, is able to operate a microwave
oven and nothing more powerful than that. But it doesn't help when there are people
out there who actually can use these computer things quite well. And you just frustrate
those people. It must be difficult balancing act. I'm glad I don't maintain websites for
a living.
That's what I've realized is sometimes by implementing some of those strategies, you're
actually taking away from some strategies for really good security as well. So you're
leaving everybody kind of in the middle. Uh, so you're not allowing bad security, but you're
also not allowing very good security. You're just allowing like, like, like some websites
having a eight character password must. It's like, you can't go over. You can't go under
is like, well, really? Are we still with that? Eight past eight characters?
Yeah, the fact that there is a finite number of eight character passwords just makes this
just ludicrous.
Yeah, I feel like we should be past that by now. Um, you ran in recently into a situation
that we don't necessarily need to mention, uh, the business, but you ran into a situation
where they weren't, uh, doing verification emails either. And, uh, that gave you a bit
of trouble, right?
Yeah, I see a lot of that. There's a lot of companies that will, they're eager for you
to sign up for their service. And so just visiting their website and punching in your
email address basically signs you up. And it's pretty common for me to get signed up
for stuff where people have just put in an email address, maybe slightly wrong. Um, and
I get the email because I own a domain. I get all emails for that domain. And so people
will put in something at the domain.com. Um, and sometimes it's, uh, it can be seen as
malicious and sometimes it's just stupidity, but I get signed up for stuff and then immediately
get signed up for marketing emails or, you know, promotions for their other products.
And those are really hard to get off when it's not Mike, I bought a thing from you.
I am a customer. We have a relationship and I would like to hear about your new products.
Please sign me up for your newsletter. It's not even that it's randomly out of the blue.
I get signed up for a random thing that I've never heard of that I don't care about. I
don't want, I will never use. And Oh, here comes the newsletter as well. It's like, no,
just aggravating the situation. Yeah. I have a tendency to rant at people a little bit
when they do that kind of stuff because it's just, it's just rude. It's just not nice.
You got in contact with someone or at least you signaled to someone that that was happening.
Did you get a good end result with them connecting with you? I felt kind of bad. I always, I,
you know, I should do that count to 10, you know, look out the window, think about what
this is like from their perspective. And then I just think, no, screw it. They should not
have implemented this badly and they did, they should do better. And so I tweeted at
them and got nothing. And then I got a newsletter the next day. I was like, okay, this is enough.
So I tweeted at them again from another account and you know, rather aggressively said they're
doing it wrong. And I got a sincere apology and you know, by the way, we use your products.
I'm like, Oh God, why did you have to say that? I feel doubly guilty now, but you know,
but they shouldn't have done it. You know, pragmatically speaking, they screwed up. It
wasn't my fault that they signed me up for a thing I didn't ask for and then sign me
up for their newsletter that I didn't ask for more things you didn't ask for.
But I would consider that one of those bugs that you're talking about as well. It's like,
it's just another form of bug, right? You know, it's a bug in their strategy, I guess,
to get people on.
Yeah. And I think too many people are keen to get people signed up and it's a numbers
game. You know, once you get a certain number of thousands of people signed up, a percentage
of those will be converted into paying customers. And you know, you've got to aggressively market
at those people who are the 99.9% of non-paying customers to try and convert them and upsell
them some special offer without considering that some of those 99.9% of people don't actually
care and maybe they just signed up because they want to see what your product is.
And you know, over the years I've signed up for products just to see what it is and see
what the product can do. And I can probably figure that out myself from playing with a
demo or reading their material on their website, which may be hidden behind a login screen.
And then five years later I get a marketing email from them. I think, where the hell is
this from? And I search my email and I find I signed up for them five years ago just to
look at the product. I was like, you don't have to do that. You know, I very clearly
am not an engaged participant in your community. I'm very, very obviously not a customer. Don't
try and upsell to me by harvesting your entire email address portfolio of everyone who's
ever mentioned your product or looked at it or breathed near your website. Not every single
one of them can be converted into a customer.
Yeah, exactly. I wanted to bring up, you mentioned a long time ago Wimpy, because I was going
to think that the emojis in your Twitter handle were because of Wimpy's influence. I know
he has a tendency to use them a little bit everywhere. And I thought that was your way
of kind of supporting him in that. But I see now that there may be a different strategy
there.
But the other way around, I think I have unfortunately unleashed the beast on Martin of emoji because
yeah, I've been putting emoji in all over the places since, well, since whoever it was
on the Launchpad team erroneously thought that Launchpad was impervious to these kind
of problems. But I haven't been using them quite so much on social media. So I think
that's both of us. Because both Martin and I have access to a number of work social media
accounts, both on our desktop browser and on our mobile phones. So yeah, we can often
be out and about and have an idea for some social thing that we should do and post it.
And Martin is very clear in basing his social posts on data. So he has data that suggests
that if you put an image in a social post, it's going to perform better than just plain
text. And shorter social posts perform better than longer ones. And ones that have up to
three emojis perform better than the ones that have none. Now, they perform differently
with different demographics, obviously. But that's the basis, I think, for where Martin's
love of emoji comes from. And it's quite infectious. And so I've started using them as well quite
a lot in my social posts. I did one today because as we recall, this is Black Friday.
So I thought I'd do a social post about it being Black Friday and we have an Ubuntu exclusive
special offer to download the desktop for free on Black Friday. And to follow it up
with another tweet that was like note also available for free every other day of the
year.
I thought that was a great deal.
Yeah, totally. It's while stocks last, grab that ISO image. Yeah, it's all pretty stupid.
But it's just a bit of fun and a bit light hearted because sometimes the social media
posts can seem very sterile, corporate, boring. And so we try and lighten the mood a little
bit and make them a bit less dull. And we do that a little bit with emojis with some
animated gifs, maybe a video here and there or something like that.
Yeah, I think, you know, we have to remember that we are talking to other human beings
who have some necessity for comedy in their lives as well, right? Martin explained in
the brunch with Brent that we did together a few weeks ago, how exactly what you said
data was driving that decision, but also his desire to just make the communities feel a
little bit better, like to just bring some light heartedness to these otherwise, you
know, sometimes very technical discussions, like a release post or something like that.
And I thought that was really lovely.
It's funny, we, we did a post a little while ago, which were one of when one of the releases
came out, I think it was when 1904 came out, which is an interim non long term support
release. And I put a poll up that I thought was fun. And it said something like 1904 is
out, are you going to upgrade? And option one was LTS for life. Option two was, you
know, I've already upgraded. I can't remember what option three was. Oh, option three was
something like still running Ubuntu 7.10 or something like that. And the final one was
by the way, I use arch. And whenever you do a poll on the internet, obviously, by the
way, I use arch is the winner, of course, obviously. But we engaged with people replying
and suggesting this was a stupid idea for a poll from Ubuntu to talk about, you know,
a different Linux distro, which is a bit of fun. It's just, you know, it's Friday afternoon.
People need a little bit of amusement in their life. And someone took a screen grab of that
with the poll, posted it on Reddit, and was like, this isn't going well for them. As if
what, like we're gonna change from being Ubuntu to like, right, that's it, I'm gonna quit
and I'm switching to arch. As a result of this stupid poll I did on a Friday afternoon.
It was just a bit of fun. But the replies were great. And they were like, you know,
someone replied they're saying something like whoever's their social media manager is killing
it. And I'm like, well, thanks. It's funny, though, how something that's intended to just
be kind of light hearted can just get taken in so many directions. One of the things that
we've always tried to do in the Ubuntu project is not rain on any other project. You generally
won't find canonical employees and Ubuntu members dissing other projects. Like we won't
talk down another Linux distribution or talk down the people who make another Linux distribution,
because we're already 1% of the market. Like why? Why would we do that? Like my friend
Michael Hall says, if you blow out someone else's candle, it doesn't make your candle
any brighter. And so it doesn't make sense, even if we are competitors, and I use that
in inverted commas, if we're competitors with these other distros, it doesn't do us any
favors to knock them. And so since Ubuntu started, we've always strived to be positive
and always strived with a code of conduct to not knock other distros. Now, that doesn't
always work and sometimes people make mistakes and sometimes people are not completely positive
and I fall into that trap sometimes too. But it's something we strive for and I wish more
people did that. I think the Linux ecosystem would be a better place if we could each share
the good work that each other is doing non-maliciously. So when Fedora puts out a release from the
Ubuntu account, we'll congratulate them. When KDE put out a release, we congratulate them
because we have quite a wide social reach and it's a good thing for us to point people
at these projects because it doesn't do us any harm whatsoever to point at KDE or point
at Fedora or point at Elementary or Manjaro and highlight their success because highlighting
their success doesn't make us any worse.
I can only agree completely. I know Wimpy mentioned the same thing in the conversation
we had with his brunch and Rocco mentioned the same thing in his and I feel like it's
a theme that is just continuing to propagate and I hope it really takes off for all of
the people, you know, in the Reddit subs and all over social media and all of the places
where you tend to find this negativity or at least this kind of, I don't know if it's
a rivalry kind of nature, but it's, I agree with you completely. Like we're all on the
same team.
It's tribalism and validation. I installed this thing. If someone else says their thing
is better, then maybe I was wrong and I can't be wrong. So people feel it's not a lot different
than the rivalry between people who have one particular gaming device and people who have
a different manufacturer's gaming device and that. It's all cooked up by the users.
It's not cooked up by the manufacturers. There'll be a bit of tongue-in-cheek back and forth
between Microsoft and Sony about the Xbox and the PlayStation, but if you get Xbox developers
and PlayStation developers in the same room, they're going to talk to people like human
beings. They're not going to be at each other's throats, just the same as when I went to the
Linux application summit in Barcelona. There are people from Red Hat there. There's people
from Purism, people from Pine. You know, we're all grown adults and we can all have conversations
together. You don't have to turn everything into a cage fight.
And I think the reality is that we are all connected with a bunch of the software that
we're making, right? Lots of it is propagated in all of those distributions and a piece
that someone writes might help someone else and or change someone else's perspective.
So it's all really constructive. The way I've sort of come to see it, or at least challenged
myself to see it recently, is there's a big difference between being right and wrong and
just having preferences. And I think those two often get mixed up. You know, if a user
has a preference of a certain piece of software or a gaming platform or distribution, that's
very different than one being better than the other.
Right. And it's very, it's sometimes very difficult for people to separate those two.
And also in Ubuntu, we've sometimes made decisions where a small set of very vocal people will
say that's wrong. You shouldn't do that. That's wrong. I prefer it like this and everyone
prefers it like this. And it's like, well, you might be right in that you prefer it like
that. But it's very difficult in the Linux community to be able to speak for everyone,
because everyone has different tastes. And, you know, the fact that we moved the window
control buttons from one side to the other side, deeply angered a small amount of people
who were, you know, very vocal online. But it turns out most people are like, meh, they're
over there now. Okay. Don't care. Where's the button? Oh, it's there. And they click
it and they move on with their life because the window controls position on the screen
is not the most important thing in their life. It turns out, opening the web browser and
surfing Facebook or reading their email or placing a bet online or whatever it is.
Getting something done.
Yeah, getting stuff done is way more important than where the window controls are. And it's
difficult having those conversations with very passionate people in the Linux community
who feel like their perspective is the one true perspective.
It makes me wonder, characters like maybe some Apple CEOs that we've seen having such
a strong conviction that their ideas are the best ones. And sometimes that does push the
envelope faster or further.
Yeah. And, you know, I'm not trying to draw a parallel between an Apple CEO and the lead
sponsor of the Ubuntu project and CEO of Canonical, but Mark Shuttleworth does have like, executive
sign off on many things. There are many decisions that happen inside Ubuntu that are taken by
people at all levels. And Mark may not be involved in those conversations at all about
which version of which library is used or how a particular dialogue is designed and
so on. But broad brush, he will have decision making power over things. And so for example,
when we switched from GNOME 2 to Unity, that's largely a project driven by Mark, who was
running the design team at the time. And so he will have received some flack and the company
will have received some flack because of that decision. But he made that bold decision.
And as a result of making that decision, I'm very confident that we sold more machines
running Ubuntu using Unity than we ever did before that. And while some people don't like
it, you need someone to take the hit for that, someone to take the can for making that decision.
Now we may have introduced it too early. It might not have been ready. It might have been
slow performance when it first released. And I've spoken to Mark about this publicly in
interviews on the Ubuntu podcast. And he said, yep, we were too early with that. And there's
some other things we may have been too early with. But sometimes you just have to push
the envelope. And it needs someone like Mark to do that. Because the smaller distros where
everything is done by a common consensus will often not have the push, the drive to try
out those new things that, yeah, they might be controversial. They might annoy some people.
But someone's got to try this. Otherwise, we're all going to be looking at motif windows
and you know, GNOME 2 for the rest of our lives. Someone's got to push that stuff forward.
There's something about being so confident with your own perspective that it becomes
visionary and you can lead other people to sort of go in places that no one's ever been
before.
Doesn't mean we get it right all the time, though. Some people would say Ubuntu Phone
was a complete failure in inverted commas. And I've seen that written online that Ubuntu
Phone was a failure. And it's like, well, there were thousands of devices that shipped
with Ubuntu Phone. That's like a drop in the ocean. That's very few devices in the grand
scheme of things when you think of how many billions of Android devices there are out
there. And we eventually canned the project and handed the open source parts over to the
UBports guys and they've run with it and they've grown the community bigger than it ever was
under Canonical and have supported more devices and have moved the project forward. But someone
needed to actually have a go at doing that. And thankfully, Mark had the bags of money
to throw at it to have a go at it, really.
Well, and maybe it, you know, failure or success necessarily depends on what you're measuring.
And so if you're measuring progress instead of total sales, then that's maybe a totally
different picture. Or impact, you know, if you're trying to measure impact or innovation,
for instance, and those kind of things, then failure or success isn't necessarily obvious.
And it was also very difficult because the way it ended was with cutbacks within the
company. And so that was very painful for the people who worked on it. It's very different
from just drawing a line under it and saying, okay, we're not going to contribute to this
thing anymore. And we'll make it open source. And everyone who wants to work on it can work
on it. It was we're no longer going to work on this thing. And the staff that were working
on it now no longer work for us. And so it was an incredibly painful time for those of
us who worked at Canonical at the time to lose that project effectively, because some
of our friends left the company.
Yeah, that doesn't sound easy at all, right? When you when you put it that way. Maybe in
that sense, it's a shame that you lost some great people as personal relationships, right?
Right. But the flip side is, would the company still exist now? Two years later, if we hadn't
done that?
Those are the really hard decisions that some people in leadership positions have to make.
And us as simple users, we're lucky not to have to make those, right?
Right. And I don't have a time machine. So I can't tell in an alternate universe what
would have happened if we'd carried on working on it and throw more money at it. I don't
know. And I don't think anyone can know that we can guess, but it's hard to know.
Can we talk about the Ubuntu podcast for a little bit?
Sure.
I was fascinated by Wimpy's story about how he got involved there and how you both are
now sort of a tag team duo at conferences and things like that, which he said you would
laugh about. I wondered a little bit how you got started in podcasting, because you had
been doing it quite a bit earlier than Wimpy had, right? Can you walk us maybe through
that a little bit?
Yeah, so we started we're just coming to the end of our 12th season and we do one season
a year. So whatever that is, 2007, sometime around there. So around about 2006, I was
a community contributor to Ubuntu. And on the UK IRC channel, the Ubuntu UK IRC channel,
we'd often have conversations about maybe there should be an Ubuntu podcast, who would
do this. And at the time, I was a keen consumer of a number of podcasts. And I thought, yeah,
I think we could probably do this. I think we can generate enough content to put out
a show every other week or so, interview people, discuss what's going on in the project. And
I contacted a few friends who I'd known through my local Linux user group. And also through
the Ubuntu community in the UK and said, do you fancy doing this podcast thing? And we
each went out and bought some hardware, bought microphones, mic stands, got a mixer. And
everyone came over to my house and we recorded an episode and it took all day to record one
episode.
Oh no, how come?
Well, we just didn't know what the hell we were doing. And we made some mistakes, like
we recorded a segment and then we went and had a cup of tea and a biscuit and had a
think about what the next segment was going to be. And then we go back in the room and
sit there and record that segment. And we edited really heavily. Every um and er was
edited out and it took a long time to post process those early episodes. And also the
the fact that we were driving to each other's houses. So initially there was myself and
Tony and Laura and Davey and we live 50, 60 miles away from each other, which I know by
US scale is not a huge distance, but in the UK, nobody drives 50 miles to see a friend.
Especially not to record a podcast. Like, yeah. So it it was it was a bit difficult,
but we we once we got a few episodes under our belt and a UK VPS provider Bitfolk provided
us with some hosting for free. And we got it all set up. It kind of started working
and we would interview people who worked on Ubuntu and it we we started off very amateurish
and the audio quality was terrible and it took ages to get an episode out the door.
But I think we've after 12 years, we've streamlined it. Plus we we outsourced the editing to your
good selves, which is most welcome.
Yeah, those were kind of early days for podcasting really when you start to look at it. You know,
you mentioned 2007 and there weren't really that many podcasts at that time compared to
now, of course.
Yeah. I mean, I remember there was a bunch of podcasts I used to listen to. There was
the ones that Leo Laporte did, you know, Twit, that kind of stuff and the stuff I mean, the
ones he still does now. And there was Dig Nation. That was Kevin Rose talking about,
you know, whatever's popular on Dig at the time and a few others. And I used to commute
a lot and I used to listen to them on my commute. And after a while I thought, yeah, I can do
this. And there were a couple of Linux ones around at the time and they were pretty awful.
And to the point where I remember falling asleep on the train listening to one.
Oh, that's not a good sign.
No, this is like, I reckon we could do better than this. And I'm not saying we're great
at doing podcasts. I know we are amateurs. We are not particularly good microphone technique.
You know, we um and err and we have, there are things that I would love to improve about
the whole thing. But it's a bit of fun and there are some thousands of people who download
it every week. And if we talk about something controversial, we get a lot of feedback. And
there's a little community that's built up around it. Our little Telegram channel that
we have for the podcast has today hit a thousand people in there.
Whoa, that's not a small thing.
I don't think many of them are bots. I think they're mostly human. But that's, it's really
not, I mean, there's 100 or so people who are active at any time. And it's a nice little
community of people who, you know, give us feedback and let us know when we're doing
something wrong or send us news articles to talk about. And yeah, it's just a bit of fun
on a Tuesday night to sit with Martin and Mark and chat about stuff and then out it
goes on a Thursday. And it's not even part of either of our jobs, but we're not paid
to do it. We're not sponsored. You know, we don't get paid by any sponsors. It's just
a bit of fun and we've been doing it for 12 years, which is kind of surprising really.
I think the human aspect, similar to what you were saying about like tweets and stuff
earlier, the having that human aspect is super important, especially when it comes to sharing,
you know, a little bit of technical information. I think you guys have an amazing balance there.
And I know it's really entertaining as well to listen to and you get some great perspectives
with with your crew. So please keep doing it. I know you're probably gonna have a curry
this this coming up.
We have a break every year. It's it's funny when we when we did the first season, we did
one. The first season was from about March till December, and we all decided we wanted
to take a break over Christmas. And we weren't sure whether we were going to come back the
following year. And now it's become this meme that at the end of the year, we go away and
know will they won't they and obviously there's 100% track record so far that we have come
back, but there's no guarantee that we will. You know, Mark has just had a baby and Martin
now has more responsibility on his plate for work. So we never know if we're going to come
back for another season. We might, we might not. And it's a stupid game we play with the
audience where we say, well, we just don't know. But we don't. And we and we never know
until we do the curry because we stopped recording in December. And we actually don't talk about
the podcast. The three of us don't talk about the podcast at all for at least a month the
whole of January. We never talk about it. And then we talk about going for a curry.
Do you feel like that is almost like a necessary break that's really helpful actually to gain
like new perspectives and ideas?
Yes, it's a way to take a breather, have a think about what worked in the last season,
what didn't work. And whether if we come back, whether we want to do something differently,
we'll differently move the day because when a year passes, you know, when you've got children
like I have, my son has changed which day he practices football on. And if he practiced
on a Tuesday, which is when we record, that would mess up my ability to do the podcast.
And my daughter does dancing and sometimes she has to dance on a Tuesday. So I'm rushing
around in order to fit in the podcast because we always do it at the same time on the same
day. And one thing we learned very early on is if you want to build an audience, you have
to do the episodes regularly. And if you want to get the episode out on time, you have to
record it on time. And we sometimes fail and we sometimes postpone, but more often than
not, if you pinged me online at 8.30 in the evening on a Tuesday, you wouldn't get a reply
from me for a couple of hours because that's the time that we always do the recording.
Yeah, there's something about consistency of schedule, especially when you have a bunch
of people involved, right? That's so necessary. I'm starting to learn that. I'm working with
the JB team. I've been a sort of freelance photographer being able to do whatever I want
to all the time. But some of that consistency actually is super powerful. So you did mention,
you wanted to mention something before our chat. You were talking about, well, I think
this ties into a bunch of stuff. So lots of people know you for the Ubuntu podcast. Also,
I suppose user error. You guys do some really hilarious stuff there. So I would encourage
everyone to check it out if they haven't yet. And you mentioned earlier in our chat, some
ThinkPad stuff that you might be starting to get famous with that.
So this internet famous thing, you know, where you're known by a tiny subset of people on
the internet for something, you're notable for something. And I have been recognized
in public for being on the podcast. Now I'm not, you know, any of our comments famous.
I'm no Kim Kardashian, obviously, but it's quite nice.
You're like niche famous, right?
Well, yeah, like Zed list internet celebrity famous. And it's quite nice, but it's also
quite weird when people recognize you. And I've kind of got used to it, but I haven't.
It still weirds me out a little bit because it's an audio podcast. Nobody knows what I
look like unless they happen to be following me on Twitter and see my avatar or something.
But I had it years ago. I think 2001 was the first time I ever experienced it. I was working
for a drugs company in the UK and I had a really rubbish website, my blog, popy.com.
If you look at the internet archive for popy.com, don't do this, but I'm sure you will. Go back
and look around about 2001. It was, it was proper 2001 era web log, right? With stupid
icons and stuff all over it. It was awful. Actually it's a bit of the precursor to emoji.
I had little icons in between the texts to indicate stuff. And these were icons I ripped
out of the SAP system that I was working on at the time. So yeah, that's the precursor
to emoji, I think.
It sounds visionary.
Yes, totally. But they were, the place I was working were interviewing someone to join
the team. And I wasn't part of the interview process because I was just a contractor. And
they came back from the interview and we were asking, you know, how's this new person that
you're interviewing? What are they like? And one of them apparently asked how big the team
is. And the boss said, well, we've got like five or six people. We've got this person,
that person, we've got Alan Pope. And apparently the person they were interviewing said, you've
got Alan Pope. And she went, yeah. And the guy went, the Alan Pope. And she went, yeah.
And from that point onwards, I was known inside that company as the Alan Pope. Everyone just
calls me the Alan Pope from that point. Just some nerd online who happens to have a website.
But I met them later when they did get hired and they came and introduced themselves. And
I said, oh, I'm Alan. And I shook their hand and they went, Alan, have you got pictures
of cats on your website? And I said, yes, yes, I have. And that was like, brilliant.
I'm recognized for, you know, the Alan Pope and having pictures of cats on my website.
So I've kind of got used to that being recognized, but I've always been recognized for stupid
reasons.
Your website has been updated since then, which is kind of nice. And I just want to
point it out. I think it's it's such a wonderfully simple and yet really cheeky website. So I'll
encourage everybody to go check it out. Popeye.com.
Popeye.com. Yeah, there's not a lot there.
No, I know. But that's the brilliance of it. And what is there is hilarious. And yet also
quite astute. So I like it. I like it a lot. Aside from Popeye.com. I wanted to ask you,
are there any non computer projects that you tend to get excited about? I know a lot of
people know you for your ThinkPad tinkering and all of that stuff. But is there anything
these days that's like really grabbing you that's not necessarily tech related?
I will often make a note somewhere of a thing that should exist I wish existed but doesn't.
And some of those will be games. And I've had a ton of ideas for games. And I have a
friend who I bounce ideas off of. I'll put him on Telegram and say, Hey, I've had this
idea. And I will describe the game or describe the application and and we'll both agree that
that should exist. And sometimes it's a bit of a con and I try and get them to help me
make it or get them to make it. Just get them to make and sometimes that works and they'll
say yeah, I could probably not cut up in Python in no time at all. And they'll just send me
a link to a Git repo a few hours later. And I'm like, Oh, brilliant. That's great. Thank
you very much. And I feel super bad about this because I feel like I should be creating
those things myself. But I get these mental blocks when I try and create stuff and I get
very frustrated. I've often said I don't consider myself a developer. I'm not a programmer.
And I can create a shell script and I've done coding on computers for 30 years. I've written
Z80 assembler 6502, I've even written 8086 assembler and I've written in Pascal and various
other languages. But I find it really difficult to get past that block. And I don't know how
to fix that. So my problem is in answer to your question, yes, I have a ton of projects
outside the stuff that I do on a daily basis, but none of them are finished. And I get so
frustrated because I don't know how to move them forward. And I because I get frustrated
that I can't move them forward. I get more frustrated that they don't move forward and
then I give up on them.
Oh, it's Yeah, recursive. Could I send a challenge your way? Oh, my gosh. Go on then. Could you
take a few of those ideas and just put them out into the world? For instance, like send
them out on Twitter and in a hope that someone else picks them up? Because some of the ideas
sound not necessarily like huge or, or massive business opportunities or anything like that,
but just something you wish existed. So I wonder what might happen if you just kind
of send it out into the world and see what happens.
I know I have inspired a couple of things in the past, I have said to people in the
past, you know, what should exist, this thing should exist. And then suddenly it exists.
And that's great. I feel guilty because I didn't make the thing. I just had the idea
for the thing. And I kind of would like to put those ideas out there. But I worry a bit
that I'm just the ideas man. And the biggest one is Ubuntu Matei, right? That is now many,
many thousands of people who run Ubuntu Matei. And that came about because of a stupid idea
that I had that there should be a Matei spin of Ubuntu. Martin comes around my house picks
it up walks away with it. And now I basically don't contribute to Ubuntu Matei at all since
day one. He's done it all. And I just had the idea. I mean, that's a good example, because
somebody else picked it all up and every so often he'll ping me and say, what do you think
about this idea from Ubuntu Matei? And I go, yeah, great idea. And somebody else somewhere
on the planet does the work. And all I did was just, you know, agree that that sounds
like a good idea. And maybe there'll be more of those.
Perhaps your real gift and contribution is just creating the seeds and then you hand
off those seeds to others who are more interested in maintaining the seeds. You know, that has
huge value for sure.
Well, it doesn't, it doesn't. Because, like, whenever you open a bug tracker, for an open
source application, you'll get a load of people giving you ideas on how you could improve
your thing. And I worry that I become yet another one of those. Like, I'm just throwing
my ideas out into the big pool of ideas on the planet. And, yeah, some of them might
turn out to be, I don't know. I'm also very resistant to people telling me they're terrible
ideas. Which is why I run them past my friend Stuart on Telegram before I even think about
them any further.
But yeah, okay. I think over Christmas, I will try and turn these into documents which
could be shared more widely than just between me and my friend Stuart.
That sounds lovely. And it doesn't have to be all of them, it could just be a few. That
sounds like a fun little project. See what happens, you never know.
I wanted to ask you if there's anything that you would like the community to try? Like,
sort of an ask? Something you'd like them to try or go check out or think about?
So a thing that I've been, we touched on earlier, is the whole testing thing. I wish more people
could push the boundaries of testing stuff out. And not specifically Ubuntu, like any
Linux distribution. Go and find one you've not tried before and test it out. Find out
what their process is for filing bugs and issues and follow that process. And give them
feedback about what works and what doesn't work. Because I know often developers will
create things and, you know, it works for them, but they don't appreciate that people
out there have different size screens or different accessibility requirements. You know, maybe
people with impaired vision or impaired motor skills aren't able to use that software because
of the way it's constructed. And I think it would be great if we did more of that testing
in the community because it's such a low impact thing for normal non-developer people to do.
And I've shown this in videos I've done on my YouTube channel. You know, chucking an
ISO image onto a USB key, booting it on a machine, and then just noodling around for
an hour and trying it out as if you were using it on a daily basis is a really easy thing
to do. Just dedicating an hour or so to noodle around with it and then dedicate another half
hour to an hour to filing any bugs you find and continuing to converse with the developer.
Continuing that conversation and making sure they understand what's broken or what's not
working or what's glitchy. I think that's the thing I would really love to see more
is people contributing meaningfully to Linux distributions rather than seeing Linux distributions
as a one-way street because the Linux distributions rely totally on volunteer contributors to
help them out. So that would be my call to action is go and test a distro and I don't
care which distro it is.
That's lovely. I would imagine too as a user having that bi-directional communication would
actually be a real treat. You know you get some insights on where the project is headed
or can you know I imagine once you do that for a while you can request some features
or maybe share some ideas that would really make you have a sense of ownership for this
product that you really love or are learning to love.
I think that's a key thing is feeling a sense of ownership, feeling a member of their community.
It's very easy to do drive-by bug reports, boot an ISO in a VM, throw a bug report over
the wall at a developer and then walk away and never look at that distro ever again.
I think it's more useful for people to find a home, find a distro they like, get involved
with the community, actually jump on their IRC channel or their Slack or their Mattermost
or wherever it is they chat and ask you know what can I do and they will almost certainly
ask you well what can you do? What are your skills? And if you say oh I can I can test
your distro they'll almost certainly be happy to point you to well we've just landed this
new thing do you want to test it?
I even saw a distro whose Slack I'm sat in a couple of days ago posted secret ISO images
and said hey can people test this stuff out and so I did but I'm not even part of that
distro I'm not even part of their community I just happen to be lurking in their Slack
and I thought yeah I'll help them out I'll try out their ISO if it crashes in a thousand
colors or formats my hard drive without me asking then I'll tell them but if it all works
I'll let them know it worked well and it's an hour of my life that is not hard to contribute
to so like I say I work for Ubuntu but I appreciate that everyone has their own personal taste
and everyone wants to contribute in different ways to different distros so go and find a
distro and contribute.
As little as an hour is helpful and if you can give more than that even more helpful.
Yeah totally.
And so for someone like me who's not necessarily a developer do you feel like that process
is quite approachable?
It depends on the distro I mean largely all you're doing is downloading an ISO image and
chucking it on a USB key and booting it and seeing what happens.
Almost any of us could do that right so that's great.
Yeah and that's this I mean if you've if you're a Linux user you probably have done that at
least once in your life.
If not it's a great opportunity to learn.
Right yeah why not and also it's nice to test other distros like I've tested out quite a
lot of distros over the last year partly because I need to make sure that some of our technology
works on other distros but partly just out of interest and I've tried out some that I've
got really wild user interfaces that I would not be happy using on a daily basis but other
people love like it's their you know number one child and so I can have a perspective
of an outsider just looking in and saying okay this is a bit weird but it doesn't crash
it works and so that's feedback I can give them you know I don't I don't have to tell
them I don't like it and I think that's a key thing is doesn't matter if you don't like
it you've go and find one you do like use that one and contribute to that one and yeah
it's it's really pretty straightforward it's it's it's really just a case of installing
an operating system and trying to use it like a normal person and you very quickly can find
the edges of what's possible and find you know whether it's easy or difficult to install
the software that you want and whether it's easy or difficult to customize the interface
to be the way you want it maybe that's by design maybe that's just you don't know how
to do it or maybe it's just not well documented and all of those are opportunities and trying
to put emojis in places where you might not think they should go oh yes yes definitely
try try and put your username being one character and try and you know weird characters in your
password and all kinds of stuff probably if people want to get connected with you where
where do you think you would send them I'm pretty much poppy everywhere except a few
places where some random people have got poppy so I had to go with poppy DC as the alternative
so if you ever see poppy DC that's probably me as well so people always ask what the DC
means the DC just means dot com as in poppy dot com I was not very inventive when I came
up with that one because at the time I was really frustrated that I couldn't have poppy
so I was like oh poppy DC will do so yeah twitter.com poppy is a good place to start
great yeah well poppy thank you so much for chatting with me this has been a real pleasure
and thanks for your time too appreciate it yeah it's been lovely thanks thanks so much