So we have a very special guest coming on the show this afternoon.
And he is the developer behind Merger FS.
But joining me in studio today is the host of Choose Linux, Drew.
Hello, hello.
And I also have the one and the only Brent.
Well, hello.
And the reason we have these two folks is Brent has never used Merger FS before.
He is a curious mind.
He is looking to build the ultimate photo backup storage solution.
Is that right?
I don't know about ultimate, but I need something that really works for me.
Yeah, that pile of external hard drives.
Don't tell them too much about that.
Oh, my goodness.
I was watching a video with Linus Tech Tips and the guy behind, what was it?
Smarter Every Day.
And Linus went to this guy's house and he lives in Alabama near the, near
the like rocket city, what's it called?
Just outside of Atlanta anyway.
And this guy had huge plastic totes.
I'm talking, he had over a hundred terabytes worth of external hard drives, all
neatly labeled.
And this guy went to a spreadsheet and looked at, right.
I want to reference this project.
I want to look for Apollo landings.
I need to go to hard drive Q37.
So you go to box Q, get out hard drive 37 and copy that folder to his.
Was he a librarian before he started doing this?
I have no idea.
Did he use the Dewey Decimal System?
It's a heck of a system when we have projects like Merger FS in the world.
So, Drew, what's your, what's your background with Merger FS?
I've been using it since I found your blog post talking about Merger FS and
it's joys and I've been loving it.
I run it on a Ubuntu 18.04 server with a bunch of Docker containers and
Linux containers you mean?
Well, yeah.
I mean, okay.
So yes, they are kind of like, they're like, they're like,
containers running under Docker.
I call them Docker containers all the time as well.
I'm just as guilty.
Well, I'm using it with Docker.
If it were Podman, then they'd be OCI containers.
Correct.
So the funny thing is before the show, actually, we were just talking and I
showed Drew my blog post from 2016 and he went, I've read this before.
Yes.
Before we, long before we met, cause we first met at LinuxFest Northwest this
year in April.
That's right.
And, uh, it's just funny how the internet is so, it's such a small community
that you never know who you're going to run into.
Yeah, it's a little world.
But yeah, it's, uh, that got me up and running with, uh, MergerFS and SnapRate
on top for Parity and I am a big, big fan.
So I'm really excited to talk to Antonio here.
And what do you do with it?
Is it mainly media files?
It's media, Nextcloud, mail, uh, you know, I got a little bit of everything going
on.
It's a big, big server with lots of RAM and lots of storage.
And so you're not running databases off this thing then?
Um, well, there's a Nextcloud database.
Does that count?
Maybe not.
Yeah, maybe not.
I mean, nothing, nothing high power.
For your container app data, how do you handle that?
Do you have a separate mount point?
Yeah, so I found that MergerFS wasn't very good with databases, so I ended up
moving all of my databases and what I call control for my containers over to an
SSD and then it's just data, just dumb, dumb data living on the MergerFS pool.
And it does a great job.
Write once, read many.
That's where it excels.
Exactly.
Large, static, often unchanging data sets.
And so we've heard from Drew and Brent, uh, I'd like to pull in Antonio at this
point, who is the main developer, I think the only developer of MergerFS actually
looking through the GitHub.
He has 69,000 lines of code to his name and the rest of the world has about 70.
So Antonio, it's great to hear from you.
Thank you for having me.
Well, thanks for being on the show.
So first of all, I wanted to, uh, ask you, what is MergerFS in your own words?
It's a, uh, union file system.
I don't know.
Uh, I ha I think my, uh, tagline on, uh, on GitHub right now is a
featureful, uh, union file system.
It's just a simple way of, of taking a union of all the directories and files
that you may have on a, uh, across a number of file systems or even the same
file system, but from different, uh, paths.
So it's more or less just a proxy with some smarts for routing where the, uh, the
specific functions of a file system, uh, get, uh, dispatched to.
So it's, it's really just, uh, like any other proxy, uh, mostly, I mean, there's
some additional features that are relevant for, uh, the file system space.
But if you think of a web proxy or anything else, it's
largely doing the same thing.
And, uh, the purpose is just to simplify that, that workflow, that, that behavior.
There's many use cases for unionizing, uh, existing file systems.
And, uh, there are many different implementations and I created MergerFS
due to a, I think, uh, a technical limitation that existed in, in the
different popular, uh, implementations that were out there at the time.
Yeah, I use it a lot.
And, um, the way I would explain it is it allows you to take just a bunch of
drives and make them appear as if they're an array of devices, if you like.
So you could have five, 10, 20, uh, different hard drives, each with an
individually readable file system on it and present that under a single mount
point for your applications to use.
Is there a limitation out of interest on the number of devices that
we can put together under Merger?
Not a specific one.
Um, 65,536, I guess, right?
Not even that it'd be the amount of RAM that you probably have.
Uh, I think you're going to run out of, uh, connections before you run out of,
uh, like physical connections to mount drives before you run out of, uh, the
ability to, to merge them together.
Uh, I had a question about, um, you mentioned there was a feature that was
missing, uh, in most of the popular, um, system alternatives that you were
looking at previously.
Um, can you, can you mention that specific feature that kind of made you dive in?
Well, I think the biggest, this might not be a feature per se, but support
was a big one, um, MHTDFS, which I think a lot of people, uh, used to use and
I find, uh, a number of people still use, um, the author had abandoned it quite
some time ago.
That was one of the primary reasons I started looking into this space.
And, um, when I did, I recognized quickly that there was a lot of, uh, security
issues with the software and, um, lack of configurability.
So I think one of the biggest features for MergerFS versus MHTDFS is the ability
to choose what I call a policy, um, in the, the way in which it figures out which
drive or which branch to work on within the union.
So this is a really interesting feature of MergerFS that I absolutely love.
And this is the create policies.
So how, how would you explain it to the layman, right?
Cause the, the, the first, uh, and the default setting is existing path, most
free space.
So, I mean, how would you explain that to the layman?
Uh, so most free space should be somewhat obvious.
You know, each drive has X number of bytes.
And if we look at the more simple version of that, those, that policy is just most
free space at the time a create request comes in, it simply looks at all the drives
at that time, takes a snapshot of those values of how many bytes are free and just
picks the one with the most.
Uh, it's a very simple algorithm.
Most of the algorithms are quite simple and it's a snapshot in time, unless it's
being cached, there's some caveats there, but, um, the existing path part in
retrospect, I actually regret making that the default because it leads to a lot of
confusion, but the intent was, uh, so existing path, there's a behavior in
mergerFS called path preservation.
So imagine you have four drives and you want, uh, media of some sort on one, say
movies, uh, TV shows on the second drive, and you have a lot of eBooks and you want
them on the other two drives and, uh, the path preservation would allow you to sort
of manually go in, create the paths, uh, in each of those drives that you wish to
have that particular data on. So you might make a movies directory on the first one
and the TV directory on the second one and, and books on the third and fourth.
And so the path preservation will filter out in effect, the drives when it's making
decision based on the path, the relative path of that file.
So it's kind of, basically it does a, uh, a, uh, der name.
If you were thinking of it from like a command shell, uh, perspective and looks
for that path across all the devices.
And if it finds it, it is included in the kind of secondary filter, which is most
free space.
Um, and there's other filters too that happen at that time, but so it's kind of
creating sub pools based on the directory hierarchy.
Could you see this as almost like a hybrid approach in a way that it's
kind of, you know, the defined folders that you've preset on those specific
drives are sort of, um, chosen ahead of time are sort of the legacy way of
storing data as we typically see it.
Uh, and then everything else that you pull on those drives is just sort of, um,
dealt with through the algorithms.
Would that be a way of seeing it?
Yeah.
I mean, most people, you know, grow out their collection or of devices, their
storage devices, pretty organically.
Unless you're a business or whatever.
And, uh, you tend to kind of just put a, this drive's going to have X and this
drive's going to have Y and that drive's going to have said, and then you have to
remember which drive is where, which one contains which data sounds familiar.
Right.
This data manages that, or this behavior, I should say, manages that for you.
Um, it does require a little overhead.
It does require you to either seed those paths, um, or to, at some point, you know,
in the future to manage them, if a drive becomes more full or not.
Um, and, and that's why I was saying that there tends to be confusion because as
default, if you follow through step-by-step of, if you have a pool of, of a number of
drives and they're all empty, then the first time you create a directory, it's
going to end up on one of those drives with the defaults.
And so a lot of people get caught up and they're like, Oh, I just copied over a huge
amount of data to my pool and it's all going to one drive.
And that's because the very first maker happens on one drive and they all had the
same amount of space free effectively.
And then that one, that one path is then used for, you know, all the sub directories
are associated with that path.
So it's something I can't really change now, uh, because it's the default, but, uh, if
there's a merger FS three, I might change that.
If you were to change it, what would be your preferred default now?
Just, uh, most free space.
I think the, the average person using merger FS is that's what they're expecting.
Uh, some people would prefer a percentage wise or least free space or whatnot, but
I think, um, most free space is kind of the, the common expectation.
I think that's wise.
Uh, I'm, I'm a merger FS user myself, and I was, uh, a little taken aback when I
first discovered that it was not using least free space or, uh, most free space,
excuse me, and ended up, you know, switching to that and then balancing the
drives, uh, which leads me to another question.
Is there a particular reason that you decided to keep the merger FS tools
separate instead of including them in the base package?
Mostly the release cadence, um, and the language.
So merger FS is C plus plus and the tools they're written in Python three.
And the reason there is just, they're doing very simple things.
It's, it's kind of easier to get off the ground.
And I wanted the tools to be more easily manipulated by third parties,
cause it really started as examples of how to accomplish certain things out
of band so that they didn't have to be in merger FS.
The concern I have is that, you know, I'm the file system or merger
FS is your file system, or at least a proxy for your, your data.
And if I ever screw something up in merger FS, I can screw up your data.
Uh, worst case, I could corrupt it silently, uh, best case, you know,
maybe it crashes or it, uh, you know, deletes a file, hopefully that's.
You know, in a, in an obvious way or whatever, but there's a lot of subtlety
there and granted merger FS is way, way, way more simplistic than most file
systems, but fuse, uh, historically has not always been the most stable.
So I was kind of bounded by the stability of lib fuse and the kernel.
And for any of those who've followed a fuse or merger FS over the years,
they've seen that there's a number of issues that are outside of my control.
And, uh, so with that in mind, I've tried very hard to limit what I put
into the main product so that if there are any issues, these things can be
managed out of band, um, or, or, or at least like even if merger FS isn't there.
Cause one of the nice things, one of the appealing aspects of merger
FS that a lot of users, uh, say is why they like it is, is that you can always
take it out and you can always remove it.
And there's no merger FS isn't really a file system.
I mean, technically it is, but in terms of the traditional sense where it's
controlling the blocks on the device, it's not doing that.
It's just a proxy and as a result, you can always remove it and all your data
is going to be totally accessible.
Um, and that has other side effects.
Meaning if you have a drive that dies, you only lose that one drive, your stuff,
full access in real time to all your other data.
Um, but making everything the separate repo, separate apps, uh, it allow it,
it's, it's in that vein so that, uh, if you want a balance tool and I didn't
write the balance tool the way you want, it's Python.
There's a lot of people that know Python, uh, go at it.
So you touched on the balance tool just then.
Um, which of the other tools do you think that people need to know
about that they perhaps don't?
The dupe tool can be useful.
Uh, so it, uh, it allows you to point at a directory or a file and give like
a number of copies that you want and it will find the drives with the most
free space and make, uh, uses rsync under the covers because I'd rather, rather
than trying to create all that very solid logic of copying files, uh, safely.
I just leverage rsync, but, um, Python is orchestrating that and it will go and.
Uh, find a drive, make end copies, and, uh, it'll just kind of recursively go
through the path that you have instructed it to that's quite useful if you're
if, uh, I know the drive pool has the ability to replicate across, uh, a number
of drives mergerFS doesn't, and in some ways that's purposeful, but, uh, this kind
of allows you on a schedule to do something similar, uh, there's the FSCK
tool, which I don't think I've updated in quite some time, but, uh, a lot of issues
with mergerFS come down to permissions and that tool can help suss out some
of those permission issues.
For instance, if you have two relative paths on two different drives that have
different, um, permissions or, uh, owners, then it can help you find that.
I ran into that issue the other day, actually.
So I now know how to fix it.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Uh, one of my coworkers, uh, has for long has, uh, for a long time, uh,
complain that I allow there to be inconsistencies on the underlying drives,
but the, the problem is with it being a file system, you really don't have a good
API or mechanism for reporting that you found these inconsistencies.
And while I could in effect, just when I notice it, report it in some log
somewhere, uh, why add that to the main product and complicate the code when
it's just as simple as right, uh, to, to write something in Python that just
doesn't audit once in a while.
Uh, usually the only time you need that is when you're mucking around underneath,
uh, merger FS or you're adding in preexisting drives.
So it tends not to be something you need that often, but I think it
was the full first tool I wrote.
I guess the other question there is, could the file system just be doing
that since it has, you know, maybe that's a job it should be doing as well.
So merger FS really needs to be running as root.
And certainly I could go and change permissions, um, or change, uh, owners
or whatnot and try to make them consistent, but what's the heuristic, right?
So if you have four drives and three of them say it's owned by nobody and, and,
uh, the fourth one says it's owned by root, w what do you choose?
Do you choose the one based on the policy for stat?
Do you do it based on a different policy for a different function?
It's not really clear and to try to make it configurable adds like a whole
another level of configuration to the product that would almost
never be used by most people.
I wanted to touch on the fact that you say that it's safe to run as root.
And I was just wondering, um, if we could, if we could talk about
the security of it a little bit, I'd like to know a little bit more about
what safeguards you have in place for that.
Sure.
I mean, there's a section in the docs, which I try to recommend everyone
look at the merger FS docs.
Uh, I have a long career in software development and documentation tends
to be very crappy for most products.
And I spend a lot of time working on docs.
So when in doubt, first check the documents.
From a, from a user to the developer, I'd just like to say a huge thank you.
It makes such a difference when someone puts this much effort into the docs.
So yes, please, if you're listening and haven't read them and are
interested, go take a look.
And these are some of the best written docs I've seen in any
project in a long, long time.
They are really fantastic and robust.
So yes, thank you.
Thank you.
Uh, that said, um, I am biased.
It is my software and I've been using it for a long time and I've, I'm very
intimate with systems level development.
So if there's anything that is unclear for some, uh, Linux newbie, which that
tends to be the, uh, the, the issue, um, feel free to contact me.
There's all the co all my contacts are also in the documents.
So I'm happy to try to reword anything to make it more clear, but, uh,
back to the original question.
So there is a section in there where I go over this relative to M8, uh, MHC
DFS, so MHC DFS could be run as root.
And in fact, generally expected you to run it as root.
If you were, if, if you were only ever running stuff as one user ID, then you
probably wouldn't ever notice if you didn't run it as root, but in the code,
there are very explicitly, um, assumptions that it has the ability to
shown or chmod any random file.
And the way it worked was let's say it creates a file and it's
was, let's say it creates a file.
It would create the file as root and then change the owner to whatever
it was supposed to be based because the way fuse works, you get an instruction
or command from the kernel and a part of the payload is to say, uh, this is
the PID it came from, and this is the user ID and the group ID and some other
metadata.
And so, you know, who has made this request on the other side from the client
app and, uh, MHDFS would simply shown or chmod the file after creating it as root.
Now, from a security perspective, that's not actually a bad idea.
However, that leads to non-posix standard behavior, because if you're root,
uh, you cannot, uh, well in traditional file system APIs, you couldn't, you
couldn't really replicate the permission checking that would happen at, in the
same way that would happen by the current via the kernel.
So your root, you can, uh, ignoring capabilities and such, you can basically
open any file and in certain circumstances, it would allow you to, so
you would be able to do things through MHDFS running as root that you
shouldn't be able to do.
Uh, the proper behavior, uh, is to change before you're do any of these, uh,
commands to change to that user, to that effective user or effectively change
that user user, I should say, and, uh, that's what merger FS does.
So anytime a request comes in where the user ID is relevant, because not all, um,
there's a overhead to changing user IDs.
And so I don't do it if it's unnecessary for like a read and a write, um, the
kernel doesn't actually check the permissions.
So if you chmod or chown a file while you're reading and writing it, um, it's
that's irrelevant to, to, uh, the situation.
And so I don't actually change in those for those commands, but anything else
like a stat or create, mkdir, et cetera, you, it, the only solution that I
use secure way to do that is to become that user and then to, uh, take that
action just like you would normally.
And so that's, that's the biggest security change, um, relative to the,
uh, MHDFS and some others, similar file systems out there.
It's in effect, the same thing that, uh, Samba does.
And I use the same tricks that they do.
So in Linux, or I should say POSIX in general, uh, says that every thread within
a process needs to be the same user ID, but Linux doesn't work the same way as
traditional Unix.
And it uses for those who are familiar, the clone system call, which is a much
more flexible version of fork basically.
And every thread it can have its own, uh, user ID and its own credentials.
And so I abuse that, uh, by calling directly into the kernel so that as a
multi-threaded application, merger FS can simulate being multiple users at once.
And this is a behavior that, uh, Samba also uses.
That's super interesting.
Uh, I always wondered why there was so many processes showing up in top or
something, and now I know why.
The number of threads are configurable now.
Um, that was something that I, when I vendored the libfuse library, I, uh, made
that more configurable because you do lose some throughput when you increase the
number of threads, because there's more contention on the pipe going into the
kernel, but, uh, generally, yeah, that's, that's why you, you by default will get
one thread per core and then the, there's a primary thread.
Um, let's shift gears a little bit.
What, uh, what considerations do people need to make in terms of CPU?
Because traditionally one of the limitations in fuse has been it's high,
quote unquote, high CPU usage.
What sort of CPUs are people going to need to, to sustain a
gigabit transfer, for example?
That's hard to say.
Um, for those who don't know fuse is a serial protocol that, uh,
that the kernel exposes to user space.
And it allows an app, a user land application to serially communicate
over, uh, a device dev fuse.
And every time, uh, say your client app is, uh, LS every time it's making some
system call that's, that's a file system API, it's got to go into the kernel when
the syscall say an open is, is called, there's the open from the app gets
translated, there's a wrapper for the C library, then that calls a system call
into the kernel and with fuse, it's got to see, Oh, okay.
You're talking to a fuse file system.
So I have to look up who's on the under other end of this file system,
transfer that through this, uh, character device.
And that's kind of where this overhead comes from.
So you have to go into kernel space, into user space from user space back at well,
as a proxy, I'm going back into kernel.
Like, so merger merger FS is going back into the kernel to ask the question like,
okay, I need to start this file, whatever the original app was asking.
So that's another round back into the kernel, then back into user space and then
back into the kernel and then back to the original app.
So it's, it, there's a lot of latency there because it's serial.
It's, uh, copying this data back and forth into the kernel and that there's
a lot of overhead to that and it's CPU intensive, not in the traditional way.
So it's, it's more IO intensive.
And because it's a user land app, you're seeing the CPU utilization.
So if you're using ZFS or butter FS or similar, those can take a lot of compute
as well, but because they don't represent themselves in user space in quite the
same way, uh, you don't see the CPU grinding away doing block deduplication
or in ZFS or, or the raid behavior or whatnot.
Um, and so in some ways, I think fuse gets a bad rap because of that, because
you're seeing the actual compute that it needs that said there is this extra
latency introduced because there's these extra hops going in and out of the
kernel and the speed at which you can do that, um, Is it doesn't seem
dependent entirely on the CPU.
So I have had people use raspberry PI twos and no problem whatsoever.
Fully, you know, uh, getting full throughput as they would expect either
from the Nick or the drives they have connected and minimal CPU utilization.
And I've had people on Xeons say that their CPU utilization is through the
roof and I haven't been able to figure out why that is, uh, I've had similar
systems, same kernel, same OS, uh, different drives and HBAs or controllers
for the drives and had different behavior between the two.
And I'm still trying to figure out why that is.
I don't know if it's a driver issue.
I don't know if it's a drive issue.
Um, if it's a, there's a bunch of other crap going on on the machine that's not
being accounted for issue, uh, it's hard to say.
And, uh, what I really need to do is there's all these variables and arguments
that I allow to be modified in merger FS that I would like to hide from the user.
But the reason that they're there is because I've found that different
people get different performance, um, based on those different options.
And what I really need to do is stop being lazy and build a, uh, like a
benchmarking tool that just kind of goes through all the different permutations
of those arguments and then runs, you know, very simple DD kind of benchmark
and tries to find the best, um, the best permutation of values.
You heard it here first folks, measure of first three is going to have a built
in tool for testing performance.
Nice.
Um, so I had another question for you.
Uh, how long has measure of first been around and what was your, your
motivation really to create it?
I know you touched on that at the beginning with the, uh, the lacking
features in other products, but, uh, just curious, really sure how long it's been
around, um, we'd have to check it hub.
It's been longer than I, than I'd probably say.
Um, cause if, for instance, this other tool I have BBF that I've been working
on recently, which is a tool that is kind of bad blocks, plugs and
blocks plus, uh, HD parm, um, plus some extra features, uh, that tool I thought
I wrote like a year ago and it turned out I wrote it three years ago.
So, um, my memory is not so good.
Yeah.
Time flies.
It really does.
But the, uh, I guess a little backstory is that I've always been a, uh, media
collector.
So in the eighties and nineties, I had all the CDs and all the movies.
And once it became, uh, financially viable to store digital media, um, in
bulk, I started doing so, and I had a iRiver H, uh, three 40 with all my
AUG level six encoded or AUG Vorbis, um, level six encoded, um, music.
And I had to immediately when I bought it, I bought an upgraded hard drive
on the, you know, third, third party and took it apart and upgraded the hard
drive to like 60 gigs, I think it was, um, just because I had a bunch of music
and I wanted all my music in one spot.
And, uh, as my music collection grew and hard drive prices declined, I
started ripping my DVDs and, uh, I never liked the idea of transcoding it to
some other format, especially because even if you're not someone who's ripping
and then selling, which I don't, I just have tons, tons and tons of, uh, um,
CD holders, DVD holders up in the closet, but just re ripping stuff as a pain.
And so I ended up slowly building this hard drive collection.
And it became, as soon as I got to a point where one hard drive couldn't
hold the full collection of certain types of media, it got really annoying.
And that's when I started looking for a solution, which led me to MHDFS.
And cause that was so simple to do.
And I, you know, I wasn't gonna spend the money for a raid set up or whatever.
I think we both use MHDFS for a while.
Cause before I use mergerFS, uh, I used MHDFS and AUFS and Unraid for a bit too.
And I even tried FreeNAS, uh, and then your tool literally came out of nowhere.
I've just found the first commit was March, 2014.
Yeah.
And I, I had a coworker who was also using MHDFS and, you know, it was a data hoarder.
And, oh yeah, I love that subreddit.
Do you?
Oh, I'm on there and you'll find me, uh, anytime there's a, I have a, uh, if
then, then that, uh, search for mergerFS.
So people apparently know that anytime something comes up, I
come in and snipe a response.
You do.
I've noticed that every time I post something, there you are, like a bad smell.
So what does your home server look like?
How many terabytes are we talking?
I have, um, so, uh, I do have a Wiki page on the mergerFS GitHub, uh,
account or whatever repo, and I invite people to go there and add their own home
setup, um, mine's on there.
So I have currently, uh, so I just redid my system.
So I actually don't have that fancy of a setup, um, though I do have a lot of
storage, so I used to just have a four port, uh, eSATA, AS media based multiple,
um, can, uh, eSATA controller card.
And then I had four IC dock port multiplier, four port, uh, enclosures.
They fit well in my entertainment center.
You know, I don't need a lot of throughput.
It worked.
Uh, but when it doesn't work, it really doesn't work because unfortunately port
multipliers, uh, don't handle failing drives particularly well.
And so just about a month ago, I decided I was fed up and I bought a old, uh, uh,
LSI 90 201, uh, four port 16 or 16 port, um, uh, HPA, and I bought two generic, uh,
eight bay, three and a half inch drive enclosures.
I assume you flashed that LSI thing to it mode.
Yes, yes.
And, uh, these enclosures I linked to them on the Wiki page.
I'd never come across them before.
They're basically the, if you've ever seen an eight port SANS digital, it's
that enclosure, but without anything, without a backplane or anything.
Um, and so it's pretty bare bones, but at $70 shipped, it's pretty good.
Nice if you're just kind of putting your own thing together and you don't have
rack space, which I don't, I'm in a Manhattan apartment, uh, downtown.
So I bought two of those and I bought four, um, For, uh, mini SAS to four port
SEDA connector cables and just fish the wires through and hooked it all up.
And, uh, that's what I'm on now.
It works.
It's way more stable.
So I have, uh, let's see, I have 12, eight terabyte drives.
I have a few thrown in there that were like dying drives, like a one, a two, one
and a half, something like that, that I'm using as guinea pigs for my, uh, hard
drive tool.
And then I have a, uh, the audio isn't bad.
Um, or, you know, how loud the drives are, aren't that bad.
They're all sitting in the car.
You know, how loud the drives are, aren't that bad, they're all sitting in my
living room.
Um, and I I'm in Manhattan.
There's a lot of outside noise, so kind of all drones together.
It's not the biggest of deals, but in terms of heat and the noise, especially
from the fans gets annoying at times, um, I have updated the fans, so they're,
they're less awful, but in any case, I've kind of started moving to two and a half
inch, five terabyte drives.
The, um, Seagate, oh, I forget what the serial numbers are, but
in any case, they're the only five terabyte, two and a half drives out there.
They're reasonably priced per terabyte and I've started using those.
So I have, uh, three of those now.
And so my total capacity is around a hundred terabytes.
And unfortunately it's almost full.
So that's really impressive.
Do you have any kind of parity on there?
Uh, I don't.
So I used to use snap raid, but I kind of, I was using crash plan.
So if you look in the trap exit, get hub, um, account, you'll find a repo.
That's just, uh, examples on how to set up different environments, different
storage environments and how to use different tools for maintenance and
formatting and et cetera.
And you'll notice that there's numerous mentions to crash plan, which I still
technically have a crash plan plan, but I haven't been using it much lately.
Uh, and for those who don't know, they were kind of the last, maybe
kind of still are besides, um, well, I guess the only cross-platform fully,
um, unlimited backup service, like true backup service, not a cloud, um, kind
of data source like G drive or Dropbox.
And so a lot of, I know a lot of data hoarders, including myself use that for
years, but the company I don't think is doing that great or whatever.
So that was kind of my backup plan because it, once I successfully backed
up all my data, that was fine, right?
Cause I have, I also have another tool called scorch, which is used to find bit
rot.
So if I ever lost a file or drive, if I ever found bit rot, I could just
restore it from crash plan.
And because it was true backup in the same way that maybe time machine or
snapshots and in ZFS or butter FSR, then it really wasn't a big deal.
I really didn't need, um, parody, um, or any sort of, uh, backup like snap rate.
Uh, when that started giving me a problem, mostly because they store all their data
when they're scanning your drive in memory.
And so you need a ton of Ram to, uh, scan.
And the more data you have, the more Ram you need and it just doesn't scale well.
Uh, I did move to, uh, to snap rate for a while, but I realized that if I had a
different backup service, then I could get rid of that again and get that storage
back, which at the time I really needed similar to now, I guess.
And so I kind of got off of snap rate at that point when I found a better backup
service, which is I use G-suite now and our clone and that works quite well for me.
Very well.
Yes.
I use that myself as well.
Um, so you got, you mentioned snapshots just then, um, is there any technical
reason why snapshots couldn't ever make it into merger FS one day?
Is that something you might consider adding at some point?
It would have to be based on top of existing technologies.
Like the underlying file system would have to support it in some way, uh, because
there's just too much going on there for me to replicate.
I do have a number of optimizations that I really don't talk about because you
wouldn't notice, but if you've ever used the CP, the GNU CP tool, right?
Like CP, you're copying a file around.
If you look in the man page, there's the ref link argument.
And so certain file systems like ZFS, butter FS, and new versions of XFS have
this ref link thing.
So this copy on right, the ability to say that this file and this file use the same
blocks.
And so if you're going to copy a 10 terabyte file, it can happen in, in a, you
know, in a second because it's really just making references to preexisting data,
which is how snapshots work.
And so in merger FS, when it is needing to copy a file from one location to another,
and there's a few situations where that may occur, uh, it'll try to use those
optimized, um, behaviors.
And if they fail, it falls back to just traditional, you know, read from one file,
copy and write to the other file.
And so I could in effect extend on that.
And if certain commands were made to, uh, merger FS, I could forward them
appropriately to the underlying file system, but because merger FS is really
just a proxy and I'm not messing with the data itself, there isn't a real way for
me without in effect rewriting the whole product to offer snapshots.
Yeah, that makes a lot of sense.
You mentioned very briefly earlier how, um, if merger FS is removed from the
system, uh, then the drives are still, the data is still available on the drives.
Um, that is one thing that has kept me from exploring various options.
I'm, I'm looking to build my own sort of storage system, uh, in my place.
And I've been sort of looking at a bunch of tools, but haven't jumped in.
Although Alex has convinced me that merger FS is probably the way to go.
It is.
Um, and so you can stop looking.
One big question that I have is, and which I have applied to all of my systems, uh,
in various ways is that I want to be able to understand the data if something goes
wrong.
So can you give me sort of a run through of what the data might look like if
something goes wrong?
Exactly as you would expect if it was a single drive.
Well, I guess, uh, to dive into that a little bit, like I know the, let's say I
write a file, it gets sent to the, um, free most drive.
And so if I'm looking at several drives, um, that have a similar folder, for
instance, uh, right.
So, uh, I mean, in, in that case, what you're going to have is a federation of
that data across those drives, um, but at a file level, right?
So you're not going to be, let's say you've got an album and, uh, you've got
most free space enabled, um, that album, you know, say of three drives and
there's 10, 10 songs and they all happen to be around the same size, you might
end up with three files, three files and four files, uh, across those three
drives, uh, that's really not predictable at any one time.
I mean, obviously at the specific time of creation, it's predictable.
That's how merger FS is working.
Um, though there is a random option, uh, policy, but, uh, you're not going to
know ahead of time, obviously where that data exists.
However, it will be in the same relative path.
You'll be able to very easily see that this specific data, I mean, you'll know
that that data is missing, but you're not going to be missing like half a file.
You'll be missing maybe half an album, but, uh, you'll know every, every drive
will have the same, largely the same layout.
They'll all have the same directories or at least, uh, the directories that
matter to be on multiple drives.
You'll see this, the same relative layout, but so defined like a specific
file, we would then use find or locate or whatever search tool against the drive
Mount paths rather than the merger FS pool, correct?
Right.
And, uh, and my tool scorch, uh, to plug that a little bit, I actually use
that, uh, for this kind of use case.
I need to enhance the tool to make it so right now it hashes everything.
I want to make the hashing algorithm configurable, and that includes no hash.
So that would make the tool more of an indexing tool, but when you're merging
together all these different drives and you lose a random drive, it's incredibly.
Frustrating to not know what data you're missing.
Like it's convenient that I still have my other drives live.
Um, and I'm missing only this one drive, but then you have to go through
the process of fixing that situation.
And I started writing scorch in part because of that, where I wanted
to know very simply, I wanted to have a database in effect that I can say, okay,
show me every file in this system that I'm missing, uh, since my last, uh, you
know, update of the database.
And if you pointed that to the mounts rather than say the union, then you could
find exactly what files you are missing.
Now I'm going to probably release these random scripts that I have, um, where it
kind of creates an audit of every drive that's in my pool every day and then
creates a diff and so, and I use like a log rotate to keep those for 90 days or
something.
So if I miss a drive or accidentally delete something or, um, you know,
whatever, I can just kind of unzip the file, check, do a quick grep and find
where the file was at any particular time in the past 90 days.
Um, and then that combined with scorch, which gives, I use to index all the data
in my main union, uh, mount point.
I can very easily find the data that I need to help me reconstruct the situation.
I need to start using this scorch tool.
It sounds wonderful, but just to expand a little bit on what's just been
said, um, the, the key thing that merger FS lets you do, and to be honest, it's
the same with, um, unraid and many of these other kinds of union file systems
is you still have a, an individually readable file system on each disc and how
that differs from traditional raid or, uh, ZFS or something is that rather than
the data being striped, uh, across multiple drives.
So if you lose disc five, you better hope that the stuff that was on disc five is
striped somewhere on disc one through four, whereas with merger FS, like, um,
Antonio said, it writes entire files to a disc rather than partial files or
anything like that.
Um, and so if you pull any of these drives from underneath merger FS and stick it in
another Linux system, you'll be able to read that ext four or that XFS or that
ZFS drive, but you know, that, that for me is the real win of these kinds of
systems rather than striping dates or it's individually readable on each drive.
So, yeah.
And there are certainly, I am in, and I try to make this very clear in the FAQ
section for merger FS, uh, that this is not a substitute for certain
workflows and workloads.
Um, you know, raid has its place, uh, granted with very large hard drives,
raid is becoming precarious, but that aside, um, merger FS is really meant for
the casual user who has numerous random drives and they just want to have some
kind of single view into their data or prosumer who knows the risk or is using
some other tool like snap raid or has full backups or whatever, and is willing
to take these trans, uh, these trade-offs between, okay, I can lose one drive and
the rest of my system will continue to work just fine.
And I don't have to worry about, you know, okay.
If two drives go, oh, that sucks.
I'm going to have to restore a bunch of data, or maybe I've used a path
preservation policy.
So I put all the data that I really don't care about on these two drives.
So if they die, you know, so what?
And I back up the other number of five drives, whereas on raid, you may, if you
lose two drives, you know, all your data is gone.
So it's, it's really just about offering another tool.
And I try to be very clear about where merger FS falls flat and where it is,
uh, more beneficial than some of these other technologies.
And because it's so much more simplistic to use, um, you know, certain people try
to make raid systems like, you know, uh, free NAS and un-raid, they try to make
things extremely simple.
I don't think it's safe for un-raid.
I don't think it's the cost that is a barrier to people.
I think it's, you know, it's closed source or it's just scarier, you know,
there's just a lot more knobs to tweak.
I mean, granted, there's a lot of knobs to tweak and merger FS, but out of
the box, it just kind of works.
And, um, yeah.
So most people, I think understand that trade-off and, uh, it, for a lot of us,
it's worth it.
Yeah.
But un-raid, uh, has a GUI and merger FS doesn't, so it must be better.
Uh, you know, I'm trying to fix that.
Uh, the problem is I'm, I'm very much a low level developer and web development
makes me want to rip my eyes out and, uh, uh, no offense to the web people, but.
The web people, the web people.
I love it.
The web people.
Um, anyway, uh, so I, uh, I've looked into doing it myself and, uh, that's
probably just not going to happen.
I ideally in the same way that I try and make merger FS as simple as possible.
I know the guys over at, uh, open media vault, they have, you know, their front
end and they have a merger FS exclusively as their union file system
option, which thank you for them.
Uh, but you know, it, their UI is very simplistic and obviously you have to have
the whole package and not everyone wants to use open media vault.
Um, what I would like to be able to do is have a simple binary or.
You know, script that someone can download that it's its own web server
that you run as root, um, or give proper permissions to access the merger FS,
um, control runtime API that would allow you to kind of just start up a web
browser, go to, um, whatever machines IP address that you've launched it on and
just kind of drag and drop drives that you have, you know, it'll query my, the
way I imagine is with query all your drives, look at the ones that are probably
your boot drive, separate them out from your data drives, and then give you click
boxes or dropdowns for all the different options and for merger FS.
And then maybe I think it would be nice after if I could get that done to add
maybe some snap raid stuff since that's a very common tool to use with merger FS
and anything else in that space.
But, um, I do have a number of web, uh, developer friends, but none of
who are in this space.
So I've been meaning to go on like data hoarder and, and home lab or any of those
subreddits and just throw out a, um, requests to see if anyone's interested.
I wanted to say thank you very much for joining us.
It's been a pleasure speaking with you and, uh, from the community as well.
I know that many, many people are very grateful for all the work you've
done on this, on this amazing tool.
Um, do you have any way you'd like to send people to follow you like Twitter
maybe, or plug your GitHub?
Yeah, just, uh, you can find me.
I mean, trap exit is, uh, so that username comes from Erlang.
I was a big Erlang or am a big Erlang fan and, uh, kind of, uh, use that as my handle.
It's you'll almost always find any, any service.
If you look up trap exit, it's probably me.
There's a few that aren't, but that's pretty rare.
If you just go to github.com slash trap exit, you'll find all my stuff.
And, uh, I work on all these tools regularly.
You can find me on Reddit or email, whatever, like contact me
any way you will, you wish.
I have a discord as well for those who want to chat about stuff.
Um, yeah, I'm very open.
Feel free to contact me.
Contact me any which way.
Well, thank you very much.
Thank you for having me.