Well, hello, everyone. Welcome to Brunch with Brent. I'm Brent Gervais and joining me today,
I'm very excited, is Philip Muller. Philip, how are you doing?
I'm fine. How are you?
I'm doing really good. Thanks for joining me. Many will know you from your involvement with
Manjaro. For those who haven't heard of Manjaro, could you give us a one to two sentence introduction
to it?
Well, Manjaro is a Linux distribution or an OS where you can have a free operating system
with a lot of desktops. So we have the standard Xfce, KDE, and GNOME, and many more in our
community like Deepin, E3, MATE, and so on.
Sounds like you have all of them.
Mostly, yes, yeah.
Which is no small feat either. It feels like, you know, those are some of the community
additions you were mentioning there. And it sounds like there is this really large community
around Manjaro that is kind of coming together and making a lot of it happen. I would imagine
for you that feels exciting.
Yes, it is exciting because a lot of people are there and we created a tool so everybody
can use it and create their own Manjaro edition. So all the official versions are just examples
and the examples are so good that we got some momentum there and everybody is liking them
and try to put out their own version of Manjaro and we don't hinder them to do that.
That's kind of the open source spirit, right? Here are the tools we used and do with them
what you will. But it sounds like that is kind of exciting for the community as well
because there's whichever desktop you would like to use is definitely available as one
example.
Yeah, we have a lot of varieties and some niche stuff like only window managers and
people put even their own new creation on our platform cause it's easy to create the
base system and then put their own operating system or desktop environment on it. The latest
what we have is the Jade desktop, just another desktop by Vitor and he is our homepage creator
and he said, hey, when I use HTML and web designs, then I create an own version of Manjaro
and use only JavaScript and stuff like that. And boom, we have a new, and I think the last
version, which is the first alpha version I did just yesterday, loaded up and he posted
me back a YouTube video about the newest version of Manjaro and he laughed at me and asked
why I, well, he used the old version three years ago from back then and didn't review
the new one. So I missed it a little bit.
That's funny. And so if someone wanted to go see that, for instance, where could they
go check that out?
Well, they can go to our download page and to the OSDN servers and it's in the community
folder and it's called Jade.
Perfect.
It's the desktop, but we have it named as WebDat cause Jade is trademarked, so we cannot
use Jade. So for that reason.
Got it. Yeah. The joys of trademarks. I did skip over sort of how important you are to
the Manjaro project. As far as I understand, you co-founded it with a few others back in,
oh, I don't know, like something like eight or so years ago. Was it in 2012, 2011?
It was 2011. It was, yes. It was kind of funny cause I was back then in a different project
that was called the Chakra project, which was emerged out of the Kadimod project, which
was again an addition of just the KDE packages in split version cause back then Arch Linux
didn't had, so it's like the KDE in one package and more or whatever applications there are,
they always were packed in this huge tarballs and you had always this issue with getting
only one application and we said KD mod would be that modification and we created split
packages and it was always the Kadimod game chasing Arch cause whenever they updated library,
we had to repack our packages.
Oh my goodness. And that's quite a bit of work for seemingly nothing, right? Like that
was sort of the motivation then?
To create the Chakra project cause we said, okay, we can back then take the package bills
and create our own base system. Only the package is what we need. So we did a semi-rolling
version like a solid base system and put only then our Kadimod packages on our top and it
worked I think three years and then the project itself split it up. So one of the female developers
created the Chaos project, it was Anke and I was a little bit not with the team anymore
and looked for something else and then there was Roland Singer and he has this nice installer
for Arch called Manjaro and I said, hey, let's meet up cause I like to see what you guys
are up to cause I had a project and it's similar and maybe we find something better to do a
thing which might be last longer as just installer. And it was really funny cause he lived two
towns away. So I went in my car, drove over to him and had a cup of coffee with him and
talked about it and he said, yes, let's do it. And so it started and yeah, there we are.
I think most open source projects don't necessarily start over a cup of coffee. So that actually
sounds like a really nice way to go about it. And quite clearly, you both seem to have
gotten along and it was just the two of you who kind of were there in the beginning or
was there a bit of a community surrounding you as well?
No, we had also one who was doing the artists and the theming, creating wallpapers and stuff.
And we had a French teacher who was doing the package manager. So we were four people
starting it up and I said, okay, let's do it properly. Get one year dark, really dark.
Nobody know what we're doing. And we established all the base systems. And then out of that,
we emerged and said, here is the new version of Manjaro, which is not arch. It's not based
on arch. It is just using the packages, but we have our own servers and yeah, it's something
new and you can install it easily.
And how does it feel like Manjaro has sort of evolved for you from that beginning year,
for instance, and where it is now?
In the beginning, we only focused on one desktop environment, which was Xfce. And then we started
to see, okay, Roland liked to have the GNOME desktop, so he was keen to use that. So we
added that as well. And since I had the past with the KDE, I said, okay, beside Xfce, I
would also do KDE and we had the main editions and we kept them maintained a couple years
ago or so.
And it seems like your team has grown as well. You've got quite a few people on the team's
page now and I would imagine lots of community contributions.
Exactly. So we have 14 people in the core team and many more as forum moderators. So
yeah, a lot of people are joined the project and now we have this new thing called Manjaro
Company and with that we will establish the security of the operating system itself. And
one of the goals is to employ people out of our community and give them an opportunity
to do their hobby as the job if they want to.
That sounds really interesting. Can you tell me a little bit more about the motivation
behind that?
Well, it was kind of fun. It started with a large donation of some person and the person
came over and asked again and said, hey, let's do it properly. I want to meet you. And then
we went over and this person was Clemens Tuners and he said, well, what is needed? And we
talked about it and then in September 19 we signed the contracts and from there we went
with the company.
And so you are currently holding that CEO position. Is that right?
Exactly. So I'm one of the CEOs. The second CEO is Bernard Landauer, who is from Austria.
I met him also through the community and he was back then the community manager. And there
was a nice thing called with the emails. We got a lot of emails, hey, you have momentum
created and we want to create a project with you guys with the hardware. And the funny
thing was, we got one time with starlabs, which is an UK company. And the second time
with station x. And we went for the second company because the first company didn't have
the homepage. And the CEO of station x was Eddie and Eddie said, okay, let's meet up
in person. And we said, yes, why not? And Bernard said, okay, let's go to Salzburg.
And in Salzburg, he knew someone who owned the Red Bull area with all the airplanes.
So we were there on this. And since we did the research and Eddie was in pilot, so he
was really keen that we meet on that airplane. And we did a normal tourist tour. And then
we went over on the roll field, which is not part of the tourist tour and went into the
garage and then we showed them how the airplanes get fixed. And it was all this old airplanes
with the Spitfire and stuff like that. And our research was really good because his laptops
also called the Spitfire because he was a fanatic of old airplanes. And this gave us
the deal. So we went over to London and he has an office in London in an old building
and also Batchelor Park, the second office. And we went there as well and did some YouTube
videos like repairing the Spitfire and stuff like that. Doing a little bit of a tourist
tour in the Batchelor Park, drinking a lot of pines with him and had really good fun
and released the laptop. The laptop was 1k and back in 2007, as it was, it was too high
and we didn't sell as many as we thought. So this project died, but we kept the relationship.
And yeah, so recently, Eddie telegrammed me and said, Hey, Philip, I need a laptop, which
Mancero laptop you recommend to me and said, let me check with our vendors, which of them
best for you.
And check if there's one that's still called the Spitfire, right?
No, I didn't call it the Spitfire in Tuxedo laptops, the same laptop called Infinity Book.
And then we got the second time written by Starlabs and we had no time because we weren't
involved with Tuxedo. And then the third time is a charm. Starlabs is also one of our vendors.
So if you are interesting and keep pushing us and we have the right time, then you might
get a partnership with Mancero.
Yeah, it sounds to me like hardware has been a really interesting area lately. I know you've
joined us on Linux Unplugged quite a few times in the last several weeks, just talking about
some of the updates to hardware that's available there. And I would imagine for the project
that probably seems really motivating as well, because not only are you creating software,
but hardware that's so nicely paired with it, and you're creating these relationships
as well. Does that feel sort of like a nice round way of approaching open source software
and hardware for you in the project?
Well, the operating system itself is always free. And if you wanted to gain some revenue
out of it or something like that, you have to create projects around it. And having a
hardware project might help you to get some traction out. And based on the sales, the
company earns a little bit. And also the other companies gain more customers because our
community is really large. And each partner we look up is have to have the same vibe.
So Tuxedo, we met up in a trade show in Chemnitz, north of Germany. And we were actually at
the same hotel. And one of my colleagues said, hey, there's a Tuxedo car. And he had his
magnet stickers. And he plastered the car full of the magnet stickers. We went the next
day to our booth, and then some new person is coming over from Tuxedo and said, hey,
what the heck? Why he plastered our car with the stickers? How we can take them off? We
said, hey, they're magnet sticks. Easy going. Enjoy the simplicity. And it was so funny.
And that's how we met them. And a year before we met Pine64 in Forstam, also a trade show
where everybody you meet there and one of them, Lucas, got ill. And we said, hey, we
are a lot of people from Manjaro. And we went there, took over the booth and plastered again,
the pine books. It was then the classic one with the Manjaro sticker, go to CEO and gave
him a sticker on the t-shirt. And he said, hey, it looks good on me. And he put a sticker
of him on my t-shirt. So we had the Manjaro pine 64 t-shirts there. From there we go.
The power of stickers. Yeah. It sounds like you know how to have a lot of fun around some
of these relationships. And why not? Right? They don't need to be all serious, but they
do lead to some really neat collaborations, it sounds like. Yeah, you have to be special
and to be remembered. So with those little tricks we do there and there, it works out
just fine. It sounds to me like that's maybe something you learned in some of your sales
experience because I know you did sales for quite a while before starting Manjaro. Can
you tell us a little bit about that sort of part of your history? Well, I was a sales
manager from Conrad Electronics, which is an electronic store in Germany, has many shops
around Germany in the north and the south in the middle of Germany. And I was there
a team lead for the telephone department and later on, additionally, for the computer department.
So I always was with hardware and doing contracts, talking a lot of people and figuring out what
they want and always selling them the right things and selling them additional things
as well because that was a policy of the shop. And they go from selling lamps to telephone,
mobile phones, some picture frames nobody uses after Christmas and everything else around
the Fritz boxes, which is routers and computer as far as parts of computers, laptops, monitors
and so on and so on. Everything what is electronic was my thing. And I used also Linux and when
I got some money for Christmas, they gave us coupons and we had to use them in the shop.
So I bought hardware and every year my hardware stack goes up and up and I didn't know what
I should put on them. So I choose Linux and did my projects there. So was that your like
around that timeline? Was that your first introduction to really using or getting familiar
with Linux? No, it was pretty early because my father has a computer shop. And back in
the day, I got the parts and I had to build a computer, install the operating system and
do everything. So I had MS-DOS with my games and then Windows 3.1, XP, Millennium, 20,000
and so on. And at some point I said, I don't like Windows anymore after I coded my application
to rip some DVDs to learn English. And it was really fun because I was coding all the
time. And then when my mom was angry and said, Hey, dinner is ready. And it didn't hear the
power off. So I had to learn how to do backups. That's one way to learn, isn't it? Thanks mom.
And based on that, I always bought the DVDs and I want to have them collected on my media
server. So I had to figure out how to rip them on the hard drive and store them a little
bit less compressed, but the same quality. I created a tool which helped me and it was
one of those things. I changed also just doing one application when I do the operating system
as well. So it sounds like almost a natural progression for you from a relatively young
age sort of playing with hardware and software and that just evolving and evolving and evolving
to where you are now, really. Did you ever think you'd be where you are today? No, actually
not. I did a lot of things. I did IT support. I did refurbishing, repairing computers and
stuff like that. And each station of my area of my life, I learned a little bit something
new and all comes together. And now I'm here where I'm doing something totally different
than before. It sounds like those evolutions for you these days are really quite exciting
because you're getting to sort of meet people from all over the world and collaborate with
people from all over. And you know, just our conversation before we hit record here today,
you were talking about how you've sort of have your finger on the pulse of some of these
sort of hardware companies and the software evolutions that are happening on a daily basis.
I would imagine that feels pretty neat and rewarding as well. Yeah, because if you are
in the pulse and develop and see what is going on and going with the flow, then you get emails,
for example, from Canonical. So Wimpy, Martin Wimpress wrote me, hey, we have this Snapcraft
summit in Montreal, and it would be keen to have you there. And I said, Why not? I can
ask around in my team if somebody else wants to join as well. And what Wimpy said, Yes,
why not? If you find some, then tell me. And we'll pay everything and we fly you guys over.
But no one had time. So I flew over alone. And the goal was to have snaps integrated
in Mancharo. And, well, I already had it integrated. And I said, Hey, what about making it full
compatible equal to Ubuntu standards. And then I talked with Alan Pope and everybody
else there. We had a lot of fun and some pines went around in Montreal, had dinners. And
I was one of the persons who had a tuxedo laptop. So I did a little advocating with
the hardware we had. And everybody was amazed about the battery life because I was always
on. And even when they got their drinks, I was still hacking because I wanted to have
the snaps thing done. And in the end, it was integrated and Wimpy and Alan was really off
the hook. What only one developer of Mancharo achieved in this week of summit.
I'm getting to know some of these really great people around the open source community. Like
I did a brunch with Wimpy, with Martin Wimpris. And I also did one with Popey, Alan Pope,
as well. And what I'm always amazed with and what I'm hearing from you here is all of these
collaborations that are happening amongst projects to really forward everyone's ambitions.
And it feels like we are all getting quite far together, especially when those interactions
in person are happening. So kudos to you for sort of making that happen and being willing
to work with them as well. I think that's super important.
I think that the tribal wars, which is still there, is only at the communities and not
the companies or projects itself. They are always helping each other. So if you see what's
pine 64 community does, there are several groups trying to get the pine phone ready.
But everybody else has a telegram chat and everybody is there and help each other. Here's
a kernel bug and I fix it already take that patch and then it will also a new distribution.
Other guys do the UI and put other stuffs together. So in the end, everybody's helping
and this is also seen by canonical and other projects. I already met in person. And also
calamari is one of the installer we use on our end. There is Adrian and last foster.
I missed him. He was in the same pub, only two desks away. I didn't have time to change
desks because it was interesting discussions on my desk. And last foster, which was this
year, I met him in person and we connected there as well. And yeah, so it's always good
to see a person in person cause if you only see an online, then the connection is not
as solid. And if you meet them and drink with them, talk with them, chat with them in person,
you make a really strong bond, which is long lasting and everybody understands you better
as just texting and writing costs, lost in translation, stuff like that.
Of course. And I would imagine with so many different languages, people collaborating
in different countries, different continents, that sometimes it's nice to meet in person
and to share some of those cultural differences too. I know that's some of what happened the
last time I was with wimpy and poppy. We just laugh about all the differences, but that's
such a nice way to connect and to then bring those in person relationships to, you know,
the next four months of collaborations that you do online and through code and through
chat. So that feels, I would imagine, especially important these days, considering many of
us can't meet in person, but we will soon. So it sounds like those relationships, those
investments that you've made in the past are really paying off.
Yeah, you always have to be keen to keep the connections ongoing cause if you, if you stop
them, maybe they will break up. But if you're one of the persons who's always on the buzzer,
always following everything, keep in touch with them, then it's good. And they will help
you as well and say, Hey, we have this new release. Did you test it already out? Or as
we mentioned in the summit, you had these and that problems. We already fixed it. Here's
the patch. Can you check it to double check it? And if everything is fine, we will give
it to the new release. So those kinds of corporations only get established if you have meet them
in person or at least did a video chat.
Because I know how you're a bit of a person who looks forward. You were mentioning how
you, you tend to look to the next five years and be a little bit maybe visionary or at
least try to place your mind in the future to see what's possible. And I'm just curious
if some of those collaborations help you point in the same direction as some other projects,
not in a sort of, uh, well, more in a collaborative way, I suppose.
Well, if you not look into the future or what the future might be, you never changed the
future cause then why should you change it when everything what is now is perfect for
you. And it's always a lack of vision in the future to see what can be done or what might
have been done the better way. And we also learn from things we did in the past and maybe
stuff will be more simplified as them now. And this is one of our things we do at Mancharo.
So keep the tools open, keep them easy so everybody else can use them. And if there's
a person said, Hey, why not do this? It's much more easier as the things you did in
the past, then we will adopt and take the better things. And in the end, it is what
it is. The operating system is there and we want that more people will use it.
And are there some things that you have your eye on in the next five years that are kind
of exciting you some, some things you maybe are your, your projects that really kind of
get you inspired?
Well, I think that the current project, which is really inspiring me is the pine phone.
So we have now the opportunity to have a hardware which is open and everybody can hack on it.
It's not restricted like you have an Android base and then you have to put your stuff on
top of it. You can really use the hardware as is and use it like a normal PC and just
plug stuff in, get it started and work with it. And just the first thing I think will
help the whole open source community to get things also in small form factors.
I can remember myself five years ago, imagining that this should be possible and that we should
have this as an option. And at first I was a little disappointed that it took this long
and yet it's still so exciting and it feels like there's some real momentum and lots of
collaborations with different projects making it happen. So I could see why, you know, quite
a bit of effort is going into it because it's a game changer that we really need. At least
that's how I feel.
Yeah, especially because the things are now everybody is starting to track you. And if
you have a Linux phone, this is not happening because you are the king of the software as
well and don't have to relate on big companies and you can verify everything what's happened
on the devices and having the network with all the projects. One project is better to
do applications, the other project is better to do the base UI and other projects doing
better with the base system like kernel and libraries and stuff like that. And if you
put everything together, then you have this Linux phone which is working and only small
things, the distributions change will make it attractive to the community. But overall
you use the same base.
You know, I'm not a developer, but I'm certainly a deep user and it excites me to no end to
know the possibilities that might come in the next five years around these kinds of
projects.
Yeah, but you don't have to be a developer. You can also join projects like you just translating
stuff or what you do talking about the Linux community or about the trend is coming on
or you want to translate stuff. So there is no need to be the developer itself. It's only
one part of the community and there are a lot of other things you can do to help open
source. Even if you're a singer or just an artist and provide a wallpaper, same thing.
You know, I'm so glad you said that. And it's a theme that comes up relatively often during
these conversations is that yes, yes, yes, the developers are great, but so too are the
designers and so too are the translators and so too are the community managers and so too
are all of the people who kind of collaborate to make this big open source city that we
have run as it does. So thank you for mentioning that again. I think that's super important.
You can be the expert on everything. So you have to have experts around you to help you
to be the collective mind and then you can fight against Goliath.
You did mention a little bit of privacy stuff earlier around the phone. I'm curious about
where that sits for you. It's certainly a topic that I feel quite deeply about, but
I don't find necessarily comes up as often as it should. Can you give me a sense of sort
of what motivates you there? And also, I know it may be a little bit of a difference in
Europe versus North America, just culturally around how important privacy feels.
Well, I think the stickers on the webcam on your laptop is a common thing all over the
world. And it's good to see that open source hardware have those kill switches for the
pine phone, you have to open up the battery pack and under there you have some switches.
And those you find also on the pine phone on Pinebook. And when we delivered the Pinebook
Pro, we forgot to deactivate the kill switch for the VLAN. So everybody has to activate
the Wi-Fi to get Wi-Fi. Right, right. No, we wanted to be secure. So that's a sort of
teaching mistake. But it forces, I guess, an education around that we've figured out
pretty well, because some users posted, Hey, there's no Wi-Fi. And we said, Yeah, we tested
it was on the Wi-Fi. Okay, you know, and then pine 64. And as opposed to Hey, you have to
do this switch and this keyboard combination, and then you have Wi-Fi.
So that's on the hardware side of things. But how does it touch you sort of on the data
side of things? And you know, all the services that are being offered these days, and just
sort of hoovering up all of this personal stuff? How does that sit with you? And where
do you feel like we should be going?
And always depends how collective you are with your own daughter. Some people say, Hey,
it doesn't matter if the government or companies earn money with my daughter, others say I
know data at all, because I'm a private person, why should my daughter be free for everybody
when I browse the net. So that's why Linux creates some projects like the p Hall was
a Raspberry Pi, which will direct everything to DevNow. And then Amazon and Google can
search DevNow for all the data, which is they're not anymore.
They'll find quite a lot in there, I think,
if we have an open source operating system, you can decide yourself how far you want to
give your data away or not. And this is not given with Android and Apple phones anymore.
I hope there's a day in the near future where that's the default for most people. But I'm
unfortunately a little skeptical and not convinced. But I sure am glad we're headed that way,
at least for some of our devices.
Well, the phone, I don't think it will be soon. The one and only phone you have to use
if you have online banking, you might need to steal an Android phone because the banks
is really complicated to get them on board on a Linux phone. So of course, you have to
have a standard. That's why Canonical is trying to get snaps out there. And Fedora over Gnome
wants to spit out the Flatpak. So we have two systems and we will see if both of them
have good, good ways. And if we see some banking applications, either on Flatpak or snaps,
then maybe, you know, that's fascinating to me. I had never realized that that was a problem
that some of these package standards could solve. But of course, it makes it easier for
the banks to sort of roll out that software in one place. And hopefully, it can be fairly
smooth and fairly quickly. But just occurred to me, like, thank you for sharing how those
are, that's just an example of some of the problems that we are trying to deal with.
And everybody, well, most of us are doing some banking, right? So these are the hurdles
we have to go over.
Yeah, you can create a lot of applications like video player, audio player and stuff
like that. But if you have a key application, which is banking, you have a hurdle and you
have to take that hurdle. And if you say, Okay, Linux distributions, how many are there
200? And there is no standard and the bank director says, What the heck is Linux doesn't
work. And if you say there is two versions, and there are companies behind them, and they
help you to get your application even packaged for that. And if you get involved and call
right with them, then you get the software in it. And that's how it goes. But you have
to have persons out there talking to them and say, Hey, this software would be nice
to have on Linux over and I really don't understand why people hate snaps and flat packs so much.
Because there are so many distributions and we need a standard and the standard in Linux
is not given yet.
It sounds a little bit like I'm hearing your your sales voice there again, you know, going
to see some of these companies and creating collaborations is a sales process. I know
it might not be a monetary one, but it's a really important one to build those relationships
and build that trust moving forward so that we can make this possible. So I really appreciate
that perspective.
Exactly. Yeah.
One question I have for you that's come to mind for me in the last week is around development,
specifically and how open source is a combination of so many different types of development,
but I'm interested in your perspective on paid developers who work on open source versus
unpaid developers. And do you have a sense of sort of where that is, where the trouble
is with that, where you'd like it to be, how to make it sustainable, etc. It just feels
like one of those things that we need to make sure exists. And so how do we take care of
everyone?
Well, if you start in Linux, around this Linux open source platform, you have the problem
that operating systems and stuff you cannot sell. So you have to have something around
it or you have some supporters which say, hey, I support you, what are you doing? If
you concentrate on the operating system because I'm using it, then I pay you the money for
that. And based on that, we can go on and make this company and employ people. So that's
how we do it on our end. And sure, community developers are given and they do it in the
spare time. And some of them do that for fun, because that's a hobby, and it will still
be the hobby. And others say, Okay, if there's opportunity to make the hobby a real job,
then why not?
Mm hmm. Yeah, I hope we can all sort of support those who do such good work. I think that's
really important. Philip, if there was something that you'd like to ask of the community, something
you'd like them to go see experience, and maybe something you'd like them to think about,
what would you put out there?
Well, if you're interested in open source, then look not at the big projects like KDE
and Nome and all the out there. And there are little projects as well, which might help
you to understand how open source works cause less people less problems. And if you see
a bug tracker in GitHub, and you have a solution for it, simply start provide a patch and merge
request. And with that, you can get you started as a open source developer. And if you have
the opportunity to join a company out of that, then you will be paid developer doing open
source. So many ways and little projects like if XFC and others which are in need of developers,
might will thank you to join them.
Start small and grow. Sounds like a nice trajectory. If people wanted to get in contact with you,
where would they reach you?
They can write me an email, go to the forums, ping me there, write me a PM. Look at me at
telegram. I have many ways to contact me.
Great. And we'll certainly link to those. Philip, thank you so much for joining me today.
I really appreciate your time. And I definitely learned a lot. So thank you.
You're welcome. No problem.