Well, hi, Jackie, hi, Brent. How are you doing? I'm good. How about you? I'm doing great.
So to give a little bit of context, I'm here with Jackie DeVore. She is a whole bunch of
really great stuff, but I'll give you a little bit of context about where we are physically.
So I've been doing a little bit of a East Coast US trip, which has been really fun.
So I've been staying with Alex from Self Hosted for a little bit. And now I've come and seen
you guys as well because you're not too far, which has been a real treat. So you've taken
me into your home.
Yes. And it's been an absolute delight for us.
Right. So you and Drew have taken me into your home. Drew does most of the editing for
the brunches. And many of you have gotten to know him through the brunch that we did
together, one of the early ones. So we will link to that for sure. But Jackie, it's such
a treat to get to chat with you in person.
Yeah.
So joining us as well is some of your rabbits that you have in your home.
We have a lot of rabbits. Yeah, and there's one. She was laying on me when we were setting
up here, but now she's coming in from the side. This is Min, a very, very fluffy bunny.
She's going for my juice. She has a drinking problem.
But totally welcoming. And you guys have taken me in and I really appreciate that. So it's
been so fun to spend the last few days with you and checking out Savannah here together.
We have absolutely loved having you here. It's been a few days full of food and music
and great conversation. So yeah, well, it just continues here, doesn't it?
Can you give us a little bit of an intro on what you do?
Well, I'm an artist, so I make a lot of different kinds of art. And I'm a podcaster. I'm one
of those people that never really has a title.
Which is a good thing, I think.
Yeah, I guess.
Tell me a little bit about the podcast that you're doing.
Okay. So my main podcast is Sirens of Scream. And we've been doing this for four years.
It's an all women-led horror podcast. And we talk about absolutely anything horror. People,
when they think about horror, they think about just movies or shows. We talk about comics.
We talk about art. We've even talked about hairstylists that do horror-themed hair. And
it's, honestly, it's wild. We've had some absolutely incredible guests on the show.
We were actually talking the other day about, we were talking about music, and that led
to our shared love of Nine Inch Nails.
Yeah, I'm a huge Nine Inch Nails fan, for sure.
And coincidentally, we had the art director for Nine Inch Nails who also writes a comic
called High Level, Rob Sheridan, on the show a few months ago. And he was a phenomenal
guest to have on. He and his wife do these insane Halloween haunts at their house that
they post about every year. And he does this absolutely incredible glitch art. And these
people that we have on the show, typically, they don't just do one project. They will
do, like horror will really encompass a lot of different areas of their life. So it's
really interesting to have them on to talk about the project or talk about something
that they're interested in horror, and then really get to know them as people and what
got them into horror, what happened in your past to make you really want to look at this
traumatic stuff.
But what I've learned, because I have mentioned to you in the last few days that I have a
really good friend, her name is Miranda, and she is totally, like, I would say her entire
lifestyle is splashed with horror in the best kind of way, right? She brings it to her decor
in which you guys have around here. You've got a few sort of horror themed decorations
around your home. It's pretty much always a horror theme around here, which is super
fun. And I love how you can take something that some people feel is really uncomfortable
and take it to a place that brings a lot of joy to people. And that's what I've noticed
of people like you and my friend Miranda and Nine Inch Nails, how it just, like, surrounds
your entire life and all your different projects. But you as an artist, I would imagine that
splashes into everything that you do.
Oh, absolutely. Horror definitely comes into a lot of my art. But at the same time, I also
pull a lot of color and, like, a lot of bright color, a lot of weird, happy themes into art
too. And I like to combine the two in a sort of surreal sort of way, which I think is strange
for some people.
It sounds like it pushes the envelope of what's generally accepted as horror or not.
Yeah, yeah. That I do like to question a lot. Like, I was showing you the other day, I have
a series of animal head girls that I do in watercolor and my favorite is one that I call
Goldie and it's a chicken headed girl and she has an arm missing with her bone sticking
out of it. But she's, you know, the background is a bright neon pink and she's got a, you
know, a neon blue for her body and everything and like gold gilded throughout the piece.
So the colors are bright and happy and they bring you in. But, you know, she's got these
elements of these big glowing dark eyes and, you know, I like to make things uncomfortable
while also making them kind of fun.
Well, the neat thing that I've picked up on is like horror doesn't need to be said. You
can have, it may sound weird to say, but you can have horror that makes you happy.
Absolutely. Yeah. And there's an entire sub-genre of horror comedy even. So yeah. Like one particular
movie that comes to mind is Warm Bodies or even one that's exceptionally popular, Shawna
the Dead.
Fair enough. Yeah. Okay.
But I mean, or Tucker and Dale versus Evil is another great one. If you haven't seen
that, that's fantastic.
I haven't. You'll have to show me that.
I think that might even be Canadian.
Oh, well, apparently I'm learning that a lot of that kind of stuff is Canadian.
Yeah. Canada has the best comedy these days. Hands down. There is no doubt about it. Canada
definitely has the best comedy these days.
Oh, nice. So at least we're known for something.
Yeah.
That's great.
Best comedy and best maple syrup.
Well, you know, sorry Maine. We were chatting earlier as well about how on your podcast
you end up bringing a whole bunch of personalities that are really excited to hear about from
you guys, like Nine Shnails you were mentioning, but you have had some other special guests
as well, right?
Yeah. We had the Soska sisters on and recently-
Who are Canadian.
Yeah, they are Canadian as well. And they're pretty big in the horror industry. And we've
had other horror celebrity types on like Colin Bunn was on and we had Andre Gower and Ryan
Lambert who are movie stars on. And people ask us sometimes, you know, do you just harass
the hell out of these artists and these stars to get them on your show? And no, we just
simply ask them, Hey, do you want to come and talk about your really cool project with
us? And-
I would imagine most people are honored to talk about the stuff they're doing right now.
Nine times out of 10, they'll be like, yes, absolutely. I would love to talk about my
cool stuff with you.
And maybe it's a fallacy to think like that, oh, they'll never reply to me. I'm just a
podcaster or whatever, right? But I feel like there aren't really any rules around this
stuff. So if you have a means of contacting someone, you should just go out there and
try it, right? And that applies to anything. You don't have to be a podcaster. Like if
you want to get a question answered from one of your mentors or your heroes or something
like that, just just kind of reach out and you never know what will happen.
Yeah, exactly. And I mean, like Wayne Gretzky and Michael Scott said, you always regret
100% of the shots you don't take. That's great. Yeah, just try. The worst case is you're right
back where you are. Yeah, they either don't respond or say no, and then you can move on
with your life. Right. Do you have a wish list of people that you're chasing or hoping
to get on at some point?
Absolutely. Right now, we would really love to get the Dupless Brothers on. Do you know
the Dupless Brothers?
I don't because I'm new to this genre.
Oh, my God. They're wonderful. They're both actors and they're both writers and producers.
And they were all actually both on the Mindy project back when that was a thing. But Mark
Dupless specifically wrote and starred in Safety Not Guaranteed. And right now they
both write and direct and produce Room 104.
I don't know it.
Oh, it's great. It's a show that is basically, it focuses on one room in a motel and all
the weird stuff that goes on.
Oh, it reminds me of, is it Five Rooms? This is a Quentin Tarantino. Well, it was a whole
bunch of directors. I'm taking you on our side now. But it was a whole bunch of directors
that focused on five hotel rooms. It's totally worth checking out. There's like Antonio
Banderas saying, oh, here I'm showing you something. There's some really cool, wacky
stuff that happens in there. So it's a recommendation. But continue with what you were mentioning
as one hotel room.
Yeah. And it's basically like a guideline to how to never get your deposit back in a
hotel room. It kind of like tows that line of what's horror. It's one of those kinds
of shows that it will really vary from episode to episode between horror and comedy and just
straight up tragedy. And it's really fantastic. It's very out there. I think it's on HBO right
now in its fourth season currently. But it's fantastic. There's a lot of great writing
going on there.
Nice.
The Uplus brothers, they're very eccentric. And they choose very interesting projects
to work on. So I'd really love to talk to them. They seem like they would be very interesting
to sit down and talk to.
Great. So if anybody has a connection to them, feel free to reach out.
Oh, I sent them an email already.
Good, good. Of course you did.
It was actually like just a week ago. So we'll see if they reply.
Yeah, that would be so amazing.
And so tell me a little bit more about the podcast or some hosts that join you as well.
My co-hosts are Sierra Halk and Melissa Meagan. And Melissa is the one that actually came
up with this idea for The Sirens. And how this actually started was quite a while ago,
I actually helped Chris Hardwick with a social media site called The Node. This was like
a side project of Nerdist. And it was an invite-only social media site.
Oh, fascinating.
Yeah. And I helped him run it. And on that site, it was just like a couple thousand members.
And I happened to meet Melissa and Sierra there. Another girl and I, Steph, had a blog
site called Nerds in Babeland. And we just wrote geeky articles on there.
Did you say Nerds in Babeland?
Yes.
That's such a great name.
I know, right?
Lovely.
And that actually went on for a while. It was just a blog site where we posted stuff
about comics, just various nerdy things, really. I actually got invited to attend a NASA launch
because of that.
Really?
Yeah.
Oh, my goodness.
I'm actually a social media liaison for NASA because of that site.
That's so cool.
I know, right? So, Melissa was a regular writer on Nerds in Babeland. And Sierra helped out
every now and then, too. And Melissa approached me out of blue. She's like, I really love
horror and I really want to start a podcast about horror. And I want to do it with three
ladies on the show. And you're the first person that came to mind.
Cool.
Melissa had always been on Talking Comics before that, which is a really popular podcast
about comics, obviously. And she asked me, do you have anybody else in mind that might
work for this? And I said, Sierra.
Nice.
Our personalities really work well together.
I agree completely.
Yeah, for sure.
We're very different in a lot of ways. Our interests in horror really intersect. Melissa
is very family-oriented. She has a young son, so she really looks for horror that kids can
get into, which is really important.
There's some amazing books out there that are sketched in a way that is horror-themed,
that is written in a way that's kid-friendly.
Yeah, like Edward Gorey.
Yeah. I guess some popular films have been like that, some animated films as well. But
I have often thought that those two worlds can't really coexist, but I'm learning that
they certainly can.
Yeah. And I'll circle back to that in a moment.
Okay, great.
Great.
And she also really loves comics, so she kind of handles that side of things for us. And
Sierra is a very, very ferocious reader, and she really loves board games, so she really
covers that side. And I hate silence, so I always have something playing in the background.
And I also am an avid video gamer, so I cover that side. And we all really love art. We
all love music, so we all come together with our various likes and dislikes. And Melissa
likes slashers, Sierra likes found footage, I like ghosts, and it's-
So you sound pretty well-rounded then.
Yeah.
That's awesome.
So it's nice to have three of us that really cover this huge genre, and it works very well
for us, I think.
And have you had the opportunity to meet them in person?
No.
Really?
Oh my goodness.
For four years, and we've never met in person. What's weird is Sierra used to come down to
a town just outside of Savannah every year for Thanksgiving, and we could never make
it.
Oh no. That seems like a shame.
And then I was supposed to go out to Seattle just a few months ago, and then that-
Of course.
Didn't work. Last minute.
Yeah. So it's like the starts would never align for us meeting.
It'll happen. It'll happen.
It's so weird.
Yeah, there's something about being there in person, as you and I are doing right now,
that is such a treat. And I've talked about that before, that you can build this really
amazing relationship with people at a distance online, which could never really happen before.
It's almost like a pen pal, right?
Yeah.
But there's these amazing connections that can happen that way. But when you sort of
reinforce those with an in-person meeting, it's such a treat. So I'm looking forward
to hearing when you all get together. That's going to be great.
But the kids and horror, let me circle back to that. As I mentioned on another JP episode
recently, I think it was an extras episode that Drew and I did for Halloween.
Yeah, that was a great episode. I loved it.
He and I met while we were planning a zombie walk. And one thing that we really learned
with the zombie walk is that kids love horror.
Really?
Kids would get into those zombie walks so much. You would see these four and five-year-old
zombies running around like, rawr, trying to scare their buddy. And they would get so
into it.
And do you think it's linked to an open imagination at that age?
Oh, absolutely. Kids, they don't really get scared the way people expect them to. I went
to a show where Neil Gaiman was talking. And it happened to be at a theater where Drew
used to work. So we got to hang out backstage and talk to him afterwards. And I talked to
him a little bit about kids and horror. And he has a lot to say about kids and horror.
And he writes a lot of kids and horror, like Coraline. And he has a really great take on
it. Kids are just, they will accept things in a world much more openly than adults will.
Adults will apply these rules that they're used to every day to these imaginary worlds
that are presented to them, where kids will see an imaginary world and dive into it and
be much more open to what's happening in that world rather than apply these rigid expectations
that adults have.
That's so interesting, right? When we were kids, our imagination was one of the places
that we played very often. And as adults, that almost atrophies a little bit, I would
imagine for artists that might not be as true. But it seems to me like what you're saying
is it's important to not cling on to those rules too much when you're approaching something
like horror genres or stories that really push your imagination.
Yeah, it's important to step outside of that rigid comfort zone. Be open.
Yeah, of course. And so I was just about to say, do you know of any kids who listen to
the podcast? But you may be a little explicit on the podcast sometimes, right?
We're a little bit too foul-mouthed for that.
That's all right. That's all right.
So like pretty much the first 15 minutes we started talking when you got here, I warned
you straight up, I talk like a sailor. And it's true. I've been bringing it in a little
bit here. Actually, I haven't been censoring myself at all. It's just coincidence. But
I do, I curse like a sailor.
But what I like about the podcast and the use of it there is that you use it pretty
tastefully. Like it's in the places where it really enforces a point.
I appreciate that.
Yeah. No, I think it has its place, you know, it's nice to hear. If you've listened to,
for instance, like user error, I feel like it has a similar feel in that it has splashes
here and there. But it's only to highlight the things that really matter, right? Sometimes
its uses is exactly perfect. And okay, with kids, maybe that's not so appropriate. But
I say don't change a thing.
Yeah, thank you.
Yeah, absolutely.
Well, coincidentally, my best friend Blue, she's this incredible, incredible woman. She's
an ironworker. And she does a lot for women in her field. And she's a huge advocate for
badass women doing awesome things.
And she was actually listening to one of the Sirens episodes. And she mentioned to me that
she likes how much I cuss on the show.
Really?
Yeah. And it inspired her to start a podcast of her own that she's going to call Women
Who Cuss. I kid you not.
That's awesome.
And her show is actually going to be kind of centered around women who do really interesting,
big badass projects. And she wants to bring them on and talk to them about these projects
and then talk to them about them as a person to really give a well rounded, you know, three
dimensional view of these, these women and what they're doing. She and I are also launching
a project later today.
Oh, cool.
It's called HBIC or Hell Bunny's Independence Club. And we, the shortened version, the HBIC
and the relation to the other meaning of it, head bitch in charge, is absolutely intentional.
The purpose of this club will be to bring boss ass women together in a very supportive
and inclusive kind of environment. So where we can support each other, lift each other
up, a place where women can vent safely, where we can network, basically just a common ground,
like a meeting place where we can come together and have a place to be safe and talk and do
great things and anything we want.
Wow. And it sounds like that spans different professions and different occupations and
everything is like not really too many limits on it, right?
Right. What we're starting with is actually going to be a, um, a discord channel.
Okay. Oh, that's a nice way to do it.
Yeah. We were talking about creating a forum space on a website and that gets complicated
so fast. And we were trying to figure out the details of that and how to, how to work
that out. And oddly enough, Blue and I met on forums on, uh, Rooster Teeth long, long
ago. I've been an admin on Rooster Teeth for over a decade, but that's, that's a whole
other story. So we, naturally our minds go straight to like an old school BBC forum kind
of thing, you know? But as we're sitting here and making it overly complicated for ourselves,
suddenly I look to my, one of my screens to my right and I'm like, oh, I keep discord
up all of the time. Why don't we just open up a discord server here? And I just sat there
and made a really intricate, intricately detailed server for us there. Um, and we're, we're
finally launching it later today. We actually, uh, sought legal advice on it and everything.
It's, it's going to be quite a detailed thing and, um, we are not limiting it, um, strictly
by gender. Uh, we don't want to be that exclusionary cause of course we're not, we're not TERFs
over here. We do want to welcome allies. We, we, we don't want to, you know, say no trans
here. We are not, we don't want to be that kind of people.
That can be, I imagine a little bit tricky too. Cause how do you keep it safe at the
same time? Right?
We do have a, um, uh, system in mind for, uh, bringing in, uh, allies and public support
and, uh, upgrading people to what we want to call members as we vet people basically.
That sounds really wise.
Yeah. So keeping people at like a very basic level and not allowing them to interact fully
at first before we completely vet them and then moving them up to members as, as we vet
people. So we want to, we want to be able to keep it a safe space and we want to be
able to keep it a place where, uh, women and allies can speak freely and, uh, free of consequence
and, um, be able to support each other without worrying about who else is there. This is
something that we've actually been talking about for literally years. Uh, we want to
do a lot more with this project. This is really the very, very basic first step.
Yeah.
Uh, this is something that we want to create, um, speaking events with. This is something
we want to do a charity with. This is an entire massive project that we have been talking
about for so long. And I'm so glad that we're taking this first step. It's very exciting
and kind of frightening, but most important things are right. So we're going to put it
out into the world today and see how that goes.
Great. Well, I, you know, it feels like this topic has come up in a few of my conversations
before. I know Elle talked about it a little bit and Emma did as well and Jill too. And
those are all really great conversations, but it's this theme that keeps coming up,
right? It's like, how do we include everyone? How do we include everyone? This is such an
important thing. Uh, and I totally support that approach and I hope that it, it gains
some pretty long legs and, and really gets going. It sounds like a gift actually. So
thank you for that.
And it was very coincidental that I, uh, specifically brought it up to you. I think yesterday I
said, who was that woman that was on your, on your show? Just that, that last episode,
I loved her. I want to reach out to these strong women that you're having on your show.
These are great people here. So I'm learning so much in these conversations. Like that's
a topic that I didn't necessarily think was, uh, so deeply at the forefront of someone
like Emma, who you're mentioning. Uh, but she feels at least as far as I understood
that this is one of our main missions, right? It's like include everybody, especially in
tech or, or you were mentioning horror as well is often sort of seen incorrectly as
male specific or male only, which is totally wrong, isn't it?
Right. And, um, one thing that I don't think people realize is that women don't really
have a lot of spaces where they can speak freely without backlash. You can't really
say to your male coworker, Hey, you're making me uncomfortable or, Hey, you're not including
me. Why can't you say that? Um, a lot of times women will get flack for that. They'll get
punished for that. That's awful. Yeah. Women will be overlooked as being, um, dramatic
or causing problems, uh, just because they spoke up for themselves. Uh, they'll be seen
as that, that person that just has a problem with everyone just because she spoke up about
sexual harassment. And it's, it's insane that we're still dealing with this in 2019 completely.
And it's also very upsetting how much more prominent it's actually become in the past
couple of years. Oh, you sense a change. Yeah. There are certain factions of people that
have been a little more outspoken with their misogyny and it's a bizarre and terrifying
trend. Terrifying is accurate. Yeah. Um, being a woman that has been in tech specifically
that has been in the art world, that has been in the horror world, the gaming world, right?
Yeah. Gaming world, especially. Oh my God. That's something that I, I know is it's a
needed space. It's something that we absolutely need. You know how, when you hear, when you
learn a word for the first time, you suddenly hear it everywhere. It's true. Yeah. As we're
getting closer to launching this project, I'm suddenly seeing everywhere just how needed
it is. I've known in the back of my mind that it's a very needed thing, but just in the
past couple of weeks, I've been really seeing women itching for this exact type of project.
So it's, I'm very excited for it. I'm very excited to see how it blossoms and I really
hope it grows in a positive way. Yeah. I'm sure it'll evolve in all sorts of directions
you can't predict right now, but that will be necessary in many ways. Right? Yeah. Um,
how do you see the discord server being approachable by some people who may not, um, know what
discord is or, or have experience with it at this point? Discord is, uh, fortunately
pretty user-friendly. Okay. Um, so we're writing up a little guide, uh, for people to just
be able to read through and they'll be able to chat there. But it's, it, I mean, it'll
be a very easy to use, just chat form sort of thing. So it'll be basically be like the
old school chat rooms of the nineties for those types of people that don't, don't really
get into the internet that well. Yeah. Reducing those barriers is such an important thing
for something like this, right? It's like, how do we make it accessible to everybody?
Absolutely. Yeah. That's awesome. Very important thing. And so where can we learn more about
this? We are setting up a website right now that will be hellbunnyindependence.club. Nice.
Okay, great. And we'll definitely link to that for sure. And literally right before
I got on the air with you, I said to Blue, okay, what domains do we have these days?
Let's go ahead and set up a, let's set up a website and you know, just make sure we
have info there so that I can send people somewhere. Gotta plug these things for sure,
especially when they're so fresh. And, and I love how this was completely unplanned,
the timing of all these things, of you and I chatting and this coming out, but it just
like is pretty serendipitous that it's all happening at the same time. So it's great.
It's one of those things that feels meant to be because of the timing. Yeah, yeah, for
sure. Which is awesome. Okay. I wanted to ask you a little bit more about some of your
art. I know you hinted to me earlier that some of your art got picked up maybe by a
brewery by chance. Can you walk us through that a little bit?
So I have a friend, Megan, who is in Ottawa and she does a lot of work with LGBT groups
there and she's another incredible woman. I love that I have surrounded myself with
incredible badass women doing amazing things. I was just thinking, how do you find all these
amazing people? It's just coincidence. Well, you must be attracting them with some energy,
that's for sure. I hope so. Oh, you have good energy, I like it. Thank you. So Megan actually
just coincidentally asked me a few days ago, how do I make a logo? I'm like, well, I do
graphic design. I'll do it for you. What do you want? Basically, you ask someone who knows
how to do it, right? And she just told me what she wanted. So I went ahead and whips
it up for her. And her organization there is called Bell's Corner. Well, she's in Bell's
Corners, I'm sorry. So her organization there is called Queer's Corners. Oh, nice. That's
a nice play on words. So we made this logo and she went ahead and put it with her organization
and a brewery in the area called Whippersnapper saw it and loved it and said, we're going
to go ahead and make a beer with that logo on it for you guys. Oh my goodness, that's
amazing. Within hours of all this happening, it just all happened within a day there. And
I had actually never heard of Whippersnapper because it's very localized to the area it
seems and we're so far down here. I don't know Whippersnapper either and I lived in
Ottawa for like eight to 10 years or so. So I wonder if they're new. It seems like they
might be pretty new, but it seems like she knows the brewer there. But their flavors
are very inventive. We went through quite a few of the flavors. You were showing me
some of these earlier. They were amazing. There was like a blueberry pancakes one.
Yeah, there was one with guava and oh my God, guava. It almost seemed like it wasn't beer
or it was a whole other like parallel universe of beer. Actually, maybe that's a nice way
of putting it. So over there, like talking to her kind of salivating over these various
flavors he's making and telling her how jealous I am. So she and Ian the brewer are actually
working on sending me some. Oh, cool. That's nice. I'm so excited about that. Cool. But
it feels like kind of probably feels like a treat to you that some of your art is getting
around that way.
Yeah. I also have some art out on Ghost in the Burbs merchandise right now. Ghost in
the Burbs is a podcast that is wildly popular in the horror realm. It's about a woman who
lives in Wesley, a suburb of Boston, and interviews her haunted neighbors.
That is so great.
It is wonderful. She transcribes the interviews and puts her own voice to these transcriptions
and she has such a beautiful writing voice. The podcast itself just recently ended last
month but she did it for three or four years.
So there's lots of content there.
There's so much content.
Beautiful.
And the story is wonderful to go through. Her name is Liz Sauer. She was on Siren's
screen for an episode there and she and I became friends through that. But I did a couple
of designs for her and one of my designs, which is a Ouija board with one of her sayings
on it, is still up on the shop there.
Nice.
And that design got pretty popular. So it's actually really fun to see people on Instagram
post their mug or their shirt with this design that I have and the little tag there. I even
have Liz send me one of the mugs with my design on it. So sometimes I get to have my tea in
my little mug with my design on it and it's nice and fun there.
It just reminds me of the power of art in any form really. Either digital stuff like
some of your design work, but also you've got these beautiful tattoos and some of your
painting stuff is pretty incredible. You were showing me a mask that you made out of all
sorts of stuff and it just feels like the string that ties all that together is artistry
and yet can help share some pretty powerful messages too.
Yeah. I feel like being creative is a pretty important part of my life in general. I feel
like that's something that people don't really do enough of, but that's very much a huge
driving force in my life. I mean, it's the way I solve problems. It's the way I approach
everything, literally everything. We were talking about even cooking and we were talking
about cooking vegetarians specifically and how people when they try to incorporate vegetables
in their diet if they're just eating meat a lot and they'll steam some broccoli and
be like, I hate this.
Because broccoli can shine, but not if it's boiled, right?
Yeah. Well, obviously you hate that. Look what you did to it.
There's a real artistry in your entire life, even in cooking. I agree with that completely.
Art in the kitchen can be such a delicious thing.
Yeah. Creativity through everything in life I think is a fun way to live life and a great
way to live life, for me at least.
I have noticed as well that you're pretty good with tech stuff and you're a gamer and
you bring in some of that artistry. Those often are seen as exclusive that art and technology
can't necessarily mix, but I think that's a completely a huge fallacy, right? It's like
one can increase the other.
It absolutely can. In fact, in that next room over there, hanging over the mantle, you'll
see a massive picture.
I do, yeah.
That is an art print from my favorite game, which is Portal 2.
Oh, that is such a great game.
And that picture is called Approaching Wheatly. Coincidentally, that print, the way I got
it is really interesting. Do you ever do Reddit gift swaps at Christmas?
No, but that sounds fascinating.
Oh, so Reddit does Christmas gift swaps. They do the biggest secret Santa in the world.
I used to do it every year and it's a lot of fun. Sometimes you'll get handmade things
from somebody in Lithuania or something. It's incredible. These absolutely charming and
wonderful things that you will get from other people and you'll get to know other people
that way. It's wonderful.
This person that I got matched with one year, almost a decade ago, he just fucking slayed
it. He went through my profile there on Reddit and saw that I love Portal 2 so much. He saw
that I'm a gamer. He saw that I'm an artist and love art and he found this art print.
It's a limited edition signed by the artist. Massive art print from my favorite game ever.
Oh my goodness. That's unbelievable.
When this came in the mail, I was floored. I did not know how to handle this. It was
so incredible.
I think anyone can do art and I have been really fortunate to have integrated photography
into my life. Previous to that, I hadn't had that much experience with artistic endeavors.
It was mostly because I came to technical topics much easier and much more easily like
science and especially computers, that's for sure. I realized that once you dive into technology,
there's a huge amount of creativity that goes into it. Solving problems, as you know, can
be a very creative endeavor. I've been lucky enough to see that with combining photography
and computers, but I encourage everybody to find some way of expressing yourself creatively.
It's such a wonderful outlet.
Jackie, can I ask you a question?
Go for it.
I was wondering if you had an ask of the community, of anybody listening, maybe something you'd
like them to try or to do?
Well, you're asking that at absolutely the perfect moment because my ask would be to
look for creative ways to do things in your life, whether that be to go out of your way
and paint a picture today or to go through your usual routine and add a little spice
into your lunch today or maybe find a colorful way to get to work, a little more scenic way
to get to work.
That's nice.
Find some way to add some creativity to your life.
Put on your artistic glasses and see the world in a slightly different way.
Absolutely.
That's lovely. If people want to get connected with you, where would you like to send them?
I am Jackie the Robot on Twitter and Instagram. I post a lot of bunny and art pics on Instagram.
It doesn't seem like you at all.
No, not at all. My personal site is uselessprogress.com.
Nice.
And sirensofscream is just sirensofscream.com.
Great.
So it's easy.
That's wonderful. Thank you so much for chatting with me today. It's been a real pleasure.
Thank you for having me on. It's been absolutely wonderful getting to know you the past few
days and absolutely wonderful talking to you now.
Great. Yeah. Thanks for having me in your home and for sharing all of the bunny love.