Well, hi, Jill, hello, Brent. I'm so excited.
So this is another Brent with Brent and you have been wonderfully excited to be on. And
so I should introduce you a little bit more. So I'm joined here today by Jill Bryant Reinecker
and Jill, I would love for you to just give us a little taste of what you do.
So I am a co-host on Linux Weekly Daily Wednesday with Linux Game Cast on the Linux Game Cast
network. And I do game streams with them. And I'm also the community organizer, otherwise
known as the morale czar. That's what they named me. And I'm so I do lots of podcasts
and I love joining in with Linux Unplugged and yeah, regular guests there. That's how
we got to kind of meet for the first time. Yeah, that was awesome. And the Friday stream,
which I do miss. Many of us do. Yeah, for sure. And then I'm also in part of the Big
Danny Linux community as well. And just was interviewed by Rocco, too. I should also mention
there's Linux Checks LA in there as well. Oh, yes, yes. Very, very important. Yes. I
just want to point out that I gave a listen to your Linux spotlight with with Rocco, which
came out very recently. And, and it was an amazing conversation. So I would encourage
everyone to go give that a listen. It was I was laughing throughout, I was smiling,
I learned a lot about you. So I'm going to try not to sort of repeat that because I think
it's it was a really great conversation everybody can enjoy. So I'm here, I think with you and
I were just going to dive into a whole bunch of other stuff informed by that. So one thing
I want to start with actually is how come you have such a bright and wonderful personality
that's so contagious. That's one of the things that just like, was immediately apparent to
me. And it seems like you're always smiling. You know, for for those of the podcasts that
have a little bit of video and do you get that a lot? Like people are just like attracted
to you for that energy. It seems like a really great gift. Yeah. Oh, thank you. Yeah, I get
that a lot. And I've just always my glass has always been half full. Yeah, that's such
a nice way to look at the world. Right? Yeah. Yeah. Tell me a little bit about podcasting.
So I know you've been doing it for a long time now. And so give me a little taste of
how you first got into it and where you think it's going. And I know you wanted to mention
Chris in there. Yeah. So Chris Fisher, you're the one who inspired me to get into Linux
podcasting. I had been wanting to do this for so long. I've had years of broadcasting
experience. In fact, I did produce and DJ my own show for almost 16 years in my 20s.
Tell me more about that. That sounds really fascinating. So I did it. It was a what we
call synth music or crowd rock music, electronic music show. And because it's it's not the
genre music that is typically heard here in the United States, but it's a very part of
the European art scene and an experimental scene. And how did you first get connected
to that music then? Well, I had been a listener for years on another radio show. And this
is this is, you know, years ago in the 80s. And I started co-hosting on a radio show here
in Los Angeles at Loyola Marymount University on a show called Alien Air Music. I love that
title. Yeah, that's great. Pat Murphy was the first to play this genre in music. And
then I decided to do my own show where I played, you know, different music than he did some
of the same overlap, but different. And, you know, there were also no ladies into this
genre in music. And that was that would be that was really interesting because a lot
of the the musicians and artists who would contact me and send me music to play on my
show thought I was a guy. Interesting. Yeah. Because Jill is Gil in, you know, a lot of
the European countries and Russian. That's fascinating. Yeah. So they just assumed they
were talking to a guy. Oh, that's hilarious. That's like maybe a strange advantage, actually,
like a pen name. So that's really funny. Yeah, it was. In fact, I taught one of the
artists from Russia. His name is Edward Artemiev. He's done quite a few soundtracks. And I got
to talk to him in on the phone and he was asking, you know, is is is Gil Bryant at the
residence? And I think my dad answered the phone and, oh, she's here. And I started talking
and he's like, oh, my gosh, this is like a lady. This is a girl. I've been communicating
with a girl. It's like Linux and my all my other hobbies and that I'm into. It's it's
male dominant. And I'm just used to that. Well, and I want to ask you a little bit more
about that, actually, because, you know, women in tech is certainly a totally great thing.
And I'm a huge, massive supporter of it. For those who have listened to the episode with
Elle, there's a whole bunch on that topic. Oh, yes, there, which was really great. But
you know, does that has that felt discouraging at any point? Like it sounds like in the music
in this music scene and also in the Linux scene, you're you're surrounded by a bunch
of men, which, of course, can be totally fine. But has there been some challenges there,
too? There has. But, you know, it was in the beginning, like in the early years of Linux,
I'd gone to I'd gone to a lug and didn't feel welcome. Really? And I was just not even
I they didn't even acknowledge me. Oh, that's so sad. Yeah. I was going up to introduce
myself and say who I who I am. And and I didn't get acknowledged. And that was, yeah, really,
you know, that really depressed me. And then I found out it turned out that my brother
had worked with the person who ran that particular lug and said, oh, he's a bad seed. Oh, wow.
It sounds like it wasn't about you is more about him. No, it just I guess he's just like
that to everyone. But all the people that were part of that community were really nice.
I wore one of my first Linux shirts, which was user been girl from ThinkGeek, you know,
years ago. And I wore that and I got a lot of comments from the community there. But
I just it was really I felt like, you know, it was very standoffish. That's too bad. And
my brother said, Yeah, he was really hard to work with. So that was your one of your
first experiences with that. But as far as I understand now, for instance, with like
Linux checks and things like that, there's there's a whole positive spin to it, right?
Yeah. And then after that, you know, I went a couple years without, you know, I was, you
know, I've always been a huge Linux user and had been using it. And, but, and, you know,
I started using it and literally 93. So, and I wanted to get involved more in the community.
And that was, that was really sad. But things changed. Yeah. So this user is group. Did
you go that one time and then feel kind of turned off and not go again? I did go again.
And I still felt, you know, I figured, well, let me give it another chance. Good for you.
Yeah. And I still felt not comfortable. So not your place, then not your kind of people.
Yeah. And but then a few years later, I wanted to attend scale, the Southern California Linux
Expo and purposely sought out the Linux chicks of Los Angeles, because I know, you know,
they were like minded ladies in the field. And I had seen their meetings posted on the
internet and the articles about the different conventions and the Linux chicks that were
in the Linux journal, our favorite Linux journal is gone now. But I, I knew I wanted to connect
with them. And that was one of my main reasons for going to scale. And that was scale 5x.
And the first place I went after I registered is the, the gentlemen, the workers there were
nice. Then it was Gareth Greenaway, and Ilan Rabinovich. And Gareth actually directed me
straight. He, he, he took me straight to the Linux chicks LA booth. And I would have gone
to scale the previous couple of years. But I was a little nervous. I thought, well, maybe
I just I'm not as good enough in Linux, you know, did you feel like you might have had
that same initial experience then? Yes. And there was a little bit of that too. I was
a little a little nervous about that. But it was exact opposite. I went to the booth
and they had they had a questionnaire on what apps you use on Linux. And I named, named
all my favorites, of course, the GIMP and, and Inkscape then and Blender, and Xterm,
you know, everything.
So it sounds like you're well versed for sure.
Yeah, I wrote down like little like 50 apps I use. And then then my favorite window managers,
you know,
you put an S on that, which I love
window maker, you know, flexbox, openbox, TWM, the whole nine yards. And they were just
kind of blown away. They're like, Oh, my gosh, you you you know, all the stuff you've been
using Linux for so many years.
Well, that's what I love is is like, there's many of us who are just kind of like, before
we get introduced to the community, the greater community, there's a lot of us doing some
cool stuff kind of just in the shadows a little bit, right. And I think for you and I now
it's our job to kind of invite them out and say, Hey, come on out here. Like, it's pretty
friendly out here. So but please continue the Linux chicks story. That's great.
Yeah. So what was what was so amazing, it was one of the best days honestly, of my life
going to that first dance scale. Wow, that is huge. And then then going to Linux chicks
booth and within literally 20 minutes, they're like, they're like, they just give me gave
me hugs. And it was exact opposite of what I experienced before in the whole scale community,
you know, it was just a big if you're a Linux user, you got a hug. And they're inviting
me and I'm like, Oh, come come behind the booth, Jill. And then I started helping them
with their booth. And we were best friends forever. From that point. Wow, that sounds
like a really powerful experience for you. It was and that was, you know, early 2000s.
So and so you were a big Linux fan before going there. But I imagine having this experience,
you were just a fan for life after that, all of a sudden, I was part of the community.
And that just, that's, that's what did it was my, my scale family and my Linux chicks
delay family. That's awesome. And that family continues up to today. Like you're still quite
a bit involved. Tell us a little bit about that. Oh, yes. So. So it didn't take just
literally that day. And they made me you know, they're Sharon's like, she was the president
at the time. And within a few days, she's like, Jill, you're now a co organizer of the
Linux chicks. Wow, that's awesome. So there's three of us that are co organizers. So it's
an amazing organization, you know, basically to, to, you know, help get not only ladies
in into Linux, and diversity in Linux, but men also, you know, we were not gender exclusive.
So we have just as many men in our group as woman, which is great. I, I really applaud
that sentiment of trying to be inclusive to everyone. And not necessarily leaving anybody
out, right? I think that's super important, even if you come at it from from sort of a
different angle. So yeah, kudos to you guys. That's really important work. I think that's
great. In fact, at our meetups, we do hands on workshops teaching how to install Linux
on raspberry pies and on computers. And we encourage, you know, new users, you know,
of anyone to come. And usually we have more men than than than woman. But that's kind
of normal. So there's just more, more, you know, men getting into it than women. So
and how do you think, for yourself, how do you like, what, what led you to being just
hooked on computers? Because I know, from what I've learned recently, that you have
a number of them behind you and all of that stuff. But I know you had a brother who was
interested in it. And what was this an older brother? Yes, yes. He's four years older.
His name is Jack. So it's Jack and Jill. Yes. Oh, interesting. I have an older brother named
Chris, who's four years older, who got me into computers. So it's really similar, actually.
Oh, that's awesome. Brett, we have something in common. We have tons in common. Yeah. Oh,
yes. Yes, we have everything so much in tech. And so I imagine Jack had a huge influence
on you. Yes, definitely. He was one of the the first people to get into it in the 80s,
you know, and that was before most people even had computers at home. So and we had
just about everything at home. And he had an ad elite BBS. It was truly lead. In fact,
he ended up getting jobs working directly with Bill Gates and Steve Jobs because of
that BBS. Yeah. Wow. That that sounds amazing. And and your grandparents, too, had some kind
of connection there as well, right? Yes. Apollo. Yeah, they were because here I live in the
middle. That's that's why I grew up here is because of aerospace. You know, we have JPL
and SpaceX and and Northrop Grumman and which was TRW and International Rectifier and all
the big this is the think tank area where where a lot of the products are made that
go into space. That sounds so fascinating. I want to know so much more. My grandparents
were both top top secret with Apollo. So I just I grew up with that and my grandfather
worked. Grandmother both worked, built tubes for the very first computers. So it's just
been part of my family. Right. So how could you not be influenced by that? Yeah, it sounds
like there's a real there's a real trade of that being handed down throughout your family.
So that's a kind of an amazing history, actually. Yeah, I'm very, very proud of it. My give
you a little bit. My grandmother was the one who built the engine that brought Apollo 13
home. Oh, man. That was her engine. It wasn't intended. It was intended for the the the
lamb not to bring them home, but it had enough power and was built so well that it could
bring them back to Earth. That's unbelievable. She got a medal from the president and everything
for that. So that's so cool. Wow. Yeah. I just got a pause for a moment. There's there's
it sounds to me. So you started at a very young age being interested in computers then
and and so that has brought you all the way to today where you that hasn't given up in
any way. It seems like right. You're still you seem like a tinkerer at heart and just
a voracious learner for sure. Yeah. And you know, my brother always says, Well, it wasn't
just that we had it had it around in the house and you had access. You wanted to do it. You
had the drive to learn how to build computers. You know, I took our Apple two apart, which
much to my parents chagrin as long as you put it back together. I put it back together
and got it working. And then the first computer I really built was my 286. So and I did animation
on it and led to my becoming an animator later in life. So I want to dive into that a little
bit because I think as you know, I'm a photographer and I do all my stuff on Linux. And cheese
does some design work, some of it on Linux. And so I want to jump in a little bit about
sort of how you feel about the creative community using Linux because as far as I understand
this, that's a relatively new thing. Of course, you're maybe a bit of an exception to that.
But give me a give me a little bit of your perspective on that. Well, you know, originally
in the eighties, you know, I was using a PC at home to do animation because I couldn't
afford the, you know, fifty thousand dollar Unix. Of course. Yeah, right. You know, and
the, you know, software that they were using for animation at the time. So the industry
honestly is particularly with film, not so much broadcast TV, which is still predominantly,
you know, Mac and Windows, but still Linux on the back end for rendering. But the film
industry really they just moved to directly from Unix to Linux. And one of the the pieces
of software that brought about that change was Maya. Originally, it was alias Wavefront
for Unix, and then it moved over to Linux. And as soon as that started happening, all
the software's proprietary proprietary and open source started moving to Linux, not just
for rendering, but for creative content. Do you have any idea what was the original impetus
for them to make that switch price cost? Because in the film, see in TV, they actually have
more money to spend on their productions in film. You know, they have like a two year
span and they can only spend a certain amount. And that's what it was. It was it was the
ability to have not just free software, but maybe even more important to that to be able
to develop the software that they wanted, you know, with an open operating system. So
they can add like, for instance, Pixar and Disney, they have software they developed
under Linux just for doing like underwater scenes and finding Dory and finding Nemo.
And all that development was done on Linux. They use, you know, they use Maya and Blender
and a lot of different software packages together as well as proprietary. But Disney is in the
process. They've been open sourcing a lot of their animation software. And what was
really cool is recently, actually, two years ago at Seagraph, the big international computer
animation convention, someone in the audience had asked one of the developers of the software
they were using for finding Nemo if it was going to come to Windows. And they said, we
don't need to bother. We're using Linux. And I was just like, yeah, that's so awesome.
And they even had system 76 laptops on stage. It was awesome. That makes me smile because
that's exactly how I feel about it. Right. It's like, why would we translate the software
to Windows when that feels like a downgrade? Right. Yeah. And and that Linux is available
to everyone.
And then another thing is with recently, it's just over a year old. The Academy Software
Foundation has been incredible because it's it's helping all these companies and businesses
who want to start using open source software, not with just usability, but the licenses
and everything they need. And it's specifically made for Hollywood. And, you know, Blender
was the forefront of that movement back in the early two thousands. I've been using it
since then. And so do you have any personal experience with that foundation then? No,
but I am thinking of becoming a little bit more involved. And I did get to talk to the
executive producer at the Open Source Summit recently in San Diego. There was a long, long
line of people to talk to him after he did a talk talking about, you know, doing an introduction
about the Academy Software Foundation and and what it's doing in the industry. It was
a, you know, a learning tutorial for new people who didn't know. And so most of the people
that were in line were young students who want to get in the animation industry. So
I came up to him. I was at one of the I was the last person to talk to him and I said,
oh, no, I'm a podcaster and I've been talking about the Academy Software Foundation since
the beginning. I do, you know, Linux pod news podcast. And I said, I've been working in
the industry for years. The companies I work for, we've had, you know, multiple awards,
everything from from Webby's and Telly's to Emmy's. And I've been in it for many years.
And he was just like, oh, Jill, I want to talk to you. He was really he was so excited
to talk to someone that was in the field, you know, at the Linux convention instead
of just students. And so did you guys go for coffee or something or did you keep chatting?
No, he had to he had to take a plane home. Time constraints. That's always the challenge.
Yeah. But he talked with me a good half hour. We had had a nice chat. That must have been
great. Yeah. So that was really nice. And I got to tell him, you know, my experience
and and how it's it's changed. It's, you know, not just Linux on the back end anymore. It's
it's in the development and creative now. So on the front end, yeah, on the front end,
which is so nice to hear, like, from my perspective, with photography, you know, we're using similar
tools but a little bit different. And so I've watched even in the last Oh, gosh, I guess
it's almost eight, nine, 10 years, something like that. I've watched the software grow
quite a bit and enable many of us to do it full time with the tools that are available
in open source, as opposed to the commercial stuff. And so it sounds like the transition
that animation and film made many years ago, seems to be just happening now.
It's so true, you know, now the graphics are arts just in photography, it's really starting
to, to come of age now. So that's, yeah, I've been really awesome.
Of course, I'm biased, but that's very exciting. And I hope it can reach as wide an audience
as it as it has in in your world, really.
Yeah, I think I definitely know it will. I mean, you've got, you know, programs like
dark table that are really, you know, taken off and then you have, you know, critter and
GIMP and photopea and all the open source software that you can use now in Inkscape
under Linux, that's really, you know, taking over. And now we also have the proprietary
have DaVinci resolve, which has taken over the Adobe suite in the industry, because it's,
you know, it's its premiere and after effects all in one.
You mentioned something that I want to go back to a slight for a slight moment. You
mentioned during your experience in film, you worked with a whole bunch of businesses
that that got a whole bunch of awards. Can you tell me a little bit more about that time
in your life?
Yeah, no problem. So it was after I graduated. I was the very first computer animation graduate
from the Cal State system. I was what was called a special major, I created my own,
I combined communications, fine arts and computer science.
Oh, cool. That's such a great combination.
Yeah. And, you know, it took a year to get it approved, but they were all so impressed.
Like this is the future. This is, you know, back then we called it the information super
highway, you know, the future of the creativity.
So that was in fact, I had to do a talk in front of the director of the Cal State system.
And that was the big term was the information super highway was going to bring creativity
to a new level.
And has it?
Yes. Oh, yes. We don't call it the information super highway anymore.
Right. Things have changed.
Things have changed. But yeah, so I had created my own major. So what had happened is after
I graduated, you know, I was real a nervous student, you know, wanted to get into the
field, but I'd already had worked most of my life doing animation all back, you know,
through the apple too, when I was a little kid and work really, really hard.
And then I got connected with a freelance animator and who had a studio and did quite
a bit of work for him starting in the, in the mid nineties and on. And we, he had contracts
actually, you know, cause we worked together for a long, quite a few years and we had contracts
with, with Fox and Warner Brothers, Disney, ESPN, Electronic Arts.
And yeah, so one of the first pieces I worked on, my very first animation was of all things
a commercial for the Russian hockey team that was going to be viewed on ESPN. So whenever
they traveled and they were, you know, one of the top teams at the time. So wherever
they traveled, the commercial ran and I saw it for like five years after I had done it.
That's funny.
That got nominated for an Emmy.
Wow. That must feel pretty good.
Oh God. My very first piece I had ever done for the industry gets nominated for an Emmy.
And Kevin, my other animator, we worked together. He's like, Jill, he goes, your career is set.
You have Emmy on your resume. It's like Emmy, just even being nominated. Cause at the time
it was the, it was 1998 and that was the first year that a commercial that was all computer
graphics was, was one of the topics for nomination. So the first CG commercial. And so that was
a big deal. And there were, you know, like over 500 submissions and uh, yeah, that was
a big deal.
Does that feel a bit surreal at this point? Like revisiting that?
Yes. Yeah. I watch it and I said, Oh gosh, it looks so amateur. But at the time it was
high tech, you know? And that actually the other significant thing about that piece is
one of the reasons that the studios give freelancers their work is, um, is that they don't have
time to do it in house. And so you have a major deadline, you know, we're staying up
for four days without sleep to get, get, get it rendered and which can take time. So after
you create it, then you have to have time to render it. Well, we didn't have enough
power to, to make that final render, to get it to them in two days. So I actually stayed
up all night that first night as you know, I created the, my animation I need to and
my model modeling and I stayed up all that night and built another computer, which was
a 46 at the time to, so I could render. So I'd have three computers I could render with
that home. And then that started my render farm, which later grew into a Pentium, you
know, dual processor, Penny and pro to, to, uh, quad processors, eons and deck alphas
and, and, and the whole nine yards. But yeah, I, and what was really neat is he told the
company he goes, he goes, my animator built an extra computer just so that we can get
this job done. Wow. That's dedication, isn't it? Yeah. There's something about having a
need that just drives you. Yeah. So, yeah. So I did that piece and then, you know, we,
there got like 20 tellies and Webby's and then, um, and Emmy in the future, but that
was kind of what launched that. And I could, I could tell you one other project I'm really
proud, proud of. Sure. Please do put it out into the world. It sounds great. Oh my God,
I'm telling the world. You don't have to know, but this is, I, I, I'm it's, it's time. Cause
this was very special. Um, yeah. So we actually ended up doing the editing on the trailer
for the perfect storm, right? Which, which many of us probably have seen. Yes. And most
people have seen it. So a lot of people have seen my work, but the really cool thing is
we worked really hard, not just on the editing, but we created our own effects for that final
wave scene. Cause we didn't, we didn't like what the studio gave us and we didn't think
it looked kind of real enough. So then at the time the studios, um, water is what we
call caustics has always been hard to render. And we didn't know, there was no one piece
of software that did water really, really well. Um, it would do the mass like an ocean
mass or mask, a mass or a lake, but it was not good at doing splashes and waves where
there's a lot of different details and reflections and all that movement. Yeah, exactly. And
studios were able to do a lot of that, but they achieved that with, you know, really
like hundreds of people, you know, trying to get this right. And it was just me and
one other animator. So, um, not as many resources, not as many resources and darn it. And one
reason I wanted to bring this project up is because darn it, I wish we had open source
software then. So this is, you know, 2000 and we just didn't have that. So we had to
combine, I combined, um, uh, some effects from 3d studio, um, release R4 for dos. This
is before, you know, I did that on windows and a light wave. Um, we had some Maya in
there and, um, I had to write a script that would go from one program to another to get
the effects that we needed because one program would have the part of the effect and the
other program would have the other. So, so to make this, the splash look real, you know,
we had to use several different programs of different particle systems from different
programs. And then I would script it and we added chaos to it. And, um, that ended up
on the final splash of the wave. And the big deal there was that the studio was so blown
away with what we had done that that's what was part of the original film. Oh, wow. That's
cool. Yeah. So it became, uh, so that was one of the first films that we had worked
on. That's unbelievable. Instead of just a commercial, for instance. Yeah, exactly. Wow.
You must feel super proud about putting that work in and then having it be recognized.
Yeah. And it was just, it was a lot of, it was so much just thinking about it. I remember,
you know, going to Kevin's house and we were just, you know, pounding our heads like, how
are we going to achieve this? You know, it was just cause we didn't, you know, the tools
weren't available and we didn't have access to those at home, you know, at our own, in
our own studios like Warner Brothers did and Pixar, you know, so, but then we were able
to do something that they were having a hard time achieving. So that was a proud. So two
people beat a hundred people. Yeah. That's so cool. Good for you. And thank you for sharing
that story. That's amazing. That's a really amazing. Yeah. Oh my gosh. I'm sharing it
on the internet. Cool. No, it's out there. It's so funny cause that's what's unique also
about podcasting. I've been behind the scenes most of my life, you know, except for, you
know, doing my, my teaching and teaching computer animation and motion graphics with my students.
And they've seen, you know, we, you know, instructors show the students our work after
they've been taking the class a while so they can see what you can do and it helps them
get them inspired. But I've never put this out really on the, on the internet too much
except talking with Ven and Pedro on LWW and the pre-show and after show with our, our,
our patrons and chat. So I've shared some with them, but not in an interview or chat.
Well, thank you for sharing it. I feel like a lot of people would love to, are going to
love that story. So that sounds amazing. How do you think that open source would have changed
that story a little bit? Oh boy. Well, I would have had, I could have had tools more like
blender at that time. You know, we could have hired a software developer to, you know, help
us do these special particle systems, you know? So you feel like it would have made
it easier than trying to daisy chain and pull like little pieces from all these different
tools and have them create the effect that you needed, right? And now, you know, a lot
of the freelancers that are left do have a lot of developers cause in the animation industry,
half of it is, you know, we need coders and developers to create, create the software
needed. Well, I love the juxtaposition between technical creativity, which would be the developers
who are trying to achieve a vision and the actual, like the visual creativity as well.
And how those two now these days, um, are, are such a cool place that, that technical
people who traditionally haven't been seen as creative can really show their creativity
in many ways. Yes, definitely. And yeah, as you know, it's just as much technical as it
is, um, creative and artistic. And especially in the freelance world where you kind of,
you've got to know everything. You gotta be a Jack of all trades or a Jill of all trades.
Yeah. And I encourage that in my students because a lot of times, you know, they want
to be character animators or do textures or do sound or do lighting. And I try and give
them as broad experience. I, you know, want them to create their own movies with all these
elements together so they get to learn a little bit of everything so they can see what emphasis
they would like to, what area they'd like to focus on, but also set so that they're
well rounded for the industry. Cause I want my students, you know, I want them to not
just learn character animation. Um, a lot of the other schools, that's what they, they
just churn out students learning, you know, character or materials, but they don't focus
on the whole person and the whole, you know, area of knowledge. And I even, um, not only
of course teach them Linux, but also, um, I always do a session on how to build a computer
because that has helped me. And it's good for them to, to know how it all works.
And do you feel like the students are responsive to that these days?
Oh yes. They're coming to me knowing that this is the field they want to get into. Most
like half my students want to get into the field. So they're willing to learn and they
understand that they need to need to know a lot of this for, to be relevant in the,
in the industry. And, uh, so they not only coming in with that art background with,
with life drawing and years of drawing and painting and sculpting and color theory and,
um, uh, computer graphics with, with, um, Photoshop or GIMP or Inkscape and you know,
all those skills, but they also need to know the technical, very important.
Well, and I totally associate with your giving them like a rounded view of the industry and
then allowing them to jump into a niche. Um, because I feel like, um, the same is true
with podcasting, right? Is that if you, if you, if you know all of the pieces that go
into sort of the whole pipeline, um, then you have this perspective, uh, that even if
you're only working on a little piece of it, um, you have this perspective that makes your,
your work sort of fit in, in a different way or, or allows you to solve different puzzles,
right? With that creativity,
Exactly. Solve different problems. You realize, okay, well I'm doing, I'm working like if
they're doing materials, I'm working on this material. Well, how can I help help the people
that are animating these materials?
Also thinking of the impact later on in the process. Oh, that's really fascinating.
That's always been a goal is to make sure they're really well rounded and, um, you know,
that, that also that they have learned to have a really good work ethic cause the hours
are grueling. So can be grueling in anything you love it. It is. Yeah, for sure. Yeah.
And anything you love, you know, whatever you're doing.
The cool thing I've noticed is when you're working on something so passionately, you
kind of forget about time and you forget about, um, you know, that staying up all night is
kind of crazy, right?
Yes. It's happening to me right now with podcasting. Oh really? In what way? Well, just doing all
the research for it. I try and get to bed at a halfway decent time, but ended up staying
up sometimes till two and three in the morning, reading Linux news stories for my show and
listening to all the podcasts cause I love all the Linux podcasts and I listened to them
all.
Pretty soon you're going to have, there's going to be too much content for you to possibly
take in, right?
Yeah. And it's already kind of coming to that cause there's, there's new shows coming out
and I'm just like, I can't keep it up, but I try to.
You can just play it while you're sleeping. I've heard it gets in your brain anyways.
And I just love it. I'm just living it. In fact, I'm not doing much watch, watching other
content than YouTubers and Twitch streamers and, and podcasts. It's been pretty much my
life cause I've just loved it and just going, you know, putting myself all into it and I
love it. I love all the communities.
Does that feel like a big treat for you now? How when you were first starting, maybe it,
the community or Linux wasn't spoken as publicly and that now it's sort of everywhere.
Yes, we have a bloomed, the flower has spread forth. Yeah, it's about time. And this is
what we've needed. For me, it's a continuation of the community we have at scale and the
Linux conventions and the lugs. You know, this is a continuation of that. The podcasting
is, you know, online lugs like Linux Unplugged, one of my favorite shows.
Well, thanks. Yeah. The Linux Unplugged, I think as I've mentioned before, is the reason
I'm even here. And it sounds like that was a huge impact for you as well.
I started watching Jupiter Broadcasting in the beginning since it was the computer action
show and not the Linux before it was the Linux action show. And I was listening to Jupiter
at night and stoked and I'd always wanted to become involved in the Jupiter Broadcasting
community. But at the time I was really busy with my, you know, my animation career and
had, I already had so many hobbies.
I've heard you have a few.
I've been collecting vintage computers. I have several hundred. So when I started podcasting
with Linux Gamecast and I knew that was the community I wanted to start with because that's
the one I became friends with everyone and because it had a graphics end to it. It was
Linux Gamecast. It was gaming on Linux. And I had done some work in the field. I'd worked,
as I mentioned earlier, a little bit for, actually a lot for Electronic Arts, doing
game development and 3D models and artwork. So in Linux Gamecast, Linux gaming was my
passion and this is, you know, the days before Steam, before we had Proton and all that.
You know, after I started with Linux Gamecast, I've been full time with them now a year
and a half and I knew it was time to start giving back to the Jupyter broadcasting community
because of all the wonderful Linux content that Chris has worked so hard and all of you
work so hard and who he has given us so much in the Linux community and over the years
and I just wanted to give back and that's one of the reasons I wanted to get involved
in Jupyter broadcasting. So I wanted to help give back to the community that Chris worked
so hard to create and just it's my thank you to him.
Wow. Well, I'm sure he'll listen to this and I'm sure that means a heck of a lot to him
for sure and it does to me as well as purely a member of the Jupyter broadcasting community.
I feel like, you know, if we all have gained so much from it and continue to gain so much
from it and it's that giving back somehow, whether it's just coming to say hi at a conference
or something like that, all of those little gestures make a huge difference, right? And
of course you've showed up quite a bit in the mumble room when we're doing Linux Unplugged
on a weekly basis live, which anybody can join and it's been so nice to have someone
like you there because it just adds to the diversity of all the people that are included
in that group, right? And I know you and I sometimes after the show we just end up just
chatting for no reason and just having a really good time.
Oh, I love all you guys, you Brent and Cheese Bacon and Wes and Joe, you all, you know,
everyone in the Jupyter broadcasting community and Elle, I love Elle. I was so happy to
see another, see another lady in Linux podcasting after I started, you know, I'm like, oh, good,
Chris has Elle now. Yay.
Yeah, for sure. And Angela, I think she's been behind the scenes, which is kind of a
thing you mentioned, right? Like there's a lot of people behind the scenes that don't
always get seen.
Yeah. And I loved her, her a woman in tech, a podcast she was doing and the Faux show
and Angela has been amazing driving force in a Jupyter broadcasting. So I've always
looked up to her too, a lot.
That's great. And, um, you mentioned some of the earlier shows, it sounds like, um,
you know more about the history of Jupyter broadcasting than I do in many ways. Cause
I came to it a little bit later.
I was just a ravenous listener, you know, I was so quiet other than, you know, I donated
and you know, I've been a patron of Jupyter broadcasting since the very beginning, but
I've been, you know, I was buying the t-shirts and I have the challenge coin and
Wow. You're outdoing a lot of us, I think.
Yeah. And so I wanted to give back and also because of Ed Stone, the producer of Linux
game cast got his start because of Jupyter broadcasting.
Oh, cool. I'm learning all of these things is really cool. Yeah. I like the idea that,
you know, there are a lot of communities now and you're part of a lot of them and that
we all have our, you know, concentrated time. It's like, okay, Tuesdays at, at whatever
time it is in your local time, there's Linux unplugged and then you can bounce to another
one somewhere else that has a bit of a different crew and some overlapping, um, community members
to and go be a part of that community as well. Right. I just love that. I think you're totally
going to agree with me. Um, in that it's really special how it's okay to be a part of all
of them and that there are all these connections that have been between all of them, like a
web of, of really neat interconnections, right. And that, that we all grow because of it.
Yeah. We all grown, we all, all learn, you know, in different points of view. Like for
instance, I'm doing, you know, LWDW is a Linux news show. Well, of course, Jupiter broadcasting
has lots of Linux news shows, including, uh, Linux unplugged and Linux action news and
all the other shows, but we all cover different things. We have our uniquenesses and, and
the way as in, uh, not in just, uh, the stories, but, and how we, we, uh, produce them and
how we talk about them. So, you know, we all, all learn from each other. We all share, you
know, knowledge, we're sharing knowledge. Yeah. Which is, is that's open source, right?
Is, is sharing all of it. Exactly. I appreciate in the podcast that there's different perspectives
and different ways of presenting the information. Like, as you know, as a teacher, not everybody
learns the same and not everybody connects with information in the same way, right? So
to have it be presented in all these different ways is a huge asset and, and, and kudos to
open source for, um, keeping that spirit of, of sharing and, and the collaboration, right?
That's what's just so amazing. I love it. We've spread that to the internet, the Linux
community and all their, you know, we used to be, you know, these quiet lugs and commit
conferences are now spreading that love online. It's spreading everywhere. That's awesome.
Tell me a little bit more about, um, some of the other conferences cause you mentioned
scale, but it sounds like you bounce around a little bit more too. Yeah. So, oh gosh,
I want to go to Linux Fest Northwest cause it's the next big one that I haven't been
to yet that I've been wanting to go. It's amazing. I'm totally biased because that was
my first experience with conferences, but it would be great to see you there. Oh, I'd
love to go. So I'm going to work on that. But I do, we've been having, uh, here in Los
Angeles, uh, quite a few, um, open source summit, uh, conferences as well, which are
fun. They're not quite as community based, but they're, they're growing a little bit
more in that way, but it's, it's, it's more, you know, big business, but I, you know, I
go for, um, the hallway track, you know, so it's the best place to be. It's the best part
of a convention anyways, really the talks are wonderful expo halls, incredible, but
it's those connections that you make in the hallway track that I love. That's what's really
memorable. I find. Yeah. Tell me, I, I'm interested a little bit more in, um, some of your teaching.
Oh, um, because you mentioned it sort of in some of your stories, it was the, it was some
key aspects in some of your stories, but, um, what inspired you to move from kind of
being the professional doing stuff behind the scenes to sharing that knowledge? You
know what? I always was, I actually started out, um, in the nineties as a, uh, a tutor
in the animation department. And then I went to TA and then ended up being on the board
of directors for the department. And, and so I had always been doing that, um, uh, through
my college years. And, um, that helped me get a lot of connections actually, you know,
because I was doing that and had that experience, um, that helped me with my work experience,
uh, getting into freelance work. So yeah, I ended up doing the teaching first. Yeah.
And then both things I just said at the same time, and I feel like that's the real gift
of, of, of, of a teacher. Sometimes you see, um, and maybe now I'm starting to speak about
my personal experience, but you're sometimes you see teachers who were in the industry
and, um, either have retired or decided to get out for some reason and they teach and
they don't, they don't always have the same perspective as someone who's working in it,
uh, alongside the teaching. Right. And so I really appreciate how you were kind of doing
both. And that's the best benefit for the students, right? Is that you're, you're teaching
them exactly what's happening in the industry today.
And I get that actually from my students cause they, you know, know a lot of their other
instructors, you know, used to, to do their profession, you know, and they're, they're
now just teaching. And so I get my students are always amazed and you're still doing this.
And they're, they're thrilled that I'm doing podcasting too. And they like that. I'm, I'm
what we call it, Twitch tubing, Twitch tuber. And they're like, cool. My teacher is a Twitch
streamer. But yeah, just, just, uh, you know, being able to, to share that enthusiasm with
them and all the areas that I love. And then I'm still continuing to do work and, um, just
love that.
You're giving back to the community in so many different ways, you know, from teaching
to, um, some of the podcasts stuff that you're doing and even just showing up at conferences
and Linux checks. And so, uh, thank you, I will say from the community for your, your
big, big heart and your giving back. It's, it's really meaningful.
Oh, it's been an honor to do it. It really has. This community is amazing.
Yeah. And it's, it's growing and it's continuing to be even more amazing, which is, which is
such a treat.
And what's really been just really exciting for me is a lot of my students who end up
getting work in the industry and becoming, you know, producers and animators and whatnot
are part of the Linux community now and part of the Linux checks.
You're seeing them evolve in your footsteps almost, right?
Yeah. They, in fact, they call, they call themselves Jill Siples.
That's awesome. You have a following.
Yeah. So it's so funny cause at scale when I was introducing all the Linux game casts,
all our hosts who, um, a lot of people at scale, they're like, Oh, is another student,
another student, another former student, you know, yay, bringing them in.
Well that must mean you're doing some good work. That's good feedback. I want to say
thank you so, so much for chatting. I know you and I will continue to have these kinds
of conversations and maybe we can share some of them in the future as well. Um, but thank
you so much for your time. And this was really, really fun.
Thank you so much for having me, Brent. This is an honor. And I can actually say, you know,
it's kind of a dream come true. I've always wanted to get involved in Jupiter broadcasting.
So here you are. Thank you so much for, for, for being involved in many ways. Um, is there
anywhere that you'd like to send people if they want to get connected with you or just
hear you giggle or those kinds of things? Uh, so, um, I get several places. One is,
um, at Twitter at Jill underscore Linux girl and at Mastodon at Jill underscore Linux girl
at mast.linuxgamecast.com and on email it's Jill at linuxgamecast.com.
I wondered if you had an ask of the community, um, either like, uh, something you'd like
them to do or explore or try.
Yeah. So I actually have two things. Okay, great. Bring it on. One is a current news
story that's been happening. Please help support the gnome foundation and fighting the shot
will image app patent troll and help send a message to patent trolls everywhere that
they should never target free software. This, this is scary. This can be very scary, especially
it's Ross child that's behind it and it's not good.
The implications are huge, right? And so if we, if we can kind of get together and make
a difference, I think, uh, that speaks volumes.
Yeah. And you know, I had donated the first day I found out about it immediately. And,
um, and if you can't donate monetarily, just spread the word on social media and on the
internet, you know, all it takes is one person to spread the word and a hundred people will,
will hear it and see it and they may contribute. So we're going to help them.
Yeah. So let's get, get everyone's eyes on it for sure.
Yeah. And the other thing is there are so many wonderful Linux podcasts and video casts
out there, whether it be an RSS feed on YouTube, on Twitch or all three, like we've talked,
been talking about, um, I encourage everyone to go find and watch them. You never know
what amazing communities you will discover and learn from, and you just might become
one of the contributing members yourself.
Which has happened to both you and I, right?
Yeah, exactly.
Um, members of the community. And then you get a little closer and a little closer and
all of a sudden one day you find yourself in the chair. So, um, I agree completely.
Yay, Britt. If you can show up, you know, if it's at a conference, if it's at scale,
if it's at Linux Fest Northwest or any other conference that catches your attention.
Yeah. Get involved.
For sure. Um, even, even in the online communities, you know, there's, there's all these telegram
groups and live podcasts that get recorded every week. So, um, just show up. You never,
you never know what's going to happen. Well, thanks Jill. I hope to connect with you really
soon and, uh, thank you so much for your time and for connecting. This was really fun.
Thank you, Brent, so much. You're one of my favorite people in the community and I can't
wait to give you a hug when I see you in real life.
Oh, thank you. Yeah, we did just figure out that, um, we're both going to be at this coming
scale.
Yeah. Yay.
Um, can you remind, uh, some of us when that is coming up?
Yeah. So it'll be, uh, March 5th through 8th of 2020, uh, scale 18x. Amazing.
That sounds great. Uh, I am, I think in for a treat. It's going to be my first scale experience.
So.
Oh, I'm so excited.
And I really look forward to meeting you there in person too. That's going to be great.
Yay.
Thanks Jill.
Thank you so much, Brent. Love you community. Love everyone.
Yes. Lots of love to the community. Thanks everyone.