We've got together on the live stream today to really put Brent to the test.
He's in the studio, and if he can get all the way to $32,000, he will earn 1,000 Satoshis.
Brent, are you ready to become a Linux millionaire?
I'm sweating already.
I think that's a good sign.
Now, none of these questions have anything to do with Linux, but we're still going to
have fun.
Welcome in, Brent.
Good to have you here.
Thank you.
This seat feels hot.
Did you turn it up?
Yeah.
We definitely have the seat turned up when you're in here.
It's just part of the intensity of it, you know, to get you really kind of in the zone,
get you stressed out.
Thank you.
Plus, the sweating looks really good on camera.
It's the shine.
Yeah.
So, you're in from out of town.
Let's see, where are you from there, Brent?
Well, there's a place north.
You may have heard of it.
Canada?
Yeah, the land of the snow.
Yeah.
It's a little colder there.
So, Brent's in from out of town.
He crossed many borders many times to be here.
Did I ever?
Took the long way, I think.
Do you have any friends or family listening today, Brent?
Oh, I don't know if I do, but if I do, I'll give a wave.
Yeah, give them a shout out for us.
I'm waving.
They can't see.
Yeah, you let them know that you're here and that you acknowledge them and that you appreciate
them being here, okay?
Yeah, I think my mom actually is tuning in from a snowy, snowy cabin.
Good.
Everybody say hello to Brent's mom.
Hi, mom.
Hi, Brent's mom.
Thank you for joining us today.
So, Brent, if you win the 1,000 satoshis, what are you going to do with them?
Well, I'm trying to wrap my head around exactly how much they're worth.
At this point, I haven't got a good sense of that.
It sounds like a heck of a lot.
It does.
I'll tell you what.
As a little treat, if you win them at the end, I'll tell you how much it is.
What do you say?
You want to do that?
Yeah, that sounds fun.
1,000 satoshis to you or the cause of your choice.
Oh, wow.
Brent, are you ready to try to become a Linux millionaire?
I'm ready.
Okay, Brent, which of these subjects is taught at a graduate school informally, known as
B school, A, business, B, Bible studies, C, biology, or D, basketball?
Which of these subjects is taught at a graduate school informally, known as B school, Bible
studies, business, biology, or basketball?
The first question is supposed to be easy, right?
Yeah, it is.
It is.
If I get this wrong, do I get a second chance?
No.
Yeah, listen.
You got to figure this is the first question, right?
So they probably are going to make it pretty easy, right?
So you could probably think the most obvious answer is probably that one, right?
You don't know the answers, though.
I can't tell you if I do or not.
All right.
I can't tell you.
But I can tell you it'd be horribly embarrassing to lose at this stage.
Well, the one that seems the most obvious to me would be basketball because the others
seem like, no, I don't want to say anything bad about basketball.
Taught at a graduate school.
Mm-hmm.
So graduate school fields.
Informally known as B school.
Oh, I misunderstood this.
Oh, oh, oh.
I don't know.
I'm not saying either way, but I'm just saying that's it.
Which of these subjects is taught at a graduate school, informally known as B school?
Oh, got it.
Got it.
I misunderstood the question the first time around.
I'm glad we did this.
Well, it's all in the cases, really.
Yeah.
Yeah, thanks.
I don't know if that really changes anything for you, though.
Well, I'm going to not go with basketball.
I think it's now the worst answer.
Okay.
All right.
That's a big shift.
It's exactly opposite, actually.
Yeah.
Okay.
It's a big shift of business.
All right.
Final answer?
Yeah.
Let's go for it.
All right.
Let's see what we say.
Locking it in.
And survey says...
You got it right, Brent.
Nicely done.
I almost sunk it there.
What does that say about MBAs?
You know, B school?
Not very creative.
Oh, Wes.
Wes is here.
He'll be our emergency call a friend and also color commentary, as you can tell.
Are you ready to continue, Brent?
Yes.
Wait, wait, wait.
What am I at?
$200.
Oh, okay.
We don't really fret about that at the beginning, Brent.
Oh, sorry.
Yeah.
I know.
Wait.
You said dollars.
Yeah.
$200.
Dollars.
You got to get to...
When you get to $32,000 to get to Satoshi...
I know.
It's very confusing.
You got to earn the dollars to get the SATs.
Okay.
According to a popular saying...
Although now the timer is going.
It's all a mess.
According to a popular saying about hot tropical weather, it's not the heat.
It's the what?
Humidity, rash, cold, or fuzz?
Humidity.
Final answer?
Yeah, go for it.
All right.
I like your confidence there, buddy.
Survey says...
All right.
Nicely done, Brent.
Thank you.
Under pressure.
15 seconds.
All right, Brent.
Which of these terms is used for the most luxurious section of accommodations on an
airplane, on a ship, or on a train?
The psychology class, first class, Ritz class, or alpha class?
This should have been question one.
I think it's first class.
All right.
No, no.
I know it's first class.
You know, I got to say, I prefer alpha class.
Well...
I'd like an alpha class seat, please.
That's the future.
We're not there yet.
Okay.
All right.
So you're just going to boldly say B, first class?
Sure.
All right.
Here we go.
Attention.
You got it, Brent.
Thank you.
You got it.
Good job.
All right.
Now for $500.
Which of these is not one of the Energizer Bunny's primary characteristics?
I'm trying to read it without laughing, dude.
Okay.
He carries a bass drum.
Yes.
He has a buck teeth, wears sunglasses, wears sandals.
Not one of his primary characteristics.
A bass drum, buck teeth, sunglasses, or sandals.
I'm going to go with buck teeth.
All right.
Buck teeth.
Final answer?
Final answer.
You got it, dude.
I know.
I wasn't sure about the sandals.
I wasn't either.
I have to be honest.
All right.
You're now at $1,000, halfway to earning 1,000 Satoshis.
Only a few questions left.
What happens if I go above 32?
Well, then we'll have to figure that out.
Okay.
Maybe you will.
Maybe you're in 2,000.
Which of these shapes also fits the common definition of a rectangle, a circle, an ellipse,
a square, or a triangle?
The common definition of a rectangle, circle, eclipse, square, or triangle?
I think they must be saying ellipse.
What did I say?
Eclipse.
It's almost the same thing.
Oh, jeez.
Oh, yeah.
Obviously.
Did I say eclipse both times?
I don't know.
I don't think so.
Let's say you didn't.
Okay.
I'm going to go with a square.
A square?
Similar shape.
All right.
Final answer?
Yes, please.
You got it.
Oh, man.
Almost had me there.
I'm sorry.
It's a little too early for me to read, apparently.
What continent is closest to Antarctica, Africa, Asia, Australia, or South America?
Closest to Antarctica?
I believe there are penguins in Argentina, so I'm going to say South America.
D final answer?
I think so.
Yeah.
Let's go for it.
All right.
Submitting to the computer.
And survey says...
You got it right, Brent.
Nice.
Nicely done.
Thank you.
Now for $4,000.
Just a few away from those sweet, sweet sads.
In 1981, the movie Chariots of Fire, in that movie, one athlete refuses to compete for
religious reasons on what day of the week, Thursday, Sunday, Friday, or Saturday.
You do have a couple of lifelines here.
Thank you.
You got the 50-50, you got the phone a friend, and you got the audience survey.
I'd like to go with the audience survey here.
All right.
Let's do it.
We're going to stop and we're going to ask the audience, okay, Brent, here's what we
got coming in from them.
Coming in right now, it looks like 61% of them say B.
What was B again?
B is Sunday.
That was my inclination.
Eight seconds.
Let's go with Sunday.
All right.
Final answer?
Sunday answer.
You got it, buddy.
Thank you.
Wow.
Thank you to the crab.
I did not know that one.
All right.
The Puget Sound is located in what US state?
Alaska, Washington, Massachusetts, or Maine?
You will be kicked out of the studio if you get this wrong, Brent.
Is that a hint?
I think I should do a 50-50.
Okay.
All right.
We are going to take away two wrong answers from the board.
Massachusetts and Washington remain on the board.
Washington or the nuts.
Which one is the Puget Sound located in?
I'm going to go with Washington.
Final answer?
Final.
All right.
Let's lock it in.
Yes.
Okay, Brent.
One away from 32,000 and unlocking 1,000 SATs.
And I still have a West.
The state of Montana derives its name from a Latin word meaning what?
Northern, snowy, mountainous, or vast?
I'm going to go with mountainous.
Wow.
You're just down.
Ready?
It's the Canadian French that's helping me out.
Okay.
Final answer then.
Yeah.
Go for it.
All right.
Locking her in.
Oh, you got it.
Nicely done, sir.
All right.
Now, get this one right and you get 1,000 SATs.
For $32,000, a brown recluse is what kind of creature?
A spider, a snake, a bird, or a fish?
I'm going to call a West on this one.
Oh, you want to phone a friend.
Very good.
Mr. Payne, we're going to dial you up here.
And we'd like to know what you think a brown recluse is.
You got 30 seconds.
I do not have a sound effect for dialing me up.
Oh, yeah.
This is it right here.
Ready?
Starting now.
A spider, a snake, a bird, or a fish?
Can I talk to West?
Yeah.
West, I'm leaning to the legged one.
No, I think I'm familiar with these.
Let's go spider.
Yeah.
Because they have caves and stuff.
Final answer.
Yeah.
West and I.
Lock it in?
Do it.
Five seconds left.
Locking it in.
Do it.
All right.
And you got it, Brent.
Nice.
Thank you, West.
Nicely done.
I think they're even here in Washington.
So watch out.
Now you're on a roll, Brent.
You've just secured 1,000 SATs.
You get these right.
I think we're going to do 2,000 if you can get to a million.
Here we go.
All right.
Weston Bernstrand is a 1981 book, the breaks of the game is an account of a team in what
professional sport league?
Okay.
So David's book in 1981, the breaks of the game is an account of a team in what professional
sport league?
In the NBA, the NHL, MLB, or the NFL?
You can ask the Mubaroo.
Maybe the Mubaroo.
Please help me.
We've got a freebie here for Brent.
This will be the moment.
We've got, what, 18 seconds?
I feel like Brent should get a translation of what those league names are to the sports.
MLB, Major League Baseball, NBA is basketball.
Breaks of the game.
Eight seconds.
I'm going to say...
You take it, Chris.
Oh, no.
I don't want to do it.
Do it.
Okay.
Here we go.
A.
Unbelievable.
Oh, no way.
Well done.
Wow.
All right.
Moving on.
I don't even know what A was.
For $125,000, which of these substances contain no carbon atoms, dynamite, sugar, rust, or
grain alcohol?
No carbon atoms.
Dynamite, sugar, rust, or grain alcohol?
What was C again?
Rust.
25 seconds.
I'm getting conflicting answers from...
Chat room.
You've got 15 seconds.
Yeah, rust is...
Well, since we love rust so much...
Let's do it.
I think we're going to go with rust.
Oh, my gosh.
Can you handle that?
Let's do it.
Oh, my God.
Two in a row.
Unbelievable.
I think this game is rigged, but I can't quite tell, but I'm okay with it.
For $250,000, who was featured in the 1998 Time Magazine cover with the headline, Is
Feminism Dead?
Martha Stewart, Callista Flockhart, Pamela Anderson-Lee, or the Spice Girls?
1998.
Time Magazine.
Is Feminism Dead?
Martha Stewart, Callista Flockhart, Pamela Anderson-Lee, or the Spice Girls?
Martha Stewart had that big hoopla back then.
She did, yeah.
So I'm going with her.
I think that's a pretty good guess.
She was in the news a lot.
Yeah, it was a big deal.
She went to jail.
She did.
That was crushing.
For stuff that the banks would later do just as a matter of practice and totally not get
in trouble.
Well, I mean, she led the stage.
All right.
So A, final answer?
Yeah, go for it.
All right.
Logging it in.
Oh, no.
No.
Oh, Brantley.
I'm so sorry.
What was the answer?
It was B, but I didn't actually see what it was.
I don't know if anybody caught it.
Callista Flockhart.
Oh, it was Callista Flockhart.
I don't know anything about Callista Flockhart.
Who played Ally McBeal, which is apparently what this image is referring to.
Yeah, okay.
Wow.
You still got a thousand sets, though.
Okay.
But my heart is still sunk in my chest.
Yeah.
Well, 2,000 is better than 1,000.
All right.
Yeah.
Does anybody else want to play?
That was fun.
Thank you.
Mr. Wimpress, would you like to play The Millionaire before we wrap it up?
I think, culturally, I'm going to struggle.
I'll join the club.
It's true.
But you know what?
You are a worldly man, so you may have a better shot than, say, myself, for example.
No, I'll pass.
Thank you for the offer, though.
That's fine.
That's absolutely fine.
Make Wes do it.
Come on.
Yeah, we got to work on Wes.
Wes, you want to do it?
Sure.
Okay.
Well, we'll flip it around, Wes.
And you can phone a Brent if the situation comes up.
Does that sound fair?
Oh, all right.
All right, yeah.
All right, let's do this thing.
Welcome into the show, Wes, a Seattle native, or at least a Washington native now based
in the Seattle area.
You doing good today, Wes?
You got any friends or family watching?
No, they all don't think I could make it here, but I'm going to prove them wrong today.
All right, Wes.
Well, let's kick it off.
Which of these words is often used to describe a very successful movie?
A flamethrower, a blockbuster, a Smash Mouth, or a water world?
This is way easier than your first one, right?
I love the idea that it's a water world.
I know, me too.
Well, water world was one of them, I think.
Water world is historically a financial failure, and yet it's a movie I actually enjoy.
I thought there were some cool ideas in there.
That's true.
Blockbuster.
Final answer.
All right.
B. Blockbuster.
Final answer.
Checking the computer.
Yeah.
Yeah, you got that one right, Wes.
I know, right?
Okay.
For $200, if you want someone to stop bothering you, you might ask them to get off your what?
Your sidebar?
Your brief?
Your case?
Or your closing argument?
You want them to get off your what?
A sidebar, a brief, a case, closing argument.
Let's go with case, although, I mean, there's a lot of good options here.
Yeah, I like them all for some reason.
All right, we're doing C, case, and survey says...
Yeah, that's right, Wes.
Okay, here we go.
I'm gonna start saying get off my sidebar, though, so, I mean, it might not work, but
they'll at least be confused for a moment.
Can you just get off my closing argument, please?
How come lawn wasn't part of the options?
I know!
That's what I was expecting.
That's why I started laughing when I read it first.
Okay, Wes, according to a popular phrase, a person who achieves success through others
is riding their what?
A, coattails, B, rickshaw, C, golden goose, or D, sidecar?
Oh, man, rickshaw is a fantastic answer, but no, coattails.
You sure?
I mean, I feel like I've heard a lot of people say that guy's just riding his golden goose.
Yeah.
All right, coattails, locking it in, and we'll see what the computer says.
You got it, Wes, and now we're at $500.
You're one away from a thousand sats.
Which of these terms best describes money set aside to use for improper purposes, like
we're doing right now?
For improper purposes, pension, slush fund, net worth, or margin account?
Okay, well, there's a lot to unpack in margin account and how you want to judge things with
improper there, I think.
But slush fund.
All right, final answer?
Final answer.
Okay, locking it in.
All right, Wes, very nice.
This one gets you the sats.
The plumage of an adult male cardinal is predominantly what color?
Blue, red, yellow, or orange?
The foliage of an adult male cardinal is predominantly what color?
Let's go with red.
All right.
Final answer.
You feeling good?
I like that.
I'm feeling good.
It's an attention catching color, right?
Yeah.
I mean, who wouldn't want to be bright red?
Right.
Locking it in.
There's no bird cops out there to pull you over.
Oh, you got it, Wes.
That means you get the sats.
You get the sats.
I would like to officially donate my sats to the Brent cause.
Whoa.
Wow.
Such a generous gentleman.
All right, Wes, the capital of Nevada is named after whom?
Jedediah Smith?
Kit Carson?
Jesse Lee Reno?
John C. Fremont?
The capital of Nevada?
I feel like Wimpy would know this one.
It's true.
The Mumble Room can always jump in.
You also have a couple of lifelines here.
You got the 50-50.
You got the poll the audience, and you got the call of Brent.
I'm going to go with Kit Carson.
Kit Carson.
I love it.
Makes sense.
Let's lock that sucker in.
B, final answer, and survey says.
I think you knew that one, Wes.
I did.
I mean, I don't know why I know that.
That is close enough, I guess.
Yeah.
You know, they try to get you with that Reno one.
That's true.
Tricky, tricky.
That was.
All right.
For $4,000, which of the following is a common symptom of cerebriolic dermatitis?
I'm sure you know what this is, right?
Baldness, gray hair, split ends, or dandruff?
Okay.
It's something to do with the head, it seems.
So it's cerebriolic.
How do you say that?
Cerebriolic.
Thank you.
Dermatitis.
Cerebriolic.
Is it balding?
Is it gray hair?
Is it split ends?
Is it dandruff?
Let's go with the 50-50.
All right.
Eliminating two wrong answers.
And what you have left now, Wes, split ends or dandruff, 17 seconds.
Let's go with dandruff.
All right.
Here we go.
It was tense.
You got it, Wes.
Nicely done.
That was a blind guess.
I'll be honest.
All right.
Now for $8,000.
Thank you, PixelPimp.
I'm impressed.
Okay.
For $8,000, by definition, which of the following might be portrayed in a still life painting?
A bicycle race, a fruit basket, a flowing river, or a singing choir in a still life
painting, Wes?
I'm going to phone Brent.
Make sure you have his Canadian line, though, right?
Yeah, we have to actually pay a little long distance for that, so I got to limit the length
of the call.
All right, Brent, you've got 28 seconds.
You probably heard the question.
By definition, which of the following might be portrayed in a still life painting?
A bicycle race, a fruit basket, a flowing river, or a singing choir.
You've got about 15 seconds.
Well, I know of still life photographs that they're generally inanimate, and all those
other activities seem pretty animate.
So I'm going to say fruit basket.
Yeah, I was thinking fruit basket, right?
I mean, there's stuff going on down there, but we just-
All right, I'm locking it in.
You're out of time.
Yeah.
You got it!
Thank you, Brent.
You're welcome.
Nicely done.
I am really impressed, you guys.
All right, for $16,000, what shape's volume is calculated by multiplying the area of the
base by the height and then dividing by three a hemisphere, a cube, cylinder, or a pyramid?
So a shape's volume is calculated by multiplying the area of the base by the height and dividing
by three.
30 seconds.
Hemisphere, cube, cylinder.
What lifelines do I have?
You've got an audience poll.
Yeah, let's do the poll, all right?
We're doing the audience poll, and okay, we're getting numbers in right now.
The audience is voting D by 44%, which is pyramid.
Which is pyramid.
Okay, and then what was the formula again?
By multiplying the area of the base by the height by dividing by three.
Five seconds.
Okay, yeah, let's trust the poll here.
Let's go with pyramid.
Okay.
The automatic pilot system is not functional.
Is it going?
Uh-oh.
It seems stuck.
It does seem stuck.
I don't know if it's going to take your...
Maybe that means...
Oh, I think we lost internet.
That's what that means.
Now we have to wait to find out.
Oh, Chris!
Oh, it worked, you got it!
Oh, nicely done.
There was a disconnect, but you got it.
I can't even believe it, to tell you the truth.
You got it.
You got that last one, but an internet interruption reset our progress.
But I feel like you were probably going to win.
I mean, I don't know.
I think so.
And you know what?
I think something just released that's a present for everyone listening at home too.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, yeah, right.
We should probably wrap it up.
All right, let's wrap it up.
Let's wrap it up for the day.
Good job, Wes.
Good job, gentlemen.
I couldn't have done it without the Mumble Room, without Brent.
Same.
I mean...
And Brent needs to find out what he's won today.
Brent, you need to figure out...
Let's see.
So let's see.
Why don't you do the math?
You tell me.
You tell me what 2000 SATs is.
Well, you can ask Google.
Google.
Google will tell you.
You have to do a little math.
So first find the volume of the pyramid and then find out.
Divide by three, is it?
All right, I want everybody to head over to extras.show right now because we just released...
Yep.
Extras.show.80.
We just released a really fun one-off episode that Brent and I just recorded.
And it turns out, surprise, we were recording during the entire road trip to Denver and
we had a whole mountain of audio.
We still have more, actually.
Is this like that Beatles movie?
Turns out.
It's the behind the scenes stuff that we captured and we played some of it in the road trip
memories episode, which just released on extras.show and there'll be more.
There'll be one on Thursday too, I think, is when the next one comes out.
So go over there and check it out.
I feel like we wanted to have a clip for you guys, but then we didn't really know.
We didn't want to.
We didn't want to spoil it.
We both thought of the same clip at the same moment and then we thought, no, no, that's
the...
Yeah, we didn't want to spoil it for you guys.
So go over to extras.show and grab that.
And that's it.
Thank you for being here today.
I think that was fun.
That's all we had planned and I feel like we've accomplished it.
So podcast out.