Well, hi, everyone. Welcome to Brunch with Brent. I'm so pleased to be joined today by
Nuritzi Sanchez. Nuritzi, how you doing?
Hello. I am doing really well because I am in sunny California and it is a beautiful
day here today.
Nice. I will admit that I'm in Northern Ontario and we're supposed to get a lot of snow. So
a little bit of maybe the opposite, but I'll be thinking of you.
That sounds nice too.
Well, that's the thing though, right? Is I think it's all about attitude and I've kind
of taken that approach to weather in the last several years and it changes everything. So
glad to hear you mention that. Nuritzi, you are now kind of a new thing for you, but a
senior open source program manager at GitLab. Is that right?
Yeah. I just joined at the beginning of this month and I'm really excited to be part of
this team helping to really get more open source projects to join GitLab by helping
them solve any issues that they have, helping them with the migration process, all of that.
So I love GitLab and I love open source and so it's the perfect thing for me.
What a nice match when you can combine a lot of things that you love and we will get into
that when we dive a little bit into your history. But I would imagine being a month into GitLab,
you're still kind of learning the ropes and getting to meet people and all of that stuff.
Has that been sort of nice getting to meet the people behind it?
Yeah. It's the first time that I've been part also of an all remote company and I think
that I was a little hesitant about it at first because I love meeting people and having those
hallway conversations, coffee breaks out. But GitLab has an amazing all remote culture
and so I've just been scheduling lots and lots of coffee chats with people, getting
to know as many as possible and yeah, it has been great so far.
Good for you. I actually love that term of remote culture. I admit that I haven't heard
it before and that seems kind of silly considering I have my own remote culture considering I'm
self-employed and all that stuff. But it seems to me like maybe that's what makes remote
work successful or not, is having the tools and having the people. But also, you mentioned
just scheduling coffee chats and that sounds like, even though maybe on the outside it
seems not relevant to getting work done, I would imagine it's actually extremely important.
Yeah, it is. One of the things that GitLab does that's very different from other companies
that I've been a part of is that mindset of being handbook first and so they have very
detailed documentation of everything, which is really good for that asynchronous sharing
of knowledge. But it's one thing to look at a page and another thing to really meet the
people behind it and so as you said, it's really important to have those relationships
with the people behind it and really knowing who to go to and learning all of the little
tips and tricks that you just can't find on a sheet of paper. So yeah, big fan of coffee
chats. Yeah.
You mentioned documentation in there and I just want to quickly say that it's actually
been a theme that has happened throughout the conversations I've had here on brunch
and I didn't expect that at first. Like for instance, the conversation I had recently
with Heather Elsworth, she's a huge fan of documentation and how useful that is but you're
describing it sort of useful internally as well, which I love, but you're absolutely
right like maybe that's the first step but having that human connection is almost the
necessary second step and the deeper dive into understanding anything. So I really,
I love that idea of those scheduled coffee chats. I mean, I know you're kind of new with
the one month thing but could you give us a little bit more of an understanding of what
a senior open source program manager does on a daily basis? Have you figured that out
yet?
Right. I'm in the process. But the first thing is that the program was set up because GitLab
is an open core organization and a big part of just the culture there is to give back
to the open source community. And so they've tried to foster this in different ways and
one way was by providing open source projects with access to their premium levels for free.
And then also that's the enterprise edition. And then they have a community edition that
is fully free software. The enterprise edition you can do either like GitLab.com or your
self-hosted instance and it has some proprietary software there too. But the community edition
is completely open source so it's great for projects that are very concerned about the
free software side of things or just follow further along that spectrum. And so what I
am supposed to be doing is helping to really grow that program because so far it's been
very reactive and we have our internal processes set up to handle these requests and to start
to assist large organizations like GNOME and KDE and Debian has also been one. There's
still a lot of room for improvement and it's my job to really go in and analyze the current
program and start to fix little bits and pieces that could be fixed and really to start doing
more of that outreach and letting people know that the program even exists. And that is
my bread and butter. I love doing that stuff. I love going in and finding challenges that
need to be solved and then talking to lots of different people to figure out who I need
to go to. Also, the other thing that was really interesting about this is that everybody at
GitLab seems to be new because they've just experienced so much growth in the last two
years. A few people have said they were there about a year and a half ago when it was about
250 people and it's now 1,200. And so there's this joke that you're there in the room or
like, you know, the video chat room with people that are new to GitLab, newer to GitLab and
newest to GitLab. So it is fun. It's awesome. But yeah, I never feel like out of place is
the new person because everybody is like that.
Well, that's actually really nice. I would imagine too that there's quite a bit of like
great energy considering that people are new. I know oftentimes that newness is actually
a really great feature.
Yes, exactly. It's really, really awesome to be at a company with people from all sorts
of different backgrounds. Some people haven't really been part of the open source world
or haven't been part of the dev ops tools world. And, you know, they bring in their
own expertise. I love thinking about diversity in all its forms and you do see lots of different
types of thought diversity. And again, it's my first one there and I've already heard
that there are ways that GitLab are trying to continue to constantly like build out other
types of diversity or just in general like be a more diverse organization. But my experience
so far has been really awesome with that. And it comes from, as you say, like a bunch
of new people coming in from different areas and, you know, working on this common product.
That sounds really amazing as an environment to try to do some of your best work. I heard
you there earlier get a little bit excited about the people aspect of things when you
were describing it. I would imagine that's actually a lot of fun too because it sounds
like you're kind of reaching into a whole bunch of different communities. How's that
been?
I haven't done as much community work at GitLab yet because I'm first focusing on kind of
like the infrastructure part. So right now, when I was talking about, you know, talking
to lots of different people, it was all internally. And this comes along with trying to streamline
the processes better. I have to, you know, better understand the different teams that
will touch my project or that would be interested in my project and find ways for us to better
collaborate. And an example, like a tangible example of this is that the way like we really
dog food our project. And so all of my organization for my program, which is I love dog fooding
things. I do it. It's great to like, I actually don't know. I don't know what that means.
But dog fooding is basically other people also refer to it as like we drink our own
wine. So it's basically eating your own. I can't explain it. Okay. I know the term.
It means you use your own products, but why is it dog fooding? Maybe a follow-up question
for me the next time.
We can go with it. I still really like it.
Yeah. So anyway, the point is that I use GitLab for my daily work and this is great because
I'm not an engineer. And so it's a tool that can really be used by lots of different people.
And that was actually part of the reason why I was so excited about it in the first place
is that I've tried all sorts of different tools and this is the one where I could see
lots of different teams actually using. And so back to my tangible example, I have a label
called open source that I work with, but it was only part of the community relations project.
And so I'm now promoting it to like the top level so that everybody can use it within
the organization. And this is my way to start to really be able to promote the work that
I'm doing internally so that people know to come to me when they need help or just in
general to get more awareness about the program that I'm building.
Keep the dog food flowing. Now, when you describe that you have a chance to use GitLab for yourself,
what for you are sort of the features that really stand out in your current workflow?
Because I would imagine, you know, some of us listening don't necessarily have experience
with GitLab yet, especially in a non sort of developer capacity. So what is it about
you that really grabs you about it using it on a daily basis?
I think that in the roles that I've been, I have had to work with engineers, sometimes
very heavily, sometimes not as heavily at Endless, which I'm sure I'll talk about later.
Yes, please.
A lot of it was working with engineers to develop like applications or to create like
a beta testing program or, you know, various initiatives that required a lot of direct
work with engineers. And I worked very cross functionally. So at Endless, we decided to
actually go with Fabricator, which is another project management tool. And we tried to show
it to the design team. They like ran away crying. And that's not to say that Fabricator
isn't a lovely tool. It's just that the interface of it is not as easy to use, or it's not as
intuitive and it's not as beautiful as some of the other tools that we were evaluating.
And so when we went with Fabricator for like utility at Endless, our design team was just,
you know, not super pleased. You know, eventually they were able to adopt it and everything.
But I think that at GitLab, Gnome was one of the first like big projects to migrate
over to using GitLab. And that was partly just to consolidate their tools and use a
single platform as part of the newcomer story so that people didn't have to start signing
up for all sorts of different tools. And again, part of it was like that ease of use and being
able to attract a lot of newcomers. And I just, I fell in love with the product because
it was usable and it had all the same functionality. When you asked about like specific features,
the Kanban boards and labels, milestones, or like being able to set dates and assign
tasks to people, all of the same things that I had liked about things like Trello or Basecamp
or Asana. In my mind, those are some of the more like user-friendly project management
ones that aren't as commonly used for engineering teams. And so I just really saw GitLab as
something that provided a little bit of something for everybody. At Gnome, my focus was on that
engagement team and helping to grow the community and to also evangelize for other skill sets
and you know, like just in general diversity. I kind of mentioned that as a theme that I'm
really interested in. And I saw it as, you know, a tool that people could start using
even if they weren't very familiar with engineering tools and practices. And even if somebody
joined the engagement team just to do marketing type work, they could start to get familiar
with the tool and then build that confidence so that if they then wanted to start dabbling
in some of the more like, you know, either documentation or some more like code contribution
type work, then they were at least familiar with the tool and could, you know, transition
more easily to that. So those are, I guess, the reasons why I get excited about it.
A great many good reasons. Thank you for sharing that. It sounds super powerful. I admit I
don't have experience with it, but now I'm itching to get some. So that's a good side.
Yeah, it's really pretty. You mentioned in there some of your experience working with
the Gnome team. And I know you've been quite involved there. Can you walk us through that?
Sure. So I first got involved through my work at Endless. And just kind of quick background
on that Endless is a company that was started back in 2012. I was one of the people who
helped start it. And we at Endless, we were building a Linux based desktop. We first launched
on our own hardware. But Endless was designed to reach people who didn't have great internet
connection, perhaps no internet connection, or were new to computers. And so we're really
all about simplifying the Linux desktop experience to make it easy for your grandmother to use,
you know, or anybody like your two year old daughter, anybody. And so we started to, you
know, really contribute upstream. We were a Gnome based desktop. And so we were contributing
very heavily upstream to Gnome. And I was invited to one of the initial, one of the
annual conferences. It was in Sweden. I was super excited to go to Sweden.
Lucky you.
Yes. And I got to speak about, you know, some of the ways that we had changed the designer
when designing for our audience considerations that you had to have. And so, you know, I
first of all loved the atmosphere of the community. They were all very welcoming, very, you know,
I didn't feel like an outsider.
That is so important too, right? Because if you're trying to make any change or recommendations
or trying to collaborate with anyone, that is a necessity to be sort of welcomed with
open arms and to be, yeah, collaborative. So that is very good to hear.
Yeah. I think especially, I had never been to an open source conference before. As I
said, I'm not an engineer. And so I had a lot of, not hesitation, but I just wasn't
sure how I would be received as a non-engineer at this conference. Most of my colleagues
going were all engineers and had been part of the open source world. So here I was like,
I'm a non-engineer, new to open source, let's do this. And it was great. Like people were
so nice and they were, you know, willing to explain things to me. And I just, I got really
excited about it. And you know, the whole thing is that when I first started learning
about open source software and really helping to figure out which applications to pre-install
on EndlessOS, I was one amazed by how many awesome applications there were available.
I had no idea coming from like a Windows and Mac background that the Linux application
ecosystem even existed. So I was like, wow, I don't have to pay for Photoshop. This is
great. Like let's do GIMP and Inkscape.
It's an enabler, isn't it? Right. And for Endless, that's the whole idea is to enable
creativity and access and all of that stuff. So what a beautiful thing.
Exactly. And while I was so excited about like the practicality of all these applications,
I was a little less excited about how they looked and they felt. And you've already kind
of heard me get excited about how pretty GitLab is. Like this is a reoccurring theme in my
life is that I like beautiful things. And I, you know, I'm all about experiences too.
Like when I really value experiences. And so it's like, at Endless, I think they said
like pixels don't cost anything. So like, let's make this really luxurious and let's
make it feel super high quality so that our users, even if they can't afford, you know,
luxury items, you know, they feel like this is a luxury item. And that's really what I
wanted. You know, like I care a lot about the usability and the experience. And I felt
so hopeful for how the Linux application ecosystem could keep evolving to have that in mind.
And for that, that's why I got really excited about the diversity, diversity of thought,
diversity of like lots of different aspects. So that, you know, you could really create
software that was not only functional, but a delight to use. And so that's how I sort
of got plugged into the GNOME community. At the time, the engagement team was just a few
people. And so really was excited about joining that and helping to grow the team and start
advocating for like hearing more about our brand and marketing and outreach and building
a community, all of that stuff. And I guess they found it valuable. I was asked to run
for the board of directors.
Wow.
Yeah. And I ended up serving three terms. And during that time, when I first joined,
we didn't have an executive director. So I helped with that hiring process. And a lot
of my strength is in project management and really driving things forward. So I was able
to bring that in. And then, you know, we went through the whole restructuring of our organization,
because as we started to care more about the newcomers experience and about, you know,
like really caring about our community. And actually for us, the move to GitLab was a
huge part of that because it was, you know, completely changing our tools to be more modern
and, you know, easy for newcomers to join. That's when we started getting more donations
and more, like, publicity. And there were a lot of, like, little things and big things
that happened. Ubuntu changed to, came back to us as having GNOME as the default. And
we ended up having, you know, more newcomers join. And it was just a very, like, momentous
period for us. And during all that time, we had to change a lot of the way that the foundation
was running, because we went from having one employee to having seven employees. And for
us, that was a historical record. We'd never hired anyone outside of our director of operations
and executive director full time. And so now we're able to, you know, help not only keep
the GNOME community healthy, but start dreaming even bigger than we ever have before. And
yeah, it's been an exciting time.
It sounds exciting. You must feel, you know, I'm going back to your describing sort of
that, that feeling of showing up at that very first conference and not really knowing if
you're going to sort of fit in. And then, you know, fast forward to that moment you
just described as as being, you know, helping to form what is really an exciting time for
the GNOME community and the foundation. And it sounds like those have really been catalysts
to a lot of positive change in many communities around. So that must be must feel really good
for you to be a part of that.
Yeah, definitely. And I'm always amazed at, you know, again, going back to kind of experience
it at events. I see events as like the lifeblood of a lot of open source communities because
it's the time when, you know, you get your core members together to work on things or
it's a place to draw in newcomers and to really have that in person touch point that will
carry on throughout the year when you're all remote. And, and yeah, I just think that it's
something that sometimes people don't value as much, but there's so much value in creating
awesome events and experiences for people. And it's something that, you know, in addition
to all my other interests, I feel really excited about.
You're a multifaceted human being. That's a good thing.
Yeah. I get pulled into lots of projects.
Well, you probably allow yourself to, it sounds like you, you, you jump in full swing. And
so maybe that's a really nice segue then into your efforts with the Libre application summit.
It sounds like that brings together a lot of your efforts all into one place. And I'm
actually admit to not being that familiar with what happens on the ground at the Libre
application summit. So what's it like there? How are you involved? What are the people
like? I'm sure they're amazing, but give us a sense of it.
We started the, we used to call it loss gnome. And that was when it was Libre application
summit as a way to really move forward the experience behind Linux applications. And
we had a couple of iterations of that, and then KDE expressed an interest in also participating
in the organization of it. And, you know, it was something that to me was made a lot
of sense where, you know, we're only going to be able to move the dial on this if we're
working together strategically and, you know, able to provide big organizations with sort
of a united front where we say like, these are the options. And we were really seen as
a collaborative community as opposed to, you know, like each doing their own thing and
having a lot of segmentation.
Yeah, it sounds like breaking down some of those perceived sort of rivalries is really
beneficial, even if, you know, that's not the reality. But there's been a lot of sense
that, oh, these two camps can't collaborate. But that, I think, has been, at least from
my perspective, one of the greatest gifts that has come out of Libre application summit.
And you've described that as really meaningful, too.
Yes, exactly. I, you know, before really getting involved in the Libre application summit,
I, well, now, what I was going to say is that we rebranded to, instead of last GNOME, Libre
application summit hosted by GNOME, we rebranded to Linux app summit. And that's the more like
neutral version so that, you know, we can have both GNOME and KDE be the hosts and also,
you know, continue to evolve it. We're still not sure how far the evolution will go if
it'll become its own organization at some point or if it will continue to be co-hosted
by KDE and GNOME. There's still, you know, lots of room for growth and discussion. But
yeah, before my involvement with that, I didn't really know many KDE people. I think I knew
one from a conference, two from a conference in Brazil. And they were great, but they expressed
too that they were really interested in doing more with GNOME. And that sort of planted
the seed in my mind of, you know, I have to get to know more KDE people. I'd really like
to understand areas where we can collaborate. And this just naturally made sense. They were
incredible to work with. I worked very closely with Alish Pol, the current president, and
they were just so supportive and collaborative. And yeah, I think that because of them, we
were able to double attendance and to have much more of an outreach than we had in previous
years. So lots of great things.
That must feel amazing to be part of all of that. I'm sitting here just like jaw dropped
at how important that stuff is and bringing people together and just seeing what comes
out the other end when you combine some, you know, really some people doing some great
work all in the same room. What a gift. Can I ask you how it is that you ever came to
the tech world in the first place? Because it sounds to me like you have a big heart
for the sort of human aspect of it and organizing people and organizing projects. But how did
you come to tech in the beginning?
Yeah, that's a great question. Let's see, when I was younger, I thought I'd be a doctor,
obviously.
It's a good choice.
Yeah. Well, that was the thing is it was through a lot of exploration. Actually, in high school,
I interned at a hospital. Don't ask me why they let me in as a high schooler, but they
did. And it was at a children's hospital, at the Stanford Children's Hospital. And
my heart broke because I didn't like seeing children when they were sick. I wanted to
do something to prevent that. And that was sort of the reoccurring theme also within
the different internships or programs that I tried out where I also thought that I might
become a lawyer. And I interned at an immigration law clinic, and I just had so many stories
of heartbreaking stories of people battling through immigration stories. And it was something
where I didn't want to fight at that level. I wanted to fight at the higher level of like,
how can I prevent this from happening? Or how can I do a deeper level? I just felt kind
of helpless in that situation.
So anyway, I graduated with an international relations major and a minor in psychology.
And that still goes along with my interest in people all around the world. And growing
up in Silicon Valley, you're just surrounded by tech. And what I really love about it is
how it's almost like a superpower, where just a few people can create something that
can enormously impact other people's lives. And this is kind of an extreme and not the
best example, but the person who created Flappy Birds was used by so many people. And it's
just still like the core concept is that a person can create something that can touch
so many lives. And so that was really where I saw, okay, well, if I want to make a huge
impact on this world, I really do see tech as that tool of reaching people.
And I know there are social ramifications of technology. That was something that I was
really aware of also. But that was even more reason to join because I care about these
things. I care about cultural sensitivity and about making sure that you're not forcing
technology to people who are saying that it's better than their way of life. And so those
are the human aspects that I think should be infused in technology. Because after all,
technology is just a tool to help you improve your life. So I really see it in that lens.
It's a means for us to express ourselves, right?
Yeah.
That is actually, you know, the reason that I came to open source in the first place was
hitting pause on sort of my interest in the technical aspects, because that's easy for
me to get into the way my mind works. But then hitting pause and using my heart to say,
well, how does this change people's lives? And it sounds like you spent a lot of time
and effort and energy thinking about that throughout your years as well. And what amazing
things we can do when we use that as a guiding light, especially in the world of technology.
Yes. And what you say, how it draws you towards open source, I think that's been the biggest
kind of twist in my journey. I didn't know what open source was. And then now I find
myself really interested in it and having it be something that is really guiding my
path forward. And it has to do with what you said of really, you know, like the people
aspect of things. And something I didn't share about my background earlier is that
both of my parents are from Mexico. And I had grown up, you know, really like going
back and just seeing so many things that I wanted to fix there or help, you know, challenges
that I wanted to help solve. And it was as simple back then as my dad wanted to go visit
his mom and, you know, wanted to find the cheapest way to get there. And we knew that
there were buses, but there was no information online about bus schedules or train schedules
or anything. And so, you know, like having a simple website would have helped my dad,
but also probably lots of other people. And, you know, the cost of setting up a website
could be difficult or, you know, prohibitive for some people. And so now there are tools
to allow that. And there's obviously a difference between free software, free of cost software,
and free software in the philosophical sense of free to reuse, modify, do whatever you'd
like with it. You know, I think that the being able to do whatever you want with it is so
powerful because it really allows somebody to not have to do something from scratch,
but really build upon somebody else's work and to continue to focus on the problem as
opposed to have to deal with some of the more logistical effort in solving that challenge.
So anyway, I really have been drawn to the open source movement as a result of my family
background even, and just kind of the hopes and dreams that I have for making a difference
in the world.
Yeah, it sounds like it necessarily touches a deep place in you. And yet that's also the
place where you get a lot of your courage and a lot of your motivation to make those
differences. Do you feel like with your experience working in Endless and helping create what
Endless has become, do you feel like you've achieved that in some ways? Or do you feel
like you got to see that firsthand in some instances?
Yeah, you know, I was really involved in all steps of that. And so, you know, one of the
coolest things was going out into the field. We had this policy where they wanted everybody
in the company to go to our target markets and meet our users and really hear from them.
And that was so rewarding because you could see how people who normally shied away from
technology or didn't see how it could really benefit them, really see how it could be a
huge enabler. And, you know, for example, there was in Guatemala, one of the things
that is difficult is that children are being required to do homework and research things
on the internet. And because a lot of children in rural areas don't have internet connections
at home, they have to go to a computer lab or internet cafe and pay for that. But because
their parents aren't able to support the cost of sending five children to do reports at
internet cafes, sometimes they're unable to complete their homework. And then, you know,
they end up having to drop out of school. And so, having a computer that has a lot of
preloaded information and just had like the 80% of the most searched for articles for
that particular country preloaded and it had a lot of other resources, again, completely
available offline. And something as simple as that could really be a game changer and
help people, you know, be able to continue to go to school. So, I saw lots of these different
stories and, you know, ways that our technology was really impacting people's lives. And when
you ask me, you know, did we accomplish everything? I think I always in all that I do, I really
try to have both a micro and macro level of impact where I really try to do things immediately
for my family, for my friends. But then I also like to dream big and think about the
billions of people, how can I serve there? And, you know, so for those instances, like
I saw some real impact even there. However, we really hit some challenges when we were
trying to expand. I think that our business model didn't completely work and we had to
shift to try to, you know, find ways to gain traction in different countries. And we just
were hit again and again with how, you know, especially Microsoft is really good at business
development. And we often found that if we had started up, you know, to talk to a government
or something like that, then, oh, actually our project got canceled and oh, something
with Microsoft happened. And not to say that, you know, there was any shady business or
anything, but it just shows that they are a huge player and they're doing something
right where they're really going out and spending, like they have the network there to really
continue to grow. And for a small company that was, you know, trying to also get more
people to see the value in LibreOffice as opposed to Microsoft Office, it was tough.
And it just, unfortunately, we weren't able to do as much globally as we wanted to. So
the company shifted to focus on the hack computer, which is to, it's still endless OS, but it's
now more designed to help children learn more about open source software and to start programming.
It's like a really cool game where they can start to, it's a game, but it ends up helping
them modify applications within their own computer. And it's just, it's really cool.
And so, you know, shifted strategy to really help the next generation see the benefits
of open source software, which I think is still a really awesome thing to do. But yeah,
so when you ask again about, like, did I reach the goals that I wanted to with Endless, I
would say my goal in touching people's lives, definitely. And I would have, you know, I
wish that it had been wildly successful in the global outreach part. So.
Well, and that's the thing, like that is a massive hope to reach, you know, very large
groups of people and make a difference in the world. Just that word, you know, that's
trying to reach more than just your neighbors, right? And so to have that sort of as your
horizon allows you to accomplish some really amazing things while you're doing the work.
But so I don't think you should necessarily be too hard on yourself because it sounds
like you made some really profound impacts on even a few individuals that you had experience
with. But it seems to me like, you know, I heard years ago about Endless OS. And so even
someone like me who was reading about it because I cared about some of these same topics, just
knowing that Endless was out there doing some of that important work feels like a real success
overall.
And I think that the lasting impact, too, is our contributions upstream to GNOME and
just in the various technologies that we touched, really advocating for making it really user-friendly
for reaching an audience beyond just, you know, engineers or technical users and really
pushing that upstream in a, you know, community that I think had predominantly technical users
or basically faced that type of an audience.
So I'm really happy to see some of those changes. I think one big thing was Flatpak and FlatHub
really having like a store, a place where people could go to find applications in one
single area. We were, of course, not the only ones that contributed to that. In fact, it
was led by others, but we contributed heavily towards that and shared our knowledge of,
you know, usability testing and all that kind of stuff to help improve it and make it really
usable. So, yeah, lasting contributions.
They sound quite lasting. And those are the kind of things that just kind of inform the
future. I know you're using Endless OS for some of your daily work as well. Is that right?
Yeah, I still use it as my personal computer. I just I love how simple it is to use. It's
something that I can, you know, show any of my friends and family and have them instantly
be like, oh, cool, like that makes sense. So, yeah.
And so would you say, you know, for those listening, is it approachable by anyone, even
if it was designed maybe for a specific purpose? But it sounds like the design energy that
went into it was to try to just make it friendly for humans, period. Do you feel like that's
true?
Yes, definitely. And I think that one of the big things is that it uses OSTree, which basically
makes the updating process really easy. Again, I can't delve into the technical details behind
all of this. But one of the things that initially kind of scared me from Linux in general was
having to deal with command line to do anything.
Yeah, that's a fairly common fear, right?
Yes. So, you know, even just that was a huge one for us. And it's something that, you know,
in certain cases, like we've seen a lot of people who want to bring open source software
to schools or to communities that would benefit from the technology. And it's just something
that they can leave there and not worry about people like breaking or, you know, like not
being able to update. And it's just super easy. And this makes me think about like the
adoption process. And we're often compared to one laptop per child. And one of the things
that we learned from that project is that if you bring technology to a new area and
you don't teach the teachers to use it, oftentimes the technology will fail because the teachers
don't know how to use it. And so they don't necessarily encourage the students to use
them or, you know, they might even not use the technology because it's embarrassing or
any other reason. And so one of the things that we tried to do when we were trying to
get more people to use it was to also invest in the training programs. But we found that
it was already really easy for people to use, but it was more so about like helping people
understand the utility of using a computer because sometimes they didn't even like think
that it was relevant to them. So that was really fascinating for me.
Nouritze, is there a question that you would put to our audience? Or it doesn't even need
to be a question. It could be something you'd like them to go see or something you want
them to experience or think about even.
I would just say that, you know, there's so much buzz around diversity and inclusion.
And I know that people have different thoughts and feelings about this. Overall, people seem
to agree that diversity is important. However, you know, there are people who are not as
enthusiastic about the methods to reach this. What I would like to stress is that it's about
experiences and how you make people feel and about really trying to connect with others
and understand other people's perspectives. And I think that if we keep that in mind,
that's really what's going to help us create better products. And that will sort of naturally
lead to diversity and inclusion. That's not to say that we shouldn't put an effort into
programs that will help foster that. But just as we're creating these programs to really
think about that experience that people are having. And so, you know, we all care about
technology. And I think that if we keep in mind that human-centered focus, that that's
really where we're going to create magic.
I like magic.
I do, too. I'm a huge fan.
If people wanted to connect with you, then where would they reach you?
I have lots of different ways to be contacted. But my personal email is probably the best
way to go because the Magnum one's having a little bit of problems these days. I can't
send mail from it. So, yeah, it's nuritsi s at gmail.com. My name is really difficult.
So N as in Nancy, U, R, I, T as in Tom, Z as in Zebra, I, S as in Sam at gmail.com.
And I'm also on Telegram as Nuritsi, my first name.
That's great. I'm sure that'll be plenty for ways for people to connect. So thank you.
Yeah, I want to also say thanks for connecting with me. We've had a lot of fun during this
chat. And I hope we can get connected in the future, too.
Thank you so much for having me. It's always a pleasure speaking with you, Brent. So thank
you.
Thank you for your time and for giggling with me and all of those great things. So we'll
chat again soon.
Sounds great.