It's Office Hours, with Chris.
That's me, Office Hours, welcome in.
Hey everybody, welcome to a new thing I just made up.
It's called Office Hours with Chris, where I thought I'd answer questions and read emails.
And since I never told anybody I was doing this, I just had to pick some random emails
to start with.
And that's how, what I'm going to guess is Vekko, Vekko, Vekko, I'm going with Vekko.
That's how Vekko got into the show here.
He writes about the enthusiast trap.
And keep in mind the context of a couple of weeks ago as I record this.
There was a big hoopla around Mangero bundling free office in place of libre office.
And so that's the context for this email.
And of course I should say, Vekko, welcome, welcome into the office.
I'm glad you're here.
Anyways, he writes, I recently heard of a name for the phenomenon that is happening
with the Mangero community.
It's called the enthusiast trap.
I first heard about it from a video by LowSpecGamer.
I will put a link to that video in the show notes so you can see the whole thing.
But the TLDR is the enthusiast market is very small, very demanding, and the least loyal
of them all.
I'm going to pause here for a second.
The loyalty thing struck me when I first read this, but then I think about it.
One of the number one kind of reactions on the negative side of Mangero bundling free
office, one of the number one go to responses was, well, that's it, I'm leaving.
Which distro should I switch to next?
Boom.
All that loyalty gone.
So I actually, at first I read that and I kind of didn't like the way that felt.
But then I thought about it and he's right.
Like the enthusiast markets educated, they're capable of shifting to a different product.
And so they'll take advantage of that capability.
He says, and for a company to grow, it will eventually need to abandon these enthusiasts
to appeal to a more mainstream audience.
This of course will then upset the enthusiasts who are very aware and they are demanding.
And as we can demonstrate non loyal customers, which will jump ship very quickly, the enthusiasts
can't really be blamed for being upset either since they probably did a lot of the free
marketing for that company or like in the case of a Linux distribution for that distribution.
Even some more demanding work like reporting bugs or fixing bugs and submitting patches
or doing tech support in the community.
And they do have a legitimate claim to that time.
He goes on to say, in hindsight, this applies to a lot of things that seem to happen in
the Linux community.
Love the shows by the way.
Well, thank you, Vecho.
Hopefully I'm getting somewhere near, well, I guess it doesn't really matter.
That's just how it's going to be pronounced because you're not here to correct me.
You're in my office, but it's my rules.
All right.
I love your, I love your finding here.
And it's interesting to watch the LowSpecGamer video, which was really more about why some
of the founders of Oculus are leaving and be able to drive sort of insights into your
local community.
And that's actually a pretty powerful tool because humans be humans everywhere.
And there's a lot of that in every group.
And I think we sometimes get really hard on ourselves because we think Linux users are
so bad.
It's enthusiast.
It's tribalism, not such a loaded term, but it's people that want to signal what kind
of ideals that they have and hold.
And they're looking for other people that hold those same ideas and signals because
it's a way to determine safety.
It's a way to determine common values so they're more likely somebody you can trust.
It's instinctual.
It's necessary for human survival.
And without it, we wouldn't be able to have an economy.
You wouldn't be able to have a market system.
So it's, I don't know how to solve the problem other than trying to talk about it in a way
that is both open and understanding, but doesn't really encourage it.
I've really been trying to take on this mantra of, you know, this type of Linux doesn't work
for me, but that doesn't mean it doesn't work for you.
An example is Gnome Shell.
For a long, long time, you know, just Gnome Shell hasn't really worked well for me.
But somehow the project continues on with more and more users all the time.
So what should I take away from that?
That Gnome Shell is crap and garbage and should be completely redone?
Or that perhaps it just doesn't work perfectly for me?
And that there are tools that work better for me, just like Gnome Shell is a tool that
works better for others.
And I think we just have to start encouraging that kind of conversation and it'll catch
on.
That's something we try to do through the shows.
I don't know if it is catching on.
It seems like people are becoming more aware of it.
And it's definitely like by these emails, it seems like the awareness is increasing
in the audience.
And I agree.
The enthusiast trap is a really tricky thing for companies to deal with because you do
have to start to appeal to a broader audience if you want to grow beyond a certain niche.
Or you have to determine that you can sustain a business in that niche and you're happy
with it.
But that doesn't happen a lot.
I mean, you look at Apple, for example.
When the iPhone was exploding, they really had a hard time paying attention to the needs
of their Mac users, especially the professional Mac users.
And now, as the iPhone is becoming about 40% of their business and the other elements of
their business are making up the slack, all of a sudden the Mac is becoming more important
again.
And now you're starting to see things like the Mac Pro, the iMac Pro, the refreshed Mac
Mini, and the new rumored MacBook Pro.
Plus on top of that though, which I think is even more of a signal from Apple, is their
top executives like Craig Federighi and Phil Schiller are going on enthusiast podcasts.
They're going on those guys' shows.
That's like talking directly to the enthusiast market now.
They've gone from ignoring the enthusiast market to building hardware for them and going
on platforms in which they tune into.
And I think that is sort of a re... you can see in these last two years.
I think it's kind of neat to watch, especially from afar because I got no skin in the game
so I can go, look at this.
They're listening again.
They're putting decent hardware out again.
It's unbelievably expensive, but that's a different conversation.
And I think you see this realignment in their priorities and companies struggle with this.
They really do struggle with this.
And so as they grow to a wider, broader market, listening to that niche audience who can seem
extra demanding and pandemic almost can feel like a waste of your time because you have
this broader millions of more potentials X of whatever it might be.
And but the thing is, you really have to walk a fine line there because your most loyal
fans are really the ones that can help you get the word out.
They can, they'll be the first to try that new product.
Maybe it's the watch or not my case.
Maybe it's a podcast, right?
They'll be the first to try that new thing.
So it serves them.
It serves the longterm health of the organization or the project to keep the fans happy.
And that's why when I cover in love, Mangero's deciding to take out free office, but instead
give the user a choice of free office, LibreOffice or no office at the install time is a pretty
reasonable compromise because for those folks that want to still take advantage of the free
office improvements for particularly types of cranky doc format conversions, it's there
for them now.
And for those that want to stick with LibreOffice, still available right there front and center.
And for those like me now that want no office, that's even better.
So anyways, thank you for the email and I'll go ahead and get out of here, go.
Jack's got to get in here.
So Jack, welcome into my office.
And he wrote in about Nextcloud, we've been talking Nextcloud, haven't really said much
about it recently.
So I thought this would probably be a pretty good chance right here.
Here's what Jack writes.
Hey Chris, I had some tips for Nextcloud features that I didn't hear mentioned that you would
definitely find useful.
I've been using Nextcloud since the own cloud fork.
So maybe about three years, and it's become my favorite, most useful self-hosted server
other than my Plex and Jellyfin VM.
Number one is external storage, allows you to map a folder in Nextcloud to an external
storage provider by either SIF, Samba, Amazon's AWS, OpenStack, SFTP, Dropbox, etc.
And then you can use it natively within Nextcloud's clients and the webpage.
It can request credentials on access, store them, or authenticate against LDAP or federate
with other Nextcloud instances.
And then they're shareable with the Nextcloud permissions.
That's a really cool thing.
I actually am aware of external storage in our Nextcloud server.
One of our production Nextcloud servers is, I don't think it's using the formal external
storage, but it is doing digital ocean spaces, which is really kind of a cool thing.
So check that out.
So we are aware of external storage.
I have had some performance issues with it in the past when I connected it to Google
Drive and to Dropbox, so I haven't been all over it.
But for those of you that aren't aware of it, that's a good one.
He goes on to say it's a great way to also provide highly available interface to storage
objects that otherwise wouldn't really be accessible outside the LAN or VPN, which leads
him to the next one.
Now this is a big one.
Full text search.
This is a plugin stack that provides an elastic search interface to your Nextcloud files and
servers.
It also has support for OCR.
Combined with external storages, you could provide a full, incredibly fast search for
not just file names, but the contents of everything Elasticsearch supports.
Office formats, text, PDF, etc, etc.
When my grandfather died, he asked me to make his documents and emails available to the
family.
And I used Nextcloud and full text search to do it.
And it's an easy interface.
I also used it to provide a text search for my entire home NAS, which is great when you're
looking for, say, a tax document that you didn't name all that well and maybe didn't
file in the best place.
Hope you find these useful, Jack.
I do find those useful.
Thank you, Jack.
That's really great.
Now if you want to get into my office in the future, there's probably several ways you
can do it.
I'm monitoring different show inboxes, so sometimes I'll be picking up some of those
questions that slip through the cracks and don't make it into a show, or your best bet,
like if you specifically want to get in here, extras.show.com.
You go over there and I'll be watching that.
We can get something in here just for you and me.
You got a question directly for me or Prospector Chris.
That's who was just talking there for a second.
You can go over to extras.show.com and drop it in there and I'll address it on a future
office hours whenever that is.
The office is busy, all right?
I don't know when those are.
So the best thing to do would be to go to extras.show.com and just get them.
See you next time.
Office hours are closed.
Thanks for visiting.
It's over.
It's all done now.
The office is closed.
You got to go.