respectful of the University of British Columbia andloop
Welcome to a very special extra, man do you remember when we used to play this song for
way too long?
It's so long!
It is really long, and then the other egregious thing we'd do is we'd play the music for like
a full minute and a half under us while we did the show.
It's the slow fade out.
Well, we actually just were sitting down to put together another fantastic episode of
the Unplugged program.
You know, it comes out every week.
I did a little behind the scenes on the Chris Lass cast recently, and then I think it got
in the back of my head that maybe we should do a full blown legit extra on this.
And so while we were show prepping, we thought, well, let's talk about what goes into a show.
We're here doing it right now.
Let's sit down and record this.
And we thought, wouldn't it be fun to kind of look back because Linux Unplugged was launched
on August 12th, 2013.
That's like seven years ago.
Seven years.
And a lot has changed in actually what the show looks like and sounds like.
Seven years on the internet might as well be 30.
It was a different internet back in 2013.
It was.
It was a very different Linux Unplugged.
See Linux Unplugged started as a concept to relieve a problem I had in Linux Action Show,
and that was too much damn email, and I felt really guilty that I wasn't getting to all
of the emails coming into the big show.
And so I thought, I know what I'll do.
I'll create a podcast where I read emails.
It was it was a rough concept, but you know, Matt Hartley was down to clown on this idea.
And so we jumped on mic.
We launched with our virtual log on Hangouts.
The audio quality was atrocious.
Wow.
I'm glad I missed this episode.
All right.
This is embarrassing.
But I'm gonna play this for you.
OK.
This is gonna this is gonna be this is gonna hurt me because I sound like I'm on helium
and I'm going a million miles per hour.
So it's it's really tough.
You are just young and excited about Linux Hangout.
So far, we're a little hit and miss.
But we'll bring that we'll bring in the panel that we have assembled later in the show as
we get going.
But first, I want to just take a minute and talk about the new show.
We don't plan to do this too often, but it's kind of an opportunity to talk about ourselves
a little bit.
Matt and I were kind of brainstorming on a couple of problems that the Linux Action Show
has faced.
And one has been that we just have this torrential amount of feedback that we generate every
single week from every single show and ideas sometimes on how to do something differently
than how we talked about in the show.
Whoa, bro, slow down.
I don't even know.
And I can't even do it now.
And ideas we had talked about to do it in another show, like it's like I can't even.
I mean, you were streaming it live after all.
Yeah.
You got to be got to be on your game when you're live.
Or maybe you were nervous.
We were on it.
Google Plus Hangouts.
Big audience.
It's it's hey, did you actually know that maybe that's not the best way to do it or
anything like that?
Right.
Exactly.
And trying to find a way to present that in a way that wasn't going to just actually become
a time suck.
Right.
Yeah.
Because it would drag down the whole show.
Exactly.
And I had I had threatened for like a long time.
I was like, one of these days, Matt, I'm going to make a feedback show and also kind of talk
about his feedback.
Even my old man.
Yeah.
That's gotten a lot better.
That sounds like my old man's way better now.
Much older.
What's so sad about it is we don't even have to do like some sort of musical transition
between old clips and new clips because it's so patently obvious which one is young Chris
and which one's old Chris.
Oh, yeah.
And this is 100 episodes before you join the show.
So it was Matt and I just riffing.
That's kind of what we're doing, although that's not the show in its entirety.
That's only going to be a component of this show.
You know, I mean, the feedback, I think, is going to generate a lot of good discussion
and a lot of ideas.
But I'm hoping that this show is even more of an opportunity to kind of get down into
some episodes.
I want to just like totally just dig into a topic and we're just going to only talk
about really just that.
And maybe we'll just spend an hour discussing something, just really go deep.
Sometimes I want to just be all over the board and just talk about topics that have come
up throughout the week, things that people want to bring up, you know, do panel discussions
kind of like we're going to try in this episode.
That kind of has bared out to a degree or other.
In some ways, that's the core of the show.
It's funny because the arc of the show, which we'll talk about in a moment, didn't actually
go that way.
It's funny to me.
Have me say that episode one, the show ends up not going in that direction.
But now here we are, I think we just were recording 341 or 342, 343.
And we're now more closer to what I'm talking about here than we were 100, 200 episodes
ago.
That's weird.
Some ideas take a long time.
I'm real slow, Wes.
I'm a I'm a slow approach, you know, you know, I don't win the race.
But I get there eventually.
I don't know.
There's no excuse for it other than I think we'll actually talk about it.
We'll talk about there's a couple of things that came up that sort of affected the show's
evolution.
But let's go back to that first episode.
I'm pretty excited about the prospect of it.
I think it's going to be interesting to see how this comes to fruition, which direction
we end up taking it and really where the chat room guides us to.
Yeah.
And what from this will kind of surface up into the big show and make that an even better
show.
And I'm looking forward to it.
But I wanted to start, I thought, with the most classiest way.
And that would be me complaining.
Always, always a classy, a classy approach.
Right.
Like whenever you want to impress people, the new show, the first thing you want to
do is try to offend a good subset of your potential listeners.
That's Podcaster 101.
Everybody knows that.
I don't know why more shows don't do this.
It's glad.
I'm glad I nailed the essentials.
Even back then.
Yeah, that's a policy we follow today.
Do you know what I was upset about?
Do you have a guess?
It's a classic love topic.
System D?
No, because there was no System D then.
But this is pre, oh, it's 2013, right?
Yeah.
I'll give you a hint.
It has to do with a reoccurring problem back then in a desktop environment.
Wi-Fi?
It wasn't quite, Wi-Fi wasn't quite so bad in 2013.
But audio, particularly under plasma, was a real problem back then.
And so I was about to get in a good old too much choices causing this.
You would never complain about desktop Linux.
No, no.
It was one of those, this problem ultimately comes down to too much choice and we rely
on that.
I mean, it was a decent early rough rant.
You were still kind of honing the soapbox.
Oh man, the Hangout Audio 2 was so bad.
I'm so much happier with Mumble.
And we had, in the pre-show, we had Rando stop by.
They were just like browsing Google Plus, Windows users who were like, what, you bunch
of Linux geeks.
We had weird drive-bys.
Are you saying maybe we should start streaming on Hangouts again?
Well, yeah.
I mean, definitely.
It seems obvious.
Let's get Google Plus back up.
There was also, I'm surprised, we had ads in the very first episode, which from like
a getting my business together standpoint.
Impressive.
Yeah.
In 2013, the business was enough together that I launched a show with ads.
But the ad itself, you're not going to believe it.
Oh, I'm excited.
But look, here's something else that I worry about, and our next sponsor is going to help
you solve a problem that is becoming more and more of a concern for a lot of us with
a lot of the recent NSA revelations going on, ProXPN, a VPN provider in 2013, way ahead
of the trade.
Way ahead.
But listen to this read.
They are what I think is becoming one of the up-and-coming premier VPN solution providers.
They got all types of VPNs, great VPNs.
The best VPNs, great VPNs.
This is way ahead of the curve.
I was shilling VPNs Trump style before it was cool.
It's got all the VPNs, the greatest VPNs, the best encryption.
Do you still have your ProXPN account?
I don't think so.
OpenVPN, which obviously I'm a huge fan of.
Huge fan of OpenVPN.
Huge fan.
Of course.
So if you haven't thought about why you might want a VPN, obviously the first is to kind
of protect your identity online, and the other would be to keep what you're doing private.
It's funny because I just recently, in one of our team meetings, was like, when we were
considering doing a piece on VPNs, and I was like, I want us to discuss the fact that fear
mongering is being used to sell these VPNs, and the VPNs add consolidation of traffic,
which we should definitely look at as another potential security vulnerability.
And then here I am, in episode one, doing that.
I remember how this came about.
It was a new partner we were trying that got an ad slot for me.
It was like a one or two time deal, and we were just testing it.
And now listening back to it, I'm like, oh man, I'm so glad we didn't stick with this.
Because you don't remember me doing this, right?
This is what I tried and stopped doing it.
Even though you might be VPNing to somewhere else, it might eventually get monitored.
It's at least one step removed.
Oh, I guess I was at least, old Chris also worried about it.
Listen, this might not be that effective, but if you think you want a VPN, buy this
one.
I got to give myself credit for at least addressing the traffic, since I just raised that.
I forgot.
Wow.
I'm proud of myself right there.
I at least said, hey, you are centralizing your traffic.
To put yourself physically in another location.
So maybe if you need to be over across the pond, either side of that pond, ProXpn can
help you do that.
And we've got a great deal for ProXpn.
When you go to ProXpn.com and you decide to buy, you can take 20% off the lifetime of
your purchase.
And I think their base rate's only like seven bucks a month.
It's super cheap.
It's crazy cheap.
Yeah.
Solid contribution there by Matt Hartley.
Thanks, Matt.
I like, I just, I think it's so funny that there's so many VPN ads and they're basically
using those same, be more secure online, watch content that's not in your region.
It's great.
So there I was.
But I obviously had a lot to learn and took a lot of experimental trajectories.
One of them was bringing in a live chat, which you would think would be ridiculous.
Live audio open to the internet.
Honestly, I'd shoot that idea down today.
And so there was a lot of experimentation in format, including trying to create and
cultivate a show that felt really low key.
And this is, these are people that love Linux and we're just hanging out.
And part of that was the realization that we should probably have a little bit of a
pre-show, a warmup, get a conversation going with folks.
And we were digging through the archive and we found one more clip that I think is the
most embarrassing clip of them all, worse than the ad.
In episode 67, I don't know what was wrong with us, but we had a five plus minute pre-show
where we were rambling on about something that I actually couldn't tell you what we
were talking about.
Obviously highly relevant to Linux Unplugged.
Started with zero context and listening back, I'm like, I have no idea what we're talking
about.
I don't want to listen to this.
And then it goes on for five minutes.
I still don't grok the context.
And then, then the real tragedy happens, my worst introduction in Linux Unplugged history.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's celebrating its cheat day.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Matt.
Hey Matt.
So it's been a few weeks, almost a month, that I just have been kind of going like really
light on the breads and stuff, not like 100% cut it out, but what am I doing?
You know, you never give us diet updates at the start of the show anymore.
What could have, five minutes of incomprehensible talk followed by an introduction where I talk
about cutting bread out of my diet?
What am I doing?
This is, 2020 Chris looks back at that and I would never start a Linux podcast this way.
And I must have been trying to just like keep it super cash, but I obviously went way too
far on the old cash lever.
Really light, you know, just really going back to that, getting back to that.
And it's, oh, it's been great, Matt, it's been great.
But today before the show, we're working on something huge for tomorrow.
And I don't, you know, it's like in this last stage where it's the most work and you don't
know if you're going to make it in time, but we have something really big for the Jupiter
Broadcasting Network tomorrow that we're working on today.
The compression is horrible.
The audio quality is subpar.
It's funny, you know, I recognize it because I listened during this stage of Linux Unbugged.
It doesn't sound like you, but it still sounds eerily familiar.
The music is still playing and by this, this is like six and a half minutes into the show,
actually longer because the intro music went on forever.
And we still are not talking about Linux.
Like this would be considered like an egregious error in 2020.
But I'm like starving and I'm like, okay, I got to order a Jimmy John sandwich.
What am I doing?
I can't leave.
You've been listening to the radio.
No, it's just like, I know I got to get this work done and then I got to go do the Unplugged
show.
I got to go do the Unplugged show.
So I figure I'll order Jimmy John's, but I'm going to be a good boy.
Lettuce wrap that sandwich.
I'm going to get a lettuce wrap.
I am still talking about the bread stuff.
We got to be eight minutes into the show, real showtime here.
How do I sell ads for this?
Yeah, a little roughage, sure.
So I order Rekai's sandwich because you know, he's working on this project with me and I
order myself a nice big lettuce wrap.
Double up on that meat, Matt.
I get double up on that meat.
What's happening?
What is happening?
Giving like a Jimmy John's ad.
I know.
I'm like talking about meat.
What is happening?
And it shows up at the front door.
I grab the bag.
I go upstairs.
We get all situated in our offices.
We sit down and we start working again.
And you know what?
What, Chris?
Please, please let it be about Linux.
Please be about Linux.
They put it on bread.
And at that point, Matt, I was so hungry and I've been wanting a sandwich so bad, Matt.
I've been wanting a sandwich so bad.
I ate the whole sandwich, Matt.
And I got a little bit, I think if I went to the doctor right now, they would say, Chris,
you are clinically diagnosed with food coma.
Am I trying to be a stand up right now?
With like a 10 minute lead up to a job?
Clearly this like whole sandwich debacle was a major part of your day and all you could
think about.
I'm like, I'm just free flowing.
I'm going with my id.
You are currently in a state of food coma.
So we're going to get through today's episode.
It's going to be kind of a thick episode.
There's a lot of things going on with the Debian project.
Oh, there it is.
Finally.
How long do you think that was into the show?
Got to be dang near nine minutes.
Probably.
It doesn't even sound like you want it.
We're going to get through this episode.
Doesn't sound like you want to do the episode.
That is so embarrassing.
That is.
I'm like in tears.
That's so embarrassing.
Wow.
There's nobody that would say that.
Say, what are you doing?
What are you doing, man?
Stop it.
Well, lesson learned.
I guess we did learn over time.
We've tightened up a bit.
We have.
There was really sort of the middle years that came after that where the show got really
news heavy.
It was almost all news from top to bottom with a little bit of feedback.
There's a real transition point in there where the feedback and the follow up, which we started
every Unplugged with, moved to the end of the show.
And then as a little time went on, it just kind of became less and less.
We're making more effort to bring it back.
Yeah, there's sort of a feedback comeback.
Yeah, there is a feedback comeback now, but there was a transition where we just went
to sort of a topical discussion show because it was easy for the virtual lug to have opinions
about.
Right.
This is stuff they could all reference.
There's articles written up about it.
And I mean, you know, this was still during the Linux action show era for a lot of this.
And so, you know, you guys were doing big projects and had interviews there.
There was no Linux action news yet.
So there was a little more room on the network, too.
Well, not only that, but there wasn't nearly as many Linux podcasts.
So there's less people doing the news.
But also, there's a reality to it is I didn't have a team back then.
It was people with their volunteer time.
So a news show where you just have a group of people talk about the news is easy compared
to anything where you're building something or you're installing something or you're testing
something or you're benchmarking something.
It all takes exponentially more time than keeping track of the news, formulating an
opinion and then jotting down some notes and then repeating those opinions into a mic.
Right.
And everyone can sort of collaborate.
Everyone sort of pitches news stories and you just got to pick through them.
And opinions are easy to come by.
Oh, yeah.
So then it really becomes, well, is there something about your opinion?
Is it informed by a certain angle?
Is there something about your opinion that is special?
And the reality is, when you just have a large group of topics and a large group of people,
you kind of just kind of end up with the same standard conversations.
That was sort of the middle age of the show.
And I think it worked for a period.
And also, I think, marked some of the transition to Linux Unplugged also being something of
an online Linux users group.
You know, we started thinking of the show that more as we bonded, got some regulars
in there.
That was a big part of it is having some regulars that pop in from time to time.
And then a big moment for us that shifted us into a more news-focused era, like that
middle layer of LUP as it sits right now, was SystemD.
SystemD sort of tracks all the way back to early LUP, like the 20s, but it really built
over time and it became a story that we kind of kept checking in.
And it's still sort of true today, really, that I looked at the Linux action show as
Star Trek The Next Generation, and I looked at Linux Unplugged as Deep Space Nine, where
Deep Space Nine had ongoing narratives through multiple episodes.
We're checking back in on things, following up.
Yeah, we could have a topic take two or three episodes sometimes, whereas last was showcase,
you're done.
That episode is self-contained, much like Star Trek The Next Generation was.
Different products of different eras.
And the SystemD conversation, I think, really cemented that format and sent us down the
news path for a while.
Well, and it was, you know, at that time, there was a lot of shake-ups.
The news had big news in it.
And I think it was useful, frankly, we kind of needed to talk about it, right?
We were going to be talking about it anyway, it was this big change that was happening
from the outside.
So I think it was useful for the show to have an outlet like that.
And it was a moment for us to realize, hey, if we take the extra time to really read both
sides of this, try to understand how it works from a technology perspective, try to figure
out, okay, what's the motivation for this massive change?
What problem is it solving?
Now can we communicate that to the audience in a way that is relatable and understandable?
And SystemD taught us, I think, in a big way how to do that over its run.
Right.
While we may even like or want to use SystemD, you also have to acknowledge the design flaws
or things that just aren't done in the way that you would like them to be done.
Now I think as time has gone on, we have the news component, but it could be sometimes
no more than one or two stories.
And then there's a mix of conversation pieces in there.
But this has now transitioned as we've become full-time at doing this, we've tried to level
up the amount of time we spend prepping an episode of Linux Unplugged, and it's put some
pressure on us.
But it's pressure I think we're happy to carry because we're trying to, in every episode,
create some original coverage.
Yes.
Well, there's things that we need to talk about as a community that aren't always timely
with the news, right?
That just change on different scales or are too complicated to be really written up in
the sort of shallow textile.
Yeah.
And we have a pretty good list of contacts now.
So when there's something going on with WireGuard, we've been able to email the WireGuard author
or when Nebula from Slack was launched as their peer-to-peer VPN solution, although
I don't think they like to call it that, we're able to get that developer on the line.
And in fact, something we did with that episode that I really liked is we had the Tink developer.
Gus Koos?
Yes.
Good memory, Wes.
And that was such a neat episode because it's like, here's two products that are in the
open source ecosystem.
One is brand new to the scene and one's been here for a decade.
How do they solve this problem differently coming at it from these two different eras?
And I really enjoyed that kind of stuff.
That's the kind of stuff we try to do now more of that we couldn't really afford to
do in all of the senses of the word when people were volunteering their time.
And then you came around in episode 100 when we had that barbecue and just hit the ground
running.
You know, it's been too long since we've fired up that old barbecue.
That is for serious, Wes.
That is for real serious, especially when we've had a couple of surprise nice days.
It's ridiculous.
So here's what we do.
We get a couple of wireless mics that we can, you know, attach to our shirts.
We get a little outdoor grill cam.
Sure.
And that's the pre-show.
I mean, I think we tried that once before.
I mean, the barbecue is steeped in tradition on the show.
It's a touchstone element that we need to get back to as part of this self-reflection
process we were doing now and we have been doing recently with this show.
We need to get that barbecue element in there.
I think it's pretty important.
A lot of the work, all of the work, all of the work proportionally for Linux Unplugged
is before we ever sit down on the microphones.
And it really, I mean, it almost never stops in a sense.
Once one episode is recorded, there's another one.
You got to kick off planning for the next.
And the more intricate and more, you know, if you want a guest or if you want to set
stand some stack of software.
Right.
Are you going to try something that you really need to experiment so you can comment on meaningfully?
Are you going to run a desktop for a week?
Like you got to start basically as soon as we get all of the description done for the
one we just recorded, we start working on the next one.
And that can ramp up depending on the ambition of the show.
Sometimes it means we both go off to our own camps and work.
Sometimes it means we collaborate at the studio like we're doing today.
We both sit down here in the studio and work on something and we try to get as much done
as possible because at noon Pacific, the show starts and it's all live to tape.
Every clip that we play, every sound bite, it's all live.
Every interview, it's all live, done to tape.
And then we're done.
The actual production of the show in a big sense is the least amount of work for us because
we just sit down and talk.
We've already prepared.
We know what we're going to say.
We've done it for so long that it's not like we have butterflies.
It's not hard for us to sit down and start talking.
So we got all that.
It's everything we do before then and then it's everything that happens after the show
when we flack out each individual track.
Everybody's recorded on their own individual tracks.
We flack all that up.
We use Nextcloud to send it off to Joe for editing.
That's really worth talking about almost as its own part of the era.
When Joe started helping out, started editing Unplugged, I think that was one of our triggers
to realize that we could take things to the next level because we had someone who could
just really improve the quality of the show.
Yeah, you're right.
Going multi-track and having Joe come on board to help with not just the editing but also
help direct some of the content has been really beneficial because it's brought a critical
air to the show so that way I don't do dumb things like do a five-minute intro talking
about bread.
Could you imagine?
That's kind of never going to happen now.
With the multi-track audio, we can do noise removal for each individual voice.
We can EQ each individual voice.
We can really go to the next level of quality that we'd never even gotten near before.
Joe's so dedicated to it that he stays up till way late on his time.
He's probably up till 3 a.m., 4 a.m. working on every Linux Unplugged because we don't
start till noon here our time.
That's new.
Yeah, we've tried to move it a little bit to accommodate, but he stays up until the
show's out.
If it's a big show with lots of tracks and extra guests and editing that needs to be
done because we did something extra, he's staying up until 5 a.m. to get the show out.
Well, he's also able to get clips ready for us.
If we do have a guest on, he can make sure that's pre-edited and ready for us to just
play live on air, which is very helpful.
Yeah, and he'll match the EQ of the interview so it sounds natural.
It's a nice secret sauce and being dedicated so much to stay up late like that to get it
out so that way it's available the next morning so it's as relevant as possible, it's ready
for the morning commute.
I think it's a big part of why people tune it up because it's right there.
You know that episode.
If you're listening to it, it's as relevant as physically possible for a show of that
production quality.
So it really has been refining our hosting approach, refining how we interact with the
community, refining our audio production, and then refining what we cover in the show
to try to do more original stuff, more guest interviews.
We've really gotten pickier.
I mean, I think we have a lot of the same ideas we've always had, but fewer of them
make it because we just have higher standards.
For better or for worse, sometimes it makes us feel like we're a little stuck, but other
times we feel like we've really nailed it and it's like this great, like, oh man, we
really pulled something off there.
That feels great.
So I think it's very common for this kind of work actually.
I think that's a very common thing.
You can't stay still, right?
I mean, no one else in this space stays still, and if we kept doing the same thing, we'd
all get bored.
I think we probably can't say enough, though, how important our virtual log has been.
It's been such a huge component, and they've stuck with us throughout this whole show.
We'd love to have you join us live.
We do Linux Unplugged live on Tuesdays at noon Pacific.
You can get it in your local time at jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
You know, if you can't make it to the mumble room, we've also got an IRC channel.
We love our chat room.
IRC.geekshed.net, pound, Jupiter Broadcasting, Octothorp, Octothorp, yeah, yeah, it's good.
Hey, guess what?
We'll see you next Tuesday!