How you doing Brent? So we were talking on telegram earlier about upgrading your wi-fi
and your router and your firewall and stuffs and things and things and stuff.
So tell me what's going on man?
I mean you have a small part in this. We've been upgrading some of my devices.
So I got an axe 250 and it seems I'm just taking all my legacy devices and getting fancier. So I
was thinking geez that router I've got in the closet over there is pretty darn old.
It's an old WRT-54G which were pretty classic what like 10 years ago.
It's got some custom firmware and all that stuff which is super great but it's,
I think it's time. It's feeling really slow on the wi-fi.
What are you running on the firmware side?
I'm running tomato on that thing. It hasn't been updated maybe in two years.
Some say tomato.
Tomato. Some say tomato and router. So I'm just feeling like I don't know it seems like
the time to start upgrading everything. At least I've got some momentum so I thought geez
you might just be the perfect person to ask. So I don't know what I'm doing
and I'm quite stale on the hardware side so I need some recommendations.
I can certainly help you spend some money if that's what you mean.
Oh well I wasn't that wasn't at the top of the list.
I'm good at that. Let's not make it too formal like you must have some idea of what your
requirements are like low power or something. Open source preferably that kind of stuff right?
Yeah I would say at the top of the list if I'm trying to do it prioritizing I would say
open source all the way. I would say low power is always nice but a higher priority than that
would be you know things like stability and for me honestly the most practical thing would be
some really reliable Wi-Fi. Other than that I'm pretty open you know so you know as low of budget
is great but I would rather look at options that would last a long time. I'd rather do this once
and have it be really kind of flexible so that's my preference.
Sounds like Wi-Fi is the primary driver here is that right? Is that fair?
Yeah ethernet's easy.
Yeah so your current router firewall situation have you ever felt that the
the ingress egress kind of performance is not where you need it?
Well I have quite low needs I would say you know the needs that you have may be a little
bit more sophisticated than mine so at this point I'm just you know I'm probably more like your
regular old user than I am sort of a power user. Now I would love to change that but in terms of
my sophistication I would say I don't know any better so I would love to gain access to local
stuff because you and I are probably going to have another one of these chats to set me up with a
local NAS and stuff like that to do some fancy things and I am container uninitiated so there's
a lot that can happen here so I want to put in a solution that can accommodate all that you know.
That's quite literally Pandora's box you're opening here you do realize that right?
Hey man bring it on.
So I'm a huge fan of separating my firewall from my Wi-Fi and there's a few reasons for that but
the primary one is that I can reboot my firewall and all of my Wi-Fi devices don't freak out for
10 minutes whilst they find the Wi-Fi again. So about five years ago I bought some uh it was a
pair actually of UniFi AC dual radio pro access points. I was on the fence at the time about
buying the pro version because everybody told me it was overkill and you won't need it and blah
blah blah but here I am several years later and I don't feel any need to replace or upgrade my Wi-Fi
so that's the first benefit. The second benefit is that if I want to switch out my firewalls
for any reason so let's say I decided I wanted to switch from my ISP provided router to PF sense
or ViOS or monowall or whatever else it is a UniFi security gateway even it makes the entire solution
a lot more modular. So kind of what I'm thinking might work well for you in this situation is I'm
not hearing any complaints about the throughput or routing performance of your current router
that basically your firewall seems like that's doing the job that you need it to do where it is
failing for you seems to be the Wi-Fi. So the obvious solution to me at this point would be to
get a hundred dollar or so UniFi access point plug that into one of the ethernet ports on the router
and then just use the UniFi SSID that broadcasts and the modern AC Wi-Fi standards and then if and
when you ever decide that that tomato based router isn't doing what you need it to do maybe you could
look at a PF sense box or something like that. That's not even a solution I thought of was just
breaking out the Wi-Fi into into its own little category. Now I've heard a lot about these UniFi
access points and fairly positive things but does that check the open source part of it? I believe
these are closed source no? So it doesn't look like UniFi is actually open source completely.
There are certain portions that they want to open source but apparently there's some FCC
restrictions around open sourcing software defined radio stuff. Oh that's curious. It's a bit beyond
my pay grade that kind of thing but unfortunately it doesn't look like UniFi is the open source
panacea that you want. I don't know of a good solution that is. I know that you can self-host
the UniFi controller. Okay. These access points are designed to be deployed at scale. They connect
back to a central controller. Now you can buy off the shelf from UniFi something called a cloud key
which hosts this controller software and is stupid simple to set up. You literally just power it on,
look at the IP address on the little OLED screen on the front and off you go. But those things can
be expensive. Easily running into the one to two hundred dollar range which you know if you're
deploying a hotel's worth of Wi-Fi might be worth it but in your apartment it's probably not. So
I've run for the last few years out of a docker container the UniFi controller software and this
might be a good in for you into the container world. One other nice thing about these UniFi
devices is that they're powered through PoE. So installation of them is really really easy. You
just have what's called a PoE injector between the ports on the back of your router and the
access point. So if you want to mount one of these things on the ceiling it's really easy. All you
have to do is run a network cable to that location and then at the other end of that cable is where
you have the plug socket that actually provides the power. That's actually brilliant. It makes it
so simple right? Really simple and when you start scaling these things to having four, five, six,
seven or more on a single site you can actually get PoE switches which are really easy to use.
Which have eight ports, 16, 48 port switches that are all powered so you can run IP cameras over PoE.
You can run the access points and only ever have a single source of actual power plugged into the
wall. So that means you can run your Wi-Fi quite easily on a UPS even. So there's a lot of nice
small things you can do to really upgrade the network just simply by having the Wi-Fi separate
from the router. What a great idea. I never even considered that. As always Alex your insights are
very valuable so thank you. Your wallet can thank me later. So what do you think you're going to go
for? Does that sound like a reasonable solution? And so this seems like an easy answer that you've
been testing for a long time. Is there anything else I should even consider? Probably not.
Okay. Not to toot my own horn but this has worked flawlessly for years and it's transported with me
across one, two, three, soon to be a fourth house and I've not had to reset the Wi-Fi up. In fact
when my mum came to stay with me this summer her phone connected to my Wi-Fi and she was like,
oh wow this is amazing. Last time I was on your Wi-Fi it was in London and now I'm in America.
I'm like yeah. That is so cool. If I'm not mistaken too these are deployed at the studio
as well the JB studio and haven't been thought about for a while. They just kind of work.
They just do the job yeah. Now the other thing to consider is that in my situation I manage my
family's Wi-Fi and when when doing that remotely that can be a challenge but these access points
at my parents houses both connect back to my central unify controller which I run on a droplet
and so I'm able to control their Wi-Fi and fix any Wi-Fi issues they've got remotely
which is really nice. And so can we talk about my router for a moment? It's quite old and I'm just
wondering if that's something I need to worry about. I guess maybe the hardware as a plain old
router might just be fine if it's not you know if it's disjointed from the Wi-Fi and so if I just
update that thing maybe with a new like OpenWRT software that might just be fine. Do you even
need to? You know I suppose that stems from the question of can it do some of the fancier features
like allowing me to connect in with WireGuard and that kind of stuff. You know you could spend
easily 100 bucks on a new router or you could spend 30 on a Raspberry Pi and do it on that
instead and it's still low power. Interesting this might be the first implementation of my very first
single board computer in some infrastructure. Yeah now that Pi could run WireGuard it could run the
unify controller software it could run Home Assistant if you wanted to get into that as well
maybe. You know the Pi 4 is super powerful. So is the Pi good enough for like set and forget though?
Yeah I think so. If you were to get the Pi 3b plus that boots over USB so you just get a USB
hard drive whereas the Pi 4 currently doesn't yet support USB boot but I believe it's coming
air quotes soon. We'll see. So with regards to whether you should replace your current router
or not like what's your what's your upload and download look like? I don't have very large needs
I think I'm getting five no I've got fiber so I'm on the lowest fiber and it's 10 down it's like
five up or something like that and that's plenty fast for what I'm doing you know I'm never needing
to do anything very quickly on a time schedule so I'm uploading lots of photos and stuff like that
to a you know a server that I can serve to clients but it's never on like a I don't need it immediately
kind of basis so that's been working just fine for me. So if your current route is working just
fine I would I would leave that alone and then save save that money and spend it on as good a
wi-fi on your LAN as you can afford and then store your files locally connected to a Pi or maybe a
Pi or maybe a cheap x86 box. I have a few of those. I sent you a link in telegram to my
PFSense build which is a it's a hundred and one hundred and sixty dollars or so I spent on this
thing and it's got an i5 low power version in it i5 3470T it's got an Intel motherboard that's got
dual Intel NICs and I spent a hundred and sixty three dollars on this thing and it it would make
a fine base for a NAS system. So you know I think realistically you're going to look at spending by
the time you've done the wi-fi and have some kind of a local system that can run WireGuard a minimum
of 150 US but you could spend obviously you know the sky's the limit but you you know you could
spend 250 and have an x86 box that's always on low power that kind of thing as well as really great
wi-fi and then start scaling the system up from there really. So I have some things to think about
sounds like. Always it's always a trade-off in terms of how much money do I want to spend how
little do I want to eat this month. I eat quite a bit. I know I know you do. I feel like those are
really great options. I'm gonna have to think a little bit more if I want to tackle this all at
once or or split it up but at least those are two sound forks in the road right. Well that is the
beauty of a modular approach right you don't have to necessarily do all of these things all at once
you know you can just upgrade the wi-fi this month and then in a couple of months time you
can then tackle the WireGuard situation and just keep building slowly but surely and
eventually after time you'll have built a really quite sophisticated system that if any one thing
fails you've only got to replace that one thing and not the whole thing. You know there's something
kind of beautiful about that approach. I always say have backups to backups so it feels like if
one little section breaks it's easy to switch it out so tempting. Thank you for your insights that
sounds amazing. All right you do realize you've jumped the Ask SSHQ by doing this right.