It's Tuesday. Hello, guys. Looking nice, Brent and Sharp. Welcome back. You weren't supposed
to be here. What the hell are you still doing here?
Well, come on. I can't miss another Tuesday, especially because you're wearing your robe.
Yeah, well, I had to be comfortable.
Wes is looking good right there. Although, sorry, Wes. Brent kicked you out of your spot.
You know, he just came in here early.
I know. Between Brent and Levi. I mean, I'm just sitting on the floor at this point.
Yeah, space is a premium, you know, in a recording studio. It's just how it goes.
We have just started the stream up on a Tuesday, just kind of hanging out when we normally
be doing the unplugged program. And the Mumble Room is trickling in. So, if you'd like to
join us in the Mumble Room, come on in. And the IRC room is also open at irc.geekshed.net
pound Jupiter broadcasting or go to bit.ly slash Jupiter chat.
We had some good blues playing earlier, but then Brent wrecked the whole thing because
somebody gave him access to the mixer.
Geez. That's my bad. I also told them about FreeBSD and we've seen how that's gone.
Yeah, I know, right? I tell you what. I was talking to my co-host Mike yesterday on Coda
Radio and I was saying, hey, you know, I noticed something weird is going on at Blizzard. They
just fired like 40 people this morning. And I was like, oh, that's interesting. I wonder
what's going on there, you know? And then this morning I wake up and there's news that
Microsoft plans to acquire Blizzard for $68.7 billion in cash. That's at $95 a share. It's
going to go down in financial quarter 2023. And of course, the stock's up 25% on Activision
side. And Microsoft is kind of pitching this as with this acquisition, Microsoft is going
to give the gift of Blizzard games to quote everyone across every device. So, Microsoft
is going to give you the gift of more Blizzard games if you pay for their streaming service.
This is another company that they've kind of scooped up.
I think that feels like a pretty smart idea though. They're kind of buying a bunch of
reputation, aren't they?
Boy. I mean, some of the biggest games in my life, Starcraft, Diablo, those were Blizzard
games.
I'm kind of interested in how the, yeah, definitely. But I'm kind of interested in how the reputations
align because, I mean, I don't think Activision Blizzard was anyone's current favorite in
terms of, I mean, employee treatment, just their behavior over the past couple of years.
And then of course, we know that many have mixed feelings about Microsoft already.
Yeah, but you're right. Activision sort of dirtied the waters a little bit when they
came in.
Yeah, right.
It says here that through the great teams and great technology, Microsoft and Activision
Blizzard will empower players to enjoy the most immersive franchises like Halo and Warcraft.
The CEO is out. So even though this is going to remain as a brand, the CEO is out.
The people they fired seem to have been involved in perhaps some sexual harassment issues in
the company. And so the question becomes, why were they not dealt with sooner?
And it seems pretty obvious that as this deal went down, they're like, these people have
to be dealt with before they're Microsoft employees. Deal with your stuff.
And then the CEO tweets, yeah, I'm not going to stay on, but I will be totally an advisor,
which is code for I'm going to fade away, but they give me because it's like it's part
of the deal because they still want to have everyone to walk away from this deal with
a smile and a safe face. They allow him to claim he's an advisor, but they're not going
to take any advice from him.
I just don't know. Do you see a lot of Microsoft games on the Steam store? I don't. I don't
go out looking for them, but I have looked for Age of Empires and I just I guess I don't
feel like this is a net good for Linux users.
Because it's subscription only. Well, it's going to be the access to it. I think ultimately
it's about pushing. Ultimately, it's about Xbox. I would totally say so. Yeah, it's about
Xbox's. It's about Xbox's. It's about Xbox streaming service. And it's, you know, not
intentionally, but it will have the net effect of also continuing to cement DirectX's dominance
as Microsoft owns more of these shops.
Like, do we know? We should look this up. They're probably seeing some of the movement
and trying to hold on dearly to it. That's what I would imagine this motivation is.
So this isn't the first time somebody's Google very quickly completes gaming company's
Microsoft owns when you search for that. Not good. Oh, it looks like PC Gamer has an updated
ongoing page that. Oh, my God. Really? So they own Zenimax, which owns id Software
where Doom comes from. Right. They have Bethesda Studios. They have more studios than I've
ever even seen the names of here. This list is massive, actually. So I'll name it by games
that people might recognize. They own the they own the companies behind these games.
Wolfenstein, Ghostwire, Fallout 3, 4 and Fallout 76, Elder Scrolls Online, Halo, we know,
of course, Psychonauts, Broken Age, Wasteland, Bard's Tale, Minecraft, South Park, the Stick
of Truth. OK, that's weird. Obviously, Gears of War, Frozen Motorsports, State of Decay
and like I just mentioned, Age of Empires. And that's actually not even everything on
the list. Those are just games I've heard of before. There's other ones on this list
I haven't heard of. But Microsoft also owns. Those are they're like the Disney of game
franchises, but I'm not a gaming expert by any means, but those all sound like pretty
old titles to me. Like Wolfenstein, obviously. Yeah, but they sell those all sell. There
seems to be a fair amount of I don't know if you should call it sentimentality or not,
but yeah, right. Like some of these franchises have a lot of mindshare. And I mean, I can't
speak for gamers really, because I am a casual gamer at best. But yeah, some of these titles,
you know, like there's just a lot of emotional response to them. The other thing that strikes
me is if these aren't on Steam, they're pretty much a nonstarter for the deck unless people
put Windows on there. And you know, we kind of yeah, we kind of joke around about what
happens if people buy a deck and put Windows on it. But when you look at the games that
are really popular, I think only only I don't know, but I think only a small percentage
of them or at least a not a complete chunk of them are on Steam anymore. Like they're
on either the Microsoft Store or the Epic store or some, you know, Blizzard has their
own thing. They're all on these independent platforms sort of like we're seeing happen
with streaming services. We're seeing the same thing happen with these game stores.
It's the same example.
Are you now saying that Steam is cable?
Seems like the ultimate cable bundle. And then these other streaming services are like
the add ons that you got to everybody's everything's turned into cable television, hasn't it?
Maybe it already was.
All right. Well, so there you go. That's what's going on today. Microsoft became the Disney
of video games and now owns all of the properties. But moving on, it is I was just commenting
this to the guys before we started streaming. It is frickin impossible now. It is frickin
impossible now to have any kind of tech news headlines that don't have a ton of crypto
stories in them, cryptocurrency stories. And so yesterday, it seems, Crypto.com, which
I was just talking to Wes about, halted withdrawals on their exchange and is forcing users to
sign back in and reset their two factor authentication. Research shows that they lost forty six hundred
Ethereum worth about 15 million dollars in a presumed hack. Yeah, Crypto.com, which just
bought that stadium, which has Ben Affleck as a spokesperson. Crypto.com tweets, quote,
we have a small number of users reporting suspicious activity on their accounts. We'll
be pausing withdrawals shortly as our team is investigating. All funds are safe.
What's a small number? Do they state that there?
What is a small number? A thousand? Five thousand? What's a small number? I don't know.
It's probably number times account balance. Right. That's how that's how support prioritizes
it.
I think the tell in this is that they're forcing users to reset their two factor. That is interesting.
Also, it appears that some people did lose funds, but Crypto.com has already covered
them and made them whole. And I guess that's kind of the upshot to these centralized wealthy
exchanges is when they do have something like this happen now, crypto insurance. Yeah, they're
basically covering it. And what's interesting is Crypto.com does have their own token called
Crow and Crow's price was completely unaffected by this news, which if you were to rewind
the clock a year ago and you had news about an exchange hack, the currency would tank.
Yeah. Yeah. In fact, the whole crypto market might tank that day.
So what gives? Why? Why not?
I think because we haven't seen any of these hacks that aren't pretty quickly contained
and covered. Like the companies seem to have processes in place where they identify the
issue like the day of or around then they isolate it and then they cover everything
and then they pay out bounties for the bug finders.
But is it also suggesting that this is just regular everyday business? Like these hacks
are just like just the way it's going to go?
Well, the banking system definitely has normalized them. Like, you know, my wife called into
Bank of America and gave them the wrong address accidentally because she'd forgot that she
had still had it at her old business address and they locked her out of her account and
they told her she can't do phone banking anymore. She has to go into a branch now because fraud
is so rampant that they have to do these extreme measures. I worked at a small bank and 40
branches and in our operations quote unquote department where we had people who are responsible
for maintaining the ATM network and helping branches with logistics and stuff, we had
an entire row of cubicles. So about 13 gals that just dealt all day long their entire
workday with debit card fraud because the debit card fraud is so rampant that the banks
don't even make a big deal about it. They just cover the cost because to them they've
done the math and they've identified that if they set X amount of millions aside and
they just cover the fraud costs and just let the system operate, everyone makes more money
on the net.
But is that cheaper than, I don't know, getting better technology around debit cards?
They have decided it is. Yeah. I think in part because they're so constrained by regulatory
movements so, you know, anything they invest into is a massive five-year process.
I also think it sounds worse than it necessarily is. I think that's pretty common in a lot
of businesses is you just make pragmatic trade-offs, right? Like it's kind of a benefit for us.
Like I don't really worry about it too much. I mean, yes, like Hadid has had a really bad
experience, but by and large I feel like, oh yeah, well you've set up, this is a normal
part of your workflow, you're accustomed to dealing with it, even if I don't love how
you deal with it.
Yeah, I agree. I think it works until it doesn't. Like for example, if the fraud, you know,
were to exponentially grow, obviously they would have to figure out something quick and
probably wish they would have addressed it. Like I can imagine, you know, a situation
where it's business as usual and that's fine and then all of a sudden it becomes kind of
a big burden. And, you know, it seems like the right move would be to invest in something
and build a system and I don't know.
Yeah, I agree, Wes. It's kind of the same kind of thinking though that leads to how
they plan for cybersecurity attacks where they kind of just do the math and figure out,
well with insurance it's cheaper for us to take a breach and maybe we take a five million
dollar drawdown, but, you know, we don't have to spend ten years investing five million
dollars every year for a decade to get a system that's impenetrable. We'll just spend one
time five million dollars and take the loss. And so they don't invest in their cybersecurity,
but meanwhile they're fine financially and it does work out for them. The insurance pays
out and they get to cry cyber victim, but all of their customers' information is just
once again leaked. And, you know, everybody works out, it's fine for everybody except
for the customer. And it kind of feels like that's what happens with these, this kind
of banking system. Like everything was fine until one day my checking account got compromised
and they shut it down immediately because they're constantly dealing with this kind
of stuff. So now they've just codified sort of this one size fits all approach. They shut
down my checking account. Well, the next day my credit card went to go clear and my credit
card payment failed. So then my credit card company deemed me as delinquent and insufficient
funds at both of those things, which both went on my credit report, which I'm still
dealing with. And I kind of just stop and go, well, if they just built a better system
that I thought I could rely on, but it turns out I was just getting lucky. If they just
built a better system in the first place or switch to something superior as it came along,
perhaps something like that wouldn't happen. And if that happens to me, it's probably happening
on a larger scale.
I think the question is, does that exist? And I think the good banks are doing both,
right? Like you have to have insurance and you have to work on your security.
That's pain throwing shade on my bank, but you're probably right. Oh, I hate your bank.
Yeah, it's a really moment. It's really a factor of momentum, not out of selection.
Partially because I've worked with someone who used to work in their security operations.
Oh boy. I've been thinking about it. You know, I have been thinking about it. Speaking of
maybe unbanking. How about this one? So there's a couple of crypto stories in here. Coinbase
has partnered with MasterCard to let users pay with a credit card in its upcoming NFT
marketplace.
Of course.
Just all pain points. Buying NFTs on a credit card, that sounds like the worst possible
idea. The only possible upshot is that some sucker is willing to buy the NFT at a price
that outpaces your interest rate and your payments on that credit card. But that seems
like a long shot. Unless you could turn it around within a couple of days. I mean, you
give that market three months and then nobody's going to be interested in your stupid ape.
So could you imagine buying a bored ape picture on your credit card? I mean, I'm pretty bullish
when it comes to a lot of crypto technologies. And I even think the concept of NFTs is going
to be very useful. We're just seeing the very first ideas around it. But this doesn't seem
like a great idea. Is it just to try to enable simpler transactions via credit cards? Yeah,
for sure. But yeah, that's sort of it. I think if I was assuming I didn't want to spend cryptocurrency
on it, or I was just getting into the space, I think that credit card is how I would buy
it. That's how I buy almost everything in my life. And if it gets stolen, then the credit
card has a little bit of insurance you can bank on. Yeah, maybe it's better than hooking
up your bank details to your account. Hey, credit card, I'd really like to return this
NFT. Right. I bought it on accident. Here's how you really leverage it. Somehow, maybe
one day there'll be like a cryptocurrency perks credit card, right? So you buy with
your credit card, and you get perks and points for buying the NFT. Like right now, I get
points for buying gas. Well, don't you have that Coinbase card? Yeah, you could use the
Coinbase card and make cryptocurrency on the transaction. That's true. Or there's some
interesting stuff like M1 Finance has as you get like rebates if you shop at a company
and you own some of their stock. Oh, that's interesting. Yeah. What a system. That's a
definitely know your customer set a circle to get that working. But wow, huh. Okay,
we got one last one last crypto story. These are all just taken from the tech feed headlines.
We didn't go out and look for crypto stories. But this one's pretty shocking, I think. Intel
has announced plans for a low voltage, energy efficient Bitcoin mining ASIC. They're gonna
have a session on February 23rd to talk more about it. They call it the bonanza mine, an
ultra low voltage energy efficient miner. They plan to go into direct competition in
the Bitcoin mining ASIC space going up against Bitmain and Microbit. And of course, a lot
of the Chinese manufacturers as well. And I guess the idea here is is make a little
bit of money on this thing, you know, as especially as you really I think the beam out there is
that people are using graphics cards to buying Bitcoin. But the reality is, nobody's been
doing that for a while. It's all on these ASICs now. And so this would give US companies
a US manufacturer to pick from, which I think is a really interesting development. But did
you see this coming? Like, I thought Intel was too busy throwing shade at the M1 to actually
have their head above water enough to see something like this.
Well, it sounds like maybe they want in the game too. And that's just their way to get
in. But it does sound like maybe it also addresses the energy issue that everybody's all up in
arms about, you know, if they can put some real smart heads together to try to address
that.
Yeah, they also I think it, it plays into some of their stuff, you know, where they're
farming out more their, you know, really next gen stuff to TSMC. And so maybe this is some
of their attempt to, you know, diversify their fab business.
Yeah. Let's go into the mumble room. Hello, mumble room. Hey, guys. How you doing?
Hello, everyone.
So would anyone in here buy, let's say this is never going to happen, but let's say Intel
got the price point to $1,000. You could get like a NUC sized device. You plug it in, it's
lower power and it just quietly mines Bitcoin at a slow rate. But, you know, interesting
rate. Would you buy one?
Now, here's the advantage of mining your own Bitcoin. Number one, you could join a pool
so you could make smaller amounts when anyone else in the pool mines so that you could,
you know, it's not just an all or nothing thing. You could have a lower power Bitcoin
miner that still makes a nice little steady income. Secondly, you're offering security
to the network. But third, a very interesting reason to mine your own Bitcoin is, is then
it really has no traceability because when you buy from an exchange, an exchange knows
who you are. When you buy a Bitcoin, they know the address that you bought. When you
send it out of their exchange to your wallet, they know what address you sent it to. That's
all available. That's all available to anybody that needs to audit that, that has the right
to audit that. But when you mine a Bitcoin, there's no originating address. You are the
originating spot. So it's your own private Bitcoin. So there's that advantage as well.
Perhaps maybe you'd want to collect a few Satoshis that are original and untraceable
for whatever means. So there could be another incentive to buy yourself a cheap little miner.
Would anyone do it? The thing is Bitcoin for me, it's still a
black box. But yeah, maybe. I don't know. Yeah. What about you, Wes? Would you buy one?
We're at a thousand bucks. A thousand bucks. Hmm. You know, I could see it. I suppose it
would depend on. Yeah. What's the operating cost?
I think you dropped off Mike or something fell off there. Where'd you go? Come back.
We can hear you a little bit, but you just got quiet. Yeah. What's the, what's the, I
think what you said is what's the run cost. Yeah. What's the run cost. What's the like
time to realistically perhaps see a net return. Yeah. I mean, it does kind of sound fun. It
is interesting. I think what would happen more is that you'd have the data centers that
are being built out with, you know, they'd be able to say, we're, we're, we're working
with us companies. We're using us renewable energy, you know, that kind of thing. You
could really see that being a branding thing. I think I would buy one if I could plug it
in and at the same rate that I listen to podcasts, I can invest that back into those podcasts.
So it's like a one to one. Wouldn't that be something I like the way you're thinking.
Okay. Then the last little, Oh, go ahead. Somebody else wants to jump in. Yeah. I was
just going to say that I would possibly, if it was, would do like alt coins. I don't know
about just Bitcoin itself, but I mean, I would probably pick it up either way. I'm trying
to get into crypto right now. So I have another question. Um, what else could this thing be
good for? Or is it so purpose built? That's the thing about a six. Yeah. They're like,
they're like application specific processors. Um, optimus gray in the chat room points out
that if you could maybe have it pay itself off in a year, I wonder, I don't know. All
of that said, I would be shocked. It'd be stupid. It'd be really stupid for them to
get into a low cost mining with the exception of pools because the difficulty rate is at
an all time high right now. And in two years, I think it is, I don't remember, but I think
it's two years from, from about now, the distribution rate is going to half. They call it the having
the halving or whatever they call it. But anyways, it's going to have, so rewards are
going to drop down in half, same amount of mining work, half the amount of rewards. Um,
so that's going to make the price, the operational cost to mine Bitcoin more higher. And so you
got to imagine it's going to be even less appealing to average consumers and you're
going to have more of these public companies that are now Bitcoin mining companies. And
the really fascinating thing that's happening there is these Bitcoin mining companies are
holding their Bitcoin a because they think the price is going to go up, but B because
it's an equity that looks good on their balance sheet. And so it is attractive to investors
to buy their stock if they're holding Bitcoins. It's like this weird proxy way for companies
to get in on the Bitcoin action via the stock market without having to actually own Bitcoin.
They just buy stocks in these mining companies that are holding their Bitcoin. And yeah,
that's weird.
Like people buy stocks and people, you know, when you, when gold is up, people buy gold
mining stocks. Sure. Yep. And they don't have to hold the gold directly. Uh, and you know,
it, it, it seems like a, it seems like a way for companies to get in on the action before
they can own the pure asset directly without having to go through all the hoops that large
companies already familiar with that system. Comfortable. Maybe. Yeah. Are we going to
see a big push in the next, you know, before that drop happens to mine like crazy? I wonder
maybe it seems like a huge incentive. Yeah, I will bet. They better get on it. Just about
that time. China's going to realize what a mistake they made kicking all the miners out
and they're going to be, they're going to be kicking themselves. So Apple shipped an
estimated 22% of the global smartphones in Q4 of 2021. Uh, which is not bad, but it's
down from 23% in Q4 of 2020 Samsung is following up. So Samsung is number two at 20% Yame at
12% and Oppo at 9% with Vivo at 8%. And of course, when we think about these percentages,
we got to remember the insane number in the absolute term. So even the, you know, that
1% down difference ends up being a lot of millions of devices. I would imagine, right?
I would have to think, but it makes the iPhone the most popular smartphone during the 2021
holiday quarter, which is quite the feather in Apple's cap. Yeah. That's the thing you
can, you know, tout around in your marketing PR. Yeah. I wouldn't, I would imagine looking
up there on stage at some point and fluff their feathers about it. Uh, oh yeah. Oh yeah.
This is the last story that I thought was interesting. They want to talk to you guys
about, um, and this is by the way, I'm skipping, I'm skipping the other crypto stories. There
are more crypto stories in the general, but I'm just, it's enough already. Um, variety
is reporting amongst others that YouTube is winding down its YouTube originals program
after six years of pouring money. I mean millions and millions and millions into this hole.
They're shutting it down. They're only going to fund programs that are part of its black
voices and YouTube kids funds program. Does anyone remember a YouTube original? I, I thought
it was, you know, the first thing they did is they tried to, they really screwed it up.
They launched it with celebrities that were not native to the YouTube platform. Oh yeah.
Mistake number one. Yeah. And everybody's like, but I'm on YouTube to watch the YouTubers.
And so it took them about two years and then they figured out, Oh, we'll work with the
most popular YouTubers. So then, you know, like MKBHD and some of the others that I follow
started doing these YouTube originals, but they just sucked. They just were like, why
did they suck? Cause they were, um, they were like a low budget discovery program. Like
if you remember good old discovery TV, when you could learn about something. Yeah. Uh,
they were like that, but worse. And, um, you know, you go to watch sometimes YouTube to
see somebody that's slightly unscripted and what you get is a very flat scripted version
of a YouTuber. Cause there's a committee or something that's making sure that it's all
scripted. There's a whole crew there cause they're spending millions on these shoots.
And so it's a giant operation with an entire crew, you know, right producers, et cetera,
which is the opposite of what made YouTube successful. And it's just the most basic misunderstanding
of the very own platform. It shows you that the people in charge have no idea what they're
doing and now they're shutting it down. And you know, they wanted it to be the big competitor.
They thought they were, they actually thought they were going to have their own Netflix
on their hands. They already do. Just it's different. They could have, they just won't
recognize what they actually have right now. Yeah. And meanwhile we're like, just make
the platform better. And you know, some of the things you could do is just roll back
some of the changes you've made. You can just undo stuff. You don't even have to make new
stuff and they can't get that right. It's so sad. Just sell YouTube and they'll be independent.
I mean, wouldn't that be something? Wouldn't that be, although can you imagine Wes, the
operational costs of running YouTube? I mean, it has some of the best streaming, um, resiliency
out of any streaming service I use. Like I can watch a YouTube video in places I can't
watch any other streaming service. Well, they've been doing it pretty much everybody else.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah. You're both right. Yeah. It just works and they've been doing it for
a long time. They've got all these partnerships. They've got a good client that's good at adapting
to different bandwidth situations. And um, I also really appreciate the shortcuts that
you can use keyboard shortcuts on the videos. I'm constantly shifting sort of time speeds
and going back and forth, 10 seconds and that kind of stuff. I am always craving on other
platforms and can never get. Oh, it really feels like Microsoft's looming large. You
know, looking back at over these stories we just talked about, the one that really strikes
me as like this is going to have a long term impact on us is these Microsoft game studio
purchases. And it just seems like a massive headwind against the deck. I can't, I can't
help but feel some any other way about it. And maybe I'm wrong. Maybe most of the Microsoft
games are on steam, but the ones I've looked up aren't. I haven't done an exhaustive check,
but I think you're going to be forced to, you know, buy this deck if you like, say Age
of Empires, which is one of my all time favorite games. You guys ever play it? Oh, really?
Oh, man. Wes, you ever play Age of Empires? Oh, yeah, definitely. I mean, it's been a
long time now, but yeah, just a classic, you know, classic. What do they call it? But you
built you build up a society and you it's an RTS. Yeah, it's a real time strategy. Exactly.
And I used to play Stronghold a lot. I never really played Age of Empires a lot, but I
love Stronghold. So it's a similar, very similar game. OK. Yeah. Well, they own that too. So
we do. I think so. I think the studio that owns that. Yeah, I'm not positive. I don't
keep it. I don't keep extensive track of this. But every time I glance over it, their list
of studios and you know, because part of what happened is over the last decade, a lot of
these gaming studios consolidated and then Microsoft came in and bought the company that
owns three or four companies underneath it. So that's why they have a bunch of game titles
that we don't even realize because they've they've bought these parent companies. And
I wonder if we're not going to end up in a scenario where we've got these expensive decks
with these incredible AMD GPUs and these impressive feats of engineering to get the drivers inside
the kernel and everything working really great and hours and hours and hours and hours of
valve engineer time trying to optimize the entire graphics pipeline and make everything
as possible, get just the right screen, make sure, in fact, perhaps they even chose the
plasma desktop because of some of the limitations in terms of refresh rate on the GNOME desktop.
And then everybody ends up loading up streaming services to play games on a Microsoft server
and it's just an H2 64 video stream to the deck. That's a really sad scenario and it's
not going to be the only scenario, but it may end up being like.
Honestly, if I were Microsoft, I'd publish the Xbox streaming service in the Steam store
and just get done, get it over with and just let everybody use their thousand dollar deck
or whatever it is as a streaming device. Here's the thing. If they actually did release like
the the game pass for the Steam Deck and or Linux, I would actually subscribe to that
because I would do I would do I used to subscribe to it back when I was on the Expo. And when
I moved to PC, I just let it expire because I didn't really have a need for it anymore.
But I would subscribe to it if they if it worked on Linux because I want more games
on Linux. Yeah. The reality is, if you have the Internet connection for it, streaming
games is a lot like the promise of the consoles. You just turn it on and it just works. Every
time it's always updated. Yep. You know, and like with the GeForce now, they're there.
They've already read the graphics cards, one revision since I've been a subscriber. So
I just got an upgrade in my graphics. My only issue is until I had Starlink, I'd never
had service good enough at home to use game streaming. Our buddy Alex, actually, before
we just got on the air sent us a video. He just set up his Windows PC headless and he
set up the NVIDIA streaming stuff and he's using Moonlight. Nice. Yeah. And it looks
great. It looks so good. It looks like he's running it right there on his machine. Yeah.
He's got a nice high speed plan. So it does kind of make me go, oh, be cool to have like
a headless Windows box. But. I'm just not ready until you start having to administer
it. Yeah. Well, and what I'd really want is the ability to stream like three games or
four games. So, you know, me and the kids could play and then you're really talking
about a beefy box. It'd be easier just to just to do the gaming streaming service. So.
We'll see. I'm sure Microsoft is going to play. You can just pay Alex to set up your
own custom, you know, hosting platform. Hey, Alex, come on over. We'll do it on. We'll
do it on like a prox box and two GPU pass through. And yeah, exactly. Yeah. I think
it's like I'm down. I'm smiling and I can't hear my smiling. I think you're down for it.
I like it. I'm down for just pushing the envelope, I think. Well, there you go. There's the headlines.
That's it for today. There's a lot going on today. Tuesdays, I guess. I guess. Yeah. Tuesday,
actually, we've noticed. There's a lot of times when we move the show, we didn't want
a lot of news to help us make the show. It made it too easy. Well, it does give a few
days to digest the news. There is that come up with a good line on it. Because, you know,
your instinct really a lot of times is to just go hot on the mic with your first take.
But not always the best option. Sometimes it works out. But not always the best option.
And I think sometime in the next decade, you might learn that lesson. Oh, this is interesting.
Unrelated, I'm sure. Just saw this pop up. YouTube's global head of original programming,
Susan Daniels, is leaving in March after seven years. Well, the original program has been
going for eight years. Yeah. So not only are they shutting down the program, but she's
out. Hmm. That wasn't in the first headline. That came out later. Funny how that works.
Yeah. Huh. I guess that, you know, in a way is actually a healthy sign. I think there's
not enough corporate accountability. When, you know, a corporate initiative like that
fails, they really should be looking at why and make corrective actions. I mean, it sucks
to see someone lose their job.
And then I guess I hope, I hope that they're actually doing that and not just, you know,
acts in this position and not questioning anything further about how it went on for
so long, what the incentives internally were, etc. Not that I love Google, but like they
own so many things that I kind of like and or use. It'd be nice to see them get their
corporate house in order a little bit.
Mm hmm. That's a good way to put it. Brent Lee. Yes, sir. Why don't you tell us about
why you're still here? Why are you still here? Weren't you supposed to be home by now?
Yes. So. Hmm. Where to start, Chris? I guess it's tricky. I did move my flight one time.
Why did I do that again? Projects. And I stole your bag so that you couldn't leave. So that
didn't help. That's true. So I was supposed to fly out yesterday. But it so turns out
that Washington has this kind of unadvertised testing COVID testing shortage. Yeah. And
not just like a kind of a shortage. So you got to go to the next place over like state
wide shortage of code of COVID testing. Right. Right. To the point where like the Walgreens
and the right aides are picking up the phone and saying, hey, you've reached Walgreens.
We don't have any COVID tests. Can I how can I help you? The reason that's important to
me is that to get back into my own country in Canada, I need one of these before I can
get on a flight. And it has to be the PCR variety has to be the PCR one, which is the
one that takes a few days. It can't just be the the quick test was OK to get into the
US, but it's not OK to leave. So. It's been tricky to try to line up all the ducks in
a row to try to get home, really. So I think Chris and Wes are conspiring and have something
to do with this. But I had to. Job one was I kicked out the sunroof in the focus so you
wouldn't have a car while you were here. So that way you'd be reliant upon us for all
transportation. I get that. Yeah. Yeah. That was that was me thinking. I did that like
a solid three weeks before you came down. And oh, yeah, the repair place just can't
get the window despite the Volvo getting a new window in like a day or two. Yeah. Yeah.
This has actually been an ongoing. We have been trying to get a new sunroof for our Ford
Focus for a frickin month and a half. And it's just nobody will get us at the sunroof.
Like nobody has it. They just it keeps never like your tests. They don't tell you. But
then it turns out when you press them. Yeah, we can't get a hold of it. Could have said
that in the first place. So you ended up you ended up having to go all the way down to
the airport. Yeah. Wes was kind enough to after our Linux unplugged episode last week.
Sunday I always think Sundays are last week, but that's like the first day of this week
for some people. Right. I don't know why I think that. So anyway, Sunday, Wes was kind
enough to let me stay at his place and try to figure all of this out. But was it ever
a journey? The only testing place I could find and had yet to confirm had tests was
at the airport. I figured, sure enough, they have a lab set up right at the airport. They're
not going to want to run out of tests. Right. Yeah. Well, and people's entire like transportation
plans hinge on these damn tests. That doesn't seem important to airlines or testing places
at this point. But so Wes and I figured after much consulting and exploring of options that
it would be best to just go there and to just assess the situation. And of course, they
have a website and of course, you can book an appointment. But it's all over the place.
Like there were no appointments until after my flight should have left. So I just figured,
OK, well, there's no way I'm getting on this flight with what I require. So. I had to call
the airline, but the wait times are crazy, like 50 minutes. So, Wes, you can certainly.
You know how long I stayed on the phone and I got kicked off. Oh, my God. I mean, it must
have been like six hours of total hold time. It was ridiculous. And holy crap. Yeah. The
thing that was most frustrating is the last time I did this, which unfortunately was only
a week ago, they had this cool system that everybody should have where they would just
call you back and say, oh, OK, the wait time is going to be like an hour and a half. We'll
just call you back. No problem. But that option never showed up this time. Of course, different
phone tree, different number. Who knows that stuff? Well, and really, the other thing that
is sort of ridiculous is when we were in Denver, you had to go through the same process and
there was plenty of testing available at Denver. I could just show up at a Walgreens, do a
drive through test and it was free. Yeah. But now as time has gone on, we've bungled
the system up so badly that we have less test availability and they don't want to panic
people. So they're not saying anything. Yeah. And the other thing is the cost. The only
test I could find at the airport, which it turns out they could do a test and I got in
yesterday somehow by some miracle, is 250 US dollars. You know, basically the price
of your flight home. Basically the price of my flight home. Wow. Think about that. So
I actually have COVID right now. Oh, I'm sorry, man. Oh, it's all good. Very, very mild symptoms.
So not really worried about it. But I thought, you know, because I found out by taking one
of those at home tests because I was feeling a little bit under the weather and it came
back positive. Um, but I was, I thought for work I'd have to go get a PCR test. So I was
looking everywhere for them, uh, try to find one and I can't, they're out everywhere. My,
the closest appointment I could find would be next Friday or this like upcoming Friday.
And I eventually called work and this was like, Hey, just FYI, I have COVID. I got it
from an at home test. All right. Found out from the at home test. Um, but, uh, I can't
find a PCR test anywhere. They're like, Oh, we actually accept the at home test. Now I'm
like, what? Well, that's good. Yeah, it is. I'm glad about that. But I was like that,
that information was never communicated to anyone. Of course not until, until it's an
absolute, right? They need to find it. Right. Yeah. It's kind of weird because for the PCR
test, you know, it takes several days. If you go through a lab to get these results
unless you pay $250 and it only takes 60 minutes, but you know, so, but what's curious about
that to me is, you know, I take the test 72 hours before I'm actually flying. So what's
the guarantee that I didn't pick it up in those 72 hours? So, yeah, you could get sick
while somebody comes over to the studio and then you had to, I mean, I was coughing all
over you or I could even get sick while I'm waiting in line to get these tests because
it's these giant lineup seems very likely that you would be exposed at the airport actually.
Exactly. That's what I mean. They're not thinking through the whole system. And so it seems
like it might be a better idea to take several quick tests, like maybe, you know, two days
before you leave the day you leave or something like that. And then, and then you have more
data points. I don't know why that's not a thing. Sounds cheaper. Well, you know, this
whole thing just got off, just got started. So, you know, give us a couple of years and
we'll have it figured out. Oh yeah. I know it takes time. You know, here would be like
have the 72 hour one, right? And then maybe while you're waiting in line at the airport
to actually take off, they have you do the Binax like the, the rapid or the essentially
at home test to say, Hey, I don't have COVID right now.
Hey, you know, I've been, these guys have heard me say it a dozen times, but I don't
think I've actually said it on air. But if fricking Joe Rogan can rapid test every podcast
guests for the last year and eight months, we should be able to rapid test ourselves
before we get on an airplane. I mean, it just is so silly, right? You said that on the unfilter
one. Yeah. Yeah. I'm filter, but nobody listens to that. So I can say it again. Um, so I want
to get a new beverage and then, um, we were going to do an impromptu brunch on the air,
right? We probably, uh, we probably have a couple of minutes while I refresh. So, um,
we could slip in probably one more topic. Oh, what do you think? Anything else? Any
other? So yeah, basically you had to delay the flight. So that way you had time for the
testing to clear, which means I get to work on a few other projects. That's true. It was
really fun. So many projects. Were you impressed West when you came over and saw the state
of the bathroom? Holy crap. Yeah. I can see why we're trying to trap Brent here because
I mean, we can just get so much more done. I know. Imagine what I could get them to do
for the RV, right? You know, one thing I discovered at West's place, cause I had the chance to
stay over, which is always a great thing. West, your shower is plumbed incorrectly.
Oh, the hot water and the cold water is backwards. It's a ridiculous thing. Um, I grew up in
a shower like that. So it's kind of normal for me. Well, I didn't even notice. I cranked
it to like, Oh yeah. Most checks, cause as you might imagine with travel, you know, most
checks, I have an average of where most places. That's okay. That's a good way to put it.
But I'm like, okay, a good place to start is like the three quarter mark. Cause it's
generally not scalding, but if it's a little too cold, then at least he got the hot water
kind of coming through. I did that at your place and thankfully I tested the water before
getting in, which I don't usually do. And it was frigid. So I quickly sort of had to
figure that out. I don't actually know. I'll have to warn future guests. Yeah. Right. Make
a nice little sign with. The other thing is you have a lovely washroom. It's got this
skylight with like daylight coming in, which is my such a luxurious way to do it. But your
shower curtain, there's just a man staring at me the entire time I'm in there. Why does
he have as a shower? Are you not used to that? What does he have? What does he have as a
shower curtain? What is it? Is it, uh, what's the gentleman's name? Oh, he's got, he's got
this hilarious Jeff Goldblum. Jeff Goldblum is like there with an ape and he's got his
arm around an ape or something. And it's just see-through enough that you can also see Jeff
Goldblum's, you know, mug while you're trying to take showers. So anyways, it ended up being
a great experience. I'll post a link in the IRC for anyone curious. I mean, if you got
a stare at something, right? Like I'd rather that than boring old color. Oh, it made me
smile. So there's something to that. Um, did you ever see the, um, Jeff Goldblum had a
show for a while? Um, and one episode I watched, yeah, I'd like to watch more. One of them
was all about shoes and he, you know, he's got this way, but it was a fascinating exploration
into the world of high-end shoes. And then I think that may have been the only episode
I saw. But, um, if anyone's interested, I say dive right in. It was, it was really well
produced and super funny and like kind of quirky and awkward in the way that I think
most of us in this community either are like or love or have come to appreciate. So it
was really nice.
It's nice when he's like, um, it's always nice to see genuine curiosity and excitement
about stuff, you know, and he can portray that pretty well, I think.
I completely agree with that. And yet he's okay to say when he doesn't know something,
which is really important.
Mm-hmm. Yeah. That's the other part, right? That being, uh, being cool enough in your
own skin to be like, nope, no idea what's going on with that.
My frog is out today. I tell you what it is out and about, uh, we have a studio frog and
he is all over the place. You know, this has been a lot of fun. We should just make this
a podcast. Wouldn't this, let's just figure out how to turn this into a podcast.