Before we get started I got to give props to mr. Popey who pointed me out to this pretty sweet deal
Over by googs. You can get two gigabytes of additional Google Drive storage
If you just do a security audit check up on your Google account really seems like kind of a good idea anyways, right?
Well, yeah, I mean pay me to do something. I should be doing anyhow. Yeah
Yeah, you know you're not okay to call it the googs anymore, right? We got in trouble didn't we? Yeah, we did
I gotta hear the story. There's just people are complaining as usual people don't like
Yeah, people complain about system D. But we like that. So no, I guess googs is actually like a slam term in some areas
Like oh, oh, it's a cultural thing. Okay. Yeah. I'm I know that see I got googs. I didn't know Google
Yeah, I didn't know that either
Googs is actually kind of an endearing term. And meanwhile, no, they're saying googs. He's a guy who walks around wearing Google Glass. Yeah
Well, a good comparison is if you walk into a house in the 70s in the US and you say wow look at that shag
You're talking about carpet you do that in the UK. I'm pretty sure you're talking about two people doing the monkey
So, you know, I mean it's it's cultural. It's cultural. You could call it Google
It's like it's like if Google and I were like lovers
Like oh googs like that. We might know what my love nickname
Boy, there's there's really here's the thing Chris because I always have to start stories with here's the thing
The thing is I don't ever call anything by its actual name. I don't call Walmart Walmart. I call it Wally world
I don't call Google Google. I call it gooks. I mean I have abbreviated names for everything. It's an opportunity for fun
But I might they might be confusing it with that word. I do the same thing. I call mate a mate
And Tara gross and I don't know
To it's to two distinct syllables. It's supposed to be my tape. Yeah, right, right
Mate pay attention to feedback Chris. Yeah, I know
Once again, I can't help but point out that all of you will say something wrong at some point
And so long as you get the message across it doesn't really matter how you say
Oh, that was so beautiful. I know it actually made me feel better about myself
Welcome to the Linux Unplugged show or a weekly Linux talk show. That's definitely stuck in the Pacific Northwest rain
My name is Chris. Hey, my name is soggy
Right, I I was really nice my wife and kids stopped by a few minutes before the show started and
You know, that's that's a nice treat when they show up in the middle of the day
One of the benefits of working for yourself, I suppose but you know what wasn't so nice
What's that? You know, I go out there to be you know, just say goodbye and you know, sure
you know get everybody else situated buckle in the kids and
I wore my jacket and in that time I got rain and it's a pretty heavy jacket
I got rain through my jacket and the shirt underneath I'm wearing got totally soaked. So I'm standing here. Oh wearing wet clothes
Man, you know, they they that's funny. They have these things on sticks that apparently project the rain around you
I think they're called umbrellas
And living in Washington, I'm just you know, I should have stock
Well, it's it's manly in in this day and age to have an umbrella. It's no longer like a city we could do that now
Okay. Yeah, it's totally okay black umbrella. You're fine
Well Matt we have a great show today umbrella notwithstanding
Later on in today's show after we get through the feedback. We're gonna talk about Ubuntu phone. It's here. It's real starting next week
You'll be able to pre-order yourself a BQ phone run Ubuntu touch
We'll give you more details about that what the pricing is gonna be what the software situation looks like right now
We're gonna pick up Opie's ear on the launch event. They had an insiders event
I don't know what the heck that means, but I know people got their hands on special units. That also sounds very interesting
That in the show and then we're gonna really do a deep dive on this because normally we would
Cover a lot of this in the Linux action show on Sunday, but Linux action show this week was pre-recorded
So we didn't get a chance to fit this in so there's so much to talk about
So we're gonna we're gonna go in deep on that this week. But first gotta talk a little about own cloud 8.0 just came out and
I wanted to kind of noodle around with the mumble room see who's in the mumble room using the own cloud
So let's bring them in time appropriate greens mumble room. Hey guys
Oh, so we got a great note in the subreddit from seal 20 and
He's talking about kids from a rose
I was wondering how many people use own cloud in the last community and for what with the release of 8
I thought it'd be nice to ask the community. I'll start by describing my use case
He's got it on a cent OS 6 VPS own cloud 7 soon to be version 8
He uses that obviously the core own cloud components the contacts the gallery the documents the tasks news music chat
Calendar all that stuff. He's got six users on it. He's using mobile apps using cal dev and car dev and own cloud sync
Completely he's using as a complete replacement for Dropbox almost a replacement for Google
He shares photos with it shares files that are too big for email
Isn't currently using encryption has about 300 gigs in own cloud
Anybody in the mumble room currently experimenting with own cloud maybe done the upgrade own cloud 8 by chance
I have fun cloud now, which you know, is it so I use it. Yeah, I'm still using 7
No, what are you using on cloud for now? I yeah. Well, I started unbeknownst to me
You're not supposed to put all of your data into own cloud. It's not it's not quite there yet
Oh, so somebody forgot to tell me that and so I put every last bit of it
I tried it for a couple of weeks first on my laptop and everything worked out great
So I moved all of my data that I carry my laptop on a daily basis to own cloud and for the first couple of months
I thought I thought things were dandy every time I'd restore my laptop, which is you know
Once every three weeks or switch laptops
I would I just sign into own cloud and all my files would show up and then one day I went to look for a
File and it wasn't there
And so I started doing I started doing comparisons of the backup side made of my laptops and realized that over time
I had just been slowly losing files. No, and then what well, yeah, and then I brought it up to everyone thinking that everyone
Would have a solution and everyone's answer was yeah, you know that that that happens with a lot sometimes no
Well, so
I'm kind of out on cloud for the time being well, yeah
Yeah, I've noticed a lot of people online say I use own club, but I don't use the sync feature
And and then I think that's kind of how I use it. I do use own cloud sync
But I only use own cloud sync for a director that holds maybe 200 text files
That's about all I think and a few pictures things like that that I'm using for in production stuff
And then when it gets to heavy lifting for sinking
That's when I go bit torrent sync and I use a dedicated sync system to handle a lot of file sinking
I have to had issues with own cloud more in like I get all in and then I start hitting performance issues
Haven't had that as much with the later versions
So I've been bit a little bit by own cloud too. So I am a little trepidatious
What I use own cloud for today is card dav and cal dav sinking. I
Use it for minimal file stuff. Like for example, we have our assets for our shows
women's tech radio or how to Linux or Linux unplug that there's you know
You have PNG is of the logos and you have whatever the designers sent you the file and all this stuff that we need to share
Amongst people own clouds great for that
Outside of that I have ran into a few issues that have made me go kind of slow
And another one that we got in this kind of along the same thing is a 19 caster in the subreddit
And big bold letter says read the documentation
Before you upgrade to own cloud 8 because if you just do a pseudo app just upgrade it could break your own cloud install
So there you gave some links what you need to read
So if you if you are upgrading to own cloud 8 soon
I checked it out. Anyone else in the mumble room want to share their own cloud story
Yeah, I've really never had a problem with own cloud
I'm running on cloud 7 on open VSD and it's a manual install of own cloud
Not a not a distro install or anything like that
And honestly, I use it for syncing my files and I've never had a problem in this
Quite a few of us that use it that sync across
own cloud different files different folders all that sort of stuff and and I haven't noticed any any
File drops or anything like that and and performance wise it's been spot-on. So no problems here
No, do you remember what version of own cloud it was where you had data loss?
And I'm wondering if it was like if it was like seven seven
Oh, oh, I was gonna say like if it was like version six or five
I think that's when they initially introduced file sync
My question is to the gentleman that was just speaking
Did you have you do you have any files that are over like six or seven gigs?
And have you noticed any problems with those?
No, I don't true. I don't try to push that that size file in Australia. We our uplinks are absolutely pathetic
So we we sort of don't push big files, but I mean, you know
I've got a couple hundred Meg files and the checksums are still still spot-on on those. You know, they're ISOs. So
Yeah from from my point of view. I don't move gigs, but that could be a PHP limitation where you've got a configuration issue
Post yeah, that is that is something people that are running on cloud installs often run into is like settings in their PHP config
That prevent file size or timeout issues and things like that is a is a common issue
And the guys talk about that they do address that
Yeah, I'm running it on nginx with PHP FPM. So that's the only difference. I bet that's it
Well, I bet that's a pretty good setup though
Oh, yeah from a performance point of view. It's stable. It doesn't use system too much system resources
It's actually only running on a on a
VPS of you know a 512
Meg of RAM and you know, 20 20 or 20 or 30 something something only you use or do you have multiple users?
Now multiple users
Very nice. Well, I'm glad to get this
So we got it. We got a little mixed input mine
Mine has been somewhere in between what Noah's experienced, but I have had some issues
So just take it easy and start what I do is whenever it comes to data like this
I start slow, you know, and and I'm sure Matt would tell you to have a backup
Always backups for your backups. Yeah, and are you still are you still primarily using bit torrent sync matter?
Are you kind of now?
Are you been able to get off the box sauce because I'm having no getting fully off the Dropbox sauce still
I tend to use Dropbox for more of a I won't say backup because that would be entirely accurate
But for more long-term sending things back and forth as far as like over the web
But as far as like just on the land bit torrent sync is definitely what I do
It just makes sense because it's easy if something breaks, it's stupid easy to fix
You know, I just haven't had any problems with it
And I'm gonna give a obligatory plug for sync thing because we always get in trouble. We don't mention sync thing
Yeah, I I happen to like bit torrent sync a lot because I publicly share keys with folks and we sync over the internet
But if you if you don't have that requirement and you're like doing LAN thinking or syncing even not over land
But just a few machines sync thing is a very viable option
Yeah, I like bit torrent sync, especially when it comes to large files. Yeah, it doesn't give me grief
I don't have to worry about it. It just works and I can walk away and go have coffee. It doesn't matter. Yeah
Easy. Hey, you know one way you can make all of this work is with a digital ocean droplet
Whether it's own cloud or bit torrent sync or even sync thing
Digital ocean would be a great place to host that head over to digital ocean comm right now
In fact right after this one of our next emails is somebody's hosting something really really really cool on digital ocean
And again, it gave me a great idea of something I might try but I'll show that to you in a second
Uh digital ocean though. It's it's a it's a perfect opportunity for you to play with something like this or put it in a full
Production like we do here at Jupiter broadcasting. That's the great thing about digital ocean because of the value that they have you can go
You can easily easily justify going over there and and setting up a machine purely purely for educational reasons, right?
But because these are all SSD power because they have tier one bandwidth because it's Linux and KVM
You could also put in a full-scale production like we do and like my co-host on quota radio does for his clients
He puts their client back in app stuff on digital ocean and you can transfer those images around
It's great because digital ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you to get started
Go over there in less than a minute
You'll have your own cloud server spun up and pricing plans start only five dollars per month for
512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte of frickin transfer. That's amazing
And they have data center locations in New York San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam in London
So you can get that deal that geo diversity go out there and set up your own CDN or
Quite honestly one of the things I use that for and it's a small thing
but it to me it's like it's a nice thing I can do for the unfiltered audience without much cost because it's just five dollars is
I have a
Droplet in New York and I have a droplet in San Francisco and I have a droplet in Washington
All right, I'm sorry. I have a server in Washington and all three of them act as like a three-way CDN
so if you are in on the East Coast you can pull from my East Coast server much faster than you're gonna pull from my
West Coast server and if you're across the pond you can pull from all three locations at the same time and all of them come
From different routes. So it's it's a really cool way that I did like a cheap
Really kind of overnight bit torrent sync CDN and it's is a perfect probably not but man
Does it do the job for five dollars a month plus?
I've got other stuff running on that rig and I'm always setting up new droplets because it's so quick to get started that interface
It's like it's no it's no barrier at all
I can just sit down and get working because the control panel is so crazy intuitive and you can replicate the control panel on a
Larger scale with their API so that way if you end up getting a lot of droplets
You can scale the management of those droplets using that API taking advantage of tools already created by the community or ones you create
Yourself if you got the skills plus they've got great tutorials to help you get anything set up you need
This is really a great combination. They're taking Linux, right? They're taking SSDs
They're taking all this tier one bandwidth in these connections that they've managed to get in these great data centers
and they've brought all of it together with incredible customer service a
Expanding community that means great apps great tutorials incredible value backed by Linux
It's awesome digital ocean.com. But here's the thing. We got a promo code for you and you can use the promo code do
Unplugged digital ocean unplug do unplugged lowercase all one word do unplug get a $10 credit
Try out the $5 rig two months for free and see all the things you can do with it. Go deploy something amazing
That's all yours
It's extremely gratifying digital ocean.com do unplugged and you get that $10 credit trap the $5 rig two months for free
Go all in a big boy
Absolutely, you know something here
I did recently as I was working with a client and they were looking at setting up something with Moodle and that's like
Oh, well, you know I can set Moodle up and when I was googling around sure enough. They had a
digital ocean tutorial
Very very awesome and it was cool because I could go through with this client actually show them how it was being set up and what
All these things meant and all that sort of stuff. That's very awesome
Yeah, you know and that is a nice piece of mind for them, too
Is I'm gonna set this up on a digital ocean droplet right you and I ever part ways
You're not high and dry. They've got all of this information for you and you can yeah
That is slick and you know more and more when I'm searching for stuff
I'm seeing the digital ocean tutorial show up in the search results because they're just they're just great
So David my favorite. Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah. No, that's to say my favorite part was where they're like, oh, hey
That's great. But you have control over it because it's on your droplet and like ah, but I don't and I clicked a few buttons
It's yours. Yeah, it's your droplet. Yep. So David set up something kind of cool on one of his droplets
He says I'm a longtime fan of less and I want to tell you about a project
I have been working on it's a website called distro Plaza running at
Www.distroplaza.com you guys can go check it out while I talk about it if you want and it lets anyone upload a torrent of any
distribution for free
Every distro upload it gets a download page a forum a blog and a place for users to review the distro
Distributions also get user groups where they can use where you just can stay informed about what's going on with their favorite distro
Distro Plaza launched in January on digital ocean. Thanks to the awesome promo code JB provides
I would love to hear some feedback on distro Plaza
And if you think any other features that would be good for distro Plaza, I'd love to know you can check it out
distro plaza.com
And so we're looking at it right here. And so the idea is you have a you know
You have a distro you love a lot you upload the torrent
So now they're seeding the torrent here or part of that they give you the forms. Here's the official Ubuntu forms
Here's their forms for it. Here's blogs. It would be specifically around Ubuntu. It's empty
I mean it needs content. And the other thing is I think it needs content from outside sources
I don't think you can depend on self-generated content. That would be my feedback to distro Plaza, but
It's kind of neat. It's a neat idea. It is a neat idea
Yeah
I could definitely see a direction where this could be really really powerful
Like a one-stop place to get information get the downloads the thing is this has been tried before so you got to really figure out
A way to do something different here. I think right right. I I would I would caution against so I would go one direction or the other
I would definitely caution against the community aspect of it unless you're vetting specific people that you trust or at least you know
No, I'm gonna just spam spam your stuff. You could try that approach
But I think really the idea of showing folks that you know, you're this type of person
You should be looking at these distros
You're that type of person you should be looking at that distros and look at the other attempts that have been made try and fine-tune
That dial it in a little better. I don't know
Maybe some previous things failed. Yeah, cuz there's some that have tried that aren't really that great
This actually is very clean. I like the layout. So good. It's very promising mumble room any thoughts any advice for our friend
David who wants to set up distro Plaza a place to feature distros and talk about them and download them
No going once, okay
Nobody had well, there you go David
You got Matt nice advice and the the mumble room will check it out after the show perhaps you can you can to listener distro Plaza
calm one last topic and then we're out of the feedback
I know I know but I want to give everybody a chance to chime in
I love the community interaction. In fact, it was one of the reasons why we started this show. It's wax of the reason. Yeah, so
Well, right then it sounded to me like Chris was pronouncing you block as you block, but I think it's pronounced mu block
He's not even shitting. You know the one that spelt you block. It's actually obviously it's a moo
Yeah, how because it's actually a Greek you so it's pronounced
Oh, yeah, like a micro since it's a lightweight regarding but anyways, he says back to adblock plus
I started using adblock plus shortly after it started even back when there's no option to allow Google text ads
He thinks that people care too much about it the acceptable ads program that we talked about last week
It's easy to change subscriptions in adblock plus so the one doesn't have a whitelist ads if you don't want them
But I think adblock plus is playing with fire a little bit. It reminds me a bit of the net neutrality issue
How block plus wants to provide?
To provide some privilege to some ads over others
Resources or money in other words and are necessary to review ads and decide what is acceptable and when it isn't they have chosen to
Let companies pay to be reviewed faster, which effectively means companies can get in ahead of other people
They will stay they will say that the prioritization does not impact their criteria for what is acceptable ad
But their money incentives for the program really don't line up with what is best for the user and this is something I didn't realize
I didn't realize that I knew you could pay adblock plus not to be on their block list
I didn't know that you could pay adblock plus to grease the wheels a little bit sort of like when you're getting a passport
You want to you want to rush it?
Yeah, see here's the and I I did and here's why I don't care because I mean I care in a sense
But I think it's important to really really take this way until it's being bundled into browsers or forced onto people
It'll take care of itself. I think it'll snuff itself out
I think he's gonna pay a heavy price for it because I think it's a bad idea
But if it was pre-installed, yeah, that would be very scary
That would be very that'd be frightening because then it then it isn't that neutrality issue at that point
Yeah, and it is you're right is the user's opt-in. So yeah, that's a good point
Yeah, but it definitely I agree that it's a it's a very shady sleazy not very long-term healthy kind of approach. So
Yeah, I still remain I still I think one of the reasons one to read this emails
I'm still pretty undecided on the whole ad blocking thing
I mean obviously where this show is an ad supported show and so I wouldn't want people to block ads on this show
I'm sure a lot of people skip them
I would hope they don't and we try to change them up a little bit
So that way you won't and it would cut it would hurt us
Like so if if there was such a thing as ad block for podcasts and 90% of the people listened
We would go out of business
Well, so here when it comes to advertising and this includes Adsense or audio ads
The thing you have to remember is is that advertisement?
Does it have any slim potential of offering a true benefit to the user our ads do we like them?
We feel that they're awesome things that we're excited about we want to share them
even Adsense to a limited degree, especially when it first came out did potentially offer some advantage to a user they go to a
Maybe a decor website
They're gonna have decor ads that might help them enhance enhance what they're wanting to do
Now that being said when you have flashing banners and pop unders, that's not a value-added situation
That needs to die in a fire. So, you know, so my philosophy on that is you know
People are gonna use these apps. They want to do that. That's fine. So in tech circles
Yes, ad blocking is gonna happen outside of tech circles. It's a mood issue
I think we're in a good position because our stuff is audio based and video based where it's really not as not as big
Of an issue in that regard except for obviously Adsense and things like that
But yeah, and I think you made a good point like it's the wash
It's on it and this is and then we'll get off this because it's not strictly related
But I guess this is why I have kind of kept opting back to turning off ad blockers is
Because if the publisher wants to publish a full-screen takeover ad
Then I want to be able to judge them for that
And so like one of them like you said one of the things is we make sure like the ads we pick
There's not a single sponsor. We have that, you know, we don't actually use like right exactly. That's a big deal
We actually like these so it's not like we're just you know, picking random people out of a hat, you know
And so yeah, that's that's where I think they so they cross the line
They sort of like they sort of take the audience for granted in that regard and they shove too much in their face
And it's never it's it's it can't work when you when you do that much as its noise
And that's why people I think resort to using ad block
I think it's and most importantly does it inhibit the user experience?
That's when an ad block is acceptable at any case in any scenario if it's in literally legitimately inhibiting an experience now a quick
Commercial before YouTube video is not inhibiting your experience
20 a few seconds in it gives you the option to skip it get over yourself
Yeah, yeah
but if it's a big but if you're on a mobile phone and you've got that big ad that just covers up the entire screen and
It's playing video and you can't find the X that's inhibiting my experience. They need to that needs to stop. Yeah
And now I would like to take a moment to tell you about vitamins and
And power shakes, yeah
I we the numbers been pretty quiet on the ad issue anybody have any final thoughts before we close the book on this topic
Mamba room. This is your chance
well, you know, it's
the adverts on TV and
Podcasts and you know radio or whatever. They're they're all a lot a lot more difficult to
Get away from than adverts on the web
I mean brevets on TV
I used to have a PVR that actually had an advert skip button and all it was was a
One-minute forward skip and I knew that I could go bam bam bam bam and forward skip through the TV others and I had no
moral compunction during that whatsoever right yet the
Yeah, and there's a big TV company and I'm paying for the delivery of that that service to my house
Anyway, whereas an independent
Content creator on the web. It's it's a different story. There's like
Sometimes one guy who's creating that website and maintaining it keeping it running running the server and creating the content as their full-time job
And so I generally don't run adblock at all
Unless the site looks like a bag of crap like for Onyx in which case I will
So far that's totally that's totally larval like you're explaining these one guy runs the whole thing he matches all of that but yeah
Right. It's a tough line to walk and it's particularly hard. I mean not to not to take this in a weird direction
But it is particularly hard to monetize probably more hard than normal in the free and open source software community because oh, yeah
yeah, you know what I mean, so like I mean not necessarily I mean obviously people are willing to pay with in the I mean
Look at the humble bundle and our patreon people are willing to pay when they feel there's value there
But I think some people are a little afraid of that and I can understand people also pay when they're guilt-tripped into it
I mean look last week what happened to the the GNU PG developer guy story comes out and suddenly his
Donation goes from like 20,000 euros up to 120,000 years in a day
And you know when people feel guilty about it, then yeah, they they will throw a few coins in in sure
So, you know help maintain it but often they won't do anything
You know people will pay the minimum for humble bundle no matter what anyone says about the fact that Linux users pay more
Many people pay the absolute. Yeah
They they need to so, you know, and everyone's in the same boat. Nobody has like buckets of money for us, right? Yeah
It's a lot of things also try to get under Google's example when it comes to things
So they don't really know of many other alternative ways to fund their project. They just do that the Google way had
otherwise
Yeah, but I think having or asking or saying that you need something and if it's a really good project like, you know
GNU PG or
AdLock if you ask their users and you have a good product that's worth paying for well, I pay for it. Mm-hmm
Yeah, that's exactly how I feel, too. Yeah, I'll make two points is I think that it really behooves the content creators to do their
due diligence and
Looking into who's advertising and how they're advertising such as you guys do and the other thing is, you know
sometimes you'll get caught up in people using ad block because of all the sites that don't do that due diligence and
We have to be reminded to go turn it off for your pages
Mm-hmm. Well and read it has a nice approach if you use ad block and read it
It says hey, you know, you're using ad block and that's cool
But if you don't use it, they actually have a little banner that appears to says hey
Thank you for not using ad block on our site. Yeah, that's that's the way to do it
I find reddit ads are pretty pretty tame. Yeah, I don't really mind them at all
And and I do like being thanked for turning off ad block
I know that's a stupid thing, but I do kind of like it. It helps. It's psychological. You can't argue. Like you know what? You're welcome
Because that exact little thing is what's reminded me in some instances
Oh, I have ad block on or you block and you go turn it off. Yeah, and I just whitelist them now
I mean, it's like I'm okay with that. Yeah. Yeah, good point. All right
Well, you know what a chat room wants to talk about it
Maybe in just a second before we get into the world just real briefly then we're gonna be a bunch of fun stuff
Chairman really wants to talk about this Raspberry Pi 2 problem. Oh, yeah. So yeah, okay. We'll do that
We'll do that. I think we'll have a quick one on that
Why don't we you know what? We'll mention one of our great sponsors one of the ones that we use one that I've used for
Over two years now. I've been a ting customer for over two years. I think math clocking up on that, too
It's got a really close. If not, I mean, it's got it. I mean really it's yeah, it's got to be close two years
and so I
Can say now confidently that I am truly a ting user and I do recommend them start by going to linux.ting.com
That's gonna give you $25 off your first device now
I'll tell you why that's a big deal here in a second if you have a ting compatible device and because they're adding
GSM there's more and more all the time
You're gonna get a $25 credit that credit might just pay for your first month. Here's why?
No contract
No early termination fee. You only pay for what you use what you only pay for what you use. I know I know it's crazy
You're here's what you're saying. You're saying Chris crazy things too crazy. They can't afford to do that. You know what you're wrong
You're wrong Kyra's here to tell you why?
Ting keeps rates simple. We don't make you pick a plan instead
You just use your phone as you normally would how much you use determines how much you pay each month
You can have as many devices as you want on one account
That's good
Because when you use more you pay less per minute message or megabyte of data
Your usage plus six dollars per active device on your account plus taxes is your monthly bill
Simple that's what we mean when we say
Mobile that makes sense. Yeah, go over to linux.ting.com just get that savings by the way remember how I said that $25 matters
From time to time ting get some great deals in on my fi hotspots
And they just got back in the Novotel my fi 5580 once you go to linux.ting.com
That's a $96 tri-band LTE hotspot
$96 you own that thing. It's not it's not locked either you own it
It's yours, and it's six dollars for the line
You can even turn that off when you don't need it, and then you just pay for the data usage
Why wouldn't you just have that in your pocket now?
They don't have this device all the time, so I mentioned it right now again. It's the Novotel my fi 5580
$96 tri-band LTE hotspot with a LCD screen on the front that gives you your signal stats your connected devices your battery information
What type of cellular network you're on and this is great even if you just use it when you travel?
This is an unbelievable value, and they got every kind of device you'd want start by going to linux.ting.com
And if you have any questions you can call them at one eight five five ting
FTW also on their blog right now if
And I know from some of the emails
I've gotten net neutrality and title two are on your mind ting has been very upfront about their position and
What they think is important in this debate and discussion, and they have another blog post up on there
It's on its ting.com slash blog
But start by going to linux.ting.com to read that
And they also up on the blog have a tip for how you can download Google Maps for offline use if
You're gonna go somewhere. We don't have signal or you want to save some data
Turns out there's actually a really great way to save the maps in Google Maps offline
So you can get them without even a connection they have that up on their blog as well linux.ting.com
And a big thank you to ting for sponsoring linux unplugged and thank you all of you for out there and trying them
I can say I really do recommend them and by the end of February
Things are really gonna get crazy for ting when they're rolling it when they're rocking
GSM and CDMA at the same time that is it's gonna be huge huge. Who else is doing that nobody exactly nobody else is doing that
Linux nothing calm
Okay, so real quick
I guess it turns out this new Raspberry Pi 2 that we were talking about last week
If if you expose it to a bright flash like a xeon flash like on a camera flash
Not just like room like you don't just turn on the light
But like you really explores it to a bright light it like kills power to the device and causes it to reboot
So you can reboot a Raspberry Pi 2 by flashing a light at it
So what you're telling me is no Raspberry Pi's can be used in
porn studios photography situations, I mean like so
I mean, you know, well, I got one in my basement, you know, so you just totally killed my dream here, right?
I mean, it's like oh my god that just that totally just see I can't that just totally changes everything
I gotta go and get nuts or something
I know I think people just find this to be funny because it's probably not and I guess there's even like an epoxy paint people
Already using to cover up the chip and and make it so it's not but it's just it's hilarious. Oh
In a go-go way you have something to comment about lasers on the Raspberry Pi. This sounds um
But someone I was reading a reddit. Someone also said the laser also affects the Raspberry Pi and does the same effect
lasers freaking lasers
On their head
Yeah, I didn't I don't know what to make of this but I know people that adore them I thought that was funny
So yeah
Is it me or does it strike me as Jerry Springer in a way like you could actually have a Raspberry Pi sitting on a on
A chair and you know the other person with lasers and flashlights attached to them having this conversation
I don't know the whole thing just seems silly
I was picturing like like elite government agents who take over like a
Middle-eastern compound that using Raspberry Pis by going in flashing lights at the Raspberry Pi is causing the security grid to crash and then they
Infiltrate and drop troops in and and it's a big American
It's the next big American movie and it all happened because they flashed lights at Raspberry Pis
No, that's pretty in-depth
That's where I was going with that. All right. Oh any other thoughts?
They'll just put that in the black hatchet or something. Yeah, sure. Yeah, exactly
Advertising as a feature you could yeah, you know, you could set up lighting in your in your server room
We have a bunch of Raspberry Pis and you could flash the lights when you need all your servers to reboot. There you go. Yeah
All right. Yeah, let's let's let's talk about what we're all really here gathered today to talk about and that's this new BQ phone
That goes on sale next week. It's like around 170. I think what is it? Like probably like a hundred?
I don't know about 175 dollars. I don't know what it's going for exactly us
and
There's even a little video now. I don't think there's a lot of words in this video
So I'll just I'll just put up on the stream so we can look at it
I mean, it's it's definitely a very fancy video after all of the waiting
I mean it I know it's only been a couple of years, but it feels I mean, that's a long time
In the scheme of developing something like this. That's not actually a long time
But more people sitting on the outside. It feels like a long time
And so this is this video is extremely well done. I hope I don't know if you know any of the background on this video like
This is the first time I saw it was last Friday. It was it was shown off at
An event in London and I'd never seen before and actually that's at the bits where you see outside
They go on top of a building is actually on top of our office building
Yeah, I can recognize certain, you know parts. Oh, that's funny in the video
Yeah, I think and we'll have the video linked in the show notes
I think one of the things the video does really well for me is it it's essentially without being too obvious about it showing me
You know kind of how Ubuntu touch would sort of fit in with like the ideal daily lifestyle that of course nobody truly lives
But if you live that like it I get like contextual information becomes available to me just by watching that commercial like it's surprisingly effective
Life at your fingertips is the slogan. That's pretty good. This is really well done. I
Think so, I think they did a nice job with it. I think it's gonna be interesting to see where it goes to
So the Aquarius e4 5 4.5. It's 4.5 inch screen, huh?
Well, so there you go, so the bq phone it's not like it's not a screamer of a phone
It's not gonna blow you away with its stats
It's got a 4.5 inch screen runs at 540 by 960 resolution
1.3 gigahertz quad-core ARM Cortex a7 media tech CPU a molly 400 GPU at 500 megahertz again
Media tech 8 gigabyte EMC storage 1 gigabyte of RAM 2150 mil amp battery dual micro sim and 8 megapixel rear shooter
As far as first goes it's not bad, especially if you consider that, you know for a certain sector of the market
That's plenty phone. Oh, yeah
I think anyone coming into the smartphone space for the first time is gonna be pleasantly surprised and I think that's really where they're gonna hit
Their sweet spot now, that's where I would target. I think that seems like that's what they're doing now
It's not launching in the US yet. Yeah
But it is available it'll be available I wonder I wonder if I'll still be able to buy it
The the
The event that will happen last Friday there were 30 people invited from this is around the world
Yeah, it's called the yeah, the insiders event the Ubuntu inside is they were actually invited a couple of months ago
We built a list of people that we thought might be interesting to come along and and see it
and there was a couple of journalists a couple of video bloggers and
some
some like blogger bloggers like written bloggers and
Members of our community developers and what you might call outsiders from the community
Just come along and we give them a phone and they get to be the the first
People with one of these devices
We also gave them a few little tidbits of information over the over the month leading up to it
and then we flew them out to London on on Friday and they they came and saw the
that video and a couple of talks by
I was a guy from BQ there. There was a
Couple of people from canonical giving talks
It was really good fun
Phone right?
Yeah, we gave them all phone and it was in a special presentation origami presentation box
there was a phone and a
Pair of nice headphones. Yeah, it even it even warranted the Ubuntu phones first official unboxing video
Which omg Ubuntu picked up and ran that Ubuntu phone box is slick. I gotta say that's a nice looking box
it was funny the
We were asking them. Look do you mind if we video you?
Opening because we know what it's like, you know, people want to see the thing on the box
Yeah, and so the video that you're showing now of that's Jordan Keys
Unboxing yes his he actually ran back to his hotel room
Or ran back to another room in order to to do that and then we went out for beer in the evening while his video
Was rendering out and then he uploaded it to YouTube when he got back after a few beers
It was it was good. It was a good day
I noticed too that I noticed that they come with a
The the insiders edition came with a very nice set of just headphones like an extra perk there. That's really cool
yeah, yeah, we wanted to give them a little bit of something extra say thank you for taking part and and you know
Coming all the way to the UK
I mean some of them flew over
Some of them didn't have far to come but it was nice of them to come over and just take part and and give us
Feedback as well, you know, we've been capturing feedback from them
You know, I was walking around on the Friday with a notebook old-style paper notebook right now
We're saying hey what about this and how does that work?
And why is this like this and I was making lists and you know
I've been giving feedback to developers and filing bugs like, you know
Doing all the due diligence because these are the first people that have seen them outside canonical. We've all seen it evolve
You know, I've had one of those phones since August last year and I use it every day
But there are things you just don't notice and then when someone
Why why is it doing allowing me to do this? Anything? Oh, wow. Yeah, you're right. Yeah
It's just something because you use it every day. You just don't think that's yet. Very much do that
Yeah, very much. So that is very true. So so actually they they go on sale as a flash sale starting tomorrow
Which is Wednesday the 11th of February at 8
8 o'clock
UTC so it's 9 central European flash sale means only gonna be available for a limited time or suckers like me
Are we gonna be able to buy it or is it only gonna be a region?
It's all day. So it's 9 9 the central European time till 6 central. So 8 till 5 UTC
So yeah, it's a fairly lengthy amount of time throughout the day. It's not like, you know, a 10-minute flash
So it's not like the whole world has to be dos. So I might actually website for the day
I know you could try
Yeah, I'm certainly going to bed early so I could get up
It's like Christmas for me tomorrow because I'm gonna be ordering one. Obviously. Yeah, you know, we're all gonna be ordering them
Are you pretty excited?
Yeah, it's it's you know, the fact that you know
I started working at canonical three years ago knowing that this was gonna happen and
It's taken a long time for us to get here and we've you know
we've had a lot of flack along the way and the method by which we've developed this and the software choices that we've made and
the
Hardware specification of the first device, you know, this is remember. This is the first Ubuntu phone, right?
Hopefully one of many devices, you know if we come back on
unplugged episode
600 they'll be you know a plethora of these phones out there who knows
You know, are you already looking at the next device a little bit because I know they we've already said the next one is there
Yeah, yeah, that one's gonna be a little more like a larger screen, right one thing and yeah
It's yeah, it's quite a bigger screen and more it's more cores more round, you know
Yeah more and bigger of everything. But yeah
How important was it, you know
You mentioned that you've had one iteration of this another since August is that part of why you know
you got to start and you kind of have to lock in the specs at some place and then start developing for that and so
This bq phone. Yeah, it's sort of been locked in for a while. I take it
Right, and so we initially were you know, we've had loads of different hardware over the the time that we've developed this
We started off with a tablet edition on an Asus transformer TF 101
Yeah
And we've moved through very and Nokia n9 and various Samsung galaxies and Nexus devices and you know
Then we got a partner in bq so we grabbed a bunch of those devices and we started doing the hardware
Enablement and making sure all the apps work because you know if we've been focusing on the Nexus 4 then we discover that
Oh, actually certain dialogues don't feel on the screen. I was this thing slightly different
so so we have to make sure all our apps and the dash is responsive and you know scales down to
Devices of this size and it's actually made us more disciplined having a device that has
more constrained hardware resources is probably better for us if we had the MX for first and
Had your octo core with 2 gig of RAM, right?
We could have gone nuts and you know made some decisions that actually we'd regret later because we'd have to try and scale it back
whereas
from what I'm told
Even unoptimized on the MX for it flies along. I haven't actually got one myself
But I'm told it flies along
And it's you know, it's pretty good on this bq device and we've still got some more optimization to do
So yeah, there's still work and we're still ongoing and and the good thing is that we continue to deliver updates to that device
so even when we've moved on to the to the
MX for and the next device and the next device all the previous devices continue to get those updates
The MX for looks so sweet
Wow, this looks like a yeah. Yeah, I mean I want the bq just to have the experience
But I think the one I'm gonna land on would be the MX for this is an incredible phone
I want them all. Yeah. Well sure, of course. That's like trading cards. Yeah. Hmm. Yeah, exactly. Yeah
so
How much how much energy do you do you suspect canonical will put into?
Sort of like I don't want to know if a generic image is the right one
But an image that's essentially with some modifications that'll work on most smartphones. Is that something canonical ever come?
You can't really do that because the arm architecture so let you so there's a couple of things
Yeah, arm doesn't really have the concept that the PC world has in terms of a CPI and device discovery
You know, that's that that's very mature on the PC and you can have one code base
Stickers USB stick in it and it will boot auto discover everything and figure out what drivers to load at runtime
And the second problem is most
SOC is most of the chips that are in phones have
binary blobs and you know
That's that's sad and disappointing and but that's just the world we we live in right now
There are no free soft fully free software phones. None. No whatsoever
So whenever anyone complains to us that we're not a fully free software phone. Well, good luck finding one
Well, yeah, if you want to if you want to phone just phone calls
Right. Yeah, or is usable in any way shape or form. Yeah, so
We you know, we we have to build an image that is used, you know usable on a specific device
but that's that's actually where we've been quite cunning with this is that we have multiple layers to the
To the image that goes on the on the phone
There's the very base layer which is the device specific part and that's you know
There'll be a device specific bit for BQ a device specific bit for the MX for and then
What is that is that is that a specific kernel what what is that layer composed of?
Yeah, so that's the that's effectively the kernel and the drivers for things like the GPU the radios and all that the sensors
You know, so so for example if a device comes along that has a fingerprint sensor just for the sake of argument
You know, we might want to support that and there'll be a device specific thing driver
Yeah, we need to go in but on top of that is the second layer, which is the user space bit
which has got all of our
Ubuntu stuff in and the dash and then on top of that is your apps
But also the the OEM or the carrier can put their own
additional bit on top so so we control a bit in the middle that's that's the
the app the the
Api's and all the stuff people right? Yeah and the dash and the common bit that you would see across all the devices
The bit at the bottom is the device enablement
And so that means that when a new device comes out
All we need to do is do the device enablement and then it's the same user space that runs on those
And so when and when when we want to update an old device
We just update the middle section and the device enablement bit stays the same
That's a really good approach and you can see it means you don't have that fragmentation that that Android has we have you know
We can have as lots of different devices on the market and they're all effectively running the same code
well, and it seems like it's approachable by just a
You know a fairly well organized community could come together and say, all right
Well, we'll take on supporting the Nexus 4 for another couple of years or we'll make a Nexus 5 port and me as a more
sophisticated user could say you know what I know this community I'll go use their image because if I'm following you the only thing they
Would really have to modify would be that first layer that that lower level bits, right?
Right, and so someone has already created the Nexus 5 as you know, and you know, it has issues
It's not perfect hardware wise we're gonna continue to maintain the Nexus 4 Nexus 7 and Nexus 10 and then what other
wherever other devices come along that we have to support, you know for
Contractual agreement for things like BQ and Meizu and and and so on
So we'll continue to maintain, you know a whole bunch of devices going going forward. Hmm
All right
I got a couple more questions and then and then I'll open up the moment because I know they have a couple questions
This is really I I'm exceptional. I'm exceptionally excited about this because I know we've all I
We've all just been watching this and so this is a really exciting first step and I know the BQ phone isn't perfect
maybe we'll talk about that too and and kind of get poppies idea on sort of what expectations we should have maybe performance wise and
You know battery life and things like that. But first I'll tell you about Linux Academy
Linux Academy is a sponsor that I think is truly great for our audience
And maybe it's I'm a little biased
I I believe that when somebody or a group of people are extremely passionate about something if they can line up the right things
They can provide an incredible wealth of content and information
and I think this is so so perfectly demonstrated with Linux Academy and
To sort of validate this theory that I've been thinking of I sort of look at the other
Larger outlets for sort of semi equivalent content and it's just a joke. They so obviously are checked out. They're not Linux users
They're not passionate about open source. They couldn't care right they're monetizing and that's fine
There's just there is room for that
But if you're spending your money, why not go somewhere called Linux Academy created by Linux enthusiasts and open source professionals
Who truly believe in this stuff who combined with educators and developers to create a platform for you to learn things like?
Docker like OpenStack like just DevOps in general pearl python ruby
R-sync backups the basic Linux administration Apache engine X they have coursewares on all of this stuff
They have live streams that you can watch and ask the educators questions directly
You can choose from seven plus Linux distributions. They have scenario based labs at Linux Academy
So not only do they have standard lab servers
You'll receive access to their scenario based labs that put you in the middle of tasks common to everyday environments
So you'll actually get real experience with these scenario based labs
They also have a really really great community
So if you're maybe slowing down a little bit or having a downtime that community can kind of give you that boost you need
It's really neat and I've been able to kind of jump in there and get my feet wet from time to time and get an idea
Of what kind of things I might want to pursue and in fact this recently happened to me with Ruby where I was like
I I feel like maybe it's time
I just I don't want to get stagnant maybe keep myself moving forward pick some pick a new skill set to pick up
But I thought you know really probably be very beneficial for me to learn a little development
I've always been sort of been able to roughly read some stuff, but I can't really do much more than that
And I thought well we have some Ruby use in-house
Maybe I should learn Ruby and it wasn't really until I went to Linux Academy
And I saw kids can take five hours and 30 minutes to learn Ruby, and I don't know what I've got
I can figure out five hours
Like what I put it in that in that terms like I can wrap my brain around that that's a concept I get and
They'll let me set up a learning plan
So I just say how much time I have and then they'll work with me and they can do the same for you
It doesn't matter if you have a little time or a lot of time
Linux Academy is where you want to go check them out Linux Academy dot-com slash unplug go over there get our special discount I
Think you're gonna be really impressed
I think yeah, I know I've been you know I know I've been talking about Linux Academy
I've been talking about learning Ruby, and I'll tell you I
Think that realization for me has just sort of resubmitted
Submitted for me why I think this is such a great resource and why it can be such a great resource for you
And I want you to try it. I want you to have that moment
It's extremely empowering
It gives you a level of control over your future that I I think if you're if you don't have that it's worth going over
There and trying it for a little while. I don't have a better way to put it
It was it was extremely gratifying to know that I could set a goal for myself
And that this was a tool that would help me accomplish that goal, and it's not a bullshit goal either
It's actually making myself better educating myself and learning something new I would like all of you to experience that
Go over to Linux Academy dot-com slash unplugged
Get our special discount. Thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux unplugged show
I think you guys be really impressed all right, so mr.. Popey
I got to ask you now we've talked a lot of good stuff
Is there any disclaimers you want to make about like expectations like if I buy one of these?
Is there maybe gonna be performance issues you think it's gonna work, okay?
So the first thing I'd say is don't expect every single app you've got on you know whatever phone
You currently use to be there. We we you know we're realistic about this
You know we're new to the market, and we don't have the app ecosystem that the other platforms have
We just don't yet have the Skype and the what's app. You know they're not there yet, so you do have tell them
Yeah, yeah, which is really cool. Yeah, that's a neat mobile app as well. Yeah, it's it's open source
It's the codes on launchpad
You can you know contribute if you want to if you want to add features that that you've seen in other telegram apps then
Knock yourself out, and it even does badge like little numbers for unread messages in there. That's really cool
Yeah, and you get notifications and all that alright, so that's a good disclaimer. You're not gonna
Have all your apps probably pretty expected you could probably fill in some of the gaps with web apps
But it's just probably not quite there. It's not gonna be there for a while, but that's pretty expected. I think
Right and and part of this is you know I think some of the stuff we do have
Conversations with software vendors all the time you know we have a team of people who are constantly discussing
you know you should bring your app to Ubuntu or you should bring your framework to Ubuntu or whatever it is and so we're
We're constantly having those conversations, and we know that they're those companies are are
Keeping an eye on Ubuntu. Should we say yeah kind of seeing where things go and I
Have noticed what what the hell is it about you guys where you managed to get?
Just managed to get attention like no other company in the Linux space does like I mentioned to you today on the pre show
I was just digging around for stories for tech talk, and I just kept coming up with all these various outlets
They're not even really attached to the Linux or the open source community
Necessarily talking about it like for example the one that stood out with me this morning was I was going over some Bitcoin headlines
And one of the top Bitcoin headlines one of the top stories in Bitcoin today
Was the launch of the Ubuntu touch phone and if there was a Bitcoin wallet available for it?
Like it's not interesting to just see how it permeates it seems to reach out to a level of consumers
It's not like Apple or Microsoft level of reach, but it seems like a wider reach than pretty much
Anybody else in the Linux space gets and I've seen a lot more people talking about Ubuntu touch than I would have expected I
Think partly the fact that it's that
Real Linux device you know yeah, I know
Android is Linux at heart really
But it is a real Linux device in that you know you can SSH into it and do all the kinds of stupid
stuff that you would do on a normal Linux machine and and that actually enables quite a lot of creativity for
In terms of what you want to run on the device and and you talking about the Bitcoin wallet
There is a Bitcoin wallet in the store, and it's been in the store for a long long time about 18 months. It's been there
Central place I can go to find all the apps available for my Ubuntu phone
There is we we haven't made a web front end yet, but someone in the community
Looked at our store API and built one for us
So there is one and you can go to it
And I'll give you the link and you can put it in the show notes and you can browse the apps that are in the
Store and you can see the ratings and all the kinds of stuff that you would see on like iTunes
Q5 you had a question right
Yeah, now I'm gonna frame this poppy and that let's say this Ubuntu phone is incredibly successful
We're five years down the road
There's multiple devices out there my question has to do with that because one thing I've noticed with Android devices is you buy a
Device you load it up with apps everything runs great a couple years go by even though the you know your hardware is the same
The apps run like poo because of the automatic updates the programmers the developers of the applications are now building them for
the newer hardware which then doesn't run on what you have and I'm wondering if as
You know Ubuntu has you know older software updates for older repos if there's gonna be something similar on the phone side of things
so that if you get a phone
you don't have to worry about a semi planned obsolescence because
Applications are being updated and basically update to the point where your hardware can't run them anymore
So it's a it's a great question. I've been bitten by that myself
I have an iPad first generation and there's half a dozen apps on there
I just cannot run anymore because when I first run them they say you need to update me and when you try and update them
It says oh you need iOS 7 or you need iOS 8 or something?
And so yeah, I can appreciate that problem
one of the
One of the issues that there's a few issues one is you know
We can't necessarily control what app developers do if they won't if they see a new
device that comes on the market that has a 4k screen and
128 gig of storage and
16 core CPU and they want to do something amazing with that whatever it might be
Let's say they make the most amazing touchscreen video editor on Linux on a phone
that's got that kind of specs then yeah, I would expect that to run like a pig on the BQ device because this is a
960 by 440 display with a few cores and 1 gig of RAM so that you're gonna have a bad time and I don't
Think that's our you know department to start telling app developers. No, no, no, no
You need to write your your apps as if you're running motif on you know on a Pentium 200 in order to you know
Come into our app store. I don't think that's what she we should be doing. We should foster innovation and you know, the
Advancement of more complex and fun and interactive and useful applications on the device
I don't think we should bring them in in terms of the platform
We are trying to keep our platform as lean as possible
And as I said before having this as our first device
Helps us to get to that goal because we've committed to continue to maintain this
Device, it's not like I'm not trying to throw stones but with the
Firefox OS first phone that I bought the ZTE open. There's no updates for it. Whereas the Firefox flame
I can move to Firefox OS 2.0
But I have no way of doing that that I'm aware of on the ZTE open and we don't want to be in that situation
Where we leave devices behind
You know, my question wasn't are you going to force developers to you know, maintain
You know like you can't
Do anything newer on your programs because of older devices what I'm specifically asking is will there be a way unlike for instance the Google
Play Store where once an application is updated
You do not have the option to reuse the older version if your phone auto updated unless you can somewhere find
The APK online to be able to sideload it like will write when an application is updated
Will the original older version still be available for those who don't have the money to go out and buy that new 4k?
Yeah, that's a good question actually and we're working on the best way to do that
Yeah
whether we whether we need to support having
multiple different versions of the same app in the store to support different versions of the framework of different versions of the
Devices that we've got out in in, you know consumer land
we haven't got a solution for that at the moment my workaround is that I
Personally mirror all of the clicks in the store every single day
So I have a copy of every version of every app that's in the store on my home server
You know, that's my personal way of doing it. But yeah, you you
You might be able to manually back up those click packages
Yeah, I mean if I wanted the old version of telegram for some reason I could maybe somehow keep that
I mean, it's you could we've got the tools you can you can get a click package and you can side load it over a
USB cable and just type a command and it installs it
You know, I I have done that today installed loads of because I wanted to test the upgrade process
I installed a load of old apps on the phone and then went through the upgrade process
So yeah, you can do that kind of thing
We do make it possible for you to side load old versions of stuff. Is that something that canonical will try?
Well, would they have a problem if someone in the community took up that role of hosting all the older versions?
Or would they be okay with that?
well, we got to remember is that the packages in the store are
Licensed under certain terms and they're not necessarily all GPL the developers. Yes some of them
Yeah, it's up to them whether their apps are you know?
Distributable redistributable or not, you know that and now it's something you would have to check, you know
There's actually some some decent apps that I use like readability and instant. There's an instant paper web app in here
There's a rotten tomatoes. I mean some of these are web apps to be sure but hey
You know web apps fine as long as it takes me right to it for the most part
I don't need things to be native for like rotten tomatoes
Right, and there's a few games, you know
We need I I would love for there to be more games on there because you know
I'm the same as anyone I sit there and when I'm bored, I pick up my phone and start playing stupid games
There's a couple of really good ones. There's one called machines versus machines, which is a really nice
desktop tower defense game which is infuriating and I'm almost a hundred percent certain canonical have lost a lot of productivity over the
last
Game in there. I like this a lot. This is really neat
It is that I'll have a link to this app store website me pulling in the reviews here
This is really tiny tiny RSS app. Very nice. Oh, very cool
Yeah, I mean the nice thing that that store nobody asked him to do that
he just noticed that we had a well-documented API for the store and so he created his own his own web front-end and
Put it on github. So anyone can can can do that. I've noticed a couple of other
Questions in the IRC. Yeah
So and I go go says is there tethering the answer is yes and no there isn't a gooey for at the moment
But I think it is possible with a couple of commands. You can tether to the device
And we do plan to have it so that you can press buttons in order to tether in the same way
You would expect to do that on other devices. And the other question is is there a mobile terminal? Yes
Yes, of course there is
so it seems like
For a lot of us the selection of apps won't be a big deal
But for the average consumer like, you know, an audible app is kind of important maybe ways or something like that
That's gonna be the big fight, but I guess that only gets solved after some hardware has been on the market for a little while
Right. Yeah. Yeah, exactly. And once you've got a couple of those out there and you can go to places like MWC or
GDC or you know any of the conferences over the next six months and start waving the device around and say look, you know
We've got this
open hardware open platform with you know hardware in the in the market and you know
Here's our SDK and here are people who've developed apps and here's a selection of code that you could look at to show you
How to develop your own apps, maybe we can get people ported
I mean, I I thought I understood the difference
I thought I understood what a scope was but I got to tell you some of these apps in here that are called scopes
Look like apps. I don't know. It's like this gmail scope looks like an app to me, but this is just a scope
Right. What does that mean? Yeah, so so the scopes are away, you know when you showed that video earlier
Yeah, the the people in the video were just looking at scopes. They were just
Take the phone out of the pocket and swipe to one side, right? You just swipe across check what the weather's like
It's all about
Specific information at your fingertips right kind of like right and think I've explained is Google now without the creepy
And the rituals you do every day like, you know
You check what the weather's gonna be like before you get before you get up you you know, you might
See what appointments you have that day to see whether you need to wear a suit or we can dress down
So you check your calendar and you all these kind of little things that ordinarily might be siloed away in lots of different applications
Like I have to open the weather app or I have to open my calendar app, right? I have to go and check my email app
And and rather than you have to open each of these apps one after the other that information is pushed to the front screen
So it's just a case of swipe swipe swipe and you see that information right there
I think that's that's the key goal is and that's where the whole you know
Your information at your fingertips is just a quick swipe away
Big deep in that isn't that what isn't that canonical saying in a way and they're not saying it's bad thing
But isn't that canonical in a way saying you know what?
Guys some stuff doesn't need to be an app your your stuff is is a feature
It's not it's not a dedicated app. Just write a scope
It kind of feels like a little bit like saying to developers. Sorry your app
I know you want to brand it you want to have a yahoo weather app and you want to give everybody the yahoo weather experience
But really people just wanna know if it's gonna rain that she could just be in a scope. Is that kind of the message?
Yeah
Do you think you know especially is and you can aggregate data from multiple scopes?
so, you know, I could say well, I I like the the
Weather reports I get from yahoo and I like the weather reports I get from the weather channel
But I also like knowing how windy it's gonna be
So there's this where this website where I go to find out what the winds gonna be like
So when I go surfing, you know, I have a better idea and yahoo don't show me that kind of data
So it's nice to be able to aggregate all of that kind of information
So you can get multiple perspectives on the same piece of data if that makes sense. Yeah. Yeah, I do like that
You get you can get alternative opinions
And of course one thing you'd the first app you'd want to get for your Ubuntu touch device is the jupiter broadcasting app
Well, of course, obviously
Which is pretty cool and it actually resizes pretty well, too
I think this is and this app this app is really well done the authors put
You know the host information right there and it's just a really well done app. It's really cool
It's it's one of the it's I think one of our best mobile apps out there
Of course, I love all our mobile apps, but I think it's one of our best on and it's on Ubuntu touch right now
So the author of that Simon was actually one of the insiders. We invited him along
so he's one of the people who got invited last Friday to come along and get a
Phone and the headphones and all that
Kind of thank you for yeah, I'm glad because I know working with him on that app
He was super excited about the platform or he is super excited about the platform
So yeah, and and the other nice thing is what we've said to all these people who came along last Friday
It's important to know that they're all they're not all
Yes, men, they're not all people who we've said you must say positive things about Ubuntu. We've given them the phone
They can say whatever they like, you know, we've had people
Posting YouTube videos telling us that the boot performance is bad. Yeah, telling us that the scrolling performance is bad
That's exactly what we want. We want them to tell us their experience not tell us only the positive things
Tell us what's wrong with it as well. You gotta fix that stuff too. Yeah, exactly. That's good
That's a good outlook to have about it. I think I I
I wonder if
You know if I even like a podcast app could be a scope thing
I mean, that's a fascinating thing that I think I want to play with more as I get the device and I wonder if I
Well, yeah, there is a jet. There is a generic cast app that's written by Mike Sheldon
He's one of the one of our employees. Is that the bird on screen keyboard?
Is that popular? Yeah, and I think he's looking at developing a scope as well
So you could just scroll across like first thing in the morning on your commute
You just scroll across to your podcast scope and it lists all the you know
Upcoming episodes or what's new in the book and you can just hit the button and make play
Rather than having to go screwing around with your podcast. Yeah, so
The other thing I think of is and then I'm then I'm then all my questions are done and we can
Wrap up but anyways people are sick of hearing about it. Yeah
One of the things like I know whenever we're writing apps for platforms is what kind of what kind of features is the platform?
Just gonna give me for free. Can it just do video playback?
Like if I just say put a video element here
We'll just do video playback or do I have to write the player?
Figure out how I'm gonna pull down the mp4 file figure out how I'm gonna break that up and play to the user
Especially when I'm moving on connections, is there like, you know, like on iOS there's like a core video
I'm a core is there anything like that on a bunch of touch yet? Or is that in development?
Yeah, there is so we have a bunch of core services that the platform provides. So for example
For example, there's location services so that if you develop a map app, you just request the location and
The user gets prompted to say do you want this app to know your location and you accept or deny and yeah
Then you're done and the app can then find out your location and that that location detection is provided by our location service
Similarly if you if you're writing a podcast app and you want to be able to download
You know video podcasts that take a very long time to download
you can
Use the download service
so when you choose to when the developer chooses to download a
Long video podcast it downloads in the background and then when it finishes it signals to the app that it's done
What was the other one? Oh media playback. So yeah, we have a media hub, which does audio playback
We have video playback as well. And we also have a media scanner service
So if you put your music on the device
It will scan all your music figure out what the ID three tags are go and get the artwork all that kind of stuff as well
Oh, that's really cool. And then last but not least how much do you want?
One of these cases that has the cutout for the notification thing
That is really cool. No idea that thing existed
It turns out the BQ guy who was at the thing last Friday had one and I just didn't notice it
He yeah, you touch phone gets its own exclusive phone case with a custom cutout for that little notification ring
That's how sweet is that? That's really cool
That's awesome. That is neat. All right. Anybody the mum broom have any questions for Pope before we wrap up on the
Idea, okay. Go ahead. W. Popey. You can answer not answer. It's totally up to you
Okay
My questions are if we import this to the US if like one of us decides to
would I be able to like put it on Tang or some other mobile network and
how good is like the Wi-Fi on this if let's say I just don't want to use a mobile network and
Just use it on Wi-Fi just to contact people online
So you could you could get it shipped to the US and in fact, we have some of our employees
Who are in the US who use it?
The downside is because the US uses different frequencies for 3G. You'd only get
GSM 2G
It does have Wi-Fi. So yes, it'll do
2.4 I think and 5 gig like I'd have to check that but
Yeah, it does. It does Wi-Fi perfectly. I I mine mine is mostly on my my Wi-Fi. Actually, I think it's only 2.4
Yeah, it doesn't do 5g. It's 2.4. Okay, so
Yeah, that's not too uncommon when you're bringing a phone over kind of depends on what bands are in it
I didn't last yeah, it's a bit of a bummer. You know, we get
Unfortunately, it's um, it's it's a bit out of our control
Okay, I had one last question
Could you do you have any insights to share about the integrated traffic data service that's going to be shipping with the phones in the UK?
And is that something we're gonna see more of where maybe canonical has a bit of a hole in in
Something the phone does that maybe some of the shipping ones already do and so instead you just partner with somebody who does that like
Like Ironix here with the traffic data. Can you you know, you know, I I learn about that from OMG
I'm too so Joey who runs OMG a bunch who came last Friday as well and you know, he writes a blog post or
Tweets about something I think oh, that's cool. I didn't know we did that. Yeah, so
These insiders are not just you know, I don't know
Maybe there was an ounce with I missed because we've all been heads down for the phone
Yeah, they say they say it's a partnership with I in our X to do or I and Rick's or whatever to do the traffic
And I think that when I saw that I was like that seems like hey, you know what?
We have a gap here and we can plug it with a partnership
It makes sense to me right and that's exactly what we did for the location services. So we you know, how
Android have Google have their own
Location services and Apple have their own location services. We partnered with Nokia here for our location services
So they provided some software to us that allows us to do the fast fix
Location detection so that it does a GPS when you're you know, when you're out and about near Wi-Fi access points
It can find you pretty quickly without that. It would take a long time to get a GPS lock. It's
Painfully long so we partnered with them. So yeah, there is a there is a precedent for us
Partnering with other companies to provide services for the phone. Hmm
Okay, any last questions for mr. Pope before we wrap this thing up. I
Think you just saw he sold me on it
Yeah, oh and we have a torch app. So, you know
That base is covered as well. Yes, gotta gotta be able to make sure I can
Find my way in the dark. Yeah, so very cool and exciting to see an actual ship date. So tomorrow's the day
Yep
Oh my gosh, oh, oh really so then there'll be another so there's gonna be another one later
Maybe yeah want I got to figure out what those times are Pacific time
And I'm gonna set an alarm and I want to try to get one. I
Mean seems like we've all been waiting for so long, right and it's not it's under $200. So it's a pretty good deal
Yeah, it's it's pretty cheap really, you know 126 pounds. What is it 169 euros?
I don't know what I is in funny money you have over there. Yeah, it's not it's not
Expensive. No, it's pretty cool to see it actually come to fruition
All right. Well, I think we'll wrap it up right there and if I get one eventually
I'll give you a review
However, it is and I'll watch it as it goes like I kind of other reason I kind of want to beat you so I
Can get the you know, I can get updates and kind of track the price of the phone
So I can get the you know, I can get updates and kind of track the progress as the platform matures because there's gonna be things
It'll be pushed out as you know, they find stuff and it'd be good to keep track of that
So very true. I'll give you a report next week. If I managed to grab one. It's already tomorrow here says Juba in the chat room
Well, that's true. That's a little confusing and the people could be listening at any time. We're talking to people in the future
I mean, how cool is that? We're time travelers. That's right. We're time travelers. We'll put Rogers
Thank you for letting us pick your brain all that. Yeah, it was a it was a good download of information
Yeah, thank you. Cheers guys. Yeah, congratulations to you and everybody over there to cannot seem for working your asses off to get this far
I think if nothing else, that's a hell of an accomplishment and just right there. All right
Well, then we'll wrap it up here on the Linux unplugged show. We'd love to have you visit us
Why don't you join us? You know, you could do this with us. Yeah, you could come over to the website Tuesdays
We start at 2 p.m
Pacific you go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash counter to get that in your local time zone and join us in that there IRC
Chat room share your opinions as we go or even better join us in the mobile room
maybe we can hear you and what you actually think about these things because I think
We have a pretty smart audience. You probably have a pretty educated opinion on a lot of this stuff. Why not contribute?
We're just gonna check your mic. You can also go to Linux action show dot reddit.com and submit content that way Matt
Have a great week. I'll talk to you next week. Sounds good. See you then. All right, everybody
Thanks so much for to this week's episode of Linux unplugged. We'll see you right back here next Tuesday
Okay, I've got a
$10,000 ethernet cable to sell you. Are you ready for this for a $10,000 internet cable? Yeah, let me get my checkbook
Now here's the good thing Matt
If you if you're willing to pay ten thousand dollars for this ethernet cable
Not only am I gonna include data in this ethernet cable, but for no additional charge on top of the 10,000
I'm also gonna give you high fidelity audio. Hmm. No, I just better be a unidirectional one
Cuz I don't want any of your cheap bi-directional
Now that I've got you interested I should probably disclaim it's actually ten thousand five hundred dollars for this cable
It's got an RJ 45 connector made from silver with tabs that are virtually unbreakable
The plug comes with the added strain relief and a firm lock to keep it in place that way
No critical data is lost silver, huh? I'm gonna wager. This is put out by monster. I'm just call that a hunch
You know what they're doing all this crap. Oh my gosh makes it sound better. Wow
It does look amazing though. This does look like that. It's got a really cool braided cable, too
This is the coolest looking HD or ethernet cable. I've ever seen I'd probably wear it like mr. T. I'll be honest with you
Audio quest diamond. Yeah, you could it would be a piece of jewelry. All right, JB titles calm
Yeah, I have a feeling it's gonna be something to do with the Ubuntu phone. I don't know could be yeah
Yeah, so, you know how you know how I talk about Chrome and how I like Chrome. Oh, you're a Chrome maniac
Yeah, so over the weekend my Chrome profile just got corrupted for some reason and now every time I launch Chrome
it thinks it's launched for the first time ever which
It's not like an unusable because it sinks so well and so fast that all of my stuff sinks back
but the one thing I really end up missing is my URL
Autocompletion and the reason why that's handy is turns out like I need to type while I'm doing a podcast often and it's really nice
If I could just type in JB T and then JB titles is automatically and I just enter so that way I don't otherwise
I'm over here going like hey, welcome to
Hold on. I got it
Hold on. I'm typing. All right. Welcome to the show. No, did you not restore your Chrome profile from your backup?
my what
Well, it's a fun trick that I've used I've never done this on chroma
I used to do it in Firefox a lot and I keep like multiple I I create when I
Profile. Yeah, and then I got all my autocompletes done and then I move them away and that way when it goes to crap and it
Will there you go?
I'm paranoid now. We're tinfoil hats. Ubuntu is calling is not bad. Ubuntu phones arrivals also pretty good
I like both of those. I like Ubuntu calling. It's cool. Ubuntu is calling
Very Avon. It's kind of working for me the Ubuntu blob phone. Oh my gosh. It's already starting
Yep, yep, ahoy Ubuntu. All right, JBtitles.com suck my googs. No, I suck my googs. Oh boy
Yeah, and I just got that out of my brain too. Oh, right. Yeah. Yeah. Oh, man
You guys hey might as well my you know what we started with it. We might as well end with it, right?
Yeah, it's the circle. It's the circle of life
Circle of googs