All right well before we get the show started there is one topic I thought
this is probably gonna be one of the top news stories in the Linux action show on
Sunday but maybe we kick it around the virtual lug first did you guys see the
story that broke this morning that factory for openSUSE is moving to a
full-fledged rolling release distro full-on rolling distro now what do you
guys think says the canonical guy we're in a year you know Ubuntu is gonna be
doing the same thing here's what I wonder is you know how they announced
that this next release was kind of just gonna be a maintenance release while they
worked on the back end stuff I'm wondering if this was a one-two punch
all along like well they knew they were gonna do this and so they had a lot of
replumbing to do and so they were working on this and and the way they're
gonna do this now is it's kind of an interesting system where there's still
gonna be some automated testing that goes in before it lands and instead of
having to do like big release candidates and and stable beta snapshots before a
big release is essentially they're just gonna firm this thing up as a release
gets closer and then just carve it off and say here you go well only you don't
make the the daily the rolling version of it like like a sanctioned what would
you guys call it a respin like I you know like from a yeah we do we do on the
phone this is exactly what we do right right right I'm interesting will come to
the desktop in the future so how does it work so on on Ubuntu there's not like on
Ubuntu phone there's just new builds all the time there's not like this is rc1
rc2 it's like nope this is just the latest building is every build then QA
tested yeah automated testing on desktops and devices in the lab like
physical phones in the lab probably much the same way as openSUSE we're doing it
and and then you you bless one that passes you know 100% clear testing well
here's what they said in the old development model an army of packages
would shoot new packages and updates to factory with a relatively small team of
factory maintainers taking care of the integration process of all those
packages this took a long time to stabilize and rip for release in the new
rolling release development model package submissions cannot go to factory
directly first they have to prove to be functional and trustworthy in a staging
project staging projects are projects in our open build service where groups of
submissions are collected reviewed compiled and tested with open QA after
the packages survive the staging project they go directly into factory so they're
using open build service and open QA to bang on it first and then that system
then I guess releases it into factory so when you're doing on your rolling open
SUSE release when you're doing a daily update you're theoretically pulling down
updates that the open QA process has already banged on this to me and what's
interesting I don't know if you guys have picked this up I got a couple links
in the show notes like the muck and a few other places are really really
really pushing as this is a comparison to arch they'll say well in arch they do
it this way or in a response to arch do you guys think this is really openSUSE
it trying to respond to arch no it's just is them responding to the way the
application developers are doing this if you look at the way that Chrome and
Firefox are pushing out updates to their applications they they have a very rapid
release cycle and you can you can very quickly get the very latest crack on
your machine by subscribing to a particular particular channel being like
the beta channel or canary or whatever and I don't think arch matters one iota
to openSUSE because opens the open build services supported arch packaging for a
good while now so they've embraced the arch community some time ago and I think
arch has claimed a lot of longer term power linux users now but I do wonder
how many of them are simply there because like Popey says they want the
freshest crack but if you could give them super fresh crack without some of
the arch hassle or you know arch intimidation that some people still see
arch hassle well the setup right and not having things pre-configured for you so
like that's only once you only do that once don't you once you've done that you
get the daily crack every day well who you telling you're a winner well you
tell me I know that but I'm just thinking from people outside that you're
kind of lying that you have to go through some magical hoops to get to
that goal it's only once yeah yeah I don't think that openSUSE's decision to
do this matters one I don't think arch was a deciding factor to be honest yeah
probably not I don't suspect it was more to do with fedora spinning off their
core and desktop next and all the rest of it initiatives I mean kind of like
Popey was getting to too though doesn't it just make more sense from a
development standpoint shouldn't this be how yeah oh absolutely but it's kind of
funny because that testing spart spot is the new factory the and factories the
new tumbleweed yeah is the way I see it it does see like I think so and tumble
weed I guess kind of goes into like it's still being used but it's not as
directly involved anymore I am kind of confused on yeah well Greg Crow Hartman
did write something in our it a kind of response to it yeah he at this point
doesn't know what's gonna happen to tumbleweed as a result of this but it's
not like a huge thing for him anymore it's kind of sounds like he just been
nursing it along for the last couple of months he says yeah so yeah that's
that's the gist I got from that if he consolidates them both into one then
less work for everyone and more benefit for everyone else yeah I know you know
soos has a kick-ass system manager and also they've got snapper that better for fs
snapshot tool right into the system manager so they've got a lot of maybe
just got the other PR kind of sucks and you know the other thing that's
interesting on the opposite of they have the evergreen which is essentially their
LTS so now they've got rolling I guess they've got something in the middle the
stable versions that they'll release still which will have which will have
support windows and then they've got the evergreen LTS style releases so now
there's the whole gambit there that they're spanning I really think this is
interesting because we were just talking what does open suits are really have to
offer the Linux community and this I think we're starting to see that come to
fruition manager maybe we need to step up the PR though you know get their
team going and like reporting and shit if they put the name out of open suits a
little bit more so then we're not just talking about it as if it's some you
know loner in the corner it might actually be good seems like everybody's
always talking about open system but nobody actually uses it well I wonder if
this isn't sort of isn't this sort of a tuck and roll to make them like to sort
of adapt to the changing way things are done in Linux and say okay we're where
we want to kind of pivot and become a great distribution for those of you who
want to really be working on the edge of open source software you want a system
that's been well engineered and that some real thought has gone into that has
some tools to make your daily Linux driving use a little bit easier like you
know things like yas and actual graphical update management utilities
because let's remember I mean yes we're up we've been talking about arch but on
arch everything's command line some people don't like that that sometimes
is enough for some people they just want a graphical front end to some of these
tools plus you got a big company behind it which makes some people feel a
little bit better so now you can say okay I'm a developer I'd like to have
cutting-edge software but maybe have it'll be a little more stable and tested
assuming that they can keep things fresh and tested and I want something that's
well designed and that could be people could be looking around going well open
Sousa could be the way to go and I think this is why it is more of a response to
fedora than anything else so then maybe this is really what they're bringing to
the table I think it's a response to the world everybody wants stuff faster they
have to do something to keep the market share up yeah do you think that maybe
the perception about open Sousa and its marketing and its message is regional
because certainly in Europe open Sousa is a big big thing everyone knows that
message gets through quite loud and clear yeah yeah I think it is somewhat
regional but then again I mean what we were talking about in the context of
last week is if you wanted not necessarily like in like it's great you
know the open Sousa does really obviously has markets it does really
well and what we were kind of making the case was is if you were going to sort of
introduce a brand new game-changing technology to Linux like systemd or some
standard desktop application container technology across the board or a
universal package format something crazy pie in the sky right if you were going
to do something like that could it be the open Sousa group that would be able
to introduce it and have it take off and I would argue we've seen some things
they've done that are really cool like like OBS or the gallery that you would
think other that were built for other districts distributions to take
advantage of that are you know like they're they're even paying the bill for
it and still it really hasn't gone outside of their ecosystem that's where
we were talking about relevancy before and I don't know if this changes that
position or not the problem with open Sousa is that they have a ton of awesome
ideas and they create like the OBS in the studio all these things are just
like concept wise they're awesome but they never fully finished them and never
polish them so there's a ton of breakage with the OBS I mean it's so much of a
pain to use the OBS that's why people just ignore it hmm I wonder if to by
being rolling and faster and more nimble like this if they introduce a cool
technology that maybe it gets faster adoption because people can get their
hands on it quicker and start playing with it sooner maybe also getting
packages into the factory it's a lot easier as well
welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show the rocks of beard and
knows how to use it my name is Chris my name is Matt I just you'll get the
beard reference later on I'm just gonna leave that out there now we got a big
show today because we got back from OS con and we're like well we have a huge
Linux action show and we still have more stuff to play so we have some exclusive
interviews from the floor of OS con coming up as well as our takeaway from
the trip some interesting trends we observed and also a plea if you will
plus we'll recap the trip itself and then later on in the show we got a
little stuff that's coming up that we could use the community's input on so if
you are a crux user or have looked at the crux distribution stay tuned towards
the end of the show we got a special call out for you guys Matt big show
today big show so let's bring in the mumble team so that way they can
assemble and join us mumble room prepare your minds for the feedback because last
week we dared to boldly venture into productivity land I had no idea you know
what people use Linux for getting work done turns out that's right not video
games no no no silly video games we like to get things done yeah yeah so when we
talked on the topic of productivity we apparently we sparked some feedback so
I'm gonna cover just a couple of them because I don't want to like the people
who don't care about productivity stuff under Linux I don't want them to tune
out so we got two two I wanted to start with our first email this week it came
in in regards to my Thunderbird quest which I didn't get like a great answer
but this one was a really great extension I'm by the way I'm looking if
you have great extensions to make Thunderbird really rock I'd love to hear
about like I got some of the basics like I have one that lets me see the mail
agent that people used to send me emails so I know when they're on Outlook and
I've also got you know like of course the GPG encryption for Thunderbird and
stuff like that but Mark wrote in with an interesting one it's called
conversation threads and he says I highly recommend the Thunderbird
conversations extension it displays email as a chronological thread rather
than a single message even if the emails themselves are spread across folders like
you know between inbox and sent which is pretty cool Matt I seem to remember this
since you said conversation thread I instantly flashed back to my Thunderbird
days yes it is an awesome application I have it does not care where the email is
it works great that's nice I like that it goes across the inbox there I have a
link to it in the show notes if you're a Thunderbird user and watch it I
actually I put this one on there the one thing that it does that I don't like and
you could probably turn this off and I haven't looked into it is it also
changes the way Thunderbird displays your email so it looks like Gmail and
the reason I'm using Thunderbird is to get away from the way Gmail displays
some things so yeah yeah there's a little bit of getting used to if I
remember correctly it does like little mini panes kind of overlapping and you
can collapse and expand and what right I was okay with it I was okay yeah the
benefit is that you can also use Enigmail for like encryption and whatnot
that Gmail can't do yeah so there's plenty of and some people like the way
Gmail does it right so that's then it's a win-win if you do I use it with
Thunderbird when I'm using Thunderbird when I just feel like it and yeah it's
amazing it just organizes it it gets rid of that huge thick header bar yeah
that's true that is nice Matt and I were scratching our heads on
Sunday one of the I think Matt you mentioned Nitro tasks I meant to mention
wonder tasks we also mentioned to do dot text for task managers under Linux
Randy writes in with a really great suggestion he says love the show so my
first time commenting on last 323 you had listener asking about a task manager
application as someone who is always searching for the perfect task manager
this caught my attention so I have a suggestion to offer of course here he
says its selection always depends on your particular requirements that's a
standard disclaimer but here's what he wants from a task manager and I think
we'll probably all agree with this cross platform so you can use it on any OS
work or home synchronized across multiple machines specific task
management features I like such as subtasks oh that's nice allows me to
print out my task list and scribble on it during the day oh that's nice too and
accessible from an Android device all right so this is this sounds perfect he
says the solution I found and I'm pretty happy using is task unifier pro task
unifier one word pro as a task manager which is very full feature gives me the
kind of interface I want it syncs with to doodle to doodle which gives me cross
machine syncing access on Android and as a backup I know some of the audience
might find this helpful he says I was able to finally settle down on one task
manager after a long search keep up the great work Randy so there you go it's
called task unifier pro I haven't tried it out yet but that list sounds killer
oh it sounds like because I've been kind of looking for something like that that
might actually scratch my itch yeah yeah and you can find it at task unifier dot
com it looks like here's a it looks like maybe it's a Java app actually
potentially yeah I'm looking at it right now I don't yeah it works for Mac
Windows and Linux task unifier yeah it's any operating system supported by Java
so there you go I won't judge it based on the Java thing I'm not a big Java guy
but I would check it out yeah had me until Java yeah I mean there is that but
you know I already I just what I just put job oh I got a new game I got a new
game that requires Java so now I've got Java on my computer so I already got
Java minecraft isn't new no not minecraft it's like a fallen sky I
think is the game have you guys seen this it's on Steam right now you guys
follow gaming on Linux remember we had the one the the main writer from gaming
on Linux on the show a few weeks ago he did let me go find it he did it he did
it he's been doing a really interesting kind of like from time to time he's been
emailing popular Linux game developers and getting them to actually release
their Linux sales numbers to him and yeah yeah and it's really it's not
awesome it's really not awesome usually isn't no he just he just posted part 3
on gaming on linux.com and the game that I picked up after this list that I
realized I didn't have he's got a whole bunch on here and some of them are
pretty good Linux like spy chameleon 5% Linux installs rust rust says that 0.4
and 0 1% in July so rust sales are 1% in July the fall represents 4.5 sales for
Steam and when you and humble if you if you factor all those in flash out to 16.1
percent of Steam sales are Linux well that's not bad 16% almost noticeable
quest of dungeons 1% Linux 5% Mac 94% Windows far sky with oh that was the
game I got 0.89% Linux that was that surprised me because far sky is actually
a pretty cool-looking game where you go underwater
and you get to explore an underwater world and find like cool stuff and it's
got pretty good graphics too and there's like underwater facilities I don't know
I guess it takes place in the future I just got it but it requires Java but you
have to survive underwater find food find items find money you have to grow
stuff in like hibernation chambers under the water obviously there's fish you
have to battle with so for the kid like the boy was like oh yeah I want that
game I was like yeah we could easily he's got less than 1% Linux sales let's
boost that up a little bit I think it would be an obvious game but maybe it's
just the fact that people aren't aware of it enough on the Linux platform that
yeah that's what I was wondering because after I got it I'm like yeah why is this
not more popular to be honest with you because it just gets cooler and cooler
as you play it too so it's called far sky and it's see it's it's maybe this is
why I don't know it's 15 bucks on Steam yeah I guess I might be a little high
for some folks but I feel like we've all gotten a little out of whack and what
our game pricing is it's been out since April so if you want to check it out you
can maybe boosters anyways and then the game go check out gaming on Linux where
they have have more stats for Linux sales it's it's getting better we're not
competitive yet with the Mac and I would say the Mac isn't quite on par with what
the sales need to be at so I continue to buy and I just like to remind folks too
that if you do if you do want to buy steam games you should do it under Linux
because then it counts always always yeah don't don't ever buy under windows
because at that point you're really sending not only mixed messages you're
sending the wrong message yeah exactly I think I think it's pretty so I mean
$15 for a game that's gonna give you hours of entertainment how I don't I
don't get why people aren't willing to fork that over I mean have they gotten
so spoiled by like the humble bundle and all these free-to-plays that they're not
willing to fork out $15 really people I think so and app stores have skewed our
perspective too I think it's app stores and I also think it's a matter of
something that the folks on the Windows platform will do often as they reach out
to be folks that do let's plays if you're a if you're a game developer and
you're not doing that you're an idiot I'm sorry yeah I mean it's like you are
really screwing yourself on that one because at the end of the day that's how
you get your word out for maximum cheap they got to learn how to market to the
Linux community because they've never really had to reach out to us before and
spread the word and you know I also I look I look at it this way too I think
that if if maybe it's one of these things where people start to it's gonna
take a long time to kind of warm over the crowd because it's been it's there's a
culture built up around it now and even when we talk about it on the show people
hate it even though it's like one of the biggest things to happen to Linux
desktop people hate it when we talk about games and we'll see what happens
with it keep watching it I hope their sales improve I really do because I'd
love to see Steam OS really take off and maybe it will once Steam OS itself
actually actually ships in in in more homes maybe like cuz you know you can
get Steam OS now but you have to roll it yourself hey I want to talk about
something huge that's happening on the GTK side that we have lambasted them
for right here on this very show because you know Gwadek's going on and so of
course we got to get some gnome news and I think some people are gonna be happy
about this be curious to get wimpy's reaction to first I want to tell you
about an awesome opportunity head over to Linux Academy dot-com slash unplugged
right now go over to Linux Academy dot-com slash
unplugged because they got a special promo going just for you guys it's the
summer of learning and you know there's sunshine out there and you need a good
excuse to avoid that sunshine absolutely right I mean who wants to get stuck
actually out in the nice weather not me my friends Linux Academy dot-com slash
unplugged but on a serious note this is a genuine resource for you to go and
take your Linux skills up to the next level they have so many really awesome
courses and you can see why you'd want to subscribe to this for example you
could just take the basic Linux level 1 exam 101 type stuff but then you can
move up through the stack everything up to introductions to Android developments
they they span the entire gamut plus they have seven plus Linux distributions
you get to choose from and the courseware then is automatically adjusted
based on the distro that you pick and they have downloadable comprehensive
study guides audio and video that you can watch and learn and listen to while
you're say driving or sitting at the computer doing the courseware they have
a ton of self-paced labs which is really cool because then later on you can go
back and quiz yourself and see what you've picked up this is for me I have
found a great resource to kind of see what do I have a into it for what can I
kind of pick up what's in my wheelhouse do I have an interest in this particular
technology do I want to learn Python these kinds of questions are so easy to
be answered just by going to Linux Academy dot-com slash down plugged and
get that 33 percent discount that's only $50 per quarter the other really cool
thing is they're doubling down on AWS infrastructure courses as well so if you
need to do a little Linux and AWS stuff they have scenario based training you
can go through and actually implement something so you walk away with an
actual usable product a skill set you could apply to a job something you could
put on a resume something that you can learn yourself to see how that system
works Linux Academy comm slash unplugged to get that nice deal so let me get the
straight if I'm in a hard place and it's like look I'm looking at gaining some
new skills and I've got three months to kill and I can pop 50 bucks forward I
get three months 50 bucks and I get a new marketable skill that's awesome oh
absolutely and there's a community there that helps like people to go out and get
testing and gives them support and answers and you know it kind of keeps
you going because there's people that genuinely care they're also doing a lot
of live stream events now so you can interact with the folks that are doing
the teaching so there's a good back and forth there it's an amazing resource
mat and what's really cool is it's essentially three Linux advocates are
like you know we need to have we have between all of us here we've got web
development skills we've got years of training experience we can build this
right and we know exactly what other Linux users would want from a service
like this and I think that's really remarkable because what you walk away
from is a new understanding of perhaps how a different distribution does
something how to deploy something I mean it is genuine tangible benefits that you
get to walk away from with a service like this Linux Academy comm slash
unplugged go take advantage of the summer of learning and you get to keep
all of the courseware the study material all of that stuff they have tests where
you can check yourself how far you've gotten it's such a cool service and I'm
so happy they're a sponsor Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and thanks
everybody who supports the show by visiting our sponsors okay I teased it a
little bit you guys might have saw this it was a blog post blogs.nome.org
client-side decorations is getting a revisit and they've posted some
screenshots now of different scenarios where you can have the GTK software
detect if you are in a client-side decoration environment and automatically
display those big header bars or if you're an environment perhaps it isn't
friendly to client-side decorations it'll drop them now and go back to a
more traditional look kind of on the fly this is sort of them saying all right so
the client-side decorations thing wasn't that well received we still think it's a
good idea we'll implement it in certain scenarios and we'll automatically remove
it in other scenarios and if you're watching the video version I'm showing
you some screenshots right now it kind of it's kind of a kind of like what we've
seen with gnome itself when they make these dramatic changes there's a ton of
blowback and then you start seeing things like classic mode and extensions
that kind of bring back functionality now you're seeing this people were
really responding like whoa whoa whoa whoa if GTK is going off crazy like this
I don't know if I want to be using this this seems like it's something just for
gnome and now this seems to be them coming back and say all right guys well
look no we still want you to use this in other environments wimpy you're you're a
mate guy I'm a tag guy you're using GTK and all kinds of different environments
is this good news in your perspective it is because it's gonna save us a ton of
work really how so well at the moment we've had to put some patches in to kind
of adapt client-side decorations because there are ways to override them at a
system level but they can still be overridden at the application level so
if you look at the new GA client-side decorations I mean actually it's quite
it's quite nifty the way they've integrated the menus into the title
bars there but you can't override those at a system level because it's kind of
intrinsic to the way the application is designed to work now but this approach
it does mute the critics and it does make GTK a platform that anyone can use
and and certainly go some way to silence in the critics saying that GTK is sort
of becoming a lib no library Popey did we just jump on him too soon were they
gonna do this all along when we just didn't let white out to see the final
version maybe maybe they've seen what Apple are doing with Yosemite and
they're following up and very quickly posting what what they've been planning
all along I'm sure you think so so why not come out from the very beginning and
say we're working on this but for non gnome 3 environments we're gonna have an
answer for you soon why not say that from the beginning there under no
obligation to do that it's an open source project you know there's no
there's no reason why you know you stamping your feet and demanding that
they tell you what their future plans are means that they have to do that but
doesn't this doesn't this go to what we have so often see in the community where
there's this abrasive sort of way of presenting the future from the known
project and then the community reaction says oh once again
gnome is shoving something down our throats and doesn't care what we have to
say there's just like this visceral reaction that you see on on reddit and
and and on on on discussion forms all over the web and it's kind of like if
they would just come out and maybe communicate slightly differently and say
our long-term plan is to solve something for everyone I do wonder if maybe those
initial reactions wouldn't be so much oh gnome is once again cramming something
down our throats I think if no spend all their time responding to reddit and the
rest of the gallery then they wouldn't actually get anything done I think I
think they're doing the right thing yeah and they definitely are I mean it sounds
like it's a good change regardless of they're gonna do it all along or if
this isn't about face this seems like a great change it's it's one of these
things to where I look at and go this is perfect because I really genuinely have
some GTK applications that I'm gonna use regardless of what desktop I'm on and
this has been a problem and you we've seen some of those horrible screenshots
of like archiver on cinnamon before cinnamon supported client-side
decorations really much better well they had to start somewhere as well true yeah
I suppose so I suppose they could have done this from the beginning but yeah I
suppose so all right even if it wasn't their idea that I mean like if there if
it wasn't their long-term solution and then you know they meant to just do what
they did and then people had backlash isn't it kind of a good sign that the
known project is showing that the listening and they're actually trying
to solve the problem that they are you know being informed about yeah that's a
great point is it does seem like either way they're listening more I have to go
ahead I have a house for no sorry to be fair to the name developers they've
communicated quite well what their intentions were with regards to
client-side decorations with the development community through through
their blogs and through their documentation effort and although it
wasn't received with open arms let's say through some projects that are dependent
on GTK the the developers that were affected by these decisions didn't throw
their toys out the prime and didn't get too worked up about it it was quite a
pragmatic reception and certainly from Marte's point of view in addition to
adapting to the system overrides we also abstracted some of the toolkit to change
the way that that GTK three works to suit better the style that Marte works
with but most of the backlash and vitriol that you see isn't from people
that know what they're talking about I think I think I think our favorite K
win developer probably was the most vocal about it and he's very technical
and very experienced in that area I agree that there are technical
commentators that have a point of view but the overwhelming feedback comes from
people that will read something that Martin has posted or other people that
know what they're talking about and then repeat bites of that about the place as
if they're expert on the subject and don't really know what they're what
they're espousing at all and it comes down to something we were we were kind
of discussing on the live stream on Sunday is there's a bit of sometimes it
happens is drive-by technologists that can come in and kind of fire shots over
this but I I kind of looking back at this now there was it was there was
certain people in the community that did very bloudly condemn it and what we
don't know now is if it was that vocal pushback that maybe for before I get on
Martin for going to the blog and going to Google Plus and sort of ramping up
sort of an anti client-side decoration campaign perhaps it was that very effort
that sort of convinced the known project to make these changes we don't know well
when when GTK 3.11 which was one of the development cycle it was one of the
point releases for 3.11 I know that a couple I think three of the developers
from the Marte project we're talking to some of the developers from name and
explaining some of the the difficulties we're seeing and and how it it could be
better implemented yeah and we and we already got a feeling that they were
like yeah okay we're going to address this in a later release somewhere and
we're good we're going to change the way that this is applied so you know from
our point of view we kind of knew that that wasn't a step down as such but a
change of direction to be more accommodating to other projects yeah and
I also I also noted when they originally started talking about the whole
client-side decoration thing it was couched with a lot of this is in
development this is a work in progress this is something we're moving towards
what do you think about us putting the buttons here you know there wasn't like
it wasn't it wasn't an ironclad this is how it will be designed it was this is
what we're thinking about I remember specifically like blog posts or like
here's a mock-up of how we could do it and it was very I actually think it is
an indication of how the gnome project has changed you're not just with
client-side decorations but really starting with about gnome 3.10 the way
they have been communicating their future changes to me is much more open
it's much easier to like sort of grok some of the new stuff coming towards
gnome and I think they're firing a lot better on the communication cylinders
now and I think it's definitely improving yeah I mean I think this is
another another thing another bump in that direction another another trend
bump you could call it definitely been my experience it's good news it's good
news everybody and also it's good news because arch and gnome are gonna take
over Linux in a couple of years so I mean what all right hey we have some
OSCON stuff to follow up on got some more goodies from OSCON and both that
Eric and Noah went down there with me so I I have a few photos I wanted to show
so if you're watching the video version you can grab you can just watch that or
I will have the link to the photo album in the show notes you don't worry we're
not gonna do like a big slideshow but I just want to talk a little bit about our
trip and say it right off the top a really special thank you to Noah Noah
went all out for this trip not only did he and his family fly out here a week
before they needed to be out here for a wedding they were going to but they also
rented an SUV so that way they could haul our butts around Noah FedExed out
camera gear and microphones like overnight so this is no and I driving
down Noah took me down to the train station where we where Eric and I went
to the yes what is it a Union Station Eric that is King Street Station in
Seattle Kings we went down to King Street Station which was really nice
riding the train is so much more chill than riding on the plane because you
just walk up like there's a there's a gal at the front she's like what where
are you going and I tell you where I'm going all right go sit over there and
then they they announced over a horrible speaker when it's time to get on the
train and then you just walk up to the train and get on after like like stamp a
thing and you go past a guy so it's pretty casual because you can just you
know it's like I don't know you just like we just walk right up and get on
there the train was nice too I think this is underrated way to travel and
plus you get a nice view the whole way you go Eric got the the seat view both
ways both ways okay did you get any good pictures you know I did I should
probably post those but I got some great views like the train goes right under
the Tacoma Narrows bridge which is a huge suspension bridge in Washington
State and it's I got some really neat pictures of that I got some pictures
like what Chris is showing on the livestream right now the st. John's
bridge in it turns out Eric is like a walking Wikipedia of road trivia highway
and bridge trivia out the wazoo it's ridiculous which makes it when I was
picking you up from the train station what about that what about what about
so here's Eric and I at the train station where we had an opportunity to
spend about an hour and 45 minutes well to be fair it wasn't really Noah's
fault so I mean to give Noah credit so Eric and I we get on a train right and
we're all being super like cash train has Wi-Fi the whole way down there so
that's really nice and easy it's kind of spotty but you get Wi-Fi meanwhile Noah
and the family unbeknownst to us are going through like a special like
welcome to Washington hell trip where like the mall they go to gets evacuated
when all they want to do is just eat and pee so then Noah drives the whole
family from Seattle down to Portland Oregon while Eric and I are on a train
then he goes an hour yeah and then he goes to pick us up and Google Maps sends
them like 25 miles in the wrong direction oh no well see that's your
first problem you weren't using ways this is the night before I saw and so
Noah's like Noah finally after a while like I'm like I first I don't want to I
didn't want to bug him because I wasn't sure like you know he's got the whole
family maybe you know like there's some stuff to settle before he leaves you
know so I'm like about 45 minutes go by and I'm like so how's it going and he
like writes me back he's like just so you know man this is nowhere near the
hotel I'm like oh dude it's like seven minutes from the hotel what are you
talking about so then we start like sending each other map screenshots back
and forth to compare notes all over vibrate no I got a nice tour of the
Portland Oregon area let's well I think he was driving too fast to see most of
it to be honest with yeah when he got there he came to a screeching halt yeah
like when he got there that the vehicle smelled like burned rubber cuz he was
funny that what put us behind the curve to begin with was we wanted Indian food
and we went to the Indian food that was probably so we go to this we go to go to
this restaurant and the restaurant is closed so we go down to this mall which
is nothing like ten blocks in in a different direction then yeah somebody
pulled the fire alarm so they evacuated the mall the funny thing was on Sunday
when we got back into Seattle we went back to eat to eat Indian food again and
we found an Indian restaurant literally like three blocks from where that mall
was go figure yeah yeah so we stayed at the Red Lion Hotel and which was nice
because it was only it was you know five minutes walking distance from the
convention center not a great hotel you can see here this is my curtain this
looks like something that Sound of Music would make dresses out of they were like
just it was like really distracting but you know what was what was chiefly
important OSCON day one I figure I'm in Linus Torvalds territory it's safe to
rock socks and sandals I proudly rock socks and sandals at OSCON it's super
comfortable it's the way to go and then we got some food there's a Noah rocking
his Google glass and Eric taking phone calls there at the food table making
business deals of course yeah and we saw one of the coolest things at OSCON what
was the hardware alley and I got some more of that in a little bit but this
here is Noah do you remember the details of this split keyboard where the guy had
handwritten all of the info and they felt so good yeah so essentially it's a
customizable keyboard so you can take the keys and you can arrange them any
which way you want it you have a picture of the metal one I know that board those
keys those keys what he's showing on the wooden they're not stuck in that pattern
like you can slide those keys any which way you want there's not in the picture
it almost looks like there's their specific spots where they have to go but
they can put them anywhere on the board yeah I'm somehow they work yeah they're
really neat and they feel really good we saw some custom like little arm Game
Boy like machines the guys were super excited about making them aren't we know
yeah yeah we saw the open so I think I had a little bit I have the open source
laptop and of course Erica Noah so there's Noah's camera and there's Eric
they're getting set up because we had an interview with Krista Bona I think that
was one of our highlights of the trip was getting to chat with Krista Bona and
yeah it's funny man because when you walk up to these places the way the
conversation goes is who are you who are you with if they don't recognize you how
many subscribers do you have and then you give them the answer and either you
pass the test or you fail the test and and thankfully we passed the test yeah
and here's a here's a great example like Zen you know the virtualizer they had a
booth and they had well funny enough they had like an iMac mounted in the
booth and then they had like Linux stuff being displayed on the iMac but they had
a pretty cool booth to sit at and Linode was there rocking some cloud hosting
information and then we saw like all kinds of funny like makeshift things
like there was this was a four node cluster that was built out of these
little machines Red Hat had a pretty good booth we stopped we'll have a
we'll have a chat with one of them here in just a minute there's me rocking the
OSCON boy towards the mid bit of the first day I was starting to feel a
little ragged because it's a lot of walking around it's hot but then you
know we started to see the fun side of OSCON like this giant chess set that
they have on the floor there there was a ping-pong table and then we got to chat
with Karen from the Software Freedom Conservancy which was exciting because
she's really like she's passionate so that got us all fired up again and then
we walked around we saw the open source laptop this is such a cool I mean I
think no is this maybe your favorite stop that we did which the hardware
laptop yeah the hardware laptop with these stegnographers keyboard that you
wanted to switch to over Devora it's really cool I'm not gonna deny that but
I have to say my favorite booth which I don't even think we have pictures of
what was the orange of s the blue right the appetize social that that right now
we don't have any shirt we don't have any pictures from that but they're
working on a really cool open source post to all social networks at once kind
of like your hootsweets out there but totally open source and free that you
can self host so if you're a company and you you have to manage a social media
account like a lot of distros do and things like that they have essentially
just go to their github repo check it out and you throw it up on your own
server and now you can you can manage multiple social networks with this one
open source suite and they also do other stuff like a parallel file system and
all kinds of other stuff but that was what we were really excited about I'm
gonna look at the file system too it looks actually pretty cool there's
another shot of the open source laptop really neat I just love a wood laptop I
mean it's it's no macbook air or ultra pro but it's you know it's pretty sweet
and the guy was really passionate talking about the different hardware and
stuff Noah got a great interview with Simon St. Lauret we're gonna have that
here in just a minute he is a senior editor at O'Reilly and also one of the
chairmen's of OSCON and then Noah drove us back I think this is almost it right
here here's the oh this was cool I really liked this at the Libre office
booth up on the projector they had in a Libre office document projected up on
the screen guess what this morning the UK government announced that they're
standardizing on ODF the same more the same format Libre office uses natively
that was a pretty fun thing to be there to see them celebrate that when that was
announced so they were so excited about that I cannot tell you I mean we had
like a five-minute conversation before I drug you guys over so we could get an
air view of them yeah so it was so excited and why Noah was talking to the
Libre office folks I was talking to one of the guys from the software
conservancy they the one of the developers of PHP my admin and I was
like man I love your project thank you for making it easy for my clients to
back up their sequel databases like you've enabled them to use my SQL thank
you that's kind of neat that's just who you bump into while you're there and we
just start chatting up again I love the Linux action show also Michael Dexter
of the Portland Linux Unix group yep he was pointing us in the right
direction for people to be interview I just want to give him props to nice
such a good such a nice guy it's always fun he's always at these events that I
go to and it's so great to bump into him because it's like seeing an old friend
and it was also he also got us to hook up when we did the live stream of the
Linus Torvalds chat at the Portland Linux users group so let's get to we
interviewed Ruth I think her name was from Pi Dora and you know this is a
really fascinating project to see Fedora get into the whole arm space get into to
get into making a serious distribution for the Raspberry Pi they're writing
books about it now they're really getting they're getting really serious
about it so I want to talk about that but first let's thank our next sponsor
on the Linux unplugged show and that's the awesome folks over at Ting Linux
dot ting.com Linux dot ting.com will get you $25 off your first device if you've
already got a device well good news you can bring that over to ting check their
BYOD page and they'll just give you a $25 credit everywhere I went when I was in
Portland I was rocking LTE coverage and even more to the point which is really
unique is while I was on the floor at OSCON I was able to take pictures and
send them back to Angela who was sitting back at jbhq and then posting like the
guys are on the floor interviewing Chris Tabona the guys are on the floor
interviewing Chris Christian Hellman like all of that was happening while I
was on the floor and actually be able to get LTE or sometimes 3G depending on
the because it's just crazy in these conventions I had to give mad props to
ting Linux dot ting.com go find out why ting is awesome here the highlights no
contract so no early termination fee and you only pay a flat six dollars per
month no data caps no minutes you have to use up or don't get to take advantage
of it's just what you use every single month add it up six dollars for the line
and then whatever the tax man's got to take to give yourself a little taste go
over to Linux dot ting.com and click on that savings calculator now for purposes
of demonstration enter in exactly what you actually use not what you pay for
right because which one of the hardest things about switching to ting is you
have to kind of change the way you think about wireless you don't have to buy like
a certain set amount of minutes that you might use in a certain set amount of
data that you may or may not use or text messages you only pay for what you use
and it it's if you think about the way the mobile industry should have been
structured this is it what ting has done is hit the reset button and it makes so
much more sense once you kind of change the way you think about things so I've
plugged in actual usage here so minutes used per month let's say 400 that's kind
of that'd be very generous for me but let's say it's 400 text messages 500 I
say that's probably about right megabytes use let's say this month I met
you know I'm about three gigs so I'll just put three gigs in there now before
I switch to ting my bill would have easily been a hundred and forty nine
ninety nine before taxes one forty nine ninety nine US if I click calculate
savings I can see that if I would switch to ting over a two-year period I would
save $1,919 linux.ting.com go try out the savings calculator put your info in
there and see how much you would save and see why switching to ting might just
make a lot of sense for you plus no old customer service means when you got a
problem they're gonna solve it for you they're awesome dashboard also means that
if you want to take care of it yourself you can because their dashboard makes
sense and yet it's extremely powerful linux.ting.com and a really big thank you
to ting for sponsoring Linux unplugged it was it was awesome having LTE down
there okay so let's cover some of our first interviews this was this first
one just something fun didn't quite fit into the show but one of my favorite
booths at OSCON was the github booth yeah the github booth because they had
an actual DJ and they weren't like crazy with the music it was it wasn't too loud
but it was good like you knew when you were near the github booth because they
had music going so I chatted with one of the guys from github I said okay why
github and music so I noticed here that you have a very handsome looking DJ booth
over here is github gonna be rocking music all day all day so tonight during
the booth crawl you'll find us we're basically blowing the place out and
we'll throw out the breaks and whatnot today yeah that's awesome so why github
and music we have a lot of creative people at github you know that's one of
the attributes we hire for so music is one of the parts of our culture we have
a lot of code-based parties around the city and whatnot so yeah and it was it
was pretty cool it was pretty neat to have it's the different take on every
every booth that's major tries to do something interesting so we had to stop
by the red hat booth and Ruth was there and Ruth has talked to Noah in the past
in fact Ruth and Noah are like best buds like they just started catching how you
doing Ruth oh I'm good Noah like they just started catching up like old pals
so Noah talked to Ruth about piedora and all those goodies at OSCON we're here
walking around at OSCON 2014 here in Portland Oregon and we ran into Ruth
from the red hat project how are you Ruth I'm great how are you doing all
right now Ruth I had the opportunity to hear you a couple months ago talk about
the Raspberry Pi and all the interesting things I think you had a you had a suit
that you had you had you had made you know it was all powered by Raspberry Pi
now I understand that there are some major changes that have come out
hardware-wise on the Raspberry Pi can you tell me a little bit about that yeah
just last week they released the model B plus and the reason it's not model C is
because it's still the same chip the same RAM and all of that but it has
some significant improvements there are four USB ports now instead of just two
the corners are rounded you know some easy things like that it's a nicer form
factor the composite jack is gone the option is still there through the audio
jack but it just kind of streamlines things the other significant changes
they've switched it from an SD card to a micro SD card and the biggest thing
about that for me is the SD card holder was plastic and if you depending on your
case or what you were doing it had a tendency to break off and so the the new
micro SD card holder is metal which is a really nice improvement that's
outstanding now does that SD card does it still stick out a little bit or with
micro SD is it completely encased it looks like I don't have one yet they've
only been out for about a week and of course they pretty much instantly sold
out they're getting easier to come by now but it looks like it's gonna be
flush up in the system and not have that that piece sticking out yeah that's one
thing that always bothered me particularly when you're trying to
deploy a Raspberry Pi as an appliance base you know device where you don't
want it to be so much hackery as you want it to be you know look more
professional now on that note I wanted to ask what some people would say that
the Raspberry Pi is really primarily meant as a learning tool and not really
meant for anything remotely related to production even though many people are
says the guy with Google Glass on his face using I think I even saw maybe a
year ago or so somebody was using it in in in biomedical for a biomedical
purpose so what what's your opinion I mean can the Raspberry Pi be used as a
serious production tool the Raspberry Pi was designed for education that is its
original intent it was inspired by the BBC micro which was a computer back in
1981 that was designed for educational use but that said the reason we all love
it is because it is so infinitely useful and the new model B plus has 40 GPIO
instead of the old 26 you can do so many things with it and on top of that it's
cheap and so it's not the fastest it's not the greatest there's so many other
of these small boards but a lot of them are 80 or 90 dollars and the pie is 35
dollars and that makes it infinitely useful and so if it meets the needs of
those projects and sure it's perfectly sufficient for all sorts of things as
long as you have the right power as long as you have the right power can you tell
me so you've you've spent a lot of time looking and not only doing your own
projects but looking at what other people have done with Raspberry Pis if I
were to ask you what's the first coolest project that comes to mind what would
you say I think my favorite is still the bilingual functional r2d2 that thing is
so awesome and it's it's a year or two old now but it's still one of my
favorite projects and I think part of it is that a guy made it for his
girlfriend he decided to make this life-size functional takes commands in
Japanese and English r2d2 and then she married him so clearly it was a
successful project you you obviously you work for Red Hat and I understand that
that Fedora has a distribution that runs on the Raspberry Pi is there anything
you can tell me about Pi Dora specifically my favorite thing about
Pi Dora and and I tell people obviously as I work for Red Hat and I work on
Fedora a lot Fedora and Pi Dora are my preferred distributions but when you're
working with the Raspberry Pi you should choose the distro that most suits your
needs but my favorite thing about Pi Dora to that end is that so many of the
fun hackery projects are headless if they they're too small they don't you
know they run away from you they don't have a monitor attached and so my
favorite fun Pi Dora fact is that you never have to connect it to a monitor at
all if you add this little file when you flash the SD card you can have it flash
the IP address out the LEDs and then it reads them out the speakers in a
delightful British accent voice out the speakers huh yeah I knew about the
lights I knew that the lights flash but I didn't know about the speakers now is
that something that's something that that script is specific to Pi Dora I
believe that you can't you can grab the files off of github and I think you
could probably use it I've never tried using a distro why would I why would I
use something besides right why why ever straight from Red Hat so people wanted
to find out more about the Raspberry Pi or about your projects with the Raspberry
Pi or about Pi Dora where could somebody go for Pi Dora you would go to Pi Dora
PID ORA dot CA that is the site for Pi Dora for Raspberry Pi stuff Raspberry Pi
dot org if you're interested in other Red Hat community projects besides Pi
Dora herbicides fedora rather community dot Red Hat comm is our place for all of
the Red Hat upstream community projects well thank you so much for taking time
to speak with the truth Oh pi Dora that's cool that was a cool
interview no I'd like to hearing about my door haven't followed that much the
other interview that Noah managed to grab right on our second day right
outside the opening of the Expo Hall and this is a little behind the scenes
Simon's who Noah got to interview it was a great big thinker in the community
Simon st. laureate he's Simon STL on Twitter he's senior editor at O'Reilly
he's one of the chairpersons of OSCON and so Noah being like instinctually the
great interviewer that he is is like I know what I'm gonna do we didn't even
discuss it we were just on the same wavelength like we were just sharing the
same brain wavelength Noah's like this is the chairman I'm gonna set this up as
the opening interview we'll roll this as the first interview in the Linux action
show it's gonna be great it'll be the setup and you'll hear Noah do a great
job of setting it up as like we're here at OSCON and right outside the Expo Hall
about to go in and right in the interview the guy kind of blows it and
what I love is if you watch Noah's face you can see Noah's like god damn it I
worked really hard on that all right so here is Simon st. laureate a great chat
and a thinker welcome to OSCON 2014 we're here right outside the Expo Hall
where many exciting things are about to happen outside here we have Simon who
you are affiliated directly with O'Reilly the company that is putting on
OSCON thank you so much for taking time to be here with us today how are you I'm
great it's the show's about half over everything's going smoothly the pieces
are coming together outstanding so tell me a little bit about what it is that
you do for O'Reilly and what and I know this might be a loaded question but what
exactly took to get OSCON to come together okay so most of what I do
historically has been editorial so I've been an editor I started out bringing in
books I focus on a couple of different areas but mostly these days it's web
stuff I'm also co-chair of our fluent conference which is the web show I so I
have two shows that fluent I have OSCON and then I'm also helping us figure out
what stories we should be telling about the web whether it's in print or in
conferences or online so that yes there are many things there OSCON is special
for me and that it goes outside of my usual boundary zones this works really
well that I have two co-chairs Sarah and Matthew make that much easier and we
also are trying to connect things to more of the stuff we're doing internally so
the web stuff I know really well this stuff beyond that I know less and less
well but there are also pieces that make me really excited so we mix it up so
tell me a little bit how the web connects to to to OSCON I mean I you
know there's it's not it's not it's not necessarily live coverage of OSCON or
anything like that right it's so the web the web is sort of the background in
lots of the talks here people are doing you know Python this or PHP this and the
result is a web app we have we have a track that does cover front-end stuff
but it's a fairly small part of it because of the historic programming
languages and the open source in general is really compatible with the web but
you know a different thing so that it's sort of a piece of it we have a lot of
we have a lot of things that are more specifically programming we also are
starting to get really into the open hardware stuff and we're also there's a
lot there's a lot that you can do at a conference that hasn't been done enough
yet with like what we're calling geek lifestyle right now so you know
combining these different pieces to look at the way we we live in a different way
so I would consider myself in the truest sense the word to be a geek tell me a
little bit about this geek like lifestyle it's it's varied year by year
and it's a it's a very flexible category we it could be everything from home
automation there was actually a great talk a few years ago on garden
automation it involved like making sensors and then the the speaker was a
Linux kernel developer so everything was in C++ and you know using that to
control garden hoses you know it's become more normal I mean the nest
obviously is doing a lot of these things and we're seeing these things happen
it's still people at OSCON still tend to be a few years ahead of what's normal
out there so we try to bring in as much of that as we can so and as I've walked
around I've certainly seen a couple of those booths I mean they had the open
hacker laptop you know it's absolutely fantastic and projects like that you
know just it really just lights a spark in my eye right but one of the things
that I guess I was a little disappointed with and maybe you can speak on is why
at a at a conference that is primarily geared towards open source do we see so
many closed source solutions we walk around about you know the operating
systems that some of these people using are not open source operating systems
I'm wondering why do you think that is and what can we do to change that so
this is a lot harder of a question to ask than it sounds when Noah asked that
question it almost seems natural but if you think about it this is one of the
chairman of a convention we're saying hey we've noticed a lot of the people
coming here are not necessarily practicing open source themselves in
some regards and I want to touch on this more in a few minutes we have an
interesting conversation I want to get into so listen to his answer and then
keep that in mind as we go forward well there are a couple of different stories
on that so one is that you know when Apple was first coming out with OS X it
just it was they had an open source story at the core of it there still is
an open source story at the core of it it's just become less and less of the
story and that and the Unix tools gave developers a sense of hey I can do this
yeah I'm shifting the other direction these days I'm running Linux at home I'm
you know moving moving further and further away from that the other thing
that's happened though less with Apple more with Microsoft is that I'm seeing
the companies that used to be these completely closed systems opening up
more and more and more of it so like Scott Hanselman gave a talk yesterday on
like the Visual Studio ecosystem and how that was changing I was like really
happily surprised to see that like Windows is actually like part of their
open source story here not as much as I'd like but they're they're coming down
the road with us finally that's a pretty good answer too and I something I
noticed too is even companies like Microsoft are integrating a lot of open
source services now and and making it more maybe it may be the right approach
is making it more making their software more accommodating to play in that field
so it was a pretty good answer so we'll continue on so I always look at those
things it's like a wolf babysitting your child do we really trust do we really
trust these companies that have been so wrapped up in proprietary closed source
software do we really trust them even if they are willing to venture out into
the open source world I mean is that really what we want to see or would we
rather see like you were talking about before you know these these real
grassroots hacker type projects where it's it's somebody doing something you
know themselves I'm always gonna be happy with a grassroots hacker project
unless it doesn't work but you know right the trust question is hard I mean
for me like a lot of the sting I have a natural tendency to cheer for the
underdog and when I see companies that are no longer in the powerful positions
that they used to be and they're adapting open source I feel it's odd I
feel sort of I it's not just that I'm happy that they're changing or happy
that they've fallen it's that they're less powerful right and that makes me
feel a little better that it's probably a nice wolf maybe yep once so much of it
comes down to you know what people think they can get away with right and even
the best companies these things can change suddenly when people change so as
power gets a little better distributed in this system I think we're going to
see more and more okay we don't have to control everything yeah well let's hope
that the direction moves that way because that that would be a fantastic
world I think that we'd all like to see walking around the Expo Hall you've been
in there what what has been your favorite present or not presentation but
what has been your favorite booth exhibit so far I'm really really fond of
the hardware showcase I you know I do some soldering I do make some things but
I've never made anything like what they're doing and the combination of
open with things you can touch and play with and you know just having the
creators there to explain what they're doing has really been the most exciting
part easily for me yeah it really is and it's a fantastic conferences is there
anyone is there any place that you would point people to or anyone you would
point people to directly if they wanted to become involved with OSCON find it
more information about OSCON or maybe a plea for people to join us here next
year 2015 OSCON well we're just getting started on what OSCON 2015 will look
like it'll be here we know that it'll be similar timing but the program you know
we'd love to get input what did you love about OSCON what didn't you love about
OSCON we're starting that conversation not quite tomorrow but pretty close to
tomorrow so we're trying to get as much lead time into figuring out what the
shape of OSCON should be before we start asking for specific proposals so by all
means let us know oscon.com is the easy place to find us but you know to contact
me contact our co-chairs we're just happy to have the conversation about
what's working what more do you want perfect well thank you so much for
taking time to speak with us we really appreciate it great thank you very much
yeah really thank you very much to Simon for joining us it was a great chat and so
I he touched on a lot of stuff there that I want to kind of circle back on I
know heavens you had some thoughts on the sort of Microsoft going to all of
these Linux and open source conventions and really trying to have a presence
there what do you think it's about well considering Microsoft has been a little
bit more they're not so desktop focused anymore and more putting a lot of their
development and money into Azure and Azure is generally for the web so node
is one of the big things that they focus on for their Azure platform they've
finally tasted node and how the node package manager works and they've got
their own little new get package manager they're starting to build their own
software repo went in Windows inside Visual Studio to get all their package
updates library updates all that crap yeah they're tasting open source they're
like who I see what the hell they're why everyone's starting to like this it's
got good stuff yeah in fact just recently they moved their their
TypeScript development from their sort of isolated code plex website to
github which is um you know pretty yeah they were talking about that they were
talking about how they're how they're gonna be putting more stuff on github
now it is interesting we asked them and we said so how many people at Microsoft
work in the open site I think they call it the open source division and you know
before the Nokia acquisition Microsoft has a headcount I think of around 50,000
before the acquisition and she said a hundred a hundred people at Microsoft
are working on open source now but she did she did point out she emphasized
that it's because in a lot of ways they're using open source in different
areas throughout Microsoft now so where it used to be contained to a singular
group now more and more of the departments and divisions of Microsoft
are looking at how they can use it so it she's like that that hundred number
doesn't really quite equate to anything anymore but that's the group that's like
their core focus is you have a budget to go to these events demo you know
interface with communities that's that's what that core group does so it's kind
of it's kind of an interesting deal oh I we had an interview with Krista Bona in
the Linux action show last Sunday and he touched on pretty big interview and I
didn't see a lot of response from the community on some of the things that he
said so I wanted to pull out a couple of quotes and then bounce it around with
our virtual lug to get your opinion on it so the first thing that the bonus
said that I thought was it's obviously it's a Google way to look at it but I
want to ask you guys if perhaps the concept isn't potentially worth
considering he mentioned that the fragmentation that Android now faces is
simply a problem because winners have fragmentation and the reason why we
think it's a problem is because open source itself is used to losing here
I'll play it but yeah Android though it's just a whole different world I mean
the thing about the billion devices that's under mentioned at Google I own a
during his keynote that a lot of people sort of didn't parse was that he was
just talking about the devices that register with Google you know that's not
counting the hundreds of millions of other devices that ship and infractional
shares from China you know Chinese factories you know the Amazon Kindle
fire those things are all Android too right and it's like you know this is how
you know that Android is really open source this is how you know that
chromium is really open source because other people ship it right and we're not
going oh no you can't ship it you know because we're not that company we really
shipped it under a real open source license that people could use and it's
kind of cool you know now do you think that that providing that level of
freedom also provides the ability for companies to abuse it so for example
when I bought my Verizon Samsung phone I have a lot of Verizon apps I have a lot
of stuff I didn't really want on the phone that isn't really part of the
Android experience it just Verizon wanted that stuff on it and the and and
and the ability for those OEMs to modify that operating system could be seen as a
detraction for some users right yeah I guess I mean I hate to say it but that's
a problem winners have you know you know your platforms winning when you have
those kinds of problems fragmentation is a problem winners have and and I think
that open source was so used to losing losing the desktop losing this losing
that even though we had you know something done such a great job winning
in the server that you know feeling the win in a consumer market felt like
betrayal for some people okay so let's take that on is is is the Android
fragmentation simply a result of its popularity and is maybe the reason why
we react to it as a bad thing is because open source is so used to losing that's
a pretty that's a that's a pretty big concept so before we get into that I
want to thank our last sponsor this week and that is the awesome folks over a
digital ocean a digital ocean is rocking it these days you guys go over to
digital ocean right now because we've got a promo code for the month of July
and I would love to represent for Linux unplugged use the promo code unplugged
July when you check out and you'll get a $10 credit now what is digital ocean
digital ocean is simple cloud hosting dedicated to offering the most intuitive
and easy way to spin up a cloud server and boy is that not the case they have a
brand new data center in London where some of the folks in our subreddit are
getting new cloud servers spun up in 21 seconds now what they're really gonna
say is look you can expect to have a cloud server spun up in 55 seconds
that's amazing and pricing plans start only five dollars a month for 512
megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one blazing fast CPU and a terabyte of tier
one bandwidth and digital ocean is data center locations in New York San
Francisco Singapore Amsterdam and London brand-new London their interface is so
simple and so intuitive the control panel really gives you the ability to
deploy a server in under a minute and have complete control over that it
doesn't feel like you have reduced functionality and the best part is they
have a straightforward API the power you just can replicate on their own on them
so you could have you could have an interface to the digital ocean droplet
system that is all through a bash script using their API deploying servers as you
need them scale up scale down using digital ocean infrastructure starting
only five dollars per month but when you use unplugged July you get the ten
dollar credit I've been talking to folks this morning about how they're setting
up own cloud 7 on a digital ocean droplet running Ubuntu 1404 and I'm
thinking I'm gonna do the same thing why not right five dollars I have my
dedicated droplet I can move it around I can back it up I can snapshot it I just
have it's it's so straightforward and that is so worth five dollars a month
for me there's other things you can use digital ocean for two that you might not
have thought of but because digital ocean has seen such incredible growth
specifically in the developer and Linux communities you're starting to see
awesome solutions built around digital ocean that are just sort of a result of
their success in fact here's rolling your own CDN build a three continent CDN
for $25 in one hour now this isn't necessarily a digital ocean thing but
this is a blog post that shows you by how using digital ocean engine X and
Docker you can set up your own CDN that does distribution content all over the
world now if you're a podcaster you know if you have a podcast right now and
you're serving up your mp3 files from a single web server stop it that's a bad
experience for your users it's bad it's just bad all around because every time
somebody's downloading that mp3 file that's hanging up one of your web server
sessions so it's not responding to serving up a web page and also makes the
download slow it's just inappropriate it makes you look unprofessional but for
$25 you could set up a worldwide CDN using digital ocean droplets your end
users get their podcast faster your web servers more responsive and during peak
download times you don't have that chugga lug that happens on your web
server and everybody's either loading web pages or downloading mp3s for $25
and this blog post tells you how to do it you see how when you combine KVM you
combine an amazing interface you combine great data centers SSD drives in tier
one bandwidth and incredible value you can really start to create a whole new
class of technology digital ocean comm use the promo code unplug July when you
check out get that $10 credit that'll get you started on your own CDN for two
months for free right go check it out digital ocean comm unplug July when you
check out and a really really big thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring the
Linux unplugged show okay so let's uh let's kick it around to the mumble room
is is Android fragmentation simply a result of it being success I want to
start with you Noah since you were talking to the bone and what was going
through your head when he gave you that answer were you agreeing or were you
like this kind of sounds a little bit like spin okay so my problem with
Android I think it's I think it's one of your gripes too is that Android because
it was late to the game had to make compromises in their operating in what
they would have liked to have seen as an ideal user experience in order to cave
to what the carriers wanted and I think that makes for and yes it makes it much
more prolific than I'm sure that he says what does he say 85% or whatever of all
devices are running Android and that's great but it's a crappy Android
experience there's a lot of really crappy Android devices out there so I I kind of
think it's a crap answer he acknowledged to that it falls down when it comes to
the security aspect of it but the way so I want to take particular like I
actually kind of agree with it is a problem that winners have in the sense
that when you reach a certain mass adoption there's so many people are
going to start experimenting with your operating system or just going with it
like when I had a chat with Aaron Sigo about challenges of building the
Vivaldi tablet one of the thing he's one of the things that really stood out to
me that he said was when we talk to these manufacturers if we tell them it
needs to be Android compatible it clicks they know they know exactly what we want
to give us all the specs but when we tell them it needs to be Linux
compatible they have no idea what we're talking about right and so part of that
so you just see there's this adoption level that's through the entire stack
from people making software all the way down to the people assembling in it on
the manufacturing line so there's just this mass adoption level where Android
almost can't help but have all kinds of weird incarnations of it because it's
almost a de facto operating system it's like it has become one of the general
purpose platforms at least for low power devices so that part I agree with the
part that I take issue with is I don't agree that open source is used to losing
and he gave kind of a mention to well except for in the server but let's be
honest Apache crushes the competition nginx is rock-solid there is so much
open source technology that is winning Android itself is open source
technology that is winning so to say that open source is used to losing I
think that is a mischaracterization I think you could argue perhaps the
desktop is used to losing but to say open open source is not just used to
winning open source has won well yeah here's my perspective on it is when I
look at this and I've interviewed Chris before so I kind of get where his
mindsets coming from he's looking at it as if I walk up to Joe blow on the
street and say oh yeah you're really you're using an open source product
they're gonna look at you with a blank stare they have no idea what you're
talking about if you say Android or something they recognize then in fact
you've actually made that connection so I think he is talking about the desktop
and I also think he's also expanding on the the branding the recognition do
people understand that they're benefiting from this thing called open
source people don't I understand I agree if we're only talking about Linux
enthusiasts who critique Android but in reality it's not just Linux users who
critique some of these problems with Android but it's actually the entire
technology industry who really you know doesn't even follow the Linux desktop
necessarily so I don't know if that's influencing the way they see it I do
agree that you know maybe we're not used to seeing what success looks like in
some regards on the desktop I don't I think it's also how we define success I
mean I think geeks and casual folks definitely when it comes to technology
we just do we define success very differently I use my myself and my
mother-in-law as an example for her success in technology is when the
button she pushes on the remote works properly and for me it's when I saw this
amazingly complex problem that took a lot of work to do you know so usually I
think it just differs from person to person all right well I know the mumble
room has a couple other thoughts on that but I want to move on because here was
Chris's response to why fragmentations actually gives Android its edge and he
thinks yeah okay if we accept there's fragmentation I'm not even sure if it's
a problem and the thing is if you look at the the Verizon builds if you look at
the you know it's funny actually I I don't want to sound like I'm betraying
my people but I actually prefer the Moto X build to the stock Nexus build right
now because it has this really cool feature where you can shake it and take
a picture yeah you know so you don't have to worry about unlocking it in
other ways so I can whip it out of my pocket while shaking like you know look
I'm having a seizure but it's fine though and then I can take my picture
really fast and I really like that feature and I really like the the
Bluetooth trust feature in the Moto X and those are things that Motorola
brought to it and Motorola is not part of Google anymore so I'm not just
kissing corporate butt here and and I think that it's not wrong to try to
excel by adding new things to an operating system now I would hope I would
love if those are open source and brought back into the platform or they
were available through an app or whatever I can accept that so he's saying
you look sometimes the way you get some of these new innovations is by having
different people try stuff and don't we see that in just Linux distros itself
you know you look at things that have come through like different installers
where one distribution really lands on a good way to do an install and you see a
lot of other distributions pick that up or things like that so sometimes they're
in the fragmentation there can be sort of this organic slow evolution of a
consensus so that I can buy on to but he goes on to kind of say you know if you
think about it in some sense on he's he calls it open source but I really think
he means Linux when he's saying this he's like you guys are forking all day
long so you got to check yourself before you come all up on Android's territory
that's why I'm also pretty unimpressed by fragmentation arguments and that kind
of thing and I'm like you know what you know in the open source world everything
is a fork every time you ship a distribution every time you ship a
program you're forking it you're putting a moment in time and you're
sticking with that moment right until they upgrade again or until they app get
update or you're forking every time you do that so the measure of us as
programmers or as app developers or as carriers or handset manufacturers is how
we keep up with those updates how we keep bringing in the future of software
development to our users and and that's why Android's at 84% boom so he says hey
if you look at it this way when Ubuntu LTS 1404 ships that's a fork yeah I
think he's splitting hairs on that one I can't defend that one at all I disagree
I think that I see what he's saying but I and he is definitely including software
in addition to Linux distribution so he's kind of using the true open source
broad term but I disagree with him I think that he's wrong in stating that
merely by putting the open an open source license on a product that you've
instantly forked it because magically someone else is gonna come along and do
something else with it not necessarily hmm yeah he's messing up with
terminology a little bit same with how in programming we say that monads are
the most evil or they're really weird little named things and no one ever
likes to talk about them I kind of see his point to a sense though I've always
kind of felt like when you take I've always felt like maybe one of the
reasons rolling distributions make the most sense is because when you carve off
a stable Linux distribution you're introducing sort of a fake structure
where none inherently exists and this is something that just us humans do all the
time we always have to go in and create structure everywhere gotta set up a
system gotta gotta make sure we follow a process everywhere we go we got to
organize it and I feel like perhaps it's kind of like trying to set up a dam in a
river like you can hold back the water for a little bit but eventually it's
got to break through and whenever you stable snapshot something essentially
it's a race against time as it deviates further and further away and like if you
look at what Red Hat Enterprise Linux does is they literally have to back
port stuff from future fixes to the old stuff because they are in a sense
maintaining their own fork of the Linux kernel in Red Hat Linux and then all the
other stuff to Debian as well yeah all of them all of them yeah they really
actually fork but sometimes it's just a snapshot of time instead of a fork
see I think that's where you can play semantics is it a snapshot in time or is
it a genuine fork that's maintained for like ten years and that's where Red Hat
just gonna you also fit you also think about this way like for instance you know
he was talking about how fragmentation is a it shows how much success is a
winner Android yeah well one thing I was thinking was that's true to a certain
extent because if you look at Debian it's got to be the most forked yeah
distribution on the planet yeah and it is the biggest in terms of packages so
and it's probably the biggest in terms of development as well I mean you've got
Ubuntu it's kind of a quasi fork of it and it's got all sorts of forks of its
own so it's yeah very true right yeah you know it's interesting it didn't it's
in the full interview but one of the other things he said that jumped out at
me as he said the way I look at all of this the way I look at Android on that
phone the way I look at Android on Noah's Google Glass and the Android
that's gonna be on your watch he this is the bone he says to me I see those as
different distributions those are different distros in my world that's an
interesting way I don't again I think you could play semantics there you're
redefining what it means but it's an interesting way to think about it now
the elephant in the room for Noah and I at least there was one there was one
topic of conversation our entire trip at OSCON that really sort of dominated
basically anytime we stopped to take a breather no and I would kind of turn to
each other and and talk about the unbelievable undescribable amount of
Macintosh laptops we saw at OSCON and yeah yeah and to give you an example
kind of funny when we were walking up to OSCON and there's to this hallway and
this hallway is lined with tables and chairs and every table and every chair
had at least one or two people working on a MacBook all facing us so as we
walked into OSCON we walked down this hallway that was end to end lined up
with Macs and that white glowing Apple logo as we walked into OSCON and I can't
put a I can't underscore this enough literally almost every computer there
was a Mac now there were for sure some PCs but most of those were like at the
registration booths provided by OSCON or like somebody's work Lenovo that they
brought with them to the booth but more often than not I mean Colonel Linux
jump in here with me right I mean it was unbelievable that the ratio right and so
here's and this is what I've been waiting the entire episode to dig in on
it I'm sure you're this is what this is what bothers me right so we have we went
to a convention that's called OSCON Oh the open source convention the place
where I'm supposed to be able to go as an open source user and feel like I'm at
home I'm at home with open source software and here is what here's what I
took away from the conference and it's a lot like like Linux con their mentality
is that Twitter was there for example Twitter uses I guess because they're at
OSCON they use open source software who cares who cares I don't care what
Twitter's using on the back end I cared ten years ago because I thought ten
years ago that if these big companies picked up Linux and adopted it and put a
bunch of money into it then it would eventually trickle down to the desktop
and as I see that not happening it infuriates well I think you're
conflating two things so let me back up I think think of OSCON a little bit like
this this is something I came to it's as much as for us the community to go see
how business is like the the end product of open source are these companies like
everything we talk about you go there and see the end results of how they
actually use it I think that's beneficial for the community itself to
see but you can flip that around to Noah like if you noticed when we talked to
some of these folks like we are also it's them reconnecting with the open
source community so I think it's by going to these events like OSCON that
they kind of connect back to the original roots that everything starts
from so I think it's a two-way street in that regard and I kind of tip my hat to
the OSCON folks but what I think you're the core thing you're getting at here is
essentially supposedly here's a bunch of people making money off of open source a
lot of developers were there a lot of people there from their profession and
they're all pretty much at least I would say a ratio of 20 to 1 using max and
probably a ratio of 7 to 10 using iPhones to Android devices and that's
being and that's being generous on the one side but and the thing that really
irks me is that these the companies that that benefit the most from the backs of
the community in open source then those people that are in the community are the
first to get shafted when when the when desktop clients come out for things like
Netflix or Google Drive right I just I feel like you should eat your own dog
food if you're going to come to a conference and talk about how everyone
should use free and open source software and open source is the best use it and
not just not just on your server and on your back end boot into it use it as a
desktop daily here's what I think the problem is is and it comes down to a
little bit of market dynamics so Apple just released their quarter quarterly
results a couple of days ago by Friday or something like that their Mac sales
grew 18% in the last quarter the rest of the entire PC industry is down 2% overall
Apple is up 18% and everybody else on all on average is down 2% they are seen
because honestly they're well-built machines I think they're seeing a huge
adoption curve right now and this is a trend I've noticed over the last seven
years as I've gone to these conferences it's more and more max and it started
with some max to now it's all max it's all max in the booth it's max and in the
users it's ridiculous and I think part of the problem is a lot of times in
professional uses people are using Linux on the server so all they really need is
an SSH session to that Linux box so they get a Mac because it's trouble-free it
runs Netflix it runs Photoshop it's got all the commercial software all the it
honestly has all the open source software too you put brew on a Mac now
you got a package manager Bob's your uncle you're installing stuff from the
command line then you SSH into your Linux box you do your development all
day long and sublime text yeah you're happy you go home and for them they just
buy this laptop it's got 10 hours of battery life it's fairly trouble-free
and it gives them SSH right out of the box I know it sounds trivial but I
really think that's what's selling these things and I think as a community what
we've got to do is nut up and I'm not using that sexually I mean in the terms
of like let's seriously come to a realization that our boat is sinking and
that these people are jumping ship to the Mac like crazy but the reality is
eventually they're gonna get bored they're gonna want something better but
we're not there when they're ready to jump Linux runs like but on these Mac
books these freaking Mac books are selling more than any other PC in the
industry right now and we can't manage to get Linux working on them oh you want
Thunderbolt go F yourself sorry oh you want a high HD a high DPI resolution
hey it kind of works on depending on which desktop you choose oh you want
thermal management sorry Apple has an SMC controller we can't do that we won't
we won't even bother like trying to reverse engineer it obviously it's not
an ideal solution but the problem is a huge huge number of our community is
buying these machines and we do not as Linux have a solution to make it great
out-of-the-box experience on these Mac books it's it's half-assed you got
trackpad problems after sleep you have no Ethernet support you've got crappy to
zero thermal management and it's still a pain in the ass to make it work in the
first place so what are we gonna do I think the problem is actually even
bigger than what you're talking about because that is assuming these people
want to come to Linux in the first place and the reality is I don't see a lot of
Mac OS users complaining about their Mac OS experience and wanting to come to
Linux and the the best way to get those people the best way to get those users
is right now while they're on Windows when they're looking for something to
jump off the instability and and and the bugginess of Windows that's the time to
get these users because once we lose them to the Mac it's gonna be twice as
hard three times as hard five times as hard to get them to come to Linux well
there as somebody who came from Mac as somebody who came from Mac I gotta say
what's going to might be the major driver is when they have to upgrade
their computer every two years just to keep current software I can't I had that
problem I was like I cannot spend that much money on computer hardware I'm
switching to Linux because I know that I'll future-proof my machines would be
you think the targets move right out from underneath us well I just listening
to your discussion it strikes me that you know a few years ago we might have
been having this discussion about people using Windows machines and now we're
talking about people running Mac OS 10 on Apple hardware so is is now the
principal target for Linux adoption the Apple Mac audience I feel like what Noah
was worried about will apply to probably the majority percentage of people who
switch however there will be still a large number let's just let's for fun
say 20% of people who switch that are technically inclined switch switch after
a year or two from Mac OS to Linux I don't think this is actually all that
unusual I've seen threads about coming from Mac to Linux because people get
bored after a while and I feel like when that happens and I for a lot of
technically inclined people who are intellectually curious I believe that
does you arrive to a point in Mac OS 10 without after that long of usage where
you've essentially mastered the operating system and if you realize
okay I'm now seeing the walls of the holodeck I would like a better program
than this and you go look for Linux and maybe you start as a dual boot and then
you could switch over if if we were there and ready to to supply this
hardware and I think what's at the end of the day what's selling is the Mac
book I think the Mac book air I mean Linus Torvalds use a Mac uses a Mac book
air for God's sakes right I think this is hardware no I think he still has one
yeah no he still uses him yeah he still has it I think he just has he just has
like more than one machine but he also has a pixel right so I mean he's got a
few machines but I guess what the point I'm trying to get at is I feel like the
target like wimpy said the target has moved and we are not responding we need
to be working like on better Thunderbolt support better hide high DPI support we
need to get you know we need to reverse engineer the SMC controller in
these Macs that way there's thermal management and then the battery life
will be better too and all of this stuff and it definitely set off like the the
red alert we we have a major problem and nobody's talking about it and I guess I
kind of also feel like until you go to one of these events and you see it for
yourself when you go to an event filled with your peer groups and none of them
are using Linux I mean it really it's one thing to hear about it through a
podcast it is another thing entirely to be standing there and seeing it and
realize oh man we have a huge problem well I would expand I think go ahead
Matt go ahead oh I was gonna say one thing I would expand on and this is
something with a wife that uses a OS 10 and actually uses a Mac that I
experienced is the number one reason why people use Macs and she and I bet
Angela probably attest to this as well is it's called Apple care it's not an
extended warranty we the logic board pops because Mac logic boards are crap
I'm sorry they are they're garbage and so but the user doesn't care because
they know they can go to the Mac store like we did it's under Apple care she
exchanges it they fixed the logic board didn't cost us anything took three days
and she never missed a beat she didn't the experience was completely seamless
her data was safe she didn't have to care the other that phrase right there
the other thing especially for folks who are not technically inclined is they
you know they really need a brand that they feel like well at least I know this
brand puts out quality at a certain level and I don't know I don't know
about RAM I don't know about megahertz I don't know about SSD but I know that
Apple is known for a certain kind of machine and if I'm willing to spend the
money I can get that and I think a lot more people are willing to spend the
money than we realize because a lot of these folks now are buying a machine and
they're using it for like five plus years so it's not a deal I mean I have
an old I mean I don't use it hardly but I have an old iMac that I'm running off
an external hard drive the point is as people are buying these things because
they understand the experience they don't give a flying crap if it runs on
hamsters they know what it does they understand it they're able to wrap their
brains around it max have now gained in global market share for 32 of the last
thirty three quarters in a row I'm not saying they're the largest machine but
I'm saying we're just ignoring them go ahead heavens no it's not even an
experience it's a company that people can blame or sue that is the backing
thing that will make most people or companies decide on what to use they
just want someone to blame no one wants to get like to have the X what the hell
the responsibility to need to own up to your own hardware that's why Apple or
that's why a lot of companies which sell a lot of software or OS's are good that
that's crap the reason they disagree the I completely disagree the point of it is
that people that value their time that aren't willing to are interested in
spending their time doing that maybe they're a chef an artist I don't know
maybe they make music whatever it is the point is is they don't want to geek out
they don't care they want that experience I've worked closely with
Chris Perillo he'll tell you the same thing he buys these machines because of
their experience he does he knows how the stuff works that he doesn't care you
know Chris Fisher for example runs it because it does certain tasks well I'm
not a Mac person I freaking hate them with a passion but I'm not I'm not naive
enough to think that it's this you know we look at it from a very technical
point of view and Joe average doesn't care right just don't give a rat well
what I'm finding though and what I guess struck a chord with me because I I
wholeheartedly agree with your assessment there Matt what what struck a chord with
me is now we're going to OS con and and also by the way I'm coming from like a
multi-year trend to this whole sure sure now we're going to like the geeks like
the people writing software the people that are creating server platforms and
you know like you go to rack space and rack space has the rack space cloud and
they're deploying bare metal servers with core OS and everybody there has a
MacBook yep I really don't see why that is an issue though I mean if they're
developing open source software software I could go out in the world and say even
if it's gpl3 and download and use I don't give two craps what they are using
on they could be developing on Windows 8 I don't think they care either yeah I
think you nailed it of Apple most of the time it's like what you said before
there because someone is they just want the ecosystem I always explained or
tried to compare Apple to be this metaphor of being a stick or a steak in
the ground on a chain you're on this chain and in this bubble of happiness
that's Apple that's it's a nice environment it's a beautiful little
bubble everything is desired or given to you and you're very happy whenever you
want to get outside that bubble you're screwed you cannot leave that place I
think why and I like I think the point that hey at least these people are
making open source software is a valid one we should underscore that my point
is what I want to try to begin to push on to the community at least to think
about is if we want these people to someday switch because I would think I
mean I as a desktop Linux user really want more desktop Linux users because
I want more of what I need to do on Linux to be more available to me and I
want it more available to everybody I know kernel Linux feels the same way
very passionately more people using Linux is better for everybody and I just
want to win these MacBook users who are professionally technical and decide they
do want to try something else wouldn't it be amazing if we could make that
transition actually work because right now that MacBook in some ways is a
prison they're the only other direction they have that's even kind of halfway
supported is Windows and I think colonel Linux would actually agree with this
assessment and that the direction to get people to begin to use Linux starts with
the PC repair text when they come in with a broken Windows machine send them
out with a Linux install if give them the option say look you're doing this
this this and this nothing that can't be done on Linux give this a try let me
know how it works I'll go ahead and mirror your drive with it fixed if you
don't like it we'll put it back on but give this a shot that's where change
happens we could talk about it all day long but unless we're knocking on doors
or something you know and we've seen that way I see that on a daily basis
exactly what you're talking about Matt but what I just posted in the chat and
I'll reiterate it I would rather be running all software like Steam and
Netflix and all this proprietary stuff on my Linux box I would rather have that
flexibility then have the flexibility of running all open source programs but I
have to do it on a Mac right so I do care I do care what those developers are
using I do care what operating system they feel is most valuable and they
think the market owns if everyone has a Mac they're gonna write software that
works well on a Mac if they all right I think that's a completely closed-minded
mindset to be honest with you it is a good one though if everybody's using a
Mac and they're writing software then it's gonna work better on the Mac than
it does on your Linux desktop and that's a valid concern don't you think
Josh oh I always see them all around the place on most of the conferences I look
at ice watch tons of conferences and they all have Macbooks all over the
place well maybe apparently really good apparently we should be launching the
Macbook action show apparently based on the demographics that I'm saying but
stay tuned for future developments yeah go ahead but absorb on is that you know
let's instead of just talking in circles about it what do we do to fix this and
I was pointing out to know it's like Noah nailed it so it's like okay let's
introduce this to our customers let's introduce this to our family members
let's introduce this to people that might be interested before they take the
Mac bill you know what I mean yeah all right hey Noah I wanted to tell folks
maybe you could give us a little info there's this great place especially if
you're in the Grand Forks area called AltaSpeed.com where people could find out
all kinds information about Noah and his company in the services they provide so
check out AltaSpeed.com give them a look I've had the pleasure of working with
Noah out in the field I've seen how he works with his team as somebody who's
done IT contracting in the past I could tell you that I spotted a good one and
no one his team could definitely handle it AltaSpeed.com check them out they've
also got products available to buy there too all right the plug we go ahead I'm
just gonna say we run every technician that works for a company runs some form
of Linux every software piece every piece of software views runs on Linux
and that is the primary desktop we install for any customer that comes to
us with a PC problem yep and Noah's Noah's even like all right here's your
work machine this is Linux you feel free to break it I don't care if you break it
just have fun and if you break it we'll fix it together I like that yeah yeah
all right well let's wrap it up there I just a couple of a couple of bits and we
can maybe talk about this more in the post show too but on Sunday we're gonna
do a review of Crux Linux and I would love to also maybe enlist some of you
out there so mumble room stay tuned after the show we'll talk about this in
the post show about helping us do a review because on Tuesday's Linux
unplugged following Sunday's Linux action show the next upcoming episodes
on Tuesday we'll have a developer from Crux Linux join us so I'd like to get
the mumbles room thoughts on it so we can kick it around so tune in on Sunday
for last we'll do the review of Crux Linux we're also gonna have Frank on
from own cloud to talk about the new own cloud 7 they've just released and then
on Tuesday we'll do a community review of Crux Linux and talk to the developer
and we if you are interested if you're a Crux user or if you have questions about
Crux go to linuxactionshow.reddit.com we're gonna have a Q&A thread up there
stick it probably right there at the top where you can ask your questions to the
Crux developer for Tuesday's show and if you're a Crux user I'd love to get your
insights or anything you recommend we try look for that thread or probably be
posted soon if it's not already linuxactionshow.reddit.com to get in on
the Crux action and last but not least a quick plug we'd love your feedback go
over to jupiterbroadcasting.com click that contact link and choose Linux
unplugged from the drop-down I know it's so confusing but it all makes sense
because what we have is an automated system where you can send in your
feedback our robots process it and they send us to it they send it to us humans
for reading right here on the air all right Matt all right well that's gonna
wrap us up today I want to say I'm gonna see you on Sunday go download Crux Matt
if you haven't already because get ready we're gonna do the action review I've
never tried Crux before never tried out yeah so I'll be curious to hear what you
think on Sunday so I'll see you on Sunday Matt all right see you then all
right everyone well thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux
unplugged don't forget you can join us live on a Tuesday go over to
jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar to get the show times jblive.tv is where
you'll find the in bed for the chat room you can also get the mumble info there
if you'd like to join our virtual log all right everyone thanks so much for
joining this week's episode of Linux unplugged we'll see you right back here next Tuesday
the show cannot prosper if people listening don't tell other people about
it I think part of the problem is that people mistake Jupiter broadcasting as
passive entertainment that's incorrect this is active participation you are
encouraged and in some ways like gently encouraged with a poker to get involved
share content ask questions disagree agree share ideas and just yak in
general do something well and I guess I kind of feel like I don't know because
people see some sponsors they assume oh well they've got plenty of money they
don't need my help and it really was like yes spread the word tell people
about it help us grow I mean I mean I'm not you know at the end of the day we
still make great content that's what matters but I was just a little
disappointed because we do need to help really bad it's not like you know some
PR yeah we need some PR help you know there's the patreon page patreon.com
slash today there's funding there to help cover costs like this anything
resharing it helps all that kind of stuff being here live you know I
appreciate everybody who shows up live that's really great to get there get the
instant feedback and stuff like that too so and the mumble room you know all this
stuff is incredibly helpful so I'm very very very grateful in so many so many
ways in so many ways I just kind of felt like this last week we went above and
beyond and it kind of fell flat and I felt bad I take it very personally you
know because I follow this stuff very closely what do we think of the new
final Mozilla CEO Chris Beard the man doesn't have a beard but he's got a
great last name he's been the Mozilla project since before what Firefox 1.0
shipped he seems to have worked in almost every aspect of the project it
seems to be a good change right well I think my number one positive on this is
that finally you know your facial hair has gotten a job that's fantastic you
know because I think that's been overdue no I know all seriousness I think I think
he sounds like a good candidate I think he could potentially be a performer
that's why we're the show that has a beard knows how to use it that's right
in a way I'm unhappy that someone even needed to fill in for the CEO Brendan
Ike was fucking awesome he was a really great guy Chris Beard was the interim
CEO during this whole mix-up too so he he's kind of was already doing the job
yeah as long as someone's took took the helm yeah take take the helm as it is
that's it you know fresh blood yeah all right let's go see what our title is and
then we'll get out of here well we'll get what's the guy's qualifications
compared to Brendan like I mean obviously he didn't invent JavaScript but
yeah I mean like server script and server I think about hex code in my head
you know as in the binary and backtrack doing the bug the debugging that's what
gave him the idea to make a tracing JIT compiler I am backtracking through hex
I am or you know just look through on the cover his qualifications in today's
tech talk today he does have some good qualifications so that would be one to
watch if you want to