This is Linux Unplugged, episode 27 for February 11th, 2014.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's watching the Debian mailing
list and it's fresh all out of popcorn.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Matt.
Hey Matt, here we are.
We actually got the first word of it on Sunday as we were wrapping up last that it looked
like Debian was going to go with Systemd and I thought, okay, that's good, but let's not
run with it just yet.
It's not even crazy, because Debian doesn't just make decisions like that, right?
I don't just, boy, it has been an interesting couple of days.
And I know a lot of you are thinking, why do we care so much about an init system?
Well, we're going to talk about that a little bit.
There's a lot of actual larger ramifications.
I think a lot of people are very aware that Debian is the base of so many distributions
and a lot of things are changing in the Linux world.
And at the same time, some of these things are coming together.
And that's what the Systemd discussion isn't just happening at Debian, right?
It's been happening across all of the Linux distributions for a couple of years now.
And the Debian one has been one of the most watched and, unfortunately, not really been
the greatest example of open community collaboration.
And we could get into that whole discussion about should this stuff be on a public mailing
list, but it was.
And I kind of want to talk a little bit about that, too, and if maybe we've sort of sent
a bad signal to the rest of the industry.
We'll see.
I don't want to overstate it, but I think we'll discuss that aspect of it, too.
I think at the end of this episode, if you haven't been sure why this has been a topic
of interest for so many people, I hope by the time we're done, you will know why.
You'll feel like you've got a good grasp on it.
Hey, Matt, before we go too far, we should do a Valve update.
I just thought this was really cool.
I wanted to update a story we ran a couple of weeks ago and unplugged about Valve donating
games to Debian developers.
Well, they're expanding that program now to Ubuntu developers, too.
How about that?
That is exciting because it's not only showing that they're – because the Debian thing
could have been seen as a fluke, but I think the fact that they're being inclusive to
the Ubuntu guys as well is that they're saying, look, we really want Linux to take
off and we want to embrace those that put their time and energy into making Linux awesome.
And so they really get that.
Yeah.
1204 was there.
That was the distro they recommended.
That's right.
Yeah.
So, man, if they get Steam boxes, this is your chance now, guys.
Go sign up to become a Debian developer or an Ubuntu developer.
Get your Steam box.
Because you never know.
What's going to happen, that's going to be next.
And there was – what was – there was another Valve story today, too.
Oh, that's right.
Right, right.
We were just talking about it on the pre-show.
Steam Dev Days, the videos from Steam Dev Days are now up and there's some of interest.
One we talked about on last is this switching to Linux, where Ikyulys went through some
of the reasons why switching to Linux, porting your game to Linux is not nearly as bad as
everybody thinks it is.
It's called getting started with Linux game development.
Anyways, all of the videos I think that are available now are linked on the SteamDevDays.com
page and I'm going to go through some of them.
And if there's something really crazy, I'll pull out and put it in the Linux Action Show
on Sunday.
But otherwise, you can just go check it out on your own because there's so many on there
that I'm sure we'd only be able to cover a tiny, tiny percentage of what was actually
said.
Speaking of last, on Sunday, one last little bit of business before we get into our main
topic of the day, Sunday, Linux Action Show, 10 a.m. Pacific, jblive.tv, the place to be
because it's episode 300.
Oh my goodness, big, big, big, big, big, big, huge, huge.
So we got a lot of stuff to talk about in episode 300.
We're going to celebrate.
It's not going to be, I haven't really decided how much of a regular Linux Action Show it's
going to be.
Probably depends on what's going on in the week.
But we have some stuff planned to talk about, so I'd really love to have you guys there
because it's a good one to join live and I think we'll have a good active community.
Maybe we can break the IRC server.
Maybe we'll load it up with so many people.
So I'd love to have you there this Sunday.
It'll be February 16th, I think that's it, yeah, 16th.
Yeah, I think that sounds right.
That sounds right.
And I think it's definitely one of those things to where if you don't normally show up for
a live show, make this the live show you show up for.
I think you'll be pretty glad you did.
Yeah, you know what?
It's better than getting bit by a dog.
This is true, especially if that dog wants to bite you.
Yeah, yeah.
That was redundant, but you get the point.
Well, point well reiterated, Matt.
All right, well, so I want to take a second here and just thank Ting.
Ting is one of our sponsors this week and they're doing something really awesome.
So get started.
Go to linux.ting.com and if you're watching this live today, go over to their blog.
I don't know of any other cell phone company that would have done this.
Ting now, right now, if you go to ting.com slash blog, has the message up that a lot
of sites are running with today because it's take back the privacy day on the internet
and they have the call your legislators numbers and the submit for an email address right
here.
Ting is so out of control that the authors of the Patriot Act are sponsors of Lena Bill
to reign it in.
So they have these.
We have one running right now on the Jupiter Broadcasting website too.
Let's see if you go over to our, yeah, so here's the Jupiter Broadcasting website, thedaywefightback.org.
A lot of sites are doing this.
I just thought it was so awesome that Ting is one of them.
They didn't need to do this.
I mean, they, you know, but they did because Ting is, they're really kind of internet savvy
and that's one of the things I like about them quite a bit.
It shows in their dashboard too.
They have a really awesome and easy to use dashboard that follows web standards.
In fact, it even supports the Mozilla login system, which I like a lot.
We've had one of their developers on Coder Radio before to talk about it.
And what's great about Ting is there's no contracts, there's no early termination fees.
You only pay for what you use.
Each flat line is six dollars and then, you know, taxes and then it's just your usage.
If they take your message, your megabytes and your minutes, they add them all up at
the end of the month, whatever bucket you fall into, that's what you pay.
It's really straightforward.
You buy the device outright.
You own it.
You're not paying some sort of subsidized price over the time of the device.
It's yours.
And one of the great things about Ting is every plan includes hotspot and tethering
and it's just part of your data usage.
You don't have to be in some sort of special plan.
You just turn it on.
You know that feature built into Android?
You should be able to just turn it on.
That's why, that's why Google put it there and that's how Ting works.
Ting also has awesome no-hold customer service.
You can give them a call anytime between 8 a.m. and 8 p.m. eastern and an actual person
answers the phone.
What a concept!
I've been able to activate like 14 devices though, all through the dashboard.
It's really great.
They have an iPhone and Android app to manage your account as well.
And you can check them out by going to linux.ting.com.
They'll take $25 off your first device or $25 off your first month if you already have
a compatible device.
Check out their BYOD page.
I'm telling you, I've been using them for over a year and I love it.
They just, they just announced too that you can buy the Nexus Red phone from the Google
Play Store and put it on Ting.
Just get the Ting.
Oh, that's cool.
Yeah.
You know what's, you know what's actually really cool?
This, here's a, so not only do they have, not only are they like really savvy about
the net in general, but if I go over to their Google Plus page, I'm going to wait for this
bad boy to load up, they check out, here's how they, here's how they posted it.
This is on their Google Plus page.
Okay.
So they did this on social media.
Cool.
We're now selling the Nexus 5, but please don't buy it from us.
Order it on Google Play and save yourself 95 bucks.
Okay.
Let me get this straight.
So they not only said, Hey look, you know, we want you to, we want you to put the money
back in your pocket and not in ours, but they're going to actually even provide you where to
go and do that.
I mean, that's really cool.
Here's their, here's their announcement on a fight against mass surveillance.
Help spread the word by sharing our blog posts and signing the official petition for every
share before the end of the day.
We're donating a dollar to the Electronic Frontier Foundation up to a maximum of $10,000.
Wow.
So go over to linux.ting.com.
See this is why I've always talked about vote with your wallet, support these kinds of companies.
And you know, we also had a listener reach out to them and ask them about Ubuntu Touch
and they said they're eagerly following that project.
So they're really kind of onto all of this stuff.
And I think you could go check them out, try out their savings calculator.
They just lowered their data rates.
Try the calculator again, see if it's even more of a deal for you than before.
Linux.ting.com and a big thank you to Ting for being so damn awesome.
That's really cool.
Good guys.
Good stuff.
All right.
Let's jump in the mumble room.
Bring in the guys.
Um, guys, we got a couple of, uh, we got a couple of things I want to, I want to hammer
through before we jump into the, uh, to the Debian topic.
I want to read some of our feedback, but you guys feel free to chime in on any of the feedback
too.
All right.
Our first email came from Dalek.
Hmm.
Dalek, huh?
Interesting.
He says, Hey Chris, I just wanted to comment on your recent snafu on last and your comments
in Coder Radio and Linux unplugged.
I gathered your report on something incorrectly and someone complained on Google Plus.
This was a, we mentioned that we, I reported that the KD Plasma next dates were firm when
they weren't.
I said, get over it.
He says to me, the only things that matter are number one, you owned up to it when you
found out that you were wrong.
It wasn't intentional and you're taking steps to address the issue.
If you made a, you have made a pledge to be more accurate and to me that is all that matters.
Mistakes can and will happen.
It is what you do about them that makes all the difference.
This is my opinion and I will probably get trolled for saying this, but you're doing
the KD project a favor by reporting on anything on the project.
Instead of hitting Google Plus to complain, they should come directly to you and say,
Hey Chris, you got this part wrong and you should probably fix it.
Oh, and by the way, insert a link here.
This is where the post about info that's correct is happening at.
I definitely agree with the latter part especially.
I think definitely going straight to the source versus a publicly bemoaning crap is definitely
the way to handle something.
Yeah, for sure.
Although sometimes, yeah, yeah, I mean, I don't know, see, here's where I fall down
on this is I kind of, I've been thinking about this a lot and I think mistakes will inevitably
happen because there's not a ton of original reporting happening in the Linux and open
source landscape.
A lot of it is blogs, it's rewrites of mailing list posts, it's pulling out company announcements
and then posting them online and then people either do meta coverage of them or they go
do some research on their own and do some, it's very little actual original reporting.
So when you are trying to do some original reporting or trying to just cover some of
the original reporting, there inevitably will be some errors that crop up just because that's
human nature.
Sure.
And I think as long as, we always try to follow up and make corrections in this show and I
think if the mistake is big enough, we make corrections in the main show itself and we're
very clear and open about it and plus in the subreddit, we get caught pretty quickly.
And I think as long as, one of the things about a podcast is you make it consumable
for one episode if somebody is just doing a drive by and they pick it up.
But what you really want to do is curate a long term community that can depend on quality
of content.
And I think as long as we're addressing that by continuing to do corrections and updates
down the road, then that audience is served in the long run and I think that's what really
matters.
So I'm always going to do my best not to have mistakes but when they do, I'll also always
do my best to make corrections.
And I think that's all you can really do.
Yeah.
Alright, well next bit of feedback comes in and this is from Red Hands Guitar.
Read Hands Guitar.
Ah, well I'll get it eventually.
Give me about four more tries.
He says, he says, he's following up on an email we got at the end of Linux Unplugged
last week and the emailer said, hey, you know what, maybe I prefer Linux not to have that
big of an adoption.
Let's keep it tight and small.
Right?
Make it a small community.
Maybe it doesn't need to go out to the masses.
And I think we all kind of kicked around and said, nah, to really be successful we need
to get a wider adoption.
He said, so Read Hands Guitar says, I think it would be, I think I would be satisfied
if Linux became as popular as the desktop OS as Mac OS is, but maybe even more would
be better.
I think the most beneficial kind of growth initially is to allow other kinds of growth
by hobbyist users, so we start there.
If we have a huge influx of hobbyists who can commit code, Linux and free software become
better products and give better impressions to more casual users.
I agree up until the last point.
The last point, generally speaking, the more coding and the more coders and things you
come into it, you do end up with better stuff, but a lot of times little things like UX and
stuff like that tend to go out the window, especially in the Linux space, so I don't
know.
Maybe so.
Yeah.
See, I do kind of, I see some aspects of like, sometimes if you build something for the geeks,
that serves a point, that serves a purpose for a while.
That does help with getting you to a level of adoption on a class of user, a lot of times
it's sort of the trendsetter.
You know, Matt, one of the things that I know, I'm sure you must have noticed too, over the
last 20 years maybe, let's say, is like there used to be a day in an age when I would go
to a restaurant and if somebody dropped a computer term like modem or windows, I would
immediately pick that sucker up and be like, whoa, somebody just said something about a
computer in a public place.
And now these days, it's common vernacular to be throwing out, you know, Facebook, dot
com, Twitter, whatever, right?
So I think in some ways you could argue that the internet used to be a place only for the
geeks that eventually, because of the work they did and then the work to bring other
people to it, eventually it became appealing to the common person.
And I think the Linux desktop could be like that and the Linux desktop shares a lot of
similarities with the development of the internet in some ways.
The fractured nature of it, right?
The competing standards, all these things, but eventually it all sort of moves forward
as one big evolutionary organic beast and I kind of feel like in a way this phase the
Linux desktop is at right now could be its glory days in a sense where it's for the geeks,
it's really great if you're a nerd and you really want to tinker with your system and
you look at sort of the Ubuntuization of a desktop where they're putting a lot more polish
on there, they're changing things, polish might not be the right word, but they're
packaging and productizing it, going with their own display server because that fits
the needs of the product, not because it might technically be the better thing for everyone
in the community, but it helps them create a product that is good for general consumers
and so they're going that direction.
I think what Canonical and Ubuntu are doing right now is going to be the leading edge
of what's going to happen in a lot of products using Linux.
I think that's one way Linux will be brought to a lot more people.
It might not be that everybody has a big tower PC with a monitor and a keyboard and a mouse
hooked up to it and an Ethernet jack and power and all this kind of stuff, it might be tablets
and it might be Nest thermostats and it might be robots hooked into your Google Plus account
and all these kinds of things that are running Linux and eventually everyone will be using
Linux in every single way, it just might not be in the exact vision we have today.
That's a good point and I think in many ways we're already well into that direction as
it is, especially in the embedded markets and things like that, because I think the
desktop market is such a tough – it's like whack-a-mole in so many ways trying to
find that perfect sweet spot to where the market is saying, we don't care if it runs
Cheetos, we just want to make sure that it's accomplishing the tasks that I want to do.
Right, look at the huge success of Chromebooks now, right?
Yeah, exactly, because it accomplishes tasks versus what display server does it run and
whatnot.
I think what display server and that sort of thing, that stuff matters, but it matters
to a very compartmentalized group of people.
To people such as myself, I care, but getting someone like my wife or someone else to care,
that's a little bit tougher.
So it's going to be an interesting divide until we can begin to smooth out those edges
I think.
Yeah.
Well, when we move forward, one weird crazy device at a time that we all think is going
to fail until it doesn't like Chromebooks, you know what I mean?
I honestly was a big Chromebook hater.
I still think it's a little wonky.
I tried it, but you know what, the market speaks, and I think a lot of it's price based,
but yeah.
I think they're cute.
I mean, I think they're like the ideal, I don't know, college student, teenager kind
of thing.
I mean, I think they're great for that.
It's like you drop it, you shrug, and you go buy a new one.
I think the Chromebook shows a version though where it's not just the DVR or the closed
camera system like who me is saying, it's like it's all devices.
All consumer devices, because it seems like you look at, we just had a really great chat
on Coderadio yesterday about how what Microsoft is really up against is their whole model
is software licensing, and that is completely vanishing.
Subscription models, reoccurring subscription models where it's essentially a license and
you're getting access to the program like Adobe Creative Cloud or Office 365, but selling
somebody an $80 OEM license when they go to build a product, that's going to go away.
We speculated about perhaps even Windows going completely free at some point in the next
year or two, especially with this new CEO stepping in.
And I think if they don't, there's really going to be no reason people don't use these
free operating systems when they just need a base level OS and they're building on top
of that.
You know, when you look at Chromebooks, right?
Exactly.
Well, and I'm not super familiar with Windows 8, so I'm going to go out on a limb and say,
I assume that Microsoft still makes their business out of selling stickers, you know,
the little licensing stickers they like to put on computers.
You know, they are the biggest sticker based business I've ever seen.
And so if you lose that sticker, your CD becomes a coaster.
And I think they need to realize that that model is not only the worst customer experience
possible, but as you pointed out, it's not going to work.
Let's get out of stickers and let's, you know, maybe they can look into, I don't know, opening
up a nice pub or something.
So what really helped Windows back in the day was they had a really kind of good relationship
between their desktop product and their server products.
So if you ran, and that drove a lot of people to run Windows server and Windows desktops
in the business, which then drove a lot of people to buy Windows in the home because
they wanted to use what they're familiar with work.
You know, I remember my stepdad specifically didn't want to buy a Mac, didn't want to
use Ubuntu because the job he was working at used Windows XP and that's what he wanted.
He wanted to use exactly what they used at work at home.
That way he wouldn't have a problem at all.
And you know, to be frank, I understood the logic there.
I felt like, okay, I can totally empathize with that when you're not very comfortable
with computers.
And so in a sense, that's going away now with the whole bring your own device initiative
and a lot of those devices are Linux powered, primarily through Android and things like
that.
So Microsoft is transitioning to this whole cloud infrastructure, Azure, Office 365 subscription
models, and you know, also attempting to do the devices thing.
But the problem is Linux is already there on both fronts, on the cloud front and on
the devices front and not just like a little bit, right?
Like it's dominant, like it's the boss there.
And so they are really going to be up.
This new CEO has a ton of work and I wonder if because Linux is already the boss on the
server space, it's already the boss on the device space, if you almost have that same
thing again where, well, because we run it on the server and because I have it on my
devices, I'm also going to put it on these other devices.
And just for developers and for companies that are just trying to wrap their head around
products and delivering a decent product, it almost just makes it easier for them to
just put everything Linux because, well, we're already using that on the servers over here,
we're writing code for that, we're already shipping these Android devices, we're writing
code for that.
So you know what?
Let's just make it all Linux.
And I think that's sort of the thing we could be seeing put in place right now.
I think we're seeing that and that is what Microsoft's up against and it's like this
silent monster.
It's not this big company, it doesn't have any one particular logo on it, but it's still
this massive battle that I don't think they're fully equipped to fight.
They're equipped to fight IBM's and Apple's and Oracle's, right?
That's who Microsoft is armed to fight.
Microsoft, in my opinion, is going to continue to eat their own face when it comes to the
consumer market.
They hired who seems to be a really nice guy.
I'm sure he's going to really means well and is going to do his very best and I'm sure
he's great.
I don't think that, but they continue to make the same mistake they've always made and that's,
oh, why bring in someone new that might be able to help us in our shortcomings when we
can hire someone from within again?
Granted, he's got some great skill sets and like I said, I'm sure he's very talented,
but it's the bigger problems they're still hiring within.
They really do.
They need somebody to go and do some weed whacking.
Now, Bacon Drinker, you were going to make a point that you think if Windows goes free,
it's better for Linux?
No, it's worse for Linux, sorry.
Oh, it's worse for Linux.
Tell me.
You think people will do…
It's the web browser model.
You say like, well, the web browser idea is to say like, when a web browser is, when you
see someone running IE, you switch them to Chrome or when someone's PC breaks and you
reinstall it, you switch them to Chrome.
Well, if someone's PC breaks, you haven't got the moral problem of torrenting Windows,
so you're probably going to install Windows for free anyway.
Yeah, but who's going to want to run Metro on it?
I mean, you know, I think Microsoft is solving that problem for us.
I think they are going to, I think web applications, HTML5, that kind of crap, the crap that we
all hate hearing the buzz terms about, are making Windows less relevant and I think Microsoft
is doing us all a favor by making Windows less relevant.
Paul Thrott over at winsupersite.com ran a story, I think, I can't remember what the
title was, but it was a good title, and he makes the case that he goes through and lists
all of the people that have lost their jobs, the entire divisions that they've done house
cleanings on, and he even proposes Balmer's loss of his job is because of what a catastrophe
Windows 8 is, and he writes, he says, he's talked to people in there that, you know,
they think it's worse than Vista, and they think, not in terms of sales, but in terms
of public image, and they think that they may have set Windows back a decade, is the
term they're using internally, that Windows has been set back a decade.
Ouch.
Yeah.
Not shocking, but ouch.
That's, that's pretty, you know, that's pretty damning.
And so some people are speculating now pretty openly, well Paul Thrott is the person I'm
talking about, but other people as well that, you know, maybe this, maybe the reason why
they went with Satya Nadella, I think is how you say the last name, Satya Nadella, is because
they just really have to double down and focus on no longer making Windows the center of
the Microsoft folks.
Remember back, I think we all remember that quote for Balmer saying, Windows is the future
of Microsoft.
Hey, we want to make an Xbox, you put Windows on it.
Hey, you want to make a device, put Windows on it.
Hey, you need that servers, doing something, put Windows on it, and then load SQL on it.
You got yourself a winning combo everybody.
And it was Windows this, Windows that, Windows this, Windows that.
Now it's all going to be about these reoccurring subscriptions, this Office 365, Azure, and
all these things.
But the problem with these is they inherently have a very high run cost.
And while that might work good in the rich Western worlds, it's not going to work good
in some of the poorer places in this world.
And it's never going to lock them in as a dominant force.
They're never going to be number one in cloud hosted services.
That's already been claimed really.
And they do it to themselves too.
It's like if you look at Office 365, which I've had some limited experience with, it's
been a couple of months, but when I looked at it, I'm thinking, okay, so compared to
the Google offerings, which are free, you want me to pay for something that for a non-enterprise
user isn't really compellingly different other than maybe visually different.
They seem to shoot themselves in the foot as soon as they launch something like that.
They launch these products and say, okay, how can we either overbrand it with too many
versions, charge something when quite frankly no one's going to pay for it, not out of
the enterprise anyway, and what the hell?
Their thinking doesn't make any sense.
Yeah.
It's like a lack of focus.
I agree.
It really is.
Craig.
We're also ignoring something kind of important that people will just use Windows because
they know Windows.
Yeah.
I've seen that change more and more though.
That is until they have a reason not to, and there's going to be a thousand different reasons
not to, I think.
Even if it's like tablets, right?
If you shift, if you're an average user and you shift 70% of your computing workload over
to a tablet when you're at home, like reading email, checking Facebook, all of these things,
tablets actually in some ways better at really.
So isn't that a loss for Microsoft?
Just right there?
Even if people are just using the Windows desktop 70% less of the time?
Well, not just that, but I also know of three computer technicians here in town, one of
them who's a pretty big player, is tired of offering Microsoft's only solutions and has
now begun offering some Linux solutions.
He's not going to say this publicly because he has a Microsoft agreement, but the point
is that this is happening and he's actually, a lot of people are saying, oh, okay, well,
I want to do Windows 7 or Windows 8.
Oh, I have old hardware.
Oops, sorry, I'm screwed.
I've got to buy new peripherals because nothing's supported.
And so it's becoming a value proposition for him to offer them an operating system he can
still support and not look like a douchebag.
So and then tablets and things, that's more of a younger audience.
There's a pretty much 45 and up.
I don't know.
I think seniors, I think there's a pretty good use case and I say that because in our
own family, some of the older folks who had computer phobias, the family got them tablets
and they've really taken them.
And one of the things like on the Kindles that they really like is they can really increase
the size of the text.
So it makes it a lot easier for them to read.
Kindle fires have been pretty good.
Yeah, I've seen a few.
You know, my grandma hasn't had a computer her entire life and now is on email all the
time and she's emailing with the church group and constantly on the thing.
I mean, she's like.
So for her, and it wasn't just her, it was also several family members who were just
anti-technology, but once they got their hands on one, gosh, you know, it really was like
a pretty big transformation for them.
So I don't know.
And perhaps the other value for the family members too is that you're no longer, you
don't feel like you have to be afraid of it anymore, like you did with the Windows box.
Right, you're not worried about the malware, and it's so dead simple, it's like you just
turn it on, right?
You just turn it on and push the mail icon.
And honestly, for some of these people, like the barrier was the mouse, like they just
didn't know how to use a mouse.
Now they can touch the thing.
But Craig, you were going to make a point that it's convergence that's doing Windows
8.
Yeah, what I've seen while I worked at Memory Express was that the biggest issues with most
customers computers were that they didn't know how to use Windows 8 and that when they
went from a tablet to Windows 8, it still wasn't the same, even though they're made
the same.
And there's just a whole bunch of issues with people learning the new OS and they're
shooting themselves in the foot by making it too different without leaving in some key
information that helps people transition.
And by having a cell phone that acts like a tablet and a tablet that acts like a computer
is just confusing people even more.
Yeah, I think they didn't go far enough, like in the sense, like I think maybe the work
that's being done now by folks to have that device more like role change and then try
to be the same thing all the time.
I think that's probably the more winning recipe.
And it also makes more sense as devices get more powerful, they can afford to do that.
You know what I'm talking?
Like you put in a dock hooked up to a computer, you get a desktop UI.
I think the biggest problem is the model of quote convergence they went with.
In article they're going with a fairly similar UI and with Unity 8 applications should be
able to run across the different platforms.
The KDE plasma interface, you have the plasma that you have on the desktop, they'll be your
main plasma interface on a tablet.
Yeah, there's plasma active which is definitely very plasma driven and then the idea there
just like with Unity 8 would be that it would switch and I think as long, I think what we
are all worried about in those scenarios is that the applications in desktop mode will
feel like mobile applications and I think that's maybe almost impossible to avoid for
the first year or so as developers are just working on this stuff, adding features and
changing things based on user feedback because sometimes you just don't know until a couple
thousand people have banged on it for a while.
Sorry, I think the death of Windows 8 was in the desktop, not the tablet.
Yeah, for sure, yeah, absolutely.
Because if you look back at it, the uproar was really not being able to access the start
menu.
No, actually people are pretty positive about it in the mobile sense.
People love the tiles.
Ooh, the tiles.
Yeah, I definitely would say that when I was experiencing it and then listening to other
people talk about it, they loved it.
Some of the lower end Windows tablets, they weren't real impressed with the performance
in comparison to other tablets but they did like the layout.
They felt it was easy to navigate but yeah, the desktop was a boy.
That's a mess.
All right, we got one more.
I think a KDE tablet would own them all for looks.
We will see.
We'll see.
Stay tuned and find out.
All right, so one bit of feedback.
Speaking of desktops, this is our last bit.
The traditional desktop, Voodoo 6, who says he was going to make it this week but I don't
see him in here.
He says, I've made fun of Mate in the past and now I feel kind of bad about it.
I listened to the show and decided to go grab the live CD and give it a run in VirtualBox
and I have to say I'm pretty impressed.
They've actually come a long way with Mate and made some improvements in all the right
places and also holy hell is it fast.
Even running from a live CD in VirtualBox with compositing enabled, it just zipped right
along and then later on, he said, I went ahead and set it up on one of my workstations and
I've been using it all morning.
It's really good stuff.
I felt like my opinion about the Mate desktop was changed during last week's episode too.
So it's cool to see that some of the folks in the audience felt that way.
All right, Matt, well before we jump into the Debian stuff and this is why we have a
big mumble room today, we got a lot of folks in there.
I think people have been following this topic with quite an interest and it's been one of
these things that has just, I mean it's been like, you could have sports commentary doing
a live stream of this at some point.
It has really just been a heck of a thing to watch.
So before we get to that, I want to thank DigitalOcean, our sponsor for this week's
episode of Linux Unplugged.
DigitalOcean is so great.
It's simple cloud hosting dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way to spin up
a cloud server.
These things are so super quick.
Users can create a cloud server in about 55 seconds.
I got it down to 47 seconds.
I believe, what, our record right now, was it 44 seconds?
Was that what it was?
I haven't seen that beat.
I think it was.
I think it was 44 because I think you had the record previously.
I did.
Now I kind of want to create another one just so I can try to beat 44 seconds.
I think I can do it.
I think I can do it because I'm getting the UI down.
It's so simple and intuitive.
I kind of just know where to go without even looking.
I could do it without even, with like one mouse tight, I don't know.
Anyways, DigitalOcean, check this out.
A little bit of an announcement here.
DigitalOcean has locations in New York, San Francisco, Amsterdam, and now Singapore.
They just added Singapore today, so congratulations to DigitalOcean.
Here's what's great.
Users, while you're over there and you can spin up this cloud server in 55 seconds, that's
awesome, right?
Sure, that's good.
But check out what you get for $5.
You ready for this?
If you're a user of DigitalOcean for $5, you're going to get 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte
SSD, a CPU, and one terabyte of transfer.
A terabyte of transfer is really quite a bit, and I love that it's a fixed cost.
Boom, I know exactly what I'm going to get, so you got to go check them out.
Just for their intuitive control panel, and they also allow you to replicate it on a much
larger scale with a really straightforward API.
So go over to DigitalOcean.com and check them out.
They got a great droplet system with images that are all ready to go.
You can pay by the hour if you just want to do testing for a little bit, tons of really
great features, and Linux fans, which I think you might be, will appreciate that they're
doing this all on top of KVM.
This is a great example of how Linux empowers a company to do a whole new category of product
that just a few years ago wasn't even possible.
This is just they're taking advantage of technology built into Linux.
They're using great hardware, tier one bandwidth, and it really just all comes together.
This is the kind of stuff as we're about to start talking about system D here in a little
bit.
It's this kind of stuff that when these distributions make these underlying infrastructure changes
it has such wide reaching impacts, such ramifications, and the implementation of KVM into the Linux
kernel.
This is a great example of how something just blew up a whole new industry that is now providing
a whole new level of service at a whole new price never possible for, and what's even
better is you can get it for free for two months.
If you use our promo code LINUXUNPLUGGEDFEBRUARY when you check out Linux Unplugged February,
all one word will get you a $10 digital ocean credit.
You can use that $5 server for two months.
I've been running that $5 server for a while now and it just, man, Linux performs like
a champ and you combine it with those SSDs and their bandwidth, man it flies.
It's so great.
And the fact you can actually if you want to like say bang out an arch server, you can
and it's super fast, it's easy, what a great place to, it's like oh I wonder, I've heard
some things about this package, I've heard it enhances or hinders something, I can try
it out on the server.
It's like oh that's what it does.
You know without actually having to do anything locally.
It's great.
They're big fans of the Docker project too.
They're always really staying in sync with that project.
They're making it so awesome to deploy applications up on the server.
It's really cool.
So go check them out.
DigitalOcean.com, promo code LINUXUNPLUGGEDFEBRUARY and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for their
awesome support of Linux Unplugged.
Okay.
So, Ron do you want to start by bringing us up to date on, is he in here, Ron are you?
Yeah, Ron do you want to start by bringing us up to date on kind of where we're at right
now with the Debian init system because I got to be honest, I got to make a disclaimer.
After Sunday came around and we kind of looked like we were locked into system D, I sort
of stopped carrying a little bit just because it seemed like a lot of drama was, it seemed
like things were getting a little nasty, a little personal.
So what's happened in the last couple of days since like say Sunday, Rod?
Well the main issue is that they've kind of officially decided that system D is what they're
going with and the drama started with Ian kind of calling for a vote for BDale to be
pulled down as chairman.
That kind of pretty much backfired in him and people were starting to say that he needs
to be taken out of the TC.
So to kind of stave off that, right the technical committee, he decided to stave off that happening.
He kind of voluntarily is taking a break for a couple of days he said and then as soon
as that happened the next day BDale cast his vote which kind of solidified system D being
the choice.
And if I'm correct, tell me if I'm not, BDale because he's chair, in the case of a tie,
his vote counts as two votes.
So it'd be two votes for system D if there's a tie, right?
Anybody else know if that's true or not?
Well, I'm pretty sure it's something like that but it wasn't necessary because basically
Ian pulled himself out of voting.
And this is kind of interesting voluntarily standing down now, is that because did you
guys get the impression that's because people were accusing him of having some sort of ulterior
motive here?
What was the what was the reason for the step aside just because emotions were getting flaring
up and things like that?
It was getting really heated.
So whether that's why or not but essentially when he called for the BDale to be dropped
down, I think three people called for him to be kicked out.
Wow.
Okay, so I here's this is kind of stuff I just I'm not really that big on following
but I just wanted to sort of set up what's been going on so that way people have some
context of sort of the you know the scope of this decision that apparently is it's really
weighing on the on the Debian project here and what has really struck me on the onset
of all this is how it all seemed like a foregone conclusion to me and I think this is part
of why I've been so frustrated with this whole thing because technically speaking system
D seems like just from a pure technical standpoint the superior solution but then when you also
consider the things like the CLA and other and other problems that would be introduced
that also seems like it clearly eliminates upstart unless they want to take on some sort
of fork and then you look at other solutions like open RC that have a lot of critics it
always seemed like system D was the proper choice and the fact that system D is already
available in Debian testing seemed like it made it the obvious choice.
So what the hell what the hell am I not seeing here what am I not getting what is it what
is it they have been debating over what has been the big roadblock here for them making
a decision on this kind of thing and the reason why I almost sound a little upset is because
it's almost getting a little embarrassing at this point.
It's Debian though.
Well well it's pretty much done now it seems but they I'd say the only thing they were
really arguing over is the well two things is the CLA and the other kernel connection
which basically system D breaks that.
I guess what I'm worried about is this are we watching sort of the are we watching Debian
become an ineffective project or has it always been this bad and this is just sort of the
recent thing that highlights it I guess is that does that seem like a fair question?
Well I think it is I think you've mentioned before in the past that you know these type
of debates and discussions have pretty much always happened inside you know different
Linux communities but now with so many different mailing lists and people looking to put out
news articles the moment something gets said it gets repeated around so many times.
So I think it's just as you've stated in the past the speed at which we now broadcast this
these discussions and these disagreements has grown so much that now it seems like it's
worse than I believe it really is.
Yeah it's basically the same for it's been like the same for the past five years at least
that I can remember.
This one seems particularly bad though.
But it just didn't get as heated.
I think maybe that's why it's gotten the coverage it has and it's not just news outlets anymore
it's just general interested bystanders are tweeting out links to the mailing list it's
every every major new post is you know there's four posts of it to reddit.
Daredevil I want to give you a chance to chime in here what do you think?
You know what I was about just to say is that pretty much the discussions on the mailing
list is always a slow communication medium and until getting that it's just a matter
of we're constantly looking because it's an interesting project that's it.
But other decisions on Debian have been always sort of posing ethical and technical questions
they don't focus on only on the technical side.
Crossroads do you think this is a lack of focus problem?
I mean yeah I think that they want to I think that they want Debian to be available to as
many people as possible so they want it to even be available on the on the BSD and systems
and system D requires C groups that they won't run on BSD.
Popeye is our resident upstart fan I'm always interested to hear what you think.
I wouldn't say I'm necessarily an upstart fan.
I'm just poking.
Yeah I know I'm not so sure I mean I mentioned last time that there's more eyeballs on this
partly because you know there's more eyeballs on everything because of social media and
everyone wanting instant updates on everything and everyone reporting everything pretty quickly
after the event occurs and keeping an eye on mailing lists and that becomes news.
But also don't forget the other side which is a positive side Debian is much more popular
and much more heavily used than it ever was before so any of these discussions that happened
on a random Debian mailing list the only people who are interested were nerds whereas now
you've got Ubuntu users, Mint users, system D developers, Fedora users, Red Hat users,
all these people who are interested in Debian.
So there's a lot of focus on it not just from the media but also from people who have a
vested interest in what goes on in Debian.
I think that is a big point to underscore right there and Bank and Drinker you sounded
like you had a kind of a perspective from a new Linux user is this look like insanity
from the outside?
No it sort of looks like it's been overblown so the way I look at it is from what I can
see from a newbies perspective it sort of doesn't matter as much as it's been shown
us because from what I can see if system D isn't your thing you can just install upstart
or open RC.
Yeah I think you know I think this is part of I think there's I almost feel like there
was a bigger decision being made in a sense at the same time they were picking the init
system and I feel like that decision was do we want to unify a great part of the core
of Linux in a sense and some people feel like in part of doing that we're throwing out a
bit of the Unix philosophy and there's this constant reevaluation in the Linux community
about the our Unix roots versus practical needs and I feel like that was the meta discussion
being had and perhaps that's why the interest was so intense and the Debian committee technical
committee and the other Debian developers maybe felt the weight of that meta discussion
what do you guys think?
I also think sorry that it was a lot of it was emotion to be honest it was quite an emotional
discussion more than the technical one.
Go ahead Poppy.
Russ Albury posted a lengthy mail recently which kind of sought to explain some of the
stuff that went on on the list on the technical committee and the fact that these guys are
all friends and they get on fairly well and maybe people's perspective from the outside
is not the same perspective as those guys on the inside have.
Right right yeah that's fair Q5 why don't you chime in I know you had something to say.
Yeah I've talked with a lot of people recently about this and I've noticed a trend that there
seem to be a large number of people you were discussing about meta discussions that a lot
of people have become pro System D just because they're against some of the business moves
that Canonical has made and by extension I want to reject Canonical by rejecting Upstart.
So it's like a form of Canonical hate in a sense to just like System D because it's
not Upstart.
Yeah I've actually heard that statement from people before regarding System D versus Upstart
where people have said you know I don't really know much about System D I just don't want
Upstart to get it because that's what Canonical made.
I guess there's probably always some of that going on and I wonder too like I look at I
look at the big like down the road now what these kind of events do is they look really
dramatic while they're happening but in a sense I feel like a lot of consensus has been
built around System D now.
Like I think the end result is the rest of the community just had this massive conversation
and came to an agreement that they then all exerted upon the Debian community but as a
whole collective System D kind of went from this Lenard's interesting thing that he's
building for Red Hat to oh yeah this is probably the way that all Linux that can should go
but it's not the end of all Linux's that don't and I think I think but I do think it does
underscore this interesting consensus making process that happens as a result of these
big flare ups and in the end result the community the hive mind comes to larger conclusions
what do you think of that?
I'm inclined to agree with you and I think there are there's a lot of focus on these
things at the time but then later on we we move on like you know who really cares now
that Ubuntu move the buttons to the left hand side who really cares that Ubuntu doesn't
have GIMP on the CD who really cares that the CD is the image is over 800 megabytes
so only fits on a USB stick at the time these things seem so important it's like the Beatles
or Justin Bieber you know at the time it seems like it's massively important to everyone
on the planet right now but you skip skip forward three years and nobody gives a crap.
You know my favorite go-to for that is the whole Microsoft Novell deal that like we dedicated
like three weeks of the Linux action show to covering and everybody was ready to burn
Novell at the stake and here we are what three four year five years later and it doesn't
really seem to have made too much of a difference on anything and we were all worried that like
it was had some there was some sort of patent play at it that you know the Samba project
was doomed and all these kinds of things that really turned out not to be a big deal.
It's interesting how that comes about in hindsight because I mean at the time yeah that was you
know it was perceived as just like you know the the clouds are turning blood red and the
sun's gonna fall out of the sky and everything and I think the problem with this kind of
consensus building is there are now tools available to manipulate the hive and like
sort of and I think I think Lenart and crew kind of comes out looking like the good guys
and not the good guys but kind of look comes out looking better on this whole thing and
and really that was because he was able to go to his own Google Plus feed and have a
platform to influence a lot of people and what they were how they how they viewed it
and I think really you really think Lenart comes out being the good guy in this.
I do not necessarily in terms of like like like the traditional sense but in terms of
like the most logical maybe I don't know like like having the having the clearer perspective
of the group it's not the right way to put either I think I think he comes away looking
like he was he was right in the end maybe is that the way to put it?
So he may well be technically right but I challenge you to go back over the last six
months of Google Plus and whatever other mailing lists and find every occasion where Lenart
has taken potshots at upstart pointing out bug reports pointing out things that upstart
does or doesn't do.
Now I agree.
Now now now go back and find upstart developers doing the same thing and you know what you
won't find them.
I agree that that's not I don't really mean I don't mean all of that feed I just mean
like during the heat of the discussion he's able to go and have a platform that he was
able to influence a lot of people's thinking on the matter I mean I think if you look at
like r slash Linux a lot of people were just repeating things that he posted on his G plus
feed as if it was their own ideas and their own concepts and right it reminds me of an
American presidential campaign exactly all these kind of Google Plus messages need to
say underneath my name's Lenart Pottering and I approve of this message right it's that's
exactly what I mean and I think that's why we have to be a little bit worried about this
form of consensus building because it is ripe for manipulation and that's my point is that
and I say most of my opinion regarding this matter actually came out of these Linux unplugged
discussions and I kind of figured it was either going to be open RC or a system the nothing
against canonical nothing against technically against upstart but I don't think they would
have chosen that for the CLA crossroads I want to give you a chance to jump in to
I don't really think that anyone came out looking like a good guy because the system
D people what like Toby said we're going through and buying the bug reports and I almost looked
petty and an upstart folks were just kind of silent so I don't think when there's this
kind of arguing and this kind of tit for tat stuff if no one looks like a good guy good
guy might not have been the right way to put I was just trying to think of a way to kind
of frame it where I think people kind of rallied around the points he was making and kind of
decided to you know to pick up on what he was what he was championing championing well
I think I think he had technical accuracy on his side you know he was he was able to
point out the odd bug report here and there or point out where system D might be technically
superior and he and he certainly has that on his side and this it's very easy to rally
round someone who is articulate and able to express how their product is technically better
than someone else's but you don't have to be a douche when you do it that is that is
sort of the underscores like if you can if you can manage to if you manage to do all
that without offending a bunch of people that's sort of a win-win Baker drinker I wanted to
let you chime in on the sort of the state of the debate yeah so all girls receive some
as intense as it was Linux debate is sort of meant to be this way it sort of I was watching
a talk a TED talk with Linus Torvalds boss and he explained how intense debate comes
with a better decision at the end of day and I sort of think that people saying that the
way the debate was not gone so politely if you will is kind of wrong I think it debate
should be this way and it's worked out better it's actually almost been sickingly polite
in some ways like here's be Dale's announcement that they're going with system D he writes
thank you Anthony for your analysis of the votes per six dot three dot two I use my casting
vote to choose D as the winner therefore the resolution reads we exercise our power to
decide in case of overlapping jurisdiction six dot one dot two bias by assuring that
the default init system for Linux architectures in Jesse should be system D should the project
pass a general resolution before the release of Jesse asserting a position statement about
issues of the of the day on init systems that position replaces the outcome of this vote
and is adopted by the technical committee on its own decision that's a really interesting
way to speak you know it sounds like it's like a like legislation being I could well
yeah except the differences as things are actually happening that's true dubbing actually
has activity no the bigger thing there is I think that it's it's not only sounds official
but it'd be hard not to bust into laughter doing it really I would think yeah I mean
they wanted they want to make it official I suppose they are the way making history
with some of these decisions sure I guess there is that element to it all right guys
will any other comments before we round off this discussion I will just like I would just
like to say that actually earlier someone mentioned that the coverage like it wouldn't
matter because we thought it was important at the time but I think actually covering
such issues sometimes is what provokes people to think about the as an issue and actually
try to find the better the best resolution and not attempt misleading directions yeah
it does make for interesting back listening to when you go back and listen to the issues
of the day in a way it's sort of a living documentation of what happened in some sense
you know you get some of the nooks and crannies of the issue that you don't get when you look
back on it three five years later so it's kind of fun from that standpoint talk about
today and it you know open source and Linux so much is about building one piece at a time
and and it's at that in itself inherently calls for analysis and discussion about the
piece you're working on because every future piece after it is built on top of it so every
piece matters in a sense and I think this one in particular because of the weight of
the overall decision because of the meta discussion going on in the greater community it's been
going on for a couple of years now I think this one in particular reach beyond just the
interest of bloggers and podcasters and etc I think it really reached to the general user
like poppy made the excellent point it affects it affects so many people now because the
Debian project has grown and you know with with other huge projects like Ubuntu based
on it it is really it's an important player now and what's really interesting about it
is you could you could easily make it's one of our most important players and it is truly
community driven and we have just watched this process unfold I mean who knows what
kind of discussion there was internally at Red Hat before they set off on system D we
probably could glean some of it from mailing list but I bet you don't get the full scope
like you do here with Debian and it's just kind of interesting to watch it a truly community
based project go through this process and yeah I don't know if it's necessarily a bad
thing it took him as long as it did it just I wish it didn't get as heated and I wish
maybe people would give folks a little more slack and consider that you know they are
watching something from the outside I think yeah I think that's true I mean there's we
do need to be sensitive to the fact there may be a lot of underpinnings we're not aware
of and I have no problem with the amount of time that it takes but I think unless there
was actual like threats made against people or whatever I do think the emotional side
of it really is going to be hard to justify but the rest of it I would definitely agree
I think that there's no question there's got to be things we're not aware of that could
definitely get people a little bit riled but you know but we're all adults guys you know
we got to at some point you got to like the person that stepped away that's the right
approach that's good yeah it was a good decision you know if you're still kind of a little
stuck on all of this well I got good news because it's one of these things it's it's
maybe hard to wrap your brain around until you can play it as a video game well good
news we actually have a video game version of the Ubuntu init system debate I'll have
a link to the show notes you're kidding me no it's for real it's like it's it's here
we go I'm playing it right now it's an it's an attorney game yeah the Debbie in init case
get great emerald's trial and it explains to you what the hell's going on with all of
this in video game style there we go there we go yeah yeah what kind of achievement do
you get if you get the right one this is so this is so 80s awesome right now early 90s
awesome and so look I mean come on how is this not the best way it's like Final Fantasy
meets the Debbie in init debate I'm really disappointed that your idea of a game for
this is not flappy bird it kind of felt like watching flappy somebody play flappy bird
I'll tell you that yeah that's true well anyways I'll have a link to the Debbie in init case
in the in the show notes if you want to get in on some of that craziness and then you
know you get to learn a little something out and have fun this is true maybe next time
they'll take poppy's advice and make the flappy bird edition assuming that well and if you
install it on your phone and then you can flip it on eBay for 50 grand or what isn't
that crazy I know all right so Ben a 14 year old listener writes in and he says hey there
Chris and Matt I'm a 14 year old Linux user who would self proclaim himself as a Linux
geek and I'm an avid listener of Linux unplugged well hello Ben says I use arch well how about
that inspired by inspired by the arch challenge and roll my own arch Linux Raspberry Pi lamp
server as well as being a happy user of a custom rig built by myself oh man I want to
adopt you he says and more he says and the more I look around the amount of Linux advocates
of my generation is very a very small number and it worries me it worries me and surely
could be some concern to people of your generation as kids aren't getting sufficient education
about computers other kids my generation in my so-called IT classes don't seem to be educated
enough unless they really go and look for it like myself which most people will not
do personally I I think that kids of my generation probably of others are not being stretched
and not getting the sufficient grounding they need I could be arrogant here although I reckon
I could teach my IT class better than my minimum wage teacher does well it sounds like you
might be able to which brings me on to my next point Linux doesn't seem relevant to
a lot of people and it seems somehow minor to them I have largely covered my thoughts
on the matter of Linux's popularity which I cover on a blog that I call the Linux situation
be great if you would just look over it and share your thoughts thanks for the thanks
guys and keep up the good work so Ben says that a lot of people don't find Linux relevant
anymore and the darn kids now we talked about this a little bit the darn kids aren't finding
Linux that interesting and I just saw an article I don't have a link to it I just saw an article
recently that said Linux should be part of IT curriculum and that doesn't yeah doesn't
that kind of make sense to for an IT curriculum that makes complete sense if you want to teach
computers teach them what teach them like to load a Linux distribution you can learn
so much about disk partitioning and so like if you're really taking a computer class it
almost doesn't make a disservice to use Windows because it's like teaching somebody how to
work on a car and you give them a car with the hood sealed that's right that's right
because I know I folks now that are suffering because of that they they specialized in Windows
and now we're having to backtrack and learn stuff that they could have had the opportunity
to learn a long time ago so it's actually become a hindrance yeah yeah go ahead I'm
sorry go ahead I was just gonna say that I think the biggest part of all this is mainly
like you know if you teach them one specific technology then a few years later you have
this big setback and what should really be the core part about it is teaching okay here's
the basic parts of the computer here's how to get a good sense for being able to read
error messages or whatever to basically give the foundation for a flexible mind about computing
so that you know as time goes on you're able to adjust to whatever various things may come
in just because you have enough of a foundation that you're able to reason your way through
anything that gets put in front of you and and of course knowing how to use Google or
whatever to do your own research yeah well that sounds good but it's highly debatable
what is a good foundation so that would be hard to do a curriculum for yeah that's true
so the guy in here says he's part of this generation he has some thoughts on this go
ahead the guy hi Chris less yeah so I'm part of this newfangled teenage generation and
I just wanted to say that I really agree that there's not enough education about that this
sort of thing I go to a school with over a thousand kids and of them I'm one of maybe
like five people that's heard of Linux and I'm the only person that actually uses it
that I'm aware of it's just a matter of people don't know go ahead everything that I learned
about Linux was just on my own I mean I first talked about it through a con what's it called
a conference and most people don't go to that sort of thing yeah yeah urban urban 120 go
ahead yes I think that I heard first of Linux one time that I was with some guys that know
a lot about computers but I actually started using Linux because I started watching news
action show and I figured out that it is awesome I'm 16 years old and in my school we mentioned
feelings that it exists but we in school views word views Microsoft everything is based on
not free software right and everything is from Microsoft or from other companies yeah
when we gave an assignment for school we need to we need to have it in font times new roman
which is from Microsoft and dots dots file and everything is based on the proprietary
solutions all right bit puffin go ahead yeah I was just thinking that this doesn't only
apply to like operating systems but also like software in general like for example in my
school with 3d program we learned Maya and Photoshop but it would have been better I
think if we learned gimp and blender because that we could use after school yeah you can
get on your own I know that's what you do like freelance work so yeah crossroads you're
from this generate that the generation we're speaking of what do you think I mean I go
to a school probably about 2000 there are very very few kids who know what Linux is
and I can say the word Linux or the word open source and I just get kind of this look like
what are you talking about actually our home our homecoming King this year what is a Linux
nerd he's one of my best friends but um anyway I would love for there to be some basic computer
education because I've had people ask me why the Internet's broken and why I mean it's
just there needs to be something and even if it's not Linux there needs to be something
like this is the Internet yeah I mean I do worry about getting down a path of like you
see on Star Trek where the Captain Kirk arrives to the planet and it's being run by one giant
computer and nobody knows how to how it works and they all think it's a god and they all
worship it or something with her done I know you want to make a point go ahead I think
the problem goes further than that I mean I've just completed university and the number
of people that couldn't even install basic software was ridiculous so I don't even think
they're teaching anything at all in IT classes so it's pretty much a joke isn't this isn't
this why tablets are seeing the success they are because it is really just so much easier
for people to pick them up and install apps I mean I literally I mean I'm looking at people
who've never used a computer in their lives and they're in their 50s 60s and even 70s
and they're picking these things up and they're they're installing applications like Netflix
and Kindle and they're using them and it's just blowing my mind I mean there's still
kids my age who I had one girl come up to me and ask me how do I install this app and
she was running she was an iPhone it's not like it's even difficult she didn't even know
how to install an app well there is that daredevil I want to give you a chance to make your point
so I actually think we can have a different view for a while on this matter I think in
the overall picture IT education has been focused on application usage and getting just
whatever the school is sponsored to sort of make advertising propaganda and at that point
I don't think it's a matter of what the school teaches but actually if we look at the user
base that Linux has has been pretty much a matter of getting people into learning on
their own and they actually become much more informed and at that point I think it benefits
the overall community and helps actually introducing users not just as users but as also contributors
or part of the community and I don't think that's a bad thing I think it could be improved
and I think actually shows like this do their part on putting the word out I hope so and
I think you're right to an extent that if it's important enough and people need to get
a job done they eventually come across it in a lot of cases people don't know about
Linux is simply because they've never needed to solve a problem that it solves all right
well we got we got we're gonna wrap up with the last two here MW for her M woofer M woofer
I like that I make you I apologize for that I never really thought about the name ever
being pronounced out loud it's just my initials and then the first four characters in my last
name so it's okay yeah well I was just gonna say that what I've been seeing more and more
of is developing this blind spot where it's it's not quite fear but more just willful
ignorance of some kind where they just say well it's a computer I probably can't understand
it I'm not going to try to understand it and you know when when they have to do something
on the computer they go in and they flail around but it's like they're developing this
mental block that maybe at a lot of points they aren't even realizing is operating that's
just keeping them from picking up information it's a computer therefore I'll never learn
how to do it so therefore I just won't that kind of thing bacon drinker do you want to
take us out with your last point yeah I think the problem lies in in modern technologies
and I've succeeded some from the new generation but when you know when you go back in 10 20
years when you have when you bought something you had a screw in the back of it and you
could open it quite easily with the Phillips screwdriver and look inside but nowadays you've
got like talk five screws on the MacBooks and glued to get the phones and it's no incentive
to go ahead and open this stuff right in fact there's every incentive not to open it exactly
damage it and void the warranty in the case of good phone and things like that yeah I
don't truly own a device until you avoid its warranty that very good right very true or
until you've taken it apart and put it back together again well let's let's take the rest
of this in the post show discussion because I think that's a good a good point to wrap
up to in a response to Ben's email and Ben I hope some of that's help provide some insights
and you know one thing you can always do is show folks a way for folks to have a need
to be solved a problem to be solved and show them how Linux solves that problem and I think
once you show them make what it can do for them maybe it's maybe they want to finally
get into some sort of application development maybe they want to set up a file server at
home and run Plex honestly it always depends on the person you know that's one of the reasons
I used to love comp is is I used to show comp is off at work and clients and people just
like oh my god what is that what how do you do that oh this is Linux let me show you and
that was a door opener and nowadays I just had somebody over at my house a total computer
noob and they were just blown away by Plex blown away by Plex could never see anything
like Plex can't believe something like Plex exists it's incredible like well here's what
you need and you know that could be an example well here let me set up a help you set up
a Linux box install Ubuntu here we'll put Plex media server on it Bob's your uncle Bob's
your uncle all right now well I think that's a good spot to wrap up here for this week's
episode of Linux Unplugged you know I know I mentioned it earlier but you got to come
over on Sunday to jblive.tv everybody and watch this we're gonna be doing Linux action
show 300 don't worry I think we'll probably release it for download if you can't make
it live but you know that's coming up yeah all right well very good Matt also I want
to I want to remind folks you can also watch this show live and participate in our virtual
log we do this at 2 p.m. on a Tuesday you can also go to Jupiter broadcasting.com slash
calendar and you just get it converted in your local time you don't have to do the time
math and you can hang on our awesome chat room thanks chat room and thank you Matt I'll
see you on Sunday see you then all right everyone thanks so much for tuning this week's episode
of Linux Unplugged see you right back here next week!