Hey look there's a picture of Popey. Oh, oh, he looks so happy surprise. I bet he smells good there, too
What the hell are you using the laptop is that your phone Popey that you have hooked up to a keyboard ten times the size
Of your phone. What is that? That was that was for him because he wanted a photo of a phone doing convergency stuff
Oh
I see I see I like the image text where the desktop was the phone is now says I love stroking the rich mahogany
He blew his ex we ask you. Yeah, really
What kind of that is a heck of a keyboard is there a lot of battery in that thing what's going on with that
Why is it so big?
The Logitech one. It's so you could you could sit a tablet in it and but it's only got a double-a and it lasts forever
Like you lost a year. Well, you got one. It's brilliant. Oh, I love I have a oh, so it's not that thick
So I have a Logitech this because that looks really thick in the picture and the Logitech I have is quite thick
Oh, it's quite scary
It's it's quite I think about a centimeter and a half thick Chris, which is about no furlongs or something
Oh, yeah, some students and it's gonna work. It's got something like that
Well, there you go. Either way you can tell that's a man who smells good. That's all I know
Look at that USB cable to there. Look at that. That's a nice flat USB cable. I like that poppy
Is that an internet phone there on the table to get an iPhone 4 or something there? What is that?
There's no iPhones there. That's a BQ phone. Oh
Okay. Okay. Well, they all kind of look alike these days. There's a bunch of phones. Yeah
Yeah, I moved all of the none of them two phones out of the way, yeah, right
Smart man, this is Linux unplugged episode 139 for April 5th 2016
Oh
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's celebrating Wes's upcoming birthday with a little birthday beer that he brought himself
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Happy early birthday. Well, thank you
Thanks for bringing your birthday beer
Every time well coming up on today's episode of the unplugged program
We're gonna do some updates on our favorite open source projects like we always do and here are some of those
Directly from the horse's mouth then in the in the second half of the show if you will
We're gonna try out a brand new distribution that promises to be beautiful elegant up-to-date fast
Ultra customized and arch-based and it's not a district. You've probably heard of before
Yes, kids. We're gonna look at this guy and tell you if it truly is something you want to take out on a rig like
Yours, maybe Wes has sacrificed his own rig for you to find out standby. We'll tell you about that in a little bit after that. I
Gotta admit it. I've been bit a little bit by the hype bug. I
Want to play with virtual reality Wes, but in Linux land, there's not much going on
Or is there is there a virtual reality desktop environment?
Are there projects available for Linux users right now if you have virtual reality hardware?
We're gonna take a look at the state of virtual reality under Linux and some of the things you could play on
Right now and some of the interesting things that Wes and I discovered we were digging around about the state of VR under Linux, too
Which is just kind of an interesting tidbits that we're gonna share plus
We got a whole bunch of other things in today's show, but to top it all off
I did mention we were drinking birthday beers Wes brought in something fun
And I think the moment was gonna give us a hard time about this one
So maybe we'll bring them in first before we really read this one time appropriate greetings mumble room
Okay, now you gotta forgive me
Okay, so you gotta forgive me cuz I I'm just I'm just gonna read it the way I see it crikey IPA an American Indian pale ale
crikey
IPA there you go. It's got an 89 beer score 90 from the community. It's an American IPA with a 6.8 alcohol by volume
from Ruben's brews
in
Do-do-do-do-do-do-do. Can you guess where West? Do you know where it's brewed? Yes, I do. Go ahead Seattle, Washington. That's right
It's a local brew ladies and gentlemen, so that's what we're drinking on today's episode that are was sexy. Yeah
Yeah, you're right. That is it reminds me of rain here a little bit. That's what they're going for there
So we have much to talk about today
And there's a topic that we haven't floated before or we actually talk about this on the show
This never come up on the show or is it only something we've talked about behind the scenes. I'm not sure
I don't know because it's a big deal. It's very scary
developers I've warned us over and over again about uncorrectable issues and
Freedom problems. Yes
Freedom no, no, I'm talking freedom problems negative in the freedom
Dimension x86 is just getting a bad rap these days and another developer a long developer involved in core boot
Libre boot is trying to call attention to the uncorrectable freedom and security issues on the x86 platform in a newly
freshened
post and a newly freshener
attempt to get everybody to realize that post 2009 Intel systems and post 2013 AMD systems have massive flaws this is
Mainly he argues in the fact that you have these management platforms the Intel management engine and the AMD security processor
which require these binary only blobs that have major vulnerabilities in them and
He also has issues with you if you EFI secure boot and he wants the community
He is calling upon the community to make a move to arm power MIPS or even risk v processors
He does then provide a summary that is not very exciting about making them. Yeah
But it is a good summary of the estate of the available now, this is a topic
I think that is particularly tickled your interest for a little while. What is it about the whole concept?
Because you've you've been tracking the story since a couple of other reports recently that have said, you know
We have to abandon x86 immediately
We must move to another platform if security is and it is at all important to you
What is it about this x86 story that keeps grabbing your attention? I just think it's not brought up that much
I mean it comes up occasionally
That's why it piques my interest when it does and you just don't hear very much about it
Some of these features are really useful a lot of you know, especially enterprise management
But in particular like I haven't heard very much about the AMD, you know
The piper true true that's not very much and obviously we're not gonna all drop x86
but as we see arm coming up, which again has some problems in some implementations, but I
Don't know
So daredevil in in the mumble room. I know you have some thoughts on this one share it with us, sir
So I'd start with first of all, it's interesting that now there is a competitor
There is trying to get into that realm that there is more research about the actual security of this
Who should be financing this sick of this research?
I mean not saying that the research is biased
I'm saying that there is financing towards researching the issue
Nothing says that there isn't the similar issues on the other platforms or their architectures
So we need you know, it took us years until we realize those things
and having that said
The secure boot scenario is all about you start by opting for devices that actually allow you to control the keys
You have in the device moving towards, you know the ability to then replace the thing when we have a free software implementation of it
Since there's interest in the public
Developments are up
Someone something about the idea seems
Fantastical to me like that. We would all make a huge migration like like a migration West like we all get in our
our low-powered
under-resourced arm
Machines and we just all double down on arm or something like that
I'm not saying it'd be armed
But the idea of one day all of us just sort of mass migrating away from x86 is right now seems ludicrous
But it could start to happen
I think it will start to happen at least for once and maybe it is already there arm beats out the chips from
2009 and 2013 if you are concerned about security, right?
There's people who buy the older laptop so you can still get core boot on them. Oh boy
That's not a good solution at all at some point that will cross with where arm is going in terms of capabilities, huh?
Huh? So that's that's a start, but obviously that won't be the mass market
But to be fair your primary computing device almost certainly is an arm device right now my phone
Yeah, I don't know if I classify it yet as my primary, but it's definitely
Damn close you
I think you as in the average person who is considering this a ludicrous proposal might
Actually then pull out. You know, they're they're probably even reading the article or arm device
You know, you're probably right. I have been I have been shocked at how many people I now know that their primary computing device is
Is is a is a phone I was I already showed that I already shared the story on Kota radio
So I'll just make it super brief, but the community I live in a lot of people there
Are just using their phones as their primary computer and we have like community events
You know, we're all like we had we had a Thanksgiving event. We had an Easter event and a Christmas of any is adorable and
It when we get together
It is interesting how
Technically they are a very aware that they could like it's not like they don't have a computer because they are scared of them
They have them at work
But in their estimation they can do everything they need on their phone
Including like they were doing the healthcare gov stuff like they're getting health care exchange coverage on their phone
And and then when they need a computer they just do it at work
And so I think you're right poppy
I think for a lot of people and that's kind of where I was going where I could see this is
What if a vendor like Dell or or Apple came out with a really successful arm based laptop?
I'd also peel off a whole bunch of people. I don't know about for me though
Let's stay focused on the issue though. The issue is non free firm or non free code
You're right running at a higher privilege level and almost every arm device has that a proprietary blob that runs in the trust zone
Yeah, you have to run their trust zone. Yeah, there's no way for you to know it's actually inside that yeah
It's really no better than Intel's management engine. Yeah, that's your primary issue. You're right
Go ahead with me and that trust zone has been riddled with security
issues for a long long time
Well
You know what actually you know what I've heard people talking about
Oh
Not not risk
But what is it? What was the what is the CPU design that was originally from such spark, right?
Is this spark open source aren't spark chips like isn't like the entire spark design or completely open source?
But ship is open source
I think Fujitsu still produces some but all the new ones made by Oracle are completely locked up
They don't release any of the specs for those. I think the old ones all the very lock is out there, isn't it?
Okay, okay North Ranger. There is oh good. There is at least IBM's power
So if you look at like the tell us your workstation
Yeah, at least all of the code that's running on that is open. Even if the chip design is not sure, right sure
North Ranger, did you get a chance to jump in with what you wanted to mention?
Yeah, I think you know, it's it's already been alluded to a little bit, but you know, even if you swap out the platform
You know with the CPU that can be booted in an open manner
We're still going to be stuck with peripheral peripherals that have
Binary blobs, even if they're not binary blobs that have to loaded by the OS, you know
Your hard drive has basically an OS running on it to manage all the flash
but none of that though as is as critical as your CPU like if the CPU is the core source of either
If we're just care if we're just if we're just concerned about blobs or really security issues
Then that's a fundamental problem. If a peripheral is that's not as egregious
It's still egregious well in the case of a hard drive. It could be pretty egregious
Yeah, I could control what data you're accessing and so it could put in whatever data it wants
Okay, well seen examples of that. Oh
Wimpy's got something for the show notes. I will add to yes open spark. Right? Exactly. Very good. Hmm
Well, there you have it is doesn't sound like we even though we've had we've and it's interesting
you've been following the story for a little while West it's interesting you've been following this push and yet we don't really have a
super clear alternative that doesn't also have its set of downsides and to bring myself down and not to mention not to mention that we've
now got decades of
R&D and x86 and software built around and all of that speaking of decades speaking of decades
That whole scope versus Linux. I don't believe what you've read. It's actually still around again
Yeah, the scope versus IBM is alive 13 years later and continuing now
If you know what you might not even have been alive if you're listening to this show when this lawsuit started
So I had its core the sco group which was then named caldera systems filed a lawsuit against IBM in March of 20
I'm sorry 2003
for allegedly contributing to
contributing sections of the commercial Unix code from the Unix system in it to
Scos from sco to the Linux kernel code base sco group claimed that they alleged presence of its proprietary code in the open source
Code named Linux devalued its proprietary codes value
And so therefore they were suing IBM for that along the way sco filed for bankruptcy and the group claimed that anyone who used Linux
owed them money all the while novell successfully claimed ownership of the allegedly infringing code and then said okay everybody's gonna be
Indemnified from it if you run on Linux
But all of that has not stopped the sco group from continuing its battle with IBM the group on Wednesday
Which is last Wednesday did not actually
Reveal the nature of their appeal only as a solely as a solely as a notice to the appeals court that they would be lodging an
appeal soon
So they're not it's not sco versus IBM
Which is one of the oldest stories I've been following is still not done. It's still not done
It's unbelievable one of the first stories tracked for a Linux action show
really incredible
All right, I don't want to go into all the April Fool's this week last this past week
There was a lot of April Fool's shenanigans, but one I thought was particularly good because you know
Like what ThinkGeek does is ThinkGeek has these products sometimes as April Fool's and then people want it so much that ThinkGeek actually ends up
Making it. I
Think that's what can happen to the KDE project the KDE project
I think ended up with an April Fool's that they're gonna have to make
They the on April 1st. They posted plasma 5.7 will let you log in through an online account
KDE is going to provide an own cloud installation to let plasma and KDE PIM users sync their data
You can already use own cloud with Car Dev and Cal Dev
To get at your calendars and things like that synced
And now and now you will be able to use own cloud to sync plasma
Configurations and manage them work will be when your work is completed
You'll be able to load a plasma session by specifying units username and password and own cloud provider
that's right, and then you can log into your KD desktop and have your settings synced via own cloud in plasma 5.7 a
Massive feature West a massive feature now. I kind of want it. I know right so did everybody else so ha ha April Fool's
That was a super funny April Fool's everybody super funny April Fool's
What was the Ubuntu one I don't remember that
It wasn't Ubuntu one the thing of the cloud that you could also put your backups in there
a
Service that was discontinued at some point. Yes, your box like yes
Yeah, now, but I got enough people's attention
They say they're actually it happened that they were already be going to be meeting at the at their
Vdg you know the developers group meeting that they have and so like people are really excited about this April Fool's
And so they looked at it like God you know there might actually be ways
We could actually accomplish some of this now not the login stuff
But integrating more syncing stuff a better place to store stuff in own cloud
It looks like they were actually looked at some of the ideas from the April Fool's and went
Maybe we're trying to be negative. It just seems like a huge expense for very little benefit
Well, not the login part not the login part, but some of the other files thinking stuff
Yeah, yeah, yeah, Wendy you were you were mentioning Google's April Fool's that didn't go over so well I
Heard some people got really upset about that
Did you go where'd you go Wimpy? Where'd you go? Oh, hi. Hi
I I think the people at Google need to remember they've been employed to be
Kick-ass engineers and various other roles and none of them are employed employed to be full-time comedians
Yeah, and they should just knock this on the head. It's very tiresome and
You know, they're April Fool's this year a couple of them went bad and none of them were very good
What happened to the halcyon days of the Google April Fool's like, you know, Google Glass and Nexus Q. I mean, those were cracking
I agree
and you know
Those are hilarious. I
Saw some people that were tweeting like they were writing like condolences emails to people who had
To family members who had had somebody passed away and it inserted that mic drop thing
And anyways people were upset so it might be some fun stuff coming out of plasma soon
And also Katie has come up with a vision for the future that well
I'll read it to you the Katie statement for their vision is a world in which everyone has control over their digital life and enjoys
freedom and privacy
They go more expanded it goes on but in greater detail their vision has no geographical barriers
Katie should be able to be available to everyone
Katie wants to put their users in the driver's seat and Katie wants people to control all aspects of their digital lives
Okay
Hard to object to that is the Katie E vision and you can find out more at dot Katie e.org
And this is kind of an interesting thing. I wonder I wonder so the group that put this together
I wonder how much connection this actually has to people that are actually writing code
That's always something I kind of wonder when I when I watch the Katie project from afar
I I get kind of confused about what is
actually directly connected to the project and what is just sort of like people who are associated with the project that do in the project's name and
I've been running the plasma 5 6 desktop since about
Five days since before plasma 5 6 or maybe seven days before plasma 5 6 was released to final and now I've been right
I've been running it since then so I guess I'm coming on like I must be on almost a month now and
Just recently. I'm starting to have issues on this Intel skylake machine
But I I have I have really I have really profoundly changed my position on the plasma desktop and it no longer
With each release of the plasma desktop
I have felt like there's just a couple of things that were really fundamentally broken didn't work for me for a while
It was sound was really bad
Didn't be able to go in there and understanding like when they at one point
I think it was like in five four or five five when they updated the sound or the multimedia
system
Control panel where you could go and disable hardware devices. It was a process of elimination. I could make the right sound card work
That was a huge game-changer for me and when the stability got so that way I didn't just when they when the session was idle
I would sometimes just have the plasma shell crash when those things stopped happening
You know, that was another game-changer for me. And so five six has been really a great great release
But at the same time as much as I see improvement
I see a lot a lot of room for continued improvement still and I think that's a big thing
room for continued improvement still and
last week we covered a mailing post that mr. Brown who is in our
Mumble room right now who hails us from the Sousa project wrote up
And I he sent it in to the KDE mailing list
And and if you guys recall he talked about how there's multiple text editors and multiple start menus
And there's there's so much going on in there that it might meet a little refinement and I don't want to actually make it too
clumsy, so mr. Brown if you wanted to
Maybe just really recap really briefly for our audience who didn't catch the episode last week kind of what your message was in this mailing
list post
Because I thought it nailed my thoughts
I thought you were actually really able to verbalize some of the things that I've been thinking
In a really clear cognizant way that wasn't hostile that came from a place of I love what you're doing
I love everything we've accomplished, but we still have room to go
And so would you mind summarizing your post really quick for the audience? Yeah, I don't mind at all
I mean, yeah, it comes from a lot of the discussions. We're having with the KDE project at the moment about
well their relationships with distributions, you know some pain points with our
packages and stuff like that and the the conversation kind of ended up talking a little bit broader about sort of
just distribution positioning and stuff generally and
Yeah, the the key message that I wanted to kind of get across is yeah, there's parts of the KDE stack which are
Absolutely phenomenal and of good quality and great. But if you look at kind of KD is a whole
It's hard to get a handle on
What the project is trying to do. It's it's
And and if you ask like three different KDE developers you generally get three different answers on pretty much everything
I mean
You made a point that that clearly translates to what the what that happens is the KD project and the plasma desktop is not
Messaging to the distros what's awesome about the plasma desktop so then they can't turn around and and and relay that to their users
they don't they don't there's like a disconnect there and
So that's sort of the big problem when you said the big with the end result is is KDE actually has to is KD doesn't
Just market to end-user. It also has to market to distro makers themselves, too
Yeah, and there's like little snippets and like little glimmers of what I think is a wonderful
I don't use the word vision because they're using it now at mission goal, whatever
of
like
from what some of their plasma maintainers of like just thinking of plasma as a
Workspace and thinking of the applications of something different and if you think of it as something different, which is
clearly a mindset that some of the KDE project have a
Lot of these problems and pain points go away because all of these duplicate applications are certainly available to not be included
You know if you stop thinking of KDE is a huge stack
But as a pick-and-mix selection of technologies, you might want to put in your distribution
Things get really exciting again. Sure. The whole project isn't angled in that direction yet. The messaging is not there
Well, you know what you think of link as an end-user when you think of the plasma desktop, don't you aren't you?
Isn't one of the things you think about is how well all the applications integrate and how they all play off each other and how it's a
Whole suite. I mean when I think of the KDE desktop, I think of plasma 5-6. I think of
All of the text editors. I even maybe consider k-office included in that
I mean, I think of the entire suite when I think of the plasma desktop
You think that way but the KDE project is no longer working in that way
So it's is that a smart thing to have those expectations so far divorced from each other
If you haven't got maintainers on the KDE side maintaining all of that stuff to the same level as the plasma guys and the K
Wing guys
Aren't you setting yourself up for?
Disappointment and failure or something, right? Yeah. Yeah. Hmm. That's actually a great point
So but how does a project like KDE which?
Has been labeled in the past as a bit chaotic
How does a project like that come together and say we're gonna we're gonna unite around a single editor
We're gonna unite around a single this or that or is that the job of a distribution and and if that's a job of distribution
Why has it never happened?
Yeah, that's it. That's a tough answer. I mean the I think there was room in KDE for
Some kind of leadership in that area of like just people stepping up and saying okay, we're gonna make some of these tough choices
It won't make those people friends just like some of the changes no mate
It didn't make necessarily make certain people friends, but in the long run it's proven to be a pretty good thing. I
Think that might be part of it
The other part of the distributions is the other stuff that we were talking about before we got on to this conversation of like these
I was gonna say a hundred paper cuts
But at the moment it feels a bit more like a thousand of like just living with the KDE stack packaging the KDE stack handling
You know new new yeah new dependencies new changes and and we're having a bit of a hard time getting that communication from
Them as the developers of like what are they expecting from us? What where what dependencies do they need?
What versions of X Y & Z we just get these big old?
Tables and it's expected to get it out there and they you know uses hands as fast as possible and
That can be really tough sometimes
Yeah, absolutely now you also
Really effectively broke down the rather dominant position that GTK based desktops are in versus Qt based desktops
And I find that to be
Not not shocking and not a huge surprise
but if you walk into a room of Linux nerds and
You ask people to raise their hands on
What they prefer Qt or GTK a lot of people are gonna raise their hands for Qt
In terms of application development a lot of people say like Qt is superior or cute yet
Right exactly yeah, yeah, and I'm kind of in the same
I'm using plasma right now, but I I'm kind of in the same boat so what what's going on here?
Why has Gnome or GTK desktops essentially dominated the the top positions on distro watch and the and the larger distros?
When plasma desktops been around for a long time the Qt technology is pretty advanced
You have folks like canonical who are investing a ton of resources into it. What are your thoughts there? I?
think it's a case of
just like hitting that sweet spot of the
implementation like if you think of the
many of like the core audiences of Linux these days we're talking about you know tablets and stuff earlier and mobile devices if you if
You think about you know who is using a Linux desktop these days
You typically have like you know developers techies sysadminis guys who?
generally fall into one or two camps either sort of the
Lightweight guys who just want the most simple window manager or whatever that can you know just does the thing that is meant to do
And you know probably some old-school stuff that no one's seen for 10 years or seen an upgrade for for 10 years
And then you have another lot who just want
Something that keeps out of their way, and I think most of the GTK ones generally do that in a very elegant way
The KDE appeals to you know these control freaks who want all these options and all these buttons and everything
But does that necessarily overlap with like the most of the core than its users these days. I'm I'm not so sure
and
I actually want to give a chance for daredevil and jump here because daredevil and you say to maybe it's it's the money
There's more money behind GTK. What do you mean there?
I mean that there is just as much money being poured like cute has the support of the corporation DJ right and
GTK has just supported red hat that's not a small feat. That's not a small amount of engineering in there and when you look at
That money being poured into hey
This if you're going to make an application
That is going to work in in your company, and you're already using those red hats or this fedora
You know it's just that they document in a way, and there's also the cycles
Just remember that there's also still the very first reason why GTK was created is you know there was the doubts about the licensing now?
There's no longer many doubts about licensing
But there is an attempt to you know show a different path to a different license on you
It's not necessarily the GTK camp. Yeah, that's good. That's a good point
Richard also, it's not just red hat that you know have money behind and you know GTK
You know Susan the next enterprise also standardized on them with the last release
Well, that is a perfect segue to my next question question Richard
so this is semi awkward here now all of a sudden because
Everybody kind of thinks of open Sousa as primarily as focusing on the KDE plasma desktop
But your enterprise distribution is focused on the known desktop
You kind of talked about this a little bit is is this requiring Sousa open Sousa to pivot more towards user demand or?
Do you play the role as a desktop advocate here and try to get more people to try the plasma desktop?
What what decision does open Sousa make in light of the reality of GTK's?
market predominance and
apparent user preference in some cases
Well first
I guess it's clear to say like Sousa's business decision regarding the enterprise distribution is like totally separate from open Sousa like in the sense
Of like Sousa made this decision about NOMA as a default quite a while ago. They did it for 11 as well
And at the same time the open Sousa community had a discussion made their decision
went and stuck with KDE and
And you know where open Sousa is always free to go its own road
Do you know make its own decisions and we have an absolutely awesome KDE team?
I mean to be blunt the best KDE team out there
Doing a wonderful job of packaging all of this stuff despite the stuff that I've been complaining about
Yeah, and you know, it's if you want a KDE expense
It's the best one that where that comes to like what does open Sousa do in the future?
we I at times coming that we'll probably end up having a discussion about this soon and I
Think there's some really interesting options to put on the table like in the case of tumbleweed
because one of the things with the community with open Sousa is we're not the
Perception that we are KDE first has always been wrong. We've always treated every desktop equally
So do we put KDE on there?
Do we put no desktop as a default in some example in the case of time?
We might be able to get away with that. It might make sense since it reflects the community as we are
but for the leap
Probably not. Hmm. What makes the difference there?
Just the target audience of leap of you know being an easier
Not rolling less techie user friendly distribution
I see
I mean
We could maybe put no default there that that's another thing that I kind of stumbled on when I was writing all this stuff to
Kde like there's a lot of distros out there that don't have a default
Um, you know, we thought we were crazy thinking about it. Maybe it's an idea to go for that
Yeah, I guess so. I I think you know the idea of the default desktop
I mean doesn't it feel like that idea comes from we are gonna put all of our focus on this
We're gonna do our theming our customization all of our effort goes into this
Which is really kind of a commercial company way of thinking because it's really a we only have 10 developers to do this
So we must put all of our energy into this desktop in the reality though in open source
You may have multiple contributors that want to work on multiple desktops. And so you can ship multiple desktops
Is that true or is there an advantage of just focusing on one desktop?
Which I think is where that kind of mentality comes from
I think if you ask other projects you'll say focus is the way to go in the case of openSUSE
We've been doing this now for 10 years of the the traditional
Every developer, you know as long as we have contributors
We will do it and we'll find a way to do it. And if we have two sets of contributors pulling in two different directions
We find a way of doing it together and that's like one of the things that we're exceptionally good at doing these days
so for us
That's fine. But then you do have to think about the user experience of like, okay some guy puts in your DVD boots it up
Do you really want to shove a desktop selection window right in front of them when they have no idea what all those options mean?
so this sort of moving on from this I guess I
Kind of wanted to ask you just as a follow-up to last week's I think it was 138. We talked about this
What do you think would be the major breakthrough to make to make the floodgates open for people to move say from
The Ubuntu desktop or the Fedora desktop or whatever and say, you know what this time this time I install this machine
I'm doing openSUSE and I last week. I think I made it into the show
I'm not sure if I made in the final version
I proposed that the thing that might finally break those floodgates open is universal application installs across Linux because if all of a sudden
software availability was sort of
the same across all of the major distributions
then you could start picking your distro on other things like technical merits and
You might see a lot more people picking openSUSE
it seems like right now one of the barriers is software availability despite all of the
Nice tricks in and means you got a long way
But despite that it seems like that might still be the thing that holds up a lot of people
But I don't know Richard what your thoughts are
As far as if there could be a big shift that would all of a sudden make it much easier
Less friction for people to start jumping to SUSE
Yeah, I think I think that's part of it. I mean we've been thinking about the software availability thing from sort of the other direction of
Tidying up some of the rough edges around like software.openSUSE.org and the OBS and then bits and pieces like that
The the universal application stuff is is interesting. I'm
Parenthetically worried about the baggage it might bring you know libraries that need patching and maintaining and all the other stuff
we
We've got some expertise in that area because we've been playing around with like Docker
We have zippers the only package manager that can patch inside a Docker container, for example. Wow
Kind of fun. So, you know, maybe we end up, you know patching inside application containers too and having fun with that but
So yeah, I think it's it's part of the story
But I think in the case of openSUSE of the the main part has actually been sort of actually having it like a consistent story
The same thing that I'm being criticized in KDE about
You know
I know that's been a weakness for openSUSE in the past and I think we're finding our feet without getting that message out
It's just a case of taking time listening to feedback
iterating tuning
One last question and then I'm gonna I'll toss it air devil
and I think we're I'm and then anything you want to bring up but my the
last week the thing that really got my head spinning was Microsoft's announcement of bash on Windows and
To mr. Popey's delight. They specifically said you can run Ubuntu apps on Windows
In fact, I think when you run the user land now
In the command prompt when you type bash up in the little window. It says Ubuntu as if the application
You're running is Ubuntu and Ubuntu is now an application in your in your task taskbar Ubuntu with a little Ubuntu logo and
On Windows and I'm wondering when you heard this announcement. Did you think to yourself?
Shit, I wish they would have just said the Linux command line. Why did it have to be Ubuntu?
Actually, I heard the announcement logged on to this mumbo-jumbo and asked Popey a few questions about the technical stuff because I reckon we can
Possibly dump open Suza on top of that instead. Yeah, I would love to hear because they call the subsystem the Linux subsystem
They don't call it the Ubuntu subsystem. The user land is Ubuntu, but
Popey now last week in the show
We were covering the rumors that there might be bash on Windows. Did you know at that time what was coming? I
Didn't I knew like about an hour before?
They went on stage and said it and that was it
Uh-huh. See we got a we got to get a we got to get a line to Dustin and we got to get somebody
Giving him beer to give us the inside scoop. I dare Devon before we move on from mr. Brown
I know I wanted to get your your question
So no, I was just saying the universal apps one
Don't you guys think that it will change what what they mean or what it means when you now have to consider Windows platform?
I mean, isn't that the appeal?
You mean you mean that particular neck that compatibility layer now?
Wow make an application for Ubuntu and now it just works on Solaris BSD
Linux your regular distro and it will work on Windows
Yes, when this comes yes from CLI apps they come from the graphical apps yet
No, but you know, someone's gonna get X working on that thing, you know, somebody's gonna get it
Well x-ming is already a thing. Oh
Well, I know I hope so
I wonder if somebody will takes like somehow if somebody will come will merge Sigwin with this somehow and make like just some sort
Of Frankenstein said an unholy Linux box, right? You know exactly what I'm thinking about
Richard was there anything else you wanted to touch on before we move along?
All right, sir, well, thank you for joining us and I thought that was a great post well-written and it was it was really
well stated too and I hope the KD project takes up some of your suggestions and we
We will just have to wait and see I will mention DigitalOcean sponsor right here of the Linux unplugged program
Hey, yo, Wes. Do you have any DigitalOcean droplets? Oh, you know I do
Yeah, I do. You know, I have own cloud running up on DigitalOcean right now
I got the I got the version 9 running, you know the version 9
They got a one-click deployment now of own cloud night one click. That's fast. Boom. Boom
I tell you what DigitalOcean is great
It's a great way for you to get your own Linux rig up in the cloud
They call it the cloud but really what they magical place
Well, it could be magical but really what they you know what it is. It's DigitalOcean's magical servers
They have they have data centers all over the world totally specked out
They have them in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, London, Germany. They have a new one in India
40 gigabit e connections to the hypervisors what all SSDs
super fast CPUs Linux on the entire
infrastructure KVM for the virtualizer and then all sitting on top of it is this incredible web app and
It is so well designed
but yet extremely powerful and then to top it all off like sprinkles on top of a cupcake for Wes's birthday an
API that is straightforward and easy to it is so easy with lots of great open source code already written taken advantage of dat
API I love their interface and I love this if you use our promo code do unplugged
You get a $10 credit $10 credit over at DigitalOcean to save yourself when you're trying it out
I have DigitalOcean also running an EMR application
Well, I think it's called open EMR actually they'd like the name is not all that creative
but my lady runs a medical practice and
Noah set up one for her a while back and she tried it out for a little while
He did the same thing he spun up a DigitalOcean droplet
But the first thing you do she wasn't really ready to try it then he was being a little pushy
You know how Noah can be you know how I mean, I'm just saying I know it's a good guy
But he can be intense. So she's
Yeah, I hope so. I hope so. I said I'm not quite ready
She thought you know, but now now she's ready to jump in. It just takes seconds
I'm a busy guy with and the fact that I can manage my DigitalOcean droplets. It melts my freaking face
It is so great and when you use a promo code do unplugged you can try it out
Their pricing is very straightforward. You can just do hourly pricing. You can go get a big rig
Here's a fun one. I would I would totally suggest you use DigitalOcean to set up a mumble server
If you have not played with mumble for yourself, it is a great open source
Voice chat program. It's what your friends just chat or your own virtual log
it's what we do for our virtual log our virtual log uses mumble running on a DigitalOcean droplet and
It works great people connect from all over the world to that DigitalOcean droplet and it runs all the time
DigitalOcean.com use their HTML 5 console to manage your box or their API or their fantastic interface
They got Debian, Ubuntu, Fedora, CentOS, CorOS, and even that free BSD
They already have tutorials popping up on their site too for 1604. They're on top of it. DigitalOcean.com
Just use that promo code
Do unplugged one word a lowercase and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the unplugged program
and many many of our friends out there in the open source world are also taking advantage of
DigitalOcean either as like DigitalOcean sponsoring them by providing the server hosting
Or they're just already choosing to run off them. In fact, I recall I think I think wimpy uses DigitalOcean for some Ubuntu Mate
stuff and
Speaking of Ubuntu Mate it is a new month
And so we look back at the month of March and we see that the Ubuntu Mate project has had yet
once again another good month and
wimpy has outlined how he'll be spending the monies or how the monies were spent I guess better put and
I wanted to just let him jump in. Is there anything from the update you wanted to share with the audience wimpy?
Well, those people that are following the blog they can see all of that stuff in there see where the money's going
we've put some aside because
we've got the
1604 a couple of weeks away and we'll be releasing the Raspberry Pi images for that
We anticipate a spike in downloads and that gets expensive. So we're
We put some money aside to cater for those downloads
You know, I think I I've been thinking about what it is about these updates that
I like, I mean, I like knowing but it's not just that what I like is
I assume it's true
But whether it's true or not you give the impression of a financially stable and financially sustainable distribution
Exactly and as somebody who's been watching distributions come and go for a long time
I makes me feel good about that distribution that you have a sustainable path here
But I wanted to kind of I actually wanted to push you a little bit on that
I wanted to kind of I actually wanted to push you a little bit on two of the line items you have here because I
Don't know what these mean and they sound really interesting. So Luke got got some cash for working on a buntu Matei
Welcome that's very generic wimpy because a buntu Matei welcome has been a project you've been working on for a long time
What did you want to share any specifics because I was curious. I would like to know what did he do?
Well, he's effectively the principal developer for a buntu Matei. Welcome and the software boutique now
So it's it's really
Luke falls into the category of people that really doesn't isn't interested in the money doesn't want the money
And this is just a way of me saying thank you for the hours and hours of effort that he's put into
The project, you know and also, you know, he's the forum
Administrator in the community. So he's he's taken on a lot of responsibility and it's just nice to say
Thank you for all the time and effort. Well, I would bested into the project
I would say Luke you have helped create one of the best software centers or
Deployment tools for Linux that I have ever used. Absolutely. I think it's fair to say that he hasn't helped. This is Luke's imagining
so I
Started the ball rolling in 1510
and Luke's involvement is kind of interesting because
Very very early on when welcome was really really fresh and new early in the 1510 cycle
He posted a mock-up in the forum of the rolling in logo
Animation that you see in the 1510 right buntu Matei welcome and I said, oh that would be so great
If you implement that and the next day there was a pull request and he'd implemented it all and the rest of it
and that kind of sparked his involvement and then I didn't hear much from him and then as the
1604 cycle started I got this colossal pull request
And he clearly spent weeks, you know working on it and it was just this
BAM
This is what I've been doing for the last I don't know how long and it was just like, okay
And all of a sudden like wow, we've got something for 1604 here. That's great. Yeah
Yeah, and so and and he was very clear, you know, he he he got what welcome was all about. He
Totally understood why it was important and he really wanted to go for it
So I kind of stepped back a little bit from active development
I've had a hand in it, but he has really driven
buntu Matei welcome and the software boutique in 1604 with the help of
Robin Thompson as well who I approached to help us with the translation work that we've been working on the last six weeks or so
So also I noticed that it looks like there's been some continued effort to porting Matei desktop to GTK 3
Yep. Yep. So the upstream guys Wolfgang and Vlad
And another guy called Luke who I don't have any active contacts with
but Luke from DC, I think you go by on github. You really need to get in touch with me
I need to reach out and say thank you to you for all of your hard work as well
But yeah, the the three of them have been working tirelessly for months and months
To really refine the GTK 3 implementation
And I think the target at the moment more or less is that
Matei desktop 1.14 will be released in about a week's time
And it should be the first one that has a stable GTK 3 implementation for those people that want to build against GTK 3
That is exciting impressive GTK 3.20 is the
Version that they're targeted so they've worked really really hard on that
So you want to chat a little bit about
Some Raspberry Pi stuff. I know that you've been working on several different things in that regard
I don't know how much you want to talk about what you want to share, but
There's several things that are would be pretty interesting to the audience
Yeah, yeah, that's my sort of favorite favorite pet project. I like tinkering with the Raspberry Pi. I have lots of
Friends with Raspberry Pi. We like you tinkering with the Raspberry Pi
Yeah, it's lots of fun. So
Yeah, I alluded to the fact there'll be a Raspberry Pi release for
1604 for Ubuntu Matei
And I will also build the same versions that we've had before
So I've made versions of the
Ubuntu, you know traditional Ubuntu server
And also Lubuntu and Xubuntu images
for those people that want to play with those and I think a couple of months ago
We were talking about this stuff and I alluded to the fact that you know
There was some experimental work going on from the Raspberry Pi foundation with accelerated drivers for the video core
for
Chip and that you know, if that went well, then we could potentially start seeing some of the composited desktops running on the Raspberry Pi 3
So I've spent a couple of evenings playing with that and having some fun with that. Yeah, and how has that gone would be?
Well, I've got to the point where
so at the moment I I can boot and
run in air quotes
Ubuntu Unity, Kubuntu and
Ubuntu
Gnome
1604 on the Raspberry Pi 3. Wow, that's awesome
Oh boy, the Raspberry Pi 3 is getting awfully appealing all of a sudden
Now it's it's progress because in 1510 that just wasn't possible
And the video core 4 drivers are still very experimental
so
None of those desktops are what you would call usable. Okay, they're kind of interesting
You know little moose bush and and I'm sure it'll improve so over the course of the year
Have you seen my plasma desktop? It literally is glitching out all over the place right now
So actually the the k the kubuntu thing
Uh, I don't I don't really i'm not really familiar with it the issue there and this isn't a kde
Issue it's you know, it's the uh video core 4 drivers, you know that there are some rough edges there
Right. So some of the rendering's not right. So right some of the icons and some of the fonts are a bit
You can't make them out
But when I can get it to do stuff the animations are
Just silky smooth just perfect. Nice. You you can't complain. Um
On ubuntu unity that generally works. Um, I although when I tried to take a screenshot of the desktop
That locks something up. So that's why I had to take a photograph of
Of that one running rather than a screenshot
Um, but you know that broadly works, um kubuntu works, but I don't know if it's going to work
But you know that broadly works, um kubuntu works, but I can't make it out where ubuntu
Uh has better, you know, it doesn't have the rendering glitches
Um, it has some other issues and then ubuntu gnome looks perfect
It absolutely looks perfect. There is no rendering issues whatsoever
But as soon as you launch any application the whole thing dies on its ass and it only works
It only works in classic mode. Oh, okay. So, you know these these drivers are
Evolving so they'll get there in in in due course, but it kind of whet my appetite. So i've i've now started
Experimenting with some of the other acceleration
Uh facilities that are available on the raspberry pi
Two and well, in fact all the raspberry pies
But obviously i'm targeting the the two and the three because of the ubuntu base supporting that architecture
And uh, so i'm now working on uh video playback acceleration and that's a much happier story
Now this could be huge because uh, a lot of people that i've heard in the audience that have tried the pie
For a media center said it is great. It is great when you're watching sd content or 720p content, but
You get up to around 1080p and it starts to be a different story
And it has made the pie sort of unattractive to me as a cody box
Uh, and you know to be honest with you
Even as a production box because if I can't get 1080p playback
Then I can't capture at 1080 and that's no good because that's what we capture at here locally
Um, and so it's sort of eliminated as a possibility as even something I could have as an extra studio computer
Yeah, and and the other issue is is that if you have a dedicated um media center
Uh application such as um cody running on something like open elec it works very well
um
And I agree on the older models of the raspberry pi
You could comfortably do 720p and depending on the bit rate it would do 1080p. Yeah, i've never tried on the three though
Yeah, yeah. So this is this is what i've been playing with just recently
and uh
It's looking really good. So
There's a guy in the ubuntu mate community called
arrowan
Who posted a load of tips and tricks on how to compile various things with acceleration?
For the raspberry pi 3 so i'm going through his stuff and sort of
Piecing it together and filling in the blanks and what i've got going at the moment is I have um
A vlc fully accelerated. Yes for the raspberry pi 2 and the raspberry pi 3. Yes
And that's properly great. So that's using the open max api
Which is the same api that things like cody on the raspberry pi use and the omx player use
so although you've got the user interface for vlc you launch the
Um, you know pick your media player and set it playing and it immediately goes full screen
And you just use the keyboard bindings to then control the playback, but it is absolutely super slick and it is
It's super smooth and it works perfectly man
That's going to have big that could have a big impact for people that are using the raspberry pi in a battery situation
Which uh, I I could I could see a lot of people doing
Yeah, I mean i've got one of these um
Atrix laptops and right running on that. Yes, it's like a portable media player now. It looks fantastic
It's got an hdmi screen hdmi audio
Can run it off a battery. It's got a built-in battery that can power the pie. It runs for about 10 hours
It's just fantastic
Producer q5 sis has one of those atrix docs and I borrowed it for like ever from him
I think I think I gave it back to him now
Uh, and it is ideal. It is ideal for the raspberry pi if you could have just a way to to attach it
Um, and I could you know for me
I something I could I could easily connect to like different tvs in the home or in the office
That would then have fully
Accelerated playback that is a that is a big deal now. Is it just in vlc wimpy or is it other applications as well?
Yes, i've started to branch out into other stuff
So the thing about vlc is that in the past we've only been able to offer omx player, which is a command line utility
So there's a barrier to entry there. So now having vlc you can you know, right click on things launch in vlc
And it will just start playing or you can do it through the vlc ui
but um
Uh this evening i've got um a build of ffmpeg
Which is fully accelerated for the there we go. Yeah. Yeah. No
No, this is neat and that uses a different
Uh api this uses the uh ml which is the multimedia abstraction layer for the video core
chip
and
So you can use ffplay for example to for a command line to launch your content and that's windowed
So you can do it in full screen or you can have it in windowed and that all is fully accelerated
And I will confirm i've even seen a screenshot that actually confirms it is actually real which is yeah. Yes. Yeah
Yeah, yeah screen screenshot. Sorry. It didn't happen. Yeah, right
So the next step is uh, I should be able to compile
Mpv and link against that version of ffmpeg
To give a fully accelerated mpv now, would you ship that in 1604?
I don't know if i'll install these things by default ffmpeg will be included by default. Definitely vlc will
Uh mpv will be so, uh, the way that the build works is that there's a ppa stacked on top
So, uh, if you installed mpv
On one of those ubuntu flavors built with the ubuntu pi flavor maker you would get the accelerated version of mpv
and
I'm I i'm fairly confident I can get mpv working
And then the final step is to then build an accelerated version of kodi
Um, oh nice. Yes, which of course loads of distributions have as you know, a a dedicated
You know kodi box
Uh, my idea is just to build kodi in the desktop, you know version so you can run it window
Well, maybe window maybe full screen i'm not quite sure which which api to use yet
But the idea is is to have kodi as an install option that's fully accelerated
That would be splendid this because everyone wants that you are
That's a tool tool. So i'll see you like that
If you get this if you pull this off and I know you know, everything is subject to change
But if you pull this off, uh
You what you are going to do is you are going to apply
Bacon grease to the already incredible momentum that ubuntu mate has for the raspberry platform raspberry pi platform
Uh if this if these having if if I knew
If if I knew that there was a distro out there that I just downloaded
And ffmpeg was already patched to be hardware accelerated on the raspberry pi
That would always be the distribution. I download that would that you seal the deal right there
You already it becomes it becomes the premiere the ubuntu the mate desktop, which is obvious on a raspberry pi 3. That's obvious
combined with hardware accelerated ffmpeg or maybe even vlc and and and
Heaven's be perhaps kodi. Yeah
Whoa, this would be an un this would be an an obvious
Premier distribution for the raspberry pi and turns out there's a lot of raspberry pies out there
Is this your goal or are you just I mean this seems like almost like evil mastermind level, uh, planning
No, this is this is answering what the community has asked for
so
uh, the first goal was to make ubuntu mate, um
as
Useful to the makers as raspbian is so i've got lots of friends who make stuff with the raspberry pi
And you know, they've got
This is all alien to me
They've got breadboards and they've got widgets and wires and things and they glue it all together and they make stuff work
One of my friends albert made a mind mind controlled game with the raspberry pi imagine that so a headband
You put on your head and you think like flappy birds you think up down and it responds to your thoughts to play the game
So, you know epic epic levels of makers combine that with vr and you got my attention
Yeah, so when when I ask albert, you know does this work?
I've got to the point where albert is satisfied that all of the stuff he needs to do
And and isaac as well. All of these guys are from the pi podcast. They're the presenters on the pi podcast
They're like the unofficial official ubuntu mate test team. So when they tell me stuff works, i'm fairly confident it works
So i've kind of got all of that gpio
maker level stuff working really well now
And the next thing that everyone is asking for is they want kodi they want vlc
They want it accelerated. So that's what we're trying to do
So definitely we've got vlc done that's in the bag. We've definitely got ffmpeg that's in the bag
Um an ffmpeg is there because we use that with the youtube downloader, which is but got the gooey built in
and and
Next is to try and ace kodi and I make no promises about that because i've tried several times in the past and flat out failed
We'll see how we go. Hey, at least you're trying I guess well that is that is quite the update
Uh, that is that is really great. I boy i'm excited about that
um, you know, I I am uh, so i've been for for weeks now i've been using uh plasma desktop on ubuntu, um
And for the last two i've been using it on 1604
And uh now i'm switching over to unity i'm going to be running on unity until until final comes out
But I wouldn't be surprised if the one I end up on is the ubuntu mate 1604 on the apollo
Well, that just makes sense. And then when I run it on my raspberry pi 3 same exact setup. I love it wimpy
That's pretty cool
Yeah
Thank you. That's so yeah. Thank you to everyone who contributed to the project in the last month. It was really great. So we shifted
55 terabytes of downloads of raspberry pi images in march
What are you using to distribute 55? What did you say?
55 terabytes. Yeah
What are you using to do that just for the raspberry pi
We've got um three servers and two of them are responsible for for shifting that data
Holy smoke one in canada and one in france. You should maybe talk to alan because uh,
You need to move. Yeah, maybe yeah, holy smokes
Uh as somebody who moves many terabytes of data a month, too. Um
There are not many independent shops that are able to move that much data I am extremely impressed
I thought I was one of the only that got away with that. So that is
Unbelievable, that's the easy bit because you know doing large scale server stuff. That's my day job
I can do that all day long accelerating video playback and
You know plugging things into gpio ports not not so hot at that that that takes a bit more time
Yeah, but you're doing it. Yeah. Yeah, exactly. Well slowly baby steps. Yeah. Oh shoot. I was just trying to look uh,
It's no longer. Hmm. It doesn't seem that alan no longer
He doesn't put it in there anymore alan used to put the total terabyte of transfer in the invoice
But I don't see it
But uh, yeah, it's a it's a pretty significant amount of terabytes per month
And so that's that's impressive wimpy just for the raspberry pi too. That's
Yikes, all right. Well, uh, i'll tell you what i'm gonna take a minute and tell you about my mobile service provider tang
You know i'm going on a road trip west road trip road trip
Everybody go to linux.ting.com real quick once you i'm going on a road trip
So you know what i'm gonna do before I go on my road trip
You know what I do. This is legit. I log into my ting dashboard and I go turn on my mi-fi line
And then I have a mi-fi
Yeah, it's easy. Wow. And then when i'm when i'm back from the road trip, you know what I do
I log in with the ting dashboard. I turn off my mi-fi
That's that's your boop was better than my boop. Thank you. That was a really good. That's your is that your first boop?
I think so. That was solid linux.ting.com go there and save 25 off your first device now
Why ting? Well, that is easy. No contract
No early termination fee and ladies and gentlemen, you only pay for what you use six dollars for the line
So I got I when I activate
So do your boop boop. No. Oh, come on. That was boop when I activate the mi-fi
That's six dollars a month and then my usage on top of that and then when I deactivate the mi-fi boop
No, no. Wow, you peaked dude you boop
Uh when I did when I deactivate the mi-fi then I don't pay for it at all
This is really nice. So I generally have about three active devices
So i'm paying six dollars a month for each line and then my usage on top of that minutes messages and megabytes
Well, guess what? We've got wi-fi right here at the jupiter broadcasting studios and guess what? I've got wi-fi at home
And i've got wi-fi when I go to angela's house. I've got wi-fi when I go see my dentist even my dentist has wi-fi, dude
Dude my dentist. Um, there is a grocery store up in the city that I live in that has wi-fi
The leconner grocery store has wi-fi. Wow. Yeah
I tell you wi-fi everywhere. Well, no
No, I don't and that's why I have ting because when i'm not on wi-fi I can choose between gsm or cdma networks
They're like, yeah
I look at my cellular data sort of like my backup data when I need it and I primarily and that
I because of that and rikai. He's rikai. He's like that beard is like a ninja dude
It like it like soaks up wi-fi signals. It's like a booster. So
Between them between us with three lines. We're doing like 37 bucks this month for our ting line. It's ridiculous
Uh, and then you combine with that dashboard ting is an unbelievable deal and great customer service
They got like these fanatical customer support reps that are going to talk to you. They're going to work with you
They'll stay on the line. They'll talk to you until the tilts completely resolved my first road trip. I went on
I had like a little uh sim smid mix-up or whatever
I don't even remember anymore because it was a while ago, but when I was going over to noah's house for the uh,
When he for the uh for the uh for the tour of his house with all the tech he had in there
I my my first day on the road or a couple days into it
I had to like troubleshoot some sort of sim issue. I don't remember what it was now and uh
Uh, there was legitimately a point 45 minutes into the call where I thought they were like gonna like well, mr
Fisher, thank you for you know, blah blah and I was like because there's nothing we can do
Yeah, I was like look you've done everything you can i've done everything I can
I understand at some point in time you got to move on and this is totally cool
And dude, I kid you not they stuck with me for another 25 minutes and uh, they went they went they went above and beyond
Uh, and they really the problem got resolved and I was back online good to go. I mean
It was like and when they had and like I think at one point like they had to call someone and they put me on
Hold and and then let me listen in on their call to them and I could hear them like telling them
What what was up and it was yeah, they were really cool. Uh, and then later on they sent me a postcard
A postcard a postcard. That was pretty cool. Uh, so and they do that
They I guess they do that from time to time go check them out go over there
Look at all the great devices they have they also on their blog just recently put up a post
I love long reviews a long review is the best kind of not these reviews where they get them five days before the device is
out for the public
Uh, but these reviews my month with the moto x pure edition that just went up on the ting blog
Go check them out linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring
the unplugged program
Linux.ting.com. Thanks you guys for going there and supporting the show by checking them out. So mr. Wes I
I am surprised almost every week
It seems at least for the last few weeks we have found a reason for you to have to format your hard drive and try out
Yet another off the wall linux distribution long serving hard drive. Yeah, and this week is no different. We're going to call it. I think um,
Apricity apricity os apricity os
Uh, and it is arch based
And a gnome based desktop or cinnamon. Thank you, and it uses the power. Oh jesus going so fast
I can't read the power line shell. Uh, it's a modern intuitive operating system with the cloud integration designed for the cloud generation
And by that they mean it it ships with a lot of interesting defaults. Uh, one of them being pushbullet
So your android notifications are synced between you and your device
That is that is kind of handy, uh, you know
There's other there's other actually kind of rather nice things like they ship it with play on linux included by default
In fact, it's it's rather stacked all together all things
uh, it ships with a tlp for uh,
Battery management installed by default sync thing is installed by default. I've got it
I'm already syncing with my really with my droplet. Yep. Google chrome is installed by default not chromium
um, it also has uh, uh, well
A rather design heavy desktop. I have it running here in a virtual machine west has it there running on a desktop
So if you're watching the video version i'm gonna pull it up here
So you guys can just kind of see here. Let me
Log in with my super secure. I have like a demo review password that I use. It's funny
So i'll zoom out a little bit I apologize here, you know what I will remote in
And uh, I will i'll turn off the lower third just for a second
So you guys can see the whole uh, you can see the whole desktop there
So there you can see I have it running in boxes under my kde desktop here. I'll go full screen
Why not what could go wrong?
And it kind of reminds me almost immediately of elementary os because it has a dock along the bottom
It has the transparent top pretty clean. Yeah
Um, but what do you think west so as somebody who doesn't uh, your daily driver doesn't run arch
But you've probably ran arch on many occasions everything else in my life mostly does. Yeah. Yeah. No, it's nice
I'm i'm enjoying it. I've kind of already got everything replaced. I'm you know doing the show from and i've got irc back up
Uh, it was very easy to get installed and going and since it's arch
Uh, you know, you can just one tick enable the aur in their little add or remove software
Or I can have pacman on the command line like i'm always used to
now, um
You and I both thought the installer was pretty nice pretty clean
Did you recognize that as an installer from anything else?
I didn't either. I didn't recognize it now
It felt so well done that it must have it felt like it must be a fork of
And the only reason i'm saying this is because it usually takes a couple of years for an installer to be pretty well
Flushed out to be one of those areas. Yeah. Yeah, and uh, this seemed like
a pretty spot-on good installer and it handled, uh my partitioning just fine it
The only thing it didn't do that, you know
I've come to expect from a modern day installer is it didn't appropriately detect my time zone. Oh, yeah
Yeah, it didn't didn't for me either. But yeah, but let me set it. I mean that would probably yeah, exactly
Super easy. It's not a big deal. But I mean that's just like one grub screen was really nice polished
It found my other and so did you know because i'm writing a vm
I might not I might not begin the same experience as you did
But if for mine my grub screen kind of in fact, I could reboot right now and just show the audience
Uh, my grub screen kind of looks like the gnome 3 login screen like it's that same color and that tech that great textures
That would all right. Yeah, so right there so it kind of and then when it boots up
That's the same color and the same general look you're going to get your login screen
Now I don't get I just get a text boot here. Do you get any kind of graphical like a plinth type boot? And you know
I'm not sure you haven't rebooted yet. Well, I did once but yeah nonsense then. Yeah. Okay, that's fine
Yeah, so it's um apricity I guess it's kind of a new distro
Based on arch. It does have its own repos. I haven't really dug into that too much
I probably should because that's always kind of an achilles heel of these kinds of things but
These this is an interesting trend where you have these super design distributions
And I think that was kind of what I found to be interesting about this
So you got solace right? You got elementary os those are kind of two of the jump to mine
But there's many others that are very design heavy
And x-metal says that it reminds him of in a mix between elementary and antigross which I could see that too because it's similar to
the arc theme which reminds me a bit of the bungee desktop and it's similar to antigross because it's
Arch base. Yes, and they're using yeah, it looks like they're using
West do you remember the name of the shell that they have here? They have power line. Yeah, okay
So they have power line installed by default, which is interesting because that's kind of a a jazzed up bash shell there and it's um
It makes it is it yeah, I don't know if you're watching the video version
But it makes it look a little nicer than normal and um, so if I if I go into downloads here
Oh, look at that. That's cute. Uh, you see that
Oh, look at that. That's cute. Uh, you see how the uh, my path is in the yeah
Yeah, isn't that it's kind of neat. It's very clean. It's very easy to read
Um, and uh, yeah, that's just something there's a lot of little things like this that they've done by by default
They make it a very well, I mean i'm actually making a very attractive desktop
They have like telegram right in their own repo. There's a binary so we got that. Oh, really?
Yeah, I don't know what else they have already. No, I guess I can just get that from the aur though
Yeah, they also have a graphical package manager that is is
Actually kind of palatable. So search telegram there. You'll see I think you'll see them both. Oh, okay
Okay, telegram. Let's take a look. Oh telegram with an e now. Did you know they spell with an e now?
I don't see it in here
No, you're a big you're a liar. Oh, okay. Well, maybe you have to you might have to enable aur and
Let's check this out. Check this out. They're using this gtk3 front end to lib alpm, which
Essentially gives you a graphical package manager for pacman and it even gives you the ability to install local alpm packages
Which is really kind of an interesting thing for an art user. Yeah
So this is a gtk3 interface to the package manager that they ship here. They've got caffeine just by default
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, I bet they have a you know, what if we launch gnome tweak, which they also have in the dock
Right. Yeah by default. I bet you we have quite a bit of extensions in here. Wow
Yeah, always zoom workspaces caffeine dash to dock flippery move clock media player indicator
Places status indicator. Yeah, there's a bunch in here wes
But you know what to be honest with you. These are actually all all of these
In fact, there's even a couple I would add
Um, these are all good. Um, these are actually all great
Uh, in fact, I know some of the people that make some of these and these and they're they're all really dedicated people
So these are all really high quality extensions. Um, so and then again, this is these are all these are really good defaults
Uh, it's kind of it's kind of interesting and one of the other things that they're doing that I find to be interesting
Is this is a patreon?
Yeah, they've got a patreon
this is a patreon fund and they've only got a few backers right now because it's early and I imagine this concept too is
kind of odd for a lot of people but uh,
I I don't know. I find it to be really neat
I I kind of i'm if I wasn't in the midst of my like 1604 mega, uh deep dive I would be
You know, I guess to put it another way when I go back on my arch binge
I might be tempted to go this route. The only thing i'm gonna have to spend time is I gotta look into uh,
Uh, what what always maybe you could check for me if you don't mind. Yeah, sure. Um
How are those gnome extensions coming from their repository?
Uh, what what all is coming from the repository because when gnome, uh 3.22 comes out
That crap's gonna break and that is always what what sort of dooms those arch-based gnome desktops in the long term
Is when they pull too much from their own private repository, but like yeah
So they have they have that fancy bash terminal installed, which is really nice. They uh,
They also have pre-built several packages like telegram in their user repository play on is installed steam is pre-installed obviously then wine
Because you have play on is pre-installed
um
It's an interesting arch-based distribution. Has anyone in the mumble room played with this one? I doubt it
It's pretty new apricity. I think is how you say apricity os
They have a cinnamon edition available as well, which neither one of us gave a shot
Okay, I mean i'm not seeing too much here's a list of everything in apricity core i've got installed. Okay, give it to me
Um, they've got like a bunch of themes other icons
Uh some broadcom at 10k drivers bt sync cower gnome terminal google chrome google talk plugin
That kind of stuff, uh pack aur so just kind of their own
their own modifications, uh, but it's not very much and it's none of the gnome stuff bitten mentions in the chat room real-time follow-up that that
Gdk3 gooey for the package managers that I was loving there that uh that pacman front end is what mangero uses. Oh, yeah
Uh, okay. Well, I I don't i'm not sensing a huge interest in this
Um, even though I actually think this is kind of a fascinating distribution. I will just wrap with this
Um, they're focusing on web apps
In a way that i've actually recently become a little more uh hip to myself
I've been using google chrome's uh create create it like what does google chrome call it when you go in here you can say um,
You know there's a way to isn't there a way to yeah like a way to make this a
Save uh add or save page as or add to desktop or something like that add to desktop and it makes it a desktop application
Right. Okay add to desktop makes it yeah, so that's a way to make it a desktop application
Right. Okay add to desktop makes it yeah, so they are shipping something called ice
It lets you put your favorite web app on the desktop a simple ssb a site specific browser manager
These specialized browsers are minimize the number of steps between you and wanting to use your favorite web app. They say
Uh, it embodies our vision here at apricity
We want to help your make your workspace and your play space more productive and elegant
Now as someone who has fallen into using an online markdown editor a lot
Not always an online document program google docs
Um an online chat program, uh irc cloud from time to time or matter most or slack
It starts to make a lot of sense to have these be separate processes that show up as separate icons in my task manager
See what i'm what i'm seeing is this seems like a great
It's such an easy thing to slot into you got syncing right? So bam you're syncing with yourself
You've got your key pass. You've got whatever you need now. You're signed into chrome
You're signed into your accounts. You make web apps for slack for telegram
And you've got your full desktop experience in like 10 minutes on a fresh install
They also say a fresh install usually idles after everything's up and running around 500 megabytes of usage
Which really isn't too bad. They focus on battery usage with tlp installed by default
Push bullet for integration with your android device to get notification notifications texts and phone calls across all your devices
Uh sync thing like west just managed also sp backup
Which is uh, kind of a nice backup program that allows you to do both compressed and uncompressed backups and split uncompressed backups
And like multiple parts if you want to do it across like thumb drives or something
uh, you can do scheduled backups and manual backups with it and
Also backups to remote destinations and they've built it in
Right there installed by default
and then like earlier mentioned the power line shell, which is the
pretty nice terminal prompt
Uh, it looks really it looks really classy. They've gone throughout and made sure that the things are
Well rendered under high dpi
And I like their defaults, you know
They're using gnome photos for your photos gnome music for your music gnome calendar for your calendar
They got steam installed by default. They got a library office installed by default
And like, you know other things like we mentioned so I it seems like a really cool project that's really thinking about this stuff
Uh, and you know arch base which kind of gets my attention down the road, I think so apricity
We'll have a link in the show notes apricity os.com
If you guys want to check it out
Derek delvin, you had to mention about chromium embedded framework. Go ahead
I don't hear you. I guess he did have a he did have a comment. Yeah, he did. It's fine. It's fine
Um, uh, I think these in web apps, uh inclusion into the desktop are natural
Evolution of the chromium embedded framework. I mean google did this
Uh simplify you development. I mean if you think atom brackets those editors are using that principle
But I guess it's time that we before we start just jumping on board and this start making the question
Aren't our browsers already doing quite a lot and do we really want to be in this completely remote?
So the application can run somewhere else and you just get that face. No, no, no, no, but in some cases, yes
Yes, yeah in some cases, especially for stuff. I don't care a lot about the south is not super important
Yeah, I think so, right? Yeah
Um, but yeah, that's a good question patreon.com slash apricity. They have four patrons right now. They're making 30 bucks a month
I doubt that's covering much
Yeah, I doubt I doubt so but that's a it's an interesting try and so, uh, i'm glad you installed a west
Yeah, we'll see. I might just be using it next week as well
I'm not seeing I mean I can mount my other one if I need it. I'm not seeing a lot of reason to go back
Do you uh like the performance on the physical hardware performance is okay on the spot there? Yeah, absolutely
I mean I it's I suspended it all the way here. Things are working great. Yeah. Yeah, you know wes
I think we should take a moment and we should thank linux academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
Now all of us know that if you really want to get a great job
You're probably going to have to have a few certifications under your belt
Also, it's kind of nice as personal challenges and it's also helps at review time
Linux academy has had a ton of success in the last few months
Uh, I I mean they have had success for
A lot longer than that, but they've been publishing it on their blogs in the last few months and really sort of demonstrating
What a difference people can see when they go to linux academy
Especially when they're looking to learn something around linux or aws other learning sites. They don't quite get it right
They don't quite have the passion and the drive to actually care enough to understand the difference between red hat enterprise linux and fedora
Or debian and ubuntu there are differences, you know
There are but they can barely even understand what they are. That's not linux academy
Linux academy is a platform designed by people that are extremely passionate about linux and wanted to sort of promote it
In a way that would get wider adoption for linux
They came together with educators and professionals and developers and created the linux academy platform
Linux academy.com slash unplugged go there support this show and give yourself a discount
you know
I think also one of the things you might take for granted about linux academy because it
It's a website. You probably think it's only useful when you have an internet connection
But if you're going to be offline like i'm about to be for several days
Uh, they have downloadable comprehensive study guides. They have pdfs for reading wow
They have audio and video stuff that you can get while you're offline as well
Uh listener seth
Listens in the shower
He's not bringing his laptop in there. He's got a plane through his speaker system while he's in the shower. That's awesome
Yeah, I know it is kind of awesome. Uh, and that's a really nice functionality of linux. They also have of course
Yeah, okay
So they so on the other end they also have live events and you can ask instructors questions and they have instructor mentoring and
All of that and they have an active forums. It's packed full of jupiter broadcasting members. They have great courseware on red hat. I mean
I mean noah is all about the red hat enterprise certified like
Administrator and engineer and he's always yeah. Well and the clients love it man
That's I mean, I don't know how much noah is into it
I mean, I think he respects red hat as a company, but it's the clients that really want it
And it's the same when you're trying to get a job
Uh, and so that's why he pursues it and you know
He's done a lot of different avenues and red hat is totally is a seriously respected certification
And their courseware at linux academy is top notch also on the aws stuff on the front of aws
just when I started getting into like s3 and storing my uh,
Web assets and like the complicated system that they have for it and it's like, okay i've got this
I don't need any courseware on this right? I mastered this on my own
Okay, so then I went further and a client needed a windows 2003 server
And well, you know what i'm an aws expert now i'll go set this up for you. Yeah, I had um
I had like a couple of weeks of like, you know
Going back and forth with the client and citing how we were going to do what and what was going to run
Where and all me all all in the meanwhile this brand new server I set up for them was running on aws
and uh
I didn't I didn't quite grok the fact that that was like like costing me like this as the cpu runs
it costs me money like
Per cycle it costs money like unbelievable right unbelievable. They're charging me per cpu cycle unbelievable
Who even tracks that is what I was thinking?
So I got this bill and i'm like, uh, yeah, you know that server that we haven't even deployed to production yet
We're already paying for it. Sorry, and I was using that time to learn the system too
Kind of you know at the same time
That's a podcaster folks. Yeah
Yeah
Linux academy.com slash unplugged when you go there and you're going through one of their courses or they have a scenario
Or a live lab they'll spin up the aws instance for you and manage all of that
So you don't get stuck with that fine
Uh, they also have android development courses php python ruby the whole dev ops category chef is their chef tutorials are very helpful
Dude, they're linux basics and all of that and they have like nuggets on ip tables and net tables and fire and tables
whatever it's called now and filter all the things all the things ssh all the things really they have great nuggets, too
If you just have a little bit of time and you want to just do a deep dive
So go check them out linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and avoid that huge bill that uh that I got I got one day
Okay, so there was a thread over on our linux that kind of got me wondering, uh, it said is you know
What's the state of vr?
Uh for the for the linux desktop, uh, what do we have?
I3 on multiple monitors those kind of things and there was a couple of different answers that came out of the thread
But one of them west was kind of intriguing
It was a qt5 or qt5 based 3d wayland compositor
Oh snap. Yeah
So what this now this is totally early days, but what they have designed is sort of a wolfenstein style
layout of a of a map and in
In each room is a different virtual desktop. So when you go between rooms you're going between virtual desktops
And you have like different windows and then you can you know, you would have perhaps like a bot in there west
You know about bots wait and you heard about bots. Yeah. Well, you could have a bot in there and things like that
So that's that's one representation of it
But there's there hasn't there's not a lot of progress
There's not a lot of progress for the linux desktop. Um,
Uh hololens sdk hackaday.io has a great one that they posted back in 2015
Where they had like a couple of different a couple of different examples
That were that looked pretty exciting you put the headset on and now you're doing window management
And again another room concept i've seen a bunch of different concepts ibx is one that runs on windows and linux
but maybe i'm just
Maybe i'm just smoking the hype too much wimpy. Do you think there will never be a real use case for vr on linux?
I'm a skeptic
Um, yeah, but i'm not much of a gamer either but I I don't know wearing a great big heavy thing on your head
People weren't prepared to wear glasses to watch 3d films
But what about what about just the fact that it would be the world's largest monitor?
Okay, think about that think about you know, 27 inch monitor 30. No the entire room is your screen
But strapped to your head and also until they're completely wireless, you know, you're just tethered. You're just you know, like a pony, you know
A pony
Okay, okay, okay. All right, mr. Skeptic, but okay. Okay, you're probably right actually i'm fairly skeptical myself
I really i'm only playing devil's advocate. But what about something like a mumble room ask poppy?
He's got a cancer argument. I'm sure poppy. Do you think we could have a vr desktop on linux in the future?
Uh, what come on poppy, maybe you could maybe you could slap
Your ubuntu phone into a google cardboard headset and now you are in vr
unity
And you know they built in support for mirror too they've built support in the mirror for vr in the future
Oh poppy doesn't answer now. I guess he doesn't have an opinion. Sorry
Go ahead
I just left the room to make a cup of tea for my wife and all I heard when I got back to the microphone
Was poppy isn't answering so poppy that is you are such a romantic. You are a gentleman
Uh, the question was is you know wimpy is sort of an on the record vr
Um skeptic you could say
And i'm somewhere in the middle. I'm sort of a vr hopeful but 10 trending skeptic
What do you think? Uh, we're just talking about sort of the lack of a vr desktop, but there are a couple different projects
They're mostly school projects that create a virtual linux desktop in vr. What about poppy? I'm just going to throw this out in your face
ubuntu touch
in a google cardboard headset
ubuntu vr unity desktop your thoughts
Can we get our existing desktop working first
Ha ha ha great answer. That's a good answer. Well, okay
We're gonna go 10 20 years and no we're gonna go five years in the future
Do you think there could be a vr desktop? I really feel like linux is missing out on vr
But maybe i'm just sort of getting excited by
I don't know the tweets of some people that are working on vr. I mean i'm just getting hyped
I don't know. I see this as being a bit like the the tesla. It's something, you know quite desirable and
And it might be useful for a small set of people on the planet, but for the vast majority of people
They will almost never see this and therefore it won't be useful for them. Therefore. We shouldn't devote
99 of our developers sure sure that's it
Okay
And it seems like it'll start where a lot of things start where like first entertainment and then in like particular
Power applications like cad modeling or you know, whatever where they really take advantage very
Very specific 3d use cases for it
But then like if i'm looking at a document I can't
You know call me an old fart or lack of imagination
But I can't see how a libre office document can be improved by the adding of an extra dimension
I agree with you there. I've already got that a plane in a third dimension if I just look at my life
But I but you I could I could agree with you there, but there could be use cases
I mean, I think of it as just more screen real estate to be honest with you
And you're right and yeah being able to look behind things and look around things is is novel
And we've seen demos of this for years and years that guy who strapped a couple of
Wee motes to his head and did a nice demo of you know
being able to move your head from side to side and look around things and get a real parallax kind of view of
Of things on your desktop. It looked interesting, but that was years and years ago
And nobody ever did anything with it partly because it's kind of impractical
Would be coolest thing. Oh, sorry. Go ahead dear devin
So I think the use case for documents is when we have the natural voice commands working
So you're not necessarily writing the document. So a libre office the application definitely is not an application to benefit from it
But let's say you are searching your computer and you're seeing the results
In a graph window and then you're seeing the other graph available to you
And whatever else and maybe you are actually projecting this to what is your reality?
So it's a more of an augmented reality than just virtual reality
And now at that point that you're talking with your computer and you're getting the results and they're coming to you
I guess now you can have different ways of manipulating these data
Rather than think of the normal conventional applications with that we are talking about
I think the benefits will be in there. Hmm. So
So, you know you're looking at stock or you're looking at the company or you're doing your search and suddenly you are
With the data that you wanted for stocks for example for that application
And then you can do the math next to it and you can get the result, right?
producer q5 sister says that he thinks that
Perhaps there could be an interesting use case in terms of interface for managing vms
Running a vm on a virtual computer in your vr world. So it's like you're really sitting at that virtual machine. Yeah
Huh?
Uh, well, it's a cinema killer as well. Yeah, it could be I agree
Now when I tried it on the the most low-end implementation of vr
I've tried is on the samsung galaxy vr and to me it just seemed like a glorified way to watch great movies
Yeah, but it was a great way to watch movies
Janus vr jn
Us vr is something that already works on linux today
Uh, and it's what they say it combines the power of the internet with the potential of virtual reality
Websites become immersive spaces linked by portals
Where users can explore collaborate and create content on a platform that builds upon the open internet?
Um, and it's so retro in so many ways
It's like how we actually would have visualized the internet to work in the 80s when we did movies
Yeah, right, uh where you go through portals to go to different rooms and there's avatars and people have keys and it is
It is so neat in its in its in its intricacy
But it is so impractical in its actual usability
That I find it to be a fascinating experiment and it's using browser technology
Now the hardware thing was you and I noticed when we were looking around it's like
It looks like nobody is taking the plunge on the linux side and just like
Trying to see what works under linux. Yeah. Now the vive is just starting to ship but
Everybody online right now is asking does the hdc vive work?
That's this that's the that's the official steam backed steam vr headset
Does it work with linux and everybody's asking the question, but nobody's really got an answer right now. Yep
Uh, and you got google cardboard, but that doesn't really work with linux desktop and oculus, you know
They could go suck an egg for all I care
Oculus, yeah, go ahead and there is a big reason for why in linux there hasn't been much development
We have usually huge issues with graphics drivers. So yeah, that's fixed
You really can't do anything right, you know, all I want all I want is just the game
I just want there to be a standard
I just want to I want there to be a vr standard
And games just need to support that standard and then if I have the hardware that that understands that standard plugged into my
Into my machine that's all it needs to be
I just want to get to that level and that's when it's going to be that's when it's really going to be something
Um, yeah, yeah, you know, I have a little bitterness with the oculus
It's true the way they draw, you know
I backed it because they had linux support. Yeah, and then when they dropped it
You know and I uh
I the reason why i'm not a full-on skeptic like wimpy is and I I was until I got the oculus
uh dk2 and when I got the dk2 and um
I know i've shared this story
But when I got the dk2 and I went on this little raft that's floating out on the ocean
And I just I just I sat there for I had a chair here in the studio
So it was like I was sitting on the raft and I had the oculus here in the studio
So and the studio is um is is sound insulated and I had headphones on
So it was like there was no and it's dark in here. There's there's no outside influence. It was
It was it was very much
perceptually like I was um
Like I was on this raft and because I was on a swiveling chair
I could turn my whole body to to turn with with the vr environment and so it was like I was
Turning around and looking at the ocean
And I I kind of got like that feeling you get when you're just chilling on the beach
And when I started to feel like I was chilling on the beach when i'm sitting in my studio in my chair
I realized there's something here. I don't know exactly what it is
But there that just gave me a totally new experience
Yeah, and that was really something and so that's why i'm hopeful we figure it out
But right now the hardware requirements are ridiculous. Yeah
And the linux support is weak
And the most economical implementation is going to be the cheap stuff built into the phones
Which have the weakest graphics and the most disappointing applications?
So yeah, uh wimpy asks, uh, you were asking how much the oculus is
Uh-huh. I think it was about 300 bucks, but I can't I can't it might be it might have been what was that?
You know, it was one of those
Like second round fundings, so I don't recall how how many times have you been out on the raft virtually?
Only a few because i've been i've lent it out. I've lent out the oculus since then when they dropped their linux support
And i'm just thinking you could probably have rented a boat and experienced, you know bobbing up and down on the ocean for real
For about the same money fair enough and there you get smell. Yeah, that's true
Well, this reality needs to offer something other than a poor simulation of reality to be compelling. I think you're probably right
You're probably right
Um kitson you had a thought though. Go ahead
Uh, yeah, uh one more serious thought on this is I just think the vm would is just overkill for most gaming
Applications and just computer applications, especially in general
Uh, most of the best games that i've played had really simple graphics
And they were able to place me in a world where I was more
Convinced of things true than a lot of these games that try to force graphics and cinematics on you and it's just
Yeah, yeah, that's true. You are talking to the guy that just got mario
Working again on his uh television at home
A funny side effect of that is that because of the power required for vr
The current vr games are less graphically intensive just like you described
Yeah, that's why it feels like it's going to be a real catch-22 for them to ever actually take off
I will say that eve valkyrie
Demo did seem pretty neat. Well, what's that one the eval create? Is that an e3 in 2015? Oh, yeah
Yeah, yeah, that's an older one, right? Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, that just always stuck with me
There's not a lot standing between linux and having broader vr support because a lot of the engines
That that like like the unreal engine for example, you know, if you make a vr game
Okay, here's what here's what it is. This is i'm just gonna i've just got to be
This is going to be linux unplugged confession edition
Uh, I want to walk around the starship enterprise
and
and there is an oculus vr compatible starship enterprise project that is
Unbelievably detailed and the man has recreated areas of the enterprise that you've never seen that in order to connect it all together
So you can walk the entire thing. I included like areas of the shuttle bay that are absolutely stunning and compelling
I mean it is wow, it is transcending
and now you've just described something that actually makes it
compelling because
You can't experience that in the real world
So he took the blueprints to the starship enterprise and made them into a virtual world
Yeah, it is here. I'll show if you're watching the video version. I'll show you a little bit
It's pre-alpha footage here. Um, and he's been working on it for a long time. He has a patreon for it. Uh, but uh,
What he did is he took the blueprints to make the most accurate representations if he could from like it's about season six or seven
From what I can tell by watching it
And I am that much of a nerd that I can tell it's about season five six or seven
But I would guess six and it is uh, it is remarkably accurate. It starts with a
It starts with a tour of the shuttle bay in a way. It shows you how the uh, how um,
The cargo bays and the shuttle bays are connected in a way that is brilliant, but yet never demonstrated in the actual show
Um, and he goes and he goes on to show you areas that you are very familiar with
Oh, here's another he spends a lot of time on the shuttle because he's very proud of it
The lot and this is all based on the unreal engine
So it looks
Really good and it's all oculus compatible. So this is a 10 forward lounge
That he's showing here and i'll go forward because you know
What we all want to see though is we what we really want to see is the meeting room here and things like that
so this probably gets pulled down from youtube, but
Of course, it does also have sounds
Oh, man
What's that? He's in the conference room and this is why I say it's like season four five six seven on it
It's it's later on in tng
And then he had to make up this hallway and he took the old conference room gold chips from the conference room and put them
In the hallway connecting to the bridge, which is just brilliant because they
Those were destroyed because they used the set in star trek 6 now he's on the bridge
And it's it is immaculately done
Now you would
So I I would I would pretty much I would die to have this under linux right
The detail
Photon torpedoes armed
And targeted and he walks around, you know the whole thing he's got he's got just about every even oh, he even did the bathroom
Look, he even finally did the bathroom. Now. This is based on schematics. There's three shells, which is a
Yeah, a nod to a stalone movie
And uh, he's got three shells in the bathroom, which is just hilarious
You can sit in the captain's chair
protects fools
little children and ships named enterprise
I don't think i'm cut out to be captain
First officer, maybe
And go check out the ready room
It really is remarkable it's so well done and so uh, there's also there's other air there are
One of the things that the gear vr was really good at was photographic tours of paris
Which I thought was i've never been to paris
Uh, so I took a photo tour of paris and it's not like google street view
It's way cooler than google street view. And of course you can do 360 degree
You can look around uh that tearing is not in the video by the way
That's just on my i'm having some problems with kaywin today
Um, but the tearing isn't there and the the engine is is is just you can see the graphics are
So
Yeah that I can't wait I don't know I don't know what vr solution is going to provide me this but uh,
I'll pay for it. That's for sure
Yeah, I love it I love it so that's what I I want that but I don't want to have to run windows
You know, like that's a real conflict for me. I want that in my life
But at the same time I don't want to have to run windows
And so we got to get this figured out under linux
So if anybody out there has tried or it gets their hands on the htc vive. You've got to let us know
Uh, yeah. Yeah, he's uh, you gotta let us know how it goes x metal x metal just comments youtube is going to hate this
Yeah
Yeah, i've already got one of my shows pulled down this week. So why not have another show pulled down?
It's only tuesday
So might as well get two shows pulled down one a week one day one show a week. Why not everybody?
So yeah, I agree with you wimpy if you make it compelling enough I could get interested
I think I also agree with the rest of you. I'm not looking to do a vr desktop anytime soon. I'd give it a go
but
Just for a desktop it'd be too much hassle. Yeah
Yeah, let's let's just get the main desktops working. Let's get wayland out there. Let's get mirror working
Let's get unity finished up then we could worry about the virtual reality and you know and the whatnots, right? Don't you think?
All right
Yeah, I might reconsider if I get to use the nintendo power glove
Bring that all in bring it all together. Why not? Let's do it
That seems like that actually seems like a pretty good idea. I think you should you should capitalize on that
You might have something there that will bring us to the end of this week's episode of the unplugged program
Thank you to everybody who joined us in the mumba room. You guys were great
I'm preparing to go out
On spring break first spring break trip with the kids what gonna take lady jupes out on the road
That's awesome. Yeah, i'm pretty excited about that. I've uh, I got our cody installation packed up with media
So we can watch tv offline to save bandwidth and whoever you yeah
If you'd like to join us live we'd love to have you here go over to jupiter broadcasting.com
Slash calendar to find out when this show is live. You can catch it live at jblive.tv
The calendar page will convert to your local time zone and you can submit content by going to linuxactionshow.reddit.com
Why don't you join us for 140 live next week? If you don't we got feeds. You can always download get automatically
Thanks for joining us. See you right back here next tuesday
So
That was a lot of fun, thank you everybody for joining us
We had we had a lot of all come together and I think it made for a nice medley of the unplugged program
I think so. Thank you very much. What was that?
do that the plasma kill shortcut that uh
Oh, yeah, what was that plasma kill shortcut? I that might do it does that but that probably doesn't restart kwin. Does it?
I don't know
What was that plasma kill shortcut? It wasn't on this computer. So I don't have it in my recent history
Oh, that was nice. Wow. Look at that. It's so bad. Look at my look at krunner. Oh, that's
Unusable that is not even that is like yikes
Holy smokes. Look at that
That is getting in the seizure territory, right? Yeah
Rekai records this for a bug report. I gotta tell you we saw that on open qa once it's flashing as fuck. Yeah
I wasn't an x and mess and stuff. Are you running? Uh, I you know, I uh
I have no idea be whatever the default I could go bring up
You know one thing I do and I did play with is like the kwin rendering settings, but I don't even know it
Oh my gosh. Oh my gosh
Whoa
Whoa. Oh my gosh. All my icons just did like this little blurry thing for a second
A little like holy smokes. This is getting crazy. I wonder if it's gonna make it the show now
we're gonna now it's gonna be like a race against the uh,
So where do you go? Okay, so I can I still can never figure out kd settings. There's so many freaking
So where do I guess i'm reloading this machine, uh, where do I go to find where you configure is it not
God, there's so many options in here
That's not the bonobo by the way. No, this is on the apollo
Uh
Where do you go to manage kwin now, where the hell is that at?
Maybe if I just up there and search type in window manager, I know but
That is such a cop out window
Just start management
None of that's coming up. I know how about just like what if I just type for kwin will that work kwin?
Here we go. Wow. Oh there. Can you see my icons? Do you see that? Look at that?
We'll look at the window management icon. Do you see what i'm talking about? Come on there. It's back now
Yeah, it's listed under one of those categories, but it doesn't say kwin explicitly. All right. Okay, so let's see here. Uh,
Kwin rules kwin scripts task switcher. Nope. No, none of this is what I want
I'm looking for the thing where you change what your renderer is in kwin
desktop behavior
This is this is this is the problem really
This is really the thing. Okay compositor. Here we go. Open gl is what I currently have
I'm going to try 3 1 and see what happens. I mean what what could go worse than what's happening now?
Nothing, it stopped
It stopped
You see that
Let's see if I can aggravate it
It's not doing it with boxes
It's not doing it with spotify
I think switching kwin from wait a minute. Nope. It's doing it again. Damn it
Oh, it's happening again. Although it's not look it's not happening on the second screen yet. That's interesting
Oh now it is now it's happening on the second screen
Well that lasted a good few seconds. That's too bad. Got your hopes up though. I did I did. What if I do x render?
Okay, it stopped I did x render it stopped
I don't know if I go aggravate it a little bit
This is this is definitely a kwin issue though
There's no way about that there's no this this is definitely so now i'm not using open gl as my render
I'm using x render which I would imagine means it's cpu-based, right?
Seems to be working really good though
All right, now i'm not having a problem. Awesome. So i'll go with x render for the show. Yay
Perfect. Yeah, perfect. My definition of perfect exactly