Are you all packed up for our trip?
No, not at all.
But that's going to happen tonight.
Oh, yeah.
So I can say it, too.
Well, I've got to do laundry first.
That's right.
I'm totally going to do it after the show.
Wes and I tomorrow fly out to San Antonio, San Antonio,
Texas for the Texas Cyber Summit.
Before the show, we were both checking in
and realizing neither of us is prepared for this.
What about you, Cheesy, are you packed?
Yeah, I'm pretty much packed up.
I've got a few things to add, some swag to throw
into the back of the vehicle.
But other than that, yeah, I'm ready to go.
Looking forward to hanging out with you guys, obviously.
I know.
That is going to be a lot of fun.
Well, L set us all up with an Airbnb,
so we'll be hanging out at the Airbnb, doing stuff.
That'll be really good.
Feel like it's going to be kind of like Red Hat Summit was,
where we all get to decompress at the end of the day
and kind of rap out for a few.
And like last time, we always get
geeky sitting around talking about Linux
when we get an Airbnb.
That's the greatest thing, to get the geek out in person.
Oh, hey.
Welcome into Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
This is one of those episodes where we got together last week
and we thought, well, let's chat about next week's episode.
And about 10 hours later, we've got something really cool,
but we went down a few rabbit holes.
So hopefully, we'll save you some time
when you're trying to set up an ultimate LAN mesh powered
by WireGuard.
WireGuard, WireGuard.
In fact, we'll talk a little bit about that,
because I think soon you'll be hearing
much more about WireGuard.
Let's hope so.
Yeah, it seems like there's some pieces that
are moving that are going to kick things into high gear.
And it turns out things are a bit more
complex than maybe you might appreciate,
but some things are a little easier.
So we'll get into how I bridged a mobile network with a LAN
network using WireGuard and making
all the devices on each end of the LAN
accessible to each other.
It's really neat, and it's essentially
enterprise-grade networking tech,
like stuff that you used to have to pay Cisco tens of thousands
of dollars to do, and now it's baked right into Linux.
And I don't know, maybe people haven't seen your RV,
but you don't have room for a network rack in there.
So we'll talk so much more about that in a little bit.
Of course, we've got the community news.
There's some good stuff in there to get to.
As well as our virtual log.
Time-appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Hi, good to see you, Wimpy, and Minimac, and Bitten,
and Carl, and Bruce.
And I'm going to say, Aknomad?
I can't quite see from across the room.
What is it there?
Read it for me there, Wes.
Wes is closer.
Ace Nomad.
There you go.
That's it.
Hey, you got it.
You got it.
Nice.
Ace Nomad.
Well, welcome in.
Glad to have you here.
And of course, Mr. Bacon's there too.
Hey, Cheesy.
Hey, hey, hey.
What's up, everybody?
Oh, you know, getting ready to fly down to San Antonio.
Looking forward to seeing you.
Hell yeah.
Yeah, I think it's going to be nice to get
a little shift in weather, too, from the Pacific Northwest.
More than a little shift.
Well, let's talk about some community news.
And Linus kicks it off this week after, well,
some not-so-surprising comments about Microsoft, I suppose.
I was going to say somewhat surprising, but if you know
Linus, he's very pragmatic about these kinds of things.
So SVJN from ZDNet was at the Linux Plumbers Conference
and put the question to Linus about how
he feels about Microsoft.
Linus is then quoted as saying, the whole anti-Microsoft thing
was sometimes funny as a joke, but not really.
Today, they're actually much friendlier.
I talk to Microsoft engineers at various conferences,
and I feel like, yes, they have changed.
And the engineers are happy.
They're, like, really happy working on Linux.
So I completely dismiss all this anti-Microsoft stuff.
If you want more context, you can read the full article
over at OMG Ubuntu.
We'll have that linked in the show notes.
This, to me, sounds like an individual, Linus,
that has to interact with other individuals, Microsoft
developers, on an ongoing basis and has
formed what is pretty much considered a cordial working
relationship.
Right.
I mean, I think it's very different from our perspective
watching development happen and different parties interested.
Linus is right there in the mix of it all.
And yeah, there are probably things
about kernel development, in terms
of people, less so than as an abstraction a far away.
You recall he had a very pragmatic stance
about Android and the use of the Linux kernel
and having really zero issue that people don't know
they're using Linux.
He was fine with that.
That's not what we created Linux for.
So the whole anti-Microsoft thing
was sometimes funny as a joke, but not really.
That's the line that stuck out to me the most.
Because he's kind of like saying the whole MS dollar sign thing,
it never really was all that funny.
And it feels like, in a couple of big ways,
the community is being told, move on.
Move on with the Microsoft stuff.
Move on with Richard Stallman.
Let's just move on.
And it's a big ask, both of those things.
And they both represent a massive sea change.
And I think that's why it's taking so much processing
by everyone.
It kind of makes me think we need
to be more nimble in general, right?
It's not to say that Microsoft's going to be a great Linux
ally forever.
We just need to judge it based on what's happening now.
And I don't mean to say forget the past,
but also remember the present.
By the time we get it figured out, things will have changed.
Exactly.
Well then, moving on from that, let's
talk about the future of OpenPGB in Thunderbird.
I love Enigma.
It's my go-to first thing I install when
I have a new Thunderbird installation.
And it makes using GPG encryption really straightforward.
I can sign my messages really simply.
I can decrypt and encrypt them.
It's a great piece of software.
Yeah, something tells me if you had
to go do this in the command line,
you just wouldn't do it.
I mean, maybe make my keys and stuff.
It's actually not so bad, like I suppose,
if you're just going to encrypt a text file
and then attach a text file to an email.
It's not that bad to do it from the command line,
but a whole email?
It's really crazy, that workflow.
That's why I was a little surprised to see
that Enigma is essentially, for Thunderbird,
going away with the new releases of Thunderbird.
This is interesting, right?
Because people use it a lot.
It's kind of being depended on.
It has a pretty substantial feature set.
It is a really full-featured, and sometimes
maybe overly complicated, piece of software.
But it appears that the Mozilla developers are actively
working on not just improving the old code
base of Thunderbird, but integrating encryption support
for OpenPGP directly into Thunderbird as a core feature.
Yeah, this is kind of huge.
I'm excited about it.
Yeah, I am too.
I think it's good.
I think it means more people have access to encryption.
And having it built in means that perhaps more people will
use it, so using encryption becomes
more of a norm, which I think is tremendously important.
But the Mozilla developers, the Thunderbird developers,
and the Enigma developer are very upfront about the fact
that the stuff that's going to be built into Thunderbird
will be nowhere as feature-complete as to what
Enigma could do.
Yeah, although Patrick Brunschwig,
the maintainer of Enigma, makes a good point here.
But in my eyes, this is by far outweighed by the fact
that OpenPGP will be part of Thunderbird,
and no add-on and no third-party tool will be required.
And that's probably worth it, right?
If you need more features, I'm sure new add-ons
will spring into existence.
And well, go make a PR against future Thunderbird.
Yeah, Enigma itself won't be moving forward.
They write that the new API is just nowhere as feature-rich
as the old web extensions API that they
could use to create extensions, and there's just
less stuff they can do now.
But overall, it makes Thunderbird
a more secure product.
Yeah.
Patrick's going to continue to support and maintain
Enigma for Thunderbird 68 until six months after Thunderbird
78 comes out, and will also continue
to support Enigma for Postbox, which is running
on a different release schedule.
What do you think, Wimpy?
Could the team pull it off?
Could they get you to switch back to Thunderbird?
No.
Never?
Interestingly, there was a period
at which I had Thunderbird and Evolution installed
on my machine whilst I was evaluating Evolution.
And I had a need to send a signed and also
an encrypted email.
And I chose to do it with Evolution
because that encryption integration is just better.
It's simpler, too.
Yeah, it's simpler to use.
Yeah.
So I chose to use Evolution to send
my signed and encrypted emails.
So consequently, no.
Thunderbird has served me very well for a very, very long time.
And it has been for me, and is for many people,
a staple of the Linux desktop.
But I've found a new place to manage my email,
and I'm very happy with where I've landed.
Yeah.
It is particularly straightforward and easy
to use in Evolution.
I say good on the Thunderbird project,
though, for baking this feature in.
I think your points are well taken, Wes.
We should probably just step away from the old show
here for a second.
Come here.
The cone of silence.
Don't tell anybody this.
It's so cozy in here.
I love the cone.
OK, I think we've got a problem.
I don't know if this Atari VCS is going to work out.
Do we have a problem, or do you have a problem?
Yeah, I have a problem.
Well, I mean, as the royal we as a show,
because I backed this thing for the show.
Oh, yeah, right.
I mean, not for myself.
I backed it for the show, Wes.
Oh, here we go.
Oh, Wimpy's in the cone of silence.
Yeah, so this is bad.
It looks like a designer who was contracted
to work with Atari on the VCS has told the register
that they haven't been paid going back over six months.
The consultancy has not been paid by Atari.
And he says, as a small company, they're
lucky to have survived this long.
Because it's been rough, Wes.
Yeah, I mean, if you don't have dollars coming in,
how are you supposed to keep working?
Here's the concern I have.
This launch of this retro console
that looks like the old Atari running Linux that's supposedly
going to have the ability to run other operating
systems on it as well, it's already late at this point.
And it's also listed as one of the three operational goals
for Atari in 2019, 20, and 2020, along adding more games
to their portfolio.
But it's not here.
And they're not paying their bills.
And it's running super late.
And the more delayed it gets, the more Raspberry Pi can do.
And it's just getting more and more embarrassing in all
of the ways.
So what's your bet?
Am I getting my Atari VCS ever, do you think?
I don't think so.
No, never.
It's not evident.
You think never?
Never.
Yeah, I agree with Wes.
Now, the next question is, will you be refunded?
No.
You don't think I'm even going to get
a piece of crap hardware?
No, I didn't think this three years ago.
I thought it would be delayed.
I mean, I thought it would be.
I'm like, actually, one of the reasons I backed this,
I'm like, well, this is going to be a story.
So that part has been working out.
Yeah, it's definitely become a story, that's for sure.
But I think it's interesting, too,
where some people that have worked on the project that
have chosen to remain anonymous have basically
said that the executives have no clue what's
going on, that they wanted to build a Linux-based OS,
but it may not be, that they were trying
to sign a deal with Walmart.
But Walmart wanted them to be under the $250 price point,
so they just pull four gigs of RAM out of the machine,
that they show up to a game conference with empty shells
with no hardware in them.
I don't know.
I mean, it's all adding up to be pretty sketchy.
Yeah, that is sketch.
Well, I congratulate them.
Congratulations, Atari.
You are continuing on in a long tradition of hardware
fundraisers, and we appreciate you
keeping that culture alive, keeping it strong.
And I would love to be proved wrong.
I would also love to be proved wrong.
I would love at least a little piece of hardware,
a little something, a little retro-looking piece
of hardware that I could play video games on.
Godspeed.
Godspeed to you.
I hope you guys are wrong.
Jeez.
All right, let's change gears, do a little housekeeping here.
We just released a, I don't know,
I wouldn't call it a breakdown so much,
but maybe like a guide to reverse proxy.
I was going to say just like a nerd out,
because we were all pretty excited to talk about it.
Yeah, that's true.
Yeah, thank you for joining us.
So Wes, Alex, and myself got together for a Jupiter Extras
on how we do reverse proxy, when we use NGINX,
when we use traffic, and how it all works with containers.
Yeah, why you might need a reverse proxy at all.
Plus, we talk about a bunch of really great applications
and little tricks and tools for updating your Let's Encrypt
certificates and your dynamic domain, or your IP
if you've got a domain name, and all these little tools
we use to do our own sort of fundamental hosting
of reverse proxy.
So go check out xers.show slash 19 for that.
It's 28 minutes long, and hopefully you
kind of will walk away with a pretty good concept of how
it all works.
And something we use quite a bit in production.
We have traffic now on two different systems
in production, and Wes Payne's making me a convert.
I was an NGINX man.
Yeah, I mean, I'm looking forward
to playing with version two a little bit more,
so I'm sure we'll be talking about it again.
I should mention as well, with that xers.show release
we did of reverse proxies, we have another one coming out
that is all about the basics of containers, what
it is at a fundamental level, and some things
you need to know about them.
No hype, no sales, it's just Alex and I doing a breakdown
of how containers work.
That'll be coming out in the xers feed as well.
And then later this week, selfhosted.show,
my home network for under $200.
How I set up my whole home network for under $200.
That's in there.
That's coming out in self-hosted this week.
And then, of course, I should mention
we're going to be in Texas.
Tomorrow.
Tomorrow, and this weekend as the show comes out.
So if you're in San Antonio, going
to make it to Texas Cyber Summit, or just in that area.
Come say hi to us.
Come say hi.
There will be a barbecue Thursday night,
or Wednesday night?
Wednesday night.
Which?
6 PM local time, I believe.
Yeah, you and I will just be landing around then.
So we may not make it to the very end
if we make it.
But there will be a barbecue going.
Cheesy.
You'll probably try to make it to most of that,
I would imagine.
Oh, yeah.
I'll be there for sure.
I hear that the cake is not a lie.
It will, in fact, be there.
So come help us celebrate the un-birthday for Elle and Allie
and just kind of get together and hang out.
I think we have something like 30,
33 people so far signed up for that meetup.
People don't say no to barbecue.
Never do.
You don't say no to barbecue.
And Carl has vetted the barbecue for us.
So we know it's good.
I love that.
All right.
There you have it.
That's what you need to know about.
Moving right along now.
We, well, really me, had a situation
that was particularly challenging to solve.
In my home network, I am afflicted by double net.
We all have it from time to time, every now and then.
Maybe you're in a hotel.
Maybe you're going somewhere that's
off of your regular beaten path.
And you wind up, even though you tried your best,
in a double net situation.
And you've got kind of a complicated setup.
I mean, you've got a mobile home, right?
Right.
So I frequently find myself in the double net.
Now, just a brief explanation of what I mean there.
When I say double net, I mean that my internet connection
is getting a 192.168.1.something address
as if it were on a LAN.
That is the quote unquote public address
that my router is getting.
So you've got that from your ISP regardless.
Yeah, so I'm on a 192.
And then my LAN's also on a 172.16.0.0, whatever.
So I have a net just for a day.
So it's net all the way down.
This makes accepting inbound connections
essentially impossible.
I can't SSH into my LAN.
I can't VPN into my LAN because of this double net situation.
It's the worst.
Yeah, no just easy open up a port on your firewall
and call it a day, right, that you don't have access to that.
Right.
But I demand, I demand full remote access, Wes.
The goal I wanted was to connect the studio network
and my home network together.
So when sitting on either LAN, I could access systems
from the other LAN.
Right.
I mean, you've been, as people following self-hosted, well,
no, you're doing all kinds of fun stuff,
hosting things on all manner of gadgets.
You've got your RV just automated and wired up to the nines.
Yeah, this upcoming self-hosted episode
goes into some of that.
There's a lot of ways you can solve this.
Tink VPN is something we've talked about.
Sure, open VPN is very popular.
I suppose at the end of the day, you
could really just do it with a SSH tunnel.
Sure.
There's also a lot of services out there
that will sort of forward those ports along for you
and give you a port on their public IP address.
But that's not really the spirit of what we wanted to do.
Right, right.
I wanted to solve this using some open source software,
built-in stuff to Linux.
We could have used open VPN too, but we
wanted to mess around with WireGuard
because it was a great opportunity
to learn what it's capable of and what it's not capable of.
And there's some infrastructure that you
have to build yourself when you're using WireGuard
that you might not with other solutions.
So a quick recap.
WireGuard is a new type of VPN connection
available for Linux that right now
uses some very clever crypto called Zynk,
but sounds like possibly in the future
we'll use the standard crypto that's in the Linux kernel.
It creates a new interface on your box, a new network
interface.
Shows up like any old interface, like eth0, now you've got wg0.
Yep, like just another interface.
And you can up and down that interface.
When it's up, your VPN is established.
And you can interact with it like you would
any other interface on your system.
It's so great that way.
Another nice thing about it is it's just minimal and clean
and fast.
And unlike some other options like open VPN, say,
there's not as much complicated, stateful tracking
of connection status because all the cryptography handles it.
And you just basically are shoving encrypted packets
at a host.
That host that's receiving it knows that if it can read that,
it's got a big map of allowed IPs
and which keys can send from those IPs.
And it just handles it.
So instead of having to make sure that your VPN's restarted
correctly, if you've got your interface up
and you have an internet connection,
WireGuard's going to figure it out.
Now, the other thing that it does really well
is it bounces back.
WireGuard can get knocked down, but it gets back up
every single time.
And this is particularly useful in an RV that's
going down the road that sometimes will have connectivity
and sometimes will not.
Sometimes I'll be parked in a national park that
has no wireless signal for miles.
And then when I get back into civilization,
I just want things to kind of pick back up and start
working again.
No futzing.
WireGuard's really good at that, too, a fault.
We had even bit Wes today as we were setting some of this up.
Yeah, we've been testing things out.
So last night, I was working on some of this.
And I VPNed into the studio from home.
And of course, forgot to town that interface.
And then we're doing some troubleshooting.
And I'm realizing, I can't ping that host.
What's happening?
It's working on your machine.
And of course, I was routing through WireGuard
because it had just magically bounced back.
It reconnected.
And it just does that.
And that's one of the aspects that I really want
in this particular kind of setup.
The idea being that when I do have connectivity,
I can traverse both lands with ease,
as if there is a connection persistently through them.
Right.
I mean, you might be doing a show, let's say,
remotely from the rig.
And you want to come in and be able to mess with the mixer
like you're on the local network.
The other reason why I really want to do this
is I'm trying to not expose any public ports on my homeland.
So there's no inbound connections
other than an outbound WireGuard connection.
So I have an outbound WireGuard connection
on a Raspberry Pi in my RV that runs Raspbian.
And then on there is Docker, which is running PiHole.
So this is essentially my network services Pi.
And on there, I have a persistent WireGuard connection
back to the studio.
The neat thing about it is WireGuard
is pretty clever on how it routes traffic.
It's pretty intelligent about that.
Yeah, you have all kinds of options,
especially if you're using some of the nice like the WG
quick script that comes with the WireGuard tool set.
As long as you've given it the right information
about what IP ranges are in play,
it's going to run a lot of the right IP tables
commands for you.
So you don't have to worry so much about that.
Yeah, that is really nice.
I really appreciate that.
And with a little bit of extra clever DNS trickery,
we've got this thing working pretty well.
So let's talk about a couple of the things
we had to do to actually make this work.
So we have an outbound connection from my RV
coming into the studio.
From a box here in the studio, just any one of these computers,
I can now access the systems in my RV.
How did we make that possible?
We had to do a bit of routing trickery,
a little bit of DHCP trickery, and a little bit of DNS.
But at the end of the day, once you know what to do,
it's only about maybe a half hour's worth of work.
Yeah, so once we've got our WireGuard VPN network,
it's got its own IP space.
And then there's an IP space for the studio,
and there's a different IP space for your network at the RV.
So basically, we just had to make sure
that both sides knew about the other one.
So somewhere you need to add a route entry that says,
oh, if you want to get to space A,
here's the machine to do it, whether that's the Pi
or whatever gateway box we've got here.
For the most part, depending on how you set it up,
WireGuard will handle that, or you
may need to add a routing entry somewhere
if you don't have that pushed from your gateway.
So in your RV, we're using DNS mask on the Pi hole, which
is kind of great, and added a little bit of extra config
that basically tells anyone who's pulling a DHCP lease
that, oh, hey, there's this additional network,
and to get to it, well, use me as a gateway.
We didn't quite have that option here at the studio
for really some boring reasons.
So we've just added some manual routes for the moment
to machines that need access back to your RV,
and that works just the same.
Yeah.
And so every device at the RV knows how to route back here,
but only select systems in the studio
can route to the RV, which I kind of prefer anyways.
Yeah.
I mean, my laptop doesn't need access.
No.
And you know how to do it if for some reason
I needed your help with something,
so it's not like it's not a possibility.
And then we also used DNS mask to put some nice names to all
these different IP addresses.
Yeah.
I mean, since we were already using Pi hole,
and then took the opportunity to deploy another Pi hole here
at the studio, and it's using DNS mask under the hood,
it's just so easy to add that stuff, right?
So we just added an extra file where
we defined some new hosts entries
and statically add them for any of the ones we care about.
And that file, it just looks like a host file,
you just put the machine and the IP in there, and done.
It's really easy.
And now all the machines that get that from the DHCP server
can query that.
Now they can talk to each other by machine name.
And we have created, essentially,
a little two-way tunnel using WireGuard
that involves no inbound connections to my homeland.
Right.
It's nice that way, so that as long as you've
got internet connection, well, WireGuard's
just going to go build up a tether right here
to the studio.
And of course, what we may want to do down the line
is add a few other redundant connections.
We've got some VPSes out there in the cloud,
and we could add some there too, so that as long as your RV's
got connection and not all of our machines are down,
you're going to have a backdoor in.
Westpane, you're always watching my backdoor.
Now we also decided to play around,
and really this is how this all got kicked off,
to tell you the truth, with a tool called Subspace.
Not only does it have a bad ass name,
but it is a very elegant, simple-to-use WireGuard VPN
server GUI.
Yes, friends, it's a graphical front end to WireGuard.
It's called Subspace, and it has a couple of catches.
It really wants to own the box it's on.
Yeah, so this is coming from portal.cloud.
It's open source.
It's MIT-licensed and mostly based in Go.
And if you're just running this as a machine,
you want to have some VPS that you're
going to connect a whole bunch of other devices
to when you want to sort of form a VPN that way, it is great.
Especially if you don't want to customize any of your configs,
Subspace works very well.
Yes, I'll also just add a little side note here.
When I was messing around with Subspace,
I noted that Lin Note has a community image that's
ready to go with WireGuard all pre-installed.
WireGuard is not hard to set up on pretty much all major
distros, because there's so many great guides.
But there are now some VPS images
that are one-click deployments with WireGuard ready to go.
And then you could just throw a Subspace on top of it,
and you're done.
Yeah, I mean, we were just running it from a container.
But since it's Go, I'm sure you could
find all manner of ways of running that.
Yeah, it's going to give you a UI to manage devices,
to manage keys.
And while we didn't test this aspect of it very much,
because we didn't require this, it
may also do some easy name resolution for devices
that are on the VPN IP space.
Yeah, it turns out it's also running DNS mask,
and then adding host entries for as you add them,
configuring them, and giving access to your VPN.
And that's really where Subspace shines.
The kind of trickiest part about WireGuard often
is managing all the keys that you have to keep track of,
especially once you've got, say, five, six, 10, 20 machines.
With Subspace, you've got them all there as a list.
And you, as the administrator, can go download those configs,
modify them, mess with them if you need to.
Now, unfortunately, you're going to have to do that manually.
And this is where some of the limitations of Subspace
comes in.
It seems to me like a project ripe for some community
involvement, because right now, it hasn't been updated
in a couple months, and sort of seems like it's probably just
tossed over as an open source contribution, which is great.
I don't mean that as a bad thing.
It just means it doesn't have a lot of customization built in.
Yeah, it's made by a VPS provider
to just create something that's easy for their customers
to use.
And I think it is very much sort of like,
here's the open source version of it.
However, it's so fantastic, a little bit of love,
and it could be perfect.
In our testing, I can't remember how long.
I want to say 10 seconds is how long
it took me to get a WireGuard VPN created and connected
on an iPhone.
Yeah, I just sent you the URL and the password,
and you were in.
It's so good, because Subspace will create a QR code that
contains all the config info you need for the WireGuard
VPN on the client.
So as fast as my phone could read the QR code,
my VPN configuration was set up.
I tap in my iPhone pin code once to add it to the network stack.
And at the network level, I can now WireGuard VPN
from my frickin' iPhone.
That's what's so great about WireGuard.
I mean, one of the many things that's so great, really,
is that the mobile clients have really come a long way.
Even on iOS, what feels like it should
be a pretty foreign platform to WireGuard,
those apps are rock solid.
So Subspace is killer when you're just
trying to create something that's really easy for end
users to consume as well.
Family members that you want to give remote VPN access
to your LAN, maybe you have, like for me,
my notes now are on my LAN.
They're offline, and I use WireGuard.
Just I leave that persistently connected when I'm not home,
and I just access everything as if I were there.
And so it's such a great tool.
Cheesy, I think you happen to be playing with WireGuard
over the weekend, too.
Yeah, so my use case is a little different.
I wasn't necessarily trying to connect to LANs.
I just wanted something that whenever I was traveling,
I could easily connect through a VPN
and kind of tunnel my traffic through and stuff.
And I connected to a private VPN provider.
In my case, I'm trying out VPN AC.
There are a ton of different ones out there,
though I will say that it seems to be the least supported
option WireGuard does compared to OpenVPN.
So you might end up paying a little bit more for it.
But I found that it was less expensive for me
to buy a yearly subscription than what it would cost me
to run the cheapest Linode.
Yeah, it is kind of expensive if you're only
using a VPS for WireGuard.
You could do something like this and get just a hosted service.
Were you worried, though, about privacy or security
implications of connecting to a third party VPN versus one
that you have a little more direct control over?
Well, absolutely.
I mean, that's always a concern.
But I felt that given the use case,
I think it's going to work fine for me.
I'm not overly paranoid about it.
You're more thinking like in the hotel scenario
and you want to protect your traffic
and you're not so worried about the other end.
Exactly.
I wouldn't necessarily be opposed
to using a hosted WireGuard service provider.
I think I heard NordVPN does it.
Yeah, more and more are.
Actually, I had an existing account
with one of the providers.
And I saw the other day, they have WireGuard support.
Let's go around the horn in the mumble room.
Does anybody in the mumble room want
to volunteer a rough overview of how they do a VPN solution
if they have one?
I'm sure not everybody does.
But someone there must be using a VPN for something.
Well, in fact, I have one.
I have a little dacha, so I mean a little apartment
in the Alps, in the stress Alps.
So I have direct access to this router.
But it's using internal router software.
It's a Fritz box.
I don't know if you know these in the United States.
But they have good VPN solutions.
Cool.
So you can directly access this router.
And from then, you can access whatever you want.
You know, I wouldn't be surprised if, for a lot of people,
the answer is don't use a VPN, but just use SSH.
Because you'd be surprised what you
can get away with with port 40 and whatnot with just SSH.
What about you, Wimpy?
Do you have any remote login solutions?
I mean, you travel a lot these days.
You must, every now and then, wish
you could get back to your LAN.
Yes, I do have VPN running.
I've got VPN running on a Raspberry Pi that
is NATed through my router when I need
to get to my home network.
Very nice.
So you're using the Pi.
And do you find it to be sufficiently fast enough,
even with the network limitations and whatnot
of the Pis?
Yeah, once the key negotiation is out of the way,
it's perfectly fast enough.
Because I'm usually just wanting to SSH in.
I'm not wanting to stream video or anything like that.
Sure, right.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, fair enough.
What about you, Carl?
Do you have any remote access solutions
when you're on the go?
Yes, sir.
I'll use SSH tunnels pretty regularly.
I just got used to it for my day job.
And it's just my go-to now.
Yeah, I think that's probably, if somebody wanted a hot take,
I'd say don't use a VPN.
Use an SSH tunnel.
You know, one nice thing about doing it,
the way you're doing it now too, is sort of the dynamic DNS
stuff, well, it doesn't really matter as much,
because you're not going that direction.
Right.
The connections, they all start from the RV,
which is great, because that's where the connectivity is
going to be the most hit and miss.
There could be days where there's no connectivity.
It's funny, as we were sort of testing this out,
both on the RV and here at the studio,
setting up those SSH tunnels just as back doors
in case we messed something up, that was handy more than once.
Yeah, yeah.
One time, we couldn't get into the WireGuard server.
So it was nice to get into another machine on the LAN.
And then until the WireGuard tunnel was up from the RV,
we had really no way into the RV other than an SSH tunnel.
So I just was able to connect out, in that case,
to a machine that we share.
And then we came back in over that machine.
But there are a lot of different ways
you can pull these tricks off.
Even if you, like me, suffer the plague of double NAT,
there is a solution out there for you.
And a WireGuard may be it.
An SSH tunnel may be it.
And the other options out there, like OpenVPN and others,
are still perfectly viable.
Wes and I just, we think you're going
to be hearing a lot more about WireGuard
over the remainder of this year and early next year.
I think it's going to be a pretty big story as it gets
merged into the Linux kernel.
Yeah, there's already so much support, right?
I mean, we were able to get it working on a Raspberry Pi.
It took a little bit of doing here and there.
But we got it to work.
There's already devices out there
that have WireGuard support, routers that you can find.
So there's all kinds of gadgets.
And once it's mainline, I'm sure there'll be more.
We had a really brief but great opportunity
to just have a quick email exchange
with the developer of WireGuard as we
were doing some of the preparation for this project.
And it's hard to read much into just a quick couple of emails.
But Jason seemed really, really accommodating
to our questions, really clear spoken, and really engaged.
Like, he was right on answering the stuff.
He gave us really clear, concise answers to our questions.
And I just sat there for a moment
thinking, how awesome is this?
At the end of it, I said, thank you for WireGuard.
Just thank you, because it's such a great project.
And then to also have him answer our questions,
we're just a couple of yokel podcasters.
Yeah, he's very active, giving presentations.
And if you're more curious, too, there's
a WireGuard mailing list that you can follow.
Stay tuned for updates.
Yeah, there will be updates coming.
He said to us that there'll be some more significant
developments over the next week or two,
and to keep an eye out for that.
Oh, boy.
Yeah, I think you will be hearing a lot more about it.
And I am elated with the setup now.
It's so slick to be sitting on either LAN
and be able to get access to everything on either side
from any machine.
And I think it's kind of just enough.
WireGuard integrates so nicely with the rest of Linux.
It plays nicely with IP tables, and the IP route to package,
and all the modern Linux networking stuff.
Plus, since you don't have some demon running somewhere,
if you're not touching it all the time,
it's just simpler to administer.
And I think that's something that will give it staying power.
So I'm glad you said that, because I
think that maybe was the unspoken piece that we haven't
really made clear, is what makes it so great
is it's just enough VPN.
And then it works with all of the other things on Linux
that you're used to working with.
So even an old blockhead sysadmin like me
is able to work with something relatively brand new,
because I understand default routes, DNS, IP tables.
I get that stuff, and all of that is applicable here.
That's so great.
And that, you're right.
It's just enough VPN.
And it's that perfect Unix philosophy,
where it's the right tool for the right job,
and it doesn't do too much more than that.
And we love it.
Anyways, enough fawning, I suppose,
because we have an app pic this week
that Wes Payne built just for us.
He set up a container even for it.
It is truly something that the internet's been demanding.
Spotify on the command line.
Finally, ladies and gentlemen, you
can have a Spotify UI written in Rust on your command line.
Oh my, let's just come on now.
I know, you've been laying awake at night thinking to yourself,
life is great, except I can't run
Spotify on the command line.
So why did you have to create a entire build environment?
Well, right now the release binaries
they've got over on GitHub are only supported on Mac OS.
And since this is Linux unplugged,
that wasn't going to fly.
I know you're shocked to hear this,
but on the current setup on this laptop,
I didn't have the Rust build chain already installed.
So what do I do but pull down a container?
So there's a Rust build environment container?
Yeah, of course, an official one even.
I love it.
So then you just use Cargo, the excellent build tool,
install the package.
And again, since it's Rust, I just
copied the built binary out of the container
onto my local system.
Yeah, once it's built, you're done.
Good to go.
Why don't they just do that then?
Well, if you're developing on a Mac,
you have to set up a Linux build server.
And it's a little bit more work.
What they had to do is they could download this container.
Oh, that's a great idea.
Now one little catch here, it has a great little introduction
to help you go through the create an app,
and you have to get the token and the secret
so you can off do it.
And apparently, somehow I actually
signed into your account.
That's amazing.
Yeah.
I'm also not clear in that I'm just trying this now,
it seems like it's actually used to control another device.
So when I loaded it up, it gave me like.
You were controlling the soundboard machine.
Yeah, the soundboard machine, or I can control it
running on an Echo, say.
Yeah, that's Spotify Connect right there, yeah.
So I don't know how that happens since that's
on your own machine, but it's great.
And yeah, so the thing is, we were thinking,
wouldn't it be fun just to have, again, some sort of device,
like a Raspberry Pi or something that's just sitting around
with this always going, and then you just
could turn on the speakers when you want to listen or not.
And I love a nice terminal user interface like this.
It feels so clean, I don't have to mess with anything else,
and it's right there in a terminal,
which I always have open.
Can I admit something?
Yeah, oh, please do.
To me, that terminal UI, this end curses style layout,
is easier for my brain to process and understand
than the actual Spotify UI.
That is clean and simple and well delineated.
I can understand all of that just
by glancing at the screen.
You know what's also great?
You can use the arrow keys, or it's got VI style movements,
too, right?
It's fantastic.
OK, all right, there you go.
There you go.
I'm glad you got that in there.
So we'll have a link to that in the show notes,
linuxunplugged.com slash 322 if you want to build it,
if you have a Rust build environment and want to build it.
I want to make it clear, it's not ready to go out of the box,
unless you're on a freaking Mac, and then
apparently it's just a brew away.
What kind of, I'll tell you what.
Next week on macOS Unplugged.
All right, well, we're going to wrap up here,
so Mr. Payne and I can go pack.
If you're going to be in the San Antonio area,
do come say hi to us.
Otherwise, we're back next week.
We're just down there for the weekend,
so it doesn't really impact the show production at all,
other than Wes won't be doing headlines.
No, we've got some fill-in, so.
And I'm not doing headlines.
No.
Neither one of us are doing headlines for the rest of the week.
We're done for the week, woo-hoo.
If you haven't checked out the new daily podcast,
linuxheadlines.show, it is a breakdown of the day's news
events at Linux and open source in under three minutes.
Yeah, if you don't want to go troll hacker news
and find out all the things that are happening in the world,
we'll do it for you.
There is a really fair amount of research analysis
that goes into that.
We have a team member, and that is their job.
Yeah, we're tracking trends, making
sure we follow up on things.
It's not one of our on-air people.
It's just somebody who's dedicated to that task
and puts a lot of work and research into the headline show.
Our staff in the newsroom.
That's right, we have a newsroom now.
All right, so we do this show live like next week over jblive.tv.
We do it on a Tuesday.
We'd love to have you here.
Oh, please join us.
Yeah, we've got the virtual lug you can hang out in.
We've got the chat room, or you can just sit back and watch.
But there's a lot more show.
There's probably about an hour or more
show if you join us live at the beginning and at the end.
jblive.tv, Tuesday, 2 PM Pacific.
Or get it converted at jubilabroadcast.com.
Or you want audio only, jblive.stream.
That's right.
Got to mention, too, that's also a really nice low latency
way to listen, jblive.stream.
Go check out West, techsnap.systems.
I'm at Chris Elias, the network at Jupiter Signal.
Go find the Ubuntu podcast, too, ubuntupodcast.org.
Yeah, do that.
And go get Mr. Cheesy at Cheese Bacon.
That's right.
All right, everybody.
See you next Tuesday.
Thanks for watching.
Minimac, you were pointing out that Spotify app looks a lot like another famous command
line music app.
Well, it was Cheese Bacon that pointed that out, but I'm using Seamus.
Oh yeah, okay.
It is much easier for my muscle memory to look for songs because just slash and then
you do some letters and then you get the songs you want.
That's so nice.
It's so easy.
It is so easy and it's so fast, you know?
Have we mentioned Seamus before on the show?
I don't know that we have.
I guess you did.
I'm going to put a bonus link in.
You know, you even have GTK3 integration when it comes to notification and everything.
You can just launch Seamus in a terminal and then you get notifications for song change
and everything.
I'm putting a link to that in the show notes.
That looks great.
By the way, I have a question about that Spotify tree.
Do you have to be registered for that or can you just use it later?
And do you have all the ads still or you got to have a token, so you have to have an account.
Yeah, I had to go create like a new client.
Yeah.
And I think the ads are added in line to the audio stream itself.
Oh, okay.
I see.
Mm hmm.
That's how they get you.
Seamus is definitely an app pick.
You have to look if you just have on because Seamus is really great.
I didn't mention this in the show, but I've kind of in the last three weeks, four weeks
kind of started reevaluating how I'm doing my music and I think I'm going to do more
local music.
What?
More all or do it.
I'm going to try to just do all flack local music.
All flack even?
If I'm going to go local, right?
I've got a couple of different areas where I can, I have speakers where I can really
tell the difference.
And I'm like, well, if I've got two areas that I spend a fair, one of them is my car
and I spend a lot of time in my car, I can really hear the difference in the car speaker
system.
So why not?
Why not?
Right.
And I'm just going to, I'm not going to rush.
I'm just going to take my time.
I'm going to listen to music, not waste a bunch of disk space.
Cause really there's like a, you know, you have a hybrid approach.
You have a streaming plan account and you have access to all this cloud music.
So you just start collecting the things that really matter to you.
I blame Alex.
You know, all this self hosted stuff.
He's really got me going there.
And now I'm loving it in the RV cause I can, I can take all this stuff with me offline
wherever I go.
You're no longer hooked on the cloud.
I am so jazzed about self hosting right now.
This perfect time to launch a self hosted show.
Tell you what.
On speakers, have you guys noticed that the, uh, uh, Alexa devices favorite distribution
is we want to, do you guys see that this week?
Yeah.
What was that?
I saw the headline go by, but what does that mean?
Well, just ask Alexa what his favorite operating system is.
All right.
Hold on.
We, okay.
You keep getting a trigger.
You keep saying, you want me to do it?
I'll do it right now.
Do it right now.
Alexa, what's your favorite operating system?
I'm glad you asked.
It's all about windows.
What?
She said it's all about windows, dude.
I just asked her and she said it's all about windows.
How dare she?
Did they change it already?
Did they already change it?
That's too funny.
I'll screw again.
All right.
Okay.
I'm going to ask her again.
You ready?
I'm going to, I'm going to, I'm sorry for everybody at home if I'm triggering your,
uh, your echo devices here, Alexa, what's your favorite operating system?
Definitely windows.
Oh man.
She's picking up all the windows.
You're running on your network there.
That's what's going on.
You know, what's interesting is she shortened the answer to it was a tighter answer this
time.
I don't want to answer this again.
Holy crap.
What's going on there, Alexa?
What's your favorite operating system?
Definitely Ubuntu.
What the hell?
Interesting.
That'll be on account of all the Ubuntu I'm running on my network and all the windows
you're running on yours.
There's probably never been a windows box on this network in the lifetime of that echo
device.
No, no.
It's reactOS.
It's just getting confused.
It's the country.
It's the country you live in.
You're in the windows country.
Oh, it's cause we're in Washington and it knows.
That's what I thought.
Yeah.
We're in Redmond town.
I don't know if all those previous tweets were UK based.
Do we have any Cupertino based friends here to check in?
Yeah.
Has anybody else got a lady tube near them that isn't in Washington that could ask?
Because somebody in the chat room asked you something.
Because what's not only weird about it to me, it's weird that she changes the answer.
That's something I've noticed they're doing more and more is she'll give you a long answer
and then she'll give you a short answer.
And then somehow if she thinks you're not very busy, she'll be like, by the way, sometimes
she does it at the wrong time.
By the way, did you know that and then she'll tell you about something else that they can
do now that they've added?
Yeah.
It's very clever.
I noticed that our family was barking orders at the echo and I felt a bit bad about that
because it felt rude.
So I started being polite and occasionally it acknowledges your politeness, which is
also a little bit creepy, but quite clever.
Like a little.
You're welcome.
Yeah.
Oh, it's no problem.
Isn't that something?
It's kind of nice.
I mean, I suppose it's all trying to increase engagement and the more human it feels, the
easier it is to talk to and the more you'll talk to it.
Ding.
Yep.
Absolutely.
They're aggressive.
The echo team is aggressive with these features.
Google is a little bit slower and Apple is glacial.
I am flabbergasted that the other lady tubes haven't ripped off whisper mode.
If you have an echo, you've got to turn on whisper mode.
It's the best thing for night times because if you whisper to it, she automatically recognizes
that you're whispering and whispers the responses back to you.
That's so smart.
Super clever.
And there's a lot of little things like that.
Like now they have celebrity voices like Samuel Jackson and they have like you can play with
Jimmy Fallon.
I assume there's a Chris Fisher voice in the works.
Nobody is making a wiretap device more appealing than Amazon these days.
I tell you what.
And it can order you packages.
Oh yeah, that too.
Oh man, I wish my craft would have been a thing.