So Rekai has a story to share with the class
that surprised me.
That it impacted the release of User Error.
And it's a significant trying times we live in, Wes,
when a problem like this exists
and no one steps up to solve it.
One man must come to the people,
must inform the people of the duty we must all take,
the R-syncs that we must all pick up,
and the scripts that must be written.
What happened, Beard?
I want to know why Ubuntu still sucks.
Oh!
Darn!
Say it!
Well, to be fair, to be fair, Debbie and Two,
I want to know why in 2017,
we do not have the ability to automatically check
and see if our mirrors are up to date.
Because I had to,
I figured out this problem later.
I had to install TeamViewer
and TeamViewer would not installed
because it was missing packages.
There's your first mistake.
That's your first problem.
Oh, I had to be that guy.
We all had to be that guy.
Well, you know, give me another easy remote desktop solution
that doesn't require forwarding ports.
I will today.
Oh.
Well, that is what I will give you today,
but except for that last part,
you will have to forward port 22.
But, so I couldn't install TeamViewer.
It was telling me that packages were missing.
I assumed it was just because packages had changed in 17.10.
But no, it turns out,
I found out completely unrelatedly later
that the mirror that had been chosen for my Ubuntu install.
So like when I installed,
because that's the install I set up.
Yeah.
I didn't change the mirrors.
I didn't change any of that stuff.
Well, whatever it defaulted to had out of date packages
because later I switched to a different mirror
for an unrelated reason and it resolved everything.
Everything was fine again.
Now, do you think this is...
Is this, do you need graphical access to the machine
or are you remotely controlling a Windows machine
or is this, is SSH enough without port forwarding?
No, it doesn't.
I need graphical access.
Do you need the desktop?
Which I have a solution for today's show,
but except for his specific scenario,
he needed the logged in sessions desktop.
Yep.
Right.
Which is definitely a little trickier.
TeamViewer's not bad.
X11.
We've talked about Splashtop before.
If you, so today what we're gonna talk about
is if you just want a remote desktop session
that you can connect to and disconnect from
and that session remains like running on the computer.
Yeah.
See, the thing about TeamViewer is I installed TeamViewer,
I logged into my account,
I clicked three boxes for unattended remote access
and then I left and I was able to connect on the other end.
So how, wait, so I gotta go back.
How did you discover that it was out of date packages?
Like I'm not clear on that.
So you came to the conclusion that the repo
hadn't like synced after 17.10 or something?
Like they just didn't have the right version
that supported Ubuntu 17.10?
It was 17.10 packages
because clearly it was getting packages from somewhere.
Yeah, that's true.
But some of the packages it was saying
are referenced but don't exist on this mirror or whatever.
And others. Oh, really?
Yeah, others.
And when I did a apt-get upgrade,
it updated a couple of packages,
but not as many as you would expect after a release.
And then later I switched to a different mirror
and I had a whole lot more updates
and it solved the missing packages for TeamViewer
because TeamViewer was like half installed.
Because it was like, you know,
it's installed but we're missing dependencies.
See, this is, we have to rally the people
because there's only one thing that can be done.
So I'm just wondering why like in the process of,
you know, checking for new packages,
why aren't they checking the freshness of a mirror?
This is your cause now.
Mirror freshness is like your mission in life
to make sure it stays fresh, I guess.
Maybe it's just easier to blame Popeye.
So I've just, yeah, sure.
And I've just posted a link that tells you
how up-to-date each of the mirrors are.
Yeah, but what I'm asking is,
why is this not part of the automatic process?
I didn't realize this could be a thing, actually.
To be honest with you, I didn't-
It usually isn't.
It typically isn't because there isn't a gigantic churn
like there is at release time
when hundreds of machines around the world
are all hitting the same machine,
trying to update at the same time.
Okay, yeah, so I see here-
I suspect you probably happen to hit
the wrong time of the year for it, and that's all.
Yeah, so it looks like there's one mirror
that's a week behind, one that's two days behind.
Most are all up to date, but yeah, this does,
this is actually a pretty good thing to know.
So that is launchpad.net slash Ubuntu
slash plus archive mirrors, plus symbol archive mirrors.
Cool, thanks, Popeye.
I'll toss a link to that in the show notes.
Sweet.
I literally had no idea that was an issue
because I just assumed these things
slowly are synced to the background,
but of course that's me being naive
about the size of the data that they're moving around.
They actually usually really quickly
are synced in the background
because they've all got stupidly fat connections
to the internet.
Yeah.
Actually, I think I ran into that
the other week as well, and then later it's like,
oh yeah, everything's there now, all right, that's fine.
You see, this is why I prefer boutique distributions
because their small user base means
that they can just download everything off a single mirror
and I don't actually have anything, I'm just making that up.
Actually, there's something to be said for simplicity
is when you've got like a giant complex arrangement
of moving parts, things can go wrong.
Well, that's why-
I mean, when no one uses your software,
it's really easy to maintain.
Or you take the Linux Mint approach
and you just outsource that extremely complicated,
massively expensive part of your infrastructure
to somebody else, you know, that's like-
Even look at like what Aiki just went through
with his upsizing.
You know, he pretty much got banged offline
with his OVH server and then he had to go hunting
for a CDN like as quick as he could.
See, I guess what I'm asking is why don't they have,
like when you do an app get update,
it checks something like a mirror freshness list
and says, hey, your mirror may be out of date,
would you like to try another mirror?
Yeah, like some sort of like-
Because vast majority of the time it's never a problem
and the mirrors are up to date and it's not an issue.
Yeah, but when it is a problem, it's a huge problem.
Like some sort of like apt update mirror or something
that would also ping mirrors and stuff like-
Well, there is.
There's a software sources thing on the Ubuntu desktop
where you press a button and it will choose
the farthest best mirror nearest to you
and all that kind of stuff.
That's very fair.
I just mean like sort of, just sort of like-
Or you could just choose the central mirror
and not use one local to you and choose the central one,
which is always up to date.
You could do that.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's one of the problems of having stuff
distributed all over the place.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 220
for October 24th, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's Linux box is being held together with bubblegum,
a little bit of duct tape and some hope.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And Beard's here.
Hello, Beard.
Hey, I'm just over here taking out your sound server
with systemd.
Someone's gotta pre-chew all the gum.
That's helpful too.
That is very helpful.
Yeah, I'm kind of like scraping a system together
as we do this show.
I'm just trying to figure out what's going on
with the systemd.
I'm scraping a system together as we do this show.
Took us about 20 minutes to get the sound board working,
but we've got that.
So what else do we need other than a great lineup,
which we have today.
We have some news we'll get into, some community stuff,
couple of follow-up stories.
The Fedora Project has a post that they'd really like you
to read and we'll give you some highlights from that.
And then I've gone and created myself, not one,
but two remote desktop solutions.
I wanted to create myself a workstation in the cloud,
completely independent and isolated from anything else
that I could get access to anywhere in the world.
And then I wanted to create a separate remote desktop system
that was on the LAN of the studio.
That could get access to our huge recording files
that has a big fat GPU and a monster six core i7 CPU,
lots of local storage.
So one system up in the cloud with incredible bandwidth,
unlimited storage that I could pay for if I want to attach
and one system local with lots of GPU compute power,
both of them running Linux using X2GO.
And we've covered X2GO before on the network.
Noah did a great how-to on it ages ago
in Linux Action Show episode 374.
And this is my take on it.
I'm gonna talk about it a little bit differently.
I'm using Ubuntu 17.10,
so we'll talk about using modern Linux distributions
to do this, how I'm doing it, what I'm using it for,
what some of the downsides are,
and how unbelievably easy it is to get set up
and how it can just really change the game.
And I'm using it even when I'm here on my LAN
and I'm connecting to systems over the LAN using this.
It's so, so great.
So I'll share my project with you
and give you a little demo of the entire thing too
later on in the show.
So stay tuned for all of that stuff.
But before we go any further,
we're gonna bring in our virtual log,
Time Appropriate Greetings Discord channel.
Hey, hey.
Hello.
Hello, guys.
Yeah, so episode 220.
We're trying out Discord for this week's episode.
And it's bumpy so far.
You know, we're just, we're giving it a go, though.
We're giving it a go.
And we got a good amount of people showing up,
so thank you, everybody, for helping us do that.
Helps really actually put it through its paces.
So let's start with some community news, Wes.
What do you say, sir?
What do you say? Please.
I noticed, by the way, before we go any further,
you're still running 17.10 on that monster.
I sure am.
You're stuck with it for the week, huh?
Yeah, it's been a lot of fun.
And Beard, your rig over there, still running 17.10.
So all three of us are stuck with it for the week.
How unusual.
Against my better judgment.
Yeah, yeah.
All right, so let's talk about the Librem 5,
which has been an ongoing story,
spiked almost every single week by some new development.
And it has come to a conclusion.
The fundraiser is over with 142% funds raised.
They raised $2.1 million.
But they're doing something interesting, too.
They're leaving the pre-orders open.
So if you still want a Librem 5,
you can pre-order one right now and still get it.
So while the fundraiser's over,
they'll still take orders for it.
Librem 5, it's funded.
Now, as we've said before, the hard work begins.
But they've just recently announced a deal with,
or I guess a partnership with Nextcloud.
So they're gonna ship Nextcloud's apps by default
on the PureOS devices and on the Librem.
They've obviously, they've talked with the
plasma mobile folks, the GNOME desktop people, the Matrix.
They've been creating this network of partnerships
with the big names in open source right now.
Not the only, but big names in open source right now.
Nextcloud is a bit of an open source celebrity project.
Matrix, again, a bit of an open source celebrity project.
GNOME and Plasma, obviously huge heavyweights
with large fan bases.
And they're all kinda coming together
on this Librem 5 thing.
Why is this the first time we're seeing this?
Why didn't we see this earlier?
I guess the time's just kinda right.
Yeah, all the projects are in the right position.
Yeah, and good enough places have had enough polished,
let's say, releases where they feel like
these kinds of things are things
they can dedicate energy to.
I don't know.
Anyways, I am surprised, to be honest with you,
that they made it this far.
I thought the goal of 1.5 million was achievable,
but a long shot, and they surpassed it.
And however this fundraiser went,
now we actually see what the results
gonna be when they ship the hardware.
Yes, this'll be the really interesting part.
Okay, well, wow, congratulations to them.
I'm really surprised.
I've also seen rumors coming out of them
that they're gonna be shipping tablets.
They wanna work on a NAS.
And of course, they've also recently announced
that they've disabled the Intel Management Engine stuff,
which we talked about on Linux Action News,
if you'd like to check that out.
But yeah, anybody in the Discord room?
Oh, that's weird.
Anybody there in the Mumble Discord thing?
Have a take on the Librem 5 funding,
or maybe a hope or a dream or a wish?
Wish upon a star for a Librem 5?
Oh, go ahead, JJ.
I saw you light up.
I don't hear you though.
It's all right.
JJ, you're excused.
I don't know that I'm ready to buy one,
but I would like to have friends and acquaintances
who have them, and you get to see them in real life.
That would be exciting for me.
Yeah, they're starting to tempt me,
but I think I'm not particularly motivated
to be an early adopter on my phone anymore.
Maybe if I didn't own a business and have kids.
Or if carrying two phones was a thing
that someone could do realistically.
But I would be willing to do it
if I started to see this thing ship
and it looked like it was a viable,
if even in an early stage, but a viable product.
I'd be willing to carry two phones for a while
as I sort of tried this thing out,
and then eventually switch over.
I could do that.
So I could be willing to get in that position eventually.
The competition is tough these days though.
I wonder if there's any angle to,
like their focus on freedom and security,
if there's any angle towards journalists
or other people who are really conscious
and really need to know what's going on with their phone.
Maybe you don't use it when you're at home in the States,
but you're traveling to Russia to do a story
and you want something that you have more control over.
And it really gives people in the open source community
who have held really, really steady to this principle
of I'm not going to use a mobile phone
because it violates either my privacy or my freedoms
or my personal views of technology.
There's a lot of reasons why people have just chosen
I'm not going to get a smartphone.
And maybe this would be a phone
that might appeal to some of them.
It's not a huge market.
It's not going to make a company millions of dollars,
but there may be a loyal customer base there
if you can make a product that actually serves them.
We'll wait and see.
It's still a lot of this stuff up in the air,
but I could see it.
I could see it.
And now that they made their funding,
I'm hoping they'll be able to ship a few.
Let's talk a little bit about Fedora
because we've been talking a lot about Ubuntu
and we still are going to talk about Ubuntu a bit more today.
We have some news, too.
But I thought, well, then we should take a moment
to talk about Fedora just to make sure we talk
about some hard work that's happening over there.
They felt that way, too.
They took to their blog over there.
This is Christian who he blogs quite a bit
about the development of GNOME.
And he took to his blog right around the release of Ubuntu
in 1710 and said, well, let's take a look
at where Fedora's coming from and where it's going.
And so he says, while we're putting the touches
on the final finishing touches on Fedora 27,
I'll try to look back at everything we've achieved
since Fedora Workstation was launched with Fedora 21.
So we're going back to about Fedora 21.
This blog is about taking stock and taking some pride
in what we've achieved so far and major hurdles
that we've passed along our way
to improve the Linux desktop experience.
First one on this list, Wayland.
We've been the biggest contributor
since we joined the effort, he says.
But lib input is another area
we think we've made a big difference.
GLVND, which deals with multiple OpenGL devices.
Porting Firefox GTK3, Google Drive integration.
Flatpak gets a mention.
Could come back to that in a minute.
The Linux firmware service, GNOME software,
MP3 and AC3 support and AAC support landing in Fedora.
And a few other things like working
with some improved touch support,
Nautilus improvements, the nightlight mode in GNOME
that makes it a little easier on the eyes after the sun sets.
And some other GNOME shell improvements.
And of course, one of my favorites,
GNOME Builder and PipeWire have been projects
they've worked on, including other ones
that are important specifically to Fedora,
like Fleet Commander and a few other things.
It's actually a pretty impressive list.
I have the entire thing linked in the show notes.
And I thought, you know what, it is fair.
It is fair to take a moment and say,
Ubuntu 17.10 was a really great release.
And it's because they're able to stand on the shoulders
of what the GNOME 3 community has been building now
for years and years and years.
If 17.10 had launched when GNOME 3 was new,
and they were shipping GNOME 3 years and years ago,
it would have been a train wreck of a release.
Oh yeah, definitely.
So yeah, I thought, okay, fair enough.
At first I was giving them a hard time
for kind of doing a me too post
right around Ubuntu 17.10's release.
I was like, oh, come on Fedora.
It's okay, we haven't forgotten about you guys.
But then I read that list and I'm like,
damn, that is a list, that is a really great list.
Like the Linux Vendor Firmware Project,
you know that's a personal favorite of mine.
LibInput has made a huge improvement
for using trackpads under GNU slash Linux.
And of course, it's really important for going to Wayland.
Yeah, the list really cements the feeling I have like,
well, I may not use Fedora desktop
on a lot of workstations I actually have.
They just do a lot of really important backend work
that you don't necessarily appreciate.
Circling back to Flatpak, I've been trying to take stock.
You know, Flatpak's had a couple of delays in Fedora
for where they wanted to be at right now.
So I'm like, where's the adoptions?
We've had a lot of conversations about Snap,
a lot of people talking about Snaps.
So what metric do you measure success, right?
Well, I have a metric that perhaps we could use.
The piracy metric, porn and piracy, what are they using?
Which Universal Linux packaging format
are the pirates using?
And it appears to be so far, Flatpak.
Hey, yo.
Yeah, pirates are now packaging Windows games with Flatpak
because they can bundle like a little wine
or DOSBox runtime in there.
Like they've got like this whole way
to distribute Windows games on Linux now using Flatpaks.
So here's your use.
Open source for the win.
And on the Waraz site,
because you know, on these platforms
where all your stuff is commercial
and you got to pay for everything,
this is like something that's like a huge market,
like stealing software.
Like the open source community,
we don't even have to worry about this.
It's just in our repos, but here, you know,
they have to describe what you're getting.
So they say Flatpak is a new package management system
built for simple universal single click installations,
games that just work neatly stuffed in a locked sandbox.
It's perfect for them.
So there you go.
Flatpak, the choice of Windows software pirates
for games on Linux around the world.
If that's not a niche market, I don't know what is.
Year of the pirate Linux desktop?
I'm not sure.
I mean, if you think about it though, you know,
you download a Flatpak
and you just have a full wine setup all done for you.
Right, I know.
It could be the choice for Linux pirates.
It's kind of like what,
it's kind of like a shades of what Ikey's working on
with the Linux Steam integration project,
but for just one specific game.
So when are actual game developers
gonna start releasing games in Flatpak?
Right, right, or, you know, it seems like app images
would make a lot of sense for game developers.
And I could see snaps too,
especially if you wanna make it easy on people.
But what about the maintainers?
What about the distro maintainers?
Let's talk about maintainers for a moment.
Wes found this really interesting piece
over on snowyman.com, manipulating maintainers.
And he says the alternative title really could be
how to get members of any open source community
to be interested in helping you,
but manipulating maintainers is a catchier title.
It sure is.
And he makes a core point right here
at the beginning of the piece
that really smacked me in the face.
And it's, God, is this not true?
It's so true in Linux podcasting,
quote unquote, Linux media space too.
He says there's an old ha ha, only but serious joke.
If you go to a Linux forum
and you ask for help fixing your wifi driver,
everyone will ignore you.
If you instead say, Linux sucks,
you can't even get wifi to work,
then thousands of people
will try to solve the problem for you.
So if you just say Linux sucks, it can't get wifi,
all of a sudden everybody wants to help.
But if you say, I need help with wifi, nobody helps.
This story is a great example of manipulating people,
but it's obviously a negative take on it.
I'd like to share some thoughts on this
from a much more positive standpoint,
which will help you get people to pay more attention,
be more helpful, and perhaps most importantly,
create a healthier open source community overall.
And he touches on core points
to getting involved with open source communities,
like don't waste people's time,
demonstrate that you've actually
tried to solve your problem.
That's a huge one, yeah.
Help other people, don't be rude,
and he gives examples of what might come across rude
and what you could maybe say instead.
And I know some of this sounds like basic stuff,
but it's a good read, it's insightful.
Say thank you, admit if you're new,
offer to help, and maybe consider giving money.
It's not a universal, and to be clear,
don't necessarily think they're asking for it,
but sometimes people just need a little cash
to help make something a priority.
I think that example at the top really just shows
that here we're talking about motivations.
I know for me, all right, so you respond in anger,
someone's dissing your favorite OS,
and you're like, well, I'm gonna show them,
yeah, it's super easy.
You're just responding, and it's not the interaction
any of us want, and it's not really the solution here,
but you're not thinking about,
I know I've certainly seen requests for help,
and when they're vague, you're like, well, I just don't.
You imagine all the work you're gonna be in here
trying to understand this person's problem and identifying,
and then once you've started helping,
you feel this obligation to continue helping.
That's not really so when you're just responding like,
yeah, of course Wi-Fi works, try this, right?
And so all of these tips help show
and make it more reasonable.
So if someone has a very specific problem,
you're like, oh, okay, I wanna figure out what's going on too.
I don't have to wade through the 10 steps
of introductory debugging that this person may
or may not have done.
So if you can get any of those barriers lower,
you have a much better time.
Yeah, I think it's a lot about how you approach it too.
If you come into it with sort of a, more of a, not humble,
because that makes it sound like you have to tiptoe around,
but if you come at it with,
maybe I don't have the full context
when you ask your question,
and then realize that sometimes those strong reactions too
are because you're not asking the right question,
and so people respond negatively.
And so sometimes you have to come in with the understanding
maybe I'm getting this response
because I've asked something outside the context
of where I'm supposed to ask it or something.
What about you, Beard?
You are involved in God knows how many IRC communities,
Discord chat rooms.
You must see people stumble into the rooms
and communities you hang out in all the time
and just blow it from time to time.
Yeah, I mean, basically just be nice
and don't act like you know everything,
and you'll pretty much get all the help you need.
Yeah, that's even true when you think
you're an expert on something.
I had a moment one time
where I was troubleshooting a network problem.
Table unplugged, yeah, I know.
It was close.
It was really close.
It was like a loop because I had a hub loop.
I had some sort of network loop.
Oh, yeah.
But I thought it was an ISP problem.
And so I'm talking to the tech,
and I'm like 45 minutes into it,
and I'm generally a very nice person on the phone,
maybe too nice, but I got a show I gotta do.
45 minutes into it, I start going, look, man.
All right, I've done the router reboot thing.
I've done all the little troubleshooting things you want.
Here's what, I can ping this.
I can traceroute this.
I'm just giving them all this information.
I've fixed networks for a living.
Can we just skip all this stupid bullshit
and just work on getting a trouble ticket established
for a connection issue?
And the guy's like, well,
could you just do me one more favor?
Could you go down and just check to see
if you have any hubs plugged into each other
or anything weird that could be causing
some sort of network loop?
Fine, I think to myself.
And I go down, and I check the switch.
It's fine, everything's fine.
I'm like, idiot, this guy's such an idiot.
And I'm huffing and puffing my way back up to the stairs
where I left the phone, and it crosses my mind.
Hey, dumbass, you have a little hub out
where your NAS and your Wi-Fi access point is in the garage.
That could be where your problem's at, smart guy.
And I go, oh, crap.
I walk back down the stairs, out into the garage,
and sure enough, I had a network loop,
and I had to go pick up the phone and be like,
okay, I'm sorry, yep, that did resolve the problem.
Thank you for your time.
Just stuffed this whole crow right down the gullet.
That's why I heard that, goddammit, Noah.
Yeah, yes, actually, that did happen, didn't it?
That was actually a separate time.
From that lesson I learned that's usually just Noah's fault
is actually what I learned from that.
Yeah, all right, well, that was good.
If anybody in the, oh, I see, Bashful,
you had something you wanted to jump in with.
I'd love to hear, go ahead.
That was more so earlier when you were talking
about the communities and stuff.
No, go ahead.
For example, Rika, I was saying just ask, be nice,
all that kind of stuff,
but it's also the sense of entitlement
that you have to, things like have an answer immediately
or that people are gonna be online 24 by seven
or so on and so forth.
They just expect you to be there nonstop.
Right, yeah, so that's the hard thing.
So the entitlement thing is hard
because nobody wants to be told
that they have a sense of entitlement.
Nobody wants to hear that.
So that's a real off-putting thing.
And then the second problem is nobody realizes
they have a self-entitlement problem
because they just are coming in like their time of day.
So they're up, and you sometimes don't stop and go,
well, these people might be on the other end of the world.
They might be asleep right now.
Yeah, that's actually one of the things you see
the most often in support channels
is you see somebody come in, ask a question, and leave.
Or come in, ask a question,
complain that nobody's talking, and leave.
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
And if they would just idle for a bit.
And it's all within like two minutes.
Yeah, idle for a day.
Yeah, it's just more of a perception thing
on both sides of the fence.
Like I don't mean it in sort of the point of view
that people can't expect an answer or should or shouldn't.
It's just more so both sides of the fence
need to be conscious of the fact
that there are things like time zones, availability,
families, all that other kind of stuff.
Yeah, good points.
Okay, so I would say we could make a little room
in next week's episode if anybody in the audience
has a couple that they feel like we've left out,
especially anybody involved in some open source communities
where there's something specifically on your list
that people do. Yeah, definitely.
You know, your shit list.
Let us know, leave a comment,
or go to the subreddit, linuxunpluggedatreddit.com,
and leave it on this week's episode.
And if we get a couple of good ones,
I'll carve out some time in next week's episode
to try to include those because I think it's kind of
particularly important for an open source community
when a lot of people are constantly coming in
that have never interacted with different communities,
and it's different cultures,
and different people use online platforms differently,
and people email me all the time
thinking I'm gonna respond maybe that day,
or maybe within a few days,
and sometimes it's like four or five months
before you get a response from me.
And I don't mean for it to be like that,
but that's just what happens sometimes,
and it's a stressful thing for me to go in my inbox
because I know I have a bunch of old emails
where people expected me to respond faster
because that's how they do email.
And that's the same thing.
You just have to understand that people
have different expectations for these systems.
Especially in the open source world.
All right, well before we move on,
let's mention Ting for just a moment.
My mobile service provider, oh, it's Ting.
You go over to linux.ting.com.
That'll give you $25 off a Ting device,
or maybe even better because if you can bring a Ting device,
they'll give you $25 in credit,
which will probably pay for more than your first month.
It's pay for what you use wireless.
It's really great because take Beardsley here.
He's mine?
Hey, you know, Chris, I actually have a new Ting Sim.
Ting-sponsored TwitchCon.
Oh, really?
So you just got an extra ready-to-go Sim,
like a standby Sim?
Just sitting in my room.
Yeah, that's nice.
But you know, for Beardsley, it's a great example.
So JB has a Ting account with like three lines on there,
I think, maybe even four lines,
and one of the lines we give to Beards,
so that way he has a phone where we can get a hold of him,
and he has a little device that he can use
to take over the world.
And most of the time, Beardsley's somewhere
that has Wi-Fi, almost all the time.
But he traveled to TwitchCon,
and during that time,
it'll be like a little more for service.
But if you take the fact that maybe this month,
we're gonna pay $15 more, maybe at most,
for his usage,
but you average that out over the fact
that we almost pay for nothing most of the time
when he's on Wi-Fi, it's a great deal.
There is definitely a data spike.
Yeah, and I know of at least one phone call,
because I got one.
Oh, but it's perfect for that kind of setup.
It's great for me too,
because with a little bit of planning,
I can preload my podcast for the day,
I can pin the music to my device,
and when I'm driving, I can basically use no data,
and then when I get to work, I can use Wi-Fi.
Man, it's so great, because it's nationwide.
When I travel, I use it the entire time.
They have CDMA and GSM.
There's no contracts, there's no other termination fees.
So if Beard wants to throw that SIM card
in a tablet for a couple of months,
and then decides, I'm not really ever using it,
there's no penalty to just turn it off.
You go into their dashboard, it's simple,
and you can control it there.
You can also monitor all your usage.
They have so many different devices
you can pick from or bring your own.
Like I mentioned, they have a CDMA and a GSM network,
so there's tons of options there.
Check out their blog too.
They have a blog right now about earning some side cash.
It's a little bit of extra money, whoa,
off of Google opinion rewards.
So check that out too on the Ting blog.
Start by going to linux.ting.com,
support the show, and sign up over at ting, linux.ting.com.
Let's get into the Ubuntu corner.
So we have some Ubuntu news to get to.
Yeah, as you would expect after a big major release.
And ever since the announcement
that they would be switching to the GNOME desktop,
discontinuing active development on Unity,
and restructure the company a bit,
all of us armchair analysts like myself specifically,
I'll just talk about me,
all said, ah, ha, ha, ha, here we go.
Mark Shuttleworth is refactoring the company,
getting it ready perhaps for some funding here and there,
and eventually to go public, do an IPO.
And it seems that is exactly the case.
He was interviewed over at eWeek.com.
We've got a link in the show notes by Sean.
And some interesting things were revealed by Mark.
He said that as long as we stay a private company,
we have complete discretion as to whether we,
maybe I should read this in like a more epic voice for Mark,
even though it doesn't sound like,
as long as we stay purely a private company,
we have complete discretion
as to whether we carry things
that are not commercially sustainable, Shuttleworth said.
Now what he's really saying there
is when we're a private company,
we can dump money into projects
that don't make us any money.
JB has that luxury,
a luxury which we may sometimes maybe abuse.
And as perhaps Canonical was potentially abusing,
because if you look at it from a perspective
of maybe a company that needs to make money
or a company that wants to go public, then things change.
You can't necessarily really justify that.
And then Mark goes on to say,
what you'll see at some stage soon
is that we have broken even on all the pieces
that we do commercially without Unity,
as in Ubuntu makes money,
the server stuff makes, the cloud stuff makes money,
the consulting stuff is making money,
the OEM deals are making money.
They're becoming self-sustainable.
If you go outside the Unity projects,
Unity 8, stuff like that.
At some stage after that,
we will take a round of investment,
which will be a growth round
that will be aimed at helping us become a public company
in due course.
So there you go.
Yeah, all right.
And- Big stuff in the works.
Yeah, that's what it means, basically.
There's nothing too shocking,
nothing too majorly revealed there.
It's all kind of what we speculated,
but the speculation in this case was correct.
And I think it's gonna result
in a lean, mean, canonical machine, actually.
Like, no hard feelings.
They tried it.
They did the whole, the phone thing.
They played with Unity and Mir and Go in their own way
and innovating on the Linux desktop.
Turns out that's not really what the market wants
or how things are gonna go.
And so, yeah, there's a smart pivot
back to what their core is.
He mentioned shutting down Unity
being one of the toughest things he's ever had to do.
I bet.
I'm sure, right?
I mean, there's obviously a ton of people there,
engineers, developers, designers,
everyone pouring their heart into it.
So that's hard.
And he went out specifically on a limb himself
to try to say, let's do this as the future.
And then nobody bit.
And then he's like, oh God, now I gotta own up to that.
And he did it.
JJ, you had something you wanted to say.
Go ahead.
We've had bad luck
with people being muted or something today.
There's a scoreboard.
I don't know if it's Discord or.
I think it might just be JJ.
Yeah.
Oh.
What do you got?
You got some sort of switch flipped over there, JJ.
You got like some sort of like NSA privacy screen up.
What's going on up there?
Must be using FreeBSD.
There is a.
I think he's using the lead one five, that's.
There is a video interview of Mark over on the E-Week website
if you want to see that.
The beautiful thing about Ubuntu is
we created the possibility of a platform
that's free of charge to its end users
with commercial services in mind.
In the sort of dream that might define the future
in all sorts of different ways.
And we really have seen that Ubuntu has moved
into the mainstream in a bunch of areas.
You know, you think about it
and you watch the full video on their site.
It's really good timing still for them
because the desktop thing is sort of sorting itself out.
Wes and I were just having the conversation earlier
that desktop Linux in a lot of ways
has gotten really, really, really good recently.
Like we just read that list from the Fedora project.
That's a solid list of really good stuff.
Ubuntu 17.10, all three of us are still using it
after that review.
We're like, we're actually still working pretty good for me.
And I've put it on even more systems.
And that was without, like I've hardly configured a thing.
And we have some good stuff like PipeWire in the work soon
that's gonna solve some really longstanding issues
that I've had.
You might even be able to get audio
on the machine you use for the show.
I don't know.
That's the pipe dream.
And so like that problem is sort of solving itself
because you then have OEMs that are then taking
that product that's getting pretty good.
And then they're doing the marketing,
targeting at developers and the niche market.
Yeah, they're doing the polishing
and you have same system 76 trying to do the same thing
to a greater extent with Pop!OS.
And then they can focus on the cloud and IoT
where there is a ton of traction to be gained.
And they have a pretty good in-road already.
So it does seem like they have a pretty good chance
of making this thing a money-making machine.
I gotta say it takes some big cojones to cut your losses
rather than doubling down again.
Mm-hmm, yeah.
Chris. Yes, sir.
I don't wanna reveal anything that's a company confidential
but back in April when Mark announced the end of life
of some of these projects
and it was clearly a difficult thing for him to do
with letting go a bunch of people in the canonical family.
I found it interesting that I saw a different side of Mark
very keen on the welfare of the people
who were leaving the company.
He knew that he couldn't continue to fund these things,
that it wasn't possible for us to continue developing
all these different projects
that were super interesting and cool and fun
but at the end of the day,
they wouldn't make money in the real world.
And I think he felt really terrible
having to let those people go.
And I think some people see Mark
as a very hard-headed businessman.
And when you look at how much he's financed,
not just Ubuntu but he's used a lot of his money
for other things as well, philanthropic stuff
but also other open source projects.
He's used some of that money
to fund some other distributions, not just Ubuntu.
I think it's interesting to see this news come out now
that actually it's a little sad for him
that things didn't work out.
Yeah, well, who in their right mind
creates something like a project like this?
I mean, nobody gets into this stuff
to have to make these really, really awfully hard
sucky business decisions that only business owners
or people in that position end up having to make,
people in that top role.
And it's gotta be hard to see.
These are real people who've been brought
into the whole Ubuntu ecosystem.
A lot of the people who work for Canonical then and now
are ex-community people who were hired in
because they were active in the community
and they wanted to do cool things with Ubuntu.
And there was this guy who came along
and enabled them to sit at home in their office
and work on stuff that's super cool.
And there aren't many opportunities you get in your life
to sit at home and work on something super cool with friends.
And he enabled that.
And I think it's a little sad.
And this recent interview coming out is difficult
for those of us looking back on the difficult times
back in April.
But equally, we've got a positive thing to look forward to,
which is the company is streamlined
and we're not spreading ourselves super thin
across a large number of projects that we used to.
I mean, I think a common criticism that I used to have
is they have too many projects, they're too distracted,
there's no chance they're gonna get into mobile.
And those were just common, those were criticisms
I might lob, but they were just common ones
that would be parroted.
Yeah, everyone said that.
Yeah, and I don't know, who's saying that now?
Because none of those things are true anymore.
Like the focus seems to make a lot of sense.
The end results are pretty impressive so far.
And we're not even privy to all of the ongoing back end
business deals that are profitable to Canonical
that are also a result of this work.
But they are happening and they are-
It was interesting to see Mark point out
that there are areas of the business that are profitable,
obviously as a privately held company,
he doesn't have to reveal details about how profitable
each part of the company is.
But on the road to IPO, he's going to have to reveal
some of this to potential investors in the future.
But it was interesting to reveal that something
a lot of us internally have known for a while,
that this is more profitable than people think.
Well, Canonical has, from my experience,
and this is something that was very apparent
just at the rally too, is they have a unique combo going
in that they're making the software,
they're selling the support, and the Ubuntu brand
is carrying quite a bit of weight in enterprise now.
And so a lot of big companies that are scaling out
very, very fast, you could think of large media companies
online that you know of, or just large web companies
that you know of that are scaling very fast,
perhaps they're in a growth trajectory right now.
And scaling out large data centers
is a massive time commitment.
They know that their system runs on Ubuntu,
they know that they want Ubuntu-based data centers,
but they want somebody who really knows their shit
and somebody who will keep it up to date
and running well and secure, because damn,
isn't cyber security an issue now?
And man, do we not want to have to be the ones responsible
for managing that?
Well, guess who we can call?
We call Canonical, because they're making the thing.
So now all of a sudden, Canonical's got a contract
to build out a data center, load the software,
and then maintain the software.
And Canonical can either hand the keys over to them
and say, here's your data center, or they can say,
actually, you know what, funny thing,
we don't feel like hiring 15 people,
do you guys just wanna take care of that for us?
And there are multiple ways for Canonical
to make revenue by Ubuntu being free.
And they all seem obvious, because they seem like ones
that corporate America would just totally click with.
Like that is an arrangement that would make sense
to corporate IT people, especially people
that are evaluating risk and time to get something spun up.
It's a no-brainer for them,
and that's gonna be an obvious moneymaker.
And then we know that they have an OEM program
with companies like Dell and HP,
where there's some kind of arrangement
where there's money made on machines that are sold
that also is profitable.
And so with that, we have now to look forward to 1804.
And now we are almost out of the Ubuntu section,
for those of you that are sick and tired
of hearing about it.
I know some of you couldn't care less.
This is a great little title, though.
I'm enjoying it immediately already.
Yeah, I know, and we just got it, this is news.
And it'll be like this probably
for like maybe a half another episode,
because we have in the works an interview
with some friends from Canonical
that worked really hard specifically on the 1710 release,
and we're gonna hopefully get them in next week's episode,
as well as a couple follow-up items.
But we now have, before we get out of the Ubuntu corner,
a name.
Beavering Away at the Brilliantly Bionic 1804,
Mark Shalloworth today posted on his blog
the name of 1804 Ubuntu, and it is the bionic beaver.
The bionic beaver.
There are so many B-words in this post.
It's pretty good. It's incredible.
Yeah, he has some fun.
There's a line in here that maybe I could poke
Popey's brain about that I feel like maybe
I should know more about, and this was sort of news to me.
He says in one of his paragraphs here
that there's an IRC channel people can join
to work with those who are updating Unity 7
for the newest X and kernel graphics in 1804.
So, is that a community project to keep Unity 7 going?
So, I think there's a number of people
who have come out of the woodwork saying,
you know what, I actually quite like Unity 7,
and I would like it to carry on working the way I like it.
Now, I appreciate it's like Marmite.
Like, not everyone likes Unity.
Of course.
There are people like i3 or Gnome Shell
or whatever else takes place.
Marte, Asma, XFCE.
Yeah, exactly.
But, turns out we shipped a bunch of machines
through hardware vendors that had Unity by default,
and a lot of people actually quite like that.
And we have noticed a lot of community people
who've rallied around and said,
we'd like to help keep that going.
Now, it's great to have community people
who are interested in keeping that going,
but what we really need is developers
because we need people to be able to review patches
and understand bug reports, triage them,
all the kind of usual stuff you do
in the development cycle of a desktop.
And we would love to keep Unity 7
well alive through 18.04 and beyond.
It will be pretty much in maintenance mode.
It might be that there could be some new features landing,
but given that the fact that Unity 7
is still active in 16.04,
like I'm running it right now,
I'm talking to you from my Unity 7 laptop,
it's not that we're just going to throw it over the wall
and to GitHub and say, there you go.
It's still hosted on Launchpad.
We still have all the build system in place.
We still have the bug tracker in place and so on.
So if we've got people in the community
who want to get involved in that,
then get in contact with us.
There's a thread going on on the Ubuntu Community Hub.
If you go to community.ubuntu.com, you'll find it easily.
It's the thread that says Unity 7 in it.
And if you're a developer
and you want to see Unity 7 continue,
jump on board and we'll get this thing
continue rolling through 18.04 and beyond.
I would love an echo effect there, but-
Beyond, beyond, beyond, beyond.
I'll be your backup guy.
I am, I'm not surprised.
Not going to say I'm surprised at all by this development.
In fact, I now feel kind of stupid
that we didn't have a betting pool going,
but part of me, for some reason,
feels like this is the desktop environment to run
on the OBS system.
I like Unity 7 enough and I want something-
Yeah, at the end,
I really didn't have any major problems with it.
Literally.
How long have we had this machine running now, Beard?
I mean, it's been since Linux Fest, right?
Yeah.
At least, yeah.
And that's the thing.
It just keeps rocking and keeps rolling along
and along and along.
It's literally the least trouble I've had.
Right.
We're not making massive multi-infrastructural changes
to Unity 7.
There's bug fixes, sure.
There are bugs in Unity 7.
We all know that.
There are bugs in Compiz and Nuxt
and the other components that make up Unity 7 experience.
And if people want to get involved,
we'd love to hear from you.
But yeah, we'd love it to stay alive.
But Compiz is still maintained, right?
That is actually still being actively maintained.
So in a way, that's sort of the core part of Unity 7
that really needs any TLC.
And if there's even somebody just nudging that along
to make sure it still works with X or whatever.
I think a lot of it will be integrating with new stuff
that comes along and making sure it still works
on new versions of whatever components come along
within the next six months.
It's a short cycle between now and April next year.
I know that the desktop team don't have a huge amount
of time to dedicate to this
because they're obviously working on the LTS,
which is going to be Gnome Shell based.
But I'm sure there are people there who would mentor people
in the community who want to get involved in this.
And if you're interested, I'd love to hear from you.
What a hell of a thing.
I'm going to seriously give it a consideration
for the OBS rig, because it's worked so damn well
for the other Skype machine.
When I say it's a Skype machine,
it runs like a dozen other apps too,
just for different tasks.
Like one of them is it runs a digital version
of our soundboard.
I have it up right now on the screen.
I have, isn't that great?
Yeah, it's awesome.
It is so great.
Our soundboard has a Linux client
that connects over Ethernet, over IP,
and it is exactly synced by the millisecond.
And if I move a slider on the digital soundboard,
it physically moves the slider with the motor
on the physical soundboard, yeah.
If I didn't have a Dan's face there during tech snap,
that's going to be right there.
Oh yeah, it's a real winner.
But you want your machine to be pretty rock solid
that you're controlling your soundboard from,
and this has been the one.
And I really, really like Solus.
I've really enjoyed Budgie,
but we had about 25 minutes this morning.
It's kind of unbelievable.
Yeah, of like, GNOME MPV has died
for the third or fourth time,
and this time it's blaming, ironically, I think,
lib systemd.so.0, which is really great.
We don't talk about such things.
And I'm in the process of trying to do all the updates,
even the optional ones,
just trying to get the system working again.
And I've had some weirdness in the software center
where it said I had like 46 updates,
and then I hit apply and it's like 146 updates.
It was a big discrepancy.
And those kinds of things, they're not a big problem,
but it did delay the show by a pretty good factor today.
I don't know.
I feel like you just don't have that problem.
Not having a functioning video player
and not having audio are pretty big problems.
Yeah, I'm trying to be nice because I really like Solus.
I really like, and I don't,
I might've got caught mid-update cycle or who knows.
So I can't really say what the problem was.
And that doesn't necessarily mean
there's not a place for Solus, right?
Like this machine can dual boot.
You can play with multiple things.
Oh yeah, absolutely.
A lot of this we ended up talking about
the appliance machines where you just don't,
you don't want to fuss.
Now we're in a place with snaps and just
using newer Ubuntu's where you have enough of the,
you know what I mean?
Like, okay, 12.04, OBS wasn't really a thing.
You couldn't expect an updated package,
but in the 17 and 18 worlds, you get a recent build,
let alone their snaps.
Took them a few days, but now there is a new build.
And Docker and other, it's kind of a different world.
That's true.
Where an Ubuntu LTS can fit a lot more roles now.
So not only are people in general
updating their repos faster.
So when 17.10 came out, there was no OBS package for 17.10,
but you know, you check three or four days later,
now there's an OBS package.
And snaps and flat packs also neutralize
that particular problem, like you're saying.
There is several, yeah, no, it's true.
There are several solutions that are converging together
to solve the software availability problem
for all distributions.
Depending on which particular methodology you subscribe to,
there's multiple of them, there's multiple now.
And that means, like you're saying,
it would be conceivable to just, to take a little time
and have like that classic reason
why a lot of us switched to Linux,
because Windows was so crashy
and you wanted the most rock solid system possible.
Like, I'm gonna get back to that.
Like maybe I'll just use Unity 7 on 18.04
with just a few confined applications.
And I bet you that thing would run
until the day that 18.04 was no longer supported.
That sounds really appealing to me.
That doesn't mean I'm gonna do that on my laptop
or my main workstation, but the three or four machines,
one, two, three, four machines,
that we need five machines that we might reload in here.
Yeah, I might do it to those.
The other nice thing, which I'm still loving,
is just you get the ZFS module,
you don't have to do any wacky DKMS or precompile.
So like, we can also do that
and then take snapshots of machines
that are particularly important
so we can have restores or easy backups.
There's still a lot of options going on here.
What I'm hearing is Wes is upgrading the studio.
I think that's what's happening.
Yep, I just signed up for it.
So this discussion about reloading the machines
in the studio, it's happening.
This is something I've been working on
slowly over last week, after our episode last week.
Hello, hello.
You know, I heard somebody told me this recently
that they never hear the airplanes that we mentioned,
so I'm gonna stop mentioning
if there's airplanes flying overhead.
Yeah, if you guys can't hear it,
it'll just be our little secret.
Yeah, we'll all be the only ones that know.
Anyways, back on track.
This week, I started loading
like my lower priority systems to 1710.
And I've been working my way up the chain to the studio.
And now I'm at the studio.
And so I wanted to take a moment
and figure out another solution
while we're in this transition.
And that's when it really struck me,
this is a case for setting up a remote desktop environment.
One on the LAN and one in the cloud.
So that way, why we destroy the installations
of these machines, and then begin to reset them up
with all the little teensy-tinesy things we need.
In a pinch, when I'm on air,
I could remote into a system that is completely configured,
has been for maybe a couple of weeks
before the transition even started.
So it's well used.
It's been well set up.
I can remote into that box.
And it doesn't matter if the system here in the studio
is a blank slate.
Because inside that remote session,
I'll have everything I need.
But to make that work,
it has to be extremely high-performant.
Because I wanna be able to show visuals on the screen.
I can't have crazy, weird lag.
I can't-
It's gotta meet your regular standards
for a desktop usable system.
Yeah, and if possible,
I'd like to use it for work during the day.
So I'd like it to be pretty responsive.
So that's pretty responsive
and maybe even support video playback.
And so that is what led me down this path
to where I'm at today.
And I would say this is still somewhat in flux.
Like one of the things I'm considering
is instead of using the Monte desktop,
maybe try a system,
like a parallel system running XFCE.
You know what?
I'll explain why in a moment.
Because Monte has been pretty good,
but I have had a couple of hiccups.
So if you're considering doing this,
I wanna pre-warn you.
It might not be a big deal,
but I just wanna pre-warn you.
So let's take a moment.
Let's think DigitalOcean.
Go to digitalocean.com, create the account.
And use our promo code Linux Unplugged.
It's a way to get really fast systems
up in their infrastructure,
which is data centers all over the world within seconds.
SSDs for every system you deploy
and a beautiful dashboard to manage all of it.
And there's still a few days left
to get in on this Hacktober fest.
Are you hip to this Hacktober stuff?
No, tell me more, tell me more.
Well, first of all, DigitalOcean is just pretty awesome
because this at the end of the day
is just supporting a bunch of open source projects.
It's getting open source code written
and then giving people some swag for doing it.
Did I get a t-shirt if I do this maybe?
Yeah, you actually, you'd be good at this.
So Hacktober fest is open to everyone in the world.
Poll requests can be made
on any GitHub hosted repository or project.
And you sign up anytime between October 1st and October 31st.
You make four poll requests between October 1st and 31st
in any time zone.
It can be to any public repo on GitHub,
not just the ones that they've highlighted.
The poll request must contain
commits you've made yourself,
poll requests reported by maintainers of spam,
or they are automated, will be marked as invalid.
It won't count.
But they have a couple of examples here.
And they're all open source projects.
And there's some open source projects
we talk about all the time.
Some of them are less known.
Like here's one for Discord, discord.net.
That's interesting.
Thanks.
They had a Rocket Chat on here earlier.
They have nw.js on here.
They have Hugo, which is really interesting.
It's a really cool, flexible static site generator.
Written in Go.
Yeah, and so the idea is just to give a little help
and exposure to some of these open source projects
and then also give away some swag.
So that's their Hacktoberfest.
It goes to the end of the month
and it's open to anybody in the whole dang world.
Digitalocean.com.
Go there, try them out.
I'm gonna be talking about them in this coming segment
because one of the two remote desktop sessions I've set up
is running on DigitalOcean.
And one of the things I did
is I got the three cents an hour system.
And then I attached 100 gigabytes of block storage,
which I am dedicating just to my home directory.
That's on spinning rust, right?
That's like really slow.
That's all SSDs, my friend.
Okay, okay.
Yeah, yeah.
In fact, it's extremely fast.
It's nuts, nuts fast.
In fact, I invite you to play around with it.
It's really satisfying.
And so I just dedicated from 100 gigs
of DigitalOcean block storage to my droplet
that runs remote desktop.
So I have a big old home drive,
which I really, really like.
They have a new object storage system
they call Spaces as well.
And the network is blazing fast.
40 gigabit connections coming into their hypervisors.
Go check them out.
Go to DigitalOcean.com and use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
It's DigitalOcean.com.
Use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
And a big thank you to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring this year Linux Unplugged program.
So yeah, I'm using X2GO.
And I'm using it with Ubuntu MATE.
And it's pretty good.
I'll give you guys a demo here in a minute
if you're watching, you'll see.
But even if you're listening, I'll describe it to you.
And to make this all hum, I'm using X2GO
on top of Ubuntu MATE 17.10.
17.10 for both the systems.
To do that on DigitalOcean at this point,
I had to install a 17.04 image.
And then I did an upgrade to 17.10, which went fine.
Just totally fine.
It was a pretty clean base system too.
I even realized I could have snapshoted it
if anything had gone wrong.
But I just didn't.
Yeah, use them features.
Yeah, and what I love, love, love about X2GO
is that you can run it on a headless system
that doesn't have a full X setup,
doesn't have a monitor, mouse, and keyboard.
So it works on a system that's just up in a rack somewhere.
And X2GO is a graphical remote desktop
that works really well over low bandwidth connections.
It has a lot of scaling options.
It has the ability to disconnect
and then reconnect to a session.
So I can be working, close it,
come down into the studio and reconnect.
Everything's right back where I left it off.
It has sound redirection.
It's a little wonky sometimes, but it supports pulse audio.
And it has support for shared folders,
which I have not really tried.
I did not know that.
Yeah, my understanding is it's using SFTP
on the backend to do that.
Though I guess you could set up,
there's a lot of options for that.
Yeah, all the traffic is tunneled over SSH.
And so everything's going over SSH.
What makes X2GO cooler than just say like
straight old traditional X1140?
Because a lot of people would just say,
well, we'll just use SSH with X1140
and then you don't need to install any extra packages.
But X2GO uses the NX library,
which was developed by No Machine.
And they stopped releasing it as open source
a little while ago.
But X2GO is based off the last released open source version
and it has been approved upon.
And it has basically solved all of the latency intensive
parts of X1140.
And they've worked around those really latency intensive
parts by creating an NX proxy on each side
of the network connection.
So on the client and on the server.
And then it's sending compressed updates
between the two proxies.
And so X is getting immediate response
from these two proxies.
And then they handle the transferring of all of that stuff
in a much more efficient means.
And by doing so, you only have to install a few extra X stuff
to get X2GO working.
You don't have to have a full X2GO graphical environment.
And I'll have the commands you need to run
to install that in the show notes.
And I'll tell you what guys, it is pretty impressive.
It is pretty impressive how fast you can get.
Now there's just certain limitations I'll go into,
but just as a base start,
if you start with a desktop environment
that is not composited,
so like your Mates or an XFCE,
so Gnome 3 and Unity 7 and Plasma Desktop,
the latest versions are all kind of out
unless you use software rendering.
And there is a way to get it working
with Gnome fallback mode to the classic mode,
but I chose not to do that.
So if you use like a 2D desktop basically,
you get essentially damn near local performance
on the LAN and scaling performance
on your remote connection.
I went with Mate and the main problem I've had so far
is I will open up a resume session on different computers
at different resolutions.
And sometimes the system tray area of Mate
just is really gummed up.
Like all of my notification icons
all be stacked on top of each other.
Yeah, that seems like a tricky area.
And here's what happened.
So I set up Dropbox because I want to get
all of my unfiltered clips on both systems
so I can edit that stuff remotely.
And I'll talk more about that in a second.
So I set up my install Dropbox
because I'm still using Dropbox for the unfiltered show
because we have like a terabyte of data in there.
It's a hard thing to move around.
It's actually more than a terabyte of data.
And so I started installs.
And now the way Dropbox works on Linux
is it starts syncing instantly.
Starts just immediately as soon as you connect
to your Dropbox account.
And I go in there and I use selective syncs.
That way I only pull down about like 10, 15 gigs
of the over a terabyte of data.
But because all of these icons in the system tray
all stacked all over each other in some weird crappy bug
after the screen size had changed,
I kept right clicking on the system tray
and getting everything but the Dropbox icon.
Well, this is on a DigitalOcean droplet.
And this thing's pulling down my Dropbox
at just maddening speeds.
It's filling the disk at just an unbelievable rate.
And I'm like, I-
Just load testing Dropbox for them.
Yeah, I was like, I got no option
because I can't get to this icon
to go into selective sync mode because of this.
So I had to kill the entire desktop session
and log back in.
So that way the system tray bar little area,
notification applet area would get redrawn.
You're saying Dropbox needs a text-based config file.
Well, it needs some sort of like-
No, I'm just trolling.
It does have a command line actually,
but it needs some way to talk to the GUI version
from the command line.
And then once I logged back in,
redrew the system tray area,
I was able to solve the problem.
But quite a bit of gigabytes have been downloaded by then.
Where I feel like maybe XFCE wouldn't have had
that problem, perhaps.
You're probably right about that.
So I'm just gonna play with that,
but I have Monte on both of them right now.
Bashful, you wanted to jump in about compositing desktops.
I would love to talk about that for a second
because that would, oh, I would love to get
like a Gnome 3 remote desktop session if that's possible.
Well, so just to give a little history,
with my day job, we work in this exact space
except more on the performance side,
like leveraging GPUs and such for a bunch of our clients
like Pixar and all those guys.
So a lot of them, even with the performance stuff,
they still traditionally go without compositing.
So while you can get the performance for CAD
and video editing and even like video streaming
and so on and so forth, a lot of the desktop stuff
people still tend to disable.
Okay, and that was sort of what I kind of come to
is in my rig that I have here on the land of the studio,
where I can get to the OBS files
and I can talk to all the other machines on the network,
that's the machine I have the GTX 960 in,
where if I need to do some sort of GPU job,
that would be the remote desktop.
So here's my setup, tell me what you guys think.
I got the two rigs, I've got orbital and suborbital.
Orbital is a system up at DigitalOcean
and its key strengths are insane bandwidth,
it's just incredible bandwidth performance
and essentially unlimited disk,
I just gotta throw money at the problem
and very, very, very fast disk, as well as snapshots,
so it's a good system to take risks on.
So that's my orbital system.
And then you could probably, if you needed to,
you could destroy it and rebuild it,
let's say you were hanging out in Singapore
and you wanted it local there.
Or move it.
So that's orbital, and then I have suborbital,
which is here in the studio and it's primary,
it's the same, I'm trying to match the interfaces
as much as possible.
And suborbital's main advantages are local GPU
with 960 with the NVIDIA proprietary driver,
a fair amount of local storage, but not too much,
not nearly what I have in the drop.
And then, of course, the gigabit local access
to all the studio resources.
And for me, it is sort of like,
it's sort of great, because if I have
a network-intensive job, I log into one system,
and if I have a compute-intensive job,
I can log into the other system.
And I'm kind of playing with the idea
of trying to figure out all the ways
I could sync more of the settings
to make sure if I change something in one system,
it synchronizes to the other system.
I'd really like to start looking into that now.
But again, I've really got to-
We're just right back to configuration management,
aren't we, on this episode?
I guess so, oh boy, it really is.
But then I've really got to nail down
that desktop environment.
Yes.
What do you think, Bashul?
You say Mate is the winner, Mate?
Yeah, it is, kind of by far, too.
I was running it for quite a while at work here,
and out of all the desktops, it was the only one
that was decent if you wanted a full-blown desktop,
versus going with like a pilot manager.
Did you try XFCE?
At the, let me think about this, all right?
You know what, I'm not gonna say yay or nay on that.
Now you got me thinking, I might go load one
just to test on-
I'd be curious, I'd be curious.
The thing that really blows me away about X to go,
if you're putting it on Ubuntu or Arch,
actually it's in Solus too, but if you're doing it
on Ubuntu, it's you add a PPA, and you do all the dance
you have to do to update your sources list.
But then it's just, it's really, you just need two packages
if you already have two packages.
Two packages, if you already have Monte installed,
or whatever desktop environment you want.
You just have to apt-get install X to go server,
and X to go server dash X session.
Not all of Xorg, like it'll pull in its dependencies
that it needs, but you don't have to pull,
it is really simple to create a system on a VPS,
like DigitalOcean or any other one,
and install these couple of packages,
and then you remote into it, and you're the display,
you don't need a display attached.
Because the way X to go works is it has,
sort of like if you're familiar with Citrix
and other remote desktop clients,
it has a client manager, a session manager,
where you can have multiple servers listed there,
and you can set different settings,
and different compression settings
for the different servers.
You can set up your shared folders.
It's all done with a graphical interface.
It's all in the GUI.
It's so straightforward.
In fact, I'll give you a little demo.
Because it's not perfect, it's definitely not perfect,
but it's pretty powerful, and I would definitely
trade the power for perfection in this particular case.
And all of this stuff is really sort of,
kind of basic, like if you just leave the defaults,
you're gonna generally be okay.
Let's take a moment to thank Linux Academy,
because honestly, if any of this stuff
sounds interesting to you, you could dive in even deeper
over at Linux Academy, so this would be
a good moment to do this.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
Go there to sign up and get a free seven-day trial.
They have self-paced, in-depth video courses,
hands-on, scenario-based labs that really help it stick
and instructor mentoring by real human beings
when you get stuck and need some help.
And course scouts are when you're busy,
comprehensive study guides you can download
and take with you, and audio nuggets
that are sparkly bits of wisdom that you can deep dive into,
and a community that's full of clones of Westpain.
It's kind of weird, actually.
Yeah, we get along great, it's awesome.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
They also have iOS and Android apps,
and flashcards that get forked.
It's a pretty great platform, really.
If you think about it, it's something that would be like,
if you could just take all of Linux Academy
and go back in time and give it to yourself
like eight, 10 years, you'd be like Biff
bringing back the playbook.
You could get so ahead of everybody.
It's one of our precious resources.
We should launch it up and encapsulate it in a satellite
for future humanity.
That's how important it is.
Or for aliens, they need it, too.
That's true.
I mean, Linux is gonna be the kernel
that takes over their world once they learn about it.
The GPL is a viral license.
Yeah, exactly, we all know.
So go get hedged now.
It's kind of wild.
I have to say, you're motivated, right?
You wanna learn Linux.
You're listening to this show.
Obviously, you're interested in these topics.
But when you have a job and a family,
and you have the end of the day and you're tired,
there's a million reasons that you can come up with
not to learn something.
Go girl.
But Linux Academy breaks down
every single possible barrier.
They can't actually make you type things
and do the learning, but everything else
is set up right for you.
It's so true. It's awesome.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
Big thank you to them for sponsoring the unplugged program.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged
is where you get a free seven day trial,
and you support this here shenanigans.
So I am in the process of reinstalling
a bunch of packages on Solace.
Oh, you know what?
It launched just fine.
Isn't that wonderful?
So you have the X2Go client session manager.
Were you gonna say something, Beard?
I was just gonna ask, have you tested out X2Go at all
on a more flaky connection?
Well, on a MiFi, which is pretty, pretty crap.
Pretty, pretty crap.
What kind of bandwidth do you get on that thing?
It ranges depending on the day.
So it depends on which connection I'm on.
So if I'm on a TIN connection, or an AT&T connection,
or a public Wi-Fi connection,
because I sort of use all of them.
Listen to user error back catalogs for more information
where I've outlined it all.
And in there, I have a large variance.
And I can get up to maybe seven megabits
where I'm usually at, and I can get as low as easily
as low as 400 kilobits a second.
I mean, it can be a pretty dramatic range
depending on how much bandwidth I've used,
how loaded the network is, and all of those things.
So I have tested this from everything from gigabit
to probably around 500K a second.
And so maybe that's a good place to start.
We could take a look at this.
So in X2GO, you have the client session manager.
And I have two connections up right now.
And let's take a look here at the sub-orbital one.
This is the one here on the LAN.
So this could be an example of how you would maybe do this.
So I can disconnect my session, I can pause it right here.
So I'm suspending a session I already have open,
which is always a lot of fun.
And then I can go in and I can edit that session.
And I have my different options I can choose from.
And in here, you can see the host,
the username I want it to use by default,
and the port.
So if you're maybe forwarding a random ass port to 22,
you could override that and put in here.
You can, with a dropdown option,
you can choose the desktop environment
that you're gonna be logging into.
So they have MATE right here in the dropdown already.
They also have Unity, Cinnamon, Trinity,
XD, MCP, connecting to a local desktop,
and notably, support for connecting to an RDP server,
a Windows terminal server.
Oh, is that right?
Mm-hmm.
But here's the really interesting stuff.
So on the Connection tab,
this is where you have your connection speed preferences.
And because I'm on a LAN, I have a slider.
So that's that baby.
Yeah, it goes everywhere from modem to LAN.
And this change is not only compression,
but what the size of the packets that get sent.
And so when you're on a MiFi, you go to modem,
and here on LAN, I can go to LAN.
But then they have a million different compression options.
This is something I spent some time playing with
because they have, you can do no compression,
you can do adaptive compression,
but you can also say lock it in at 16 meg JPEG,
or lock it in at 24k PNG.
So you can choose different image compression
depending on if your preference is speed or image quality.
And I have found that the 16 meg JPEG
has been pretty good for me.
They also even have some RDP compression,
which all works pretty well.
And then they have your input and output for the size of it,
the DPI, so if you're on a high DPI screen,
you can pass that along to X2GO.
So it does support high DPI,
but you have to manually enter that in here.
Then you have your sound options,
so I can have it redirect sound to my local Pulse audio.
You can use SSH port forwarding
to tunnel the sound system connections through firewall,
so you do not have to open up a separate port.
And then on the shared media tab,
in here is where you can add your local files,
and it will use SFTP to actually transfer those files.
So now here, I'll show you what it's like to log in.
So I'm logging into the one here on my LAN.
In the background, I have, let me minimize that guy.
In the background here,
this is the system up on DigitalOcean right here.
And you can actually start to see the problem right here
in the system tray with this double volume icon thing
that's going on.
Oh yeah, I haven't seen that before.
Mm-hmm, that's due to me changing the resolutions.
But to Mate's credit, if I resize this X2GO window here,
Mate will snap pretty well to that, boom,
and it resizes pretty dynamically.
So to its credit, I can't sit here,
and I can screw around with the window size proportions,
and Mate actually handles it pretty good.
It's just sometimes those notification icons
lose their crap.
Yeah.
But before I log into the local LAN system,
while I have it up on the screen,
here is the system that I have up on DigitalOcean.
I call this one Orbital.
I'll try to get it on the screen.
And I just thought maybe,
if you're watching the video version,
I'd show you what the performance is like.
Yeah, walk us around a bit.
So let's open up, here's my file manager,
and you can see, when I maximize the window,
you can see there's a, it's pretty good.
There's a real slight delay, but it's pretty usable.
Here's me dragging the window around.
Again, maybe not quite as smooth as,
if I was running locally,
I'd also be using Compass to them.
But in terms of latency, when I type in terminal,
it's right on the money for me.
There's no delay there, right?
It pops up on the window.
I can start typing immediately.
When I hit enter on commands,
they'll show up instantaneously on screen.
There's really, there's no delay here
which would prevent me from working.
Let's try browsing the web.
This is usually the most challenging, actually,
is this browsing the web thing,
because it involves redrawing.
You've even got it signed into your account,
and look at this, that's great.
Oh yeah, it's ready to go for me.
Oh yeah, it's ready to go at all the times.
This is actually probably the best test.
Scrolling a complicated web page.
This web page is Twitter,
it has video playing on it right now,
and you can see there's some sort of herky-jerky
as it reloads, and there's a little bit of delay,
like when I stop, it keeps going
for just a brief moment.
We could...
And the remote server, we have to keep in mind,
doesn't have any sort of GPU even integrated
to help with the fancy rendering.
Right, exactly, totally.
So now let's compare that to,
here, I'll log into my local system.
Now this is with my compression settings
basically saying, let's have at it.
You're on a LAN connection, so let's just go nuts.
And so this will kind of be a good comparison
if you have a pretty fast connection.
So that's a slower connection, what we just showed you.
It's usable, it's very usable.
There's just some herky-jerky when you're scrolling
or dragging windows, but it's definitely usable.
And if you're working in a terminal,
you're working in a text editor,
you're browsing web, you're chatting Telegram,
all these things, Slack, all work just fine
in that slower connection.
But now let's take a look at the LAN speeds,
where I feel like it really shines.
Let's go back, we'll do the Twitter test here again.
We'll make it nice and big so that way it's the same size.
We start doing the scrolling much smoother.
And it's right on point with me too.
There's no latency.
When I stop scrolling, it scrolls.
This, you, if I didn't tell you this is a remote session,
I don't think you would be able to tell on your own.
I think you could legitimately sit down at this computer
and not suspect this is a remote session.
It is that performant over the LAN.
This is key for me because that means
I can sit down at any of these systems
and have a really great, really well-performing experience.
So much so that, check this out.
We'll go into the unfilter archive here
and we can play a little cyber news.
And the video actually plays.
Are we gonna get full cyber here?
This is their audio too.
This is from the remote session.
Is now putting nearly all of them at risk.
Wow.
A bug known as crack.
No, not crack.
Fundamental flaw in the technology.
And that is live from my remote session,
video and audio, and they're synced up.
It's playable.
I mean, it's damn impressive.
And this is a headless Ubuntu box.
That's awesome.
Out in the garage right now.
Side note, it's really fun to watch mainstream media
try to cover things like that.
Crack.
Yeah, they are the worst at that, aren't they?
So you can see there's a,
so let's go just as a comparison note now.
Let's go try to play that same video on the remote session.
Cause again, I have these things pretty synced up.
So I have sort of the same stuff on both systems.
So we go play the same clip now on the remote session.
Let's see how that works.
Well, a security feature.
Ooh, much herkier jerkier.
Barely, not watchable.
The audio is staying current though.
That's impressive.
Audio is staying current,
but it is a disastrous slideshow.
That could be because there's,
I doubt if that's a GPU thing.
I think that's just a compression thing.
I'm pretty sure that's just compression.
But it is such a game changer for me.
That's awesome.
Because it's still usable even over the MiFi.
It's still completely usable.
And I'm able to do bandwidth intensive things
in the remote session.
And then when it's time for me to come into the studio,
I close the window and I sit back down at the system here
and I reopen the window.
And if I'm working off of suborbital,
it's just super fast.
But if I'm working off of the remote system,
everything's the same, nothing's changed.
And it performs great here on the connection for the studio.
So X2GO is definitely worth a look.
It's still very, very relevant.
I don't know what its future is in a Wayland universe,
but to be honest, I'm not as concerned about that yet.
You'll get there.
I don't think the production systems
are going to Wayland in the next year or so.
So that's a problem for future, Chris,
in about two years, maybe.
Unless that GNOME Wayland session doesn't crash so much.
Or if Pipewire comes up with some really
badass remote system.
If anybody knows a way that's even more
performed than X2GO, I absolutely would try it.
Because video editing's still a little herky-jerky for me.
I know that's a very high bar, but boy,
wouldn't that be a treat.
In the past, I've used XPRA, or it's also
part of the WinSwitch project.
I know WinSwitch supports multiple operating systems.
I don't know how X2GO.
And if you look online, if you search
for a comparison between the two,
you'll almost exclusively find Hacker News posts,
Reddit posts asking for a comparison,
and then no further comments.
So it's a little bit different, and I
haven't used both of them.
But maybe XPRA is something you could try and just compare.
In the past, I'd been running OBS on a droplet,
and I'd been using that to control the stream,
and that was working pretty nicely.
I did not do any intensive editing, necessarily,
so I can't speak to that.
I'm not talking intensive editing.
I'm talking like Avid Mux, clip off the end,
clip off the beginning, grab 30 seconds of a clip,
very basic mark in out, mark the in, mark the out, export.
So it might be worth just throwing that on that same droplet
and just connecting up and seeing what the experience is like.
Will you toss a link to that in the show notes section?
I sure will.
I would love to take a look at that.
I mean, you were suggesting a couple other things, too.
Go ahead.
I know you want to say something, seriously.
You had suggested Splashtop, which
could work because it basically encapsulates
the entire desktop.
Yeah, it's basically just a video stream.
It's an H.264 stream, yeah, that then takes your inputs
and outputs and forwards them.
Kind of sounds like a water park ride, but that's just a perk,
I guess.
Splashtop might also be a good solution,
but the thing I really like about X2GO
is there's no session running at the physical machine.
These are sessions that run headless
that I can pop in and pop out of,
and I could still go hook up a monitor, mouse, keyboard
to that machine and log in at the desktop, I suppose,
if I wanted to, at least on the local one.
Really cool.
There are ways to connect to the local desktop, too,
so there is ways to connect to the running session.
That's not what I'm using it for.
Does anybody have any input in the Discord
there on this particular topic or how they do remote desktop
for Linux?
And I am specifically going for remote desktop, not just SSH,
because this is using SSH, actually.
I have that as an option, too, now, obviously.
Right, but you need the graphical thing.
You already have a solution for remote terminals.
We figured that out like 10 years ago.
You know what works?
If you do, by the way, in the Discord room,
just toss a hand in the chat.
You know what works super well for me
is having a basic-bitch terminal that I'm sitting at that
has a couple of X terminals or something,
like whatever, that I can SSH into these boxes
that I'm X2going into.
So then I have a graphical interface,
and in the background, I have an SSH terminal command line
into that box.
And if anything gets weird in my graphical environment,
I am one second away, less than a second away,
from tabbing over to that terminal
and killing a process or fixing the issue.
It's like I have a backdoor into the main system
I'm always working on in a way that gives me
this really supreme confidence that I'm
going to be able to handle anything that
happens in that graphical session,
because I've got this emergency persistent backdoor.
And because both these systems, like the one on Digital Ocean
on the LAN, are so rock solid, my SSH session
has been running to both these systems now
on one of my boxes for like six days without being broken.
So the terminal is always there, always connected in.
It's always just a couple of commands away.
That's great.
It is.
It's just a cool way to work.
I really like it.
Bashful, you had a comment on GPU.
Go for it.
I'd love to hear about that.
I'm just curious out of a bunch of the stuff
that you've done research on, have you
found anything that actually leverages the GPU?
Well, I think Splashtop would, because it
might be when it's encoding.
For me, I don't need my desktop session to be composited.
What I need the GPU for is encoding video,
or potentially maybe running OBS,
which maybe that's where I'd run into this problem.
Because I do want to experiment with that as well.
So I could see some workloads in the future
where it'd be a problem.
Yeah, I know a couple of the big three
are looking towards GPU workloads with remote desktop.
But I'm wondering on the pricing behind it.
There's already things that can leverage it both for the desktop
session and so on and so forth, but it's pretty damn pricey.
I could see for my orbital system,
the one that I call it orbital because it's out in the cloud,
I could see moving that to say if Amazon or somebody came
around or your rack space or an Azure came around and said,
we can do hosted Linux desktop.
And it'll have a GPU, and you can connect to it
from any operating system, and it's $25 a month.
I may give it a serious consideration
because this is a legitimate work tool for me.
But it's going to be impossible for any of them
to compete with suborbital, the system I have on the LAN,
because that's got gigabit access to my OBS recording.
It's got gigabit access to all the other machines.
It's got physical hardware that I can come in
and I can plug into it and then get access to.
So maybe I want to one day plug in an SD card reader to it
or something, weird stuff like that that I could never
get in a hosted system.
So to me, having these two boxes is the invaluable part
because the orbital system is totally
independent of the studio.
If the studio goes offline or I'm in some weird place
and it's way faster for me to connect to that,
I've always got that.
But I can't ever see replacing suborbital
because that's unique because it's here on the LAN.
I think the GPU instances are probably, at least not
in the short term, never going to come in at like $25 a pop.
If you just look at what it costs
to go and rent one on Google Compute or Amazon or whatever,
they're significantly more expensive.
And that's not even running them full time.
Well, I'm grateful that Mate works as well as it does,
actually, really.
When I look at how I can resize these windows
and just sort of abuse it and it just sort of snaps back
for the most part, I'm pretty grateful for that.
And I'm really grateful that it has, I have put it,
I took the Redmond layout and I've modified the Redmond
layout, which puts essentially everything
in one bar at the bottom.
So you have your task switcher, your launchers,
your system tray.
I'm not doing any docs or anything like that.
I just have like some quick launch icons.
And then I've got one of the Mate launchers here.
I don't think it's Brisk, but maybe, oh yeah, it is Brisk.
Yeah, in fact, I replaced the one it had for the Redmond
and I added Brisk.
And it's just so freaking functional.
It's just unbelievable.
Like I've got just, I could rave for two episodes
about how there is really something
to that just straightforward, practical,
everything works as I expected.
It's rock solid.
I mean, these systems have been running for days now
and I just pop in, pop out all the time
and they're always there ready to work
from whatever machine I'm connecting from.
It's really great.
And if you haven't played around with it,
the barrier to entry is super low.
I'll have the commands you need to run
if you're on Ubuntu to install it.
It's really just a few packages.
It's also available on a lot of other distros.
I really encourage you to play around with it,
even if you're just playing around on your LAN
or you just want to get more use out of one
really powerful system in your house
because you can have multiple people logged in
at the same time.
Or even, I mean, like you can use it
for more traditional things too,
like supporting family members or others
if you have that installed.
If you have these instructions now,
just get it set up one time
and then when you need to jump on their box, there you go.
But you could also, if money's tight,
you could get one really nice family system
and then just scrape together
and get a couple of dumb terminals that are.
I was immediately thinking about that.
Yeah, right.
Or Chromebook even.
Get some Chromebooks and then the Chromebooks run next to go
and they connect into it and the one central box
in your house has got the i7, it's got the GPU,
it's got the disk.
You can also then easily manage backups
and all kinds of stuff that way.
Well, start thinking about how it changes
your media management too.
If I load MB on one of these things
and I start just doing my downloads
and my media management on one of these things,
then all of a sudden life just gets a lot easier
because the MB server's running locally on the box,
the media files are all locally on the box,
I can remote into it and have local access
or I can stream it over MB.
When you take a basically Linux
or when you put a desktop on it
is essentially what I've done.
There's actually surprisingly nice uses
for having a desktop on a server
if it's not hosting web pages
or performing traditional server roles.
If it's doing more like syncing your media,
maybe downloading files for you, things like that,
all of a sudden it's very useful.
I really like it.
And it's a solution that's not new to me.
I did something like this eight, nine years ago
when I worked at a school
that had very restrictive web filtering.
I would remote into a physical box
that I had in a rack in a data center somewhere.
And I used No Machine back then, No Machine NX,
which is what this is based off of.
And it worked back then.
And it's sort of an old idea
and it just still really holds a lot of water,
especially with 1710, Ubuntu MATE,
I'm not making any kind of compromise
in a modern desktop environment.
And you, I mean, as we all know, Chris, you're somewhat picky
in terms of interactions, other things.
So if this wasn't usable, you would be the first to say it.
Oh, that's true, I would, yeah.
And I'm still like, you know, I may try XFCE
and if I could have a GPU accelerated composited desktop,
I might like that.
Right, yeah.
I'll have to have one.
We'll get there.
Yeah, yeah, we'll get there.
In the meantime, it gives me the freedom
to sort of wreck havoc in the studio
and at least know I've got a couple of escape hatches
where all my stuff's already logged in, ready to go,
Telegram's right there, Slack's right there,
all my S, all my bookmarks, all my show notes.
Can go on.
Mm-hmm, and that's really what it's all about.
And it really, you know, gosh, it's just so low overhead.
I love that about open source software.
Yeah, I didn't have to go spend hundreds of dollars
to get some sort of remote desktop package.
I didn't have to hassle with any of that.
Not to, you know, not to overstress that,
but that is just such a nice thing
when you all of a sudden get a wild hair
and you think, oh my gosh, I could solve this problem
I'm about to have with free software.
It really is empowering, it really is great.
And that's the message right there we want to end on.
But I'd love to hear what you do for remote desktop access,
especially if you've got one that performs super, super well.
Please, please let us know.
Comment wherever you watch this,
jupyterbroadcasting.com slash contact
or linuxunplugged.reddit.com.
That subreddit definitely could use some love.
Okay, Wes, guess what?
It's time to end the show today.
Yeah, yeah, Beardsley, how do you think
the Discord test went, pretty good?
Pretty good.
We're gonna be back on Mumble while we evaluate,
so join us back on Mumble next week
if you want to participate in the virtual lug.
Find out when the show is live
over at jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar
and join us live at jblive.tv
where we've got the live stream there
as well as links to watch it in other places.
You've been commanded.
No excuses now.
There is no excuse.
Make it happen.
Make it show, as Captain McQuarrie would say.
Follow the network at Jupiter Signal.
Thank you so much for tuning this week's episode
and we'll see you back here next week
for episode 221.
Say goodbye guys.
Goodbye.
Goodbye, Mama.
I
Think I got a little post show in me. Yeah
Some posters bashful's got some follow-up some real-time follow-up here. And then before Poby goes I have some FOMO stuff
I want to talk to him about but bashful
Yeah, I got it. I got it here. Which I got it. He's over there. He's over here
well, I got to be careful how much I say but
Long in the short of it is is that where I'm working right now?
We actually have an agent a different that runs over the PCIe protocol that can leverage the GPUs natively
For remote a whole want yep
Yeah, well it's it's kind of on its way
Like our whole company runs remotely everything in our office is just either a laptop or what's called a zero client
Interesting and so there's no
So, I'm pretty sure it's fire when it comes you guys you guys are already hip to this notion
Yeah, we've been well
I mean
That's what the company work for it was founded on and stuff like that
And so for example Amazon workspaces their windows offering like that's our agent. Yeah, that's really hot guy and we actually
This kind of stuff doing remote desktop terminal services stuff. It's interesting. It's still now. It's just getting hosted by larger companies
Well, it's that and also a lot of people tend to look at it for now
I almost equate it to application streaming
So where a lot of our workloads are going is people bringing specific
Applications over the net and it's a lot of like CAD and video editing and stuff like that. Basically everyone wants to leverage
Remote resources and I was gonna I should have mentioned X to go also has support for publishing just a
Just a single app. But yeah, so poppy I have to ask what's tell me you you are I
Believe you are preaching the Church of rust to everybody and I I feel like I'm totally left out
I'm not I know rust is a game. I know there's something that's not just a programming language
but
Chase someone right now. Is it so it's like a game. Is it like an open-world game?
Yeah, it's a blow
Discord outed you that you were playing
Yeah, I'm playing at the moment and and it obviously works under Linux and I take it poppy. Oh, yeah
Can I ask how many penises you see in the past half hour? Penises
That's pretty personal there. They're
Russ is notorious for having a lot of male genitalia
Swinging around. So is it like a is it like co-op environment? Is it self-hosted servers?
What is the is it a multiplayer at all poppy? Is it single-player? Yeah. Yeah, it's totally multiplayer
So it's a big open-world think minecraft but with the yeah, no wonder it's so big exactly
It's it's hilarious
Sorry, I I'm playing it right now while we're talking and
So the premise is you arrive naked on an island and you have to run around and gather resources and
Fortify your base because other people will come along and kill you. Oh, no, we'll kill you. So, how do you know like
How do you know you can't you can you build your own server?
Like can you run your own system? So you could just have your own world where people won't kill you. Yeah
Yeah, you could do totally do that. I'm running on there. I'm I play mostly on the gaming on the next
Server so Liam the guy. Yeah. Yep. I saw him tweeting about it. Yeah
Yeah, he has his own server and we play on there, but there are other servers that are modded
there are some that are stock and some that are
Tweaked to be you know better faster different in some ways it hostile. Is it fun? Like is it?
Oh, it's it's generally shoot on sight. So if you see some
Naked person running in front of you you shoot them first and then run up to their body and steal their stuff
And if they turn out to be your friend, then you revive them
But it's generally shoot on sight. It's survival like just now
yeah, just now when you were talking to be an aeroplane flew over and did an airdrop in air drops you on you find automatic weapons and
All kinds of other useful
So if I join do I have any shot of making it before getting murdered at this point?
Is there just too many people? So the interesting thing is the servers reset every month because it's currently an alpha
any server you join pretty much any of this the stock servers will wipe and
So if you join soon after the wipe you're in with a bit of a chance if you joined
now
Like a few days or a week before the server wipes
Then chances are everyone else has automatic weapons and you arrive as a naked
And the interesting thing about these kind of games and I believe rust is one of them is if you log off your body stays
In the world so you can go and find somebody that's like laying around just steal their stuff
Yes, so this is why you fortify your your place and you build a house in which you're protected
So when you exit the game your body is left in a place where nobody can get you
But people could build c4 and explode the walls bust through wall steal your stuff
so yeah, so um
So that must be like some sort of mad rush for resources and territory when the server is actually yeah
Yeah, that sounds really stressful and then just a constant war until the reset
But it also sounds really fun. If I was good at it, it would be fun
But until I was hilarious, you don't even have to be good
I I have I have shared some space with wimpy me and him have a little compound
It's adorable have high high walls around it with an automatic door and automatic turrets
So if anyone busted through the door, they get shot as soon as they come through the door
And all kinds of other like ways in which to protect our stuff. It's the alliance all ephemeral anyway
Yeah, it sounds fun though
Cuz it's in a week in a week or so this is all gonna get thrown away and we all start again as nakeds on
The beach so yeah, it's good fun. Yes. There's really kind of profound in a lot of ways actually
Yeah, is what it is. It's like a society if what would happen if society completely collapsed. This is what we'd have
Yeah, that's the weird thing. We have we've built up knowing that they're so when you know that the server wipe is coming
When it gets close to the server wipe nobody cares about anything because you know
You're all gonna get wiped out in a week. So everyone just goes attacking everyone even people you had as friends
Oh, what does this say about humanity? What does this say?
you start building up a stockpile of food and weapons and armor and clothes and
You know the resources you need to survive the apocalypse. It's brilliant. That's pretty great. All right. I just bought it on humble bundle
I'm gonna give it a go. I gotta try it. I gotta try it. Okay server. What do you guys say?
You know gentoo challenge next week for Halloween