Now, Wes, before we start, I gotta let people know, next week, we're having a schedule change.
Just for one week, because we're making room for OSCON.
You know about OSCON?
That's a big deal.
Yeah.
We're going to be at OSCON on July 22nd, which is a Wednesday.
You can go to meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting if you want to join us.
We're going to meet up and we're going to be at OSCON itself.
If you're going to be on the floor, you're welcome to come up and say hi to Noah and
I or go out to dinner with us afterwards, meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
To make room for that, we're going to have to leave on Tuesday, though, which means unplugged
on Monday next week.
Woo!
Yeah, same bat time, just a different bat day.
Does that make sense?
I think so.
Is that a thing people say?
Let's just pretend that it does.
And a bat channel, too.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, so we're going to do it Monday at 2 p.m. Pacific, but you go to JupiterBroadcasting.com
slash calendar.
And I want to put this right here at the top, because we love having you guys join us live
in our virtual lug.
So join us live next week, Monday at 2 p.m. Pacific, JupiterBroadcasting.com slash calendar,
and come say hi to us at OSCON.
And remember, you can also use the promo code LINUX to get a 20% discount off of your OSCON
pass if you'd like.
If you want to come down and say hi to us, I think the base pass is like 50 bucks, and
you get 20% off that.
It's not bad to come say hi.
What a deal.
And you get to say hi to all the vendors and all that kind of – it's a great pass.
The expo pass is a great one to go.
So that'll be next Monday at 2 p.m. Pacific, JupiterBroadcasting.com slash calendar.
Join us live at jblive.tv.
And I would be up for the VR debate, because I'm back on board.
I'm back on the VR train.
I'm back on!
I got off the hype train for a little bit, and I'm back on.
So we've just recorded two episodes of the Ubuntu podcast.
Yeah.
Apparently, Popey's on holiday, but we've just done a segment on Google Cardboard.
And?
Yes.
I think I'm going to get one, just to try it out.
I think it's a low enough barrier to entry that it's interesting.
I think – you know what, Pope?
I wimpy.
I'm sorry.
I think you should wimpy, because – and here's why.
I'm going to get – I'm going to get junk – people are going to call and tell me I'm
a – no.
No.
Here's what I think you should do.
I think Cardboard is the best solution, because – so having tried the Oculus DK2, right?
And having tried that hooked up to the PC, I will say it is very, very clunky.
It is not production-ready.
But if you scale it down and you go with something like the Samsung VR Innovation Edition or
the Google Cardboard, it is not as dramatic of an experience, it is not as necessarily
as high-powered, but it is so simple and straightforward, and there's already a bunch of good stuff
in the Play Store.
And in the case of the Samsung VR Innovator Edition, there's an entire Oculus app store
filled full of stuff that you can try that is legit.
And in the case of the S6 Innovator Edition, because the screen on the S6 is like 544 ppi,
it actually has a higher resolution than the Oculus.
So you can actually get smartphones that have a higher resolution now than the Oculus and
Google Cardboard too.
Yeah.
And it's a low – like you say, it's low cost, so it's almost zero risk.
So Mark, who was discussing Google Cardboard, he bought, you know, the cheapest cardboard
version he could find for four quid, and he tried it out, and from that he's decided
actually it's quite good and it's good enough and there's enough content that he'll
probably buy a slightly better headset to, you know, use more frequently.
He's more into games than I am.
Well, you know –
Mark's case is a little bit more disturbing, but just as much fun, I think.
What is it?
Well, so, you know, if you get a new cat, you know, eventually you decide to buy them
catnip and you all sit in a circle and give the cat catnip and then, you know, all enjoy
the cat wigging out on catnip for the first time.
No, I've never done that.
No, no, of course.
I'm just wondering, you know, what would Google Cardboard do to four and five year
old girls?
I'm kind of interested to see what it does to children.
You know, I put Dylan in the DK2 and almost a year ago and about two weeks ago he brought
it up to me and he said, Dad, can I do that – can I wear that headset again and ride
that roller coaster again?
And I haven't talked to him about it in that entire time and now he's six and it left
enough of an impression on him that he brought it up on his own to me.
And so our conversation that Wimpy, you and I have had, and Popey has been involved in
too about VR in the pre-show here, and then Dylan's sort of, like it really made an impression
on him and it made an impression on me, I decided I wanted to revisit the VR topic and
not maybe – because after Oculus abandoned Linux I kind of was like, I'm done, screw
these guys, right?
But you know, I did end up with a Galaxy S6 and the thing is, is once you have the Galaxy
S6, you basically have the most expensive component to getting the Galaxy VR set up.
Because once you have the phone, it's basically, you just need the headset.
So yesterday I received the Galaxy VR Innovator Edition headset.
And it's pretty, guys.
Yeah, and Wes has had a chance to play with it too, and there's some things that are
awkward about it, like you have to have your phone on and unlocked before you put it in,
but once you do that, it has a USB port built into it, the mini USB port that the phone
clicks into and then it snaps in and now it's in virtual reality mode and it has a light
sensor in the headset so it detects when I have the headset on and right now I'm in
a Samsung Gear VR theater room where I have an Oculus library in front of me of different
games that are built on the Oculus platform that I can pull from.
I also have movies that I can watch and what's truly, truly, truly amazing and thrilling
is what I expected to be really fascinating about this was the gaming and the tourism
element of it.
They have amazing photos, like there's a tour of London and a tour of Paris and they have,
of course, they have space travel, which is virtual, but Wes, as you saw, it's very impressive.
Oh yeah, definitely.
So I'd be interested to hear more from Wes, given that you're in the studio and you can
actually see this thing and you're an impartial observer.
You can play with it and it might be hard with the headphones, but yeah, so Wes, you
got to, let's see, you did the, and it does work a lot better if you have headphones,
so Wes is going to have to kind of compromise on that for this part of it, but what was
your impressions of it?
Actually, I was very impressed, you know, it's sturdily made, clearly they had at least
one industrial designer on this thing, it's like, you know, kind of the opposite of the
cardboard in that respect, lightweight and...
It does feel really well built, huh?
It does feel really well built.
Yeah.
You know, it's solid, it fits well.
It's interesting, it's got a touch pad built into the side of it, it's got an Android back
button and then on the other side, it's got a tiny little fan that you don't really hear.
No, I didn't hear it at all.
What did you think of the graphics?
You know, it was, there were a little blurry at times, but a little screen door effect
at times.
A little screen door effect, but otherwise, it was very smooth, it was very engaging,
you know, it fits really well on your head and so just being able to look around and,
you know, we were sitting in the restaurant having probably a million people gawk at us,
but...
Yeah, yeah, we did it.
Yeah.
I really had no idea, you know, I could have been anywhere.
That's how geeky we are, you guys, is at the restaurant.
I was at the restaurant, I had Wes try it out.
Now, Wes, I want you to try something that you didn't get a chance to try out yet, and
this is truly one of the most incredible experiences I ever had for virtual reality.
This is going to put you on stage during a Coldplay conference, and I don't know if you're
a Coldplay fan, and this is going to be a little hard for you to see, but they have
a 360 degree camera, yeah, so now what do you think of that?
Oh, wow.
Now, you can look all around, and I want you to go until they launch the paper on the stage.
Isn't that amazing?
Look at him dancing there, and you see all the different bands playing.
Oh, yeah, you know, the resolution's really not bad.
Yeah, for real video, it's quite good.
Yeah, smooth, very little blur.
It's not surprising that the two largest install bases so far are Cardboard and Gear VR, experience
oriented.
Yeah.
You can look around and see all the people dancing in the crowd, and yeah, isn't that
a...
Sounds pretty cool, except for the Coldplay part.
Yeah, the Coldplay part's a bit rough, but it's a pretty neat experience to see these
guys and, you know, to see them dance right in front of you, you can even see his man
boobs jiggle.
Yeah, it's very much that.
Yeah.
Oh, wow, yeah, here comes the paper.
Yeah, isn't that neat?
Oh, wow, yeah.
That's really something.
It kind of surprises you, honestly.
That's awesome.
Yeah, and so what's great about it is in theater mode, you get a full 3D experience.
It's better than any kind of movie theater experience, because it's truly, you know,
you're truly immersed in the whole thing.
Here, let me...
Honestly, I would rather watch things on a TV.
Hold on, I'll turn your mic on.
Sorry.
There you go.
Say again, Wes?
I would probably rather watch some things on that than on a TV.
It's way more engaging.
I watched some movies last night on this, and it is, and you know, if you want to watch
something 3D, screw a 3D television.
This is where it's at.
And way less of an investment.
Well, if you have an S6.
It runs off the power of the phone, which is good and bad, because it does drain the
phone, but it means that all you have to do is take the phone and this, and if you're
going on an airplane for traveling or a train, this would be, yeah, it's a theater wherever
you go.
So what do you think, Wimpy?
Are you impressed?
Can you charge...
I'm interested.
I don't know if I'm impressed yet.
I've got some more questions for you.
Can you plug a, you know, an external charger into the phone whilst using it?
Yes.
There's a little mini USB port on the bottom of the VR that you could plug in, and that
would supply power to the phone, too.
So if you were doing your train journey or your flight, you could power the thing as
your phone case.
Yeah, or maybe even just run it off like a portable battery.
And for those of us that have not seen these, is this the shutter effect 3D, or is it polarized
glass effect?
I don't know if it's either, to be honest.
I don't know.
That's a good question.
Yeah, I don't know exactly how they do it.
It may be a shutter effect.
So you know, what's happening on a technical level is the galaxy screen goes into like
a stereo optical mode, and then there's lenses in the VR that tune those in.
And I don't know how it does it, but it is a very immersive 3D experience, you know.
It's full...
So is it half the screen for one eye and half the screen for the other eye, effectively,
that then the lens filters?
I don't know.
I don't actually think that is the case.
I don't think so, but I don't know how it works well enough.
The fact that you don't know bodes well.
Yeah, and I think part of it is the screen resolution is so high to begin with, right,
that it's way higher than...
It's like a...
I forget what it is off the top of my head, but even if you had to bring it down, it would
still be probably higher than 1080p.
Both Cardboard and Gear VR do have a divider, so it must be splitting the screen in half.
Yeah, every now and then when I pull the phone out, I've seen it like in sort of like stereo
optical mode, and it's kind of funny looking on screen and the screen snaps out of it.
And you know, if you run it for about 45 minutes to an hour, it'll start to say, oh, it's too
hot depending on what you've been doing.
Take the phone out for a while, and you gotta take the phone out.
So you need two.
Yeah.
Swap them into two.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 101 for July 14, 2015.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that just finished a virtual tour
of the solar system.
And man, Jupiter was beautiful.
My name is Chris, and joining me in studio, Wes is back.
Hey, Wes.
Hey, guys.
Hey, how you doing, buddy?
How you having me?
Good.
You don't have food coma, right?
Oh, no.
I'm good.
The beer's helping a lot.
Yeah, the beer helps, right?
It's like, it's the opposite of caffeine, but for some reason it wakes you up.
I don't know how that works.
We'll just keep telling ourselves that.
Well, I don't know about that.
But coming up on today's episode of Linux Unplugged, I'll tell you what I do know about.
There is some big news happening in one of our most beloved things to hate.
That's Flash.
We're gonna talk about the big changes coming to Flash and how it's gonna affect Linux users.
Coming up in the show, a really, really, really well-done write-up about a KDE user who spent
a week in Gnome, and he was able to put his thoughts in a way that really resonated with
me and a lot of people in the audience.
I'm getting a lot of feedback on this write-up, and I want to talk about it today with our
virtual lug.
And then after that, OpenSUSE, so we've talked about it a little bit on the Linux Action
Show, we've talked about it a little bit on this show, OpenSUSE 42.
It's a big new proposal, big dreams, a lot of changes coming.
The success of Tumbleweed has made OpenSUSE re-evaluate the OpenSUSE project, and we covered
that on Sunday's show.
But I think maybe some people didn't like our opinion or have a different opinion.
We're gonna cover that feedback and discuss the nuances there, and I think it's gonna
be a really, really fascinating discussion.
But Wes, before we get to all of that, we actually have some really great emails we're
gonna read this week, since in 100 we didn't read any feedback.
So let's get into all of this.
Let's invite in the virtual lug.
Time-appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Good morning.
Good afternoon.
And it's the evening.
So, guys, we have so much to cover today, and maybe it's the beer, maybe it's because
we just started the show, but it's starting to get warm in here.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Okay.
Roasty toast.
You know I'm not making it up, either.
It is warm in here.
It's nice to have somebody who validates it like, yeah, Chris is not making it up.
All right.
Earl writes in, and I love this.
Do you guys remember the conversation we had around Linux Mint?
Last week we had the review, and the week before that we had a conversation, is it too
boring for us Linux users?
Is Mint going the direction that maybe long-term is going to kind of leave it behind?
Or is that exactly the sweet spot?
Well, Earl writes in, and he has a very interesting perspective.
He says, hi, Chris, in the Mumble Room.
He says, I'm a 70-year-old Linux Mint user.
He says, I started Linux in early 2003 by installing Debian on a Savage Spark 64.
What a chore and a lot of fun.
I installed Debian on a Savage dual processor P2 later on.
That was an awesome experience, but yet another challenging task.
Then I discovered Ubuntu 4.10.
By Ubuntu 5.10, I'd switched to Linux completely, and in 2007, I bought a Dell laptop with Linux
installed on there, and I used GNOME 2.
When Ubuntu moved to Unity, I moved to Linux Mint.
I've been running Linux Mint with Mate ever since.
Not a real tech geek, but I still feel I have some knowledge, and I wanted to comment.
Mint Mate Edition doesn't get in my way.
It just works.
It's not about the desktop.
It's about the programs and what I can do.
I like the desktop, and I like the fact it doesn't change every month or so, other than
maybe a few improvements when a new release comes out.
I like that it doesn't keep changing things underneath me.
It just keeps improving, and it works.
Maybe it's boring, but it works.
It also is about the community.
I love this point.
Clem keeps the users informed about what he and the team are doing and why they are doing
it.
He responds to user input.
He addresses user issues personally.
I've had some users on Linux Mint.
I've had some users on Linux Mint, I guess, as you pointed out.
He says, I'm a brand.
All the computers are Savage, no latest and greatest.
They all are just great desktops.
I keep experimenting with distros, but nothing's replaced Mint Mate for me for reliability and
ease of use.
So he says a lot of users in this respect need this, and I completely agree.
He says I watch all of the shows, and the Savage HP has a crappy video card, so he downloads
and then watches what he calls his Linux soaps later, or his friends called him that.
I love it.
That's great.
Clem writes in with his perspective on why Linux Mint for a 70-year-old is just the right
distro.
That makes sense, right?
Totally makes sense.
And we kind of said that.
What distro do you use?
I use Arch.
Oh, really?
Well, there you go.
I do have Mint deployed at work, though, and I will say I just need to use an application.
It's there.
It has very similar key bindings.
You can do a lot of things you can if you're coming from Windows or you're coming from
Linux.
So when you say you have Mint deployed, like Mint is your desktop at work?
Yes, for one of my machines.
And then at home you're running Arch?
Yes.
Oh, I got you.
And Rotten Corpse, you're running Mint right now?
Yeah.
I actually dropped Arch and went to Mint.
What?
Tell me about this.
Yeah.
Well, okay.
So I've been using KDE for the past couple months, and I was trying to test it out because
I'm a huge GNOME fanboy, and I wanted to stop talking out of my butt about KDE.
So I started using it, like deep dive, full in, everything.
Oh, you're going to be perfect for today's episode, then.
I guess so.
And I've actually changed my opinion of KDE a lot, and I am now a huge fan of KDE.
There are certain things that I can't stand, but KWin, for example, is fantastic, but that's
not the point.
Yeah.
We'll get to that, though.
The reason why is because when I was using Arch in February, Arch destroyed KDE, like
unusable breakage.
So I did some updates, I did some bug fixes, I sent some workarounds and things like that.
And after about 20 of those, I got sick of it and just left.
So I wanted to see, okay, maybe Debian, you know, Debian is the de facto standard of not
breaking anything.
Right.
Good, old, stable, steady, true Debian.
Yeah.
So I was on Debian.
I actually went to CID because I wanted to get the latest versions of things.
Naturally.
So, you know, technically, Debian has really good rolling compatibility, and it's actually
more stable because they take, even though their stuff is rolling, they take longer to
test things, even in the unstable branches.
So then when I get the update for KDE, I was like, let's see if Debian has messed anything
up.
I'm curious now.
So when I check it, I see if there's any bugs, no bug reported.
Then I pull in all of the KDE's new stuff, and it destroys pretty much everything.
Like to the point where system settings, the most important application, doesn't work.
Oh, geez.
Like, it doesn't even show you any of the settings.
All of them are gone.
And now, when I went back like a week later after I was laughing about it, because now
it's just hilarious that all of these transitional things are just breaking everywhere, I went
to look at the bug support, bug reports, and it said, completely unusable, on the report
of it.
So then I was like, okay, well, Kubuntu, you know, they don't update that much, you know.
Yeah, it's also broken, because they went to 5.2, which is not ready, and they broke
it.
Yeah.
So Kubuntu right now is just a mess.
So this is why you ended up on Mint?
Yeah, because Mint hasn't broken anything, because they haven't updated much of it in
a long time.
Funny how that works.
Yeah, they haven't broken anything for the core.
So like, this transitional phase between 4 and 5 is like, just, it's just crazy to the
point where right now, it's not a reasonable solution until, unless you stay on 4 and you
don't update to framework 5, or you just go straight to 5 and deal with the bugs, trying
to do this weird combination thing, it does not work.
So I'm on Mint 17.1, because they don't have a KDE version for 17.2 right now, and I am
perfectly happy with stuff not breaking.
I think it echoes what Linus says a lot, you know, what his views on his kernel is, you
know, get out of the way, let people run the applications they want to run.
Yeah.
Yeah, Mint is very much a distro like that.
And you know what?
I think my argument mostly wasn't around that there isn't a place for it, because I don't
argue that at all.
My argument was more, if I was going to cold recommend a distro to somebody, and I felt
like they were the type of user that wanted that environment, which would be a lot of
new users, Windows switchers, enterprise users, a lot of people, or like Earl, right?
I think I would recommend Ubuntu Mate.
I do not think I would necessarily recommend Mint necessarily.
Mostly because I would, if it was a perfect world, I would like to be able to just recommend
vanilla Ubuntu.
Just go download the Ubuntu ISO and use that.
However, I'm not convinced that Unity 7 is something I want to start switching people
to right now at this point in time.
And also the search scopes are still embarrassing.
Like we actually had a problem this week when we were trying to shoot a screen cap for Linux
action show, and the first time through, like bra and underwear came up in the search scope.
And it's like, really?
We don't really want to put bra and underwear?
I mean, it's kind of funny, but at the same time it's like, really?
We're trying to have a professional demonstration here and bra and underwear is coming up in
our search results.
And I just don't want to recommend that to somebody, but I want to stay as close to the
upstream distro, so an official flavor to me seems like a pretty logical choice.
And the Mate desktop environments, classic desktop environment, people are very familiar
with it.
You can get the LTS version.
When I stack that up against Mint, I'm not quite sure why I would recommend Mint over
the other, other than they do take care of some of the other niceties.
And like Earl said, Clems, like I really, if I was in Earl's position, I would like
to be able to have a community leader who was also very clear and very transparent,
and that would be something that would appeal to me too.
But yeah, mumble.
Any other thoughts on that before we move on to our next email, which is really kind
of one that made me think?
Going once?
Yeah, I'd like to say I agree with the official flavor thing.
The only reason I'm not, I'm using Mint right now is because the Kubuntu thing's weird.
But if somebody wanted Mate, absolutely, Ubuntu Mate is the better option.
I think the only other reason for Mint right now would be if somebody wanted Cinnamon.
That's what I'm using.
Yeah.
Okay.
I mean, my work machine has a business card.
And how is that?
So, it handles it very well, actually.
Yeah.
Three display point monitors, hardly ever a glitch.
Yeah, and Cinnamon's a pretty good environment for like a, for sort of a parallel to, somewhere
between Gnome and KDE.
Yeah.
A lot of people I work with kind of come from a Windows background as well.
And so, you know, you can split Windows up on the four sides.
You have some start bar.
Yeah.
It has some graphical niceties that they're used to.
Mumble room?
Any more?
Chris, I was wondering, are we getting to a point where anybody that's just a casual
user or interested in getting work done should be on an LTS?
And the only people that we recommend rolling to are people that are looking for the latest
and greatest teacher or have a specific hardware support issue?
That's a great question.
I think you should recommend rolling to anyone unless they want it, they ask you for it.
I think we should answer that question.
I think we should see if we can answer that question when we get to the OpenSUSE follow-up.
Because that's exactly the question OpenSUSE says, so you're going to have Tumbleweed,
which is a rolling release.
They're going to, oh, they claim it's going to be the world's first stable rolling release
because only things go into the rolling release after they've been fully tested by our magic
testing system.
That's according to them.
So they're going to have rolling releases, then they're going to have OpenSUSE, which
is going to be somewhere in between a real steady enterprise distro, but it's going to
be sourced from an enterprise distro.
So that's kind of going to be somewhere like in the CentOS range of type products, somewhere
between CentOS and Fedora if I'm following.
And of course, we're going to talk about all this in a minute.
And then you're going to have, of course, the SLE, the SUSE Linux Enterprise editions.
And what you just said, that could be where OpenSUSE is going to fit very, very nicely
potentially.
So we'll just have to, but maybe not.
And maybe I have that wrong.
We'll talk about that in the SUSE segment.
But first, I want to get to Stefan's email.
This one got me thinking, long time listener, he says, huge fan of just about all of the
shows.
I'm sure he meant all of them, not just about.
Of course.
He says, I'm writing because the conversation around privacy and trusting your data and
information, especially with companies like Google, seems to always result in, and this
is his quote here, we shouldn't because that's just creepy.
We feel that it's not morally right for companies to sell or use our data in order to serve
free products and services, to which I do agree, or at least I think I do.
Would it be possible for you to talk about why exactly this is not okay?
What are we afraid of?
Why should we take so good care of our privacy and personal information in the first place?
Is it all just aggregated?
And isn't it all just being aggregated and impersonalized by a bunch of computers anyways
and grouped together with thousands of other people's information?
Has this just become a principle that storing user data is wrong?
Why is this fight so important to fight?
We want technology to engage with us in every aspect of our life, yet the companies developing
these technologies are not allowed to know anything about us?
That doesn't sound about right.
Why is my weight, age, sex, height, favorite food, most used train station, travel history,
etc., so damn important that I should know them and only I should know them?
And again, is that really privacy?
Best regards, Stefan, and keep up the amazing work.
What a fast, why, Wes, what do you think?
Do you ever get creeped out about Google?
You know, they are somewhat integrated.
I do appreciate his argument.
I was installing Telegram on my girlfriend's iPhone the other day.
You know, I've been using it with some of my friends, and she wanted to use it too.
And I was telling her about some of the encryption, and I'd used TechSecure before.
And whenever I mention encryption, she does kind of just laugh.
You know, she understands, but...
Not a priority for her.
Not at all.
Yeah.
I don't think she has any problem with Google, you know, knowing every little bit about her.
I waffle on this.
I go back and forth.
I do too.
Sometimes I think it's really a great service, and how can you have JARVIS and Star Trek
Enterprise computer system and all these things without that data collection?
At the same time, though, I think I have put my finger on what creeps me out about it,
but I'm going to hold on to that for a second.
I'll let Wimpy jump in.
Wimpy, you go first.
What do you think?
What's your take on this topic?
Well, I live in the UK.
And the UK is doing some crazy things at the moment.
So our government believes that the UK citizens have no right to electronic privacy anymore.
And I would say that this is important because if your civil liberties and your privacy are
eroded bit by bit, piece by piece, and you don't think it's important, these are just
stepping stones.
And it might not be this thing or the next thing, but maybe the thing after that or the
thing after that is the thing that you think is too much, too far, that encroaches into
your life.
And certainly in the UK, if they're going to ban, in air quotes, some of these encrypted
messaging platforms, which we've now concluded is basically anything that's encrypted, then
that gives people the right to, or gives the government the right to potentially siphon
and archive your message streams that you're using over encrypted channels, such as like
Facebook Messenger.
So if your family is using Facebook Messenger to send photographs of your family members
and your children backwards and forwards, and the government is taking a feed off that
and doing percentage of flesh tone analysis, is your account now being flagged up because
you've got young children that are prone to taking off all their clothes and running around
in the garden naked?
And do you now look like a suspicious individual?
And should you not have a right to privacy?
I wonder about that same thing.
Like if my wife sends me a picture of our daughter's butt in the bathtub, and that goes
through Hangouts, and they're analyzing everything that goes through Hangouts, is there some
algorithm analyzing my daughter's butt and flagging my account for having nudity in my
...
That's a good question.
How do I know?
Exactly.
I think that's a big part, too, is for right now with the technology we have, maybe there
aren't that many ramifications, but we don't know what kind of retention policies maybe
are in effect.
It's a huge part of it.
You can recognize people based on iris scans, face profiles.
I'm not trying to be a conspiracy theorist, but...
The computing power just keeps getting better and better.
Right.
The map produced these things, and you can learn a lot.
Wimpy, also there's a certain amount of power a company like Google has when they know everybody
I'm with, every location I'm at all the time.
Does that concern you?
To some extent, more so if now governments are wanting to put hooks into organizations
such as Google and Facebook, because there's a proven track record of people that work
for the security services to not be discreet in the way that they access this data for
lulls and giggles.
Your stuff isn't private anymore, because they're just perusing over it when it takes
their fancy, and that seems to be.
The only papers I've seen published about that were from North America, but it seemed
to be an alarming number of people that had abused that privilege.
Yes.
That's a good point.
The people that are in that position sometimes abuse that.
Ubi, you want to take the other side of the fence as somebody who's not quite as concerned
about privacy, right?
To be honest, I am quite concerned about privacy, but I know people who aren't, as a lot of
people do.
A point that I find hard to argue against, maybe there can be some ideas here, is why
care because there's so much data they're collecting that they won't be interested in
looking at mine?
Because it's not individuals looking at your data, it's computers looking at the data in
aggregate, and computers are flawed, and so my example of flesh tone analysis is a real
example where your legitimate and legal use of a service could flag your account as being
suspicious and now you're under observation for doing nothing wrong.
It's not that you've got nothing to hide, it's that you shouldn't have anything that
people are prying upon.
I mean, if the UK government suddenly want to conduct all of their communications in
the clear, then I'll back their proposals, but until they do that, it's a nonsense.
Yeah, that's interesting.
Just as easily as computers can anonymize the data, they can also de-anonymize it.
Yes, very good point.
Okay, so here's kind of where I come down on it, and I think about like the long-term
picture here, and I think what Wes was kind of touching on is like computing power is
only going to get better, storage is only going to get greater, and they can keep this
stuff for years and years and years, and sometimes what you find when you read through history
is what we find to be sort of totally acceptable and okay today will not necessarily be totally
fine and acceptable 20 years ago.
And when I think about my son and my daughters, who will, my son, for God's sakes, already
has like a children's Google account.
Oh, wow.
Yeah, because he's at school and he's six years old, and now he can get on YouTube and
look at like a kid's version of YouTube.
He already has a Google account.
Now I know they have different policies for how they track children, but in a large sense,
my son at six years old has already begun getting just about everything he does online
logged.
Does the 20-year-old him feel that he really consented to do that?
Right.
And will 20-year-old him really want to be, you know, like once it's recorded, it never
goes away.
Exactly.
And people change a lot, and it's just to have all of that on file and then to have
this AI that can sit back there and analyze it and determine what kind of person you are
so that way they can better target dick pills at you.
I just don't find it to be a valuable trade.
It's not worth it for me.
Sunsol, you think the convenience does trump in the end?
I mean, it appears to be so far, right?
Yeah.
I mean, I think like let's just be frank.
Like when you get a cell phone, your privacy is out.
You know what I mean?
Like once you turn on that phone, like you've almost given a lot of your privacy away.
That's true, huh?
I mean, not trying to, you know, be the devil's advocate here, but it's just that like users
really love convenience.
You know what I mean?
Like just whether it's your Siri, iPhone, whether it's Google on your cell phone or
whatever it is, like just having that convenience to get data at your fingertips is what users
really like.
Yeah.
Or you know what?
You could zoom out.
I mean, phones is what's on our mind really, but it's if you use a credit card, you know,
a bank account, all this stuff, there's data brokers that are aggregating all of it, but
that's a great point.
Wimpy, I want to give you the final word and then we'll move on to some other Linuxy feedback,
but I want to give you one last chance to jump in.
So cryptography allows us the facility to have non-repudiation, which is to prove that
I sent something and it hasn't been tampered with.
In the meantime, a hacking team were beautifully hacked last week.
The delicious irony of that is not lost upon me, but one of the products that they sell
is a product that deliberately injects false evidence into a target's computer system so
that they can be tried in a, air quotes, court of law.
And if we are now in a position where you have no expectation of privacy and encryption
is not a tool that's open to you, then what's going to happen in some of these oppressive
regimes or even in the UK if they decide that they don't, you know, you're not flavor of
the month anymore.
It makes it all the easier to actually inject evidence, you know, false evidence into your
system.
Hmm.
Yeah.
And Corky makes a great point in the chat room.
He can't join because there's a ping spike, but he says, when data is permanent, you have
to hope that every single executive or CEO or government that has access to that data
does not use it against you.
One government gone wrong could have a large leverage to prosecute you or prison you or
to destroy your reputation or to silence you.
That's a big part, too.
Corporations go bankrupt and sell off their assets that, you know, you might trust Google
to have that, but the person who buys Google in 30 years, you don't like someone.
Or when Larry and Sergey step down, does the new guy that runs the place have a different
concern about how much privacy users get to enjoy?
Well, I think this is fascinating.
You know what?
I see NorthRanger has a topic.
We'll pick it up in the post show, too, if you guys want.
It's a fascinating topic, but I want to get to some of the other Linux emails we've gotten,
but it's one that, you know, privacy and security is a huge reason why we use open source in
Linux, so I don't think it's a conversation that is not worth having.
I just think we have to bide our time, but we'll do more in the post show.
That sounds pretty fascinating.
I wanted to get to an email that came into the show about, well, about Flash, to be honest,
in a sense.
But sometimes people that want to watch our show have to use a proprietary technology
to do so.
Like maybe you're going to watch an HD64 encoded video, or maybe you're going to watch the
live Flash stream.
Well, some big, big developments are happening this week, really big, actually, today that
may finally change this for good, I hope.
And a very public company and two very public browsers are taking a very public position
on all of that.
But before we talk about, hopefully, the final death of Flash, I want to mention our friends
at Ting.
Go to linux.ting.com.
Now, when Wes got here the other day, he was like, geez, Chris, how many phones do you got?
And I was like, Wes, man, I got plenty of phones.
Why?
Because it's $6 a line.
Yeah, I love Ting.
So I've got right now in my hot hands right here, I've got the Galaxy S6.
And it's been a really great phone for me.
It's recently available on the Ting network.
And here's what's fantastic about Ting.
You only pay for what you use.
Ting takes your minutes, your messages, and your megabytes, and they add them all up.
Whatever bucket you fall into, that's all you've got to pay.
And it's just $6 for the line and then the taxes.
So it makes it very economical to have several lines if you've got like a family, or maybe
you have a small business and you want to give folks in your business some lines.
Or in my case, when we had a nanny for a short period of time, I got her a phone.
And it sounds like, oh my gosh, you're such a baller.
Well, no.
You can get an unlocked phone for under $100, and it's $6 for the line, and you just pay
for your usage on top of that.
And then what's really fantastic about Ting is the way their business is structured, they're
really able to focus on the customer.
And so they're able to build out additional functionality that most carriers wouldn't
bother with.
Like they have really great mobile applications and a fantastic web UI to manage all of this.
It's really good stuff.
And they have no hold customer service.
You can call them at 1-855-TING-FTW, and a real person answers the phone.
Now here's the core essentials that I love about Ting.
Unlocked phones, you own them outright, and you're only paying for what you use.
Like hotspot tethering, it's all built in.
So no more like prepaying for like, oh, I might use 800 minutes, so I better buy the
1,000 minute plan, like that kind of crap.
Or like I might need three gigs of data, but they only offer six gigs if I need that much
data.
That is done.
And really, it is so liberating when you realize that once I get the phone and I do all that,
that's done.
Like that's the hardest part.
I'm easy.
I'm ready to go.
And here's the best part.
When you go to linux.ting.com, you're going to take $25 off an unlocked device.
And if you've got a Ting-compatible device, and there's a whole S-ton of Ting-compatible
devices, because check this out, they've got a GSM network and a CDMA network.
And if you get a fancy phone, you can swap between the networks.
I've done that with the Nexus 5, for example.
So you get these phones.
They're unlocked.
And if you get your phone to a high-end like Nexus 6 or Moto X2 or, I don't know, the OnePlus
or the S6 or iPhone 6, whatever you want to get, Ting's got it.
And then you're on the plan and you're done.
The hard part's over.
And that's not even that hard.
$6 a month, pay for what you use, call them any time you've got an issue.
It's really slick.
Go to linux.ting.com.
That supports the show and gets you the discount.
Also, this is a really slick way to go if you want like a MiFi device.
If you're in any kind of job or if you just have a need for a high level of connectivity,
what a great way to do this at an incredible value, because you're only paying for what
you use with Ting.
So go get a MiFi device, you buy it once, and then it's just $6 a month and then any
data usage.
As an independent contractor when I was doing IT, I had this really expensive MiFi device
from one of the duopoly mobile providers.
And I lived with the guilt every time it sat in my drawer for like a couple of weeks and
I didn't use it.
I could hear Angela in the back of my mind, that's a waste of money, that thing costs
us $60 a month, how come you're not using it right now?
And I would just like bring it with me just in case I might need it because I am paying
so much money for it and I wouldn't use it.
Now this is gone with Ting because you're only paying for what you use.
If you don't use the MiFi device, it's just $6 for the line, but here's the even better
part.
I can't even believe Ting let you do this.
You can just turn the line off for a while.
You can just turn it off.
How slick is that?
Go to linux.ting.com to get started, check out their dashboard, they have a savings calculator
there.
Also, while you're there, peruse their blog.
They've got great app pics, they have an unboxing of the Moto E second gen edition and they
also have app pics there as always and like tips for Google Maps, really cool stuff.
Linux.ting.com and a huge, huge thank you to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged
program.
Linux.ting.com and thanks to everybody who visits that because that supports the show
and lets Ting know that you appreciate them keeping us on the air.
Right Wes?
Oh yeah.
Hey, thank you for grabbing me another beer, sir.
I really appreciate that.
My pleasure.
All right.
So we got a little bit more feedback.
I kind of want to pick up the pace just a tad because I want to get to some of the big
topics today, but let's talk about this huge, huge, huge story and I want to start, kick
it off with a piece of feedback that I get almost at least a weekly basis, more often
in the chat room on a daily basis.
So this came in from Yellow Mango, which is kind of funny, he says, while setting up my
new Fedora install, I went to add my favorite podcast to Rhythmbox.
Oh, thanks man.
And however, when I went to play the video, I noticed I needed to download a decoder.
The decoder just happens to be a non-free one.
Why in the world is an open source focused podcast using a non-free encoding?
Maybe there's a legitimate reason I just don't know about it.
And this comes in in a couple of different phases or different ways like you guys have
a flash player, for example, like our livestream.
And Wes, what are your thoughts on when it comes down to this codec stuff?
Do you have a hard line on this at all?
I mean, I definitely follow the people over at Ziff.org, you know, Monty and his wonderful
demos and I would love for open source and free codecs to rule the world, but I think
the top commenter in this Reddit post does have a certain point that...
What did he say?
I didn't see that.
He said, because he wants to actually be discovered and watched by 95% of the world who live in
proprietary prisons, which unfortunately many people do.
Oh, there is a sort of a sick truth to that.
There is definitely a sick truth to that.
So yeah, we do actually pretty make...
We make every show available in WebM.
Yeah, which is awesome.
But we don't necessarily make it available for direct download.
We, in most cases, make it available via torrent, which is linked in the show notes in most
cases.
The thing is, is we've not been very happy with WebM, so it costs us a lot to store it
and distribute it.
It actually costs us more to distribute a 420p version of a show in WebM than it does
to distribute a 720p version of the show in x264.
So it is only because we want to see open standards progress that we actually pay...
WebM is the most expensive thing we distribute.
So it is...
Kudos to you guys.
Well, it makes HTML5 playback work, so that's another reason why we have to do it.
And then Rekai can attest to the fact that it is by far, by far, by far the slowest file
to encode.
We can get...
We could crank out four HD versions almost of a show in the time it takes one 420p WebM
version to come out.
Almost four versions of the HD version in the time it takes one WebM version to be encoded,
almost that long.
And so this, though, often comes up in terms of our jblive.tv live stream, which is powered
by Flash, because really, live streaming...
We have other options, in fact.
By the end of this segment, I think we should all just disable Flash in our computers for
a week and see if it works.
Amen.
Go to jblive.tv and grab the RTMP or HLS stream and watch it MPV or VLC.
So I'll say that up front.
But we do have one Flash player on the Jupyter broadcasting site, and that's our live player.
Well, today, depending on what browser you're in, you may have had troubles loading the
live stream, because Mozilla, and I think Google Chrome too today, have started blocking
Flash, just as Facebook's security chief calls for its death, all in light of the hacking
group that Wimpy was just talking about getting hacked and zero-day Flash vulnerabilities
being splashed all over the Web.
Adobe's been scrambling to patch these new zero-day vulnerabilities, and in response
to that, the Facebook security chief has taken up the Steve Jobs mantle of saying, kill Flash,
kill Flash, and is proclaiming its death.
He says the time is now, and in response, Mozilla is disabling Flash because the zero-day
is affecting Flash installations right now as we record this show.
There's a lot of stuff happening here.
Do you think the Web is ready for Flash to die, Wes?
I really wish that it was.
Personally, I am.
I don't think I need it.
But I recognize there are a lot of users with random use cases, like, oh, my one banking
company requires me to use Flash for this login form, or who knows.
But I feel like we hear a lot about those one-time uses.
Wimpy, I bet you have a few of those use cases in mind, don't you?
Mr. Wimpy?
Oh, sorry.
Oh, there you go.
Yep.
Thank you.
So can you hear me?
Yep.
We got you.
Yeah.
Can you hear?
OK.
Yeah.
In the UK, Amazon Prime, the BBC, ITV, Channel 4, Channel 5, and catch-up TV services all
use Flash.
Some of them even use the DRM module in Flash, which is no longer supported on most Linux
systems because HAL went away that used to provide that little crypto stub.
So if Flash goes away, then all of the major UK streaming services cease to be relevant
for Linux users because there is no other option.
Wow.
You know, the only one that continues to work is Netflix using Google Chrome, which is also
proprietary.
But this is not about Flash on Linux.
This is a Flash in general, and that Mozilla and Google are blocking it across the platform.
So yeah, but the same is true.
These services, with the exception of Amazon Prime, which you can use Silverlight for on
Windows, all of those other streaming services require Flash regardless of whether you're
on Windows or Linux.
Right.
But I'd rather Flash die and those services not work and make them actually use something
that isn't garbage for a downtime of like a month or two than to just throw your hands
up and give up.
Yeah, those services aren't going to change in a hurry.
Well, let me, let me, let's just, as for, just for fun discussion purposes.
If anyone was going to move away from Flash, people have started doing it more aggressively.
But don't you think now, Wimpy, with them disabling it in Firefox and things like that,
don't you think that's going to accelerate, because this, like Rotten said, this isn't
a Linux thing.
This is everybody.
And plus, the iOS platform and Android platforms are not Flash friendly still, so there's incentive
to get off there.
Do you think this push could do it?
Hopefully.
I mean, if it was just Mozilla doing it, then, you know, there'd be a, you know, you couldn't
guarantee it.
But the fact that Google is joining the force.
And Facebook, I think, Facebook too.
And it's going to put a huge dent in Flash and hopefully even kill it.
So I think here, it's pretty obvious, the streaming services are the ones still rely
on Flash.
Yes, yes, yes.
But if you access the streaming services through a mobile phone nowadays, you already see that
they don't really require Flash.
So currently, Flash is there for convenience.
Well, I'll tell you this, unfortunately, so the way it works currently, and man, Alan,
it would be way better explaining this.
He does a great job explaining this.
But the way it works on mobile currently, most of the time, well, I think every time,
it is delivered, live video is delivered via HLS.
And HLS, and I'm sorry, I'm not going to explain this as well as Noah, or I'm sorry, as well
as Alan would.
But HLS, what it essentially does is it takes H.264 video and MP3 or AAC audio, whatever
your audio is, and it wraps it in tiny M3U playlist files.
Yeah, oh, you know how this works?
I've streamed from it before.
So HLS is about as proprietary as it gets, because it's using H.264, and it's really
very clunky.
Yes.
Because what the player is doing on the other end is it's constantly cycling the playlist
files.
Constantly pinging to download the newest playlist.
Yeah.
It's pulling the playlist file, pulling the playlist file, and then loading that into
the player, and playing it as fast as it can, and pulling down the playlist file and loading
it into the player, and playing it as fast as it can, and it's really dumb.
Yes.
And easy to lose the stream too.
And so you get, and on a mobile, you get a little hiccup there, and you know, you lose
some of that playlist file, one of the playlist files, and you just drop the whole stream.
And so we don't really have a solid, ready to go live Flash replacement yet.
And anybody who watches this show in VLC sometimes notices that MPV handles it a little bit better,
but yeah.
I honestly used the Flash player when I first started watching, because VLC couldn't keep
up.
It's definitely better now.
Mm-hmm.
But MPV is great too.
I heard somebody, and they're going ahead.
I don't like, I don't like VLC at all.
Actually, I think that its streaming features are so clunky that it gets way more hype than
it deserves on, at least on Linux.
Maybe on Windows there's nothing better, but on Linux there's a lot.
Now Wimby, very true.
I have had not that experience.
Oh, go ahead Daryl.
I was just saying that I have had, I haven't had that experience with, regarding to VLC.
I'm pretty sure that that's a discussion for another show.
Yeah, we could.
Yeah, we could have another.
Wimby, do you, are you joking, or do you really think that if we prematurely kill Flash, which
I can't even believe I'm going to say that, but let's just argue that maybe it's too soon.
If we prematurely killed Flash, do you really think people would jump to another proprietary
alternative like Silverlight, or is it like H.264, are we just going to lock in some other
proprietary garbage if we kill Flash right now?
That was for you, Wimby, if you're still there.
I don't mind proprietary garbage.
Yeah, I am.
I think there's a bit of lag on the line here.
I'm not sure if it's me or someone else anyway.
I'm not sure, I don't mind which proprietary solution people pick so long as it's one that
runs on multiple platforms.
So I don't have a problem with H.264 because Cisco are backing the licenses for that being
embedded into Firefox, for example.
So our rule, Gabe, I'm not pro-proprietary, I'm just pragmatic.
If the only way Linux users are going to have access to premium content which is going to
be DRM encumbered, then at least give us a level playing field so we can all access it.
But there is a new streaming service, a Netflix-alike service in the UK that launched on Silverlight,
and that was only nine months ago.
So yes, there are organizations that still go for Silverlight solutions, even on new
products.
I know, just it's crazy, isn't it?
I would say, I want to take the DRM discussion, I just want to table it, yes, I agree DRM
is bad, and I also agree proprietary garbage is bad.
And if you don't want to watch DRM content and proprietary garbage, the solution isn't
in what the browsers are implementing, the solution is in the customer stop paying for
it and stop watching it.
So if you want DRM to change and you don't want proprietary garbage, you got to change
what you do and let the market follow it.
And that's a hard thing to actually, it's easier said than done when you say something
like that.
But I think that's the silver bullet to DRM, not convincing these companies.
Or just cross-platform proprietary garbage.
Yeah, that's what I'm saying.
That gives everybody a chance to at least play, at least until we stop using it.
Yeah, I agree.
I do have to say that potentially in the near future, the new copyright directive on the
new level will actually kill DRM with copyright legislation.
Because it's currently seen as breaking the exceptions to copying your private copy.
So it will have to be dropped.
That'll be fascinating to watch.
Thanks guys.
All right, so let's shift gears and talk about this gentleman who was a hardcore KDE user.
And he tried out Gnome for a week and then wrote up about it.
And I saw this article and I thought, oh, here's some clickbait.
And I read through it and I went, that was really well done.
Really articulate.
And I want to talk about it in the show.
And I know we're going to have some different opinions here, but we've got a lot more to
get to.
And then we also got the OpenSUSE to discussion.
So let's take a quick moment and thank our next sponsor, Linux Academy, linuxacademy.com
slash unplugged.
Go there, get our 33% Linux discount.
Linux Academy is a platform set up by people who are truly passionate about Linux and open
source.
And they really follow the content.
They really follow the material.
And they've got step-by-step video courses to help you learn.
They've got downloadable comprehensive study guides.
The courseware comes with its own server.
It spins it up in the lab for you on demand.
The seven plus distributions you get to choose from.
Refresh topics that you care about all the time.
Docker, OpenStack, virtualization.
All of the technology around Linux as well.
Everything from like Ruby on Rails development to Android development to Linux basics.
They've got over 1500 self-paced courses.
And I love the way the interface works.
You log in, you get a great map of how long something's going to take you.
You can download the guide for that before you go jump in.
You can tell they have availability programming, so you can go in there and say, I have this
much time available.
It'll automatically generate courseware that matches your availability.
This is all really high-tech stuff.
And of course, they're using all Linux on the back end too.
Their virtualization platform, I learned a little bit about it when they became a sponsor.
They were just finishing building it out.
It was so, so slick.
There is obviously a passion for the technology over at Linux Academy.
And I think that when you're learning from somebody, that passion truly makes a difference.
It's almost like CG in a movie.
When you look at a CG character, you're like, oh, boy, that Uncanny Valley, that is just
enough creepy that it's not a real thing.
That's how I feel like a lot of these online training course systems are.
It's real close, except for, well, they needed to have a couple of check boxes in the Linux
and open source.
Let's get the Apache course in here.
Let's get the Linux course in here.
Let's get the engine.
They check the boxes.
And that's their commitment to Linux and open source.
That's not Linux Academy.
Linux Academy is truly people passionate about this stuff.
And that closes that Uncanny Valley gap.
That makes it real.
That makes it people that are truly living it and breathe it and trust it.
And that's what they base their life around.
And that's who you want to learn from.
That's why you listen to podcasts made by people who truly love Linux and not a podcast
made by Engadget talking about Linux.
That would be awful.
Right?
It's that same kind of disconnect and that big difference in that closing the gap that
Linux Academy makes.
They just refreshed their OpenStack course where they just really updated the Red Hat
certified stuff.
It's great.
Go to LinuxAcademy.com.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged to get our special 33 percent discount that supports
this show.
Also, shoot, while you're over there, see if they've updated any of their nuggets.
I think these nuggets are the greatest thing ever.
Oh, look at this one.
So these nuggets are like anywhere from like two minutes to 16 minute like deep dive on
courses that just show you like, hey, you want to know how to do X?
Just do this.
Well, look at this one.
Video conversions on the command line with Handbrake.
Oh, that's awesome.
That's great.
Right?
VirtualBox.
Start a headless VM on boot.
That's genius.
They got some AWS stuff in here.
They got building a firewall with IP tables.
Just go deep dive on a topic.
Right?
Just dig in.
You know, it doesn't feel like a lecture.
It feels like a new toy that you've just got.
Right?
Exactly.
I love it.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged and support the Linux unplugged program.
It's a really good setup.
And I also just I love that they've built it around the Linux environment in such a
cool way with those virtual servers.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
OK, guys.
So I couldn't believe it.
I thought for sure there was no way I was going to get sucked into this article, but
I did.
A week with Gnome as my main Linux desktop, what they get right and what they got wrong.
And I'm just going to read a couple of bits from it and then we'll get into discussion
here.
It says, yeah, I know I have a couple of points I want to touch on, but let's start on the
article itself.
An important distinction between KD and Gnome, the author writes, Gnome feels like a product.
It feels like a singular experience.
When you use it, it feels complete and that everything you need is at your fingertips.
It feels like the Linux desktop in the same way Windows or OS 10 have the desktop experience.
What you need is there and it's all written by the same guys working towards the same
team goal.
It feels like the Linux desktop.
Now, Wes, KD, Gnome user?
Gnome user myself.
Do you agree?
Does Gnome feel more like a Linux complete desktop to you?
Well, you know, I think what we were talking about earlier, a lot of things Qt does feel
much more, you know, wider world.
It runs on so many things.
I really love the framework and to code with it.
Maybe not so much GTK.
But you're right, Gnome really fits in with Linux, you know, especially the hardcore support
that they get from Fedora, how well integrated it is.
Sits right on top of system D.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So, the author spent five days of his week logging into Gnome manually, not turning on
automatic login.
And I love this observation.
It's the small things in Gnome.
It really is.
In fact, the alternative article title was a cut, a death by a thousand paper cuts for
KDE.
Here's like an example of something that bugs me under KDE that I like under Gnome.
And it's like this times a hundred.
He says, I spent the first five days of my week logging into Gnome manually, not turning
on automatic login.
On the night of the fifth day, I got annoyed with having to login by hand and so I went
into the user manager and turned on automatic login.
The next time I logged in, I got a prompt.
Your key chain was not unlocked.
Please enter your password to unlock your key chain.
That's when I realized something.
Gnome had been automatically unlocking my key chain, my wallet in KDE speak, every time
I logged in via GDM.
It was only when I bypassed GDM's login that Gnome had to step up and make it do me do
it manually.
It was at that moment I realized something simple, something that made the desktop feel
like it was working with me.
When I log into KDE via SSDDM, before the splash screen is even finished loading, there
is a pop-up over that splash screen animation, thereby disturbing that splash screen, prompting
me to unlock my KDE wallet or GPG key ring.
And then it goes into the dysfunctions in creating those.
And I thought that was an interesting point.
It is the small things about KDE that bugged me.
He also talks about the login manager and the way that looks, but this point, this KDE,
when you log into the KDE desktop and you have to unlock your wallet and this dialog
box pops up before you've even finished logging into your desktop, it just feels disoriented.
It feels jumbled.
It feels disconnected.
Which is a big criticism of Linux in general, right?
Yes.
A hodgepodge of different tools.
Gnome doesn't feel that way.
Here's another hodgepodge.
Software manager.
Something that's been seeing a lot of push in the recent years and will likely see a
bigger push in months to come.
Unfortunately, it's an area where KDE gets close, but then fell on its face.
Gnome Software is now his new favorite software center, minus one gripe.
But Muon, which is the KDE one, it's a design nightmare.
And he's got some examples in here.
I'm not bashing KDE, but he's right.
There are, there are, there are wiggles in the software center, like the fact that the
updates in software and two different applications, the fact that software discovery is a total,
like you look at this, it is, and what's really kind of a tragedy about it, and he goes on
to point this out, is that KDE knows about this.
That's why they created the visual design group.
And the visual design group had mock-ups for the software center that looked totally different
than what shipped.
Wow.
He says someone must have gotten drunk when they coded the UI.
That's the only guess he has.
And then I'm gonna, and then we're almost done and we'll get to jump in, but I just
want to get through his major points here.
When we bring up an important distinction between KDE and GNOME, GNOME feels like a
product, right?
That's what he says.
It feels like a product.
But KDE, that doesn't, KDE doesn't feel like a cohesive experience.
He says KDE doesn't feel like it has a direction it's moving on.
It doesn't feel like it's a full experience.
KDE feels like it's a bunch of pieces that are moving in a bunch of different directions
that just happen to have a shared toolkit beneath them.
Right.
I think this speaks a lot to what we see in general, where, you know, a lot of people
gripe about GNOME, lose customization, all that kind of stuff, and I think there's very
diverse camps within the Linux group.
Some people want to be able to tinker, they want, they're okay if it doesn't work for
the first 10 hours, but afterwards it works great.
But GNOME really does feel like a product where it's been integrated, it's been considered,
it's been designed.
And it looks like, you know, you feel like a lot of elements were painstakingly thought
about.
Exactly.
He says, so then I thought this was a final conclusion here, and you'll have the whole
article linked in the show notes, which is a good read with lots of good screenshot examples.
He says, well, I still use GNOME after this week.
Probably not, no.
GNOME is still trying to force a workflow on me that I don't follow or abide by.
I feel less productive when using it because it doesn't follow my paradigm.
So at the end of all of this, he's not switching back to GNOME.
But this hit a lot of pieces for me, and Rotten, do you want to open up, because I know you
just mentioned at the top of the show that you've been running KDE for a little while
now, and as you switched from GNOME to KDE, do you detect this sort of, I thought this
line that he put here, a bunch of different moving software pieces and going in different
directions that use the same shared toolkit beneath them, that really struck a chord with
me when I think of KDE.
It's like, everything does talk super well together, but at the same time, it is a bit
of a mess in terms of jumbled together, like, man, look at the sound.
You go look at the sound settings, right?
When you're looking at the sound settings in KDE, don't you think it's really bizarre
that they have, in fact, he has a screenshot.
So here's a screenshot right here of GNOME sound versus KDE sound.
Now here is what blows me away about KDE sound, the sound settings.
You see what's at the very top of the GNOME, what's that very top slider right there, Wes?
What is that right there?
Output volume.
That's the output volume.
You know what's missing completely from the KDE sound applet?
There is no effing volume slider.
But you know what there is?
There is a left-hand list of device priorities for application notifications, music, video
communications, audio recording, video recording, and in each one of these categories, I can
move around which sound card takes priority.
Pretty neat feature.
Probably not used as often as the volume slider in the volume control panel, though.
Ten to one right there, yeah.
Right.
This is what I'm talking about.
What kind of sense does that make?
For developers and advanced users, that's a really slick feature, and I bet even advanced
users and developers set that once or twice when they set up the KDE desktop, and they
never go back and change that priority list.
I never mess with that priority list.
I just want to set my default audio device and set the volume.
I just want to do two things.
And this Gnome system lets me set my output device and set the volume right there.
And it's like that everywhere.
The defaults are crazy in KDE.
Now, Rotten, have you noticed this as you've moved over from Gnome to KDE or to you?
Is it refreshing in a sense?
As far as the way the cohesiveness of KDE?
Yeah.
Does it feel like a bunch of different stuff just share the same toolkit?
No.
I mean, it feels like a cohesive unit.
It's just a messy cohesion.
The example of the sound slider does exist in KDE.
It's just not in the settings section.
It's in the applet that's on the panel, or the taskbar, as they call it, which is fine.
You would say, well, these are settings, so you want to change the different devices and
stuff like that.
So it's nice, and it's more polished the way Gnome does it, but it's not necessarily a
complete necessity for KDE to do that way because they already give you the slider,
and KMix gives you a ton of control over the different sliders for the different applications
and the different outputs and stuff like that.
It's really nice because it's all right in that one widget, so you don't have to open
up.
For example, if you want to change stuff based on a particular application or a particular
output for, say, a plug-in that you have two different YouTube channels playing.
Yeah, that's neat, but why not – okay, so this is a use case scenario.
Let's be honest.
How many people are doing this?
Probably not very.
I mean, people that could do that could just install Poova control.
Yeah, but my point is that if you have – it's not really that polished if the aspects of
what you want to do are available in KDE, but they're not available at all in Gnome.
I would say –
And then vice versa, the same kind of thing.
I would disagree.
I think what they have struck is such an imbalance between polish and options that it's a mess.
It's not polished at all, and I think if – yes, there is a sound slider –
Gnome is the polished one.
Yeah, okay.
Well, that – I just – I think it is a little – the sound settings here is a little
indicative of the whole problem.
I know there's a sound slider in the menu bar, but every other desktop environment – literally
made every other desktop environment, like Windows and OS X included in that, have the
slider there for a very good reason, because when you're changing your different output
devices and you're changing your different alert settings, you want to be able to adjust
the volume to see what – I do this all the time.
This is a very, very common function, and it just makes sense to have it there.
Anyway –
But to be fair, they're still porting a lot of stuff to 5, and he's showing a screenshot
from Plasma 5, but that's not really a fair screenshot considering that's KDE 4 version
of that application.
So just because that's how it looks in Plasma 5 doesn't mean that's what it's going
to be when it finally releases the new port.
Well, here's what I was going to ask.
It's also true with pretty much most of their applications.
Does it matter?
Like, is the KDE approach necessarily wrong?
It's sort of – I mean, what's the Unix philosophy?
A lot of little tools working together to build something great.
Is that necessarily – if you could have a nice desktop environment, a lot of different
tools that use a common toolkit and a common design language, which is what the visual
design group is supposed to be pushing, but it depends on the projects adopted, then is
that necessarily the wrong approach?
I think a lot of times we see two different approaches to something, and we just assume
one is right and one is wrong.
I don't necessarily think that's the case.
I think, for me, I like – so I said this a long time ago – I really like the fact
that GNOME feels like the Linux desktop.
For some reason, like, from just something about the whole thing, it feels like GNOME
is sitting directly on top of more fundamental Linux technologies than site KDE is.
And so, to me, the whole cohesiveness feels like a really good desktop environment.
That's what I want out of my environment.
But like Rodden's saying right now, there's a whole other group of people who want those
other things.
Doesn't mean that's the wrong approach.
Yeah, definitely.
I think it enriches our ecosystem to have both being actively developed.
Yeah.
Were you going to say Rodden?
No?
Okay.
Rodden has nothing to that.
Actually, I –
Yeah, go ahead.
Oh, no, I totally do.
I totally do.
I always have something to say.
So, I just posted a screenshot in the IRC of KDE – what my KDE looks like now.
I'm not done, but you'll see it kind of resembles something, right?
Wow, it looks a lot like GNOME, to be honest with you.
Yeah, that was actually the purpose.
Yeah, it looks exactly like GNOME.
Yeah, it does.
So the reason why is because I think KDE is atrocious looking.
It is like the default for 5 is actually to the point where it's reasonable to say that
I might actually try that.
But the default for KDE 4, which is the current stable release, is atrocious.
So the reason why my KDE looks good and it looks like a lot more cohesiveness is because
I changed a crap load of things.
I've done that too.
It just seems like such a waste of energy.
It almost feels like you used KDE to make a GNOME.
I did, actually.
But my point is that you can take KDE to any direction you want, and that's the power
of it.
The design group is actually going to fix the overall cohesiveness of it.
So eventually, it will be a very good solution, but it's not necessarily there yet.
I'm starting to doubt the design group will actually have much influence.
I mean, they've had some great influence on the desktop itself, but then other projects
outside of the Direct Desktop don't really seem to be like Dragon Player, for example,
or Armor Rock, for example.
Not seen a lot of changes there.
They haven't gotten to the point of actually starting to port those.
Even Dolphin is one of the most important applications for KDE users, and it's only
had slightly started the porting process right now.
It's painful.
So they still have a lot of work to do.
And it's actually impressive how much work they've done in only like nine months.
They've essentially rewritten like 70% of the code of KDE in order to do Plasma 5, and
it is very impressive.
It's not ready by any means, but it is getting to the point where you can see the potential
of it.
But Rotten, that's where it's been since before Plasma 5 was even a thing.
You talked about one of the, well, there's always been a couple of constants.
Qt's always been badass, and Kwin's always gotten, well, Kwin's gotten extremely badass,
right?
In fact, Martin's just recently been talking about all the work on his, to get Kwin working
on Wayland.
It's getting really close.
It's really exciting.
Yeah.
Kwin is actually fantastic, and it's more fantastic, people know, because Kwin has this
built-in feature for window rules, which is basically like saving features of how you
actually lay out your windows.
So if you don't want window decorations, you can turn it off, save that.
If you want your windows to be a specific size, specific location on your screen, which
screen you want it to be on, what desktop you want it to be on, different things like
that, you can control it to ridiculous degrees that there are certain settings that I would
never even bother because they're so specific.
And the coolest one right now is, 4 does not have it, but Plasma 5 is an example of the
design group seeing how this is going to be a benefit, is that the window rules in 5 allow
you to change the colors per application.
But are you, well, okay, that is kind of cool, you're going to do that and I'm like, well,
maybe you would just so it grabs you, yeah, okay, I mean, I love this stuff.
Yeah, exactly.
Functionally, KDE is amazing.
Visually, right now in 4, it is actually kind of like hurts my eyes most of the time, but
it is getting to the point where they actually have improved the icons, they've improved
the window decorations and they've improved a ton of things and it has potential to eventually,
you know, even visually compete against GNOME, but right now, GNOME is definitely the more
visually appealing, but it's also not as powerful functionally as KDE is, so it depends on which
one you want.
At the end of the day, I think the big problem, KDE's biggest problem is that there might
be too much desktop for what people really use today.
I think a very common use case scenario for the Linux desktop is a couple of applications
running all the time, like a web browser, a chat program, email probably, and...
Throw in a terminal, please.
Absolutely.
And you're pretty much done.
And you don't need a lot more functionality from your desk, that's why so many people
are able to use Tiling Window Managers.
Yeah, exactly.
Now, that said, I too, Rotten, have gone down the path you had where I, I mean, I really
spent some time, I got the icon-only launcher sidebar going for a dock, I got a, you know,
a top bar going with the clock, I mean, it really made it look nice, but it just still
didn't feel as one cohesive product.
But I like...
Well, I mean, I just, I don't think that GNOME feels like a cohesive product that's got certain
pieces that are broken.
And just to point out, I'm a GNOME fanboy, I've been using GNOME for a decade, and I
actually love GNOME Shell and GNOME 3.
That is the, the reason why I, my current KDE setup looks like GNOME is because I actually
enjoy the workflow of GNOME.
So the guy who's wrote that article said he hated that workflow and didn't want it anymore.
I was like, well, I actually love that workflow.
Yeah, it works for me too.
And I will use it on either KDE or GNOME, it doesn't matter, I love that workflow.
Yeah, me too.
But the point is mainly that if I set up something in KDE, it will remember, it will save it,
it will do exactly what I tell it to do.
With GNOME, if I tell it to, I have to install an extension in order to get it to load an
application on a particular workspace, but if I put it on a different monitor, it won't
remember that monitor.
Yeah, that drives me crazy.
I have to move everything.
I know, I know, I agree, I agree.
And Dolphin, in my opinion, Dolphin is a better file manager than Nautilus too, in my opinion.
I would say Dolphin is the better for Linux, just in general.
So that's, that's, that's.
Gosh, you're kind of making me want to try KDE out for like a week again.
Kind of making me.
I'm actually, I'm kind, I'm actually kind of feeling dirty about saying all this stuff
as a GNOME fanboy.
I even, I've released, I actually like released updates and patches to extensions for GNOME
because I use them and someone didn't, wasn't maintaining it, so I started maintaining it
and stuff like that.
And I still do it even while I'm running KDE, so it's, it makes me feel a little weird,
but I have to acknowledge the fantastic features that KDE provides.
I agree.
Yeah.
And you've made it look pretty good.
It didn't take so much effort to make it look good.
Exactly.
If it didn't take so much effort to do that, it would be a fantastic desktop environment.
How long do you think it took you?
How long do you think you spent?
To actually make it look right?
Well, for me, it's not fair to comparison the time.
For other people, it would take a lot longer because I'm a graphics artist.
I know how to modify SVGs and everything like that, which, by the way, KDE is dependent
on SVGs for the desktop shells themes.
So if you don't know how to do that, you're pretty much hopeless if, I mean, it is hopeless
for you to do it because you have to learn how to modify SAGs to do that.
But you have to figure out what app, what widgets fit and what, but like the very first
time I did it, it took me probably about a week and a half.
And this time it took me about two or three days because I had to first teach myself how
does KDE do all these different things.
And it was a lot more effort than I expected, but it was still possible to do it.
But I think the majority of people who don't have the skill set I do would not have as
fast of an experience.
And even though it's not, it's still a couple of days and it's not fast, I think it would
be much worse for them.
Yeah, it took me a couple of days to get it the way I want, I might, gosh, dang it.
Hmm.
I'm going to have to install it again, I'm going to have to give it a go.
I can show you another, I actually have like a whole, the very first time I made my Gnome
like KDE set up, it looked different than what I have now.
But I did like a full layout of like, here's a screenshot of here's what it looks like
in here because I finished it.
It took me about a week and a half.
I don't know what I get.
I mean, Gnome works for me and I don't have sound issues.
That's what I keep coming back to.
But I want to try it.
I keep wanting to, when I try KDE for you for a little while, I usually really enjoy
it.
So.
Here's the other, here's one of the first, last thing I'll say, the reason why I actually
got really annoyed at Gnome and I love Gnome, I got really annoyed by multiple monitor support.
Yeah.
Because it is, it is like, not only does it not remember the applications where they're
supposed to be, it actually wouldn't remember which one I wanted to be primary.
And it would, it would start breaking in the point where one monitor would want to take
over to the primary and then it would switch, swap back and forth, like weird things started
happening.
But so it just, it got so, it happened so many times that it just, I just kind of threw
my hands up.
I was like, well, let's see how KDE handles multiple monitors.
And I haven't had a single problem with it at all.
Yeah.
We were talking at lunch, KDE does have pretty good monitor control and yeah, all right Rod
and you convinced me.
Anybody else in the member room want to jump in on the topic of Gnome versus KDE when they
switch between?
Any final thoughts?
I really want to recommend everybody go read the article.
I thought it was a particularly good one though.
All right.
Going once, going twice.
Chris, I think as you mentioned before, there's definitely a spectrum from the bare bones
Gnome, very polished, but not a lot of options to KDE with all of its options.
I'm curious to see over the last year or so that Gnome has, the Gnome community has kind
of come back or learned their lesson from the initial Gnome three days.
Well, I hope so.
So I'm curious to see as time goes on if Gnome plus extensions are going to continue to be
supported enough to eat into the user base of KDE users that want all the options.
Yeah.
I mean-
The extensions are actually very solid.
This is actually a misconception I'd like to clear up about the Gnome extensions because
I've been maintaining some and this is just, it's a problem with the Gnome version software
checking that it doesn't do it very well and it doesn't have like, for example, Firefox
does a much better solution.
It's this version plus future versions.
With Gnome, it's this version or nothing.
So if it doesn't detect in your, just your metadata that you are using that particular
version you are currently on, it just breaks the extension.
That's a really bad way to do it, but that's their current solution for making sure that
you're not running stuff that's broken.
So people think that every single time you update, you're breaking an extension when
really it's just because the version number is not telling and it's the right one.
If you just go in and change that version number, almost like 90% of them work immediately.
And also means most of them, it's a quick update by the author to make it work too.
So that's been happening.
It's getting turned around immediately these days.
Like that plugin is getting fixed all the time.
Now Wes, have you noticed a change in tone towards Gnome 3 in the Linux community?
Yeah, I would think so.
I mean, probably two years ago, a year and a half ago, mostly negative.
Yeah, right?
At least in, you know, publicly facing discussion.
Yeah, okay.
That's what I observed too.
But now it feels like, you know, it may not be everyone's favorite, it may not be what
you use.
You know, I usually use a tiling window manager at home, honestly, but I'm always happy to
stick Gnome on something and use it.
Yeah.
What's your favorite tiling window manager?
I'm using Awesome currently.
Nice.
Interesting.
I think I'm going to try KD on a secondary machine, but I'm not planning to switch away
from Gnome anytime soon.
I just keep getting happier and happier with it.
Probably just about in time to start hearing about the next Gnome 3.18 release too, which
could be pretty cool.
All right.
Well, if you guys have any thoughts on that story, we'd love to get your opinions, especially
if you've been recently trying one of the other desktops and have a good perspective.
Go to linuxactionshow.reddit.com and look for the feedback thread for episode 101 of
the unplugged program.
Now on Sunday's Linux action show, we talked about the big changes coming to this open
SUSE project, and I know several people wanted to give us some feedback on that.
Before we get to that, I've got to thank DigitalOcean, sponsor of the Linux Unplugged Program, and
DigitalOcean is great.
If you want some Linux infrastructure right now on demand for testing or production, check
them out.
DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and
easy way for you to spin up your own cloud server, and they have fantastic Docker support
on their droplets, so you can create a nice local container, get a system all set up on
your laptop or your desktop and push it up to the DigitalOcean cloud.
No problem at all.
And here's the best part, you know, you could do that and save yourself a ton of time, but
if you just want to create a server from scratch, it's amazing.
You can get started in less than 55 seconds and pricing plans are only $5, that's where
they start, $5 a month.
Then the pricing structure goes up from there, really nice, makes a lot of sense, and they
even have hourly pricing available if you just want to do some testing.
For $5 though, you're going to get 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, because they're
all SSDs, one CPU and a terabyte, a terabyte of transfer.
And DigitalOcean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam
and London, and they've got a brand new one in Germany, which is a great location.
Now what I love is all of this is backed by Linux, it's all running on top of KVM and
all of the disks are SSD based, so you're going to get really, really good performance.
You log into DigitalOcean's interface, it works on your tablet, it works on your phone,
it works on your desktop, you get HTML5 console access, so if you want to watch the machine
post and all the way up to the login screen, you can do that.
It is a slick system.
They've really taken the best open source Linux technologies and wrapped it around in
a package that makes it very presentable and very easy for you to use.
And I don't know if you've ever tried it, Wes.
Oh yeah, definitely.
Oh yeah?
Oh, of course.
So one of the things I love about DigitalOcean is it's like I know that if I want to go over
and start getting working on something, the delay isn't going to be the creating the server,
deploying the software, like that's no longer the barrier anymore.
Getting started on that stuff, which 10 years ago was like a two week process to order the
server and install the operating system, configure the firewall, rack it.
Wait for the ticket to get updated.
Yes, right.
Talk to support.
And now with DigitalOcean, you go over there and it's like, well, it's under a minute.
You have a Linux virtual machine deployed and if you use our promo code DOUNPLUGED, you'll
get a $10 credit and you can try out the $5 rig two months for free.
And you can do one click deployment of applications.
Like I've done one click deployment of Ubuntu 14.04 with Apache already just ready to go
on there.
So I don't have to bother with that.
And the nice thing is it's already subscribed to the repo, so it's going to get all the
updates from Ubuntu.
And I'll do local mirrors of the Ubuntu repos too, so you can pull it down at like tens
of megabytes a second.
It's crazy.
It's so cool to watch that.
I love watching the updates go boom, boom, boom, boom, like, yeah, that, it feels like
it's supercharged.
Their interface is so great for managing all this.
Very intuitive.
But the best part is they have an API to let you replicate it, which is really nice.
There's some great apps around that.
They have really, really good tutorials too.
In fact, go over to DigitalOcean.
Remember, use the promo code DOUNPLUGED.
Check out that community section.
They're updating this all the time.
Like here's one, how to update the scaling of your web application on DigitalOcean.
That's genius when you think about the fact that DigitalOcean is hourly pricing, so if
you need to scale for a little while, ooh, that's cool.
Oh, buddy, buddy, buddy, I've been waiting for this one.
How to create a blog with Ghost and NGINX on Ubuntu 14.04.
This is it.
If you're going to do a blog for yourself or for your company, WordPress is great.
Mad props to WordPress.
Check out Ghost.
And they have a community tutorial on it right here, or how to use a Rango DB.
Are you familiar with a Rango?
I am not.
I don't know what a Rango is.
I like how it has avocados as it's a...
I know where we can learn more though.
Yes, exactly.
DigitalOcean.com and use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
They've also got FreeBSD if you're a masochist, CoreOS, Fedora 22, Debian, Ubuntu.
I'm kidding about the FreeBSD thing.
I think it's really cool.
They have support for it.
It's actually no technical joke either.
They got that working in KVM.
They worked upstream with the FreeBSD project.
Same with CoreOS too.
They worked directly with the project to make this stuff happen.
It's really cool.
And you can try it out two months for free when you use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
Go get yourself a Linux rig.
You want to try de-Google-fying your life for a little while?
Maybe you want to do an own cloud instance or maybe you want to see if you can host your
own photo gallery or maybe you want your own mumble chat server.
Set up your own lug.
You do it all on a DigitalOcean droplet, DigitalOcean.com.
Use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED and a big, big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring
the Unplugged program.
All right.
So this was the basic feedback we got from Sunday's show.
One lost user wrote, I don't really get why Chris and Noah are puzzled by SUSE and what
OpenSUSE intend to do.
The new distro will be SUSE Linux Enterprise to what CentOS is to Red Hat Enterprise Linux.
There will be Tumbleweed, the bleeding edge, always rolling distro.
They'll be in much better shape than Rawhide because OpenSUSE actually expects people to
use it as a desktop OS as opposed to Rawhide is always borkin'.
There will be OpenSUSE 42 which is going to be based on SUSE Linux Enterprise sources.
People will be able to use it as such others do with like CentOS.
It'll be extremely easy for OpenSUSE and SUSE to switch between 42 to switch to the Enterprise
version of back and forth.
It looks like a very smart move, he believes.
Now Rotten, you were watching live and we covered it and you said you wanted to jump
in on the feedback so I'll open it up to you first and then we'll kick around to other
people.
Rotten, what was your main takeaway from the coverage and your opinion on the setup?
Well, the first thing is that this guy is wrong.
The guy who you just read wrote in, that's wrong.
It's not a CentOS to Red Hat.
I agree with that too.
I don't think it really is a CentOS to Red Hat Enterprise thing either.
So basically what they're saying, they even specifically were asked if they did this,
was OpenSUSE going to become like an OpenSLE thing and they said no, definitely not.
They're going to be doing, their OpenSUSE is just going to be based on SLE so it's going
to have all the same packages for SLE but it's not going to have the, you know, it's
not going to be the exact same thing.
They're going to have SLE packages plus their own packages to create the OpenSUSE desktop.
The goal was to have like an integration with SUSE and OpenSUSE which they didn't used to
have.
There was a huge gap between the two.
But also, sorry, my dog's actually drinking water.
Yeah, I know.
That's all right.
So we got a lot of different feedback, Rotten, on it and some people like this a lot.
So here was a response we got from R Brown from SUSE.
He says something like this is what he wanted to do.
He gave us a couple of links.
He says, what we realized is we were building here doesn't fit into traditional models anymore.
We find that for us that we're not really serving the purpose they used to traditional
release models do for a community-based distro or even an enterprise distro perspective.
With all the testing we do for Tumbleweed and our open QA process, we've managed to
make a rolling release that only rolls when we know the test, the thing isn't broken.
So they test it first.
Given the motivator for so many people for traditional community releases is I want the
latest shiny new stuff but I only want it when it works, Tumbleweed managed to do that
without a six or 12 month waiting period.
Is that possible?
Yeah.
They actually had known first before Arch.
That doesn't mean that it's flawless.
It actually wasn't flawless.
I think it's an exaggeration to claim flawless.
But it was very stable.
And I tried it out because I was being impatient.
And it actually was really good.
I didn't notice any huge breaks or anything.
I noticed some Gnome specific things but that was just Gnome things.
But the point about Tumbleweed though is they kind of explained in a weird diagram of what
the initial goal is that Tumbleweed will be like the sources for SLEE eventually in snapshot
form.
So Tumbleweed will be constantly being updated and maintained and then at some point in every
couple of years or so, they would take a snapshot of Tumbleweed, throw it into SLEE, then SUSE
would do their stuff to it, then they would become the core base to OpenSUSE which then
does their own stuff on top of it.
So basically what Noah was talking about last how he wanted a desktop enterprise solution,
that's pretty much what OpenSUSE is talking about.
It seems to me though that OpenSUSE is essentially going to be just about as, and I think it's
where the comparison to CentOS comes in, it's going to be just about as stale as Slew's
Enterprise Linux, right?
No.
Because you think they'll replace certain components as they need to?
Yes.
They've already said that they were even thinking about updating the desktop environments away
from SLEE.
They haven't specified whether they're going to or not but they said that there's a potential
that they will so that there could absolutely be, the core fundamental packages are going
to be the same, I guess stale if you want to say it, like with SLEE stuff, but the user
space on top would be pretty much not as fast as Tumbleweed but a lot faster than their
current structure.
So it would be kind of like a LTS base with a nod on it.
Right, okay, that's what I was going to ask, am I picturing the right thing when it's like,
I guess, here's what, and Richard, I really appreciate him responding in the subreddit
too, I guess what I don't quite understand is how, I still don't, why would I choose,
why would I choose, I guess I would have to wait and find out what components they're
going to individually choose to replace and upgrade apart from SLEE before I know if OpenSUSE
is going to fit for me.
And right now it sounds like there's a lot of what ifs, well no, hear me out, if they
decide to update the desktop environment and the web browsers and things like that, all
those user land applications, that's pretty slick, kind of sounds like what Mint's doing.
But if they decide, well, we don't really have the manpower to do that, then it seems
like it could get to be just a basic CentOS kind of clone, and here's why I am concerned
about that happening, A, I don't believe that OpenQA is going to catch all this stuff, I
think the way you catch stuff in Linux a lot of times is just a function of, a lot of people
use it for a while, they eventually find a bug and they fix it and then somebody patches
that bug and then a distro finally ships it, otherwise, right, because otherwise you could
just use rolling all the time.
So I think, I don't know if unit testing is really going to make a rolling distro that
much stable over another one, and I think you could have a bit of a reputation burn
there, okay, but that's point number one, now let me make a second point.
Second point, the reason why I'm concerned more about OpenSUSE and what components they're
going to replace is because I think if we're totally honest with ourselves, why are we
in this position right now?
Why are they making OpenSUSE 42?
Why are they doing Tumbleweed?
Why are they going to base OpenSUSE off of SLEE?
Why?
Because only a couple of people are working on the project anymore, OpenSUSE, nobody's
working on it, nobody cares about it, they're all working on Tumbleweed or SUSE Enterprise,
they said so themselves, in their own presentation and in their own blog post, the fundamental
problem with the last release of OpenSUSE is nobody wants to work on it, they all want
to work on Tumbleweed or the big dog, and so if that is a problem today, how is that
not going to be a problem two years, a year down the road, when they have this thing that's
based on something that's already done, but now they have this pain in the neck where
they have to replace certain components and stay on top of that and ship it all the time?
It seems like they'll eventually just be right back in the same position they're at today,
Tumbleweed will get all of the current active attention, and SLEE's going to get all of
the stability and money focused attention.
How does this solve their fundamental problem?
Okay, so to answer one about what is the reason to use this, you use Arch, so everything is
rolling anyway, so you would be Tumbleweed, like the exact transition, you would just
move to Tumbleweed and you'd have the same stuff you would have right now.
Yeah, and I get that, Tumbleweed makes sense to me, I get it, I don't know if I believe
it's going to be as trouble-free as they say, but I bet it's going to be more trouble-free,
but I saw it, Tumbleweed makes sense, SUSE Enterprise makes sense to me, and I also see
from a business standpoint, where they have the dedication and resources, that it all
makes sense.
Okay, so the second one, you don't understand why they would do this.
So OpenSUSE to me, 42, sounds like what it's going to be, is a pretty cool product based
on some pretty nice stable Enterprise upstream source code.
Now then they're going to go, well this chunk and this chunk and this chunk, and they've
explained they've made it very easy to modulize and replace these chunks, they're going to
say this chunk, this chunk, and this chunk, we're going to swap out and we're going to
maintain this ourselves on top of this SLEE base, KDE, Gnome, Firefox, whatever, we're
going to maintain this on top of the SLEE base ourselves.
Well then aren't they just getting right back on this treadmill that they've been running
this entire time, that they all jumped ship from, and I'm mixing a lot of analogies here,
but isn't this, what is different?
What changes?
Isn't the core issue, the focus for the distro, wasn't the core issue that sort of prompted
this, was that nobody was working on OpenSUSE, and I guess what this sounds like is it sounds
like we're trying to manage OpenSUSE a little bit.
We need some, you know, Red Hat has CentOS and Fedora, they're doing Fedora Core, they're
making Fedora Workstation and Fedora Cloud, they're getting very serious with the Atomic
project about making Fedora an actual cloud deployable system.
You're seeing places like Rackspace, you're seeing places like DigitalOcean deploy Fedora,
you're not seeing them deploy OpenSUSE, that's got to bother them.
So they want to get OpenSUSE into a place where it could be part of a VPS package, it
could be something that's installed on demand.
It's kind of embarrassing, isn't it, that one of the biggest, for a long time, well-known
distributions has like had very little game in the whole cloud space.
Like Ubuntu just came and ate their lunch by surprise, and now I agree, they have to
do something to make OpenSUSE relevant in this space, it'd be great for them.
And I think this could do it, I think this would do it.
If I knew OpenSUSE was based on enterprise source code, man, I'd feel a lot better about
deploying that on a production VPS for sure.
I still don't see though why they are incentivized to maintain these individual layers of it
and keep those competitive when they're not incentivized to do it today.
That's the part I'm not seeing.
Okay, there's two things.
There's the gap between SUSE and OpenSUSE.
For example, with Red Hat, they have the code in Fedora, they have code in CentOS that they
can take improvements from Fedora and CentOS and easily put them in the Red Hat if they
deem worthy to be in there.
SUSE and OpenSUSE don't have that, they don't have the integration that Red Hat does.
So for one, it solves that integration problem because the core structure of OpenSUSE is
going to be based on SLEE, and then Tumbleweed would eventually become Snapshots for SLEE,
so they would get this integration level back into the benefits of SUSE with the backing
and funding of everything and actually have a lot of work that's not just on the OpenSUSE
side.
So right now, the reason why, your example, they didn't have much attention in OpenSUSE
because they wanted to do Tumbleweed, well, it's a community effort in that case, and
the people choose what they want to work on, and OpenSUSE didn't have a lot of people working
on the OpenSUSE stable release because they wanted to be on Tumbleweed, and they didn't
have a base that they could build on to actually make that work.
So this is actually solving that problem, so it doesn't matter what they want.
What does it change?
Because they're not going to have to put that work in, because the whole point of OpenSUSE
right now, the reason that was a problem is because they only had a handful of people
working on this fundamental thing that they're handling everything, now they don't have to
handle it.
Because they're going to pull it in from Tumbleweed.
Because they're going to do the work in Tumbleweed.
Pull it in from Tumbleweed and in from Sleeve, so it's kind of like a hybrid in those.
And then, plus, I'm sure they've, and maybe you could tell me if this is true or not,
have they finished development on LibMagick that totally resolves all of the library issues
between major versions when you're going from a stable enterprise district to something
rolling?
Does LibMagick just handle all of that?
I don't know.
I mean, let's look at Cinnamon.
Why has Cinnamon had so many problems landing in Arch when it's a rolling distribution?
Because GTK underneath changes, and Cinnamon depends on an older version of GTK, and then
all of a sudden, you can't install Cinnamon on a rolling distro anymore.
Now, is Tumbleweed going to make the decision in this case to hold GTK back, or am I going
to be able to replace the entire GTK installation using the OpenSUSE build service?
How are they legitimately going to solve these real-world problems that have plagued every
other Linux distro since the invention of a rolling distro?
How are they going to solve that?
They're not going to roll everything.
Like, Tumbleweed will roll everything, and you're not going to have any kind of connection
with the stability issues whatsoever.
The part where they're pulling stuff from, they're going to pull stuff from Tumbleweed
when it suits, like, for example, application level of, like, Firefox and things like that
that will not have any kind of linkage.
That makes sense, but it seems like then there's going to be limitations.
There's going to be a certain pressure to keep OpenSUSE at least in somewhat compatibility
sync with Tumbleweed so that way they can move more stuff over, because the further
those two drift, the less and less things they should be able to pull over from Tumbleweed,
I would think.
Well, yeah, but like fundamental things, yes, that'd be the problem, but they also are saying
that it's not just Tumbleweed that they're pulling from.
They're also going to be, as the community of OpenSUSE, not just of Tumbleweed.
Yeah, sure, but why isn't that happening today?
See, that's part of the argument I don't get.
Yeah, sure, they can custom develop that stuff.
They can make that stuff keep working on OpenSUSE, so they could be doing that today and they're
not doing it.
I mean, they are doing it, but barely.
They're barely getting it out the door.
That's because they are doing everything.
Yeah, you know, that could be, right?
Yeah, maybe this will be enough of a pressure release.
Yeah, boy, that'd be great.
Good point.
That'd be really cool if this could – I have these questions that I've raised, and
I guess sometimes when I ask these kinds of questions it sounds like I think it's a really
dumb idea, or it sounds like I don't think they should do it, and that's not the case
at all.
I'm just wondering, like, how are they going to – these – I guess what I'm trying to
do is I'm trying to identify what I perceive to be challenges they're going to have to
overcome, and I'm really glad somebody's trying this approach, because I don't really
think the Fedora one's going to necessarily resonate for a lot of people on servers, and
I just think that there is a great space in here for OpenSUSE to fill with this sort of
SLE based upstream source codes that give me a sort of assurance that it's based on
a really quality enterprise product.
I think this could be a killer.
I'm not saying it's going to be a flop, but I am saying I think there's going to be significant
challenges that I don't quite see all the solutions to, so I'm not trying to poop on
it.
Well, I mean, I just think that – like, the fundamental changes is that the people
who are working on the stuff to improve the user space in OpenSUSE, and they also had
to deal with the core fundamentals as well, but now they don't have to do that so they
can do a lot more even in the OpenSUSE stable release level without the Tumbleweed, so they
have – they can – like, the pressure release is the biggest benefit of this, but you also
have the people who want a stable base with a rolling top, or not even necessarily rolling,
but just more up to date than a regular release of most distros.
I got it.
Oh, man.
I think for me, I think – because I don't really care what happens with SLE or OpenSUSE
as so much as I think Tumbleweed is going to get really appealing to a user like me
because – so not only do you have some really interesting technologies there, but I also
find the technologies around SUSE or OpenSUSE to be pretty sexy, like the OpenSUSE build
service and the images where you can go custom machine and crank that out and download that
as an ISO, and it's like, here's my machine already pre-set up, like, all that stuff really
makes me hot.
I think that's super great.
And so you build a really great distro around that, and I actually think Zipper is a pretty
decent technology, and I like that they're bold enough to back butter FS, even if I think
it's currently a train wreck that makes people lose data, but, you know, like, Martin from
the Netherlands wrote in, and Martin said, what makes OpenSUSE unique is that it's easy
enough to understand for anyone with a Windows technical background.
You kind of have the Windows paradigm when you use their KDE desktop, Yast is a lot like
the control panel, all system settings can be configured via a GUI, unlike Fedora, and
at the same time, it remains fully focused on open source, where everything is contributed
back upstream, unlike Ubuntu, which is...
They have a corporate backing, giving me a feeling that the distribution won't disappear
anytime soon.
He says, and I love this line, Martin says, it's like the Toyota of Linux distributions.
It's a bit boring to drive, but from a technical and reliability standpoint, it's the best.
That's not bad.
That's not a bad way to put it, really, and I don't think that's a slam at all.
I think that's a...
I think it's a really good spot to be in as a distro, especially if you want people installing
your servers.
All right, guys, anybody have any closing thoughts before we close the books on this
one?
Well, finally, just the OBS is another example of the updating software.
So like the PPAs that Ubuntu have, OBS are going to provide a similar thing, but a lot
more organized way to do it.
But also...
And more approachable.
Definitely.
The cool thing is not only is the sources from SLEE coming to OpenSUSE, they're actually
going to the OBS.
So really, anybody who wants to get a source can do it.
You can actually, if you wanted to, maybe, this is just like...
I'm completely talking out of my butt right now.
But SUSE Studio, plus the OBS, plus the SLEE releases, maybe you can make your own SLEE.
Yeah, I think you definitely could.
I think that's a...
Wow, yeah, especially with the build service, that's going to be a thing.
That's definitely going to be...
And that could be great for enterprises.
Oh, yeah, definitely.
Ah, good, good, good thought.
Good thought.
Well, Wes, man, thank you for joining me in studio today.
My pleasure.
It's good having you here.
Thank you, everybody, in the mumble room for joining us and giving us your thoughts.
If you'd like to join the Unplugged program, hang on our virtual lug, go to jupyterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar.
You get the live times over there.
We do it over at jblive.tv where you can have your Flash player armed and ready to go.
No, disable Flash this week.
That's our mission.
Disable Flash.
Use HLS, RTSP, RTMP.
We've got it.
They're linked.
Or go to jblive.fm and listen in audio.
Now, we do it over at jblive.tv.
You don't have to use Flash if you don't want to, but we do it at 1 p.m. or 2 p.m.?
2 p.m.
Yeah, that's right.
That's right.
Because we've got to have time for lunch, guys.
Right?
Got to have time for lunch.
And beer.
LinuxActionShow.reddit.com for feedback to this week's episode, and join us right back
here next Tuesday.
Okay, just do this.
And another show is in the bag.
Any post-show topics we wanted to get to before we skedaddle?
I got a meeting I gotta get to in a little bit.
I feel like I talked just as much as you did.
Yeah, you did talk a lot.
But it was good because it was a good thing you were here today because it was topics
that were up your alley.
I'm glad we got it covered.
First hand sushi experience.
Great topics and great conversation, guys.
Yeah, it was.
Thank you.
And it's great having Wes.
It's fun having someone I can look over to and talk to because otherwise I'm just standing
here by myself.
Now, there was a privacy topic I wanted to retouch on.
But maybe, I don't know, since we don't have a lot of time, maybe it'd be better to address
it next time when we can actually spend some serious time on it.
The mumble's got an update that's coming out soon for the next version of 1.3 is not going
to have the stupid lips.
What is it going to have instead?
It's actually replacing the theme with an actual good theme from this guy named X-Poke
and he made something called Metro Mumble, which looks pretty slick.
Using it now.
Is that the skin you and I were already using?
Yes, it is.
Metro Mumble, huh?
It does look pretty though, doesn't it?
Yeah.
A thing to note though, if you have a custom theme already applied and then you update,
it will unapply your custom theme and default to the light new theme.
So if you're using the dark theme, like I was, it'll just go away randomly and you wonder
why.
And then you go and see that, oh, there's new options in the look and feel section.
Not only is it new options, they've completely rebuilt the system so the skin structure where
you can control what you use is gone.
You have to change a new arbitrary folder structure that you have to place the themes
in and they don't tell you on Linux where your stuff is.
They tell you on Windows and only Windows.
I had to figure out where everything was and it's like a stupid arbitrary location that
even in its own selection is just absurd because it is, I'm just going to type it in the chat
right now actually.
I'm so close to jeopardizing my mumble setup here.
Is this just a theme that you could apply to an existing mumble?
Yeah I just applied it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You can apply it to your existing mumble right now.
BOOM!
But in the new version...
Go ahead, if you want to download and play it, you can.
It's up to you.
All you have to do is restart the mumble and restart the client.
Oh, I didn't even have to restart, I just hit apply and then bam, I had it like a boost,
I think.
Well, some of the icons won't update once you restart.
Oh yeah, you're right.
I'll do that.
I'll restart.
I posted the location of the themes folder now.
It's local share mumble mumble themes and the mumble twice is important and also the
themes folder does not exist.
You have to create it first and then put the theme in there.
So hey, would you mind, Mr. Corbs, if we reset just really quick so we can put this in the
pre-show since a lot of people listening to this show use mumble.
If you want to say, say how can we do this?
Actually why don't we make this the mumble pre-show?
Sure.
Yeah, so maybe the theme, where to get it and where to put it on Linux while I go grab
this printout and that will be like the pre-show.
Sure.
All right, I'm muting my mic.
There you go.
Have at it.
Okay.
So mumble is, they're actually updating to a new version.
This currently you can get in a PPA or in the AUR in a snapshot version and it's 1.3.
They're instituting a new default theme, which is actually really nice looking, but you can
get it right now.
It's for use in 1.2 to add as a skin.
And you get it from the GitHub link I posted in IRC and put it wherever you want.
And you can just go into your settings for configure and then choose the QSS file inside
of the skins structure.
This is how you do it in 1.2 and 1.3 it's automatically already available and you can
choose between the light and the dark.
The problem with that is that in 1.3 the theme is embedded into the program so you can't
change anything.
And one of the reasons this theme is actually awesome is because the majority of the icons
are SVGs.
So like for example, when you open this theme by default the non-talking icon is red and
I think that is hideous, especially when it goes into my system tray and it just falls.
So you can change that in the SVG code with just a slight hex value, change it to white
or gray or whatever fits best on your theme and it's good to go.
So the problem with the 1.3 is that you can't do that unless you download this theme and
put it in the correct themes folder.
And the correct theme folder is an arbitrary location that actually does not exist.
You have to create the folder there.
It is the location I just posted in IRC.
It's.local slash share slash mumble slash mumble then themes folder does not exist.
You create the theme folder then you put this extracted theme into that folder and then
the new 1.3 snapshot will notice that theme has been added and you can select it from
the drop down and it will save all of your modifications and things like that.
So I just applied it and lost all my audio.
That shouldn't make any difference for the themes.
And I've just switched back and the audio came back.
It's very weird.
It's just again it shouldn't change any audio.
Yeah it doesn't change any audio whatsoever.
I got the new theme installed and working.
I'm running the new theme on 1.3.
The thing that was annoying to me is that when I had the theme already and they updated
and it went to the same theme but it turned into white and it also essentially ignored
all the modifications I did because it wasn't looking for the right folder anymore.
And when I went to ask them where it was they had no idea.
The developers or maybe not the developers that actually made the change but the people
who are the support team in mumble for the IRC had no clue where the stuff was located
in Linux.
They sent me a link that said here's where it is.
That's Windows only and that's not very helpful.
So essentially I had to figure it out myself and it took me about 30 minutes but that's
the folder structure where it is now so at least no one else has figured it out.
I'm going to edit their wiki so it actually displays it properly.