All right, Eric, you got me to boot into Windows.
Oh, nasty.
I know.
Blame me.
Blah, blah, blah.
Oh, jeez.
This is a bad sign.
So it's a Broadcom manufacturer.
It says it's a Dell Wireless 1560.
What have you got?
Ayo, it's a Broadcom chip.
It's in a Dell laptop.
It says it's a Dell Wireless 1560 802.
What Dell laptop?
Is it that new sexy, shiny one with no bezels?
Yep, yep, yep.
Oh, you're a bad man.
Is it nice?
Yeah, it's very nice, except for the wireless on the Antigros Live CD isn't getting picked
up.
So I'm trying to work back what I've got to do to make this happen here, because I'd love
to get it installed during the show, but jeez, I don't even know where my USB adapter is.
I'm willing to bet the Broadcom STA driver will do just fine.
All right, well, I will be right back.
I'm going to go see if I can find my USB.
Oh, yeah.
Okay, I'll just share this.
So in the Ubuntu documentation, or Ask Ubuntu, or all those various places, it says about
installing the Broadcom STA, bloody, bloody, bloody, and actually what I found worked best
is installing the Linux firmware package, and magic happened, and my Broadcom card in
that one laptop that was a pain in the ass just works with the firmware.
So I shipped that in Ubuntu MATE because it works on those machines where it says, oh,
what you really should do is, you know, if you go into the Give Me Additional Drivers,
it recommends that Broadcom STA thing, which, by the way, doesn't work for this particular
chipset in my laptop, but just lobbing the Linux firmware on does.
So I'd start there because it does less damage than installing the Broadcom drivers, which
if they don't work are a bit of an ass to then yank out.
And it has to be compiled with DKMS, yeah.
Okay, so I'll go see if I can find a USB adapter, and maybe by the end of the show I can try
to get the wireless working.
Oh, what?
Now it doesn't see.
I brought, so I realized I got the Ethernet adapter all set up, but of course, guess what?
All my Ethernet's in use in here right now.
So I went and took a Wi-Fi adapter off of our Raspberry Pi here, but for some reason
it's giving me a hard time.
Oh, here we go.
Here we go.
Now it's prompting me for the password.
So I'll be using an old Wi-Fi adapter, and then once I get it installed, hopefully I'll
be able to get the drivers installed for the built-in Wi-Fi adapter.
So as a-
I've got-
Pre-show flight-
I've got questions for you, Chris.
All right, yeah.
So as a pre-show flight, right now before we go, I'm at the Antigros live CD.
It's updating the installer right now.
I've got a wireless dongle off on the side.
We'll see if by the end of the show if I have a successful installation.
What was your question, Mr. Whippy?
Well, first of all is aside from proprietary Wi-Fi chipsets, is it nice?
Oh yeah.
Oh yeah, it's pretty exceptional.
So it has a nice sturdy bottom feel to it.
It's definitely very thin, and it's surprisingly light.
In fact, when I picked it up, I wondered if the battery was missing.
And the screen is indeed touch, and the touch works under Linux, which is nice.
And the glass is pretty much edge to edge.
It's pretty nice.
And the keyboard looks like a good size keyboard, and the trackpad's a good size too.
So hopefully by the end of the show, I'll have working Antigros, and I'll tell you how
else it works under Linux.
The main thing right now for me is I'm a little worried about the Wi-Fi, which I'm sure
if folks got the Sputnik edition or whatever they're going to call it, they'd probably
have that worked out.
So do you think you could remove a panel on the bottom and expose the Wi-Fi chip and replace
it with an Intel something works in Linux variety?
Well, it looks like it's one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight torque screws,
and there's a panel that pops off, and then the bottom comes off.
I can see the motherboard through the ventilation, so it's probably doable.
Okay.
Well, yeah, we don't want to do that yet.
You don't want to bastardize it before you get started.
If the Linux firmware trick works and I can get the driver working that way, that'll probably
be the way I go.
Yeah, because I'm cheap, I only buy old hardware, and the first thing I do is yank out the Broadcom
things and buy an Intel something from Germany for nine euros, and then install that and
all your problems go away.
So do you want to hear a story from the other side of the fence?
You've got this lush new Dell machine, which is felt and is an Apple Mac beta, so at work
my boss has decided that it's time for a new laptop, and it absolutely is time for a new
laptop for him, and he wanted something that was relatively lightweight and super powerful.
So he scoured the internet, and he asked me a few questions, and he found the HP ZBook
14 mobile workstation, which on paper is a very competent machine.
It's got an i7, and it's got integrated graphics and discrete graphics, and it's got automated
flip-overs and all of that good stuff.
He doesn't care about Linux, so that's not an issue for him, and it just works.
So he said, I want one of those.
Can you get me one of those?
And I said, sure, no problem.
Of course I can.
So you go to the HP website.
The first thing about the HP website is unlike any other PC manufacturer, you can only buy
what they're prepared to sell you.
You cannot customize a system and say, I want this with these modifications.
So that sucks.
So then I say, right, well, we want this one, so order that.
And then he comes back to me and says, oh, no, no, I want the one with the touch screen.
So I say, right, no problem.
So I phone up HP and said, that order that you've placed, we want to cancel that because
we want to order one with the touch screen.
So they cancel the order, and then they tell me, well, there isn't one with the touch screen.
And I say, but your specification document says that there is.
A week goes by, the order that we've canceled arrives, and we have to arrange for it to
be picked up and returned to them.
They then tell us, oh, yeah, actually, we do make that one with the touch screen, but
it wasn't in our sales catalog.
So we're going to add that to our sales catalog.
So another few days pass, it's in our sales catalog.
Would you like to place the order now?
So yes, I'd like to place the order now.
So I order the laptop and all the extra accessories.
And this is last Friday, and today I get an email out of nowhere saying, your order has
been canceled.
And we don't know why, and we're not quite sure what happened.
But could you phone us up and place the order again, please?
Oh, my God.
I hate that.
HP suck.
If anyone from HP is listening, you suck.
Lenovo and Dell have got you beaten hands down six ways of Sunday.
You suck.
You have wasted three weeks of my life to buy one fuckmothering laptop.
Waste of my arcing time.
And it's not even that stellar.
I've been trying to talk my boss into getting a Lenovo Carbon X1.
Awful, awful, awful people don't buy HP computers.
It's like they don't want to make money.
Oh, it's just crap.
I actually had a little bit of a bumpy ride with the Dell.
So the Dell is, first of all, the whole buying process on the Dell website is way too cluttered.
I don't mean to make comparisons, but like, and obviously System76 has a lot less parts,
but it's so much more clear what I'm getting and if I'm getting the right one.
On Dell's website, I fundamentally question if I'm ordering the right part under the right
division, et cetera.
So that's very confusing.
Then they canceled my order at one point, but none of the accessories.
So they were billing me and shipping me the next day all of the accessories instead of
shipping all as one shipment, they shipped each thing independently.
So I've had the inverse of that.
So today we've replaced the order and the order is just for the laptop, but for none
of the accessories that we had previously requested in the original order.
So then I'm like, okay, so I'm getting the, so then I call them up and they had to verify
something about the address.
So the studio here is, it's a duplex, so we have a unit A, unit B, and I put the address
in and then the second address line, I put unit A. Well Dell's system wants unit A on
the first address line and the street address on the second address line.
And because I did those backwards, they canceled the order.
Yeah.
Brilliant, isn't it?
Honestly, it should be buying a computer be this difficult.
And the thing is, is that I'm going to phone them up to, I'm going to put a, cause I was
busy with other stuff today, so I had to ask one of the guys in the office to sort the
reorder out, but I'm going to phone them up to her and give them, well, the air will be
blue around my desk tomorrow morning because you know, I order all of the equipment for
all of the people that work in the company and all of our customers, which is not an
insignificant amount of hardware and I am not going to buy any HP equipment ever again.
And my purchasing experience, you have to set as a backdrop to ordering some really
sophisticated complicated server hardware from IX systems and you cannot, you cannot
even begin to compare the difference.
Right. So much more complex too, which is ironic.
I know, I know a lot more complex. Each individual machine we're talking, you know, $30,000 per
server versus a couple of thousand dollars for a laptop. And you know, it takes weeks
to negotiate the parts and the build and the fit. You remember those mega core systems
that FreeBSD Foundation have got? Yeah, we're buying like those, like they go out of fashion
at the moment.
Really?
We think they're great.
Oh yeah.
I'd love to see pictures.
Do you ever get to see them?
Yeah. I'll get you pictures. We've got a floor to ceiling rack of those.
Woo!
Doesn't TechSnap have a discount code you could be using?
No, just the URL.
Don't you, I'll tell you what, I first got the idea through listening to TechSnap and
went off and read about IX, say August, whenever it was. And I didn't actually get around to
calling them and placing an order until about six months later. But in the order code, it
triggered the fact that I'd first visited the website from TechSnap months and months
and months before and attributed the thing to TechSnap.
Thank you.
Even though a lot of time had passed in between the first contact.
You maybe you're a big part of the reason why IX renewed for 2015 then.
I hope so.
I hope so. That's really cool.
But they make stellar.
Aren't they?
Like I really wish when I was doing IT purchasing that I, I think they were around for a big
part of it, but I just didn't know about them. And I instead fought with folks like HP and
Dell all the time.
Yeah. No, we use IX for all of our server equipment now. And as much as I like love
Linux, for firewalls, we use HACOM for their PF sense firewalls. They're pretty great.
So they're active passive PF sense firewalls.
Oh, they are PF sense on the software side though?
Yeah. Yeah. So it is dedicated to PF sense. So it's a 1U rack with two blades in it. So
two firewalls.
Are they loud?
With carp. No, no, no, they're quite quiet.
Yeah.
How much does one go for?
I think it's about two and a half thousand, $4,000 I think by the time we'd got all the
bits and bobs I did.
Of course.
So, you know, they're, they're, they're proper, they've got six Ethernet ports on each blade.
So they're, you know, proper, proper job.
So you guys want to see another gadget. So I, with the Dell, I ordered a bunch of accessories.
This I don't know if you're watching the video stream. It's a, it's about, it's about the,
it's about half the length of a credit card, maybe about a little more than that and thicker.
So it's a, I don't know what to describe it. It's, it's smaller than a Roku. It's a small
little thing. You could probably fit it in your pocket. And what it is, is it has a USB
3.0 plug that flips out on one side and on one, on one side it has VGA and HDMI out.
And on the other side it has gigabit Ethernet and another USB 3.0 port. And so you plug
this into the Dell and you get HDMI and you also get Ethernet, which I thought was probably
pretty good because I'd like to have both of those pretty much every time I sit down.
And I think it was like 60 bucks or maybe even less than that. So, cause there's no
Ethernet.
That's a nifty gizmo, isn't it?
Yeah. And I think it's all using standard stuff. So I'm going to find out. All this
is, I mean, I'm going to try to do the full review. I'm going to try to, you know, say
these accessories work and don't work and stuff. Oh yeah. Oh yeah. Oh yeah. Did you
guys hear about this? This is a great post from Linus over the weekend. Linux kernel
development halted. Linus is pretty upset. Of course he's not on the East coast, but
it's still when it snows on the East coast, it affects Linus pretty bad. He says, you
people on these coasts think you have it bad with snow storms and whatever. That's nothing.
My coffee maker broke and calling the service hotline says we're not open today due to inclement
weather. You guys get a little snow and suddenly civilization breaks down. My coffee maker
is broken and nobody's answering the phone and CNN just keeps talking about snow. What
about my coffee? Priorities people priorities. What am I going to do without my coffee maker?
Am I just going to sit here in a corner crying? That's what I thought that was supposed.
Some of the comments were pretty good too because it's like, well obviously you need
your coffee maker in a raid. Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's
installing all its updates and blocking kernel modules right now. My name is Chris. And my
name is Matt. Hey there, Matt. How you doing? Doing pretty good. Doing pretty good. I'm
excited today. I got a new laptop in that I'm messing with right now. I just got the
base OS installed during the pre-show. That's exciting. I got that new computer smell. Right.
Also that new computer wireless frustration. So I've got like a, I've got like a wireless
dongle that's hanging off the side of the thing that I took from a raspberry pie. Other
than that, it's not so bad. So yeah, I got the new XPS 13 in and it came a lot sooner
than I was expecting. And uh, I guess, I guess the big point, I guess they want safe and
assuming there's a Broadcom thing going on. Yeah. It's called Dell wireless, but it's
a Broadcom. And I guess Dell wanted to cash in those Bitcoins before they dropped any
further. So they send it quick. And uh, so I'm, I'm, uh, I'm providing you right now
as we do the show with the wireless, I got a few things. I got, I just installed the
before or whatever it is firmware. I got the firmware just installed, but I think I'm like
halfway through there. So we'll see if I get it by the end of the show. I might get distracted
by the show, but I gotta say it's, it's a nice device. So I'll give you a quick update
about the, uh, the laptop and my first impressions, uh, later on in the show and just a little
bit, because I got a few things and then I'll run Linux on it for a little while and give
you the, uh, the final opinion. I've already gotten several emails, people asking what
I think about it. So I'll tell you that. Hey Matt, you know, it's not a, it's not a real
Linux unplugged without bringing in our virtual lug. So let's delay no longer time appropriate
greetings. Mumble room. Hello. Hi. Hi. Hello. So we've got a great show today coming up
on today's episode of Linux unplugged. We're going to do the feedback like we always do.
Then there's been a topic that the IRC room has been chatting about all day. It's this
new Vivaldi browser. No, not the tablet. No, not the Vivaldi tablet. Stop it. No, it's
a browser. And, uh, it's, it's making a lot of waves today. And of course it premiered
on Linux. So we're gonna talk a little bit about that and I'll give you a quick demo
of it in the show. Uh, there's also a couple of items to follow up on in, uh, from last
week's show. And then, uh, we have a little surprise for Matt at the end of the show.
Ooh, really? Yeah. Surprise for Matt. Surprise for Matt at the end of the show. So we'll
see what that's about. So let's start with a quick followup sort of errata from a Sunday's
Linux action show crossroads one, one, one, two writes in to say just a quick note on
the Lumina desktop on arch thing. I actually just had to rename the AR package is now Lumina
dash desktop dash get to avoid confusion with the German locale. Uh, so he says, uh, please
stress also on air that it's missing some features. Most of the network management icon
does not show up yet. Uh, probably cause PCB SD has its own network manager. There's some
upstream work to make it work with Debian. When I get time, I'll look into further Linux
improvements. So it's just early, but just a reminder, the Lumina desktop, which we've
talked about on the show, we've demoed it on the show and we've interviewed Chris, Chris's
brother who's working on it on this show. So I just quick follow up to that. You can
get it on the Lumina desktop. It has now moved over to arch, but there's a few pieces missing
in the packages called Lumina dash desktop dash get and Crossroads wanted me to make
a quick mention of that. So there we go. Jed writes in, and I love this email, Chris, Matt,
my son has finally gotten motivated to actually do something more than play flash games on
Linux. He's been using an old Dell lapi with a broken screen hinge. I decided he could
have my broken Lenovo T 43. I like it. Just give him die, passing down broken rigs. Just
like I do. Uh, one of the offices, but here's the conditions. He backed up his old computer
home director using our sink. Uh, he does this his, and then his own district install
and then he installs wine. I gave him links to some, to some tutorials about using our
sink and he already knew how to use G edit. He installed an SSH key for his backup. He
installed 1404 Ubuntu and the XFC weather plugin. And then we churn through a play on
Linux and he learned that we needed to move aside his previous post files and restored
his backup from his files from his first laptop. So now my sixth grader runs Guild Wars two
from his own install effort. He made a deal to get on track and fit and, uh, on field
team and the school in the spring as sort of like a tit for tat. Matt, thank you for
all the efforts on last. We cannot wait for your tutorial show listening since episode
one, Jed.
That's awesome. That's so cool. Sixth grade man. And he's already rocking SSHs. That's
so cool. I love that. I mean, that's like, wow, I'm thinking about like what I was doing
at sixth grade and it's like, uh, had that been an option, that would not probably been
what I was doing. So that's really cool. Yeah. I wonder about like, uh, my kids, like I want
to, uh, I have, uh, I started with the, uh, the Chromebook, but it's just such an unreliable
piece of junk when it's running just Linux and I haven't replaced the, uh, the bios that
they nuke it from time to time. So, uh, I, I have like this old HP that's falling apart
that they've used for a while. And I have this really old janky iMac that's it's old,
but I was thinking about maybe putting Linux on that, but really what, what, what my son
Dylan wants it for is to play Minecraft. That's what he wants Linux for. Yeah. He wants Minecraft.
Respect that. Respect that. Yeah. Yeah. I, uh, I, he also, you know, would probably play
around with it, but I've, I've, I've been thinking a lot about like, what's the right
computer to get for a kid. Something that is powerful enough to play Minecraft and maybe
a few other games, uh, but not super expensive and a really good Linux box. And I keep thinking
of like the NUC and stuff, but even that's pressing the price of what I want to pay.
So this is an area I've been thinking about. Maybe I need to do is just buy myself more
computers and give them a hand-me-down. This is what he's talking about. That sounds like
what Jed does too. And you know what, in a way that's kind of what I've done with my
smartphones. Uh, it's, and it's so straightforward with our first sponsor Ting because you only
pay for what you use. So I can actually have them get like a little tablet and then they
just, whenever we go out in the road and they have, they have to do something that has data,
which happens from time to time. I don't, I don't stress about having to have some sort
of data plan. They just pay for it when they use it. Go over to linux.ting.com to check
out our sponsor Ting. I've been Ting customer for over two years now, saved over $2,000
and I still recommend them every single day. I'm really happy. And I got to say almost
every month since I've been a Ting customer, I feel like there's something new for me to
be excited about something that Ting is bringing that I'm like, like they read my mind. And
of course the one I'm thinking of right now is the rollout of GSM. They've already sent
out the first SIM cards to early GSM beta testers. You can actually go over and order
one on the Ting store right now. And I got two of them and I'm going to slide one in
the, I'm going to reload my Nexus 5, get it all clean just cause I wanted to start fresh
anyways and we'll have, or I'm going to try to talk Rekai into doing it. And then after
Rekai does it, I'm going to put my new Ting GSM SIM in there. I'm going to rock Ting GSM
for a while. And you only pay for what you use with Ting. They just take your messages,
your minutes and your megabytes. They add them all up. Whatever bucket you fall into, that's
what you pay at the end of the month. It's just $6 for the line. You starting to see
how much sense this makes when you can take advantage of CDMA or GSM. Plus you then consider
all the value you get from an incredible dashboard and no hold customer service. And Ting has
a ton of great devices. I wanted to recommend also you check out their blog. They have a
ton of great tips and tutorials over there. Like here's one. It turns out G plus can be
a huge data hog. The app on your phone, the G plus app can be a massive data hog. So they
just have a quick tutorial on how to clean that up so you can keep G plus, but maybe
not have it use up as much data. Nice quick tips like that. Here's just an idea of devices.
Right now you can pick up an iPhone 4S from Ting for $130. That's it. You own it right
there. No contract, no early termination fee. iPhone 4S, $130. What about the HD Desire
510 Blue? Also $130. Just add it. A great HTC built phone for $130. Or if you want to
go get the Cadillac, the HTC One, $340 over at Ting and you own that phone that's yours.
And that is an amazing phone with an incredible screen, unbelievable speakers, and you might
think that the universal remote that it has built in there is kind of gimmicky, but it's
super cool, especially if you have kids and they lose the remote all the time because
you can turn on stuff with your freaking phone and it really feels like the future. Plus
those front facing speakers kind of alleviate the need for external speakers. So if you
like to listen to podcasts on the go or maybe like when you're doing something and you just
want to set your phone down, like I set it down next to me when I'm doing dishes and
I can hear podcasts, perfect with the HTC One. $340, you own that phone, it's yours
from Ting. Isn't that neat? They have all kinds of great devices including just SIM
cards if you want to put a CDMA or GSM SIM in your own device. Linux.ting.com, that supports
the show and saves you $25 off your first Ting device or if you have one you can bring,
get your $25 credit. Linux.ting.com and a big thanks to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
Great devices, great prices, and great stuff coming up. There's a Wolf writes in and this
one is kind of, I'm going to punt over to our mumble room to see if they have any experience
with this. He wants to know, he says, hey Chris and Matt, but I'm going to ask the mumble
room Matt if you don't mind. He says, I've heard about ArchBSD. The site is an exact
copy of the Linux homepage but with some BSD modifications. It says the project is all
about porting Pac-Man to free BSD, which they did back in 2010, and they say they keep following
the KISS philosophy. I'm not a BSD guy at all but this might actually be worth a try.
He says keep up the great work. He says he's practicing Markdown, he loves all the shows.
So anyone in the mumble room have any experience with this ArchBSD thing?
A tiny bit.
Yeah? And?
It works and it is BSD with Pac-Man on it. It's kind of compelling.
Interesting.
Is it current BSD?
That I couldn't say because I'm not so familiar with BSD to tell how current the underpinnings
are, but in terms of the packages I could install in it, the packages were definitely
current.
Too bad Alan's not here. I'm sure he'd have something to say.
Yeah, yeah.
I'm sure he'd have some mocking to say. He'd say, what's the point? That's what the port
system is for. That's what package add is for.
Well, that's what the AUR is. It's just a kind of portstree effectively, isn't it? Compile
from source portstree.
Yeah, a better one.
Yeah, well said.
Well, now that I have package NG, which I think is a port of Debian package manager.
Well, it's similar, right? Like in functionality, I've only used it very little. So I, yeah,
but I mean, it's, I mean, FreeBSD, honestly, in a lot of ways is doing it right. Yeah,
you have the core system and then you have the port system. And so I would imagine if
you could add the AUR on top of that, the problem I would imagine, I have no idea and
having never used this, but it seems like a crap ton of stuff wouldn't build. It seems
like a lot of stuff wouldn't build.
Why not?
Well, because it's like, it's just a totally different system. It's not an arch system
and there's, it's a totally, I mean, I don't know. I don't move a lot. I don't move around
a lot, but it seems to me like it's already a little tenuous sometimes if stuff is going
to build using AUR. It's not super tenuous, but you still have situations where stuff
just fails to build because something's different. I guess, I guess if you had a completely separate
copy of the AUR and you could modify all the package builds and I guess that was, I guess
if you totally had a separate AUR, then I could see it working, but it doesn't seem
like it would be as beneficial because it wouldn't be as popular. Am I missing something
here?
No, no, no, no. I mean, I don't know about, I think cross-platform compatibility won't
be such a big, big issue for most projects. I think most things all port almost seamlessly.
I think a lot of the upstream developers these days pay attention to making sure their stuff
works on other platforms other than just Linux.
I suppose the problem's getting less and less as FreeBSD gets more and more popular.
And if you look at projects like Arch Linux ARM, for example, they pull in the Arch Linux
packages and they just replace the I-686 and X86-64 architecture flags for ARM6 hard float
and ARM7 hard float and things just flow in and 99 times out of 100, stuff just works.
But why would you have the AUR? I mean, it would take the focus away from ports.
It's not just the AUR. They've actually got the community and extra repositories, you
know, so they're binary distributions of the packages rather than everything compiled from
source.
Yeah, I suppose the way I look at FreeBSD and OpenBSD, because I mainly float around
the OpenBSD world, you're better off getting those resources that want to work on an AUR
to sort of come on board and submit patches into the ports tree and then maintain ports
because then that way it gets a lot more coverage, a lot more visibility and a lot more testing.
You have a lot more people looking over the code that you're submitting as a port and
then that way you've got a better balance of quality.
Most of the Arch derivatives just use the AUR without any abstraction though, because
by adding a few architecture flags to a package in the AUR, it's applicable to ARM and PowerPC
hardware for those architectures and those spin-off projects that support those platforms.
I find it to be interesting, but it to me never seems like it's something that would
go mainstream.
Yeah, it is interesting. It's not for me, but it's kind of fun to tinker with.
Yeah, it could maybe be for somebody, it could be like the perfect setup, or for a lot of
somebodies even.
So I want to talk about... Oh, a couple of quick things I wanted to mention. I have this
XPS 13 laptop. I'll give that just a quick overview. And then also, if anybody out in
the audience has considerable audio production editing, like with music and creating sequences
potentially even, and laying that down to an audio track and things like that, and multi-track
editing, send in a shout... Just send me a shout, chris at jupitabroadcasting.com. Let's
talk.
That was one thing I had. And there was another item, but I forget what it was, but I'll think
of it as the show goes on. But there's another topic of business that I need to talk to the
audience about. But why don't I mention while I'm thinking about it, this XPS 13, because
that's what's got my attention right now.
So I didn't actually expect to get this until halfway into February. So when somebody rang
the doorbell, my response is, who the hell is that? That was a joke.
Matt came by to troll you.
Right, so I go down there, and of course it's a small box, and I thought, well this can't
be the laptop, because it doesn't come in a box. It's like this small little box. But
no, it was the actual laptop. And it came with Windows 8.1 installed. And I normally,
if I was buying this for myself, I probably wouldn't buy a Dell to begin with. That was
a question that came up on the subreddit. I kind of bought this for two reasons. The
first reason is we have a machine that's going to be getting replaced here in the studio,
and this could go there if it meets all expectations. But the real reason I wanted to get this is
I think this is going to be, from a hardware design standpoint, people who love Lenovo
love Lenovo. But if you're not a Lenovo fan or maybe you want something else, I think
this is going to be the laptop to beat Buildwise. I think this is a MacBook Pro killer, really.
This screen is better than what's shipping on the Macs right now. The resolution's fantastic.
The edge-to-edge glass is super nice. It really looks good. Plus it's a touch screen, which
I, you know, it's not like a big deal for me, but it's an augmented way to do input.
The keyboard's nice. The trackpad's nice. The button reach is good. The build is very
sturdy but it's light. I feel like it doesn't give at all when I'm holding it with one hand
and shaking it. And I don't hear any moving parts. Everything's solid, which is really
cool. And it's got two USB 3 ports on it. It has a DisplayPort, SD in, and audio out.
It also has a little battery gauge button on the side that you can press. Speakers are
also on the side. I haven't had a good chance to test them yet. And the battery life, when
I took it out of the box, said 14 hours remaining. I didn't leave it unplugged because Andrew
gross bitches at you during the installation. So, and the keys light up and the keyboard
does feel quite nice. The top has this sort of pattern etched into it that it feels good.
It's not overdone. It's not irritating, but it feels good on the hand. It kind of feels
like a carbon kind of stamping. The hinge is very strong. You know, I'm shaking it right
now and it doesn't give at all. So I think from like a portable tiny Linux rig, I think
this could be a killer unit. Right now I'm fighting with the wireless. So, and I think
if you were to buy the, the developer edition is what they're probably going to call it.
When it ships, you'd probably wouldn't have to worry about things like wireless. I'll
probably just put it like an Intel chip.
They'll probably give you Intel or something. Yeah.
So I'll give, I'll give this further, you know, I'll use this more. The things that
really jumped out at me so far is the speed's great. I got an i7 in there with eight gigs
of RAM and the display is very vibrant. It really pops. I don't know how things are going
to work high DPI wise. Gnome itself looks real good. I, you know, I, you know what I'll
do here real quick cause I'll fire up Chrome. Cause I'm thinking where I'm going to, and
the terminal looks really good. So that's, that's kind of the only apps I've used so
far is just Gnome and the terminal. But I'm, I'm firing up Chrome right now and we'll see
how that works. Let's see. Oh yeah. Chrome's a little small.
Oh, is it?
Yeah, it's a little small. I think there's some tweaks in the config you can do, but
yeah, it's definitely a little on the small side. Yeah. So I'll have to do some of that.
So I'll experiment with all of that. So I'll have a full report on Linux and high DPI support
and what tweaks I had to do a wireless tweaks I had to do and stuff like that. Hopefully
I'll get it all a straightened out. And then if you guys make the purchase, by the time
you buy it, I'll have a full report on if it's worth your money or not. And that's the,
that's really the reason why I wanted to get it now. Well, and that price of Bitcoin was
totally crashing. So there you go. I'll give you my full impressions very soon. I got the
one with the 3,200 by 1,800 resolution. I did that on purpose because in a lot of our
distro distro reviews, one of the areas I felt like we didn't really touch on a lot
because we couldn't is how it handles a high resolution display. High resolution displays
are here. High DPI is a real thing in 2015 and a lot of laptops across the line are going
to start shipping with it. So it's time for the Linux to really step up and have good
support for that. So I think it's time to incorporate that. It's not going to be a deal
breaker for the reviews, but I think it's kind of important to incorporate that in the
review. So, you know, if this is a distribution or a desktop environment or whatever it is
we're talking about, that'll look good on a high DPI display. So that's another reason
I got this too. So I can speak to the audience from that standpoint too. There you go.
It makes sense to come up with some common set of criteria that people could test their
laptop against, like a list of all the things you should check.
Because I know that's something that we've tried to come up with for a different open
source operating system whose name I won't say just because. Anyway, the problem becomes
everybody goes and tries to test things, but they always forget to test the thing that
matters to you, right? The thing that like, you know, high DPI, they might not consider
that. You know, they didn't consider does this feature work and how granular is the
backlight control or whatever. And it just seems like it would make sense to come up
with a big set of common criteria that anyone when they bought a laptop could just run all
their laptops through all these tests and post the results so that, you know, you kind
of crowdsource the information gathering since, you know, you can't buy every model of laptop
to do this with.
Right. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Crowdsourcing reviews would be interesting. I'm looking at the
myfixguide.com breakdown and it looks like not only is the bottom pretty removable, but
the wireless LAN card is right there front and center and labeled very, very generously
by Intel.
Yeah, they're usually like mini PCIe, right?
Yeah, and it doesn't look like it's too buried. Looks like it's just you take off those eight
torque screws and then there you go.
So if you do get one that doesn't have wireless that works, like I think that's the problem
you're having with yours, right?
Yeah.
The Intel Centrino 6205 is like $19 at Newegg.
Yeah, I might just get that anyways just that way when I reinstall I don't have to fight
it even if I can get it working.
Yeah.
And here's the SSD storage right there too. So the storage and the wireless look like
they're really easy to interchange. So I like that a lot. So cool. So I'll give you an update
because I literally just took it out of the box before the show started. I put it into
Windows once. Yeah, there's a better shot of the wireless card right there. Yeah, that's
going to be a really easy swap out.
I think that OS that Alan was referring to just a little bit ago rhymes with CDFB.
That doesn't ring a bell, Eric. I think he's talking about Haiku.
Yeah.
No, BUS.
Yeah. Oh, jeez, gosh, guys. The question, Marky asked, what's the Markdown editor I
use? It's called Herupad. Herupad's really great. And there's other ones too.
Spell that for us.
What's that? Herupad? Yeah, sure. It's H-A, let me pull it up right here. Of course, it
doesn't just say.
Even Chris doesn't know how to spell it.
No, I just want to make sure I get it right. H-A-R-O-O-P-A-D. And this is it right here
on my screen. This is today's episode of Tech Talk Today on my screen. And you see in one
column is my Markdown code, and the other column is the output. But what, okay, you're
like, okay, that's not too neat, Chris. A lot of Markdown editors do that. What's really
cool about this Markdown editor is you can go into the settings and you can pull down
your CSS files from your website and have the stuff in the preview rendered with your
website's real CSS, and you can really see really what it's going to look like on your
website. That is really cool because, for example, the Jupyter Broadcasting website,
it renders quotes slightly different than other websites render quotes, just the way
the block quote looks. So it's nice to have that. So yeah, it's Herupad, and it's a bit
of a monster. It's written on top of Node.js, but it has all of like under the insert menu,
it has all of the Markdown, like all your basic Markdown stuff all ready to go, and
these are also hot keyed. You can pull up in the help menu, it has all the key commands.
And so, you know, like, for example, Control Shift I inserts an image. Control Shift Q
makes everything a quote. Control 4 is a heading 4. Control 2 is a heading 2. So it's really
nice and makes it really fast to rip through Markdown. So it's Herupad, and we've talked
about it before. I've made it a pic a long time ago on last, so it's probably also linked
in the last pics. So there you go. If you can stomach Node.js, you won't even know.
It's all like a self-contained Chromium app.
You know, I think you should do it just for the shortcuts alone, because shortcuts rock.
Yeah.
I love shortcuts. I'm all about the keyboard.
Yeah, and don't forget, if you want to practice your Markdown, we have OpenYourMouth.recipes,
which are open source GPLed community recipes written in Markdown. It's a great place to
scratch that Markdown itch. And Herupad, you could write in there and then post it up on
our GitHub page, OpenYourMouth.recipes, open source recipes from the community. Hey, Matt,
you know, if you're going to say maybe you want to have your own GitLab or host your
own Ghost installation, or maybe you want to just mess around with free BSD, well, then
our next sponsor might have something that could interest you. That's DigitalOcean. Yes,
DigitalOcean's a great place to go to get your own cloud server. They're a simple cloud
hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you to spin
up your own cloud server. You'll get root access to it, powered by Linux and KVM. You
can get started in less than 55 seconds. Jay e-mailed me today. 23 seconds was his spin
up time. He got it all set up in 23 seconds. That is nuts. And pricing plans start only
$5 a month for 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a freaking terabyte
of transfer. Oh my gosh, I cannot even, this just blows my mind. I've been around for a
long time. This is just, I cannot, I remember a time in a data center when I had a colo
rig and I spent over $1,500 for a terabyte of transfer in a single month. DigitalOcean
has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, and London,
and their interface is amazing. It's so simple and intuitive and extremely powerful at the
same time. They didn't water it down. You can do your DNS management. You can take your
backup snapshots. You can resize your images. You can add RAM. You can move them. You can
transfer them. You can do console HTML5 level access, even watch the boot up screen from
post all the way up to your main Linux rig. It's so, or freeBSD, it's so cool. And they've
got core OS as well. And they've got this API that the community has just written a
ton of great stuff for. You could write your own stuff for it and, you know, extend the
functionality of the dashboard, however you like, snap it into whatever you need to snap
it into for management. But me, I just take advantage of all the great apps that have
been written. DigitalOcean.com. Go over there. Use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED. DOUNPLUGGED.
That's one word, lowercase. DOUNPLUGGED will get you a $10 credit. You can try out the
$5 rig, no credit card needed for free. Go try out a Minecraft installation. BitTorrent
sync. Sync thing. OwnCloud is crazy easy and they've got tutorials for everything. If you
get stuck on anything, they've got great tutorials. So once you get the rig spun up, you're ready
to go. DigitalOcean.com. Please, use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED to support the Linux Unplugged
show. Keep your favorite Linux talk show going every single week by supporting our sponsor.
And why not just de-cloud yourself a little bit? Take a look at what you have up in the
cloud, what third-party services you're using, and ask yourself, could I easily move that
over? This week's episode of Quota Radio, Mike was giving some tips on ways to save
money for development and primarily a great way to push updates out to your websites and
stuff totally for free once you set up the DigitalOcean Droplet. It was a great tip and
it's another great example of things you can use DigitalOcean for. We've got it running
a whole bunch of Ruby. We've got it running our BitTorrent for the backend syncing of
all the unfilter stuff, which is nuts. I mean, we have hundreds of syncs going on there.
It's all running off DigitalOcean Droplets. It's really awesome. It's unbelievably, it's
just an incredible great value and the management is so straightforward. DigitalOcean.com, use
the promo code DOUNPLUGGED, try it out for a little bit and see what I've been talking
about and support the show. DigitalOcean.com. DOUNPLUGGED. And a big thanks to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
Now, I want to talk a little bit about this Vivaldi browser because everybody's writing
about it. Everybody's talking about it. Chatter's been going about it. It's not a tablet. It's
a Chromium-powered, multi-platform browser. It's making some waves, if that's still a
thing. It's supported by Linux, Windows, and OS X. It's currently offered as a tech preview,
so it's got Chromium under the hood, but another, a bunch of features that sort of remind you
maybe of Opera during its glory days. Among them is speed dial and mouse gestures. Also
new features like allowing multiple tabs to be combined into a single stack. Support for
note-taking within the browser. You know, you need to take notes on a website. And other
improvements to the Chromium base. Started by a former CEO of Opera who has not been
with Opera for years. They plan in the future to include things like mail built-in, sync,
spatial navigation, greater performance. They want to be the fastest browser in the universe,
they say. Extensions and other community features. And it's available right now for Linux. I
have it installed right here if you're watching the show.
Matt, are you ready for another browser? Oh yes, absolutely. You know what we need?
We need another browser. And preferably one that's based on an existing browser because
then we can really hit, geez. You know, I'm going to not be cynical about it. It could
be awesome. It really could. I'm going to just hold my hopes up.
Well, okay, I'll play devil's advocate. I mean, I kind of agree with you, but if we
accept that maybe Blink and WebKit are as good as we're going to get for a little while,
then maybe it is good that the innovation's done more at the UI because I think you and
I both have lamented, the browsers really suck still. Like, there's not a browser, either
one of us are like totally jazzed up like, man, I just love Chrome. I love Firefox. You
know, like I use Firefox, I use Chrome.
So for me, it's like from a UI perspective, and this is excluding bookmarks because that's
a separate issue. From a UI perspective, Firefox makes people want to eat bags of glass and
Chromium and Chrome are frankly just more pleasant to use. Now, that being said, Firefox
performance destroys Chrome and Chromium because it sucks on Linux, and then you have bookmarks,
which is a completely separate issue because the problem with bookmarks is, hi, 1995, can
I have my bookmarks, please? I mean, this is stupid. The bookmarking system is what
really needs to evolve, more so than in my opinion. Bookmarks suck. I add stuff. I've
got bookmarks from like 2002 in there. I don't even know what they are. What is this?
I do like the UI. I think it's very nice, but they're not bringing a lot of new stuff
to the team, you know, and they don't have all of my plugins that I want to use. It seems
pretty fast. The UI is okay. It actually does have a few specific features that I've never
seen in anything else. Alright, lay it on me, sir. One, UI changes. Yeah, chameleonic.
If you ever used, what is it? That little fucking text editor, it actually has a little
command UI you can press F2 and you can do commands. Yeah, it does support like hotkey
navigation and stuff. Yes, that. I've never seen that in anywhere else. Also, since Opera
has done a lot of those weird little browser enhancements, it's got little tab UI. You
can drag the top down and see previews of your tabs or hover over them, which is what
the old Opera used to do. Oh, that is nice. But it's actually quite interesting. I like
the way it displays your current tab too. It's really easy to see which is the current
active tab. Okay, so the first implementation, it's not so bad. This is actually the way
they color the tabs is actually kind of smart. It's chameleonic depending on the... The whole
top bar changes. Yep, take a look at the whole top bar. Everything changes. I gave it a snapshot
of Jupiter Blood. Those tab stacks are brilliant. Yeah, that is pretty cool. Oh yes, there is
some interesting bits about it. Yeah, so tab stacks in their words, yeah. I think tab stacks
I like better because you can see it right by hovering over it. For me, tab stacks is
easier than tab groups because tab groups are put off somewhere else. They're hidden
in a way. Whereas tab stacks are just right here. And the way they demonstrate the lines
so you can see how many tabs are in this stack is really clever too. You can actually drag
down right above the URL bar. You can actually have a little thing like the little drag down
and you can drag down the top and have visual pieces of tabs right up at the top. And their
settings looks very deep in our progression. Oh, I see. The settings manager is very interesting.
Oh, look at that. You can just get a little peek too. You can just have a little peek
of the... That's really cool. Yes, it's the old Opera. It's coming back. The guys, the
real balls are actually putting their ideas forth again. That's cool. I don't know how
much you guys have used it but I've been using it all today and it is super fast. This is
the first time I've tried it. I mean, after Chrome and Firefox, this is refreshingly quick.
It feels like 2015 on the internet, the speed at which... Oh, and you can put the tabs on
the left side which is really nice for widescreen. Actually, you can remove the tabs. Completely
say none. No tabs at all. There's no other one I've seen which can remove the tabs. Chris,
this is one of the reasons that people that used to use Opera are so passionate about
it is because they do things in a completely fundamentally different way. And when you
get used to it, going to a standard Firefox or a standard Chrome browser is just... It
feels clunky. I'm digging all the key commands. So Wimpy says it's super fast. I find that's
the case on a brand new clean install of Chrome, Chromium, Firefox, or basically insert name
of browser here. As soon as you start using it and fill in some... Throw in some extensions,
yeah. Yeah, throw some extensions in there and then all your bookmarks and then you start
visiting a load of pages. They all slow down to a bag of crap. All of them. If you take
a fresh Chrome or a fresh Firefox and you don't fill it with the shit ton of plugins
that you use, Poppy. You know I don't use shit ton. I have like three plugins on all
my browsers and they all run like you're swimming in treacle. If you go for a plugin less Chrome
or Firefox and compare the speed that this renders pages and visit pages that you've
not been to in any of the browsers, this is very, very quick at rendering pages. Are we
doing another browser challenge? I've not been that excited about a new browser since
I first started using Chrome in 2008. This is really good. Should I tell you the one
drawback? Yeah, sure. Sounds amazing. The user interface is basically Amiga OS 3.5.
It's so flat. It's $19.99. But other than that, it's brilliant. I like the loading bar
too. Sublime text. The little command thing. You can press F2 and it'll give you a sublime
text command. Oh my gosh. That is so cool. That is the neatest. Oh my gosh. Oh my gosh.
Oh my gosh. That is so cool. Can you hear that guys? Look at there's all my tabs and
then here's all of the commands I could do. Oh my gosh. This is so cool. One of the reasons
why Firefox can slow down over time is because you're building up that SQLite database for
the awesome bar and a bunch of other stuff. So if you feel your browser is slow, try a
fresh profile. It's not necessarily just plugins that make it slow. That's excellent. If you
can add this alongside a fresh profile. I'm pretty sure that's exactly what I said just
now which is any browser which is super clean is good and then after you use it for a while
it turns to shit. Yeah, but you were saying it was the plugins that were default and usually
it's not. No, I didn't. The only thing that I miss is the ad blocker. Have you seen how
the... Is the databases and stuff and maybe we should find something better. Yeah, I noticed
this. It's a nice little touch. The navigational buttons, so back home, reload and all of that,
as you visit a website it automatically themes those controls to the color profile of the
website that you're viewing. For a debut, for a technical preview, this is really polished
and very slick. Yeah. And I've already mentioned on this forum to open source this thing as
much as they can because I want them to because this is pretty darn interesting. Yeah, that
is the thing we have to talk about. That's the elf in the room is that it's not open
now. Blink or whatever, Chromium or whatever you're going to say it's based on is but the
Chrome around it is not. Well, Opera is the same situation. I'm trying to put their balls
in a vise to get them to open their code. I guess the question is how do they make a
business out of it then? Donations? Like most open source projects depend unless they're
going to sell their code to the Wii again like they used to with the old Opera. So Wimpy,
you think it's a bigger deal than we're giving it credit because the browser is the new OS?
You think this is a huge thing? Yeah, this is precisely my point. I think that from this
point onward the browser is the operating system and Chromebooks have proven that point
over the last year more than anything else. And I think having a choice in our browser
options is as important as having choice over our operating systems. I would agree. The
only reason internet browsers got better is because we've had competition otherwise we'd
all still be stuck. Helpy competition is a good thing. May the best browser win. May
the best browser help everyone else. And I think this is one to watch and I like that
they launched with cross-platform support out of the bag. I think that's a really good
sign. I don't think it's going to make me switch. Well, maybe. It depends on where the
plug-in direction goes. I see the thing is that that launcher that it has, I could probably
go get that for any browser with an extension, but I do like that a lot. That is really cool.
So it's the Vivaldi browser. We'll have a link in the show notes if you guys want to
check it out. That sounds like a lot of you have been trying it though. So I'm going to
keep it around for a little bit. I need things like tab sync and all kinds of fancy stuff
though. I really am pretty demanding. All I want is a better bookmark handling. That's
all I want. And I've tried the plug-ins and I've tried all these hacks and variations
and well, everybody's got the new, what? No, it's crap. It's crap. It's still the same
old. What is the problem with bookmarks though? I have 5,000 plus of them and I'd like to
make heads and tails out of them. I have Firefox bookmarks because I actually can't not use
Firefox because of the bookmark structure is so awesome. With the keywords searching
where I can just jump back and forth with just using commands. I need something to automate
bookmarks. I think there's probably a self-help group for Matt. For people like Matt who have
thousands of bookmarks. I personally have zero. I just don't use bookmarks. I just
use Google really, really well. I have about a thousand. I use Pinboard as a third-party
service I can access from any computer in any browser by logging in. That might be an
option. Yahoo failed as an entity because they tried to catalogue the internet by themselves.
What would you try? They tried it with humans was the problem. All right, I will give...
X marks has some kind of like auditing the stuff. Yeah. I'll give, because Alex has been
wanting to say it a hundred times. Alex, you wanted to say something from the perspective
of a Firefox user. I've been using Firefox with a lot of tabs and a lot of bookmarks.
For me, bookmarks are like my own personal search engine. What I would like one day would
be to have Yacy integrated into Firefox. Sure. A real search engine in my browser. Yeah,
that'd be cool. About tabs, the old Operado version 12 and the current Firefox are the
only tab browsers that support over 200 tabs. I usually have around 100 open tabs at some
point and the maximum I reached is around 600 at some point. That is respectable. I've
heard a few other people, like I had a client that always had a whole bunch of browser windows
open a whole bunch. I always get worried. I always get worried that my browser is going
to die on me and that I'll lose all that. I don't have faith in the auto restore system.
That's what I actually use bookmarks for is I use just mainly my menu bar and I just stashed
stuff in there. Matt, we have a surprise for you that I want to get to, but before we do
that, I've got something really exciting to talk about. That's Linux Academy, the sponsor
of the Linux Unplugged show. Linux Academy is always rolling out tons of new features.
That's why I want to encourage you to go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and take
advantage of our discount. They just rolled out a new Ruby course, which is perfect for
me because Matt, I'm going to go, I don't know if I'm crazy, but I'm going to go teach
myself Ruby. I hadn't decided. I was on the fence and then Linux Academy was like, yeah,
we got a new course on Ruby. I'm like, all right, well now I feel like I've been given
the pathway to follow. I can't really mess it up if I go with Linux Academy. I want you
to go check them out too. Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged. Get your special unplugged
discount. They've got step-by-step video courses for everything you're doing, comprehensive
study guides you can download, getting to break you out time estimates of how long each
stuff's going to take. It comes with your own server as the lab course requires it,
pins it right up, whatever Linux distribution you've chosen. That's what the server OS is
and of course all the courseware just kind of adapts to match that. And I think that's
a pretty nice feature if you're maybe moving from one distro to another, like if you switch
jobs from a Red Hat place to an Ubuntu place or Debian to CentOS, something like that.
You get to keep track of your progress as you're going right as you log in the dashboard
to give you a percentage heads up of where you're at with your different stuff, how long
the next section is going to take you. They have learning plans. You go in there and you
say, hey, I've got this much time on Monday, this much time on Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday,
Friday, Saturday, Sunday. I can allocate this much time, generate me a plan, and Linux Academy
system will create a custom plan that matches that schedule that you've laid out with reminder
systems to keep you going. Plus, as a Jupyter Broadcasting community member, you'll meet
lots of like-minded folks who are there from Jupyter Broadcasting in the community that
can give you a bump when you're kind of slowing down a little bit. Also, go make sure you
check out their new Docker courseware. There's not another technology that's hotter right
now in the Linux space and they've got great stuff, great courseware on Docker. Also, vagrant
virtualization options up the wuzang from KVM to Zen. They got it all. You guys should
go check it out at Linux Academy. Ruby, Android development, OpenStack, the whole DevOps category
they've got courseware for over at Linux Academy. It's a really valuable service. LinuxAcademy.com
slash unplugged. Go check them out and support your favorite talk show, Linux Unplugged.
That's a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged show. LinuxAcademy.com
slash unplugged. Thanks, you guys, and thanks to all the audience members who support Linux
Unplugged. Okay, Matt. I think there's probably a portion of folks who watch this show or
listen to this show that don't watch or listen to last. For those who are not current, this
Sunday, the episode that just aired, was Matt's last official day as co-host, although I'm
sure he'll be back to the show from time to time to visit. He's launching with producer
Q5SIS who's here today as well. The rebirth, the raising from the ashes of our How-To Linux
show. Better focused, stronger than before. Matt, we thought we'd do a little parting
tradition as a send-off for the years of great service on the Linux action show right here
on Unplugged for our last segment of the show. I'm going to kick it off. You may have heard
there's this great new graphics card that's out there on the market. In fact, Ferronix
just gave it a great review for Linux gamers. It's called the GeForce GTX 960. It uses the
latest Maxwell GPU from Nvidia. I, as a thank you to Matt, now it's here at the studio,
Matt, but I ordered you a brand new video card, a GTX 960, so you can try out the 960
in the Linux rig and give us a report back on how it works here on the Unplugged show
because now on Sundays you're going to need to get some gaming picked up. Some folks in
the Mumble Room to kind of sweeten the deal a little bit are going to send some Steam
games that they have available in the library. I want to encourage anybody in the audience
too that wants to help Matt put his new Nvidia 960 card to use. I have Matt's Steam profile
linked in the show notes. It's ironspankingmatt, which is, I don't know, where does ironspanking
come from, Matt? Is that like a metal reference? Oh, that was an unreal, actually a little
bit. No, it was actually an Unreal Tournament thing. Back when I was really playing that,
someone felt like they, there's like a backstory to it, basically long and short of it. It's
an Unreal Tournament ironspanking kind of deal. So I thought a good way to do it would
be to get you to waste a bunch of time. So the audience and I came together and Blaster
chipped into on the video card here. So that'll be here in the studio next time when you come
down to shoot your first batch of how to Linux, you can leave with the new GTX 960. Oh, that
is awesome. Thanks. I appreciate that. That's fantastic. That's really cool. Then just give
us a report here on Unplugged in the future of how it went. Yeah, for sure. Thanks, Matt.
And watch out for Steam games coming your way. I think a few folks in the audience are
going to send you some. Yeah, I'm still sorting through email and I've actually got a couple
thanks to send it out. Cool. And then you'll keep us posted on when how to Linux launches,
which we'll have probably in February sometime. Q5, is there anything you want to jump in
at this point before we move off from that topic? You good? Going once? Just that if
anybody has ideas for good topics, send them in. That's about it. There you go. Okay. And
we'll have ways to do that too. And I think we still have the, we still have the how to
Linux email account you can email as well. Or you can ping us in the subreddit. We're
checking that or email Matt or Q5. Yeah. Either way. There's a lot of ways to get in your
suggestions and we'll come up with some official ways to submit them into the show. I know
we've had some, we've had some like spreadsheets in the past, but we'll figure it out. So Matt,
enjoy the new gaming setup. Oh, definitely. You now got like a way nicer video card than
I've got, I think. I was going to say that's really stylin'. That's hard, Matt. I was like
no, no, it's a nice parting gift. It's a have fun with this. That's awesome. And then on
Sunday show, I actually don't have the full show planned out yet, but Noah is landing
in the Pacific Northwest probably Thursday, depending on his work schedule. And he'll
be in studio for Sunday's Linux action show. And I'm probably going to take him out to
dinner and stuff like that. So I don't know what all our plans are, but I think it's going
to be a really fun show on Sunday. We'll have some, some shenanigans that we'll probably
have planned by, by Sunday. So we'll have Noah in studio to kick off his new reign as
co-host on the show. And we'll update you guys on the how to Linux progress as we've
got it. I think it's getting, it's coming along quite well. So we'll probably have an
update very soon. Okay. Cool. All right. Well, and thanks to everybody who sent the stuff
to, to Matt. We were talking about it on tech talk after today. We were scheming while still
on the air and I wasn't sure if you were listening or not. I didn't think you were. I thought
we were safe. Cause it was, you know, I was obliviously. Yeah, no, I was actually, I think
I was picking up dog do at the time. But yeah, my glamorous life as a co-host. I like that.
It's good. I think that's a good way to do that and listen to Chris's other show. I think
that's, you know, you can do both at the same time. You can do both at the same time. Yeah,
you can, you can. Although, although it's an art form to pick up the poo. You just go
over to jblive.info on your portable device and we've got a high bit rate and low bit
rate audio streams. Or you can go to jblive.tv if you're on the wifi where you're out there
picking up the poop, Matt. So there you go. It's a little tech talk tip. That is the tech
talk show. We do that on a, we do that in the mornings. You guys should check that out.
But Hey, don't forget who cares about tech talk. Join us next Tuesday for the episode
78 of Linux Unplugged. Come get it in. If you've never made a live show, get it in before
we had episode 80. You got a little bit of time left. We do the show on Tuesday and if
I don't see you on Tuesday, hope to see you on Sunday. Bye, everybody.
Matt, picking up poop like a good neighbor should. Well, you know, after a while, you
step in it so many times. It's just a sanitary, it's a sanitary thing for the dogs. I don't
want to walk through it. Yeah, no kidding. Yeah. No, I'm old school. Get yourself a bag,
be a man, bend over, pick that stuff up. I don't understand why we're wasting our times
on Roombas when this is a job that can be done by robots. I don't get it. There's actually
a poop 911 business here in town, you know, for people who don't want to pick up their
own apparently. All right. JBtitles.com. JBtitles.com. Yeah, Matt, they have those on the East Coast.
It's called Duty Calls. Nice. I like that. The fourth browser, the fourth browser is
not bad. The fourth browser is not bad. All right, you guys go over there. JBtitles,
go boat. I had a little shout out. I noticed a thread in the subreddit that needs more
of. A day ago, Stofaloaf2 submitted, what does your prompt look like? And he submitted
his and we've got a few other folks. There's 12 comments in here, but not a lot of pictures.
So I want to look at people's desktop porn. So if you would go over to that subreddit
post and I'll have it linked in the post show notes. Go submit your desktop. I like looking
at people's desktops. I even tried to do an episode of it once. It's in the subreddit.
I'll link to it in the IRC right now and I'll have it linked in the show notes for this
episode of Unplugged. But I like looking at people's desktops so much, I tried to make
an episode out of it. It was like a super boring episode. So I don't do it anymore,
but I still like looking at them. So go over there so I can, I get ideas. And I just got
a new laptop. Just for reference, when Angela did it, it was an exciting show. I know. Because
she does it with awards. I don't have awards. I just gawk. But I got a new laptop set up,
so I want inspiration. I've actually converted my KDE set up to look like Gnome. Oh jeez.
That's where it starts. And by the way, I have 931 unread Reddit messages. So if you
message me on Reddit... Good grief. Good luck with that now. Yeah, I'm sorry. I don't mean
to ignore you, but at a certain point I can only respond to so many different communication
methods. Same with Facebook. I don't really respond on Facebook either. Okay. JBtitles.com,
Vivaldi, the 4th browser. Is that too long? What about just the 4th browser? It just seems
like it, because it's four words. Yeah, alright. I do like having Vivaldi in the title. Yeah.
Alright, we'll go with that. Nicely done, Wimpy. Nicely done. You're welcome. I'm glad
you had a chance to get the tires too, because you guys had some great tips for me to check
out, because I literally just installed it before the show. Or during the pre-show. And
it's pretty nice. I think I'm going to live with this for a good little while, because
it's really terrific. Well, I'm going to check back in with you then. Oh, geez, Wimpy. Get
a room. Well, you know, I'm usually a miserable old curmudgeon. I've found something that's
really quite... It's new and it's good. What is it? The Luddites say? This is the antithesis,
the opposite of that. Some change is progress. Popey, don't judge. It makes them happy. And
I know Alan, don't ruin my mood. You've been super helpful the last two days. Don't make
me all grouchy and miserable, coming in here and bitching at me.