This is Linux Unplugged Episode 32 for March 18th, 2014.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's stockpiling bananas in preparation
for this Sunday's Monkey Suit Spectacular. My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
Hey there, Matt. We've got a good show lined up today. Falling right on the heels of our
review of SolidXK on last, we'll be discussing the distribution with the co-founders themselves
coming up in a little bit. And I don't know, I'm really conflicted because there's a lot
we could talk about this week, but I also kind of have to keep it a short show because
right after we get off the air, I've got to run to meet up with an electrician at the
new studio. That's going down like crazy. Rekai landed yesterday. He's at the studio.
He's actually getting goodies right now to get ready in preparation to prepare his body
for editing of these shows. So he's got to have sustenance. So Angelo's out with him
right now taking care of all that. It's been a pretty crazy couple of days driving back
and forth with a lot of gear. And so one of the other things I have to do for all the
studio shenanigans is meet with the electrician. I've got to start up a new conversation with
a new contractor. I know why contractors have a bad name now, Matt. Let me tell you.
Well yeah, I'll tell you. There's a lot of back and forth. Although I will give a shout
out to your previous contractor. He did kind of have some life circumstances.
That's true. What are you going to do, right? The universe is a cruel place sometimes.
But nonetheless, we're going to just go for as long as we can and get as much covered
as we can today because there's been some interesting developments even just since Sunday
that I want to discuss. And I'm really looking forward to talking to the Solida XK guys.
So stay tuned for all of that stuff. But first, I thought maybe we'd cover a little feedback
and see if we can't solve a Mac user's problems. Yes, that's right. Because he wants to switch
to Linux. We should also tease, in case we forget later in the show, this Sunday on the
Linux action show. It is monkey suit time. The bet comes due this Sunday. Now, for those
of you that don't remember, Matt made a bet, and he's willing to pay up, that Mir would
ship on another distribution outside of Ubuntu within a year, and it didn't happen. Now,
I think some folks at Canonical at the time probably agreed with Matt.
Oh yeah. I won't say there were promises because that's not fair, but I will absolutely say
that support was given on my behalf.
They said they would do their best, but it just didn't work out. But we'll just use the
opportunity to kind of just look at the state of Mir development, alternative display managers
on Linux, and if everything goes as planned, we'll have Kevin on from Canonical to talk
a little bit about the state of Mir. So I think we're going to have monkey suit shenanigans,
we're going to have a good conversation around where all of it's at a year later. So it'll
work out to be a great episode coming up on Sunday. But why don't we start by seeing if
we can help out Simon's problems here. Simon really wants to switch from the Mac. He says,
hey there Chris and Matt. I'm a web developer and a Mac user, and I feel it's time to move
on. I feel that Apple is focusing more and more on their iOS platform and losing sight
of its desktop power users. I'm not blaming them. That's where the money is. I get that.
But that's not the computer experience I'm looking for.
I have some experiences with Linux, both on the server and on some older desktop machines
here at home. But I want to go all in and use Linux on my desktop, the machine I need
nine hours a day to get my work done. But now I need some help from you guys. What distribution
should I go for? I'm tempted to go with Ubuntu as I feel it might make the switch easier
for me. He says maybe I can even replace an iPhone with an Ubuntu touch device down the
road when it's ready. It's close to the Mac user experience and might be the smoothest
transition without preventing myself from getting any real work done. Later I learned
the pros and cons. Maybe I could switch to a different distro at that point. But with
most Linux users, they don't seem to like Ubuntu. Lots of you complain about Unity
and Mir, but no one likes to explain why. What's up with that? It's simply a matter
of personal taste? Is it envy because of canonical success? Is that the reason for the hate?
Thanks for helping me choose. Simon.
Boy, you know, I think the first question I would have to ask him is what is he using
for web development? Are there legacy applications at work that could potentially create a bit
of a hurdle making the switch completely? Now, if he's just doing this straight from
like a notepad or something like that, no big deal.
Yeah, he said web developer. So I'm going to just give him the benefit of the doubt
that, you know, he could probably he'd maybe he's using a sublime text on the Mac. He could
use sublime text on Linux.
Sure. Okay. So let's say he's going that route. I think he's going that route. I think Ubuntu
does make sense simply because it does feel very natural to a lot of Mac users. My wife,
if she's going to use Linux, will generally prefer Ubuntu simply because she finds the
flow is more familiar to her. Generally speaking, compared to other distros, although she's
pretty comfortable in most distributions, it's really not such an issue with that. And
I also think the App Store coming from the Mac also then going to Ubuntu is also fairly
familiar in that regard as well. What do you think as far as hatred, though?
What about the idea of making his Linux desktop match whatever web server platform he's deploying
on? So if he's deploying on a CentOS box, maybe Fedora might make more sense or CentOS
is enough, maybe? I can't think of very many situations where
a newcomer in Fedora would ever fit the same sentence. I think Fedora is a great distro,
but it is not. And anyway, I couldn't picture that unless it's maintained for them and then
that's different.
What do you think, Mumble Room? So you got a Mac user. He's a web developer. His name
is Simon and he's thinking about switching from the Mac to Linux. What distro would you
say he should pick?
I think something very similar. I came from Mac to Linux, and I felt very comfortable
at the time with Unity on Ubuntu.
It really depends on what sort of workflow he's desiring. If he's desiring a Mac-like
workflow, I'd almost recommend elementary OS, and therefore maybe GDK.
Please no.
Ouch, wow.
Their packages are so out of date that it's not worth using them.
They're based on a stable 12.0 for LTS.
Right. If they just updated their packages, that'd be fine. They update the security stuff,
but they don't update any of their packages. For example, my app hasn't been updated in
Ubuntu for like two years. So by default, the package in elementary is also two years
old.
There will probably be an update when the new LTS comes next month.
I'd probably recommend Ubuntu, maybe. Partly because it's awesome, but partly because with
the LTS just around the corner, he'll get a nice shiny new kernel, long-term support,
and every app he needs, basically.
To be fair, I think the hate against Ubuntu is purely Unity and pretty much preferences.
I don't like the Dash, but everything else in Unity I like. The local menus, it's in
14.04. Awesome.
Okay, so he could get the benefit of having the kernel and switch and use XFCE or Gnome
Shell or any one of a bazillion other desktops that are all in the repository. You don't
have to switch to show some random distribution from some guy in his bedroom. You could use
Ubuntu and just not use Unity if you don't want to. That's fine.
I think he should just try out some different distros, maybe start with Ubuntu and just
see what he likes because we're not going to be able to...
You're saying Linux from scratch? Is that what you're saying?
I think he was saying Gentoo. I think I would recommend SolidXK. That's what I would recommend.
Seriously, that might be worth consideration.
The other thing I want to recommend to Simon is he said that in his letter, he said that
he's got some older machines that he's had some experience with Linux on, both a server
and an older desktop machine. I would not recommend you say switch from a relatively
recent MacBook Pro to a several-year-old PC machine and load Linux on it and experience...
You're not going to have a great experience because you're going from pretty high-end
hardware to lower-end hardware. So give Linux a chance to breathe. If you're used to...
If you work at a machine, like you said, for nine hours a day to get work done and you're
used to that machine being very powerful, then don't limit yourself with a resource-limited
machine just because that's the one you can load Linux on. So position your hardware correctly.
Try out some different distributions. Try Integros. Try Solid. Try Ubuntu. Try SUSE.
Try all of them, really. I'm betting like the most of the chat room, you might end up
liking the more recent Ubuntu versions.
Yeah. Well, and I go back to what I said about the user interface. For a lot of Mac users,
that's a big deal. And I think Ubuntu nails a pretty close match for my experience.
Yeah. Yeah. Gnome 3 is pretty refined these days, too.
Yeah. Gnome 3 is okay. Gnome 3 would be all right. I could see that, especially with a
little dock action going on.
Yeah, a little dock action. But I just say, just try it out. And like you said, it sounds
like you're pretty open to the idea of moving later on. The Ubuntu hate kind of just comes
from... There's a lot there. You basically... Just listen to the back catalog of the show
and it'll actually explain it pretty well.
Yeah. Listen to that last one episode.
Yeah. Listen to the last episode. Exactly. That actually covered it pretty well. And
I think that if you're comfortable with the things I discussed there, and I think you
probably would be, like we got an email from a viewer who said, you know, I'm long time...
Actually, I think I have it in the pile here. I'll see if we can get to it. Because I think
I do have an email from... Yeah. We have an email from somebody who's going to touch on
that. So we'll get to that in a minute because I think there's a lot of people who just don't
care about some of the things that get people all riled up. And then there's a lot of advantages
to Ubuntu. There's a lot of advantages to all of them. Try them out, Simon. Keep listening.
Check out our back catalog. I think that'll give you some help. But the big piece I wanted
you to take away from my recommendation is don't straddle yourself with lower end hardware
and then expect to be blown away. You're not going to have a bad time necessarily, especially
if you go with something like Popey was saying with XFCE or Solid X. But you probably won't
need the same amount of hardware. But I am somebody who's very sensitive to low performance
hardware. And if I had a MacBook Pro with 16 gigabytes of RAM, an SSD, and a high end
video card, and then I switched to something with a spinning drive, maybe an integrated
GPU, and a core to do or something like that, I don't think I would use that machine very
long. And I think I would have a pretty bad time. And I think that would influence my
opinion of that operating system in general. Because it just would feel restrictive.
Well, it's an excellent point. The bigger point of it is, too, is that I don't care
what version of Linux you're using, what distro you happen to go with. If you're using a lot
of resources, such as like a browser with a bunch of tabs open, you're going to care
about the hardware it's running on. Really, you can run lightweight desktops all day long.
I also agree with Ayamakan in the chat room. I'm not a big proponent of putting Linux on
a Mac. You can do it. But there are always compromises. And people who tell you there
aren't compromises haven't been running it long enough.
Or all.
Yeah, it's just, unfortunately, it is the truth. Like for example, whenever I had tried
it on a Mac, I've always had issues with the webcam. There's a blob that you have to load
up at the time of boot up that you have to... I guess the Mac operating system actually
loads like a firmware onto the webcam every time Mac OS X starts. And you have to replicate
that under Linux. And you have to go extract that firmware out of a Mac, move it over to
your Linux install, and then, you know, follow some sort of guide online to make that work.
There's other things that don't work. Like on more recent, like say, 2012 Retina MacBook
Pro, I'm reading a discussion thread here that was a really good one on Reddit over
the last weekend. Wi-Fi is extremely flaky for this guy. He says he doesn't have any
problem under Mavericks, but when he's under Linux, his Wi-Fi drops out. Reduced battery
life. Under Linux, he gets 4.5 hours compared to 8 hours under OS X. Once the video and
video blob loads, he's unable to switch to one of the TTYs, you know, by doing Control
Alt and hitting F1 or F2 or F3. He says the touchpad is extremely quirky. He says I've
ironed it out as well as I can, but I'm still not completely happy with it, particularly
when typing from the web like this one. A little more than just a slightest touch or
reposition of my typing cursor and the position of the mouse cursor. It can be infuriating
at times. He says I've had to reread this exact post three times just to make sure I'm
catching the errors that this one single issue has caused. So don't necessarily load it on
a Mac and expect it to work well. Different Macs have different success rates. Generally
the newer the Mac, the less things that work. So also consider that, Simon. You might want
to consider a dedicated machine that's really, you know, going to give you a better experience.
And if this was Linux Action Show, I'd say go over to check out System76 because they're
going to give you a Mac-like experience as far as hardware compatibility and setup. Something
to consider. I will mention one of Linux Unplug sponsors right here, right now, and that's
my mobile service provider and, by the way, Matt's mobile service provider. That's right.
That is Ting.com. You guys, go check out Ting. Mobile that makes sense. Go to Linux.Ting.com.
Linux.Ting.com. That'll get you started. That landing page will also tag your shopping session
to take $25 off your first device or if you're going to bring your own device, $25 service
credit, which for me paid for my first month. Now what's unique about Ting? I'll tell you.
You only pay for what you use. It's a flat $6 per month plus taxes and then just your
usage. It's really straight. Like you can wrap your brain around that and which is great
because like, hey, guess what? I needed hotspot and tethering over the last few weeks when
I was working out of the studio for a few hours. I just checked the box on my phone
and now all the devices that we had with us were immediately on the internet and I'm getting
14 megabits download at the studio using my Nexus 5. Oh yeah, they support the Nexus 5.
You can go buy the Nexus 5 directly from the Google Play Store, a device that you own outright
that you pay a fair market price, you bring it over to Ting, you activate it, $6 a month,
no contract, no early termination fee. You only pay for what you use. Plus Ting has an
awesome, awesome dashboard. I love this dashboard because I was just setting up Reiki in the
new studio with the HTC One. Oh, it hurt. I gave away the HTC One, Matt. It pained me
so deeply. That was the hardest phone I've ever had to give away. I've given away a lot
of phones and the HTC One, cut deep. That's a great phone. It's available on the Ting
network and what's so nice about it is that Ting dashboard now lets me manage these accounts
so transparently and smoothly. I can let them see where they're at with their usage. I can
set up alerts so if all of a sudden Reiki is using like 10 gigabytes of data on that
phone, I can have Ting send me a push notification to my Android app. I can log into their dashboard
which supports web standards from a mobile device or from your desktop, whatever it is.
I can set up caller IDs options. I can turn off voicemail. I can turn on voicemail. I
can set up where a call forwards. I can activate, deactivate lines, transfer lines, set up account
managers. It's all, it's so awesome and it's so smooth and here's the best part. If you've
been considering switching to Ting and you're stuck in a contract, Ting has an early termination
relief program. You can find out more going to ting.com slash ETF and that early termination
relief program will pay you up to $75 per line you have to have canceled. And the other
thing I like about Ting is I like to be an informed consumer. I like to make sure that
I am voting with my wallet, that the money I am spending is going towards a company that
is promoting something that I believe in. Ting is trying to clean up the wireless industry.
They're trying to shake things up and I think they're doing it successfully. You're seeing
some of the bigger players try to copy what they're doing but it's not genuine. Ting is
genuine and they put it all out there. You can go over to ting.com slash about and you
can get videos from just the top, the CEO, the EVP, the VP, the director right there,
VP of marketing, the CFO. They also have behind the scenes tours with just the service reps,
the people who are on the ground because they have a fantastic customer service program.
When you call them anytime between 8 a.m. and 8 p.m. a real person answers the phone.
I don't know of any other cell provider that does that. If you're in a business, if you've
got family or friends or even if you just need to solve a problem yourself, it is so
nice to know that when I handed Rekai that HTC One and if we had a problem at any point,
I knew that I would just call up Ting and we'd have it resolved within a few minutes.
It wasn't going to be a big waste of my time. Lately, a lot of people that I've had to deal
with over the phone have been wasting my time. It is so great to know that people that I'm
spending money on every single month for my mobile phone are not wasting my time. Ting
really is changing it up and you can help them do it by becoming a Ting subscriber.
Go over to linux.ting.com. That'll take $25 off your first month or $25 off your first
device if you don't have one and it also lets them know you heard about it here on this
show and you appreciate them supporting Linux Unplugged. So go over to linux.ting.com and
a really big thank you to the really great folks over at Ting for their awesome support
of Linux Unplugged. Linux.ting.com. Alright, we've got a couple more emails to get through.
Last week, we asked for folks to send in their AutoCAD replacements because this is something
we hear about all the time. I can't switch to Linux because AutoCAD and it seems to be
a lot of people in this field are interested in Linux but AutoCAD. So Scribbleton writes
in. He says, hello awesome duo. He actually wrote that. So that made it right there. He
tells us about DraftSight. It's a professional grade and free as a beard 2D CAD program made
by the same company that produces SolidWorks. Okay, now SolidWorks I've heard a lot about.
They introduced it as a way for engineers to convert AutoCAD DWG files to DXF files
although I think they're also trying to steal some of AutoCAD's market share. It behaves so
much like AutoCAD it even uses the same command lines that a coworker and I completely switched
over in just a matter of days. It runs on Windows, Mac, and Linux and it can be found
at draftsite.com. He said, I also have a comment after watching Linux Unplugged 31, the Ubuntu
punching bag episode that we just recommended Simon listen to. He says, I'm not a programmer,
a dev, or an IT guy. I'm just an average user that loves to use Linux. Yet I have not
missed an episode of last since I found it in 2011. As a small business owner, I watched
last to keep up with Linux developments and learn about new programs. As you were discussing,
I don't care about the internal battles of Wayland versus mirror system D. I just want
my stuff to run as simply and reliably as possible so I can get my work done. So Ubuntu
has worked just fine for me. Someday I may want to try Antegoros, but only after I find
some spare time. Keep up the good work. I'm really looking forward to the new how to show
so an average guy like me can effectively implement all this great stuff. Scribbleton.
Great comment and I think he echoes a lot of the silent majority there. That's why I
wanted to read it. I think he's definitely onto something. So Esquero Tamero writes in
Matt. I don't know how you say it. He's got a whole list for us, Matt. He says, I used
to do drafting for my family's business, civil engineering related, and I tried some of the
solutions a while back while trying to find a cheaper alternative to AutoCAD. I haven't
used all of these solutions, but they're all present for Linux and they're related to CAD.
He says, here's one you could try. FreeCAD. This is an application used to 3D models.
LibreCAD. This is basically a fork of the community edition of QCAD. BLRCAD. Haven't
used this one, but he says it's another option. QCAD. This is a program with a free and paid
version. And then he says there's commercial software like DraftSite, which we just had
recommended to us. VeryCAD, a 2D, 3D CAD program. Eris Commander Edition. This is a compatible
2D, 3D CAD program with a ribbon interface. And BricsCAD. This is probably the most complete
solution for Linux, along with Eris CE, but it's as expensive as AutoCAD. And it seems
to stumble on 64-bit systems, he says.
Hmm. Now that could be a problem. I mean, you would think, okay, I can just go ahead
and switch over to this, but I think so many people are using 64-bit systems. That would
be kind of a buzzkill.
It also says DWGs are not exactly supported in FOSS software. As far as I know, support
is limited, and there are GPL compliance issues incorporated into other programs.
This is a good list, and I wanted to say thank you for sending this in. It feels a little
bit like the list I get when I ask people for their favorite Linux video editor, and
then I get a list of a lot of really good options with links and names, but then I actually
go sit down and I'm like, oh, well, when you actually use these programs professionally,
you discover a lot of limitations. And I kind of feel like this might be a little bit of
that.
I think so.
It's hard to say, so we will link. We'll have a full list in our show notes. You can
go check out. It sounds like the one people are really going on about, though, is DraftSight
from, I guess, the same folks that make SolidWorks. And DraftSight is, technically, it's free,
as in cost, but it is commercial software. It's not open source. And they have it available
for Windows, Mac, and Linux. They have an RPM for Fedora available.
Okay. Well, I think anytime you have something available for Linux, even if it's not perfect,
at least it's there.
They have a dev as well. They have a dev.
Okay.
So you got a couple options there. So that's DraftSight. And hopefully, that helps some
folks out there that have been looking for AutoCAD solutions, because it's been a surprisingly
popular one. Art of Illusion. What's this? Art of Illusion is a free open source remodeling
and rendering studio.
Oh, okay.
Oh, wow.
Many of its capabilities rival those found in commercial programs. So here's another
one. Art of Illusion. I'll add that to the show notes, too. Thanks, Nexuiz. That's a
good one.
Yeah.
So, all right. I'm adding that, right? There we go. So thanks for sending those in, guys.
That was a good list. We had a few folks round up. We also got four or five emails on it
as well. And so I just linked to a couple of them, but we got a lot of good feedback
on it. So I really appreciate all of you guys sending that in to us.
Matt, before we get our guests on, I want to thank our second sponsor this week, and
that is DigitalOcean. What is DigitalOcean? Oh, man. You guys have got to check this out.
If you're thinking about learning how to do something on the server, if you have something
you need to deploy in production, you've got to check out DigitalOcean. It's simple cloud
hosting dedicated to offering the most intuitive way and easy way to spin up a cloud server.
Users can create a cloud server in 55 seconds, or less if you're our audience, and pricing
plans are only $5 per month for 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, and a terabyte
of transfer. I've got an arch box I've had running up there. Yes, I said arch, running
up there for months now, and it's just constantly doing more and more stuff. And as I am moving
between the current studio and the new studio, and I start thinking about, well, wait a minute,
I need to have shared resources between these two locations. I got to tell you, this $5
DigitalOcean machine, it's just starting to get more and more valuable, because I just
keep thinking of things I can do with it. And by the way, DigitalOcean has data center
locations in New York, San Francisco, Amsterdam, and now they've even got them in Singapore.
They have a very simple interface, an intuitive control panel, which power users can replicate
on a larger scale with the company's straightforward API. They got KVM on the back end, it's all
running on top of Linux, sitting on these SSDs, in pair with their tier one bandwidth.
And the reason I can say all of this is because I've been a DigitalOcean customer for a long
time now, and I have not had a single outage. I have never, ever been disappointed with
the performance, and I am constantly impressed with the feature sets and the things they're
adding. And DigitalOcean is a company. They are growing like crazy. They're hiring right
now. You can check out their hiring page. They have it linked at the top of the DigitalOcean
website. They just recently got a good round of funding too, so they've got a ton of runway
underneath them. This is a company that is going places, and I'm really excited because
not only is that all great, but it's just a really great service to use. The technology
is great, the interface is great, their droplet system is super smooth and straightforward,
and they have an API that if I ever wanted to get fancy, and I ever wanted to do something
like start automating stuff, I know that API is there to make it easy for me. So go over
to DigitalOcean.com and get a $10 credit by using the promo code Linux Unplugged March.
Linux Unplugged March will get you a $10 credit. You can try out that $5 rig for two months.
Try out that $5 rig. Even if you're just using it to explore what you can do on your own
server, why not use this instead of something like VirtualBox? Go up there, deploy this.
You can take snapshots before you break anything. Yes, it actually, in a sense, can have training
wheels. That droplet system can really help you get out of a jam, and it also helps you
deploy a new system immediately. My co-host from Koda Radio, Michael Dominic, uses DigitalOcean
for the backend infrastructure for a lot of the apps he develops for his clients. It's
a super easy system to deploy. He can do it with reliability. He can quantify the cost
for them. They can totally wrap their brains around it, and $5 a month doesn't break the
bank. They have a really straightforward pricing system where it goes from $5, $10, $20, $40,
$80, depending on what you need. Each tier brings a whole bunch more stuff, more processor,
more storage, more bandwidth, all of that stuff. If you just want to do some testing,
maybe you've got a web app you want to try out, maybe you've got an app that needs some
backend infrastructure for a little bit, but you don't need it for an entire month, they
even have hourly pricing. DigitalOcean has hourly pricing. Think about that $10 credit
at that point. That $10 credit is going to get you a ways. Go use the promo code LINUXUNPLUGGEDMARCH
when you check out over at digitalocean.com. Try out that $5 machine. See what we've been
saying, and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
That's awesome. What you were saying about the whole virtual machine thing, that really
resonates with me because I don't always have a machine handy that can really support that
as well as I could at virtual, going to a whole other setup.
There's that. There's the resources of it. If you're on a laptop, it makes your laptop
run hot. There's all these reasons, and you don't have the performance drag, plus you're
actually up on the web where you can try some things you might not be comfortable bringing
into your house, and you have that droplet system, so if you mess something up, boop,
Bob's your uncle, you revert right back, just like you would on VirtualBox.
All right. Well, I'm really excited to welcome the co-founders of SolidXK onto the show.
I'm going to try to get this right. We have Shilja and 00. I don't know how well I did
but guys, welcome to the show.
Thank you very much, and happy to be here.
Hello.
Hello, 00. We were pretty impressed by the distro when we checked it out on Sunday, so
I just had a couple of questions after we kicked the tires that I wanted to throw your
guys' way. What I'm going to do is I'll just go in the order, so I'll start with Shilja,
and then we'll ask 00, or you guys can just bounce it around, but let's throw this first
one to Shilja. Could you guys give us a little background? Is SolidXK based on Linux Mint
Debian Edition? Is it just inspired by Linux Mint Debian Edition? We noticed that it uses
the Mint tools, such as the Mint Software Manager and the Mint Updater, but is it actually
like, did you clone the Linux Mint distro repos and build on top of it, or did you start
with a Debian base and just pull in those tools?
We just started from scratch from Debian.
Okay.
At that time, I wanted an L&D version.
Right, right. Go ahead.
And Kleiner Lefebvre didn't have any plans for that.
So you decided to break off on your own and create one sort of based around the same ideas
of Linux Mint Debian, but with the desktops that you had a passion about?
Yes, yes. And at first, we planned to make it an official version of Linux Mint. The
Mint team didn't want to support that. My choice was just an edition, or go on my own.
ZeroZero was also very in favor of going on our own, so we did.
Very good. And ZeroZero, I wanted to, let me ask you this question. So could you explain
to me the difference between the business and home versions of SolidXK? I know that
the business, for example, says it has a focus on stability and security, but the home version
says it's stable and secure. So what really is the difference between those two?
The business edition, it's based on the Debian stable, and the home edition, it's based on
Debian testing. That is the main difference. So then we build the business edition based
on stable with our tools and with our interface, with our ideas, and we give the home edition
with the latest software and more up-to-date software. So they are two different concepts
that we give to the users.
So I gather that you guys both have an interest in KDE and XFCE, but we got a couple of questions
that came in primarily around the Cinnamon desktop. How does the support look for Cinnamon
desktop on SolidXK? Does it use it? So do you guys have like a repo that you're going
to set that up in? Are you going to just pull it from Debian, or is that something you're
not really even worrying about if the users want to figure it out, they can?
We're not planning on supporting Cinnamon on SolidXK. That's because the name SolidXK
does not include C for Cinnamon, so we're going to have a problem with our site.
So I take that as the same answer then for say something like MATE, even if say MATE
really takes off on Debian stable at some point.
MATE is to be included very soon in the Debian testing, so our users will update MATE when
they want.
Gotcha.
So Cinnamon was in Debian testing until a few months ago. Then the transition from GTK
3.10 broke Cinnamon, and Cinnamon was removed from Debian testing. At the moment, it's not
available upstream. There's a few how-tos in the forum, how to get Cinnamon from the
Linux Mint Debian repo, but that's it. We have to focus, that's our main focus, on the
two D's that we support and the distributions that we support.
So the tools you ship with SolidX or K, do they have any dependencies on let's say KDE?
So for example, if I decided I'm going to have a solid MATE desktop, would I end up
having to pull down a whole bunch of KDE libs or something like that to use some of the
tools like the software manager?
No, those packages don't have any KDE dependencies.
Now here's the other thing we got some questions about, and I decided during the review not
to really tweak the look too much, but some people thought it was pretty surprising to
see the oxygen theme under XFCE, and is that just personal preference? You guys like the
oxygen theme, or is it consistency? What's the story there?
When we started, we needed to decide on if we wanted to make it look like two totally
different distributions, coincidentally maintained by the same people. We would like to have
some consistency between the two, so we chose for the latter.
Okay, so it's a consistency thing.
Yes, and the oxygen theme was the only one working on both KDE and XFCE without a problem.
The choice was easy.
So now that you're at this stage and you're seeing your community grow, are you guys concerned
about long-term scale? Are you worried about how to hold it all together if more and more
people start using the distribution, and how do you plan to address that?
It's, of course, always a – we're now at a time that we are at a fast growth in our
user base.
Yeah.
Last year from, well, zero to, what would you say now, more than 1,200 users on the
– about, I think, 20 or 30,000 users for our systems. So it's growing very fast. We're
still looking for a suitable business model, like a solid scale more.
You are hoping to make a little bit of a profit at doing this. Do you hope to turn it into
a full-time job?
Yes. Realistically, seeing now that it's not possible, it's so much fun. I would like
to do that.
Yeah. It definitely seems to be something that has challenged many companies and people
to turn a profit out of a desktop distribution.
Yes. The business models in open source, especially for Linux distributions, are very difficult.
We're not searching there at the moment. I'm a business consultant by trade.
So do you hope that the business edition might lead to some sort of – like a revenue model
of some kind?
I don't think that the products are going to bring the revenue we need.
So you think it might be like a service-based thing? People will contact you for support?
Services support, maybe some products that we can provide as a service, like cloud solutions
or integration solutions on back-end systems.
So that's sort of a long-term thing then, because the distribution has to see quite
a bit of growth before you probably reach a phase where that would turn it off for profit,
right? So it's a long-term thing here.
Yes. When you – different phases. So you have to think about what do we do on the short
term, so we could think about sponsorship or something like that. But you also have
to think about what is our vision, and is it clear for the community what that vision
is? And how can we shape that?
Do you believe then that – do you believe that the need is strong enough for a rolling
distribution with this quarterly update pack cycle? Do you think that that is solving a
big enough market need that would obviously then be – the thing you could assume from
that is companies like Red Hat and Ubuntu are leaving this need unfulfilled, and so
there's a space for Solid to come up and say, well, look, we're going to offer you
the advantages of rolling with this safety net, and you think that's a big enough of
a market need that you might be able to carve out some business support for that?
Yes, especially for non-profit organizations and governmental institutions.
So when you're pitching somebody – I'll give 00 a chance to jump in. 00, when you're
pitching somebody –
Business, it's with Joel J.
It's his department. It's his department.
I wanted to shift gears and actually change to the rolling release. I would like to get
both of your opinions on why – what do you – what do you convince somebody of a rolling
release? When they say, why do I want rolling, what do you tell them?
Well, first of all, the non-reinstall, again, the non – as you said Sunday, Nuke and Pave,
I think it's the biggest selling point in that pitch.
So you don't have to reload. You finally get it all set up, and you're not forced
to reload.
Yeah, yeah. If we can offer, as we are trying to address with the update packs, if we can
offer an increased safety, I think it's an extra bonus because with the home edition,
we are sitting on top of testing. Testing might not be always stable. So that's why
we opt for this quarterly update packs.
Right. I think it makes sense. It's kind of – it's more – it's rolling with
sort of some safety built in.
With a safety net, exactly. So basically this. And we offered as well, because we are with
testing, we offered as well, an updated user land and the system and base system. Not necessarily
interesting for everybody, but can be interesting for some of our target audience.
Right. Very good. All right. Well, guys, is there anything that we touched on in the review
that you wanted to amend or add during Sunday's Linux action show?
No. I think it was a great review. You both were fantastic.
Oh, thank you.
Oh, jeez.
We enjoyed it.
Yeah. Yeah, it was fun to take a look at it.
We saw that you enjoyed it. It was good.
Very good. Well, Mumble Room, as we wrap up, if you guys have any questions, go ahead and
–
Yeah, shoot. Yeah, shoot. Yeah, exactly. A 00 says shoot, if you have any questions.
I just wanted to say one thing. I've been watching that project ever since it was just
kind of getting bowled around in the – on the Linux forum, Linux Mint forums, and I
got to say it's been interesting to watch it evolve from an idea about a KDE release
to full-blown distro taking on the XFCE from LMDE, which – so that was pretty good. But
I just want to say kudos to both of you for doing such a good job and adding to the community
in that way.
Yeah, it's going to be a really interesting distro to watch, and I wish you guys the best
of luck. If you guys want to hang around, we're going to kick around a few topics,
unless anybody else has anything else they want to throw in there. I want to do –
I have one more question.
Oh, go ahead, Rod.
One more.
Okay. Yeah, we can do it.
The update packs, they're not for – they're just for the home edition. They're not for
the –
Yes, only for the home editions.
Okay.
I had one question. How about to secure boot UEFI in the installer?
We are testing it right now. Shoji finished the installer UEFI capable last week, two
weeks ago, and we are testing it right now. So our next – the next is those during the
month of April, second half of April should be UEFI capable.
Very good. Wow.
If all the testings go as so far they are, go according to planning.
Right.
I have one more question.
Yeah, sure.
If it's a long-term – like for someone long-term usage, let's say I have someone
who I want to – I'm considering moving to Solid because the whole reinstall thing,
not having to do that, it's very nice. But the issue I have is if they have this one
computer that they would have – they're so far they've been using the same version
distro for two years, maybe three years, and it's kind of got to a point where the updates
on this distro is kind of not working anymore. They're just kind of stalled.
So the Solid solution, if I put them on it and then three years later, would the update
packs with the Home Edition still make it – obviously it's not LTS, but would that
continuously make it – even for that many years?
As long as Debian keeps the testing branch open, we'll keep supplying updates packs.
Sounds good.
I like that. Hopefully, unless something really bad happens, that's going to continue on.
We can't predict the future, but we can hope that Debian keeps the testing branch
open for another two, three years. I think it's safe to say that.
Oh, I was going to ask you guys, what do you think about the whole Debian system D thing?
How does that affect Solid?
We'll follow upstream when they move. So we've been testing, we've been trying system
D. It's not exactly still completely usable in testing, because system D is still a bit
old. You use it, not using. System D is still a bit old, so it's not completely usable.
But when Debian moves to system D, we'll move to system D as well.
Okay, I got another question. Let's say you have a system that you want to have stable
and you want to have the updates kind of thing. So you want a Home Edition and you want the
updates, but you have it where they don't necessarily have an internet most of the time.
Do you have the updates? Are they possible to do like an offline package update?
Not the Solid SK solution, but there are tools in APT for that.
Okay.
Yeah. Okay. Yeah, right. Yeah. Right. You could. Well, guys, great work. Keep it up.
And I hope you can build out a team so that way you don't burn out. That's my big worry.
And I always worry about that with Clem, too.
Thank you.
And it sounds like, you know, you guys said the one thing that sort of resonated with
me that I hope will help you prevent that is focus. You said you know you're focusing.
Yeah. That was one of our first decisions. Focus, do less, but try to do it, well, at
least according to what we think would better.
Good on you. I know Q5SIS wants to take us out with the final question. Go ahead, Q5.
Yeah, I was just wondering what your guys' plan is for when Debian locks down their updates
because they're going in, you know, getting ready to merge into a new branch. Are you
guys still going to be providing updates or are you guys going to freeze just like Debian
does?
No. On the home edition, we follow upstream. So coming next November, Debian will freeze.
So we will, on most of the updates, we will freeze as well. There's a lot of software
that will keep updating, Firefox, Thunderbird, our specific software that it's independent
from Debian. But most of the, all the rest of the software that comes Debian will follow
upstream in there. Unless in the very specific that we find issues during the update packs
and that is, was defined on the, in the beginning, we can pull to solve issues or breakages.
We can pull from, for example, Seed to solve a particular situation. So we have some freedom
in that. We are not, we follow testing, we follow upstream, but we are not absolutely
tied to.
Right. Yeah, I noticed. Go ahead.
Just wanted to say that, is there a service?
No, I was just going to say thank you for clearing that up for me because that was something
I was kind of wondering about and there were a couple in the chat room who were curious
too.
Yeah. All right. Well, I think that, if you guys haven't checked out a review yet, you
should go watch the Linux action show, but I think they got some serious potential there
and maybe, oh, one other question for you guys. Do you guys, are you guys looking for
folks to get involved with the, or are you guys keeping the team lean right now? What's
the plan there?
We can still use a lot of testers and I would like to find somebody who would like to think
about possible business models for SolidXK.
Okay. So where should they go to get a hold of you?
I can do that by going to our site, solidxk.com, as a form, or you can directly mail me at
school year at solidxk.com. There's a lot of possibilities.
Okay. Very good. And we'll have links to their G Plus and Twitter handles and the website
and all that good stuff in the show notes if you guys want to check that out. Before
we run, we don't have time to get into it today because I have to run to a meeting,
but I wanted to pitch a question to the audience. Maybe we can incorporate it into next week's
feedback. This week, Mark Shuttleworth took to his blog and he said the title of it was
ACIP, ACPI, Firmware and Your Security. And he made the case and the one that I resonated
with was he said, if you read the catalog of spy tools and digital weaponry provided
by Edward Snowden, you'll see that the firmware on your device is the NSA's best friend. Your
biggest mistake might be to assume the NSA is the only institution abusing this position
of trust though. In fact, it is reasonable to assume that all firmware is a cesspool
of insecurity, courtesy of the incompetence of the worst degree from manufacturers, incompetence
of the highest degree from a wide range of such agencies. And he goes on to argue that
we need to have a new way of doing firmware. And I'd like to get your guys' take on this.
I've also shared my thoughts in the Linux action show subreddit. I feel like the ship
has already sailed, especially in mobile, but perhaps the opportunity could be opening
up again in ARM in the server room and on future desktops as sort of these big incumbents
sort of have less entrenched interest and move into mobile, maybe they'll lessen their
grip on the desktop. But I'd like to get your guys' feedback. So go over to JupiterBroadcasting.com,
click on the contact link and choose Linux Unplugged from the dropdown. And what do you
think about Mark Shuttleworth's rant against ACPI? I mean, I think nobody here has any
love for ACPI, right, Matt?
You know, I think that he may actually be onto something. I mean, because it's one of
those things no one really ever stops to think about. So I think the fact that he's addressing
it, whether or not it's founded or not, I don't know. I've spent a lot of time. I think
it's important to ask ourselves that question.
Do you think his point's right that we're sort of at a point again where we can re-ask
some of these questions?
I think if we're not there yet, we're approaching it like a freight train. I think we are essentially
there. I think we really are.
Yeah.
All right. Well, very good. So send us your thoughts in on that and we'll incorporate
it in the next week's show as well as send us in your thoughts about anything we covered
on this week's episode of Linux Unplugged. We'd love to get your feedback and don't forget
that subreddit, LinuxActionShow.reddit.com. Matt, I hope you're washing and brushing off
the monkey suit because someday should be a heck of a show.
Got it all vacuum sealed and ready to go.
Okay. Well, I'll make sure to set aside the bananas so that way we have plenty of entertainment
and I'm looking forward to it. So join us on Sunday for Linux Action Show for the monkey
suit spectacular and the retrospective look at Mir. And don't forget you can join Linux
Unplugged live on Tuesdays over at jblive.tv. Just check jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar
for your local time. And we'd love to have you here in our chat room. All right, everyone.
Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged. See you right back here
next Tuesday.