Hey, you know what we ought to do in the pre-show?
Is document right here for eternity
the fact that Wimpy broke our Mumble server this week.
So we're using Jitsi.
You're welcome.
Do I even want to know what you were doing?
Do I even want to know?
I just pasted the bomb emoji into the comment
and hit save and it blew up the Mumble server.
It was beautiful.
Ah.
Hello friends and welcome back
to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And my name is Brent.
Hello gentlemen, anchor down
because it's a windy day in the Pacific Northwest
and I don't want either one of you to blow away
because we've got a lot going on in this episode.
But first, I must say it's brought to you by a Cloud Guru,
the leader in learning for the cloud,
Linux and other modern tech skills.
Hundreds of courses and thousands of hands-on labs.
Get certified, get hired, get learning at acloudguru.com.
So coming up on the show today,
it's our episode where we defend the command line.
In this particular week that we are recording,
the command line is coming under attack
and we're going to hunker down and defend it.
In fact, I may even attempt to argue
that the command line could be new user-friendly.
And I think everyone who is discouraging learning
or using the command line
is actually burying their head in the sand
and they're doing a disservice to Linux adoption long-term.
I think we should be teaching people the command line,
not avoiding it.
That's key to future Linux user success.
So we'll talk about that
and why I feel that way so strongly.
And then we'll round out the show with some great emails,
some pics and more.
So before we go any further,
I'm going to bring in our virtual lug.
Hello, Jitsi Room.
Hello, hello, hello.
It's got its pros and cons compared to Mumble.
You know, I think Jitsi is a pretty cool tool.
And I like seeing some of you, that's very nice,
but it doesn't quite have the same smoothness
handling audio from everyone like Mumble does.
Yeah, WebRTC just can't compete.
Yeah, Mumble is really kind of good at that.
And plus we can have structured rooms
with permissions and stuff.
And you know, it's not so with Jitsi, at least not yet.
Yeah, and so far Wimpy hasn't figured out
how to break Jitsi, at least I don't think.
Oh no, I have, I'm just not going to do it.
I don't want to torpedo the show twice in one evening.
I appreciate that.
So before we jump into the community news
and whatnot today, Wes,
I think it's time for maybe the very last time
we do an ARCH update.
Ah, dang it, I thought you'd forgotten.
I think this is it, because a lot of things are in motion.
We have parts in route.
We have more things happening this weekend.
And I thought maybe for one last time
we should officially check in.
Cause you never know, this could be the one that breaks.
This could be it.
I mean, it could be.
Yeah, and I'm going to miss these when they're gone.
I know, it's been fun.
So tell me, tell me what we're looking at.
Cause it's been a minute.
Woo wee, 127 packages, 652 megs download,
only 63 megs net upgrade,
but there's some good packages to upgrade in here.
ButterFS, Cockpit, Containerd,
we weren't using that, Docker, Docker Compose.
Yes, we're getting a new Linux LTS kernel,
update to Snapper, SystemD,
and of course a new ZFS DKMS module.
Oh boy.
And that's not even to mention the fact
that there's a new SSH server,
new Samba, this is a huge update.
So I guess, I guess hit the go button,
let's start the downloads
and we'll come back and see, see what happens.
Wish me luck everyone.
All right, and then while you do that,
I have the pleasure to announce something very special
coming soon.
It's the 2021 Tuxes.
All right, so the nominations are open.
You can go vote for the best free software projects,
Linux distros, text editors,
the big impactor of the year,
server distros and a lot more.
What really stood out in 2021?
Head over right now to tuxes.party.
We've only got a little bit of time,
tuxes.party or I'll have a link in the show notes of course.
It's not too many questions.
I tried to refine it,
thanks to some help from the virtual lug
before we started the show.
We kind of whittled the list down a little bit
and I think it's gonna be pretty quick to answer.
Not everything's on there.
Cause if you think about it,
we could rabbit hole this thing
like a million different ways.
So we tried to just kind of keep it concise
and do something that we could build year on year data.
So maybe after a few years of doing the Tuxes,
we'll have some trends and interesting things
that come out of it.
So go to tuxes.party and go vote.
We are trying it out with next cloud forums too.
So West stood up a new next cloud server for this
and cause we honestly didn't wanna make
our precious next cloud servers,
which we have two of available to all of you.
Well, now we have three.
Now we have three.
So go over there and vote and let us know what you think.
And then towards the end of the year,
just pretty much like maybe one of our last few episodes
of the year,
we'll announce the winners
and the winners of last year
received not only our accolades,
but some of them that I could track down
also received a little Tuxy trophy.
I think this year we'll do something else
pretty special for them too.
So go try it out.
And I guess this is our big test
to see how next cloud does for forums.
It's gonna output all the data as a CSV file, right?
So gonna have to massage that a little bit.
Yeah, I mean, I totally tested it with one entry in there
in that network.
So it should scale to the size of the audience, right?
I wanna mention our friends at a Cloud Guru
have a Linux web services course
that might be right up your alley.
Learn about the various software tools
and utilities to configure web services on Linux.
And yeah, that means the differences
between NGINX and Apache,
setting up squid and reverse proxy,
figuring out how to do HTTPS and SSL and load balancing,
getting metrics out of Apache,
all of that stuff is in a Cloud Guru's course.
So I have a link in the show notes
or go over to a cloudguru.com
and search for Linux web services.
Again, that's a cloudguru.com
and the course is Linux web services.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
But one of the big stories over the weekend
is that System76 is reportedly developing
their own rust written desktop, not based on GNOME.
It all really stems from a couple of comments
from a System76 engineer on Reddit.
I mean, this whole story just blew up
from just a few comments about some challenges
with what they're experiencing
with I think maintaining cosmic.
And I didn't really know how legit this story was,
because when you read through some of the articles,
you can see some frustration with the engineer.
Like one of the things that he wrote in the Reddit comments
is what are you expecting us to do?
We have a desktop environment
that has a collection of GNOME Shell extensions,
which break every GNOME Shell release.
Either we move towards maintaining tens of thousands
of lines of monkey patches, or we do it the right way.
We make the next step of fully fledged desktop environment
equal to GNOME Shell.
And that just took off like wildfire.
And so I emailed Carl, the CEO of System76,
and I said, you know, is there smoke to this?
Is there fire to the smoke, I guess is the saying?
You know, how legit is this?
What are you guys, where are you at?
Where's your heads at?
What's going on here?
And of course I asked, why not Plasma?
Oh, good man, yeah.
I mean, right?
I mean, isn't everybody thinking how amazing would it be
if a well resourced vendor came along
and got their hands on Plasma
and really gave a go at doing a deployment of Plasma?
And we all wanna see what would happen.
But that is not this day, my friends.
Carl writes, we are designing and writing codes
towards a cosmic desktop environment.
Both are experimental and intended only to test
the tech stack that we will eventually land on.
I think it's likely this will result
in a new desktop environment,
but we have other questions to answer
before that's official.
The investment we're making in POP is large regardless.
We're putting similar resources into the 2023 version of POP
that we put into the factory.
The desktop environment is only one part of the story.
There's more to come.
And then in regards to when I asked about Plasma,
he says, Qt is C++, and it doesn't have rust bindings.
We considered Kaywin and had the same problem.
Our team's expertise is in rust.
Most of all, we're spending more time adapting upstream
than adding value for our customers.
Building and maintaining the desktop environment
will be considerable, but at least it will work
towards our vision for the future
of a desktop operating system.
So what I've took away from this email from Carl,
and I'm curious if this is what you take away, Wes,
is this is a direction they're heading,
but it's in the R&D phase right now.
Yeah, I mean, we haven't seen a whole bunch of fanfare
as you pointed out.
I'm definitely maybe a bit skeptical on one hand,
just because I think that's the default
whenever you hear about a new desktop environment
coming out, I think.
But I have enjoyed watching what they've been trying
with Cosmic, and yeah, I mean, it seems like
the way they've done it so far,
there were just gonna be some limitations,
and if they're really hitting up against those,
you gotta do something else.
I kinda wanna go around the horn on this one.
I'm looking right now, because I have video with Jitsi,
and I'm seeing Neil's eyebrows go up,
and of course, I've got questions for Wimpy,
so I'll start with you, Neil,
and then we'll go around the horn from there.
What was your initial reaction?
Because I think it's pretty easy
to have a knee-jerk reaction of,
well, we have too many desktop environments,
why do we need another one?
But it seems to me that System76
could be in a unique position
where they do have a very tight feedback loop
with their customer base.
They sell a physical product that is gonna come loaded
with whatever they end up creating,
and if things don't work, they're gonna hear about it
from those customers who are working through support,
and in a way, they have kind of a tighter feedback loop
than just about any free desktop environment has right now.
Does that give them a special position
to create something here?
Absolutely, it certainly does.
Fundamentally, free software is all about creating projects
that solve your own problems,
and their problems weren't getting solved
with the way Cosmic was being done now,
with the extensions layered on top of GNOME Shell,
and I totally get where they're going with this.
From the perspective of what Carl Richel was saying
about them creating their own desktop
gives them better control to focus on their vision,
I can totally see that viewpoint.
It makes a ton of sense.
However, it is already difficult
to get people to do stuff on desktop Linux as a whole,
and the more splintering in actually advancement
of desktop technologies to support various users,
the more difficult it is for the Linux platform
as a whole to succeed.
Like, already today, for example,
accessibility and internationalization
are really, really not in great shape
in all the desktops except for GNOME.
That's because 20 years ago, Sun Microsystems
put a buttload of effort
into making that happen with GNOME 2.0,
and GNOME has reaped the benefits of that
in the 20 years after.
And with KDE Plasma, for example,
because you asked that of Carl,
I think the real reason that KDE Plasma
doesn't really go further
is because there isn't somebody
doing that tight feedback loop
and has the correct incentives
to stick at it and drive it forward.
But I also think that the reason why they're doing this
is because their experience with GNOME
was painful enough to turn them away
from doing this again.
And so I understand what they're feeling
from that perspective.
With that in mind, where I kind of almost feel
like there's some echoes of falling out
that we saw with Canonical
when they decided to launch Unity.
And so, Wimpy, is there a parallel there that you see?
And then the second question I have for you
on top of whatever else thoughts you might have
is when you look at System76's products
as an option in a marketplace,
isn't it a pretty big risk to hit the reset button
on a desktop environment right now
when there's some really serious competition out there?
So the first thing I'd say is there's a quote,
I forget who said it,
and it's people that care about software
should make their own hardware.
And it seems to me that System76
are kind of coming at this the other way
and coming to the same landing place,
which is they care about their hardware.
So now they're caring about the software
that they ship on their hardware.
And I think that that's a good place to be.
Like you say, they know their customers,
they know what their customers are looking for,
they know what they want to give to their customers.
And if they're not finding that with the available options,
then as Neil says, yes, the whole point is
that they've got this massive tool set
of amazing software that they can use
to put something together.
Now, there's gonna be some significant effort
to actually create something of their own, but why not?
Well, we shouldn't resist people's desire
to be creative and make something new.
This conversation is the first time I've heard about this.
I didn't see any of the discussion on Reddit,
but yes, on the face of it, it does sound similar,
that when Canonical had a vision
for what they wanted to deliver to their users
on the desktop and that deviated from Gnome's vision,
then Canonical ended up going their own way.
And that's fine too.
You don't always have to use something existing.
It's a big undertaking though.
Just maintaining a desktop environment
is a significant effort.
Actually creating something new
and then building it, that's a ton of work.
Any significant software project
you should look at as a 10-year endeavor.
So if they're gonna go this way,
it will be an interesting journey
and one that I will enjoy following.
I don't think they will be alone in doing something
like this.
We've already seen Josh Strobel put out
sort of not a manifesto as such,
but he wrote up that he was stuck
between a rock and a hard place.
And I know from my time at my past employer
that things are in the works.
Right.
That's all very insightful, Wimpy.
And I'm struck by this also sort of opens up
the Gnome project to just push forward on their vision
and collaborate with people who are on board
and people who are not on board
can focus on their own vision.
It actually seems like long-term,
it's gonna be better for a lot of projects.
But Brent, there was something Carl said in that email
that jumped out at me.
And I wonder how you interpret.
He said, we're going to invest in this.
I think he said in 2023, like we invested in the factory.
And you've been there, you've seen what that factory,
what that means is staffing, it means equipment.
I mean, it means a lot of things,
but where do you think that could go?
Like, what's your interpretation?
Well, I think what we all saw
when we got our really, really fascinating tour
of their factory recently is that
when they jump into something, they jump full steam ahead
and they try to get some of the best talent to work on that.
And so it's not a 50% effort from them that we see,
it's sort of a hundred percent plus plus, you know?
So what I would really love to see maybe in,
you know, he said 2023,
is if they take that same idea of innovation
that they applied to something like the launch keyboard.
You know, we had some pretty fascinating discussions
about what went into even the starting phases
of implementing those ideas into what is a keyboard
that we sort of assume was optimized already,
but they threw in some innovations
that weren't necessarily obvious,
but now seem really fascinating.
And they even told us they had to scale it back a little bit
to make it a bit more approachable.
So I'm really curious, similar to Wimpy,
to see if they jump full in as they tend to do,
where will that take the desktop?
And will they implement ideas
that are maybe a little bit different
than what we're seeing out there already?
Right, you could say obsessive,
and that would be an understatement.
So Wimpy, I know you have a wrap up thought, go ahead.
As we were saying, they are not alone
in having feelings of sort of disenfranchisement
over the current situation.
I wonder if System76, if they move beyond
what sounds like sort of prototyping and experimentation,
if they move beyond that into actually scoping something,
whether they'd be up for approaching individuals
and teams of people who probably feel the same as them
and trying to sort of bootstrap a project
that they can sort of lead.
Because I feel like there is a community in the making,
behind something else.
That's a really interesting question, yeah.
Can they form a new locus of community around this?
Because that was my other thought when we were talking about
there can be this tight fit with their customer base
and the people they support.
And that just made me wonder,
well, how well does that map onto the general wider community
and do we lose out on some of that?
But if there is something of a new consensus
forming around that, maybe it does have
something broader in its reach.
Well, I know we have more thoughts,
but I wanna move forward.
So save them for the post-show,
because we have one more news story to cover.
It's been nine years since the Steam beta rolled out.
Take that in everybody.
I still can clearly remember putting together the research
and trying to verify some of the rumors
that Larbel had printed on Foronix
about the beta potentially coming to Linux one day.
I still clearly remember the effort
of trying to reach out to contacts and sort all that out.
I mean, this couldn't be true, right?
How could it be true?
It just seems impossible,
because that must be like 10 years ago now.
That's, it's unbelievable.
And it, in a way, it feels like it's built more momentum
in the last three to four years
than it had for all nine of them.
And we were just on the precipice
of the Steam Deck being released.
And we also just got updated from BattlEye,
the anti-cheat folks,
that it looks like support is in good shape
with the new Proton experimental version.
And it doesn't, I don't know
if it's actually shipped to people yet,
but the takeaway from it is truly that BattlEye,
and what was the other one?
Oh, Easy Anti-Cheat?
Yeah, so both BattlEye and Easy Anti-Cheat
have done their updates.
And you know what, I'm pretty impressed.
And then last but not least,
we don't need to spend a lot of time on this,
but I just think it's totally worth a mention
because of the incredible effort that's been going into
a brand new calendar application.
I know it's not, you know, it's not like,
it's not super, super exciting,
but calendar spelled with a K is out.
And this is really looking great.
I mean, Linux needs a solid native calendar application.
There's some out there for sure,
but something that's really competitive.
And this honestly looks like one of them.
And I mean, you guys listen,
I wouldn't be putting it in the show
unless it actually looked really legit.
And I've been following the development
since the very beginning,
and I've been waiting to give them their plug.
And they just put out, I think it's actually 0.1.
I may have misnoted it, but either way,
they have a release now,
and I want you to go check it out
if you need a calendar on Linux.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 and 60 day credit on a new account.
And you go there to support the show.
Linode's how we host everything we've built
since going independent.
And I think it could be a secret weapon.
See, as part of these reads,
I'm telling you how we do stuff.
You get to peek behind the factory,
but you can have Linode as your secret weapon.
You can go out there and have 11 data centers,
have 40 gigabit connections coming into your servers,
have brand new MVME storage rolling out
to your block storage,
have object storage that's S3 compatible
that you can rely on.
I mean, that's actually how I kind of think about Linode now
is I think about it as my infrastructure.
It's how I'm gonna build everything going forward.
I've seen the light.
And the knock-on benefits once we've gone all in
have been just fantastic team-wise.
Everybody knows how to use the Linode dashboard.
We can build automations using their API.
And as we start talking about
approaching the JB infrastructure as if it were code
and using things like Ansible or Terraform
or probably not Kubernetes,
but I know some of you out there would wanna use that.
Well, of course, Linode works with all of that.
So it can also be really part
of a multi-cloud strategy as well.
You get 11 data centers to choose from.
And every single service level is backed
by the absolute best customer service in the business.
And I just underscore that because for me,
I'm running my business on Linode.
I mean, it matters too when it's your personal blog
or a gaming server or something like that.
But man, when it really matters,
it's so great to know they've got your back.
Every step of the way since 2003, Linode's asked themselves,
how do we really use Linux to accomplish this task?
They've really innovated in that area,
starting with the early days of virtualization in Linux
to networking and user interfaces
and so many other things that really have,
we just kinda, we take as obvious now
and Linode was at the very early steps of that stuff
because they're geeks, they're into this stuff.
I can really kinda connect with that.
That and the fact that they're independently owned
and independently funded.
That's huge for me.
So head over to linode.com slash unplugged.
Go get that $100 in 60 day credit
and try this stuff out for yourself.
See what we've been talking about.
See why so many listeners of the show
have been trying it out.
I mean, think about that for a moment.
You think Linode would still be here
if people weren't still trying it out and sticking around?
Thousands of Linux Unplugged customers
have signed up for Linode and are loving it.
Go see what you think and get $100 and support the show.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Unplugged.
Well, the video we've all been waiting for,
dreading maybe, it's finally here.
The latest on Linus's adventures with Linux.
Yeah, it's titled Linux Hates Me.
So you can probably guess how it went.
It's Linus and Luke over at Linus Tech Tips.
We've been really resisting the urge
to talk too much about this on the show
because, you know, it doesn't,
it's not gonna have much impact
beyond day to day life right now.
But today, as we recorded the day the video dropped.
And there's a theme that's in the video.
And there's actually a theme that Linus and Luke touched on
in their WAN show that I want to expand on here.
You might be asking if you're not familiar with these guys,
why are we talking about this?
Well, they are in the top 10 channels on YouTube.
So they have a very large audience
and they are the number one tech channel on YouTube.
And they are doing potentially up
to a five part Linux challenge
in front of their ginormous YouTube audience.
So it's a pretty big milestone for Linux
in terms of tech coverage and new potential audience.
So there's a theme in there that I thought though,
I'd like to pull out.
Because I think if you watch this first video,
it bit Linus and it caused him
to sort of rush through something
and end up actually wrecking his Pop OS install.
And we've all heard it before.
Once you go command line, you've gone bust.
I have a quick example from a recent WAN show.
So my bottom line on this,
my take and you can hate me for it,
is that the Linux community needs to stop relying
on the command line as a crutch
for creating user experiences that are actually usable.
They can't just say, well, the GUI doesn't need to do this
because it can just be done in the command line.
Because until that attitude changes,
I'm never gonna be able to get
my brother-in-law using Linux.
And I think it's pretty understandable
why people outside Linux would be sort of,
I don't know what's the right word, anti-command line.
They'd be sort of skeptical of using the command line.
There's a whole vocabulary on the command line
that you have to know.
You have to know how to even start to invoke things.
There's really no reference point where to start.
Just a scary blank black box, right?
What do I even type into this thing?
Yeah, exactly.
It's not obvious, is it?
Especially if you've never used a command line before.
Yeah, and you compare that to the sort of
default discoverability of a lot of GUIs, right?
Where you sort of just like, well, all right,
there's a file menu or there's a whole bunch of buttons.
Now you still may not know what they do exactly,
but you can at least see that they're there
as an option to use.
And I think also there's an appeal to the idea
that something can be automatically done by a wizard
or you check a box.
And there are benefits obvious to a GUI
when you're looking at the settings.
It's great to see the check boxes
and the dropdown menu with your different choices.
And it gives you an idea of what is capable.
So there's clear advantages to the GUI.
But I think what we should do is try to build a culture
that embraces learning the command line over time.
I think what we need to work out is this.
Once you go command line, you go broke.
Once you're gone command line, you've lost.
Like we have to get this mentality away
because there's a couple of realities
when dealing with Linux.
And that is that GUI interfaces change frequently.
And the command line syntax changes much, much,
much less often.
Some command line syntax doesn't change for like 20, 30 years.
And so when you go look up a guide online
or a how-to article, the command syntax,
even if this article was written in 2008,
is probably still the same.
But if that article is written in 2008, 2015,
even 2018, 2019, and it's telling you how to do something
in the GUI and Linux, there's a very good chance
it's out of date or you're using a different GUI
because there's a lot of GUIs.
Yeah, this thing doesn't even mention Flutter.
What am I supposed to do?
Right, and maybe I'm on Plasma,
but the guide was written for GNOME.
The other thing about the command line,
the command line syntax can be spoken.
I can say do ls tac lh.
It's a little bit harder to actually walk you through
how to sort your file manager by date
if somebody's completely new to it.
Additionally, the command line can be copied and pasted.
So if you're doing remote support for somebody,
you're in a Telegram session, a chat session, whatever,
you could send them the command
or they could look up a command.
And the reality is the command line's actually
one of the very best things about Linux.
I mean, the command line is what sold a lot of MacBooks
back in the day when they switched over to Mac OS 10.
Command line is a lot more approachable
when you're doing any kind of remote session.
Command line is a lot more clear.
It can be spoken, it can be read, it can be typed.
It's consistent, right?
There's no like trying to, you've all probably,
I imagine most listeners of this show
have had to try to walk somebody through doing something
in a GUI when you can't see their screen.
And then there's the realities of Linux.
To me, and I mean, this is an area I'd love some input on,
but it doesn't seem like we're ever gonna have
a GUI tool for everything.
It moves fast.
Linux and all its tools and abilities come quick.
And GUI tools, especially ones that are good, move slow.
So there will always be gaps.
There are always gonna be things that roll out
that only work on the command line.
We'll have a lot of good tools, but we can't have everything.
So I feel like we ought to try to change the perception
in some way about command lines.
They are user-friendly.
They are new user-friendly specifically.
We have to make them less scary.
Am I off the mark here?
Everybody give me your thoughts.
Start with you, Brent.
So tell me, what are your thoughts on this?
I have several and they don't necessarily all agree.
One of them is my experience a long time ago with Mac OS.
I think many of us would agree
that the Mac user interface is pretty friendly.
And a lot of people who aren't power users
using that pretty successfully.
But the best thing about the Mac for me
was the ability to go from using the visual tools
to growing as a computer user
and then being able to access the command line stuff
to play even more and accomplish things
that the visual interface had never intended me to be doing.
Now that's one of the reasons I got off Mac OS to Linux.
But I think it's a nice transition
into being more of an adventurous user.
If you're interested in the inner workings
of computers and stuff,
I think the explicit nature of how the command line works
is great for understanding the underpinnings
of how your computer works.
I think visually, there's a lot of obfuscation
of how all the stuff that's happening in the background
where the command line sort of exposes that
in a really nice way, at least for my brain,
worked really, really well as a teaching tool
and still does every day.
And I think a point I take away
is even the commercial operating systems,
you end up using the command line from time to time.
It's not like this is only a Linux problem.
If you wanna edit some P list on a Mac
or you wanna do something on Windows
that requires reloading the service,
the quickest way to do it is from the command line.
So Bight, I wanted to give you a chance to jump in.
I have a friend that as soon as you tell him
he needs to open a command line, he goes hyperventilating.
He goes almost into shock by,
oh no, the command line, I don't know what to do.
Well, I think that's actually what happened
to Linus in this video.
He's trying to install something
and he kind of goes into a fugue state
and just rushes through the command line experience
because he just wants it over as fast as possible.
And we've been there, right?
I mean, I've definitely been there.
And it's also that with the command line,
you usually need to know what the syntax is,
what your options are, in what order.
And with a graphical user interface,
you get that all handed to you.
You get only your available options.
You have just the options in front of you
at that moment in time.
And the thing is that with the terminal user interfaces,
those have evolved quite a bit
because if you're looking at some setups for terminals,
those are usually quite graphical for being in a terminal.
But yeah, being open source,
it's also, again, there are many forms of that
and there isn't a baseline in there
except the command line itself.
Standard, yeah.
I wonder too, Wes, like, could that be an area
where some distros could kind of push forward a little bit?
Is take some of this stuff
that makes the command line a little slicker,
that auto figures out what you're trying to do a little bit.
Is that part of maybe the solution?
Yeah, I don't think any of this is to say
that we shouldn't have intuitive GUI systems.
And at the same time,
that we can't improve the command line user experience,
right?
Like, there's a lot that can be done better.
You know, like we were just using an NC do in the studio
the other day, Chris,
and that's a thing that happens in a terminal,
but it's a lot less scary than some of the other options.
But it doesn't need maybe the same complicated maintenance
that a whole graphical GUI does to do the same task.
So I think there might be some sweet spots in between
where we can have some better methods
to introduce people to the command line
because there's that part where, you know,
you're almost having a conversation back and forth
with a computer and in some ways it can be simpler.
I agree that we could have as good a desktop experience
on Linux as, you know,
people that are super familiar with Windows or Mac OS
have on those platforms.
But I don't think we should pursue that
and forsake, you know, the command line in the process
because the command line is the super user's
killer macro feature.
And it's also Linux's USP.
We have that, nobody else does.
And that's why Linux runs the world right now
because it isn't bound to a graphical user interface.
So I think we should keep it
and we should make the terminal experience better
and we should have more terminal utilities and tools
to supercharge our experience there.
But there's no reason why we can't have a slick UI
on top as well.
Yeah, I wanna encourage people
to look at the command line a little differently.
And I've been trying to think about legitimately
how we could do it on this show.
And I think talking about tools like NCDU
or just talking about that kind of stuff
a little more frequently might help a little bit.
And so Wimpy, if I could get your permission,
I'd like to continue on the command line love segment
from time to time here in the show
to sort of inspired by the Ubuntu podcast,
carried on with respect and love
and feature a command line tool from time to time
here in the show to try to, you know, not push people,
not be pushy, not do that kind of thing,
but just walk people through cool stuff
you can do on the command line
and say it's out there if you want it.
Yeah, that well is very deep.
You will never gonna run out of, you know,
love for the command line there.
No, so I mean, it's inspired,
I admit completely by the Ubuntu podcast.
The command line love segment was great.
And so from time to time,
I should have thought of one for today,
but that's just thinking about this.
I guess we'll make it NCDU.
But I just, something we could do
to put a focus on great command line tools
so you can give us some of your ideas
at linuxunplug.com slash contact.
And you know, maybe tools that we already have
that we could just use a little better.
Things we've forgotten about
that still need a little bit of love.
There's a ton of that stuff.
Speaking of things we've forgotten about,
we have a couple of new options up at jupytergarage.com.
Some random swag bags are back,
including old swag and some new swag from the road trip,
some new stickers, some old stickers,
bonus road trip swag items at jupytergarage.com.
The swag bag is back.
We also, for $5 more,
have a random swag bag with the Jupiter journal.
So it's the same great random swag bag,
but we also are including a limited edition JB notebook.
It's got the rocket pressed in on it.
It's really nice, it's a good size.
And we'll include that in the swag bag with journal
for $5 more.
Or you could just go grab the journal if you want.
You pay a little bit for it.
Well, not really, it's like seven or eight bucks.
It's pretty much what the cost is.
But you can pick your color if you just buy the journal
by itself, because there is a blue version
and a gray version.
It's nice, it's great for taking notes.
It lays flat, I love it a lot.
And then just for fun, because it's the winter,
I've also added a bearded tux bomber jacket.
It's pretty nice, it's low key.
It didn't want it to shout that you're a geek,
but I wanted a nice subtle low key
where you could still fly your geek flag
without making a big fuss about it.
And so the bearded tux bomber jacket
is also up at jupytergarage.com.
So two new random swag bags.
There's not a ton, but we have at least enough
to do 10 right now, I think.
And they'll go quick.
And then we will ship out what we've got.
We'll check both.
I got two different swag caches
that were sent to me since the road trip.
So we ended up with a bunch more
so we can do some more swag bags.
And the journal just, it turned out great.
It's something I set up a while ago
and I've been waiting for the right moment
and it just seems like now is it.
So if I were you, I'd spend the extra five bucks
and get the one with the journal
or go grab a journal directly.
There's not a ton of any of this stuff
because we're not a big warehouse.
So go to jupytergarage.com and go grab some of that stuff
because I like all of it a lot, including that jacket.
Might be all I'm wearing right now as a matter of fact.
And we'll do a little housekeeping.
Go check out Linux Action News 214.
We busted some thick Red Hat FUD this week
and we chatted about a new Ubuntu desktop tool in the works,
a brand new tool written in Flutter for the Ubuntu desktop.
Covered that a little bit.
And don't miss Self-Hosted 57.
Alex is building a Self-Hosted Notion Notes replacement.
He's just getting that started and it's awesome.
And he also shares the story
of how he accidentally deleted his server disk setup.
Oh, I got him to share that on the show.
So that's Self-Hosted.show.57 if you'd like that.
Thank you to our members at unpluggedcore.com.
I'm gonna go there after the show today
and plug in the member discount, same promo code as before.
So you can take a little money off our original swag items.
The bags, they're just sold at cost,
but the jacket and whatnot, the new original swag stuff.
Members get a little bit off that merch, unpluggedcore.com.
You also get two feeds to choose from,
a full live stream edition.
We run it through some compressor, but that's about it.
It's just everything uncut, every mistake, everything.
Or you can get a limited ad feed.
Nice tight production, just less ads.
And you support the show.
Unpluggedcore.com.
And we'd love your feedback at linuxunplug.com slash contact
and linuxunplug.com slash matrix for our matrix community.
And last but not least,
join the love plug this Sunday and every Sunday
at linuxunplug.com slash mumble for details on that.
It's at noon Pacific, jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar
for that.
We have some feedback this week, quite a bit of it.
Akseli got tired of the Windows 10 update
and gave Linux a try.
He writes, here's a very long, enthusiastic ramble
I wrote about Linux and I just really wanted to share.
To start, I'm not completely new to using Linux though.
Since I installed my first Linux on my Xbox,
the classic first one.
I've also tinkered with it every now and then
with my other devices,
but never really fully committed to it.
That changed this summer.
I was tired of Windows 10 updates,
but most importantly, I read all around the internet
that games are now working better and better on Linux.
Now I like gaming a lot and I also like making games
and I felt like it's now or never, I gotta try this.
I got myself a Kubuntu ISO and did the switch.
Although I left my Windows 10 installation
on my other drive.
Probably good thinking.
Yet here I am almost six months later
and I haven't touched my Windows installation at all.
I've rediscovered my enthusiasm for computers
due to being able to actually look inside of everything
to see how things work.
I can fix my issues myself.
As an example, myself and some others on GitHub
figured out how to fix the GSP 670 headset
to make it work properly on Linux.
And now that fix is in the kernel.
On Windows, I would have had to wait
for the manufacturer to fix the issues,
but on Linux, we just rolled up our sleeves
and began to figure things out.
All the games I play from Eevee Online to Quake Champions
work really well thanks to Steam Proton
and that it's big for me.
Sure, there are some issues sometimes,
but then the community for the game
will either butt heads together and figure things out
or work with the developers if they're chill enough
and soon we're back to gaming.
On the game dev side, I've felt way more productive too.
Unity works really well on Linux.
I started learning how to use NeoVim.
I really, really love it.
And my open source game project
is much, much easier to work on in Linux
since C development is much easier to set up.
Here's a link to his game called XMO Game.
He continues, I also created a tool
for Elder Scrolls Online players,
a native GTK app that downloads add-ons for the game
since the semi-official tools don't really work with wine.
It's not as feature rich,
but it makes the add-on updating way easier.
That's ESOLinux add-on manager, we'll link to that.
And he continues, just being able to contribute
to a community of computer enthusiasts like this,
just doing things and helping each other.
I hope I can contribute to the Linux community
in the future too, and my future games
will be made Linux first.
All in all, I'm super happy that I switched to Linux.
I haven't had this much fun using my computer
for a long time, and I think it's pretty much all thanks
to gaming being way more possible on Linux now
since it is a very big part of my life.
Oh, that's just great.
You know, I love that sentiment that you have this fun
and excitement and discovery as you're trying out Linux.
I mean, you can have the bad sides too, right?
And maybe this LTT video is some of the dark side to that
when you have to do that and you don't,
you haven't really opted into it.
But the upsides are, yeah, if you're interested
in this stuff, you know, in the Linux world,
it's all exposed for you to learn about if you want.
Yeah, just enjoy the process, right?
Don't rush it, don't make it a challenge
where you give yourself a timeline.
Don't do that stuff.
Well, and it sounds to me like it's building a community
behind these games of a very different sort
than just players, but also developers.
And that's kind of really fascinating to me.
So we got a lot of folks, like a handful,
a bushel of that wrote in and said,
we should try out Silverblue or KinoKnight.
So that is on our list of kind of to-do.
We kind of have a list right now of items
because we also have our server that we need to work on.
We have the router, firewall, VPN box
that we still need to build.
We got projects, baby.
Yeah, we do.
And it's just parts that are coming in slowly,
but surely they are arriving right now.
And so we may, you know, maybe after that,
we may revisit Silverblue or KinoKnight.
I could see that.
People thought, you know, give it a real go
is what they was the general sentiment is,
you know, don't just look at it,
but really give it a go and live with it for a bit,
which I would be down for that when the time was right.
I had a discussion with George Castro along those lines
on Thursday or Friday last, Thursday last week,
where we were sort of saying, you know,
this is where people need to be setting their minds
to what the future of, you know,
the Linux desktop looks like.
And we were looking at Fedora, Silverblue,
and then using containers for all the messy stuff
that we do, you know, software development,
playing games and all of that sort of thing.
So yeah, Silverblue plus Toolbox
is a fairly potent offering.
I'm very keen on NixOS for similar, you know,
for similar reasons.
Yeah.
I am happy to hear you say that, Wimpy,
because that has been my observation as well.
And, you know, we kind of watch this stuff
and I feel like there has been a lot more chatter
about Silverblue with the Fedora 35 release
than in previous releases.
Like it seems to me, awareness is really picking up.
And I think a lot more people are starting to see it
the way you see it, Wimpy, and seeing it as
this is probably the way things need to go
for a really robust workstation.
And so I get that,
which means we probably should give it a really solid go.
I also saw an Ubuntu effort along this line
that's also using OSTree.
I don't think it's using Ubuntu core has launched.
I don't know, I don't think it's official,
but I don't know if you saw that go by the internets.
We also, as a last bit of feedback for this week,
we got a letter from listener Chris.
He writes, Chris, I love Macedon,
but it's not clear to me it's right for you.
You've repeatedly said your goal is to reach your audience
and Twitter in the large or matrix up close and personal
may be your best bets for that.
I love that it's the wild West.
I was temporarily banned from Twitter for saying,
don't shoot yourself in the foot
as allegedly this promoted self-harm.
Macedon reminds me of the nineties internet,
wild, wooly, and full of all kinds of people
with an equally diverse range of beliefs and opinions
and a whole bunch of outstanding technical content,
but you have to be willing to invest the time
and seek it out and engage with it.
Is that for you?
I'm not sure.
Thanks for all you do.
He also says, PS, maybe consider giving the KD spin
a try in fedora 35.
Well, see our last episode for that.
And thanks for listening.
That's right.
I think that's a pretty good take listener, Chris.
I appreciate that.
And I am finding my feet.
I was really bad about matrix this last week.
I kind of messed up somehow in element.
I don't know where I went wrong,
but every room I joined,
my notifications are on by default.
And so I look at my phone sometimes and I'll see like,
I have 30 unread notifications
and I just, I can't bring myself to open it.
That doesn't make you want to check them.
Nope.
But I got that, I caught up.
I'm back current again.
And I do like the conversations I see happening
in that matrix room.
Yeah, me too.
It's some really good,
just organic community discussion about neat tech stuff
and a lot of stuff I might miss otherwise.
Yeah, it's interesting how it's sort of shaking out
right now.
And I don't really know how many days are left
for our IRC room,
because it seems like it pretty much goes to idle,
except for when we're live now,
but the matrix and telegram are popping along all day long.
So we'll see, we'll see.
I mean, I just don't know if I could, why shut it down
when you could, well, we can't bridge it
because of geek shit, I suppose.
Right.
Put a user in there who just hit links to the matrix a lot.
Hey, they're over here.
Hey.
Every five minutes.
Brentpot.
So we have a cut, well, it's like a pick pack.
It's a pick pack for you this week.
A whole pack of picks?
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
A really, really, really awesome,
but complicated backup tool for GNU slash Linux
is Borg Backup.
Yeah.
Talked about it on TechSnap forever ago.
Yeah, you're familiar with it, Wes?
I sure am.
Borg Backup is a really solid, comprehensive,
old schoolish backup solution.
And today, I'm gonna tell you about Vorta.
And Vorta is a desktop client that simplifies Borg Backup
into a pretty easy interface.
It gives you a lot of the same power,
but walks you through setting some of it up.
A great example of where a GUI can take something
and make it discoverable, as a matter of fact.
It helps you manage your encrypted backups,
it does de-duplication, it'll compress the backups.
Of course, it's all open source, works even on Mac OS,
if you wanna backup your Macintosh-based system.
And it's available on Flathub.
If you want a quick install, there's packages available
for your distro of choice, V-O-R-T-A.
Do you recognize the name, Wes?
Oh, I sure do.
Look at them keeping the Star Trek references going.
I mean, I was already pretty fond of this tool,
but now, I'm definitely giving it a go.
Yeah, yeah, I encourage to go over to, if you can,
go over to Flathub and search for Vorta
and just look at the screenshots of it.
It's really straightforward.
It's a little more old school in terms of backup,
but that might be what you're looking for
for this kind of tool.
Well, yeah, and Borg's already something
that I felt comfortable using,
but maybe unless I was totally managing the process,
it might not show up on some of my supported systems
of family or friends or something,
but this adds a new layer on top
that might push that into the next category.
Totally, totally, so go check it out.
We'll have a link in the show notes, all of that.
Everything we talked about today
is linked at linuxonplug.com, slash, four, three, one.
You can get all that good stuff right there.
You'll find links to our profiles over there as well.
We just sort of put it all there.
It makes it easy, you know?
And then, really, all you have to remember
is when we do it live,
because you can always go get everything
we talked about from the website,
but when do they do it live?
When do they do it?
6 a.m.
No, no, well, yeah, where?
It must be 6 a.m. somewhere, right?
Here, we'll do a little, what is it called?
Like neurolinguisty, neurolasagna.
I'm not sure what it's called.
Neurolinguistics, something like that.
I think it's called neurolasagna, that sounds right,
where we will program your brain
by associating it with something else.
So when I say join us live Tuesdays, noon Pacific,
and then you hear.
See you next week.
Same bad time, same bad station.
Now, I'll do that over and over again
for the next three years.
Every time you hear that, you'll think,
ah, Linux Unplugged, Tuesday, noon Pacific,
3 p.m. Eastern, jblive.tv.
I admit, it's gonna take a little while,
but I'm committed to it.
I'll eventually have everyone saying it.
My plan, my ultimate plan, it's been revealed.
I think it's gonna be a huge success.
Thank you so much for joining us
on this week's episode of the Unplugged program.
We'd love your feedback, your comments,
your ideas, your picks, your command line tips
for some command line love
at linuxunplugged.com slash contact.
Go there, send them in,
and we'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
The Unplugged program is a production of Linux Unplugged.
So I meant to fit this in the show,
but I forgot I do have a slight minor Starlink update.
Number one with a bullet that is bugging me about Starlink
is I have to say it's really unfortunate
that the ethernet cable does not detach from Dishy.
It is permanently plugged into Dishy.
It's baked in?
Yeah, so like when I'm packing up,
I have to like bring in a wet dish
with a wet 100 foot ethernet cord.
And when I wanna run it out my window and all,
it's just, it's not ideal.
It'd be really nice to be able to, you know,
plug it in like an ethernet cable.
The other thing is, is you need to shut it down in the app.
Otherwise you have to kind of forcibly collapse
the leg down and it feels like you're breaking it.
But yeah, that's neither here nor there.
You just gotta remember to shut it down
before you pack it up.
Not many people will be moving it around.
And then the last little thing that I have
just sort of as a followup is you really do have
to update your service address when you move.
I tried to move within the 30 mile radius
and see if it kept working.
And I was just getting poor, poor, poor results.
Went in and updated my service address,
which I was a little nervous to do
because I was worried it would say sorry, no availability.
But it updated just fine.
And then within about 15, 20 minutes,
my service has been great,
even with some blockage from tree leaves.
So it's been really good.
And other than those little minor things,
I'm still really enjoying the StarLinks.
The StarLinks to the internet has been fantastic.
All right, did I stall long enough?
Do we have an arch update?
Oh, we're ready to reboot.
All right, let's do it.
Rebooting.
And it looks like J-Bot's having problems connecting to GeekShed.
All right, we'll see how long that takes.
I'm getting in position to start the pinging.
Ping's in progress.
Oh, man, I should have mentioned in Coda Radio this week,
I did a takedown of Craig Federighi
and this horrible talk that he gave at a web summit
about how dangerous and scary sideloading is.
And the Mac press has not talked about it.
I mean, they announced that it happened.
But nobody's really talked about the contents of his speech.
And it's so cringey.
And it's clearly Apple's new position on sideloading
or firm position.
So I recommend you do actually listen.
So that'll be in Coda Radio tomorrow.
Oh, oh, oh, are we back?
Did we actually ever stop?
That part I'm not sure about.
Is it still shutting down?
Is it just taking a long time to shut down?
Because I don't think it actually stopped pinging.
I tell you what, Wes, this is stressful.
It is stressful.
I was thinking maybe I could jump on the jitzy
and I could go out in the garage.
You should do that anyway.
All right, I mean, this took a little while when
I rebooted before for ZFS.
Hey, whoa, it's Chris.
Chris got a rocking beard, too.
Yeah, his beard's looking great right now.
I don't have any lights out here at the moment.
Is it booted, Wes?
No pings yet.
OK, I'm going in the garage to get a little light.
And I'll go to the console.
We'll see.
This actually works way better than how it normally does,
because you can see Chris's trepidation here.
All right, I'm bringing it up.
I've got my remote hands if I need them.
Uh-oh, that doesn't seem good.
What's it showing on screen?
So what it says is that the monitors for new snapshots
has failed.
It's a snapper dependency service.
But I think it is booting.
Yeah, so let's start it up.
Most likely what's happened is that it
failed to create a snapshot.
Yeah.
All right, good.
Go, Biggie.
Just in time for this server to fall apart.
Right, just time for the snapshot to quit working.
Oh, I'm getting pings.
So is it accepting connections yet?
Yes, it is.
It is, I'm in.
I'm just about to do a Docker PS here
and see what we got going for us.
I'm about to do a mount.
Oh, yeah, I see a lot of ZFS stuff mounted.
Yes.
Sweet, Wes.
You know what I think that is, then?
Good job, Wes.
All our containers up and going.
Hello, little friends.