Man, I tell you what, that Windows 10, that Windows 10, I am impressed at how Windows
it still is.
It really is just Windows still.
I tried it recently on that $10,000 Dell laptop and not impressed.
First of all, I am shocked at how badly Windows 10 shits the bed when you have previously
had Linux installed on it, so say you have existing Ubuntu partitions, like just extended
4, nothing even fancy.
And maybe they are GUID instead of MBR, I do not know.
So Windows 10 will see all of the partitions.
You go to click a partition, say you just want to use like the same sizes, the sizes
all work for you, you go to delete the partition, okay, so far so good, you create a new partition,
it automatically says you want it this size, which is the maximum size available, you hit
apply.
Okay, good to go.
It says it is formatting.
Then when you go to click next, you get an error message that says BitLocker is enabled
on this disk, go to control panel and then it tells you where to go in the control panel,
which obviously you cannot do because you are in setup, the only thing you can do is
do control F10 and bring up the emergency console, you cannot go to the BitLocker control
panel and turn off BitLocker for that drive with the instructions, so it is unbelievable
that this company in their latest version has an error message in their installer that
comes up, which is completely wrong, the drive has totally been reformatted with NTFS, it
does not have BitLocker turned on, so but then the error message comes up and it tells
you all these steps to go to the control panel, which do not exist and what you really have
to do is you have to bring up the emergency console, you have to use their disk utility
emergency thing, you have to go into the volume and you have to select the partition and then
you have to reformat it again from the command line and you cannot reboot in between, if
you see what I did is the first time I did that I made the mistake and then I rebooted
just to make sure everything was good and clean and went back in the installer, same
exact problem, threw me for a loop, I am like oh shit that did not fix it, I thought for
sure that would have fixed it, no, no, no, no, no, what you got to do is you got to delete
it again in the installer, then you got to go to the emergency console, then you got
to run the disk utility, go in there, you got to reformat it again, close the emergency
console and then go back in the installer and finish the installation.
Well that is probably what happens when less than 1% of your users use your drive encryption
technology.
And even I do not think they totally test for installing on a system after Ubuntu, but
what I was surprised by was how little.
No Chris, I hear that Microsoft loves Linux.
I was surprised, first of all when you search for that error message you get very little
information, I was surprised by that, thank you Mr. Beard for stepping in.
I hear Mr. West is here.
Yeah I hear that too, I hear that rumor.
He's a jerk, he's kicking me off the air.
Yeah you know him.
I would never.
Hello Wes.
Hello.
I missed you, it's good to see you.
So that was my Windows 10, I mean it's like just that whole thing, it's just such garbage,
crazy garbage, crazy, crazy garbage.
What are you doing with Windows?
Oh well I got, I stole this laptop from Dell and I wanted to try out Premiere on it, just
to compare it against Lightworks 14 and that sounds reasonable, and was just blown away
by the amazing problems that you still have with Microsoft and this is a fully like anniversary
update or creator's update or whatever they call it, whatever stupid name they have for
it.
It's all fully like the latest ISO, yeah latest, all that and it still does all this
stupid shenanigans.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 193 for April 18th, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged and yes the band is back together this week, we've got a great
show and my name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello Wes, very excited about some of the things, we have like a new segment, a new
segment, that's one of the things, yes and we also have a very interesting introspective
look at Ubuntu 17.04 if I don't say so myself, but there's something in there that nobody's
really covered yet, it's kind of a shame, so we're going to talk about that, Wes and
I have been kicking the tires, we have some interesting hardware news to discuss in a
little bit and we're going to go through a bunch of our favorite open source project
updates, maybe add a couple of new ones to the map as well, yeah we'll tell you about
those coming up, coming up in a little bit, it's good to be back Wes, Wes, it is great
that you're back, you did, you did a fantastic job, now I feel like I should just be, I can
go all the time, well there you go, I feel like I can leave all the time, I think it's
in the network's interest for you to adventure, how did it go for you, how did it go, it was
good, it was a lot of fun, yeah.
I heard there was a bit of a mixer situation where something was going on, you had to unmute
all the channels, yeah something crazy happened, so you know what I'm going to do, I was thinking
about this, because I know that, that software mixer, that's like the worst thing about it,
it is right, absolutely, for me I use it every day, so like it's no problem, I'm learning,
I'm getting better, I'm getting better, but yeah, no don't worry, don't worry, I have,
I have good news, oh, I think probably before the next time I'm gone, we'll have a big old
huge Linux powered console right here, good old, that would be awesome, yeah physical
switches and dials and all that, so you can look at it and you'll know what's going on,
I can press buttons, yeah, I think it's going to be, I think it's going to be real good,
so yeah, that'll be nice right, yeah, it'll be a good upgrade, so look forward to that,
alright well, before we go any further, what we really got to do is take care of a little
business, we got to bring in our virtual, time appropriate greetings mummer room, greetings
brothers, hello, hello, hello, have you missed them Chris, I did, I did, you know, I wish
I could have joined in the mummer room, because that's always fun, yeah, but it turns out,
you never know what kind of reception you're going to get, that's right, you never know,
speaking of reception, the reception to the announcement that Canonical is discontinuing
their efforts on Unity and switching to GNOME, go figure that happens when I'm gone, right,
what the, damn it Mark, like right after you left, damn it Mark, you know, I thought, I
thought we were buddies, I thought you and I were buddies, kind of ironic, I don't know
if Noah got to share this tidbit, he must have, but I got the news on my phone, I got
a push notification to my phone, as I'm sitting with the Project Sputnik team, who of course
are basing these products around the Unity desktop, and so I had to break the news to
that team, wow, that's kind of a bummer, yeah, and it was like, well it was just a very interesting
position to be in, like, because I got to watch them go, oh shit, well I guess we're
going to be, see the wheels turning, we're going to be responding to that, yeah, so that
was interesting, and so that's going to sort of flavour our discussion a little bit later,
coming up on 1704, yeah, but I want to talk about something kind of from like a project
standpoint that is inevitable, and of course this is going to happen, there's a lot of
different takes on this, a lot of different forks of like the mobile aspect, the guy behind
Ubiport is keeping that going, there's also folks that are going to try to create their
own version of the Unity desktop, and the one that grabbed my attention this week, and
you guys may have heard about it, is the, I'm going to say enjade, yeah, I think so,
desktop, yeah, and so right now it's early days, but they call it a modern unified desktop
environment, what it really is, is Plasma that's been sort of mixed up to look a lot
more like Unity with a few other things, the way they describe it is a community project
to recreate and continue the Unity desktop environment, from the versatile dash down
to the global menu, enjade promises to provide a familiar experience that Ubuntu users love,
while adding new features to keep it up with the latest trends, I don't know what that
means, but I think that sounds good, it does sound good, the entire desktop created from
Plasma, compatibility with Wayland, distribution through Snappy and Flatpacks, hey, and it's
going to have a search function, okay, you know what, I'm good on the search stuff, I'm
good on that, let's put our efforts into other things, because we just, it always, like the
indexer always manages to go crazy, it always, anyways, right, people are sort of downplaying
this one, but something about this one to me, feels like they've got some real momentum
behind it, first of all I think the idea is kind of solid, some of us were looking forward
to a QT Unity 8, kind of seemed like a good idea, and I've been a big fan of the Plasma
desktop recently, running on half my machines right now, and it's very possible to make
the Plasma desktop a lot like Unity, there's just a few things missing, yeah, totally,
and the Plasma desktop is very extensible, configurable, so it seems like a natural platform
to try to build that on, yeah, yeah, we'll watch and see where it goes, there's a few
other projects out there, including ones that are just like themes that can be applied and
styles that can be applied to the Plasma desktop, so clearly there's a lot of interest, or at
least right now, yeah, and we're going to talk a little bit more about it later on in
the show, but I just wanted to talk about that, and then on the other end, so if you're
a GTK desktop fan and you're not going anywhere, but you did like a few things from Unity,
a lot of people have said to me, you know, the thing I really liked about Unity was the
HUD, in fact Wimpy, you remember when Wimpy used to come on this show, oh yeah, that Wimpy
back before there was some things going on at Canonical, I suspect, I haven't heard from
them in a while, but back when Wimpy used to come on this show, one of his favorite
things about Unity was the HUD, they've even worked on it for the Mate desktop, so that's
something that I think a lot of people that are coming from Unity and going to the GNOME
desktop might miss, it's kind of a neat feature if you get used to it, and it's sort of unique
to Unity, well there is a GNOME extension that sort of recreates the whole Unity HUD
experience for GTK applications, so if you're familiar with like Sublime Text or Addams
Command Palette that you can fire up, it's a lot like that, you get essentially anything
that the menus can do, you can do from the keyboard, it brings that to every application
that uses GTK 3, it automatically extracts all available commands, and it does that by
also observing what is the running application, it will adapt the UI to match the appropriate
application which sounds really cool, also to relevant actions, and it requires no modifications
to the applications because it's using just the features of GTK.
It looks pretty slick, I might give this a try.
Yeah, it actually looks really cool, and really if you think about it, if HUD is one of the
things you like the most about Unity, but you're trying to get to where the puck is
going to be hit by a Canadian or something, something about Canadians and pucks, if you're
going that direction, this might be something to try.
Absolutely.
Pretty cool.
And we will have that linked in the show notes, because it's up on Github, but it's, how do
you say it, what are you going to say it was, Plotinus, yeah, so it's P-L-O-T-I-N-U-S, Plotinus
perhaps.
Yeah.
It's really nice, and it's an example of ways that you can tweak Gnome.
Ryan and Noah had a conversation about System76 making modifications.
If I were System76, I'd probably be looking at extensions like this.
Yeah, definitely.
And then the market will decide if they like something like that.
Yeah.
Like, wow.
Now's the time we can dissect what we like about Unity, spread that across the other
desktop environments.
In some ways, I wonder if in a few weeks, in a few months, people will be speaking more
positively of Unity.
Because now that they know that there's a light at the end of the tunnel, that this
great travesty that was committed against the Linux community will finally be coming
to an end.
Right, the part they hate, which is just the, you know, not invented here, or fork, or whatever,
that part's done.
Yeah.
So now we can talk about all the great things that Unity did right.
I don't know about that, but maybe it's coming a little bit.
So I'd also, if you're switching over to Gnome for the first time, and you've discovered
a new extension, tweet me at ChrisLAS and let me know what you're trying.
I'd like to know.
I want to talk a little hardware here for a second.
So I was just talking about the Sputnik team.
This is a blog post by Barton George, and he is announcing something that we got our
hands on while we were at it.
It's their new Precision desktop.
It's an all-in-one.
Now, I'm talking about this for a couple of reasons, because I think this is a super badass
machine.
And this is one of the reasons why I was recently really considering trying to switch to Lightworks.
It's a 27-inch all-in-one, but it's like, this Precision one has a Xeon processor.
You can get it with ECC RAM, you can get it with, I think you can even get it with Ryzen
graphics.
Oh, wow.
27-inch screen.
It's the Dell Precision 5720, but I got to play with it.
I don't know if it's Ryzen or not.
They say the latest AMD Radeon Pro graphics.
Does anybody in the moment know what the hell that means?
Does anybody know what the hell that means?
I don't know if that means Ryzen or not, because it's the latest Pro graphics.
But it's the Precision 5270.
It's a pretty monstrous machine.
The thing that I should be talking about is probably the graphics and that stuff.
I got to impress upon you, the coolest thing about this machine was the soundbar that they've
built into it.
Really?
It's essentially a soundbar.
Okay.
It shouldn't be the speakers, but you guys got to understand how cool these speakers
are.
We had a little demo, and it doesn't convey very well, because we're just listening with
a microphone.
But I'll give you a hint of what it was like as I cut out a part of the demo that we didn't
air because it doesn't really translate very well, but it gives you an idea.
There's this integrated soundbar here, basically.
We actually partnered with a multiple Grammy Award-winning record producer, Jack Joseph
Pewig, to design and tune this audio solution.
It is best-in-class audio solution in a PC, hands down.
It's got these... You can see the six front-firing speakers.
There's two down-firing speakers and two passive radiators, so it's 10 total speakers.
It is the only system that includes both the front-firing and the down-firing speakers.
We're going to do an audio demo.
This is a mix playlist here, so we'll get to experience and hopefully you can hear the
audio come through.
It makes me feel like... It makes me feel like...
Now, remind you, this is right on Noah's directional microphone here.
You kind of get a sense of how loud it is, but what I did is I cut out the audio demo
here because a very funny thing happened.
You got to picture the scene.
We're in a large conference room.
The room, you can kind of tell by the audio, it's a very large room.
You could easily fit 25, 30 people in this room.
Thick walls, thick doors, double-paned glass.
This is like an industrial conference room where people can have hearty conversations.
We kind of disturbed the entire office.
Wow.
I'll cut a little bit here.
Somebody walks in and they're like, you got to turn it down, turn it down.
Then we're like, well, no.
They're doing a demo.
They're filming right now.
No, you've got to turn it down.
You've got to turn it down.
It's so good that we got the teams over here enjoying it.
Now what's funny is I cut in a little bit of the Dell promo for this where they show
the speakers.
That was pretty slick.
Check this out.
In the promotion, they make reference to disturbing the neighbors.
So watch this right here.
Not this part, but that is kind of cool too.
So they show you the diet, how all these speakers are built, but I thought this was right here
so the neighbors can enjoy it too, which was very ironic when I went back and watched this
promotional video because they had to come in because the rooms next to us, it was too
loud for them.
And then what she says after we were done, she says, yeah, that was only like a half
volume.
Wow.
Okay.
So you're legit impressed with this thing.
I was really, I was like, okay, all right, this would be a great machine for editing
because you can get a really great processor in there and get a ton of RAM in there.
See, that's like one of those features where I would be initially skeptical of it.
There'll probably be some standard, I'm going to get other speakers anyway or use headphones,
but that's awesome.
Sounds like a good deal.
What I think is interesting is, so you have this, so what I now understand about Dell
is that I like the dimension and precision lines.
I didn't realize that, but these are like the workstation class stuff.
It's a lot better.
That's when you start getting like the Xeons and you get the high quality build materials
and all this kind of stuff.
So now it all clicks now that I've gone there and seen it.
And the reason why I think this is a big story is, so not only is this obviously a vendor
that has tons of enterprise relationships and school relationships and an incredibly
large brand recognition, but they have transitioned from a company that when they first... When
I bought... Oh, it's in the other room.
When I bought the XPS410 from Dell a decade ago, I bought that computer actually almost
11 years ago from Dell.
It was one of the first what they call client devices they ever tried to sell shipping Linux.
And the whole idea behind it was, how cheap can we sell a computer?
Because if we knock $100 off for Windows, we put a 5400 RPM drive in there, how cheap
can we sell a computer?
And part of making it cheap is putting Linux on it.
That was Dell's approach.
And to me, that was what I was always extremely skeptical.
I even said in my predictions episode for the last, at the beginning of January, I don't
know if Dell's serious about Linux, because that to me was like, you're screwing around
here.
You're not taking it seriously.
I want a nice computer.
So now what we have is we have them shipping the Precision 5720.
We have them shipping that crazy $10,000 laptop that we covered, that monster machine.
I think it's called the Precision 7720.
They have these really nice systems now that they're shipping with Linux that they're not
shipping because they're cheap, they're shipping them because they're high end workstations
with Xeon processors and ECC RAM, and I think it's going to be big for them.
He said just on their developer laptop program, they're seeing a year over year 100% growth.
So in two years, they've seen a 200% growth.
Those are big numbers.
Could be huge.
It would be pretty nice to imagine getting a new job, you get a new laptop, you can get
this supported right from Dell.
Well maybe kick Lenovo in the butt a bit.
Get them off their game, or get them on their game.
Get them off their butt.
Get them off the pod.
Realize there's a market here, or could be.
It'd be really good to get some competition in that area, and then everybody wins.
The more people in the market, the more competition, I think it's better for everybody.
We'll see.
We'll see where it goes.
You know what else there's competition for?
Highly skilled folks.
Go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and become one of them.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged, support the show and sign up for a free seven day trial.
This is a platform to learn more about Linux.
Now you could be somebody who's worked with Linux for a decade, and you know there's still
little things you can go learn.
That's what I love about the Nuggets.
Even if you're a busy person already with kids or a job, I know how it feels, and sometimes
it's hard to continue your education.
That's why I love their course scheduler and their Nuggets.
These are features I probably talk about the most in these spots because they relate to
me the most.
It's where I continue even after a couple of years now to get value from linuxacademy.com
slash unplugged.
You go there to support the show and you sign up for a free seven day trial.
One of the things that I really realized that Linux Academy was clicking with the community
is when they developed their flashcard feature.
It's simple, but it's perfect for somebody like me who just needs little bits to study
from, but they can get stale after a while.
The Linux Academy flashcard system not only can randomize a set of cards for you to study
from, but they can be forked and improved by the community.
The community is full of Jupyter broadcasting members, so it's like top grade stuff.
They have Nuggets for just little bits of wisdom when you have just a little bit of
time, and they have study tools and lesson audio and personal notebooks that you can
take with you offline, iOS and Android apps to help you study on the go.
They spin up cloud servers on demand that you can SSH into.
They have Learning Paths, which are a series of courses and contents planned for very specific
types of certs or exams.
It's great.
And to top it all off, like the sprinkles on top of a delicious cupcake, they have instructor
mentoring.
And what that means is they have real full time human beings that can help you with the
subject material.
That's huge.
Huge.
Very big.
Also, if you're at DockerCon this week, stop by and say hi to Justin.
He's there from Linux Academy.
He's down there taking notes for the team to see what's coming up.
And I think also, he's going to be at the AWS Summit as well.
I mean, he's got guys all over the place.
Check it out.
Then check out Linux Academy on Twitter as well, LinuxAcademy.com, where they're telling
you about all this kind of stuff.
You can stay apprised if they're at an event you're going to.
Check out their Twitter feed.
You'll probably see about it.
And you can go say hi.
Go check out the booth.
Maybe get a little penguin plush from time.
I hear they have those from time to time.
What?
My kids love them.
Go to LinuxAcademy.com slash unplug to support the show and find them on Twitter, LinuxAcademy.com,
and probably coming to Mastodon sometime soon.
Mastodon reference.
OK.
I wanted to start a new segment in the show.
And I wanted to take projects that have been in a darkness, a silence, perhaps a cone of
silence.
I want to take these out of the cone of silence.
Shine some light.
I don't want to shine some light.
Because I think these are fascinating.
And if anybody in the moment has any experience with any of these, feel free to interrupt
with your set experience.
The first one up, Wes, is Torrent Peak, a new contender for our favorite open source
projects here on the show, Torrent Peak.
Distributed search engines.
Oh, got me there.
Using BitTorrent.
Oh.
Oh, you're hooked already.
OK.
And SQLite.
Now, this is a real fresh product.
I mean, we're talking updated just as a matter a couple of days ago.
It's a distributed search engine using BitTorrent and SQLite.
And that's kind of a cool idea.
So site owners create a SQLite database and create a torrent file from this.
They then proceed to seed this torrent, just like they would seed any other file.
Site users then start downloading the site torrent.
But rather than downloading pieces of a torrent, they download pieces based on a search query
they've performed.
In other words, a given search query, such as Indiana Jones, Torrent Peak knows how to
download pieces of a torrent where data for Indiana Jones is likely to be stored at.
Results are given to users in a timely manner without having to wait for the entire database
to download.
And since search queries are just regular torrent piece downloads, a search query can
be satisfied by many different peers in a swarm, effectively allowing for distributed
search.
That sounds nice.
Yeah.
It does have a couple of other pros, too.
You can create...
Hosting your own is just as simple as seeding.
So if you can seed a torrent, you can do this.
That's pretty great.
You don't have to buy a domain name.
You don't have to put it up on a server somewhere.
Since you control your address, your public key, which is broadcasted via the DHT, it's
much harder for governments and institutions to block the content you're sharing.
And via SQL torrent, you drive your users...
I don't even know what this last...
It's hard to read.
Anyways, but here's a couple of downsides.
Read only sites for now.
Your site doesn't get a pretty name.
And there's really not any standards in place to do this.
But the idea is kind of interesting.
Yeah, it definitely is.
So I thought maybe we'd add it to the watch list and see where it goes.
This seems like one of those things where you might not use it.
I mean, it's not even used as a library, but it pushes things forward.
We're building the tools slowly that we need to solve these problems.
And Yacy is great, but it hasn't gone very far.
I keep playing around with it, and it just is sort of the same.
And I just wonder if something like this might come along and move things forward.
Yeah, definitely.
I'm always...
There's always a conversation when Noah is in town.
There will be when he comes in for Linux Fest Northwest.
You wait.
You watch for him.
I'm calling it right now.
It's the, you can do anything on the command line.
It usually goes, well, actually, you could do that on the command line.
And then the conversation between Noah the Beard and I for the next hour is, no way could
you do that on the command line.
And usually it's video editing, podcast editing, photo editing, something like that, where
maybe you technically could do it, but if you're just so much more efficient if you
have a...
Yeah.
Well, maybe Noah can check another one off as you can do it on the command line list,
because I think he's going to have another one for his list.
Audio editing of images.
Audio editing...
What?
Of images.
Yeah.
Check this out.
This guy, I believe it's a gentleman, has come up with an incredible way to edit images
as if it was audio data.
He calls it AudioShop.
AudioShop is a simple script that was cobbled together that gets you started with mangling
image data as if it were audio data.
The script wraps three individually excellent tools, FMPEG, ImageMagick, and SOX.
The way it works is by first converting an image to a raw format like YUV.
This is done to prevent audio editor from destroying the structure so you still have
the original PNG or JPEG or whatever.
If converting to a raw format, then after it does that, it imports the raw image data
into the audio editor.
And he can then apply audio editor techniques to the image to get the results you'd expect.
So for example, he can overdrive the signal to overdrive the image and you get a very
blown out red and green image.
Yeah, look at that.
He can apply a reverb or an echo and you get multiple...
So he has a picture here of the Eiffel Tower and you get four instances of the Eiffel Tower
because he applied a reverb or an echo to the image data.
You never open it up in a graphical application, all done with a script.
AudioShop.
It's got a great name too.
Yeah, definitely.
So that just came out.
I think I will play with this one because it seems kind of cool.
Yeah, yeah.
It's up on GitHub.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
So that's another project we'll be keeping an eye on.
It's actually not that complicated.
It's like 300 lines, it's all scripted, you can go check it out.
Because it's really sitting on top of FFmpeg, ImageMagick, and Socks.
And so they're all doing the heavy lifting and they're all tools we're familiar with.
Maybe Socks for those of you...
Because you're probably all familiar with ImageMagick and FFmpeg, but Socks stands
for sound exchange.
It's a cross-platform utility that can convert various formats of computer audio.
So you can use it...
I've had clients that even use it on Windows for like a call answering system once.
Oh really?
Yeah.
And then this is your language warning for a moment.
Hello everybody.
Get it out of here.
You've got three seconds left before we use a swear word.
The next open source project is called The Fuck, which is an app that corrects your previous
console command.
That's what they've called it, The Fuck.
And they have a little animation here that shows it.
Essentially, you type the wrong command here and it says, that command's not found.
Did you actually mean this command?
And if you did, you type fuck.
And then it corrects the command and then runs it for you.
It's pretty cool.
It's just nice if you, oh, I meant to type Python, but you typo'd Python.
You know, The Fuck takes care of it for you.
Yeah, definitely.
So that's a project that I've actually, I think I've seen before, but it looks, you
know, this repo, okay, I have seen this once before, but it was updated just as of eight
days ago.
Days?
Yeah.
So I wonder how broad the support is.
It's apparently pretty active in development still.
There was an original version where it just added sudo in front of everything.
So you screw up and forget to put sudo and you type it and then the next thing you just
type in is that and then just put sudo in front.
It like just converts it back into and puts some sudo in front of it before you do anything.
But this is kind of cool because if it's like detecting what you're, it's even better.
But if it does that and this, that's pretty cool.
Yeah.
So, okay.
So now if that's too obscene for you, if that's too intense, then on the other end we have
Tiny Care Terminal, Tiny Care Terminal with emoticons, with hard emoticons, a little dashboard
that tries to take care of you when you're using the terminal.
Is it that sweet?
It's wonderful.
It is so wonderful.
This is a little dashboard that tries to take care of you.
It tells you you're cute.
It tells you to take care of yourself and it tries not to stress you out.
It shows you the last tweets from at tiny care bot, at self care bot and magic is real
bot.
Oh my God.
Speaking of echo chambers, the first two tend to tweet reminders about taking breaks, drinking
water and taking a look outside.
The latter tells you strange whimsical stories.
If you don't like these bots, they're completely configurable.
Your good commits from today and the last seven days will also be shown and when you
get stressed out because you think you haven't done anything, it turns out it'll show you
all of the hard work you've done recently and also it'll tell you about the weather
because you might get rained on.
Oh my God.
And then so they have a screenshot here and they show you your commits today and for the
week.
They show you that maybe you should download a mindfulness app for your phone so you can
meditate.
There's a end curses type animated parrot that tells you to breathe.
It looks pretty good.
I mean from a design standpoint, it's a pretty handsome looking terminal app.
See this is good.
This like goes right back into just you could do anything on the terminal and this will
help you maybe feel more at home while you're there.
That is so true.
Oh my gosh.
This would be, you know, would be great.
This is actually just a, this would be fantastic to replace people's shell with this.
Right.
And just so like, you know, somebody leaves the machine unlocked.
This is the new thing.
You change their shell to this and then they open.
What the hell is this?
You know, they're told to breathe deep.
So they're upset, but they're not that upset because they meditate about it.
They're like, okay, well it's cool, man.
If they get upset, you just give them the Care Bear stare.
Oh, that always helps.
So there you go.
There's a couple of open source projects to help make things right in the world that we're
watching.
There's also one that's not really a project, just kind of a neat idea.
I think it's by a guy named Scott.
So Scott had a great idea and I don't know why Red Hat or somebody else like the Linux
Foundation hasn't thought of this, but it's linuxlifecycle.com and I guess what it does,
it tells you how long the support cycles are on major distributions in one place.
Simply easy.
I mean, it's not an official page put together by like Linus Torvalds.
I mean, it's not, it's a guy named Scott doing this, but hopefully he keeps it up.
And so he breaks it down with Red Hat and CentOS, Ubuntu and Debian, and he tells you
which releases are still supported and when the end of life is.
And it's focused on enterprise, but it looks like Scott plans to set up like an API as
data is JSON, so people can, this could eventually be a legitimate resource for this kind of
thing.
And it could be expanded to cover a lot more, especially if there's a JSON where you could
pull out other distros and display it on your own page.
I mean.
The API, you could have like monitors.
Your software is going to go out of state.
How does DistroWatch not have this?
They have individual things.
I like how.
They have a list.
There's Wikipedia has a list too, so maybe he's like just collecting all the information
and putting it in one place.
Yeah, it's nice.
And you see how he displays it in like these easy, so he's got rel7, rel6 and rel5, green
check mark, green check mark, RedX.
Nice and clear, really straightforward, easy to understand.
So if you, you know, if you don't often, this would be perfect for somebody like me.
Like if I had mostly worked when I was in IT, I'd either be rel, CentOS or Debian Ubuntu.
I wouldn't very often sit down at the SUSE machine after I left banking.
But if I did, I could easily just go to this page and say, okay, well, I'm on SUSE Enterprise
10.
Oh man, it was end of life on July 31st, 2013.
I've really got to get this client to update.
I mean, it's just those sort of simple things because when you go look it up from the vendor
themselves, you read all this weird vendor speak and you have to dig through these knowledge
bases.
That's nice to see.
That's linuxlifecycle.com if you want to check for yourself.
Pretty handy.
I'd be okay with some free BSD or other things on there as well.
I'm sorry, what?
Just saying.
I blacked out for a second.
A broader list, right?
Just maybe on a secondary page.
It makes so much sense for a BSD kernel to be on a website called Linux Life Cycle.
I mean, it's not like there's a lot of BSDs to keep track of either.
True.
See, it's a small ass.
We have some huge BSD news to talk about today on the show.
We've got to talk about FreeNAS Coral.
In fact, we're going to do that in just a second, but I wanted to ask you before we
do it, do you mostly now use Ubuntu at work for the server side?
Yes.
No CentOS Red Hat?
No, there is some CentOS.
Oh, okay.
But for what you touch?
Yeah.
I've been pretty much exclusively Ubuntu.
You know what you need to get your hands on?
A new Linux Action Show t-shirt.
What?
Yeah.
So Linux Action Show, there's three episodes left, and people have been like, Chris, you've
got to do a going away swag, teespring.com slash all good things.
It is my favorite version of the logo we've ever done, and I kind of wish we would have
done this all the time.
Yeah, that's nice.
We wanted to have something special as like a final edition, so we tweaked our Linux Action
Show logo to represent the runtime of the show, so it's like a commemorative edition
of the shirt, but we also gave Tux a dignified badass beard.
I don't know why all Tuxes should have a beard like this.
This is something the community should take and run with, but it starts here.
The revolution starts here.
You go to teespring.com slash all good things.
We've got a t-shirt, a hoodie, and a long sleeve.
I'm mentioning it in this show because with only three episodes left, it's not like this
is going to be something we're going to be promoting very much.
We're doing it right now.
Yeah.
Anyways, check it out, teespring.com slash all good things, and you've already got one
on the way.
Ooh.
Mm-hmm.
Rumor has it, Wes.
Rumor has it.
This is a big story that I think happened while I was still in Arizona, and I tried
to follow it as closely as possible.
I'm not putting RIP on the back.
Oh my gosh, iMacon.
Oh my gosh.
A purple hoodie.
You know they have, by the way, I think... Sorry, you blame iMacon.
He's just sidetracked me again.
Blame.
Blame him.
It's totally his fault.
So I think if you look at the shirt, they have some interesting sizes this year.
I think they have different sizes or something, so you might look at the... Yeah, okay, okay.
I'm looking at the long sleeve too.
Anyways, teespring.com slash all good things, and if you guys are Star Trek fans, you probably
get the reference to the... Do you get it?
Oh yeah.
You do?
I'm proud of you, Wes.
I'm proud of you.
So anyways, this was a huge story that I was trying to follow because we're a FreeNAS user
here at Jupiter Broadcasting.
We have friends that work on the FreeNAS project.
I love the folks over at IX Systems who are the sponsors of the FreeNAS project.
It's the BSD thing that even gets Linux users to turn their heads and use it, right?
Everybody loves FreeNAS.
Noah's all in on FreeNAS.
It's sort of the number one DIY NAS solution, and then when you combine it with some of
IX's hardware, it can be a serious business solution too.
So everybody had their eyes on FreeNAS 10, aka FreeNAS Coral, and Jordan Hubbard, which
is one of the guys that's been... He'd been at IX for a long time.
He's up in the high ranks, very, very involved with the FreeNAS 10 project.
He gave us a demo when I was at MeetBSD California.
Oh, really?
Yeah, he gave us... Man, Wes, he was showing... First of all, this was like this revolutionary
new UI for FreeNAS.
I mean, it had gone from the FreeNAS UI we might know to this totally new dark-themed
click and drag.
He did this maneuver where he added 35 hard drives at once to this FreeNAS server because
they had this huge, crazy setup back at IX.
Naturally.
He had VPNed into.
And so he VPNs into his... He's up on stage at MeetBSD, and this is out of Berkeley, one
of the Berkeley campuses, so everybody's in this auditorium, and we're all watching Jordan
up on stage as he gets up there and VPNs back into IX systems and connects to this monster
demo FreeNAS rig, Coral rig.
He's talking about all of the massive changes, and he's talking about the fact that they're
rolling out Docker support, and this totally new UI, and this engine, and they're rebasing
on this version of FreeBSD, and all of these fundamental changes.
My last show before I left for Texas, the last show with Linux Unplugged I did, I sort
of gave a heads up.
I was like, I'm hearing some bad things about... I mean, I'm hearing people are getting
a little concerned about FreeNAS 10, and I'm hearing some bad things, like plugins are
getting disabled, your data's safe, but you've got to reset up all your plugins in Docker.
People are not super thrilled.
Just FYI.
It was kind of like the general vibe of the coverage right before I left for Texas.
And then while I was gone, huge news, huge, huge news from the FreeNAS project, and it's
the kind of news that sort of sticks to a project for a while, and I think maybe it
explains why when last time I was on the show, we talked about Jordan leaving IX to go into
the bio... he couldn't do a bio field.
Well, I think now we know why he left, and so we're going to talk about all of that first.
I want to say thanks to Ting.
Go to linux.ting.com to support the show, and save $25 off your device.
Or if you have a CDMA or GSM device, whoa, yeah, because you know, everybody's got one
these days.
Heck yes.
Just check their BYOD page.
It's probably compatible.
Then you get $25 in service credit.
And you know what, Wes?
Average monthly Ting bill?
$23.
What?
Mm-hmm.
It's pretty cool, because they've got... so this is the genius of it.
So it turns out, guys, it's 2017, and the cellular infrastructure in the United States
is pretty much in place.
Everybody's heard of cell phones at this point.
We've all kind of got it figured out.
So Ting wanted to do something that was really different.
Now, I've been a Ting customer now for like two and a half, three years.
I don't know.
I mean, it's been a long time, and I love it, because they are an MVNO.
They are able to ride on top of other carrier networks that they create agreements with,
and they can create these agreements sort of as business needs drive it, so that they
have sort of an incredible flexibility here.
But the big thing is, is they're not out there digging holes in the ground and putting up
big towers.
I've actually had clients that were responsible for designing and zoning cell towers.
It's an entire industry on its own.
It is the kind of industry that only multi-billion dollar corporations can even think of getting
into.
And so Ting said, well, let's just short circuit all of that.
So they took the MVNO approach, and by creating agreements with multiple cellular providers,
DMA and GSM networks, they can invest in things like an in-house call center of human beings
that work there in the office with them.
Their support staff actually works in the building.
That's where they can spend money on their website, and on their app, and on customer
service, and on creating incredibly competitive pricing plans.
It's pay for what you use wireless.
It's $6 a month, and then just your usage on top of that.
They got a great dashboard.
You can turn services on and off as you need it.
You want to turn off a line.
There's no early termination fee.
There's no contract.
You don't want data.
You need data.
You only want calls.
You only want text.
You can do it all with Ting.
And they've got a savings calculator you can try out.
And when you go there, linux.ting.com, also check out their blog.
If you've switched to Ting since you've heard some of our ads, and you have a story to share,
you could win $100 Ting credit.
Just start by going to linux.ting.com, and a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring this
here, Unplugged Program.
So let's finish the FreeNAS thing, because we started that, then we'll get to Mobi.
Mobi is happening right now.
There's a DockerCon going on, and it's all happening.
But while I was gone, FreeNAS Coral was canned.
Development was halted.
It was relegated to technology preview status.
They're going to revert back to the FreeNAS 9 code base.
My rough understanding, and I'm going to tell you that I don't know much, and you could
get a much better, much clearer explanation tomorrow on BSD Now, because I think they're
going to have Chris Moore on to talk about all of this.
And Alan happens to know Chris, so that should work out pretty well.
They should be able to cover this.
I would expect BSD Now to have probably the best coverage out there tomorrow.
But what I seem to understand at this point is that there was essentially two teams on
FreeNAS working FreeNAS.
There's the FreeNAS 9 team kind of keeping that going and supported, and then there was
Jordan's team, which was sort of creating the new revolutionary product, the FreeNAS
Coral.
And what happened is their internal metrics were showing that they were having a massive
abandon rate of FreeNAS Coral, something like a huge percentage.
I think it's maybe somewhere in the 50% range or greater.
We're reverting back to FreeNAS 9, and so they were just seeing... I think that metric,
this is from what I've read, I think that metric freaked them out the most.
And they probably said, Jordan, you should probably go find something else to do.
We're going to not do this anymore.
And the team that they had kept around working on FreeNAS 9, in the meantime, was shoring
up the existing base, was developing a new UI, and actually has a lot of super great
plans in place already for FreeNAS 9.
Chris Moore was pretty clear about some of the features they're working on in a forum
post, and he was already showing screenshots of the new UI.
They're working, I think, maybe on getting some of the FreeNAS Coral plug-ins to work
as well under...
Okay.
Yeah.
So, I mean, they're definitely doing a pretty tight about face, and have a pretty good plan
B, but there is some egg on the face here, because FreeNAS has sort of achieved this
rock solid appliance status, and when you take a big leap like this, and it doesn't
land right, it can sometimes, that can stick to the reputation of the project a bit.
Now I got to really think that any serious enterprise installation wasn't jumping to
the next version of FreeNAS yet, so the effect rate is probably exaggerated.
Hopefully it's just people who are curious about it.
I think probably because the type of user base it was updating is the type of user base
that goes to Reddit forums and IRCs, it's probably more of an exaggerated issue, but
they have their own internal metrics that showed that there was a high abandonment rate.
That's my understanding, at least.
And it sounds like they have a pretty good plan going forward.
But whew, that is a rough thing to do.
Yeah.
And, you know.
Not the kind of thing you want to see for your storage appliance.
Yeah.
50%, it was 50%, says the chat room.
Yeah, that's a huge, that's a huge reversion rate.
So Chris will be on BSD Now tomorrow to talk more about it, so I'll be watching that, because
that, that affects us.
So let's talk about, we have a little, right now while we're recording this show, there's
a little bit of breaking news.
What?
CNN breaking news.
The DockerCon in Austin, Texas is going on right now, and the Docker company announced
Moby.
And I wasn't really going to talk about it on the show, but after going back and forth
a lot in chat, you and I actually kind of whittled down what the hell this is and why
it actually matters, and why it could be a good thing.
So we're going to talk about it now.
But I want to start just reading it to you, and I want to see, okay, somebody, let's see,
let's, we got to pick, I say, let's, let's, William, are you up for a game?
Is he there?
William, are you there?
How about, okay.
Let's, let's pick on Rotten.
Michael, are you up for a game?
Somebody, somebody, nobody.
It depends on the kind of game.
Well, I'm going to read to you the description of the Moby project, and I want you to guess
what it is that it does.
Fun.
Okay.
So the Moby project is a new open source project to advance the software containerization
movement and help the ecosystem take containers mainstream.
Okay.
No, yeah, I wouldn't have a guess, but that's, that's their description.
All right.
I'll read a little more.
It provides a library of components, a framework for assembling them into custom container
based systems, and a place for all container enthusiasts to experiment and exchange ideas.
Is it a store or something?
I know, or a forum.
It could be like something like a discussion forum, right?
All right.
I'll read a little more for you.
I mean, you know, we just got to go through this corporate ease.
Maybe we can figure it out if we just read a little more.
It turns out that Docker has been innovating in open source.
As a company, Docker uses open source as their innovation lab, they say.
And last year, our customers started to ask for Docker on many platforms beyond Linux,
Mac, Windows, and desktop, and Windows servers, and cloud platforms like AWS, Azure, and Googs.
We created a dozen Docker editions specialized for these platforms in order to be able to
build and ship these specialized editions in a relatively short time with small teams
in a scalable way without having to reinvent components, but also assemble components and
borrow an idea from the car industry where assemblies of components and reuse to build
completely different cars.
Okay.
Oh, see, I know exactly what this is now.
So okay, so we've read quite a bit.
In fact, we've read through the entire description of what this is now.
That is the extent of what it is.
Then they then later reiterate that it's a library, a framework, and a reference assembly.
It took Wes and I five minutes in chat to parse what the hell any of this means, and
I bring this up just simply because I find this astonishing that first of all, a company
... Well, actually, I think it plays a larger role here.
I think I figured out what my problem with Docker is.
My problem with Docker is they're shipping... They're basically taking advantage of
a feature that comes built into the operating system.
And so because that's such a commoditized product, they have to commoditize the ecosystem.
They have to monetize the ecosystem.
And so Docker has to come up with a way to be relevant when you can mix and match your
environment.
In fact, in here in this blog post, they talk about containers have been massively adopted,
but in a lot of cases, customers are building their own unique individualized component
stacks for their particular industry like manufacturing, or healthcare, or web hosting.
And that translates to Docker not being in the game.
The problem is that people... Because you can just use built-in components in the operating
system, you don't really have to use Docker if you just need something specific.
If you don't need to share with the wider Docker ecosystem, right?
So they had to come up with a way to solve this problem because the issue is-
How do we get to there?
The issue is they're selling water to a community that has a town well.
And so they have to either sell the cups or the buckets.
And so they've come up with a way to sell more buckets, in a sense, right?
What is Mobi, Wes?
Help me understand.
Mobi is like a toolkit for making something like Docker.
So it's frameworks, libraries, tools to help you take various pieces of what you might
need for a full containerized application, maybe even distributed, right?
So like schedulers, loggers, storage appliances or abstractions, networking configurations,
all of those things, right?
You can get with different pieces.
Sure, right now it uses all the default Docker things, right?
So container D is their default runtime.
But in theory, they're trying to make it so you can then easily and with tools to help
distribute them, package them, slot these pieces in and out.
So you could use Rocket or LXD maybe instead of Docker as the runtime, but you could still
use the Docker...
Yeah, or maybe even something as minimal as Run C or other things, yeah.
I don't know.
I've not played with it.
They do have a GitHub page up.
It actually looks like Docker is moving all of their open source things under the Mobi
project now.
So here's what I found interesting about the story, is essentially what happened at Docker
is they had to come up with a way to create Docker for Windows and for the Mac and all
these other web cloud platforms.
And I have wondered, how the hell are they building all these additions and not being
crushed by the weight of maintaining all these different versions of Docker?
Because the whole idea seems like it's just insane from a maintenance standpoint.
Especially if it's like the same, it started as this very like Linux specific thing.
Yeah, yes.
So what they did is they took the tool that they created to do all that work and they're
now releasing it open source and calling it Mobi.
And that's what this really is, is this is what let them build this mix and match pieces.
So on Windows, you can use the Docker runtime but use the Windows event log for logs and
stuff like that.
So anyways, Mobi project, big news everybody, and it probably actually will be a good way
for Docker to stay in the game even when you're not using a Docker stack.
Well, I think the thing they're missing is they haven't really convinced me yet because
they have to tell me about their synergy.
Right?
Yeah, definitely.
You should read there and count how many...
Wes and I were joking in chat that like they had like a quota of how many times they had
to say open source.
They were just throwing open source in there randomly, yeah.
It's super thick.
It's almost like they don't want you to understand what it is they're doing because there's easier
clearer ways to describe that.
I think the way we just described it is more clear and they didn't choose that.
And then you have to wonder what's the intent behind that.
Why are you choosing to write so thick?
That's the best I can describe it.
Like, you know, you take a look at the Solace project, nice, concise, clear communication
both in social and on their official blog post.
And part of that is because, you know, Josh is a great communicator but our friends over
at Solace have a new release that I think we'll talk more about next week after I've
had a chance to run it but what's interesting about this release is it's the first official
GNOME edition of Solace.
And also...
Interesting.
If you recall our conversation with Ikey a couple of weeks ago where he talked about
Clear Boot and doing bulletproof boot management.
Yes, I'm very interested in that.
This is the first version that ships with that.
Okay.
Yeah, so the Clear Boot manager is in there now which means down the road it'll be easy
to run different types of kernels.
It'll be easy to roll back if there's a kernel upgrade gone wrong.
I thought it was interesting is they've done a few tweaks to the GNOME stack.
So it's GNOME 3.2.4 and they've made a few patches to like the EJ...
Where is it?
Oh, here it is.
They made a few patches to resolve items not appearing in the GNOME menu.
They've tweaked a few options in Nautilus, a few things for SDL games.
Pretty minimal stuff.
Pretty minimal stuff though for their...
So it's a pretty and they've even turned on a couple of extensions like a dash to dock
and a couple of other things.
So otherwise they're pretty straightforward GNOME implementation and now they also have
the Mate edition as well.
Three flavors now of Solus started out with just...
Those are all tasty.
So if I want to play with the Clear Boot manager, which flavor should I pick?
I want to ask Ikey if the Solus GNOME edition is a hedge against his whole switching budgie
to QT blowing up.
Oh, yeah.
That's a good question.
I mean, or is there, I mean, which is a fine motivation, is that why you're including it
because you want to give the people who are going to cry wolf over the changes, you want
to give them a place to go?
GNOME is just everywhere now.
Yeah, it is everywhere.
It's just everywhere.
Sounds like overnight.
Like 2017 is the year of GNOME.
It's what the entire internet is talking about right now.
I feel bad for my Plasma desktop friends because I'm over here running Plasma desktop and I
feel like I'm a loner now.
We need to talk about the Church of Neon.
There we go.
Yes.
Are you feeling this at all?
Heavily.
Yeah.
Yeah, I am.
I've actually been in conversations with many people who all the time they would say something
about GNOME being like, it's so great they're switching to GNOME.
Not really because it means that they're kind of abandoning all of what they were doing
because they even said that they're going to ship basically what GNOME wants.
So GNOME is not typically known for being receiving and receptive at all to anyone's
opinion from any topic from any place in the world.
So I would be shocked if Canonical had anything changed in GNOME ever.
So I think that it's going to be basically just GNOME with Ubuntu slapped on top of it
as like a branding and that's it.
Which I consider that incredibly sad.
I want to talk about that too.
Let's go right into the 1704 review right now because I've been running Ubuntu GNOME
1704 and while it's fine, it's very sad in a sense because so Rodden, it feels like there's
no character to it.
Like there's no distinctiveness.
There's nothing unique about it.
It's just GNOME.
That's it.
It's GNOME with Ubuntu branding.
Which was great when I needed a refuge from Unity, which felt very Ubuntu heavy.
But when there's nothing that represents Ubuntu anymore and it's just, I mean they've got
to do something and it's got to be more than a wallpaper.
I think that they're probably not going to do much at all.
I mean I don't even think they're going to try to take over extensions at all, like even
try to make a global menu or anything.
I think they're just going to accept, just wash their hands of the situation of the customizations
and just ship GNOME.
Which I think would actually be a kind of a travesty because all of the cool innovations
that they have done will be just thrown away.
Yeah, I completely agree and it was weird because I didn't expect it.
When I loaded Ubuntu GNOME, I was like, okay, here we go, I'm going to go to the future.
I'm going to see what it's like in a future Ubuntu, oh my god, it's so sad.
It's so sad.
Like Antigros.
You can't say that 17.10 will be different, they might do more customizations because
they weren't really technically backing them yet, but I still don't think so.
Yeah, Antigros has way more character and unique, Fedora even, just way more character
and feel to it.
Why do you pick Ubuntu?
Once it's GNOME, is it just for their package repository?
Compatibility, software compatibility.
How does the GNOME desktop, how does it market itself there?
How does it fit in with that?
Well, now GNOME could be the... It's the same thing as what it was seven years
ago when it was just 2010, 10.04, whatever, where it was basically GNOME, but with like
... Well, okay, so I don't want to go too far
down this path because I think this could be a separate discussion, but I disagree now
because GNOME with GTK since 3.20 and with Flatpaks and the Software Center and all this
work they've been doing with Builder.
It's more now of an application target, like come write a GTK application for the GNOME
platform.
It's much more of that now than it was back when Canonical was originally shipping a GNOME
desktop.
I just wanted, before we move on, because Ike just joined us and so I want to talk about
the Solus GNOME edition too while we're talking about GNOME, but Poppy, remember when Poppy
used to come on this show?
Yeah.
Oh.
That was great.
I love that.
I miss those guys.
I would love to go visit Poppy.
Yeah.
I would love that.
That would be a lot of fun.
Love that.
But he did a really great blog post about how he configured GNOME on his 1604 desktop.
So if you want to stick with the LTS to look more familiar.
Just speaking of the Plasma thing, I made a video explaining how you could make Plasma
look like Unity and function like Unity with the global menus, merging title bars, all
that good stuff like the system menu and all kinds of stuff.
And I think that if it wasn't even remotely possible for the canonical to even consider
it that Plasma would be a fantastic foundation for Unity.
And I don't mean like they should switch to Plasma.
I think they should switch to Plasma for a foundation to continue the focus of Unity.
Yeah, but I always thought that should have been the case when they were going to use
Qt to begin with.
Maybe Ike can tell us why he's not doing that.
But before we get there, I also just wanted to say in the land of 1704 releases and all
of the associated Ubuntu editions, our friend Wimpy has really blown the doors off with
Mate 1704.
And I'd say that even if he didn't come on this show.
This is, I said it on last and it's true.
This goes back to the era where there was a time where the dot 10 releases were so damn
good that you were willing to throw out the LTS and upgrade.
I remember that.
That's what this is.
You know, he's had work with, Ike's gone into this, work from Daniel from elementary OS
has gone into this.
But a lot of folks have put a lot of hard work in this.
And I think it's just a killer release.
And in fact, there's even a credit for producer Michael in here.
Nice.
What did you do, producer Michael?
I helped with the graphic stuff for icons and high DPI support, stuff like that.
Yeah, we've got the Brisk menu in this one that Ike helped with.
It's got a really nice theme.
But the other thing that I thought was just a standout feature that just makes deployment
Mate desktops really nice is the software boutique now by default does queued installations.
You can queue up a bunch of stuff.
I like that.
You combine that with the fact that you've got a genuine GTK3 desktop using the traditional
desktop paradigm.
There's more options now for like pre-configured desktops that are really great.
And the theme is, I can't even believe they can make Mate look this good.
So it's 17.04.
I think out of all of the Mate edition of 17.04, I think out of all of them is just
an easy win.
Yeah, it's a really nice one.
If you want to, if you're installing it for anyone, you know, who works for so many people.
I wish I could have all of these things on the LTS because I have a couple of computers
in the studio that I want to reinstall.
And I would love to put, so I have this machine over here that runs my mixer that soon will
not be running my mixer anymore.
And I'd like to put Linux, I'd like to put Ubuntu Mate, but I want it to look like this.
But I want an LTS.
Yes.
But you don't want the, yeah, the temp.
Damn it, Wimpy.
Also, other people should definitely, if they installed 17.04, they should make sure that
they check the box for the Ubuntu Mate welcome update because it inactivates a PPA that you
can continuously get things, which is really important when applications are removed from
the software boutique because of, like, they're not building for 17.04.
And then as soon as they start building for it, it gets added back.
That's nice.
Oh yeah, that's really good.
And you just get the latest, if you get the latest version, you get that?
Yeah, it'll automatically, if you check the box, it'll automatically update Ubuntu Mate
welcome, which also updates software boutique, so every time they make a change, you get
it.
Perfect.
I also wanted to shout out, so for those of you who, like me, are trying out Ubuntu
Gnome again for kind of, like, the first time, trying it out again for the first time, it's,
yeah, you may run into a few problems if you just have straight-up Chrome or now Firefox,
so I have a link in the show notes on getting extensions installed, but cooler than that,
you can also sync Gnome extensions between your desktops using Google Chrome, between
your Gnome desktop.
Really?
Yeah.
Tell me more.
Yeah, sure.
Isn't that interesting?
Yeah.
And you have to install the Gnome shell extension on your desktop using, there's a little sync
feature in there.
Once enabled, you can sync your Gnome extensions from, say, your desktop to other machines
pretty much automatically.
Now, you have to go in and turn the sync feature on on each computer, but once you do that,
yeah, and you don't have to have, you don't have to have straight-up, like, binary from
Google Chrome.
You can just get Chromium from the repo if you want.
Isn't that neat?
Yeah, that is awesome.
Yeah, and only, you have to have the corresponding Gnome shell extension, Google Chrome shell.
You gotta get that.
Actually, I also made an extension for basically every browser, which gives you access to download
the zip files for each extension, so you can just, like, store them if you want.
Oh, good idea.
Yeah, that's nice.
So, you need the tweak tool, you know, the Gnome tweak tool, but you just get the zip
file and just install it from there, and there you go.
All right.
So, let's mention DigitalOcean, then I'm gonna, let's talk to Aiki, because we gotta,
this is, I would like to talk about the Gnome edition, and also if Aiki feels like he's
more on an isolated island with QT now than ever, now that Canonical has gotten cold feet
and running away.
Running away from their dreams?
DigitalOcean.com, go fulfill your dreams with a server in the cloud on their awesome infrastructure.
Yeah, I mean, you could go rack it if you want, if you're insane, but DigitalOcean
is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering an easy and intuitive way for
you to get going.
You just spin up, create an account, and use our promo code DEO, unplugged, one word, and
you get a $10 credit.
You can use that to spin up a $5 rig, run it for two months, try it out, put a project
on there, a blog, maybe you wanna try Mastodon.
I've seen a couple of guides now, I was looking on the pre-show, for setting them up on DigitalOcean.
Or what about Mumble?
Yeah.
Mumble's another good one.
If you wanna try out an Elias sync engine, run that on a DigitalOcean.
I should probably try that again.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, you know, they got a new version out which uses less syncing.
Ooh.
Less.
But you can still run a component on your own server if you'd like.
It's seriously easy.
So we were talking about Docker earlier, one of the things that's really nice about DigitalOcean
is you can deploy an entire application stack with everything installed for some apps, or
you just do the base installation, or the sweet spot is Ubuntu LTS, Docker pre-loaded,
with the repos from Docker, with the right GPG keys in there, with everything up to date,
good to go.
Easy peasy.
Yeah, that's crazy powerful.
That's just you can get trying something in no time.
When you use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED, you can try it out for free.
They got data centers all over the world, and they have the best interface in the business
with an API to die for.
An API to die for.
I'm trying to make it rhyme, but I need something, an API to cry, cry for the API.
I cry for that API.
I'm trying hard, Wes.
You really are.
Crying for that API over at DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED, go spin up
a Linux rig on their infrastructure, they use KVM for the virtualizer, Linux for the
host, 40 gigabit connections into that hypervisor, I know it, and a beautiful control panel to
top it all off at DigitalOcean.com.
Also, check out their block storage.
It's all SSD-based.
It's crazy.
DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
Ike, you're supposed to be in bed.
You weren't going to come on the show today because you are supposed to be asleep right
now.
That was the last I heard of it.
You're a maniac.
Well, you said things about solos.
It's sort of like-
It's turned off.
Yeah.
It's amazing.
I don't know.
That's almost spooky in a sense.
So, Ike, first of all, congratulations on the new release.
Yeah.
Thank you very much.
You've got a big deal.
Got clear boot out the door.
Very excited about that.
Yeap.
Well, let's talk about the GNOME edition because that's the big news, I think, and I say, sir,
you're hedging.
You say I am hedging.
Right?
Well, I don't know about that, but it seems like it could be a possibility.
No, I mean, we've had GNOME in the repos for ages.
Like we've had GNOME, Shell, GDM, you know, it's been up on the Wiki and now the Help
Center.
And basically, it kind of felt a bit stupid not having an ISO for it because we have the
infrastructure tooling and all that just to put one out.
And especially with budget going towards in the future, having that GNOME stack there
and then not using it and then not making an ISO out of it kind of feels a bit stupid.
And there are going to be people who are diehard GNOME.
They want to stay on their site.
So it's like, okay, well, here's an option and here's GNOME how we think it should be
within soldiers, you know, like kind of fitting with our sanity.
So that's what it mostly comes down to.
So Josh is responsible for that ISO and he uses GNOME Shell daily.
Well, thank you, Josh, because I think it's going to be the one I'll be loading on my
machines for a bit, too.
It's fairly sexy.
Tell me about the EGL device for EGL streams and mutter.
What the hell is this and why does it matter?
Yeah, I mean, that's certainly not the sexiest news on the segment.
I found it interesting.
That's what Pharaonyx picked up on.
No, I'm sitting here and you're bum reading right off the blog post here.
Yeah, it's basically preliminary support for the Nvidia proprietary drivers on the mutter,
so.
Oh, no wonder why Pharaonyx is covering it.
Yeah, that does make sense.
Yeah.
I like that, though.
That actually, I'm actually I'm excited about that.
I'm glad I asked.
And then, of course, I have to ask, how is things going with Budgie?
And do you kind of feel like you're off on a cute island now?
No, not at all.
I've got Budgie 10.3.1 out now.
We've actually fixed all tab.
Yeah, congrats.
Yeah, so basically, I kind of knew the way the release schedule was looking this weekend
and I was like, OK, let's be sensible here.
I'm not going to get it done because I haven't got it done so far.
So I put a bounty up and I basically said on Thursday, I think it was, if anyone can
get it done before Sunday evening or was it Saturday evening, I think it was Saturday
evening.
I'll pay you 500 euros.
Wow.
And I was like, yeah, I mean, I wanted it done and a way for the community to get involved.
That's great.
I think it's awesome.
And then there was free pull requests in and I basically said the first one that was, you
know, first value pull request came in would be merged.
So we had two active by the end of it and basically, they were both making fixes in
parallel.
It's like, well, it's kind of hard to say who really came first now.
I was like, OK, well, there are bugs in each.
And this particular one, which is by a member of the community called Tim, kind of ticks
the boxes and it's something I can extend and fix afterwards, which it did.
So Budgie 11 has been blocked by the lack of Budgie 10.3 because the idea was we fix
these last little regressions and these annoying minor bugs like Altab, right?
It was like the meme of Budgie.
So if we can fix those, get those out of the way, then it's almost like 10.3 became a bit
more like, well, I guess our Unity 7, really.
Already already.
I know, too soon, too soon.
So that becomes like our kind of LTS thing.
And it buys me time to get Budgie 11 done and done how I want to do it.
So yeah, it's going to be cool, it's going to be cool.
All right.
So now I got to go get this installed on a machine.
Oh, yeah.
OK.
Let's just let's play armchair futurist and let's speculate for a moment.
What if like what if you wake up one day, you look at some statistics, some metric that
you look at and you say, holy crap, the gnome edition has become our number one download.
People are downloading the gnome edition above and beyond everything else.
Does anything change?
Is there a is there a change in plans at all?
I mean, not really, because it's kind of hard to gauge that with an existing user base as
well.
I mean, I can tell you now basically how they're doing.
Let's look at Linux tracker on the torrents because, you know, I mean, Ike, you think
about it.
You're spending this weird, weird, weird time in the resurgence of gnome.
It's huge.
And it's I mean, it's across I mean, even solace now you can get a gnome edition.
And so it's really becoming it could become this really close to universal desktop.
Almost.
I mean, the other the other benefit that also brings in as well is flat back.
Yeah, exactly.
Think about it, because it's like they go hand in hand.
So now we know across every distribution, there's going to be known, there's going to
be flat back.
Right.
Well, that depends on your definition of benefit.
Well, yeah, I mean, just loosely skating around that one.
But looking at the download numbers now just for the torrents, because I know earlier on,
between two of the mirrors, they've been 800 and 700 downloads total earlier on.
We released I think, like five o'clock this morning or something stupid.
So the Mate ISO has had just 241 downloads.
The gnome one has had 347 downloads.
So it's more popular than the Mate one now.
And the Budgie one has had 499.
The gnome one is repping pretty well.
Of course, people are curious, right?
They're taking a look.
Oh, it's now 500.
Real sad updates.
Well, and of course, I probably I don't know.
I don't know.
I don't know how I'll pull it down.
I probably get a torrent.
I've debated which one I want right now.
I think I got to do the gnome one.
I think.
They are a little bit bigger this time.
Like last time, there was 900 makes or so.
And you know, like, we've been four months since we've done a release.
So it's been a bit of a while, you know, you're getting a bit rusty doing this kind of stuff.
So I started looking through some of the older YouTube reviews, and you know, even listening
to some of the old Linux Unplugged things, and it's like, you start to collect some of
the problems.
And one of the ones that kept coming up is like, why is there not an office suite?
Ah, so now they all have an office suite in them, which basically LibreOffice, you know,
it's standard, but it's a bit chunky.
So we put that in, taken out VLC and put in gnome MPV, but the Mate one still has VLC
because gnome MPV just looks weird there.
Like you have to go for traditional.
Yeah, so now it's just under 1.2 gigs, so we got a little bit fatter.
I think the choice to switch to gnome MPV was a good one when I saw that in the release
notes, I thought.
It's pretty.
And enabling dash to dock by default, I think is a good choice too, especially for people
that come in from Unity.
Yeah.
The one I'm most fond of in terms of the extension there is the tray icons plus that he's put
in there.
What was that?
Well, normally you get the tray icons come out on the little legacy tray on the bottom
left of the screen and just pokes out like a little freakish antenna.
I never liked it.
And now they're all up in the tray.
So it's like it's the top icons extension kind of.
Yeah, I think it's like top icons plus or something.
Yeah, top icons by legacy tray.
I see.
Yeah, that little tab just never quite, I just literally just accidentally activated
it.
What is this?
While we're talking, I accidentally just triggered it.
It's always, go away, go away, and it shows up on screen all the time.
Yes, it does.
So we also have brisk menu now in the Mate edition.
They're all 0.3, 0.5, I think we're on now.
Basically the same version as Ubuntu Mate, like we're going parallel on there.
That's great.
Mm-hmm.
And they've got a lot of theming in which I'm jealous of.
Martin got the theming sorted out.
So it's even better integrated into Ubuntu Mate's theming now.
So it looks really nice over there.
Which also brings in with Mate 1.18, also brings in lib input, which is nice.
Yeah.
There was a bit of a bug in the last release we did back in January where, unfortunately,
the lib input driver got dragged in on one of the updates, which isn't fatal, but it
stopped some of the configurations from being configurable.
I see.
But then as soon as we put Mate 1.18, it's just like, well, now it has lib input support.
So that fixed that out.
Which means they're all using lib input now across all of the ISOs.
I couldn't help but notice, too, there's several things in here that seem to be, well, overall
improvements to NVMe drives, but also sort of a secondary effect is a couple of things
in here ended up making MacBook support a little better, including better backlight
support, it looks like, and support for the 2016 SSD.
Yeah.
I was looking at the 2013, 2014, and 2016 ranges of MacBooks and enabling support for
them.
So we've got initial support for the new MacBook Pro from 2016.
There's going to be some device drivers still missing, basically, until we backport more
from 4.11.
But we do have initial support for their NVMe drives, which that was the one that was up
in the news last year.
You couldn't use Linux on that at all.
So backported that, you know, while it can.
We've got the NVMe power saving patches backported from 4.11 as well.
So they'll save like two to four watts or something overall.
So it's a slightly lower power consumption.
We've also changed basically the way that we do the CPU governor now.
When it used to be back a while back, well, about a year back, we were always using the
performance governor.
Then we changed it to on-demand or power save, depending on whether you was using Intel P-state
or CPU pre.
Now we boot up all the time in performance, and once we got to the multi-user target,
you know, using the directed system D, which everybody hates, but it was really useful
here.
So I like it for this.
Yeah.
We'll then change.
If you're using Intel P-state, then it'll go down into power save.
Sure.
So you end up with maximum performance for boot up, and then once the system's loaded.
Exactly.
So you boot up as quick as you can and then save the battery afterwards.
It's disabled under virtualization, so it'll just stay in performance mode, which is kind
of logical because then it's controlled by the system outside the hypervisor anyway.
That is really nice.
Good.
That's a good way to do it.
So you're telling me that if I blow up the Arch install on my 2013 Macbook...
When you get known 3.24, yeah.
You're telling me it's possible to put that Solus might work pretty good on that 2013
hardware?
Yeah.
I mean, I'd love to get some feedback, and if it's not, then we can just start doing
more rapid snapshots.
Interesting.
I mean, I can't get myself one anyway.
I would love to, but I can't really go out and justify that kind of money on one.
So the more feedback they're getting, the more I can fix, really.
Yeah.
I mean, if they made it with 32 gigs of RAM, I would almost consider falling on that sword
just so I could also have a faster Final Cut machine, but you just can't justify it.
You can't justify it.
Yeah, it's a bit of money.
My machine would literally have to die before I could justify it.
The battery's not as great as it used to be.
It's still okay, and the speakers are all right, but...
Just too useful.
It's just like, damn it, why won't this stupid thing die?
And then the problem is, but then I would still have...
I would have a mourning period if I had to buy a Macbook.
I would mourn that purchase.
We'd have to talk about it.
Big buyer's remorse.
The only way I'd feel better is if I could somehow improve a distribution support.
So I'd do it.
I would do it.
Well, Ike, I'm pretty excited about the release just for myself, personally, because I love
the GNOME edition.
I know it was in the repos, but you know what I always do is I would install the Budgie
edition and then I would go, yeah, I'm good.
Yeah.
Now you have something that's actually set up to be sane out of the box.
There's no fiddling.
And obviously you've got the normal stuff installed, so you've got the Chrome GNOME
shell extension stuff, GNOME Tweet tool, that kind of stuff.
Sorry, Andy.
Oh, we were just talking about that.
Cool.
So that's awesome.
There are a couple of updates coming through in the next day or two.
I basically wanted to speed up the boot even more because apparently I have something wrong
with me.
I can't stop.
Yeah, I don't blame you.
I just can't stop it.
And I was like, oh, I've spotted an opportunity.
So you don't quite get a silent boot at the moment, and part of that is regressing the
boot time.
So I fixed that today so it's an absolutely silent boot.
I don't want to splash in there because then you're adding like 30 to 40 megs to every
upload because you're including Plimoth and then you're adding like five, six, seven seconds
to the boot.
It's like, let's just make it silent instead.
So I've managed to do that.
So until X starts, you'll see nothing but black screen.
It's lush and that in itself on my system.
So I'm already booting in about 1.7 seconds on this Broadwell NUC.
Today I've managed to shave in over 450 milliseconds off of that.
So if that's my SSD booting in that time on my Broadwell NUC, you can imagine how something
like Skull Canyon is going to go.
Or even people with older systems because then it grows exponentially.
So those updates we come through, we now we pre-link all of the binaries in the unit Ramfests
and strip them so that they actually start up quicker because they haven't got to work
with a linker to find anything.
We now got AMD early boot code support now as well.
So that'll hot patch the microcode onto the CPU when it's starting up.
So we've got all of that sexiness to come from this couple of days.
And that'll be 4.9.2 free, which I got packaged today.
That's awesome.
I mean, he doesn't fall asleep at the keyboard because he's staying up.
Yeah.
He's like, why does the commit message just say zzzz?
Well, congrats.
So the snapshot for 2017.04.18.0 is out.
I'm going to go download it.
And you can read.
I like also the nice, clear snapshot notes by Josh.
It's nice to just read through all of that.
Type free.
Yeah.
Did you see the change log at the end of it?
Yeah, actually.
You know what I was thinking when I saw that?
That was machine-generated.
Yeah.
We'll be honest.
But it's been a long time since I've seen that, really.
That doesn't happen as much anymore.
There's a few projects that still do it.
Yeah.
I mean, we do that for the primary one.
And then when we looked at it, it was like, Jesus Christ, that's obscene.
We've got to include it now, right?
I love that.
That must be.
Yeah.
We've definitely got to put that in there.
That's basically four months.
But that's only showing what's changed on the budget I saw.
Oh.
Oh, really?
Jeez.
Wow, that's quite the list.
So that's not like the repos themselves, which have now grown to such a point that, well,
you can imagine when we started out with Solus, like certain scripts and systems that we used,
everything just worked.
And we've got this script that monitors the packages coming into the repo.
And that's been fine for a long time.
But we started to get to a point where we'll keep free back versions.
And in between those, you have the deltas, which is fine if you follow that bit so far.
Then when I actually counted the packages the other day in the repos, it was like 75,000
EL package files flown across the repo.
And the script that monitors them has to index the repo every single time.
Oh, boy.
So it's going through 75,000 files just to add one new one each time.
I was like, right, this might have been a design flaw.
So that made our release 104 minutes late the other day.
We started off with a different version number.
It was the 17th.
And then because the script was so long, we switched back to the 18th.
I'd already put up the Twitter post as well with the version number.
Yikes.
That is funny.
That's a good story.
The secrets of releases.
Yeah, the behind the scenes secrets right there.
Well, Ike, thank you very much, sir, for coming on.
My pleasure.
I'm glad we were able to make it work.
And we'll have a link to the release notes in the show notes if you guys want to download.
And check out Ike and the team's fine, fine work.
They also have a link to the 1704 releases in the show notes.
There's just so much good stuff to try.
Also, go check out more of Ike on Late Night Linux.
That's a great podcast.
They just had an episode come out a couple of, or yesterday, I think.
So go check all that out.
Mr. Wes, where can people find you on the Twitters?
At WesPay.
And also on the TechSnap program.
That's right.
Just stay tuned.
I'm at Chris Elias.
The network's at Jupyter Signal.
Find us live at JupyterBroadcasting.com slash calendar.
We'll be back here next Tuesday.
I secretly use ArchLina.
Oh, probably stop by.
That was good.
Hey, good.
I thought he was able to pop in there for a second.
That's nice.
Missed you, bud.
I think, I think you should take the Solace challenge, Wes.
Yeah.
I think you should do it.
All right.
It's happening.
I think this machine, too, right here, possibly could be good for Solace.
Yes.
You know, now that I'm not going to be doing last, I don't have to install a whole bunch
of apps for the pics all the time.
It changes a fair bit.
Yeah.
It's changing a lot of things for me, actually.
I'm realizing all the little things in life that will be different for me.
Yeah.
So yeah.
All right.
JupyterTitles.com, guys.
JupyterTitles.com.
Did you guys see the new Google Earth came out today?
No, really?
Yeah.
Check this thing out.
This is, like, serious, like, 3D rendering happening.
So like, yeah, look.
WebGL.
This is, yeah.
Using WebGL, we're going to zoom in here to the Eiffel Tower, and look, they 3D render
everything now.
Wow.
Yeah.
That is actually kind of neat.
Looks pretty neat.
And then they have this feature now where you can randomly go to cool places, like,
you can roll the dice.
Why fly?
You could just Google it.
Yeah.
So like, let's go over here to, like, vwoom.
Over to Hawaii.
Look at that.
Zoom right in.
That's actually...
That's pretty cool.
You see how it renders the mountains all cool, like, and whatnot?
Like, it really puts some work into this damn thing.
JupyterTitles.com.
Oh, sorry.
Hello, my group.
Hi.
I missed you.
Thanks for being here, guys.
All y'all.
Yes.
Very much so.
Look at that.
How cool is that, Wes?
Wow.
All right.
We're going to have to play with that later.
Yeah.
It's smooth, too.
Well, it's not on all my computers, but on the ones with the higher-end video, dedicated
graphics, it seems to be working pretty well.
Now we're going to go to Lake Superior, one of the large Great Lakes in North America.
Look at that.
That is big.
Yeah.
So that's the view.
And then when you zoom in, you can go to 3D mode here.
So if you tap 3D mode, it starts to render everything out.
Oh, wow.
Some are better than others.
Yeah.
Look at Google Go.
Look at them go.
It's really...
If you think about...
I don't want...
Oh, you can...
Big Bend National Park here.
Let's go look at Big Bend.
Look.
We're going all around the world, Wes.
Going all around the world, Wes.
See?
And you do podcasting.
You get to travel the world.
Look at that.
Yeah.
Cool.
All right.
JBtitles.com.
Yeah.
Let's pick a title.
Is there anything in the mobile room that we wanted to pick up that didn't get covered
in the show?
Anybody want to...
Oh, there's an open floor for a couple more minutes before we go.
Ubuntu's bare gnome.
That's not bad.
The giant gnome rolling in the Linux.
The chaos of disunity, gnome hunter gnawing on gnome, year of gnome, Docker's whale of
a tail.
Oh, ww.
Nice.
You're so funny.
I like it.
I see what you did there, ww.
I see what you did there.
Tee hee.
Tee hee hee.
We love you.
Tee hee hee hee.
Oh, my God.
Mr. Sending Man.
Amazing.
Oh, my God.
Making the cutest rat I've ever seen.
That's fantastic.
All right.
And you should send me that so I can play it with high fidelity over here, because that's
good.
Yeah, that's probably not good through my mic.
Is it online?
Can you link to it?
Yeah, I can link to it over here.
That's funny.
I don't have the files right now, but I can get it.
Let's see.
Fairly sexy.
I had it on my phone.
A quote from...
You'll probably get copyrighted.
Yeah, right.
I know.
Ubuntu's bear gnome is up there by Kawasaki.
Oh, I'm hungry all of a sudden.
Didn't I have lunch?
I did have lunch.
What the hell's up with that?
The giant gnome...
You've been podcasted, man.
Yeah, I worked up an appetite.
Woo.
Alexa.
Appetite for a nap.
Turn on JB1.
Get those lights going for you.
That was a good...
That was really well done.
Now that's really stuck in my head.
What do you think of Ubuntu's bear gnome?
It's not bad.
Yeah?
You don't love it?
I don't know how I feel about it.
I don't hate it.
I bet the people seem to like it.
Gnomeo gnomeo.
I thought as far as echo commands go, I think that echo one's safe because probably nobody
else has any devices called JB1.
Yes.
That seems pretty easy.
Yeah.
I also like these.
Are we gonna have to get to the point where all your commands are random strings?
These are.
I call these Shatner's hair lights just because there's so many lights in here that Alexa...
Cancel.
Starts to get confused and mixes...
Stop.
Shut up.
There we go.
She wants to be with you.
So she gets confused because they all have light in the name.
So you gotta come up with these totally diverse names.
So I got flow lights and I got hair lights and ambient lights and accent lights and...
Yeah.
So you should just like...
Have you tried, Alexa, what is a Whopper?
I know, actually.
I haven't tried that.
Alexa, what is a Whopper?
It's a signature hamburger sold by the international fast food restaurant, chain Burger King and
its Australian franchise, Hungry Jack's.
I want to be some Hungry Jack's.
I didn't know they had a Hungry Jack's subsidiary.
I didn't know that.
It's really too bad when Hungry Jack is not nearly as...
I'd rather be the Burger King, personally.
The OK Google thing.
I'm amazed at how well that works.
My phone was completely across the room and that TV was able to trigger my phone.
I was...
Actually, so Google says they put out a command to stop it, but what it really does is it
still recognizes the trigger word and it still bleeps at you and then it just immediately
cancels.
But it still triggers your phone and wakes it up.
Interesting.
So it's still annoying.
Yeah.
You know what's actually kind of genius in the mad genius way of trolling where Burger
King was like, we know Google is going to break this.
Yeah, that was next level marketing, actually.
I don't think it was a flop at all.
I think it was actually brilliant.
And here we are like a week or two weeks later still talking about it.
It's even better because they knew that Google was going to break it and then they did the
same type of thing on TV marketing, TV commercials, and it was a different phrase so that when
Google broke the previous phrase, the next one would still work.