I wouldn't want to judge you for using Outlook, Wes, but rumor has it you have a little Outlook
rant for us.
A little pre-show Outlook.
It was just a weird experience.
Yeah, at work we have Outlook 365, and honestly it's fine.
It works with Linux, obviously, because it's a web client.
It meets my needs.
And they pay for it.
How practical of you.
Yeah.
Not what I would set up for myself at home, but I don't have to.
I was trying to send a SQL dump, right?
So I gzipped it to save space, getting ready to email it, send it off.
A couple hours later I get a, you know, come back and say, hey, could you send that again?
This looks like a binary data file.
And I was like, all right, maybe I made a mistake.
I know how gzip works.
So I didn't think so.
It turns out anything with a.gz extension, Outlook gzips.
Like it will just, so it was a doubly gzipped file.
Why would you do it on something that has a.gz?
I don't know.
So I tried with.xz,.bz2.
Like none of those.
Doesn't touch them.
Doesn't touch zip files, but it wasn't even after sending it, all I had to do was attach
it.
So like once it uploaded through the browser, it even was to the point where if you, if
I made a tar and I named it tar.gz, just change the file name and then upload it, it would
then decompress it for me.
And it doesn't add an extra gz.
No.
So that was just bizarre.
And it took me way too long to figure out what was going on.
I was like, why can't I send this guy a file?
And then how was it, how was the checksum different after all I did was upload it to
them?
I don't know if it's a consequence of them trying to do virus scans or just a bug on
their end.
Hey, you know what?
Notify them about it.
You got to make sure that those PST files don't get too big, Wes.
That's true.
We got a pixel 2 leak.
This is funny.
Did the doorbell ring or did I just imagine that?
No that, well, I am pulling the case out of the box and I accidentally punched myself
in the nose.
Oh my God, Ben.
Oh my God.
That's not great.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 215 for September 19th, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show, or at least part of it's getting
ready to ship out to New York.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Hello, sir.
And as always these days, it's the beard, what's up beard?
Not much.
Good.
I'm glad because you know what?
I got a little podcast I need you to help me with right now.
That would be great.
I'm down.
All right.
Well, we've got a great show coming up on this week's episode.
We're going to cover some community news that I figure we should talk about.
That's what we'll do at the top of the show.
Then just a little bit into the show, we have a special guest joining us from the newly
announced PipeWire project.
Very excited to jump into this project, explain what it's about, clear up some misconceptions
and hopefully get to the bottom of why Linux needs a little something like this.
Then I hope you'll stick with me to the end of the show because I got something I got
to get off my chest.
It is an issue that is near and dear to my heart.
It's not really unfamiliar to some of you on this show.
I hope you'll stick around because it's something that's super important I want to talk to you
about.
And I think it has major ramifications for the entire open source community.
So we'll dig into that towards the end of the show.
But before we can do any of that, there's one ritual in which we must always follow.
And that is saying hello to our virtual log.
Time appropriate greetings, mumble room.
Hey babe.
Good day.
Hey there.
Hello guys.
Hello.
Look at that.
You guys all came to say goodbye to me.
You guys all come leaving right after the show and they all knew that they knew that
they're going to storm the studio try to take over and then I'm driving to see poppy.
That's my plan.
That's really why I'm going because poppy is going to be there.
There's some others.
Big draw.
There's some other people there.
I mean, I heard Ike is going so I almost considered not going obviously, of course, but stay in
North Dakota.
Yeah.
Is that why you're bringing Noah's insurance?
Well, I got to have my muscle.
You know, I heard Ike wants to throw things at me from windows.
So I got to be ready.
I got to be.
I'll admit I'm fairly jealous.
I'm looking forward to it.
Anyways, let's let's get into some of the news today.
I think this first story is pretty big for a lot of us more and more so for me these
days because I found myself on public Wi-Fi a lot.
Core has a new release that I think is pretty interesting and it is specifically version
3.2.1 alpha with support for the next generation onion services.
This is, I think, inspired after some recent trouble that they've had.
It uses the new version three of the onion service protocol and it adds a new circuit
scheduler.
Hey, that sounds good.
It does sound good.
That's like that sounds good for more responsive forwarding decisions from relays, which also
seems like a great thing.
There's a bunch of other changes in here, too.
I'm actually just telling you just the super, super highlights of it.
They have new major features that I can only barely understand, but it's called the kernel
informed socket transport.
Yeah.
How about that?
It's available on Linux system.
It uses feedback from the kernel to prevent the kernel's TCP buffers from growing too
full.
Oh, nice.
Okay.
Yeah.
Which I would imagine probably has big improvements for Tor network speeds.
So that's the new version 3.2.1 alpha.
That's a great step in there.
Yeah.
Are you much of a Tor user?
I feel like I'm a criminal when I'm on Tor, but I've been thinking more and more about
it.
I've been using a VPN a lot these days.
Using that.
I have certain...
I don't use it a lot currently.
I have certainly used it in the past and I'm glad it exists and glad that they're making
good progress.
I'm sure, Beard, when you're hanging out on the dark web, you're probably using the Tor
as well.
Yeah.
All the time.
I'm only on the dark web.
Yeah.
That's...
Yeah, exactly.
I mean, I guess you stream on the regular P web, but you just...
Because that's where the eyeballs are.
Yeah.
I use dark Twitch.
Oh, dark Twitch.
Gotcha.
Dark Twitch.
Good, good, good.
It's got a lot of illegal things on it.
Yeah.
It's far more interesting than regular Twitch.
Well, when you're using your dark web, you can also use Keybase teams to kick Slack in
the balls.
It is a new app to replace Slack and it uses their famed security and encryption by default.
It's got channels like Slack or your Discord out there.
It's end-to-end encrypted, which means you don't have to worry about their server reading
it, they say.
And you can lay awake at night fearing the breach of your company.
You don't have to lay awake, I guess.
They say that's either use their system or lay awake at night.
That's pretty hyperbole.
But anyways, they say Keybase accounts are simpler.
You don't have to switch at the top level of an app.
Teams can be casual and small.
Nice.
That is kind of a cool idea.
It's quaint how we try to do this.
I mean, good luck to...
I like Keybase.io, respect the people over there.
Good luck to you.
Looking in the good footsteps of Skype competitors and Facebook competitors and everyone who
likes to launch an alternative to a platform, Goliath, I say, good luck to you.
I think...
You know what I've been saying, gosh, Rocket Chat and Matrix, and just not enough.
Not enough.
It matters most.
Yeah.
Not enough.
And Nextcloud is also kind of squaring in on this, too.
And not enough.
And I'm glad the guys at Keybase recognized this need as well that none of us had and
decided to set up a...
Set up a affiliate.
Now...
It's not like we also had a specific one from Amazon or anything.
No.
This is not enough.
Just not enough.
So that's good.
And I hope them...
I wish for them the best because it seems like they're a great team over there.
And if nothing else, I'd rest a little more comfortable thinking open source projects use
something like this or at least your Isises and your Alcataz.
This would be nice for them.
Oh, yeah.
I like the no upsell about message history.
That's...
Yeah.
That makes it nice for me.
That is nice.
And you know, as your terrorist cells have to migrate off of Telegram, they got to go
to something else.
They got to go to something.
Governments got to lean on something new.
So I think this makes a lot of sense.
And you can find out more at Keybase.io slash blog, and we will have a link in the show
notes.
I want to talk about something serious that happened yesterday, September 18th, 2017.
And it was the EFF formally resigning from the W3C.
And now the W3C is the, quote, unquote, standards body that has standardized the recent encryption
media extensions that all browsers happily lapped up.
Well, I guess not all.
And as you can imagine, Cory Doctorow and his colleagues at the EFF were very disappointed
and they challenged this decision.
There's a lot of controversy about how that challenge was handled.
And now that things have run their course as a result of the way things have ended up
on behalf of the EFF, Cory Doctorow has resigned from the W3C and has also publicly said here
in his post that they will defend those who are put in harm's way for blowing the whistle
on defects in EME implementations.
In other words, the EFF is publicly stating they will defend people who try to crack EME.
This is a really complex issue because you have what are the expectations of what the
W3C actually is expected to do in this day and age, especially the way browsers are actually
developed and the reality of the actual market.
What were the EFF's expectations?
And you could debate EME as a topic itself.
Right.
Then there's a separate tertiary debate on how the W3C handled the challenge to this
entire thing.
So this is a deeply complex issue.
And as usual the dialogue is just mostly consisted of people shouting at each other so far and
making rage quit posts.
I thought that's how arguments work, Chris.
Don't you know?
That's how you get to the bottom of everything.
Now I will give Cory Doctorow, the man writes, the best rage quit post of them.
This is an example for the internet on how to write an eloquent rage quit.
Really well done.
I'll keep that in my back pocket for the future.
Definitely gives the umplexed dab of approval there.
So that was a big movement story that we're following here and I think it's one of those
where we have to wait for a lot of the hype to settle too.
Yes.
Speaking of hype, speaking of hype, let's see, we're going right through the news because
I'm very, you can tell I'm excited to talk about pipeline.
Oh yeah.
So we're just busting through this stuff.
1804, speaking of hype, Ubuntu 1804.
You're ready.
You're ready already.
Oh my body's super ready.
And as you know, Popeye's good buddy Dustin Kirkland was out scouring the web to get
users feedback on what default application should be in 1804.
In fact, here's from the horse's mouth.
We asked the community across three different forums, when I posted the previous thread
about what do you want to see in 1710 to Hacker News, I immediately got emails from the editors
of both Reddit and Slashdot saying, you know, our users want to contribute to this thread
as well.
And so I said in the future we'd certainly make this, we'd open up the feedback to Reddit
and Slashdot.
And so we posted this in July and it was a coordinated effort as opposed to the first
one, which was something that we just sort of shot from the hip.
This was one that we put together.
I worked with Will Cook, who's the desktop manager at Canonical and some of his team
to put together what amounted to a survey for the desktop apps.
What desktop apps do you use on Ubuntu?
Out of curiosity, did anyone here contribute to that survey?
So Dustin goes on to provide some of the data that people suggested for default applications
in 1804 and you might be shocked, I say shocked at the conclusion.
Desktop users like to use the same old boring crap that they've always liked to use.
It seems overwhelmingly the data revealed that people would like to see Firefox as the
default web browser, Thunderbird is the default email client, VLC is the default video and
music player, LibreOffice is the default office suite, geedit as the default text editor,
and Nautilus as the default file manager.
Everybody shocked because they also would like to see Gnome Terminal as the terminal
emulator, GIMP is the image editor, Pigeon is the chat messenger, Gnome Calendar, etc.
Now, not too surprising, I was a little disappointed in the VLC on this whole list and Thunderbird
a bit, but VLC mostly because it feels like a list of people that are stuck in the mud.
Sorry, but Gnome MPV clearly better.
Anyways, moving on from that, perhaps realizing that the vast majority of people taking the
survey had no taste.
I'm totally kidding.
I'm teasing.
VLC is great.
I use it.
I mean, it's totally fine.
Yeah, I use it as well, but it's kind of frustrating that we can't have something you might love
and share some respect.
I would prefer to have Chrome.
I would prefer to have Gnome MPV.
But Gnome MPV seems like an even stronger argument to me because we should also be excited
and we don't want to hype and we want to still love on VLC, but there's a cool new open source
option that maybe people aren't hearing about or don't consider.
So to this end, this means Dustin says that they are investigating a potential approach
to make Ubuntu desktop experience perhaps a little bit more like choose your own adventure
where you could plug in the different applications you want.
That's pretty probably out there, but it is something they're considering is maybe in
the future you'll just plug in Gnome MPV and plug in Vim and Emacs for all the things.
Poppy, you were sitting in the room there, I saw your magnificent head a few times.
Is there anything, any takeaways from that talk that Dustin had that you wanted to share
with the class?
Yeah, I think one of the things you've got to be aware of is a lot of people don't actually
use desktop email clients or desktop music players.
A lot of people use the cloud for their calendar and everything.
So I mean, the graph was a long tale.
He showed graphs of how many people responded to each of those categories.
And yeah, sure enough, Thunderbird was on the far left hand side and a very tall graph.
But there are a ton of people who just wrote Google or Google Calendar because their calendaring
is synced to their phone and is done in the browser.
And similarly, there are a bunch of people who use Spotify for their music or Pandora
or something else.
There's a significantly sized trend of people who just don't use desktop applications for
doing their daily stuff and the vast majority of it is done in the browser.
Look at a Chromebook.
The vast majority of people who use Chromebooks are perfectly happy and can listen to music
and can look at their calendar.
They just don't use big fat applications to do it.
Yeah, I did notice that.
There was a very long tale.
Just about everything you could imagine or name was on there to some degree.
And to your point about GNOME MPV, I think a sizable proportion of the open source community
had no idea that exists, like VLC is in everyone's head, the stupid little icon that everybody
recognizes that everyone has fondness at Christmas when it's got snow and a hat on it.
That's what GNOME MPV needs to compete and really take over.
Right.
Yeah, that's what you need.
You need a comedy icon is what you need for your application.
But I think a significant people just don't know GNOME MPV exists and don't realize that
it may or may not be better than VLC because VLC for many years has been the go to application
for that.
Yeah.
And if you're coming from Windows, too, it's much more likely to be something used on Windows.
It's probably easy.
Oh, shoot, great.
It's got VLC.
Woo.
My favorite was the guy who replied for every single application category, Emacs, except
text editor.
Vim is for the text editor, yeah.
One of the things that was actually just side note, too, really kind of interesting is not
only was it obvious a lot of people were doing software as a service, but Rhythmbox was surprisingly
well represented in the data, which-
Interesting.
Yeah, that surprised me a little bit, but I'm trying to...
There was one pop-in.
You might remember what it was where, oh, it was VLC actually, wasn't it?
Nobody was really using Totem, even though Totem was the default out of the box in Ubuntu
desktop.
Most people switched to VLC, which was sort of an unusual trend.
Yeah, I think there's a sizable number of people who just default to VLC, and that's
just what they use.
But also, we've tried to make Totem so that it can play anything.
I know the upstream developers and the people on GStreamer and Upstream Gnome have all tried
to make it as slick as possible that when Totem can't play something, it does the right
thing.
It goes and gets the right codec package or whatever, and it should.
But sometimes that fails, and people have got it ingrained in their head that when Totem
fails, I install VLC.
And I think it's got to the point where people preemptively install VLC just to avoid having
that situation.
It works.
Yeah, yeah.
VLC, MPV, I have the codecs built in automatically and you don't have to worry about it.
I haven't actually tried Totem in a couple of years solely because every time I tried
it, it was like, hey, you want to install this thing?
No, I'll just install another application.
Yeah.
That whole thing, years and years ago, I remember when I used to run Windows before Linux came
along.
There was all these little special packages of codecs that you would install and you'd
get these codec packs from here and a codec pack from there.
And then when I moved to Linux, there was still like, oh, you got to go and get this
codec pack and you got to get I just never do any of that anymore.
It's just not a thing.
And I'm frankly surprised that people still consider the fact that one distro ships codecs
over another one that doesn't is still a thing as well, because, you know, I just never install
it.
And I, you know, view some ropey, dodgy MP4 and strangely encoded stuff all over the place
and it all just works.
So maybe that's a solved problem.
I think it is.
We should certainly be grateful anyway.
The whole talk's pretty good.
It's a little like a little bit of getting inside the head of the semi silent majority
that runs Linux.
It's not like the total silent majority because they obviously fill out the survey.
But it was over 10,000 respondents across multiple sites.
It was a huge one of the number one threads on Hacker News for a long time.
So you got quite a bit of data.
They did some language processing against it, did a lot of reading.
And Dustin just does like a high level overview of what some of the team has pulled out.
And that video is embedded in the show notes.
If you'd like to watch the whole thing and get inside the head of the average Linux user
or quote unquote, I don't know about average because they're on Hacker News and other sites.
But maybe your typical DevOps, IT, sysadmin, cloud worker, what do we call these people
that they're trying to target these days?
That category of user, that's who they got to hear from.
So if I were a System76 or a Dell or an Intraware, I think I'd be watching that talk by Dustin
and just getting a little insight into what the users are doing with the system once you
ship it.
All right.
We got to talk about pipeline.
Well, we'll get into why I think it's going to be great.
Let's take a moment right here and thank Linux Academy for sponsoring the show.
Go to linuxacademy.com slash unplug to support the show and sign up for a free seven day
trial.
And that's sweet because you can kick the tires and get an idea of what the platform
is capable of.
It's a full featured training library with everything you need to learn new skills and
advance your career.
Self-paced in-depth video courses on every Linux cloud and DevOps topic with hands on
scenario based labs give you real experience and confidence to work with it.
Stream paths, which are a series of courses and content planned by instructors for a career
track you're trying to get into, human beings when you need them, which is unique and great
for an online platform like this, exams and practice quizzes and things like that to get
you ready for the test.
And they also have certification training, which are courses that are created specifically
to prepare you for the exam.
One of my favorite features is you choose your distribution.
The courseware matches that and the cloud servers that they spin up for you on demand
when you need them and then you can SSH into to work all match.
And they have nuggets when you're busy, they have course schedulers when you need to stick
to a time when you're just crazy busy, like maybe you're going to New York or something
like that.
They got course schedules for that.
It's great.
It's one of my favorite features.
And also I loaded up their iOS app on the old iPad and tried that out on the road trip.
That seems very convenient.
Yeah.
I'm excited about that.
If you want to sign up for a free seven day trial and a big thank you to Linux Academy
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
So PipeWire, a game changer in Linux multimedia possibly.
I'm very, very excited to, I'm going to say Wim.
Is that how you say your first name?
Wim Tamus?
How do you say it?
Give me your whole name.
I sound like a jackass.
It's pronounced Wim Tiamans.
Okay.
And you're going by W-Tay here in the mumble room.
So thank you for joining us, Wim.
It's great to chat with you.
I'm glad to be here.
I've been kind of tangently covering PipeWire, but I don't really, obviously I don't know
much about it because it's so new.
So could you kind of give the audience a basic overview of what PipeWire is?
Because a lot of them are going to be familiar with things like Gstreamer, PulseAudio and
those types of technologies, but I don't think they're familiar with PipeWire yet.
Yeah.
So it's a new attempt to try to combine the good things that you can find in Gstreamer
and in Jack and a bit in PulseAudio and also in the CRAS audio server.
That's a Chromium audio server.
So yeah, it's kind of like Gstreamer, but different, built differently.
So there's plugins that is more like modeled around real-time plugins, the kinds that you
find like in lots power LV2, they do very little, but they are very, you can achieve
very low latency with them, stuff like that.
Let me ask you, let me double check to see if I'm tracking you.
So essentially PipeWire is eventually a replacement for PulseAudio and it would also be a video
pipeline or API that applications could use to make sound or get sound or create video
or send video?
Yeah.
So to understand that you have to think a bit about the history.
So at first I wanted to write video sharing or video camera using Gstreamer.
So using a multimedia framework to do these things, which worked.
It was called PulseVideo.
But then I started to think, okay, I can do audio with this as well.
There is no reason why I couldn't do that.
And then I started to think, okay, I could start to do something like PulseAudio.
I could write it in Gstreamer, but then I started to bump against limitations such as
low latency, which were difficult to achieve.
So then I set out to build something better that is still a multimedia framework that
would allow me to build these things like PulseAudio and I'm also targeting Jack.
Yeah.
And the plugin aspect, I don't want to chat more about, but I guess to kind of keep with
the background here, is it also a major factor in this Wayland and applications sharing audio
and video inside a sandboxed Wayland world?
Yes.
So exactly.
Well, currently all video applications that capture from a camera, they directly access
your device, video zero.
So from a sandbox point of view, you just have to make that node visible to the sandbox
with zero security.
So any app can just open the camera and start capturing whatever you're doing.
So you need some way to move that outside of the sandbox, which we've already done with
PulseAudio.
There's a demon running outside of the sandbox.
The sandbox goes to the demon to access the device and we implement policies to restrict
what you can do.
So we need something similar for video.
So you need to have a demon sitting there that accesses the camera and restricts who
can do what with it.
So that is one aspect to make this work in a sandbox world, we need a demon that sits
there and does the control of access, which we don't have for video at all.
So this is the first priority that PipeWire was built.
So if we didn't have something like PipeWire in the Wayland universe, you would have exclusive
application access to say the webcam and then no other application would be able to get
access.
Am I tracking that?
Yes.
Well, if you're doing a demon that controls access to the camera, you can start implementing
share.
That makes sense.
Okay.
All right.
Yeah, that does make sense.
So let's talk a little bit about the difference between this and GStreamer because if I'm
understanding you, it does support GStreamer audio plugins to an extent for the audio capabilities
and plugins, but it's not GStreamer.
So there is a plugin system, which is way, way, way more low level than GStreamer plugins.
So yeah, it's really more low level, you have to do everything yourself, the memory management
of the buffers and all of that.
And on top of that is actually the PipeWire layer on top of that, that does all the negotiation
and manages these plugins.
So it's not exactly like GStreamer, which is one big, because it's everything.
I would like a little clarification.
I've heard discussion around PipeWire about getting latency down on the audio in Linux
for recording purposes and mixing purposes.
Is that a goal of PipeWire?
And can you talk a bit about that?
Yeah, absolutely.
So currently the only thing that is reasonably low latency on Linux is Jack.
So the way Jack works is very to the point, I would say.
It's very efficient, the way it's implemented, but it's also very insecure.
You can't really use it in a sound box.
It has a huge, it has 100 megabytes, sorry, yeah, something like that, a huge file in
shared memory that is mapped by all applications where you actually have the whole data exchange
happen.
So any client can look at anything else from everything else.
You can actually write in that memory and destroy it.
Oh, wow.
Yeah, that's pretty interesting.
Yeah, from a security point of view, that doesn't work, but it's very efficient.
But essentially the way it works is you get your sound card, there's a sample ready, and
then it does a few texts, it wakes up an application, and from the shared memory, the application
can immediately read the memory, process it, and put it in another piece of shared memory
where the daemon then picks it out and plays it back again.
So there is super, super low latency there to compare that, for example, with pulse audio.
It has the same kind of wake-up mechanism, but then it goes through different threads
to signal applications, then it goes through another thread, which lots of data structures
goes back to the server where it gets picked up, gets a copy, and then it gets copied and
stuff like that.
So it's a bit less efficient and it is not exactly, you can't achieve the same kind of
low latency.
It's also not designed for doing these things that Jack does.
Like Jack, it wakes up every two milliseconds, let's say, and all the applications that are
part of the graph, they get woken up, they do their little thing, so it's like lockstep,
every two milliseconds something gets done.
I see.
Yeah.
That is fascinating insight.
That explains a lot of the audio end.
Can you talk a bit about, for my personal interest, I'm curious more about the video
end.
Is this a means to an end to efficient video-accelerated GPU-decoded video?
Is that part of Pipewire or could be part of Pipewire in the future?
Yeah.
That is definitely something that I want to do eventually, but currently that is pretty
well handled by Gstream as well.
Ah, okay.
Okay.
Yeah.
So in the future, will Gstreamer then be able to leverage Pipewire?
So currently I have a couple of Gstreamer elements where you can get data from a Pipewire instance
and send data to a Pipewire instance, so there is a communication mechanism there.
You can upload stuff and download stuff, and that works with compressed formats video.
So when do we start seeing this land in our Linux distros near us?
When does this stuff actually start shipping?
So currently it's in Fedora 27, so we will be shipping Fedora 27.
The idea is to use this for screen capture.
So there is a bit of stuff going on behind the scenes to get this working with the screen
capture.
There's a portal API to start it, and then what basically happens is that the GNOME Shell
mutter creates a new Pipewire stream, which is basically the screen as it is being rendered,
that you can then fetch from several different programs.
So you can start a program, for example, to stream this to a remote desktop, or make an
RTSP server, or encode it to a file or something like that.
I am very excited about that functionality, and that's going to give us remote desktop
on Wayland, which I am really thrilled about, because it's been a number one complaint,
I'd say, by the audience when they talk about switching to Wayland.
Audience, Reddit, everywhere.
That's a great feature that Pipewire is going to bring.
I know Eric in our mumble room had a question for you, Wim.
Eric, do you want to...
Go ahead.
Yeah, among other things that I do for a living, I'm actually an audio and video engineer,
and I'm just curious as to how...
If this would be one of the goals, perhaps the ability to do multi-track audio recording,
say via USB or something.
I mean, I have the same mixer that Chris does if they're in the studio, and it's capable
of doing 32 tracks in and out via USB.
Is that something that this could maybe one day be capable of?
Yeah, that's one of the goals, yeah.
Excellent.
That should be.
That's great.
It's going to be a beautiful Linux multimedia future.
That is really great, Wim.
Is there anything else you want to mention about Pipewire before we chug along?
I could talk on for hours, but you'll have to watch my talks in the conferences that
are coming up.
Okay, very good.
I will keep an eye out.
I will also have a link to the blog post about the Pipewire launch, too, that people can
check out to read more about it.
So that's a really exciting, Wim.
Thank you very much for joining us and talking a little about it.
I look forward to watching this develop.
Yeah, definitely.
All right, thank you.
Now, we have many things to do today in the show, so I have something very near and dear
to my heart that I want to talk about.
This is a good one for me.
This is a good last episode, because I was really looking forward to talking about Pipewire,
and this next thing, it wasn't really going to be a show topic, and then, I don't know,
something just switched on in this morning in my head, and now it has to be.
So let's take a moment and thank DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
And thank you for visiting DigitalOcean.
And then you use our promo code.
You use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
It's one word you apply to your account after you've created the account, and then you get
a $10 credit over at DigitalOcean.
And keep your eye out, because very soon, DigitalOcean, a little birdie tells me they'll
be rolling out object storage.
Very, very soon.
I was just playing with that beta.
Were you?
Yeah.
Nice.
They turned it on for me, too, so I could play with it.
It's a lot of fun.
DigitalOcean's always added new features.
So they recently added load balancing as a service, and monitoring, and metric performance
monitoring.
They've also done what they call cloud firewalls.
It's actually pretty brilliant, because instead of you doing the firewall at your machine,
they apply the firewall rules at the network layer, so the packets never even make it to
your machine.
They have lightning fast networking, too, 40 gigabit connections coming to those hypervisors.
They run Linux on those things.
They run KVM for the virtualizer.
Data centers all over the world.
Load balancing as a service, pre-built open source applications ready to deploy, and pricing
that's going to blow your mind.
Look at how affordable this is.
For $5 a month, you could run that rig.
And with our $10 credit, you get it two months free.
My favorite system is $0.03 an hour for 2 gigs of RAM, 2 CPUs, 40 gigabytes of SSD,
because it's all SSDs, and 3 terabytes of transfer.
And you know what's crazy, Wes?
It's a lot of really good stuff, and I haven't even mentioned the dashboard yet.
What?
You haven't even mentioned that?
No.
You haven't even mentioned the game features.
I know.
Dashboard for days.
It's because it's so easy to use.
You kind of forget about it.
It is.
And they also have that API, which we've now built bots around and stuff, which is really
well-documented, easy, straightforward to use.
It's been great for us.
DigitalOcean.com.
Go over there, create your account, and then use our promo code of absolute power and knowledge,
DO Unplugged.
That's one word.
DO Unplugged over at DigitalOcean.com.
And a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Okay.
So, I want to talk about something that is not a totally new topic to this show, but
I do think it's a pretty big problem.
But I want to set a couple of ground rules, some disclosures up front.
I'm not talking about any one particular person.
I'm not talking about any one particular business.
This is a bigger problem than any one person or business or company or media outlet.
I'm sorry, Chris.
Thank you.
And it's something that I'm personally very invested in because I've followed the Linux
news for 11 years, very closely, every week, reading and analyzing it.
I cover it in a lot of my shows.
And so watching this has been, it's actually taken a toll a bit because of something very
special about the open source community.
More than ever, I really feel like the quote unquote open source media or Linux journalism
has taken a nosedive of quality, specifically in the written medium, but also with some
of the media outlets too.
Just really gotten bad.
There's fewer and fewer reporters that are actually going to a story, that are creating
new content.
And what's mostly happening now, because it's easy and good business, is we have lazy virtue
signaling clickbait journalism that touches on people's emotional buttons and gets people
fired up and sharing content and retweeting and thumbing down or thumbing up, either way,
angry and happy.
And it works so well.
It works so well, you see it all over the place.
It's media everywhere.
It's not just a Linux problem.
But I believe in the open source community, it has devastating consequences.
I think it murders people's passion and energy to contribute.
And we all know that a large reason why people contribute to open source is because it's
a passion project, or why people go out on a limb and advocate in their commercial company
to be a member of the open source community, to work upstream.
It takes a passion to be willing to take that risk.
So when the tone of conversation is mostly discourse based around toxic straw man arguments,
that the bar has been set by this bottom feeding media, who's not creating anything new.
That's the most offensive thing.
They're not making anything new.
They're creating discussion about the discussion.
This community, the open source community, is a worldwide community of developers of
different cultures, creating different projects for different reasons, coming together to
make something amazing, and predominantly the conversation in the open source media
space is discussion about the discussion.
Things to get people riled up and excited, virtue signaling.
And I think it's devastating in the open source community.
And what's really troubling to me is it's getting worse.
And there's less and less actual quote unquote journalists going to these events and covering
events or going to communities and finding out what they're making.
And I will use us as an example for a moment here, but look at the projects that have come
on the show over the last 215 episodes.
They generally do really well afterwards, not because of this, some magical effect of
the show, but because they connect with our audience and they express what their goals
are and their intentions.
And our audience likes that they buy into their ideas and it doesn't, it's not about
the show, it becomes about the project and that project grows and they get contributors
and they get mouth, word of mouth.
It creates something, it contributes something to the open source community.
But this diverse of click bait, emotional button pushing, bottom feeding journalism
that we have now does the opposite.
It's devastating.
So this is my rant.
This is my rant.
And I always, I've made this case before, I've made this case before, and I'm not done
making it.
So now I'm going to, I'm going to just going to, I'm going to call out some names and I'm
going to give you some examples right now on the show because this is a problem that
is getting worse and apparently not talking about it enough hasn't done anything and not
calling out names hasn't done anything.
So we're going to get to that next.
I solemnly swear by my oath as a crime fighter that this outrage will not go un-avenged.
I want to thank Ting, go to linux.ting.com and sign up for the nation's best mobile coverage.
What a company, linux.ting.com.
Go there to experience really incredible customer service, pay for what you want wireless, $6
a month for your minutes, your messages and your megabytes, no contracts nor the termination
fees.
Again, another fantastic, wonderful dashboard.
It's like people are starting to get this.
It's mobile how it should be done.
I hear that from people outside the US all the time.
They have a GSM and CDMA network.
You pick your device, you make it work.
Oh, you're going to get yourself the new internet phone or the new Samsung or the new Pixel,
whatever.
It doesn't matter.
Ting don't care.
Just make sure it's compatible.
Check their BYOD page, pop in a SIM, you're good to go.
You want to grab one from Ting directly?
No probs.
Check it out.
Go to linux.ting.com.
You'll get $25 off your first device or $25 in service credit if you bring a compatible
device, linux.ting.com.
Thanks to Ting for sponsoring the show, linux.ting.com.
Yes, sir.
And none of that was clickbait.
It's all true.
It is true.
It is all true.
I'm going to be using Ting all the way across the nation.
Tried and tested.
So I generally have a lot of respect for Matthew Garrett, but I'm going to start here because
this is the beginning of a beast right here.
And it is a disgusting, grotesque aspect of the Linux community, and it's perfectly displayed
right here.
So Matthew Garrett tweets on the 23rd of July, 2013, sitting on a plane watching Jim Zimlin
use OS X.
So he's shaming the head of the Linux Foundation back in 2013.
Four years later, this is September 10th, 2017, four years later, at Jim Zimlin is still
rocking an iPad and doing his slides under Mac OS X.
This starts a cascade of shit, including people jumping in, hocking hardware, hocking open
Seuss.
But it develops then into a series of YouTube videos and Reddit posts where people get clickbait,
and itsfoss.com posted this, Linux Foundation head calls 2017 year of the Linux desktop
while running Apple's Mac OS himself.
And takes shots at Jim throughout the entire article.
He even says here in the ITFoss article, perhaps I'm creating unnecessary controversy.
Perhaps this is simple, should be ignored.
This thing that we do is gross because it's shaming people for their choices.
And it wouldn't be accepted in thousands of other contexts in our daily lives.
But when it comes to picking a Mac or Windows, and we're Linux users, all of a sudden we
get to shame.
If they were Jews, we couldn't say these things.
If they were black, we wouldn't be saying these things.
If they chose to have bisexual sex, we wouldn't be saying these things.
If a man wanted to become a woman, we wouldn't be saying these things.
But because Jim runs a Mac, it's okay to publicly shame him.
Now I happen to know there's people in this mumble room right now, shocker, they're not
using Linux.
You're going to call them out, aren't you?
That's what's going to happen next.
Watch out.
But what really gets me is someone sees Jim on an airplane and he's using an iPad.
Well, depending on the day you saw me, you might see me editing video on my Macbook.
Because guess what?
PipeWire isn't shipping yet.
So I use a Macbook to edit my videos.
Now I own three laptops, only one of them is a Mac.
The other two run Linux.
But if you saw me that day on my Mac, you might tweet out, oh, just saw Chris Fisher
had a Jupiter broadcast and using a Mac.
What a dick.
Well, you know, Chris, all the shows are edited on a Mac too.
Yeah, we are.
We are just a bunch of heretics.
Trying to sabotage Linux from within.
Yeah, we're Mac lovers trying to pretend to be like Linux.
So with no information, with no quotes from Jim.
Right, this is not an interview discussing like, you know, maybe he feels the same way
about it, we don't know.
Maybe he has two Linux desktops at home and just prefers to have a Macbook for a laptop.
Because guess who else does that?
Linus Torvalds.
Maybe he has a Macbook running Linux.
Well, I mean, even if he's running Mac or Windows.
But the point is, or an iPad, at what point do we stop shaming?
When does that not become an acceptable thing to shame someone for a choice they made because
that tool works for them?
Not everybody takes this as a religious thing.
I mean, that's a good point.
But also the fact that there's literally no evidence whatsoever that it's even true and
people went off on like on Crazy Train to yell at him for something they have no idea.
And every single time someone does it, they always like, well, you know, I couldn't get
it confirmed or anything, but I'm going to go still go off on a tangent and yell at this
guy.
He's using a Mac up on stage.
And I am not arguing that the optics of this look bad.
Like get a loaner laptop running Linux and go up there.
Of course, then there would be headlines, head of Linux Foundation prefers Fedora, head
of Linux Foundation prefers OpenSUSE.
So then there would be those headlines, but they would be at least of a different caliber.
So I agree that the optics look bad.
However, the Linux Foundation is not a Linux desktop advocacy group.
Wake up, everybody.
That's not what they're there for.
That's not where they have members like VMware.
They're not there for the desktop, OK?
They're there for the business.
Microsoft.
Right.
Microsoft is more of a Linux desktop advocacy company than the Linux Foundation is, though,
because Microsoft makes Visual Studio code, for God's sakes.
And they make other applications for Linux.
The Linux Foundation is a business representation of Linux and that arm.
And they do they fund other projects that do good work, like the Core Infrastructure
Initiative.
And if you go to these conferences, like the camera that's pointing at Jim, if you turned
that camera around and took a picture of the audience, it would I would be willing to take
a rough best 70 to 80 percent MacBooks in that audience.
The rest would be mostly Lenovo's and Dell's and the half of them would be running Windows.
So Linux is a minority at these conferences.
Don't kid yourself.
And the the idea here that people have to pass some sort of purity test.
And we all love to take a shot at our at our authority figures in Linux.
So everybody got a shot at the Linux Foundation.
We got to take them down a notch, got to take Jim down a notch.
So everybody feels really good about that.
And Jim passed our purity test.
So now we all get the virtue signal about that.
And we're all feeling pretty good right now.
It's gross.
And it doesn't get anything done.
That's the part that stands out to me.
Or we're not like what are the reasons he can't use Linux on his desktop if there are
some.
Those are things we maybe we should be talking about and figuring out how to how to make
that better.
And isn't the mechanics of this interesting?
It starts with like if you think about it, the very origins of this are gross.
Matthew Garrett, they're publicly shaming.
He's Mac shaming someone.
And then he does it years later again on his Twitter feed.
And then you have YouTubers and bloggers who then try to get clicks off of it.
And none of them have a single poll quote from Jim.
It's remarkable.
It is the bottom feeding journalism that is suffocating the dialogue in the open source
community.
It makes us spin and chase our own tails.
And it lowers the starting point of the conversation.
And you can say, well, Chris, it's just about filtering the news that you take in.
It's just about making sure that you pick the right sources.
The problem is the dialogue in at a at a at a wider, higher level is getting set low.
The bar is getting set low.
It doesn't matter what source you're getting it from the conversation.
Just look at the big things that have happened to Linux recently or go back to system D.
It's eating us up and it's it's it's something that I feel like I am almost powerless to
solve because, like I said, it's bigger than one person and it's bigger than one company.
And I think about the amount of people that go to these events and cover these events
and it's it's painfully small.
Regular Linux journalists who go to like Gwadek or they don't go to that, but say they go
to DebConf or the open source summit or something.
It's four or five people and two of them work at Jupiter Broadcasting.
I'm serious.
It does make it hard to have like a diverse, you know, network of of coverage.
The only thing I can figure to try to fix this is to compete at a at a level that makes
clickbait journalism not as appealing and makes them have to compete.
And I don't know how to get there.
And my thought is starting to go to things like the Ubuntu rally or going at talking
to projects as as things are being developed and spotlighting them on the show is maybe
a way to do that.
Go to the story.
You know, when I when I think of this Ubuntu rally, I don't think of it so much as an Ubuntu
event as I do about going to a large person, a large company in the community who's at
an interesting transition right now, learning how they work, how they interact with the
community, networking with people and using that to influence and give insight into my
future commentary.
Right.
You get a different view of this that you can you can share.
And it's it is it is a type of it is a type of perspective that you don't get by just
sitting in front of your crappy YouTube set up and blabbing your mouth or throwing up
some cheap post on a blog somewhere, hoping that you get a few ad clicks off of it.
And the the cost of doing it is substantially greater.
And the time it takes is substantially higher and more.
So it seems like an impossible fight.
And it I you know, you have to go by my word that I hear over and over again.
In fact, it's one of the things I hear the most is people burn out because of it and
they they give up.
And it's it's it's it's people that if I said their names, it would shock you.
And it's people that you've never heard of before.
It's the whole frickin spectrum.
And I know it's a real problem.
And I hear a lot about it.
And I feel powerless to do anything about it.
And it feels like it's getting worse, like we're slipping deeper and deeper into this
shitty clickbait abyss.
Yeah, it's it's awful and there's the hate that people send about all kinds of different
things like the canonical hate for no reason.
But and there are other companies that are doing something similar that it gets no attention
whatsoever.
Yet, you know, other companies just get hate regardless if they just open their mouth.
Like why?
Why do you need to hate someone for making open source software?
Even if you don't want to use it, shouldn't you appreciate the work they're putting out
there for you?
Yeah, we covered it.
We covered an intense story in Kota Radio this week that just went out a couple days
ago or yesterday.
Well, I just wanted to clear up something I looked up.
I'm looking since this entire thing started, I've been trying to find any evidence whatsoever
that this is even true.
It's not true.
Are you sure?
You can like see a picture of it or something like that.
There's not a you can go on the YouTube channel.
They don't they don't show what you're kidding me what slides there are.
There's no photos whatsoever.
I couldn't find a single photo.
Right.
And none of these articles I've seen have a photo of it either.
No, I saw someone had a stock photo of a MacBook as if that's proof or something.
Wow.
But every single one of them are referencing each other in a cycle of cyclicals, crazy,
you know, attack like the one like the its boss was referencing some YouTube channels.
The YouTube channels are referencing the Twitter.
The only thing we have is Matthew Garrett's word that it happened.
But so he took the time to make a tweet.
You're like, well, that's not a big deal.
He also took the time to find the older tweet that he made, but not the time to take a photo
to prove his statement.
Like that's kind of weird.
Yeah.
And because he's using on the plane doesn't mean he was doing it from the podium either.
That's I didn't right.
And people are blowing it up as if he didn't did it on the keynote.
You know, I think I think there I think I think there is more and more talking to rotten
made me think rotten has really well researched coverage like on his channel.
Like there are people out there that are doing like well thought out, well researched pieces.
You know, like like a lot, like our friends that went to podcast and late night Linux
and the work they do there.
Again, I feel like people that are thoughtful about it.
There is a place for that.
You know, you don't always have to be like creating something brand new or interviewing
somebody.
Like there is a place for thoughtful conversation that does add to a dialogue because, again,
it is an open source community and that's a huge part of it.
So there is a so I feel like there is more and more good stuff, but it's getting outpaced
by the click bait emotion button pushing and that there's such a template out there from
like the buzz feeds of the world on how to pull it off.
Oh, my gosh.
Just I mean, like going through for, you know, preparing for this show.
How much of that do you have to filter, cut away and just not.
And I feel like it's harder to, you know, maybe for people who haven't don't see that
much or don't follow as closely or other things.
It can be pretty confusing when you're just trying to like you look at various aggregator
sites or other things.
And once it starts being shared, those clickbait titles, I mean, if you don't know any better,
those will pull you in.
Suddenly, you've loaded their ads, you've continued, you've been in their click count.
So it can be hard to like actually signal that you're not interested in it.
It's funny is that you're mentioning about the whole researching like the people who
research their topics and stuff that I've actually when I first saw this last week,
I was like, I'm making a video about this, although I'm going to research and make sure
what I say is that I have like another day or two before it's going to be released because
I still have some things I want to make sure that I'm correct about.
But so far, through all the research I've found I've looked through, there's not a single
reference of any kind to have any proof whatsoever.
Here's an idea.
Why doesn't somebody just email the guy and ask?
Yeah, that's what I was wondering.
I mean, if that was him, I wouldn't answer anyway, because it would just create like
an extra like him denying and people are like, how could you deny something that we know
is true or something?
But I could tell you how the conversation would go with Jim if I was at one of the Linux
Foundation events where Jim's at and we're on the sidebar, I'd be like, boy, can you
believe that fucking shitstorm you got for that?
And he'd be like, yeah, that's really just unbelievable.
When you get real and you get outside your little virtue signaling bubble, you realize
people are humans.
And to him, he's sitting on a plane, guess what, the MacBook probably gets four hours
more battery life than whatever Linux laptop he was going to bring on the plane.
I mean, I hate to be the bearer of bad news, but that iPad that this time he got busted
for, probably has 11, 12 hours of battery life.
That's very freaking competitive.
And it feels like it just kind of paints a bad image of desktop Linux users, especially
in that world that's so dominated by servers.
You're like, well, look, here's this weird, strange internet culture.
They're not making money.
They're not like, it's not part of the same class of people and here they are being dicks
to me.
Why do I care about that?
I'm just going to stay in the world I know.
I had a really interesting...
Oh, go ahead.
There's also an argument of like, well, he's running something that he could be using it
to learn more about the thing he's using so that he can convince people why this is better
than this.
If you have no reference, how can you say something is better than something you've
never tried?
So he could be saying like, maybe he has Windows machines and Mac things and he's just using
them for like, well, he's doing a presentation on a plane.
That's not like it's his main primary desktop or anything.
Yeah.
Although people are saying that in articles, of course.
Well, you got to jump to conclusions to make it worth clicking, I guess.
So Swampy, he's one of the journalists that actually goes out there and actually goes
to the story.
I just kind of speak to those people and he has a YouTube channel now and he had a topic
on it recently that, oh, oh.
So it came across our YouTube recommended and it's a totally, for me, I don't even think
about it.
I'm trying to, I can't find it right now, but it was to me like a totally normal title
and it was stop converting users to Linux and migrate them to Linux instead.
It's a pretty good time and it's, you know, it's done pretty well for him.
But Hadia saw that and she goes, wait a minute, is this, this is legitimately the conversation
we had last night.
So, and I think it's related to this.
She says, is this, is this converting everybody to Linux thing?
Is this something more than just Noah?
Like, I thought that was just a Noah thing.
I'm like, no.
She's like, so is that a normal thing for you people to talk about?
Like not, you know, like that kind of, that's a little creepy.
I'm like, what?
She's like, you don't think it's weird that you guys talk about converting people to Linux?
That sounds like a religion.
Yeah.
Like religious undertones.
And I'm like, oh yeah, I, yeah, I guess it, I guess it does have a religious undertone,
doesn't it?
Like you're, you're converting and we do or, or very culty and we very, very frequently
talk about that.
Evangelist is a common title and there's, I've never, ever said church of neon ever.
We all do it.
And it's because, you know, we all, we want to advocate and we think it can actually help.
And a lot of us probably have personality types where we're sort of like the trend,
the technology trends that are in our social group or something like that.
So it's, it's not like it's, we're all a bunch of crazies, but to her, she, I guess she had
made the assumption that that was just, well, that's just Noah because he's crazy passionate
about Linux.
And she was, which is a fine assumption for a few moments.
She was creeped out by it.
And then I explained to her, it's like, well, you know, when you discover something you
think is really great, you kind of evangelize it.
And she's like, well, you just said evangelize, okay, I'm digging a hole here.
You know, she got to, in her business, she runs two Linux computers, but it's not about,
it's not about the license or the, or, you know, because she likes unity or Matei it's,
it's because it's just practical for her.
And I think it's all kind of like, we get kind of swept up in this, like I said, morality
testing and things like that, and we don't even really realize what we're doing and we,
we jump into shaming and attacking.
Yes.
Right.
Instead of pointing out things like, Hey, look, Linux can do this better in some cases.
A lot of the dialogue ends up focused being on like, Windows is garbage and here's why.
And when they're like, well, no, but Windows works fine and it has these, you know, it
doesn't, it doesn't feel like a full debate.
That's right where we're back at with this.
I've now got two stories, one in an email and I think one in the haircare discord channel
from a listener who has heard me kind of talk about this a bit on the pre-show last week.
And he said, I came to Linux Fest Northwest to see you guys to kind of get more about
Linux been thinking about switching.
I have an old Mac book, which I brought with me and I got harassed by people in the booths,
not by people at Linux Fest, but people behind the booths.
Like somebody was giving him a hard time for bringing a Mac and he felt shamed and I kind
of lost my enthusiasm to switch.
Two people told me that they got a hard time at Linux Fest Northwest.
It was totally the opposite atmosphere that we could want or imagine.
And Linux Fest Northwest is always so cool.
It's just such a cool, chill place.
Like of all walks.
Welcoming.
Yeah, exactly.
And to be fair, how often have we commented on one of the shows that how many Mac books
are showing up at LinuxCon?
Yeah.
I know we are not, we are not innocent here because especially back in my switcher days
when I was, when I was really aggressively trying to get people off of Windows and I
did consider myself an evangelist.
Now I'm more like a, I'm like a, like a, like a, I'm like, what's a converted evangelist
who's now just like, I practice the faith, but I'm cool if you don't want to practice
the faith.
I don't know what you call that, but that's the kind of Linux user I find myself to be
these days.
You show off that Linux works great for you, but you don't pressure others.
You're not, yeah.
I think that's a bit of the shaming a bit feels like insecurity about it.
Like you're insecure that for some reason the guy that runs the Linux Foundation needs
to use an iPad.
I think you see the same like with programming languages or anything like that, right?
Like you, you worry because you're thinking like, well, it clearly works for them.
They must think it's so much better.
Yeah.
So what about the devil's advocate position?
Like, so right.
And what about this?
What if, uh, what if, um, you know, a different CEO of a different company, I guess, cause
that's not really fair because it's a foundation.
It depends on the company.
Someone would just automatically get a password regardless of what they do.
But the Linux Foundation doesn't make a product.
They're a foundation.
Part of this whole thing is the nebulous connection between Linux and the Linux Foundation and
Linux just is a kernel also.
So it's all kind of like it's the company model is there to be easier to say yes or
no.
That makes sense.
Or yeah, it's more of a, they're an advocacy group, so that's why you're not really doing
very good advocacy.
Right.
Yes.
I mean, they are because they're, they're showing that they're willing to use the things
that other people are using and can show, like, you know, show them that they're not
like creating this leadism or anything.
But there's another thing I thought of was funny that the same people who would bash
him for using an iPad are the same people who say that Android is not Linux or anything.
So like, as far as tablet go, there is no right answer.
Not yet.
I think there was a new replicant release this week.
That might be the.
What are you going to say, Bjerg?
What if you saw, you know, chairman member and former CEO Bill Gates using a MacBook
at his charity events?
Well, that's, that would be more.
I'd give him a high five.
That would be more surprising.
But again, the Linux Foundation isn't like making an operating system directly.
They finance Linus and Linus uses a MacBook and nobody gives shit one about that.
It's only because, because we like to take a pop at our authority figures, but not our
cult leaders.
Like our cultural icons, they could, they can pick their toes and they can run MacBooks
and we're good.
But if you are an authority figure, well, then you are, you're an open target and we're
just going to take a few, a few shots because we hate you apparently as far as the super
double standard.
The Bill Gates and the Steve Jobs interview, joint interview proved that they hated each
other.
Of course.
Yeah.
That was a good interview.
See, I think it would be different too.
Right?
Like Bill Gates, much less attached to Microsoft.
I don't think I would think anything of it.
Now if like Sacha was doing it while they were trying to launch the next line of Windows
phones, I'd be like, well, you can do whatever you want, but that's probably bad marketing
for your company.
Or Tim Cook using an Android.
Yeah.
That would be crazy.
And that would be, you know, that would be hard for them to explain it for.
My argument would be like, if you have like, let's, especially the phones, cause the phone's
the easiest one.
Let's say you have, you're a developer for some kind of platform and you have the other
phones that you carry around to test things and to make sure that they like to see that
it's true interactions with different features.
In fact, you almost hope they do do that sometimes actually have references to see what does,
what works and what doesn't and things like that.
Like that would be a reasonable thing.
I mean, if he was going onto like a Mac, an Apple stage or announcing the iPhone pulling
out a Samsung or something, that would be weird.
But just having it in general is kind of ridiculous that people are freaking out.
I feel like anybody that wants to criticize Jim and they're welcome to do it, but what
they should do first, if they don't want to be a D bag is they should pack up their laptop.
They should take a long flight.
They should try to prepare for a presentation in front of thousands and thousands of people
because it's also streamed and released on YouTube and a stand up there and give a presentation
about whatever the hell Jim talked about and then you can criticize them for using an iPad
or a Mac book.
I really, I mean, at the end of the day, we really have to come to the understanding that
for the majority of people that are going to use Linux ever, it's just a tool.
It is an ends to a means and many of them will never even know it is Linux and that
is the reality of our world and it's one that we've discussed before.
It's one that Linus, we've read his quotes, he thinks it's great.
That's what it is.
And especially in the business space.
Definitely don't care.
Yeah.
It kind of feels like it goes a little bit back to that, like the GPL enforcement questions
and like the writings Greg had on that and just about, you know, like if we come off
as this really aggressive, mean, super opinionated community, then it's really easy to see that
and not all the value here and instead of like, you know, we're all trying to push for
more open source, more DRM free things, all of this and a lot of times it's not the popular
opinion, so we need to be seen as nice people and so that we can have a reasonable discussion
with others and be like, look, we're not saying that you need this, but here's why it causes
us a problem.
Well, why can't we just have the tone, you know, a little more chill, a little more mellow.
Everybody just be kind to each other, be nice and know that everybody's in here because
they got a certain particular itch they're trying to scratch.
They want to do it by writing code that's an expression for themselves and not every
single person has to be an advocate or an evangelist and Linux will be okay.
It will continue to grow.
It will go on and you'll still be able to log into your desktop.
Don't don't get your system in a bunch now, especially when it's system because that could
be a real mess.
So here we are.
We are hard.
We are hard up against our out time and I got to go to New York and I feel bad because
your caravan out.
Yeah.
My ride is here and Caleb is he's going to quit listening to the show.
Caleb tweeted me, punting the Gentoo challenge was funny, but now it's really irritating.
Say what you do.
He's got to quit the show now and I'm sorry, Caleb.
I'm sure you guys will get to it next week, though.
Right.
I don't know if it would be right to do it without you.
Oh, no.
I really want to find out about your Gentoo feelings.
I think Chris is trying to ditch the gender responsibility.
I will listen.
I absolutely want to get into it because I spent all that time working on it.
But the problem here is, is my ride.
I know.
And so did Wes and Caleb is really, really upset.
So I'll tell you what we're definitely going to do when I get back.
That's right.
We will for sure.
All right.
In the meantime, follow me live on my trip.
I'm leaving in just a little bit at Jupiter broadcasting dot com slash Rover.
That's also where I'll post videos at Chris Elias for the Twitter at Jupiter signal for
the network.
At Wes Payne.
And Beard, where would you like people to find you?
Twitter dot com slash Rakai LP.
Rakai LP on the Twitter.
Very good.
Thank you for joining us, you guys.
Yeah.
Come back next week when it's the Beard and I.
Join you guys.
Just you two.
I won't be here.
I hope you guys have a great show.
Be right back.
Yeah.
And all that good stuff.
We'll see you right.
Well, they will see you.
I guess not me.
They'll see you right back.
Thank you so much.
Alright, so the title should probably either be about PipeWire, which would be my inclination,
but also I like this as a title because it's true, Linux Journalism is in a Nosedive, ahhh.
Yeah.
Thank you Mumble Room, you guys were great, appreciate it very much.
Thank you Chris for having us.
We will, well they will be back very soon, I have to go soon so we should pick our title.
Well, I just want to point out that on next week's show and future shows, I should be
on my new honkin' desktop with that case I just got today.
Woo-woo!
Excellent.
Congrats.
And it's probably going to run Gen 2 10.01.
Maniac mode engaged.
Chugga chugga chugga chugga.
Gen 2!
Alright, yeah be titles, and also you can toss it in the Discord like I have if you
like for a title suggestion.
I installed Discord and I don't even know what the freaking room is.
Dev PipeWire is title number one right now, Chris hates us all, great suggestion, Popey's
porn problem.
That was good.
Did you notice how Popey just admitted to watching porn on the show?
And then he left.
That's terrible.
That's the best thing ever actually.
We should call it, pipe out the crap, pipe in the light.
Yeah.
Oh beard.
Hey Chris, what's the link to the Discord?
Discord dot me slash Jupiter colony will give you the invite link, and if you just want
to use the web app instead of the Electron, it's Discord.