So let me tell you about the, uh, before we just start, uh, actually maybe I'll save it
for the show.
I'll save it for the show.
That could be how we start the show.
Alright guys, this is Linux Unplugged episode 239 for March 6th, 2018.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's all over the world this week.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
I miss, I miss being in the same studio with you.
You know, I don't, I don't get to watch you, you know, stare at you as you talk in the,
I mean, what?
No, that definitely doesn't happen.
We'll be reunited soon, but it's amazing that this isn't working at all and I'm very glad
to be here.
Yeah, yeah, it is.
And we've got a great show.
So we've got a couple of interesting things that I want to chew on today, like some big
picture stuff.
It does involve Microsoft and other companies and maybe what your company is doing wrong
in open source and how some of these other companies have figured it out, companies that
used to battle it.
Plus, we've got some interesting project updates, some weird things happening with Java Enterprise
and some Ubuntu news, some other things, as well as a few anecdotes from the road, Wes.
So I think it's going to be like a fun one.
It's like the pre-scale storm now.
Yeah, road check, road trip check in.
You know what's great about this is, so this setup right now that we're doing, I'm connected
to you through a microphone, a USB interface, and a box running Chrome.
That's so lean.
It was going to be my XPS 13, but I ended up actually, I'm on the, you remember the
old MacBook that you set up running Arch?
How could I forget?
We've had such a tender relationship.
Yep, yep.
So I've got that in here and so I have that running Chrome and connected to a MiFi and
that's how we talk now.
Well, you sound great.
This is incredible.
It's amazing what we can do in this modern day, and we haven't even turned this thing
up to 11 because we have remote controls into the studio so that way I can do things like
bring in the Mumble Room.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
What's up?
Hello.
Hey, hey.
Woo.
That was amazing.
That was good.
Good job, Mumble Room.
That was really good.
Yeah.
You guys are on point.
You know, Wes, I'm kind of missing out right now.
Levi and Hadir are out exploring Sacramento as I record.
That sounds way better.
Yeah.
Maybe I'll just jump out of the studio, go join them and good luck on your own, Chris.
They're like, well, see you later.
I'm like, what?
And we're going to go explore the capital.
She got an Uber and they're out walking around Sacramento while I'm inside the RV and it
is surrounded by wasps.
Down in California, apparently there's bees already and they're like crawling all over
my mirrors trying to get in while I do this show.
That's my situation.
Oh, okay.
Wow.
Yikes.
I have no choice but to just sit here hunkered down and podcast.
So that's what we'll be doing.
Well, at least you have us to join you in your suffering.
So we're going to start with a couple of big meta topics that I think might come up later
on in the show.
First one doesn't really have anything to do with Linux other than, well, we're going
to get to it in a roundabout way.
Jeff Bezos has spent $42 million building a clock that will run for 10,000 years.
This is part of the Long Now Foundation.
It was created in 1996 in the hopes to provide a counterpoint to today's accelerating culture
and help make long-term thinking more common.
One of its initiatives is the Clock of the Long Now, which is designed to run for 10
millennia without any need for human intervention.
And Bezos took interest in it six years ago and has invested $42 million.
Think about trying to build a system that could last 10 millennia without any human
intervention.
You can do that with Linux, right?
You can do that, Wes?
Come on.
I mean, I certainly wouldn't try to do it with Windows.
I suppose not.
The heart of the clock is a titanium pendulum that beats once every 10 seconds.
Now the falling weight that powers the clock can be wound by hand, but it is otherwise
kept wound by solar power.
It shines into an aperture in the 500-foot deep chamber in which the clock sits.
Oh, that's great.
It then strikes the air-filled cylinder.
The expansion of the cylinder provides enough energy to lift the falling weight slightly
and also provide some correction for solar noon timing.
And one key feature of the clock, and this is kind of weird if you think about it, the
displays are not active until a human enters the clock chamber and fully winds the mechanism.
Interesting.
So it's still keeping time, but it doesn't display time until there's a human there to
observe it.
But yet it's built to last 10 millennia without humans, but if there's no human there to observe
it, it never displays the time.
Just sits there in silence, displaying nothing, keeping time.
That's so weird.
That is so weird.
And he spent $42 million on this.
What do you think?
10 millennia, 42 million, you think that like dollars per millennia is a pretty good deal
for this or no?
Well, actually.
I mean, it kind of does seem like it's a decent deal, doesn't it?
I got to be honest with you, Wes.
It does actually seem pretty legit.
Also, I imagine the people designing this have had a lot of fun.
It seems like a great project, just in that it's weird and kind of interesting.
So it's neat that the, you know, crazy rich can fund one-off projects like this.
Now I know that this isn't going to appeal to you, but some of you out there are on Windows.
Now don't deny it.
I know it's true.
I've seen the download numbers.
A good number of you are on Windows, and it just may be getting a little bit easier to
run Ubuntu.
We talked about this on Linux Action News, and now with only three mouse clicks, once
this is completed, you'll be able to get an Ubuntu VM that offers full clipboard integration,
drive redirection, and enhanced display performance.
Right there, three clicks in the Hyper-V Gallery, boom, Ubuntu 18.04, ready to go.
You know, some of the really cool stuff that they've done, and I don't know a lot about
this, but they've worked with the open source XRDP project to bake in communication to Hyper-V's
communication bus, which there's already like a socket that's been upstream to the Linux
kernel to enable this communication.
So it goes from the kernel socket to the Hyper-V socket, and they talk, well, XRDP to transmit
the graphics, and it makes it a really fast interface and really low latency for the remote
graphics of the VM, which are not actually remote, depending on how you're using it.
Anyways, when you combine it with drive integration, clipboard integration, and XRDP integration
over this HVhook or HVsock system, this is going to be a pretty compelling step up from
the Windows subsystem for Linux on a Windows 10 machine.
You know, you're sitting there, you're hacking away on something under the subsystem, ah,
screw this.
What's left?
Well, now three clicks and you have this really hyper-integrated Ubuntu VM.
What do you think about this, Wes?
Is this the death knell for a virtual box on Windows?
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, you know, I was going like, what does this mean for people switching from Windows
to Linux?
My brain's been racing with that.
I hadn't thought about the competitors.
This is like home turf advantage.
I also know a lot of people who haven't yet been able, for enterprise policy reasons or
otherwise been really able to work the subsystem into their workflow, but are already using
virtual machines.
So it seems like this rolling out when it does will have an immediate impact there as
well.
I can also imagine developing, you know, as you're saying in the subsystem, but then still
having a fleet of, you know, development servers running locally in these VMs and be able to
test there.
I almost don't need a Linux laptop, and that's a little scary.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, there's two ways to look at it.
Yeah, that is scary.
You're right.
Because it is, it could potentially mean less Linux switchers.
That's definitely a possibility, but there's another way to look at it.
It's possible that now more people will be using Linux.
Yeah, the barrier to entry now is a lot lower.
They get hooked on the good sauce, right?
And they're like, why am I running this in a virtual machine?
First taste.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, once they get the first taste for free, right, and then they'll go out and buy.
How insidious.
Yeah, no.
Also, speaking of this kind of stuff, oh, does somebody else have something they want
to add from?
By the way, I think they just added Debian and Kali Linux support in the Windows Store
as well.
Yeah, that's what I was just going to mention is Kali Linux is in there now as part of the
subsystem, I guess.
Or is this part of the Hyper-V stuff?
I don't really know.
It's a subsystem.
Hmm.
And it doesn't have the hacking tools.
Like, you have to install that separately.
So I mean, I'm sure it's pretty easy to do that.
Yeah, well, this is what Kali Linux is one of those tools that, you know, Windows administrators
still end up using because it's just a really good tool to test yourself.
And it has everything and often it often comes with a lot of things pre-configured, perhaps
not in this case.
Yeah, but if it has scripts to set that stuff up, that's probably legit.
Yeah, I could be legit.
I don't know.
I'm not super jazzed up, but yeah, yeah, we're all kind of like, man, man, it's good to see
it.
And it means more users for Kali.
But they probably might just run it in one of those fancy new VMs anyway.
Yeah, yeah, that's true.
You could.
If that XRDP stuff goes upstream, which Microsoft did submit it upstream, and the HV hook stuff
is already upstream and it's integrated into kernel 4.15, then any distro could really
take advantage of that.
So yeah, you're right.
That would probably be a great way to use Kali because then you would have the full
Kali.
I'm just trying to think if there's any network stuff that wouldn't work because of the virtualized
card because that could be a possibility.
You would have to configure that depending on what you're trying to do.
That's for sure.
Yeah.
I don't know, Wes.
You know what the only way to find out would be for you to get a Windows 10 machine and
test it.
I guess you have to.
You're right.
Oh.
You know, I want to take a moment and thank Ting.
Why don't we do that right here?
Go to linux.ting.com.
I was really, really impressed yesterday when I sat down, I compared all the different carriers
that I had with me and the Ting CDMA was the fastest, but more importantly, the lowest
latency.
And sure enough, sure enough, here I am now in Sacramento, same thing.
I would have sworn it would have been the GSM network.
That's what I love about Ting is they have both and I just turn these devices on when
I'm traveling because it's $6 for the line.
And so honestly, if you have a backup line or a data device you need to use occasionally
or a phone that you can just be kind of savvy about using Wi-Fi, well then $6 a month.
That's nothing.
Linux.ting.com is where you go to get started and you get $25 off a device or if you bring
one that's compatible, just check their BYOD page, they'll give you $25 in service credit.
Now your average Ting bill is going to be around $23 all in, probably before Uncle Sam's
cut.
$23 for your minutes, your messages and your megabytes and the $6 for the line.
So a $25 credit will probably pay for more than your first month because that's how Ting
rolls.
Linux.ting.com.
Go there and then check out their blog post about comparing their Wi-Fi, I mean their
internet connection with Wi-Fi.
So their LTE with Wi-Fi and the differences there.
I was super impressed.
I was just talking to Wes on the pre-show, I pulled up, I was getting 22 down, even got
as high as 28 up and I was getting, yeah, I know, it was just nuts.
Those are some numbers.
But the thing was that really rocked is I was getting around 18, 20, 15 millisecond
ping time to the different servers.
And right now where I'm at, I'm getting around 30 milliseconds, which is still really, really
outrageously great.
That puts it in that territory where you start thinking about differently, right?
It's not just this shaky Wi-Fi connection, it's a real first class internet connection.
We can use it for broadcast, which is great.
In fact, I'm thinking about when we get to the next story, I'm tempted to try turning
up the broadcast quality another notch because I haven't turned down right now because I'm
also remote team viewer into machines in the studio.
I'm thinking about just pushing Ting to the limit and turning it up another notch.
I don't even know what the software would do, but damn if it isn't tempting.
So you know what?
I'm going to do it.
Go to linux.ting.com.
One way this is going to work or another.
So I would imagine this is going to disconnect Wes and then reconnect.
Okay, we'll hang tight here.
Finish up, you tell people to go to linux.ting.com and then we can go over to the Ubuntu story,
but I'm going to hit the button.
I'm going to go up another notch.
I don't know, in three, two, Ting save me.
See we can't do it without Ting.
That's it.
Oh really?
Was that it?
That's it.
Wow.
It did it.
Wait.
Oh, I bet you I have to refresh.
I bet you it hasn't kicked in yet until I refresh.
I'm still tempted to try it, Wes.
I know.
All right.
I'm going to hit refresh.
You ready?
Okay.
Wish me luck.
Here I go.
Good luck.
Oh, okay.
Well, there we go.
Now we know it was real.
It's all possible with Ting.
Head on over to linux.ting.com so you can be as impressed and satisfied.
And now we're happy to welcome Mr. Chris Fisher back to the Linux Unplugged program.
That's awesome.
That is great.
That was a lot of fun.
Oh, that was great.
That's like living on the edge.
Talk about adrenaline rush.
Real time doing it live.
Now we're up a whole other notch.
We're at 128 kilobits now.
So I don't know.
Are we going to start talking about the big exciting news that will probably happen just
a little bit after this show?
Jump right in.
Okay.
So I may just take a back seat and actually let Simon jump here in a moment, but as we
record this, if things go as planned, going by the schedule here on the Ubuntu Wiki, we
should see beta 1 for 1804, if not tomorrow, probably the day after or somewhere around
there, March 8th.
And then the Optin flavors as well.
But right before the show started, Simon started telling us about this and I said, wait, wait,
save it for the show.
So Simon, pick back up where you left off.
What's sort of the story that you had to share with the 1804 beta release?
So with the 1804 beta, we just, this is something that we are sort of working on today, actually.
And I've been working with Dustin Krysek, who's also here.
We were just sort of gauging interest because for the first two alphas of this release,
it ended up being bad timing because we had the Spectre and Meltdown stuff that went on.
So they disabled all the Launchpad builders, so we couldn't build anything.
And then after that beta or alpha 2, we also had some other difficulties in it.
This is the first 1804 milestone.
So you're going to see a couple of different things that you would usually see in like
a daily build.
Like just today, for example, we landed a new point release for Qt.
That's something that I was working on specifically, otherwise the flavors that I know of participating
right now in this are Lubuntu, where it's just general bug fix.
Lubuntu Next is also participating in this release, which Lubuntu Next is going to see
a huge overhaul of things with different applications coming in and different theming and that sort
of thing.
Then there's Ubuntu Budgie, Zubuntu is participating, all different sorts of flavors.
But this is really a sort of a community release because the Ubuntu desktop, they don't participate
in any milestone besides the final beta.
So this is a really good time, I think in my opinion, to go and see what's going on
in each of the flavors because this is really the first milestone of the 1804 release.
So it's really, like I said, it's a really good way to see what people have been working
on thus far.
Yeah, and I am tempted to do it.
It's funny, 1804 is sort of like 1710, although not quite as strong because it's not the switch
to know.
But I have a lot of people in my circle of friends and family that I take care of their
computers and they're all kind of due now.
Some of them weren't on 1604, like Dylan, he's on, I think he's on Loki Elementary OS
and Hadia, I think is on the last LTS, before 1604, I can't remember, but she's due for
two of her machines to get replaced.
And my dad has a system, I don't even know if he's using it anymore that I got to contact
him about.
1804 is going to be one that I think a lot of people in my circle are going to end up
using that I maintain their computers for.
People have been waiting, letting things bake.
Yeah, you're right.
It will be kind of how 16 felt like a similar moment in some ways, it will get wide deployment
and suddenly everyone will be on the latest Ubuntu.
Including probably Westpain, huh?
Are you sticking with the plasma?
Including me.
What's going on?
Oh.
Including JJ too.
Yeah.
What's the plasma status?
I so far have stuck with it.
Yes, I have been sticking with it as well.
It's been really smooth.
I think I got enough configuration down.
I know a little bit more about how to tweak the things that I actually care about where
I think I could replicate that pretty quickly on a new install.
I'm actually thinking about paving and doing that just to make sure that I'm right there.
And with that down, I feel a lot more comfortable with it.
Before it was just that, you know, GNOME had defaults that I really liked and worked really
well for me.
Now that I have that on KDE, it's great.
I think the thing that's helped me set up the Neon workstation was I did all KDE Neon,
so it's all the same distro.
It wasn't a mix this time of Ubuntu and Arch, which is what I've done in the past a lot.
That could be more complicated.
And I also just sat down once, and the first time I launched Dolphin, I went through and
changed all of the defaults I don't like.
The first time I logged in, I changed all of the desktop environment settings that I
don't like.
And so I just, each time, just said, OK, there's going to be a slight tax each time.
But then once I've done it once, they stay.
I've gone now for weeks, and I haven't had settings revert, windows reopen where I want
them.
The console stays the same size I had it last time.
I know.
It's so simple, but it's so nice.
And you know, you're sitting down there using AirMaster, and you haven't had to reboot it
before.
You could use it like we were having with Unity 7, which means none of the...
So when you do have to reboot it, say, for an update or something, it's better at remembering
the display output options into the OBS capture.
That is such a tiny thing, but it's like killer for our use case.
Yeah.
Yeah, it really is.
It's one of those nice little things.
So hashtag Rodden was right.
It's a great professional desktop.
And I think if a company came along, even a company like, oh man, I really shouldn't
go down this rabbit hole.
But a company like System76, you know what would make Pop OS 10 times more compelling?
Is if they were doing something that wasn't Gnome.
Because really what people could do is, right?
You could just go get their theme on Gnome, on stock Ubuntu and call it good, and then
you're close to mainline, you're close to what you're running in production, and you
still have their design aesthetics.
But if they were taking their design aesthetics and applying it to the Plasma desktop and
really just sort of getting down those rough edges, man, that would be, I would be a really,
really compelling distro.
And it'd really stand out, you know, be something that's different.
Yeah, you know, there's not a lot of that shipping, and there might be a lot of value
add they could have in just having it really well configured from the start.
Now what do you think, Simon, we don't give enough love to Kubuntu?
Yeah, I think it's going to have a nice release because no, the 1604 really, really wasn't
that good of a release for Kubuntu.
The 1804 is going to be interesting because it's going to be the latest LTS Plasma on
top of the latest LTS cubes, and it's going to be baked in with the LTS Ubuntu.
So while you do have KDE Neon, with them sunsetting the user edition, or the LTS edition, it might
be a good opportunity if you want to try Kubuntu, if you want a really rock-solid, stable KDE
Plasma experience.
Are we calling it sunsetting, is that what we're calling it, of the LTS edition, because
it's still there.
It's still there.
No, it's gone.
It's going away.
Okay.
So it's sunsetting.
It's not able to download, but it's going away.
It's just like right now you can still use it, and the repos are still there, but they're
focusing away from the LTS version of Neon because there's really no reason for it to
be there, because the majority of the time they put their effort into the regular user,
and that was kind of like the original point of Neon in the first place.
They just kind of made the LTS version because it made sense at the time, but now with Kubuntu
providing an LTS solution on an LTS base with a solid LTS release of Plasma, there's really
no need for it.
Yeah, okay.
I can see that.
I don't think Kubuntu is going to have a lot of interesting updates for the release of
1804, because I'm participating in making those updates.
Oh, can you get any teases, any hints of what we should look for?
Well, I mean, if you just boot the Kubuntu 1804, you will notice a change immediately
with the theming much different.
So one of the things that I did not like about Plasma, like there's a few things
that Plasma doesn't do good by default.
I'm trying to fix those, and Kubuntu are very receptive to those, so that's really awesome.
One of the biggest things that I've convinced them to change is that the default breeze
theme is super bright, and it's kind of awkward for the panels and widgets and menus and stuff.
So they've switched it so that you have the dark theme breeze for the panels, the menus,
and the widgets with a bright theme for the windows.
So it's like a hybrid approach.
Okay, nice.
Well, good on you.
I like that sound, Ron, because I got to tell you, yeah, I got to tell you guys, I have
light sensitivity in my eyes, and that's why I wear glasses.
So one of the reasons why, other than my stigmatism, and I got to tell you, light themes just hurt
the heck out of my eyes.
So this is a good notice for me, as well as another thing I wanted to mention was Xfce
and especially Xubuntu, I've been waiting like hell for good Xfce high DPI support.
So I'm thinking of until that happens to have Kubuntu installed and have this with my MacBook,
because I got to tell you, I hate that Xfce doesn't have good high DPI support right now.
Yeah, yeah.
And that's a ways out.
So I'm thinking of switching to Kubuntu for this, man.
That's a ways out.
Switching to Kubuntu, because I know that they have decent high DPI support, so I'm
thinking of going to Kubuntu instead.
Well, I'll tell you this, Ben, is if you try it out, you're not going to go back.
That's what's going to happen.
You won't go back once you try it.
Yeah, that's what I'm thinking of doing is downloading Kubuntu 18.04 and just chucking
that on there instead.
Yeah, yeah.
You're going to like it.
Yeah, that's my plan.
Yeah.
People tweeted last week or the week before and said, hey, how come you guys didn't talk
about the plasma update?
It's just sort of now we're there.
We're using it and we're not switching.
And it's stuck.
And I really, really like it.
Yeah, it is the new normal.
So I'm going to transition from that and I'm going to mention why I'm on the road just
because people probably already know.
But just in case it's your last chance, Scale16x, the 16th annual Southern California Linux
Expo.
It's going on at the Pasadena Convention Center March 8th through the 11th.
So it's starting in just a couple of days.
I will be in the Pomona area Wednesday evening.
And Wes, it's funny, when I get into California, because I've got the live tracker going at
the jupyterbroadcast.com.
I was going to ask.
That's perfect.
We can all creepily follow along.
Well, people do.
And I totally encourage it.
It's great because what happens is as soon as I get into California, it's New York, California
and Salt Lake City.
When I'm in either one of those areas, it goes from like, yeah, let's go out and get
a bite to eat.
Yeah, that sounds cool.
Let's meet up and get a bite to eat.
And it goes from, well, OK, we've got a big group.
So we're going to have to go do a meet up.
Where can we go where we can fit like seven people?
It's just way more people because everybody's so densely packed in here in New York and
in California and apparently Salt Lake City.
And so I may potentially be going out to dinner with five different listeners.
That's incredible.
I know.
After driving like a madman.
We got on the road before sunrise, before 6 a.m. and drove, drove, drove, drove to get
here so that way we could sit and park somewhere and do the show.
And I've just been getting telegrams and tweets.
It's great.
And I've already got listener Jeff on the way to meet up after we get off the air with
Unplugged here at the RV.
Oh, wow.
So do you think you're ready?
I mean, does the scale starts on Thursday?
Is that right?
Pumped.
Yeah, I'm pumped.
I'm pumped.
I have some listener Ryan, a tech guy who a couple of years ago helped us out by letting
us borrow his Cadillac when we got into Pomona because it's about 45 minutes between Pomona
and Pasadena, which is Pasadena is where scale's at.
And so Ryan's like, well, you're not planning to drive your RV in there, are you?
And we're like, no.
He's like, I don't think you realize how expensive that's going to be on Uber.
Why don't you borrow my car?
And we're like, OK.
Whoa.
OK.
So he shows up and it's a Cadillac and which I just have an affection for because my grandparents
always had Cadillacs and so it was, you know, it's pretty great.
So Ryan reached out to me again this year and said, hey, you need another ride?
I could I could meet you Thursday morning and bring you into scale.
So yeah, Ryan and I are going to be meeting back up again and riding the Cadillac into
town and going to scale Thursday morning.
I think Noah is going to arrive in town like Thursday evening.
So I'll be there in the morning to get like the beginning, do the meet and greets with
with folks and meet a few people, get some interviews lined up, all that kind of stuff.
And I don't know.
It just go.
You know, this is the scale.
So scale was talking to us and they're like, so do you do you want the booth?
And we're like, no, we don't want the booth.
You don't want a booth?
Nope.
But how are you going to do a live show?
We're like, well, maybe you could give us a room somewhere that's quiet.
What?
Like, yeah, that's how we want to do it this year.
No booth.
Totally different.
We're just going to go enjoy ourselves and try and really try to get a sense of where
Linux is going in 2018 because you got a lot of good projects there, a lot of different
industry representation.
That's one of the reasons I'm taking all this effort to go to scale is because it's like
the biggest event in the States.
And so I wish it was Linux Fest Northwest, which because that's up there.
That's a big one, but it's not as big a scale.
And in fact, the folks from Linux Fest Northwest usually go to scale to represent.
And so I got to go to scale if I want to go to like the big community event.
The big community event.
And you know, it's another side of the community.
There's different people that can make it there.
So I'm sure it's a lot of fun.
Yeah, I am so, so, so looking forward to it.
I'm trying to document bits of the journey too as we go down in Tech Talk today.
I just published episode 264, Parking Lot Podcaster yesterday and kind of captured the
first bit of the trail and the trek down here.
Tech Talk dot today is where you can go to get that.
And if you want to track me live as I'm making my way down to scale, Jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash Rover, that tracker is in the RV, not in, not on me.
So people like people show up at the RV and they're like awkward about it and they're
like hanging out around the RV and I'm not there.
I'm not there.
It's not on me.
Like, you can get to the RV by watching that, but you got to telegram me or tweet me to
actually find where I'm at.
But if it's during scale...
Oh, so you move around outside of LadyJubes?
Turns out I leave LadyJubes.
Yeah, I know.
People have asked me, well, could you just put the tracker in your pocket?
And I feel like that's the line where that's too far.
That's too far.
It's like, no, it's installed in LadyJubes.
I've considered it.
When we were in New York for a short period of time, we did remove it from LadyJubes and
we installed it into Dia's car.
But yeah, well, I love this app that you found, Wes.
It's like a, it's like salvation for Slack users.
Not that anybody ever uses Slack.
No, certainly not.
I wouldn't.
Nobody on this show, nobody in the mumble room uses Slack, nobody in the IRC or Discord,
nobody listening ever uses...
We only use what mattered most.
Yeah.
Yeah, and there is some.
There is definitely some of that.
I think the same value is Slack at work.
Do you?
Yeah.
Is it pretty entrenched into the workflow?
Actually yes, because we use it for most of our communication, especially my department
when we're away from each other or inter-campus, that kind of thing.
Yeah, and I know, Wes, I know you use it with the network, but you also have a day job use
for it too.
So you're pretty heavy into Slack, just for work reasons, right?
Yep, definitely it's on all my devices just for that.
If not also the network, you're absolutely right.
So I want to try to find different ways to use Slack that are quick and easy and low
bandwidth.
And so that's why I love this app that you found, Wes, Slack Term, which is a Slack client
for your terminal.
And it's simple, install away, and you just download a binary for your system and run
it.
I think it's written in Go, yeah?
Did you check and look?
I think it's a Go app.
Let's take a look here.
And it's got a whole set of keyboard commands.
Yep, it's a Go app.
Yeah, it's written in Go.
So you get a nice static binary you can run, yeah.
And it really is, I mean, if you just look at the interface, it's pretty minimal.
I like that it may not have all the features that you want.
But if you just want to be able to reply quickly, not jump out of your terminal, this might
be the thing for you.
I love the idea of SSH sessions running with certain applications just omnipresent.
I don't know.
I do it rarely, and then it all falls apart, and I stop using all of it, and then I build
things back up over time, like torrent clients, and SSH, and IRC, and things like that.
And then I sort of tear it all down, depending on my use case.
But like a team up session where you could stick this in there and just come back to
it anytime you needed it.
Or I've done X2Go as well, which is also really nice, and just have it up in an X session.
But anyways, this is sort of like a low bandwidth way to take care of Slack.
But the point I was getting at here is you can build a set of tools like this.
So what I had set up was an X2Go session on a DigitalOcean droplet that was just always
running.
It's still running right now, which is great, because I'm on a MiFi connection, so maybe
something really big and intensive comes up.
The MiFi connection is fast enough to do an X2Go session.
And that's secured over SSH, right?
And so then I'm working on a machine that's on a DigitalOcean droplet that has a 40-gigabit
connection, digitalocean.com.
Go over there and create your account, and use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
And for a limited time, depends on engagement, there's a great deal.
And Wes, do you have the paper there?
There's like a URL.
It's like do.co slash unplugged, I think.
There's like an email somewhere on the table there.
There's a note there.
Okay now, here's why I wanted to make sure he got that, because that's the email where
DigitalOcean is informing us that for a limited...
Yeah, that's great.
Nice.
That sounds good, Wes.
It's a limited time $100 credit for your DigitalOcean account if you're a new customer.
Wow.
Because honestly, the $10 credit is more than enough because you could run the $10.
Pretty great, yeah.
Yeah.
So $100 credit, that's insane.
And the reason is because they've got new systems.
They've got mix and match droplets where you can mix and match the different resources
that you need for your application.
They've really improved the competitive pricing on their standard droplets too.
Basically all my rigs just got an upgrade.
My $0.03 an hour rig is just unstoppable.
You didn't do anything, and now they're better.
And you were there.
Weren't you there?
We were doing something for...
We did it live.
It was beautiful.
Yeah, we were doing something for TechSnap.
We were doing an experiment.
This is a great use case that we do with DigitalOcean all the time is Wes and I are about to talk
about something on TechSnap, and we had a question functionally about how it worked,
and we wanted to be able to speak from a position of experience, so we spun up a droplet.
In this case, it was a droplet that I already had some of the tools installed on, so I upgraded
the droplet, installed the applications I needed within seconds, and within 10 minutes
total we had run through different scenarios.
We had tested the application, and we were able to incorporate that into our notes for
the TechSnap program.
And it's that kind of flexibility when you're trying something out, when you want to learn
something, or when it's just time to build something and put it in production.
There's all kinds of great uses for DigitalOcean.
Go over there.
They have great documentation, do.co slash unplugged, simplicity at scale and unbelievably
easy to use interface.
That's why companies like Slack and Tesla and Jupiter Broadcasting and many, many others
and lots of open source projects use DigitalOcean, do.co slash unplugged, and go check out their
documentation as well.
Thank you, DigitalOcean, for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
So let's talk about Java just for a moment because I don't know what the hell is going
on here.
Oracle has handed over Java Enterprise Edition to the Eclipse Foundation, and now that the
Eclipse Foundation has taken over Java Enterprise, they're renaming it to Jakarta, and they're
dropping the Java trademark stuff.
There's no Java trademarks now.
They're calling the new Java Enterprise Jakarta, and it's under the guise of the Eclipse Foundation.
Did all those words I just said make sense to you?
I think so at a high level.
They barely did.
Yeah.
But it's, I'm still not clear, will Oracle still be publishing their own version?
Will people start actually calling it Jakarta?
What's actually happening here?
I think it is a handover, and the thing that screwed me up is that Jakarta isn't a new
name.
The Apache Foundation used the name Jakarta, which was their open source Java efforts in
the late 90s, till recently, at least till 2011.
So that was an Apache thing.
So then this thing comes along, and it's really confusing, but my understanding is that essentially
it's a group of Java experts, including the Java creator, James Galsling, and others that
wrote Oracle and said, hand it over to us.
And they wrote a long list of reasons, and I think Oracle has complied.
This is all news to me, and I barely, barely care.
But it seems like we may have a new product on the market called Jakarta EE, which is
Java, but now under the Eclipse Foundation.
So that's my takeaway story from this.
Is that thick or what?
Yeah, I mean, of course it is.
We're talking about Oracle here, and so there's obviously going to be a lot of details that
have to be argued over and then lawyers involved.
Is there any chance somebody in the Mumba Room has a better breakdown of the story,
and perhaps could summon some bit of courage to actually care a bit more than I could?
I just...
No?
Nobody?
Okay.
We'll get the Well Actually email, and they'll set us straight, I'm sure.
They'll tell us.
That's why we love you, audience.
Now, Mr. Foray couldn't join us today, and it's my bad, because I believe he's in my
neck of the woods right now.
So I should have caught a hold of him and said, why don't you come over to LadyJuice
and have...
Oh, that would have been amazing.
Yeah, I could have shared this pineapple cider with him, which is prickly pineapple.
Prickly pineapple?
Say that 10 times fast.
And he could have told us about Juno, which they're now actually starting the hype machine
on.
And they don't talk a lot about their future releases, but we're starting to see some updates.
And there is a couple of things that jumped out at me.
Number one, besides just an overall refinement to almost all aspects of the user interface
and the photos app and the terminal, but they have a new nightlight function.
Nightlight?
Which you probably...
Yeah, you probably can guess what that is.
It's a nightlight tab under the new display settings area that there's a new function
there.
And you can set the temperature and the schedule.
And then there's a really nice dropdown indicator where you can set there and adjust the shade
from a dropdown indicator.
They just really...
I don't know if you've seen the screenshot of this, Wes, but they've really done a good
job of taking a feature that I rely a lot on.
This nightshade feature combined with dark user interfaces is sort of my trick to using
my computer late at night.
Sometimes I just don't sleep.
And what happens is, don't tell her I said this, but I go to bed and I get a real good
sleep going.
You know what I mean?
Like a solid sleep.
One of those, oh yeah.
Mm-hmm.
I'm out.
And then Hadia comes to bed or gets up and does something or the kids or the dog wakes
me up like 20 minutes into this nice sleep and I never fall back asleep for the rest
of the night.
And so what I have learned is after about an hour or so, maybe two hours, I just give
up and I go work.
You might as well get something done instead of restlessly sitting there.
I'm cracking open that XPS 13 in the middle of the night.
Sometimes it's like 2 a.m. or whatever when I've finally given up.
And if Redshift isn't kicked in just right or whatever, it's a blast of blue light that
almost guarantees I'll never go back to bed.
And this functionality sometimes can be too much when I'm editing and I need to turn this
down or turn it off.
And so it's really just a slick implementation they've done.
There's all kinds of things.
I really like the work they've done with the terminal too.
It's those little tweaks that often I think set elementary apart just in that, you know,
for you and I, it's not a problem.
We can install any of the tools that exist to do similar things, but to just have it
right in the OS that you've installed with that came on your computer, have it be a first
class in the UI and in the settings menu, that makes a big difference, I think, especially
people coming from Mac or other fancier platforms.
Yeah, I almost wish I wasn't all in on Plasma now.
It's looking so good.
But the Plasma hype beast has me hard right now.
There's just no way.
You know, once it's out, I won't blame you if you want to flirt around for a while.
That's okay.
You know, what we need is somebody in the mumble room to be like a third party arbiter
because, you know, Dan's going to say it's great if he shows up.
And I'm not trying to right now because I'm all in on Plasma.
So we need somebody from the mumble room to step up and be our elementary OS ambassador
and try this out and let us know how it's going and be like our 1804 on the scene reporter.
It could be you.
Somebody's got to do that.
It could be.
So if you want to do that, let us know.
Go to jupyterbroadcasting.com slash contact or hang out in our mumble room, mumble.jupytercolony.org
for info on that and be part of the virtual log because it's going every Tuesday.
We do the show at, we try to start around somewhere in like the 1.30 to 2 o'clock time
range Pacific and then we go until Noah's done with Ask Noah.
So it's a good time to hang out.
A wonderful afternoon of Linux.
Heck yeah.
jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar for the lifetime for that.
There you go.
If you want to see Daniel's post on that, they have a update for the last couple of
months and it's looking really good.
It's looking like they're really putting some serious work into that and you can go check
that out.
There's all of our links, jupyterbroadcasting.com.
Go over there and then find the episode.
This is episode 239 and you'll have links to everything in there.
I don't know, Mr. West.
What do you think?
Do you think, oh, you know what I was going to mention too is I'm going to try to, well,
you know what?
I'll save it.
You are a tease today.
We'll tease it.
We have this.
Actually, okay.
Let's get into this.
Let's do this.
So just really quickly, earlier in the show, we talked about Jeff Bezos' clock and Microsoft
making Hyper-V friendly version of Ubuntu, also Kali Linux coming into the subsystem.
I went down to Microsoft.
I had some interesting conversations with them.
It's almost quaint now to just kind of like, what's Microsoft doing with open source?
There's something I actually want to talk about in this area and the topic that Tech
Republic ran with was what Microsoft understands about open source that your company doesn't.
It's an interesting post, so I want to talk about that for a moment, but before we do,
let's thank Linux Academy, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Thank you Linux Academy for sponsoring the show.
It's a platform for you guys to go to, to learn more, to get more out of your career,
to maybe advance it, or to just challenge yourself, whatever you think might help build
the resume.
It's a full-featured training library with everything you need to learn new skills, self-paced,
in-depth video course on every cloud and DevOps topic, hands-on scenario-based labs that give
you experience on real servers, and if you ever need help, they have full-time instructors
that are there to advise and answer your questions.
And they have learning paths, which are a series of courses and contents planned by
instructors for specific career tracks.
Are you ready to either switch track or go deeper?
Really recommend that.
And now, a lot of you ask about certifications, and yes, they have courses created specifically
to prepare you for certification exams.
They also have practice exams and quizzes to prepare you.
They have flashcards, which use custom randomized decks of cards to help you study.
They get forged by the community and made better all of the time.
They have iOS and Android apps so you can study on the go, and they have a deep content
library.
They have staff that are adding to that and also going back and keeping it relevant all
the time, so that way your subscription is always valuable.
And if you're ready to learn AWS or OpenStack or even Azure, they have great courseware
and all of that.
They're really becoming the leader with all of that stuff, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Go there and sign up for a free seven-day trial, linuxacademy.com slash unplugged, and
a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
So the sub-headline is, Microsoft understands that its future depends upon contributing
to open source, not just using it, and your company needs the same strategy.
And when I was talking with Jeffrey, the technology fellow at Microsoft from the Azure group,
he talked about, well actually let me reframe this, I told him the reason why it's hard
for us to understand what Microsoft's overall strategy is, is because from the outside we
just see these big code drops.
So.NET Core, boom, code drop.
Visual Studio Code, boom, just code drop.
And then all of a sudden PowerShell Core, boom, code drop.
And it just looks like this sporadic, like now we're doing this is open source because
developers, and now we're doing this is open source because developers.
And it feels like it's an attempt to just take a shotgun approach to solving a problem.
But what I realized, which is obvious if you have any kind of insight inside a company,
what I realized is these are the manifestations of three or four year long processes.
Like Joey, who was in some of our interviews a couple of weeks ago, he was hired like four
years ago to help specifically begin the snowball effect of this process, which involved training
the team on using Git, which involved getting people on Mac and Linux, which quite frankly
involved firing people who weren't on board with the new program and were always Windows
first.
And it was this realignment that they have been doing internally to not just make money
off of open source, which is what they're doing, but the way they're making money off
open source is by trying to contribute to open source and get legitimate...
Get legitimate, I don't know if standing is the right word.
So I'll give you an example of where I'm going with this.
They talked at length internally about how the open source community would react to them
open sourcing PowerShell and what they could do to sort of appease that reaction, to sort
of address some of those concerns.
And they specifically had to jump into action when the developer of Curl was one of the
first people to submit a bug and it was, hey, you've got to remove your alias of Curl so
people can actually use real Curl.
And then they have this big conversation, like, okay, now we've got to make sure we're
responding.
This is what we're doing now.
This is what we're doing here.
And it wasn't just like our PR department's doing this now, our developers are working
internally.
It was the people actually touching the code had to get involved.
And there was some sort of shift that they had, some sort of mind shift that they had.
And I wouldn't be surprised if it was perhaps just watching how Red Hat does it and figuring
out how Red Hat's making money and going, well, geez, they're actually contributing
code upstream.
They're actually writing that stuff for their competitors to use and they're still making
money on it and they're being taken serious and they're considered legitimate.
Well, maybe we should do that.
So it's not like there wasn't somebody out there for them to look at, but they actually
got it.
And so what we're seeing today is sometimes something that's been in the works for four
or five years now that they're just getting around to dropping on us.
And so the key point that this Tech Republic article makes is if you actually want to be
taken serious at like a platform level or at a tool level, you've actually got to go
all in.
You can't just be like the PR division or a part of it.
And I kind of take some of this and I kind of direct some of this at Dell right now.
Like Dell is pretty all in on Linux on the server side and on the Sputnik line, but,
you know, I mean, it feels like there's more they could do.
They do contribute source code upstream, but I feel like there's more, like there's further
steps for Dell to take.
And I don't know exactly what they would be.
I mean, they still, they will definitely still, quote unquote, recommend Windows 10 for the
laptop that they're trying to sell you.
Yeah.
And I guess, yeah, I guess that's understandable for business.
Absolutely.
No, it absolutely is.
But it doesn't, you know, there's a lot of conflicting feelings.
You're not quite sure like, well, how, how much, how invested in this are you?
So you and I talk about a lot of, on TechSnap, a lot of tools that people can use to manage
their server infrastructure and their crazy container sprawl and all that stuff.
And can you think of any of those tools that are really serious, like what are the big
ones in that space that are completely commercial where they don't have like a, like half the
tools open source?
Like what, like, is Ansible all open source?
What's the...
You know, the Ansible tower component didn't used to be, but it is now.
It really has been the trend.
There still are, you know, some like enterprise focused proprietary systems for monitoring
and configuration management, but they're definitely not the things that you end up
seeing at big tech companies or a lot of startups or, you know, maybe if you've been paying
for them for 20 years and it's part of your workflow, sure.
But it's not, it's not where the momentum is.
The only thing I could think of that's server based is web server cPanel.
Yep.
Yeah.
I was thinking cPanel is definitely something that's more consumer facing, but yeah.
Is cPanel still strong?
Is it used much?
Yeah.
It's one of the top ones.
Still, huh?
What a nightmare.
That and Plask.
Yeah.
Oh yeah.
Wes, when's the last time you used cPanel or Plask?
Thankfully quite some time, but I definitely have friends, you know, or people in unfortunate
situations and you're right.
They're still, they're definitely still out there.
Yeah.
It seems though like if you want to be like a legitimate platform player, you have to
open source.
I mean, look at Apple with Swift.
You had to open source Swift to be taken seriously anymore.
I think it's a pretty big statement right there.
And Apple is an example of a company who's like half in with open source.
They obviously use a lot of it, a lot of the BSD tools, CUPS, a lot of that stuff is open
source in the development chain.
Even Darwin itself is open source, but it feels like that's more of an open source out
of convenience where there is a different type of commitment level to open source coming
out of Microsoft now.
And you can, you know, you can be listening to this and be skeptical and say, oh, Chris
has bought into the Kool-Aid, but I went down there and I talked to the people and they,
they said the things that you say when you're legitimately trying hard and you're a large
company.
And I think that that formula that they've cracked is going to be one that other companies
are either going to have to try to try to copy or they're going to be just perceived
as disingenuous.
Yeah.
I mean, it was like a legitimate.
It feels like almost like you almost have to assess it from that perspective in terms
of open source is just what you have to do now.
So even if you don't trust Microsoft, still don't like Microsoft, whatever, they're smart
enough, savvy enough, at least it appears that even if they didn't genuinely believe
these things, they're willing to do so just in their own interest.
You know, what's going to be, you know, what's going to be weird is to see where Google goes
in the next few years with open source because they've got Project Fuchsia.
They've got Android One.
It's a little bit different of a thing.
But there's also today there is news that Google has unveiled a 72 qubit Bristol Cone
processor, which they say brings them to quantum supremacy in the quantum computing race.
Now it's not like we're not talking like they're cracking Bitcoin crypto codes yet, but that
is going to be a really interesting thing to see where this all goes with Google and
where where they still continue to contribute to open source and where they become more
Apple to try to stay competitive with Android, you know, that line that they walk.
Very much so.
And it's funny you mentioned that because just the just the other week to Microsoft
released their quantum development kit, including support for Linux.
So it's they're all they're all playing in these spaces.
I think it will matter like, how genuine do they believe it?
Is it a Google style kind of it is open source, but all the good stuff gets put proprietary?
Or will it really be first class open source?
That seems to be the way it's going to it's like these big centralized obviously, because
of just the cooling requirements and all this crazy stuff when they build these quantum
computers.
IBM is doing that, too.
Did you see that there?
There's like some IBM Center down in Texas.
If you're a local, you can go use IBM's quantum computer.
Yeah.
And then they have an API you can use over the web as well.
Really?
Yeah.
Oh, my gosh.
Well, there you go, Wes.
Maybe we could encode some podcasts on there.
Let's give it a shot.
I don't think so.
No, I don't think so.
All right.
If you want to contribute something to the show, go to linuxunplugged.reddit.com.
That is our subreddit linuxunplugged.reddit.com.
Yes, we have a subreddit.
We don't mention it very often.
But it's over there.
I'm not big on Reddit these days.
So I just shut down our Jupiter broadcasting subreddit.
Because I was in there and I was like, this is a fuck.
This is, I shouldn't swear, but this is a dumpster fire is what my thoughts were.
But the unplugged subreddit still seems to be chugging along just fine.
And there is a post in there that was submitted an hour ago by Mr. Motang about Skype bragging
that their maintenance updates could be easier because of snaps.
Now, I think there's also the possibility that we could see more things coming down
this channel.
I don't know how much I can say.
Yeah.
I don't think I can actually say what I know.
Do you remember we talked about it?
It does seem like there's some momentum behind the scenes that we aren't, I don't get to
be privileged to, but just quiet releases of things.
That's got to be building.
Well, see, here's like, I'll tell you, there's a capability when you have a confined application
and you ship with its own libraries, if it's using, if the application is typically doing
something wrong, there might be a way via packaging to solve it.
So say you had an application like Skype that was broken into two pieces.
You had an electron version of Skype and then inside Skype, you still had like a C plus
application to do like all of the voice calls that actually was the voice engine.
Let's say this is theoretically new Skype is set up.
Well, new Skype uses electron wrapper for like the chat and all of that.
And of course, because it's new Skype, that's using pulse audio.
But core Skype that's like embedded in that electron app that's doing all of the management
for the voice calls, that's still using ulsa.
Fun.
Okay.
I totally believe that that would happen in this theoretical Linux universe.
Exactly.
And it's possible that perhaps one is communicating at ulsa with one rate and it's communicating
and then the electron apps communicating to pulsa with a completely different rate.
You see what I'm saying?
I can't, I mean, I don't, I certainly can't hear what you're saying because that sounds
like an audio clusterfuck.
Sorry.
I would, are you talking about sample rate or yeah, yeah, we might be, we might be, we
might be talking about sample rate, not bit rate.
That might be what we're talking about.
Maybe you're talking like 44 Hertz versus 48 Hertz.
You know what I'm saying?
That kind of thing.
Like perhaps the electron app is at 44 Hertz and perhaps the C plus plus or the C plus
apps at a 48 you saw, you know, who knows, I'm just spitballing here and via packaging,
you might be able to have some libraries in there that solve this problem and fix this
problem for the vendor that, that doesn't require them doing a complete rewrite of their
application.
And so that vendor may be very excited about the packaging format because of the possibilities
of solving problems for them on the Linux platform.
That could be potentially what we're dealing with here, but I don't know.
I'm just speculating.
You see what I'm saying?
Yeah.
I could see a sample rate mismatch, but not so much a bit rate mismatch because that would
just make a compression sound weird.
A sample rate mismatch would actually speed up or slow down the audio.
Yeah.
Hadea just got back from, uh, from the Capitol with Levi.
Levi, welcome in little buddy.
Yeah.
Levi is now here.
He's here.
Come here, Levi.
Come here.
Come say hi to the unplugged program.
Come up here.
Come here.
So yeah, he's nice and warm here.
Lick the microphone for me.
There you go.
Yeah.
He likes to sit and he likes to sit up here and look out the window.
But how was that?
Was that good?
Yeah.
Is it warm?
It looks pretty warm out there.
I'm getting pretty warm in here.
Did you just turn on the air?
Okay.
Nice.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, so, uh, Mr. West, I have just a couple of parting bits to talk about before we get
out of here.
Let us in on your secrets.
Do you have, do you have any secrets you want to share with the people?
Maybe like a Twitter place they could check out something like that.
You can find me over at, uh, at West Payne.
Very good.
You can follow me at Chris LAS and why not check out the Instagram.
I'll post a few pictures.
Yes.
I said it.
Do it.
As long as, as long as there's Levi pictures, I will be there.
You know what?
I'll make sure I put a Levi picture up there just for you.
Okay.
Just for you.
Um, Insta Chris LAS on there.
I'll be posting some pictures on the road to scale tech talk dot today for the story
as we get to scale.
And if you're in the Pasadena area, let me know at Chris LAS on the Twitter or on the
telegrams.
I'd love to talk to you guys and Jupiter broadcasting.com slash calendar for our live time.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode of unplugged and we'll see you right
back here next week.
All right, well, now we just got to pick a title and then we're out of here.
Let's get that titles on everyone.
Noah may be stopping in a little bit too.
Noah that dog.
I know, right?
I know.
Boom, JBtitles.com.
Go get your vote heard right now.
The only election that matters, JBtitles.
I shall be back after game the kid.
What'd you say?
We'll just put quantum in there a whole bunch?
That's probably what we want.
We were, you know, we have, uh, it's funny how you notice how like the mumble room attendance
is pretty decent today, but it could be double this some weeks, you know, and it just sort
of ebbs and flows.
It really does.
We should get some graphs on that.
That would be really interesting.
On Twitter, check out the trends in the US player one is trending and it seems to be
all retro, um, movie titles and or, uh, retro characters feeding, um, being, uh, subbed
in with a ready player one.
Oh really?
It's right.
When's ready player one coming out?
I'm ready.
My body is ready.
My booty is ready.
All right, Wes, I'm going to go find a Levi picture for you right now.
Wow, what a dear.
How about, uh, we call, here's one that we call, uh, Levi the Copi.
Levi the Copi.
He's so cute.
Now he's been to California.
Look at that.
Uh, he may have before because, uh, you know, he's from Texas.
We had, uh, we parked somewhere where the people that parked next to us, they had a
rescue dog from Texas too.
Nice.
Did they get along well?
They did.
You know, you know Levi.
Yeah.
You know.
He just wants to be everyone's friend.
Yeah.
There ain't nobody Levi don't get along with.
Know what I mean?
Yeah.
Right.
And if so, I don't trust that person.
They've clearly done something wrong.
It'll release on the 29th of March.
Oh man, that's, that's forever.
That is forever, dude.
Yeah.
Could be worth the wait.
Plus it, I think, uh, Spielberg is directing.
There you go, Wes.
Just for you.
Posted Levi the Copilot.
Oh.
Boom.
Um, all right, so we got to name this thing.
This is going to be a, this is going to be a weird Poe show.
Yeah.
This is a weird Poe show, but that's just what happens sometimes, you know?
Yeah, it is.
It's a weird week because it's a low mumble attendance.
It's kind of a light news week and-
Everyone's too excited about scale.
How are you going to-
And yeah, yeah.
And also this is put kind of put together at the last minute because, you know, road
trip.
Well, you're not supposed to reveal that part.
Okay.
All right.
Scaling, unplugged, remote access, unplugged, unplugged on the road, uh, unplugged road
show, um, what about, uh, what about, uh, what about Jeff's clock or something like
that?
Or cleaning, cleaning Jeff's clock.
Oh, cleaning Jeff's clock, huh?
Uh, millennium Linux.
Microsoft strategy.
Because it wasn't-
That was too bad.
And it has, we have, we had two stories at least.
Uh, the Microsoft, uh, the Microsoft millennium, the Microsoft, uh, Microsoft millennium.
The uh, let's see, really what you got here is, you know what I was going to go with?
You know what I forgot to, you know what I forgot to put in there was where I was going
to go is both Microsoft and Amazon are really powerfully positioned to, uh, just dominate
for a couple of years and, uh, Amazon more so I think.
And I wanted to kind of work that into the segment because that's kind of where this
is headed.
It just, it didn't work.
There's too much going on.
I don't know.
We didn't get there.
But, uh, that's where this is all going is Amazon is going to become like the titan of
our industry because look at, they already run the internet with EC2, um, they're gonna,
they're gonna turn our own homes into stores with ring video doorbell and the echo devices
and the security products they're about to launch and then home delivery of prescriptions.
They're going to just own our home completely or our own, they're with the echo tubes and
dash buttons and all these other things.
They just turn your, they don't need a store because your house is the store.
Um, and then they have amazon.com and, uh, then they're going to have their media section
with the prime stuff, the prime video stuff and, uh, they're opening up another headquarters.
So do you feel like a little pawn being bounced back and forth between like three big tech
companies kind of deciding what your life is like?
Yeah.
Did you guys mention about the, uh, gaming, uh, service that they just bought?
No, no, no gaming, game streaming service.
So the future is theirs.
The future is like, what do we, what can we, where can we go with a title from this?
Microsoft millennium.
Um, the next Microsoft millennium, the next Microsoft decade.
Yeah.
I don't know about you guys, but I'm not allowing any Amazon echoes into my, uh, this, uh, residence.
Next Microsoft.
It's kind of long.
I don't know.
People just think it's about Microsoft.
Yeah.
Right.
Um, the future is open source.
Uh, hmm.
That's closer.
That's not bad.
It's not great.
It's kind of generic.
It's probably more in the direction, um, open source millennium by the way, can we check
the IRC discord poll?
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
Uh, yeah, it is.
It's in the, it's in the show notes from two weeks ago.
If you want to check it while we, while we tile it up, uh, there you go.
Levi, the co-pilot picture posted just for us.
Boom.
Yep.
Look at that.
It's beautiful.
Got it up here on the stream.
Isn't he a dog?
Oh yeah.
He does get very sleepy.
Yeah.
He, he does get very sleepy.
You're on the road a long day traveling.
It takes it out of a little pup.
It does.
Poor little guy.
Oh gosh, he's so cute with his little sweater too.
He probably hardly needs it in your warm California air.
Yeah.
It's off now.
That was earlier this morning when it was up in the twenties.
Okay.
What else do we got here?
Anything new?
Unplugged on the road.
I've been unplugged everywhere.
Hashtag rotten was right.
That's great.
Um, plasma millennium, well we only really talked about plasma just as the check-in.
Let's see here.
Okay.
It looks like IRC is winning over discord with 77%.
Yeah.
That is surprising.
I think 77 is down from 79 from last check.
Correct?
Oh, it is.
Huh?
Oh, there you go.
Uh, diddle it, did it, did it, Morty.
Just use an external USB sound card.
Don't use the sound card built into your laptop.
Yeah.
For hiss.
So, okay.
Um, something about Jakarta, um, no, selling, selling, selling out for open source.
Oh, that's kind of, that's actually not bad.
Yeah.
It's kind of, it's kind of nuanced.
There could be multiple interpretations.
It's got open source in there.
Let's say Microsoft, but it's obviously what we're talking about.
Huh.
I kind of like it.
I like it too.
You're making me like it.
You're making me like it, Wes.
I could, I could live with that.
All right.
Okay.
Maybe we'll do that.
Hmm.
Selling out.
I mean.
Well, who are we talking about?
We may not be.
Yeah.
We may be talking about, um, Apple, I don't know.
Oracle.
Yeah.
That's, that's who we're talking about.
I like that.
Yeah.
I don't know.
Dumpster fire.
If I had, if I had, if I had better connections at Microsoft and more time, I would be tempted
to go to build this year and see how much they're talking about open source at build.
That would be fascinating.
Because that's their big developer conference.
Yeah.
Speaking of Microsoft connections, did you get a contact with anybody significant yet?
Um, well, what do you mean?
Because I sent your email over to the contact I have, uh, at, uh, who's a co-host of twight
who's from, who is a Microsoft development head of the graph.
Oh, Lou.
Uh, no, but I've been talking to other people.
Yeah.
I've been talking to other people.
Lou would be a good perspective to have on, uh, on the show with regards to the Microsoft
graph.
So, and he runs a Linux on occasion.
How dare he?
Well, I mean, it is open now with such an Adela.
No, we're just teasing.
We're just teasing.
Sorry.
I see that sense of humor.
Oh, there he is.
There he is.
The moment we've all been waiting for.
Yeah.
Welcome.
Hallelujah.
Hi there guys.
You saw today.
Hooray.
Did I, did I sound bad before?
I don't know.
There was a, there was a week ago or something.
There was that one live stream where your audio was garbage and then we had to, yeah,
we had to ruin that.
We had to bail on the pre on the post show cause it was so bad.
Yeah.
That was last week.
That was, well, no, that was, to be fair, that was not, that was my studio audio.
I was, I was on my laptop or something like that.
Not my fault.
It's not my fault.
I love you though.
Yeah.
I wouldn't go that far.
It wasn't my fault.
It just, you know, you know.
So you're at, you're in your regular old Graham Forks studio, you know, just old boring studio
that's been custom built for you.
Just old boring.
Well actually, so I, I don't know how, I know you get excited more on the studio side of
things than the transmitter side, but we got a new transmitter and this, it's a transmitter
made for Chris.
Chris.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
The whole thing is a web UI.
So you log in and you can set the power and you can turn it on and off.
It's got, it's got so many bells and whistles on the stupid thing.
I get emails from my transmitter now telling me your audio is a little bit low and it's
not modulating quite as much and it's not quite as loud as the, as this station that
I'm listening to.
And so you might want, it's crazy.
Ooh.
It's like, like, what do you mean, what do you mean like it, like the software emails
you?
Like it's not a human.
No.
Yeah.
It's, it's actually, it's a little arm computer that's inside of that process.
It's inside of that transmitter and monitors for a bunch of different things.
And like, even, even like when I show you the interface, even though you're not much
of a, you're, you're not like, I don't, I don't think you, at least I don't think you
get gung ho over like the, the RF side.
You'd look at it and be like, man, that is cool.
I don't even know what that is, but I want to play with it.
Oh, that's a, that's a strong selling point.
Yeah.
I could see that.
I could totally see that.
So what's coming up on the show today?
Oh, we are doing some, we are doing some really exciting things.
We are talking today about all of the tools and software packages and stuff that people
self host on their home servers, on their business servers, and how those tools work,
what the best ones are, what are ones that you might want to stay away from.
And if you don't want to host them yourself, what are some of the alternatives you can
go to, to get some, to, to, to pay somebody to host that stuff, is there a managed provider
that provides that?
Yeah.
I, I've been wanting to do a home server hoedown on the Unplugged program for a few
weeks.
That's, that's, I think I love, I love that topic, something, you know, you can self host
or not.
It's exploding in the industry, which is why it's so interesting to me.
Whoa, really?
Really?
Yeah.
I was, you know, I get monthly sales reports of where we make the most amount of our money
and this month, the only, the one thing that I can say has, that brought in the most money.
If I was to categorize something, it is maintenance support or installation of self hosted services.
Huh?
Good.
I know.
That's also good longterm too, for you.
Yeah.
Yeah, it really is.
I just, you know, there, there are some trends in the IT industry that they got me worried
sometimes.
Yeah.
Well, I'm glad to hear it.
I'm looking forward to it.
Now what else?
Come on.
What else?
Get us excited here.
This is your space.
Give us a tease.
Oh, well, here's the thing.
I can only go so far with, but before, oh, you don't want to reveal live.tv and tune
in.
I'll give you a little bit of a tease.
So have you, have you played with C file yet?
Is that, is that maybe that, that has to be a thing.
You got me close.
You've, you've got me close.
Yeah.
We should do a little demo during Linux Fest.
I think the best way to sell you on C, I think the way to do it, knowing what I know about
you, I feel like I, so first I think I should make the disclaimer, like I'm going to manipulate
you.
I think that's how I excuse myself from the manipulations I talked about.
If I tell you, then you can't be like, oh, he's no, I'm just being upfront.
All right.
So that'll be our, that'll be our, that'll be our system.
I think the way to do it is to just offer it to you as, as if it is a hosted thing that
you could just go sign up for, you know, because you think that's what it takes a service to
get them.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
Now, now say like the thing that's going to trigger me.
So no, I think I will really, what I thought, I think it is, is if I were to put words to
it, I think the words are Chris wants all the benefits of self hosted stuff, but he
doesn't necessarily have the time or the, or the, or the luxury of being able to have
to figure that out unless it's something that he relies on.
So I feel like if you were going to, if you're going to go all in and like base your business
off of it, no doubt you'd host it yourself.
But I feel like for just like, I'm going to try this, not really sure.
I feel like the way you do that is to say, here's a given instance, go play with it,
see what you think.
And then if it works, then you say, okay, now how do I move this onto for myself?
I'm looking forward to that.
And I'm definitely willing to try it because honestly I, you've really kind of sold me
on it.
That, what was it?
Two weeks ago you did an episode on there.
I can't remember, three weeks now.
And you were talking about it.
Oh yeah.
And you were talking about it when we were in person too.
And so that really kind of got me, that really kind of got me sold.
All right, I'll give it a go.
I'll give it a go.
You know, I'm not married to Dropbox.
I just, I think it's done pretty well, but it's expensive and you know, I would imagine
things are going to be changing there now that they filed for an IPO.
Yeah, and the other thing is too, is when I look at the, when I look at the cost and
I start saying, man, the amount of flexibility that you would have with this software thing
over here and the amount of flexibility that you have that I know exists with Dropbox.
And I'm like, I'm looking at some of this stuff and I'm like, man, from a production
standpoint for what you have to do with file syncing and it's just, I don't know, it's
pretty amazing.
Well, isn't, isn't the limitation of self-hosting servers, don't get me wrong.
I love the idea as sort of a hacker, hacker mindset, but isn't the limitation if you need
to access that from outside the, your network, you're limited by your upload speed connection.
Yeah, of course.
But we have ways we've partnered up with some, with some managed hosted providers that I
can, we can get servers now for 25 bucks, two terabyte, four terabyte storage arrays,
you know, eight gigs of RAM and dedicated Xeons for 25 bucks a month.
Like when you start getting to there and you can start putting those servers all over the
US and then you start hooking them together so that one talks to the other and so that
your data starts to basically set up your own little mini CDN, you start getting to
that point and all of a sudden it's like, man, how is Dropbox going to compete with
us?