Brent has been officially initiated into the stay-up-all-night-at-the-studio
cramming to get a project done right before you got a travel club.
Everybody gets to join that at some point.
Yeah, it doesn't come with a lot of perks, really.
There is a jacket, but we have to measure Brent first.
Yeah, we forgot to do that.
But Brent really banged it out with some help from my wife.
Absolutely as well, Hadeah, she helped.
And the two of them stayed up until 3 a.m.
before Brent's flight to build something really special for us.
You got to tell them what it is, Brent.
I don't want to steal your thunder.
Well, I'll just say, you know, originally I was disappointed
because all my flights changed and I wasn't going to be able to do this project.
And then last minute, Chris, I don't know, you must have changed things
so I could manage to build the server rack.
I bought out all the COVID tests around here.
Clearly, I don't know how much you paid for that, but it must have been a lot.
It's probably more than a server rack.
I bought them all out so that way you had to delay your flight
and yeah, it worked out perfectly.
Yeah, we actually, you know, loaded the SUV up with a whole bunch of wood
and went and bought some used casters that are pretty awesome
and built a pretty sweet custom case for all the servers that we have inbound.
So 3 a.m. at the studio. Totally worth it.
Yeah. And now we have a sweet server rack for our server studio data center garage.
I think we're going to need to remember to put some links on the show notes for this one.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. And my name is Brent.
Hello, guys. Both of you are looking sharp and ready to go.
We have a great show.
You know, we've been looking at the data, we've been following the trends,
and we think we've cracked what it really takes to drive Linux user adoption these days.
Like, if we were saying, you know, we're going to need a lot of data,
we're going to need a lot of data, we're going to need a lot of data,
if we were savvy YouTubers, we'd have a zany face,
and our thumbnail would say something like,
don't miss this one trick all distros should be doing.
And it'd be really kind of like attention grabby.
But we think we have something here.
We're going to share with you our hypothesis that we formulated
after some late night binging of server builds.
But before we go any further, before we get into that and the picks and the feedback,
we got to say hello to our virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
What a handsome bunch.
Look at that.
Oh, man.
And they all got matching hats.
Why didn't we get –
Yeah, we weren't clued in.
There's a whole like swag black market happening around the show,
and we're not getting any of that action, you know.
So I'm sure some of them will show up next Sunday,
because next Sunday is our meetup, meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting
if you're in the Pacific Northwest.
We're going to do a little – here's what I think.
I don't know exactly how it's going to go down yet,
because we're always – we're flexible.
We're a couple of wild and crazy guys, so we're easy.
But I'm thinking we do a little meet and greet at 11 a.m.
So start showing up at 11 a.m. is what I'm thinking.
So that probably means you got to get here at like 10.30.
Yeah, yeah.
And then we do a little meet and greet, do some introductions.
I'll have a couple of devices out that I'd like to see if people could get working,
the devices that Brent and I have been playing with recently.
A few meetup challenges to go around.
I like it.
I like many of those devices.
Yeah, actually, you know what I'm looking at?
Here's another one right here.
We could throw that in the pile too.
I got to get these charging though.
You're right.
I just walk through the studio and pick a few up that are sitting around the studio.
Then we'll do the show live, right?
So we'll put the speaker out there.
People can hang out in the living room.
Throw the live stream on the TV.
You got it, right?
And then after we're done with that, we'll go out there.
We'll start cooking it up.
And I encourage people if they got something they can bring with them
that they can heat up in a microwave or an air fryer or oven or on the grill,
bring it with you or if it's cold.
But if you don't, we're going to try to come up with a few things.
And then we'll just do eating and hanging for a bit.
Talk about cryptocurrency, I'm sure, because that always comes up now
anytime you do a public event.
And talk about Linux because whenever we're doing a JB event,
that always comes up too.
So we'd love to see you.
Meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
It'll be happening next week during the live stream.
And, you know, we could probably have the stream going.
I could see that.
People come in.
We'll probably do, you know, a couple of chats on mic.
Have them hot.
Why not?
That could be fun.
Try to capture a bit of the experience.
Yeah.
I know it's limited because it's just up here in the corner of the states.
We are.
But it is the times as they are.
But we are actually formulating plans for a 2022 road trip.
By formulating, I mean we're talking about how we should probably make plans.
That's how far we are in the planning.
The only one is think about needing to think about it.
We got real good intentions.
We sure do.
We got the best intentions.
We have some news to get into.
One of them I just love covering because one of my predictions is already coming true.
How great is this?
Flat Hub is going to verify first party apps and allow developers to collect the monies.
We'll have a link to gaming on Linux here where Liam did a write up that's really good.
And he says Flat Hub is going to gain a way to process and verify apps from first party teams.
As in developers who directly publish their app and manage the Flat Pack package process for Flat Hub.
Not only that, but Gnome want to give developers a way to collect donations and subscriptions too.
Maybe important for sustainability.
Then there's some talk about having a way for developers to share some of that revenue back up with Flat Hub.
So interesting.
That I think is a great idea because Flat Hub is a good service and that listing.
I mean it takes resources to run.
And I think it plays a good important part in the ecosystem.
It looks like there's also going to be a way to distinguish first party publishers and third party publishers.
That's good.
We've discussed this a few times already.
It comes up a lot unfortunately.
So some clarity there.
That's appreciated.
And I think it means I've already won my prediction.
I think.
I mean we don't know the details but I feel like.
See now unfortunately I'm hoping that somehow Flat Hub goes bankrupt in the year.
Flat Hub doesn't exist at the end of the year.
Just so you know.
It's not worth it.
Never mind.
How badly do you want to see me lose?
I've just been so good lately.
I don't know.
Did I do all right?
I can't remember.
But I am very happy to see that news.
And isn't it fascinating that one of the things that's driving Flatback adoption and just sort of user adoption and developer adoption is centralizing on Flat Hub.
But one of the very core issues that people had with snaps was the centralization at Canonical.
This is just a different group with a different kind of centralization.
But because I guess it didn't start here.
We're OK with it.
Or is it just because it's not Canonical.
I'm not sure.
I don't I don't know.
There is a fun.
I mean we're a funny bunch in that sense.
You know it kind of matters the some of the intention some of the philosophy for how we built it.
You know that.
Well we could run our own if we wanted to.
We mostly don't though.
Because why would we want to.
But we can.
OK now I want to talk about the Seuss Liberty Linux announcement.
This has been quite the clown show to watch.
Now our backstory on this just under full disclosure is we've been watching this since I don't know October because there was some data that showed up in the repositories that suggested a distribution named Seuss Liberty Linux was hitting the update repositories in the Apple repositories.
And looking at it it seemed to be maybe there is even a good amount of them.
You know not just like one or two enough to be noticeable.
Yeah yeah.
But this week we got the announcement of Seuss Liberty Linux and it's not a Linux distribution.
It is a support offering.
I've been a fan of Seuss recently but I have to say this is one of the more hilarious boondoggles in Linux recently.
So they announced Seuss Liberty Linux which on its own sounds like a Linux distribution.
It does.
Yeah yeah.
It turns out it's a support offering that supports Seuss systems and RHEL based systems like CentOS.
You know those mixed Linux environments.
They use the offering of breaking you free of lock-in as like the main value pitch of the platform.
But the entire claim is ironic because if it was locked in they wouldn't be able to offer the Seuss Liberty service in the first place.
So it clearly shows there isn't lock-in and that you can use different vendors like Tuxcare or others.
Was that ever surprising?
No. And so that's ironic too.
But then here's the other thing is nobody knew if it was a Linux distribution or not because it was the worst kept secret.
Everybody knew there was a distro in the works for a bit.
And clearly all of the marketing and all of the communication language and the branding is Seuss Liberty Linux.
So when it launched there were even Seuss employees on Reddit claiming it was a Linux distribution.
And kind of embarrassingly the register ran with the headline that reads,
Seuss announces something for those who missed the old CentOS Liberty Linux.
And the whole pitch was it's their new distro and they say it seems to be based on a rebuild of CentOS 8.
Although how they knew that since there was no distro released is anyone's guess.
And everyone was confused by this and it's hilarious.
And I have a little bit of bacon.
Oh fry it up.
Before I get to it, do you have any thoughts on this entire boondoggle since we've been watching this since the beginning?
No, I mean it just does.
Hearing you sort of go over it right now.
Okay, trying to laugh a little less.
It's unfortunate that there's not very clear communication here.
You know like that's too bad.
Maybe some folks will actually find this new product offering useful.
Trying to look at that part of it seriously, it's just kind of unfortunate that that's all going to kind of get ignored for what we're talking about now.
Right, and then to kind of add to the kind of funny launch.
It may not even still be, but the day that they launched it when Wes and I were going over everything to really try to put this all together.
Because we wanted to get our first take in LAN right.
What was this?
Right, we didn't want to go out of the gate calling it a distro because it's not.
But like at the time they launched it, I couldn't even see a way to buy it.
Like they talk about it on their website like you can buy it online from the SUSE online store.
But when you go there it's not actually offered in the drop down of product offerings.
And you didn't, I tried to get you to, but you didn't seem interested in scheduling a call with them.
So I wouldn't be surprised if the sales aren't off the hook.
But I could see existing.
It's still 404 in at least this product page.
They changed the URL slugs for products.
So the link in the announcement, originally they edited it now.
But originally it had a singular word product in the slug.
But the URL is actually products with a plural.
Yeah, yeah.
See that's just unfortunate too.
So there's that and then you have the whole issue of why did everybody think it was a distro?
Like why did everybody get it wrong?
Besides the messaging just being totally wrong and the way they describe it, it sounds like a distro at first.
I got my theory.
Here's my bacon about this.
I think it was a distro.
I think it was a distro until about the end of the year.
And then they pivoted strategy because maybe somebody listened to LAN or maybe it just became obvious or, you know, enough momentum build up.
But this was my take in LAN when we first talked about this rumor.
And I think it all kind of holds out.
Everything makes sense if this was going to be a distribution and it was going to be part of this offering, right?
It was going to be part of the support services.
So if you wanted to get this, you could manage your SOO systems, CentOS systems.
And if you wanted to just maintain compatibility and not jump into stream, you could use their CentOS 8 rebuild.
That is what they were going to do.
But then they realized they would be creating the same exact paradox that Red Hat found themselves in, right?
Red Hat had a problem where the thing that paid the bills was also be given away for free.
And it was basically engineering versus sales.
And you're never going to resolve that kind of conflict.
Eventually, sales is going to win because sales has numbers they have to hit.
They have a KPI they got to hit and they got to deliver results.
So eventually that machine turns inward and looks for where they're giving away the milk for free.
And they stopped that.
That's exactly what SUSE was about to start doing.
They were about to start giving away for free a rebuild of CentOS that competes with SUSE Enterprise Linux.
And how the hell can you charge a premium, which they do charge a premium, for SUSE Enterprise Linux if you're giving away CentOS for free?
It just doesn't make any sense.
And I think they had to have that conversation internally and they realized it's a lot harder to fix this once we make this launch.
And we'll just end up committing the same exact crime in communities' eyes that Red Hat did.
This had to be the conversation.
This is our chance to not make the mistake.
We got to make this decision before we release it because once the cat's out of the bag, once the genie's out of the bottle, it's really embarrassing to put it back in.
It gets worse from that, right?
If you think about it, the other aspect of this that I don't think a lot of people think about is that those sales pay those engineers, right?
So it gets – what's the word I would use for this?
Particularly sadistic or masochistic.
Masochistic, that's it.
When you do this to yourself because then you wind up in a situation where those people that build those things that you enjoy for free aren't getting paid to keep doing it and so they can't.
And that makes things super, super complicated.
Yeah, that's complicated is a good way to put it.
So this SUSE Liberty thing, I know it sounds confusing.
It's not a dis or at least not yet.
Maybe that's still part of the plan.
Who knows?
We're going to keep an eye on things.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Now I kind of feel like you should do this one.
Somebody wrote in and said have Wes do the Linode read.
I wonder if you've heard me do it enough that you could do a Linode read.
So it's Linode.com slash unplugged.
Go there for $100 in 60-day credit and support the show obviously.
I mean you've got to support the show.
But why use Linode, Wes?
Oh, there's so many good reasons.
I mean one, it's kind of a – it's one of the services that Chris can use reliably, you know?
You don't have – you can interface with all kinds of programmatic APIs and fancy command line clients.
But also –
You could use your Kubernetes.
You can use your Kubernetes, yeah.
But you can also just spin up, you know, Linux machines.
As soon as you want.
They've got like the distros that you probably already want to run.
I mean oftentimes –
All the distros really.
It's easier, you know, if there's a new server release.
I don't need to bother with something on my laptop because Linode's got the distro.
They've just released it.
It's on Linode.
You can just boot it up right there.
Yeah, you want to go play with Stream?
It's on there.
You want to try Alma?
You know what else we use the heck out of?
That block storage.
I mean do we store things any other way at this point?
No, probably not.
I mean if you want to mess around with disks and partitions like an animal from the 90s, you could.
That does not sound like our style.
No.
There's so many great reasons to use it.
Plus did you know, Wes, you might not have known this.
Best customer support in the business.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
All the time.
They're available for you when you need them.
And 30 to 50 percent cheaper than those big hyperscalers that are just trying to vendor
Lucky in anyways.
Yeah.
And when you look at some of those hyperscalers, they've got everything.
There's no way to tell like is this a good product?
Is this one of your like premier things or just a random offering you have to be competitive?
And I feel like with Linode, the things that they offer, they're really going to stand behind.
You nailed it.
You know why?
They've been doing this for 18 years, almost 19 years now.
And like legitimately 20 years on the internet is like 100 years in real life.
Maybe even more.
Same as dog rules, right?
Yeah.
Maybe even more, man.
Like 20 years doing something on the internet is mind blowing.
They were really in on this stuff early and they just made a great product.
And you know, they're independently owned.
They didn't have to go the crazy VC funding route.
They got 11 data centers around the world and they've been supporting the hell out
of Linux media now for like almost two years.
They've also got some pretty great out of band access for when you really break your
machine.
Not that I've had to use that.
No.
Like when you want to load some crazy image on there that they don't have in the dropdown,
you can actually get it done.
Yeah.
They're not going to artificially limit you.
They're ready to get weird with it.
We have.
We have gotten really weird with it.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
All right.
Well, if there was one trick to win over Linux users, maybe we've discovered it.
I don't actually think it's us.
I kind of say all this tongue in cheek.
Well, we've crunched the data, done our research and maybe, maybe noticed a trend.
I don't know.
I'm not too serious.
But I think we found something of a draw for Linux users.
Yeah.
What they're looking for in a distro.
I think so.
In 2022.
At least a large percentage of Linux users.
I think it's almost beginning to trend depending on what data sets you.
Yeah.
You know, it's hard to generalize.
We're not trying to say this is true for everyone.
Yeah.
To understand where we're going with this, you got to come take a stroll with us through
Linux Mint 20.3.
What?
Yeah.
So this is going to get us to our point.
20.3 came out recently and it's a nice looking release.
Brent, I think probably has the most experience with Mint as a former longtime user.
So I think we should start with you and your impressions on 20.3.
Unfortunately, I didn't get to spend like a week or two with it, which I probably would
have loved to.
Hey, not yet anyway.
Not yet.
There you go.
But I do have a long history with Linux Mint.
When I first started, I used Subuntu for like, I don't know, six months or something and
then was desiring a little bit more and landed on Linux Mint.
This was probably, I don't know, five plus years ago, maybe even more than that.
And I used it for a few years.
I even tried their Linux Mint Debian edition for a while, which is their sort of rolling
release cadence edition.
And I liked it.
Eventually it felt, I've been trying for years to sum up why I moved away from Linux Mint
and I think it's because it felt like there were some restrictions on it.
It's almost like Mac in that if you're doing what they want you to, it works great.
If you're trying to do anything outside of what they want you to, then it becomes a little
bit of a challenge.
But at the same time, I was really interested in jumping back in.
It's been several years and I think I do have this fondness for Linux Mint, even though
I haven't thought of it for several years.
So jumping in was interesting because Cinnamon feels exactly like it used to, which was really
kind of nice.
It actually felt like coming home in a sense.
And then when I poked around, I started discovering, oh yeah, yeah, yeah, there's all these like
defaults that are seem sane and are pretty lovely for, you know, what they advertise
on their website, which is that most of their users come straight from Windows.
And I think that's a really reasonable approach.
But as I dug in, I started remembering all of those limitations that just felt, I don't
know, not quite our style these days, maybe.
And so I got mixed feelings.
I think that's fair.
I agree with everything you said.
It really is iterative improvements with Mint, which means that if you've taken a few years
off from trying it, and I also tried the Cinnamon edition, and you sit down and try it, I really
can perceive the improvements over time.
I felt specifically from just the last release to this release, out of the box, high DPI
support is nice.
The GTK theme is cleaner.
And so I, just as a thought experiment, because I haven't been using Mint for a while, I first
installed the previous release, brought that all up to date, used that for a day, and then
wiped it and installed 20.3 and immediately just wrote down my thoughts on the differences
just to kind of get an idea of what kind of improvements.
And for the most part, it's like new apps, like the new things app and the high DPI support
out of the box is really nice.
I also felt that Cinnamon was greatly improved from the time I'd used it previously, a little
less shiny, like less transparencies and window effects.
But now it feels very solid, really stable.
I didn't have any crashes.
I even threw a bunch of widgets in the menu because I used to always be a surefire way
to crash it.
But no, it did fine.
It really does kind of now hit that sweet spot between Plasma and Gnome.
There's rough bits still.
The app store feels really low effort, like they're just shipping the default and not
putting any curation in there.
Like when you go, for example, right now on mine, when you look at the editor's picks,
there's half a dozen apps that are listed in this editor's picks as if somebody hand
selected these.
But then there's two entries for wine with two different icons and one's version 3.7
and one's version 4.0 and I can't really determine which one is like the one they consider the
default because it doesn't expose that information.
And there's no flat hub, there's no flat hub integration.
So that kind of stuff I was a little disappointed to see, but I could see them adding that stuff
over time.
But what I'm really impressed by is if you get out of your head as a long time Linux
user, and you look at this as somebody who's just trying to get some damn work done, they
have really nice things in there like a USB image writer is installed by default, an application
called backup is installed by default, and it's a decent little app.
We've talked about time shift before.
They have just system diagnostic and information, you just click that, it's in there, it's obvious,
and they've managed to keep it uncluttered, which is impressive because you could see
adding all these little tools and these X apps over time would really clutter things
up.
They managed to keep it pretty clean and kind of decide when to pull things out as well.
So because they've done this iterative work, and they've been evolving all of this stuff
for a while, and they've been able to keep up in this release with some of the more recentish
GTK trends.
I mean, of course now GNOME 42 is out, and Libidwadi is now a thing, and they're nowhere
near that.
But...
You're right.
I mean, in the longer view sense, it was nice to see the dark style support and some
added accent colors and stuff.
None of that was there the last time I tried Cinnamon.
Right, yeah.
And it's just all...
I could go over to the advanced side and turn on experimental fractional scaling.
Oh, right.
And I think I'm running to 140 or some weird number, but it actually looks fine.
It doesn't look blurry.
They did a good job, and that kind of day-to-day steak and potatoes thing somebody needs from
a desktop computer like it used to always be, it really kind of feels like they're nailing
all that stuff while not getting sucked into the technology stack of the week kind of situation.
I'm curious on your thoughts, though.
I think I agree.
There's a lot of elements that stand out as being thoughtfully looked after.
And then there are some holes where they're just missing pieces.
I liked a lot of the welcome experience.
It detected and asked about, did I need to improve my video driver situation, which I
thought was pretty nice.
And there's just a few things kind of like prompting you to set things up.
Although once you start diving into, say, snapshots or the firewall, you do kind of
run out of rope on having your hand held.
So I think some of this stuff is maybe more easy in the welcome screen for someone who's
really just switching from Windows, and then it gets advanced kind of quickly.
But I can't fault them for that.
Those are just complicated topics.
In the past, you know, I did use Cinnamon a lot on a work machine that I had to do a
boot with Windows.
And so that kind of, you know, the interface style matched up pretty well, and it wasn't
a machine I customized.
I was just curious to revisit.
Could I just could I use it as a boring old workstation?
And yeah, I think it still works pretty nicely for that.
It's somewhere in between, you know, maybe the pure simplicity of a GNOME experience.
You get some of the plasma things, but without having as much customization to maybe need
or be tempted to do, because that's exactly where I think I would still deploy Cinnamon
is.
In an environment where I just want to forget about the DE, you know, it's not ugly enough
to be offensive.
I can just forget about it.
Gets out of your way, but does have some power features when you want it.
It is interesting also, we mentioned sort of catching up in the, you know, the GTK world,
but catching up on the Ubuntu derivative world, when I was going through the, you know, the
boring old installer, I don't mean that in a bad way, but just the boring old installer
still knows EFS.
You know, you just get ext4 if you don't go with LVM, right?
Maybe wonder what's gonna happen with that flutter transition?
Is Mint keeping the sold version?
Are they gonna adopt where Canonical goes?
I bet they don't.
Yeah.
Good question.
I wonder.
I mean, I'm kind of tired of that installer.
I mean, it sure does work, but I feel like I've been using it for about 10 years.
I don't know.
But I guess it gets the job done, right?
It'd be nice to see some like advanced options around ZFS or ButterFest, but I get that's
not their demo.
And I gotta take that into consideration.
So here's where we're going with this.
Even with all of this said, you know, it's the steak and potatoes.
It is the, what is on the label is what you get Linux distribution.
It's a great landing spot for Windows users.
And I think that makes sense for a lot of us, but there's still an element that's missing
that seems to be drawing users away from Mint at a rapid pace.
So much so that they seem to be attempting to address this over the last year or so.
And I wasn't familiar with this until I went digging around, but I've discovered that Mint
is now publishing Edge ISOs.
Have you seen this?
Yeah.
They've done it for the last couple of releases.
And it is simply a version of Linux Mint with newer kernel drivers, a newer kernel.
Like right now they are shipping 5.4 in Mint, but in the Edge version they're shipping 5.13,
which has a bunch of nice improvements in there.
And we talked a little bit about this on Linux Action News.
So for an expanded look on this, it's worth listening to that, but boilingsteam.com ran
a post and the headline is this.
All roads lead to Arch, the evolution of Linux distros used for gaming over time.
And you look at the data from ProtonDB and from Steam, and it seems kind of obvious.
Linux users are migrating over time in considerable numbers away from Ubuntu and Debian and Mint.
Those are taking it the hardest.
And they're moving over to Arch Linux, Manjaro, Garuda Linux, and Endeavor OS.
Boilingsteam writes, Arch has gained progressively, some share solidly now at 20% for several
months, but the whole landscape looks a lot like Arch derivatives now.
Manjaro is almost as big as Arch itself, and Garuda Linux and Endeavor OS are 6 to 7% of
the mix.
In effect, almost half of the gamers on ProtonDB are running some form of Arch.
And when you look at the data trend, which they visualized here, we'll have a link in
the show notes over the years, you just see a steady progression of Arch over and over.
And it isn't really even kind of like a, it's not like a huge jump, it's just this slow
and steady, it does seem to speed up as we get closer to now.
What do you think this is?
Do you think it's the Arch user repository, Wes?
There's probably a lot of things, you know, we've kind of mentioned maybe the, what could
be perceived as a lack of investment or excitement around the Ubuntu desktop.
There's probably also an element of some of these Arch derivatives being more explicit
about marketing to gamers and having a lot of improved experience around just getting
up and going and having a system that's like ready to game.
So there's probably a few factors maybe combining, and Arch is just fun.
Yeah, I think you're right.
And I think that one of those factors, which is what Linux Mint recognized is newer kernels
because people want newer drivers and they want newer drivers because they're switching
over to Linux to try it for gaming and they want the best frame rate, the best performance,
the best hardware support possible.
And while I was on Mint, I tried out the tool called Mainline.
So there used to be this Ubuntu kernel picker that would use the canonical PPA and install
a mainline kernel, but that developer quit work on the project, I guess.
But there's Mainline now.
It's a command line app that you install and it makes it really simple to list all of the
available kernels for your system.
And then you can just do like a mainline install latest.
Oh, cute.
Like a little kernel manager right there for you.
Exactly.
And it takes care of getting the right headers and the build files and doing all the boot
manager stuff and it all makes sure it gets pulled down from canonicals PPA.
So it's a legit source.
And so last night on my Mint box, and you could do this, you wouldn't have to get the
edge ice or you could do this on Ubuntu.
I installed kernel 516 using this tool.
Oh, look at you.
But hey, I mean, there's some stuff in Proton, you know, for Proton in there.
So why not?
You get the few tech stuff.
And here's the reality now is you get this really nice, tried and true, slowly iterated
Cinnamon Mint desktop that isn't going to change on end users very much.
And with this kind of tool, or you could do it yourself, you could get the latest kernel
and you get a lot of benefits that way.
And I think users are just opting to go with distributions that do it for themselves.
And I think even canonical sees this.
They see what's going on with these trends because they're hiring a Linux desktop gaming
product manager right now.
And canonical wants to, quote, make Ubuntu the best Linux desktop for gaming.
And they want to, quote, work with partners in the Silicon world to ensure the latest
graphics drivers and tweaks are built in for optimal frame rates and latency.
Well, how do you do that?
You got to get their code upstream in the Linux kernel.
So that means you have to ship a new kernel, right?
That's what the deck has to solve that you can have all this code going to Linux kernel.
But if you're shipping five dot four, it doesn't matter.
It's all it's not in a kernel that you're shipping anymore.
So canonical can't solve this problem.
They can't work with this is from their job post, quote, work with partners in the Silicon
world to ensure the latest graphics drivers and tweaks are built in.
They can't do that.
And they also say they want to work with mechanisms such as anti-cheat capabilities and make sure
that they are available to ensure fairness and product availability for Ubuntu users.
They're not going to do that again unless they work with an upstream kernel because
some of that stuff is landing in the kernel, thanks to Collabra.
I mean, I suppose you do have what you have hardware enablement, you got PPAs, but does
that just not have a different lack of appeal to feel more of a as an afterthought?
Well, I think if you look at why people are deploying Manjaro or Garuda, it's because
it's just the default.
It's defaults rule supreme.
You got that.
Plus, then you got, well, they're not testing against it, right?
Like the idea is these other distros are building their distro with the idea that you're going
to have the latest kernel like Fedora, but, you know, the Ubuntu developers aren't.
They're assuming you're using the kernel they're shipping.
I would imagine that probably factors into some people's thinking.
But you know, it kind of makes it more appealing to me to use an Ubuntu or a Mint with a newer
kernel.
There must be a downside, though.
So if somebody knows linuxunplug.com slash contact, I assume stuff breaks at some point.
You know, like I could see maybe virtualization or container software thinking you have the
wrong version of the kernel.
I think you just have to try it and find out.
So I'd like to know what you think of our growing hypothesis here that it's perhaps
gaming that's driving this change.
Like it is so common now for people to start recommending things like Pop or Manjaro, especially
in the YouTube community.
Like we just saw that with the recent Linux challenge.
People just a couple of years ago led with Ubuntu.
Like do you remember however many years ago when Noah and I did the Linux switch challenge?
How long ago was that?
Was that 2016?
Maybe.
I mean, it was just it was never a debated topic.
The USB thumb drives that we were handing out had Ubuntu on them.
It wasn't even a debate.
And it made the most sense because it had the largest network effect.
And I still think it makes probably the best new user distro when you consider that.
Because when you are on Windows, you have the whole world of software and everyone else
is using what you're using.
So there's tons of guides and information, but when you switch to Linux, it's a smaller
circle.
Yeah.
And you haven't learned the right terms to Google yet.
So you got to hope that, you know, the generic results match and that's Ubuntu.
And Ubuntu is the biggest supported one out there.
And so I still actually think if new users are going to use Linux, I mean, you know,
Pop and Manjaro get really close because they're the same structure and all of that.
But it is interesting how, you know, for the existing Linux user anyway, like, I guess
I have to admit that as gaming has so rapidly improved, again, we still have a long way
to go, of course.
But now that gaming is so viable, I suppose I might consider thinking about that more
for my desktop install.
Where in the past, you know what I mean, like I might have a dedicated system or I might
just not care about that so much because I would just do casual gaming.
But if it's really easy to do some pretty good gaming, then yeah, right.
Maybe suddenly that's something you're interested in changing.
Well, you and I have been following the kernel development pretty closely for the last year
and a half.
And the thing is, there's a lot of cool performance improvements landing on Linux kernel right
now.
There's been some recent major performance work gone into there.
We cover that stuff in LAN and it makes me so stoked to run a newer kernel.
I want that.
There's a lot of things.
Totally is.
All right.
We can cover, we can follow this up in the post show.
So if you got comments, save it for that or go to linuxunplug.com slash contact and
let us know.
You think we're crazy.
You think we're onto something here.
I'd like to hear your opinion on it.
We do have a spot of housekeeping around here.
I want to say, first of all, thank you so much to our members, UnpluggedCore.com or
our network supporters at Jupiter.party.
You get access to the full live stream, like everything.
It's a whole other show in there, plus no like cutting stuff out, no swearing.
It's like raw, man.
Probably shouldn't put it out there, but we do and we make it available for you in a feed.
But if you're, and if you're a network member, you get access to all of the shows ad free
out there.
Also, I want to say thank you to the people who've been using the new value for value
payments in their podcast app via lightning.
We got helipads set up this week and now we can read messages as they boost in real time.
It's so cool.
And it makes a little pew pew sound when people boost.
So if you have no idea what I'm talking about, you can go to newpodcastapps.com and go get
yourself a new podcast app.
But it looks like the most popular one amongst our audience is the fountain podcast app.
Yeah, I'm trying to myself.
And it is a pretty interesting app.
And what's neat about it is they have this little boost mode.
You hit that and you can leave a message and it tells us what episode you're listening
to, which is that's a bit of data we've never gotten before.
Yeah.
Less people self report, right?
But yeah.
Yeah.
Oh my God.
That's so cool.
Like it was like all of a sudden we were sitting there and we were working really late.
It was like eight or nine o'clock on a Sunday.
And we had we pulled this thing up and right then somebody sent in a boost.
And it was like all of our moods.
I called Brenton from the garage.
He was working.
He was working on the rack.
I called Brenton.
We all like looked at the boost because the first time we brought a helipad and it changed
our night.
You know, it's not like it's like it's not a bunch of money, right?
They're just a few sats.
But it's so cool to see those messages coming in real time as people are listening.
Yeah.
And some of you are so sweet.
Yeah, there was some really nice messages in there, too.
And helipad lets us read them.
So that's pretty neat.
I think we'll do that on future live streams.
Our community on Matrix has grown like crazy.
Linux Unplugged dot com slash Matrix, if you want to join that, we'd love to have you join
us over there.
And we have several rooms.
We have rooms for each of the show.
We have a crypto chat where people are having rational, level headed, honest conversations
about crypto currencies, even during a crash.
And all that's going down at Linux Unplugged dot com slash Matrix.
And you can join us over there.
And I suppose I'll plug the fact that we'd love to have you join our Mumble room because
we got the Luplug.
We've got this year's show that we do live.
We do other events in Mumble.
Details Linux Unplugged dot com slash Mumble.
And you can hang out with us on Tuesdays.
We've been doing a little live stream here and there.
And every now and then we put them out as an extra, too.
Hey, it's just a, you know, a friendly community of nerdy people.
That's right.
What's not to like?
So the air the airline lost Brent's mailbag.
You hear about this?
No.
Yeah.
Those airlines, you just can't trust them.
Yeah, I guess I still don't really understand why you're putting all of the feedback out
on that thermal printer and carrying it around with you.
We could just save it on security, security, Chris.
Maybe.
OK, I guess.
Just doesn't seem like a good way to do it, Brent.
You know, I will say I had to start my fire with something and I ran out of fire starters
and you know, just saying.
We do have a pick for you this week, though.
This is so cool.
Like if it was just one of these, it'd be worth it for the pick segment.
But this is a suite of tools called SSH tools.
Yeah, you heard me.
That's right.
And the first one alone, I feel like, is completely pick worthy.
It's called SSH ping and it checks to see if a host is reachable via SSH.
Like are your log in failing?
Is there is it, you know, denying you and is the syntax is exactly what you'd expect.
So SSH ping, then the number of times, so like dash three for three pings and then the
host.
And then it checks to see if it can get connected on that port and it tells you like the same
kind of output you get from ping.
Yeah, it looks just the same.
And over here, my terminal, it's got some nice colors, too.
So that's handy.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
A few other nice tools, though.
Like I'm just I'm like an SSH fax.
Yes.
And that's just, you know, what's what's the deal with this machine print out a handy little
print out about what the service running, disks available, memory, that kind of thing.
That is my that is my other favorite one.
It's also just a great way to figure out what your machines are advertising via SSH.
So that one is really cool.
So that one's called SSH dash fax.
And then, of course, there's also SSH host keys, which prints the server host keys in
a couple of different ways to read that.
You got SSH key info in here, a bunch of other ones, including SSH force, which enforces
password authentication, even if they do have a key.
I mean, all that stuff.
It's really neat.
And they have packages for a bunch of different distros, including 2204 and a bunch of other
systems.
So we'll have a link to that in the show notes.
Also, it's just bash so you can download it from GitHub if that's your style.
Oh, look at you.
Is that what you did?
I assume.
Indeed.
That sounds like US pain.
You maniac.
I have no idea what we're going to talk about next week because I haven't been able to square
like how are we going to do a meetup and an episode like, right.
So we're going to figure that out.
I don't know exactly because I think so.
I think we're going to homework now.
Yeah.
So that's going to be our that's going to be our job.
But if you can make it, we'd love to see you come hang out with maybe bring a topic as
well as a snack.
That would be pretty great.
But I know it's such a it's such a long shot for people to make it.
But honestly, we just really want to see people.
It's been a while.
That's how long I can make it between road trips and meetups and stuff.
I've made my.
The audience is amazing.
And we miss you.
That's true.
All right.
And we'd love to hear more from you to Linux.
Unplugged dot com slash contact.
We'll probably have your feedback next week.
You can also join us live.
We do this now on Sundays.
You start around noon Pacific.
See you next week.
Same bad time, same bad station.
And be sure to catch Linux action news to find out everything that's going on now.
It's released on Thursdays and we're capturing what's going on right there in the week.
I'm liking it.
Turns out we really nailed the kind of timing as far as the news cycle goes.
It's been nice.
And we'd love to have you join us.
Linux action news dot com.
We put it out every single week.
Links to what we talked about today at Linux unplugged dot com.
What else, Wes?
What else do we got to mention?
Hmm.
Live.
Did that.
If it's been a while since you checked out the extras feed, now's the time to catch up.
No kidding.
That is.
See, the man knows.
Extras dot show for that.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode and we'll see you right back here
next Sunday.
Hey, Brent, could you step over a little closer here?
We need to.
Yeah, I got to get in the cone.
The cone of silence.
We got a we got a major problem, guys.
Major problem.
I didn't want the audience to hear this.
There's a leak is there?
No, no.
That would be a big problem.
But I don't I don't I don't want to tell the audience this, but I don't think the Sunday
crew is as good at making the titles like the Tuesday crew was.
I don't want to throw shade.
I know how they're going to take that.
So I don't know what we should.
We got to come up with a way to inspire them.
Some sort of title contest.
I mean, this title is.
Are you seeing this?
Yeah.
Anyways, we got a post show to do.
The cone of silence.