This is Linux Unplugged Episode 4 for September 3rd, 2013.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, pour yourself a cold one, because honestly this show probably
makes a lot more sense if you've had a few drinks, otherwise it sounds like a couple
Linux users rambling about using Linux.
My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
Hey Matt, so we made it to four episodes, that's a month solid man, that's awesome.
So I was just telling the, well I was just about to tell the story, I thought, no wait,
I'll share it on air because it's embarrassing enough that I should share it with the audience.
So when my wife was pregnant, you know one of the things preggo ladies do is they like
to have certain foods, right, they want to have a food, for my wife it was citrusy flavors.
So lemonade was perfect, it's summertime, it's hot outside, let's get some lemonade
going on in this house.
I got hooked Matt, I got hooked on lemonade, like I've never been hooked on it, every day
gotta have a little lemonade.
Oh this glass of water doesn't have any lemonade in it, I'll fix that, pour a little, you
know.
Yeah, gotta have lemonade, so I'm mixing it with everything, so I'm at the grocery store
doing the shopping because the wife was on bed rest, and I'm like, we got a lot of lemonade
at home, look at this, lemonade vodka, didn't know that was a thing, I mean I've never tried
it, I knew it was a thing, but I've never tried it.
So I grabbed myself a big bottle of lemonade vodka, or lemon vodka, and it turns out you
could pour like half of that into a cup and pour half the other half with lemonade, go
half and half and it's just a delicious treat Matt, well, I had two of those like a week
ago, and I'm still feeling a little hungover from that, just a little bit.
Oh yeah, well vodka doesn't play around, especially if you get the good stuff.
Well I did not get the good stuff I don't think, I think it was being sold in the grocery
store.
Alright so we have a fun show today, one of the things that's new is we've dialed into
a new mumble server, we called up on our 56k modems and called in, and no we got it set
up, it's now hosted on Scale Engine, PriceTX has been working, took us off, got it all
dialed in, we were on a hosted solution, the Arbulous had set up for us that was awesome,
but we kept hitting user limits.
Turns out people wanted to hang out and chat with each other while we were doing the show,
they wanted to be involved with the show, and it was a lot more popular than we expected,
so now we're on a new mumble box at TS.JupiterColony.com, and hopefully somebody in the IRC chat room
will paste the port in there, but it's on a funky port.
I'll try to put it in the show notes, because it's going to be open 24-7, so if you guys
just want to hang out, it's essentially kind of like, it's an adjunct to the IRC, it's
always going.
And we got rooms in there for every show, we got general hangout rooms, so we're going
to jump in there, we've got an on-air channel now, it's port 64-734, which by the way, if
you just highlight that line that Tox put in the IRC, and then you open the mumble client,
it will automatically detect that on your clipboard and fill it into the server settings
for mumble.
It's really nice.
That's kind of slick, right?
Yeah, that's, you know, that's an application you can really feel like was meant for the
Linux desktop.
Yeah, I like that.
And that audio ducking thing they do, it feels like that Linux version of mumble is a first
class Linux desktop application.
Makes me excited what we might see in the future.
Oh, definitely.
So, we're going to chat with one of the, Ray, one of the folks that's in there.
He's replaced Dropbox with InkFS, and I think Git, and a couple other things, he's sort
of put these things together, he's wrote up a good post about it, and we caught it in
our subreddit and said, let's talk to you, so he's come on, he's joined us, it's like
11pm where he's at right now, and he's had a heck of a day.
Today was one of those days, Matt, so on Friday I went to PAX, as you know, and while I'm
at PAX, go figure, my phone starts buzzing.
And I look down, hey, can you give us a call, we have an emergency.
And so the way this works is, I don't have any clients that I go to on a regular basis
anymore, but in a few circumstances, if their main IT guy is out, and then their backup
guy is out, and they're really, really screwed, they'll call me.
I'm like third guy in line, and if you're calling Chris, at that point, you're really
screwed, right?
At that point, you really don't want to be the guy going in.
Oh, so true, man, so true.
So there I am at PAX, and I'm getting the third guy call, and I'm like, oh no, this
is bad, this is real bad.
So I ended up working out a schedule with them, and worked them through some problems
Friday night, then Monday was Labor Day, a holiday here, so they were closed, thankfully,
so I was able to do code radio and all that.
Go in there this morning, first thing, I roll in there at 8.30 a.m., and they've been down
now for three days, essentially, they went down roughly Wednesday night, Thursday morning,
they were down all day Thursday, all day Friday, and they are under contract with Washington
State to have certain things posted on their website within four hours of receiving it
from the state.
Oh, that's not good.
Or they're in violation of this contract, right, and that's a huge revenue source, right?
So if they violate that contract, then the contract goes up for bid, they lose it, and
then they lose like 70% of their funding.
So of course, everything's on the line.
And that was my morning, and I got in there, it's this whole custom scripted up system
using R-Sync and NFS mounts all over the place, every server's got a mount to every
other server, R-Sync's running, GNU parallel running all up in this place, it was, I mean,
it is a spider's web of automation, Matt.
It sounds like a mess.
It was a mess.
So before we get to talking with Ramy and do a couple of follow-up items, I wanted to
do a quick public service announcement, speaking of things that are fantastic and optimized.
Today, just before we went on air for Linux Unplugged, the Jupyter Broadcasting browser
plugins for Chrome and Firefox, which are linked to the bottom of our website, were
updated.
Now, first thing you should probably know is, at least in Chrome, not sure about Firefox,
it's requesting permissions, so you have to go in there and re-enable it, it'll be under
the little hamburger menu, the little three-line button, that's officially, by the way, being
called the hamburger button.
The hamburger button.
So yeah, you click that, there'll be a notification, and the reason why, it is requesting new permissions,
and it's very vague with the way they make it look, but the reason is, we've made it
a little more polite.
So now, if you're on somebody else's website and they have an Amazon affiliate link and
you click it, our extension will not override that, it'll detect that, and it'll be graceful
about it.
So that requires permission changes for that to happen, but that's one of the things.
And then we've added woot.com, so now if you're shopping at woot.com and you have our browser
extension installed, we will get a portion of your shopping session, which is awesome.
And then on the Firefox side of things, I'm not positive if you have to re-enable it or
not, I haven't tried it on my Firefox install yet, but we have Firefox integration improvements,
performance improvements, and goodies as well, of course, there's woot and all that stuff
over there as well.
So new extensions being updated today, so your browser will probably get the update,
and if you don't know about this yet, these are open source extensions, we have them linked
up on GitHub in the Linux Action Show show notes, or you go to jbdev.... Where was that?
I can't remember, there's a jbdev site I have linked to on the show notes, and those are
posted up on GitHub, they're open source, and we've actually got a good amount of people
now, this is so funny, when we launched these extensions, I said, well let's go open source
so that way people know we're not doing anything shady and anything like that, and if people
want to use them, they can, that's fine.
And people didn't necessarily think that was a good idea because there are other podcasts
networks that take them, right?
Oh, right.
Exactly.
Yeah, I mean that happens, but the other thing that's been really interesting is it's been
big in churches.
Oh.
So, I've heard from several people that are grabbing it for their church, setting it up
and coding it for an affiliate code for their church, and then the people, the members of
that church, when they shop at home, are using a modified version of the Jupiter Broadcasting
extension to benefit the church.
That's clever.
Yeah, so I thought that was kind of a neat use of it.
So there you go, so you can find links to those linked at the very bottom of jupitabroadcasting.com,
and then when you have those installed, they just automatically take your shopping session
at Amazon, Newegg, Woot, Monoprice, eBay, lots of popular sites, and then it helps keep
us on the air.
All right, well I'm going to unmute our Mumble channel here and say hi to the folks in the
Mumble room, and specifically I want to welcome Remi to the show.
He's been a contributor to the network for a while, he's sent in emails to many of the
shows, and he's active in our subreddits.
Remi, welcome to the show.
Good evening, Chris.
So now, did I have it right, it's about 11 p.m. where you're at right now?
Yes, that's correct.
It's now just 11, 9 p.m. in the Netherlands.
Well I know that you were fighting server outages all day, so I appreciate you joining
us after the day of hell that you've had.
And you caught my attention, I think it was last week when you submitted a blog post about
your encrypted file synchronization solution.
Can you tell us what it is and what tech you're using?
Okay, yes, it's correct.
I just recently bought a Chromebook and I used Spideroak, which is a locally encryption
and then upload to the cloud.
And it doesn't work on ARM, and I have an ARM Chromebook, so I had an issue.
I was already having issues with Spideroak because of RAM usage, because I have over
90,000 files in there and it doesn't really like that.
Wow.
I've also tried Oowala, and it's also a local encryption and then dump the blobs in cloud
tool.
And it also had RAM issues, and so I was looking for something else.
And I already use AnkaFest, AnkaFest is a user space tool that mounts your local folder
and you have an encrypted folder and then you mount it and then you have the unencrypted
part.
It just works with a password.
And that's the encryption part and the synchronization part, because that's really important that
you also have the files on multiple devices, is using DVCS auto sync.
It's distributed version control system auto sync, and it works both with Git and material
and other version control systems.
So you're not using Spideroak at all because you're on ARM?
Yeah, I had to switch because I also needed the files on my Chromebook.
The Chromebook runs Arch Linux, but Arch Linux ARM.
Oh, okay.
So you're using, okay, so just so I get this, you're using AnkaFest for the encryption,
you're using SSH to Git?
How are you doing SSH to Git?
Well, I have a VPS just somewhere else and the point is, the AnkaFest folder is only
decrypted when you mount it.
So the folder which I sync to the cloud is the folder, the encrypted data.
And how does it handle like small file changes?
Like if you do like, you're only updating maybe three lines in your notes file, does
it update the whole file?
The AnkaFest part works like this.
It works per file.
So that's very nice.
It's not like you have a true grid volume and you have to unmount it.
Yeah, right.
It works per file, but because I have it set very strictly, you can give options if you
want per file chaining and that kind of stuff.
I've set it very strictly so that every change I make in a file after a write makes the entire
file gets re-uploaded and synced.
But you can also set less restrictive options which make only bigger changes to a file make
it upload again.
Now any way to make this work with a Windows machine?
Yes.
You have, I think it's a few tools which support SSH on Windows.
You have a few tools which support Git on Windows.
What is your solution for mobile?
Well, Android.
I only use Android phones and there is an open source application in the Android app
store, it's called Ankdroid, which I use to mount it, the encrypted folder.
And there's also a few Git clients in the app store so which you can sync back the encrypted
part.
The beautiful thing is you only in the cloud you have the encrypted part and everywhere
you have AnkaFest, you can mount a local part.
So with Inkdroid, I'm going to go look that up right now, I did not even know about that.
You also have an app that's called, I think it's Boxcryptor and it's a closed source app
and it supports AnkaFest, but it's for me really important that you have open source
code so that you can make sure that nobody else gets your password and key.
Yeah, big advocates of that here.
Wow.
With this solution when you set it up and I use it on a Chromebook, on a MacBook Pro,
which I have for my work, on an Android phone and on two other Ubuntu and Arch Linux machines
and it really works fine.
It also handles deletions of files and folders.
So when you say deletions, do you mean it handles revisions of deletions?
No, just when I remove a file, it's also removed in the version control.
Yeah, okay.
Okay, so that's the same.
Despite the issues on that, when I had deleted the file in one machine, on the other machines
it would just re-upload it because it thought it was a new file on the machine on which
it was deleted.
So how do you, so with having all of your files in Git, then are you able to go in with
like a Git Explorer and like pull out certain versions of stuff that you want and things
like that?
No.
And that is because in Git, only the encrypted part is.
So that's quite of a disadvantage, not really for me, because the important files, I make
manual backups.
So because Git doesn't, because it's encrypted, Git can't make revisions because it doesn't
know.
What is what?
Yeah.
Yeah, it makes revisions of the encrypted data, but not of the decrypted data.
That's the whole point.
Right, yeah.
That makes sense.
One other disadvantage is that you cannot have selective sync, so you cannot have a
big mess with all your files in your phone with just a few.
And also because it's a disadvantage of not knowing what is what and having to mount it
encrypted locally.
Right.
Selective sync is nice, but it does allow you to be lazy too, which honestly that's
how I use it.
This is true.
And complacent.
Yeah.
And one of the other nice things with this solution is that, as I said, I have a lot
of source code for companies I work for in my encrypted folders.
And as I said, I had over 9,000 files and it has totally no performance issues with
that RAM usage of the syncing process and the anchor phase is, I think, less than 90
megabytes, where Spyder Oak was on three to four gigabytes.
Holy cow.
I got to play more with that.
That's interesting.
So you've got how you've done all of this written up on your site, rayme.org, and I'll
have a link to it in the show notes.
It's also linked in the subreddit.
You know what a nice part was about, I put the article on Saturday evening.
It's the first article I did with a picture, with a diagram, and it was also on the front
page on Hack News.
And normally my website has about 1,000 visitors a day, and it got 40,000 extra visits in the
last four days.
Whoa.
Oh my goodness.
You really notice that people are looking for such a solution.
Exactly.
And it's not a one-click easy solution, but it still is there.
People are really looking to go off the grid, in a sense.
Not actually off the grid, but off the surveillance grid.
Well, to put themselves in more control, too, I think is really the big focus.
Yeah.
Isn't that interesting?
Because now, on the other end of it, I've seen such an explosion in bit message adoption.
I'm just buried now in bit messages.
It's awesome.
Yeah.
No kidding.
So it's like people are really looking, and we've seen a huge interest in mail servers,
too.
Well, Remy, before we move on to the next topic, is there anything you wanted to mention
about it, or anything you want to touch on?
Well, just as I said, it's not an easy one-click solution, but I hope it will help people with
having their encryption and data truly secure and locally.
Yeah, I mean, you've got an encrypted sync solution here that is off the surveillance
grid, and it's using all open source code, right?
Yes, that's totally correct.
Yeah, I mean, that's awesome.
That's very awesome.
That's very cool.
So we'll have a link.
Thank you.
Thank you for having me on.
Yeah, you bet, man.
Thanks for staying up for us after your rough day.
I appreciate it.
Have you experienced rate cards that only detect issues when you reboot the server?
Oh, oh, oh.
Yeah, it's funny how something about that reboot process, if there's something that's
going to die, that's when it will die, even if it's a drive.
But yeah, I've had the rate card go out on the database server.
Today I had eight servers which had that issue, and about 24 drives are now dead.
Eight separate servers?
Yeah, with all the same rate card and the same firmware, the latest firmware from HAPI.
Oh, wow.
Oh, did the firmware nuke it?
That might be it.
No, the rate card only detects changes in disk issues when you reboot the server, so
we had to reboot after scheduled updates, and eight servers just said, whoa, my hard
drives are dead.
Bye.
Oh, my.
Oh.
Goodness.
That is not a good day.
That's a bad day.
That's OK.
I was up at 6 a.m., and it's now 11 p.m., and I'm only home for about an hour, so I'm
going to sleep now, and my alarm goes at 4 a.m. the next morning, because I have to
be in the data center again.
Well, arm that coffee pot, man, and thank you for joining us.
Yeah, we'll have a good show, and I will listen to it tomorrow.
All right.
Thank you for having me on.
Yeah, you bet.
Thank you.
Bye.
Yeah, bye.
Thanks.
So I wanted to just mention a couple of follow-up items before we chat more with the mumble
guys there.
I meant to follow up on this a little while ago.
I mentioned that I was frustrated that the GNOME search in GNOME 3 is not searching documents.
It's just on my machine, and the only GNOME time I've ever used GNOME 3.8 is in this
installation of Arch.
In fact, when I installed this installation of Arch, it was like one of the few places
you could actually get GNOME 3.8.
It hadn't hit the other distros yet.
Well, so I don't know why it doesn't work on my machine.
It does work for everybody else on the internet, though, and they all told me.
So we even got like on the comments section for last week's show, we even got like a really
nice screenshot.
I don't know if you saw that, but it even looked, of course, it's GNOME related, so
it just looked gorgeous.
Sure, sure, sure.
Oh, that's bizarre.
That's bizarre.
You know, I'm using Synapse or whatever you want to call it, and so I just, yeah, I don't
really have too many troubles there.
Yeah, your days are numbered, my friend.
That Synapse project, they haven't been pushing new code for a while.
They have not.
I'll probably go to GNOME do.
Yeah, there you go, yeah.
And also, just a quick update, I made an app pick on last, GDmap for scanning your drive
and showing up in blocks.
For us KDE users, K4derstat.
Durst?
Really?
Okay.
K4derstat.
Yeah.
And that is a KDE version.
That's very German.
Some people say that even Winderstat's based off of, so take that as you will.
Okay, so I wanted to get to a topic today that it kind of got me thinking.
In the subreddit, I think it was like an episode, actually one of this show, I said, man, it
sure would be great, gosh, it'd be great if there was some sort of website out there collating
the Steam numbers and giving us some nice charts to look at.
That would be fantastic.
Right?
And, well, that happened.
One of our listeners, Mateci, I bet it's Mateci, I bet that's how you say it.
He started a Steam survey charts over at his site and it is not looking good for Linux.
Not looking good, Matt.
In fact, when I say not looking good, I mean it looks real bad.
It looks real bad.
Would it be bad, and I'm going to get probably set on fire for this, but is it bad to say
it's because the folks that run Linux have jobs?
I was going to say it's because I was going to ask you, and so here's what I'm thinking.
I think we take a break, we'll thank our first sponsor, then I'm going to toss it to you.
I got a couple things I want to throw your way.
I'm going to toss it to you.
Are Linux users, on a whole, obviously there's going to be individual cases, but are Linux
users cheap?
I'm going to convince you otherwise, I think, but we'll see.
We will see.
But first, Matt, I want to thank our first sponsor this week, and that is Ting.com.
Now Ting is mobile that makes sense, my friend, and Ting was the lifesaver at PAX.
I think I mentioned this on Sunday's last, but really I was the only guy, except for
another guy that also was on Ting's service, that had a working cell phone.
I cannot tell you, when I had a client who was in full-fledged freakout mode and they
needed Chris to make everything better, having to make that phone call, being able to make
those phone calls while I was on the exposition floor of PAX was invaluable.
I would have paid any monthly service for that, and of course I'm just paying for what
I use.
That's one of the great things about Ting.
Look, go to linux.ting.com.
We got Linux for this show, so go to linux.ting.com.
That'll get you $25 off your first Ting device, or $25 of service credits for your first month
of service.
I have the HTC One, and that guy powered through it real well, real good.
I was quite happy.
However, now I know this is the same phone, but I just noticed now Ting has the HTC Blue.
Ooh, hey, that's new, right?
Yeah, yeah.
Oh, and they also have this S4 Purple, I didn't know that.
The HTC One Blue is gonna be the phone I want, but what?
I'm holding out.
I'm gonna see.
I wanted to say, if you've been looking at phones, go over to linux.ting.com, and you're
not sure which one you wanna get, because these are off contract.
That's a good thing, but it also means they're gonna be a little bit higher in price.
Of course, in the long run, you're saving money, and even after the cost of the phone,
you're probably gonna save money in some circumstances.
Oh yeah, you're gonna save big buckets of money.
Right.
However, you can buy used on Ting, and there's really a lot of options here.
On that tab, they have buy used, and they have the personal shopping service, where
you go out and find a device, you just give them the parameters, screen size, OS, etc.,
and they'll go get you a refurbished phone that works on Ting.
That's awesome.
That's really awesome.
However, maybe you might be in a situation where you wanna have multiple people on the
line.
Ting makes that real easy.
It's just $6 a month, and you pay for what you use.
So you could have yourself a smartphone, and maybe there's somebody else in your family.
Maybe it's a significant other, maybe it's a parent, maybe it's a kid, and they don't
need to have a full-fledged smartphone, or you don't want them to have a full-fledged
smartphone.
You don't want a full-fledged smartphone.
I mean, I can totally understand that.
They have got the Samsung, which is a really great flip phone, the Samsung M370.
It's very sturdy, very reliable, $52, and if you go to linux.ting.com, Ting is gonna
take $25 off of that.
So that's practically nothing.
That's practically nothing to get you on a Ting phone, and then you're only paying for
the price you use.
Ting just takes your minutes used, your text, and your data, adds them all up at the end
of the month, and then puts you in a bucket, and you can check on their online dashboard
at any time to see where you're at, to know exactly where you're trending.
And the great thing is, if you go with a smartphone, you get all these great features like built-in
hotspot and tethering.
You've gotten caller ID, and all these things that the other cellular companies will sort
of fit into the tax brackets, or sort of fit into like these bolt-on services, and none
of that happens.
No ride-alongs with Ting.
It's just nice, easy, straight, simple, forward mobile.
They've also got that airwave, so if you want to boost cellular service in your house, you
can plug one of these into your house.
It'll use your internet connection, and then you get four bars, or five, or whatever your
phone reads.
You get full signal in your house, but the phone, the OS, everything is just talking
over the cellular, so everything that you would have work over your cellular works right
over one of those things.
It's really, really cool.
That's cool.
Yeah, and to be able to take 25 bucks off of any one of those, especially that little
flip phone.
That's pretty cool.
I know.
When you're starting at 50 bucks, and then you take 25 bucks off, and then you're paying
just for what you use every single month, this is the value.
This is the best value out there, and the service is great, the people are great, and
the company's really good, too.
So go to linux.ting.com, and get yourself something nice on a really easy to use, simple
to follow site.
I was so impressed when I activated my devices, how easy that was.
Matt, you just recently did that.
Tell me, is that not the most straightforward device activation process?
I couldn't believe how simple it was.
Even though I had to make sure it was basically deactivated from your stuff, because I got
a phone from you, it was brain dead simple to do.
I mean, it was just like, type in a couple buttons, I mean, the instructions were easy
to set up, and then once I actually activated the phone, it was like three seconds, like
boop, boop, bam, boom, done, reboot.
I feel like good UI designers, and I think maybe Ting's got a real good group on their
hands, and maybe, here's what their trick is.
If I was a good, here's what makes a good UI designer.
I say you get three or four beers into the wind, then you try to use your site, and if
you can use it efficiently, you know you got a really well-designed site.
Well let me tell you, Ting passes the three or four beer test.
I've been on Ting's website several times, three or four beers in, and I never get lost.
So I just say, if you're an interface design person out there, go take a look at their
site, learn a little bit, and try the beer challenge for yourself, and it makes for a
fantastic website.
It makes it super clear and easy, so that way when you have family members, like my
mom's on Ting, and when I have her go to the Ting site, I can just remember it all from
the top of my head when I'm walking around, because it's so straightforward.
So I'm like, yeah, click there, click there, okay, you're done, bye mom, and we're all
set.
But if mom wanted to call into Ting, she could.
Ting has representatives that answer the phone, you can call them, 1-855-846-4389, and they're
available 8 a.m. to 8 p.m.
You call in, and a real person answers the phone.
And so if there's something mom can't do on the website, I just have mom call Ting.
Well, and that's awesome, because not only are they going to get a real person when they
call in, but if maybe they're not really into doing stuff on the website, they prefer to
deal with a person, what a great option.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely, yeah.
So go to linux.ting.com and start saving right now, you guys, don't be crazy.
Don't be crazy.
All right, Matt, so here we go, you ready for my Linux users might be cheap?
And I'm a Linux user, I'm not cheap, but I'm just saying.
So I got an inside guy, I don't know if he's in the chat room right now, but I got an inside
guy, and he's been sussing out the number, suss is my word of the week, he's been sussing
out the numbers from the Ubuntu Software Center.
And we're looking now, Ubuntu, supposedly the number one deployed desktop Linux operating
system.
Our own web stats would back that up.
The number one app in the Ubuntu Software Center right now is FileCryptor Professional.
The number two app is WPA Generator, and the number three app is FileCryptor.
All right, of these top apps, the first app goes for $4.99, the second app goes for $3,
and the third app goes for $2.99.
Now here's the thing, these are the top three applications in the Ubuntu Software Center.
None of them have ratings, none of them have average, none of them have comments, nothing.
They're all blank, I should take comments back, ratings, none of them have any interaction
on that level, and when talking to these developers, they're making at best a couple hundred dollars
a month.
And that's being pretty generous.
From the software center.
Really, yeah, that's pretty generous.
It is, and that's like the top, that was like the top app, actually, that made that much
money.
Now the time skew was a little short, it wasn't a full month, but still, it is, the numbers
are devastating.
Now we go over to Steam.
Since Steam has launched, it has gone in a sharp decline.
On January 13th, Steam had, Linux Steam usage, had a 1.12% market share.
On February 13th, it went up to 2.02%, that was after we were out of beta and all this
good stuff.
Then from that point forward, June, it goes down to 1.07%, July, 1.06%.
Now in August, we're below 1%, we're at 0.93%.
So we're dropping off.
Now you gotta ask yourself, because Linux is free, and a lot of the software is free,
is it more attractive to people who don't wanna pay for software?
Is this not a marketplace where you can make a living writing software and selling it to
Linux users?
So here's how I see it.
First of all, if I'm gonna buy anything, if I can get an equitable alternative for free,
I would be mouth breathing stupid not to.
So of course I'm gonna go that route.
Now as far as the two marketplaces, whether it be Steam or the Ubuntu Software Center,
the Ubuntu Software Center is a little bit like trying to do grocery checkout at your
dentist's office, or at the B&B, it's horrible.
It is absolutely hideous.
Now for free apps, it's reasonably painless because all you're gonna do is enter a password
and you're done.
Yeah, but when you buy an app, you gotta put in your shipping address and everything.
It's just stupid.
So that's hideous.
Steam's is actually not so bad, but I think that the bigger problem, especially when you
look at it from the fact that, like I'll use Steam as a better example because that's really
where we had a nice peak and it kind of dropped off, I think the people that were really excited
about getting on the games have then done so.
And I would be interested in comparing a contrast with what's going on in the Windows space.
Is there also a decline there?
Or perhaps maybe there's a surge of new Windows games coming out to where maybe there's not
as many compelling new Linux coming out.
The Windows penetration seems to be fairly steady and in January it was 94.56%.
It drops down slightly between February and July, but then it's back to 94.59%, slightly
above where it was in January.
So since Linux has come out for Steam, Windows usage has actually gone up slightly.
And so I would say that it's not so much a problem, I don't think the problem was with
Linux at all.
I think it's a lot of its availability of give me something compelling, you know, okay
for existing Linux games, do you have a map pack that's come out?
Maybe there's something compelling to add on to my existing games.
What new things are out there as an existing Steam user that's going to make me say, oh
hey, let me make that purchase.
Maybe there are some games that are out there, maybe there aren't.
Maybe you're already into your game and you would like to expand on that existing experience.
So I would need more data before I can completely rule it out as a Linux thing because I mean
like, you know, the Humble Bundle is done really well.
But then again, it's something different and I think honestly the success of that Humble
Bundle was one of the things that brought Steam over.
I mean, you know, so yeah, that's a good point.
I'm going to, so I'll ask the mumble room.
I don't know if the guys in the On Air channel have any, if anybody in here has any thoughts
on if Linux users are just cheap, you know, with software I would say yes, but not with
games.
That's my big difference.
Do you think it's maybe Linux users are willing to pay for certain things and not other things?
Oh yeah.
Well, I mean, I look at like when I try and find something on OS X, because I have to
do this occasionally, it astounds me at the stupid software titles that are being, they're
charging $20, $30.
Oh yeah.
I know, right?
It's just like, and it's like, you really think I'm going to do that?
No.
You know, it's like, I'm not going to give you my money.
So I think that it's a lot of what you're used to.
Linux users have an expectation that if they hunt hard enough, because the Ubuntu Software
Center is not the end all to be all of software, you hunt hard enough, a lot of times you can
find a package that's compatible with your distro.
That's going to offer you a way to accomplish the task you're trying to do.
May not be as glossy, may not be as pretty, but a lot of times you can get it done.
And you can get it done for free.
So we got the mumble room up and we just heard Jack in the box type in a little bit, but
I'm curious, anybody in here, Josh or Mad Joe or Miracode, we haven't heard from you
or Westeros in here.
We haven't heard from you guys.
You guys think Linux users are cheap?
Do you think it's something else?
What is your explanation?
Go ahead, Miracode.
You first.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I'm a few milliseconds closer than any of you.
I think it's a mix of the fact that people are a little bit cheap, however, I think a
lot of professional users also use the new systems.
That may be part of the issue, where we have people who are generally busy filming and
not having time really to play these games.
All right.
So Josh, what do you think, Josh?
Is it Linux users are too busy?
No.
So my opinion is, for instance, with the Ubuntu Software Center, those apps, half of those
apps are not integrated with the operating system.
They're using an old GTK library, which for instance, GTK 2, which one, looks terrible
and two, the apps just suck, and three, then they're just charging an obscene amount.
Well, it's $4 or $3 out of an obscene amount.
So the top, we had $4.99, $3, and $2.99.
I think for apps that don't integrate with the OS that are outdated, or for instance,
when I went on there the other day, I saw a Windows Phone 8 app in there, which is just
like, I don't even know how that got through the review process, but it was in there.
Oh, so you're talking about applications rather than...
I'm talking about applications within the Ubuntu Software Center.
Regarding Steam, I think people want a very smooth experience, and I don't think we're
quite there yet, and it's not at the fault, it's not exactly at the fault of the developers.
With some, it's regarding their game optimization, but with some, it's the drivers.
We're getting there, I think it might be a couple of years, depending on Linux adoption.
I think Valve's really pushing it, so I think we're going to see drivers improve a lot,
but I just don't think we're quite there yet with a lot of the games.
And a lot of the AAA titles aren't even on Linux, so until then, I'm kind of stuck on
Windows.
Yeah, that's true.
We are still missing...
Okay, well, so is it this?
Oh, so Green in the chat room is mentioning System76, and I would say they are a premium
brand.
It's a high-quality device that delivers on what they say, and I feel like, as a Linux
user, I'm more picky about what I spend my money on.
I'll buy Steam games if it's a good game.
I've bought apps from the Ubuntu Software Center, now I can't really use them, but I
have, and I'll buy a Bonobo when there's a good Linux laptop.
So for me, is it actually that Linux users maybe are just more discerning?
Yeah, I would lean with that.
I think that our expectations are, the first bill of goods that you serve to us, we're
not going to necessarily jump on board like we see with OS X and Windows, OS X especially.
That's where I've really seen it the worst.
So I think that's definitely a big piece of it.
But as far as integration and all that, and as far as making an application center that
doesn't suck, I hate to beat the dead horse again, but I'm sorry, it's been done, and
Ubuntu went backwards.
Not only did they go and hire Linspire developers that worked on CNR from Linspire and actually
integrated them into the Ubuntu software project, they then managed to make it suck harder.
So it's like, I don't know how that works because Linspire sucked, don't get me wrong.
I hated their model.
I didn't like a lot of what was going on there, but that piece of it, before they decided
to make it available to all the distributions, was the most seamless software experience
I've ever seen.
It was just apt.
It wasn't anything wonderful.
You could do an entire aisle of software, go to another computer, log in, aisle bam
done.
It was very, very seamless.
So the Ubuntu Software Center really lacks that seamless experience.
Steam, however, is pretty close.
I think Steam is probably closer than anything else out there for Linux.
But we're going to see that.
Go ahead.
Sorry.
Go ahead, Josh.
Yeah, go ahead.
I just think, going back to that question you asked, are Linux users cheap?
I don't think we are cheap.
I think because we're power users, we're all power users, we want to find the best for
us and we will look until we can't look anymore to find what we want.
And then at the end of the search, if there's something that's not free, then we will end
up buying it.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Well, I'm going to move on.
I'm going to move us on.
Can I address something?
Yeah, go ahead.
Go ahead.
So with Ubuntu Software Center, yes, there are some issues.
Performance is certainly one of them.
And one of the other issues is the minimum payment level is quite high.
So there are no 99 cent apps in Ubuntu Software Center because of the payment provider that
Canonical uses to do the payments for apps in Software Center, which makes it less attractive
for people making very small apps that could potentially get very high volume sales.
Not everyone in every region can pay because certain restrictions with credit cards and
certain ages, it makes it difficult and they might not be able to use PayPal either.
And there's also a significant hurdle to installing apps because you have to sign up for an Ubuntu
single sign on account and that's seamless inside Software Center.
And the fundamental issue, there's a lack of content.
When you don't have enough content, when there isn't the sea of applications that you get
on Android and on iOS, where you can just page down and page down and page down and
keep going, okay, you'll find some dross in there, but there'll be an awful lot of stuff
in there for you to choose from, you'll almost certainly find it.
And until we've got that vast amount of content, it's very difficult to get realistic sales
figures.
So is AppGrid going to solve some of this problem?
Is Ubuntu's new Software Center redesign going to be sort of a reset on some of this?
Yes, to some degree.
I mean, part of it is that we haven't jumped the chasm yet.
We're still, as Chris says, we're geeks.
The people who are using Linux and Ubuntu, even now, are mostly geeks and so they're
looking for geek tools and they're happy with Wget and downloading an RPM and using alien
to turn it into a deb or that kind of stuff.
Whereas normal people, we haven't got to them yet.
The moms and dads and then the kids, we haven't got to them.
So it's very difficult to say that this is like normal behavior.
It's normal for us, but it's not normal for them.
And ideally, yeah, this will all be fixed with 14.04 and 14.10 with click packages and
in-dash purchases.
So you'll be able to just scroll down through the dash, see an app and just click on it
and install it.
You won't have to go off to a store to go and find it.
I've always wondered if that would be coming to the dash.
That makes a lot of sense that that would be in the dash because the dash has the ability
to suggest and recommend apps in the software center.
And then the dash becomes useful.
You can kind of see the pieces of it are there.
So cool.
I'm going to link to a little article here that's talking about getting the app grid
on 13.04 and it takes a little look at it.
I know it's something that Canonical is working on.
So I'm hopeful that what I come back to is I hope it does come down to it's the challenges
to payment.
It's the challenges to create an account.
It's the price issue.
It's the inventory issue.
And it's also the volume issue.
And so it's not any one particular thing.
So it's not fair to say, well, Linux users are cheap.
That might be a component of it.
I would say it's they're more picky.
And there's also we haven't had a decent unified SDK across across all the platforms.
And now we have now we're building one that works on phones, tablets, TVs, desktops, you
know, everything.
Yeah.
So effectively, a developer can write their app, sell it for 99 cents and run on all those
form factors.
Ideally, that should bring more people in.
I don't know.
We'll have to wait and see.
Come back in a year.
Right.
Yeah.
It's fixed.
So it's definitely if it doesn't cause if it if it if it doesn't result in that, it's
at least the right move to make.
And it seems to only be setting up for success.
Who knows if it'll bring success, but it's at least positioning in the right direction.
So let's hope so.
I'm hopeful.
All right.
I'm hopeful as well.
So we declared Linux users not necessarily cheap and to stay tuned.
And you know, honestly, I think what you see there in the steam stats actually being reflected
is initial excitement and then sort of people getting like you guys are all saying, getting
back to work.
And what it does show you is when all the Linux users are really excited to go in for
some reason and maybe it's some new release or some update, you can get up to two percent
of steam on Linux.
Now, maybe your maybe your sustained average run rate is one percent.
But on peaks, if you can get up to two percent, that at least means the audience is there
for steam.
And, you know, it could be different members of that two percent are in there at different
times at any given time.
Their concurrent rate is only one percent.
That's true.
That's a good point.
I still think that could really do wonders if they could find a way to get people to
come back and say, hey, I've got the games I'm really excited about.
That's not going to change.
I'm not necessarily looking for new ones.
Get me something that's going to enhance my existing game experience.
That's why I like that natural selection too so much.
That just feels like a triple A. I turn people send me in bit messages and turn down your
texture quality won't crash as much on you, which always hurts.
Right.
Because on the bonobo, the first thing I do, I go in and say everything, crank crank, crank
everything.
It's out of principle.
Yeah, exactly.
I just wanted to kick a topic around with you.
It's not too related to Linux, but it happened today.
And you got to wonder, you look at Ubuntu Touch, you look at Firefox OS.
So I'm going to ask you, Matt, Unity Sync.
I got to talk about Unity Sync before we go on.
Our second sponsor this week.
What is Unity Sync?
We'll find out for yourself.
Go to derwiz.com slash Unity Sync, but I'll give you a hint since you're asking me.
Unity Sync is a centralized service that synchronizes data between different types of directories.
Now I don't mean like a directory on your hard drive.
I'm talking real enterprise-grade directories, actor directories, Zimbra directories, OpenLDAP,
ComniGate Pro, Oracle Internet Directory, Sun One, iPlanet.
Yeah, it'll do iPlanet group-wise.
Yeah, enough people actually asked.
They implemented group-wise support.
It'll also do Microsoft SQL access, Oracle, Sybase, MySQL, Postgres, SQLite, LDF, CFV
files.
Here's what you can do.
You can move either the entire directory or just attributes of the directory seamlessly
between the different directories and all from the Unity Sync service that runs on either
a Windows box or a Linux box and doesn't require its own database.
Unity Sync allows you to solve this problem that has plagued IT for centuries.
Since we have had online databases, IT has struggled with this.
I know.
I know your plight, friends.
I know your plight.
Here's the good news.
No scripting or programming is required.
All of Unity Sync's attribute management is handled by an easy-to-learn template system
requiring no programming experience.
However, there is a little Python under the hood, or not Python, Perl, that you can get
in there and do some Perl scripting if you want to do some massaging.
These templates are great.
You can make sure data is exactly what you expect.
Look, when Susie in HR updates her application because somebody changed their last name,
you need to get that reflected in whatever the IT database has pointed out for the global
directory for your entire company.
You want to look like one unified organization with different data stores?
Unity Sync solves that for you by bringing all of these things together and letting you
control.
Plus, Unity Sync's easy-to-use web interface lets you do dry runs, lets you get reports,
lets you just check on the status of things.
It's really quite easy and quite simple to set up, but yet extremely powerful, clocking
in at just under five megabytes.
This enterprise-grade software, friends, and of course, it runs on Linux, is used by some
really big names, including, oh, the Canadian Department of National Defense.
Yeah, yeah, those guys, yeah, yeah, you've heard of them.
What about General Dynamics?
Yeah, General Dynamics, they're a customer of Unity Sync, and they use Unity Sync to
move data between their different directories.
Oh, the MLB, Washington Nationals, as well, MLB Major League Baseball HQ also uses Unity
Sync.
You baseball fans, FYI on that one, you're welcome.
Go over to durwiz.com and check out Unity Sync.
Just go to durwiz.com slash Unity Sync.
And when you decide you want to grab it, just to try it out, you can get a free trial.
If you use the code LINUX, it'll extend it to a full 30-day trial, so you get an extra
extended trial, plus your first year of maintenance is going to be absolutely free.
So once you pull that trigger, you're going to be taken care of for a year, and that's
a really great deal.
So go to durwiz.com slash Unity Sync.
Check it out and be impressed.
I know it's going to solve your problems.
I have struggled with this myself, and if you're out there with this kind of problem,
Unity Sync is going to make you the IT hero.
So thanks to Durwiz for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
So I'm going to ask you, Matt, Microsoft today announcing they're buying the Nokia phone
division for $7.2 billion.
This is coming from, well, everywhere on the internet.
Stephen Elop will be stepping down as Nokia's CEO, and he'll be heading up Nokia's devices
and services division, which is actually going to just become part of Microsoft.
And Nokia will now focus on their Nokia Now brand, which is their mapping stuff, and their
Nokia network services stuff, which I guess they've had some good traction lately.
And the 30,000 employees of Nokia will be joining Microsoft, and Microsoft will be taking
the Apple route and the Nexus route of developing their hardware more closely, sort of like
the Moto X or the iPhone.
Right, right.
Well, yeah, they're following Google suit.
I mean, that's exactly what they're doing.
So what do you think this means for...
So it's already a very locked down market.
I mean, you got your incumbents, Android, iOS, and Blackberry, and Microsoft in there.
And we were already saying, like, gosh, this doesn't seem like it's very practical for
somebody like Ubuntu Touch or Firefox OS to break in.
Is Microsoft becoming a phone maker?
Is this a big deal?
Is this going to lock it down completely, or is this a total irrelevant move?
Well, here's the problem is that, first of all, let's go to the Firefox phones, for example.
They've mastered grassroots.
They obviously have got it nailed.
I think they totally nailed that one.
So that's something...
They can go to eBay or something totally obscure and still get the sales happening.
Microsoft is under the...
I'm using a delusion that they're still relevant in this space, and it just cracks me up, especially
as the CEO is retiring.
Anyway, so, you know, cough, cough.
Yeah, right.
Anyway, so the whole point of it is that, you know, so just because you go and buy a
company like Nokia, who back in the 90s were really awesome, and they still maintain decent
numbers out of the United States, I'm sure there's still people that use those phones
over the borders.
But honestly, I don't really see that as being a real relevant, exciting thing because, you
know, the Firefox phone comes out or the Ubuntu phone comes out.
It's something completely unique and different that we haven't tried before, where with the
Windows phone, we already tried it, we weren't real impressed with it, so now we want more
of it.
It doesn't really jive.
I get you.
You know what I mean?
Let me give you a devil's advocate here.
So, okay, I'll play devil's advocate.
I'm in the enterprise.
I'm a business.
Let's say I'm a hospital.
I've got a lot of Windows applications.
But one of the things you can't argue is Surface RT is kind of a snore, right?
And it's crap.
But Nokia, on the other hand, makes fantastic hardware.
And if I had a Nokia-made Surface X86 or whatever, and I'm a doctor's office, I'm a hospital,
I've got all of this stuff already on the Windows platform, I can get these devices,
I can have them cooperate with my file formats, I can have them access my Windows file servers
and join the domain potentially and all this kind of stuff, I can have group policy applied
to them, etc.
Maybe not an RT, but on the X86 version.
Could it be that what Microsoft is going to do is sort of lock down this sector of the
market where it's a personal device, but it's a business device first?
And it needs to get some work done, and it needs to be compatible, and maybe this is
what they're going to do is create a hardware platform that is all of these disenfranchised
Windows 8 corporations who are refusing to go to Windows 8 eventually going to have to
pick something.
They're either going to have to go to 8 or 9, whatever it is at the time they make their
leap, they're going to have to switch to Linux, they're going to have to switch to the Mac.
What if Microsoft came to them and said, well look, a ton of your staff members are coming
in with iPads and Android devices, and this is driving your IT crazy, and you guys can't
standardize on this.
But they obviously need this functionality, it's great for meetings, it's great for taking
inventory, etc, etc, blah, blah, blah.
So here's what we're going to do, we're Microsoft, we now own this hardware company, we're going
to work directly with them to make a Windows product, and this is what you can move to.
You can have Windows on the desktop, you can have Windows on the server, and now you can
have Windows on the mobile client device, and we create all of it.
I think that if they, that's the right idea, but here's why they won't do it.
I mean, they should, and that would be, if you were working for them, they'd actually
be doing well, because you're right, that's exactly where they need to be, they need to
be an enterprise, and they need to make things seamless for the end user, as well as sane
for the IT folks.
Look man, I got a good piece of malware, and I need to get that across your entire organization
as fast as possible.
Exactly right, well yeah, but I mean, they can still lock it down at some level I'm sure,
but it's Windows, so you're still going to always have that as an issue.
But besides that, I think that yes, if they stuck with the IT market, or stuck with the
enterprise market, and really continue to master that's where they do well, that would
be fine, but that's not what's going to happen.
What we're going to see is we're going to see another commercial with dancing idiots
and flapping tablets, and they're going to try for consumer again.
That's the problem.
You see, if they stuck with what you're talking about, that would actually make a lot of sense,
but they won't do that exclusively.
They'll dabble in that, but the consumer market is sexy.
They want to be kind of the Apple folks, and when they get a new CEO in there, I think
that's what's going to happen.
I think that they're going to be like, well, we need to be more relevant in the consumer
market because that's really where growth is, because the enterprise market, they tend
to kind of lock down in segments and blah, blah, blah, blah, but you know.
Yeah, stagnate.
Yeah, I mean, I've seen banks still using Windows 2000.
Oh yeah, oh yeah, it's bad, it's bad.
So they know that, so they want growth.
I'll ask, okay, mumble chat room, anybody in here that wants to chime in, what do you
think, is Microsoft buying up Nokia bad for the free and open mobile operating systems?
I'm thinking specifically Firefox OS, Ubuntu Touch, because I kind of saw them as having
potential inroads to the enterprise, especially Ubuntu Touch with Convergence.
I think that could be big in enterprise, but if Microsoft comes along and they've got
Nokia hardware, they've got the Windows desktop, they've got the Windows mobile crap, it's
all crap, but enterprises will buy it anyways.
It's standardized, that's why, yeah.
Is this sort of closing the door of opportunity for these up and coming mobile operating systems?
Mumble room, I ask you.
Not, I hope not, but as Mr. Mango also in the chat room mentioned, Nokia owns a lot
of patents and I think that Microsoft is going to use those patents to hurt Firefox and all
the other operating systems.
Oh, that's a great point, yeah.
Nokia still owns a large segment of their IP.
The difference is Microsoft has a 10-year reciprocal license with Nokia regarding those,
so I believe Nokia still owns a lot of its patent portfolio.
The Qualcomm stuff goes to Microsoft.
The other stuff, Microsoft has a 10-year license, I believe, with the option at some point,
at any point, to make it a perpetual license.
Right.
Now, regarding Nokia getting bought out, for the most part, by Microsoft, it shouldn't
come to anyone by surprise.
Back in Build 2012 and reiterated in 2013, Microsoft clearly stated that they're pushing
more towards becoming a devices and services company.
Because they've done so well so far.
Yeah.
Right.
Well, apparently, Surface Pro is doing all right.
It's just the Surface RT that's been a complete flop and everyone knows why.
That's true, that's true.
But Nokia is a very established brand, and if they could bring that level of hardware
to Microsoft's other products, we might see a bit more success.
I don't know, and I guess time will tell.
Yeah, I think the patent thing is going to be the scary thing to watch.
I totally agree with you guys.
The patents are still owned by Nokia, and Microsoft just have a cross-license to use
them.
That doesn't mean they get an opportunity to use them in court against other people.
Well, some of the Qualcomm stuff will be owned by Microsoft, and there's a lot of cellular
stuff in that Qualcomm portfolio.
Right, but they don't own Qualcomm license.
They just are allowed to leverage the current deal that Nokia has with Qualcomm.
Yeah, right.
So they probably couldn't sue over that.
They can't pull the trigger on it.
Yeah.
Okay.
Good point, good point.
What I find interesting is that Microsoft used the name Nokia on their products.
And Nokia can't make smartphones under this agreement until 2015, in which case they are
allowed to make smartphones.
And the announcement said that their award-winning design team manufacturing and assembly facilities
around the world that Microsoft are absorbing, but it doesn't actually mention engineering,
software development, and research.
Right.
In fact, I believe Nokia's lead engineer, or I mean lead designer, just announced he's
leaving Nokia to pursue entrepreneurial opportunities, it was.
Yeah, and that could be a good move for Yola, or Mozilla may go around hiring.
True.
Oh, man.
In Canonical.
That would be interesting if they snapped him up.
And like Jarem's saying, man, am I glad QT is out of Nokia now, right?
No kidding.
QT has been saved.
Now, what do you guys think about the kind of the elephant in the room is, so Stephen
Elop, former Microsoft employee, goes to Nokia, everyone has always said, he's a Trojan horse.
Now he's going to step down as CEO, and he's going to become head of devices and services,
which is getting absorbed by Microsoft.
Julie Larson Green, who had just gotten promoted in this whole reshuffle, she got like moved
way up to the top and was reporting right to Balmer, now reports to Elop, and Elop reports
to Balmer.
So do you think Elop is our next CEO of Microsoft?
Yes.
I would say he's either that or he's going to be Arthur Cheney.
I'm sorry, I mean, he's not, I mean, just looking at this picture, you got to have someone
that's, no, he's, I can't, you got to have a nice figurehead in there, and I think they
learned their lesson from Balmer that he's just not really, the consumers just aren't
really buying it.
You got Elop pulling the strings of some public.
Yeah, I got him pulling the strings.
I think he's the brand of the operation for sure, but I don't think he's the front man.
I think he's behind the scenes.
Yeah, yeah.
Might be.
I mean, almost anybody would be an upgrade from Balmer though, right?
Oh my gosh, don't get me started.
Man.
So, Heaven's Revenge just joined us.
Before we move off on this topic, did you want to chime in with any thoughts?
Well, Balmer might've kept them as a, if you can hear me all right, Balmer might've kept
them as a devices or a personal computer company because I don't think they're going to try
to stay as a PC company for very much longer.
Not at all.
I think we're seeing them advance more towards promoting Windows Azure, which is already
a $1 billion business.
We see them bringing Office over to multiple platforms, which, lol, good luck.
I don't think they're going to drop it, right?
I think they're going to canonical focus a little bit on mobile.
They're going to kind of make that shift where mobile is the priority, but desktop is an
important client operating system that also interacts with some of the same cloud services
that mobile does.
I'm not saying this is a good idea, but what I'm saying is I think they see the consumer
devices as just as critical to the success as their enterprise devices.
Because what Balmer, at least Balmer, I believe, has felt like he's learned from Apple is if
you get the consumers to buy the gadgets, they'll bring it to the enterprise.
And so you kind of, it's like a front.
You got to have a stake in the consumer space and you got to have a stake in the enterprise
space because the two merge together and meet.
So I think he's thinking, I mean, I would assume Microsoft always sees Windows as key
to that overall strategy, but right, it's no longer going to be a Windows company, right?
I mean, Windows is going to be part of that company, but it's just like Canonical is no
longer the Ubuntu desktop company, right?
Exactly.
Yeah, no, I see them just and with their heavy focus on going into basically a hardware mindset,
someone said, well, they do hardware well.
I mean, remember the Xbox and that's true.
But from my memory that that division was left alone enough to where they were able
to be successful.
The other departments in Microsoft, not, you know, it's kind of hit and miss really.
And I think Windows is probably the one that's really taken the biggest hit.
So I don't know, this whole reorganization thing where Ballmer ends up, you know, he
leaves, who comes in, all this sort of stuff.
At the end of the day, what you're left with is they need to make a decision as to who
the hell they're marketing their product to.
I don't care if they're selling pears or bananas or what.
It doesn't make any difference who's their market and they can't seem to get the brain
around that.
You brought up a great point that, you know, they start with the enterprise and then, you
know, or they start as consumers and bring it into the enterprise or even vice versa.
In Microsoft's, honestly, Apple was always strongest in consumer.
Microsoft was always strongest in enterprise.
They need to figure out a way to keep it in the enterprise.
And if they can get it down, trickle down to the consumer, great.
But anything to do with consumers is just going to backfire.
One of the things that they said that was interesting is that they put out this PowerPoint
presentation that All Things Deep posted up on their website and I don't know who this
presentation was for, but Microsoft, I guess, has got to have a PowerPoint for everything.
In the PowerPoint presentation for this acquisition, they mentioned that right now Microsoft makes
$10 on average per Windows phone device.
Now it's funny because I think they make more than that on an Android device.
However, if once they own Nokia, they project they will actually generate $40 per device.
So it's interesting to see as a licensee and they talk about how in the, they say it used
to be common knowledge that the best way to have a successful platform was to license
it and become the standard.
But now we've learned that the best, now the market has changed and the best solution is
an integrated approach of hardware and software and services.
We're going to do it all, try to be the one all, answer all.
And the problem with this is it's very against the whole Linux, Unix philosophy where you
have a lot of tools that work together that do one thing really well.
And I want to go back, I want to go back to when the iPhone just launched and Android
just launched, Amazon didn't have their own mobile device, Google was totally cool with
integrating with everybody, Apple didn't want to have to own absolutely everything and have
an iCloud service and all this garbage so I could use Amazon for my MP3s, I could use
Google for my search.
It was this really nice, you know, now everybody has to own the whole stack, right?
Everything has to be an integrated, custom-built solution that's custom-tailored to you.
I'm just getting so sick of it.
But I think there's a market for it, you know.
My wife certainly is a market for it.
She wants iEverything because she likes all that.
She doesn't want to get an app, she just wants it to work.
I think your wife would probably agree with that.
Yeah, yeah.
You know, that's kind of her thing.
So there are people that definitely want that for sure.
Yeah, and it's interesting too because I think we're moving, oh sorry, Miracode.
I think we're moving towards a world that maybe not all users realize we're moving because
when Angela made the switch to Android for a little while, she was like, wait, wait,
wait, wait, wait.
What do you mean I need to put all of my photos and music up on the server?
I want them here on my hard drive.
I don't want them up on the server.
Why would I want to use my data to listen to my music that I already own?
Why am I paying for it twice in her mind?
And you got to figure a lot of people are smarter than we give them credit for.
Sometimes people can just see the common sense of a situation and say, wait a minute, wait
a minute, I got to buy this track and then I got to pay for the storage and I got to
pay for the data to stream it instead of just having it sync over to my machine for my hard
drive.
That doesn't, for her, what was the killer for Android was that it was too dependent
on Google services.
She wanted to have everything local.
She wanted to be able to just plug in a USB cord to her computer, click a sync button.
Everything is copied from her hard drive to the device.
There's also a strong network effect with these platforms.
Like my daughter has been saving up her money to buy herself and she wanted an iPod touch
and I said, well, how about a Nexus 4 because it's ridiculously cheap and it can do everything.
And she was like, yeah, okay.
And then when she thought about it a bit more, the reason she didn't want a Nexus 4 and she
wanted an iPod touch was because all of her friends in her class use FaceTime and that
would lock her out and she wouldn't be able to talk to her friends.
So there's a strong network effect that once, you know, half the kids in the class have
an iPod or an iPhone, the rest of them are guaranteed to get one.
It's the whole ecosystem thing, isn't it?
If you've got Apple's ecosystem, you're tied into it.
The people at work, they don't want to move over to Android because they're tied into
iTunes.
Everything's into iTunes.
The same happens with Google.
You get tied into Google with all of those services that ship on an Android device these
days.
You can get very tied into the Play Store and you bought all your purchases in the Play
Store.
You've got all your email in Gmail.
It's a hard thing to switch away from.
Yeah, I agree with that.
I think Miracle, you might be making the same point and so is Alex Bell in the chat room
is iMessage gets a lot of crap, but I think it's the most understated feature and FaceTime
as well.
Although it kind of sucks that FaceTime is being relayed now, but iMessage and the thing
about iMessage is different than Hangouts because Android has this now with Hangouts.
In some ways it's superior because it can be opened up to groups.
It's easy to throw Hangouts on any computer that has Chrome.
So Hangouts are superior in every single way except I'm a paranoid bastard and I know that
everything I say is being stored indefinitely by Google and available immediately by a Homeland
Security note.
And it's just stupid things, but if I say to my wife, oh yeah, I'll go upstairs and
I'll beat the children and she knows I'm joking because I would never do that, but that's
in a text message now that is logged on a Google server forever that is being indexed
by the National Security Agency potentially.
What's to say that Apple, the biggest consumer company around, isn't also storing everything?
You never know, especially with Apple and especially in a closed source environment.
You never know.
Now their docs illustrate what happens is the Apple servers essentially are involved
for the initial handshake.
So if Matt was an iPhone user and I was an iPhone user and I sent Matt an iMessage and
that initial iMessage is coordinated by the iCloud service, whatever you want to call
it, their push service.
Once the two devices link, there is a key generated on each handset that is then exchanged
and they then communicate directly to each other from that point forward.
Maybe that's just because the Apple ecosystem has been directly tied into the business world.
So they've had to develop that kind of encryption.
I think when it happens to Android, they'll update it or they'll have to update it to
be able to enter into that ecosystem.
I think it's deeper than that by an order of magnitude.
What I think it is is Google is inherently an internet connected company.
Everything is orchestrated through the cloud.
Everything is synced through the cloud.
Like in Google, you don't sync your calendar, right?
Google Calendar is the master source of the calendar you can push and subscribe.
But Apple was a company that existed before there was an internet.
So what Apple does, Apple is local land first and they don't have any reason to be internet
first.
For example, AirPlay.
When you AirPlay something from an iOS device to an Apple TV, that is a direct IP connection
from the iOS device to the Apple TV.
But when you use Chromecast, that sends a notification message up to the cloud.
The cloud then orchestrates the connection from the YouTube video down to the Chromecast
initiates the play, and then the commands from your handset are sent up to the cloud
server and the cloud server sends the commands down to the Chromecast.
Potentially, each one has its advantages for sure, but one is inherently more private.
One is inherently more private because it never has to leave your land.
The fact that iMessage and FaceTime can in some capacities work like that and the fact
that it enables free text messaging and that they support pictures and messages is a huge
advantage to that platform.
So that is a lock-in that we don't even talk about when we talk about Ubuntu Touch or Firefox.
We talk about apps, but we don't even talk about all of these services like video stores
and music stores and these messaging services, Hangouts or iMessages, that are sort of becoming
indispensable for some people.
I think both Google and Apple are inherently evil, I just think they do evil differently.
I know we get some flack for the Ubuntu Software Center, but if you buy stuff from the Software
Center, they're just a bunch of PPAs and you can just log into Launchpad and get those
packages back out and port them across to another Linux distro if you like.
It's not so easy on either iOS or Android.
Another thing, back to the original point regarding whether the move by Microsoft to
Nokia is going to affect Ubuntu Phone and such, Canonical and Mozilla and Yola, they
don't care if you use Amazon for your books and Google Music for your music, they don't
care.
It's just to create this wonderful OS that everything can coexist on and I think that's
kind of the point we need to get back to regarding these new, I guess you could say, indie OSs.
I think it also helps define their market.
That's their market.
For people that want to select and choose those individual services, folks like us that
care about that sort of thing, that's attractive.
I think that's great because it definitely defines that market for folks.
My solution for this was kind of the final straw that made me roll my own XMPP server.
I just wanted to, all of this NSA stuff has made me just, it's not that I'm worried about
being monitored, it crosses my mind now.
I think about it.
I was doing a whole bunch of reading about Syria recently and then I got down a path
so there's been protests outside of John Kerry's house.
I haven't seen that on the news so I wanted to see pictures of it.
Now I realize I'm searching for Syria locations on Google Maps, I'm searching for chemical
weapons, I'm searching for John Kerry's house.
And nothing happens.
But the fact that I have to worry about it makes me uncomfortable.
And so I'm just like, you know what, I'm going to go to XMPP, I'm going to chat with my wife
on our own private chat server so that way I never have to worry about it at all.
It never even crosses my mind.
It's not a distraction anymore.
And I like that peace of mind and I like the idea that Yala or Ubuntu Touch or Firefox
OS is more about the phone getting something on there but not necessarily locking you into
any particular service.
That to me as a customer might be their biggest advantage, that they don't have that ecosystem.
I completely agree with that and I think the way I've always looked at privacy long before
all this stuff with privacy concerns really came about is I always looked at privacy as
a very simple analogy in that absolutely I can if I choose to stand in front of my window
and get undressed and hop into the shower and if someone sees me it's really no big
deal.
Please don't.
But I feel more comfortable if no one has to subject their eyes to that and I just pull
the blinds and that's kind of where I see this taking privacy back into our own hands
thing is that for me it's out of principle.
It's just like it's none of their damn business period.
Doesn't matter why.
It's just none of their damn business and that's just my perspective.
I just keep it simple.
Alright so while we got the mumble line open I wanted to toss something around in the chat
room and I'll watch you too.
So something I get an email about once a day is hey the CAPTCHA isn't working on the Jupiter
colony.
The Jupiter colony is the form not you know Jupiter colony is kind of what we is is an
overall branching title that we have for a lot of things but the Jupiter colony form
specifically the PHP BB bulletin board that we have up at Jupiter broadcasting.com slash
forum is retired.
It's in sort of read only mode we're not allowing new account creations there's still activity
there.
Partially because I don't know.
So the main reason is I don't have the time to take care of that anymore and it just it's
something that just needs attention from time to time and I don't have it.
So I thought well okay social networks have kind of replaced this but then not everybody
wants to have a social network account.
Reddit kind of replaces but not everybody wants to have a reddit account.
So we have a great G plus Jupiter colony community I really would like to have seen everything
move from the forums to that but so many people said I don't want to use G plus.
So what in this day and age so there's apparently some forums that the community still wants
to organize on and discuss a subset of the community but they don't want to create accounts
on some other services servers or anything like that.
What do you use and or maybe is it our forms just dead is it just maybe time we just say
goodbye forms you're in read only mode stop trying to make accounts everybody.
I mean I kind of have but people but people are still trying to do it.
Still trying to sign up still trying to engage in conversation in there.
We've been in Ubuntu we've been promoting discourse which is made by the same people
who make stack exchange Jeff Atwood and it's brilliant.
We've stood up Ubuntu discourse dog and it's a really lovely way to have discussion.
It's it it looks a bit like a forum and a bit like stack exchange it's got the best
bits of stack exchange and the best bits of forum.
What's the management like so like what's the up is it hosted or thinking about for
a while.
So we we run it on I think we run it on HP cloud but you know you can run it on anything
it's it's it runs on Linux.
We've written a juju charm for it so we can stand up an instance anywhere at any time
and we we we have the the upstream developers contribute on our discourse when this is when
I use this.
Yeah this I like.
Yeah I agree.
I think this is and you don't have to sign up it uses an open ID or whatever so you can
you can sign in with some other you know single sign on.
That is pretty cool.
All right that's a good recommendation.
What's attractive and yeah like you said with the sign on that's great.
Yeah so is this actually hosted as in could we host our own copy.
Yes.
Okay.
It's open source.
It's something I've been thinking about for quite a while Chris because I'm I'm one of
those people that try to sign up.
I'm actually a PHP developer and I was going to send you an email actually and ask if you
wanted something built but it's funny that you've spoken about it now.
Yeah yeah I know I get emails about it a lot so I know it's kind of a topic of that I just
don't really have a great forum to address a forum to address it.
I do like this discourse thing but I guess my the fundamental question I have is is it
still needed today.
I mean between all the social networks the IRC a mumble server TeamSpeak servers the
subreddits do we really need a forum too.
I personally I've sworn off forums ever since the change of the last Jupiter Colony forum
change.
I've been through forums ever since.
Dude that was like six years ago.
Wow.
Never have I gone on another forum since.
Well I was thinking of maybe doing something similar to maybe have a forum but with the
social networking aspect built in kind of with our own custom accounts on the Jupiter
Colony.
So how would that work?
We would have to find some software to run it on or have somebody develop it.
Well since discourse is open source why don't we just extend that.
Yeah I think that's something we should look into right there.
I like that.
I think that's the smartest approach.
All right.
Well thanks guys.
Sounds good.
Thanks guys.
So I'm going to mute the channel just for a little bit as we get to a couple emails
then we got to run because we're running long.
I don't you know it is it is a hard thing to get to these emails Matt but we got some
good ones.
Oh yeah.
We got some good ones and I think this one came in.
I think this one might have been on.
We got some bit messages too and it was from B via bit message.
Chris and Matt great job last unplugged.
We're going with Linux unplugged now.
Thanks to you clowns.
I will never ever get through my podcast back catalog.
Not only do I have another JB podcast on my list but you've turned me on to Star Trek
podcasts.
Now I get around 130 podcasts in my current queue.
I guess I'll have to tell my boss that it's your fault.
On the subject of mail service I've been running one for years.
I started out running CoLab on a spark station back in the day.
That box died about 10 years ago so I began running Zimbra on a P4 rack mount I had in
the basement.
He likes Zimbra quite a bit.
He says I was getting an email from my public mail service and collected them locally however
since ISPs had enough force I had to push the ISP had to push the force server used
but I'm going to jump ahead here.
He says that he says that he now that he's got now these really now the NSA shenanigans
have happened that he's doubled down on this in light of all of that and he's going to
set he's going to set it up for real again and maybe this time include Nagios alerts
and things like that for when it goes offline.
Yeah.
Sounds pretty snazzy.
I know I agree.
So all right.
So I want to read just a couple more.
I'm going to make it quick because I promised Matt I promised we would do it so I cannot
go back on my promise.
Here we go.
We did make that claim.
Juris, Linux handhelds.
Hello Chris and Matt.
Can I share can can you share your opinion on Linux handhelds in the open market at the
moment?
Like for example the open Pandora also the I have the new GW you want to know what we
thought about Linux on like handheld consoles.
Matt do you have any thoughts on that?
Honestly I can't speak intelligently to it because I haven't really subjected myself
to it extensively.
I think that actually is kind of an answer.
It's kind of like I want to.
I'm interested.
I'm open minded.
I know this GCW zero but it's kind of like you'll be really great.
What would make this GCW perfect is that if good old games were just like boom that's
our console of choice and we're now you're talking right.
Yes.
Right.
Because you can run DOS box on this thing.
So if you got DOS box going on this you could put you could run a ton of good old games
and if good old games could make a package and just be like pow I really think then you'd
really have something because the thing is is these little these little handheld consoles
like the open Pandora and the GCW zero are really cool.
They're open.
They're really neat.
They have.
Each one of them does something unique and interesting.
But the end of the day they're really going up against smartphones now.
You know if you know five six years ago that maybe not have been the case but now they
really are going up against smartphones so it's really got to stand out in some way.
So I'm hopeful the GCW but we'll see.
That would be cool.
I love the idea with good old games because that really solves the ecosystem problem for
that particular thing.
Yeah they just got to see the light and I am a big GOG fan.
But you know just like we've kind of seen them not really get the whole Linux thing.
All right.
We'll see.
Well chicken or the egg.
Chicken or the egg.
Exactly.
So John writes and he says I've been using play on Linux for some time now and the most
part I had moderate success.
What are your thoughts or experiences using any of these and which has worked best for
you.
I'd love to see some information on the subject.
Well boy for myself as a as a rule I think wine is a fine project where developers have
put in a lot of work and done wonderful things.
As a usage thing I won't use wine.
I will play in traffic on the freeway before using it just because it's not really my it's
just not my style.
I try to put my feet down and stick in a native environment if at all possible.
I almost in some cases will prefer to just do full on virtualization.
True.
That's it.
And this I think goes back to as a Linux user when I see something of value I buy it.
And since the mid 2000s I don't know when I mean for a very long time I have bought
every release of crossover office.
I have a current version as of today and I'm not a huge I play on Linux I've had really
hit and miss success with but crossover if they say it works in that.
So in crossover you first of all you get a really nice wrapper around wine.
You do.
You get bottles real nice so each thing you want to you get right under wine it has its
own self-contained configuration you can you can load stuff into it or you can have everything
isolated you can have different versions so I can have an XP bottle a 2000 bottle and
a Vista bottle or whatever.
And that's how I do Star Trek Online is and once you know and to their credit once crossover
said yeah we're going to support Star Trek Online it has worked solidly.
And a lot of things are like that and sometimes their list is a little lackluster like it's
like office 2010 is the latest but I found it to be accurate that's one thing I will
give them props for us that if they say it works it works yeah it's you know that I'll
give them props.
They've expanded a community supported section now so they've got ones that users can submit
that have been sort of vetted.
It's nice it's still not great though I mean like for example Star Trek Online takes ten
minutes to launch once it launches it's okay but for some reason under crossover wine it
takes ten minutes.
I know that so I just accept it and it works fine and it's fine.
But you know I'm with Matt I it's my it's my last resort.
Exactly and one other thing I thought they did well is at least they used to do bounties
so where there were you could actually chip in to help make this more compatible I don't
remember if they still do that or not now but they used to be you could actually throw
money in that direction to say I want this particular game or particular app to run.
I don't know I haven't tried that for a long time but yeah they had a voting system I think
that's still around.
A couple of quick things I just wanted to mention this is like pissing in the wind here
but if anybody out there has access to a computer around them that has iTunes Linux Unplugged
just hit the new and noteworthy section of iTunes if you give us a rating in the comment
that helps Discovery keeps us kind of in the charts for a while.
Once we're up there it helps and and the reason why I mentioned that is because if we stay
up there for a few days we'll probably have a few new thousand people several thousand
people find the show and that's that's a great thing for Linux and for the network in general
so I know it can be challenging for some of you Linux users out there to get access to
iTunes but if it happens somehow we would appreciate a vote absolutely and that's another
thing you can use wine for while you're not gonna be able to do a lot with it yeah you
can probably get an older version of iTunes cross over has like an installer script for
that yeah yes yeah it does okay so I think that was all the emails now I was kicking
around an idea before the show okay we don't have to do it you you have final call on this
Matt all right a lot of the pre shows on unplugged have been Star Trek heavy talk a lot of Star
Trek on the live show I unplugged we're recording Tuesdays a 2 p.m. Pacific over JB live TV
which is 9 p.m. UTC I believe join us over JB live TV if you can do it what do you think
Matt of watching Star Trek deep space 9 episode 1 before next week's unplugged and then at
the last last like 10 minutes or so of unplugged we'll sort of wrap up all of our topics and
we'll talk about that first episode it might just be for just like a minute or two or something
oh absolutely no I'm totally fine if that shoot me a email reminder the DS9 challenge
you want to the DS9 challenge okay and I that's one I'm actually my favorite out of the entire
I actually prefer that over TNG in a lot of ways so yeah I'm I've watched the hell out
of it so there's not a problem I I was I was really not sure what direction to go TNG
I lean heavily toss I definitely had to consider I mean it's the original the reason I'm not
doing toss is there's already a really great podcast out there that's talking about toss
mission log I mentioned them before and I don't want to step on their thing and it's
their whole show and but I need to I need to bring DS9 back into my life as a Star Trek
fan I go through these cycles of Star Trek re-ingestation where I reprocess and re-watch
and re-understand and I am now at that point with deep space 9 and I need to do it in order
so I'm in for this the long haul as long as the audience and you are so if you guys can
stick with it every single week I'm up for another episode I have I can somehow manage
to watch one episode of DS9 on Netflix between now and next week I can make that happen you
can make that commitment right yeah I can do it I can do it I'm you know I don't remember
it was a good episode you got like some bored cube action in there you got Jean-Luc in there
right there's a it's a very and it's really setting the pace for that first season yeah
so we'll see how it goes we'll see how you guys respond to that and and I know I said
I'd give you some more of my thoughts on the GCW zero but honestly I just haven't had much
time to play with it since last I did play with a little more and kind of waiting to
see my wife really likes it she thought it was really awesome she thought it was like
she said I think her words were like it looks like a much more modern DS or something she
said it looks really good so I'm gonna see how my kids react to it too because they haven't
really done a lot of controller stuff so maybe the next week or so we'll do a little chat
about the GCW zero sounds good alright so I'm gonna bring us through a close then if
you want to email the show you can do that just email Linux action show at Jupiter broadcasting
dot com we'll be watching that also you can submit things to our subreddit over at Linux
action show dot reddit dot com and that's a that's probably your best out of all of
your resources that's probably the best way to get something in front of us you can always
hang out in our IRC room too of course and join us there and chat with us and don't forget
to join us live and subscribe and download and if you're near an iTunes machine we could
use the help a little bit there too absolutely alright Matt we'll have a great week I'll
see you on Sunday sounds good see you then alright everyone well thank you so much for
tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged we'll see you right back here next Tuesday.