So Wes, what do you think of this concept of Linux speedruns? Oh, I'm hooked. I love it
I mean, I don't know if I'm up for it without reading some manuals first, but I like the idea
It wasn't it wasn't our idea. It was a post over at Rachel by the bay calm
She's blogged quite a few times and this one caught our attention because well, honestly
It's kind of a neat just idea on the surface
you start with a minimal system and then get yourself to the point where you can do something meaningful like I
Don't know download a picture from reddit or get in the IRC chat room like no nano no VI
Maybe you get cat
Okay, but you know certainly nothing like net cat or FTP or Ruby or Python or any of it?
Can you build yourself up from a bare bones Linux? Yeah, you could do that or another speedrun example could be like go through a testing
spree and
Test the latest Ubuntu release or test the latest fedora and see how fast you can spin them up
But go through a sequence of things and if you discover a bug report it and time yourself
I wouldn't mind doing some arch install speedruns. I think we have West
Hello friends and welcome to episode
349 of your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hey there, Wes. Hello looking great today
I'm sorry about the plexiglass between us social distancing you understand. Yeah, that's alright. I've got this nice suit on them
It's comfortable. Yeah, I'm actually impressed. It hasn't affected your audio quality
It's a special fabric. The mask is a little distracting West we have
One of these episodes that it felt really appropriate. We're gonna do something. You should never do today
Don't do what Wes and Chris are going to do. We're gonna build a server like you should not this is not a how-to episode
We're going to expose a server to the public internet open up a telnet port and have you pound on it to prove the scalability
Of a piece of hardware that we're going to be abusing in this demonstration. I think it's gonna be a lot of fun
but we have of course our
Steak and potatoes as well like community news and our virtual log time appropriate greetings mumble room. Hello. Hello
Happy happy Linux Tuesday. Happy Linux Tuesday everybody. Nice to see you back in there poppy
Hello Brent has been a little bit for you, too
And we have a great lineup there is 31 of our virtual lug in there right now. Wow, it's pretty great
We love you all. Yeah, it's really nice to see you there. We had we had a really fun pre-show over at JB live TV
We do the show on Tuesdays at noon Pacific, but you can get that converted at Jupiter broadcasting comm
Calendar, so let's start out with a little community news before we get into abusing hardware around here
there's a couple of stories that caught our attention and so this wasn't was
a partially inspired by our weekend activities
It's a little steam update. It's been a while since we've had one of these it has it has in part
It's both news and our weekend. It looks like really nice improvements for the 80 AMD
Easy for me to say radion graphic driver in version 5.8 of your Linux kernel will be landing
That'll be a good one lots of nice fixes in there and then also Nvidia just pushed out a new update
That helps improve some recent game releases run on proton, which I thought was just noteworthy because
Nvidia is specifically updating their driver to support proton now. Yeah, right
I think a lot of this is for doom eternal and wow
I mean something there's users complaining and Nvidia is actually being receptive. I guess I mean, this is like what is it?
This is how it works on Windows. This is weird. This isn't this is just awkward. I think first class
Yeah, so that's in the Nvidia version four dot four zero dot eight two stable long-lived
Quote-unquote Linux driver a Michael Arbel over at for Onyx has some really good coverage
But I think I just want to take a moment and check in with you guys because I know myself Wes and cheese have all
Been playing some proton games recently
before we get to that
Popey mentioned some really interesting data on a buntu podcast just some numbers that he noticed when they covered it on a recent episode
About the difference in graphics card usage. So yeah, I was reading the article and digging into the
Usual Steam survey and it struck me just how many
Machines in the Steam survey run Nvidia GPUs and I know it's anecdotally
We talk about how popular Nvidia is but I hear a lot in the community people saying I am D is trouncing
Nvidia and AMD is way more popular and they got much higher sales figures, but then when you look at the stats
It's nothing like it. There's way more like multiple more Nvidia cards than there are
AMD cards and in fact
There are more people with integrated Intel cards than there are AMD cards according to the steam stats if I'm reading them correctly
That's how I've read them too. I just assume it's people that are super casual gaming playing card games and simple games and hey
I'll raise my hand. I'm one of them. There's not many the Intel graphics will do for me
But there are some that's really interesting and I guess it's the video cards you have right sort of the reign of the default there
It just struck me that I would have expected there to be some parity there
I would have expected Nvidia and AMD to go toe-to-toe and have a similar spread of GPUs
Across the board from super high-end ones that you know, the real gamers have down to the low-end entry-level ones
But it really wasn't like that. It's just Nvidia from top to bottom and then a couple of AMD and a few Intel cards in there
It's really fast. It's worth a look. You really really should go and dig into those theme stats. Sometimes they're quite fascinating
What would your bet be for a year down the road?
Much the same. I
Don't see that everyone's gonna suddenly throw away like however many I can't remember the numbers
But it was something like of the top 40 cards in the list
60% or so were Nvidia
I can't see that many people throwing away their Nvidia cards and replacing them with with AMD overnight
I just can't see it. It'll be a long transition
If so, it's more like a next build do you think about it?
And if AMD is still really kicking butt then then that's probably the route you go
Well, you can also pick up a 2080 right now. I think for right around five six hundred dollars
So, you know that was a fourteen hundred dollar card six eight months ago. Yeah, yikes
I'll take one if you're buying cheese. Yeah cheese if you want to yeah God dang
That is I I would need to see hard data that proves that you have any real advantage with those cards under Linux
I will I will couch that same perhaps maybe under Windows in certain circumstances for sure
But I'm just not really sure if Linux games are fully taking advantage of it
I'd love to see the data that says they are if you're gonna invest
$600
Just you could buy a whole computer for that and play on the graphics that it comes with and maybe not notice a huge difference
I know that's old man Chris speaking, but but that frame rate Chris the frame rate
So I've been playing over the weekend Batman Arkham City on proton and it's pretty good
It's I I really actually don't have any complaints even on the e GPU. It's worked pretty well
I've only played for about two hours. So I don't have a ton of experience. So perhaps it gets I don't know
Maybe it doesn't work. Well, but this one's rated as gold on proton DB
So I think that's to take it works pretty good
Some people have had some crashes
I have not but I love love love the amount of games that are available now via proton and when I spent a
month on the Mac about a month ago now
I was shocked that the Mac has such a crappy game selection, which I believe there's actually more steam users using the Mac
But there's when you consider proton
Way more games available for Linux and then when you add the fact that you can get a much wider range of gaming hardware
Yeah, you're not just stuck on whatever man yeah, yeah
It's way better on the Linux platform despite what the numbers may what a weird switch of scenario. It really is
It's it's I mean fantastic. Yeah, totally. So what have you been playing? I'm playing risk of rain, too
Well, I started off playing some tabletop simulator, which I'm pleased to note does have a native Linux built
Which worked beautifully. I hadn't had steam installed for a while
I like gaming but I'm very much a casual gamer when I have time, you know
And as many folks are doing these days
I was having a virtual video hangout with some folks and they were all gonna start playing I'd never played risk of rain 2 before
It's a third-person shooter roguelike a lot of fun lots of fun enemies to shoot and kill super fun
Yeah, and I was like, okay. Well, it's been a while since I tried proton. It's has platinum support over on proton TV
Let's give it a go. Yeah, when you said you tried it and I looked it up on proton DB
I said, oh so you must have had no problem playing this
So this is where me being a little bit of a newbie to proton. Maybe wasn't the best. I had just reinstalled steam
I'd you know installed everything I needed to go along with it
I tried a couple other proton games and that worked this one the launcher would load up
We'll scroll bar going, you know loading the game and then nothing just it even even sometimes it would say it was running
But nothing showing up on my screen
So I had to go dig in and try to enable logging and still nothing and eventually I found some post somewhere that
Reminded me I didn't I didn't have the Mesa Vulcan drivers. Oh, yeah, so one little package and then it was perfect
yeah, and some distributions make that a little more discoverable than others and there's other ways of
Installing it that sometimes pull in some of those dependencies, right?
Yeah, in this case, I was just installing steam right out of it. But so once that got
No complaints at all and it even ran on this ThinkPad right here with integrated graphics
I mean I did turn the settings down a little bit, but that was fine worked on the Intel chip, huh?
that's right, so you're one of those numbers there and
Like me your experience was probably like you would have no idea. This is a
Not at all didn't have to mess around with wine or bottles or any of that nonsense. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah
I know I love it so much. So what about you cheesy? What are you been playing? Is it on proton? Yeah, it's on proton
It's platinum level. It's raft
Essentially you float around on a raft try not to get eaten by a shark and you can play with I think up to four
people no
This sounds great
It's a super fun game
you build out your raft and you kind of float to these different islands and then eventually you can unlock a
Radio that'll allow you to get beacons so you can direct toward different islands and you essentially just pick up ocean trash the entire game
And build your raft with it. It's a really fun game
works right out of the box. I haven't had any issues any crashes or anything like that running on top of a rx-580 and
It's it's it's a super fun game. I played on with you know for hours on end with it and
Never had any issues. You know what I'm thinking is we need to do a game sesh between you me and Dylan and
You know get a little raft going this sounds like something he'd love game on. That was his birthday today
His birthday today happy birthday Dylan Dylan turns 11 years old Wow
which the thing that really blows my mind about that is
It was right around when he was born that I was like, I'm going serious with with the whole podcasting thing
So it's been 11 years since it's been my full-time job
11 years full-time podcasting. Can you believe that that doesn't seem and in his world is totally normal, right?
He's grown up with that like oh, yeah, my pops just a full-time podcaster. Yeah, he's got it
Yeah, he's got this building we go to this his studio for podcasting. It's really it's really kind of it's kind of remarkable and
He and I have been loving loving playing games via Steam on his laptop and I have it on my laptop and it's just been
Awesome. So I'm really pleased with the state of proton
I know there was some issues around like a development capacity for it
But so far it really seems to be kicking ass and now
Both AMD and Nvidia are spending resources on development time to make games work
It's it's not perfect. It's not native games. It's not the ideal scenario
But you'd be surprised how often weird abstraction layers like this exist in the gaming industry
I mean, it's one it's just it's just very technically clever
I'm very impressed with the work and two
I mean it might be a good long-term play in the sense of alright
Well, once you start seeing how many folks on Linux are willing to play these games once they work
That's some good data for perhaps more native games down the line. So some really good game suggestions, too
I really have been enjoying Batman Arkham City. It's it's a little bit on rails
But at the same time you can fly around Arkham City and it gives you the instructions
You need to feel like you're playing the game like a competent person when you're not necessarily
So I like it if you're not of a serious as a gamer
Risk of rain 2 was Wes's that looks like a lot of frickin fun and then raft which I'm installing after the show cheese
There will have links to their proton pages and stuff in the show notes at Linux unplug calm slash
349 if you've got any great picks yourself. Why not? Give us an email when it's unplug calm slash contact now
There's some news that just broke that poppy brought to our attention before we hit record that Wes and I are still chewing on and it's
Github's huge announcement that it is now free for teams Nat Friedman writes on the github blog
We're happy to announce we're making private repositories
with unlimited collaborators
Available to all github accounts all of the core of github features are now free for everyone to use
This means teams can now manage their work together in one place
CICD project management code review packages all that and actually a whole lot more
We want everyone to be able to ship great software on the platform developers love
So this also very practically means I'm no longer paying a subscription for private repositories
Yeah, you got a free plan now, but yo
But you spotted a comment that Nat Friedman made about this on hacker news, which I think adds some context to this
Yeah, he wrote
We've wanted to make this change for the last 18 months
But needed and this parts key needed our enterprise business to be big enough to enable the free use of github
By the rest of the world in general. We think that every developer on earth should be able to use github for their work
So it's great to remove that as a barrier. Is it a strategic move computer kid?
That would make sense since they are very competitive
Since Microsoft bought github get lab has been kind of gaining more users since a lot of people aren't trusting
Microsoft and moving over to get lab. So it would make sense that they're trying to
Get another one up
It seems like a competitive move against get lab and just at the end of last month get lab moved a bunch of stuff
You know that had previously been in there their private version over to the the free version
There's also some good comparisons in that same hacker news thread around what things you might you know the difference between what what's free and get
Lab what's free and github?
So there's still some reasons you might choose one over the other and I'll also note there's been some
Some nuances here as there always are sure it's cheaper now
but for instance used to get if you had this this old pro plan you got a certain number of action minutes for the
New github actions and on the free one while you get less and it turns out to get back to that same amount
You probably have to pay two times the price. So great news in general
Go check it out for whatever your particular needs are
I think bitmux you make a good point that it's in Microsoft's interest for a lot of their other
Ancillary service to get as many people using github as possible. Yeah, I was just thinking about it
It's like well, we host code and we solve problems and we sell software and it's like I have a problem
I think I'd like to see if there's a solution for it. Oh, I'll check my own product
Good github. I'll look to see if somebody solved this problem for me and they're they're already been doing that for years and years
But now they own the platform and so if they can bring the entirety of the world's development brainpower
Under their under their roof. They'll take that. Thank you very much
You could also say that this is a win for the open source community to some regard too because I mean this now allows
teams and you know to possibly develop applications together where they might not have
Been able to do that otherwise or just couldn't afford the four bucks the nine bucks a month to do so. So I
mean
I see it as kind of a positive move, but I can also see the Microsoft aspect as well
And I've been following the whole github and gitlab thing for a while now
So I don't think that that debates ever gonna go away personally, right?
I mean, there's always the issue of it's easier now to use a proprietary platform and that is good and maybe a little bit bad
too, yeah, but it does ultimately mean there's gonna be
Probably more software developed and published online. That's more accessible to more
So that's good. Seems like totally kind of a net win because it makes
Get lab more competitive. It makes github more competitive. It's kind of a win-win and I also know
You know some of the folks over it get lab jumped in the comments, too
Of course, and it does seem like it's a friendly rival. You know, they're not out to get each other
No one's slashing throats here. It's they're both making great products. There's use cases for everything and
Thankfully, it's all powered by git. It's true. All right
Well, let's look a little head because just around the corner is the release of a buntu
20 Oh for we're cooking up a review right now
weeks in the making
Going deep on this one. The current target release date is April 23rd
2020 so it's coming up just next week. So your Linux unplugged program will likely have its review next week for you right on the nose
It's gonna feature Linux 5.4. And why your card is essentially
Pre plumbed at least the holes are dug right West you actually got it going on 24 pretty easily
Yeah, I mean the modules already ready for you
So just you know mod for a wire garden away you go and then the you know
The tools the wire guard tools package is just an apt install away. Yes, that's nice. It's right there in the repo also
The snapshot system that's built into the ZFS file system that happens like every time you install a package
things like that has seen a nice couple of tweaks including one that makes it much much much quicker to
Go through the list of possible snapshots in grub
and the way this works is you have just an entry in grub you select that and
That will have all of the previous snapshots which you can boot from and we're talking a pretty dramatic
like a hundred
Seconds sometimes for something to load so well over a minute. What's wrong with my computer?
Why won't it boom and now it's near instantaneous?
Which is pretty great and I got some hands-on experience with that which I'll try to include in my review next week
So it's coming pretty close Wes. I know I mean, you know still
Experimental and ext4 is of course the default file system still but from when this option first appeared
I'm really impressed and it's it really I think points the way to the glorious snapshot future that we might all have
And probably I believe the testing week just wrapped up. That seems like it was pretty well attended pretty well utilized
That was great. It was a community organized test week. We you know, we always have these test weeks, but we don't often have
as much visibility and as many people participating and use of Phillips who's
active in the ability community decided to take the bull by the horns and
Did a whole lot of promotion invited a whole load of people from all the different ability flavors
So the XFC flavors of one two and come on two and so on get them all on board
so they all promoted it individually as a central effort and
loads of people joined in and started testing this thing and we got a whole bunch of
bugs reported as a result because you know who knew software has bugs and
Put more work on the desktop team before the release a week before the release whoopsie, but yeah, it's really good
It's really really good. It's a model that others could follow. I I love there was community started too. That's really great
That's super cool. So we'll give you our take on that next week now
before we get to
Exposing our telnet server to the internet and releasing the hounds onto it
We do have just a little bit of housekeeping
So I start with some unfortunate news
This week you may have heard that we have ended the production
immediately of Linux action news
choose Linux and
user air which
Really stings because I was a personal favorite podcast of mine. It just hurts. I loved user air
but after a
lengthy internal investigation a cloud guru management who owns
The podcast Jupiter broadcasting who we are all employed by
Determined that they had no choice but to terminate
Joe Resington's contract with a cloud guru, which means he'll no longer be on any Jupiter broadcasting podcasts or
employed by a cloud guru effective
Immediately, so the ramifications of that are obviously pretty dramatic
Not only do we have to immediately cease production on some shows which I've worked on and essentially for 14 years like Linux action news
but it also
Does have an impact on this show?
Joe joined us. I think in the spring of 2018
Took our audio from amateur to pro, you know
It's when we went from a mixed to stereo track where everybody was talking over each other
No edits right to multi-track polished sinking it up. You can tell I mean if you go back and listen to the archive
You can tell immediately
It's just I couldn't get it across the line on my own and I mean it wasn't just that I mean
You know all the care he had for the audio the mastering the mixing that the sound
But also the behind-the-scenes the production work the critiques of things we did wrong input on topics
Mm-hmm. Yeah, so his mark will always be on the show and on that on that ring of shows that he had there
But moving forward drew will be editing and I can genuinely say he's a fantastic editor
it may sound slightly different, but I think it'll still sound great knowing drew it will and
He if you've heard him on choose Linux, you've heard him on this show
He's another one of these exceptional assets to our team much like Joe was
and
Drew will be taking over the editing of the show and I I have confidence in his ability completely
but I just personally want to thank Joe for his time one of the things that he did that was special for the show is
He worked and an unrealistic schedule that
Meant that he was up until 4 or 5 a.m. To work on the show
So that way we could get it out Tuesday night or Wednesday morning for people's commute
You can't just ask someone to shift their timezone eight hours. Yeah, and he did it so that way the audience got the show as fast
as possible in the best quality as possible and
I think that's been something that we're gonna try to continue to do. You know, it's of course within
Expectations of the team's capability now, but one one advantage that drew has is he's not in London
He is he is actually here in the States. So
That will help time zone wise but Joe made a statement on late night Linux
Which I recommend you go check out at late night Linux
Go go subscribe in your favorite podcast catcher because it's a great show anyways, but he covers it right there
He says all that really needs to be said in
That episode so go check that out for his statement. I mean, I think there's not much more that can be said to it
Right. That is just what it is
And I will be putting my focus from what I did some of the time I spent on Linux action news
into the show
One other adjustment that is happening is we are reducing the cadence of Linux headlines
from every weekday to Monday Wednesday Friday and
Some of the news that would have gone into LAN will go into headlines. So we'll just sort of divvy up some of that work and
That is the state of things for now
The plan is to keep trying to invest as much as we can in fact make Linux unplugged bigger and better than ever and that's our
focus now going forward and
I hope you will keep subscribed Linux unplugged comm slash subscribe and join us for the next series of episodes like
You know as a team, we're just really trying to kind of put it all together still. It's still new for us, too. Mm-hmm
I was not involved in the decision process. So I found out after it was official and
Just kind of dealing with it as as we can and that's true for all of us. Yeah, so we're sorry
It was you know, it's it's quick. Sometimes things go that way
It's not how we would have planned it, but that's the world we live in. Yeah, that's that
You know
We are our intention is always and always will be to try to give you as much notice before we wrap up a show
But one of the things I've learned about the media business is sometimes that it just does not work that way despite your best
Intentions and I felt that way super strongly since the finale of Star Trek Voyager. Yes, right
That was that is that is when I learned an important lesson that you need to brace yourself for the end of something you've been
listening to or watching every week and from that moment, which is what 2001?
I don't know from that moment forward. It has been a core belief of mine
So we always will strive to give you as much heads up as possible. Sometimes it is outside our control though a
little bit of good news though
Our good friend Heather from side bite has rejoined us for a very special extra the resilience of the Voyagers
These things were built to last the Voyager probes 42 years in county
They probably won't be lasting much longer. In fact, we're about to enter a very crucial period where we will be dismantling some of these
Infrastructures that are on the planets. Yeah, the big old radio telescopes
so we will not be able to communicate and
It's all detailed in the resilience of the Voyagers about how they were built about some of the special things about them
I tell you what with everything going on right now. There was something about that episode. I found super inspirational
So that's at extras dot show slash 70 right on the nose
So great to talk to Heather again, too. She's the best so you gotta give that a go give that a go and then I want
I want to also give a plug for something that's pretty neat that's developing in the community right now
It's the luck plug our virtual lug is also assembling an extra day in the week on Sunday
Sunday at noon Pacific that's when we would normally do the show our regular live time, but on Sunday
This Sunday myself and cheese are gonna try to make in attendance. I think I'll be talking a little bit more about the hardware device
We're using today. That's gonna be something I'd like to talk about
I guess they did it last Sunday and they were saying it went for hours
You know people come and go as they can so it's a virtual lug on the weekend
If you can't make it on a Tuesday, the virtual lug is assembling on the mumble spot. You same spot same bat time
It's just different bat day. And if you google search Jupiter colony mumble
you'll get all of the information on how to connect just get mumble installed from your repo and
Except the fact that the certificate has expired apparently
I love that. We have another great reason to get the mumble set up
You know like join the lug hang out and then you'll be ready to go for today
I mean, I'm gonna be doing it maybe with like a sparkly beverage with my feet up at the RV
I think that's how I'm gonna do it. It's gonna be like totally chillax. Well, and I love that
This is spawned out of the community. So the community thought hey, let's get together and just have a have a lug
And I think this will be a great opportunity for everybody to learn a few little things and from the the sounds of it
There's no itinerary. It's just free-flowing. So everybody will get a chance to chime in. Sounds like a fun time
It's just nice to chat with other people that know what you're talking about when you're talking about Linux stuff
That's just that's just a great rewarding conversation. It'll be in the lobby of our mumble server
So again, just google search Jupiter colony mumble or join the geek shed IRC IRC geek shed net
There is now a hashtag lup lug geek shed channel
That'll be going all the time. So IRC geek shed net hashtag
lup lug and people in there probably help you get connected to the mumble room if you have any problems
How great is that? Fantastic and it's just a quick mention for our telegram group at Jupiter broadcasting comm telegram
That is the persistent universe of this podcast. That is where the conversation continues
Even when the podcast is not being produced or released as well as conversations around the network
Jupiter broadcasting comm telegram
The persistent universe, you know, it's like an MMO but only chatting
Something like that. So we're gonna do something that you really should never do. We are going to build
what we think is
near
Ideal pine 64 rock pro 64 server grade setup. And I think this could be a candidate for
Just about anyone's home server anyone who needs to maybe run some plaques some network monitoring
Maybe a little authentication some name resolution some ad blocking. Maybe you want a self-hosted wiki
Maybe a little home assistant all of these things on one device that takes 12 volts of power
I mean, we know you've been a little bit obsessed with these, you know, I mean computer boards with arm
You've got raspberry pies, I think basically everywhere in your I do and I was I really like the raspberry pie because it feels
Like a platform that is well supported with a community around it, right tons of guides tons of images
I think and you guys correct me if i'm wrong, but I think the second to that now has become the pine 64 boards
You know, i'm happy to see that you're kind of
Now falling into this addiction for single board computers. I've been dealing with this for quite some time now
My shelf is full of these boards. But man, the rock pro board is one of the best boards out there right now
A great great little machine. I'll tell you what put me over the top on it is it has a pci express slot
So let that sink in for a second express by far man pci 4x
and
That meant that you could put a gigabit nick in there
You could put a sata expansion card in there or you could do like we did again
Not recommending you do this, but you could do like we did and you could get an mvm
e
pci adapter that will take an mvme drive and
Click it right into that pci slot
And then you're doing
Like real data transfer speeds, right? I mean so this has been sitting around on the shelf for a little while
We hadn't had a chance to really check it out yet. And so of course when we first booted it up on the sd card
well
It was slow. I mean it felt almost
Somewhat perceptibly faster than the raspberry pi, but that's a hard thing to quantify at the command line
It didn't really seem significantly better
And then you combine that with the network effect and community effect or the raspberry pi and you start to think well, maybe a right
I mean, you know, you have to find different images. There's like a you know, that's a little bit of a
Process and they're you know custom builds from members in the community
And on top of all of that, how do you tell performance when everything's waiting on the desk? So the rock pro
64 is special in a couple of ways. It has
ddr4 ram lpd ddr4 ram so it's faster ram than what's on the raspberry pi. It has gigabit ethernet
It has an emmc module slot
It has a full-size 4k support hdmi video out
It has usb 3 it has usb 2
and it has
the 40 gpi opens you'd expect as well as
That pci slot we mentioned and a real-time clock. Okay, that's actually also worth mentioning isn't it?
Because the pi doesn't have that does it right?
So that's also uh, kind of great and kind of nice and cheesy
You have been sort of trying to get me to try it out for a while
And I think the part that where you're trying to get me to try it out for a while
And I think the part that where you convinced me was when you showed me like some of the nas boxes people are building with
This thing pine themselves actually sell a nas case that you can buy but
There are all there are tons of 3d printed cases out there for the pine 64
And I think really what it comes down to is adding that pcie lane breaking that out
Really kind of expands what you can do with this board and you know
Just like you said this would be the perfect board even if you just slapped a couple of sata drives in
The nas case I think will support uh, two three point fives or two two point fives
perfect for your little home file storage or
Home assistant or any any sort of you know, shinobi or anything like that
This would be the perfect box for that. This probably would be a lot better box for my for my shinobi setup at the rv
So let's get into the setup here
I want to give you a price range and I I want to challenge you that if you're setting up a home server
That is based on an x86 box right now
And you don't have more than 12 people living in your home. You need to really seriously consider what i'm talking about
But don't do what I do, but you should think about it. So the rock pro 64 4 gigabyte
System is 80. I'm rounding up here in all these numbers. I'm rounding up
A power adapter which it will not come with will cost you 12. You need 12 volt 5 amp power adapter non-switching
I bought a 250 gigabyte
I bought a 250 gigabyte mvme western digital blue drive standby on why I went blue
$55
And then the mvme pci adapter
$11
So my total rounding up for all of this for a system that I think would compete with a nuke for most home server uses
150 us greenbacks 150 total all in for a system
that is
remarkably performant and the other nice thing about the rock pro 64 4 gigabyte board is it is designated by pine 64
As a long-term support board, so they're committing to supplying it for five years
So that's until 2023 at least which is maybe one of those factors that helps build the community of people using it
When you add in this 11 dollar pcie adapter and then you just snap in the blue and I went with I went with the one
I'll have linked in the show notes because it supports the western digital blue drives
And I think possibly according to their wiki the pine 64
Pci mvme adapter does not support western digital blue
The reason I opted to go for blue is they have a good life cycle
But also you're not gonna get the full beans with this disc on the pine 64
The reality is the PCI bus is limited to such that you're gonna get good performance
But you're not gonna get high-end MV me performance. So here's the numbers you're gonna see it essentially works out
What did we decide? What do we figure out was a 30 30 times speed difference about?
Yeah
when we switched from an SD card to this MV me drive that
Took an $11 adapter and then a $55 West digital blue off Amazon
We went from a 22 megabyte a second transfer rate
to around
110 615 megabytes a second on average and it peaks above that and
When you open up the disk, I owe like that all of a sudden you truly appreciate
What the rock pro 64s CPU is actually capable of it is truly IO bound by that SD card or eMMC
I would assume and you just open up the floodgates. It's remarkable what you can achieve
And so we thought we'd have a little bit of fun with it here on the podcast, right?
I mean you said you wanted us to use it as a server
So we thought why not set something up on telnet that we could give out to folks that they could they could connect to
So are you ready for me to give out the URL? Yeah. All right, so I would encourage you if you're listening live right now
Let's see how many connections this pine 64 rock pro 64 running off an MV me can take what we have here in
a container
Because what else would it be is I believe it's the Star Wars new hope in ASCII
That's right the famous one, you know, you can see we've got a self-hosted version
So, let's see how many ASCII streams of Star Wars the new hope we can get going right now chat room
Telnet to telnet Linux unplugged calm everyone telnet
Linux unplugged calm launch it up right now
Additionally for yeah, people are joining are they all right, I'm gonna open up two over here. Oh, yeah. Okay. I got mine going, too
Now if we can't bring this thing to its knees
We have prepared a punishment script
Oh God that will spawn hundreds of telnet sessions and start this thing now in our original tests off air
We were only able to test against the SD card, which was intrinsically bound by disk.io
I mean every time you'd launch a new client you'd be like, all right
Well, I'll wait for it to read the text off the disk. All right, give it a go
I am currently getting the Star Wars scroll right now same. Yeah, I got to say no
We've got I mean looks like like 20 plus already. All right, and
Let's how's it doing in that? Let's bring up the net data. Wes
Let's bring up the net data. So Wes and I are both monitoring on net data right now
Now you got to imagine this thing is rendering this ASCII out and then spitting it out over telnet to how many over 20 plus
Sessions, right? It's not it's gotta be 30 now. It's not a super complicated task, but it's a significant task and right now
it's sitting at a
Range of 8 to 14 percent CPU usage Wow, and every time it's doing this
It's spinning up a whole bunch of Python in the back end
Reading these files. It's it's actually a kind of an IO heavy workload surprisingly on the back end
But we're not even we're not even really cracking 14 percent 11
11 percent CPU usage right now
22 percent RAM usage a consistent near 3 megabits of telnet data is coming out of this thing right now
Pure text pure 3 megabits of text
Do you want to launch the punishing scripts? Oh, oh do I let's do it now this script will launch
hundreds of telnet sessions at the pine 64 rock pro 64
We just peaked up to 24 percent there for a second
I'm curious. Do you have a rough guess on how many connections we have there because we just hit 30 percent there for a second
Yeah, looks like well, let's let's pop over here
I mean, it's it's gotta be 40 50 my movies still streaming. Yeah, man
Hey, what do you expect that we get thrown out of there? So the telnet session is closing or what?
I don't know if it's gonna freeze up or
If our internet connection goes first, I'm curious to see which one it is
We're up to 32.2 percent 32.6 percent. Actually, it's climbing pretty pretty fast
We're now at 33 percent RAM usage seems a little slower
35 we almost just cracked 40 percent load 200 additional telnet clients
Just hit 44 percent. Oh, yeah, okay
So now we have like like what nearly 300 telnet sessions coming off this thing. I think it's getting slower now
I'll tell you my laptop is handling it poorly. Look at this
You can really start to see the load average increase on the box. Now. It's starting to get cooked. Oh
We just hit 45 percent. I think the internet connection is gonna go
Do you have passive cooling on that one or do you have some kind of ventilation just passive?
It's gone up not too much. It started around like 46 or so and now it's up to 52
It's just out in the open. Like I said, don't build it like this. I think if I was gonna build this for real I
Would probably probably try to get some sort of cooling solution on it, but I'd want it to still be quiet
So it'd have to be somewhat passive, but there's no heat sink or anything on it right now
I didn't get anything like that on the box. So we're just using it out of the box. Whoa
Oh, oh, we just hit 54 percent there on the old usage. Look at the net data charts
It's really starting to get up there now. I
Wonder if I could see how many network connections we have will it tell me? Oh my gosh
Oh
Holy crap
We have over four hundred and four hundred nineteen active sessions right now on this box
Look at that line just rocking up there and this thing's still going. I
Don't know if we can kill it. I don't know if we can do it
Do you know in that laptop handle? Can you launch another 200? I can try
Doesn't seem very convincing there. We're running into the limits of what West's think-pack can handle. What do you think Wes?
All right, launching if anybody listening live has a way to spawn multiple telnet sessions
Go ahead and do it. Just give us the number in the chat room so we can do it. I've got like 60 of them. Go. Yeah
Yeah, one easy way to view if you launch a whole new terminal telnet can be a little fussy to run in the background
But if you just launch a whole new terminal and find whatever your terminal is for console stash
II and you can pass in the telnet command. So now we're at 47% 45%
We're almost halfway pegged. It's really impressive. We're at 61% ram usage now
We did hit a hundred and thirty megabytes a second on the disk IO for a brief moment
But it's settling down now because I think the batch of sessions is has settled. Isn't that impressive though? I think I think
Point may I mean you have nearly I wonder if we could see again
I mean the number of connections is just staggering at this point five hundred active connections
Could you imagine doing this back in the day? Oh, we're up to like five megs
Your text goodness five megs of pure text. How about that? Isn't that something?
Well the pine 64 rock pro 64 gets
My such a solid nod of approval after this modification
that
This is what I'm buying from now on. So the other nice part is I just SSH back into the box and you can't tell anything
Right, so it's not like it's a horrible experience for the admin while this is going on
Wow, wow, wow, wow, you guys can keep throwing at it if you want
but
This is this is a game changer as far as I'm concerned
I mean, it's just for the power and the price and all of that. It's just it's remarkable
So Wes, we did a real quick brief modification to start loading the system off of the MVME
Versus the SD card. So job one was to attach the MVME format it
Label it and then our sink over the SD card to that excluding like, you know proc and things like that
But then there was another tweak that we had to make to get it to actually load from the MVME
Yeah, and maybe here's a good time to mention that we're running in Mutt & Jones
Yeah, and maybe here's a good time to mention that we're running in Manjaro arm on this thing. Yes
Thank you. It started out with army and and that was working. All right, but
Manjaro has been such a dream
Partially because it already had kernel 5 6 ready to go working perfectly and that also man
It was really easy right now. We're funneling this through a droplet back here so that you don't get the studio
I yeah, it's just over wire card
that's a nice little advantage to using Manjaro on the pine 64 is
That the latest kernel means wire guards ready to go
And so you guys have all been doing this through you're going through a wire guard connection. You didn't even know it
So on top of that it's handling the crypto for wire guard like a freaking champ
I might add so we that's really impressive and it's meant that you know
All the various tools we needed getting you know Docker up and running
Getting the benchmark tools we were using going all that was easy because it was just right there in the repo. Yeah, and
with them focusing on the
pine book
Which is essentially the same internals as far as I understand it. It means that this thing's pretty much ready to go
So we grabbed I think it was actually labeled the pine book image for those
Which has worked just fine to get it actually running on the nvme was surprisingly easy
It looks like they're using the ext Linux bootloader at least as part of the boot chain
So really all we had to go do was modify ext linux.com and change, you know at the start
It's just it's just a label brute. So it finds that on the SD card
We just repointed that at the nvme drive and no problems that I mean we were a little skeptical
We hadn't tried this before and we're both not that familiar with some of the booting on these ARM systems
I figured it wouldn't work
We'd have to pull the SD card off and you know change things around a couple times worked first time flawlessly. Yeah, and
We knew instantly because it booted in a blink
We put it so fast. We're like, oh well that that had to be it
And of course we logged in and immediately confirmed it and I just I got underscore all of this for
150 US greenbacks off Amazon or wherever you get your pine pine rock pro 64
So man Jarrah was pretty great having wire guard in there is really nice
There's also a bunch of other OS as though cheese you told me about arm being recently
Yeah, so there's arm being it's out there that
You know is developed for a lot of these other boards, but there are a ton of other builds available for this rock pro 64
I mean if you want to get your slack wear on your
Open media vault might be a great solution if you're gonna use this as a NAS
centos
Manjaro obviously
Straight-up Debian if you want
You know, I would like to see maybe
Punishing it with other things as well
Like I don't know throwing a mumble server on there seeing how many we could get on there or something like that
You're getting you know
610 megabits a second
Read write on the disk compared to the 22 that you were getting off the SD card
You'd probably get anywhere from 100 to 150
Off an eMMC module, but at that 610 that you're getting off the NVMe
You could go with an SSD might be a little bit less expensive if you wanted to double up drives
Might cost you a little bit more money, but you're gonna run around the 500 megabits a second
Speed on that so you are gaining a little a little bit by using the NVMe and I'm sure
Like you said whenever you initially logged in you immediately were able to tell the difference the pine folks. They sell a rock pro like compatible
SAT adapter that has two ports on it. So you could easily probably do that. That's a great. That's a great idea
I wasn't really clear on what kind of performance I was good
I didn't I was just gonna be happy with several hundred megabytes, but I'm pretty thrilled because it's peaked above 600, too
Which is nice. I'll tell you what. I'm building everything with this for my home server stuff. I'm gonna keep my pies
I think they're great. But in the future, I'm just gonna use these they're just that much faster
the PCI slot means that I could use them for different tasks Wes and I are already kind of
Thinking about how great you could
Really build a router out of this thing if you just put a nice gigabit Nick in that PCI slot
Yeah, I think over the weekend. I saw Ryan Huber
One of the nebula depths we've had on the show and he's got himself a little PI router
This seems like it'd be a great upgrade for that. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, especially because it'd be out right there on the PCI bus
It's sort of it sort of sets my benchmark now for any kind of small board computer
It needs to have PCI Express like this is the game changer for me when it comes to these devices
And manager has been super solid on there. I look forward to also trying to boot too
I don't know if but is there an Ubuntu image for I don't think oh no I did
I said I know for one at least I haven't seen a 2004 one
One of the things the pine 64 folks have is I think it's a fork of etcher
That just downloads images that are compatible with the pine 64 that you so you select which one you have
Which model of device you have and it downloads the image and then writes it for you to an SD card
Which makes it really simple. I mean, it's pretty big difference
I mean an average of 610 megabytes a second versus 22 and then you're really fueling that processor
you combine that with the gigabit Nick and
It's remarkable what Linux can do on a computer that costs
$80 to make this all happen. We discovered a handy little open-source Python program called ASCII tell that server
Yeah, it does exactly what it sounds like so we didn't have to go
You know hammer some other person's server and it's a pretty simple little Python script ready to go in a Docker container
And if you want to try yourself
Just hit the show notes
Why wouldn't you so everybody kind of calmed down on the old server punishment and then Alex got in on the fun
And he spawned a thousand sessions and for a second there
We just hit 60% load when he after he spawned a thousand telnet sessions to this thing 10,000 sessions
Well, I'm sorry what?
10,000 sessions at least that's what his numbers say. Are you serious? Mm-hmm. Oh my gosh. That's a lot
It really is impressive. It's it is using 74% of the RAM now
And it is definitely loading up the CPU
Oh
Man, that is really nuts. Look at that thing go. It's hitting that disk, too
That's fascinating every time a new batch starts the disk IO really kicks up
Yeah, there are some optimizations that could be had in this Python program. Yeah, but it seems like it's really delivering
so that's pretty neat that was fun. Thank you everybody for participating and
Don't do what we do. But if you do, I think you're gonna be impressed with the results
All right. How about some app picks before we get out of here? This is one
we've been kicking around for a couple of weeks, but we finally had a chance to
Sneak it in its beats and not the headphones
So yeah this week beats with its cute little beat icon is a media library management system for
Obsessive music geeks is how they label themselves
Basically allowing you to pull all the metadata from your collection of music or media files
Allow you to easily tag those with music brains discogs a beat port
Transcode your audio into any format that you'd like and even launch a web server from within beats to allow you to
You know query your your music collection that way you can listen to your tracks there provided
You know, you have an HTML 5 browser, which you wouldn't
you know, it's a great little tool command line basically and
get in there and tag all your music and and
Get it all sorted up the way you like to have your music tagged and sorted and I think it's a cool little app
I think it's perfect for people who are obsessive about
Tagging their music and wanting their tags to be correct
Or at least consistent so get out there and give it a shot. Very nice. That is something I will check out
It's beats be ETS and we'll have a link in the notes if you want to check that out
It is nice to have that stuff figured out. I know I've got some old music collection
Then I just kind of stay away from it because I know it's a mess. Yeah, it's MIT licensed to so have added Haas
It's all yours. That's pretty nice. Well, there you go. That's our episode for today
Be sure to check out the Ubuntu podcast where you can get more poppy
be sure to check out tech snap where you can get Westpain along with Jim Salter and
check out my personal site Chris last calm where I have new projects and
What nots over there as well as self-hosted where a lot of the stuff about things you run yourself on your own infrastructure
Or where you make compromises and host in the cloud are discussed on the self-hosted podcast at self hosted dot show
Any other business with maybe you have some homework to finish watching Star Wars after the show. I
Like this whole outfit this quarantine outfits good. I I didn't know they sold the quarantine outfits sort of styled as a pimp suit
It looks good on you. I mean, it's getting a little warm, but thankfully it's sealed up. So you can't smell anything
Yeah, no, it's kind of nice. It's kind of nice
Although that hole in the face mask so you can use the microphone seems like it invalidates the entire point
I have to look up the science. Yeah, I noticed you coughing into the mic, too
I don't like that check out Linux unplug calm slash three four nine four notes for everything. We talked about please join us live next Tuesday
We love having you here. It makes it that much better at JB live TV noon Pacific
And of course, we're in that mumble room this Sunday at noon. See you next Tuesday
Well, we've now hit 82% 86% on the rock pro 64 at 98% memory usage
Wow, I can't believe we haven't run out of sockets yet. This is unbelievable really Oh up to 61 degrees Celsius
And how is net data even still responding? I don't even know that data. You're the best. How is this happening right now?
Yeah, what are you doing? What are you doing? What are you doing? What are you doing? What are you doing?
To accomplish 81% CPU uses. Oh, we're starting to get drops in the data. I just got my first drop in the data
So we're really getting there now
98.1% memory usage by the way, we are doing a consistent
253 megabits of disk reading
Can I just read these stats for a second 82% CPU usage?
253 megabits consistently from the disk and 98.1%
RAM and I think it may have just finally locked up. Are you still on the console over there? Are you still ssh-ed in?
Yeah, it's still responding. It looks like net data has died
Yeah, I got dropped too. This is so bad. I was just in the middle of the movie