Maybe before we start the show,
let's talk about something that we can't really include
in the show, because it's not only extremely visual,
but it's one of those things you have to just kind of
poke and explore yourself, radio.garden.
And I could only describe this to you as
a way the internet may have once looked in a retro future.
You remember when, in like the late 90s,
we would visualize the information superhighway
as like this 3D plane that you would drive down,
and websites and company sites would be like
these 3D objects that you would approach and go inside of,
and that's how we thought the web was gonna be, Wes.
That's a Unix system.
Yes, yes, that's a perfect example in Jurassic Park
where they're flying through all the 3D objects.
Well, now it's real.
Radio.garden is a overlay on top of a Google globe
of the Earth, and it's hotspots all over the Earth
of radio stations.
They've mapped online radio streams
to their physical geolocation, and then represent that
on a globe as points of lights.
And so you can move about the globe,
and it moves a cursor over the area,
and then as soon as the globe stops,
it begins playing the stream from that region of the Earth.
And it's a super cool way to move the planet around
and get a different feel for different music cultures
all over the globe.
It's so neat.
Yeah, right, instead of just scanning your radio band,
do it visually, and you might actually discover
you oftentimes don't know where a random radio station
that you can hear it's coming from.
Yeah, I had not ever seen this.
Popa, you've seen this thing before?
No, because I get punched in the face
with a this experience requires WebGL,
please try again on a WebGL supported browser dialogue.
What are you using?
The latest version of Firefox.
Oh, I got a Firefox here in the studio.
Interesting.
I'm getting a retry for a live version
cloud-free prompt and I try.
Oh, we've DDoSed it.
Well, all right, that'll be an exercise
for after the show then.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 275.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's just trying to stay warm.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes, it's good to be connected with you.
We have a great show, some super great community news,
a bunch of it, we've kind of defined and distilled
like the best news stories of the week from the community.
We'll have those in there.
And then Christian from Red Hat is joining the show.
He'll discuss seamless Linux upgrades,
replacing Paul's audio, some of the recent desktop projects
that Red Hat's been working on, and the value
that Red Hat gets from those desktop projects.
Why are they doing it?
And then a little Thunderbolt 3 doc follow up.
Really looking forward to chatting about that
with Mr. Wimpy because I'm looking for a new Thunderbolt
doc from Milo Novo.
And then we have the poll to name the automation system
and then we'll wrap it up with a couple of app picks.
It's a solid show, Wes.
Oh, it's huge.
There was a lot going on these past couple of weeks.
So it took a lot of effort to distill this.
I hope everyone appreciates.
You know, to make sure we get it right,
we're going to bring in our backup group.
And that's our virtual log.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Peep, peep.
Hello.
Peek-a-boo.
Hello, Brent and Cubicle Nate and Mac and Mini Mac
and Popey and Sean, the Silent Drifter, and Mr. Wimpy.
It is good to see you gentlemen in the show.
I am remote again.
So it's not really different for any of you,
but it always feels different for me.
But it's probably the same for most of you out there.
But I had quite the experience that I just
wanted to share at the top of the show.
It won't take a lot of time.
I met a Zune guy, Wes.
You remember the Microsoft Zune?
Yeah, of course.
That MP3 player that didn't go anywhere?
I actually owned one.
I got it on a Black Friday sale.
I went down with Brian Lunduke to, I think, a Kmart
or, you know, like one of those type stores,
like a Fred Meyers, a Kmart, a Toys R Us.
I think it was maybe it was a Toys R Us.
And we waited in line.
This was years ago.
Yes, to get a brown Zune, which I wanted, I think,
for a honeymoon flight.
I was going on a flight for my honeymoon,
and I wanted something to watch videos.
And it's interesting, though, seeing the Zune again today,
because it is so huge.
These things were discontinued in October of 2011.
And they all have their own Zune service
with its own Zune software.
They are so thick.
They're like two decks of cards stacked
on top of each other thick.
And I'm looking over at this guy.
And I noticed, you know, he's got sort of a look about him,
like a mid-level management look.
And he sits down, and he busts out the Zune player.
And the first thing that strikes me was how much of that UI
is in use today, where you have a very sort of like what
became sort of a famous Microsoft mobile UI really
started on the Zune.
So that was really fascinating to see that.
But towards the end of the flight,
he starts to bust out his laptop.
And I can't help it.
I'm sitting next to this guy.
He's got a Zune player and this convertible Fujitsu or Sony
Windows PC laptop.
And then the guy, I'm sitting right in the middle,
in coach, in the cheapo seating.
And the guy that's got the Windows seat
has got an iPhone XS Max, an iPad Pro, an Apple Watch,
and so I've got a guy with a Zune and a Windows foldable PC
next to me, and then a guy with an iPad Pro and the phone
and all that stuff next to me.
And I'm sitting there watching both of these two,
how they use their technology.
And I don't mean to pick, but the guy with the Windows PC
was too big for the seat on the plane.
And if you picture Kilroy or the home improvement neighbor,
where they're always just like their nose up is over the fence
and they're peeking, this guy had the laptop in his lap
with the screen flat on his lap.
And then his nose peeking over the ass of the laptop,
looking at his screen down into his lap
because he couldn't fit this thing.
And then he keeps getting all of these Windows 10 error
messages and prompts for firmware upgrades
while he's watching the movie.
And then the browser edge crashes on him.
He has to reload it, he has to reauthorize Flash,
and the movie loses his place.
And I mean, I'm trying not to stare,
but just watching him have to interact and like
haphazardly mash the touch screen to do all of this.
It was a real interesting use case.
And as we landed, I lean over to him and I say,
I couldn't help but notice you're using the Zune.
Like, that's pretty retro, man.
Like, what's the story there?
He's like, not only do I use the Zune, but I have two Zunes.
I said, what?
You have two?
Yeah, I carry two Zunes with me.
Because he says, as you know, because I told him
I was a former Zune owner, the power bricks for these things
are huge.
And so instead of packing a power brick, he packs two Zunes.
And he runs one Zune down, and then he
runs the next Zune down.
And he hasn't synced them for like two years.
But he tells me there's still an active community out there
of people that love their Zunes.
And I'm looking at this guy like, you've got to be kidding
me.
You're still rocking this thing.
And as we are deplaning, he picks up a bag
with Microsoft logos all over it.
And I say, oh, so do you work at Microsoft?
Yeah, oh, yeah, I work at Microsoft.
Ah, OK, everything makes sense now.
Like, my whole world was collapsing.
Like, here's this guy.
He's using this touch convertible PC.
He's got a Zune player.
Like, he must be this big Microsoft fan.
That makes a lot of sense.
My whole world's like, it just doesn't compute, right?
But no, he's an employee.
So that makes a little more sense.
There's also some people out there that just don't.
You and I, a lot of the people who listen to the show probably,
we're upgraders, right?
We want technology.
We like technology.
But there is a subset of the populace
that they find a solution.
They put in work finding it, right?
Like, I spent all this money.
I bought two Zoons.
And they don't want to have to reinvest.
They don't want to learn a new ecosystem.
Yeah, I suppose.
I suppose.
I mean, I understand not upgrading and getting money.
And that was my first impression.
My first impression was kind of one of respect.
Like, man, that guy is getting a lot out of that purchase.
Like, I respect when you can push a piece of technology
that far.
There's something about that I can respect.
But I have a sense it was more of an unwilling to change
kind of thing.
Ah, yes.
Combination of loyalty and just stubbornness.
Yeah.
And so what he did is he just doubled down and bought two.
Instead of replacing the Zoom, he just bought another one.
That's a lot to manage, boy.
OK, then my last travel story is I saw a side of Texas
I've never seen before this morning.
And I've been sold, I'm going to say it right now,
a pack of lies about Texas.
And I am angry, Wes.
I have been told that Texas was warm and temperate,
even in the winters.
It is below freezing out there right now, Wes.
Wait, what?
It's below freezing outside.
And there is a damn wind chill that
makes it feel like it's 10 below freezing out there.
It's an aggressive, mean Texas winter right now.
So you flew hours south of here, leaving the beautiful Pacific
Northwest just to be uncomfortable.
Yeah, and I get the sense that this doesn't happen a lot,
because everyone lost their damn minds this morning on the road.
It was a commuter's battlefield.
I've never seen anything like this before.
It was intense.
So I guess the sort of chain of events
that happened is a few fire hydrants exploded
because of freezing.
Yeah, I mean, imagine they're not super well insulated,
right, when it's normally warm.
Yeah, right.
So a few fire hydrants explode, which then
spews water all over the road in below freezing conditions,
which just started a chain of effects
that really screwed traffic up.
But what really blew it open was all of the train track
crossing bars went down with the red lights,
ding, ding, ding, ding, ding, but there's no train.
All of the intersections in this entire Keller town
that I'm in right now, they all had the train tracks come down.
So here's Chris, bopping into work this morning
because he's here to do a live stream
in about a half hour or so.
I mean, I had a little bit of fudge time, but not much,
cutting a little close because I thought I had a 15-minute drive.
And I end up getting rerouted by cops.
I end up circling around for 40 minutes.
Long story short, I eventually found a patch
of train track intersection that had recently been shooed away
by their local cops.
And then they had moved on, so there was no other cars.
And I was able, let's just keep it short
and say I had to go into oncoming traffic,
had to put my rental vehicle into four-wheel drive,
and had to drive over train tracks.
And me and about 30 other Texans had
to drive over these tracks through the navigation guide
bars, just all this crazy stuff.
Then through a multiple-lane highway intersection,
it was the most insane thing I'd ever seen.
Texans driving in the wrong lanes, going against traffic,
people doubling up in single lanes,
people like me driving over train tracks.
It was every Texan for themselves.
It was total car warfare this morning.
And that's my drive as I'm coming
in to do the live stream for their big 200 announcements.
I tell you what, nothing wakes you up
like that kind of adrenaline rush.
Wow, we are lucky to have you today.
You could have died on those dangerous Texas roads.
It was a side of Texas I'd never seen, Wes.
It was a side of Texas.
You know, it's a balmy 55 here, so come back soon.
You bastard.
That's my travel update for you.
Man, oh, man.
Let's talk about a side of Sony we've never seen before.
You know, Nintendo has the Super Nintendo
Classic and the NES Classic.
They're these remakes of these old consoles,
and they come preloaded with a whole bunch of essentially ROMs
on them.
Yeah, right.
Turns out these old games are better than anything
we come up with now.
Yeah.
Apparently.
And it looks like following in those footsteps,
Sony's going to be releasing a similar take on the PS1
next month.
The PlayStation Classic, you may have heard of this,
it's loaded with 20 of the different ROMs.
But here's something that's different than the Nintendo
versions.
The PlayStation Classic is going to use an open source
emulator on the hardware to run Sony's games.
Yeah, I guess Kotaku got some early hands-on time
with this PlayStation Classic and discovered that it uses
the PCSX ReArmed emulator, which is a modern version
of the open source PCSX emulator that was originally
developed way back in like 2003.
Wow, I can't believe they've resurrected this
and it's still working.
I guess it actually still does a decent job of being accurate
to those old games.
Yeah, and in a way, it's sort of Sony saying,
this emulator is better than what we could build ourselves.
Nintendo went their own route.
But here they're saying, this is probably
the closest we're going to get to really recapturing
that original experience.
Now, that kind of feels like a bit of hypocrisy to me,
because Sony's a bit famous for going
after this type of community, the ROM community
and emulators.
And they've been criticized in the past
as being very aggressive.
And so now that very community that's, in some ways,
been chased by Sony for years is calling them lazy.
Like, you give us so much crap and then you use our software?
You lazy bastards.
There was that whole like running Linux and then not
running Linux anymore.
I mean, there's been a lot of Sony-related scandals.
Yeah.
It's also, I mean, it might just be a good testament
to the quality of open source, because you
would assume in-house, paid engineers, access
to all the proprietary stuff, they
could develop a really good emulator specs
for the chips, all that.
But no, I mean, it turns out that open source
is the way to go.
Yeah, it sort of goes back to what we talked about last week,
open source by default.
Also, didn't know this, but the Super Nintendo emulator,
SNEX9X, one of my favorites, still alive and well.
In fact, it's seen some really nice improvements.
On the Linux side, the GTK version is now GTK3 ready.
That means you also get Wayland compatibility
fully implemented.
I know, right?
Yeah, that's for sure.
So GTK3 and Wayland support in a Super Nintendo emulator.
I am impressed.
Also, yes, I mean, that's just a great emulator.
Yep, recently got my son into that.
And don't tell him this, because it's going to be a Christmas
present.
But there are some really solid Super Nintendo controller
knockoffs that just show up as USB input devices to Linux.
Oh, really?
Yeah, and they're not very expensive.
So I got him one, and I got me one.
So I could try it and test it.
Of course, of course, that's for the show, yeah.
Right, totally professional.
But yeah, it does work.
And so I can't wait to give him one.
And he'll plug it into his elementary OS laptop, which
I just updated to Juno recently, too.
So he's getting all the goodies in there.
Did that go pretty smoothly?
It went super smooth.
And he really likes the update.
He feels like he got a new computer out of it.
He even feels like it's a little bit faster.
He was running two releases behind.
Hey, that's how it should go.
Yeah, I was like, that's a best case scenario.
It's great.
He's really thrilled.
Now, let's talk about Canonical for a moment.
Mark Shuttleworth had a chat with Frederik
at TechCrunch at the recent OpenStack Summit.
And that's in Berlin, I believe, because we
have a couple of people from Linux Academy there right now
as well that are giving talks and doing project meetups
and just all kinds of really cool stuff.
Really well represented, actually.
There's a lot of experts there.
I didn't even think about going.
I mean, it's in Berlin.
That'd be awesome.
But anyways, Mark's also there.
And he had a chat with Frederik.
And he says, I value my independence.
He told Frederik that during a brief chat
on the outskirts of the OpenStack Summit in Berlin.
The outskirts in Berlin.
In part, that's because he simply
doesn't personally need the money,
but also because he'd like to see all the way
through his vision for Canonical and Ubuntu.
Now, of course, it's no secret that Shuttleworth would rather
like to see Canonical get an IPO.
But apparently, it still needs some work
to get the numbers right.
I would also just say that after this whole Red Hat news,
the IPO, the public company, and the Linux backing,
I feel like there's a little bit of questions there, right?
A private company is a little more free to, you know,
make their own risks, be a little less profitable,
or at least sort of choose philosophy over profit?
Less so in the public space.
Yeah, I mean, that's obviously why this is even coming up.
You know, that's why they're asking him about this,
because of the Red Hat sale.
And I saw a story recently that more and more tech companies
are sort of bailing on the idea of IPOing.
They're just kind of, I don't know,
like maybe it's coming to an end.
Like, obviously, it's not coming to an end.
But the hype cycle around it, like everybody rushing
towards the IPO, I think, has faded.
And now people are taking a calculated, really,
a much more practical and realistic approach
to doing an initial public offering.
Right, we had this world of unicorns and other things.
You get a bunch of VC money.
You try to go for the IPO.
You try to build this really big, successful company.
But for niche players, people that
aren't going to be an industrial giant,
maybe that doesn't make sense.
Yeah, yeah, I think that's well said, Wes, yeah.
The Open Invention Network has a bit of news.
This is after Microsoft joined them.
And then we all started talking about that Linux system
definition.
It's all about the Linux system definition.
Well, the Open Invention Network,
which is now the largest patent non-aggression community
in history, with more than 2,750 community members,
has announced today that it's increased its patent
non-aggression coverage through an update to its definition
of the Linux system.
This expansion is part of the Open Invention Network's
program to regularly revise its Linux system coverage
to keep pace with innovation, as they say.
Right.
Now, this expansion includes 151 new packages,
bringing the total number of, quote unquote,
protected packages to 2,873.
As they say, with this update to the Linux system definition,
the OIN continues with its well-established process
of carefully maintaining a balance between stability
and innovative core open source technology.
Oh, of course.
Of course, Wes.
Of course.
And while the majority of the new additions
are widely used and found in most devices,
that update also includes a number
of key open source innovations, such as Kubernetes, Cassandra,
and packages for automotive grade Linux.
That last one, kind of surprising.
Yeah, I mean, it's not bad, right?
And this is directly addressing the major complaint
that a lot of people had about Microsoft joining the OIN was
that, well, it's only covering the stuff in that definition.
Well, I think that the message they're
trying to get across here with this press release
is we reevaluate that definition on an ongoing basis
and are open to expanding it.
That must take quite the process, though,
because you've got to get, I mean,
don't you have to get buy-off from 2,000 members
now that we're going to just all of a sudden
expand this definition?
That's got to be a process now.
I mean, anything surrounding all of these patents, right?
That's going to be a lot of lawyers, a lot of rooms full
of lawyers negotiating, and that just takes time.
It also kind of strikes me that we only
need the open invention network because a lot of the patent
system, especially in the US, it's just broken.
Yeah.
Yeah, and like architects pointed out in the chat room,
it's not a perfect solution.
It still has limitations.
It's kind of a bone, right?
It's a bone thrown to the open source from the big companies.
Like, we have to have this because the lawyers
and the executive suites say we've got to protect our
intellectual property, but we also
rely on all this open source technology.
Yes, and you also want to give some insurance to companies
that are considering building products around open source
that they're not going to get sued,
because that was a major topic for a long, long time,
especially in the bad old days of SCO.
It was a major concern.
I personally had several conversations
where I was trying to pitch companies on Linux
and was shot down because they were
concerned about being sued for using free software.
And it was super hard to hear that every time,
because it felt like they were buying into FUD,
that companies were generating intentionally
to just create doubt.
And it was, I wouldn't label it as heartbreaking,
but it was really hard for me to hear people say that.
Right, you're like, I have this technology.
You can use it for free.
And then the cynicism of lawyers just shuts it down.
Yes, exactly, and it was better.
It was better.
You can use it.
It'll make my work cheaper.
It'll be more stable.
It is a better solution I can give you,
and the software is free.
It's a business move.
Yes, yes.
So it was really, it was hard.
And so I do appreciate the need for just setting people's
concerns down, just turning down the notch on the concern.
I do see the need for that.
I've got also kind of a concern about LastPass these days.
I mean, I know we've talked about it before.
And I know the general take is just
try to always use free software.
I wanted to give them a solid period of time
after LogMe and bought them just to kind of see how things went.
And as time has gone on and I just,
I wanted it to go another way, but I've
gotten less and less happy with LastPass.
So it's with kind of a wanting eye
that I've been looking at Bitwarden.
And this week, they may have announced something
that's going to tip me over.
Bitwarden has completed a third party security
audit of their software.
And if you're not familiar with Bitwarden,
it's a 100% open source password manager.
Identity manager is probably the term they would use.
And the nice thing about it is it also
has a public bug bounty program as well.
And they write on their blog they're
pleased to announce that Bitwarden has completed
a thorough security audit and a cryptographic analysis
from the security experts at Cure53.
Actually, it's a good step.
It's not perfect.
There were several issues that were identified by the audit,
some with immediate impact.
But the good news, all of those have
been resolved in a recent Bitwarden update.
Yeah, and it wasn't anything disastrous, really.
I looked at it, the PDF.
There's about five vulnerabilities.
And they range.
One of the vulnerabilities was you
are allowing people to use too simple of passwords
for the master password.
Yeah, fair enough.
I mean, that's not exactly a security vulnerability per se,
but it is something they needed to change.
Other things in there, there was a vulnerability
with one of the browser extensions.
But the core stuff all looked really good.
And it's just a big moment for an open source project, right?
Because that takes money, that takes community,
it takes funding and commitment to development.
Yeah, it is a big milestone.
And it takes a lot of work, so that's awesome.
I will probably be talking more about Bitwarden,
I have a sense.
Wes, don't you?
Oh, I think so.
And then one last little bit of just sort of updates here,
and then we just got a couple other community things,
is the LVFS project has a nice improvement
coming down the pipe.
They've just added an optional feature
to FW update and LVS that some people may find useful.
The firmware update process can now
tell the user how long in seconds
your update is going to take.
So you'll actually get a bit of feedback on that.
That's pretty cool.
Yeah, right.
I mean, this means that users can now
know that a doc update might take five minutes or so,
so they can start the process before they go to lunch.
A UEFI update might require multiple reboots,
could take up to an hour, 45 minutes.
So the user can know, like, don't do this right
before your important meeting.
That is really cool.
And LVFS is one of those projects
that I'm going to talk with Christian about when
he comes on the show.
It's, I think, one of those that has
checked one of those fundamental boxes on Linux.
Now, only users running the very latest versions of FW update
and GNOME software will be seeing the duration countdown.
Older versions, it's unchanged.
Nothing really doesn't work for you.
It's just, you're not going to see it.
And it's just ignored.
Now, and of course, for people that aren't familiar,
LVFS is the Linux Vendor Firmware Service,
which is a great way that you can get firmware updates right
on Linux.
Yeah, especially these days when those chips are essentially
running little micro operating systems packed
full of vulnerabilities, it's pretty important
that you update that stuff.
It matters more than it used to.
And so it's really good to see LVFS out there shipping
that stuff.
But Arthur writes into the show, and this is so awesome.
He's looking for help with SuperTuxKart networking.
He says, hi, first of all, I want
to thank you for the suite of great podcasts.
I've previously been a listener to several of them for years
now, and I enjoy them a lot.
I am representing the SuperTuxKart project,
which, as you may know, is a free software
and open source racing game.
So I don't know if he's actually a developer,
but he's representing them and focused on fun rather
than realism, which probably means
it would be a hit with my kids.
We are nearing a new stable release
with the headline feature of bold local and internet
multiplayer availability.
We're looking for people willing to test and compile
the game from the latest sources and help
test gameplay over the internet in particular.
Later on, we'll announce a beta release,
which will provide binaries.
But at the moment, we want testers
to be able to compile for themselves in case
we need to debug the output or we need
them to test a fix later on.
He's got more information linked at blog.supertuxkart.net.
And they say they'd be grateful if the listeners could
help spread the word about this.
You'll see it posted a few other places.
And if you do read this, it'd probably
be easier if you just call everyone by my nickname, Arthur.
OK, very good, Arthur.
We will.
He says, I look forward to hearing more on Linux Unplugged.
So I went over and checked out the SuperTuxKart blog
as he talked about there in that email.
And holy crap, Wes, they got a lot going on
with this multiplayer stuff.
This looks good, huh?
Oh, it looks great.
I mean, it has been about a year since the last release.
And I would also like to say, adding network play, especially
non-LAN network play, I mean, it works on the LAN too.
But like, internet play with real latency,
that is a significant undertaking,
especially on top of a code base not necessarily designed
for it.
Yeah.
I mean, Wimpy is really into the racing games.
So this isn't like the type of racing games
that Wimpy's probably into.
But if you like the Mario Kart kind of racing games
that are more like, it's like bowling when you
have the bumpers in the lanes.
Yeah, right.
You don't have to just focus on realism or accuracy.
You just get to go wild.
Yeah, exactly.
You get real drunk, you go on your go-kart course,
and you have a good time.
It's a great party game.
It so is.
Or you play it with your children,
which is where SuperTuxKart fits in my gaming agenda
these days.
Absolutely.
That's absolutely what I'll be doing.
Also, what's the game called where Tux slides down
on his belly?
That old game that we've all been playing for years now
that I've just completely blanked on the name
where he's in the snow?
Tux Racer.
Yeah, OK.
Is that just Tux Racer?
Kids love that one, too.
I think so.
Yeah.
So SuperTuxKart, pretty awesome.
And we might chat more about that in the bit.
It's interesting they're asking for just people that
are willing to build it themselves.
What do you think of that, Wes?
Mostly, it's early days, and they
want to be able to switch things into debug mode
if you run into a problem so they can get
all the necessary information to go actually investigate
that, things that you would leave out
in a real production build.
It looks like when everything's all said and done,
you'll be able to run your own SuperTuxKart server.
You can host it yourself if you want,
if you just want to have a nice little LAN
or something like that.
And they've got an IRC channel set up.
It's SuperTuxKart on Freenode if you want to get in and chat
with people about it.
I'll also say I checked out over in the AUR,
one of our favorite little user-curated repositories,
and there is a SuperTuxKart-git package already.
And if you go look at the package build,
there's a line to use the network branch, which
currently has all these changes.
Nice.
All right.
So you need the network branch.
OK, that is good to know.
That's so cool that they reached out to us to talk about it.
I love hearing that from them.
And I hope that they do get some people
to help them test it out, because that's such a fun one.
And that's great.
Even if we can't have AAA open source titles right now,
if it's just something you get a lot of fun entertainment out
of, it doesn't really matter.
Well, the other thing, too, is if you're
an up-and-coming person interested in both open source
and game development, while it might not
be the cream of the crop, here's an open source game
you can go look at.
You're curious how to make a networked game.
Soon, you can learn from them.
Absolutely.
So I wanted to chat with Christian from Red Hat here,
because they have a lot of desktop projects
that they're working on.
And I started to notice a theme across all of them.
But nominally, the thing I really
wanted to get them on the show about
was they've just completed another PipeWire hack fest.
And now the conversation is just beginning
to change to, how are we going to manage the Pulse Audio
replacement rollout?
That's a big milestone.
And so I thought, let's get Christian on the show.
He just landed back in his hometown a little bit ago.
And I wanted to make sure I got the name right, too.
Christian, welcome back to the Unplugged program.
It's been a while.
And you deserve a proper pronunciation of the last name.
So help me there so I don't sound like a doof.
How do you pronounce the last name?
I pronounce my surname Schaller.
Technically speaking, I'm not sure
if it's correct in the sense that it's a German surname.
And I probably pronounce it in a very Norwegian way.
But that's how I pronounce it.
But you are located in the States?
Yes, I am.
I live in Westford, north of Boston.
And your day job is technically working for Red Hat, correct?
Yes, that's correct.
I'm the senior engineering manager
for the desktop team at Red Hat.
OK, well, then you probably are the perfect guy to talk to.
We've been emailing back and forth for a while.
It's been ages since you've been on the show.
But the thing that has always kind of kept you on my radar
is you're often one of the forward-facing people talking
about pipeline developments.
We just recently had Wim on the show.
And you also were with Wim at a hack fest even more recently.
And so I thought, gosh, let's get Christian on,
talk a little more about pipeline,
but then kind of get more in towards your general day job,
the Linux desktop itself, and that position,
and all those things.
So why don't we just start with a quick recap of the Pipewire
hack fest?
How did that go, man?
Yeah, I thought it went really well.
We got a bigger group than I actually expected together.
Cool.
Because my background, of course,
was that Wim had been working on Pipewire for quite a while.
And he felt it was time now to see
if he could try to help pull in more people
and sort of get a larger group working on it.
Because the more people helping out,
the sooner we can actually have it in production.
Sure.
So yeah, it was really good.
We had more or less the whole core Pulse Audio team
attending.
And we had people from the also community.
And we had multiple people representing various embedded
use cases.
So was that conversation being had about replacing Pulse Audio
exactly kind of how that might look?
Is that going over?
Is that too awkward?
What about that?
Yeah, no, the conversation went really well.
I mean, the thing is we had been talking to them long time
before.
I mean, Wim is actually our contributor
to Pulse Audio at times.
He knew the people well.
It wasn't like he was like this person from outside
who's suddenly jumping in saying, hey, I have this new thing.
OK.
So when I started to put together the hack fest,
I actually reached out to Arun Raghavan,
who's one of the maintainers of Pulse Audio,
and said, hey, do you want to help co-host this thing?
Because he and I had been talking about eventually
wanting to move towards Pulse, sorry, PipeWire anyway.
So he was more than happy to do that.
And then we got the group together
and, of course, started discussing, well,
first where PipeWire is today and where
it needs to go to be ready to be that drop-in replacement
for both Pulse Audio and Jack.
That seems like a major milestone when that happens.
And in a way, it's sort of, to me,
it seems like the PipeWire model is more of a Jack model
than it is a Pulse Audio model.
So when we replace Pulse Audio one day,
people are going to see something
that might be more familiar to them as Jack than Pulse Audio.
That's kind of a transition in itself, too.
Yeah, Olle, I think for, like, if you're an end user
and all you use the songs are for is basically, like,
playing back music or getting audio from a browser,
I don't think you actually would even notice the differences.
I mean, of course, the interesting thing
is that this combination of things
makes some interesting combinations.
I mean, Tanu Kaskinen, who's another commentator of Pulse
Audio, actually brought a post on Patreon recently
where he talked about the hack fest.
And the one thing he mentioned he thought was interesting
was the fact that, you know, Jack has his tools
where you can see all the different applications
that Jack application is running
and, you know, how they're linked together and so on.
It's really cool.
Yeah, and the fact that with PipeWire now,
you can certainly get Pulse Audio applications
into that same graph.
Oh, okay.
That's personally exciting to me.
Yeah, and so we were basically, you know,
running unaltered Jack applications
and seeing, you know, Totem or Rhythmbox
or whatever appear in that graph
so that you can basically connect
your Pulse Audio applications directly
to your Jack applications.
I mean, I'm sure there's sort of practical concerns
where you might not necessarily want to do that
just because they are not written to, you know,
work in the kind of way a Jack application is meant to work,
but in theory, you could, you know,
connect these things together now.
Hmm.
This is sort of one of those bigger under the covers projects
that is in the works or has been in the work
semi-recently at Red Hat
that is kind of what I want to talk to you about today
because, okay, so you have PipeWire,
which I think is just a fantastic initiative
that Linux really needs for professional audio production.
So I'm very excited about it,
but there's been other kind of like lower level improvements
that are just kind of important and needed.
Like the one that comes to my mind almost immediately
that I don't think people think about very often is Bolt,
which is crucial for Thunderbolt security settings
and having a way for the user
to interact with that on the desktop.
So why don't we take a second here
in the context of PipeWire and some of the other initiatives
that Red Hat's doing,
how do we talk about the desktop in a whole
as something that's just as relevant
or almost as relevant as all of the other major desktops?
I'm not talking about millions and millions and millions
and millions of users.
I'm not talking about it being the year of the Linux desktop.
I'm simply saying how much work is it
to get it to be a relevant desktop?
One that's at the discussion table
with all of the other desktops.
What are your thoughts there?
Yeah, so I mean, I think the way I've been thinking
about it for a long time now is that,
you know, we don't need to be at 50 or 80 or 90%
to be, call it a player here.
I think if you can get the Linux desktop up to let's say 5%
or the total marketer,
which I guess similar to where Mac is today,
I think that's enough to make us relevant
and make sure we stay relevant.
And I mean, that's not necessarily too far away
from where we are today.
I mean, I think, you know, depending on the statistics
you look at, the Linux desktop often ends up maybe around 2%.
So if you're able to climb another 2%,
I think that sort of brings the number where it should be.
Right.
Or where it needs to be.
That actually seems achievable to me.
Yeah, yeah, to me too.
So actually when I came in about six years ago,
and took over the SOP, we sort of sat down and said,
hey, let's have a serious discussion about,
A, where are we putting our resources today?
And are we addressing the things that needs to be addressed
to actually get users in?
And in some sense, we thought, said like, you know,
to achieve growth,
you basically need to have two things happen, right?
A, you need to have new people come in
and you need to have existing users not leave.
So we said like, let's try to look at these two.
And we said like, okay, in terms of leaving,
we've ended up doing some surveys
and trying to figure out like,
why were people leaving their Linux desktop behind?
And I think what we found was the number one reason
at least we could see it for people
not wanting to use a Linux desktop anymore
was hardware support.
That, you know, after this maybe started
with Linux during their university years.
And then as the golden time went by,
they got more and more frustrated
with the fact that, you know,
every time they got a new laptop,
it was, you know, half a year or more
where things maybe were a little bit hazy
whether how well things worked
or there was like always these two functions
on the laptop that never worked.
So we felt that, you know,
A, that needed to be addressed.
And then of course there were other things too
in terms of like, you know,
application availability and so on.
But the hardware issue was something that we sort of said,
okay, that's definitely where people feel the pain
and get frustrated with Linux.
So we basically started saying,
okay, how can we reallocate
all the resources we have available
to try to look more on the hardware side
and also try to be a bit more proactive?
Because I think what often has happened also with Linux
is that a new hardware feature comes along
and, you know, eventually we do get support on Linux,
but it's sort of like maybe a year, two after it
become mainstream available in new laptops.
So I think one of the first things we started looking at
where we wanted to be a little bit more
ahead of the curve was that we spent a lot of time
working on the high DPI support
to ensure that, you know,
as we saw that these laptops were already on the way
into the market, that it wouldn't be once again,
the case that, okay, you got your brand new laptop
with a high DPI screen,
but you had to run it in 1080p mode
because Linux didn't support anything else.
Right.
So we've been sort of trying to, you know,
build relationships with harder vendors
and start planning things up front.
I mean, Bolt, I guess it's another area
where we're seeing that like, hey, you know,
there are going to be a lot of peripherals,
especially docking stations now moving to Thunderbolt.
As you said, let's put some on it
and work together with the hard vendors
to make sure we have an infrastructure there
to handle these kind of things.
Or, you know, another one that crosses my mind,
I mean, it does serve a purpose in the data center,
but the Linux vendor firmware service,
which has been huge for those of us on laptops now
that can get security firmware updates
via our software update mechanism.
I mean, to me, that's a massive,
huge first-class desktop experience
that that project is bringing to desktop Linux users.
And it seems like it's kind of checking off
one of those fundamental boxes,
like this is a fundamental thing we need to have.
Yeah, no, I fully agree.
And it was also like a product that came up,
I wouldn't call it randomly,
but one of the people on my team is a guy called Peter Jones,
who's actually a Red Hat's representative
on the UFI Standards Forum.
And he actually just approached me one day saying,
hey, you know, it'd be really good
if you can do something here to provide UFI firmware updates
because, A, that's what's coming.
I mean, people are moving away from the old BIOS model
and switching to UFI firmware.
And the thing we hadn't known for years, right,
was that people, well, first of all,
it was extra work for our kernel team
because often they end up doing workarounds
in the kernel driver to work around for firmware bugs.
And in some cases, you know,
people would often have a laptop and say,
oh, God, Linux is broken, this thing sucks,
and, you know, my battery life sucks,
or, you know, my hard drive is slow, whatever.
And the problem was that they didn't have
an up-to-date firmware.
Of course, if they had, they would have gotten a fix,
you know, years ago that actually improved their situation.
So, yeah, so we kicked off that LLVFS effort,
and, I mean, had to give a big call out there to Dell,
actually, who was one of the first major companies
who came on board and said, okay, hey,
we want to work with you and make sure this happens.
And, of course, today it's, you know,
we also have Lenovo signed up,
and, of course, a host of peripheral vendors.
Yeah, it's so great,
especially as we get more and more software in these chips
that are full-fledged machines that are doing a lot
and have some security issues, potentially.
And so that kind of first-party update service
is just super important, maybe more than it ever has been.
And in a way, I think maybe a lot of desktop users
can't even really wrap their heads around
because it's all just a black box to us these days.
Well, you know, Christian, I feel like I'm kind of seeing
a theme here, so we talk about Bolt,
and we talk about the firmware service,
and getting those firmware updates is super critical
as these devices do more and more,
and this is, like, another one of those fundamentals,
but the one that really seems like
the most practical compromise
coming out of the Red Hat and Fedora group recently
is the support for binary drivers, like the NVIDIA driver.
And this is something that I think
I've always kind of criticized a little bit.
They made it for a bad end-user experience.
You know, you buy a machine, it's got a $400 part in there,
and you get about $80 of value out of it
with the free driver.
And that was always sort of my proposition
to the Fedora camp, and the response generally was,
we really want to focus on free software
and building a free desktop.
But as time has gone on, there have been,
I don't know what else to call them,
maybe compromises to make it a little more practical,
to sort of check another one of those fundamentals.
I'd love to know the backstory
around getting those binary drivers into Fedora.
Yeah, no, it came from the same thinking here, right?
It's like, we know a lot of people,
of course, are getting laptops or desktops for this matter
with NVIDIA chips, and they needed a binary driver,
and it was always this pain
because you had a conflict between Mesa
and the binary driver.
And of course, the binary driver was available
only from a third-party site and so on.
And we sort of said, like,
hey, we are a major backers on the wall.
I mean, we are the only company
who actually are paying people to work full-time on the wall.
But at the same time, we need to realize that,
as you said, when people buy expensive hardware,
they want to be able to get max use of it.
And at the same time, we should then use this
as a way to develop an even better relationship
with NVIDIA to improve our roles on the wall, right?
Right.
So we started up having conversations with NVIDIA,
saying, like, this is what we want to do.
We want to, if step one, figure out a way
to avoid this SO file conflict
between Mesa and the binary driver,
because it makes life hell for packagers.
And end users, of course, who have to deal with the fact
that, you know, they might have a package
depending on Mesa and then that that gets uninstalled
to deal with the NVIDIA driver and so on.
So we set off a lot of discussions of projects.
And of course, we did the whole GLVND project
that had this vendor neutral dispatch system
so you can have multiple implementations
of your GL drivers and talked about, like,
how can we eventually get to a point
where you can support discrete graphics better?
And of course, at the same time, you know,
figuring out how can we also collaborate better
on making sure the wall work better.
So, I mean, all in all, I mean,
I don't feel we're there yet.
I mean, this has been an ongoing process,
but I think we're miles ahead of where we used to be.
And I believe that, you know, within a year,
I think you will suddenly feel that, you know,
these challenges around NVIDIA hardware
will to some degree be a thing of the past.
Interesting, I like that prediction.
What I see here is a multi-team effort
to solve this problem.
And when you add it all up,
it's a pretty sizable investment.
And I'm curious, in your opinion,
being inside Red Hat now for six years,
what do you sense the value is to Red Hat
to invest in these particular areas?
You know, the desktop for Red Hat
isn't almost a special product.
I mean, you know, Red Hat was actually started
as a desktop Linux company.
I mean, I think people tend to forget that these days,
but you know, the original starting of Red Hat
was being a desktop operating system.
And to this day, though,
to see the desktop as a valuable asset,
not necessarily as a revenue generating one,
but you know, it's important in terms of like,
just training people to use Linux.
I mean, a lot of people who today work as sysadmins
or developers around a lot of companies around the globe,
I mean, they got their start with Linux
through running a Linux desktop.
Absolutely.
Mm.
So for us, it's more like, you know,
the more people have using Linux on a desktop,
then the more people are available
for both us and our customers and partners to hire
who has, you know, experience and knowledge around Linux.
That is an interesting answer.
I hadn't considered the education angle.
That is playing the long game, but it is a smart one.
I guess my only other question to you would be,
is there anything else you wanna mention
or send the audience to something going on?
Is there any resources you'd like to inform people
about because you guys are working on a ton of good stuff
and some of it deserves a lot more attention
than it's getting.
Yeah, I mean, one of the projects we're currently doing
that I'm pretty excited about is called Silverblue.
I think you have covered it before on your show,
which is basically this idea of trying to make
an image-based operating system out of Linux
or for the Linux desktop.
Because I think what we are concerned going back to
when we looked at, you know, the problems people have,
right, and that is this recurring problems
that upgrades are not seamless.
So of course, I think we've done a lot of work
over the last five years for Dora
to make it a lot more seamless.
And I think it mostly works now,
but the problem still often happens, right,
is that time goes by and you install that, you know,
random package that you found on some website
that, you know, provides application or feature you wanted.
And that package starts creating problems
when you try to go to the next version,
because it, you know, depends on an SO file
that has changed versioning or whatever.
So we, of course, well, I guess we have two efforts
trying to address that problem, right?
One is of course, Flatpak, which is, you know,
this core effort of trying to make application bundles
that of course keep most of their dependencies with them,
just to avoid this problem of migrating.
And of course, for Reddit,
Flatpak brings another valuable feature, right?
Which just means that we can have one package
that targets both Fedora and RHEL.
We don't need to like, you know,
rebuild Firefox, for instance, for each.
Of course, yeah.
So that's part of the story, but at the same point,
we felt that, you know, we still want an upgrade set up
where that's sort of rock solid.
And that's sort of where Silverblue comes in,
where we can say that, hey, we have an image of the core
and all the packages that are part of that core
are upgraded as a group.
So we can basically upgrade, you know,
call it oversight, verify that everything works
and that there's no scripts or anything that messes up.
And then just ship that as an altered image
to place on your computer.
My goal is that, A, more people want to try Linux
because it works better.
And at the same point, less people leave
because they have problems with it.
That's sort of where we're coming from.
And I guess to cover another thing
that I know was sort of a little bit covered
in some stories recently was that, you know,
it's been announced now that we're not doing KDE in RHEL 8.
Ah, yes, right.
In fact, I did want to chat with you about that.
And well, there's a couple of things to make clear.
One thing is that, yes, we're not supporting running KDE
as a desktop, but we're still supporting people
running KDE applications on RHEL.
So that's an important distinction to make.
But, I mean, one thing I went back to
when we started to look at, like,
why are people leaving Linux?
And I guess you could say that, you know,
if there's one area where Linux
beats every other operating system,
it's in the number of desktops available for it.
Yeah, that's for sure.
Yet, of course, as we see, it doesn't mean
that we have a sort of, like, you know,
taken over the market based on that.
So I think we've sometimes concluded that, you know,
having a choice of desktops isn't really what drives
adoption or retention, for that matter.
And it's quite costly to maintain,
because, for instance, for my team then,
who maintains all the desktops in Red Hat,
it's sort of thinking, it's like, well,
first of all, the most horrible message
you can give any customer or user, right,
is like, oh, if you want to do that,
then you switch to this desktop environment.
But if you want to do that,
then you switch to that environment.
And if you want to do both, then you have a problem.
So we said, like, no, we need to be able to say,
this is what you support, and this is when we get requests
from users for features, where we'll implement those.
And at the same point, in order for me to be able
to move quickly on these things and do projects
like Pipewire and Flatpak and Silverbill and all those things,
I need to be able to do them both,
as opposed to sort of feel that we have to re-implement
the feature, you know, two, three, four, five times,
depending on how many desktop environments
we are supposed to support.
That seems like a tight line to walk, though,
because at the same time, if you want something
completely universally accepted, of course,
you'll need the Plasma desktop to be on board
with Pipewire as well.
So there's a line to walk there.
There is, definitely.
And I mean, the thing is, of course, we are still actually,
you know, despite the plan to not ship with the KD desktop
in Relate, we are still contributing to KD,
especially, of course, in this area that we care about.
So Jan Grulish, who's a member of my team,
he attended a tech fest for Pipewire in Edinburgh,
and he's the one who's been working on making sure
that we have full Pipewire support in KD.
That's great, that's great.
I mean, but it really, I mean, to steal a business metaphor,
which everybody loves, it really feels like it's about
putting all of your wood behind a single arrow.
You know, like, it's about focus.
Yeah, it's about focus, and that's it.
So it wasn't like, you know, an anti-anything.
It was more like, hey, we need to focus our resources,
which are limited, on solving what we know
we are costing as customers, and as opposed to, you know,
trying to keep a small subset of people happy
by offering them, like, this choice of desktops,
which, as I said, doesn't seem to be actually
what drives people to adopt an operating system.
Yeah, yeah, I could see it maybe keeping people around
every now and then, you know, if some desktop environment
has just failed you, and instead of switching back
to Windows, you could switch to Plasma and be happy.
That could be a potential, but I see what you're saying.
People aren't coming over to Linux and going,
oh boy, after I spend a week picking my distribution,
I get to spend another two weeks
picking my desktop environment.
Yay, that's not a big advertising point.
No, and of course, as I said, like, I mean,
we had cases in the past, right, where people were
dumping desktops basically to, like, you know,
hey, multi-monitor is working better here than there,
but then I discovered that my Wacom tablet
worked better there than here, and then of course,
it puts a customer in an impossible situation, right,
because it's sort of like, well,
and I have to choose that feature versus that,
and then we are on the other side sort of struggling with,
like, well, I don't have enough engineers available
to fix both this and that, so what we're doing here,
and then people also might think that features
haven't been fixed because they're, let's say,
using the wrong desktop environment compared to the one
where we implemented the fix and this kind of thing,
so it's like, it's a challenging problem to overcome.
Yeah, well, Christian, I really like the approach
that you're taking here.
It's sort of, you know, shave away at these rough edges
and make the desktop just relevant in the marketplace.
Don't necessarily chase the market share number.
Just make the Linux desktop relevant,
and I think we're close,
and that seems like an actual attainable goal,
and I think you guys are playing a big part
of getting us there, so thanks for coming on.
Thanks for keeping everybody informed on what you do
and traveling around to participate
at those hackfests and whatnot.
I'll have links to the blog and other things.
Anywhere else you want to shoot people to check out?
No, I mean, once again, I actually would like to say that,
you know, of course, yes, we are doing a lot of work there
and trying to fix it, but I mean, there's other people,
I think, doing critical work to these days.
I mean, once again, I would like to actually
give a shout out to Dell for all their recent efforts.
I mean, I guess we're the first major maker
who got serious about Linux on the laptops,
and then, of course, in addition to those,
we have, you know, smaller but thriving businesses
like System76 and Purism and so on,
who are also pushing Linux on laptops forward
and making that a more reliable experience.
And I mean, another thing that I often felt held us back,
and we knew we got feedback from people
saying that they ended up using
or keeping Linux around for was gaming,
and of course, Valve has been doing an incredible effort,
in my opinion, getting Steam going on Linux
and making sure we have a huge selection of games.
It really is a full-spectrum community effort.
Well, Christian, thanks for coming on the show
and chatting with me.
Yeah, my pleasure.
I really like talking to him because it's a reminder
of all of the things that I use every day
that they're working on,
and that is more important than ever
in the context of the news with the IBM purchasing Red Hat.
And, you know, that was sort of what I was getting at, too,
with what's the value to Red Hat for these projects.
And so I enjoyed that entire conversation with Christian.
You can find links to his blog and other things
in our show notes at linuxunplug.com slash 275,
including his most recent post about the PipeWire Hackfest,
which I know Wes and I are super excited about PipeWire.
Oh, boy.
Yeah.
Well, Wes, we should keep moving right along
because on the Christmas list for me this year
is a Thunderbolt 3 dock.
I think I'm gonna do it.
Ideally, I'd like to do one
that even maybe has a GPU or something.
Like, I've got all of these embedded right in there,
just stock ready.
Yeah, ready to go.
Thunderbolt aspirations big time over here,
but I don't know exactly what to expect,
where the Linux compatibility is at.
So what I'd like to do is let Wimpy take all of the arrows
on some of these hardware purchases
and then check in with him.
We'll learn from his mistakes.
Exactly.
Or successes, or successes.
Yeah, I know Mr. Wimpress has recently become
a proud owner of a ThinkPad P1, a beautiful new rig.
And I believe he has tied that with a Thunderbolt dock.
And I'd just love to get your take
on how this is going, Wimpy.
Yes, so I have.
And I've been using the dock for about a week now.
So I've got a ThinkPad Thunderbolt 3 dock
and it's the second gen unit.
All right, so you went with a Lenovo branded dock.
I did, and I will explain why.
So technically there is a single umbilical cord
that connects the laptop to the dock.
But what Lenovo have done is made a connector
on the laptop side, which is a single connector,
but actually bridges the power port
and the first Thunderbolt port.
And then that connects to the Thunderbolt port
and connects the same way on the back.
So it connects into a power port and a Thunderbolt port.
So technically two cables,
but one umbilical cable to connect the thing together.
Okay, all right, that's nice.
And is that delivering a higher wattage?
Yeah, right, because you can only deliver
a hundred watts over Thunderbolt 3.
So insufficient for a laptop with a Xeon processor
and a discrete graphics card.
So that's why you have to sort of provide power
and Thunderbolt.
Okay, and so this allows you to what, hook up Ethernet,
USB devices, like what's the port layout on this thing?
And what's the capabilities that it brings you?
Because these things are, over here at least,
nearly $400 US, is it worth it?
Well, it depends what you're going for, in my opinion, yes,
because it now makes for a very convenient way
to connect and disconnect the laptop.
So this laptop is now going to be
my main workstation and laptop,
and I will just disconnect it from all of this gubbins
via one cable now to take it out with me
when I go out and travel and work.
Yes.
But the first thing you have to do is use Bolt,
which of course you talked about in your last interview.
So Bolt is the mechanism by which you actually authenticate
your Thunderbolt device so that it is now trusted.
So you run that to connect that,
and there's command line utilities,
and if you're using GNOME, then that's all built into the UI.
Hmm.
And then once you've done that,
on the back of this Thunderbolt dock,
there are two full-size DisplayPort connectors.
There are two HDMI connectors.
There's a plethora of USB 3.0 A ports,
and there is Gigabit Ethernet,
and on the front,
it's got USB-C and headphone,
and it's an audio interface.
And is that everything?
I think that's most of the things.
And Linux is pretty cool with all that stuff
just appearing and disappearing.
It's not really a big deal.
Yeah. So I've just been, I mean,
I think back to my days when I had a Commodore 64,
and you used to have to sort of turn the computer off
when you wrenched the cartridge out,
and that sort of baked into my DNA.
So I think, can I really just, you know,
yank this out and it'll all carry on working?
And it turns out it does.
So yes, I just pull it out,
and the screen has a little bit of a dance
as everything sort of collapses down to one screen
on the laptop lid again.
But yes, it all works fine.
The one area where I've had to do
a little bit of sort of hackery
is I've got two external 1440p monitors,
and the internal panel on this laptop is UHD.
So you run into this mixed DPI environment
where one of the DPI's is going to be dominant.
And what I've done there is I've written a little script
that manipulates XRender.
So it enumerates what monitors are attached.
It lays out the monitors in the right order.
So effectively, I've got the monitors in front of me,
left and right, and then the laptop sits right
in the middle between the two of them.
And this XRender layout actually positions
the laptop monitor in the center of the crease
where the two monitors line up and uses the correct offset.
So as you drag down, as you move down,
you're directly moving into where you'd expect the mouse
to appear on the laptop lid beneath you.
And then I use some scaling in XRender
to basically make that internal panel,
the effective resolution, approximate to 1080p.
So that now means that I've got effectively the same DPI
across all three of those machines.
Now, there isn't a UI that enables you
to facilitate that in X at the moment,
but using XRender, it is possible to create that.
So yeah, I have this little script
that just checks periodically,
sees which panels are detected,
and adjusts itself accordingly.
I know it's sort of a small script,
but have you thought about tossing it up
on your GitHub or something?
Because that's something I might use.
Yeah, well, I was discussing this with Popey earlier,
and the first thing he said is, I want it at the moment.
It's very much sort of hardwired to my screens
because it's my display IDs, it's my resolutions,
the offset calculations are all hardwired,
but I think I'll put it up as a gist
and just sort of document what it's doing,
and then other people can try and take advantage of that
and figure out how to reuse it.
But ultimately, what we need to do
is make the display arrangement UIs
in the desktop environments be smart enough
to be able to accommodate these more exotic display layouts.
Absolutely, especially as this becomes
more and more possible, there's gonna be lots of laptops
with Thunderbolt 3 ports.
So if I recall correctly from a couple episodes ago,
you got the Thunderbolt 3 workstation dock,
which Lenovo sells for $356 here in the States.
Now, this is where I'm torn, because you're right,
it's a beautiful dock.
It's got two HDMI, two DisplayPort, Ethernet,
and it's got that bigger connector,
which delivers more power.
But Lenovo also sells a Thunderbolt 3 dock for $362
that has a few less ports, but has a GTX 1050 built into it.
So I would go from Intel graphics to getting a 1050
when I plug in that Thunderbolt dock.
Now, I grant you, a 1050 is not gonna rock my world,
but it's better probably than the Intel embedded.
And that's really tempting.
Do you think that would possibly even work?
Yes, I know it will work,
because when I have this dock attached,
I have a single additional Thunderbolt port spare,
and I've been able to connect my Razer Core to that
and use the 1080 Ti in that to amplify things.
Now, as it happens, this laptop also has
Quadro P2000 discrete graphics in it,
which is more or less equivalent to a 1050.
And the 1050 isn't to be sneezed at.
I was just using it to play Horizon Chase Turbo
before we came on air this evening.
It's not the most demanding game in the world,
but it was flying along at plenty of frames a second
and was very enjoyable.
That's what I was thinking.
Like, I could play a game,
and all I have to do is plug in my dock.
So, and it still has a couple of DisplayPorts.
I think it has two DisplayPorts on it, but only one HDMI.
Right, right.
Yeah, I mean, I'm only ever gonna use two monitors.
I don't have space for any more monitors than that here,
and the ones I've got are plenty big enough.
I might give it a go and report back
on how that GPU integration works with Linux, too,
just after some testing.
Yeah, and I can explain, you know,
the way that that actually works is,
I've written an applet for Marte to make this easy,
but the way you use it is you just run the Nvidia settings,
and there's even a switch to take you to the right portion
of the settings where you can just flip-flop
between Nvidia and Intel.
Ah, good to know.
Thank you, sir.
Well, I always like learning vicariously, as they say.
It's the least expensive way to learn.
It really is, and maybe we can pass it along.
But, you know, I've got dozens of USB devices connected here.
You know, webcams, the mic, the USB audio device,
multiple keyboards, mice.
A bunch of other stuff, controllers, all sorts of things.
And now, I just have one cable to connect,
and the monitors and all of those devices just power up.
That is the dream.
One cord, and it's powered, data, everything.
It's stuff, and it's no longer just on the USB bus.
It's on the PCI bus now,
so we're talking, like, real hardware, too.
It's on the PCI bus, yeah, yeah.
So, yeah, this is not too shonky.
So, there's four PCI lanes available to that hub,
to that dock, rather, to deliver all of those pieces.
Obviously, the more displays and things
and the more bandwidth you're using,
but it runs really nicely.
I've had no problems with it at all.
Hmm. I'll put links to both the one that Wimpy got
and the one that I'm going to grab and try out in the show notes,
if you guys want to check that out, linuxunplugged.com,
slash 275.
How's that P1 treating you? Is it going good so far?
Yes.
Well, that doesn't sound like a super yes, though.
Well, you know, I'm an early adopter,
so you can always expect problems, can't you?
So, there are two issues.
These issues will be the same for ThinkPad P1 owners
and ThinkPad X1 Extreme owners.
The first one's minor, and that's that the...
what do you call it? Fingerprint sensor scanner thing
is not currently supported.
Oh, of course.
So, that's a minor issue.
The other one that's a bit more interesting is
hybrid graphics don't work on this at the moment,
and I spent the weekend having a poke around
with the GPU manager,
and I've got a hacked up monkey patched thing here
where I've kind of got it half working.
So, where I say half working,
it means that I don't have black screens
and I can't do anything.
I actually get the displays to initialize,
but I'm not at the moment able to switch between
hybrid and discrete graphics.
But I'm a bit further forward in that,
you know, when I first tried to use it,
I just had black screens,
and now I have screens that function.
Well, yeah, that is a bit further forward.
You're right. Okay.
Yeah.
Well, that's good.
Well, I wish you luck there on your journey, sir.
I would love to know how it goes.
Yeah, it wouldn't be fun if it didn't have a few problems.
You don't feel like you own a computer
until you've solved some of these little gremlins.
You know, I've been there,
where there's times where I buy sort of the ambitious system,
and then there's times where I buy the really practical system
that I know is going to be taken out of the box and get to work,
and it just sort of depends on what you want to get out of that system,
and the ones where you eventually get them working
are sort of rewarding in themselves
because it's like an accomplishment.
Now, we have just a couple of bits of business to take care of
before we get out of here for this week.
We won't spend a lot of time on it this week,
but the official voting is now opening for our automation system.
You can find the link in our show notes.
Go give your vote.
We'll deal more into that next week,
but if you want to get the early vote in,
you can find the link to our new system.
But I just wanted to take a second
and talk about a really cool tool that Wes found this week
that he's actually already managed to put into work,
and I think it was from an email from a listener, Brandon,
that tipped you off.
Yes, that is right.
Brandon wrote in to us and was asking if we'd ever heard of the Junest project.
I don't know if I'm saying that right,
but J-U-N-E-S, or Jailed Under Nest.
It essentially lets you run Arch Linux with fake root access.
It really uses PRoot,
but that basically means you get a whole little user space Arch install.
You don't need root.
All you need is a home dir,
a little bit of modifications to your path, and git.
But you probably already have all of those things,
and now you have all of the Arch packages, the A-U-R,
and that wonderful package manager, Pac-Man.
Right there on top of any distribution you want to use.
Is that what you used to try out the SuperTuxCart build?
Yes, it is.
I mean, because it was already in the A-U-R, right?
That's one of the nice things about Arch,
even in the days of Snap packages and Flatpak and all that.
Arch just has a lot of packages.
And if you're like me, I mean, I just spent so many years on Arch.
Even though a lot of my systems are Ubuntu these days,
I'm familiar with it.
It's easy, and a lot of times you kind of just get that minimal baseline.
You don't have to worry about a whole bunch of different extras you need to do.
It's all right there.
It's up to date.
You get the latest.
And now with Junist, you can have it all in a throwaway environment.
That's pretty neat.
Thank you to Brandon for tipping us off to that,
and thanks, Wes, for kicking the tires and giving that a go
while I'm out and about.
Junist, Arch on Linux without root.
We'll have a link in the show notes for that as well.
Go get more poppy and wimpy.
Mark as well at the Ubuntu podcast, ubuntupodcast.org.
A special shout out to producer Michael
for helping us out with our mumble room disaster
we had right before the show.
Go get his great This Week in Linux on YouTube,
and go get more Wes Payne.
He's over there at techsnap.systems
for another podcast that he's on with us,
and he's over on the Twitters at Wes Payne with a Y.
Oh, that's right.
Payne with a Y.
Yeah.
I'm at Chris LAS, the network's at Jupiter Signal.
Thanks so much for joining us, and we'll see you back here next Tuesday.
You know what?
So producer Michael in the chat room says,
Chris LAS, could you not have given the option of cast-a-blast-a?
I had that same thought when I looked at that list.
I thought we should just maybe call it cast-a-blast-a
because that was the first podcast we ever did.
It's too perfect.
Yeah, it does seem like it'd be really perfect,
but then I thought we're creating name collision
with like a piece of our history maybe,
or it's an homage.
I don't know.
So I just sort of dropped it.
What are you linking me?