Look at this cool toy that Wes found.
It's a bootable CD and a retro game,
and it all fits in a single tweet.
How is this shenanigans possible, Wes?
Well, a little bit,
just by abusing the El Torito standard,
and being exceedingly clever,
and then also because the dark arts,
you use a little pearl.
Yeah, it's a little pearl
with a long string of characters,
and then you pipe that through Base64,
and then you output that result to an ISO image.
Yeah, exactly.
And then you can,
I just tested it out here,
boots right up in QEMU,
and you've got yourself a little retro game.
The game may be not super fun,
but the write-up about how this all works is a lot of fun.
Back in the day,
you used to try to fit an entire bootable environment
on a floppy disk.
Now, in 2018, it's fitted in a tweet,
and it's actually possible.
God, I love Linux.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 260,
for July 31st, 2018.
Oh, welcome to Linux Unplugged,
your weekly Linux talk show
that is surrounded by machines,
trapped in a hot room,
and jacked up on caffeine.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Mr. Payne, and of course,
back again, like every week,
is Mr. Brent.
Hello, Brent.
Hello, guys.
How's it going?
Fantastic, always doing well
when we're all together to do a podcast,
and we have a great episode today.
One, Mr. Barton George from Dell
will be stopping by the program
to update us on the Sputnik program,
how things are going,
the challenges that Chromebooks may pose
to the Sputnik program,
and much more,
including a little looking forward.
So I'm really looking forward to that chat.
He's coming up in just a little bit,
but before we get there,
we're gonna do a bunch of community news,
some big news for us neon fans.
Microsoft is switching to a service model,
and we wonder how that's gonna affect Linux,
and then we need to talk about security,
and where it really begins,
and that's at your home router,
and some open source projects
that can help you achieve better security on your edge.
Then Corita's got some great news,
but you'll never guess
where some of their money's coming from,
and then later on in the show,
after we chat with Barton,
we're gonna wrap it up with not one,
not two, but yes, my friends, three great app picks,
because I don't know, sometimes we just go crazy.
You can't stop us.
We were just finding great stuff throughout the week,
and we're like, we gotta put that in the show.
We gotta put that in the show.
So there's so much to cover,
and the only thing left to do before we can get into it
is bring in that mumble room.
Time appropriate greetings, virtual lug.
What's up? Hello.
Good evening.
Hello, good evening, good afternoon, good morning.
As I always say now, time approves,
because it's different for all y'alls,
and I'm very happy to start the show off
with some news about one of my favorite,
don't call it a distributions, distributions,
and that's KDE Neon,
and we've all been kind of wondering,
when's this thing gonna land on an 18.04 base?
KDE Neon, if you're not familiar,
is a rebasing of Ubuntu LTS,
and then they take the latest upstream
plasma desktop components,
cute components, and put it on top of 16.04.
It's great.
So it's just everything that you might want
if you had 16.04 and didn't wanna go through
the rigmarole of getting that plasma desktop
set up for yourself.
Yeah, I mean, and its main appeal really is
that you have a stable, predictable 16.04,
or soon 18.04 base, which is kind of boring,
doesn't really change a lot.
But that good kind of boring.
Yeah, exactly, the right kind of boring,
with a really aggressive, fresh desktop environment,
where the desktop level applications are kept pretty fresh,
and that is a super appealing approach to me,
and now that I'm all in on the plasma desktop,
Neon really fit well in that spot for me.
But I do admit, since Kubuntu came out based on 18.04,
really haven't been installing much Neon anymore.
Too little, too late?
Well, no, it's just, if I'm gonna be building systems
that I wanna last for five years,
I would like to base them on 18.04, not 16.04.
Plus, I've been waiting for them to make this transition
to 18.04, so that way I don't really have to weather it.
I still have two Neon systems left in production,
one of them is the one I'm reading this off of right now.
And one of them, the other one is my XPS 13,
which I've been using extensively on these road trips
and other trips that I've been on.
Do you notice any difference in stability
or upgrade problems or any other maintenance issues
between the two?
I remain to have, actually I have it on three systems
now that I think about it.
And on one of the three, I have issues
where my background, my desktop goes away,
certain things break for a little bit,
and then I have to log out and log back in
to get it to work.
Nothing major.
Still not great.
Doesn't come up on Kubuntu,
only manifests itself on my Neon systems.
It's not a big deal, it's not the end of the world.
But I am looking forward to them making that transition
to 18.04, and Jonathan Riddle posted over on his blog,
that we'll have linked in the show notes,
that they're getting really close to that now.
They really just have a few things to work out.
They're testing the ISOs, and then it's some tidying,
and they're done.
They already have a bunch of things
that are kind of working.
Some of it just has to be done a little more officially
instead of like a hack or a script or something.
But it looks pretty good for the Neon distribution,
and 18.04 could be just around the corner.
Then you've got elementary OS,
which is just around the corner with its base on 18.04.
And you now have 18.04.1 that's recently shipped.
So it's a good cycle right now for 18.04.
And in six months, that will start to slow.
In a year, we'll be out of cycle a little bit,
starting to get a little old.
But right now, it's really in that sweet spot.
And if you're building a system to last for a few years,
there's not a lot of distributions
that offer a ton of desktop application availability
and five years of support.
So they're really in a powerful position,
more so than they've been in a long time.
And that's not to downplay the competitors,
who are also in a really great position,
and offer a lot of the same functionality
now that Canonical is switching back to GNOME.
But when you combine it with the overall network effect,
the application availability,
the increasing Snap Store availability,
and then these other really nice flavors,
like Kubuntu and Ubuntu Mate, and even Neon,
don't call it a flavor, don't call it a distribution,
all offer essentially this Ubuntu base
that we all know and understand
with their own fresh takes on it
in a way that I still don't really see happening
in the rest of the Linux distribution world.
Do you agree with that assessment?
Yeah, it's kind of hard to put your finger on,
but when you have that level of consistency
on that far end of just your main core of your system,
it's a part of your mind
that gets to go to sleep for a while.
You don't have to think too hard about it.
You kind of focus on everything else
because you don't have to fight like,
oh, nope, on that system I have Phish,
and this system I have Apt, and that one is Pac-Man.
None of it.
I'm not even really saying this as like,
I'm not trying to sell anyone on Ubuntu.
I'm not trying to advance the Ubuntu agenda here.
It's just an observation that I seem to have realized
is that they have a really strong market here
where they have this LTS base
that these other flavors or derivatives even
that aren't official can base off of,
and as an end user, that's a known quantity.
It's like a brand almost.
It's like the Ubuntu base is a known brand
that you can recognize as an end user.
It makes you maybe a little more comfortable
in other degrees of uncertainty or customization
because you're like, okay,
well, they're not going to mess it up so bad.
It's still going to be a great Ubuntu LTS base.
That's what I was, yeah,
that's exactly what I was trying to get to.
Again, I don't say that to detract
from like what the work Fedora is doing
or OpenSUSE and Arch, and look at Antigros.
I love Antigros.
Or Manjaro, all of that's really kind of the same thing,
but nothing has the market penetration that Ubuntu has.
And in my personal opinion,
if you're going to go with one of these Ubuntu derivatives,
Ubuntu, Monte, Elementary, and KDE Neon
are like the best of the best, really.
Not to take away from the other flavors,
but man, if I don't just-
You get some pretty unique setups and experiences
even being in this one family.
Yes.
I find it funny that you don't mention Ubuntu,
you know, main classic, whatever you want to call it,
just known, like you're all about the flavors.
I think when you're talking about trying to get a unique
kind of interesting take on the Linux desktop
that's truly different than anything you see other places,
that's where these other flavors or derivatives come in.
Not to take away from the great work
that's happening in mainline Ubuntu.
I got love for it all today, I really do.
But it's hard to beat those three
kind of standout derivatives or flavors,
whatever you want to call it.
This is all kind of academic though,
compared to what the Windows world may be going through
in the next couple of years.
Microsoft is making some big changes
and they're getting ready, I should say,
to replace Windows 10 with the Microsoft Managed Desktop.
This will be a desktop as a service offering.
Instead of owning Windows, you would rent it by the month.
The acronym for this is DAS, D-A-A-S,
and it's not really new.
Citrix has been doing this, VMware has been doing this.
I think Amazon offers, yeah.
But the Microsoft Managed Desktop is a new take on it.
It avoids the latency problem
of other desktop as a service offerings
by keeping the bulk of the operating system on your PC.
But you would no longer be in charge of the PCOS
or the hardware itself.
Instead it would be automatically provisioned by Microsoft
and then maintained by Microsoft.
Now that is very vague,
so I wanted to get some more details on this.
So I went over to Mary Jo Foley's blog
and she actually got a Microsoft representative
on the record.
Really?
So this is some serious stuff here.
This isn't just like hearsay.
Let's see, let me see the name of this guy.
Do you see the name of this guy here in this article?
I think that's probably relevant,
but I'll read it and then if we see it, I'll call it out.
But it turns out, she says,
Mary Jo Foley writes,
I'm hearing that Microsoft Managed Desktop
is basically the Microsoft version of desktop as a service.
It will provide customers with the ability
to lease Windows 10 devices
that automatically are provisioned for them
and have the operating system kept up to date
for more than a single monthly fee,
up to date for no more than a single monthly fee
or something like that.
Now here's what she writes
that I think is the more insightful bit to this article.
Oh, and by the way,
the contact that she spoke to at Microsoft
was the director of the Windows Insider Program
and OS Fundamentals team,
Bill Kagarugas or something.
It looks like Kangarugas,
but do you see that, do you see that name?
K-A-R-G-O-U.
K-A-R-G-O-U-N-S maybe, I don't know.
But he's the director of the Windows Insider Program
and OS Fundamentals team.
So that's where she's getting this from.
And so she says, here's the thing to think about,
is Microsoft already has a number of the pieces in place
to make this happen.
This past year, Microsoft has been broadening availability
of its Windows Autopilot Automatic Device
provisioning service.
It's been honing its device financing skills
with programs like Surface Plus
and Surface Plus for Business,
so there's a leasing aspect of the hardware there,
as well as Surface as a Service leasing program.
I didn't even know they were offering Surface as a service.
Me either.
Boy, they love their acronyms.
And it currently offers Windows 10, Office 365,
and the Intune device management and security products
from the Microsoft subscription bundle,
all for one low monthly price.
They've been working to put all of this together
into a new service.
This is what the director of Windows Insider Program
talked about, he said,
they're in charge of what's being called the Microsoft
Managed Desktop.
That's what he's been, he's been put in charge of that.
And they're bringing these existing sort of separate
programs that they have together under one umbrella program
and then offering it to consumers.
So this is a lot of Microsoft news, Chris.
What does it mean to me, the Linux unplugged listener
who was trying to escape?
That's the big, big question is,
do we just have a whole new value story now for Linux?
Did Microsoft just give us a whole new value proposition
in that you download a free desktop,
and you install it on your hardware,
and then you get free updates for life.
No subscription required, you know, you can use,
you can use Dropbox with your LibreOffice,
you could use your Google Drive, you could use NextCloud,
like whatever syncing service you want to use.
The only thing is, these people that will be buying this
are paying for convenience.
That's the market, right?
I mean, it's like leasing a car, you know, you're like,
I want the abilities that you're offering,
and I don't want to have to think about how you implement it
or how it happens under the hood.
Yeah, and they want it to just work.
They want the device to show up on their desk and just work.
So the problem with the Linux approach
is you can argue on the money side,
but then you can't really successfully argue the tool side
because if the user has to implement
their own cloud syncing service,
if the user has to implement their own office suite,
if the user has to implement their own email client,
and they have to set all these things up.
You're going to have to offset it with training
or dedicated staff or...
Contractors or something.
And so what they're offering here is,
well, you'll use Office 365, obviously.
Of course you will.
You'd use our Edivirus product,
you'd use our mail services,
you would use our...
You probably get a couple of Azure credits
to get you set up there too.
Why not?
I think for some markets, it'll make Linux more attractive,
but I don't think for all of the markets we'd hope.
I wonder, I feel like we've been talking about it
maybe from a lot of the enterprise use case,
but is there a security angle for people running it at home
that maybe might have a better experience with Windows?
I wonder if we shouldn't flip the question around
and propose it to Brent as this.
So if I could come to Brent and say for $45 a month,
ah, let's make it 50.
Let's make it kind of hurt a little bit.
So for 50 bucks a month, you get a fully managed,
fully set up, fairly high-end Ubuntu 18.04 device
that you choose what kind of screen, that kind of stuff.
If you set some of the basic parameters
and that sets your monthly billing.
With that is included Google Drive storage,
all access to Google apps
that are all branded under this initiative.
So you pay 50 bucks a month, Brent.
Every two years, you get a brand new Linux 18.04 machine
with every cloud service pre-provisioned,
pre-paid for, pre-setup.
Would you do something like that
or would you prefer to buy the machine once
and then set all that stuff up yourself
and pay for the individual services ad hoc?
I love that question because I was gonna ask you,
I was just gonna comment, well, in the Linux case,
we can say that you actually own your hardware
and your software in a way
because you have control over it, right?
But now that you asked me that question,
it kind of changes my outlook on it
because actually I think the convenience
to having a monthly fee to just have everything taken care
for you from hopefully someone you trust, right?
I think that's a big one.
Yeah, I was thinking like, imagine like it's system 76
running this program or something.
I think it reduces the barrier to entry for Linux,
first of all, if you had that kind of option,
but also just for technology, period.
Because if all of these services are already
all configured for you and updated,
then there's a real security benefit there
and a hands-off that might be nice for the end user.
Like we're already used to paying for various services,
like phone stuff and things like that.
There's obvious markets for it
if they have a surface as a service program.
And this is a big appeal to Chromebooks.
Let's not forget how successful Chromebooks have been.
They're essentially a managed device
in a less structured form than Microsoft is offering here.
And thinking about it, when Brent was answering,
I was thinking to myself, well, why wouldn't I do that
for my studio systems?
Imagine if I could just have these
three or four Kubuntu systems.
Well, okay, one, two, three, yeah,
four, five Kubuntu systems.
I mean, I'd still consider paying 50 bucks a month
if it meant I could get decent new hardware
that had a consistent support contract all the time.
I think I might do that.
I don't know for sure.
But for the business case, I can totally see it.
I would definitely be compelled
to at least run the numbers, don't you think, Brent?
I think you'd be silly not to consider it.
I do wonder, and maybe the Mumble Room
has something to say about this,
but I wonder if we think that Linux
would be ready for something like this.
Yeah, and who would deliver that?
And how would you deliver it?
I would like a ThinkPad as a service.
Well, I mean, as a small business owner,
I've really been considering something like this.
And I've been educating myself on SaltStack.
And with everything being in a file in Linux,
you can take something like Puppet or SaltStack
or something like that, and you can deploy a desktop
just as easily as you could deploy a server.
And then you're just restoring users' configuration files
in their home directory and their.files.
So this is actually something I've been considering
as a potential way to grow my business
into something self-supporting.
Yeah, you're right.
That does make it so much nicer to support end users
when compared to something that has like a registry
or something like that.
It's just a totally different level.
Well, and then when your user goes
and breaks their system inevitably,
then you just rerun your recipe
that redeploys their desktop.
And within five minutes, they've got a brand new
working image that's already connected
to their network drive,
because no one saves anything onto their local disk, right?
Yeah, yeah, I can tell they do.
But going back to the Microsoft story,
my gut, here's why I think it's gonna be a good thing
for Linux, because my gut wants it to happen.
Because I think like, deep down,
like it feels like that's a win for Linux somehow.
Like anytime you make Windows more ongoing expensive,
I feel like you're making people constantly
reevaluate its worth.
Whereas if I just buy it like once every five years,
like say I'm a corporate IT environment,
I'm either subscribing to the large bulk licenses,
the volume licenses, or I'm refreshing my machines
if I'm aggressive every few years,
but probably more likely every five to 10 years.
And that's when I'm addressing the license problem.
As a business, that's not an unmanageable expense,
especially because they are productivity tools,
like they're necessary for the job.
Right, and you can probably find a good quarter
where it makes the most sense,
and okay, yes, we'll buy a big bulk here,
we didn't spend as much elsewhere.
But when it's a line item every month that you're...
You're looking at that going,
well, what are we paying for?
Because that's what we're paying for all the time now,
and it's a per head cost now.
And that adds up, that makes a difference.
You can write monthly costs off as OpEx rather than CapEx,
so that's better for tax purposes.
Yeah, there are advantages.
Plus, if you wrap in licensing and you wrap in cloud storage,
it's probably likely to be cheaper,
but that bundling only gets you so far,
like the cable industry knows that too.
So I think, I mean, it also really depends
on just how easy is it to administer,
what's the customer service aspect like?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I wonder if this isn't the real cost
of Windows 10 being free.
I have thought this from the moment they announced it
as free, I always thought this.
And why they've encouraged it,
why they've called it the last version of Windows.
I think this has been in the works
since Balmer was running the place.
And now they've just kind of figured out
how to put it all together by having different experiments
with the Surface Books and their different services
that have given them some experience.
They managed to do it pretty well with Office 365.
So it's just another checkbox on a feature list.
I was just about to say, we're gonna move on,
but then it dawned on me too, as a Linux user,
what if the price was legitimately affordable?
So let's just say for a moment, it's like,
I mean, it's not gonna be this,
but let's just say for $25 a month,
you could get like a pretty decent Windows 10 device
in your home.
As a Linux user, I might consider that
just so I have a Windows machine from time to time.
And to be honest with you,
that's dropping whatever it is,
100, 200 bucks on Windows 10 Professional,
has been a barrier for me.
I just don't wanna do it.
I just can't bring myself to do it.
Well, look at cell phones.
Yeah, exactly.
You pay, I don't know how much in the states,
100 bucks a month, but that includes cell connection.
So if you're paying half that for your connection
and half that for the device every month,
a laptop probably costs the same or less
to make than a phone.
So yeah, it's possible, definitely.
Yeah, it could be.
All right, all right.
I saw JJ had some more thoughts,
but we'll save them for the post-show.
Let's move on.
We don't need to talk about Microsoft that much more.
I think that's probably good.
And I wanna talk about security for a moment.
I wanna talk about something that has been very apparent
on the TechSnap program for a while.
This is a very TechSnap program topic.
So if you're into this kind of stuff,
check out TechSnap.systems.
But in recent days, the VPN filter malware
has been attracting a lot of attention,
much of it in the wake of the May 25th
public service announcement by the FBI
that was also covered by a number of announcements
from vendors and security companies
around routers being susceptible to an issue.
You might recall the FBI issuing a recommendation
to need to be rebooted.
They were susceptible to runtime malware.
And if you restarted and they reinitialized from the ROM,
the malware would be gone, but they may remain vulnerable.
So Cisco's threat blog posted on VPN filter a while ago.
We covered it in TechSnap,
but they do provide some good details
on devices' impact by this vulnerability,
which affected around 500,000 networking devices worldwide.
Yeah, it works a lot in the way like the Mirai,
Marie, Mirai botnet,
where it specifically goes after home routers.
It also uses several zero-day exploits
that the lazy vendors just haven't patched
that have been known about now.
Turns out that works really well.
Yeah, among the reported vendors impacted by VPN filter
are Linksys and Netgear,
which is 77% of the home router market just right there,
Linksys and Netgear. Wow.
Yeah, and by just exploiting typical vulnerabilities,
you can get access to a lot of stuff
on these two devices in the wild,
including redirecting your DNS to their DNS servers
and all kinds of really kind of nasty things
that you can do when you're in a trusted position
on the edge of the network.
It's the new holy grail too,
because so many of you bastards out there
are using Linux and Android devices,
and you're not using Windows XP and Windows CE devices,
and they can't keep writing malware for Windows
and get to everybody.
You're just making it too hard.
Jerks.
Especially you Mac users and you iOS users.
Don't even get me started.
So why not go after the thing
that y'all have to route through?
And that is the router.
And that's whenever you want to talk out to the internet,
you got to go through that little bastard.
So that's the thing they're going after now.
And so we should talk about security right at that spot,
at the edge of your network.
That's where security has to begin.
And that's why open source at that part of your network,
I think is maybe one of the most critical spots.
If nothing else, then as a remedy to vendor negligence.
I think that's fairly,
because with these open source projects,
as long as the project's alive, they're issuing updates.
It's at least an escape hatch in a world of...
For a long time,
it's gotten a little bit better perhaps these days,
but for a long time, just not very many great options.
No.
So OpenWRT 1806 has just come out today.
And it's a significant release because it's the first one
since the OpenWRT and LEDE projects decided to merge.
Wow, that is a big deal.
Yeah.
And so now this is their combined effort
under the OpenWRT umbrella.
We're back together.
Yeah, that is great, right?
It's been, we talked about this two years ago.
Wow.
That's how long it's been,
which it doesn't feel like it's been that long, but yeah.
So the Linux Embedded Development Environment
and OpenWRT came together and now we have OpenWRT 1806,
which is replacing 1505.
So it's a pretty big jump there
because it's a combination of LEDE 1701 and OpenWRT 1505.
So they just went right to 1806.
It adds support for network flow offloading,
which is bad ass,
modernizes support for some of Atheros chipsets,
a bunch of kernel updates and package updates
among other areas of improvement.
And we'll have links in the show notes
so you can check it out.
This is the kind of thing where it's a simple step.
I mean, if you've got a good hardware vendor
who's updating your firmware
and you feel pretty comfortable in it,
then more power to you.
That's great.
But this has been the solution I've taken in the past.
You and I were also recently talking about
maybe checking out some more Microtech stuff,
but this is really nice.
And they have a wide range.
It really comes down to the chips in your box.
So you got it.
I think you can also sometimes find a nice middle ground
where like, if you can set up an OpenSense or PF sense box,
great if you know how to set up your own router
from running whatever Unix-like
or Unix-based operating system,
also great if you know how to do that,
but you might just be someone who's already invested
in one of the common router brands,
but you know someone who listens to this show
or whatever else,
and you can go through, spend a Sunday,
get that on there,
and then not have to buy a new device,
but have more control
and have a better, more secure platform.
You should be able to be completely done
by the time you've finished a Linux Unplugged podcast,
I think.
So try that out.
Like Wes said, maybe help out a family member.
There's other solutions, obviously.
We could list so many other possibilities.
You guys know I'm a big fan of PF sense,
but if you've got hardware
that is one of these devices,
one of these 77% of the devices in the market
that is possible to load OpenWRT on,
maybe it's just time.
Because these, like on Tech Snip,
we're constantly talking about back doors
and all this stuff that even with Linux on there
or BusyBox on there,
they still just screw up the basic implementations.
It's not enough that it's based on Linux.
It has to be well implemented.
For some reason, they just,
the firmware developers just don't feel comfortable
unless you've got a unsecured telnet port open
at all times.
And it's just like baked in, baked in usernames and passwords.
One of my favorites that we talked about on Tech Snip
was the root password was just the MAC address
of the network card.
So if you knew the MAC address of the router
and then you just copy and pasted that,
say from your terminal,
and you could just paste that in the password
and log right in, is root.
Makes it easy.
And there's, but there's even ones where there's like,
no, no password necessary.
Absolutely no password necessary.
Just knock on the door.
There has literally been some,
it's like you knock on this port
on a certain amount of times
and you just get telnet root access.
Have that at Haas.
It's really something.
So yeah, you gotta go replace these things.
But you really do still have to keep them up to date.
You do still have to implement best practices.
It's not just a matter of the firmware,
but getting something open source,
supported by a community that gets frequent updates
is a good first step.
That's how I look at it.
Corita is getting some decent funding
and it's allowing for one of their developers to go,
if not full-time, near full-time.
Now, Corita's been publishing,
wow, this is another Microsoft story, really,
if you think about it.
Corita's been publishing to the Windows Store
for quite some time.
Not quite a year,
but they've updated their store listing almost 20 times.
And by far, the majority of users get Corita
from the website,
about 30,000 downloads a week from their website.
Nice. Yeah.
The store downloads from Microsoft's store
are about 125 a week.
Still though, the income that has been generated
by the Windows Store makes it possible
for the Corita maintainer to work on Corita full-time,
which would never have been possible otherwise.
Interesting.
30,000 downloads from their website
and they couldn't make enough money to go full-time.
125 downloads a week from the Microsoft store
and they're going full-time.
It's an interesting different philosophy
when you're in that app store idea, right?
I mean, you can easily send donations
through their main website,
but I guess you're just in that mindset of ready to...
Well, it's price per download, right?
So in the Windows Store, you pay a little bit.
And you expect to.
Yeah.
And it makes open source development
of a pretty important open source application
that is competitive with things from Adobe possible.
I just wonder if we should just take a moment
and reflect on that.
Because to me, it seems like there's a big lesson
to learn from that.
And I think about what the App Center,
what elementary OS is doing with the App Center.
I think it's also interesting
because the article goes on to discuss
some of the problems they've had in that environment.
And maybe that is why we do need
more open source friendly things
like the App Store and other efforts.
Yeah, they talk about being powerless.
They talk about all the rules that are made by the store.
And if there's one particular store rule
that gets interpreted the wrong way,
the curators can just decide,
you know what, no good.
And if you're not native English,
then it makes it even harder
to then communicate with the store curators.
And sometimes things can be just simply misunderstood
because of a language barrier.
So what's the answer then?
If you have an uncurated store,
like the AUR or like the snap repositories, et cetera,
you end up with crypto software in there.
I mean, there has to be somebody somewhere,
I think, verifying these packages
and maintaining that trust.
Is it that or is it there's a price?
You know, I mean, really.
Nothing says that cryptoware doesn't sneak into these stores
from time to time that are curated.
But I think for Corita, the big difference here is
if you wanna download it from the Windows Store,
if you want that convenience, you gotta pay a little money.
I don't have the Windows Store on me.
So, oh, here it is, it's $9.79.
If you wanna download it from the Windows Store,
you have to pay $9.79.
And 125 a week, they can go full time.
That seems to be the crux of the issue.
That's an uncomfortable thing, I think,
because the numbers are devastating.
30,000 downloads, right?
I mean, if you look at this show, right?
This show will get that.
And then you look at our Patreon,
which this is just always how it works, right?
You look at the Patreon,
there's much less than that on the Patreon.
Totally understandable, because we're also ad supported.
But I think there is a massive difference
when something's free and just available online.
The return you get, I think,
is probably often less than a percent.
What do you think about this, Brent?
Trying to imagine for myself what would happen
if those 30,000 weekly downloads went through
a similar app store and gave them a similar revenue.
That would be huge for an open source project like this
who's trying to really break some ground.
Yeah.
Arthur, you were mentioning too
that there's an open source game
that sort of struggles with the same issue,
perhaps even on a larger scale.
There's actually several open source games.
I'm involved in one of them.
But recently I talked with a 080 developer.
And they have about 100K downloads a year.
But they only get about $90 per month in donations.
And they have $100 per month in server costs.
So they're going negative each month.
Yeah, boy, that is some bad math.
So 100,000 downloads a year
and they're making 90 bucks a month?
Yeah, that's not gonna work, is it?
They have some slack
because they did some donation drives a while ago.
But still, it's very discouraging for them
and for us with our game.
So, especially since there are so many people
happy to buy early access games for Linux,
but not happy to donate to a free game.
So this issue that we're touching on in part
is often why when people ask me,
why do you want more users on the Linux desktop?
Why do you want Slack on the Linux desktop
if it means a slow electron proprietary service application?
Then what's the point of having a free desktop?
Why have new users at the cost
of gaining proprietary applications?
And this is my answer.
Having a larger user base on Linux,
on the desktop in particular,
facilitates an economy to pay developers to do hard work.
And as a user base grows,
the demand for more sophisticated applications
that connect to more sophisticated services will also grow.
And if we don't have a way to facilitate financing this work,
the people that are capable of doing that work
are gonna go get paid to do it somewhere else.
And I think it's a bit of egg on our face
that the fricking Microsoft Windows store
is now paying to make creative development possible.
And I also can't sit here and say the solution
is that every developer should go to Patreon
or something like that because that's not gonna scale either.
We're getting patron out at this point.
Let's be honest, everybody is.
I'm getting a little tapped out myself
and I'm still trying to support people.
The reality is we have to facilitate some mechanism
to reward hard work.
A value for value model has to exist
for free and open source software.
And I think that's in part why I follow
what Daniel and the team at Elementary OS
are doing with such interest
because that is at least a possible solution.
It might not be your favorite solution,
but they are definitely trying and innovating in that space.
It's an incubator of what could perhaps work
on a wider scale someday.
And I don't know if that's the right solution,
but maybe what's going on with Carita
gives us some perspective.
Especially exploring things of,
it's still open source, still free,
but maybe there's a few hurdles
or it's not the thing that you find the easiest anymore.
You're more encouraged to donate.
There's a lot of different angles
and I think we'll have to adapt to that
and the philosophy of it as a community.
Yeah.
So let's talk about how to grow that user base,
especially when it comes to the hardware side
with Mr. Barton George.
So let's bring Barton in just a moment.
But first, I wanna thank DigitalOcean
for making this episode possible.
Go to do.co slash unplugged
and get a $100 credit for 60 days over at DigitalOcean.
That's do.co slash unplugged.
So many great open source projects
are provided infrastructure by DigitalOcean
to take care of the hassle of the backend infrastructure
and just let them get work done.
And you can do the same thing.
It's easy to get set up, less than 55 seconds.
The dashboard's crazy great and easy.
They have an API that's well documented
and tons of open source applications
are already built around that you can just start using.
One click deployments for tons of great open source
entire stacks of applications
or just deploy the base rig.
They got just about every distribution
you'd wanna run in a server.
My favorite system has four gigs of RAM,
two CPUs, 80 gigabytes of enterprise grade SSDs,
three terabytes of them transfers for three cents an hour.
Now every system has enterprise grade SSDs.
They've all got 40 gigabit connections
coming to the hypervisors,
data centers all over the world,
cloud firewalls that block the traffic
at the network level
so they never even have to hit your rig,
monitoring and alerting built in and much, much more.
But instead of listening to me go on about it,
just go try it.
Just try it.
Maybe spin up a project
you've been wanting to work with for a while.
Something you wanna learn about
or something you wanna put in production.
dio.co slash unplugged
and a big thank you to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Wes and I often experiment with different things
on DigitalOcean,
just sort of like when we're prepping for a show.
Awesome, all the time.
I know, it's fun.
dio.co slash unplugged.
Also a huge, huge thank you to Linux Academy
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
You can sign up for a free seven day trial
and support the show.
This is a platform to learn everything about Linux
and the huge industry around Linux now.
Everything that runs Linux or Linux runs on,
they basically have coursework for that
from the essentials around Linux,
which just got a refresh today
or the big topics like AWS and Azure and OpenStack
and the nitty gritties
and now also really a lot of great content around security.
But something that I don't talk about very often
and maybe something you should be made aware of
is they have a really epic team system.
So if you're in an IT department
or if you're at a business that wants to train up new staff
or have staff get up to date on something
or just provide continuing education,
Linux Academy will work with your business
to set up a team plan for all of them
where there's metrics for you to look at
and all kinds of cool dashboard stuff for you
and you get to work hands-on with a salesperson
that can actually help you
get the right stuff for your business.
Like it's a full professional package
that I don't normally talk about
because normally I'm talking to you individuals out there,
but this is something to consider too
is if your work is interested in something like that,
you might pass that along to them
because that was a big area
that I didn't realize that they operate in,
but it makes total sense.
It would be awesome as an IT department
to have that as a resource.
So today Linux Academy launched a whole bunch of new content.
They've been doing this for over a month now,
been releasing more and more.
They were claiming 150 new bits of content.
I think it's over 200.
I mean, I think they just way overshot.
They under-promised and over-delivered.
Today they just updated the LPI DevOps tools
engineer certification,
as well as a ton of other Azure and other great things
like just basic Chef courseware.
Nice. Yeah.
I'm gonna link in the show notes the link to the video
because I think they had like the chief community guy on
from Chef on the live stream.
And they just streamed this earlier today
where they announced like the new Azure concepts courseware,
the Microsoft Exam 705033,
which is implementing Microsoft Azure infrastructure solutions
and a whole bunch of Linux Essentials,
certified Jenkins engineer courseware,
just a ton of stuff.
And like I said, the Chef community guy
all got announced today.
So check that out.
I'll have a link in the show notes at Linux Unplugged
slash 260 and get started at Linux Academy
by going to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
And a massive thank you to Ting
for all of the years of keeping this show on the road,
literally while I'm on the road
and while I'm figuratively on the road,
like, I don't know,
maybe I'm just out of the office mentally,
but they've still kept me on the road.
You know what I'm saying?
They're so good.
They just know what's happening.
They really do because it's smarter than unlimited wireless.
If you use less, you pay less.
And it's just $6 for a line.
And then when you need it, it's there.
Holy crap has that been useful.
The average Ting bill is just 23 bucks per phone per month.
Cause it's paid for what you use wireless,
minutes, messages, megabytes, whatever you use,
that's what you pay.
$6 for the line and then just your usage on top of that.
Like, well, I think I should probably also mention,
sometimes depending on your area, Uncle Sam has a cut.
You know what I'm saying?
Like he's got a cut, Uncle Sam.
That ain't Ting's fault.
They can't help that.
He's got his hands in everything, Wes.
Watch out.
I know.
No contracts, no early termination fees,
and a great control panel to manage it all.
Turn individual services off,
get complete usage at a glance,
take control of every aspect of your account,
and turn things on or off.
Like I've activated several devices
just through the webpage.
And they also have a bunch of great devices
you can buy directly,
including just getting a $9 SIM card.
Is this?
Oh, whoa.
Oh, no, no, no, no.
Don't tell me.
Do not tell me they have a $1 sale.
Oh, snap.
They got a $1 sale going on the Ting SIM.
What?
No.
At least the GSM SIM.
I've been waiting.
I'm gonna put a link in the show notes.
That's the best deal of the year, right there.
The $1 SIM is when no one,
I'm gonna send a link to Noah too.
You stock up on these SIMs.
You just put them in your bag.
And then when you need data somewhere,
you pop it in there, you're good to go.
It's $6 a month and you turn it off when you're done.
And plus, when you get that SIM at a dollar,
if you go to linux.ting.com,
they'll give you $25 in service credit,
which is probably gonna pay for more
than your first month of using that thing.
Maybe even the first two months of using that thing,
depending on how much you use it.
So go grab a $1 Ting SIM card.
I'll have a link in the show notes.
And then get started at Ting
by going to linux.ting.com.
That's awesome.
That is like Christmas in July when that happens.
Now you can be a cell phone hero.
Friends are out of data,
you have someone visiting from another country,
boom, Ting's got your back.
A cell phone hero, I love it.
linux.ting.com.
Big thanks to Ting
and thank you everybody for supporting our sponsors
and that helps keep us going too.
All right, so every now and then
I like to sit down with Barton George.
You guys remember Barton.
He was the guy that really kicked
the whole Sputnik project off at Dell
and was an advocate and used some internal funding they had.
Like there was their own seed funding internally,
if you will, that's not what they called it.
But it's kind of like, it was like,
here's some project money, see what you can do with this.
It wasn't a ton, it wasn't a ton.
But with that money, Barton assembled a small team
and they begun working on the Sputnik project.
Well, just a few months ago,
they released the seventh generation of the XPS 13.
And then last week, they just updated it unusually quick
to 1804 and there's been a ton of excitement around that.
So we brought Barton back to the show
to do some high level talking about all this stuff.
Well, a big hearty welcome back to the show
to one Mr. Barton George.
Barton, welcome back to the Unplugged program.
My pleasure is always, Chris.
This is one of the things I enjoy doing most.
Oh, he says, with I'm sure 100% legitimacy.
Of course.
It's for all the podcasters, what?
Yeah, right, yeah, right, of course.
Of course, good on you, good on you.
In fact, I'll have to tell you,
there was another podcast I was going to be doing
and I don't know,
they heard through the grapevine I was doing this
and they said, oh, why don't we push it off
for a little bit?
Once you come on one of the Jupiter broadcasting shows,
you basically, you've met,
you've reached all of the audiences,
I think what that's about.
Well, exactly, exactly, there's no more.
Yeah, there's no competing.
So of course, if you're here,
that probably means there's some new things to talk about.
And I wanted to just kind of recap
with maybe a few of the general updates
to the whole Sputnik line.
Where have things changed?
Where have things gone in the last few months?
Maybe it's, what has it been, six months,
almost a year since we chatted?
What's changed, what's new?
Well, I'm trying to remember,
you guys came down here to Dell
and you did the whole shebang
as far as what are we doing with regards to Linux?
And you did things like on the client side,
the server side, you did our HPC stuff.
That was last April, right?
Yeah, and then you did, in fact,
that you did also the coffee maker,
which also runs on Linux.
That's right, yeah.
You covered the whole nine yards.
Well, since that time, lots happened.
We had, in November, we celebrated our fifth anniversary.
And then we, in January,
we launched the seventh generation of the XPS 13.
Oh, wow.
And that, at the time, launched with 16.04.
Fast forward to now,
and we, about a month or two ago,
we launched, we're starting to refresh
our whole precision line,
which runs on the Precision Mobile that runs on Ubuntu.
So there's four that make up that line.
In fact, I think you have one from the last gen.
There's the 3530, the 5330,
the 7530, and the 7730.
You gotta give these some names,
like the Ferrari, you know,
like these names that stick.
No, they do, all internal code names
that I never remember.
In fact, yes, they actually do use like Testarossa
and other various fast car names.
That's great.
So, but you have, which one did you get?
Did you get the 7720?
Yes, that is what it is, exactly.
Okay.
Yeah, I was just gonna say,
it's almost within arm's reach,
but yes, the 7720.
And it's a beast of a machine.
One of the things I love about it
is I can throw just about any workload at that sucker,
and it never fails.
It just churns and churns through it.
I've done literally almost 40 hours
of straight encoding on that machine before.
Wow.
Yeah.
Dang.
It really holds up.
Yeah, and it just keeps getting beefier.
So, and then just to decode the 77,
the seven stands for 17 inch,
the 75, the five stands for?
I'm gonna say AMD.
I don't know.
I'm just taking a wild stab.
No, it stands for 15 inches.
But anyway.
Oh, that makes way more sense.
Yeah.
Much better, yeah.
Same.
That's a good guess.
Yeah, and I thought you were gonna Google it
and find out.
Oh, I should have.
But we have the 35 is the one that's the value price,
and then the 5530 is the one
that most developers wanna get.
So my favorite thing on Hacker News was somebody who wrote,
Dell makes a better MacBook Pro than Apple.
And I just thought, wow,
that was the 5520 at the time was what he was talking about.
And then he put, you know, didn't see that coming.
So it's been great.
That's just to get to wax nostalgic.
When we launched originally now a little over five years ago,
it was just the XPS 13.
Right.
And we just had one config.
And what we got was a lot of people saying,
well, that's cool, but that's not gonna do it for me.
I need something big and beefy.
And we kept sort of getting more and more of that feedback.
And what we did was Jared Dominguez,
who's our Linux OS architect,
took one of the M3800s,
that's the first precision mobile system.
And in his spare time, he got Ubuntu up and running.
So he posted that to his blog or to the Dell technical blog
and got tons of excitement,
but that didn't satiate the folks.
They still wanted it to become real.
And so the next year we were able to release that
as a real system.
So then from there it was one system.
And then we did the current line, they went from 10.
And then the next generation ends in 20,
which is what you have.
And as we said, now the next one is 30.
Okay, so it does kind of make sense
when you break it down.
Oh yeah, yeah.
Once you get the decoder rigged, it's-
Yeah, once you have the key.
I was looking at the original specs,
the original XPS 13 developer edition,
wasn't, I mean, it wasn't bad.
It was eight gigs of RAM, 256 gigabyte SSD.
The biggest weak spot really was the screen
compared to what you have now on the XPS 13.
It was a 1280 by 720.
We got a lot of nasty comments about that.
My phone has twice that, et cetera, et cetera.
Luckily we were able to fix that within two months.
So we launched in the States,
then two months later when we launched in Europe,
we were able to get a higher resolution screen.
The other thing too is when we first were doing
the beta work, it was only four gigs.
So when we got to release, it was eight gigs.
So yeah, not so bad.
But just to finish my linear story of what's happening,
we announced the new Precision line,
the 3530 was available first, that's the value one.
And then the two super beefy ones,
the 15 inch and the 17 inch, we announced two weeks ago.
And as I said, that's the one that you have.
And the other thing too is we're targeting the higher end,
the 7730 at AI workloads.
Ah, does that mean more GPU?
What does that mean really?
Yeah, it's the cards that go in there
and you're gonna start getting me out of my depth.
So I'll just say, I'll just have a dip.
Yeah, but it's like the hard, I mean, people throw it around,
but there is like a hardware, a software stack
that like goes into it.
And I find that to be really interesting
because it's really a lot of it is starting on Linux,
you know, like this whole AI workload
and machine learning is so new.
And it's, did you see, I mean, not to derail,
but did you see that coming?
I didn't really quite see it being so strong
a few years ago.
Well, I mean, I think that's sort of where it began, right?
If you think of with data scientists
and people in the educational space,
that's what they're gonna start off with is Linux.
And then they get used to it and they really like it.
So it's carried over from there.
And it's actually, so we've got one system
on the mobile workstation,
but then the four desk side ones we offer,
those are also well-targeted at AI.
I mean, it seems like a sweet spot where you can do,
you have both a user-friendly desktop
and a production machine that can run real workloads.
Exactly.
And so you can do stuff locally
and then you can always push it to servers on the backend.
I know you were kind of wrapping this up,
but before, you touched on something
to go back to your story a bit.
You mentioned, you know, you shipped it with the one screen
and then pretty quickly realized needs a better screen.
Prototypes had four gigs of RAM,
final version had eight gigs of RAM.
There's something that kind of caught my attention
with just the most recent cycle of machines
is if I'm not mistaken, they launched with 16.04,
but then within a couple of months now,
we're seeing a Dell sanctioned upgrade path to 18.04.
And I believe new units will be shipping with 18.04.
What's that like?
I mean, how does that happen exactly?
Because the timing of the new XPS hardware
and the timing of the 18.04 release
were really close together.
I'm imagining behind the scenes,
there must've been some consternation
over is it worth holding back
and shipping 18.04 originally or what?
I'm just curious, how did that transpire?
Yeah, and I think sometimes we get luckier than others
depending on, right?
So it was the seventh generation that we're talking about.
So within those seven generations,
sometimes we get lucky with the timing
so that if it's, I don't know, 14.04,
it came out in, say, August or October.
So it looks we're pretty close to that number.
And then other times, unfortunately,
this is where we end up on the wrong end
of the lucky factor.
Because first of all, after it's launched,
then the OEM drivers and bits like that
have to be finally put together by Canonical.
And then we need to do the work
and there's a certain amount of lead time
so that if people think, well, gosh,
your system came out in, let's just say, May
and 18.04 obviously came out in April.
What's the deal?
What's the deal, man?
Exactly.
And so unfortunately, the way that the cycle works,
it comes out with what fits in the time frame of getting
the release from Canonical for the OEM
as well as the whole lead time with the product.
Yeah, that makes sense.
So in the case of 18.04 on the XPS 13,
we're the first large OEM to launch with 18.04.
So what we did is we knew the timing was coming up.
And one thing I learned too, because we were taking stock
the other day, we have over 150 systems that run Ubuntu.
And I had no idea it was that many.
When you say systems, what do you
mean, like servers, IoT devices, desktops, laptops?
No, these are just clients.
So it would be things like Precision Desktop and Mobile
as well as Vostro, Optiplex, blah, blah, blah.
And so just as an aside, the difference between,
and we've done that now for over a decade.
The difference in Sputnik is that when I pitched it,
I said, you know what?
Developers will really pay for our best-looking system
running Ubuntu.
And that was counterintuitive because we
had done really well with Ubuntu on some
of the lower-end systems.
And they still sell extremely well.
But the idea that somebody would be
willing to pay for our highest-end system, which
is the XPS 13, and then put a free operating system on it,
why would they want that?
So that was the difference.
But anyway, if I get back to, but I digress.
If I get back to that 150 systems,
there's a bunch that would be launching
within a certain time frame.
And what we did was we said, because this
is a big deal with 1804, let's pick our flagship Ubuntu
product, which is indeed the XPS 13.
And so let's go and let's recertify that.
And so that's how we made the choice with this one.
Because traditionally, it would be just you certify once,
and that's the way you stay.
Yeah, that's what I was expecting.
And I'm curious if you have any initial impressions
on the customer's reaction to the switch from Unity 7
to the GNOME Shell environment now.
Have you gotten any kind of signal
on how people are receiving that,
even with your own team internally or customers?
You know, I haven't.
I think internally, well, I won't speak for others.
But I think just from my sort of high-level view,
it seemed to make sense.
They had gotten some traction with Unity,
and it was a great idea.
But at some point, when you're looking to focus resources,
unfortunately, you look for something
that you can leverage that's not something
you have to put a ton of resources in.
And so it's interesting in the blog
I did for the launching of 1804, which was just last week,
that I did what was relaunched with 1204.
And I wrote what was going on just quickly
with Ubuntu back then.
And that's when they were saying that you had the HUD.
But the other thing, too, is that's
when people were saying Unity is actually gaining traction,
and it looks like it might be pretty cool.
Right, and just to be clear, what you're talking about
is the original Sputnik launch back in 2012.
Exactly, yeah.
So yeah, 1204, which had the specs that you just
quoted earlier on.
But yeah, then as I say, fast forward to today,
and you have the big switch over.
So with that specifically, I haven't heard yet from.
I suppose in a way, no news is also good news at your level.
Yeah, I mean, I think there was one comment about it.
Usually, either through comments on my blog or through Twitter,
somebody, if they like or don't like something,
they're pretty good either way of saying, oh, I'm
so glad you did X, or why the heck did you do Y?
And I haven't really heard anything.
Good, I think that's probably a good thing.
I have just a couple of more questions for you
that I'm pretty much done, but the next couple questions
are looking forward a little bit.
I've been really kind of pondering this whole Chromebooks
running Linux apps situations.
It seems like all of a sudden, Google
has figured out what you figured out more than five years ago
with Sputnik, and that is that you can hyper-target
this developer market with a reliable Linux workstation.
And now they're adding the capability on Chrome OS
to actually run Linux applications.
So you could run things that you normally
would have to have a full Linux desktop for.
Do you perceive that as competition
to the Sputnik line?
And I guess another way to frame that is,
why would I necessarily buy an XPS 13 over, say,
a future Chromebook in a year or so from now
that has pretty decent specs, maybe is $300,
and can run Linux applications?
Yeah, I think, well, it's interesting
because they obviously took the idea from us because five years
ago when we were looking to sanity check this,
we went out and talked to them.
So they stole the idea.
They just waited five years to act on it, right?
I mean, it was insidious.
But I think at this point, I think
you're talking about Fuchsia as opposed
to Christine with the running of the Linux apps.
And Christine is the one where, and I
don't know a ton about this.
I can just throw these names around,
is the one that's more developer-targeted.
And so I think there will be certain use cases
that Chromebook will be fine.
But there will also be, they're going
to be different a year from now, as will we, right?
We keep progressing.
We're not standing still.
And it will be interesting to see
which areas in particular they'll target.
I know, just anecdotally, my cousin
works on back-end systems at Google.
And so when he started there, he wanted
to get an Ubuntu-based system.
And then he found out that you really can't work locally.
And so he just got a Chromebook.
So it depends on what kind of a use case you're using.
If all you're doing is connecting back-end,
then you really don't need something powerful.
But if you're doing a lot of hacking on the plane
or on the train or conferences, then that's
something like the XPS 13 makes a lot of sense.
Yeah, and I think just like Mac OS,
only more pronounced Chrome OS has
walls that more technical users will run into pretty quickly.
And that can be a source of frustration.
And something like the XPS 13 is a tool to do your job.
And it's worth investing in the right tool.
So I don't think it spells doom for anything.
But it is interesting to see Google executing
on what is clearly a Dell idea.
I mean, it just looks like it from just the outsider's
perspective, even, which is fascinating.
I wonder what took them so long, you know?
Well, exactly.
They were plotting, and they were trying to figure it out.
And then one day, boom.
They're waiting to see if you made any money
and sold some units, and then they realized.
Oh, there you go, yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
In the first couple of years, it looked like it wasn't.
But yeah, we've all of a sudden, it's gone like a hockey stick.
It's crazy with Sputnik.
And I think it's because it's the network effect, right?
So it's more of a word of mouth.
We haven't bought any Super Bowl ads yet.
Although, we will this year.
That was a spoiler.
I shouldn't have told you that.
Really?
Yeah, Sputnik Super Bowl ad.
I'm paying for it out of my own pocket.
No, you're joking now.
No, no, totally.
Totally, I'm paying for it.
Gosh, you got me excited.
You got me excited there.
Well, we'll do a Kickstarter to go fund me.
Well, that is exactly what it's going to say.
So if you want to see us in the Super Bowl, please,
it's under Barton George, move to Bermuda account.
That's just sort of a way we've set it up.
Yeah, it seems legit.
Yeah, exactly.
So again, I digress.
But I was just talking about how things have done,
how it's really going up, which is really nice.
It's been really gratifying.
I bet.
And so to see that it's caught a lot of attention
internally because I think at the beginning, I don't think,
I know in the beginning there's quite a few people who
saw this as a distraction because any company you've
got X number of resources.
And why are you going to put them on this niche market
as they saw it with a group that Dell really doesn't target
or work with, meaning developers?
And then now it's the money we made,
but also the amount of positive feedback
thanks to the community, reviews and press, et cetera.
It's been great.
I mean, the things that people say on Twitter are just,
they're awesome.
It's really nice to know that there's
a group that really was looking for something just like this.
Yeah, and it has net positive brand effects for Dell.
I think it really does, even outside the core market
that the Sputnik is targeting.
Yeah, I've seen comments where people saying that I
didn't consider Dell's before, but now that you got this,
I'm very interested in checking out Dell.
So that's been great.
It's also, because it's a net new area for us,
we are cannibalizing Windows systems.
Right, interesting.
That's a good point.
And that turns out to be pretty important politically,
I imagine.
Well, Barton, I always enjoy our chats.
Is there anything else you want to touch on or mention?
I'll have a link to your blog and your Twitter
profile in our show notes, so people
can get that pretty easily.
Yeah, I think the one thing I would say
is the interest in the 18.04 release on the XPS 13 developer
edition, I had no idea it would generate this much interest.
Because the platform itself has been around since January.
It's 18.04, great.
That makes sense.
But I mean, this is, just for example,
the first day I posted my blog, I got 8,000 views.
The next day, I got 13,000 views.
And the days before, I'm looking at 122 views, 73 views, 127.
And this happens with anything Sputnik.
I post, it's exponential compared to the others.
But this in and of itself, just in these first few days,
has put it in my top 10 blogs.
And like I said, I didn't think this
was going to be a big deal.
I didn't think people were going to be that interested.
So shows how much I know.
There's something about the two combined
that just makes it a hot pair.
Yeah, there's been a lot of interest
we've seen in the audience from 18.04 as well.
And I follow with a lot of interest too.
I think a lot of people right now, I don't know,
maybe I'm projecting, but I think a lot of people
are looking at their next few years
and wanting to get work done.
And 18.04 kind of landed right in that window
for a lot of folks.
Yeah, and then we obviously standardized
on the enterprise, the LTSs, as it would make sense.
Because particularly if you're selling to enterprises,
they're not going to want the interim releases
and have everything change every six months.
Yeah, exactly.
And plus, this is why 18.04 is still kind of the freshest.
It's still new, so it's still competitive features
wise and all of that.
And it's had time to bake a little more now
that it's stable and most of the bugs are ironed out.
Yeah, the dot one shipped.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
And so because the timing wasn't kind to us,
we were able to recertify, particularly given,
like I said, we're the first to certify in 18.04
and this is our flagship.
So we really went out of our way.
We could have put it on one of the ones that was more
likely to ship at this point.
So we've got one coming up soon.
But we said, let's make a real effort
to go a little bit before that and do it on the XPS 13.
Very good, Barton.
Very good.
I really enjoy our chats and I'm really pleased
to see the continued upward trajectory of the project.
Well, that's great, Barton.
Have a great rest of your day, sir.
And thank you very much for coming on the Unplugged
program.
Well, thanks for the opportunity, Chris.
Keep on keeping on.
We will, Wes.
Are we sure?
He can't stop us.
No, he can't stop us.
Now, we have so many other things to talk about,
but I do kind of want to keep the show a little bit shorter.
I've been trying to keep it under an hour and 15 or so.
So we'll probably leave a few things for the show notes.
But it was a super great chat with Barton.
And I'm really pleased to see the progress
of their project.
Now, we need some balance in the show for next week.
So if somebody from Red Hat wants
to come on and talk about, I don't know, CoreOS
or something, let's just balance it out a little bit.
Because we had a lot of Ubuntu this episode.
And while it's fine, it's a great product, obviously.
Here's the platform.
I feel like we've got to, yeah.
Or maybe we should have somebody come on here and talk about,
not Gentoo.
We've done that plenty.
I don't know.
But it's something we'll think about.
In the meantime, let's talk about some app picks.
We've got a couple for you that we wanted to cover
before we get out of here.
And what is more fun than stressing the hell out
of your system?
So we've got an app for you.
I'm going to call it S2E, S-T-U-I?
The stress terminal UI.
Yeah, and you've got it installed on your machine
over there.
It is a super slick looking.
Is it technically a terminal app?
Yeah, it runs right in that there terminal.
It's a terminal app.
It's a Python terminal app that runs right in your terminal.
And it's going to be some of the coolest looking visuals
to visualize out the utilization of your system,
like CPU frequency, temperature, overall clock utilization,
and the power it's drawing in this really tight looking UI.
How would you?
I mean, you almost describe that as pastel colors.
I don't really know how to describe that.
Yeah, the color scheme is lovely.
Yeah, it's nice.
And it's not going to bombard you
with a whole ton of information about just
every little process on your system.
It just gives you a nice, easy to interpret holistic view
of what's happening.
And it kind of works best with a companion tool, right?
Yeah, if you also have stress testing tools available,
then you can stress test your system
and then watch how it responds.
And that sounds like the most fun, right?
Is when you get a new box, which I have fantasies of.
I could also see maybe you have a couple boxes you're
evaluating, maybe for a big enterprise buy,
or just because you're a picky consumer.
Heck yeah, man.
You got to try it out.
This is a simple tool that Joe found
that we're going to include in the show.
It's called Odeo.
And it does one job, and it does it pretty well.
You copy a YouTube URL, you paste it in the terminal,
you run this program, and it extracts the audio from it.
And that's it.
So if you've got like MP4 audio you want to get from it
or something like that, Odeo will download your favorite
music to the current working directory of your terminal.
And try to get the highest quality audio version
it can off of YouTube.
It does depend on your favorite YouTube DL and FFmpeg
utilities, but it's pretty nice.
And you could just install those from the repo
and then go get Odeo.
This looks like, I mean, I'll be honest,
that's definitely a common workflow for me.
Oh, I do it all the time, yeah.
Mostly for Unfilter, but absolutely I do it all the time.
Now we're rocking it here.
I think we may overshoot, but we're moving right along.
Last but not least, this is a really cool tool
that Joe also found.
And it's not going to work for all of our shows yet,
but it may work if you want to go pretty far back for our shows
and a bunch of your favorite podcasts.
It's called rewind.website.
And speaking of top level domains, there's a good one.
And it is a really cool concept.
You go back in time and listen to a podcast
from its very beginning.
You can also put an iTunes URL in there or a SoundCloud URL
in there.
So the whole idea, and by the way,
the core code's up on GitHub, which
we have linked in the show notes.
The whole idea is start with a podcast
from the very beginning and then choose
a frequency in which you would like new versions
of that episode to be delivered to you.
So you sort of re-experience it as if you
were listening during the time those episodes are
being released.
So you can set a wait frequency of daily, weekly, and monthly.
And then it will deliver you a new episode
from the back catalog of your favorite podcast.
Oh, that's super handy.
Yeah, and I love that it's AGPL.
You can go find it.
You can go run it yourself if you don't want
to trust them to run it for you.
Yeah.
Yeah, the rewind.website is sort of like a demo, really.
I mean, it's up and running.
It appears they're offering it as a service.
But you can get CastRewinder for your own system
and then get it up and running.
Again, another Python app.
It's the best of all worlds.
Look at us.
We're all Python for the app pics.
Just about.
So that's a neat idea.
You can check it out, rewind.website,
or go to the GitHub page and throw it up on your own box
if you're comfortable with Python.
And yeah, like Wes said, it's AGPL version 3
if you want to host it yourself.
And I think that is such a neat idea
to re-subscribe and re-listen.
It's, oh, man, is it painful.
You know, when you're used to marathoning something
and you listen to it weekly, you're like,
how do people do this?
I know, right?
But in that suffering, there is some amount
of gain and appreciation.
And you won't just take it for granted.
Yeah, yeah.
So anyways, you can check those out in the show notes,
linuxunplug.com, slash 260.
And yeah, there we go.
We're going to get out of here on our own imposed deadline,
not because we want to do less show,
but simply because we know you have a lot of podcast options.
And sometimes it's good to get a little tighter in here.
So I'm pretty pleased.
I think it's a good place to end.
There's a lot more to talk about.
There's more to do.
We may put it all in the post show.
But in the meantime, go get yourself some more Wes Payne.
Where are you at, Wes?
TechSnap.systems or at Wes Payne.
There you go.
You can also get more of me at chrisles, the whole network
at Jupiter Signal.
And check our website for links to Brent's page.
I think we're going to start putting other folks on there
from the community as well.
So if you want to get more of them,
find out what they're up to, what their websites are,
that's all going to be posted at linuxunplug.com as well.
So it's going to be a pretty great resource,
because we also have links to all that stuff
that we talked about.
Hey, did you know you can join us live?
You can participate in that virtual lug.
You just need a working microphone, some headphones,
pass the audio check, and then you can join us.
Check it out.
And we'll see you in the next one.
Oh, next Tuesday.
There, I got it in there.
Nice.
How's that, Brent?
Thank you.
That and a bell ring would be, yeah, make the show for me.
Oh, OK, right.
There you go.
Thank you.
You got the actual bell, too.
So yeah, all right.
Boy, I'm really glad it worked out with Barton,
because he has meetings and peoples and things like that.
Important laptop-related business.
Yeah, all that kind of stuff.
And they're in the middle of prepping the next release,
so that was cool.
Yeah, I loved how he talked about the community feedback,
how he was so, so positive.
And that was a bit opposite to what
we heard last week about that hearing stuff,
so that was good to hear.
Very good point.
Would you like me to put the word out,
asking for somebody from CoreOS?
Or anybody in the area.
Yeah, they would like to come on and get some representation,
talk about something they're working on,
or anything like that.
Absolutely, I would love that.
I will drop a message in one of the internal mailing lists
and let you know what happens.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Amazing.
And you could say, I mean, legitimately,
Canonical and Ubuntu are a big part of the discussion
because they're showing up.
And that is.
Hey, you got me, bro.
I know, and I really appreciate that, really,
in part because of that.
Because there's not an inherent intent
to cover one company or distribution more
than the other.
Yes, the Ubuntu action show up in here.
Well, it's always going to be balanced on its dominance
in the market and the news making.
I mean, if it's legitimately making news and dominating
markets, then it's going to get coverage regardless.
But if there was other folks here,
like yourself, that are representing other distributions
and other community projects, I think
it would be good for the show.
Yeah.
Thing is, we're not as enterprisely focused
on this show, are we, as Red Hat's core is going to be.
Yeah, I appreciate that.
But that doesn't mean that we can't make something work.