I know I know a little something you guys don't know West told me before the show started that he managed to pull off a
heroic measure with one of his arch Linux systems
And I gotta give respect because both beer and I have been there you got an arch box something falls off your radar
You don't update it for weeks
Maybe even months and then it comes it comes due and you got to fix that box. Maybe even years. Yeah
Maybe what happened not quite a year is probably like nine months. I moved this laptop perfectly serviceable laptop
But right now it doesn't have a working battery. So it's like a desktop laptop. Let's call it hadn't updated, right?
So I finally set it up set it up on a desk
Started looking around. Oh, yeah, right. I was running. I had awesome set up and some other things
Couldn't install anything
But it really wasn't I had to add a update a bunch of GPG keys
I had to purge all the caches get rid of all the key stores that I had then
Work my way back through the arch home page
resolving each and want every one of the little you know
user intervention required example, but I
Mean, I've done those before I would have had to do them anyway, so it was really just paying my dues
Work just fine now. I'm really no problems. It's the GPG keys that that you really got a that was the that was the
Triggiest bit. So what does this box do? It's like a home server. No, it's just a it was another laptop that I have
Oh, okay
I was about to give you a hard time for on your home server on arch because I have been there
I do have a home server on arch my route my router runs arch you maniac
This is Linux unplugged episode 214 for September 12
Oh
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show. That's loading snaps installing sound boards and playing clips
My name is Chris. My name is what and of course the beards here. Hello beard. Hey, hello, sir
Beards fresh off rebuilding our mumble PC
I could do the show today like legitimately four minutes before the show started. I told you I timed it, right?
We got a good show today. So I'm really glad you got a fix cuz holy smokes
You've been hearing about this Equifax breach. There is a small open source story. We'll tell you about that aspect of it
Linus has got some good ideas
We'll tell you about those after we get through some community updates including some potentially new man. Jarrow hardware
Thank you. Gnome 3.26 goodness and benchmarks our replacement for Nileus and an update from Ubuntu
We're gonna get into Kali Linux for a bit. I revisited Kali Linux
I'll tell you about my adventures and why I decided to hack my IOT devices
I decided to blow off some steam and try to break all my IOT devices. You've never been very trusting anyway
So I'll tell you the tools that I used and the way you could audit your own network with Kali Linux
It's been a little while. We'll give you a little history on Kali as well. And then
at the end of the show
By popular demand you've been waiting to macOS
Pretty close to that. We'll cover the new iPhone event. No, no, no, no. No, it's the Gentoo challenge
finally
Finally after a month of waiting after absences and travel
We're gonna get to the Gentoo challenge. We've been building software for weeks and we're here to tell you how it all goes through
the roof
But before we get to all of that, we got to bring in that mumble room time appropriate greetings L mumble
Hello
Hello everybody good to have you here today. So
There's not a lot that I feel like we could add to this Equifax story
In fact our friends over there at the Techsnap program just covered it today
So that'd probably be where I would point you but at this point in time
Everybody's heard about the credit bureau here in the States getting hacked
nearly 200 million identity and really personal identification information has been stolen and
It turns out it's all open sources fault
It's all not again. It's not Equifax's fault. It's not shoddy
Network hygiene it's not poor update practices. It's not bad security auditing
It's open sources fault you I know you know about this story because you're talking about it on Techsnap sure did
So it comes down to they're simply blaming a patch Apache struts
Mm-hmm, and Apache struts is like a it's a obviously it's from the Apache projects
it's an open source offer programming model view controller like an MVC framework for Java and
it's
it is at the core a lot of these old business applications and
And
They had Equifax they Equifax hired an auditor to come in and this auditor
Discovered that they were using a version of struts that has a vulnerability
That's just recently been disclosed as of a couple of days ago, September 5th
But of course the hack happened earlier in the year
Somewhere between mid May through July
So we're not actually sure if it was this vulnerability or baby a different one that came out in March that they just never patched
again right and then those two stories are like are very different it is totally possible that at the core of its struts was the
Issue, but I'd like like your take on this West because in my opinion. Maybe I'm wrong
Maybe I'm just too much of an open source defender
But to me it seems pretty obvious you can have vulnerable software be a proprietary or open software
And it's about like an onion layered approach to security you you build your network assuming. There's going to be compromises
Yeah, I think so. I mean you're definitely right about that and while there there may be cases where you know some software open-source
Or proprietary does lead to information disclosures despite best practices being followed but before before that and like obviously we want to get this patched and
upgraded
You do have to understand some of the like what is the update hygiene patch policy Etc that Equifax is is is using?
And if that's not up to speed that is really the problem not whatever vulnerabilities may exist in the
I'm sure myriad of different open-source software that they're using yeah at the end of the day there is a there is a flaw in struts
There's right. There's a problem. No one is disputing that well plus
You know Chris the codes open so they can just look at that code and find all the vulnerabilities
Yeah, that's how it works. You just read it like you would a nice book. Yeah. Oh
I need something else to make me feel better
I need something nice like wimpy you got a new piece of hardware
I see you talking about there in the discord like that like the smallest little portable phone
I think I've seen in a long time. Do you have it with you? I?
Put it down, and I can't see it because it's so small
What what is this little thing is this is this an Android device? You've got here the jelly Android device the jelly Pro
Yep, and you have it next year to a pie zero to give us some scale in this picture Wow
Yeah, so it's about the size of a pie zero so if you imagine a business card
It's about the form factor of a business card, but a bit narrower nice
And is it is it a performant device?
It works very well. It's a quad-core
Cortex a53 it's got two gigs of RAM. It's got 16 gigs of internal storage
to SIM cards
microSD card
Wi-Fi with 2.4 and 5 gigahertz
And Bluetooth front and rear facing cameras a torch and FM radio
How did you get this is this is not even shipping yet? I?
Backed it. Oh wow, so they're so they're really on top of it there. That's great. This looks so cool
It's it's a a really nifty device. I'm
Very impressed with it. I have to say and I got mine with a few accessories and the accessories are extremely well made as well
What kind of accessories?
Well the reason I got this is because when I go out and do my walking and exercising or having a strapping a bloody great
Big you know five and a half inch phone to your arm is a bit much
This is why we and I were just talking about watches like this is almost a reason to get a watch these days
So yeah
I got this with a an armband a case with an armband and I'm gonna use this as my effectively my fitness tracker
So I've got my fitness tracker and Spotify installed on it
And this is what I'll go out and use for exercising so this thing is small enough to fit in a jeans
watch pocket
Yes, it's really small and it has to sim and an SD slot. Yep. Wow
Holy smokes
What's this thing called?
It's the my ones the jelly Pro and then there's the the smaller that well, it's not physically smaller
But there's a lower a lower spec version just called the jelly. Is it USB C?
No, it's micro USB. Okay, so almost perfect does have a headphone jack though. So it does have a headphone jack
There's something for that luxury. This thing looks so neat
It's it's actually very good. I mean, um, I'm genuinely surprised at how good it is
What about reading on that screen like the Twitter feed or a news article? Is it is it just painfully? No, it's it's perfect
It's perfectly usable. I mean you can imagine how big you know watch screens are and this is about three times the size of a watch
screen
It's quite low resolution, but it's it's remarkably good. I mean as a small device, obviously, you know
You're not going to be typing long messages into it, but you can overcome that using the you know, the voice input. So
I'm not very good at using voice but on this device you kind of use it by default for everything
Surprise, it's just it's very very good. It's a really nifty little device
I'm not sure how long I'm gonna hold on to it because my daughter's seen it and she quickly worked out
This is sort of exactly the right size. Yeah. Yeah, my son would love this too. Yeah
It's and also they're not expensive either. I think I
There are about 120 bucks. Yeah. Yeah, they have some early birds that are still available for under $100 even
Yeah, so, you know for a phone for a child that you just want them to you know
Be able to make calls and get in touch and not worry, you know, if the phone gets ruined. It's it's quite a nice device
Yeah, that is
Hmm. Hmm. And with the dual SIM when you come over to the States into into New York you could in theory
Put a ting sim in there and just pay for what you use while you're here. Yeah, I feel like that
You know, this is totally totally spontaneous, but I'm gonna mention that go to go to linux.ting.com
Just do that. Just do it right now
You know
Seriously when you come to the States and anybody else that's coming to the States that wants to be able to use their phone
And doesn't want to get totally just unless you have some amazing plan
Go to linux.ting.com when you're coming
I hear from the audience that they do this because one of the things people always give us feedback on is well ting is a
US only
Opportunity so I can't get outside the US but when you travel here Alan Alan has done this
This is this is something that I really think I wish I could do
I wish I could do the opposite of this when I leave the States
Linux dot ting comm it's a really great simple way to get easy pay for what you use wireless
You just pay for the minutes you use and the megabytes you use while you're here and there's no contract
No early termination fee you can log into the website and turn off the line
It's really nice pay for what you use nationwide coverage CDMA and GSM with a great dashboard
That's I'm gonna do like a quicker one because I didn't plan to do the ting read there
but then when I see that device, it's so it's so perfect because
You can buy this thing for a hundred bucks 140 bucks. You can put a ting sim in there
I wonder if you could switch between CDMA and GSM live too. Oh, that would be slick. Hmm
Well, that's really really cool wimpy and I'll be curious to hear your thoughts on it later
Have you tried like the built-in speaker? How's the sound on like for podcasts?
It's good enough. I mean, it's it's just it's for what it cost and its size
It's a pretty remarkable little gadget. I am I am very very happy with it. Nice
Yeah, I'm
Surprised surprised and impressed by just how good it is
I was just reading an email on here just to answer your question. Yeah, perfectly read
I assume you put telegram on there telegram performs. Okay, I haven't put telegram
I've kept it just to the things because there's only two gigs of RAM. I've just decided to keep it to the minimal
Exercising yeah, but I was thinking I I did put a 32 gig
microSD card in it and used the option to
Merge that with the internal storage. So it's now got about 40 gigs of internal storage available
You know as it reports as a a single file system, so it's um, yeah, it's pretty great, really
Yeah, I say good on you to to keep the distractions off the exercise device
That's pretty neat and it's you know cheaper than a Fitbit a decent Fitbit
So that's pretty cool the jelly the jelly smartphone
This jelly probe the smallest everybody's going big and this is the smallest and then you know like again just free free pluggy here
But you put on the ting network. That's that's two things. I like this. I like small indie stuff. That's that's cool
If you break it, it's not the end of the world. Mm-hmm. It makes me a bit jelly. Yeah
I see what you did there. I see what you did there. So Linus has an idea. How about instead of hacking Linux?
Okay, stay with me instead of hacking Linux
You join and participate, huh? You mean hack online? Yeah, whoa
Actually, you know I joke but this is legitimately an advantage that open-source software has so Linus is you may not be able to reach
Absolute security but people that deploy default models are so much better off today. We're making obvious improvements
He's talking by the way
about the kernel
Torvalds also noted that technical persons that have that have been impressed that have impressed him have been people who go after the Linux
Code there are smart people doing bad things
Yeah, yeah exactly I wish they were on our side and they could help us Torvalds said
Where I want us to go is to get as many smart people as we can before they turn to the dark side
We would improve security that way and get those who are interested in security to come to us before they attack us
That's all it would take Wes
I mean you're right that that is an advantage of open-source is that like yeah, come join us come make it better
Yeah, yeah, you know, maybe I mean you can still still exploit it on the side to make money
He's not saying that you can't do that. Just also fix it upstream afterwards. We'll save that part for the Kali Linux
Yes, right. That's right. Well, so gnome three two six lands tomorrow
I think is it this Wednesday this coming coming up? Yeah tomorrow. Yeah. Yeah, so if all goes well, which I believe it will
Yeah
By the time most people here in this show, it'll be old news, I guess
Think about that guys. That's frightening right now. We're living in the pre gnome three two six world
But the people listening they got the edge up on us. They're already in a gnome three two six world
It's just if I just pac-man a little harder. Is it well I get it now. Can I do that?
Yeah
And there's some interesting benchmarks over at Veronica
Michael larbel has posted benchmarks of gnome three dot two six on
Wayland
versus your x11 and
notes at the Wayland desktop loads slightly faster I
Like that, there's no real significant difference in memory and battery consumption between Wayland and X at this time on
the benchmarks that use Wayland directly there's no significant difference between mutter and using with modern Wayland or mutter and X org and
On benchmarks that were forced to use X Wayland
There's about a five frame per second loss using X Wayland versus straight X org. Hmm
But what struck me about this? This is my summation of reading his article. What struck me about this is
That it wasn't a huge penalty to use Wayland that it wasn't a dramatic issue to use Wayland
like we that Wayland is essentially at
Competitiveness with X org right now. Don't you think that's kind of don't I don't beer we then to me?
That seems pretty remarkable. Actually, I would have figured it would have either been way behind or way ahead
Yeah, right. I mean this it isn't in performance
This is what these benchmarks are talking about like it doesn't talk about the fact that it's missing a ton of features, right?
It's just frame rate low desktop time. Yeah, I guess I expected Wayland
I thought we'd be palin a Wayland price for sure. We'd be disappointed that it's not a lot faster
Well, that's what the Internet's taken away from this the the average internet comment reads like see I told you X works fine
That's always fine. We don't need anything else. There's this guy. He's flying around an airplane outside the studio right now
He's running excellent. He has a big banner says X org is fine. Yeah. Yeah, that's that is that is what's happening right now
And I take I take from this at least that part of the transition this
Singular isolated part of the transition to Wayland. Hopefully won't suck too bad. That's what I took from it
No, I'm three dot two six gonna be in that there Ubuntu too. I believe gonna be there then that's it is
Gonna know there's a there is a there's a negative side to 326 though
Removal of the API for the system icon. Yes, we talked we talked about it a little bit
And it's worth touching on because I don't really understand what I'm gonna do other than load the top icons extension
It's like they've forced my hand
There's actually like a weird situation where the top icons extension currently works now and will not work in the future
So they pointed out that you know in the in the post they're like, well if you're going to continue using top icon stuff
That that'll be available
Yeah, but they didn't point out in the comments that in the blog post that GTK for removes the support for what top icons
uses oh
So that it's not even gonna be possible to use type icons. It's going to be deprecated automatically. This is why I'm switching a unity
well, there's there's actually a
One to notice that and saw that that's that's going to be a going away. There is a different
Extension called case status notifier app indicator or something like that. It's it's really long. It's hot. Yeah, they
They forked that and are using that because it doesn't depend on the same API that top icons uses
That's why the new Ubuntu version has that so in theory if you in the future
You could use that extension instead of hot top icons. Okay, I
Look at I'm looking at mine right now and I see Spotify
I see Dropbox and I see Skype and I see mumble and I think out of all of those the only one that has any chance
Of updating you with any reasonable amount of time is mumble. Mm-hmm
Dropbox isn't gonna give two shits. Are they is what do you know anything about that rotten is is is this uh, I
Don't think mumble is gonna carry that I don't honestly either but if any of them was going to right, I mean, yeah
They're the best likelihood. Yes, I I think that
it's it's
It's because they're their gnome is looking at it as if because they don't like something they think something is antiquated
That means everybody else should just follow suit. Whereas, you know the platform people switch from have this incredibly
No
Long ingrained. Yeah, they're expecting this type of thing to exist and then you just remove it regardless of what people think like
Yeah, yeah, that's problematic at best. This is this is my issue now that is tempered by the fact that
Gnome 326 also has the new settings pain. Oh, yeah new redesign and excited for that more like
Mac OS 6 I know if you guys remember Mac OS 6 from the 80s
But it's more like that control panel and it's way better what what is old is new again. Yeah
That's really is but that is how computers work
It's way easier for my brain to process a list on the side and then I click it and then the you it's gonna be
More like gnome tweak, but it looks way better
and um
That's in 326. So like 326 is like a mixed bag for me because it's a good release
It's got updates to epiphany. It's got updates to gnome photos, which I just like for just basic photo viewing
But it's got this like like producer. Michael was just talking about this removal of the system tray icon support
Which every time we go through this is a huge pain in my arse and it's a constant source of questions
And it's probably like one of the top five extensions people use in the first
Yeah, I got all I got all worked up. I think was it last week about the gnome project recommending people install an extension
Yeah, no, I think are yeah, that's just they also they recommend other things too for extensions because they don't really want they don't see
So little things they want to do is default
Default it's uh, it's problematic. But if if they were managing the extensions that'd be one thing
But they just you know letting the community do it. What if someone what if they remove some api like they're doing for this?
What if they?
Just annoy someone enough where they just give up and stop maintaining them. Like I mean you're you're exactly you're setting it setting it up to fail
Do you uh when you hear stuff like this?
Do you think boy if I wasn't already using plasma as my main desktop i'd switch
Because it makes me think I got to be honest ron. It makes me think just screw this
i'm, just going to go use the plasma desktop and make it work because I was a gnome maintainer for extensions
At one point and I quit because they the example I gave people abandoning it is because I was one of them
yeah, I maintained 10 10 extensions and
Every single time there was a new update all of them broke and and there was nothing wrong with my extensions
Like they they all worked. I even adopted other extensions from other people and like fix them
And most of the time like the auto the audio input switcher like there was nothing wrong with it
It worked perfectly fine. The only thing it needed was to have a version update
so
Like the fact that that's like, you know
Not only you're not going to make a system where when it updates it's going to like check to see if it works and then
Say if it works or not and give you like a flag where you have to update it or something
Update it or something. It's just we're going to assume it's automatically broken and just break it
So like at that point where I had to update 10 and then I started getting requests from people updating stuff
and then I was like, you know, I
After about I think I tend like the most I ever had was like 16 at one release and I was like i'm i'm done
I don't i'm not trying to fix this right? Yep. And so here's where i'm at right now and um
Um, i'm kind of waiting to see but I feel like maybe as gnome grows
And as the as they move the platform forward and as they make decisions that they feel are the best that
the decisions to make for them, uh
Maybe we are moving into a world where if you're going to use the gnome desktop
You need a high level curator like canonical to come along or like fedora to come along and
Really sort of think about this stuff think about how to do the doc extension
Think about the system tray icon notification problem. Think about the theming issues
Uh, think about all of the things around that and implement it correctly
and that's really the only way to have a usable workhorse gnome desktop perhaps and
And rolling it yourself on a gentoo or an arch which we'll get to here in a moment. Um,
You know is is it's two hacked together unless you really follow this stuff
Like if you listen to every episode of this show, you could probably make it work
So yeah, I would agree with that except I would point out that fedora is on the same side as gnome as far as like
The top icons and stuff like that. They made a blog post about yeah
it was hilarious because they made a blog post about like
And these developers are not getting uh are not updating their application. What's wrong with all these developers?
They're not following the whims of the gnome team. What's wrong with them?
And I mean I do feel the alter of like they want to be able to update but
When you are shipping things that people use in a stable way
You have to do that in a non-breaking way or at least try especially hard not to like producer michael's saying
Especially when it's something that is a is like a paradigm of how you interact with your desktop. Yes
The the question then becomes for me is do I really want to be using a desktop where the developers?
Can't do that work themselves and you have to have an additional maintainer to make the desktop good. Well, at least it can be done
You know at least you can have somebody create their quote-unquote saying defaults
Yeah, maybe there's a there's another issue of what about you know, how like for a long time gnome has been like
I don't know like the powerhouse as far as like what de's are based on
but if you look at like budgie where it was
Um, there's they did announce that they're going to switch to cute and other applications other things that are switching to cute already
Like LXQT, yeah, but like if you look at the code of budgie
There's some weirdness in there like where they actually have to pretend to be gnome in certain cases. Yep
It's like so like it when you said that they were making decisions that worked best for them
It's like I think that's like the detriment to them. Yeah, maybe you know
They're trying to have a vision and they're trying to have a philosophy. And so part of this
Notification tray icons thing is that philosophy in their world?
The user never had any control
You installed that son of a bitch application and that sucker put that tray icon down there. You never asked for that
You never asked for that stupid notification or that spinning sync icon
Spinning sync icon and you you know
You really have no other way to interact with the application other than guess what that tray icon?
And so gnome wants to give the power back to the user
It's a philosophy and it's one that I can I can I can understand and appreciate
But there's a there is a practical aspect to this and it feels like they're kind of far away
Separated from like the day-to-day support concerns of someone using that right? Whereas a bunch who knows how to do that
That's a great point. So let's pause right there because that's
Damn, you just nailed it. Um, because I want to talk about what they're doing and uh,
Specifically there's a new post, uh about uh, uh gnome shell in ubuntu 1710
I'm trying to trying i'm trying to be like cautious about what I say because I don't want to give too much away because I
Really want us to roll into it. So let me start by saying thanks to linux academy for sponsoring this here show
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged. Thanks to you guys for going there and
And letting linux academy know hey on the unplugged program. I heard about you
I came here you have that in your log now, you know that they sent me and as a thank you
They'll give you a seven-day free trial linuxacademy.com slash unplugged. So why am I sending you there?
Well, it's in the name linux academy
It's a platform to teach you everything about linux created by linux enthusiasts linux professionals people that really love linux and want to spread it
people that honestly I think
Have the intention of getting more users to linux and I really could connect with that because anthony the guy that founded linux academy
I talked with him for ages before he was
An advertiser before he launched the platform just talking about how to get linux out into the hands of more people
So when they launched I was so excited
To be one of their launch partners to have a sponsorship here
I remember talking to anthony while they were building the virtualization system
That'll spin up servers on demand that match the courseware you've chosen for debian or redhat or ubuntu. They'll also do aws azure
Open stack courseware. They're really high level stuff
They'll help you focus on certifications if you need to go that route offline study is no problem at all it again
It's a real platform for this kind of stuff
It's the linux academy new to the world of linux azure and aws open stack and devops
A sharp skill set is an absolute necessity to succeed meet linux academy an online
Linux and cloud training platform that uses self-paced video courses and hands-on labs to give you real world
Experience for a wide range of skills and their community is full of jupiter broadcasting members. They're always adding new features
So that way you get the most out of your subscription linux academy.com
Slash unplugged go there and try it out seven days for free. And thank you to linux academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
Linux academy.com
Slash unplugged
so we have another post from didrocks and we've been linking to these for quite a while in the show notes and
I love this. It's the it's like a blog journey to 1710 and the decisions that they're making and this week we talk about gdm
collaboration and theming
Now i'm covering this for many reasons because uh, it's it's historical to watch canonical make the switch here on the show
Can't believe we're documenting this
Think about that for a second
Wow
Wow, it's really hitting me like right now as i'm talking to you guys. It's really hitting me that
I watched I have been podcasting
I have been podcasting since ubuntu was created
I podcasted
The announcement of unity wow brian lunduke and I covered it at linux fest that because it was news then
I remember the episode that we covered the announcement of unity
I remember watching the um
Netbook edition of ubuntu. I remember watching that be born and unity inspired from that
Gnome 3
All of it i've watched all of it and now i'm watching them transition back to ubuntu
No, and the weight of that is really hitting me as we record this episode right now
Like I am I i've really watched the transition here and I got to tell you watching them re-land back into gnome
um
If if you had asked me to make the most optimistic prediction of how they would handle this
I wouldn't have gotten it this close. I I couldn't have I couldn't have asked for a better re-landing into the gnome world
So this week we're talking about gdm. It turns out gdm
The gnome display manager that login screen that ugly login screen that runs in the background and takes up a ton of memory
It's a really a son of a bitch
Uh, it's also hard to theme and it's one of the areas where the gnome developers have been particularly protective of
Because if you're having any kind of problem in your gnome session
They don't want gdm to be affected because you got to get back to your login screen
Right so you can choose like it keeps everything running in that sense. So one of the ways that they have
Accomplished that the gnome team is they have hard coded the theme for gdm
So that way it just uses something simple and it always works
and it's
rock-solid regardless of whatever
Crazy lunatic theme you've loaded in your gnome shell your gdm session rock-solid add wadia, buddy
Unless you don't want that
Which pretty much no distro maker wants they want to re-theme gdm to make it match the login
Of course, and they want the login. I mean the desktop sessions the login session matches the desktop session. It's a big kumbaya
And it's something that i've noticed some people are commenting in the early betas of ubuntu about already the gdm theme here and there
Um, and it's something that the poppa west folks have been working on
And this is where we end up today this little problem
The guys over at system guys and gals over at system 76. They want to solve the problem of an ugly gdm
And canonical also has a problem. They want to solve they want to be able to apply their ubuntu style
Without stepping all over the toes of anybody that might be deriving off of ubuntu
And they'd like to do it in a way that is maintainable and upstreamable
And uh, I believe these two things are not 100 aligned, but they're pretty close
So it sounds like over the last couple of weeks canonical worked with system 76
Worked with jeremy over at system 76. Wow, and together they came up with a way to sort of fix this problem to sort of
Apply a patch to gdm that would work upstreams that people could change the theming
Now I don't really know I don't really you know when I start to gloss over when you start talking about applying css themes to gdm
But I do see that this is a wider problem that we've been running into for a while and
It's nice to see a proposed solution. Nothing's going to happen. Nothing's going to happen
Proposed solution. Nothing's really been accepted upstream yet
but uh
I I feel like there might be there might be a a larger ramification larger impact here, which i'll get to in a moment, but
uh
wimpy if your ears are burning because i've missed or i've gotten something wrong if you want to jump in with any corrections at
This point probably a good chance before I keep going
Well, you have me a disadvantage actually because i've i've been away. Oh, yeah for a while
So, um, I haven't had the chance to catch up with my colleagues and so let me wrap this real quick
And let's talk about that. So, uh, uh short the short version of this is is that diddler and uh,
And jeremy are working together to come up with an upstreamable version where patches can be applied where people won't be stepping on each other's toes
Uh, I I will save my commentary for now on how this could be our first example of pop os
Development colliding with the wider ubuntu development. I'll save that for future commentary because i'd love to hear about
Wimpy's trip to perry. He just got yeah. Yeah, I saw some I saw some
Once in a lifetime selfies come across wimpy's twitter feed over the last week
I've got to go find those because you know, whenever you can get the eiffel tower in your selfie
That's a that is a rather good selfie. So where were you wimpy?
Uh, well, we were in paris so and we were at uh ubucon europe
Uh, which was being hosted by the french
loco
At a massive museum, uh in paris
That is too cool. That sounds awesome
Ubucon ubucon boy all these conferences you got new york coming up soon. You got paris. You are a world traveler wimpy
Yeah, so ubucon is an entirely community
Um created event and they happen
all over the world and different
Locos and lugs and what have you organized these events around the world. So when the ubucon happens in
uh, california, it's usually
Coinciding with scale and happening at the same
Venue, um, you know a day or so beforehand. Yeah
Uh, but this one's just a standalone
This was um
Yeah, it was um, it was a four day four day event
um
so it started when it was a a three day event for the ubucon, but there was um
Um, I sort of a get together the day before it started with sort of the um, the core organizers
um to come together
Uh and sort of, you know, make sure they were all set and ready to go
Uh, and we were fortunate enough to be there and catch up with them that evening and some of the early arrivers
uh, some of you know our friends from the ubuntu community from around europe and it's you know, great to catch up and socialize so
you know during the day it's um,
tracks of talks and workshops and um
Uh, there's even a gaming room set up, you know with pcs with games running and all the rest of it
um and rooms with
All the audio equipment. So, um the various podcasters can go and record, you know live podcasts and what have you
So there's you did right? Yeah, so poppy and I participated in two podcasts whilst we were there
We um, we both appeared on the on the spanish podcast and then we were part of
a podcasting panel so we had um
Uh the guys from lubuntu podcast in france poppy and I from ubuntu podcast
I don't know the name but the I think it's um ubuntu podcast portugal and then ubuntu fun
so there were six or seven of us
and sort of um
Scripted by the german guys, you know, we had some show notes and then very much ad hoc
In front of um a live audience. That sounds like a lot of fun. It's always good fun. Yeah
That's some fun. I uh, so I was inspired by a slide that uh
It was from a talk that I think dustin kirkland was giving at ubicon where he listed like the top 10 features
Uh or the top 10 new features for ubuntu 1710
And I wanted to take that list. I want to I want to put it in text somewhere
So I want to I actually kind of like to get your your take on it
But I expanded on the list and I actually think is I already have more features to add to it
But let me know if i'm missing anything. So 1710
Um, and I I want to I want to preface before I say this i'm
I don't have any skin in the game. Uh right now I run solace the machine to my left
runs
Arch the machine the next machine to my left runs arch. What are you running right there to my right?
This is running arch. Okay, so we have and then we have two arch systems upstairs
We have an arch server here and a proxmox server
The only ubuntu system in the jupyter broadcasting studio is the one running the mumble machine that noah installed
So I don't I don't have like an agenda here. I don't have any there's nobody paying me to say this
No agenda, but i'm going to say that I will say this
um
I would ask both of you and anyone in the mumble room to tell me what what distribution release
Has ever had a feature list like this and I haven't even added all of them yet
This is what I have right now the top 14 new features for ubuntu 1710
And gnome replaces unity number one, obviously
Tons of bluetooth improvements a thousand bug fixes a new blue z stack
number three
Switch to lib input number four improved 4k multi-monitor and scaling
Technology support we've talked about that high dpi improvements number five upgraded to network manager 1.8 much improvement big improvement
There number six new sub sub equity equity, whatever. It's the zoo server installer
Number seven is the minimal images 36 megabyte 20 smaller images huge. That's a huge that's a huge savings
Number eight finally for fuck's sake auto remove of old kernels from slash boot
Number nine extended for encryption with fs encrypt number 10 improved cuda and cpu acceleration support
And this one i'm i'm feeling like could almost be two but i'm including hardware accelerated codecs in that one
Hardware accelerated codecs
I'm going to say it one more time hardware accelerated codecs. Just going to mention that
Uh new doc that we've talked about with the upstream collaboration the gschema support for uh
Elegantly handling settings changes and disappearing when you turn on dash to dock and now with the status icon support, which is great
Net plan by default switching from if config is number 12 number 13 is gcc7 out of the box
And number 14 is wayland by default and number 15
Which I don't have on the list yet because it hasn't happened yet because all of these have happened
All of these have happened what is about to happen?
What is about to happen potentially is kernel 4.13 as well, which will be feature 15
And i'll have a top 15 list for ubuntu 17 10
Now I haven't seen anybody put a list together quite consecutively like dustin did now i've built off of dustin's list here
But I challenge you to tell me one other release of any linux distro
Ever since you've been following linux that has been this packed full of features and this big of a change
Hmm chris, I can't think of one dude. I can't either. Like this is this is big. This is really big
And this is this is in the middle of a company restructuring
Reorganizing of the company
Like there are some companies where that would put them on their back heels for a year just to sort that shit out
Well, I gotta be honest chris I have been through distro after distro lfs as you know, uh, gen 2
Arch the whole nine yards and I gotta say
I'm more impressed with this new ubuntu spin than all of that. Yeah
Yeah, it is and that's and I haven't even finished the list yet. No, you haven't
You know
I can think of things with individual components like maybe system d switch or other things that were that were of similar scale
but these is a
It's a far-ranging set of changes. This isn't even the lts like if all this stuff is decent in 17 10
All this stuff just has to be even decent in 1804 for the lts to be great
Like yeah, but that's that's exactly the fact. I have to test it for the lts
I mean you can't introduce these to the lts. You have to test them first
It's the way to do it though. It is it's a classic ubuntu style development approach. It's a tried and true method
So if I can just add to to that list, yeah
the
Um dustin gave a couple of presentations whilst he was at ubicom
Um, and the slide that you've used there was from he was doing the closing keynote
So he did the the keynote that that that that wrapped up the event
and
What he was presenting
was all of the feedback that had been captured from those various user surveys that
That he's been running
Through hacker news and reddit and slash dot and omg ubuntu
And all of those things that were on um, dustin's slide
Were the top thing so they he did a whole load of natural language processing to actually figure out what people were asking for
and basically
Everything that was in dustin's slide were the top things that people were asking for
And therefore they got addressed in this cycle
So that was the the crux of his presentation in that your feedback is important and matters to us
And here's us
Actioning the things that are most important to you. I i'm not going to name names of other distros
There has been distro releases recently
where legitimately the new wallpaper is
Part of the release notes because that's like the the minimal amount of change
um
I I just I really am impressed. I am really impressed like when
When when mark made his initial initial announcement, I just was having a conversation with somebody about this yesterday
That's somebody being michael dominic when mark made his announcement that uh canonical was done with unity and that ubuntu would be shipping
gnome, I think a lot of people walked away with the impression that it was sort of like a
Wiping the hands. We're just gonna we're just gonna give you a stock gnome. We're not gonna bother with it and uh have at it
That the desktop wasn't being focused anymore. Hope you enjoy your stock gnome. We're done and uh,
I I just I
I have a I have a loose appreciation from the outside of the amount of work that must have gone into this
Which means it must have been 10 times the amount of work that i'm picturing
So it was anything but that it was the opposite of what a lot of people were pontificating was the end of the ubuntu desktop
It's uh, yes, and that's top 14 new features that like are worth like talking about how many of those are like server?
Features, right? There's a lot of stuff here that shows like they they're they still care
They are innovating on these things right and seeing this kind of feedback cycle and work that's exciting, too
And one of the reasons i'm excited for kernel 413, which is on target, you know
We it's not locked in yet, but it's on target for 1710 is it's got the baked in mainlined app armor support
So it's like it's sort of like a
It's like it's sort of like a coming of age in a way for app armor
which snap confinement's based on which is the which is the
mandatory access control horse that both susa and ubuntu have bet on
And it's my preferred out of s between se linux and app armor
Having worked with both of them production. I clearly understand app armor and se linux
I just sort of funnel my way through and so if I had to implement one I would prefer to use app armor
So talking about the kernel as of yesterday 413 is in the proposed pocket
That's awesome. Yeah, that is I will update that list
I can't I'm holding that as my 15th feature to add to the list because that's okay
Well the one to add alongside network manager is in addition to network manager 1.8
The captive portal stuff is enabled and fully working now and lots of people were making good use of that
Um at ubu con because everything was behind a captive portal and it was kind of fun to see them all sort of
Blinking and then grinning at the captive portal screen just popping up when they joined the wi-fi networks
I have no idea what to expect network wise while i'm in new york
Uh, we're trying to decide if if we should try to do user air from the hotel room while we're in new york
So no one we're gonna be there should I think so?
I but we just don't have we have no idea what the connectivity is gonna be
You know, I wish there was a way like we need like a database. Mm-hmm has a captcha
Has you know requires you use their dns like well all these like little qualifiers, you know, google has this database
They just don't share it with us
So getting that built in into network manager or is it is a part of network manager wimpy or is it a component?
Alongside a network manager. I wasn't clear. Yeah, so there's there's two pieces to it. There's um a component in network manager that needs to be enabled
um that actually does the um detection of
Of um, you know your connectivity state and whether you're behind a captive portal or not
um and that that emits, um
over dbus and then there's
a component that's
Hardwired to the gnome shell that then looks at that to determine what the network status is and when it
Picks up the signal that you're behind a captive portal
It fires open a web view and takes you to that captive portal brilliant. I really will appreciate that
That's become very important recently in my life
um now I got oh go ahead I will just say because
Let's just get this out of the way because there are people that care about this stuff
In order for that to work. It has to ping some known host in order to look for various status. Oh sure. Yep
Okay, and that's connectivitycheck.abuntu.com
abuntu.com
In the privacy settings for abuntu 1710 is the option to disable
That connectivity check so if you don't want it to leak, you know stuff
Um, then you can just disable that and you will have no captive portal automatic detection
And if you want to run like that an interesting feature I noticed in firefox
Which I don't know when it cropped up, but i'm told fairly recently
If you open firefox and it's behind a captive portal firefox detects that now and prompts you accordingly as well
That's nice. That is really nice. That has been something that has kind of been wonky on some setups in the past and
Really hurts inexperienced users. I think so. I have two more items now that you're here wimpy
Just that I would love to chat with you about
um i'd love to sort of back our way into 1710 matte edition of abuntu here because
Um, I know that there is a big feature for me
That uh, I loved when I was on the unity desktop that has made its way into abuntu matte 1710
And I don't know if you saw the feedback
I imagine you must get all kinds of different feedback for this stuff
But one thing that I saw people talking about which seemed really misinformed was well now I have to drop matte because it's just
Adding all of the bulk and cruft that modern desktops have and what i'm alluding to is pretty much full-on
And correct me if i'm wrong full-fledged hud support like we had in unity 7
Unity 7 in abuntu matte
If you go with the mutiny theme you turn on hud support you turn on compiz
You're getting really close to where you were with unity 7 and it's got certain people certain neck beards
Upset and so I got this email from this guy who says that he's switching now to xfce
Because matte is getting too bloated
So I thought maybe if you explained a little bit of how hud works
About how what what what talks to hud and how that all happens and maybe help people understand how it's not a bunch of bloat
And tell people what the feature is
Well, the feature is the ability to search the menus
So, you know your file edit view tools help menus that you see in all of your applications
It's the ability to search through those so you hit the alt key
An overlay appears and you start typing to filter down
What features of the menus you want to see you could type print for example?
Instead of having to go grab your mouse go to file go down to print
You could just keep your hands on the keyboard and type in print and that would come up
Yeah, and it's particularly useful for applications that have lots of filters. So audio editors, um, you know the office suites and
inkscape and
Gimp, yeah, you know when when there are no convenient key bindings to complex filters. It's a great way to find them very quickly
Now behind the scenes the way this all works is through um, gtk models
model menu and some dbus services, um, and
What's providing that dbus registrar is the new global menu?
So the global menu provides that dbus registrar and then we also
Load a gtk module which is called unity gtk module
Which is kind of a misnomer
What it's actually doing is providing the app menu model stuff
It's got very little to do with unity itself. And so to just sort of clarify your point there a bit
What's happening is these menu options are being exposed via dbus. So it's not like there's some
Global scraper running in the background that's reading all of the menus of every application
The applications are advertising these features to dbus dbus then enumerates that to the hud and
That's already happening in the background regardless. It's not a big bulk out of processing, correct?
Yeah, and if and if you run one of the themes that doesn't use the global menu, then none of that stuff is there
Anyways, none of that stuff is resident in memory. Okay. Okay
Now what I would say is if you
Really feel that that is an unacceptable additional
amount of memory and it's
Not much by the way
Then fine run libuntu run zebuntu go elsewhere. That's absolutely fine
From the very first day that we created a buntu mate. I have an objective in the
In the objectives of the project
the application choices would
feature feature rich
Applications and wouldn't um chase after lightness or whimsy. Mm-hmm
and
Ubuntu mate still runs on a raspberry pi with one gig of ram
If you've got less than one gig of ram and you're upset that ubuntu mate doesn't run well in you know
One gig of ram then fine go elsewhere. I that's absolutely fine by me. I think it's a perfect balance
I think the I think the project I mean is
Is constantly evaluating this question and striking such a good balance between modern-day desktop features and a traditional computing paradigm
It's it's with as much as I talk about 1710 right now
I'm not necessarily sold on running straight ubuntu 1710
I'm also heavily considering giving the ubuntu mate spin a try simply for all of these little added extra perks here
How is the how's the new alpha been received by the community?
How's the new alpha been received by the community? Uh, very
Very well, it's beta one now, right? It's it's beta one. Yeah, um, I did a presentation about it at ubucon
It was very well received. Um, yeah, uh and where I was also um when I was at ubucon
The etienne is our new qa lead
He's been involved in the project for some considerable time but has recently taken on the role of qa lead
Oh congrats, and he lives in france. So he made the trek up from the south of france to paris
And we met for the first time over the weekend. Oh, very good and spent some time together planning
So that was really great, you know to to meet people on a project who you know, you've not met in person
Um, I absolutely love that. That's one of the reasons i'm looking forward to going to new york
Yeah, and this thing about you know, i'm gonna rage quit a particular distro
Um fine, but the thing is is you're talking about leaving a distribution where all of these options are options
And you could just use a different, you know, we've preserved that traditional layout the the as granddad remembers it to panel layout
That has been there forever with gnome 2 is still the default layout
Yeah, and it doesn't use indicators and it doesn't use the hud and it doesn't use compiz or any of this stuff
So I don't understand the rationale for right i'm rage quitting because it's got all of this stuff
Yeah, but I have to go and turn on that is not default. It's crazy talk. Yeah. Yeah, I agree
All right. So the second item I have before you can uh before you can stop talking so much is uh, this is all
This is your fault just as I was coming to closure
On the lais and one. Oh, yeah, just as I was getting to some sort of peace with that
You tease me with mail spring, which isn't actually available for download yet. No, but it is a fork of nalaya's mail now
Wes, I know uh, you myself wimpy. We've we've been a little community here
We've been big nalaya's users in the past and then they announced that they were shutting that ass down turns out their api
Makes them a bunch more dough. I guess. Yeah. Yeah, so wimpy found uh, mail spring at get mail spring.com. Say hello
Say hello. I'm kind of looking forward to this looks nice though. Yeah, it has essentially all the same features that you came to love
And expect uh from the lais it has uh, the really creepy but yet advanced and surprisingly useful open tracking features
I don't know about self-hosted or any of that
Uh, but i'm thinking about signing up none of that. None of that self-hosting is required. So nihilus mail
Um or nihilus n1 was the original mail client
Mm-hmm that used all of the cloud services to do all of the mail syncing, right?
The nihilus mail which was the open source was more like an offline had that sync engine integrated locally
So you didn't have to go elsewhere
now what's interesting about uh, get mail spring is that um
Ben gotto who was one of the original members of the nihilus mail team, right?
Right. His company is now stewarding this fork
And he was the principal developer of nihilus mail. That is interesting, isn't it?
Yeah, and what they're already doing is they're like reworking that sync engine
So the sync engine was written in java script
I imagine node and they've already replaced it with a new sync engine which is implemented in c++
Plus and they're claiming that it's uses 50 less ram and it's considerably
faster and
improves battery endurance
So it looks like they're trying to get all that new that
refactored sync engine integrated before they
They make uh make it available for download
but i've i've already signed up to this to
Stay informed of developments and i'm very very interested to see how this pans out. I'm thinking about doing the same
I I I really I really liked nihilus mail specifically in one but nihilus mail, too. So i'm thinking about doing the same
What do you think wes you you think it's possible? Maybe like a new hope. Maybe it's a new hope wes
Yeah, well, I mean I appreciate a lot of what what they had done and having a bunch of this all be open source anyway
Yeah, right like why not? This is this is what we continually talk about as being an advantage
So if there's even a shot that it works out for us i'm i'm on board i'm I wouldn't uh, I
I'm
Not always in favor of c++ strictly better than node or not
But if it's actually faster and more performant, it seems like they are like what I got out of those summaries is
Like a you know craftsmanship and a care and a loving tuning that I would love to see
Um, and uh, I think it's it's a good sign that it's one of the original authors. Mm-hmm
Um, thanks for pointing out to me. Yeah. Yeah, I can't wait to see how this develops. Um, because
Uh nihilus was the great white hope for the you know, the the new generation of mail clients pretty mail clients
And I I was only saying, uh to poppy a few days ago, you know when when these projects die somebody, you know
There's usually like, you know five or six rage forks immediately afterwards and there was none of that with nihilus
Probably because it's a complex code base and then I saw this and I was like, yes, this is this is what we wanted
I know it sounds you're saying it sounds kind of silly but I I
I really got my head around email for a few months there like I haven't for years and after they announced they were killing it
Off I switched back to my traditional like webmail thunderbird kmail combo, which is horrible and um,
I don't I don't think i've opened my inbox this week
Because I've just been when I get busy like that without the ability to see the thing that nihilus gave me was
Two things that were so great was the I snooze for later
So I could set a reminder and I could come back to it so I could I could clear them out of my inbox
But but get back to them
and the other thing that I found super useful was it's surprising the the
creepiness and and
Well done implementation of tracking they had where they had some sort of server-side component
With embedded code that was really good at at detecting when you opened the email
Which is an incredible indicator for when you're about to get an email it turns out
And this is what I learned after using and one was that almost everyone who emails me on a reoccurring basis
Opens the last email that they got from me and just hits reply and changes the subject deletes the body and sends me an email
Like everybody does that. I thought that was just something I did
Everybody does that and so what happens is when they open up the old email I get a notification
And I know in about five minutes. I'm gonna get an email from a sponsor
And so I know this sounds dumb, but I can mentally prepare myself for that communication
I can I can like clear psychologically clear my schedule, okay?
I'm gonna respond to this. I'm gonna think about this and I actually was getting email done
It was a couple of just snoozing and really good notifications
Snoozing and really good notifications. Um, yeah, I really loved it. So i'd love to see a fork
You know i'm gonna be watching that with some some interest
We'll have a link to that the show notes if you want to check it out
I have a quick mention before we move on with cheese. We still have oh my gosh
We still have backtrack and the gen 2 challenge to get to wow. Oh my gosh jam packed
This is a lot going on. Um, so just a quick mention. I wish we could quick now
I wish we could spend more time on this. Uh, the mangero project is happy i'm sure I would assume
To announce that they got an oem
To ship a laptop pre-installed with mangero
xfce edition, so uh
There you go, joe
It's good for you. Uh, and it's uh, it's the spitfire mangero special edition
It's powered with a seventh generation intel processor 32 gigabytes of them rams
dual drive bays and um, it can
Pretty much probably take whatever you throw at it's got a 1080p ips display. We don't talk much about mangero
I mean, I haven't used it for a while
Yeah, well, you know, uh growing up. My grandma always told me if you ain't got nothing nice nothing nice to say
I can't even I I um
Yeah, i'm not a big mangero advocate. I don't we don't review mangero very often
I don't talk about mangero, but I know there's a portion of our audience that that definitely has had success with it
So I and I mean they seem like they have a fair amount of momentum
They've got their own community going which is great
I this is why I thought we could have made a segment out of this because to be honest with you
It feels like a trend
Distributions more and more are starting to ink deals
I think probably the most prominent and successful one is the entryware about to
Mountain one because to me that's sort of like the best of both worlds great hardware great company great distro
Uh, and you're starting to see elementary os with different trying and solace rumors and all this all these things that seem to be brewing
And it seems that all of them sort of have one common denominator and it's clevo
And I think that's the enabling technology here because clevo is providing the base platform of the laptop
uh, the
Oems can then focus on the software implementations a bit more
And so what you are getting and it's going to take a little while for the consumers to catch up
I would think except for our audience is you're going to get different levels of implementation
So you're going to have some clevo resellers that have a really solid implementation. They really have nailed the firmware issues
They've nailed compatibility issues. They've worked back and forth with clevo
Maybe they even have some leverage
I wonder if at some point we'll see like a clevo competitor
so that
so
Yeah, I was I was going to say
It's not always clevo undoubtedly clevo features
Is could you give me an example of one that's not clevo?
uh
The first couple of generations of the entra where apollo were top star. Yeah top star. Uh, but this one is clevo
Uh, the current generation is yes. No, no, no, I mean, yeah, sorry. No, I mean the station x the the mangero spitfire
Is um, i'm not familiar with what what's being shipped there, but it could be it looks i'm just saying that yes
It's the these linux oems are not
Absolutely always clevo. Okay quite often they are but there are other odms that get used as well. Yeah. Okay. That's a fair point
I think that's a fair point. I think this one is this one. Um, I can't remember
I I got the clevo make at one point, but i'm pretty sure I I tracked it down to a particular clevo make which is
similar to probably the
Apollo galago line of machines i'm not I I to me I feel like that's um
Um that only matters in so much as how good is the oem at doing the implementation? Yes
What kind of constraints does that put on the whole process and you can't get around obviously do you like the clevo hardware?
Like that's a component some people do some people don't that's fine. Yeah, um, but I do feel like these odms
top star or
clevo or whoever are making it possible for
distributions to offer a out-of-the-box distribution experience so instead of
Of buying a box of cds now you can buy a laptop
And how long did we talk about how that that was important for the linux desktop, right?
Even if it's not the hardware we want or even the distribution we want
It's certainly a different category than I have to buy and hope that this will work
Yeah, and it you know, if you think about it in terms of selling a box set of dvds
I used to buy the susa box set. It was like six discs
Um, you know, I used to get the free cd from uh, ubuntu
Um, man, jero and mandrake was mini disc. This is kind of like that same thing. Don't you think?
What and what's important about this is that you know, we've we've said for years and years and years
The reason why linux isn't more widespread is because you can't go into brick and mortar stores and buy it
Yeah
Now the next best thing to that is having online retailers that make it available
Um, and you know, we've seen a number of these
Uh linux vendors popping up recently particularly in the uk
um, obviously intro where i've been around for some years now, uh, but we've had
Station x star labs and I think this one called nimbu or something like that
So there's been three pop up in the uk in you know, quite quick succession
And then another one that i've known about in spain
But um had the good fortune to meet at ubucon this weekend is slimbook
And they have some very very nice gear
That they had on show and there were lots of us and ours and lots of people saying i'm going to struggle not to buy
One of these they had some really terrific kit
Um and chassis that i've not seen before so I don't know where they're coming from, but they're really impressive
That's exciting. And and they're the company that are providing that kde neon book
Oh, yeah, very good
huh, okay, so
This the more we talk about it. Um, I I not only did I see this taking off more and more
But I can also kind of understand why system 76 feels compelled to ship pop os imagine if they had
Um an inside track or they saw the way this thing was blowing
This wind was blowing this direction where you're going to start having super specialized
you're going to have solace laptops and elementary os laptops and
ubuntu mattei laptops and mangero laptops
and
Then you're going to have the large vendors like hp and lenovo and of course dell
shipping stock ubuntu
So they don't have that extra value add area
There's a gap there. I can see the logic path. However
My my counter argument to that would have been there's still a market for somebody to do a really rock-solid
Vanilla ubuntu implementation because at the end of the day that's going to sell way more than any of these things do
Probably combined especially with what we were just talking about like customer feedback. Like
I like I have no problems with dell but like
Close customer feedback about software design is not something that they have a ton of experience with compared to say
Let's like system 76 is a little bit closer with their customer base. I would say yeah, and I could so you can see that
That path. Yeah, you know, you look skeptical beard. No, I was just gonna say it's still really interesting to me that it's
It's manjaro that's coming out with a laptop. Like if I made a list they'd be pretty far down on who I would have expected
To come out with the laptop. I guess that's who you know, right? Yeah, I guess
Because you could see like certain distributions
Well, I guess yeah, are you implying that maybe it's it's uh implying
More growth to manjaro than we realize is that what you're saying? Like maybe there's maybe there's more going on than we realize
like
I I feel like they they must think that they have a fairly large user base if they're coming up with hardware now
Yeah, I mean they gotta figure they're not just manjaro, but whoever's shipping the laptops must think they have enough user base as well
That's it is it is that statement, isn't it? It's the they somebody did the business math here
So it's now time for the manjaro challenge. So where's my integrus laptop? Yeah
Well, but that's the thing. I mean the thing is is that you know, there are lots of people using arch linux
Or so the internet would have you believe
Yes, it would I
I would suggest that most of those people that say they're running arch linux have either installed antergos or manjaro
There are probably very few actually installing arch
Do you think that's true? I mean really though wimpy because once you install arch
You don't really have to install it again
Like it's just installed and it can be installed for a very so you can install it once six years ago
And then have you ever installed arch linux? Yes. Yeah, I have and I would say it you have have you yeah
You've not always just installed and gen 2 and gen 2 but I always I will I will grant you
That if I were if I were in the last two years going to install arch
I would absolutely go integros and not even consider going stock arch. It's just why waste the time
My point exactly it's all about time. Yeah. Yeah. Okay fair enough fair enough
I always just boot into an integros live cd and then install stock arch really? Yeah
because then you have a gooey you have chrome or whatever and but otherwise I can install everything in antergos and like
Two pacman commands if I was going to do it today if I for some
Reason wanted to install stock arch today. That's probably maybe how I would do it if I was going to think about it
Huh?
It's just I think you're right wimpy is it really is. Uh, it really is like uh, it's
Now it's a it's a badge of honor in a sense on the internet to run arch and so everybody proclaims they run arch
But maybe the most maybe you're right. Maybe the majority of them are really mangero users. Maybe they're all mangero users
That's not arch
I mean, I hate to be that guy. I hate to be that guy because I hate that guy
I hate that guy when you're like looking for a problem. He's like, oh you're using mangero. Sorry can't help but it's not arch
I can't believe that mangero has more users than antergos though
It's been around longer
No, not by much. Yeah, but you remember people used to really buy into that mangero is tested arch thing for like years
Yeah, like they have the delayed release. Yeah people that always pushed me away from it though
Well, yeah, because if you thought about it for more than 30 seconds, of course it would but people that didn't think about it
That that sounds like yeah arch but tested like debian does well shit
I'll put that on my rig. I mean, you know, if you hear it like that, that sounds good
It's like arch but all that. Yeah, but then when you you know, yeah, of course if they only have maybe 3000 people running the testing version
It doesn't really do anything other than just slow down the updates. That seems like a bad idea, but that takes 30 seconds
I feel like we're suddenly crapping on mangero and I feel bad
Yeah, I mean, you know, you're right if you have nothing to say we should be celebrating
We should their glorious success of getting an oem behind. Yeah, because it's a big deal for any
Validation and it's a big deal for linux because it means you know, we've we we saw those
Uh net craft is it net data? Yep, statistics three point something percent. Uh linux uses a growing trend there
There is obviously a growing market for these oems to sell linux devices and linux laptops
And we should be applauding that and encouraging it because it doesn't actually matter what distro is being sold. That's one more
laptop
One more person joining us and one less of them and more resources spent like getting
Getting firmware getting polish ironed out things that are in theory somewhat portable to whatever you want to run one
You know you think about two the other the other net effect
This is having is it's another reseller who is pulling on clevo to support linux better. So
There could be a come because of this because of this market now
There could become a point where clevo is one of the best supported
Out there because they got all these people selling clevo machines
And I know that some of these oems that are using you know
The likes of um clevo are starting to talk to the firmware update guys to actually get these
You know the firmware and bios for these devices
Supported by gnome software and firmware update
So, you know if this trend grows there'll be more people putting more pressure on these odms
to
Release their bios and firmware
under licenses, um or agreements that enable these things to go into these public repositories so they can
benefit from automatic updates and we don't have to be like barbarians booting off, you know
Yeah, yes, this is a serious
This is a serious tip of the hat to the managerial project because like we said earlier somebody did the business math here
And decided it was worth their time which is a real validation to the project
This is the kind of like real supply chain
Like you were just saying like the supply chain stuff that will make longer term change that is very different than just
You know some software. I want to know your thoughts wimpy though on them choosing to do a customized xfce spin
That's been quote unquote tailored for the hardware
I don't know anything about xfce. So you're asking the wrong guy. I'm sorry. What do you think? I mean, really?
What do you think it means to say? Why why xfce? What's that about? Is that a mangero thing?
I thought that was the default desktop for mangero. Maybe I thought only masochists use xfce
I can't I can't I can't joe's not listening. You do know one. Yeah
I can't you know, you spot you thought of speaking of speaking of joe the market research
Uh, I did a little digging for linux action news a couple episodes one episode ago and uh got some of the
Insk got some of the information behind where that market share number came from
And um why we hear about it from time to time and how many sites are involved in that information
So I would recommend you check out recent episodes of linux action news
I think it was 16, but that's off the top of my head
Where I kind of did a little deep dive into where that three percent number is coming from
It's actually um
Of course i'm saying this but uh, I actually think that three percent number is low
And I only and I I say that I say that after I researched how they're getting to the number
And once I realized how they're getting to the number i'm pretty confident, but I don't know of course
But i'm pretty confident saying that it's low and you you think so too wimpy. Well, pauline hub tells us so so
Yeah, well, yeah. Oh my god
Oh, yeah, well, yeah. Oh my god
Okay, so it's true they publish the stats every year
We've got significantly more perverts than three percent. Well, let's be honest. I mean, it's a great platform for porn
We've said that before it truly is
It's the best platform for porn as far as i'm concerned
Because and I think uh, you know porn shops have been good to linux running linux servers on the back end serving tons of video
Absolutely, the server side the infrastructure side and the fact that we don't launch executables has been really great for
linux, yes
Oh man, well there's be safe everybody
This is the more you know on the unplug program
Okay, so we have many things still to get to I don't know if this is going to work
Uh, but we I do I I spent some time to blowing off some steam this week
Uh, I got a lot going on. I got a lot. I got a lot in my head
I got a lot i'm trying to figure out and I thought what better way to focus all of this random energy
Than to try to break my tp link and belkin, uh smart devices turns out my tp links run a 26 kernel
linux 26
Yeah, yeah, so I had some fun and uh, what is this 2005?
Kali linux, we're finally going to talk about it. We should have we really should have led with this
I didn't really we just kind of meandered this whole episode
Uh, but we're going to talk about kali linux here in a moment. But first, let's take a moment and get real
Let's get real about digital ocean go to digital ocean.com
And use our promo code do unplugged. It's one word after you create your account. This will give you a $10 credit
You can spin up a server. It could be a buntu. It could be fedora can even be free bsd or centos or debian
I mean
Do you have any free bsd droplets beard?
Hmm, why would anybody do that? Yeah, I don't know. I mean wes would you have any reason for a free bsd droplet?
Well, maybe you want to run some jails. That'd be a great way to run like yeah
I guess if you want end-to-end zfs, I just prefer the industry standard docker on my uh, on my uh industry standard abuntu
I mean, I just me, you know, it's just me wes
I don't I don't know why I am still needling the bsd now guys and I don't know why it's like
It's just something I just it's in your blood
Now this is my moment in the show to needle the bsd now guys and I take it almost every week
I take it almost every week
But anyways, we're gonna catch you with the net bsd droplet someday and you are gonna have so much shame
You know chris is probably because i'm bsc now. They need a less. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, that's true. That's true
Why would anybody install linux? Uh, I was just gonna say, uh digital ocean has been saving my bacon recently
I spun it up by droplet to run open vpn
And that's been very very very handy, but uh, i'll save that for another story because I believe uh, mr
wimpy has one from the
ubucon ubucon
Yeah, I do
Poppy and I did a couple of snapcraft workshops at ubucon as one does
One on the saturday one on the sunday
And we went into a classroom and it wasn't set up the way we needed
so we span up a bunch of do droplets and
configured all of the course material on it and we did it all with do ctl
And a simple script to go and zap all of the machines with what we needed and we ran our classrooms off do droplets
Ah, very good. That's nice. And then afterwards do you destroy them or do you still have them just destroyed them?
Yeah, and it cost us a few pennies to run, you know
Several hours of classes on on dozens of droplets that reminds me of the time that uh, just this last linux fest northwest
I think it was this last one. I can't remember if this was the event
But during the live stream we spun up a digital ocean droplet transferred some stuff over to it
And then when we were done we destroyed it
And it's I it's I don't know there's something about that
This feels ultimately powerful
Like it's really a lot of incredible compute power
On demand and you can spin it up and you can use it and you can run your linux that you like to use
And there's great documentation and a simple dashboard and an elegant api and they got data centers everywhere
And it's just available to you when you need it
If it makes you feel a little bit like tony stark and I I just love it if you use our promo code
Do unplugged one word you get the ten dollar credit and then you can play around
Run like the three cents an hour machine with our ten dollar credit
It's great digital ocean.com use the promo code do unplugged after you have created your account over digital ocean.com. And by the way
In their community documentation section
They have a new tutorial on I guess it's really an introduction to load testing your box
So if you want to test network latency cpu memory disk io all that kind of stuff
They got a really great tutorial on it and it's it's applicable to anybody running linux
But it's just an example of the value that they add to digital ocean users too
Because obviously it's applicable to digital ocean droplets. I want to give a challenge to the community chris. Oh, yeah, I want them
to
Come up with things
To do with a digital ocean api that nobody's ever thought of. Ooh, that would be good
I want to see ridiculous things like stuff. They never plan for yeah digital ocean.com create the account that user promo code do unplugged one word
now
Finally, let's talk about kali linux
And I feel like the only way to appropriately talk about kali linux would be to talk about backtrack linux because last time you and I
spoke about this audience
We were really talking about backtrack linux and it was a solid distribution
People came together and they created something that was kind of unique. It was kind of the
uh smashing together of slacks and
Opix
And then they would sort of smash it together and do these big releases with all these kind of features and I really loved it
um
Full disclosure. I I used it professionally to make a living for a while. So obviously i'm a little biased about backtrack, but loved it back
Really was a great tool and um, but but things move on people move on projects change and they later on down the road decided to
Essentially change things up and rebase
And they rebased on debian
And around this time they launched and they called it kali linux
and kali linux is a
Penetration testing distribution that's targeted towards ethical hackers. So let's crack open a beer here
and talk a little bit about kali linux because this week I was having some fun and I
I want to say there's a few different ways you can use kali linux you
Surprisingly could legitimately use it as your desktop distribution gnome 3. They've got a couple of extensions installed like the applications menu
In fact wes if you want
This thing right here I was running it this week on the i'm going to turn on you see
Let's see if the studio cams working because if I don't know if it is or not because I want people to find out
I want people to see this thing here. So i've got it here on the dell precision 7720 laptop massive, which is just a
Monster and the thing about this laptop is it reminds me a lot of the bonobo that I had back in the day
When I was doing penetration testing
And uh, so here wes i've got this is oh, yeah
This is kali linux running off of the live uh thumb drive there and take a look at like the application menu stuff and whatnot
It's um, you could just use that as your daily driver. I'm running gnome here. It's not bad
Yeah, gnome 3 and they also have uh support for vmware. They have in fact vm kernel 4.9. Yeah
Yeah, it's you know, it's they got vmware fusion
Boot images and all kinds of different ways. What is this traditional style menu plugin?
They've got installed and one of the nice things they support is persistent mode
So you can still boot off a live media but save your data on a gpg encrypted persistent state. That's excellent
Yes, it is. It is excellent
It's very nice when you're doing different kinds of work when you're doing a multi-day project
And that is a very nice feature. Oh, they've got open vos in here. That's one thing I was going to mention
Well, let's talk about that. So open vos is where I wanted to start
so I want to I want to walk people down breaking their own network and
You got to start by discovering your own network and there's a lot of different ways
You can do this end map is a great tool as well
But I want to point you to net discover it's installed by default on kali linux
And it's a network address discovering tool and it will really quickly it'll if you if you pull that
I've got some screenshots. So anyways, it'll it'll quickly it identify all the machines on your network and the vendors who make the hardware
So I could very quickly see all of the tp link and the belkin and the three amazon echo devices that are on our network
Because it gave me vendor and what I assume it's doing although I don't know this for sure. But what I assume it is doing
Is in the background it's looking up the mac addresses of these devices with a vendor database
And it's matching mac address to vendor and then it's saying okay. Well it has these ports open
It has on this network ip address and this is the hardware
So within about 30 seconds using net discover and the command is really simple in my case. It was net discover space
192.168.0
Dot zero slash 24
And that told it to scan my entire network
192.168.0.0.24 now my network is a 192 network if you had a 172 or a 10.1 network
You would need to adjust your command but net discover space 192.168
Zero dot zero slash 24 you execute that command and within seconds net discover will find every device on your network
It'll give you the manufacturer information about it
And see this seems super helpful because there's a lot of tools I've used where I've been very frustrated with like a like an NMS
That does auto discovery, but does a bunch of other stuff, too
So if I could just have one tool that would keep me apprised of changes to my network
But without having a bunch of nonsense, I don't know that too great for that. It's really great
yeah, so then you get your list of machines you want to go after the machines you want to attack or audit and
For me it was the TP link devices, and this is where open vos comes in so how did you know about open vos?
Oh, I'd looked at using it at various employers before yeah, so there's there's several different
assessment tools these are tools that will scan a host IP and just bang on every single port try executing different commands if it
Gets a telnet connection
It'll try to log in like it just does everything to abuse a box and you can have it abuse an entire network
Or you can have it just hammer a machine, and it's not necessarily going to execute a payload
But it's going to tell you what doesn't work. What is vulnerable
If it leaks a certain time stamp that could be used to decrypt data
It tells you all these things about a host which I was curious about with these TP link devices
Which didn't really give me much information
Unfortunately, but open vos or open VAS the reason why I went with it
It stands open VAS by the way stands for the open vulnerability assessment system
That's what the VAS is is the vulnerability assessment system
And I started using it because it reminds me a lot of a tool that I used back in the day called Nessus
Oh, yeah, the Nessus vulnerability scanner. Yeah, so this is along that same line
It's an open source vulnerability scanner that subscribes to a database guys
This is key it subscribes to a database and it pulls down all of the latest vulnerabilities and exploits constantly
So you have the latest
That's where the real like automation stuff that you don't have to do anymore and by the way the first word ever doing
And all of the open VAS packages are in Kali by the way, so it's real easy
there's a meta package you can apt-get you can apt install open VAS and it pulls down the common and the core and
There's a first-time setup wizard you can run under Kali Linux and it will go down it will set up the database
Which I believe might be Postgres by default on Kali
Excellent pulls down all of the vulnerability assessment updates which on on our hundred megabit connection here at the studio took 45 minutes
Download so it will take a long time and do it where you have a fast connection
But once it's done you can throw the weight of the security community's entire knowledge set at a system
And you can just punish it to see what it what it is vulnerable to
And one of the things that's a lot of fun is once you get results in open VAS
And there's other ways to do this under Kali open VAS is the way I like to do it
But there's other ways but what I do is I take the data set I get from open VAS and I run it through
something called Metasploit
Metasploit is more like a list of known exploits and and it's like
Macros to execute them Metasploit is like
Imagine a whole bunch of shell scripts that do bad shit on your system. Only it's everything. It's like remote RPC connections
It's sequel database connections. It's HTTP stuff and you tell Metasploit. This is the host
This is the vulnerability it has which I got using open VAS you tell Metasploit now. Okay, here's the IP. Here's the port
Here's the it's running Apache go execute a shell on that system. So you say here's Apache. Here's the IP now go give me shell
That's what Metasploit does and it's it's so much fun because you can look at a system with open VAS and go
Oh, they have a vulnerability in MySQL and then you go tell Metasploit go talk to MySQL at this IP
And now you own the box. Yep, and it can be a great way to go verify that
Did your patch sets actually apply go Metasploit it if you get in then? No, they didn't yeah
Exactly, and I've linked in the show notes an article on the Kali Linux docs page about using Metasploit and it's a it's it's
Something you could load to your machine and have it and dedicated to a hard drive or something like I'm doing we can have
On a thumb drive and from time to time you fire it up and just do an audit of your network a little Kali and Docker
Yeah, I like to think of Metasploit as like unit tests for vulnerabilities. Mm-hmm
Mm-hmm. Yeah, and it's um
Kind of complicated to set up. It's not hard. I won't say hard, but I'll say it's complicated to set up
But once you get set up, it's pretty easy and met and Metasploit. It's pretty much set up out of the box on Kali
Yeah, which is really cool. So what I decided to do was just sort of bang on these TP links now
They don't really return much. So what I noticed is TP link is
They have they've they've changed all of like the return codes all that although like they had the the version identifiers doesn't return any of that
Stuff so I think when people say they have like a hardened Linux they have Linux
It doesn't respond to any ports except for the ones they need and the services that respond don't give you any identifying information
So if you somehow knew the version of like some software that was on there
via like another leak of the companies like if there was a TP link a
TP link leak about the version of Linux or the version of
Node or the version of NGINX that they have on that little tiny little plug
Then you can attack it with Metasploit, but because when you do a vulnerability scan
They're not revealing any version information. They're not except for the kernel version, which is exactly what you would want
That's that's what you you don't you don't want somebody be able to come into your network and scan your network and get all the version
Information for the embedded Apache server and the embedded database server. You don't want that so
Based on my just really quick scans of both the Belkin Wiimote devices and the TP link smart switches
While they're running old versions of Linux these little smart plugs they're running old versions of Linux
There's $65 computers running Linux or $35 if you buy them on sale, right? Yeah, but they're
They're like bastard I'd bastard eyes versions of all of the software that have been modified and gimped to not fully be functional or report
Themselves correctly, which I guess at the end of the day. I'm happy about I wouldn't necessarily want them to
but it was sort of it was sort of like a
Revealing in a sense to just even get like the kernel version and the ports and all of the IPs and all of the Mac
Address like I felt like I had a better
Understanding of my network. Yeah, even though I didn't really crack a TP link
I didn't crack one of these Belkin's and I didn't I kind of didn't really try too hard
I kind of didn't really try too hard. I
Did walk away with the sense that now I have like a complete picture and I took screenshots, too
So like now I have like all the IPs of all my network devices
What their Mac addresses are what the vendors are so I know how many you know, it's a nice baseline, right?
So that you add future stuff and it looks way different or you see a bunch more activity like you can now
Benchmark against. Yeah. Yeah, I I really I
I really just would say just just for fun go spend an afternoon banging around with Kali Linux
I highly highly recommend it and
If you're if you're looking for different implementations go check out their download page
They have several I've linked to a couple different ones that I use but they have Kali hunter or net hunter
They have the VM version. They have 64-bit and 32-bits. They have Katie Matei
enlightenment 17
It's just to have like a hundred different spins and I just I just went for the stock 64-bit Kali ISO
Which is a gnome 3 based and you can find it at K a li org slash downloads for that and
If you got an extra one pour one out for backtrack, that was a real tool back in the day
I really like that guys. We are we are plum overtime. We're not just out of time
We are over time right now and I and I wanted to mention before we go
So let's you know what? Okay. Alright, so let's do this. Let's I hate to do it. I can't believe it
I see the pain in your eyes
Let's punt the gentoo challenge to next week because before we go I just want to give everybody a heads up about I know
I'm sorry guys. I'm sorry. I'm sorry. But before we go, it's okay Chris. I'm still compiling
Anyway, there's a community announcement. I want to make the our friends over the Ubuntu podcast have something special in the works
Whippy, are you still here? Can you tell us about what's going on in regards to a giveaway over at the Ubuntu podcast?
Well, it's not a giveaway. It's a a hard-earned competition
We ran a competition in partnership with intro where
We reviewed the intro where Apollo the current generation and they allowed us to use that as the prize
and in a competition
Which we've been running for many weeks and the winners of that competition will be announced this Thursday
we've been tweeting all of the entries via the Ubuntu podcast Twitter channel over the last three days and
On our subreddit all of the entries are there so you can go and upvote those entries
We've already picked our winners. We're interested in seeing what the audience thinks compared to what we've picked as the winners
So you can go and have a look at people that have composed music written stories
Poems
created applications
Drawings there's just a a wide range and the theme was
20 so create something in 20 colors or 20 shapes or 20 lines of code or in 20 minutes and
people have really
Run with it. We just really interesting selection
We got it. I got a you and I have to consult next time because we just gave away the XPS 13 we just gave
It away and you got you got real stuff. You're like comics and music. Yeah. Yeah, that is great
Yeah, it's so interesting because every time you do a contest like this, of course
I can say this for you because I don't know if you guys want to
You really discover how awesome your audience is
Absolutely, I mean we we loved looking over these entries and they they're all fabulous and
It's we opened it up because we didn't just want a load of people giving us a bunch of code
we deliberately opened it up so that our listeners, you know who are
Authors or artists or musicians and not coders could also, you know compete on a on a level playing ground
And it was absolutely brilliant. I think that's great. So check out the Ubuntu podcast and I look forward to hearing that episode now
Unfortunately, that means the gentoo challenge will be punted. Whoa. Who saw that coming?
I didn't see that coming couldn't have happened couldn't it couldn't have been predicted couldn't have been all those times
I hours spent compiling for nothing. It's darn it this time. I'm going with dash o3, you know what?
I'm gonna wipe the whole thing and do it all over again
Oh come back next come back next week Beardsley
Where should people find you throughout the week twitter.com slash your Kyle P or Oh rec dotnet rec dotnet
Mr. West at West pain and you can follow me at Chris Elias at Jupiter signal and Linux unplug dot red dot com
See you back here next week
Oh
Okay, oh, yeah
Well since we didn't do the gentoo challenge, I got a different idea for my my title
Suggestion is changing. I feel like maybe we should go with the Kali Linux segment instead since that's what we in. I
Guess the sad part is I was just about to install good. No, you should still do it
You can you can report back next week about how installing gnome went
And I'm doing it without system D from a third-party repo as well. Oh you crazy girl. You crazy
That is save it for the future. We'll definitely talk about yeah, I'll save it for next week man. Don't worry. Okay, okay
Speaking of the abundant podcast contest that you know as you know
He opened it for designers and things and as a designer and a writer I submitted some Python code. Hey, oh
I also installed a boon to 17 just now by the way
I know the it's ironic that we're trying to do the gentoo challenge because all I really want to do is just load all the different
versions of a bunch of
Yeah, it's a good for them though good for the by the way
I put it on my macbook that I got for my birthday really a new one or a used one
It was one off of eBay because my dad didn't want it. What's the year? What's the year? What's the year?
2013 late version 15 inch with Nvidia graphics. That's what I have. That's that is the sweet spot right now
I mean and you know what? It's still a good system. It's still
The high dpi display on it looks crisp as hell. Yeah, I know I
I've night cuz I had had you know, it really sucks though
The only thing is the only good desktop that looks on it with the no display. No, I'm
Yeah, I know. Oh, I know
I that really bites because you can't do XFC. You can't do Katie. You can't do none of that with but it looks
Amazing. It looks like the screen good it
But please don't don't like the screen. Yeah
I've had high dpi on a 13 inch screen
But when we put Linux on the MacBook Pro with a 15 inch high dpi whole nother level, but yeah, it's a whole nother level
It's so good. The only thing that I've had troubles with is getting this graphic switching to work properly
Oh, I don't even bother. I just run the Nvidia all the time. Yeah, I get you. I tried gentoo on it
Oh talk about a nightmare