Yes, I'm still using Gnome.
Yes, but I've made decisions.
Look at the, listen to the tone in that.
I know, well it's because they're right and they know it's going to probably crash on
me during this show and I should know better by now, but the thing is I've been stuck in
Indecision Valley for so long and now I've come out the other side and I feel like I've
seen the light and I've gotten a cold drink of water.
Now I just have to reload all my systems.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 203 for June 27th, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that screens are covered in fingerprints.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Yes, we have a touch screen powered machine.
It's not powered by the touch screen, but it has a touch screen.
Yeah, that's right.
It's important that it does.
Yeah.
We'll be talking about this massive Dell Precision 5720 Linux rig.
What?
I'm going to say right now, not getting into performance or other things, but in terms
of build quality, just probably one of the finest built machines running Linux on the
market today.
So we'll give you a review of that Xeon monster in a little bit, but before that, Wes, before
that, we've got quite a bit of community news and updates to get into.
An old friend is coming back from the dead.
It's not quite dead yet, and you're not going to believe what Mir might be used for next.
We'll give a plug for some upcoming open source events, a couple of new desktop application
launches that look really, really good.
Mozilla's $2 million bounty that, actually, I think a lot of folks in the audience could
probably get.
I think so, yeah.
So we'll tell you about their kind of cool idea, a big problem that the Debian project
has come across.
Uh-oh.
Yeah.
So we've got like all kinds of good stuff in here, Wes.
It's been a very fruitful week for open source.
So before we can get into any of that, we have to stop right here at the top of the
show and bring in our virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Greetings.
Hello everybody.
Well, look at that.
We managed to get a pretty good turnout.
You guys are the best.
That's pretty nice.
Hey guys, it's really good to see you all, and I want to probably start with the most
newsworthy story, because in some ways, Linux is ahead of the rest.
But we'll get to that in just a second.
Intel has a bug, and it's in their Skylake and Kaby Lake processors.
It's related to hyper-threading.
So if you have hyper-threading turned on, an unfixed Skylake and Kaby Lake processor
could, in some situations, dangerously misbehave when hyper-threading is enabled.
If you disable hyper-threading immediately, you're safe.
So this is on Debian's mailing list, is an advisory about processor and microcode defects
recently identified on Intel Skylake and Intel Kaby Lake processors with hyper-threading
enabled.
The defect, when triggered, causes unpredictable system behavior.
It could cause errors such as application and system misbehavior, data corruption, and
even data loss.
It was brought to the attention of the Debian project that this defect is known to directly
affect some Debian stable users, thus the Debian advisory.
Now what do you know about this story?
It's interesting.
You don't hear about these that often, at least not ones that are really big news like
this or that are public outcries.
The problem is that under complex microarchitectural conditions, short loops of less than 64 instructions
that use AH, BH, CH, or DH registers, as well as their corresponding wider register, e.g.,
AX, EIX, or AX for AH, may cause unpredictable system behavior.
Yeah, obviously this isn't a Debian issue.
This is an Intel microcode issue.
So you know that proprietary Intel microcode that when you install Ubuntu and you go to
additional drivers and it has this little checkbox where you can install the microcode?
This is the kind of stuff that is, this is what the microcode is responsible for, and
this is the kind of stuff that if you get new versions of the microcode, you get a patch.
Also on Linux, like in the case of Debian here, for Debian they already have Intel microcode
packages that are patched for Untable, for Unstable, they have them for testing, they
have them for Debian 9, Debian 8 backports.
So they've already fixed it in Debian and they're probably fixing it, I would imagine,
in other distros too like Ubuntu, but you have to be installing this proprietary microcode
package to get this.
So this is one of the things your microcode, that weird crazy package does, and kind of
related to all of this, you found this project, or at least this post this week, about trying
to build a system where the Intel microcode could get uploaded directly from the Linux
kernel to the processor and sort of eliminate the need for initramfs to do this.
So Linux is maybe going to have a simpler way to update this stuff in the future via
directly the kernel.
Hey, that might be handy.
It could be, yeah, because depending on how you're trying to build a system, you know,
if you're trying to build it, basically, the goal here, the end goal they're trying to
get to is a system that you can boot, a Linux system you can boot without any initramfs.
I mean, really, initramfs, as handy as they are, and they are very fun, handy, useful,
it's kind of a hack, you know.
This microcode stuff, though, this flaw at the kernel level stuff, it's spooky because
it means you're hooked on the sauce.
You're hooked on the Intel microcode sauce if you want to get this fixed.
And it's like, if you don't, well, okay, but in some conditions, you might trigger a crash.
But you're already hooked on Intel-dependent software in the first place, like your whole
BIOS spring-up process, all of your EFI services and things that run, you're already dependent
on and really do need to be updated as well.
And in most cases, machine vendors will release new BIOSes, and those contain microcodes.
So if you get the newest BIOS for your machine, it's very likely that you could get the microcode
that fixes this issue, like you're going to get the thing that you can load in Linux after
the fact.
But not all vendors do update their BIOSes, some of them let the language.
So it's nice to do it in Linux because you know that you're going to get the microcode
update applied.
Otherwise, you're looking through change logs for each hardware iteration thing that you
have.
So William, you're completely right.
And two things that jump out at me, though, is number one, like you said, not all vendors
distribute BIOS images because sometimes their upstream ODM agreement doesn't permit them
to redistribute BIOS updates.
So there's that problem.
But secondly, it seems to me the goal should always be to try to move away from things
like requirements of microcode or uploading from Linux or like anything that's sort of
non-transparent.
Well, but if you don't have microcode, then you live with the defects the processor shipped
in.
And this would be one of those defects.
This is what they didn't see this edge case when they built the processor and shipped
the initial microcode.
So the microcode fix that you get now distributed with your Linux distro fixes this issue, which
you would just never fix otherwise.
That's what I said.
And I mean, it really highlights that like, you know, we're at that boundary of hardware
and software.
We're hooked on the good stuff.
It's becoming more complicated.
Like this is some weird L1 cache behavior with two different lengths of instruction
or register modifying instructions.
So William, do you have a kind of an idea of like how likely someone would be to actually
trigger this?
My understanding is you're probably not going to find it in your typical workflow.
Yeah.
It seems like if it took this long to come up.
There's no generation that results in those instructions all fitting in the L1 cache and
performing the behavior that results in triggering the bug.
It sounds like this bug was maybe first found in the OCaml community and they kind of reported
it.
Yeah.
It sounded like, yeah.
So I think it also kind of highlights, there's just a lot we don't know about what's going
on at the hardware layer.
You know, it's like we're already running all this microcode.
You don't know what it is.
It's not very inspectable or suitable in any way.
And then you have this kind of, I mean, you can go look on Hacker News and stuff, but
the thread for this.
There's a lot of people talking about, you know, questionable practices by hardware
vendors around acknowledging hardware defects and how you do that because we don't have
the same kind of tools we've come to expect in the open source software world for identifying
and fixing these kinds of problems.
But at least Intel does seem to publish the errata.
Like I think there's a thing, there should be an errata listing for each of these generations
of chips.
So like for all the Skylake and Kaby Lake platforms, they have the errata published
for these things.
So you can go look up your chip and look at the errata and this will be in there.
Yeah.
I mean, as the chips are becoming more complex, the errata is becoming much larger.
So you're going to see a bunch more of these issues show up because chips are just becoming
increasingly more complex and hard to validate.
I got to be honest.
I really thought when I went back in the day when hyper-threading first was announced as
a thing, I thought, well, that sounds like a damn hack.
And you know, we really haven't really had much fallout from it.
I mean, it's not the best thing ever, but it's kind of funny.
So I guess one immediate fix would be to just go turn off hyper-threading in your bios.
So old school skeptical admin Chris was like, yeah, just turn hyper-threading off.
Just it's fine.
What's funny is it's only this implementation in Skylake onward that's broken, it's not
the older implementations.
Right.
Yeah, right.
Skylake and Kaby Lake, they're the chips that...
And I guess that would mean that the chips came after Skylake and Kaby Lake maybe also
have different types of hyper-threading?
My understanding is it's some caching behavior, I think, of the micro-instructions and that
interacted with hyper-threading in such a way that you got this effect where you have
multiple logical streams happening simultaneously and some kind of corruption happening.
Whoops.
So interesting.
Yeah, it's hard.
It's a system that's hard to do integration testing on because as you add these features
that seem like they gain you performance, they can interact in just really unsuspecting
ways with other features you added before.
But the sort of cherry on top for Linux users is it looks like a fix, I would imagine for
both, I guess Max too, but I saw, I read somewhere that Microsoft won't have a fix for quite
a bit coming down.
My understanding was Microsoft already released the microcode update at least for the Skylake
chips.
I don't know about the Kaby Lake microcode.
Okay, that was...
Because what I was reading is it looked like it would be included in...
But I have read it was in the April rollup.
Oh, no.
So what I was reading would be...
But that may only be for Windows 10.
Ah, okay.
So what I was reading would be included as an update after summer.
But I don't know.
So I really didn't follow that closely because I couldn't really care.
But what I thought was, boy, what an interesting contrast though that I could have seen a time
where Linux would be maybe just completely SOL or totally, totally out of luck on something
like this.
Yeah, the Linux kernel has had the updating support for years, I want to say at least
five years.
Intel's been in there working with the Linux kernel community for years now.
It's just a matter of actually having the proprietary package and then deal it, depending
on your distro, whether you have the update functionality because you may choose to go
with Libre only stuff, in which case you're not going to update the microcode.
Exactly.
So just disable hyperthreading, I guess.
Or don't worry about it.
Or update your microcode.
Yeah, back up, back up often and see if there's another way to update the microcode.
Yeah.
See, the thing is that...
So, William, maybe you can clear this up because what my understanding was is the microcode
with this fix has to be uploaded at every boot.
You can't write it to this processor.
That is correct.
The microcode has...
There's a ROM on the processor that contains the microcode shipped from the factory.
But the microcode updates you apply are applied at runtime every time they're not persisted
on the chip.
Yeah.
So how do you...
And I think that's actually kind of a good thing because if you uploaded a bad microcode,
you could break your chip.
Sure.
But if it comes from the factory working, you know it's going to continue working.
So if you update the microcode and it broke, you can just reboot and do it again.
So how does the...
That is the nice thing about this process.
How does a Triskel user do this, handle this problem?
The Triskel user could update their BIOS since they're probably...
Maybe they're using a proprietary BIOS.
If they're not, then maybe, I don't know, they're just screwed.
They have to accept that they need some binary to be loaded onto the CPU.
Stop running that horrible closed source x86 platform.
Yeah.
But yeah, if you're on Skylake or newer, I think you're basically stuck with proprietary
code that runs at boot so you can do the microcode update.
You're just going to have to deal with yet another proprietary process.
So it looks like it hasn't been released for Windows yet, but I'm sure they'll get updates
out eventually.
You sound so confident.
Yeah.
Now, how about this for a story?
You guys ready for this?
Now, I'm going to ask you something before I get through this whole thing.
Please stick with me on this, okay?
But it's not dead yet.
Mir may live on as a Wayland compositor for the Mate desktop.
Say that again?
Just one more time.
One more time.
Mir.
Yeah.
Canonical's display server project, which was going to ship as the default in Ubuntu
13.10, which is very optimistic, is actually, despite what people believe, still under active
development, I've been watching, it's still getting commits.
And so this week, friend of the show, Martin Wimpress, suggested that Mate developers could
be talking to Mir developers about how Mir might be used as a Wayland compositor.
And I believe, yeah.
Yeah, here it is.
I have it.
He posted a shot on the Google Plus stream somewhere.
I'm not sure.
I can't remember where it was.
He was on one of those places.
And you could see a whiteboard of how they were kind of conceptualizing this thing out.
So here's the kind of the important thing to take away.
Remember that Wayland itself isn't a display server.
It's a protocol that handles the communication between a compositor, like Mudder, or Weston,
or KWin.
A thing that actually spits things to the screen.
Right.
And its clients, like the applications and the windows and stuff like that.
So Mate doesn't necessarily have something that speaks the Wayland protocol.
So they would have to build that in to the Mate back end.
And so Wimpy points out that migrating to Wayland is something that the Mate desktop
is going to have to do.
Right.
That's just something that's going to have to happen at some point.
That ship has sailed.
And they could add Wayland support to Marco.
But it'd be a huge undertaking.
They could switch to Mudder.
But Gnome Shell, I've covered some of my concerns with Mudder recently.
I mean, that has a lot of caveats as well, as Joey points out on OMG Ubuntu.
So using Mir as the Wayland compositor.
So they're going to teach Mir to speak Wayland.
Mir will act as like a set of APIs that developers can write to, that then we'll be able to understand
and can speak the way to speak Wayland.
It'll be the Wayland compositor.
And Wimpy says that, yeah, it's a chunk of work.
But it's less work than rewriting Marco or switching over to, say, Mudder.
It's like it's probably-
Even without explicit Wayland support.
Mir is closer to what they want than something like Mudder or Kaywin.
Now I'm going to take this a step further.
And I think this is where this should go.
I think this should go across every distribution.
This should not be an Ubuntu-only thing.
This should be how almost every desktop environment on Linux speaks Wayland, with the exception
of the really big boys and girls like Kaywin and your Mudders out there, who already are
working on this and already have pretty solid support and have very special use cases.
But here's the reality.
Without something like Mir that does a standard API that everybody can write to, without something
like Mir, every single Tom, Dick, and Harry desktop environment is going to have to create
their own Wayland compositor.
And it's going to be this patchwork of features and support that's going to fragment the Linux
desktop in a way that we've never even considered fragmentation before.
We think of fragmentation as package managers or library versions or system D or no system
D. But true fragmentation will be copy and paste, highlights, screenshot capabilities,
remote desktop capabilities, support of communicating between X applications and Wayland applications
could be different depending on which desktop environment you're using, depending on which
Linux you're running on top of, depending on which version of Linux you're running on
top of.
It is going to be a layer on top of layer on top of layer fragmentation.
If each one of these Tom, Dick, and Harry desktop environments have to go out and figure
out their own way to communicate with Wayland and not to mention all the stuff still new.
So not only is it going to be rough because it's brand new code, but it's going to be
rough because all of these amateur projects are creating their own implementation from
scratch.
It's devastating in terms of usability.
So to have something that is well developed in a company that is familiar with the problem
set that is trying to solve it for their own desktop interests that can create a common
API that desktop environments could just adopt across all Linux could save us from what is
going to be years of fragmentation hell.
Or it's just going to raise the bar.
It's going to raise the bar way too high for entry for desktop projects because now you
don't get X.
You don't get the X server.
So you've got to write all that stuff on your own.
You've got to do all of that legwork now to get your desktop environment up and running
on a Wayland powered Linux desktop or you've got to fork somebody else's open source project.
And that is a way bigger bar of entry than it used to be.
So we are in a sense locking the Linux desktop to the establishment projects that have the
resources, the know-how, the technical understanding of how to build a display compositor and
we are limited to those projects that are going to be able to do something that's actually
usable on desktop unless we have something like this that multiple communities and multiple
distributions and multiple desktop environments are all working towards.
At least that's how I see it.
And it's one of the things that concerns me about the future of desktop Linux the most
and it's something we're barely talking about.
So it sounds like to me you're calling kind of for like a bog standard display server
for Wayland.
I'm calling for like a common API set where you know this version of the API has these
capabilities.
I can take screenshots.
I have copy and paste.
Well there you go.
So that's the thing and I wish this article had talked more about that is because like
it's not that Wayland doesn't have those issues that they're different levels of abstraction
and you have different capabilities, right?
So it doesn't provide those things.
Well and right and different projects are at different points of progress in implementing
those features.
Right.
So just because so just because the KWin display compositor is now making it possible to take
screenshots doesn't mean that Mudder can do it.
And so you could you could literally have a reality where you can have some basic desktop
functionality not work simply because that project hasn't gotten around to making that
work yet on Wayland.
Right.
So this would almost be like a like a desktop API where something especially like you know
for Monte or things like that like this reminds me in some ways of Vulkan and you know we're
like we have this newer layer where we give more power right so like if you are a big
project you want to be able to implement those things because you're like well X does this
terribly I'm always gonna get screen tearing and all these problems let me fix that in
KWin and we're gonna get it right and we're gonna have buttery smooth super great compositing
but as you're saying a lot of pressure is like well I just wanted to make a cool tiling
window manager that did things a little differently.
Is XFCE gonna adopt KWin?
Not likely.
Yes.
So what you're saying is like well if you can surrender some of that control we need
something that can be that middle layer so that you can be like hey I just want to take
a screenshot I don't care how you do it go talk to Wayland for me help me a little bit
with those middle layers I don't need to deviate from that.
You still have to build some of the hooks and support into your desktop environment but
this is what you write to and if you write to this version of the API you will get these
things.
And I imagine like I think the other thing I'd like to see more of is the comparison
to Mudder because I understand the concerns like it's not I don't but I think that it
would be good to have those spelled out and I think part of it may be too like that like
Gnome the Gnome project doesn't really think of Mudder as that as the thing that you're
describing you know whereas Mirror kind of doesn't have a home as much anymore or it's
right you know the state of transition so maybe this is something it really could excel
at.
Yeah and why toss out good code and if it can be open sourced and you know I would love
to also know what the situation is with the CLA when it comes to Mirror and if it could
you know.
That's a good question.
You know would it have to be moved off of Launchpad and put up on GitHub really to get
real community involvement.
These are all questions you'd have to ask and maybe we'll get somebody on here and they
can answer some of those questions but I think interesting though.
Yeah I think the concept is worth considering and if you hear the name Mirror getting kicked
around again in community forums and discussion places I'd say don't don't don't dismiss it
out of hand give it some consideration because there's a real problem here that we're going
to be facing and this could be solving the problem before we even start to struggle with
it.
Not that we can't engineer our way out of it once we're there but it would it be amazing
if we just hit the ground running with the solution.
That would be amazing.
What a what a concept.
This is so neat this solves some problems I had just this weekend Eternal Terminal.
Wes found this and it's a remote terminal for the busy and impatient.
It combines like some of the aspects of MOSH which is the popular terminal we've talked
about before Auto SSH and SSH.
The whole idea here is that it'll reconnect without interrupting the session and it uses
some fancy TCP to do it too Wes.
I was looking at it that's kind of part of its secret sauce is as the they kind of break
it all down in the how it works section but they say the eternal TCP is a layer between
the application and the Unix TCP sockets that make the sockets robust to TCP disconnects
including roaming and connection failure and they go into why that's actually particularly
hard thing to do and how they came up with a reader and a writer and.
Yeah I think this is really interesting and it kind of I've liked MOSH but there are they
talk about them here a lot you know it's like the MOSH does have some limitations especially
how you know MOSH only tries to communicate the current state of the screen.
It doesn't it's not it's very different than how we traditionally have had these kinds
of connections and this is seems like it's you know it doesn't have quite all the capabilities
it has some different drawbacks and limitations but if you're just tired of you know my internet
went out or you know just be able to go from one network to another and then having that
SSH connection reestablished come back up and you don't lose your place.
That's awesome.
I mean again I think that it's you know if you can use screen or Tmux then maybe you
don't have this problem as much and it's not that big of a deal but it can be a layer of
convenience and I think it's really good software engineering to try.
So it's something I'll definitely try out because this weekend I had a multi-day benchmark
running in an SSH session and it was over the gigabit LAN so I was like this is good
this is solid I mean these never these sessions I have running for days they never.
Yeah it died and of course the the whole the whole thing just died.
Bummer I thought and then you linked this to me I was like oh I could have used that
just a few hours ago.
Where were you earlier?
I want to give a quick shout out to odd camp 17 which is coming up very soon you can find
out more at oddcamp.org Saturday August 19th and Sunday August 20th 2017 in Caltonbury
I think that's how you say it right?
Canterbury?
Something like that.
In the UK which looks like a lot of fun doesn't it yeah if you're over on the better spoken
side of the pond.
We're flying over right?
I wish man I wish also a tip of the hat to Entraware for being like a platinum sponsor
over there which is really cool to see them stepping up the community support and odd
camp is an unconference celebrating free culture free and open source software hardware hacking
digital rights all the things we love talking about on this show so you can find out more
at oddcamp.org and again August 19th and the 20th that's awesome and then next week very
soon our virtual log some of you become an actual log you're gonna come here to the studio
you know we have this thing set to 12 that's probably pretty good that's probably pretty
good and you and you and Dan are doing a double of the text nap so we could even go long yeah
we can totally go long cool so yeah next week is the is the barbecue here at the studio
to celebrate episode 200 I'm excited me too I'm not gonna eat for the whole next week
I'm thinking like okay I better get an extra tank of propane gonna bring over maybe a charcoal
barbecue gotta make sure the sous vide machine is prepared I guess we gotta think about sides
too cuz I feel like I've only thought about which is not that that's bad that's the important
part but Hadeen is thinking about making like an ambrosia salad so that could be one side
but yeah we need like beans and stuff we got a couple of chairs in here I figured we'll
have the mumble room a couple chairs that people come in here we'll chat it'll be good
it'll be a lot of fun meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting to sign up if you can make it
next week I don't know how we're gonna stream I still haven't figured that out I'm like
just gonna take that right up to the red line and then figure that out the last minute I
guess in true JB style originally I was gonna vlog the whole thing and then just do a big
release but then it's not fun I know but then I'll live the in all of the material we put
publicly it said well live stream and I'm like oh shit okay well we're live streaming
it then we're doing a live meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting if you can make it and
the meetup will be here at the studio so hopefully you know it's right up just a would you say
Wes how many minutes up around noon or say around 11 on a Tuesday is it from Seattle
it's a drive you probably make semi-frequently so yeah it's probably like depending on traffic
like 45 minutes 40 minutes plan for like a 45 50 minute drive to make it up here from
Seattle yeah from the Seattle area that's but it's it's a nice drive it's worth it is
just the burbs of Seattle are we in the burbs getting that way you know when you live in
the burbs you don't really consider is it because like outside of the cities the suburbs
right you know you don't think of it as the burbs and you live in the burbs yeah I guess
I mean you might be like you could think of Everett as a Seattle suburb and then yeah
like a suburb of Everett no no no I reject that I was gonna skip over that middle section
here's the thing to like when I travel and people say where you from say Seattle yeah
you say yeah that's what everybody knows yeah it doesn't like and when you're like to you
know you know even like even 500 miles away when you're like 2,000 miles away or 3000
but even like 500 miles away like it like the nuance of the difference between Seattle
anywhere else is totally is lost so yeah all right well let's take a moment and let's thank
Ting for sponsoring this episode of the unplugged program go to linux.ting.com not only is that
a powerful URL that you want in your history but it's also the way to support the show
and get $25 off a Ting device they got a lot of great devices that you can buy directly
from Ting no contract no other termination fee no weird quote-unquote agreements hate
those you can also just bring a device and then get a Ting service credit now I did that
that's how I got started with Ting I was like I'm gonna be a little skeptical and dip my
toe in here a dip my toe in the water I brought a device so I got $25 service credit and that
thing lasted me more than my first month and I realized oh man something shifted here because
you're just paying for what you use your minutes your messages and your megabytes and that's
it it's just six dollars for a line so if you use say 15 text messages you just pay
for the 15 that you have to use instead of like having to pay for like a plan that gives
you 800 texts just in case you use this it's all kind of silly it's all kind of arbitrary
it's all just really a scam and Ting is here to make mobile simple and make sense that's
why there's no contracts you pay for what you use they have nationwide coverage you're
in control with their awesome dashboard they have tons of nice devices and a CDMA network
and a GSM network which means not only is that a ton of devices you can bring but that
gives you flexibility down the road too when you're traveling I use that all the time I
bring a CDMA phone with me and I bring a GSM either hotspot or phone with me to one or
the other so I can always have good network signal wherever I'm going because it's just
different areas they different companies different have different agreements with different cities
and you just never know you're looking to move or something and you don't want to change
carriers like that's the last thing you want yeah yeah yeah when I when when we did the
shows back at the house I had CDMA coverage there that was really great when we moved
here I got just a slightly still great coverage on CDMA but I got just faster data on the
GSM network I switched to the GSM you don't have to do you don't have new accounts there's
no canceling or sign up you just and it's one of those things where you never have to
think about it if you're if you're not like a like a geek if you are a geeky you know
what those things are it's great that you have that flexibility check them out go to
linux.ting.com and save a little money support the show and get started with a better way
to do mobile linux.ting.com linux.ting.com thanks to ting for sponsoring the unplugged
program one of my favorite open source desktop applications admittedly because I have the
cutest kids on the entire planet hashtag bias digicam has a new update digicam 5.6 and this
is the thing here that I was I always wanted this because when I want to share my photos
like oh look at this really cute thing my kids did because they're the cutest kids in
the entire world I think I mentioned that but I didn't really want to like throw up
a whole gallery on google photos and share it with family or what other photo sharing
services are there flicker still the thing I don't know it's weird and it's like well
what am I what am I really what do you know why so this is a problem that is now solved
in digicam 5.6 which is what I really I wanted to call out this feature it's a new html gallery
tool that lets you quickly generate a web gallery from a set of albums or you know just
a couple of photos and then they get immediately uploaded online you can show them to friends
and family and then there's also a tool built in there they'll take a slideshow and just
create a video that you can share so instead of trying to figure out wow yeah so instead
of having to figure out how to do the slideshow thing it'll which this is a common question
my family has so this is this is gonna be my go-to answer now is just use this digicam
program it'll you know you build the slideshow and it will generate a video for you you just
email me your mp4 and we'll all be fine you know my aunts and stuff are gonna be putting
that up on facebook the moment that feature yeah and then for us geeks you're gonna love
this digicam 5.6 comes with improvements for database backends and support for mysql databases
so not only sqlites hey you got a real database yeah we're almost real i mean it's you know
when you got a lot of photos or what i was i and i think somebody told me that their
setup was like this once is a shared freaking mysql database between your machines yeah
there you go right you just have one put the photos like on an nfs mount you put the database
on a mysql server you throw you need the high availability digicam because you need to edit
at any time well to tell you the truth this problem yeah right i hate having like some
of my photos on one machine that's one of the things google photos it was really appealing
is i could just put them google photos could be the canonical master source but i want
the actual files on my file system and so digicam sort of that nice middle layer because
when i want the photo experience digicam is there but i know in the back end they're on
the file system throw it on a nas shared mysql database if i had an afternoon man i'd i would
seriously consider it i also love that the html expert like you were talking about that
is neat so like you could just go throw that on s3 or whatever or digital oceans new object
storage and then just go run a website that way huh you know the other thing too i'll
just mention i know for the paranoid this is not your top feature but for those of us
that leave the gps coordinate taggings on for the phones that support it they've brought
back the feature to show like where your photos are taken on a map stuff oh neat yeah always
fun with the kids it's always fun let's talk about this particular one in a mumble room
if anybody wants to jump in on this story in fact i'd like to actually maybe we'll toss
some of this to the mumble room because i'd like to hear their ideas on how they would
do this so prepare your minds because mozilla wants to give you two million dollars upfront
right like they'll just give it to me and then maybe i give them deliver no uh damn
no the two million dollars do they need my p-mail address yes or your bitcoin address
maybe i'm not sure chris it's all about ethereum these days come on i know that's what everybody
tells me uh except for i can't i can't i can't get into that uh so this is uh really it's
a prize to decentralize the web and they're looking for people to apply today mozilla
and the national science foundation are oh okay it's also the national science foundation
are offering a two million dollar prize for big ideas that decentralizes the web and they're
accepting applications right now uh so to give you a little idea of kind of what they're
looking for they want something that would work off the quote unquote grid when disasters
like earthquakes and hurricane strikes so keep this in mind mumble room communication
networks they say are going to be critical infrastructure and they want vital messaging
and mapping services to work after disaster uh the applicants will be expected to design
both the means to access wireless network i.e the hardware and the applications provided
on top of that network i.e software and project projects should be portable and easy to power
and simple to access what do you think sweetly what would you start with i was thinking like
some sort of mesh network and that like maybe okay you got to give me hardware and the software
you'd use to do it because it's part of the challenge so what would it be like phone based
would it be laptop based because you got to have something powerful enough to route the
traffic if the network gets busy probably maybe something server based in that it would
have to maybe go a little bit high end and that because you got to have something powerful
enough to handle the load and that not having an unintended uh ddos right yeah exactly that's
what i was like a tech man if you say a ham radio has already figured out some of this
mr tech man go uh all right fine but i mean i think i mean that's a good that's a good
point if i can speak for mr jimmy yeah um just that for some of these things if you
don't need high bandwidth then that might be a legitimate thing because in emergency
scenarios yeah you know you might just need like hey over here or we need food or whatever
it high bandwidth you would you would definitely need high bandwidth all right bash basheru
is what what is it bash flu ru bashful robot oh bad robot man i get for looking across
the room uh distance versus cost hit me with it well because if you think about it you
need to look at traditional carriers they they don't reach everywhere uh based on you
know last mile fiber or even you know that's why they're jumping on like a lot of the satellite
or the uh point-to-point wireless uh in canada here i mean you we have good transit across
the nation but you get us into the last mile and we're we're hooped like you just can't
get it and no one wants to pay for it uh there's like an s ton of dark fiber between vancouver
and seattle that's been sitting there from when uh what was it 365 was in there and no
one wants to buy it because it's too expensive yeah huh uh i guess that kind of is sort of
maybe in line with your thinking producer michael satellites uh yeah there's a there's
a project being done that allows anybody to contribute it uses open street maps and gps
to share data through like without any kind of actual like data service so you just need
to be able to access the gps so what's being done is anybody can go into the service sign
up for the project and you can spend anywhere between five to 30 minutes and they have like
these tasks that you can take data information that's been provided on the local level of
of like reporters and stuff and you can go in and change and manipulate the map data
so that people in emergency situations would get a notification really quick interesting
that would be so okay that kind of gives me an idea so what about well i got i think i
know how i would do it i think i i think i know how to do carry your pigeons maybe dude
maybe hey let's talk about it do you have an idea like how you would do this like to
me like at least i mean there's two kind of challenges here right there's the off the
grid and the smart community networks one and to me like thinking about it it depends
on what disasters are other things we're talking about here but it kind of seems like a software
problem like we've already seen some chat apps or other things on mobile that will work
without internet to do like nfc chat or wi-fi ad hoc chats so really to me it seems like
the the problem is that we don't have a lot of um schemas or specs or things around how
to share okay sure you have like a windows home group or something but realistically
there's not a lot of great ways to interact so like you know like you lose your internet
connection for the whole neighborhood but you need to share resources you're already
connected if there's still power between your is if you're on the same is like we could
have a lan but there's no there's no tools software or management would it be amazing
if like this if you could have a so uh devices that mesh network even when there's no internet
and say you had a wikipedia app and your phone had um the article's cache that i wanted i
could retrieve them from your like if some if you had if the software was smart enough
to not only announce what local data you had but if it was also smart enough to know that
the privilege level this is public information that's important like i have no way to offer
a service to my neighbors even though maybe we're all on the same isp the coax is connected
there's a switch that connects us all there's just not standards like it's like a proxy
server for everything in a over okay so here's where i was going with this is i think it's
also a software problem because i don't think you would do just one particular fix like
one of the things they mentioned in here is uh here's an example they said a backpack
containing a hard drive computer battery and a wi-fi router the router provides access
via wi-fi network to resources on the hard drive like maps and messaging applications
like doing a data drop off or here's a drop off but now you need a way to know that data
is there and you can access it so i think it is a software problem and then the other
thing i was thinking is why why have one why only have one approach here why why only one
thing why why just satellites why why just air balloons why not a like full spectrum
in some areas it's a raspberry pi stuck in the corner somewhere at someone else's place
they've got an x86 rig in their garage that's been sitting there providing a resharing networking
now for a year somewhere else it's something built into a television because it's a high-end
television and this is a common wireless chipset that's now been created at another place it's
somebody's phone that's just helping fill in a bit of a gap and in another area it's
a dgi drone that somebody strapped a raspberry pi to the bottom of but it's getting connection
and sharing signal and if the network exists the software is smart enough to make the access
happen if the connect however the connection is being provided if it's anything from a
dgi drone to a x86 rig in a garage like whatever is sharing the connectivity that doesn't matter
you make that irrelevant so that way that could be just hodgepodge because that's gonna
be geographical to there's gonna be some areas that are that are poor that can only afford
certain things that have hectic wiring and power and there's some areas and more connections
will be a part of this yeah yeah exactly so you know it reminds me of our conversation
with Michael Hall last week and endless OS and you combine what they're doing with offline
things like recipes and Wikipedia and reference material and books and you combine it with
something like this Mozilla challenge I wonder I just I'm fascinated by the whole idea especially
when you use things like the lens of the net neutrality debate like say say we go to some
dystopian future with net neutrality and corporate lockdown of the internet and the geeks had
to save the world how would they do it what we say you had to rebuild the new network
how would we do it we'd have to use the tools we have and it would be our phones our raspberry
pies I mean like we're kicked off YouTube we can't live stream anymore and that's the
only way you get videos I got selfies to post yeah right so join us over on the new internet
where you just take your tin can and piece of string and you tie it to your neighbor's
house and it's you know you watch JP it's cool but I think we could come up with something
so here's what I'm saying go to the Mozilla blog read more about it win the two million
dollars and then kick back a couple hundred bucks to JP for for hooking you speaking of
Mozilla they launched a new podcast this week I wonder if they have it up on their website
with their IRL podcast with Veronica Belmont you hear about this no yeah she's got a new
show working for Mozilla see this is why you got to listen to the ask Noah show you got
to listen because of Veronica Belmont joined Noah July our Noah July on ask Noah episode
14 Belmont IRL look at that yeah and Noah talked to her about her projects the upcoming
show the IRL podcast and all kinds of good stuff and they had a little Linux chat in
there too Veronica Belmont is as a class act and so it was a good interview on super exciting
yeah I think the new show launches today so how about that how about that I'll be curious
to see where that goes because I've liked her on thing I mean I've been listening to
Veronica Belmont since buzz out loud so I've liked her on all that stuff so I would I would
imagine she'd probably put together a pretty decent show oh yeah episode 1 is now out on
their IRL podcast dot org there you go oh you did listen to it yesterday Bash what'd
you think it wasn't bad it had a very produced feel to it kind of almost scripted but they
went heavy with the editing on it for sure yeah that's kind of a new thing you know shows
where we sit around here and just don't don't edit out when people don't answer and hitting
the microphone that's a that's a we are a dying breed we are legacy yeah we are legacy
podcast we don't need season chapter markers and podcast apps and all these I mean it's
just it's a straight brah mp3 feed sometimes we're an hour long sometimes we're an hour
and a half it's a real train wreck it's a real train wreck it is a hashtag disastrous
hashtag need data that's got to get that got to get that data well speaking of data West
oh DigitalOcean's got data for days go over to DigitalOcean.com and sign up and use our
promo code Linux Unplugged and get a $10 credit you heard Wes mention earlier they're introducing
object storage they have they have block storage which is okay for me I'm gonna be honest when
I when they introduced block storage I was good I was like this is all I need this is
what I done but the beauty to object storage is then you can build your applications in
a way that can scale for days and this is probably honestly if I was starting out today
how I would do things as well so it's pretty brilliant that DigitalOcean is launching this
and if you sign up for early access you can get a terabyte to play around with until like
October what yeah that's nice so DigitalOcean is a really simple and straightforward way
to spin up a nice rig on their infrastructure in seconds you they call them droplets I call
them fast Linux rigs they got SSDs for all of the different types of machines they have
lightning fast networking they have a beautiful UI to manage it and a simple API with tons
of pre-built command line utilities that really that's really what matters about the API is
the open source community has really embraced it something else that's really cool is they
have load balancing as a service they have monitoring and alerting and they have hourly
pricing available so you can get a 2 gig system with a two core processor 40 gigabyte SSD
of disk and three pair three terabytes terabytes of transfer for three cents an hour DigitalOcean
I tell you what go over there sign up use our promo code do unplugged get a $10 credit
and mess around they got data centers all over the world and you can even run free I
say fast Linux rigs but you can even run the good old free BSD what DigitalOcean.com use
our promo code do unplugged and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the unplugged
program so I I I am up for interruption at any point mumble as I go through the Dell
machine I have here so please feel free if you have any questions to stop me and I'll
answer them I had a I had a chance Dell I I guess I should probably back up so Dell
sent me a couple of weeks ago I've been running this machine for a few weeks the Dell Precision
5720 it's an all-in-one and this one came with Ubuntu 1604 and this was probably one
of the hardest machines I've ever reviewed I feel like it's getting hard because how
do you review a machine like this this is this is a it's a system it has Intel Xeon
E3 1275 processor so it's quad core with hyper threading this one had 3.8 gigahertz clock
which turbo boost up to 4.2 gigahertz with 8 megabyte cache you can put three drives
this one had a PCIe m.2 drive and a I think I was spinning terabyte drive in it I mean
it's just it's super fast and so you almost know immediately if you need a machine like
this or not like I don't really need to tell you if you need a Xeon system with 64 gigs
or up to 128 gigs but this one had 64 gigs of ECC RAM like you know that you know that
you know immediately if that's too much system for you so then I was trying to figure out
okay well so who are these people and what what are the workloads specific to the Linux
desktop for a system kind of like this and I kind of broke it down into a few different
areas definitely for a high-end photo management station and photo workflow like DigiCam this
thing looks like it would be super fast disk I oh so if you have large megapixel photos
from your DSLR high-resolution super vibrant screen tells been killing it with those screens
lately I also did some video editing on it Linux itself is not super great at 4k playback
right now but if you get hardware accelerated video decoding it works fine I did it and
this machine is a great one for it but I think probably the other area that this thing would
stomp would be software development I ran a series of open benchmark org benchmarks
on this rig and what's really if you if you're curious about any of this stuff check out
the pharaonic test suite it is really it's really a great piece of open source software
we've talked about it before on the show but goodness goodness or as commie says lordy
lordy lordy is this thing not great so first of all it simulates all kinds of workloads
and installs the actual packages on your machine from your distros repository and then goes
through and executes different workloads documents at all uploads it open benchmark allows you
to compare it to other similar system allows people to compare their system to yours it
is very very useful and so some of the benchmarks that I ran on it specifically to software
development were some of the most impressive wow so one of the highlights is I was able
to build Linux kernel 4.9 in under two minutes on the system now that would be a so there
would be a way you could just a quick takeaway from this review if you're curious how fast
the system is compared to yours go get kernel 4.9 source code on your system and build it
and time that and that give you kind of a baseline in some sense of how fast just phenomenal
how fast the system is this also means that if you're you have to use a custom kernel
you can't complain about it well and I just try to mention I just I just it uses the stock
kernel I just mentioned that as a benchmark because it if you can build it just gives
you a perspective you're building your own projects how fast they might totally this
comparison to the Linux kernel and I thought that was I thought that was just sort of an
interesting perspective but I have a link in the show notes where you can actually run
the comparison benchmark so you can click this link you give it the the address to the
phronics test suite and it runs the exact benchmark I ran and it gives you the comparison
result yes I have that in there so I spent I spent about a week using it to edit photos
and video and I found it to be pretty exceptional at that and so I'd say that whole that whole
sort of like high-end media production workload this thing's obviously great for anything
that has a lot of disk I owe this thing's pretty great for and if you're if you're clever
enough to monkey around with your system codecs or you're brave enough might be a better way
to put it because it's really it's maybe it could be a stability issue I I really say
you got to be you got to be willing to mess around with your codecs but you can get great
4k video editing if you're just working with 1080 video this thing's gonna it's gonna slide
yeah it's gonna slam it it I worked with this thing it even under heavy load it never felt
really bogged down at all it was it does seem like it would appeal for the you know creatives
or professionals who are just trying to get things done cuz you don't I mean like it's
all it's an all-in-one type unit so you just put it on your desk you plug it in and then
all right you got a computer now yeah let's talk about that is there really so if you're
getting a system this powerful who wants a system that's this powerful that's also an
all-in-one that was one of the other things I was trying to I was trying to figure that
out because to me at first it wasn't obvious but having used it for a little bit I can
tell you it's it's pretty low hassle and I think that's probably its biggest appeal if
you use the Bluetooth mouse and keyboard it comes with you and you use Wi-Fi you have
one cord coming out the back that's pretty nice and it's it's very clean it's very simple
the speakers are incredibly we'll talk about more of those in a little bit it's it's that
all is really nice where it gets kind of where it gets kind of interesting is if you combine
it with the touchscreen option because the whole thing folds down right sort of like
a surface studio but this is way more powerful than a surface studio and that is actually
kind of a useful feature for certain types of work especially for certain types of video
editing so I liked I could I started to use it more I was like I could kind of see this
machine is powerful enough I feel like this machine spec'd as this was which is about
$3,600 which is still like half the price of the iMac Pro would probably last you ten
years you have USB-C up the wazoo on the back of this thing you have Thunderbolt 3 the back
is removable the back is completely you you do two screws you do pull you remove two screws
and the whole back of the thing comes off and you have access to all of the hard drives
you have access to the memory I don't know about the CPUs I don't I believe they're there
they are socketed but I don't know if you'd actually want to upgrade them and I don't
know if that would void the warranty either but so it's it's much more sustainable than
an iMac because it's nothing's really soldered you can get access to all of that stuff pretty
quickly the screen is going to you mean where there's not going to be better screens really
for there will be but it's gonna be a great screen for a long time yep it's it is fast
enough with you know 64 gigabytes of ECC RAM 1.5 terabytes of super fast storage it the
all-in-one aspect of it kind of makes more sense now than I think it used to because
you're not really going to be super hard pressed to upgrade this thing that's where I thought
about it as like from like the business or small business or design company or something
like you could just buy that for an employee they're new you don't have to think about
anything else the keyboard mouse done mm-hmm speakers exactly that when I put myself in
the small business mindset and I thought oh yeah this could be a machine that you buy
an employee don't have to have IT staff who can set it up and network and all of that
yeah and you could you can buy the same one for your folks that run Ubuntu or Red Hat
and you could buy the same one for your folks around Windows 10 yeah totally and so that's
sort of an advantage that Dell has oh I don't know that was that's actually that's a good
question I I'm not sure you know I I use Katie and live in my testing and I I find it to
be usable if you use proxy media with high resolution stuff and I I put out a vlog that's
more of a real quick look at this that's more visual heavy because this is a very pretty
machine and I it is and I showed off some of my example work that I edited under this
machine in the vlog I have it embedded in the show notes which is sort of a more of
a quick take and my impressions of it and I thought that also be a good a good chance
to show off some of the work you can do with the machine so that's sort of the that's sort
of the my my oh I went through I had to go through several levels of realizations and
the one was there is a workload for this even if it's not high resolution video editing
there's still several really good workloads for this machine and software development
being one that I think is probably high on that list and then then I had to kind of wrap
my head around the hall all-in-one aspect of it like why would you want this as an all-in-one
versus like like a little mini tower under your desk or something connected to like a
5k screen I had to like I had to bridge that and it it wasn't until I sort of put myself
in a small business like well this machine is fast enough I buy this for myself for an
employee as a business this could easily be three four five six seven machine your machine
and then it started to make a little more sense because it's also it's also just a very
portable in a sense it's heavy but you can you can move between deaths it's not like
it you don't have to move a whole bunch of a whole bunch of extra stuff it it's a I don't
know it's it's kind of more appealing to me than it used to be and they they make it with
this really heavy base that sits on the desk so that way you can move the screen around
I was watching that and that's that seems nice like it doesn't it doesn't move around
doesn't rock or tilt so it means it's a little awkward to carry but you're not moving around
a lot right yeah so there so there's sort of the the first part of it I suppose the
second part of it would be sort of the thermals and the noise stuff because I had an opportunity
to punish them this machine and when it was very hot out it's very hot in the JB lab when
I when I did this test so it was probably 90 degrees in the room only a small piece
of the case melted it was it's fine yeah yeah what what Intel CPUs are running it's got
you depending on what now this is of course you can you can get with a range but the one
that I have is the Xeon E3 1275 so you have a huge range of CPUs yeah well they also essentially
have something similar this in the XPS line which is I you can do which then you can even
get with i7 or i5 so you have the XPS line of the all-in-one and then you have the precision
line and this is the precision line which is the workstation grade enterprise grade
line so that's why you have ECC and Xeons but it looks like the on the site they still
offer the the yep i5s and i7s if you want if you don't need the Xeons so I and I think
if you do that I think I might be wrong I think like starting price is like seventeen
and eighteen hundred dollars yeah sixteen ninety nine yeah maybe I'm shopping for one
right now as we're doing this so that is even more remarkable when you compare it to the
iMac Pro it's obviously not competitive really but you have a starting range of seventeen
hundred dollars and then you can configure upwards from there my favorite part here is
you know all right well it shows like windows for me I can upgrade to Red Hat Enterprise
for seventy more dollars that makes it look like a premium option well you get the Red
Hat support so in a sense it is a premium option yeah yeah I I found it to be I found
it to be fun because I I was like okay well how the hell am I gonna break this machine
like what do you throw at a computer like this with that much RAM and and and and CPU
so that's what I tried to do so over the weekend I really punished the hell out of this thing
I put it in a 90 degree room not intentionally but that's how it worked out didn't have any
other rooms and yeah well it was hot too it was a hot weekend Sunday especially oh yeah
that was when I was really that was a hot day oh my god not really but we're from the
Pacific Northwest so our conception of hot is not that it's like a hundred and it's moist
AF I'll just say that I'll just say that it's moist AF but this thing also yeah so the so
the back's removable where you can upgrade the components but then just IO wise you have
display port out you have HDMI out you have Ethernet gigabit Ethernet I think it's got
three USB C ports on the thing plus USB a plus SD card reader on the side so it's got
tons of connectivity including connectivity for external graphics down the road this one
came with the AMD workstation graphics eight gigs of video RAM he's yeah yeah so I was
whoof it was it was even rendering all day yeah so I got another question architect was
saying in chat that it has a base amount that where's that located because yeah I think
I think this would be awesome if you had a base amount on the back of the screen so you
have no base and it's like you could have a floating arm on your desktop and it's like
you have no people will be going hey where's your computer and it's just the screen so
I think you have two options actually I think so I think the stand comes off but that takes
some trickery and I believe it on the bottom of the stand to the heavy part the plate there's
a base amount capability too so you I think you have two options with the sucker to mount
it which is pretty nice yeah because it would actually go really well on the wall I mean
a killer killer system for something like that and like especially like a doctor's office
where you wanted to be fast and reliable alright so let's talk about let's talk about thermals
let's talk about the speakers and all that stuff but because we got to we got to prepare
our we got to prepare ourselves let's take a moment and thank Linux Academy Linux Academy
dot com slash unplugged I know I know this you got a machine you got to learn right you
got to learn you got to learn you got to learn on a machine like this when we got yourself
the precision workstation why not go to Linux Academy and learn learn how to put it through
its paces they have self-paced in-depth video courses for every Linux cloud and DevOps topic
hands-on labs and scenario based labs that really help you work with the material so
it's not just check in the boxes you actually walk away with experience and confidence to
do the work and instructor mentoring if you ever get stuck and lots of really great vibrant
community members from the Jupiter broadcasting community that are working there forking the
flashcards making things better practice exams before you take your big quiz iOS and Android
apps for the go it's it's a killer resource Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged and
a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program Linux Academy dot com
slash unplugged sign up for a free seven-day trial thanks Linux Academy so looking at this
thing I thought for sure that with Xeon processors and PCIe storage which often runs hot I thought
for sure once I really started pushing it I would hear it make quite a bit of noise
and I'd seen in I think it was swamp Swampy's review that he posted recently somebody else
posted a review just the other day while I was finishing up mine and complained about
some fan noise so I expected to hear quite a bit of fan noise and I think maybe depending
on what you're pushing the machine you might get different results but when I was pushing
the CPU super heavy and really working that doing things like builds and crypto benchmarks
almost inaudible in a 90 degree room which really really surprised me when I started
pushing the GPU more and more I could hear a different type of cooling kick and I don't
know if it's just one fan in the system or if there's multiple fans I didn't take the
back off to look to see how they're cooling it but I could definitely hear a bit more
of an increase in odd in sound but I actually tried to record a little bit of the machine
noise to give you a sample and the and the room the lab that I was in just the ambient
noise of the room was louder than the machine noise even when I was pushing the GPU so it
wasn't it wasn't too bad I think probably the thing that I'm the most mixed on and of
course I don't think Dell's gonna like to hear this but the thing that I'm the most
mixed on with this machine is the speakers they they some people have complained they
don't look good I actually think in person they look fine they're not very noticeable
I've so in like some photography of the machine I've I've I've lit it so that way you could
see where the speakers were at and there's three speakers along the front three like
a soundbar essentially and then in the base of the machine there's a sub so it's essentially
a seven speaker system and to say Dell is proud of this would be an understatement while
we were at Dell they made sure to demo it to us and told us about the Grammy award-winning
tuning and then when they sent this machine to me they included a literature that went
on for quite a bit about how advanced the sound system is in this and it's interesting
to see how companies like there's aspects of their products are extremely proud of and
the sound system was definitely one of them so I feel like anything negative I say about
this is gonna be disappointing but I have to tell you the truth and the truth of it
is for mids and they're great anything in mids like any music or a voice that's got
a dialogue listen to some podcasts while I'm working on this no problem yeah or you know
anything with guitar or cymbals or anything mids is gonna sound fantastic Spanish guitar
podcast Chris obviously I feel like the highs began to distort a little bit at the high
end just a little bit but here's why I say I feel like because what it really is is these
speakers brutal brutally handle bad audio like they just are brutal with it like I guess
here's a comparison I'm trying to make because I'm trying it's hard to like because we're
coursework I can't like play a sample because we're re-encoding this audio so like it's
really hard for me to to describe this problem to you but take out take take this sort of
analogy if you will if you if you ever had a high-definition television that you got
you brought it home you hooked it up and you plugged in your standard definition signal
to it and all of a sudden standard definition television with look which looked just fine
on your 22 inch CRT looks like total ass on you know that is how bad encoded audio sounds
on these speakers to my ears to my ears YouTube videos like a 480p YouTube video or even
a 720p YouTube video I can hear compression artifacts much more clearly with these speakers
than I could hear them say on a standard set of very nice monitor desktop speakers and
I think it's because these things accentuate highs and mids in a way that expose compression
artifacts that if you if you know what to hear you will hear it constantly with these
speakers because it turns out the internet is full of bad audio now if you have good
and I did a little AB comparison I took mp3 tracks and I took wave tracks and I played
them side to side and noticeably even with mp3s I could hear improved audio I perceptibly
could notice the audio sounded better with these speakers like they if you give them
more material to work with they do more and if you give them a compressed file there's
just less for these speakers to work with and so they produce less and it's not that
it doesn't sound good it's that once you hear these speakers sound great everything else
sounds like shit right and so then you want everything to be uncompressed or to be flack
and you don't want to watch any YouTube video under 1080p and Spotify has to go out the
window and like it's really just it's an interesting problem to have and also then combine that
with the fact that the lows are pretty weak like there's not a lot of bass it's got a
built-in sub but I mean they're only so big right so how do you right now for most people
they probably don't need a lot of boom in their in their desktop audio and if you're
doing content editing or creation on this machine these speakers are great if you're
doing podcast editing speakers are great if you're you know doing dialogue and stuff
like that they're great you're playing games even if you don't want a lot of bass I think
they're really great if you're watching a lot of YouTube if you're listening to a lot
of compressed audio it sort of drove me crazy a little wow so that was my sort of like it
was this really weird torn issue on the speakers because yeah I acknowledge they're great and
I can tell Dell's very proud of them. It's almost like a like studio monitor type thing
you know it's like unless you've got a they won't compensate for your bad audio they don't
bass boost they don't do anything you know it's like you'll just hear if it's good it
sounds great if not then hmm. So the way I looked at it's like well okay so when when
I have that problem I could wear headphones which I might be more inclined to do anyways
and then when I want built-in audio I have great audio available to me if my source is
good right but it is kind of awkward because like if you're an audio engineer then you're
gonna have headphones or very nice speakers anyway so you probably won't use those. Yep
yep yeah yeah that is interesting you're right about that it might make to me they almost
make more sense in the XPS line which is more consumer focused and yes to answer the question
it does have a headphone port so it's right there on the side too. If you look at the
shot I have up on the video there's the SD card reader there and then right below it
is the headphone. You're totally right though that like in person also I that bass is heavy
I was just I was just playing with it and you're totally right like the fingerprints
do show up but you're right like it's it's like a bezel on you know screens that don't
have great bezel but you just you're looking at the screen you don't notice the speakers
at all they don't take away. They stand out more in the in when I lit the face so you
can see the features but it has a very infinity pool feel to the front of it and that's one
of the things that's neat is because you combine it on this floating hinge and then it has
the black infinity pool front so when the screen is off it just looks like this it's
just this infinite black hole sitting on your table and your soul sinks right in it's fine
and then when you turn it on it's it's one of the best screens you'll see I think for
a long time and so it goes from this deep black infinity pool to this vibrant 4k screen
that almost goes all the way out here's a shot where I tried to demonstrate where you
can see the edges almost goes all the way out to the edge of the screen Dell's getting
really good with these things yeah they are and it just makes it totally pop and it everybody
that saw it commented on how how good it looks visually and so it's sort of hard to capture
that and then you combine it with the great IO and the super fast performance then you
have Dell support that you get with it I honestly you were right about the production quality
like the build quality of the thing yeah it's solid yeah it's I I I'm really impressed it's
like when they decide to do it they really decide to do it it's it's so solid like I've
carried this thing around now for weeks moving it between my place and the studio doing different
tests on it on hikes clearly I did and I mean I'm telling you having moved this thing around
it is even though that whole back panel comes off it is super solidly built which makes
me really happy even like I feel like there are like we've talked about the caveats about
like maybe this isn't for you you don't have a purpose it you being the audience member
or whatever but the fact that they can make something like this I'm excited to see this
trickle down or be this kind of approach in other product lines I honestly feel like if
I'm being honest I'm enough of a gearhead that this would be a machine for me like I
don't I guess I can't always justify Xeons and workstation graphics and ECC RAM but I
also I also know that I like my system to be extremely stable I also know that I want
my business investments to last a long time I actually I don't think it's that big of
a jump for somebody like me this would be a really I think this is a really great route
to go now and it because it doesn't start at $5,000 it now that Apple see Apple set
the entry price for the iMac at $5,000 wow so the fact that this thing spec'd pretty
nice as it is it's $3,600 well now it feels like a deal you know like thanks Apple you
just sold Dell's machine for me because that one yeah it's it's very nice so I thought
it was shockingly quiet very low fan noise even after multi-day benchmarks and the sound
system for the most part is really great and if you have invested in a good audio like
a good music collection you're gonna enjoy the shit out of these speakers I took this
thing I took it out in the lab and took it out there because like I it was too loud to
play in here it's too loud I have clips of me I tried to come up with a way to demonstrate
how it sounds but how do you really if you don't have the speakers if you go you don't
have the speakers to play it back you don't know what it sounds like you have to have
better speakers or you know at minimum I'm the same I do have b-roll of of me playing
music really loud on this thing and then trying to shout over it to demonstrate how loud it
is which I don't know if maybe the patrons want that I might wave file that you upload
somewhere I have I have video of it let me try to shout over this machine like this will
demonstrate it and then I got back to editing I'm like that is stupid as hell I'm not putting
that in the show that's a dumb idea but they're pretty impressive so anyways it's it's a really
nice rig it's also got a 1080p front-facing camera I think is that right yeah so I can
video chat my grandkids and actually a decent multi-array mic too so it's not not too bad
it's the precision 5720 if if you'd like to get your hands on one and also if I've peaked
your interest a little bit check out my review I posted it's a vlog 46 it's up at Jupiter
broadcasting.com right now I call it in the vlog the Linux powered iMac pro killer it's
very click baity but the reason the reason why I did it is I want to I just want to get
the word out there like this is not a paid review Dell denied there was no exchange of
goods for me to do this review I'm just extremely excited by the idea of a really well-built
all-in-one computer that really kicks ass performance wise and less than half the cost
of the iMac Pro and you can buy it from them today Linux on it right now right now and
the iMac Pro is not even available till December so I actually think it's like it just underscores
how late to the game Apple is with the iMac Pro and so much of the market that they used
to address with a device like this is being addressed by this machine really if you don't
need Final Cut in motion yeah or Xcode and then we've talked a lot about how much like
the developer story on Windows has gotten a lot better with the Linux subsystem and
all of that like you could buy one of these I put Windows 10 on it and then run Linux
subsystem and that's very enterprise friendly yeah I think it's a very competitive machine
so I put I titled the vlog Linux powered iMac Pro killer not to be click baity so much as
to just sort of set the conversation is hey there is already competition out here today
and it runs Linux and I think that's a different that's a different state than things years
ago a machine like this that devastated something Apple released would have been would have
been a Windows machine that would have been the big headline it's a Windows this Windows
seven workstation just destroys the latest Apple machine right no now it's an Ubuntu
machine and yeah I'll put the compare I'll put a couple of comparison benchmarks in the
show notes if you want to compare it to your own machine just to kind of see what kind
of Delta you'd have if you did an upgrade like this it's just early days I'm messing
around this open benchmark stuff so if you like it leave me some feedback and give me
suggestions of which benchmarks I should run it's not about coming up with stats and benchmark
numbers that we can sit here and look at charts that's what for onyx is for what I really
want to do with these is just give you some value so you can have comparisons to your
own computer so you can actually walk away from a review like this and have an idea of
what kind of difference it would make for your system if you were to upgrade so it's
not really you know I'm not I'm not like some big some big benchmark guy all of a sudden
I just think it's a great way for the audience to sort of have a comparison to their own
thing you know it gives you something to make it more relevant you can yeah you know I would
love to get I would love to get people's feedback on that on what kinds they use and what they'd
like to see from us so yeah check it out if you were curious more go google the Dell Precision
5720 with Ubuntu they have it on the developer site and check out the vlog too.
Mr. West what else should we mention before we get out of here today because we you know
I mean we got some apparently people are already arriving at the studio for the barbecue.
Did you hear that doorbell?
They are early I think but that's fine.
Barbecue's not till next week.
Yeah come back or unless you have burgers now.
Any other questions or thoughts about the Dell rig before we wrap up for the day?
Do you think your kids would use it if you put it in front of them?
Oh yeah for sure absolutely.
If I put my back on it.
It's almost too nice for the kids.
Yeah I would go more for an XPS line it would make you know if I guess if you had the extra
money it's but I if you're just buying a family machine I might consider the XPS line I don't
know I for me I've always found precision lines to be very very reliable systems there's
like that I've always been a fan of the business class systems and I'm willing to pay just
a bit more for business class if you know it'll last you right yeah yeah yeah yeah
I don't know it's a good question.
All right Mr. West where should people find you throughout the week?
You can find me at Westpac or on the TechSnap program that's right hey just stay tuned we'll
be live with that right now yeah yeah that's coming up next on the jblive.tv stream if
you show up on a Tuesday you can hang out our mumble room hang out in our chat room
and then stick around kick back and wind down with Dan and West on the TechSnap program
go check out the latest episode of Ask Noah for his interview with Veronica Belmont check
out the vlog for a quick video tour of the Dell system I just got done yammering on about
nice and I hope I hope you'll be able to tune in or join us next week for the barbecue
wow that might be a fun show to make it live if you can I guess okay everybody thanks for
joining us and we'll see you right back here next Tuesday for episode 204!
Now it is our duty to title this thing JBtitles.com I'll be curious to see if anybody actually
takes me up on that open benchmark thing because I brought it up in the vlog too and I haven't
really gotten very much traction I think people don't actually want to take the time to do
it unless they're really serious about making maybe we need to make it a little more competitive
you know like hey guys think you can beat Chris's sweet open benchmark I was what I
was now I'm thinking about that is like a server I can go run this on and shame you
or that should be a challenge like here run open benchmark yeah yeah I thought about doing
that in the vlog I just never really executed on it it didn't cross my mind really quick
that's what a lot of people do benchmarks for there's probably like a whole subset of
the PC market or enthusiast PC market that runs 3d mark and other benchmark tools to
do that and go okay this is like the best score with this crazy system how high can
you get and things like that so we've got the Dell review and I think also the fact
that mirror could save desktop Linux so whichever no just kidding I don't know it could go nowhere
yeah that's true who knows who knows I'd like to find out more about that I know I thought
the sway guy was working on something like that too yes I was trying to rack my mind
for the word sway I could not remember during the show I need to try that maybe I'll switch
since you're gonna switch away from now maybe I'll try sway for a while just see if I can
get by with it and that'd be fun yeah let's do that I think it's wasted effort he's such
a cynic don't listen to him mates Wayland miracle oh my god that is some fucking maneuver
in every guy tell you what that Dell looks nice I got burn with the dub rod he says yeah
yeah yeah yeah hybrid graphics with Radeon and guess what I can't use it because no 1604
driver and hybrid graphics is rough man hybrid graphics it's rough yeah now that's probably
not gonna happen with their new developer line of machines I would bet you know you'd
hope not yeah that you know the we have the original Sputnik in production we have an
XPS from like two models ago and they've all been pretty solid