I'm very excited about today's show.
We have something very cool in studio today.
You can tell I'm excited about it because I'm flashing a USB drive right now, and I
only do it when it's for something really important, and it is important.
It is very important.
Did you use Etcher?
Yeah.
You know what?
I just like it.
The only thing I appreciate about Etcher is you can plug in a thumb drive after you've
launched it, and it still detects it.
Yeah.
Because sometimes, oh, stupid me.
Did you get a chance to talk to the resin guys at the fest?
No, I don't think so.
Because they're the ones who make Etcher.
Oh, well, I would have loved to.
I did not.
That would have been great.
But somebody from the fest did drop something off on their way out of town.
Oh?
Yeah.
In studio today for the show, I'm doing a first hands-on with the new System76 Galagopro.
Look at that thing.
Yeah.
So we'll be talking a little bit about it, and we're going to be using that flash drive
to put a proper Arch install on this.
I'll be testing under Ubuntu, too.
I mean, because you have to.
Yeah.
Well, I mean, you've got to check it out as shipped.
You've got to check it out as shipped.
Yeah, absolutely.
So let's get the System76 here in a little bit into the show.
But first, you've got to get that flash drive.
First we've got to get that flash drive taken care of.
Then we can move on.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 196 for May 9, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, Jupyter Broadcasting's longest-running Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Welcome to the flagship Linux program on the Jupyter Broadcasting network.
That's right.
Mwa ha!
Oh, I'm sorry.
I'm sorry.
I didn't mean to get it away there.
With the power, you see.
Yeah.
Well, welcome to the show.
I even managed to override the mic a little bit.
I got so excited.
We have a great show on the program, despite this clipping.
Coming up, Wes, I'm thrilled to say in studio we have the System76 Galago Pro, which we
will be giving our first hands-on impressions on in just a moment.
We have some awesome news from the community.
We have big news for the show itself.
Which next level stuff.
You know, I don't know if you noticed.
Next level.
I don't know if you noticed.
We're getting close to episode 200.
Yes, we are.
I know.
Isn't that wild?
It's shocking, Wes.
But we have a little celebration coming up, and we'll tell you about our first bits of
those plans.
Our friends over at Mozilla have some big news.
Ubuntu is safe on the desktop, kinda, kinda, kinda, sorta.
It's really confusing.
I'll play Mark Shuttleworth's words directly, and then we'll discuss what it means.
Server and IoT though, totally safe.
Totally safe.
You're locked in.
Good to go.
We have a lot of stuff coming up in the show, as well as some news, some open source projects,
and new things that we want to talk about, including the first one, a tool to dump your
login password for the current Linux users.
We'll talk about all that stuff.
But first, you know what we gotta do.
You know what the appropriate thing is.
You know what happens next.
We bring in that virtual lug.
Time appropriate.
Greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
Hey.
Give me a hug.
Whoa.
Dang.
You know, that moved me a little bit.
I'm gonna be honest.
You moved me to belching.
I appreciate it.
Hello, guys.
It's good to see you.
I've missed you.
I feel like it's been three weeks, even though I realize we haven't missed a beat.
I wanted to prepare you though, because we all are now at risk.
A great threat has fallen upon the Linux...
What?
Oh.
Oh, I'm sorry.
I thought I was on cable news.
No, we have a cool new plugin to talk about, or application.
It's called MiniPenguin.
MiniPenguin, not mini, mini.
And it's a tool to dump the login password from the current Linux desktop user.
It's adapted from the idea behind a popular Windows tool called Mimikatz.
And it's just what you think it is.
You run it, and it takes advantage of the clear text credentials that are in memory
by dumping the process and extracting lines that have the highly probable area that's
containing the clear text passwords.
Yeah.
And so in this example, you can see he's able to pull down the Apache user and password.
He's able to pull down the user that's running the GNOME process and the user that's running
the VSFTPD process.
So it's not necessarily limited to just the current user.
Yeah, that's wild, actually.
Now, he's doing this with root credentials on this particular machine.
So you have to have root credentials.
But I think it's worth mentioning just this is possible.
Because when you think about someone getting remote access to your machine, this helps
kind of frame what they are capable of doing once they have access.
And this is a good way to also audit and test, too.
So it's also worth mentioning for legitimate uses.
So you can go find it.
We'll have it linked in the show notes.
Meme program?
Meme?
I don't know.
So there you have it.
We have C Sharp.
You had a question on the top here.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
Essentially, is this something that would be closed by GRSec or Pax, which have recently,
as pointed out on the latest Linus Action news, they've kind of removed themselves from
the process, the development process, or at least the patching process for the current.
You mean sort of like the isolating processes from each other and not letting them snoop
into areas of memory they're not supposed to?
Yeah, I think that is-
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
I think you're right.
That's probably a great example of why things like that are pretty important.
It's also a great example to remind us that this stuff sometimes is just running in memory
somewhere.
You can have the best encryption on your file system, and you can make sure that you keep
all your applications up to date.
But if someone's locally on your box and the stuff's in memory, well, there's not much
you're going to be able to do about it.
That's a lost cause.
Yeah, unless you do something, like C Sharp's saying there, C's Harp, no, it's C Sharp.
Like C Sharp.
I get it, but it's with C.
You got it.
You're a clever one, Chris.
Are you a C Sharp developer?
It's more of a music pun than anything.
Oh, really?
But also a DSP pun, because I'm into DSP as well.
Oh, nice.
I actually went musical first, and then I thought, no, no, this is a geek crowd.
It's probably heens.
Yeah, I can tell.
You guys have the best compression of pretty much every Linux podcast.
Well, thank you.
Aww.
That's the nicest thing anybody has said to me all week.
Dang it.
Those are the things no one else will notice.
Yeah, we also have the best-
Oh, man.
It's so appreciated.
Anyways-
We also have the best mic clipping.
Nobody has our mic clipping.
That's right.
20 dB over, baby.
Guaranteed.
All right.
Well, we've been following the saga of Thunderbird, and we have finally some resolution.
Nothing's going to change.
Pretty much the weird, awkward relationship continues.
But you know what?
That's my interpretation.
I won't put words in Mozilla's mouth.
On the mozilla.org blog, it says, the investigations on Thunderbird's future have concluded.
The Mozilla Foundation has agreed to serve as the legal and fiscal home for the Thunderbird
project, but Thunderbird will migrate off Mozilla Corporation's infrastructure, separating
the operational aspects of the project.
So this means just sort of like even less of what we had before?
Yeah, I guess so.
Not a strong change here.
They write, legally, our existence is still under the Mozilla Foundation through their
ownership of the trademark and their control of the update path and websites that we use.
This arrangement has been working well from the Thunderbird point of view.
But there are still pain points and build release, localization, and divergent plans
with respect to add-ons, to name a few.
These are pain points for both Thunderbird and Firefox, and we want them resolved.
However, the council feels these pain points would not be addressed by moving somewhere
else.
Thus, not much is really changing.
What's next is Thunderbird Council and the Mozilla Foundation executive team will maintain
a good working relationship and talk and make decisions in a timely manner, they say.
The Thunderbird Council and team will make meaningful progress, they say, and they're
going to give either side six months notice if things get shitty and they want to separate.
So this is what we get.
This is what we get.
Now, not addressed in here is the very fact that Thunderbird is really sort of up a creek
because Firefox is moving away from Zool and they're implementing new process technologies
that essentially break all the add-ons and hacks that Thunderbird uses to exist.
And none of that really seems to be addressed in this post.
Nothing really seems to be changing other than now that these guys are going to be responsible
for running their own infrastructure.
Also the section at the end titled, A Bright Future, that didn't sell to you.
You're not optimistic.
No, it just didn't grab me.
Didn't really sell it to me.
I think the real reason why is it feels like exactly what happened to Firefox, only way
more dramatically worse because solutions like Nullius are really starting to gain traction.
I talked to a dozen people at Linux Fest that are using Nullius.
Noah is using Nullius now, you use Nullius.
I know that there's several people in companies that we're familiar with now that are switching
over to Linux on the desktop and Nullius for their mail client.
And there's plenty of other really good ones too.
We're going to talk about System76 in a little bit and they're eyeballing Geary.
Is that right?
Sure.
Oh, future is not bright.
Not bright.
Mumble room any thoughts on Thunderbird before we move on?
I hate to be a downer, but I know it's a topic that people actually seem to care about
because we get lots of people submitting links to Thunderbird stories.
I was trying to find this last time when we were talking about it and I couldn't find
anything.
So I found this blog now, but I really have no thoughts at this point outside of I'm still
going to be using Thunderbird while I read this and then decide what it means to me.
I think that's fair because it's not like the world is crumbling around you.
You still have Thunderbird if it's working for you and you're perfectly fine for a while.
Yeah.
Okay.
I think that's a fair assessment.
Anybody else?
Okay.
I think the harder part is like what would you recommend to a new user if they're starting
today?
Yeah.
Probably Noleus.
I wanted to also just mention really quick.
This has come in across our radar a few times throughout the week.
There's a – I'm going to say – I'm just going to call it a lap book.
There's a 12.3-inch lap book for $329 pre-running Ubuntu, but it has something unique.
It has a 2K screen.
Oh.
Which I really think is a sweet spot.
That's interesting.
I love a 2K screen.
Oh, $329.
That's a pretty nice price.
Yeah.
It's going to have an Intel N3450.
So that's the Apollo Lake quad-core with 2.2 gigahertz burst, and it has an integrated
Intel graphics 500.
So not a workhorse, but hey, it'll open your Chrome.
Yeah.
And you get almost all of the perks of a high-resolution screen without the baggage of high DPI.
You can get 6 gigs of RAM in it.
It has a storage slot where you can add more storage through M.2.
Not bad.
Is that right?
It has a 36-hour battery, which is actually the same that the Galago Pro there has.
Nice.
This seems like it might be a really handy little travel laptop.
Not your main thing, but throw it in your bag and go.
Yeah.
I mean, for $330, US greenbacks there.
That is pretty good.
And you can also, I think, get it with some Windows.
I'm not familiar with it.
Now there's a bad taste in my mouth.
Yeah.
It's got some sort of digital assistant that will read the weather to you or something.
Some people like it.
Yeah.
So there you go.
Listen, Wes, I got a secret for you.
If you want to dig into all things Linux, you want to get a little bit further.
I really do.
If you want to go further, go to Linux Academy.
Just go there.
LinuxAcademy.com.
You go there.
You can get a seven-day free trial.
Learn.
I'm not even going to say try it out.
To learn.
To learn passionately about things like Linux and things around Linux.
AWS, for me, when I first had to go hands-on for a client, was a nightmare.
There was no resource like Linux Academy back then.
I just tried to go in and learn it myself.
And it's doable.
But, man, could I have gotten so much further and really, really used my time better if
I had something like Linux Academy.
Also now, same is true for Azure.
OpenStack conference is going on right now.
A lot of buzz around OpenStack.
You've probably seen a lot of news this last week.
If you follow the news closely about OpenStack, it's because they've got a big conference
going on.
That's right.
We're going to be playing quotes from Mark Shuttleworth when he was interviewed there
here in just a little bit.
And it's a huge topic.
And it's a huge industry trend.
Especially for folks that want to build their own local cloud.
They don't necessarily want to be on another provider, but they want to have some of the
benefits.
OpenStack is essential to, and really, Linux is essential to all of this.
And so Linux Academy is the perfect blend, because it's all things Linux, put together
by Linux enthusiasts, people that are passionate about this stuff.
And then as they have grown, they've met the market demand.
And now Linux Academy stands alone in this category.
From containers to DevOps, big data, and all things nitty-bitty Linux, go to linuxacademy.com
slash unplugged and sign up for a free seven-day trial at linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
And a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
I just had to do a little dance there.
Did you see me?
That was only for you too, because it's not like it's a video show.
Nobody else got to see my dance, Wes.
That was just you.
Unplugged program.
It was lovely.
You should all be very jealous.
If you're lucky, it'll show up somewhere.
Apricity OS.
Oh, Wes.
It comes to an end.
Like all good things, it too comes to an end.
They say it's been their privilege to develop the operating system and to be part of the
community.
But unfortunately, they no longer have the time required for the upkeep.
I think they're shutting it all down too, like updates and all that kind of stuff.
Boom.
This was an Arch-based distro.
I thought these were the big up-and-coming thing, like Arch-based distros were the new
hits.
The new hits.
Yeah.
Is the Arch bubble popped, Wes?
Maybe.
Boy.
Dun-dun-dun.
I mean, we've got Antigros.
Sanjaro is like almost weirdly popular, it seems like.
I did run Apricity for like the better part of six months.
It was really just Arch.
That's why I like to put it in here, because you actually rocked this as your daily driver.
Good old Apricity.
And it was a good out-of-the-box Arch experience, right?
Yeah.
Little did you know, they were struggling to keep it afloat.
Right.
And that's always the risk with these niche, smaller distros.
It can be really hard.
Like, okay, is this something they're dedicated to?
How much, you know, I know like there's some questions like when Solus first appeared,
how you decide, you know, the marketplace of ideas, which things are worthy of support,
which things will actually get that support can be really hard to figure out.
I don't know if Apricity was unique enough or had enough of its own thing or, you know,
just not enough support.
Yeah.
I mean, I don't want to piss on its gravestone.
I would say that I think when you were running it, I generally, you know, would have a reaction
of, oh, I got to try that out.
I never really had that draw.
I was like, oh, okay, so it looks like I could get that with Antigros and I just changed
the theme.
And I never really could connect with what it, and I'm sure it was more than that, but
it failed to connect with me to what it actually was.
And so in that aspect, I'm more inclined to go with one of the larger Arch variants or
Arch itself, if I want that experience.
I think good on them.
They decided they didn't have the time for it, better to move on.
Yeah, there's a lot of trade-offs both ways.
And yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
There you have it.
Apricity, we barely knew ye.
But thank you.
It was fun.
And it was great for Wes for a little while.
I mean, if there's anyone who was using Apricity and hasn't tried Antigros, they certainly
should.
Yeah.
Go give it a look.
Give it a look.
Speaking of Antigros, ours just finished.
Oh, did it?
Oh, very nice.
Thanks, Wes.
Thanks for keeping an eye on that.
You know who else is bailing out of Linux?
Google.
What?
Google sort of.
So do you have any familiarity with the Fuchsia smartphone OS project they have?
A little bit.
I hear it mentioned from time to time.
Yeah, it's like their Skunk Works kind of like in the back room project.
Oh, that's what that smell is.
Yeah.
And unlike Chrome OS or Android, no Linux.
It uses a new Google-developed microkernel called Magenta.
And Fuchsia is running on top of Magenta.
And in this case, Google will not only be dumping the Linux kernel, but also the GPL.
Oh, who?
Yeah.
What's the license here?
It's BSD, Clause 3, MIT, and Apache 2.0.
And dumping the Linux kernel might come as a bit of a shock to maybe some of you listening.
But if you look at Android itself, they really haven't been keeping up with upstream Linux
kernel releases for a while.
Android is maybe a little better off.
But like the Google Pixel, you know, the...
I had that thing right in my pocket.
Which I think is...
I mean, I think they have a current newer build in development that runs off a newer
kernel.
And this new one, kernel 3.18, I believe.
Hmm.
Yeah.
Sorry.
That's rough.
You should have seen...
Oh, man.
The only reason this should be a video show right now is so people could have seen your
face when you...
Ooh, he says.
Oh.
That's just no good.
That was good, Wes.
I mean, I'm a kernel hipster, but still.
That was good.
Yeah.
Google's documentation describes Magenta as targeting modern phones and modern personal
computers with fast processor and non-trivial amounts of RAM with arbitrary peripherals
doing open-ended computation.
Now this is also neat because the apps, they're written in another one of Google's background
projects called Flutter, a project written in Dart, which is Google's reboot of JavaScript,
which on mobile has a focus on high performance, like 120 frames per second type app performance.
It's also Vulkan-based and their renderer is called Escher, and it promises to have
volumetric soft shadow capabilities in its UI.
Yeah.
It's designed to run the design-heavy material design from Google.
So their whole thing here is maybe a mobile phone OS that would free them away from the
GPL, and if you look at it, the basic design elements just kind of look like Android.
They are getting this to a point where this is going to be a one-to-one UI swap.
If your stuff uses material design, like all of Google's stuff does, it's just going to
look better.
You wouldn't even know.
Look at these design mock-ups and these early prototypes.
It really does just look, yeah.
Looks like Android.
It's those shadows, man.
So even before we ever really get to good Android apps on the Linux desktop, that whole
hope is just going to go right away.
Well, the problem is I have is I love that everybody here has got a Linux in their pocket
line.
You know, they've got the Linux in the pocket.
Yeah, that is a good one, isn't it?
We're all fucking around running with Linux.
You know, I love that go-to because it's like so poignant, like how Android is Linux-powered
and ergo Linux is everywhere.
And then you get into the cloud and you get into networking and all, and then of course
huge.
It's just that whole line of, they're in our pocket, if they do this, they're going to
exclude that.
And that, Google would wrong me.
That's all I care about.
I really, I actually, in some regards, hope that they do drop Linux.
I wonder if this will be worse for small players, you know, like with less hope of, you know,
if there's less upstream development, they don't have the, you know, the crazy momentum
that the Linux project has, what's the kind of, what's the hardware enablement story going
to be like, right?
I mean, it's no problem for Samsung to make sure their latest system on a chip works with
it because they want to sell this, you know, use this platform.
But what about like, you know, third-party retailers, are you trying to use, you know,
more generally sourced components?
I wonder if this will be worse.
C-Sharp, you feel like it would be a bad development.
I actually kind of feel like it could be a good development if they moved away from Linux.
I don't know.
I feel like if the NSA, which is so at odds with the citizenry, especially of the US,
I mean, I'm in Canada, but is he constantly in contention with a government body, then
I don't see how Google is really going to steamroll anything more than the NSA could,
you know what I mean?
Okay.
Fair point.
Well, Mini-Mech, you actually make a strong point.
One of the best things that's happened to Linux is manufacturers have to support Android,
huh?
Well, the problem is, you see, that if manufacturers start to develop drivers only for that foxy
system, Linux is out of the, yeah, you can't use it anymore.
So these devices will become some kind of wallet garden controlled by Google.
I've always felt like Linux is a bit like time travel and that you can use it for powers
of absolute good, like Captain Kirk does to save the world from aliens that want to communicate
with whales.
Or you can use it to go back and save Hitler.
And I feel like what Google does is they use Linux to surveil and monitor the people on
a mass scale and then privatize that and sell it back to carriers, they use it for advertising,
the government gets access to it through information requests, and they do all of it with the assistance
of Linux.
It's like using the ultimate tool for good for the ultimate suppression of the people,
privatized domestic spying is a huge problem and they use Android to do it.
And to me, I just, I can't get over it.
It's like they took something great and they used it for evil, it feels like.
And part of me hates the fact that Linux is complicit in this.
And so if they stopped using Linux on Android, this mass surveillance operating system that
we all happily buy and then pay carriers to track us even further and sell that information,
at least they won't be using Linux to pull it all off, at least in the devices themselves.
So that's worth it in your eyes?
I don't know.
Like relevance drop that Linux may have?
I mean, I feel like, I mean, I guess if this thing is awesome and gets a really good upstream
community, but what will the governance look like, right, and will this ever be targeted
for other devices?
Will there be third party ROM?
If they could do something that would make application or I'm sorry, operating system
updates more deliverable to more devices and get more security patches out to consumers,
this could be a net benefit for consumers too.
That's true.
I doubt that it's Linux that's preventing them from doing that.
So in fact, all of the issues I think that I have with Android, it's none of its Linux.
It's all performance stuff, which is on the Android layer.
It's all the other things around Android and none of it's because of Linux.
It's not the kernel that's stopping you.
Yeah, it feels like if they wanted to solve some of their problems, dropping Linux isn't
what they need to do.
But at the same time, maybe it's, I don't know, maybe there could be some good for it.
Although Minimac makes a really great point, I really think that Linux has benefited greatly
from device manufacturers having to work with Android, especially at the embedded level.
I think it's been huge.
So that would be definitely a step back.
Yeah, we'll see.
We'll see.
We'll see what happens.
Project Fuchsia looks like it's going to be interesting, and we're seeing more screenshots.
We're seeing more stuff about it.
Yeah, becoming real.
Yeah, exactly.
I have something really, really cool to talk about.
So last week we mentioned the caster soundboard, and this week, holy crap, Wes, I can say it
has really gotten a life of its own.
So thank you to everybody who's been taking a look at trying to make this thing better.
We've been getting a lot of submissions and our poll requests.
And it's also...
Oh, that's awesome.
We have the AUR, too, so now you can rebuild it from the AUR if you want to install it
really easily.
We have eight contributors, 31 commits, two branches already.
And if you don't remember from last week, this is a soundboard for Hot Keen and Playing
Back, all the little like sound bites and music intros and stuff like that we have on
our shows.
And look at this, Wes.
You can...
Here's how to build it from source.
Here's how to install all the requirements on Fedora, Debian, even some Mac OS X thing.
Oh, it's in brew.
Look at that.
Yeah, it's in brew.
Yeah.
It's so cute.
And then you can pull it down.
The whole thing is in the AUR, though.
Gosh, that's cool.
It's really neat to see the community come together like this because people are now
pulling it down and playing with it.
And like producer Michael before the show was saying, you know, I just have it down
on my machine.
I've been playing around with it.
That's awesome.
It's starting to look really cool.
It's starting to really come together.
Yeah.
So if you want to check out, it's an open source soundboard that we're working on right
now with the community.
And we're adding in features that there really hasn't been something like this on Linux.
There's a few on the Mac that are pretty good, but we're trying to do this on Linux.
And Caster Soundboard is pretty much there.
It's so awesome.
And it's not even an Electron app.
No.
It's a C++ in the Qt 5 app, as they say.
Caster Soundboard, an awesome community effort, originally created a couple of years by a
community member.
He's back, too.
He's in there working.
Oh, awesome.
Yeah.
That is so cool.
I really appreciate it.
Yeah.
Covariant sensor or covariant tensor.
I can't remember.
It's something like that.
Yeah.
Michael's in there.
Maelstrom's in there.
Chasing Logic.
Of course, the Beard's in there.
ASC is in there.
GDogg is in there.
Freq Labs is in there.
Freq Labs, whatever he goes by.
So thank you guys for working on it.
You can see the little spike right there in the activity.
It's really cool.
So it's Caster Soundboard.
We'll have a link in the show notes if you want to play around with our free open source
soundboard that we're developing for production purposes here at Jupiter Broadcasting, but
really creating it so the entire community has something they can mess around with.
And it's like caster soundboard-git if you want to install it from the AUR.
Now, oh, I wish I, speaking of the soundboard, I wish I had my soundboard set up right now
because I would totally do a breaking news clip because this is breaking news right here
on the Unplugged show.
Yeah, that's right.
It is.
So Linux Unplugged is at an interesting point.
It's the last big Linux show that we have right now.
User Air is about to start back up.
Linux Action News is about to start.
Ask NOAA is brand new.
Brand new.
Growing.
And so really the now Linux powerhouse in the Jupiter Broadcasting lineup is Linux Unplugged.
So let's take a moment and talk about something we're doing as episode 200 closely approaches.
This is just between you and me and the audience and the community listening.
So nobody tell anyone we're going to go into the Cone of Silence.
I am deeply concerned.
All right.
So the Cone of Silence here.
I just love that clip.
I should have a reason to use it because I actually want you to tell everybody.
We are launching a Linux Unplugged subreddit to replace the Linux Action Show subreddit.
It always felt like Linux Unplugged was kind of like the younger sibling that was tagging
along Linux Action Show and being like, I want to have fun too.
I want to have a subreddit.
We like Linux.
Yeah.
And so now, no, no.
We're grown up.
We graduated.
And our Linux Unplugged is officially a thing and we're hoping it can be used to input content,
give us feedback for the show, really kind of let's take another shot at this and make
something that could be possibly known as one of the cool places to get really good
conversation and discussion around a story and links around Linux.
One of the things that I am really thankful for for the community of our Linux Action
Show is what an awesome collection of just good Linux news resources it is.
Absolutely.
Other Linux subreddits, but we always had the best stuff and sometimes first.
And I love that about our Linux Action Show.
I'd love to see that continued at Linux Unplugged.
And it was like an organic, like, this is exciting to me.
I want people to, you know, talk about this.
Yeah.
And I would love to also, speaking of things, I just really love to see for like our goals
and our intentions for this.
I like this is like my high point items is the conversation around these stories, insights,
people's opinions, but like a good level discussion that is really kind of valuable and helps
give people a better idea or thought or see a different perspective on a story.
Doesn't have nothing that gets like all like flame worry, but just good discussion and
context around stories can be so valuable and also help weigh how the community is interpreting
the story.
So I know if I doesn't always necessarily decide if you go on a show, but man, it helps
our discussion in the show a whole bunch.
So if you want to participate, reddit.com slash r slash Linux Unplugged.
We also don't forget we have the other subreddits.
We have our Jupiter Broadcasting, our Ask Noah, Koda Radio, Techsnap on Filter.
They're all rocking and rolling too.
Yeah.
I'm really thinking it could be neat and maybe like in the next 200 episodes, this place
will blow up too.
Yeah.
What do you think, Wes?
You think it's crazy to launch a subreddit in 2017?
Are we nuts?
No, I think it makes sense.
Does it?
I'm a little worried we might have lost it.
Maybe we've gone crazy.
Maybe.
I mean, we'll see.
Right.
We're taking a risk.
We're going to try it again.
Yeah.
I suppose so.
I suppose.
I mean, the Mumble Room is always good.
It's like a direct place to talk to us.
If you want to be live, go to jblive.tv on Tuesdays.
We're almost always live at 2 p.m. Pacific and we just kind of lock it there so that
way you know when to join the Mumble Room.
You can get it converted to your local time at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar
and you can get in our chat room and if you do bang mumble, you'll get the server information
and then you connect.
We do mic checks and we ask that you have headphones on, you have like a headset or
a good microphone or some kind that we can at least hear you clearly and then you get
in and you can chat with us one-on-one.
Yeah all right.
So anyways, I made a post up on the, I don't really have much more to add, I guess that's
kind of it.
I made a post up on the Linux Action Show subreddit if you guys want to read more and
I have the details in there.
That is linked in the show notes.
Yeah.
So thank you everyone to our Linux Action Show.
That has been such an awesome resource for not just Linux Action Show but also the Unplugged
program.
The discussions there have been helpful, the stories have been helpful and I ask that we
take the best of all of it and we move to Linux Unplugged subreddit.
We take the best and we do it all over again.
I'm not afraid to start to build all over.
Just bring it up from the beginning again Wes.
Also be sure to check out linuxactionnews.com, no ww right now, just linuxactionnews.com.
Subscribe to the RSS feed there because episode one will be landing very soon.
There is a prototype beta episode over there, skip it.
It's fine.
But you know, it's Joe and I sitting down for the first time trying out a show and it
went good.
And so we're like, all right, we'll publish it.
We have something to create the RSS feed around and we can start working with us.
But it's not intended as the first episode.
It's more like a concept pilot episode.
Practice.
It's over there but the RSS feeds are live now.
The episode page is up at linuxactionnews.com so check that out.
Also Wimpy, who couldn't join us today, he's traveling, but did get a chance to stop by
Ask Noah live at Linux Fest Northwest.
Did they have a good conversation?
Oh yeah.
So that's in the latest episode of Ask Noah.
I would also suggest you check that out if you haven't listened to Ask Noah yet because
a really thought provoking conversation and if you are an Electron lover or hater, I would
really encourage you to listen to Ask Noah.
Here's another thing that's really nice about Ask Noah.
You always know exactly how long it is because he's also broadcasting on the radio so it's
always exactly the same length so it's easy to fit into your schedule.
Ask Noah 6 live from Linux Fest Northwest.
If you miss Wimpy on the Unplugged program, check that out.
They had a great conversation and of course you can find him on the Ubuntu podcast too.
It was so great to get to meet Wimpy in person.
Yeah.
That was one of my highlights of the Fest this year.
And he really made the best out of the Fest.
Turns out he's even more fun in person.
Yeah.
You know what's great about Wimpy is this is what I really appreciated about him.
If you got an inclination that he's a pretty cool guy online, it's like that but way more
in person.
And that's what's so great.
It's like when you meet somebody in person and they're even cooler than they seem online.
Just a genuinely really great guy and a gentleman.
So it was great to get to meet Wimpy in person and hang out with him for the weekend.
Odyssey, you made it back too, huh?
So you survived the long drive?
Good job, man.
Yes, indeed.
That's great.
You made it back just in time for the Hanford site to start to have an emergency so that's
got to feel good.
Yeah.
Yeah, Albert made it out here too as well as a whole bunch of other people but we had
a good time and it was a pretty cool Fest.
We had a little bit of coverage of it in the Linux action show on last Sunday if you want
to check that out.
All right.
So I want to cover what's going on at Canonical and I want to talk about what Mark Shallower
said today and then I want to do our first hands on with Gallego Pro.
So we have much more to come so I want to thank Ting for setting us up for the next
bit of the show and you can go to linux.ting.com to sign up and get $25 off your Ting plan
in credit or if you bring a device or if you need a device, you can get $25 off a device.
Now consider my friends, this could also be an opportunity to get a very reasonable usable
smartphone that maybe gets updates for a little bit, things like that because one of the great
things about Ting is they don't stand in the way of security updates, they don't have any
games to play, they don't have some image they have to lay on there or some sort of
weird ass services that the OS has to support.
They don't care how you use Ting, it's just use what you want and then you pay for it.
Your minutes, your messages and your megabytes, whatever you use and that's what you pay.
It's $6 for the line and that includes their awesome great customer service, their fantastic
dashboard to manage it all.
That includes all of the great perks of Ting like anything you would expect from a standard
phone line because it is like your voicemail, your text messaging, picture messaging, hotspot,
tethering, it's all in there for $6 a month plus your usage.
It's so fantastic, the average monthly bill per device for Ting customers is $23.
I've been a Ting customer for over two years, linux.ting.com, you go there, you sign up,
you try them out and you see what I've been talking about.
Also, really great, they have CDMA and GSM network.
So whatever works better in your neck of the woods, you can use on Ting and if you go to
another neck, you can use a different network if you need to.
It's for somebody like myself who likes to go on road trips, killer freaking feature.
Linux.ting.com and a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring this here unplugged program.
Linux.ting.com.
So Canonical is on the path to IPO which is the initial public offering for those of you
who might not be familiar with the term and that means they become a public company with
all of the responsibilities and duties therein, i.e.
Obligations to make profits and things like that.
This is confirmed by Mark Shalloworth at the OpenStack Summit.
He said that they are pushing on, so this is in the shadow of course of the recent announcement
that they're dropping investments in Unity 8, the phone and convergence and that Mark
would be coming, would be regaining the CEO title, stepping in for Jane.
This is big and this is going to be a fundamental shift in the gearing of Canonical.
Do not misunderstand.
This is a huge development.
It's going to mean a realigning of the company's priorities, refocusing and Mark seems pretty
fired up about this.
Putting the company on the path to IPO, he said we must figure out what steps we need
to take moving forward, focusing Canonical on its most profitable business lines.
Ubuntu is not going to die.
Ubuntu is the default platform on cloud computing in Juju and storage and OpenStack and on
the edge.
He says it's nearly unstoppable.
We need to work out our IoT path and at the same time we had to cut out those parts that
couldn't meet investors' needs.
The immediate work is to get all of the parts of the company profitable.
I mean that sounds like what they'll need to do in the future.
So it's within that context that Mark was at OpenStack and The Cube, welcome to The
Cube live from the OpenStack Summit conference, asked him this question here.
The three legs of computing, personal computing, data center computing or cloud computing and
the edge, the IoT world, which is neither data center nor personal, of those I had dreamed
of Ubuntu as sort of going mainstream in all three, clearly Ubuntu is the de facto standard
now for cloud computing and the data center and also I think arguably for the edge.
Where we failed and I feel responsible for miscalculating effectively is our push into
personal computing, phones, tablets, PCs.
Where we failed was our push into personal computing, phones, tablets and PCs.
And PCs.
Where we failed, our past tense, past tense, which I think is also pretty important there.
And yikes, you know that to me sounds like a man who had a bit of a dream and that dream
got crushed and now he's dealing with a new reality and he's just done with it.
And you know he's like really, he calls it my miscalculation I think is what he said.
Ubuntu is sort of going mainstream in all three, clearly Ubuntu is the de facto standard
now for cloud computing and the data center and also I think arguably for the edge.
Where we failed and I feel responsible for miscalculating effectively is our push into
personal computing, phones, tablets, PCs.
Wow.
That's a strong statement and I think that is a statement that if you take it into its
full entirety it obviously represents a lot of reflecting on Mark on this particular issue.
And so the question is in this context in which he now views the landscape, where does
desktop Linux fit in?
Where does Ubuntu on desktop fit in?
And so I think the desktop remains really important to us in support of developers who
are really the lifeblood of free software and open source and IT innovation.
But as a business we chose to focus on these two, the cloud where we are very strong and
IOT where I think the story is only just beginning but again we're at the center of everything.
So they're going to focus on the desktop for developers essentially, which means it sounds
like a narrow focus like this is going to be our market.
You know what's interesting about that statement?
Sounds like Fedora workstation.
No you meant something else.
Hey, you made me clip again Wes, you made me clip again, you are getting me this week,
you are getting me.
I apologize guys, it's all Wes' fault.
It's my fault.
It's all Wes' fault.
It was good Wes, no, now you made me forget because I was so good.
No it reflects exactly what Dell told us when we were down there Dell said you know we kept
trying Linux and we thought it was going to be like this low cost desktop, we thought
it was going to be the cheap way to maybe take a hundred bucks off of a PC.
So that's how we initially positioned it and it wasn't selling.
We didn't understand.
We didn't want these Celeron machines and these Atom machines.
What they wanted was they wanted to develop on Linux and so once we started creating the
Project Sputnik and we focused on developers specifically with Project Sputnik, we started
selling like crazy.
Now we have a hundred percent year-over-year growth.
They're selling numbers that are just intense right?
Now the reason why that I think it's interesting that Mark's sentiment and Dell sentiment lines
up is because it must be reflected in sales numbers.
The part that's disconnected from all of this for me is the thing that we hear over and
over again is that Ubuntu is selling like crazy in India and China and that it's almost
half of the PC sales over there or that you go into the stores and the half of the store
are Ubuntu machines and half the store are Windows machines and that Ubuntu is extremely
successful in India and in China and are all of those developers?
No because then you're told that the story is well these are people that don't have a
market bias so they're able to go in and you know assess the computer not based on Windows
or Mac or Linux but just is it a computer and they're buying these Ubuntu machines and
it's successful there.
So it would seem like they also are getting quite a bit of successful in the totally new
user market but and I hear that a lot but then when we talk about it now we're just
going to focus on developers.
Hang on Chris, aren't a lot of those installations just getting wiped for a pirate version of
Windows straight away?
Perhaps, Dell would say no but I don't know.
I don't know.
Of course they would.
Maybe and so you think that's why they're so easily ready to just jettison that type
of user?
They're not real Ubuntu users?
Well yeah and as for the developers well what's the whole subsystem for Linux on Windows all
about?
Isn't that about developers?
Yeah seemingly so.
Yeah that or yeah let's not go down that path because that leads to a dark path because
there's so many other solutions for that.
I'm getting a mixed message.
I'll tell you what I'm getting a mixed message because it's while it's consistent from what
Dell would tell you Project Sputnik is only representative of their success in the US
market.
Outside of the US they're just selling to average users and I think Canonical is saying
we're not going to be targeting those users anymore.
I mean it doesn't seem like there's a lot of glamour there.
I don't know about the profitability or the business incentives but like does it seemingly
they're placing the bet that it matters more to become you know completely adopted and
ingrained in these IoT and cloud markets than it does to be the low-end desktop for a lot
of the world.
Or just that like is the return not that great like they already have you know they'll continue
making an open source desktop that you can install if people want to use it if hardware
retailers they are already using it you know what does it get them to continue to invest
in it?
And I think the thing that we will just have to wait and see in this whole story is and
it's almost it's getting to the point now where it's starting to I think pass its prime
and we can move on until things develop but how much of a desktop experience do they end
up creating?
Like we will see the priority that the desktop has inside Canonical will be represented in
what we get as a product in 1710 and 1804 if there is a significant amount of tweaks
or theming or you know you can define significant however you like but if there is an amount
of tweaks or customizations or changes to make it more palatable in some some way out
of the box that would seem to imply resources testing personnel i.e. effort.
If it is stock Ubuntu GNOME with no changes really just hardly any you know we've just
repackaged things up we put it in our repo and now we're going to give you security fixes
that to me would suggest a low amount of effort and energy putting and personnel etc. put
into the desktop and that's just the proof will just be as your buddy Bill says in the
puddin it'll just be in the puddin right there in that puddin yeah under the skin yeah just
just right there skin deep.
Mini Mac I will give you one more chance to chime in go ahead yeah thanks.
So I guess Ubuntu will stay the base for a lot of distributions and they will continue
to publish a somehow default configuration for that system but it's not their primary
goal remember China has its own Ubuntu distribution called Kalin right I don't know if I spell
it right but it will stay the base for a lot of distributions we all love.
That is a great point and I'm surprised I forgot about that because that's exactly that's
exactly solves that problem doesn't it of course it makes much that that actually that
fills in the gap Kailin or Kalin Kailin of course that's why that's okay.
What is it?
Chillin yeah chillin right chillin right thanks Joe it's chillin that is of course that fills
in that gap so that's why there's something stepping up to fill that need of that makes
sense so that that really you know what geez the more I think about this the more sense
this makes I think Canonical is going to knock it out of the park I think I think I've never
been tempted to invest in a company I don't know if I should or not but man I would be
tempted to buy a few shares in Canonical because what has been the criticism of Canonical all
along why can't they just focus like they have these things that make money but they
just keep going off and doing this stuff and now that's exactly what Mark is doing he's
narrowing things down he's going to go with what works and they these are profitable aspects
of the business it's not like they have to figure out a way to make they're not Twitter
they already make money they just were spending it on stuff that wasn't making money they're
already going to make money there if you were an investor that wanted to get in on this
market how could you not be interested in investing in the company behind the thing
that runs the most on AWS and Azure and Rackspace and on private clouds like how could you not
want to invest in that company that has a very solid IOT offering that's pretty much
ready to go and already being used by companies like Dell I would be pretty much in on that
if I if so it seems like a slam dunk and if they're going to let some of their other projects
like Chillin or Ubuntu Mate or the Plasma you know Kubuntu slash Neon groups they can
continue to serve those markets they can then now focus on the very thing that seems to
be selling XPSs and HPs and system 76 machines and make a great desktop there if they put
energy into it so they could be lined up for like a super home run like if they do this
right this could be they could be the next Red Hat don't you think and only I think in
some ways they're better positioned I don't know about revenue wise but they're better
positioned in terms of deployment in all of these markets that are making all of the money
right now seems like investors are going to go nuts go ahead but is it not the case they've
invested all this money into the community stuff and the flavors and now it's kind of
like they can just almost abandon the desktop to them and they've put enough investment
in and they'll keep helping them but they don't need to pay developers so much anymore
because they've got a bun to go home which is fine and they're basically saying we're
just going to ship stock that as far as I understand it yeah I think that is smart it's
what they can make a difference on what they make money yeah exactly and they probably
only need to support the desktop as much as it helps their own dog food in an internal
uses right it's going to be great I was I've been everybody coming up at Linux we've been
talking about this stuff talking about it's been a really big pot I don't think anybody's
ever talked about Ubuntu as much as they did this year it in fact in years past I've actually
been like where's Ubuntu this year there was a booth this year people were talking about
it was a big topic of conversation and what I realized was is damn did Joe and I pick
a good time to launch Linux action news yeah no kidding it's like nailed that and user
error we're gonna have a bunch of discussions and this show where the mumble room and you
and I can chew on this stuff like we've it's never been better time to have shows to be
launching shows right now around Linux to where we can actually talk about this stuff
in a way that's really appropriate for the size of the topic and all that just I think
it's going to be an ongoing interesting point and we're going to be watching a massive transition
by a big player and I don't think I've ever felt better about their potential I think
if you step back and look what they're doing here it's going to be the most sustainable
long term for that company we all were sitting here waiting for them to pull the plug on
the is and it really is sad that it means it's a lot of people are losing their jobs
and I think we'll be hearing more about that pretty soon and it's you know it is a very
unfortunate aspect of this story and I don't want to underplay it because some of those
folks some of us probably know and you know so there really are some ambitious things
that they were trying to do that would have been awesome if they could have if they could
have super like I was just talking about how awful Android is imagine if Ubuntu Touch
had come along and saved us from that like there was I know I know so I don't mean to
underplay that aspect of it but at the same time we were all holding our breath hoping
that this thing didn't run the company into the ground because it seemed to us on the
outside like it was an intractable force to to defeat right so well we can be sad or
miss some of these elements it's certainly better than a world that didn't have a bunch
of it all mm-hmm yeah yeah so there you go the Ubuntu desktop will remain important but
it sounds like it's gonna be more developer focused if I follow with Mark's Mark who had
to say I OBG Ubuntu also had a write-up on that particular aspect of the interview and
I have the entire interview where Mark also talks about taking over CEO roles again and
some of the products are doing specifically for OpenStack that is also available in the
show notes and you can read Joey's write-up at OMG Ubuntu hey Wes you know what I do from
time to time in fact I was just doing it this morning creating droplets what creating droplets
Wes I'd be creating droplets like other people be creating problems I got you're not using
that API that mm-hmm Wes I'm all about that API I'll tell you what to I'm all about that
dashboard yeah I like that dashboard what I love about digital ocean is somebody came
to me today and they're like I need to do something like you know what we could spin
that up on a droplet in no time it's so nice to know that you can get started within seconds
you can do a full support totally like installed stack with Ubuntu LTS Docker and an application
ready to go or you can deploy a base system and set it up yourself beginner expert you're
gonna have no problems if you're messing around in the container space and you know quote
unquote messing as in probably running your entire infrastructure on it now at this point
hey oh you got you got it you got it you got guys it's no problemo at digital ocean digital
ocean honey badger about containers in a way that's epic you ever done anything like that
anything anything like that craziness like oh I don't know Wes Docker LXD containers
on that they're digital ocean infrastructure with the SSDs and the bandwidths and the CPUs
yeah it's amazing I know it's it's amazing yeah I got next cloud going I've even got
I'll tell you what new fedora installs oh go check out digital oceans new fedora update
little pro tip for you if you want to mess around with fedora on the server specifically
maybe fedora atomic go check out digital ocean you want to mess around with core OS digital
ocean you want to go put an Ubuntu or Debian box into production digital ocean yeah just
go over to digital ocean.com and sign up and when you're there use our promo code do unplugged
you get a $10 credit you can try out the $5 rigs two months for free you can try out one
of their high memory systems or request early access to the high CPU you'll be able to deploy
in seconds SSDs for all of the drives lightning fast networking highly available block storage
which you can attach up to 16 terabytes as a block device to your Linux box tons of amazing
open source applications you can use out of the box community documentation that is the
best load balancing as a service monitoring alerting and that is just on top of the simple
straightforward pricing did you mention that block storage that block storage one block
at a time up to 16 terabytes show up as a block device play with setup best why not
why not and look at this West for three cents an hour you can get a crazy great rig if you
use our promo code do unplugged you apply that to your account and you get a $10 credit
oh I know I know digital ocean.com go over there sign up use our promo code do unplugged
in a big thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring this here unplugged program digital ocean.com
I did a little dramatic there at the end he did just for you speaking of things that are
dramatic holy smokes am I excited about this Gallego Pro this thing is dramatic a dramatic
design a dramatic flair look at where the power buttons that isn't that cool right on
the side interesting I like it a lot so yeah I have a I've had the opportunity here at
Linux fest Northwest to steal a Gallego Pro and get my hot grabby little hands on it so
I've been trying it out for about 24 hours at this point so I'm not doing a review I'm
just giving you first on first impression hands on and be an unboxing but it's already
out of the box it never was in a box never was you know it's true what's true it does
have quite a bit of ports which is really a crazy number of ports and I've been reliably
informed that the USB-C port on this is a four PCI lane Thunderbolt USB-C port which
is what you would need for for a full external GPU that would be slick yeah wouldn't that
be interesting if that developed later on so this Gallego Pro here is I think a pre-production
so I'm sort of doing like a like a like a like a early review kind of look at it and
right now I've just kind of got the in bag in hand experience carrying it around for
about 24 hours it's really nice because it goes right in the bag a little bit of extra
room because it's you know it's like 13 not huge yeah screens really nice and vibrant
I like I like the availability of the ports I'm I'm still trying to work out what the
battery life is like because like I said I've just been messing around with it a little
bit and I'm get I get different readings at different times so there's there's all that
we just tried putting an arch on this thing so that'll be you know that looks like it
woke up from suspension yeah yeah and we're gonna be of course putting Ubuntu back on
this thing and putting the system 76 PPA on there and all that it's got an NVMe hard drive
in there yeah yeah in fact I think it actually has capacity for a 2.5 inch as well oh that's
kind of awesome two hard drives on this little thing which I think is really nice if you've
got a bunch of clips you're editing or whatever HDMI display port USB 3.0 a and of course
is that Ethernet uh-huh that's Ethernet right there's got a little door and they say it's
their best latch yet on those you know those Ethernet ports that have the little latch
on them they say it's their best their best latch you know that's not one of those features
that's big for me but I you know talk about it I understand you know I understand that
for some people that really is important oh my gosh I mean for me it's it's like fundamentals
here because every day I'm copying gigabytes and gigabytes of footage around I think just
for me like I'm okay with the like USB C or USB dock just because if I need to use it
then like I'm gonna set it I don't like I'm not going to a data center where I have to
go plug in some Ethernet thing but I get that people do yeah I mean that makes sense yeah
if yeah if you were if you could just like if your workflow was like I'll just sit down
the dock and you know but it does say a lot about system 76 that they've thought and put
in the care to put that there because they understand their user base and that people
really do want it yeah I mean this is essentially what I like about it is you get the advantages
of a thin and light machine but no dongles required right ww you had a question is this
part of the new systems 76 they're going to design it and make it themselves or not yet
no not yet they're so they're going to do desktops first and I bet I would bet we would
see that around the beginning of 2018 and then we will see laptops shortly or maybe
depending on how it goes a little bit after that because you think about it it's two problems
you have to solve right first you have to get the manufacturing plant up and going and
get all the robotics and any personnel staffing that's needed things like that then you got
to get once you get the supply pipeline you you kind of have to work out some of the kinks
and to do your own custom laptop you then are also custom designing the motherboard
and things like that and so I think they've got a they've got to work through all of those
stages so this is this is from an upstream provider that they've heavily customized in
fact they are the only OEM offering it in this specific configuration too so they do
have an exclusive on their hands but they didn't design the all of the internal motherboard
components and stuff like that yet but they do work with the with them like right now
they're working on refining some of the firmware firmware cooling functionality and stuff like
that you got to keep it cool you do yeah what'd you think of the keyboard when you were messing
around with it so far it was pretty good yeah it would felt comfortable yeah I nice to type
on yeah I really didn't mind it yeah I'd say the key travels actually pretty decent really
especially for a laptop this thin it's got a core i7 in the thing too which is nice for
a laptop of this size yeah I'm looking forward to trying this thing out and coming back with
a with a full review yeah I think I'll really be curious to see especially since you've
spent so much time with with X various XPS models and yeah Dell offerings and previous
system 76 right yeah yeah I had a chance to play with it some to add Linux fast where
they have their new theme and stuff on there yeah and so they had known three installed
with their system 76 pop theme and whatnot I don't know if this is a consequence of the
high dpi and the beautiful screen but the one they had at their booth at least for a
little while the trackpad it was just not I think the acceleration wasn't turned up
or what hadn't been tuned at all so that was a little bit like that was not the best experience
that I had there so I'll be really curious what you think of it after after some time
yeah wonder if they had it with a wonder if their system there had lib input or not that's
yeah I'm not sure a big difference so speaking of system 76 and their gnome intentions Carl
the man behind system 76 has posted essentially like a gnome manifesto if you will over on
the system 76 blog and he writes home sweet gnome it's been a while but we're excited
to be back and we've been playing with our new toy for the last few weeks he says they're
gonna make a consistent theme that was born to desire when the desire to provide customers
with a consistent experience all the way through the OS pop is bright and beautiful and very
system 76 they're gonna have pop ship on their computers with a boon to in 1710 this October
and they're already testing it obviously there's different things in here like they talk a
little bit maybe about working with Katie connect the integrating Katie connect with
gnome and potentially it sounds like he implies maybe some iOS support because he says in
this post Katie connect only works with Android friends so I have to buy a new phone maybe
we can do something about that kind of like hey yeah I don't know what that awesome yeah
this though this one we got to talk about this one I'm really you know I'm not so sure
about PPAs anymore I feel like the world is moving on anybody writes in here specifically
a portion about PPAs you say system 76 delivers fixes themes and drivers via the system 76
PPA which is a boon to his personal package archive when a book to upgrades from one distribute
version from one distribution version to the next it disables PPAs the stopping customers
from receiving updates to their products disabling makes sense for unmaintained PPAs but for
maintained PPAs there should be a mechanism to keep them active we will submit patches
for update manager that adds a config file to allow listed PPAs to remain active during
a release upgrade he says that we think other OEMs partners and projects will appreciate
this functionality as well the only thing is that I'm reading there which kind of sets
off like a worry for me here is it sounds like they're gonna fork update manager and
even if it's a small fork like but they're gonna they're gonna have their own version
of update manager that checks a config file and then they will submit that upstream and
if OEMs or Ubuntu want to take that on they can the the the issue I would have with that
is what at what point does it stop becoming Ubuntu so if you have a PPA a persistent PPA
that persists through upgrades and you're applying fixes and patches to it between upgrades
is that still Ubuntu then is that or is that more like system 76 to which might be a good
idea as well maybe that's a good idea system 76 because I I I have found that the you know
in total the disabling of PPAs is a better practice than keeping them enabled between
upgrades in in whole now the idea here of course the system 76 could test and fix things
before they ever ship it right but it seems like you could still end up with a window
where customers are jumping on board they're upgrading before the PPA is ready then they
and it doesn't get properly disabled and things get broken I mean it seems like this so this
is the one part of all of this strategy I'm like this seems like there could be a little
derivative of Ubuntu happening here there could be some upgrade shenanigans but if they
manage it correctly and they test it which they do a lot of testing they should be able
to hammer out I'd say 90% of the issues so it should be doable but it does sort of red
raise a little bit of red flag and I do understand why they why they would want that right like
especially for users like yeah I'm gonna update and but don't know enough to go you know check
out their PPA list or their sources list or anything like that to be like oh well why
don't why don't I get the new themes or the you know whatever yeah I would wonder too
I would if it would become less of a problem so it sounds like they're gonna upstream a
lot of stuff mm-hmm and so if folks upstream just accepted some of these patches in then
they could reduce the amount of stuff they have to shove in the PPA over time to sort
of sort of negating the issue over time maybe yeah but that would depend on upstream
picking them up but anyways if you're curious about what they're going with gnome this is
really interesting and they they toss in some details about the pop theme which I think
this is gonna be really cool to see system 76 get behind their own theme here and really
do something different because it it obviously could be used by other folks that aren't using
system 76 machine so you could just end up having a well-known hardware OEM that's that's
keeping a theme alive that just ends up being a really well like theme on the gnome desktop
which could be pretty cool too we'll see because people are liking it the pop theme
is pretty it's pretty good it's forked from a couple of other themes from I think both
a main gnome theme and also an icon theme and all that stuff I think I think we think
we had details about that in a previous show but we say goodbye to unity 8 and the and
the dreams of what that had and we say hello to different folks's take now on the Ubuntu
gnome desktop system 76 is definitely taking a leap here because we don't we don't really
even know what canonical is gonna do with their gnome yet so there we've heard more
from system 76 than just about anyone else yeah they're really they're really they're
really going at it full speed and you know it's more than just words because they had
a gal go pro like I said at Linux fest running this stuff they're talking about right here
so they're testing and dogfooding it at system 76 right now and I was asking folks at the
booth at system 76 as they walked up like what do you think what do you think what do
you think and you know different people had different takes on it obviously because it's
always a taste thing it's always you know people have different opinions on that but
it's definitely a very eye-catching theme and on high dpi it really looks sharp yeah
you get a good monitor so what do you think ww interesting times ahead oh yeah I mean
like like canonicals doing their move system 76 is kind of like going hey we're gonna up
our game and be you know evolving how we make these things and this could be an interesting
time to see how these two different companies have worked so close together either go step
separately or they still work or you know things like that it'll be interesting to see
sure yeah because what happens say if in 1804 it comes out that well we have this new Ubuntu
human theme for gnome and we're really happy with it and it's got all of our energy and
effort into this and this is what we think the Ubuntu desktop should look like then what
system 76 gonna do I would imagine they'll probably stick with their look because now
this is gonna be part of their branding switch to KDE yeah actually I think this is clever
on their part is I think what their plan is if I remember right now I suppose all this
is subject to change but I think they're gonna have like a login menu entry item on like
light DM or GDM that says system 76 gnome session or stock gnome session so if you don't
want any of this stuff yeah you just choose that and then you just get the whatever the
stock Ubuntu gnome session is which is kind of like a kind of like a best of both worlds
yeah that's a good way yeah as long as it's not confusing for people that sounds pretty
nice yeah so if you have questions about the galago pro tweet me at Chris LAS and let me
know what they are and I'll try to work them into see if you can get him to run a fork
bomb yeah yeah maybe that's probably not what I'm gonna do but yeah I think probably I'll
have it I'll probably have my review ready by the next Linux unplugged oh cool yeah I'm
gonna just only gonna run arch on it for a couple of days and then I'm gonna load Ubuntu
with the system 76 PPA on there and give and that'll really what the majority of the review
is and I would imagine by that I'll have a better idea of laptop battery life and the
other thing I want to test is what's laptop battery life before I put things like TLP
on there and what's blacktop battery what kind of improvement are you able to get here
and I'm not gonna I probably won't come back with like exact numbers because it's always
it's so varied based on workload and it's not like I have some sort of stringent regime
for battery testing so I'll just give you my impressions on it but I'll try to do my
best job so we'll probably have that question for you yeah yeah sure I've got a question
for you about the Gallego Pro could you please do me a favor and try and spin up the latest
alpha of Trisco I think it's Trisco 8 and see what works and what doesn't because look
I'm not going to use Trisco you're not going to use Trisco but if you spin it up and everything
works then that's a nice warm feeling isn't it that okay it's running Libre software the
graphics doesn't work if the Wi-Fi doesn't work then it tells you okay it's working in
Ubuntu Fedora arch but it's using some binaries and then at least we'll know that a blob informal
blob count yeah so put the latest Trisco on there and see what happens I can do I'll give
it a spin yeah that's a good idea thanks Joe if you and of course of course if you are
particularly interested join us in the mumble room next week and answer your question directly
otherwise tweet me at Chris Elias I'll try to get some of them in there and if you want
to get the pop theme I suspect there's if you're on Ubuntu on 1704 or 1604 you can get
the pop theme in unity or known by adding their PPA now this PPA I think this PPA I
think is just the pop theme but I'm not sure so just double check on all of that it's all
they have all the information in the blog post as well as links to the github repo which
I think so adaptia or adapt a was the original theme and paprias and Fira if I'm getting
those names right where the upstream projects that they've sort of forked from and I think
they're contributing back up to those projects also yeah so check it out we have the post
in the show notes and congrats to some 76 for getting that out there and getting the
galago pro close to shipping it seems like there's a lot of excitement around there there
was also a lot of discussions there you know one of the other things I don't know if I
mentioned it's just one more Linux fest this is like littered with throughout the show
one more Linux fest observation was a lot of new users at Linux fest this year yeah
wasn't that wild yeah folks it didn't yet run Linux and so as a consequence the Linux
like 101 courses where the standout hit I was right as I was going out the door I talked
to the Linux fest organizers and I said so what were the big you know what were the big
talks what was everybody what was all the feedback and he said the 101 courses you know
those Linux newbie courses were great and in fact while we were at the booth during
those courses we had people stopping by the booth going yeah well I went to the 101 class
but it's standing and people are out the door in a line and there's just there's too many
people in there it's hot so I had to leave so I think they'll probably expand that next
year so do you have to lay some Linux 101 on something yeah we just quizzed him real
quick I said call it Linux Academy I think it's a good sign that people that were just
genuinely just interested in technology but weren't yet Linux users were there there were
more of everyone there was there was kids there yeah my kids include but there were
more kids there this year than normal I think in my impression of course I don't have hard
numbers but it seems like I've never seen as many women there as I saw which is it was
a great sign and like I said new users which is a great sign and of course Brad which was
great yeah the diverse crowd great great great presenters good booths just just a great fest
overall and he said I didn't have official numbers by the time I was leaving but he said
it's probably their biggest one yeah that's awesome yeah yeah and boy did it show in that
Expo Hall and what oh my gosh I have to tell this story and maybe I'll try to get it in
my vlog because it was it was so cool and I did have my vlogging camera with me but
they had a gaming den yeah and it was the most badass gaming den I had ever seen so
they they were all playing when I went up there Rocket League and so all of the machines
were running Ubuntu all had Steam with Rocket League and then they had in this on the projector
because it's like a big college classroom on the projector they had spectator view where
you could see everyone playing so you could see the entire court awesome they had an elimination
hierarchy scoreboard where you could see who won and who was getting eliminated and who
was still the champion they had prizes they had great prizes they were giving away I mean
I couldn't find the gaming den at first and I started hearing all the hooting and hollering
I just went that direction and it was high-energy a ton of fun super well organized and you
know you really go in there and you see all these folks that are new to Linux and they're
just sitting down playing video games like it's no big deal like of course it that's
awesome of course Steam is on here and they just sit down there's there's like you didn't
see people going like oh what do I do they just like click the Steam icon okay Rocket
League play right and they're on you know and my son Dylan sat down he just started
playing he's never used Unity before he just sits downstairs playing launches Steam like
this is so cool it was really the face we want to put up for new users like good effort
look a fun spirited they also had a robotics area where school kids have been building
robots and they have this robot that shot balls and ran a Raspberry Pi that was running
Linux that did the optical image recognition so we could recognize objects in real time
and so it was a remote-controlled robot that would go and have some autonomy for a short
period of time while it recognized objects and then return control back to the remote
user built by freaking students and up there up there own in one of the rooms up at Linux
Fest on the second floor so there was really cool stuff tucked around too it was neat and
Sunday was way busier than any past Sunday and yeah it was like a whole other Saturday
we had we had a ton of people watch Linux action show live it was a good experience
you know I went to one of the last talks in the day and there were still like you know
they're starting to take down the booths and stuff but there were still tons of people
around oh yeah checking the talks that was great yep yep yep yep Alan Jude shut the place
down whoo he sure did so if you want to see that go check out the last Linux action show
which was just posted yesterday and then I may have some of it in my vlog soon too speaking
of the vlog you can find it linked at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash Rover the Texas trip
to Dell and back the series from that is now posted which has turned out pretty good I
thought so if you want to see the trip to Texas a little more behind the scenes at Dell
and then the crazy long haul back whoo I bet it was nuts Wes well as you made it it was
nuts it was it was squirrel nuts at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash Rover that's where
you go to find all of that sans the squirrel nuts part just sense that yeah just unfortunately
as much as as much as I regret it well Wes that brings us to the end of this week's episode
of the unplugged program you know it's good to be here on Jupiter broadcasting the largest
Linux podcast that's right maybe the world's I don't know I'm not gonna make that I don't
know I don't really know if not we'll work on it yeah in fact help us take over the world
at reddit comm slash r slash Linux unplugged email us Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact
he's at Westpain that's right I'm at Chris LAS the networks at Jupiter signal and we're
live at jblive.tv where you can join us in our virtual lug thanks for being here we enjoyed
you hope you enjoyed us and we'll see you right back here next Tuesday goodbye everybody
say goodbye Wes goodbye
so did you did you hear the big news the big news with Amazon echo and Alexa you can use
your voice to play music control smart home devices and get news and information yeah
and now introducing the newest member of the family Amazon echo show hi there this is Doug
first time dad yeah we'll stop there because it's just starts getting patronizing after
that but did you see the news the yeah what do you think of the echo show Wes it looks
kind of I can see why they're doing it I don't know that I'm interested in it yeah they really
push the video calling really really pushing that and I'm like okay is there a time where
video calling is ever actually gonna become like a thing that people do a lot I don't
know I mean ever I actually think I think FaceTime actually is pretty it's pretty successful
you know if you're gonna go for that but yeah I know it's like I can see it for a long you
know family people you see infrequently yeah meetings yeah sure but like for day to day
I don't know they also introduced something else kind of new which I actually am excited
about because I've got a couple of these devices and this is supposedly rolling out today Alexa
call dad again calling dad oh boy what did you do Alexa answer Alexa hang up calling
through the echo devices is actually kind of useful because I've got some here in the
studio I've got some and they also have a messaging feature so you know it doesn't have
to be a call you can leave a message for specific individuals and it'll play that's actually
not a bad feature I think so people that are people and the thing is is again Amazon builds
this lady in a tube once and sells it to you and then they just keep piling these services
that is their way isn't it whoo welcome to the future West what actually other Alexa
devices right for the yeah oh yeah yeah of course yeah but they're Alexa send message
to link to map for like what I can't find it products for gorilla masks yeah I mean
there's gonna be weirdness about it but the the thing about the whole echo strategies
the echo themselves are Amazon's versions of the Alexa enabled product but there are
many other products like GE just launched a lamp a really cool looking expensive lamp
that but so cool like you kind of would want it that also oh by the way has Alexa built
into it right cancel