You guys follow Lifehacker right? Hey Noah's in studio by the way. Hello. Hey you follow Lifehacker right?
Did you know that they do these Linux packs? Have you seen these these here Linux packs?
No. Yeah, they do these Linux packs of every year and Winston Gordon did one this year
And I wanted to go through a couple of the apps with you guys
And I think some of them have been app picks on the last but not all of them
So I thought maybe we'd go through a couple of them and see what we thought and then it's you know
It's like pre-show stuff
I don't think it's main show stuff, but we'll take a look at it and see what we get
So here's a couple of the apps they picked okay?
For productivity Matt you might like this one. They thought the best launcher was synapse
Not knowing nice. Yeah, they say app launchers bring a lot to your workflow now
They both note that unfortunately app launchers are in a weird spot in the Linux world
Noam do hasn't had any major update since 2009 and synapse
Also doesn't appear to be all but abandoned now, so I guess it's probably because a lot of desktops just build that in these days
I think it's gonna take it all broken for anything to actually happen with it
I think that's what will have to happen. Yeah. Yeah, okay. You ready for the text editor
All right, Kate from KDE and genie which genie has been a pick before on the Linux action show
I guess I don't know I supply him text to made a mate. They gave it a mention, but I
Like Kate kind of you know it's great. If you're a KDE person. I don't know
That's fine. It's kind of like saying yeah, it's great. If you're a good own person or a no person
Yeah, I mean whatever. I want something a little sexier more exciting G. Okay. That's cool. Yeah, he's all right
No is that I got it. I am oh, yeah, you know why did you do you know that or you know?
I'm guessing I knew well you use Fedora, so it right well Red Hat is what it comes from oh, yeah
Well here's the thing at Red Hat if you take any Red Hat course you'll be so sick of
Knowing you have to do everything in vim basically
It's all the courseware and everything for it you don't but the instructor will come up and go well
I don't know how to oh yeah, you do
Oh, you don't because when I was looking at it you did oh it was all oh in fact
You know what when I was doing the Red Hat course the guy next to me couldn't remember how to get
Repo configured and he broke into the oh no copy the RPMs off installed
Instructor comes over calls Red Hat and they go did he use the internet no did he bring an outside material no he passes
No, they don't care. They don't care how you get the objectives. No. I know that part
Yeah, I know, but like like the culture of it's all it's gotta be inside. That's right. Yeah, yes
Okay, they said best office editor Libre office all right. We can give them that best web browser, okay?
Let's see here. The problem is it's negative in the freedom
Dimension gave it to Chrome. They gave it to Chrome. It's not that's totally really. Yeah, it's not necessarily
That's actually my next article topic. That's really funny really okay, and then email interesting, okay?
I got a I got a I got a Thunderbird problem. There's definitely an advantage to Chrome in that it's getting
Capsicum support even on Linux yeah, Chrome is you know I mean I keep trying to switch back to Firefox and Chrome keeps pulling me
Back for a few reasons. I'd like my fire box. Yeah, especially under Linux
Are you saying Thunderbird because that's what I could probably argue with you about they say Thunderbird development is slowed down
But there's still their favorite desktop email client well
Yes, there's no more development to do because it works perfectly fine stop breaking it
The last couple times they've tried to do stuff to Thunderbird all they've done is made it worse
So if they're just gonna stop and just do maintenance on it. I am a very happy badger. Yeah, I agree. I agree
I think the pimification of it
You know the personal information manager
Effication of the Thunderbird was probably where they really went south so I think by sticking to just being an email client doing that well
Oh, yeah, that's cool for me. It was mostly when they moved buttons
Yeah, they did do a big redesign semi-recently
And I like it now having tabs is very useful being able to keep all my sense stuff open in a second tab
It's actually very useful. It's just every time they moved the buttons it messes up my entire flow man workflow. You got a flow
I appreciate that because that's exactly how I am about I'm having I was gonna
I was gonna bring this up in the post show
But I'm having in fact I will remind me to I have a Thunderbolt like it's like a UI
Wiggly issue that I thought I had solved a long time ago, and now I can't fix it, but
Let's move on in the list, and then we'll wrap up because it's not too too amazing
Now pigeon came in for the best instant messaging client they gave mention to empathy
VLC for best video they gave mention to a few others Plex beat XBMC
Which I thought was interesting those two they're kind of different though, right? Yeah, like ones for one thing and ones for another
I Spotify for music wow
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that just hit 50 and never looked better
My name is Chris
Hey, Matt. Hello welcome to episode 50 buddy. All right already. I know can you believe it?
Can you but it's crazy, and you know what it's a special episode too because we're packing up
We're getting ready to go down to OS con and so Noah mr. Colonel Linux himself has joined us
I have in studio Noah welcome to life some plug. Thanks for having me good to have you here in meat space
It's nice. I like the Google you were still rocking the Google glass have you been recording this whole thing I?
Actually, I did record the intro just a little bit. Okay good good. How's the fedora install going absolutely well actually
I'm just in a terminal in the IRC so I haven't really played with it, okay
Yeah, I loaded him up a box with fedora 21
So he'd feel right at home because he's a fedora guy he shows up with an arch box man and set it right on your desk
Wow, yeah, you know respect a curveball curveball. Well. We got some good stuff to get into today
We're also joined of course by our virtual lug over there the mumble room glad to have them along. Hey. Oh everybody
Hey, I wanted to start with some feedback like we often do there was some pics
We had on Linux action show for bandwidth monitoring
I think it was MBW Mon on Sunday, and we ended up getting a note in from a plasma widget author named Rob
And he wrote and he said hey Chris and Matt on the last show you were discussing
Your appreciation for a simple bandwidth monitor at the risk of tooting my own horn
I wanted to add a quick plug for my own project socket sentry
Which is my favorite bandwidth monitor on the KD desktop, so it's awesome to hear from him
He says it's a bandwidth monitor in KD plasma widget that you can leave on your desktop or dock as a panel icon
What sets it apart from similar tools though is that it breaks down bandwidth per process or program?
So you can quickly see whether your network slowdown is caused by Firefox or SFTP for example
It uses lib pcap under the hood so you can filter the traffic at monitors using the same expression language and tools like TCP
Dump a wireshark and also goes easy on the CPU in fact when it's hidden in your panel as an icon it stops monitoring until
You pop it up, so there's no overhead when you don't need it
It's in the AUR as KD plasma dash applets dash sock century or socket century
I haven't updated in a few years
But that's mainly because it does everything it needs to do and it works under modern versions of KD
So I'd love to know what you think and thanks. Give up the great work
Well, I've already tried it out before every time I set up KD. I set this thing up
Are you like this I know with your do you have like?
Conky and bandwidth monitors on your desktop, so here's the thing I test out a lot of different laptops
To see how they're gonna work and how they're gonna work in specific circumstances
So I switch like I have a different machine now than then when you saw me a couple months ago
Yeah, because of that I try and keep it
I change things as I go along it starts out sucking that when something bugs me
Then I'll add it in that is that is exactly how I do it especially like right now
We've been moving hardware around. I'm not even like using the same computer week to week anymore right so
Having the ability to just keep it as close to stock means that I can get up and working a little bit faster
And then the longer I use a machine the more I bring it under my control mm-hmm
What about you Matt are you a tweaker with your like do you have a CPU monitor on your desktop and all that stuff?
I do I generally prefer to kind of go with a gooey option
I usually I'll have it something that can kind of peek at although recently I found myself
Kind of removing myself from using that more
And I'm almost just kind of trusting what I don't know because I find that my OCD tends to yeah
Yeah, I can it can be distracting can it too like it can like you can be like what's going on up there
And it really let's be honest computers are powerful enough and Linux is good enough and managing processes that it's not really necessary
You know what I mean, so especially
Killing it anyway, so whatever yeah
Go ahead Alan
Yeah
Well you have eight processors the percent CPU load actually can matter less and then a widget can't be big enough to
Display all eight threads on your CPU right it might be showing one core in the widget
And you have seven other cores that are idle yeah, you know if you have eight cores then each one's like 13% or whatever and so
when your CPU usage you can't actually tell that some program is actually pegged on one CPU and
Would be going faster if it was multi threaded or whatever so I don't know I don't ever see the my desktop
I always have whatever I'm working on like I might have multiple windows
But I never see what's in the background like my desktop wallpaper or any and we just have it up and put there
Yeah, yeah, if you're saying your desktop. You're not working on
Sounds like he's saying hey guys. You know while you're looking at your desktops and making them pretty I'm getting work done
What if you're like me and you just have a monitor just for all your crap like I have a crap monitor sometimes in some
Of my setups. I'm a bad person
Yeah, in fact that brings us to our next email from steve-o now unfortunately q5 sis who rocks a six monitor Linux setup
Didn't join us today because he's working late
But maybe he'll be able to chime in those chime in on this feedback style, but steve-o writes, and he says hey guys
I've been researching
Possible multi monitor setups for gaming under Linux and there seems to be a lot of conflicting information
I found a reddit post talking about how difficult it is to set up particularly with two video cards on the other hand
I found posted for Onyx any links to a for Onyx quad monitor review which seems to indicate. It's fairly easy
I'm a Linux admin by trade, and I've been using Linux on my desktop since 2006 however
This will be my first time really considering more than two monitors for my home setup
Ideally I'd like to get a six monitor setup going cheers. I know right
Anybody tried a multi monitor setup with gaming is it get weird
You ever tried it Noah. Nope. I have multi monitors, but I don't use it for gaming. Yeah
well, I bet I go ahead I've tried it for I've tried it for like flight simulation and
It works kind of but that was also like back in
2004 when it didn't really work as well as it does now
I'm not sure about now Riley now a lot of times it comes down to whether the game supports it or not sure yeah
If the game isn't meant to be split then you end up with like an after screen on one monitor and half on the other
Monitor in this and under the Linux to that
There's a bit of an extra like what toolkit or whatever did they write it towards like are they using SDL or whatnot Riley thinks?
Riley you think this is a case for awesome? I think I remember q5 saying he uses open box
You remember what he says he uses for his setup. What's the default in in puppy? I don't know well except
He doesn't use his open box. He's crazy. Does he he's crazy using puppy, but anyways
We'd love to get your inputs because I mean I you know what I just got X plane on Steam
It was it was not cheap either, but yeah, well that's on my wish list X plane is have you played it? Yeah, it's amazing
Yeah, you know they have actually hardware devices you can bring in and have like the full experience. Yeah, yeah
I mean they're crazy expensive. Yeah. Yeah, I looked at the only computer-based flight simulator that is certified by the FAA
Right or actually doing stuff from getting time. Yeah, you can log hours. What's amazing?
Yeah is ours you can take off right here at our local Arlington Airport and or SeaTac
So I was just blown away by it
So I I I could see where steve-o is coming from here because I'm looking at the I'm looking at X plane
And I'm thinking I had a few monitors this would be kind of amazing
And I'd love to hear how it works out for you Steve and if anybody out there has any advice or feedback
You can drop us a line in the Linux unplugged
feedback thread over at linuxactionshow.reddit.com or go to Jupiter broadcasting.com slash contact and
Shoot us an email with your thoughts on what Steve could do to win with six monitors and video games
Yeah, that sounds like that could be a bumpy ride right I'm thinking zone minder
That's the first thing that comes to my mind is is to have a compound and to have zone minders and gun turrets you got
to have gun turrets I
Want high-caliber gun turrets. I'm talking about like full. You know set them up on raspberry pies. They motion sensing
I'm talking the whole package. I like this now. This is this is like the zombie apocalypse bunker
That's powered by Linux
And I think there's a I think there's a role to play in there for some raspberry pie devices, too
And you know Matt before that zombie apocalypse hits you might want to get yourself a digital ocean droplet
So that way you can back up your data and protect it from those zombies go over to digital ocean comm and use the promo
Code get ready for this because July is almost over. It's your last chance to use it unplug July
How about that unplugged July when you check out over digital ocean comm that's gonna give you ten dollars towards a digital ocean droplet
Run that sucker for two months why because for five dollars you can create a cloud server in 55 seconds and pricing plans are
Straightforward you start the five dollar mark, and then you'll work your way up at each incarnation
You get something really great more storage more bandwidth more CPU really straightforward
But here's what you get for five dollars you get 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte
SSD one blazing fast CPU and a terabyte of transfer all at a fixed cost for five dollars
So you know exactly how much you're gonna pay and I want to underscore that I don't want you to go out there and get
A cloud system where you get oh, here's my CPU bill. Here's my transfer bill. Oh, it's a $200 bill
That's actually happened to me, and it's a painful process. I had to explain it to my boss, and it was very awkward
I is like hey boss. Sorry. Yeah, I put that on the card. I hope you don't mind look
That's what I love about digital ocean
It's a fixed cost which also means that as a contractor if I was gonna resell it it makes it super easy if I'm building
An open source project or I'm using it as a back end for an app
I know exactly what my run cost is gonna be and digital ocean is so simple
They're dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy to spin up cloud service you get root access
We've had users out there. They've done it under 31 seconds. It's unbelievable how fast you can do it
And they've got a brand new London data center
They just spun up the new London data center pretty cool and some of the audience members have been jumping on that
They also have data center locations in New York San Francisco Singapore and Amsterdam
their interface is simple and their control panel is incredibly intuitive and power users can replicate that control panel on a much larger scale with
their straightforward API which is
Gorgeous now. I'm not one to just talk chauvinistically about API's
But as far as good-looking API's go this digital ocean one is good-looking
I've heard good things
And that's why you're seeing really great apps in the community prop up
Apps that integrate with the Ubuntu desktop the Mac desktop Windows desktop you can manage your droplet right from your desktop check on its status
Get its IP and then when you need to go to the digital ocean website their interface is incredible
their interface sets the bar it
utilizes the power of Linux KVM connected to tier 1 bandwidth and data centers all over the world and
Gives you access to do all of that in a matter of seconds
Go create yourself a droplet right now and use the code unplugged July when you check out to get a $10 credit
You can use that $5 rig for two months for absolutely free and a big thanks to digital ocean for sponsoring Linux unplugged
Yeah, man. I tell you what we just spun up a new one here for a little secret project
We're working on in the skunk works laboratory over Jupiter broadcasting comm
All right, I got what we're kind of a follow-up email from jay-z a longtime viewer of the Linux action show
He writes in on encapsulated Linux applications. We've been talking about
Container izing applications on the Linux desktop quad X next week. That's the gnome developer conference
That's gonna be a huge topic there. Yeah, maybe the main topic
I don't know I'm just guessing but it's gonna be big so jay-z a writes in it says hey
I wondered why you haven't talked much about Linux portable apps. It's a really great
It's really great for users that don't deal with dependencies on different distros and such
Even the portable Linux games is awesome since games are non-standard on Linux installs
And he links us to portable Linux games org. He says let us let me know what you think and check it out
Have you seen this man? No, no, I haven't you're probably familiar with the whole portable apps concept on
Winders, have you seen the portable? Yeah, it's really kind of cool. I'll tell you a little bit
It's it's based around this technology called app image kit and app image kit is a format
That is it lets you have that if you're watching the video version here
I've I've brought up a little bit of a diagram and you can see it's essentially a self-contained image file
You've got an executable in there that could be 32-bit or 64-bit and then you've got a directory structure
That sort of replicates slash user slash bin slash lib and slash share
So everything lives in this single image kit file and then you can move this around and it can link to
Libraries outside the image kit file or you can have everything statically linked self-contained in there. I basically got it, right?
Yeah, that's it
And so the portable Linux games site has taken this technology and applied it to video games and essentially
Some of these are just a simple download and run
Some of them are a quick download you run the shell script or the pearl script and then you have a completely containerized
Application that you can put on pretty much any Linux box and just distribute as an HTTP download. It's pretty cool
Interesting. Yeah, and I think it's something I want to play a little bit with I've heard of it never used it
I don't know how I don't know if it works out of the box on arch or what, right?
To say but I think that's how the PDI system that the new version is is going to work is kind of the same idea
Is it the app is in this like virtual file system and self-contained so you just move it around
And I don't want to be the guy to say but I think this is how the Mac does it, too
Oh, really? I think it is. Yes. I think that's been done at least a couple of times before
So how does this compare to say the old click click project?
I mean, it seems like there's a little bit of a correlation there
Yeah, I'm not sure like how they distributed it on like how they did the libraries and things like that
I don't know if there's a correlation there or if it's more just similar and functionality and concept
Okay, it's not here to talk about it. Oh that poppy go figure, right?
He's probably doing something Ubuntu ish. You can find a chicken. Yeah
Yes
Poppy chasing the chicken is the thing
The app image kit is up on github and they're working on it and the Linux portable game guys are working with them, too
Oh, hi there. Hey chrome. How you doing? And
They got a lot of good games from quake
She's look at all this stuff. You just have a crap ton you guys star conflicts up there, too
Wow Z NES the emulator is up there
Zero AD is on the site. Look at all this stuff abuse pioneer flare. I got to check this out
I think I'm gonna try this maybe on my train ride. Yeah, what all right
As long as that Wi-Fi connections working just do a little download
I'd be really curious to see if it just works and I guess it's supposed to support 64-bit or 32-bit
So jza sent that in it. So just for some of the details the app image
This is something that's already out there. That's why I find this fascinating since this is becoming such a big topic
Yeah, I'm app image is an ISO
966 oh file the contents of the file can be compressed with the ZF so you can even make it smaller and the standard supports that
The after contains one desktop file per the free desktop or dot org spec
So any desktop that implements that dot desktop file, which is all of them
Will be able to read the file and just add a menu entry to your desktop to KDE or GNOME
So it even works in with your integrated
Desktop menu system. Now. Do you think this could larger scale become a
Larger scale become a unit a way to bring a unified installer to Linux. Yeah, I do
I mean, I think it is actually I think it's offering that today. I think that's exactly what it's offering today
It's just not widespread. Do you think it'll become I guess culturally accepted? No, I
Think this is one of those things where something this scale
It almost has to come from somebody with the appropriate weight to move it. Oh, you know what I mean?
I'm kind of saying I'm kind of saying Red Hat. Yeah, that's kind of working on it. Cool. Well, you don't think so
No, I think no. No, I I I yeah, I mean come on Sousa
No, I'm serious like I mean I you guys know, I mean just over the record
We know people we like people who work for Sousa. I used to deploy Sousa Enterprise Linux as part of my job
I thought it was the best Enterprise Linux
I was a hat. So how how I mean, how is Sousa stain relevant these days?
I love what they're working on too, which is the shame of it
I love the evergreen cons or the whatever the evergreen concept they have
I love the build service all of that the studio
But so what do you go to when you want a when you want a desktop environment that that's commercially supported CentOS
Well, yeah, but that's not I mean that's you can buy support for yeah, but it's meant more towards servers though, right?
I mean, you're not gonna sit there. You're not gonna have somebody do realistically Chrome OS. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, that's yeah
Yeah, I mean that's what's unfortunate right is now that CentOS is a legitimate Red Hat project
That's and then you have Ubuntu who's rocking it on the cloud space to that markets really getting tied up, right?
I think in the back end. Yes, but I don't I don't see too many people sitting down at their workstations and using CentOS to
Yeah, I don't think there's I don't think people are really competing right there right now
I mean, I think the only person really competing there is Google sure. I mean I'm canonical sure
I mean you're seeing a lot of LTS deployments there, but I think that's despite their efforts. Mm-hmm. I
Don't know. I don't mean to dog on openSUSE, but I've been it's just actually something
I've been thinking a lot about off airs
Where do they really fit in in the political structure now for Linux and when you think about moving something like this app image
kit format forward
I I mean, okay. Let's this isn't as big but it's almost as big as like system D
Almost could you picture system D succeeding if it was an openSUSE effort or a SUSE effort? No
Could you see it succeeding if it was anybody but right now?
But I say that primarily based on the fact that upstart was so heavily backed by canonical and canonical had so much
Driving force behind it behind upstart already
So you have to come to the table with something that offers a lot more and be backed by someone that's as big or bigger
Right. Yeah, Riley makes a good point. Go ahead Riley
Yeah, I will no I think it's a really well engineered high quality distribution
I think it may be sometimes people find the package management with zipper and stuff is a little foreign still
It's maybe not quite as tight as they want and you tied in
As far as a nice Nome or a nice KDE implementation goes openSUSE or 13.1 is great. Mm-hmm
Mm-hmm. Yeah another really good. I
Thought the point of SUSE was basically to be the alternative to Red Hat for enterprises
But I don't know if anybody really wants an alternative. Well, I think it's I think it's Ubuntu LTS. Unfortunately
Yeah, I mean you really is you've got existing market moment
I guess you've been to good works on servers, doesn't it? I think I think they've I think they've pretty
Handsomely surpassed the SUSE's installation base Google. Yeah, they have a specific
Download for installing on servers, right?
I've seen that and on easy to when I guess when Google went to dump a lot of the Red Hat servers
They went to Ubuntu. So yeah, tell you yeah
Yeah, well on to actually and it wasn't it just was it just Spotify who just publicly announced they're switching from Debian to Ubuntu
Yeah, that's right. That's right
And and the reason is is because they just get a slightly better mixture of packages and they like the LTS schedule that they can
Set their IT clock to
And I well, I want to make sure I'm being clear
I don't I'm not dogging on the quality of SUSE the people who work on SUSE or what SUSE it does
I think he asked is great. I think it's still one of the most well thought out distributions from top to bottom
It has saved my ass several times. They have like recovery modes
You can go into that literally got us back up and working. I'm not saying any of that
I'm saying the market seems to be deciding these things
Mm-hmm
Despite their best intentions and efforts and so when I look at this app image kit
It feels like you know
Red Hat and fedora and Ubuntu would all and Debian really together would all have to get behind it to really make it work
But it has to start with somebody that has the ability to push it
It can't just you know what I mean?
Like eventually there has to be an entire
Consensus consensus like we saw with system D eventually and it was awful and embarrassing but we got there
We're still kind of not there, but we got there
The same thing would have to happen with this right and it has to be started off by somebody who can just you know champion
I mean would system D have been successful if it wasn't for Lenart out there taking on every criticism or responding with massively detailed technical
Explanations explaining why things are the way they are
I don't look Lenart was the person who you could probably attribute a lot of publicly pushing system D through
Who's gonna do this for the standard right?
But if you have the gnome group working on desktop container ization you get some of those same people now
They're gonna be pushing that standard right and that might have the momentum
All you need is just a couple distributions to latch on so that it becomes
You're the you're the you're the you're the ugly red stepchild
Yeah, if if you don't follow that standard right once you can establish that right then everything else
What's your odd man out?
It's actually harder to work on your system because you don't do something right even if Ubuntu and Red Hat
You know you get like two or three of them that had a standardized package installer
I think everything else would follow yeah, maybe not everything I mean you're always gonna have yeah like you arch people or slack
Yeah, something like that. Yeah, I'm sorry fedora guy couldn't hear you over the sound of your fedora still installing all right
Well, I wanted to move us to us
Something kind of cool that we have coming up get your nostalgia hats on everybody
You know we're gonna go back in time here in a few minutes
Q5 system been working on a way back machine for the Linux unplugged show
Something kind of we've all been running some of us been running links for a long time some of us are new
But I think it's always good to go back and see where we come from before we do that
I want to thank this week's sponsor ting go over to Linux dot ting.com why because it's got Linux in the URL
Seriously Linux dot ting.com that also lets them know you appreciate them sponsored Linux unplugged show
But unless you check out ting what is ting ting is mobile that makes sense my mobile service fighter and Matt's mobile service fighter in
fact right well over a year now and ting rocks because it's only a flat six dollars per month and just your usage on top
Of that no contract no early termination fee, and I gotta tell you that's very handy as I'm going out on a trip
I don't have to worry about any of that stuff. Yeah, I'm gonna be using my phone a lot more
I'll just pay for what I use easy-peasy
No problemo if I get to a spot where I need hotspot or tethering I just check the box in the OS
I don't have to be part of some sort of mobile family share program
I don't have to pay some certain amount of data just in case I use a gigabyte
I just pay for what I use and I use the features built into the operating system
You want to use ting as a mobile ISP do it they like it. They don't care. They like it plus
They've got no whole customer service you call them a 1 8 5 5 ting FTW anytime between 8 a.m.. Or 8 p.m.. Boom
A real person answers the phone. I know it's crazy your mobile phone operator can actually help you because they've empowered their support staff
What a concept plus they have an incredible dashboard over to the last or linux.com don't go to last.com Noah
Except on Sundays well, that's true. That's true
Yeah, you know what you know what you know the last time I went to linux.com was
30 seconds ago well no
But but last right before I left I had this problem I the my wife helps me answer the phone for our company
Oh great. Yeah, well. She's with me. So she's gonna be hard to answer the phone right?
Yeah, so I hired a girl that was gonna answer the phone at the times that she wasn't gonna be available
Yeah, well now she has to have a phone right, but I can't give her a cell phone
I don't have an extra two hundred dollars to spend on a cell phone right and then I'd have nothing to do with it
Afterwards right so they have this home connect thing that I bought for like $30 off of eBay
Yeah, and with the BYOD bring it over I activate it
I plug a phone in and now she's got a phone in her apartment and a laptop six dollars month
That's right easy peasy. Yeah, and you can you can go in the dashboard. You can set alerts
Yeah, we we've hired a part-time nanny which turned out to be even cheaper than daycare which is great
But her phone service is super spotty well
She's got our kids sometimes so we want to have really make sure that she we can always send her a message always get her on
The phone so we're just gonna get her a great device from ting because then it's only six dollars a month
And it's just gonna be super cheap for text messaging it
There's all kinds of opportunities and possibilities go to linux.ting.com
That'll take $25 off your first device if you've got a device compatible with the ting network
I'll give you a $25 credit if you're like me that lasted more than my first month of service
I'll tell you what the first time I ever had a total free month of cell phone service
That was a special moment in my life
I will never forget that
Linux.ting.com go get a special moment in your life and see why I switched a ting
They've also got early termination relief programs if you're stuck in one of those
contracts linux.ting.com and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring
Linux unplugged
Okay, let's go back in time five years ago July 2009
That's not too long, but it's a long time in computer history right mm-hmm especially in internet time
You know here's a couple of things that happened in the Linux world
And then you guys jump in at any point if there's anything you want to nostalgia ties about
But let's talk about probably the one that just is the most relevant to the conversation. We're just having in July
2009 Google officially announced Google Chrome OS
They say we've designed Google Chrome for people who live on the web
Searching information checking email catching up on the news and shopping or just staying in touch with friends however
The operating system the browsers on the people browse on we're not designed in an era where there was a web so today
We're announcing a new project. That's a natural extension of Google Chrome the Google Chrome
Operating system in our attempt to rethink what an operating system should be so there you go five years ago
Google Chrome was born this month. Do you feel it does it feel like it was five years ago to you
Does you know I seem to remember all the going back and forth about how it's all well?
It's never gonna happen or you know the Google's never gonna actually do this sort of thing then it happened and everybody seemed to be
Almost in denial about there was a lot of room
Last Microsoft will squish them. You know no big deal five years ago
I don't think living in the cloud was as feasible as it is today, right? It's more crazy didn't it?
Yeah, I wasn't started
I was just starting a university at the time and then when they announced Chrome OS to actually be or Chrome
to be released I
Predicted they will make a friggin operating system based on Chrome
And that was right when they released Chrome when I first started University when they started Chrome OS
I was like yes, no I have don't have to build this damn thing on my own
They're gonna build it for me
Yeah, it was like gubuntu like a lot of people thought there'd be gu linux like they thought they were gonna do something
I'm going to call it talks box. I will admit this Joe's name
I don't know for sure, but I'm pretty sure I was a naysayer about because I just thought this was a dumb idea well
To me it seemed like netbooks reheated
I still think it's a dumb idea, but I think it's I think it's a dumb idea because I can't like I bought a pixel
I bought the nicest Chromebook money can buy right yeah, you did and I left Chrome on there for almost 30 seconds
Yeah, I tried yeah, yeah
It just doesn't I can't I can't live. I'm a I'm a traditional right word mouse right
Yeah, you ever just use Chrome OS like you have it on there you ever go back literally the first 30 seconds
I tried it just to see what it was like and then I
Went oh, I plugged in my thumb drive where I have all my files
Yeah, but they're encrypted with Lux so I couldn't get to them right and that was the end of Chrome OS
You know that's so funny
You say that because my experience with my c720 was I basically gave it about a minute 30 and at the end of that
I was like okay. Well. I can't get to this. I can't get to that all right time for arch. That was it
and I kind of regret it a little bit because I feel like maybe I should have given it a go because
Now that that was over a year ago now here
We are and now I'm going between the studio and the house all the time
mm-hmm and
There are there are more days than not that I just don't bring a computer with me when I move between places and I just have
Everything synchronized between the two locations
And I sit down here at a computer and I sit down there at a computer at the house and everything's there and some of that
Is because of Google Docs and Google Chrome sync and stuff right?
But the problem is you're gonna have to make significant compromises in the Fort Fisher project to be able to make that happen, right?
I got yeah, I know that's why
The good opportunity or advantage of Chrome OS is that you cannot have to worry about getting binary
updates from whoever gives you your updates you can patch or check at the source code or the
Freaking code and fix the problem yourself on the Chromebook if you really want to instead of needing binary packages all the time
Riley do you think this?
this last five years has been a hit to privacy I
Don't think it's actually a joke I would say this last five years has been I
Think unequivocally privacy out of all things that suffered the most in the last five years
So but you have to pray easily
You have to prioritize all right like if our goal as Linux users is to switch as many people as we can to Linux
But the I know that the fact runs in Linux and now everyone's going to stick us
Let's face it. You're only moving more and more towards browser-based application
The fact that Google Docs works as absolutely as well as it does under Windows or Mac is a huge win for your Linux
I had to ask myself a couple months ago when Matt back in the predictions Matt
Made the prediction that Chrome OS would be the new face of Linux, right?
And yeah, my I had to sit down and ask myself. Am I okay with it?
Would I be okay if when everyone thought of Linux?
They thought of Chrome OS and I'm okay with that up to the extent that things start happening for Chrome OS that don't translate to
Yeah, Netflix, right? Like why does Netflix work in Chrome when it's on a Chrome OS?
But if I install Chrome on my house, but then I know if that becomes more prolific then we have a problem
Then we're right back to where we started
Well, and you are starting to see that because now you're gonna have things like Evernote run under Chrome OS
But there's no Evernote for Linux. See that's bad. Yeah, that's really bad. That's actually worse than we were before
Yeah, because everyone hated Microsoft Windows. I don't think everyone's gonna hate Chrome because it won't hang up all the time
And it doesn't cost as much as well now, I mean if it's in Chrome
Theoretically anything they add to Chrome OS if it's actually in the Chrome browser could come to regular Linux eventually, right?
Well to kind of update the whole prediction thing here today and I forget exactly where I saw it
But basically there's a news article talking about how the it's actually up
250% as far as how they're selling and then the same comparable notebooks for Microsoft are just at a standstill
Yeah, so, you know the market's speaking loud and clear Microsoft's is they're gonna have a $99 Windows competitor by holidays
They have to they look at look at what the majority of home users are doing. They go on Facebook. They write letters
They check email. Yeah, they go on Spotify. They you know, and so if if those are the things that you're doing
Yeah, you can do that in a Chromebook. So why would you spend more than $200?
I say Microsoft should bring it because think about you know what those are all gonna become cheap Linux boxes
Most of them are gonna write eventually you become a Linux box make a $99 laptop. I'll run Linux on that. It won't take that long
All right
Yeah, exactly that's exactly what I would be thanks for the nice hardware Microsoft. Yeah
Let me let me just put Linux on that
All right
So also in July open SUSE 11.2 got firmed up
Sabi and 4.2 rocking it five years ago. In fact, there was a review of it
People thought it was maybe one of the best gnome desktops if you wanted comp is fusion
Yeah, crunch bang version 9.04 came out I don't let's go take a look
I q5 got us a little time machine link here. Let's go see what crunch bang was doing five years ago
Much improved boop. Oh, yeah boot time. Everybody was talking about boot time five years ago
Every distro was talking about boot time and that's when we were seeing upstart make its way throughout Linux
This transition over to transmission open box and GTK themes are now installed. You know made basic stuff
It's curious. It's curious to me to see which distros were we're still releasing back. Oh, we still talk
Right gotta have a JPEG turbo in there. Hey
Mozilla just announced their version of JPEG turbo that makes smaller. Yes. Yes
Yeah, and there was a there was an article at top of tech meme today about WebP from Google about why they want
WebP to take off
Hey Alan, you'll like this one five years ago
2009 PC BSD seven dot one dot one was released
This version was a maintenance release that they said this is the gale the gala gay
Oh, why can't I say Galileo Galileo version of PC BSD is the most stable release yet is what they said
It was seven dot one ten dot one is going to be amazeballs though. Oh, yeah
Is that when the new desktop
You can use the new desktop on ten dot o dot one as a beta
But I doubt it'll be ready in time ten dot one is like three months away at most. Oh, man
I'm it'll come out. It'll come out probably around the end of October beginning in November
I'm pretty interested to see what they do with that. It's all QT based you talked to
I
Think it's a little fancier. I think it's a little smoother Q5 sis was talking about it when he went to self. Okay
Yeah, he talked to Chris's brother who's working on it and it's all QT
Sounds from what I've heard and I don't know. I think I might have saw a little tease of it
It looked pretty impressive like way more polished than I was expecting for something this early on
Imagine PCB SD man, it lands with ZFS out of the box. This brand new QT desktop is pretty it's pretty nice
Right like PBI system
Starting to get pretty serious
You you won't really need the PB eyes unless you specifically want portable apps because the package manager in previous D has gotten so awesome
Now that you just use it. Well, there you go
But that's why PBI has been reformatted to be more like the Apple dmg's because the need for them is basically been supplanted by
The awesome work and now you know what Chris needs to do Chris Moore
He needs to mail Gabe at valve a PCB SD rig with a nice video card in it so we can get native. Yes
Yeah, yeah, we're working with the 64-bit Linux you later to be able to just run the Linux version. Yeah
There you go. Yeah
Already have better than make some video drivers. Oh snaps. Here we go. So
Speaking of snaps. Do you guys remember one of the early canonical controversies before the dashboard before unity?
Before buttons got moved to the left. Do you remember what we used to always get on canonical sack about?
Do you remember what the big controversy was what fucking Brown? Well the brown? Yeah, that's true. That is one of them
What could brown do for you? Yeah, no, but no actual controversial like canonical hates freedom because of they're doing this
It was a big upset. You ready anybody?
I'll give you a hint
It's something that the canonical project uses that no other open source project used at the time, but now it's a little more popular. Oh
What is it? I don't want to say launchpad. No, you're close those landscape
Landscape yeah landscape was the big upset. Well five years ago
I landscape this it's sort of like it's a bug tracker. It's a forum. It's a issue
It's all this stuff in one, you know, like go here. Here's the public
It's sort of like a everything host, you know, it's much better than all of that that we're moving towards
fabricator
It actually came out of Facebook, but the guy that created at Facebook spun it off in its own company
We're still using we just moved to bugzilla
So we're not gonna adopt it but it's a code review tool that also has bug tracker and a wiki and community and all this
Cool stuff, but just the way it handles code review and stuff makes it very very valuable for any open source project
So the they actually open sourced the code five years ago. They were under a free software. Actually, let's go
Look at that announcement q5 is by the way, a lot of the stuff we're talking about. Mr
Sis has linked us up in the show notes
So I was trying to remember I don't think they did GPL though
So it was still kind of an upset on this article doesn't say what the license was. That's too bad. That's too bad
It links to something else, but I do remember that being a big moment. Okay, moving on you ready for this one?
Amazon fails in its irony detection. I thought this is interesting as Linux users and polls George R
Orwell's
1984 directly out of Kindle ebooks that readers already had purchased you remember when they did this I wasn't a kid
I'm still not a Kindle user really but it was a big controversy. Yeah
Well, it was the publisher that made them do it for a reason wasn't I forget? Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, but they were getting sued but yes
It kind of it showed that you could buy something and then have it unbought
Well, and the thing was in the Linux community back then we were really grappling with DRM
What did all this DRM mean for Linux users?
should we as Linux users reject all things DRM and
this was sort of the
Like the key thing that all the anti DRM group which obviously it doesn't take much of the anti DRM
that that group would say look this is the perfect example of why DRM is a bad thing and the free software foundation jumped on
It and then you started to hear the swindle. That's where swindle came from was after this. That's where they coined the swindle term
It was huge
We talked about on the Linux action show even though it's not particularly Linux related because Linux users were so impacted by it
Mm-hmm, which I thought was I don't know. I I yeah, I remember that I remember going yeah, and I went back to reading my Kindle
Yeah
Like yeah, well, you know that sucks, but I mean it didn't affect me personally. I'm really selfish that way
I don't know why but it's like wow, it's not affecting me directly. I I just don't care
I I'm not really I'm not feeling the pain point that the other folks are feeling I guess well and also
You know you and I come down to it now because this the debate has been sort of reignited with steam games having DRM in
Them and well and Netflix if you want Netflix, it's gonna be HTML 5 a DRM, right, right and to me all of these things
They they fall into a category of like casual entertainment like as much as right like the same category that going to a movie
Falls into I don't get all worked up that I only go to see a movie once
But I still have pain like 30 bucks when I go to the theater to me
It is you know if you want it well
Well if you try to bring a backpack and they say well yeah
I feel differently sure they want to make sure that you don't record it
Listen the monkey wants to punch a button and have his entertainment and if they want to charge me a certain amount that is fair
Then the monkey will pay that amount and if the monkeys entertainment is wrapped up in a controlling scheme
It doesn't really matter because to be honest with you the monkey has a short attention span
And he's gonna move on to something else anyways and just because the monkey has a predilection to collect everything and hoard everything
Like some sort of squirrel preparing for the winter
It doesn't necessarily actually mean that is the thing you should be doing and perhaps maybe not having so much digital clutter is actually a good
Thing that's what the monkey thinks at least here's the other thing to you
So your your end goal or the the end goal or the the end idea would be that we'd all be able to use games
On any platform we wanted and they would all years
I could shut down ten years and they would all be there
I'm free but the reality is in order to get there
We have to take small bites small steps and the first step is to be able to actually run the games on Linux later after
We have all the software working and Linux becomes a usable platform for the majority of people then we can worry about
Finding better solutions that are more free, but at this point. I feel like the fact that steams on Linux at all yeah
Let's stop there. That's a huge right that for a year or two before we start complaining. Yeah
I think you know we're talking about five years ago. You go back five years
Nobody would have believed where I gave me now nobody it's unbelievable where we're at now
I mean just the fact we're talking about x-plane. I'm playing freaking x-plane, and it's awesome
I think x-plane I could be wrong on this, but I think x-plane actually had stronger Linux support
Yeah, because the flight schools all run Linux no
I know, but I'm just saying like there's these quality of games now right except five years ago
I'll just blow my mind that we have now. I remember like when y'all were making fun of her on it
We're always recording on being coming to run it
This will never happen
Actually, I think I actually kind of gave him a little I was coming down on the bit of I might believe it
I was starting after a while. There's a saying in the news business where there's enough smoke
There's probably a fire and it started to see like there's a lot of smoke
Here's something like Veronica like a report something like nobody would believe it
Well, yeah
Cuz they were pulling what he was doing early on where Michael got onto it early on this is probably about two three years ago
Was he was finding like like screenshots or something in the windows binary or something like he was taking stuff apart
Or like the installer and finding references to Linux
That's how it started and everybody was like they just explained it away as oh that was just for some testing stuff
I don't pay any attention to that valve doesn't even have a Linux developer on staff
That's what everybody was saying. They don't even have any developers in staff
Sorry go no you go you go
I was gonna say I'm sure there was a period where Michael was saying that he was
Going into valves offices and talking to them about it
But that he wasn't allowed to relay exactly what he was talking about, you know to anyone but just simply going it is happening
I promise you I've gone in and seen it, but I can't show you any kind of real proof or anything like that
Right. Yeah, that's always people, you know, then that depends on your reputation and everybody has a different interpretation of that
Hey, so we're working on more retro look back. So we're just getting started. This is just a new concept
We came up with our episode 50. Let's let's celebrate our 50th episode by doing just a little look back over
The history of Linux and we want to do one next month too
So if something happened a few years ago in August that you thinks was a sentimental moment or maybe even not just something that's fun
To talk about in the Linux space
Email us go over to Jupiter broadcasting comm click the contact link and send it into Linux unplugged
You might see it in next month's retro look back
We're gonna try to do this from time to time if you guys like it
So you got to let us know because you're the boss
Hey before we get to the end of the show and I got I got a little question and maybe a problem the audience can
Help me solve. I know our audience. I know somebody out
There is a Thunderbird user who is empowered to solve my problem and it's a big problem. What's the problem?
Well, I'm gonna tell you after the ad spot cuz first I'm gonna talk about Linux Academy another problem that Linux Academy solves
Are you busy? Are you a busy person like me and are you sometimes wondering if you're in the right groove?
Are you working on the right product? Are you doing the right type of technology?
Do you should get into web services should you get into OpenStack or virtualization?
Do you want to just kind of see how other distributions work or do you want to take your skills to the next level?
Well, then go over to linuxacademy.com
Unplugged that'll get you the summer of learning discount
This is a great opportunity to take your skills to the next level make you more employable
Make that next review have an extra checkmark that said you accomplish this thing or give yourself the opportunity to expand your skills
Like take Noah here. He's a Red Hat guy. Let's say he got thrust into the Ubuntu world
Well, one of the great things about linuxacademy.com is you have seven plus Linux distributions to choose from whichever distribution you choose the courseware
Automatically adjust to that distribution. They have comprehensive study guides that you can download mp3s video. They have self-paced courses
You see exactly where you at
So if you you work for maybe a half hour
You'll log off for the night you come back a couple of days later
You can resume right where you're at you see your percentage if you feel like you need to double-check yourself
They have self-testing a community that will keep you motivated and on the right track
And if you go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged, you'll get that 33% discount
That's $50 a quarter and they're adding new stuff every single week new AWS courses
If you got an AWS gig coming up go do a scenario based lesson on it learn by actually deploying a web-based
AWS application and on the back end they'll spin up the virtual machines for you. Now. Here's a question
Do they have instructors that you can ask questions? Oh, yeah
They've got they've got a full crew and they've also started recently doing like live sessions
So you can go there and ask questions and interact with them and then they'll make the video available if you weren't able to attend
The live session later on so it's a really cool like back and forth and it gives you an opportunity to ask because they're real
You know
They're educators when I when I first started when I first started doing professional training
One of the things that really bothered me was I had to block off an entire week of work
To go do this
And then the other thing was to is because you were in a classroom full of other students
You would ask the structure a question and he would tell you, you know, go grow up a man page. That's not really helpful
No, it's not is it?
No, I can do that at home and send it
You know an email in and then get a response and then read that when I have time and move on that's appealing one
Of the things I found that I've really liked with my subscription is I hear about something new and it's like well
Why don't I just go jump in for a half hour and see how much of this technology I grok and see if I have an
Innate talent for it and it's really cool because I don't have to spend the time of setting up the VM
Loading the software stack and all that's like when I just I just go through the course material
I get the fundamentals and when it comes to that spot
They manage that part for me and what's awesome is if that's on AWS
They're covering all the cost of that too. So I'm not paying out of pocket while I'm learning AWS
I just go right over to linuxacademy.com slash dumb plug get the summer of learning discount
This is a great sponsor for our network
I'd love to have you guys support them because I
They're an independent team who have built this system from scratch and we're an independent team who have built our system from scratch
and it's really cool for us to be able to connect together and work together in a common area like this linuxacademy.com slash
Well Noah you're here and you sent in that awesome runs Linux from the radio station. I'm glad you enjoyed it
It's at the benchmark man. You set the benchmark, you know
I've been making a call to have people send in their runs Linux like a YouTube you did a perfect
Yeah, you took the YouTube you took a video you uploaded it to YouTube sent in the link and or you submitted to the subreddit
I did. Yeah, even better because I'm more likely to see it than email. Yeah
That worked really well. Honestly, I didn't I've given up with you an email and I like completely yeah, totally
That's right. You've got other methods
I'm trying to help after all
I don't know. I think I mentioned in the show, but did you edit that on your pixel?
Uh, no, okay. I have a production rig, but you know on Ubuntu though. Yes. Yep
No, but everything everything from start to finish was done on Linux
Even even even the glass that everyone likes so much even that at its core is technically running Linux. That's true. That's true
Very nice. How is it working with light words? I know you've been doing it more and more. Yeah, it's we actually switch
So we do professional video editing and we actually we just switched
Well, actually a couple months ago, but we switched to all light works based and on Linux. So yeah
There's no longer any proprietary. Well proprietary operating systems running. Yeah, they call it open source, but it's really not
It's a very liberal, but you get to use it on top of Linux. Yeah, which is what I care about, right? Yeah
Yeah, I've got light works installed here on the bonobo and I've been doing a couple of custom projects here and there on it
But I just haven't gotten enough time in it. It's a pretty big change up from what I'm used to
I'm come from a previous editor. I did I so when I went when I went to school for for for broadcasting
We used obviously Final Cut. Yeah, and then when I was done
I spent half my time in Adobe Premiere and half my time in Sony Vegas and
Between the two I didn't really have
And when I went to light works it like I swear some developer at edit share sat down where they're like
What is the most confusing way we could lay out a GUI?
Yeah people to use and then right they made it a little more complicated and then that's what they went with because it doesn't work
Like any other NLE out there. No, but once you get in the way of light works editing, I wouldn't go back really
Oh, absolutely. Oh that gives me some encouragement. It's I look at it almost like an operating system
Well, it's neat is because it like takes over your screen. Yeah, it doesn't matter if you're using it on Windows Mac or Linux
Everything else that applies
Dig that thing is for me is it's so different and I don't necessarily think it's different in a good way
Yeah, it was hard for me. Yeah, it was one of those things too
I walked away from the computer two or three times and I went that's it. I'm done. Never going back. I'm not using this
Really? Yeah, it took a while. Oh, man. Yeah, I'm a little conflicted
But I'm gonna what I figure is I'll just keep working on like little projects that I just don't like it's not critical that
if things go wrong and that's fine, and I'll just keep poking away at it over time and
We'll see I'll give you guys a report. Maybe I'll do a review soon
Hey before we wrap I wanted to ask and I'll ask the mumble room in the post show
But I wanted to ask you out there in the audience
What are your tricks to work with Thunderbird?
Because you know
I am serious about this fortress Chris and I think one of the things is when I move off of Google apps for Jupiter broadcasting
I'm probably gonna be using Thunderbird primarily
The other reason I want to use Thunderbird is I really dig the GPG encryption
Plugin tools and I want to get more into that too. And so the two go hand in hand
But there's a few things I have that bother me about Thunderbird and you got to keep in mind
I'm trying to use it at a scale where maybe each inbox is getting 50 to 120 emails a day
And maybe there's four or five inboxes. So it's it's it's at a scale where you need to build a process
So my question for the audience is is what?
Extensions what tips and tricks do you have themes anything to make Thunderbird rock?
And I know some of you're gonna be like Thunderbird rock that doesn't even make any sense
But if you're using it, you know what I mean? What do you do to make a rock?
Do you have any do you use Thunderbird anything? Oh, yeah, that's all yeah
That's my email flight what them I'll tell you the main bugaboo and I'll ask the mumble post show
But the main bugaboo for me, this is huge dude for me is in Gmail and outlook you get in the actual message list
I'm not talking the preview box. I'm talking in the message list
You get like a one or three line preview of the email
Sure
and the reason why that's critical is because you can get a quick sense of what the email might be about without clicking it and
Thus marking it red because of course my system is if it's red that's processed if it's unread it's not processed
So if I click something just to get a sense of what it's about and I don't want to respond to at that moment
I will never go back to it again because it's now marked red. Mm-hmm
I swear there used to be a way in Thunderbird to get that preview
I swear
So I just want to get tips and tricks and I might do like a little collection on the Linux action show of things
I did to make Thunderbird work well for me going back
So snake doc says that Thunderbirds capable of it. I know yeah, I think so too, but I can't figure out how well
Apparently snake doc does know how well snake doc smarter than I am. Yeah
Yeah, maybe you could do a team viewer sessions and and and system administrate your computer. That'd be a great idea
What could go wrong with that, right?
Hey
So I I'm gonna be out at OSCON well with Noah and Eric and while I'm gone Tuesday and Wednesday
I've I've pre-taped two episodes of tech talk today Tuesday's episode is great
We've got some Tesla security information in there
Which is actually Linux related and some really deep dive into like the dirty details of some of the Google quarterly results
But on Wednesday, this is the one you guys are gonna want to tune into tech talk today on Wednesday is a retrospective
look back at the birth the humble beginnings of the internet and from ARPANET up to the proto podcaster we take about a
About a 15 year span of the early humble beginnings of the internet and just go deep dive into that
It turned out to be such a fun episode. That'll be out on Wednesday
I think it's gonna be episode 31 of tech talk today. So go check that out. I think you guys really like it
It's gonna be a good episode and you can also support the network funding wise patreon.com slash today
If you want to help invest in us
We're trying to keep it weird here at Jupiter broadcasting and we need the audience's help to do it
They're going off to OSCON and things like that. Your funding makes projects like that possible patreon.com slash today
You can find out more information about that and last but not least don't forget
We do definitely want your emails go over to Jupiter broadcasting comm click the contact link and send us in your feedback if you would
So that way we know what you're what you're thinking about we can cover at the beginning of our show
You can also go to Linux action show dot reddit.com and leave your feedback
Right there in the feedback thread. We want to read it. We want to talk about it
We want to chew on it spit it up
Gurgitate it and then put it back into your ear hole kind of like a mom to her baby birds
But instead of their mouth their ear holes
Yeah, it's an interesting analogy. Yeah
All right, well I know thanks for joining us in studio today thanks for having it was it was great having you here
It's always good to have an in-studio guest Matt. I'm looking forward to seeing you on Sunday
I'll have OSCON stories for you. Okay, sweet. All right. I'll see you then all right everyone
Thanks so much for to this week's episode of Linux unplugged. We'll see you right back here next Tuesday
I
Already got a tip from the chat room about the fun the Thunderbird thing, but it didn't work
I went to the message pane and I checked the message message pane thing layout
It's I hear I'll show you here's what my Thunderbird inbox looks like right now
So if you're watching this, this is my Thunderbird inbox and see what I want is in the list here in this list
I want it's like a three
I want each basically each mail item to take up an extra couple of rows and give me inline previews a little bit
That's what I want
Like gmail does gmail does I swear Thunderbird used to do that guy's email doesn't do that sure it does yeah
I know but what I would say there is a couple things. Um, I do you like the wide
I'm sure I was trying it. Yeah, I bounce around the wide one is just for people that were coming from I look
Yeah, yeah
I just was trying it to see if I turned it on because I know outlook has that mode
Like I used the threaded thing instead and you know when I like half my screen is a message preview
Although I I work the same way you do with the market is red except I have my setting is don't mark
The email is red until I actually mark it mark it that might be a way to do it
I suppose there's also an option to just say don't mark it in red unless I've read it for at least 30 seconds
Yeah, maybe that's why I hate that setting sometimes because sometimes I don't but sometimes I want to just click it
And I also want to mark it red really but I could just do the markers red button
I might try just change it up like that
What I do is your screens not so
But on mine in the list of messages
There's a little green circle a little green light beside each message and if you just click the light it marks it. Yeah, that's true
Yeah, I can turn that you know what I like about you over over users that I support is when you say I have problem
a if I go
We'll change your workflow to be and then you'll be able to do that. You're not like well, that's not what I asked you to fix
I don't mind changing. Yeah, that's really helpful