This is Linux Unplugged Episode 26 for February 4th, 2014.
You're listening to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's green with
Hulk rage! My name is Chris. My name is Matt. Hey there Matt, I'm gonna tell you right now,
we might get into it if we have time later in this episode, but I'm considering banning
Fronix from all Jupiter broadcasting productions from here on out. Wow, yeah, I'd love to hear
more about that. Well, you know, it's not his fault. I mean, I actually respect Michael quite
a bit. We've had him on the Linux Action Show. I've got a link to it in the show notes. I respect
somebody who works hard and, you know, he has a trade that he puts a lot of energy into and,
of course, maybe he's spread a little bit thin and, you know, he's created a respectable property
there. But at the same time, at the same time, I get so mad when we make mistakes in the Linux
Action Show, especially in the news segment. The Linux Action Show has the privilege, because it's
coming on, what, its eighth year? It has the privilege of being one of the sources of record
for Linux. Now, it's not the only source, but it's definitely one of the most like time capsule
like sources for Linux history, because you can go back now eight years into Linux history and
hear about issues at the time that they were happening, you know, the drama, the things that
needed to happen and all of that. And it's sort of like reliving that experience. And it's a great
way to sort of get a Linux history lesson. That's why it really bugs me when we get the news wrong,
because that's a big part of that. Oh, I would think so. Yeah, well, so a mistake slipped into
this week's episode of the Linux Action Show, and it's been it's been bugging me since Sunday.
I know it's Tuesday afternoon here. And I want to talk about that in a little bit, what happened.
And and also I want to give a little bit of history on how important news accuracy is to
me on the Linux Action Show and about some of the actual fundamental changes we had made behind the
scenes of the show over the years to try to improve that because it's so important. And,
you know, this mistake happens still. And I want to try to kind of address why and kind of come
clean a little bit, because that's absolutely just as much my responsibility. It's not really
Veronica's fault. But we're not going to talk about that just yet. Not just yet. No, we have
some feedback to get to. And we also have a guest who's going to join us in a little bit. His name's
Martin and he works with the Mate project. He does also the Arch packaging of the Mate desktop
and is a project advocate. And we're going to chat with him a little bit because we also featured the
new Mate desktop live CD that's based on Arch on the Linux Action Show on Sunday. And he's the
creator of that live CD. So he'll be coming on the show in a little bit. But first, I want to
do some follow up. I wanted to do some corrections before we get to all of that, because there was a
point that I failed to mention on the Linux Action Show this last Sunday when I was talking about
the Qbox I4 Pro. And I mentioned that it has a gigabit ethernet adapter on it, which is
technically true. It does have a gigabit ethernet adapter. But in terms of actual bandwidth, and
thanks to omak777 in the subreddit for cluing me in on this, you can't actually achieve a full
gigabit. You're limited to 470 megabit actual transfer rate due to just bus limitations in that
system, right? And it's pretty much true for all ARM real gigabit. You know, you got to have a
super fast PCI Express bus, I guess. I mean, it seems to be a limitation in the speed of the ARM
system. And it seems to be affecting all ARM chips, which makes sense. I mean, gigabit is pretty
fast. And I didn't actually ever stress test it because I was using it as a desktop. But I thought,
you know, it has that ESATA multiplexer port. I thought to make a great file server. Yeah, 470
megabits isn't too bad, though. So if I'm understanding you correctly, you're basically
saying that the actual, you know, the ethernet port itself technically could in different
circumstances, different bus and whatnot actually support the gigabit. But because of bus
restrictions, that's no longer that's not actually possible. Yeah, it's one of those things where it
says gigabit on the box, not quite gigabit, you know, gotcha, gotcha. These some of these these
ARM systems do have some limitations. But I think it's important to know if you're considering using
it as a home file server, which you make pretty good and make a pretty good home file server. It's
only used like a watt when it's idle. That's I love that aspect of it. Oh, yeah. The port really
made it makes for a good cheap portable computer for someone that might want one and might not
otherwise be able to afford one. Yeah, we're you know, it's funny, too, because just my last thoughts
on it was when I was looking at this thing, it's one hundred and twenty five dollars. And I also
have the OUYA. Do you remember the OUYA? It was like this Android based console and it was kick
started and it got a ton of money and it shipped last year, mid year. It's bigger than this QBox is.
I think it's what is it, ninety nine dollars? So it's technically it's twenty five dollars cheaper.
It's so much slower and it's so much more limited. And it shows I mean, I really think you look at
that and you see how the OUYA is kind of doomed because it's already the OUYA looks old in
comparison to this QBox. And that's just, you know. So I guess in reality, I mean, with both of
these side by side, despite the fact that the OUYA is a reasonably new device, it's already dated
just based on things like I think these armchairs. Remember back in the day when it seemed like as
soon as you got a new Intel processor on the market, the next one was already out and they
just got from like, you know, 80 megahertz to 90 megahertz and then boom, all of a sudden we're
120 megahertz and 133 megahertz and boom, we're at 160. Now we're 220, you know, just 400 and
420 and 440. And it just seems like ARM is doing that right now, where it's just rapidly increasing
just at a crazy pace. Well, it almost creates a perpetual buyer's remorse to where you really
can't win. I mean, you try and buy these things and it's like, OK, I'm all set. Oh, wait a minute.
Now it's faster. Darn it. You know, and I went ahead and invested that money. So it does kind
of create a perpetual buyer's remorse, I think, over time. But I think maybe it'll start kind of
coming in its own and settle down a little bit. But it does seem like they're just going at such
a rapid pace. It's impossible to win. Yeah. Yeah. Well, that's why, you know, you know what? You
know what? The speaking of mobile devices and rapid pace, this is why I have Ting's. This is
a great, this is probably a great time to mention Ting. Ting is a sponsor of this week's podcast.
And Ting is mobile that makes sense. They're my mobile service provider and Matt's mobile service
provider. And Ting has no contracts and no early termination fees. But they just turned two. Ting's
birthday was earlier this week. It was Monday and yesterday. And to celebrate, they're giving you a
gift. This applies to all existing Ting customers and all new Ting customers. And you can find more
details over at Ting.com slash blog. First go to Linux.Ting.com to get started. That way we get
credit for your visit. But when you go over to the Ting blog, you'll find out they just slashed
their data pricing in a massive way. They've done a huge reduction on prices. This is a great time
to go back over to Linux.Ting.com and try out their savings calculator. Because the data plans
just got a lot better. This is a perfect example of why it's so rewarding, even a year into it now,
to be a Ting customer for me. So I know a little bit, I won't share too much, but I actually know
a little bit of the behind the scenes details on how this worked out. Ting has had a very successful
two years. And as such, they were able to renegotiate with Sprint. Ting is an MVNO of the
Sprint network. So if you've got good Sprint coverage, you're going to get great Ting service.
And so they renegotiated with Sprint and said, okay, well we're making you a lot more money now,
so what can we do? And they got this drop on the data rates. And Ting looked at that and they said,
we could just not say a word and take all of this as profits and we would be making even more money
than we're making now. Or we could continue to make the revenue and profits that we're making
right now and just immediately pass that savings on to our customers. And that's what they've done.
They just moved that savings that they got when they renegotiated the contract and they're giving
to their customers. And what's so awesome about it, because Ting has no contracts,
you immediately get those new rates. You don't have to call up and sign up for another two year
plan. You don't have to get a new different type of plan and lose your unlimited whatever. No,
you just get it because it's just the next billing cycle. That's at the next rate now.
If you go sign up for Ting right now, that's what you get. Ting is paid for what you use.
It's $6 for a flat rate. That's it. $6 a month and you just pay on top of that. Every single
plan includes hotspot, tethering, voicemail, caller ID, video messaging. It's awesome.
And it really does make sense. When you start to think about it, it's definitely a different way
to do it than the rest of the cell companies, but it is the way that makes the most sense.
It really is mobile that makes sense. And on top of that, Ting has an incredible customer service.
You call them any time of day over at 1-855-846-4389. That's Ting FTW. 1-855-TINGFTW and a real
person will answer the phone and handle your problem right there. You're not going to get
transferred. You're not going to get moved around. You're not going to have to go to the next tier.
Everybody who answers the phone is the top tier. And then they get your problem resolved. They'll
call you back if they need to. They're really great. And I think you'll be impressed. And on
top of that, if you're a do-it-yourselfer, the Ting dashboard is incredible. Go over to
linux.ting.com and scroll down on that page and check out that dashboard. That is not a
fake picture. That's really what it looks like and it is completely functional. I've
been able to do everything I've needed to do over the entire year through that dashboard.
Go check it out. Now is a better time than ever to rerun through their calculator,
linux.ting.com to support this show and save yourself some money. I pay 30 bucks a month for
my Ting line. I'm using it in ways like a mofo. I use it all the time and it's like 30 bucks. And
I got hotspot. I got tethering. It's great. So go to linux.ting.com and a big thank you to Ting
for sponsoring Linux Unplugged and their support of the Jupiter Broadcasting Network. Boy, I'll
tell you, between the panel and those new rates, it's just full of win. Really, it is so awesome.
And it really underscores how cool they are as a company. They're like, you know, we're just going
to pass that right along. And they still got the ETF relief program and all of that. It's really
cool. Good. Mad respect to them. I think that's so awesome. So I want to pull in a guest who's
joined us in our mumble room this week. His name is Martin. Of course, he's going by Wimpy in our,
I don't know what that means, but he's going by Wimpy in our mumble room and he works with
the Mate Project. And Wimpy, sorry, Martin, welcome to the show. Thank you. So can I, let's
start with where we were just, what we were just talking about on last on Sunday, and then we'll
just kind of go from there. So you've been working on this Mate Live CD and the reason that this
isn't the first Mate Live CD I've ever seen, but what caught my attention is I think it's the first
one based on Arch. So Wimpy, why Arch? Well, I'm an Arch trusted user. So I do the Mate, I'm going
to get in so much trouble. I do the packaging on Arch Linux for Mate desktop. So when the idea was
circulated among the team about making a live CD, it was natural for me to base it on Arch.
And how was that experience? Did you find there were shortcomings? Cause you know,
I think of things like Fedora spins and the openSUSE build service and even Ubuntu,
they all sort of have facilities built into them to make it easier to generate a live CD work. Arch,
what are you doing all that from scratch? How does that work? Well, surprisingly Arch also
has a facility built in. You can Pacman install Arch ISO, which is a suite of scripts. And from
there, there's a base template that if you just then run the build command once you've copied the
the configuration will make you the Arch live CD that you can download off the Arch Linux website
every month and use as the install media. So you can start with that. And from there you can
customize the packages that are built in and a whole raft of other things. I'd never done it
before and it was really straightforward. Oh, very cool. That's good to know. I'll have to
look into that. So you are a Mate, I'm going to have a hard time. I'm going to try it though.
You're a Mate advocate. Why, why the Mate desktop environment? I mean, it seems to me that it,
it's sort of, it's sort of seen an increase in popularity. I know we're seeing a lot more
distributions included. Is, is it sort of, is it getting a lot of momentum behind it and why did
you choose to become an advocate? Right? Well, yes, it is, it is gaining in popularity. I think
we've, there's been a lot of effort in the team to push all the packages into some of the larger
distributions, such as Arch Linux and more recently Debian, and that's now circulating
down to Ubuntu. And we're certainly seeing it trending up on the Debian package install
statistics. And the reason I got involved with it is I had been using Name Three for about 18
months or so, and I was reasonably happy with it. And I'd installed it on my wife's laptop some
years ago. She'd since got a smartphone and was pretty much using that for everything and time
goes by. And then one evening she decides she wants to organize some photos and she sits down
in front of this Name Three thing that she really didn't pay attention to when I was showing her how
to use it a year or so earlier and was hugely frustrated with it and almost hurled it at me.
So it was marriage, marriage protection. The spousal approval factor was low is what you're
saying. Okay. Yeah. So I very quickly yanked Name Three off that machine. I put the Mate desktop on
and that restored an environment that she was familiar with because she's been using Ubuntu
for many years previous and was familiar with the Name Two setup there. So that's where I got
started. And when I had installed Mate, I noticed that it was working okay, but there was some bits
missing and there were some bits that were broken. So I just decided to get stuck in and I started
submitting pull requests to the project to fix up some of the packaging. I wonder, it seems like
potentially as the XP era comes to a close, if maybe more conventional, these types of standard
paradigm desktops will see a big boost just because of people looking for something other
to move to. Have you seen some of that? When you're doing outreach, who are you outreaching to?
Well, that's a new thing for me. It's something I've decided to start doing for the project this
year. So this is the first time I've sort of done a proper promotion to talk about the project and
try and make people more aware of its existence. But certainly within my family and circle of
friends who I've helped move to Linux, they have been more comfortable with Mate because most of
them are moving from Windows XP machines. And a couple of clicks change the menu layout, move the
bar to the bottom of the screen and it's much like Windows XP with the start button and a familiar
looking programs menu. So it's been very familiar to them. And once they've got Thunderbird and
Firefox installed, they're away. I want to do, if you'd let me shift gears a little bit to Arch,
you mentioned you're an Arch trusted user and I realized that there's a lot of people who probably
have heard that term but have no idea what it means. So what is an Arch trusted user and how
did you become one? I became one through the work I'd done with the Mate desktop. So I'd done all
this packaging and I was maintaining an unofficial repository for the Mate desktop project. And then
I took over all of the Mate packages in the AUR because they were very old, had been put there by
the original Mate project creator some years previous and brought them all up to scratch.
And I was actually contacted by another Arch Linux trusted user who agreed to sponsor my
application to join the team because I wanted to get Mate into the Arch Linux official repositories.
So yeah, there's a process that you have to go through there. There's a peer review assessment
and voting to actually vote you in onto the team and you sort of have to prove your worth and how
you're going to improve the team. The main responsibilities of Arch Linux trusted users,
they are the moderators if you like of the AUR. So there's the mailing list where people can say,
can you merge these packages? Can you delete these old ones? Can you rename these? If anyone
needs any help with package creation or wants their packages checking over, that's something
that the trusted users do. The trusted users can then pull packages that they're interested in or
that they see in the AUR that have got good adoption. So plenty of votes and something
that can be redistributed. We'll then choose to adopt that package and pull it into the community
repository and then maintain it as part as an official package. And then some of the TUs have
other responsibilities within the team. So there'll be forum moderators, people that are working on
backend infrastructure and things like that. Well, Arch and Matei seem like actually a pretty
good combination because you could have a pretty tight lightweight system on there. So that's why
I was drawn to that live CD and obviously I just had a pretty strong interest in Arch these days.
But is there anything else, Martin, you want to touch on with the Matei desktop or Arch before
we jump to our next topic? If you don't mind, I mean, one of the things I worked on was I did
the initial porting to get Matei working on ARMv6 hard float and ARMv7 hard float.
Well, you know, I was just using that this last week. That's awesome. Tell me about that.
Well, curiously, that Qbox that you've got, I've got the previous generation, the Qbox Pro. So in
air quotes, I created a cluster at home of two Raspberry Pis and two Qbox Pros to actually do
the package building for the ARM ports. And the reason I did that is I had this aspiration to get
it into the official repositories. And I knew if it hit the official repositories, it would
automatically percolate into the build surface for the Arch Linux ARM project. And I wanted them
just to flow straight in without any problem. So I was building the packages in the unofficial
repositories for four architectures for x86-64 and the two arms. So yeah, I've got some of those
Qbox or the older generation of the Qboxes, but it's hilarious. It takes about 50 minutes to build
the whole Matei package tree for Matei 1.6 on a relatively modern PC. And it takes about 28 hours
to build it on two ARM boxes. Wow.
Well, I can't tell you how happy I was when I was sitting, I had LXDE was what I started with,
and I thought, okay, LXDE is fine, but I really would like to have, like, I was trying to think
if I was going to actually use this as a workstation to do like server work and stuff
like that, I would probably want more than LXDE, that's just me. And it went off, I was sitting
there and I couldn't really decide what to go with. And it was like a light bulb. I just knew
all of a sudden, you know what, I got to go with Mate or Matei because it's going to be lightweight
and I didn't know if it was going to be available for ARM. So I just, I went to the command line,
did a pacman-s and I said, mate, and I think that's all I did. And before I hit enter,
I went and did a Google search or to the over the arch Wiki and made sure I did like the right
package and hit enter and boom, everything was there. And I got a full desktop and I really made
that Qbox go from, you know, this is something that's really limited to, okay, now I could have
a full desktop experience. And I think it's perfect for that kind of device. It really is.
And something that I'm working on, the next little project I'm working on is an image for
the Raspberry Pi, which will be Arch Linux with the Mate desktop installed, but with a series of
tweaks so that it really flies. In fact, I think you had one of those laptop devices in a previous
show. I've got one of those sat in front of me here with two, I've got two of those and two
Raspberry Pis and I've started working on this. So soon enough there'll be a Mate image you can
download with it all set up, ready to go with Arch Linux. Wow. Well, so Q5 Sis, who owns that
laptop I was using, wants me to ask you if you know anything about Mate and their plans with
Wayland. Have you heard anything about that? Yeah, I have. So, Mate 1.8 currently on the
roadmap is to support Wayland and the precursor to that is to provide GTK 3 support. The work on GTK
3 support is largely complete, but there are some Mate 1.7 development table releases. I've got an
unofficial repository for Arch Linux users where you can go and install it and try it out. Although
my build is currently still GTK 2, but I've got a GTK 3 version that I run locally. So that GTK 3
work is there as the precursor and then the Wayland support will follow. Interesting. So I
got to ask the obligatory, any discussions around Mir? Is there anything changed there?
As far as I know, it's not planned to be supported. Well, I'm glad to hear that you guys,
I think the compatibility or is that the right term? You're not switching to GTK 3,
but you're supporting GTK 3. Is that right? Yeah, that's right. So we're retaining the GTK 2 support
and adding GTK 3 support. So at build time, you can choose which toolkit you want to build against.
That's cool. And this is so, for example, the Raspberry Pi at the moment, there's not a decent
accelerated driver that's available. I think that's going to come in due course. So it would
make sense to continue to build the packages for the Raspberry Pi against GTK 2 and keep it that
little bit lighter. But then for the desktops, then maybe GTK 3 would make more sense. And what
I'm wrestling with at the moment is do I really want to support both toolkits? And I think the
answer is I'm going to have to, but that's going to effectively double the number of packages.
Yeah, yeah. But that seems like to me, that seems, I know what that is. That means more overhead,
but gosh, that's a great combination. If you can have GTK 2 and GTK 3 playing together,
everybody's happy, it seems like. And although the GTK 3 toolkit support is not in MATE 1.6,
GTK 3 applications will integrate seamlessly with MATE even though the desktop is GTK 2. So all of
the theming and everything is transparent. So for example, if you run network managers in the live
CD, for example, you won't notice that that's any different from any of the GTK 2 applications.
That's really great. That's really great. Gosh, sounds like people have a misconception about the
MATE project being old fashioned and out of date, but it sounds like you guys are right there on
the cutting edge and some exciting stuff coming. In some respects, I mean, yes, that is one of
the myths that I'd like to bust about MATE. It is seen as that everything got forked and
it was a great big dirty hack that sat on top of the forked project. But in recent years,
our lead developer, Stefano, he's really put a lot of effort into turning it into a proper project.
So there is a roadmap. I mean, a lot of the obsolete libraries from the GNOME 2 days have been
either replaced with the modern alternatives or just thrown out altogether. So that's one of the
reasons why MATE is lighter than GNOME 2 used to be. But Gconf has been replaced with Dconf and
Gsettings. And there's a whole raft of other changes like that. And then that will continue to
be the case going into the future. So we're trying to align more with the GNOME libraries
that provide the functionality that we need whilst preserving the MATE desktop and its
traditional desktop metaphors. Well, Wimpy, aka Martin, thank you very much for joining us today.
And I'd love to have you stick around for the rest of the show and jump in and comment with
the rest of us as we go forward. And please feel free to stop by any time. I love getting
perspective from people who work with the projects and also people who work with Arch Linux. I'm a
huge Arch fan. So thanks very much for joining us. You're welcome. Thank you. Yeah, absolutely.
Good stuff. Yeah. Hope we'll see you some more. All right, Matt. Well, before we go to the topic
of the little snafu that got me all in all grage this week. Oh, man, I got to tell you,
I'm actually glad we're doing this on a Tuesday because I was really flared up about this Monday
and I probably said some things I shouldn't have in Coda Radio this week. But I've had some time
to think about it and, you know, accept some of the responsibility. So I'm going to talk about
that. But first, I want to thank our second sponsor this week. And that is DigitalOcean.
DigitalOcean is simple cloud hosting, and they're dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy
way to spin up a cloud server. Now, Matt, you know, I've been on here bragging about my 47 seconds,
right? Oh, yes, you have. Yeah. Well, so, of course, of course, you know, you leave it up to
our audience. Mark writes into the show. He says, I beat the champ. I spun up a DigitalOcean cloud
server in 40 seconds. Oh, 40 seconds. Yeah. And he actually this is you knew I wouldn't believe it
because I had 47 seconds as the and DigitalOcean says you can do it. Users can do it in 55 seconds.
Right. And I always got it down to 47. I was feeling pretty good. Mark clocks in here at 40
seconds. And he even included a tiny can't really see it. Sorry. Actually, I was trying to get a
shot of it for you guys. But he included a tiny screenshot. He got it in 40 seconds, his DigitalOcean
droplets. So let me tell you a little bit about DigitalOcean. You can create a cloud server in
55 seconds. If you're like myself, 47 is my record. See if you can beat Mark at 40 seconds. I don't
think it can be done. See if you can beat him. Mark can create cloud server in 40 seconds. Pricing
plans start at $5 per month for 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a terabyte
of transfer. Now, this SSD actually makes a difference. I've had a DigitalOcean droplet
running Arch Linux. Yes, I've got a server in Arch Linux. And yes, it's been fine. It's actually
been great because I've been keeping real close to the updates to BitTorrent Sync because this
is a BitTorrent Sync server. Now, Mark said what he's doing, he said, hey, I know you enjoy hearing
about what people do with their DigitalOcean VPS is this particular one is used to host
a Starbound server, which Starbound is just exploding on Steam right now. It's like the number
one Linux game on Steam and it's cray-cray. I should talk about it at some point, but I know
how much you guys hate it when I talk about games, but it's really good if you want to check it out.
So he's running a Starbound server on there. I've heard from people who are running YASI search
engines up there. BitTorrent Sync is great. Michael Dominic from Coda Radio uses it to
work with his clients. He'll either use it for temporary backend hosting or he'll actually set
them up a server over there because what's great about DigitalOcean is it's fixed pricing. So you
know exactly what you're going to spend and clients love that. It also makes it really easy
for budgeting of projects and things like that or just I know every month I can pay in five dollars.
You know, we have people in the audience now that have web mail up there and they just know it's
five dollars for my mail service. That's perfectly reasonable to have full access. And of course,
DigitalOcean has a super great control panel that lets you image it and set up backups and deploy.
You can configure a machine and save that and deploy it later. They also have data center
locations in New York, San Francisco, and Amsterdam. So go check them out. Go see that
intuitive control panel and you can also replicate it with the API if you want for your own tools.
And DigitalOcean also has a vast collection of tutorials in their community section on their site
and users can submit articles to the community and they get paid 50 dollars per published piece.
But here's the deal. Here's where we're going to get you a little something something because
you're a Linux Unplugged listener and we love you. We're doing this for you. So go take advantage
of this because why wouldn't you? It's cray cray. If you use the promo code Linux Unplugged February,
let them know that you appreciate they're still here. They've been here for a few months. Go use
this promo code Linux Unplugged February to say thank you for continuing to come back for another
month of Linux Unplugged. We appreciate you supporting Jupiter Broadcasting and Linux Unplugged
Show and plus that's going to get you a ten dollar credit. That'll let you try out that five dollar
machine for two months for free. You're going to get root access. You can run Ubuntu, Fedora,
CentOS, Arch Linux, Debian, whatever you want son. Go do it and see what I've been talking about.
This is a great thing to learn and experiment on or use in production and it's super fast with
those SSDs and their tier one bandwidth. So thank you to DigitalOcean for supporting Linux Unplugged
and Jupiter Broadcasting and thank you to everyone in our audience who uses that promo code Linux
Unplugged February to get a ten dollar credit. You can also click the link in our show notes
and a big thank you to DigitalOcean. Boy 40 seconds that's just wild isn't it?
I mean like I wonder if he had to like create a few of them because you can make them real quick
right? So right I wonder if he like ran through it a few times and then timed it and then just
sent me his best one. Do you think he had a Rocky montage happening while he was doing this?
Totally motivated and I like that. That's what I'll try. Maybe that's how I'll beat him.
Okay so on on Sunday I was filling out the news and we had this KDE story about designers coming
over to the KDE project to help spiffify up the next version of the plasma desktop and I thought
okay this is good but this isn't this it's really early days on this story so it's not
it's not a full story in itself I need a little something else to go with this story to kind of
let's spend a minute this qualifies it to be in the news segment right that kind of thing so when
I found this article and I was not thinking clearly and I fully admit that I was sort of
just looking for something to round out the overall story and so I kind of cheated and just
when I saw the headline I grabbed it and it's it was an article ran on Ferronix KDE Plasma next
gets a release date and in here it talks about the plan to do a feature freeze in March which
we talked about in the show beta in April and then the final version comes out in June will
be called 2014.6 should it actually ship now nowhere nowhere in here does it say this was
a proposal and I didn't report it as such because I didn't realize that and that was my bad because
I made it sound like that's an actual planned commitment on the KDE projects point and I have
a lot of respect for the KWIN developer Martin I'm not even gonna try to get Martin's last name
because I know I gotta get I just gotta convince him to come on the show so he can pronounce it
for me but you know there's some developers I follow in the open source community and Martin's
one of the ones that I hold the highest regard as far as his talents and his insights and so
I felt pretty bad when he went to G plus and he said reasons why sometimes hate the openness of
free software we are not able to discuss anything without the media reporting about it on the same
day sigh dear free software media you can leave the internal discussions as internal till there
is a public statement thank you and so what he's saying there is so that pharaonic's post was a
post from the mailing list on on you know whatever mailing list it was on uh and that was where the
discussion was having on the plasma devel mailing list that's where the discussion was having
taking place and it was being discussed as a hypothetical proposal it got ran as the as
kde's plasma next gets a release date and then I grabbed it to round out a story and so you can
see how we just sort of perpetuated this mistake that sort of all of a sudden commits the kde
project to a timeline that they never actually agreed to and we're just discussing in their
mailing list you know I can see yeah and I'm looking at this as a writer definitely I'm fine
with the title but I think it needed to be in big bold print within the article that this was a
proposal that's where I see the big that's why I think I think I would have the biggest issue with
it is that this needs to be very clear I get the attention grabbing title that's fine whatever but
be clear in the article and I didn't get that just when I was reading that um it definitely felt like
that that should have been made much more clear and you know I mixed feelings on the list though
honestly if it's on a public list you know as long as it's made clear and that part wasn't done in
this case but as long as it's made clear I don't see that as a big problem as long as it's really
really really really clear yeah I think it's I think it comes down to um my mistake was in not
going to the mailing list itself and reading it and the reason why is because I get so sick and
tired of reading mailing lists because from an outside perspective uh you know I'll give you an
example so we had another story this Sunday on the Linux action show about OpenSUSE uh getting some
changes at OpenSUSE where uh folks from SUSE proper would not be working on OpenSUSE for the release
they'd be working on the ancillary services around OpenSUSE I first found out about that by following
the mailing list but I was so confused on what I saw that I wasn't going to run the story because
it it seemed to be saying that people from SUSE wouldn't be working on OpenSUSE anymore and to me
that was like no way am I reading this right because first of all English isn't the primary
language in some of these mailing lists uh there's assumed cultural references and you know assumed
knowledge that people have to other people on the mailing list that is really hard to follow
sometimes these conversations are 30 emails deep sometimes they're not and so it's these it's one
of these things where I a lot of times I've sat on a story from a mailing list but one of my one
of my sort of self checks is if I see another publication like LWN or Ferronix run the story
then it kind of confirms what I found and I usually will then go with it and in this case
with the OpenSUSE thing not only did LWN confirm it but I even before LWN had a story up oh no it
was after LWN had a story up I reached out to an old friend of the show who now works at SUSE
proper I don't know if he's made that public yet and I had a 45 minute conversation with him to
try to really try to figure out am I really reading what I'm seeing now that resulted in
five minutes of coverage in the Linux action show but I probably spent two hours on that story to
verify it just because it seems so massive now I can't do that for every story and in this case
I was being lazy and I could have gone into the KD emailing list and saw that they were
saying proposal but I just went with the Ferronix headline that was my mistake but it seems like
I think potentially what bothers me about this Ferronix mistake here is I actually think he
probably wasn't even aware it was a proposal either got sent to him and he ran with it like
somebody posted in the forum and then he republished it or he grabbed it and he was working quick and
he didn't read it all the way and he made the mistake and that perpetuated the mistake now I
also perpetuated it so it's my fault too well I think also that another differentiator is essentially
at its essence it's essentially a blog versus a major publication like you know a mag and like
an online magazine or something like that so like the CNETs of the world while I gripe you know I
gripe at various publications online usually there's multi-tiered editing that happens and
fact-checking that happens in a written format and so when we read something on these sites
we trust that that information is in fact actual and Ferronix has been we you know would assume
had that same level of clarity but in this case we were kind of let down it feels like
I feel like okay so again I want to give you guys so this really bothers me when we make these
mistakes in the show because I so I don't remember what it was exactly but this whole problem of
somebody reading something on a mailing list and then it getting reported as news isn't unique to
the KDE project like I remember this happened to Arch I was reminded recently that the announcement
when they were just discussing Arch switching to systemd people grabbed that and ran with it as
Arch is officially switching before it was actually officially switching so it happens
all the time and so originally I was trying to think well how can we improve that process
and I think you know when the first so the last time the show had a kind of a I can't even remember
what the gaff was but there was a we covered something wrong in the show and that was the
inspiration for the creation of the Linux action show subreddit the idea was is I don't want I
don't want if we're gonna have the podcast of record for Linux I don't want to have I want
to minimize mistakes as much as possible because every time there's a mistake it really it really
eats at me and so at least in the news and so I thought okay I could drop the news because I'd
rather not do the news well and I don't think you need to drop it I and not to cut you off here but
I want to point out that if I had a dollar for every time I misquoted or got something wrong
that's what corrections are and that's what this show is it allows for a correction and that's
that's allowed so I thought okay dropping the news that's going too far but I just want to
show you I want I'm trying to illustrate my commitment to trying to get this right is I
would rather not do it at all than make the mistake so okay that was the inspiration for
the subreddit was here's what we'll do we'll assemble an army of informed Linux enthusiasts
and the crowd knowledge will sift through all of the news and I won't let a story and in fact I
even think I said this on air I won't let a story into the show until it's been vetted by the
community however that was a good theory but the problem is is I think first of all Linux news is
sort of going through a slow period right now so it requires a lot more digging so hence the going
to the mailing list right and so you can't you can't expect the burden of a loose group of
community enthusiasts to actually do all that digging and try to do original reporting and
submit it to a Linux action show subreddit so I take that burden on because it Linux action show
happens every single Sunday and the one thing I can count on is that I will get something in
place for it so I take that on and I do the digging so sometimes I fall short a little bit
and what happens is is if I do digging outside the subreddit which I always am doing because
I'm always trying to one up the subreddit too and try to find something they didn't find
it means it never makes it never gets vetted through the show because it doesn't go through
that process and so I'm either left with not covering stories that don't go through the
subreddit which doesn't seem very likely or trying to come up with another way to sort of improve the
quality of news and and I'm kind of I'm kind of wondering I kind of want to open this discussion
up to the mumble room and of course to you too and and see what people think of our ideas on ways
we could improve the news and one idea I had I'll tell you my idea up front was maybe we we drop the
amount of news we cover and focus on a couple of stories and maybe one of the one or two or three
of the stories maybe it's four stories I don't know what that mix is but one of them we try to
get an interview on with the person who's making the story now the problem with this is is this
would actually just require like somebody from the community become a producer for that and they
track down the story then track down the person and line up the timings that way we can chat with
them because I just that's not something I have time to do I it is it's more work than it sounds
it sounds like it's not a lot of work it's it's probably four four to six hours of work oh it's
tough I mean you're calling Google you're calling LinkedIn you're calling pretty much any place you
can think of to hopefully find an email address and then there's a few tricks that most people
don't know and then there's then there's the 30 email back and forth lining up and answering all
of the questions I mean it is this massive process that it takes a ton of time so but I feel like if
if the show's going on eight years and I feel like we could take it up a notch by sort of
having the newsmakers come on and make the news right there and say I I think if if we established
you know the linux action show news segment you're going to hear from some of the newsmakers every
episode I think that would be a huge uh upgrade for this news segment and I think also it would
sort of establish like people eventually would figure out hey we're about to have an announcement
let's schedule something with last uh so I don't know what do you guys think yeah go ahead I think
what you said is what I've managed to gather is most of your common mistakes seem to be coming
from generally one news source and that's for onyx oh yeah I mean there is that I mean that's like
you know I mean like but at the same time everybody was claiming he was wrong about steam
and then it turns out he was right about steam wait isn't this what um unplugged is for though
so like you can get feedback from them like news segments so like you can correct yourself
on unplugged if you need to yeah we do perfect yeah but there's a mistake later and it's fine
in my eyes you can't really expect everyone to listen to two podcasts though no baby but you
can't expect someone to go back to an old article either that I published or someone else publishes
and say oh wow I was completely wrong they've already read it they've moved on you know so
all you can do is put your retraction out there and let the chips fall maybe what you have to do
is have your new studio troll do the research for you well see here's the other thing too is
I think what I'm trying to address this is a problem and this is actually when I scratched
down my thoughts on this what I actually titled this as is fixing linux news because what what
we've talked about on this show uh it was episode 11 of linux unplugged we titled it bankrupt linux
news because it is there is just not a lot of good linux there's some there is some and I
want to give them credit but there's not enough and I thought maybe we can improve the quality
of news coverage in last and at the same time improve the overall state of linux news coverage
like like actually become a new source and in that sense that's why because we have this access to
communities we have these we have these personalities and these developers that we
can reach out to I think we have an opportunity to have instead of getting misquoted blogs
and and and reddit posts from see the problem is this is not a problem that's going to go away
because you got reddit you got twitter you got google plus people are going to be grabbing stuff
and misreporting stuff constantly ferronics made the mistake today but all it takes is some
reddit enthusiasts to post it and it could become it could quickly become the top vote on r slash
linux and be completely inaccurate right so there's it's not just ferronics it's a larger
problem that I think I'm trying to solve here I'd say just it would require some more research
before it even makes it into the show and ultimately if you do want to bring somebody
in for an interview make that for the main section of the show not necessarily the news section
I think I'm thinking the interview would be like two minutes long so you bring somebody on you say
okay so uh we saw there's a new version of uh this that shipped today can you tell us a little bit
about it boom boom super quick then we move on and we do a couple other news stories and I like a
pundit yeah they come in they well they just they just tell us what they're up to or the other thing
we could do is in lieu of getting the person that actually is behind the story maybe we could get
the person who broke the story and ask them some of the and clarify some of the questions right
there and get it on the record that's a really good idea but I think as long as you can catch
it ahead of time like if you find it and you can catch it as long as you just put it like a little
thing in his show notes and a little comment on a youtube channel I think you're fine I mean
everybody's human like people make mistakes as long as you actually like catch a mistake and
own up to it I think you're fine so uh q5 sis pointed out in the chat room that uh he he said
that maybe um since feronix is being filled is getting more and more ads maybe it was a clickbait
type title and regardless of whether or not that's true maybe something uh maybe the same
philosophy that you applied to unfilter with um you know that news should be without sponsors
maybe that needs to be applied to linux news as well um no the the easiest fix in my opinion is
to basically subdomain this out on news have it have it you know have the news story posted
always have two separate unrelated citations as to where it came from maybe it's a mailing list
and an actual statement or blog post from that developer or whatever it may be and then it can
actually and if you can't obtain two then it is then flagged as uh speculative not news you know
so that way you know if we're gonna have pundits we're gonna have to have this fox news or cnn
sound effects i don't think pundits is the right descriptor i would be more like
even more like the developers know what they're talking about
first we need a situation around colonic yeah you know and the thing is is the more i think
about it i mean it's really it it's it's almost infeasible production wise on a weekly schedule
like that but it would really have to i would be something i'd be willing to take on if we
had somebody in the community who who wanted to sort of step up and be that coordinator sort of
be that production person like he's definitely willing to do that he's actually mentioned he's
trying to get in wanted to comment on this but uh he did indicate in the chat room that he would
be interested in taking on that role if that was something you wanted to do oh well all right well
i'll talk to him more often because that yeah i'm definitely i'm definitely down for that if
you want to oh well you know make headway in that direction yeah okay yeah let's talk more because
uh i mean i'm not i don't want to convert every last new segment into an interview segment but
i feel like if if nothing else i want to i want to maybe yeah if the big stuff and we can get
stuff in there and if we can just i just want to try to get as accurate as possible because it
really bothers me when we get the stories wrong so you and i will chat more and maybe we can work
something out there i gotta i gotta ask are we gonna have a situation room because we really need
to have a situation right and i don't want a wall of that's what i've been saying this whole time
you get like three screens all over the place i mean all right all right here you go here you go
this is cnn's wolf blitzer and you're in the situation room uh matt i'm reporting live on
the scene from the mailing list right now i can tell you i've reviewed the thread i've actually
read every single email and i can confirm these dates are simply proposals situation situation
thanks chris now we're all gonna get flagged on youtube oh that was hysterical
or we could do like fox news and have those oversized monitors of death you know i got that
too chris i've got the uh wall of screens already taken care of yeah you do that's right you are in
the situation room you got like uh yeah you got uh shep and uh wolf beat well um so speaking of uh
last sunday um i was wondering about something back to the uh desktop app you picked the uh
live streamer um i actually found something really cool this weekend uh it's called youtube viewer
it's actually a command line tool to view youtube in your terminal so it's youtube uh viewer yes
it's youtube in a terminal and that sounds like it's gonna that's a pretty generic search but
actually i found it right here it's on github all right is the video then ascii i mean how's that
work no you like you load youtube viewer in a terminal and pops up you can log in like you can
see all your subscriptions and it'll give a video and it'll just have a number beside the video so
you press one and then a video and it'll play it through in player does it does it use like a vlc
as the as like the back end you can use the vlc as in player or employer i think so uh and you
just what you just just put the command in the command line and then uh you just put the youtube
url in there and then bob's your uncle no you don't need a url like you search for the video
and then youtube viewer you know like display them and you just hit the number next to the video and
it'll play it oh and you can actually select the uh video quality too i feel like that's that is for
720p like dash 10 for 1080 that's really cool i just put a i put a link in the show notes and
in the chat room so you guys yeah i just want to get that out real quick before we get out there
that is cool and there's also an app called youtube dl to uh right download from the
terminal that's a gooey one though or is that coming it's not gooey no it's a terminal
yeah there's another one it's a gooey but this one's a terminal one so um i want to talk a little
bit about my news process and uh because i do i i think maybe the there might be the wrong
assumption that way there's not a lot of research done in them now so right now uh first of all i
think one way we could address this problem is i'd like to call on a new focus in the linux action
show subreddit on news correlation i'm not saying off topic i'm not saying all the other discussions
aren't fine but please just want to remind everybody if you see a story uh let's post it
there because i've been noticing some stories that i'm tracking that are not showing up in
the subreddit which is normally it used to be the subreddit was like the best place to get the latest
breaking stuff so i just kind of want to maybe refocus on news there too and i also along with
that it's equally important that people vote up and down the stories they think should be in the
show and if you know something's wrong please say so in the comments or if you have an alternative
take or if you have some additional thoughts please engage in the comments all of the stuff
all the other community stuff that happens there right now is awesome i love that subreddit it's
funny because i was starting to say you know we created it because of a mistake and it was just
going to be a news vetting tool for the show and it has developed into this vibrant awesome community
that is really you know one of the driving forces behind the show and so i don't want to break what
it's doing but i also want to call for a focus on um using it really as a tool for content that
should be in the show and vetting out the stuff that's crap well here's an option like you said
earlier that you try to compete with the subreddit about breaking news and stuff and instead of doing
that you could post the articles on it and say this is a potential for a news yeah i've been
doing that now but you know what the problem is is like if you got i want to every now and then
have a few surprises in the news segments that way if somebody goes to that subreddit several
times a day they can turn on last and still maybe hear a story they didn't see in the subreddit i
don't always get there but hey chris i wasn't necessarily saying you weren't doing the research
it's just you are very busy with all these shows going on and you know maybe having somebody like
rick i help you out would be a huge benefit yeah i think i i am going to try to build out a little
team there because there's other you know then that could benefit the other shows too you know
it's not just last i um not to bash it or anything but i don't use like stuff like ours technica or
or gizmodo or stuff like that i usually try to find the primary source because i feel like that
sometimes when you have things like ours technica or gizmodo or or kodoku or or whatever website that
is i i feel that it's sometimes opinionated right and and i'm very factual so i i like to get
just straight to the facts and i don't want to hear about oh well you know it could be used for
this feature i i can kind of discern that for myself but for the most part i use primary resources
if i could build on that i think some of the biggest offenders in the linux world would be
like ferronics or omg ubuntu yes definitely definitely the sites like that do kind of have
the advantage that a they give new users easy to digest information and they also aggregate uh
stories so that a new user who wants linux news wouldn't necessarily have to go find the mailing
list or something like that that's true i just feel that sometimes when we reach out into those
type of sources that it sometimes is a little bit too opinionated to one side than it is to the other
i just don't like the idea of sorry sorry i don't like the idea of putting ferronics in the same
area as like network world because i mean if you really want bad coverage anything from zdnet i mean
well this is the problem you guys is everywhere it's bad coverage it really is pretty bad there's
there's there's a handful of legitimate community-based or or even business-based
outlets that get it right but they're in the minority yeah and i'm just to pipe in on this
a little bit just to give you guys some perspective the bigger the company the worse it is honestly
i'm gonna i'm gonna be real blunt with you and then it just it's just the way it is now if it's
technical information only it's not so bad but if you're trying to actually your job is to grab
eyeballs that's what your job is um be factual if you can but by all means come heaven or hell get
good eyeballs that's really what that's why i love the linux action show because of not only
your commitment but the community's commitment to accuracy right yep yeah i realize this i realize
this probably isn't possible but i think it'd be great if we could get like a uh jupiter news.com
and have a like the community write pieces that's interesting just tell me you wanted to before i
go too far from ours technica you wanted to make a defense there right well yeah oh well yeah there
are technica it depends it depends if how long the article is when i really love their coverage of
like uh geohots and the whole sony hack and the whole doxxing of of um ah that one security
researcher by anonymous that was those were great articles yeah i think so i don't think it's a
black and white thing like i think pharaonix does some good work too with benchmarking and they do
some good work with the steam coverage that they have there so i don't think it's all black and
white most of it's bad on pharaonix if it's like gossipy type stuff but like if it's benchmarked
and things like that that's where pharaonix has its place i think i think when it comes to site
select pharaonix a lot of what i see is the writers are typically people who use windows or os 10
they give linux a try and give it a review based on okay they're giving an ubuntu try for a week
or something a lot of times and also a lot of times when something usually when something
inaccurate happens a lot of times you're looking at a slow news week and so they're combing through
mailing lists looking for any hint of something that can maybe tweak into something that's not or
exaggerated a little bit i mean it's a problem that that really happens but when you have really
good coverage that's not a reflection of how awesome that site is that's a reflection of
really awesome news being there available that week all right wizard wizard jed there has uh
one last remark on pharaonix and i think we'll close the book on pharaon okay yeah i just wanted
to say uh for even pharaonix even for benchmarking you've really got to take a good look at it uh
he's gotten better with time but if you look at any of his old stuff i think he's been learning
with time that you know to get closer and closer and to use the same hardware with everything but
if you go back he'll go and you'll you'll use the same processor and say yeah this is the exact same
bench but he's using it on a board that has a lower lower bus speed than the other one so it's
never going to be the same uh never going to be the same uh benchmark at all but he puts his
hardware in an advantage one of the things he's testing already has an advantage versus the other
thing but he did that for a couple of things like even file system tests and stuff i uh i think i'll
shift gears i think you know i'll wrap up the news discussion with just sort of this comment is i
think i'm thinking more about this stuff too as we reach episode 300 uh so it's my commitment to
martin and the kd project and all of the listeners of the show and that you know i at post 300 i
really want to improve our quality of news and i i want it to be as reliable as any news outlet for
linux it's last isn't about breaking news it's about analyzing the news of the events and and
and commenting on that development for that week and it's sort of every week we're taking a slice
of what happened in the linux and open source world and analyzing it and trying to pull out
the most important things that happened that week so if you if you only listen to one thing i want
the linux action show to be the thing you can listen to and know that you're getting the best
stories of the week and my goal isn't to sort of try to change that model it's just to improve it
and say you know if we can go directly to a source in some cases and just get them on the show and
get it right out of them and quickly as we're doing some or other coverage i think that'd be
a good improvement to the show and i don't know if that's the end goal because that is it is a lot
of work but we'll see post 300 i'd like to see if we can't get there um and uh we'll at least try
to make improvements where we can yeah go ahead i'd like to just uh just say one more thing
regarding last um the great thing about linux action show is even if it's a slow news week
the other main section of the show can really provide something to give that show some um
compared to the news section sure yeah yeah oh yeah that's that's i mean that's what we always
try to make sure that we know last even if you don't like the main topic there's going to be news
and feedback and pics and if you like the main topic and it's a bet it's a win-win etc there's
always something there for everybody uh but why don't we i got an email from uh from somebody
named cash i love that name nice and uh this is an argument that i think i've heard kicked around
i've even considered myself he says hey guys i'm a big fan of linux action show and linux unplugged
it's a great video podcast i have a question though do we really want linux to be a mainstream
os for example imagine everybody in this world able to drive a ferrari or some kind of rare car
it doesn't feel special anymore once again do we really really want linux to be a mainstream us
thanks you guys and keep up the good work cash in malaysia that's an excellent point i mean i think
for myself personally i'm okay with i want everybody in my circle of influence to enjoy it
you know if that makes sense if you say they were a bunch of hipsters now
you know that's kind of where i so here i come down on two minds of this i'm with matt at the
same time i'm like hey as long as it makes me happy and makes anybody that i get to use it or
wants to use it happy that's all it really needs to do and it's up to everybody else to figure it
out on their own and then at the same time i don't know i think maybe it's it's it's maybe
a little bit of that richard stallman in me get it out of here but i i wonder if if if we don't
sort of owe it to try to make this free and open platform available to everyone who doesn't want
to be restricted by the computer systems that are really just designed to monetize them and lock
them down and keep them locked into ecosystems see linux sort of provides this general computing
platform that frees people from the corporatization of computing and in some ways it almost feels like
a duty to make that available to everybody else but the other way i'm like it doesn't mean we
need to sacrifice making an awesome desktop i don't know what do you guys think i i disagree
with the fact that it shouldn't be mainstream i personally would love to see more stuff like
netflix be easily available on linux just to be able to like click and watch without having to use
something like pipeline and have to worry about some bug and wine preventing me to be able to
watch it or some graphics drivers you know getting better see even if the linux does go mainstream
you can still be a hipster if you use awesome or x9 that's true well so i mean like i think wizard
jet here brings up a good point i mean he thinks we've gotten as far as we have because we haven't
been limited just to geeks go ahead wizard yeah uh we we we've always taken in input from everyone
else because linux only exists because the community has made it exist you know just the
kernel doesn't make all of linux just just the new user land doesn't make just all of linux
it's because we've all gotten together and made certain parts and because everyone's had input
we've made what we have today and it's only through going and you know having more people
in there we that i can only see benefits of having you know the clinics get better i know this is
going to make a lot of people form at the mouth but i think canonicals efforts in the past what
is it uh 13 i mean no i mean eight nine years that they have done to bring ubuntu to it used
to be linux for human beings but now it's i guess mainstream that has helped bring linux so far to
where it is now i think that's what linspire attempted to do and wasn't able to do successfully
but they learned from their mistakes and built up built upon it yeah yeah i i agree they've
helped a lot with uh getting a lot more people to try it and you just look at the adoption you've
seen in business too that that's that's not quite fair to all the other projects that you know
wouldn't be able to exist if it wasn't for them too so it's it there's a lot of there's a lot of
love to go around but i think i agree in the end bringing more and more people in all the time
improves the linux to look at look at it in a different way uh linux has seen such an we're
going to cover a story on sunday that i've already been researching uh that about uh where the code
growth is in linux over 2013 and uh the linux foundation put out their analysis you guys
probably all saw the link now and uh it it to me is so it so underscores how bringing in arm and
going to mobile even though like we see a lot of companies like google and android and samsung sort
of using linux for all these different things it actually has brought so much to linux itself so
many new features so many new improvements have come from that work and continue to come from
that work efficiencies too and that's by bringing in a new class of people and a new class of
hardware partners because it's not just users it's not just desktop users it's developers it's
hardware manufacturers it's business interests and we've brought them in and because of that
we've gotten better we've gotten stronger and i would argue that you know we we used to bang on
tevo for the tevo ization of linux but i don't think it's harmed linux one little tiny teensy bit
here's my only fear and the you can call me richard stallman for all you care but
but um i just don't want to see that we have a whole bunch of developers developed to a point
where a lot of the linux kernel or a lot of the linux stuff that's in there is closed off from
people so like only the development comes from the developer teams i i would prefer to see kind
of like a symbiotic relationship between the developers and the open community just a little
bit because say like you know like how we have adobe killing us on flash so we have to figure
out ways of working around with flash a little bit more it it would probably be more beneficial
if yes i do think that we need more people but we also want to have people that would be willing to
contribute to the community not just not just in a software fashion but also in a communication
fashion i don't even necessarily think they have to directly contribute but i mean if somebody
you know is helping support them or if it's a support team that may run into these issues
the more people using it the more issues that get highlighted and fixed i think wimpy fills
this role really well right now with the mate project where he's uh you know he's here he's
advocating made he's very informed about he's communicating with the developers he's working
with a large distribution uh it's it's it's exactly what a lot of these projects need and
so i think he's a great example i'm another reason i'm glad he could join us this week
uh well there you go cash there's the uh there's the community's uh the virtual lugs thoughts on
linux staying mainstream it sounds like for the good of linux we have to continue to grow we must
assimilate all as the borg would say uh all right matt well i think we'll wrap it up right there at
that point um i'm not gonna say what we're gonna talk about on sunday i'm just not gonna do that
anymore because every time i commit something comes up and we have something else but i will
say there is a possibility according to the forecast that we'll have snow so if matt ends
up skyping in on sunday that you can assume we got a good uh snow dumping here in washington
yeah and i and because of where i live i live i live in a valley but i also live in the highlands
it's kind of hard to explain but we get the worst of it in town so you never know but we'll find out
and i live on a nice hill yeah you do oh oh that's right oh god i just remembered that yeah i'll
probably but depending on what it looks like i'll either uh i may be skyping in we'll find out there's
a there's a long route you can go that's not quite as steep but uh yeah i should make a programming
note here too uh if you're a jb live uh streamer uh and you watch tech snap check out uh tech snap
it's going to be a double texting up on thursday we'll be starting at 11 a.m uh jupiter broadcasting
time that specific time 11 a.m but you can go to jupiter broadcasting dot com slash calendar
to get it in your local time zone and we're doing a double show because uh tech snap won't be live
next week but tech snap never misses a show just like this actually here we are 26 weeks in we've
never missed a show what's up we know what's going on so here why don't you come participate
join our virtual log hang out in our chat room you get to help title the show you guys get to
get your thoughts in there i'm watching that the entire time go over to jblive.tv on a tuesday we
start at 2 p.m pacific jupiter broadcasting dot com slash calendar has that in your time zone
we'd also like to get your feedback on any topics we discuss we like to feature that in every show
we put it right at the top because you guys matter to us jupiter broadcasting dot com click on the
contact link choose unplugged from the drop down all right matt i'll see you on sunday