anybody had a chance to catch my new video series you guys seen the new the
new video series I launched I think I've done three videos three videos are out
now we're just now getting to Berkeley and at meet BSD so I've got a question
for you sir and what why have you struck out with your own individual YouTube
track channel excuse me well because it's a couple of things is I have good
question I have been I've been over the last year I've become more of a YouTube
content consumer you know I've always just sort of viewed YouTube as the place
that is it's like another RSS feed we just dump we give it we put another dump
of our stuff on YouTube and I haven't given a lot of thought to how people
actually watch content on YouTube and so as I started watching more and more my
content on YouTube because I don't have any other really great way to watch
current daily television and I got the Android TV and it just sort of changed
how how I how I consume YouTube and I realized that I don't like the channels
that post all kinds of stuff political stuff development stuff tech news stuff
Linux stuff it's like it's too much it's I when I sit down and watch the
television I like I'm kind of an eminent I'm gonna track I have something I want
to watch and so because this wasn't technical it's not really about Linux
it's not about information security or networking it's it's just it's really
more about me and it gets more personal as it goes on it sort of felt like I
would be disrespecting the subscribers of the Jupiter broadcasting channel
because I was sort of dumping something in their feed that wasn't why they
subscribe to Jupiter broadcasting they subscribe for technical content oh and
here's ten videos which are tangently connected to technical content but only
for a small percentage of them enjoy it just but people like it and so it just
felt like it was probably more appropriate to do something that was
like this on my own channel and and then if there is probably I don't know yet
but long term if there seems to be a lot of interest and it's worth a lot of
effort on my part I would probably continue to produce it as a side channel
to Jupiter broadcasting that's more like this the show behind the shows this is
Lennox Unplugged episode 173 for November 29th 2016
Oh welcome to Lennox Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's got a random craving
for curry and beer my name is Chris my name is Wes hello Wes yeah you've got me
hungry let's be honest Wes we have a newspack show and and Chris has been
complaining for the last few weeks hasn't he yes it's the dearth of the
news what's going on but now we've got it's back I guess everybody was just on
Halloween break I'm not sure what Thanksgiving break now they've got their
food they've got fresh energy they're making they're all back and they're
making tons of open source updates we're gonna cover a lot of them coming up on
this week's show we're gonna start with like the only non Linux stuff that's
worth talking about just right here at the top we're gonna take our medicine
and then moving on into the show did you hear about the core VLC developer who
says no one cares about Linux that hurts it did hurt and apparently it hurt him
too just as much we'll tell you why plus Debian is making a big change Ubuntu is
gonna go with a rolling hardware kernel what is that really what's happening
we'll tell you about that snaps have some nice updates coming along we'll get
a little state of the snap the new XPS is out but there could be some big
limitations and then we're gonna get super nerdy with Wes we're gonna talk
about net data net data back ends data miner DB and all the crazy stuff he's
been working on in his day job recently you know what I'm really looking forward
to this because Wes you know we don't I don't know if it comes up in the show
very much but you are heads down in this stuff all the time and you're working on
some of the most buzzword heavy stuff that we talk about ain't that it is
actually your day job so we're gonna talk a little bit about that then also
just sort of a heads up for noobs on managing devices in Linux and then last
but not least I'd like to round out the show with a classic conversation it came
up in light of the fedora 25 review we did and that is upgrade versus nuke and
pave when you're doing a new install or like a new release or etc etc so
obviously if you just watch this week's episode Linux action show I'm referring
to my upgrade from fedora 24 to 25 I've gotten a ton of feedback and by feedback
I mean extreme criticism one nice probing like hey Chris why did you
choose to do it this way and about 95 you moron so we're gonna we're gonna
talk about those and talk about upgrade versus a new campaign because I think
that's sort of a classic that we really haven't tackled much on this show so
there's a ton of stuff to get into I did mention we have some veggies so to help
us chew on these let's bring in that virtual lug timer appropriate greetings
mumble room sandwich in there and I am hungry I don't know I don't know you
know I get some child Chris I do you're right I oh well Wes has helped hooking me
up though he brought in like this cozy sweater brew which is from Iron Horse
brewery which that sounds kind of interesting cozy sweater a vanilla milk
stout it's rich it's not too heavy I think where's this one from here canned
and brewed by Iron Horse brewery in Washington hey Ellensburg you have yet
to bring something outside the Pacific Northwest there was one the the Melvin
but wasn't in the Pacific Northwest all right I won't but that was a really good
beer so there has to be an exception so I'm gonna give it a go I'm gonna give it
a hold on survey says beer is delicious that's a great beer that's quite tasty I
might say that beer is tasty Wes thank you very much cheers to Linux so this
headline is a little revolting this I I'm not gonna do I'm not gonna decry
fake news but this headlines a little much Microsoft is telling developers
whatever you're doing in Linux soon Windows 10 will do it and better
whatever Linux can do we can do better the tech giant Nick Heath writes lays
out its plans for the future of Ubuntu and bash on Windows 10 there's a couple
of interesting little tidbits in here I thought we might cover mm-hmm it's laced
with this language that I find myself exhausted by and I'm really hoping as we
move on people can stop speaking and writing like this and you know it's
sentences like this the firm recently updated Windows 10 to let users run a
range of Linux tools from inside the OS the firm the firm being yet another way
to refer to the tech giant which is another way to refer to the company in
Redmond which is another way to refer to Microsoft I'm so sick of it and then it
goes into this this sentence structure that implies that Microsoft were the
ones to create this Windows 10 runtime that Microsoft did the development work
when it was canonical that did the heavy lifting there Microsoft did the kernel
enablements but that stuff was there for other compatibility layers they've had
in the years past and the previous version of this sentence it wrote the
firm quietly updated Windows 10 to let users run quietly updated and they
removed the quietly since since we first started and it's just kind of that's
that's obnoxious but they say whatever this is a quote from a Microsoft
representative whatever it is that you normally do on Linux to build an
application whether it's in go Erlang or in C whatever you use please give it a
try on bash on Windows and they also want you to file bugs they say you know
it's a big part of it the article goes on to say forthcoming updates some of
which already available to those using the early builds of Windows 10 under the
insider program includes support for Ubuntu 1604 hey more Linux tools like
IF config and ping so you can which is really nice because there's a lot of
tools that rely on IF config to get information so if you don't have IF
config a lot of other tools don't work the other major new addition will be
increased interoperability between bash and Windows environments effectively
this will let developers call Windows applications from within bash well
allowing them to write a bash script to automate complex builds that include
Windows applications and to invoke bash applications from Windows PowerShell
this all makes me feel very funny inside Chris so all of this is moderately nice
right good for them at one point is Microsoft advocating that you stop using
Linux and switch to Windows because the headline says Microsoft tells devs
whatever you're doing in Linux Windows 10 will do soon too the tech giant lays
out his plans for the future of Ubuntu on bash on Windows 10 the only thing the
guy said is whatever it is that you normally do on Linux to build an
application whether it's in go Erlang or C whatever you use please he says please
comma give it a try on bash on Windows that's that's a very that's right it
seems like really they just want users and they want to make it better which I
mean yeah perhaps with no ill intent I mean were you gonna say something I was
gonna say Windows does it better except for running dotnet and SQL Server Linux
apparently does that call out to a Linux action show story week yeah dotnet got
that dotnet team was starting to run stuff on Linux and was surprised by 2x
performance improvement before the identity optimization this is another
kind of story like I said we just got a couple of non-linux stories that are
kind of Linux related here at the top can I just say yeah good I am sick of
them calling it bash for Windows when they implemented the Linux kernel
compatibility layer and they're still just calling it bash it just seems so
weird do you think they should be calling it for Linux when should they
call for Ubuntu on Linux I don't know it depends on what their ultimate goal is
yeah they might just want to call it like a Linux compat layer because that's
exactly what it is the technology is called Windows subsystem for Linux yeah
that's its actual name I'm just it's the people calling it bash for Windows but
actual Microsoft representatives are saying bash on window a better say bash
on WSL or something like that they say bash on Ubuntu on Windows that's how
it's pitched not in that article though all the ZS users really hurt I do
actually feel like Ubuntu should get more prominence not only because it's a
name brand that people recognize but also because it is the Ubuntu user land
you're using and they did a lot of the work to you know help make this happen
seems weird to lean on to leave it's not like I mean I've seen arch running on
there but I'm not seeing I'm not seeing a lot of people running anything but a
boot to at this point and if you're doing anything in production you're
gonna be using the official image from Microsoft like bootstraps the Ubuntu
image and gets apt working everything whereas like getting another environment
working is incredibly painful the way they've set it up so far so there was a
bug on Azure that specifically affected Red Hat instances did you see this mm-hmm
this is a thing that I guess Amazon had probably engineered around because of
their long experience but every now then you know I mean as you're in some senses
is a newer platform right and the vulnerability was discovered by an Irish
software engineer called Ian Duffy Ian Duffy I'm sorry I bet how how how how
great would have been if it was I key right I mean how good that would have
been amazing that would 100% anyway so I key discovered and reported on my to
Microsoft as part of its bug program I key discovered that the glitch while
working a while that while working on a hardened Red Hat Enterprise Linux for
use on both Amazon Web Services and Azure now here's what it was kind of
interesting is because part of the spec you should have operated under a
metered billing pricing model consuming software updates from a local Red Hat
Enterprise Linux repository owned and managed by Azure or Amazon depending on
what you're using mm-hmm both AWS and Azure utilize deployment of the Red Hat
update infrastructure places super boring I'm sorry anyways he noticed that
some Red Hat packages RPMs contained client configurations for each reason
region on Azure from this he was able to discover all the URLs for all of the
regional reddit update applications on Azure and obtain access to archives
containing log files configuration files and SSL updates and they could be used
to gain full administrative access to the update appliances he said that
despite the applications requiring usings and password-based authentication
it was possible to execute and run their back-end log collector on a specified
content delivery server when the collector service completed the
application supplied URLs to archives which would then contain multiple logs
and configuration files from the servers he said it might have also been able to
get access to the storage accounts because he was able to read all of the
information in those logs Microsoft has since taken action to prevent public
access to log monitoring application and the Red Hat update appliances but it's
not really known if anybody ever exploited these particular vulnerabilities
in the wild so he's looking around seeing these RPMs these RPMs have all of
the source URLs for the main servers he then goes to the main servers discovers
the logs are available from by reading the law you can just grab those files he
gets the whole map of the Azure Network and starts getting access to the systems
it's probably pretty hard to run a cloud it's like they're getting better at it
but there's always these little problems you know what else is hard and that like
I said just we're just gonna talk about a couple of these we're not gonna spend
a lot of time on this but damn it this pisses me off so much this pisses me off
so damn much Android is hard especially the security on it and this is an
article that is probably worth your time and the you may have seen the headline
floating around Android security in 2016 is a mess he points out the obvious
vendors like LG Samsung you know me etc after selling you the phone have no
incentive to keep your phone software up to date with Google's fixes and
everybody knows this and he goes in and makes some really brilliant points in
here this talks out it talks about the media tech and blue phones that were
available on Amazon they were uploading all of your information oh right I goes
into how the A-list phone makers manage he talks about how Google's incentives
don't really stack up either and then when we get to the what can we do
segment of the article he says if money is no object my only sound advice can be
to buy an iPhone Apple is still shipping security updates albeit iOS 9 for the
iPhone 4s which was released in 2011 that's five years ago kids the iPhone
5 is still being kept up to date with iOS 10 furthermore then you look at the
things like encryption implementations iOS 4 released six years ago was already
more advanced than the encryption in Android 7 Nougat released in August of
this year in short already Apple has made better choices and how exactly
different files are encrypted while Android went for a whole disk
encryption which tanked battery life tanked CPU performance nobody used it
all the OEMs disabled it yeah exactly and Android's finally gone its file
base but they're actually not even doing that and they're not encrypting
important parts of users data which is detailed in another blog post so he says
if you're gonna go Android if you're gonna stick with Android you got to go
pixel or Nexus so mr. pixel um why didn't you get an iPhone you know I've
had an iPhone before I had an iPhone 4 for quite some time and it wasn't bad
but it's just so it iOS just feels like a different abstraction than a
traditional computer or a computer that I recognize and know how to use well
that's a great way to put it and so it's not bad and I can see how other people
might like it they've done a lot of very you're never gonna get access to the
file system you'll never understand the structure of it you don't have an
understanding of how applications can actually communicate with each other
yeah you have no visibility over the processes on the machine I'm also
someone you know who falls into weird little niches and I like to do weird
things like try to run tink on my phone or whatever and so it's just without
jailbreaking and then breaking a lot of the you know security that iOS has I
don't really have no way to do that boy that is a that is a great point
William did you specifically have I know you and I kind of talked about this
before do you have any thoughts on this particular topic I'm so frustrated by
the iPhone but it's so much better than my Android experience I think overall
that I stick with it what frustrated I'm frustrated that like a lot of
applications won't run in the background all the time and so you know like sync
clients and things which I have three of I have to open manually when I want them
to sync yeah yeah that is so frustrating and technically is infrastructure to get
that working but none of them have it working so I don't know what the deal is
yeah yeah they can't check to see if you're plugged in or on battery which I
think is frustrating like I know sync thing on Android is super nice because
you can set it so that it only activates when it's plugged in and it only
activates on Wi-Fi and then you know you're not gonna drain your battery by
connecting to sync thing but it was when you I were talking about this in
pre-production I was like well what do we have anything new to really add to
this conversation I mean you've got the pixel so you've made your choice there I
have the iPhone 7 specifically because of this reason this was the thing that
pushed me over that and application stability but your mom she's on an older
she's on an older phone yeah she's got the Nexus 5 not no longer getting the
new new updates does that as a geek does that bother you a little bit yeah you
feel like gosh maybe I should get mom a new phone for Christmas yeah you know it
makes me yeah it makes me think about that like should I have just told her to
buy you know buy the book at the iPhone even if it was expensive mm-hmm and I
wish I could give her more but you know there's just nothing I can do to help
her and she's not gonna buy a pixel that's just she doesn't need a phone
she doesn't use it to that capability she just needs a smartphone for the base
stuff you know wimpy is in there with the the Ubuntu touch you know that's
right so he's like a whole nother level when it comes to this because even when
you're on the iPhone you know you really you're putting your trust and faith in
Apple not to screw something up or not to work with somebody or etc etc so
I feel like wimpy he's like he's like the prepper you know like the crazy
prepper who's got like the bunker that's filled with all of the stuff for y2k
that's wimpy right now I don't want to be that might wake you up really what
are your thoughts on this it was security one of the things that moved
you towards the Ubuntu mobile platform or was it what what not not security so
much as just the data pooling and you know in light of oh yeah that's right
the Google aspect of which we're not we haven't even broadened the conversation
yeah point and not just not just the Google aspect but now I don't know if
this is being publicized in the US but the Investigatory Powers Bill has now
passed as law yeah you can I've done a little bit of following yeah replacing a
something that was declared unlawful by the courts last year and was due to
expire at the end of this year so fortunately for the government they must
be so pleased this new law has been passed and enacted that now makes the
previously unlawful thing lawful which is just terrific so yeah so you know
with those sorts of things and therefore you know companies like Google who
obviously got access to a lot of data they now become the government's best
friend when they're looking to mine information and it's not so much about
my own personal data because it's all in aggregate it's how the we were talking
about YouTube incorrectly content IDing stuff earlier I think you know a trend
that we will start to see is data mining for particular keywords and you know
photo image analysis that incorrectly indicates that people are subject to or
should be subject further deeper investigation in error is going to be
something you know maybe a nightmare scenario would be let's say you're using
Google Allo for your text messaging and you know you you have young kids and
sometimes you you you would pass photos back and forth as the kids those would
be those would be indexed but then also you know sometimes like you know I don't
know I'm this hypothetical but like maybe I'd put a joke in there about oh
I'm so sick of the kids let's put them on the street corner and see if we can
sell them for 50 bucks mm-hmm you know or some joke like that that is an in
joke between two people that know it's an absolute joke but now what happens if
the government gets access to that data and can index all of it and build a
personality profile about you or something creepy like that and the other
example I've used in the past is that being in a family where there are lots
of young children and as I've explained and any father will know young
children have a predisposition to take off all of their clothes and run around
but naked or or as near as when when photographs of taken of your children in
those situations and you happen to have cloud-sinking services turned on the
flesh tone analysis algorithms that can run over those photographs aren't
associating you as the parent of that child and the innocence of the situation
it's just a whether this is a suspicious image or not and and if that then gets
flagged up as you are now a person of interest you know that's not what you
want so that these are where my concerns it's not about my individual data it's
about how that can be I think even if you don't have a specific scenario even
if it's not about kids because that's sort of hard to connect for people that
aren't parents I think where my where my concern lies is if we're if we're
monitoring collecting and storing the date the data and records today what
information will they be able to generate and suss out you know years
down the road because once you have it stored what you can analyze and look at
that data it's endless right and as we know there are so many laws that it's
easy to violate even unintentionally or you know what that means true so I
William I heard you sign is there anybody else that wants to jump on
before we move on jump on jump on you know no okay oh well I got that took a
weird turn that took a weird turn I got weird you know we started I came in no
it's good it's good I just how have you been liking the pixel let me pick it up
you've been liking it oh you let me hold it again yeah sure so you're right now
two weeks into it yeah I still need to get a case and protect I'll probably
order that tonight yeah what I have what have you what have you thought so far
I'm liking it a lot it's a I haven't I haven't done much I haven't like
customized it very much or used it but obviously I'm enjoying USB C that's very
nice it does charge fast as advertised I am liking the camera there's some
differences I did like some things about my previous phone as well but I'm having
a good time with it and the battery life has been great so I feels like I'm on
like a modern platform I'm getting I'm you know I've got the updates from
Google yes I feels like it's a phone I can use and like not have to think
about I do agree with the author that if you're on the Nexus line if you're on
the pixel line you're in a much better position that is I do feel like I if you
set aside the other Google privacy aspects and you just go for the OS we
all know we all know this stuff needs patches constantly I mean if they're
running with Linux kernel in there you know you know there's not only them not
only is their own their own software have vulnerabilities in it but there's
just core fundamental vulnerabilities in the underlying kernel and so getting
those security updates for me was sort of like a baseline and I I'm not trying
to be fancy about it I'm not trying to say like oh you can I'm not trying to be
like some like Android master race user that says you can only buy pixel or
Nexus I'm saying really like if if you care at all about like the security of
your laptop or your servers or your desktop you should honestly really care
about the security of your phone and I think that's why I talk about this
because there is such a mindset out there and I don't mean to call anybody
out but you know I go to these meetups and I see people and they pull out their
old Android phones and I'm not trying to shame them but they're really old and
insecure and I understand absolutely when it's a when it's a budget thing but
you know even a 5x would be still getting updates and you can pick it up
for fairly cheap definitely so I don't know it's oh I really would like people
to to to think about this I would really like people to to walk around devices
that are getting updates just simply for not just them but for the rest of the
network yeah exactly it's a community thing well speaking of networks let's
let's stop right here and we've been talking about mobile let's talk about
our first sponsor that's this week this fit it all in let's bring it all
together that'd be ting go over to linux.ting.com to get $25 off your first
device or $25 in service credit ting is a great solution to this if you have a
Nexus or a pixel device they don't have like an agenda to get you to install
their version of a launcher or their skin there's nothing there's nothing
about that experience that ting uses to monetize the user that requires they
stay on the way of the updates it's it's totally opposite of their business model
ting does not get in the way of the updates from the upstream OEM if you
have a Nexus device you get the monthly updates if you have a Samsung device when
Samsung ships an update you get a day of on the ting network there's no there's
no incentive for ting to delay it and that's the business model you want now
that's that's sort of just a side ting is just great all around also because if
you only pay for what you use wireless it's six dollars for a line so if you
want a couple of phones if you have a Nexus 6p and you have an iPhone 7 like I
do because I'm working on both two lines six dollars a month
Rekai upstairs he's over he's working up he's working in the upstairs basement
right now editing this show as we go and I'll tell you what it would be extremely
expensive for Jupiter broadcasting to pay for a traditional phone line like a
giant family plan because he's he doesn't you know he talks to friends and
family over Skype isn't they all do Skype he's on Telegram all the time and
when he's here which is most of the time he's on Wi-Fi yeah and so why would I
pay for like even a hundred minutes he doesn't use it why would I do that it's
so great because I can give him total mobile freedom if he wants to go outside
the studio and go do stuff he's got data he's got cellular he's good to go from
a business perspective you can communicate with him as you need to
exactly otherwise when he's here I'm only paying for what he uses six dollars
for the line I think it's so great so go to Linux dot ting comm to support the
show and get a twenty five dollar discount they have a Black Friday sale
and I think maybe ting forgot to check their calendar I think some of these
devices are still on sale yeah like you can get the LG tribute 5 for 50 bucks
Wow and look at this you can also get the tin tell it I don't know it any tell
I don't even know what this is a wearable phone and GPS tracker for 150
bucks plus 50 and ting credit look at that it's like a that is so cool it's
like a little tracker runner thing that has a CDMA yeah and ting is great for
that things you just need a data connection for you know I know because
you can get just the GSM you only pay for when you use it look at this thing
has GPS you can track it on a map that's pretty cool pretty cool and it has a
phone too that's amazing for 150 bucks Wow I never even seen it that's that is
the greatest check them out linux.com mobile that makes sense shake up the
mobile industry and get your patches don't let your mobile carrier stand in
your way linux.com let's move into some more updates now we have things that are
a little more controversial you might have seen the headline core VLC
developer says no one cares about Linux and open HMD is a joke oh my gosh over
at VR on linux.com this is a spicy post an email exchange between Norbert and
one of the core developers of VLC and always in gadget do you remember the
details on this I can't remember the details it was very heated it was
very the video land dev said this is well let's get to the because this
actually doesn't really matter because this is the part that just caused
everybody get upset right the video land developer said that no one cares about
Linux and the VR has no shot on Linux mostly it's a driver issue and this got
a lot of attention today and it's kind of disappointing because when the story
was posted to r slash Linux JB stopped by and answered and said hey I'm I'm the
guy that was being interviewed in this email exchange here and I never said
that about Linux that's not what I said now it's not clear exactly what how that
happened right yeah but I want to get into the quotes I want to get into what
he says actually happened but before we do that this is all sort of gotten the
ball started got rolling here when VLC announced 360 degree view in the Windows
and Mac OS versions of VLC but not in the Linux version so the website VR and
Linux decided to reach out to the VLC project find out what what would the
deal was hey guys how come we don't have 360 degree video in VLC and as wimpy
will often advocate this is a core feature that we absolutely have to have
on the Linux desktop is 360 degree VR video and so I believe I believe no okay
so the VR on Linux site reached out and got kind of I don't know a snappish back
and forth there was a bit of a culture clash he goes into their IRC they start
making some typical jokes about Linux in their IRC that everybody kind of knows
are just jokes this journalist supposedly quote-unquote
journalist this person that runs the website supposedly takes these quotes
out of context and then creates the headline VLC developer says no one cares
about Linux that's the background so here is what that VLC developer actually
says he says the issue on VR is that there are a very large number of
headsets and that all of them require some different drivers and different
API's to work with them even on Windows it's not very stable and unfortunately
the people riding the drivers do not care about Linux hence the quote but the
very very very three varies large majority of developers of VLC are using
Linux because it's the only same system you can use to base your work on
therefore I have never ever ever said no one cares about Linux this is the most
stupid thing I have ever seen especially outside the VR context but yes so far
very few people care about Linux VR the drivers are very bad compared to Windows
and the gamers using VR are very few on Linux seems pretty fair yeah very few
anywhere aren't they mm-hmm right well maybe we'll see there's a Star Trek game
coming out that might get me to get a PlayStation if I could I would I had a
prediction on that other podcast you know the other one for this year which
was that VR would continue to lack adoption and I found some figures to
demonstrate what the market thought the VR adoption would be this year oh and
what the adoption has actually been and it is abysmally below target by millions
and millions and millions of units so I don't think calling out Linux for poor
VR support is an issue because there's very little VR support and what VR
support exists is beyond the means of most people anyway unless you have an S6
or S7 and that I say that because I was at a Thanksgiving event over the
holiday and one of our family friends was there with a Samsung s7 and the new
VR headset and it was here how much does an S how much does an S7 and the
matching headset cost you know the S7 out the same as a VR gaming PC and you
know what it's it's so bad it is so worse than even the oculus than the
5 it is it is it is it is baby VR it's baby VR with a diaper on it and with a
with a stinker in the diaper and it's going around telling everybody it's VR
and it I you know I watched everybody there try it on and that was their first
VR experience and I went home yeah you can look at a dinosaur yeah you can you
can look at the up to the Jeeps over there and you can look at a dinosaur
that's VR all right it is very disappointing it's very expensive the
hardware requirements are ridiculous the headsets are not standardized the all of
it is just it's a total it's a total doesn't give a good approximation of
what like the most exciting aspects of VR at least like the good ones are at
least looking from the outside and I got it I will I will admit I am NOT a VR
enthusiast I do not follow it super closely but at least looking from the
outside it does look like it is stacked for failure core companies haven't come
together like I would have expected them by now there's no standardizations like
I would have expected by now big companies that I would have thought
would be in it are not in it right now it's still kind of small there's not a
solution for the cable problem right now we haven't seen like 2017 you know
concept models of VR headsets that are totally wireless what we're seeing
instead are backpack PCs that have huge power cords coming off of them this is
this is not looking good so maybe Linux not being on the forefront of it isn't
the biggest deal yeah I guess I'd love to be wrong because I really felt like
my experience with the oculus was sort of revolutionary yeah I know a lot of
people who like the vibe a lot yeah I heard good things do you have any
thoughts on Debian putting everything in slash user screw it we're just gonna put
everything all of the things no that's not actually quite true but there is
evidence of a shift that can be found in the bootstrap option that has arrived in
the latest unstable branch where Debian developer has posted news in the mailing
list as well saying that if you use Deb bootstrapping with a certain command you
can now merge slash user with slash bin s bin and lib they'll be they'll put
symlinks in their former positions or something to that effect do I have that
right mm-hmm you know and there's consolidation like Arches done is that
what you're gonna say would be I was gonna say exactly the same thing isn't
this what fedora and arch have done several years ago yep yeah I think I
mean it's it's funny in the historical sense that now like everything is under
slash user you know given like it's like some of its original purposes and just
like it's we could just have those things under you know just under the
root directory perhaps but I think practically you know we have the file
system we have we have the you know legacy and dependencies on the file
system structure so this seems like a very practical thing to do I was looking
it looks like arch did this back in 2013 mm-hmm which means I've been using
that's when I switch I switch to arch right as the systems I just first set up
we're switching over and then the systems I set up slightly after already
had this transition said it so that's that's my milestone was this big switch
that arch did that's a long time anyways if you're curious the new option is sort
of it's sort of nice one of the reasons for the change that the current hierarchy
creates busywork for developers they have said like back in January developers
were talking about the change would mean that we don't have to try to harass a
thousand package maintainers into doing essentially on untestable busywork to
move things around between slash user slash business live to support a tiny
handful of systems for which other approaches are available and they also
say another good reason for doing this it greatly simplifies the creation of
read-only file systems which are useful for things like USB Linux distros and
secure environments transaction updates things like that
hey sounds like a good thing not a big deal really
Debbie and just sort of coming in line with changes but I guess this means that
Ubuntu will also be making this change that I guess is newsworthy too and I
don't really think it's gonna cuz with symlinks left in place it almost don't
imagine the majority of people will see this I was like I would like them to say
hey no symlinks nice and clean you know what that breaks though there's a there
are distros there are distros out there that have radically different file
systems mobile can any of you be my external brain what's the one I'm
thinking of that has a totally different file system hierarchy that makes a lot
more sense that they're the only distro bow Linux maybe I think that's it yeah
gobo was posted there nixos also does something yeah every package is stored
individually every single build hey you 1604 users would you like in a little
hwe huh huh you want a little hwe yes I do a little hardware enablement that's
right sick starting with Ubuntu 16.04.2 and beyond you're gonna get hardware
enabling hardware enablement kernels which are backported from newer Ubuntu
releases in order to allow new hardware to work on the older LTS release that's
not new that's not all of that interesting but what is new is they're
calling this new version a rolling hardware enablement kernel a rolling hwe
kernel essentially consumers of an hwe kernel will automatically be upgraded to
the next kernel offered in the subsequent point releases until reaching
the final kernel offered in 16.04.5 so it's not like true rolling it's just
that you automatically get your kernel upgraded to the next hardware enablement
kernel with future LTS point releases I think I'm getting that right I mean
perhaps a more yeah not quite rolling but at least more frequent I like that
though approximately I was talking with mr. Tonell there in the in the Mamba
room about neon and neon is based on 1604 and if I do decide to try out the
plasma desktop again I think I'm gonna do it on neon and I like the idea that
I'll get a modern neon desktop right LTS 1604 that gets hardware enabled
kernels which means newer laptops will be supported and whatnot so hopefully a
very stable system that's not gonna you know you get new things but it's not
gonna break on you yeah yeah that is that is particularly appealing to me you
know kinds oh yeah oh you are what do you think about this as somebody who's
kind of doing that very approach do you care about news like this is this seem
like this is gonna be kind of a compelling feature to what you're now
using as your standard desktop this is great for future proofing stuff I mean
even though it's not really a thing but it's more like my hardware is fine I
don't have a problem with it but the the fact that this they're using a 1604 and
their their goal for neon is to always be LTS so in a year or two oh well not
two but a year and a year and a half it'll be more of a problem that is it's
based on 1604 just like every district that's our ever been LTS based that you
know 1404 like elementary or mint or whatever they always had the same kind
of problems with hardware support and stuff like that so this kind of yeah
that was very nice provides a benefit to that too and also because the church of
neon maybe can I pick on you do you know does this mean like if I'm running an
1604 install will I have a newer version of the kernel will it be like version
4.8 or is it stuff that actually gets back ported to the 1604 kernel that
shipped every right so this this isn't so different from what's been done in
previous year or previous LTS is so the point to release is always the release
where the hardware enablement kernel first lands and traditionally that has
been named after the current interim release kernel that's out so at the
moment that's Yakety that's from 1610 so the 1610 kernel will get back ported
into 1604 and traditionally it's not just the kernel it's also the graphics
stack comes along with it as well oh right I remember that yeah that is kind
of a big deal too but the names of the packages were always named after the
interim release so they were something something hyphen Yakety and I think
what's happening this time round is that that naming convention will be dropped
so that once you opt in to the hardware enablement kernel which you have to
manually do it via updates if you're running 1604 dot one or earlier or will
be embedded by default in the 1604 dot two ISOs once you've opted into that
you will get the subsequent releases for zesty and whatever a and B might be
automatically through updates once you've opted into the hardware
enablement kernel that's pretty neat you and do you know if this is changed all
if I've also opted into the live patching service or can I have my cake
and eat it too you know I don't know the details on that I will imagine that the
live patch will work but I tell you what why don't we discuss that next week and
I'll get an answer from an authoritative source I guess I'm sort of fantasizing
about like a 1604 machine with a current desktop environment a hardware
enablement kernel that continues to give back ports and live patches that's
sounding like a great workstation it really does yeah exactly I was about to
say perfect work so this the only thing that's changed here though is that in
the past you would choose to opt into a particular right kernel release it
sounds more like how I'd want to be stacked whereas this time it will now
move with each of the interim releases automatically which seems ideal really
yeah and and sort of playing into this sort of making that the ideal
workstation is I saw a really popular story today on Twitter was actually from
OMG Ubuntu about I think it was five applications I already snapped up that
you can install right now and of course one of them was telegram which is of
course they're gonna get you up the top of my list and I it seems to be there's
some serious movement happening around snaps so I kind of wanted to pick
wimpy's brain if we go a little bit further and and talk about this story I
saw on softpedia this is now you can package your apps as snaps without
bundling their dependencies which I would think would make these snaps
significantly smaller but I but at the same time that feels like it's sort of
defeating the entire purpose I thought the whole point was that I download this
one thing and everything runs what's going on with me well this is utilizing
the content sharing interface which was tabled at the snappy sprint in the
summer which was the sprint that all the community people were invited to so the
likes of the elementary project and the KDE team via blue systems and myself
then as well so this is when we first heard about this content sharing
interface and the idea here is that if you have got a common platform that lots
of applications target then that platform can be snapped and it can share
its assets so that applications can connect to them so for example in this
in this case the the article in question is talking about the Ubuntu app
platform which is essentially Qt based applications so those that you will find
in Unity 8 for example so here you now have a platform snap for Qt and you can
now elect to connect to those assets in that common platform for your Qt based
snap so does that mean the client is aware when I install something that says
hey I've already got all of the Qt dependencies and since that's that's
something that's so specifically these are not dependencies this is a word you
absolutely have to avoid this is this is a either a bunch of libraries or a bunch
of assets but it essentially a collection of files that another snap
can connect to and behind the scenes they're effectively being bind mounted
into your application at runtime oh okay so so if another application I've
installed has those libraries the new application I install will mount that
image connect to the and use the libraries in that image yeah yeah
exactly so so how does that affect like updates like if I update one snap but
the other snap doesn't get updated but it's dependent I'm not depending but
linking in order to control that there's a mechanism called assertions that make
sure that you can ensure that this particular platform snap can is
compatible with this particular application snap and and and the those
those connections won't be broken in any way how does that avoid be feeling like
dependencies though because it doesn't that sound like okay would that then
prevent one snap from getting updated if another snap is using its libraries not
necessarily because the platform snaps can be versioned independently so in the
GTK parlance you could have a GTK 318 platform snap and a GTK 320 platform
snap and a GTK 322 snap okay and within the application that you're creating so
let's choose get it you can define in the get it snap which which version of
the platform snap it requires I see okay it seems like it's like a handy option
where like you then you know if you don't want to depend on one of those you
still have all this capability and roll your bring your dependencies with you
exactly and and you know there are some big wins here so the sizes of the
individual application snaps come down considerably sure yeah the example of
these cute applications they were looking at individual applications using about
86 Meg and coming down to about 1.3 Meg by using content sharing and also the
build time reduces as well it doesn't have to pull in all of that stuff so the
build time plummets considerably from you know close to 1 minute 50 down to a
few seconds so those those are all those are all good wins for sure and it's not
just it's not just the Ubuntu platform snap that's available in this fashion
the KDE team have been working towards snapping KDE 5 and the plasma
frameworks and they've been using this technique for some weeks now and have
demonstrated significant gain so I think their platform snap is like a hundred
and sixty or a hundred and eighty megabytes and if you repeat that many
times over for each of the individual applications that obviously you know
doesn't scale very well but they they create this platform snap and then the
individual application snaps are you know measured in one or two megabytes
or smaller so you know it works 300k 300k yeah and there was a great
introduction to this given by Harold sitter who works for blue systems on KDE
at the Ubuntu online summit a couple of weeks ago so if you go to summit.ubuntu.com
and look up the the KDE presentation which I think was on the
Wednesday he gives a good introduction to how and also actually shows the code
behind so shows the snapcraft.yaml behind the scenes in terms of the
platform snaps and the individual application snaps and demonstrates how
they're connected and how they work so he did a great job of actually sort of
showing this you know in real terms and how it's benefiting the KDE team he's
also involved in developing neon so in him most of the guys in blue systems are
yeah you're making me you're making me you know you're making me want to use
neon I gotta say rotten dang it you'll find out on a future show maybe so yeah
well how hey rotten what do you do to mount Samba shares what do you do how
does that ever something you do oh yeah just auto mount what do you mean well
okay so you're doing it like when you boot up or you're doing it so like what
I was one of the things I love about one of the things I love about Nautilus is I
can show up at a network I joined I joined the wireless network I hit browse
for other locations all of the different Samba shares and AFP shares and SSH
servers show up I can double click an SSH a server I can double click a Samba
server I can double click an AFP server and it mounts using the gnome virtual
file system as an actual folder on my file system which we're gonna get to in
a little bit why that's a big deal and for me the fact that dolphin can connect
but when you double click a file it has to download the file to your local hard
drive and then open up the associated application like that doesn't work when
you're looking at a 20 gigabyte MKV file right it's rough that is rough yeah and
that explore ability especially if you're you know you're roving around
you're taking your laptop to different networks so you use a like you use like
you just you just mountain to the file system rotten that's what you know I'm
mounted as a network share I'm tempted I'm gonna do it I think you've talked me
into it I'm going to I'm going to install the plasma meta package I will
point out one thing what while neon and arch are both currently up-to-date neon
gets the newest release the same day arch is like a couple weeks at the most
it's like a week we can be two weeks maybe but neon is day of within hours
that would be nice and I think here's what I'm thinking I'm thinking I'm gonna
install it right now while we're doing the show we'll see how what happens at
the end of the show I'll log out and see if I can use if we have a show still
yeah but here's my thinking if I like it then maybe I would go neon but I might
as well dip my toes here I love I love the arch package management tools I love
just getting in there and installing things from the AUR like an animal all
of that so I'm gonna do it right now I'm gonna do it like a like a like a just an
animal do it do it live on the show I'm gonna put in my s right here hmm 426
packages it's only gonna download isn't that interesting 154 I like it yeah I'm
really excited to see how this goes so as of recording it looks like I'm seeing
a lot of plasma 5.8.4.1 packages 5.8.4 seems to be the first time installing
as we record so I'm gonna say yes to this and we are off to the races it is
West it is super satisfying you know that reminds me of that same satisfying
feeling when I install packages over a digital ocean for serious digital ocean
if you want to have a great package experience install them on a digital
ocean droplet what's a droplet a droplet is an all SSD powered Linux rig
or free BSD over at digital ocean comm in fact if you use our promo code of
power did you hear that it's on paper you know what that means it's official
because a tree died fitness right here you hear that you can't make those sound
effects up you can't put that in the sound board nope you can't find that on
freesound.org can't do that it's right in house special effects do unplugged
all one word lowercase you create an account you put that in there you apply
it you get $10 you can go spin up a Linux rig and guess what Wes they're not
sitting around over digital ocean they're now offering fedora 25 over a
digital ocean comm so you can spin up a four door 25 server of course they've
got the Ubuntu's they've got the Debbie ins I got the core OS sent OS and free
BSD and they have data centers in New York San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam
London Toronto Germany the pricing is great five dollars a month for a basic
rig but you can also do hourly I've been getting a rig now that's like it's like
three cents an hour it's great so reasonable it's so nice and the
interface is perfect I could perfect balance of powerful but easy to use and
their documentation is top-notch they just published on the 1st of November a
guide on configuring next cloud on Ubuntu 1604 so if you've been thinking
about setting up next cloud want to roll your own cloud you want to have some of
the services and what's really nice too is you can set this up on Android and
iOS to sync with the next cloud instance and it's your own and you manage it at
digital ocean comm use our promo code you can get it for two months for free
just got to use that promo code do unplugged one word and apply it to your
account over digital ocean comm and you can dig around in their tutorials and
there's all kinds of handy information in there and now you can deploy fedora
25 fresh look at that that's pretty cool and you know it's nice how much they
keep up with you know various Linux communities it shows could very much
what's also super nice about it is they're working upstream they're working
with the projects it's not like they're just going off and taking the ISOs and
like they're communicating with the projects they're setting up channels for
updates and patches so everything's handled super smoothly great
relationships yeah digital ocean comm use the promo code do unplugged and a
big thank you digital ocean for sponsoring the um so I think this is a
good sign now there's some concerns I have with this but I think this is a
good sign the XPS 13 the Sputnik that's been been sort of like a trial balloon
by Dell right is getting another update sort of right right on the nose I
believe it's right on the anniversary of the Sputnik launch too which is kind of
funny the 59th anniversary there's a new version of Dell's and they call it like
a developer laptop right yeah it's not I don't really even know if there it's I
don't even know if project Sputnik is the right term anymore but that's what
everybody knows it by so they have a new XPS 13 developer edition that's what
they call it developer edition laptop it's got seventh generation Intel core
processors it ships with Ubuntu 1604 preloaded the killer wireless card which
are the rebranding of Qualcomm a Theros and infinity edge display either 1080p
or in their 4k version so it's a slight bump from what we're familiar with and
it starts at nine hundred and fifty bucks under a grand yeah that's nice
for an i5 8 gigs and of RAM and 120 gigabyte 128 gigabyte flash goes all
the way up to an i7 apparently they say with 16 gigs of RAM and 512 gig SSD
however when I tried to configure one out of out of just curiosity I couldn't
get it above 8 gigs so I don't know if maybe it was just Dell's horrible
horrible horrible horrible horrible horrible bad website or if you really
can't get it in more than 8 gigs but it does seem to be encouraging that Dell is
continuing to update it now the commenters on Hacker News say it's not
all roses the battery lasts for 13 hours under Linux which I guess is less than
expected seems alright he said that I'm like good
god man that sounds great the headphone port is very noisy with Linux and not
noisy with Windows I have I have personally experienced that a lot with
different machines Wi-Fi Wi-Fi that's the that's Wi-Fi the Wi-Fi performance
is I guess horrible under Linux and supposedly fine under Windows just in
you know I don't know that I that feel this I don't know the HDMI port I guess
does not work under Linux correctly so there could be a couple of things that
maybe are not perfect yet maybe if you ran arch you wouldn't have that that's a
good question as well there's not a lot of details there but I think this is a
good sign I think this is a good sign from Dell that they're continuing to
build this thing and I look at a lot of the options out there and I still think
the XPS is a very competitive offering I love mine I love mine and my drive
just died last week I was I was reviewing fedora 25 that my hard drive
died so that's like the Mac right you can't service it at all no I can pop the
bottom off and I can replace it it's just kind of a bummer that I've got
terrible I have lost yet another you burn through those things Brandon you
just ordered next ps13 yeah I did well congratulations the mr. new owner do you
have it yet no not yet oh well I would love placing my
MacBook Pro oh dang what was running on the MacBook Pro Mac OS this is a big
this is Brandon this seems like a big deal to me am I am I right this seems
like a big deal well I switched to Mac OS and from Linux in 2008 so yeah this
is a big deal for me well I'm gonna be really curious to hear how it goes will
you come back and let us know and give us an update on on the transition yeah
interesting okay so wimpy you have the 15 and the 13
XPS models what are your thoughts about this continued revisioning even though
it's not a very exciting one from Dell well it's good because you know the new
new line of processors have just come out and they've immediately revved those
two models with the latest stuff so that's really good to see because they
are I mean I don't know this but it outwardly it looks like Dell are trying
to compete with Mac in terms of developer mindshare and high-end
machines for developers yeah high-resolution screen seventh
generation Intel processors yeah and on the XPS 15 dedicated graphics as well
and yeah you know HDMI ports and multiple USB ports is that 15 is that a
Linux pre-loaded machine or is that something you put Linux on I put Linux
on the 15 the XPS 13 came pre-loaded yeah yep my my lady friend just loves
the XPS 13 she for her it's gorgeous it is that that that edge-to-edge display
beautiful it's sitting in the lab she's doing NaNoWriMo it's got a decent
keyboard on it she can do a lot of typing for her it's like a great machine
so it was a real bummer when the hard drive died makes me it makes me want to
just I mean I I I've now lost a hard drive in my Apollo I've lost the hard
drive in the Librem and now I've lost the drive in the explicit what what the
only thing I do that's the only thing I actually whether when I when I replace
them I replace them with Samsung's off of Newegg so that's kind of a common
theme but they're all you know whatever the OEM ships them with the only thing
I do a lot is I reload distros on them constantly that's the only thing I'm
doing that's unusual I don't I don't notice that I mean I'm I'm loading
distros on my machines like every day I wouldn't think it would cause any action
no no the right endurance on modern SSDs now is is pretty significant you're not
gonna be those concerns about or am I gonna you know burn through the right
cycles on the SSD is pretty much a thing of the past now I should get a hold of
Dell and tell them to send me one of these new ones for testing yeah because
I've got my mind's like two years mine's like two models behind it's like three
years old two miles behind but it looks the same as the current model right it
does it's gorgeous that screen is gorgeous that by the build is perfect I
really like the overall feel of it in the hand it's a great little machine
laptop to be proud of it's just a little underpowered and so I don't use it for
anything serious other than when we're watching TV and we want to browse the
web together that's what and it's got a touchscreen so when you're sharing when
you're sharing a computer you know she can she can touch the link and move the
screen and I can move it so it's it's a really nice like shared experience
computer yeah and it sits right there and the battery lasts forever that's all
really nice but because it's a it's a two core slow yeah I don't use it for
you don't use it for any production work yeah I see not anymore but I do use it
for testing high DPI and it's great for that that's green yeah I love testing I
love testing high DPI next it looks good and so recently I've been testing high
DPI on the MacBook retina 2013 and the which is a 15 inch screen and on the XPS
13 which is a 13 inch screen and it's you really I didn't realize this and it
seems obvious I mean it's gonna sound stupid when I say this out loud but I
didn't realize that high DPI made such a difference on different sized screens I
know that sounds so stupid to say out loud but I just thought like high DPI
was high DPI but there is a significant difference to look at a desktop
environment on a 15 inch high DPI screen versus a 13 inch high DPI screen
yeah well you can see that like right you know your phone may have a very high
DPI screen but to see that on the 15 inch screen yeah something else yeah it
was it seems stupid to say it out loud but when I actually started testing this
is this is something to happen a while ago when I started testing the different
distros on different screens and just getting blown away by how gorgeous some
of these things can look so yeah so let's talk about something that sort of
blows my mind away and that's net data so net data is getting support for
backend so let's back up what is net data and why do I want a backend on it
net data is a very handy utility written by the same person who has written the
firehole IP tables manager that we've covered a little bit before yeah I use
personally and to great effect and so you know in his operational life
managing service etc he really wanted a something that he could just look at to
give him the real-time performance information quickly assess you know
what's the state of the server you know not like a huge history but look you
know see like absolutely what is it doing right now yeah snapshots type
type stuff what's going on yeah so so net data implements that it's a you know
just a tiny little binary that you run they've done I think pretty good work
continually making it so the overhead on the host is less and less you know I
think we've talked about it a little bit on last before too it's a really neat
tool yeah and it's nice because you just you just throw it right on the server
yeah and then and then it pops up a nice web interface that you go to it all you
know it uses the dynamically updates you kind of have live real-time information
right there in the browser graphs and all of that yeah yep yep and so like in a
larger picture it's it's useful it's especially useful if you have a couple
machines I use it on a lot of my machines you know just start the service
and go but it becomes harder when you really want to you know do you want to
have historical information or you want to aggregate this information and so you
can look across your entire fleet and they have added some support so that
like one net data interface can look at other net datas which is really nice
that's huge ah so this is we start recording on a back end this is where
you started working on like multiple machines and historical stuff yeah so
like so that works it's kind of new but a lot of places will already have had
some sort of time series database a popular one is graphite which was open
sourced by orbits right and so you know and and so now net data can interface
with that they support both graphite and open tstb which are two big players in
that space and both have protocols that other players support and so this just
means that like you know either you can use net data as part of your solution if
you already have this infrastructure or it just makes it really easy to connect
and then you have the the real-time information of net data and the
historical trending and other stuff that works with like graphite which has a
huge community of tools and other stuff to work on hmm so how are you using this
because I know you started that you're starting to poke at this right yeah I
have poked at it you know right now I'm just using it for a personal use and
that's mostly because it didn't have this you know back end stuff and so for
working on the things we already have graphite infrastructure so this we need
something that would play along and in the graphite world you have collectors
that kind of sit on the host in every X intervals collect information send it to
graphite and then it stores it and gives you graphs right so net data does the
same thing but before it was kind of its own system often its own which worked
really well for small deployments really well for you just want to drop something
you don't want a lot of configuration you just want boom you have graphs it
can do some like minimal alerting stuff like hey send me an email when my disk
is over 90% or whatever so I think now like I'm I may not actually use it at
work but I think that for a lot of maybe smaller companies middle-sized things
people who are building a new monitoring stack it seems like a great tool no
kidding no kidding man if you were building something today this would be
such a great way to go and if you look at the the github there's like a pretty
good amount of activity people are adding plugins so that you can have it
monitor other things besides just that's cool that's very nice and Wes has some
additional information and links in the show notes you know we should mention
this if anything we just said went over your head at all if you're not sure
about anything or if you're just sort of lost maybe things feel a little weird
right now you got a little upset about that you got a little clamp like I did
Linux Academy Linux Academy comm slash unplug go there to support the show and
send it for a free seven-day free trial this we can learn all of the basics but
also all the really cool stuff coming down the pipe the stuff that people are
making money on basing their careers on getting jobs getting contracts and now
with Linux Academy's public profiles you can brag about what you've done but
really can also show your employer or your client what you've achieved Linux
Academy is a platform to learn more about Linux if you're an expert or a
total noob they got stuff for you video courses self-paced in-depth video courses
on every freaking Linux cloud and DevOps topic labs that give you hands-on real
experience instructor mentoring when you need that human help learning paths which
are series of courses and content planned by instructors for specific
types of tracks you might be going down or if you're just going for the certs
they got courses specifically to prepare you for exams they got a great
community I can say that cuz it's full of Jupiter broadcasting members and they
got note cards that are forked by that community that help you prep and learn
and they have nuggets when you have just a little bit of time available you can
just do a deep dive into a single topic and they have a core scheduler to also
work with your busy schedule servers that spin up on-demand you need them matching
the distribution you've chosen Linux Academy Linux Academy comm slash
unplugged go there and check them out and a big thank you Linux Academy for
sponsoring the unplugged program kind of speaking of the basics there Wes there
was a great article over at open source comm by David both I think it is and
David wrote managing devices in Linux using the slash dev directory and how
the slash dev directory gives you access to your devices this month I cover some
fascinating aspects of the slash dev directory now I kind of say in a mocking
tone but this is a super useful tool when you switch from Windows and come
over to Linux or Unix devices as items on your file system is a mind-blowingly
awesome concept paradigm shift it is a total total paradigm shift so I want to
put this officially in the show notes for episode 173 for all of your friends
that you have switching over to Linux that are a little bit savvy with Windows
or the Mac and they don't understand how this works give them this article this
is a great article and I feel like most of time you like you know you interface
you like with slash dev slash SDA what a you know SDA one that kind of stuff
right but that's as far as most people go you don't get into the details these
days you dev like auto populate slash dev anyway so yeah you don't you know
most people don't have to deal with this or make you know use make node or
anything like that so I found it helpful I think a lot of new users will find it
helpful too yeah and it's it's well structured with visual guides and all of
that too so you can find that over there we'll have it linked in the show notes
but it was at open source comm and it's managing device limit under Linux but I
just I remember I remember when I wrap my head around that how awesome I
thought that idea was and how cool it was the way the kernel does that and all
of that was it's such exemplified the difference where like Windows you know
you would anything you'd learned you felt like you would just kind of scrape
together hack-and-claw to just try to pry this information from this black box
and there's Linux is just like but you're like boom here's everything that I
know about so I got a lot of crap this I mean it's only Tuesday and I have I
have I have taken a beating on this particular topic already so yesterday
no two days ago we reviewed Fedora 25 on the Linux action show and in Fedora 25 I
talked about my upgrade from Fedora 24 different toward 25 and I just want to
play a little bit of that moment from the show right don't wait for it right
here just jumped ahead let's see what it says
error running transaction on libmpeg123.so from install the mpeg123 conflicting
files oh we have file mpeg123 libs conflicts with libmpeg123 wait does that
mean my entire installation is done uninstall and move on so am I stuck on
Fedora 24 now the struggle is real and I'm pushing on using the terminal I'm
gonna do a DNF system upgrade I'm doing dash dash release version 25 and then
tack tack allow erasing that should do what I'm hoping is uninstall stuff
that's blocking and just move on let's so I want to take a minute and talk
about upgrade versus nuke and pave and so one of the big pieces of feedback I
got is Chris you damn moron why the hell are you using United RPMs garbage that's
trash you should be using RPM fusion apparently the Fedora community feels
extremely strong about this so I just wanted to make it clear that the reason
why I was using United RPMs is because we had covered United RPMs as an
announcement in the show and they promised that I would use it to follow
up on how it went so that's why I was using United RPMs so I got a lot of crap
for that you're espousing or trying to tell the audience what to use but really
the whole concept of well that's a third-party repo they got all crazy
kinds of applications you don't know what their standards are how could you
possibly expect your core distro to upgrade successfully that's that's the
core sort of sentiment that I was receiving I don't know really know where
to come down on this I used to be a nuke and paver like nobody's business yep all
the time sick every six months a nuke and pave nuke and pave runs better cleaner
etc etc get to I like resetting things up I enjoyed the process now in the last
year or so I've transitioned to I never want to reinstall kind of guy and I the
last thing I want to do is set up a new computer I just like it working out of
the box where do you fall now with a nuke and pave thing and do you think
that I maybe I is this something that distribution should work on this upgrade
path or is this something that users should let go of and just nuke and pay
you know it it strikes me that it people seem to fall into and very strongly into
both camps and I think it depends a lot on how you view your distribution what
you get out of it so if it is just a tool you know if it is more you view it
more like a Windows style operating system where you've installed that you
just expect it to work you're not necessarily tweaking it a lot or you
have made those tweaks but you really don't want to do it again you didn't
spend if you didn't spend the time necessarily documenting as you set up
you just you know installing Linux these days is supposed to be easy you it is
easy you install it it just works so in that regard I think it you know
especially when you feel like that or it's an appliance that you just want to
be able to upgrade it right like you expect you it performs very well it's
very stable you expect that same stability in the upgrade process
personally I do like the nuke and pave model I don't have to do that much arch
is nice in that you know I only really do it when I change machines or if I'm
doing upgrades or other things but I do think the nuke and pave model helps you
track your personal dependencies helps you understand what things you do need
what makes a complete system for you that may not be a journey that every
person wants or needs to go on you know and if you're not changing machines very
often you're not changing setups or you're you're comfortable with you know
it depends you like some people if you're not installing a bunch of weird
packages if you're not making dramatic reconfigurations to your system then you
may not need to nuke and pave or you may not feel the that you want to nuke and
pave right but yeah sometimes like right now you know I'm downloading in the
background and I'm upgrading to the plasma desktop I'm like yeah maybe this
would be better as a nuke and pave this might be better as a nuke and pave but and if I
if I decide I want to switch to the plasma desktop for a little extended
period of time I probably would nuke and pave and something that I I think the
nuke and pave does help or can help maybe can help is that it can teach you
know like make sure that your data is not local to your system yeah you know
that was that was why I was such a big fan of it even like a year ago I was
like I'm a nuke and pave every time because if because to me there was a
period of time for a long time West like it for you for years where like I could
format a computer on a time like if somebody like I got no problem like I
know I knew I knew persistently everything was synced it was all backed
up no problem I'll pave it right now and even you know and maybe you use
something like ansible or something else or you have like well I didn't have a
bash script that installs all your favorite packages you can that means
that you can go from nothing to yeah you're running just like you were in
minutes yeah yeah exactly but that's not for everyone and not everyone needs that
yeah go ahead on our GPU if you nuke and pave when you use the plasma thing if
you install the plasma desktop you could nuke and pave and install the
intergos build setup for plasma whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa whoa
whoa how come you didn't tell me that what a few minutes ago when I was
installing the plasma desktop what now what can I do what can I do you can
install the intergos build setup for plasma where you get all the all the
modifications well what do I do what how do I do that
intergos dash KDE dash setup are you serious okay I'm gonna try this right
now because I have all my packages so I do a kid integrals what okay give me the
give me this give me that give me give me the knowledge here rod is a kid
integrals dash KD dash setup yeah all one package name all right I'm doing it
right now let's do it live on the air let's do it let's do it so we'll do okay
yeah like your color terminal thank you look at all this stuff so what is all of
this rotten what is all I'm sorry mr. to know what is all this and it's all the
modifications for all the stuff that you do k3b if you install the key if you
choose KDE and the install for the in century it gives you this this looks
like a bunch of stuff I would have wanted installed this looks like stuff
why I installed plasma dash meta right like for example how is KDE base dash
lib not installed how is Kate that how is Kate not installed like what the hell
did I install plasma dash plasma dash metaphor if this crap isn't installed
will you ask for the dependencies of everything that's plasma console not
everything that's KDE console was not installed by the plasma dash meta
package console right yeah that's unbelievable it's it's understandable
because that's what it's for it's a DE you want the entire KD stack that's a
totally different thing so what should I if I wanted to use console and Kate what
should I have installed because I thought installing plasma meta would
sort of cover me there's not really there's there's not arch doesn't have a
solution for that ah install it like it is big list of installation stuff that's
that's some horseshit I got to be honest with you that's that's really
disappointing because that makes it seem like the only way I so that so that's
sort of the way to do it that's sort of the way to do it isn't it is install
that anagros stuff I mean if people want literally everything and they want it
come modified by the well not literally everything that's that's exaggeration
you want a lot of the vast majority of the KD stack and you want the
modifications that integrus does with the theming and stuff like that then
yeah you could use the integrus package content and it is kind of the integrus
value add on top of arch right like they're picking your defaults you don't
need to go find all the KDE package right I might want right so it looks
like it's up and oh it's already it already feels fast I've got it and I've
got it up installed right now it it it feels oh geez oh geez the multi monitor
setup it's no good West it's no good didn't pick the right default for you
no it did not but this is exciting so I'm gonna play with this a little bit I
have a feeling this might develop into a show I could have a show I've now lost
all of my notes yep yep I've lost everything but I do have the plasma
desktop and what's funny seeing that in the on the video version there you can
see the windows that I can't see I don't have those on my desktop so those are on
the monitor across the room from me and I can't I can't you guys can see windows
on the video version of the show right now that I can't see how funny is that
how can I move okay now I'm gonna try I'm moving it yeah uh-huh where is it oh
haha it's back I got it snake you know this is this is pretty nice this is
feeling pretty slick you know like not like in terms of like how it's handling
my dual monitors but it's feeling slick in terms of like how smooth everything's
moving across the screen which is which is kind of done arch and plasma before
oh yeah oh it's been a while right and every single time I do it I spend the
first three days thinking about how much I love Kaywin that's really like every
time every single time and then it's great it is really good but then then I
miss know after a little after a little while okay I'm gonna try unifying
outputs I'm hitting apply and let's see survey says hey look at that beautiful
now I have dual monitor setup and so now I've got mirrored monitor setup under
Katie I'm pretty much good to go the world just changed and look I've got
quake still which nice yeah so I'm pretty much I'm pretty much set I think
you'll totally switch to your quake eventually yeah or or you yeah you wake
yeah well let's see so here's the question will I well while I have it
installed right now and I suspect I'll have it installed for the next few days
will I have it installed by Sunday's Linux action show and will I still have
it installed by episode 174 that's the big question we will see if you if you
experience all the greatness that is Katie yes thank you mr. to know wow
that's an endorsement right there and now let's see let's get it working on
Wayland let's just go all in West what do you say yeah let's do it
Linux actually showed our vetted calm if you want to go all in some of this
topics show ideas leave us feedback go to Jupiter broadcasting calm slash
contact if you'd like to leave us some notes also check out my new video series
the ones that just published as we're recording today are yeah all about the
meat BSD I've left like two weeks ago remember when I was gone that was
horrible I mean it was nice to see Noah but that missed you Chris I guess you
youtube.com slash Chris Fisher if you want to see those thanks for joining us
and I hope to see you back here next Tuesday
oh I'm already setting up a K wallet which is the most obnoxious thing ever
as soon as I have one of Google Chrome and Google Chrome doesn't look right
that doesn't look good it's got it doesn't it doesn't look like if it
doesn't look like it belongs on the frickin plasma desktop look at that look
how crappy that wasn't really look like it belongs and oh wow even worse though
yeah boy sure feels good though look at that look how good that moves that does
feel that that's like that's like KY jelly on your screen right there that's
nice I like that oh oh does it have that option to use like yeah yeah let's go
there let's do that I think if you right-click on the top maybe or
somewhere JB titles calm JB titles calm now we go boat now where do I go to do
that settings instinctually go to bank suggest calm but it's still that hover
landing page and it makes me sad oh use system titles that seems like oh okay
that's that's better that's better it doesn't look like it belongs but that's
better there's the if you get the GTK breezed theme it'll blend perfectly
mm-hmm okay GTK breeze thing mr. tunnel is also there's also breeze dart for GTK
as well I'm gonna go down the deep end will you if you have any like it tips
for me and you want to drop them in the slack that'd be good because I kind of
think I might want to do a lass on this and I'd like to give people tips for I'm
kind of thinking I'm trying it too the first tip is to explore the wonders of
window rules window rules yeah this is what makes K when the best people talk
about how with you know gnome like you it'll remember where you where you have
your window and bigger area and the size and stuff like that it doesn't remember
workspaces unless you you know install that extension port but there's window
rules allows you to have a whole load more control hmm that does kind of sound
appealing so like I can set every time so I could say every time mpv opens up
do this or what is it what it was it that it does for me
I think he's I think he laughed it looked like he was he's uh he's red and
mumble is he talking oh sorry dude oh sorry rotten there was a there was a
rogue muting of the soundboard go ahead sorry but your answer got cut off no
problem so basically what it does is you take
mpv and it would say load mpv on this with size this position this when
workspace this monitor whether it has window decorations or not whatever what
gravity level you want of whether it has it's above all applications or only in
a particular priority whether it has a specific shortcut associated to it let's
see you can I can be great for playing clips on a filter I remember Dolph there
was a problem like Dolph there's something wrong with Dolphin versus not
a lot I can't remember but we thought with playing clips you also choose
opacity of the window I've done like a little bit of that stuff with like when
I was using awesome a lot but that sounds very nice to have in is that
with with plasma with K when you set the window this like how you want it like
the size the location the monitor blah blah and then you just go into you just
start you activate the window rolls on that window and you go in and check the
boxes like okay remember this and we're done nice that's cool all right so I'm
gonna play with that that's a good one West you see any titles that are like a
super awesome latest Linux updates is kind of has a nice ring to it state of
the snaps it's a snap to run Linux the latest Linux updates it's not bad it's
not great though well Chris get plasma burns oh shoot it's not bad oh great I
don't want you to get plasma burns oh man we got to do a user error cuz Rekai
tried out this plasma desktop on his new machine oh really oh I wish I had more
time to do user error because that would be a great you know the people crave it
you know what I mean it's just it's busy these days West it's busy these days
with the holidays and the the double recordings and yeah there's actually
something that KDE does that even gnome can't do GTK like specifically a GTK
thing okay so if you and if you have a program that has weird like let's say for
example you want to do dark thing like a global dark thing like I like you know
you're gonna do probably yeah yeah there's there are some side effects and
some applications that where you have like some things that are dark that
shouldn't be and the biggest one of the most obvious examples is a Firefox and
Thunderbird do it mmm yeah no is rare that I don't use I don't use Firefox or
Thunderbird anymore but no it has run into that well I I've figured out the
best option I'm actually going to make like a tutorial about it but there is a
an environmental variable that allows you to invoke the system T said it's the
text boxes and that's the biggest problem with that they're all forms
basically you and you invoke this environment environmental variable for
GTK and you can tell it to load a different theme than your degree global
settings just for that one application hmm so you can fix it by making it
ignore the the globalization of it hmm so do you set that in the in the desktop
file then yeah you do yeah okay so let's see I'm gonna go to audio volume
settings the reason it's it's what the reason I brought it up is because that
if GTK 2 has that environmental variables function and also GTK 3 but
when gnome introduced GTK 3 support for it they broke GTK 2 support so KD is
the only one that actually still has both hey let's see if audio works you
want to see yeah oh yeah you want to see you have to see you want to do a little
little little little test because these what you got this is chrome alright I am
unmuting the computer's channel we'll see if we have audio right now I have a
YouTube video playing in Chrome at this moment yeah so I got audio working I
was you know what actually in some ways I like the way the plasma desktop
displays my desktop little notification tray items better than gnome does I'm
sick of that little sweat out tray mm-hmm I'm done with it I'm gonna play
I'm gonna play around with Crusader and then I'm gonna I don't know we'll see
what we'll see if I can if I can reproduce some of my workflow stuff yeah
see if it's production ready for for what you're doing yeah I'm kind of
looking forward to this I'm gonna I'm gonna put on this I'm gonna put it
upstairs on my machine KD the Chris last homecoming