So it went up on you know the free software foundation is doing a big fundraiser right now
They've raised a lot of money, but they're trying to get to five hundred and twenty five thousand dollars now
They're at two hundred forty eight thousand dollars. That's not bad
What's what what what are they gonna do with that money?
Well, they it's their biggest fundraising event of the year
They have a lot of work to do and this video makes the case for the work
They have to do this video Popey the value of this is negative
No, no, the value of this video is not negative this video that I'm about to play for you
We'll tell you what they're gonna do with that money. They're gonna explain to you why you want to spend that money
Are you are you ready?
Feeling are you feeling while it downloads? No, it's downloaded now. Here we go
Software is all around us and sometimes inside us
But what happens when the tools we use are obeying someone else a
Tool you control serves your interests
But if someone else controls it
They serve their own
When you can examine tools to see how they work you're able to learn about them
Even modify them to work differently or better
When you can share a tool and its changes you help others and in turn they help you
In fact, this is how early computing developed
Everyone could see a program's code and people shared their work freely to drive its growth
Every user was a potential author
But when companies began to lock source code away
It stopped being possible to participate or even to know what the code was doing in
Response hackers formed the GNU project to create a computer system designed to respect the autonomy of users
They adopted a copyleft maneuver and built it into the GNU general public license a legal structure that preserves user rights
In ten short years the free software movement had produced the GNU Linux system
Computing that nobody could own but anyone could use
Today it's keeping planes in the air stocks trading
And the global internet running
We all encounter free software in invisible ways
But software freedom was designed for people
It's about what shape the technology we inhabit will take and what kind of society we use our digital powers to build
And
We've still got work to do
Make the future and they show cross going across the screen a bunch of Linux desktop activities making art
Using some of the best free software out there
And it ends with 30 years of people of propelling user freedom the free software foundation 30 years of propelling user freedom
Join us contribute and learn more
Interestingly, I recognized one of the faces at the very end when it flicks around it was
Jacob Applebaum from the tool project. Yeah in the video they were playing. Yeah
So that's what they want to use the money for that they and you know
You got oh, you got a kind of applaud
I mean, that's a really well done video and it does help kind of explain what the idea is here that
There is a new form of expression that is being locked away and the free software foundation wants to free it
But they need support to do it. Hope we though you sound skeptical about where that money would go
Well, no in the past I've been skeptical and that video doesn't actually say what the money
And in the past many of the free software
Foundation campaigns have been highly suspects like the
Doing a denial of service attack on genius bar people in Apple stores. That was just moronic
And they had a whole load of campaigns against Windows that were just ridiculous
And so there was a lot of negative campaigning about proprietary software
But not enough positive campaigning about the virtues of free software
And I don't I think I think actually personally I think since Matt Lee left he was behind some of those campaigns
I think they've turned around and they're doing more positive things. Yeah, this seem more positive and you know the it wraps
with a free software user just
Ripping through a whole bunch of really great free software apps now like with that video what I kind of thought about when I saw
That video is oh, yeah
We do have a ton of really good like just great apps now
I was talking to Michael Dominic from Kota radio. I said so how's your switch to Ubuntu going?
And he was he's like well
You know truth be truth be told chrome is chrome and sublime text is sublime text and I need a terminal and it's working pretty
Well, but I like it for everybody. It's something else like for him
It's sublime text, but for somebody else is another application, and there just is more and more of them
You know for me a really big change for 2014 is I managed to start editing the clips for unfilter
Under Linux and doing it in a way that was better than I could accomplish the same task under OS 10 and for me
That was a really really important moment because for a long time
I've been able to accomplish a lot of the stuff with way more time and frustration under Linux now
I'm not talking full editing, but there's a specific use case that I have for clips and unfilter that is
Now it's better under Linux and lets me do more stuff
Thanks to just some of the great apps that are available and so I think this video what they showed there at the end
I was like, oh, yeah, that's awesome. That's great. So watching this back
I'm like, this is a more positive free software foundation and it made me think more about
their larger mission
Without them having to come and put their larger mission right up in my face hole and saying this is what we're trying to do
And I I felt like I don't I thought it was a good attempt
Yeah, it's great video. It's good. It doesn't really say anything new to any of us
Yeah, it's a good way to get the message out to normals. Yeah
And and it was well produced to which appreciate. Yep. I'm looking to see they don't take Bitcoin though
Sorry poppy you're out
Yeah, I know you were looking forward to that
But they would take PayPal. Oh, no, never mind. You can do Bitcoin. I'm sorry. I'm sorry
You just can't do it through this campaign. You can just donate you could donate of course
Oh, yeah, they've been taking Bitcoin donations for a long time
But if you want to contribute directly to this fundraiser, it doesn't look like you can use Bitcoin
So poppy, maybe I can tempt you into Bitcoin. You need to go and look up coin corner coin corner
Yeah, it's a Bitcoin exchange in the Isle of Man, which I know it's very popular with somebody close to poppy
Oh, oh, it might be might be a thing. Yeah, so it's a good it's a good exchange
Sure, you can also oh you buried the lead wimpy. You can also buy and sell toes
So yeah and like coin as well
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that never ever provides financial advice
My name is Chris. My name is Matt Matt. So episode 73 and we're doing it on December 30th
2014 and last Sunday
We had our chance to look into our action crystal balls and try to figure out what was gonna happen in the world of Linux
A little behind-the-scene bit of information though that people may or may not be aware of especially if you didn't watch live
That wasn't what we planned on doing that episode
In fact, I think I'll check the show notes. You can probably get an idea of what we had planned to cover
But things just sometimes with guests don't work out and you got to work
You know, you got it. You got to work with that situation. You got to move on your feet
You got a pivot as they say that's what they say Matt. They say pivot pivot always
You got a pivot and so what Matt and I did is we pivoted
And we just kind of came up with our 2015 predictions
Literally on the fly as the bits were being committed to disk. We hadn't we didn't we didn't have a chance to think ahead
really brainstorm
Get in our zone, but now here we are episode 73 of the Linux unplugged program
we are gonna be joined up by our
Virtual Linux users group and we are going to bounce off each other the best set of 2015 predictions
You will find anywhere on the internet for what is going to happen in Linux and how do I know that?
Because I have faith in the people that we have assembled our mumble
I have faith you might say of the heart and I think that probably be the best time to bring in the mumble room time
appropriate greetings mumble room
Really
Nobody got the enterprise. So that happened. Oh, I'm sorry. I know it's the end. It's a holiday season man. I can't help it
I always drop in Star Trek. Yeah, so we got it. We got it. I got I got I got a new bag of
Balls that I brought that I'll pull out a few and rub and get some predictions out of I know the moment rooms got
Some we already blew a few during the pre-show that we didn't mean to because I didn't have the record button going
I blame wimpy and so
And so what we're gonna we're gonna we're gonna have a bunch of good ones and I want to start though
With some follow-up Linux unplugged shows all about the follow-up
And the continuity if you will and I got to talk about telegram and Matt
I love it cuz I know you sussed this one out
Well, you saw in the subreddit. We were gonna have ourselves a bit of a problem with the telegram app pick
Just a little bit. Yeah, I basically dropped in said hey guys, you don't care no stickers. I'm good. I walked away
Just before the s-storm starts I'm just gonna lay this out there and I'm out
I'm not coming back. I'm not coming back in this and that was wise and here's what happened is Chris got all excited about something
and
He talked about it and it was telegram and I got so excited about telegram
That I actually even gave out my my contact information on telegram. Oh, that was great
No, no, no, no, it's cool, you know, I've enjoyed talking to everybody it's been great
Really have I got some actually my favorite one so far as I got some snow pictures from Australia. Oh, well, that's kind of cool
Okay. Yeah, so Australia's got snow. I didn't even know that was a thing
And now I've got a picture in telegram about it now telegram for those of you who didn't watch the world's largest Linux podcast
That is a secure instant messaging program that promises the entire world when it comes to security
And we've been using something called Viber. Yeah for Jupiter broadcasting production purposes
And and Viber kind of does the same thing if you're familiar with WhatsApp or hangouts or any of this thing kind of stuff
You get the idea they each have their varying levels of features a couple of core fundamentals that we have here
And I'll just super quick because I know I'm retreading ground here and then we'll get into the telegram stuff because I think it's important
our requirements are
Mobile really has to be
Just as supported if not the most supported and that's feels even dirty just saying that because I'm not that guy
I'm all about the desktop
but the fact is our production teams literally all over the world and
They are oftentimes the majority of them or at least a significant portion of them are only available at that moment via their mobile
So that's sort of right there sets our limitations of what our mediums are what our end devices are for communication
And when you think of mobile you got to think about all of the restrictions therein
they're also because there are producers there at FES and conferences and the
Network at FES and conferences are notoriously bad
Which means connectivity is always in a state of flux and you need to know if somebody sent a message and receive that message
You need to know if the service acknowledges that you were able to transmit that message because your connectivity can be so fluctuating
So that's a requirement we have from a messaging program. And then of course because it's the Linux action shown Linux unplugged mandatory
It's got to run on Linux, right?
We got to be able to have a Linux client because some of our back-end staff are on Macs
Well to you got to have the Mac client, right?
So you it's you you you you start to then of course, there's gonna be some people that need Windows. I don't know
Probably rotten corpse wants it on Windows or something. I don't know
On top of all of that then there's the features of that client
Can it send pictures pictures are necessary because sometimes we just like to have fun
Sometimes we got to send a picture of the booth what it looks like right?
Can it send voice memos sometimes that's important because people are driving or you're giving something very complicated
You don't want to type it all out. So does it do voice back and forth?
there's those kinds of things that are critically important then you get to stuff like
Is it encrypted? Is it private?
If if you came to me and said Chris
I believe there was a way that anybody in the Jupiter broadcasting audience could read any telegram thread. I
Almost wouldn't care because there's nothing really in there
That's confidential if I wanted to use a confidential messaging platform. Well, I sure as hell wouldn't use somebody else's service, right?
I would go fire up my own XMPP right?
I would make sure I'm using a fully open source client to use that XMPP server and to be totally frank
Like if I'm super paranoid, I probably don't even use a computer right Matt exactly
Well, that's just it
I mean first and foremost my two rules in life are if it executes code it can be exploited
And if it's communication besides actually, I don't know keeping it in your brain. It can be exploited same thing applies
I mean really I mean even paper and pen can be exploited
So, I mean, I think a lot of people got to figure out how deep they want to dive into that and in reality
You know, does it use some base level encryption? Yeah, it sounds like it. Okay, cool
All right
So that is where we're coming out from telegram and we got some feedback around telegram
And a lot of it centers around the encryption that telegram uses and wimpy
I wanted to give you a chance to jump in because I know you know about it at contests they have going
Yeah, well, this is the second contest they've run now
So they've they've put out a three hundred thousand dollar bounty for somebody that can crack
The the encryption on telegram and every so often they keep bumping the value up
So it started at a hundred thousand then it was two hundred thousand now
It's three hundred thousand and they keep on
Relaxing the rules of engagement as the bounty goes up and nobody's broken it yet. So they're obviously
Fairly confident in in their encryption
Yeah, I'm not trying I'm not coming here to advocate for telegram is encryption or one way or the other
because you know it it sounds like from my understanding is
They still have the the problem where telegram could hand over in keys and some a third party could get involved in the conversation
If not for anything else other than monitoring and beat off on the subreddit writes in he says being the good
Being good. Okay. Here's Paul. Oh, he's taking a shot at me
I see he says being good at going full salesman on things comes with a certain responsibility. Apparently. I'm full salesman on telegram
If you care about your audience, okay. All right. Thanks. All right. How dare you like a product Chris? What were you thinking?
Yeah, come on touting the security of telegram should be avoided by all means use it if it fits your needs
But please don't portray telegram as something vetted and secure
That's doing the audience a disservice only half of the equation
The client is open source and the protocol is full of weirdness and outright flaws
I believe their crypto contest charade was even featured and scoffed at on one of the network's channels a while ago
Perhaps if its encryption score is the following table then he links to the EFF
He includes the EFF
Or card of secure messaging clients. They did recently and
I'm looking for telegram on the list right here
If it's if it's so flawed and they've been offering a hundred thousand two hundred thousand three hundred thousand dollars then
That that's enough motivation for people that know their stuff
Break it and claim the prize money and that hasn't happened yet. And what I get from these crypto contests
I haven't looked into the crypto in any any degree but they're clearly thinking about
Cryptography first rather than an afterthought and it's baked into the product
Yeah, I say telegram
They you know, they I'm looking at this core the scorecard here from the EFF has there been a recent code on it
They say fail that check mark that checkbox and our past communication secure if your keys are stolen and they don't have that checkbox
I would also add I believe the way telegram works is at some level
They're storing your messages on their server until all of your clients have downloaded. That's probably something you should be worried about, too
You not only that but I mean stepping back to the show and what we actually what you actually said about it specifically
I seem to remember the words not open source used open protocol and is reasonably secure
I mean was kind of that, you know, yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I don't really under I mean it's like well
Okay, so I can't use online banking because that hasn't really been vetted. I sure as hell haven't vetted it
I can't use anything with you know, any type of SSL because I personally haven't vetted it and I don't know who does
You know, I mean you can just it just becomes a really ridiculous argument
Well, I guess that's kind of where I wanted to take this like if I feature something on the Linux action show like telegram
What is my level of responsibility for that disclaiming that kind of stuff? Yeah
The fact that hey, I really like this product here's the fact that it's open protocol and we're using it
I think it's kind of you kind of hit all the nails on the head
I think I mean if you really look at it logically, I don't understand how
That's unclear. I don't recall you saying that this is NSA quality encryption or you're like, you know
I mean, I guess I'm just confused by the whole thing
Well, what is here's some good news and by the way, I will link in the show notes. We've also in the subreddit
You know, there was a link to somebody who takes apart some of the some of the issues with the protocol
Which is totally legit
It's fine, but there and then somebody also linked and I meant to grab the name
I'm sorry a really good stack exchange thread where somebody a hello world goes there
I'm really does break down kind of like if you are super super concerned about
Really secure chat perfectly secure chat. Here are the things you need to consider
some of them are design philosophy things some are just the way the telegram works and
Some of them are perhaps key issues and I thought this was a really good article and last but not least
I also was provided a hundred percent open source
Android client for telegram in the f-droid marketplace or whatever you call it
And this is completely GPL to and it it's a it's an open source client
So I guess my take is as I it seems like a lot of people have really been enjoying telegram based on the message
Yeah, I think our whole team is pretty much switched over now too
Which is happens really usually when the whole team adopts something like that that fast
Usually is a good sign. I think what people have really liked is
It it's very clean and I think Matt you kind of like it doesn't have like a Fisher Price field
Oh, man, you know, I love this. I loved it when viral be like, hey, you know, you need you need a sticker
It's three in the morning. Let me send you
It's like seriously leave you and then you dismiss it that keeps coming back. I don't get that with this. I love it
They sold me. What do you think in rotten corpse?
I'll just wanted to point out that you know when you featured Viber a couple months ago or so and
No one freaked out
But for some reason when something you're featuring an alternative that's more open
It may be not open source in the client
But open protocol and there are clients that use the protocol that are open source that you can easily use and
But then people are freaking out about the one that's more open and didn't snap on the only one that's completely proprietary
Yeah, that is interesting. I guess maybe it's because it's more of the category. I don't know
I I'm not quite sure that's a good observation. I wouldn't be I know you had a note about a Android client
Yeah, so I had been using
WhatsApp for a couple of years and all of our family over our Christmas gathering
We've all switched over to tell it telegram on our Android phones and we're using telegram telegram X
For Android, which is made by delicious, which are the same people behind
The chomp and texture SMS clients. So if you've ever used those
It's a really decent
messaging
Implementation that's familiar to the chomp and texture users but uses telegram. It's pretty good. No kidding chomp is awesome
So yeah now I'm more excited to use that. Yeah, that is really I did see I did see them
Telegram X they've wonder though whether it was just a clone or something to be trusted or not
So that's good that it's been vetted. Thanks. Yeah, I will grab that
I've been pretty impressed overall with the speed of it, too
I didn't I didn't have a good way to demo it on air on on on Sunday, but
You know, I'm sometimes I'm when I have these chats going I've got it on my mobile device and two computers at the same
Time and I am I am blown away with
It's not perfect. But a lot of times I send a message and it shows up on all three devices
Instantaneously, like I don't even see how I could transfer the data that fast and yet it's there now that said I
Have been it's funny because like I think sometimes a lot I come to these things and I test them in a way
They've never been tested like I kind of did this to bit message and now I've done it to myself a telegram
Where I put myself out there and so what ends up happening is I just get an S ton of messages and I think sometimes
these messaging systems have never had somebody that has that happen and so I'm noticing like the desktop client will not show like if
I get say
Like it like you say I don't say I have the desktop client open
And maybe overnight I get eight new chat sessions start and they'll all show up on my smartphone
But when I open up my desktop
I have to close the telegram desktop client and open it again before the chat show up and I prefer to reply on the computer
So yeah
Anyways, there you go
and the other last last thing I'll say about telegram is the other thing that's nice is you can give out a user ID instead
of your phone number with like other messaging programs and
you can integrate it in with pigeon because they've already right written a plug-in for lib purple and
You can just use your existing desktop messaging client, which is kind of cool. I'm not saying it's
Don't forget the fact that you can also say that it's a whatsapp club
Basically, so it's very very easy to show to others because they'll pick it up straight away. Ah good to nice
All right. Oh, go ahead one last one last. Yeah. Sorry. I'd also like to add that
It's also available for Firefox OS. I just had a look. Yes. Thank you. That's right. I meant to mention that
It is on Firefox OS as well
So there you go. Okay won't be one last one. Go ahead. This is the last last one
Yeah, what my family liked about it is unlike whatsapp
They were able to have telegram on their phones and their tablets and have their entire message history available
So it didn't matter what device they were on they were able to see all of their messages receive all of their messages and reply
Yeah, that is really nice, especially for like the family members that switch to the tablet
Once I go sit on the couch and watch TV, that's we have we have family members
I just noticed when we went over to the for the holidays that just have the tablet next to their favorite table
That's next to their favorite chair, right?
And when they're watching TV, the favorite tablet comes out and they sit there and they play on the tablet
I'm guessing I don't think it ever leaves that spot and the fact that they often don't have their phone with them when they're sitting
there
Is is a is a big boost for a telegram
Yeah, so yeah, and I I think it I think overall
The thing to sort of note about this is this is our last episode of 2014
And this is obviously going to be a huge area in 2015
And I hate to be that guy, but this is the post Snowden
This is one of the butterfly effects of the Edward Snowden leaks is everybody's hyper conscious now about encryption and and a little more
Suspect about encryption when people are saying we have PhDs
So you can trust us and then people are not trusting them like they used to so some of the pushback
We are seeing about telegram is like totally legit
like exactly
Where our head should be at now because we've just gone through a year of some shit and it really has shown us that we need
To be a little bit more critical of this stuff. So I'm not I'm not begrudging anybody
I just wanted to clarify that you know, this is where we are taking the input on this on this topic
It's something we're thinking about. I'm not totally sure though like for us if it matters
so you just have to make those same kind of values at value decisions yourself and
There you go. Actually if you if you're cool with everything we talked about check out telegram
I think you'll like it quite a bit and
it looks like a lot of people in the mobile room are using it too and
When we go out to events and stuff, we'll really put it through its paces
Okay
So I think the real thing to just kind of leave it out is it's something that we like that serves a purpose for us
that's pretty much where it comes down and and
That doesn't mean that in the future. You won't see a segment from us on like like an awesome XMPP server setup or something
Like that. It's just for
For us and going out in the field to make these shows for you that that that's what works for us
And it's a huge part of it really and it's really hard for me to wrap my head around is
That we needed something that was that was genuinely mobile first because so much of our team is on their mobile and they always have
a data connection on their mobile and when they're at
Conferences they're on their mobile and that was something that once once I had made that as Matt and I like to call it
New term pivot once I'd made that pivot
I had realized this is I got to rethink the way I'm doing this
And speaking of mobile and rethinking mobile and making sense ting go to linux.ting.com right now sponsor of the Linux unplugged show
Linux dot ting comm will take $25 off your ting device if you have a ting
Compatible device and there's more and more of them and in February
There'll be even more because ting's going GSM's you got CMA and GSM if you have a ting compatible device
They're gonna give you $25 of credit that might just pay for your first month. It often does it did for me
Linux dot ting comm go check them out and try out their savings calculator
You plug in your existing information and see how much ting would make a difference for you for me
it's a huge difference because it's no contract and no early termination fee, but
what I really love and
And to be honest like to know where the termination fee thing like
That's nice if you're in a contract, but for me that doesn't matter
I'm not gonna switch from ting like that nowhere the nowhere the termination fee is not a big incentive for me anymore
I can totally get like a family if I'm in the old paradigm like that. Oh wow really that's great
No ETF like how can they even do that well turns out they can right? It's easy now
I'm it now that I'm a ting customer
It's not the no ETF that keeps me around that doesn't make any sense
What keeps me around is that I'm only paying for my daily usage
They just what I use so if I make a couple of calls today
I'll just pay for that
Yeah, I don't have to have a huge plan
But if I need to make a ton of calls this the plan
Easily scales and the pricing makes a ton of sense ting just takes your minutes your messages and your megabytes whatever you use
That's what you have to pay well guess what?
Guess what just happened to me my files box died at my house
My firewall is fine all of that's fine the lands fine
But the literally the Ethernet port on my files box sitting outside in the freezing weather popped last night
Yesterday no no internet for Chris well
What would I do just call up my cell phone provider and change my data plan for that month? Oh?
Hello mr. Carrier. Yes, I need 10 gigabytes this month and not the regular 2 gigabytes that I know dude
I pay for what I use I just turn on the hotspot tethering and now the devices in my house connect to my Nexus 5 over
The Wi-Fi and we're going out over tings LTE. I'm paying for my usage because that's how it should work
It's mobile it makes sense to give you tools to watch all of this you can set alerts with their Android or iOS app and they
Have no hold customer service
They've got a ton of great devices over at the ting store if you want to just grab a GSM sim you can or you can
Go up and get yourself anything from the latest Android devices to a feature phone like I pulled out this feature
Phone here the kill Sara Verve the kill Sara Verve
It's like wow okay. Yeah, I see a number pad there wait
So you mean I use that number pad to make phone calls that's weird
It's got a camera, but then check out this badness slide down full QWERTY keyboard
Yeah, you can still get one no contract. No early termination fee a hundred and seven dollars when you go to linux.ting.com
Why not I mean if you just need a phone why not right all right? Here's another example the iPhone 5s
315 dollars no contract
Right on ting are my favorite the HTC one
no contract
$340 linux.ting.com and they've got the latest and greatest devices they got everything
Linux.ting.com go over to ting try out the savings calculator
And then just go look at those devices
And then keep your eye out because in February things getting even better when they go to GSM linux.ting.com and a huge
Thank you to ting for sponsoring the linux unplugged program
Love you guys good stuff
Okay, what can we do just a couple more quick emails before we get the predictions? I know absolutely okay?
all right, okay, so I know I'm honestly not trying to get us in trouble, but
You know snow train great username writes in and says why isn't Debian as popular as Ubuntu on last
He says I great question
I've been following and loving last for some time now, and you know so he probably knows both you
And I love Debian, but he says it always bothers me that Debian the mother of so many great Linux distributions
Isn't discussed as a primary Linux distro option when you just throw things out there like arch open Sousa Ubuntu and so on
What's the deal with that?
Thanks for the great year and queue up the good work on last so what he's saying to us Matt is like
Not like why don't you do more things about Debbie, but like when you're just saying hey try out open Sousa
Hey try out fedora. Why isn't Debian in that sentence? What are your thoughts well for me personally as a general rule?
I found that packaging is generally my first thing I look at
And this is probably all wrong in most people's eyes, but for me packaging is the first thing
I look at when I look at a distro arch and Ubuntu nail it
Open Sousa, you know they do pretty well
Thanks to their packaging service and whatnot and all the goodies they got going on
But when it comes to Debian, it's kind of hit and miss if it's not in an existing repo
You're generally gonna be hunting down a dead package or adding your own repo, which is a whole nother set of issues
I do use Debian on a netbook
I actually have lot OS on a netbook right now, and it's a great little distro
I love it all day what I brag about it or recommend it to people no
I would recommend it to an advanced user maybe even an intermediate user
But I wouldn't recommend it casually just hand in foot
so I think also some of it comes from a little bit of bias for me in terms of
Well actually ninja Aaron said it best he said dude
Linux action show when does Debian do something exciting when they do that's when they cover it for the most part
Debbie just plugs along and keeps going and doing its thing for which we are all very grateful on the other hand
It was basically all they talked about in Linux unplugged this year, and let's not kid ourselves Debian's fonts yikes
Yeah, so snow train falls up. He says I understand that Debian isn't covered very much by other distros
But he thinks that maybe we should talk more about it and Red Hat Enterprise Linux and slackware as well
So that's fair enough. It is fair
I mean you know to get Debbie into I don't know to get it to where you really want it
It requires a little nipple rubbing and it sounds a little weird to say that but it's true
You got to kind of massage things out to get everything where you want it
You got to work with your fonts
You got to kind of decide on what you want to look where which desktop all this stuff
You know it's not really an out-of-the-box experience in my opinion so okay, so last email of the day
And I got the whole mumble room here
I know a lot of us looked at fedora 21 a lot of people in the chat room have been trying out fedora 21
The new anaconda installer isn't new for 21
But it's new ish, and it's new enough that Erno writes in he says I've been a linux user since the year
And I can install a linux system without a problem I've I've I have probably installed hundreds of linux distros over the years
I've been meaning to try out fedora sabian and other distros that use the anaconda installer specifically as
For the life of me though. I cannot figure out how to use and set up a multi-disk setup in anaconda
Is it just me or is the anaconda installer way too damn
complex after the redesign
Thanks, huh, what do you think Matt? Did you find it complex?
You know I was doing a solid like a just a flat install, so I wasn't doing anything multiple partition
I know the auto thing too
Yeah
Now if I was to try that it would be interesting because I'm pretty sensitive to that not because I can't but because I expect
That sort of thing I expect it to just work well
I'll have to take a look I did run into a few issues with the partitioner where like if I had existing partitions
That I wanted totally wiped out the part the auto the partitioners auto suggestion system was like
Never would never suggest anything that would wipe data of course because it's trying to be safe
But that's actually so I felt a little inflexible because I said I wanted to have an auto option that said just use the whole
Drive anybody anybody in the mumble room have any thoughts on anaconda a rotten corpse
I see you just said something chat go ahead, and what do you think about anaconda? Did you find it complex?
Well I'd say it's probably like a
Intermediate, but it's a it's more complex than it needs to be but but you what you're saying is you don't want them
My anaconda don't want on okay, all right. Thanks. That's all that
I think it's just a transition thing or no
It has been a little more complicated than I would like for a while, but at the same time. I still
There's only a few installers. I like the ubiquity installer. I like quite a bit the anaconda installers, okay
I mean, it's just
Yeah, yeah, sitchie sitchie's all right. Yeah, I don't even know how you say it, but yes, it she's okay
Yeah, I think it's cinchy. I don't cinchy. Oh that would make sense. It's like a cinch. Yeah sure
Yeah, as far as I as far as I'm concerned the best installers freebsd installer and all the other players can go home
All right, so we do have a few things to get into we have of course our predictions
And we have a couple of more a couple other items to get to in the show it is the last episode of 2014 and
We have our 2015 shenanigans to get into so before we do that before we talk about all of that stuff
Let's talk about digital ocean. You know that's where I spin up my droplets. I think I I probably over 2014
I probably did like a
Total of like 15 droplets. I think I've kept three that's one of the things I love about digital ocean
Because when something just strikes my fancy
I just go over there and create it because I can get started right away
Digital ocean is really really simple and very intuitive
The dedicated offering the most intuitive and easy way for you to spin up a cloud server
You can go over there right now and use our promo code. I mean this is the last day for you to use it
But it'll work for a little while into January. Don't worry, and it'll give you a $10 credit
It's unplugged December, and you can get started in less than a minute when you go over to digital ocean
So you get think about that if you got an idea
Your vert you start a virtual box on your clunker. I mean that's gonna start in like a minute right, but you can get a whole
Sweet rig spun up on digital ocean in less than a minute, and you get an amazing interface on top of that
It's such a better way to go and then when you want to slide it in production
It's so easy to do so you get started in less than a minute and pricing plan start only five dollars a month
five
Dollars for our Linux rig that you have root access you can install any package
They've got one click installations here to get 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte of freaking transfer
For you yours you can have that
For five dollars a month and digital ocean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore
Amsterdam and a really nice one in London I
You know it's like as like sponsors
They should probably send me to the London data center so I can tell you more about it
They should probably just you know just so you might want to put that bug in there
They can run with that if they want to I'm just an idea guy, but it's the interface
That's what keeps me going back when I when I know I got to go do something. It's it's never like oh, man
I got to go manage this I could take care of this like let's go cuz it's the digital ocean interface
That's really really the sweet thing. It's simple and intuitive, but very powerful and power
You just can replicate the interface on a larger scale with digital oceans excellent API
And they have not only great documentation
but a bunch of really good community open source apps that you can use for inspiration or
Libraries that you can just take advantage of already and save you a ton of the work
I think one of the coolest things though digital ocean has done over there sort of the latter half of 2014 and
The audience for Jupiter broadcasting has really paid a huge played a huge role in this
Has been the tutorials at digital ocean
Right they they now are getting to the point kind of like where the arch wiki is like when you google for something
Like what you find is like a digital ocean tutorial and an arch wiki tutorial on it
And and like that's the level of quality they're getting to because digital ocean is doubling down in this area
They're paying you a Jupiter broadcasting listener to go over that you can use the link in our show notes
And there's no gimmick. There's no trick. They just they really want good content in their tutorial section
So they will pay you up to $200 for it. They'll have you work with their editor, and this is an area
They're investing because once you get going in under a minute with your droplet you get something deployed on there with a one-click installation
Maybe the entire docker setup. Maybe it's the lamp stack. Maybe it's git lab. Maybe it's ghost. I don't know it own cloud
I mean, it's so easy to get things going over there
But then if you ever hit a bump you have those tutorials you can fall back on but if you're an expert like I'm not
Gonna run into a bump. I'm an expert you can still go take advantage of digital ocean and write the tutorial and get paid up to
$200
I'm really I think it's an area that they've and they've really like the hardware is incredibly fast
The bandwidth is tier one bandwidth out of these data centers the interface is bar none best in the industry all running on top
of Linux KVM SSDs, and they're like you know what else we need to do tutorials and
Of course sponsor your favorite Linux podcast digital ocean calm unplug December when you check out and a big
Thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring the Linux unplugged program. You guys are firing on all cylinders. I love their tutorials
I'll tell you if I had a dollar for every time I came back to those like oh, that's how you do that
Oh, yeah, it's great. It's good for it's I mean
I probably don't mean to say you know how to be done you can just go over there
They're good for everybody it really are all right
So I guess what 2015 just around the corner Matt you and I made our predictions right over the cuff on Sunday show
But we haven't I've been looking forward to hearing what the Bumble room has I?
I don't know exactly our best format for this because I know everybody has a lot of ideas so mumble room
Why don't we use the you just ping me in the chat room like we normally do and?
I'll start with I'll start with one, and then we'll just get things rolling okay, and chat room you bang suggest away
That'll be your job, and here is my first
2015 prediction hold on let me get the bell hold on okay
High DPI support becomes a priority a top priority for at least one desktop project
High DPI support because you're gonna you have things like the yoga the Macbook retina the 5k
I Mac the 4k Dell display you're gonna have a ton of 4k at CES right CES is just around that's one of things
We always have to remember when we do these predictions is we're doing them right before CES
And that is where I think the for it's gonna be like a no-brainer you have to have high DPI
I think you're gonna have a ton of Windows machines showing high DPI you got the whole Mac line going high DPI
It's you're gonna have all these just like at one point boom secure boots here now
We have to deal with secure boot high DPI is here in 2015 by the end of 2015. We've got it solved
We're super close gnome has it very very close gnome is gorgeous on a high DPI display you open up an application
It totally falls apart, so there's got it like there's a big gap still and it's not it's not I
I wouldn't even say it's 80, but it's like 80 80 ish. It's not 85. It's definitely not 90
It's it's it's close, and I think we can close the gap in 2015 that right there is my prediction wimpy
I know you have something around these lines go
No, I was just querying whether high DPI had actually happened this year with
Gnome 3 I don't think so push on a high DPI cinnamon elementary does it does it?
I don't think it counts if like is
We know don't call it the chrome, but you know the frame around your screen if that's high DPI
But every single thing you do on it is not high DPI. That's not high DPI support. That's like
Yeah, yeah
So catching up with with Apple basically maybe and also I think Windows
I think Windows 10 is gonna be it's gonna be a big thing is gonna be showing off at CAS. I suspect
Oh, uh poppy. Do you have any Ubuntu? Maybe unity 8 related prediction?
Yeah, okay a couple I think
2015 with the yearable two switches to a rolling release
Is this a buntu snappy core kind of rolling release or is this more like repos and I'm app dist updating
all the time I
Don't know. I'm not sure. I think both potentially, you know, both could happen. I'd like to see the ability for you to
Separate out the applications from the underlying
platform and not have to worry about the underlying platform and not and get your applications delivered whether they're clicks or
Snappy or Debian packages, whatever. I would just like you to just keep rolling. Okay. All right
so poppy I think with regards to like
Snappy and click packages and having a base on which those applications are installed
That's potentially possible to roll in that model
But I can't see any way Ubuntu is going to enter a rolling model with its Debian packaging
Not this year. No way
Hmm, well, let's see. Yeah, I I tell you what
Pants on my head at the end of 2015
Ubuntu goes to a rolling release model on the traditional on the traditional Debian package
The pants wager has been made the end of 2015 wimpy will wear his pants on his head if Ubuntu does not
Or does I'm sorry if Ubuntu does go rolling. It does go rolling
This is outside of snappy and click packages because on that model it could work but on the on the on the traditional model
No way, and to be clear, you know, I still I still think it could work even with Debian packages
That's effectively what we're doing right now with
When you run the development release, you know, you're effectively run the development release and then every six months take snapshot do QA release it
and then everyone else just carries on but the thing is is that your upstream is Debian and
Ubuntu don't pull everything in that comes from Debian because you've so heavily patched an s-ton of stuff that you you
Have to block things and that then prevents other packages being pulled in because that's dependency breakage
You would have to sink against Debian
Absolutely
Well, hang on if we're sinking from
Unstable not not testing not
Have a gigantic. Yeah, sure
But but you don't know rolling doesn't mean you have to have bleeding edge of everything rolling just means it's rolling and you'll get continuous updates
It doesn't mean yeah Debian experimental
Yeah, you're saying you're saying it's rolling as far as Ubuntu could do it
So as pack as the Ubuntu project is ready to push out a package, they push it
But even so I've I've experience of this of working with a truly rolling release
distribution and
Understanding how you have to orchestrate the changes when there's an SO bump in something and doing that in Ubuntu with all of the patching
It's just gonna be a colossal nightmare
Really if a bun to pull it off brilliant, I will wear my pants on my head, but I I think with your
Focus on phones and all the other stuff you're doing trying to push to a rolling release model is is gonna be
Massive burnout and hugely frustrating for everyone that's involved. Hmm
To a very opposing predictions poppy
You don't have to accept the pants challenge if you don't want you're already in pants debt. So I I am I am down one pants
Debt. Yeah, I have another one. Okay. Go ahead. This one
Little bit curable. I predict that in 2015 Amazon will buy canonical
Whoa, that's a that's a mind job. What?
Yeah, and that actually isn't implausible when you stop and think about it. I
Mean it does kind of make sense. Look at the direction. Oh my god. It does right easy
Look at the field mobile product that didn't work out because honestly they were trying to use a Google thing on it
And I mean, yeah, I mean it adds up. It's
All this and it gives them the desktop and server
Oh wow, a boon to touch would be a excellent platform from the for them to deliver a bunch of prime stuff
They could bring that in they are AC to its ammo. It's our ability is already all over easy to yep
You got it. We would want to own like like one of the biggest technologies on their own cloud platform
It makes sense
If we're doing troll predictions, I'll go ahead and say that arch is gonna have a snapshot LTS version
Wow, I think I just to be clear, I don't think either no troll, but no, I know the Amazon thing has some validity to it
If you really look at one factor, yeah, that's you just blew my mind Poby and I like it a lot. You're welcome
That's a good one. I never would have come up with
Amazon would buy canonical I would switch distributions and buy some stock in Amazon because I think it's a smart business move
But yeah, I'm going to destroy. Yeah, you know what in a way it would I would seriously be one of the smartest business moves
I've ever seen Amazon make it will make sense. I mean if they mount their their phone was successful, which it was not
Yeah, maybe not but because of that failure. I think that shows them. You know what? We really need
Someone to come in and you know fix our bridges
Essentially Wow, huh, but would mark do it poppy? I don't know. That's
This is just a wild. Yeah stab in the dark. I don't have any inside knowledge. I don't know of any
Plans in this direction or discuss the only way I could see the only way I could see it happening
Is like if it like if it enabled some kind of big vision or goal like if it like if at the end of the day
Like it was uh, it was it was maybe sudden injection of cash
You remember it wouldn't have to be like a full-on takeover, right? It could be more like a Zappos purchase
Where like they get some money, but Zappos keeps it weird, too. Yep. All right
So I said Amazon will buy canonical, but I'm willing to accept any kind of you know
anything where they give us a
Crap ton of money and you know, we brand something Amazon thing
I'll accept that you're giving an Amazon a lot of credit but you know the thing is is the thing that would put a buntu in
Front of them right would be competition in the mobile space, but also just watching ec2. I
Mean they could they might want to do that just because of ec2 let alone the mobile stuff and all that Wow. All right. Okay, that's
Yikes, all right. So I let's let's make a big gearshift here Keller. I love your presentation
You think to have one huge success in 2015. What do you think?
I think far from a success one. You've got a
You get it's very little out of the project to I think everybody is looking forward to the future
I mean it's a backstep and I don't think it's a backstep that everybody is going to be willing to adopt
Mmm. Yeah, I think it'll be a lot of talk. But what do you guys think about the whole systemd controversy?
Is it is it played out? I think dev1 will collapse
It will just just fall apart. They're just gonna take their money and have
Go at it in the Christmas sales you think or you think they're just gonna maybe not eat or you just it'll be like a it'll
Be it. Well, let's shift our expectations and we're just gonna keep plugging away at it and it'll become like
Like her there'll be like two guys left running it and it will
Take forever and nothing will happen. Hope you there is two guys running it two guys from Italy that I've got no experience in
Running a Debbie and derivative. So
So does that mean does the systemd stuff kind of die out with them or does this debate continue on I think everyone
Accepts pretty much everyone outside that circle of tinfoil hat systemd
Haters everyone outside that circle is accepting that this is a way forward for Linux, you know, even us, you know, yeah
It makes sense. Why why have this fragmentation or why have this backward step? It makes no sense
Well, it was interesting
I thought one of the people that kind of just sort of put it in the best soundbite possible is Mark Shuttleworth when he you know
When I when I asked him about the you know, why did why systemd like I said, I asked him
I said how can you make the logical justification that you got to go with systemd because everybody else is going with systemd
But yet you can go mere and I thought he did a pretty good job of saying well
Look, this is this reason this is that reason and he kind of just put the whole thing in like basically a 30-second soundbite
Which was good. He's quite good at that. Yeah
So let's talk about I said telegram and I know it's a d-bag thing to say
But I said telegram was a post Snowden product
I think also some of this stepped-up security audits. We've seen Red Hat and Google have done a ton of auditing of like open SSL
And stuff like that. We saw shell shock and we saw heart bleed this year
I I feel like one of the things is people realize oh crap
We've all been talking about open source code being open
But none of us have really been checking it and then like some some some even groups formed up to go check the code and like
Some commercial ones and some private ones and so we got a lot of stuff discovered this year. Are we done?
Are we through it is 2015 gonna be a ton of more security issues? What do you think Matt? I
think that
No, I don't think there'll be a ton of new security issues
But I do think there's some stuff that we probably haven't really addressed by and large just in the brick-and-mortar world
We really haven't done squat other than react when it comes to POS
Systems and things like that banking networks, you know, just infrastructure stuff in general. I think there's so much
I don't know less
Newsworthy stuff that hasn't been touched on yet that we're probably still yet to experience some unfortunate stuff
Do you think Linux will take a few more bruises over 2015?
I think that it will I think it will be forced to be vetted a little harder
I think that it will actually become
The actually of the opposite of that I would say that it's going to be a little bit harder
It will actually become the actually of the opposite of that I would say that you're gonna probably see more switching to Linux because of
The fact that the existing systems a lot of them incredibly dated
We'll be switching that direction
But then because of that then the focus will be even deeper on Linux because of that point. Yeah very much so I would imagine
That that actually lends itself to some other things that I think will happen this year. Yeah is more
Devices and more software will ship with encryption
Yeah, by default. Yeah, great. Yeah, I could definitely agree
And you could even maybe see carriers like I could even be something like T-Mobile carrier of encryption or something
Wimpy you had a thought on security and privacy breaches
Yeah, so
What poppies Mike?
There you go. He got it. My predictions
historically
terrible
so
Exactly the opposite of anything I predict this evening is likely to happen, but I think that a major cloud service
So something like Twitter Facebook Google Dropbox eBay Amazon
Mm-hmm. They'll suffer a significant privacy or security breach in 2015
Yeah, that will change precisely nothing for the average users. I
Think 2015 will see the passage of sis, but we won't call it sis
But but there's already the they're always in the wake of the Sony thing. I've been tracking it for unfiltered
There is already legislation working its way through the system today
President Obama has already called for legislation and it will be a cyber sharing act
It'll be the government needs to share with the private industry and that'll be how it's pitched
There's too many cyber vulnerabilities that the government knows about they have all this advanced monitoring all of this know-how because they're cyber warriors
But it's the dumb industry the dumb private sector doesn't know about it. So we can't share with them cuz of laws guys
So if we pass these laws then we can share the super cyber information
What it really is it'll be the same thing that happened during the Bush era during the Bush era
We indemnified all the telcos to allow us to install of the NSA taps. This is the same thing
This is gonna be tech company indemnification
You got to be part of the big boy club to get in but you'll be in and they'll do some sort of
Cyber security information sharing after exactly the kind of event that wimpy is talking about the only reason why I say that is because
There's literally already legislation ready to go
Just needing an event to happen and it just takes an opportunity and it's done and we'll look at it as sort of like
Oh now hopefully they'll work together
But in reality, it's just gonna be capitalizing on exactly what wimpy is talking about nothing to really change for the end-user
I think to 2015 is gonna be like 2014 was boy. They're really figured out like cyber boy
We really ended the year with a cyber boogeyman. So going into 2015 that's gonna be a good one
And I I think you've nailed it wimpy
Unfortunately, I'm a bit of I know that sounds awful
I'm a con you have a thought about point-of-sale systems under constant attack over 2015
I'm a con. No. Okay. Well, I think that one's going twice. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. There you go
I guess that was kind of his thought is I and that's something we followed a lot in tech snap is the point-of-sale
Devices a lot of them still XP. So hopefully we'll get that sorted out
Well, and even someone is not, you know, someone like myself who's by no means an expert in any capacity in that area
I would just looking at it. I'm looking at the reaction to it and the lack of anything happening. I find that interesting
Hmm, let's wave our arms around a lot and scream and yell and put it in the news and then we'll go back to business
As usual. Oh, I'm sorry. I thought I'm coming
Never mind wimpy. Let's you know what? I like the way you're I like the way you're thinking. Let's stop talking about the negative stuff
Let's talk about VR. I've got an oculus right here. I'm looking at it. What are your predictions for 2015 and virtual reality?
You're not gonna like it
Prediction is the VR will continue to lack adoption in 2015 and I cite the
Adoption of 3d televisions as reference
For that prediction. I think VR is not going to penetrate the consumer market
at all if ever and it will be the preserve of
commercial applications such as
Digital surgery and things of that nature now, have you ever used an oculus?
Nope. Hmm. Like I said everything I say this evening is probably going to be completely wrong, but
No, if you're just talking 2015, I think I would agree with you I just I think the cost is still too high
You know what the the over 2014 we talked about it on tech talk and it's really gone nowhere on tech talk today though
We covered Samsung's attempt. They licensed oculus VR
technology and they created about a
$100 $200
VR kit that's totally wireless
Which is good and bad, but it's totally wireless you put on your head it also though it requires a note 3
Specifically a note 3 and that's like a you get that unlock. That's like a $700 smartphone
So that's just the cost is way to the oculus dk2. It's totally not ready for average consumers
You know, you got four wires hanging off that thing. You got you got a monkey with your video settings like like an animal
It's just ridiculous
But wimpy I got to tell you a I feel like in my life
I there has been a handful of moments where I have seen a
Technology before I feel like everybody else has seen it and I've gone this is gonna change everything
like this is huge and I feel like when I put
When I put that oculus VR headset on and I put headphones on and I I was on a raft in the middle of the ocean
It was it was tranquil as hell. Like it was super tranquil. Like I was so peaceful
It was ridiculous and I'm like, this is amazing
I am standing in my studio right now, but my whole body thinks I am on a
raft in the middle of the ocean
Chillin and I seriously had a moment and I just think that if other people could experience that it's nothing like 3d
It's nothing like 3d, but you've got to make the picture better right now right now
The GPUs aren't powerful enough and the gear is too expensive
I think no point about experience is the key point is that you want to experience these things with other people
And the problem with 3d televisions is that experiencing 3d TV with other people is difficult and expensive
Yeah, and the same applies to VR
experiencing VR with other people is
difficult and expensive and I think these are the reasons why it won't be a mass
It's difficult and expensive in person
But it's the exact opposite for a remote experience imagine Skype oculus VR style
Then it's amazing because you can be in if you can be in a 3d space and you and I could be looking at each
Other right now and that you know that
That you just think about how that could impact podcasting like we it future versions of you know, Linux unplugged episode
2000 we could all be sitting at a virtual roundtable having this conversation
Holodeck. Yeah, I don't know. Well, I think
The new VR space is missing two things
One is a good input device
The keyboard doesn't really work when your eyes are covered with you know, this display
there's some really cool new things being developed and worked on and I think
Like I'm hoping that something really cool is going to come out in 2015
And then all once that's done and there's some nice comfortable
Input device for VR. All we need is in killer app. Yeah, maybe you know, well
The killer app for previous technologies that have had this problem this this barrier is
Basically porn that's the killer app that has accelerated HD streaming. Hold on. Do we have a prediction? Do we have a prediction?
Well two related to that one would be I think the opposite of wimpy
I think VR will take off but it will be the low-end Google cardboard style
Yeah, and I think that will take off dramatically this year. Yeah, which will push the higher-end stuff
Maybe the year after or the year after that, but I think once porn gets into VR then you'll see a massive up
I'm not gonna lie. I'm not gonna lie
If you came to me and said there was a really good porn app for the oculus just out of journalistic
Interest I would have to check that out so I can report back
Video online and it shows up they have a 3d player that if you have an oculus or the Google
Cardboard you can watch video online in 3d. All right
Yeah, yeah, you would yeah, I do agree on it. It looks like I think
Keller also agrees
I look at it
And I think one thing I'm happy about this at this point in 2014 is you guys know?
I was pretty I was pretty ticked off that I bought the oculus SDK
Being told I would have Linux support and then it got here and it took a month
But now the Linux support is here now go figure now the Linux support here is here
I have three monitors hooked up
I don't have any more room, but I'm gonna hand it over to a chase is gonna be experimenting with it and reporting back soon
I have another I have another a prediction. I want to make and I want to get everybody's take on this I
Think over 2015 we're gonna see a fork of the elementary OS project. I think people like the idea
They like the look of it, but it's moving too slow and people want something faster
I think because we're geeks we're nerds, and I think maybe it'll either be an internal division of the project
Which if that happens?
They're tight control. Why not? I disagree. Why not just people contribute to elementary I
Wish man, I wish
Contributions will be added in two years. Yeah
Might not be fast enough for them. So yeah, that's what I'm thinking to achieve that level of
unification
that
Elementary has you need that slow development process. I agree a new app
Pops up. Yep. It takes a while to refine all the UI elements. Yeah, so it feels
Comfortable within the ecosystem of that. Oh, yeah over elementary. So that's no development is the result of
Other priorities that elementary developers have and this is not going to go away with a fork
Mm-hmm. Well, no, no it will it will and that fork won't have some of those same values
And that's the very reason why the fork will have a small following but not be as successful
Elementary OS is slowness is actually in a sense what makes a difference, but I think that's a dream
I just don't think the the the average Linux user base is using Linux because they want a slow stale
Experience they want something new they wanted that new code
They don't have to doesn't have to be super cutting but you know
Maybe more than a year old would be good. And so anything that falls below that I think
are
Linux distros that are Ubuntu based and
So look good and want to have like somewhat unified look to all the applications
But update faster, there's no need to for just switch to a different distro. Oh, hey, man
I'm just don't tell me tell the dev one guys. I mean, I'm not the place saying logic applies
I just think it might happen over 2015
I wouldn't be so I'm not making a I'm not gonna make a pants bet over this one
You know what? I got a prediction. I can make a pants bet about though
I'll be willing to make a pants bet about this. Okay. All right. You know what? Okay. Okay. Hold on
I got a ding. I got a thing for the
Pants over here. Yeah. All right. That's the ding for the elementary OS fork prediction. I'm trying to ding
I maybe I'll find them in editing
I don't know later on so that we want to go play these back because we all will have to
Count for our predictions. All right, so I my next prediction
I'm willing to go on the record and make a pants bet about if I get this wrong
For at least an entire segment of last I will wear my pants on my head. Okay, I don't know when I get
Chatterum will have to set the date
Well, I do I was thinking us pants would be very funny because then I have to deal with like these long-ass pants
But if I mean there's room for negotiation
Negotiation what we'll negotiate, but first I'm gonna tell you about Linux Academy Linux Academy comms. That's right
I'm telling you about Linux Academy right now Linux Academy comm
Unplugged to get you our special 33% discount go over there and check them out. I know
You're expecting me to talk about New Year's resolutions right now and give you a hard time about
How you always want to do something over the New Year's and how you want to get your skills
I'm not gonna do that because I think you could use Linux Academy anytime
I don't think it needs to be New Year's. I think sometimes that gets us to think about these kinds of things
But truthfully I think we've all been thinking about a way to keep our skill set up a way to check out new
Technologies without having to go through the entire implementation stack and being guided by experts
I think we've all thought about that from time to time
Linux Academy is a unique opportunity. First of all
They're sponsors and you can support our show by checking out our sponsors go to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
But second of all and I think this is actually probably the more and more probably should so this one first
But I'm selfish. It's it's content created by people that
Genuinely give a shit about this right? They care about Linux. They care about open stack. They care about all of this
Fundamental things that they're teaching you about unlike all the other online education systems that are these one size fits all come in
We'll teach you all of these subjects because we bring in all these it's crap
That's not how it works
You start with a core group of people that really care about Linux and open source and people that are genuine
Educators that want to spread information and then people that know how to build all of us and people that know how to create
Livestreams and websites and do the coding you bring them all together
The sys out even it's great because it's like there's a sys admin element because they have they have labs that autospin up you bring
Them all together and that that rare thing is Linux Academy
You just do not get
This kind of accumulation of all of this talent in one place too often and it's Linux Academy go to Linux Academy comm slash unplug
You'll get step-by-step video courses downloadable comprehensive study guides your courseware comes with its own server
So as you get to a point in the lab, they spin up a server for you
It's on AWS don't matter you pick from seven plus links distributions
They'll automatically adjust the courseware to match the Linux distro
If you're hopping around distros like Popey is you don't have to care you just feel good
You know when you choose the fedora stuff and automatically adjust all the courseware to match fedora
They're honey badger about that kind of stuff and you get to keep your progress right in check as you go
So, you know right where you're at how long something's gonna take they got learning plans, too
You're busy. You don't know busy, but I know busy and let me tell you I still make Linux Academy work
I go into Linux Academy. I have a learning plan. I say Linux Academy. I got this much time available
I want to learn something. They'll automatically they're
Dynamically generate a courseware for you with little bits of here's where this how long is gonna take you
They'll send you reminders about quizzes. You can download mp3s. You can check out the live streams of the courseware
You can ask questions of the educators
They have a community where you can go participate and give you that bump when you fall behind and they're always adding new content
puppet Docker
Vagrant open stack constantly adding new content Linux Academy comm slash unplugged go check them out get the 33% discount
I'm really excited about Linux Academy because I think this kind of niche focus on the technologies
It's super kick-ass that we all care about
That's what it takes to make money making that difference is what it takes and that's what Linux Academy is all about Linux Academy
Comm slash unplug go check them out and a big thank you links Academy for sponsoring the Linux unplugged program
I have been a member the entire time that they have been a sponsor and I'm always checking out their new stuff
All right. So continuing on with our 2015 predictions. I
Last year when I was reviewing the Linux action shows prediction for 2014
There was one topic that obviously was dominating our mindset and that was steam and steam machines
It was all about what's valve gonna do. It's gonna change everything steam games. Oh my gosh, they're gonna come to Linux
So I'm gonna make
My steam machine prediction right here
now it's hard to say because valve has already said no steam machine business at CES and
So that to me was like, oh
They're not ready to show us anything. Okay
They're not ready to show steam machines at CES. That's probably a bad sign. Plus nothing ever shipped this year
Really? We never really I mean one thing that shipped right was that was the Alienware thing that runs windows
So we remember how we predicted that would go yeah, yes, we were correct
Here's my prediction convention though. It yes exactly
Exactly. What's that called? I'm pretty I'm for blanking. Yeah, those GDC and G and e3 both of them
Yeah our prime opportunities for a steam machine to be released and I think by the time we were doing this episode in
2015 I think there will be a steam machine on the market that we can buy
I don't know
I cannot predict what its success is gonna be because there's so many variables involved there
But I do want to go out on a limb and say end of 2015 a steam machine that we are at least perhaps
Somewhat compromising but happy with and if that doesn't happen
By January, I'll wear pants on my head
Well, Doug Lombardi said valve is planning a large steam machine presence for GDC
2015 which is in March so it could well happen
yeah, the thing is and I didn't know that but the thing is that I
Presence well, that doesn't mean much because we've actually had a steam machine presence a year ago
Like we've seen steam machines before
The scene a steam machine and then having maybe potentially millions of them in people's living rooms are really two different things
I'm not saying millions, but I'm saying it's a it's available for purchase
Since then the OS has had a lot more of a workout and they've been doing
Delivering updates and getting used to delivering updates and more and more games are available
I think something like seven of the top ten games on Steam have Linux. Yeah versions available
Yeah, something like that. Yeah, so it I mean even by then it'll be even higher
So I I maybe it just market wasn't ready for it last year, but it maybe is this year
I I reckon by the end of the year. There will be steam machines on market
Keller so I look at the price and I think by the time that steam machines hit the market the ps4 and the Xbox one
We'll probably have gone through at least one maybe two more pricing revisions. What do you think about the price Keller? I
mean if you can get
decent hardware at a lower price and what your
Good console our show built the library. You have a good chance to to gain the users
For the Christmas season, but they're gonna have they right now you're going to that transistor phase building at the library
Now thing like I said again if you can just get the cost of hardware down to where it's below the Xbox or the ps4
We can do it. That would be a slam dunk and it's got a good name recognition already
So they give is really about the price. I agree. All right, so that's my steam machine
prediction
MX or M Fox dog and Fox dog really to G's Fox. I know you have a prediction about digital production for 2015. What's that?
Well at the moment
Digital production on the Linux has gone in leaps and bounds like with editing and actual animation
So I believe that in 2015
Most production will be either Linux or you or
Apple based
Because apples are great for design because the high DPI
That's true
So with Linux and its graphics drivers going really well as well with CUDA and OCL
It's just becoming more and more
Efficient to do production work on a Linux box. Yeah, so I believe that the vast majority of
Digital production will be in Linux space
I wouldn't be I wouldn't say the vast but I wouldn't be surprised to see more and more and we might not even hear a lot
About it. One of the things I've noticed in our production workflow here Jupiter broadcasting is
one of the heaviest editing shows
For Jupiter broadcasting is actually on filter which is a little bit of an understatement
But if you think about it, I'm filter show one show might have a hundred clips in it or 30 clips
It there's a huge ass range and every single one of those clips is edited by hand by me and
2014 was the year where it became not only
Faster for me to do it under Linux, but I actually got more features
One of the things is we started adding more video clips to unfilter
And I have been editing all of those under Linux using a set of tools most of which I've shared over the year as app
picks in Linux action show and and that for me, I
Guess I need to back up because which got to understand is for me
It's always been this guilt like oh, I should be editing and producing under Linux
But oh my god, it takes so much time and oh my gosh, the tools are not there yet
It just drives me crazy
What I have now with these clips for unfilter is I've gone from that this this oh, what a burden
To man, you know what? It's faster. If I just do this under Linux, it's better
The results are better when I do this under Linux. It is more efficient under Linux now
That is not like see that's a big deal because it's not just like I can do the work under Linux
It's it turns out better when I do it under Linux
That is huge for media production for Linux. So if that continues on if that kind of you know, one by one the little tools
Right now it's it's small tools that I'm chaining together if that continues on that progress. Whoo
That's gonna be awesome
That'd be really great. I don't know. We'll see 2015. I think it's just gonna be a slow steady march
I don't think I'm not I don't think you make any big predictions there
So we kind of we've kicked around a bunt to touch a little bit
Anybody want to make any specific a bunt to touch predictions? We we suspect we'll see something from BQ in early 2015
Don't know who's gonna be able to get their hands on it, but probably a lot of us
No, what do you think
You think you know a major carrier you think it you think you know
If you think if you're on a major carrier, you'll be able to use a bunt to touch if you want to somehow
So here's how I see the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the the
See the perfect storm playing out
If we can get a major carrier to hurt badly enough to where they're forced to pull their heads out of their butts and look for something
New yes, then I see a major carrier coming along and saying okay clearly we've Android it ourselves to death
We need to try something new fresh
tap into the army of people that are still rocking flip phones or people that maybe are
In the market to change their mobile operating system into something different
I think I think it's entirely possible the key is to which carrier that's gonna be and that's hard to say
Verizon's incredibly stubborn AT&T, you know, they're kind of head the clouds T-mobile, you know, they might it just it's really hard to say for sure
But I think it could happen but it will take that pain point. Hmm. Yeah, I would like to just I guess what I'm looking for is
Yeah, I guess it seems to bet the better approach would be then over 2015 is devices carriers have already blessed and then you've reflashed
Yeah, right now that could happen too. I mean it's but as far as any carrier embracement they need pain points or they don't care
It's either dollar signs or others hurts. How do you think? Okay. All right. How you feeling about Firefox OS any different? I
think that's got a real chance of
Seeing adoption in areas that have not really had a lot of sense of smartphones before I don't know
I see them like on eBay and stuff like this and it's like they're really approachable unlocked price-wise
I honestly think that someone got there got themselves together and actually gathered up a bunch of these and just started popping them into kiosk
Somewhere they would sell these all day long. I really believe that yeah, and I think a bone two phones could do the same thing
But again, it's its presence its presence. Hmm
Yeah, I I find it interesting that I felt like I was more confident to make predictions about Ubuntu touch at the end of
Last year than I am of this year. Yeah, just a lot of unknowns. I mean, it's a great it's a great option
It's a great idea, but people need to touch and feel things. They need tactile experience
That needs to happen. Yeah, this year was hard this year. I really struggled with Android
I think this I think 2014 became a year where for me I I became a disenfranchised Android user
I still have my Nexus 5 I'd say Android is
70% of the operating system to runtime like 70% of my time in an OS is Android
I I now fluctuate between Ubuntu touch and selfish OS and Firefox OS
But I I just I can't get past the fact that at the end of the day I enjoy using iOS more
I think iOS is more performant. I think it's simpler for what I need to do
I just need a phone that does text messages and listens to podcasts. That's literally all I need a phone to do and so for me
For me Firefox OS selfish OS and Ubuntu touch are very appealing because they essentially could very easily be able to satisfy those needs
Now it's funny because I'm also the same person where when I go somewhere my requirements for a smartphone
Totally change now all of a sudden needs to be ways right needs to be able to do
Yeah, so it's it's it's I find it
That's what I like about the Nexus 5 is that right now I like when I become that person I
I can use Android and when I'm the guy that just needs to listen to stuff and do and make text messages
I can use a different OS, but I find none of them to be ideal at this point
Yeah, I think anything that it can embrace your existing ecosystem has an edge over the other true
Yeah, you know stuff, you know, obviously Android's the most likely to be embraced ecosystem
I think that's really the main piece of it for myself. I like to use apps just to run my apps so that I can manage
my apps I
Live in apps. I have everything. It's ridiculous when I came when I dropped iOS years ago. I
Don't know three four hundred dollars of crap. Yeah, I mean, you know, I lost a fortune
So I'm very sensitive to that ecosystem. Yep. Yep. Great point and that's a bigger deal than ever now and
Wimpy we got to talk about I mean, I know this is this is a family-friendly podcast
We got to talk about the c-word though convergence. What do you think?
Well, I have a prediction about convergence and that's canonicals definition or Mark Shuttleworth's
Definition of convergence. So right now I've got a Samsung note 2
Which was issued by work and that's now two years old and it's up for renewal in terms of the hardware
There is nothing on the market today that is significantly better than this phone that I've got that's two years old
Yep, you know the cameras have got slightly more megapixels. Yeah, there's a touch more RAM
There's a couple more cores on the processor
But there's not much to compel me from a hardware point of view to change the device
I feel the same way about my Nexus 5. I feel the same thing because I've got cyanogen on this phone
You know from a software point of view. It's perfectly fine. This could this could march on for another year quite happily
so my prediction about converge devices, and this is canonicals definition of convergence where your
Mobile phone could be your desktop PC is that this convergence story will be adopted by the big players on
The Android platform and that convergence story of turn your phone into your desktop
will drive the next generation of mobile specs on your phone with regards to CPU GPU RAM and
Story now when you see this is it HTC's implementations Samsung's version of it like is it like yeah?
Each each of the yeah, so the Samsung's HTC's will have their own. You know
Adaption to what happens to your device when you hook it up to a keyboard mouse and and fixed display
But they I think they're all going to move to that convergence story because the the
Only way you can justify all this extra hardware is to make the extra hardware. Do something. Mm-hmm. Yeah, I
I think I think this already like Google already started making significant
Moves towards making this happen because as far as I've been able to figure out in the new material design
Specifications or whatever you call it
They actually included something like Ubuntu has which allows the application to scale from
easily scale from a phone-sized application to a
Full
69 screen type of application and still be usable. So they're making
Moves in that direction. So
As far as I can doubt that that might be a very correct prediction. Yeah, I think it makes a lot of sense too because I think over 2015 will be the year you see 64-bit processors hit all of the anything that's considered a modern smartphone over 2015 will point towards the end of 2015 will have to have 64-bit. I'll make that a prediction because that's gonna be a marketing thing, right? And once you start, why do you need 64-bit because you need more than 4 gigs of RAM and why do you need 4 gigs of RAM because you want to run desktop apps?
It sounds horrible, I mean we all remember the A tricks, but I also had a client that would love this
I can think of a specific person. He was a big hitter for a company and this would be perfect for him
As long as it was rock-solid. Here's where I don't think it's gonna be rock-solid different implementations like Samsung's Sam Samsung's gonna do horrible at that, right?
Yeah
HTC probably gonna do horrible at that and so maybe
We'll look at this and go but you know who baked this in at the core level is Ubuntu touch
Maybe that'll happen. Maybe not or what's gonna happen?
more likely is
Apple will come along rip it all off get it right and then nobody will ever talk about anybody else but apples
I
Can't see Apple doing it
I'd be surprised if they do and I really hope I really hope that
canonical are in the right place at the right time with Ubuntu touch and
the the devices with the specs actually actually deliver on this because
for all the people that knock
Canonical and Ubuntu touch this is proper Linux on a mobile device and we we should all be supporting that endeavor really
Yeah
Hell yeah. Yeah, I think boy that's it. You know what? I think you nailed it
I think they're gonna have to use convergence and you know
The other thing is they're gonna be you know, they're already looking around for ideas
They're looking over at Mark Shallow Earth and they're thinking way that guy's saying something smart
We should grab that and they're gonna go do it. I think you nailed that
I'm gonna give that a double ding. All right Keller you want to close this out on the convergence topic with a thought about
thoughts about Intel
Well, I mean if her true convergence to happen
We can't have two separate processor lines to focus on arm versus your your eye
We're gonna have to find a way to get Intel
More integrated into the mobile space. Yeah, I mean they're fiercely working on that
But yeah, you're right that that you can already buy Intel
phones and tablets
Yeah, what's gonna run on how are they selling? I
Mean, well, yeah, that's the other thing we you know canonical could make a platform and software that runs on both
I mean Android already does yeah, you shouldn't download the same Android app
I mean, they're their fat binary builds that have x86 code and um HF code inside
But the same thing could happen for pure Linux like a bunty
Yeah, you know and I wouldn't my 2015 another maybe just as my final 2015 prediction would be I don't think Intel is gonna make any
significant inroads in mobile because
the reason why I think that is because I've been along I've been around longer than five years and
Seriously, I've seen Intel talk about this since the 90s, right? If they've been it's just around the corner
It's just around the corner. It's then it's just it's always just around the corner with Intel when it comes to mobile
And I'm not trying to be this guy
But at the same time you're seeing some amazing ass come out of the arm shops. There is really gonna start kicking their ass
You know you look at the performance some of the some of these high-end tablets coming out of Nvidia and coming and the new
iPad to air like these things are crazy like six core GPUs and stuff like that like Intel wake the F up
It's it's the ship is sailing so they've really got to double down and I think at the end of the day
It's gonna be more solved like Popey saying by things like Dalvik or whatever the hell
It's gonna be at the time or QML or whatever the hell
It's gonna be it's gonna be more
It's gonna be handled in the software side less on the processor side
And so you'll have devices that are Intel you have it you'll have devices that are ARM. I've for two years
I've been predicting the ARM desktop. I'm not gonna make it this year, but I'm surprised
Well in interestingly the the Intel based tablets that are on the market at the moment were subsidized by Intel
Yeah, they were cheaper and that yeah, and I think maybe people will be less reluctant this year to do
Intel based devices or maybe they'll be more inclined to do it because the way has been proven last year that it is possible to make
Intel tablets that you know survive a decent battery life and our performance and you know can run all the same applications
Yeah, I mean this good. Sorry Chris gone. No, I just gonna say I wouldn't put it past Intel to be able to pull it off
You know this time last year
My dad was looking for a tablet an Android tablet and one of the Samsung tablets had an Intel chip in it
And it was significantly cheaper than the the Samsung
10.1 arm box and I advised my dad not to get the Intel
Device because I said you're gonna be limited in the apps that are available at this point because it's um, you know fairly new
Technology and not everyone's adopted it yet. Yeah, I'd feel a bit differently this year if it was me spending money on a tablet
I might seriously think about an Intel tablet because I can hack more with it
Yeah, my main my main tablet is an Intel one. Yeah, and it's it's better than any arm tablet
Yeah, I would much if I was gonna buy a tablet that I would much prefer to have an x86 tablet
I want all the things about an ARM tablet too though
But that's just me and you guys like we prefer x86 because well
It's just easier to load anything we want on it a but B
We prefer it because it's x86 and it runs our stuff consumers. Don't give a crap about that though. They don't give a crap
I actually want the ARM laptop though. I
I'm surprised we I mean there are some out there. I'm I'm honestly surprised like an Android
How come how come some major OEM hasn't released an Android based laptop in the US? I think there's some in Asia
I
Could have stamped on a few people that have done this haven't they? Oh, okay
Chrome OS arm. Yeah, I'm laptop. Yeah. Yeah Chrome OS is gonna have a good year over 2015. I think
You Samsung Chromebooks are hard to get in Canada and this is the only reason why I don't have a
Arm laptop. Yeah, those of you who are on Google Plus today may have spotted
that a Google intern
Now with I guess potentially Google blessing. I'm trying to find the post on Google Plus right now, which never happens for me
I said earlier you might oh you did. Oh, okay. All right. I'll go search for you
So, you know what I'm talking about then that that that there is a crew ton like in a window now
Yeah, here it is right here. Yeah. Oh, yeah
Yeah, so a Google intern has added support to run crew ton in a Chrome OS window
Thanks to four hundred and forty seven one lines of code
Fearless people can now run their favorite Linux distributions on their Chrome devices in a window without jumping between terminals
So now now Ubuntu or another distro could be
Essentially like an app on Chrome OS. So part of me thinks that's great. That's awesome. It allows you to
Switch more easily between the two and part of me thinks is this Google doing their best to try and keep you away from
the second OS that people are putting on they're
Very cheap, you know Google so yeah Chrome devices in order to keep you in Chrome. I think it has to be that
That's it that's because that's the only thing it does that's it doesn't improve performance
It keeps you in Chrome OS and it makes this a feature of Chrome OS. I
Which is fine for some people and we shouldn't be doom and gloom about it because
You could make the same argument about you know open office and Libre office and get being available for Windows
All those people stay on Windows it helps, you know people make the transition
I think though it's it's gonna be I think it's telling I think it's telling how 2015 is gonna go
my thoughts
It's gonna be interesting. I you know it's gonna be one of those things
I think we're gonna have to hold up a stick to see it move cuz I don't think it's gonna happen quite as quickly as
People anticipate we'll get to the end. Yeah, well. No you're right. We'll get to the end, and we'll be like whoa
Whoa what happened what happened? Oh?
Oh, yeah, that makes sense now that makes sense and we could be all wrong about all of this
We may be wrong you have a chance timing in context you have a chance to prove us wrong
You never know you can hold us accountable you can because it's now it is documented forever right here on the Linux unplug show
So Matt if we got it wrong. It's on the record
That's right. You actually got like the best record out of all of us though, so
You you like nailed all of your predictions last year, so I don't even want it
I'm the guy that said the Google public offering thing was a
Classic there's that class you go back far enough
If you'd like to make your prediction go over to Linux action show dot reddit.com and leave your feedback in this week's thread or go
To Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact and send yours in and we might read it on a future show
Don't forget you can join us live on Tuesdays 2 p.m.. Pacific over to jblive.tv for that
Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar to get it converted in your local time zone and last but not least
We'd love to have you join us in that mumble room. It's an open mumble room
You can be part of our virtual lug you just gotta get your mic checked jblive.tv on a Tuesday
See you back here next week everybody. Thanks so much for listening to this week's episode of Linux unplugged. See you next Tuesday. Oh
I have a last-minute breaking prediction for myself
I will spend an inappropriate amount of money on steam games and my wife will give me a hard time in the month of December
In 2015 that's my prediction
What was it a fist of Jesus or something like that?
Wasn't as good as I had hoped but there's some other good ones out there. Yeah
Yeah, oh yeah, you got more you got more my prediction is that Sony is going to be hacked and
And aliens will be blamed for it. Oh aliens. All right. All right
JB titles like on everybody
Wimpy did you have more?
Why I didn't have more but nobody mentioned wearables or Windows 10, which is surprising
I would have thought somebody would have had a prediction about those two things either
We don't give a shit about it and what we think is irrelevant and therefore
not not discussion worthy or
I don't know. I think maybe on wearables. I think yes, I think on wearables. That is true
I think on Windows 10, we're all a little melancholy because
Microsoft's ripping us off and it's probably gonna help stop the bleeding a little bit
Yeah, I didn't want to say it, but I've got a horrible feeling that Windows 10 could suck some Linux users back
No, they weren't good Linux users to begin with then
These are the kind of people that are using Linux because it doesn't cost them anything. Yeah rather than right
They you know buy into the culture. Yep. That's very true
Hmm. That's a yeah the Windows 10 and the wearables thing
Yeah, and the other thing about it is I think the Apple watch probably the most successful and that sucks so bad because it's
The most locked in one like you can't use it with your Linux desktop. You can't lose use it with your Android device
It's the iPod iPhone situation all over again meets watches
Yeah, yeah is Windows 10. I'm going to be free. Yes for consumers. So I don't think the business one will be free though
No, there's gonna be some
Hobbled version for home users isn't there? There's gonna be free and I think that will tempt people back
Well returning the conversation to wearables. I still think that pebble is the only
Smart watch that I would consider buying
Yeah, that is a good that that one's very calling. Let's see. The for me is I already have to charge my
Phone every day. I already have to charge my laptop every day. I have to charge my tablet every day
I
Don't want to add another device to that list
especially something that a watch used to be something that I didn't have to
Think about yeah, it would just run forever, right? Yeah
The ones that have like a dock that you can put next to your bed and our bedside clock with an alarm
You know every time you go to bed, you just take it off. Yeah, like the motor that see yeah, that makes it way more
This is a valid argument
But I don't think you know how often I forget to transfer my phone and then wake up in the morning with like 5%
Of the body lead. Oh, I guess yeah, so the same I I collect
Classic digital watches from sort of the 70s in the early 80s and some of the models from the 70s that have got the LED
Displays. Oh, yeah
They burn the battery really fast in that the battery burns out in about six months
which used to be considered a major pain in the ass, but against smart watches, which
At the end of the day
You're mostly going to use for telling the time on that you need to show at least once a day
Look fucking epic all rumors. Now. That's long since gone
So is the foosball table and pinball machine and the the cocktail arcade cabinets and I know Popey's got one of those
Popey you've got bomb Jack haven't you you bugger? Hmm cocktail bomb Jack never even heard of that. Ah
Bomb Jack is the best arcade game from the 19th. Oh, maybe I'm just
I
Know you do we've discussed this. Yeah, he bombed Jack is great. Okay. All right. I'm looking up right now
It's one of the it's one of the only games where I had to rotate the screen in my arcade cabinet
I had to like the screen out
Cool bomb Jack is ice and the reason I love bomb Jack is um, I
Participated in the the world arcade games on two occasions and the games that I
I played were a bomb Jack
1942 and GR kung fu and I was European champion for bomb Jack
But I did I didn't get the the world title. Well done, sir. I see that I get to get this looks fun
It's really good. Yeah, a little stressful little stressful
No, it looks a little stressful because you only got a limited time to get around and there's a lot of guys in your way
And you have to do it in sequence as well. That's where you really ramp up your points
That's the whole the whole point of the game is learn all the sequences on all of the levels
It's great. And and the blizzard detection is just
Forgiving enough that you can pull off some really tight moves around the the enemies. It's a really well designed game
Hmm that was in fact new into the android
Uh play store is free jack
Yes, free jack has a free version and a paid version that's only just turned up and it's basically a clone of bomb jack
So, uh, yeah, give that a go
Huh? I have heard of free jack. Did you guys see that the uh, did you guys hear about this, uh, ide for gnome?
Did you see this?
No, i've been hearing about it. Yeah builder and ide for gnome is doing an indiegogo project
They've raised 12 000 out of 30 000 so far gnome a modern elegant desktop with a wide range of applications
And high focus on usability
But underneath the surface gnome is showing its age. Our developer tools on linux are from the last decade
meet jim
Jim wants to start contributing to free software
Our community is strong and happy to help but how should jim begin writing software?
As of today, there are too many tools jim needs to learn first get the group builder the perfect development environment for jim
Builder is an idea of mine
This summer I quit my job to focus on creating a new ide from scratch with everything a developer will look for in a development
Environment by integrating gnome's documentation and platform api with a powerful editor and ui designer
We can make it easy for people like jim to contribute
With the funds this fundraiser can provide I will work on builder full time
If we reach 30 000 I can work full time for the next three months and implement builder's core features
Here's a spotlight of three of them
With global search you can find and open anything you need
Builder will as you type find files and documentation
This can even be extended by additional search providers in the future
Many free software projects use a combination of tools to manage themselves known as auto tools
Builder intends to automate the use of these tools
This will make it easy for anyone to build and manage their projects
Builder will have autocompletion for c and c plus plus if we reach our stretch goal. We'll add support for vala and pythons
To make writing even easier builder will also provide auto indentation and api exploration on the fly
So the idea is like if you want to start developing for the linux desktop, uh, you know right now
There's not a real clear path you're supposed to take this is something we've heard about from people that write in necoda radio
They're like, you know, you're not going to be able to do this
This is something we've heard about from people that write in necoda radio. They're like I
I've been writing applications for this platform for my entire life now
I want to write for linux and I have no idea where i'm supposed to start
Uh, do you have any advice and this is kind of like you would the idea here
But you point them to this and to give the uh, the project credit like the guy quit his job, uh in the summer
He's been working on it over the whole summer and the budget of 30 000 is also included like
Going to conferences to talk about it with people and you know doing collaboration and stuff like that. I'm kind of impressed
I think i'm gonna back it. It's not
You're not impressed why you think it's just a text editor. What's the problem?
Do you want all my concerns about this in the form of a list or should I make a presentation?
Wow, just give me the top give me your top three
Okay. So first of all, if you want to contribute to any
Linux based projects regardless of your skill level if you just want to contribute go to the irc
Uh channel of that project and tell the guys that you want to contribute
So that's how you have to do
That's antiquated and painful. Yeah, and the thing is they don't know that a they don't know
They don't they don't know that and b the thing is then what tool you tell them to go use
What tool are they supposed to go use because they don't like that
but no see that the thing is is like there it's
It's hard for us to understand but there's one tool. It's causal. Well, I think I was gonna say vi, uh, no
No, if the the thing is is like you tell them that and that that to me makes sense
But then when you tell developers that that I don't have any familiarity with the linux platform they glaze over there's too many options
There's too many choices. There's no obvious path
No, dude
It works like this if you want to write for ios or you want to write for android go to this website create an account
Download this single program and that's all you have to tell the developer and they can go make an app for that platform
When they don't have to wait for someone in irc to like answer their question or hopefully get the same answer twice or whatever
And when you or or have a holy war like oh you want to use eclipse?
You should use vi like or no like they just need something and I totally agree with you
I I think it's kind of silly
But when I see it from their perspective I can see where builder fills that niche a little bit and it could you know
Maybe help the developers get started
Okay, but as far as I can tell from the video and from this the description on the project
And this is my second point. Also, it doesn't really
Help you it just in the search bar. It also searches the documentation
And it's not really that impressive what you get is this
unity scope style search of everything and it really
Distorted results because half the time the top result will not be what?
Even in the category of what you're looking for
They they well, it also has a ui designer as well and a few other like debugger and things like that in there
So you have those tools already?
Yeah, we do. Um, and we have something like cute creator which does all of this already very nicely
So but it's not gnome specific and they want something for gnome. That's why
And there are gnome tools for c and c sharp with ui designers already
Well, there's a difference between there are and are they good
In the video it specifically says they want one tool to do it all. Yeah. Well, yeah
Another thing is like a valid point. Yeah, is it it doesn't exist or is it good?
I have no guarantee that what this guy is making is going to be any better
No, that's fair. It may it may suck toes, but it'd be interesting to see him try. Yeah, you know, what were your thoughts winnie?
Is the order of things calm?
Chris was talking about, um, you know building a tool that's going to help you build a tool
Chris was talking about um, you know building something for linux
Um, and I don't want to rag on this project because more development tools is a good thing as far as i'm concerned
But this is a development tool that's aimed at building applications for gnome gnome 3
And what poppy has described is an sdk
uh that's designed to build, uh, uh applications for
ubuntu
Specifically ubuntu touch and what will become no, I think to create. Yeah. Yeah, so it's going to be you know
Ubuntu in the future. No
Creator is independent of us. Yeah. Well, yeah, I know but it's it's ubuntu, isn't it? It's about making apps for ubuntu
I have to support wimpy here. The only time I used cute creator was to make apps for ubuntu
No, no, no, it is not an ubuntu thing. But I think what poppy's or what wimpy's getting at is
That's what poppy wants to see right? Yeah. Yeah, I mean no no no if I if I if I went meant to say that
I would have said ubuntu. I agree. I specifically said cute creator. I think wimpy's it's already existing wimpy's having a go at you
Uh and one that I appreciate
I am pointing out that
Ubuntu is is
Heading down a road of you develop for ubuntu. You don't develop for linux you develop for ubuntu and that's no bad thing
That's that's an admirable
Objective, you know
It's kind of a commercial objective and I can understand where those commercial pressures are going to come from
But this is not that neither of these tools are addressing
Uh developing for linux