As we record, 10 years ago, Steam's beta went public on Linux.
It's been 10 years, boys.
Congratulations, everyone.
November 6, 2012, the initial beta was limited to just select participants.
They wanted to work out early bugs and then they announced they'd be
releasing it to the wider public later as more Source Engine games became
available and they based the original Steam stuff on Ubuntu 12.04.12.10.
That's what I'm still running around.
And now, you know, with the Steam Deck out there, things are looking pretty good.
Steam on Linux was at a pretty healthy 1.28%, which is, I mean, 1% sounds small,
but when you consider the massive base of Steam and how it's always growing,
that's almost, you know, 1.3%.
That's pretty decent.
Mac's only at 2.23%.
So we're sniffing at the bottom of the Mac heel right now.
And as the Deck sells, there'll be more and more soon.
That's pretty nice to see.
You know, you look at where Valve's at now with Linux, it seems like we're in a
pretty good position for that market share number just to get bigger and bigger.
Yeah, right.
It's getting great.
I think it's only getting better.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And my name is Brent.
You're back.
Welcome.
Thank you for having us again.
The boys are back in town this week and we're surprising each other with three
unknown topics, so I can't tell you what we're going to talk about because I don't
know.
What I do know is that I've got a big update on my Odroid H3 Plus.
Finally, really looking forward to telling you about that.
And I know we'll round out the show with some great boosts and picks and a lot
more.
So before we go any further, let's give a shout out to that virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello, guys.
Hey, Wes, and hello, Brent.
Hello.
Hello, and hello, everybody up there in quiet listening.
We got a big crowd up there.
They're being very quiet today.
That's the nature of it.
But are they listening?
I hope so, because I'd like them to go over and say good morning to Tailscale.
Head over to tailscale.com.
It's a mesh VPN powered by WireGuard.
We love it.
I used the heck out of it recently.
I just got to go into my most recent Home Assistant installation as well.
It's a powerful mesh VPN product.
Go say good morning to our friends over at Tailscale and use it for free up to 20
devices at tailscale.com.
Tell them I'm plugged a program, sent you.
All right. So before we get into the show today, we got to sort this out.
We got some geocache drama, and I don't know if Brent just has selective memory
holing or if I'm confusing locations and names again, but one of us is right and
one of us is wrong, and we've got to settle it now before we go any further.
So you put it in the doc, so I'll let you start, Brent.
Sure thing.
Jared wrote in with a little note that made me wonder if our geocache at Folsom
might be a flop.
Jared writes, I stopped by the Folsom geocache with my kids and spent over an
hour looking and digging around without success.
Just a note.
We didn't bury any of them.
Apparently that's a faux pas in the geocache world.
Jared continues, I met another fellow listener who happened to be looking for
it too, which was about, okay, that's amazing.
Isn't that great?
So that got me thinking, how many people are looking for this stuff?
I really want to know.
We love hearing that.
So please, if you went looking and didn't find, don't be disappointed.
Leave us a note.
We'd love to hear it or stash another one.
If it's missing, hide one.
I don't know.
That's actually a great idea.
I don't know how you'd market like a JB community one.
Maybe you put a note in there or something or a thumb drive with some JB shows.
Maybe we could send them some stickers.
We put in a t-shirt that we were hoping that was going to work.
Jared continued at this point, I think it's either one found by someone else
as the area doesn't, does get frequent traffic or two.
It's so well-hidden that we need another clue besides Chris's burnt trees.
Listen now, come on, why are you coming at me?
Why are you coming to me with that?
Oh, you hit the cache.
I was there in person, but I had no idea where you hit it.
You had to tell me and, uh, I looked for a little bit and had a hard time.
So I think that's, I mean, that's part of the balance, isn't it?
It's it's balancing, not having just random people find it because
we want our JB fans to find it.
But also, so it needs to be hidden well enough that not just a random person
finds it and the excuses come out.
You see how he's attacking my hiding styles here.
He's attacking me.
I had this exact same challenge on the other geocaches.
Oh no, I know what's going on here.
You see, here's what happened is I got a personally good, reasonable spot
to hide it, and then Brent couldn't find it.
So he's got it all in his head that I made it super hard.
And you know why?
Here's why he can't find it.
Here's why Jared couldn't find it.
I believe this was found almost immediately.
Oh, really?
I have a clear recollection on one of our shows, and I think it was the
peak of our travel, so we don't remember it.
But I remember in one of our shows, this was the first one that
got found was the Folsom one.
No, I disagree.
I think it's the one that Wes planted in that tree that got found first.
Mine was definitely found.
Okay.
All right, that might be true, but I swear, I remember talking about
the Folsom one being found, so we need someone else to go on location.
Okay.
Did we even ever hide one there?
At this point, I'm beginning to question it.
I've heard a lot of stories, but I think we need either trackers in these
things or something so that we could tell if they've been moved.
But actually, I think one thing that might help is maybe we need a central
place to collect all the geocaches and the status of them, whether they've
been found, not found, et cetera.
So, uh, actually take off seven, five, one on our GitHub suggested
that we implement such a system.
So I am going to put out a pledge.
Here you go.
You ready for this?
Oh, so by next Linux unplugged, that's in seven days, we will have a
geocaching tracking system in place.
Now it might not be fancy.
We've talked about in that issue, some really fancy ways of doing it, but we'll
at least have something and I will go back and try to figure out which ones
have been found, which ones haven't.
And I'll collect all of the, you know, coordinates and everything
in a nice, easy to find place.
There you go.
I believe the Folsom one has been found.
I will give a little bit more context because I'm looking at the
video I took of it right now.
And what I would say is you go down the trail to the shore where there's, um, a
river, no, it's a lake or whatever, and there is some burnt logs, pretty much
right off to the right-hand side when you're walking down there and those
burnt logs under one of them here, here, I'll show it to you too, Wes.
Maybe you can think of a way to describe this, but so here to grab the phone, you
can see the, that's the video right there.
How would you describe that spot?
It's just kind of down on the shore under some burnt logs.
I mean, it's not, there's nothing, not especially burnt from this picture,
just kind of some, some regular logs.
There's, I mean, at the time there was a bunch of leaves.
That's the one clue I give is burnt logs and youth.
Maybe the area is kind of previous.
No, I'm, I'm agreeing with Chris in person.
It's clear that that area, someone, I don't know, threw down a cigarette and
got burnt and everything else is super lush and green.
So I think the burnt part is actually a great tip because it's the only area
around there that sort of looks like that.
And Chris, when you had me in person, try to find it just based on our little,
this was the first one we dropped.
So he was like, okay, now try to find it.
I had a hard time because I didn't have any hints, but I think that
hint is actually a really great one.
Now that leads me to believe, I think someone else grabbed it.
That's just, that's my conclusion.
You could see if you're walking by it, you could see the blue.
I can't show it on camera, but you could see the blue of the lid walking by.
It's actually visible just walking by it.
It's not like, I like that you put a little bit of leaves over it, though.
Yeah, it's a little, it's like little, yeah, it's a little bit, but, um,
wasn't the lid red, it looks blue in the picture.
Uh-oh.
Brent, get it together.
How burnt was it?
You know, all right.
So, uh, you can come at me with my hiding styles or what lids I use, but the reality
is I think it was one of the first ones found.
So therefore one of the most successful, Wes is being thus most successful.
At least by one measure.
But anyways, we should do more of these because clearly there's not enough.
That's amazing that they're two different listeners at the same time.
We're out there better get out there while the weather's still good.
And Jared finishes, we had fun looking for it, nonetheless, and my daughter
implored me to get out there sooner.
The next time we have another geocache to find.
So thank you for putting it out there.
It was great meeting everyone at the Sacramento meetup and having this
fun little activity along with it.
Yeah.
Uh, you know what makes me just want to travel again a little bit, which is good.
I thought maybe I thought maybe my travel bone would be broken.
Although I have to say with the weather, what it is, I'm looking
forward to just hunkering down for a bit.
And, uh, I got plenty of projects to work on.
Oh yes, you do.
And the biggest for me personally, although probably not for the whole
family is my new home server to replace my dad, raspberry pie server.
Rest in peace, little buddy.
Yeah.
It's time came too soon.
However, the timing could not have been more perfect.
I was pretty bummed when the server died because my home
assistant setup was very complex.
I got like a lot of devices and I was like, I'm going to have to
a lot of devices and it was responsible for a lot of the automation.
But then additionally, like we just talked about, um, on the pre-show,
I like having my media locally because I'm often on a mobile connection.
Yeah.
And so I also had it serving up local media.
I have it doing all of our documentation and Markdown.
I had it running our DNS.
I had it running all kinds of things like smoke ping and, uh, sync
thing and, um, the heart of the RV.
Yeah.
And it died when I was down in Pasadena for the JPL tour, it was
back up in Sacramento dying and I didn't even know it, but the timing
was like unbelievable because when I arrived home from our road trip, my
home assistant yellow was sitting on the porch, just amazing.
After a year, I could crowds, I crowdfunded that thing like a year ago.
It shows up.
And so I get, uh, I get my home assistant set up going and it's rock.
And I talked about that and self-hosted recently, then right around the same
time, hard kernel folks announced the O droid H3 and the H3 plus, which is
an X86 based raspberry PI alternative.
It starts around $165 for the plus.
So a little spend here, but yeah.
X86.
And you get a quad core Jasper Lake processor, which goes up to 3.3
gigahertz, four cores, it goes up to 64 gigabytes of dual channel DDR4 RAM.
It has an MVME slot.
It has dual 2.5 gigabit NICs.
Oh, I've mentioned it before on the show.
It's like, it was the perfect solution at the moment that my system had died.
And I, I was waiting, I knew I needed to redo part of my setup anyways,
cause I had some home assistant issues, but I just didn't want to, didn't
want to go through all the hassle without also getting a performance
upgrade and then this stuff just, and, and not only did this get announced,
but they actually shipped it on time.
You have it.
I have it.
And so I've been running it in production over the last week or so.
I really banged on it pretty much all weekend.
This is like what I focused on the most when it was raining.
And, um, I am going to give it a Hardy endorsement.
I give this one the LUP seal of approval.
If you're looking for a low power device, when this thing is running idle, just kind
of, and I would define idle as your services are loaded, but nothing's really
being taxed 1.5 Watts for an X86 box.
I can run any X86 application.
I want, it's got a modern Intel processor with quick sync.
I've got super fast storage, 1.5 Watts.
That seems amazing and impossible, but how does it compare to arm stuff?
Is it, it must be in the same area.
It's around there.
That is crazy.
Where it, it can go up a little higher.
I think it's depending on your load.
Yeah.
What you're doing with it.
I actually, I haven't really seen a lot of that.
How does it feel to be back on X86?
I feel like another way to spin this little segment is a Chris abandoned arm.
Well, I don't know about abandoning arm forever, but I am done with the
raspberry PI I no way, not compared to this.
This blows it away.
Oh, it's I'm done with the PI.
Seriously.
I never thought this day would happen.
Are you feeling okay?
It's the storage, it's the CPU.
It's the two SATA ports having a, so I also picked up a four terabyte
Saturdays from Amazon for like a ridiculously great price.
And I hooked it up over SATA and now I have, I've gone from USB
storage to actual SATA storage.
And the only thing I'm not really satisfied so far with the
old droid would be the cases.
They're kind of clunky.
They're kind of rough.
They're a good price, but if anybody knows the better cases, I
would definitely be interested.
Have you had a chance to play with the dual NICs yet?
Cause I'm real curious about that.
No, I only, I'm only using one.
I don't actually need dual in this, but not buying raspberry pies anymore.
So like when I do eventually get this firewall set, we get a firewall
set up here at the studio.
I'm going to go with one of these.
I'm done with the raspberry PI.
I'll find something to do with a few of them I have left, I guess,
but it's just so much better.
Melt them down in a sort of ceremonial.
No, I mean, I'll use them for something, but I don't know.
Maybe mine Monero.
I've got another question for you.
I noticed there's a massive fan on that case, which in one way is probably
good because it's quiet or quieter.
I'm curious, have you had a sense of the heat output on that thing?
I'm not pushing it a lot.
So I've been checking it and now I'm also monitoring the booth, you know,
cause it's in the booth and the temperatures are all totally normal.
So I don't have a fan on mine.
The case does have room for a fan.
It does not come with a fan, but they sell a series of accessories for this thing.
Including a fan, if you want to run it with a SATA disk, make sure you get a
power cable because you're going to need that.
It doesn't, it doesn't come with that.
Well, one of the things that's made this real great, got to give a shout out to
Nix, never saw that coming.
So what I did before I decided to deploy this thing is I took my dev one because
I'm, I was getting a new, can pave it to put fedora on there anyways for testing.
So before I did that last week, I, uh, put a fan on it and it was, it was
working, I did a minimal Nix install and started configuring it.
Like I was going to set up the Odroid on my dev one laptop.
So I got jelly fins set up.
I got my storage mounted where I wanted it with everything in the
right file systems and all that.
Got all, got all this stuff kind of preloaded and configured, figured out
what I didn't like, fixed a few things, got some tweaks going.
Yeah.
And then when all the parts arrive for the Odroid, which is really, I was waiting
for it, I just sat down and I decided to do a GUI install because I'm lazy.
And also I just wanted to run, I wanted to get the Odroid all the way up to a GUI
again, right?
So make sure everything was there, test the networking, test everything.
And so I went and I grabbed the NixOS gnome installer and ran that, did a live
session, made sure everything was working, made sure I could see the storage.
Everything was good.
Cause I brought the disks with me.
I had them attached to the dev one over USB, but on the Odroid, I
had them installed over SATA, but it all still worked.
No problem.
It was still dev SDA on both of them.
Perfect.
So I get everything going, launch the installer and I choose the minimal
install option, which is fantastic.
So when it's all done, it reboots into a headless setup, essentially,
and a real minimal config.
And so then I just SSH in, drop my config that I kind of built over a week on the
dev one onto the Odroid, do the old Nix config rebuild.
And, uh, within like, I don't know, 15 minutes, I mean, maybe not even that
the thing was crazy fast and it's pretty minimal install.
I rebooted and I had everything and you're done and like everything worked.
It was incredible.
And I opted to use containers for a couple of things instead of using the
next package manager of mostly for my media stuff.
So sync thing, jellyfin that's all via container, but then things like net data
and duplicati and all, of course, all of like the command line tools, that's all
installed via the Nix system.
I'm thinking this is going to be a really solid long-term install because I have
rollback capabilities with Nix now.
And it's a pretty minimal base install and config, and it's all just
defined in that config file.
Easy to back up.
Easy to, I already have it backed up.
And so I think I can just keep that base system rolling and I'll just update the
application containers that I run in containers over time.
And I think with the performance of the Odroid.
You're not going to be super taxing this box all the time, right?
So we can just kind of sit there, hum along, do what you need it to.
I think I'm going to get a quick sync as you said, so it's not even going to have
to be like too hassled there.
Years, years, Wes, years.
I'm going to get years of use out of this.
Wait, but then what are you going to do if you're not constantly
rebuilding your home server?
I'm going to be buying more of these things and putting them in all kinds of
places.
I mean, I ended up with like four raspberry pies over time.
This is so it really, they hit it out of the park.
The 1.5 Watts at idle matters a lot because there are long stretches of time
where I'm running off solar.
And so anything that runs consistently matters, even if it's just a couple of
Watts over a 24 hour period time or a, you know, a week, that really adds up.
Okay.
Do you think you could do a show off?
I was wondering, I was wondering, um, definitely, definitely fed a PCI slot.
Definitely.
Yeah.
But, you know, the disc guy, it was really fast, maybe, it would depend on
the CPU and all that, but maybe I've thought about, I've thought about,
could these be used as a desktop?
Swap out the studio.
You know, we got to replace these studio rigs.
That's actually what I was thinking is the Reaper machine.
I was thinking because it'd be silent, tiny little thing, more space below here
for fun snacks.
Cheap, right?
I love how your, your thoughts, what, two weeks ago was to put out a
Thalio in place, and now you're talking about putting this right there.
No, the Thalios, no, the Thalios is going to, no, no.
The Thalios is for the OBS machine.
That's sorry, sorry, sorry, sorry.
We might get that ordered tomorrow morning, but for the Reaper machine.
That's a different, that's a different set of requirements.
It might work.
Yeah.
I'm very, very impressed.
And I've done two separate orders.
So I ordered the Odroid and then I also had to order a, like a cable pack and
stuff, and I'm like, okay, I'm going to order a Thalios.
Bull shipments were just, I mean, not as quick as Amazon, but within a few
days they arrived, no problem.
Like, no supply chain issue.
Availability feels good.
Yeah.
I'm very, very impressed.
That matters when you need a replacement in a pinch or, you know, the next piece
for your next project.
So I'm going to get, uh, going to get just things kind of dialed in on this thing
now.
I got tail scale set up on it last night.
And so that's, that's going now.
And I got, um, a real kind of nice, clean, like I really took everything I've kind
of figured out over the last couple of years since I built the Raspberry Pi and
applied it to this one.
Yeah.
It's my first Raspberry Pi builds were Raspberry Pi OS.
And that just doesn't make for a good server.
What a world ago that was.
And then my second generation, which is what my PI server was that died.
My second generation of Raspberry Pi builds was all based on Ubuntu, I think
2004, their first LTS that officially supported the PI.
And I got to give Ubuntu credit.
It worked really, really well.
It did a very good job for what I needed, but there's a lot there compared to a
minimal Nix install.
There's so much more installed on that Ubuntu system and so many more services
and like snap stuff that I didn't want on the server.
Just a bunch of things you don't particularly care about that might be nice
on a more generic server, but not for what you're doing here.
And there was something really nice about getting a, kind of like having a system
to make mistakes on, on the dev one and do things wrong a couple of times.
Cause like one of the things I did the first time is I tried to just do JellyFin
as just using Nix.
Yeah.
And one of the things I discovered is that presently, although they're working on
it, but presently they have an older version of JellyFin packaged in Nix.
You think of it as a rolling distro, it's got everything brand new, but in this
case, JellyFin was actually out of date.
And there are solutions to solve that on Nix, but then I also have to solve it for
FFmpeg because I need a version of FFmpeg that works with JellyFin.
And then I also have to solve it for this plugin that I'm using.
That's based on a certain version of JellyFin.
It kind of just started becoming like this rabbit hole of like fixing stuff to
make it use the Nix system versus I could just go get the container that just had
it all.
And obviously NixOS runs containers just fine.
Exactly.
So that was sort of one of the things I realized on my test system was like,
maybe I won't do it this way.
Yeah.
I can see it's nice not having to worry about containers and not worrying about
any of that, but for these media applications, Plex2, the creators of these
containers have done things to optimize like hardware transcoding and stuff like
that.
And you probably, a lot of these, like you don't really want to look inside,
right?
You don't really care.
Like as long as it works and it pops up its web interface and like does the thing,
you're not trying to go mess inside the container anyway.
Yeah.
It's not like a, it's not like a core business tool.
It's how I just want to watch something on my TV and I just want to watch something
on my TV.
Damn it.
You know, now when it goes down, it suddenly becomes a core business tool,
but you know, yeah, right.
No kidding.
Uh, at least for me, but, um, you know, I, so I made those mistakes, fixed them.
And the beautiful thing is, and then I'm all done on this, but the thing I just
effing love about Nix is the moment I realized, yeah, this is probably better
as a container.
I just went and commented out the stuff I added to the Nix config, rebuilt, and it
was like, I never installed Jellyfish.
It was like, it was never there.
It was a totally clean system again.
So nice.
It's so nice.
And then I just went and got the container and it's like, never did that.
Nothing, nothing.
You know, just pretend like I never made that mistake that you can just have
access to this giant array of software that you can just sort of arbitrarily
compose together into different systems whenever you want in different ways,
which everyone works better for me too.
It's such a great platform in that regard.
And you just have to invest the time and, and you have to, you know,
invest the time in educating yourself to figure out which one works right.
And sometimes you just have to do it the hard way, like I did.
Try it one way, but I love that.
And then, and then the thing that makes it so great is I just pick that config
file up, drop it on the new rig, rebuild, off to the races and done.
So it was a real success and getting the Odroid up and going combined with the
compatibility of x86, but the power usage of like a traditional ARM system really
hitting the sweet spot for me.
Hey, good job x86, I guess too, huh?
That's that's impressive.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
That's where you go to get a hundred dollars in 60 day credit for a new account.
And it's a great way to support the show while you're checking out something
pretty great, IE Linode.
Linode is easy to use and powerful cloud hosting.
They have 11 data centers around the world, soon to be like another
dozen over the next year.
But really I think the key thing is that a really solid Linux infrastructure.
They make it super quick to deploy systems and you get to choose from a
very wide range of Linux distributions, pretty much all the great distros.
And there's even guides on how to build it up from the ground up.
We've done that a couple of times for various reasons.
They now also offer bare metal servers and we use the absolute snot out of
their S3 compatible object storage.
That's what's behind our peer tube instance.
That's what's behind our next cloud instance for our team here.
It's just kind of like our go to solution for anything that's going to
sort of have a various amount of data.
I don't want to like slice off this like, like an old caveman or something.
They have a brilliant VLAN support where you can actually bridge different
Linode data centers together, a powerful DNS manager.
They support Kubernetes, Ansible and Terraform.
If you're using that tooling, super fast networking because they are their own
ISP and their pricing is 30 to 50% cheaper than the other major cloud
providers out there.
And they're a true, genuine Linux loving company.
They started because they saw what you could do with VMs and Linux before,
before there ever was an AWS or cloud hosting, as we call it.
And because of that, they built a company around the merits of the product, the
capabilities, the speed, the features, the reliability, and the support.
They have 365, 24 seven support by phone, top tier support when you call them.
Additionally, they have tons of resources on their website.
Just a couple of days ago, they posted a, how to revert your last Git commit
tutorial.
This is really just a tutorial to get you going on Git.
We talk about it all the time here, but what about some practical examples?
How do you actually roll things back when you make a mistake?
They've got an absolutely free tutorial.
It's really nothing Linode specific about it.
It's just about getting you those skills.
And then I think they hope something you'll be able to use on Linode, get even
more out of Linode, I would imagine.
Lots of great tutorials. I'll put a link to this one.
How to revert your last Git commit.
What a great guide.
I'll put a link to that in the show notes.
I love that kind of stuff about Linode.
Great online resources, great technical resources in the company and a website
that I've noticed.
Everyone on our team at various skill levels can use to manage the systems.
It's really fantastic.
And their community support runs super deep as well.
So go get that hundred dollars and support the show.
You go to linode.com slash unplugged.
That's linode.com slash unplugged.
We do have some housekeeping to get to this week.
I think number one, we got to talk about, I promised to try to bring it up earlier
and I'm already sliding on that.
The tuxes are coming up.
So we're getting serious about this year's tuxes and we're looking for people to
help us maybe organize it, work on the submissions, get the questions in better
shape. I have launched a tuxes boardroom.
Put your tuxes on folks. Yeah, get your best on and come join us.
We'll have a link in the show notes if you'd like to join us in Matrix and help us
organize this. Or you can go to bit.ly slash tuxes board and that'll take you there.
Tuxes board. Who doesn't want to go there?
And we'd love to have you join us in there and help make the tuxes the best awards
ever. It's the number one award show.
I mean, we have, you know, out there, there's a lot of really great projects and we
won't help you out there, but we want to make sure that you get the tuxes board.
We won't help trying to try to honor them.
Yeah. Is that next cloud instance?
It's still up, right? I got to start it with a little blank entry.
We can start crafting. Yeah.
So if we could find enemy, we could work on it.
Perhaps somebody feels like they do a better job.
Yeah, definitely possible.
We're already sliding. Then we could give them access to the next cloud instance.
And that's where we have the forum that gets composed over there.
And if you have ideas on things that we didn't get in the tuxes last year, that
should be in the tuxes, you can boost them into the show or you can join that Matrix
chat room and let us know as well.
Now, there is an event going on, kicks off tomorrow as we record and it runs through
the ninth. It's something that we haven't said for a long time.
It's been gone. It's been missing from the community calendar.
And it is the Ubuntu Summit 2022.
It's back. And Brent wanted to get you all, I guess, up to date on it, I guess.
You can't go.
I noticed that there's registration for kind of tuning in remotely.
I don't think all the talks are being streamed, but I think the main room is being
streamed. So they have a bunch of tracks, including the Ubuntu desktop, of course,
which seems obvious, but some community tracks and data science, app ecosystems,
infrastructure, devices and content and design, which is, you know, close to my
heart. And so I just thought, you know, the people should know this is happening.
I know you can go ahead and register right now for some remote viewing stuff.
I wasn't able to find a link right away to where it's going to be streamed, but I'm
sure they've got that all figured out and we'll probably get an email or something
with where it's going to be at. So that's my little PSA.
That's great. There was a possibility the JB team was going to make it, but it just
didn't work out scheduling wise.
So hopefully this will become a trend that they'll keep doing.
It certainly seems like Canonical's really excited about it, and I'm really curious to
see what this new era of celebrating the really awesome Ubuntu community that exists is
like. There's a lot of neat folks in it and participating and helping it grow and, you
know, keep it diverse and active.
It's nice to see these kinds of things showing up more.
I agree. It's something that I'm really happy to see because it brings all the
stakeholders together in a way that can help make the Linux platform better, regardless
of which distribution you're using.
Yeah, message we can all get behind.
I will say, if you are planning on joining in, it is happening in Prague, and so you
might have to check the time zones on that one.
I think if you're in the Pacific Northwest, it starts at like 1 a.m.
tonight. So that's something to take into account.
Just check their calendars.
I'm sure they make it nice and easy for you to figure it out.
It would be great if they posted the videos on something like YouTube so people could
see what it's about. I can tell you just from behind the scenes.
It seems like they're very serious about this.
They're really committed to it, just communicating diligently with us.
And they're clearly trying to bring in as many people as they can and cover a wide
range of topics. I used to love these things.
Yeah. So here's hoping that this becomes an ongoing yearly thing.
And I think it also shows a sign that Canonical is willing to spend real money to
invest in the community, because I have a sense they are flying in a lot of people.
And the cost of that and stay and all of that and the food is just astronomical.
So it's a big commitment.
And then also just a PSA.
We're going to take a look at Fedora 37 next week on the show.
So if you'd like to download it and try it out and join us, join us.
Yeah. You can either listen along with it or join us in the Mumble Room.
Of course, we'll be live noon Pacific, 3 p.m.
Eastern over at Jupiter got to.
And then last but not least, also on our radar, the end of year holiday loves.
They're coming up. You can boost in your prediction or you send an email.
I was thinking people could use 20, 23 sets for their for their predictions.
Oh, I like that.
Go to Linux Unplugged dot com slash contact to send in your predictions to start
collecting some of them and then Brent will read through them and steal a few of them.
Of course. Maybe I will, too.
I'm looking forward to it.
It's been a while because last year, it's been a while since we've done our pre-record
format for them, because last year luck just missed all the major holidays.
But this year we're going to land smack dab, I think, on Christmas or Christmas Eve or
something like that. I believe so.
And then and then New Year's.
Yeah. So there's that's right.
So there's that. Yeah.
So we're going to probably pre-record that so that I'll be coming up on the calendar at
Jupiter broadcasting dot com slash calendar.
But that's why we're putting the word out now.
We need your help. Yeah.
Because it'll be coming up sooner than you'd think since we're pre-recording.
So if you want to get your predictions in, boost them in 2023 with a little prediction.
And you know, we need help if you've listened to any of the previous prediction.
You do know, right?
Seriously, although I think maybe this is what it was my better.
Yeah, you're going to crush it.
Maybe I just don't read it already.
Speaking of boosts, we got one from Mike Piso 1970 and he sent in two hundred and
twenty two thousand two hundred and twenty two I'm a duck.
D.U.K. duck loaded with talent and it's also a big baller music.
Ice is Chris, Wes and Brent.
I've been a listener since episode one hundred and twenty five.
Oh, just a little after you started, Wes.
I usually just listen and then just consume the information.
Rarely do I comment or interact with the hosts of media, but I wanted to give back for all
that I've learned now that the Lightning Network allows me to do so for the first time I've
invested in Bitcoin, changed my podcast app, and I'm finally able to give you call two
thousand two hundred and twenty two a row of ducks.
Well, for my first boost ever, I am sending in you a row of super ducks.
That's where the two hundred and twenty two thousand two hundred and twenty two sats comes
from. Things are looking up for all that duck.
Thank you so much for everything.
Well, Mike, thank you.
Yeah, no kidding.
And Mike, you you don't even realize it, but you also put us at the top of the fountain
hot list for Friday night, Saturday morning.
So we picked up a new batch of listeners thanks to your boost.
That's so amazing.
On top of that, you came in at a really great week because our node was down twice, once
due to a software upgrade and once due to a very long power outage.
And so we missed a lot of boosts.
And so I appreciate that very much.
And this also is the week that John A lost his streak.
Oh, which we still know we we said we we said, yeah, he's welcome.
And he quit boosting. So that tells you something.
But I think he will join us in the studio at some point.
But so thank you very much, Mike.
We really appreciate it. It was sort of the perfect timing, the way it all came together
with your boost and and of course, the generous size of it.
It meant that we picked up some new listeners and I got a note from somebody who said, hey,
I found you in fountain today.
And loving the show. And it's just it's so awesome.
It's such a great thing because a Linux podcast is never going to be at the top of an iTunes
or Spotify chart.
It's never going to be at the top of their store ever.
Well, what about when Joe Rogan's our next guest?
Right. And it's incredible because we're on we're on a list of really, really great podcasts.
And it's it helps people with discovery.
I also love the idea of a new like an old time listener, which also just it's it's it's
also just it's always delightful when, you know, we get to hear from them.
Yeah.
Inspires a new listener to like that's that's just amazing.
It's also it's like price of Bitcoin is going to be low for a while.
It's a great time to experiment.
Sats are cheap.
Experiment.
You know, see how hard it is and play with the different stacks because they're self
hosting involved if you'd like.
And a lot of that.
So it can be a lot of fun.
All right.
So this week, we're three wild and crazy guys.
I have no idea what you all want to talk about.
But I'm really looking forward to these are some of my favorite episodes.
So let's start with Mr. Brentley.
He's been on the road hunting moose and doing family time.
And he's back now in his cottage.
And he's got a topic for us.
Yeah, I am, as some of you might have picked up over the years, a big fan of signal.
And I noticed that there's been kind of a snap signals snafu that happened recently.
There was a the signal snap had a bit of failure on multiple levels that was confusing at first.
But I've dug in and I'm hoping to just kind of touch on it here with the hopes of asking
one or two bigger questions once I'm done explaining what happened.
All right.
OK, yeah, I did hear something about this, like this, like they had to pull the snap
or something from the snap store.
Yeah, as far as I understand, it kind of vanished more so.
And then users who were using the signal snap just saw that it was missing.
And upon investigating with snap list that you can run on the command line, it just indicated
that it was in a snap quarantine, which I had never seen before.
Have you guys seen that before?
I have not.
No, I have not.
So that got me kind of like, oh, well, I like signal and well, snaps can be useful.
And I wonder what happened here.
And it turns out a lot happens.
Mostly a bunch of communication breakdowns from a bunch of different sources.
So those are the communication breakdown between canonical and their volunteer snap maintainer,
Galgalesh or Merlin Sebrecht.
OK, so this is a volunteer maintained signal snap.
Yeah, community maintainer who maintains like an unofficial signal snap, which we've seen
before in, you know, flat hub as well.
Some of these more popular applications are available, but aren't sort of the official
flavor that comes straight from the, you know, for instance, signal developers.
Well, generally, the company doesn't really often even know about flat pack packaging
or snap packaging, or they're not interested in supporting it.
And so somebody in the community is like, well, this is an in-demand app, so I'm going
to step up and I'm going to make sure it's packaged and God bless them.
Yeah.
But sometimes it's like a little bit of a security concern there, too.
I could see, especially with an app like signal.
Yes, it seems signal vanished and users noticed, but the snap maintainer didn't know about
it until they started seeing issues on their issue tracker and also just users saying,
hey, what's going on?
It's kind of missing and they expected to hear from canonical if something would have
changed there.
And so there's this kind of rabbit hole of different information that's a little bit
everywhere that I've tried to put together.
So from what I can tell Marlin, the snap maintainer discovered the problem from users who linked
some snap craft IO forums where users were asking the question, you know, where did the
snap go for a signal?
So Merlin responded, I had to find this out myself from users reporting it on our bug
tracker.
There was an initial communication breakdown between me and canonical due to how the snap
crafters publisher is structured canonical is changing their procedures to make sure
this communication breakdown doesn't happen in the future.
Due to how the snap craft publishers worked canonical was communicating with the wrong
person about the takedown.
They've since amended the process to make sure this doesn't happen anymore.
Now, Daniel Menrique, who works at canonical as a policy reviewer responded.
I have updated the process documentation to be very, very explicit about this.
For future cases, so it sounds like small communication breakdown there that seems understandable
because a huge delay in getting this resolved, but it kind of gets more complex from there.
Okay, so if I'm following they had to do a takedown, they do a takedown, but they don't
know who to notify properly.
So they just do it anyways.
And then through the process of like realizing they didn't notify the right person, they
come up with a new process, which they've now documented, but what's missing for me
is why they had to remove it in the first place.
Why was it so urgent to just rip it out of the snap store?
Well, I'm leading there and the reason I'm making it a bit of a question for you is that
this is exactly how the users felt, so I wanted you to feel exactly how they did.
So there was also a communications breakdown with users.
So at first in some of these threads canonical said the snap store administrators had to
remove the snap in accordance with our policies.
We hope to have it back shortly, and that's kind of all that they wrote in there.
So it was very cryptic, at least from what I can read.
So it turns out that the signal lawyers asked for a DMCA takedown of the signal snap.
And now it's not their official snap offering, so I suppose because of perhaps trademark
issues, that that is definitely something they can do.
Now Merlin, the community maintainer, just wrote a bit more once they did get involved
and dug into it behind the scenes.
This is due to a DMCA takedown request coming from the lawyers representing Signal.
Canonical is currently working with Signal to resolve the issue.
I've suggested to Canonical to be more transparent with DMCA takedown requests, similar to how
GitHub does it.
Last I heard, they were discussing that internally.
Due to how lawyers and legal threats work, Canonical is very hesitant to publicly talk
about what's going on, understandably.
You can expect a thorough postmortem after the legal issues are cleared up.
So I also noticed that Brian Acton actually spoke up about this on Hacker News.
I did not expect to see Brian Acton, the Signal co-founder, leaving a little message there,
which is kind of fun.
He wrote, we spoke to our attorneys and found that there was a breakdown in communication
between us and our attorneys.
We are working to rectify and reinstate the Signal desktop as soon as possible.
Sorry for the confusion.
You don't say.
So the lawyers preemptively went out, discovered this trademark violation, took action on behalf
of their client.
Do they just have like a blank check in which they're operating from?
So that's a good question, you know.
Is that actually the case or is this just them sort of covering their butts a little
bit?
Could be.
The lawyer is always a great one to blame.
I mean, that's part of why you pay them.
But I also could see it being like maybe there's just ongoing trademark protection.
You know, I could see something they would do.
Could be.
Yeah.
I know in the past they've had some issues with having Signal, for instance, in F-Droid
as well.
So there might be a history there that we could dig into a little bit more at some point.
But this whole kind of situation, which is multiple layers of communication breakdowns,
it sounds like, just got me thinking a few questions that I thought we could explore.
And I think the most obvious one is this third party app bundling that's happening for snaps
and also for flat packs.
I just wondered, is it still a good idea?
It was really essential when those platforms and technologies first came to light because,
you know, that's pretty essential to get users on the platforms is to have the apps that
you want to use, like, you know, the commercial ones.
And also, even though this is an open source application, Signal, it still has some trademark
issues there.
So I wondered, now that snaps and flat packs are a bit more mature, should we really have
the original developers be the snap maintainers instead of community members?
I wanted to get your thoughts on that.
Well, but even if snaps are more popular now, or, you know, these types of packages, you
still got to get the maintainers to be interested, right?
Like we wouldn't need it if they were interested in maintaining the snap themselves, we wouldn't
know.
Probably, hopefully none of this would have happened.
Yeah, that seems to be the chicken or the egg problem, isn't it?
And then do you get it on like multiple stores?
Is it going to be snap and flat hubs?
Right.
You know?
Yeah.
And I could see why they're hesitant to commit to that for sure.
I think maybe Canonical has struck the balance here a little better than flat hub has where
they make it pretty clear now after they've had some issues in the past, Thunderbird,
you can see is being published by Canonical.
They make the publisher clear, and then they also have this thing called a verified account.
And then if you go, say, take a look at Slack, here it's very clear that Slack is actually
being published by the Slack group, who has also been verified by Canonical.
And I think that's lessons they learned to try to make that more clear.
But I don't know if A, users are even aware to look for that difference, and B, I don't
know if it really answers the question of what happens when it's something that needs
like significant trust.
Signal comes to mind, maybe like a Bitcoin wallet or something that you would use to
encrypt your files, like something that you want to place a lot of trust into.
Should that be packaged by a third party maintainer?
Or should we only trust it from the original source?
So far in Linux, we've made the trade off and decided, well, the maintainers will do
it.
If you look at a traditional distro, none of the packages in there are generally being
packaged by the upstream person, typically.
For Signal specifically, I've traditionally used their official deb, which seems like
a perfectly fine way to go.
But since we had our summer of immutability, I dove a little bit more into Flatpaks, thanks
to both of you.
And I kind of ran into that issue, which was trying to discover whether it was an official
or not.
And then when I discovered that it wasn't, trying to determine if I should trust these
people or not.
And I tend to love open source and everyone involved as a basic default.
But then the question becomes, well, should I?
And I found that difficult to discover, because you end up going down a rabbit hole and ending
up on the project's GitHub, where there's like three maintainers.
Sometimes there's more than that.
But these are still people that I don't know their association.
So it's a funny little pickle we've got there.
The nature of this whole problem comes down to a very ugly paradox that we don't like
to talk about.
The paradox is, we want all these applications to exist and be available for the medium of
delivery that we need or want to use, but nobody cares.
Because nobody cares, somebody has to do that work in the first place.
And maybe an ISP, because we're going to call them what they are, independent software
vendors.
An ISP will pick some mechanism in which they're going to deliver it, whether it's a tarball,
an app image, an RPM, a deb, or even just like a self extracting shell script, which
is the most horrifying way to do it.
But there you go, they'll pick a method, and it will not be the method you want.
And so somebody has to do that transformation from one method to the other.
And that is never, ever, ever going to stop.
Because there is no incentive for it to stop.
You have tug of wars across all the different dimensions.
So you've got people who are gatekeepers of the software centers, who in the various distributions
will pick one format or the other.
Even if they could enable both, they won't, for either jealousy or ego or because there's
a technical problem or something like that.
And this comes back to a second order of issues that we have, which is that in the open source
space, we have this unwritten contract that there are actually two levels of responsibility
here.
There's the responsibility of the creator of the software, and there's the responsibility
of the deliverer of the software.
With Flat Hub and Snapcraft, Snap Store, I don't know if they have a name for this, but
in those worlds, they're trying to essentially break this contract by saying the person who
creates the code should be the one that delivers the code, in theory.
But they also know that they don't have the pull to do it, and that this also creates
a legal conundrum, because whenever you're delivering software that is not yours, you
are actually taking on legal responsibility and liability.
Again, not a lawyer, can't really, not legal advice, yada, yada, yada.
But generally speaking, if you look at how all this stuff works, the moment you take
a piece of code, whether it's compiled or not, and you do a transformation to deliver
it, you're taking responsibility for that code at some level.
And this is why a DMCA takedown by the signal people elicited the response that it did,
because at the end of the day, whether Canonical likes to admit it or not, and they definitely
don't like to admit to this, they are ultimately publishing every application, and at some
level are legally responsible for every application delivered through the Snap Store.
This is also true for Flathub, at some level they are responsible for every single thing
that's on there.
And if something is wrong, they are the ones in hot water just as much as everyone else,
possibly more so because they're complicit.
There's a whole lot of things that, like, Linux distributions have historically done
quite a lot to avoid that these new age systems don't do.
And because of that, we are going to see a lot more of these kinds of things happening
as that exposure goes up and the proponents of these systems push it harder and harder.
And the end result is going to be, with these new formats, probably what's going to eventually
happen is essentially maintainer bankruptcy.
If it is not delivered by the creator and it is not an open source solution, it is just
going to disappear from all the stores, because the legal risk will go up over time, not down.
Because this unwritten contract of, you don't sue me for making your software available,
will be violated over and over and over.
Oh, you should write this down, Neil.
I feel like this would be a good spicy prediction for our predictions episode.
Oh, yeah.
It's going to keep happening.
Like, Signal has a long and storied history of really not liking redistribution of their
application.
It doesn't matter what platform it is, if it is redistributed by someone else, they're
going to go after you.
Neil, it's just the lawyers.
Neil, just blame the lawyers.
So the lawyers are operating on a directive that exists at the top level that says, this
is a thing we care about.
And you know what?
There's a lot of vendors that are the same way.
Some of them hand wave it away.
Standard practice at certain sizes.
Yeah.
So some vendors hand wave this away.
I know, for example, that TeamViewer, even though their EULA actually forbids redistribution,
they implicitly kind of hand wave it away for Linux people, because they're too small
and nobody cares.
Yada, yada, yada.
Yes!
Sneaking it in.
If you actually read the end user license agreements of virtually every proprietary
software package, you're not allowed to do this.
Yeah.
And that is actually a thing we've all blatantly kind of ignored.
Well that's not, you know, shh.
Yeah.
And so like, this is going to keep, this will keep biting us.
Ironically, as Linux becomes more popular, it will start biting us more.
And so, you know, places like, you know, the infamous third party repos that host non free
software in the various Linux distributions, I'm not going to name names, but we all know
what they are, and the flat hubs and the snap crafts and all these other things in the world,
they're going to get bitten and burned over and over and over again.
And we're going to see a bankruptcy of those things.
Save it for the prediction show.
That's spicy.
I won't, I won't steal it.
That's good.
You own that one.
I think if you guys will allow it, I think Colonel and I should be these guys just for
a moment because not only do I hear the belly aching about Signal getting pulled out of
the Snap store, but I also been hearing a lot of belly aching about them dropping SMS
support and girl, just use Matrix already, right, Colonel?
Just use Matrix.
So one of the things I wanted to say on that is that Matrix is a decentralized program.
You have multiple clients that are all compatible.
You have a distributed network of servers.
There is no one place that it can be taken down, whereas Signal is a centralized proprietary
application with one set of servers, one app, and is, in my opinion, hostile to the open
source community.
Oh, and I would also say is sort of subjective to one large ego who sort of has a vision,
is very particular about that vision.
Moxie Marlin Spike has been very hostile to the open source community, not just Signal,
but also other places as well.
There was an application that in F-Droid that they took the Signal mobile code base, used
the web hook for the desktop application just so that they could have an Android application
that didn't rely on Google services framework.
They went after them hard and basically shut them down.
And that project was willing to work with Signal, was willing to, you know, what do
we have to do to make this okay with you?
And at the end of the day, Moxie, through GitHub comments and whatnot, it's still all
out there.
You can go find it.
He shut them down and said, no, this is basically, he said, it's my project, you'll do it my
way, and I don't want you.
That's the thing.
And before we completely move off the matrix thing, I'll just say, not all matrix is element.
Fluffy chat is very much a Telegram-like experience or Signal-like experience, because I'd say
Signal is even simpler than Telegram.
Fluffy chat is very clean, it's cross-platform, it's GPL3.
And it takes the complexity of matrix and it puts it behind a UI simpler than Telegram.
And if you're on iOS specifically, there's Neo, N-I-O, which has been built with Swift
UI from scratch using all of the iOS design languages.
This is MPL, it's also open source, and it gives a very clean, very minimal messaging
experience.
It's all matrix underneath it.
And the reason why that's powerful is because you could be sitting back with a big old full
scale element client, or you could be on Android with a totally different client, but you can
still communicate.
And they can't pull any one client and they can't pull any one server.
And so it's not just element when we mean matrix, when we talk matrix, it can be these
more purpose-built clients too.
And if you go to matrix.org slash clients, you can see a surprisingly big list of different
clients for different platforms from mobile to desktop to the web.
So matrix.org slash clients for that.
You know, had you presented matrix as an option to replace something like signal maybe a year
ago, eight months ago, I would have said, no way, it's not even close to being usable.
But these days I'm changing my mind on that.
It's actually been really nice.
So I think you guys are onto something here.
Yeah, it's harder when you already have a whole social group on a particular service.
You know, I get it.
Sometimes people move quick though.
Sometimes something comes up and people, they just jump ship.
So when that moment, when that opportunity comes up, be ready.
I also have two, let's call them notes because you guys are all friends here.
As far as I understand the signal desktop is a GPL v3.
So it is open source.
And so the backend service, I don't believe is, maybe that's the distinction.
And I'm pretty sure from what I've been reading that Moxie is not with signal anymore.
So maybe that's a good thing.
So Moxie is not with signal and yes, the client is a Faro GPL, but rebuilds that are not officially
blessed by signal will not be allowed to connect to the signal server.
So it doesn't matter.
Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Go try it for free as an individual.
Or if you're a team, maybe you're in an enterprise, you can get a free trial when you go to bitwarden.com
slash Linux.
Straight up.
I have to be honest with you.
I have tried them all.
And Bitwarden I have found to be the best and easiest way to store, share and sync your
sensitive data.
And I love that Bitwarden is open source.
It's trusted by millions of individuals, teams, open source projects, organizations and more
for all their secure passwords, storage.
And when you do have to share that stuff, also Bitwarden helps you there too.
In fact, it's really the only way you can feel safe kind of moving that sort of stuff
around the internet between individuals.
You don't want to write it down on a sticky note.
Wes and I have been using it personally for years.
I think Wes longer than I have.
And Bitwarden has been rolling out great features like account switching in the mobile app or
fast mail and DuckDuckGo integration so you can use a unique email address with every
site or service or app that you're signing up with as well as a secure password, as well
as a unique username.
I mean, that's really, you can just layer on the security there.
And I noticed Bitwarden just recently posted a great tutorial.
So I always like to keep my eye on the stuff for you guys because, you know, why not leverage
this and just get even more, I guess, secure because they have Bitwarden CLI, of course.
Yeah, that's right.
They have a command line version of Bitwarden and you can use this and pop in your passwords
in your shell when you need to like log into something on the command line.
You can leverage Bitwarden CLI and shell functions to create simple workflows that just allow
you to unlock your secrets into environment variables whenever you need without requiring
you to hard code your secrets into your dot files.
How nice is that?
Especially if you want to move them around between machines.
So Bitwarden CLI could be a really great tool for your tool chest.
Is that the phrase?
I'll put a link to the guide in the show notes so you can check it out and see if it'll work
for you.
But go over to bitwarden.com slash Linux to support the show or send it to somebody you
know that could use better password management.
Maybe a friend, a family member, place of work, open source project, you know they're
out there.
Send them to bitwarden.com slash Linux.
It'll be worth their time and you know it's the best way for them to stay secure online
too.
Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
All right Mr. Payne, so what would you like to share with the class this week?
Yeah, I just wanted to send a little love to Godot, the cross-platform free and open
source game engine.
It's MIT, don't you know, launched in January 2014.
And it's one of those really special projects I think because you know in the game making
ecosystem there's just not that many great tools that I mean you might be able to get
it for free or use it but that's you know some student or creator license or you know
if you make any serious money they're going to want to cut or you're going to spend a
whole bunch of money on all these assets through their system.
They don't do any of that?
No, no.
They're trying to make a project that has a big set of common tools so you can just
focus on making your game you don't have to like you know shell out and use a whole bunch
of go find all the top leading industry applications that you're going to need to do your audio
stuff and to go make your graphics and of course you can do that and import stuff if
you want.
But Godot's trying to make like a friendly you know you're learning about how to get
into games.
I mean you can use it for serious games too but with a holistic approach that lets you
really have everything you need under one roof.
Looks like they just had a brand new beta release just a couple days ago too.
Yeah 3.5 came out in August which was really nice and they're working on a 4.0 they're
in the beta steps right now and that that's got some well that's got a lot of promising
stuff and you know you can you can export native Linux games just you know right from
Godot so they're platform friendly for us you can target Android you can target Web
Assembly it runs on Linux as well as of course you know a bunch of other platforms you can
compile it for BSD if you want to or run it on Windows or Mac.
Yeah there's even a web editor.
If you want to go crazy there's a web editor.
It's interesting you bring this up because okay so they just released a new beta a couple
of days ago and then a couple of days before that they moved to a new foundation.
They did yeah.
Okay so as I mentioned they started way back in 2014 you know just a couple of people who
were trying to pack together a game engine in 2015 they joined the SFC and SFC provided
them you know a foundation structure a way to sort of take donations from projects because
you know they'll sometimes get sponsorships from game studios or you know various other
players in the industry and you need legal frameworks you need processes you need accountants
who can help you like do those things and it's but it's been you know I think both parties
have been really happy with it it's maybe a good example of what the SFC can do for
open source projects is you know let them start to hire people part-time eventually
start to hire people and support them full time to work on Godot but at this point you
know Godot has really taken off it's grown a lot and so they're launching their own foundation
now and they're they're pitching this as it's a it's a graduation from the SFC to launch
their own foundation they're trying to take a lot off of how blender does it I think we've
all been pretty pleased you know I don't know that they're perfect but as far as foundations
go it seems like blenders got a good a good foundation in order so that gives me some
hope that you know they are part of this is does seem to be that they want to mix up the
different approaches that they can have you know maybe tailor some things to a thing that
would make sense for Godot that didn't make sense for all the projects under the SFC umbrella
so they're thinking maybe they're going to have crowdfunding campaigns like like blender
or Krita do they're talking about maybe setting up something that lets users start to sell
assets for an asset library and integrate that in maybe sell merchandise or you know
just get a little more flexibility with sponsoring events or having events how might you fund
that or try to get fly people in to be there so there's a lot going on and it's just it's
really easy to get started with they've got a python like scripting language like Godot
script that's built in oh okay you can also use c-sharp if you already know c-sharp so
that's that's supported right out of the box I think you can even use c++ or rust or you
know there's some like community supported versions too yeah yeah you can use rust with
it okay that sounds like a really cool pic or it's not a pic but I guess it's a it's
a cool subject to bring to the class I guess but I'm curious why it's on your radar are
you are you fooling around with making a game I've dabbled a little bit yeah well so it's
actually I've been trying to help my brother is very creative in this aspect and he you
know he's he's a big gamer he likes these things plays D&D and you know isn't just sort
of crafting all the different aspects of a game and so I've been trying to help him he's
learning some and that's been a fun adventure for me to sort of sit alongside and as he's
learning the technical side and I'm trying to support him there and fun this path of
Godot yeah he found it Godot Godot he actually found it first I'd heard of it you know I'd
followed it and looked at the looked at the news but it was so neat because you know he's
got I do I did give him a Linux laptop a couple years ago that he does use but he's using
it on his main sort of Windows gaming PC but it didn't matter like I could just load his
project in and make some updates like oh maybe try doing it this way and share it back with
him and he could load it up on Windows no problem so that's powerful yeah it's been
it's been a really nice fun and now I'm an expert I haven't made any fancy games yet
or anything but there's a lot of tutorials out there there's a strong community on on
YouTube of creators who are you know sharing you walking you through except got example
project files you can download so it seems super accessible before today I was aware
of it but I think in the back of my mind I thought it was like like using go for creating
games mm-hmm I didn't really would be a good name for it that's why I thought it was Godot
the Godot and I think in the past they were had a little more limited scope it seemed
like maybe it was better focused on like 2d games and stuff but these days they've got
you know rich 3d capabilities you can make VR applications if you want you can publish
to WebAssembly you can publish for all the mobile platforms like it seems like you know
if you're not a professional you're trying to just learn or explore you could go a long
way with Godot before it was gonna be your limitation you know what I like about their
website seeing a lot of tux the penguin mm-hmm and I'm seeing a lot of open source stuff
on here I'm seeing the open source logo seeing open source listed as one of their main features
great that is really slick well thanks for telling us about that mm-hmm so I wanted to
share with you guys a little thing a little trend that I've noticed and I know some of
our community members have because I've seen it getting discussed in our matrix kind of
recently and that is since Elon's announcement that he's taking over Twitter you know that
rough timeline we are seeing reports of just massive user gains for Mastodon 70,000 users
joining in the last couple of weeks is one of the numbers I've seen going around I know
I've heard it on some you know NPR type segments other news coverage people it doesn't get
a lot of play but its name is thrown out there CNN CNN headline from CNN updated yesterday
with Twitter in chaos Mastodon is on fire this is from your CNN news here and this is
the bit this is the bit that I noticed that I thought was pretty interesting they say
the service speaking about Mastodon the service has a similar look to Twitter with a timeline
of short updates sorted chronologically rather than algorithmically it lets users join a
slew of different servers run by various groups and individuals rather than one central platform
controlled by a single company like Twitter Instagram or Facebook now isn't that interesting
that that is one of the things they decided to kind of emphasize to the audience there
it's decentralized nature and I I don't think that you know Twitter's dead and Mastodon's
gonna take over anything like that but I find it interesting and I'm curious to know what
you think about these open source projects that build and build and build for years and
years and we know about them we hear about them and they kind of hover and they and they
have some users and we kind of keep them alive as the enthusiasts and we kind of use them
a little bit but then every now and then something breaks in the world and the normals hear about
one of these things has been around for years and they rush in and all of a sudden a project
just has tens of thousands of more users and there's tons more instances going along it's
a fascinating phenomena what do you attribute that to that it's like just wasn't good enough
to replace the main thing until well you know you've got that you've got the network effect
you know what do you need it what do you need a harder to figure it out harder to set up
you got to make some choices to pick your instance sort of system if you you know you're
already on the functionally the one instance everyone cares about I wondered is uh is the
poll hitting do you guys feel like it's time to join the mastodon or get on get on a mastodon
if you're not I am curious again you know I've never I don't know that I've ever actually
set it up I have you know followed it for a while but yeah what about you Brent Lee
are you getting the mastodon urge at all well the first time I got curious was when I was
in Alan Jude's basement doing a brunch with him and he said hey are you a Fediverse guy
and uh so I looked into it a little bit um but these days I feel like it's almost irresponsible
not to at least check it out a little bit I was just not interested in any more social
media like telegram twitter matrix several others that I can't think of off the top of
my head those are sufficient for me I didn't really want to add another one so I just sort
of said no then when the podcasting 2.0 stuff came along and they had a mastodon to just
talk about podcasting 2.0 it all of a sudden made a ton of sense because it was like a
niche category they're talking about app development namespace development they're you know hashing
out what the new standards should be for things and it's like people discussing podcasting
you know something like okay I'll join that that makes a ton of sense so I do have a mastodon
account but it's on a very specific instance and you're not really using the sort of federation
aspect no am I missing something because I love the matrix federated aspect but matrix
seems to really fill this this hole for me but I wonder if it is the time to have like
is it is it time to have a JB mastodon or should I just be joining somebody else's mastodon
what is the protocol there are mastodon servers a pain in the butt to run I know you looked
a little bit into setting it up didn't seem that hard I mean there's some you know official
containers out there and such this is exactly the conversation we had around matrix and
what is the size of that box running these days okay fair we did it's on like a 48 core
rig now yeah we also made some mistakes that maybe we've learned from yeah we have to find
out you kind of want to set one up don't you what is wrong with you what is wrong with
you I mean I kind of be down I suppose what's the point of having a system you can run yourself
if you don't at least try but then what happens if I already have an account I have an account
on mastodon I believe there's a way to migrate I don't know I don't know how easy that is
and then also I know like the peer tube instance is a sense is also part of that federation
it's very confusing to me if you've created an a mastodon presence on one home server
and decide you want to migrate to another there's in in pretty much every mastodon I
should say every activity pub Twitter clone like implementation so that's basically what
this is yeah in their account UI you can transfer your your account to another to another account
that you have created and it'll basically create a forwarding address and so all of
your followers will move in theory all of your followings will move it'll create a continuity
between your posts all that other fun stuff so picking one is not a forever choice if
you don't like your home server at some point in the future you can jump ship if your home
server is now broken and you want it and you need to move somewhere else you can do that
too so would it be weird see I think what we probably should have done with matrix is
we should have set up matrix and just left it to the JB people and then everybody else
uses matrix.org to create their account and join our server that was one of the mistakes
I was thinking about earlier that's what the tux digital folks did with their system was
they didn't they only allowed people to create accounts on the tux digital server when they
were creators of the network so I wonder is the solution with mastodon to do the same
it's more scalable that way because like matrix mastodons underlying system works off of synchronizing
events via a pub sub mechanism activity pub and matrix behave very similarly even though
they're different standards and so you have the same kind of resource constraints and
performance constraints so yeah you probably want to create a lockdown mastodon server
that only y'all are using and then everyone else just kind of connects with you through
their own I mean part of the whole federated benefits right I mean just have our own and
then connect out to all our friends but the important part is to make sure that your your
server is discoverable right like if it's not then all of that doesn't matter what I
like about it is it's sort of like it's our own form of verification because we'd have
an at Jupiter broadcasting.com domain it's like you'd know it really is us and you know
we don't have to have any blue checkmark that's eight bucks a month it's just we have our
own domain name I like it I think one question I would have is what can it provide that our
matrix instance and use of it for the last six plus months wouldn't provide well I suppose
there's people that are on the mastodon fediverse that aren't in matrix you could follow them
there is an argument for matrix to be used for real-time discussion and something else
to be used for more longer term stuff that people can post and come back to at all different
hours and review in a feed on their own schedule right I mean because one I mean I suppose
like that the Twitter style things are used for different purposes by different groups
and all that but one of them is a sort of like broadcasty or musing or you know whatever
jokes things that you wouldn't really put necessarily in like a public channel unless
you were very social about it the more we talk about it the less I want to do it I really
do it's just I hate social media so much but then I remember like except for this is selecting
for very high quality signal like the open source community the free software community
and in particular the JB audience which this would skew towards is higher than average
signal so then it does make it more worth it again and so here's the thing to think
about right so activity pub the underlying protocol that what we call mastodon where
some would use called pluroma or some of these other ones right that underlying protocol
is not just used for Twitterati style messaging it's also used for things like blogging so
I believe what's it right freely is an activity pub based blog platform and there are a few
others out there and basically one thing you can do is to combine long form and short form
in such a way that somewhat you would post on on a system attached through activity pub
and someone could comment on it through this and then you wind up having this federated
mechanism of connecting these two so having and and again this same address can exist
in different solutions at the same time because again the activity pub publishing address
is what matters here so for example Chris last at Jupiter at Chris last at Jupiter broadcasting
.com I really hate the scheme that they picked correctly yeah it's really done but all right
put that aside that address could be both a blogging platform where you are writing
about or blogging or whatever because peer tube is also activity pub oriented right and
all these things connect and as you're using a singular identity to publish as everyone
else can see them and they can reply to them which turn into comments and visible feeds
and things of that nature and then you wind up having this interconnected relationship
and this goes for like pixel fed as well right the the federated image hosting thing that
also operates on activity pub and I've noticed that a little bit I've already noticed some
activity pub cross publishing with peer tube and that is pretty powerful activity pub is
designed for multiple forms of transmission from a single identity whereas the matrix
protocol is designed for real-time communication or at least a facsimile of it across across
a single identity across different servers and things like that with a single identity
so the idea is with activity pub you take these disparate services and you connect them
to a unified identity and different types of content are published with that identity
and everything weaves together and clients that respect these different types of events
process them correctly so if you're looking at a federated blog viewer or if you're looking
at a Twitterati style client or if you're looking at you know a photo gallery Pinterest
style thing or whatever right the idea of activity pub is that you have a coherent singular
identity that can have all these multiple forms of content and then the clients will
interpret that and do what you will with it whereas with matrix you're just talking about
you know you have a dedicated purpose these features are being built around a particular
single method of communication and you're supporting that mechanism with its clients
and servers so that's where the core difference is like yeah that's a good distinction to
make you're not going to see matrix do like image galleries I mean technically I suppose
you could do that but like nobody's like going out there and doing that whereas activity
pub that's a very real thing you would do all right so let me know everyone out there
what your thoughts are on if you're feeling the pull towards Mastodon I would go if there's
enough audience there I think it'd be something I consider like to hear your thoughts on it
MJVC wrote in just wanted to report that I've been successfully using NixOS on the Steam
Deck as a desktop replacement dual booting SteamOS and NixOS gives me the best of both
worlds there are a few hiccups with the touch screen but aside from that it works pretty
flawlessly that is really cool on the Steam Deck oh man I replied very quickly saying
tell us how we want to do this so we might have an update coming soon and I wonder is
it plasma or are you using GNOME tell me tell me tell me good question I think this is more
of a teaser than a you know full description so I'm gonna wait for the update and we'll
come back on that five also wrote in about NixOS surprise surprise I have an idea you
keep saying Chris that you don't want to pollute Linux unplugged with too much NixOS well we
did it again this week didn't we well I agree I think NixOS is so vast that maybe you can
start NixOS unplugged that's what we need we need another show just what you asked for
what we'll do is we'll just geek out and then we'll just surface the best of we'll condense
it down and just really bring you the nuggets from time to time right is that what our that
you like that plan is that so I think so all right let's go with that and now it is time
for the boost so the first boost we're gonna get to this week is actually follow up on
a boost that was sent in from Neve a couple of weeks ago who offered to send us an arc
GPU from Intel incredibly generous so we wrote back and said no but we'll borrow it for a
little bit and guess what it's right it's here we have it right here it showed up the
ASRock Challenger ITX Intel arc a380 I'm gonna open her up here there's there's actually
a pie in the box I actually have not opened it so if there is or a bomb we're gonna stream
it live we will find out I would be not what I want but not like totally disappointing
I think that might be our version of a rickroll at this point I don't know there's a there's
an envelope in here you know I feel like we should do the Johnny Carson thing so we'll
read the tracks oh here it is this week died doing what we love now if you're the best
aka Josh the best look at this look at this beautiful card oh there's a there's a thumb
drive in here okay what you know better than to put it strange thumb trap there's a thumb
drive I wouldn't that be fun tempting well maybe we'll find out in the members feed we'll
figure out what's in the thumb drive but yeah this check it out Wes that's a compact little
card the a380 is doesn't look bad though and I imagine our or I think our Thalia order
is gonna go in Monday morning I've been dragging I've been so busy I haven't got around to
it that's how you was you want to savor that click you know when you actually hit the order
to you I mean the right state of mind glass of champagne in hand I I've come I think with
a really reasonable build I think it's a very reasonable build of the Thalia and I'll share
it when we get it but that's going in there okay take it out let's pull it out let's pull
it out oh yeah yeah that is beautiful Intel thank you thank you for making this Intel
finally look at the fan on that thing hold that up a little bit there West so we can
look at it yeah look at that thing it's got a almost like a hundred almost probably not
quite as big as a hundred and twenty millimeter fan on the top of it yeah but one big fan
so hopefully me there we go yeah it really moves good job Wes you got it you gotta do
a fan test that's gotta do a fan test leader of the mind Wes blows across the fan to prove
to the listener it's really there we got one HDMI three display ports here nice little
plugs it ships with I mean it's not quite that it's almost half the length of a new
Nvidia card it's not quite but it is stout it's wide and stout it's nice so we'll throw
that in the new Thalia and through throw it through its paces and hopefully we'll see
hopefully get OBS going with that is it up to the challenge will it meet our needs it's
not ready yet OBS I think just is I saw the pull request go in to turn on quicksync video
stuff for for free codecs and support for the new generation of the Intel arc stuff
like like the last week so I don't I don't think that that's a thing for a little while
building OBS from source again we're back here yep also just a couple days ago Michael
Arbrol reported that you need an Intel ME enabled system to update the GSC firmware
on the arc right now so that means a it's got to be an Intel system to even update the
firmware and be you need Intel ME enabled which I don't know what that means for the
Thalia but since we're only borrowing it it's not the end of the world for us but it's something
weird clearly clearly a new product but that's okay yeah on system 76 machines the management
engine is turned off so that's gonna be a problem yeah well I mean like I said if I
was gonna if I was buying this forever's yes but since we just want to test it and we're
willing to do a little bit of the grunt work to make that work I don't actually know if
the system 76 things give you the ability to turn it on you should tell us when you
get the paleo whether they give you an option to turn it back on yeah well I'll also try
a firmware update if there is one just to see what happens hopefully I don't think it
would break it right all right now Chris do you know how long you have this for is there
like a loaner expiry date have you come to some agreement there um so basically in and
you know until I were done I guess you didn't really say I don't intend to keep it too long
you know a few years you know no big deal you know just just a few years it sounds great
okay update I guess Intel reached out to say that firmware updating will work on AMD platforms
I just don't think all the details of like what weird app you have to run or how exactly
that will work okay so it will work well the good news it's only 120 ish dollars so you
know if Chris breaks it he can afford to pay the guy back we'll take it out of Brent sets
all right night 62 boosted in with 40 96 sats this is my first boost I use the blue wallet
I'll be combination so blue wallet to get the sats and then I'll be as the lightning
wallet the idea of setting up my own lightning node seems very appealing but I found that
the setup is actually working really easy I loving that I can just give some value this
way now here's a question about Nix OS versus ansible on other distros can you go deeper
into what makes Nix so much better in your opinion couldn't a well-documented ansible
setup do most of the same things I'd also love to hear more about the next package manager
on other distros does this replace ansible it's a great question because we get this
one a lot and I don't think the position of the show is one is better than the other to
make that clear and ansible is obviously gonna support a lot wider range a combination of
devices services hardware distributions software in general and we use ansible here so it's
not like we're anti ansible I think what I explained earlier today with the setup I was
doing where I you know just took a config file off my laptop and dropped it on my Odroid
very different systems very different hardware and I just rebuilt and I had a fully functional
system without having all of the overhead of also having ansible and having to understand
how to write a playbook and manage all of that it's just basically some yaml and you
can almost always find an example and it's there's a simplicity if you're only using
Nix it doesn't really work so great outside of that you could use the Nix package manager
just about anything but yeah I like I use it on my work Mac love it yeah they're super
super helpful yeah I think it's better than brew in most cases so I think the other part
too is you're right like ansible super flexible you can you know use it all kinds of different
places it's trying to solve problems that Nix is not primarily targeted at there's a
lot of differences because ansible is a big tool and Nix also is a big tool then especially
between Nix and Nix OS but the other part is I think for you at least from what we've
talked about kind of wanted to get away from those other distros right like okay if I if
I use ansible I might not have to think about as much because I wrote that playbook in itself
but like you're still using apt under the hood or things like that like Nix is a much
more holistic for the things it works for you've got this package and system that all
feels tightly together and lean and mean and not just sort of bolted on top to try to pack
paper over some of the limitations of the base system yeah I think you nailed it and
you and I both just trend towards a preference for very simple servers minimum viable server
nothing more than it needs to be and and then because you and I apparently are masochists
when we can we also make them rolling because if you keep it simple and you appropriately
separate applications and data and you've got good backups and snapshots I actually
think the best experience in Linux is a very modern system I wouldn't say cutting edge
because there's some stuff in Nix it isn't super cutting edge but and that that all has
worked really well without having all of the ansible overhead so yes you put it very well
well our next boost comes from Caspeeland with 3690 sats b-o-o-s-t just a simple message
but this time I hope the boost in streaming sets will help you podcasters good to see
you again costs mm-hmm thank you very much ah another favorite of ours wait all boosters
are our favorites but it's rusta casta versa boosted in with 1000 sets and calling out
something that I think we all noticed and appreciated big mumble room energy on the
intro last week yeah so hey thanks mumble room it was really painful not to be here
last week and having that strong intro knowing that you were here to support Chris that that
helped a lot I was yeah also a big shout out to Neil in there specifically in the whole
mumble room was just great I think they had my back you know because you guys are both
out Brent on his secret mission to moose hunt and you with the sick and so to have them
just there with my back was great but the funny thing was is literally everybody internally
on our internal chat like that was the first comment that mumble intro energy yeah totally
killed it it was great so thank you very much I will say we also did get some feedback specifically
saying that Neil was very much enjoyed last episode so thanks Neil for for filling in
for us well I don't know how to take that I guess thanks I don't know I don't know how
to answer that he's blushing tater boosts in with 2050 sets tater says coming in hot
with the boost we love that one that's my favorite I feel like tater took my advice
I said you don't have to write us something profound to kick off a huge discussion just
send us the boost for support because we love those thank you very much tater well nor
Kyle geek wrote something profound hello nor cocky with 8080 sets you're doing a good job
hey I know I'm a few weeks behind but I wanted to put in my two cents on the butter fs discussion
I mean we're always talking about butter fs so I think you're right on time I'm currently
using open Sousa micro OS desktop as my daily driver micro s is an immutable OS which uses
butter fs snapshots instead of OS tree like silver blue does for me it's been a rock solid
the updates apply every time and I haven't had to break or roll back yet that's a W for
butter fs to me I agree and I think open Sousa too and one of the things that they point
out here is they're using it as the desktop daily driver and to have that kind of rock
solid performance that is a win that is super nice we spent a period of time between distros
we spent some time with open Sousa and I played with the immutable version for a little bit
on a cm4 and we set up a jellyfin server on it and we all kind of added a bunch of different
stuff to it and I was really impressed I really was again there's a lot of OS there and we're
more of a minimum viable OS type guys but it's a great OS it is that yeah I think it
could be you know it seemed very administratable you know designed with that kind of in mind
which can appreciate when things when things go wrong user 720 also wrote in with a hundred
cents gif gif let's hold a boost ballot here's a hundred sats on gif wow then gif is winning
right now we'll find out next yeah that's it right there right I guess okay who are
we to stand in the way pull over yeah so far gifts the winner maybe it only takes a hundred
sets maybe it's settled maybe it's not JPC also boosted in with 22,222 sets love the
show by the way I'm using boost CLI just like that awesome it's the new by the way I use
arch right they kind of well it is more technical than setting up arch yeah maybe you want to
set it up by about a mile I am so impressed JPC thank you also for the for the generous
but yeah but also boost CLI is a serious badge of honor you have mastered multiple layers
of the stack and you are very impressive thank you for the boost I I haven't even got that
working yet and I've been playing around with Bitcoin for 13 years and I haven't even gotten
that working yet so give me a break all right maybe maybe 11 years anonymous boosted in
with a thousand sats just to say regarding caring about if the art is generated from
AI when I'm looking at it I'm looking at it not because of the artist I'm looking at it
because it's beautiful much like diamonds even when they're created in the lab they're
still beautiful they're still art you know we got a couple of people that actually wrote
it and said they would listen to AI generated versions of the show well how do they know
they're not listening right now to that how do they know we need to generate some more
stills how do we do this oh yeah we do need to yeah I'm running out of project I'm running
out of stills but I do we have the GPU power anywhere or do we spin up another one I don't
know you tell me I do not know we also got a bunch of boosts that either had no message
or they were streaming sats so we don't cover all of them so that way we can keep this tight
enough but I do just want to do a couple of shout outs 250 sats from tepulus 500 sats
from code Michael and 100 sats from now science news thank you to them thank you to everyone
who boosted and even if you didn't make it on the show and of course to all the ones
who do make it on the show if you'd like to participate in the grand experiment you can
get a new podcast app at new podcast apps calm we're building a network of people that
are armed with sats and we're starting to see a couple of open source projects come
on but we're also seeing a lot of podcasters come online and I think this is a critical
moment in podcasting I think we are witnessing West what was the one you were listening to
recently where they had just these horrible dynamic inserted ads yeah I think it was the
Conan O'Brien podcast yep and it was like it was one of those gambling you know platform
sports betting kind of things and then after the ad it was this supercut and slightly tight
and and sped up sped up yeah like 1.25x speed without me doing the ad but just of the ad
and them doing all the disclaimers state by state for the different hotlines if you have
a gambling problem which that's good people should get help but like it was a solid 30
seconds and I was like I just was trying to listen to the podcast I don't mind a little
ad because most of his ads are kind of like you're you know like yeah they're funny and
they're like organic this was just garbage well you know what they do is so when when
revenue dips and this is going to be happening more and more is you just turn to the dynamic
ads it's kind of like monetizing on YouTube and I just not the direction to go and there
is it's there somehow they made them worse than radio ads which is what's remarkable
is like you would never thought it was going to happen in podcasting and I hate to see
this happening and I feel like we're building an alternative with podcasting 2.0 and the
value for value stuff so I'm hoping that this is an idea that spreads and if you'd like
to participate new podcast apps calm if you're in the States and you want to grab some stats
really easy the cash app and the strike app make that super easy to do the cash app just
recently added lightning support so there's a major vendor on lightning now hey yo and
then if you're outside the states blue wallets and robosats and others are great ways to
go now we're running kind of long so we're going to skip the pics this week so why don't
we mention that we will be live next week we are doing our fedora 37 review we'd love
to have you join us for that that's at Jupiter dot tube we usually kick off the stream a
little bit before noon pacific 3 p.m. eastern over there so get your browser fired up or
your VLC client or your MPV head over to Jupiter dot tube and help us peer out the stream see
you next week same bad time same bad station we need like a phrase for that like when you're
when you're helping seed the stream is that it because it's all peer-to-peer it is all
peer-to-peer and so it lets us run our own YouTube basically right we're not paying our
big CDN bills up and it's part of the federation it's a powerful set of tooling I love it self-hosted
value for value self-hosted live streaming self-hosted live interaction you know like
just love it self-hosted Twitter self-hosted and masks on you know I don't know maybe let
us know what you think thank you so much for tuning this week's episode of the unplug
program links to what we talked about today at Linux unplug comm slash what 484 384 you'll
figure it out figure it out see you next week
I have a question and I am very afraid of what the answer is gonna be but I think I
know what it's gonna be I think my car has a blown head gasket not my not my car but
my wife's car has a blown head gasket oh typically if you think that it does it probably does
here's the symptoms I'm seeing we're using we've we not always but we've had to refill
the coolant a couple of times but there's no dripping oh and the catalytic converter
is clogged up oh oh god I did a ob2 port scan and I noticed that bank one is running rich
and it's adding fuel especially at low idles it's adding like 16% fuel and then on the
freeway doing like 2% and I'm thinking like okay so coolants gone not rapid coolant but
a little bit of coolant thinking running rich thinking clogged cat does it report like
compression on each cylinder as well do you have that kind of detail you know I didn't
see that look for it I think that's a good that would be a key indicator huh I think
I'm gonna bring it in and find out I like our impromptu car talk segment here yeah little
car talk little Linux core talk before cars are computers pop up a pop Prince garage well
cars are computers yeah they were especially this one let me tell you Chris did you try
a last-minute upgrade see if that fixes it right