I guess screw the rest of August, it's almost time for Halloween.
So Humble Bundle has got some pretty good priced Linux games out.
Yeah, I'm surprised this isn't coming out in October.
I know.
Well, and weren't you just telling me about a sale for a Steam game on Linux 2?
It's like for sale.
Hell of a sale.
It's like free, right?
Yeah, it's free.
Yeah.
What was it called?
Shadow Warrior?
Yeah, Shadow Warrior.
Yeah, so you have the Humble Spooky Bundle, which is available for 13 days, and then Steam's
got the Shadow Warrior game for free right now for Linux users.
Actually, I think the best game on the Humble Bundle is actually Alien Isolation.
Alien Isolation.
Is that available for Linux?
Yes.
That would be awesome.
Yes, it is.
Alien Isolation, huh?
That sounds cool.
Discover the true meaning of fear in Alien Isolation.
It's based on the Aliens series.
Yeah.
It looks interesting.
Supposedly I saw a review that was saying that the story mode of it is fantastic.
Yeah, it is.
Really?
Oh, guys.
It's pretty intense, too.
Might be worth the bundle right here.
Here, I'm going to watch a little bit of the trailer.
This might be...
Oh, it's a Sega game.
Yep.
Okay.
All right.
I already love it.
The graphics look great.
Good sci-fi graphics.
Yeah, it's a AAA title.
Oh, this looks super creepy.
It's about your mother.
Oh, I'm getting this.
Yeah.
I'm probably going to be playing that on Halloween.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 211 for August 22nd, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that really wished more cars were
running Linux these days.
Yes, I mean it.
My name is Chris.
That's your cue there.
Oh, hello.
Yeah.
Hello, beard.
I thought normally where Wes would jump in, we're going to have the beard jump in.
Now that worked out.
I actually thought you'd be filling in for me sooner than you'd be filling in for Wes.
You know, I can just fill in for everyone and do the show alone.
You probably could.
That's some sort of beard superpower.
Would you cut yourself to reply to the answers or would you just work two mics?
Have you thought that through?
I mean, I figured I'd just put the mics together and have this nice stereo warbly sound.
Well, while I'm still here, I'm going to try to put together a great show for everybody
today.
I'm going to give you just a quick update on the solar eclipse trip I went on, but then
then there is a rumor that some solar is powered.
Maybe maybe actually.
I already don't believe it.
OK, all right.
What about what about rumors about Ubuntu Budgie Edition shipping on hardware?
What about that?
No, that's that's that sounds crazy.
Crash plan users got screwed this week.
We'll cover what Linux users can do to move off of there.
There is an app based around Electron that, well, it may be a line too far.
Even for me, Chrome OS is coming for Linux in the enterprise.
There's a great way to generate your bash files.
Ubuntu is showing every other distribution how it should be done.
We've got some interesting conundrums from Firefox and Plex, and then we'll wrap it all
up with something that's so amazing.
It's probably going to change your life.
And it's based on the real engine for and it's essentially the Oasis.
If you have a ready player one, prepare to have your entire life sucked away.
You're welcome.
We'll tell you more about that.
Yes, of course, it runs on Linux.
Of course it does.
We'll tell you more about that, though, as this here show goes on.
Beardsley, what's up?
We must go no further.
We must welcome in our virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Greetings.
Hello.
Pip, pip.
It is nice to see some of you in there.
We have a lower showing today, and I would imagine it's probably because Wes isn't here.
Since everybody's like, screw it, I'm not showing up.
Well, usually people show up for the beers Wes brings.
Yeah, well, and they knew he wasn't coming somehow, even maybe before we even knew.
Well, he probably matches them first.
So yeah, I just got back hours ago, actually, from going down and seeing the Tote Solar
Eclipse 2017 of the Heart in Oregon.
And it was pretty great.
Bumped into a listener down there who is a Linux user.
Didn't bump into another listener I expected to, but I bumped into somebody that I didn't
expect to, and that was great.
We chatted a little bit about all the crazy things going on in Linux right before the
solar eclipse hit, which was pretty neat.
And drove down there in one long, just crazy six hour, seven hour-ish.
There was a lot of traffic getting down there.
And got down there, slept in the car, woke up, and then we had to take care of a few.
There were some challenges that we faced.
Took care of all that, bumped into the listener, had a good chat, saw the eclipse, then hightailed
it back up here so that way we could do Linux Unplugged this week.
So there you go.
I'll give you, I'm going to give, I'll do the whole story on my vlog, eventually.
Yeah, I was going to say.
I think you can get the full story.
I got to edit it all together.
There was some pretty good stuff going on.
And of course I managed to actually end up with a few of my own really amateur shots
of the eclipse, so that's pretty cool.
And I had the drone up in the sky during the eclipse.
And your eyes still work.
As far as I know, although sometimes I think it takes a while for it to set in, so you
never know.
But having the drone up in the sky during, it wasn't, you know, I wasn't really watching
it because I was watching the eclipse, but it really shows you how dark it got down there.
That's a crazy progression.
Yeah, yeah.
We're showing it in the video version, a progressive shot that was taken down from Oregon.
There is, it was pretty neat.
It was a pretty cool event.
It's so impressive in person to see something like that.
Yeah, I'm really glad I made it.
And I only got to say hi to a couple of people, but I'm glad that we were able to say hi.
So that was, I think our next meetup will be here at the studio again.
I think maybe we'll do like an end of summer barbecue soon.
We're going to do another one of those.
I was thinking too about maybe doing a raffle.
I got to look into the details around that, but maybe taking some Jupiter broadcasting
gear and raffling it off during the next barbecue.
So I got a few ideas.
So that'll be, we'll have another meetup soon.
And then eventually, eventually, so that way I can start prepping for the 2024 eclipse,
I'll make trips over to the East coast.
And if I hold up to my promise, I'll eventually make it across the pond too.
I have one question for you, Chris.
Were the crowds as crazy as you expected?
Yes and no.
So getting down out of Washington was a nightmare and it was super packed and I-5 was all screwed
up.
Once we jumped down the highway 101, which runs along the Pacific coast, the Pacific
ocean coast really was no big deal.
And then we high tailed it out of there.
But for the most part, actually just everybody was cool.
Everybody was super, like there was a lot of people and there was zero issue.
It's all them hippies are going to check out the eclipse.
People came from all over.
Behind us were people from Canada and then in front of us, parked alongside the road
because where we ended up, were people from Utah.
So people just came from all over to see it.
It was pretty neat.
People come all over, from all over to run Ubuntu Budgie 2.
I've been hearing more and more about Ubuntu Budgie Edition.
So it's Ubuntu but with the Budgie desktop from Solus and there are rumors are percolating
that there could be hardware shipping very soon with Ubuntu Budgie Edition pre-installed
on it.
There's a rumor circulating around today.
This is a post over at OMG Ubuntu and it's based on hints that were dropped by Ubuntu
Budgie's social media page, which I noticed that none of them are in the room for today.
Some of them are often in the room but nobody's there today from here.
So if you take the image that they tweeted out, right, right, they did two context-free
images on their Twitter feed.
They just posted like an iMac looking rig and a ultra-thin laptop looking rig with the
lid closed.
So you take those images and you do a reverse image search and you know what you end up
with?
Clevo!
Yeah, you end up with Clevo which is the same hardware ODM that Entraware and System76 use
and Nimbusoft and others use.
And you know, the thing I say with the Clevo is it's like getting a nice midsize sedan
or something.
It's like when you get a mid-level car, it's very reliable like a Camry or like a, you
know, an Accord which I've owned.
Those are great cars but they're not like, they're definitely not Tesla, Teslas and they're
definitely not BMW i-series, you know, they're not like, they're not crazy performance.
And they're not like, you know, super broken down cars either.
Sometimes depending on how the ODM chooses to tweak it though, they can really put together
something that's very, very compelling.
And so if they could get the balance right, you might have something here.
Now there's two laptops it looks like from Clevo that are two different rigs because
one was an iMac.
One's the Bologna laptop and the other is the Neptune all-in-one.
And Nimbusoft, which is a company out of the UK that resells Clevos, already actually sells
both of these devices with Ubuntu Mate, Kubuntu on it.
So you could see them pretty easily adding Ubuntu Budgie for Ubuntu Budgie users who
want to grab that.
Which could be great for people that are looking for something that's still GTK heavy as Canonical
moves away from Unity, but they still want something with an Ubuntu base.
Could be good timing.
I haven't heard anything from Nimbusoft in the past.
I've never reviewed any of their equipment and I'm not very familiar with the company.
I've never heard anybody in the audience has ever bought from them.
But they apparently are also working on their own distribution called Eloquent OS.
There's apparently every hardware OEM except for the ones like Dell and HP and IBM.
Except for the ones that are shipping lots of product.
Yeah except for the one.
Yeah there's an OEM program and then there's roll your own distribution apparently.
And to hell with even bothering being a flavor anymore.
Screw end users.
Speaking of screwing end users, CrashPlan is doing just that and shutting down its consumer
backup service.
And I'm bringing this up on this show because CrashPlan is something I've mentioned as a
very cost effective, unlimited, or close to it backup solution for Linux users.
And one of the things I loved about CrashPlan is A, they actually had a client that worked
on Linux and B, they had command line integration and C, you could ship them a disk.
You could just ship them a four terabyte spinning rust to seed your backup and then just back
up the updates and differentials.
Which was huge for me back in the day.
But unfortunately of course anything too good eventually has to go away.
Yep.
Have you experimented much with online backup?
You just use like Google Drive or what do you, because I know you recently suffered
some pretty serious data loss.
Like have you thought a lot about this?
Yeah, I've mostly been leaning towards actually trying to use TarSnap.
Oh yeah, yeah.
Yeah, that's definitely one of my recommendations.
Because they recently just came out with version 1.0 of the TarSnap GUI apparently.
Oh really?
Which makes it a lot easier I imagine.
Anybody in the mumble room using CrashPlan now or using a competitor to it that they
would give a recommendation to?
I was using CrashPlan.
Oh really?
Yeah.
But I was also, I actually had people who were friends and I had a couple of clients
that were using CrashPlan.
So that's going to suck.
Yeah, I'm definitely in that situation.
Some of my former clients are using CrashPlan and definitely like my mom's on CrashPlan.
I got a few family members on it too because it was so economical.
Which is probably why it's going away.
I was using it because, well I was also, some setups I was using it because it was free.
Because you can do it where you can do an FTP over SFTP over to multiple networks.
I love that feature.
You have your own computers and it was like it was fantastic but then I would still pay
for one of the premiums just because it was so useful but I wasn't going to deploy it
everywhere.
But now, you know, drawing board.
Man.
Yeah, most of the alternatives are really expensive too.
Yeah.
So I've been looking, Backblaze is very competitive but they don't and have no interest in making
a Linux client.
Which really pisses me off because it's not even a matter of, it's not even a matter of,
well we can't be bothered to even write a command line interface which would obviously
be simple.
Which there is a Python way to do this but anyways, let me get back to the main point.
They've been asked about it numerous times and they're very upfront about it.
You can ask them, we asked them today on Twitter.
And they'll just say, yeah, it's not really in our, it's not really in our business priorities
right now.
Nothing against Linux, just not really our business priority.
But they do have this B2 cloud storage system and I don't, again, never, I'm not personally
a customer of this, although Angela does use them now after CrashPlan.
But B2 is like a cloud storage service and there's going to be a cost associated with
that.
So keep this in mind.
But there's a tool you can use on Linux that works with B2 storage, it works with Amazon
Drive, obviously S3 Dropbox, Google Cloud Storage, Local Disk, Microsoft OneDrive.
It also will just do SSH and SFTP, it'll do a Yandex disk, which is kind of neat.
It's called rClone.
And rClone is sort of like rSync but it allows you to sync to these cloud storage services
that I just mentioned, including Backblaze's B2.
This might be something you could look into.
rClone might be a good way to move the data around to a new service as well.
So rClone.org is where you find that.
We've talked about it in the past, rSync for cloud storage.
And if you want to know specifically about the Backblaze integration, it's rClone.org
slash B2.
rClone also apparently has support for Amazon Cloud Drive.
Or Google Drive, you could do that as well if you're okay with that or you want to encrypt
your data or Dropbox if you're already paying that monster.
None of these really exciting.
Is it just storage cloning or is it just incremental cloning?
I think it's more file system based, so I don't think it's like doing block images or
anything like that.
Because it's more like rSync than it is like a block backup or something.
And it does support some of the same syntax as rSync too, like the commands to preserve
timestamps and those kinds of things, some of those same flags, like the archive flag
and stuff are the same.
The other thing that I find kind of useful about it is it does support syncing one data
set to multiple cloud storages, which is kind of a neat feature if you think about it.
So you could spread out your risks.
Say you have a locally encrypted set of data or something to that degree and then you could
blast a copy of it on Dropbox, Amazon S3, and Google Cloud.
Now would I really want to do that?
Generally no, however there's something that I feel like we as a society at whole have
not really wrapped our brains around and that is the ephemeral nature of digital media,
specifically our pictures.
And one of the things that stands out for me is a very strong memory from childhood
is going through family photo albums and seeing pictures of grandma and grandpa getting married
and how young they looked and seeing pictures of my mom and dad as kids and how they kind
of looked like me and my cousins and my uncles and my aunts.
These are pretty clear memories I have of going through these old photo albums and those
do not exist anymore for most people that are shooting digitally.
Some people print it out but for most of us they don't and then you move between computers
and you move between phones and all of a sudden you don't have the video of the marriage or
whatever it might be, the kid's birthday that was super important, and it's just gone.
It's just gone forever and there's nothing for your kids to flip through down the road
or your grandparents to flip through down the road because there's no physical object
to represent it and there's no solution to this problem.
There's nothing, you can update and upload all day long to Dropbox and Google Drive and
S3 and there's no way your kids are going to download that or your ancestors are going
to download that and look at it later on but at least it is preserving it in a way that
you could manage it and you can get access to it at some point.
And so spreading that out and the fact that this supports FTP, SFTP, the local file system,
so you could do an NFS mount if you wanted to or it supports multiple cloud storages
and it'll do hashes to make sure everything goes up there, everything's got good integrity.
It does partial syncs if your upload gets canceled.
So if you got to move off of CrashPlan, rClone could be a solution for you.
There's also kind of nice for restorations especially for basic end users is there's
an optional fuse mount called rClone mount and as you'd expect that makes it kind of
easy for regular people to browse through their backup and you could just have this
as an icon on the side of their file manager that they click on, kicks off using the background,
it does a mount and of course you just have to have rClone installed to do that and you
could also even use WinFCP and there is actually a proxy module available for Windows which
uses a combination of rClone and CG GoFuse, I can't remember what it's called because
I have never needed to use it, but there's actually even a way to mount rClone backups
on Windows desktops which could be great for clients or people that you're setting up in
an office that need access to that but you're backing it from a Linux file server.
That's a situation I've been in where I've used a backup system on Linux for Linux file
servers and then guess who needs to restore the data?
Some user on Windows and that has a solution for that.
So links to all of that crap in the show notes.
So I was doing a bit of research while you were talking, apparently Duplicity and by
extension DejaDup, since it's the front end to it, can directly sync or directly backup
to Amazon Cloud Drive.
I am so glad you brought up Duplicity because that's a great one.
On top of that, there's an asynchronous upload flag that will encrypt as it uploads.
So you can encrypt your backups and not have to worry about Amazon looking into your backups.
There's also sort of name collision but there's also Duplicati which is a backup software
for Mac, Windows and Linux they say that does local encryption and then backs up to probably
using rClone on the backend all the same cloud services that rClone supports but this gives
you a big old stinking web GUI for it which makes it nice and easy for people to manage.
So it might be something worth looking at too.
That's Duplicati and Duplicity.
Duplicity is like a GTK based app that you run on Linux desktop.
Duplicity is the command line app.
DejaDup is the GTK app.
Oh, okay.
Oh, right, right.
Thank you.
So DejaDup is the GTK front end.
Duplicati is a web based like a project around rClone.
That's a lot of things we just dropped at you.
I know that's all confusing because all the names sort of collide.
So here's what I'm doing right now is I'm putting links to all of this stuff in the
show notes, jupyterbroadcasting.com.
Go to Linux Unplugged 211s and you'll see the big section on rClone there that lists
all of the cloud services that it features.
Yeah, DejaDup has been an app pick before too.
If you want good advice for data stuff in general, the Data Hoarder subreddit is a great
place to go.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, I haven't been there in forever.
And also anybody in the mom room, if you have any other like backup apps or tips.
Plus it has some really nice storage porn.
Yeah, it is a great subreddit to hang out in.
And like if you're ever like in the mood to like research and set up like a new NAS.
Yeah, some of the most chill, informative guys on Reddit.
All right.
I think I got links to everything now.
Duplicity, DejaDup.
Go ahead.
DejaDup is also great because it's really easy to use.
Yeah.
And it's like even like, you know, for basic end users that could pick it up.
All right.
So I think that's...
And it has a fun name.
Look at that.
All of that.
Live show note editing right here on the show.
Proud of us.
So those of you that are getting screwed up by CrashPlan, hopefully some of these will
help out.
I feel really bad about that because I've recommended CrashPlan in the past.
I wonder if DejaDup can upload to Tarsnap.
That'd be interesting.
Yeah.
I got to play around.
If Tarsnap has a GUI, I got to play around with that too because that would...
That's a slam dunk.
It apparently just like hit 1.0 like this past week.
That's worth it.
That is a slam dunk, I think.
Also feel free to tweet us or leave a comment wherever you're watching this to let us know
how you're doing your offsite backups on Linux.
I am more particularly interested in offsite backups.
Local backups is good too, but offsite is really sort of the sweet spot.
And however you do it, let us know.
Leave a comment where you watch this or go over to jupyterbroadcasting.com slash contact
or tweet me at Chris LAS.
Also got the subreddit, linuxunplug.reddit.com.
Let's talk about mobile.
This is my mobile service provider.
It's also Reiki's mobile service provider, and it's a Ting, linux.ting.com.
It's just a better way to do mobile.
There's no contracts, no nationwide coverage.
You just pay for what you use.
This is so nice, especially when new phones are getting released.
You don't have to sit here and try to do the crazy complicated, am I eligible for an upgrade?
Do I have to go into a quote-unquote agreement if I do that?
It's just so straightforward, especially with some of the leasing programs that the iPhone
has, or if you want to go grab a used phone off of Gazelle when the new phones come out
for a crazy great price or eBay, this is the perfect time to bring it over to Ting, because
you can just add a SIM.
You just go get the SIM card from their store, and if you go to linux.ting.com, they'll give
you $25 to play with, either off a device or in service credits.
And if you get that SIM card for nine bucks, they'll probably just give you... I think
they just attribute it all in service credits.
That first month you bring that phone over will probably be paid for.
It's nice.
Do you want to know a secret, Chris?
Sometimes they even cut the price of those SIMs.
Yeah, they do.
And sometimes they have them on sale on Amazon, too.
I will say, the only time I've ever had to contact Ting was to get my unlocked phone
on Ting, and it only took like five minutes.
I feel like on other carriers, it doesn't take nearly as-
You know what will really sell you on Ting?
If you can do the whole bring your device process online through their website, and
it's done in minutes, and you never even have to talk to... It's so well done.
You start using different aspects of Ting, and it's how you just immediately realize
it's how every carrier should do it.
It's how they would have to do it in the US today to be competitive if the industry was
starting over.
Yeah.
The only reason I even needed to call them is because the other carrier screwed it up.
You can also get some great... Like Rika was just mentioning, when they bring things
up on sale, you can get that kind of information on their Twitter account.
They also have TingTips.
Look at this.
Look at that.
They got TingTips on there.
I didn't know they had TingTips.
That was pretty hip Ting music too.
Oh, I like that.
So they got tips and stuff on their Twitter page, at TingFTW on Twitter, where you can
find out about giveaways, sales, like on the SIM cards and whatnot.
It's no contract, no early termination fees, you only pay for what you use, they don't
play that crazy OEM game where they want to flash a certain experience on your phone,
so they hold back updates.
If you get a device that gets updates from Google or gets updates from Motorola, they
don't get in the way.
They ship it.
It still blows my mind to have an internet savvy phone company.
Yeah.
It is really nice.
It's finally the way it should be.
Linux.ting.com, and thanks to everybody who supports the show by visiting that site and
checking out Ting, and checking out their blog, and signing up, Linux.ting.com.
Now here's something you never thought Electron would be used for, and this is a line that's
just even too far for me.
I can't even with this, guys, a file manager built using Electron.
I love it.
Check it out.
It's JMPfm, JMP file manager, and it's described as a dual-pane file manager, cross-platform
Qt based, and it has a terminal tool built in that lets you do certain things.
In fact, it takes its key influences from the LS command, it says.
It's a keyboard-driven file manager, and as you might expect, I have it loaded right here.
I've been trying it out, and I'll tell you one thing.
Its main gimmick is pretty cool.
If you type the J key, it brings up the JMP menu, JMPfm is the name, and it shows you
all your favorite directories, and you can just bam right through them super quick.
Bam.
It also, I think, has a flat file mode where it will show you all the files in the directory
you're in, as well as all the subdirectories.
Okay, let's see here.
So it's got a whole series of plug-ins, too.
The configuration's done through a series of text files and whatnot, though.
That's kind of a turn-off.
Well, it's early.
Yeah, it is early.
It is early.
So I've been running this and Nautilus all day, been browsing files in both of them,
so I thought we'd just check in and do a little memory usage.
So how much does an Electron file manager take?
Now I'm not normally this guy.
I just had a whole soapbox on last week's quarter radio about how I think Linux users
are too hard on Electron apps, but I've got to do this.
We have to go here.
So sorting by memory usage, the only thing on my system that's taking more memory is
definitely Chrome.
Chrome's taking a lot more memory.
Geez, look at Chrome.
That is really something.
Well, it's isolating every process.
So Jump FM, if you look at just the...
If you look at just the Jump FM main process, and it has a couple of processes, but if you
look at just the main process right now, this is really remarkable, actually.
This is not the results I had earlier.
Jump FM is currently consuming 27.9 megabytes of RAM, and Nautilus is currently consuming
23.4.
So Nautilus is only a few megabytes lower.
It's 23 megabytes for Nautilus, 27 megabytes for Jump FM.
So if you go back into Jump FM, Chris, and you pick a folder, and you hit R, it'll do
the flat mode.
Oh, okay.
One more thing on the memory usage, though.
So Jump FM's main thread, 27.9 meg.
So essentially 28 megabytes.
But then there's also an app image thread that gets launched when I mount it via app
image.
That takes up five megabytes of RAM.
There's also a dedicated thread for the GPU with no sandbox mode turned on, dual GPU turned
off, and driver bug workarounds enabled, and certain GL extensions disabled.
That thread is taking an astonishing 62 megabytes of RAM, taking more RAM than the main file
manager thread.
And then there is a tertiary thread besides the main thread that is taking 5.8 megabytes
of RAM that is just apparently some sort of like no sandbox thing.
Anyways, so that is quite a bit of memory usage.
But if I go into flat mode here, that is kind of great, actually.
Yeah, it shows you all the files in the directory and in all the subdirectories.
Wow, that's a lot of files.
That's a lot of crash files.
And it's really quick, too.
It is quick.
I'll give it that.
Once it's loaded, like all Electron apps, it loads a little awkwardly for a moment.
But then once it's loaded, it is very quick.
And then it's got other crazy stuff like filtering where you can hit F and just type in part
of a file name and it will find the file for you.
All right.
So let's do jump.
Let's see if it helps if I spell it right.
Jump.
Hmm.
I don't know.
You might be searching the directory you're in.
I just feel like this is a line too far for me, dude.
Where do we stop building Electron apps at?
And for coders, if you hit Control-G on a file, it'll instantly make a gist.
Huh.
Okay.
So here was my thought on this is there is some value to just maybe Control-G.
Yeah.
That's pretty great, actually.
It's creating a gist right now.
That's pretty great.
There is some...
Yeah, I guess if I am stuck on Mac, Windows, and Linux...
Yeah, there's my gist.
Of course, I did it out of an image file, so of course it's ass, but it did it.
It did it.
If I'm stuck on Mac or Windows, but my main OS is Linux, maybe then I would want to have
a file manager that's cross-platform like this.
But come on.
Go with me, dude.
Would you ever use this?
Yeah.
Why not?
Well, Explorer sucks.
Maybe that's why.
Nautilus sucks too.
Yeah, but not as bad as...
I mean, I don't know.
Just look at them side by side.
So here is JumpFM, and here, let me bring up Nautilus.
Nautilus looks so much better.
I disagree.
I hate how Nautilus looks.
This looks like a Flash application on my desktop.
It looks like it's weird.
It doesn't follow my desktop convention at all.
Yeah, but that's just a problem with the implementation of the app.
You can make Electron apps follow your desktop.
Man, I don't know.
To me, it seems like Nautilus is way better looking.
It also doesn't help that you're running a cute app in a GDK environment.
Yeah.
Well, I mean, I just tried Jump inside of Plasma, and it looks like...
About the same?
Yeah.
So what are your impressions?
I mean, it looks interesting as far as the speed of its searching.
The find tool is not that useful, it seems so far.
The flat thing is cool, although it's not as effective as you would assume.
It flattens some of the stuff and shows you some files, but it also skips other files.
If I just flatten this, it should be showing me files that are in the main folder, but
it's skipping that and showing other folders, so that's weird.
But overall, I mean, it's interesting, although 200 megs total on my system is not acceptable
for a file manager.
I'm so tired of the whole memory usage argument.
But 200 megs for a file manager?
We're in a world where 32 gigabyte PCs are common.
It's 32 gigabytes for a file manager that is not even that good.
I'm looking at my folder right now.
At this point, I'm just talking about the whole memory usage argument in general, not
specifically for this app.
Okay.
I agree with the argument in general.
There are some Electron apps that manage it very well and even do hibernation in certain
cases and stuff, so those are fine.
It's just the ones that recognize that Electron needs to be managed, I'm okay with those.
Things like this, where the features it's offering are not even implemented very well,
like if you go to the flat mode, it looks cool, but I have stuff in the home folder.
I'm in the home folder just to see what happens if it finds every file.
It finds random files in some folders and it skips the rest.
I feel like if we crapped on every project that didn't work on one of its earlier releases,
then we'd have a lot less projects.
I guess where I go with it is, is there a line?
Is there a line where you say, these things should be native applications on a platform?
Like for a house, you have to have a foundation for your house.
You could build the house materials out of anything, but the house has to be a solid
foundation.
Yeah.
I mean, I don't think that native really matters anymore.
Look at Discord.
It's not native.
You got to have something to launch the web browser.
Well, yeah.
I mean, native is not that necessary, sure, and Discord is a good example, but it is still
important.
In a file manager, native is important and just because it's going to be faster, because
this is fast, but it's also incredibly inaccurate.
If you do the flat system and it shows you these files and it's cool, but it's skipping
files that are in the current folder I'm in and going to other folders, it's not reliable
in any way whatsoever.
For me, it's not fast enough, to be honest.
I mean, it's fast once it's running, but it does that thing that some Electron apps do
where the frame of the application comes up and then the inside of the application flashes
white, and then the UI elements render in, sort of like how a webpage loads, actually.
When I want to just open up my file manager super quick, I've already had to do the mental
gymnastics of, is this something I do on the terminal with LS, or is this something I bother
firing at my file manager?
So I've already made that decision tree, which already takes time, and then I go through
that decision tree and I end up with this app that's taking me, I don't know, noticeably
longer than my native app to load.
The thing is, you guys are making arguments for problems that can be solved by better
code.
Would you...
Yeah, I suppose, like they could do a TSR in the background and leave it always running
to launch faster, I suppose.
Well, no, you can just optimize the code so it launches quicker.
I don't really know any Electron app that launches as quick as a native application.
Once it's up and running, I agree, you can have it pretty competitive, but launch time
seems particularly important for a file manager, like your terminal, too.
That also seems like something you want to launch really fast.
I'm playing around with it.
Discord takes forever and just has little splash messages like these weird, like the
rabbits are loading or something.
That's not a bad way to go.
A splash message isn't a bad way to go, at least then you know it's working.
I think Discord takes long because it's loading all the messages from the server and stuff.
Yeah, and it's checking for updates and every time, too.
I would say that this jump FM is interesting, but it doesn't do what it claims to do.
If it didn't claim these things and say these things are good, that's one thing, but it's
claiming like the flat system doesn't work, the searching isn't useful, it's not finding
any things.
I'm like searching for files that I know are in like one folder, like lower, and it's not
finding that at all.
Have you turned on the syntax highlighting, the quote unquote, where it does different
color coding for different file types?
No.
I think that's useful.
That's actually kind of nice, especially when you're working on like a website, and
they have a screenshot here, and you've got-
You need to skim to the greens.
Yeah, you got your index.html, which is always green, your JSON files are always red, your
CSS is always gray.
It's interesting, but if it doesn't do the rest of the stuff, then what's the point?
Yeah, there's stuff in there I like.
Actually, I think their jump menu is pretty great.
I would like every freaking file manager to do this jump menu thing.
Yeah, I'm not saying the app is great as it is, I'm saying it has potential.
Yeah, I agree with you.
The jump menu's pretty cool.
Yeah, like the-
It reminds me of Sublime Text.
Yeah, exactly.
It's just like the Sublime, or Gnome do essentially, or whatever.
But the other thing is, is like being able to upload a gist, and files that are displayed
depending on their git status, the jump menu and the git integration is really shit that
every important Linux file manager should be shipping already, if you think about it.
Because we keep talking about on this show and other shows, and obviously Dell and other
companies, and System76 keep talking about focusing on users that are creating software.
People like the Sputnik program, for example, is going really after the web developer, sysadmin
market that is using Linux on production and using Linux on the Sputnik laptops.
And that focus, they have seen 100% year over year growth by focusing on that niche within
a niche of Linux users.
They realized they had to hyper focus at a certain niche of Linux users, which is incredible
if you think about it, because Linux is already such a niche.
And these users, these are kinds of features that they want.
And I feel like our...
This is just a short rant, but I feel like our projects, like GNOME, are so focused on
bringing in the new user that it takes a damn memory eating monster to come along and actually
ship something that's new and innovative.
We haven't had anything interesting happen in our file managers in years.
In fact, on the GNOME side, features have literally just gotten removed year after year.
Some have finally been re-added recently.
And this kind of stuff, meanwhile, has just been sitting out there.
This should be...
This GNOME file should have been shipping this a year ago.
Dolphin should be doing this already.
This needs to already be happening.
And this is kind of sad you have to go get it from an Electron app.
Dolphin does have the syntax thing.
Dolphin has everything else like the Git integration and stuff.
Oh, I was specifically talking about Git and the jump thing.
So if it's got that, then I take it back for Dolphin, because that's the thing I really
think.
Can you, does Dolphin do that?
I don't think so, no.
So that would be great.
It does have the Git thing.
The Git stuff is good, too.
That's awesome.
So I've got to play with that.
Dolphin just feels terrible to use.
Is it like the services KIO slave stuff?
Or is it like legit, because the thing about this is you can actually sort the files in
your file browser based on their Git status.
That's a whole other level.
I think it's KIO stuff.
Yeah.
Even having something is nice, though.
And then, of course, it's got plugins and filtering and stuff like that.
So yeah.
There are filterings.
There's the filter in the search bar and stuff like that that does something, but it's not
like automatically loading stuff like the jump thing is doing.
The jump thing, I think, is particularly great.
I think the Git stuff is particularly great.
The plugin stuff, I don't really know if I need that in my file manager.
Filtering stuff, yeah.
You can basically do that.
I don't know, Chris.
You've got plenty of plugins in GIT.
You know, if it let Google finally release a Google Drive client for Linux, maybe that
would be worth it.
Well, I think you need-
There's Google Drive support for Dolphin.
Yeah.
It'd probably be pretty easy to implement in Jump FM.
Oh, gosh.
Yeah, probably.
Nice web extensions.
Yeah, really.
Yeah, no kidding.
Anyways, it's an interesting thing to play around with if you want to play, A, with an
app image, because that's what it is, and, B, with a file manager that's actually trying
to do something different for the first time in a few years, so you could check that out.
I definitely like the thought of being able to just take all of my apps with me on whatever
platform.
Yeah.
I completely agree.
I think one of the things that I've said for a long time is a great way to convert people
to Linux and-
Just have a completely portable workflow.
Put people on LibreOffice, Firefox, and now Jump FM, and they're ready to go.
You put them on Windows and let them run that for six months, then move over to Linux, use
the same apps, nothing changes.
It's legitimately the smoothest way to move people over to Linux, but they're not going
to need to anymore.
That's going to come to an end, because Google is launching Chrome Enterprise subscription
service for Chrome OS, essentially signaling to the entire world that, okay, we're ready
for Chrome OS to take over in the enterprise.
They've experimented with this a little bit, actually, in the past with Chromebooks for
Work was the program, but this is a totally different beast.
First of all, it's $50 per device per year, which for a business is just an unbelievably
low price.
They could have charged legitimately 50 bucks per month, and businesses would have paid
this.
Chrome OS as a service.
Yeah.
So you get a number of nice capabilities.
They have a little chart here.
Holy crap.
Can I zoom in on this?
Because this is quite the chart.
So additional things that you get above and beyond stock Chrome OS with Chrome Enterprise,
and this isn't the browser.
This is the OS.
They just call it Chrome Enterprise.
They dropped the OS for whatever reason.
You get managed Google Play beta support for the apps that can be installed on Chrome OS.
You can manage the browser better that's on Chrome OS.
You get full-fledged remote printer management support, but this is the big one that they're
really marketing right here.
Full-fledged Microsoft Active Directory integration, including single sign-on with their Google
accounts and everything, all authenticated via Active Directory.
You also get kiosk mode and public mode that it automatically delete.
You get managed network and proxies that you can remote push to the devices, which I thought
you could do with regular Chrome, but they say Chrome Enterprise.
You get theft prevention wherever the hell that is, and of course, of course, 24-7 enterprise
support for $50 a year per device.
All at a much cheaper price than Windows licenses.
Much, much, much, much cheaper, and the hardware is cheaper.
It's more interchangeable.
There's this thing that has happened many times, and I bet a lot of you that are in
IT know this story.
There is a thing about the very high levels of a company.
Every now and then, you get one of these employees, it's man or women, who are high enough in
the company where what they do is so damn important that any disruption is immediately
addressed, even if it means they go through computers at least once a year.
I had this client every six months.
It was his computer.
We finally got to the point, I think I talked about this in one of our shows, where we just
built this monster maniac system, when SSDs were still really expensive, and Xeon processors
put this thing in a raid, started doing image snapshot backups every single night, just
went all out, and he burned through that system.
He just burned through that system.
The thing for him was, in a day, he's working with five, six million dollar deals a day,
maybe more, so a $7,000 monster machine was no big deal to him.
There were other employees who would just get some of his hand-me-downs that would still
work.
He was all filtered down.
These things, these things are so cheap to replace that your employees can destroy them.
They can lose them.
You can wipe them.
It's such an enticing business proposition, especially when you look at their other cloud
services that this ties in with, because when you start integrating Microsoft Active Directory
with single sign-on to the Google cloud services, you get the Google App Suite with this thing.
You get Chrome OS.
You get cloud storage.
You can authenticate and manage the permissions via Active Directory.
This is that final piece that clicks Chrome OS into this really ideal position for businesses,
and then, for some really stupid reason, they're only charging $50 a year.
Like I'm saying, people would pay $50 a month for this.
Well, it's a good way to lock them in for all the other services.
You'll also be able to have a managed enterprise app store for just your users.
It's something that's in beta right now, but it's going to use Chrome OS's new ability
to run Android apps, and you'll be able to give them a branded Play Store page that's
the only section of the Play Store they can access that has all of your company apps on
it.
Google is working their ass off to compete with Microsoft.
I sort of set this up as Linux is a little screwed.
All these companies that run Linux are just going to go with this instead, maybe, but
I don't really think that's the case.
I think people that are going to run Linux on the desktop need a more powerful operating
system to begin with, but who this really is going to screw over is Microsoft because
this is not only eating away at their OEM's hardware sales.
It's eating away at the whole office lock-in thing because this also comes with all these
great Google Cloud services.
They're going for it, dude.
Google's going for it.
They're really going for it with this.
Good on them, I suppose.
Good on them.
It does seem like a typical Google thing.
You just have this product that sits there and is a sleeper for half a decade or more,
and then all of a sudden, it just clicks into place.
Yeah, I suppose.
That sounds like how Microsoft used to do things.
Google more and more to me feels like the new Microsoft.
That was a Microsoft move for a long time, and this whole ecosystem lock-in strategy
is a Microsoft one.
Google's just doing it with Cloud services.
Microsoft did it with file formats.
It's the 90s all over again, everybody.
Hey, speaking of the 90s, let's make your Bash prompt even cooler.
Your Bash RC is a handy little place you can go to make your prompt look badass and stuff,
like from the movies and whatnot.
I forgot who passed this along to me, so apologies, but this is EasyPrompt.net.
I think it came from our Discord.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think it was in the content channel in our Discord.
Thank you to whoever did this, because this is so fun.
It lets you pick the elements that you want to show up in your prompt.
Say you want maybe your host name to be in your command prompt, your shell version, the
current directory you're in, or the whole path is actually my favorite one, the shell
release, or date and time information.
Isn't that cool?
What you get here is a webpage, and you pick these blocks that you want.
You have your basic elements.
I like to put in username.
I also like to put in the current path of the directory, and why not also have some
status elements in there?
You could have things like get status, or you could have time.
You could have time or extra characters in there.
Maybe you like to have a few extra ASCII characters in there to make it look badass.
I totally understand.
What's great about this is as you click these different things, you can move them around
in this web interface, and it gives you a real-time preview output of what your prompt
is going to look like, and then in a fourth box, just four boxes, in the fourth box, it
gives you the code that you copy pasta into your Bash RC file to make your command prompt
look like that.
How cool is that?
I was messing around with this.
I was just deleting stuff and adding new stuff and putting the full DNS name in there, all
that kind of stuff, shell version.
It's really neat, and you can add spaces in there if you want it to look right.
You can mess with all that kind of stuff.
It was CodeChris on Discord.
Thank you, WW.
CodeChris.
Thank you to CodeChris, and thank you to WW for pointing it out.
It's easyprompt.net if you want to play around with that and make your RC all cool.
If you want something a bit more advanced, more crazy, there's something called Powerline
Shell.
Oh, yeah.
That is really intense.
We've got to have talked about that.
Right?
Maybe, but it's really damn awesome.
Okay.
In fact, I think it's installed by default in Solus.
Really?
Yeah.
I don't know.
Ike knows what's up.
I don't know if it's turned on by default, but I know it's in there.
Yeah.
So PowerShell gives you...
So if you've ever seen screenshots of people's computers that have the terminal up, and then
they have in the terminal on the command prompt, they have the directory path in these cool,
almost capsule-looking...
How would you describe that?
I don't know.
It's kind of like a graphical representation in your command line.
Yeah.
It's neat.
It's neat-looking.
There's a lot of cool things that it does.
You can...
Yeah, that's really cool.
PowerShell is also a cool way to make your trip.
Okay.
Now, just all of a sudden, we turned it into a cool thing to hack the terminal.
Yeah.
I actually had it on my mind because somebody I know from IRC just rewrote it in Go, and
it's actually way, way faster.
Oh, man.
What?
PowerShell?
Yeah.
Is it available for Linux in Go?
Where do I...
Yeah.
So it's navigation trees, what some people in chatroom call it.
You know, if that's available for Linux, that'd be pretty cool.
Yeah.
It's github.com slash justgen slash powerline-go.
Powerline-go.
Of course.
There's...
You know what?
No way.
Okay.
Now, wake me...
You know what?
I'm gonna wait.
You know why?
Because just wake me up when the Rust port comes.
That's when I'll...
DigitalOcean.com.
Go over to DigitalOcean.com, create an account, and use our promo code of absolute power and
performance.
That's D-O Unplugged.
You create your account, then you apply D-O Unplugged, one word, and you get a $10 credit.
Now, keep that in mind, because DigitalOcean's pricing is amazing.
I love their three cents an hour machine.
It's very fast.
It's a great way to try out a project, mess around with something, and then totally economical
to leave in production.
You can get started in less than 55 seconds, you'll be logged in and ready to go.
They got SSDs for all the different types of systems you might want, from the really
high-end CPU systems and the rigs with lots of memory, all the way down to the $5 a month
systems.
They got SSD.
And the hypervisors have super fast 40-gigabit connections coming in.
Of course, they run Linux and KVM for the virtualizer.
And then DigitalOcean has built an API that is really nice, super smooth and simple.
We work with it all the time.
In fact, I think all of their tools use it as well.
And because of that, there's lots of open source projects available using it.
You can just install them on your phone or your Linux desktop.
There's some that work right in your tray that you can manage your droplets.
They have a block storage to make it quick and easy to attach, lots of more storage up
to 16 terabytes to a droplet.
Pre-build open source apps that you can monitor or you can deploy really quick.
And monitoring.
I do like that monitoring too.
We use it mostly on and off.
See, the thing about the monitoring that's really nice is, how do you know how powerful
of a droplet do you need?
How do you know?
So it's...
You monitor it.
Yeah, you monitor it.
And it's easy to expand.
So go with the $5 a month and see if it works for your workload.
A lot of people like to just use it for something like a WordPress site or an email server.
I don't recommend running your own email server, but you definitely can.
And you don't need more than the $5 a month droplet to do that.
I've expanded a couple of droplets.
All you have to do is basically just go into where it asks you how you want to expand it.
You change the things and then you just reload it and it's got the new stuff.
So just try it that way.
So, you know, whatever you're doing, like a Nextcloud system, this is a great example
of that.
I've done this very...with my Nextcloud instance because we uploaded a bunch of pictures.
It grew.
I'm like, I think I want to keep that stuff on there.
So I'll just add more storage.
And it's so economical.
It's seamless, too.
Like you don't have to go and like edit config files.
No, I know.
It's DigitalOcean, dude.
DigitalOcean.
DigitalOcean.com.
Just use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
DOUNPLUGGED.
It's one word.
You apply it to your account after you sign up, DigitalOcean.com.
So this week I got some things to say about Ubuntu.
And we have sort of like a low summer turnout.
I think as the summer wraps up, I'm going to be glad in some ways because I think we'll
have more people show up in the mumble room.
Either that or everybody wants us to switch to Discord.
That could be the subliminal message they're giving us.
By not showing up in mumble, maybe they're saying, switch over to Discord, guys.
Because if they wanted us to stay on mumble, they'd surely be here.
So something to think about.
But in the meantime, this is actually to my advantage because neither Popey nor Wimpy
have joined us for today's episode.
And I have some things to say about Ubuntu.
I don't run Ubuntu.
I'm running Solus on this machine.
I mean, I do run Ubuntu on some of our systems here at JB, but none of my personal daily
use systems.
The mumble room.
Yep.
I know that one does.
But none of my personal daily use systems run Ubuntu.
So I don't have really much of a horse in this race.
So just full disclosure, this doesn't really impact me.
But I was going to save this.
I was going to save this to talk about it with Noah on user error so that way he could
back me up.
So it wouldn't just be me saying this because it's just going to sound like Crazy Chris.
But I think what we are seeing with Ubuntu 17.10 is what happens when an adult makes
a Linux distribution.
And I don't mean to be demeaning to all the other projects out there, but Canonical is
doing things with 17.10 that I simply can't understand why it's taken, frankly, it's taken
until they've come along and made a gnome version for any of this shit to happen.
It's sort of opening my eyes to how this could be done better by all the other Linux distributions.
So there's several different avenues I could take.
I could talk about the thousands of fixes they've now submitted to fix Bluetooth upstream.
I could talk about that for a moment.
I could talk about the fact that they're finally the only distribution that's actually taking
on hardware accelerated video playback and testing it and applying patches and getting
it to work from the web browser down to the video on your screen.
Everybody has claimed they have it, but no one actually got it working until Canonical
came along.
I could talk about that all day.
But today we're going to talk about the new doc.
Because this simple, simple thing that they are doing perfectly illustrates what I'm talking
about.
And I guess maybe for context, I'll give you one more example of something they've done
recently that needs a lot more discussion and no one's talking about it.
Canonical is doing something very unique with the way that they are implementing their GNOME
desktop in Ubuntu 17.10.
They are shipping it as a session option, just like the way that upstream GNOME ships
GNOME Classic.
You choose GNOME Classic and it's like you're in a different version of GNOME Shell, but
you're not in a fork of GNOME Shell.
You're not in something that conflicts with your totally tricked out version of GNOME
Shell.
You're just in a different GNOME Shell environment.
GNOME Shell has been specifically architected to support this.
This was a design intention of GNOME Shell.
But every distribution out there from Fedora to Anagros just cocks up your main GNOME installation
with their extensions that conflict with extensions from the actual publisher.
They'll just install the favorite stock and just say, ah, screw it.
Doesn't matter if it has the same extension ID as the one upstream.
And then you consistently run into issues when you update your system.
They couldn't have just implemented it in its own session.
No, they didn't do any of that stuff.
With 17.10, if you don't like the way Canonical ships GNOME, you log out, you choose the default
option and you've got stock GNOME.
None of their extensions are installed.
Their new custom doc we're about to talk about doesn't pop up.
It's just GNOME.
And it's been built to support this.
And yet it took this company to do it.
The GNOME developers tried to show the way with the classic session is to show you how
it could be done, but nobody did it.
Everybody just had, for some reason, had to just modify the default GNOME session.
But when we see them now doing something as simple as modifying a doc, you really see
the care that's being taken in their approach with 17.10 and the sustainability that they're
building into this distribution now.
And anybody who said that Canonical isn't focused on the desktop, you've got to reevaluate
the facts because this is a great example.
So they're going to launch a doc that's their own doc by default in Ubuntu 17.10.
It is a light fork of sort of the most famous and well-known doc for GNOME, Dash to Dock.
And they've basically made a few tweaks to it.
But it's how they've gone about all of this that really matters.
I'm looking at you, Mint Project, with all of your different fricking forks.
Xapps.
Yeah.
So how did Canonical do this?
And why didn't they just ship Dash to Dock?
This is, I guess you could call it a light fork.
It's a fork done right.
And I think it's really a sustainable approach.
So first of all, let's cover some of the basics here.
Why would they want it?
Why would they want to have their own doc?
Why not just use, if it's so popular, why not just use Dash to Dock?
Why even bother?
Why waste the time?
Why have to invent their own thing?
Well, first of all, this extension is installed by default on Ubuntu, just like I was talking
about how Antigros does it.
It means it comes from a package.
It comes from a deb from the main Ubuntu archive.
So they've got to package it because that's how it's getting installed.
So now they're immediately, instantly, without ever even shipping an ISO, they're in this
problem where Upstream is shipping their own version and publishing on the GNOME extension
site and their version is different.
It's immediately an issue because that is a very popular extension that's under active
development.
If Canonical's extension kept the same GNOME shell extension ID that Dash to Dock had,
it would mean that users couldn't swap them out.
You would either have to use the Ubuntu one or uninstall your doc, which would probably
uninstall a whole bunch of other dependencies and then try to get Dash to Dock installed.
So they've done this, for one reason they've done this, is so they have their own extension
ID so you don't have this conflict.
But what's so badass about their implementation is the settings you tweak, they're schema
overrides so you can actually share settings between the Upstream doc and the Ubuntu doc.
If you install the Upstream doc, the Ubuntu doc automatically gets disabled.
If you uninstall Dash to Dock, the Ubuntu doc automatically comes back on.
Exactly the kind of behavior you would expect.
They tweaked a few other small things about Dash to Dock, like they automatically made
it top to bottom vertical, just like the Unity launcher is, so it looks like Unity.
They tweaked a few things to make it look a little more like Unity, so that way it's
sort of an easier, smoother transition for existing users.
But here's the great thing, too, is they worked with the developers, they're all on board,
they agreed this is a great way to do it, and they've been submitting patches Upstream,
which they are already applying to their code base.
In fact, if I recall, you can actually find canonical, yeah, so they've done an Upstream
branch that has all of their own modifications, and they're gonna regularly rebase on top
of the Upstream Dash to Dock to keep everything basically cozy.
Yeah, so it's a fork that's different but compatible.
It's an Upstream fork, they're working with the developer, and what I love about it, which
I think is so awesome, is the settings are, like you can invest in one Dock and then switch
out and you don't lose all of your special settings.
And they say also the probably most important, unvisible, the thing that you can't really
see is the fact they use a different extension ID, because that makes it possible to swap
between them, you can stay up to date on each of them without having to worry about it.
You don't have to uninstall one to get the other one like you have to do on Anagros.
It's like Ubuntu went to them and said, well, we like what you're doing here, but our vision
is slightly different, but we want to maintain compatibility, so how can we do this so that
our stuff will work with yours, even if we're doing something a bit different?
And then the last piece that I really think is classy, that I think all the other forkers
out there should try to integrate, is it's using two things that make it really respectful
to switching back to Upstream.
If you install and enable Dash to Dock, you don't have to have it enabled, but if you
turn it, when you do turn it on, even if Ubuntu Dock is still turned on, it politely just
vanishes and goes away, and just lets Dash to Dock take over, and then if you change
any settings in Dash to Dock, like anything that would modify DCOM for G settings, those
modifications will be reflected in both, that's super smooth, and then you turn off Dash to
Dock and the Ubuntu Dock comes right back.
And that sort of classy sharing of settings, using schema overrides, and then gracefully
bowing out when the Upstream version comes online, I think is nailing it, it's nailing
it.
I think my only question would be, is there an option to actually disable that sharing?
Because I can see a use case where some people might not want to share between the two.
Probably, I'm looking at it right now, it looks like you can turn off the override mechanism,
so there is a way to turn that off, but I haven't tried it yet, obviously, so I don't
know.
And they talk in this blog post, this is Ubuntu Dome Shell in Artful Day 5, I've been following
these series, and it makes so much sense when you're thinking about moving users over and
how to do this right, and you look at it in the totality, you look at the Upstream fixes
to Bluetooth, why is a thousand things they found in this development cycle for this one
version of their distro?
What's going on?
Why has nobody else done that?
This video acceleration stuff, the Gnome session stuff, and now the way they're handling
this Upstream fork, I mean, this isn't even the LTS release yet.
Well, I mean, they're doing all the heavy lifting now, so the LTS will be nice and stable,
I guess.
It seems like a very sustainable approach, because by encapsulating everything in their
own Gnome session, they don't have to worry about breaking or conflicting stuff that people
want to install different extensions or don't like their configuration but still want an
Ubuntu base, by modifying this dock to sort of bridge the move over from Unity 7, which
is the most visible aspect of Unity 7, and it's legitimately the thing that when I sit
people down in front of Unity 7, they click with immediately, is that sidebar, and to
do it like this, I don't know, I mean, I'm definitely looking forward to trying out 1710.
I am very excited about this release.
I got to say, it's maybe the most excited I've been in eight years of releases.
I mean, I got to go back quite a way to get this excited about an Ubuntu release again,
and it's all going Upstream.
I think it's always been something that I respect about Ubuntu, is that rather than
look at what is the quickest way to do this, they say what is the best way to do this,
except now it's being applied to other Upstream projects instead of them rolling their own
stuff.
What I was surprised by was how popular the survey was for docks, because I was just saying
last week, I'm kind of over docks.
I'm just sort of done with them, but you look at all of the results, and they're right.
They link to it.
People want docks.
People want to use a dock.
I don't know.
For me, you put a bar down at the bottom of the screen, put the clock in there, put the
tray icons in there, and call it good.
I mean, aren't the bars just really docks without animations?
I suppose.
One of the things I like about the Budgie desktop is I can now put this bar on my side
screen, and I suppose if you've got extra sides room on these 16 by 9 screens than you
do on the bottom, so there's that reason for it, but anyways, good post.
Lots of other stuff in there.
Link in the show notes, but want to talk about one more thing before we get to something
that is going to ruin the life of any Star Trek fan.
There is a proposal by your good friends over at Mozilla about turning on data collection
in the Fox.
Now I want to be clear about this.
This isn't like creepy data collection, and they are starting very gracefully.
They fully admit that they really don't have enough data on their users right now.
They need more data about the types of sites they go to, the type of browsing they do.
Are they using Flash?
Are they seeing a lot of junk?
How are the load times?
And so what Firefox wants to do, what Mozilla wants to do, is they want to use a privacy
project that allows them to collect data, but does it in a way that anonymizes essentially
the data using something called differential privacy.
So I believe the project is Rappor, Rapper, R-A-P-P-O-R, I think it's spelled.
And it's a project that Google works on, and it uses differential privacy, which sends
bogus data and real data, and then it's just sort of supposed to all work out in the wash
if you have enough users.
And they would install this, and they would anonymize the reporting, and then you would,
along with good reports, you would also be sending them completely crap stuff, which
is a weird approach.
But the idea is that the average is more good, and then if you look at that data, you get
something.
But so the theory behind it is they can't even use your habits to try to narrow down
who you are.
Now, initially, they're thinking about rolling this out as a opt-in to try it, but if they
decide to implement it, it's going to be turned on by default, and that's the part that's
really getting people pissed off.
Yeah, it's interesting that they're bringing this up so soon after the whole, the privacy
concerns with the plugin stuff.
Yeah, I thought the timing on this was kind of weird for, like that was just a couple
weeks ago, wasn't it?
From like a, so when you're down and out, and you know, you're getting your ass kicked
in the, you know, you just get kicked all over, I mean it's bad man, you get your ass
kicked on the ratings, I mean on the usage numbers, is that the time to launch a hey
we want to spy on you campaign?
I mean, I guess it depends on whether you consider it spying or not.
I don't, WW, what do you think?
Differential privacy is kind of the new hotness, Apple says they're going to use it in future
IOSs to anonymize data reporting, Mozilla says they need the data, what do you think
about this?
I think this should be an optional thing, it should be popping up when you first set
up Firefox, it should be hey, we want to do this, and we want your consent, and the thing
that I don't see with a lot of tools is that they don't give you an option to control the
data, so like, what's the, like.
You could, you can turn it off, you can turn it off, see.
Yeah, it should be upfront, they should be going, oh we're turning this off by default,
you know, just kind of like when there's telemetry, you know, it's on by default, oh, this patch,
it's like at what cost, you know.
I'm kind of on the opposite side of the fence with that though, because for usage analytics
to be useful, you need a large amount, and most people are just probably going to click
no.
I think they're going to, I think if they do this, they're going to bury the setting
probably in like a privacy tab inside settings, I don't think they would give you a pop-up
because of that reason, and I think that's why they, because they say currently we can
collect this data when the user opts in, but we don't have a way to collect unbiased data
without explicit consent, and so the problem that they're seeing is they're getting biased
data by people who are willing to opt in, and so they've got to solve that particular
problem and they're trying to use differential privacy to justify monitoring everyone.
And apparently the project they're using, the Google or whatever, apparently it's the
most widely distributed usage of differential privacy.
Yeah.
It probably would vary about config probably if they were to do or have that option though.
I mean, I don't really get the objection to truly anonymized usage statistics.
Like I can understand if you can be tied to it, but this seems like a pretty full-fledged
implementation of we're trying to anonymize this as much as humanly possible.
And you know it's data that Google and Apple are getting.
Yeah.
So, and their competitors are getting it.
What about, you know, years ago I used to think about this, I don't think about it anymore,
but doesn't collecting all of these metrics and having data collection points at every
little end of the application slow down the application?
Doesn't collecting this stuff in the background and uploading it constantly slow down the
network?
I mean, what the hell?
I mean, it can't be a lot, but damn, I mean, I want this shit to be as fast as possible.
It's just so frustrating.
But I know that's neither here nor there.
They say they-
Do you remember when Ubuntu had the Amazon scopes and people got obsessed?
It's kind of like that because with that you had the option of totally turning it off and
that's fine.
Or maybe on one system I had it on to if I was looking at Amazon or buying some things,
you know.
I can understand the objection to the Amazon scopes way more though, because it was directly
tying to individual users.
And the initial implementation wasn't all that secure either.
Yeah, that too.
So that definitely led to it.
But Minimac, you say it's sort of like equivalent to submitting a crash report.
Yeah.
I think if I remember well, if you first start Firefox with a new profile, you get a little
note at the bottom of the page which says, decide what you share.
And if you click on it, you see that the health and crash report is enabled by default and
you can disable it.
So I guess they just add another option for your personal data collection.
Or it might just be another line in that paragraph even.
Yeah.
That to me has way more potential to tell what you're doing with your browser than this
other stuff because you can get URLs and stuff in crash reports.
So they're validating this right now or they're about to.
They're about to.
They're doing an opt-out shield study, they say, to validate the implementation of this
differential privacy project.
The study will collect the value of users' homepage, which is that tile page that they
think is so important it's worth selling advertising on, the one that I spend exactly half a second
looking at once a day.
So they're gonna collect how much you guys click on those tiles and they're gonna select
a random group of their release population.
And they hope to launch mid-September, which isn't that around the time?
And then in November, you have 57.
You gotta wonder if this isn't gonna ship in 57 because they expect that one to get
a lot of downloads, I'm sure.
Yeah, maybe.
57's the, not only is it gonna, like the accumulation of a lot of their different projects, but
it's also the new UI.
Yeah.
It's gonna get all the attention.
If it's not in 57, it'll almost definitely be in 58.
Yeah.
So they're gonna launch their test pilot soon.
Speaking of privacy, Plex really stepped in it over the weekend and they've backpedaled
a bit already since we've recorded this, but they announced that they were going to launch
a data collection process that wouldn't really report on the files in your library, but would
give them all kinds of metrics and you couldn't turn it off.
So they're upping their privacy policy and they're retracting on some of that.
But I gotta tell you, I saw a lot of angry comments from the audience who said they're
trying out MB after this, so check out some of our past episodes on MB if you're looking
for an alternative.
Honestly, to me it seems kind of like the same situation, because it wasn't about them
collecting data on your files, it was collecting usage statistics again.
Yeah.
Well, a lot of people are watching pirated content on Plex.
And I feel like a lot of people will probably go in there and turn that off specifically,
so they're not getting the usage statistics that they want.
So they've been pretty clear now after this release that they have no way of tracking
which files you're playing unless you use a client that talks to a cloud service to
initiate playback.
So if you're using an Echo or a third-party app that uses the Plex Cloud API to start
a file on your Plex server, in that case they do have logs of which file you're starting.
I like that they actually made that clear.
They said if you're just using the Plex app on your phone or on the TV or on your web
browser and you're watching the latest episode of Game of Thrones, they didn't say that,
I'm putting that part in.
They don't know.
They don't know what file you're watching, they just know you're watching content, basically.
Don't know, man.
I'm getting really...
I feel like I'm getting privacy bankrupt.
That's what it is.
In one or two instances, I'm okay with this.
I made this compromise when I put Echo dots in the studio.
Well, see, the problem is all of-
But in the totality, I'm getting sick of it.
All of these different developers, they need statistics on how their stuff is used to make
their products better.
Yeah.
I know.
I guess the first 30 years of making software where they didn't have always-on internet-connected
machines constantly sending back metrics, somehow they still managed to make good software.
Do you think software was good?
Yeah, actually, in some ways, I think it was better than it is today because it didn't
have so many damn interdependent connections.
I guess I agree.
I understand this is a hard problem.
We need to know what episodes are downloaded, although we don't track beyond the number.
I really hate to see Plex going down this path, and I hate them doing it ham-fisted,
and the fact that they've had to make this big, huge public retraction is embarrassing
for Plex.
And honestly, I think in some ways, because we don't collect more information, we're
disadvantaging ourselves, but we do that consciously.
Yeah.
Wouldn't it be interesting if we had...
If there was some way...
And I don't know how you would have this.
If there was some way we could know exactly how many new users use Linux versus how many
computer experts use Linux?
Or even stuff like being able to track what part of the show people watch.
Yeah, YouTube gives you that.
Yeah, but that's a limited subset of our audience.
It's a very small subset, so it's kind of...
I mean, you can draw some conclusions from it, but it'd be...
There's so much more data out there if you could get all of it.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's what...
You could tell our content to what people want without having to poll them for what
they want.
That's what big advertisers have been trying to get different podcast apps to start collecting
data, which is a creepy, slippery slope in my world, because to me, there's other ways
of sussing that out besides getting playback locations.
You can tell by feedback from the audience, what they respond to.
You can tell by all that.
There's all kinds of ways to get that.
But the problem with that is you're gonna get that biased feedback.
I guess.
But really, I mean, built-in metrics to everything we use, it feels like I'm getting nickel and
dime to death with my privacy.
I mean, you really don't care that every app you almost use today...
Think about it.
Every app we pretty much use today is sending back usage data.
Doesn't really bother me, to be honest.
I mean, as long as they're not using something to try to track me down specifically, I don't
care.
Hmm.
I draw the line at health information or stuff around my house.
I don't really like them collecting when certain things turn on or off.
That kind of stuff feels like it's too far.
That definitely is too far.
That's where things are going, though.
Well, I mean, it depends on what you choose to support.
Yeah.
Anyway, Mumbo, any thoughts on the Plex data collection, Firefox data collection, or the
topic of data collection in general?
I know it's gotta be on some of your minds, because just everything...
Are you guys feeling this, like nickel and dimed privacy death here?
The thing is, for me, is I understand that projects have to have some way to monetize
and some way to get this information.
Going about it like a jealous boyfriend or someone that's gonna key log you to see what
you're doing is not the way to go about it.
You can talk to people, have a discussion with people that use your software, and make
it so they can actually use the software.
I really want companies, or if I had my own company, I would make it so users had an option
to see what data we're using, and when they want, delete it.
You have to have some kind of level of respect for people that are giving up this privacy
for these services.
Okay.
That's a great point, WW.
Let's take that the next step, say, okay, they need this somehow, plus some of them
can monetize it, so it's a way to fund future development.
If we hold those things true, and for sake of argument, we accept that differential privacy
is legitimate, and that this project that Mozilla's using from Google is also legitimate,
is that the right compromise then?
Is the beard right?
Like, okay, you can collect your data, but use differential privacy to fuzz it, and still
give me the option at the end of the day to turn it off.
It's gonna be on by default, but it's fuzzed, and you can turn it off, and is that sort
of a good enough compromise for you, because it gives Firefox the data they need, it lets
them make a better product, it lets them know where to focus development, but it is at least
using differential privacy.
It depends, like, how is this going...
Like, the thing is, once you're on the slope, how slippery does it get?
Yeah, that's how I'm feeling.
Because you have to, like, okay, we know, like, you, me, Rekai, anybody that's mobile
right now and watching, like, we're in techno, like, you're either technologically advocate,
you're technologically inclined, you work in tech, we know that there's DEF CON, there's
someone out there, like, looking for weakness.
You just know that by default.
So to us, we know the covets of such things, but to the average user, they don't know,
they're not gonna know, they don't care.
That's a lot of what I run into with people I know, or other people, so...
Default reigns supreme.
See, I feel like, especially in the case of Firefox and this differential privacy project,
both of these are open source, so people can go and see exactly what they're collecting.
This is actually rare, not probably super common, but thank God.
I mean, really, if you're really super worried about it, there is an escape hatch here for
you.
You're right.
And it does look like it's a legitimate project, it does seem to be very popular, it does have
a lot of contributors, and Google is a main sponsor of it.
Google obviously has skin in the game to create ways to monitor people that doesn't get them
in trouble.
It's probably how they watch students.
Especially with recent EU lawsuits.
How much you want to bet this is what they use for Google apps, to say that they're not
specifically tracking you, but they're still collecting metrics.
That's probably why they...
They are so creepy.
All right, well, let's take a moment, because I'm so excited.
In fact, there's something that happened to me this week, besides the solar...
This might be more...
Boy, that's...
Let's see.
Seeing celestial objects line up in the sky in front of me and be in the path of the shadow
of heavenly bodies is a big event to happen to a person.
But stage nine also happened to me this week, and I'm going to tell you about stage nine,
which may have a more long-lasting impact on me, and more importantly, you.
But first, let's talk about making yourself better before we kill all of your time.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Go there to support the show and sign up for a free seven-day trial.
It's a platform to learn all about Linux.
They've just expanded on some of their AWS stuff just recently.
And I think for me, I would have killed for something like this, because I really suffered
from anxiety of, I got to go to this client, and I have got to go do this thing that we
just...
Our sales guy just told them I knew how to do, and I've done it maybe once, two years
ago.
And that's where these hands-on labs for me were just...
Boy, that'd be a game changer.
And now, just giving me just the ability to experience it, such a great feature.
If they only did this, Linux Academy would be worth it.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Of course, they have so many more features.
You know, Chris, I'm going to take a different tack with this.
Go for it.
I mean, you took the whole nice business angle.
Me, I'm going to say that you can become a Linux genius in your underwear.
Well, that's definitely true.
I mean, you think about it, what better way to become a genius on something than in your
underwear?
Exactly.
Because you're not distracted by all those scratchy clothes.
The best way to learn is no pants.
I completely agree.
No pants and just the right temperature, the music you like going, I think it's maybe
light a candle.
I mean, I'm not going to judge you.
They also have self-paced in-depth video courses in every Linux cloud and DevOps topic.
They have instructor mentoring, you know, humans that are available to help you.
In fact, one of those humans is in Seattle right now.
They have a course schedule that works with your busy schedule.
They have flashcards that get forked by the community.
They have cert training that goes right into courses for like a path to get a certification.
And I really think that if you want something that is sort of scratching that podcast itch
and that sort of audio book itch, their content you can download and listen to offline is
perfect for that.
So let me be clear.
You're telling me that I can, there's the humans doing this and not Elon Musk style
AI?
This is what they do.
They're all about it.
In fact, if you check out their Twitter feed, you'll see some of that.
Linux Academy com.
Also, they were just honored to be one of the companies included on the 5,000 list of
fastest growing companies.
Have you seen this at Inc 5,000?
I just saw this on their Twitter feed and I pulled it up right here on the show.
Inc.com, Linux Academy.
Look at that number 78 on the-
Wow, top 100.
Yeah.
That's amazing.
Holy crap.
Look at those.
Boy, you should go there.
You should go to-
That must be some pretty big roads to be on top 100.
Here's what I'm going to tell you to do.
We'll leave it as an exercise to the listener to go to Linux Academy's feed, to a Twitter
feed, Linux Academy com and then look at this link.
But give me one guess on what you think their three-year growth percentage was.
1,045%.
More.
2,800%.
10,000%.
Hold on.
I'm not going to give it away.
I'm not going to give it away, but the link is in their Twitter feed if you'd like to
know.
LinuxAcademy.com.
There's a reason why they've grown like crazy in the last three years.
It's probably because they've been sponsoring us.
The Jupyter Broadcasting Effect, LinuxAcademy.com slash Unplugged, a free seven-day trial and
keep us on the air.
Now this is a self-indulgent moment for me, but it is newsworthy.
A version for Linux will be shipping today, a brand new version of Stage 9.
Now what is Stage 9?
That sounds like a Microsoft video blog.
Yeah, no, it doesn't, does it?
It is a project to recreate the entire set of the NCC-1701D Enterprise from the Star
Trek The Next Generation.
And it is using the Unreal Engine 4, which means it works on a lot of graphics systems.
And if you have a good graphics system, it's unbelievably gorgeous.
If you're on Windows, it also has VR support.
The Linux version, ironically right now, is just being held up by packaging issues.
So remember how we were saying that packaging isn't a big problem on Linux?
Yeah, it's, yeah.
I thought they should ship it as an app image.
Well, I actually suggested a snap, but yeah, an app image would also be really great.
But they do have the last release for Linux available right now, which is still great,
still a lot of fun.
And if you're on the Mac platform, they also have a Metal version, if you want to see what
Metal's like, I guess.
Sorry, I don't mean to laugh, but you could do that too, if you wanted to do that.
I think I might have an app to slip in Wimpy's pocket.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
Well, that may or may not have already happened.
Oh, yeah.
That may have already been a thing.
So Stage 9 is available for Linux.
You can download version 7 very soon, version 0.7.
Right here, I've got version.06.
And it's as cool as you would think, even on my NVIDIA GTX 960 here.
This is running on Solus with the proprietary NVIDIA driver.
We'll start here.
I'll show you the bridge a little bit, if you're watching the video version.
It looks great.
And I actually have this on medium camera settings, I can actually turn it up a little
bit to high.
Hey, Chris.
There we go.
You know what?
We are under attack.
Oh, really?
Do you need me to trigger red alert?
Yes.
Okay, standby.
There we go.
All right.
Battle stations.
We are now at battle stations.
So this is pretty great.
And like I was talking about, if you've got a good graphics card, it's a great way to
really push your Linux right, because one of the things that is a little disappointing
sometimes is some of the games can't really push the high-end video cards.
This thing definitely can, and if I had VR set up on Windows, I would definitely be giving
this a go.
Anyways, stage nine.
A nice way that they hid the loading screens, Chris, was...
Through the turbo lift.
Yeah, the turbo lifts are the loading screens.
I would call out a few things.
So this shot, it's just a really simple hallway shot here, but the lighting, and this is on
a GTX 960 on medium graphics.
It's the last generation.
Yeah.
And there's reflections on the metal wall panels that are gorgeous.
When you come into the main engineering here, there is a little bit of a JJ Abrams lens
flare effect from the warp drive.
I don't know if this will come through in the download version, but it supports positional
audio.
So when I move around the engine room, the sound of the warp drive changes depending
on where I'm standing, which is just the coolest thing.
All of the panels that you saw used, everything's accurate.
In fact, I've been walking around this ship by memory from the show.
It is remarkably accurate.
It is an incredible recreation.
It's one of the coolest Star Trek things I've ever used, and it's on Linux.
You know what, Chris?
You say that, I got to say I'm really disappointed.
Oh yeah?
What's wrong?
It's called stage nine.
Yeah.
Where's Deep Space Nine?
Out right outside the window.
Yeah.
Check this out.
Let's go here.
So let's see.
We'll go to 10 forward.
I'll take you to 10 forward.
So here's the funny thing.
I don't know about this version, but in the version seven I watched in their YouTube video,
they have a shuttle bay.
Hello there.
Hi.
How are you?
Are you having a good day?
So are you saying that there might be a possibility someday?
You can take the shuttle out.
You can take the shuttle out, and you could probably one someday go to Deep Space Nine.
Okay.
I'm in.
So if I go out the window here, I think, oh no, I guess not.
You can see Bajor, but just right there is Deep Space Nine, but you can only see the
bottom of the docking because it's above the ship.
It's all spatially correct.
This is really cool.
It's cool.
But really, we want to go and visit Quark's.
Yeah, that would be great.
So they have all the different levels on here too, which is just, again, if you're a geek,
it's a lot of fun if you're a Star Trek geek.
But even if you just want to push your Linux rig or play around with an Unreal-based engine
game on Linux, there's a few of them now, obviously, but this one's a pretty special
one.
Lots of hidden stuff.
All the cool sets, including the Arboretum, data in the worst quarters, the data center
of the Enterprise, which is a particularly great map on this.
It's almost, I wish we could show it.
If you want to see it, check out the full live stream if you're a patron.
I walked through the data center of the Enterprise in the pre-show, so I'll be posting that for
our patrons.
Here's a critical feature question.
Can you sit down like a Riker?
Yeah.
You mean step over the chair?
I don't think so.
Yeah, I don't think they've added that yet.
They should.
There's a few things.
There's definitely a few nods and stuff like that that are in there, but yeah, so it's
stage nine.
I had a chance to chat with one of the developers on Discord this morning before the show, and
I was asking him, what's going on with the Linux packaging stuff?
What's a hard time?
Oh, well, look at that.
He just legitimately, right now as we're recording, wow, four minutes ago, just posted the log.
If you might be able to help him get this off the ground, they have a Discord server
where the devs prefer to be reached, and that is linked on the stage nine page, and then
he just posted, and I'll link to this in the show notes, their build log issues, and this
is what's holding them up from getting the latest version on Linux.
It looks like he keeps getting a lib curl issue.
Yeah.
Yeah, I'll put a link to that in the show notes, and maybe I'll send that along to some
of our friends that work in packaging, because it'd be really cool to get this available
easily for Linux users, because it's a pretty cutting edge thing, and when VR support comes,
it's going to be one of the few really nice Unreal 4 things that we can try out.
I know that's not on everybody's priority list, but something about me, the old Linux
advocate in me, I just don't want to see a slip behind on this kind of stuff, and it's
so great to see just some fan project like this that doesn't have a ton of time trying
to make it work on Linux.
I really appreciate that, and in big parts because of the Unreal Engine, but sure makes
it look pretty.
Stage 9, if you want to check it out directly, the website is stage-9.co.uk, and I'll have
a link in the show notes, and that's where you, at their Stage 9 websites, where you
can find their Discord channel.
They also have a subreddit, which, as you would think, which figures Stage 9 on Reddit.
Anyway, I thought that was kind of a neat thing.
I know you're not a big Star Trek guy, but if I did manage to get the VR set up here,
would you give it a go?
Does it have to have the walking component, because I guess that's part of it, right?
Well, I mean, you can use the controllers.
But I don't know.
I really want it.
I want DS9.
Yeah.
Boy, the amount of work that it goes to creating this, these are every detail down to the materials
and just like everything, like the stitching to the carpet is accurate, so I can't imagine
the time.
Just imagine all the time that they had to go through and re-watch all those episodes
and rebuild these scenes and probably look at concept art and all kinds of crazy stuff.
So I asked one of the developers, I said, so is this a license?
Is this a license?
I'm kind of getting at it.
If this is open source, this is something that people could really kind of get around
here.
And the official answer is they're just distributing it as a binary, and there's no implicit license
they're attaching with that at this time.
So I would imagine that's all rights reserved.
Keeping their options open.
Yeah, all rights reserved for the time being.
But not only is it just an impressive technology demo, because you download this thing on Linux,
you run it, and now you're in this incredibly gorgeous 3D rendering, which is a lot of fun
to try out on your graphics, different graphics cards, and seeing how they perform, which
for me is just a fun benchmark, and seeing how hot they get and all that kind of stuff.
But then to see such an accurate recreation of something that I'm such a big fan of, it
was pretty impressive.
And it's been, you know, there's been times, there has been times where as a Linux user
I was left out, so it was really great that they...
And these, by the way, screenshots that I'm showing, if you're watching the video version,
are in-game renderings.
They even have the battle bridge.
Speaking of Star Trek and times you were left out, how's Sto going?
So they've moved to DirectX 11 only, and Wine is at a good clip, but Wine is still fully
implementing DirectX 11 support, so yeah, I've had to take a break.
That might explain my passion for this.
For jonesing.
Yeah, because I've been lacking any Star Trek gameplay on Linux for a while.
If anybody else out there has Star Trek games that they've played under Wine, let me know
at ChrisLAS, because I'll definitely kill time while the Wine project gets...
I know they'll get there eventually.
Yeah.
They'll get there eventually.
Hey, so want a little more Beardsley?
Want a little more of the Rekai here?
Check out User Air.
He's on User Air every damn week, and we've got a new episode coming out in a few days.
And my old buddy John, who hasn't been on for a while, joins us and shares some pretty
funny stories.
It was a great episode.
We also talked about Linux extremism.
Yeah.
Also, just a warning, this episode is probably a little bit more not safe for work than most.
Which is really saying something, actually.
Yeah.
Okay, maybe a lot more.
Well, it depends.
It depends.
I guess it depends on what you're into.
Yeah.
So did you have anything you wanted to plug before we ran out of here?
You can just find me on Twitter at RekaiLP or over at Rek.net.
Rek.net.
Yeah.
Or my Twitch.
I've got to come up with a good name for the vlog, because I'm going to be posting our
clip story.
There were some interesting challenges on our way down to the eclipse, so I'm going
to post all that on my vlog, which is YouTube.com slash Chris Fisher.
You know what, Chris?
It needs a good name.
Chris, I can offer you a free subdomain, hair.rek.net, you can forward to YouTube.
There you go.
I guess one more thing I'll plug, just because it's been pretty popular the last few days
and it just seems to be growing more and more, is our Discord, Discord.me slash Jupiter Colony.
There's a lot of people on there and it's a pretty nice place.
And if Telegram is more of your flavor, well guess what?
We got one of those too.
Go to Jupiterbroadcasting.com slash Telegram and join in the group conversation over there.
I try to pop in all over the place, in and out, but the conversation's always going on
even when I'm not in there.
You can also find Beardsley in there from time to time.
There's just all kinds of ways to get you.
It's pretty good.
Alright everybody, well thank you so much for tuning in to this week's episode.
Hopefully Mr. West's car troubles are all fixed.
We've got to get him a Linux running car, so the Linux powers, it doesn't break down
on him.
Because I'm sure that would solve all of his problems.
And for people looking for a tech snap after they finish watching LUP.
Oh, that's coming.
Yeah.
It's just going to be a little bit.
Yeah, a little bit.
Alright, we'll see you next week.
Alright, JBtitles.com, let's go pick our title.
Mumble Room, we were small in number, but you guys did great.
Mr. Fax, I never got it.
Or Robo, we have Robo the Arms back too.
RoboArm, RobotArm, whatever, I never get it right, but it's good to see you guys.
Thank you for making it two this week.
Impersonates it.
And now let's go pick our title.
What do you think?
One more job before we get out of here, gentlemen, before we ride off into the sunset, should
we go pick our title?
JBtitles.com.
Well, Beardsley, I was glad you were able to make it.
Kind of a lower key show, it felt like overall.
It's a lot easier for me to make it.
Yeah, that's true.
Well, you have less car troubles.
But yeah, it felt like a lower key show, but still good, right?
It still felt good, didn't you think?
Was I right?
If you have any notes, as they say, chat room on today's episode, or mumble room, feel free
to submit them to us before we get out of here.
But I thought it was a good episode, just a little low key.
I think, as with every week, many people are going to hate me.
Oh, you think?
And some people are going to love me.
Geez, I mostly hear all good things.
People like hearing, people call you, you know, the, what do they say?
The man of the people.
The pragmatist?
Yeah, the man of the people.
I just think it's like people, like I grew up with a net, like when it was really starting
to penetrate into the public.
And so my opinions are different than Rekai's, but I love hearing Rekai's and talking to
him about it.
That's what I love is that I can respect him and talk about him and get more information
or get links and just process him more.
Sometimes you have to just disagree and move on.
Yeah, I agree.
Yeah, exactly.
We need a lot more of that.
How young do you think I am that he doesn't think I was around when the internet was new
too?
I mean, thank you.
I'm like five years older than Chris, so.
Fair enough.
So what about, so Privacy Bankruptcy by Token Ring is good.
It's in competition with Windcloud's Cry, which is also good.
We could also jazz it up and we could say Mozilla's Privacy Bankruptcy.
No?
Okay.
Too jazzed?
Firefox?
I don't like Privacy Bankruptcy myself.
Wow.
Of course, I was also taking the opposite opinion.
JBtitles.com, JBtitles.com.
Windcloud's Cry?
It rains.
What's that in reference to?
Specifically?
I would imagine Mozilla not have enough data.
Or maybe the backups.
I think more of the backups.
So I guess it multi.
It sort of covers both, which is kind of good.
That always kind of, you know, I'm going to toss a boat in for Windcloud's Cry.
I'm going to give it a boat.
I'm going to give it a, now we're.
I also kind of like Forks Done Right.
Forks Done Right is good too.
WW coming with it.
Oh man.
All right.
So we got to do some consolidated voting because we got a bunch of really good contenders
here at the top.
So everybody head over.
Do me a solids.
Oh, how about how to measure off Fox?
Windcloud's Cry currently leading.
JBtitles.
So now that I'm back on Solus, I have the actual Spotify desktop client installed again
for like the first time in a while because that shit definitely broke at Anagros months
ago.
So yeah, someone earlier was having trouble with tap to click or something in me.
The problem.
What's that?
The tap to click is always a problem.
So Forks Done Right and When Clouds Cry are tied now.
Forks Done Right was probably the most energetic time of the show.
Tell you what, Chris, how to measure a Fox is climbing up there.
Jeez.
That's I like the way it looks on the screen.
Yeah.
JBtitles.com.
So we got to break out.
We got to break out.
Oh, God, you guys.
Are you guys are you guys screwing with me because that was happening right now because
we have we have a tie.
Ah, I've never installed GNU slash Linux.
Forks Done Right pulling ahead with one boat right now.
We need like a timer.
Alexa.
Set a thirty second timer.
Thirty seconds.
No, just she's too stupid.
She's too stupid.
We need the 24 sound effect for the time counting down.
What did she set the timer for?
What?
This is too stupid timer.
I presume for 30 seconds.
So she wanted a name for the timer?
Is that what she meant?
She wanted the time, but then afterwards we named it too stupid.
The thing with the echo is if you don't nail that syntax, it just don't work.
That's so dumb.
Anyways, Forks Done Right is pulling way ahead now with 12.
I kind of like it, too.
Oh, it's done.
Just do stupid timer.
That's good, dude.
Stupid timer is done.
All right.
Good job, everybody.
We're gonna go with Forks Done Right.
Why is she still talking?
Apparently she was letting you know again.
Okay, Alexa, I feel like she's harassing us.
Alexa, remove timer.
God damn, it's broken.
Alexa.
Stop.
He's not answering me.