Holy smokes, Wes, look alive.
It's perfect timing for Linux Unplugged today.
We are going to be getting into a conversation around different methods of crowdfunding open
source projects, and one of the titans of Kickstarter has launched their brand new Kickstarter
project today.
They're not struggling, though, Wes.
They have already raised, of a goal of a million, four million, oh boy, 22,000 backers with
36 days left to go.
They're only a few hours into this thing.
It's the new Pebble 2, Time 2, and the Pebble Core.
Hey, Kickstarter.
We're Pebble.
Hey there.
In 2012, we came to you with an idea called a smartwatch.
Your incredible support helped Pebble smash Kickstarter records not once, but twice, and
ushered in a revolution in wearable technology.
OMG, OMG, OMG.
Today, we've come home to Kickstarter to push these boundaries even further.
Introducing Pebble 2, a sporty, ultra-affordable smartwatch with a built-in heart rate monitor.
Time 2, a premium smartwatch for the active professional, and Pebble Core, an entirely
new device for runners that connects to your cellular network and fits in the palm of your
hand.
Hey, gang.
It's time to write the next chapter in wearables.
Am I part of gang?
I want to be in the gang.
Yeah, we're in the gang, dude.
Pebble 2 is our latest smartwatch, now with built-in activity tracking.
So they got the new watch, now hold on, because this isn't the one you're interested in.
But it's neat that it has real-time heart rate all the time.
It's waterproof.
It does microphones so you can do dictation.
That's all neat.
But oh boy.
And with a single click, Pebble 2 is an all-around amazing smartwatch.
And starting at just $99, it's the most affordable smartwatch ever.
All right, so that's the Pebble 2.
But now...
We're excited to announce Time 2, our all-new premium full-color smartwatch.
Machined from marine-grade stainless steel in gold, black, or silver, Time 2 introduces
a crisp new color e-paper display that's 53% larger than the original and packs twice the
text on screen, keeping you up to date at a glance.
Time 2's battery lasts up to 10 whole days on a single charge.
Now that is amazing.
10 days?
Wow.
And like Pebble 2, it has a mic, heart rate monitor, and is water-resistant to 30 meters.
Both watches also feature an updated version of Pebble Health.
Now you can tell Pebble your activity and fitness goals, and it sets targets that automatically
adjust based on your performance.
Now they also have the new Pebble Core, which is basically just a voice-activated push-button
little activity tracker.
Pebble's getting big into fitness, huge into fitness.
So you could leave your phone at home.
I like that.
Core streams music from Spotify to keep you motivated.
So that's kind of a neat thing.
So we're going to be talking about this today, and not necessarily the Pebble, but I think
it's really interesting timing for some of the subjects we're getting into, Wes.
Are you ready to get started?
Oh yeah.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 146 for May 24, 2016.
Oh, welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's skipping pebbles into
the body of water that is our Mumble Room.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Was that profound, Wes?
I'm not going to pretend that made sense, but let's just keep going.
The body of water.
I also liked Rekai's fighting the Windows 10 upgrade menace.
Oh, much better.
Yeah, stay tuned for the Poe Show for more on that.
Coming up on today's episode of the Unplugged program, we are going to talk a little bit
about funding open source projects, but in a new light, in something we've never really
done before, in projects that have a bit of a name and a bit of a reputation, good and
bad.
We're going to start with the Mycroft project today, which is delivering some actual software,
which we have loaded there and HamRadio has been trying out, but we're also going to talk
about Purism.
They have a new initiative, a new piece of hardware.
They claim it is the Microsoft Surface for those of you who respect your privacy and
freedom.
Big promises.
But can we rely on Purism to deliver a product like this when you could argue they haven't
even mastered the last product they launched?
As you can imagine, I have thoughts on this topic, so we'll be discussing that coming
up in the show.
But before all of that, Wes, before all of that, we have some great open source project
updates.
How did you get all these links this week?
Like, this was a Wes blowout.
They've just fallen out of the sky.
You were blowing it out, this.
You were just blowing it out, Wes.
Just blowing it out.
Speaking of blowing it out, you were blowing it out with the beer, too.
Well, hopefully you won't be blowing it out.
It's a delicious beer, and I...
We have to restrain ourselves, Chris.
Once again, you have managed to bring a beer into the Unplugged program.
This is from a local brewery that I've never heard of.
Sneaking it in under your radar.
Copper Donkey.
Copper Donkey from the No Lee, I think is how you say it.
No Lie?
Probably, probably.
It's L-I.
L-I.
I don't know.
It is... Oh, it's a good beer, though.
It's kind of new.
It's from a new brewery they launched just a year ago.
And it is also fairly strong at 8%.
They're doing a good job already.
So Wes brought us a couple of pints.
So we'll be drinking that on today's program, drinking along with you, water, beer, whatever
your beverage of choice is.
Let's bring in that Mamba Room.
Time of property greetings, Mamba Room.
Greetings, users.
Greetings.
I've never installed Gnome slash Linux.
Hi, hi.
Wow.
That is a huge turn in.
I think I even heard some Richard Stallman in there.
That is unbelievable.
Oh, you guys.
Oh, jeez, Louise.
Okay, so I want to talk about this one just really quick.
Well, there's a plane flying overhead right now.
Wes, do you hear that?
I do.
Our friends from the south, Mr. Bowen.
So maybe it's somebody from this new project to come here to talk to us in person because
it could be a big deal.
You may have heard it before, formerly known, the artist formerly known as XDG App is now
Flapjack with a brand new fancy website at Flap or Flat Pack, not Flapjack.
Although I got to imagine, if you think about it, Flapjack is a good metaphor here.
Yeah, I picture stacking individual delicious pancakes on top of each other that don't necessarily
connect until I take my delicious butter and syrup and I mash my fork down in between them
and then bring them all together with my fork stab and put them in my mouth, hence installing
software.
This is why Chris is not a software architect.
No, but they should just talk to me first because I think if they would talk to me-
That's a great breakfast bar though.
Because, you know, they're going for those Ikea easy to pack things, but I'm telling
you a pancakes might just play a little better.
Anyways, Flat Pack is the future of application distribution, according to them.
The days of chasing multiple Linux distributions are over.
You hear that playing with?
Standalone apps for Linux are here, self-contained and future proof.
Distributing applications on Linux is a pain.
Different distributions-
Don't we know it.
Different distros, multiple versions, each with their own versions of libraries, but
Flat Pack is here to change all of that.
It's cross-platform, it's stable, and it's secure.
So you've, you know, another thing you've heard of in another way.
So XEG apps, you've also probably heard this referred to a sandbox apps to make it possible
for third parties to distribute applications.
We talked with someone from the known project in Linux action show about this in our Linux
Fest Northwest coverage.
I don't know Wes, they have a demo here.
I think they're really close to shipping it.
It almost feels like it's now in that spot where is anybody going to ever adopt this?
That's what's going to matter here.
We have that.
We have a app image.
Mumble of many thoughts on anyone ever adopting this.
Will it actually take off?
Will upstream packages embrace this?
I think no, we're going to embrace it quite heavily.
I mean, they're the ones really pushing this.
It's their runtime that's doing all the flat pack stuff right now.
The sticking point for me is still the inefficiency of it.
Like I don't want to have 20 copies of the known runtime for my 20 different flat pack
apps.
Yeah.
Do you see a way around that though and trying to accomplish what they're accomplishing?
I don't, but I think the use case of where they're trying to accomplish it, you know,
it might be a case of just needing that niche of, it's the same niche that's kind of taken
out by rolling releases.
So if I kind of think with my tumbleweed hat, it's like, yeah, I don't care.
If I think with my leap hat on though, yeah, I can see us bundling up flat pack apps and
pushing out shiny and new versions of known maps when previously that would be like a
complete and utter no no.
Yeah.
They have right now on their page, they have nightly builds of GIMP, Inkscape, Darktable,
MyPaint and Scribulous, and they're working on stable builds of the known core applications.
The other thing we have to keep in mind is at the same time this is happening, Canonical
has their own solution, which is snap packages, which is sort of a similar solution for their
specific platform.
And I wonder if that's going to be sort of a duplication of effort on some levels.
For example, if the Gnome desktop could be bundled up as a snap package, then what about
also bundling up as a flat pack?
Is who's going to do that work?
I think flat pack has way more going for it because they're trying to be cross distro
because they're working with all these other other projects, other distros that then, you
know, it's known.
They don't just think about themselves.
Whereas Ubuntu is going to work fine on Ubuntu, but is it going to work anywhere else?
But I think if you I see I would tend to agree with you, except if you look at the way history
has played out when it comes to just packaging up installation packages for distributions,
you see very much very much like in terms of people will go out of their way to package
up for Ubuntu and in a lot of cases, just Ubuntu.
Yeah, that's true.
And that feels like the same thing.
Maybe they're just going to focus on snap packages instead of flat packs.
I look at you know, I look at there's there's projects out there that we are all familiar
with that will soon be repackaged individual components in the entire desktop as snap packages.
They're working on it right now.
And I don't think they're working on flat packs.
That's the thing is the projects I'm thinking of, I already know are working on snap versions,
and I don't know they're working on anything else.
But doesn't that kind of like erode the whole cross distro, you know, appeal?
I mean, the appeal of a flat pack is you do it once and it will work on every distro plus
Ubuntu.
Yeah, I agree.
I mean, if you apply it so much to snap packet packages right now, the only people interested
in snap packages are Ubuntu.
It's like you might as well just do it Ubuntu dev.
I completely agree.
I just I worry that the problem is the people that are making these decisions are idiots
or something.
I don't know why.
I mean, today, I couldn't tell you why so many of them only package for Ubuntu.
I mean, I could it's market share related, but that might just be what pushes them to
use snap packages.
I don't know.
It's probably you're right.
Because flat pack includes Ubuntu, you hope that gives it the nudge ahead.
That just means people will and if they can get behind the mind, if they can get mind
share out there.
And the other issue is Canonical has some momentum behind mind share already.
And they just the ability to promote a little bit better as a company that has resources
to do so and avenues to do so.
And if they can have a good, you know, they can be like, hey, look, have the shiny apps
user base that's already going to install 1604, then they might have a good in road
to actually get people using it.
You can get you can try that right now, though.
It's out there.
So I really want to talk about today just so that we sort of have flat pack now on our
radar instead of XD.
I guess it'll probably depend to like how easy is it to create one or the other?
Yeah.
How well will they integrate into different build tools or build change that people are
already using?
I'm listening to that right now.
It might be worth playing with.
You'd be like, hey, Mike, just target this and go.
I actually like the idea of flat pack and snaps just because I don't have to worry about,
you know, whenever I update my system or right now that I'm on 1510 and like 20 apps that
I want to try, I can't even get yet.
I agree.
I think it makes the I think it makes long term support and enterprise distros way more
viable to if you can get more modern applications and have a nice stable base.
I think that's going to be really sweet.
What do you what do you think, Wes?
So the chat room is asking, why not?
Why not app image?
Why are we why are we not just app image is already a thing.
There's already project shipping with app images.
Why don't we just use an app image, Wes?
It seems like it's going to be the same thing.
It's going to come back to adoption.
And there are a few people like subsurface obviously thinks it's great.
And I don't know, I haven't made an app.
So I guess it would come back to like, how easy is it to integrate into existing build
systems?
How, how hard is it to just go from packaging for distros already and having it ship in
one of these packages?
You know, if Ubuntu provides a really good thing where hey, you're making a dab already,
bam, now you have your snap package, then that would be really nice if it's harder to
make a flat pack or an app image.
App image seems like it's pretty simple.
I haven't looked too much into, you know, here installing a runtime, etc.
But I'd be interested to see a comparison.
They have their own build kit and to it's not it's not bad at all.
And app image is really interesting, because when you first run it, you have to give you
have to manually give it permission to execute.
But once you launch it, it asks, do you want to put it in your your menus, right, like
automatically does that.
So that's pretty cool.
And maybe it's the excuse that or that the complaint that everyone goes against canonical
is like, not developed here.
Maybe gnome is doing the exact same thing.
And for some reason, people aren't mentioning that.
Yeah, and it's a shame we don't have something like the like what we're they're working on,
like on container standards, you know, some sort of here, we're gonna have static static
images keeping contained at all, actually, well, I will just in the same way of having
some sort of standard for if we're gonna do if we're gonna have less, you know, dynamic
linking, etc, in our in future ways that we're shipping software be cool, if we had some
sort of underlying target so that we could have, here's a snap, we can convert it to
a flight.
Right?
Yeah, for sure.
Like, yeah, absolutely.
I think, I think it's two things.
I think it's two things to answer the core question, why not app image right now, I think
the first thing is, is that the gnome guys have been and gals have been working on this
for years, I if you if you recall back, I covered this story as gnome OS, and it's in
a sense, years ago, like they've been working on different iterations of this crazy idea
of applications that can move around.
And it's only really once they kind of let it die off.
And it was only really once since containers and sandboxing and all these kinds of different
things like Wayland and namespaces all started to become available options that we could
actually ship one day, they got serious about it again.
And a core component of it for them, this, I believe, is the second part is sandboxing.
They believe sandboxing fundamentally, and I've linked it in their wiki why they believe
this.
And they don't they don't want to use sandboxing for the reasons that like you traditionally
think of like, prevent you from getting access to things on your system, it is legitimately
to isolate the application to move it around and to protect the overall system.
And that's a core functionality for them.
And they see it not just core to security, but core to how these things are portable
to begin with.
And I think app image is a great solution.
I personally am I'm happy to download an app image thing.
I just really have it really hasn't been an issue for me.
Yeah, exactly.
App Images has actually been around for a while too, because they were originally the
portable apps.
Mm hmm.
That's true.
And it's really it's a really cool idea.
But as far as like, the containerization in the sandboxing, they don't really have any
of that.
So so I guess in a way, they're kind of improving the concept with the Flatpak, and also Flatpak
is a cooler name.
Yeah, way better.
Yeah, they're doing a better job with the branding.
So hopefully that will help, you know, people ship.
And I think the other thing that just maybe just to finish up the mindshare thing is I
think this is another example of mindshare, where mindshare makes a difference in app
image has gotten traction among some of us, but it just really hasn't gotten the mindshare.
And part of that is, and this is the part we just have a hard time connecting the dots
with is there are people from the known project that are going out to technology conferences
like Linux plumbers conference and, and, and then in the Gwadek and Fedora's and all the
different conferences, and they are they are promoting this idea, they're talking about
this idea, they're engaging with people about this idea in a way that is probably at a higher
intensity than the app image project.
Well, it kind of makes it feel like if you're targeting our platform, here's our solution
for this rather app image feels a little bit like you're an independent developer with
a one off app.
Here you go.
You can package it up with totally, totally nailed that I think that and that's a big
way about me.
That's a big, you have to remember that's how the known project thing, right?
That's a and that's a big part of it.
Also, I would say last but not least, I think it just underscores how important the in person
application and meetings and discussions are to really move some of these important technologies
real.
Yeah, to move them through an open source community where everybody kind of has to sign
off and implement and all the different fiefdoms.
And the and that's something I think that the known projects just better at.
Speaking of that exact thing, system D, system D has a big update version two, three, oh,
when's the last time we even mentioned system D on this show.
And the reason why we're in a while, yeah, we're bringing it up because let's not kid
ourselves in terms of how long these things have been around, still kind of an early
project.
And this is a big update.
A lot of things are changing, right?
And it's one of those that they recommend themselves.
The project recommends that even the more aggressive distributions keep this one in
testing for extra longer.
Did you see that in there?
I did see that.
Yeah.
So there's a bunch of stuff like DNSSEC being turned on by default, etc, etc, etc.
But I wanted to jump right down to the one you're the most excited about.
This because it's, I get it on some level, but I think you have a bigger reason why you
like it.
And essentially what it is is the system D networking stuff will now allow a unique identifier
to be sent in a DHCP request.
And you can configure for each system in the.network file managed by system D networking
or network D. And they'll have different like DUIDs and DUID raw data and IAID options.
And I would guess this would be, well, I'm guessing so that when you're spinning up a
bunch of machines, you know what machine it is somehow.
I mean, why not just use MAC addresses, etc.
Well, it's mostly that.
So you do have control over the MAC address, but with IPv6, and like if you're using DHCPv6,
you can no longer for a lot of systems use a MAC address.
They use something, the DUID device unique identifier or something like that, which is
a longer string of hex characters in a similar fashion, like any kind of DUID.
But that is sent to identify a device.
So this adds support.
I've enjoyed system D network D. It's not going to do everything, but for servers or
especially containers where you probably already have system D, and you can make like a two
line file to enable DHCP on all your interfaces.
So when you're spinning up a new container, bam, you have addresses.
And then this just lets you add, which I've been looking forward to do for when I want
to, you know, I have some containers where I just like, they're going to be ephemeral.
I just want them to spin up, get an address, do something and disappear.
Some like I'm going to have more permanent and maybe they need static IP addresses or
I'm going to have them in DNS or something like that.
So this will let you easily just add a line where you can change that identifier and you
can change like interspace specific or for the whole system and you can change the DHCP.
You can change it to have send a unique identifier instead of the MAC address.
So it'll just make it a lot easier.
And then your, you know, your DHCP server will just pick them right up, give them the
address that they want.
Also a bunch of stuff change your system D login D in this release too.
So that user, the user stuff is pretty big.
Yeah.
What is it?
And from my understanding...
So that's where when you, when your user session is over, now all of your programs will be
terminated.
Right.
If you have a team X running, it will be terminated.
So that's one of the big changes that they're stressing here that people will be looking
out for.
That was it.
Yeah.
And, yeah.
And I think in some regards it will, there'll be a point in time where we just think that's
obvious that it should be the default behavior, but it's a big transition.
It is a huge transition now.
And it, and it, you know, it just kind of makes sense.
It does fit if you, if you adopt what they suggest and you, you know, use it system D
run to run it in the right scope and is in the right user scope and everything, then,
then yeah, you can account for it well and you can control its resources, et cetera.
And probably you'll have, you know, there'll be a lot of stuff where you're going to set
up like a user level service for it anyway.
So it won't matter.
Yeah.
And that was, that is definitely the, that's going to just definitely make sure you do
set that up that way, which is just best practice anyways.
Right.
There are, I have seen way too many people where you're like, Oh, I'm just gonna, yeah,
it works.
I tested it out.
I run it into my session.
It works.
You don't have to really demonize it and you're like, yeah, yeah.
So watch out for that one.
And we have a link in the show notes with more info.
Anything else to about at you?
Yeah.
I mean, there's a lot of, there's a lot of interesting stuff.
It depends on how you feel about system D, but they keep plugging along.
Yeah, they do.
So the, the full release notes are in there.
All right.
Then watch yourself.
We got a little valve update kind of sort of not directly, not directly.
It's just a, let's see, where's my, here it is.
Oh yeah.
Oh, I got it right here.
My my steam controller, I bought the steam controller thinking this is going to become
the defacto Linux controller.
This is the one you're going to use.
You're going to try to erase the sun.
That's what you'll be using.
Yeah.
No more Xbox 360.
It's going to be this guy.
And I think.
No go?
No.
Well, um, the big problem was, is it's been so directly attached to steam.
Right.
That I just, the extra hassle of having to open up, even if I want to just play a game
I installed from a repo, having to open up steam and configure and all that kind of stuff.
It was a real bummer for me.
So I want to introduce you to SC controller.
Man, I love open source.
Look at this thing.
It's a GTK.
Well done.
Yeah, it's a GTK UI for configuring your steam controller, setting up all the buttons, what
they do, mapping all of the different stuff.
It allows you to configure it completely without ever launching steam profiles.
You can switch between games.
It's got stick pads and gyroscope input, haptic feedback support, macros, rapid fire mode
shift.
And you can also enable emulation for the Xbox 360 for a mouse pad and balls and keyboards
and all that.
Yeah.
So maybe some, maybe next week we'll have to give that a go.
Maybe, maybe.
Yeah.
Cause it was just pretty, pretty, just a post over at gaming on linux.com and I'm really
impressed by this.
When was the last time you played with that bad boy?
Hmm.
Well at least two machines ago.
Right.
Yeah.
Cause I've had some machines in and out here.
Cause we've been moving hardware around.
Yeah.
So there you go.
I think that's really neat.
And it's posted up on GitHub.
We have a link in the show notes.
Yeah.
That's interesting.
That's a good, Liam says at the bottom of his post that a valve should really hire this
guy to speed up uncoupling the steam controller from big picture.
Yeah.
There you go.
Have you tried it?
Do you want to, have you, have you want to, you want to manhandle it there?
You want to?
Ooh.
Yeah.
That's nice, right?
It is smooth.
That's nice.
Okay.
So just a super quick little heads up for you out there that are on Fedora and want
GUIs for all the things.
Yum extender is a GUI for managing, you guessed it, yum and DNF.
Really DNF.
Now it's a front end graphical interface for DNF.
You can check it out.
I think in the show notes called yum extender and yum extender powered by DNF.
Man, between that and that system D.
I know.
What can't you manage?
That's right.
That was the thing.
That system D manager works pretty well.
Looks pretty sweet.
Yeah.
We talked about that in this week's Linux action show if you guys haven't seen that.
Okay.
So before we jump any further, we have a lot still to cover in the updates.
We probably need to pick up the pace.
We probably need to shake, shake it off like Mariah Carey.
So first let's talk about Ting because we got to get legit here for a second.
We got to get real.
We got to get real mobile that makes sense.
No more messing around with stupid guesses on how many minutes you might use or megabytes
or messages.
It's just pay for what you use over at Ting.
They got no contracts, no other termination fee, six dollar dollars.
That's it.
Six dollars is all you pay for the line.
Girl, are you hearing that?
Whoa.
Six dollars.
Plus you got the Uncle Sam taxes because Uncle Sam loves his cut.
Got to pay for that.
It's such a good deal he needs something.
Got to pay for all them important federal programs somehow.
So Ting's got to pay the pet taxes.
So all right, so it's six dollars taxes and then just what you use.
You on Wi-Fi?
You're not paying for nothing.
You want to get updates from your Android phone?
Ting don't care.
Ting is honey badger.
They don't care.
Why would they?
You can get updates.
Go to right now.
You ready?
Linux.ting.com.
That's where you go.
You get yourself a little savings like 25 bones.
You support this show.
If you got a compatible device and you just might because they got CDMA and GSM, you get
credit on your account.
I'm not playing.
You get credit.
It's probably going to pay for more than your first month because that's how freaking inexpensive
Ting is.
All right, so you get the credit on the account.
Then you're so happy with it, you go do a little evangelizing.
Now I'm not telling you not to send people to linux.ting.com because that would seriously
help out our show if you spread that around.
But I'm just saying if you're a Ting customer, they got a referral program.
They got a referral program.
A referral program.
What kind of program is that?
It's a referral program.
And if you get people to switch over to Ting, you get a little something something.
And the reason why I don't want to say too much is because I think it's a better deal
than I can get you.
But just get started by going to linux.ting.com.
Just go right there.
Check out your prices.
They got early termination relief programs.
If you got stuck on one of them duopoly contracts like a sucker.
Never again.
I was there.
I feel you.
I'm not there again.
No, no.
I don't go to Ting, Linux.ting.com.
It's different.
Ting keeps rates simple.
We don't make you pick a plan.
Instead, you just use your phone as you normally would.
How much you use determines how much you pay each month.
You can have as many devices as you want on one account.
That's good because when you use more, you pay less per minute, message or megabyte of
data.
Your usage plus $6 per active device on your account plus taxes is your monthly bill.
Simple.
That's what we mean when we say...
Alright!
...mobile.
That makes sense.
I like this one too.
They got a good post up there by Luke about data caps, and about what an SOB they are
when you're trying to cut the cord.
They got a great blog too.
You can go read it.
Just start by going to linux.ting.com, linux.ting.com, and thanks for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Alright, roll up your sleeves.
Whoa!
LibreOffice is getting to work in the Italian Army.
Following the announcement made last year, the Italian Army has moved forward with its
plans to replace Microsoft Office with LibreOffice.
So far, the Army has tested its plan across 5,000 workstations.
Wow!
That's a pretty big roll up.
Without any major problems too.
Yeah.
Now, they have those...
This is just the beginning, Wes, because once they get through this test program, this is
the part I really like.
I'm like, okay, yeah, that's great, you know, they're aiming to replace all MS Office by
the end of the year.
Okay, I've heard this story before.
This is the part I like.
The Department of Defense is also working on e-training materials to help new users
adapt to LibreOffice quickly, and once these materials are complete, the department aims
to release them under a copyleft license.
This will be a great contribution to LibreOffice project and will increase the adoption of the
Office suite across Italy.
Now that's a very good point.
Yeah.
I was just reading Visual Basic turned 25.
But VBA, right, the scripting language in so many of their Office projects, that still
exists, but it's not a major...
It's used all the time, but it's not being heavily developed.
There's so many things with open source here.
If the army has some sort of pain point or they need enhancement of a feature, they can
pay developers to do that, and everyone benefits.
That's true.
And they don't have to wait for it to be in the interest of the parent company.
Yeah.
And really, why not, if you're going to use the public's money to do something like this,
why not?
Absolutely.
Yeah.
That's a nice thing too, you know?
Okay.
So, Wes, you had a little bit of an arch story.
I secretly use Arch Linux.
And I thought this was kind of perfect, because it's about bringing PPAs to Arch, which, as
Popey is a recent Arch switcher, I'm sure this is going to be great for him.
This will kind of make it all...
Need something like this to, you know...
Yeah, make it familiar for him.
...facilitate his workflow.
Yeah.
So, this is a new tool that would allow you to create basically what they're calling PPAs
for Arch, which is kind of...
I don't know if I like the branding or the title, but the functionality does seem like
something maybe I could use.
Think of the Arch PPA like a do-it-yourself PPA personal package archive in the style
of PPAs.
Think popular Ubuntu's operating system PPAs, but hosted for you on your own terms, either
locally or on a server that you have access to, and they allow you to distribute packages
to hundreds of thousands of possible Arch users.
Arch-PPA developer Ryan McGuire says that he created this utility to help the Arch Linux
personal packaging ecosystem be more secure than it is right now, by making your own
private repo that doesn't get its audits contributed back upstream, and officially recognizing
software repositories where anyone with the proper skills can now upload, they can have
their own repo.
Wow!
This is where Arch-PPA comes in handy for AUR package maintainers who are looking for
an easy way to create a manual repository that they can maintain with the Arch Linux
packages they want to distribute in a secure, safe environment.
I love it for a LAN-like repository.
Yes, exactly, or on your VPN or whatever.
Nothing about that's like a PPA.
No.
It's more like an overlay.
I don't think people are going to suddenly add a bunch of these repositories when there's
already the AUR in place.
I like the Popeye and the Charms, just as we start moving PPAs to SNAPs.
But boy, I wish I had a comedy horn for that.
That's a good point.
That's it.
I will probably set this up and play with it.
Really?
Now, what's the use case?
Seriously.
Well, mostly things just like maybe like the ZFS module, you just build it once there
and then anyone else can jump right in.
I think it's because he hasn't refreshed his machine in a while, so he wants to trust more
weird stuff.
Yeah, I was thinking, that's what I was thinking, ChilledPrimary, I guess, ChilledPrimary says
that it's great for the enterprises.
Yeah, exactly.
You can kind of have, you can build your own, build your own use arch in the enterprise
though.
I mean, some must, I grant.
You are.
That's kind of crazy.
But you could now, I guess.
Well, it doesn't have to even be from the AUR, right?
It's just kind of a way to like, you can make your own package builds for whatever, your
own proprietary software, whatever, and then this will compile it and host a repo for you
so that any other arch machine can be configured.
Maybe you want your own custom kernel that you want to compile on your build host, host
it here.
You know, that seems fine.
What I was thinking is instead of getting it directly from the AUR, before you push
it to users, you check out the script, yeah, it's fine.
Then I push it to users.
You know, you control the rates of how much comes from the AUR, how fast.
Or you then, and then you whack out your latest version of your package.
You run all your build tests, you run all the rest of your tests, and then you push
it to Brad.
Yeah.
And if it does handle some of the dependency logic for you, that is, yeah, that is really
nice.
You're right.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Now I'm starting to see it like for, for, I wish I had more droplets that still used
arch.
I only have one left that uses arch.
I was like, I just have it as a matter of principle now.
You know, I just keep it up because, well.
You have to.
I can.
I can do it every day, brother.
This was a big story out of Google IO.
We really haven't covered Google IO in any of our shows much, except for Coder Radio.
But I thought maybe we could talk a little bit about this one, because I think you found
this link here, Wes.
It gives us a little insight about how they're going to be running Android apps securely
on Chrome OS, and you guessed it, containers.
They're going to be using containers on Chrome OS, yeah.
Not just containers, though.
I'll tell you about it.
So this is looking at a development preview, which is, you're going to have other versions
available in August.
You guys can get your hands on.
But apparently, Chrome OS has taken advantage of containers to get this Android app compatibility.
The full Android framework is implemented in a Linux container that isolates Android
from the rest of Chrome OS and puts its apps in a sandbox.
And here's a little bit of a diagram if you're watching the video version.
Yeah, that was a nice diagram.
A hardware abstraction layer has been built between Android and Chrome OS that runs native
ARM code on Chromebooks using processors with ARM instruction and emulates it on Chromebooks
using Intel processors.
With SE Linux, ah, yes, the secure version of Linux implemented in Android 4.3 back in
2003 on Android and in Chrome OS in 2012, the Android framework runs in a container
that isolates it from other containers and OS modules using Linux functionality called
namespaces.
Android is granted only specific privileges to view and interact with Chrome OS hardware
resources such as keyboards, cameras, communication stuff.
The isolation prevents potentially harmful code within the Android container from interacting
with code outside Android containers.
So containers in SE Linux is how they're going to get Android apps on Chrome OS.
Hopefully that does mean we'll be able to see it ported to other Linuxes at some point.
Yeah, but there's going to be a lot to set up.
Yep.
Yeah, every time this comes up, I think, would I actually use these apps on Linux?
It's also so strange to see, like, using, you know, kernel technology, but in such like
a far removed and heavily packaged and consumer focused, taking some hardcore like server
grade stuff.
Very strange.
I mean, it's cool.
It's neat.
That's, but I guess I would check out the Photoshop app.
If I could try out the Photoshop app, I might try that.
And Evernote, maybe.
Mm hmm.
Yeah.
Evernote, Photoshop.
I don't know.
I mean, there's a few things.
Bubble, UPMPs.
Sling TV.
I would like that too.
I would like that.
So I guess there's a few.
There's a.
Yeah.
OK.
All right.
Maybe Google Play Music.
Maybe.
Oh, yeah, that's true.
Hmm.
Yeah.
Look at that GitHub script there.
Muahaha in the chat room links the DigitalOcean Debian to ArchScript.
That is a thing.
That's also a great script.
If you want to learn a little bit how, like, init RAMFS and pivot root and that kind of
stuff works, I would definitely recommend checking those out because there's some clever
stuff you could do to convert a running system.
Yeah, you convert a running Debian box into an Arch box.
It's just awesome.
It helps now that there's a system involved.
Like, if you ever, like, in a conversation with someone, like, what can Linux do that
Windows can't do, really?
What can, what can?
Like, because I've got video games and I've got Exchange and Outlook.
What can Linux do?
And you're like, well, let me show you this.
Right.
Come here, son.
Sit down.
Let me show you something.
Yeah.
All right.
So anybody in the moment have thoughts about Android apps on Chrome OS?
I don't sense a lot of interest from you guys.
I'm already interested.
Okay.
It's cool.
It's something that I would like for people who already have a Chromebook, because I know
people who have them, even though I kind of didn't want them to get one, they get it anyway.
So it was kind of because they wouldn't, and immediately they started complaining about
not being able to install stuff and things like that.
So we kind of solved their problem.
But really, other than that, I don't care.
All right.
Who else?
I know a couple of people want to speak up.
Go ahead.
Yeah, and the Play Store has a wide variety of apps, which is-
And games.
With them.
Yes.
Which is far better than the Linux desktop that's available right now.
For example, Bacon Reader is the best Reddit client I've ever used, and nothing on Linux
can imagine.
So-
Those are fighting words right there.
But you can't have too many selection of apps.
So adding the Android ones is good.
I mean, they're not going to be- Theoretically, they could become Linux-based with the container
structure.
But right now, they're not even released yet, and it's going to be like a couple months
before it even becomes beta.
So the likelihood of it becoming Linux will be a very long time away.
I'm kind of curious to hear what Richard thinks, just from the perspective of OpenSUSE too.
I hear, well, Android Play Store has a lot of great apps that Linux desktop doesn't have,
and I guess maybe like this little primitive part in the back of my brain goes, uh-oh,
is that a threat?
Is that a threat to Linux?
Is that a- Hold on, are we never going to get to the desktop now if something based
on Linux has these great proprietary Play Store applications?
What do you think, Richard?
Is that not really apples and oranges?
Is it a fair threat?
Your thoughts?
I've seen a few times now of trying to get mobile apps running on the desktop.
I mean, it's- I think I even had it running on one of my machines a while back, like way
in the early Android days when that kind of stuff wasn't too crazy.
It never really appeals because it isn't the right- the wrong form factor, the wrong screen.
It's like the same thing you already have with Android phone apps and Android tablet
apps.
Well, you're going to have, what, Android laptop apps?
Yeah, that is going to be funky, huh?
Yeah.
Embedded West, your thoughts for people that might want this over, say, an iPad, like your
real basic user?
Yeah, I mean, I think it has a place for people like that who are just going to use it to
check mail or play games.
I think that it could be more beneficial than a tablet because it gives you a little bit
more flexibility.
I just don't think it could ever replace, at least for me, a true operating system where
I get file system access and stuff like that.
I mean, it is compelling to be able to buy a $300 or $200 or $180 laptop that has Chrome
and Android apps, but-
And I could see people who are already heavily invested, they've got the Pro apps for all
the different-
Yeah.
Oh, sure.
I've got my juice SSH Pro, whatever, all the things-
Or if games could actually work and there was a well-known game that comes out in the
Play Store.
That's true.
West, let me ask you this because this move and instant apps, which I'm sure you're familiar
with, you search for something in Google search and a link comes up and actually instead
of taking you to a website, it launches just the bare minimum app from the Play Store on
the fly.
Mind-blowing is this move, Android apps coming to Chrome OS, which Chrome OS, the web operating
system, the operating system for the web, the open web Google-
Yeah, I'm sent you.
Open web platform.
Is this and instant apps a massively anti-web, anti-open web ecosystem move?
Is this Google saying, you know what, you can't really have good app experiences in
the browser.
If you want good apps, you got to go native.
I mean a little bit.
I don't know if that's fully their intention but I can definitely see it as a potential
consequence of that.
I think they are still invested enough in the web that they don't  I don't think
that-
Sure.
All of them, especially as the giant organization they are, could be invested in that.
But you're right and it does build in that weird side premium extra layer that it just
doesn't  it's not really standard.
Well and as somebody  you got to wonder too like it really  I would rather just
if I go to the web and I search for something in Google on the web, there's a very high
likelihood that I want a web result.
Right.
You're already using it.
I don't want  if I want that app, I will go install that app.
I find the whole thing-
I have already been like frustrated by that.
Yeah.
So I guess it is  things are changing and Chrome OS is becoming a new beast that will
be entirely competitive on a different level and I think Richard absolutely is right.
If they don't nail the UI experience, which is going to be damn near impossible, I just
don't see how serious users will want to use it outside of note taking apps and things
like that.
I guess, JM, I will give you the last words on this because it does kind of feel like
a convergence of the two platforms in a sense using  because in a sense, if you look
at that diagram, just core fundamental Linux technologies to bring the two together.
Sure.
I mean this has been the long term strategy with Chrome OS and Android.
They've always planned to bring the two together eventually and they're going to
be the premium place where developers will go to publish their apps because it will be
Google first.
Forget Windows.
Forget Mac.
It will be on Google's platform.
Interesting.
I think you're probably right and nothing else we can do other than watch at this point.
So we move on.
And talk about it.
That's what we're here for.
Yeah.
And observe.
And then when it lands, we're like, told you.
You know what else they told you about is digital ocean.
This is really where you should go to spin up infrastructure on demand.
Now we know that the key decision you have to make is when you're using cloud computing,
it has to be done on a system that's actually good.
This is where digital ocean comes in.
They've got data centers all over the world, all over the world, using Linux as the base
operating system, KVM as the virtualizer, SSDs for all the disk IO, 40 gigabit e-connections
into the virtualizers, Class A data centers all over the world.
It is really, it's like nothing you could ever do without yourself.
That's a beautiful picture.
And then they come in there.
They come in there with that crazy VC funding, that Hoopspa and that great product and all
of a sudden they blow up.
And they're able to offer you real time, I mean, like, well, less than 55 seconds, spin
ups of virtual machines, starting at $5 a month for 512 megabytes of RAM, sorry, what?
A 20 gigabyte SSD, a blazing fast CPU, and a terabyte of transfer with a batacle, batacle
UI.
Nothing like this you've ever seen to manage your digital ocean droplet, shoot, son.
Girl please.
I wish I had an interface like this, but then to back that up.
The best API.
Oh man.
Woo!
You know.
First class.
If you're, if you're an API snob, you're hanging out in the bar, you're talking about
APIs with your API snobby friends, drinking your martinis.
Digital ocean's the top of the list.
Everybody talks about digital ocean.
It's that API.
It really is.
What's great about it is there's tons of open source applications already written that you
don't have to write yourself to take advantage of, so you can be super lazy.
But if you hate all of them, the API docs are great, so you just write your own.
And you know, back to that interface, back, back, back to that interface they got.
They got HTML5 console so you can manage your machine from boot all the way up to post.
One click application deployments.
One thing you got to do though.
One thing.
Hold on, West.
Let me make sure it's legit.
Let me see.
Double check.
I'm checking here.
Okay.
Multiply that.
Carry the two.
Go this over here.
Let's see.
And I'll just run this crunch over here.
Let's see here.
Get it out of here.
Oh yes.
That's right.
If you use the promo code DOUNPLUG, that's the thing they have to do.
I thought it was just go there, create an amazing system, get your work done, experiment
with something, put it into production, use whatever damn distro you think is best, and
then enjoy their incredible documentation.
I thought that's all I had to say.
But then I remembered.
We would like to do episode 147.
We really would.
So you got to use that promo code DOUNPLUG.
That's the thing.
Keep us here.
You got to do that.
You get a $10 credit.
You try out their $5 rig, two months for free.
Keep us going.
Use that promo code DOUNPLUG and a big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Unplug
program.
Now Wes, there's this crazy upstart out there.
I don't think Ryan's not in the Mamba Room, is he?
He's not in there?
No, I don't see him.
There's this crazy project out there that's working on this thing to compete with Google
Home or whatever they're calling it, the Amazon Echo.
And we've talked about it before.
It's called Mycroft.
And recently, the Mycroft project released Mycroft Core 0.6 Alpha.
Shipping.
Shipping some code.
And they put it up on GitHub.
You can download it and get it running on Ubuntu.
Whoa.
What was that?
I think that was a space-time distortion.
I think so, yep.
Yeah, we hit a micro fragment.
That was the Mycroft AI in the future reaching back.
That's exactly what I was thinking.
Tell us to keep going.
Because I was about to show you the Mycroft with his pants off.
Look at this.
Isn't it just so cute?
This is the dev unit here.
And if you're watching the video version, we have this linked, the video in the show
notes.
The Mycroft with his pants off, so you can see all the guts here.
And this thing is looking really good.
This is just a prototype, right?
I'm impressed.
But what's so great about Mycroft in this Amazon Echo era now is...
You mean besides their name?
Yeah.
Yeah, that is a great name.
You're right.
That is really brilliant.
What's so great though, and it's not...what also is great is they're open sourcing tons
of different code, but the thing that I really love about Mycroft, the thing that really
gets me excited about Mycroft is you can just get Mycroft Core and install it on any damn
thing you want.
And that means I could truly, eventually, if I had the chutzpah and initiative, I could
deploy Mycroft ubiquitously in my life.
I could have it on my Kodi box.
I could have it on my server.
I could have it on my desktop.
Mycroft.
Start the show.
I mean, it truly...because I'm not going to buy 50 Google Homes or 50 Amazon Echoes or
whatever.
But if I could get a couple of Mycroft devices where I don't want an easy button, and then
I can install the software in all the other places, like my phone, like my desktop, like
my laptop, like my server.
Computers, whatever.
Yeah.
So, I know you've been playing around with it.
I think Ham's been playing around with it.
I don't know.
Have you actually gotten started yet?
Because it's pretty early days still.
I haven't quite, but I haven't had time to look into too much of the configuration.
What's the process like?
Well, it's a Python app, and they have some nice scripts that'll install all the app dependencies
for you and set up in a virtual environment.
I haven't gotten the sound...I haven't gotten it working quite yet, but I'm sure if I play
with it for a little bit longer, I'm excited to get it to work.
Now, Ham, you were saying in chat earlier today that you've been playing with it too,
yeah?
Yeah, I actually got it working.
I cloned the Git repo, and I read the README file.
Super easy.
It was 0.6.0, I couldn't get it to build, but they released a new version just a day
or two later, 6.1, and that one built for me super easy.
I rebooted the computer, like they said, opened the terminal, three terminal instances, and
ran the commands they said, and I got Mycroft running.
I said, hey, Mycroft, open up CNN.com, and it opened up CNN.com, opened up Thunderbird
just fine, a few problems here and there, but it's pretty cool.
That's great.
Now, did you also have to create an account with the intent parsing service or something
like that, which I guess is going to be...they're going to be moving to an open source solution,
but right now, you have to go create an account somewhere, right?
Oh, that is correct, sybaris.mycroft.ai, I think it is, yes, I did have to create an
account there.
But that's just pretty quick and simple, and that's just used to do some of the speech
recognition, I guess?
Oh, yeah, I signed in using my Google account, and so it took like two seconds to sign in,
and I just said, Mycroft, pair up my device, and Mycroft gives me a little code.
I put it in there, and I was paired within literally two minutes, is that...
Can you try other things, like can you ask it for weather?
Is there any additional things you can ask, or is it pretty basic right now?
I asked, what's the weather, and it gave me the weather for some place in Kentucky or
something, and I'm like, hey, Mycroft, change my location to Lewiston, Idaho, and it totally
didn't get it at all.
So does it feel sort of like a verbal command line right now, or does it feel like you're
having a conversation?
Like a verbal command line, it is not a conversation.
I mean, when I asked, what's the weather, and it said, it's sunny out here, you better
get your...
It said, you better get your sunglasses.
That's kind of fun.
Yeah, that's kind of fun.
Yeah.
Yeah, I think there's two different types of assistance right now.
I feel like Siri and Google Now and Amazon Echo really are very much...
They're command lines, and if you learn to say things in this precise order, like, hey,
they're googs, set a reminder for 5.30 PM.
It works pretty well.
And then they'll say, what would you like a reminder for?
Remind me to tell Wes that he's awesome, and then it sets a reminder, right?
And you have to very much walk through a sequence like that.
And what the next generation of artificial intelligence is doing is more conversational.
And you see, we're kind of there now, but they're not necessarily as reliable, because
they depend on being able to suss out your intent and your context, whereas the command
line is a little more intentional, a little more exact, and it can also be replicated
on text.
And that's where I really think...
I was joking earlier, but I would love to see...
So Mycroft has this intent engine, and I would love to see if this thing could be integrated
at all different aspects.
If it truly is, it's all open, and my desktop is open, could Mycroft intent be integrated
into the app launcher to learn what apps I most frequently launch?
Could Mycroft intent be integrated into my contacts application?
Could this be a pervasive artificial intelligence system for the Linux desktop?
Something that is not driven by necessarily a strategy tax by a larger parent company
or something like that.
I just find the possibilities to be really compelling, because it's not just a hardware
box, right?
Because it's software.
If you really haven't got it working yet, and it's kind of hit and miss, it is possible.
Ham's got the beginning version of it.
And this is 0.6 alpha.
That's really cool.
Anybody else in the Mumble Room have any thoughts on the topic?
Yeah.
Oh, go ahead, Poppy, and then North.
So I was at OSCON last week, and I met Ryan Sipes, the CTO of Mycroft AI, and I held one
of the Mycrofts in my hand for the first time.
I saw your tweet.
That was great.
Wow.
Yeah.
And he said to me that I asked about the voice stuff and whether the new voice was ready.
And he said they've got a new version.
They've been regenerating all the sounds.
And he said there was a problem with one of the early ones that the voice sounded a little
bit like Max Headroom.
So we go, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha.
He really wanted to keep that in, but they decided, no, it would be unprofessional to
do that.
So we got rid of that, unfortunately.
I really want that.
Yeah, that would be maybe later.
Maybe later.
That would be good.
So, Poppy, did you get it?
Was the noise environment suitable to trying it at all?
How was that like?
Not really, because the conference center was just so noisy.
Every so often you could, like randomly, it would start talking, and you'd see the little
lips, the light lips moving on the front, and it was very cute when it's talking.
But it was just way too noisy in there for us to get a good demo.
So your thoughts just overall on integrating Mycroft at more than just, to me, and I wonder
for you too, it seems to be more compelling than just a little hardware device.
I would like to see that just be one representation of how I interact with Mycroft.
Do you see it being much bigger than just a hardware device?
So you were talking there about having access to your most recent apps and stuff, like most
modern desktops have that kind of surfacing, that kind of data, or using stuff like Zeitgeist,
which would keep track of which documents you've opened.
If you could say to Mycroft, open the document I had open last Tuesday when I was listening
to ABBA or something, because you remembered the document and what you were listening to
at the time.
That is kind of the purpose of Zeitgeist, that it records what you're doing all the
time.
So there's a data source there that could certainly be mined by Mycroft, and I think
that would be awesome if it was all integrated together.
The Mycroft project is an interesting one to watch because, boy, the timing is perfect.
It really is.
It was just  I'm so thrilled that we're not really behind the curve on this.
It really felt like we were going to be missing out before Mycroft started getting all the
momentum they have now.
But since Ryan Sipes, who I think is just great.
I think Ryan  he's a great  not only is Ryan very well spoken and he articulates
the project's vision.
He's a wonderful advocate.
But he's also just a super nice guy to hang out with and chat with.
He was going to join us today, but I'm assuming he's just super busy, because he had emailed
me earlier today saying, hey, can I make it, and I said, yeah, absolutely.
So that's totally understandable.
I wonder
Come back any time.
If he was here, what I would like to ask him  probably the hardest question I would
have had for him is, is it getting too much?
Is it growing too fast?
Is this weird thing that  I don't know how to explain it, but I could tell that our
audience was not super impressed by this update and was having a hard time parsing it.
And so
It's pretty long and
It's long, dense, and it's not traditionally as well done as communication from the Mycroft
project.
And so I think it kind of fell a little flatter than maybe they were expecting, or at least
I was expecting, because I think this is a bigger deal than people are realizing.
And I don't know if every single stupid thing  well, it's not stupid, but if every single
little thing needs a video with some hipster music and a tweet or what
Chris, you know that it does.
Well, okay.
That's probably true.
Yeah.
And a scrolly website.
So maybe I just would like to ask him  and what I'm worried about is, does something
like this that has not just their ideas of what would be great, but then once you start
talking to other people and you start working with other groups, a lot of other ideas start
getting brought into the mix.
People start telling you, you should do this.
You also got to do this.
Get involved with this.
Go to this event.
Make sure you talk to these people.
Make sure you talk  and I wonder if scope creep is becoming an issue at all.
So maybe Ryan will join us soon and we can talk about that, because even from the perspective
of managing an open source project that is fairly well watched, what's that like?
What does that feel like?
What happens if you decide you're going to hit your  like really Wimpy to some degree
has this too with Ubuntu Mate.
Absolutely.
And of course, Richard has this with OpenSUSE.
What is it like when all of a sudden you're dealing with something that is very, very
heavily watched?
Richard, do you have any thoughts just off the top of your head as I just sort of sprung
this on you?
Well, yeah.
I mean, I guess I've kind of got an example today.
I mean, we've just released 42.2 Alpha 1.
Like we thought we knew the scope.
We knew everything.
And like the first bunch of feedback is, oh, we want this extra thing and this extra thing
and this extra thing.
But on one hand, you want to say yes to everything because it's  part of that's where the
enthusiasm comes from.
On the other hand, you can see if you say yes to everything, you're going to end up
with an ungodly mess.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
Like you get monster scope creep.
NorthRanger, you had a positive spin.
I'd love to hear that.
Yeah.
So you talk about what they've been out in the community talking about.
You worry about the scope creep.
I think you're totally right on the timing of this that I think their timing actually
is good because people's awareness of these types of devices and these types of services
is constantly increasing with Amazon Echo and Google Now and Siri.
But all of those existing solutions are very much focused on Amazon wants to sell you stuff.
Google wants to mine all your S. Whereas Mycroft, if you set aside what they're talking about
and focus on what they've actually done, they're showing real hardware and they're releasing
the core, the things that you have to get right, the speech recognition, the ability
to create intents and create actions.
And that's where I think the open source community can take in and run with it.
Yeah.
That's well said.
And also just as a tip of the hat to the Mycroft project, when you go to sign up for that account
where Ham said he just uses Google and you can just super quick get in there and get
the speech recognition, they literally say, like, hey, if you want to help out and give
us a little financial contribution, we're going to be able to replace this whole proprietary
have to log in thing way faster and we'll have the open source solution ready to go.
That's our direction we're going.
We're going to get there one way or another.
Here's a couple of ways you can help us get there faster.
And you look at Mycroft as a project that was funded initially by the community and
they're not done yet.
And that, I thought, I thought what that represented was a super clever way to continue additional
bits of funding because you know, you know that they can't just go raise, even if they
raised five hundred thousand dollars, that money is going to run out when you start hiring
people and you start having expenses and you start having to go to events and they're just
like world class work here, you know, like these are the things that like, yeah, of course,
they're having to like this is like, you have to outsource some of this stuff because right
now all the solutions that anyone uses are proprietary.
So they're like exploring new ground and doing work that a lot of them could be paid good
money to do.
Yeah.
So I think it's I really hope they come up with a solid revenue stream that doesn't necessarily
involve data analytics of their customers.
But it comes, you know, a great way to raise money that contributes back to the project
because you want to see something like this continue.
And it's really cool it's gotten this far because of community funding so far.
And then, of course, open source development.
All right.
Let's take a moment.
Speaking of community funding, it's time to talk about the Libram 11.
It's called and dubbed the surface book for those of you who care about your privacy and
your freedom.
What?
Okay.
I have a few thoughts on this as somebody who funded their first attempt at crowdfunding
hardware, the Libram 15.
So come over here into the hallway with me for just a moment, Wes, and let's talk about
Linux Academy.
Dot com.
Go there now.
Slash Unplugged.
You got to go there to get the discount.
Go there now.
And support the show.
So, Wes, let's get real while we're out here in the hallway.
If you don't know this, we're out in the hallway right now.
We stepped out of the studio.
The hallway always sounds like this.
This is how it sounds at Jupiter Broadcasting Studios.
Of course.
We've got all these computers here.
This is why it sounds like this.
If you want to chill in the hallway, Wes, if you want to get your employer's attention,
if you want to maybe do a little better on the next review or get a raise, you know one
of the ways to do that is to continue your education and show them you're expanding your
knowledge set.
It's legitimately one of the best ways to get your employer's attention.
It's one of the best ways to make you more employable and it's also a great way to challenge
yourself.
Linux Academy.
Dot com slash unplugged.
Come on.
Step out here into the hallway with us and think about it just for a little bit.
Go there and try them out.
Linux Academy.
Dot com slash unplugged.
You get a discount.
They have self-paced courses with two thousand four hundred and four to seven videos, scenario
based labs that put you in the middle of everyday common tasks, instructor mentoring.
Could you imagine?
You're standing out here in the hallway.
Let Linux Academy tell you what to do.
You're out here on the hallway.
You're looking at your smartphone and you're thinking, you know what, I need help.
They got it.
Instructor mentoring.
Because you're in the hallway right now.
Right there.
Linux Academy.
They got graded server exercises.
Sign up.
Right now.
Because this is not neural programming.
This is the hallway.
OK?
This is not neural programming.
Linux Academy.
Dot com slash unplugged.
You go there.
You learn more.
You got graded server exercises.
So that way, if you're like me and you s' your pants when you gotta take a test.
You know what I don't like is scenarios where there's no option other than win lose.
I like a couple of options.
I want a plan B. I want a plan B. Here, now come over here.
Now let's step into the computer room.
Yeah, OK.
So here we are in the computer room now, Wes.
Right next to the studio.
We got data to crunch here, folks.
Yeah.
And the way we learned how to do that is Linux Academy.
Linux Academy.
Dot com slash unplugged.
They got the best courseware.
I'm going to say it right now.
The best courseware on the Red Hat stuff.
Oh, you got stuck in the dev ops position all of a sudden.
Oh, I shouldn't say stuck.
I shouldn't.
One, they'll tell you what that term means.
Two, they'll tell you how to effectively use those tool sets.
They've also got great, great courseware on Amazon Web Services, Android Development,
Ruby, OPHP, and their courseware comes with their servers.
What?
Had we not mentioned that?
I got to say, I should have mentioned at the top.
See, I'm a rookie here.
I should have mentioned at the top.
You get to choose from seven plus distributions.
No, this is not neural programming.
I'm just letting you know.
OK.
Seven.
Seven plus distributions, and then they automatically adjust the courseware.
Virtual machines.
Crazy.
They spin that up on demand.
They spin up that, and it matches the courseware.
Now think about that.
That's how you know that they actually know how to use this stuff.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
Go check them out.
They've got great instructor mentoring.
They have a community stacked full of Jupiter Broadcasting members, and I think the other
thing that really speaks for them is they legitimately have constant results.
It's really neat.
And actually, I like it when you tweet me and you tell me about it, too.
So thanks, you guys.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
All right.
So we've stepped back into the studio.
We're no longer in the hallway or the computer lab or whatever that last room was.
I want to talk about the Liebroom 10, a 10.1 inch two-in-one detachable laptop tablet designed
to protect your digital life.
From the Purism folks, they say it's beautiful freedom, and they believe in users' rights.
It's a tablet and a laptop.
They say a ton of work to make the Gnome Shell ready for this.
It ships up.
Yeah, and it ships Pure OS, and they got a video.
It doesn't really say much, but I guess I could read you the highlights because I don't
think there's actually any voiceover here.
So they say, what's on your tablet?
Privacy isn't about what you want to hide.
It's about what you need to protect.
If you could design the ultimate tablet, what would it be?
You are helping design your next computer.
We are listening.
Hey, it's Todd.
Your current computer and service providers know more about you than anybody else.
Apple, Google, or Microsoft hold the master key to your digital life.
You want a computer designed to protect you rather than monitor you.
Introducing the Liebroom 11, the latest computer from Purism designed by you to protect your
digital life.
An 11-inch, two-in-one detachable privacy, security, and freedom-focused computer running
Pure OS 3.0 where you hold the master key to your entire digital life.
All right.
We've been to the Chris Last school of music overlays here.
The Liebroom 11 turns off remote spying with hardware kill switches.
It does not track you at all.
Nor does it phone home to the parent company.
The Liebroom 11 runs free software with the source code available to verify that it protects
your digital rights.
And above all else, makes protecting yourself as easy as turning it on.
At Purism, we believe protecting your digital rights should be easier than giving them up.
We make hardware and software that is designed to protect your digital life.
In order to achieve this goal, Purism has amassed an amazing team of the best freedom
operators from all over the world.
With your help, Purism will continue leading the way in protecting everybody's digital
life.
Thank you.
Man.
I'll tell you what, I'm pretty stoked about that hammock in the back of Todd's yard there.
That's nice.
That shows he's got good taste.
That looks comfy.
I'm more confident now.
So the Liebroom 11, a two-in-one tablet that protects your privacy.
They want to raise $150,000.
They have two months left, so it's a real long one over on IndieGoGo.
Real nice and long one.
And they've so far raised $12,455 with only 11 backers.
Eleven backers.
Starting at $999.
You can get a $599 if you want a less capable one.
So, I got a lot of thoughts on this, but I guess I wanted to open it up to you first,
Wes, and then I'll toss it over to the Mumba Room after that.
What do you think?
Do you, at this point, what is just your initial thoughts?
I mean, people might not be fully familiar with my history with the company, so that
aside, what is just your initial thoughts on something like this?
There are some good things and some bad things.
They're very zoomed in on this core M processor here on the page, which has me a little off
but already.
But I think the video was good.
I think there are some people with very good intentions behind this.
Bringing in your history there, I do have some questions about if they'll be able to
ship it, what it really will look like, and I also don't know how much I'm that interested
in the tablet two-in-one workflow anyway.
Here's my question.
I don't know how to state this in a way that doesn't  that maybe if you're not already
there with me, you might not understand, but inherently, would you agree or disagree that
one of the features of a tablet is build quality?
Yeah, I agree.
I mean
And would you agree or disagree that one of the features of a tablet is content consumption
and therefore its ecosystem?
Yep.
And would you agree that one of the things of a tablet that makes it compelling to a
large market is a healthy accessory ecosystem, maybe like cases for kids, charging stations
for people that want to have multiple charging options, Bluetooth speakers that have holders
that are  you know, like connector speakers and chargers that hold alarm clocks and things
like that.
It's an ecosystem that I would say you could say makes a tablet viable.
Would you agree with that to some degree or not?
No.
I mean I think I see what you're saying and that  I mean right there, that limits
the scope of who could be interested in this.
I mean if  I'm really curious to see what they  you said they've done a lot
to the Nome Shell.
It would be really interesting to see this succeed.
I don't  you know, I don't want to preclude this being an awesome product.
Well, I mean for a tablet, so it's going to have Linux, 16 gigabytes of RAM, user-upgradable
easily removable screws, six to eight battery lives, hardware kill switches for wireless
Bluetooth camera, microphone, GPS, and the cellular data if you get it.
Oh, wow.
Cellular data.
Yeah.
So I think it ties back with the laptop, you know, with the  there's a lot of things
here that I could really like and I'd love to see it succeed.
I don't know that it will and I don't know that what percentage of success that
they do achieve will be enough to make it worthwhile.
Hmm.
Anyone in the room have any thoughts about  I mean is this a good pivot?
Is this maybe a pivot from building  trying to compete in the traditional laptop space
and saying we're going to go after this sort of niche here, this surface niche?
Yeah, because what the year they were competing in before, there were a lot of providers like
in Europe there's Antroer and Schenker and PC Specialists.
There were a lot of boutique companies that just repackaged clearful products.
But there doesn't seem  from these companies, there doesn't seem any proper surface competitors.
So I think it's a nice niche to go into and from my experiences with my brother Surface
Pro and with Gnome, I really, really want to experience how Gnome works on a proper
tablet because I think it would be a very good experience of having a full desktop into
a tablet with a good desktop environment that integrates both ideas.
So I think it's a good idea.
Toby, what are your thoughts on it?
As someone who worked on a product which landed on a tablet that got some interesting feedback
recently, I would say the thing they need to nail is not just the hardware build quality
but people can be quite forgiving of hardware build quality if it's at the right price
point but what they often can't forgive is poor quality or unfinished software.
If they don't get that nailed, then people who've backed it might revolt slightly.
Do you think they could spend say several months with Gnome 3 Shell and get Gnome Shell
in a state that is usable in a touch environment?
To be fair, I haven't used Gnome Shell for a long time.
So I don't know what state it's in in a touch environment.
I haven't got it on any machines that have got a touch screen.
So I don't know.
And I don't know how touch-oriented.
I know everyone who sees any operating system that has big icons immediately erroneously
thinks it's a touch UI but I don't know how well Gnome Shell is suited to touch at the
moment.
So I don't know how far they've got to go.
I just think they need to focus on that quite hard.
I think it comes down to the apps.
I think the Shell does okay.
I mean I've used it on like not a great, some like mediocre touch interfaces and like launching
apps and that kind of stuff is fine.
It'll depend on like, you know, if you use Chromium it'll do well or Chrome, maybe some
other web browsers less so or similar for the rest of your apps.
You know, if you're using Linux apps that just aren't going to work with touch, it's
going to be painful.
But
Yeah.
What about like gestures and pinching and things like that?
So I have not read through the whole post where they say all the work they did for Gnome
but I know they did address some of that.
They also  they said they're going to eventually have optional docking station features
like a power connector, an RJ45 Ethernet port, HDMI out, two USB ports.
I'm really
Like how they solved the fan problem with not having a fan.
Yeah that is nice.
That was my solution too.
I guess they just adopted my solution from their laptop problem.
Now I look at this and I think to myself it's really, really, really a difficult position
to be in, to be a project out in the open like this, hardware or software, and be crowdfunded
and have to publicly fail a few times, which a lot of companies and a lot of initiatives
and a lot of projects do.
But now
But this is right out in the open.
Yeah.
This could be Pureism abandoning the laptop line and  like this you could see two ways.
This could be Pureism abandoning the laptop line and moving over  or not abandoning.
That's the wrong way to put it.
This is Pureism redirecting their attention and getting distracted by a Shiny and not focusing
on just nailing and really making something good and then moving on to the next thing.
They feel like they haven't finished the last thing.
But you could also look at it and say this is a company that is recognizing the competitive
landscape and wants to contribute something unique and cater to a market that wants that
product but wants to have some of their essential requirements met.
And they're recognizing that and saying you know what we couldn't nail this but we think
we can nail that and so we're going to pivot and we're going to try to make that our
thing.
That's also reasonable.
If they would actually literally say that then it would be like well you admit your
mistake but they haven't done so.
Well that's true.
That's a good point.
Yeah.
No.
True.
But I'm just of two minds of this thing.
Right.
I look at it and I go I don't know.
It would be really cool to have a Linux tablet that I loved using.
That would be awesome.
Yeah.
I look at that and I go geez a quad core, micro SD slot, HDMI out, docking station.
If the keyboard clip in business works well and it doesn't feel chintzy then that would
be great.
All right.
Jama Biz.
I don't know how you say your head on JMA, BBZ.
Go ahead.
Your thoughts on crowdfunding.
Yeah.
I mean with crowdfunding you are essentially not buying a product.
You're just investing in the hope that  and they have managed to get a product out.
It wasn't very good.
Hopefully this one will be better.
We'll have to wait and see.
But they are trying and hopefully they're contributing back to knowing that as always
there's a risk with crowdfunding and people need to be aware of that.
Well I want to say they contacted us after my Librem 15 review which you guys can go
find on your own.
And they said well would you be willing to try the Librem 13 because we really think
we did a much better job with the Librem 13.
We got a better hardware partner.
We had a chance to do it better.
Would you be willing to look at that?
Him and I haught about it because I'm not a big 13-inch laptop guy.
I'm more of a 15-inch laptop person.
And I was a little burned, right?
I was a little burned by them so I thought that might influence my review.
So what I decided should have Noah review it.
That guy loves 13-inch laptops, loves them.
And he didn't get burned by the 15-inch laptop.
No skin off his back.
So on this week's episode of the Linux Action Show, on Sunday's episode, we're going to
review the Librem 13.
It's not that I want to keep doing all these hardware reviews over and over again but every
single day I get an email about the perfect Linux laptop.
And every single week on Reddit I see a thread about the perfect Linux laptop.
And once a month somebody on Hacker News talks about how they have found the perfect Linux
laptop.
It's talked about all the time.
So we're going to look at the Librem 13 on the Linux Action Show and see if they nailed
that product.
And my estimation is, depending on how well they did that, when they got another chance,
how well they did on the Librem 13, if they nailed that, if Noah says they did a great
job.
Because that is really the test is like you just need to keep some amount of people that
will keep funding them and letting them progress.
And the brown bear loves himself the 13-inch laptop.
So if they nailed the 13-inch laptop then I think this might be a viable project.
You could rely on them to really be able to iterate on something.
So we'll see.
I don't know.
I specifically asked him not to really give me any details about it.
I want to find out during the show.
So he's had it for like three weeks or something.
Sounds like a good one to watch live.
Yeah.
Which has been interesting because he's received like maybe four.
I don't know.
He's had it for a while.
And he got it like during the Oryx.
So he's had the Oryx and the Librem side by side.
Yeah.
It should be a really interesting review.
So we'll talk about that on Sunday's show.
But we'll have links to this crowdfunding campaign if you want to go get yourself one.
Maybe just hang out.
I think it's got two months.
It's a long one.
So maybe just wait for a little bit and see where it goes.
If you want to support something today, check this out, Wes, patreon.com slash today.
That's where you go to fund the network.
Now this page is all jacked up.
It's got like stuff on there about Tech Talk today.
It's got a video of me with like an old hairstyle, which is just hard to look at.
How to date.
90s.
Whew.
But none of that matters.
Go there anyway.
What it's really about-
Put your credit card in.
What is-
Chris, put on the confusion thing.
I'm putting it right now.
I'm putting it there.
Okay.
Wait.
No.
Nothing.
Let's go to the hallway.
Yeah.
Okay.
Hold on, Wes.
We'll go to the hallway.
We're on the hallway.
Just you and me.
Nobody's here.
Tell them about Patreon.
Patreon.com slash today.
This is where you go to support the Jupiter Broadcasting Network and orient our compass
towards our audience.
Now I say that in a really kind of nice, fancy way, right?
Orient our compass towards our audience.
What does that really mean?
I'll tell you, Wes.
Well, it's just because we're out in the hallway.
It's just you and me.
Tell us, Chris.
If we were in the hallway, I wouldn't say this.
Tell us now.
Advertising on the web is only going to work for so long.
It's eventually going to go bust.
I'll say it right now.
And if you've read the New York Times recently, you know that NPR and a bunch of other podcast
advertising brokers are going to screw it all up for all of us.
They're really messing it up bad.
They want Apple to create its own garden system around podcasting.
Google Play now has its own walled garden that has its own stats and re-hosts our files.
It is, Wes, if we weren't out in the hallway right now, right now legitimately standing
in the hallway, I wouldn't say this.
It ain't going to work much longer.
That's why I think we've talked about crowdfunding today from a multiple set of angles.
I think this is a big one.
What it really does is it makes your priority your crowdfunding source.
Your priority is going to be what your funding source is.
That I think is really all you need to know.
And we want our priority to be the audience, patreon.com slash today.
Now I don't want to say more than that because we're in the hallway.
If we were in a different room, I might say something else.
But that's all I want to say about it.
You might also find an extended live edition of this show.
Extended live.
Extended live edition of this show at patreon.com slash today.
Full featured.
601 patrons.
That's really great.
We're getting close.
Well, by close I mean we need to double that.
But once we double that, subscribe again, then three times, then I'll do all these shows
topless.
Oh, boy.
Or, or pay five dollars more than that and Chris wears two shirts.
Oh, man.
I was waiting to see what you'd say about that.
No, I'm kidding.
But patreon.com slash today.
We are beginning to post the live recordings of our shows.
The whole thing.
I love it.
I was already recording the live stream.
Were you really?
Oh, yeah.
Well, it's more fun.
I love the live stream.
They are better, right?
And sometimes I can't be there or I'm out and about or whatever.
And so now you guys do all the hard work for me.
And since I'm a patron already, like, it's an awesome benefit.
Yeah, it's an early system.
We're still setting it up.
But if you want to get in on it, what essentially it lets you do is we're posting a few shows
throughout the week, the entire live stream.
Now I think it's funny because I don't know if people really like jumped on it, but I
posted the tech snap one and that's the first time we have ever showed any live clips.
We've never do outtakes in tech snap.
It's nothing like that filtered out.
It's just what's in there.
And the moment, my favorite moment in that, and it's right there if you're a patron, is
it starts with Alan troubleshooting his microphone.
And what is revealed is that A, Alan Jude has a favorite USB port and B, Alan Jude broke
his favorite USB port.
And so the whole thing is quite funny.
And it's just it's a brilliant example of what happens on the live stream before tech
snap that no one ever sees unless you make it.
Totally different show.
And now with this new Linux powered OBS rig we have here doing this extra work and all
these extra sat coms we got going, we thought now is the point.
Now we can finally contribute back to our patrons.
And we specifically had a milestone we wanted to reach to be able to financially do that.
And it worked out perfectly.
As we crossed that milestone, the hardware went into place.
That's awesome.
And now we're delivering those exclusives to our patrons.
Patreon.com slash today.
You start at the three dollar level.
You go all the way up, they got swag levels, we got all that.
Them people over there are crazy.
Just ignore everything else on the page that doesn't well, you actually it's been getting
updated over time.
It's been getting quite fancied up.
We got like a new cord cutting level.
If you're a cord cutter.
Yeah, like your Netflix.
$10 or more.
Yeah, read that.
You're a cord cutter.
You decided mainstream cable isn't how you want to consume content anymore.
And it turns out J.B. has just what you need.
This level means you support content that is tailored to your technical needs and you
are still saving money.
That's true.
Ten dollars a month is nothing.
Yeah, I know.
Right.
I know.
So check it out.
Patreon.com slash today.
You support the whole network.
And we have big things coming that we want to accomplish in 2016 that I feel like now
you've proven it right.
Like you've shown like you give more money, you get more.
I feel like we have.
I feel like we've delivered and I want Chris to go live in an RV and travel around the
country.
Bam.
He'll do it.
But what really it's about is it's not about me.
It is it is about being able to launch new shows and not have to think about sponsors
first.
It's about being able to determine what what six hundred and one people like, not what
a hundred thousand people might like.
See, one of the fundamental problems we have at the Jupiter Broadcasting Network and it
is literally our biggest competitive disadvantage is we cover Linux and open source.
And it's the stuff we love and that's why we cover it.
But it is the niche of the niche.
Technology podcasting is a niche.
Open source and Linux is a niche within that.
Like Mac and Windows are niches within that category.
Imagine right where desktop Linux and the concerns of the open source community fit
within that overall consumer market.
We're tiny.
We're absolutely tiny.
And that's why you don't see us often featured in iTunes.
That's why you don't necessarily see us listed in Pocket Cast network list.
Because you'll see you'll see tight you'll see networks that literally get half the downloads
we get listed there simply because they cover topics that appeal to a wider audience.
So one of our major competitive disadvantages is that we talk about Linux and open source.
But at the same time, that's our biggest competitive advantage because that's all we're really
about.
We really dig into that stuff on these shows.
And if you enjoy that content, if that is something that's provided value to you or
something that you just have listened to over and over again and enjoyed, patreon.com slash
today we need you because we do not have the advantages that some of the other podcast
networks have by covering Apple and iPhones and everything Google does and all of that
extra crap that we're all sick and tired of hearing about all the time.
And so that's why we're really, really hoping that we can funnel more attention to our Patreon
and grow that because that really then unhinges us and allows us to go cray cray cray cray
Wes.
And it's great to have a system like Patreon where you really can just give money right
to the awesome people who make the show and you get a little extra bonuses.
Patreon.com slash today.
Thank you everybody who does support us.
And that brings us to the end of this week's episode of The Unplugged Program.
Oh Wes.
I feel like we could go on more and more.
The whole episode had a thread through it and I find that to be interesting since it's
not really intentional with this show.
This is The Unplugged Program and you can hang out with us live over at jblive.tv, JupiterBroadcasting.com
slash calendar to get that converted to your local time zone.
If you want to think bots do it, I'll let you believe that.
I'll let you believe that.
It's fine.
We have a mumble room if you want to participate in our virtual lug.
And last but not least, we love your feedback at linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Join us in the hallway.
All right everybody, thank you so much for tuning in to this week's episode of Unplugged.
We'll see you back here next Tuesday.
All right, so before we start the show, Mr. Corpse brought it up in the mumble room and
it's amazing.
Holy smokes.
When I got on the live stream today, this was still at three million.
It's already at four million.
Wow, so this is the Pebble 2, Time 2 and the new Pebble Core.
It already has 21,000 backers with 36 days left to go.
They had a goal of a million dollars.
They've now raised four million dollars and this is very perfect timing because some of
the discussions we're going to get into today are very much around open source projects
like the Mycroft device and others that are open crowd funded.
Open source, open different, not necessarily Kickstarter, but different methodologies of
funding.
This is one of the all-time big names on Kickstarter launching this today.
I think it's kind of perfect timing.
I don't hear anything though, it's all screwed up.
I don't know what happened there.
That was really signed up pretty well too, it's kind of a shame.
I don't know.
Let's go HTML5.
Damn it Linux, why are you doing this to me now?
What's going on baby?
Don't you love me?
Don't you love me Linux?
You know I watched this not 35 minutes ago and we're just fine.
Mustaches dude, mustaches.
Well okay let's bust it out, let's go into the lab, let's figure out what's going on
here.
I'm going to pop and lock my audio interface.
Stand by, live hotswap in progress.
Okay, hold on, hold on, reswapping, utilizing gnome extension to re-default, sound interface
recognized, original output selected, refreshing web page, activating video.
Hey, I did it, nice.
I want to reset that up in purpose.
You're an IT wizard.
Not only did that solve the problem, but there were sound effects and live commentary.
See that's how you know I used to do IT, right there.
Okay now shut up Wes, we're going to start over again because I want that S to be smooth,
okay?
All right?
Okay?
Man.
I almost blew that ass Wes.
Now this is almost perfect timing for the big show today.
Wait no that's not, damn it, see now I'm all off.
Damn, man.
We're the cute little show.
OMG, OMG, OMG.
I'm too warm Wes, I'm too warm.
All right, fine.
Hear what?
The jacket's coming off.
Even though I love this matte jacket, which Wes commented on, it's a nice Ubuntu matte
jacket that was sent to me by Mr. Wimpy and I really like it.
And it was pleasant in here until the damn log guy started doing his thing.
So now, if y'all can get your crap together, we're going to start over, okay?
And we're not going to call it the big show.