Okay, alright, so I was gonna ask if you guys, before we get started, before we get into
all the serious Linux discussion, all Linux content all the time, did you see IT, cards
against IT, that's what it's called, cards against IT, I'm such a spaz.
Cards against IT, you're familiar with cards against humanity, so like here's the white
cards rotating the backup, a PCAP, RM-RF, my rooted phone, and then you go down to of
course the actual phrases, the new IT director has a sick tattoo of blank, the last consultant
was fired over blank, forgetting the blank in the data center is a firing offense, nothing
transfers data faster than blank, so it's, yeah, blank is a layer 8 of the OSI networking
model, we're going to use blank instead of updating to IPv6, blank is the last stage
of our blank rollout, these are good, if you've been in the industry for a while, these are
all pretty good, so I recommend if you want to blow off a little steam, you go print this
out, we'll have the PDF and the show notes, it's just the same kind of like spirit of
cards against humanity, but it's cards against IT.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 109 for September 8th, 2015.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that really, really needs a shower.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hey Wes, so I'm sorry if I stink a little bit, I've taken showers recently, but not
like today.
I'm sorry.
I'm going to sit as far away as possible over here.
Yeah, that's cool, you can scoot the mic away, it's alright, actually, I'll tell you more
about that in a little bit, but we have a really great show coming up, some feedback
we've got to start with from the community that touches on a couple of topics we've been
following for a couple of weeks, and then I want to jump into this convergence demo of
some pretty performance-demanding applications running under Exmere, yeah, desktop open GPL
applications running under Mere.
Whoa.
Yes, yes, Exmere being pushed a limit, we're going to talk about that, and then also, did
you see this headline, Wes, how Debian is trying to shut down the CIA and make software
trustworthy again?
I sure did.
That's a hell of a title.
It sure is, dramatic, but important work.
Yeah, we're going to talk about what that actually is, why the Debian project wants
reproducible builds, see if I can say it, if I can reproduce the words, and why other
projects are probably going to be picking that up, including FreeBSD, NetBSD, and maybe
some other Linuxes, we'll be talking about that in just a little bit, and then, towards
the end of the show, I'm going to do my darnedest to convert Wes back to Gnome, because I'm
going to tell him what is so badass about Gnome 3.18 that's not even in the release
notes.
Oh, no.
And we might just get you to switch to Gnome by the end of this episode, Wes.
I'll be the judge.
Yeah, right.
Okay.
So, why don't we get into a little bit of business, some follow-up and some show-specific
stuff before we launch into the rest of the episode.
The first thing I want to do right here at the top of the show is give a plug to an old
friend of the show, Mr. Matt Hartley, for launching Freedom Penguin, which you can find
at freedompenguin.com, and one of the cool things he's doing is he's brought on some
friends, other friends of the show.
You guys are familiar with Albert Westra, Odyssey Westra, who joins us frequently, and
of course you're also familiar with Jed.
He contributes a lot via email and subreddits and our online community aspects.
Now there are, and also Joe Collins is writing over there, now working with Matt on Freedom
Penguin, freedompenguin.com, so that was Matt's project that he was working on for a while,
and it's been in the works since he stepped down from Linux Unplugged, and now it is here
and kicking, and you can check it out at freedompenguin.com.
Very exciting.
Yeah.
Nice to see some new stuff from Matt.
I bet if you're a solid contributor, too, I bet you he's looking for contributors.
I would guess.
So along that same bit of line of thinking, why don't we also say hello to somebody special.
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
No, not Mr. Leo Leport, our new co-host on the show officially, Mr. Wes.
Wes, remind me of your last name.
My last name is Payne, P-A-Y-N-E, Chris.
Oh yeah, look at that right there on my screen, right there.
It's right there on my screen.
You'd think I'd know that.
It's just right there.
I like that.
When I heard Payne, I thought, well, that's a pretty good last name.
Well, thank you.
Now, I would go just for your on-air persona, P-A-I-N, you know, just go for it.
I mean, just own it.
Pick it up a level.
Yeah, really, because it's a DJ name.
You've got to have a DJ name.
So Wes is going to be joining Linux Unplugged officially as the co-host going forward, which
is great because when I'm on the road trip, Wes will be here in studio and he'll have
local audio and hopefully I'll have local audio.
Show should still sound great even when I'm on the road, but it'll be nice having somebody
here that can physically push the record button and make sure we get the show out and things
like that.
Yeah, we'll hopefully have an editor coming on, another editor, to help put it all together
when we're on the road.
But yeah, so Wes, I'm super glad to have you here and congratulations to Matt for launching
Freedom Penguin and we have a heck of a show to get into.
So before we go any further, why don't we bring in the next critical piece of the show.
That's our mumble room.
Time appropriate greetings, Virtual Lug.
Hello.
Hey, guys.
A great showing.
Whoa, whoa.
All right, so I wanted to know right off the top, are you guys all ready for a system
D killer?
We have a brand new one, ladies and gentlemen.
I want to bring it into the show before we go any further right here.
It's super important.
I present to you, and Wes, you help me with the official pronunciation because otherwise
I'm going to say System 16?
I guess so.
System X V1?
What do you call this one?
It's a V?
Yeah, yeah.
So System 16 is a modern take on service management.
It aims to incorporate useful functionality while maintaining a modular design in the
Unix tradition.
System 16 uses KBuild as used by VirtualBox.
There are minimal dependencies you need, like a proc CPS and a lib KQ, I'm sorry, in the
development formats, and then you just install your distros package for KBuild, and you can
run KMK, and you are good to go.
It's free software.
It's licensed under GPL3, and it's here to replace System D. And you know what?
I'll tell you one thing that's got way better than System D, that logo.
Yeah.
System D don't got that.
No.
Colorful, bright.
I love it.
Does it have any example configuration files?
Yeah.
You can play on System 5, and obviously, but it's pretty, it's just the System D alternatives,
they never end.
I would, I dare someone, I challenge someone in the Mumble Room to run this.
Anybody want to take it?
Anybody want to try it?
Like, got a throwaway rig you could try this on?
Well, given the only result I find on Google for this is a 4chan thread, no, probably not.
Damn.
You got me.
Okay.
All right.
Very good, very good.
Let's move on to the feedback then.
So actually, can I deviate, Wes, you know, can I get Wes?
So Wes got here a little early today, and so we went out to lunch, and Wes has had to
have already heard, unfortunately, quite a bit of this, but I want to share my weekend
just really quickly with you guys.
So Friday, right after the Linux Action Show wrapped up, I took the trailer out camping,
and I went boondocking, quote unquote.
Boondocking?
Boondocking is when you're dry camping, you're off the grid.
So all I had was my Dell XPS 13 with me, and I had my S6 with me, and that was pretty solid
for two nights.
I lived off the camper's batteries, lived off the tanks, the propane, the water tanks,
and I was able to get data connectivity using my XPS just tethered to, or actually hotspot,
to the S6.
It worked okay.
But I wanted to live like a king, and my trailer came as part of the whole deal I got.
I inherited a Thousand Trails membership, which I didn't really know anything about that,
but it turns out it's like a campsite you can go take advantage of without having to
pay anything.
So for the last couple of nights, I've been hooked up on the beach with water, and sewer,
and power.
Look at that spot.
It's beautiful.
Yeah, it's a very quaint town called La Conner in Washington that I've been living out in
the trailer, just getting it ready.
And the whole idea is wrap my head around what it's like, because I have to live in
this thing for 17 days, but the thing is, I don't just have to live in this thing.
I have to work in this too, and I need to understand what I'm up against, and I can't
be always learning absolutely everything while I'm also working and traveling, right?
And wanting to also have some downtime.
So I've been spending so far the entire weekend, since I got off the air, in the rig, out there,
trying different things out, and I'm living like a king right now.
I really love it.
And so I'm trying to get my head around the road trip, really excited about how things
are coming together.
Zach the Penguin writes in, and he said, hi, I was listening to Unplugged today and I figured
I'd make some suggestions to name the road show.
How about Nation Migration, March of the Penguins, or Roll Your Own?
Just a few ideas.
Hope it helps.
I don't know if any of those are resonating with me specifically, but I thought they were
good.
So I want to keep the ball rolling.
If anybody has any names, we've got to name the road trip something.
Like today, we're trying to figure out how we're going to do live tracking so you guys
can see where I'm at so we can do meetups and you can suggest where I go and stuff like
that.
We're going to try to have live tracking during the trip, but we still don't have a name for
it.
Can't track until you have a name for it.
Got to say what you're tracking.
Very important.
So I need ideas.
I need ideas for the road show.
The Penguinator?
I don't know.
I don't think so.
Not punny enough, really.
Yeah.
I do like that.
Now it does have a bird on it.
It has a jaybird on it.
Okay.
Because it's a Jayco trailer.
And so I was thinking something to do with the bird is in there.
There's something there.
But I was thinking that might be the name for the trailer, but the trip itself.
The show has its own.
Because there could be multiple road trips.
So we need to be able to differentiate the different road shows.
The journey to Jupiter.
Well, because there could be future trips.
So we got to...
We got to start with the journey to Mars.
No, that doesn't make sense.
What happens when I run out of plan is when I stop taking road trips, we need a bigger
solar system.
The final destination, well, so for those of you who are not familiar, I'm going to
Grand Forks, North Dakota.
I'm going to do a show of Linux, an episode of Linux action show at Noah's house.
Try to get a last Cribs episode in, something we committed to a while ago.
And then meander my way, meander down to Utah and visit a few national parks down there
and then make my way back up.
Linux road show seems too obvious.
Seems too obvious.
Forking Jupiter.
Jupiter ascending.
Okay.
I don't want to get copyright takedowns.
All right.
So then let's move on to the next email that is maybe a bit more appropriate for feedback.
Sean writes in about Jose, who wrote in about his MacBook.
He says, I've been running Linux on my MacBook Pro for about four years now.
I just switched back to Fedora 22 from OpenSUSE.
I've been rocking SUSE since 2007 and my MacBook has never worked better.
Now he's on Fedora 22 and he says, he thinks it's because it has kernel 4.1.
It's finally given me good hardware support for the keyboard backlight, the thermal fan
controls, CPU scaling, and the battery life is better.
One thing that I've done to extend battery life is buy the Fluendo codec suite and switch
to Gstreamer based video player.
The Fluendo codecs have much better video acceleration for video decoding, taking the
load off of the CPU.
Well, that's a good tip.
Also, not all Gstreamer video players are created equal.
Totem is still pretty heavy on the CPU, 24% when playing a 1080p HD 64 video, but streaming
something lightweight like MPV sits around 12% and this is on a Sandy Bridge i5.
I haven't tried Arch on here yet, but I imagine getting a similar setup wouldn't be too hard.
I wish Jose the best of luck.
Don't give up on Linux.
Well, that's really cool.
If 4.1 brought in thermal fan control, holy crap.
That's a huge deal.
I think MacBooks are definitely one of those areas where you get to see the exciting march
of kernel progress in terms of hardware support.
Yeah.
I actually surprised tech this long considering that Linus uses a MacBook Air.
You know what I mean?
Yeah.
That is surprising.
All right.
So Mumbo, did you guys have any ideas for a roadshow name?
Nobody?
Come on.
Everybody's got to have something very punny and quippy, no?
Well Chris, you know that there's the Empire Builder train from North Dakota to Washington,
so Empire Penguin Builder.
Wait, should I just be taking the train?
Is that what you're saying?
Maybe I'll just take the train next time.
Yeah.
Dubstep Alan, oh my god.
If Alan approves it, I almost want to call it that.
I almost want to call it that if he approves it because it doesn't make any sense, but
if you've been around in the chat room for a while, it's so perfect.
Can we print up like a vinyl of his face and stick it on the side?
If somebody can politely get Alan's consent without harassing him, chat room, it's okay
to name it.
Now don't tell him it's my idea.
I think it should be Corky.
I think Corky has been elected for this.
He might make us put Beastie on there.
Yeah, or maybe like have to name like a future roadshow the FreeBSD Trip or something.
That's a reasonable compromise.
No, I don't think so actually.
Oh man, I don't think I can do it.
Alan Jude types with one finger, he points out with the keyboard and the keyboard does
the rest.
Oh my god.
Great.
This is what...
Legends of Alan.
This is how egos are born, ladies and gentlemen.
This is how nice guys get egos.
All right, so let's get your ego better.
How do I say I know, right?
How do you do that?
I'll tell you how.
Learning, making yourself smarter, making yourself more employable.
Yeah, I'm talking about Linux Academy.
Go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and get our 33% discount, like a boss, 33% discount
is nuts.
It's crazy.
Go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and check them out.
So Linux Academy is a great resource to learn more about any technology around Linux.
I mean, obviously all the Linux basics and the essentials.
That's what you're going to get there.
And then everything around, you know, NGINX, Apache, OpenStack, virtualization, containerization,
all of that.
You're going to get that.
Self-paced too.
The courses are really good with videos and there's downloadable comprehensive study guides.
And PDFs that you can take with you or audio files you can listen to while you're naked
and wet in the shower.
I mean, good stuff.
And stuff that's going to stick with you too.
The kind of stuff that sticks on your bones and you remember because it's hands-on.
It's scenario based.
So you're really using the technology and you're working with it.
And you get to choose from seven plus Linux distributions, which is pretty sweet.
And the nice part about that is it's not just the courseware, which man, can you imagine
how dedicated and passionate you have to be just to create seven different iterations
of the courseware?
How do you systemize that in a way that makes that straightforward?
You still have to input all those different variations.
I mean, you still have to check it.
It is nuts.
They clearly love what they do here.
Seriously.
And the nice thing is it also adjusts the virtual machines that spin up.
So everything comes with labs and you can do this stuff on, well not everything, but
all the courses that need to come with labs.
And when you turn them on, they match the distribution you've chosen.
It's brilliant.
Now you've heard me talk about Linux Academy for a while.
Did you know you could actually go work for them too?
Linux Academy is hiring and they're looking for some great new content creators.
They're also looking to fill some DevOps professionals and developers.
They're looking for anybody that does Linux development like C and C++, Bash, Perl, Python.
They're also looking for big data and machine learning developers who would love to share
their knowledge.
So they have educators that can help you put this into a format that's presentable.
But if this is an expertise you have, they really want to dive into that.
And if you're not even interested in video creation, they're also looking for certified
professionals to help increase just the exam database.
The Academy is going to pay $1 to $25 per question depending on the quality, depth and
accuracy of the questions.
Maybe if you just want to write up some good questions, that might be something to check
out.
Here's how you can get started.
Email career at linuxacademy.com.
And if you want to take advantage of Linux Academy, and I really think you should, it's
a great resource, especially if you can get your work to pay for it.
Oh man, that's a real slam dunk.
And work, by the way.
They have team accounts.
That's pretty cool.
So go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged business or personal.
You can get our discount.
Try it out for a little while for a 33% discount rate, which is nuts, essentially.
What a deal.
I think like a month of your first quarter is paid for with that or even more.
It's a really good deal.
It's super sweet.
I mean, it's such a good opportunity to get started, and it's something where your money
is going to a company who's crazy passionate about the ecosystem around it.
It's not just a feature checkbox for their online learning platform.
It's actually what they do.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged, and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring
the Linux Unplugged show, program, talk show, whatever you want to call it, we think.
Experience.
Yeah, that's good.
We should just call all these shows experiences, because you experience it however you want.
So Poby was busy this week in making sure that the MIR propaganda pumped out to all
of the usual presses and made sure that Joey over at OMG Ubuntu wrote up this great article.
I'm totally kidding.
But actually, Joey did catch a good spot.
Some Canonical employees were at a recent developer sprint, and this video was distributed
internally at Canonical to distribute the progress made on Xorg compatibility for MIR.
So like X apps running on top of MIR, you know, like XMIR.
And I just want to show a little bit of the video, even though you might be listening,
it's actually still pretty obvious if you just listen what they're doing here.
And it's looking pretty good.
So this is at the sprint.
We have our legacy X app icon.
So this is Unity 8, and they're showing here like the Chrome icon, the Firefox icon, GIMP,
and these are all X applications.
Chrome, UM, Firefox, G-Edit, UM, D-Brack Office, and XChat Ganon.
My screen isn't touch, so I have to do everything via quick pad, but we will start this out
out of the way.
There, he launches Firefox.
Cool about it.
Because whenever you exit, it thinks it's crashed, but it's okay.
So this, my understanding, and if I'm wrong, anybody feel free to correct me, but this
instance of Firefox is in its own container, I believe.
It's like, it's isolated from the rest of the operating system.
It's an X application running under MIR right here using, on the Unity 8 desktop.
So now here's the OpenGL demo that actually impressed me.
This is running, this is WebGL running in Firefox, and you know, he has a ton of fish
on the screen.
Remember, this is under MIR, but this is Firefox in X application.
And that's not necessarily a very nice laptop either, I was just about to say that, yeah.
That is pretty good.
Now, I don't know much more than what's in this video.
Is there any background, Poppy, you want to fill in, or any details you want to point
out that we might have missed?
So this was done, the video was taken a couple of weeks ago when we were all in London for
a sprint, so we get together now and then in various places around the world where it's
just faster for you to all work sat next to each other.
You can have meetings and stuff as well, but it just works out quite nicely.
You can work pretty efficiently and quickly.
And Chris Townsend, who's the guy operating the laptop, was just giving a demo to Kevin
Gunn who made the video, and Kevin was just asking him to just do a demo of the progress
that they'd made that week.
And you're right, it is all containerized, and the reason for that is so that it respects
the architecture we've got for MIR applications under MIR.
So all the applications on the phone and on the desktop under MIR are siloed.
They're containerized, so that they can't interfere with each other and stomp on each
other's files and so on.
And we want to allow legacy apps to run under MIR as well, but also not be able to stomp
on all the other files, and don't allow Firefox to be able to read your contacts database
or whatever.
And so they've developed this tool called Libertine, which is on Launchpad, which is
the tool that containerizes all of this and makes it all kind of work, and it's pretty
cool.
Yeah.
So if you wanted to try this, is this something people could get their hands on yet?
Or how exactly?
Yeah, I mean, you could.
You could.
I know you probably would want to, but...
I mean, he's got a dedicated...
He actually, you see on his desk, he's got two laptops, because the one on the right
is the one running Unity 8 and MIR, and he has it set up in a very specific way.
It's an Intel machine because of drivers.
So it's a little bit tricky to get going, but once it's in a state where it's something
we can share, I'm sure more people will use it.
I mean, it's all open source.
It's all on Launchpad, so it's not like we're hiding it or anything.
It's all available.
We just haven't made an image with it in or anything yet.
It seems like the key thing here is these XMIR applications are actually working pretty
well.
And that's got to be a pretty big point because I would think, I don't know, but I would think
a large percentage of the applications people are going to be using on a Unity 8 MIR desktop
is old X apps for a long time, especially the most critical ones like Firefox and Chrome
when they're using it on the desktop.
Right.
There's going to be a few.
I mean, there's going to be a few apps that everybody...
Maybe the majority.
If you look down your list of apps that you have open right now, they're X apps and many
of them won't run under Wayland or MIR.
So yes, we need to provide...
I mean, this is the whole part of the strategy of heading towards convergences.
We still need to provide a way for people to run their existing apps.
We're not just going to drop everything and say, ha, all that stuff you've built up over
the last 15 years, screw that stuff, throw it all away.
That's not what we're doing.
We're trying to make it possible for people to run those applications that they're familiar
with, but in performant way, but siloed so that they don't stumble over each other.
Because if we go back to having all the applications able to stumble over each other, then we're
no better than running under X.
We might as well just stay with X.
So it's a nice way to allow people to continue to run the apps they love on a new desktop.
So I'm going to ask you, Wes, since you're a practical tiling window manager kind of
thing, if you were going to do this, so you're on, like your home rig right now is Mint?
My home rig is Arch.
Oh, your home rig is Arch.
Your work rig is Mint.
Yes.
So if you were going to upgrade one of these machines, would you look at the apps you're
running?
I mean, is this at a stage, say in a little while, would you switch to something like
Wayland or Mir if almost every single app you're using is X-based?
Or is it just one of those things where you would just stay on X?
I'm trying to decide from my standpoint, when does it make sense for me to switch over and
why?
And I'm looking at, it's got to be based on, that decision, which could be down the road
quite a ways, maybe I don't need to worry about it right now, it seems like that decision
is going to be based on the apps I use.
What are you going to base the decision on?
Well, you know, obviously if I'm running Arch, I'm interested in new interesting things.
So I do want to give them a try.
I'm very interested.
The fact that you can just run your X app sandboxed in Mir, that's kind of really likeable.
So you might try just from the experimentation.
Yeah, and the fact that they're already sandboxed is awesome.
Yeah.
Hmm.
I'm not sure now is a good time to switch or any time really soon.
Or even if I would, I personally, I don't think I would switch to this right now.
And that's because I'm using a lot of Debian packages on my Debian-like style desktop.
And as we keep saying, that's not going away.
Everything's baked from those raw ingredients, which are the Debian packages.
Yeah.
So, you know, I can see people like expert users like you and me, and you know, many
of your listeners are already used to that and will just carry on using that.
But someone who goes into a store and buys a laptop that has Ubuntu pre-installed, maybe
in a couple of years, right?
That may have Unity 8 and Mir pre-installed, but have a nice button that lets you install
apps that they're familiar with, that they've seen before, or that some online guide or
an expert friend has told them to get.
So I think probably those are the kind of people who would probably move first.
But we might experiment.
Like you say, Wes, you know, have a look at it, have a play with it.
Maybe it won't-
I wonder.
I think so.
I think a percent, a niche of the niche will.
But I also wonder if many people, if the threshold's always going to be, well, what are my applications?
Then I wonder if it's going to be one of those things that just keeps getting delayed and
delayed and delayed for the most people.
But I'll give Northranger a chance to jump in with visions of if we no longer had to
deal with X.
Go ahead, Northranger.
Yeah.
I mean, with your desktop environments like KDE and GNOME on the desktop, getting much
improved support in the last 12 months, and the push from folks like Canonical on the
mobile side, I think we might see a switch to these next generation, whether it's Wayland,
Mirror, et cetera, on the various platforms.
We'll see that switch happen sooner rather than later because we'll get benefits in performance
of the actual desktop environment.
You know, on a tablet, you definitely want every last little bit of frame rate, the fewest
milliseconds of touch response time where technologies like Mirror are a real benefit.
So as long as your base desktop is running it, even if your apps are containerized and
running through the second layer X server, we can live with that.
Yeah.
Yeah, I agree.
Yeah, if there's quick adoption there, that would be...
I could see myself like when I run on a GNOME desktop, I try to run like all GTK applications.
And when I run on a KDE desktop, I try to run all QT applications.
I could see a time where if there's enough applications, I might use one web browser
over the other if it was native to Wayland versus an X app.
Could you see yourself doing that?
I could definitely, yeah.
And if running the X app still works really well, then why not switch to the back end?
That Firefox WebGL demo was fairly impressive to me because that doesn't seem to be much
of a...
Even if there is a performance penalty, if it can do that fairly successful, the performance
penalty is not going to be that big to your web browsing session.
And so if you're curious what we're talking about, we have the video embedded in the show
notes.
And I'm glad you guys decided to post that, Poppy, because I know it's not like the most
polished video, but it's really cool to see.
Very interesting.
Yeah.
To really see it.
And it's nice.
I think you're going to see some more of those.
Good.
I think that was the first of...
A trial balloon?
I think we want to show off some of this stuff because we get a reputation for sitting in
rooms and doing stuff privately and all the code is on Launchpad, but because people don't
build it and run it and see it, they think that it doesn't exist when in fact it's actively
worked on.
And that video is two weeks old.
It's on Launchpad, there's really loads of changes since then.
So this video shows us it is true.
You guys are working together in closed rooms, but now you're just showing it to us.
Documented closed rooms.
No, it's just funny.
Because it's cool that you're publishing that.
It's a good point.
Well taken.
And for me, it was like, well, this is...
And you know what the other thing is, Poppy, is the Internet's full of lazy cats.
Who wants to sit there and build all that stuff when you can just watch a YouTube video
of it?
And one of the things that some of the other desktop projects have going for them is they
just have super enthusiastic fans that go and do video production.
We're going to talk about when we get to GNOME 3.18, we're going to talk about some of these
videos that show off GNOME 3.18 and some of these write-ups that the GNOME Foundation
should be paying these people for it.
It's so well done.
And so it's good to get your version of it out there, too.
That's what I say to that.
And I like seeing that WebGL demo.
I'm not going to admit it.
Slick.
Yeah, very slick.
You know what else is real slick there, Wes?
This is super crazy slick.
In fact, I love them.
I use them all the time.
DigitalOcean.
Heck yeah, it's DigitalOcean.
Where's my...
Hold on.
Here we go.
You got to go there right now, actually.
I was going to say, if you don't know about DigitalOcean, then I got bad news.
You have been under a rock because something really cool has been developing for a long
time.
And you can get on it for two months for absolutely free when you use our promo code, DOUNPLUGGED.
Go over to digitalocean.com and remember DOUNPLUGGED.
And now I'm going to tell you about them.
DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and
easy way for you to get your own Linux machine up in the sky.
Now yeah, you could also deploy FreeBSD, but come on, you're listening to Linux Unplugged.
And they have CoreOS, which is really cool.
They work with the CoreOS folks.
And they have Ubuntu on there, and they've got the LTSs, and they've got the 1504.
They even have the latest Fedora.
Like after a couple of weeks after...
I mean, I'm not trying to burn you Corora guys, but come on.
DigitalOcean has Fedora 22 up on DigitalOcean for immediate deployment before the Corora
project even gets their respin out.
Now come on guys, I know you're busy, but come on.
Come on.
Come on, DigitalOcean.
I mean, of course, you know what?
The problem is they're just super badass.
In fact, check out their interface and you can see how it's a priority for them.
They've managed to take something complicated like managing servers around the world and
make it in a super simple, straightforward interface.
In fact, the other thing that's really cool about that interface is they have an API.
And that API lets you do all the things you want to do, either automated or through some
of the great community apps.
So remember that promo code DOUNPLUGGED?
Here's what I want you to remember.
Go over there and use it because you're going to get a $10 credit and the base rig starts
at $5 a month.
They get you 512 megabytes of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a terabyte of transfer.
Now the nice thing is if you wanted to do something really beefy, like I decided when
I went Minecraft for my son, I wanted to go just kind of a little bit more beefy.
The pricing is really straightforward.
It's just $10, you get an even nicer rig, $20, you get an even nicer rig.
It's obvious.
It's right there.
And then the other thing that's really cool is if you want to do some testing or production
load balancing, they have hourly pricing.
It's really neat.
And then the other thing that they don't really mention a lot on their site, but I think they
should, I think they should put it in here as like a little asterisk, is they also have
private networking.
And you can set up private networking between your different droplets and then you can have
like a front-end web server and a back-end database server or a front-end X2Go server
and a back-end NAS server, right?
And the transfer over that private networking is free.
So you don't have to pay for any data.
So if you're doing like backups, that's really nice.
In fact, here's what you can go to DigitalOcean.
You can read more about it.
It's really straightforward to set up.
It's a really cool system.
And I think it's like we did an episode about remote Linux desktops at the Linux Action
Show a couple of months ago.
You combine a front-end X2Go server with a couple of back-end droplets, and all of these
things are like $5 a month, plus you use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED, you get the $10 credit.
It's a really cool way to do this.
And you can start kind of thinking about things a little differently because you can really
build your own private infrastructure up there, all running on top of a Linux KVM server,
all SSDs throughout, and the pricing is very straightforward.
Go check them out, DigitalOcean.com and use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED and a big thanks
to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
You guys got a great service.
You rock.
Oh, man.
I wish I could do a good...
Can you do any accents, Wes?
I can't.
I wish I could do a Scottish accent.
Oh, I can't.
I wish.
I can do bad accents.
Can you do Canadian?
No?
Usually all Americans can do Canadian, Wes.
They just don't want to.
All right.
So let's move on.
Let's talk about how Debian is going to shut down the CIA.
Oh, man.
I don't know about this.
So Motherboard, which as we were talking about in the pre-show, is a vice company, is really
getting into a nitty-gritty topic in the Linux distro world.
And I was kind of surprised to see this.
So that was one of the reasons why I actually wanted to cover it in the show today, is this
is new territory for Motherboard, and they're obviously trying to drive clicks with that,
how Debian is trying to shut down the CIA headline and make software trustworthy again.
But the effort is almost worth a grabby headline like that.
So this is from a presentation that was given at the Chaos Communications Camp in Germany
earlier this month.
So I have the full presentation linked in the show notes.
And by a Debian developer, Jeremy, oh, I'm not sure how you pronounce it, Bobbio, or
something, B-O, Bobbio, B-O, B-B-I-O, B-O, B-B-I-O.
I love it.
Whatever it is.
But this I can say.
He's better known online as Lunar.
And he told the audience how Linux-based operating systems are working to bring reproducible
builds to all of its 22,000 software packages, so all of Debian's packages.
So here's a layman's breakdown of what a reproducible build is if you're not familiar.
As the name suggests, it makes it possible for other people to reproduce the build process.
The idea is to get a reasonable confidence that a given binary was indeed produced by
the source.
This is a quote from Lunar's presentation.
We want anyone to be able to produce identical binaries from given source.
A software package reproducibility build should be byte for byte identical to the publicly
available package.
Any difference would be evidence of tampering.
Reproducible builds rely in part on David A. Wheeler's solution to this problem called
diverse double compiling.
Are you ready for this one, Wes?
Well, let's hear it.
Are you excited?
I am.
Okay, good, good.
I'm giddy.
So Lunar explains you need two compilers with one that you somehow trust.
Then you build the compiler under test twice, once with each compiler, and then you use
the compilers that you just built to build the compiler under test again.
If the output is the same, then there are no back doors.
But for this scheme to work, you need to be able to compare that both outputs are the
same.
And that's exactly what we are enabling with having reproducible builds.
According to Lunar, 83% of Debian's packages are now built reproducibly with more of the
join the party every day.
So does this sound kind of like in line with what you've read about reproducible builds?
Is this essentially you can take the source and when you build it, it's exactly what the
source should be, exactly what the author says?
Yes.
So one of the big challenges is making sure that you've got a build system set up in such
a way that you can easily do that and that other people can easily replicate.
Yeah, because there is the issue is the compiler compromise.
Like if you're really worried about a state actor, the compiler could be the weak link.
So that is a key piece of this.
So when I see this, I think to myself, well, this seems like A, from a technical standpoint,
an amazing feat to pull off.
Okay, so let's read this part again.
You need two compilers with one that you trust, then you build the compiler under test twice,
once with each compiler.
Okay, so you build the compiler twice, once with each compiler, and then you use the compilers
that you just built to build the compiler again under test.
That's how you verify a compiler.
Wow.
If the output is the same, then that compiler has no back doors.
Yeah, that just verifies that the compiler doesn't have any back doors.
Right, but you need, yes, right.
The idea is you have to have a verifiable compiler and then you have to have verifiable
packages too.
Like it's not just one or the other.
That's the tricky thing, I think, right?
Am I following this right?
That seems like, yeah.
Well, it's not that tricky.
Even though they say reproducible, you can also say it verifiable, or authentic build
builds because the output will be identical from either compiler.
Break it down.
So why do you say authentic?
What did you say?
Or because you can just hash or-
Oh yeah, okay.
Verify.
Because it's binary.
So bit per bit compatible or comparable and exact to what the other compilers put out.
So you can have an official version.
Right, yeah.
That makes sense.
That's what they mean.
Instead of just reproducible builds, they're just using a different name.
Verifiable builds are a lot more common.
You disagree, Wimpy?
No.
Yeah, I do because the issue here is ensuring that your origin compiler wasn't backdoored
at the outset and therefore everything you compile contains a backdoor that was in that
compiler.
Right.
Like the big boogeyman story is the NSA gets credentials to a repo and replaces FTP or
something like that.
Or you go back to the very first version, the very first compiler that Richard Stallman
used to build the GNU toolchain and was that backdoored and compromised and therefore is
every GNU compiler since compromised or rather everything that the GNU compiler creates compromised.
So this is a real tinfoil hat example, but the issue here is making sure that there isn't
a backdoor in the compiler that introduces backdoors into your compiled code.
Yeah.
That's also why they need to have the same Blitzy in all the libraries that they link
to.
They have to include them in order to have the reproducible builds.
Yeah.
So this is something that is essentially more of a process problem than it is a technology
problem for these distros.
So essentially what Debian is implementing is a process, right?
And so this is something that other distros should probably look at, I would think.
Should this be something that Red Hat can claim as well?
Wouldn't SUSE want to be able to claim this as well?
I would think.
It might help their verifiability or static analysis.
So like-
It adds one more thing to there.
Yeah.
Because this is, as the motherboard article points out, this is a staple of the Bitcoin
and Tor project today.
Obviously these projects, they need this kind of verifiability, so they already do this.
And FreeBSD, NetBSD, and OpenWRT have announced that they'll also be doing this.
So it seems like there's a big movement here to me for people that want to be trusted.
So you've got to figure it's something that's on a lot of people's minds.
And Red Hat's been looking into a lot of this stuff, so I don't know.
I wouldn't be surprised if we don't see an announcement at some point.
Kind of similar to the functional package managers like Nix.
Yeah.
They have like a hash of all the dependencies that go into building.
They kind of do this by default.
Huh.
I don't know if all the implications are there necessarily, but-
I'm going to make a prediction right now.
Red Hat 8, one of the features on the box, reproducible builds.
You watch.
You've called it.
Yeah.
What was it?
I know somebody was going to say something.
Also, they don't even need to just be built for security reasons.
Building for containerization and virtualization and cloud purposes also benefit from this
reproducible build stuff.
Oh yeah.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Yeah.
There is that aspect to it, just ensuring you're delivering your software completely
and things like that.
Yeah.
I think the reason why we took the bent of the NSA and CIA is because, well, Lunar says,
he says, what was the line he said here?
The great thing is that free software is... No, that's not it.
This is actually a good quote.
I'll read this anyways.
The great thing with free software is that we have the freedom to study the source code,
that it does not contain any malware, malicious code, or security, but how, Lunar asks, do
we know that the compiler binary was not built from the published source?
How do we know the CIA or other malicious attacker has not tampered with the build process?
He says, we are not discussing a hypothetical attack here.
This is a real attack.
We are talking about developers in totally good faith producing software with the binary
they would give you, and even if they are of good faith, we could be totally owned still.
Reproducible builds already are a state of... Oh, I read that part, of Bitcoin and the
Tor project.
So he argues that it's already a real attack problem, and he's kind of the one, I think,
put the CIA spin on it, that the motherboard took and ran.
Well, and it does sound here, it looks like the CIA tried to break into Apple, which is
...
Oh, yeah.
And I also think there's been some questions about the Debian project itself, too.
Yeah, I mean, they distribute a lot of software.
There was a talk given on this subject at FOSDEM earlier this year, and it wasn't just
related to this.
It was also the auditability and the fact that actually some of the packages in the
archive were built not by the builders, builders in the cloud, but actually on developers'
local machines, and what really should happen is all of those builds should move to the
server where they can be verified, because if they're being built on a local machine
by a developer, then it makes it even harder to verify that it's not been compromised.
Yeah, because who knows the state of that developer machine?
Yeah.
Oh, you developers.
Developer machines are notorious.
Developers, developers, developers.
Yeah, interesting, and it's an area that is sort of new to me, but it sounds like actually
once you kind of take away some of the... You just change the words you use, and it actually
makes a lot of sense.
It looks like they've got a link to the full slides and discussion.
Yes, sir.
I'll put a link to that there in the show notes directly.
Now, it is a PDF, but it's his whole presentation that he gave.
It looks like a lot of good information.
Yeah, and he has some good quotes in there, too.
He starts out with a really good quote, so it's worth a read if you're fascinated by
this topic as I was.
I probably will pick it up after the show, actually, because I don't have very good connectivity
out in the trailer, but I can download that to my Instapaper, too.
There you go.
Just read it offline.
I might actually do that.
That's a good idea.
I have a little bookmark that just sends it right into my queue.
Very nice.
Yeah, it is nice.
All right.
Speaking of connectivity, I've got to tell you about my good friends over at the Ting
Network.
I want you to go there and check them out, too, won't you?
Because we have a special $50 promo at linux.ting.com.
linux.ting.com will give you the $50 promo off a device, or if you have a compatible
device already, then they're going to give you $50 of service credit, which is really,
really, really, really slick.
This is only going on until the end of September, so I want you to go over there and try them
right now.
If you're a small business, too, this is a really slick way to get not just good devices,
but just constant connectivity and communications that doesn't require an arm and a leg to pay
for it.
Here's why.
No contract, nor the termination fee, and you only pay for what you use.
Six dollars is the starting rate, and then it's just your usage on top of that.
Now, if you can be really handy with your Wi-Fi usage, like we are here at the studio,
it's really slick.
You can get SIM cards right now as low as $5.
So if you've got a device that works with Ting's GSM network, $5 SIM card, and you're
on Ting.
It's really, really nice.
Free shipping right now.
Also, they've got some great phones on sale.
You can get the Kiosar Kona for $68.
If you just want a great feature phone with a good screen and the battery that lasts forever
ever, like five days, $68.
No contract, nor the termination fee.
Refurbished Samsung Galaxy S3, $122.
Now here's the good one.
Samsung Galaxy S6.
My baby.
You can get $80 off.
Now it's $568, but you own that phone like you would a laptop or a smart, you know, like
a real device.
Not a toy, but a real device.
That's nice.
And then the nice thing is if you ever get stuck, Ting has no hold customer service.
You call them at 1855 Ting FTWs.
But even better than that, they have like the best dashboard ever to manage all of this.
You can do everything from the Ting dashboard.
You can get a real easy, like they have this promo picture right here, and you're like,
oh, that's a nice mocked up image of what the Ting, no, that's what the Ting dashboard
looks like.
It's really what it looks like.
It's very, very, very slick.
And this video shows you some of it.
And it kind of gives you an idea.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
Go Wes.
Nice, buddy.
That's right.
And the next thing you can do, so we have several, we have several phones on our, on
our line and you just go in there and name them.
So I don't have to like remember the numbers.
It just shows me the name of each device.
I can see the usage so I can see like who's taking up all the data.
I can set alerts if I need to or want to, but it's not really a big deal since we're
only paying like 40 bucks a month for all three phones at the most.
You can also do things like if you want one line that maybe hides caller ID or a one line
that can't do video messaging or something like that, you can go turn those individual
things on and off in the dashboard, all kinds of stuff like that.
You can also just disable the line for a little while if you don't need it.
So it's pretty cool.
And it also all integrates in with the dash app on the phone for iPhone or Android.
You can get push notifications if you want them, but I don't really, again, because the
ting rates are so low.
I don't really care.
But you can manage all the aspects of the plan from the device right there if you need
to.
That's particularly nice if you've got like a teenager or something who's burning through
that data watching YouTube.
My son is six years old and he's already doing it.
So I feel your pain.
But the nice thing is I can get alerts if I need them.
And it works pretty good.
And you can also call them at 1-855-TING-FTW anytime between 8 a.m. or 8 p.m. and you can
talk to a real human being.
Just get started by going to linux.ting.com.
They'll take $50 off your first device or if you've got a compatible device, you can
get $50 of service credit.
Now, I'm telling you, I've got three phones, okay?
Now I'm very Wi-Fi savvy to be honest with you, but I've got three phones and I'm paying
like 40 bucks a month.
So if you can get a $50 service credit by bringing a compatible phone because I've got
a CDMA and GSM, that's pretty sweet.
That's pretty sweet.
Plus, you know, just checking them out also helps us out.
Go to linux.ting.com and try their savings calculator.
Maybe it's worth your time.
Linux.ting.com and a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
Okay, Wes, brace yourself, my friend.
Are you ready to switch to GNOME?
Say no if you're not because maybe by the end you will be.
Maybe I need a little more convincing.
Okay, all right.
All right.
Okay.
So I got to start with a shout out to World of Goo or WooGoo or whatever, WooGoo, W-O-G-U-E.
And this guy is essentially blogging on Google Plus about features about GNOME.
And he just does a really, really, really, really great job.
So I want to give him a shout out because a lot of the stuff he's pulling out that are
not in the release notes specifically, they're not really...
GNOME is not doing a particularly good job about promoting these features.
So he goes out of his way to put really great videos together that cover all the different
cool features of GNOME that you don't see.
Watch this one here.
They have one of the things...
Okay, Wes, this is going to be one of the first new features I want to show you.
See if he...
Oh, hi there, ladies.
So here's the...
Did those come with the terminal?
No, no.
So he has these videos that show the new features of GNOME and he does a really good job of
going through this.
But check out this new feature, Wes.
One of the first new features that's coming to a GNOME 3.18's terminal is they've made
the terminal much slicker.
But he's got a lot of good music going, doesn't he?
Oh, yeah.
Okay, Wes, watch this terminal.
Watch this terminal.
You see that?
Okay, hold on.
Sorry, he's got his titles in the way so you can't quite see it.
There it goes.
All right, so he's got the GNOME terminal up right now and he's changing one setting
in there and check this out.
You can drag tabs around.
See that?
Look at that.
That's very...
Very nice.
Okay, so the new GNOME terminal...
This is the only weekend that I'm building up.
The new GNOME terminal has a very much like Firefox tab-like thing.
You can drag them around.
You drag them off the terminal where they pop up into their own tab, that kind of thing.
That's not bad, right?
Yeah.
You're with me so far?
Oh, yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Honestly, I already like GNOME terminal.
It's pretty reliable.
Yeah, yeah.
But that's not bad.
Okay, I'm still getting there.
Of course, Northern Ranger, if I don't get to it, then you can announce it.
But now here's the next one.
Wes, we were talking about Wayland earlier today and I want to make the case, even though
the Kaywin project is coming very far on its Wayland support, I have to say, GNOME 3.18
is introducing some impressive Wayland features.
The most anticipated feature, for me at least, is somebody just finally said, so we're really
here with Wayland, but we're close.
Because NVIDIA doesn't support Wayland yet, so that's a big stopper.
But if you can get around the fact that NVIDIA isn't supporting Wayland, the GNOME 3.18 desktop
is pretty rock solid now.
A bunch of improvements have gone into Mudder specifically, so it's very performant under
Wayland.
They've set up shared clipboards now, so your X applications and your Wayland applications
can copy and paste between each other.
It's really good stuff.
And so the world of GooGuy or WooGoo or whatever, he has been blogging like a machine about
all the different things that are working and not working and problems like that.
But it's looking like Wayland support is looking really good, almost good enough for everyday
use, especially if you're on Intel now, starting with GNOME 3.18.
Everyday use.
Whoop.
Are you ready for this?
I might be.
You know, I swear I muted my phone before the show started, and somehow during the show
it got unmuted.
I do not know how that happened.
All right, so okay, the next feature.
Are you ready for the next feature of GNOME 3.18?
Are you ready for the next feature?
Let's hear it.
All right, the next feature for GNOME 3.18 is going to disable that crappy search in the
open dialog box and on network drives, recursive search that kills Nautilus and makes it die,
and finally fixes that up.
What do you think of that one?
What do you got?
Nothing?
Long overdue.
Yeah, I'm not.
I'm not surprising you.
About damn time.
All right.
Okay, now you're ready for the...
Of course, I don't know if I'm going to sell you with this one, but one of the big features
that's making a lot of headlines today, this is the one that everybody's talking about
as we record, GNOME 3.18 is going to allow you direct access to Google Drive right in
Nautilus.
Oh, really?
Yeah.
Right in.
Built right in Nautilus.
GNOME, you're going to have access.
That's going to mount to kind of like a web drive, kind of share, so it's going to be...
What is it using in the back end?
Probably some kind of web drive.
It's not full sync.
Okay.
Far as I know.
But NorthRanger, was that what you...
You thought the big lead was the Google Drive support, or something else you're excited
about?
I was actually excited about the Wayland clipboard support.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
And it's full like drag and drop even.
Like you can...
Oh, wow.
Yeah.
It's real nice work.
They've really done...
That's a big improvement.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
It really is kind of...
It's going to make it much easier to coexist with Xapps and Wayland apps on the same desktop.
So that's a huge deal, but if you're not running Wayland yet, it's not app big.
But the fact that they're basically saying we're getting close to everyday use is really,
I think, pretty exciting.
I think GNOME 3.18 is actually going to look like a really good release, and I didn't really
know.
One of the things is, I started digging around before we started this episode to kind of
see, okay, well, here's what the GNOME project sort of outlined about what's really cool.
But when you actually start digging into some of the release notes and things like that,
there's things they're not putting in the release notes that are...
There's a lot of little small improvements that they're bringing into GNOME 3.18 that
I don't know.
I think it's looking like a really great desktop.
So if you're going to try out Wayland...
That seems like the way to do it.
It seems like, I think.
I think if you're going to try...
I don't know how your awesome window manager is going to work, Wes, but I think if you're
going to try...
I just love that I don't...
I don't think this is looking like you're having a hard time.
I think if you're going to try out Wayland, I think you're going to have to try out GNOME
3.18.
I think you're right.
Okay, we'll see.
I mean, GNOME is fast becoming, you know, it...
All right, second prediction of the show.
Second prediction of the show, Wes switches back to GNOME.
I swear.
Because right now you've got Awesome and Cinnamon.
Yep.
Does anybody know, anybody know what Cinnamon's plan is for Wayland?
What's the, what's the plans there?
Is...
Are they working on that right now?
I know they're using GTK 3.
Yeah, yeah.
I guess as long as...
And they're...
What are they using?
What's the compositor for?
They're...
Well, it's, it's called...
It's forked from mutter and there's...
Yeah, that's right.
It's called...
It begins with M, muffin.
But when I spoke to Clem about this a little while ago, he's just waiting for Wayland to
really get to the point where it's got mass adoption behind it.
And I think what that really means is that the, the GPU vendors support it.
Yeah.
And you know, he also probably wants to see just where things play out with, with Mir
too, because I mean, if he's based on Ubuntu, that might end up being a way to go too.
So the GNOME 3.18 release, why, why am I talking about this right now?
Because it's supposed to come out by the end of the month and I might be on the road when
it hits.
And I don't know if I'm going to have the bandwidth to download it and give it a review.
So I just wanted to kind of talk about it right now because I'm going to be jonesing
for it.
When I have that...
Oh man.
Oh, that's going to be rough.
If GNOME 3.18 hits.
I bet it doesn't hit stable repos, but I bet by the time I get back, I bet it's not in
stable, but before I get back, I bet, I bet, I bet it won't hit the stable.
Can you wait?
I don't think I could.
I think I'll...
If it hits stable repos while I'm on the road, I think I will probably find a spot to get
wifi.
And I think I will do the updates.
I have to man.
You kind of have to.
I mean, I can't go a couple of days.
Yeah.
I'll go to a Starbucks.
I'll go to XT and I'll do the update there.
Yeah.
I will know.
I'm hoping.
I haven't, I haven't got all the details yet, but hopefully Ting's going to be providing
connectivity on GSM and CDMA networks for me along the trip.
So we'll see, but still it feels like an abuse of a privilege to update my, my arch boxes
while on the road.
Cause I'm going to have probably two of them, maybe three of them with me on the road.
And I don't know if I want to be doing package updates on three arch boxes because they're
all running GNOME.
Is that just...
McDonald's?
Yeah.
I would totally do it to McDonald's.
I could do that.
Nice.
All right.
So any other Wayland or a GNOME 3.18 thoughts before I move on anything I missed?
There's also other features that they're adding, but those are just ones that I don't think
are going to be in the release notes.
But I figure we'll all be talking about the ones that are in the release notes when it
comes out.
Yeah.
So, okay.
Going once, going twice.
All right.
Well then I will just, I'll just leave with a little mention that as, if you are curious
on the state of the, of the whole road trip and where that's going, as I get kind of ramped
up to it, I have posted a couple of videos up on our YouTube channel.
I think I mentioned this at the end of last, last week.
Or I guess this week.
Yeah.
I did.
Oh no, I actually, that's right.
I mentioned at the beginning of last.
Boy, I'm an old man.
Good.
So you probably already know about this, but if you don't, there is a road trip playlist.
I've only got two videos up there now.
I'm in progress of making the third.
And it's just updates because this is a whole new experience and there's a surprising connection.
There's a maker aspect to it because there's a lot of build and cut and drill and solve.
And there's an interesting technology aspect to it too.
And of course for me it's also, I'm using Linux in a lot of spots.
So it's really kind of been a fascinating kind of adventure so far and it's just starting.
So I've documented two of it so far and I'll have a third up probably the next day or so.
Connectivity is limited when I'm staying in the trailer, but I'll get it out eventually.
So you can find that at the Jupiter Broadcasting YouTube channel, youtube.com slash Jupiter
Broadcasting.
There is a trailer walkthrough in the second update.
It's a quick one.
There's a quick trailer walkthrough.
When it was empty, like I had not moved a single thing into it and I was parked out
in the road in front of the studio and I'm sitting there with my Patreon poll.
Don't ask.
I'm taking a video.
So you can find that.
It's just on the Jupiter Broadcasting channel.
And yeah.
All right.
Well that'll wrap us up.
So let's see.
So next week's Linux Unplugged.
I'll be here for the 15th and then I will be on the road for episode 111 and episode
112 for the ones recorded on the 22nd and the 29th.
We should be doing that the same regular time I think though.
So I think that all is if you listen live, oh, I could pre-warn you though.
The download might be slightly delayed because the intention is for me to have a local recording
on the road so that way my audio quality isn't that much worse when I'm doing the road show.
But to do that, the show will have to pass through another set of editing to combine
my remote audio track, Wes's local audio track and the Mumbles audio track and any computer
audio that we have.
So potentially four or five different tracks may have to be lined up by an editor and then
delivered for production into video as well.
So during the road trip there may be an eight hour delay or so on the release of the show.
So maybe instead of coming out Tuesday night it might come out Wednesday morning or Wednesday
midday or Wednesday afternoon, I'm not quite sure.
We don't know yet because we haven't tried it yet.
But just as a pre-warning for those of you that might notice that, I wanted to get you
a couple of weeks' heads up because if you're a little bit behind by the time you're catching
this, that'll be affecting you.
But hopefully it won't be a big deal and you just grab the RSS feed and you'll get them
when they come out.
Or be here live for all the fun.
That's right.
That is the fastest way to get it.
And there are clever solutions for recording the live stream too.
Yeah, I know people do that.
All right, well that'll wrap us up for this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We'd love to get your feedback.
You can go over to linuxactionshow.reddit.com and leave a note in the feedback thread there.
Or you can go to jupyterbroadcasting.com slash contact and where you'll find a contact form
for Linux Unplugs specifically.
And that's always nice because then I filter just on the Unplugged show and I get all of
that.
So that's a good way to send your thoughts into the show.
And don't forget we are live, like Wes just mentioned, over at jblive.tv.
We do the show at 2 p.m. Pacific.
You can get that converted to your local time at jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
Any topics you want to also suggest, that subreddit's also great, linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
Those are all the great places to get all the info.
And at Jupiter Signal, for any last minute changes during the road trip or things like
that, at Jupiter Signal is the network's news feed.
All right everybody, well thank you so much for your time.
Oh, wow, geez, hang up on me already, why don't you?
Thanks for tuning in.
We'll see you next week.
Bye.
Another suggestion for GPS tracking coming in right now.
Boy, this is, we're all about the GPS tracking right here on the Linux Unplugged program.
I tell you what, this is a serious endeavor because I want to make sure you guys know
where I'm at so that way you can tell me the cool places to get brews, food, or meet up
with me.
So this is worth the effort.
We got to spend a little time talking about this.
While we all go vote for titles, JBtitles.com, we've got to get into this.
This is kind of neat, so I could use this on the road trip somehow.
You can use an APS droid to connect to the APRS network via different means, either via
internet, Wi-Fi, or mobile data connection, audio connection between your radio and your
smartphone, wow, how about that, or a Bluetooth serial connection to a TNC.
Once connected, your beacon and presence see what stations are around and send and receive
APRS messages.
So this could be an APRS transmitter itself, it looks like.
Here, I'm going to put the QR code on the screen if you guys want to grab that.
I want to grab it too.
Where's my phone?
I want to get that.
Come on, Google, do I have a QR code reader?
Can you just tell Google to open a QR code reader?
Yes.
Okay, you think so?
Let's see.
Well, if you have one installed.
All right, let's see if it does it.
You ready, Wes?
Let's see.
Let's give it a chance.
Okay, Google, open the QR code reader.
Ah, I don't have one installed.
And I like, though, the link it brings up is the QR reader for iPhone on the App Store.
Mine brought up like a list of apps.
I hate you, Wes!
What did you say?
Oh, you got the same thing.
I just captured you, spy.
You captured the same exact audio, and you got App Store play results, and look what
I got.
Now, how the hell is that?
I don't know.
How did that happen?
It should be the same Google now, you would think.
Okay, Google, QR reader for Android.
And okay, look what it gave me there.
Yeah, I got the Kindle link, too.
That's unhelpful.
That's totally unhelpful.
Very hit or miss.
This is no good.
Anyways, I got to look into this app, because you know what, the Play Store should just
have a freaking QR code reader built into it.
It should, yes.
Why doesn't it do that?
QR code reader.
Didn't get it.
Hello?
QR code reader.
There we go.
Now I'm in like, okay, now I'm in like Flynn.
Oh, but there's so many to get, though.
This is the problem.
Oh, I know.
There's too many, there's so many lovely QR code readers.
All right, so, okay, has the chat, Chris last, non-vanilla camera apps have integrated
QR code readers.
Yeah, I know.
I got, okay, anybody know if I have to be a ham to use this app?
That's what I need to know right now, because this is happening.
This is happening.
According to a forum posted on the internet, it looks like you do.
But does it actually have to, oh man, okay, so it's a $5 app if you get it from the Play
Store.
To make use, you'll need an APRS passcode for your call sign.
Ah, there you go.
There you go.
Well, that kills that.
That kills that.
Does anybody else have something else that doesn't require to be a ham, to have a ham
license and have an APRS, IS passcode?
Because I don't think I'm doing that.
Man, you guys got me all excited.
All right, there's got to be a way to solve this, though, right?
Come on, Wes, you got something on there?
I know last week you were looking at the track car.
Yeah, what is that?
Remind me about the track car.
I should look at that.
Someone in Mumble Room linked something, a tutorial based on it, it looks like.
Really?
The track car.
Now, did I...
Yeah, I did, track car.
I did save this from last week.
Track car.
Track car is an open source UOS tracking system for GPS tracking devices.
It supports more than 80, but so is a client that allows you...
All right, you know what?
I'm desperate enough.
I'll give this a shot.
Let's give this a go.
XTWV in the IRC linked us to something.
Create your own vehicle fleet tracking management system which also links to track car.
That is blowing my face off.
All right, I'm putting this...
You know what I hate about Google Play is they list my Samsung Edge.
First of all, they use the OEMs like internal code names for your phones.
Oh, yes.
I hate that they do that.
Hammerhead or whatever.
Well, yeah, so if I click install here, like for my Edge, instead of saying the US...
Instead of saying Samsung Edge, it says US Samsung SMG925T.
Very helpful.
Yeah, and then it's not even the right picture of my phone.
It's a picture of a different model of my phone in a different color.
So it's just super lame.
Anyways, okay, so now I'm installing...
This is called track car, and it's available for Android.
Track car is a free open source server that supports more than 80 different protocols
and GPS tracking devices.
You can use the application with your own hosted instance of track car.
So that might be something I could do is I could put it up on a droplet.
Well, what do you think?
Should I give this a shot, Wes?
Yeah, I think so.
Sounds interesting.
I don't know if I feel like setting up my own server though, but I think I might try
it.
If the service setup isn't so bad, yeah, the app doesn't look so bad.
Yeah, okay, so I have to give it a server to connect to, and a port, and a frequency.
It's in the AUR.
Mixed provider, so I can do mixed providers, so I have a mixed source of...
It is an AUR, huh?
Yeah.
I think it runs on Java, so...
This is getting more and more likely actually.
I got to look into this.
I got to look into this because the only problem is I'm going to be...
I wonder what it does when I go to areas that don't have tracking.
We should check out this...
Maybe I call it private time.
...Osmend too, maybe.
Oh, Osmend, huh?
Just while we have it invested.
Yeah, let's take a look.
What's this here?
So this is coming from Mr. Odyssey Westray over there in Spokane.
So this is Osmend...
What is this thing here?
This looks neat.
An automated navigation directions and is a map and navigation application with access
to the free worldwide high quality OpenStreetMaps data.
Yeah.
Okay, this is for offline.
But I don't know if it does...
It doesn't look like it broadcasts my location though, right?
Yeah.
I think for track cars...
See with track car, I think the way it would work is I could have a page that people could
go to and actually watch my trip in real time.
Check in with Chris.
And they'd be like, hey, I want to meet up with you.
Okay, I really...
Now I'm talking about this, I'm really getting excited about this.
Okay, so here's a Gizmodo article that talks about different options.
The Motorola i290 nationwide walkie-talkie, wireless web, GPS enabled, hands free...
What's this?
Get a phone.
What is this?
Instamapper.
Have you heard of Instamapper, Wes?
I have not.
Instamapper.
You can install it over the air.
It's easy to use.
Accu tracking is another one.
Oh, Instamapper.
Connection refused.
What?
Lame.
Yeah, totes lame.
Totes lame.
I wonder if I have to use Internet Explorer.
I'll try their HTTP.
Yeah, Instamapper was a popular GPS tracking location service after nearly five years of
operation.
It shut down in 2012.
Womp, womp.
Wow, how old is this article?
This article is...
Oh, my gosh.
You guys, chat room, look at the gear they recommended you use in this.
What is that?
That's like a Motorola feature phone from 2002.
Guys, how old is this article?
Chat room.
Ooh, check in with Chris.com.
I love it.
Check in with Chris.com.
Is that available?
Somebody grab that for me.
Jeez.
Let's see here.
High quality, low cost GPS tracking with AccuTracking.
Track GPS trackers or cell phones.
Real time location, history reports, emails, text, and alerts.
AccuTracking.
This might be it.
They have starter kits, a pre-configured tracker for you.
What's the price like?
I don't know.
I'm going to go look on their Amazon page, but here's what I don't want.
This looks like it's for private tracking, you know, to track like a fleet of businesses.
Right.
Whereas you want something that you can easily share.
Yeah.
Oh, that's neat, though.
Here's what I love about this.
I've seen this.
Verizon has this, too.
This is so cool.
This tracker, look at that, Wes.
This tracker plugs into...
Ooh, industrial.
It plugs into your ODB2 port, your diagnostic port, gets power from that, has a SIM card
in it and a GPS in it, and it can also do a mic.
Oh, dang.
Wow.
It's free to go, no contract, no activation fee, so it's 77 bucks for this off of Amazon.
Prepaid SIM card is included.
What?
Ooh.
And what is this?
Real-time 24-7 GPS tracking, vehicle diagnostic data included.
Oh, my God, that's cool.
That's actually pretty handy.
Geofence speed, ignition, AC unplugged, SOS panic, check engine light on.
That's neat.
With the DTC code.
Detailed tracking reports.
You'll never be able to hide from Andrew, I guess.
Excellent reception with built-in GSM and GPS antenna.
So here's the thing, though, is I still don't think it's doing public maps.
Right.
Would you have to give people your login to their service to be able to see it or whatever?
Yeah, that seems like a deal-breaker to me.
That seems like...
That's no good.
So I'm gonna stick with the track car and see how that goes.
I'm a little concerned about that.
We will see.
I'm a little concerned.