Wes, you probably catch XKCD from time to time, but I thought this was hilarious.
They have posted the perfect phone, the XKCD Phone 4.
And there's a couple of things that I think are just, I don't know why they're just obvious.
First of all, it has a built-in dog whistle.
Yeah.
It has exposed duck work on the sign that is software defined.
It has a new bright glow display that incorporates genetically spliced together jellyfish protein.
It integrates Siri, Cortana, Google Now, and Alexa all at once.
They all respond simultaneously.
Yes.
Oh, that's great.
And of course, it also has a parallel port on the bottom and 12, count them, 12 headphone
jacks.
Now, that's your phone.
How often have you been with your 11 best friends and you want to listen to exactly
the same thing?
Exactly.
Or maybe Linux Unplugged.
Right?
Yep.
Boom.
There's your upgrade, Wes.
Just bring it to your local Lug.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 162 for September 13th, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's going back to school.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
How's the install going over there?
Oh, it's wonderful.
I'm up and doing the show.
Nice.
Well, we got a big show for you today.
So buckle up, Wes.
Buckle up.
Coming up on this week's episode of the Unplugged show, we're going to go through some breaking
news just as a sort of a community heads up.
We're going to talk about a drone that also doubles as an Ubuntu desktop PC.
Apparently also, speaking of Ubuntu, they're getting attacked for being copyright pirates
or something like that.
I'll tell you about it coming up in the show next.
Nextcloud's got a surprise in store.
We've got some really interesting open source projects we want to highlight, some updates
to cover, some digging around on getting rid of that Intel spyware, a.k.a. the management
firmware.
Oh, strong words from Chris over here.
I know.
Plus, I had to fix a key ring bork this week.
I'll tell you about my key ring bork.
We also have jets flying overhead right now as we record the show.
To do great honor to Linux Unplugged.
Sending your USB devices over the network, a follow up on making Linux look a little
better.
We're going to talk about it in the context of the Loki review.
You hear that?
You hear that thing?
Wow.
That's for the show.
So we'll talk about the state of Linux desktop customization and then we have a very important
email to get to.
We have a couple of good feedback items.
We're going to do something we haven't done for a while.
We're going to reach into my mail sack and we're going to read some really great emails.
Yes.
Some stuff that people have probably been wondering.
So we've got all of that coming up in today's show.
But you know what else we've got, Wes?
We've got a totally locked and loaded Mumble Room.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello guys, boy, it's great to hear all of you in there and welcome back to Popey's.
Been a long time since I've heard Popey's charming voice.
It's good to have you here.
You smell good, Chris.
Thank you.
It's handsome even over Mumble.
I know you do, Popey.
I don't even have to smell you to know.
I know.
You know what?
He truly is.
So guys, let's just sort of just as a sort of a public service announcement because there's
a lot of things we could we could start today's episode off with, but we should probably start
with some legitimately breaking news.
So there is a zero day vulnerability right now that could lead to total system compromise
for MySQL.
It came out yesterday, so it's still pretty new.
And I just wanted to put the word out there for any of you out there.
It affects, this is directly from the CVE, the vulnerability affects all MySQL servers
in the default configuration in all version branches being 5.7, 5.6, and 5.5, including
the latest versions, and could be exploited both by local and remote attackers.
That was an advisory that was published yesterday afternoon.
Both the unauthenticated and authenticated access to MySQL databases are an issue.
So a sequel, and it's a sequel injection apparently, but I don't know the details.
It's CVE, if you want to look it up, it's CVE 2016 6662.
Well said.
If that's not a sign, I don't know what is.
Anyways, so just a heads up to those of you out there that may have MySQL installed, but
I actually thought this would be a really fun story to start with.
I love this so much.
This makes it feel like we're in Marty McFly's future right now.
I might not be able to have the video wall that he had that was super cool, or the dehydrated
pizza refresher thing, which was amazing.
We could be eating pizza right now.
But I bet Marty didn't have a drone that also doubles as an Ubuntu PC.
I bet Marty didn't have that.
No he did not.
Because we've got that.
We have that.
Or we could.
Well, that's true.
It's a development kit from Parrot, I think.
Or is that how you say it?
I think so.
Okay.
I just want to make sure I'm not making fun of him.
It's designed to create drones that can avoid obstacles, like the new DJI Phantom 4 that's
super fancy, which is, I got to tell you, somebody who's tried doing, well, we've crashed
our drone before.
Let's just put it that way.
It was awful.
The development kit itself doesn't have wings, and it needs to be attached to a drone and
a flight controller.
Otherwise, the kit can be used to create robots.
It's called Slam Dunk, and it's a fisheye camera that can capture 1500 by 1500 pixel
resolution images at 60 frames per second.
The camera allows the drone to process the images, which it will then be able to identify
obstacles, which is very nice, because then it can use that identification to avoid those
obstacles.
It also has an ultrasound sensor, a magnetrometer, and, just for Wes, a barometer.
They say it doesn't need GPS to operate.
The development kit has an HDMI port, as well as ports for keyboard and mice, which means
you can build a PC out of it.
There's no price yet.
We're going to probably get something in the fourth quarter, but just, you know, what do
we always hear about what makes Ubuntu work so great on the cloud?
What makes Ubuntu work so great on the cloud, Wes?
I think it's the built-in drone support.
No, I don't.
Maybe not yet.
I think what you often hear is, I can build in my local environment and have it run just
like it builds.
Dev matches production.
Yes.
So, this is the ultimate version of that, because you can make this little kit.
You could hook it up, a keyboard and a monitor and a mouse, and develop directly on it, and
strap it onto a drone or a robot, and this is the true 100% dev matches production kind
of scenario here.
Or when your friends come over and you need an extra computer, you just sit them down
by your drone.
It has to charge anyway, right?
When you have a full Ubuntu machine up in the sky, what are the possibilities?
With a camera on it that has a 1500x1500 resolution at 60 frames per second, it runs Ubuntu 14.04,
so it's going to feel a little old.
A little old.
I'm just teasing.
It's a drone.
I want to see, like the diagram in the blog post shows a keyboard and mouse and a screen.
I want to see someone running after the drone with a keyboard and mouse and a screen trying
to use it.
Oh my God, yes.
Or like a really long USB cable.
I think it's a super neat example too of how Ubuntu can be used on a range of devices that
are actually approachable by consumers, so somebody who really had an inspiration could
go out and get this stuff, eventually at least, in the fourth quarter it looks like.
That is neat.
And it's the first time where the in the clouds is legitimate.
Oh no, that's good too.
I hadn't thought of that.
You guys are on top of it today.
Okay, so while we're talking about Ubuntu, let's talk about this.
The Ubuntu torrent was removed from Google using the infringing DMCA takedown.
It's a horrible process where big companies outsource to these third party contracting
firms who go out and do these massive sweeps of the net and then they submit these huge
DMCA takedown requests.
Or perhaps Hollywood is, hold on a second, full stop.
Perhaps Hollywood is telling us something.
Maybe the robots are on Ubuntu.
So Ubuntu 12.04 LTS torrent was taken down because apparently, according to Hollywood,
it infringed on Transformers Age of Extinction.
That was the Ubuntu release that came with Transformers Age of Extinction, right?
Just pre-installed.
Yes.
Starts right on startup.
Yeah.
That's an example.
Content.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, and I just, this, boy, if this isn't just such a great example, taking down open
source software like this, what a broken system is this.
This could be worse.
There's an even better example of why this is broken.
Last week, Warner Brothers ordered Google to remove several sites from its own websites
because they infringed their own copyright.
They had the Batman Dark Knight and Matrix stuff yanked out of Google search results
for their own sites.
Boy, I don't mean to take this down a notch.
Take down your own stuff.
What happens when this, what happens when they start taking down other legitimate stuff
accidentally?
Right.
Where does this stop at?
Well, Google aren't going to put any real effort into checking this because they get
millions of these things a day, so how, you know, nobody can be-
It'd be nice if they could charge a fee.
If you want to take something down, you have to pay X amount so they can't just generate
a bunch of bogus requests.
Moe's and Rath, you have an idea of where it stops.
Yeah, when you sit there and you think about it, what happens when they take down someone
else's stuff, then lawyers show up.
Remember how you were discussing lawyers?
I don't know which show that it was, but it was in the past couple of weeks.
The lawyers will have a field day if Warner Brothers accidentally manages to take down
something by say, Fox or something by just some other company, any other company.
Let's just say it was something that involved say Microsoft, for example.
Microsoft would say, oh, you decided to impinge upon our ability to make money through legitimate
means.
Well, we have a few people that would like to talk to you.
Snap, snap, the shark lawyers show up.
Sure.
Yeah, so basically once they start picking on somebody their own size.
Yeah, well, mm-hmm.
Well, it's not a matter of picking on because remember, as you're saying, this is pretty
much a blanket sweep, right?
So it's not a matter of picking on.
It's more like, because I have size 13 feet, so I got to be careful where I step sometimes
because if there's little kids around, I could end up stepping on their foot, their feet.
Now what happens to someone with size 13 feet, someone else's feet who also has size 13 feet,
but they're hostile?
That's an interesting analogy.
And you just came up with that on the fly.
Yeah.
That was damn good, sir.
What size are your feet?
Yeah, maybe he's probably got big feet.
He's thinking about that.
Yeah, that is a good way to put it.
That is a really good way to put it.
And it's just as shameful right now.
And I think I'm extra sensitive to it because I almost on a daily basis, I fight this problem
on the YouTube side of things, which is also a Google platform.
And I am assumed guilty.
Exactly that.
It puts the onus on the content creator who's just trying to do their thing or the people
who are just trying to distribute legitimate ISOs.
And now it's gotten even worse from a monetization.
The only nice thing about YouTube from a content creator standpoint is it's got a great user
base and sometimes you can make some ad revenue.
Now for the kind of stuff that kind of views we get on YouTube, nobody goes to YouTube
to watch long form content, except for the awesome people that watch our long form content.
Because there is definitely an audience for it, but it's not as huge as everybody that's
on YouTube to watch 15 minute, five minute, and 10 minute videos.
They see that it's like, oh, an hour and 20 minutes.
So it's never been like a huge platform for us.
We don't make very much money on there at all.
And it's almost, it barely even makes enough for them to actually even pay us.
But they've started demonetizing videos simply for covering current events.
And this happens to one of our shows on the JBL network on a routine basis all the time.
But it's also even been retroactively happening to shows called Stoked, I used to do a Star
Trek online podcast years ago.
It's recently beginning to demonetize for covering current events.
So they are, in some senses, they can do everything from revoke JB videos from certain audiences
in the world, completely revoke it, or just not allow it to be funded.
There's so much control.
And never do they start with, well, let's get the creator's perspective.
Let's get the content creator's perspective.
Just like this Google takedown.
I mean, when you get removed from Google, you're essentially gone.
Just disappeared from the internet.
But so far, it's just made for a few good examples.
So now let's talk about something that's outside of Ubuntu.
I'm going to use the word Unity, but I don't want you to get confused.
It's not the Unity desktop.
It's the Unity gaming engine.
And it looks like the Unity gaming engine is getting some proper Vulkan work done right
now.
Nice.
So this was posted by a software developer over at Unity Technologies.
And she shows here an example of a demo, a Unity demo, running under Vulkan on Ubuntu.
Pretty cool.
Pretty nice.
And not that I'm some huge fan of Unity games, but what this will mean is more games for
Linux.
This is going to get a lot more games for Linux.
And that is a big deal.
So it's not really news anywhere yet.
I just happened to catch this on Twitter today.
I was just trolling.
It's a cool looking screencap there, too.
Yeah, that's one of the demos that, yeah, that's, yeah.
I also like that hashtag Linux.
It kind of looks like a corridor of a modern retrofit Millennium Falcon.
Like if the Millennium Falcon got a facelift and they went in and cleaned it up a bit,
it would look like that with big balls rolling around.
I don't know what that's about.
But I thought that was pretty cool.
Actually, speaking of trolling around on Twitter, I found this on there, too, from NyxCraft.
ButterFS status in Linux kernel 4.7.
And this is kind of an interesting breakdown.
And by the way, NyxCraft adds the world is already moving on to ZFS.
So a couple of things that are still not working properly in ButterFS as of kernel 4.7.
I thought I would just mention them here.
Not to ding it, but just so you know.
They list defrag as mostly working okay, but extents currently get unshared.
Compression is mostly okay.
Auto repair and compression itself may crash from time to time.
Scrub and RAID 5.6 are considered unstable.
RAID 5.6 write holes still exist also, and parity is not being checksummed.
And the free space treat is considered unstable.
So if you're on a little Indian machine, you're okay.
But if you're on anything but an x86 machine, apparently ButterFS can't calculate free space
for shit.
I think that's the version 2 free space tree that you have to enable by an option.
So these are things that are considered totally unstable.
Then they have things like device replace, balance, quotas and queue groups, out of band
dedupe, and file range cloning that are all TBD.
William, what do you think of that stuff?
Anything else that jumped out at you about the current state of ButterFS?
I mean, RAID 5.6 is broken.
What a surprise.
Yeah.
It's like, we've kind of known that for a long time, that it wasn't in a great state
and it never really has been fixed stability-wise.
And I think that right there, your sentiment, is my point.
I feel like as a community, enough of us have come to a, like, ah, this is never gonna,
this is just not gonna work.
Like I, I feel a little bit like-
Yeah, so Sheep has been dumping countless hours into it, like they've definitely been
submitting patches, but it's not really getting anywhere.
I do feel like the window of acceptance, or I guess I should say the court of public opinion,
may have come to its verdict.
And that could change, but it doesn't have the same kind of, like, momentum or excitement
or general, like, trust or anything that we'd like to see.
I also don't see RAID 5.6 being as relevant today as they were 10 years ago, either.
No, I mean, and I still use it, right?
Most people are running RAID 1 and RAID 10 now.
Well, I still use it myself.
I still use it myself.
It's still relevant for me.
So how, why do you say that?
Hold on, I don't hear you.
Well, William, what else do you think people are using instead?
Oh, he must be-
Sorry, my mixer is flaky with the mute button sometimes.
It's all right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So what I was thinking is disks take so long to recover now, your large, like, four to
eight terabyte disks, because the read speeds haven't, and write speeds haven't gone up
enough to counteract how much space you're adding, how much capacity you're adding.
So overall, you're re-silvering or you're rebuilding times are taking much, much longer
than they used to.
True.
And so it's not as useful to use RAID 5 and 6 when you could rebuild much faster in a
mirrored configuration.
Yep, yep.
And with less potential for data loss.
Yeah.
That's interesting.
I do use mirrors a lot.
And also storage is kind of cheap.
So-
Yeah, and then stripes and mirrors.
It's not that big a deal to go 2X.
You know, 2X is not a big deal.
Yeah, you're losing some, but it's worth it for the speed of everything.
All right.
I think you probably, I think, you know, I think you're dead on on that.
And I think, I think I will admit part of the reason I would, I would, the configurations
in which I would still use RAID 5 or 6, I guess, would be not a lot of disks.
And I specifically want something that's kind of a straightforward setup.
And I, and I, and I, I'm thinking of like a, like a, maybe an editing, I mean, I don't
even know anymore, but maybe an editing system with a few terabyte drives into that are super
fast.
But even there, I tend to do actually just a, just like a RAID 0 type setup.
Yeah.
So instead of like, how much do you care about what are your priorities?
So I have a feeling there may be a surprise in the air.
There may be something we could be talking about next week or whenever.
I actually don't know.
I don't know when, but it's, if I was going to make a red book prediction, I'm going to
say the next cloud project has something of their sleeve, which is going to take the project
to the next level.
What?
Now they're kicking off a next cloud conference and they've just put up a blog post about
it.
There are a couple of headline speakers there.
One of them is the CEO of Canonical, Jane, is it Silber?
Is that how you say it?
Yep.
It's Silber.
And then also Karen Sandler, the executive director of the Software Freedom Conservancy
will be giving some keynotes and they're going to have lightning talks and they're going
to have hacking sessions where they encourage people to bring hardware and there's going
to be a bit of a surprise.
That's exciting.
A bit of a surprise, a bit of a surprise that I can't tell you right now, but I will be
able to tell you soon.
Come on, Chris.
Tell us, tell us.
So if anybody gets a chance to go, let us know.
Look at them having a conference.
Yeah, I think that's cool.
It kind of like gives them, you know, it defines them a little bit more as their own thing.
I definitely want to give room to continue to listen to the own cloud version of events
and just sort of break all this stuff down, but in terms of just tactical execution here,
the next cloud project is lapping own cloud.
Like the own cloud project or whatever, the own cloud company has stumbled to properly
and fully respond to the entire series of events.
When they finally did, it was through sort of indirect means and blog posts through quote
unquote bloggers.
And just all of this, and then all of this sort of has been rather, they've been rather
quiet.
They haven't really been executing.
They haven't been executing on promotions as well and now this, there's a conference
happening for next cloud, like there seems to be a lot of momentum there.
It feels like it's, it feels more like a community.
It feels more like there's like, there is life there.
There's people excited about it.
Like if it's just some quiet company that, if no one's talking about it, then why would
we talk about it?
And whereas with own cloud, I feel that there is sort of, it has the life support feeling
right now.
And the only thing that, and then part of me is just like, well, I know I need to, I
know I need, I need to keep in mind there's two versions of events.
There's always two sides to a story and we haven't fully heard their side.
We've begun to hear, but we haven't fully heard.
I keep keeping that in mind and the same time these guys are generating buzz right now.
Exactly.
But we don't want to rule it out.
They might continue to be very good and they might do some exciting things that we want,
that we're excited about, but you just don't know.
Maybe Oracle should buy them and then kill them.
Oh yeah.
Why?
And then we would know what to do.
We've established this whole path for software to die.
No.
Oracle buys you.
Then the path would be clear, right?
They can buy them.
We can have the second open office and LibreOffice and go forward to LibreOffice.
Eventually they shut to Apache and then it withers.
Their next cloud in this case.
Yeah, exactly.
Oh man.
I think that was the worst idea in the show yet.
Donated.
Hmm.
I think they donated it straight to Apache and then you know it's dead.
Well, I've been using own cloud for a long, long time.
In fact, I still have a droplet with it running on there.
I don't actively use it, but I can still connect to it and check it out and all that stuff.
So I'm keeping one toe in the water.
So that's, I think, but I'm also feeling the next cloud pull.
Anybody in the mob room running the next cloud installation at the moment with some regular
use?
Yep.
I have it as a snap on a Raspberry Pi.
And what are your thoughts so far?
I like it.
It just kind of sits there and runs.
I don't really do an awful lot with it.
It's not like active because I don't have a huge amount of storage attached to my Pi.
Yeah.
But I've just been playing with it.
Huh.
I should do something like that.
A Pi actually would be a good machine just to kind of, and I could, you know, I'd like
to use it for calendaring.
I did have a period of time.
My own cloud peak, my peak own cloud was, I got all really anti-Google for a while.
Exactly.
And I seriously was getting creeped out by the tracking.
And I went and got an iOS device.
And I prototyped this, I remember I started this, I got like an iPhone 5 or something
for free from Ting.
And they just sent it to me so I could try this.
And I set up everything to use, my calendar, my contacts, everything was pointed to my
own cloud server.
Right.
And I had a, and I didn't use Google search, I had a 100% Google free iOS devices a little
while ago now.
Yeah.
And own cloud, it reached that point where it was, I was totally unaware I was even using
own cloud.
I didn't, there was.
It was just a backend.
Yeah.
I just had, and I had it syncing with my desktop, my gnome desktop, so I had calendar events
on my phone.
That is nice.
Yeah.
And once was I ever having to manage the own cloud server, I just got everything set up
once and it worked.
And it was a pretty cool experience because I didn't use Apple services and I didn't use
Google services.
Yep.
So if I ever get around to getting that Ubuntu phone going, I might set something up just
like that up.
Oh yeah, that's a great idea.
Yeah.
But it would be nice, it does seem to work really well for that kind of stuff.
It's just when you're using it for that and then the urge to use it also for your syncing.
Maybe if it had better support for like, you know, just being strapped on top kind of as
a layer.
Yeah.
I would use it more.
Wimby, are you still playing around with a Libre Vault?
I am.
And?
And how is it going so far?
Well, I haven't done anything significantly different from when we last spoke, but it's
still working.
That's good.
Although Mark from Ubuntu podcast contacted me over the weekend because he was doing some
testing and he ran into some issues actually getting the thing to run and there was a couple
of bugs introduced in a recent update.
So but you know, file issues on GitHub and the developers very responsive.
So that was about to ask.
That's kind of a good test right there.
Yeah.
So I'm going to pick up with that.
I've had a pause on that because I've been busy with other stuff.
I'm going to pick up on that next week and put it through its paces a bit more and hopefully
look to move something important over to it.
My challenge is I've got about four terabytes of data in total that I'll be syncing using
whatever I end up using.
Wow.
And one of the things I definitely noticed with it was a major issue with BitTorrent
Sync is because that data set is so large, it was essentially constantly just working
to recalculate the hash on the files, re-index, and by the time it got...
Maintaining state.
Yeah.
Just churning.
So I had to have a...
I had a dedicated machine.
Still do actually.
I still do actually.
I have a dedicated machine.
It's a VM, but it's a dedicated machine with allocated resources just dedicated to that
task.
And so I don't know how LibreVault's going to handle that, but that'll be one of the
things.
And that's the unfiltered show notes are just huge.
It's just a huge, huge set of data.
And I don't...
I haven't even released all of it.
You should be like the testing bed for syncing solutions.
I will be.
It's unfortunate you can't use sync thing because they have an inotify solution which
would reduce the polling of the files.
Well, I don't know how LibreVault does it.
So then maybe they're using Ionotify too.
I think they do.
Yeah, they could use inotify.
I would hope if they're Linux focused.
Yeah.
There's the wrapper.
What's the lib something?
Oh, really?
Well, that does KQ and other stuff too.
Yeah.
It is...
If I have a dedicated machine, it's manageable and I just have it off on a set of disks, but
that may be changing in the future.
So I will be revisiting that.
Either way, you know what?
I will have it all running through a DigitalOcean droplet.
That's how I do my cloud component to this.
This is when I ran own cloud and if I try out next cloud, this is what I'll be doing.
And when I do a LibreVault deployment...
I've had a syncing on DigitalOcean for like, I don't know, two years now.
It's just always there.
It just sits there.
It's always on.
It's great.
You know where the light went off for me?
So DigitalOcean, you can get a droplet for $5 a month to do this.
This is a $5 droplet.
Especially if you're not transferring tons of stuff all the time.
You just need it to kind of sit there and when you need it, it's there.
And if you use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED, you get a $10 credit.
So the light went off for me when I decided it was time to do a couple of regional servers
to help people that are downloading our own filter files just get it a little bit faster.
So I sort of kick it off by seeding in their location and then other folks, other audience
member in those areas pick it up.
And of course, using BitTorrent Sync now, currently, it sort of becomes its own CDN.
And so my transfer isn't that crazy because everybody that's part of the swarm is also
transferring the files, but yet I'm able to serve them up at local speeds at $5 a month.
That is awesome.
It is great.
It is so great.
And you know, as I switch over to LibreVault, which I suspect I will, I'll just essentially
implement the same exact setup.
And you know, they have templates which makes us super nice.
They also have snapshots, which is great before you make a big transition like I'll be making.
And they have an API that allows me to automate like the rebooting and the managing of these
systems really easily.
And I can just use apps that have already been created by the open source community.
So check them out at digitalocean.com and use our promo code DOUNPLUG.
They're all SSD-based storage.
They have block storage you can attach as you need it.
So as the unfilter storage grows now, I can add that, which makes being able to seed it
with all of the content, the entire back catalog now much more possible, which is going to
be super nice.
And something else that they are sort of drawing everyone's attention to is high memory droplet
pricing.
It's easy for me to say.
It's high memory droplet plans that offer large amounts of RAM, which is super, super
cool.
That's really handy.
I mean, I'm talking like when I say large amounts of RAM, I'm talking like 128 gigabytes
of RAM or, holy crap, 224 gigabytes of RAM.
Damn.
That is nuts.
DigitalOcean, and then combine that with the SSD-backed block storage.
And you know, they're using Linux for all of these systems.
KVM for the virtualizer, I couldn't say more.
DigitalOcean.com, just use our promo code DOUNPLUG.
You apply that to your account, you get a $10 credit, and you just supported the unplugged
program.
Keep us going.
Ok, bomb DOUNPLUG, and I wouldn't mind trying out one of those 256 gig droplets.
I know, yeah.
Just for a little while, you know, just an hour or two play with it.
Geez, Louise.
You know, I wonder, so what were you talking to me about before the pre-show, what you
were talking about with the persistent RAM state, would that work on a virtual machine?
It's a good question, it might.
Yeah.
Do you want to recap what it was?
I was just talking about the kernel's persistent memory support for having like a block device in persistent memory
So apparently I had no idea
This is a module that's been available for a while that allows you to convert part of a space of memory of RAM
Yeah
So it's in storage and so it's meant for like for dealing with persisting like is this sort of the back-end technology that RAM dis
Used to create a RAM disk or is this beyond that is it similar, but this is developed developed
In theory to support like non-volatile RAM. Oh, so if you have like that bank
I don't have that but for development purposes as well as other purposes. You can mark any segment of RAM
Basically, you say like leave this unassigned and then the kernel can make a block device out of it. Okay
And that actually the store that caught wood, but the content you store there
Persists after a reboot not not like a full reboot
Not if you like actually turn the system off
But if you keep the system running and for instance K exec
Yes
Because if as long as you don't as long as you don't wipe that memory and then you boot the new kernel
Also treating those memory regions as a block device then BAM. That's cool
Yeah, so you can just have a whole system running and RAM reboot right back into it. Good. Oh
That'd be fun. So what were you using that for?
Not really anything specific. We're just playing with it
But in theory, you know
You can there's a lot of just like speed up use cases or maybe you just want to have a system who you know
All your date you use your disk just for data and then you bootstrap into that kind of environment off like a pixie boot server or something
for your root file system
This is this is officially our geeky segment
So I'm gonna play off that and I was just talking about KVM
Which I think is the world's best virtualizer and is that even the right term? Should I hypervisor?
Is that what I should be saying? Yeah, it is but this is called kimchi
It's an HTML management interface for the SOB. So you course probably are familiar with boxes
Mm-hmm. Very nice gooey to manage
KVM or whatever but kimchi is an HTML based management tool for KVM
It's designed to make it easy and possible to get started and look at these look at these screenshots
Here's the login here and here's where they've got several virtual machines running. Oh, I like those icons
Yeah, they match they recognize distros automatically and the virtual machines get the distro icon next to it, which is
Very nice. Honestly, this is so nice. I probably should have kept it
It's a secret and then done it as like a like a big segment on Linux action show
They should it has a web interface
It'll show you a list of running guests including live screenshots of the guest session you can use action buttons to shut down the guests
Or you know, you can connect to the display of the guest in the browser. I was about to ask
Mm-hmm. I think this is probably the way I'm gonna oh
Boy, oh boy, I just got an idea. Oh boy. Oh boy. I see I was thinking I was oh boy
I was thinking I was gonna use Proxmox in lady jupes. So one, you know, Wes
I'm working on setting up a Linux based network in the RV. Yes, and I
Was thinking I only want one computer. So you're gonna have like a virtualized all-in-one. I was thinking Proxmox
It's worked super solid here
It has been a total work champ and we've got machines have been running
Literally since day one that we put when we moved in as one of the first things we stood up were these machines
That's and they're still running today. It's been bulletproof. So I was thinking well, I should just set up Proxmox
But honestly with kimchi, I I probably a lot, you know
It's a lot easier to just bolt on I would I think I would rather do this with like a
Base server install and then load kimchi to manage it because the thing is gonna the other thing about it
It's gonna be under a cow. It's gonna be under a bench sealed up
I there won't be a monitor I can get to or anything like that
So this is this could be this this could be the virtualization solution. This might be my Proxmox replacement
I was recommending Proxmox to a friend, but he was kind of running into things that he was already kind of
You know the server he was had in mind. He's gonna already set it up
He was already using Ubuntu on it and he didn't really feel like, you know
He didn't want to wipe and reinstall and that guy so like he might just be able to bolt right on and bam
All right. There you go. Okay
And it could be perfect for me this because I would much rather just have like a base
1604 server install or something like that and then install this on top of it
Proxmox is fantastic
But it still is a little too free-nazzy for me in the sense that it's too much of us
Pre-built setup that I'm especially if you're only going for one device, right?
So if it's your office and you just stick it in the corner, that's fine
Yes, when you have the device that like in six months, you might need it to do a whole new function
Yeah, Proxmox doesn't support. Yeah here
We have a dedicated Proxmox machine and it runs in the garage 24-7
And that is the only thing it does and I just cannot do that in an RV
so this is gonna be the I I can I cannot wait to play with it. It's called kimchi and
We will have a link in the show notes to the github page. So while we're in the geeky category
I wanted to talk about the management firmware that comes with the pretty much most Intel machines for years now, right?
I mean, I think it's been in there since the core series perhaps
I don't know when it was added, but it's certainly been here
Yeah for the but like all things that are in bundled with the Intel stuff. They iterated on every single release
constantly adding features and it is it is some people call it like the
Sort of the spyware Intel spyware that is its proprietary. There's no we have no idea what it does
It's called the management management firmware. Is that what it's called an engine management engine? Thank you
Thank you, and it does all kinds of crazy things like apparently it uses your network connection to go out and synchronize with NTP servers
Yeah, if you run Windows, it supports functions like syncing your Wi-Fi network passwords to the firmware chip itself
And of course no source code is available for this although and the core boot project
Has been has been keen on replacing this or getting rid of it and there's been some experiments by I'm gonna say Tramel trammell
Tramel, yeah, maybe Tramel. I apologize. I'm sorry. I'm so horrible with names
Yeah, come join us and then correct us. That would be cheese. That would be great
But we could just have a name person on here
I'd be all about that, but you are familiar with his work if you're not familiar with his name
He is the one that created the magic lantern firmware. He reverse engineered the firmware on the Canon 5d mark 2 Wow
Yeah, that is really cool. Yeah, he's also he's also the guy behind thunder strike
which is a proof-of-concept EFI firmware root root kit for Apple's MacBooks that uses a
Thunderbolt and
We've covered it extensively on tech snap
I he is so he you were probably you're probably familiar with some of his work
even if you're not familiar with the name like I wasn't and
He's been poking around at trying to get
the trying to get around or disable this management engine and
He says I'm experimenting with what happens if I remove the management engine firmware from the lower
SPI flash chip on a ThinkPad x2 30
I just erased the first four kilobytes of its region take that and then core boot boots up fine and reports that this has a
Bad firmware the management is a bad firmware, but it continues on and Linux actually
initializes without any complaints
And then he went to try to remove the entire region of memory and of course it immediately wouldn't boot at all
But he's so he's beginning to experiment with where what he can poke at and what he can damage in the management engine
I like that to make it unusable, but still to make Linux bootable right which is kind of a great idea
Yeah, right what an interesting approach is we're cracking the
Destroy the damn thing x2 30. What's that? Which version of the ThinkPad? Did he say?
Yeah, it's the x2 30 ThinkPad x2 30
So I wonder if he can still do that with later models because I've heard they are locking down the management engine more and more
And relying on it. Yeah, there's some discussion about that in the thread
I believe so I'm kind of curious if the x2 30 isn't the best representative model for this no interesting
I didn't know that and you know I mean in some ways that might be true for actual production solutions
But in other ways that it allows him to poke at this and actually be able to see
What kind of results and proceed so in some ways?
Maybe it's good, but in other ways it means it's not applicable to
Some people they're getting newer ThinkPads. Yeah, that's a good
That's good to know in the in the good-to-know column. Have you have you ever have you ever had to enter in like your keyring?
Password on the gnome desktop sure yeah, yeah, maybe I think this probably apply to unity as well or Ubuntu matei
I'm not sure I mean yeah, I don't know actually maybe I could add wimpy
So the gnome key ring is that that's a that is a?
That on the matei desktop. Yep, okay, so I had a I had a I had a very privileged thing happened to me
It is one of the best things it's ever happened in my life is I had other people build a computer for me
What I had to pay for the components for my own Bitcoin, but I had your own treasure. I had other people assemble them for me
Mainly the beard and and Noah and he created we created a we covered the machines
We said this is way. This is months and months and months and months ago, and
He he even installed Anna gross for me. He set up Noah. He set up Anna gross for me
He set up real nice installed a few apps for me
And set the password to something generic and said all right have at it. See you later
And I said thanks sat down started using it and I opened up Chrome
And I got a key ring prompt for the password I typed in my password that you'd said and nothing happened wrong password I
Typed in other variations of generic passwords. I know Noah's used from various studio
Nothing happened
It was at that point. I realized I
I don't know my key ring password. Ah screw it. I don't care won't be a problem right well turns out
I tried I saw I began setting up in Elias and one okay
Yeah, I'm I said in LA is nihilus nihilus and one the mail client trying to set up my own server get all that stood and
standing interesting and and
one specifically relies on the gnome key ring to store your credentials are very like for Google and
So because I could not unlock my unlock my key ring. I couldn't you couldn't you set up and one
And so then I so then I had to set off on a mission
I was on a mission now yep to be able to solve this problem
I didn't know what I could do because I didn't know what the password was and the only way to change the password obviously is
To provide the previous password can't do that
And I don't want to reload because the machines freaking perfect except for this one thing yes
So I eat the key ring, so here's what I did
And there's probably there's probably a few ways to crack this nut so please leave a comment and let me know
but what I did is I installed seahorse and
Then I went into seahorse, and I selected the key ring that was there and I deleted it
Which means it deleted anything that had in there?
And they were prompts you for a few times, and then I went to the file menu new created a new key ring
Set in a password that I knew and then this is the key part you have to do
After you create the new key ring you have to right-click on the new key ring and say set as default
And and then go reconfigure the applications that we're trying to store their key ring credentials
So I then went and reset and reset up and one and then it prompted and actually because I already had my key ring unlocked everything
Just worked just worked right so I have links in the show notes
But seahorse was the key ring manager that I decided to use and I have I have a brief description in the show notes if you
Ever run into this about seahorse. Yeah, it worked well. Yeah, and you know you know why I was trying out and one is
Oh, this is not really related to seahorse, but and one has totally kick-ass key base
Io and it really does yeah, oh have you played with it, too?
Yeah, yeah, you should follow me
And I should follow you on key base and all that s because I'm Chris LAS on key based on IO beautiful and that I
Have been getting some emails this week that people been using my and I needed a I needed a solid way
Oh, they support it very nice. I was actually quite impressed with that
Yeah, so the so did you go for the pro? Did you stand on server? Yeah? No I ended up
I decided I'm trying both. I'm okay building my own server, but I also be so I saw so this week
I've been getting a lot of emails for on filter that are encrypted. I'm like I need a way to
Yeah, I got a so I wouldn't bought pro in the meantime
But I actually already have a droplet set up where I've already started to but I just didn't have time to all moving very fast
It's been a busy week
But damn that if that ain't if that ain't a sweet integration and it totally beats a big male or whatever you call it in Thunderbird
Mm-hmm. Hmm. Yeah. Anyways key based on IO slash Chris LAS and what are you on there?
I think I'm West pain. Let's jeez. Well, I'm noble pain. I'm noble pain on there. Okay. There you go
Yeah, so I've been enjoying the layers in that sense and I apparently it also is
super
Vigilant about tracking when people read your emails. Have you noticed this? Yes, so they have this I think that's a pro only feature
They have you know
They have like the built-in support for like read tracking and that kind of stuff so that when they open it
They're you know downloading something. Yeah, they're servers that yes track of that. They've seen it. Yeah, which maybe that's important to you. Well
I'll tell you it's been interesting because I've been corresponding with an individual from the Linux Foundation recently and
It is interesting to get that bit of information from time to time it is helpful
I will say to get that bit of information a little metadata. Uh-huh
Uh-huh. And so that was an unsurprising perk of using of using n1 that I I thought read receipts were like this
It's not even it's like it's more than read receipts though, isn't it? Yeah, something else. What's the
Pricing on the pro right now. Do you know I don't let me go look cuz it's not cheap
But I was pretty happy with their client though, and the you know, it played pretty nicely with my work
I think they make it really Oh pricing. No, here they go right here sits. Oh, it's okay
It's not nearly as much as I remembered. It's seven dollars a month
but for me, here's here's here's why I like this a lot is I
Have a lot of I have right now I have over 13,000 unread email messages
And I usually get that down to about five thousand
And it's about as low as I ever get sure and so having an email client that anything that can help me search faster
We're gonna actually today in this show. We're gonna we're gonna read email
We're gonna cover email and later on in the show
It's it's one of the it's one of the first times in probably a year that we've read a email on this show simply because
I now have a slightly better workflow to collect you can actually look at the email. Yeah, so it's been worth it
It actually has been worth it for me because it's been good for
Some encrypted communications or you know GPG encrypted communications for and filter
It's been great for corresponding with the Linux Foundation and it's been great now for this particular function
So I do like it quite a bit. I think it's rather nice. It's it's bulky it is
Not cheap you can stand up your own server
I'm going to work on that but right now
I decided to try this because I wanted to use this right away
Yeah, but it also is like you know you're using some other you're using some other background anyway
That's probably free so you know maybe there's an angle where you're like well
Is it enough of a thing on top that I would I would not I would not recommend it for most people
Just if you're concerned all about a third-party being involved in your email
Unless you're using Google services, then go screw yourself. You're a hypocrite all right
I want to talk about something else is totally unsecure USB IP. This is brilliant. This is such a brilliant project
I this is this is something that actually could be really great for Linux terminal service project
USB IP is a project aimed at developing a general USB device sharing system over an IP network USB IP
Encapsulates USB I O messages into TCP IP payloads and transmits them between computers original device
Divide drivers and applications can be also used on the remote computers, so they have with no modification
They have no idea so USB storage discs work
Just fine even even tools like fdisk and make FS and mount all work fine USB keyboards and mice webcams and speakers
USB printers even this and and
USB devices it currently is implemented as a Linux device driver and available under the GPL
It's IO performance is enough for practical it for it says this is I think the English is a little broken
Performance is enough practical and local area network for all types of devices
Including IO synchronous devices without any modification of Linux original USB device drivers
interesting
This could be big for us because this could essentially turn any webcam into an IP camera for us
Yeah, and we could bring we could bring these into our OBS machine. We could have
this of this
This could work so amazing because we could have little machines that could be raspberry pies all over
Conferences with USB web cameras that we could pull into our OBS machine amazing. Yeah, wow
I'm super excited about this project
I'm very it's it's self it I'm selfish, but I'm very excited because it if if the host network was good enough to support it
And it doesn't have to be crazy. We could really we could really
Essentially have a Linux powered IP
camera solution here
Boy yeah, if that would work I'm gonna try we should we have to try yeah, I think so well
Maybe I can get no Enrique to try yeah
I think guys yeah, hey guys. Hey guys. Let's take all the things to put them over IP. What do you think mosenrath?
I'm not so sure I would actually trust that you know like if you're gonna do that over say like a private network a
Monitored network sure go right ahead, but if you're not think about it for a second people are already hacking
Like you know webcams and all that kind of stuff already using whatever means
I'm not smart enough to remember how that's all done, but now if you're putting them all really on the net
Via the wonderful wonderful world of IP what happens if someone says oh, I know what that is
I know what that is
I know what that is and starts just pretty much using all those IPs to
Literally just record all the stuff that you're doing that way instead of recording
You know what's going on on your computer using your computer to record you so this is totally got a lot of huge massive
unbelievable
Security ramifications that we probably can't even begin to touch on I mean
This is this is the project even says you know use this for devices you trust
But on a local area network here like in the studio where we're the only thing we're doing is production, right?
Or or where we could go set up a network where you could trust that network a dedicated switch that kind of thing which is
What we would do oh man
That if you do in a controlled environment. I think it's there's a lot of potential to this
Yeah, William you have thoughts on it. We're just gonna say lock it down. Yeah lock it down
It's a little environment stick it over. You know I'd be sacred and then to be great
It'd be amazing could also this could also be a great way to do network installs you could have
Remote IP USB flash drives, or I don't know I mean just there's a lot of I think there's a lot of
Reminds me of like and DB or the network block device dr. DB. Is that what you're similar to that? Oh?
Network no, what are you talking about Wes how you can mount it you mount a block device over the network. Yeah, yeah
Oh, oh, oh, yeah, dear DB's for like block device replication. Yeah exactly okay, I follow you
Yeah, same thing, but yep now this can be just any USB device mm-hmm
Cool, it's very cool. I'm pretty excited about it anyways
Well wonder if you could do like a synergy type thing not not like as synergistic obviously because it'd be you know
Taken over by one machine, but like here's my keyboard over here. Yeah really mounted on that machine
I think you probably could I think you I think I think that would probably I don't know why that wouldn't work
I could be or and you hmm because to the Linux host it just it just looks like a USB local device
They had this the the software level is just exactly the kind of thing about Linux where it's like you know
Maybe you have like practical applications right in your mind
But there's just so much fun and playing with it
And there's like so many things that you'll discover like maybe it actually is useful to you
Just because you can do it
I legitimately on this computer over here already have a telegram thread going with Noah talking about how we could use this in production
So we will probably test this yes
And get back to you guys on it because it I think it's I think it has some serious potential
I am I am constantly trying to scheme different. I actually kind of blame
I kind of blame wimpy in some ways
But I'm constantly trying to scheme ways we can
We can come up with cool solutions for using Linux to podcast and then and then contribute back to those projects in user air
For that'll come out. God knows when because I'm gonna going on a road trip cat Dev random
that's when but in user air for we talked about some of the
Technology changes we've been doing on the back end and one of the new open source projects that Rekha has been contributing to
sending patches back to to produce user air and
It is it's pretty awesome because so far at least and I know this will probably not always be the case
But so far every upstream project. We've begun working with
For the tools we're using in-house has been damn receptive. That's awesome and in the case of the tool
We're gonna talk about user for is implementing the patches right away
So some of the stuff that we needed to get fixed to improve playback on Android devices and stuff
He's already he's already fixed it upstream Wow yeah
It's so we started we started in-house like well
We'll patch that we'll patch it ourselves and then Rekha Rekha contacted the developer
We've had a couple of successes like that now so anyways
We'll talk about that in the state user air for but it is really cool to be able to take this stuff and say
This gives Linux an advantage in production right of course
That's the lens of what I look at this
but that is is where we're gonna build a pretty good list here of reasons that make Linux awesome to do media production pretty soon and
It's gonna make the Mac look like a joke
You know what else looks like a joke the rest of the mobile industry compared to ting I mean it is
I got nothing these the duopolies they try to be creative, but really they just want to soak you for every single thing
See that's not how ting does it ting is just pay for what you use wireless
It's six dollars for the line, and then you just pay for what you use ting keeps rates simple
We don't make you pick a plan instead
You just use your phone as you normally would how much you use determines how much you pay each month
You can have as many devices as you want on one account
That's good because when you use more you pay less per minute message or megabyte of data
Your usage plus six dollars per active device on your account plus taxes is your monthly bill
Simple that's what we mean when we say
Mobile that makes sense and then they back it up with
Fantastic passionate customer service you get to talk to a real human being they stay on the line
I remember when I was on my road trip out to Noah's house
And I had a mi-fi issue that wasn't ting's fault, and I legitimately I legitimately thought at least three times
It is totally understandable for this person to bail on me right now. It's just a human that could be like listen sir
It should work. I don't know I have I have I have been in that support role before
so I'm like totally understandable and
legitimately they stuck with me the entire time and
It was I was so damn impressed with that experience, but honestly
I don't often talk to the team customer support because they just have a great dashboard
They the control panel really let's you manage anything and an app for your phone, too
It's really nice and the nice thing about it. I'll just say you can go in there and set limits on certain people's accounts
Ha I gotta lock the beard down
He's a mess yeah
They've also got a whole line of devices. They're unlocked you own them outright. They're yours
It's such like an upfront and honest way to do mobile service
There's no like secret backdoor deals. We have to call up and ask when you can get your next
agreements or contracts or
Commitments, it's early termination fees none of that. It's gone
You just got to go to linux.ting.com that'll take
$25 off your first device or if you bring a device and they get CDMA and GSM
It'll take $25 off your first month which will probably pay for the whole damn thing depending on how much you use
So just start by going to linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program
All right, so Wes you and I were sort of caveats in recently is that commencing is that about the state of desktop customization
I gave Loki a pretty good review in 434
I think it's a I think it's got a couple of rough spots, but overall it's a pretty polished desktop a unique product. Yes
But it from a customizability standpoint. That's not its strongest standpoint. It's not where it's really
That's not where you go if you want to have a really custom experience
There's a lot of other options with the plasma desktop
There is some great themes for the gnome desktop
And it's interesting because different distributions make it easier or harder to accomplish this
And if you look at if you look at distributions like arch, yep, there is easy access
But there's no direct tools that allow you to necessarily
Implement those themes right you look at distributions like Ubuntu Mate that come with the tweak tool that allow you to choose a general layout
Which is an overall interface paradigm, but not actually a theme tool itself
There's several they're separate theme tools right, but they're sort of predefined preset. You have a box in which you can play and
and and and so
There's a lot that can be done, but depending on the desktop you choose and the distro you choose
or the combination in which
The variability is very high. Yeah, really it really is and so you've been recently doing
I think you just reloaded from fedora right yeah
Well, I was just getting ready to my laptop has been polluted by all the various things
We've tried here on the show no doubt so I thought like well
Let's reinstall and I can kind of want to redo some of the partitioning to better
You know have better space when I do you want to reinstall like six operating systems at a time to give them a shot
and
I was just thinking about it, and it's not like my main workstation
It's kind of like my on-the-go laptop when I you know when I'm out and about and don't need serious power or anything else
So so it's not crucial. It's not like you know the one I spend all my time on
And I was just thinking about it. It's like I'm very comfortable installing arch
I like installing arch
But there's kind of that last layer of like picking themes choosing them remembering like which directories
I need to stick them in so that they'll be picked up by the right programs
you know even things down to like customizing my vim setup and that sort of stuff where it's
It sometimes it takes me a little bit to get going and there are just some things about
Antrigos in particular in this case. I just thinking well
It's I can get like a really nice desktop where I can still customize everything
I need to write like there's not crazy things installed by default
But I'm up and running in a thing that looks beautiful and like I'm not ashamed to have next to my wife's MacBook
That's an interesting
Criteria, and I don't I don't usually do that. I'm not saying that's like yeah what I will do
And I feel like when you say it was easier was it because that it just came pre-installed with new mix or is it or
Is it something else?
I think so I think it's more just
What what we lack is that like that sense of design in a lot of ways like elementary has it right?
And that's kind of one of the things that sets them apart other distributions have it, too
But especially in like the Wild West of arch or some other places
I feel like it's you know you see like the Unix porn subreddit and that kind of thing and there's a lot of good examples
There, but it it really is something you you have to figure out if you want something
That's non-standard, but you want it to look nice
You really have to figure it out for yourself, and there's like such a there's such a huge array of different possibilities
There's a lot of directions. I think we could go
And I I guess I have one I obviously have one take on this
But I kind of want to bounce it around the mumble room a bit
And I haven't heard from poppy for a while, so I'll start with him. I'd like to hear poppy thoughts on
desktop Linux customization
if you have just general thoughts, but also on
If it's if it's really something that we need to be concerned with at all
I'm I'm the worst person to ask because I'm the kind of guy who
Installed a desktop and then leaves it basically so I think that makes you the perfect person because it's a totally different perspective
Which is I'm kind of like I want to live your world for a second
And so I just don't care. I just want it to get out of the way and get on with doing my applications
I'll generally accept whatever the wallpaper is I might change it
but I've gone for months with whatever the default wallpaper is on my distro and
Probably the only thing I would fiddle is the size of the launcher on the side. You just make it a little bit smaller
I'll install loads of apps of course
And I might change the default so instead of having Firefox to my default. I may have Google Chrome, but
That's about as far as it goes. Um, maybe in a terminal
I might change the font and the font size, but really that's it
I I don't change you consider yourself a very distractible person
Yeah
Okay, so I guess I mean, I mean yes. Yes, totally if by that you mean, you know
I mean I have
loads of windows open with all my social networks in and all that kind of stuff and I also
You know have a phone nearby pinging me at every and yeah
Okay. Okay. I that's I
I just think that for me
I I the reason why I customize is because I can't stop until it's just right and I and I feel like it steals brain
Cycles to use a CPU term. I feel like it steals cycles from my brain right until I've got it just right
So here's a different question. Has it has it gotten easier or less important because it's easier like I feel like ten years ago
If you were using Linux like especially like when comp is was the rage and all that
Like you wanted to customize right you wanted to like show off me like look I can make this look cool
Yeah
Is it just that these days like we've done a good enough job that most distributions you install like they they look respectable like you
Don't have to try to compete to make them look like Windows or Mac because they're their own thing
I think there's a part of that but I mean when I was working on Windows or my
When my work laptop would have been a Windows machine
I would have probably done the same as Chris and I would have tuned it and moved the launcher and fiddled this
So what are those gaming things for Windows even called? Oh my god. Yes
Yes, the dark I would have done
I would have I would have done all of that to get it absolutely perfect because I'd be sat at that computer all the time
Nowadays, I actually just accept most of the defaults and I find that's fine. I have a Windows 10
Machine that I do
That mostly gaming but I do a bit of surfing when it happens to be booted into Windows
Sure
And I don't change that at all other than move the launcher to the left-hand side because that makes sense what?
Barbarian as the launcher at the bottom of the screen consuming vertical real estate that just sounds insane
So I move the launcher to the left and that's it job done job done. That's that's that I like it poppy
That's a good perspective now. Mr
Sipes is in the in the mumble room and you had a chance to look at elementary OS. What do you think about a
Distribution that really focuses on we're gonna just make it look right out of the box and call it good
You stole the words out of my mouth Chris. I used it this past week and it is freaking awesome
I'm the guy I'm kind of like you I try to tweak everything to make it just perfect and until then it's it's not right and
I
popped into elementary and
Once I got my head around the keyboard shortcuts that they write that are slightly different than unity. Yep
I was pretty much there
There are a couple of things which I got back to the team about that. I think are just little bugs maybe that could be
Squashed and make the experience even better
But man, like their defaults are like dead-on and it kind of made me upset and I hate to do this
while poppies in here, but the it kind of made me upset because
Elementary has the polish and has the the out-of-the-box experience that at this point
I really wish that I got that same feeling when I popped up unity
To your opinion right
All right, fair enough now I want to give I write I yeah, I I
I think if I could have if I could sum up my last review about elementary OS
It would be it is the default
Configuration in which my AGD mine can relax and I can just get work done
Yep, and I think I could if I could have just said that if I could have probably summarized the entire review
North ever to that last episode, but North Ranger is on the opposite side of this spectrum
He says screw just let it just sit there and don't tweak it
The tweaking is the the beauty of the Linux desktop. Is that right North Ranger? Yeah, you know
And my experience has kind of grown I think with the way the Linux desktop has grown because you know way back in the day
I vaguely remember
Messing with you know for boom and an open box on Dora. Okay, I'd had at the time
Was you know, you know actually kind of settled into I just want it to work during the Ubuntu GNOME 2 days
But when they booted or the when the unity split happened
I kind of checked out on desktop Linux for a while and it was about I want to say about GNOME 3
312 or 314. Yeah when I really jumped back in but even though I liked the way that
The GNOME folks were handling things. I still wanted things to work a certain way
So I went down the extension rabbit hole man. I probably have about 30 GNOME extensions
I don't know what that's like and I tell you the beauty I think of the system that is available particularly on the GNOME side
Nowadays is how programmable it is
I had a great example of the screencast extension that allows you to record your desktop. Yeah, and I didn't like the
Gstreamer
Settings that it was using and hey, it's just a JavaScript file
I could go in and mess with it and I thought that was awesome that it's not only the look and feel
It's actually how the desktop works awesome and terrifying. I agree. I agree
Well said I actually thought you're gonna come and come at me with the plasma desktop mini mech
I want to give you a chance to jump in go go for it, sir
Yeah, especially on small screens
I would love that all the desktop environments will have an auto hide or in tele height top bar
Because that top bar takes space and there yeah, it's space lost for me
Yeah, that that precious vertical space because all our screens are now 16 by 9 or widescreen aspect ratio
So we did it vertical spaces at a premium now. There is one voice has been absent so far and that would be mr
wimpy and like it or not wimpy may be sort of the face of traditional desktop on
Linux now traditional desktop that has moved forward in ways that make a lot of sense
But wimpy we've talked a lot or we've talked around this a lot, but I'd like to hear your thoughts on this
Okay
Yeah, I make a distro and I added a tweak tool so I could pre bundle the defaults suit me
Which is the Cupertino layout? Mm-hmm. So when I installed a bunzu Marte, so you do customize it
You just build a tool to just automatically
The rest of us get to benefit yeah
That's one way to do it. I guess. Yeah, so
There are tools and but then there is the practical matter of getting the themes and I think this is and I'm not this
Is not a this is not a arch master race thing
I just think honestly, this is where arch probably pulls ahead is the AUR has all the best themes
It really does and and and the the simple fact of the matter is you can do pack AUR dash capital s GTK dash theme dash
Arc enter and you now have the best theme available for the gnome desktop. You didn't have to Google for a PPA
You didn't have to make sure it was the right PPA. You didn't have to add it to your software repository
You didn't have to add the key if you needed to you didn't have to refresh your
Source list and then you didn't have to issue the install command separately
It's already done and you've already configured your gnome desktop to have that theme
it is legitimately one of the best distribution when it comes to choosing a theme because it's just in the AUR and I I
Think that's I think that's one area where I've really enjoyed cinnamon and the plasma desktop is in their theme selector
They just download the themes for you
I feel like because that's one of the things about themes I guess that I would
From before is that it feels very much like there's not a central index
There's not a lot of like can you and if someone knows like is there a good like 2015 2016?
really good guide about how to theme Linux and all the different options and where you go and what are popular themes and where to
Look for those things. I feel like it's kind of like something you gradually learn
You have to know Linux people who know what good themes are to listen to Chris Lass is, you know
Very good opinions about them. Thank you
So it's nice if they if you know the AUR is kind of one of those places like you have like a blessed themes
Well, you have a you are at least you can type in gnome theme search and then search by votes or or
Popularity and get a good idea of which themes people are installing. Yes, it provides like something from like that
That's a nice for some people like tweak their desktop. That is a that's an inherent advantage, but mr
Cipe says he has the ultimate solution. Yeah, so here's what I say. I say that
The canonical higher wimpy and higher the elementary team and
They work really hard on making things customer customizable, but also really nice and polished out of the box
What do you think of it? What do you think of that Chris? You think we should?
Pressure them into into doing that. I actually think what we should do
We'll all buy a bunch of phones if they do
Ryan if we're gonna play that game what I say we should well
I would say what we should do is start a campaign with in system 76 to ship one of their laptops with elementary OS
That's what I say. We should
Know I think honestly, I
Think really there is a certain design choice that should be made for the traditional desktop
Obviously that's something that canonical has
Gotten some flack for in the past and the and the switch over to unity 8 is probably gonna reignite that debate to some degree
After it happens, but I actually and I'm not gonna put words in wimpy's mouth
but in my opinion the way it seems to be working is
canonical
Acknowledges the existence of the Ubuntu Mate project. It is it is an official flavor
They have extended invitation invites to wimpy to go to things like the snap sprint invite. It kind of seems like
the ideal arrangement for end-users at this point because wimpy is able to manage his project as a
Independent project and make decisions the best benefit it and its user base while basing it on a technology stack that is
Not only aware of the project's existence, but working amicably with that project. I mean it seems right now to be
sort of an ideal
Arrangement and I mean I wish the best of wimpy could if canonical offered him a great salary go for wimpy
But I think wimpy
You have something kind of unique in your hands. I was just saying to
West before we started the show and
Then you you you kind of mockingly reshared this or or jokingly reshared this on Google Plus
But the the the sentence that stuck in my head was the Linux distribution of the year. I
I mean the year is not over yet, but there are there are only so many distributions
I would put maybe in the top three and Ubuntu Mate is there and I I think you have a good arrangement now
And I think it's that's just my opinion, but I think it's I think it's one of the best distributions of the year so far
Yeah, sadly not the best. It sounds like so
Right yeah, yeah, well, you know Ike he's been working hard. He's been working hard, and he didn't spend some time here on the West
Yeah, no he doesn't sleep
He's actually been able to so in five years
He'll explode and then you guys will be somehow somehow he's even been able to ship the Mate desktop for solace
So yeah, now who knows what could happen good to see
All right, so I want to move forward we have some follow-up and feedback to get to but I would like to hear your thoughts
out there about
The oh well actually Ryan. Did you have thoughts on polish before we move off?
yeah, the the thing that gets me is I
whenever I was using elementary this past week, and I've used Mate before and the thing that I come back to is I
I've gotten so used to popping into a distribution and having like
These little things that bug the crap out of me and having to go through
you know a series of steps in order to fix them and
It was so weird to to pop in and feel like
There had been a lot of focus on that polish, and I didn't really know what you were talking about
In your in your review till I popped up
You know elementary on my own box and started playing with it, and I realized
Just the just the little things that have gotten neglected
neglected for what I think our visions outside of you know that that experience of I
Have a desktop. You know I have this desktop distribution. I'm gonna make it as great as possible and
Anyway, that was super frustrating and and I've and I'm glad that that we have like Mate and I've talked to Aiki quite a bit
You know solace talking about his
his full focus being on
his desktop distribution and
Elementary it sounds like they're doing the same thing and I just really wished that there was that same focus
From from other projects as well and making the desktop experience. Just work and be
consistent and nice
So anyway, that's that's I'll get off my high horse, but that's that's that's where my head's been today, and I was just so impressed
the past few days playing with elementary that I so wanted to
To talk about the great job that you know some projects are doing around that polish and that great experience
I feel like
elementary solace and Ubuntu bate
Might be my top three for the year right now at this point and
For different reasons for each one of them. I feel like they're they're they're all
Or at least to some extent distributions you can recommend and the the caveats that you would have with that would go along with that
Are pretty minimal, you know, well, there's a lot of other distributions that like are amazing in some ways
But you have to be like well
but except for this and you're gonna have to do that and
But all those would be like I could set those up for a lot of people and just they would be that's they would do
That's dead-on. That's exactly that's better than I could have ever put it. It's a that thing where you start apologizing
This is good, you know, but you're gonna run into this and I just turn it off to Wi-Fi off put it back on
It's fine. Don't suspend don't suspend
Yeah, that's exactly it. Yeah. Hmm. Yeah, it is
it's
2016 I think some of the surprises have been so far now that we're more than halfway into it has have been these distributions
but also and not just because Ryan's here because I also say same same goes to Entraware is
Some and and and purism is working on it to some aggressive improvements some some really aggressive improvements to
the desktops and laptops that run this stuff and I think there's still people out there that have
a perfectly legitimate reasons to choose a ThinkPad or a or even a MacBook Pro
I mean the or a Dell Sputnik
there's a lot of different hardware out there at this moment that Linux will run on but the the the
locally sourced
artisan homegrown
100% organic
Laptops that run Linux have been better penguin tattoo right on them better than ever and now we have these distributions
that are better forever and it's kind of a funny because
I
Don't I don't think we really talked a lot about this at the beginning of the year. No, we didn't
Interesting. All right. Well, let's move on let's I think we've probably spent enough time on this
But thank you mumble room this yeah
And if you have if you have thoughts on Linux desktop customization, feel free to let us know in the comments
I want to mention Linux Academy before we move into our feedback Linux Academy comm slash unplugged go get the advanced
Skills you need around Linux the basics
But also really all of the cool things around Linux that are more more sophisticated they have advanced training tools that increase your skills and encourage
Critical thinking and give you hands-on experience at Linux Academy. You start by going to Linux Academy comm slash
Unplugged they have labs and exercises that give you real world servers where you get to actually work on this stuff
Really feel confident with it and walk away like you've actually done it before in that interview can be like, yep
I I totally hosed that easy to instance. I just destroyed it
And now I know what not to do and you know
What's nice about like specifically with the ec2 stuff all included as part of Linux Academy subscription
It's not like you got to go set up a separate thing and all of that
You can SSH right into the servers
They have practice exams and quizzes learning plans that give you a time frame and you can just work within that
In fact, if you're busy, they have availability planners that'll sort of work with you on your days
You have available and set up reminders. It's a super cool system full of Jupiter broadcasting community members
and
Created by Linux enthusiasts. I think the big thing for me is like
Even just outside of the JB community the amount that I've seen people jump on the Linux Academy bandwagon is amazing
Like yeah, you know like big old-school admins just a whole gamut of people who use Linux
I've seen just like they're getting really big the people who use Linux they they know about Linux Academy because it's made by people
Who use and yeah, it's high-quality stuff and they're getting bigger and bigger all the time. Exactly
It is pretty neat to see them grow Linux Academy comm slash
unplugged
Alright, so this is an email that came into the show from storm 77
He says warning they may use a pro 5 Ubuntu manual that we linked to last week
Suggest formatting the external SD card. Hi. Hello by the hello there. Hi there. Hello in an episode real pain in the flash
Love 161 you added this manual to the show notes any links to the PDF by the way
He says in the TWRP section on wiping the device. It also selects the micro SD card
This is the external SD card. Not the internal one. I saw it in time. It just let you know
I almost formatted my 120 gigabyte card
Just wanted to prevent anybody else from running into this
The backup is also incomplete
So I wrote a small tool to back up the entire flash onto an internal SD card
He links us to that too and he says give wimpy his regards. Well, that's just great. Thank you for the warning
Yes, likewise the tool improvement. That's amazing. And it's great that that you're doing that
I think you you should let us know more about your experiences. It's going forward. Oh wimpy. Can we get an update from you?
Fine going well, thank you
Good legally awaiting OTA 13 in the hope that
Bluetooth is
Bluetooth specifically Bluetooth audio is resolved for for my my device
I thought I thought literally you were gonna do with all is going well. Thank you
Yeah, I don't ask you about your phone do I
Mm-hmm. Yeah, I was in fact, I'm gonna cover OTA 13 a little bit in the next week's episode of the Linux action show
Yeah, no, it's all good it's good
I think it's it looks like a pretty great update. So I just talked about that a little bit in the next episode of last
which
I'll be honest was pre-recorded. I know I'm going on a little road trip and so we pre-recorded that but so we I do happen
To know the future and that we talked about that new update. So Bluetooth is what wimpy is looking forward to it
Sounds like yes. Yeah
All right, I'm a whole bunch of stuff. I'm looking forward to but that in particular
I'm gonna keep asking you wimpy all the time because you I'm living by
Prepared in the future. This is revenge for you asking about when the Libra was kind of
I was doing that for about six months
Chris you need to buy something so we can bring that back. You should take mental notes wimpy
You could take it. No, I'll just ask you next week. Actually, I just really want to know
Yeah, that's me too. Yeah, exactly Paul writes in
About a bunch of touch way into the nexus 70 says that with all the talk recently about a bunch of touching KDE
Have you seen plasma dash mobile org you talked about Wayland how good that will be to have
But on arch with gnome 320, it's already available. If you just check out your gdm custom.com file
Finally, it's rumored that there will be a nexus pixel 7 this year
If that happens, do you think a boon to touch would be released for it? Keep up the great shows Paul
So mr. Popey, can I pick your brain on what is the process when a brand new piece of hardware ships?
What is sort of what is what the impetus to get a boon to touch on that devices?
I got to imagine it's a it's a starts with somebody picking up a piece of hardware
Yeah, for the most part their community ports
So it's you've got to have a someone skilled in doing the porting and be they've got to actually have the device
Yeah, and then third third the real the real killer is time
They've got to have time to actually sit down and do the port and when you have a never-ending supply of Android
Devices coming and people, you know saying hey, I want this one next this one next
It's it's actually a never-ending supply and we need more people to to to get involved in that because it's just
You know, there are more devices out there than there are possible people who can pour them, you know
I would imagine so it's it's a small team. But yeah, generally you pick up advices and
you know get the source code for the kernel and all that kind of stuff and then start the porting effort and
Follow the documentation basically so far and this could change over time
But it seems like the way it works is when a device reads it reaches a certain critical mass
Which it can sometimes be a year or two after its original release
you start to see
enough community members coming together to work on that device like
The Nexus 5 for example
Or other devices where there's just it's kind of nice in a sense because it gives a device of yours a second life
but at the same time as
The community grows I would expect that might scale a bit more right and and there's a lot of resources typical like
Developers scratching their own itch, you know
Has a Nexus 5 in front of them and once you know once the port to happen
Then they'll either try and do it themselves or they'll throw some money at somebody else to do it
It's you know
If you if you don't have it if if there's a device and you don't actually have one
You're probably not motivated to want to pull to it. Then you need that because there are a lot of people
yeah, there is like a there is a
Shoot, I'm blanking on the name poppy, but there's kind of like a bounty source equivalent for device port. Isn't there you be ports?
Yes, you before you have any ports. It's it's got a patreon as well. Okay, there you go
so that that is an eye that's a fascinating idea to in fact, I think I've I think I've actually
Well, cuz you kind of need that like you need the people developing it
They need to have the phones and then you need the people who are willing who have the phones and are willing to like run
It and then submit bugs and you know patches and core dumps and all that stuff. Yeah
It's fascinating though because it can all happen just takes a community to do it. It takes a village West
It takes a village to raise a phone. So Java King writes in and wants to know my Bitcoin Linux details
He wants me to expose all my secrets. He says hi Chris. You mentioned using Bitcoin
I'm a new bitcoiner and I wonder if you might elaborate on your setup. Maybe share you with your audience
Here are some questions. I have do you use Bitcoin core or a lightweight client with multi bit or electrum?
Have you securely backed up your wallet dot dad? Do you perform all transactions from a single desktop? And
What currency exchange do you use and what app do you use to monitor the Bitcoin value? Thanks Java King. Boom
Give us the deets Chris. So Java King. He said you're a new bitcoiner and you wanted to know how how I
Secure my setup. No, I'd say my first step is don't tell people how you use Bitcoin. That's my first hint
Because that is the worst thing you could do. But since I am here, it's helped. I am here at your service
I am here for you. I will I will expose myself
so I use electrum as my wallet of choice it has I've
Mainly since I started plan B. I've used this because I I've had an on-and-off
Conversation thread over the years with the developer and so I just happened to know the person behind it and I like it
But also I like the fact that it fires up right away. That's one of the things I really enjoy about it
Have you tried electrum? Yeah, I have. Yeah. I also like the instant on yes, really. That's a big sell
Yeah, so electrum is the the wallet of choice. So then he said do I back up my wallet dot dat file?
How do I securely back up my wallet dot dat file?
Well, one of the cool things about Bitcoin Java King is you could actually store it offline and there are methods to actually even print
It out and store it if you want. So look into that
Do you perform all transactions from a single desktop? Yes
And I back that directory up. What currency exchange do you use? I'm lazy. I use coinbase
Yeah, what do you know? I also am lazy and use coinbase
And I've also talked to the people behind coinbase before and I know them and I like them
So what desktop after you used to monitor the current Bitcoin value? Well, I
am
Apparently a masochist. I use a gnome extension. And so I have a gnome extension that works all the time
So right now at the Bitcoin price as we record this episode
$609 and 64 cents a US greenback this morning. It was at
$611 and so I made a small Bitcoin transaction on behalf of the Jupiter broadcasting
Well my Bitcoin, but I purchased something for the Jupiter broadcasting network because I made the guesstimate that that's the high for the day
And I need this thing
And so that's I kind of watch that and if I know there's something that the network needs
I watch that on my desktop and I try to I try to make my purchase in the point where it's at the highest value
of the day
and there's there's I have I have so many Bitcoin bookmarks that I also check but
I believe coin average. That's the one I was gonna say Bitcoin average is just a little pin tab. Yeah, check out Bitcoin average
We also have the we also have some Bitcoin functionality built into J bot. Oh, yeah, that's right
Yeah, and if you want to follow news of the Bitcoin subreddit, it's usually pretty good
you can go there and check that out Bitcoin still hanging around it's hanging around and
Noah is actually still mining Bitcoin to this day. Oh, is he? Yeah. Wow, he does
He has some dedicated rigs to wimpy. Do you mind any Bitcoin anymore? No, it's a false game. Yeah, I agree
Yeah, I agree
I think Noah gets the power for free for some reason and a like it's like from like this
All right, this building overall payment that he made not even sure it's worth it for the heat that it generates
Anymore. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I did look into getting some of those
faster USB
A6 yeah to plug into a pie. Yeah, but the difficulty now is astronomical
Even if you sort of used a dozen of those, you know, you yeah. Yeah, it's not worth it
You're just you're just participating in network playing your role in keeping the network healthy
But you're not actually gonna make anything you need some serious horsepower these days. I have I have I have been experiencing
some interesting like holy what you're using Bitcoin and like
Yeah Bitcoin, yeah, they what Bitcoin and I'm like
I'm totally shocked
I mean I look at them like you know what Bitcoin is they look at me like I've heard this word before but I have
No idea what you're talking about
There are more and more small independent shops in Washington
That are using Bitcoin as a back-end payment as a back-end sort of
What is the right word to use it's like it's like this it's the payment processing
They're using Bitcoin to fund the transactions and the payment processing and then they're immediately converting it into cash
Right, and so at the point-of-sales device, I give them a visa or a MasterCard
but when they swipe it the payment processor is using Bitcoin to float the transaction or something and then
the
Merchant receives the payment in cash
Interesting and this is there's a lot of little businesses doing this now and they have it hooked up to the tablets and Wow
Yeah, so you just use your your visa regular Visa card, but Bitcoin is used on the back end as some sort of facility interesting facilitator
Yeah, huh? I've been meaning to look into it more. We should definitely look into them
Yeah, yeah. So anyways, it's it's Bitcoin still out there. Yeah, Electrum is my wall
There's multi bits and other multi bits another good one. Yeah, check out but I like Electrum
So when be do you do you have a wallet that you like to mention or do you want to talk about your setup at all?
Well these days I use coin corner as my exchange and my wallet. Mmm coin corner. Yeah, nice
so they're based in the Isle of Man which is in the shores of the
British Isles, but
independently governed I
Like I like that. That was that was your requirement
Well, it wasn't a requirement back when I was looking because I went through the whole you know getting out of Mount Gox
That all yeah, I mean and and even when that was
like the only reputable exchange around it was
It was always a heart-in-mouth moment whenever you did any kind of
Yes, gosh, it was man. It was just awful. So I was looking for an exchange and
A few couple of years ago. Yeah about two years ago
I found coin corner and they were a startup then but they'd got all the right bits in that they could do
Sterling euros dollars
they'd got all the necessary financial approvals they'd got a sensible bunch of people behind them and
I
Switched all that over to them and I've not looked back since they've been a really good service
So they're much like coinbase, but that they are in this part of the world, which was kind of important
Absolutely. Sure. That makes sense. And of course our our Bitcoin expert poppy any Bitcoin update from you?
Hmm. No, it seems like he wandered off to bed. Nope. He doesn't have a Bitcoin update. I think he just
Doesn't have one. He's counting all these bitcoins. Yes. Yeah filthy rich bastard
All right
That brings us to the end of this week's unplugged if you would like to send us an email go to Jupiter broadcasting comm
Contact you're also encouraged to leave feedback wherever you watched this or visit the subreddit
It Linux actually showed our reddit comm and man
Would we love if you showed up live Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar and also shout out to the Linux gamer
Who may be joining us next week on the program. That's right. Don't forget
Tune in live at JB live TV and if you'd like to join our virtual lug go get mumble and then bang mumble in our
Chat room to find out more. We'll see you back here next Tuesday
Oh
JB titles comm let's go pick our title you guys. Let's go figure out what we're gonna call this sucker. Hey guys
Thanks for being here. It was a good show. I really appreciate a great mumble turnout. Yeah, absolutely
Hmm that mumble the room virtual log
While we do that
Let's see if I can type now with the live updating too. So have you been doing desktop customization?
What do you been you got what do you got going on over here? No, I I this has not been customized at all yet
Oh, I installed I installed it as we started the show damn damn snickety
Thankfully causal is really easy to install so that's true. That's true. That's why I'm running Firefox. Well, I have Chrome now
I just haven't switched Linux flying high Linux is for tweakers yikes
Yeah, that's right week
All right, well, let's see while
While we go vote at JB titles comm a brief distraction. Oh, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait
You said commercial software. I don't know what to make of this Indiegogo project
It's it's title it gets me excited big brother needs to be stopped
Independence Day for your private data a new way of using cloud services and messaging apps and they've got 20 days left to raise some funds
I'll play a little bit of their publicity video and maybe we can
Can I get a larger version of here? They see it's trapped in the yeah. Here we go. Let's watch this thing
Hi, we are saying we'd like to show you a new way using cloud services
Messaging apps a way that's simpler and more secure than ever before. Are you one of the 1.6 billion people on our planet?
Using messaging apps and cloud storage. It's kind of a cool track. You can share anything you want with the whole wide world
But what if you don't want to share?
Set even up to you
Think about it. What actually happens to messages when you hit sent and what happens to your data when you upload it to your cloud service?
Some cloud services are easy to use including for data snoops
Some are transparent about what's under the hood and if you even manage to keep the door shut on big brother
But there's not a single solution out there that delivers all three of these requirements, but with Zengi you're always protected
Not only do we encrypt your data with the best available code
We split every single file into countless fragments
Which we then distribute across all cloud storage services you use. So this is like a layer that says on top of your cloud services
I see interesting
So for the cloud provider and anyone else your data is just a random collection of unreadable data chunks
Because with Zengi only you have the key to the fully assembled files
Nobody should see your messages, but the people who sent them to whatsapp and other providers claim they encrypt your message
But you are also just claiming that you encrypt my message
You got to give me a little more here and don't snoop on them
But do you really believe them Zengi is open source so you can see yourself that our code secure and free of any backdoors
I like that. Or get a nerd you can trust to check for you
Zengi the world's first encryption solution for the people by the people
Not some big multinational
Even when there are secure solutions out there, they never just hand it to you on a platter
The thing is your security shouldn't be some puzzle you have to solve
He's got a Rubik's Cube
It's a serious game and you should be free to play it by your own rules
Did he saw that there?
Rules that you configure
You know what would be great is if it was part of you know
You know, it's a stretch goal for a project like this that I would be totally behind is
You know you do your main funding for for actually accomplishing this
But then in one of the stretch goals a full third party audit
Oh, that would be great. Yeah, that would be a great stretch goal that I could get behind
Using the simplicity of Zengi
Rules that protect you and the people who you really trust
If somebody is hyper security conscious
Are they less likely to use a Fitbit because he's got a Fitbit on
I don't know
Who those people are
What they're thinking
Where they're from
How they look like
What they're working on
And who they are
Basically everything they want to keep private is protected by Zengi
Zengi works and for one very simple reason
Security transparency and usability to give you back total control
Stu!
I feel like this is also them wanting to show off their entire team
Yeah, probably
That guy did just solve that Rubik's cube in the background
That was kind of cool
All right, that is cool
Other solutions lets you choose a key
With Zengi you have ownership of the key and the lock
Zengi will create a complete ecosystem where security
Transparency and usability are yours anytime anywhere
So your digital identity is always protected
And sometimes that can be pretty important
And Zengi puts you back in control of your personal data
Zengi will give you the power to protect your digital identity
These guys do look a bit like a stereotype though
Good for them though
Okay
Their music sounds like a radio spy novel
Yeah, that's a good way to put it
I like that, that's a nice way to put it
So let's look at the
Let's see if they tell us much about the underlying technology
They have good dress like a boss, that's cool
They have cool the all in
They have good price levels
Let's see though
We got to get some details on this
They say they created a foundation for a new standard of security and transparency and usability
Well, those are all things that we like
That sounds good
That's not the details I want
They say that your data is encrypted with AES 256
It is split into tiny chunks and distributed to all cloud services you use
So for the cloud provider, it sounds like it really is a layer that sits on top of your
Dropbox in your Google Drive and just gives them bits and pieces
So what happens if you split it between all these places and one of them goes down
Is all your data gone?
I think they're saying that it sounds like they're
They're not splitting it across the separate things, but they're splitting it
They have to know how to put pieces back together and they're all
They have all the bits, but they're put there because they're separated
You'd have to have the key to put them all back together
It looks like Linux isn't supported until $70,000 is raised
But it says it's a messaging app, right?
It's not clear
It says it does those things
How does it actually sync with other users?
Does your phone do the federation?
Here's the question
Can I use my existing cloud accounts?
Absolutely
You can link all your existing cloud accounts or simply add new ones
However, the data in your existing accounts must be re-uploaded to guarantee full security
Wow, that's interesting
Geez
These guys become the gatekeeper for all of your online services
That's what I was thinking
You're now trusting a company you've never heard of with all of your online storage
They would argue that's their advantage
Is that they are a non-multinational small group of folks
That are creating something by the people for the people
That's what they say
That's their argument
I mean, you trust inseminators for something
Even your grandma can use it
Is that thing plugged in?
Does that say it's plugged in there, Wes?
Is that what it says there?
Can you tell, I don't know what those icons mean
Windows
Yeah, I don't
It does look like it, yes
Okay
Fully charged, 100%
Does have a little
Their goal is only $35,000?
Yeah, and they don't have Linux support until 70
What?
But like, what are they going to do with $35,000?
Are they planning to bang this out in like a month with four people?
They would have to have already had a bunch of funding, I would think
So I think, unfortunately, even though it's something we'd all like
I think we're all saying nope
I think it's kind of a nope
The goal just doesn't make sense
Yeah, they would be such a critical point of failure
How do you sustain yourself on $35,000?
And how do you, and then, so they show it right here in their diagram
If you are the front end proxy to all of these different services
And the ones they have, they have Box, Pax, OwnCloud, and Drive on here
They actually don't have Dropbox's icon, but they have all the other ones on here
So two things, like was just mentioned
If they go offline, you can't get access to your data potentially
But aren't you just giving the government the best gift in the entire world?
They just have, instead of having to go to four different providers
They just go to one provider?
And even if they just got the metadata
If they just got the time and date and where you upload it to, that'd be something
I mean, this seems like this is one place to serve a national security letter to
Instead of four different places
Even if it's not getting the data
Even if you're just getting the time and date the user logged in
The IP they logged in from
And the amount of data they uploaded to and the services they went to
That's valuable information
Well, is Sangy actually storing anything on their end?
Or is it just a software solution that combines all your cloud accounts?
Well, I'm not saying they're storing the data
But they probably have logs of when you connected and logged in and transferred
I've been asking them
They should tell us these things, perhaps
There's a lot of implementation questions
What are you doing this?
I like how they're growing that
We created a foundation for a new standard of security and transparency
They keep going after this
But then they're not very transparent about how this works at all
They say that they're going to put their code up on GitHub
But that doesn't make it transparent
No, not really
That's like the first thing that you do on the transparency
Doesn't tell us what you're doing on the server side, though
Doesn't tell us how you're logging it
Oh, where the phones go
This is good
They're making it secure for Linux
Because you're not able to use it
Right
Oh, excellent point
You have a thing that says where the phone
Oh, where?
Yeah, scroll down on their Indiegogo page
And there's like bars and these graphs
And it's like 50% of the stuff goes to development and admin
And then there's like marketing
Oh, that's what that is
That's known as a chart, Chris
Oh, there it is
There it is
That's at $100,000
$17,000 goes to development for your base goal?
For what it's supposed to be like a world premiere secure product?
Yeah, it has to integrate with like eight different services out of the box
Yeah, who's like, are they like going to take on the burden of maintaining all of those API wrappers all the time?
Yeah, boy, that just right there could be a job
Yikes
Not to mention, I'm sure that Dropbox and Google is not super keen to having a third party between them and their customers
Because from Google's standpoint, Google wants to do their utmost
Supposedly to protect your privacy and data
So they're not going to like this
This reminds me of like when you used to be able to use a
If there was a fuse layer so that you could store files in your gmail storage by like split it up and do a lot of different emails
I think somebody, I think a company should take LibreVault
Or something like SyncThing and productize it and just say use
Use and sell it as combining all of your computer's hard drives into one online secure storage
Right
No online cloud account, no service, no account required
Just uses all of your devices storage and pools them together in a super secure encrypted way
Why is that not a product that people are selling on Indiegogo or Kickstarter?
That seems pretty obvious
Because grandma couldn't use it
It's all about grandma
And also they wouldn't be able to do a subscription service
Oh you got it, yeah that's true