Since you a web-based IRC client. Oh you did. Where did you send that to me? Oh, oh in the slacks
Oh, okay, speaking of slack speaking of slack
Oh jeez no not that oh no not that not
Anything but the Gibson I just actually with full Gibson just for a second full Gibson
So what is this West what is this? Oh, a
Self-hosted web IRC let it speak for itself. Hmm. Yeah, so this is called shout a self-hosted web IRC client
That's pretty cool. Always connected shout never sleeps
Just sign in and pick up where you left off the client works smoothly on every desktop smartphone and tablet
Shout is open source and licensed under MIT
This is exactly exactly what I was talking about West. Let's say we got a demo right here. Let's try it out. Yeah
So let's call did now your name is gonna be Chris demo. Okay guys, don't be a jerk. Okay, don't don't troll me
Okay, so oh, oh, they won't let me change the server. Oh, yes, they will Willie. Nope. I can't change the server
Well, okay. We'll just go then I was gonna try to connect to geek shed
you know, this is
This is pretty plain, but it's quite plain. Yeah, is it is it configurable?
Here's the thing. I'm gonna go ahead and show you what it looks like
Here we go. Change sessions show join show parts. I like that. I like that. You can turn that off. That's cool
Show quits. I don't need any of that enabled colored nix. I like that. I
Enable notifications do not want that
Okay, so it's got some configuration options, but the one thing it doesn't let you configure is the look of it. Apparently
It's pretty stark. I mean would be nice, but it's almost doable
You know
I think I'm gonna give it a I think I'm gonna give it a try
Because I was looking at IRC cloud and this is I'm liking this so self-hosted web IRC client shout. Thanks Wes. Good find
How did you find that? I think that is a good find found it somewhere laying on the Internet
I don't know just laying around laying around that crazy. You know, I'm I should be making use of that
I did something else with a web IRC thingy today and
I'm gonna replace it with this. What a web IRC thing. Does anyone tell me what was it? What was it? Oh
I said, well, I guess it's very oh, it's awkward. I can't I can't say oh
Was a proprietary garbage it was wasn't it? No, no. No, it's it's for another podcast. I've been always another podcasts website a
Facelift
This isn't no, so this isn't IRC client you embed in the website
This is a web based IRC client. That's always connected that you bring up in your web browser
Yeah, no, that's that would be better than what I've done today
I'll put a link in the in the show notes
This is Linux unplugged episode 130 for February 2nd 2016
You
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show and it's Jones and for a new rig. My name is Chris
My name is Wes. I don't know Wes
Maybe it's because before every show Wimpy gives me a hard time about the fact that my that has something to deal with it
That might be stoking the flames as they say well coming up on today's episode of the unplugged show
We're not talking about my drama. No. No, we actually have a great show coming up for you on this week some really interesting updates
We're gonna spend a little more time than usual going through some big stories that have come up
Since the Linux action show was on the air
We have a lot to cover up on and then we'll talk about this Linux command that's getting blamed for bricking laptops
Even when you're not running away. Yeah, I love these controversies that we just seem to fall into we'll do a quick review of tails
2.0
They say it's Edward Snowden's always of choice Wes has got it loaded right here
He's gonna give us his take and some of the challenges he ran into and then later on in the show is Linux mint drunk
with power
What the heck is X apps? I know I I we got to talk about this
Maybe they are brilliant or maybe they're going off into the weeds Linux mint is introducing its own suite of applications
We'll talk about that in the show today. I got it. I just got to get your guys's take on that
I gotta know I gotta know and then did you hear the news?
Dell is
making their own Linux what Dell is making their own Linux and
You're not gonna believe the name
Do you have a guess what it is? Do you know what it is? No, I don't you don't I'm not telling anyone
No, no, I if you have a guess
I would love to hear your guess as to what you think Dell is gonna name them
We're gonna talk about it later in the show, but I think we give away the name now
I think cuz it's so great. It's so great. No, I don't know. Should I not say should we wait?
Okay, we'll wait don't say chat room. Don't say don't say we'll make everybody wait till the end of the show
But you're not gonna believe the name of of does links. Don't say it. Don't say it
Jerem we have so much to get into but before we do that West, you know
We got to talk about because it's become a tradition now just sort of accidentally on the show is the beer we're drinking
Yes, it has and I like you. So you heard me complaining and moaning on the
Last as you do as I do I was beer desperate and I went and I grabbed this coffee beer
Which actually was delicious by stone IPA or by stone?
This however is something completely different. This is a local Washington brew where so I doubt they'll be able to
To drink this so they'll just have to drink vicariously through us. How do you suppose you say that coal?
Colchon, I believe Colchon
You're probably absolutely right so this is their this is their red ale and
It's actually it's it's not it's surprisingly good. It's not amazing, but it's surprisingly good. It's easy drinking on the show
You know what? It matches the weather. It's very nice out. It sure is kind of clean and crisp out
So there you go. I could almost be spring that almost like it's teasing us
So that is our beverage of choice today while we're getting started now, let's get into the show
Let's bring in our virtual lug time appropriate greetings mumble room
freedom
Hello, I like it. I like it. Yeah, it's fired up today for a good show
Well, so let's get started with some updates. We have a little bit of a birthday party
I'd play the jingle but it'll get us taken down on YouTube
15 years of
VLC and I think actually specifically it's 15 years since VLC went GPO. Whoa. Yeah, can you believe that you know VLC?
Everybody has a VLC trick right like you have anything like you use VLC for that maybe is a little unconventional
Well, I mostly I just I do stream it every every which way. Yeah when possible
I my favorite is I take our TSP our TMP streams a lot of the television networks
Use these for their back-end streaming between each other and if you can find them
You can use them to get the raw feed and then you can record it which is great for unfiltered
And so you can use VLC to read it right to an MKB file with perfect, you know x264, whatever your codec
It could be Vorbis and Theora, whatever
And it is I mean that's what I use it for. I know a lot of people. Oh, oh
We use it here in studio to send
Where as you can see over there on that screen we have VLC that is playing reruns over there
Yep, and then we have OBS run this so that's on an arch desktop
We have OBS that is taking that VLC window and recapturing it and sending it as an RTSP stream back over to
This machine to run as reruns and I can tune into that stream using VLC from any computer in the studio
And I can check on what's going on in the live stream just by doing that. It's really cool
I did that over the holidays. I set up a repeating Star Wars stream for some of my friends
You know before before the movie came out with the VLC up on a droplet and your password protected with nginx
You just have to sign in and we'll see there and that's awesome. That sounds like a segment. That is super cool. Yeah
So congratulations to VLC 15 freaking years. What would we do without you now Wimpy?
Have you had a chance to try out them beautiful blu-rays in VLC?
Just recently I have yeah, I've got blu-rays playing in VLC. How are you? How does the encryption work in that setup?
So you need a few bits and pieces. There's lib
AACS which does the decryption stuff and there's two ways of doing it my old
Desktop workstation. I patched the firmware to in the blu-ray drive
Did you know you had to get this blu-ray player? Yeah, I've had it for donkey's years
No, no, I've had this since blu-ray was new so it's very old and that's what I've been using to
Dump my blu-ray discs into plex for the longest time
But it died about a week or so ago. So I've got a new blue USB 3 blu-ray drive and
I needed to dump the blu-rays, you know with make MKV
So I needed to do that with the way where you get the key DB file and all those bits
And then I thought well, I wonder if you can get them playing as well
So I've been working on that for a bantu mate and that's all all going now
that
Yeah, I met make MKV man. That's great, too. So
Yeah, also just sort of related. I also just want to give props to VLC
It has become such a badass on Android and the VLC iOS app is actually pretty great
It's great. Yeah, and I can't believe this either
But they have a VLC has an Apple TV app and when one of the things that the Apple TV app can do
I have not tried this
But one of the things the Apple TV app can do is it sets the Apple TV up as a media server
So you can send any video stream to the Apple TV using VLC
I know that Chromecast support is coming that I mean it is so the Android app is great
The Android TV app is great. The Apple TV app sounds cool. I know the
Really, so they've they've been able to sort of
Keep up and they're 15 years old. This is really cool
So yeah, there you go. I five years before it was called VLC. It was called Network 2000
It's called Network 2000
So never been the best with names no that doesn't matter because it turns into a Christmas code that is one of my favorite things
Okay, I'm hoping somebody in the mumble room
I saved this story just for unplugged because I'm hoping somebody in the mumble room knows more than I do about the new
Pac-man that was released Pac-man version 5.0 came out and
I guess here's what I know that's new about it, but I don't know much
Pac-man 5.0 is finally here after many months of development during which maintainers managed to add a great number of new features such as support for
running hooks
Before and after transactions, which sounds pretty cool
Pac-man 5.0 also ships with support for handling sim links to folders that have been replaced by a directory
support for recording the package a variable in a local package database and the ability to print extra info for dependency errors and
Support for comparing the internal versions of a package with a database where you can store your files
You can store your files in a folder that contains the internal versions of a package with a database one after downloading it
These all seem neat. Yeah
Anybody in the mumble room have any more info about Pac-man 5.0. I know it's kind of a big deal
But I don't really have I'll just start with using Pac-man is always a pleasure. I don't know
It's just I'm very rarely unhappy with it. Yeah, and it just works. I guess my systems if it's out
I guess my systems are upgraded. I didn't really notice
So nobody has any comments on that. That's fine. We can move on from there quickly moving then to something that I bet people
Do have some comments on
Edward snowden's favorite distro tails 2.0 is out. That's what they that's what they get to market it now
And they really push that uh, so a couple of things new about tails 2.0
Lots of changes to the gnome shell environment debbie and 8 base, which pretty much means all the software has been upgraded under the hood
Uh, you're using the gnome shell. It's in classic environment and you're sitting here right now wess
with the new tails 2.0 on
How's it going?
It's actually working. It's actually working, isn't it? Yeah
It's working. All right. Uh, so let's start there actually was a little bit challenging to get working
Well admittedly I was trying to install it in a very handy way with grub 2's loopback support
So you can just dump the iso file on a hard drive actually that works brilliantly totally supported
um
Although their live cd disables root permissions by default, which probably does make sense
There's like an extra boot option. You can check to have that happen
Okay, I have not been able to get that working
So I believe you'll probably need to you may need to install it or set it up to boot just from the iso to get
All of the options so i've not been able to set up the wireless
But the gnome shell environment is nice
What was with the error message you got about it not being compatible with your hardware?
I'm not sure. It is like a little dell laptop here. So yeah, it doesn't have an ethernet port
It just has wireless and you're not getting that error message now, or are you still getting that error message?
That's a good question. I'm not sure
So, I mean that was really kind of strange like when it was quite strange when he booted up
He literally got an error message that said it's not compatible with your hardware just trying to get to the network settings
Yeah, and uh, it was like a gtk air air message
Really really strange, uh, but uh, you know, but they've got a lot of great built-in stuff
They've got a tor browser. They've got an unsecure or unsafe browser. Do they have a bunch of great
built-in stuff
libre office
p2v
Life era. Yeah, I don't know about those things. Why the hell are these on my super secure distribution?
Can you give me a single justification because you know what those sound like to me attack surfaces
They sound like software that can have flaws. They sound like software that can be exploited sure
They're not a super critical software, but why is anything that's not necessary on my security distribution?
See I was gonna I was gonna say that but they probably need libre office because all those leaked nsa powerpoints lives
Okay. No, I think what it is is they are setting themselves up as a full-time desktop distribution the switch to gnome shell
The upgrade of libre office and p2v. I mean give me a break
Also the switch to system d like they're coming up now as a desktop distribution
That you can use if you're security-minded
I don't believe the two things hold up. I think what makes tails secure is that you only use it when you're in right like
Stealth mode when you need to be secure
You can spin it up and throw it away and just because it just seems to me
Reasonably so that the longer you use a desktop distribution the longer you make it more insecure the longer your passwords get cached on
The hard drive the longer your your web history builds up the longer you have a piece of software
You don't update or that a zero day vulnerability is available for for a stretch of time that you're not aware of
Like there's so much more
Exposure when you use a desktop full-time than when you just boot into it to do banking or buy your bitcoins or whatever
Right, right. It's useful to not have as a real desktop environment
Uh aco says that it's so that media creators can create with privacy. Yeah, but nobody's actually going to use p2v
So there's not that's not really why I mean I don't mean to be dismissive
But I just I don't that sounds that sounds like a really niche
possible use case that probably doesn't actually happen
And what it actually does is exposing everybody for editing
Family trips but for witness relocation, it's so that isis can post their latest jihadi. John 2.0 videos
That doesn't make any sense
It's just that's such a edge case that it's not worth making the rest of the distribution more vulnerable
I mean, this is supposed to be a security distribution. Am I missing something mumble room?
I don't think so. Also, I don't think youtube creators are going to use this to
To make their videos. Yeah
Yeah, you will be happy to know
High dpi displays are better supported. Yeah
Yeah, go ahead. Sorry going. Oh, is this a live cd you'd be willing to uh boot into during black hat for example
Yeah, exactly. This is yeah
It's that kind of thing or or like I say when you're when you're doing your online bitcoin or stocks or whatever
It does come with a bitcoin wallet
Yeah, they do because that's something you can use it for or you know
If you're going to communicate with a journalist for some purpose, maybe I mean, let's be honest legitimately
You could be a savvy member of the us military witness something that you think somebody in the journalism
Industry should know about and use tales to communicate with them and it would be a mistake to continue to use tales for other
things yes, it would
I just don't I mean, but good for them for the new release. I don't mean to crap on the new release
uh
They also are shipping the vivaldi browser with it
Uh, which is weird and they got the tor browser, of course
Uh and gnome shell, it seems reasonable in classic mode
It's pretty straightforward hard to yeah, it's hard to miss anything that you have there
Yeah, it's still a great distribution being based on debbie and eight. I think it's just a little confused
Yeah, so what is your impression overall of just sort of does it feel like a debbie inbox to you?
Does it feel like something different?
Yeah speed is good speed is fine. Uh, I might try installing it in a vm later and just play with it there
Yeah, that would be cool. Like a vm you could go into when you're doing certain things
You know like your uh, like your big bitcoin exchange enterprise you got going on the side, which is hosted on github. Yes
Well naturally naturally, hopefully it doesn't go down. That's a lot of that's a lot of income
Um any closing thoughts on tails good pro
Uh doesn't have to be related to them being a full-time distro anybody in there tried it before or is this one of those distros?
We all talk about but nobody's using
I've used it before been not for like a full desktop environment
I've used it just you know, do some things and then you know
You know just boot out of it to the regular os
That sounds about right. Yeah, it sounds about right
Uh, I would love to have somebody from the tails project come on the show. Yeah, that would be great
Wouldn't that we have an open mumble room our virtual lug is open to all of you even windows users
Even windows just don't say anything. We won't ask I mean probably sometimes we do
So just say when they're on when their audio seems to be working really well, then we get suspicious
I kid I can't
Bitter much no, I just I'm just joking. I've never installed gnu slash linux. All right
So before we move on, uh, there's something really big that has gotten a lot of headlines from snarky tech press about linux
Brick and laptops and and and the headlines have been
I actually did read this headline, uh
Ubuntu can brick your laptop even if you run windows
Isn't that a good one? Yeah. Wow. Yeah, I I thought that was pretty great
so
And i'm like, okay
And it's right as del's about to announce a new uh, new developer edition of the xbs laptop, too
Then we go come on guys
Uh, so we'll tell you about what's going on there and what actually and actually how you can actually brick the laptop
Now that is actually legitimately something you could do
Uh, but first let me tell you about ting go to linux.ting.com to support this show and get yourself a 25 dollar discount
discount
Linux.ting.com. You can also get 25 in service credit if you have a compatible phone and you might because they got cma and gsm
average monthly bill per device for ting 23 bucks
Isn't that something linux.ting.com? You just pay for what you use. It's a flat six dollars for the phone line
And then your usage on top of that I would suggest to go check a look at some of their devices so you can get an idea
Uh, so this one right here the samsung m400
47 dollars kiosara dura xt. This is the one that no has tried out for a bit
47 he says the speaker on that thing is ridiculous and the battery life is ridiculous
I myself because i'm a classy lady. I would probably upgrade to the ansetel one touch fling. It's new. It's got a camera
It's got an I think it's oled on the front. It totally has a cpu in it. It's a feature phone
And the more I the more I look at the smartphone landscape, I think geez
63 dollars for an unlocked phone. I own that outright. No contract only pay for what I use that
That's ridiculous. You can also get things like the motorola g
Or go all the way up to the really nice phones
In fact, like the blue studio 6 is a great deal for 181 bucks. You own these motorola g third gen 193 dollars unlocked
It's yours. No contract. You only pay for what you use no early termination
nothing like that a really good dashboard super fanatical customer support that rocks and
Geeks, they're geeks too. In fact, they have a blog post up
Watch the Super Bowl without table. Look at that. This is this is like I am NOT a sports ball guy, right?
But I cannot avoid the Super Bowl hype. It's a good excuse for nothing else to have some great appetizers. Yeah, that's that's true
Yeah, have great appetizers be judgy about the commercials
And drink some beer. So Super Bowl 50. Yeah, you guys all know it's upon us
And they have a great breakdown about ways you can watch it. Even if you're a cord cutter, which I think is pretty cool
They also have some internet fiber services depending on your location. Go check them out. We had the
Linux dot ting comm visiting their supports this show try out the savings calculator. See why I've been a customer for three years
Linux dot ting
Commit a big thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program. You guys are fantastic and thanks for the
MiFi on the way down to back from scale. Yeah, that's great. Mm-hmm
That's how I was able to listen to you and Noah do the unplugged show
Legitimately though. Um, I'm this is I missed I missed about 30 minutes of the show
Not because ting got disconnected but because at that point in time I was an organ
Mm-hmm, and you know, you know, do you know about Oregon gas? I do know about Oregon. What's the deal about Oregon gas?
What's the deal? Well, it's a it's a hazardous liquid. Yeah
Trained and certified to handle so it's so funny you say this because so we get down to Oregon and we're gonna fill up the
Lady, Jupiter
We're almost down to scale right? I mean cuz we got a lot of California is the next the California is the neck
Yeah, glory, ladies. Glory to lady Jupiter, California is the next state and I'm like, I'm gonna blow half a tank and
If I need a boondock, I want to have enough fuel for my generator. So I'm figure we'll fill up
pull off
thing about Oregon is
Like Wes was alluding to
You are not allowed to fill your own gas up
You can it is state law that somebody pumps your gas for you or your petrol or whatever you want to call it
And so we get into a flying J which is designed for large vehicles
Okay, and should have a high pump capacity we get into a flying J truck stop a truck stop
Because lady Jupiter is big and we need a truck stop
I pull in there I go over the ding ding and I spend five minutes lining this huge rig up with the pump
Which wasn't big enough and I had to be pulled way into the parking lot
I'm pulled way into the parking lot blocking the flow of traffic and I sit there five minutes go by
Ten minutes go by oh boy 15 minutes go by
20 minutes go by I'm getting pissed at this point cuz I'm waiting 20 minutes
I'm like I could go out there and pump this gas myself, right and I'm sitting there at least I'm listening unplug
So it's not all lost right 25 minutes go by I start the rig back up
I put lady Jupiter in reverse I go over the the court again to make the thing ding
I go back over the court again. I go back up again this huge motor back up over the court ding ding back up over the
court ding ding
So that way they hear like four times I do this, right and then I park it
I turn it off and I go outside and I wait for the guy he go. Oh, sorry. Yeah. Yeah, we've been real busy
Forgot sorry comes over there. It took it's a hundred gallon tank. It took forever
It took 25 minutes to pump it
So I think so not only to have to wait 25 minutes then took 25 minutes to fill it and I missed that whole part
of the show
So I made a declaration right there. No more fuel in Oregon. No more
We drove through the rest of the one that did not stop again for fuel in Oregon
I was not gonna put up with that crap. And so while we were sitting there in the chair like
We're like, okay. Now we got to know is the state law. What is the reason that it is?
2016 and we are not allowed to pump our own gas in Oregon
What is the reason and so then we found like the whole controversy like there's a for it and against Oregon drama and the against
It folks are like gas stinks
It gets on you it makes your clothes smell and it's gonna kill a bunch of jobs
And then the for people like it takes too much time. It was we fell into a whole controversy
Trying to get our dinner. Are you guys split on opinions? Oh, no, we wanted to pump our own gas. I'll tell you but anyways
Moving on from there. It's just a story from the road that didn't get get on camera because I was too grumpy
So let's talk about this command that can permanently brick some laptops. It is actually a thing
It is really a thing and some people are actually dumb enough to do this
So what we're gonna have to cover it now because it's made controversy and I want to arm you with the knowledge to combat
The controversy some fun may develop and we're gonna be the anti fun solution
So as all things that are relevant and important to the Internet a user posted on the arch Linux forms. We're all great things start
Back in January, which is still this month. I don't know why they wrote it like that
Wondering why their laptop wouldn't boot at all after running the simple RM
tack RF tack no dash preserve dash root slash so
Delete the entire freaking root directory
It's a fairly stupid thing to run such a command, but usually not destructive anything, but the Linux installation itself
And I've done this to myself sure who hasn't spun up a VM just to see well
How long will it keep kicking or a old install of like Red Hat 5 really mad at your friend?
And and it was like the first thing you tried doing it. Anyways, however, it turns out on some MSI laptops
It is possible to completely wipe the EFI boot partition from within Linux. So this is what's happening
It completely wipes it at the directory that destroys that gets destroyed is at slash sys
Firmware slash EFI slash EFI vars it stores information and scripts that the computer uses to boot using the modern EFI standard which
Of course once you wipe that out, it's like not having a BIOS on your machine
essentially and so because it's under a slash sys slash firmware slash EFI slash EFI bars
When you delete everything under root, you are also deleting that right?
and then it no longer boots a
Thread discussing the issue
The system to your repository on github is full of discussions between developers arguing the director where the EFI boot data stored should not be
entirely writable
How about just don't mount it writable? Yeah, that's not bad
So far the issue appears to only affect MSI laptops
But that's only because there are a handful of cases of it happening the wild few people are wild and brave and have tried on
Their own machines. That's a good point. It could affect other machines, but who wants to be the person to try it?
At how you know, I saw it. Have I told you my story? No, I was actually still in school
so this was a really really long time ago now because I'm an old man and
I
sat down at a Red Hat machine that somebody had set up for me and
I don't know why RMRF was a thing. I tried maybe somebody told me maybe it was in the bash history
That might have been possible. I did RM dash RF slash
And she was this it was this it was one in the computer lab
So it was a school machine and I was logged in as root because why not?
Somebody must have set me up looking back on it
I wish I remembered because it was such a pivotal moment in my young computer history because I
I remember watching the system fall apart completely degrade in front of me and I remember thinking to myself
This is a badass OS
It let me do that. It just let me delete itself and everything that's in RAM is still running
I can still like cuz it was some old desktop environment and the windows that I thought open could still be used and I remember
thinking
This is something I want to learn like I something that lets me delete itself and then continues to run until I restart
At least everything that was existing is like this is freaking impressive
And that was really like so then later on when Linux was suggested as an alternative to NT
I was like, let's give it a shot. That thing was cool. Yeah, it was like a real pivotal moment for me
Wimpy you had a story that I wanted to hear
well, I used to work for a Unix vendor back in the day and
When there were the conferences, you know, and everyone's got all of their workstations out on the on the stands and everything
We did used to go around and accidentally RM minus RF slash our competitors workstations
Really?
At lunchtime, you know when they're having a break just do that and reboot
something kind of equivalent from the technical side is when you're using Linux terminal servers and
the clients lose connection back to the terminal server
They still have x11 and any applications that were loaded in RAM, but they've lost their root file system
It's kind of the same effect and and what's actually really damn impressive and I haven't seen this for a couple of years
But I did see it a couple of years ago is when when the internet connection or the network connection
The LAN connection or Wi-Fi connection, whatever it is comes back online
The clients just resume keep working like in any in just no big deal
They guess there's yeah, there's some errors, but it's no big deal. It was it was like wow
This is a really cool operating system. This is really neat and I remember like some stuff was even GPU accelerated and it still worked
So yeah, yeah, there you go. There that is the that is the rumor this spring around. There's lots of news stories about it
And I guess it is technically possible just don't it should be noted that a lot of this the EFI standard lets you do this
It should work. It just may not be tested go figure was an arch user, right?
Yeah, yeah handles and also some of some parts of the EFI system need to be mounted read write in order for the stuff
to work
Change the very long. Yeah at your next boot things like that. Yeah
Yeah, that is a thing. That's a bit of a problem and it's probably gonna happen again
Okay, so I don't really have any action to take on this myself
Because I'm not on the right side of the pond, but if you are in London or in the area
You might be able to make an impact on the future of the unity 8 desktop
Canonical is posting on their social media accounts that they saw on Twitter g-plus and Facebook so far
They're conducting a research
And the research is a user experience research the studies about Ubuntu
Applications developed by members of the Ubuntu Linux community for the next generation unity 8 user interface
The research study is being led by Ting Ray Chang a user experience researcher at the Canonical or maybe it's yeah
I think it's Chang and it's targeted mainly at Ubuntu or
Fedora users yeah fedora users probably because gnome 3 I guess
Yeah, swathpedia that speculates. They don't know why
But anyways there, so they're gonna do some research and they'd love your help
They're looking for two for participants in a research study on a community developed a unity 8 apps in this survey Canonical
Would like to know what email terminal calendar diary and music after use as well
So I have some links to this there's a survey you can find out
and if you're in the area, they're gonna be doing a study at
they have the
Say it looks like it'll be about about an hour-long study, then there may be a cash incentive
Oh, and you get to talk about Linux mm-hmm. Mm-hmm, so we'll have info about that
the unity 8 desktop West
Do you think they have to nail it when they first ship it as default or do you think there's gonna be?
Capacity to let them improve do you do you think people are at a point where your premiere desktop can be a little undercooked?
I mean it does keep happening. So maybe I think it'll go a lot a long ways if they do nail it
Because people already using it installing it and if it just comes with like that's really first rate
Then you know all the better. I think they do have staying power that if it's improved in a you know
Pretty yeah quickly, then it'll be fine
Micah 68 says I wish they could do the user study more openly than London, but at the same time
What other?
Linux distribution is doing actual real-world user studies that we know of I don't know of any other ones
So at least they're actually doing some
That is extremely
New road trip, I I hope I hope
Wimpy, what do you think? I'm curious to pick your brain as somebody who probably is gonna try it out
How much do they have to nail this right out of the gate?
Oh, you're asking the wrong person really aren't you but I'm very interested in participating in this
So yes, I shall enroll and try and go along to it
You're not gonna try it when they ship it
Well, I'm already trying it. I'm already running
The converged experience on my Nexus 4 and my Nexus 7 and I'm trying out all the new stuff and have are you really using?
Are you really using it?
I'm experimenting with it. But starting next month. I'm going to go for two months just using
the
Ubuntu touch on a phone in a tablet and I'm gonna actually turn off and set aside my Android phone really
Are you gonna do you're gonna use the Nexus 4?
Gonna use the Nexus 4 and an extra 7. Yeah
So when when and when the new I did it last year and it didn't go so well
I did it for one month last year and it was hard work and
I'm doing it again one year on to see you know
It kind of sounds like what your answer then is for a certain category of users
They've already started they're getting close to nailing it now. So it's just gonna depend on who's using it
It's improved an awful lot over the last year
You know, I got a chance to play with it quite a bit at scale and I wasn't super impressed
But I was playing with it on a Nexus 4 and I guess a lot of the canonical folks there are using it on a one-plus
And getting much better
Were you?
Using it as a phone or were you using it as the converged just the phone. I was just experimenting with the phone
There's a really there's a couple of great Jupiter broadcasting apps and I was playing
Yeah, I was playing around with those and stuff like that
But I haven't tried it on anything as powerful as the Nexus 7 or up
They really all my experience has either been on the Nexus 5 or 4
so
I'm I'm gonna set out my criteria of what what I'm going to attempt to get get it to do and
Work for me because there are a number of things that I need to do on a day-to-day basis with it as a phone
but I think really the
Convergence stuff is starting to become
Like the silver bullet because it's really compelling
It's quite amazing actually when you connect your Nexus 4 up and you realize this is a desktop and this is running off a phone
It really is very good
So yeah, if you haven't seen that you're really missing out on the whole point. I think I could see it
I mean, I I do see the point of it. Yeah, I can see you know, it's something I have at home
I bring it to work
I hook it up and I have all my stuff there all my notes that I already had up on my text editor are still
Up on my screen people are already moving to laptops that are you know, but today today for example
They just got the full Chromium browser working. Oh
Oh, that's a touch in the converged mode. So not you know
I've sort of a full-blooded browser, which is that's really, you know important. I think
Important step forward. It's a shame. Popey's not here. I think he must be busy
But maybe another time you can pick his brains about all of this. He's much much closer to it than I am
So how do you just stuff just an observer? What do you square the user between?
So this is really interesting
I find it fascinating that you're so following you're following this so closely on the cutting edge
and then you're also
You know behind Ubuntu Mate edition, which is sort of like this
distribution that epitomizes the traditional desktop environment that is kind of so far away from convergence and mobile that
So, how do you how do you slice that? Like what is it? Is it the different workloads?
Is it different use cases? Where do you see that sort of lighting up?
Or do you think maybe eventually everybody who's seeking out a Mate type desktop would eventually go for a converged device?
well
so many questions, so obviously I'm I
am close to all the new
innovations and advancements in the Linux community just because I work on Ubuntu Mate doesn't mean that I'm
laser focused on on that paradigm
I want to experience everything from the Linux world and learn what I can from all the different projects
But you mean you really are investing a lot of your time and energy and life into one particular paradigm
Yes, and that's mostly because as I've said before family
Depend on having that computing platform, you know, and so that's really where it comes from and it's become popular in its own, right?
So I will continue to support it and back it
But for example, there was a guy at the weekend who had Ubuntu Mate running on a huddle tablet
You've probably not heard of those but that's some the Tesco supermarket over here. Hmm make a line of tablets
I don't really tablets and
He's put Ubuntu Mate on it and I have to say it worked remarkably well and I was thinking to myself
Hmm, we're just a few little user interface tweaks. This could be you know, really quite usable and another guy actually got
The Mate desktop via an Ubuntu CH root running under Android's and
Another one has got it running under
Ubuntu touch as well. So it's interesting that this convergent stuff, you know canonical
Er, you know pioneering this on their platform
With their user interface, but already there are people in the community who are experiments
Experimenting with other desktops and getting them to run under
X mirror and what have you?
and I'm not not sure that I
I want to try and turn Mate into a touch
Platform because that's a bit nuts, isn't it?
but I'm certainly interested in experimenting with all of these touch devices and particularly Ubuntu because
Android has become very entrenched in my life and I use it because
it was the best option five years ago, but I
I'm not I I don't want it to be the thing that I'm wedded to I very much feel that way too
So I've put a lot of effort in the last six months
Get getting to know Ubuntu touch and I've written a couple of apps for myself and I'm starting more and more to get familiar with
snaps and mirror and XMir and
That's something I'm definitely interested in in learning and doing more with
In the coming year, but that's not to say Ubuntu Mate is gonna stop or go away that will continue on its merry way as well
I I find it to be
Exciting that it's actually getting so, you know
We've talked about unity and convergence and all this stuff for it feels like three years now
Yep, but being at scale
I find it to be really exciting to be at scale playing with these devices and seeing real community apps created for like a telegram
app like a jupyter broadcasting apps and
Yeah, I was talking to Ryan from the mycroft project and he was there with his Ubuntu touch device and you know
We're talking about the pros and cons of it and you know for the most part he does
It and you know for the most part he likes it
But when using his device, I could definitely see the performance
Issues there and that's something I'm pretty hypersensitive to because I I just I have a very high expectation
but if I you know if I could read
If I could reconsider some of that stuff and if they could close the gap on some of that stuff
It might just be right just right and when there's a phone that runs it very well and you can get it. I
I liked the idea that was floated that to someone should take an Android device
That was this far into its lifecycle as as the Ubuntu touch phone is now and compare the two and see where the two are
And I was like, oh somebody could get me, you know a good idea of what hardware to use
I would like to try that has a little review is where it's aware was Android at this point in its development lifecycle versus where
Ubuntu touches well, it was sort of the gingerbread
Stage, wasn't it? Would you consider this gingerbread or is this still more like the like the
The well the Moto G or whatever. What was that? What was no not Moto G
What was that first phone called the one that had a little roller on I can't remember now
But it feels like because it's all since we've only gotten really one industry phone. It's like their first phone
Well, if you're talking about, you know device launches, then yes, it's closer to that
I thought you were referring to you know time of time incubating and being developed
Yeah, I guess that that would be they'd have to figure out those ground rules. Do you want to go by that rule or hardware rules?
Yeah, I think what you need to do is work out how many people Android had working how many people Google had working on Android
Yeah, and then and then because what you actually work out from that is that actually Ubuntu are punching above their weight because they've got far far
far fewer people
Yes have made you know pretty much a full fully fledged mobile operating system that with the convergent story in
Three years and I think that's pretty amazing
Yeah, you know people are giving up into a hard time about it and saying it's not good enough yet
And it's not quite ready
But they've achieved such a lot so it can only get better from here because the foundations are pretty solid now
I don't actually I don't know that like that mocking attitude towards Ubuntu. I don't know if it actually
exists in the real world at like
Beyond be I mean beyond internet keyboard warriors
There I just I didn't get the sense of that
I don't you know it's just to keep drawing not to keep drawing on the scale thing
But Ubuntu came up a lot at scale because it would become was going on and there was never any shame
There was never any oh
eye-rolling
And when like display servers which I heard several conversations about display servers
It would go X mere and Wayland or mere Wayland X or Wayland mere X
You know it was just like whatever like it was just these are the things it wasn't like this. Oh effing mere
You know there was time. Yeah, I think there was sort of some it was a community meme wasn't it sort of three years ago to just
outright
Slander Ubuntu for everything they did and I do think that those days of sort of generally behind us now
Yeah, it seems like it. It seems like it was not even a thing
At least in person and so then you still see some you know disro shame and things like that online
But I think the other part is is that people are looking at what they're doing okay?
They actually got something that really working. I think there's a lot of excitement for this upcoming LTS in April
Maybe so Micah. Maybe that is true. I mean yeah
I think it's still it's people that are trying to be funny
They're still gonna be able to take a shot at it
But I think people that are getting work done we recognize the fact that they're trying to get something interesting done and accomplished
I don't know. I I walk away from scale. I didn't really get the opinion that people shamed Ubuntu
I thought that was a good thing it and you know there are just a lot of conversations to about sent OS and Debbie
I'm really yeah, that's great. Yeah, that really seemed to come up a lot
So I it is interesting times and I say good for canonical for actually reaching out to
Actual human beings and getting them in London and paying them for getting feedback on using these applications now
What'd be really cool is if they published the information yeah?
All right, well let me tell you about something else you can get on that's a digital ocean sponsor of the Linux unplugged program
I love digital ocean is my on-demand Linux infrastructure
You can get a super fast rig and if you use our promo code do unplugged you get a $10 credit
Try their $5 rig two months for free
We were just talking a little bit ago about setting up a web-based IRC client
Yeah, put that on digital ocean do it that on do it put everything on digital ocean
They've got all the different distros. You'd really want on demand
Even free BSD well
What is that about? I don't know, but they you know what they got a great implementation of it
They got a great one if you use the promo code do unplugged you try it out two months for free in less than 55 seconds
You get a rig with 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte
SSD because they all SSDs
All SSDs a blazing fast CPU and a terabyte of transfer. They got data centers in New York, San Francisco, Singapore
Amsterdam London Toronto
Right by Alan Jude and Germany, which is actually a really great spot if you want to distribute to its neighbors
But they really really have excelled at the interface. It is a really good UI very straightforward and
Not only they have a great UI
They have a great API and a bunch of good open source code is written around that API in fact
I was just looking at some of the projects on there
They have a whole bunch listed, and this is just like a tip of the iceberg stuff and like things like a command
Command at IO can integrate using the API a lot of different services with that API
Oh that API the droplet your digital ocean droplet manager. I love that one
But also really good tutorials really good tutorials that help you get a lot more out of your rig
So they have one click to application deployments
So you can get something set up and really you can get you could get we were talking about setting up matter most right?
You can get an Ubuntu LTS stack
Set up with your web server in less than 55 seconds. It's not some weird custom version of Ubuntu
Yeah, it's just it's just really straightforward using great open source code and the KVM
Yeah, all the run on top of Linux
Which is great all sitting on top of the mess SD's and then they have these tutorials to sort of round it all out
So five dollars a month you get a great rig pricing plans are really straightforward, too
So if you want to take our ten dollar credit and just use it for learning or experimenting
You can break it down hourly like that use the promo code do unplugged at digital ocean and go set up a Linux rig
Go play with own cloud. I got myself the own cloud the bit torrent sink the sink thing quasi core. I forget minecraft
We have mumble for the the right
Installed free switch this how do I not mention the fact that we have our virtual lug on a droplet?
That's what makes the show work. I should probably say that from time to time
The mumble on a droplet. Yeah. Yeah, lots of core part of the show infrastructure. You think I would have thought of that
Well, you can try something out either
Little experience or lots of experience you'd be surprised digital ocean comm use the promo code do unplugged and a big thanks to digital ocean
Okay, Wes get ready for this one
I I hope I don't I hope I don't upset anybody
But I I got I got to ask if mint is just a little drunk it with power. I mean this seems this seems like
Biting off way more than anybody would ever want to chew in
2016 you might have heard about it. We covered in the Linux action show Linux mint is getting its own
Application starting with the Linux 18 branch. We're gonna call them X apps for Linux mint distros meant to work across multiple desktops
It'll be gtk3 applications with traditional interfaces. I eat no us, you know, what CSD? What do they call them?
Clients decorations with the header bars. Yeah
no client-side decoration header bars and
the idea would be that anybody could really take these on but they're really gonna be meant for the cinnamon matte and XFCE desktops and
this is part of the mince project of sticking to their guns and
you might say
Askewing new design trends they they say we've all witnessed the rise of the iPad the iPhone
This is in the mint blog and this has caught this great a whole bunch of new trends
But we will not be swayed by those trends
And so X apps are gonna be introduced and you know
I think it's is it Clem that wrote this yeah Clem that wrote this Clem talks about some of the challenges
He's run into with gnome 3.18 and things that depend on that and moving that into mint
it's just a big mess and so the whole idea here is X apps X app X apps and
My initial reaction was a little strong
I don't know. I wanted I wanted to kind of consult with the lug and see if maybe I was overreactive
Maybe there's a point in missing and I definitely want to pick wimpy's brain. So let's start with you wimpy
What do you think about X apps and what Linux mint is doing here?
I've got lots of thoughts about this
I've been very careful not to
Criticize or rag on other distributions and projects since Ubuntu Marte got started. So
Everything I'm about to say isn't intended as a bashing or a ragging on Linux mint. It's my opinion
So if anyone thinks I'm trying to dog on them, that's really I want to say too
I have a lot of respect for Clem. He's worked really hard and he's built a very
Very good distro that I raved about the last version
Yeah, um, I do understand where this comes from so I
I understand technically why
Clem probably feels this is necessary and
I'm active in my local community with small businesses and home users and I can also see why
They don't give a fig for these fancy new. Mm-hmm
Desktops. Sure. If you look at what's happened with
Windows a lot of people are really disenfranchised with with Windows now
These are
Home users and small business users that just need their computer to do stuff
They don't care for all of these redesigns of the user interfaces. They just want the user interface
is they just want the
Look and feel that they're familiar with so they can carry on their merry way
So there are an awful lot of people out there who don't move in technical circles
who are quite happy to stay the course with
traditional user environments, right so I can understand
Why Clem would want to do this and it's been a while now, but there was some discussion
Within the Marte and
Linux Mint teams and a couple of others from some of the other projects, although I think they may have moved on now
About one one idea was potentially forking a tool kit. Hmm. So looking at forking
GTK 2
Retrofitting retrofitting
Modernizing where needed. Yeah. Yeah, and the other idea was forking GTK 3
so that we could establish a
I
Use the word stable to represent a non-changing API rather than
Suggest the GTK 3 is an unstable buggy platform because it isn't the issue with
GTK 3 that a lot of the projects that are trying to write against it are encountering certainly, you know for full desktops is that it's
It's a moving target and it's difficult, you know with each new version of GTK 3
There's new features that primarily target genome 3, right?
And it requires an awful lot of work for the other projects to actually adapt
to those changes
So with that as a backdrop you can understand why forking
These projects to create X-apps is an idea and we did discuss this idea of creating a common
set of cross desktop applications and
At the time we were talking about looking at what?
Cinnamon required what Marte required what XFC required and what LXDE required and the aspiration was is that
all of those desktop environments could
Collaborate and work together on a common set of things
It's it's a sensible suggestion, you know rather than having four different file browsers and four different text editors and so on and so on
That you know, you will coalesce around a common a common set of applications
but then of course, there's nothing to differentiate them and
One of the reasons there's all these different desktop environments on on Linux is because
People have different wants and needs and they want to go their own way and do their different thing
So there was never going to be sort of broad
agreement from all of those desktop environments about you know
Which way to go on which of the file managers would be the you know
The chosen one and all the rest of it. So I imagine that's how Clem has got to
The point he's got to now which is to effectively
Go and cherry-pick different applications that are out there
And bring those in under this banner of Xapps
To use in Linux Mint to sustain this, you know, traditional environment
And I think you said at the weekend that you know
They weren't, Mint weren't keeping up they'd stuck their head in the sands and they weren't
Adopting header bars and client-side decorations, but by and large most of the other desktop aren't
The desktops aren't either. I mean Xfce have started to
Or rather Xfce, I'm not, sometimes the lines are a bit blurred between Xfce and Xfce
But certainly within Xfce some of the newer applications that have come along some of the settings bits and bobs that they've added recently
Those use header bars and client-side decorations
I don't know if that's a trend that Xfce is going to follow
Or if it's just for a few bits and pieces that they've developed recently
It seems like that would be the real winner here for these Xapps if if Zubuntu and other distros started to also
Yeah, as far as I can remember there was not enough engagement and obviously LXDE are going with Qt now
So, you know, they're kind of out of that that discussion
Besides Xfce, it's kind of just Cinnamon and Mate who are the ones they're talking about here. Yeah, I also acknowledge
No, there's two others. There's two others and there's this elementary and they seem to be they do seem to be
Adopting client-side decoration and header bars. I think I think that's their
You know the direction they're headed in from what I've seen. I think that's where they're going. But here's an interesting one
Unity is not a client-side decoration header bar desktop environment. Canonical have been actively patching out
Client-side decorations and header bars from those forked applications that Unity is built upon
And continue to do so, you know, I still see this come up in the um, you know
The Ubuntu desktop IRC channel from Qt. I don't know if that's a trend, but it seems like it's a trend
Ubuntu desktop IRC channel from time to time when a
A new version comes out and somebody has to go in there and refactor the patches to remove it
so
In some respects, you know Gnome is trailblazing this and it's not that the other desktop environments aren't keeping up
They're choosing not to do it
I wonder if uh, this isn't the perfect timing for something like this. He's
you know, uh, he's got to be looking ahead at at
At the desktop for the next couple years and going the demand for a really well done
Tightly controlled Linux based traditional desktop is only going to go up safe easy to use
Pretty predictable. I mean
Clem has been
very shrewd in the way that he's put mint together and he's clearly listened to his user community and I should imagine
This is what they want
But I think forking the applications is not
Not the way to go
um
It and this sounds a bit strange as somebody involved in Marte, which is one of those big, you know forking efforts
um in in some respects, I think we've been justified in doing that because it wasn't
initially it was more about
um, sort of refused nicks, people didn't want to adopt the new thing, but now it's more about
preserving
what was GNOME 2
uh and and keeping that, you know, usable
desktop paradigm available for, you know, the next generation of people to, you know, use
um
I think that just keep forking things and
it's a lot of it's a lot of work and
Uh, I think these XApps will only ever be available in Mint. I don't see that they will
They will get used much if at all outside of Mint's ecosystem
A couple of things strike me about this that make it seem like a a challenging long-term strategy
XApps
Uh and the avoidance of client-side decorations
So client-side decorations, like Tyler points out, doesn't look super great on non-GNOME desktops
I've actually not really had a problem with them, but then again, I'm kind of a fan
Yeah
And I want to make a difference here
We need to we need to be we need to be clear client-side decorations and the header bar in GNOME
Are two different things. Client-side decorations is simply how the decoration is drawn on the client window
And the GNOME header bar is a certain implementation of a client-side decoration
So the reason why that's sort of important to understand going into this conversation is client-side decorations are going to become more critical
When we move to Wayland
Uh and because it'll no longer be up to the X server to draw the decoration because there won't be an X server
So the client will be responsible for its own decorations. Hence client-side decorations
Uh, it's not just for vanity. It's also to support Wayland better
So what Mint is also saying here with these XApps
Is they're saying Wayland is not in our future
Maybe
Maybe that is what they're saying. Um, and what I would what I would add to that is that um,
All of the energy
Almost all of the energy in the Marte team at the moment is focused on uh, GTK 3
um, and
That we had a 1.10 release. Um,
April-ish last year. That was the first experimental version of GTK 3
Uh, we had a 1.12 release, uh towards the end of last year
And that was a much improved GTK 3 implementation still considered experimental
We've got 1.13, which is uh, just trickling out as um, testing tarballs at the moment
I think about three quarters of the components are
Out with um, 1.13 and with 1.14 to follow, uh early this year
And we're getting to the point now where we've only got a handful of sort of
Issues to overcome for for where GTK 3 is a really
um, targetable platform
unfortunately, GTK uh, 3.2.0
Has thrown a couple of spanners in the works. So we've we've we've tried to
We've tried to adjust our release cadence to match GNOME and GTK 3
And because we hadn't had uh, that many regressions to cope with in the last couple of cycles, but um,
A lot of stuff's busted this time. So it's just difficult just as we were about to
Just get comfortable for it. Yeah. Yeah, but um,
You know Marte is
Supporting GTK 3
He is supporting GTK 3
And we do have support for client-side decorations and some of the applications that I ship by default
In Ubuntu Marte
Do use client-side decorations
They don't look horrible
They just look a bit different. But they work they work just fine. They do work. Yeah, that's a good point
See this is what we're now
This is sort of I see three tracks in the Ubuntu based distro world
The heavy hitters, of course, I do not mean to take away from Kubuntu or Zubuntu or Neon or whatever
But uh, you have yourself in one corner the Unity default desktop
Which is going to be undergoing radical changes like we've never seen from a completely
From a transition from GTK to Qt and apps that are designed for both
Mobile and desktop and that powered by an entirely new display server called Mir
That's in corner number one, right the primary contender in corner number two
You have Ubuntu Mate edition where you have a traditional desktop paradigm, but is integrating current technologies in a very logical
Reasonable fashion keeping up right and then uh, but it could but that could mean in some circumstances
Your apps look a little different or things are just a little different like maybe systemd sneaks in there, right?
These kinds of horrible things, right?
But and then in corner number three, you now have Linux Mint 18
Which as Clem promises in his blog post will give you one button to make it look exactly like Linux Mint 17
So that way nothing looks any different nothing changes
It's going to be again based on a very long-term support and these X apps are now going to be a thing and
I'm two minds of this because it's like these are three very unique
And very radical approaches in their own right on in a belief of what the desktop should be
And so that's my first thought and then my second thought is man as a reviewer
This is really going to be a treat because now these are three very unique and distinct beasts
That uh, you know fully deserve their own review and in the case of mint, you know, i'm going to be using different apps
I mean, yeah, they're maybe going to be very similar, but they're going to be their own set
I mean, it's a really its own unique experience
And in some ways it is it is sort of like this. I know I should I actually shouldn't leave out elementary OS
Yeah, in the fourth, it's right in here. There's a fourth quarter west with elementary OS
The ring is getting full
And all there's a fifth corner as well because LXQT is going to be a thing this year as well. Oh
A new contender enters with the sixth ring
the six rings of Ubuntu
Uh, and they all are extremely fascinating all based on one
mother distro if you will
Uh, I just find that to be really and and which are all based on Debian
I find it to be really interesting the way it's all shaping out and uh,
Uh, I I guess in that regard more power to the mint team
I mean, uh Clem brought in more funding for his project than ever. I wonder how many of these there will be
And they might be good. I like I like nemo the the file browser. Yeah, it's not bad
Yeah, nemo's not bad like if they fit in really well and they
Maybe somewhat limited feature set and they just perform well and are well integrated and easy to use then maybe it'll work
Well, if you zoom out and take it to its ultimate conclusion
This is what well what's really happening here is these these individual groups are taking Linux
And they are truly building their own platform and their own desktop vision on top of it
They are not necessarily trying to make a distro that plays with all other distros
They are trying to make a desktop experience or a mobile experience in some cases
That is a unique platform all into their own and Linux is the software that is making that possible, but it's not
You know, it's not what's defining what it must be
No, it's kind of just at the bottom of the stack hiding away. Yeah
Uh, which is kind of which makes exactly or Chrome OS. Yep
But uh just a little closer
That's interesting time
All right, uh, we should go to uh this Dell Linux distro speaking of distributions that are uh,
This one I I would argue may actually well, you know what?
I'm just gonna you're not even gonna believe it. But first
Let's talk about Linux Academy go to linuxacademy.com
Unplugged, please. Why don't you go there to support this show linuxacademy.com
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and read more about a great education platform to learn not just about Linux
But all the technology around it i'm going to tell you more about that in a second
But first for those of you who've heard about Linux Academy before I should mention they have had recently had some major updates new courses
Ansible and AWS courses advanced AWS security. What's up, Docker and Elastic Beanstalk?
They have a new Cloud Cadet episode as a new series they're doing
Uh, and also I love it
They now have a mobile app they're working on but on top of all of that i've mentioned they have group accounts before
Taking it up a notch
Now you got big old enterprise accounts big old enterprise accounts west where you can have big groups and sub teams
Linux Academy is really stepping up to the next level here. So if you've got an organization
I encourage you to go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged. This is a great resource
Started by Linux enthusiasts who first thought well, how do we spread the word?
I am so excited about this technology. Let's go spread the word now
They they teamed up with friends that are developers and educators and they created the Linux Academy platform now
They've gotten some success
You might say I think so you might say and as a result of that
They've been expanding their team bringing their content up refreshing it keeping it current
They have an incredible system where there's seven plus Linux distributions you get to choose from you choose that distro
It automatically adjusts the course where which when we were trying to figure out how to Linux
We're like how how good we were we were running through ideas like this and when I saw this I was like, okay
That's cool. And he's like and I remember I was talking to Anthony about he's like, yeah
But it doesn't just change the course where it also
Adjust the virtual machines that we spin up on demand right as the courseware calls for it the SSH into it
It's the same environment you chose earlier. It's really slick. They have over
2200 self-paced courses. These are great courses. You can go in there self-paced
So you do it at your own convenience at a speed that is comfortable to you
And you can also set up timelines and reminders
They have scenario-based labs that put you in the middle of tasks common to everyday environments instructor help is available when you need it
They have graded server exercises. You can get immediate feedback. They have AWS training
So when you need to do something on AWS, they spin up those instances
You don't got to worry about Amazon charging you a whole bunch of monies
They have a community stack full of Jupiter broadcasting members live events where you can ask the instructors questions
Or get news directly from Linux Academy folks. It's a really great way to run an academy
It's a great resource for our audience and it's a super cool way to support our show
So go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and a big thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
I'm telling you that instructor help is so valuable for a topic like this. Yeah, no kidding
All right. So Dell is uh, well, you know what? Maybe they've been looking at Ubuntu snappy
And they're thinking to themselves. Hey, this might not be such a bad idea
So Dell is launching its own Linux distribution get hyped everybody get hyped. All right, I'll tell you the name
You've all been patient Super Dell OS. They're calling it OS 10
Wait, isn't there isn't there an operating system called that already? I think so. Yeah, only this one isn't with an X
It's with a one and a zero
OS 10 that's a little more clear actually
This is unbelievable
This is their Linux distro called OS 10 and they plan to make it a strategic operating system offering
Expanding Dell switches and their storage products OS 10 is based on a native and I like that they're promoting this
As somebody who's worked in the enterprise west. Have you ever heard this term before?
A customized hardened Linux kernel. Yeah, right
Here's a new spin. This is 2016 spin on this
an unmodified Linux kernel
That's stock. That's their marketing an unmodified Linux kernel
Uh that can support broad range of applications and services from the Linux ecosystems Dell officials say
Dell claims this differentiates from cumulus's network cumulus Linux and HP's open switch because this one's meant for open network systems
You know because of open OS 10 is I can't believe I'm saying that it's comprised of a base module
And various operational application modules
Separated to offer choice control and programmability. I'm gonna get me some of those application modules later
Yeah, because you get control. This is an alternative where things are bundled tightly
Essentially what Dell has done here. Tell me if this reminds you of something
separation of the OS 10 application modules from the base modules allows customers to tailor IT operations for different use cases and
operational processes
Dell didn't comment if they're just forking Ubuntu snappy or if they just think it's free BSD. Yeah, right. Yeah, right
Yeah, exactly. So they've got they're basically doing the Ubuntu snappy thing or the free BSD thing where you have your base OS
And the applications are separated out and the base OS is a read write or read only image and they're calling it OS 10
OS 10 maybe it's in binary. Is it one zero? I just
I just don't understand what's wrong with Dell, you know
because like at one hand Dell's like watching the Linux scene and totally into it releasing drivers and stuff like
It was this week. It's announced that Dell's about to ship a new XPS
Developer edition based with Skylake processors, which means they're taking like a hundred bucks off the Broadwell ones right now if you want them
Which are probably better. Yeah, I have I have the Broadwell XPS
I think my I don't know and I think it's a pretty good machine
I and and I would not get it with high DPI and you get a bunch more battery life and
Better video performance. Yeah better application support so
You have one hand on one hand
Dell keeps revving a pretty damn nice machine on the other hand
They're relaunching their own custom Linux called OS 10
What is that said I it would be kind of nice to run and you know
Be running a nice Dell switch in production and be like, hey, it's Linux and I know how it works
Well, I don't know how you'll see it though. We'll be caught your your binary joke and you have it. You have an observation
Go ahead. We'll be
So the first is they've missed a trick because I wonder if they're trolling Apple here and they're just
And this is just you know to get it out in the press and they'll rename it after you know after the dust settles
But why isn't it? You know Dell OS it goes to 11
You know you go back to cool back to spinal tap and
If it's binary, then it's some OS 2 so neither of them work, particularly well
The worst possible name, yeah
X apps is worse. But yeah X apps is worse. I
Jacob in the chair. I'm just asking if I'll update my XPS 13 to OS 10. Yeah, sure
I'll run OS 10 on my XPS 13 just ask me where yeah, it's just this just a train wreck though
It is of the pics. It'll be the top application. I know it's it's almost a joke
It is almost joke, but it is it is it is actually true
And I don't know maybe somebody out there have experience with it because there's your Dell OS 9. Yeah
straight to 10
No, that's that's what I'm wondering like is it just some
Something built for data centers that I wasn't aware of no
I've had clients that have had Dell switches and they did not call it that they didn't call it always no
No, that is that is funny. Wow. Well, there you go. There's marketing 101
We're watching it in right here. Just go straight to 10 the next show
We can we announce we just gotta call it 10 start with episode 10 call it 10
That's ridiculous. Well linuxactionshow.reddit.com. You'll find a feedback thread for 130 stories community out
You know like spotlights or call outs anything like that application modules. Yeah, sure sure application module separated from your base
OS those are welcome at linuxactionshow.reddit.com
Also, I'd love to get your help supporting the entire network at patreon.com slash today
We have a lot of big things in the works and we want to do it from community funding instead of commercial and if you chip
In Chris post a lot of fun updates on that page just for the patrons. Yeah, right just for the patrons patreon.com
Slash today. It supports all of our shows. Don't forget to join us live. Oh, hey there Wes
Join us live next Tuesday. We do this show Tuesdays live go over to the broadcasting comm slash calendar for that
We invite you to join us at jblive.tv
Alright, thank you so much for tuning this week's episode athletics unplugged now that I'm done smacking microphones
You get the hell out of here. See you next week
See ya
Oh
Alright JB titles calm let's boat. Oh wimpy. I love that. Tell me about your New Year's resolution
Yeah, so, um, I've obviously been consuming independent content for some time now
Yeah, it's true. It's really true and I was thinking about you know
New Year's resolutions and what have you like everyone does at the end of the last year and I you know wrote up the usual list of
New Year's resolutions, you know go to the gym more often. Mm-hmm eat healthily
Not my whole intake alcohol intake to 60 units a week all that sort of thing
And um after I did that, I thought no, I'm I never keep these resolutions
So let's try and think of one. I'm actually going to keep so I I decided right. I'm going to support all of these independent
Content creators and then I thought well, how do I
How do I do that? How much am I gonna spend on this?
So you might be familiar with the fact that in the UK we pay for a TV license. Yeah
And yet that supports the BBC
And yet that supports the BBC so I looked at how much that cost a year
And I took the exact same amount and I have spread that amount of money
across all of the
Content creators that I consume content for so i'm effectively paying the same amount as I pay for my UK TV license
For all of the independent content creators that I listen to and watch
That's really cool. Yeah, i'm i'm working on something kind of similar
I was looking at the price of satellite TV where i'm at
And I think i'm going to figure out how much that is and then first i'm going to contribute that to independent media
And then once if I can i'm comfortable doing that then maybe i'll let then you maybe i'll get this
And I actually feel like that's actually since i've done that
I'm more comfortable at patreon signing up on patreon. It's like it's all really like I feel much better about it
And and honestly, you know what?
With all the great set top boxes now
It's easier on the go to get online content a million times over than it is to get your traditional. Yeah, right
Especially for someone like you who's roving all over the place quite literally
Yeah, good point wimpy
All right. Well I finish up
I'm gonna ask you wes
And then you I mean then somebody in the moment room anybody in the moment willing can it can answer but wes
What would you do?
What would happen?
How screwed would you be?
If github shut down tomorrow
If github went away off the internet
Totally offline mildly inconvenienced too quite frustrated after after about a day or so
How would I update youtube to yeah
See this is the thing is I think the way would impact me is all of the open source stuff
I use that's on github that would be like offline like aur things would break
And now updates would get around mumber of anybody in there having thought how screwed would you be if github went offline tomorrow?
Uh, I think it will
Sorry fretsel go ahead. I think that
primary thing for the links community would be that um
Like for example aur a lot of aur packages pull sources directly from github
a lot of people who use go applications would be screwed because
go
resolves dependencies by
downloading stuff directly from github, um
I have for the reasons that there is a chance of github going down. I do have um
a private git instance running on the server that has a lot of stuff that I need but
But it would be massive inconvenience I would have access to my own stuff and all the dependencies that I need for my own
stuff, but if I
Want to install something completely new?
Yeah, it would be horrible. Yeah, that's kind of my take on it
Like it would be hey, you know because if you had a cause git it's git so your own code you see
Yeah, you have on your own machine. It's all the other stuff you depend on that probably doesn't have everything tamir
You don't have local. Yeah now free. So do you have a way to bring that mic closer to your mouth?
Because we're getting a lot of room echo and background noise on you
Go ahead will be
Um, well, I was just going to say that um, yes for all of those other dependent services
A lot of things would stop working
But if you're an organization or an individual that puts stuff in something like github or trello or bitbucket even
There are tools out there to back up
your stuff
So that if github or bitbucket or any of those go away
You actually have your own copy of your data
And a lot of people think that simply having a checkout of github's enough
But if you're an organization with lots of developers with with code checked out
That's not actually a recovery position
So, you know if you're using those services, you should be routinely
Um mirroring your repositories to your own instances inside your organization
So if it goes away, you can just repoint your origins and carry on
Very well put well said
Well, here's why I can feel that i'm slipping because I am coming up with more and more ideas to use slack for
And now i'm realizing okay
This is starting to speed up to a pace where if I don't watch out this is going to become irreplaceable
And I have learned that lesson
I have learned that lesson
So now i'm i'm putting a plea a call out to anybody who could help me get a mattermost install
Ideally i'd like to put one on a digital ocean droplet because that's where I manage all my stuff
I would like to do it there if anybody has uh
Anybody wants to help me with that?
I would love to chat with you because it's happening fast and not only that
But I have ideas that I want to take public
And it would just make sense to have people if i'm going to work with people in the public
It would make sense to do it do it on mattermost and not require people to sign up for slack and things like that
And yeah, that would be nice. Yeah
So i'm putting a call out there if anybody does have any experience with mattermost or a slack alternative
I know of I know like there's trello and things like that, but I want something ideally that would be on my own droplet that
I can take snapshots of and things like that. So wimpy you're gonna you say you're you're about to play with it
No, no not about to play with it. No, it's on the very long list of things to do. Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, I could see how I could see there's a lot of
I guess I guess I took I guess I didn't
I guess I didn't take slack seriously first and like it's irc and I have telegram. I have irc and I have telegram. Why do I need slack?
But the really nice thing about one really nice thing about slack. I don't even know if mattermost supports this
Well, first of all, it has a good phone app
Which is really nice because if I have an idea on the go I can just quickly open up slack and throw something in there
And it can include a picture or audio. That's super nice. But um, the other thing that slack really nails
And I don't have any experience with mattermost is
Switching teams so I can be an I can be a member. I'm like a member of three slacks
Right. Yeah, I have two
that is
That is so that way and I because for me it's all about
Divisioning off things because I work on things as you know
I have time for them and that being able to slice things up like that is really nice
You can just ignore one for a while if you need you just don't look at it
I have no idea if mattermost has anything like that, right?
So having heard of slack, uh, but never used it and having used irc and telegram
How does slack?
How does slack differ from telegram and irc?
well, so a few things that are nice about slack is
Um, it's persistent chat for everybody. So regardless of anybody's client setup
They're always getting all of the chat history that even though the stuff that they weren't present for
Um, it has bot integration which is actually kind of handy and of course any major service it has integrations for so
Uh, for example, we have a bot that monitors the google calendar and whenever there's a calendar change
It it sends those changes to a specific channel
Uh, and it also does a daily check of the calendar and post the recording schedule to the to the channel
And this has helped us. I mean, it sounds like a really dumb simple thing, but it has helped us keep the calendar accurate
It's like the thing that's helped us make the calendar accurate now is because there's a thread where we're seeing
We're have we have to look at the calendar every day every show that we do
Has a next thread so the next episode of that show
So that way we can we have a spot to communicate with the people who are involved in each of those episodes
Uh what we need to have in place for the next episode
And uh, what's really nice about that is if you like if you link a youtube video
It will it will preview the youtube video right there in slack or you can get the link
It doesn't do a bunch of like crazy redirector
Urls, you can just get nice clean
Links, uh, or it does it has uh, you know
Like support for a lot of uh, like you can just plus one a comment instead of having to say I agree
That's kind of nice. Um, it it has support for some offline functionality
And it has limited markdown support
It has like code snippet support and and things like that that are also
You know nicer than you get with any typical irc client and and regard and I guess what and really the thing about it
Is is there's a ton of good irc clients and telegram and things like that
But what you get with slack is every single person is on the same playing field as far as functionality and capabilities go
And then the other nice thing that comes with that is a lot of people know slack already
Just like like one of the great things about using skype is
A lot of people use skype one of the nice things about using google docs is a lot of people have a google account
Use google docs
And it's the same thing now with slack is you know when I invited west to the
Linux unplugged slack. He already had a slack account. He was already set up. Easy peasy. Yeah
Yeah, so there's that too. Okay, so so it is a sort of um
It's taking irc
And abstracting away some of those bits that you would have to have an admin set up for you
Yeah, and then and then making it super easy to integrate things like dropbox and google docs and you know
So like if I post a link to a google like i'll say okay
The uh, the doc is up for this week's episode of unplugged and when I post that link in there
It it gives it a big google doc button. It's obvious this google docs like it's so sort of intelligent about that kind of stuff
um
It's all and and I guess and then of course all you get all of that and it takes you a grand total of 30 seconds
To set up a team slack, which is also very nice
Right, but like anyone can do it
well, that's the other the other thing is
Uh, it's pretty much free until you want like fancy stuff like maybe private channels archiving of messages
Yeah, but even then like you still get an incredible history like it's still ridiculous 10 000. Yeah
uh, so
There is and then and then it's eight dollars per user basically after that
And and it costs you your freedom, of course
Yeah
And if you really want some of the fancy integrations
You have to have like a heroku account
And you have to host some of the apps on there, which means you're using another closed platform
But then you can really start doing some serious shit that is you know
people are really integrating like with their business workflows and stuff like
And there's like there's a lot of support for people who do development work and get integration and things like that
That I don't ever use i've made a few slack integrations. They're they're pretty easy
Yeah, like what kind of things?
Uh, like we have a an alert console at work for things that happen
And uh, so we just made it so like if you're away from that you wanted to ping you on slack
It'll just send all the new alerts new emails for things. We like share inboxes right to live. See this is the problem is
Is there is a community now out there that knows how to do this and if I go to something like mattermost i'm
I'm forfeiting that
We got to start making some mattermost plugins, I guess
Yeah, maybe maybe that could be the goal is to get enough traction publicly that people get interested to build that stuff
I'll help set up a mattermost server
Have you done it or you just you're just willing to take that challenge. I would like to play with one
Oh, no, I i'll take the challenge to set one. Well, you know what ham if you do it build it on a do droplet
Because then if it works you could transfer it to me then I could just start paying for it
Okay, sure. Well, I got some instructions on how to build do it on a ubuntu 14.04
Yeah, use one of our promo codes, right?
And uh, and you get so you'll get two you'll get you can try it out two months for free actually
Build it on a nicer rig. So do like uh, do like one with one gig of ram
Just that way because I like to do one gig of ram now
Uh, so do a one gig of ram rig. This is going premium up in here and i'll get you one month
To build it and then you transfer to me and i'll just start paying for it
I've already used your promo code. So they won't let me use them again
all of them
Uh, what's the latest good man good man? No, let's just you have okay you could use coder digital or last digital, right or uh,
We got here you got snap ocean do you use do unplugged use support this show snap ocean coder digital or last digital?
I've been pushing that do unplugged man. Good man. Good man. That's right. Anyways, i'm just saying uh,
Uh, yeah only probably only one promo code per I don't know exactly how it works
But either way or you know what for god's sakes ham i'll send you the ten dollars whatever it takes
but I would love if
I got a big I
Got something I want to do. I want to go big. All right, boy, that's you know, that's the sign i'm done
I might just walk out of the studio