Kind of funny this week. I was I was at a bar having a beer
You know like one like one does occasionally mm-hmm as a responsible adult. I'll pretend
And I was talking I talked with the very nice guy there. He just drops this bomb on me I
Grew up in a Linux household
Was like how is how is someone that I've never met saying this to me. I'm not at a Linux conference
I'm not in a Linux users. Well. You've got that look apparently look yeah
Well, he was asking me like I'm in there a lot like I'll just you know be working on something or show notes or whatever
You probably sell up over your shoulder. He may have yeah anyway
It turns out he didn't he doesn't use Linux currently
But I guess one of his parents was in the IT field so when he was growing up
They switched the whole he told me some stories about like he spelled play Diablo 2 which he liked a lot and then they switched
The whole house over to Linux, and he couldn't do that anymore, but he got into it
I guess at one time he was like a regular contributor on some Ubuntu forums
It was just funny because I had brought back a whole like a whole life ago for him
He didn't do any of it now totally had different interests
But yeah, I do think he did say he had some live CDs here live USBs
He carried around and I was encouraging him. He was curious about hey
You know what are the what distros might have not heard of that sort of stuff?
He was actually really interested in solace especially when I told him it wasn't you know it wasn't just a new derivative
It was its own first-rate distro
Yeah, so maybe there's a new solace convert out there next time if I see him again. I'll have to ask
This is a Linux unplugged episode
206 for July 18th
Welcome to the Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show
My name is Wes and joining me this week. Oh my it is an oh so special guest
Oh guys who is that the one the only the beardiest it's our friends Rekai the editor who keeps
everything going around here
Welcome to today's episode. We've got a you know. It's a special show anytime Chris is away. We've we've convinced him to take a vacation
Finally yeah out of the house out of the studio
We get to play do whatever we want so you know the show probably be a little bit different
But I think it's gonna be a lot of fun. We've got we've got some complicated things explained well obviously
I've been convinced that this is a good thing by my bomb the tech snap program by
Deep dive master Dan over there, so we've got some highlights of just some things. I think around the web that
There's a lot of complicated things that are hard to explain. It's always a great thing when they're explained
They're explained really well. We're not gonna go as deep as you know it will not be a dandy dive
Don't worry. We don't want to put them out of a job. We won't even talk about let's encrypt
So you just it's fine. It's fine
But it should be fun after that we've just got some updates from some of our favorite
Favorite projects around the web and maybe not so favorites
But they you know they deserve updates to plus. There's you know as always a couple news a new things to highlight
Enrique, I found a very interesting handheld
Project over on Indiegogo that it's not every day that I think one of these is actually interesting or that it might happen or that
It's worth talking about but
This one seems kind of unique and had some had some interesting things going for it that hey like maybe some new AMD
technology
I like the sounds of that
and after that of course because I'm hosting we're gonna talk about containers and
about the evolution of containers and how they've gotten a little bit more friendly a little bit more confusing and oh
So many more daemons
Plus there's some birthdays for our some of our favorite distros or not so favorites. We'll kind of talk about what does that mean?
What does it mean to be a distro in today's in today's world and what should you reflect on on these birthdays?
And if we have time I'm gonna pick the beards brain about some Linux gaming and maybe some not so
Linux gaming but before we get there
We should really bring in our good friends the people who make this show possible time appropriate greetings mobile room
Oh, hey guys, I didn't even see you there. I know they were just hiding there in the corner this whole
Time and boy aren't we glad?
To have them you are you guys how you guys how do you feel about a beard on the show?
I'm pretty stoked about it
Not bad awesome
Yeah, see there you go nice a warm welcome for his beardiness the beard
Okay, so first up today in our new category probably one time only but complicated things
Explained well, we've got a real-world guide to web
RTC
Talking directly from browser to browser sign me up web RTC just makes so much sense and lets you do many awesome new things
That simply weren't possible before anyway, that's the promise of web RTC
I mean we've certainly played with a lot here at the studio
It kind of promises to be that thing where you don't have to I don't have to super learn all of the ins and outs
of VoIP and SIP and all of that or have an ISDN line between
Studios do they have the part where they explain why it doesn't work half the time. Yes, so
That's where the real world aspect comes into this and looking at some of the discussions over it, you know people talking about this
I think that's the key is that web RTC has been talked a lot about how easy it is how simple it is to get started
distributed peer-to-peer all those things but
There's a lot that has to go on there's a lot that has to get right and it turns out yes peer-to-peer is important
But you also still need a server
And there's a lot of things you have to get right things like stun and turn and NAT busting and all those things just to
Get two browsers to talk to each other in a way that will work be reliable and provide like acceptable video quality. Mm-hmm
I have you had much experience. Do you use any of these, you know conferencing programs or just video chat?
mostly just hangouts
yeah, that's a
That's a good problem because most of the the other options tend to as you pretty much explain not work reliably
Yes, so they talk about here like what do you what do you need to get started two things a reasonably recent browser and drumroll a
Server. Yeah, that's right. So they go on to explain like isn't WebRTC all about peer-to-peer communication
Well, yeah, it is but these peers need to find each other
So they kind of go over like what all this means they talk about ice which is interactive connectivity
Establishment, which is a just a fun way to say
How can you actually get two people maybe behind that to talk to each other?
You think that eventually we'd be able to figure out IPv6 and get through some of these things, but no it's not gonna happen
well, you think you'd also be able to take some of the the
Info that the the browser itself has that where it's able to negotiate various connections to do some of this stuff automatically
But I wonder if there's security reasons for that. Yeah, that's a good question
So they just got some you know, we're not gonna dive any more into it
But they've got a lot of cool
cool details here stuff about data channels mesh connectivity audio and video screen sharing a lot of stuff like if you're just getting started or
maybe you have a pipe dream that you want to
You know implement your own WebRTC solution. You kind of just need some JavaScript a back-end server and a lot of time. Yeah talking about
The stuff like stun and ice it kind of makes me realize that WebRTC is really just sip in your browser. Yes, exactly
Yeah
We're not gonna talk about today, but that makes me think about
You know the the matrix project that we've talked a lot about before and I know I've seen them and there's a couple other things
Too free switch does some of it trying to marry that where you can, you know make a WebRTC call through a sip gateway
That goes and talks talks sip to another thing because you got to complicate it more
you've got to complicate it more but we might have a glorious solution where I can be on Wi-Fi on a bus and
Make a WebRTC call that goes through sip and then I can just ask Noah questions on his show whenever I want
Except that the connection will never be established
You'll never be able to have that or it'll be like really distorted and he'll keep asking and then drop me and
Yeah, I'll have to yell at him later. That's no fun or he'll get really angry and confused. Could you talked about Windows?
Oh, you know that happens that happens a lot. Yeah, I think especially with you. Oh, yeah
Mm-hmm. You just like to troll everybody mostly know mostly know that's why if you guys haven't seen it
Make sure you check out the most recent user error cuz that that show there's always something worth listening to there
And we try to make it worthwhile plus there's that sweepstakes, right? I think it actually just ended. Ah, I
Think it ended at 11 o'clock actually. Okay. Well, there you go
You were too late if you're hearing about it now
But I bet there'll be some announcements about what's gonna happen with that in the future. Probably in this next episode
excellent
Okay, so you're admittedly someone who spends some time on Windows, right? Yeah, that's true
So maybe maybe you don't know about this, but have you heard about the SS command? No, okay
Well, I've got the article for you beard an introduction to the SS command over at Linux
Dot-com news for the open source professional. That's us. I think right. Yeah, it's gotta be us
So Linux includes a fairly massive array of tools available to meet almost every need
from development to security to productivity to
Administration if you have to get it done Linux is there to serve. Yes. Of course it is. The SS command is a tool
Used to dump socket statistics. You may have heard of this in the past a similar capability was exposed in the netstat tool. Ah
Yeah, see there you go
So there's a lot of people a lot of people end up using the you know
The IP command which is the new new replacement for IF config. These are all part of the IP route to
library or set of tools rather
but I feel like a lot of people end up missing SS or
Actually just don't like it very much a lot of my colleagues kind of it kind of has a bad wrap around them or they're
Just so used to netstat net stats been written in British about every guide everywhere
it has command line arguments that you're used to reading simple to use but
SS exposes actually a lot more functionality in some ways. It's faster more modern and
It's gonna be here for the future
There's probably a lot of distros that at some point will no longer ship net stat out of the box
You'll have SS. So if you are on the system where you need to troubleshoot something
Maybe you don't have the ability to install net stat
It's probably a good idea to learn even if it's not, you know your program of choice
I don't know. I tend to use a net stat for for basic
troubleshooting but then if stuff gets
Much more complicated. I just switched to wire shark
Yeah, that's I mean that's right sometimes you're when you have to get to that level of troubleshooting, you know, you're in trouble
Yeah, all right. Well, I need Kappa packet captures. That's something's wrong here. Is that something you have to do very often?
No, no, I hope not. Although I did use it to figure out why our live stream was getting knocked offline
Because Noah accidentally assigned the same IP to a printer
Yes, I
Will refrain from comment, but maybe we already gave him crap. Yeah Linux action show
Excellent, and maybe that's why you should go check out our pre show where we've got a DHCP solution
That might be right up Noah's alley
Anyway, this article, you know, it's not crazy in-depth, but it does have some handy guides if you haven't used it before
I'm sure that's not many of our audience
I just want to throw it out there because you know
It's good to stay with the times and honestly, I've been using SS a lot more just like a conscious effort
It's really not too bad
It makes it pretty easy to choose between IP v6 or 4 if you just want to listen for you know
Listening sockets or UDP connections in the unconnect state pretty simple pretty quick
It shows the you know, it's easy to filter easy to say things like don't you know?
Don't try to resolve all my IP addresses show me the program that owns this socket that sort of thing
So you have some homework to do I think I guess so. Yeah get with the times beard get with the time
Contrary to popular belief. I do have a Linux box
So I can do this stuff. Do you yeah. Hmm. It's just the knock. Okay
So it's not as beefy as the the Windows rig. Well, it doesn't need to be it doesn't need to be right
You're saying that because Linux makes such great use of the system's resources. Yeah
Why are you grinning at me?
Why I never I would never
Okay, so there's still a couple more things
Really? I've just got you know, you haven't heard of SS. Maybe you're a mere BSD convert
You might fall into you know, the target audience of this next piece as well
System D for impatient sysadmins
System deep it's the in its system that some love to hate I think more than some actually
So full disclosure over here at tie blog. I
Find system D a little overbearing although by no means would consider myself militant militantly anti system D
It has obvious advantages and though I'm at philosophical odds with at least some of it
I see no reason why everybody shouldn't understand it a bit better
Especially now that most people will need to deal with it on their favorite distros
This post is sort of just a formalized set of operational notes that I've made frequent use of in my experience with system D
I hope this purse post serves as another tool in your operations sysadmin utility belt
We need to get solutions quickly, but are working with a system that relies on different tools than your normal sys5 toolbox
Just a note the paths and examples here will be drawn from Arch Linux, but
Most of them should carry over to too many other distributions. So really that I mean, I think that's it right there like
We can really get past especially for a lot of people who have to use this stuff at work or on systems
They didn't get to make you know get to set up or dictate all of the software on
Even if you don't like system D or especially if you don't like system D
I don't there's a lot of people who didn't like sys sys5
RC in it kind of thing you still had to use it. You still have to know how to do it
I never loved upstart had to learn how to use it. So from that angle, I think this blog is just a great post
You know, it's like a field guide. It won't teach you all the theory. It's not a man page necessarily
But if you just like I'm on the system, I need to disable services. I need to edit this unit file
Boom, here you go. You don't have to read anything written by Leonard. So you don't have to like
Strangle anyone or erupt into a ball of hatred and confusion
No, my friends just head over to tie blog here. I think it's really handy
I I can think of some people in my life that I will definitely be handing this out to just as like
Don't hate it. I'm not saying it's the best thing ever does come with your system now. Here's the system D cheat sheet. Exactly. Yes
Are you a system D person on your Linux box there? Yeah, I don't have a problem with system D
I actually kind of like it because
It's very easy to look at the unit files and see what what's going on
It's very easy to look at the unit files and see what what the hell is going on
Which I did not find that to be the case with sysv in it. Mm-hmm
because
Sometimes those were very complicated scripts
No, you know, I think I think that's true. There's a lot of the very as as he points out
There's a lot of very legitimate
You know problems with system D things where especially experienced
Sysadmins experience Linux users or developers don't like they lose control
They do things in a stupid way or dangerous way or insecure way, but I will say from the casual user
It's pretty easy, especially when like I have one. I have an executable. I'd like it to run as a service
Done, you know, there are other in systems that I should point out here that can do that
Just as easily as not a unique feature to system D, but it is a it is a benefit
I do also appreciate system, you know system control status on a program
It will actually show you if it's running or not gives you an excerpt from its logs
It's a pretty nice little drill down on a system. If you don't, you know, I will say also from a casual users perspective
The logging system is less straightforward
Yeah, that's for sure. Like, you know with sysv. You can just go and look at a log file, but with
System D you you have like six different commands to get different sets of logs that tell you different things
Yeah, yes, that's certainly true. There are there are definitely
Disadvantages and advantages to the journal and I think that's probably one of the most controversial pieces of system D
I will say I think both however are better than upstart. I really do not like upstart
I have there's so many upstart scripts that I've just never gotten to work and gave up on and
Actually reinstall the dis a different distro just so I didn't have to use upstart
Wow, that is dedication. I mean, I think upstart had a lot of good, you know, a lot of good things going for it
It was obvious. It was modernization. It was advancement
Yeah, but at the same time it was very it seemed very easy to break to me
Yeah, and it didn't quite I didn't enjoy the interface to it very much and it was yeah
At least on the systems I used especially around like a 1204
Period and it's kind of awkwardly integrated and confusing and the documentation for it wasn't very clear either
Yeah, I felt like one of those things where it was an awkward stepchild where it could have been the future
But then before it really got to the point of being polished and used widely system
Yes, exactly. I think that's the perfect
phrasing
Okay. Well enough about that because we certainly don't need a flame war today
Well, unless the beard once won he gets what he wants
Still in the topic of interesting things complex things explained well or questionably well, perhaps
We've got over on Kushal Das's blog. We've got a piece about
encrypting drives
With Lux. So if you're not familiar, you know encrypting hard drives
It's a common step that you see all the time now, especially on smartphones
Maybe on laptops a lot of installers even these days will make it pretty easy for you to get started
And this article I think is just a nice he's got some good pictures here that kind of
Sketch out some of the concepts that you're you're going to run into
Starts off write it off with an X AD X e X K CD. Excuse me comic, which is you know, a
Classics, you know, you know, he knows what he's talking about in that regard, but it's basically just a you know
A breakdown over you know, what is Lux its Linux unified key setup is a disk. It's a disk encryption specification
first introduced by
2004 by Clemens fruit with fruit worth. That's fun to say
notice the word specification instead of trying to implement something of its own
Lux is a standard way of doing drive encryption across tools and distributions
You can even use drives from Windows using the LibreCrypt application that I actually did not know that's near to me
So he kind of just goes through it this in this tutorial. He's using USB sticks
Which may be more practical for you know, a lot of people you're not
Not everyone has a laptop or a computer. They can just like I'm gonna wipe the disk play with encrypting it
I
would suggest maybe stay tuned for some of our sponsors later and we'll have solutions for that as well, but
Virtual machines USB sticks. That's a great. That's a great way to do it
He does have some very diligent notes here about you know, execute things with caution. You will be erasing your hard drives. Watch out
But otherwise, it's just kind of a it's just a great explanation
It walks you through things and hold your hands in ways that things like the arch wiki
Well, it may have more detail may have more technical specifications or examples
it's not necessarily for the first-timer it can be if you're an experienced first-timer, but I
Remember, you know way back in the day when I was first playing with encryption and you're kind of like well
What what's happening here when it's not like one command you're like trying to piece all of the pieces together. I
Don't know it can be complicated. So I think I would have I would have really appreciated a guide like this say eight years ago
Do you encrypt much over there? You got BitLocker on all your Windows systems? No, I actually don't encrypt anything
I don't really have much that I feel I need to secure. Mm-hmm
Anything I think needs to be secure is not on a computer
Interesting a hard copy man. Well, I mean
Nobody can hack into your stuff and steal your data if it's not there
That's true. And I suppose you're not you're not too worried about the physical security aspect here
Yeah, no, no one's breaking into the studio for your precious secrets
If they want they got to go through me and if they go through me, I'm probably dead and don't care
Most of it I think they're after is that large photo collection of the beard that you have?
No, yeah, various beard shots profile pictures. It's
It's highly sought after it is highly sought after. All right. What about you guys mumble room?
You guys have been pretty quiet over there anyone
Play with Lux or any other forms of encryption that they want to talk about. I think it's becoming
Increasingly popular increasingly used and now that people people seem to trust Libre vault at least a little bit
and
Been using it a fair bit. I mean it'd be more of a solution
I was literally talking someone in IRC last night in the JB IRC about like they wanted something that works on Linux and Windows and
Let's would work except for the Windows set apart. So bad. I'm not sure because I just lost some
Some keys, so I'm not sure if I'm gonna be Lux again. I'm debating it
Yeah, no that makes sense, you know, I've I've I've had some friends in that in that position as well where if you don't do
it all the time if
You're unfamiliar with it. If you aren't, you know, you've got yourself in a situation. We have a system that you don't necessarily understand how to
administer
Well, then you can you can lose data
You can lock yourself out and you know
You don't have a cloud cloud provider that you can call up and be like hey, I lost my key
Can you guys use your back door and get into my stuff for me?
When you do it this way, that's just not an option
I
Saw some some points here though. I guess no no disks has gotten a lot better in recent days at you know
Including encryption support. So there are a lot of gooey options as well for people who want
Encryption they want the security of it, but they don't necessarily want to master
Running all this stuff to Crip setup
Managing their Crip tab all of that stuff on the command line
I can realize can be done even some people or just extra administrative overhead that you know
That's not really what they're trying to do
But hopefully and as the author notes, you know, hopefully this post encourages people to use encrypted drives more
All of his drives are encrypted. Most of mine are not on my current system because I just reformat it, but
It is something I try to do on sensitive systems or on laptops, especially when I can and you can use Lux encrypted drives
With Windows now, can't you? I believe that's possible via I think it's Libre Crip
Yeah, I believe that's true. Yeah, and that's actually what the author notes here. I have not tried that
Yeah me either, but that would actually be awesome
Yeah, because then you've got a cross-platform solution as long as you don't have a Mac. That's open-source
Well, you can probably get it working on the Mac. Yeah, you probably could yeah, that's that's probably true
Okay
I'm using BitLocker on Windows, haven't used open-source last year
I had some problems with it, but Microsoft helped me solve it and for Ubuntu
I'm using whatever is standard when you press encrypts in the Ubuntu Mati installer
Oh, see, there you go. I think that might actually be like I would imagine so
Yeah, unless it's only doing the user stuff, but I don't think anything does that anymore
Nah, I know that used to be the styles like you could have your own little encrypted, you know, home dir. Yeah
But I think those technologies were largely proven not to be secure
Makes sense. Okay, so moving on
Do you ever have slow systems, you know systems that you're just not happy with their performance and you're struggling to understand why maybe
JBots not not
Doing titles as fast as it should
It's that memory leak Wes. Why are you gonna call me out? I'm sorry. It's not your fault. You can blame someone else
It's a Ruby's fault. Yeah, it was whoever coded that part of the code. Yeah
Just you know, not me. Certainly not me
Well, our friend Julia Evans who is maybe the one of the masters of explaining complicated things. Well
Just got a guide for you
Uh linux tracing systems and how they fit together. So everyone knows we don't have detrace
It sucks
It sucked since like the mid-2000s or whenever detrace was first released
We've always wanted it. We haven't quite had it and there just hasn't been
There hasn't been like a you know, the solution for that on linux
But a lot of workloads are on linux a lot of our systems, you know
Especially here at the show like you you want to be able to have insight you want to be able to understand your production system
You want to be able to troubleshoot them?
So I think this is a great guide. There's been a lot of developments in the recent years
There's a lot of different systems that have a lot of overlap and I think Julia does a great job of talking about
You know, what's what are the things that are going on in Linux that are going on in Linux?
You know, what's what are these? You know, there's strace
ltrace kprobes tracepoints uprobes ftrace perf
ebbf
That's a lot
Of things. Mm-hmm
I mean that's kind of that's crazy. So she's been doing some work. She went to uh papers we love
uh and uh
hung out in in montreal where I guess lgtng comes from
And she's been working on trying to understand how all of these can fit together
So you can split linux tracing systems into data sources where the tracing data comes from and mechanisms for collecting data
For these sources an example of this would be something like ftrace
And tracing front ends the tool you actually interact with to collect and analyze data
The overall picture is still kind of fragmented and confusing. Amen
Especially since some of these also fit into multiple categories like ftrace. Yes, exactly
But it's at least a more approachable fragmented confusing system
Uh, so here we have a summary in pictures and I just love this. She has great pictures. I really appreciate that
Let's see if we can't
Something like that. There we go. So
Linux tracing systems and how they fit together for data sources over there. You've got kprobes which are basically kernel functions
You've got kernel tracepoints
Uprobes which are user space c functions usdt detrace probes and lttng user space tracing
So these are ways that we can actually collect data inside of the kernel and in linux systems
Then you've got ways to extract data which include perf which actually perf is a great tool
If you haven't used it, you should definitely try it out ftrace lttng system tap sysdig
And ebpf ebpf you may be familiar with it's been worked on. Um
A lot by some of the people over at netflix brendan gregg in particular who's done great work on linux profiling and performance
In general, so I definitely recommend checking him out if you haven't already
And then you can see a lot of the overlap right here as as rika was talking about in the front ends category
You've got things like perf ftrace catapult kernel shark. Actually i've never heard of that one trace command
Bcc sysdig lttng and system tap. Well, i'm instantly excited about kernel shark just because yeah shark
I like that a lot
So, you know this uh, this article goes on and on because it's awesome
And there's a ton of great pictures and they really are worth
Thousands of words in this case and actually the pictures are like 90 words
So you can tell that it's a kind of complicated, uh, but I think if you're at all interested in this stuff
It's a great place to start it can maybe tell you some of the tools that you should look in personally
um
There's a lot of tools that are just not
It feels really inaccessible sometimes I guess
um, but
I've recently been upgrading, you know
Been able to work on more recent systems that have newer kernels and can take advantage of some of these ebpf tools
And it's awesome. And in particular the bcc project has a lot of pre-compiled pre
pre-built scripts that you can use to measure things like
Like um run queue latency or you can you know, see where see where things are blocking you can
Chart mysql long running queries based on query execution time
Or even one of the ones i've used just to troubleshoot some systems that I was you know
A system I didn't build but I had to go in and diagnose
Uh, they've got one called exec snoop, which is great and you just run it
And it reports everything that gets executed on your system
Well, they specifically say here that one of the newest and most powerful ways is to write a small ebpf program
Then ask linux to attach it to a kprobe
Slash u probe slash tracepoint and then the ep
Or ebpf program will send the data to user space with ftrace perf or bpf maps
Yeah, exactly. So I mean I think that exactly covers how
Confusing that is and why i'm glad there are guides like this
But like it's getting a lot better and there's a lot more options
Especially like just between perf and ebpf
Like there's just a lot of ways that you can get information that will help you
Start on this path. It does seem like a lot of them
End up glomming around ebpf. So maybe that's where you should start
Yeah, I think so and I think that's where a lot of the more recent uh momentum has been um
So definitely worth checking out brendan gregg
This article links to there's got a ton of there's got a ton of great stuff there continual development
So go check it out go profile some of your uh systems. Let us know how that goes
I think i'd be curious to see this evolve and it's great that we're finally
You know with ebpf and some of these more recent developments. We're finally in the place where we can build things that
Olumos and solaris have had for a long time and and freebsd and osx even
So we can finally be in that category and hopefully that goes a long way to
Making people more confident to run serious workloads on linux systems
I don't think there's any dearth of that now, but you know
There's old school admins and holdouts that are rightfully so or like well, I don't have the same kind of insight that i've had
on other systems, but
Uh on recent kernels, that's finally changing
All right, well keeping with this theme
You like complicated things but you need them you need them explained well
Just pop on over to our first sponsor tonight
And that's our friends over at linux academy. Head on over to linux academy dot com slash unplugged
There you will find basically the premiere place
To learn about linux and related technologies. They do it differently than pretty much anywhere else
They're not going to teach you how to maintain your garden
You're not going to learn how to repair your car, but you are going to learn from linux
Experts industry insiders people who've been doing this for years and who are passionate about linux
You're going to learn what you need to know to to get a job to pass exams and to be prepared to use linux
In the real world. Yeah, I will say I haven't used linux academy personally
But I have recommended it to some people that were looking to get into the it field
And they took some courses and ended up getting a job. That's awesome
I'm i'm kind of consistently
impressed that
People that you know, I don't that don't watch these shows that uh don't seem particularly
hip or even you know
They've been doing this for years. That doesn't seem like they really necessarily even need linux training necessarily
but
linux academy has gotten a great reputation and and totally deserves it because it's a great reference and it's
Employees are starting to employers are starting to recognize that linux
Linux academy is serious serious business if you can go get some certifications or go take some courses and show that off
Employers understand that that means something that means that you're a passionate about this and b you've gotten really good instruction up-to-date instruction
You didn't learn on some outdated six years ago distro that just won't apply anymore
You already know about system d you can do that and it supports some of the latest stuff like go check out their courses
It's awesome
They make it super easy to get started
They have things like a you know a scheduler so you can understand how long some of these things are going to take for you
If you don't have a lot of time, they've got nuggets which are just little tiny things little facts
I mean some of them are a little bit long. Some of them are like five minutes of them are like an hour
They're fascinating and it's a great way to just you know, you have a little time to kill you got stuck in the train
You're on your way to work and someone else is driving a nugget is perfect to increase your linux knowledge get things started
If you take a look at all their courses
you'll see that they really have pretty much any linux thing that you want to know and what makes them so different is
You don't have to do this on your system. You don't have to set up all this stuff
You don't have to worry about paying for that. It's all included and when you go to linuxacademy.com
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged you'll get a seven day free trial
Well, and even if you're trying to get hired at an employer
For example that doesn't know about linux academy because they're old and behind the times and they they suck
But you're trying to get hired there. Anyway
You still get the certifications and on top of that
It it becomes pretty obvious that you have a good foundation of knowledge
Even if they don't know what linux academy is. Yeah, right exactly and it shows that
It shows that you know what you're what you're doing and I think it makes it, you know
You'll be backed up because employers can go to linux academy and check out
What they teach and it'll I think it'll instantly show them that oh these guys know what they're doing
Plus they do things like, you know, they customize it. You're trying to learn about a red hat system
They'll make sure that the the vms they spin up for you
Are they the the distribution that you want and all the courseware automatically customizes for that?
So you'll be running the right packaging commands. You'll be running the right, you know, init commands. It doesn't matter
They've accounted for that. They make it super easy. And I know for me. I use it a lot both learning chef and
working with aws resources I hadn't used before because
I mean sometimes to model some of this aws stuff you have to spin up your a whole vpc for yourself
You've got a ton of stuff. You're getting databases. You're getting load balancers
That's a lot of money to spend just to learn how to do something
On your own time with linux academy you pay them. They manage all those resources
They help you do it and they make sure you don't waste your time
You don't waste your money and you just get the best educational bang for your buck
So go on over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
Get your learn on
I agree
beautiful
Oh linux academy, you really do make things a lot
Easier i'm glad they exist. It's kind of funny to think about like a couple years ago. They didn't and
What what would you do?
I don't know. You'd have to you'd have to go learn from some some worse resource. I think I don't I don't want that
all right, so
Now we move on
Yeah, read man pages. I think that's about it
ww
You read man pages, which is not a bad way to do it if you have the stomach for that
But I think it you know, it helps lower the boundaries. It makes it more digestible more digestible. Mmm
tasty
Plus you can't deny. There's some man pages that are pretty crappy. Yeah
Like I love man pages, but some of them not so great. Yeah, exactly could could be info pages
Oh, I like that irc room colonel panic. You're brilliant
okay, so
Up next we've got our updates section and this is just I thought we'd just take you know
Not nothing crazy long, but we just talked about a couple things we've talked about before on the show. So first up
How microsoft brought sql server to linux now sql server is not something I actually have had to use
Very much. What about you? Nope, I've thankfully managed to avoid very much investment in the
You know in the dot net stack, but I know a lot of people who do maybe that's what they learned in school
Um sql server is actually I mean legitimately a really good product
It's a great sql server if you have the money to pay for it or you work somewhere that does
um
And I know for a long time
They've had a lot of features that people have relied on
So it's interesting this article just kind of explains some of the explains some of the history
You know back in 2016 when microsoft announced that sql server would run on linux
The news came kind of as a major surprise to users and pundits alike. But over the course of last year
microsoft support for linux
And some would say open source in general
Has come into clear focus and the company's mission now seems to be all about bringing its tools to wherever
Its users are so they first launched this back in
Sorry, excuse me. They today launched the first release of sql server 2017
Which will be the first version to run on windows linux and in docker containers. I
It I think that kind of shows that microsoft's really they are trying to pivot to this cloud first mentality containers
They they use the word docker all the time
Now the docker container alone has already seen more than one million polls and I think they get like, you know
they really are trying to target developers with that like if I can just
I can already go like docker run mongo db if I can do the same thing for sql server
Maybe i'll start considering it. Yeah, exactly
Do you use docker much at all in your development work? Uh, not really. I I just run it in vpss
Yeah, that makes sense. Yeah
I think I think a lot of this too like they they talk here like, you know talking to enterprises
It became clear that doing this it was necessary, you know, we were forcing customers to use windows as their platform of choice
um
And it's funny to think about because in another incarnation of microsoft that probably would have been seen as something positive
But the company's strategy today, you know, it's it's quite different
It's it's interesting to see them actually think about you know
They acknowledge now that linux kind of dominates the server world and they have to
They have to play ball if they want to get a piece of that money, which they really do
Um, so this article kind of just continues on they've got some some nice graphics here kind of explaining how they managed to
You know change the abstraction layers change the architecture or work with the existing architecture
Of sql server to make it run on windows and linux and to do so really well
I mean, I think it shows like microsoft's got a lot of developer muscle
And when they actually pour it into something like this or similarly like the windows subsystem
They produce some interesting things even if i'm not personally using them
Have you used that uh subsystem much? Do you use that on your your windows hosts?
I've used a little bit
But I ended up not using as much as I would like because since I do do a lot of my development on vps's
It would be nice to have the linux subsystem there
but
I can't
Do sshfs because it requires a kernel module. Oh
so
It became pretty useless. Yeah
Your like existing workflows no longer really worked. Well if you're interested sql server for linux should reach general availability later this year
Um, but even today there are some people using it in production. So i'm sure we'll hear some more about this story soon
Speaking of another somewhat foreigner in our in our midst. Did you know rikai that
Zfs is the best file system at least for now. Yeah
Okay, well i'm not this is not this is not news news to you at all. No, is it?
Zfs is it's the best option. It's just too bad that we have to use it via dkms on linux
Because that makes it a lot worse. Hey, unless you're running the most recent abundance true
They've got that should compiled already for you, but i've also not seen that work. So
I haven't messed with it much admittedly, but
Yeah, no, that's fair. Well, uh, stephen foskett
over at foskets.net
He acknowledges zfs is the best file system, but he starts out with zfs should have been great, but I kind of hate it
Zfs seems to be trapped in the past before it was sidelined. It is the cool storage project of choice
It's it's inflexible. It lacks modern flash integration and it's not directly supported by most operating systems
But I put all of my valuable data on zfs because it simply offers
The best level of data protection in a small home
Small office or home office environment
Here's why
One does not simply return zero
Instead of one. Yeah, I mean that that that is that is pretty much pretty much how it works, right?
I mean you need a file system that has checksums you need file systems that
are designed with failure in mind and plan for that ahead of time and zfs is really the
Ultimate example of a file system with those kind of thinkings designed right into it
Right into it. Uh, so he goes in, you know talks about the zfs revolution circa 2006
um
When it first appeared in like 2005
It was absolutely with the times right copy on copy on riot had been a research thing that was now starting to see
general deployment
um, but he does kind of talk about some of the things he'd like to see be improved with zfs or
Things he'd like to see in a you know an even newer more modern file system. Mm-hmm
I know there's a lot of complaints about
It's not that you can't expand it. You just have to be a little bit careful or plan with how you'll be
You know expanding your arrays, um or building them. It's certainly not necessarily for the
Casual admin if you're going to be administering a lot of storage, I think you can use zfs just fine
There's a lot of fud out there about memory consumption or difficult, you know difficulty to administer
I think really actually the tools are really good
but
There are just you get to a point where you have enough data and you have to or enough redundancy or not enough redundancy
And you have to do things, you know appropriately zfs does have somewhat high memory consumption
But that's because it's doing a lot more than pretty much any other file system out there
Yeah, yeah, exactly
So they kind of talk about you know 2017 to 2010 zfs is to derailed and then talk a little bit about the
sun to oracle transition and the changes there
How that all goes wrong then he gets into what's wrong with zfs
today
So, uh, he talks about money remains skeptical of deduplication which hogs expensive ram in the best case scenario
And I do mean expensive. Um
And and goes on a little bit about how you know, he'd like to see a more first clash notion of flash storage
um, you know, there are things you can do things with the zil and l2r caches, but um
There are some limitations there which he gets into so I think it's just an interesting article
He may not agree with all of it. I think his conclusions
Are uh are reasonable for his use cases
But maybe a little bit over exaggerated the point I kind of took away was like look at all the things that zfs has
Got right here the things that we should focus on in the future
Where should we be taking what should we be thinking about for the future file system development because like it's not like we need
the next file system today, but
10 years from now. Are we still going to be able to use zfs?
Will it be feeling a little bit stale? Is it the kind of stuff that we can change especially in the way?
You know incremental change without breaking things but getting new features or at some point
Are we going to actually have to have you know, a new file system design not from scratch necessarily, but you know what I mean?
yeah, I think that the
Your willingness to learn zfs is directly reportionable
Proportional to how much you care about your data
The more you care about your data the more willing you're going to be to learn zfs
yeah, I think that's uh
That's entirely accurate. That's yeah, if you take it seriously, that's kind of it's kind of what you need to know. Yeah
So maybe maybe zfs isn't anything. Um, I will say even you know as the irc rightly points out
It's really not that hard to set up even on linux
You do on a lot of distributions have to compile the kernel module dkms tries to make that nice and easy for you
If I was running it in production, I think I would almost certainly compile
That myself and then ship my own repo that had those pre-built
I know on entergos you can just use zfs as part of the install process
Yeah, you can even install on root. I would not recommend that it often breaks systems
Which it's like you can certainly make it work
Um, but that's the category where it's like, all right
Well, you are now administering this be prepared for failure know how the command line works
Also, I hear that if you want to learn about zfs or if you're having issues with zfs
There's a guy named alan in the jupyter broadcast and chat room
He has no problem receiving any pms
About zfs. You're right like pretty much at any hour of the evening
Zfs problem 24 7. He's like a zfs helpline. Mm-hmm, but then you do have to say
Alan switched me to zfs, right? I think that you have to say that. Yeah when when you go to buy your file system
Is that how it works? Yeah, exactly. Yes
Oh beard
Okay, so maybe maybe zfs isn't your thing. Maybe you're not
You just missed the boat on that one. You're like zfs. That's so 2006
I want something new but obviously butter fs. I just don't it leaves a bad taste on my mouth. I'm not going to talk about it
Really? The only thing we've got going for us. Actually, there's a lot I shouldn't say the only thing but in the linux world
It's our friend kent overstreet
working
On bcash fs. So we've talked about this
It's kind of something we like to highlight occasionally just not not because I think it's going to be necessarily be great
Not because that's necessarily the future but it's one possible future and its development that I like to see
um
There's probably better ways to do it. I'm not saying this is optimal or
Going to be perfect
But kent overstreet has a has a great history of writing good code bcash has proved very fruitful and useful in the kernel
um
And it's just exciting to kind of stay up
You know, I I contribute to his patreon if you guys want to as well. I think linux needs to get over this butter fs thing
There's just so much
The license issue with zfs. We'll see what happens with the bun too
I'm not confident that we'll actually see easy to use or at least as easy as in kernel solutions to zfs anytime soon
But we do need a file system that we can use that's modern
Um, hopefully bcash fs can go at least part of the way there some developments here that I thought were kind of interesting
He's been asked a few times about the potential for porting bcash fs to other operating systems, right?
We were just talking about like, you know
If you can use lux or you know zfs is sometimes something that you can actually use that's very portable
If you can use it on mac and linux for instance
um
but
Nearly about 90 of the bcash fs code already built and runs in user space and is used by bcash fs tools
So the core file system code is more or less structured as a library
And bcash fs tools mostly just implements command line interfaces to it
So what this means is that most of the code is not actually particularly tried tied to the linux kernel
Uh, you know if most of the code already works and where's our space?
We're just we're kind of most of the way there to be able to run it on other operating systems
Well, the problem is the other operating systems
Outside of windows, which will probably never be able to use bcash fs anyway
They already have file systems with these features like apple is starting to roll out apfs or whatever the hell it's called
yep, and which has most of the features of zfs and
The bsds and salaris they already have zfs. So
Why do they care?
I mean not to be mean linux could definitely use it but it's true the portability. Not really
No, I think that would only be you know
If if eventually there were some open source projects that that took up that banner, you know
And then let you I mean it would be nice to have a you know, a nice file system
Yeah cross-platform that wasn't ntfs or fat
Yeah, that makes sense or xfat or ufs all of which have issues
I mean there isn't really a great
A colonel panic in the chat room says that net bsd could potentially use bcash fs
I guess they don't use zfs for some reason. I don't know. Yeah, that's a good question
We'll have to look into that. I'm not i'm not sure
That would be interesting. I would also love to see more, you know development of the linux of uh, you know
bsc file systems hammer 2 in particular see that used or at least
The potential of it being used on linux. Do you know what license the abfs is under? You know, I don't that's a good question
Let's find out. It'd be interesting if it were open and it could be ported to linux. Yeah
I'm not an apple fanboy by any means but
It's a good technology, right? I mean and they're paying talented developers to work on it
So you can't you can't really ignore that some of which are former zfs developers if I remember correctly. Yeah
Yeah
I don't see. Okay. Well wikipedia doesn't mention the license. Okay, so it's probably proprietary. Yes, I think so
That's unfortunate
We'll see what happens with that. I mean apple definitely does a uh, I mean they open source swift
They open source a lot of stuff. I think they're picking up on
On that this is an important thing to do. So yeah, we'll stay tuned. Um,
Um, hey, there we go. Hey tech map. Thank you. Okay, so there's there's some licensing link there
We'll check that out and have to update the show that seems to be for apfs cloning though
I don't know what that is or how it relates to the direct apfs code base
So it seems to be some sort of example code. Yeah, that makes sense
Yeah f2fs is another contender flash focused. I've used it a little bit but I haven't played with any
You know any of its necessary any any of its features to a large extent that something we'll have to play with more here
Okay, so another update from a project we've talked about before on the show
Wire guard has just gone through formal verification
Of their protocol. So I should stress here. This is not a verification of
Implementations not saying that the code that you run that runs wire guard
Has been verified. No, but it's still important
Um, if you're not familiar with wire guard, it's a you know, a new intended to be hoped to be in kernel vpn solution
for linux, um
There's a lot of issues with the
Complexity of current solutions open vpn is a huge project
Um that has has some known problems
And performance issues ipsec is pretty is pretty great and and reasonably well trusted
But is also very complicated has a large formal spec
uh and
Doesn't deal with key exchange and the key exchange itself is actually quite complicated in many cases. Um, and
It doesn't have easy user land support in linux anyway
Uh, so wire guard aims to have a lot have lower overhead have high performance be simple be built on modern crypto
And work. So this is a first step here. Um,
It's based on noise, which is a modern cryptography framework that you may be familiar with from
um, some some of the other podcasts here as well as
It's used in some of the stuff like from signal
uh, so what they've done here is uh
Yeah, they've they've used a software called a symbolic modeler called tamarin which I had not heard of before but it's called the tamarin prover
It's a security protocol verification tool. It sounds like a spice
It sounds like a spice. It does sound like a spice, but it supports both falsification and unbounded verification
In the symbolic model. So what they were working on here is proving that if implemented correctly the security model around the protocol
Is actually secure. Um, so the paper is a work in pro
Progress, but they are using you know computer aided proof here to try to show that the wire guard protocol is secure
When done properly and that's kind of the first step
Um, it will help audit and conformance of the actual implementation and then it it opens the future for you know, if you want to build
a um a verifiable in like a verifiable programming language something like f star
Um, you could build a wire guard that would be provably correct. Um, this is obviously very important, especially in
Times we see china cracking down on personal vpns
The internet at large is you know more government interest more surveillance more corporate surveillance all of those problems
It's important to have an easy to use
Vpn where you can get security, right or at least understand the security of it or have others understand it
Yeah, that's been designed from the ground up to be easily audible. Yes, exactly not have to go back on this
You know large thing that's been developed for years and try to figure out if it's proved open vpn code base. Yeah
So what do you think of wire guard? Have you used it at all? No
I don't have any uses for a vpn really
Yeah, that's fair. Yeah
I gotta say i'm i'm excited about it. I don't know but it's super easy to set up. I enjoy that it's
They make it really easy to implement with standard linux user space tools
um
And i've got great performance. I mean nothing i'm doing is like super performance critical where open vpn wouldn't work
But this is easier to set up by far than open vpn
Um, yeah, they say that they specifically wanted it to be as easy to set up as ssh. Yeah, exactly
I would say it's it's approximately in that category. Um, and so I think i'll I it's not in the kernel yet
Um, but they do have an up-to-date repo dkms builds it really quick. It's actually a very small module
So it doesn't take ages to build or anything
They say it's even capable of roaming between ip addresses just like mosh. Yeah, and that's the thing
It's like it's really nice. I've been using it for a while now on my laptop and it's
It's one of the better vpn experiences i've had because you don't have to worry about it
I don't have to worry about it. It comes back up wi-fi comes back up. I connect back up to the server
It's kind of amazing how it can handle so much while being so small compared to all the other ones. Yes
I don't I guess they do have the the bonus of being able to
Start much later than the other ones and learn from all their mistakes. Yes, it seems thoroughly modern and
You know, I don't advise production use of it
I'm not saying that you should go ahead and deploy it everywhere
But it's definitely something i'm i'm trying to keep track of and i'm excited to see future development. They do say that they
Make conservative and reasonable choices and that they've already been reviewed by cryptographers. Yes. So there's already been some work
They're trying it's it feels really like they're trying to do it trying to get to that the right part where you can trust them
Yes, exactly
We'll see though. So while i'm using this project, of course, I need somewhere to like put the end of my vpn, right?
That's like a thing that you need or I hear is great at tor, you know tor works pretty well. I could use my house
Uh, but a lot of times I choose digital ocean. So, uh, head on over to
Digital ocean.com there you will find
I'm, pretty sure your future cloud provider because it's cloud computer designed for developers. I mean really it's designed for admins linux
Enthusiasts anyone who's tired of complicated apis
Inane user interfaces or just paying too much or paying an unknown amount for a questionable
Service if you go on over to digital ocean.com, you can use our promo code do unplugged
Oh, yeah, that'll get you a ten dollar credit and when you find out that prices for their awesome droplets
Yeah, what what's a droplet you might say that is a vps in the cloud on real kvm hypervisors with incredible
40 gigabit e networking right to that hypervisor. It's like the rain cloud. It's just a series of droplets
I think that's exactly right
And the droplets contain little bundles of linux goodness or bsd goodness
It's all honey badger on digital ocean like an actual clouds where they only just contain water. Yes much better on the internet
Yeah, much better on the internet. That's why we recommend it so much
So you get like a ton
For that five dollars a month, right when you go on over to their pricing page, they make it super clear that
You don't know. There's not you're not like wondering about how much you're going to be spending each month
I I never I never worry about that at digital ocean
They make it super easy to do and it's it's kind of a bargain. I mean for okay you get the ten dollars
So maybe you just want to use that you're like, all right. Okay one free month. I'm sure I won't need it anymore
Actually, you're going to be hooked. So we're two months for two months. Yeah, it doesn't matter
If you go with the ten dollar you get a whole gig of memory
One virtual cpu which these are some nice cpus too. So don't don't think that that's some skimpy arm thing
No, no, certainly not 30 gigs of all ssd
Disc and a whopping two terabytes of transfer
Plus receive free access to services including monitoring cloud firewalls and more maybe that's not enough for you though
Maybe you're like, oh, I really need more from my provider. They've just rolled out
high cpu
Droplets, so if you're crunching tons of data really putting the cloud to work for your projects digital ocean is now totally viable
And they've done a ton of stuff like adding monitoring load balancers
Attachable block storage. They're working on object storage, which i'm super excited for
There's a ton of things that you can get that you can find at other cloud providers that don't have nearly the same kind of
ease of use
Simplicity of digital ocean. They've got an incredible api. They use it to build their awesome. Super clean super easy to use ui
We use it here. The api is super easy to use all the all the apps are super easy to use
It's just it's simple. It's no nonsense
It's easy to get started with and when you use it, you're going to be able to do a lot of different things
Easy to get started with and when you use our promo code do unplugged
You get a ten dollar discount. We wanted
To be able to turn droplets on and off via the irc
To control the live stream to youtube
and
So I asked one of the people that was helping me develop j-bot. Can you?
Find a way to hook up these commands
To j-bot to be able to turn the droplets on and off within
In 20 minutes he had finished the plugin
Because the api is that good? Wow?
That's kind of incredible. Yeah, I I like I I was talking to chris and noah about it and they're like
Yeah, that'd be cool if you could do that
So I went upstairs I messaged him and I came back downstairs and I checked a little bit later
I'm like, oh, I guess it's done
Wow, yeah, that's awesome and we use it like every day here. I mean all the all the freaking time
It's pretty reliable. It yeah, I think it is pretty reliable
so
Awesome. All right. We'll go check that out
Thank you very much to digital ocean for sponsoring the linux on program unplugged program and that promo code one more time. It's do
Unplugged all one word all over case. Oh and all those vpss that I was saying I was doing development on digital ocean droplets
Of course, so sly that's your secret sauce super cheap and no effort to set up
that is
Awesome. All right. Well, okay, but to set that all up right you do need
You do need internet right? Like you got to be able to get to digital ocean. Yes. I don't think they have
IP over paper yet. Mm-hmm
And you know a lot of these people a lot of people today. They don't
They've heard a lot about security problems
They want to secure secure wi-fi router
Maybe they maybe they went with the google wi-fi router, you know
It's been pretty popular these days a lot of people buy it for maybe loved ones or family members without looking at the chatter
Right now i'm going to say that they're probably saying that anybody that thought that google would be secure is
kind of dumb, but
And I would agree
I don't know if I agree
Yeah, I mean it depends on there on the product line, I suppose. Um, anyway, you may have had one of these
I know some people who got them or uh, you know, inherit them or are troubleshooting to family members
And I know for me, it's always frustrating when you're on like, uh, you know
Stupid proprietary router and you can't troubleshoot things. You don't have access to a console
You can't use all this linux knowledge that you've just gained or i've always had
Especially on super lockdown things
but
If you're on google hardware my friends, there is a new open source project called gale force
Which allows you to customize your google wi-fi
Router like the wind. Yeah, like the wind
So I guess the hardware name for google's wi-fi is gale
You know much like they have the hammerhead for the nexus 5 or for all those fun names that they have
So I don't I don't expect anyone to go out here and buy google wi-fi necessarily
But if you are already administering one
Gale force is kind of the best of both worlds
It lets you run your own vpn server customize your gateway ip address or do any other system administration sort of thing that linux makes possible
the bad news
You do have to get your hands dirty to put the router in development mode
You'll need a screwdriver a usb-c adapter with
power delivery
And some very precise button presses. So, you know fat-fingered people out there. Maybe this is the one for you get a helper
Don't let noah set it up. Don't let noah
Set it up
But this is pretty fun. Actually, I think it's uh, it's neat what's nice about gale force. Uh, it's that it's gonna keep working
Even if you get updates so it's not some sort of thing where you you know flash your router with alternative firmware
You're stuck. No, they've just kind of they figured out a way to
Unlock down things so that if you want root access you want to get things going you can but you still get security updates
You still get feature updates
It still has a nice ui that your parents can use. They just probably replace user space stuff. Yeah, exactly
So you can go check it out. Um has a github project
And that makes it really easy to get started
Basically enables you to get root ssh access so I have anything any extra features you want
And they keep mentioning this apparently with the stock firmware stuff. You can't customize the gateway ip address
Which personally that would frustrate me at least a little bit
it actually makes uh google wi-fi more appealing to me because i've been doing research because
As some people might know i've been planning on moving eventually and I was looking at uh, what the best way to do
Whole house wi-fi is yeah
And apparently google wi-fi is one of the easiest ways to just get repeaters and coverage without really having to deal with it
So maybe that combined with some of this more open stuff would be really nice
Interesting. Yeah, that that's what I kind of thought too
Is that yeah, maybe this is suddenly like we'll open it up to enthusiasts in a way where it didn't didn't have any interest
there before
um
I'll have to look into that. I actually hadn't looked at the hardware at all kind of for those reasons
I was like, well, I don't need that like i'd rather run something that I can actually, you know play with or or mess with
Interesting. When are you looking at moving or is this kind of just off in the future off in the future?
Yeah, that makes sense
Hopefully next year. Yeah
So i'm running my linux router still which has been working really well
And then I just this year just added a ubiquity ac pro which has been performing quite well nice
But I live in an apartment so it's not like I have crazy wi-fi needs
It's just like, you know a couple hundred square feet and then i'm set. Yeah
okay, so
Speaking of things the beard is interested in
You pointed this out to me and it's not all the time that we talk about an indiegogo
Indiegogo or kickstarter project because it's actually on both. I don't understand how that works interesting
but uh, yeah, so
There's this project. Uh, what's the name of it again? You have it up there? Yes
Smach smach smach z. Yeah, I think it's smock smock. Yeah, that makes more sense. So essentially it's a
A desktop pc in a handheld form factor
That's what the the pitch seems to be anyway
So basically it's based. Well originally it was based on
one of the the amd mobile processors
and
Some sort of amd gpu now they're saying actually i'll just read it. Yeah, please do. Uh, where is it?
It is over here
Uh, they they posted an update to their exclusively to their backers
But I happen to have a way to see that post outside of there. We won't talk about how
Uh, they said amd has kindly agreed to let us inform backers about their new soc upgrade
We can officially confirm that we are moving to the latest generation amd technology, which will be based on ryzen and vega
We are working together with amd to bring the best performance to smac z
So it will be the most powerful handheld console on the market
The new generation looks amazing and we want to thank amd for all their support and efforts contributed to our project
At this point we can't say anymore, but we hope that will alleviate the long wait
Because uh, this kickstarter happened like sometime last year. Oh, okay. Yeah, and then they they had a
um a partner that they were partnering with for the the soc technology back out
And because they backed out that caused delays but on the other side that let them work with amd to get this new tech in there
so it's kind of a handheld that's basically
a
low to mid-range pc in a
Uh handheld form factor so you can basically run
All your windows or linux games because you can install either os on there. Wow, and it ships out of the box with linux
Out of the box assuming it ever comes out. Yeah, assuming it ever comes out, of course and to me
That's the kind of handheld although admittedly still way too bulky for my taste. It is pretty big. Yeah, I will still probably get one
But uh, that's the handheld i've been waiting for a lot of the people, you know
They're like you should get the pyra or you should get the the pie top
Or all those mini boxes and laptops, but to me
This is the one i've been waiting for because it's got
new
recent hardware in it
rather than something that's like several generations old like the
The pyre for example has a resistive touch screen, which is very old technology. Yes, totally. This has a
six inch 1080p
Capacitive touch touch screen. Ooh, and look at those like uh, those big
But I don't even know what to call those the pads there for controlling it. Those look nice
Oh, yeah, it's it's it reminded me a lot of the um, the steam controller. It does remind me. Yeah, exactly definitely. Um,
Interesting. So yeah, look at that like powerful enough to play almost any game on steam portal to dota left for dead 2
To portress 2 they've got benchmarks there somewhere haptic touch pads the evolution of the mouse
Like it's you're not going to get like top-end performance out of it
But at least from the the benchmarks they did on their prototype you can play
Most games with medium to high settings on 720p for serious gamers. This looks like maybe something where you know
Yeah, it's not it's not your pixel perfect 60 frames per second that you get on your desktop with your sli card, but
You still have to take the bus to work sometimes and you can keep gaming. Yeah, so for people wondering the tech specs, um,
The the old setup that they were using they haven't updated with the new information yet was the merlin falcon rx421 bd
Which is like a 12 to 15 watt soc. Okay. Yeah that had four cores and an iradeon r7
Nice the 4gz ram. That sounds actually pretty sweet. Mm-hmm
I like that a lot. They claimed at the time that it would get five hours of battery life
I don't know if I believe that but maybe if most of that bulk was the battery I could believe that
I mean it is it is sizable. I mean we should be we should be clear about that
But it does have a micro sd slot a usb type c
connection and hdmi port and wi-fi or
4g lte connectivity
Wow, and apparently a front facing 5 mAh battery
Wow, and apparently a front-facing five megapixel camera because everything that is portable has to have a camera
Yes, exactly
Interesting. All right. Well, that's pretty exciting and
The multi os support comes with linux right out of the box. Yeah, and yes, I do believe it has a headphone jack
Somebody in the chat unfortunately, you have to ask these kinds of questions today
But does it work with my air pods? It's it's not a phone. Well, it does have bluetooth. There we go. Alrighty then
That's awesome
Yeah, so i'm kind of excited for that
So what do you think about vulkan then?
Are you excited for vulkan? Uh, i'm excited for when I actually start seeing games that are shipping with vulkan
So I do think I've I found two things around the net this week that maybe will help the first one was just some
Beginner friendly vulkan tutorials. So I right out of the bout i'd say you probably don't want to learn vulkan first
It probably shouldn't be your first intro to graphics programming. Um, just because it's you know, it's it's a lower level library
Maybe you experiment with some higher level stuff get your fundamentals down
There's a lot of math that you likely need to understand as well as you know hardware specifics
Uh, but if we want to have vulkan roll out and be successful and be adopted we need
pipelines to get devs involved trained up and be able to you know, make
Make new games with this stuff or new tools or you know, i'm sure also machine learning stuff. So
uh, stephanie hurlbutt
Recently put out a call for beginner friendly ways to learn vulkan for those who don't know vulkan is a new graphics
Api in other words a fresh new way to talk to your gpu and make it do things
It's managed by the kronos group, which means no one corporation controls it
It's pretty cool. Anyone wants to do work on gpus not restricted to graphics programmers
That's an important point in today's world should at least have a high level knowledge of what it is by beginner friendly
I mean that a total newbie should be able to at least understand what vulkan is and after some programming knowledge is assumed
You know, of course, no graphics api knowledge should be assumed
So this is just kind of a you know, it it talks about a little bit about what what this should be
um
And just provide some some really good links and it talks about how vulkan has actually kind of helped people, you know, like, uh,
Her friend dustin has writes that
So, how did I finally break through that wall of understanding? I'll give you a hint. It begins with a v and ends with vulkan
But vulkan is the hards. I hear you saying shouldn't I start with something easy like open gl and actually
No
Maybe you shouldn't the point is that vulkan removes the mystery
It spells things out plain as day and for a programmer. This is awesome
It's intellectually honest about what it needs and what it's doing
It will teach you what it really means to program a gpu
Don't think of all the extra code as a mountain to climb but instead as a clearly articulated set of instructions to help you get
Where you need?
To go so go forth friends and enjoy learning some vulkan
So they've got some links down here at the bottom that can uh, that can help you out. Um, you know
It's not top of my list of things to learn but uh, I think there are a lot of people that are and i'm really
excited to see what happens
And you know, maybe you try out some of these tutorials. You probably want to go benchmark your results
We've got some news there too introducing vk mark more than a vulkan benchmark
Ever since vulkan was first announced a few years ago the idea of creating a vulkan benchmark
In the spirit of you know, gl mark 2 for example
It's been kind of floating around
Recently, thanks to alexandros's employer
Collabora
Collabora, I don't know. How do you actually say that? It's the people they do. I think it's collabora. Yeah
Okay, that's what I thought as well, but you know, you got to explore especially i'm in chris's chair today
So i'm callabora. I'm kind of obligated to mispronounce things. I think that's how it works
I feel like that's a combination chris. No, uh mispronunciation. Yeah. Well, i'm trying to channel them
Yeah for inspiration you see anyway, thanks to them
This idea has materialized. It's now on gintub github. And the result is the vk mark vulkan benchmark
Like its sibling gl mark 2 sibling project vk mark's goals are different from the goals of big
monolithic and proprietary benchmarks instead of providing a single complex benchmark vk mark aims to provide an
Extensible suite of targeted and configurable benchmarking scenes
So just kind of a new tool set as you're learning vulkan. You can kind of go see what what does the performance?
Actually look like so I thought that was kind of fun
And since we're already talking about games, I thought we'd just touch on real quick
Something that we'd been discussing earlier today
Which is the pterodactyl?
panel
pterodactyl panel, it's a free open source game agnostic
game
management portal, what is pterodactyl?
It's a free open source game agnostic
game
Management portal. What did you think of this? I'd be curious for your opinion
Well, it seemed to me like it was a super easy way to set up game servers if I understood correctly
which appeals to me because I am a lazy sob
no, you don't say and
Anything that makes that easier is good in my book especially I don't know
Does it handle like uh steam games like steam servers?
If it did, that would be amazing, because Steam servers are notoriously difficult to
set up.
Yeah, that's true.
It does mention Team Fortress 2 and CSGO here.
Oh, so then yes.
It sounds like yes, yeah.
So Teradactyl Panel is a free, open-source, game-agnostic, self-hosted control panel for
users, networks, and game service providers.
Teradactyl supports games and servers such as Minecraft, ARK Evolution Evolved, CSGO,
Team Fortress 2, Insurgency, Team Spike 3, Mumble, and many more.
Some of those aren't games, oh, they're servers, yeah, that makes sense.
If you're a Linux gamer, you probably don't know, we don't mention ARK.
ARK is a bad thing these days.
You're okay.
Yeah.
You're right, I didn't know.
They did very bad things, like early access DLC and raising their price from $30 to $80.
Ouch.
See, this is why we need you here, for context, I really appreciate that.
You'll notice that it looks like you can even use the web UI on a Mac, so even though you're
not gaming on your Mac, probably you can administer from it.
Well yeah, you have your Macbook that you're not using off to the side running the website.
And then Linux is on the server, and then you have your Windows gaming machine, that's
how it works.
Or your Linux gaming machine, a lot of those are available on Linux.
That's a very good point.
So it looks pretty sweet, it's got a nice looking web UI.
The other thing I like about it is that since it's open source, you know, if you want to
see support for a new game, you can probably just go open an issue.
Yeah, exactly, right, like this is something we can do.
It's secure, it's themeable, Docker based, which is maybe a plus or a minus, but I should
hopefully mean it's really easy to get started with, that's kind of the whole idea.
It's free, open source, user friendly, and scalable.
So they've got a bunch of screenshots, I've not had a chance to play with it yet, but
as someone who does like to casual game, but is not always an expert at running the server
necessarily, just because I don't do it a lot, this looks awesome.
What I would like to actually try is see what, yeah, what does adding a new game look like?
If it doesn't have out of the box support, what are the hooks there, what is the interface,
how do I get that started and have it understand the new game?
How can I set this up myself, or maybe see if I could get somebody else to write that
for me?
Exactly.
Yeah.
So anyway, I thought that was a great development, might make things a little bit more accessible,
and maybe this is the final drop in the bucket where you've wanted to run your own game server,
you want to have a game server for you and your friends to play on, but you're not a
great admin, you're a little wary of having that all work.
Go check out Pterodactyl.
Yeah.
So I'm going back to smock for a minute.
Yeah, sure.
Somebody in the IRC chat room asked how much it was.
They don't have retail pricing yet, but at least when they did on IndieGoGo, the price
for the original version was $350 for the Wi-Fi version or 550 for the 4G version.
Also supposedly from what I was reading, some of the, or all of the parts are replaceable.
So potentially there could be upgrades in the future to like the GPU and CPU.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
And just as an aside, it's a group of Spanish people doing this particular project, which
is something you don't often see.
No, totally.
So go support it.
Yeah.
We need a nice diverse community of people making these awesome handhelds.
So does our very quiet mumble room have anything to say about any of this stuff?
That's a good question.
Yeah.
I guess that's enough.
I was about to say about the VKMark.
It sounds like a wonderful set of tools to develop Vulkan based games, just to continuously
figure out how to get away all the things that are stunting performance and just streamlining
development.
Yeah, exactly.
And maybe something you can set up and maybe not quite continuous, but some sort of pipeline
that as you're going, you can keep track of what does this look like?
Make sure you don't have any performance regressions or get an idea as you're experimenting with
new techniques.
Sure.
If it's something we'll see integrated into the Ferronics test suite at some point.
Oh, that's a good question.
So they can test more Vulkan-y things.
Yeah, as that continues to roll out, interesting.
Anyone else have any thoughts?
None of these guys are gamers.
That's true.
It's not something we always talk about, but yeah.
Also Vulkan actually had an update last week, so I'm surprised you guys didn't see that
with new extensions and some parts of it are promoted to stable, so that's also good.
So hopefully they'll announce some more stuff at SIGGRAPH 2017 in a little while, but outside
of that, not much else.
I'm just waiting to see the first breakout hit game that runs on Vulkan primarily.
That still hasn't really happened.
I know it's still like everything has Vulkan as an option, so you kind of really want just
something that runs on Vulkan.
It's easy to port over so that it can run on Linux.
Yeah, exactly, exactly.
Well, so we were just talking about trying to make these things easy, trying to make
them simple to use.
I think that just leads us right into our final sponsor this evening, which is our friends
over at Ting.
Head on over to linux.ting.com to discover a smarter way to do mobile.
Did you know, Rekai, that the average Ting bill is just $23 per phone per month?
Seems unbelievable, right?
That seems crazy.
Have you ever been on any of those big name carriers with their unlimited data plans?
Yeah, especially T-Mobile.
I'm not a fan of T-Mobile.
They charge a lot of money for not a lot of stuff.
And it puts you in the position of trying to figure that out, right?
You're like, okay, well, the cheapest plan I can get is X, and I assure you X is more
than $23.
I have to make sure that I stay within that limit, otherwise I'll get charged a boatload
more.
Yeah, either you get charged a ton more.
Ten kilobytes over.
Or you're in the position of like, I got to try to use my data because I paid for this
much.
I'm just not getting the good deal with it.
Or you want only data, but all of the plans tack on minutes and messages that cost a bunch
of money.
My friends, this is just a bad way to do mobile.
Go on over to linux.ting.com and find mobile that just makes sense.
It's mobile a la carte.
So if you're curious what the beard's talking about here, just go on over to the rates page
and you will see exactly.
Turns out you only pay for what you use.
Each line starts at $6 a month.
Now there may be some taxes and fees.
That depends on your locality.
Ting can't do anything about that.
That's just a fact of life.
But they'll charge you $6 per line.
Two lines, just $12.
It scales just like that.
It's so simple.
It's easy to understand.
And if you have a line you just want to hang around, you're not sure if you're going to
need it or not, $6 is like nothing.
That's less than a sandwich.
I could be wrong, but I think that $6 is actually to cover those taxes and fees.
That may be true.
Even better.
But don't quote me on that.
I could be wrong.
Don't quote us on anything.
That's just not cool.
But after that, you just tally up how many minutes you've used, how many megabytes and
how many messages.
Probably no messages.
Maybe a few minutes.
It depends.
Sometimes people call you.
Nothing you can do about that.
But it doesn't matter because you just pay for what you use.
So let's say you just, you know, a little bit of messages or a little bit of minutes,
you know, just to cover it.
A little bit of messages, same reason.
And then a whole bunch of data.
You're still only using $32 a month.
And that's all of it.
You get three-way calling, tethering.
That's included.
You don't have to pay extra.
There's no limits.
There's no special tethering budget.
And there's no early termination fees, no overages, no weird, strange extra fees.
It just is simple.
You can bring your own device.
They support both CDMA and GSM, which is pretty much all of your options here in the U.S.
So you'll be covered.
And honestly, that's great because I know at my parents' house, CDMA is king.
But in the city, for whatever reason, GSM ends up being a lot better.
So it's super simple to keep those, you know, we can all be on Ting.
It doesn't matter.
It's the thing that works for where you're at the most.
Or for just $6 a month, maybe you have an extra phone or an extra SIM hanging around.
Totally worth it for $6 a month.
You can bring your own device or shop their devices.
Did I mention?
No, I did not.
But I should have, when you go to linux.ting.com, you'll get a $25 service credit.
So that will probably pay for the majority, if not all, of your first month.
Or you can use it on one of these shiny new phones.
It's cheap enough that you could have like an emergency backup phone for when you lose
your main phone, tossed away in a drawer.
And if you lose your phone, well, here's your other phone already ready and ready to go.
And the Ting interface is so easy.
Whether you're using their app or their web interface, it's just super simple to do that.
It's super simple to activate or deactivate or register a new phone.
I will say that if you use Ting smartly, your boss that has your phone on a business line
because I have my phone on a business line because I don't use my phone much, he'll forget
that he even has, that he's even paying for your phone because it's that cheap.
Like I mostly use my phone on Wi-Fi, so there's not much data and I make like maybe a dozen
calls a year at most.
Yep.
Mostly to harass me because I didn't finish the text snapshot notes.
Yeah.
Well, no, those are usually text messages.
True.
When you don't have weird blocking things that don't let me talk to you.
But yeah, I barely hit 10 bucks a month at most.
That's awesome.
And that's not something you could do on like any other carrier.
That's the thing.
Yeah.
And Ting doesn't have to focus on like building new poles or lines or anything.
They can focus on keeping things simple and customer service.
So whether you want to pick up the new Samsung Galaxy 8 or just bring your crappy burner phone,
it doesn't matter.
It's super simple, linux.ting.com and thank you to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged
program.
Ting's pretty great.
Yeah.
I mean, it's just so easy.
The only time Chris notices that I'm even on the JB Ting account is when I go home for
a week and I actually have to use the data because Maine has no internet.
Maine has no internet.
Yikes.
All right, well, I guess it'll be time for tech snap soon so we should probably get out
of here.
But before we do, I just wanted to talk about a couple of things real quick on our way out.
The first of which is it's a little bit late now, I know.
Happy birthday, Slackware, 24 years of awesomeness.
That's pretty cool.
Something I learned about Chris last week because he's never used Slackware.
Never?
Never.
Really?
Apparently he skipped that phase.
Just wasn't a Slackware person.
He ended up on Gentoo, but he's never tried Slackware.
That's hilarious.
He was going to try Slackware at some point, but then he took the Arch challenge and started
using Arch and never used it.
Never got back to Slack, huh?
Yeah.
What about you?
I used it in the 90s and not since then.
But I respect people that use Slackware.
Yeah, I think you have to really.
It's a very different kind of distribution.
It is.
And it's the kind of thing that, especially in the Linux community, we shouldn't be focused
on conformity or trying to press people into our favorite boxes.
So like you're saying, it's great.
Slackware offers a particular thing.
It's a different kind of minimalism.
It's a different kind of minimalism, but I think one that I can certainly respect.
People who use it know what they're doing and understand the distribution that they're
using.
And I think that's great.
Anyone in the moment room want to chime in about Slackware?
We got any Slack fans here or people who got some good stories?
Still haven't used it.
So I'm with Chris.
Magic was popular in my day.
So you know.
I feel like if you haven't used Slackware, you're missing a bit of the Linux experience.
Yeah, you know, that may be true.
It is the first distro, if I remember correctly.
Is that right?
I think that's right.
Let's just find out, folks.
Or at least the oldest still existing distro.
Yeah.
Okay.
I think it's 2015, which is slightly out of date.
But I don't see how that would change because Slackware is still around.
So the oldest currently existing Linux distribution is Slackware.
Awesome.
I haven't used it that much myself, but my web hoster is using it.
So whenever SFTP files, PHP and HTML files, the web hoster company is using it.
And I have a couple of friends that use it, but I haven't used it myself as a client
or server.
That's interesting.
Other than using it on other servers.
I would not have expected a web host to use Slackware.
That seems peculiar.
I like it, but it's peculiar.
Yeah.
The Swedish web hosting company FS Data from Skne using Slackware.
I found out what they're doing, like cat etc. and catting files and stuff.
Interesting.
I wonder why they chose Slackware.
You know, I could see it from some, you know, it's kind of like some people who use this,
like Gentoo, for instance, where if you really, if you're doing something special or you have
a particular way or you're really knowledgeable and you know what you're doing, you know,
it might be customized enough that you can get what you need without all the bloat.
Or it just might be that web host.
That's what they know.
Yeah.
Might be comfortable with it.
All right.
Well, then Slack is great.
Keep using Slackware.
Some, another birthday, not really a birthday, but a release that we should talk about just
real quick on the way out here, Magia 6.
It's finally ready to shine.
The whole Magia community is extremely happy to announce the release of Magia 6, the shining
result of our longest release cycle so far.
Comes with many new and exciting features, a new range of installation media and the
usability and stability that can be expected from any Magia release.
So are you excited?
I have not heard about Magia in so long that I forgot everything about it.
So I will have to say no.
Luckily for you, if you're a little concerned, we do in the show notes, we will have a link
back to an article from 2010 called Forking Mandriva Linux.
The birth of Magia.
Oh, right.
It's the Mandriva fork.
Yep.
Mandriva, one of my favorite Linux distributions has been forked and the new distribution is
named Magia.
Mandriva is no longer around, right?
I believe that is the case.
Yes.
And so Magia is what lives on.
It's a fork that's outlived.
It's fork-y?
Yes.
Before that time, there was Mandrake.
And then Mandrake before that.
Yeah.
And before that, that was forked from the Red Hat stuff.
There is a fork called Open Mandriva.
Oh, nice.
Interesting.
I haven't checked on it.
That's much other than seeing it on Distro Watch.
So some of Magia's gold...
This is Rosa Laff.
Oh, go on.
Oh, Rosa Laff.
Got it.
So some of Magia's gold...
Rosa Laff.
Yeah.
So some of Magia's gold when they launched...
That makes sense.
We're to make Linux and free software straightforward to use for everyone, provide integrated system
configuration tools, keep a high level of integration between the base system, the desktop
and applications, especially to improve third-party integration, be it free or proprietary, target
new architectures and form factors, and improve our understanding of computers and electronic
device users.
So the thing with that list is it sounds like the same list that every other fork has.
It does kind of.
So my question is, I've lately become kind of an anti more distros, more forking kind
of guy.
Understandable.
As you can hear on user.
What sets Magia apart that would make me ever want to use it?
Do you know?
I'm not really sure.
I'm going to throw this to the mumble room.
Do you guys have any insights here?
I kind of put this in the show because I wasn't super familiar.
I did download the ISO.
I didn't have a chance to try it today, but I will try it later this week.
I never was on the Mandrake, Mandriva lines.
I don't have a lot of insight there.
I assume it's RPM based because of where it came from.
But at that point, why wouldn't I just use something like Fedora?
Yeah.
They do have...
This new release does have Plasma 5.
They've got DNF in there.
They support AppStream and Gnome software and Plasma Discover.
They've support Copper and the open series build service.
And they've got a new DNF Dragora GUI tool for package management.
So it sounds like Fedora with a couple more GUI apps and open build service.
Right.
And I guess more focus on providing good integration with third party services.
So maybe this is a Fedora you can install on your friend's computer.
Yeah, but that third party integration, isn't it just a matter of adding a text line to
something?
See, once again, I don't see the point of having a fork just for that.
I think that may be true.
But I will say congrats on their sixth release.
That's awesome.
I'm sure they're doing lots of hard work.
I just personally don't understand why it exists.
Yeah.
So I think this is a great way to provide feedback if there are people out there either
right now in the Mumble Room or who want to write in and give us feedback to the show.
I would be curious as well.
I think that's something ongoing.
What does it take for a distribution to really carve out its own way and exist?
Well it should have a consistent release because I'm kind of with the Rekai with this, but
I thought it was dead.
So you're saying Magia is around, I'm like, wait, they're around?
I think that's what a lot of people thought.
All right.
Anyone else?
Yeah.
Please chime in.
Don't break when I update.
Yeah.
Have the software that I want.
That would actually be something in its corner is if they have the third party integrations
and when you update it doesn't break because that is a problem that some people have with
Fedora when you enable things like copper and they try to go do the DNF update to the
next version or whatever and their system basically breaks.
Exactly.
So if Magia could handle that, that would be a differentiator.
I think you've hit the nail on the head.
And with that, I think it's time to bring this episode of Linux Unplugged, episode 206,
to a close.
Thank you very much for guest hosting, Mr. Rekai.
It has been an absolute pleasure.
If you want to see more of this show, you can head on over to jupiterbroadcasting.com.
There's the archives, a ton of other shows.
If you want to see more of me, I'm at Westpain on Twitter.
And where can they find more of you, Dear Beard?
Well, they can find me on Twitter at twitter.com slash RekaiLP.
Or they can find me on Twitch, streaming usually almost every day.
Hey-o!
The short URL is R-E-K-D dot net, Rek.net.
Or if that doesn't work for some reason because I screwed something up, it would be twitch.tv
slash RekaiLP.
Perfect.
Well, thank you very much for joining me.
Thank you everyone who joined us in today's Mumble Room.
You really make the show, as well as the IRC.
And hey, we'll see you next week.
Alrighty, thanks everyone, that was a fun show.
Hopefully you guys enjoyed it as well.
So now it's time to go on over to JBtitles.com and get your vote on.
So we have a bit of a problem with the titles here, Wes.
Do we?
All these titles are about me.
Of course they are.
So you want something filed under B for Beard?
That's what you want?
I don't know, Wes.
I'm going to leave it up to you.
I think we leave it up to our dear friends, the voters out there.
The voting public.
The way this works, though, it's kind of like it's, you might call it an electoral college
where there's the public that votes, but then there's these mysterious people in the background
that make the final decision.
We don't speak of them.
No.
We can't actually.
Forbidden.
And then one of our titles is President.
For the whole next year.
Ooh, Linux Unshaved, that's kind of fun.
I'm kind of partial to Beardy McBeardface, but at the same time, I feel like having the
title be about me is really self-serving.
But it's a special episode.
I guess.
But what happens next time?
I'm on.
Exactly.
Kind of like the Dubstep Alan thing.
It'll have to be even more creative then.
We named an episode of last Dubstep Alan, and then we had to end last.
Yeah, that's true.
So think of the show, people.
We couldn't top that title.
Think of the show.
Man, we just had so much stuff today, I didn't even get to ramble about containers at all.
You didn't get to ramble about containers.
You didn't get to piss off everybody that was listening by talking about Windows games
like you wanted to.
That's true, yeah.
Wes wanted to do that, by the way, not me.
Not you.
You were a willing participant.
I said we could do whatever you wanted, but I wasn't going to take responsibility.
That's what you always say.
No one wants to take responsibility.
I've been too busy with file systems to even game.
Hey, that's not a bad thing.
I'm going to rat Wes out here.
Wes has been gaming on a Windows box, I'm told.
There is now one in my house, yeah, it's true.
It's true.
Last fever.
Yeah, pretty much.
You're losing quite a bit.
Oh, come on, Wes.
I'm still also gaming on a Windows box.
It has both.
Wait, wait, you're gaming on a Windows box and also a Windows box?
I mean Linux box.
God, Windows has infected me.
What am I going to do?
This is what happens, Wes, that's what I'm told.
Windows isn't good for anything.
So in full disclosure, it's not like it's a shared system that is dual boots, Linux
and Windows.
It just also now boots Windows for some games that other people in my household would like
to play, but it does open the possibility of if there is a Windows game that I want
to play or have wanted to play or should be playing, I now can.
Not saying I will.
I still keep it booted into Linux most of the time, but it's a new world.
Some games that I don't like.
Or an old world that I'm back to.
Are available for Linux that you might be interested in, Factorio.
Oh, yeah, I've seen you stream in that.
And Rimworld.
Oh, okay.
I'll check those out.
Yeah.
Yeah, I tried the beta of Lore Breaker.
That's kind of fun.
New FPS by the guy that did some UT stuff, Cliff V. Also the Battlefield games doesn't
work on Linux.
One of my most entertaining games.
I've been watching a lot of it.
I'm not playing it much because I'm really bad at it, but it's Player Unknown's Battlegrounds.
It's kind of a battle royale game with more of a realistic bent.
So you just have like a hundred people that are dropped from a plane all across a map
and you kill everybody until there's only one person left and they're the winner.
Yeah, it's similar to DayZ, right?
But instead of having like that eternal continuous map, you have a closing in map.
So you have to stay within certain bounds of a certain radius or else you'll die.
That way it keeps it interesting because people have to continuously get closer to each other.
Yeah, because you start with the full map and then as time progresses, you have a circle
on the map that gets smaller and smaller and people that are outside of that slowly take
damage and later in the game, they take more damage until basically, if you're outside
that circle, you'll die within a couple of seconds.
Wow.
Okay.
So it kind of forces PvP until there's only one person left.
Cool.
I've seen a coworker played some of that.
It's a lot of fun.
Even when you're bad at it, it's still fun.
I might have to give that a shot.
There's a lot of good suggestions here.
There we go.
All right.
There's a humble bundle of some Telltale games, but I don't think they run on Linux.
Some of them do.
I believe.
I thought I saw a Linux icon on there.
I could be wrong.
But even if they don't, if you happen to have a Windows box, I would highly recommend any
of the Telltale games.
They're almost all great games.
That's awesome.
They're all point and click games, but they are very story heavy and most of them are
based on existing franchises like The Walking Dead or Back to the Future or Batman or Minecraft.
Borderlands.
The Borderlands one is actually really funny.
Nice.
It is.
I've played the entire thing.
It's so awesome.
Even if you don't traditionally like point and click games, I would still recommend trying
them.
My favorite one, I think, is The Walking Dead series, which if you're a fan of The Walking
Dead, it's amazing.
If you're not a fan of The Walking Dead, it's still a fun zombie story.
Huh.
Here's a classic, basically Beneath a Steel Sky is available as a flat pack or a snap,
I think.
Oh, that's nice.
That's a really old school point and click game.
It's really fun to play.
Once you've got the audio working too and it works, so it's nice.
That's awesome.
Here's another tip.
I used to play Monkey Island on Linux when I was younger.
You can play the older adventure games in SCUMVM.
Is that right?
That's something too, one of the JBLives in the chatroom said you could probably play
most of the tailgates via Wine because they're on the simpler end of the technology scale.
Yeah, you know, that's nice.
Also hitting back on, you had two machines, one that's Windows and one that's Linux.
I don't know how good Windows 10 supports IOMMUs, but maybe you could just bypass hardware
to your Windows install on the partition and play those games on Linux.
Oh, virtualize it?
Yeah, that's totally worth investigating.
I'll have to see what that hardware supports.
The slightly older system with a modern GPU, so I'll have to look into that.
Okay, so I guess we should pick a title and get out of here because we've got a live tech
snap coming up next.
I've got to go edit a show.
And you've got to edit a show.
So Linux Unshaved or Beardy McBeardface.
As the guest, I think it's up to you, Mr. Beard.
Or Unplugging the Beard or the Bold in the Beardy Fool.
Those are all hilarious.
Not that SS.
I like that too.
What do you think?
I think we're going to stay away from the SS status.
Yeah, I agree.
Let me refresh here.
Yeah.
Doesn't it auto refresh?
Didn't you make this?
Well, it doesn't seem to be working on mobile, so that's a bug.
File a bug.
Yeah, it hasn't been working on desktop for me.
Also, you had to restart JBot earlier, so that might be a thing.
Yeah, that might have been it.
Yeah, that's fair.
Yeah, as I mentioned in the show, JBot has a memory leak that I can't really track down,
and it only happens on certain distributions, which makes it even weirder.
Weird.
Yeah, by the way, I'm looking for people to help me with JBot because I have no time to
develop it.
That's fair.
So if anybody knows Ruby and wants to help out.
Jim and I know Ruby now.
I should help.
All right.
I'll help.
Stop twisting my arm.
I guess we're going to go with the beard title, since that's all the top-rode titles.
Yeah.
Well, I do kind of like init it to win it.
I also like that.
Or init to win it.
Init to win it.
I'd be okay with that if that's what you want to choose.
Colonel Panic offers to rewrite it in a real programming language.
I mean, if you want to support it, then yes, do it.
Do it.
No, don't, because I won't use it.
Ruby or not.
The problem is I'm the one at the end of the day that has to maintain it and make sure
it's running for JB.
And if something breaks, I have to fix it.
So I still have to know the language.
And the only language I'm really comfortable in is Ruby.
That's fair then.
I think that's how a lot of things get made.
One last gaming thing is there's a game called a survival game called The Long Dark that
I've been playing.
It's a good game.
It's got 205 hours played in it and it's coming out of early access in August 1st.
So the story mode will finally be coming out.
So maybe once I've played that, I can say whether it's good or not for someone to buy.
Well if we're going to talk about games where there's thousands of hours in games, I can
recommend a couple.
Civilization 5, great game.
I have like 600 hours in that game.
Path of Exile which is kind of like a Diablo 2 clone with a much more extensive skill tree.
We're talking like hundreds of different variations on skills.
That's something if you like action RPG kind of stuff.
And one that I'll probably get a lot of crap for from some gamers, Final Fantasy XIV
Online is an amazing story based MMO.
I hate most MMOs because they all feel like fetch quests.
But Final Fantasy XIV, it has a crap ton of stories.
So it kind of just feels like a regular RPG where you happen to be playing with other
people.
Nice.
That actually kind of sounds exactly like what I want.
I think I have like $3,500 in that game.
I'm impressed.
I think Path of Exile is like $1,500.
I game a lot.
You sure do.
And that's why we love you.
All right, we should probably get out of here.
Thank you everyone for an awesome show.
Your feedback and input has been very much appreciated and a lot of fun chatting about
games too surprisingly.
So this is awesome.
Thank you very much.
Stay tuned.
We'll have a live tech snap coming right up.
Lots to come.
Yeah.
Awesome.
So streams will blip, et cetera, et cetera.
Hey, Elixir's actually kind of fun there, Colonel Panic.
Anyway.
I actually have an article I can link about how Discord used Elixir to scale to millions
of people.
I'll put that in the charm later.
And don't worry, the Beam VM is written in old school ADC so everyone can be happy.
Nice.
Okay, with that, let's get things switched over.
Beard, thank you so much.
This has been a lot of fun.
We'll have to do more shows again.
Let's get rid of that Chris guy.
We'll just post all the shows together.
Yeah, who needs it?
It's Jay in Montana.
I'll take over on LAN and then we'll host this together.
I don't gotta do anything for tech stuff because you got that under control.
I guess I have to do on filter?
Yes, you do.
Or do you want to do that?
Well, we can switch back and forth or bring Noah on.
I guess I'm going to have to replace you with Chris on user error since I'm already on there.
Or Chase does user error?
I don't know.
We'll replace Noah with Chase.
There we go.
Yeah.
Okay, I think we've got it settled.
And we'll never speak about the hair again.
Yeah.
Woo!
Alrighty.
He can just stay in that Montana place.
Hopefully.