I think I've made an interesting discovery regarding the Raspberry Pi 4 that I haven't
seen a lot of people talking about.
You know how they announced at the launch of the Pi 4 that it didn't yet support USB
direct boot?
Right, a lot of people have been waiting for that.
Turns out it appears to be just a Raspbian kernel issue.
It's not actually a hardware issue with the Raspberry Pi 4.
No.
Yeah, I just got Ubuntu 2004 flashed to a USB SSD and I have the SD card in there simply
for boot and I have the SSD still plugged in and it's now booting and running entirely,
the entire OS, from the SSD.
I think I have to leave the SD card in there for boot.
I should try pulling it out and see what happens.
We've got some homework.
Yeah, yeah, but it's been really interesting because I was going through this entire process
of trying to figure out how to get the Pi 4 to run off of an external disk because the
SD cards are so slow.
So slow.
And so I was looking at this and I started thinking, reading between the lines of what
these people are talking about in these patches, it seems like I could just reboot and try
it.
And so I changed a couple of disk labels, reboot, and boom, there I was running the
whole thing off of a USB disk.
And I found a form thread where somebody else had announced that they had the same revelation
that I just had because people are coming across this and in there they say, yeah, it's
just a Raspbian kernel bug.
I haven't found verification of that, but they say it's actually totally capable of
doing it hardware-wise.
I had no idea.
Hello friends and welcome into Linux Unplugged episode 347.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Hello.
Looking sharp today.
Nice to see you.
I like that hat.
You know, you got to try to dress up when you have the chance during quarantine.
That's right.
Listen, we have a show for you that has been many, many, many years in the making.
I am very excited about today's community news.
Plus we have another batch of fantastic community feedback as well as some early adventures
in Ubuntu 2004 LTS on the Raspberry Pi 4 running from an actual proper SSD performance glory.
I'll tell you about that in a little bit, but before we go any further, we got to say
a big hearty hello to Mr. Bacon.
Hey Cheezy.
Hey Chris, Wes, and the Antinets.
How y'all doing?
Oh, we're doing all right.
You holding in down there?
Oh, I'm holding in, man.
Just hanging out.
I just picture you just like chilling, really, like anybody's going to handle this is going
to be Mr. Bacon.
Well, the only thing I'm missing is like actually being able to buy a brisket to smoke one,
you know?
Yeah, I agree.
But other than that, I'm holding in pretty good.
As long as you are stocked up on them brats.
Also a big time appropriate greetings to a massive virtual log.
Hello Mumble Room.
Is this a record?
I think we're breaking a record right now.
We have 40 people in the Mumble Room.
It's absolutely bananas.
I would sit here and give a shout out to everybody, but I think that would take too long.
I just want to make a specific mention that I think it's so awesome that those of you
who can are showing up it's it's such a huge sign of direct report and I want to
say a special shout out to Philip from manager who will be chatting with a
little bit more hello Philip good to have you here today hello I'm happy to
be here as well I am happy to talk about your news in just a short bit so before
we get to that I want to mention my adventures with the Raspberry Pi 4 I I
I have decided to yet again purchase another Raspberry Pi 4 I think this is
my fourth now that's fitting I'm very happy with them and I just enough
machine I really like the fact that I have three of them running and like
collectively I think they take like 50 watts of power collectively maybe and
that's with the switch and the router on the same meter it's like all of it with
the full networking infrastructure it's it's how it's wonderful and for me be
running off battery that really matters and so I just kind of scale out
horizontally with these raspberry pies instead of getting one really big
powerful box but the key thing that has really driven me crazy is SD card
performance and then there's another thing that I I have lived with but not
have not have been thrilled about can you guess what that might be you know me
what's my key what am I complaining about with my Raspberry Pi 4 right now
Raspbian yeah I mean I love the project I'm very grateful for it but just
different enough right it doesn't always fit with your sys admin instincts
exactly kind of feels I don't know it's consumer grade mean cheese is that the
wrong way to put it it just doesn't seem like it's a server OS no I don't feel
that it is but I feel that it's supposed to be an entry-level OS you know I think
in with the Raspberry Pi you know from their conception they've been kind of
entry-level devices for tinkers and and I think that the the OS they ship is is
what we should expect them to ship you know yeah and they've done a great job
with it but it is it is quite different you know their own config tool which
is nice helps out a lot with a lot of things but but yeah it's it definitely
feels consumer consumery to me and I had some weird breakage recently where it's
complaining that my time zone data file has missing lines and that my Linux
image packages are empty I have done nothing with this device it is a minimal
Raspbian install that I've just kept up to date about once a month and then
everything else is in containers there's nothing installed on the base OS and it
broke on me I mean it just sort of suggests some of the problems from
running a smaller distribution sort of customizing things versus just you know
one of the big ones that's really well tested and perhaps it is something at
some point I did maybe experimenting with WireGuard or something yeah and
that is that is also why it's maybe not the best OS for me because those are not
the mistakes I might make on Ubuntu I wouldn't make that mistake necessarily
on Arch but because I'm just not as familiar with a Debian base these days
I'm more familiar with Arch and some to some lesser extent Ubuntu right you're
not installing Raspbian or Debian on any of your other systems right exactly
exactly and so when the opportunity came around when Canonical made the
announcement that they were making the Raspberry Pi like a full featured
platform I was like all right well when 2004 gets close I'm gonna give it a go
and so I think we should emphasize that because instead you're migrating away
from a custom build operating system for the hardware that should be like a great
match to a LTS release that hasn't even been released yet yeah I mean I'm not
throwing this in production yet but I probably will if it all goes well and so
I downloaded the Raspberry Pi image the current daily used gnome disk to your
and wimpy suggestion to restore it quote-unquote it works pretty darn well
now it does and I like seeing the transfer speed and it's nice not having
to install anything extra it's just right there and I popped that SD card
into the Raspberry Pi 4 and it is about what I expected because I've actually
tried I've tried to get other versions of Ubuntu on the Pi 4 working before
although everything works all the hardware works everything's detected
that's wonderful the only problem was it was on that dang SD card and I want it
on something much faster there's a lot of ways you could you can crack this
including hats that give you SATA interfaces oh yeah I don't know if
they're over USB or not I assume and as well as USB 3 adapters that plug
directly into an MV and eDrive so it's just like raw MV me or whatever into a
USB port and it looks ridiculous yeah I mean it must work well but I like to
have my Raspberry Pi is nice and tight I got them in flirt cases they're velcro
to the inside wall of my booth seat like it's all nice and tidy I have everything
labeled you know it's like my one space where I've been able to really have a
little craftsmanship and so I got one of those Samsung SSDs that must be just an
MV me in the little enclosure and it's just a USB C port no power that goes to
USB 3 port on the Raspberry Pi I wrote the same image that I wrote to the SD
card I wrote that same image to the SSD I booted off the SD card first checked
things out didn't update anything but I did change the default password
generated an SSH key I eventually changed the hostname as a test then I
plugged in the SSD that I just written the same image file to change to disk
label I'll put the link to that in the show notes rebooted the box and the
Raspberry Pi 4 from that point forward runs off of the SSD and it's fantastic
and every operations faster yes it's USB 3 but that is something a limitation
because of the type of workload these things are doing I'm willing to take
mostly the applications I run they load up and RAM and then they only write to
disk when they're logging I mean you could tell immediately just SSH out of
the box that all right this feels like a regular system like an x86 box right
that was my first thought is oh this feels like an x86 machine which is
probably old thinking now obviously is but it's incredible when you look at the
size of these things the power draw the only the only part it really fell down
is I tried to go next level and I know this was a risk I didn't even know if
would be possible so I'm not disappointed that it didn't work out but
I thought to myself okay the ultimate setup I'll run my home assistant
appliance in a VM on a Raspberry Pi 4 because this thing's fast you know it's
fast it's legitimately fast so we could do that right that's got KVM on there
yeah you got KVM for ARM Raspberry Pi CPUs are designed in a modern era surely
they must have some VT and VTD type analogy and they're built into their
CPU that makes virtualization so damn great on the Intel platform this should
be a no-brainer get KVM installed I even get a remote vert manager from my
laptop connected to it I'm setting up VMs I'm importing disk files it's
looking really good power it up and it is unbearably slow things that when
you're running off a native disk would happen so fast you could barely see them
go across the screen we're happening at what would you say like a minute or two
oh yeah yeah even though we weren't trying to emulate x86 we were just
trying to run an ARM OS in an ARM VM still was so slow I don't know maybe I
set something up wrong you can tell it's kind of on the you know edge here we had
to hunt for some solutions of other people actually trying to do the same
thing and you've got to carefully select a lot of the virtual machine parameters
that it's actually going to start booting correctly yeah don't make it a
SATA CD-ROM make sure it's a SCSI CD-ROM otherwise it won't boot and don't try to
make it a spice remote viewer if you're using virtual manager because then it
won't boot in fact don't even bother with graphics a serial console just go
serial console or it's not gonna work if you follow these things you will get a
ARM Ubuntu VM inside KVM running on the Raspberry Pi 4 it will just be so slow
that it's unusable and maybe I did something wrong but I don't I had I had
you take a look at it too and you didn't see anything it was a very good reminder
of just all the little differences when you're running on a totally different
platform so and the reason why I wanted to do this is I was only going to run a
single VM I just wanted to have that snapshot capability so I could have a
several layers of protection and also make it crazy super portable it's just
nice to have right it's a pattern that's worked well over an x86 world and these
pi 4s are just so cookie cutter the same that I could just move it over to
another one powered up and everything's the same it's it's even simpler than
like from I could buy I could probably buy a Raspberry Pi 4 in five or six
years even because look how long some of the older players around you can't say
that for like a Dell mini form factor PC or a NUC unless you go maybe on eBay
maybe get lucky but these are like exactly to go yeah right you have your
little Raspberry Pi VM image available gosh that was the dream so instead I
will just dedicate the entire pie to the task which means I will continue to
scale out horizontally I'm curious if anyone in the audience is maybe given to
try know some things we're missing yeah I will say that canonical is making a
smart decision doing this because it is a first-class experience now on the pi
4 and it's it's great I think I'm as much as I appreciate Raspbian I think
I'm probably done with it and I'm just for my comfort level and my knowledge
level and just because I actually for some crazy reason to decide to use these
as servers and not necessarily as desktop devices or devices I'm I'm not
trying to configure the GPIO pins and I'm not trying to do all the things that
raspy config does I just want something to run containers and so it does that
for me so I'll just I'll just put LTS on there I could I could maybe do home
assistant in container but I kind of want experience with the whole right
you want the whole stack Alex has been talking me into that on self hosted so
that's how I got down this hole you're just trying to find the laziest way to
run containers that you can that's the real he convinced me that I got to try
out the whole stack because I'm missing out on part of the overall thing and
he's right he made his whole case and it's self-hosted and I was like I
thought maybe he was wrong so then I listened back to the episode I was like
damn it he's right this is the arm 64 version of Ubuntu right yeah 64 bit it
was a four bit it was really nice seeing it over on their you know CD image
server and daily pre-installed yeah here these ready-to-go daily images for the
raspberry pi 4 yeah that's great Chris I was wondering about the hardware if you
feel like you have enough personal experience now to speak to what you
think might be the longevity of these boards I know some of the older ones
just keep kicking but do you feel like you have heard enough in the community
or have enough experience to speak to that at all I don't think I've heard of
many failing I'm sure it happens I have at least three running 24-7 training
maybe I even have yeah I think it's just three right now running 24-7
definitely helps there's like no moving parts right so yeah and two of them are
under pretty consistent high load I have one home assistant pie that's also
running four or five other containers including ones that are constantly doing
network diagnostics and logging that and visualizing that logging and then I
have another pie that's running shinobi full-time and that's bringing in four or
five yeah five camera streams into shinobi as RTMP and then in recording
those pass-through recording but recording those to a USB disk
simultaneously and then I have an I have another one that's just a network
appliance that does my DNS my DHCP and runs pie hole and that one's probably my
lowest usage but all three of them are required for my home network to function
properly and I never have to mess with them I mean they just run 24-7 inside
that little seat you know what I'm talking about the dinette there where
it's just a it's a it's an enclosed seat and I've it opens up and it's hollow and
I've put them in there so it's not even vented properly and it seems to be
working great and part of the really nice thing for me is they're really
they're really low power and eventually I'll be able to power them entirely off
of DC so there's other advantages there may be more robust hardware in fact
there's even more robust arm hardware Jesus just talked me into getting the
pine rock 64 Pro which is I know anything about that thing really other
than just what we read in the news I've never run one production either but it
sounds like it's a hell of a board and so putting that into production too soon
I'm trying other stuff but part of the thing I love about it is they're so
swappable right and you've and we would talked a little bit about the value of
having an operating system that sort of standardized across things and now
you've got a standard platform too so you just have the fewest number of
variables that you can yeah yeah so I'm gonna so I'm gonna try it out run it for
a while and then I'll do my final thoughts in our Ubuntu 2004 review as
part of that can I make a little late impromptu prediction here yeah I think
you get two more pies before the end of the year I love them I really do in fact
I want another one just for tinkering since all the ones I do have I end up
putting in production so I want one just to mess around too you know all right
well let's get into the community news we just have a couple of items and
they're both just super super great news we start this week with the announcement
of Linux kernel 5.6 which includes WireGuard 1.00 in the kernel
I love that sound cool that's great I am so elated to announce this Wes and I
have been explaining covering and introducing WireGuard over and over
again since June of 2016 if you can believe it that's how long we've been
talking about it on this show some of these things are really just long
processes some things get integrated really fast but I think it's great that
we've been following for that long because we've really documented the
entire history of this project really wasn't that one of your predictions as
well and the person must have been I believe having a WireGuard in the
kernel was one of your predictions too this is so great it's so it's so great
so you can check it out if you want to hear our early early coverage I actually
did listen to it I meant to before the show started it's Linux unplugged comm
slash 151 and here we are at episode 347 and it's almost like a new beginning now
you know now that it's in the kernel it's gonna be deployed future embedded
devices can start to take advantage of it there's other things in here though
that are pretty neat you did a little bit of a West deep dive and found a few
things I imagined that popped out at you I noticed one of the things I noticed
was some nice performance improvements for butter FS for those that are using
it including a smarter way to handle SSD trim yeah right before that was totally
synchronous so you're writing and you have to wait for the trim operation if
you've enabled it of course to succeed now that's asynchronous and gets
handled in the background which should speed things up and I noticed came from
Facebook so looks like they're still using butter FS over there huh and that
wasn't the only file system to get some improvements f2FS that flash focused
file system that's getting an experimental compression support which
should speed things up and help improve the longevity of the of the SSDs and our
favorite ext4 is even getting some performance work to improve things like
database workloads which is really nice to see and it seems even XFS got a few
32-bit fixes yeah it was kind of a little laggard there I know we like to
talk a good XFS game here but it's finally ready for the future oh man and
it seems there's some networking stuff in there as well right yeah multipath
TCP support is finally making its way mainstream there's been out of tree
support for a long time oh it's actually in yeah I don't know if it's everything
but it's sort of the first batch of stuff that's gonna make it really start
to work which is good because that iOS platform has had it for ages yeah yeah
so you'll see that it is as a user facing feature on iOS it's implemented
as as supplementing bad Wi-Fi with LTE something the phone will prompt you hey
you know I can I can use both connections right and it's just protocol
support built right into the protocol so that all this makes sense you don't have
you know janky reconnect reconnections it's all understood yeah some stuff were
a little slow on but some stuff we're like ahead of the curve on yeah there's
a new some new changes a new scheduler so to help fight that buffer boat problem
so you see stuff for you know devices as well as servers which really speaks to
all the crazy ways that Linux is used one thing I know even though I don't use
this very much you know virtual box that that Oracle product if you've ever used
run a Linux VM inside one of the first things you have to go do is go get there
get the you know the extension CD so it has all the nice support and features
whatever right go to the Oracle website and download it and they make you sign
you know agree to some license and all this horrible stuff yeah there are now
there's now open source versions of that in the kernel we should make one in
Linux VMs on virtual box a lot simpler yeah especially setting up those shared
folders it looks like so that's really nice and before you get too excited no
this work was not contributed by Oracle you can thank the community for this no
I might not surprised I was surprised to see USB for support landing in kernel
five six I I can't believe how far I don't know if any USB for device on the
market yet yeah they're coming soon there's a couple of things in the works
I've been able to find but it was the specification was little finalized I
think back in September 2019 so it does help that it's basically just Thunder
bolt 3 turned into a USB standard but sure but it has come along with some
nice cleanup too for the existing Thunderbolt code in the kernel so that's
good you know what else we're getting as well
ex fat native in the kernel this is the release this is the release and it's not
the Samsung written ex fat driver but it is ex fat so Brent another hallelujah we
can actually read SD cards from cameras now that's great yeah you know that's
only that's only a Canon problem I don't have trouble with that I'm I know listen
to this guy listen I literally I literally solved this problem for my
brother like three days ago wow it feels like the ex fat it's funny so
that's an example wire guards is 2016 ex fat feels like it was what like middle
of last year we talked about that and boom it's already there looks like
actually it looks like it'll be in five seven oh so it's not quite they're not
quite there but it has been emerged into the VFS next repository so it's coming
so there could be okay so it could be very soon okay all right well you know
what don't get my hopes up juice don't get my hopes up well that's a pretty
solid release the only thing that is like kind of a come on about this
release is that I just deployed Ubuntu 2004 and it's using kernel 5 4 which is
fine it's fine and they're back porting wire guard right that's a thing yeah
yeah back back ported to 2004 and then Debbie and Buster and then there's also
by a different back port to five five dot four LTS release so it's all over
the place all right you don't have an excuse not to be running wire guard
frankly I think it's pretty freaking fantastic that it's 2020 and there's
still things landing in the Linux kernel that we get excited about and this is
something that you don't get on Windows and Mac OS like we we know about
features sometimes years in advance you can plan for that you can start to build
for that and you and I are already using wire guard nearly on the daily and it's
you know it's something that we because we were able to follow this you're able
to see the state of the technology you're able to read the mailing list
sometimes you can get started ahead of the curve and it just gives you such an
advantage the proprietary platforms don't have because yeah it's handy for a
couple of podcasters here sure but imagine if you are building this at
scale for an enterprise and you you could maybe already have a year two
years experience with this tool as it lands and I just can't emphasize how
freaking grateful we should be for that insight it is I think maybe reflective
to know things get tend to get done in Linux it's definitely not always ready
for everything right there are still a lot of enterprise use cases where by the
nature of wire guard you're gonna have to roll some of the stuff like user and
key management by yourself but that's also a great thing because it means you
can totally take this rock-solid minimal secure technology in the kernel and
build it into whatever you need and we're seeing tools almost every week
now to help manage wire guard I just saw some crazy one that sets up a whole like
home or small office network with a intranet and a wire guard page that
generates the keys for you and gives you the QR codes to make it super easy for
users to just scan with their iPhone or Android phone and set up wire guard and
I think now that it's actually mainland we'll probably see even more of those
yeah all right well let's shift gears and talk about some big news coming out
of Manjaro felt welcome back to the show it sounds like we're gonna see some new
hardware very soon preloaded with Manjaro on it what's the details exactly we
launched our Intel laptop now with our partner Tuxedo and the new laptop is
pretty slick yeah congratulations first of all and I noticed you said it's Intel
for now so it sounds like an AMD version is also in talks yes I can even give you
some details for that later on no problem is that oh interesting so I'm
looking at it right now the Manjaro infinity book pro 15 it's got a really
really slick I guess back to the to the to the top of the screen talk a little
bit about that did you guys work with them to design this thing from like
colors and logos and stuff like that well the logos and colors we designed
together so yes the red version we already saw at the last export they did
so we choose that model cause a red pops yeah and yes we we decided to make it
like the logo from us and logo from them and join them together and decided also
that we have to Manjaro super key and so on so it's really designed for the
laptop the OS and the other way around as well well yeah that sounds like a
real partnership yeah it's a tell me kind of big picture here is this is this
kind of like a premiere Manjaro experience if I get this it's kind of
like maybe gonna be eventually or is already like the best of the best well
to see you has their own deployment system called Faye full automated
installer and we managed to get Manjaro into that and yes we have to special
wallpaper for it and the logos and the battery life and so on is optimized by
Manjaro we have patched the kernel a little bit to make this machine really
good working with it so yeah you will have a premiere Manjaro feeling when you
have it and you can load it up with pretty premiere hardware to up to 64
gigabytes of RAM you can get with a core i7 that has eight threads and up to 4.9
gigahertz per core oh boy oh my gosh that's amazing and in a really nice
looking machine so about how big and heavy is this thing if that's kind of
hard to tell here on the site it doesn't look like it's too thick though it looks
fairly thin yes person it's 1.6 kilograms heavy and it has an 15.6 inch
monitor and it's matte no glare so you can even use it in the Sun and look at
all those ports on the side I even see Ethernet there I see yes yeah we have
either net we have also the new Thunderbolt 3 including this report and
you can even hook up an external graphics card if you fancy for that oh I
do fancy I do fancy that so you must have one of these right you must have
gotten a test unit or got to try one out for a little bit or maybe even keep one
tell me about that burns has one I have a different machine after MD machine so
he's doing I'm doing the other one so we have to split it up of course somebody's
got to take the AMD one I understand so what's next then so next is to watch for
the AMD release do we have a kind of like a rough expectation to set for that
it would be May if everything works at best based on the current situations and
so on well congratulations I think this is this is not only kind of like a
milestone for the project but it's also such a great service for new fans of the
distribution especially people that are already in the market for a laptop
they've heard so much about mangero maybe they've even you know seen
something from Linus tech tips or something like that and they can get if
they can get a complete package like this and it just looks like a great I
mean I just love the design of it just looks like a great combination and a
great partnership so congratulations Philip it's great I just think it's
wonderful and maybe maybe a desktop someday in the future in hand hand we
are working with a different partner on that as well so let's see what the
future brings I find that fascinating I really I really do I mean I wonder if
we'll see other distributions taking this up to also I seem to notice that
there was a announcement around mangero arm is there a new update to that I see
now too that there's 80 plus mirrors worldwide for the project that's
fantastic yeah we bumped it up cause with the next Pinebook Pro we will be a
stock image so we need some coverage so we decided to move our distribution from
their infrastructure to our infrastructure and the sad news for the
32-bit versions it's now a third-party distribution from mangero we have to
find a new home for that so if people still fancy about 32-bit versions we can
help us out to form the new team if it's still something we should go for yeah
it seems fair you got it you got us you got to be careful you spend your
resources I think I'm getting myself a Pinebook Pro and I think I'm putting
manager I think that's the thing that's gonna happen you should definitely and I
will say that I recently updated my mirrors list on my Pinebook which is
running Manjaro already so and thankfully we have a nice group of
listeners that you know directed me to that as soon as it happened so I was
able to jump on that and fix get my mirrors fixed on my Pinebook oh good I
I want one with manager up reloaded talk about the easiest way to run arch right
just like ready to go you've got Manjaro going you've got this great ecosystem of
available and up-to-date software I don't know if I ever thought I'd see it
especially at the price points that's what's I mean with the Pinebook Pro
that's what's so mind-blowing is the price points well and from my
understanding all of the packages that are in the Manjaro repositories are also
compiled for arm 64 so it makes it really easy to grab like you said all
the cutting-edge software that you could want is it's already there hmm well that
is a really maturing it's just what a what a good day to be a Linux user is
it's nice to see so Phil thank you for joining us keep up the great work and I
look forward to seeing that AMD laptop land to oh boy mm-hmm that's gonna be
great do you want some details for that machine or not yeah if you got if you
ready to share members I wasn't sure if you meant our fare you want to tell me
off air but yeah if you want to me on air absolutely so we have it for a
business line so it has a really great battery life so Winston's from tuxedo
even popped it out to 25 hours in what what that's insane yeah it has a great
91 watts per hour battery in it so it's more like the laptop is more battery
than the laptop so she won't though how big is the screen the big it's 15.6 inch
so it's a similar to the Intel based one and you have an rise in five three
thousand five hundred you and a bigger eight and you can pop in up to 32
gigabyte of RAM so yeah and probably no early word on rough price range at this
point oh yes it's under 850 stop it stop it no oh oh boy oh boy see 2020 is gonna
get better it's gonna get better everybody here this right here it's
gonna get better oh man hmm man that's really great I'm really excited about
that I kind of a kind of feel like that might be a perfect machine for me it is
more for business like so if you if you want to casual gaming or something doom
runs well and other games as well cause the vega graphics aid is also good for
gaming and that's more for the business because it's that price range but I
think with that price range and the horsepower it has it works also for
gaming and coding and stuff like that so we will see how we go with that very
cool no you go s got your next laptop picked out for you okay then you're
welcome mine too probably I have a pine book for like my lightweight Chrome OS
type tests I'll have myself a nice managerial AMD laptop we better go in
for a bulk order yeah that'd be great kill me and well when it when it lands
Philip you are you have a standing invitation to come on the show and tell
us all about it okay sure we'll do and maybe ship out some test samples out to
you so you can have it first hand and test it out would love to do that would
love to run through the paces and give it a good review well I mean a good
review honest review yeah give it a full go on the review because I tell you what
it's got to be in that sweet spot for folks really I mean I just saw a video
recently just going over some of the benefits of the new AMD laptop platform
and the battery life is mind-blowing the performance is far beyond what you're
getting on the Intel chips it's like AMD is finally there on the laptop in a big
way so I'm very looking forward to laptops based around that platform I
think it's gonna be fantastic so very good all right felt well would love to
get a review love to give it a good go and let everybody know what we think and
in the meantime let's do ourselves a little housekeeping here on the old show
now mr. Payne got a couple of things we need to announce number one haven't
mentioned user air for a long time error dot show slash 88 they go over the
details that the guys think make a distro great things that make them wince
which oh man I was driving when Pope he was describing what makes him wins and I
was like twisting and turning in my seat and there's a bunch of other great
things in there too like they just got some posture syndrome taking great
photos etc user air is my favorite show to listen to when I'm on my way to work
it just makes me smile my whole way and I get here I'm just in a great mood plus
they don't mention that thing that everyone else is talking about so it's
perfect entertainment right there's that too which you didn't say also do you
know we're live because a lot of people are here and they're here rocking it
live that's so awesome the virtual lug has has never been bigger it's okay it's
huge and we'd love to have you here too you don't have to be even in the
mother we can just watch live or join us in the chatroom it's a great way to get
some extra show now if you want to know when we're gonna be live you can get it
converted to your local time via robots at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash
calendar we'd stream at jblive TV pow pow also I think we should get that
telegram group over 2,000 we can do it we're around 1700 now but I think we
should do it because now is the great great opportunity because telegram just
enabled folders at least on mobile so you can put a lot of these group chats
into folders and then you can just dip in when it's time to do that so between
pinned chats and folders telegrams arrive for me now so they can have some
more notice I won't say actually they can have some notification stuff they
could clean up they could clean that up but now with folders it makes it so much
cleaner to just jump in to get with just what you want so why not celebrate that
by going to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash telegram join us in the chat it
goes all the time it's persistent there's always fascinating stuff going on
I mean a little bit too much sometimes I can't keep up with it but they're easy I
mean here's the reality there's a universe that is going all the time
you're not a participant of now I think you owe it to yourself and the entire
human race to participate in every universe you can participate in I mean I
think that's just it just behooves you to do that I don't I can't come up with
any other reason Jupiter broadcasting comm slash telegram we miss you come
join us yes now apparently cheese we get apparently we got telegram oh great so I
just make that big pitch for telegram and now apparently there's been some
telegram spam now listen you got folders don't mind the spammers cheese is doing a
great job that's true that's true and we got a bot in that there thing now which
everybody else has now for some reason anyways it's great Jupiter broadcasting
comm slash telegram if you get a weird sketchy looking telegram that maybe is
from just just pretend like it's not you know the internet rules apply yeah
profile picture is a pretty pretty lady or something like that yeah just watch
out yeah watch out let us let us know and we'll deal with them hmm there you
go there you go that's a good idea cheese will cheese will bring down the
Kraken chief telegram it's a cheese and Kraken all right thank you cheese
appreciate I appreciate I appreciate you bringing the Kraken all right that's it
that's all we got for you today I felt like there was something else in the
housekeeping so I was stalling a little bit there at the end but I just got
nothing they just got nothing let's do some feedback we got we got a bunch of
that we should get into here we wanted to pick it up from last week by the way
links to the Ubuntu 2004 LTS daily build for the Raspberry Pi 4 will be linked in
the show notes should have mentioned that earlier I don't know why that was
that's just difficult for me to find so I'm glad to have found it yeah now let's
talk about switching from arch to free BSD this comes from John think about
this Wes you're ready get ready to noodle on this I just wanted to throw my
two cents in for your arch server I would be interested to see it replaced
by a free BSD server I have heard some solid things about free BSD including
positive reviews you all provided about BS at the BSD event you all tended wow
that was like three years ago John dang he says I myself have really not made
any sort of exploration into free BSD yet but I would be interested to hear
and learn about the side of the OS familiarities it may be a solid
discussion for an episode of the relationship between Linux and BSD
communities as well now I had like two waves of thought there's a lot going on
with this one now one of the reasons we went from free NAS to Linux was
intentionally to move our server environment is something we're more
familiar with which is exactly what I'm doing again with the Raspberry Pis and
moving right I just I'm a more efficient admin and if it's not a detriment to
move to that platform for me if it's both a good platform and I'm better at
using it that sounds like a win however when I first read that that wasn't my
line of thinking my line of thinking was free BSD on a Linux show what and I
realized why not in fact then I started thinking now we're not doing this but I
started thinking should I even be open to the idea of putting Windows Server on
there like that never even crossed your mind did it no but like how far do you
go with this and to be to be a legitimate critic of Linux we have to be
willing to have an open mind about trying other things so that way we can
genuinely compare two things right otherwise we're just going off things we
read on the internet or comments or assumptions or old things we've tried
years ago that maybe aren't current anymore it's no good pretending Linux is
the best if it's not so then when I went down that line of thinking I thought
well then maybe switching to free BSD on the old server isn't so crazy I mean we
know it has a great ZFS support and it's a use case right it's a it's a server
operating system we're running it as a server and that hardware was specifically
purchased to run free and we know it runs yeah and to do that I checked it
against BSD compatibility so we know it's a totally BSD compatible box I
think it would be a really interesting experiment and I think it would be
unique because part of the additional problems with running free nas was that
we didn't be not understanding BSD that well and not understanding green as that
well frankly we didn't know how those systems were interacting what we could
tweak on the command line on the system level versus in the gooey in the app
level so if we started from scratch and use the excellent handbook there might
be a way to actually understand the system better and feel a little more
comfortable man managing it the only thing about it is I don't feel like
we're done with the arch experiment yet like part of what makes it a valid test
is a prolonged use of arch as a server platform because anybody could do it for
six months yeah I think we're actually do for some
updates yeah I think we are too I know I know but I think we're good now right
yeah it'll be fine you should and so what I almost feel like the answer to
there should be like the next time we need to stand something up maybe we
should do it on free BSD but these days what we would end up doing is what can
you run you can't run a Linux container on free BSD can you well that's kind of
boring I get what they do it in free NAS but they do it using beehive which is
their virtualizer let me find a play with yeah I don't know if it doesn't run
Linux containers I'm kind of out that might be it I mean actually wouldn't I
wouldn't mind actually if a really if we really had all the time in the world
what I'd like to do is stand up the entire infrastructure but do it with VMs
or do it the non container route whatever we determine that be and and
then comparing contrast the management the time well we could start playing
with some jails you know yeah that just sounds like something that would be
limited return on results like at the end of the day are all of us gonna
switch to BSD no but I do like the angle of you know we appreciate a lot of open
source technology and previous days out there doing a lot of good for the world
very true I and I think it is worth trying I think it's worth staying
current both from a skill standpoint but also just as somebody who's into
technology well and I kind of think of it as the way with ZFS to you know pays
to investigate the the less popular tools are not always open but sometimes
you discover like ZFS some real gems that outperform a lot of the more
mainstream options so if free BSD works really well for your use case it might
be a step up against your competitors or against doing it another way okay all
right artsful lodger in the chat room is linking a wiki page for free BSD
about running Docker on free BSD it seems like it's possible however it
currently says dockers currently broken we're working on a fix and then they
linked the bug but it says its limits are 64-bit Linux compatibility subsystem
will impact some Linux ABI containers so you have to be saying okay yeah it seems
like it actually wouldn't they get the bug fixed whatever that bug whatever
okay I suppose it depends on what that bug is I'm looking at the bug right now
but it does look like they want they want to integrate Docker into free BSD
well that's kind of it's kind of wild that's kind of wild right but great
great I mean that I was kind of joking but that is actually kind of a
consideration is being able to run your applications that you've right I mean
they were they were first with the containerization technology in many ways
yeah and to their credit way before WSL they had their own version of it run in
Linux programs right you said it that's amazing they really were kind of a head
on that a lot of things a lot of things huh yeah yeah so I think it is worth
experimenting I don't know if it's worth or like what we're doing with arch right
all the all the work we did to set up those ZFS snapshots and stuff mm-hmm
easy peasy and BSD one mm-hmm I don't think it's worth throwing out the arch
experiment because I think we need to continue it for a little bit longer in
the fact that we haven't updated in a little bit so good because that's gonna
happen every now and then like we need to so I think we got to live that for a
little bit longer but I wouldn't be opposed to a future project using BSD as
the host maybe you'll be running it on one of your raspberry pies be a good
excuse to talk Alan the coming back on the show Paul writes in and has some
good news about the raspberry pi forces even though I bought my raspberry pi 4
after Christmas because I didn't get one as a gift oh I believe it has the USB C
fix that everyone is just now talking about remember when it originally shipped
there was a bit of a problem where if you had one of them e USB C chargers
that's a little bit smarter it would actually not properly charge I think it
would get like detected as like a display adapter or something right they
used some non-standard setup in the USB port that needed to get fixed on the
pieboard side yeah but Paul says it looks like the fix is in Wes he says
when you cat proc CPU info it comes back with what appears to be a updated
revision and he has a picture of the old one and looks like he's right they moved
the voltage switch location yeah I'm gonna link in the show notes if you want
to go see what the difference is what they look like on the actual physical
board huh and I think this matters because we'd already heard that it had
been fixed upstream but with you know supply lines how long does that take to
filter down into what you're gonna buy on the shelf today and it sounds like if
you gotta go go get a pie you'll get the new one hmm I wonder if mine is through
the one that we were playing with today cuz that's a I just ordered that from
Amazon last week so it could be I just bought I see when I buy a raspberry pie
because I buy a lot of them I just buy it with a with a dedicated power adapter
because I like I like my raspberry pies to have a power switch so my power
adapters that I buy on Amazon for the Raspberry Pi include a little interrupt
power switch so that's how I prefer to do it but this one's one revision behind
so maybe there's maybe so you just hang it see that's what I thought is I
thought that they would probably they would probably have a whole stock
wherever I bought it from I uh I don't mind I bought it with a dedicated power
adapter but I would like to see it fixed speaking of the pie for Jason writes in
he says I've been playing with the pie and I just wanted to share with you my
recent project based on the recent pie for discussions I've purchased the
following geek worm x2 or I'm sorry x828 for my pie for I don't know what an x28
it is do you know what you want to Google that he says I had some oh the
next line gives us some context I had some spare SSDs laying around this is a
backup ZFS node for my main ZFS server that's brilliant brilliant especially
now with the dedicated bus for Ethernet instead of yeah to replicate the ZFS
data storage and snapshots I'm using Jim's s-noid six noid or however you
pronounce it okay thank you you would know Jim from tech snap and ours
technica it says it works wonders very fast and that's just it it's simple and
it's reliable I can very easily fail over to this and keep serving my VMs
while I repair my main ZFS server I have a stack of this pi 4 4 512 gigabyte
SSDs 2 mirrored and a terabyte total storage all in it's great
says I run a boon to 1910 across the board on my edge device is Debian and my
edge device is VY OS yeah the network focused which is based on Debian exactly
so that's awesome you put a link to that x828 adapter in the show notes so thank
you for doing that one other pleasant little note Jim Sanoid tool has now been
packaged in Debian so it's easier than ever to get yeah can we just stop for a
second and talk about that so you buy this $30 computer you if any and and
this is if you want to do it fancy you buy this $37 raspberry pi NAS SATA
adapter stack which has one two three four SATA ports on it that you then
stack and it comes with all the parts I literally stack it and screw it down to
the top of raspberry pi 4 and then you load it with this Debian based OS and
this little sub $100 setup can be a full ZFS replication node that can keep a VM
cluster online Wow guess arms really here the thing is obviously the hardware is a
fundamental enabler here but that hardware would be nowhere without the
free software that makes all this possible there is a thousand different
free product software projects coming together to make something like that
happen and there are thousands of people all over the world that are super
hyper focused on their one area of open source maybe an area that doesn't even
get that much recognition doesn't get that much attention and they're all just
sitting there working away year after year and now here we are where something
like this is possible where a consumer board for 40 bucks and then a stack add
on board for another 40 bucks can run an enterprise grade OS and keep a VM
system online it's just it's really remarkable so we'll put links that so I
woof woof if you have some other raspberry pi projects you want to get
started I talk about a lot of the different containers I run on my
raspberry pi like renteo or renteo it's a open source simple markdown knowledge
base for home you just you just save markdown files in a directory and then
it renders them nice on a website I mean and to set that up for myself so that's
how I do my home documentation I love smoke ping there are different projects
that replace it but I think nothing's as good as smoke ping that's something I
run from a raspberry pi I've have a bunch of others that I cover in self
hosted three really early in the show's run I just went through a lot of this
all of that stuff that I talked about in October of 2019 I'm still using and
still happy with so the setup is still valid I've just added to it which I'll
cover at some point self hosted show slash three for that episode I also just
realized that in there I talk about my favorite travel router that supports
WireGuard so speaking of WireGuard boom built right into there that was a good
email I like talking I'm enjoying the raspberry pi chat these days as you can
probably tell Jason finishes with some thoughts on network performance he says
I have to say in my initial testing of the pi 4 the dedicated 1 gigabit NIC is
well worth the upgrade I initially had 6 terabyte drive connected and moved over
5 terabytes in 13 hours it cranks and it saturated that connection at 1.5
gigabits at time my main server runs on a 10 gigabit back end and I've spent the
past three weeks converting away from VMware to KVM I've been a longtime
VMware user and a user of VMware at work but since running KVM I am much happier
and it seems much faster I won't be going back at this time open v-switch is
next on my to-do list oh yeah open v-switch would be really cool right in
Jason when you do that let us know how that goes it sounds like Jason's having a
lot of fun with his home web I love it there's a now there's a follow-up is
this a follow-up to a conversation we had about the downsides of Jason in the
show do you want to take this one yeah easy or writes in about episode 341
where we talked about that tool I was really fond of called JC which wraps
existing shell commands and converts their output to Jason there was also a
follow-on blog that sort of described that we need to bring the Unix
philosophy to the 21st century we talk a lot about PowerShell in reference to how
it has you know fancy objects and not just raw unstructured text and that
blog sort of explored the idea of well maybe maybe Jason is something that
Linux could start adopting he's not sure that that's really the right way he
writes about the bringing the Unix philosophy to the 21st century blog and
the JSON tool from the last podcast I posted a reply to the blog with I like
the JC tool very much and it makes sense for JSON usage but remember Unix tools
have been tested time and time again JSON is great for REST API calls but in
a shell environment I worry could provide some challenges text format is
fundamental through any file system and the ability to read and write data in
text requires very little the text way does not require additional tooling or
programs and just about anything can read or write I agreed that having an
additional output for JSON will increase the flexibility but I also
think it will introduce complexity to the technology isn't all data in the
form of text anyway wouldn't JSON create complexity to edit is read more
critical than writing or editing files don't get me wrong I do believe there
should be improvements but the questions of moving forward are more significant
than just converting data to JSON hmm I think the fact that we just got a
machine running over a tech serial console this morning may be coloring my
perspective on this but I kind of see where it's coming from it's like text is
just so simple and universal although I mean JSON's really just text right I
mean I think it's pretty easy to edit and work with there's a lot of tooling
around that I will say so for like the power of shell for instance that's got
the whole dotnet system backing it you know it has it's much richer objects and
this this JSON support it's kind of sort of just ad hoc with schemas and
specifications and all kinds of relationships yeah it's a bigger ecosystem
on the power shell site it's like it's born of that right designed in I will
say however I don't support changing things where we should do this in a
non-breaking way where we add JSON support and that I think just there's
not that much overhead to it right if suddenly there's a flag or an additional
text file sitting under proc that has the JSON version what's the harm I
think that's it that's it right there that should be pretty low overhead right
and that's probably where maybe JC the tool will find a sweet spot because
it's sort of just at the very end of the stack where it's got parsers for a lot
of you know core utils and other programs so if we maintain a large
program of that or there's some way to sort of work that into the project
eventually maybe we'll just end up with JSON and all the places we need it did
you see wimpy wrote this massive bash script oh yeah that's I mean that's like
peak bash script right there isn't that it's nice to see I mean it looks like
some well-written bash it immediately reminded me of why I would never want to
write a tool that large with bash that's pretty cool the Ubuntu podcast is back
mentioned for those guys they're back there we were editing it for them but I
think they've got a new guy now and they launched a new season and that's exciting
I know I as somebody who feels like my week isn't quite right without the
Ubuntu podcast in there like I've been feeling been trying to find something
for the end of my week content and when there's not a user and there's not a
text have to listen to what is a guy to do I think it sounds like a good week
to get some curry and put on the podcast so let's talk about my favorite topic
bulletproof Linux which always seems to really resonate with the audience and we
have tried to build a bulletproof arch server and so it reignited the
conversation and George wrote in on thoughts on episode 341 of the program
where we talked about time shift he says time shift is great it also shows that
Linux mint teeth the Linux mint team is focused on adding important user facing
features it's worth noting that time shift is donation where I don't know if
mint is paying developer Tony George but I didn't hear you guys recommending
donating I have donated good point absolutely something we should probably
keep an eye out for more I don't think we've made a good habit of that so I
think George makes a good point there he says testing time shift I tested it but
I have not yet had the kind of system failure from which it would provide a
critical restore perhaps you guys could try it on something important like that
arch server or where we have it implemented in a graphical way is here
on our Reaper machine it's just such an important machine so we put it on there
but I it's just been running we did do a little bit of testing although we
removed some non-critical files rather than critical files yeah that's true
that's true so as long as it just function the same way in the test it
should be working I love the people right and I'd love getting people's
feedback and ideas on how they bulletproof their Linux install different
snapshot techniques or like I was trying with a VM like what are your solutions
that is a topic there's something there about getting a server but also I think
just as important a workstation that is guaranteed dialed in ready to go every
time you sit down at the machine you move the mouse cursor the screen comes
on it functions every single time every time always I love that and you have a
very clear rescue path if for some reason it doesn't function like that I'd
love people's ideas on that Linux unplug calm slash contact Cameron wrote in
about time shift as well and he had time shift saved his save his bacon to
preface this I am a novice and was monkeying around trying to create a
script that resulted in me messing with permissions I shouldn't have hey we've
all been there that's kind of the fun of Linux right and I accidentally deleted
slash bin so I use time shift and it restored without issue so maybe that
gives you a little bit of some clarification Cameron does run into some
problems here though because you can use it to back up the system and you can
have it include user directory stuff if you want to but there's no mechanism for
separating those out at the time you want to go and roll it back so Cameron
was kind of wondering are there ways to run two instances of time shift I'm not
sure I've not tried that but that probably wouldn't be the route I would
go I think I would leave time shift just for the system stuff and then use some
other backup tools for your user data man all of this changes with 2004 this
entire conversation is different now in just weeks like every time I install a
package on my ThinkPad I have a snapshot of my system I have tons of snapshots I
don't do anything it just it's there I can revert we've tried it it works it
really changes the game on on how to get these systems more bulletproof our new
answer is just install 20 24 on ZFS and there you go it's not there yet right
because first of all one copy is no copy but second of all there's other pieces
that need to be done it's not a complete implementation yet but he says it's still
new we are getting to a point where between universal package formats
snapshots and tools like butterfess and ZFS yeah there will be a time where
maybe all you have to do is just install the dang distro and you're bulletproof
you're not there yet so there's still some wiggle room but if the baseline is
your OS has built-in snapshots and every major change invokes a snapshot pretty
good baseline pretty good and I'd love to see other distributions start doing I
know I know openSUSE it does I know yeah why did it take us so long yeah all
right so Ryan says well forget all that stuff for the love of Linus will you
please try out Nix OS I don't know if you ever heard it I don't think I've
heard you guys discuss Nix OS I imagine Wes would be particularly interested in
this distro as it uses a completely functional declarative build language
for configuration all of the configuration is done in a single file
or in a set of files you import into a single file and then the configuration
is run through a build system determine what packages users etc files and other
configuration should be generated to match the configuration that you've
declared then a new snapshot of the OS is generated and can be switched into
immediately for testing or just set up to boot in the grub menu the next time
you reboot all previous configurations sit and grub until purged there's
something very cool about having my entire configuration all contained in a
single file I don't have to do less and grep to my get my way around Etsy I
don't have to remember which format if it was a YAML was a JSON I just I think
that is a fairly that like all that stuff is ticking my box he says there is
far more to Nix OS than just that it looks like they have their own container
management system but also they have robust support for talker as well it's
definitely a strong contender for any future servers I might deploy all right
Ryan I admit that actually has me more interested than free BSD yeah I started
this thinking for you should try out free BSD but you're you know behind the
scenes you and I've been talking about this for over a year it just hasn't
really come up and I don't think we've had the perfect use case although the
way Ryan just described it it does seem like it because right also sounds like
backups will be some super simple with the you know on the one file anybody in
the mumble room a Nix OS user or tried it out yeah I just set up Nix OS server
running on digital ocean awesome there's a Nix OS infect script out there that
just next to us on any digital ocean droplet and I'm currently running a ton
of things on it you know mumble I'm running my own matrix server like it's
really great sounds like there's a lot of things really that are pretty nice
about it but what do you think is probably like the greatest thing that
made you say all right I'm running an unsupported OS because I love it this
much what was that what was that thing main thing is I can basically just blow
away my entire droplet and have it back up with the same configuration in a few
minutes yeah that declarative configuration where everything users
everything and it sounds it's nice to see it integrated right I mean people
are already doing that with configuration things like ansible or
chef but you have to hack it on top right you got to go then like basically
compiles down to a bunch of apt commands that you do or writes out all these
files having it at the OS sounds pretty clean seems like it'd be really great
for hosting providers you'd have like different different Nix base you know
one-click deployments that all right just easy to document and store hmm you
know there's also the canoe project has keeks I believe it's pronounced GUI X
which is inspired by Nix but uses a uses scheme which is a lisp variant instead
of the Nix OS language that it uses which hey that interests me a lot
anybody got Nix of us working on a Raspberry Pi 4 cuz I mean how does this
not seem like a especially if you're doing everything in containers like you
really just want a super solid base OS and something that I love this idea that
you could actually jump into a test snapshot before you reboot that blows my
mind I mean what kind of what are they doing kexec magic they're like how is
that possible how can they do that blows my mind like that's that's solid and the
idea that I just do the configuration one spot and then I just save that and
back that up somewhere and then just use that to deploy a new system peaks my
interest really does I do see in open over on github open issue for Raspberry
Pi 4 support and on their wiki they mentioned the Raspberry Pi 3 so maybe
it's just a matter of time huh we should put this on our list of semi to-do
soons I think right now we're deep in 2004 land but as that and then we'll
probably have a new fedora pretty close after that but as that kind of cycle
fades maybe there'll be a summer low in distribution releases and this will be
the yeah I like it some fun summer projects with Nick's OS you know when we
do it we should really go all out because we've been wanting to do it for
a long time and maybe I then they'll have Raspberry Pi 4 support too yeah it
looks like it's just starting to come online supported by the packaging system
it's just sort of experimental maybe not well tested just yet sounds like it has
good potential though so summer might just be perfect I think we have to do
it let's try to remember that because I think that'd be really great well thank
you everybody for sending that stuff in I like that we started at FreeBSD and we
ended at Nick's OS it doesn't take FreeBSD off the table it just means we
have multiple fun projects now we found something even more niche to play with
all right we'd love to have you hang out live we do it every single Tuesday over
jblive.tv it starts at noon Pacific but you can get it converted at Jupiter
broadcasting comm slash calendar check out my personal site Chris last comm for
my new projects and ways to get ahold of me get more Westpain at tech snap dot
systems and also at Westpain and I just I don't know it's too easy that's why well
honestly because if I was you I'd lead with the last name or the middle name
with the last name just the middle name last name lead with that you know that I
do use that and it was taken on Twitter oh okay okay yeah that's fair play then
it's fair play what are you gonna do right anyways thanks so much for to this
week's episode of the unplugged program and we'll see you right back here next
Tuesday
Something that we didn't sneak into the conversation there, but Cheese was telling me about last
week is Armbian.
Yeah, Armbian's great, man.
If you got another board that may not be a Raspberry Pi, because I don't think any of
the PIs are supported, so an Orange Pi, a Pine board, Odroid, etc, etc, check out Armbian.
Armbian's freaking awesome.
I think that's what I'll do when I get the new Pine board.
I'll put Armbian on there.
Armbian.
Yeah, well, and then, you know, you got to think, too, you're going to have a PCIe slot
with that Pine board, so should be able to do that.
Oh, that's so cool.
You know, because your bottleneck right now really is the USB 3.0 right on the Pi.
I know, you're going to wreck everything for me.
You know this.
I'm going to realize the extreme performance difference and the minimal power increase,
and I'm going to just redo the whole thing now on Pine boards.
Well, maybe you just put your, you know, your little personal NAS Shinobi storage or something
on a Pine board and then keep the PIs around for other things.
Yeah, maybe.
Yeah.
Or we'll just have to go to your eBay page right here.
Previously loved Raspberry Pi 4.
You can sign them, maybe?
Yeah, there you go.
Yeah, you would want it.
I think that would decrease the value.
But if I do it, I'll do it with those silver paint markers, you guys are going to be real
fancy.
Yeah, you're going to be real fancy.
Yeah.