This is Linux Unplugged, Episode 5, for September 10th, 2013.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, Episode 5. This is the show, probably the only show, airing
on a Tuesday that won't be talking about the new internet phone 5S, because we're Linux
users. My name is Chris. My name is Matt. Hey there, Matt. Welcome back, man. Episode
number 5. We've crossed the month mark. And we've got an interesting show coming up because
we're going to try something new. Later on in the show, we're going to do a recap of
DS9. Just because I've been re-embracing DS9, I thought this would be a good spot since
we have a no-format show to just talk about it. And I grabbed some Clippy Clips. So we'll
be talking about that later on. But up first, we've got some follow-up to last week's show.
And also today, Linus was causing a ruckus on the internet. We're going to talk about
that. And then maybe we'll kind of tuck and roll into a little chat about the NSA. It's
been, these NSA topics have been blowing up on our subreddit and the Linux subreddit and
on discussion forums. I think it's really particularly affecting Linux users because
we're a little more savvy. And then one of our favorite companies, GOG, or Good Old Games,
made a proclamation about their future Linux support. And it's not very good. So we'll
talk about that. Not too much. No, no. Not too happy about that. But Matt, I thought
maybe just, kind of just going to spring this one on you, okay? Okay. You and I have been
debating. We're doing a Friday Linux action show this week. We're going to, because we're
going to give you a little time off for the up-and-coming birthday. And I'm going to enjoy
myself a Sunday off. So it's kind of, you know, just nice to just change it up from
time to time. And we've been kind of debating like, well, what should we do as a topic?
Because really Friday and Saturday are kind of the days that are used to put an episode
of Linux action show together. Because there's a lot of work that goes into it. And so yeah,
we're trying to find something that's going to basically be of interest, but at the same
time, not create a problem. Right. Yeah. Cause there's other shows that have to be in production.
So there's not like, there's a ton of time. And so we come up with two topics, this possible
topics this week. And I like them both a lot. And obviously I'm particular to one, but I
got to, I got to acknowledge maybe the rest of the audience wouldn't. So I thought maybe
what we could do is put it to a straw poll. Like we put it to the audience right now listening
live on the show and they vote on what the topic is on Friday, on the Friday edition
of the Linux action show. What do you think? Are you down for that? I like that. I think
that's a great democratic way to do it. All right. So not only can people bang suggest
to help vote for a title in this week's episode, but now you're going to pick the big shows
topic on Friday. I just put the straw poll in the show notes. Okay. Here are your topics.
So you're ready to chat room. Your choices are on a Friday edition of the Linux action
show. Should it be Trek meets Linux or taking great notes on Linux? So we have two topic
ideas with that. Star Trek one is sort of like Star Trek meets Linux. Here's a bunch
of great Star Trek themes, Star Trek apps, Star Trek oriented things around Linux sort
of in just having fun with the fact that unplugged just kind of started the Star Trek segment.
So in the big show we do a bunch of Star Trek related stuff in Linux, tons of fun there
or should we focus in on taking great notes on Linux? There's a couple of different options
out there. Some, some really, really good open source projects that are trying to tackle
this and there, you know, to be fair, there's a lot of closed source competition like Evernote
and uh, and you know, even things like Google drive can be kind of used for notes. So this
is one of those things where, um, I think with school kind of starting back up, that
could also be a popular topic. And also for people who are using Linux in the professional
space or for people who just want to get a little more organized. Um, so kind of, you
know, not that we wouldn't necessarily do one or the other down the road, but this Friday,
just this Friday, you guys get to pick in the chat room and then we'll check back on
this as we go right now, we've got only 12 votes, so we're going to let it, we'll let
it flesh out for a while and then we'll check back in towards the end of the show. Although
I got to tell you that sometimes early votes are an indicator. Yeah. Yeah. The warp speed
heads pulling ahead right now is 69%. I wouldn't be surprised if it doesn't, uh, if it doesn't
really, if the overall percentages don't change much. It could. Yeah. It's really going to
be interesting to see where that plays out and I could be totally wrong and it could
go the other way. If you're listening to the audio feed or something like that and you're
not in the chat room, go to straw poll dot me and it's 42 1477 and then you can vote.
And a part of the notes thing too, it's kind of in that getting off the other cloud services.
So that might not, that could always be a topic we touch on in the future in the future.
All right, Matt. Well, uh, this week, uh, I thought we'd kind of start with a Linus sort
of lighting up the internet again, like he often does. He's got a sort of a way of word
with words. You might say he's like a digital fart with a lighter. Sometimes he just lets
one go and he just ignites it and it just happens. Right? Yeah. Yeah. Well, I'm not
sure which part is the fart and which part is the lighter, but I think you might've gotten
it. And some people just like the fart and lighter joke. Some people love a good fart
and lighter joke. I personally do. I think I can watch that several times a day on YouTube.
But, uh, before we get to that, and this is even better, this also is lighting the world
on fire because friends, Ting is mobile that makes sense. Ting is my mobile service provider
and Matt's are both rocking some pretty nice Android devices on Ting. And one of the great
things about Ting is you only actually end up paying for what you use. And this is pretty
powerful because often a lot of us geeks have multiple devices. Well, guess what? Unlimited
devices on your account with a, with all with a pooled plan. So if you've got a family plan,
a business plan, if you need to test multiple devices, if you're a developer or a support
specialist, you need to have several types of devices. I used to have three Blackberries
back when Blackberries rang during the reign of Blackberry. I still have a Blackberry.
I still have my AT&T Blackberry. Now, thankfully back then, uh, I was an employee, so my work
paid for it. Uh, but they were, they were, they were probably, um, they would have been
a perfect company to take advantage of this plan for a small business that Ting has is
first of all, they just break out your minutes, your text message and your megabytes and they
bill you at the end of the month, whatever bucket you fall into. Okay. Well, so you know,
if I don't use a device, I'm six flat dollars for that line. There's no guilt there. That's
less than me buying two apps in the Android marketplace this week. I don't, I mean, I
don't really have a big issue with that and I think it's a really fantastic way. We could
have phones on standby. If you've got somebody going out in the field, you send a phone with
them. If you need to test for the application you're developing on, you know, one of the
things that we do here at Jupiter broadcasting is a ton of video streaming. Well, guess what?
Video streaming behaves extremely differently on different mobile devices. You wouldn't
think so, but it does. HLS support is a little spotty, so it's been, it's been nice from
time to time to have multiple Android devices to test on. If we were going to go onto a
big mobile push, this would be a must do and Ting really makes this possible. And if you
go to linux.ting.com, you're going to save $25 off your first device or $25 off your
first month. If you bring your own device, they've got a spot on their website that tells
you all the different devices you can bring. If you've got a sprint phone, there's a good
chance you can get it ported over and they'll tell you how that works. Now also, this is
really interesting, they'll also sell you some used devices. They've got the LG Optimus
Black for $68, that's not a bad entry Android phone. They've got a Ting personal shopper
that will find you a device that meets your requirements. They've also got the LG Marquee
Refurbished which is a great little like kid's phone for $87. It still plays all the modern
Android games. You know, there's a lot of options they've got, new and used. And of
course new, they've got the new, they've got the LG Optimus Purple which is a great deal
after your discount supplies like $230, contract free with no early termination fee, no ride
along services, nothing you wouldn't expect, just your rate that you pay and any taxes
they legally have to charge. Ting is a really great and very transparent company. You should
check out their blog too. They talk about a lot of the stuff and sort of the thought
behind a lot of what they do. It's pretty cool. So go to linux.ting.com to save $25
off your first device and thanks to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged. Remember, people
love Ting and I'm pretty sure you're people too. So it's a good fit. That's right. It's
a good fit. All right, so Linus. Are you following like the NSA revelations that have come out
regarding potential back doors into crypto standards? Have you caught any of this? It's
kind of one of the more later revelations. Yeah, I've been following some of it. After
a while it just almost becomes depressing. It does, right? But I've been passively following
just so I'm at least. Yeah, and I've been interested too to see this stuff continue
to roll out even though Syria has been dominating the headlines. This NSA stuff is still getting
some coverage. Well, so about four days ago with 42 upvotes in our subreddit, this one
hit the subreddit. NSA foils much internet encryption and this one's actually from the
New York Times too which kind of gives it an extra little stamp of credibility because
a lot of times the New York Times is almost an authorized leak in some senses. So this
stirred up this big concern about the NSA working with standards bodies to sort of weaken
the standards so that the NSA knew how to actively attack it and then foil that encryption.
So it's sort of a, it's sort of a combination approach where the NSA is getting keys from
some service providers so they just have the SSL key. So that's one way they can decrypt
it. And it's also a combination of weak encryption, improperly implemented encryption and then
encryption where they have influenced the standard in such of how it's performed. Now
there's a device in Linux which will generate random numbers that you can use to seed like
something new like a generation of a new key or something like that, right? And so the
concern that the community came up with was that the standard that influenced how these
random number generators was affected has been implemented in Linux. And so people were
kind of like banging on Linus' door, Mr. Torvalds, could you please wake up and smell
the coffee, Mr. Torvalds? Please. In fact, and I kind of agree with him, Vermunda in
the subreddit said, it's time to start taking RMS seriously. For decades he's been warning
us that this is what will happen if we court proprietary software and services to the detriment
of privacy and freedom to express ourselves in an unfettered fashion, i.e. people buying
these fancy smartphones that are essentially listening devices. In fact, in a separate
report that ran, some new NSA slides came out about their ability to track smartphones.
And they had three slides up where they were making references to how smartphone users
are zombies, particularly they're making fun of the location bug that was in iOS that was
keeping your location indefinitely. And the NSA was actively exploiting that. They knew
about that and they were using that. And they had on a slide, they had 1984, who knew he
would be big brother. And then a picture of Steve Jobs implying that the implementation
of the iPhone has ushered in big brother. However, I believe that's a bit of a misdirection
because really it's the NSA who's big brother. They're just exploiting that technology to
do it. And they're exploiting Android and they also have an active group that exploits
Blackberry. And so all of this has just made everybody explode. Has cryptology been sabotaged?
Well and here's my view of it. There's two real important things to consider. For one
thing, if someone wants in to a home or into a file or into whatever it may be, badly enough,
they're going to get in. I don't care what you're using, how you're doing, it does not
matter and we're seeing that now. At some level, the right people will be influenced,
the right set of circumstances will be laid out and things will be overcome. So that's
the problem I've always had with really getting heavy into the encryption and stuff like that
is that it's great if you want to keep ISPs out of your back door, if you get my drift,
but as far as the government, they're always going to find a way. It's just I don't see
any way around that. I mean it's a novel idea that I would love to think happens, but we're
a nation here in the States that has been very vocal in that, oh please, we're more
than happy to trade our security and give you our freedom. We don't need that freedom.
We want our security. We want ease of use. We want sexy phones. We want a fun experience.
Security, we'll talk big about it, but we won't actually take it seriously. That's
my opinion and that's why RMS has never really been taken seriously by the mainstream because
it's not a sexy argument. It's not attractive.
Right. They almost just don't really care.
Yeah. I mean they do passively, but not enough to act on it. It's like you got to stop eating
junk food. Well, I can do that. Wait a minute. You mean I can't have a Big Mac? It's that
kind of mindset of you don't get to do those things that were enjoyable. It's a tough call.
Right. You're right. Yeah. In some ways, it is all these warnings about sugar, about unhealthy
lifestyles and yet here I am sitting 10 hours a day minimum, maybe more in my seat and not
getting the right exercise and often cheating on a diet because I want to. Yeah, it is sort
of the same. It is hard to have that same... It's almost the same kind of weakness
in a sense.
My solution honestly is a very simple one in that RMS is pretty much a hard line, hard
direction. It's really a tough act to follow and it's tough to follow up on, but I think
we can make personal choices and personal decisions in our life to minimize our participation
in that kind of police state. We're not going to eliminate it. That's not going to happen.
You can minimize that.
Yeah. I don't think there's any going back really.
No, but you can be aware of who you're voting for. Be aware of what you're participating
in. Really be aware of it.
My new campaign is unplug from the surveillance grid. Go local first. Whenever you can go
local first, go local, unless it's not private. But there are enough people who started banging
on Linus' door and there was a petition for him to remove the RD rand from dev random,
which is where this implementation was that people are concerned about. It gets on Hacker
News and Linus, which I believe this comment's now been deleted by him or by somebody, responded
to this petition with, where do I start a petition to raise the IQ of kernel knowledge
of people? Guys, go read the drivers of charrandom.c. Then learn about cryptography. Finally, come
back here and admit to the world that you were wrong. Short answer, we actually know
what we are doing. You don't. Long answer, we use RD rand and one of many inputs into
the random pool and we use it as a way to improve that random pool. So even if RD rand
were to be backdoored by the NSA, our use of RD rand actually improves the quality of
the random numbers you get from dev slash random. And the really short answer, you're
ignorant.
God, I love Linus.
And the great thing is, it's open. It's open code. So of course, shortly after that, people
went and posted what they found right where Linus told them to look. And from the couple
handful that I have read of people's take on it, they're all extremely impressed. They're
like, oh yeah, these guys really knew what they were doing. And what it is, is what Linus'
essential argument is, is even if they have one part of an implementation that has an
NSA backdoor, it's one component in a chorus of data points that are used to generate something
random. So it's not really a big deal.
But people are still concerned about it. And I'm curious, I thought maybe we'd go over
to our mumble room where we have a fine group of paranoids and ask anybody in here, you
guys, are you concerned about NSA backdoors and Linux? And now that we know that maybe
it doesn't have to be a code that's been compromised, but it's could just be a standard that a good
programmer is following that's been compromised. What do you think of Linus' response? And
are you concerned? I open it to the room. Floor is yours.
No, nobody has anything.
Well, to be honest, it's kind of hard to keep track of the live stream versus the...
Oh, you guys are on delay.
It is, it is. There's a bit of lag.
You don't hear us in here?
No, you mute yourself. I don't hear anything.
All right. Well, I won't do that again. I'm sorry.
I hear you now.
Okay. So the question is, are you concerned about NSA backdoors because these standards
have been influenced in Linux? And are you current on what Linus' response to all this
was and what do you think of it? Was he over the top? Was he being too hard? A lot of people
have said that this is redirecting the conversation from the actual concern about the NSA having
a backdoor into a standard and the conversation is now about Linus' behavior.
Typically, Linus has always been very direct, hasn't he? And very open with his comments
that he's made in the past. But like, I have to touch on what Matt said. If anybody needs
to get your information bad enough, they will get it regardless of what your cryptography
is or security measures that you're using. So in a way, I kind of agree with Linus as
well.
Yeah, so do I. I mean, there's a lot of fud going on about this NSA thing as far as I
understand it. And Linux users, despite their expertise, are not immune to fud. So that's
the thing. I mean, Linus Torvalds built the kernel literally from scratch. He knows what
he's doing. I think people should trust him more rather than just say that, oh no, he's
sold out to the NSA and he's this and he's that. I think we need to trust the man who
built this.
Yeah, it is interesting that some people have said that Linus sold out to the NSA. People
even said that Linus stepped in and pushed this NSA standard in when people were pushing
against it. So there has been a bit of name calling in this whole thing and accusations.
But I really don't think that Linus would sell out to anybody because he's very protective
of the Linux kernel itself. And like Davos said, he built it from the ground up himself,
more or less. And so I really don't think he would sell it out to anybody.
Yeah. Okay, I'm kind of along the same lines. Any thoughts on that? Any more thoughts on
that one, Matt?
No, I think everybody about covered it. I mean, at the end of the day, unless his family
is being held in a bunker somewhere, I don't see him budging. And if that happens, we will
on that moment send in a SWAT team of Linux ninjas to rescue his family so he can get
back to the kernel development.
We could assemble it right here on Mumble.
That's right.
The rescue operation right here.
You bet.
Even if we have to wear monkey suits to do it.
Absolutely.
That could be our call sign. That could be our uniform. I like it.
Monkey suit one, monkey suit two.
All right, Mumble Room, thanks for the thoughts. Stand by. We'll have more here in a minute.
So one story I want to touch on that just sort of hurts my heart deeply. It came up,
but I didn't get a chance to talk about it in the Linux Action Show. I think it did come
out before, let's see, it came out on the 7th. And today is the 9th, and last was...
So yeah, it came out on Saturday. So Good Old Games made a public statement about their
plans to support Linux. And Good Old Games is actually a former sponsor of the Linux
Action Show, so that might have influenced some of this a little bit. The fact that they
sponsored a Linux show might have maybe set the wrong expectation. But at the time, the
point we were trying to make was that there's a lot of great DOSBox games that work too.
So people continue to push GOG, and they say, quote unquote, for the foreseeable future,
they don't plan to support Linux due to fragmentation. Here's the quote. And this is the head of
PR speaking from Good Old Games. He says, for every game we release, we provide a money
back guarantee. If we can't get the game working on the customer's computer with the
help of our support team, we return the money. He goes on to say, the architecture of Linux
with many common distros, each of them updating fairly often, makes this incredibly challenging
for any digital distribution company to be able to properly test the game in question,
and then provide support for the release, all of which our users are accustomed to.
So no plans for the foreseeable future, because there's no way the economics of Linux support
makes sense for us. Good Old Games is investigating how to do it in a variety of issues beyond
Linux support, so don't give up hope, but just don't expect it tomorrow either.
So here's my interpretation of it, like comparing them to, and this is a bad comparison, but
it gives you an idea, comparing them to Steam, for example. Steam basically is a catch-all
working with, if I'm understanding correctly, a multitude of different developers each developing
their own games. GOG, if I'm understanding correctly, basically is not only the distributor,
but is also porting these games so that they will run on the operating systems that they
support. So basically, they're in charge of supporting multiple titles, where Steam
is not. Steam is basically the distribution arm. That's really all they're...
Okay. I mean, fair point. You're right. Good Old Games has a lot more hands-on gaming.
They're not really porting so much. They're generally packaging it up maybe into an emulated
environment and making it so it's just like a double-click experience, when in the past
it was like load multiple CD-ROMs. Yeah, but you're right. They're more hands-on than Steam
is in some ways.
Absolutely. Yeah. So Steam's got off easy in the fact that the really deep development
is the developer's problem, from what I'm understanding. And so for GOG, I can see it
from their perspective of that, they're a completely different business model. I mean,
there's no way that they can possibly go to that level. Now, backtracking a little bit,
I do think that if they felt it was worth it, they could absolutely choose to support
Ubuntu or OpenSUSE or whatever.
Why not Ubuntu and these dozen games? Does it have to be... Because honestly, there's
probably about 30 games I want to buy from GOG.
And see, I think that they would need... If I was GOG, I'd say, look, we're not ready
to make that financial investment, but at the same time, we don't want to drop the ball
on you guys completely. We're willing to put in the man-hours to do maybe a Kickstarter
campaign or something like that, something to kick some cash around.
I think what your argument is, is quite reasonable. The problem is, when I read that, and I think
a lot of people, just based on the reactions I've been seeing online is, when I read that,
it honestly sounds ignorant of the market realities. Because I think... Now, I guess
you can't quite say Steam has proven anything just yet, but what you...
Because it really hasn't. I mean, it's been awesome at the beginning, but the stats are
so messy that they're really hard to interpret. And when you're the numbers guy, the CEO can
be amped all to hell, and he goes to the CFO, and the CFO is going, yeah, are you nuts?
It's not going to happen.
It just seems like to me, a lot of these developers, like we played the clip in last week where
they said they want to move away from DirectX because they need to move away from Windows.
We see Steam and Valve actively trying to push an alternative viable marketplace on
Linux because they're concerned about Windows. Shouldn't good old game be kind of sitting
in their seat right now going, gosh, we're making old DOS games, and we're making some
of these old Windows 95, 98, and now beyond that, too. They also do new games now, too.
But we're making a lot of these games to work on Windows, and that is moving fastly away
from their target market.
I think the problem is that they look at their existing numbers, and they're probably pretty
comfortable with it, and they basically say, look, Steam is very much a bleeding edge company.
They're really going for the bleeding edge. They're looking five years down the road.
GOG is probably looking at next month and saying, eh, you know, when it's a problem,
we'll address it, but why do this when we can let other folks pave the way? If it starts
looking like the tide's shifting, we'll jump on board at that point.
I can't necessarily – if I was a non-Linux user, I would totally agree with them. As
a Linux user, I think it sucks, but as a non-Linux user financially, I get it for their business
model because they're not like other development companies. They are very much – they have
something they're comfortable with, and they see no reason to change that.
And they're a smaller shop.
They're a smaller shop, yeah, and they're just a totally different model.
I would love to see like – you know, if they ever listen to this, if they ever hear
this, here's Chris' advice to you. Pick your top five, ten games, focus them on Ubuntu,
but do it in a way, like Steam has, where the community can step in and make it a flawless
experience on their preferred platforms.
I am an Arch Linux user, and I have never had a problem with a Steam game that is actually
in full release. I've had games with very early games, and I understand as an Arch user
that I might run into an issue at some point because the supported platform is Ubuntu,
but I'm making that choice, and I'm still willing to throw my money at Valve even if
I have some issues.
So – and then I guess the other upshot to this is a lot of the GOG games work fine under
VirtualBox.
See, that's – and this is what I'm talking about. So when they're pitching this to their
financial guy, the financial guy is going, but you can do it this way already, right?
Yeah. Why are we having this conversation? It becomes a numbers pitch, and so the idealism
goes right out the window, and it sucks, and I wish it didn't, but financially, that's
probably where they're at. They're a small shop, and they're going, this financially
doesn't make a lick of sense to them.
All right. I could have predicted this outcome. You guys got to get in there and shake this
out. The straw poll is split down the middle. Our audience is split on every single thing
we ever do.
Oh my gosh.
It is always split down the middle on every topic, and here it is in living proof right
here. 21 votes for – no, it's 20 votes for Star Trek.
Uh-huh.
Forty-nine – it's like – people got to go in there and vote.
Just case scenario, if for some reason we find ourselves in a position to where it is
literally a split tie, you and I each cast a vote.
That's true. Yeah, that's true. Well, I think the chat room can help us here. Go to
strawpoll.me, 42-14-77. Get it done, people. Get it done. It is in your hands.
Yes.
All right. Well, I want to spend a little time on email, because that's one of the
main things that the show is kind of –
Oh, yeah. That's what we're going to do for the show, right?
There's been so many interesting things to dig into that we've been spoiled, really.
However, this week, I set aside a bunch of emails ahead of time to make sure we got some.
So I'm going to start with a couple. Are you ready?
I'm ready.
So the first one comes in from John. He says, hi, Chris and Matt. I caught some of your
conversation today on Linux Unplugged. This is last week's episode. I just want to add
my opinion that I agree Linux users can be cheap, but I think that most people who use
software are cheap to an extent. Most people have a real life and real money concerns,
and they don't want to pay for software if they don't have to. The only difference
between Linux users and everyone else is that on Linux, there's a ton of functionality
that's just given. That functionality is purchased on other platforms. I suspect that
the reason why the Ubuntu App Store doesn't sell software is because people don't really
need it. Same for Steam. Games, by nature, are a luxury. When people have money problems,
games are not purchased.
Now, for my other related topic. Linux needs more proprietary software. I posted this on
Reddit. It may be a badly written post that I'm sick of not having important programs
on Linux. I think talking about professional-grade, commercially-supported software that businesses
have confidence in deploying. For me, in my field, engineering, this includes CAD software
and simulation software. I think that it's a real reason why Linux is not taking off
big time. I'm sure there are companies that would be willing to switch to Linux if they
had their employees' workflow not broken. And just from a technical standpoint, I think
that most people will agree that Linux is superior. The problem is the workflows are
broken using Linux. He mentions he refers to Jupyter Broadcasting as a dependence on
using a Hackintosh for our video editing. Anyways, I wanted to suggest somewhere within
your domain, we could build a list of programs and brand names that your viewers need available
on Linux to have completely working workflow. I was thinking that would be an interesting
Wiki thing on the subreddit.
That'd be fantastic, actually.
Good thoughts. I do agree that Linux distributions have a lot of built-in functionality. Over
the years of using Linux, I've purchased a good handful of software. I've definitely
purchased more software for the commercial platforms even though I use them a lot less.
Yeah, and see, for me, I found the opposite to be true. It's definitely made me more cost
conscious. I'll go to other operating systems and look at software that I would have readily
available in Linux and think, oh, wow, do people pay for that? It changed my expectations.
But as far as what he was talking about with AutoCAD and things like that, proprietary
applications at that that are available for their existing workstation and then asking
them to drop that and then go to something that may not be as good on a Linux distro,
I can understand where they're coming from. I think with Jupyter Broadcasting specifically,
we use the operating system experience that's best for that particular need. We use a lot
of Linux. We do use some OS 10, but we mostly, by and large, are using more and more Linux
than we used to. I think that it doesn't have to be an all or nothing kind of situation.
I think that you can, in fact, have your dedicated setups for what works best for that particular
situation, but if someone's just working in an Office document, there's no reason why
they can't, and we've seen this in other countries, to why they can't look at open
source alternatives.
Yeah, and I'll tell you, especially for Unplugged, as I've moved more production onto all of
these audio-based shows, almost the majority, except for just clipping the ends, is done
on Linux now. However, for the video shows, it's still not quite there yet, and I'll tell
you though, as I've moved more of the work process over to the Linux box, it's so nice
where like, okay, one of the things that's really kind of nice is there's so many ubiquitous
ways on Linux to mount a file system, so like, if the easiest way for me to get to one box
is NFS and on the other box where maybe I'm grabbing a source file off the Hackintosh,
you know, maybe I'll do it because Samba sucks on Mac OS X so badly, but you know, on Linux,
no bags, not a problem, not affected, I just do an SFTP mount and boom, I pull the files,
like it's nice to have like, all of this extra versatility that is useful in Linux in general
also is great in a production workflow, and I feel like I've made more of a custom workflow
now because of the flexibility that gives me, like, it's kind of happened at around
the same time that I'm implementing that storage system in the studio, so like, I've been able
to integrate NFS at a much deeper level now into the production workflow, and it makes
switching between the different systems so awesome, and BitTorrent Sync is now doing
a lot of the lifting behind the scenes, so if I create an asset on the Hackintosh because
I need motion, you know, there's an example of an application, Motion and After Effects,
there's just literally nothing else to do, Blender is not, Blender is great, but Blender
is not the type of, you know, Blender doesn't create what I need it to create to do our
motion intros and things like that, but I can create that motion intro on a Hackintosh,
export it out onto the NFS share, Bob's your uncle, I open up on the Linux box, and now
I'm slapping it down and I'm good to go, so it's getting easier to move between them,
but it's definitely, there's certain things that are locked up into different operating
systems, but with a common backend file system, and a common name working space for everything
where everything can, you know, knows how to connect to each other, it kind of just,
it really feels like, well that's not so much a Mac, that's the motion output machine, right?
Exactly.
It's like this, it's almost like if I'm in a shop, like you've got machines that puts
airs in, you've got machines that puts air in tires, and you've got machines that take
oil out, you know, you've got all these different, that's what it feels like to me, and...
Well it's like a POS system, sometimes they run Linux, sometimes they run other stuff,
you don't care, it's a POS system.
It really is, it really is an appliance, like if I look at it right now, you know, this
thing is running OS 10 7.4, it's never once been, nothing on it has, except for some of
the applications, but like none of the operating systems, none of the main production software
has been updated since the moment it went into production, because that is generally
how it works in a business, you get a stable functioning system, and because I don't have
to do security updates on Final Cut, it's not a huge issue, you get a stable workflow
where everything's compatible, and all the scripts work with everything, where everything
goes out, all that kind of stuff, you just, it becomes an appliance in a lot of ways.
Exactly.
So, I move on, but thanks John for the email, Zaytech wrote in, he said, I did not see this
addressed in Linux Unplugged, so I'm just going to send it in to you guys.
As for Linux users that are cheap, I would say, yeah, that's why we picked a free OS,
and love it.
Not much Linux users are able to completely give up Windows either, and that's where the
wallet drains go.
I have, however, been running Linux, and only Linux for four years, and now I've decided
that the money that would have gone to some big corporations will go to small shops and
give them something at a good, they give me something at a good price.
These are one way that Linux users spend money, and that may not be properly accounted for.
I donated to several products, and bought a new, oh, the LN Sync, which is a great Google
Drive client, and I'm also addicted to purchasing the humble bundles.
Also, my netbook just died, so I'm going to get a System76 machine soon.
He's got to work out some shipping problems.
Well, they can help you with that.
Love the show, hope to chat with you on Mumble someday.
Well, I wonder if he's on Mumble right now.
I don't know.
Yeah, that'd be awesome.
That'd be a good time for it, you know.
We'll see him on there.
All right.
We'll get to our last email, or actually, it's not our last email, our second to last
or so.
Hi, Matt and Chris.
You were talking about a lot about self-hosted cloud storage, e.g. ownCloud and BitTorrent
Sync, but you never talked about the open source tool C-File, which is at C-File, S-E-A-F-I-L-E.com.
It uses a version control model similar to Git.
While ownCloud sucks at syncing a lot of small files, C-File is rock solid in this area.
Maybe you should have a look at it.
Greetings, Marcel, from Germany.
Interesting.
I haven't checked out C-File yet, but that's like the second or third person who sent in
an email kind of recommending it, so you might have to check into that.
Yeah.
I would be curious to hear people's experiences with it.
I'm pretty happy though now with my current implementation.
It's going to be hard to break me away from that.
We also, in the subreddit, somebody sent in a service that looks pretty interesting.
I don't know about the security, so I'm not going to say I vouch for it, but the concept
is pretty cool.
It was a BitTorrent Sync remote storage.
It was submitted by Army One, or Army, I guess.
It's incloudably.com.
They do a whole bunch of DDOS protection and storage stuff, but one of the products they
are offering now is like, you can go buy it, is a BitTorrent Sync remote hosted.
They are reselling a sync dump location, and you use that as backup.
And now the transfer is AES-256 encrypted, but I don't know what the storage is, where
Spider Oak is pretty explicit about that.
So I don't know.
You can check it out.
We have a link to that in the subreddit.
It's worth checking out.
I mean, like I said, we can't necessarily recommend it, but it's certainly worth investigating
on your own accord.
Now, the big question, Matt, before we get to the poll, actually, maybe we'll save the
poll for the end of the DS9 stuff.
I don't know.
We'll see.
If people want to go do one more vote, you guys get a chance, if anybody wouldn't mind
pasting that link in the chat room.
Now, the big question of the day, what is Chris going to wear on Monkey Suit Day?
Oh, my goodness.
So this is a great question.
So for those of you that aren't aware, I have a birthday wish list that's been put out there
on Amazon, and one of the items on there was, in fact-
Which is at matthartley.com.
Oh, yeah.
It was at-
That's right, matthartley.com.
There's still plenty of stuff on there.
I'm desperately trying to get the zone alarm stuff put together, or zone minder stuff put
together.
Yeah.
That'd be a great segment.
Oh, and I've got an idea for that.
I'll get to it later.
Now, getting back to the monkey suit, and I don't want to take away from that.
So the monkey suit was on the list, and that was totally more for you guys than it was
for me, because I'm basically just going to sit and sweat in this thing.
But I put it out there, and sure enough, someone did pick that up, and that's awesome.
And what we're trying to figure out now is, I'm going to be wearing this for both Halloween
as well as later on in 2014.
Well, so is that a good idea, though, or should you save it for the big event?
Because it's kind of like seeing the bride before the wedding.
I think they've been patient enough.
I'm willing to do it.
It's going to be fun for Halloween to do.
Okay.
You're right.
Is the episode on Halloween?
Or is it?
I don't know where it falls, but I think it'd be kind of fun to do.
Okay.
All right.
And I did throw that out there.
Well, I should wear a costume if it's on Halloween.
I mean, that's just-
Well, a few people suggested banana.
That seemed a little-
Oh, man.
That seemed a little phallic and strange.
So I decided to maybe sidetrack off that.
Maybe go for another, I don't know, not sure what a good alternative would be.
So maybe we should put it to a vote.
Oh, okay.
All right.
Well, we'll have to come up with options.
We'll have to come up with options and see where everybody falls down.
You know, a Tux penguin would be cool.
I wonder if there's a Tux penguin.
If you guys find good costumes on Amazon, link them to us in the... Okay, so we put
the feedback thread in the subreddit for this show in the comments in there.
If you guys find it, put it in there.
Or I guess you could submit it to mattmonkeysuit.
So go to reddit.com slash r slash mattmonkeysuit or mattmonkeysuit.reddit.com.
Yeah.
Someone made a subreddit.
So I appeared in there.
It's like, all right.
That's cool.
Oh, wow.
Well, I like that big clock they got of you up there, too.
That's awesome.
Okay.
So I think maybe what we'll do is since we're going to get into a bunch of Star Trek stuff-
Yeah.
Oh, I know where you're going with this.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I have a few clips I want to play to kind of warm us up.
But I think maybe we should let the Linux... People who don't want to talk about Star
Trek, maybe we'll just say, okay, this is where you can sign out.
So I'll leave you with a couple, if you're going to leave us and not join us for the
awesome DS9 chat that is about to ensue, I want to let you know that you can contact
us by emailing us at linuxactionshow at jupiterbroadcasting.com or popping the contact link at the top of our
site or even better, we got that subreddit over at linuxactionshow.reddit.com and we'd
love to have you join us over there.
The unplugged show is live at 2 PM Pacific, which is 9 PM UTC over at jblive.tv and jblive.info.
That's the audio stream.
We've got the mobile versions of that and don't forget to go to linux.ting.com to save
yourself something.
And yes, I think that's probably all the business to cover before we get into the Star Trek
stuff.
But I just wanted to say officially, we are now getting into the Star Trek stuff.
We will unveil the poll at the end of the Star Trek stuff.
So you guys still have a chance to vote on the poll though, so we're not all Star Trek
stuff.
Okay, Matt.
All right.
So last week I said, hey, you know, I've kind of been getting into DS9 and trying to find
where it fits in my Star Trek lineup.
I've been questioning my Voyager-ness and my DS9s lately, and after just recently rewatching
a lot of TNG because they went on Blu-ray, I felt like it was perhaps the greatest Star
Trek of all time.
And then I thought, well, I really can't make that declaration without digging into DS9.
And so I should have waited until the DS9 Blu-rays came out, but I just decided we had
to go into it.
Oh, by the way, just a quick mention, NextUIs is working on a Samsung Smart TV app.
How cool is that?
Whoa!
Yeah, so people have Samsung Smart TVs, which has got to be a lot of people, I would think.
We'll soon be able to watch the Jupiter broadcasting goodness on the Samsung TVs.
So thanks to NextUIs.
We'll give you guys a heads up when it gets that.
Okay, so we decided to pick Emissary.
That's DS9 season one, episode one.
This is actually a two-parter, so it's actually episode one and two.
So next week we'll be watching episode three, technically.
I thought maybe I could just give you a little bit of trivia about this episode before we
got rolling, okay?
All righty.
This is in tradition of one of my favorite podcasts, Mission Log, which if you guys are
Star Trek fans, go listen to Mission Log podcast.
So a little trivia.
Did you know?
Bet you didn't.
The sequence of Dax and Sisko within the wormhole where they're flying through the wormhole
was actually one of the last sequences filmed, and that was filmed on October 24th, 1992.
This is the 20th anniversary.
This year is the 20th anniversary of Deep Space Nine.
By the way-
Hard to believe, isn't it?
Yeah, it really is.
By the way, this is the only episode where in the intro, they don't show the wormhole
because they didn't want to give it away in the opening credits.
Right, right.
So in the opening credits, it's all just stars, and then in syndication later on, and in some
foreign language versions, they just went right to wormhole.
But in the intro credits for this episode, there is no wormhole.
So also for the scene depicting Sisko where he's idling in the wormhole with the prophets,
you know that really super crazy white effect they had?
The director of photography used diffusion filters and overexposed the image as to achieve
the effect of the white bleeding into Sisko's skin, and the big number here, 250 special
effect shots were created for this episode of Star Trek, Deep Space Nine.
And one of the things that's quite interesting about Deep Space Nine is... Oh, I'm going
to have to... I'll see, can I... Well, I have to mute... Sorry, Mumble Room, I have
to mute you guys again because I have to play some clips, but we'll be back soon.
One of the things that is pretty interesting about Deep Space Nine is it actually opens
... The first lines spoken are by Picard, which means Picard opens TNG and Deep Space
Nine.
Resistance is futile.
You will disarm your weapons and escort us to sector 001.
If you attempt to intervene, we will destroy you.
So, pretty epic opening just right there.
That's the first line spoken in this episode, and they're Lekutis, which is one of the strongest
moments in Star Trek The Next Generation.
The Borg were huge during this time.
Oh, yeah, it was big time.
Big time stuff.
So, DS, that's a strong opening.
You open with the Borg, you open big, right?
And it moves quick.
It moves quick.
What was important about that entire piece right there is that it not only established
the interchange between TNG and this now new show, but it also helped in critical important
character building for Cisco, his history and so on and so forth.
It was a big deal.
It's really, and it's an interesting way to intertwine into Trek lore a really pivotal
moment with the new character to really make those universes come together.
And of course, these first few moments are pivotal throughout the entire episode.
They come back to it over and over again.
And one of the things that honestly, at this time, I remember, and I was curious to see
if it would have the same effect now.
After watching this, I really didn't like the character of Cisco.
And one of the things that put me off about Cisco is he seemed a lot more concerned about
his wife than his whole crew.
I mean, he's supposed to be the commander of this ship, of his crew, or even of his
son.
Jennifer?
Jake!
Warning.
Damage to warp core.
Containment failure in three minutes.
I'm going to get your mom.
You're going to be okay.
Jennifer!
Okay, Jake.
We'll get your mom out, and we'll get out of here.
Commander!
Help me!
Help!
Jennifer!
Jennifer, hold on.
Sir!
Just help me to get her free!
She's gone!
There's nothing we can do.
We have to leave!
Warning.
Damage to warp core.
Containment failure in two minutes.
And then they abandon ship and he's this whole time as the commander of a starship he's completely
worthless like they're dragging him to the ship he's he's not helping he's not giving
any orders he's completely incapacitated well so here's the thing that and I and I heard
other people mention similar things but they don't take into account remind me again how
many other captains in the Star Trek series various series were married and had their
spouses on the ship yeah yeah and I didn't Kirk didn't and so we never got to see that
side of them well and actually yeah it was until this episode it had only been established
the galaxy class vessels had children on them that's right and this this was the first time
we'd seen a non-galaxy class now you know and also look back at Picard with TNG remember
when he thought he had a son right right yeah yeah what how quickly he his whole mindset
of everything just did a 180 completely changed so I mean realistically yeah my wife and I
have days where we want to kill each other but you put us on a ship and if it's between
my crew my and my wife it's been fun crew but you know what you know I think I see that
now see at the time when I was watching this I still feel like he's a little dismissive
with the kid like the kids oh yeah here you go again he just hands the kid yeah the kids
alive the wife's dead he's like freaking out about the wife but I agree with you now like
with the perspective on that is yeah that you could see but back then I was a kid I
wasn't really married so but the other part that really kind of put me off about Cisco
is he was mean to my buddy Jean-Luc I have a son that I'm raising alone captain this
is not the ideal environment unfortunately as Starfleet officers we do not always have
the luxury to serve in an ideal environment I realize that sir and I'm investigating the
possibility of returning to earth for civilian service perhaps Starfleet command should be
considering a replacement for you that's probably a good idea I look into it in the meantime
however in the meantime I will do the job I've been ordered to do to the best of my
ability sir oh snaps dismissed so I was like dude he's being harsh on Picard but I didn't
really appreciate that from Cisco's perspective at this time he's got a boy and he's got a
nice desk job the boy's got a good safe life and now he's been put out in the frontier
he's been put on the front lines he's not too happy about it well he's essentially put
out into the you know Siberia tundra Siberian tundra it's essentially what's happened here
and you you're basically again that's what I like about DS9 is that they look at things
from it's it's less I don't want to say froufrou but it's more it's deeper character stuff
not as much about the the next horizon the next challenge the next exploration the next
conflict the in the first in the first season especially especially the first episode it's
very much about the people and the interaction and and how different events change how we
look at stuff and someone who might have otherwise been a dedicated first off you know I guess
he would have been what commander you know how quickly that can change when they're confronted
with someone that potentially not only killed the life of the crew but also basically got
off I mean really what kind of slap on the wrist of the man get yeah yeah yeah I mean
I totally see it now yeah back then I was like why doesn't he like Picard I get it now
and it things that kind of pick up and move real quick right you have he makes a trip
down to the Bajorans in this really odd like commander it's time to go and he just all
of a sudden he goes down to see this the most holiest Bajoran of all Bajorans and he goes
down there and she touches his ear a little bit and then gives them a little a little
bit of acid aka one of the prophet orbs and gets him kind of motivated so he takes this
or back to the station this is where we meet Dax we find out that Dax is a trill all this
characters are getting some pretty good setups you know you get lots of flashbacks are used
to like show Dax getting surgery and so they go off to find a location of where these orbs
came from and they discover a wormhole the first known stable wormhole now this is going
to be the show's hook because this adds a little spice because now they've got they're
on the very border of this brand new frontier and that's why they're supposed to be that's
why supposedly the concept works it's a stationary station because people are coming to them
and more importantly this is the you know to borrow from Star Wars this is like the
cat cantina on Tatooine this is a non federated area it's like you know no Federation presence
really western and it's a frontier town Odo's the sheriff right yeah and so it's and they're
on the they're on the frontier so of course Cisco's got to go into this wormhole and he
ends up getting trapped Dax Dax gets taken out but Cisco gets left behind for some reason
and what's the crew decided to do they're strapped on the station the station's currently
orbiting Bajor I love the logic so they immediately say well Cisco's not here let's move the whole
station to go rescue him but the problem is and I don't understand how this works maybe
the chat room does the problem was that darn station is too heavy what would it take to
move this station to the mouth of the wormhole this isn't a starship major we've got six
working thrusters to power us and that's it 160 million kilometer trip would take two
months it has to be there tomorrow that's not possible sir that wormhole might just
reshape the future of this entire quadrant the Bajorans have to stake a claim to it and
I have to admit that claim would be a lot stronger if there's a Federation presence
to back it up couldn't you modify the subspace field output of the deflector generators just
enough to create a low-level field around the station oh Dax so we could lower the
inertial mass if you can make the station lighter those six thrusters will be all the
power we need this whole station could break apart like an egg if it doesn't work I love
that line there this whole station could break apart like an egg it's kind of seems feels
like an homage to Scotty a little bit it totally does it totally does but now if you listen
carefully now you can under you they actually tell you why they're bothering to do this
to rescue him yeah yeah it does actually because he's the face of the yeah he's face of the
Federation they they have a report the start of a rapport basically he doesn't Kira's not
liking anybody but she's liking him a little more than she was before and you know she's
kind of warming up to him a little bit and then he doesn't really want it to break in
a whole new guy one of the things that happens is there's kind of interaction between Cisco
and Quark to get Quark to remain behind which kind of impresses Kira like oh he actually
handled that pretty well oh yeah yeah totally totally only because you know this is our
first real in-depth uh you know experience with Ferengi that isn't based on TNG logic
where they run around grunting with whips yeah you know in TNG they wrote them in there
because they wanted them to be the new Klingons before they came up with the board concept
they wanted them to be the new Klingons and they realized very quickly oh these guys are
laughable so but I think Quark single-handedly turns that image around and makes them into
cunning conniving capitalists oh Quark is my hero yeah I mean the dude's awesome yeah
and Cisco kind of has like a real slow period during the show where he ends up in the wormhole
just like explaining time to aliens my species lives in one point in time and once we move
beyond that point it becomes the past the future all that is still to come does not
exist yet for us does not exist yet that is the nature of linear existence and if you
examine it more closely you will see that you do not need to fear me it's it's it's
a it's a high level strong concept but it's just a little slow it felt like it dragged
things down a little bit for me I was okay with it in that it was I considered it part
of that character building process you know you're calling the prophets characters and
it allowed them to kind of you know it kind of intermingled a little bit so I was okay
with it yeah it was a little boring and it's actually a pretty good description of what
time is like like because they you know the one of the concepts is what is time in this
movie and these aliens have they live in a reality where there just is no time it's everything
is what it is it exists and so having to like explain you know because sometimes with my
son I've he's asked me can I explain something and I have to explain it without using another
word that needs to be explained and they did a pretty good job there but meanwhile the
real fun is actually still back on the station there's a great O'Brien character creating
scene where he fights with the station computer to get the station to actually move and this
is like a thread that continues throughout the first or even second season and I love
it.
Partial field established instability at 12 percent.
Partial field.
Is station's inertial mass low enough to break orbit?
Procedure is not recommended.
Dammit I didn't ask for an opinion.
Just tell me whether or not we can get enough thrust with only a partial field established.
Affirmative.
All right thank you.
Initiate transit mode.
Three axis stabilization.
Aye sir.
Engage thrusters.
Warning.
Field integrity declining.
Instability at 21 percent.
We've got to close that gap in the field or we'll tear ourselves into a million pieces.
Warning.
Subspace field collapse in 60 seconds.
Computer transfer energy from the inertial dampers to reinforce the subspace field.
Procedure is not recommended.
Dammit.
Transfer the energy.
Unable to comply.
Level one safety protocols have canceled request.
Canceled?
Warning.
Subspace field collapse in 30 seconds.
I'm going to transfer it manually.
On my mark redirect the flow to the deflectors and keep the power balanced.
Aye sir.
Field collapse in 15 seconds.
Now.
Field energy now within flight tolerances.
I love it.
Yeah and there's also a great scene where he's trying to get the transporter to work
and he ends up just kicking it.
Well and that's what's awesome is that this is the series, even it's through season one
that really established his character.
Yeah, yeah.
And there's an awkward yet appropriate goodbye between him and Picard where, and I couldn't
quite understand what they were trying to tell me, O'Brien visits the bridge, spends
time looking at the ready room but doesn't go in to say goodbye, then goes to the transporter
but Picard stops him before he beams out to say goodbye and like Picard is being more
emotional than O'Brien.
Like he's trying to say like, you know, this was your favorite transporter room, blah,
blah, blah.
And O'Brien's like, yeah, whatever, sir.
And then he gets up on the pad and gets and tells him to beam them out and meanwhile Picard's
like sitting there heartbroken.
I like, but I guess, you know, they were just trying to do a handoff and that is how two
guys would do it.
Like it would be awkward because it would be two guys, right?
Well Picard's acting like a girl.
I mean, no offense, but I mean, he's acting much more, you know, in that mindset of he
has things he wants to express, guys of course don't want to express anything and that's
kind of how we're wired.
And it's interesting because they kind of come back on it later on in DS9 where every
now and then you wonder if maybe O'Brien wasn't always totally happy on the Enterprise.
Now there is another really strong character moment and this time it's with Kira.
Their lead ship is hailing us.
Gul Jassad wants an answer.
Are you ready, Mr. O'Brien?
Yes, sir.
When they penetrate our Thorogh field, it should raise a few eyebrows over there.
All right, then let's give them our answer.
There are six photon torpedoes across Jassad's bow.
We only have six photons, Major.
I love that.
We're not going to win this battle with torpedoes, Chief.
Aye, sir.
An urgent hail from Jassad.
Looks like we got his attention.
On screen.
This is your answer?
You don't think Starfleet took command of the space station without the ability to defend
it, do you?
Defend it?
Your space station could not defend itself against one Cardassian warship.
You're probably right, Jassad.
And if you were dealing with the Starfleet officer, they'd probably admit, we have a
hopeless cause here.
But I am just a Bajoran who's been fighting a hopeless cause against the Cardassians all
her life.
So if you want a war, I'll give you one.
Love that.
It's so perfect.
She plays it so well.
The chat room picked up on something.
Everybody calls her sir, and DS9 followed that a lot more closely.
Like when Dax took over the Defiant later on in the series, everyone called her Captain,
even though her rank was like Lieutenant Commander.
They followed a lot of more naval traditions.
In fact, another example of DS9 having some really smart dialogue that kind of keeps you
in that world, keeps you in that reality, like they're creating a universe, is right
after that line from Kira.
The camera pans over to O'Brien, and he starts to talk, and before he even finishes the sentence,
you know what joke he's going to make.
And these types of jokes, they often bug me on Star Trek because they're essentially a
joke that we make using current 20th century references.
But instead, DS9 takes it as an opportunity to enrich the reality.
So, you know, you know he means poker.
I'm never going to play poker because you've got a good bluff face, but they don't say
poker because that's a human reference for the, you know, 20, 21st century.
But I think it's a truism that, you know, while the verbiage may be different, I think
it dates back further, just it probably, you know, uses different language, I'm sure.
It's like exactly like that turn of phrase is still used, but they use different things,
like in DS9, instead of using coffee, they get Ractaginos, right, a lot of things like
that.
I just appreciated that.
And then, of course, after the tension has been mounted and built properly, there's only
one person who can come back and save the day at this point.
Of course, it's the last few minutes of this episode, and that would be Captain Sisko coming
back from the wormhole.
And remember, at this point in the show, the Cardassians believe that it wasn't a wormhole
that took away Dukat's ship, it was perhaps the station.
And so that's why they're threatening to attack the station and they want to take it over
again.
And just as their attack on the station is reaching a climax.
Signal the lead Cardassian ship that we will proceed with major.
I'm picking up a huge neutrino disturbance 15 kilometers off the forward docking ring.
It's the wormhole.
On screen.
Hail the lead ship.
What did I tell you, Jasad?
There's your wormhole.
And he's got Dukat shipping a tractor beam, which for Cardassians is a big statement because
that's a show of weakness.
That's a lot like a dog being on a leash seen to other dogs.
Exactly.
And it diffuses the situation.
He's like, Hey, I've noticed you have a few problems.
Of course, he doesn't say why the hell have you moved my station, but right, which I had
a problem with that.
Yeah.
But then at the end of the episode, Cisco talks to Picard and makes good.
Well, you've put Bajor on the map, commander.
This will shortly become a leading center of commerce and of scientific exploration
and for Starfleet, one of our most important posts captain regarding our conversation about
someone to replace now it's yes, I am sorry I haven't had time yet to communicate that
to command.
I would prefer you ignore it, sir.
I'm not sure that I can, are you certain that's what you want?
Because we cannot afford to have a commanding officer who was, I'm certain, sir.
There you go.
He's certain.
He was, he was energized by the experience and now he's ready for the, uh, for the challenge.
And I was kind of surprised at how often Picard actually popped up through this episode.
You know, I just expected a quick cameo and that would be it, but he actually had a recurring
role throughout this two hour episode.
True.
This is true.
And I think it definitely sets sets because I think all these events needed to happen
for that first season to make any sense.
We needed to understand his psychology.
Exactly.
And that's kind of why we spent a little extra time on this episode because it really is
the foundation for the rest of the series.
That's one of the things that's kind of interesting about DS nine, although in TNG they managed
to bring it back home too.
But, uh, so before we go to the mumble room and get their thoughts on all of this, give
them a time to catch up on the stream, Matt, after watching this again, how did it land
on you?
Does it a does it hold up and B does it, where, where does it leave you?
It was like your overall review.
I maintain that, you know, I, of course we haven't gotten to where we really got to enjoy
Quark and it's in his fullness yet.
We haven't even touched on Nog or any of these other things, but I think as far as the characters
that really made their, their, uh, shiny moment in this first episode, it really drives home
for me that this was a piece of Star Trek that needed to happen without the utopian
stuff, without the, you know, just explore, explore, explore more stuff that we as humans
in the 21st century can relate to.
I think that we, it's more relatable in our day to day struggles, in our, uh, war conflicts,
all these things.
I think it, it lets us know that it, Star Trek isn't just utopian.
Yeah.
And that, and that, um, it actually caused some internal strafe because you still had
the T and G crew around a lot of the people who were there in the original Roddenberry
days.
Oh yeah.
There was some internal strife about that if, if Gene would approve of it or not.
But you know, you touched on something kind of, you know, one of the things that DS9 was
really good at was taking current events and reflecting them into the future, abstracting
them away so that way we could have a rational conversation without special interest getting
their feelings hurt.
Right.
And one of the things that struck me through this, and it's not a direct parallel at all,
but there is a lot of similarities between what the potential outcome could be in Syria
and the state of the Bajoran people, like, and there's an oppressive regime.
Um, there is a falling of that regime.
There is a civil government that is established and then that civil government requests that
this larger empire, AKA the federation comes in and brings in military to help them.
And then a local aggressor in their backyard, AKA, you know, another Eastern, Middle Eastern
country.
Something like that is an aggressor in their backyard who the, the, uh, the new hired guns
have to constantly keep an eye on.
I mean, there's a lot of reflections in modern day politics intertwined into this first episode
of DS9 too.
And in my mind, that makes it hold up even stronger.
Oh, I would, I would say so.
And I think that entire set of circumstances, both in the past now and even in the future
is a timeless thing.
Um, I've seen it time and time again, you know, it seems like it's a constant cycle.
And so it's interesting that even in a whole nother part of the universe or another part
of the galaxy in this particular case, that something so familiar can still unravel despite
the fact that they're not, you know, it doesn't involve humans.
History continues to repeat itself.
All right.
Until humans insert themselves.
I'll ask the mumble room, uh, guys in the room, I'll open the floor to you.
Did anybody get a chance to watch along with us?
And what were your impressions of the first episode of Deep Space Nine?
How does it hold up as a Star Trek premiere?
You got, think of it now at this point in time, we've seen every Star Trek premiere
has been.
We've seen Enterprise, TNG, Voyager, even TOS, if you've got the gray hairs to prove
it.
And where does DS9 fit into those other Star Trek premiers?
Mumble room, I bring it to you.
Well, I watched it, uh, well, I never really got into DS9 when I was on TV, uh, it never
really grabbed me, but I watched the first episode this time and I really watched it
and uh, yeah, I do enjoy it.
It has some weaknesses, um, for instance, the, the, the, the, the moment in that Cisco
was in the wormhole and was stuck there, I felt that it was going on, it was dragging
along a little bit.
That's at least, that's my opinion, but, uh, I did like the episode.
It was a strong start.
Yeah.
I think it was a pretty strong start.
Anybody else want to chime in before we wrap up?
Yeah.
Go on.
Yeah, I have to admit that the beginning of the episode, you know, it kind of showed what
was going to happen, especially later on, um, in some of the later episodes with a fast
pace of action, which you didn't normally see in the previous, uh, seasons and series
of Star Trek.
But the good thing about, um, this was a bit grittier, um, you could, you could definitely
see what was going to be happening in the future.
Excellent point.
All right, guys, any last thoughts?
Anybody else?
Yeah, all I'd like to say about BS9 is that it has diversity to Star Trek.
It says that it's not just about flying about in space and exploring new worlds or whatever.
There is a universe there, there is a people there, there is a culture, there is everything.
There's depth here.
There's diversity here.
Right.
Exactly.
Which you cannot ignore.
Yeah.
I think I would maybe argue that it is the, uh, that it is the absolute, uh, and I'm
going to, I'll wrap it there cause we're running a little long, uh, but thank you, Mumble Room.
I would argue that I think it is maybe the strongest premiere of any Star Trek.
Uh, and it does, you know, the show like all Star Treks gets better, um, as, as it goes
on.
But I think, you know, if you look at TNG, there's, there's a lot, you know, you've got,
you've got Deanna in a cheerleader uniform.
You've got Wesley who's just derping up all over the place, right?
And by the way, I got a lot of respect for how they handle Jake throughout this whole
series, but specifically here, there's a strong connection.
Like when Cisco gets back on the station and, you know, Jake sees him for the first time.
I mean, I, that was touching to me as a dad.
I thought they'd handled that really well.
And instead of making Jake Wesley 2.0 or Echeb from Voyager, they handled them really well.
And it's typically Star Trek really screws up kids really bad.
They get it wrong a lot.
And I don't feel like they did.
Echeb's a great example there cause that was just, that was terrible.
So, yeah.
Uh, so I felt like as far as strong openings go, yeah, some of the acting was a little
rough because it's their first episode, but the effects were solid, the concepts were
great.
Um, and the execution was powerful and it, except for it moved, moved, moved, and then
wormhole.
All the scenes outside the wormhole, I really liked it.
As soon as we get into the wormhole, I don't know, maybe I just need to get really stoned
and maybe have a few beers or something.
But as I'm sitting there watching this, I'm like, come on, this is two hours.
You really got to spend this much time on here, but overall, I enjoyed it.
All right, Matt.
So I know this hasn't been popular with everyone, so we will do another straw poll.
I have linked it in the show notes right now.
So we will have two straw polls this week.
The one that the people in the download and stream versions can watch later, we'll have
the voting poll to see if we should do this again.
So in the Deep Space Nine challenge, there will be a link at the top of that for the
straw poll and you go there and you vote if you want us to do this again next week.
And if we get, uh, if the yeses have it, then we will do episode three of DS9.
If the nopes have it, we'll drop it there and we'll just stick to other stuff.
But I thought it was kind of fun and it's, I think there's benefits from time to time
to taking our same community and all the, all of the people who hold similar interests
and exploring other topics and, and, and going into other things that we all enjoy because
it is good to get out of that bubble and it is still good to have the chat and the discussion
and get people thinking.
And it's, it's also just kind of a fun way to get people to get into DS9 if they haven't
been there before.
So it's, it's, I, but I understand it might not be popular.
So if people don't like it, we don't have to do it next time.
Super quick piece of advice before I let it go.
If you watched it back when it aired, forget everything you ever watched, watch it commercial
free on Netflix.
It's a completely different experience.
I really felt like I, I really felt like I watched a different show in some ways.
Yeah.
All right.
So here we go.
But before we run our final, our final tally for a Sunday's topic, Friday edition, or I'm
sorry, Friday's topic, Friday edition of the Linux action show Trek meets Linux or taking
great notes on Linux.
And the notes have it with, I did not expect that with 43 votes, 56%.
Well, I wouldn't be surprised if there's a few Star Trek app picks that work their way
into the episode anyways.
You know what I'm saying, Matt?
I know what you're saying.
Okay.
All right.
I can do the note thing.
I got a couple of good note apps.
You and I will share notes after the show.
All right.
Yeah.
You get what I'm saying, Matt?
I get what you're saying.
Um, so yeah, just a little reminder, we'll be doing Friday, uh, edition of Linux action
show at 10 a.m. Pacific over at jblive.tv.
No show on Sunday, but it actually should be available for download hopefully around
the regular lifetime.
So you've got to just watch it on demand and, uh, enjoy it that way.
All right.
Well, uh, thanks to the mumble room.
Hey guys, thanks for joining us today.
You guys were awesome.
I'm going to mute you here in a bit, but, uh, we'll chat some more after the show.
We keep going a little bit after the show and, uh, we'll, uh, share some more thoughts
and don't forget, we'd love to get more con more, uh, more topics, more, uh, concepts
to kick around.
You can submit a lot of those, any of those really to linuxactionshow.reddit.com.
It's a great place to get things into the show because now the things, now that we've
got two places to cover some of this stuff, stuff that doesn't make it into the big show
might still make it into here.
So stuff's got double the shot to make it into the show.
Matt, you have a great week.
Enjoy your ramp up to the big day.
I will.
Thank you for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
I hope we see you back here.
Don't forget to go vote in that straw poll if you liked it or didn't like it because
it's going to depend on your vote.
So you got to show up and vote.
We'll have a link to that in the show notes, right under the deep space nine challenge,
as well as links to where you can stream deep space nine online.
If you have access to us servers, if you get what I'm saying with that, all right, everyone,
thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of unplugged.
We'll see you right back here next week.