Check this out West found it wiki house. It's an open source project to reinvent the way we make homes
It's being developed by architects designers engineers inventors manufacturers builders
Collaborating develop the best simplest most sustainable high-performance building technologies that anyone can use. This is kind of an awesome project
They're like on their fourth and a half iteration right now of it
This video gives you a little bit of details about it here
This is the team we're at the beginning of an industrial revolution which is allowing us to use the web and digital tools
To make it much much simpler to design homes that are customized to each of us
So they're showing a website where you go in and kind of customize the home and it creates the like the printing spec that can even
Be locally printed using digital manufacturing tools and then simply assembled even by small businesses and homeowners themselves
really robust sustainable beautiful homes that has the potential to fundamentally change the rules of
How we make houses in Britain instead of selling the land to just one developer
We divide sites up into plots to be bought or rented
Directly by local families at a price that they can afford together with the local planners
The community would develop an outline
Neighborhood plan and a basic set of design rules as long as you stay within the rules
You can build modify or extend without having to get any further planning permission from the council
That's residents are then free to create their own homes using any building method supported by not just one or even ten companies
But hundreds of companies so I watched a couple of videos they have on YouTube from a couple
One of the ones I watched was a couple that made a house and they said that there's the first time they've ever done anything
Like this, but the thing that was really awesome for them was that there were so many other community members that built a house before
Them where they had found something that didn't work quite right or made little changes
And so the by the time they were on version 4 another beyond the version they were even using
There were so many little things as they were so many like, oh, I'm so glad somebody thought of that
I'm so glad somebody thought of that. It's awesome. And it's kind of like how you would share a 3d printing spec. Totally
Really neat. So it's a wiki house dot CC
Yeah, I don't know
I part of me loves the whole tiny house thing because I think sometimes
People just by default think they need some huge palace to live in when you could probably get by with a lot less and have
A lot less to have to manage and keep up, you know, keep clean and keep on top of repairs
I think a small house could work for a lot of people
But if you're somebody like me, I'd have nowhere no idea where to start
Wiki house dot CC seemed kind of fun an open-source house. I'd like to see what some of these finished houses look like
Somebody build one and let us know. Yeah, there we go. Come on audience
This is Linux unplugged episode
188 for March 14th, 2017
Oh
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's so excited about Pi Day. It's borderline obnoxious
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello, Wes. It is a big day today. Not just Pi Day
It's a major birthday of 23 years today and nobody's talking about it. Do you agree?
Yeah, no, we literally had to fact-check it three different places because nobody's nobody's talking about it
Well, we're gonna talk about today on the show. It's a big deal. We're gonna get into that. Plus, are you ready for the challenge?
I have no idea. I like that honest answer, Wes. On Pi Day
We thought what would be better than Mycroft on a Raspberry Pi?
How about Mycroft and Alexa on a cancel on a Raspberry Pi?
cancel
We're gonna try to load them both Mycroft and the echo software platform on a Raspberry Pi
Live on the show and see if we can create the ultimate
personal assistant powered by a Raspberry Pi on Pi Day plus we're gonna give you an update on some of our favorite open source projects that
we follow every single week and then
Despite Wimpy's denial
VR on Linux
Had a big boost this week. It actually ladies and gentlemen, may be crossing into the legitimate territory
What what I know I I did not actually think I'd be saying that on this show anytime soon
But I we got everything from gaming to creating a VR Linux desktop
Yeah, and also those people who say AR is the future
We're gonna talk about that too wimpy
I mean, we'll be talking about that later on in the show and we're gonna wrap it
We're gonna wrap it wrap it all up with a celebration of 23 years of the official release of
The Linux kernel and only in the only way your Linux unplugged show could the only way so we got a really big show
So big so let's real big great show ever great best show ever
So let's bring in our mumble room to make it all happen time-appropriate greetings virtual lug how
Hello everybody it is good
Alexa and stop. I'm not talking to her. Did you she's very eager to gosh?
I I feel like something to prove I feel like she's getting triggered more today than she ever has before
I think she wants to be in the show. She wants yeah, she should dial into the mumble room
Well guys I want to start with I we always like to open the show with some of our favorite open source project
And there's nothing too much higher on that list except for maybe comp isn't barrel
It's the matte desktop, and we have a big release version one dot one eight
released
just yesterday
Martin Wimperth, I'm not familiar with who Martin is but maybe wimpy could help us understand
What's new and mate one dot one eight hello wimpy hello there? How you doing good good?
And very excited about the new release it seems like the March towards gtk3 continues, right?
Well the March towards gtk3 or completing it. I should say yeah
So we're finally there as in everything is now only
buildable with gtk3 and
any of the remaining GTK to support code that we had kicking around has been ejected and
the
One dot one eight release has really been focused around
Cleaning up that gtk3 implementation. There's still a bit of work to do, but this is a huge step forwards
On a number of fronts bringing the whole underpinnings up to date
Fat and it looks like oh hi there. It looks like it's based on three dot fourteen is that right?
It supports gtk3 14 and up. Oh, I see that's what it. That's the lowest I see
That's the lowest it will support yeah, but it supports all the way up to three two two
Notifications now implemented awesome lock screen will load the user selected background very nice new features
Yeah, that one. I think is probably going to be about the most popular. Which one's that?
the
Setting the lock screen on to whatever the selected backdrop is rather than the system really really we've had people asking
Things everyone notices I suppose
it's it's a curious one because
Where that where that image is set it runs in a in a
Process with elevated permissions, so the reason that we hadn't done it for such a long time is there were security considerations
So had to be done properly which it has been done
So now when you change your backdrop, and you lock the screen that is the backdrop
You'll see on the lock screen which is a small thing, but lots of people have been asking for that for ages
So this I believe also is landing in 1704 so anyone that will have a point to 1704
Will have a point to one dot one eight is it my m is that right am I getting that wrong?
Yeah, it has landed in fact. Oh it has already
Yeah, it's it's it's landed at some point today, but yeah, it's all in there now
So if you're running the up into Marte 1704 alpha
Yeah, and you apt update and apt upgrade you'll you'll get all of this stuff now now
Was there a debate to go directly to two?
Well, yeah, so yeah, yeah
I I was myself and the fedora maintainer were keen that we call this to do. Oh, yeah, okay?
That's my thought you know democracy is king
There was a 50-50 split on on the vote as to whether we were going to go to dot naught and I decided that
It wasn't worth it wasn't worth fighting over so step down
So this is one dot one eight
But this has got all of the features in it that we discussed when I was I was trying to push the agenda and say
That this should be a 2.0. Release. Well, I suppose it's it makes it seem less of a big change
Which is probably comfortable to imitate users and some just some degree to some. Yeah
Yeah, some of the other developers feel that it needs some a bigger significant
Step forward in terms of technology support for it to be a 2.0
So they're suggesting that the 2.0 will only come when?
When Wayland is supported so that could be some time
Interesting idea though. We get there interesting. That's the same thing as like that, you know, Linux 2.7
hundred and fifty
Yeah, it's gonna result in the same kind of ridiculous thing
Joe you had a point about the shifting sands of GTK. I want to hear that
Yes, so Martin good to speak to you on this show one of the many we've spoken to each other on
But GTK it seems to me is just a constantly shifting sand
Isn't it where you you you seem to not be able to be sure exactly?
Which one's going to be the stable version and stuff? So that must factor into your decisions
In terms of porting it to GTK 3 and finalizing things and making things stable as Marte is famously known for
Yeah, so the we've been you know
Struggling with keeping pace at the at the rate of change in the GTK 3 toolkit for a number of years
But with GTK 3 2 2 that is now
Behind us. So GTK 3 2 2 is now
That is now behind us. So GTK 3 2 2 is going to remain the same
There's not going to be a 3 2 4 3 2 2 is just going to get point releases that fix stuff
But no API or API changes as far as as far as I'm aware
so the Marte desktop is going to or at least what we've discussed is stick to GTK 3 2 2 now because
Because we can stabilize and coalesce around that and refine what we've been working towards
And there's a lot of good stuff that we can still enable
on top of GTK 3 2 2
And GTK 4 is just around the corner
But the GTK developers have made it clear that GTK 4 is going to be
a very much iterative development with lots of API and ABI changes in the early versions
and that they will
Make it clear when a GTK 4 release
Gets to an API stable version
So it's not how things have been in the past where they've you know attempted to maintain or that with GTK 3
This is part of the problem why that why they're changing this in GTK 4
But they're not going to try and maintain stability in GTK 4. It is going to be very much rapid and right
All things are going to change for quite some time. So
Not a platform we're going to target because we've been living with that for a number of years
And we now just want a quiet life and just want to just clean things up and maybe add a few features rather than keep on fighting
You know the constant change in the API
So I also had a little inclination that perhaps we should oh is it chillin? It's chillin, right?
Ubuntu chillin. We should follow up on that because was it was it two three weeks ago you and I were talking about it
And I think what sort of piqued your interest. Do you have any updates on that particular project for us?
Yeah, so um, i've i've spoken to a couple of guys from the chillin team
So when we last spoke whenever it was a few weeks back
They'd obviously announced that they had um forked. Uh,
Some big chunk of Marte and called it UK UI
And that they'd given it very much a windows-esque look and feel
And this was going to be the new default in uh, Ubuntu chillin, which is the distro that's specifically made for the Chinese market
Um and working with them what we've been able to do is instead of forking like a
We've been able to do is instead of forking like all the things we've now got that down to just seven packages
so they're forking seven packages and
I think two of them are actually
um, not so much forks but
derivative works, um in their own right so that they don't really count so there's five packages that are forks of Marte
Um, so what that means is that they're going to be sitting on top of most of the Marte stack with just a few packages
Um that they need so obviously they need their own session manager because they need to identify as their own desktop session
and
most of the other
Uh packages that they've forked things like i'm not quite sure how it's pronounced but peony or peony or something like that
Which is their file manager?
which is forked from kaja and
um
That we're simply not going to accept the the changes that they've made upstream because they've basically made it look exactly like windows explorer
Which just doesn't fit with you know, what Marte is setting out to do
So there are some things that they're just going to fork they're going to maintain that themselves and it's fair enough
Um, but then most of the other stuff they're going to sit on all of the same underpinnings
So they will get to benefit from this new
Uh Marte release in 1704 because that's going to be the first release of Ubuntu chillin
That features the new uk ui desktop
So um, they get a new
new uh set of packages as well
So they uh, they've they've modified it to look more like explorer. That's interesting
I wonder if they'll also update it to include the new ads that windows 10
Oh, i'm kidding
So wimpy, how has it gone just communicating with them?
Has it been is it been fairly effective and efficient and they seem to be receptive to talking to you. Yeah
Yeah, it's been great. So they filed a bug in launchpad that outlined everything that they wanted to fork
um
and there's another guy who works on Ubuntu gnome and he's also one of the um,
Uh the community developers for on the on the desktop side of things as well
So jeremy beecher and he's he's been helping them as well. So we responded on the
um on their bug and basically said do you need to fork all of this stuff and here's some ideas about how you can
save yourself some effort and
just
Use some of the facilities that they exist in marte so that you don't have to fork everything
So we talked through there and and I said, you know, come and join us in irc. This is our channel
These are the people you want to talk to which they did
So we've had a good a good discussion with them and um, yeah, uh, I don't know that we'll be
Closely collaborating. I think they've got a lot on at the moment to try and get this first release out
And then after the first release out is out for them. I'm going to go back to them and see if I can get them more
More involved with with marta as a whole because obviously they're they're going to be using great chunks of it
And it'll be nice to see
If they get a lot of users on it, too
It'd be good to get some of their observations and bug fixes or at least bugs they find
I've heard there's quite a lot of people in china. Yeah, and there's quite a lot of people using Ubuntu
Yeah, definitely
China seems like you could get some good feedback and input at least if nothing else indeed indeed. That's fascinating
I I wanted to uh shift gears and talk about uh rising just for a second
But it was actually following up to something that uh poppy and wimpy
Were discussing on the uh latest episode of the ubuntu podcast of the new season. Yeah, and it's something we touched on too
A little bit and it's it's rising and I wanted to I wanted to pick your guys's brains. Uh, specifically around
We so your ubuntu podcast covered it and I think we discussed it on
It was either this last little linux action show or the one before I can't remember exactly because we pre-recorded a couple of them
uh, and I I noticed that
Hoping you seem to sort of shrug it off. But the more i've thought about this. I really think that perhaps amd might be willing to make
a big
A big product differentiating change here. Uh, and so what do you think poppy? Do you think we could be?
Looking at the at the possibility of amd stepping up and saying we're going to take the amd control processor
We're going to take some of our binary blobs and we're going to open source them and not just for the desktop
But maybe also for server and other uses do you think it could happen?
I'd love to see it and I feel a bit jaded because I've heard
Numerous times that amd are going to do the next big thing and you know this next
Product that they're going to come out with it's going to be open source. It's all going to be clean and it's going to be
The thing that's going to kill nvidia or it's it's it's the thing you want to put in your computer and
I just don't I just don't because I don't trust them. I don't trust them
To deliver on what they keep saying they're going to deliver
But do you think it also betrays the fact that perhaps there has been some internal discussions and debating and they feel like it's something
They should do but I can't quite figure out how to pull the trigger
And that was exciting to be able to see, you know a conversation on reddit turn into a ceo level conversation
Yeah, that's great. And I hope it follows through. I hope it doesn't just die as yet
Another project internal to the company that you doesn't actually materialize or they realize well actually there aren't that many desktop linux users
So we don't really care. It just seems like even if they didn't even if they didn't care about the desktop
Even if they didn't care about the desktop if they just totally ignored the desktop the benefits of doing the server side for gpu-based
Tasks and entire server systems built using amd's whole platform
It feels like they would they would almost become the default for really reliable completely open
And and by the way by completely open also means auditable linux servers
I would love that to happen. I'm just not holding my breath. Yeah
Yeah, okay. All right. It feels like to me and I hate to use this term because it kind of feels like a debug term
But in the post-snowden quote-unquote or the post vault 7 reality
If I want a highly confidential highly secure cloud server, I would like to have something that is
From the blobs that run the hardware all the way up to the code that runs my web server
And the web apps that run on top of it
I would like to be able to audit that especially if i'm a government institution or or a non-profit of some type that might be
In the political light. I feel like this is this was the market pressure would almost would almost just
Handsomely reward amd enough to make it worth it just in the server area alone. I could be wrong
Does anybody else in the moment have a sense of that before we move on?
I'm, pretty excited about ryzen, even though I don't have any intentions of buying. In fact, I may be buying a
A 1080 graphics card from nvidia pretty soon actually for just a vr, but i'll save that for later
All right, so what happens?
I share poppy skepticism because it said the same thing in 2009
And I think I kept believing that right up until vulkan came out. Yeah for every other platform, but amd
Yeah, I I agree. Joe you were going to say something too
Yeah, I was going to say what happens when they do their next deal with microsoft or sony for playstation or xbox?
And have to put a processor in one of those
You can be sure right. They are not going to want that stuff to be open source, right?
Right. I just really would love to see some solid competition to intel because it's not just the graphics, right?
It could be it could be the whole platform would be so I agree
I'm trying not to get too excited about it, but just the idea and who knows how accurate it is and perhaps I
Sorry, chris in a dream world. Yes. I agree. I would love this. I would love for it to be yes
The comp the compute platform of choice, right?
Like whether it's you know, you could throw out your intel cpus throw out your proprietary nvidia drivers and you could go all in
amd and have your racks full of
CUDA cores doing all your compute and you could be super happy with everything being open source and auditable
I'm
Yeah, imagine really 4k gaming and vr with uh open source amd drivers, right? That is surely the dream
Yes, joe joe you mispronounced ar there
There it is
We're getting there. We're getting there
Yeah, okay, um, so ryzen's an interesting development from amd, but I think it's most interesting, um in for server use because
What you're getting is something that's a little bit cheaper
Um almost equivalent, um in terms of compute power not quite intel can best it in in in most areas by just a smidge
But the big thing the big thing at the data center is is power
And this these new ryzen chips are significantly lower power than the equivalent intel. That's a great point
So I think that's where it matters and likewise if amd have any aspirations to
Uh make their uh cpus available through libre boot or core boot or whatever
Um, then it makes most sense in the server market because the linux desktop market share just isn't big enough to warrant them
Uh putting that time and effort in but they could be persuaded that on servers
There's there's some benefit to that imagine a world
Just just just because often you'll see well, why do we want commercial software on the linux?
Desktop, why do we care if we have more users for linux desktop? Maybe it should just be for us technical people
We'll have a haven of an os built for us. Oh, that sounds nice. Yeah, it does
But imagine for a moment if you will ladies and gentlemen, let's imagineer that adobe has released photoshop premiere and after effects on linux
If this is the if that if those applications existed on the linux desktop amd would probably be all in on doing this
This would be an obvious decision for them because they would want to dominate that workstation market
So that's why I say like I don't I at the end of the day
I don't necessarily want a desktop full of closed source applications on my linux desktop
But if we got a couple of market dominating applications for a couple of segments
Then all of a sudden there is a lot more reason to invest in the desktop platform and right now our best in
Is the server or mobile market and we hope to god that there's a trickle down effect that applies to us desktop users
That's what we have right now. And if we had a couple of just totally category owning applications
that demanded
Great hardware. You would see companies like amd tripping over themselves to deliver this and we're just we just we're not there yet
What were we talking about dream worlds a little bit? Yeah. Yeah, I know well, even if you look at it
Seems like it should be an adobe's best interest unless they feel like distributing uh photoshop via the microsoft app store one day
It seems like it should be obvious
They should be seeing the same lights that valve is seeing the same warnings
But we're going to get there actually in just a moment. Uh, but
Yeah, yeah, maybe I maybe my uh, maybe my linux goggles are just too rose-colored for me to understand why they don't do it
But I tell you what, uh, there is like a suggestion why they don't do it. What is it?
Package distribution is a massive pain. Yeah, I know but it's that that is actually solvable
It is it really is it's not perfect, but it's it's not only is there things like snaps
But there's also just target an lts of buntu. I was gonna say that does seem to be like a it's not ideal
But it does mostly just every other distro will figure it out
They would have to be like, you know
Dealing with a bunch of hate from us to like so many people like oh, why are you picking me?
I disagree. I wouldn't I agree deal with hate from a very small minority people who would never run their software and the professional market
Would not care
Yeah, plus stick it on ubuntu and what's going to happen people are going to port it to arch and exactly
Yeah, there'll be an aur in 15 minutes that pulls down the deb and installs it on my arch box
That's just you know, that's why also if you look at what valve did where they just created an ubuntu runtime inside their directory structure
And now they just did they just held their directory structure and they just they just held their directory structure
And now they just did they just held they have all of their folks play target to that and that works fine
Adobe could do that adobe could create a horribly out of date runtime environment full of libraries
They do not take advantage of the latest features of my system and they could target that and make applications
For all the linux desktops that would still be 20 times better in performance than they are on windows
snaps is a new lsb
I would also take a snap. I would even I would even take an app image
I I I tell you there is hardware out there now like the oryx pro and the xps 15
That if I had a competent video editing software and and and compositing software besides blender
I would pull the trigger. I would pull the trigger
I would I would not be doing the show right now. I'd be buying that hardware. I would pull the trigger so hard
I just would love to see it and then maybe that we'd have a viable platform, you know for real creative professionals
You can put some elementary on there if you had that lts support. I love that. I love it
So we're gonna we're gonna get into valve here in a moment and also our old friend sync thing
Some interesting. Yeah, some interesting numbers from syncing in a while since he's come around, but yeah, it's back. Yeah. Yeah
It's back in town. Yes visiting the pacific northwest all synced up
We're gonna sync up with yeah, that's right. I see what you did there west that's that's pretty good
First we're going to talk about linux academy at linuxacademy.com
Unplugged go there to support the show and sign up for a free seven-day trial a free seven-day trial of a platform
to help expand your mind about linux linux the nitty itty bitty details and also
The really big heady stuff built around linux like that open stack azure containers
Infrastructure management they make it all really accessible
whatever it is, if you're just learning how to manage a firewall on a linux box or
Browse the directory or if you want to go all in on the really huge topics
They've got self-paced in-depth video courses
They have labs give you hands-on experience instructor mentoring when you need it
I don't know what to call it because the platform feels like something that is
Like like like a platform sounds like something you do to to to connect a whole bunch of stuff and sell stuff
Like it's not a it's it is a learning. It is well, you know what? It's an online academy. That's what it is
Whether you're an experienced sysadmin or new to the world of linux azure and aws open stack and devops
A sharp skill set is an absolute necessity to succeed meet linux academy an online linux and cloud training platform
That uses self-paced video courses and hands-on labs to give you real world experience for a wide range of skills
Trained for your certification learn the latest devops tools and grow your skill set to do better work
Linux academy is not just a video library our scenario based server labs and quiz system allow you to learn hands-on
We also have full-time human instructors who answer questions and help you earn that certification or promotion at work
We add new training every week. So you'll always be up to date on the latest tech
Sysadmins of every experience level use linux academy to stay on the bleeding edge of the linux ecosystem. You should too
I've never installed gnu
linuxacademy.com
Plugs where you go to support the show sign up for a free seven-day trial check out some of their downloadable comprehensive study guides
The vibrant community packed full of jupiter broadcasting members the course scheduler that works with your busy schedule
The note cards that get forked and improved by those very community members and of course the instructor mentoring the real humans that help you
When you need it at linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged. Okay before we get into the sync thing. Hey, hey wes. How's it going out there?
Yeah, yeah, you're doing it. He's got a raspberry pi. Why are you doing it in the other room wes?
Are you using the tv out there for your screen hilarious? That's awesome. I feel like I should take a picture of that
So, uh, what do you have right now on the raspberry pi right now? We've got a minecraft
It should maybe be working. I might need to restart it. I just plugged in the microphone
I brought for it. Oh good thinking, but it's all paired up with their online service now
So good so the step is alexa if that's working
So the minecraft portions might might be working right? That's awesome. All right. Well, we'll check back in good work
I mean, that's it. Nice. That's a nice that's that's a pretty good accomplishment right there wes i'm impressed already
So sync thing has published some I don't I I think this is new data dot sync thing net
It's new to me at least and they're showing the total number of unique users that have reporting turned on which by the way
Not on my default
uh, and uh, it's fascinating because what it basically shows is a
consistent with the exception of uh, the release from dot 9 to dot 10 a consistent trend line of growth
Uh new users joining every single day growing
Uh each version getting more downloads than the last version files managed per device growing
Memory usage growing. Haha, I get it. So, uh, I thought actually
in in the age of of
Uh constantly talking about how dropbox is this or dropbox is that or libre vault's gonna be or libre vault can't be
I thought it was interesting to go back and revisit our old friend sync thing and see how active it actually appears to be
um with uh
Nearly now 30 000 unique users that have data reporting on per day
Active not bad
Yeah
Yeah, I saw some discussion about this too. Like some folks are saying there's not very many relay servers still so uh,
Uh one guy's got one going on digital ocean and it's like on the san francisco data center
It's like one of the most popular on the west coast
Oh, wow, not that many running
So people are working on setting up containers with the relays in there to help make it easier for people to throw those up
Yeah, have you messed with it at all sync thing? Have you ever have you been I still have a couple things going
They've just been running. Yes, uh
Very much in the background. So this is actually a good motivator for me to kind of
Check back in with that. See I mean it's all been working because I use it
Uh, but really it's just a way to easily shuffle files around right now. Mm-hmm
Wimpy, you know i've got to ask. Oh, go ahead
I use it every day. You are you are producer michael. Ladies and gentlemen to the rescue every day. Tell me about it
I use it to sync all my some config files for multiple computers and also for a
Custom to do system that I built and uh, it syncs through my phone through multiple computers and a pie
on a pie now is there um
Um, yeah
Is there ever any issue of like, uh?
You have the same program running on two computers at once and the and the config files are getting written to by both programs
Uh, no because you can set it to be one as a master. So if there's a conflict it always pulls from the main one
That's it
That's exactly what i've thought about using sync thing because the nice thing about sync thing as opposed to something like dropbox
Is you can have sync thing look at any folder on your file system
So multiple sync folders. Yes. Yeah
I and the best part is that you don't have to have like a specific
Um folder for this you can just pick one random. So I don't I don't have a sync thing
Uh infrastructure in this like you just go in and say you can actually
Create like ids for each folder so you can have a different name for the different folder on the thing
As long as the sync idea is the same
That's a good tip
Wimby do you have anything to contribute to the sync conversation before we move on because I always go to you
But I don't know if there's much you have
I haven't used sync thing in ages because I switched to a different solution for what I was using
Any updates or anything you want to share with the class or nothing in particular?
No, not about sync thing. I can't add anything about syncing in general. I can't remember what you switched to
Uh, well my my use case for sync thing and bit torrent sync before it was to sync
Dot files and stuff like that and i'm now using yadim, which is yet another dot manager and uh, that's git based
And that's right brilliant. That's what i've been thinking about using too is something git based
I hadn't had a oh look into that. Thank you. Yeah, it was great. All right, so let's talk about your favorite subject. Um,
I feel like we well, you know, I feel like we can we can talk about it now
We can you want do you want i'll give you a little more time i'm gonna give you a little more time
Let's talk about vr on linux. Oh, yeah, let's do it. Let's do it. Let's do it
I got an htc vive sitting in the other room right now. So I feel like uh, I just got to bring it all out
Uh, so valve starting with this particular story not necessarily directly vr but probably going to play in a little bit valve has hired
Another developer who a well a well-known one too keith packard
He's worked on the x windows system in the past
He worked for intel then he moved to hp and now he's at valve to continue development on the linux driver stack for graphics
So that's a bit of news. Yeah, it's a bit of news right there. So that's something that I thought was worth mentioning also
um
Steam vr has gotten some update builds for steam vr beta now with linux support. Ladies and gentlemen
valve has pushed out linux support for their steam vr
And uh, they've set up a couple of different resources that I want to point you to if you're trying to make this work
Number one is they have a github issues tracker for the valve software account
Which I have linked in the show notes
And there are some community threads in the steam vr group specific to linux. I have those linked as well
If you're on arch, I also have a warning for you
It looks like there is currently an issue with the invidia beta driver
Which is required to use steam vr and the module failing to build for the arch kernel 4.10
So if you're on arch and you want to play with steam vr
It looks like you need to use the lts kernel on arch for now because that module will build
That's that seems to be one issue right now because you have to be on a fairly recent
Kernel and you have to be on the beta version of the invidia driver and you have to have something that supports balkan
Balkan so that is uh, that is sort of the state of steam vr right now
And it looks like also there is sort of uh at the same time
A really interesting write-up about somebody who decided to modify a few programs
Chain a few things together and create a vr workspace for linux
And it's kind of fascinating how he did it. He said first
I needed to figure out a way to capture the images running on my desktop
There's a lot of ways to do that. So I ran the xypher display server
Then I had this thing set up to take screenshots which used some python scripts
The screenshots are handled and are base64 encoded
He made those images available for a smartphone with through a data distribution service. He chose crossbar
The crossbar system is a networking platform for real-time applications
It has a static web server built in which can be used to distribute javascript to a smartphone
So then his smartphone client then connects to crossbar or whatever
Whatever the in-between thing is could be the linux client could be anything connects to crossbar
It feeds the images from something uh from from the system and it titles them as topics
So then crossbar is configured around the web server and it runs on port 80 80
Then you point your machine at that on the same network you open, you know ip address port 80 80 and it's set up to run
linux desktop applications
In vr now, I just blew through all that because there's no way i'm going to walk you through all of the python code
That he set up and stuff like that
But we do have it linked in the show notes a way to take individual apps
And project them into vr using any kind of anything from the vive to google cardboard
And uh, so he looks at things like stellaris and uh and apps like that to uh as a way to take advantage of this now
having listened to uh, episode one of season 10 of the ubuntu podcast
I heard wimpy talk about his uh experience with augmented reality and I heard wimpy proclaim
That augmented reality was the future and the vr was not going to be the future and I have to I have to strongly
strongly disagree because a I will present that I believe what wimpy was experiencing was in fact virtual reality and not
Augmented reality because there was no jet engine in the room. It created the entire jet engine from a virtual reality
So a I would I would argue wimpy did not in fact experience augmented reality and b
Are two which I forget which mechanism i'm using I would argue that
That ar and vr are not mutually exclusive and that they may be more closer to the same thing than that's not a coke
And pepsi competition is what i'm trying to say now. I look at this. I look at steam vr
I look at the fact that you have even just these
easily
Put together methods to put some sort of rudimentary vr experience together and I say to you with htc vive shipping
With steam vr shipping and with systems like this that even work with simple applications like vr cardboard simple
vr has arrived for linux
With all due respect chris you're wrong. Okay, tell me
That's why we like yeah
Is an ar system because while the jet engine isn't in the room you can see through the glasses and the yeah
um, the user interface is on the wall so you can glance up at the wall and
Navigate through the menus. They're over on the wall over there. So you could leave them on the wall
Oh, I like that
But couldn't they do that in a virtual room just as well
You could but you can't see what's what's around you because with vr, but the jet engine isn't there?
No, but with vr nothing is there with
The table what you made everything around you is there okay what you may not have gleaned from the the demo that I
I got to do was
Uh, the use case is i'm a jet engine repair man
There is a jet engine in the room
And I want to bring up this vr overlay sure and the service manuals in front of me
as part of
the additional context to what i'm doing and the idea here is that as a maintenance
engineer you have access to stuff in front of you immediately and
And you can reference that and the hope is that there will be fewer human errors when you're doing these sort of maintenance
Operations because all of the information you need is available to you and you can check out
Uh where the parts are on the virtual model before you actually go and start, you know
Spanning the real engine. I like that. I would I would say two things. Number one. I would say, uh,
Uh, I feel like you could still do all of that in vr. You would have a headset on you wouldn't see through it
But there would be sensors that would be aware of the physical shape of the object
And they would that physical shape would be represented in the virtual reality that would be proportional to the actual object
But that said i'm really just playing devil's advocate because to me ar does seem to make way more sense
Especially in the industrial applications where you have a known setup
It's maybe a factory or it's a jet engine or whatever
It's it's a reactor even and but it is it is always in this spot in the room
It is always this dimension. It always has these components. It always has these attributes
And and that to me seems like a much more achievable
Practical a practical application of this technology simply because
Those variables are locked down and they're known quantities when you have people's homes
where you'll never know the layout and the lighting is always going to be different and the colors are always going to be different and
The and all of these all of these random variables. I think that's where ar begins to break down and vr will be stronger
Can I just find an analogy that I often like to go to right and that is with networking
Okay
It took quite a few years for us to get
wired networking perfect with the tcp ip stack and all that kind of stuff and we got to gigabit and
And all that kind of stuff and now that's working perfectly
and beyond and then
In parallel we were also working on wireless and we got to um, you know g and n and then ac and beyond
and it feels like
ar is wireless wi-fi and
Vr is wired and they're kind of two ways to look at the same. That's how I see it
That's a that's a great analogy. I really do see it as two almost complementary technologies in some sense
They are complementary, but they're not the same
Right. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, but the wireless isn't the same as wired, but they they're still complementary and you you kind of
Need to to build that base of virtual reality first I feel and perfect that
And then once you have that then you introduce cameras and blending of that into the rest of reality
And and that's when it's going to be truly useful. Also, don't you think virtual reality seems more applicable to entertainment?
Games movies porn perhaps whereas augmented reality seems more applicable to industrial applications
Or getting getting work done or even here in the studio west wouldn't it be nice to have ar
Overlaid on the equipment when you're setting up for tech snap. Absolutely
I want to jump in here because there's there's a key point that you're missing and and you're right you're talking about
Using it in the home, right? So at the moment if you've got a vive you've got to blindfold yourself and tether yourself to a computer
Yep, and then stand in a room big enough that can accommodate all of the other poles and things
Yeah
Yeah, so you need a very much actually that's that is legitimately a problem. Yeah, so you talk about entertainment
I don't think any of that is particularly entertaining and also it's kind of solitary because
Doing that with two people. Basically, you're just going to chin each other aren't you? I mean you you're going to be walking around blind
Hang on. Hang on wimpy. Hang on yours. You're trying to tell me that people don't want to play games on their own
Connected to a billion other people in the world
Uh now, I know they like to play with the other person in the room
Well, I I mean, let's not let's not forget I two
Really apparently smart individuals would seem to think people are very interested in this and that would be mark zuckerberg and gabien
They both seem to agree that people are going to want to put these full visors on and be completely
Lost in this virtual holodeck
So yeah, it's like you're sitting in front of your workstation your battle station. It's it's very similar. There are a few people
There is there's a niche of people who are going to want to do that
But probably more mainstream is more like the wii where it's kind of more cartooning
You've got these motion controllers and and now with the switch and stuff like that. So it feels like there are two markets there
But the the ar headset I had on a couple of weeks ago
Was was a helmet it you you wore it like um a hard hat. Okay?
Um, there were no cables. There were no wires. The whole thing was self-powered running a boon
And and I wasn't blindfolded. I could see everyone and everything around me
And I was also able to see
The 3d images that this thing was projecting into a space that I could move around it and interact with it
That to me is light years more compelling than being
tethered and blindfolded and
Not being able to see what's going on. And whilst I agree. There's an application for vr for gaming. I I can totally see that
At the moment. I haven't actually seen any compelling game. I'm not a big gamer, but I haven't seen any compelling games
That utilize vr at the moment. We just have a shitload of tech demos
I-racing is amazing. I but I think wimby. I did one compelling. Yeah, I kind of take your point there
I take your point there overall to be that is true. Like I I can't I can't I can't articulate
The absolutely killer app for vr. I I am interested in this why it's just really quickly blasted through it a few minutes ago
I am kind of interested in
In what I could do with vr and and my desktop just for a little bit
Do with vr and and my desktop just from like a maybe a content creation standpoint
But that's so far down the road. It doesn't really seem
And ar may be even better for that. I don't I grant you I can conceptualize the the real good use cases for ar
Uh much easier and that's why i've been more of a kind of more of on that side of the fence
But I i've come to see it more like joe's with joe's analogy is wireless and an ethernet
Uh, I I think vr the time the time I was really blown away by vr
It was sort of a hippie good feeling experience where I I got the oculus dk2
I put it on my head. I put on headphones and there's like tech demos same stuff tech demos
And so what tech demo did I try? Well, I tried they go float on a raft in the middle of the ocean tech demo
and um, I think it's in part because I had had headphones on so it was a more immersive experience, but
I I took that off after five minutes and I felt like I just meditated for 30 minutes
It was a really powerful sort of like holy shit. I really kind of
not all of me, but
50 percent of me maybe even 40 percent of me felt like I was actually on a raft in the middle of the ocean
And that was uh, that was a pretty intense experience. It took you out of where you were
Yeah, because I was actually in this room. Yeah, but it uh, that was a pretty so and then and then I
Then because I was so impacted by it. I then wanted everybody around me to try it
So I then I put the helmet on there. I try this. Oh, you think it's crazy
People were generally pretty impressed. Uh, I saw intense experiences a second
Um, what was it that made vhs successful over beta max?
And what was it that made uh blu-ray successful over hd dvd?
Speaking of intense experiences that you touched on earlier chris
It's it you know, it's it's not a comfortable topic for most people to talk about but it's very
Very possible that porn is going to drive what becomes the next
uh, yeah
In the case of hd dvd and in blu-ray that was sony spending billions of dollars and getting
Uh exclusivity deals with movie companies
That's true, too
That is you know
We will we all we will all just look back at this in five years and laugh at all of our of our floundering
To figure it all out. But yeah
Okay, so I we just got a note from uh, dan for techsnaps. There's a blizzard west. There's a blizzard over there
That's uh, so we're gonna pick the pace up
But I do want to celebrate the 23rd year anniversary or the birthday if you will of linux 1.0
And then we'll follow up on west's challenge over there. So before we jump into the rest of the show, let me thank ting
Thank you ting. There you go. Thanks. They're the best. All right linux.ting.com. Well, we're basically done
What you you didn't know that ting is a is a mobile service provider super simple
Have you been six dollars a month for the line guys and you just pay for what you use? It's amazing
Go to linux.ting.com and check them out. They have such a simple
I really feel like it's almost too good to be true
Like this can't be possible if I hadn't been a customer for like two and a half years now
I'd tell you this can't be true. I didn't believe it. This can't be true, but it's true
It's actually how they're structured. They're so first of all, they're owned by two cows
So this is like they've been around for a while
They know how to do this kind of stuff and they've set up an mvno network where they have cdma and gsm
You get to pick from it, whichever one works better for you. You pay six dollars a month plus your usage
Whatever uncle sam takes that's it for a line. That's it. It's really nice. They got great customer service. Go check them out
They also have a blog right now on the most
well
Capable is probably a generous thing. I was gonna say the best smartphones for under a hundred dollars. I'm gonna say the best
Capable smartphones under a hundred dollars. Yeah, check it out. They have it at their blog. Just do us a favor and start
By going to linux.ting.com and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring the unplugged show
so
These are the final moments of the show west. I know you're doing great. You got a lot going on
So what I want to do
Is i'm going to give you a little time by celebrating the 23rd birthday
That's of linux 1.0. Yeah 1.0 came out on march 14th
1994 and what I decided to do to sort of celebrate this moment. I was trying to think what could we what could we really do?
I wanted to do a little time machine
I wanted to do a little time machine and i'm going to play i'm going to play an interview on this show
I would be willing to bet I I got a guess nobody i'd be willing to bet nobody
Has seen this before it's possible
But i'd be willing to bet you haven't because this was taken from a live recording of cnn
recorded to vhs
And uploaded by a dude to youtube recently
I've never seen it before and I and it's it's great because it's linus around
1997 98 if from what I can kind of grok
And it's it's so awesome because the clip starts out in the typical
Do you worry about bill gates? Does bill gates worry about you?
Is mike, you know this whole threat model and you could tell him the answer bill gates might be worried about linux
But linus ain't worried about microsoft. Do you think that bill gates worries about you?
No
Um, I think he thinks about linux a lot because I just think that he's a person who likes to be in control
I mean microsoft is it's his baby
and
he worries about anything that
Keeps his baby from being number one and linux is one of those things
I don't think he really really worries deep down because he can always look at and look at his pile of cash and then say
Okay, i'm, okay
So do you see that?
Somewhere down the line that linux is going to be bigger than microsoft
I think this microsoft is going to be smaller than microsoft. Oh
that
Microsoft is obviously in an enviable position from a market sense right now
But at the same time this is what what's called despotism to control a resource
And that's what happened in the old west when when people control the resource of water and became very rich in the process
It's a powerful tool for for making money
But it does have one downside and the one downside is that
It never lasts forever and when when it breaks as a tool
Uh, you've lost everything
That field that that was pretty good. That was that was that was late 90s
That was late 90s, uh linux was just a baby back then but starting to get some server traction
So now let's fast forward to 2001
about uh
About four or five six years out from the mobile revolution
Yeah before android before ios and uh linus sits down with uh charlie rose
Or a stupid question to ask will linux supplant windows?
It's a hard question to answer. I don't know if it's a smart question to ask. Why is it hard to answer?
I mean either well, it's
This just be a niche operating system that I I think linux has a very strong future on the desktop actually
It's a desktop
Including the desktop. I mean linux already has like a quarter of the uh web server market or more
So so in certain markets linux is very strong today. The desktop is obviously for a lot of reasons
It's a very interesting market
And it's also very obviously a market that microsoft completely dominates today
And makes a lot of money dominating
Uh, and it's a market that a lot of people have tried to enter I mean apple
IBM tried with os2
Uh a lot of the unix vendors tried and the only reason
Like your average person doesn't even know that they tried is that they failed so horribly
And uh, the reason I I think linux actually has a chance
and
Why I feel in five years the situation will be different is that linux kind of works around the market it
A lot of people are very interested in the desktop
So a lot of people will be working on all the applications going on the desktop making it look nice
And you can really see the the changes that have been going on in the last few years now
He was close, you know, he says you know
I want linux to take off on the desktop in the next few years
But there was something he said in there that was very accurate and that was linux works around the market
And so it's I think that with that sort of mindset that uh when he talks about this next thing
I thought this was fascinating linus says
What would be most disappointing for him about linux in the future?
Would be if it all went exactly how he expected it would go
I don't control the thing. I'm actually the
The single nicest thing about linux as far as i'm concerned has been how it has evolved in ways. I hadn't expected it to
People are doing things with linux that I never envisioned
People are doing things linux that i'm frankly
Not that interested in that's fine
And it's very interesting to see how people use linux even if they use linux in ways that I would never use it
So i'm hoping that I mean in five years
If I were to make a prediction right now
Which i'm not going to if that prediction actually came true i'd be really disappointed part of it
Because there ought to be unexpected. Yeah, a lot of the fun has been that people have done things. I never expected
I wonder if android would fall into that because that was that was about five years out from from android being announced
A world before smartphone. Yeah, isn't that something and so I wonder if android would fall into that category. So here we are
23 years later this day in history march 14 1994 linux 1.0.0 was released
Of course, it was 91 really when version zero zero. What was it zero dot zero zero two, I think was announced by linus
So that's some people celebrate different days, but I think if you go by the 1.0 release that's today pi day
Especially where here, you know, it's starting to become a little more serious and the you know, like the enterprise server thing
Yeah, the linux we know today. Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, uh, I will have some links to some of those videos
Uh, yeah, because I was doing some trolling to find those I had not seen those interviews before
Linus was on charlie rose to promote a book
Yeah, let me see if you know what? Let me see. I don't know if I have the original beginning
But that is actually kind of a fascinating
That's a fascinating aspect of it is I in fact
I think I made i've created like a linus folder now where I just have interviews with linus torvalds
And uh, yeah, here it is. Here's part one where I think he's introduced as as with as amongst other things an author
Oh, we don't need the old charlie rose intro wow, although it's so 90s it's almost perfect it's so
Actually, it's kind of what it is now that's horrible
Charlie rose
Linus torvalds was just a 21 year old student in 1991 when he created linux the groundbreaking operating system for computers
After developing the system, he posted it on the internet for free inviting users to download share and modify
Its popularity has skyrocketed over the last few years. There are currently more than 12 million
In addition tech stalwarts including sun microsystems oracle and ibm have begun incorporating it into their operations
Today torvalds is hailed as a hero by the open source community
His new book is quote just for fun the story of an accidental revolutionary
There you go. I have that book just for fun. Yep
19 uh
Was it uh?
Or 2001 when that book came out 2001
Wow, it's so weird to look back. It's so weird to look back at a different time. Mm-hmm
How long how young linus looked so how young so how young?
All right. So I thought that was fun and happy birthday to version 1o of the linux kernel
And thank you to linus for continuing to work on it for so long. It's a fascinating interview
I will try to get links to the entire ones in the show notes west before we check in on the
mycroft echo challenge
Let's thank digital ocean if you want to run your own infrastructure
Maybe you want to run jarvis or maybe you just want to run your own webmail client or heck
Just a sync thing instance digital ocean could have you coverage the simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way
To spin up a super fast linux rig on their super nice infrastructure all ssd storage
40 gigabit e connections into them hypervisors, of course the hypervisors run linux running kvm
They got data centers all over the world and they have the world's best interface
Other people are like trying to adapt and compete with digital ocean
But I I think they can't actually compete with digital ocean because digital ocean's interface was created by an organism from the future
That doesn't actually take our corporeal form
And what they have done is they've interfaced directly with the digital ocean computers and they have coded right into their editors
This amazing interface. It's the only thing that explains it
And then thanks to a time flux vortex
They're able to pull in this main this code for this amazing api that makes it all simple now
The the I like to mention the interface because it's great
But once you actually start working with digital ocean
You're going to be using the api even if you don't know what an api is
You're going to end up using it because it's so great so straightforward so simple so bootiful
Check them out at digital ocean.com. The pricing is to die for if you want to go hourly check this out
Three cents an hour two gigs of ram two core processor a 40 gigabyte ssd and three terabytes of transfer for three cents an hour
three cents
That's crazy. Like they have one-click deployments of like an entire ubuntu lts rig with docker
You could try out sync thing or set up one of those syncing relay nodes the discovery nodes in seconds
And just try it out at three cents an hour
It's and and if you use our promo code do unplugged you get a ten dollar credit, right?
In the time it takes you to complain there's not enough relay servers
You could have one going on do use our promo code do unplug to support the show get a ten dollar credit
You just go over to digital ocean.com you sign up
Once you've created your account use our promo code do unplug to support the show and keep us going. It's
Very much appreciated digital ocean dot com and thank you digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged program
And thank you to everybody for using the promo code do unplugged
All right, wes
I noticed you're sitting here at the laptop. You're not at the raspberry pi anymore
I assume you have an ssh connection. Oh, yeah
Oh, yeah
What are we running as our base linux distro? We are running. Uh, it looks like a fork of raspian
Okay, so something debbie-ish debbie-ish debbie-ish. Okay. All right, and we got microsoft running. We got microsoft now
Hold on. Should I?
Are you ready to what with with poppy's voice? No, that's yep. Oh, yeah
Unfortunately right now wait wait, what what it's only outputting
on the 3.5 millimeter
Oh, okay, so we don't have a way to play it. We don't have a way but we could set that up for the future
Yeah, that's pretty darn easy. All right, so it's it's just plugged in a usb
So the process of getting microsoft set up on the raspberry pi stupid simple
They even have it so that it'll start up their own little microsoft ap at first
You connect your phone to it then it does like a chromecast style. Hey, what's your lens wi-fi password?
And then from there just it popped up you did like it gives you a little pair which will speak for you
Or you can see the speech log really pair that on their website
And then it just started working you can ask it stuff. So like to log in over ssh. I was just like hey microsoft
What's your ip address?
Really? Yep, I secretly and that's exactly yep, and then poppy was reading me 192. Really?
Yes. Now, how did it go when you tried to get to the echo software? So here's the thing. Uh-oh
It's it's installing but it is a lot more the microsoft stuff was pretty there's a lot of it is in python
It was pretty lightweight to get going
This just downloaded the oracle 8 jdk. So
It's a little bit different. Uh, there's also like you have to jump through a fair number
I mean I had to go to the microsoft website to be fair
Right and I had to put in a code and stuff and I made an account but the account was very easy
The alexis service you gotta go register as an amazon developer. You gotta check out a number of boxes being like no
I'm not making money. No, this isn't for kids
Etc, etc. Yeah
And so I think it's gonna work beautifully
Whenever the thing I liked about that is if you are if you are in that camp of this is a cia surveillance device
Put into your home run by a private corporation that has a deal with the cia to run its infrastructure
You're a maniac for using an echo like if that's the camp you kind of find yourself in which I can understand
uh, I think
This shows you
What a tech tech hack this product really is in some sense like once you go through this process you realize
The limitations very quickly of the software. Oh, yeah, that's a good point
So it's a good way like if you're concerned about the security of the echo it
It is a good way to get intimate with what the actual technology stack is that it's using and you realize it's just
It's really plain jane vanilla stuff running on linux. They I mean they they tie it in with their backend infrastructure
I know. I mean i'm just to that point, you know
I just sourced their install script and away it goes and actually that part was actually pretty nice
Like it has some good like hey, yes, do you agree to this?
But then it asks hey, do you want to output over hdmi or 3.5 million? So that part I was actually pretty impressed
Oh, where's the mycroft one?
Yes, I imagine there's a way to go tweak that obviously, but do you have a speaker hooked up to it right now?
No, I just have headphones. I know I want to hear poppy speak. I know right? Yeah, I can never get enough of him
I think it should just work. We just have to move the stuff and we just have to find a way to plug it in
Yeah, well, I could just actually I would just I would like to get earbuds so that way poppy's in my ears
You know, I want to just hook them up
One of those batteries yeah, just like that
You get a battery pack for the pie and then you can tether it to your phone through your ting connection
And then you can just be talking with mycroft. There you go all the time. You can also just wiretap poppy's echo
That would work too. Yeah, that might be easier. Yeah, that's probably already done. Let's be honest
Uh, actually they got a little credit bit of credit recently for uh trying to fight a court case
So did you hear about this? Yes, I did. Yeah amazon and then the defendant decided actually
I think we might talk about that very briefly in today's room. Oh, really, you know what? That's a good tease
That's a good tease right there. I will leave it there
In fact, if you're not watching wes on the tech snap program, what's the matter with you?
Dan and wes are really, you know, it's been what how it's been what episode number you on now?
Uh eight three ten ten ten ten weeks, although some of those were doubles. Yeah. Yeah, that's true
But damn guys, wow, you guys are cranking those things out. I like it
Uh, well, all right, so then we should probably end it there because yeah, dan's in the middle of a blizzard out there
And he doesn't know how much longer he's gonna have power
So we on the west coast have it easy. I complain about the rain, but dan's in the middle of a blizzard. Yes, exactly
Yeah, uh, well, are you gonna poke at it and see if you can get the echo on there?
We can have some updates. Yeah, maybe we'll do that
We'll follow up on that and see so happy pie to everybody
But so it does seem like what we weren't sure before the show started
I guess I should make this point clear before we go
What we weren't sure before the show was could you take the same base linux image that you use to set up microsoft?
Could that also support the the echo software stack or is there going to be version conflicts?
Would there and it does appear you it seems like it's going to work just fine
I don't know not quite done setting up but uh fingers crossed. There you go. Tune in and find out next week
That's the that's the word on that. I guess i'm kind of curious because that could be the ultimate personal assistant
Yeah, a little bit of this a little bit of that
I'm also curious to play with it, but i'm not like I haven't been at the
Level even to buy a dot yet. Right? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah now if I have one there. Wow, what's my excuse? Yeah
Yeah, you know, I got the assistant on the phone. Oh, yeah
It's really not that different. Yeah. Yeah
All right. Well that brings us to the end of episode 188. We're going to get out here on the account of snow
There's so much more show we could do there's so much more show. So check out the show notes
We got more stuff in there that didn't fit in today's episode. Check out next week's episode of the linux action show
We're gonna have a really unique take on our visit to scale
I like it. I also if if it's if i'm somebody who's never been to scale
I would really like it
If somebody's gone every year, I would like it. I watched the video already. No did a great job
So check out linux action show this sunday
Thank you for being here on this show
Give us your feedback in your comments linuxactionshow.reddit.com
Give us your emails at jupiterbroadcasting.com contact and find out the live times at jupiterbroadcasting.com
jplive.tv is where you watch it. See you right back here next tuesday
So
Most of the web runs on servers powered by linux it's for people who like to mess with computers
JBtitles.com that's not us. No. No, certainly not. Wow
Like we we tried to hustle but we're almost we're still almost just on a regular time jbtitles.com
Sorry dan, we're we're working quick
Arguably better than vr a focused mate. That's not bad
Uh, thank you. Mumble room. You guys are excellent and wonderful and the best as always. Oh, yeah
Penguins are assholes
That's also true
Those stinking penguins bite and dip that chilling people at the end of shows to share the show
Oh, you know, I should do that. I guess that yeah, everybody go share and like was that what you say?
What do you is that what the kids say? Everybody please share and like this like comment and subscribe to like subscribe button
Yeah, smash smash that thumbs up retweet and share it with your friends and your family, please if we could get a hundred thousand likes