So Popey you you made a post about 11 gig. Oh
Yeah, yeah 24 oh
You left yours running as well
The recorder you left with the recorder running or something or what? Yeah
So we all use NTP to make sure we're all in sync
So we don't have to clap or click or anything. Oh, you're all using your own custom NTP server
Is that what you're doing? Like yeah, well, no, we just all point at the same one. Oh that works
Yeah, so we're only ever like no, yeah, not to write
It's not like that so they all the audio recorders start at the same time very smart
So they're very easy to line up. But the problem is because we've said it to like start recording at nine o'clock
And audio recorder by default will auto
Spawn when you log in so the next day off now
Yeah, me too. I reboot and audio recorders sat there in the background. I didn't even know
started recording
Four days later and I'm shutting down my PC for like a kernel update or something and the very last thing to shut down
I look and see hang on a minute. That thing's been recording for four days and there's an 11 gig file
No, no, there was there was me babbling away in a conversation with my wife about birthday presents and wish lists
I was like I need to delete this there is going to be something incriminating. Yeah, I'm gonna get rid of it now
I was
What drew my attention to it was I suddenly thought why is the system monitor showing? There's always CPU activity
What's going on? And then I ran h-top and I was like, what's all do you record a doing running now?
Oh, I've been recording audio for half days. This is a legitimate reason why I have I try to always have an extension that puts my
CPU usage up somewhere on my screen because that's often how I'll catch stuff is I'll just glance up and notice wait a minute
That's CPU usage looks a lot higher for them what I'm doing right now on the computer
And I don't I normally don't check it and sometimes I wouldn't even notice unless I had a little system monitor applet that told
me so if you've seen
There's a new Chrome bit
So now we've got Chromebooks Chrome boxes and now the thing that's long as ever Chromecast
That is effectively Chrome in a in a year in a HDMI stick
And you plug in the power and you plug in a keyboard and there's your computer. I was just looking at this actually
It's funny you say that longer Google are completely eating our lunch with these machines. Are they you think you think they're totally like taking
away, that's how smart their number
Yeah, totally. There's no number one
Laptops on Amazon if you go to right if you go to Amazon and look at laptops the number one seller has a Chromebook
Yeah, no, not a Windows laptop, right or Mac. We should be there
Well, I agree and we are in a way but the thing is is Google's got brand
They got OEMs working with them and it's a simplified package
It's it's sort of it's capitalizing in a way isn't it almost in a way capitalizing on the failed promise of tablets
You know the tablet didn't do it
You ended up needing a keyboard
But you still need something kind of simple like a tablet and something cheap and I don't know maybe this is maybe this is
Maybe this is the right product for the right time
Doesn't necessarily now I wonder I don't know about these USB sticks, but a Chromebook doesn't necessarily mean it's a loss for a Linux
Installation people might get bored with the very basic nature of Chromebook and one look elsewhere. I
Mean well, maybe it'll eventually make more like switchers
I mean like I look at those those stream PCs those really cheap HP PCs that come with Windows 8 1 pre-installed with Bing
And you know what I just look at those as a future Linux boxes as well, I'm not too worried about it
Yeah, I I wish I wish Google would have just wouldn't have been crazy
You know in a crazy universe if Google just would have done like Ubuntu
That would have been nice
Considering that they have their own I know exactly exactly would have been so cool if they just would have done that
Originally it was crime crime OS originally was based on Ubuntu then they switched
Building their own packages using Gentoo, right? I mean that would have been a heat. That would have that would have changed everything
And it used to use Firefox. Oh
Right
Right, it did didn't know it did that the very first Chrome OS was before the Chrome browser, right?
And it was Firefox based, wasn't it? Yep
What yes, this is
Yes, the original concept was Firefox and a really really thin Ubuntu ish thing
Yeah, and it wasn't like Chrome OS so much as it was a distro really. I'm gonna go look for it
Yeah, I wasn't from Google yeah, and I was using it from like
Well, not when it was a Chrome OS release right right as a product when they were coming up with the concept for it
It was Firefox based. Yeah, and I think did you read this in a book?
Is that where you and I both saw this in in the entering the plex? Is that where you got this? It wasn't a book
I can't remember where I remember this from but just know it's somewhere on the history of Chrome OS. Yeah
When Chrome OS was based on Firefox and rejected by Google
My goodness, you're right. I had no idea. Where did you find it? Where did you find that? Yeah, I'm looking for the verge
There you go
Chrome OS was originally based on the different rails of Firefox
Yeah
Could you imagine if they would have gone with Firefox and Ubuntu how different the world would be after at this point?
I wonder if we'd be as successful
Hmm see people still refer to Google having their own in-house Ubuntu
But I think we're you know looking back quite a long time Popey
I mean, do you know anything about that or is it really an internal thing? They still use it internally
Yeah, and is it Ubuntu or is it their their own, you know, spin of Ubuntu?
It's it's Ubuntu. It's called gubuntu and it's it's Ubuntu with some stuff ripped out and some other stuff added
Like any corporate desktop is windows stuff ripped out and stuff added so it's no different than that
and
The last time we interviewed, you know, if you listen to the show you would have known we interviewed the guy who's responsible for this
at Google and
it's it was
Um, basically isn't it as a new starter at Google you you would have three choices
Sorry two choices. You'd either have a PC or a Mac and if you got a Mac you'd get OS 10 if you chose PC
you'd either get Windows or
Ubuntu you could install something else if you want to but that's what you would get
And yeah, good one too is basically a bunch
I mean we have bugs in our bug tracker from you know, the Google IT people who are you know
working on problems
Delivering it to their to their users, but I haven't I haven't heard much about it for the last night year or so
I don't know. Yeah
Whether they all use Chrome OS
You know is Chrome OS their new internal desktop operating system
So and this is what I was told from someone who got hired recently and so puppy
I wonder if this lines up with what you heard is
You get like three choices when you get hired at Google right now
You get a gubuntu which is based on
1404 and and and they they rev in a new one every new LTS and that's what they've been doing for a long time now is
The official gubuntu is based on the latest LTS and then so that's your first option
Your second option is a Chromebook and your third option is a MacBook and I guess like if you want to buy a Windows machine
Like you have to get approval and like I think there's like a whole different like path
You have to go through to even get a Windows box at all
So that I don't know if that lines up with what you've heard at all
Yeah, it may well be their policies changed over time. But as I understand it gubuntu still exists. That's all that's all I know
I heard it was the first choice
I heard gubuntu is the top choice
Chromebook second choice or Mac books are second choice and Chrome and Chromebooks are third choice or something like that on on average
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that is bracing for the fools of April
My name is Chris Ted. My name is Matt. Hey Matt episode 86, buddy. That's not that's not too bad
86 already. No, that means we're getting I mean, I don't know if you're familiar with the way this works
But I think that means we're nearing episode 90. I
Believe so. I'm you know, mathematically challenged, but I do believe we got 87 and then a few others
Hey, so but don't worry. We're not even we're not even looking if we're not looking ahead. We haven't lost track
We're focused. We're hunkered in we're in the trenches of episode 86 this week
We got a lot to cover first up. There is a horrible rumor
Horrible rumor spreading around the internet right now
And that is that the Linux kernel is being forked by a very ambitious team
I will tell you more about that in just a little bit as the show goes on and if it's true or not
and you
You probably have heard this rumor. It's spreading like crazy right now. Also some new improvements coming to the cinnamon desktop
We're gonna talk about that
Official Linux fest Northwest planning coverage begins and also
We're gonna hopefully get to it this week. I have we been
Have we been negligent in our coverage Matt?
Have we been negligent in covering some of the other distributions that we all know and love out there?
So Matt today we will so we will find out we'll take audience. We will take a test Matt
I will challenge that assumption of yours
And then last and then last but not least there's a really cool device that runs Linux
That is just one of those things reminds you it's really 2015 and it's pretty exciting
And we'll talk about that coming up a little bit in the show
But Matt before we go too far
We do have a you won't be able to hear it
But they over far in the distance Matt if just over the horizon wolf blitzers over there with a little
little breaking news
That's right. Yeah, we're going to talk a little bit about that
It's a little breaking news breaking news. Yeah, that's right. Yeah, we have a little breaking news right now
You might have heard it
But apparently the systemd team is planning to fork the Linux kernel everybody get your pitchforks
It's time to fight. We are going all-in
No, not really
They are not forking the Linux kernel but various places on the internet it even made it to hacker news
the pharaonic forms the reddit
And apparently a github account was even created with the name system Damon and registered and registered to somebody
And the whole rumor was is that the systemd folks were going to fork the Linux kernel in order to
Make things just work a little better streamline areas and have full control over the entire stack
Turns out it was totally an April Fool's joke
Totally a mumble room. Did you guys did you guys catch this the systemd is forking kernel the kernel story?
I saw something saying that it wasn't true on reddit, but yeah, I saw the chatroom talking about it all morning
Weekly and it got linked to an actual github repo and the name of the github repositories name
Or at least the system Damon's name is Ivan got you bitch gotcha Ivan gotcha
Yeah, in other words in other words April Fool's April Fool's, right?
This isn't really it makes a nice change from people saying the next thing canonical will fork is the Linux kernel
So that made me
Oh
I gotta pull that post down then hang on
Yeah
People like are you gonna talk about this Chris are you gonna double think? Yeah
I'm gonna talk about this. It's for somehow somehow it missed the Linux action show this weekend
I don't I don't quite know how that happened
Also, I also wanted to give a shout out to the digi. Oh, hi there
I want to give a shout out to the digicam project there at CBIT 2015 and
Digi digicam got an award. It's really cool
They actually got the best open source photo management application and digicam is often compared to Adobe Lightroom
Which the project considers to be pretty much in a compliment
But it's an application Lightroom is an application popular among enthusiasts and professional photo photographers on Windows and Mac OS
So they consider that to be an achievement and congrats to digicam. I've been specifically looking at digicam perhaps for a close family members
photo workflow in the near future as
as the fruit company who also makes hardware is
Sunlighting their long-term ifoto photo management program now seems like the perfect opportunity for those of us who are open source
Enthusiast to recommend a really solid open source alternative to ifoto. I don't think photos is it?
I don't think Apple's replacements it I'm not a big fan of the nearline system
I don't totally totally trust iCloud for the things that I consider to be the most precious digital asset that I own the photos of my
Children so for me perhaps that's a great opportunity to recommend the transition to an open source photo management program
So I'll be doing that for a few people in my life
And I think digicam is probably the one I'm going to pick because the timing is now
It makes sense. I mean because I'm actually in a similar situation with my wife who is not real pleased with that news either
Yeah, and you know and that might actually be a solution
I could actually she's perfectly comfortable with Linux so it's certainly plausible
And what do we always say if you give people tools that are available on Linux and available that you can first set them up
On their existing platform when they make that transition to Linux. It's even easier because all the applications are the same that they love
Exactly
Congrats to digicam
We just want to give them a little shout out at the top of the Linux Unplugged show episode 86
See it's good luck. It's good luck and then last but not least
Get ready to run that gnome application everywhere you want anywhere everywhere across any distribution
Could it be true? Can it be real? The gnome project thinks so
We've talked about a little bit before but the official first gnome SDK runtime builds are out
Yeah, this is a gnome runtime
So you can build your gnome application against this runtime and then this runtime gets distributed to any distribution
And as long as you have that runtime the app runs doesn't matter what distro it is
It's based on gnome 3.16 run libraries
And there's this is definitely just a developer preview. So they're considered to be weekly supported
The developer will try to keep them somewhat updated as major issues and API has come up, but right now it's a work in progress
And I think it's kind of neat
I don't know if anybody in the mobile room has any thoughts on this, but I thought this was a neat way
This is this is kind of clunky. I'll totally admit that it's a little low tech
You're bundling up a whole bunch of libraries and stuff and sticking them in some directory somewhere and then telling developers to write to that
That's what steam does today, but it works and steam selling $60 games doing this
I don't know. I'd like to pick wimpy's brain. What do you think wimpy?
Well, yeah, it's a departure from the traditional way of doing things on Linux
But I think systems like this, a way that you can bundle either a runtime or an overlay to give developers a predictable development target is the way that Linux is going to have to go
If we're going to continue to want to drive adoption, particularly for application developers
Could you see a distribution like Ubuntu Mate shipping this runtime out of the box?
And maybe even having a package in the repository that gets updated or Ubuntu might or somebody. Could you see a world like that?
Yeah, I can. I can see Ubuntu doing it. I can see OpenSUSE are doing it. I can see Fedora doing it
And as soon as you get the big players doing it, then everyone's got it and then you've you've cracked it, haven't you?
Yeah, because you've essentially you create an API, a stable API that people can write to
You've created a certain set of expectations that you can write to and that a certain and gnome 3.16 is no slouch
That's the latest and freshest gnome. So it's not going to be that far behind even after a few releases
Having 3.16 as the base is actually going to be pretty good
I mean, Steam seems to be successfully doing it. So maybe others can successfully do it
And we have the hard drive space to have a few extra libraries
And if as long as they keep updated for security fixes, which is always the trick with this kind of stuff
But that's not a challenge we're incapable of solving. We have package managers everywhere
So, yeah, I think it's kind of interesting. We'll see. This could be a great way to get
It would be funny if like Qt has like all the real nice technical advantages and market share advantages
But GTK comes along and says, well, but we've got builder
We've got this runtime and we've got a pretty good looking desktop
So here's all the things you just here's your here's your complete solution to delivering it on across all distributions
And you don't even have to have like file system overlays and containers
And I think it's not a bad solution. We'll see if anybody really uses it
We'll see. It's going to take somebody to actually package up their application with it
Someone's bound to do it
Has anybody tried it? I mean, how difficult is it?
Super new. Super, super new. Like yesterday new
Yeah, it was just posted online yesterday
So I don't think there's much of anybody using it
But I've just been following it closely on the show because what I'm really trying to crack
And maybe I should make this more obvious, right, is universal application distributions across all distributions
Because on Coder Radio, the email we get in all the time and when we started Coder Radio
The email we get is, hey, so I'm an iOS developer and I just got myself a little Linux machine for the first time
It's really cute and quaint and I want to write an adorable little app for that Linux desktop
Can you point me in the direction of the SDK?
Can you point me how I'm supposed to get started? What I'm supposed to do?
And every time we just have a different answer depending on the trend, you know, it's
And this is a this is a full fledged answer, which I think is kind of exciting
I think it'll be interesting to see where it all ends up in the long run
I agree Matt, I agree
So you can find out more information in the show notes or check blogs.gnome.org
And maybe it goes nowhere
This is all part of their work on sandbox applications too
So I imagine if you're going to be sandboxing apps, this will become more important as well
So it all fits in with application distribution, sandboxing, the future of different desktops
It's a big picture that we're watching come slowly together in front of our eyes
Speaking of bringing things together in front of your eyes, how about your education?
Over at Linux Academy, I mean it, go over to Linux Academy right now and check them out
They freaking rock
Linux Academy is our sponsor right here on the Unplugged program
And they I think are I think one of the best sponsors for Linux Unplugged
Because they're such a great fit for you guys
It really is the matchup of open source enthusiasts, Linux administrators, and educators coming together to build something special
And you can take advantage of it by going to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
Head over there right now, check them out and get our special discount
Discount at linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
Step-by-step video courses for everything they cover and the content is always expanding
So that's very nice and they have downloadable comprehensive study guides you can bring with you on the go
Ah, maybe you're in the shower
Maybe you're traveling
No judging, I'm not going to judge
And they're always, they're always like the best, the best
Because these people really truly get the content and what your goals are
Because they've been in your shoes, they've been in your position
And so when they see things that come up like Docker
And things like Vagrant and Amazon Web Services
They really can wrap their brains around how to make scenario based labs
So that way you can go in and really get your hands on with that technology
And they have self-paced courses where you can set your own limits
You get your percentages when you log in
See exactly where you're going to have to take off, where you're going to leave off
And exactly how long it's going to take you to get through that course
And I like that, I guess I'm a bit of a data head
I like to be able to break it all down and see how long something's going to take me
The idea that I could see the goal of learning Python will take six hours
Or I think it's like five and a half hours on Linux Academy
That is such a, that is a quantifiable thing that I can put that in my head and go
I can learn the basics of Python in five and a half hours?
That is a huge, huge pivot from like I have to learn this nebulous thing called Python
And it's this programming language that's going to be very complicated
You know, it just cuts through all of that
Plus you've got instructor help, you've got live streaming, a fantastic community
And they're going to do some big content updates
April 16th, they're going to do a live stream
New content coming to Linux Academy
I've also gotten notes about folks that pass their certifications after training at Linux Academy
And it happens more and more all the time
It is a really, really great setup
And I think one of the things that I've found is when we'll follow things in the news
I'll be like, this is obviously going to be a big deal
I end up talking to the folks who run Linux Academy, they're already working on courseware for it
They have a really cool lab setup
When we first brought them on as a sponsor, I got sort of geeky with the backend technology
And really sort of was like, wow man
I was talking to Anthony who runs Linux Academy
If I was going to do this today, like if I was going to launch Jupyter Broadcasting today
I might seriously do something like this
Because it's so genius
They've got everything
You've Red Hat training, Python, OpenStack, DevOps, Android, PHP, Ruby
The Amazon Web Services stuff is particularly great
Because I find that to be an expensive thing to learn
And the fact that all of the Amazon Web Services are just included with your Linux Academy subscription
Makes that really stress free
Makes that you don't even have to worry about getting that accidental charge from Amazon
Which I have done
And it is not cheap
I accidentally one time got charged $200
Because I left an AWS services server running for 30 days by mistake
Not doing a single thing
But it was like $280 just running
Because I was just trying to learn Amazon Web Services
I don't have to worry about that with Linux Academy
linuxacademy.com slash unplug
Get our special Linux Unplugged discount
And a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Unplugged program
You guys are powerful
Alright, so we got some feedback into the show
Tell me that I'm a dummy
He says, Ubuntu touch apps and other distributions are how Chris is wrong
Right, so this has been stopping me from sleeping for a while
Because, well, it wound me up
On a certain episode of Linux Unplugged
Chris questioned how Ubuntu applications made with the Ubuntu SDK
Would look on non-Ubuntu desktop environments
And quite rightly came to the conclusion
Well, they would probably look out of place
Fine, let's stop right now and talk about something else
GNOME apps
GNOME apps are effing s
Under anything that isn't GNOME, however
Nobody is giving GNOME a hard time over this
GNOME is essing all over everyone else in their poorly designed applications
And the Ubuntu desktop and other desktops are suffering because of it
And he includes some examples
Here is a GNOME app
Under Unity
That looks horrible with the client-side decoration
Here's one that also looks quite horrible
Because it doesn't have the right decorations
He says, this is just totally effed
This is Canonical's responsibility for patching GNOME apps to make them look right under Ubuntu
You could make that argument
But he disagrees
If that's the case, Canonical should be allowed to do whatever they want
And everybody else just patch that as well
It goes both ways
So if Canonical could make their own applications
Look or don't look remotely
Look remotely okay under any other desktop
Then that's just fine
Because GNOME is getting away with it as well
Canonical shouldn't have
The TLDR is Canonical shouldn't be given a hard time for making their applications
And if they don't work on anything else
That's nothing different than GNOME and the GNOME apps right now
Or you could say maybe the elementary apps and things like that
What do you think of this argument, Matt?
That's like, hey, if they want to reinvent the wheel
And make them only work okay on the Ubuntu desktop
And not look okay on, say, Fedora with GNOME
That's totally fine
And this is just my opinion
The whole thing, in my opinion, is just completely ridiculous
It's like, okay, look
As long as they're willing to make their efforts public
And the code available and all that sort of stuff
I don't care what they theme it with
Because that's really where the ethical responsibility ends
Is that, hey, we did something cool, here's the code for it
You want to pretty it up, go ahead
But it's not their responsibility
They are, in fact, looking out for their desktop environment
And what they're doing
And if that doesn't play well with other things
Well, whether it be GNOME, Unity, doesn't matter
Same thing applies
It just feels like a real straw man kind of argument
I have a hard time getting behind it
Hmm, okay, alright
I can see, yes, I can see that point
Anybody in the mumble room want to jump in
Before I share my thoughts?
If I'm an individual, you know, working on an application
I wrote an application called Journal
For the GNOME desktop
And, you know, that's
It's because that's what I use
If I was going to port that over to Ubuntu Touch
That would be fine
But, you know, I would want some assistance
From some actual Ubuntu Touch developers to do that
So here's my question
So, I think there's a pretty big difference between
A desktop environment implementing something like a client-side decoration
And the world's most popular Linux distribution
Coming up with a new way for applications to look
Because, and the reason why there's a difference
Is because one is a desktop environment
And one is the most important Linux distribution in the world
For desktops
Okay, you see the difference there?
So if you want to write applications for Ubuntu
They are going to look different
And there's more people that probably want to write applications for Ubuntu
Than they do for the general Linux desktop
So now do you see the difference there?
More people want to write applications for the Ubuntu desktop
Than they want to write for the Linux desktop
So that means more applications will be looking like they're designed for Ubuntu
Regardless of the distribution you're using
Do you see a problem with that, anybody?
It's, no
All the way through this I've just been thinking
It's kind of like Qt and GTK
If you run a GTK application on a Qt desktop
It looks absolutely horrible
Yeah, and you know, I just
I actually don't know if it's going to be a bad thing or not
I think maybe I was getting a little more hate for it
I'm pointing out it's going to be a thing
Doesn't mean it's going to be a bad thing
Maybe it'll be fine
In fact, maybe
Because there's going to be like a standard design language
Maybe there'll be the best looking apps on the Linux desktop
Maybe
Could be, could be
Maybe it'll just take off because it looks good
We'll wait and see
I doubt it
One more little update before we get into Linux Fast Northwest stuff
I thought we'd talk a little bit about Cinnamon just super quick
Because yesterday Clem did a blog post
An update for Mint
And he said a huge amount of work has gone into making Cinnamon load faster
And I just got an email into the show the other day
It said, how come you guys never talk about Cinnamon?
So he says, we're only halfway there
The results aren't conclusive yet
One of our test machines on there
Cinnamon was able to load in less than a second in normal conditions
But can take up to 12 seconds to load the very first time the computer is turned on
Investigations show that this delay took place in Cinnamon menus and Cinnamon desktop
During the initial loading of application infos
From like the menus and the user share applications directories
And the icon themes of course
Through optimizations the loading times were reduced from 12 seconds to 7 seconds on average
Which is the first step but doesn't yet solve anything
He says, we're still working on this and hoping we'll be able to drastically reduce that initial time
Wouldn't it be cool if Cinnamon becomes one of the fastest, snappiest desktops?
That would be very cool, especially considering all its little bells and whistles
Mint has also made a call out for photographers and graphics designers and web people
They need a lot of work there
And they'd eventually like to have somebody that could maybe even take over responsibility of the look of Linux Mint
Some also some information about upcoming releases
Linux Mint 18 is going to be released sometime in 2016
We don't have a specific date yet
However, Linux Mint 17.2 which I believe is based on Ubuntu 14.04 will be coming soon
Probably very soon
So we'll keep an eye out for that
Congrats to the Linux Mint people
I wanted to try to give them a little coverage since we've been kind of missing that
Anybody want to chime in on anything before I move on?
Okay, good enough
Sometimes there's nothing to say
I wanted to mention that I started a meetup and a couple of things
Boy, there's a lot to cover today
I'm sorry I'm going kind of fast, but I wanted to get to some of our other topics
So I decided to do something
I decided to create a meetup group for Jupyter Broadcasting
I've been kind of trying to figure out the best way to sort of organize future meetups
And as well as Linux Fest Northwest
So I kind of wanted to get an idea of how many people are coming to Linux Fest Northwest for planning
But I realized long term, as the weather gets nice in the Seattle area
I'd like to maybe do semi-frequent meetups with Jupyter Broadcasting audience members
Maybe like once a month
Maybe we could even record them or stream them
You know, eat chat, talk about show stuff
And then of course if we travel and we have an event
We would use this meetup group that I set up to organize events in your local area
So I have linked and I will link it right now in the IRC as I'm talking too
I've created an event for Linux Fest Northwest
And I've created just a general Jupyter Broadcasting group on meetup.com
I don't know if meetup.com is the best place
But it seems to be pretty popular in the Seattle area
There's lots of open source meetups already on there
So I was hoping maybe we could capitalize on some of that too
So I created an event for Linux Fest Northwest
If you're going to be going
Please go to meetup.com slash Jupyter Broadcasting
And go to the Linux Fest Northwest event
I'll have it linked in the show notes
And RSVP
So we just get an idea of how much food and swag items we need to bring
It would be a rough idea
I think it's got a lot of potential if you think about it
Because there's a lot of local folks that would love to do that
I think maybe then we could get a list of local folks
And in the future we'll have the list
And we can let them know we're going to do other meetups as well
I don't know if meetup lets you
But maybe we could just notify you when you're going to be in your area too
Because I figure when we travel or we go to other fests
We could use this as a way to sort of organize events in that area too
So the site or the page is meetup.com slash Jupyter Broadcasting
And the event is linked in the show notes
So we start with Linux Fest Northwest
Maybe give us an idea of how many you're going
And then we'll use it for other stuff
That would be neat
Who needs a mumble and bye guys? I'm replacing you with people in real life
Ha!
No kidding right?
I'm just kidding
Actually Wimpy sounds so good this week you'd almost think he's in studio
I know, it's a new mic or something?
What did you do Wimpy? Tell Matt
It's an old mic
I got some old kit from the loft
And a few USB adapters
And had a bit of an experiment last night
And you sound good
Wow
Doesn't he sound good?
He sounds really good
He sounds so good you'd think he's going to be here for Linux Fest Northwest
But he's not
I really wanted to try and go
Really wanted to try and go
I know, I know
Maybe next year
I think next year definitely
Maybe even present
Really?
That'd be really cool
Yeah you could go
Totally Wimpy
Oh my gosh don't tease
I would like that a lot
Alright so if you are going to make it
Check out meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting
And you'll find the Linux Fest Northwest event there
Let us know if you're going
And also if you'd like to maybe volunteer for Linux Fest Northwest
They do have a contact page
Linux Fest Northwest slash contact
And you can give them your info
Maybe you got something you can help them do
That'd be kind of cool
Just give them a mention
Alright
So I want to talk about this hardware device
This
It's made it on
It's like one of the top stories in our subreddit this week
It's called the Onion Omega
And it looks like it's smaller than a USB thumb drive
I'd say it's a little bit bigger than a quarter
And it's kind of amazing
It's a tiny but powerful Linux
With Wi-Fi
An app store
You'd think those Chrome sticks look interesting
They got nothing
They got nothing on this thing
So I want to show this to you guys
And see if this could be a viable thing
And if it is
Maybe
Well maybe we'll get one
And maybe we'll review it on the show
And put art on it
I mean matte
I mean
No I'm just kidding
But first I'm going to tell you about our friends over at Ting
Go to linux.ting.com
linux.ting.com
That'll take $25 off your first device
Or you know what
You probably have a device that works with Ting
Because they just take all these GSM devices now
And they take a whole bunch of CDMA devices
So if you got a device that already works with Ting
They'll give you $25 service credit
Wait you don't know what Ting is?
Oh my gosh
How did you not hear about the best thing to happen to mobile ever?
I'm serious
Ting is really here to shake up the mobile duopoly
It's mobile that makes sense
No contracts
You only pay for what you use
Flat $6 dollars for that line
You want a new line on your Ting?
Boom
$6 dollars
That is less than a sandwich these days
For a cell phone line
$6 dollars a month in your usage on top
They have a kick ass dashboard
That totally dominates all the other carriers dashboards
It takes their dashboards
And smashes them into the ground by the face
It is such a great dashboard
But then to like lap them
They have no hold customer service
You call that Ting at 1855 Ting FTW
Any time between 8am or 8pm
And a human answers the phone
And that human is empowered to solve your problems
You know why?
Because they're like hey here's an idea
Let's hire Android geeks to do our Android phone support
Let's hire iOS fanboys to do our iOS support
So you get the enthusiasts
And then they said hey you know what
Let's give them the ability to actually just solve the problem on their first call
Solve the problem on their first call
What a freaking concept
That's Ting
And they just like
That kind of just very straight forward logic applies to everything
I'll give you another example
You want hotspot and tethering?
Turn it on
Just check the box
That's why Google built it into the OS
And that's why Apple built it into the OS
And probably Microsoft does it
I don't know what Microsoft does
Anyway that's why it's there
You should just be able to turn it on
It's a wireless ISP
You want to treat Ting like a wireless ISP?
Do it bro
Go for it sister
I don't care
I'm not judging you
Because you're only paying for what you use
They take your minutes
They take your megabytes
And that's it
Go to linux.ting.com to get started
I'll tell you how crazy like a Fox Ting is too
Look up over on their blog post right now
Ting Tip for Android
Make calls through Hangouts for free
They talk about this app
That's in the Play Store
That just sets up your dialer to use the Hangouts app
So when you just make calls
And you dial phone numbers on your Android phone
It just routes the call through Hangouts
So all your calls are free
Now that's going to cost Ting money
They're going to make less money off you
Because you are not going to use as many cellular minutes
You're going to be making your calls over Wi-Fi
That's crazy like a Fox
That's Ting
linux.ting.com
Go check them out
Been my mobile service provider for well over two years now
linux.ting.com
And a big thanks to Ting for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program
You crazy Foxes over there
You keep it up
And I can't wait to get myself a brand new spanking Android phone soon
And put it on the Ting GSM network
linux.ting.com
Alright so this is maybe the coolest thing ever
We've shown many hardware devices on the Unplugged show
In fact I want to show more
But we've also shown many a Kickstarter
Many a Kickstarter
But you guys
Not only is this one of the coolest Kickstarter devices we have ever seen on the show
I think this is the best Kickstarter video I have ever seen
At least for anything that runs Linux
So here it is
The tiny but powerful Linux Wi-Fi development board
With 166 backers
It's currently at $5,285
At a $15,000 goal
A nice modest goal
$15,000
That's modest
34 days to go
Here we go
Check this thing out
This is so, so freaking cool
And I think I gotta give mad props for a great Kickstarter video as well
There are two worlds
The real world
And the digital
And then there's the cat world
Oh the lovely cat world
The problem with the two worlds is that
In order to connect objects in the real world with the digital world
You need to be a rocket scientist
Or some sort of physicist from the Manhattan Project
Or one of those brains in a jar
But not anymore
Meet Onion
For the past year
We've been hard at work building something that's small, affordable
And really easy to use
So that we can merge the two worlds together
We wanted to be like Tony Stark
And be able to build whatever comes to our mind
Without learning how to build these things
And that is exactly why we created this
The Onion Omega
Thanks Oliver
It's a tiny computer with built-in Wi-Fi
And it runs the Linux operating system
This little bad boy lets you create connected devices
In environments that you're already familiar with
Using tools such as SSH, Git, and MPM
And it also allows you to write software in Python, Node.js, PHP
Or whatever language you feel comfortable with
You now have the power to build anything you can imagine
Such as smart home devices
Security drones
Security spiders
What?
I don't want that, I do not want that, I do not want that, I do not want that!
Or even a cat feeder
A cat feeder that realizes your cat is too fat
With a laser?
And then makes it exercise
Laser pointer
Or if you don't want to build from scratch
You can browse the Onion app store for ready-made apps
In fact, if you want to see what you can build on the Omega right now
Click on the live demo below and start to experience the Omega in real time
I want the cat stuff, that's cool
Yeah, okay, so this is the Omega Onion
And I'm telling you, it's the future
You're going to have one of these in your backpack
You're going to have one of these in your, I don't know, your milk jug
This thing is nuts, it's tiny
It is one fourth the size of a Raspberry Pi
Wow, it's ridiculous
It's got a full Linux environment
Full Linux environment, they say, with a powerful processor
Capable of running the full Linux operating system
That is just
I mean, it's just the stuff you can do with it
And the ready-made apps, that's going to make this work
That's what's going to make this work for people
Yeah, the app store is
Because someone like me that's lazy
It's just like, I just want the cool stuff, you know
Right, yeah, that is actually a pretty good point
And it comes with a pretty nice little UI out of the box where you can load stuff
To me, this looks like a
Finally a version of this kind of
Tech that might be more approachable to somebody like me
Whereas I think the Raspberry Pi and the Arduino boards
And the BeagleBone Black are super cool
But I just, I am not inventive enough to see them and come up with something
Right, but this
But this
This looks a little more approachable to me
I don't know, a number of them
Any thoughts, would you guys back something like this?
The prices, here, I'll give you the prices
And you guys tell me what you think, okay?
So here's your backing prices
If you just want to get in sort of cheapo style, you know
Like low rent
You could just
You could get
Oh, they're all gone
They did start at $19
They're all gone now
For $25, you get an Omega and a dock
$35, you get an Omega and a dock
And a dock or expansion
But you really start cooking when you get up to 99 bucks
99 bucks, you get a camera kit
Which is, you get an Omega and a dock
A camera kit
A tilt mount
A servo
An Omega servo
And accessory instructions
And wiring
And then it just keeps going up
Like $109, you get the printer kit
$119, you get all that stuff
And a starter kit
And essential items to build something else
You know, like everything, you get more and more stuff
So it's a pretty straightforward pricing structure
Starting as, you know
You can go as low as $35
Or really $25 for a little bit longer
There's only 21 spots left, I think
But, you know
I don't know
My thoughts
Seems like a pretty reasonable price for a pretty interesting device
Yes? No?
I'm not really happy with the software
Well, I think it is
What was that? I'm sorry
What about the software?
They've kind of made their own Onion Cloud
Yes
Own lab
Own everything
Yes
I'm not sure how future proof it is
If they're only a small company
It's actually a pretty fair critique, actually
I have two reasons
Okay
Two things
One
Called the Onion Omega
Yes
Which, I mean, it gets points right there
And then two
The guy almost sounded like Morgan Freeman
Yeah, yeah, that's great, right?
Strategic viewpoints
So just based on those two things
I guess you almost have to
See, okay, that was what I was thinking
Is the Morgan Freeman really did it for me
I thought, I like this idea too because
You know, last week we talked about
Oh, I should follow up on that too
Last week we talked about a computer for my kid
And I think it was Wimpy that recommended
You know, get him a computer
But maybe also get him a Raspberry Pi
I think that was you, right, Wimpy?
What do you think about this
As opposed to the Raspberry Pi for kids?
Well, this is, I think, the step on
From the Raspberry Pi, isn't it?
This is the next level of
DIY computing and experimentation
So yeah, definitely something
When you've surpassed the initial novelty
Of the Raspberry Pi
And using it a bit more like a traditional computer
And you want to get into robotics
And actually embed a device in something
Or, you know, motorize small things
Then this looks like a neat solution for that
And not too expensive
Lots of language support as well
And I see Python in there
Which of course you're soon going to be an expert in
So that'll be good
Oh, I see, although now they're trying to
Get me back onto Ruby again
Don't do that, don't do that to yourself
You know, so a follow up
I wanted to get a computer for my son
And I had an exchange
With our friends at System76
Now I won't say who
But I got like an Apple-style rumor for you
You ready for this?
Rumor has it
Now I cannot confirm or deny this
But rumor has it
On Thursday of this week
So let's see, what day is that going to be?
So this is Tuesday the 31st
So on April
Oh yeah, it's probably a good idea
They don't do it on April
Yeah, so on April 2nd
A new System76 laptop is going to be announced
That's the rumor
And so it might be the perfect machine for my son
And I might have first dibs on it
These all might be things that are true
They may or may not
So we'll see
And then if they do have a new laptop
That releases this Thursday
Then we'll probably have one of the first reviews
Because I think I'm going to have one of the first units
On the Linux action show
So that was
Oh, that's awesome
I decided to go with a laptop
So that way he could come to the studio
And you know
I'll probably make him use this machine for like 5, 6 years
Or he'll use it for a couple of years
And then his sisters will use it for a couple of years
As they get a little bit older
So yeah
Hopefully that will work out pretty good for him
I think he'll like it quite a bit
And I think it's going to be the perfect machine for him too
So yeah
I really call
I'm really nice to him
I was really nice to him
So what do you think?
Should we back this Onion Omega?
What do you guys
I could go in
I could go in for 25 bucks
Is it worth backing to see if we could get one for the show?
I think so
I mean I think just based on the fact that it said
Hey Chris, would you like to be your own Tony Stark?
I think they kind of win there
So I would say yeah
I would like to be my own Tony Stark man
That is
Yeah
All right
Do it
Chatroom says do it
Mumble room
Anybody want to say don't do it?
Anybody want to vote for not backing this project?
Speak now or forever hold your peace
I'm going to do it
There you go
Wow
Okay
There we go
I'm going to back
I'm backing it right now
I'll back it $25
And because I feel like $25 is totally worth it
If we can have it here on the show
So
And I've just bought a device that you can use to exploit your new found Python skills
You're really pushing me in that direction
There you go
I feel slight amount of pressure to go in a certain direction
You'll learn something Chris
We'll back you in a way or what
Oh man all right
So there we go
I just backed it
And I felt good
I feel like that was a good choice
Like at first I wasn't sure if that was a good choice
But then I remembered that I wanted to be Tony Stark
And then I felt like a good choice
And I also want Morgan Freeman to narrate my decisions
And all decisions I make
So that sort of sealed the deal for me
And if you'd like to as well
I mean they only have a couple slots left at the $25
And then it starts getting expensive
But there we go woo-hoo
I mean at the $35 level
That's a pretty good deal
Because you get basically the same components
Now you tell me
As the
You can opt to get the network card
And then you get the same components as the Raspberry Pi basically
Now you tell me
After I just backed the $25 one
Dude way too late on the commentary
Way too late
No kidding right
I should have mentioned it earlier
I was going to mention it earlier
But then I was like eh
No you got to mention that
I pulled the trigger
Should I cancel it
Can you cancel a Kickstarter
Is that like a
What's that called when you back something
And then you pull out
What's that called
Are you talking about on Kickstarter
In real life
Oh on Kickstarter
You're not completely pulling out
You're just pulling out
And giving them more money instead
Yeah I should leave a note like
You can just give them more
And they'll upgrade
The former is called birth control
Yeah I should just send them a note like
This is not
I'm not judging you with this cancellation
I love you
Really I'm just giving you more money
I'm sorry
No I think it's fine
$25 is fine
I think you can do it
That's fine
No 25 is
I don't
Well that's
It's not too committal
You get in there early
If they grow cool
You can always add to it right
Yeah I suppose
I suppose
Yeah
I mean it's just
Tell yourself that
Yeah
Yeah I just wanted something for the show
Okay alright well
Ah jeez
If you want
If you want it
Oh you know what we need
That's why he has three kids
Wow
You can change your pledge
Okay
Alright so maybe I'll do that
I don't know
We'll save that for the post show
If I remember
Yeah there you go
That's probably a good point
Okay so we might have a little ass kicking
That we need to be handed to us
And we got a couple of good notes that came into the show
Okay
And Ryan did our friend from Evolvo S show up?
Easier
Okay who's that?
Ikey
Hi Ikey
Hi Ikey welcome to the show
Oh thanks
And you're with Evolvo S?
That's one way of putting it yeah
Okay well you are Evolvo S?
Yeah for the most part yeah
Yeah okay alright well good I'm really glad you're here because
You could give us a great perspective on this I think discussion we're about to have
And really which sort of translates into how much attention do we give distributions
That maybe don't have a larger user base as some of the other ones
Which obviously translates into audience interest
So it's kind of a tricky topic for us
But because you know part of the goal of our show is to give exposure to things
That deserve more exposure that aren't currently getting it
It's something I feel it's worth reevaluating pretty frequently
I don't want to make it obnoxious
But because you the listener have a bit of a stake in this
I think it's probably good we just have this discussion with our lug on the record
So you know where if there's a bias where it lies which there isn't one
But you at least know the logic and the process that goes into selecting what we coverage
What we cover and what dictates that coverage
So before we do that I'll thank our third sponsor this week
And that's DigitalOcean
Now this is the secret right here
You want to make yourself look like a boss
You want to offer out client services
You want to have a great back end infrastructure
You want to make sure your website runs super fast
You want to make sure your project looks smart
You want to have your own domain
You want to get your data off some cloud service
You want to do it right it's DigitalOcean
I'll tell you why DigitalOcean is a simple cloud hosting provider
Dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you
To spin up your own cloud server
You're going to have root access with an HTML5 console
And through a great interface I'll tell you about
And all of it you can get started right now
In super super no time like super flat no time
It's crazy and you can try it out two months for absolutely free
We use our promo code
We got a special promo code for the unplug show
It's D.O. Unplugged
D.O. Unplugged all lower case one word
Gets you a $10 credit over DigitalOcean
Find out about DigitalOcean
Just go try it with that promo code
Because there's no cost up front
You're not going to need a credit card
And you can get started in less than 55 seconds
You'll have a server for less than $5 a month
Or about $5 a month
I actually have three servers and I like it a lot
Because I just apply a balance to my account
And this is I think a really great system
Because I have a few PayPal accounts
And one I use for Steam purchases
And that PayPal account that I use for Steam purchases
I just also sometimes have a couple extra bucks
After I buy the Steam games
And I'll just send them over to my DigitalOcean account
But you can use our promo code D.O. Unplugged
And you get a $10 credit
And you can try out the $5 rig for free
Here's what you're going to get for $5
512 megabytes of RAM
A 20 gigabyte SSD
One CPU
And a terabyte of transfer
A terabyte
They're all SSDs too
They did that early on
And I think that's a really smart move
And made them really competitive
And they've got data center locations in New York
San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, and London
But their interface is really great
The DigitalOcean control panel is like their secret sauce
It sits on top of their great connectivity
Their excellent data centers
They're all SSD I.O.
Of course, Linux
The KVM virtualizer
Which as you know is the best out there
Come on, what's up
Come on, you know that
All of that rides on top
All of that is just controlled by this
This interface is just amazing
It's the best out there
It's very intuitive
And you can replicate its functionality on a larger scale
With DigitalOcean's very straightforward API
Which a lot of the community is already doing
You can take advantage of the stuff that's already out there
You can do DNS management
You can take care of your snapshots
Back things up
Destroy them
Use the template to get started even faster
Use one-click deployments to get Ruby on Rails going
Docker, GitLab
All kinds of stuff
Ghost, WordPress
The list is just always growing
So much good stuff
And use the promo code dounplug
Try it out two months for free
dounplug
One word lowercase
Head over to DigitalOcean
Try it out
Check out their tutorials as well
They're really top notch
DigitalOcean.com
dounplug
Get the $10 credit
And a big thanks to DigitalOcean
For sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program
It's a really good service
Okay, so let's talk about our coverage
So we've kind of got Gabriel 3 in the subreddit
Kicks it off
He says, hi there, Chris, Matt, Noah, JB Producers
Mumble Room
Fellow community members
On the latest Linux Unplugged episode
Chris announced a roundtable on distro coverage criteria
In my opinion, it's worth to express our thoughts
On this as a community too
He wanted to kind of work through this
You know, you have mainstream distros
You have new distros
Third derivative distros that are beginner friendly
Fifth is, you know, he says you also have
Fifth, despite Chris and JB's good will
Some interesting distros will not be covered
Because there are hundreds of distros
It's quite impossible
That's very true
So he started off a pretty good conversation
And folks, you know, sort of kicked in
Like some people want to see more coverage on NixOS
And I wasn't so sure I wanted to get into the specific distros
We should be covering
Although we can talk about specific distros
But I wanted to talk a little bit about
Sort of the selection criteria
And then maybe Aiki can chime in with what he thinks about it
From somebody who's maybe tried to get more attention
From a media outlet
So our selection usually is based on what we perceive
To probably generate the most interest in the audience
And also has to be something we have experience with
Or use ourselves to some degree to be able to review it
And that depends
Like so, you know, we'll try out an op
We'll try out a distro for a couple of weeks
That we don't actually run just to do a review
But things that are more in our wheelhouse
Are going to be stuff that's closer to our daily run
So that's sort of
If there is a bias, that would be it
And then what we select
The only real selection criteria is if it interests us
And we think it might interest the audience
So sometimes we will feature something
That maybe the audience has never heard of
But we think, ah, based on what we think they're going to like
Once they find out about this
It'll pique their interest
And so we'll run it
But that does mean that certain things kind of get left out
More often than not
Distributions that maybe you could label as less relevant
But I don't really feel like that's fair
Because even a really small distribution
Can have something very innovative going on
But it's maybe distributions that have a much lower user base
I don't know exactly how to say this
That sounds about right to me
Yeah, you know what I'm trying to go here, right?
Yeah, yeah
Yeah
Something that makes
Ryan, you have an idea of what makes something coverable?
Yeah, there are derivative distributions out there
And a lot of distributions that build just ever so slightly
On, you know, an innovation from its parent distro
Which is fine
But to me that doesn't make it necessarily worth covering
I think you're right when you say
You really want to cover a distro
When it's doing something innovative and new
And something that might actually be a game changer
One reason I contribute to and enjoy Volvo S
Is because they
Aiki did a really great job of pulling out a lot of stuff
And he built it on top of
It's not a derivative of another distro necessarily
Or at least not any living distros
And really just rethought the whole desktop environment
From the ground up
Yeah, that's exciting
And so when you look
What I would like to hear as a five-year listener
Of Jupiter Broadcasting is
Is about distros that are doing something new and exciting
Not necessarily every distro that pops up as a derivative
I don't want to hear about the Ubuntu derivative
Sorry, Opi and Wimpy
Well, wait a minute
Sometimes they're really good
Well, if they are, then that's great
I think Ubuntu Mate is worth hearing about
Because, I mean, where are you going to go to try out Mate?
You know, if you're not on Arch
Or some place where you're just going to
Throw it on your machine and go
Everywhere, it's in every distribution
But not done right, it's not done right, is it?
Well, no, some distributions do it better than others
But, you know
Okay, so Aiki, coming from the
You know, the Evolvo S perspective
You probably don't hear Evolvo S mentioned as often as you'd like
What are your thoughts on that sort of spot you get stuck in
When you're a distribution of that size?
Lovers
Basically
We wouldn't get a lot of attention
So, what people are interested in now is
Ooh, shiny
So, I mean, I'm not going to point out
Any specific distros at the moment
Because, like, people listen to this
And I'd get in trouble
But people are really, really interested in the whole
Design-led philosophy at the moment
So, something's really, really pretty
They take something else and basically whack a new skin on it
And that's what people seem to be interested in
So, for us
I guess you could say in that way that we suffer
Because, you know, I mean
We've got the budget desktop and, you know, it's kind of sexy
But people want all the shiny Google things
Which we're not really doing
We're more interested in making something that works
So, yeah, we do have to work a bit harder
But, unlike some of the other projects
We're not actually
Financially dependent on success
Which kind of makes things a lot easier for us
Like, we're not whacking a new wallpaper on and saying
Can we have a donation?
Because, you know, we look good
So, it's easier for us in that respect
And the thing that
It seems to be the hump you have to find
The hump to get over is
That, oh, there's something interesting happening here
And then once everybody kind of agrees
Something interesting is happening here
It seems like the coverage just sort of naturally starts rolling
And so, why don't you tell us a little bit about
Evolve OS and pique people's interest
Because it looks super slick
It looks really nice
I mean, so it's got a bit of a history behind it
So, I mean, a lot of people would know
That I was, you know, involved in
Well, involved in Solus West
I was Solus West before all this
So, what I did there is
You know, we made a couple of mistakes along the way with Solus West
One of the things I really, really, really wanted to do
Is make something that only targeted the desktop
Now, to a lot of people
That's going to sound really stupid
Because they'd be like, well, you can take Ubuntu or Fedora
And just like, you know
Only have a desktop on there
The problem with those distributions
They are very much generic
Now, I don't mean that by way of an insult to those distributions
But if we look at Debian
It advertises itself as the universal distribution
You know, it's the universal operating system
You can use it anywhere
To be fair, I mean
I only have desktop machines
And I really couldn't care less
If I had the potential to run this on a Raspberry Pi
Or something like that
I just want to run a desktop machine
I mean, it's great being able to do that
But for me, I just want something that runs on what I have
And that happens to be 64-bit machines
That are desktops
So, I only want a desktop on it
I don't want to be able to run this like we have Apache
And MySQL, and you know, all those carry-on
Sorry, MariaDB
Got to be politically correct
Got to keep it hip
But, you know, that's all I wanted
So, it had to be very, very
You know, it had to be trimmed from the get-go
It couldn't have all these possible options
So, you can only run Budgie Desktop on that
That's all you're getting
For anyone who doesn't know, Budgie Desktop is
It's a GTKM modder-based desktop
Similar to
I guess similar to how Pantheon is implemented
You know, where you just use the same libraries
And basically piggyback on all that hard work
To put it bluntly
But another approach with this was
Kind of to show people what you can do with GNOME
So, you know, I mean
GNOME has been forked so many times now
That they're going to need to puncture a packet
There's just loads of forks
Like, flying around the place
We wanted to show what you could do with the technology
You know, it's a bit more work
But in the end it pays off
So, we've got a healthy upstream relationship with GNOME
We contribute to GNOME
I know I was supposed to be saying good GNOME
But, you know, I have the remnants of an accent
And that's just not happening
I see, and you're linked to friends of GNOME here on your site
Right here on the blog, which is nice
Yeah, you've got to be nice
You know, got to help them out
I've got some bugs in them
Sometimes they're not interesting bugs to the GNOME project
So, I don't know about you guys
But, like, I like to play Kerbal Space Program
Because, you know, I'm so rad
And cool
This is not selling, is it?
So, one of the problems that I actually found
Is on older versions of GNOME
Or GNOME Shell or, in our instance, Budgie
Would just die
Which was really, really oddly depressing
I couldn't play Kerbal Space Program
I had to fix for that and send the patch upstream
And that's now living in mutter
So, that's some of the stuff that we do
That you wouldn't find in, say, a respin
Where they add a new wallpaper on
You know, there's not a lot of upstream stuff happening
Whereas we build everything
Right, yeah
And that's a ton of work, I mean, that's the downside, right?
Doesn't that seem like a huge, huge
Never-ending amount of work?
Yes and no
So, I mean, when I was building LibreOffice
Well, I mean
I'm getting flashbacks now, that was hard
I was ranting all over Google Plus
About that, and then, you know
Four hours into the build and it's like, yeah dude
I needed this tool that I didn't tell you I needed
Haha, thanks
But, I mean, a lot of it is, you know
People seem to think distribution building
Is all about packaging, because that's the
Concept we've been exposed to
You know, you get all these packages and you put them together
Well, to be honest, packaging is really boring
So, if people tell you
They like maintaining
A load of packages and updating them
They're either lying to you or
You need to refer them to the local mental health unit
Because, you know, it's
Not nice to do it
So, some of the stuff that we're tackling in Evolver West
Is basically just to get rid of all that crap
So, how does that work?
So, how do security updates work? Is there a package management?
Does it pull down updates or is it
What? How does that system work?
Okay, so, we're
Using, I can't even say the name
Of the package manager, because we've renamed it
I guess you would
Renounce it PC, but it's spelled
P-I-S-I
Yeah, anyway
So, that was abandoned
By Pardis Linux like a couple of years ago
So, the way I was looking, I wasn't really
I know it sounds bad, but I wasn't interested
In package management itself
Because I think that was really, really, really
Boring. So, I mean, if you're looking for
A real hardcore package manager that's got
All the bells and whistles and all that kind of
Stuff, then use Arch Linux or something
That really care about their package manager
Because I don't. I want
To be able to install packages and update
And, to me, that's what a package manager should do
But I noticed, like, Firefox 37, which came out today
Is available for Evolve OS already
It is, because it takes me no
Time to update it at all. So, the
Thing that we want to do is make
Everything really easy. So, it's
About the development process, because it's
Mainly me doing the packaging. I've also got Justin doing
Packaging now. But, if I'm
Going to spend hours doing packaging, then
There's never going to be a feature in the
Distribution. There's never going to be any
Level of integration, which is pointless.
So, if I'm super concerned about security fixes
Should I maybe use something else? So, this is more
About experimenting a little bit?
Oh, no. We do security updates. So,
I think it was just the other day that
We did some glibc updates. There was
Another one that went in yesterday. I'd have to check
The git log, to be honest. But it's all off
From git hub. So, one
Of the projects that I've done in my
Own work time, like in my own professional
Work, is open source.
And that's called CVE Check Tool.
Now, that's usable by all projects. So,
Yes, I made it for work, but I also
Made sure that it worked for Evolver West as well.
You know,
You've got to do these things. So, I mean,
That particular tool is something that's now been
Used by Evolver West, and it uses the National
Vulnerability database, which is synced
Every three to four hours, and maps
Into every source package we have in our
Distribution. Which, to be fair,
I mean, it's not the greatest number, but they'll then
Tell us if we have any vulnerabilities, what we've patched,
What we've addressed. You know, like
The latest OpenSSL incident, it discovered
That before it had
Been formally announced. But it's
It's all non-embargable
TVs, but there is a process to it.
You've got to have secure
Up-to-date software, but we're not a rolling release.
Right. So, it's
So, there are points in time where
I would sort of maybe reload
After a certain new release, it wouldn't be necessarily
Upgraded to that new release.
Right, and, I mean, that's
Kind of across that bridge when we get to it
Situation, because we haven't done a one-to-two
Yet, but ideally we want to make it
An update that works, because, you know,
Linux is notorious for it doing
Between two major
Releases, so we want to make sure that actually
Does work when we go ahead and do that.
That sounds really exciting. That sounds like a really interesting
Does anybody in the mumble room have any questions
For Ike?
I think I'll
Be able to download the ISO and give it a run.
Sounds pretty fun. I think it's something I want to test out.
I've actually got a machine in mind I'd like to pop it on there.
It's going through the website, just kind of getting a
Feel for it. I like the layout.
I like where it's going. I think it's interesting, but it's
Definitely something I want to immerse myself in for a little bit.
Also,
You guys would really probably want to
Shout out our software center.
It's pretty darn lightweight.
It loads instantly.
That's not a jab at anybody.
But,
Granted, right now
It's still getting defied, kind of
By our art team and our
App developers.
But we hope
That it'll both look
Sexy and be speedy
Because nobody wants to wait whenever they're
Ready to install a new package.
And I'm really excited
About what that could be in the future.
Yeah, really.
Wimpy, you had a question.
Yeah, so, hello Ikey.
I'm running Evolvo
S on one of my laptops. It's one of
The distributions that I tinker with
And take a look at to see
What inspiration I can draw
From it. But I was wondering
What's your long-term plans
For the project? Where do you want to take it?
And what's your drive and
Motivation for making it?
Sure, so I mean, I guess to
Shorten the question that's basically
Is it a hobby or is it something that's actually going to
Go somewhere, right?
Not necessarily, just
Why are you making it and where do you want to take the
Project?
So for me personally, I've had
A bit of a problem with Linux distributions
For quite a while now.
I've been around doing the whole
Linux distro thing for a while.
I kind of have a vision of what a
Distribution should be and to me personally
Nothing I use on the desktop
Suits what I want.
To me
You should never have to open a terminal.
Yes, I am a geek. I'm paid as a software
Engineer. I use a terminal
A lot. But I don't
Believe I should be using that to do something as
Stupid as make PulseAudio work again.
Or to reload a configuration.
I mean, the most common thing
You see on any forum is just
Open a terminal and type sudo apt-get install
Or sudo yum this that and the other.
You shouldn't be doing that. Everything should work
From the get-go. So this isn't a packaging
Effort. It really is like an integration
And distribution effort.
If you like the distribution
Model when we go forward from
The stable release, you're looking at
Basically two years support per release
Because it should keep working.
And why should everyone keep updating?
Because things just don't get that exciting
In two years.
So for rolling release distros, that's all
Well and nice, but I personally don't
Want to deal with a breakage in libpng.
And I don't think anyone else does.
To me
For users, the thing that are really important
Is like, is my firefox
Browser two years out of date?
No. Great. Do I have VLC?
Is it recent? Do I have all
The support I need? Yes. Brilliant.
And going forward, we can have things like
Automatic driver management, which is basically
A given now.
But there's other things going on behind the scenes
Like backup and things like that.
Cool.
It's just a silly little thing.
So one thing that's always got me
And I don't know about you guys, but when you boot up
Now and you look at grob on any single distro
You've got a recovery option, right?
Now, what if grob
Is gone?
Yes, yes.
I've actually experienced that, yes.
Right, so
It's a completely redundant option.
And you look at package manager
So I mean the package manager that we basically inherited
And slash forked, if you like
I mean it's got options to do like
It's got rollback, which you know, that's absolutely great
But that needs to roll back from the internet
So if I push out an update
Say, I don't know, and I broke network manager
Which I totally didn't do a couple
Of months ago
Yeah, that was well awkward
But
You know, I mean you're absolutely screwed
You have no network connectivity
That that's gone, or let's say like, you know
Grob is gone, or you've corrupted
The first few blocks of your hard drive. You're absolutely
Notly screwed. So I don't see
Anything out there at the moment that's solving them for
Yes, there's no like, immediate
Recovery option. There isn't the whole thing you have
Windows, yeah I mentioned Windows
People can burn me, I don't care, it's cool
But
You don't have realistic recovery options
You don't
I mean, what's the most common thing people do?
Oh no, that's screwed, I'm going to reinstall it. Well no
You have to think in the concept like, I mean
You know, I'm not making a product here, I'm really not
But you have to think along the lines that this is a product
And you have to imagine as if it was
An OEM installation, they have
No disk to reinstall it, what are they going to do?
So you have to start thinking of solutions like that
How are these people going to get by for the next 2 years
With no recovery disk, you don't want them
To reinstall, and you have to be able to solve the problems
You need to be able to roll back somewhere
So that's the kind of things that we want to address in the Volvo West
Longevity of an installation
Basically. Very nice
Lael, you wanted to ask a question?
Yeah
My question is this
I notice in
I mean, most of the distros I've tried
Right now I am on Ubuntu Mate
Most of the distros I've tried
Whether in VirtualBox or actually on my
System
They require you to
Type in the command prompt to resolve
Dependencies, how does your
Distribution answer the question
Of resolving dependency through
Installing it through your package manager?
So
The package manager is something we basically wanted
To extract, I mean you can use it from a terminal
That's really really fine, if that, you know, that's what
Gets you going, more than fine doing that
But I mean, it works the same as any other package manager
You have binary dependencies
When we build our packages, that's actually
Automatic at runtime, similar to RPM
So there's a binary dependency
By a shared library, that's automatic
So dependency resolution, all that stuff
You know, works the same as any other
Distro, but we don't really want people to use
That, because that's dull, boring
And what not, you know, not what
Quote, normal people
Do, so you'd have a graphical software
Manager where you get everything done
But yeah, dependencies and everything, that's all
Automatic, and there's one
Place that we do differ, to say
Ubuntu or Debian
We avoid package conflicts
So, in the
Likes, especially things like
Build dependencies, which, you know, not applicable
To a user, but in Debian you have
Like libjpeg, and you have libjpeg
Turbo, which both conflict with each
Other, with us we'll just choose one
And we'll use that across the entire distribution
So you won't install something, it's like, ah
But you need to remove those 49 packages
And probably break your system
So we avoid those, and design it to
Work going forward anyway
And Colton, you had a question
Yeah
So, I went
Ahead and I torrented your ISO and I
Loaded it up in a virtual box just now
And
I'd just like to say that I
Really like your desktop environment
And your installer's pretty nice too
But, it seems a little bit
Technical, like there's no options
That allow the
Installer to automatically
Create a partition
On the hard drive, or
Like the option to install
Grub is unchecked by default
So, like
Do you have any plans to fix that in the future?
Oh yeah, I mean
That thing, you know, it's
Ugly, it's like an abortion of free will
Oh no!
No, it's getting replaced, I mean that's got a bit of
History, that installer, so
It's probably, next to
Ubiquity, it's one of the oldest installers
In Linux land
It was originally the LMD live
Installer, which I mean I used to be involved in that
Once upon a time, you know
We all make mistakes, no joking
And then another
Another thing that
I noticed is when I was setting up the
Disks, like I, one thing
Is I had to open Gparted and do everything
Manually, which is, you know
Something that most people aren't going to
Want to do, and then also
Like, it didn't have options
It had an option to set up
A root partition and a swap partition
And that's it, no custom
Home partition or anything like that
Yeah, I mean I'm not proud of it
And
I mean it looks nice
Visually it looks nice, but
Just the actual content
Of it is not very useful
Yeah, I mean it sort of sucks
Do you need help Ike?
What is a situation like that?
Do you kind of like doing it sort of
With a small team, or just yourself
Or just a few helpers? How does that work for you?
No, I mean if people want to jump in
By all means, jump in, you know
I mean obviously it started out for myself
I wanted, you know, I had certain needs
That weren't being, that doesn't sound right
I had certain needs for a distribution
We all do Ike, we all do
Wow
But yeah, certain needs that won't be fulfilled
In the distribution sense
You know, so that started out for me
But then other people started getting interested
Probably because I actually spammed the crap out of Google Plus
With screenshots, now I think about it
Might have something to do with it
Yeah, I mean we're on GitHub
They can just jump in and send us a pull request
And I will put a link to your GitHub page
In the show notes as well
So, that's cool
I'm downloading the ISO right now
One thing I will say is
I know it's like a pig in VirtualBox
Everything is
I don't blame you for that
I could make excuses for it, but
I just don't think you should run it in VirtualBox
Yeah, in my opinion
No one should ever run anything in VirtualBox
But right now I don't have a free machine
That I can just load it on
So, VirtualBox is like
Oh, it's at my fingertips, so I can go ahead and do it
I mean, it does make for easy testing
I will say one thing
It is very, very, very, very fast
On real hardware
So, you'll find
I did most of my benchmarking on an Intel NUC
Because they're awesome, obviously
That's a good test rig
If it runs good on a NUC, it's probably going to run good on a lot of hardware
This is a Haswell i5
To be fair, it's got 16 gigs of RAM
It's not a slouch
But it boots in 2.134 seconds
2.314 seconds
It's really freaking fast, basically
Aiki, thank you for coming on here
And chatting to us about a distro
That we haven't got a chance to look at a lot
And you're always welcome to join us
We have an open Mumba room
So, join us for any show
And give us an update on what you're working on
Or chat on stuff
I also would love to see other distro makers
That want to stop by and tell us what they love
About the distribution they're making
Because, take Aiki, nobody knows it like he does
He's passionate about it because he's making it
He's working on it, and it's cool to hear it from him
And so, if you're out there working on something
You're always welcome to join us, we just have to check your microphone
Make sure you're going to pass the sniff test
You know what, the sniff test, Matt
That's what I call it
I don't know why I call it that, because it's a sound check
It's nothing about smell at all
It sounds cool
Hey Matt, is there anywhere you want to send folks throughout the week?
As always, I've got stuff going on
With articles and whatnot
I always have new projects around the bend
Just as it sounds
Otherwise, if you forget the URL, you type in my name
And I'm number one at the top
That's magic, that's magic
Hey, join us live on a Tuesday too
You can chat with Matt, you can do that too, you can chat with me
You can do it over at jbliv.com
Alright everybody, thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode
Of the Unplugged program
And we'll see you right back here next week. Cheers!
Oh, we've got to do it all over again
Twomp in the chat room
Twomp in the chat room, fell asleep
So he missed the whole show, we've got to do it all over again
You know, next time, I'm just going to record the thing
And then that way he can just catch it on download
That would be way smarter
Why didn't I think of that one, Matt?
Well, if we're sniffing voices, we might as well have something to wake people up
Maybe I was sniffing too much glue
Alright, let's go pick our title
JBtitles.com, last chance to bang
And suggest the title
And all of that goodness
Alright, thanks for showing up today, guys
Good show, appreciate having Roboto here
And thanks Wimpy for showing us all up with your audio quality
That was good too
You're welcome
It's just amazing
Evolve your OS isn't bad, that's not a bad title
That's pretty good
Yeah, I like that
Linux Evolved OS
For Evolve OS, I think we should go for something subtle
You know, like just so
People don't feel that it's been rammed down their throat
Like, world dominating
OS should be in your front room
Go buy it now or we'll kill you
Something subtle
Yeah, something really subtle, I like that
How about Evolve OS?
It's better than the others
Well actually
We got into the whole social media thing the other day
Because basically, I'm an absolute attention whore
I gotta be blunt
We put up a tweet
Just to make everyone feel comfortable
Everyone was like
What was this one of the first tweets?
So yeah, I haven't
We haven't suddenly decided to start competing
With all the other desktops right now
Oh wait, yeah we have
So they kind of know
You're in it to win it
Evolve your OS is coming up at number one
Right now, that's not bad
The Kickstarter withdrawal method at number two
Systemd trolls Linux at number three
I think Evolve your OS is a pretty good one
I think it's pretty good, that's where I'd go
Yeah
I feel kind of bad because we co-opted the show
No it's okay
It was actually kind of fit
We wanted to get attention
That's the whole point
That's what I love about the show actually
We have the mumble room
It's totally unexpected
We had stuff to talk about
I love having a show where we can just go with it
It works out better that way I think
Definitely
I think honestly
If you had a lug
We'd get pretty close
And every now and then somebody brought a friend to the meetup
This is what would happen
Very true
Aiki you're my friend
Yeah you brought a friend to the lug meetup
It's pretty cool
That's too official isn't it
Can we go for acquaintance?
This is too close and comfortable
Lover, whatever it is, I don't care
Bring them
We're past that
This isn't being recorded anymore is it?
No of course not