Before we get into the show, I'm glad Wimpy's here because I bet he's noticed this
Wimpy have you have you noticed that there is like a trend online now
To just do like a screencast of Linux distros and and put some music to it like
Have you noticed some of my posts?
Here's like here's like here is exhibit a Ubuntu Mate 1604 here is exhibit B
It was also very dramatic. Yeah, I like this one and then of course here is C right here. Here's a good one
Yeah
And of course you know you can put like elementary in there you can put solos in there
You'll see all kinds of stuff come up like this is like a thing now. You've missed you've missed my favorite genre
Oh, what's that? She's the this is the voice
Synthesized reading. Oh, I have seen some of these
Source site. Yeah, so you get these screen caps with a
Yeah, it's yeah there and it's bad too. It's usually not so good
Is there an audience for this shit? Is this something I should be doing here? Cuz I know okay
Your audience is the people that show up in forums and that's all they've seen. Yeah, I guess
The ones with music and stuff there is an audience for that and that's if you're wanting to
demo something
To an international audience, you know where you don't need to say anything where what you're doing is obvious and
You know, why would you put a video up that has no sound at all?
So I kind of can see
An edge case for that, but they are growing in popularity and they have got sort of limited value
This is Linux Unplugged episode 127 for January 12th, 2016
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux podcast that's got a chicken in the slow cooker for dinner tonight
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hey there Wes. Guess what?
We have a fun show on episode 127
Oh a couple of topics that we've been fortunate enough to follow here on the unplugged show got some interesting updates this week
So that's where we're gonna start then we're gonna get into feedback about butter FS as a home file system versus ZFS
Oh, that's kind of nerdy
Interview with the guys behind scale. There was a about a 10-minute interview. We ran in the Linux action show this Sunday. Well a
Interesting part of that got left out got cut out from the interview so that we would fit in the show and we're gonna play
That part it's about what's new at scale and what's big and different about scale in 2016. We'll play that and then
Wes brace yourself
for remix OS
remix OS for the PC launch today, January 12th, 2016
Are you excited? I am excited now. I don't know if I'm excited. We should try it and see we're gonna try it and see
In fact, we're gonna try it and see we're gonna get a demo of it from them at the floor of CES
I got more curious than excited. Yeah, I guess that's curious is the way to put it. And you know what Wes?
I got a run right here on the machine. Oh, no way running right here on my machine in a virtual machine
Well, that doesn't we'll do a little walk through right now. I know and then at the end of the show
You ever get stuck being tech support and Fred with friends family. How do you get out of that?
Or is it our duty? Is it our duty? We're gonna do a little debate deep questions here
I know I know and you know how you know why we can do these deep probing
Questions Wes. I think I do because we have that awesome mumble room time appropriate greetings virtual log
Alright, so guess what we're gonna do a little topic updates before we get into that whole show and I love the name
I mean, this is why I think one of the reasons we're doing in the show
It's called snap craft snap craft 1.0 is a boon to snappy creator tool officially released
It's canonical. It's got a tool out there now, and I don't know if anybody in the mumble room
Might know any more about this than I do, but it's a new tool to generate
I would assume custom snappy Ubuntu Linux images. It's pretty cool snap craft 1.0
They're already talking about plans for a new version which is gonna support 1604 because the current one is based on
1504 nice yeah
And I think this is a great way to just let people go out there and make their own snappy based images
I was wondering how exactly that custom tailoring was gonna work from like a hey
I have an idea right and I want to use snappy to do it like let's say Ryan was sitting around here
You know he's talking about doing the Minecraft project, and this is like you know down the road sure
And you just want to go with Ubuntu snappy I
Was kind of wondering what was that process like I think this kind of makes sense tools
Do you need and I like the name snap craft? Yeah, that's fun
You have any any insights or opinions poppy you want to share with the crowd?
Yeah, it's kind of moved on pretty quickly
I I don't work directly on snap craft or snapping myself, but I work with people who do of course and
It's so it's it's a tool really for to overcome the problem that you know we've said we're gonna have a different
packaging system in the personal desktop right and
Part of the problem there is people say well
I've got all these applications, and I I want them to be available to users
But I don't want to have to learn a whole new packaging system
It's hard enough to create RPMs and devs and whatever else
I don't have to learn something else and that's where snap graph was born you create a single yaml file
That defines the configuration run snap craft and boom out out pops a snappy package
And you chuck it in the store, and you're done that sounds very easy to use yeah, that's great
Hard to get simpler than yaml really yeah, yeah
I wonder if you're gonna see I wonder if you're gonna see just
This will just be like the obvious choice since there's something here to do now like there's just the same make these there
I focus on robot operating system tools is kind of interesting
Just like that term
Yeah, you know operating systems for robots. Oh, man snappy will be the end of us all so I want to just give a mention
We are we do have a beverage that West brought in look at this
This is the vertex IPA that we're drinking on the show today with a BA score of 81
That's not that's not super great for bear advocate. No. It's not no. It's not super great. What do you think though?
It's got a 76 IBU. It's all right. Yeah, I was hoping for more honestly yeah
Yeah, so you kind of you're agreeing with the yeah, I think so. I mean it's not bad. It's a fine beer all right
Well, let's crack. We'll crack up on our second one
And we'll be drinking this throughout the show if you at home want to pause and grab yourself an IPA you get to play along
With our home version of the game also a virtual lug you're welcome to crack one open
So did you see the news that KD plasma 5.6 has a new feature and that feature is
support for the unity launcher according to a
A developer on this is over on softpedia
Grinding an article over on softpedia from a from a developer
They're citing the new KD 5
5.6 release will focus on being more user-friendly by removing any functionality that you the user think stands in your way to accomplish your daily tasks
Like maybe removing activities there will be a lot of new features and updated applications in KD plasma 5.6 as well
Let's start with the new unity
Launcher support as it would appear that KD plasma 5.6 will borrow the unity API from canonicals Ubuntu Linux operating system
To implement support for app notifications in the task manager for example
Chromium web browser without a slip display download progress
Telegram yeah, yeah
but KD devs are planning to extend the functionality to a major of other majority of other applications to like dolphin and
And other task manager and Thunderbird and whatnot I look forward to better media controls
I mean, I think we've all enjoyed that for yeah, it's meant and go
What is going on here exactly what's going on what's going? I mean, I love it
I'm not I'm not disappointed in any sense of them of the word, but oh, why why why are we doing this?
It seems like a change. Yeah style
Interaction for the I just does anybody in the mobile room have any theories on why all of a sudden the plot of the KD
Plat KD plasma desktop all of a sudden has an interest this far into the project
Am I missing something?
Well, isn't it just functionality? They don't already have they don't have the little progress bar on the icon all the
Labels in the corner, and so they need to do it, so they're going with this right a sane API
I can borrow it in the same way that you know we use components out of KDE on Ubuntu
They now imagine if we just did this on a broader scale, okay?
Just stop and imagine for a second
You know what jumped out at me though, and I don't really know what this means, and I don't know if anybody has any insights
It's gonna focus on being more user-friendly by removing any functionality that you the user think stands in your way to accomplish your daily
Tasks what the heck does that mean?
Sounds like they're gonna go gnome 3 on this business. I'm sure that's not that so
It's kind of confusing when you read that it was a little removing activities. They're gonna go gnome 3 up on this business
Yeah, that's what I was thinking although. I'm curious about it. I'm really curious about it, so we'll see I was you know I was
Reading the blog post of some Linux switchers recently and they landed on plasma desktop and loved it
So it appeals it a story to hear and I I really like that they're going with the unity API notification API because
Well a crap ton of stuff already uses that
So I I have gone on the record in the past and talked about butter fs and my issues with it
And you know I I think I kind of you know it's interesting
You know apparently to according to the Linux action show subreddit. I am just a strong hater of butter fs
I'm a basher of butter fs
Under the subreddit you paid a lot of things
It's just mostly my name hard to be hard to be around you
No do go on
Oh, hey, it's Danica Patrick. Enjoy this episode and use code Linux all right, so here is here's the question
In episode 399 you talked about ZFS as being more designed for the enterprise
While butter fs is more suited for home use, but you never really said why you think that could you explain?
Why you think this thanks love the show?
Butter fs and so I wanted to give my background with butter fs so I had it on five rigs
I got it still running on two of those rigs
Servers laptops desktops your names it I've tried it on a bunch of different rigs for the most part
I didn't have a really great time however butter fs. I think for a for a little bit of a
Little bit simpler a little bit easier to understand doesn't have some of the same memory requirements as the fs has which is a big
one for the home desktop and
I think butter fs is a little more like you can work on mounted file systems in a way
You can't work on them with set fs
but the other thing about ZFS and you know even even huge advocates like Alan will admit this it truly is a
file system designed from the enterprise standpoint from the very beginning and that includes the budget of an enterprise so in a lot of
Times the the best-case scenario is well
You should do that with two or four drives at a time two or four drives at a time
I can't afford to do two or four drives at a time all the time right so
Butter fs if you were working on a tighter budget you have less RAM
very flexible
Yeah, maybe you don't drive. Maybe you want copy-on-write. Maybe you don't want copy-on-write
There's just there's a lot of things like with butter fs that it's gonna come built into your Linux distribution
It's gonna be right out of the box
It's gonna be a little bit easier to set up because you're gonna have built-in tools to use it
Because they're gonna be built into the installer
It doesn't require quite the amount of memory that ZFS does if you really want to push it
So there's a lot of things about butter fs
I think that are better for home users just because it's that sort of starting spot for butter fs
Where ZFS especially in 1604 there's gonna be no graphical front-end hookups to it as far as we know at this point
It's all command-line to set it up. It's just not really
Feasible for home users. I think for my next home box. I'll build I think I might do ZFS
Yeah, and if you were you know if you're a confident administrator if you want to take the time to you know really invest
It's great for that and you know it performs very well
It's a wonderful file system
Mm-hmm, but I think you're right
I think what you talked about too with like it works very well and butter fs works very well kind of in the cloud environments
For service that you're gonna spin up. You just want you know you want root snapshots, etc. Yeah, yeah
Wimpy, how long until Ubuntu Mate edition that lets me use ZFS from the install menu?
That's a very good question
There's a couple of file systems. I'd like to see added to Ubiquiti and you never know I've made a few
contributions to Ubiquiti in the last year or so and I might make some more I'd like to see f2fs in there as well
Mm-hmm, I do I do picture myself
I don't know if you listen to tech talk today, but we covered the the new Skylake
NUCs that I haven't been announced yet, but they were Intel is talking about it CES
There's Skylake. They've got Thunderbolt 3. They've got PCI Express 3 Oh
So the you know the PCI the PCI hard drives are gonna just be crazy fast awesome
and you know you could get a couple of those things in there and
Maybe an external drive array over Thunderbolt 3 using ZFS that could be I mean that could be a really nice Linux rig
I'm definitely excited for the Ubuntu ZFS
I use a
LXC for a lot of development stuff and use ZFS for snapshots on the back end and right now you have to install the PPA
And you know if it's more integrated
Yeah, so I think that's sort of my thought anybody else have thoughts on using ZFS for your home or day-to-day rig as you know
Just maybe single hard drive even
It's a great choice if you want integrity I used to do this all the time the problem is I wanted to be able to
Defrag my disk and so I had to go back to butter FS
Yeah, yeah, that was really the main thing that pushed you back
Yeah, just getting performance out of it as it pushed me back really even though. I did have a lot of RAM
Just having it fragment itself over time was kind of a problem
And I mean I could reformat you know every six months or something kind of alleviate the problem
But I felt like butter FS was just worth it because I was keeping good backups anyway
I wasn't too worried about my data being silently corrupted. That's not gonna happen
It's gonna be very loud when it gets corrupted, and so if it did I would just revert to a backup right
I never even had that happen butter FS has been rock-solid at least tells you you know pretty right
You guys it's pretty obvious and butter FS is going to correct your data if it does
And I just haven't had that issue so as long as you're keeping good backups. I don't see the problem. Yeah, yeah, okay, so mr.
Kitty you think it's kind of telling that before butter if s even got a chance ZFS is already arriving for Linux
Yeah, I thought it was really weird especially you know BF
Btrfs being native
to Linux whereas
ZFS is something that takes a lot of work to have to pour it over and all this and that and it is rather telling
That's something that was
worked on for years
Is not as ready as something that they had to pour it over and all that well
You know ZFS has been worked on for years, too. Yeah
It's not like Btrfs didn't get get a chance it had its opportunity. Yeah, I agree
I think the market. I think the market is speaking right now saying you know what we watched it for a while and now
Now we know that our customers want something they can trust and the brand
ZFS is just stronger than brand butter fs and that's why you know
canonicals willing to shiv it into a
LTS using DKMS to make it possible for you because they cussed the customer demand
They're so strong that that all of a sudden is deemed LTS worthy
Because they need it in a long-term supported distro that people are shipping on their servers because that's where the customer demand is and I think
That right there demonstrates how much demand there must be seen if they're willing to do that
I also think the enterprise requirements are so you know so serious like that data really matters in some
environments and like
BSD now they interviewed Joss Pate's pixel from IX systems
Yeah, and he said like you know open ZFS has been around for like 10 years and even now
It's still an immature file system, so yeah, that's the case for ZFS right it makes sense that that would that's that is
That is absolutely how enterprises think yeah, of course they cover this a lot on BSD now
Yeah, they yeah that interview with Josh is great because Josh is out in the field supporting a lot of different people's I
Jokingly called him the pool boy, but he's out there supporting a lot of people's
CFS pools in production
And he's just you know he's just seen a huge aggregate of data and so he's a I mean
He's a in real world expert on it, and so he was over to IX systems
And they let us talk to him and so yeah, that was a great episode
That was just last week's episode of BSD now to go check that out
Hmm. Yeah, all right the downtime is expensive data recovery is expensive and RAM and dis are cheap
That's how the enterprise looks at ZFS, and that's why I really when I say it's an enterprise grade file system
It's even meant from an enterprise budget, but our FS
I think still has long-term potential, but I just think its potential is it's not gonna be these huge data sets
And I think for some of us who are willing to do the administrative overhead or understand you know
Philosophically what's great about file systems like CFS that are constantly doing checks on me and things like that we might choose to go
CFS over butter fs even though it offers some of the same features
So what will be what will be interesting to see is now that now the ZFS is sort of making gains in the Linux world
It'll be interesting to see if
B3FS just loses
appeal at all or
If it will be a slow burner and five ten years from now it will emerge as an alternative
Yeah, it seems to me like because it because it's almost like the precious off now
Yeah, I almost wonder if it won't be like you format your root or your home partitions or var or user you format
Those in butter fs and your slash data or storage partitions are in ZFS
because I wonder if one of the things that wouldn't push butter fs forward just for like the OS base OS is
Maybe some sort of software deployment that uses butter fs sub volumes to deploy software
Sort of like the Mac OS uses sparse volumes
HFS sparse volumes to deploy software we've talked to Lenart about that
And he says that's in that's entirely possible that you know we would mount a butter fs
Volume and you would do a copy from the file systems
You'd have the entire file system structure
And it would be make a lot of sense that you would have butter fs
Do you wouldn't have to have butter fs on your current file system to be able to mount a butter fs file system?
But I could really see it I could see a you know integrating with snapshots and all that just makes Linux administration easy
And it's just it's built right into the kernel
And I could just see it over the next few years becoming used for that and then you just run it like that for a decade
And it's gonna be a pretty tried and dreaming
That's that's really how extended got its start, and then it you know it's a tried-and-true vial system now
So you don't think it's too early to call better fs
Dead on arrival yet. No I don't think so
I don't know you don't know not for a lot of work cases
I think there might be some workloads where the brand is too tarnished for at least a while
Yeah, I don't think it's I don't think in the next two three
I don't know I just kind of unfortunate because zfs had so much more money poured into it than butter fs
Did to start off with yeah?
Yeah
Like they had it under development for five years at Sun before it was released and they were pouring money in via developers at least
Three at a time yeah, whereas butter fs had Chris Mason for what a couple years on its own
Yeah, people sending in patches is a totally different paradigm
It's still only like four or five people. It's not the same community
And we've also got B cache fs
which has grown up out of the B cache initiative and they've now turned that into a
Full file system, so that's going to be another copy-on-write file system
So it'll be interesting to see how that develops over the coming years and whether you know
Is it b3 fs could it be cache fs is it going to be z fs, but you know those desktop type?
scenarios you're looking at where you're doing
snapshots of your system by means of
backup for restore for continuity of running your machine I think
The jury's still out on that one. I think there's several contenders to open that space mm-hmm. Yeah, I agree
Yeah, boy is the and you know what at the end of the day?
We just have to remember we're in better shape than the Mac right. That's all that matters
Sorry I couldn't help myself and cfs is better than hfs plus come on. I know I know you see I didn't
Okay, so I want to talk about scale because there's some big changes that have happened plus
We have some interview stuff that I think it's pretty neat that we didn't get a chance to talk about before so let's take a moment
And tell you about how I'm gonna stay connected while I'm going down to scale and that's ting go to Linux dot ting
Dot-com to support this show and get our discount ting is great
It's no contract and you only pay for what you use
Just your minutes your messages in your megabytes
And they have a great dashboard to manage all of it that makes it really easy as a really easy and obvious as heck
Where you're at Linux dot ting comm you'll get a $25 discount off your first device or West whoa little insider tip
They have GSM and CDMA no way I thought that was impossible
So if you got a phone compatible with one of their networks
You can bring it over and get $25 of service credit just saying and they have great devices unlocked you own them outright
Or you can bring your own and manage it all with either the ting dashboard the ting mobile app or tings awesome radical customer
Support no contracts. No early termination fees. I said no contracts
Yeah, if you stuck in a duopoly contract because you know they're even they're thinking about dropping those things
They have an ETF relief program if you want a company that thinks that your internet should just be a dumb pipe go check out
Ting go check out ting they they believe in the dumb pipe they want
They want you to take their dumb pipe and put it in your device
That's what they want you embrace tings pipe go to look at refuse ting could you no no they got a dumb pipe and they
Want you to take it go to Linux dot com check out their store browse around see what they've got and also if you've been
Thinking about it experiment with their savings calculator that thing is a lot of fun
It's nicely designed it is and you know you can actually plug it into your existing account if you want and then go get that
Business and also did you see the news that ting got a great rating from Consumer Reports?
It's pretty great Linux dot ting comm rate as an understatement there five things
You didn't know Google now could do they have a great blog too. They got a ting tip
You know that Google now it does all kinds of things look at that. This is really nice. They put all that together
I'm not gonna spoil it for you
Also, did you know that Siri can beatbox? Did you know that no? I didn't yeah, let's try it right now. You're ready, okay?
This is live every okay. Let's give it a shot. Hey Siri beatbox. Here's
One I've been practicing boots and cats and boots and cats and boots and cats and boots and cats and boots
Do this all day cats and boots and yeah, no we're good. We're good. You know what so they got the iOS devices
They got the Android devices. They have the feature phones all ranging at different prices
No contract you only pay for what you use the devices unlocked including they got the zing back again
Which gives you that nice screen that tells you exactly how much data you've used you can manage the Wi-Fi password
It is like what I'll show it to you right now
This is like you know you know you know those really crappy my fight devices that have like they're really crappy web interface
Oh, you have to wait till they're crappy DHCP server finally gets running to get one of their IP addresses
You can log doesn't register host names. It doesn't know so the zing it's all just right here on the touchscreen
You get to see the Wi-Fi password. You can change the Wi-Fi password. You can see devices connected. I love it
Oh, wow also is connected right there. Yes. Yeah, that's great. They all they offer the karma, too
if you want to get on that karma business that go check them out linux.ting.com great devices great plans great people and
big supporters of net neutrality
linux.ting.com and a big thanks to ting for supporting linux unplugged
Linux.ting.com
All right, so first up a couple of things about scale. I want to mention I
Had to move the time I had to move the time alone. Yeah, yeah, so we go and set up our meeting and then Cory Doctor
Oh, he's like hey. You know what that looks like a great time and day. I'm gonna schedule my you know
Yeah, so he scheduled his keynote for that time
So I'm like well, and you know what I really love is like some people in the meeper like I'll still come
I'll skip Cory Doctor's keynote
I'm like oh my god that guy is so cool the one guys like well
I could come for like a little bit, and then I could maybe like sneak out, and I'm like no
Here's what we're gonna. Do we're gonna change. We're gonna just change it so that way we can all go see Cory Doctor's keynote
And instead of doing it really early so a whole bunch of geeks have to get up early after partying at scale
We're gonna do it at lunch
and then you can go recruit other folks at lunch and then bring them to the meetup and we'll convert them to the Jupiter
Broadcasting way if you're gonna be down in Pasadena at scale go to meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting
We got 21 people going already
We're gonna get a power lunch after Cory Doctor's keynote and stuff
Yeah, I'm pretty excited about it West so meetup calm slash Jupiter broadcasting if you want to get in on that
You're gonna be there poppy. I added you to the event without even asking you
I went to the meetup when you lost
Who do I know that's gonna be down there, and I could give them admin access to this so that way if they need to do
Something smart. I'm like well. I'll add poppy. He's gonna be down there. I trust him
Yes, I just lost you in there already like good. That's taking care. That's love. Yeah, you know you got it
You got to spread the love. I'm excited. I hope the lunch works out. I hope maybe we can bring a few extra friends
You guys gotta show up. I mean you're anywhere near there. Yeah, it's gonna be good one
And I don't know exactly how I'm getting there yet any of that's all up
So maybe pick Chris up off the side of the road on your right. I'll be hitchin
So I wanted to spend a little minute a couple of minutes here and play an interview
From a couple of guys behind the scale effort now. There's a lot of people behind scale
but Ilian and Gareth are one of the people are working very hard on bringing scale 14x together and
Noah had a chance to talk with him last week
We played a couple of minutes of their interview in the Linux action show and I got a couple of other minutes here
I want to play for you about what's new at scale
And what's kind of cool and separating it apart, and I think the context of it is you know things like ubi con check it out
So we're one of the things that's happened with scale over the years as we've grown become a bit of a hub for other
communities that want to run their events
in or around us so
for example will be you know the
Bun to do the bun to community will be running ubu con
Which is there is going to be their their new user and developer conference here at here at scale this year leading into that
Similarly we have events from the Postgres community the mysql community
DevOps day la so
So when you come to scale really you're probably getting about ten events in in one
Which is which is one great thing?
So in terms of the keynotes that you mentioned. We've got folks like Cory doctor. Oh will be coming out
mark shuttleworth will be a keynote as well talking about
You know how open source fits in it fits in a world of app stores and embedded devices where we don't necessarily
you know have access to the
What we don't necessarily have access to
You know to the source code as we're down from from apps or things like that
And how do we make how do we continue to make open source be important in that in that sort of an environment?
And then the last keynote will be Sarah sharp
Talking about diversity in the open source community. She's a
former Linux kernel developer that
Has a lot of experience with with some of the challenges of being involved in our open source communities
Yeah, yeah, that's absolutely terrific
You know and the other thing that I I always look forward to in addition to the actual keynotes is
a lot of the presentations that are given some you know
They're not they're not necessarily everyone commuting in one big hall for one big presentation by a well-known name, but sometimes
There are really cool presentations. I think it was last year or maybe it was a year before they had a
Presentation of 20 Linux commands that you never knew that you needed but once you find out about them
They should have been included by default in the distribution and man have I been able to implement some of that stuff
Yeah, are there any particular presentations that you personally either of you are looking forward to seeing?
Well, I mean going back to what I said before where we started the conference
To to be a conference that we wanted to attend
I think the ironic thing in that is that most of us never actually get to go to the presentations because we're busy
Running the conference. Yeah. Yep
and so but but one of the things that kind of touching on that I'm I'm always excited to see is
Are those presentations kind of like what you mentioned?
where you
it's it's not a presentation that you necessarily or a talk that you necessarily think of a
Head of time they're like, oh, yeah
I'd really like to see a presentation on the 20 most commands that I didn't know about exactly. I'm excited about the presentations that
Those type of presentations as well as the presentations by speakers that no one has ever heard of yeah because in my experience
those always end up being really awesome presentations and the speakers end up becoming like really well-known speakers and and it just it's
It makes me feel really good that they got their start at our event. Yeah, right on
I'm I I can't tell you how excited I am to come to the conference
So now I kind of I've been hogging the mic here for a little bit
But West have you ever been to an event like scale before have you ever or have you gone to any kind of big?
Linux convention where there's a lot of people coming in I went to scale once
Oh you do you so I have been I tell you what I have been avoiding scale
I've mentioned this before I've been avoiding scale from the very beginning just because it's you know
Some of these some of the events they get too big and then I feel like I don't want to go to them anymore
I'm kind of curious to see where they walk the line on this one
But I'm maybe maybe next year. Maybe next year. We both go down. That sounds great. Wouldn't that be fun?
That'd be really cool. And yeah
So I hope to see you guys there at scale anybody in the mummer room any other any poppy anybody have any
I've just had an email from one of the organizers saying that my talk has been accepted
A thing that I developed with Stuart language
I
Kind of bought thing that we developed and it's quite cool and I wanted to talk about it and how we developed it now
We did it in the community. Well
That's awesome. Very nice. Very nice. You know, they rejected that Alan Jude
Yeah, he had a time. Well, rightly so yeah, I know you want to talk about BSD BSD get that guy out of here
So Linux Expo get him out of here. They can have a booth. Yeah
Yeah, my here's my here would be my perfect scenario and I think I'm gonna do this at Linux fest Northwest
Oh, I would be to park the rover outside the event and then just like have people come out like, you know
Meet them on the ground be like, yeah
Well, you come out to this location in the parking lot at this time and just do the interview there cryptic GPS cord
It'd be amazing. Yeah, like a scavenger hunt
Okay, now we're into it
Okay
so if we could do like a scavenger hunt where you could get little clues and they'd they'd walk around the event and then end up
At the rover and then do an interview on JV
That would be amazing, especially if we could have like GoPros mountain like key locations, right? Okay
Well, maybe in the future one day we can dream big. You never know we dream now
Maybe in a few years we can achieve the seeds of the future. These are the seeds
Okay, so it's time for us to talk about remix OS
Remix I'm gonna be honest. I didn't I didn't think they'd do it when I saw the when I saw the announcement
I didn't even cover it as news
Because I'm like, oh, come on. This is nothing. They got some crappy ARM based PC. That's too slow
And I'm not interested in that and then they are gonna
Supposedly release an ISO at some time in the future. When can I actually see this? Okay
Yeah, let me know when the code ships and then we'll actually talk about it. Well today the code shipped
Yeah, and they were at CES. They had a booth Wow giving demos
So we're gonna cover all of that
Remix OS is a desktop operating system based on Android
and the idea is
To turn Android into a desktop
productivity
platform
So instead of just content consumption, right you can do content creation. So they're introducing windowing
They're introducing file managers and things like this a launch bar and a menu all these people you're gonna will show you more about it
And they're calling it remix OS
You know the idea would be it's a it's a serious contender to something like Chrome OS or
Even perhaps the Linux desktop itself itself. Yeah, so before we get into that, I'm gonna mention Linux Academy
Love Linux Academy. This has been something really fun to watch throughout 2015 is to see them grow and they're not done in 2016
In fact coming up on the 14th. They've got a big event
It's got they got some announcements you can tune in and find out Linux Academy is a great platform to learn about all the technologies
around Linux and Linux itself
Start by going to linuxacademy.com
Unplugged that supports the show keeps us going. Let's Linux Academy know you heard about it here
They have so much to learn and and even if you've been using Linux forever
There's so much good stuff
Like not only are you gonna appreciate the fact that people just truly enthusiastic compassionate about this are putting together putting together a great system
But as somebody who has like a pretty good sense of what's up and coming in the Linux world
I'm pretty damn impressed with what they've been able to turn around into great courseware and content
They have over
2,000 courses with video
instructor help is available downloadable comprehensive study guides distros all up the wazoo you can choose from and the courseware adjust to that
Virtual servers you SSH into they spin up on-demand as part of the courseware. I gotta say it again instructor
Help is available when you need it. I
Really think this is a platform you should check out. I would say to like if you've been stuck in a spot for a while
you
Need to kind of see what interests you you want to kind of see what direction you want to go to this is a safe
Playground because they have graded server exercises while you're working on the system. You're gonna get real-time information and feedback
That's gonna give you a sense of where your strengths are pretty quickly
We just keep seeing success stories of people who've gotten the job after studying at Linux Academy
You know there's a lot of interest in this area
Yeah, if you can show that you you know through something like Linux Academy that you're a competent
Yeah, that is a nice thing to as Linux Academy is a rising star
You you rise with them people in the industry know it already. Yeah, they have some really neat technology
Their scenario based labs are pretty unique the fact that they're following the technologies that they are following are great
You know their nugget system for when you don't have a lot of time
You just want to deep dive into a single topic it makes a lot of sense
They were on top they had some of the first and best content on openstack before anybody else because when that was becoming a huge
Thing like well this is obvious right you know I know same thing with Docker right the same thing with a lot of the technologies
Built around Linux now and including AWS that entire infrastructure I
Really like it, and they've got some great stuff coming up. Just around the corner
They're gonna announce on the 14th go to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged. You'll get our discount. That's the big thing
But also you support this show
This is a really solid platform, and if I worked in a job where my educator paid for like a little bit of oh
Right or why my employer paid for a little bit of education
Oh, man that like when I when I had when I was when I worked for somebody else a lot of times
I was just here's the budget first for self education
You know they can take online courses I could go to like a to a local you know a college
But this is a great option. This is a really great option so Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
Stay up to date on current technologies, too
That's what's really cool about it is you can get all the current stuff
Experts were really passionate about it instructor help available on-demand and you support this show holy smokes
That's a win-win-win Linux Academy comm slash unplugged so remix OS
I've been kicking the tires a little bit anybody in the mumble room tried remix OS
Yep, all right, okay, okay, so
Installing right now all right well before we talk about it
Let me set up a little bit about remix OS and they have a they have a video here to do that for us
So yeah, what's up?
This is this is at CES. He takes a thumb drive. He plugs it into a Dell PC
We're here at CES 2016, and we're really excited to announce remix OS for PCs
It's a project a collaborative project between Android x86 and ourselves and on January 12th
It'll be available for free download globally, so let's take a look
Oh, this is the guest mode resident mode selection screen one saves no data
That's a guest mode and the other saves all your data and apps. That's the resident mode, so let's go in and check it out
On the 12th when you download you're going to get two files. What is an iso file one is an exe file?
You're going to plug in a usb drive to a PC of your choice
And you're going to run the exe file load the iso file into that program and then install it onto a usb drive
all right, so we've done that and
Probably what were your first thoughts when you had tried it out, and what did you try it on I?
Don't know I tried in a VM. I I didn't want to dedicate a machine to this. Yeah, that's what I did here
I've I've tried Android x86 on you know various machines in the past, and I thought I'd give this a go, but
two things kind of threw me
one
I'm guessing you've tried it. Have you read the end user license agreement? No, I didn't that was I've not gotten there
That's not the first thing I did. Yeah, I'm guessing yeah, I'm guessing most people would you probably want to read it?
It's interesting and some of it is probably copy and pasted from
Somewhere else and you can guess where from if I read you three lines from the EULA if that's okay. Yeah
You agree that you irrevocably waive any and all ownership legal and moral rights to your user content
How's that sounds like that sounds like they got it from Google, right? Okay? This one will give you a better clue
You're also not allowed to oppose the basic principles determined in the Constitution of the People's Republic of China
Harm its national honor or interests or undermine its national religious policy promoting cults and superstitions
What you're not allowed to spread rumor disturb social order or undermine social stability
Okay, so that's a little odd. Yeah
Those are my favorite things to do
Well, I mean you're outside China
So, you know good luck People's Republic of China for enforcing those rules on those of us in the free West
But if you did any of those things and then you went to China
Might have a bit of a problem, huh?
Don't go to China Chris. So yeah, cuz yeah, I definitely can't go to China
So I've done all of those just in the last ten minutes. That sounds like a copy-pasta little thing, right? I mean, that's gotta be
There's other Chinese companies that have that the Xiaomi phone company have it like right there on their website
It's pretty much the same kind of thing
But that yeah, that's what you get because they're you know, at least part Chinese company that side
I did try it in a VM and
You have to be you know, because it's Android and it's not a general purpose PC OS
You have to be very specific about the hardware that you give it
You know, it doesn't work on every PC is a general purpose, but yeah
There are drivers missing so you have to be you have to tweak it a little bit in virtual box
for example, but it does boot and
It it's very it's very unlike Android in that it's it's got
Windows for things like settings I went to the settings screen and I was expecting to get smacked in the face with the usual full
Screen and right now settings. Yeah, but no it looked like you know, no more solace or something like that
It looked like a normal modern desktop operating system
And you know, I fiddled around with some of the settings and some of it works
Some of it didn't I went to get a Google Play
APK
Because it doesn't ship with Google Play. It doesn't have Chrome or anything. It's got you know, none of the official apps
So I went to get the Google Play APK and that wouldn't install
In their videos they have the play they do have the place to end Chrome installed, right?
So they put that on it's not on the ISO
Yeah, I did try installing it, but it wouldn't open but I didn't give it a huge amount of time, you know
Yeah, if I may step in here. Yeah
So I installed it and there is in fact a semi-official version with GF's and I created a USB
USB stick out of it and it's running bleeding
How did you where did you find that? Is that not part of the regular loader? I
I logged into the free node remix OS channel, which is semi-official also and so there were some leaking images
But on the official server and there is a version from yesterday that comes with GF's installed
so I
Made an USB stick out of it and used it on an AC Chromebook and I was pretty successful
So it's bleeding fast. I played Star Wars Angry Birds on it. I was watching live TV
Yeah, so so it's there is some potential in this really there is some potential
Yeah, there are there are definitely some Android apps. I wouldn't mind having on my on my desktop
And you know, you've got you've got some other nice serious applications. So
Before we go on they were at CES and here's a there's also it
So there's a hardware component to this as well and a little more information about the project, too
Hello everybody
Welcome to the remix OS CES 2016 booth for all the people who couldn't make it but really wanted to be here
I wanted to give you guys
Inside look to what our booth looks like and what we're doing at our booth
Okay, and they actually when you watch this video, they actually seem like kind of neat people
They can think I'm passionate. Yeah about this. So here we are at CES International 2016
It's a remix OS booth again, and we've got a few of our team members right now
Showing off our product lines as you can see
This is the end of the day here at CES, but it's still relatively busy at our booth. So let's take a look
Yeah, I don't mind him
Jeff behind the counter right now. He's actually showing off
This is the mini which a lot of you already have you know and love if you don't love it
right us, but that's that support and
This is the mini in action right here on this screen. We've been showing it off at the booth
It's been getting really well reception here at the show if you move on down the line
This is Owen works with us on PO and what you see here is a very exciting project
Let's keep going down and I'm going to show you this project right here
So here at the show one of the biggest announcements we're making is this this is the remix
I like that there. I like that. They're also just being really upfront. We're working with Android x86 to do this
I think that's kind of cool. What it is is we've worked in
collaboration with the Android x86 team
Put remakes OS on top of Android x86 and allows remakes OS to boot from any Intel or AMD
chip PC
Tower
Laptops and about 60% of them out in the market or out in the world will work with this
ISO file so
And so it's a 40%
It's a pretty that's a pretty you basically have to have you know let some legacy USB support and things like that
But I don't know. I think it's it's interesting that you law obviously leaves me a little concerned
But if I could install G apps or gaps on this thing and I could have chrome and I could have Netflix and Plex
Might be kind of compelling
So when it comes to chrome chrome is working without problems so at least with the USB stick
And it's easy to create one you just
Download unit boot in from the repos and then you can create your stick. You don't even lose your data on your stick
It's just some persistent image files
So you get a system image a data image and so on and they're persistent image for your data
So the rest of the data that you have still have on the USB this the old daughter is stays on the disk
So it's really cool. Hope you. What do you think about the fact that they're they're essentially promising convergence
They're promising a desktop operating system that works with touch or the keyboard and they're saying whichever one you want to use
Do you think it's possible to deliver it in this type of?
It'll windowed system. Yeah, you know, it'll be
As you'd expect Android to be on a on a desktop, you know with some modifications
I think one of the problems they'll be is they're constantly chasing
Google because you know IO has just been announced is going to be in May and they'll be talking about the next version of Android
And so x8 Android x86 is always a little way behind
Upstream and so they're constantly chasing Android and part of that means that they've got to keep forward porting all of their work
So if they can keep that momentum going and they have enough contributors to
Keep their stuff working then. Yeah, they could they could end up having an interesting converged device
There's a lot of Android games. I mean
You know right there this could be an interesting desktop for some people. I don't know
Yeah, imagine imagine putting that on a desktop
Yeah, yeah, and imagine doing it maybe at a school, right where you don't want to necessarily be cooked up to Google apps and Chrome
But you want to take advantage of all the development and applications and the fact that a lot of people you're hiring are gonna know
How to write Android apps. I think they're gonna have to be a little bit careful. I mean you can see why they've not
Put a public
URL up there with all the Google apps in there, but you know giving it away on IRC
And you know done it kind of under the table kind of thing so that you know Google aren't gonna come after them
Which you know if they if they started doing that kind of publicly then Google would come after them
And that's something they've got to worry about they've got to have a you know
Or they build a relationship with Google and start doing it properly rather than you know
Based off of a OSP right? Yeah, that'd be a big indicator. See what happens, huh? Yeah
And hopefully they don't go the way a sign engine mod and start integrating with Google
Yeah, and hopefully they don't go the way a sign engine mod and start integrating Microsoft through all the OS like that's been happening lately
Cortana and like you can now you can you can get Microsoft services. It's just all over
It's just really great. They give a shot. They give a shout out to Ubuntu on there on their page, too
So anyways if you're out there tried remix OS let us know what you think Linux action showed at reddit.com
Anybody else in the mumble room and trying it or have any other thoughts they want to share about remix OS
remix
Remix OS. No, I did happen to just notice that they're already on
2.0 on the latest ones. Oh
Oh 2.0. Yeah, and at a booth at CES that suggests some funding. Don't you think it's a serious project?
Yeah, that's not a cheap thing pull off. Yeah, so that's and they're also touting the performance
They say we beat we've benchmarked remix OS performance using remix OS
For PCs against some of the best Android hardware in the biz and quite honestly nothing comes close
So they're running they show this benchmark here. This is so funny
This they show this benchmark here of remix OS for the PC running on an i7
4790 quad core up against a galaxy 5 note and a galaxy s6 and it just
It is just like it's not even in the same dimension. It's so much. I 7 is so much faster
Well, yeah, you think I guess the point is you could run your Android apps on a really fast machine
That would be kind of interesting. Yeah, but yeah, I could see installing this for like
a grandparent or something if they you know, they're already familiar maybe with Android on a tablet
Oh, I see the Internet is already beginning to gripe about the EULA
So the issues about the EULA have yeah, look at that, you know
I did see the EULA come up first thing when I when I loaded it
Harming national honor and interest national honor boy
That's will be played back to you in a Chinese court in like three years Chris. That is a loose definition this day
Yeah, well, what do they do about security updates? I don't know. That's a very good thing about Android
On your Nexus devices getting a regular cadence of security updates a week. I mean obviously this is an alpha
So it's completely unsupported and there will be no security updates, which is fair enough as you'd expect
But I'd be interested to know what the future holds and what their plans are for delivering
Delivering updates to all those, you know PC users, right? Yes, but it sounds like they have the operating system fairly separated out from user
Data and so then they maybe they have something in mind that will be fairly manageable
They don't know. Yeah, I have to wait and see you know, so here we are
We're towards the end of the show when we were towards the end of the second
Vertex IPA and I gotta say I mean, I'm glad you brought it, but I'm not loving the aftertaste
Either that's kind of disappointed. It's a little it's a little dank of my mouth
Yeah, right now. I feel like I'm gonna need a couple of cups of a couple glasses of water after this would not buy again
Yeah, that's too bad. I'd like to like the bot. I mean the can is yeah
It's got a good design on there. The dude's got a flag. He's got a nice hat. I like that
Very nice seemed like it was made with care. Yeah. Yeah
6.3 percent, huh?
Where did you pick this up?
Hagan, okay. Well, there you go. You know, Hagan's got a good selection. It was a good try. It was a good solid try
I mean, I'm better next week. I would I would also pick that one if I can't I don't think you can really be blamed
Okay, yeah. Thank you. All right
well, so we have an interesting thread that West found this week is like I think we got to talk about this on the show and
I answer kind of agree and I wonder if I want to challenge the premise a little bit too
But before we get to that good talk about digital ocean do the big do and use the promo code do unplugged all one word
lowercase
Guess what ten dollar credit? Whoa?
Linux rigs up in the cloud y'all on-demand less than 55 seconds
$5 a month you get 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte of transfer a
Terabyte of transfer over digital ocean comm and if you use the promo code do unplugged
$10 credit you can try that $5 rig two months for free and they've got data center locations in New York, San Francisco
Singapore Amsterdam London Germany and children with Alan Jude up in Toronto
Hey, hey, yeah, yeah, I think he just stops in there from time to time
Yeah, I don't know for sure, but really what I like about digital ocean
Well, I mean, I don't know why nobody else can figure this out
But boy his digital ocean got just a huge head start on everybody so yeah, they've got SSDs. That's brilliant
They would just you know they got in on that super early before any other
Provider out there was willing to spend the money, so they totally leveraged that
I think they were brilliant in the fact that they jumped on KVM and started building their product around KVM way before other vendors
Were willing to consider KVM now. They're just introducing KVM as a feature right, but they're struggling
They're struggling to keep up, and then they brought it all together with the incredible interface over digital ocean
It's very simple very intuitive and very powerful
It lets you destroy machines deploy machines one-click application deployments of an entire stacks
Or you know you want like you want everything from Ubuntu Apache and a blogging platform in a single click boom
It all gets deployed for you, or maybe you just want the base operating system
They've got a bunch of great distributions you get to choose from Ubuntu CentOS Debian Fedora core OS and even free BSD
one-click applications you can deploy
fantastic tutorials and
Incredible prices go to digital ocean comm and use the promo code do unplugged
And see why it's been my Linux infrastructure on-demand whenever I need it. I mean really at five dollars a month
There's almost nothing. I won't spin up on a digital ocean droplet, so I got an idea Chris
Yeah, so sometimes. I just don't have a great route somewhere. You know Comcast. It's everyone's on Comcast
Oh, and I get frustrated. Maybe I'm talking to Europe the worst you know maybe
Last number last Tuesday's you're having all kinds of issues all kinds of issues
Yes, right, but so what I do when I'm thinking maybe a script with their api's
There's a need you spin up a DO droplet. Whatever is closest to you. I don't you could probably figure that
I do the same friend myself. Yeah, and then SSH. Did you know you can spin up a tunnel interface?
Oh, yeah, and have SSH provide IP transit. Yeah, so you just you spin that right?
Oh, yeah, and then BAM you route everything through your have done that make a new. Oh, yeah
I have I have legitimately done that when we've had Comcast issues. Yeah, so what I'm just saying
There's other things in like Amsterdam that you might be in London
I'm saying there might be a reason why you want to be located in London
I'm not saying what it is
But or if you're in London and all of a sudden it'd be really useful to be located in New York or Singapore or?
Or Toronto or maybe San Francisco digital ocean makes it that easy it does for five dollars a month
And if you use the promo code do unplug to get it two months for free so a big
Thank you digital ocean for sponsoring the Linux unplug program you guys are the rock source
All right
So what do you do when you keep getting the geek squad treatment? He says I'm an IT manager for a website
I manage developers and perform a lot of hands-on activities to work. I'm not really a hardware tech anymore
However friends and family rarely make the decision or I'm sorry distinction when their tablet or their laptop or their desktop is broken
And they often ask me for help obviously without any compensation as a matter of gentlemanly discourse
I never ask for technical professional help for many of my friends or family if I do which isn't often
I pay in exchange for the favor immediately or simply ask for instructions
I also don't intrude on their personal time or expect anything inside a schedule
Call these my I call these my golden rules of personal professional exchange
But for some time now certain family members and close friends have mistakenly begun to treat me like the geek squad
Except without pain and certainly just as insistent and impolite as one of their customers
I don't mind helping and I don't understand their frustration and I and I understand their frustration
But it started to chat me a little bit people get snippy when I don't feel like helping and they rely on me during
outside hours quote-unquote which cuts into my personal time and weirdly enough blame me for their troubles as
If I'm the one getting their pet hair into their desktop overheating their altar book while gaming from the comfort of their comforter or
clicking pop-ups I shouldn't from an insurance browser from an insecure browser or
I'm the one who invited they're breaking breaking out their phone and breaking their gorilla glass do I seem better
Maybe anyways here's the question has anyone found a polite quick sensitive way to immediately shut down friends and family
When they ask you to be the geek squad I have really found a foolproof rejection anti rejection method
And I was wondering when we look at this
What our mumble room and what West thinks because a lot of us probably get called in as the technical support?
I imagine in this audience. I know I certainly do
In fact you know and I because I know my mom's not gonna listen to this
I just call her out so this last Sunday after the Linux action show okay
Oh, I should back up even further so about a week ago. My mom messages me
She says who do you use for hosting and I respond digital ocean right right and I'm like what is my mom care, right?
And then like the next day my mom replies to me. Oh, I see they support HTML, and I'm like oh my god
Yeah, mom. They support HTML after you deploy the Linux server you set up the Apache web server and then
You can like or you like to the one click Apple app deployment, but like might mean open mom's not
No, I'm not following exactly what needs to happen here, and so I'm like mom
I'm not sure so sure you understand, so then she messages me like a couple of days ago
Well, I would like to see you this weekend when can we can we get together?
And I tell her well
I have a little bit of time after I'm done with the Linux action show on Sunday
But you know really like I just got done with the show what I would like to do is relax
I would like your little bit of weekend. Yeah, like I got like a couple hours left on this Sunday
There's a couch over there man. That sounds good
No
So mom wants to come up and she wants to consult with me on her new business endeavors website
And it doesn't really there's not like a lot of discussion about like how busy I've been
Or the fact that I'm prepping to go to scale trying to get a new running business running my own business
It was my daughter's birthday
It was also an anniversary and then on top of all of that like I'm doing the show this weekend like there was no consideration
There's not really like I don't really have a good way to say sorry mom like I know this is important to you
But I also have a life like I don't really know how to have that have you ever been in a position like that
Yeah, definitely. I mean you know that's
There's a big there's just some users that
They don't understand like because you have the ability that ergo you are you are obligated to help
It's not yeah, it's not placing value on your time and sometimes you just have to tell people that
Marks, do you think it's weird to get into the discussion of monetary exchange for these things?
I'm not sure about monetary exchange when it comes to family, but maybe some sort of like-for-like thing because you know
Say you've got a fat. Yeah, so your sister's a nurse you might ask her to you know
Take a look at your foot when it's if you've got something wrong with it, and you wouldn't well
I mean obviously your your health system is different of course we wouldn't pay for for something like that over here, but
you know why if
If you've got if you've got a family member who has a profession and you'd you'd be
Expect them or not necessarily expect them ask them to help you out with something based on their knowledge, then yeah sure
Maybe you doing tech support for them for free isn't a big deal
Here is my current excuse and this is why I couldn't get out of the one with my mom because I got a go-to
that's pretty solid and
Because if they are willing to take me up on it
I'm willing to commit and my go-to is you know I switched away from Linux
After Windows XP, and I don't really know Windows anymore. I'm a Linux user and so if you want to switch to Linux
I can help you with that and if they do it if they buy it. I'm like all right. I'll commit to that
Yeah, I like I don't mind, but when it comes to server hosting stuff like what what do I say? Yeah? Well?
Sorry mom. I used to support ground there like it's it's not like you give her some tips on server administration
Yeah, no now you're administering her server. Yeah, yeah, yeah, poppy everybody in your family must know you work for a technology company
Yeah, poppy everybody in your family must know you work for a technology company you must get this
Yeah, so there's a couple of things like my brother is completely non-technical. He's a hairdresser. I can't cut my own hair
He cuts my hair. I saw his computers out
So is that there's a as Mark said if there's someone in your family who can do something so that that seems reasonable to me
however I I
Can't say no to my mom right and I couldn't say no to my mother-in-law in fact
Well, you've been on air my mother-in-law has has pinned me on Facebook and said hey
That new hard drive is arrived for me to do time machine backups on my Mac
But the box says it needs formatting for a Mac, and I'm my reply was yeah
Well, that's fine
Do you want me to help because she's my mother-in-law and she will cook me roast dinners. There is that?
That is an exchange. I'm willing to go down with and the flipside and also point out. She is your mom dude
No, I'm helping her. I'm helping her, but I'm telling you like I do I feel like I get roped into this stuff now
The mom one is a difficult one. Yes, but you must have this with the family too, right?
I mean they everybody must be aware of what you do. They must be where your technical guy
yeah, and
Ubuntu Marte was the solution to that problem so like yourself you get these questions about you know
Well some of the so on my wife's side of the family all of all of those got migrated to Ubuntu
versus
X so a long time ago and on my side of the family
They've been a little bit more resistance, and I played the same card. Oh well
You know I haven't used Windows for years. You know I stopped using Linux that Windows a long long time ago
I really don't know how it works and then
On my wife's side of the family they were still running 10-0 for
that was getting quite out of date and
We tried some of things and then Ubuntu Marte sort of got created to sort of support them so now
My solution to this problem is basically you spend 20 years using and learning Linux you then create a Linux distribution
You then form a hardware partnership with a local hardware company
When your family say they need help you say go to this website buy this computer
And it comes pre-installed and I never have to do anything
Unfortunately the length you really have to go to yeah, and it sounds it sounds sarcastic
But it's true because three of my family have now bought computers from Entroware and I've had them
Shipped pre-installed with Ubuntu Marte, and I haven't had to be involved go round there. It just works, so it's paid off
Yeah
And didn't you also buy and set up routers for all of your family I did yes, yeah, that's a good move
That is a good move. That is a flash them all with gargoyle. Yeah, I think that's I think that's something
I'm going to be doing to
the drawback to this approach is
Every month there are 10,000 other people who I don't know on the internet that are now all demanding
There is that problem, but you could think of them as extended family testers. They're testing
They're a new group of friends. I didn't have a year ago, so it's all good
Yeah, I had like I think I mentioned a few weeks ago. I had a successful switch over the holidays
I was out. I went somewhere. I didn't even have an internet connection when I did it and I had an Ubuntu Marte
This is bragging rights. No internet. No internet connection
And I had I had I already had a flash to a thumb drive because I actually used my laptop bag to pack my clothes
And if I took the laptop out and I put my clothes in there
But I I left my front thing that has all my thumb drives loaded cuz like I'm not gonna unload all that crap
No, and that's always like I got there the guy was having problems with Windows 8 one
He was thinking about getting a Mac and it's like try this and so
Da-da-da-da. Mm-hmm. It worked out pretty good. It was a good success
It was like hey, I had a I had a Linux switch story over the holidays. That's amazing. Yeah, so I agree there is
two solutions that I feel pretty good about when it's your mom or your mother-in-law or
Or if you give them a switch to Linux, those are the conditions in which you should support them
I think it but here's the thing remember we can also be ambassadors
We can be ambassadors to these people in times of need. So if you have the emotional capacity, I encourage you to the option
Yeah, I mean it's all on you got to check with yourself
You got an ABC always be checking before you commit
But I'm just saying if you can you could be an ambassador to the open-source world
It's an opportunity to switch or at least get them started on maybe moving from Outlook to Thunderbird or from Internet Explorer to Firefox
Right. There's so many different ways
You can sometimes solve problems like if they're having a malware issue on their Windows box get them going with Firefox
And that gets them started on the path and then down the road the switch is a lot easier
I also have to say the article do you touch on this?
But if you get some sort of beverage or delicious food item in exchange that sometimes can work out as well. Yeah
and a bit like you've just said the the other good one is I
think the non-technical people in the family are becoming more aware of the
security implications of running older Windows
operating systems
So what I've started doing is saying here's a USB stick that boots Linux
When you need to do your online banking or your online shopping
use this
Because it's secure and it will forget everything that you've just done when you unplug
Ah, so it's like Linux on training wheels because you're just doing it for a little bit
You're just using it for some web browsing stuff and it's for your important stuff to be secure
Yeah, yeah, and and that sort of makes them think oh, you know, this is just like any other computer, right?
This isn't complicated. This isn't daunting and it's just a little sort of you know taster
That's actually really smart because then later on when they want to move on you'd be like, you know
That operating system you've been used for all your really important stuff. Why don't you choose that all the time, right?
And it's like oh, well, yeah, I trust that. Yeah, I like it. Oh
That is some that is some like level two like psychological switcher stuff right there. I like it
Yeah
Pocket Casey in the chat room asked if I when I have time what I love to he'd love to see a little coverage of the
Tink talk that would be really that would be very interesting. So pocket Casey if you could tweet me the day of that talk
You could be the ambassador of that talk if you want and remind me while I'm there
I'll try to do it, but tell ask me now. There's no way I can remember but I would like to see that one
Yeah, I would as well because I didn't even hear about tink until West came along start talking
Linux action show dot reddit dot com. That's the subreddit you go to to submit content to this show or feedback next week
Because of scale no will be sitting in for me. So it'll be West and Noah in the mumble room
yeah, yeah, that should be a good time and I
He'll you guys maybe might want to get the ball rolling earlier in slack than we normally do. We're pretty quick now
We've got a down. That's true. We got it down. But you know, no that guy's new that guy
He doesn't you know, so you got to watch out for him. So go check it out
Thank you very much for being here everybody
We do the Linux unplugged show live on Tuesdays over at jblive.tv at 2 p.m. Is that right or 1 p.m. Yeah
Okay. Hmm seems really the day with you seems pretty wet, huh? You know what if I got confused I would just
If I got confused, I would just go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar
That's what I would do that's her that would converge my local time zone
You could show you could show up live hang out in our virtual log hang on our chatter
But if you can't just download it, we've got RSS feeds
We appreciate it Linux action show dot reddit dot com Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact to send us feedback
Thanks so much for tuning in and we'll see you right back here next week. Well, they will
Oh
Well, you see that where's West there hey there worse you see that
Marcus is trying out MB
Yeah, so tell us. So what do you think Mario? So you go with I got you. What do you think marks?
What do you think of the MB? Yeah, it's really good because I've got a
Cody box in my living room
and I've been
having
Reasonable success with with managing my library on it
But I I'd like having all my music on my server and streaming that so I've had them and patchy running on there for a while
Which is fairly decent, but it only does music and I've got my videos on the server, too
So it's nice to just have one solution. So I thought I'd stick MB on there and give it a go
and I found
It does the video library really well and since that's coding nicely
It doesn't sync the video library to Cody so nicely for some reason but because it's got the remote control feature
you can just
You just go into the web interface or the app on MB and you say send it to Cody
It's brilliant using the the MB plug-in at all for Cody
Yeah, so that's what I think you you put the MB plug-in in and that's what sinks your mute your video library
I think and it also means that then your other MB apps will recognize it as somewhere that you can send media
It's worked very well my but you're saying the music part does not work as well
Well, it works, but only if you use another app to like select the playlist or the music
So it doesn't sync the music library to Cody's music library for some reason. Where's where's either I am
Can you hear me? Where's is Chris recording yet? Yes
Yeah, yeah. Okay. Why why what's wrong? I've got a question for you Chris. Yeah, what's that?
15 arrived yet
No, that is you know what you know what I don't I don't even know what to say because now I'm going on this trip
And I'm I'm I am literally in the position of like I'm like which one of the which one of the machines can I?
Sacrifice in the studio and not disrupt the shows that will be going next week because the thing is doing a job
What if I need to do production from the road like what if I need to do some production from the road?
Can I do it all my xps 13? I don't think so. I need a larger screen machine
just oh oh
Oh
Yeah, I would I would I would do anything to have that rig monitor built into the rover
You know what? I would like at this point anything is
I would just like you know what to be honest with you at this point
I would just like a refund I think and I just need to get something
You should contact them and ask them if they come to scale and maybe they could bring your laptop along yeah
I should I wonder if they will be a scale
Wonder hmm. You should drive the rover over to their office, and then just camp outside until he gives you empty empty your black tank in there
Wow I
Empty my tank in your direction sir
Yikes yikes, so you know the thing is is
I've driven a gas vehicle my entire life, and this thing runs on top of basically a diesel chassis, right?
It's a it is a diesel it is more
It's more of a diesel truck than it is anything else so it's got like air brakes and air suspension
and it has like glow plugs and
Like all the add a DF and a DF tank to help reduce the diesel emissions
And so it's got like all this stuff that I have to learn how to operate
Scaling up here plus. It's got plus. It's got a built-in generator with an auto start system
So I can set conditions for when the generator automatically kicks in
But like I gotta learn how to manage all of these things in like well tomorrow morning basically
And I don't have a great memory, so I think what it really means is as Chris because you should record it
I'm gonna be good. Yes exactly. That's why I probably will record, and I'm gonna be googling while on the road
Oh the good news is a diesel is quite a bit cheaper than gasoline fuel right now, so
That's that's the good news. Yeah, yeah, that's great, and it's more more efficient as well
Yeah, and they might look at you a little funny if you show up with a GoPro on a bicycle helmet though
Yeah, well it is a lot to learn before the trip
But I had to learn everything about the rover before the last trip, and I managed to pull that off
So I got I am I'm up for the challenge
I think but it is a lot it is a lot to when I think about it
It is a lot to go through and then maybe none of it happens
And then maybe I just end up taking the truck and the and the rover and then they it's it's it's whatever
It's no big deal
Yeah, I found it interesting listening to you talking about the rover and
then
Sort of ending up living in the rover and then enjoying that space yeah, and I can identify with this because
My wife's parents have got a barge, and I absolutely love living on the barge
This is a narrowboat that goes up and down the canals in the UK so very thin and long
so not much space, but I kind of like the
Efficiency of living that you have to adopt when you're living in and you know small space like that
So what is it about living in the RV that that you find?
Yeah, it's pretty it's definitely an aspect of that so like there's no reason for me to go to a furniture store because I'm not
Gonna be able to buy anything in that furnished furniture store and bring it home and that it's sort of freeing like when we have
a really big mess to clean up it takes 10 15 minutes and the entire space is
Immaculate and it's so nice
So there is a lot less need of things and there's a lot less
like maintenance and maintaining that a big place comes with you know a big place gets cluttered up
There's stuff all over all of the wherever there's counter space or or wherever
There's a flat surface stuff ends up getting stacked on top of it
and then they have they have yards that have to be maintained, and I don't have time or energy for that and
I also hate my neighbors like I constantly I look for things like there's a new guy
There's a new guy who he's a renter that lives over in the house across over there
Hey, and he's out there, and he's smoking all the time when I'm outside
So you know I'm here
I am loading unloading stuff from the back of my truck
You know grunting and huffing and puffing and this guy's just sitting out there for like 20 minutes watching me like a 20 minute smoke
Break just sitting there staring at me the whole time and then one
And then like two weeks into it. I get out of my truck, and I lock it and I'm walking and he says hey
Your lights are on
Now I have been doing this for two weeks since this guy's moved in and he's the lights have always
Automatically turned themselves off they have since the first time he's seen me show up for two weeks in a row
The lights automatically turned themselves off and then two weeks into he's like hey your lights
And like and I'm like I just stopped there. I'm like well. Yeah, they turn
And it's not even like I'm like some famous in 2012
It's not some fancy vehicle right the lights just turned themselves off so anyways I
I developed Hicks about like and then I could tell you about these guys, so we tell you about these guys right
These guys right here. They're coming and going at the same time
I am all the time now obviously how long ago, and I tell you about this no, it's true
It's I've observed the same. I had I've complained about it
I've even sent you pictures of them coming and going when I'm coming and going why are they always coming to go when I'm coming?
And going I come and go weird times. I'm a podcaster and yet they're coming and going at weird times. It's suspicious
Maybe they have it's almost like you listen to the live stream, and then they're coming and going when I'm coming and going
Great way to spy on your neighbor. Oh well. He just has this life
Yeah, so and then and then and then this is another one where I think maybe I am I have some sort of condition
I'm not very good at
So that there's the neighbor thing so I like to be able to I like the ability to pick up and move so there might
Be some sort of condition there where I just start to develop ticks about the people you know what it is is
I observe a lot of patterns in people and then when they when they have bad patterns
I can't help but notice them and then they drive me crazy because then like I have to build the narrative around why they have
Such an awful pattern in their life
Anyways, so it's nice to be able to pick up and move so that's one you know plus for the for the mobile lifestyle
You know the other thing is is I really I really put a lot of my time and energy into the network like
So much so that I'm negligent to other aspects of my life not and it doesn't really matter how important it is
It's like could be it could be a health issue
It could be taking care of personal insurance doesn't really matter what it is
I'm just not very good at addressing it and along with that
Comes things like all of the crap you have to manage and pay and when I mean manage
I mean even having to like go into bill pay and set up payments and
and and send checks to your power company and your water company and your cable company and and the garbage company and all this all
the all of the different organizations or or
Utilities that you have to pay when you own a house. They just drive me crazy
I don't have time to manage that I don't want to bother with any of it and so one of the nice things about where
I'm staying at is it's
All just part of the deal
I pay a flat
$35 and it's just all part of the deal I can use as much power as I want I use as much water as I
Want the garbage is built in all of its one
But it's just one $35 charge that automatically goes on my card and that and I don't have to I don't have to mail anybody
A check nothing. It's just very simple for me to manage and it lets me focus on other things
So the smaller space lets me not have to focus on
Maintaining my house and making it look nice and not having to worry about the yard and the smaller space keeps it efficient
I don't need to buy a lot like
If I do get this new rig, you know along with that new rig is well
That's also my couch and my dining room table and my oven and my microwave and my refrigerator
And so and my king-size bed now all of it will just be part of like I otherwise
I would have to go out and buy all of those things individually like I don't have any of those things anymore
So I would have to go buy a couch
I would have to go buy a dining room table set with chairs, and I would have to go buy
Recliner chairs, and I would have to go buy the televisions. I don't have any televisions right
I don't to go buy the televisions and the bedding and all of that stuff it when you when you get a nice
Rig it just all is nice, and it all just comes with it, and so it not only does it check all those other boxes
But it also is mobile which is great for me to go do these events and do productions on the road and it has all
It checks all the boxes as far as things you'd have to buy when you get a house that just come with it
Don't write it. Yeah, I
Like it a lot and on top of all of that
It's pretty damn green because at max it can only pull 50 amps which you're never gonna pull that much and
And and the average US house is 200 amps so by it uses less power
It has we uses way less water in fact. We're actually very acutely aware of exactly how much water
We use every single week. I know in gallons
When's the last time you knew in gallons exactly how much water use every single week absolutely never right you need to live in
the UK yeah
So you know I mean it's it's very like we're and because also it's a smaller space
We're buying less food. We have less waste we have less things
We're getting that we're not using so it feels like it's also as a side effect a greener way to live
Which also gives you a lot more?
You know when you're not you're not having to go shopping for furniture
And you're not having to spend so much time tidying and and all that kind of stuff
It gives you a lot more time to round to us online. I think