Okay, Mr. Colonel Linux. This is a quiz for you, sir. Can you place this tune?
Okay, that's all you get so far. Then I'll give you more of a hint.
It's a clip from a sound board in the Jupiter Broadcasting Studio.
Okay, all right. Well, technically correct, but not the actual accurate answer. Don't look at my screen. I will continue on.
Now, Wes, you recognize what this is, right?
I do.
Yeah, I thought so.
Must be Star Trek, then.
Uh-uh. Nope, nope.
Come on, nobody in the chat room knows what this is? Really?
Nope.
Really? Hmm. All right, I'm going to give you one more hint, one more hint, one more hint.
All right, Wes. What is it, Wes? What is it? What is it? Let us know, Wes. Give us the big reveal. What are we listening to?
Are you ready? Are you ready?
I don't know.
It is, ladies and gentlemen, the original Star Fox intro.
Ah.
Oh, North Ranger got it.
Yeah, I got it.
Yeah, yeah.
Star Fox. Okay, so I love Star Fox.
I love Star Fox, too.
I actually saw a Star Fox thing at Linux Fest Northwest, surprisingly enough, but anyways, that's not what we're here to talk about.
I love this. You know, this is a different kind of open source. This is an intellectual kind of open source.
A fan-made Star Fox cartoon recalls the best of 70s sci-fi animation, and you should watch it really before it gets taken down.
It is a Star Fox cartoon, a fox in space, and if you liked the old Star Fox show, they have a big disclaimer that we're not doing this for profit.
We swear we're not doing this for profit. We swear.
You guys should just turn around and leave because you do not want to piss off my uncle.
Oh, just who I needed to see. Star Wolf.
Star Wolf.
This gives me happening.
All your friends are out of the game, Wolf. Don't make me shoot you down.
This is so great.
It really is great.
If you ever watched or played Star Wars, I should say, or Star Fox, this is for you.
This is really cool. I have a link in the show notes, and one of those things that's probably going to get pulled down really soon.
Right away.
Yeah, so if you want to enjoy it, you got to kind of be a fast mover.
Just YouTube DL that right now.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 142 for April 26, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's had such mush.
It's been swapping drives while the computers are still powered. That's legit.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Wes, welcome to the post-Linux Fest Northwest hangover.
Ooh, it's a doozy.
Oh, man. I don't know how, but somehow we're going to have a great show for you today.
Somehow. We will persevere. We're going to talk about it.
Yeah, don't leave. Stay here.
Stay here. Don't worry.
It's worth it.
Yeah, we got some interesting Firefox updates coming towards you.
Some good reports of the new Ubuntu tablet.
Of course, the clips you never got to see in Linux Action Show from Linux Fest Northwest.
The good stuff.
As well as a few stories, a few build projects gone awry. Perhaps some beer will be spilt.
And, as always, we'll update you on some of our favorite open source projects.
A lot of really fun things to cover, so you know what we've got to do, Wes.
We've got to focus. We've got to harness the power of the internet and bring in our virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello, everyone.
Hey, guys.
Hello, guys.
So, Wes and I might be a little punchy. My mouth may not work very well today.
None of those things should be held against us.
We need your help.
Yeah, because we're going to be leaning on you guys because I've got to tell you,
things have gotten so bad around the JV1 studios because of total exhaustion from Linux Fest Northwest
that just mere moments ago, we decided we've had too many things frustrate us.
And both Noah and I were just totally done with Ubuntu 16.04.
And I have it on this Apollo that I've been keeping. I was going to keep it in Linux Action Show.
I said I'm going to stick with this.
That was a pretty big step for you.
Yeah. And we're going to give you our full take towards the end of the show.
So those of you who don't really care, don't worry. We won't bore with you at the top here.
But to give you an indication of how mush our heads are, but yet we're still trying to push through,
I'm about to play something for you that is not the first time this happened this weekend.
Not the second time this happened this weekend.
But perhaps the third time this weekend that we had to rebuild a machine, swap drives out,
and load a new OS, and all three times.
This is agonizing.
We had to do it more than three times.
But all the three times I'm thinking of, we were in such a rush,
we actually forgot to turn the computers off first.
So I'm going to play a little bit of this clip that Mr. Kernel Linux grabbed this morning.
You think you can log in?
No.
We'll see.
So right here you are seeing this is my Apollo after I've closed the lid like 20 minutes ago,
walked out, came back into the studio, and didn't realize that I hadn't turned it off.
This is a common problem we had.
So it's just sitting there suspended.
I flipped the laptop over, started taking the screws out of the bottom, pulled the plate off,
pulled out both hard drives, swapped out the Ubuntu drives with two blank drives, powered it back on,
and it actually woke up, Wes.
And here is the login manager working.
It's kind of impressive.
Oh, you just got the wrong password.
Maybe you should drop down to a terminal.
There we go.
Now let's see if we can log in.
Oh, we're starting to get errors.
We're starting to get I.O. errors.
Uh-oh.
Extended four error.
I know there's coming in across the board, sir.
I block zero, can't find I block zero.
I know there, sir.
So much for being able to run completely out of RAM.
Unable to read.
I block zero.
Why are you running your OS on a RAM disk, Chris?
Oh, man.
Massive turbulence.
Initiating emergency reboot sequence.
Uh-oh.
Connection refused.
Unable to activate service.
Oh, no.
We're going down.
So that was me this morning.
Now I just want to give you a taste of what my nights are like.
See, I usually go to bed a little bit later than I like to.
Naturally.
Because they're hard days.
And every single day since NOAA got in town, every single day there has been major decisions
to make that have serious long-term ramifications about production and the network, and it's
just been like...
There are no off days.
It is exhausting.
But it's been even worse for NOAA and, say, Rekai, because they're the ones staying up
to all hours of the night actually implementing some of these changes.
And so this was about a 2 a.m. call that I got.
And I should point out, too, that this was stuff that we did not intend to be on the
air, per se.
Oh, yeah.
Right.
But we're going to let it on the air anyway.
This is the unplugged show.
Yeah.
There will be some F-bombs about a minute into this.
Don't worry.
They're not too bad.
But hold on.
It's a late-night call that I got that NOAA sent me that I thought I'd share with you
guys because, yeah, this was never supposed to be aired, but this gives you a little idea
of the state of mind that everybody was in after working until about 4 a.m., 5 a.m. for
about six, seven days straight.
Oh, wait.
Not this one.
That's the last one.
Hold on a second.
Hold on.
And wait for it.
I don't even see it in here.
Oh, I don't even see it in here.
Maybe I'm totally...
My head is too tired.
But I bet I'll come up to it.
I bet I'll find it in a little bit.
Here we go.
I just found it.
Oh, wait a minute.
That's what I did.
See, I am tired.
I mislabeled the eclipse.
Oh, well.
Woe is me.
I think I had...
You know what, Mr. NOAA?
I think I'm getting a little bit of feedback.
I think I'm hearing a little bit of goodness come through on your speakers there or something.
So, yeah.
There we go.
Hey, I found it.
Here.
I'm going to play it for you.
Are you ready?
Okay.
This is...
Now, just be warned.
But, yeah.
1.57 a.m. precise is when this came into me here.
And now I'm going to play it for you.
Yeah.
Hop on the other side.
Hi Topher.
Chris Topher.
Hi.
So, it's really late.
Like, super.
That's beard.
Hi, beard.
I like how laying on your shoulder just makes me go forget.
So we're all exceedingly tired.
Crazy tired.
I had to go get some water because I drank the Coke.
That rhymes with tired.
But we fixed.
We fixed your fucking RDMP stream.
So now...
Kinda.
What do you mean, kind of?
I thought you said it was...
YouTube doesn't completely work.
Because I'll start as a bitch.
Right.
You have to restart it manually.
But you're a smart guy.
So you can do that.
But we'll fix it so you don't have to do that.
Beard will fix it.
I will not fix it.
Because I don't...
I'll fix it by not using Ubuntu.
Beard, that does not seem smart.
So anyway...
And I transcoded all your files.
Yeah.
He did good.
That boy...
In other words, he's useless.
No.
Useless out of the...
No, but...
So listen to me now.
SatCom 1 is a go.
And it is working.
SatCom 2 is kind of half a go.
It's half a go.
Your personal rig?
Fucked.
Totally.
Oh yeah.
So this...
This thing.
You get to play with that.
When you...
Fucked out of 10.
I'm actually fucked out of like 150.
We try.
I don't know.
It's that hardware works, but I can't install your stupid AnderGhost.
So...
Turns out...
MVME drives.
MVME drives out of 10.
They fucking suck.
If we put it on the SSD, it'll work just fine.
But I don't know what the fuck is going on.
Might have to buy a plane ticket or something.
Maybe that's what we'll do.
Okay.
So I just wanted to tell you how hard we worked and how fucking tired we are.
Which I'm here to know at 2 o'clock.
Yes, but I...
How much sleep did you get last night?
Not much.
And I got like two out of three hours.
How...
You're...
You're in a fucking good sleep schedule.
Yeah.
But...
He's very cold, though.
I've hit my limit of how late I can stay up.
So I'm going to bed.
And just to let you know, we stayed up.
And fixed your shirt.
Hopefully it works.
Turn the heat off so you don't keep them up all night.
Oh yeah.
Turn the heat up or off.
We're going to freeze.
And then, after he gets this working, he decides to kiss the phone.
Good night.
Oh, that's adorable.
Oh, it didn't shut off.
That was really awkward.
Okay, you try it.
Okay.
Nighty night.
Here, hold on.
All right, Brown Bear.
How much had you drank before you went to bed?
Zero.
I have had no drugs.
I have had no alcohol.
It is literally just five consecutive nights, six consecutive nights of no, like, one to
two hours of sleep.
And you just, you hit a limit.
And then, all of a sudden, like, you get so tired.
And it's just, like, simple things.
Like, somebody would say something to me, and I would just completely forget about it,
like, 30 seconds later.
I had no recollection of it.
I just switched the whole hard drive and the computer, and I have zero recollection of
doing it.
It's amazing that everything still works.
Yeah, really.
Yeah, literally, he swapped out a hard drive and a machine, totally forgot about it.
So you kind of teased it there real quick.
Why don't you tell the people what the heck SatCom 1 and SatCom 2 is, how the heck they
run Linux, and why it's so damn awesome now?
So basically, we are trying to expedite the flow of streams and also create a way that
not one system is so heavily reliant with problematic internet.
And so basically, we are sending a single stream up to DigitalOcean to JBSatCom 1.
And SatCom 1 then distributes those streams to all of the various places like Ustream
and ScaleEngine and whatnot.
And then, the other thing we've done is we, SatCom 1 also sends a stream to SatCom 2.
And SatCom 2 then connects in with YouTube.
So we have a YouTube live page now.
And you will have the ability, I'm doing it right now, but you'll eventually have the
ability to, from the chat room, start and stop SatCom 2 to bring that live stream up
and down.
Yeah, using JBot, which is very cool.
So one of the things about this trip is, and I think we should probably talk about this
almost in its own dedicated thing, but these are all Linux rigs being powered by Linux
machines running OBS here in the studio.
We're now able to, this is probably doesn't seem like a big deal to most people, but it's
a big personal thing for me because it was always a polished thing.
We're now able to switch from reruns on the live stream to live shows without any interruption
in the stream.
That is really nice.
We can take equipment offline behind the scenes and all that kind of stuff.
And we'll also soon be able to have stream recordings and whatnot.
It's really like a true 24-7 live stream, which would be a big goodness.
Yeah.
So what we did to work around some Comcast issues, and really, if you think about it,
this is so perfect, is we set up a droplet on DigitalOcean, which is, of course, a sponsor
here on Linux Unplugged.
Two droplets.
Oh.
One that's like a big rig.
Like if you go over to digitalocean.com and use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED, you'll get
a $10 credit and you can try out some of these rigs for free.
They even have hourly pricing, so you get like the $5 you can try it out.
I love that hourly pricing.
Yeah.
Yeah, I do.
I decided, I went for one of my biggest droplets yet.
Ooh, how big?
Yeah, I got a $40 a month droplet.
I get four gigabytes of RAM, a two-core processor, 60-gigabyte SSD, and four terabytes of transfer.
Nice.
Now, this thing's going out to Ustream.tv, Scale Engine, YouTube Live, right?
You got all these, and the audio stream, and we want to add more.
So I wanted something with a lot of processor power.
Ooh.
What was really cool, though, is we started at the $5 droplet as we just tested the theory.
Right.
And then we just incremented it up as we needed it.
It is so nice.
And we're going to take advantage, so Noah mentioned that we'd be starting and stopping
the live stream by using a bot in our IRC chat room.
It's a really sweet API they have to do this.
So we'd be using an IRC bot.
We turn droplets on and off.
Oh, that's slick.
Right?
DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code D01PLUG.
They start at $5 a month.
You get 512 megabytes of RAM, one blazing fast CPU, 20 gigabytes of SSD, and a terabyte
of transfer, because they all SSDs, y'all, and they have super fast rigs, all the different
Linux size you'd want, Core OS, CentOS, Debian, Fedora, Ubuntu, of course.
They also have free BSD.
They have data centers in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, London, Toronto, and
Germany.
Just pick whatever makes the most sense.
They have a brilliant interface, really good stuff, really great dashboard.
It's made like, for example, so Noah could just manage these as droplets with no effort.
As I'm setting all these things up, I can just check his SSH keys, and they get added
as the droplet gets created, and he has login.
He's good to go.
So easy.
I love DigitalOcean.
You will love it, too.
Use the promo code DEOUNPLUGGED, one word lowercase, and support this show, and get
yourself a $10 credit, and go try them out.
They have the great interface.
They have great guides and tutorials, super, super, super good documentation, and now they're
just running even more of our infrastructure.
When we want a Linux server on demand, this is where we go.
With great bandwidth, great connectivity, DigitalOcean.com, use the promo code DEOUNPLUGGED.
Before we get into the Firefox news, I should mention that Wes did bring us some bruskies,
as has been tradition for quite a while now, and one that I love.
I'm not going to complain.
And did you know that this is Alasian's flagship beer?
Alasian.
This is Alasian, or whatever you call them.
Aslan?
I don't know.
Aslan, I believe.
Not Aslan, huh?
This is their flagship beers, one of them, the Batch 15 IPA.
So let's go ahead and... A medium body, citrusy, and unfiltered.
What are you thinking?
Have you been drinking this?
Another Northwest brew.
This is actually, speaking of Linux Fest Northwest from Bellingham, this beer is from
Bellingham.
It sure is.
Brewed in Bellingham, Washington.
With 7% ABV.
That's not bad.
Yeah.
It's pretty good.
Are you enjoying it?
Yeah.
It's hoppy, but it's not too hoppy.
As it finishes there, you want more, but it's not...
That's exactly how I would put it.
It's not cloying in your mouth at all.
You nailed that.
Just as it was finishing, I was like... As I was swallowing it, I'm like, this is... As
I'm swallowing it, and you're saying, it's not that hoppy, I'm like, dude, what?
This is super hoppy.
And this, just as it finished, I'm like, I could have more, and you're like, but then
you could have more.
You nailed it, that's exactly what it tastes like.
And you know, it's right from our own backyard.
Kind of appropriate.
So, that's what we will be enjoying during the show today.
All right, let's talk about Firefox 46, finally released, and it's really, truly, genuinely,
actually, honest to goodness here.
Ladies and gentlemen, I present Firefox with, you guessed it, GTK 3 integration.
No way.
Yeah, it's true.
And I know Mr. Colonel Linux is a Firefox fan.
I'm going to get to him in a moment, but I wanted to open up to the mumble room first.
Anybody out there actually cray-cray enough to try out Firefox 46 and play with the GTK
3 integration on the Linux desktop builds?
Yes, I plan on doing it.
Okay.
I've been using GTK 3 Firefox on Arch for like three releases now.
Yeah, right.
It's been doable.
And anything stand out to you?
I did run into one bug with the dark theme where you get white text on white background
sometimes, which is kind of annoying.
But otherwise, it's actually been very, very smooth.
Okay.
That bug exists forever.
Yeah.
We also have improved H.264 and AAC media support, better web RTC performance support,
which-
Those seem like good wins.
Those do seem like really good wins.
I think no one's going to be all about that using like Firefox Hello and whatnot.
Now here is the, and great for the Firefox team, no snap yet.
Right.
I thought that was interesting.
They even bothered pointing that out.
But you caught that too, huh?
There was a snap.
I would install it right now.
Yeah, I would too, actually.
I wonder if that's going to start happening.
I hope so.
You can actually just go ahead and use it anyway, because you don't have to install
it.
You can download the tarball.
Oh, yeah, sure.
Yeah, totally.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Let's talk about Firefox and Thunderbird.
Mark Sermon, he wrote up a post at his site about Firefox and Thunderbird, a fork in the
road.
Firefox and Thunderbird have reached a fork in the road, he writes.
It's now time, it's now the right time for them to part ways on both a technical and
organizational level.
So Thunderbird and Firefox, time to part ways, he says.
A little bit of background, much of Mozilla, including the leadership team, believes that
focusing on the web through Firefox offers a vastly better choice, or I'm sorry, chance
of moving the internet industry to a more open place than investing in further Thunderbird
development or in continuing to attend to both products.
Many of us remain committed to Thunderbird users and want to see Thunderbird remain a
healthy community and product.
But both Firefox and Thunderbird face different challenges, have different goals and different
measures of success.
Our actions regarding Thunderbird should be viewed in this light.
Success for Firefox means continued relevance in the mass consumer market as a way for people
to access, share, and feel safe across many devices.
With hundreds of millions of users on both desktop and mobile, we have the raw material
for this success.
If we want Firefox to continue and have an impact on how developers and consumers interact
with the internet, we need to move to much more quickly and we need to innovate on mobile
and in the cloud.
Mozilla is putting the majority of its human and financial resources into Firefox product
innovation.
Now here comes the swinging blow, Noah, for Thunderbird.
In contrast, success for Thunderbird means remaining a reliable and stable open source
desktop email client.
While many people still value the security and independence that come with desktop mail,
the overall number of such people in the world is shrinking.
Given these different paths, it should be no surprise that tensions have arisen as we
have tried to maintain Firefox and Thunderbird on top of a common underlying code base and
a common release engineering team.
Here's what they're going to do, on the organizational front, they've hired an open source leader
like Simon Phelps.
He's going to look at different long term options for a home for Thunderbird, including
perhaps the Document Foundation, perhaps Gnome, or the Mozilla Foundation and the Software
Freedom Conservancy are also on the list.
With the right technical and organizational path set forward, both Firefox and Thunderbird
will have a better chance of success and dramatic reading.
In other words, while Mozilla, over the last years, has had time to try everything from
phones to sticks and everything in between, even a browser, what we don't have time for
is an email client.
An open web is important, but an open email ecosystem, have you guys heard of Gmail?
What do you think, Noah?
I think that Thunderbird is single-handedly the most popular client I see used on Linux
desktops and it's kind of a huge disappointment that the Mozilla Corporation is either unaware
or chooses to willfully ignore that user base and it seems like, I've tried Kmail, I've
tried a lot of different ones, but like you, I have a large inbox and I don't like going
to the web for my mail.
I like having a mail client running, especially on my workstation at home, so that I'm quickly
alerted to incoming emails and stuff like that and if they pass it off to somebody else
or if they decide to abandon the project completely, I really hope that whoever picks it up steps
it up a little bit.
It doesn't need to be updated a whole lot, it just needs to work and continue to function
the way it is.
It's good enough.
You know, ironically, that's their main complaint, is they don't want – see, this is what actually
strikes me, is they talk about success for Firefox means continued relevance in a mass
consumer market, chasing mobile, focusing on the cloud and they say, in contrast, Thunderbird
means remaining a reliable and stable open source desktop email client.
Almost like saying, in opposite of our goals of Firefox, Thunderbird needs to be stable.
What?
What kind of logic is that?
In contrast, they are literally saying, in opposite, that's another – in contrast,
Thunderbird, for it to be successful, needs to be stable and an open source desktop client.
They're saying, what does that mean for the goals of Firefox?
Go cray-cray?
Go crazy with mobile?
Go crazy with the cloud and stability goes out the window?
It seems like it is absolutely a core focus of Firefox to have stability and that in no
way, in no way detracts from Thunderbird.
I don't make – this logic makes no sense to me.
Yeah, it's pretty iffy.
Now, should they be doing it if they don't want to do it?
Of course not.
Right.
I don't know.
Anybody in the mumbling room have an idea of where maybe it should go?
The conservancy has already said that they would take in the hosting and they would also
be open to like a Thunderbird Foundation split.
The other ones haven't really said anything like that.
In fact, I think – I think maybe Simon's report might actually be out as we record
this.
Yeah, it's been out for about an hour now.
Yeah, okay.
The interesting thing is that the change between Mozilla and Thunderbird has already happened
and it happened in like 2012.
So this change is actually a good thing because Mozilla has already washed their hands of
Thunderbird.
They are just kind of a little bit still putting their feet in the water but Thunderbird doesn't
want to be associated to Mozilla anyway because it limits them in what they can do for their
base for like the runtime engine and everything.
So they can actually improve Thunderbird overall.
So this is actually a good thing even though it sounds weird.
No, I actually am in complete agreement with you.
I guess I wish that the priorities lined up differently.
Mini MC, what do you think?
Yeah, I think it's the release often philosophy for Firefox.
If you have new technologies, implement them and do changes afterwards.
Unless with Thunderbird, you need still a stable client.
All right.
So here is the – the register has the report that Simon put out a bit ago.
He says software conservancy and document foundation seen as ideal new homes, they need
technical hosting, they need finance and staffing and government dispute management leadership
and trademark management.
Now the software conservancy has already agreed to take over Thunderbird if asked, FIPS says,
which is pretty great.
Wow.
Yeah, remember that's also where Inkscape lives, Git and QMU.
On the other hand, the document foundation over in Germany is close to the largest national
community of Thunderbird users.
So I guess there's another – we'll see where this – we'll follow this.
I guess Gnome Foundation wasn't super probably up on the top of this because they already
kind of tapped out these days but –
Yeah, they already – they said that they wouldn't be able to handle such a change
at this moment.
Yeah.
Well, it's good to see Google stepping up.
It's an important project.
I like the fact that Mozilla is opening to let them use the trademark even though they're
probably going to keep the trademark but they're going to let the Thunderbird project keep
it.
Yeah, good point.
Good point.
Mr. WW, do you have any final thoughts on the Thunderbird situation?
I think Thunderbird is an insanely reliable client.
It's been rock solid for me.
I have literally thousands of emails in it and it doesn't take over 300 megs of RAM.
On one end, this is going to put a lot more pressure on Firefox.
People are going to be looking closer at them and saying, OK, you're done with Thunderbird.
You moved on.
What are you going to do for us now?
What are you going to do to compete with Chrome, with Microsoft Edge, with Devalti?
Are you going to be able to fix issues that you've had?
People I'm sure are going to be looking at them more closely now.
Yes, I think I will be.
Yeah, definitely.
Yeah.
All right.
One last update before we get into some of the meatier topics.
Last week, I think it was, we mentioned that one of the first reviews of the Ubuntu BQ
tablet was pretty sour on it and not very positive.
Now Jack Wallen has his review out at TechRepublic.com and he's got a little bit of a different take
on it.
I think I like this one better because this feels more like a more longer term, bigger
picture Linux user who's trying this.
Someone who's open to it as well.
Yeah.
Someone who might be coming at it more from my perspective of I'm okay with rough edges
if I can accomplish X and then just stick with it as it develops.
Here's what he said that grabbed my attention.
Now he's also got screenshots of what LibreOffice looks like on the thing and whatnot, but he
says this, the only real issue with running full-blown version of LibreOffice on the Ubuntu
tablet is the toolbars and menus, et cetera, are really on the small side because the resolution
is super high, so you better have good vision.
But he said, for example, he ran the GIMP, it's ready to go on the Ubuntu tablet, and
here's what I really loved.
The second the Ubuntu tablet connects to the wireless mouse, it switches over to desktop
mode.
That's when the real magic happens.
All of a sudden, I'm working on a tablet that is in full multitasking mode.
Windows act like Windows in the traditional sense.
They can be resized, minimized, everything you've grown up to with on the desktop.
Oh, that does sound really nice.
Yeah, it does.
He says, the only issue with the Ubuntu tablet is when you switch to desktop mode, you do
lose some horsepower.
There's some significant lag in the cursor movement, and apps don't seem to open nearly
as quickly.
That might be one of those things you've got to wait until the next tablet, but it could
be.
He ends in a conclusion.
I don't want to spoil it for you guys, so he has a great write-up, but I haven't leaked
it in the show notes, too, but he says, canonical, I am seriously impressed.
He says, in desktop mode, I can actually get my work done in a similar efficient manner
as I would if I were standing right at my desk.
That is powerful.
That's sounding a lot better than the last review we read.
Do you think so, too, Mr. Kernalynx?
I do.
I've actually, for a number of years, been looking for a solution, a small portable solution
that I can take with me everywhere.
And when you say a number of years, you mean like 10.
Yeah, yeah.
It's basically kind of been what I've always wanted, but it seems like there's no place,
it seems like either my laptop is inconvenient to take places or bad things happen to it
sometimes.
Which we'll get into.
But if I could have a tablet, but the problem with the tablet is, every time I try to use
a tablet operating system, I get stuck and bogged down in, it's good at tablet-y things,
but I can't actually do desktop things, so the ability to switch back and forth is absolutely
essential.
Joe, you had a chance to play with it on Sunday.
Yes, thanks to Wimpy at the Egham Raspberry Jam.
And the thing is, okay, if you look at it from our point of view, it's a great tablet
in that you can get Exmere running, you can get LibreOffice, but then if you actually
step back out of our little bubble, our kind of free software bubble, and think of it as
a consumer product, the thing is absolutely terrible.
I mean, you know that gesture where you swipe in from the right and you get all of the recent
applications?
Uh-huh.
That was all juddery and whatnot.
And just the whole experience was not slick at all.
Compared to my Nexus 9 running stock Android, it's just a joke, really, as a consumer product.
And I don't know, maybe we're here to discuss the benefits of it.
You can run proper terminal applications on it.
You can do everything you can with a Linux box, basically.
But for the general public, and that's how this was sold to me, at least.
If you look at the websites where you can buy this thing, it looks like a consumer product.
I'll grant you that, yeah.
And the fact is, it is not a consumer product.
It's not ready for market yet.
Mr. Pobie, I'm sure you must have some response to this.
Hello.
Sorry if my audio is terrible.
I'm in a hotel room in Prague.
Yeah, thank you for joining us, even in the hotel room.
That's awesome.
So interestingly, I got to play with a BQ M10 for the first time today, other than the
one I looked at Joe playing with over his shoulder at the weekend.
And I understand that the performance is pretty bad with the OTA.
So the device is shipped with, I think, OTA 9, and then the first update you get is OTA
10.
And as I understand it, there's a bug in OTA 10, which makes the mirror performance pretty
terrible, which is now fixed, which should land in OTA 11.
So the performance should be improved quite dramatically.
I haven't tried all of the gestures that Joe was.
But I will certainly have a play with it tomorrow and see if it's as bad as Joe makes it out
to be.
But as I understand it, it should be better in OTA 11.
You know, Pobie, one of the things that I kind of got on Librem's, or Purism's case
for, was it felt like they were marketing towards super, super, super freedom aware
users that would require things like core boot and no binary blobs, yet were shipping
a device that had a proprietary blob and is not totally free, doesn't use core boot.
And it's like, well, why didn't they just market to a different crowd?
Why not market this to the tech enthusiast crowd?
Is it just not simply a big enough market?
Because it seems like that's all who's really going to end up buying it in the first few
generations anyway.
So it could end up saving a little face by just saying, well, this is really sort of
for the technical people.
I know you don't have an answer in terms of what the company's take is.
But personally, do you think it's maybe would be better to target more geeky people to set
expectations?
Well, it kind of is.
We like repeatedly have said, well, you know, it may be we're giving out a mixed message,
maybe, you know, the marketing looks like it's consumer grade, and it's aimed at normals.
Despite what we internally feel about, you know, we're not expecting this to be everyone
who's got an iPad is going to go and buy one of these and replace their iPad with one of
these.
Like, we're not stupid enough to think that.
And similarly, you know, I know Joe has a Nexus 9, which he covets greatly.
And I don't expect him to replace his Nexus 9 with an M10 either.
I think bear in mind, this is our very first tablet.
Yeah, we've had two major phones so far.
The BQs and the MX4.
And now this one, I think we're still iterating on things.
And yeah, it's not it's not ready for my mom yet, certainly.
And we've had this conversation before on Unplugged.
Unlike unlike any other Ubuntu experience, though, this is so closely tied to how good
the hardware is.
Because you know, you get it all as one package.
And so it's going to take a couple of iterations of BQs hardware to to get better and better.
For the higher end stuff to reach the right price point.
And the OS experience, like switching apps stuttering, is going to suffer for a while,
right?
And the flip side is, like, for the first time last night in a bar, I held a Meizu Pro
5 that I've not seen before.
And oh my god, that is years ahead of every other device that we've had before.
It's super fast, super smooth, the UI is much slicker than than all of the devices we've
had before.
And I picked up my EQ 4.5 this morning was like, oh my god.
So Wimpy, you disagree with me on the hardware front, you think the BQ tablets in pretty
good shape right now as far as horsepower goes?
I do.
And just generally, the build quality of the hardware is very, very good.
I've got a Nexus 9 and most of my family have Nexus 10.
So comparing it to the Nexus 10, it's a lot more trim and lighter and so the hardware
I've got no complaints at all.
I think hardware wise, nobody's going to be disappointed.
I've got the full HD model as well and that the screen is very, very good.
So no, no complaints there.
You can definitely feel the performance I've used up until for devices on some of the Nexus
devices, Nexus 4, Nexus 7, and the BQ5.
And this is, you know, significantly better in terms of performance despite, you know,
some of the bugs that exist in some of the transitions when you've got the desktop mode
enabled.
That's what I really where I really want the horsepower to is if I'm in desktop mode, I'm
working.
If I'm in tablet mode, I'm probably consuming content.
That seems likely.
Browsing the web, whatever.
Yeah.
Oh, boy.
Wes.
So what do you think?
What's your gut tell you on it?
I'm excited to play with it.
Yeah.
You know, I don't know.
Maybe it's not ready for a mass number of people, but we're on the track, right?
Like it's out there and it's real and when does it get to the point where next time Wes
is shopping for a tablet, this is a serious contender?
Are we there yet?
First I have to actually shop for a tablet.
Yeah.
This is kind of like making me consider tablets again as a piece of technology I might want
to buy.
So kind of like me, you've sort of lost interest in them.
You have one that lasts forever because all you do is look at Reddit on it.
Or watch Netflix.
Or maybe, right?
Yeah.
So if there's something suddenly I can just throw in my backpack and then if at work and
then there's a spare monitor, I plug it in and there's my desktop, I could use that
even if there's some rough edges.
I could tell you for sure, not to put words in Noah's mouth, but I could see on a trip
like this, a tablet that could also double as a desktop would have been super handy.
Right?
Well, I can tell you this, the tablet wouldn't have gotten relegated to throwing it on the
kitchen counter and saying, here, see if you can find a use for this to control some other
hardware because I don't really use it, so it's just been sitting in my backpack the
whole time.
Yeah.
He donated a Nexus tablet too for us to use for some production stuff.
Joe, I would be curious to hear your thoughts on the Maru.
Yeah, so Maru is a ROM for the Nexus 5, which is basically AOSP.
It just is really boring Android until you plug it into a screen and your Bluetooth keyboard
and mouse and then suddenly-
Right.
And this is based on Debian, right?
Yeah.
Then you've got a full Debian desktop and I put it on a Nexus 5 and I took a little
selfie video, then another video of it working.
I downloaded and installed GIMP and OpenShot.
I made the title cards in GIMP, edited it in OpenShot, exported it, uploaded it to YouTube,
all on the Nexus 5.
The thing about that is that it's taken two existing things that are solid, Android we
know is a great platform, Debian, that's a no-brainer.
Instead of trying to reinvent things and they're not invented here syndrome, you've got a situation
where the developer of Maru has taken these two solid platforms, put them together, and
that's exactly what we've been talking about, this idea of I can carry around a phone and
do or there's no reason you couldn't do it on a tablet as well and then get to work,
plug it in and have a full desktop.
Instead of trying to reinvent things, sometimes it's better to just stand on the shoulders
of giants and combine things that are good already.
I think that's a pretty sound and pretty often heard argument and I would say that this is
sort of it playing out on a major grand scale that we're all going to sit back and watch.
It's not just this particular stuff too, right?
It's also other things.
I mean Windows has been big on the whole there version of convergence.
Yeah.
So we're well and I think particularly with Canonical and some of the decisions we're
just going to see where this goes and I don't know yet.
I think it's too early to call.
I think we'll have to see where they and we'll have to see how the other part of the picture
is how the updates are delivered to the device, how regularly and how much of a difference
that makes.
I think all that kind of plays a big piece too.
You know, Noah, it strikes me that we should totally load Maru on that Nexus 5 that I bricked
earlier this week.
Sure.
Yeah.
We should totally do that.
I can install it on mine.
Oh, you crazy.
You should do it.
I'll have it for next week if you want.
Yeah, let's do it.
Let's do it.
We'll do a little take on it.
We could do it together.
Oh my gosh.
You know, I should mention that throughout this episode I've been installing Etagros
on the Apollo.
That sounds great.
And I decided to step away from Ubuntu 16.04 for a bit.
And safe havens of arch.
But I didn't format.
I drive swapped, hence the story about drive swapping.
So I can go right back to 16.04 because we had some spare parts.
I kind of downgraded in terms of total storage.
So I'll probably eventually go back to the Ubuntu drives, but I didn't want to wreck
that install because it was actually a pretty solid install of 16.04.
So I'm going to tell you guys more about that.
But before we get into all that stuff, I also want to cover some Linux Fest Northwest clips.
There was some good stuff, including one time where Wes stopped by the booth.
Oh, that's right.
Yeah, so people are watching the video version.
They're going to get to see what Wes looks like here in just a little bit.
Hey, a little surprise there.
But first I'm going to mention our friends at Ting.
This is luck of the draw.
You know, it's different everywhere you go.
But sometimes you just really score with your mobile service provider.
That for me was Ting.
You go to linux.ting.com to save.
They have a CDMA and GSM network.
That's going to be key here.
I'll tell you in just a moment.
Yeah.
Oh, man.
But here's what's great.
No contracts, no determination fee, and it's only $6 for the line.
And then you just pay for your usage on top of that.
That's all you pay.
You don't have to like pre-buy minutes and messages and megabytes and all that stuff
that you might use.
Like I might use 800 minutes and I might use 10 gigabytes.
That's just not a game you play.
It's super simple to activate your devices, especially like the Nexus devices.
You just put the SIM card in and activate the SIM card and you're good to go.
They have radically good customer service, radically better than the rest of the industry.
Their dashboard also is just fantastic.
But you know, we just are super lucky.
Bellingham just has crazy good Ting coverage.
In the expo hall, sitting at the booth, Noah and I have LTE coverage, which to be at a
conference and have LTE coverage is so nice.
And because a lot, just about almost all the JB crew there was on Ting, we all had connectivity.
So we could message each other and it was crucial to making it a smooth Linux fest.
And a huge part of that is being able to choose your network, CDMA or GSM means that you can
pick whichever is stronger in your area and be able to do that just if you know what those
things are, if you know there's something called GSM and CDMA and you vaguely know what
they are and you can vaguely look up coverage maps, you're good to go.
And Ting is super easy when you understand that difference and they make control all
yours with their excellent control panel.
We're doing all this stuff.
We never have to talk to customer service, nothing like that.
It's a really good service and they have really great staff.
In fact, they just recently did a blog post kind of about how they make their margins
between different towns and how they're making money on fiber internet rollout.
They're just really open about that kind of stuff and transparent.
So you can check out their blog.
But first, go to linux.ting.com so we get the credit.
Noah showed up with a $9 SIM card, which was awesome, I ended up using that.
They have the Motorola E second gen, which I don't think I would want for myself when
I could get the LG Volt, but the Motorola E second gen, $74 unlocked, you own it.
I would go for the LG Volt 2, though, because Marshmallow's coming out for that, 66 bucks,
no contract.
It can do most everything you really need in a phone.
That's ridiculous, right?
And it ships tomorrow.
It's got a decent camera on the thing, it's got tri-band LTE connectivity, it's got that
faux metal back with the little thingy there.
Oh, the thingy.
The thingy.
What's that little, it's got that little shutter button right there.
This is seriously, and a quad core Snapdragon processor for 66 bucks, and it's going to
get Marshmallow.
Yeah, I don't know if it has it yet, because they just released the press release a little
bit ago.
They also have internet phones, they have the blue dash, which is cool, for 103 bucks,
unlocked, all of these are no contract.
Netgear Zing is my MiFi that I use.
Oh, I've been thinking about getting one of those.
Yeah, that's what I use, I love it.
You can check them out, they have the OnePlus on there, or you can just go get the Nexus,
I don't know if they're still on sale at Google Play, but they were recently, and then you
just grab it and put it on the Ting network.
Just start by going to linux.ting.com, that supports the show, lets them know you heard
about it here, that keeps us on the air, and it gives you that discount.
Or, if you already have a device you can bring, it'll give you a service credit, linux.ting.com.
Linux Fest Northwest, you guys couldn't all be there, turns out, so we wanted to give
you a little flavor.
In the unplugged program, I cut things a little loose.
So I didn't cut it, like in last, you know, we'll put some transitions in there, I cut
it right to when we do the introduction, like it really stands out, like in the clip where
I introduce you, like, you'll actually see me reset and then introduce you, but I just
left it all in there, because this is the unplugged program, so I'm gonna show you guys
everything.
So let's start with, well let's actually start with something that happened before we got
to Linux Fest Northwest.
Now you might have noticed in last week's episode, 141, the energy was really high.
We were having a good, rambunctious time in last week's episode, and this is how it goes.
We got all these projects, you know, we're finally reunited in person, we get to work
on all these things, we get to do all this stuff, and so last week, we all kind of huddled
in the studio, because it was a full house, and Noah and I were sharing a microphone.
Well, that was a really dumb idea, you might notice we're not doing that this week.
And Noah had to pay a very high cost, and the question came up, if you listen to last
week's episode, you might hear something that kind of sounds, kind of like something falling
over, you know, something like, something that maybe tipped over, and you might hear
your host get really stressed out for a few moments, well I'm not gonna say exactly what
happened because, well, we covered it on the livestream, somebody noticed and asked us
about it.
And by the way, I am not drunk in this clip.
I am not drunk.
Was I drunk at Linux Fest?
Did I have anything to drink?
No.
You didn't have time to get anything to drink.
No, no, yeah, I was dehydrated, if anything, but just exhausted, because we'd worked so
hard up to this point, it was a bumpy day tech-wise, and I was so happy when Wes showed
up.
It was good to see a friendly face.
Of course, Wes, you know how sometimes you're doing a show, and things happen, and you just
gotta keep doing the show, like, maybe you gotta go get a beer, so one of us gets up
and grabs a beer, and the other guy keeps doing the show, right?
Yeah.
Well, also, same thing happens when you spill a beer.
That does happen.
So we were doing, Noah and I were sharing a mic in Linux Unplugged, as you recall, what,
what, you want this?
Yeah.
And Wes was sitting there with us, doing a show, very fun, and I was going to switch
a camera shot, and I knock over my beer, right on top of Noah's ThinkPad.
And it was great, because it wasn't like beer splashed, it was like a, glug glug glug glug
glug glug glug.
Yeah, that sound happened.
And I think all of us in the studio were like, oh crap, we can't say anything, what do we
do?
Let's be very quiet.
So all three of us just start silently communicating, like, while we're still doing the show.
That was amazing.
It was an intense moment.
Yeah, it was an intense moment.
What's funny was, I went back and listened.
There's, I mean, if you know what you're listening.
You can hear the beer fall.
You can tell, but if you didn't know what was happening, I don't know that anyone would
know anything was up.
You have no idea.
It's great, we just gave that away.
You can hear a beer fall over in the episode, but you can't hear it pouring on the laptop.
No, you don't hear the glug, glug, glug, glug.
But you hear the funk, glug, glug.
Well, yeah, and you also can hear the stress in the voice.
Oh, really?
Oh, yeah.
Oh, you can?
A little bit.
That's funny.
So what was the outcome of that?
Well, it became a project to take it apart and try to drain it.
Now it's in this UPS box on its way back to Lenovo to get fixed.
Actually, it's not Lenovo.
It's actually a guy that runs a YouTube channel that teaches people how to fix their computers
at the component level, like the soldering and stuff like that.
So if you have a MacBook or ThinkPad or anything, and the controller goes out in it, Apple will
tell you that you need to buy a new computer, that it's not repairable.
And he will show you how to buy a $0.39 component and solder it back into your computer.
Now you know he has a good YouTube channel because he led me to believe that I was so
confident in what I could do that I could fix my own computer, which did not work out
well at all.
So now I'm going to send it to him and he can fix it.
But someone more confident than you probably could have.
Yes, that is true.
That is true.
Yeah, we were sad because it looked like it might just be a simple keyboard issue.
And then, of course, in the disassembly and to try to resolve the keyboard issue, it doesn't
really go back together.
By the way, whoever came up with the ribbon cables, screw all y'all, screw all y'all.
I want a little white connector with individual pins that I can plug in and unplug.
Dude, I got it.
Yeah.
Lasers.
So as Popey would probably point out, the ThinkPad should have been fine, right, Popey?
The ThinkPad, it has the drain holes.
It should have been okay.
Yeah.
It's his enterprise hardware.
I mean, Popey is, he's like a fanatic.
So he's, he's efficient.
He knows about these things.
And of course, well, you would think so.
But first, before we get to that, this, just because you couldn't see what happened, Noah
wanted to recreate how things likely went down in the studio if we could have said something
to each other.
This is, this is that moment.
Oh, my God.
I am so sorry.
I did not mean to do that.
It was totally accidental.
But here's the thing.
I'm on air doing Linux unplugged.
So if we stop right now to address this, we have to start the entire episode over because
we recorded all in one cut.
And my feet are really nasty because this is sticky and there's stuff all over.
So paper towels could get in here.
That'd be great.
That was pretty much it.
Yeah.
I like that you put on my shirt to do that, Noah.
Although you know, you didn't get the collar quite right.
I'm just saying.
That's right.
Yeah, it's okay.
I aim for the hair to be right, too.
But I think I failed on that, too.
Yeah.
The ribbon cables.
So he disassembles it and makes sure there was no beer in there.
And the keyboard did get kind of wrecked.
Even though it has the drain holes, it got kind of wrecked.
So he disassembles it to see if anything else gets wrecked.
Good news.
It's just the keyboard.
Nice.
So he orders himself a keyboard.
Keyboard arrives.
Turns out the thing doesn't go quite back together quite right.
I was following a YouTube guide and the guy literally is like, well, this cable here,
I never quite figured out how to disconnect it properly.
So if you just yank on it really hard, it comes disconnected.
And that was about the point where I realized my ThinkPad was screwed and I should probably
send it into Lewis to get him to fix it.
Oh, Noah.
Wow.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
So this, you guys got to remember, this was Saturday.
Things were a little crazy.
Oh, Saturday.
And there was a competition, Nye.
The Switch competition was that evening.
And so that's really where a lot of our thoughts were.
And Noah, just the thing about Noah is you could try to set things up so that he'll go
to bed early.
And no matter what you do, he's still going to be up till 2 a.m. in the morning in the
lobby of the hotel talking about, you guessed it.
He goes down there to talk about Linux and ends up with a bunch of people sitting around
him and they're all talking about Linux instead of sleeping.
We get a little bit of peek of that and then watch as Noah pivots from that and starts
recruiting him to try to help with the Switch competition.
The man is unstoppable.
So here's by the way, I just included a little bit of this.
This here is the shot of our booth, if you guys didn't get to see so much of the live
coverage.
Sweet booth.
Yeah, it was really great.
It's Chase in the bottom corner and I'm over there in the other corner.
There's Albert Westra and there's Jed's butt over there, so you guys can catch that, which
is nice.
So it was a really cool, it was actually a great booth.
And so we were sitting there just kind of getting things fixed up and Noah's buddy stops
by.
Did you watch that episode?
I didn't, no chance.
Okay, no, that's fine.
So I host the show with Chris, if that isn't evident to you yet.
We should recap the story a little bit.
I was walking, you were walking in the hotel and you look over my shoulder and you're like,
hey, is that Linux?
Hey, is that Linux?
Yeah, I've heard the story.
And then you mistakenly thought you were just going to walk off and go back upstairs and
what, go to bed or something?
Like, no, that's not going to happen.
So I was like, no, come on over here.
So then you decided you had to go, you were going to go get your significant other and
your brother was with you, right?
Yeah.
Oh, there's your brother.
There he is.
Hello, Hussein.
That's Hussein and that's Devon.
Hussein.
And that's Devon.
And you're new.
Oh, okay.
Check out his tattoo.
Yeah, I like that.
Nice.
So I'm guessing you use Linux then if you bothered to ink it on your body.
He's a Linux user.
You're a Linux user?
Yeah.
You can stay.
Draft it on your skin.
You better be.
Yeah, right.
So we sat down.
What do you think it was?
Like an hour conversation?
Oh my God.
Hour and a half at least.
Yeah.
Oh my gosh, dude.
What time?
What time of night is this?
Two in the morning.
Yeah.
I didn't get to bed before two.
Dude, do you ever sleep?
You got to sleep tonight.
There was Linux to talk about.
Yeah.
He tells me he has to be here at 830.
I'm like, oh my God.
You know what?
I just sleep in.
It's not a big deal.
I'm in the dark.
I know.
And he's got to be live all day.
But there was Linux to be had.
Yeah.
Okay.
So we sat.
We talked about Linux.
We talked about Arch.
We talked about Ubuntu.
Anyway, super, super cool people.
Aw, thank you.
And you guys are...
So you actually travel here every year for the last six years?
Yeah, something like five years, four years, four to six years.
Something like that.
So tell me about that.
How did you get from Vancouver to come to Linux Fest?
There's nothing like this.
Linux Fest is unique.
Every conference is unique.
But Linux Fest being free and open to everybody is very like the community in and of itself.
And it's just so much difference than a paid conference.
The talks are more inclusive.
People are more friendly.
We had a crazy conversation at 2 a.m.
Now you've attended Linux Con.
So you've gone to both sides...
I call it both sides of the...
Corporate Linux.
Yeah.
Can you compare and contrast the two events for me?
Corporate Linux, the talks are very more in-depth.
Like the speakers clearly work in the field.
And like there's no question that they know what they're talking about.
But at the same time, it's kind of intimidating because like these are these are hardcore
heavy professionals.
And it's not that you don't get that here.
There's definitely those kinds of talks here.
But it's more like reading a forum where people just kind of talk and you get more of a community
feel with even the talks.
Yeah.
And so have you ever been to Linux Con or Roscon or any of the like the big like corporate
events?
Have you ever been to that and had any sort of like spontaneous, completely unplanned,
totally unwarranted community events like we had?
Because it wasn't just him.
It was him and it was Devin and it was and it was just right.
And then your buddy Sean was there, you know, so it's like we had like this little group
that just assembled at the hotel.
I mean, like right now we have this group that is forming here.
So how can you have you ever had something like that happen at one of those larger events?
It's different.
I chatted with John Mad Dog Hall on the bus to the after party.
So I mean, you know, that's a perk.
Yeah, exactly.
But it's not the same where people just talk.
And I think because you see Mad Dog Hall, it's hard to just interject in the conversation.
And I was talking with that guy at the Software Freedom Law Center.
Forget his name.
He does some really awesome stuff.
Even?
No, no.
Shit.
Maybe it was.
Yes.
It was even more one.
And again, awesome conversation.
We're talking on the floor.
Crowd forms around us.
But nobody wants to talk.
Yeah.
Because it's even freaking mobile.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Talk to the guy.
Yeah.
I'm weird.
I just like to talk to people.
Yeah.
So I want to I do want to talk.
I do want to talk to your brother.
I do want to talk to your girlfriend.
But can you tell me if you were?
Can you tell me what you would say to somebody that has that maybe is thinking about coming
to Linux Fest, but hasn't really been here, isn't really sure they're kind of on the fence?
What would you say if somebody asked you what you what they should do or you having so much
experience coming to Linux Fest, what you would say to them?
I wouldn't waste their time.
I just say come and check it out.
You can't know until you're here.
All right.
Last thing.
One last thing.
This is kind of like icing on the cake.
You have like the cake and then you have the icing.
Sure.
Tell me about text messages and being concise.
Oh, man.
You.
Yeah.
Everyone needs here.
This is a PSA.
Kind of like how I.
I just got three text messages while you asked that.
Oh, my God.
One thread.
Yeah.
Kind of like I did just there where I took 10 seconds to organize my thoughts and the
host didn't mind.
They, you know, interjected and said something while I organized my thoughts.
I didn't do that here.
I'm kind of spamming it out, but you organize your thoughts and you get it out in one message.
One message.
Otherwise, and you know, I have this watch and this watch vibrates every time I get a
message.
Oh, my God.
How does it help you to answer if you get like three spams rather than.
One concise message.
It doesn't.
It drives me.
I start to think, oh, there must be an emergency.
I better check right.
Oh, no.
It just spread out.
It spread out over four messages.
And when it comes to an actual emergency, you'll just be ignored.
So you're lost, but.
One message.
Keep it concise.
All right.
Can we talk to your girlfriend or your brother?
Who was ever up?
Or both?
Anybody?
Next up.
That was, that was particularly for me because he knows that that was kind of funny about
this guy, too.
So he sits down, right?
And he sees a Jupiter broadcasting sticker on our laptop and he goes, oh, do you guys
listen to Jupiter broadcasting?
And so I, you know, I stopped for a second to see if he's trolling me, if he's serious
and he's serious.
I'm like, yeah, no, we do.
And he's like, are they any good?
The shows any good?
I'm like, yeah, hosts are all right.
There's one guy in the Linux action show kind of darker skin.
He's kind of a kind of a jerk, but everything else is fine.
So then we start talking about the, you know, the, the episodes and stuff.
And that's when I told him, I said, you know, go watch the Ubuntu versus arch episode.
I think that would clarify some of the things that, you know, we were talking about or whatever,
but I thought it would be funny if he had seen it before he actually came over to the
booth.
And then he shows up at the booth and turns out, oh, that's the guy.
So there, so what happens a few moments after that, and this is super funny is his girlfriend
says, no, I don't really feel like sitting down.
And I just decided not to, I just, that was long enough clip.
I wanted to cut it.
The next thing that Noah does when the, when the, when his girlfriend declines to sit down
and he says, okay, okay, will you guys do me a favor?
Will you go out and find anybody running windows and tell them to come see me?
And then, and maybe this is actually probably a good thing I cut it out is then he gives
out his telegram handle.
He's like, or just have them telegram me.
Let's organize this thing.
Cause he's getting super competitive.
And just as we start getting competitive, guess who stops by for a chat?
Guess who stops by?
Why?
Yes, it's Emma.
And I was stepping, I had stepped away from the booth for a couple of seconds.
And so Noah and Angela were sitting on the live stream cause I was out taking a walk
around the floor.
I wanted to get a feel for it.
And Emma stops by to talk, well, talk about actually switching people to Linux, which
is really interesting if you're trying to switch people to Linux.
And she also talks a little bit about the switch competition.
Yeah, yeah.
Come over here.
Did you hear that we did a hashtag team Noah?
I did.
Okay.
Isn't there a hashtag team Emma?
There needs to be.
There is.
There is now.
Hashtag, hashtag team.
You pointed that way.
Oh, I was pointing to the sign.
No, you were fine.
It's right in the center.
Learn how to frame man.
I was just pointing.
I can't see it.
The camera got moved.
So we're not centered anymore.
I can't see it.
And when somebody does this, I think that means, I'm sorry, that's good.
Team Emma.
Hashtag team Emma.
Which is the, this is, so what we're doing here, this is the team that you don't want
to go for.
Oh.
No, I'm just kidding.
I'm kidding.
If you want a awesome, I'm going to get in trouble now.
You're going to get me in trouble.
Now my boss is going to see me hanging a sign on our camera that says team Emma.
What are you guys doing to me?
This was a setup.
Who did this?
So if you're looking for an awesome experience on hardware, if you didn't, let's say you
didn't want to be switched to Linux on your computer.
Let's say you just wanted Linux to work on your computer.
Then you might consider system 76, right?
So tell me how long have you been at system 76, Emma?
Almost four and a half years.
And what do you do for them?
I am the consumer sales manager.
And what does that mean exactly?
I manage individual sales, so if it's not a business or a university, I'll handle all
aspects of the sale, including sales questions over the phone or on our social networks.
And that's about it.
So do you get a lot of Windows users that call in and want to, that are looking to switch
to Linux?
Yes.
Everyone starts the conversation with, you know, I'm just so sick of Windows and I Googled
and I found you guys.
Oh, it's not.
I listen to Jupiter Broadcasting.
That is actually very common, too, but you guys don't have, you guys have more Linux
users listening to your show.
Sure.
Thank you.
Because I think you guys switch them by having the show.
When people call in, do you guys sell Windows hardware?
Like if I wanted to buy a computer with Windows, do you guys ship that?
So when somebody calls in and they say, I'm interested in a computer, is there a conversation
that takes place where you have to convince them that they're going to buy this computer
and have Linux installed and use it?
Or have they already made that decision when they call in?
A lot of times they've made the decision that they're fed up with it, but then they have
some questions about why they're hesitant.
So I'll answer maybe five or six questions and then they'll get happier as the conversation
goes.
I can hear them smile every time I give them an answer and they're like, oh, this is sounding
great already.
This is so much better than Windows.
I'm so excited.
So I get them excited.
And when you're talking to these people, you're having these conversations, what kind of questions
are they asking?
Do I need virus protection?
What kind of apps are installed?
What kind of software will work with it?
Can I open Windows documents?
What are some alternatives for certain types of software?
So those are pretty much the most common questions.
And what kind of support is there available?
And we offer lifetime software support, so that's a winner too.
So you have a one year warranty on the hardware?
So after that one year, they can continue to call in and ask questions, even if it's
not the version of Ubuntu that shipped on their laptop and you will continue to help
them?
For hardware, yes.
So we don't ever turn away anyone for support.
So we do offer a one year, two year, or three year warranty.
So that would cover the cost of the parts and repair.
But if you do need a part and you're out of warranty, we'll still get you the part.
How many people have called in and said, I am a perfectly happy Windows user and I don't
really have any interest?
They haven't started the conversation with switching to Linux and have you dealt with
that?
You know why he's asking, right?
I know why he's asking.
He's asking because he's trying to determine how big of a challenge he faces.
What he's trying to set here is the narrative that they're already on the way to switching
when they call.
And that's what he said.
He's sitting over there laughing and shaking his head because he knows that's true.
And so this is how competitive Noah is.
Even in the interview questions, he's setting it up that way.
It's so great.
You have talked them from, I think I'm maybe not a perfectly happy Windows user, but it's
tolerable and it works for me, into you need to start running Linux.
They're always just so close to the edge.
So I'm just that hand to hold.
Okay.
Now I have to ask, if somebody wanted to get in contact with you here at the Fest, is there
a way for them to do that?
Yes.
They can either tweet to System76 or contact us through our Facebook page or come by our
booth.
And your booth is...
How do you identify booths?
I don't know.
Second to the last...
We have a blue curtain.
I don't...
Second to the last row from the door.
If you come in the main door...
I would just call it the middle.
They are B2.
B2.
Oh, there.
Oh, look at you pulling out a mask.
Oh, look at you being smart.
So here's us.
There we are.
See, and that's...
So...
Hey.
How you doing?
Good.
They're the next row, right behind you.
Thanks.
Pretty clever.
That's System76.
Two presentations.
Well, thank you very much for stopping by the booth.
Yeah.
That's not trolling.
Well, yeah.
Are you, in fact, Team Emma?
Huh?
I am.
Then it's not trolling.
I am Team Emma.
The only thing trolling is making me hold that up when my boss is walking in.
Well, if you were interviewing someone, I was gonna come by and be like...
Oh.
That would be trolling.
Yeah.
That would be my original plan.
That would be trolling out of ten, as we're saying.
Oh, geez, Noah.
Oh, geez.
Trolling out of ten.
So, yeah.
So that was what's funny is I was, like, watching this back on the replay, I'm like, Noah is
totally pumping, and he's thinking to himself, okay, so when they come to Emma, they're already
sort of greased to be switching.
Switching.
Oh, whoa.
So that was pretty funny to see his...
That was great.
Wheels turning there.
Okay.
So, after Emma stopped by, we started realizing we may have ourselves a situation.
We had...
We started...
A couple of things had gone down on the live stream, and we decided to get up and go for
a walk.
And we went, and when we started walking around, we started picking up a little scuttlebutt.
And by the time we made it back to the live stream, we could definitely feel the tension
building for the night's Switch competition, and, well, I'll let the clip speak for itself
here.
Do it live.
We'll do it live.
Oh, and Wes stops by, too.
Hey, there he is.
Howdy, howdy, sir.
Sit down in the hot seat.
Have a seat with us.
How you doing, Wes?
Doing wonderfully.
Yeah.
Hey, it's Wes.
Wes, grab the mic.
You gotta eat it a little bit.
You gotta eat that.
Oh, hello.
You gotta do a foul when you're ready there, Mr. Chase.
All right.
Ladies and gentlemen, joining us here in the hot seat is, of course, one Mr. Wes Payne
from Linux Unplugged.
Wes, good to see you in the flesh, sir.
Oh, it's wonderful to be here.
How did the drive up teach you?
Not too bad.
I thought it was gonna rain.
It looks like it's gonna rain.
Yeah.
It's an angry day out there.
It is.
Yeah.
That is some of the best weather commentary I have ever heard.
It's an angry day out there.
And then I just play off.
It's treacherous out there.
Nothing.
It's treacherous in the present.
Yeah.
A wonderful day for Linux.
I've actually gotten a chance to go out and do a little watering thing.
You can tell we're doing an amazing job.
It's like we're going to be in the rain.
Yeah.
It's gonna be great.
We're not.
We're not going to.
It's a perfect day for Linux.
It is.
Yeah, a wonderful day for Linux. I've actually gotten a chance to go out and do it like a little
Him it is and tonight should be a pretty fun night. We have the big switch competition. Oh
Yeah, and and we're going out. How's our main man here feeling? I
You know, here's ready. No, I'll tell you what. Here's when you were born ready. We know that yeah, I was I eat you pay
Attention. That's what I like about you. No, so I think that I think that I
Really? I got it. I got to watch my back because yeah
Here's what I've here's what I know
I know that there is there is no one more dangerous than somebody who is truly motivated and I was over at the at the
System 76 yeah, and hashtag team Emma
Yeah, they are they're taking it seriously and the thing is she has a lot of stuff going for her that I don't have going
For me. So for example, she can off if you switch with em, like if you switch with me
Yeah, first of all, just supportive. Well, there's that yeah doesn't hurt you to work
But that's not gonna help you run Linux and you you're like some weird Indian I am
They haven't deported me yet, but no not normally around many people, you know
But now think about this if you switch with me the support ends when when I leave right because let's face it
I'm going back to Grand Forks and good luck with your in his rights install
But now the system 76 they've got a phone number
They have a whole team full of people on standby to switch and when you go to upgrade
By a different computer or you decide that you need a little bit more horsepower
She can easily just it's literally just a dovetail into a brand new machine loaded with the same operating system
You've already so there so she does have some major major. I'll tell you what. Here's why I'm worried and
You know we
The the fact that we are in our own backyard. Yep
Could actually be just a disadvantage to us. Yeah a little complacent. Yes. We're a little complacent and
Because we're here people, you know people watch the show. They're letting her know that they're back in Noah, right?
I like so that's kind of put her back on her heels a little bit
And I thinking when you get somebody back on their heels a little bit
They're more aggressive they are and the thing is is there will be a counter pressure to that there will be a counter wave
It'll swing the other direction
I think by the by the approach of the evening support for team Emma will be building and you actually we can see this in
The email they're saying there's people are sending it in that is high-resolution screen. I tell you what 4k display. Yeah
a raving raving raving fan writes in and says I'm for hashtag team Emma because she's so happy to help new Windows users get
Set up with running a bunch
That's what I'm saying is patient a light never makes you feel like you're stupid for not knowing how to add a printer or something
Like that plus she's pink bedazzled workspaces and you can't go wrong with that go hashtag team Emma. That's a
This is what I'm thinking is I think there will be a groundswell in for Emma because she's nice
She's got the backing of system 76. She's got she's got a pink thing in her hair that matches her shirt that catches the eye
Yeah, you know it didn't bring his glass
So that was like BSD whore that's a huge conversation starter for a huge conversation starter
So I'm just a little concerned that
So what and here's the other thing we're not doing this switch here at Linux right because these are mostly Linux
Yeah, we have to go out into the crowd where we lose our familiar advantage, right?
So I'm just yeah, and and and I think we may even Jupiter broadcasting. What's that Chris?
I know and to make matters worse. I think we may actually have a defector in our midst. Oh, yeah
I think we have somebody who may be who may have leaked at one of our planned locations to team Emma
Yeah, so there is no way isn't it?
There is a lot going on on top of the fact that we're here doing a show, right?
Like I said, I forget about the show at some point because there is just so much
Dynamics to this to keep track of and and you know
You got people in the JB crew betting behind the scenes on this thing
You got you got people now defecting to team Emma. I have a groundswell in the community. It is
down to the wire West so so like
Like every Linux fest Northwest as much as you can handle and more. Yes, exactly
Yeah, it's an extreme Linux best. Yeah
the so then it was just a couple of hours after that to the switch competition kicked off and
It was nuts and we will have the final results in Sunday's Linux action show
and it was
Really a kind of intense for us as the host because we kept it all a secret from each other and all of that
So I'm really looking forward to it. Yeah, it has been crazy and I have a couple of photos
I wanted to share with you guys too. This is a great picture here of Noah
This is what he spent a lot of his time here doing is rebuilding computers swapping parts around you can see
There's just screws and pieces everywhere paper plates pizza rolls
It's basic fuel tablets
motherboard boxes, this is this is a picture from the
After party where I could only get so many people in one shot
It was just there's people everywhere hanging out around the studio. This is a shot here of some of the pizza here
Let me take off the lower third there so you can see all of the pizza
Hey, yeah, we fed a lot of people it was healthy eating while we were all here and then of course, there's Emma
She stopped by yeah that Emma. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. She got she got in the studio and we had some fun
Yeah, so it was all good time. In fact, I got a little clip
If you're watching the video version here just a little clip of us. We went up to dinner after the switch competition
Well, that's way louder than I wanted to I apologize for that here
Let me pull it down a little bit here. Oh, so just you can see the venue a little bit
For those of you that are watching Oh, I'm on Goose
You know what video is hard for Goose. It's you know what Goose. I understand. It's been hard for us this week, too
There we go
That's the table we we took up and and the crew that helped us out there's Ian from system 76 playing on his
His game boy. It was it was a lot of fun at the day. We went to a really nice place
What was it called the Boundary Bay? Yeah, they may bay. Oh, man, and no if you said it was one of your favorite places
We'd been yet
All Hall song. Sorry. No, I don't I don't hear you. Sorry. No, hold on Noah get it get your audience
Get your audience. No, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no
Get it get your audio working. But yeah, of course we know it's here. We got to go to a lot of places
It was very good
We'll have to feature some of their beer
Like the way you think I like the way you think and if you want to change the way you think I would like to
Point you over to Linux Academy
Go to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and get our great discount right here on the unplugged program
The og source of the unplugged discount Linux Academy comm slash unplugged. It's a great platform for you to learn more. They have
2379 videos where you can obtain experience as you need to learn and practice right there on their lab servers provided by the Linux Academy
They spin them up on-demand seven distros. You can choose from automatically adjust the course where they have scenario based labs
You get right in the middle of everyday common tasks stuff that gives you real-world experience
Instructor mentoring is available on these complex Linux related topics everything built around Linux technology on top of like OpenStack
nginx Ruby Python
Android development you name it West. They've got it West graded server exercises are awesome
They have a fantastic technology stack. You know what? I don't mention enough
Because I don't want to upset Michael Dominic
PHP right. Mm-hmm PHP. Yeah, they have in-depth resources available to you a
Instructor home dude instructor mentoring is the best. In fact, we should mention I don't know if I told you this
Instructor help is available. What? Yeah, West. Did you know that? How is that even possible?
Practice exams are also the bee's knees for getting all of your practice in before you actually go out there and try to take the big
Test they have enhanced learning plans where you can tell it your availability and they will customize it for your busy busy schedule
AWS OpenStack DevOps anything around Linux they have the best courseware on it Linux Academy comm
Slash unplugged and a big thank you to Linux Academy go check out also their live seminars and their nuggets all that good stuff
It's the kind of nuggets that are actually good for you two to sixty minutes in-depth resources Linux Academy comm
slash
unplugged so I as the show has been going have been loading and hair girls on my Apollo switching it from always a
pleasant experience
Mm-hmm. It really was switching it from Ubuntu
1604 unity to enter gross and I you know, you could watch episode
413 of the Linux action show where we reviewed Ubuntu 1604
To hear my thoughts on how Ubuntu is difficult to install software. You will also hear Noah's thoughts on why it is not difficult
however
Noah himself has admitted and
This is I actually think this is kind of a big deal that Ubuntu 1604
Has kind of disenfranchised him from Ubuntu for a bit. No, I do you want to explain what's going on
Literally gotten to a point where a 1604 is no longer even usable for me
I mean I have it unloaded on this laptop
After everything I was preaching on Sunday was based off the idea that it with the LTS
I know that I'm getting limited software, but the software that is on there will work just fine. Well as it turns out
1604 has screwed even that up because I can't install the software
like I go goes in the software center and I launched into an inadvertent game of ping-pong and
Then I installed you to buy to install it and the software might install but then half of these apps don't
Actually load properly and if they do load properly the menus don't work properly and if those work properly
I realize I'm not on the internet half the time because my network manager crashes and if that works properly I
Just it seems like every time I turn around there's another problem and how this qualifies as an LTS. I
I can't I can I can't as a Linux enthusiast and you know, you see me all the time, right?
I'm somewhat of an optimist
I tend the Rekha always calls me the lowest denominator Linux like I'm like well boots and I can see something I call it good
But this is beyond unusable. It's beyond unusable and I'm sure they'll get it fixed
But they have stained the mark of the LTS at this point because they have released
quote
Reliable solid long-term support software and it's totally useless out of the box
Yeah, and when we were at Linux fest, everybody was kind of nodding their heads when we were complaining about stuff Joe
What's your experience been?
Well, I downloaded it today 1604 I'd been busy
So I've only just got a chance to check it out
And one of the first things I wanted to do is install Chrome because that's what a lot of people do
So I downloaded the the deb
Opened it opens up the software center or software install
It's called now and you press install and just nothing happens and then
Nothing happened. Yep, and then so I thought okay, right? Well d package dash I
And then the path to it and then it gave me the the issue about the char one problem because they've tightened up the security
Right now for me, I know how to get around that but for your average user who Ubuntu is aimed at
That's not a very good situation. Is it?
Just installed Chrome as during the show on Ubuntu
And I mean I paste I did it with via PPA pasting from in from a website into the terminal
But it was the same kind of experience where I was like I could do it, but that's not great
So the things that I've I've personally ran into are sort of are sort of disappointing for myself, too
I have had some serious issues with network manager and I've had some issues with Intel graphics when I'm hooked up to a second monitor
Ironically other people have had the issue when they're not hooked up to a second monitor
My issues have been when I am hooked up to a second monitor
And if you go back and watch the review, I said this was the most exciting Ubuntu release in a long time
And I still kind of feel that way in some sense. Like I'm not really hesitant to use it on the server
Yeah, right exactly. Yeah, I'm excited still there. Yeah, like I okay Alex the e2o is out, you know
They've got a support. Yeah, exactly. They've got snap packages will eventually be shipped. I'm sure I'm I hope
But on the desktop, this has been bad. This has been a and you know
The unity version seems to be the worst because I primarily spent my time on Matei and on
Kubuntu and they didn't suffer from a lot of infrastructure on those that kind of mask these problems. Mm-hmm. I
So I am I am I watched it back our review today actually on the on last and I ended it by saying I was extremely
Excited I got to say I'm I'm pretty disappointed as far as a desktop experience goes
I just every single day every single day. There has been an application that I've needed that is not available
Literally every single day it is this whole weekend, you know is a little bit of a rare exception
We're doing a lot of things but has been a so today. I wanted to I wanted to cut those videos of
Linux fest from our live stream, right?
And this is the the video editor we never talk about on the show is the best video editor out there
It is dude. It's called avid mucks and it's yeah, you can you could mark an endpoint and I took videos that were wrapped in
the FLV flash container
drop, I know that one dropped it in avid mucks marked my in and outs and save them out as
And I and I didn't have to re-encode it just extracts
H264 in the audio and saves them out as MKVs
So not only did I cut my in and outs in the stream files
But I also converted it from a dot FLV to MKV without re-encoding the video
It's a really good tool. I use it for all my clips on them filter all the time. It's my number one editor
it's like a nice like gooey equivalent of ffmpegs power and yes flexibility and
Go ahead and try to install that on Ubuntu 1604 one of the best one of the best quick little apps
You could you'll find PPAs you can get those PPAs and then dependencies won't work
You can try to download devs from get Deb, but it won't work
You cannot actually go download a 1604 Deb directly no installation candidate. No, there's nothing
It's it's it's and it's every single week. I'm sorry every single day. It's an actual useful application
It's not an esoteric strange app that just got posted up on github
It's real desktop applications on Linux are a pain in the ass to install and that is an egregious one
And 1604 has been just really extremely spotty and I had intended as of last week's episode
To keep Ubuntu on this Apollo for as long as I possibly could and now
Using it here. I I had to take it off. It was just it was just with I
Can't even use it for my workflow. It is it has got to be the one of the worst LTS releases for the desktop ever
and
Then I I don't think it's impossible to fix
I think 1604 dot one or two so in like six months you could be I would have you could be completely I would say
Maybe even three months. Yeah
But what the hell happened and they've been so good at releases in the past
Well, I just don't understand what happened. I don't I mean it's not like anyways, so
We were a little disappointed to I mean
I think probably know the most but all of us were sort of disappointed in it. And so and it was also like
So it just as another example if you want the latest version of OBS on Ubuntu you need to install Ubuntu 1404
Really even that is two point releases behind
Now guess what? We needed to use this weekend. Oh, yeah. Oh, yes
you know the only way to get the so
this week turns out
They revved OBS with Intel quicksync support and Nvidia. I forget what Nvidia is GPU accelerated the same thing
Yeah, they're GPU accelerated encoding which we have an Intel i7 processor and an Nvidia
GPU in our OBS rig and we would love to take advantage of accelerated encoding
The only way to do that cleanly in a package managed environment
It was for us. We load an arch
Well, we tried to do Ubuntu right now up on SATCOM one and SATCOM two
We're still using Ubuntu, but we need to yeah, we actually have to use Ubuntu 1404
So we just had to deploy to Ubuntu 1404 and that's not totally totally outrageous in enterprise production
But it is kind of outrageous for us, right?
so I
Even on the server. We actually have deployed a few 1604 servers over the last few days as well
But I probably will soon. Yeah, I've deployed a couple
But I don't think anything no nothing in the yes
You can see me a thumbs up or thumbs down but nothing in the video production chain now is using the 1604, right?
Everything's 1404 or arch. Yeah, huh?
Yeah, the stuff that needs to be more current and you know need to have the latest support is arch and then the stuff that's
On the back end more stable that handles like all of the back end communications SATCOM one and two are for our Ubuntu 1404, right?
And then that way and it's kind of an indictment in some sense on the release mobile room. Anybody have thoughts or an opposite opinion
Well, I was just going to say that at least the online search is off by default now
So they've kind of taken that privacy. Yeah stuff into consideration at last. Yeah, I do
I do like that a lot
It's you know, like I think like I've been saying I think it's gonna be a release in a few months
You could recommend to average people to install but I don't know like the software not installing when you click install
What the swap issue they didn't get fixed until a couple of days before release it just it gives it like a slam-together feeling
which is not the impression you want to give for an LTS and it
See if you're if you're a cynic like me like if you're kind of a jerk you start thinking
Well, you know
maybe it's because they had that BQ tablet that ended up needing to ship right around the LTS release and they needed to work on
Getting that ready and maybe they got distracted and they also had that bash on Windows
And they also had that bash on Windows project like maybe they were spread a little thin during the build up to a question
Their allocation of resources it does and that's and I could be completely wrong
But that when you when you deliver something like this people start going. What are they?
Is this a safe bet questions are asked? Yeah. Yeah
So, uh
I don't I don't want this to be a total downer because I still save those drives and I plan to plug them back in
In a couple of months. I'm still gonna do an update some deploys here. Yeah, and I still plan to run it on servers
Uh, but I I just I I think i'm gonna hold the breaks
I'm gonna and you know, I watched watching that review back. I was all in I was actually and i've been saying on this show
For for months and this is the the release i'm the most excited about
True and I ran it for a month up to the review
But you know the big mistake I made there is because I just wasn't all that excited about unity is I ran plasma desktop and matte
And and and truly, you know wimpy has has really smoothed over some of these rough edges
And it's not nearly as bad of an experience on ubuntu mattei and to that end the machines
We have put in production running ubuntu are on ubuntu mattei
Right. Yeah, so
Yeah, it's just sort of the way it's shaking out wimpy. Are you still here? Do you have any thoughts on the 1604 release?
I wonder if he i'm not sure if he's still here or not
I can't see the screen. No, I don't think so. I think both him and poppy were from hotel connections and had to disconnect
Uh, i'm curious. Maybe we'll pick his brain. I don't want to over overdo the ubuntu coverage
But uh, I you know, I will say installing that ubuntu mattei welcome package on any 1604 release really does go a long way
I totally agree. I really do. All right mumble any mumble any closing thoughts on the ubuntu, uh follow up before we uh, wrap it up
Going once going twice
I take that as sort of a tacit agreement unless you disagree otherwise
That's legit right streamer streamer says yeah
Okay stream says no disagreement
Uh, yeah. Yeah poppy had to disconnect. I know I really think that uh, it's a
Okay closing thoughts really quick just just to wrap it up because I did share these on the live stream on saturday
Part of me. Here's what I think happened. I think maybe they legitimately got distracted
They had too many things
They were working on before 1604 came out and they have this release date so much is built around
Ubuntu hitting this release date all the flavors, uh, you know, uh vps is the whole big rolling
It's an industry now based around these lts releases and so they have to hit that release date
There's a lot of pressure to hit that release date
Whereas a distribution like anagros or any a lot of other ones i'm just picking on anagros because that's what we've been messing around with
between the two
They release when they feel like they have an iso that has enough new fixes or updates to release it
Otherwise, it's just kind of developed all the time. Yeah, just update it
They just release iteratively when they feel like it and arch just sort of updates iteratively when they feel like it
And sometimes I think you get in a sweet spot where that's a good combination and things are working pretty great
And sometimes that sync slips a little bit and the ltss are a better combination and right now I think
the arbitrary release dates and uh, just slamming out the features
Yeah
I mean really even even the even like a we made a big deal about the zfs support and it's it's there
But you gotta install all if you install the desktop version, you gotta install all of the userland packages
There's no there's no user exposed way to actually set it up. You're going down the terminal
You're going down the terminal and using zpool and zcreate and whatever else whatever else at that point
You know the dkms stuff before it wasn't that much extra. Yeah, exactly like the dkms wasn't that hard?
It's like the least amount of work exactly
That's my point and like you're going to have to go buy alan jude's book to be able to set up a zfs
On your pointer box. I linked that to so many people. Yeah zfsbook.com. Uh, he just released a new edition go check it out
like seriously
Uh, and and and again, I am not trying to compare to other distros, but other distros and when you're installing
Zfs is just in the drop down. I'm not using I don't i'm not using it to set up zfs
But it's just like how much extra work if you have all the userland utilities available?
You have the kernel module available
How much extra work is it to expose that as an option in your installer?
How much if all of the underlying linux software is there how much work can that be?
and if you're like taking this big step by offering it like you think you'd want to like
Package that up as a whole big cohesive thing. And of course, they have the excellent excuse of well, we don't uh, think it's uh,
targeted for uh, end users
so uh, it wasn't really a
Priority to make it available in the gooey
Which is a very solid argument except for the very reason that ubuntu has any relevance is because they made a great desktop
Distribution to begin with and people adopted on this is their thing. That's how ubuntu got traction
They didn't start out as the server as the vps cloud distribution
They started out as a as linux for human beings. Yep
Where's that gone?
Where is that?
on the phone
Hey, oh
All right. Hello everybody end of rant. I'm just um, I uh, I just uh
I just I don't know. I guess I probably I probably should get off my soapbox because in reality
I think it's wasted effort. It's not gonna get me anywhere
Uh, and that's okay because I think over time things will get comments. Yeah
Well, that's for that. I think noah's gonna get more comments about his lack of sleep
Then I will get comments about my ubuntu hate so I think we're doing okay
Yeah, no at jupiter broadcasting.com if you want to send us an email go to jupiter broadcasting.com
Contact and choose linux unplugged from the drop down. Hey, did you know that we do this show live?
You can find out about that over at jupiter broadcasting.com
Calendar we do it live over jblive.tv where you can find out
All about our mumble room everything really that's true. All of the information is there all of it
You can do bang mumble and you'll get mumble server info. Uh, you can go to linuxactionshow.reddit.com to leave us feedback
submit content
Things we should talk about all of that linuxactionshow.reddit.com. All right, everybody
Thank you so much for tuning this week's episode of linux unplugged
I'm gonna go get some sleep and see you right back here next week
So
Yeah, we really should say thanks to chase for running the board at linux fest rocking that board
Yeah, thanks to the crew that came out to help us with everything
Thank you. Everybody including you wes. It was a it was a great linux fest
It really was amazing and uh, it was a big big big production. All right, jb titles.com. Now we go name this beast
or jb titles
Oh
Good amount of titles over here. I'm gonna so I actually I have one
I have one more show which is a lot of work, which is on filter before I can sleep
So my my marathon doesn't technically end until wednesday night, but then I think we have a pre-recorded tech stamp
That would be sweet. I think he might still be out of town. And so then i'm just gonna sleep thursday
Sleep kind of wake up sometime on saturday. No, no, I wish I wish
Uh, but yeah, all right, jb titles.com. Let's go boat. Thank you. Thanks suggest.com. That's way more fun
Good show mumba room. Thank you very much. I appreciate it