I present you the perfect pet. It is OpenCat. It's a GPL3 highly programmable and maneuverable
robotic cat that's powered by AI and 3D printing with a Raspberry Pi for extra flavor.
Well isn't that neat?
This is, oh they got a video. Should we roll the, should we roll the live dice?
Oh yeah, let's check it out.
Okay here we go.
Is it creepy or cute? That's what we want to know.
The OpenCat demo. Oh boy. Oh boy. So it's crawling. It looks like a kid's robotic toy.
It does, yeah.
It does have the ability to get itself back up when it gets knocked over.
That'll be useful.
Here's version two. You know I gotta say, version two's looking a lot better. They really,
they're really committed to this thing, Wes. They're really committed to this thing.
I mean it is pretty, pretty impressive. Now I don't know that I want to have it like around
my house if I didn't, didn't build it, but.
Right, or when you're sleeping would you always make sure to turn it off? I mean think about
that for a second. Do you want some robot cat ramp? Because a real cat, they roam around
the house at night. You can respect the project here on this.
Maybe you could turn it into like a robo-cat security droid.
Maybe mount a laser on there?
Oh yeah.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 238 for February 27th, 2018.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that is covered in barbecue and
been cleaning up dog poo. My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
It's one of those pre-shows, Wes, good and bad. Good and bad.
We made it. We're here. The show must go on.
We fired up the barbecue pre-show for the first time. Oh, I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
The grill.
For the first time and we had to feed ourselves to prepare our bodies to cover all of the
community news that we've got this week. I feel like this should be a nice, calm, relaxing
Linux Unplugged that will wander through before I head off to scale. I need something low-key
because the next week.
Take it easy, recharge.
It's going to be crazy. It's going to be crazy. Going down to Pasadena, California. So we're
going to go through just a few bits, a couple of apps, some nice community news, an update
on XFCE.
Did you know there actually is some progress on the XFCE desktop? Yes. Yes, they're nearly
to GTK3. We'll tell you all about that, their current status. Our buddy Wimpy's here with
a pretty cool option for Ubuntu Mate installers for 1804 coming up. And the crew over at KDMLive
has a killer new release that's in the works that might just give Final Cut a run for its
money.
Then we'll check in on that poll about dropping Discord and switching back to IRC, see what
the results were. And then, Wes, it's time to bring a little freedom to your vehicle.
Finally.
I've been debating this myself. Should I get one of them like, you know, Android auto dashes
because my radio needs to be replaced. It's bad. And I'm like, yeah, maybe I'll do that.
But then I don't want to be locked into like one particular hardware vendor, and they're
probably not going to update it properly, and it's probably going to be underpowered.
So I've never really pulled the trigger on like upgrading my car sound system. But friends,
if you wait long enough, the open source community always provides a solution.
So this week, we're going to talk about Crankshaft, which is a turnkey Linux distribution for
the Raspberry Pi that transforms it into an Android auto headset. All you need is a Raspberry
Pi 3 board and the official Raspberry Pi 7 inch touchscreen, which is like 60 US dollars.
And then you got a turnkey Linux distro. We'll tell you about it. Yeah. Have you heard of
Crankshaft, Wes?
No, I have not.
Well, you will hear more about it coming up. But let's start with some community news.
This has been sort of leaking out in bits and details here and there. Corbin Davenport
over at Android police.com writes that it looks like Chrome OS may soon be able to run
Linux applications in a container. Of course, you're probably thinking, well, why does that
have to do in a container? Chrome OS is based on Linux. Well, I'm sure it's many reasons,
security being one of them. It looks like this is coming from some documentation that's leaked
out. And if you go to Chrome Unboxed, they have a Chrome OS developer who uploaded two
screenshots of the container feature and what it will look like. You should get a pop up
that comes up with a description that says, would you like to develop on your Chromebook?
You can run your favorite Linux apps in command line tools seamlessly and securely. And then
it gives you a couple of prompts to install terminal.
Ooh, yeah, that I like that reminds me of the subsystem for Linux. It's like a freedom
box right there. Doesn't this kind of remind you? Yeah, it's like Google's answer to the
subsystem for Linux on Windows for Chrome OS. Does that make sense? It's like that they're
trying to be competitive with that feature on Windows. Well, I mean, it kind of targets
that splits the difference. You can still have a simple platform for most end users,
but your developers or other people that need a little bit extra, that option is there.
Is it actually usable though? That would really be my question. That's a good question. Are
Chromebooks fast enough? I don't know. Let's ask the Mumble Room. Time appropriate greetings
there, Mumble Room. Welcome to the show, guys.
G'day.
Hello.
Snuck it in there. You didn't know when I was going to do it, did you? I surprised you.
Get it out of here.
So Wimpy, what do you think of this? Do you think this would actually make Chromebooks
a viable solution? The thing that crossed my mind is students. Like my son has a Chromebook
provided by his school.
I think anything that enables people to experiment with Linux in an accessible way is a good
thing, particularly for students.
Yeah. And I could see too, like if you've got a limited budget or whatever, or it's
like again, it's provided. It just sort of opens up a whole new range of functionality.
And I wonder what the limits will be. That's really going to be the question. How far will
Google let you take this? What are they going to make available? Is it only just going to
be a couple of things? Terminal is interesting. That makes sense.
That's a big start, yeah.
Yeah. And then if it's all contained, they don't have to worry about you mucking around
with Chrome OS. So check that out. We'll have a link in the show notes. Anybody else in
the Mumbroom if you have anything to add? If you're a Chromebook user, I'd be particularly
interested.
But I'm not a Chrome OS user. I am still reluctantly an Evernote user. And this is, I don't know,
how many different Evernote clients or Evernote alternatives or Evernote killers that we have
covered on this show. But we have one more. One more because the question still comes
in. And if you're like me, you're still stuck with this thing, especially when you travel.
It's called Tusk. It's an Evernote client. And it seems to actually connect to the Evernote
backend. It's also available as a snap. They say they've improved integration with Linux.
That seems like a good thing.
That's great.
It's got some markdown sheet support. I haven't tried it myself because I still haven't decided
if I'm going to just quit Evernote cold turkey or not. But it does look pretty compelling.
And Joey over at OMG Ubuntu wrote a pretty good write up that kind of makes me want to
give it a go again. It looks good.
If you look at the video.
It is sharp looking.
Yeah.
It actually looks better than the official Evernote client. So this is almost Tusk is
almost taken to the point where it's like, I don't even want Evernote. I don't even need
them to. This looks even better than what they're done. I'm good.
And it's just a snap away.
Just a freaking snap away. Have you tried it? Wimpy, it's a snap. Aren't you obligated
to try all snaps?
In the contract.
I actually hope he's been working on that one. So I've not installed that one yet. But
then again, I don't use Evernote. So I've got no real need to.
Good on you for avoiding that trap.
I got into it like poison when mobile was brand new. And I just assumed they'd just
assume they'd eventually get something for Linux. And I was I regret that decision. But
damn, if it doesn't have some of the best OCR features, like when I'm traveling, I can
take pictures of signs of places that I need to note for like show reference or just for
travel purposes. That is extremely valuable for me.
So maybe Tusk will solve that. We'll see. Maybe I'll give it a go once I get back because
I'm probably going to end up using Evernote on my phone while I'm traveling. It almost
always happens, you know, reservation stuff.
It's just easy. It's there. It works.
I tell you what, Wes, tell you what. Let's talk about something else. Something to pick
me back up. Improving laptop battery life. This is some work that the Fedora project
has been putting in. And they've outlined some of the ways that they're trying to enable
various hardware power saving features by default in Fedora. So one of the things that
they're implementing, and maybe we're going to see this in other distributions too, I
would assume, but right now Fedora is the one that's talking about it. They're going
to make a new satellite power management policy, which actually mirrors the Windows defaults.
Surprisingly is often a good way to go when it comes to some of this hardware power management
stuff. Enable Intel HDA codec power saving by default with a one second timeout, which
saves 0.4 watts of power on an idle laptop. That's a huge amount really. And by the way,
the satellite power management could save up to 1.5 watts of power on an idle laptop.
That's a sweet deal.
That's a big deal right there. And then enable USB auto suspend for USB Bluetooth receivers
by default. We'll see how that goes. Which could also save 0.4 watts. And I like that
they actually put numbers on this stuff. When you add all that up though, it could be a
pretty decent battery savings on Fedora, which could really kind of make the distro stand
out. And I like that they're enunciating all of the stuff they're doing over here on the
Wiki.
And that stuff takes tuning, and so it's nice to be explicit about it.
Look at this too. They have this table, I guess, of the SATA power link management policy
changes testing. And so they have Dell laptops, and HP laptops, and Lenovo laptops, and Asus
Zenbooks on here as well. And it's legit. It's pretty legitimate. So they have comparisons
before and after. So I'll just pink out. Let's say the ThinkPad T400, for example, we're
using an SSD. Before their tweaks on idle, it was sitting there taking 13.6 watts of
power. After their tweaks, which will just be enabled by default, idle, it drops to 11.8.
So it goes from 13.6 to 11.8 watts. And that could really translate into more minutes on
a battery.
And some of the changes are less dramatic. Some of them are even more dramatic. Some
of them are barely noticeable. One of them that kind of jumps out at me is the Elite
Book, the HP Elite Book 8540W. It goes from 18.8 to 17.9. You know, a point actually.
It's decent actually. They're all noticeable. None of them are actually anything to scoff
at.
They're all savings all take, that's for sure.
They tried on the Lenovo ThinkPad X1 carbon second gen. They tried to enable some of the
SATA link power management stuff, and it produced data corruption.
Whoopsie.
Whoa.
That's a nice thing to know about ahead of time.
So don't go just playing with this stuff maybe. Don't go just trying that on your own distro
to see if it's going to...
Or at least not with data you care about.
But it'd be really interesting to run Fedora 28 on a laptop and then run 27 and see if
I could actually just perceive a difference, not have to measure, but can I just perceive
it?
Yeah, does it feel different to the end user?
Yeah. And what's nice about this is it doesn't require a bunch of crazy software they have
to pre-install. It's not requiring a whole bunch of new packages on the ISO.
Just some new good defaults.
Yeah. And people will talk about, hey, if you want great battery life, use Fedora for
at least a little while. So that'll be good for them too.
You just said it right there. So now people are seeing it.
It's being said. It's being said. There's some great news too for those of you that
instead of installing Fedora 28 are going to be installing Ubuntu 18.04. But we're just
talking about the future releases here, aren't we? On Ubuntu 18.04, it appears that you will
now be able to switch snap package channels. I'm probably screwing that up a little bit,
but my layman's understanding is one of the features of snap packages is that you can
have like a beta channel and a release channel. And now the GNOME software app, or I think
it's just called software, will let you choose which channel you want to subscribe to.
I think I'm getting that all right. Winby, do you want to errata any of that?
Yeah, yeah, you've got that about right. So by default, there are four channels. There's
stable, which is self explanatory, candidate, which is where developers will put their release
candidates, betas for betas and edge, which is typically what you'd hook up to your CI
system. So after every commit or your daily or nightly builds, they would all land in
edge so you can do your integration testing. And now what you can do in GNOME software
in 1804 is when you look at the details for a snap in software center, it has a label
there for the track or rather the channel that it's currently installed from, which
by and large would be stable. And if you click on that, it will produce a list of the other
channels that are available to you. So if you want to test the current beta or you want
to get the latest crack from edge, then you can switch that and switch those channels.
But what it also enables you to do is some of the people that are publishing in the store
are using tracks, which are in addition to those channels. So for example, JetBrains
have their early access program. So you can access the early access versions of all of
their products through their EAP track. And likewise with Skype, you can access their
insiders builds. So if you want to test out the really, really latest stuff, then you
can also switch to those tracks through GNOME software as well now.
That is really cool that JetBrains is doing that. The aspect that I like about it from
an end user's perspective is it's tidier when I search for an app because instead of getting
three or four entries for Slack or Mumble, it's just one entry. And then I can tack on
which channel I want during installation.
What level of risk you're prepared to take as a user.
And so if I say do an edge release of something, that doesn't necessarily mean it's containerized
or not, it's sandboxed or not. It could be an edge release and still be sandboxed.
Correct. The edge is just the release. They're just labels. So it's whatever the developer
feels comfortable inputting in those channels.
What is the terminology for one that isn't sandboxed? Is it legacy or what's the term
that when you're doing installs?
There's classic, which is it's without any confinement. And then there is also dev mode,
which you can't publish in the stable channel. And dev mode is kind of a reduced confinement
model whilst you're iterating on your snap and scaffolding it together.
Classic I think is what I was thinking of. And so now you don't even have to worry about
what was the syntax or how do I add it to the install command. Now it'll just be exposed
via the GUI for users installing software, which is great.
Yeah, it makes it seem much more first class.
Yeah, so that way when you know it's available like I just did, but I couldn't quite remember
the syntax, that's perfect for that. That's where that kind of stuff is really nice. And
is that, do you know an upstream thing Wimpy or is that unique to Ubuntu?
It's part of the snap plugin for GNOME software.
Ah, of course. So it's implemented at the plugin level. That is. That actually is. You
got to say, GNOME software is actually keeping up. When it was thought up, we weren't talking
about flat packs and snaps, were we? And in the past, I could have seen that having to
be completely revamped. I'm not going to say it's my favorite way to install software or
find software or even look at software, but I got to give them credit for the fact that
they haven't had to throw out the entire thing to support flat packs and snaps.
That's an open source win.
Yay for plugins, I guess. All right, Wes. I know you're not a big XFCE user. Have you
ever been an XFCE user?
Oh yeah, back in the day.
Oh, were you?
Oh, well, that's nice. That's nice. I was, too.
It's been probably five years now.
Yeah, same. Yeah, I'd say it's been about five years. Yeah, I actually used it quite
a bit for a while. It's a meme, in a way, in the Linux community about how long it takes
for XFCE to ship. They've been working on 4.14, I think, for three years. The big part
of 4.14 is the transition to GTK3. Don't think of XFCE as one monolithic thing, either. Think
of it as a set of many different software components. You have Thunar for the file management.
You have the window manager. You have the panels. You have the settings daemon. You
have the power manager, the session initializer itself. Then, of course, you have the XF Desktop,
which is the program that's responsible for managing desktop icons and backgrounds. There's
lots of subcomponents. It goes on, actually. There's lots of other components. 4.14 has
really been a process of porting everything to GTK3 Plus instead of GTK2 and using GDBus
instead of DBus Lib and then using symbolic icons for all the panel plug-ins and removing
depreciated widgets from code, old crap in the code. As they've moved along, they've
made some good progress. They have ported many things to GTK3, including Thunar, the
file manager, and the panel, and the power settings, and the settings manager itself,
and the desktop session manager. But there is some low-hanging fruit that doesn't even
have maintainers, like the calendar application, or the archive manager, or the CD burning
application, or the volume control. So there's a few things that just, they're not even getting
started yet. So that's a bit rough. There's 118 open bugs in XF Desktop, 119 in XFCE4
Session, 206 in XFCE4 Settings, and it goes on. So they're behind here. And I think what
my concern is, is you're dealing with 15 contributors, essentially, who are working on their free
time to port these projects, to get them ready. And there's no real big corporate interest
in XFCE. There's no Red Hat, or Canonical, or SUSE behind XFCE. And there's not any real
big major distro that's even shipping it as its default desktop. So they're kind of
let underdog here. It is just a passion project for these people. And there's no escaping
the elephant in the room that is GTK4. I mean, like, it's getting close. By the time they
get XFCE4.14 out, GTK4 could really be close to stable. And then they have to start again.
I don't know if it's going to be the same amount of work. But that's to say nothing
of Wayland support.
Yeah, I mean, XFCE has a lot, there's a lot going on. It's not, you know, it has a lot
of functionality as a desktop. It's not a bad desktop. I'm sure there's a sizable code
based support.
Yeah, it's hard for a project like that. It really is tough. And I know that we have folks
in the audience that love it. You know, Joe from Linux Action News and Late Night Linux,
it's his number one driver. And I've used it myself.
I mean, the pace is concerning, but it's nice to at least see some details of the process
that it is, it seems like they have at least semi structured way to go about doing it and
to work does progress.
Yeah, yeah. Anybody in the Mumba room an XFCE occasional user or a full time user? I'm betting
no.
Yeah, I don't I don't use the desktop per se. Yeah, but I do. I use XFCE for terminal.
Yeah, it's great for that. Yeah, or like X2GO. But honestly, I think I think Wimpy has played
a big role in making it irrelevant for me, because MATE has gotten so compelling and
especially Ubuntu MATE over the last few years.
And so where I used XFCE in the past, I now use MATE. So it's kind of your fault, Wimpy.
Well, I'm sorry. I'm sorry for the XFCE project for that. But I would like to point out that,
you know, it took MATE an awfully long time to port from GTK 2 to GTK 3. The only reason
it wasn't so obvious is we were maintaining a GTK 2 and GTK 3 code base in parallel during
that transition, which to some extent probably delayed things. But for as long as I've been
involved in MATE, which is getting on for six years now, we were doing that migration
to GTK 3. And I think as a team, we're only satisfied that we've really kind of got there
with the last release, which was last month, in terms of the GTK 3 stuff, in that now every
if def rule in the code for special casing different versions of GTK have been removed
because we're now just coalesced around GTK 3.2.2, which is the last stable release of
GTK 3.
You're right.
You know what that said?
Yeah, go on.
Well, no, I wanted to finish.
You said that, you know, the next thing is GTK 4.
Yeah.
There is no obligation to immediately start, you know, porting to GTK 4. GTK 3, everything's
just landed on GTK 3, even things like Chrome, Firefox, LibreOffice, you know, those things
have only just, you know, within the last, you know, months even, you know, LibreOffice
a bit longer, but, you know, within months have started to properly take their hints
from GTK 3.
Right.
So I think it's going to be some time and there's even, you know, the bigger projects
like GIMP, you know, that have been around forever, they're still GTK 2.
So they still, you know, catch up to be done, you know, all over the place.
Yeah, that's a great point.
That is a GTK 3 will be a stable target for, you know, desktops and application developers
for some time to come.
Even in the world of flat packs and snaps, does it perhaps matter a little bit less if,
you know, you, if you've got an application in theory that needs GTK 3.22, you should
be able to ship that for quite a while as a flat pack or a snap, even if my desktop
is GTK 4 at that point.
Yeah, absolutely.
But I think you'll see GTK 3 and GTK 4 living alongside each other in distros in the future
in the same way that we have GTK 2 and GTK 3 living along side each other, you know,
and have done for many years now.
That makes that makes a lot of sense.
You know what?
I so they're not talking about Wayland.
But I don't see I don't see Monte talking a lot about Wayland.
I've seen you make a few hints that, you know, in a recent 1804 post, I think you said don't
don't get too excited by some of the Wayland work in there.
It's not what you think I think was something similar to that wording.
Yeah, we've been having well, the Wayland, the Wayland references that you may have seen
in the change logs were actually to explicitly turn on x Wayland for some of the applications.
So for people that were installing the Marte applications in a genome session, for example,
which was, you know, Wayland by default on Fedora, and you know, on Ubuntu 1710, it meant
that those applications would actually work.
But they are is not a full, you know, Wayland implementation, it just enables x Wayland
to step in and take over.
But we have had our, our upstream conversations with the core Marte team, just this week about
our road to Wayland.
We've got some more discussions to have there, but we're starting to form a plan about how
we're going to go about that.
Is your sense that it is more work than the port to GTK 3?
Yes, although we may get lucky in terms of how we can go about doing this, in that there
may be some people who can can assist us some do some heavy lifting, as it were, yeah, yeah,
yeah.
So in the future, when when that's all fleshed out, I will, I will come back on and explain
more about that one.
I think that's gonna be extremely interesting to watch, because I think that could be useful
for other projects as well.
All right.
Well, good stuff.
Well, don't go too far.
I want to keep talking about Marte for just a moment.
But I do want to take a break and think digital ocean.
So standby while we mentioned that I did get I did get this in last week, this great deal
we have digital ocean.com.
You go to do dot co slash unplugged.
That's the world I go to right now, because I am pretty sure that's the best way to get
the special $100 credit offer.
The digital ocean is offering the Jupiter broadcasting audience.
It's a limited time offer.
And I believe it lasts for 60 days once you apply it to your account.
Now, this is incredible, because, honestly, in the past, the traditional and it's gonna
what I'll go back to is the $10 credit, which is legitimately enough to get real work done
for like two months on digital ocean.
It's awesome.
So the $100 credit blows my mind and build anything you want.
Yeah, and I think this is what they're thinking, because it's true infrastructure on demand.
Everything's SSDs, eight data centers all over the world, a killer dashboard to manage
all of it, and then an API to automate it when you're ready to go or just grab some
open source code that does it already.
But here's where I think they're going with the $100 credit is they got a couple of new
types of droplets that are killer.
So they got a $15 a month one where you can mix and match the different resources, which
depend on what you're doing, maybe you don't need just work out.
Yeah, maybe you need more RAM, and you don't necessarily need a lot of local disk, or maybe
you need a ton of CPU for something, and you just mix and match as you need it.
And they also, there are standard droplets, which you can get for $5 a month starting
there.
They just got even more competitive.
They have more everything, more everything, and if you have an existing one, you can upgrade
it for free.
They're crushing it.
It's great.
Digitalocean.com or do.co slash unplugged.
I've been a customer for, I think, four years now, which blows my mind.
We have large parts of the Jupyter Broadcasting infrastructure, which run on DigitalOcean
24-7, and that means I am now down to one server on premise, which is just a large storage
free NAS server now.
When we first started at Jupyter Broadcasting, we brought in an i7 rig with lots of memory
and lots of local disk and an NFS disk, and we ran a bunch of systems in a VM, Proxmox,
I mean, I've told you guys about this all on the show.
And over the years, it is so much simpler, so much faster, and honestly, long term, it's
costing me way less to run on DigitalOcean than having to spend thousands and thousands
of dollars on local infrastructure.
And the nice thing is we can build for what we need today and then easily expand it.
I've said enough.
Really, all you need to know is do.co slash unplugged, $100 credit if you're a new customer.
Hot off the presses right there, Wes.
Limited time offer.
Take advantage of it because I was negligent in telling you about it soon enough.
Also, if you want to get yourself some web mail set up, I'm a fan of the Roundcube.
That's one of my more, I think it's like, I don't know what else you could compare it
to, actually.
It's the closest to something like a Gmail or like a commercial web mail client that
you can run and host yourself.
Roundcube, it just connects to your mail server over IMAP and SMTP, so you don't even necessarily
have to host your own mail server.
You could connect it to just another IMAP server that you have or that you may be already
using.
Roundcube, they have a tutorial on DigitalOcean for how to set it up.
I don't actually know.
Don't tell them I said this, but I don't think there's anything necessarily too DigitalOcean
specific maybe than just the very beginning of installing the computer.
But the rest would work if you just had your own system.
Yeah, it's just great documentation.
Yeah.
Or go spin up a VPS over on DigitalOcean.
They call them droplets.
Put up Roundcube and then point it to an IMAP server that you've been using.
And now you just got yourself a web mail that you're hosting that somebody else isn't slurping
down.
That's pretty great.
do.co.
slash unplugged.
All right.
So, Wimpy, I was talking before the show with you, and you started describing the minimal
installer work that you're doing for Ubuntu MATE, and I thought, okay, yeah, that sounds
decent.
But the more you talked about it, I started thinking, geez, this might be the most popular
implementation.
This is sounding really, really good.
So let's back up a little bit and maybe just a super quick refresher on what the minimal
install is.
And I guess maybe some of the work you had to do to get it into Ubuntu MATE, because
I guess you don't just inherit that, you have to make some choices and implement some decisions.
Yeah.
Tell me a little bit about it.
So this is piggybacking on the work of my colleagues, Didrox and Lainey, who have landed
the minimal install capability in the Ubiquity installer.
So I just happened to be poking around in the Ubiquity code on an unrelated matter yesterday
evening, and I noticed that this feature had landed.
So I contacted Lainey and said, so how do I turn this on for Ubuntu MATE?
And he said, oh, it's easy.
You just create this file and you put the things in it that you want to be removed from
your install.
So I did that work for Ubuntu MATE last night, and then the nightly images ran.
So it's built for the flavors to use as well.
It was purpose built for that.
It's not just unique to just upstream Ubuntu.
No, any of the flavors can take advantage of it.
So I'll just go into some text because I know some of the flavor maintainers listen to the
podcast.
So what you do is you modify your seeds and the seeds are where you list what your distribution
is comprised of.
So the applications that are in the core image, in the base image.
And you add a new file in there and it's simply called desktop.minimal-remove.
And in that file, you basically list all of the packages that you want to be removed from
the default install.
And if that file exists, when Ubiquity runs, it will now present a new option in the installer.
So in the install screens, if you've installed Ubuntu before, you will have seen a screen
where it asks you if you want to install updates while it's installing, and if you want to
install additional codecs on that screen, you'll see a new option, which is do you want
the minimal install?
And it describes the minimal install as the desktop and utilities and browser only.
Oh yeah.
I mean, now when you're combining lightweight Mote with a minimal install, so it's just
Firefox, basic desktop tools, core utilities, no VLC, no Thunderbird, no calculator?
Well, the calculator is part of the core Mote desktop, so you get the file manager and the
text editor and the document viewer and the image viewer, but you don't get LibreOffice,
you don't get Thunderbird, you don't get VLC, you don't get Rhythmbox, all of that extra
stuff, you don't get transmission.
So everything additional to the core desktop is effectively removed.
So you get a very trim, simple system.
And I was thinking to myself, who would use this and why would you use it?
And I've heard a few people say, oh, well, I like to curate my own desktop experience.
I know what applications I want, so they would want that.
But I was thinking to myself, how would I use it?
And I was thinking, well, I've got one machine that I use specifically for gaming now, and
I would choose the minimal option on that machine.
So I just get the base stuff and then I can slap Steam on top of that, and I've just got
a real trim machine for running Steam or you could create your own Kodi boxes in a similar
way as well.
Yeah, I do like that.
I was just thinking, too, you could absolutely see it as a workstation OS, where maybe you
go to work and you install Slack and you have to install Chrome and maybe even Skype and
all of these things that just are kind of, I don't know, they're just applications now
that you can snap install or go get the...
Have a real minimal base.
Or you can get the devs.
Yeah.
The software boutique actually makes some of that easier on MATE, but yeah, I really
like that because I'm generally going to Ubuntu MATE for a minimal lean, lean, mean fighting
machine.
Yeah.
But what it retains is all of the underlying hardware support.
So anything you need for your network devices to function, that's all still included.
Anything you need for Bluetooth and audio, that's all still included.
So it's just that layer of applications on the top, but it's down to each flavor maintainer
to choose what they want to remove.
So there's no prescribed list.
The list in Ubuntu MATE is different than the list in Ubuntu, for example.
And so the question that's coming up, before we go too far off that, is how is this different
than an install script that just is like a different set of packages to install?
How is this different than an install script is essentially what the chat room is asking
in IRC.
How it's different from an install, where it's the opposite of an install script.
It's an uninstall script, essentially.
I like that.
Yeah.
Because it's an image that's getting deployed to the hard drive, right?
It's getting based on the live environment.
Yeah.
So the image that's on the ISO, there is a squashFS file system, and that is effectively
put on your hard disk.
And then at the end of that process, there are already some packages that get removed.
The installer itself, for example.
So Ubiquity, the installer, removes itself as part of the cleanup of the installation.
So what this minimal install does is it tags itself on to that piece of the code that's
already there to build out a bigger list of what should be removed.
And then it rattles through that list and removes anything that the maintainer has identified
as, this is stuff you don't need in a minimal install.
Okay.
Interesting.
That makes sense.
So it's the opposite of an install script.
And this will be landing in 1804.
It's already essentially the work's done, right?
It landed in the daily images yesterday.
Oh!
Yeah.
Fantastic.
It's just down to each of the flavors now to create their minimal remove file in their
seeds.
And then they can take advantage of that function as well.
That's really great.
It's funny that we're just getting to it now, don't you think?
In a way?
Like, why haven't we had this for years?
It's interesting because before I worked at Canonical, I did some work with the Xubuntu
team, where we were trying to achieve precisely this.
Because we wanted minimal installations, and in fact, Xubuntu make their own set of, I
think they call them core images available, and have done for a couple of years now, where
they effectively have an ISO, which is the minimal ISO.
So it's, you know, what I've just described, but already packed in an ISO.
And we did some work to try and land that in a way that everyone could have two ISOs.
So you can have an Ubuntu Mate, I think we called them base, an Ubuntu Mate base ISO,
and the full fat ISO.
But for reasons people were busy, that never got any traction.
And now, you know, now we have this, which is, I think, quite an elegant solution because
now there's still one ISO to download, but you can use it in two ways.
So did this ball get rolling from what you probably understand, because I know it's not
directly work that you were involved in?
Did Rock's probably better to ask, but did this get started based on some of the feedback
that people, like people, I like Chrome, or I prefer MPV.
And so is this sort of a middle ground?
I think you're well connected with did Rock's, and you should ask him that question, because
I don't know the origin story of how this came to be.
Because it is funny that it's just showing up now in 1804.
I mean, I'm thankful for it.
But I think this, to a degree, is probably why some people have chosen other distributions.
I'm sure not by a very large percentage.
But I bet there's people in our audience that have decided to go a different route just
because of the package selection.
I mean, that was what drove people to Ubuntu, too, at the same time.
Yeah.
And you've got both options now.
You know, those people that like a very specific desktop experience can do that.
You know, for some people, all you actually need is the minimal install, because you can
do everything in a browser.
You've basically created a Chromebook at that point.
And now you can install containers, or applications in containers, and that's all cyclical, or
whatever it is, circular, what is it?
What am I looking for, Wes?
Cyclical!
Cyclical, that's what it is, cyclical.
You got there yourself.
Well, Wimpy, thank you for telling us all about that.
You know me, I just love hearing about that.
I hope other people do, too, because even if you're not an Ubuntu Monte user, I think
this stuff is fascinating.
Because right here, I'm sitting on a Plasma Neon desktop, but yet, this, I love hearing
about.
I love the thought behind it and all of it, so I really always appreciate when you come
out here and tell us all that stuff.
You're welcome.
I don't know if anybody out there has had a chance to try Cadian Live recently.
A lot of people ask about video editing still.
We get a lot of questions, and I just sort of, I kind of punt, and I punt, and I punt.
But it's getting legitimate with Cadian Live.
I'd like to know if people who are doing actual serious amounts of video editing under Linux,
like, you know, like Ven Stone, who edits, you know, I think he's doing two shows a week
under Linux, but I think he uses OpenShot, like an old version of OpenShot, because he's
a madman, Ven.
You're a madman.
That's crazy.
So I don't know if, I'd like to know if somebody like Ven, or there's probably not as many
people that do as much editing as he does, but on a regular basis, they're putting out
complex, long content on Linux.
Have you tried the new Cadian Live, because this, to me, is hitting a lot of what draws
me to Final Cut, and this is getting, I don't know, maybe it's also the fact, probably is
a bit of the fact that I've been on a plasma kick recently, too, and this is a cute application,
so it also looks really great on my desktop.
But I downloaded the app image, yes, it's an app image, so you can, it's kind of a convoluted
process.
I will link to the fastest way for you to get the app image, because they don't just
link to it directly.
They make you attend this cafe session, and you can find a link to a text file that has
a list of the mirrors, which will then land you on this page that I have found.
So I will link this to you if you want to try it and give me feedback, because I'm going
to experiment a little bit with it, but I'm honestly just not doing as much video as I
was in the past, so I'm not the best candidate.
But it looks like a super great release.
One of the things that I really like about Cadian Live is they have this really steady
approach, and they've been like on this, we do, like, so for example, 17.12 series has
just been constant, solid, fix this little thing, solve this bug, come up with a solution
for that, minor bug fix stuff.
And so you can just say, well, I'm on this branch, that's what I get, and I really like
that about that, too.
So 18.04 is the next version, which I don't think is necessarily synced up to any Ubuntu
server, but it's sort of that same versioning system.
And they are working out the rough edges right now.
They've published it as a app image, which I'll link to.
And if you're out there and want to give them some feedback, if I was going to bet on a
horse right now for getting really good approachable video editing on desktop Linux, as much as
I respect Jonathan and all of the hard, continuing work he's doing into OpenShot over the years,
the horse I would bet on right now is KDE and Live, not Lightworks, not all of the other
ones that we send in.
It's looking really nice.
It's KDE and Live.
Yeah, there's a lot of different ones.
There's, like, a clip editor one, you know, but it's just, yeah.
So anyways, if you want to help what I think is potentially our best hope for good video
editing.
And we need one.
Yeah, I just, it's called, the link in the show notes will be called KDE Experience Freedom
with an exclamation mark, KDE dash Experience Freedom with an exclamation mark.
That's the link to look for because that's the typical kind of communication you get
from the KDE group out there.
They just, they're not so good with the way they phrase things or the, that kind of, I
love them.
It's like you haven't invested in freedom enough over there.
I know.
I need to invest in, I need to invest in freedom as their website tells me, and I need to experience
freedom with an exclamation mark.
I'm feeling pretty free right now.
I do appreciate that about it.
I do appreciate that.
That may be the new air freshener, but I don't think so.
I'm feeling pretty, pretty free.
So we'll have that linked in the show notes if you want to check that out.
Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged.
That's where to go to support the show and sign up for a free seven day trial, free seven
day trial.
What's better than free?
Freedom.
And maybe sometimes like a cold drink on a really.
Oh, that's way better.
It's really good.
But free, like that, if that drink was free, it's even better.
You see what I'm saying?
Like it can't get better.
So seven day free trial Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged.
It's a platform to learn about Linux and all of this stuff around Linux.
And now the kind of stuff that gets you hired.
That's a really good.
That's another really nice thing about Linux Academy.
I would use this for ongoing training as well as getting hired.
Think of it as whatever you need to get done if you need to learn more about a nitty gritty
thing around Linux or if you need to learn about AWS and OpenStack and Azure and all
of these things.
This is also perhaps the best solution for you.
They have some really, really great and they're frequently adding new content to the AWS stuff.
I'm really impressed with like their maniacs over there with the content and the way they
get that is they hire full time instructors, people that are really familiar with this
stuff and they just sit there and they churn out this stuff in a way that I don't know.
They got the system like they build a process where they come up with something that's really
applicable to people, that's really going to add value for something to learn about.
Then they build out the best way to do it.
They build into the system where you can choose the distribution you want to learn from.
They keep testing it out at each point then they start testing it more to get like kind
of feedback and they've reached out to me a few times on this to see if like I want
to try out a new system and then they roll it out and iterate on it in a way that keeps
your subscription valuable and then they add new content and they go back and they keep
the old stuff fresh and then they're ready to help you whenever you get stuck because
those instructors are full time.
Like this is a machine now and it's just been getting them a ton of industry credibility
and you can get hands on scenario based labs, a course scheduler for when you're busy and
they have all kinds of content that really is great for when you're like just want to
hone in on one single thing or you're ready to take on a whole certification course.
And so that means when you've got a really busy life or when you've got time to take
your career to the next level, they've got content to serve you.
Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged.
Go there, sign up for a free seven day trial and a big thank you to Linux Academy.
Seven day trial free.
So great I hit my mic because my hands are dancing around.
You're so excited.
I really was.
Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged.
All right you crazy sons of bitches, I can't be dragged around like this anymore.
Oh we're going to talk about this.
So I asked this really stupid question last week, well actually it started when I asked
the question would you like to switch to Discord and everybody said yes.
And now here we are, what, three, four months into this thing?
Maybe a little more than that?
Six months?
I don't know.
It feels like ages.
It feels like it's been 25 years.
And I actually don't mind Discord.
I've been hanging out in other communities and you know what I like is the communities
that don't have to waffle like this.
That's what I like.
It's just you don't waffle, you don't move it, you just invest and you build.
And every time I feel like we change direction, you spill off some people, you also gain new
people.
So it's got its pros and its cons.
But we went out to a vote and we said should we switch from Discord back to IRC or just
hang tight, stick it out with Discord for the long haul.
And each has its pros and cons, IRC's, well it's like plumbing at this point.
It's pretty universal and it's a classic.
It's just like amongst our community, it's got a bit of a barrier of entry to people
outside the open source community but it's a staple in the open source community.
Now Discord has the advantage of a network effect.
It also has a bunch of other fancy features that are more modern like they just have their
own mobile client and they support emojis and embedded imagery and Twitter previews
and all this stuff.
All the fanciness.
Yeah.
That if you were to say drop down on the planet today in 2018 and try to join a community,
you would just kind of expect that they might just be able to do this.
They might just have this.
So I wasn't really sure what to do.
We were thinking behind the scenes, dramatically, that it would be easier for some of the things
we want to automate if it was IRC because we're still trying to come up with this perfect
cloud OBS setup where we would ingest an IRC stream and automatically generate a video
and send that out on the video stream and all of that.
But it just doesn't seem like that would be super easy to do with Discord.
It would be pretty easy to do with IRC.
So the vote went out and it was pretty clear IRC by a 79% vote and Discord had a 21% vote.
We're not talking hundreds of numbers here, but that's a, you know, usually that's how
it sticks.
Those are usually pretty indicative, representative I believe would be the term.
So that's a 79% win, right?
That's huge.
That's a big margin of win for IRC.
That's big.
People have spoken, I suppose.
The thing is, is we go back to IRC, we go back and we just...
Right, like does Discord just die?
Is it left to wither?
What?
Well, I don't think you got to shut it down.
I mean, the main thing I'm thinking about is like, if you want to, it's like the primary
chat room.
So it's what's on the live stream.
It's where people idle the most or they're having an active conversation.
I don't know.
I don't have answers to that.
I don't like any of this, but I want to do what the audience likes in this regard because
it's a tool for them.
So Virtual Lug, you guys get first say since you're here, you're in the voice chat.
You get first say.
Does anybody have a strong opinion on this one way or the other?
I'd love to hear some input on this because I'm really, I just want to use whatever people
like.
Yeah, well, well, to me, I would see the Discord is like the, I would say the Reddit chat versus
the RC being the live stream.
And also, since there are very few, since there are very few people who go to the live
stream to participate, I mean, there are more people that are coming in a day, we got months
and years to come, such as myself that came in recently.
But it's, I would say IRC would fill that niche pretty well with the live stream.
And plus, there are some clients that do support some of the newer features that you mentioned,
so.
Hmm.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, I'm going to leave the vote up for a little bit longer while I think about it.
I'm not in a huge rush to do anything, and I got to go to scale.
But it's on my mind.
I want to do what people like.
So and you know, meanwhile, the Telegram group's going solid.
So yeah.
They're up in their own universe.
That is good, really.
That's kind of a nice thing.
That's just like, well, we don't care.
Yeah.
If you want to get on that, jupyterbroadcasting.com slash telegram to join our telegram group.
There's my quarterly plug for that.
All right, Wes.
Well, that's not actually what we're.
No, it's not.
I guess that's on my mind.
Like I said, this is a meandering episode.
I think it's on everyone's mind.
Let's talk about Crankshaft.
This is pretty, pretty great.
Now I'm going to, I'll play a little bit of the demo for you.
Just I'm going to do a couple of bits of it because it's a little rough.
But just to give you an idea of what it's like.
So you download this image.
You write it to the SD card.
You toss it in your Raspberry Pi.
You hook up the $60 touch screen.
And okay, so in this video, I just want to talk real quick about the capability of open
auto and how it's working in the alpha version of Crankshaft right now.
And let's start.
This is just a Raspberry Pi 3B.
And so he goes through and demos the functionality of this thing in it.
Once he gets it up and running, it just looks like Android auto completely with your playback
controls, your Google Now cards.
It's communicating with his Android device.
He just makes a phone call through it.
He can see the battery life of his phone.
He can use navigation.
That looks pretty handy.
But actually, there he's using Pocket Cast to listen to Radiolab.
I kind of want to do this in my truck.
You know what I'm talking about because my screen's all screwed up.
Yeah.
I mean, you're a perfect candidate for it.
I know.
If somebody has any experience with this, you got to let me know because I'm tempted
to do this.
We just need the touch screen.
I need the screen.
Yeah.
I need to pick up the screen.
And then you'd have to figure out a way to install the dash, which is not my strength,
I got to say.
But it's called Crankshaft.
And that was a developer there who you heard in the video.
It's just a project just by him.
It's just his thing.
And it's admittedly alpha.
But come on, it's going to be pretty cool.
I think Android Auto is fairly baked and it's using, I think, Raspbian for the distribution.
And there's a pretty active amount of people on the GitHub talking about it.
It's nice to be able to play in that space at all and maybe even have a system that actually
works and could be useful.
Yeah, and the main thing that I wanted to avoid with something like this was, and I
was thinking like a Carputer, I've been thinking about that for a couple of months.
I haven't really, really, the only reason I didn't go with a Carputer is in the couple
of months that I've been sort of debating what to do, I have found that I am perfectly
happy just doing everything on my phone and having it go through the Bluetooth audio.
And I don't really need my radio because I'm not listening to radio and I don't listen
to anything through the radio other than my phone now.
So I thought, well, could I just get by with the phone?
But the thing that this offers is A, your phone's still usable, but B, it puts it up
on a bigger screen with more limited functionality that's focused for when you're driving and
for like the navigation and the messages and stuff like that.
I think I would prefer that and the ability to do search and stuff.
So hello there.
Who was that?
Dang.
Now, would you prefer a Carputer with a touch screen or would you prefer one of those laptop
mounts?
That would be the way that would be the way Noah would go.
Noah's got one of those in his Jeep, like one of those cop laptop mounts.
Noah is such a gearhead, man.
You know what?
I tell you what, I don't know.
I feel like that's too fiddly.
See, that's what I'm liking about the Android Auto here on the Raspberry Pi.
If you could get it mounted well, it could be out of the way, in the dash.
It's like a distilled user interface that's simplified for while you're driving.
It's less cluttered.
And going to laptops, kind of like the opposite direction of that.
Go ahead.
I mean, you can use the Android Auto app to simulate this in order to get a feel for the
Android Auto interface.
Oh, yeah.
That's another thing.
Really, I already have the Raspberry Pi 3, I think.
Isn't there one around here somewhere?
There is one around here.
Unless I've got to put it into use somewhere.
So I already have that part.
I just need the screen, and then it's sort of a low-cost test.
It's pretty great that this guy is...
Oh, by the way, that is getcrankshaft.com.
I should have said the URL sooner.
Sorry about that.
Getcrankshaft.com is where you go.
If anybody is going to scale, scale 16X, let me know if you've got something like that
down there, because I want to see it.
If you bring your car, let me see it.
I want to see that.
That'd be pretty cool.
I want to give a quick mention, too, speaking of scale, I've been talking about scale in
the new relaunched Tech Talk today, mentioned that last week.
We've now posted two fricking episodes since last week's Linux Unplugged.
What?
Wow.
Yeah.
And there's some nostalgia, goodness, if you're a Linux action show former listener, there's
some nostalgia, goodness, in episode 262, techtalk.today was where you find those, techtalk.today.
And I'll be covering my journey to scale in that crap, up in that S, as they say.
I'm really happy with the way those two episodes have turned out.
It's been a bit of a creative endeavor, but I've enjoyed it.
And it's gotten an itch, I had that rash right there I wanted to scratch, so I've been able
to scratch that.
It always feels good.
Yeah.
And it gives me a spot to put a bunch of content in scale, like the trip there and meeting
people and all that stuff.
And we get Tech Talk back for a brief little minute here.
Yeah.
For at least 10 episodes.
So, season one, and we were two episodes in, so if you haven't gotten on board yet, they're
shorter, too.
They're about 20 minutes, so go to techtalk.today.
Really easy, yeah.
Ride this hype train with us.
Easy peasy.
If you want to catch up on two, it's a 40-minute podcast, and it's nice and tight.
I hope people like it.
I hope people like it, because I'm going to put all I can into it for the 10 episodes
I'm going to do, and then I'm going to take a break, and I'm going to be done, and that's
going to be wonderful.
Wimpy has inspired me.
You've taught me well, Wimpy.
And the value of this is negative.
You're welcome.
No, it's not.
I appreciate it.
That's season idea.
Only, I may never come back, I think.
Right, yeah.
That might be the... My twist might be, last time I put the show on hold, it was on hold
for two years, so.
You never can tell.
You never know.
All right.
Well, guess what?
We're just about done here.
We've been screwing around here, but this is just our low-key episode before I go to
scale.
So next week, I will be at scale with Noah, and I'm pretty sure we'll just do the show
live from there.
We'll just do a regular episode, but we'll happen to be at scale.
I don't know if we'll... We might have a few interviews or something.
If we get something good, we'll put it in the show.
So you'll be here?
Yeah.
Wes is going to come into studio and try to run all this crap on your own.
Good luck with that.
Jeez, Louise.
We'll probably have an episode.
Let's just say that.
We'll be down there throwing our crap together while you're in here trying to remember how
to turn all this stuff back on, and one way or another, we should end up with a show next
week.
Oh, yeah.
Speaking of shows coming back, rumor has it the Ubuntu podcast is coming back, so go get
more wimpy.
That's exciting.
Yup.
The Ubuntu podcast is on the return.
The rumor is true.
Ah.
And if you want more Wes Payne, why not a little TechSnap?
Dot Systems for the TechSnap program, which is back and better than ever.
If I don't say so myself, TechSnap.Systems, and at Wes Payne on Twitter.
I'm at Chris LAS.
The network is at Jupiter Signal.
Stick around for Ask Noah if you're on the live stream.
Noah's coming up.
Yeah, definitely.
He's got a pretty special guest.
Pretty, pretty special.
I won't say anymore, but that's coming up soon.
You show up on Tuesdays, and you stick around for Linux Unplugged, you join the virtual
plug, hang out in our chat room, and then sit back and enjoy the Ask Noah show.
You could even call in and ask him a question.
That's how that kind of thing works.
It's a Tuesday Linux sandwich, and you can get the times at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash
calendar.
Also, our Reddit's at linuxunpluggedatreddit.com.
Thanks for being here.
See you next week.
I'm Chris LAS, and I'll see you next week.
All right, let's get a title, Noah.
Let's get out of here.
Oh, a title.
Great idea.
Yeah, we got to get a title.
We gots to get some titles.
We got to get a title today, huh?
Good title.
Hello, Eric.
That's awesome.
Is your weed extraction process done over there?
Did it all work out?
Dude, seriously, once you guys started talking about the Carputer stuff, I totally could
jump in because I have one.
I have an Android one, but then a leaf blower came by.
You had a windstorm over there.
Yeah, nice.
Well, you know, that's what happens.
That's what happens.
Oh, the windstorm.
That's my furnace.
The smell of Free Breeze, that's pretty good tech, Mav, but probably a little too esoteric.
What do you got?
Anybody else got a title?
What else do we got?
KDE Freedom?
No.
Scanning.
Indications negative.
Accessing.
Crankshaft.
Scanning.
I have a Tech Talk Today question.
Yes, sir.
The feeds that I found in Pocket Cast for Tech Talk Today aren't being updated.
Have you checked them recently?
Because they had a bug on their server side thing with the feed.
Oh, okay.
Let me try again.
Yeah, that would be no good.
I just Googled the... I just Googled for Tech Talk Today and went to the one that's
listed on the website.
Yeah, if you want to just put it in, it's just techtalk.today slash RSS, if you want
to just put it in.
By the way, nice new logo.
With the feet?
Well, I mean, it's different than the one you had last time.
Yeah.
Little tweaked, yeah.
Fascinating.
Mmm.
Yep.
Yay, B-titles, yay, B-titles.
You've got to constantly iterate.
Not much there on J.B. Titles.
Oh, there's a little bore.
There's a little more.
Crank that Foss shaft.
Crankshaft on the move.
Can we GTK all live together?
I have the power.
People are reaching deep this week.
People are reaching deep.
I appreciate it.
Auto freedom.
People are reaching deep.
Easy Linux.
Small and cool.
Bad news, Chris.
What's that?
Pocket Cast says it's from September years ago.
I don't know what's going on with that.
Now what if you put in techtalk.today slash RSS?
Does it pull down a new, does the old RSS still show the old logo, Wimpy?
Yeah.
Okay.
Usually Pocket Cast is very up to date when it comes to logos and all that.
Pocket Cast.
I'm going to go get Chris.
Whoa.
Colonel, you have a hot day.
Holy shit.
Maybe that's what he was going for.
Is that Noah?
Yeah.
Noah sounds terrible.
Yo, Noah.
Yeah.
I can barely hear you.
I thought my audio was bad.
Yeah.
He's also operating a wood chipper at the moment.
He's probably just got too much for me.
Yeah.
So the updated RSS is just fine, but the old feed in it, I got to talk to him.
We actually, we talked, we had it.
So that was an issue.
We talked to him.
I said, okay, we got it fixed now.
And then the person that we were working with said it was working, but I don't actually
use Pocket Cast myself.
So I'm installing it right now.
Although by the way, there's actually a newer app that I would recommend to people who are
not on Pocket Cast yet.
It's called Cast Box.
It seems to be-
Jesus, Noah.
I don't know.
Is this-
Noah, you stop.
You're ruining my post-show.
Here, let me hit stop on the recording.
You just destroyed my post-show.