you're my hero thanks poppy yeah you're welcome you're welcome so how the hell
are you great I see you tweeting about audio editors I've been recently
screwing around with I've been I've been taking another crack at the sort of the
best quote-unquote audio editors for Linux which what would you say what
would you say is the best audio editor for Linux what would you say yeah what
would you say wimpy oh it's an audio yeah well boy boy do I agree with you
wimpy boy fist bump yeah oh it's an audio is amazing but it you know the
problem with those now it's a single track editor right it's great though
it's it's a really it's the best audio editor out there if you just need to
like need it yeah I don't do anything complicated with audio right if you just
need to like clip and trim and you know cut or if you want to like open up like
a video file like a movie and pull like a clip out of a movie it's great for
that so it's really it's it's not it's not free software but it's free as in
cost and it's really good pointing it's not open source yeah it's very good I
mean I'm not and I'm not saying it's good for Linux I mean it's not good for
Linux right it's good for any operate like it's better than like pretty much
anything out there for any operating system it's I think it's actually
available for all the operating systems but it's really good I use I use it a
lot for unfilter and I like it a lot or sometimes if I just need to grab
something small but yeah if you go in multi-track it's probably it's probably
our door which I just I have not been happy with our door what happened to is
I made a big mistake is when I I had this machine that I was testing mountain
lion alright now what's it called Yosemite I was testing Yosemite on and
for production and I installed audition Adobe audition it's so good it is an
amazing audio editor and I had used it years ago so I was kind of like I was
kind of impressed with it then but man they it's so good it's so so good it's
so good and like compare and then I opened up our door again going back to
because I edit I I'm currently editing women's tech radio in our door and so
the the pains that I've been having in our door of kind of kind of would made
me check out audition and so now I'm like trying to figure out if you can get
audition to run under wine which it seems to be currently not possible so I
think I don't know I I guess see I've been I've always said that Linux has
really great audio editing but then and then I went and checked out our audition
I was like whoo this is it's really great and like the like some of the
plugins and effects that it ships with alone like it it does some really
impressive like noise removal if you have like something in the line that you
don't like it has a it has a I mean all all editors have this but it's actually
really good like it can sample a section and then it's really good about
visualizing for you how it's going to remove that and then you can adjust the
sliders and you can it visually represents how it's gonna clean that
noise up and you can preview it in real time in any section of the audio you
want and then you can say it's just it's the tools that it has are really nice so
now now now I'm feeling like our doors it's good but what right now I think our
door is really good for recording but when it comes down to doing high high
level of production editing like more than just cutting the top and adding
music when it comes down to really getting in there I don't know all right
so somebody say something here can I hear oh I have this thing yeah here we
go hello who's there who is it is anybody listening there we go here we go
hey there's poppy there he is hey handsome of course now poppies gonna be
in mumble and there that's weird yeah there you go good man get that get them
pants on that head poke why you sound pretty good for a man that uses a blue
snowball you're not gonna see any picture from me though what's the matter
are you a secret agent you can't you can't reveal your your image just call
me paranoid right okay all right you can put up if you wanted to pull a hold up
like a picture of Bill Clinton or something you can run and go get it who
else do we have down here who else Jitzer what's your name Jits here there
you go hello mr. corpse yeah hello do you see what do you see back on what do
you see back on your screen right now from you nothing no the wall oh that's
all you get myself oddly okay that's pretty you know just how when you speak
the lights around the window yeah that's cool I like that yeah and you can switch
to whichever video yeah that's neat I like that wow this is just like
Hangouts yeah it's exactly like Hangouts only it's encrypted and secure and can
it do recording it can do recording as well on the server welcome to Linux
unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's putting out the welcoming Matt
for all of those Mac switchers my name is Chris and my name is Matt so just
before the pre-show I was asking you are you flooded at all because here up in
the beautiful rainy Pacific Northwest it is bad Matt I'm taking the I have to put
the four-wheel drive on to make it into the studio because I'm basically driving
through a river oh wow yeah it's yeah that was one of the roads that one of
the roads I take a good portion of it is totally underwater right now well I know
Sylvania's just basically get your scuba gear I mean yeah I can't get to my
butcher I can't they close the road yeah they're they're done I mean I've got
problems Matt how am I gonna get my meat you're gonna have to boy scuba gear I
mean it's gonna come down to scuba gear yeah we've been spared up here so far
nothing I mean as far as but you've seen where I live I live on a gigantic like
mr. burn style hill so yeah actually well one of the things I did early when
we moved into the JB one studio is I actually built a boat underneath the
studio I just got a wild idea to do it and so I figured we did that and so if
we have any flooding here JB will be fine we'll just float hey coming up on
this week's episode of the Linux unplugged show we're gonna get to some
great follow-up in fact we're gonna get make good on a bet here in just a
moment we're gonna cover something for the community and then mr. Richard
Stallman I had a talk recently and it was pretty standard affair he has a
pretty good talk that he gives but he had a couple of moments that he
definitely emphasized and I wanted and I think I want to have a real talk with
the virtual lug about some of the things he said and because I think there's a
lot gonna be a lot of conflict in it and it's something we need to just have an
honest discussion about it's not gonna be to make fun of our mess it will be to
have a legitimate discussion of some of the points he makes and then later on in
the show I I had a 2014 prediction that are I'm sorry 2015 prediction that more
of not all not a lot not not like millions but a noticeable percentage of
high-end Mac users would get frustrated and begin abandoning the Mac OS
platform and switch back to Linux users that perhaps we had lost along the way
a bunch of users we lost along the way that might come back well over the
weekend a total s storm developed in the Mac community they ended up making it up
on on CNBC national television lots of articles written about it about the
decline of Mac software and about developers who've been around for 10
plus years switching the Linux platform I'm gonna tell you about that and maybe
if there is an advantage in there for Linux hmm yeah we'll see so why don't we
bring in our our virtual lug a time appropriate greetings mumble room hello
hello great to have you guys no all right so poppy since you're here let's
cash in on a bet poppy you in a prediction said that if Ubuntu does not
does not ship on a phone by the end of 2014 you'd wear pants on your head and
here you are boom right there for the internet to see poppy making good Ninja
Turtles pants on his head I hope so I hope so that's kind of like a trophy of
shame now I think you should save that and then if somebody else fails a pants
bet you should ship the box but they have to pay for the shipping so it's not
out of your pocket like you should just pass that around now oh yeah pair of
pants every time well it could be I'm just proposing that as an option it that
might not be practical but as soon as it leaves my house I'm no longer obligated
to wear them anymore right yeah unless you fail another bet unless you fail
another bet so good on you I like this you know what honestly Matt you might
have considered going this route instead of an entire monkey suit oh I know right
tell me about I still got that thing oh yeah I still got my money that might
yeah I might even make it make a reappearance here someday I got my man
in the yellow hat outfit so he could always busted out you know we were
talking about production on Linux more and more recently but on the pre-show
even and Katie and life and wrote and he said hey I don't if you caught this but
there's some news about Katie and live John Baptiste has gone got the Academy
Award for the best application in 2014 here we go the score this is pulled he
pulled from the form for Katie and live he says JBM is back with a vengeance
developing Katie and live after being pretty much out of action for about a
year and a half he's been slaving away porting the
application to the latest version of Katie's frameworks which means there's
not much of for us lowly users yet but what it means in the long run is that
the application can keep moving forward with the latest developments of the
underlying application framework for which it is built so in other words it
sounds like Katie and live might be moving to qt5 and development has begun
again I live in it oh it's it's unbelievable because it used to be you
know my favorite let's crash an editor editor but here in recent years it's
surprisingly will take a beating it's fast it's stable surprisingly I can add
to it all day long I could have 50 lines of whatever it doesn't care it just
works it's like yeah and it you know it makes a lot of like compositing and
green-screening all that type stuff it makes it real easy to do I want to get
used to the flow you know for casual usage I would recommend it yeah well
then I'm glad to hear the development continues so thank you to Katie and I
fan for sending that in I I I think I've had probably more luck with the earlier
versions of open shot but um I want to like it it just it's just you know I can
only hit save so many times after a while you do you have to develop a save
tick you know and if I want to do anything with any you know you know more
than three lines or you know oh forget it it's just it needs a little work I'm
excited to see what they do in the future though so I you know since since
we moved into JB one last year Rekai has been our editor so I don't actually do
any video editing really anymore unless I unless I want to so it's not really
been something that I've had to really push very much but I have it's called
avid mucks see am I saying that right guys are you familiar with sounds close
every demon yes okay so you guys all know what I'm talking about right this
like for example today I got like three clips from RMS's speech and what it
allows me to do is I opened up the WebM file that RMS the speeches in and I was
able to go in and just say here's a marker and now here's a marker out take
these take the between these two markers and save that as its own standalone
WebM file and it doesn't do any recoding it doesn't it just takes that section of
the file out re-encapsulates it back in a WebM wrapper and and just drops it on
the file system it so there's no degradation and quality because there's
no re-encoding yeah and it does it with all basically I think you got a codec
for and so what you really got it which so so you might consider like if you
don't need a full-fledged freaking editor sometimes you can do quite a bit
which is chopping the ends and maybe even dropping in and pasting in like
maybe intro and outro clips and you don't even need a full thing because
then you just save that out to one a MKV master file and then you run that
through handbrake to make your versions and you're done it's really easy so you
don't what I'm discovering is is I started rethinking about this and what
I realized is well if my if my production needs are reduced now that
Rekai is really handling handling the editing of the shows then maybe I don't
need a full-fledged editing suite of tools and once I kind of made that shift
in mindset it really was a lot easier but it depends on your workload all
right yes very good so we've got a few things I want to talk about and Colonel
Linux are you still here yes you are but you're muted all right well standby I'm
gonna I'm gonna go to you I'm gonna go to you but first I'll let you get your
audio sorted while I take a quick moment and talk about Linux Academy so Linux
Academy is a sponsor of the Linux Unplugged show and I think they're a
perfect fit for our audience we were just talking about kind of moving
yourself forward a little bit and trying new things and reach it changing the way
you think about things that's one of the things that Linux Academy has allowed me
to do here's why if you can get started by going to Linux Academy comm slash
unplugged you'll get our special 33% discount Linux Academy comm slash
unplugged and then you get access to all of their content I've logged in there
and I've been surprised I kind of had a wreath I had a rethinking process when I
went to Linux Academy comm specifically slash DevOps and I realized that DevOps
is actually something that I guess I was I was sort of doing for a long time I
didn't realize that's what we would call it and this is an area that's growing
like like nuts and so Linux Academy has been developing courseware specifically
for that area but they've also got courseware you you get anything you'd
want to scratch an itch on for Linux really from mastering Linux to absolute
beginner stuff and you can walk away from this and go get certifications it
happens all the time in fact I've been getting some success stories which is
awesome thank you to the audience for sending that in and keep sending if you
get if you get a cert after taking a Linux Academy of course I love hearing
about it so keep sending them in it's really encouraging too because if you
ever kind of bottom out a little bit they've got a community of support that
will help you kind of get going again but they also have a system that will
give you really easy to adjust and assess time for how long something's
gonna take you'll log in you're gonna say this section is gonna take this long
this section is gonna take this long you need this much time and you can say you
know what Linux Academy bro I only got so much time I'm a busy man and it will
automatically create a learning plan that met that matches that amount of
time you could downloadable comprehensive study guides virtual labs
you can work and they'll spin them up on the back end 7 plus Linux distributions
you get to choose from they automatically adjust the courseware to
those Linux distributions I mean this is a seriously slick system because it's
created by people they're enthusiastic and passionate about Linux now if you're
a listener of this show you know what that difference means when somebody
actually cares about open source and Linux versus just a general education
site it is the final gap it's that gap that closes the uncanny valley linux
academy.com slash unplugged get our 33 percent discount get access to
everything they're doing some great new Docker courseware just went up also the
puppet professional stuff the puppet stuff they've got now you start at total
noob you know I know puppets this thing it lets me like manage servers and you
go to like okay I'm ready to go get the cert seriously it's all the way through
and you can do stuff in practicality they have scenario based courseware it's
so great linuxacademy.com slash unplugged go check them out and a big
thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux unplugged show
all right mr. Colonel Linux are you back now I got my voice back hi there I missed
you so I wanted to talk about some upcoming conferences the first one on
the list is scale 13 February 19th to the 22nd it's a big one at the Hilton
Los Angeles Airport are you still on your radar planning to go to this I am
in fact I I've been to most of the the Linux conferences multiple times but
I've never been to scale so this will be my first time at scale and I have to say
the thing I'm most excited for is apparently you can paint with you can
paint with like they have like a bio lab and you can then you you can take the
the bio biological material and paint make like drawings and stuff with whoa
yeah oh I also see they're doing the traditional PGP key signing party which
is great now do you know anybody else on the crew is anybody else yet confirmed
going not that I know of so we're gonna start organizing something around scale
so that's coming up and and if you're thinking of going make sure you say hi
to Noah and anybody else ends up making it on the crew the next big one for us
where we really go all out is Linux fest Northwest 2015 it's gonna be the
biggest Linux fest ever Bellingham Washington April 25th to the 26th this I
think is gonna be a huge year for Linux fest because it's just been getting
bigger and huger every single year and every year the feedback is always so
positive that it just seems to continually grow I know this one's
pretty far away because it's right up in our corner of the Pacific Northwest but
I'd love to encourage the audience to make it out we're gonna go all out worst
we're talking to them about having two booths so that way we have enough room
to spread out and if you know if you know what that's like having two booths at a
conference like this that's really quite an event and I think it's gonna be
amazing and hopefully and not everything's lined up yet we're all the
very beginning stages but hopefully we'll be able to live stream the entire
thing and we might even be able to do that using Linux so stay tuned for
information on that so I've links to both those in the show notes if you want
to check out more details love to see you guys at Linux fest Northwest I think
we're gonna go all out and I hope we're gonna get as much of the crew out here
as possible so we'll find out and that's again April 25th in the 26 2015 in
Bellingham Washington Linux fest Northwest org for more information mr.
rotten corpse are you still here did you have to jet off all right and are you
ready to talk about the new pick site that you set up yep sure all right so
it's a Jupiter broadcasting comm slash last picks and now with the complete
entire essentially nine-year history runs Linux and this is unbelievable made
me realize how how old the show episode one Linux action show my Tivo runs
Linux June 10th June 10th 2006 which is quite a long time ago so rotten corpse
tell us about this pick site and how maybe people could contribute fork their
own etc the pick site is it's it's written in PHP so if you know PHP you
can help out with that in that case but if you don't you can actually contribute
through adding data to from the github site so if you if you go to the github
page you'll see that there is a folder says site and then inside that folder is
the data file and everything's stored in the data file okay so there's a template
in the data files you just copy and paste and add it to the bottom of the
file and this it's that simple to just change the numbers and then add the like
the name of the pick and the URL and that's and that's pretty much all you
have to do and just send the send a pull request and I have a tutorial that I'm
working on that explains how to do everything but also another tutorial to
how to keep your stuff up to date with the main branch but the one of the
things I like about the site is that it's mobile friendly so if you pull it
up on a tablet or a phone it will you know responsively adjust itself to fit
everything and one of the coolest features I like is the the calendar jump
so you can just click that the top right button and you can choose just between
no look at that that's really go back to 2012 or whatever whoo oh that's slick
yeah it's especially useful on the runs Linux one boy you're making me feel
really old though when I realize how old the show is that's that's kind of
honestly tripping me out a little bit to see all of it linked and noted here this
is really the first time I've seen a list of the show like this because the
back catalogue isn't is in such disarray I've never actually seen it visualized
like this as funny as that might seem there's a lot of people that helped I
and you can go to the good hip thing and see that in the contribute section who
helped out so it was really I couldn't done it by myself but one of the cool
things that I set up is an API that so developers can take all the data out and
you just go to the contribute section and there's an API link right now it's
just JSON but there will be other output formats as well and you made this video
here about it yeah the video is actually just the keeping your seeing I need to
make I'm still might working on another people want their own their own list
their own copy yeah if they want to help they need to fork the original repo and
then once you make changes or someone else makes changes it might confuse
people have never used it before so this video is just to help them keep their
repo in sync with the master well it's pretty neat to see all this and this is
a common request and something we've tried in different forms but thanks to
various volunteers in the past you know they've done unofficial lists on their
own they've tried doing in different capacities but this one it's it's much
easier to find for one because it's just it's a Jupiter broadcasting comm slash
las pics so that's nice but also I like that the community can also keep it up
to date if anybody can contribute and you don't need to know how to code at
all just go to the contribute section and you know just walk through it and
then fork your own fork your own repo and that's it not to repeat myself but
if you get up if you get a new Android device or a new Linux desktop I totally
recommend going to the desktop apps or the Android apps and checking out some
of the pics there are some super really really good apps I really like this list
I work really hard to pick these apps to make sure they're as good as possible
whenever I can it's not always possible but I really stand by all of these app
picks and so if you've got a new rig to set up that's a great list to start with
right there and you can again Jupiter broadcasting comm slash las pics it's just a
great resource for the community and thank you for everybody who's helped
rotten corpse and a big thank you to producer rotten corpse creating that for
us well it was such a gold mine because I mean I remember air droid when you
guys featured that you know it's just like that's what really sold me on an
Android right there I was like I can't do this on my own my other device this
was awesome well it's also nice for me because I have a pretty good idea of
what I've covered before and I can always do a site search but to have the
list and just be able to go to listen search to see have I picked this app
before exactly sometimes there's ones I'd like oh how could I how could I have
skipped this oh my gosh I need to go pick this right now and then it's I go
search see if I've done I haven't I'm like oh I'm good this is my epic so also
helps for no duplicates too yes exactly totally that's what I'm saying man tells
what I'm saying thank you sir very much and to be interesting to see if any
developers managed to pull that into their app that could be a that could be
a neat light like when you're listening to an episode if they could pull in like
here's just the pics boom from this episode right there you never know all
right well I'll tell you about something I pick as digital ocean digital ocean
comm sponsored Linux unplug program and use our promo code we've got it just for
a little bit we're hanging on to it because we're retro because we're hip
but not stirs it's unplugged December that's a $10 credit for digital ocean
unplugged December and what's great about digital ocean you just go in there
and apply it to your account you don't even have to put a credit card in there
to try out digital ocean so what is digital ocean it's a simple cloud
hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way for you
to spin up your own server that you get root access to and you can start in less
than in about 55 seconds maybe even less than that I often see a lot less than
that and only it starts get this five dollars a month that'll get you 512
megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte of transfer and they
have data centers in New York and San Francisco and Singapore and Amsterdam
and London but they're beautiful too and they have multiple data centers in those
locations you can do private networking within the data centers which doesn't
count against your bandwidth totals so if you want to have a front-end web
server in a back-end database server or some caching that's a really really nice
option you could also do something like have a couple of front-end servers in a
back-end now server put open media vault on there there's all kinds of things you
can do once you get once you get access to the box because you've got root
control of it and what's really great is it's all powered by this dashboard the
digital ocean is created and it's so great I mean they've got the super
powerful hardware with the SSD drives and the tier 1 bandwidth all running on
top of Linux using KVM like a boss and then they came up with this interface
and I'm like are you kidding me are you serious you've made it this easy it's so
intuitive and power users can replicate the interface on a larger scale digital
ocean straightforward API and so there's tons of great community apps because
once you get a good API for a popular service well if you make the API they
will come as Kevin Costner has taught us and digital ocean knows it so they've
made that we were just on the pre-show checking out meet meet Jitsi
implementation that's running on a digital ocean droplet fully encrypted
exactly like hangouts where it does the auto switching and you get the little
tiles below of who's talking it's all built into the browser running on a
digital ocean droplet right now it's so many opportunities and there's great
tutorials because they're willing to pay money for those tutorials in fact we've
got a link in the show notes of digital ocean pay up to $200 if you got
something you can write here's an example of one I think I'm gonna go for
especially as my son gets more and more into reading and then pretty soon my
daughter this is how to create a clever a cleaver a e-book server on a buntu
yes I said a buntu yes I said a buntu 1404 right there you go get the digital
ocean droplet use our promo code unplug December you get the $10 credit you go
create yourself an ebook server cleaver is amazing it's something I want to do
an entire episode on at one point but now I'm thinking this is step one for me
try this out it's just another use of the really millions of possibilities you
could use a digital ocean droplet for unplug December digital ocean and a big
thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring Linux unplug program alright
so Richard Stallman had a talk recently and it's pretty standard affair freedom
in your computer and in the net he says for freedom in your own computer the
software must be free for freedom on the internet we must organize against
surveillance censorship software as a service and the war against sharing
pretty common approach for mr. Stallman and a message that's definitely worth
listening to in fact that's why I encouraged people at the end of last
week's last to go listen to it however where I run into is a little bit of the
practicalities and I want this is what I want to discuss with you guys so I've
pulled three clips from his talk that he normally goes down this path but he
emphasizes these points pretty hard in his talk and I think I'd like to hear
from all of us who have worked in any kind of software industry where that's
where that where that company's goal has been perhaps to have some level of
profit and make money and I think that and that could be it could be a lot of
us that work in the contract contracting capacity people who develop software
and sell it and so in Richard Stallman's talk today he talks about how these
companies that use software as a means to make money are simply doing it for a
greedy purpose and I want to play the clip and I want to talk about it because
in his opinion there's no way around it it's evil by nature proprietary software
are being victimized by proprietary malware of course the reason they do
this is typically for profit it's not that they're sadists that enjoy
mistreating people no they're totally egoistical and they do this for profit
like they the more users they make captive the more they can sell to
somebody else and in effect proprietary software is all a swindle and they're
not even ashamed of it they have conferences where they talk about their
latest advances in how to make users captive and mistreat them in effect the
proprietary software world is one where the ethical standards of treating the
customers or the users have disappeared any mistreatment of those users is okay
there may be some pesky laws or regulations they have to find an excuse
to bypass like so his point is is that they're they're fundamentally it's
gonna be an evil motive and I guess are we victims of commercial software in the
sense that we are not allowed to have control over it in the end which is what
his point was and here's here's why I asked this because right now we are in
the thick of CES the Consumer Electronics Show is happening right now
and just like Richard said these companies are up on stage and they're
bragging about the ecosystem they're bragging about the lock-in I watched the
ACES keynote and I I literally felt belittled I felt like he's and he's
holding a phone up there he's like and for those of you who like to think out
the box here's three models you can pick from because you're a renegade and it
felt like they were formulaically looking at the audience and saying well
these people identify as this so here's their product and these people identify
as this so here's their product and it felt like they were actually their
intention was the exact opposite of their message it felt it felt gross and
it's all I wouldn't and and again it's about locking me into their system so
what RMS says is very extreme but yet when I look at the background of CES
happening right now I think long term I think you might be a little right well
you know I I look at it as this from just a nuts and bolts point of view he's
accurate what he's saying is true unfortunately and I and I know that he
doesn't care about this but this is a reality convenience always and will
until the end of time unless we end up in some apocalyptic world will always
trump privacy and it just that's just a reality we give way to it every single
day oh you want to use a club savings card at your grocery store it'll save
you 30 cents sure you're giving up your privacy but you know it's saving you a
little money and it's convenient we'll always give way to that now that's not
to say everybody will but I think that that's the underlying issue you know
does that make what Richard says wrong or bad in some capacity not at all no I
think that what he's saying is fine I have no problem with it but I would
point out that no one's going to wrap suddenly change their mind unless they
experience that victimization that he's speaking of okay Colonel like show me the
money what do you think you think about the money right so what so he's right
when he says that those companies make a lot of decisions based purely on capital
and why wouldn't they those businesses exist to make money and they don't care
about users freedoms and why would they that's not a profitable aspect to them
but if you make it a profitable aspect you know to them either by one as users
if we say I'm just not gonna buy if I can't buy a device that I have
administrative access to or can get administrative access to then I just
won't buy it I'll buy all I'll buy this device or this competing device and you
don't give them your money that's one way you can for that you can you can
show those companies that if if they want give them a way to make money by
supporting users freedoms the second way you can do that is I've gone into I
can't count how many businesses I've got into and said you shouldn't use
Microsoft Office you should use Libra office now there the the the concept of
freedom and the concept of users rights they couldn't care less about but when I
tell them well instead of paying $300 a year $400 a year to upgrade to the
newest version every year you just go to this site you click on this download
link and it's free for all 60 year computers and you start putting that on
paper and shove it in front of a in front of a president's face now they
care now yeah yeah well okay wimpy are you a victim when you buy your Amazon
fire TV are you now a victim well Richard Stallman would say that
I'm a victim I'm just a slave to convenience I suppose really on time
yeah I'm a pragmatist much more of a pragmatist and Stallman is that's for
sure rotten corpse you think in the long run though RMS is right yeah I mean I
think our message kind of already proven that the the messages is right because
and when he started doing this there was basically no options for like as soon as
the the proprietary stuff took hold there was only proprietary stuff and now
there's actually people who have joined the argument in projects like Firefox
and stuff that are trying to keep things and a way for freedom is important to
them and I think in the long term it will be eventually it will people will
realize but it's in the short term it's really hard to convince them other than
the you know the stuff that's free money wise but I think that what mad dog said
is also a really good point that instead of trying to explain the freedom
explain the fact that you're technically a slave to the product the products okay
wimpy go ahead take your shot so you think fire TV and freedom there's
intersection here you're ready to defend it go no I'm not going to defend it what
I was going to say is that for me the fire TV is a convenient device because
it was inexpensive and I can plug it in and it works and it does what I need it
to do but if I needed to exercise my freedoms then I'm perfectly capable of
building a XBMC or Cody set-top box using a Raspberry Pi and streaming the
content over NFS from a server in the house so I have I have my choices I've
just chosen convenience over protecting my freedoms in this case and let's not
forget the the content that I'm consuming on my fire TV or my XBMC Cody
box is proprietary and copyright and license encumbered anyway so all right
fair enough but a daredevil let me ask you this if those of us who have the
option to implement a free system don't elect to do it then who will and will
those options fade away long term here I mean I'm talking really big picture like
this is in a way the expression of human thought it is it is something that maybe
should be protected and if those of us who have the means to implement the
version that protects that thought for the future generations don't implement
those options daredevil I'm asking you don't we sort of condemn those options
yes but I feel that we have an option to still make a transition easier but
currently the tools that we have at our disposal have been really hard to push
to the public but there is a place that we're starting to get our feet in which
is into in government institutions because of cost and through this we can
influence a future road pad that actually makes sensible copyright law
that actually fixes the problem at its core not just you know we're still on
the fight corporations free software and sometimes the corporation is aligned
with us and then it gets fuzzy right well I feel that RMS RMS would disagree
with you so you are you sound like an optimist that's nice RMS would say no
it's not going to go that way in fact RMS says well our duty is is we have to
protest these come now and we have to fight back for instance we have to
protest whenever the representatives of the companies that mistreat people show
up to speak recruit or whatever if there's an Apple or Microsoft or Adobe
or etc recruiting team coming to your university well organize a protest and
teach explain to people why it why that company is doing harm so popiah I know
this is maybe a point that you might have contention with do you think the
appropriate way to express this is through protesting like the Apple genius
by yeah well yeah I have I mean you've obviously poked something there where I
I have I I don't like some of the the means by which this is done I think the
positive way to do things is to write good software write good free software
to continually berate companies that make proprietary software I don't isn't
working I don't think it ever has really worked I think what has worked is
producing great alternatives to proprietary software in the form of free
software hmm and how do you also market that software well and yeah honestly it
even fails the core our economic economies are based on intellectual
property the real exports of nowadays modern societies is intellectual
property if you don't fix it in a way that incentivizes business to move away
from that direction then you're killing yourself it's not just asking to the
corporations to stop it's asking the country to stop and that doesn't make
sense to anybody so that I feel that there needs to be a tangible way to make
a transition if you don't offer a transition to people they won't care
because they will look at the benefits of these proprietary software and
actually discard some of the inconveniences right we need to teach
people in one hand but at the same time we need to provide a transitional and
not just with quality software because quality software can be transformed into
proprietary look at PSD license for example explicitly allows this and I
feel that if you don't fix the core issues you're going to run into them
later or sooner it doesn't matter you will run into them RMS would argue that
I think it needs to begin with the individual developer at the end of the
talkie to the Q&A and the question came up well what if I want to make money
might like to make living out of selling their software so which business model
would you okay the first question is they might point is they might like to
do that but if they but that doesn't justify or excuse doing it in an
unethical way proprietary software is an injustice they shouldn't do that but
there are there are many free software business models like there is selling
support there is constructing custom solutions paid by the clients you can
deliver the solution is free software the clients still gonna have to pay there
is crowdfunding there's just plain asking for donations there's a new
package called Lily pond for editing musical scores and the maintainer gets
enough money just from users that are happy and send it there are others as
well there are big companies that fund development of useful free software
governments fund a lot especially in Europe so yes there are ways to do this
but if you don't find one that doesn't excuse non free software next so that's
a pretty radical stance and I think that's where it starts to lose the
message with a lot of people dare W have any follow-up thoughts on that yes and
this is as a software developer I have to agree you can actually because your
client especially when it's a client that doesn't have the technical
understanding you can claim that this is the appropriate way of doing and I work
on my own bucket so I can decide these things but I understand that the models
and the great companies currently didn't weren't like in you United States you
have a red hat and we here kind of have open Sousa right so Sousa but it's still
around of a hybrid model you still have canonical it's still a hybrid model so
there has some some benefits on the hybrid model otherwise it wouldn't be
the selected model right so unless there is a fix on the policy I don't think
there will be not even a fight that will actually make a dent in solving the
issue we as developers we can bring up but most of us can actually argue that
we're already doing free software for the companies we give our copyright to
the company that paid us so as developers are really doing committing a
crime perhaps the company model is but at that point is like me saying I'm
going to enforce anyone that's got my software do not use it somewhere else
like yeah can I just interject yes and point out that this isn't actually an
abstract argument because what RMS is talking about is a framework of social
justice that is around software but is in terms of technology that we're using
now for technology that we can be more important to us in the future things
like you know heart pacemakers care I know smarter TV smart cars exactly now
the point is okay how ethical is it for someone like a right to not be have
access to the safety aspects of those devices to make sure that they are safe
for them okay when some company decides care out to look up a care right and
throw their key I look at it from a completely different perspective from
that too I look at it from a 200 year perspective I try to think ahead and I
try to think looking back at our history and our creations if these things are
locked away behind these proprietary licenses and walls in the long term
they're a loss they don't they don't better the whole which is kind of sad
well it is human nature to share things I mean the whole point about proprietary
stuff okay is that you know when man discovered a fire okay wasn't something
he hoarded himself care right and kept for himself right there's a question
okay you know everyone who benefited from the idea of care from you know
making fire that's because inherently okay it's a human nature okay to swap
ideas going to discuss and two things it's this in sort of you know
commercialistic aspect okay that's made us sort of very it is against human
nature like that's why I think a lot of people get into software like on the
commercial desktops I think that's why a lot of people get into piracy I think
that's why a lot of people share stuff before I knew about music piracy I was
making mixed tapes with friends and we were sharing them I didn't know that was
stealing music that was just sharing something I liked with my friends oh
hell back in 1982 okay I was sharing all these spectrum games on tapes and
everything yeah very much so very much so so the whole talk is linked in the
show notes if you want to check it out one thing is is you know the message is
always very strong and then if you think about a little bit sometimes you get to
the truth underneath it I'll tell you about the truth of my savings that's
ting go to linux.ting.com sponsor of the Linux unplugged show and now I have
turned the corner on my two years with tang and what's well yeah I know I know
it's awesome and it's great because I've only paid for what I use I've got no
contract nor the termination fee and remember ting's got that savings
calculator so if you're noodling around how much you would save go put in your
actual monthly usage so how many you make a lot of calls let's say you make
and let's say you make a hundred minutes I doubt it I doubt it do you even talk
on the phone for an hour let's let's say 60 minutes go you know let's say you do
let's say 80 minutes because you know grandma called text messages you know
you get that damn SMS system that goes off accidentally because something went
off on your alert system so you get 300 text messages let's say but normally you
don't but let's just say this this month you got a lot of text messages and
megabytes used because then you had to go log into the remote GUI to disable
the alerts and of course it downloads all those damn graphs every time you
have to do it let's say you used 800 megabytes so I don't so you know what
you used a gig it was a really bad month because your job sucks so now what was
your bill because you're in a contract right if it's bill if your bills like
mine let's say it's 130 bucks all right you go calculate your savings just go
see what you do now depending on your usage these numbers will change so go
over to the ting calculator and try it out but boom over a two-year period if
you're like Chris and you're at your team you're making you're just passing
the two-year mark two thousand three hundred and twenty eight dollars saved
over two years by switching to ting and ting is just starting to get better not
only do they have an early termination relief program no hold customer service
an incredible dashboard but ting is also going to GSM in February will you be
able to see them at CDMA and GSM under one account and one of the things I love
about ting is they've always got your back this model allows for them to be
unlike any other carrier and so one of their series they have on their blog now
the ting tip and the first one in the ting tip is reducing your data usage in
Google Chrome so if you use Chrome on Android like I've been using I like
Firefox 2 on Android but I've been using Chrome more they have a step-by-step
process with nice animated gifs so our gifts whatever you want so you can just
go they don't have flash come on right you're not an animal plus it works on
your mobile this way and you go in you go through these settings and they'll
talk to you about how do you do reduce data usage on Chrome the ting blog is
always featuring really great stuff app pics stuff about their GSM coverage and
now these the ting tips to help reduce data usage yeah the mobile carrier is
writing up great how-to's to save data and by the way you don't have to be a
ting customer obviously to take advantage of these tips but it's pretty
cool that things put them out there so go to the linux.ting.com linux.ting.com
it's linux l-i-n-u-x I'm sorry gnu linux was already taken we couldn't we
couldn't use that one so it's just linux.ting.com they'll take $25 off your
first ting device if you got a ting compatible device guess what you got one
you can just bring with you they're gonna give you $25 of credits would
probably pay for your first month oh ting it's pretty great linux.ting.com
and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring the linux unplugged show so one of the
things we noticed colonel linux and I when we're at these events is there in a
wash of Mac books it is gross it is full of Mac books so we're gonna talk a
little bit about this and I want to say at the beginning of the segment if
you're listening to this show and Mac OS X works for you and the Mac hardware
works for you no judging good for you I have no problems with that this is not
going to be an attack on your choices if I acknowledge that for many it works
probably many so I want to just disclaim that right now this is not an attack on
those of you who choose to use the Mac but I made the prediction in our
predictions episode that I felt like people are gonna start getting really
burned out with Mac OS 10 the quality isn't so good you start to feel the
walls of the sandbox pretty quick and you kind of get tired and burned out on
what I call like it's it's I don't have a great term for it but I think of it as
like the marketing debt of OS 10 like there's a there is a direction that
Apple as a company is going in and in order to make the whole product line
look like it's going in that direction Apple will unnecessarily do things to OS
10 to fit that like you know all of a sudden rebranding the way it looks with
unneeded transparencies that slow it down or yearly release cycles that way it
feels like your phone's firmware and you think of it as a firmware not an OS
release and in the meantime they don't have enough time to do Q&A these kinds
of things I feel like will begin to grate on people so that's where we begin
today Marco Armit who is he was a guy that originally wrote tumblr he created
Instagram he's the current developer of overcast he hosts the podcast accidental
tech podcast and he used to be the publisher of the magazine and he's one
of the top sellers in the iOS App Store and he wrote on his blog over the
weekend that Apple has lost the functional high ground that Apple's
hardware while great met does not is not matched in OS quality in fact he goes on
to say that it's gotten pretty bad and he goes on to cite that a recent
developer a well-known developer who's switching to the Linux desktop so Marco's
argument here is that essentially what my prediction was is that Apple's
marketing is pushing the OS in directions and at a pace that they
cannot sustain internally development wise that the quality has been on a
rapid decline in fact word-for-word he says I suspect the rapid decline of
Apple software is a sign that the marketing is too high a priority at
Apple today this is a long-term Apple developer who makes his money on the
Apple platform saying this not Chris this is not Chris saying this this is
Marco saying this and I think that's remarkable and this also comes just
after Jeff Wozniak or geoff Wozniak I'm not sure how you say his name 10 year
developer of OS 10 switch to Linux in late 2014 and he says it was the best
tech decision he made all year he says he started using OS 10 in 2005 when OS 10
was at version 10.4 Tiger he was having troubles with Linux and he moved over to
OS 10 he was happy as up to OS 10.6 snow leopard thought it was pretty good then
things started to show up that he didn't like an OS 10.7 features like launchpad
that didn't really resonate with him and as things progressed he became
increasingly annoyed and disconnected with the environment he said he found
he'd stopped using the majority of the primary apps that shipped with OS 10
like mail Safari iTunes and the Apple creativity apps like the iLife suite for
the more for the most part he says he ran essentially Firefox mailmate and a
terminal most of his work was done in terminals the culture of the operating
system at this point was more about sharing than it was personal
productivity in short he says I was working against the grain of the
environment I was working against the grain of the environment I was in a
gradual transition but OS 10 it went from a useful tool that got my work done
to obnoxious ecosystem that I no longer wanted to be part of he goes on to talk
about how it was daunting that there was a complete lack of transparency in
future software development and a decline in quality as he perceived it
which makes it a tenuous relationship when you're using as your development
platform and then he says 10.10 Yosemite hit the upgrade was egregious he says
messages in 10.10 is a complete shit show it's a stunning regression he says
at this point my default position on Apple software and OS 10 has moved from
probably good to probably not okay they seem more interested in pumping out
quantity by the way of upgrades it's death by it's death by a thousand cuts
but it's death nonetheless he says I came to realization I was
frustrated disappointed by OS 10 and I didn't see it getting better so I quit
now he goes on to admit I've gone back to running Linux and I consider it
somewhat inferior if not markedly inferior to OS 10 OS 10 in terms of
usability but it feels like a personal computer again I'm enjoying the
experience and look forward to working with it even if it's a monumental pain
in the ass and then he links to Paul's audio yeah you know that was probably
the most truthful article I've heard in a long time because he nailed it at the
end he nailed it in the middle yeah ten-year developer on OS 10 plus you've
got Marco arm at one of the top iOS developers now to top it all off panic
one of the longest time developers for the mac OS platform panic one of the
biggest independent development shops for OS 10 one of the most respected and
well-known creators of iOS apps and OS 10 applications did a year-end post and
they talked about the challenges in this 2014 review iOS upgrades they talked
about how iOS upgrades have not been very well done they talked about how
they had to leave the Mac App Store they say that it hasn't been going very well
in the Mac App Store and that sales the sales after leaving didn't suffer they
talked about the app review process being atrocious but here's the most
devastating number of all they break down their sales 51% of panic sales are
on iOS 49% of panic sales are on the Mac okay 51 on iOS 49 on the Mac but
revenue only 17% on iOS 83% on the Mac even though they sell more on iOS they
make dramatically less money which I believe a lot of developers are learning
about the whole entire Mac ecosystem and the whole premise of getting developers
to buy these Mac books to get Xcode to get a Mac is so they can get in this app
store this gold mine but these are top-tier Apple developers top-tier Apple
developers saying it doesn't make economic sense they say iOS represents
just 17% of our total revenue despite selling more than half of our total unit
sales that's huge it's part of this crazy huge mobile users won't pay enough
money but there's a lot of problems there so I think you know this this
promise of the App Store has pushed a lot of people to buy Macs but this
promise seems to be flopping on its face you've got these prominent developers
that are saying look at these things aren't right quality's down I lay they
Marco Armand his post says the stuff that we used to give Windows users a
hard time about like we've got no room to talk Windows is getting nice and
stable meanwhile our crap can't run very well and I totally concur with that like
you know we just upgraded the Wirecast system to Mavericks which is 10.9 even
though 10.10 is out because the quality of the releases takes about a year
before they're usable in a high production workload it's getting pretty
bad so I wonder is Linux in a good position to pick up this mess because
it's gonna get pretty bad before people are gonna switch and that could take a
little while and legitimately so Windows 10 isn't that far away right I mean
Windows 10 is a couple years away they're gonna have a really strong
message especially to power users as yours looking pretty good people could
want to get in on that Matt do you think Linux is in a position to pick up some
of these what about these folks who switch to the Mac that might be
switching back do you think we're in a position are we ready for that I think
so I well let me let me preface that yes and no yes in that we have the
bare-bones stuff necessary to make this happen yes it's absolutely in existence
if we could actually get I don't know the word out beyond the echo chamber
that would be an amazing thing that's yet to happen I hope it does that's what
needs to happen and where Microsoft will be picking up the pieces if we don't get
you know our heads out of our butts and get that happening if we get the word
out hey there is an alternative you guys should check this out then get some of
these developers to actually you know utilize it and then share the software I
don't know developed for Linux you know as an option I think we might actually
see a shift but until that happens you know I think that we're gonna
perpetuate this the usual circle jerk I really do well and I said here's a case
set up here's a case study Michael Dominic co-host of the quarter radio
program yeah longtime Mac developer hadn't needed a second workstation and
he grabbed a Dell laptop and our desktop I'm not sure and he installed Ubuntu
Mate 1404 edition that Wimby and team have put out and for him he says you
know at the end of day Chrome is Chrome sublime text is sublime text and I need
a terminal and I was able to get all of the work done I needed to do on this
machine and I think that's significant I think it is so I think that to further
preface this even more for developers absolutely we'll see a shift I don't
think there's any question of that I think where we're gonna continue to
fall down those that they're gonna be using Linux boxes to make software for
Windows and they're gonna be using Linux boxes to make software for you know for
other platforms and probably a lot of mold and web services big time on web
services I don't see anything really happening on the Linux desktop and and
that's sad no I mean as far as the developers that are actually developing
for it yeah they're doing their thing but as far as the big migration that
we're hoping for no one if I go outside and scream hey I'm using Linux no one
has any idea what I'm talking about I mean that's not changing we don't
actually get out there and change that we talk about it but no one actually
doesn't well and if we're just looking if we're just looking at the high-end
technical users the users that are looking for an exodus from the Mac
platform wimpy make me feel better are you saying you're seeing a pretty good
percentage of Mac hardware yeah within the Ubuntu Marte community I was really
surprised at how many people there are that are using Mac hardware and that's
a mixture of Intel Mac books is that what they're called I don't know I've
never seen one somebody somebody in the community has put together a power PC
build of Ubuntu Marte which runs on the the you know iBooks the g4s and what
have you so I'm actually working with them to try and improve that so I when
when I had some hardware difficulties that some of the Jupiter broadcasting
community helped solve for Ubuntu Marte and this is things like UAFI because
again I've never seen one of those whatever a UFA is it most of the people
that volunteered to help were running Mac books of some description yeah I've
gotten emails from folks on Mac books on power PC MacBook specifically saying
they're doing Mate edition I had I had 30 people participate in the testing and
the feedback and 24 of them were on Mac hardware and this was in the real early
days of Ubuntu Marte when it was in the alphas and I was genuinely surprised by
that and of course what they do is they stick plank or doki on it and they
recreate a Mac OS 10 type workflow because you know Mac OS 10 is a
traditional desktop by and large right Colonel Linux this is why we've got to
make Linux work better on the MacBook hardware don't you think I think that's
a I think that's a great first step but it it that won't entirely solve the
problem because if you had if let's just say everyone let's just say we have a
max exodus from the max and everyone comes over to Linux and now everyone
installs Linux on their MacBook that's a great first step but when those people
go out to buy a new computer it can't be a MacBook again if they go out and buy a
MacBook again they continue to give Apple their money and they continue to
put Linux on it then Apple can then then Apple continues to win they continue to
they're gonna continue putting what's what's the difference if I buy a Lenovo
with Windows on nothing nothing but but that and that's where things like system
76 where the Librem laptop come in is where where you're not supporting
Microsoft by buying a Lenovo laptop or where you're not supporting Apple by
buying a MacBook although I will throw this in there I think that Apple goes a
lot further out of their way to make it difficult to run alternate operating
systems on their computer than than Lenovo does with with Windows Lenovo
would more than happily sell Linux on their laptops that people were willing
to pay for it I don't know that Apple feels the same way sure although I would
I would argue that we've solved greater challenges and also I think you know
obviously what you say is ideal like if you know we get hardware that was ready
to go with Linux that'd be amazing in the stores that'd be great the reality
is the store experience is awful it's only getting worse and the Apple stores
are better than going to Best Buy to buy hardware from a consumer standpoint so
that's where they're gonna go and I think it's impractical if we don't
assume that not only is the MacBook appealing but that Apple is not standing
still they're gonna make better newer MacBooks like there's a rumor right now
that there's the next MacBook will only have one connector USB the new USB
reversible C connector one connector one connector you guys okay I don't know if
that's true or not but you could see a world where that happens and you know
what it's still gonna sell the reality is it's still gonna sell and if Linux
isn't there for it it's our loss yeah that's true you know and I also think
that you talked about that single connector you can guarantee there's
gonna be lots of add-on connectors so that you can adaptively connect other
legacy devices and whatnot yeah poppy did you see Lenovo's new x1 carbon
announced at CES yeah and the new x2 x0 series you know the 220 230 240
looks like they've gone back to the proper keyboard mm-hmm not the stupid
one that was on the x1 8 gigabyte max RAM yeah yeah which is stupid yes yes
yes no good that's entry-level these days really isn't it yeah yes I've got
virtual machines three doubles I have to get here okay go ahead so first I
boycott Apple products but to me this seems like it's possibly clinging to a
single example in order to move an opinion that this community tends to
lean toward other other examples I would say it was actually three examples but
yeah meeting to the fact that there was you know a caveat that their product was
aimed more towards power users which iPhone and iPad other similar mobiles
aren't you know what it really is I have a gut sense that I have a gut sense
that because when I have to sit down and use OS 10 I become very aware of
certain limitations that I think to myself anybody anybody who's sitting
there that just has a job to do you know you don't give a crap about with the
with the rest of the with the company's big overarching goals are it's really
none of your crap you know that's why I think honestly Ubuntu Mate edition is so
appealing to so many people because it is it is the representation of the idea
of the classical desktop before the vendors vision altered what the desktop
must look like so that way it matched their bold Steve Jobs Ian vision and I
think people are rebelling against that and that's why there's such a strong
appeal to Ubuntu Mate I think that same sort of undercurrent where
you're in OS 10 you feel like you're going against the grain you feel like
it's it's in an ecosystem that's not used for you you don't want any of the
native apps that is something that that it transcends a lot of people like
that's something that I think a lot of people will feel over time so that's
where some of this comes from but what we're citing is three examples Marco
Armit the Georgia Wozniak or whatever his name was and panic which is a huge
development shop for Mac and iOS so it is arbitrary examples but it's three
pretty pretty solid examples as far as examples go so there but there is an
angle that I actually liked just to bring some light to which is it seems
that people are forgetting one of the things that made Apple as successful as
they are now is exactly that they didn't have functionality and someone could
make money out of making that functionality maybe they're abusing on
the removed functionality and the people using to build things there are feeling
that pain however that's exactly what gives the money in the first place is
that the platform is lacking functionality they provide a core basis
and they give you the grounds to start running and you start running and put
the functionality in and people buy that's why there's a market there what
actually makes it even difficult to get into Linux you have almost a version of
something always there and you have to be really good on the flip side did you
see that yesterday HP announced $180 stream PC that runs Windows it's like a
Chromebox for Windows and of course the number one question is how do you put
Linux on that and could that be maybe the ultimate new low-cost Windows
machine or Linux machine ships with Windows and like you know unfortunately
yes you're voting for Windows with that purchase but if you can pull it off and
make it a cheap Linux box that could be a nice little rig too I mean how much
better are you gonna get than some of the Intel looks especially the lower
priced ones like this it's just cheaper it's like $180 well I don't think they're
gonna risk selling this in Europe as many countries imply applied a law that
allows you to avoid the Microsoft X you don't know how will they feel about it
avoid it no I don't think so I don't Italy Italy hacks least by its Supreme
Court ruled out that you cannot charge for the OS if the user rejects the
license so they actually have to refund Windows a few stories yeah I've heard a
few stories which actually works too which is really cool that's really
without it mr. corpse am I correct in in in
remembering that we have an interview with a mattei developer this weekend on
the Linux action show yes Stefano will be there well hey wimpy who is who is
Stefano will you tell the audience Stefano is the lead developer and
project lead for the Marte desktop and what should I ask him and he got you got
any burning questions oh boy I don't know ask him anything you like okay ask
him anything you like that'll be on Sunday's live access he's a super bloke
very friendly I'm looking forward to it a lot so and I think he's got good
timing alright well so that'll wrap up this week's episode of Linux unplugged
we've got links to the articles and blog posts that we discuss if you'd like to
read the numbers over for yourself you can find them in the show notes and of
course you can always go over to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact and send
in some feedback to the Linux unplugged show we like to start every episode with
your feedback so it's an important part also Linux action show dot reddit dot
com to give us your feedback we want it in our face holes so go over there put
it in there and our robots will deliver it Matt we're gonna have a great chat on
Sunday so I'll see you then all right see you then okay everybody thanks so
much for joining us oh hey why don't you join us live you can do that Tuesdays 2
p.m. Pacific Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar to get in your local
timezone jblive.tv is where it happens jblive.info for the audio you can also
find our apps on Android why not you can listen on the go thanks so much for
tuning in this week's episode of unplugged see you next Tuesday
I wasn't gonna put in the show but you know where all these Mac users are
switching to don't you don't don't don't even doubt it they're switching to arch
and gnome 3 ah don't don't doubt it don't doubt it it's happening if our
Linux is to be believed at least according to the most recent package
survey stats for the Arch Linux project Firefox comes in at the number one
browser chromium comes in at number two nano is the number one editor VI at
number two the number one desktop on Arch Linux gnome 3 followed very closely
by KDE, XFCE, Cinnamon, LXDE, Mate and Enlightenment number one file manager no
not files or Nautilus since gnome nope then are there you go I wonder how
they're measuring that though I might have to dig into the gutter together yeah
you have to have the you have to have that voluntary I forget it's like Pac
Man stats or something like that there's like a standard yeah well there's two
things there's first of all you need that stats package installed which is
like the popularity contest on Debian and Ubuntu but also you have to nominate a
package that represents that something is installed so if Thunar is the
largest user base of file manager that kind of implies that XFCE is therefore
the largest desktop deployment and that could it be that what they're using to
measure the gnome shell installs is actually some generic thing very
possible would have on the system people just prefer Thunar because I kind of
prefer it who want it for the look like the lowest you know resources so they
feel like they're telling window managers like I well and here's why I
think it might have a leg up because definitely if I'm using KDE I'm
mandatory of Thunar because if I'm gonna connect to any SMB share I want that as
a GVS mount I do not like the way Dolphin handles SMB shares so the minute
I go do anything on my network I fire up Thunar so I think a lot of KDE desktops
probably use it for that reason too because it's a really easy way to get
you know a Samba mount on your SFTP master race yeah Eric is mobile and
opinionated JBtitles.com JBtitles.com everybody both see you mentioned that HP
device that was released earlier today yeah the steam PC or the stream PC
sorry yeah this stream it is ugly ooh I like proprietary Exodus did you see
there did you see the silver and white one yeah that's still ugly yeah yeah it
does yeah it does you not order them with no OS installed from HP I don't
know no no no not these no not these stream PCs because I think Microsoft is
subsidizing part of the cost subsidy okay that's right yeah we've got a local
local computer vendor that sells the the genuine Intel NUCs and also like the
the gigabyte pocket which is a NUC style device yeah and the box does that when
you open it it's weird but they'll sell them without licenses so you can buy it
with no operating system they'll send you a form which looks very official
which says that you you waive certain things and that you you waive all of
your technical support with them because you want no operating system but you
fill out this form and they'll send you the stuff with no iOS on it that's cool
this thing is actually good on a Celeron so yeah anything you want well yeah how
do they lock you into it that's the question what are they doing to get you
to keep running Windows 8 there might be something I don't I don't like it I'm
probably missing something here but the seller on NUC is a hundred and forty
is it I thought it was I thought it was 200 no no 140 RAM is 22 bucks and you
can buy it you could use a compact flash cut 32 gigabyte compact flash card you
have the same thing except it's not you know it's not all pre-built it's not
from HP and the price is getting close but yeah I agree it doesn't look like
Tupperware I don't understand why the NUC doesn't sell more crazy I think I
think you got to put it together oh it's not that hard oh yeah people who are
buying are not gonna be wanting to do that yeah well okay you're buying them
like crazy at work let me put it to you this way anyone who's buying one of those
HP boxes to put Linux on it is it's gonna be easier to install RAM and a
hard drive and a NUC with the direction yeah way better it is to that's true by
that agent and then you can get out installing Linux on these things
probably know how to put a RAM and hard drive yeah well exactly