Who says you can't have fun in your terminal? Wes found SSHtron. Multiplayer Tron in your
terminal. That's awesome. You just SSH to SSHtron.ZackLotta.com. We'll have a link in
the show notes.
Oh yeah.
And you can play Multiplayer Tron in your terminal window. I love it, Wes. Good find.
SSHtron for the win. That's it right there.
You didn't even know it was missing from your life, but it was.
Show's over. We're done.
Yeah, we're just going to be busy playing this, so entertain yourselves.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 231 for January 9th, 2018.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's ready to kill the Gen 2 challenge
in its face.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
This should be it right here. This should be the final Gen 2 challenge episode, but
we'll have to wait and see, because first we have to get through a packed show. Yes,
my friends, 2018 is starting off with a bang. We'll give you a snapshot on where Linux is
specifically with Meltdown and Spectre. Then we'll get into a couple of new releases that
might be some of the best open source software you're not using. It's great. Then, I say
the perfect Linux workstation is Ni. The absolute perfect desktop to run Linux is Ni, and it's
well under $1,000. We'll talk about that. Plus, our friends over at elementary have
a new app, looking pretty good. Then the register says buckle up. It's going to be the year
of Gnome, and it's going to be the year of Ubuntu. They got a couple of notes on how
it's going to just be a blowout year. We'll talk about that whole Lenovo firmware bug
that cropped up while we were off the air. We'll touch on that. Then, Telegram's got
a cryptocurrency. Then, Wes, it's back. Linspire returns. Our old friend. The old Linspire.
Remember Lindos, then Linspire? Remember Xandros? Yeah. They've only been merged together and
relaunched. Linspire 7.0 launched this week, and I paid the $80 license fee to download
it-
You got your hands on it.
... and give it a shot.
Look at you.
I bought it so you don't have to, because you can't just download Linspire. No, no.
You have to buy a $79 license, which includes an install media, which works out to be $94,
all told.
The things you do for the audience.
I'll give you my take on the new Linspire. I went into it with a bit of a bias, like
$95, $95, and then I started to use it. It might be the best XFCE desktop I've ever used.
Hey, boy. Wow.
I don't know. It's early days, but it blew me away. If I could get it installed and running,
it'd really impress me. We'll tell you more about that. Then, towards the end of the show,
at least, my God, I hope, Wes, it is the final chapter of the Gen 2 Challenge.
Well, yeah, we're switching everything over to Linspire. Gen 2 was 2017, so, Wes.
The most hated segment of all time. But you know what? Damned if we didn't actually get
a little morsel out of this segment. Wes and I were talking about it before the show, and
we genuinely walked away with a lesson. What the hell is Gen 2 for? What good is Gen 2
for? What's its place in 2018 in Linux? I think we figured it out, and I think it's
extremely important. In fact, I think it's sort of as important as Linux itself is. We'll
talk about that, and we'll hopefully wrap up the Gen 2 Challenge.
But before we go even a moment further, we've got to say hola to our virtual log. Time-appropriate
greetings, Mumble Room. Hello. Hello. Happy New Year's, everybody. Take a moment from
playing SSH Tron, and let's update everybody on Meltdown and Spectre. You and Beard touched
on this last week, because it was sort of like this awkward, there's something coming.
The pre-release, yeah. Really, it wasn't supposed to be announced until today. Today was the
day the embargo was supposed to be lifted, and today was actually the day we were supposed
to learn about Meltdown and Spectre. In a different universe. Yeah. So we have some
great coverage coming out of JB. I'll just say that right now. Later today, the Ask Noah
program is doing a special on Meltdown and Spectre, and Noah is bringing on Brandon Johnson
from Red Hat to talk about their work with it, which I think is going to be an extremely
interesting insight. And then later in the week, Wes and I are doing a hell of a roundup
on Meltdown and Spectre. There's still a big part of the story that hasn't been told. We're
going to have a complete timeline, a concise timeline of how everything went down. Lots
of interesting tidbits there. So there's more coverage to come. So with that said, just
a quick state of the union for Linux as we record this episode. In brief, Meltdown is
a CPU vulnerability. It works by using modern processors out of order execution to read
arbitrary kernel memory location, which could include personal data like passwords, SSL
key information. And then there's Spectre, a second issue. Spectre breaks down the barriers
between different applications. So you could theoretically use it to trick applications
into accessing arbitrary programs, not kernel, but arbitrary program memory locations. Spectre
is harder to exploit than Meltdown, but it's also harder to mitigate. It's more of like
a design issue. So it's going to be something we'll be hearing more about through 2018.
There's probably going to be more patches coming upstream from Linux. So it's probably
just the beginning of this story. As far as Meltdown is concerned, this is where we have
some of the most traction with patches. Work is continuing though. The latest updates of
the upstream stable Linux kernel 4.14.2 have current patches. Some people may experience
boot problems with this release, however, so don't jump to get it. 4.14.13 will be out
in just a few days. And patches have also been added to the old 4.4 and 4.9 stable kernel
trees.
Yeah, I've seen a lot of questions expressed about those backports though. So if security
is really your concern, it'll probably be best to have the most recent kernel available.
Yeah. And Greg Cage has sort of been advising that and 4.14 and 4.15 are getting those.
There's still a lot of things that are happening. And it's obvious that the kernel team had
more time to prep for Meltdown than they did Spectre. It's a totally different story. There's
really no official like blessed Greg KH Linus Spectre patches at this point. There's different
distributions that have solutions, but there's nothing that's been blessed by upstream yet.
It's really all still shaken out.
Yeah, yeah. I've been seeing Red Hat issue kernel updates for the two series Linux kernel.
Oh boy.
Yeah. Canonical has been updating people on the status of their patches for Ubuntu, same
with other distributions. And there's been reports of performance impacts on certain
workloads, specifically cloud workloads that have a lot of say disk and network IO.
And where security is particularly important.
And that's sort of going to be the big story. Don't you think bashful long term?
Absolutely. There's some people that are reporting up to 40% CPU spikes. And there's a ton of
stuff where when they have auto scaling set on for something like Amazon or whatever,
and then also their bills are just bouncing way up because what used to be an adequate
workload for what they had deployed is now auto scaling up and they're getting hammered
with the bills.
Yeah, yeah. And we, I think we'll probably talk more about this on TechSnap and get deeper
into that or on Coder Radio maybe too. I was thinking about it, but this is going to really
impact the Jupyter broadcasting development audience.
And you know, really, it's no fun for anyone, especially when you when you go into something
like cloud computing. So that way you can budget like a certain set cost. And then all
of a sudden, like you got to have a bar. Yeah. So we'll get more into that later. But I also
wanted to say if you've been speculating, I know this affects all kinds of different
processors. What about GPUs? The answer is, yeah, yeah. Nvidia graphics drivers have been
updated to address vulnerabilities. In the show notes, we have linked a Ubuntu security
notice that covers 1710, 1704, 1604 and 1404. And it's the same thing. Jan Horn discovered
that microprocessors utilizing speculative execution and branch prediction may allow
unauthorized memory reads via side channel attacks. And guess what? Nvidia's GPUs take
advantage of that little trick as well. So you got to get fast. I mean, yeah, yeah. You
got to get Nvidia driver 384.111 to get that fix on Ubuntu. Good to know. Yeah. So there
is oh, and then also there's news today or yesterday that but it's been updated today
that Microsoft has halted the meltdown inspector patches for Windows 10 after AMD machines
were reported as unbootable.
Yeah, it seems like there's a lot of difficult patches. And as always, it's a, you know,
patching is sometimes it's true. Sometimes it's like, okay, two packages got upgraded.
But especially when it's your kernel, you got to be careful.
It's interesting that Microsoft can really turn the dial on this one. So they can just
go, all right, well, we're going to continue pushing patches, but not for machines with
AMD processors. Like they can get really granular on what client machines receive updates. They
have a very tight control.
Yeah, cloud connectivity, Chris.
Oh, oh, oh. So yeah, not a good day for our Windows users either. Ask Noah, if you're
on the live stream comes on right after Linux unplugged. Now, we're doing like a Linux blowout
afternoon.
It's perfect. You just sit down in the afternoon, hang out with us for a couple of hours and
have a great time.
That crazy guy's working on integrating mumble with the phone call system too. So you can
hang on. Yeah, join the virtual lug during the show. And then you just hang tight. And
you can participate in Ask Noah right with your same mumble setup. And so yeah, he'll
be taking calls and be discussing Spectre and Meltdown with his guests. So that'll be
coming up more.
I think go over to TechSnap.Systems and subscribe to our feed there because I have a suspicion
that this is a story that is just beginning and there's going to be a waning period where
people sort of get tired of it. But what we're going to do with, I would suspect, what we
always do with TechSnap is we continue to monitor story and find interesting nuggets
that maybe aren't getting reported on very much and just continue to follow it for a
while.
Three, six, nine months, pieces of this are going to be popping up.
Yeah, exactly. So we'll probably, long term, you'll probably see a lot of coverage there.
Now, anybody in the mumble room want to talk about this big story before we move on? Oh,
Batchful, you said you had some crashes at work. I didn't see that.
Yeah, a couple of the guys are doing some testing for our internal stuff. And there's
like a reg file that you actually have to import. And they've now said, don't do it
because we started getting a bunch of systems dropping out due to that. So now we're waiting.
We had to go and pull it back out. And now it's just a wait and see thing.
Yeah. Yeah, I have a sense that, you know, and it's unfortunate there's not only the
performance issues, but there's apparently some stability issues and other side effects.
And at the same time, you know that there has been developers and other people that
have just been working their butts off to get this stuff out in time, especially when
it was disclosed earlier than it should have been. So you got to take them up and say thank
you to these people, these unnamed faceless people who were working over the holidays,
working through Christmas and New Year's to try to get this stuff together. And it might
not be perfect yet. But my God, where would we be without them?
Right. It's definitely a scramble. And there are people doing the scrambling.
Yeah. So you got to in one moment, you got to go, okay, thank you, guys. Appreciate the
hard work you're doing out there.
It really just it just sucks. We did CPUs wrong.
Everything is ruined.
We all have to pay.
It's all bad. We're actually it's funny. We're gonna get back to that in a moment. We're
gonna go back to the good old days before processors were broken. But before we go there,
I want to give a shout out to two open source projects that I bet you're not using that
you really should be. And I'm guilty of this myself. So I may be projecting. But first
project that had an update since last episode is Shotcut, a really good video editor on
Linux. It's I don't understand why we don't talk about it. It has one of the features
that Rekai and I like the most in Final Cut 10, which is it renders preview stills and
waveforms in line with your media. So it's all together and it makes it easy to skim
and preview. Yeah. And it's got good performance. And they just added a feature that I am particularly
interested in. It's an audio spectrum visualization filter, which we use for a lot of our audio
only shows. And we use a series of Python scripts and whatnot. But this may be a way
to do one offs in a new and interesting way. So Shotcut just had a new update just a couple
of days ago. It's released 18.01. And it just it's I think maybe the best open source video
editor you're not using. And it doesn't have as much hype as some of the other ones. But
it's just been so steadily awesome. So Shotcut, shotcut.org for that. And then I know you're
not using this one because y'all keep talking about Evernote replacements and killers. And
the reality is, we've had an Evernote killer for for ages now. It's even been an app pick
on the Linux action show. Oh, yeah, I remember that. And it just got even better. So just
a couple of days ago, an interesting naming scheme again, 18.01.1 of qownotes has been
replaced. Now this is a plain text notepad with markdown support and own cloud slash
next cloud syncing integration. And one of the things they've recently added that I'm
all on board with, and it's it is a full featured really well done application. Don't let the
queue throw you off. If you're like a gnome desktop or a unity user or whatever. It is
it is great. It is a well designed cute application. But one of the things that they've added recently
that I really appreciate is they've you've always been able to kind of create like to
do lists and whatnot. But now you've actually got the ability to check items off in your
notes. So you can create a list of these are the things I've got to do today. And then
when you're done, you can go in there and check them off. That's awesome. It's a simple
thing, but it makes such a difference for my note taking application. I use the share
of this for like, about to hit the road and I need to do a checklist of all the stuff
I got to bring all the equipment we got to bring to go do like a live show. So useful.
And the fact that you can then sync on the back end with different open source solutions.
You can do small little like note windows that just take up tiny bits of space. Or you
can do like a full featured thing that allows you browse your tags and your your different
categories and has multi column live preview of the markdown like you can go all out or
you can just have it be this tiny little window on your desktop. It's one of my favorite cute
applications for Linux. It's a it is better than an Evernote replacement because it's
using markdown. It uses next cloud. And I don't know I don't know why we don't talk
about it more. So I just thought since they had a new release, they just pumped out a
new version that now lets you check things off. It's time to install that just right
now because that's half of what I would do. Right? Yeah, that's a that's a great app pick.
I've been looking for a placement for Zim Wiki for a long time. Yeah, I think this is
it. Yeah, this looks terrific. Yeah, I've even been wondering if we couldn't use this
for production of our shows instead of using slack and Google Docs or whatever else. Seems
like this is just got a lot of potential. So I think 2018 may be the year of QO notes
for me. I have to give some love to my next cloud instance first. Plus, there's a new
version of next cloud that's just around the corner. So I may let that land first and then
do this. But I feel like it's fair. I feel like it's happening. Apparently, you can also
import from Evernote to QO notes. Oh, yeah. Yeah. So stop talking about Evernote alternatives,
because QO notes has been here for a while. And they got the new update 1801 dot one,
which just came out. And I love it. I think there's tools like that, that we like we don't
really fully like wrap our head around yet that are that make Linux competitive desktop.
But you got to have great hardware, too. Yeah, oh, yeah. It's not just about like getting
a great LTS release or getting a great rolling release and getting your favorite desktop.
You also need to run it on the best hardware possible. And we've all we've all seen different
different different solutions for like the ultimate Linux workstation ones you build
yourself. Dell just recently updated the XPS 13, which looks like a killer laptop. I thought
you're supposed to use a Raspberry Pi. And that was that was the end of the story. Is
that not you're telling me that we can do more? Oh, well, well, there's a machine on
the horizon that wimpy and I have been talking about to each other offline for ages now.
And we finally with CES in full swing, have details on what I think is going to be 2018
perfect Linux desktop. And it's a NUC. It's the Intel Hades Canyon NUC with the dedicated
quote unquote, Radeon graphics that comes on the Intel CPU. Oh, and then you combine
that with Thunderbolt three ports, super fast disk, the latest Intel processors. Wimpy,
what do you think? This has got to be the desktop of the year, right?
I'm really hoping so. And I'm going to find out by buying one the day they say I'm very
tempted to. It's a weird situation to be in. So we talked about this a little bit on user
error, Episode 40. I've been following I've been tracking the the rumors about this device
for some months now. I have its predecessor. So this is I have the Skull Canyon NUC. And
I'm in a weird position where I've been so happy with the Skull Canyon NUC. I've been
pining for its replacement almost since I got it because I was like, if this is so good,
what's the next one going to be like? And here it is. We've now seen it announced CES
2018.
And are you satisfied?
Yes, I mean, there is there is nothing about this specification of this device that I'm
unhappy about. I'm really looking forward to getting one. Yeah, yeah. I don't find it
wanting if I was going to be really nitpicky. The only thing I would say is I can't upgrade
it to 64 gigs of RAM, I can only go to 32. Which is what I have in the current NUC. But
then the flip side of that is when I get this one, I will just be able to pop my old one
open, remove the two M2 SSDs, remove the RAM, plug them into the new one, plug my Razer
core into one of the Thunderbolt ports and power it on and I'm back in business on a
whole new hardware platform. Yeah, that's you know, almost instantly.
Yeah. The one other thing I would have asked for is two is because it has one Thunderbolt
three bus, two Thunderbolt three buses, like maybe four USB-C type would have been amazing.
I do like this. Yeah, that's true. And if I put my storage over Ethernet instead of
over Thunderbolt, then that's probably fine. There's six display options on this right
because it's two Thunderbolt three, there's two mini DVI, sorry mini DisplayPort and there's
two HDMI. The HDMI are both HDMI 2.0A with HDCP 2.2. I mean, it's absolutely spec'd to
the max. Oh, there is a third USB-C port on the front of it. So there is technically three
USB-C ports. It's just one Thunderbolt three bus.
There's also internal headers for USB ports. Really? Yeah, it's totally tripped. I really
love it. It's a bit fatter than the one that I have. But then again, the skull on the new
one is illuminated with red and blue LEDs. So you know, you can't really go wrong. Yeah,
yeah, it's it's still smaller than a Mac Mini. I think the thing I want to see is power V
USB-C. Yeah, that's just too much of a machine for that, though. I think it takes this machine
draws 6.32 amps. With similar capacities that do it? Yeah, maybe. Maybe. I don't know. 6
amps is... Maybe for the lower power model, the 65 watt model, you might be able to power
over USB-C. But the larger one that's 100 watt, I don't think you can do over USB-C.
Yeah, I can't imagine. Certainly my USB-C charger is all capped at like 65 watts, I
think. I'm just reading. I'm reading the specs. It's 120 watt adapter, 19 volts at 16.32 amps
is what the specs are for it. Man, I really like this thing. So the and so not only is
it tiny, but it's quiet too, right? Yours is pretty quiet, Wimpy. Yeah, my my NUC is
quiet. Obviously, my 1080 Ti in a Razer Core is a little bit louder. Yeah, but thankfully
through the magic of directional microphones, you can't hear it. But you have the ability
to dynamically switch between the external GPU in the Razer Core and the internal Intel
GPU, correct? Yes. In fact, up until two days ago, that's how I was running things. So when
we spoke about this a few weeks ago, I had one of my monitors exclusively powered by
the IGP in the NUC and the other monitor exclusively powered by the 1080 Ti in the Razer Core.
And the acceleration was on one monitor with the 1080 Ti. And I could, it's a seamless
X session. There's a little bit of magic in the way you need to set this up. But I can
drag windows between the two monitors and you can watch the 3D performance drop off
as you drag it from the Nvidia accelerated screen to the Intel accelerated screen. But
over the weekend, I've actually changed my setup. So I now have display ports out of
the back of the 1080 Ti to both monitors. So I'm not using the internal IGP at all now.
I'm driving both monitors just off the 1080 Ti. And I've actually had the happy coincidence
of a performance boost through doing that, which I can't explain. Do you think there's
going to be an advantage to this dedicated bastardization of an Intel processor with
an AMD GPU? I mean, that's sort of the big story about this NUC. Yeah, I mean, it's certainly
got a lot of people scratching their heads and excited in that you've got an Intel CPU
package with an AMD graphics skew on the side. A skew that it could be possible to use entirely
free graphics drivers. Yeah, absolutely. So you referred to it as Radeon graphics, but
specifically the branding here is this is RX Vega mobile graphics. And I don't know
much about how the consoles are manufactured, the PS4 and the Xbox 1S and 1X, but they obviously
have a combination of Intel CPU and Radeon graphics as well. So I wonder if this is an
evolution of that package. And maybe this is maybe the smallest games console that's
yet to hit the market. No kidding. Maybe future games consoles are going to be built around
similar architectures. Well, have you seen that they're pitching it, the 999 US greenback
version as a VR ready machine? Yeah, yeah, I have. Nobody cares about VR. No, of course
not. Yeah, there is. So the other thing about the NUC that I really, really appreciate besides
its size and its low noise profile, is that they've really built the storage ideally.
So the core platform is set up so that the M.2 slots, and there's two of them, I believe,
and the Thunderbolt controller, by the way, are hooked up directly to PCIe lanes right
off the PCH. So you have super high bandwidth hungry things like disk or Thunderbolt peripherals
that get dedicated PCIe lanes right to the CPU, which means your disk is sitting right
next to the CPU. It's got a fast track lane to the CPU. And so you combine the latest
Intel CPUs with storage that's wired directly to the CPU, and it makes for a very fast combination.
Yeah. And right now, in fact, on the model that I have the the M.2 SATA ports are both
MVME and they've both got their own dedicated lanes. So the disk performance is excellent.
What I'm really excited about in this model is I've currently got one USB Thunderbolt
port, and I have the 1080Ti connected to that. But I also have a HDMI capture card that I
can connect over Thunderbolt 3 and mimic a third screen through this capture device,
but I can't have both running at the same time. So I'm now kind of excited by this one
because I could have both of those things connected up.
I think this is going to be like I say...
And another one at the front.
I think this might be, you know, I find the XPS 13 extremely appealing. Maybe Dell can
convince me otherwise. I've invited Barton George from Dell on the show next week if
it works for him to talk about the new Dell hardware. But, you know, with the price of
Bitcoin dropping, I'm going to be more selective.
You have to watch.
2018 is going to be more selective. And if I can only buy one machine, I think it's this
one.
I actually had one of those new XPS 13s in my shopping basket on Sunday evening, and
the additional accessories I wanted. And I was sitting there hovering over the buy button,
thinking to myself, this will make my fourth XPS 13. Do I need a fourth XPS? And I eventually
decided to bail on the purchase and decided that I didn't need a fourth one of these just
yet. And I'm kind of glad I did because then the next day this device gets announced. And
I think it's going to come on the market in March, which is ahead of the projections that
I'd seen rumored of around June. So yeah, I'm going to hang on to my money and get one
of these in March.
I've been trying to convince Wes of this for about a year is I'm becoming a big fan of
the powerful central desktop that is permanently attached to my large NAS storage. So I can
run services like AmbientPlex directly on my quote unquote workstation. And then on
the edge, my edge devices can be phones, can be low end, you know, 2012 laptops that don't
need to be all that powerful because I can either remote in using X2GO to my machine
and then have my full power available. Or really what I have done is I've set up a series
of queue jobs where I have different folders in Dropbox. And when I drop files in there,
they sync to my powerful workstation and kick off different jobs for me. And so my theory
is invest in a central desktop like a NUC that could be attached to local NAS storage.
I mean, this thing's going to have dual gigabit networking. I could just dedicate one of those
to an iSCSI or NFS purpose and then the other one connected to the rest of the networking.
Then you could hook up external GPUs when I need to game and when I quote unquote need
to game. And if I don't, I could just use the baked in AMD GPU, which is going to be
great, which will support free sync, could have an entirely free open source driver stack.
And it's going to be the ideal machine to be running during the Wayland transition,
I suspect.
Yeah. And it's just refreshing, especially when you've run a bunch of random machines
with different manufacturers doing the motherboard and doing all these internals. As Wimpy said,
it does just feel tricked out and it feels like a proper computer that you can be proud
of.
The other thing that I am taking some comfort in, and I bet you agree, Wimpy, is this appears
to be a product that Intel is going to continue to invest in because the NUC now has been
around for ages and they've been steadily improving it. So it's something where you
could buy the Skull Canyon NUC last year and you essentially had full confidence that there
was going to be another NUC for you to upgrade to. And that's also kind of nice because when
you're buying some of these machines, sometimes the different OEMs will start up a product
line and they'll have it going for a year or two and then their upstream ODM changes
things up and they have to cancel that product line and launch an entirely new product line.
And there's no congruency there. There's no, you know, continuance, continuancy there.
Yeah. Now, while I appreciate that this new Hades Canyon NUC is not cheap by any means,
I think the 65 watt model is going to, is rumored to be $799 and the 100 watt model
is rumored to be $999. But what I'm able, and that comes without disks or SSDs, it comes
without RAM and it comes without an operating system. But those three parts are interchangeable
for me. So I'm going to take the RAM and the SSDs out of my old model and plug them into
this one. I don't have to buy those this time around.
And your eGPU as well.
And I'm going to plug my eGPU in and I'm off to the races. So I actually anticipate the
upgrade is going to be the time it takes me to unscrew one, remove the parts, plug them
into the other and put the lids back on.
That's what I'm talking about. That's what I'm talking about. And as a work station,
as a work station where you work and you want it to be reliable and you want to have minimal
fuss, that is, even if it only works for two models, even if you can only pull this off
from the Skull Canyon to the Hades Skull Canyon or whatever, the Hades, even if it
only happens once, that is so worth it. That kind of smooth, keep going about your day,
kind of, it's going to take you the time to reassemble and disassemble. That is so valuable.
That's what I'm talking about. The same thing here is we bought early on when the NUCs were
brand new and they were those cute little squares.
Yeah, I've had a couple of those too.
Yeah, it was the same.
I have some of those.
Yeah, it was the same thing as we were able to move the parts between them and that brought
a certain glue and duct tapeness to them. We could just stick them wherever we needed
them. They weren't always even the best machine for the job, but because they were so flexible
and so easy to move parts in, you could just stick them wherever you needed them. It is
supremely useful. So yeah, this will probably be the generation I buy in. I kind of wish
I got this Skull Canyon. It just didn't really work out, but I think this will be the year
hopefully. Maybe we'll have reviews. I'm sure you'll have a review, if nothing else, on
the Fantastic Ubuntu podcast when it returns.
Well, that's still undecided.
Of course, of course. Yes, of course it is.
Christmas break. We are very much pre-curry at this point.
Has curry been scheduled?
No, no, we haven't scheduled curry yet.
Oh, okay.
No, we are in full Christmas New Year break, not even talking about it to one another at
the moment.
Amazing. I can't even fathom.
What a world.
I can't even fathom.
Yeah, it's some sort of utopia. Speaking of utopia, why not switch over to a mobile utopia?
Go to ting, linux.ting.com. It's a smarter way to do mobile because you only pay for
what you freaking use. I know. They just take your minutes, your messages, and your megabytes,
and they put them all together, and they're like, okay, guess what, homes? Six dollars
for the line. Then your usage. That's it. That's it.
What about like weird fees? Do I have to like sign a five-year deal to get that sweet price?
No contracts. In fact, you could try it for a month, and you could say, screw you, I'm
out of here, and there's no termination fee. In fact, if you want to turn it on and turn
it off, you could do that. I have two myfis from Ting, one that I leave on all the time,
and then one that I only leave on when I'm traveling because it's CDMA, and I'm like,
eh, you know, but it's great for when I'm traveling. I just go to linux.ting.com, I
log into my ass, I turn it on. It's so straightforward. Six dollars a month for the device means that
if you need a go-to line for a monitoring device, for something in your IT bag, it's
easy. But if you want to use it as your full service, you feel like you're hacking the
system, you know? You feel like you're hacking the system because you can download your audio
books and your podcasts, and you can pin your music on Wi-Fi, and then if you don't take
calls while you're driving, I mean, for me, when I'm commuting just between work and home,
I'm like some sort of new-age, non-cell using guy. You wouldn't even think I had a cellphone.
I don't talk to anybody on the phone when I'm driving. That's crazy. And don't even
text me. I'm using the, I'm using iOS 11. You know what I turned on? You know what they
got in that thing?
What do they got? What do they got?
They got this, they got this system where it automatically using the accelerometer and
the Wi-Fi chipset, when it notices that you're blasting past Wi-Fi access points like a maniac,
the phone goes, oh, you're driving. You're driving. Let me turn on do not disturb mode.
Wasn't that nice?
So people, when they text me, they get a message back going, homeboy's driving. Do you really
need to interrupt him? Is it that important? You what? You got nothing else to do right
now? What's your big deal?
Yeah, why are you so bored?
You're so important?
Get your life on.
So they get like this thing that comes back, tells them to shut the hell up so they don't
bother me.
So you're happy already right there.
And I don't, I don't have to deal with nothing. I just listen to my podcasts.
Drive it along.
You're never spending a dime on cellular because you just pay for what you use. Six dollars
for the line, you pay for what you use. Go to linux.ting.com and I got a suggestion.
You need a phone? Do you need a phone?
Yeah. Oh, who doesn't?
What do you got?
Me?
Do you have the Pixel?
I do have the Pixel.
But you don't really need a phone.
But I mean, maybe, maybe I need a phone.
You will. What about like a backup phone?
Well, when you drop that thing.
Or when I, yeah, when I smashed this to tiny little bits.
So everybody knows that some of the best Android experiences are the Motorola devices. Check
this out. Motorola G5s Plus. Two hundred and fifty dollars when you go to linux.ting.com.
No contract. It's new. It's a multi-network CDMA and GSM. So you can just pick whatever
works best in your area. And you can even deactivate and reactivate. It's got 32 gigs
of storage. Goes up to 128 gigs with S, with an external SD.
Oh, I love that.
MicroSD.
I know. More phones need to have MicroSD. Also has turbocharging so you can charge,
you can get six hours of battery in 15 minutes.
Nice.
And it has a super high resolution. It's a 5.5 inch screen. But it's a 400, 401 PPI
density.
Oh, that's good. Yeah.
Yeah. And it's got a fingerprint unlock. All metal design. Android 7.1 with Android 8 update
coming soon.
It sounds like flagship features without a flagship price, Chris.
Two hundred and fifty, two hundred and fifty four dollars. You completely own it outright.
No contract. No agreements. Nothing. Two hundred and fifty four dollars. You completely own
this phone. You get a great Android experience. 8.0 is coming down the pipeline. Fingerprint
reader. 401 PPI screen. And you pay for what you use.
It's obvious. Linux.ting.com. Go there. Get $25 off the device. Or if you want to bring
one, if you've got something that's compatible, check their BYOD page. They'll give you service
credit. Linux.ting.com. And thank you to Ting for sponsoring this here unplugged program.
So Cassidy James over at elementary OS wrote up a post on the medium blog that elementary,
I think that's how it works. I don't, I don't get medium, but my, my, my vague understanding
is, is you can have a medium blog and elementary has a medium blog. And over there, Cassidy
wrote about a new tool that's coming to elementary desktop users. And I thought, who better to
pick the brain of than regular friend of the show, Mr. Mr. Dan the rabbit. Yeah. So Mr.
Daniel Fore joins us and from the elementary project with I, what I perceived to be has
to be the only scoop on this, right? Nobody better to go to than, well, except for maybe
Cassidy since he wrote the post. Well, we got Dan. So Dan, what can you tell us about
a, what may be a renamed to something that may be named code soon?
Okay. So I guess the big, the big thing about it is it's not really necessarily a new thing.
It's a new old thing. So we've been working, um, we released our scratch text editor in
like 2011, right? Like when we did a Luna way back in the day and hacking on this thing
for ages kind of came to a point with it where we sat down and kind of thought about, okay,
what's the point of this app? Like, what is it supposed to do? Is it for notes? Is it
for hacking on code? Is it, you know, what, what's, what do we do with this app? And we
finally decided, you know, this is an app that we use every day for programming. And
so we're going to rebrand it. We're going to change all the defaults and we're going
to make it a great code editor and not just a generic text editor.
I think this is, this is great. It looks good too. Now I have so many questions that come
to mind when I hear this. So first of all, do you, okay, uh, boy, I don't want to forget
them. So I'm going to tell you what they both are. Number one, do you think people are going
to use this over say Adam or visual studio code or sublime text or insert whatever builder
or, and, and known builder? Yeah, that's that. Yeah. And, um, uh, do you foresee that a large,
do you, do you perceive, I guess I should say that a large portion of the elementary
os user base are developers or do you, are they more end users? This seems like, um,
I don't know. This is, I love it. I think it's, I think it looks great. I think it's
a great idea, but I also wonder if it's a little bit of, of, um, of, um, a result of,
of an echo chamber or a bubble. Um, I mean, well, to answer the first question, uh, definitely
at least, um, we use it all the time and we hear about people who use it cause they're,
they're filing issue reports and tweeting at us and stuff like that. Um, so we know
that there's a good amount of people that prefer having a native app to a, um, like
a cross platform or electronic. Yeah. Yeah. I would be one of those people. Yeah. Yeah.
Just for performance and integration features. Um, I mean, there's, there's niceties in code
that you get like, uh, so in the latest version of terminal, we have style schemes now. And
if you use the terminal plugin in code and you change your style scheme in the terminal
app, the terminal plugin and code will match the new style. Cool. There's a lot of little
niceties like that where it's the apps are integrated with each other and they feel
native. So there's, there's come some compelling reasons to use code instead of using a different
a text editor app like Adam. Yeah. But, uh, and your second question was, I'm sorry, what
was it?
I mean, do you see a large portion of your user base, um, wanting something like this?
Do you see a lot of developers on elementary or is it mostly just you guys that are the
developers on elementary? Well, we're definitely, um, we're working with a new, uh, large third
party ecosystem of developers. Uh, we just crossed 70 apps in an app center. So a huge
part of our focus on our mission lately has been making sure that we have a really great
developer story for them and including great developer tools out of the box, I think is
part of that story. Right. Of course you, you want to make it easier for people to make
applications for elementary desktop users, even if it's not a huge portion of the user
base people that are, there's going to be some people that are using the desktop to
create applications for users. That makes a lot of sense. I think it looks great. So,
um, all right. Can people get their hands on it right now? Or is this is like the final
like quote unquote code version when it's completely become code. Is that going to be
something that isn't a future release? Well, you can go pull a get master. It's open source
up at a github.com forward slash elementary forward slash code. That's super easy, right?
But, um, we will, we are doing the, the stable release of code will come with our Juno update,
which is the next release of elementary OS. Hmm. So Juno is going to be based on 1804.
That's correct. Oh man. You know, you know, I want to ask you like how long until after
1804, but I know you don't have an answer for me, but just to set expectations, do you
want to, do you want to like, like, um, set any kind of expectations, how long Juno may
be until we actually are downloading it and installing it on our systems? Well, I can
tell you that we're testing a 1804 daily builds right now and that we've been, um, building
all of our apps on 1710 before that in preparation. So we have a lot of major migration work and
regression testing already done. Um, uh, so we're really hoping to get as close as possible
to that 1804 release date, uh, maybe give a little padding so that we're not overlapping
with their press releases. But, um, we're, we're really going to try as hard as possible
to get it out right away. You know, it's interesting. It's awesome Daniel. Yeah. Go you. Yeah, it
is really good. Thanks. And I, I think, um, I've, I've been looking at elementary OS in
a different perspective as Ubuntu is getting better for some reason. Like I, I, I look
at 1804 based on gnome and I think this is going to be, this is going to be the development
workstation to compete with. 1804 is going to be canonicals second crack at shipping
a gnome desktop. And I'll say that 1710 is essentially the beta test for 1804. And so
they, they're, they're trying out a lot of stuff in 1710 and what you're going to get
with 1804 is the best of what worked on top of that. Ubuntu is enjoying, um, quite a bit
of brand recognition at the moment, quite a bit of industry support. And from all indications,
snaps seem to be also increasing in industry support. So these, these things are all coming
together I think. And plus then you combine things like the new XPS 13 and this NUC that's
coming along, it's going to just be an undoubtedly great solid Linux workstation. Uh, it, to
me it seems like 1804 is going to be uniquely competitive in its, um, draw to developers
and the Sputnik type users that Dell seems success with their sales. But at the same
time elementary OS seems very poised to sort of take advantage of some of the same momentum.
And um, it could come down to your desktop has less rough edges than the gnome experience
and that's enough to sway a certain percentage of people. It could come down to the native
applications are more appealing to a certain set of users than having everything as an
electron on your Ubuntu desktop. Um, and so I, I am, I am really, I am really interested
in the Juno release because it's going to be released in such a competitive year for
Linux desktops because we're not even talking about like the work that Fedora is doing.
And so it's just going to be a fascinating, fascinating release to watch. And, um, I,
I am, I think I, at least I hope, I think you guys are going to be better positioned
the closer you are to the 1804 release, the better positions you are to be considered
a, you know, an alternative. Um, and uh, code and, and, and, and things like that I think
are a really good step in that direction. I, I'll tell you what, if you, when things
get closer, if you want to, if you want a very particular beta tester, let me know.
I'd be happy to kick the tires a bit to give you some feedback because I'm really excited
about the release. Definitely, definitely. And I'd love to talk to you more about it
on the show too, as we come up with more announcements of what we're going to be working on and we're
doing. Um, we recently kind of switched, uh, Loki over into maintenance mode and we had
been doing these, uh, monthly updates posts for lucky. Right. So I like that going forward,
um, we're going to be trying to make at least monthly posts about all the new features that
are coming into Juneau as they land. I, I think if you are, and not you, I mean just
like the proverbial, like people out there that are, that are releasing distributions,
if um, you didn't watch what happened with 1710 and did rocks blog posts that communicated
where they were going with 1710 and how, how dramatically that impacted the perception and
reception to Ubuntu 1710, then you're asleep at the wheel. If you are, if you are running
any distribution out there and didn't learn a lesson from how that communication made
a huge difference, then I, I, you're, you probably ought to just give up because that's,
I know it's difficult because it takes a ton of effort to make a great blog post like that.
It takes somebody who actually knows what's going on. You got to get screenshots. It is,
it is more effort than we'd like to admit it is, but the rewards are so high and um,
you guys are getting there with, with these, I, I've been in, I've been, I didn't expect
it throughout the Loki release. I did not, I didn't expect the updates on what's going
on and every time they've, they've landed on the blog, I've been like, that's great.
That gives us something to talk about. It makes the, it makes the distribution, um,
a relevant topic for the week. Yeah. You get an idea of what their focus is. It's like,
you can observe something over a longer period of time and get a better idea. Yes. Yeah.
So good on you. Glad to hear it. Sounds like you guys learned some of those lessons watching
the 1710 release too. And uh, boy, I just, I feel bad for the distributions that haven't
figured that out yet. Um, well good, Dan, keep us posted. I'm looking forward to hearing
that. Now the register has a story where they make the case that, um, it's going to be the
year of gnome and that when you add in flat pack and snaps, it could be a new revolution
for the Linux desktop. Um, that's right. It only took our first episode in 2018 for us
to call it as the year of the Linux desktop. Thank you, register. Um, so I guess we should
mention since our last episode, uh, where I was on it in, in, in 2017, there was a bug
rise. We got off the air that became public that, um, 1710 was causing some issues on
some Lenovo laptops and it was, uh, apparently it was the Intel SBI driver, which allows
for bios firmware updates, which is I guess not primetime ready. And uh, so that's still
kind of going on as, as we talk about this. So 1710 has, has been a great release except
for that whole laptop thing. Um, I haven't followed it closely. Wimpy, is there any,
do you have any anecdotes or any additional information or state status of where it's
at right now before I move on from it? Uh, yeah, I tell you what, I'll paste something
in the discourse, uh, discord just quickly. Yeah. All right. Uh, that's, that's the link
to the ISO testing for the re spin of the 1710 ISOs for Ubuntu and all the flavors.
So that testing is happening now and the release is scheduled for Thursday, the 11th of January.
And um, boy, so 1710 has been unavailable that entire time. Uh, it has for main Ubuntu.
Yeah. Um, so, but the, the thing is, is that everyone thinks that this is an Ubuntu problem
and it wasn't the case. Other distributions have had this problem. It's just at scale
more people experience it with Ubuntu. It's an Intel SBI driver issue, right? So it's,
it's really anything, anybody that turns on it. So the, the, the it's Ubuntu's fault narrative
has been well, canonical are the ones that decided to turn that feature on because it's,
it's actually turned off by default upstream.
Lots of things are turned off upstream that are turned on. Yeah. Boy, isn't that true?
Yeah. Yeah. Um, so, um, it sounds like 1710 will be again, like I said, it's in some ways
it's like you do this now to figure out what not to do for 1804, right? So it's like you
catch this now before it's in the LTS. Same with, um, uh, the wifi crack pass, uh, issue
and a meltdown inspector, like 1804 is going to ship with a crack patched and, uh, this
issue figured out and, um, uh, the meltdown inspector patches, right? So that's, it really,
there really is a logic to the, to the process. Um, but the register proposes that, uh, canonical
dropping unity was the biggest single story in Linux for 2017. And they think that Ubuntu
without unity will continue to be a big story for the foreseeable future. Um, because with
Ubuntu using gnome shell, remember this isn't Chris saying this, this is the register with
the Ubuntu using gnome shell, almost all the major distributions out there now ship primarily
with gnome making gnome shell, the defacto standard Linux desktop, which, um, if I, if
you were going to, if I were going to rewrite that, I might say making GTK more like the
defacto toolkit. But yeah, you're probably right. I've, I've got opinions about that
article and I'm just going to, I'm just going to start by saying these are not colored by
my involvement in the Marte project at all. This is me talking as a Linux desktop enthusiast
that has an appreciation for Linux desktops across the board. And if you look at the big
applications that people are using on the Linux desktop, Firefox and Thunderbird and
LibreOffice and Google Chrome and Skype and Slack and Spotify, just to name a few, none
of those are GTK three applications. None of those are gnome applications. So I, I don't,
I don't necessarily agree this is going to drive developers to creating gnome applications.
That's a fair point. I do think it gives the Linux desktop a more consistent target, which
is built around gnome and GTK three technologies, which lots of other desktops sit on top of.
Daniel from elementary, for example, me representing Marte here, currently budgie, but eventually
cute. Cinnamon is another one, you know, so it does give a common toolkit target, but
I really don't think that developers who want to target the Linux desktop are suddenly going
to want to learn the complexities of GTK three at all.
Gnome builder is not enough to make a, make that happen.
Personally, I don't think so. I think that if developers are going to come to Linux,
you just look at the big applications. Now you've got Adobe with brackets, you've got
Atom, Microsoft Visual Studio Code, Microsoft Skype. These are all electron applications.
Spotify's Chromium embedded frameworks, which is a similar framework tool. I think if we're
going to see the large software vendors bring their software to Linux, it's going to be
through a more portable cross platform framework like electron, right? Yeah, these moves may
have helped several years ago, but electron is still the easiest path forward, right?
The most maintainable, but it does have to count for something. I mean, if you have the
ubiquity of GTK and gnome, and then you bring in flat and snap packs, it Oh, yeah, I mean,
the story there is there is a common target now in a way that we've never had with Linux.
Yes, definite, definitely snap and flat pack, give you a way to target the Linux desktop
in terms of easing your package and packaging and software delivery in a way that third
party developers who are not in the Linux, you know, bubble. So have had before what
about what about the horrible irony? And this is my personal opinion that our friends over
in plasma land may have better solutions. Here I am. I'm not using gnome three, because
I find it to be laggy and crashy, which I do not have that problem on my on my machine
at home. I'm running the plasma desktop. What about all the KDE fans out there? Because
this is this sucks. This sucks for them. If no every major does no, no, for the same
reason. You have the open source enthusiasts who will be developing gnome applications
or KDE applications and working on KDE or working on gnome or similar and related technologies.
And then you have projects because not even Firefox, although Firefox looks like it may
integrate with GTK three, it's not a GTK three application, it only takes hints from GTK
three, as to how to style and theme and the same is true for LibreOffice. And the same
is true for Google Chrome and Chromium. Those are probably the biggest applications people
are using on the desktop right now. And the same is also true for all of the electron
applications. It was only on November the 27th last year, the GTK three support landed
in electron upstream. And even today with electron, I think it's 1.8 point something
beta three, that's still linked against GTK two. So they're not releasing, you know, new
versions of electron that are linked and built against GTK three.
But now they have the green light, they have the go ahead to say here is the next target
for us to rebase on. Part of that is nobody wanted to pull the trigger because they didn't
know what to rebase on. But now if you have Fedora and SUSE and CentOS and Red Hat Enterprise
Linux and Ubuntu all shipping gnome desktop, plus then some of the most popular derivatives
Ubuntu mate, elementary OS solace, they're all using GTK desktops. The foregone conclusion
is well, that's our new target now gnome 320 or later is our new target. And I mean, give
a time I give it give it in 2019. It may be a foregone conclusion that you just target
gnome 320 or something.
I think elementary are the exception to the rule here in that they've actually got a growing
community of application developers targeting specifically their toolkit, their design language,
and their desktop environment. And I don't add the keyword here is growing, you know,
because it's clearly growing because every time Daniel comes on and talks about the number
of apps has gone up by 10. Right. And we also know that isn't an untruth because we can
see it. But I don't think that this is true for those other desktops and their application
ecosystem. But I'm not saying that the Linux desktop is in a state of decline. I think
it could be in a very healthy place. But I think a lot of the applications that we're
going to be using aren't going to be native to the desktop environment that we're currently
running.
I do agree. Yeah. And I think it's just a market reality. It's where it's the same.
It's not actually it's not a Linux. It's not unique to Linux. It is something that Mac
users are also going through and Windows users. Slack is a electron app on Windows is just
as much as it is on the Mac and just as much it is on a Linux desktop. It's not something
it's unique to us. It's a it's a bigger story. It's a bigger market dynamic that's going
on than Linux. And so I think I think you're just absolutely right because of those forces
at play.
But I'd love to hear what Daniel has to say because I know he has opinions about this
too long enough. Oh, boy, do I have opinions. Now, you know, one of the big problems I think
is actually coming from a design perspective instead of a toolkit perspective, because
even GTK apps that are built for GNOME don't necessarily work on other desktop environments.
For example, GNOME games require some system settings that are part of GNOME in order to
configure where the library gets stored. Or a GNOME builder shows two maximize icons on
elementary OS because it expects that in GNOME there is no maximize icon.
Yeah. Oh, that's brutal. It's so basic. It's so it's so 90s. It's so basic. It's actually
pathetic.
But I can't call this a GNOME problem because we have the same problem the other way. You
know, people who are writing apps for elementary OS are expecting to use our style sheet because
we have special features that they take advantage of, style classes, things like that. So when
you use our apps on GNOME or even on Mate, like they're really broken. And the guys in
Pop OS have been doing a lot of work in their style sheet to try to maintain compatibility
with apps that have been targeted and built for elementary OS.
Sure. Yeah. Now, it to me seems like this is the downside. The downside is probably
too harsh. This is the side effect. This is the action reaction when you try to create
a platform. So GNOME builder is meant for the GNOME platform, right? GNOME software
is meant for the GNOME platform, GNOME games. All of that is meant for the GNOME desktop
platform. And we all remember when the GNOME folks were talking about building even GNOME
OS. Remember when GNOME OS was going to be a thing? Like they're not building these things
for people running Mate or Pantheon. They're building these things for people that are
running a modern version of the GNOME platform. And if you're building a platform, just like
you guys are building a platform, isn't that just how it goes?
Yeah. I don't think any amount of toolkit or packaging work is ever going to solve this
problem. The only thing that you can do to solve it as a design and development team
is decide that you're going to forgo any form of desktop integration. You're going to forgo
rules in human interface guidelines. You're going to forgo special platform features and
special design features.
And then you get new Skype.
Right. You're going to build something that's either completely non-native everywhere or
people are going to have a bad time on different platforms.
You're completely correct. All right. Well, we got to move on, but great point. And we
can pick it up in the post-show if we have more, but let's talk about where you can get
it right. DigitalOcean. DigitalOcean.com, go over there, create an account, and then
use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED. You apply that, it's one word, you get a $10 credit
at DigitalOcean. DigitalOcean.com is an easy way to get cloud resources on demand when
you need them running on top of Linux. Everything's SSD. DigitalOcean.com, go spin up a machine
in less than 55 seconds. Every single machine is SSD because they're an all-SSD cloud.
They have an intuitive API that's really easy to work with and a lot of open source codes
already built around it. But better than that, they have the interface, the dashboard for
days. DigitalOcean.com, use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED. I'm just going to mention this
because this is one of my personal goals for 2018. And I say I'm not a resolutions guy,
but if there's something about just starting fresh, I'm taking advantage of monitoring
and alerting, collecting metrics, monitoring performance, and receiving alerts so I can
optimize the Jupyter broadcasting backend. And it's just built in, no additional cost.
DigitalOcean.com, go spin up my favorite machine. They got machines as cheap as $5 a month,
so like our $10 credit is going to get you two months for free. DOUNPLUGGED. But my favorite
system is $0.03 an hour. $0.03 an hour.
It sounds insane, right? But it's a beast.
Two gigs of RAM, two virtual CPUs, 40 gigabytes of SSD, and three terabytes of transfer.
You can do whatever you want on that.
Oh, boom.
DigitalOcean.com, use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED. Also, quick plug for a community documentation,
how to use ProxySQL as a load balancer for MySQL on Ubuntu 16.04. And I'm going to add
an addendum. Consider also private networking, DigitalOcean's private networking feature
with ProxySQL. You're welcome. I just saved you some money. I just made things way faster.
I just made your whole thing look like a boss-level enterprise product. You're welcome.
Yeah, right. They just help you and they push you into doing the right things. You designed
it the right way. You have the right tools.
ProxySQL, with their private networking, that's like money in the bank. DigitalOcean.com,
go create an account and then use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED. Big thank you to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
All right. So I want to talk about, briefly, Telegram's cryptocurrency plans, mostly because
Wait, say that again.
Yeah.
What?
The Telegram Open Network. It's going to be a third-generation blockchain network. Yeah.
Not a first-gen, not a second-gen, Wes.
Third-gen.
Who sets these? Who gets to decide that?
Everybody. Did you know that Kodak today announced that they're-
Yes.
Did you see that?
Mm-hmm.
This is getting crazy. You just put cryptocurrency or blockchain in your product name and your
stock goes up 44%. Kodak is announcing a crypto coin. So yeah, the Telegram Open Network
is coming at your face soon, Linux users. I know a bunch of you are a bunch of Telegram
users. It's going to be a third-generation blockchain network building on the work of
previous cryptocurrencies to provide something groundbreaking. They got a white paper, which
is step one when you have a cryptocurrency.
Oh, absolutely.
You got to have a white paper. 132-page white paper that came out on Monday. They're going
to kickstart a new cryptocurrency that will rapidly scale to meet the needs of its users.
The wallet could launch as soon as the fourth quarter of this year, with the Telegram Open
Network open to the rest of the users in 2019. It's a proof-of-stake model, which is similar
to Bitcoin's proof-of-work model. My God. I bet you will see at least another 20 of
these this year, because the technology is open source. If you've got a large user base,
if Jupiter Broadcasting had the listener base of NPR, why not launch the Jupiter coin?
Yeah. Oh, yeah.
You download a week's worth of episodes, and you get a coin. Then you can trade amongst
each other. Of course, then you have an exchange where you can convert it to other cryptocurrencies
or maybe even legal tender. There's a little bit of a skiff, a little percentage right
off the top, the Telegram takes or the JB coin takes. How long until a Linux distribution?
If this was, it's just like, where does it stop? Where does it end? You're going to have
distros that have cryptocurrencies. They're going to have 200 million grams in circulation.
Four percent will be held by the development team. Fifty-two percent will be held by Telegram
to avoid speculative trading. And the final 44 percent will be distributed in private
and in public in sales.
So will you be part of those sales, Chris? Are you going to be buying up? Are you going
to be investing?
It's the same thing. Like, if you're going to get in on a cryptocurrency, I mean, you
got to figure, like, this is probably going to be a semi-successful cryptocurrency. It's
probably going to be a way for bot makers to make money. It's probably going to come
up and down. You could probably speculate and day trade with it. The Telegram coin.
With the Telegram bot that you also wrote to buy and sell Telegram.
My goodness.
So I have a question.
Yeah.
Telegram's a Russian company, right?
Yeah. Well, this is how they're going to break away from the control of the Putin government.
Well, hasn't Russia, like, banned a lot of cryptocurrency stuff recently?
No, no, no. No, not quite. What they're doing is they're going to start regulating it, which
is really the stamp of approval for businesses to start using it.
Well, I thought they were blocking a lot of cryptocurrency exchanges, though.
That is kind of that there is a valuation period happening. But the end result. So this
has happened in other countries, too. What happens is you get a headline like Bitcoin
being blocked in China, Bitcoin being blocked in India, Bitcoin being blocked in Russia.
What that translates to is the government's financial components are doing a review of
how they can integrate cryptocurrencies into their fee structure. And then once they figure
out how they can regulate and tax it, they turn it back on. And now all of a sudden businesses
have been given a predictable model. They know how the government's going to react to
their cryptocurrency revenues and they they go for it. So I actually think this is a result
of the recent evaluation of the Russian government. This is sort of like this is the end result
of those recent headlines.
I see.
Mm hmm. Mm hmm. Mm hmm. It is a crazy time we live in.
See, now I just now we now we need Jupiter coin. How do we let's get started on that.
I know. I know. I know. Or Ubuntu coin or Budgie coin or Solus coin. You know, ask Noah
could have the ask Noah coin. Every time you call in, you get a coin. Oh, man. Noah probably
doesn't want me to tell the story, but I'm going to tell it anyways, just just to tease
the Ask Noah show that's coming up next. So Noah was cleaning out the kids room, you know,
his parents every now and then just got to go into a big purge. And like two years ago
and his kids are young, especially two years ago, right? He gave his kids as like stocking
stuffers paper Bitcoins like like a not a whole Bitcoin, but like a fraction of a Bitcoin.
Yes, which were worth like twenty five dollars at the time. And so the wife and him were
looking at all the different stuff that they gone through and they found like these these
two or three Bitcoin paper receipts. And so Noah does a little check on him and each one's
now like worth two hundred and fifty dollars or something like that. And he's like good
work, kid. He's like, this is my life, man. I just got like Bitcoin like just hanging
out all over. I got loose change in Bitcoin at that bastard. But it was a pretty funny
story of, you know, you just get in on something early enough. So, you know, set some set some
Bitcoin aside. Or what you should do is if you've got Litecoin, set some Litecoin aside
and plan to buy Telegram coin with your Litecoin. There you go. That'll probably do it. That'll
probably do it. All right. Well, I feel like we should get into Linspire because I want
to finish up the Gentoo challenge and I don't want to run out of time. You guys remember
Linspire, right? Remember? Do you remember Linspire? I do. You might also you might remember
Lindos. Yep. Lindos, which was a common covered topic early on in the Linux action show was
a commercial distribution which changed hands a few times. It started out when it became
Linspire as based on Debian. And the idea was to give a familiar desktop to Windows
users. It was even kind of promised to make it easy to run some Windows applications.
Then later on in Linspire's history, it was rebased on Ubuntu and it continued to try
to be like a user friendly distribution. But eventually it was sort of a commercial failure
and it was purchased by another distribution called Xandros and then discontinued back
in 2008. So this is how far back we're going. Now I was a particularly heavy Xandros user
for a small period of time because Xandros was a Debian based distribution with out of
the box like during your setup active directory support. Oh wow. And full complete integration
with crossover office. So it associated exe's and autoruns.inf's and everything with crossover.
So you could actually take the office 2003 or whatever it was back then, the office XP
installation CD. You could put it in the CD-ROM drive of your Linux box and insert it and
the autorun installer would come up as if you would just put it in a Windows box and
walk you through the complete installation of Microsoft Office which be involved in a
shop that needed to be able to open up XLS files and use Outlook with Exchange. That
was a huge feature for me. So I was a big Xandros user. And in 2008 it was kind of a
bummer to see that Xandros decided that Linspire just needed to end. Fast forward to the end
of 2017 though and a company known as PC slash Open Systems LLC announced that they had purchased
Linspire and its community edition Freespire and would resume development of these two
Ubuntu based distributions. Now, just in the last week, Linspire 7.0 and Freespire 3.0
were released. Now, Linspire is being sold as a commercial product which PC slash Open
Systems is hoping to bundle with hardware or you can buy it. Now Freespire can be downloaded
today free of charge. Freespire is like a respin without all of the proprietary components
of Linspire. So what are those proprietary components? What do you get if you spend $7.99?
$9.99 USD? What do you get? If you spend what actually works out to be $94 when all is said
and done because they're going to ship you media and charge you for $10 or so for shipping.
So what do you get for $95 when you download Linspire? I had to know. Like this distribution
that's been around since the beginning of my podcast.
It's a burning question.
Like what do you get for $95 of an Ubuntu respin? So I decided to pay it so you don't
have to and I've been loading it during this show. In fact, the installation is complete.
I'm going to do a restart right now so we can kick the tires.
Right here live. Anything could happen.
I got to tell you, I played around with it for about an hour before the show too. So
these are early impressions, but I played around with it for an hour before the show
and I really went into it expecting it to be complete and total shit and was... Well
first of all, if I'm giving you my complete and honest impression, I thought I was using
the Plasma desktop at first.
Really?
It uses LightDM for the login manager. It's based on Ubuntu 16.04 and when it booted up,
I thought it was like a Plasma 5 desktop that's been reworked to remind you of the KDE 4 days.
But not in a bad way, but in a tasteful way. And it wasn't until I opened up the terminal
and looked at all the running processes that I realized that was the next thing I did.
That I realized I was actually on XFCE and that I was using Thunar and it wasn't the
Plasma desktop at all. So here it is right here. This is a LightDM login and I've already
set up my user account here so I'll log in. And there's, out of the box, a couple of things
that you don't get on FreeSpire. Number one is Chrome. So Chrome is the default browser
out of the gate. Let me clear off. So I'm running it right now under virtualization
because I didn't want to put it on my physical hardware. But I mean, I know it's a little
hard to see it all, but tell me if that doesn't look like a KDE Plasma desktop right there.
Oh yeah, I can definitely see what you're talking about.
Yeah. So it threw me for a loop just a little bit. I was surprised, but then quickly impressed.
It's got a nice menu launcher. It's got a couple of things pre-bundled in that I like
quite a bit. It's still shipping Pigeon. It's got VLC as the default media player. Skype
is pre-installed. We're going to come back to the Click and Run store here in just a
moment. There's a couple other things I was surprised by. Bleach Bit is installed by default.
Really?
That drive wiping software.
Yeah.
Yeah. Unet Booton is installed by default. And VirtualBox, as well as all of the LM sensor
stuff, is installed. And gdebi, my preferred package installer on Ubuntu desktops, is installed
by default. I actually think that's pretty great. Also, a very simple firewall configuration
is installed by default. I guess the best way to describe the theme is it's very Plasma,
don't you think?
Yeah, it is very Plasma.
It's also kind of using like the Mac OS, old Mac OS X icons.
It's not bad. I mean, I wouldn't call it beautiful, but it's not offensive.
And it's fast, right? It's very, very fast. And out of the box, Samba and NMBD resolutions
working. So let's talk about Click and Run. This is interesting. This is really interesting.
It's well, do you remember the big thing about Click and Run back in the day was it was the
first Linux app store.
And it was even the first Linux app store that supported payments. That was the huge
thing about Click and Run. And I was really curious to see if it had held up, if it was
still populated, if they had current applications.
Yeah, has it just wandered off into the weeds?
And what is Linspire without Click and Run?
Right. Yeah, that's the, that's how much of this is it Linspire in name only, or is it
really a continuation of this noble lineage?
Right. So I wanted to find out and that was, well,
I was surprised by what I discovered, but it actually kind of makes sense. I'll tell
you about it here in just a second. But first, let me mention Linux Academy, linuxacademy.com
slash unplugged. Go there and sign up and get a free seven day trial. It's a platform
to learn more about Linux, a full featured training library with everything you need
to know to learn, everything you need to know, everything you need to learn new skills or
advance your career if you're ready to kind of move forward.
I think probably my favorite feature about Linux Academy would be the learning paths
because you get content that has been specifically engineered by their instructors for specific
career tracks. And then as you go along this track, they'll spin up like virtual cloud
servers for you at SSHN and use these things really in production. They've got hands on
scenario based labs to give you experience on real servers. They have practice exams
and quizzes to help you prepare for certifications so that way you can really take this stuff
and apply it. And if you ever get stuck, they've got human beings that can help you, real instructors
that are standing by, full time people on Linux Academy staff to help you. That's something
that all of these other training sites that have Linux as a feature can't match.
Now if you go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged, you can sign up for a free seven day trial
so you can get a taste of what their content is, how the platform works. And the big thing
that I figured out within the first 24 hours of signing up for Linux Academy was things
that were nebulous as like, God, one day I'd like to figure out how to even try to learn
this thing. Things that were like categorized as that in my brain went to, oh, if I go to
Linux Academy and spend four hours or six hours, I can understand how this entire thing
works now. That is such a huge shift. And it's so empowering because even when you don't
have a specific thing you need to learn, you can go there and you can say, well, I got
two hours.
Right. Sometimes that's the hardest thing. You have to learn how to learn. They've done
a huge amount of that upfront work for you. You can just sit down and concentrate on actually
learning.
And then they give you a bunch of great study tools and lesson audio and personal notebooks
that you can use offline. And they have iOS and Android apps to learn on the go. It's
a great combo. Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged. Big thank you Linux Academy for
sponsoring the unplugged program. Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged. All right, Mr. West,
before we get back to the freaking Linspire debacle that I went down, the rabbit hole
of Linspire, how is the Gen 2 challenge going over there?
It's going quite well.
Do you think we're getting near a graphical environment?
Oh, yeah.
Really?
Yes.
We've got Wayland built. We've got Sway built.
Yep.
You've got now we don't have a completely functional boot system or we do have a booting
system. I can't remember.
Yeah, it will boot. Actually, we're rebooting right now.
All right. Okay. Well, so before we get there, before we wrap up the Gen 2 challenge completely,
let me just finish off my thoughts on Linspire here. So when I launched the Click and Run
store, I was greeted with Gnome software. The Click and Run store, yeah, the defining
feature of Linspire has been replaced with Gnome software. Now, you know, I got to say,
it kind of makes sense. It kind of does make sense. If you were going to relaunch Linspire
today, you would probably do this. And if you look at the applications that they've
featured here, hot damn, MailSpring, Hairy, Brave, Wavebox, Atom, VLC and LXD right here
on Spotify as the featured application.
Hang on a minute. Those are just the featured applications in the Ubuntu software center.
They haven't featured those at all.
No, no, no. Oh, yeah. No, and I don't mean to imply that.
Can I tell you who produces that list of featured applications?
But wouldn't you? I mean, I guess this is the benefit of being based on Ubuntu. But
if you're going to, this to me, this to me seems like the obvious way. If you're going
to launch Linspire today, why bother with a Click and Run store? Why wouldn't you just
ship this?
But okay, now tell us, Wimpy, who does?
Me and Popey.
Well, good job, sir.
Excellent work.
So how do you feel then about them sort of featuring your work? That's better than I
expected.
That's absolutely fine, right? They're rebasing on Ubuntu. They're taking advantage of lots
of the underlying technologies. That's absolutely fine. But if you open GNOME software on any
of the Ubuntu derivatives, that's what you see today.
I think I, you know, I was expecting, I was expecting the old Click and Run. I was expecting
like the purchasing infrastructure they had set up. And when I launched it, I went, oh,
yeah.
You expected it to be out of place or out of touch.
Well, I was disappointed. But then I was like, actually, that's exactly what they should
be doing.
Yes.
Well, good picks, by the way. Good picks, Wimpy, by the way. I think that's Open Arena
is also down here in recommended games, Frozen Bubble, Neverball, good stuff.
So it is, in a way, a shadow of its former self. It is not, I haven't got a chance to
try out the wine integration that they supposedly brought in from like their Xandros heritage,
which does sound actually kind of interesting. In a way, it is a shadow of its former self.
It is an Ubuntu respin. But then at the same time, it does offer something unique. When
I bought this for $80, $95, all said and done, I sent them an email and I said, hey, I'd
like to just have an ISO instead. Can I get an ISO today? And an actual person who speaks
English responded to me and gave me, here's a 64-bit link, here's a 32-bit link, have
at it.
Wow.
So their support aspect of it is legitimate. It is something that they're actually living
up to. There are people responding because I sent an email to the support channel. They're
also making some interesting package choices. This is a very nice implementation of XFCE.
I don't think it would hold up on a high DPI setup. But on a standard DPI setup, this is
got to be one of the cleanest, simplest, most modern implementations I've ever seen of XFCE.
It does seem like a desktop that, especially, I could just take someone who had used a computer
before and plop them down there and they would probably get along just fine. They're doing
a bunch of other things that I think are kind of interesting. So by default, they are turning
on pre-linking. And they're pre-linking a bunch of libraries to try to improve performance.
I don't know if-
That's the default Ubuntu feature.
Oh, OK. I was just going to say, I don't know if Ubuntu- OK. There you go. And they also
have Samba and NNBD pre-running and setup out of the gate. They've got Clam Anovirus
and Fresh Clam.
Which we can't do in official Ubuntu flavors because you're not allowed to ship with any
running services.
Right. And they've got Clam and Fresh Clam running in the background. So you've got essentially
out-of-the-box Anovirus. Again, Windows users seem to care about that more so than-
It is like a tricycle for Windows users coming over to the Linux world.
There's also a process and a user called Whoopsie. Is this- What is Whoopsie?
That's WhoopsieDaisy.
Is that a bug reporter?
Yeah, it's the bug reporter for kernel traps, yeah.
My current boss wrote WhoopsieDaisy.
My years on Arch have colored my perception of things like this, but I understand why
they're there. Also, there's a few other default tweaks, default applications have been changed.
Obviously Chrome's in here. Skype's installed out of the box. Gdebi, Bleachbit. So it is
a, in a lot of ways, it is a better out-of-the-box Windows replacement than Stock Ubuntu. If
you expect your computer to work like a Windows system.
Is it not Zubuntu with a few applications pre-installed that you can't redistribute
legally?
Yes. That is exactly 100% what it is. With Chrome, Codecs, and other things that, yeah.
But I don't, I think it would be naive to say there isn't a market for that. That stuff,
that stuff you're not allowed to distribute?
I'm not suggesting there's not a market for it, no. I'm just, I'm just saying you could
do the same thing with Zubuntu because you could install Zubuntu, open the software center
and install all of those applications that are-
Right, yeah. Right, but there's something about it being, I think there's something
about the idea of it being a pre-packaged solution. So when you think about the way
you get Linspire, you don't even get an ISO. You go spend $95 and what you get is a thank
you email saying that your package is on its way.
It's really a story about like trying to understand the perspectives and goals of the people who
are behind it.
Yeah, and it's not, it's not my goal. That's not my perspective. But yeah, what you're
basically getting is you're getting Chrome, you're getting Thunderbird with Exchange and
Google Sync plug-ins installed. You're getting VLC, Clam AV, you're getting.NET Core support,
XFS, I don't realize, I don't know why they outlined that. Intrusion detection, Bleach
Bit, these are the other things, and ICE SSB are the main things that they say are included
with Linspire over traditional Linux, aka Ubuntu. And you also get 12 months of email
and phone support with that.
And that's what your money is really buying, right? It's that support.
I suppose, or maybe the ability to distribute some of that software. And then it's based
on LTS, so it's supported until 2025.
Is it?
That's what they say, you know, yeah.
How are they doing that?
Also, apparently, if you're a business, they'll spin you custom ISOs and do non-site setup.
Yep, yep. And they have a cloud version as well that you can buy, which is actually cheaper
than the desktop version.
The cloud version?
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
This is based on 16.04?
Yes, sir, yeah.
So how are they doing support until 2025?
Well, how long is 16.04 supported?
Five years.
Hmm.
Hmm, indeed.
I mean, it does say until 2025. It says Freespire is supported until 2021, and Linspire is supported
until 2025.
Okay. Good luck with that then.
Yeah.
2022 is going to be real tough.
It's an interesting, it's obvious play towards a completely different market than anybody
that would be listening to this show or me. And that's kind of why I wanted to try it,
is when something like this comes along, when Linspire comes along again, and it's like,
what makes it worth $95?
I'd also be interested to meet someone who had found, you know, like, oh, I'd heard my
grandson had told me I really needed to get that Linux, and they ended up finding this.
I wonder if it's not more about the story that you're able to tell a potential OEM partner.
This is Linspire. It has a, you know, you go into the heritage, you go into the fact
that it's got wine sort of baked in, which is an aspect I admittedly did not get into
in this review, which is just barely a review. It's more of like a first look. And, you know,
you see you have the story of a Linspire heritage, Windows support. We ship it with Chrome. We
ship it with the Nvidia binaries. We ship it with Thunderbird that has exchange support.
It's a story that you could tell an OEM that maybe is more appealing than a free-loving
all GPL software distro. I don't know.
Or at least something they can understand a little bit more, right?
But we'll see where it goes. So we're checking in at the beginning of 2018. They just had
their new version 7.0 Linspire release. We'll see where it goes for the rest of 2018, I
suppose.
And remember, one of the only benefits when it comes to having a non-free software included
is they can actually bundle it in a box in a store and sell it.
Yeah, or on a machine, which I think is what they plan to do.
So what do you think? Replacing the studio machines? We're going all Linspire?
Yeah, 100%.
Yeah.
You've been talking it up all day.
It's supported until 2025, so it's obvious.
Yeah, install once and then, I mean, will there even be JB by then? Who knows?
Finally. Finally.
Actually laughing out loud.
I give them credit for responding to my support email requests and actually giving some thought
to some applications to bundle with it. We'll see where they go. I'd be curious.
All right, Mr. West. Are you ready, sir? Are you ready, Mr. West?
Perhaps the worst idea happened when I went to New York. I noticed you guys didn't do
a Gen 2 Challenge check-in last week. I see how that is. I see you save it for me when
I'm around, because we could have wrapped this up last week.
You've been so fascinated by the whole affair. I didn't want to deprive you.
So how's it going?
Sort of like a homecoming.
So you checked in last, during the show, you were rebooting.
We are live in Sway on Wayland.
You've gotten to graphical mode.
Do we have a sky cam? Let's see here. We do have a sky cam. We only see this. Holy crap!
It doesn't look like much. It hasn't been super configured yet, but look at there it
is. There we can almost see it. There it is. That is totally boring and a total-
It may be the most boring thing I've ever seen.
That is really boring, but so this is Sway.
Yeah, on Wayland.
Not bad.
No X anywhere.
Not bad. No anti-aliasing either.
No, no anti-aliasing. Why would you want that?
That is a full Gen 2 system boot up right there with Sway. You did it. You did it. Wow!
Up your shaft.
Good job, Wes. I don't know if it was worth it. So what was that? Five episodes? It took
five weeks of building software?
On and off anyway.
That's not bad really.
In a virtual machine.
So you probably, if you would have given it a good solid three and a half hours, you could
have gotten- Oh yeah, definitely. Plus a lot of that was trying to do the show and read
through the handbook, which had been years since I'd read through. So there was some
of that. Now I think, yeah, give me an hour and a half and a fast machine and we'll be
done.
We've had a lot of fun with Gen 2 over the Gen 2 challenge, but Wes and I were discussing
this, and we realized we actually did walk away with a bit of a lesson from this whole
thing. Because sort of the ongoing joke was, what good is Gen 2 for? What's the point of
Gen 2? Even now in 2018, do you really need these optimizations that you might be able
to get when you build your own software? What's the damn point of Gen 2? And sort of perfectly,
on January 6, a great post, a science project really, make the 486 great again. Running
modern Linux on an ancient 486 PC. This PC, which was released in 1989, which, fun fact,
before the Meltdown problem.
Right.
It was a specular of execution. And this is about as far back as you can go and still
have actual genuine kernel support. But just because the Linux kernel supports the 486
processor doesn't mean that any distribution out there and its packages do. And there was
only one system that supported it.
When you're in a situation like this, where do you turn, right?
It's only one.
There's only one.
Yeah. And Gen 2 was perfect because the issue with modern Linux distributions like Debian
or Ubuntu or Arch is that they distribute binary packages, which we all think is great.
But when you need something like a 486, while it's theoretically supported by the modern
Linux kernel, the distribution packages do not support it. Debian dropped support for
586 32-bit CPUs in 2016. The oldest supported x86 CPU by Debian is the 686, which was released
in 95, which is when speculative execution started coming along.
So you don't want that.
No. But the thing about Gen 2 is you can freaking build the packages yourself. And you can install
Linux on this crazy, esoteric edge case that most people would never even think of. And
if you think about it, that's the beautiful thing about Linux itself. It's this general
purpose technology platform that brings life to devices and enables technology in ways
we never even considered before.
Right. I'm sure a lot of people are asking, why? Why would you do this? But that's irrelevant
because, like you say, it is this general purpose. And a lot of interesting things happen
when you don't really ask why and you just are open to exploration.
Nothing else could do this.
I mean, some BSDs, but in the Linux landscape.
Nothing useful could do this. Nothing that you would want to actually use and could connect
out to the internet and clone a Git repo and install Python 3.63 could do this. It has
to be Linux. And Gen 2 is one of the few Linuxes that actually could make it possible.
Right. You don't have to be a giant corporation who has manpower to build your own distribution
or custom compile everything. You have a framework that's been developed over years to make it
easy for you to do it.
What's great is it takes about 11 minutes for boot up.
And then just have a cup of tea. You'll come back. It'll be up.
They hooked up a Sound Blaster 16 and took a couple of minutes for the music playback
to start working. It also took a couple of minutes for SSH to connect in and took about
only three minutes to clone a Git repo. And shutdown took about five and a half minutes
to shut down.
That's incredible.
The whole post goes through how they got Linux 4.14.8 running on this.
Like a brand's making new kernel too.
Yeah.
Like that, right?
Yeah. It's just really remarkable. It really is so cool. They used an old version of damn
small Linux as well to try to mess around. And this, you know, it's sort of the perfect
conclusion to the Gen 2 challenge because it does show you what is Gen 2 good for. And
it's good for people that are doing things you've never even thought of.
Yeah, absolutely. I still think it's a fun playground. I'm going to leave this here for
a while, at least just to play with Sway and maybe some other things. Also just Emerge
is great. It's really fun to get to spend a little time, especially, you know, like
I love Linux. I play with Linux, but I also get all of my work done on Linux. And so this
was a nice reminder that like the internals are fun. Configuring a kernel is fun. Really
getting to know your system.
Yes.
And I think if I was doing a bunch of Linux development, it might be a system that I would
really like to be able to just customize play and have access to all these tweakable sources
right there.
Beard chimes in with the fact that Slackware can still do high 586. Damn it Beard. Go check
out Beard at rec.net. I hear that son of a bitch is streaming more than ever. Mr. AtWestPain
right there on the Twitter and check him out on the new rebooted TechSnap as well as me.
I'm at Chris LAS. Get more wimpy at the Ubuntu podcast and join our subreddit at linuxunplugged.reddit.com.
This year's show is live on Tuesdays over jblive.tv followed now by the Ask Noah program.
So it's a whole afternoon slash evening slash insert local time of Linux. If you join our
virtual lug, you can also take advantage of that in the Ask Noah program. So geez, it's
never been better to join us over jblive.tv for quite the live experience. Thanks for
being here. We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
Oh, thank you, virtual lug. You guys are great. Now we just got to pick a title. And
I think we're done. I think we're done. It was a fun show. It was a fun show. I enjoyed
the hell out of that. Yeah. I enjoyed the hell out of it. So are you still going to
get the install media for linspire in the mail? Okay, good. That's almost a trophy.
I'm gonna follow up when it comes in. Most expensive USB stick ever. It's probably the
bare minimum. It's like just four gigs. That could be a title. Most expensive USB stick
ever. Most expensive Linux distro ever. Yes, that's someone that's there. There is the
show title right there. What about most expensive Linux distro ever? Because it really is I
don't know of a more expensive you can't where else can you spend $95 a distro? What's Oracle
charging these days? $5 more and you can get Windows 10. Wow. You know, but most expensive
Linux distro ever is very long. Is there a tighter way to say that? That'll do. That'll
do. Yeah, most expensive Linux. I almost feel like it's got to be long. I don't know. Long
and complicated. Break in the bank. Yeah, green light for Linux. Yeah, just do Linux
and a bunch of dollar signs. So hey, beer, what do I do? Do I do? Is there a scene for
ask Noah? Like, what do I do when it's asked Noah time? You turn off the stream and Noah
picks it up. Oh, that's right. What? Oh, hey, buddy. Bang suggest working discord. Oh, there
we go. So hold on. You telling me between between West Noah and beard. You I guess last
week was kind of crazy. There we go. Martin. That's true. I forgot about that. That was
crazy. All right. I understand. I thought we would have had this shit fixed by now.
It's cool. Well, you were gone. So we didn't have only there was some sort of like remote
login system on the OBS system that Noah was integrated with where he could just connect
in both you goofballs multiple times. Just give me permission. Just give me permission
and I'll make it happen. I'm a goof. What do you mean? How do you not have permission?
I installed your remote like verbal permission like screw with your broadcasting machine.
Good to be good. Actually. I mean, could you just solve problems gonna happen? And he's
gonna blame you anyway. So that's all right. So we so we do have to so I should probably
like we should probably interrupt the stream soon. So that way there's time for YouTube
to reset. Hey, so if people want to hang out in mumble for ask Noah, where should they
go?
Like not the best week of that because I have a guest. But oh, right, right. If you guys
if you guys hang out in there and and either he's he comes in late because I know he's
on a call with a customer right now if he comes in late or if we wrap up I'll jump back
in mumble. So what is that? Does that mean stay here or does that mean you're gonna be
are you gonna be sending a feed into the mumble room? Can they hear the show or do they got
to still go? God damn it, Noah. Yes. Hey, listen, we send a feed to tune in. We send
a no show. I know we said I know live.tv. We can't keep your radio.com. There's like
a billion ways. I know escape the show. Yeah. All right. All right. Good enough, Noah.