It's for people who like to mess with computers.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 308,
for some time in the future.
Oh, hey there, yeah, you.
Thanks for tuning in to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
This week, we're doing something kind of special.
We're throwing out the regular format,
and we're making an episode all about PCI Passerby.
Wait, wait, finally.
I know.
I know, finally, really.
Actually, this is actually something
I've been wanting to do for, oh, I don't know, about five years.
And we finally get to do it.
But wait, if it's not for you, I encourage you to stick around.
You may learn something.
Maybe it will pique your interest.
This is something that solves a lot of problems.
If you want to run Windows, Mac OS, and Linux at the same time,
maybe you even want to run Windows games
without having to mess with proprietary drivers
on your main Linux desktop.
This is something that can help you achieve that.
And PCI Passerby can also just be a great way
to get full performance when you distro hop.
And I use the term full performance a little vaguely,
but full graphical performance, if nothing else.
For distro hopping, that's such a great way
to try out different Linux distributions
without having to nuke and pave every single time.
Or the slowness and artificial properties of using a VM.
Oh, Wes, oh.
I have got a long sort of sordid history with virtualization.
It really stems back from maybe even
pre-PowerPC on the Macintosh System 7 platform.
You had Virtual PC, which would emulate the entire Intel stack.
It had to do translation from Intel to PowerPC
to execute on a PowerPC system, where
it might have been an 8086 system back then.
I don't remember what they were.
Those were the days.
So you were really in real virtualization.
As time went on, if money was available,
you could buy a expansion, I think
it was NetBus card, that you would
install that had an Intel processor and memory on it.
It was like an entire PC on an expansion card
that would then communicate with proprietary, expensive
virtualization software.
So desktop virtualization has come a long way.
And server virtualization has come even further.
I have a long history with VMware and server
virtualization, too.
One of the best things about desktop Linux
is we can take advantage of all of the developments
and progress in the server space right here on our workstations.
So there are a few caveats about PCIe Pass.
There's a few things you have to know.
But I thought we'd start with describing our hardware setup
so you have an idea of what works for us.
And maybe you can build your setups around there.
So let's start by going around the horn,
because also on the line we have Cheese, Alex, and Drew.
Alex, let's start with your virtualization setup.
Right then.
So this topic is something that I've
been secretly hoping you would cover for years.
And I'm so happy that I'm around whilst you're doing it.
PCIe Pass got me into Linux in the first place in 2013.
I'm just looking back at the Linux server blog.
And I have a post dated 10th of August, 2013,
how to compile a custom kernel ready for Xen and Ubuntu
Server 1304.
Oh, boy.
So that's going back a bit.
Yeah, I think you probably have the longest
standing on the panel here.
Back then, there was a whole bunch
of stuff you had to consider.
But there's a few things that have remained
constant throughout that period.
And the most important thing to get right
is your physical hardware.
So there's a few prerequisites that you need.
First of all, your CPU must support
what's called VT-D or VTX if you're in the Intel world.
I forget the name of the AMD one,
but there's a similar equivalent.
So not only must your CPU actually support it,
and you can use the Intel Arc to tell you
whether it does or not, your motherboard
must also support it.
But on top of that, your specific BIOS version
must support it.
So there have been cases where BIOS updates have
broken PCR pass-through for people
and they've had to downgrade.
So it's cutting edge, a lot less so
than it was five, six years ago.
But it's still, some assembly is required.
Yeah, that's fair.
That's definitely fair.
Now, most Xeons, in fact, I think all Xeons
have shipped with VT-D extensions for the longest time.
So you don't need to worry if you have a Xeon-based system,
because servers and things like that
have been using pass-through for NICs and SATA controllers
and all sorts of stuff for a long time.
What got me the most excited about this stuff a few years
ago was being able to put a video card in my system.
So back then, you used to need an AMD card.
But nowadays, you can use an AMD card or an NVIDIA card
with some caveats, which we'll probably come to later.
And when you say passing through the video card,
you essentially are blacklisting it
from the underlying operating system
and exclusively making it available to the virtualization
subsystem.
And it shows up in your VM as if it was plugged right
into that VM's PCI bus.
And the operating system in your VM
is responsible for the driver and the communication
with the hardware, the whole lot.
The VM has no idea that it's not directly connected
to the PCI bus as if it was a native machine.
So that's why the performance is roughly
between 95% and 98% of bare metal performance,
which is, for all intents and purposes, pretty good.
Pretty, pretty good.
And then there's also the visceral experience,
in my case, although there's other ways
to do this, which we'll cover.
I have then a physical monitor plugged into that video card.
And I'm also using a physical mouse and keyboard that are
plugged into dedicated USB ports.
So the VM that I am using feels completely
to my monkey brain like a dedicated PC,
because it's got a screen, it's got a mouse,
it's got a keyboard, and everything's fully accelerated.
Now, CPUs prior to Skylake, Intel did some skew,
skull-doggery, ooh, that's a nice phrase,
where they limited VTD to non-K chips only.
So traditionally, the K chips were their overclocking chips,
and the non-K chips were not.
And if you wanted to do this virtualization
pass-through, PCI pass-through, you
had to buy an i5-3570, not the 3570K, for example.
So from Skylake onwards, though, I
think pretty much every CPU included VTD.
But use the Intel Arc to double check what the CPU does
and does not support.
Sounds especially annoying for gamers, right?
You might want to overclock, and then you couldn't
use something like pass-through.
Yeah, it's one of these things that really turns me off Intel,
to be honest, and makes me hate them.
There's some stuff that Nvidia have done as well,
which we'll come to.
But these big guys, they just have
this way of differentiating their products that is just BS,
and it's really annoying sometimes.
Yeah, it comes down to artificial limitations,
so that way they can charge more for the enterprise-grade chips.
In the case of Intel, it's Xeons.
And in the case of Nvidia, it's their higher-end graphics card
that they sell to businesses.
Now, we'll circle back to video here in a moment,
because there's still some fundamentals that your system
has to be able to support.
And there's a very important concept
that you have to understand in order
to group these PCI devices together and allocate them
to your VM.
Do you want to cover the IOMMU grouping stuff real quick?
Yeah, so to pass a device through,
you must pass an entire IOMMU group.
Yeah, I'm sorry, but just to interrupt really quick,
what is an IOMMU group in really basic terms?
So far as I understand it, and I'm probably
going to butcher this, but it's a logical grouping of devices
on the motherboard.
So I think it's got something to do with PCI lanes
and how they're presented to the CPU and all that kind of thing.
So often, what you'll find on consumer-grade motherboards
is that two or three different PCI slots are grouped together
into a single group.
And that doesn't sound like a big deal
until you're doing one VM has a graphics card,
and then you want your host to also have a graphics card
as well, for example.
So you've got two GPUs in this system.
Now, if they're both in the same IOMMU group,
then you're unable to tell the VM to only grab
that single device.
It will try and grab everything in that group.
So the same is true of USB controllers or SATA controllers
or anything.
Each thing has to be in its own group for separation.
And you have to bring over the entire group.
So here's a perfect example that just about anybody
doing video pass-through will run into.
Most modern video cards have an HDMI port.
Well, that HDMI port includes audio.
And so that actually, the audio component of HDMI
shows up as a separate device on the PCI bus.
And you need to blacklist both of those devices
and then allocate them to the VM,
because they're all in that IOMMU group.
And the other thing that, in my case, was very relevant
is a Thunderbolt 3 device, all of those devices
in that Thunderbolt 3 device are in a PCI group
or an IOMMU group.
And that, in my case, worked really well,
because I could dedicate the entire dock to the VM
in that instance.
Yeah, and like server equipment.
So we talked about Xeons being well-supported.
Server motherboards often have very generous IOMMU groups.
So they have one group per PCI slot, for example,
because they know that a lot of their customers
are going to be doing this.
So all hope is not lost.
If you have bought a consumer-grade motherboard
that groups multiple PCI ports together under the same group,
you can apply an ACS kernel patch,
which will artificially separate those devices out
into separate groups, allowing you
to have multiple devices in the same physical group.
But so far as your OS is concerned,
they're in a different logical grouping.
So it works just fine.
There are some security concerns.
And I forget exactly what they are.
But you want to be sure that you understand
the ramifications of this ACS patch before you apply it,
because it can allow for some nasty things, breakouts
from the VMs, for example.
Yeah, it essentially does not guarantee isolation
for a particular device.
So while it does get quote unquote isolated,
it's not quite the same where something could potentially
use it to break out of a VM and attack the host.
Right, and to be clear, this is only
if you're using that workaround, that ACS patch.
And in my case, this actually works out fantastic,
because I'm passing through Thunderbolt 3 devices.
And on these Thunderbolt 3 devices,
I want the gigabit ethernet.
I want the USB bus.
I want the sound card, the display port, the GPU.
I want it all to go to the virtual machine.
So it just happened to be in my particular setup.
Having to group all these together anyways
made it actually simpler to just pass the entire Thunderbolt 3
devices through to the VM.
And in my case, I'm not breaking any isolation.
I'm not running any risk.
It's perfectly safe.
I'll tell you another use case where this ACS patch is useful.
So if you have multiple identical graphics cards
in the same system, let's say you've got two RX 560s,
for example, or two 1060s, or something,
two GPUs that present themselves as their PCI IDs
as the same device, that can be really tricky.
And sometimes you need to move the physical devices around
in the actual slots on your motherboard
to get the host to pick up the right GPU first.
So in my system here, for example,
I have an RX 560 and a 1080 Ti.
The 560 is in the top slot on the motherboard,
and the 1080 is in the second slot, which
is the other way around to what you would think to get the 16x
and the 8x slots.
In reality, that performance difference
is so negligible that I don't actually care about that.
And by having it this way around, my arch host
can pick up the AMD GPU first and use that for Linux
with all the native kernel support it has.
And then my guest just picks up the second slot,
and it just works.
Now we'll get more into our individual setups,
because each one of us has a very different setup.
But one thing that's going to be common
is all of these VMs will use an open source UEFI firmware.
They have to be on UEFI firmwares for this to work.
Yeah, so the magic that makes all this possible is OVMF.
That was one of the things a few years ago
that caused a lot of headaches.
So if I look at one of my really old blog posts
from September 2013, I am looking at a Windows 8 VM,
just to give you an idea of the context of where
we were at that point, kernel 3.10 for Linux.
So it's quite a long time ago.
You used to have to eject your graphics card
before rebooting the VM, because if you didn't do that,
then the firmware on the graphics card didn't reset.
So when you reboot your system, there's
a whole bunch of resetting of different firmwares.
And basically, the graphics card has a small BIOS on it
as well.
That doesn't sound like too big of a deal
until something like Windows Update
comes along and just randomly reboots your VM for fun.
So I had to write these very basic scripts back in the day
that ran in a registry key that ejected the graphics
card at startup and shut down in the Windows VM
to get around that problem.
Now, these days with OVMF, it's so easy
that the UEFI BIOSes on all these cards
just handles the resets, even in a VM scenario, just fine.
So you can reboot, shut down, reattach to a different VM.
You can go to town and go crazy, and it will just
continue to work, and it won't lock up the host anymore.
I have had bad luck with my RX 570
doing a full reset, where in some cases with Windows
and Mac VMs, I have to power off the system
or sleep the system, the host system,
before the graphics will reset.
Did not have that issue with the NVIDIA graphics,
which surprised me.
I thought it'd be the other way around.
OK, now why don't we get into our setups?
Because I think that's an interesting bit here is,
and then we'll get into configuring
the various aspects of it, depending
on what your setup is.
I also want to get into something
like Looking Glass, if you don't necessarily
want to have a dedicated monitor, dedicated hardware.
There's other solutions there too.
But Alex, let's start with your current PCI pass-through setup.
I have two.
So my main desktop rig is, as I've said,
it's got an RX 560 and a 1080 TI in it.
The 1080 is dedicated to Windows,
and the RX 560 is dedicated to Linux.
And to be honest with you, the only reason
I have Windows lying around these days
is for Adobe stuff, for Lightroom and Photoshop
and that kind of thing.
It's an Intel CPU, an 8700K, and 32 gigs of RAM.
So not that much RAM, but it works just fine.
You're doing a dedicated disk, or are you just
doing a Cal file or somewhere?
How are you doing that?
Oh, yes.
Disks are important to talk about.
So when you've got two machines on your system,
you're probably going to want to make sure that there's
at least a SSD per machine.
Now, you can run your virtual machine out of a QCOW image
on the same SSD as your host OS.
Obviously, that's going to limit performance,
because there's only so many inputs and outputs
physically a device can do in any given time.
So I have a dedicated SATA controller
that I pass through to the VM so that the guest just
sees a native SSD as if it was plugged straight in.
Now, there is one other thing that's worth talking about.
There's these VertIO drivers.
Now, they are developed by Red Hat,
and they enable a huge performance leap over just
standard SATA emulation.
Now, when you're installing Windows,
there's a few hoops you'll need to jump through in terms
of enabling drivers.
So in the installer, you'll need to load up
not only the Windows ISO, but also a VertIO ISO,
which is available in the show notes.
There's a link.
And with that VertIO ISO, you'll need to browse through
and find the storage driver to enable Windows
to see the VertIO drive.
Otherwise, when you get to the Install page,
and it says, select the device you want to install,
it will just be a blank list.
And that foxed me for quite a while.
The fun of Windows, ooh.
VertIO is amazing, because the system, the driver,
is aware that it's virtualized.
And so it communicates intelligently
with the hypervisor.
And just a quick rabbit hole tangent to that,
QMU developer, I think Alex, you're
the one that noticed this, thinks
that it looks like Apple is adding early support for VertIO
and frame buffer graphics to the latest iterations of Mojave
and Catalina.
So it looks like Apple is adding virtualization VertIO driver
support to Mac OS, which is going to make this even easier
down the road.
Would that justify $100,000 cheese grater to you?
No, because I can run this on a custom built Linux box
and get GPU performance in Mac OS.
In fact, we'll get there in a moment.
But is there any other notes on your setup?
That's a pretty comprehensive review.
I like that.
I like the SATA pass-through tip.
I am using a QCOW file on my laptop disk,
because obviously I can't stuff a ton of SATA disk in there.
And I do notice a bit of a performance impact.
Nothing major, ones like games are loaded and stuff.
But yeah, during patching and whatnot, it's brutal.
As a few other things, like CPU pinning, for example,
for performance.
So you need to ensure that your host system has
at least one full core available to use at all times.
Otherwise, if your host system runs out of CPU time,
you're going to have a bad time.
The other thing is, how do you handle
sound and keyboard and mice?
So sound is a tricky one.
There's lots of different options here.
The one that I'm using at the moment
is to stream from the guest through to Pulse Audio
on the host.
And that works fine.
It can be a little crackly at times,
but not enough that I bothered to fix it.
The other thing is, you could just buy a USB DAC,
for example, sound card.
Plug that in and pass that through.
And that will give you audio directly from the host.
Another neat way to do it is to use the HDMI headphone out
on your display to plug into your sound that way.
So when you switch the input on a display,
you're automatically switching the sound input as well.
So that's another way to do it.
I'll add, just for context, what I decided to do
was get a USB gaming headset.
And I use that for all kinds of stuff.
And if I want audio, I just plug that in.
OK, Drew, so you've recently set up a PCI pass-through.
And I think it's a little different than what we're doing.
So tell me about your setup.
So my setup is on a Ryzen-based system.
So I am using AMD-V instead of VTD.
And that works fine.
That I had no problems with at all,
was pretty much out of the box on the latest kernel, which
at the time is 5.1.2, I want to say.
Are you on Fedora?
Currently, yes.
And the reason I'm on Fedora is I had started this journey
on Ubuntu.
And I ran into some issues because I
do have an RX 580 and an RX 480.
And they do show up with the same device IDs.
So while they were in different IOMMU groups,
I could not select just one of them to pass through.
And I started, I even rolled a whole kernel.
But I couldn't get the init RAM FS script that
would detect the boot GPU and then pass
through the non-boot GPU through.
I couldn't get that to run reliably.
So I ended up going back to Fedora
because in all honesty, I'm just more comfortable with Drakut
and using their init RAM FS system.
To me, it's more transparent and easier for me to read.
I'm sure I probably could have gotten there on Ubuntu.
But it would have taken a lot more time.
And I wanted to get this going.
So yeah, over to Fedora.
And it turns out I needed to use the ACS patch.
Well, there is a handy dandy pre-built kernel for it
in copper.
So I grabbed that.
That'll be linked in the show notes.
And loaded up the init RAM FS script
that I grabbed from the Arch Wiki
and dropped that into Drakut and off to the races.
It immediately put that second RX card into the VFIO drivers
and dropped it out of the host system entirely.
So like that monitor, boot up, that monitor's black.
It's not picking up anything.
And I could pass it straight through
to the VM, which is great.
Now, currently, the way I'm doing keyboard and mouse
is I am also passing through the USB 3.1 ports on my tower.
And I have a little USB 3 breakout
that I can plug between the front panel on my computer
to a USB extension that runs back to that USB 3.1
that I'm passing through.
And these are different devices.
So you still have USB ports for the host system.
But then you have a separate USB controller
that you can pass through to the guest?
Exactly, yeah.
So I just move that USB hub from one port to the other.
And boom, donzo, I've switched from controlling my host
to my VM.
So that was the simplest, easiest solution.
There's a fun little USB switcher thing
that you can buy, which is a box which has two USB cables coming
out the back.
One you plug into one bus, one you plug into the other bus
that's passed through to the VM.
And then there's a button on top of it
that you can physically press.
Where do I find this?
I'll find a link and put it in the show notes.
Thank you.
Yeah, I need that real bad.
So now for disks, I had originally
started trying to use a spare partition that I had.
But because this is UEFI, you can't really
use just a single partition.
The UEFI just does not work properly,
because it'll see that there is another UEFI on that same disk
and try to boot through that.
You have to do a whole disk.
And Alex, you can correct me if I'm wrong.
Maybe I didn't do it right, but it did not work for me.
So I think I need to go out and buy another SSD
and slap it in my tower to really do it right.
But right now, I'm using a raw image, not QCOW, but raw.
Why raw over QCOW?
Just because it's a little more performant.
And since I'm just using this for gaming and nothing
business facing, I don't really need the extra safety
that QCOW provides.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Yeah, I had the same internal debate myself.
So that's curious.
So once everything was all said and done with the pass-through
and all of that, did you run into any issues with the VM?
In particular, like Windows, when
you're working with an NVIDIA card,
it can kind of suss out that it's in a VM.
And the NVIDIA driver can essentially disable itself.
And that's where you get this really common code 43
in the event log that says, or it's
even when you just go into Device Manager
and you look at the driver, it'll be disabled.
And you go in there, and it'll say error 43 or code 43.
Device could not be properly initialized.
Did you run into any of that kind of stuff?
That's really common.
No, I use AMD because they don't pull
those kind of shenanigans.
You know what?
You say that.
However, I also, in this whole journey,
I switched from an NVIDIA card to an AMD RX 570.
And man, it worked perfectly under Windows 10.
And Mac OS just automatically detected it.
Never got it to work under Linux,
so I wonder if something's wrong there.
But under Windows 10, it works perfectly, full acceleration,
until I upgrade to the absolute latest Insider build,
so that way I could try out the WSL 2.
We were going to do a little report on it.
And when I do that, when I get to the latest build of Windows
and it sucks down a newer version of the GPU driver,
it disables my card, and I actually get code 43 now
in Event View or in the log for my AMD card.
It goes from working to not working.
I'd be cautious about throwing shade
based on an Insider build, though, that's pre-release.
Yeah.
Yeah, however, I did.
So get this, Daddy-O. I went back
to a clean Windows 10 standard install, which is up to date,
but it's just on a regular default track,
and downloaded the latest AMD driver from their website,
installed that, same issue.
I don't know, because I pulled the latest AMD driver
off the website just yesterday to do the install,
and it worked fine for me.
I'm loving Drew calling you on this, Chris.
I know.
Well, it really could be something in my setup,
because it's a new video card.
So you've got to work these things out.
Well, that's a pretty solid.
So what are you using it for, Drew?
Is it Windows stuff you're using it for,
or what's the utility you get out of this?
Windows 10 gaming.
So my wife is obsessed with this game called Arc,
and they just put out a new map,
and occasionally I like to play with her.
Now, Arc has a native Linux build, but it's terrible,
and trying to run it through Proton technically works,
but it also uses BattleEye, so it's real hit or miss.
And so I thought, well, okay,
I want to play with her on this new map,
so why don't I try this pass-through thing?
And yeah, I was able to get into the game
and play a little bit, and it works just great.
It's the only way I'm going to run Windows now.
It's like, it's Windows with a safety net,
because you've got snapshots,
you can physically copy the image file around.
It really, it feels like safe Windows to me,
and I like it.
So I'll just briefly, my setup is two different setups.
I've got what I call a virtualization go-bag,
and I'm very proud of this.
I showed it to Wes the other day,
and I was just going on and on about it.
I am so jealous,
and since I have the same backpack you used,
I might have to copy you.
Yeah, I use the swag backpack we got from Red Hat Summit,
and I use that as my virtualization go-bag.
So it's a companion backpack
that goes with my laptop backpack,
and I don't take it with me everywhere,
but I do sometimes take it between the studio and the RV.
And inside this backpack is a tiny HDMI 1080p LCD screen.
It's brilliant, because it's so compact.
Like, it's just super dense pixels,
and it just looks gorgeous,
and it's a very vibrant screen.
HDMI cable that goes into the Thunderbolt 3 Lenovo GPU dock
that I got.
I've talked about it before on the show.
This is why I bought the GPU dock too,
because I plan to do something like this, you know?
And so I have that in there,
which has a Thunderbolt 3 cable
that connects to the ThinkPad T480.
I've got a USB gaming headset, a USB mouse,
and a tiny portable USB keyboard
that all go in this backpack,
plus the power adapter that powers the whole thing.
I bust all that stuff out, I hook it up.
And in that, I've essentially got in that backpack
a Mac, a Win 10 VM, and an Ubuntu 1910 VM,
which I use for all kinds of different testing.
The host system, like I said, is the ThinkPad.
It runs Fedora 30, and it's been a dream to set this up.
I use Vert Manager as the software front end
to manage my VMs.
I love it, because I also have Vert Manager
connected now to the on-premises server
that we have here at the studio,
and I can manage those virtual machines
and my local virtual machines all through one UI.
It also is a very easy way, by the way, BT dubs,
to go through and select the PCI devices
you wanna pass through to the guest.
It's just nice, because I like seeing the device names,
selecting it, hitting apply, and then it's boom, it's set up.
Oh, that sounds really nice.
Yeah, you gotta do the blacklisting
of the PCI devices first, but once you've got them
blacklisted on the host system, which is not hard to do,
it's really just a matter of getting a list
of the PCI devices on your Linux box.
Checking it twice, I'm sure.
Yeah, and we'll have some guides linked in the show notes.
That's worth mentioning, Wes,
because if you blacklist the wrong device,
your system may not boot, because suddenly
the hard drive's ripped out from under the feet of the OS.
Just be careful with that.
Pro.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so you get a list of the PCI devices,
you blacklist their individual IDs, you reboot,
and then you go into Vert Manager,
and as you're setting up the VM,
you can go in and configure it for the additional options,
and you add hardware, and one of them is pass-through devices,
and you just start clicking on them.
It won't let you add a device you haven't blacklisted.
If a PCI device is in use, it won't let you assign it
to a VM, so it's pretty easy.
You can't put a square thing into a round hole in this case.
And once you have it all set up, you double click it,
you start it.
When you start it, it is such a sensation,
because you start what feels like a piece of software
on your laptop, and all these other physical hardware
devices light up.
The monitor comes on, the keyboard lights up,
the USB audio card turns on, the blue light comes on,
I hear that pop in the speakers.
It is amazing.
You've just magicked up another computer.
Exactly.
I've conjured it from nothing.
And what's crazy about it is, with modern systems,
with SSDs, and eighth generation processors,
and et cetera, et cetera, you don't even really
feel it on the host.
I'm just sitting there, I'm still
running like a dozen and a half electron apps,
I'm browsing websites in Chrome, I'm updating packages.
You don't even feel it on the host system,
because there's so much power to spare.
I've got cores for days, right?
And I've got 32 gigs of RAM in a laptop.
So it's just brilliant, because you've
got so much horsepower to spare that you can actually
have another complete environment.
And if you're even the slightest distro hopper or distro curious,
this is so wonderful, because I finally
got the perfect Linux desktop.
I am so happy with this setup.
I am so happy with where things are at right now in 2019,
because Linux is just doing so well.
The Mac is finally getting interesting again.
Windows 10 is not like Windows before.
That's something else I've learned in this experiment,
is they're doing different stuff with Windows 10.
When you bring Windows 10 up to the latest Insider builds,
and you get everything up to date
so you can run WSL and all those new goodies, it's a new OS.
It's absolutely something Microsoft would have held back
and made a different OS in years past.
I mean, I'm talking different UI, different assistance pop-up,
different menu options, completely different
configuration options.
It's a different start menu.
The login screen is different.
Everything changes in these later Insider builds.
And it's so exciting to watch.
I'm not going to switch to Windows 10.
I'm not going to switch to the Mac.
But it is fun right now.
The platforms are actually getting interesting again.
I happen to think Linux is the best right now.
And now it's letting me play with these other things
occasionally.
But more importantly, I can keep trying out the latest Linux
distributions without wiping my main setup.
And that's where I can fence off all the proprietary crap.
All of the closed source video card drivers,
like for the NVIDIA card, or proprietary games and software,
that's all now in these VMs.
And my desktop is like this pure open source stack.
That's just a rock solid machine.
And if nothing else, that's what I love about it.
It seems like it would work really well
for any sort of appliance, right?
Like maybe if you were going to record a show
and you could just sort of dock your ThinkPad into this setup
and have all the sound devices ready,
software configured in the VM set to go,
and you don't have to fuzz with it.
As we're recording this, we're recording this a little early
because of travel.
Last night, the Linus Tech Tips channel
released a video with something like six editors, one PC,
where they're using this technology with a GUI on top.
They're using Unraid as a KVM management tool.
And they're allocating each developer an SSD,
like 30 gigs of RAM or something like that,
a Titan video card.
And they're essentially setting up one Linux
PC to power six editing stations.
Yeah, it did cost them $100,000.
So it's in Mac Pro price territory.
So my other setup is I recently got,
and I'll have a link to this, a Mantiz eGPU dock.
And this thing's pretty neat because a Mantiz,
it's with a Z, it has not only a full sized PCI slot
for a full graphics card, so I put a AMD 570 in there.
But it also has a SATA enclosure inside,
so you can have a dedicated SATA disk.
It has a USB hub, so it's got, I think, five USB 3 ports.
And it's got gigabit ethernet.
That's everything you need to make a virtual machine
essentially a real PC.
There's really not much fake about it at that point
because I'm using real USB, real ethernet, real graphics,
real physical devices to interact with it.
It's running inside a VM, but it's not really
that much more unusual than a regular machine at that point.
You just happen to be using the CPU virtually.
Everything else is real.
Right, yes, absolutely.
Right, yeah, you're just kind of loaning it some compute.
Yes, and it's all coming in over one Thunderbolt 3
cable, which also, by the way, happens
to supply power to my laptop.
So I'm doing all of this with literally only a single cable
coming out of my laptop.
Now, there's video cable and USB cables and stuff
coming out the back of the eGPU box.
But the laptop, it's one cable, and it does all of this.
But still, shut up and take my money.
That sounds amazing.
It's so great.
It's so fun.
And to really be able to play around
with these operating systems and feel like they're full speed,
I'm never going back.
And I can honestly see myself not really needing
to reload my laptop, as long as the base OS continues
to run fine.
The base OS matters less than ever,
with Docker and containers and this and everything.
I looked last night.
I haven't reloaded my art system in 18 months,
because I don't need to.
Every time I get this itch, I can just spin up a VM
and pass the graphics card through, and it's so good.
Proxmox is another way to do this, right?
Doesn't Proxmox now support PCIe pass-through?
Yeah, so Proxmox just uses KVM under the hood anyway.
And this was a second setup, which
I realized I forgot to talk about.
So in my basement, I have a file server,
which is serving Plex and a whole bunch of other stuff.
I also have a PFSense VM on there.
Now, that VM has a 4 gigabit Intel NIC card,
with two of those ports pass-through.
One plugs into the WAN port on the back of my router,
and the other one plugs into my LAN.
And so I have a fully virtualized PFSense,
and I've been running it now since I moved here,
so since September.
And it's been great.
The only time I've had an issue is when the power's gone out,
and I haven't been home, because my router hasn't rebooted
properly or something.
But that's on the sysadmin.
That's not on the software being a problem.
Right, true.
So yeah, I pass through also to my main file server.
I also pass through three different SATA controllers.
One's an MVME one, and then I have one that has,
I think, 12 disks connected, and another one that
has another four disks connected or something.
So you can really take this technology and run with it.
And if you can think it, you can do it.
You just have to know how.
Right.
Yeah, I liked your note in the show notes, like, hey,
by the way, not a bad way to mine crypto.
Oh, yeah, no.
So when I was getting into Bitcoin mining,
this was when December, what, two years ago?
When Bitcoin was going bonkers, I
built a Bitcoin mining rig with like seven GPUs in it
or something.
Turns out, Windows has a four GPU limit.
So what did I do?
I created two Windows VMs and passed through four GPUs
to each VM, or four and three to each VM,
and got around the problem that way instead,
rather than doing all sorts of crazy registry
hacks that the internet was suggesting.
Problem solved.
I mean, one potential reason you could even
justify installing a video card in the server we have here
at the JB Studio is something else you could do
is run a headless VM of Windows that's accelerated,
and then do steam streaming, and just
pass through a whole bunch of games to all your Linux
boxes on the network.
That works stupidly well, except for one caveat.
You're going to need some kind of a dummy dongle
to go into the HDMI port to trick it
into the correct resolution.
So you can buy these things on Amazon that are 1080p,
like headless, tricky dongle things.
I don't know the name.
It's not technical, is it?
Yeah, but it's been around for a while.
You need them for a lot of Bitcoin mining setups, too.
Yeah, I have a question about this.
So I tried to steam stream from my Windows
pass-through VM to my Linux desktop that was a host,
and it did crash Steam on the host, not on the guest.
Is there anything special that needs
to be done to support this, like do I
need to pass through a discrete NIC,
or does it only work if the disk is fully passed through
and it's got a discrete disk?
Where am I going wrong?
Or is it just that this particular game is just
horribly buggy, which is certainly true?
Games don't have bugs in them.
Who are you kidding?
So there's a couple of ways to skin this turkey.
First of all, I don't know what you've done with your NICs,
but the traditional way is to use
Vert.io to have a 10 gigabit ethernet link
between the host and the guest.
So I'm assuming that's the way you go,
because that's what all the guides do.
You could do what Chris did and pass
through an actual physical NIC, which is also
another way to do it.
But what you might be running into
is the CPU pinning thing that I talked about earlier.
If one or either of the VMs or the host
runs out of enough CPU time, there
can be some contention issues there.
So it's worth pinning those CPU cores.
That is one thing I haven't gotten to yet,
so I will give that a shot.
Same.
Also, something else Drew might consider
is maybe just not doing this setup,
but playing around with something like Looking Glass.
Yeah, so Looking Glass is super duper cool.
So the frame buffer technology that Chris talked about
being potentially added to Mac OS,
this technology was developed by a chap on the Level 1 Tech
Forums.
Gniff, I think, is his moniker.
Wendell and all those guys over on Level 1.
So Looking Glass allows you to capture the frame buffer
output from the HDMI port.
So when Windows renders a frame, it
writes that very short term to a piece of memory.
What Looking Glass does is it hooks into that piece of memory
and makes it available from the guest to the host.
And there's also another patch that
lets you view that frame in a VM.
So you could effectively share this piece of memory
between two VMs via the host, which
is kind of meta and amazing.
And what this allows you to do is capture, basically,
in real time the HDMI output from the guest
and display it in a window on your Linux desktop.
Oh, wow.
So you could effectively marginalize
Windows to be nothing more than just a window.
And no physical monitor, physical keyboard.
Nope.
And the latency is sub-5 milliseconds.
So it's just as good as anything.
And it's pretty amazing.
It's better than some monitors.
Yeah.
Now, really, you can tie all that together
by getting some input in there, too,
with something like Synergy, which the audience tells us
all about all the time, and we never really talk about it.
But Synergy is there's a couple alternatives, too.
But it lets you move a mouse between hosts on your LAN
or the host and the VM.
Yeah.
We talked briefly about keyboard and mice earlier.
So there's the USB switcher option,
which is in the show notes.
There's Synergy, which allows you to just move your cursor
from one window to the next seamlessly
as if it's multiple windows on the same system.
It's like magic, and it's amazing.
There are other ways to do it using EV dev,
so you can actually pass the devices through that way.
Or you can use vrsh attach device,
which is a command that allows you to interact with your VM.
You need to write a couple of XML files,
and I've provided a couple of templates I use from my VFIO
repo on GitHub.
And it's a very simple.
You can just script it and bind it to a hotkey.
So I have a hotkey that changes the monitor inputs using
ddutil and also passes through my keyboard and mouse
at the same time.
And then I have the same thing in Windows,
but it just SSHs into the host remotely
and then undoes what it's just done.
So you have to give it some thought,
but it's not too hard to get a slick setup going.
Yeah.
So Chris, I know that one of the things that you've mentioned
is using macOS in a PCIe pass-through setup.
And would this be a way for me to possibly get away
from having to run macOS as being my daily driver
because I need those Adobe applications?
And then, two, how will that affect those Adobe
applications?
So whenever I go to render out, most often it's 1080p.
But whenever I go to render out 1080p video,
am I going to see a performance hit there on the rendering
side?
How exactly would this work out?
Because I would love to eventually have
a system like this where I have a rock solid Linux
base with VMs and pass-throughs.
I could see this being great for not only my desktop,
my personal desktop, but also my travel work laptop,
just being able to plug in, pass everything through,
get work done, shut it down, or not necessarily
have to feel like I need to reload an old beater machine
to test out maybe a different distro.
Totally.
But be able to play around with it a little bit more.
Well, I'll start with the latter half.
So the last half of the question is,
is it a performance penalty?
I think it depends on how you look at it.
I think to get a Mac that could outperform
what I can match in commodity PC hardware would probably
cost me thousands of dollars.
Could I buy an iMac Pro that would outperform this VM?
Yes.
Could I afford one?
No.
And the other thing that's nice about this
is this eGPU setup also can benefit the host system
down the road if I want.
I could plug this into another computer
and just use it as a video card if I want later.
It doesn't have to be used for VMs.
And obviously, I'm using this hardware
for multiple operating systems, which that wouldn't necessarily
be the case with Mac OS, even with Boot Camp.
You could even bring it to the Sprint or something, right?
And you're sharing your GPU with others.
Yeah, I mean, I've got the Go Bag.
I've got the Virtualization Go Bag.
And I would say that that is going to probably easily
outperform a laptop or a Mac Mini.
So that's where I look at the performance aspect.
And you could go all in, right?
You could get a really expensive PC,
and you could probably allocate just a portion of that
to outpower a Mac, unless you were
looking at the really high end.
Now, the other side of it.
Could you use it to run Final Cut and whatnot?
I haven't actually done a full edit session yet.
But you and I are on the same page here.
This is what I'm thinking is I'd really
like to get back into flying the drone
and doing drone videography and photography.
And as soon as I do that, I'm going to want to edit.
I'm going to want to color correct.
I'm going to want to fix it up a little bit.
And I'm going to want to use Final Cut,
because in my opinion, my experience, it's just the better
editor for online media.
Now, maybe I'll try some other ones over time.
Like, I'm not announcing some intention here.
It's just something that's been in the back of my mind.
I thought, well, OK, let's see.
Let's just see.
Could I, as a thought experiment,
before I go learn Blender or before I go spend
a whole bunch of time with DaVinci or et cetera, et cetera,
could I get Mac OS working in a VM that could actually
be hardware accelerated and use Final Cut?
Because in theory, I could easily
buy a video card that's nicer than 90% of the Mac video cards
that you get when you buy a Mac.
And to that end, there are surprisingly more and more
guides and systems to get Mac OS,
even the latest betas of Catalina, running under VM.
So I would say it's like hackintoshing,
but it's like the most Mac way possible to hackintosh,
because you have a known set of hardware
that you have a known set of drivers for.
So it's like how Apple develops Mac OS for the Mac.
It's like hackintoshing that way.
It's becoming like the go-to way to run Mac OS really easily
on PC hardware.
It's sort of the most reliable way to hackintosh right now.
Does that make sense?
There's some risk.
I mean, it's not a Mac, but it's probably the most solid.
And with Apple seemingly adding VertIO driver support
to later versions of Mac OS, it may be even easier soon.
There's a big caveat there, isn't there?
Don't you need a Mac to create the install
media in the first place?
No.
Not anymore.
You used to could, as my kids would say.
But have you seen this simple Mac KVM guide going around?
Nope.
You're going to tell me all about it now, though, right?
Yes.
We'll have a couple of links in the show notes.
It's pretty brilliant.
So there is a little tomfoolery going on to make it possible.
The author of this script, which is an open source script,
I think, I have not looked into it,
but I think is presenting to the Apple servers
a Apple user agent ID, because it's an HTTP request.
And I think this is maybe the only tomfoolery happening here.
But what you have is he's got two scripts, basic.sh,
and then there's a second script that essentially launches
the VM for you and does some of the pass-through commands.
And what basic.sh does is it says,
hey, what version of Mac OS would you like?
And you just add it with a TAC Catalina, TAC Mojave,
or whatever.
And then it goes and it knocks on Apple's recovery server
doors and says, hi, I'm a broken iMac,
and my user needs to reload their operating system.
Can I stream the installer from you, please?
And it says, OK, here's the URL on the Akamai CDN.
We'll blast you those packets as fast as humanly possible,
or actually electronically possible.
And so it tells the recovery service
that you're a broken iMac.
And you can then, without ever having
to download from the Mac store and flash a USB disk
or anything, it'll get you the recovery ISO.
Then you boot that in the VM, and it just pulls down
the installer like a net install would.
Does it work with modern Nvidia GPUs?
Because Apple haven't shipped 10 series, have they?
Now, your mileage there is going to vary.
This is that fun corner of Hackintosh, isn't it?
Yeah, you're going to have a much better time with an AMD
graphics card.
Is that the same for AMD and Intel
as far as being supported by Hackintoshing?
See, this is where doing it in a VM
actually makes things a little easier,
because that stuff is a little more abstracted.
It's just standard VM stuff at that point.
And so it just looks like a regular Intel system
or whatever to the Mac OS.
So it doesn't care about the underlying chip architecture
at all?
No, not really, as long as your CPU supports all the stuff.
Now, to be clear, I have run into issues with networking
support and whatnot.
I'm not here proclaiming that it works flawlessly yet.
I've gotten close.
But I have not gotten it all working yet.
I have not gotten through a full test of Final Cut yet.
I have not brought in 4K footage.
So it's up in the air.
I have gotten Linux and Windows VMs.
Those are my priority.
And no surprise here, guess what operating system
works the best, Linux.
I actually now have decided that I'm
going to do all of my gaming in a VM.
I'll just have a VM image, or actually this SSD disk,
if I can say that, this SSD disk that's
in my eGPU is just going to be loaded with a VM that's
got all my Steam games and all my GOG games installed
and all my Lutris games always installed
with all of the proprietary graphics drivers installed.
I hook that up to my base system, and I start playing.
No more downloading.
Maybe I have to patch a little bit.
No big deal.
Linux is such a great guest in this setup.
So it's like, even if you never have
any intention of running Windows or Mac OS,
it's absolutely worth it just to play with Linux.
I thought, though, too, Wes has talked about this a little bit
on and off in the past.
But since we're doing different crazy great ways
to run Linux and other operating systems
without having to nuke your install,
Wes has got a clever way that he likes to run machines.
I know you've played around with a few different things.
What do you want to share with the class today, Wes?
Oh, man, there's just so many ways.
I was disappointed to hear that some of this pass-through stuff
might not work with partitions because just having
a separate partition can be an easy way down that road
where you can boot into something,
or it's really easy to use virtualization to just attach
to an existing partition.
And as long as you're not accessing that
or have it mounted in the host, then away you go.
I love that just because anytime I
can use the host system to install a new operating system
without having to reboot and go through that painful cycle
of disconnecting everything I'm doing
or having to go get a second computer,
I just don't want to be bothered.
You know, I do kind of walk kind of a happy medium here.
I'm passing through ISO images, and I am doing a Cal file.
But I also, for the Windows installation,
before I wanted to get everything all plugged in
and everything, I just clicked in the VM
and had it grab my mouse and keyboard.
I actually did the whole Windows install
with a laptop mouse and keyboard on the laptop screen using,
it's like a VN, they call it Spice,
where you can just remote view.
I did that, and then once the installation was done,
I hooked up all the physical hardware.
So I kind of do like a balance there.
Windows can actually boot from a raw image
as long as you make it in the VHD format.
So if you already had, say, a shared NTFS drive,
that's one way you can easily do it from a file
if you don't want to muck about with separate drives
or even a separate partition.
So that's nice, too, is if you're clever about it,
you can often boot into files, especially on Linux,
because you can make Linux do anything.
You can have a virtual machine image,
set it up in a virtual machine,
and then if you play around with your init RAM FS
or your grub setup a little bit,
you can reboot right into that
and not have to mess with having a separate system.
You just got to know how, huh?
You just got to know how.
So that's something that I use quite heavily.
I actually switched away from grub to system de-boot
on my host.
It makes it a lot easier to specify
which particular kernel I'm booting into
or things like that than I found grub.
So give system de-boot a try.
Oh, yeah, it's fantastic.
And the configuration files are easy to read
and easy to modify.
Very good.
And then I suppose for something completely different,
if you don't feel like virtualizing,
there's always kexec,
which we've talked about that before, too,
which is sort of like live switching to a whole new kernel.
Wes likes to make it extra spicy.
By then, when you kexec, you also are running his,
he runs his disk out of RAM.
So it's like the whole thing is just like.
Right, I mean, if you're not sure about a distribution,
you just want to give it a try.
You really don't want to commit.
That's about as close as I can get.
You could just, the ultimate rage quit,
you turn off the power button
and the entire thing is erased.
You know, it's gone, it's so satisfying.
I wonder how fast Windows would feel
if I ran it from RAM.
I might try that.
Oh, you should.
I think Windows Update would still take forever.
I'll tell you what.
Oh, that's been one thing
that I have just shaken my head at.
They've tried to make it better in the later builds,
but what they did is they added like six more screens
of options.
That's a lot.
I really just appreciate package managers after that.
All right, well,
I know we just kind of given you the basics to get started,
but this is one of those things you'll have to go deep dive.
We'll have some additional resources in the show notes
and a surprise here.
Shocker, everybody.
The Arch Wiki is also a great resource.
Who would have known?
We'll be back with a regular format
at our regularly scheduled live time over at jblive.tv.
Right here next Tuesday.
Oh, man.
I apparently in last week's code radio,
I leaked what the next free study groups are
on Linux Academy.
I didn't mean to.
I guess I did talk about it
before it was public on there.
Oops.
Well, I don't know.
You know, this is one of those episodes
I have been wanting to do PCI.
I know I said this beginning,
but I really been wanting to do a PCI pass-through
since it was ever, ever a thing.
And it always seemed,
it always seemed like just like way too much work
to get started with.
Yes.
I've been following it too, right?
Cause it's always been that sort of holy grail,
like, oh, maybe you need windows.
You don't want to deal with separate machines or rebooting.
You can have everything and I guess you can.
Yeah, I think it's totally worth it.
And it's not that bad anymore.
If you've got modern hardware, that's really the keys.
You gotta happen to have some current stuff,
but eventually everybody's going to have this stuff.
And then we're really going to be cooking with gas.
Like it's going to be,
I'm just really excited about the potential.
And now that I have an Nvidia setup and an AMD setup,
I feel like I'm going to really be able to get to play.
Like neither one of the setups
are particularly high end graphics wise,
but there's still so much to learn
and see how systems respond with different graphics stacks.
And that's going to be a particular area of interest
for me, I think.
I've just dropped into Slack a link to a file
that might help your networking issue on OS 10.
This BRNetFilter thing needs to be called by sysctl
at boot time to allow the IP tables, I think,
to be modified.
So I think my Windows VM wouldn't get an IP address
until I enabled this.
So that's worth considering.
It's in that archvfio repo that's on my GitHub.
Of course.
And in the show notes.
Yeah, I was going to say.
OS, you're on top of it.