I think PipeWire just landed the killer feature
that's gonna make every desktop Linux user
want to transition to PipeWire.
What is it?
In version 0.3.25, you can now use your phone
as a microphone to your Linux box through Bluetooth.
What?
Yeah, and that's an awesome feature.
I think that's something we need to try.
It makes it now possible to use A2DP
as a source input device.
So you can then use your phone as an A2DP microphone.
And you know, Wes, like some of these phones actually
have decent microphones on them.
This could be like a seriously great way
to get audio from a guest or somebody.
You're just tired of dragging that remote mic around.
Yeah.
Or just, you think Joe will let us get away
with using our phones for doing the show?
I think we better try without telling him.
Hello, friends, and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
And can I just say, your new 400 after-party face
tat you got is, well, it's going to heal real soon.
Aw, thank you.
But you know, you still owe me.
You said you'd paid for it if I got the show's logo on my face.
Right.
Yeah, we'll get to that.
But first, I want to thank ACG for sponsoring
this episode of Linux Unplugged.
They are the leader in learning for Cloud, Linux,
and other modern tech skills.
Hundreds of courses, thousands of hands-on labs,
get certified, get hired, get learning at acloudguru.com.
Well, coming up on the show today,
it's the show that wasn't supposed to be.
We were going to take the week off.
And we thought about it a little bit.
We thought, well, actually, there's a lot to catch up on.
We have a lot that we want to cover.
There's things from 400 we still have to talk about.
And so we're going to kind of have the no-show.
It's like a no-show this week.
From the wackos that brought you running arch on their server,
we're going to talk about hosting your own email server.
This is another one of those don't do
as we do kind of episodes, unless you really want to.
We're going to cover some server basics, what
you need to be aware of, and how we're
going to try to make it all work smooth for us
and what our use case is going to be
for self-hosting our own email.
But we'll get to all of that.
There's a lot to take in there.
The truth of the matter is we just have a lot going on.
We wanted to do something kind of fun with you guys this week.
And we'll take time off in the near future.
We'll take a week off, because we do have a great interview
all about an individual who didn't know anything
about construction, didn't know anything about diesel engines,
didn't know anything about Linux,
didn't know anything about automation.
And he went out and bought himself a school bus
and rebuilt it from the ground up as a mobile home
that he works from with his family on the road,
all powered by Linux, using automation
to manage the tanks and the batteries and all of it.
And so it's a great conversation.
If you want inspiration or just a little,
you can get your project done, that's
the interview right there.
Yeah, it's so inspiring how somebody
who didn't know something just decided, so what?
I'm just going to go learn it.
And he just, at every turn, he had to just go learn something.
And even when it came to setting up a Linux server,
he didn't sway.
He just said, you know what?
I've gotten this far.
I'm going to learn it.
So we will run that story in the future.
It just today didn't feel like the right time,
because we had a lot we want to do.
And we just had an episode that was honestly a little off topic.
So today, we're just going to have some fun.
So before we go any further, let's
bring in our virtual lug, time-appropriate greetings,
Mumble Room.
Hello.
It's Tuesday.
Why are there 25 of you here?
We told you for two weeks in a row
we weren't doing a show today.
I don't know if they weren't listening,
or they were listening when we said we were
going to do a show like today.
I think everyone's still drunk on beer from episode 400.
That's what I think.
I am.
Yeah.
You know.
Speaking of episode 400, the votes are in.
Our special 400 brew was named by the community.
It's officially named the See You Next Tuesday beer.
The See You Next Tuesday.
And I'm drinking a little Tuesday right now, Wes,
let me tell you.
Oh, you got things plumbed up again, huh?
Drinking in my beer stein, too, Wes, in my brand new 400 beer
stein.
If you ordered them early, they were already starting to arrive.
Oh, that's great.
It's actually pretty special, in a way.
You know, I mean, I'm sitting here in my studio
drinking a Linux-unplugged beer in a Linux-unplugged beer
stein.
Talk about self-hosting, right?
Right, and we're doing an episode
because we just wanted to.
We could have taken the week off.
We said we were going to, but we just kind of wanted to.
So yeah, the beer steins are shipping,
which is really great.
Yours is here, Wes, waiting for you.
Oh, great.
I've been jealous.
I mean, I've already seen a few community members posting
theirs on Telegram or on the matrix server, which
is awesome.
Please keep doing that.
They look good in your hands out there.
That's true.
I do love seeing that, and I think they do look good.
I'm really happy with how they turned out,
and I'm glad that they're shipping right away
because Coda Radio listeners will
know that I recently had my butt kicked by a robe.
I was schooled by a robe and didn't like that very much.
It's been a minute, Wes, since I really was schooled.
I went to the hard knocks of business school
for a couple of weeks.
I think we might need a sandboard clip for that one.
Really?
It was bad.
But I did learn some fundamental lessons, I'll say that.
I just learned them the really, really hard way.
And so towards the end of the show today,
after we get through the news and the email server stuff,
I'm going to share some very new and first steps
that I'm taking to grow Jupiter Broadcasting as a business.
It's kind of been just about a year-ish
since the plans to go independent were
beginning and the thought and the process was starting.
And so I want to do a bit of an update for you all
and share that with you.
We have a couple of big updates there and some lessons
I've learned, some humble pie that I have to eat,
and all of that.
But we'll get there.
But first, let's do some business
and let's get to the community news
because we have an update from Google.
It seems Google has become concerned
about the correctness of code, as they put it
in the Android platform.
And they say, correctness of code
is a top priority for the security, stability,
and quality of each Android release.
Unfortunately, memory safety bugs in C and C++
continue to be their most difficult to address
source of, quote, incorrectness, not bugs.
Here we're talking about the Android underpinnings,
not like the Java or Kotlin or whatever
framework you're using to develop your Android apps,
but all the stuff that runs at the lower levels.
And we should probably give them credit because, I mean,
Google and Android developers more widely
do invest a lot of effort and resources trying to detect,
trying to fix, or just mitigate this type of bug upfront.
And those efforts are pretty effective.
I mean, yes, bugs get through, but a large number of bugs
are prevented from ever making it into an actual Android
release.
And then from me complaining about it on air.
But memory safety issues are still a big contributor,
even given all of that.
Something like 70% of Android's high severity security
vulnerabilities are due to memory safety issues.
Oof.
Yeah, that's not great.
So to help combat this, Google is
excited to announce their words that the Android open source
project now supports the Rust programming
language for developing the operating system itself.
Rust?
On my phone?
Wow.
Google notes that adding the new language to the Android platform
is, quote, a large undertaking.
No kidding.
I mean, that comes alongside Java and Kotlin too, right?
They say that there are tool chains and dependencies that
needed to be maintained, test infrastructure and tooling
that had to be updated.
And then here's a big one.
Developers needed to be trained.
And for the past 18 months, Google
has been adding Rust support to the Android open source
project and has a few early adopter projects
that they'll be talking about.
They say scaling this to more of the OS
is a multi-year project.
So stay tuned, and there will be more updates
from the Google Security blog.
And didn't we see that the Bluetooth stack, Wes,
was one of their first kind of go out there and fix
them projects?
Yes, it was.
You know, I hope Mozilla feels secretly good about this.
I mean, I think this is Google admitting Rust is good stuff.
And they're not just talking about it in a small way.
They're talking about it alongside Java and Kotlin.
Yeah, I mean, it sounds like this
is going to be a first class language you
can use to implement whatever features you might
need in the base OS itself.
And at least once tooling is up to speed,
once all the build infrastructure is there.
But that's a significant investment and endorsement.
I love that we kind of put our eye on this about a year ago,
that the Rust type was really building.
And Google's been, for that entire time, working on this.
Also, speaking of Rust, listener Mike Kelly
was just looking for an excuse to play around with Rust
and wanted to celebrate Linux Unplugged's 400th episode.
And so he combined a little bit of Rust with a fun project
and created a mini website at lup400.com.
And you know what, Wes?
It's all powered in Rust.
Hey, and it sure looks better than any of our websites.
Right?
I didn't really realize you could develop websites in Rust.
Tells you what a noob I am.
And then the other thing he did, which is really adorable,
is he embedded episode one, which nobody should probably
ever listen to, in there.
So Mike, I guess we should get in contact.
It's time for you to rewrite the entire Jupyter broadcasting
website in Rust.
How on brand would that be?
Cool.
That's what we need.
Thank you, Mike, for doing that.
Yeah, we'll have a link if you want to check it out.
Of course, it's open source.
How great.
So this episode, we thought maybe,
and maybe one of the reasons to go live,
is that we'd have an update on that Linux-powered helicopter
on Mars named Ingenuity.
It was set to take its first test flight.
And then by just about now, as we'd be recording,
we'd have the return data from the surface of Mars.
But it turns out that helicopter flight was delayed.
During a high-speed spin test of the rotors on Friday,
the command sequence controlling the test
ended early due to a watchdog timer expiration.
And as you can imagine, those watchdogs are there
to catch things that aren't working very well.
And so it triggered a process of stop.
We have to diagnose and figure out what went wrong.
But Wes, it seems like maybe they actually figured out
what the failure was.
Yeah, that's right.
I mean, at least so they say.
The Ingenuity team has identified a software solution
for the command sequence issue.
I guess over the weekend, they basically considered
and tested all the ideas of what this could be
and how they could address it.
And they concluded that a tiny little modification
and reinstallation of Ingenuity's flight control software
was the most robust path forward.
Although that sounds pretty tough when this thing is on Mars.
I know, it's like, there's nothing straightforward
about reinstalling a software package
on a tiny helicopter in the belly of a rover.
Actually, now it's not.
But there's just nothing simple about that.
And that's why it has to go through extensive testing.
The software update will modify the process
by which the two flight controllers boot up,
allowing the hardware and software to safely transition
to the flight state and meet the time expectations.
Yeah, and so it sounds like they actually know
what this changes.
It's not gonna be that big of a deal.
They've got mockups here on Earth.
They've definitely experimented with it before,
but they've actually got to transmit all those updates
all the way there to the rover itself,
get it transferred over to Ingenuity,
and then actually run the update command.
And I mean, we've all updated things on servers
and sort of waited for the prompt to come back,
but can you even imagine?
No, Wes.
No, I am not the personality type for this kind of stuff
because I get anxious when we reboot the Arch server
in the garage.
Yeah, I think this is one of those
measure twice, patch once situations.
Yeah, so okay, so they have to get it tested.
They have to get it qualified, as they put it,
and then they have to upload it,
and then it has to install.
So they don't really have a new test flight date.
They say our best estimate is a targeted fluid date.
We're working towards achieving these milestones,
and we should be able to set a flight date next week.
So possibly by next week's episode,
we'll have an update on when the first
Linux-powered helicopter will fly on Mars.
Here's hoping.
And really, we should expect these kind of things, right?
This is all brand new science.
A few things are bound to go wrong.
Lino.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get a $100 60-day credit towards a new account,
and you go there to support the show.
Linode is our cloud server provider.
I was just messing around this weekend.
I actually love it for setting up multiple servers
and then trying out different distributions
and different software packages,
and then picking a winner,
and then that's the Linode that remains standing,
and I just destroy all of the other ones.
They're the world's largest independent
cloud computing provider,
and they make it easy to get your creation
on the internet fast,
no matter what your skill level is.
If you're brand new to Linux,
you're brand new to servers,
or if you've been doing it for a decade,
they got a technology stack that'll work for you,
and they can help your ideas come to life on the web.
And if you run into any trouble,
Linode comes with amazing,
outstanding 24-7 customer support
by phone or by ticket.
This is like the number one thing I hear now
from our audiences.
Man, I was in a jam,
and Linode stuck with me through the entire thing.
I've got one $5 a month server,
and they still help me out.
On top of that,
they have hundreds of guides and tutorials
to help you get started
and dig through what you need to know
or understand some terminology,
and they have things like how to secure phpMyAdmin
if you're gonna use that,
because honestly, I understand it's a good tool,
but you gotta be a little bit worried
about putting that out in the public.
They have guides to help you manage things like that,
so that way, you have some confidence,
some peace of mind.
That's what's great about their guides.
They give you that kind of confidence
to put this stuff into production,
and they have easy-to-use, one-click applications
for like a LAMP stack or WordPress,
but also some other really kind of really more sophisticated
and complicated things to set up,
from gaming servers to entire e-commerce stacks.
And with S3-compatible object storage,
you can find all kinds of great usage
for things that don't require a server
but still need storage in the cloud.
They have super-fast networking
and 11 data centers worldwide.
Plus, they support shows like this
and events like Linux Fest Northwest,
All Things Open, The Kubuntu Project,
a lot of Linux media out there.
I mean, they're a pretty special company,
and they have a great service.
They've been around since 2003,
and they've really dialed it in like nobody else.
And now, they're just dedicating to make sure
that if you wanna run something on Linux,
it's not gonna run anywhere better than it runs on Linode.
It's gonna run fast, it's gonna run stable,
and you're gonna get a bunch of great information
and fantastic customer support
and a company that loves Linux behind it,
and you can support one of your favorite podcasts
at the same time.
So go to linode.com slash unplugged.
Well, it looks like someone spilled beer all over in here.
I think it's time we clean up, Chris.
Yeah, we could do for a spot of housekeeping around here.
So I just wanna mention that if you wanna get
a little more show, one of the things you can do
is subscribe to the membership program.
That's a great way to get more show.
We have two feeds available, one that is a limited ad feed,
and one that is the full everything we did live feed.
I mean, sometimes it's two hours long,
but there's a lot of content in there.
We try to make it entertaining,
and we make it available as our members
as a way to say thank you.
So if you'd like to become a member,
go to unpluggedcore.com, keep the unplugged program
independent, and reduce the ad load needed
to make the show actually sustainable.
And check out jupiterbroadcasting.com.
We got a batch of great shows, like a bouquet.
Yeah, there you go, a bouquet of podcasts,
a bouquet of podcasts over at jupiterbroadcasting.com.
And last but not least, join the LUP Lug on Sundays.
They get together, they self-organize,
and they hang out and talk about, well, things you love.
That's in our Mumble Room.
You can get details at linuxunplugged.com.
And then you join Sundays, noon Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern,
and it's just right there in our Mumble lobby.
And the great thing is, then you're all set up with Mumble.
And you can come to the live show if you get a Tuesday.
Maybe, I don't know, maybe you get the Rona.
You wanna take some time off from work.
They're not gonna ask any questions, you know?
You just come show up in the Mumble,
we won't ask any questions.
I mean, how do you think there's,
now there's nearly 30 people in there right now.
You think one of them, at least one of them
must be calling in sick.
We're on to you, and you could do that too.
Details at linuxunplugged.com.
That's probably our best housekeeping ever.
By far.
I think so, I think so.
I think, you know, that was good.
You know, we connected with people there.
Well, and you decided to just double down,
and instead of cleaning up the beer you spilled,
you just spilled beer on the places
that it hadn't previously reached, so it's consistent.
Yeah, I like the way it smells.
So, don't host your own email server.
But you know what?
I don't really feel like going into a lecture
of reasons why you shouldn't.
I feel like we've covered it,
but super briefly, it's hard to get it right.
And it's something that people really rely on,
and it's really easy to get sucked into a black hole
where people start rejecting your emails.
And not to mention,
there's a lot of security considerations.
Yeah, and for some reason,
email is like internet infrastructure.
You know, businesses, banks, whatever.
They expect that emails go through,
and you probably expect that you receive your email.
So, if you are gonna play with this,
at least keep that in mind,
and maybe do it on a domain
that you can experiment around with,
and not your main one.
Well, and you gotta figure,
people in our audience, you know,
they maybe have a project they're working on,
or a small team of people.
Or you have like our Lug, right?
Wouldn't it be kind of cool
if our Lug could have an email address,
and members of our Lug could have their own email?
We were thinking for 400.
That'd be kind of a fun thing to do for our Lug,
is create a Lug Lug email address.
And so, that's kind of what we were thinking,
is that's a great example
where you got a small group of people,
you don't necessarily wanna be paying
five plus dollars a month per mailbox
to host it somewhere,
and you just wanna, whatever,
like you just wanna pay whatever the cost is
to run the server,
and create as many accounts as you want,
three to 100 or whatever.
And that's the goal we're kind of shooting for,
is creating a humble mail server with,
that's my word of the day today,
is everything's just,
I got a lot of humility after getting my butt
kicked by a robe.
Mine's not gonna be humble.
Mine's gonna be bold, brazen on the internet.
Good for you.
Mine, everything is humble pie with me.
Cause once you've gotten your butt kicked by a robe,
you don't walk around with your head hanging high.
Let me just put it that way.
But something simple, not too complicated.
And there are actually other reasons,
I think, to host your own server.
Privacy and control being big ones.
You have full control over both the server
and your email itself.
You can view the logs of incoming
and outgoing messages directly.
You can pick the applications you want,
so you can mix and match the server software
and the client software.
And you also are implementing your own
data retention policies.
Perhaps you want to keep things forever,
or maybe you don't want to keep things past 30 days.
You get to choose.
I mean, it's also probably worth saying that email is,
for all of the difficulties we were just mentioning,
it is still one of those things that like,
it just interoperates, right?
You don't have to go officially like register somewhere.
There's not one party controlling it all.
If you want to host it, if you get it right anyway,
you can, and that's cool and worth celebrating.
Yeah, and really, I think there is the cost aspect too.
Right.
This is something everybody has to find a balance on,
but there's this, you're never really gonna pay more
than just the cost of running the server in your time,
where with a lot of hosted solutions,
you're gonna pay per person.
Yeah, or I mean, it can kind of vary, right?
Like they get to choose how they want to monetize
off that service.
And so it might align with your use case.
I've been using Zoho for a while,
so for some of my non-Gmail or other hosted domains,
and it works pretty fine.
I get like aliases, but if I ever did wanna add more users
or say I started a small business with some friends
and I wanted to add them on there
or for an open source project or something for the show,
it's not very flexible, at least without paying more money.
And that has had me thinking about self-hosting for a while.
Yeah, and there's just sort of like,
can I still do this, you know?
Like, can I still make this work?
Cause I used to do this, but I haven't done it a long time.
And in fact, one of my very first jobs
when I got into IT, like my second or third job,
I can't remember, but it was early into it.
They just let me go on managing their mail server
and it was a deep dive.
And I really kind of became a, I became a pro.
I really got into it for a while.
And I'm wondering like, does that skillset still exist?
Will that come back as we do this?
Is hosting your own email server just like riding a bike?
You know, speaking of that,
I'm not sure I've seen you ride a bike either.
Oh, well, you know, if we could come up with a show reason,
you'll see me do it.
That's all it takes.
Every mail server out there can really kind of be broken
down into three separate software components.
You have the mail transfer agent that relays mail
between your server and the wider internet.
You have the mail delivery agent that takes mail
from that MTA and then sends it to the individual mailboxes.
And you have the interface that clients will connect to it,
which is often like IMAP or even used to be POP3,
which lets users check their email
from their preferred client.
And then there's like additional stuff
you have to kind of consider, right?
Because that's the basics of a mail server
and you have to pick those software components
that you think do the best job.
But there's also security components
to setting up a mail server today.
And of course, there's DNS.
Yes, our old friend, the domain name system.
You're gonna need to set something up
so people know how to reach your email server.
You'll need at least a MX record, SPF and pointer.
Starting with MX there,
that's gonna tell people how to send you email, right?
Like I've got an email west at jupiterbroadcasting.com.
And when an outgoing server looks that up
and says, how do I send email?
They go find jupiterbroadcasting.com,
look for the MX record that tells them the server
to point to, and then they can actually connect
and start sending email.
And the important thing to consider here too
is there's security things around DNS as well,
like SPF records, which help establish the legitimacy
of your mail server and reduce the chances
that somebody's spoofing as you.
And the SPF record for your domain
tells other receiving mail servers
which outgoing servers are legit to kind of receive from.
So it's a lookup for them to do
to see if the sender is a legitimate sender or not.
And don't forget to set up reverse DNS.
Yeah, I know, sometimes we just get lazy,
we just do the one direction,
but the reverse DNS for your mail server
really should match the host name of your server.
So people go to query, hey, what's this IP?
Who's sending me this mail?
That needs to match,
otherwise you might get some ugly rejections thing saying,
hey, the reverse DNS does not match your SMTP banner.
And you're not gonna have fun with that.
Oh man, this is really bringing me back.
There is a lot for you and I to consider.
And I mean, I would imagine we'd never probably have
more than 50 email accounts on this box.
But even this isn't getting into like the antivirus
and spam prevention stuff,
because one of the things I did back in the day
was I'd have to route mail through Clam AV
and scan it on the mail server.
So that way, hopefully I wasn't delivering viruses
to Windows users.
Right, and I mean, these days,
I think with web mail being so common,
especially hosted by big parties like Googs or Microsoft,
they do all of that for you.
You probably expect that.
And if you suddenly have an unfiltered inbox,
especially if you've pasted that email around the internet,
that could be a nasty surprise.
And I'm glad you mentioned web mail too,
because that's something else I think you and I
should consider for this project,
because if this is kind of like a vanity account,
it's kind of like an extra account for people
who participate in the community they wanted or whatever.
Like, I don't know,
I haven't really thought through this completely,
other than I kind of picture the use case
being lub lug members who wanna reach out to guests
or organize events for the lug
and wanna come from an email account
that kind of seems sort of semi-official and connected,
like jupitercolony.org or something like that.
But I don't really envision that being more
than a handful of people
and then whatever you and I choose to use it for.
But even there, it's like, well,
okay, so it's not gonna be their primary email account.
So how can we make it accessible to them?
And web mail is probably one of the ways to do that,
but there's a lot of web mails to choose from.
Yeah, I'd like one that doesn't suck, please.
I mean, at least if I'm gonna use it
and not just have to set up a client because it's so bad.
Yeah, this is definitely one I could use some advice from,
from anybody in the mumble room
or people that are listening
that wanna go to linuxunplug.com slash contact.
Assuming we set up kind of a standard mail server set up
with IMAP on the backend,
what would you recommend we use for the web mail front end?
Because our goal here is
to kind of get everybody's feedback from this episode
and go build something by the next episode.
It's a little ambitious,
but that's kind of what we hope to do with episode 402
is say, okay, the email server's up and running.
Here's how we built it.
Here's kind of what we considered.
Here's the web mail clients we're going with.
Here's the desktop clients we're going with
and then give away some email addresses on it
and stuff like that.
It's kind of what our intention is for 402.
But I think the number one thing I'm hung up on right now
is what web mail client to go with
because part of me is sort of leaning towards simple,
like squirrel mail.
Classic.
Right?
You know it works, right?
And then part of me is kind of leaning towards something
like round cube or something
that's maybe a little more modern,
but I don't even know what that would be anymore.
Yeah, that's just it.
It's like, it's been so long
since I've really played in this space,
but you know our talented audience out there,
there's email self-hosters among them
and they've surely got some tips.
I hope so.
And then I'm going to take all of this experience
and see if my current bias
that I still think people probably on the whole
shouldn't self-host email.
That's how I feel today.
We'll see if that's how I feel after we do this experiment
because I felt that way about Arch too.
Exactly.
Let us be your lazy admins.
We'll try it out.
See if it works.
See how big of a mess we make.
And then you can judge, is it worth the time?
Yeah, and you know what?
Honestly, I thought Nextcloud would blow up on our face too
and here we are like almost two years into using it now
and we've had to make modifications to how we use it
and it hasn't been perfect and it's sinking,
but once we learned kind of how to use it, it's been fine.
Yeah, yeah.
I mean, we definitely like to complain about it sometimes
and there are improvements it could have,
but we haven't kicked it out of our infrastructure
and more often than not, it's a dependable part of it.
Yeah, and then we can update you on how it's going to
and stuff like that and I'm funny.
I kind of enjoy the idea of my prejudice being flipped.
I like the idea that I'm coming into something thinking
we shouldn't be doing this, it's not going to work
and then have it be successful and have to kind of go,
oh, okay, it was worth doing
and then kind of try to come to terms with,
well, why was it worth doing?
What did I get wrong?
What was I missing until I tried it?
And I think that's a good experience
to share with the audience too.
So that's what I'm hoping we get out of this.
Yeah, this is definitely one of those areas
where you see a lot of different mixed advice from folks.
Some people have no problems doing it
and then you have a lot of, for good reason,
people chiming in saying like, look, this is just hard.
You might have difficulties
and if you don't want to spend hours on your Saturday,
troubleshooting, don't try,
but you can't know until you actually try it for yourself.
I'm coming into the back end of this conversation,
so I'm not going to ask why you want to do this.
Hello, Wimpy.
Hello.
But you could potentially save yourself some heartache
by capitalizing on things like Mail in a Box,
where there is a community maintaining a deployable,
full stack mail environment,
which pulls on multiple people
with experience in that space.
Wes, we've gotten a lot of recommendations
for Mail in a Box over the years.
I think, you know, probably at least a dozen.
I know there's some competitors,
but that's the one that sticks out in my mind,
even though I've actually never tried it.
Yeah, I haven't tried it either.
And neither have I, and I only cite that one
because it's the name that came to the front of my mind,
but there must be other things like that.
It was interesting, both of you saying,
it's been ages since you've done something like this.
I can't, well, in fact, I can remember the last time
I did anything to do with mail servers was in 2016,
when my last job was to maintain a fleet
of massive mail servers for a CV application
that was sending out like 27 million emails a minute,
like 24 seven or something.
I love those kinds of memories.
You know, looking back at that,
thinking that is crazy today,
like something you would never catch yourself doing now,
right, I would assume you just would never build that again.
Well, I mean, I didn't build it,
I inherited this sort of, you know, of course.
Oh, those are even better.
And you know, things have moved on
in the intervening six years that would mean
that you just wouldn't do it quite like that ever again.
But yeah, I mean, interesting experiment.
It will be, we shall see.
And I guess we know who to ask for help.
Yeah, you're gonna be our go-to mail admin.
I am tempted to try Mail in a Box.
I'm very tempted to try that
because we have gotten it recommended so many times.
You recommend it yourself, Wimpy.
It might be the way we go.
Like I say, I've never used it, it's just the name I know.
The orange one, you have a suggestion for us as well.
Yeah, years and years ago,
when I made the terrible decision of hosting my own email,
I used a alternative to Mail in a Box called MailCal,
which is sort of this Dockerise setup.
So you just run a command, it runs everything for you.
And that I found to be really nice.
It uses a alternative to Roundcube called Sogo,
which is sort of materially fancy, looks a bit pretty,
but basically is webmail and calendar and all of that stuff.
And from what I used of it, it was really quite nice
and just sort of got out of your way and just worked.
How did you spell that?
Sogo, S-O-G-O.
Oh, okay, that's easy.
All right, I will definitely look at that.
Yeah, the webmail thing is like,
I'm trying to chew on that one right now.
I'm not sure if Mail in a Box provides a webmail client
I might be worth looking into.
Maybe they've already picked something there.
The other option is that you could go super simple
and just go full on like Zimbra.
I have run Zimbra for a couple of clients.
I use Zimbra also as a mechanism
to backup exchange servers.
And I recall Zimbra had a fantastic search.
So if you're somebody out there looking for
kind of a suite of tools with really good search
and like a SQL backed email database,
Zimbra is really good.
I don't know if it's still the case,
but certainly back in the day when I was deploying Zimbra,
my citation for successful deployments was Red Hat.
I know they were using Zimbra internally.
Oh, yeah, I've come across it a couple of times.
I'm surprised it didn't take off.
I feel like it was a better exchange.
Yeah, it was designed to be exchange compatible
stroke compliant.
And it was one of these weird things.
It originally grew up out of, you know, Yahoo acquired it.
It got kicked around between, you know,
different organizations over the years,
but it was always very solid.
Yeah, I had some heavy hitting clients
that really used email and we ended up switching to Zimbra
for their archival and search solution
because they just simply couldn't find it in Outlook
when they were looking for stuff fast enough.
And Zimbra was just faster.
So that is a really good one,
but I think that's probably too much
because that's like the kitchen sink approach to email.
It's everything.
Yeah, it's all the things without a doubt, yeah.
That'd be a good, like,
if you were looking to replace Google apps,
you didn't just need core email,
but you needed like a whole suite of functionality,
including calendar and collaboration space.
Indeed, yeah.
You combine that with something like Mattermost
and you'd have a really good self-hostable
internal collaboration suite.
Those two things together would be pretty good.
So I guess we'll wait for the emails to come in.
We'll review our options and then next episode
we'll announce our decision on which way we went
and if it's up and running or not.
We'll see if we get it going.
I hope I haven't overcommitted us, Wes.
I may have oversold, but we're gonna get done.
Yeah, let's find out.
Hopefully at least we'll have some email.
We can get some tests and see how many, you know,
audience mails actually make it into the show.
Yeah, all right.
Well, before we go, I really,
I really got my arse kicked by a robe recently.
And so I thought I'd share that tale with you
because we're just about a year
into things getting serious.
We're not at the year mark of being independent,
but we're a year mark into the process beginning.
And, you know, I thought when I was envisioning one day,
back then, you know, this at this stage,
I was just fantasizing, thinking to myself,
you know, if I were to go independent again
and try to survive, especially during a pandemic,
I know that I'd have to do more than just sponsors.
And the membership program was part of that.
And so thank you everybody who has become a member
because that was a critical part in making it
to as far as we have at this stage.
And I figured advertising would be a critical part of that.
And it has, and that's why, you know,
companies like Linode coming on board,
literally, I'm not exaggerating at all
when I say I made it possible
for Jupiter Broadcasting to exist.
But I also knew that I couldn't just rely on those two things.
I've been doing this for 14 years
and that's like 50 years,
at least maybe 100 years in internet time.
And one of the things I know that's absolutely true
is if you have one or two income sources,
you're gonna die.
Because I've been around when YouTube pulled the plug
on advertising the first time around.
I've been around when Amazon,
which represented like 20% of our revenue at the time
or 30% of our revenue at the time.
I was there when Amazon just one day pulled the plug on us
for doing stuff that still other networks
and podcasts and YouTubers are still doing today.
It's really, you know, but you gotta diversify there.
So I knew when I was thinking about,
boy, do I wanna make this transition,
I knew I'd have to figure out
my merchandise and swag game one day.
And it's been just embarrassingly too long
since we've had anything new.
It's been over two years now.
And it's something that I enjoy
and it's something,
it's another one of those physical manifestations
of what we make becomes a physical product.
And we recently went on kind of like a archeological dig
here in the studio and we found a bunch of old swag.
And I had an emotional reaction to finding this stuff.
And I don't normally have an emotional reaction to things
except for Star Trek ships that those I like.
But mostly like, you know,
one of the reasons I moved into a class ARV
is I wanted to get rid of everything.
I don't really wanna have attachments.
I'm not big on that.
But when I saw this swag, I felt something.
I don't know what you humans call it, but I felt something.
And it was a good something.
And I realized this stuff is special.
We have some really special items.
And I wanna do more of that.
Because it's like, I can look back and I remember,
I see an item and I think of an event,
or I think of a show milestone,
or I think of the way that the audience responded
to an item that we did.
And it makes like the past real
in a way that I kind of lost touch with
over the last couple of years, especially the last year.
And also, getting this figured out
is just a good business strategy, really.
I mean, that's just obvious on its face.
It's critical to making a long-term business successful.
So all of this, knowing all of this,
it created this self-inflicted pressure.
Like I've been stressing out really bad to get swag right.
And I wanna do things that are unique and fun
that aren't just like the stuff you find
on every fulfillment website out there.
And so I thought, let's shoot for the moon
and let's do a fabulous embroidered robe called the Coder.
And it'll be a limited item.
It'd be a robe that we can sell on the Coder Radio program
to celebrate 400 episodes
because Coder Radio just hit that milestone as well.
What a glorious dream.
I mean, you know, a custom swag worthy
of the epic history of that show.
Yep.
Tyler's saying right now in the chat room,
he says, Chris, last I still have my challenge coins.
Right?
I mean, Tyler, I love the challenge coin.
It was the best.
I was just about to say,
I've been sorting out my office and listen to this.
Challenge coin?
Do challenge coins being struck together,
which I found from 2017 recently.
I just found a cache of them as well, about 20 of them.
And I love them.
They're very special.
And, you know, they're like limited in a way.
They're like, anyways,
it's just gave me a whole new appreciation for swag.
But so I wanted to do this robe
and the robe was the dumbest possible idea I could have had
in like a year, really.
The last year is probably my worst idea
in the last three years, maybe four years.
Now that I think about it,
it might be my worst idea in the last five years.
What I learned was that shipping a custom product
domestically is tricky to ship something that's produced,
custom hand produced domestically,
to ship that internationally, holy crap.
I had like quotes of like $185
just to ship a $65 robe to Denmark.
It's just basically not possible at a reasonable cost.
When you work with these one-off shops,
their business isn't procurement
and shipping around the world.
Their business is taking these items and doing embroidery.
And so they don't have like these depots around the world
to make shipping more reasonable at international rates.
And boy, do I have a whole new appreciation
for Amazon's cheap shipping.
What a massive market advantage that is for them, Wes.
They can ship stuff at prices I could never dream of.
No, I mean, we don't have a bulk discount.
We don't have established supply lines.
This is all new.
We gotta get that drone program up and going, obviously.
That I think we have the supplies for.
They have shipping prices that are just not even achievable
by small businesses like a shop like mine.
But for the community and for the business,
I figured I have to crack this nut.
And I figured the robe would be a learning experience.
I'd jump into the deep end and I'd learn a lot from it.
And I did learn a lot.
But one of the core lessons that I took away
is that theme of the day is be humble.
I have to start humble with something like this.
I went into the deep end with a robe
and that was such a bad idea.
If it's gonna be something that becomes part
of the business long-term, I need to start small
and then I have to grow it
and I have to learn as it grows.
I have to build on small success after small success.
So I've been thinking a lot about how to get this right.
Because I think swag and merchandise
is gonna be a fun part of the business.
It's gonna be something that we can,
we're gonna, I'm gonna, I wanna do limited stuff
like name brand stuff and items that you'd actually
wanna buy and just wear in general
or things and gadgets that you'd wanna pick up
or used items here at the studio that we're done with
that are still great, still fully functional
but we just need something maybe that has more ports
or does more channels, that kind of stuff.
I wanna have a business that can accommodate all of that.
So I'm a little nervous to do this
because I think this could be bad or this could be great
but I have an announcement to make today.
I am launching the Jupiter Broadcasting Garage sale
at JupiterGarage.com.
I am launching JupiterGarage.com today
at JupiterGarage.com, go check it out.
Let the fireworks go, go ahead, I know,
I know, it's exciting, I know, yeah.
I don't think you should be selling those to kids.
Yeah, no, I know but they do so good with the fire.
You know, they're responsible.
Oh, whoa, whoa, whoa, that got close.
So here's what I'm doing is I have a selection right now
of mostly used hardware items like a FreeNAS Mini,
a mixer, a compressor, you know,
gear that I think is really high-end and good
but we just don't simply use anymore
and instead of throwing it out,
I'm gonna sell it for really crazy,
stupid, ridiculous prices.
Really stupid, crazy low prices
just to clear out the space
because I wanna make room for the new.
For the new stuff that I wanna do,
the new swag items, the new merchandise,
the new stickers, getting ready for events to come back
and I wanna stock swag for booths and that kind of stuff.
And the way to do that is to get rid of this stuff
that I've been stockpiling forever.
And there's things in there that still work totally good
that are great items that I've always kept just in case
but I really shouldn't be, I'm just hoarding.
And I'm just kind of creating the garage experience,
the garage sale experience but online at jupitergarage.com
with the goal to make room for the new
and honestly, quite frankly with you guys,
total transparency here.
I just need practice boxing, shipping, the whole thing.
Like I gotta learn all of this and I need space.
I need space but here's what I'm gonna do.
So go to jupitergarage.com,
look at some of the items I have there.
If you're buying one of the used items,
as space and weight allows,
I'm gonna stash random retro swag items in those orders.
Like just as I can, I'm gonna just throw some stickers
in there or something like that
or I might wrap a device in a shirt or something like that.
Just sort of close your eyes
and grab something at the studio, put it in the box.
Throw it in the box.
As long as it's not Levi.
Right, no.
But you know what I figured too,
because I found a couple of caches of retro swag
and I'm not making any more of this stuff.
If you just want a random bag of retro swag,
I'm gonna make that available too.
They're going on sale right now.
They're gonna normally be $25 for a bag of swag
but right now, to kick off the new thing,
they're gonna be $15 and I only have
a small handful available.
I'm doing limited quantities
so that way I don't get inundated with orders
and I make sure we get them out the door
and that we're getting the shipping estimates right
and that if somebody orders international,
we can fulfill it and I'm literally learning
with each one of these orders.
So not only are you gonna make a very small
financial contribution to the network
and get yourself some gear or some swag
but you are basically sending me through bootcamp
to learn how to do this
and we're kind of accomplishing something together.
I'm clearing out some stuff here.
This gear that's still perfectly usable,
I'm pounding it on to make sure it works and stuff.
It's getting a new home and I'm learning
how to basically grow a new part of my business
that will be independent of sponsorships
or memberships or anything like that.
Although that said, with the memberships,
going forward, right now these prices are stupid.
Like you wouldn't believe what I'm charging
for a free NAS Mini.
There's no discounts because the prices,
they are ridiculous but going forward in the future,
I will make a standard discount available
for all of our members.
So if you're an unplugged core contributor,
you're gonna get 15% off every order
and you'll have more information about that soon.
That's true for all of our patrons
and for members of any show of ours.
You're gonna get 15% off any of your orders
from the Jupiter Garage in the future.
Right now, as I'm learning how to do this
and I'm probably gonna be on the other end of profit,
I'm gonna be paying out of pocket
for some of this stuff as I learn it.
I just can't do a discount
because there's no discount to give
but there will be one in the future for all of our members
because my intention long-term will be
to clear out some of this limited time swag that we have
to get some hardware out there.
There's a lot more hardware than what's on there right now
so there's gonna be more stuff landing.
And then kind of transition to create an inventory space
for new original high quality merchandise,
stuff that isn't just the standard fulfillment T-shirt
or something like that.
I mean, I will still do those from time to time
because who doesn't like a T-shirt?
And there is a T-shirt with the bearded tux
holding the Jupiter rocket in a nice kind of low key
gray and white on black.
That's available in the garage sale right now
as well as a hat that has the same bearded tux logo on it
because that's my favorite tux.
So there are a couple of those items
that I'll do from time to time but my goal is
I'm eventually gonna have an entire wardrobe of this stuff
because I wanna get stuff that I wanna wear
and when I start rolling that stuff out,
we'll start doing discounts for members more on the regular.
And that's gonna be more as my confidence grows
as I know what I'm doing and I know I can tell somebody
that you're gonna pay this for international shipping
or you're gonna pay this if you live in California,
you're gonna pay this if you live in Canada.
When I get to that point and we're actually getting there,
then you'll start seeing more stuff roll out.
That's just sort of as I learn more.
I'm gonna take it one small part at a time
but there's always gonna be that core part
of the Jupiter garage that will be items from the studio
that we're done with, stuff that is still functional
and we don't buy crap.
So stuff that's good and functional
but we're just done with it, we've outgrown it.
That's gonna be always a part of the Jupiter garage
and my intention there is just sell it,
not really at much of a profit,
maybe just make 20 bucks or something off of it really
and let you have something that we're done with
instead of letting it sit and rot
like it does now in a closet or in the garage.
Plus we gotta make room for beer.
Yeah Wes, that is actually part of this.
When we decided well we're gonna have a beer keg
and we're gonna have a beer keg fridge
and we're gonna have a spot to brew beer,
we gotta have room.
And we retire stuff from time to time
that's still perfectly good.
It doesn't make any sense that it just sits around in waste.
Could go out to an audience member,
they could help support the network a little bit.
Yeah, who wouldn't wanna connect to the mumble room
with a previously used Jupiter broadcasting audio gear,
right, I mean come on.
That's pretty much it.
So there's a selection of stuff there.
There will be more from time to time.
Go to JupiterGarage.com to go see what's there now.
And we have gone through our closets.
Angela just found a huge stash of stickers
that will be slipping into rando swag bags
and orders that people place.
And I found a stash of last challenge coins.
And then independently there's some really nice
retro last swag like the zip up hoodies
with the classic bearded logo and stuff like that
that will be going up for sale soon too.
As we just kind of go through
and make sure everything that's been in storage
is still in good shape.
And then we're gonna box it up and get shipping prices
that make it available at the garage sale.
That's the plan.
And then over time I hope to grow that
into kind of an arm of the business
that will be part of sponsorships, memberships,
and swag that is swag like nobody else is doing.
It's not just boring stuff, but it's stuff
that you could eventually end up buying.
One of the things that's on there right now
is the mixer I used for years of remote productions.
And it's perfectly good.
And it's got, I tell you what I love about it too.
Like it's got, you can run it all off nine volt batteries.
So if you have noisy audio, if you have line noise
on your electrics and you want a mixer
that's battery powered, this is like the total ultimate hack
to avoiding line noise is run a battery powered mixer.
And I used it for years on the road.
It's still perfectly functional.
I just now do all that stuff in Jack
and don't need a mixer anymore, but it still works.
And it's up on the garage sale.
I'm very excited about it as you can probably tell.
And I've been going on and on about it for weeks to Wes.
Just a bit.
So thanks for putting up with it, Wes.
I appreciate it.
There really is a lot of good gear that's been in there.
And especially as the setup all pivoted
to like Linux focus to more professional stuff
or just more channels we needed to set up
the studio right to have guests
and get all the crazy Jack stuff going on.
There's just a lot of good gear
and other awesome items from history that, as you said,
it really would be a shame to just see them
rot away on the shelves when we're not using them.
Yeah, grab a bit of JB history
and stuff that you could use to make content
or run right now and the chat room's right.
I need to update the website with links and stuff.
I just been getting it all going today
and wanted to have it ready for the show,
but I am often just the worst at that.
I really need, the whole JB website needs a refresh
because my intention was to have it replaced by now,
but that never came around.
And now it needs a refresh.
And links to stuff like this need to happen.
So hopefully that'll get done soon.
But in the meantime, just go to jupytergarage.com for that.
Well, Wes, that is the no-show.
That's the unplanned show that we had today.
It's almost a show.
It was kind of a show, I think, actually.
I think we just accidentally had a show.
Whoopsie.
I know.
If anything we covered today interests you,
then go check us out at linuxunplugged.com
and get the links at linuxunplugged.com slash 401.
You heard really briefly there from the orange one.
He was just recently featured in the self-hosted podcast
with his setup.
You can find that at selfhosted.show.
Hosting things like your own email server
is the core of what we talk about there.
So if you like that, go check that out.
If you do the Twitter thing,
you can follow this here podcast at Linux Unplugged.
The network is at Jupyter Signal.
And the whole gosh darn podcasting network
is over there at Jupyterbroadcasting.com.
And last but not least, may I just say,
hmm, if I don't say so myself,
picture me like a chicken who's like, you know,
fluffing up his feathers right now
and like getting braggadocious, but-
I'm also picturing high-waisted pants for some reason.
Yeah, and maybe some glasses.
But gosh darn it,
if I'm not just getting more and more proud
of that Linux action news over there,
if you work in the industry, don't miss Linux action news.
Every Monday morning, Wes and I break down
everything that matters in the world of Linux.
And something you don't know by listening to the show,
but something I want to tell you is,
Wes and I put a lot of effort and thought into
how can we say something concisely, efficiently,
and so that it's easy to understand.
And we try to get you all of the news you need to know
in less than 30 minutes.
And we pride ourselves on delivery in a way
that is understandable, processable,
with the context that you need, that doesn't drag on.
And so there's a lot of stuff
that doesn't make it into this show,
otherwise this would be like a two-hour show.
And those stories and that information,
like the recent ports to the M1 platform,
we went and got quotes from Hector Martin.
We reached out to Hector Martin for contact
and we bring that into the show.
And that's another thing we do with Linux action news,
is the stories are sourced.
We try to contact the people behind the stories,
the people writing the stories.
We try to get their takes and that information.
We incorporate that into the show,
either by what we say,
or sometimes we'll play the audio directly from them.
And that's a special kind of effort
that we spend the last half of our week doing
to make Linux action news special
and to have information that perhaps you're not hearing
or reading in other places.
Yeah, save yourself the time.
Stop clicking through the clickbait in our Linux.
Just head over to linuxactionnews.com.
That's good, Wes.
That is a, that's good.
Well, this year podcast, it's gonna be live next week.
Even when we say it's not gonna be live,
sometimes it's live.
See you next week.
Same bat time, same bat station.
So keep the Linux rolling and make it a Linux Tuesday.
Join us live, 12 p.m. Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern.
Links to everything we talked about today,
how to contact us, our mumble server, our matrix info,
that's all over there,
including subscribe links for RSS feeds, et cetera,
at linuxunplugged.com and get all of it over there.
Go get your links, go get your show notes,
and then go check out the garage sale at jupytergarage.com.
It's brand new, and I'm going to school,
and you can help teach me a lesson or two.
Thanks so much for tuning into this week's episode
of the Unplugged program,
and we'll see you right back here next Tuesday!
JBtitles.com, let's go name this thing.
Did you guys see that the GNOME project
is considering moving the top bar to the bottom
and creating kind of a layout similar to Chrome OS?
Yeah.
What?
I really hope not.
Really?
It reminds me too much of Windows
and then also obviously Chrome.
It's like that normally sort of looks unique right now.
I think that's precisely why they're considering doing it,
because it looks like Windows.
Back end of last year,
I think it was probably around October, November time,
the GNOME Foundation had like a show and tell
based on some user accessibility testing
that they'd commissioned.
So this was putting GNOME and other operating systems
in front of a random selection of people
or a selection of people with different backgrounds
and different computing backgrounds and what have you.
And it was GNOME as it was,
what was slated to be at the time GNOME 40
and also including stuff like the endless OS spin
on how the GNOME desktop is presented.
And long story short,
those people that are not already familiar with GNOME
gravitated towards the intuitive nature of using endless OS
because it had a lot of similarity with Windows,
which is what they knew.
This is a point that I had a conversation with Neil McGovern,
you know, the executive director.
Yes, exactly.
And he said, yeah,
that when people use more traditional UI paradigms,
they got to work faster basically.
Yeah.
You know, those traditional patterns didn't come out of nowhere.
You know, they're through long established design research
and human interaction research.
So it was no mistake that GNOME looked a lot like Windows 95
and Windows 95 had shared some familiar patterns with Mac OS.
All of those were influenced by the same design research
and design thinking.
Which shared some design patterns honestly with Xerox.
I mean, really.
Indeed.
I mean, it does go back a long way.
It goes back to the 1960s.
But this is, you know, well-researched,
well-funded research that goes back a long way.
So I am not surprised to learn that GNOME are taking that
feedback on board and looking to,
I'm not going to say roll back necessarily, but you know,
there is some sort of stepping away from the path they've been
on to responding to user feedback.
And user feedback is what people are familiar with is comfortable
and intuitive.
Yeah.
I wonder how, I mean, I'm pretty flexible.
I could probably roll with whatever.
But it would be a change, you know, there's forever, I mean,
with GNOME, I've always had a lot of my items up in a top bar
in one way or another.
It'd be a pretty significant shift for them.
Yeah, but what about that mouse travel though?
That's the part I've seen people kind of talking about the most
I think.
Yeah.
I just use the keyboard for everything.
Yeah, exactly.
Nobody knows which buttons to push now.
So Wimpy, the Ubuntu podcast is back.
It's active.
What else is going on?
How are you?
I'm very well.
I hear that everyone else is very well too.
Yeah.
You know, he didn't stop by the show today, but a friend of the
show, Popeye has recently left Canonical as well.
So both of you now have left the Canonical mothership, but I
assume for greener pastures.
Yeah.
Obviously, I have been at Slim now for like five weeks.
I think I've been working there.
So I'm doing my thing.
Don't think Popeye's left Canonical yet.
He's announced that he will be leaving.
A bit like I did, I announced my plans to leave ahead of time to
give people in the community who may have wanted some final stuff,
you know, from me, time to contact me and round that out and Popeye's
done the same.
So, yeah, Popeye's off to something new.
I'm not going to disclose what that is.
He'll do that, you know, when the time is right for him.
But yeah.
Well, Popeye, if you're out there listening, you are welcome to join
us when your last day arrives and you want to come and hang out with
your buddies.
What I will say is this.
Some people have reacted to, you know, there are some people that
maybe only know about Alan and I and our association with Ubuntu and
Canonical and the fact that we've both left recently.
They see as the sky is falling.
That's not the case.
And perhaps, you know, the silver lining to this is maybe the two of us,
you know, old and grizzled, you know, people from, you know, Ubuntu
leaving is a good thing because there is, you know, a vibrant new life
at Canonical who are spearheading community engagement now with, you
know, Monica and Reese.
And this is their opportunity to take things in new and interesting
directions.
So I don't think people should be interpreting this as, you know, a
negative thing.
But the opportunity for a new era of, you know, Ubuntu community to
shine and blossom.
I like it.
And I hope so, too.