How
How much of your Bitcoin stash have you still got left Chris or have you exhausted it yet?
I haven't exhausted it yet, but I am starting to get more picky about how I spend it. Yeah, I've
I've
Depleted mine by about eight and change Bitcoin this last week. Oh, what did you oh really and and and I worry
See, I've been watching the price. In fact at this very moment. It's at six hundred and twelve dollars and eighty-one cents
U.s. Not that I'm following not that you're not that I'm multiple tickers on your desk
But why why would you do you want to share the class with the transaction was because that sounds like a big chunk of Bitcoin
I mean, I gotta look that up. But let's see eight
Bitcoin can you can Google do this eight Bitcoin in USD? Is that five grand?
Yeah, it doesn't doesn't do it when you type it in but I wonder if I could ask Google 8 BTC is you basically five
Grand. Yeah. Yeah. Yep, just about yeah
Wow
That's some buying power and that is I
Have been tempted to cash mine in for a very large laptop recently. I've been thinking more about doing production on the road
Oh, that'd be cool. Yeah. Yeah. Well, this is this is how much is that Acer 21? Just curious
I don't know what the price is. I don't know if they even have a price yet. It's probably not out
Yeah, they probably don't have an announced MSRP. So is it is it a was it a laptop wimpy?
two laptops Oh
Wow, you were all of a sudden the in them in the hardware
Yeah, yeah
So I I haven't had much hardware for a long time and then this year um has been a blowout year for new hard
Yeah, sort of a restocking. Yeah, I've been selling stuff as I've been going along. Oh good. Yeah
Yeah, I've got the I
Haven't got it yet. It should arrive tomorrow. Hopefully the
The top of the line Dell XPS 15. Oh, that's nice
Yeah, and also the Dell XPS 13 developer edition. Are those both sky-like or both sky-like? Yeah
Mm-hmm. That'll be interesting. He's gonna be development machines
Yes. Yes one one
for mobile stuff and
And one for around the house sort of
dev work and
To and from family and stuff like that
But I really wanted something with them 4k screens and touch to to experiment with so
So yeah
Congrats about accessories as well. So that'll be interesting. Were you able to take advantage of Dell direct using Bitcoin?
No, I went through
some local companies that are part of the Dell outlet program
Interesting. Yeah
Whoo, that'll be really cool. But great. It'd be great to hear your thoughts on them
The I know for me
I one of the reasons I pulled the trigger on the XPS 13 was that high DPI display because that that was a game-changer
For how I do my reviews, right?
Wow, I think I waited too long even mm-hmm, but maybe I don't know it kind of depends Linux is also kind of dragging its feet
So you you got yours last year. Is that right? Mm-hmm
Yeah, yeah. Okay. I couldn't remember if it was last year's all the years but it blended to one now
And you got a windowsy version that you adapted with the adapted as a polite word
Yeah, I pulled out the wireless and I put an Intel card in and then I installed Linux. Yeah, it's interesting actually reading reading because um
There's been lots of firmware updates for these devices
Which you sort of have to apply and some of them you can only apply through Windows. So
Bust out the trial versions of Windows 10 in order to update all the drivers. That's a matches and firmware. Yeah, I know
The BIOS you can do but it's like the Thunderbolt firmware and touchscreen firmware. You can't do outside of Windows
But it's interesting how many people that are running Windows actually say swap out the Broadcom
For an Intel adapter because it yeah. Yeah, that was much simpler when I did that
Yeah, yeah, but but it's not for compatibility with drivers
It's just the Intel stuff works better than the rural cum stuff or at least it did then when it was sort of new
I think it's all been resolved now, but yeah, it's interesting to see some of the parallels between the two communities
Yeah, it's funny because I I really really like my expert
Yeah, XPS 13 is as turt as far as far as size and right portability goes but
Man having now now having worked on some desktops some newer refreshed desktops again
I really feel like the there is some serious advantage to a large machine
I can maybe I could maybe have a much more portable workload where I could do more work
We're usually less limited by things. You don't have to think about it. Mm-hmm
Mm-hmm your manual example, you know, you have a lot going on at once. Yeah, and so
I would there is so to buy that laptop in Bitcoin. Did you have to convert it first or were you able?
How did that so I'm wondering if like you were able to avoid like brexit induced
economic depression like type conditions
I can't tell you how how valueless our currencies
And that's why Bitcoin could look even more attractive at this moment. Yeah. Yeah, so for both transactions
I was able to keep it purely through Bitcoin which was a key part in actually being able to do it. Yeah. Mm-hmm
Mm-hmm. Yeah, yeah
I wonder
but for anyone for anyone listening in this part of the world specifically in the UK and you're interested in Bitcoin and you need an
exchange that is reliable and works
there is an exchange called coin corner and
You can move your money in and out of a Bitcoin wallet
No problem whatsoever and cash out no issues pay in it's really really simple works very well
So they're a semi offshore. They're in the Isle of Man, which is sort of a tax haven
and
Independently governed so a good place to put your Bitcoin
This is Linux Unplugged episode 161 for September 6th, 2016
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's not all that interested in tomorrow's Apple event
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello, Wes
I'm glad you're here today because apparently Linux doesn't take Labor Day off. Nope. We have a lot to cover
In fact, the show this week is packed full of updates from some of our favorite open source projects all over the net
Including a little suspense
Including a little distro review. Oh and even some Waylon love it is a classic episode of the unplugged program
So super excited to be here. We're back from Labor Day. You didn't miss a beat Wes
You are on top of with tons of links this week
So we're gonna go through all of those so brace yourselves mentally and let's bring in that mumble room time appropriate greetings virtual lug
Hey, oh
Hello guys, so Wes is over here rapidly tap tap typing away on his computer where he has once a gun
Trying out another distro for us to discuss here on the unplugged show. So that'll be coming up in a little bit
I'll give you a hint. It might be the best KD desktop ever. It just might but you have to stay tuned
Yeah, we then might not it might not
You never you never really know, but why don't we start out since I just hinted with a little KD news
Or a little KD review. How about we start with a little KD news?
Speaking of Waylon speaking of KD. I just threw them all together in a sandwich and that is our
first update this week the KD neon developers are switching to
Wayland
by default
Yeah
Yeah, you're ready for this now you guys remember neon that's the more a cutting-edge version of the KD desktop that sets a top
of Ubuntu
Now they're gonna start moving forward for their developer unstable packages to use Wayland by default now
There's gonna be some conditions here. There still has to be some work done on X X Wayland
Plasma 5 8 is required
There's some other upstream updates that have to be made and also if you're on Nvidia, you're still gonna be using X
It's gonna default you back to X, right?
But the Wayland is getting nice
So we have this we have this story here from the KD neon project and then here's another story for door 25
Technical technical advisory board for Fedora has given the thumbs up for Fedora 25 to ship Wayland by default if they want wow
Now the developers could still choose not to just like they did for 24 because they got the same approval for Fedora 24 and they
Decided to punt it
But it's been given the go by the FS CEO as we all like to call it around here
Which stands for fedora engineering and steering committee? I guess of course yeah, obviously
so they gave it the green light they say they agree to go with Wayland by default and
They'll make it clear how to switch back to x11 in the release notes if needed that was part of their requirements by the technical
board
Fedora 25 will be using gnome 3.22 by
Default and it's currently scheduled home to ship on
November 8th assuming there were no delays there will be never delays never delays, so let's take a moment Wes and
Envision a future where fedora 25 actually ships
With Waylon, let's just pretend like this actually happens
All of like the major major major issues are fixed
What's the first benefit you're looking forward to when you can boot up one day and Wayland is by default
It's turned on ready to go. You're no longer using X
What what what that day changes?
I'm gonna be able to watch a show a YouTube video to one of my co-workers without being embarrassed by the screen tearing yes
That's it for me. Yeah, in fact one of Wayland's taglines has always been every
Frame is perfect right that would be huge
Yeah, the famed like control it you know if I'm using MPV or something else where I can really and where it knows
What's what it's doing?
I don't really have that big like day-to-day watching problems
But there's just always those videos or it's coming from an old flash client or something. It's just
My computer is powerful enough. I have the GPU for it. It just looks like crap
Yeah, that was gonna be my pick too does anybody else in the mumble room have a big like this is why I'm waiting for
Wayland because you gotta ask yourself. What's all the excitement about it's gonna be a huge change things are gonna undoubtedly break
Is there is there something on the other end of this transition that you're looking forward to for me?
It's definitely the screen tearing thing
I wonder if you know if anybody else in the mumble has any go ahead and jump in I was just reading there's a thread
On on the fedora subreddit that talks about it
They also you know this is a good one to multiple monitors with different DPI
So you can have a high DPI monitor and a low DPI monitor and have a multi monitor set up that's like
That's it's kind of embarrassing actually on Linux if you have a high DPI laptop with a with an internal screen
It's high DPI, and you hook up an external monitor the external monitor
Is is that as it is at a much lower resolution than you would like it's it's really kind of you know
It's even more embarrassing what what?
Microsoft Office failed you high DPI on a single monitor on Windows
That's embarrassing. Well. Yeah, I mean the wind yeah, the Windows platform is not there's no excuse for that
I know Microsoft's part office should work perfectly on Windows with high DPI. Yeah. Yeah, that is but yeah, I
All right besides the besides OS 10 everyone has their problems there. I think
Guys, I got a crack one open before we get into this next story because this is not the headline
I expected to ever read on this show
Adobe is updating the flash player using the Netscape plug-in API
New version of flash is coming everybody
well
And I was trying to think about this why why would they why would they do this William?
Do you have any guesses why Adobe would do this I?
Mean besides Firefox support. I don't know does Firefox have any like workaround for dealing with that if they didn't do NPAPI
Well, I guess Firefox could probably adopt them the PPAPI if they wanted to which
Well Chrome and chromium are using the PPAPI already yeah, so it was opera yeah
So here's a couple other things. They're just noteworthy. This is a really odd like
understated
They don't make a big deal about the fact that they're totally reversing the position that they made in 2012
This is really odd, but one of the things they do mention is
Because this change is primarily a security initiative some features like GPU 3d acceleration and premium video DRM
Will not be fully implemented
Hmm. Mm-hmm. I wonder what their angle
What this has to pressure for there has to be so there has to be some sort of contract or or some sort of agreement
I mean so one of the things that Adobe had done is they said they were gonna stop updating in
2017 for security purposes, maybe this is just an easier way to do security updates
Possibly because that's what they're focusing on, but I almost wonder if there was some sort of vendor
Product that shipped using Linux and there was there was a contract in place
Oh, maybe and Adobe's like well if we have to do this work anyways
Yeah, I'll ship because I don't think Mozilla has any interest in keeping it around
Here's what it's got to be someone else using it. This is what grinds my gears though
If these bastards at Adobe
we're gonna spend all of this time and all of this back and forth and all of this rigmarole on getting flash on Linux and
supporting an old Netscape plug-in API and back porting features from their Windows and Mac version in the Linux version to make it stable and
Secure again, which can't be a small task
They were like, why is this what they choose to spend their time and resources on right?
Why aren't they doing Photoshop or Premiere ports or after effects like spend your time and energy there you jerks
Not on the flash thing let flash die. Maybe it was easy enough. It was just oh, all right
We'll kick the cron back on and they'll build that for him and upload it to their web server
Ah, so yeah, that is that was a story that caught my attention this week and I just you know facepalm
Well, I'm glad in some respects. I'm glad we're getting security updates for flash
I mean it is better to have them to have not I just hope it doesn't like
Grant some legitimacy to people still using flash or not without a migration. Oh, I think it does
Yeah
I think it does and I think part of that is because the industry hasn't fully replaced the functionality that flash offers still feels
Like one or two years away. Mm-hmm. That's just crazy. You know, it also is an
Interesting little read that I think you caught this is from somebody named Carl
And he's a software engineer and he likes to be considered an aspiring artist
Oh, and he ran into a little extended for bug that I thought I'd just share with the class because it's particularly interesting
He said after buying and setting up a shiny new four terabyte hard drive
I began filling it slowly with files from various old hard drives. I have we've all done this. Yep been there
I have he says and I so I went through I found like an old website I had when I worked in high school and decided
Why the heck not why was so much space should I not just keep track of all of this?
It's gonna be easy. So I started copying the files over and I started getting a strange no space left on device air
He says hmm. This is odd
I have this huge hard drive and I'm just trying to move over an 18 gigabyte website directory
He says as it turns out I ran into a bug with extended for that causes it to fail if there are more than
32,000 files in a directory
so he goes on to say by the way really what you should probably do is do a little bit better file management and not
Have so many files in the root of a directory
But I guess that you know, I I toss that in there mostly as a PSA
This is probably not something most of us think about but I think the real lesson here was
Do better file organization plan to have your files stored in a hierarchy from the get-go
Don't have flat folders with file explorers that just when they when you open it up
They just totally die because they can't read all the files
William do you have a sense of what this particular bug is? Oh
It's kind of a built-in limit, I don't think it's really a bug
He just hit a limit at a limit of ext4
No, just has a limit of storing 32,000 entries in the inode will be you had experience with this
It's it's not a limit. It's a bug
So really? Yeah, so I got hit by precisely this issue about
Four or six weeks ago at work and we figured out the problem and fixed it. So very quickly
In the transition from ext3 to ext4. Yeah, I knew
hashing algorithm was added to hash all of the files in a directory in order to accelerate the lookups and
Theoretically that hash should be good for a massive number of files in a directory
But in reality, there's a limitation in the implementation
It is a bug that means you start to get hash collisions after about
50,000 files or or you can start to get hash collisions after about 50,000 files
And we were backing up a large directory a single directory that was full of files millions of files
And the issue was is that the actual server was running ext3
The backup server was running ext4 and our backups were failing
Because we were running into this hash collision and and if you look into the kernel messages, it says dir index
Out of range or full or something like that
So our solution was to change the backup server from ext4 to X
And all of our problems went away
One of the favorite and file systems here on the show everybody thinks that we're on the ZFS payroll
I've been accused of yeah being but if anything it'd be the XFS camp
Which who even who even is the main was SGI back in the day?
Wasn't it? That's it? Yeah, I don't know. I think it still is SGI engineers. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Wow
Thank you ships us by default, right?
Yeah, I think so what extended for I
Have the full you know, I will put the full link to the post in the in the show notes
Between a rock and a crazy place. It says Wimby while we have your ear
I wanted to do a follow-up from our discussion last week about installing Ubuntu touch on the Meizu Pro 5
because you came across like a pretty solid piece of
Instruction like it's a PDF that kind of has everything you need
Yeah, a couple of guys in the Ubuntu community have basically pulled together all of the information that I you know
I sort of read they've pulled it together into one PDF document with links to all of the
Files and utilities that you need so you can start at step one and work your way through and at the end of it
You have Ubuntu running on a Meizu Pro 5. So it's a PDF and I've got it linked in the show notes
How has your experience been going now another week into it?
Yep, very good still works. No issues discovered still finding my way with you know, the
touch experience and
Updating some of my own apps and still finding new apps along the way
So I'm good and working working out what I'm gonna do to sort of help improve things. Oh cool
So how does the podcast playback situation? Is that is podcast player Bluetooth audio? Is that still rough? Hmm? Yeah, so
I could use it. I can use a headphone jack. I'm not an animal. I'm sure I'm sure that every Ubuntu touch device
We'll have headphone jacks for a long time
Yeah, so if you use a headphone jack, that's just fine and I've updated my so I say I've updated my
There's a guy who was maintaining a pocket casts web app. I've published my own pocket casts web app
Which is a little bit more updated and we'll keep
Will not interrupt the playback of the podcasts for example and things like that
So I'm using that for local playback because I can just you know resume
It's got you know staked between all of my other pocket cast setups
But I desperately need to actually write up a number of sort of feature requests and
Enhancement ideas for pod bird because what I'd like to do is actually move to the native pod bird player which can play
Podcasts just fine. It's if you if you listen to a lot of podcasts
You know what the rough edges are in terms of the user interface and and and using it navigating around and that's sort of
Stopping me from adopting it that and the fact that Bluetooth in the car doesn't work at all
Yeah, disappointing but that'll come I think and
Yeah, there's there's bugs for it and I've I've added my information to the to the bug tracker on that one
So there are people that are aware of it. It seems to have a high priority
It sounds like there's a couple of different options for playback of podcasts. So that's nice. I
Was pretty close to trying it out on my Nexus 5
I got the process started, but I didn't have time to let the Bantu flash tool finish going
Oh, that's gonna happen again when I have a little more time dedicated to it. It would have been really cool
That's I was trying to get the multi boot image to work, but no luck
That's the way to do it too. So that way if you really had to you could still go back to Android, right?
I see that's like to all booting with Windows though. You know, it is risky. Yeah, it is. Yeah
It's I think you've used this analogy before it's like a recovering alcoholic, you know, if you leave
You leave a a bottle of beer out on the on the desk somewhere and you can see it
You'll be tempted to drink it right the first time things get really hard
I'm just rebooting for Netflix. That's fine. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, it starts with the Netflix
No, it does
So yeah remove all of those temptations
I've I've actually reset my my Android phone, which is still doing pocket casts, but it's just all it's got is pocket casts
I haven't set up any of the eyes on it. So that's a good way. I kind of mean and I've also you know
moved all of the
Two factor authentication stuff onto the Ubuntu phone, you know, because that's kind of when you do that you there's no going back
It's like right. This is my device. Now. This is the one I'm using
Interesting I'm following wimpy I'm following this because you know, I'm looking at I'm looking at the Nexus 6 something and one of these days
Android one of these right?
Speaking of mobile. Let's stop for a second and mention our first sponsor this week
And that would be the folks over at ting
What a fitting moment to talk about ting because that's exactly where I'll be taking my Ubuntu touch device
I do know folks that have run Ubuntu touch devices on ting for like
I
Think it was a two-week period
To run a boot to touch but then I actually ended up on the Nexus 5 finding sailfish OS to work a little better for me
Ting does not mind any of the ting is really great. It's super simple wireless
they they have CDMA and GSM service, which is wonderful because you can pick whichever works better in your area and
You can get a great discount if you go to the linux.ting.com
You support the show you get a discount off your first device or if you have a compatible device that works on their GSM or CDMA
Networks then you'll get $25 in service credit ting just charges for what you use
$6 for the line and then your usage on top of that. They got real human beings that actually help
They're geeks themselves and they actually help which is sort of an amazing thing to be able to say about a company
They have a whole range of devices from exceptionally well-priced phones up to the really crazy high-end expensive ones
The ones the ones that we all drool over they've got great tools to manage your account
one of the things I really like about ting is
They don't really have any agenda other than just offering you a simple wireless service
So they the way they've set it up here is you can use ting as only a phone provider
You could use ting as only data
You could never text if you use something like telegram and never pay for text message or just only text
Maybe you love texting well
And I do know a couple of people who I've mentioned before that have the SIM cards in
Little devices that are connected to their alarm systems
Oh, yeah, and they text them when there's movement or things like that and it can just be the simplest thing and that's all they
Use it for and they get what five text messages a month. That is cheap. Yeah, it's so cool
Go to linux.ting.com to check them out
Also, you don't even have to be a ting customer taking advantage of some of the cool stuff on their blog. They've been doing unboxing giveaways
Usually it's like a matter of leave a comment on Facebook
Subscribe to the YouTube channel leave a comment and you're entered to join to get a potentially free phone, which is really cool
But they've also been covering all the different types of cord cutter problems that you might run into
So if you're a cord cutter and you want to get sports or you want to get news or you want to get the CW shows
They've been doing a series of blog posts on that and that's not really specific to being a ting customer
they're just geeks and this is the kind of stuff they're into and you might
You might just want to go there to check them out and just learn more about like in
In a piece down here where they talk about football
And they do a they do a little mini review of the sling TV service which I use to watch a food network and history
Channel and live news at home where we don't have any TV service
It's pretty cool, and they do a review in there
And it's really applicable to anybody that might want something like that
So it's kind of a nice to go over there
You can you can learn more and you can before you hit their blog you can support the show by going to linux.ting.com
And then jump around and learn more about ting try out their savings calculator read their blog
See how cool those people are linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program
That's linux.ting.com to support the show
Well, mr. West I can't believe that Adobe story like that's still right
That's still like rattling around the back. We were beyond this as a community
And you know what else I thought we were beyond is this trying to trying to get a government approved backdoor into encryption
And I think this is gonna be a major problem if this goes forward for open source software
This is something that we briefly touched on in the roundup in tech snap last week the
FBI director James commie is
Positioning for a
reopening quote-unquote of the
Quote encryption debate because right now it's dipped below public consciousness. He says and he thinks in next year
He's gonna wait to 2017 because next year. We can have a quote adult conversation in this country about it
You want to install backdoor encryption and that would it would be a it would be a regulatory thing
So that would mean if you're shipping software that uses a type of encryption in the US in order for it to be legal here
You would have to follow these rules potentially and that seems like you could have huge consequences
Question what?
And this has got a bit of conspiracy bacon here, but why is commie?
Wanting to wait. Why not do this debate right now? Is there?
Something else that's more important than that
Well, I think he I think he gives away his motivation when he says next year
We can have an adult conversation in other words once we're past the election year because everything in an election year gets crazy
Let's have a let's have a conversation right now about it
You know, well, I think that's what I'd be saying
I think I think the technology community is simply of the opinion. This is just a bad idea for all kinds of reasons
We've been at there's no such thing as just a government backdoor
There's back doors that can be taken advantage of but just for so frustrating because it feels like
It's like they're not listening on the other side, you know, you're like, well, okay
We can have this conversation to have you have you answered our other big point that we kind of have been asking you about
Well, I guess what I'm worried about is
What we're not talking about what we're not talking about is the impact this will have on the legality of open-source software
The impact this will have on the adoption of open-source software in companies that have government contracts or government agencies themselves and divisions
if all of a sudden things like Tor and I don't know what a name a Lib Lib vault or Libre vault or you'll sink thing or all of these things all of a sudden have to have back doors built into them
Well, there's gonna be a huge portion of these software developers gonna say no, I won't do that right plus now now
The technical the technical aspect of how that gets implemented. Is that gonna be GPL code? Like how does that exactly work?
Yeah, it can't be like some sort of proprietary thing that gets bolted onto these GPL projects. So
How the hell does open-source exist if this ever becomes a reality and here's why I worry about it is because they do not let up
Every single terrorist attack. Oh, yeah, it's encryption going dark. They're using that evil telegram
They're creating their own encrypted applications for communications cybercalifate blah blah blah
and then there's a and then anytime there's an attack the encryption is once again the conversations brought up and it does kind of worry me and
the other thing is is that
It's not just commie. In fact, I think one of the reasons why James commie is having so much luck with pushing this conversation
Amongst legislators and whatnot in the US is our counterparts over the European Union have expressed similar initiatives last month
The French and German interior ministers called on the EU to implement measures forcing encrypted app manufacturers to develop back doors
for use by law enforcement officials
Would effectively make end-to-end encryption where only the center and the recipient have access to transmitted data illegal in Europe
Yeah, isn't that that seems wild?
It's happening on both ends of the pond right now. They come in for my full disk encryption too. Yeah. Yes. Absolutely. That's terrifying
Mm-hmm. Yeah, and I don't it does feel like open source isn't hardly considered because it's like yeah
Well the government can strong arm that you know come you can get your Microsoft's and your Apple's and your Google's to do this
But how you gonna get the Libra vault developer who lives in Russia to do it? Yeah, exactly
And you can't I mean are you just gonna have more laws that we just?
Pretend and look the other way when you acknowledge that you're not really gonna be able to stop your citizens from using it and then you
Just turn them into criminals is open source software that doesn't have these
Mandated backdoors become illegal. Do you is it does it become a crime to use types of software like that for communication?
I don't know. Where does this end? And that's why it's kind of got me worried because in particular
We are having we are having the conversation and people like Bruce and I and other loud voices in this debate are are
Coming out strongly against this concept
But the but there's nobody advocating it from the open source perspective of how this could and if you at this point
Damaged open source in a certain like to this degree would probably have a negative impact on the economy. Mm-hmm
Seems pretty maybe we maybe we can be you know those
Advocates in that or at least the starting forces, you know, I think you give us too much credit
Damn it we can try let's let's go back to something that's more in our realm because yeah
There's only so much shouting of the wind we can do on that particular issue, but the issue has been raised
I thought this is pretty cool
KTE software is coming. Oh, that's right
It's gonna be a store soon to offer downloads in snaps flat packs and app image formats. Wow
Yeah
Dub the Katie each store the new software store is exactly that a store where application developers can publish their own open source projects and
Share them with the world also known as the Katie software store
The migration from the open desktop to our services to the new Katie software store has happened in the background
It's been going on for a while now and a Katie developer blogged about the new software store on his personal blog revealing the fact that
Users might be able to soon download their favorite open source applications in the new snap and flat pack and app image binary formats
Which was which is pretty damn cool and it's it's nice because we've seen the gnome software center
Sort of get pretty wide adoption on the GTK side of things
There's
Not a great answer for the KTE plasma desktop side of things. There's some different solutions like the muon software center and things like that
But one like KTE quote-unquote. Yes official store is great and I I remember
Talking to Aaron years ago about some of the back-end ideas I had for this which were pretty bright
So I think it could be it's been stuff's been in the works and hopefully this is a good
Good push through and people can use it anybody the mumble room have any thoughts about the new KTE software store
And again when they say store, I bet you almost everything there's yeah gonna be free. It's a weird model for open-source
Why say store? Is that just because of what they think people will understand that analogy better?
Well repos a scary word. Maybe they couldn't think of a better word like boutique. Oh, yeah
There's only so many good words that's boutique was taken
The software center has taken to I still think boutique would or something would be weird compared to store because you're used to like
The Google Play Store the App Store those kinds of things, right? That's where I think it comes from
Yeah, something something big marketing be different
Katie big list
Yeah, go ahead
If I might offer I think the software store given that people are looking for app stores, etc
And there is such a thing on the gnome side. I'm not a KTE user myself, but I
Widely would accept a software store even if it's not monetizable
And if it is that's great more app developers well, I mean and it leaves room for that later and making some money
Yeah, I mean it leaves a room for later on for them to come along and say let's sell this
And as long as they like do a good job on the back end
Yeah
Chris here's another thought how long won't be until the other desktop environments
Get their own stores or boutiques or whatever you want to call it like
For example the X F C E shop. No, no
Store no
There will be and there will there will be
It's not gonna be called the Pantheon store, but you're you're barking up the right tree there. Yeah. Yeah elementary already doing that
They've already got their App Center. I think they call it. Mm-hmm. All right. Yeah
and
So that's that is I think good for Katie because kind of by my estimation there
They were sort of I was kind of looking like where's their official solution here
So there we go the KTE software store and downloads and snap to
You know, it's been weeks. I can really haven't heard really any big
snaps
No big flat packs
Like there's no been there's not there hasn't been an ounce would have some big project or or anything like it was build up to
But then we haven't really heard anything for a bit. Maybe we're an incubation period people kind of trying them out making more of them
Maybe even using them. Mm-hmm. Maybe it'll be interesting to see what kind of distribution like for those three, you know
Well, they have mostly at one kind mostly snaps. I
Don't know. Hmm. Yeah, which ones will be the most popular all those. Yeah, maybe we get stats on that. All right
Well, let's let's move along moving on because I caught something caught my eye
Over at elementary.io speaking of this of the elementary OS desktop
There's a countdown going two days 19 hours 22 minutes and seven seconds as we record this year show I count down
Yes, right now just like last time it's gonna be for a new release. Hmm. Why would you give them?
I don't know miss Wheeler. I don't know
Hmm. I don't know. She's yeah, probably likely. I don't know today. We'll find out two days
I remember I I broke the news in the chat room the last time they did it so sweet Lou breaking the news for us
Maybe they're just merging with Apple and Apple have some big news for us
That's a good one that's a good conspiracy that they're merging with Apple. Yeah, I like that
I'm gonna I'm gonna guess it's probably not that yeah
Well, I'm gonna say that if that were the case, they probably wouldn't be the ones making the announcement
Yeah, of course. They're smart. They're smart because if you work, yeah
It wouldn't suspect a thing if it was gonna be merging with Apple would be announced tomorrow. Yeah, right
That's just wrong Apple's keeping them in the dark
Yeah, maybe so we'll find out stay tuned and find out I'm sure we'll do a little update next week
But I do kind of like the hype. I gotta admit it's fun. It makes it feel a little more like
You know, it's not just posted on the mailing list and maybe that's more your style
But it's like there's a whole involvement to it. It feels like a production. So, let's see as any
452 says that they're merging with twit
elementary OS and twit
That's I got a theory for you. How about this one?
System 76 is buying them. Oh, yeah, right
Distribution for system 76 hardware wouldn't that be good wouldn't that be something because you know
They've got system 76 got a really great range of machines right now and they have one of the developers
Works there at system 76 both share attention to detail and wanting to craft
Yes, exactly and you know because somebody who works with the project works there at system 76
They have a kind of a direct line for this kind of stuff and some of their rigs would look particularly good
Running elementary OS like like they have the disable complete all-in-one
Right, that's like obvious. That would be I mean that would
Legitimately would make and it also elementary OS has really kind of gone out of their way to make sure everybody
They're they're clear like they're there
They don't feel that their competition is Ubuntu or Ubuntu Mate because they want to go there
They say they mainly going after users that are already running proprietary OSes
They don't right that's who they're going after
You could argue that still competing with other distros
But I think it's it's an interesting approach and if you look at their distribution in that context that their their primary market is people
Who aren't running Linux yet?
I think they think their attention to details. It's pretty interesting. So the system 76 picking them up
Well now I just want that to happen Chris. I know I know it would be pretty big
I wouldn't want like the general distribution to go away because I've been running on Dylan's laptop and that's a Dell
Like I think it's almost like that same exact model you've got right there
Oh nice, and it's been flawless for over for well over a year now
So I wouldn't want them to go away as a general distribution. No, I wouldn't either but you do have to wonder
I'm sure if I'm sure if something like that were to happen
There would be some little birdies going around tweeting about it. Yeah, probably all right before we go any further into the show
I'm excited to get to the review that Wes is reviewing wait
What the review that Wes is reviewing no the distro the Wes is reviewing speaking of really well put together
distributions that pay a lot of attention to the fine details
I'm really curious, but before we get there. I'm gonna mention digital ocean digital ocean comm and use our promo code
Do unplugged all one-word lowercase, and you'll get a $10 credit at digital ocean. This is a great cloud hosting provider
Why is it great? Well when you're using the cloud you're using other people's computers
And so you want to make sure they're good you want to make sure they got great infrastructure
Running on Linux using the KVM virtualizer SSDs for all the disk I owe 40 gigabit e-connections right into the hypervisors
Some of the best data centers in the world in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, London, Toronto, Germany, even India
It's I know I know they have the best interface in the business
Never seen anybody come close to this desktop or a web app HTML5 console you get access to your rig from
Post all the way to login they have incredible
Nicely formatted tutorials and guides to help you set things up. They have entire application stacks
You can deploy boom ready to go. Everything's good to go or you can deploy a base rig. I love both of those options
They've got a bunch of good distributions
You can choose from and you combine that with the great UI the simple ability to spin up multiple machines at once
The crazy straightforward pricing get this
$5 a month is the base rig so if you use our promo code deal unplugged you get the $10 credit
But you can also do digital ocean at an hourly rate
Now girl, I am telling you do unplugged is going to get you the extra money
Plugged is going to get you the extra mile if you're using the hourly rate because you can get a fantastic rig at like
Three cents an hour. I think that's the most popular one. I mean, it's just nuts
And now they have block storage up to 16 terabytes of storage. You can allocate to your rig. That stuff is awesome all SSD based
That's pretty nice. That is pretty nice
Also, check out the digital ocean community page where they've got all of their tutorials posted right there
Including some good ones working with zfs working with own cloud
A lot of stuff is now getting updated for ubuntu 1604 and centos 7 and all that stuff
And then also they they're highlighting their projects that use their super nice straightforward api just use our promo code do unplugged and a big
Thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring the linux unplugged program. And yeah, they got free bsd too
Yeah, they got free bsd. In fact mentioning free bsd just really quick before we move on free bsd
Just announced a centos 7 binary compatibility. They've been working on it for a while
You know, but get that linux layer in there. Yep
Yeah, well, I mean like windows does
Yeah
As of yesterday a linux based c7 landed in ports for installing the centos base packages as it will allow running newer linux binaries built for
modern
Centos right at enterprise 7 era systems on free bsd
Which is very handy it turns out, uh, previously centos 6 was the default and by a little bit dated now
It is isn't it? So there you go. So now you get the centos 7 which doesn't feel like a spring chicken chicken either
But uh a nice step up. Yeah, absolutely
I was kind of wondering to see this after windows made their announcement when if free bsd was going to have any more incentive to
Keep this current wonder
I wonder what kind of game not games, but I do wonder if games are going to be more
I was wondering just what kind of class of applications this opens up for bsd that wasn't available before
And i've seen some people hacking to get steam working on free bsd and there's been scripts that do it
I guess it wasn't this yeah, this could make it easier. Yeah, maybe I wonder if they'll ever target not sent to us as well
I've asked about that and I basically got a what's the point? Yeah, and why would we do that?
Like because I think and I don't mean to disparage but I think to the bsd people
Linux is already really silly. And so if you're gonna support any kind of compatibility
Why wouldn't you do it with the most adult linux? I think it's how they look at it
Well, and if and if they're targeting a lot of server workloads centos may be the thing that you know
Is most like what their boxes will end up being used for yeah
I don't I I would be way more enthusiastic about being able to install like a debian user land set of tools and stuff
And then i'd be like, oh right. Okay. Let's go look at this true os with the rolling free bsd and a debian user land
I can install
I mean, I I would do that. What's that that mac os 10 don't uh, there's a there is a there is a like a
There's like a user land set of tools. You can install that has like apt-like functionality. I'm blanking. I don't even know
Yeah, yeah homebrew that's what it is. Yeah homebrew. Yeah homebrew that they can kind of like that. Yeah, that'd be nice
Give me all that kind of stuff. But yeah, I I you know, I I think that's probably going to hook some people up
So mr. Wes
You are trying out the distribution that jack wallen at linux.com
Says bring serious relevance back to kde. Oh strong words. Yeah
Yeah, um, so it's called chaos kaos. We have talked about it before they've just recently gotten a new update
And it is a very refined approach to the plasma 5 desktop
Sort of a gray color scheme very uniformed. What are your thoughts on it so far?
You know i've um, I haven't run a kde distro for a while
So that was a little bit of one of the reasons I was thinking it'd be a fun one to throw at you
Yeah, um, I like it katie takes a little bit to get used to I honestly there's a lot of little things that i'm
Kind of surprised by and i'm like, oh right. I really like this and so there's a lot of little things
I'm enjoying having the like the taskbar kind of thing right on the bottom. I'm enjoying
just the responsiveness and
There's a lot of effects, but there's not there's not too many effects and it's kind of just it's just refreshing
It feels light
It feels pretty responsive and i've been really impressed when I was just going into tinker with it
and they have their own limited repository and they're using pacman as the
As the tool so it felt right at home and they've got like nice colors
It feels it feels just like it's been well cared for well touched
I you know, I haven't I haven't used it long term
So I don't know
How well their software availability will meet my needs especially since i'm used to the larger arch repos
And one of the things they advertise is a limited repo. They're very focused on kd isn't arch base though
So yes, and I believe it'd be pretty easy to get
Um other other arch packages installed if I wanted to i've not tried that yet
Yeah, I think I think when I messed around with it you could but I think that's one of their things
Is they really want you to just use their limited selection?
um
It does feel like a very modern
Like if you're someone who who really likes kde
And want something that like you can just kind of set up go with it'll be a nice configured default
You can customize it if you want from there
But you have like new packages you have like the core stuff
You're kind of already using the you know k-office or whatever then I think you'll be really happy with it
So they have uh, they have a qt designer included karita cupzilla c file dolphin k3b kate sue studio image writer
Jack says the only real glaring hole in chaos's list of software would be an email client for that
You have to go to the package manager. Now. Did you did you get a chance to try out their gooey package manager?
Did you get a chance to look at this? Yeah, aren't they they're using uh octopi? Yes. Yeah
Uh, yes, I installed the installed firefox from there and a couple other things
And it wasn't uh wasn't too bad
I went back to the shell which I was also very pleased with and they've looks like they've applied some formatted options
Like they've got the fun little pacman style on pacman set and they've got some really nice spacing setup
So it like very clearly shows you some like these are your packages. Here's the new ones
Here's how much you're downloading in kind of a non-standard way, which I appreciate it
So they have they break it out into three repositories
So they've got core that contains the basic software necessary for the system to boot communicate with the bios
And set the basic shell options then main which contains the necessary libraries drivers and firmware to make the desktop function
And then they got apps and that contains all the user facing apps
Spread out into those three different categories the three repositories work seamlessly together to keep chaos or kaos
Up to date and running smoothly jack concludes by saying if you've been looking for a distribution to sway you back to the kde desktop
And by kde desktop, he means plasma desktop look no further than chaos. It's a beautiful
It is beautiful runs with us which runs with a snap of a much lighter desktop
And feels as reliable as any other option available for linux
I haven't been impressed with kde for very very long
I have not been impressed with kd in a very long time
But I am very impressed with this one and I'm certain users would find themselves equally happy to return to a desktop
That has long needed a champion like chaos
What are your thoughts on the speed? He talks about the speed a lot in this review
Yeah, I mean I was pretty
It didn't feel sluggish. I mean I haven't used a bunch of other kde distros recently
So I don't really know I can't compare them that well from that perspective
But as someone who uses who's you know
Uses i3 are awesome from time to time who otherwise uses, you know
Gnome but not that many plugins kind of a lighter gnome. It it really felt responsive. It felt light
The graphics looked nice, which they usually do thanks to kaywin. Um, so I was very pleased
It was like a very usable experience. Hmm
well
That is that is probably if you've been looking for a plasma desktop to jump into this is probably one to play around with if nothing
Else because you can get a sense of their design look and their theme they're going for and you could replicate some of that
If you want it in your own, yeah, and I I don't hate the way it looks
I don't think it's necessarily the style that I would go go for it's a little it's a little
Blue and boxy and I mean the gray is nice
Um, I don't think it feels quite as streamlined as what i'm used to in gnome
But I mean katie is so flexible that i'm sure you can
You know if you want to change it to make it something that you like that wouldn't be a huge problem
Um, i'm waiting for the plasma matte desktop version
Wimpy will be shipping in ubuntu 17, uh, oh
I will say it does come with some nice stuff like mpvs here. Yeah included by default
There's the it's a pretty good showcase of a lot of different qt software as well. That's good. Yeah, i'm i'm
Seriously tempted to replace vlc with mpv at some point. Yeah
Um, the new versions are very nice and um, yeah, i'm waiting to see a vlc
Three drops with high dpi support. I like gnome mpv a lot too, which is a nice front end mpv. Yeah, exactly
That's exactly in fact that and that new version. Um for gtk 320 is really good
Yeah, yeah
It's it's it's my go-to player now for video clips on the stream whenever i'm whenever i'm playing videos
On the show that aren't that aren't like on a web page i'm using gnome mpv because it i've been also having a decoding
Issues with vlc and where it starts dropping frames and things like that
It just gets to be all all kinds of a mess not something you can afford as a broadcaster
I like sweetloo's idea of looking at chaos desktop and then taking some of those
Ideas and transitioning them into an lxqt sort of lightweight desktop
I don't think lxqt has all of the theming and and and well, I guess unless you can use kwin with lxqt. I'm not sure
Uh, but I I look at this and I think they're doing some things that are right here
And it's that same sort of a little extra attention to detail and the plasma desktop doesn't often get it
So that's what also kind of makes it special. Yeah, exactly and it feels like they're you know, it's it's nice to have the focus
It's not just
A distribution that has oh, you can also get our kde spin. It's like this is what we're doing
It feels a little more polished. It feels a little bit more like yeah, we thought about it from beginning to end
We've picked our entire software stack. We've built our own repos just to do this project
Wimpy are you feeling the uh, the impending release date of the 1610 version of the ubuntu bata desktop?
Does it start to build up like is it? Yeah
Yeah, so, um
In feature freeze now. Yeah, and uh, yeah, we got lots of stuff to fix
Now I know there was uh, there was one feature that ended up getting scrapped for 1610, right?
Yeah, we uh, I yanked the uh, the marte hub hud
Um, we introduced that in alpha 2
And uh, we had some great testing feedback, but the feedback was clear. It was not ready
And uh, uh, we don't have time to fix it up. So, uh, we've we've yanked that and we'll revisit it in 1704
Well, that's kind of a downer you should share with us something that's going well
I mean I I respect the decision. You gotta you gotta do what you gotta do. Uh, but now you should pick now pick me back up
So get me excited about something. Yeah
What do we have to look forward to?
well, it's
It's a bit uninteresting really this release for ubuntu marte because we haven't
landed any groundbreaking
new features, but in terms of what the
end user sees
but
It's a ground up
Recreation basically so although it doesn't look like and it might not feel like it
But we literally started from scratch and built it all from the ground up all over again
And it's really all about the transition to gtk 3
And one of the reasons that we don't have time to go back and fix the marte hud for example is we did the initial
Let's go to gtk 3 and at that time it was
gtk
318. Oh, right and then part way through the ubuntu cycle
They've pulled in gtk 320
Which is a massive upheaval
For anyone that's a theme designer, you know that basically all your themes stop working. You have to redo all your theming
Oh man, so we've redone
All the themings for gtk 320. So we've actually done like two significant tool get toolkit transitions
In in this cycle, does that feel like you're bringing a lot of a lot of your time up?
um
It does and it doesn't because I made this decision that this release was going to be the we break everything we start over
You know, this is this is the new starting point heading towards 1804
We have to do this and the other thing that's happened, which is perfect timing. It was um
Um, maybe late last week. Um, it's been announced that gtk 322
Will be the last gtk 3 release
From that point onwards it will only get fixes
So after 322 then we go into this new gtk 4 development cycle, which is great. So from the mate
Desktop team. This is ideal because now we can
Stop having to do catch up on
On gtk 3 toolkit api changes and actually just solidify hunk down fix up stuff
Against that version and then the idea would be that 322 would be around for a year or more
It will be well the idea is is uh that um
Uh in about 18 months the stable version of gtk 4
Will come along in that there won't be any api changes at that point
So we've got like 18 months of sitting on that version of gtk
with no api changes
And then we have a transition in about a year and a half to a new toolkit, but we can now choose when
we jump
um toolkit versions
Rather than us all having to you know, keep pace with with the cadence of gtk. Yeah
Yeah, that's nice have something really you can target and then do bug fix and that kind of stuff
Yeah, so so we might be a little bit rough around the edges for 1610
but i'm really looking forward to 1704 because I know that we'll
only have one gtk version to focus on and
From now and probably all of the 1704 release will just be a refinement and fixes version probably no significant
New developments will continue to improve the ubuntu mate welcome and the software boutique
But in terms of all the other stuff
We'll just focus on fixing up and making good for a good long period because we need to sort of develop that
That stability and confidence that everything's working as we intend it to it's amazing
How much you know how much back end work that takes for sometimes very little actual show
But when you really do get that like no you can trust it. It just works. It's really worth a lot
Yeah, and it does sort of just work at the moment
But I know where the bugs and the wrinkles are and some of the testers have sort of identified lots of little paper cuts
And we need to start addressing that stuff
It sounds like it is it going to be an interesting it's an interesting phase
And I bet I bet you're still I bet there's still something as an end user
I'd be excited about for the for the 1610 release and I think
for somebody like me, uh, I am I
I think every six months is pretty aggressive and I don't think there's any problem at all
With using a couple of releases every now and then to just work on some of this stuff. Yeah, right
Yeah, that's what these intermediate releases are for, you know, these are the releases where you do this stuff, you know to build up to the lts
I mean
I suppose the thing that i'm most looking forward to and this isn't a 1610 thing specifically because it's um, I think it's landed in
1604 if it hasn't it's about to and that's um firefox 49 being able to play netflix. I think
That's huge. That's such a big deal. Um
So, you know amazon prime and netflix now working in uh firefox is terrific
So, you know, that's not nothing to do with tomato in particular, but that's a real good feature
Yeah, absolutely. It is man. In fact, we should do just a quick firefox update
So we're blowing through a lot of our updates right now. I think this is good. So but wimpy brought it up
Why don't we do that? Um
It's looking serious. I'll tell you about it here in just a moment
In fact, let's let's uh, reorient ourselves and talk about linux academy really quick and then we'll transition into firefox linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged that's where you go. You want to be happy like this lady up on the screen and do a little linux academy dance
Go there and learn more they got labs
It'll spin up on demand with the distributions you've chosen and the courseware and the lab servers match that choice
They have instructor mentoring when you need it
It is really a platform to teach you everything about the core essentials around linux and everything built
On top of it if you're a client if you have a client that has a new project for you
If you want to impress an employer or you want to learn a new skill
You want to challenge yourself or you want to get a certification?
These are all great opportunities to visit linux academy go to linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged check out how their dashboard totally maps out the courseware for you
Gives you download links for the comprehensive study guides and audio that you can take with you
Instructor mentoring is integrated into the platform too. So it's always available when you need it
They have a community stacked full of jupyter broadcasting members and they have so much great courseware
Plus linux academy has been staffing out to make sure all of their existing courseware stays relevant and gets updates and they can continue
And expand to make sure that your membership stays extra extra valuable linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged they got ios and android apps as well. So you can do it on the go
Check them out linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and a big thank you to linux academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
Linux academy.com slash unplugged. So this is a big deal
I think firefox could be getting up to a 700 improvement in responsiveness. Yeah, I said 700
Holy crap chrome take that. This is really something now
This is these are stats that are being reported by mozilla themselves. I'm guessing hopefully based on metrics
They're getting back from early rollout of
Electrolysis the company is reporting a 400 improvement in responsiveness and a 700 improvement in
web page load times
There's also the responsiveness for loading large web pages
Over the next week multi-process will begin coming to 10 percent of total firefox users in the coming weeks
mozilla will push multi-processing to 100 percent
Of their initial user group the group represents 40 to 50 percent of the total users
It's a lot of interesting numbers here
The gradual rollout with the next six months a major within the next six months
The majority of users can expect to have these capabilities. So here's what you're going to get in firefox 49
It's going to enable us a set of add-ons that work well with multi-processing
So you'll have for you'll have like a set in firefox 50 and 51 is somewhere depending on how development goes
Sandboxing and enabling of more add-ons turns on then firefox 52 or 53
Multiple content processes will be introduced and they talk about some of the cool things
They've done in there with their mem shrink project to really nail this memory use thing with multi processes and they say well learn from
the competition
The way they implemented multi-course referring to chrome right the way they implemented all day. Oh, yeah, of course or opera. Yep
The way they implemented multi-process is RAM intensive it can get out of hand
We're learning from them and building an architecture that doesn't eat all of your RAM. Oh, I like that
Yeah, so up to 400% improvement on load times less RAM usage. Um
rust
electrolysis
Netflix support
What is going on?
Wes is firefox all of a sudden coming around only ready for Chris is it bad?
Is it coming out off the ropes and swinging them punching chrome right in the face?
I think it is clear at least the Mozilla's kind of you know, they've really felt what users pain has been
I mean, especially like electrolysis has been a huge long rollout
But it does feel like they've been making a lot of changes now to kind of like, okay
We really need to catch up
We really need to be
Be in the spots where Chrome has us beat because there's like, you know
There's like the 80% that they both do they're both totally fine. You can do like that much of your web browsing
It's just those like extra Netflix support
Responsiveness not hanging on your one crappy site. Like these are things that people who like use the web a lot really expect out of a
browser
Ww you've run into 4 gig memory limit issues. What are you let's go. What are you talking about?
You're talking per tab per process. What is this for the entire process of firefox?
I've run into like two to three to four to five to six
Gigabits or six no six gigabytes of my eight gigs of RAM use
Just because I'm running multiple tabs or maybe I'm researching something or I'm reading cross things and you know
So yeah, firefox definitely needs a memory shrink because it's getting ridiculous
Well, I think this new electrolysis overall is gonna end up using more memory
I mean, they're just being really smart about how they're doing it
But I think it still uses more memory because you're running more processes
So I don't I don't know if that's actually gonna I don't know if that's gonna help
Yeah
firefox doesn't have that sandboxing or like that chrome thing where it separates up in orange tabs into
Separate processes right now. So on the latest, you know version for me
It's still chewing up memory. So the only thing it's saying boxes would be the flash process
I believe so that's still separate. So you'll eventually get a flash crash, but you won't as often as it was before
So it still needs
Don't do improvements and this is a good stuff and I've been waiting and waiting for like electrolysis and I I think
Michael to know which isn't here
Has been using electrolysis a little bit more so he could probably talk more on it. Mm-hmm. Yes, so
So for me right now
I'm still dealing with that and I sold and up crashing firefox daily
Just because I need to reset my memory and I need to keep tabs and I have stuff
Enabled for that to keep those sections. It's it's a process and I'm willing to wait for it. So, you know, we'll see what happens
Yeah, I'm getting hopeful though. Mm-hmm. And you should note that you can in about config under browser tabs. Yes remote
Yes, you can enable it for yourself. If you have firefox. Oh now you're talking my
So go try it out about config, right? You go in there and then it's where let's see how you got that. You got the file
I got it right here browser tabs.remote.auto start set that to true
If you then look under about support
It should have a multi process windows column. And if it shows that you have those then you're on it. Cool
I just enabled it right now is really easy. So cool. Well, all right now I kind of want to go try that
Yeah, I see if it's possible. That's pretty neat. They say and you know, I I caught the first
No, I caught the thing is for me is I'm such an extension idiot
Like I've just got I got like markdown dome be a chrome. Yeah, really
I know it's it's it's because the I find these tools useful to extend my workflow
Like I I can bang out some just some great show notes by using a bunch of different tools and stuff and you're in like
It's like a candy store right? You're like, oh, yes
Oh, come on. Oh, come on
I'm not that bad. I I do good. I do them. Yeah, I do that. I got laugh. Okay, here's what I have right now
I have two markdown extensions to yeah, because one
One can create markdown by selected HTML and one just creates a markdown link to the page
I see and then I've got last pass because I went back on the last pass juice. I got my highlighter bookmark
And I got hangouts and I got an imager. Oh
And I got Google quick scroll, which is kind of cool. Have you ever seen?
Yeah, tell me more
So like when you search for something on Google and you click the link quick scroll comes up and it takes you right to the spot
The page that is relevant here. Okay, that's really nice. Yeah, it makes it fast
And then I've got a subreddit style on it, which I don't even know what that's for
So I'm not like crazy with the extent. No, that's actually pretty good
And that you know flash is probably in there somewhere, but Google does all that. Yeah
Thanks, you make me to sound like I'm some sort of maniac. No, that's actually very reasonable
I I I'm excited to say that Wes and I will probably if all goes as planned be going to the open daylight summit
I think it was called on September 27th in Seattle
It is a conference about software defined networking and Linux etc
Etc put on by the Linux foundation, which means we might be doing like a different recording time in a week or so
So we'll update the calendar and let you guys know
Probably the 20th would be the the day we would do something if we do like a double or a late recording
I don't know what our plans are there
But because the 27th the day that the conference starts is a Tuesday, right?
And I don't really have any rigs here by myself that I think we could do a show live there from at the moment
I'm not sure tricky endeavor. Yeah, and I just don't think I don't know
Maybe I'd have time to put something to be such a bummer if like, oh
We tried that and then it didn't work. We just didn't have a show that we could always just have the mumble room to the show
Oh, yeah, I think they've got it down now. They might I bet I bet if I bet if they really put their minds to it
They could I bet I think they could I could probably do a better show with maybe Rekai Marshall on them into into place
I don't know. I could I could see I don't know. I think they could self-organize actually
I tell you what, I tell you I think wimpy would probably get drafted
Yeah, but I think I could I think they could self-organize and then and then they do their own show. Don't tell them
They'll go off and just come back to the network
It's just you and me from then on
Also, I guess before I run if you want a little more show
I got to give a plug to our brand new show you can go to error dot show and
That'll take you to the user air program. We've got two episodes out right now. Episode 3 is officially in the can
I hear it's coming soon. Mm-hmm. It'll be coming out soon
and so you can subscribe to the feed and just get it auto magically we do have an mp4 and mp3 feed at this time and
It's also getting posted to the youtubes and in the all shows feeds if you're there you've got it
But both episodes so far really well reviewed
So I invite you to check it out if you want a little more Linux discussion
You know pleasant fun manner. It's great. We we we very
We try to have a very different feel for that show. And so I think we're pulling it off
Yeah, I gotta say you episode 2 was great. Thank you. I hope you enjoy candid and yeah, that's true
It is and I hope you enjoy episode 3 as well, which will probably be out Wednesday morning Tuesday night JB time
So if you're watching the feeds what what I just like JB time that is do well
That's that's where we live. I just because it doesn't really matter to anybody listening
It's just because if I say it's specific, well who cares I could it could be East time
But if it's not your times, it doesn't matter. It's just the time that would jet evening for where we're at
Yeah, we got to do the beard time. Haha. I kind of like that too. That's that's not a bad suggestion
Beard time. I like it West. Alright, so I think that'll probably bring us to the end of this week's program
We do have a couple of more things that we'll pick up in the post show. So if you're sticking around
Well, I might put some of it in there West don't disparage. Okay, people could stick around and listen, but really you're right
The live experience like because we might get some gonna probably say hey recap put some of that in there
You know, but there's some like there's some real stinkers that are worth being there live for
JBLive.tv on a Tuesday you go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar to get it converted to your time
You got the robots there to do that
You can also go over to the contact page
Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact
Send us in a comment and if you are you if you're a longtime YouTube watcher for the unplugged program
Give us a thumbs up. Please do. See you next week
Get it out of here
I've never installed GNU slash Linux
And the value of this is negative
I'm gonna say a cucumber sour is very refreshing. It was actually very pleasant. Yeah, not too sour not super intense
It would be a good summer beer too. Like when it's really hot out. Yeah, even moan the law yo, man
Screw water you go. I want a beer and you go grab one of these this this cucumber
Sour would really do it for me. Not hoppy at all. Is this is this another local beer you brought to let's find out
You are some kind of maniac from Bend, Oregon, Oregon. That's not too far. That's that's legit. That's local
That is local. All right, JB titles calm. Let's go pick our title everybody. Thank you mumble room
Thank you, everybody. Thank you. Now. We have to go vote somebody off the island and only one person will survive at JB titles.com
Flashy extension idiot. That's kind of funny. Welcome to nope a real pain in the flash. That's also good
So from everything I'm reading that we could link me earlier
Apparently by the end of this year slash and silver light will be mostly in the NT API
For Firefox and it will be the only thing there and they're moving everything else to web extensions
You know, I do remember some talk about that web extension stuff in that vein interesting. Yeah
The beard knows the beard knows. So what do you know about software to find networking West?
Not as much as I would like to. Mmm, but it's an interesting topic and I feel like it's something that it's Linux is poised to do well with
It's too bad. A lot of the hardware implementations are so proprietary exactly
Just don't really have much option in the way of hardware things like switches. They're all very expensive for software-defined switches. I
Don't be nice if there were cheaper devices it'd be nice if like ubiquity
You got in the software-defined networking more I'm waiting for like a white box
Switcher that you can download by and like actually run cumulus on but they're all like open compute theory will provide these things
But they're still targeting way higher end than what your average home user is gonna want like they're going like hundred gig now, right?
I feel like there's like this huge software defined
culture and and community that's growing that is sort of like
unknown
Because it this there is so much happening here, but yet I don't really have any eyes on it for some reason
I and I don't know if it's just a lot of it kind of behind closed doors in the enterprise though
I think that's why hmm. Okay. I don't usually work on your switches or 40 gig plus or yeah. Yeah. Yeah
Okay, that kind of makes sense
So there is a Linux Foundation have looking at it right now
software defined networking
Event in Seattle. Oh
The open Daylight Summit. That's what they're calling it the open Daylight Summit September 27th through the 29th and
I have gotten you and I pre-approved press wise to go in the foundation actually contacted us and said hey
Do you guys want to attend and I said?
Can West go to well, thank you
Well, I don't think this isn't his this is actually not really his thing
So this is this is developers and the software to find networking community coming together to demonstrate some of the latest technology
in open
software to find networking
So I feel like this is an opportunity for maybe to go and learn what's learn what some of them are talking about and then see
We can translate that to back to the audience to something that's interesting. I don't know what you're gonna say
Well, I was gonna say it's open like open power is open to some extent like there's the protocol and stuff is open
But most implementations are not necessarily open like a lot of the ones you care about say the hardware stuff
While they're using open flow as some great API that you can talk to you still don't have any of the software or for the switch
Yeah, and see that's the kind of you're linking against some Broadcom IP or something. That's exactly the kind of thing
I want yeah, I out for that's exactly what I want to keep my eye out for and I mean
It's still cool you buy the switch and it runs whatever software as long as you can control it with your open controller and stuff
It's mostly okay. Yeah, it's still it's still an ideal, right? It's still an improvement, but it's not ideal
So that's so that's on the 27th West okay, and that's that's a Tuesday
And I don't know exactly what we should do like we there's a couple of options
We could go in the morning and try to hustle back up here in time for unplugged and do a later unplugged
That's definitely a possibility
We could pre-record on the 20th and dude we could do two unplugs and then not worry about that Tuesday at all or
And I don't think this is I don't think I have the hardware for this
But the real Hail Mary of course would be to do a show from down there. Oh, right, but I don't think I have
I mean, maybe I could do it from the MacBook Pro, but I haven't really put it in that kind of workload yet
But otherwise I I mean I need like a pretty powerful machine to do all that not to mention
I'd have to make sure I have all the analog equipment to make that possible so I didn't get permission from them
There's a good open flow switch. Oh, yeah, okay in terms of like something a consumer could afford. It's like a hundred bucks
Posted it. It'd be a good learner device wouldn't it yeah the zodiac here. Oh, yeah
Yeah, the zodiac those would be fun to play with wow look at that thing. That's pretty interesting
Yeah, I don't know how performant this would be in terms of switching capabilities. I don't even know
Learn on yeah, yeah
So I guess I'm gonna go in there with a pretty open mind
If we can make it down there, and you and I'll probably just have to figure out what we want to do recording wise
Okay, I'm open for whatever. I would love to do the show from there, but I'm thinking that's probably not doable
But if we got if we hustled we got a few interviews in the morning and then got up here say by like
233 and did it like a late-unplugged. Yeah, maybe that might be I don't know so that's something to think about
It's coming up on our radar on the 27th. They're having it here in Seattle and the Linux foundations behind it
So that's kind of awesome. Yeah, that's interesting too. I like the idea of this at least
It's the tough pie case with 15 backers. They have 22 days to go. They're looking for
5840 Australian funky money
But it and they're at 2400 right now the tough pie is an all-in-one breakout tough case for the Raspberry Pi 2 and 3
With an inbuilt 7 inch display look at that thing Wow it looks like you're toting a bomb around
You could be toting a bomb it could be high-end production equipment
There's the inside view with 3d printed mounting brackets and spaces and look at all that stuff like they're running Cody down there
Look at that. Yeah, they gotta go home with Cody on it
And of course I like that setup just for like all right
I can watch my movies and retro pie it's got a keyboard in there
I mean, it's a huge laptop
But this thing looks like you could toss it around on an airplane or or drive over it with a tank and it would survive
It's pretty cool, and it's called the tough pie by Brett Swan
Mmm. Yeah, you never know you never know 22 days left to go
He might Brett my reasonable goal to try to raise to I'm gonna send it over to know though because he and I like the idea
Of modding up those types of pelican type cases to do production stuff too. It's part of cool ways. I like it. I'm interested