Okay, boys, how we feeling about the news that Lenart Pottering has ended up at Microsoft. Hey, I hope you got a nice payday
At least you got a figure right? That's a pretty good get
There's really no clue as to what he's doing over there. There's been speculation. He's working on WSL
Yeah, do we even know like a title or anything? Oh, I love how this got discovered which was purely by accident, right through an email
Yeah, yeah, it was just and it was sort of revealed after it happened quite a bit
you know, of course Lenart famous for creating pulse audio and then later system D huge contributor to the desktop as we know it today and
Now at Microsoft for reasons we don't know but we do hope you know
It was a great move for him Lenart. You ought to move up to the Pacific Northwest be in the home base and
Shoot us a message. We'll take you out and show you some of the best places to eat, right?
Take Lenart out on the town. Ask him all of the secrets about Red Hat and system D
Hello friends and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes and my name is Brent
Hello guys, welcome on in. We got a big show a big announcement
Announcement this week. We'll have a very special guest to join us to help with our big announcement
We've been waiting to tell you for weeks. Plus we burnt another night with a big server outage
We do it. So you don't have to guys. We'll share you what went wrong and we'll share you our attempt to fix it
That's why we do it. We're doing this intentionally. I think so. That's what I tell myself
They will or end it all out with some boosts and picks and a whole lot more so before we go any further
Let's say time-appropriate greetings to our virtual lug. Hello mumble room
Hello, what a fantastic showing and hung in there with us through technical challenges today
We had a power outage before the show started how even it was crazy, right?
And that was even after West put in all those UPS batteries. Well, we forgot the battery part
But next time we'll get the batteries. Well, and someone's kind of got to join the circuit by holding both ends, right?
Right. Hey, I want to say a special good morning to tail scale tail scale is a VPN protected by wire guards noise protocol
We love it. We use it
It will change your game and you can get tail scale up and running in minutes
Get it on all your machines build your own flat mesh network in minutes. So go say
Good morning to the folks over at tail scale. Go try it on up to 20 devices for free
Tailscale.com for you can love tail scale. You got to go try it out tailscale
Com let's get right into this week's episode because Brent has put together a very special treat for us
We've got two brunches and one of them is on theme today
Yeah, previously if you remember we did a brunch with Quentin Stafford Frazier, which is really great
Check that out extras dot show slash 86, but this week the real highlight is a brunch
I did with Tim Canham that's at brunch show 87 you could find it there Tim is a
Fascinating gentleman. We've had him on Linux unplugged previously
I believe earlier last year he is a senior software engineer at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory and
Had a very deep hand on the Mars helicopter project
and so he and I got a chance to sit down earlier and
Talk about all sorts of pretty amazing topics that I think all of you would really enjoy everything from
The software and hardware that's powering NASA's ingenuity helicopter
But also and I think this is the extra juicy stuff what it was like to kind of craft
JPL switch from Solaris to Linux back in the day and
How they're using open source tools and projects and the philosophy over at JPL these days
So here's a little snippet
Tim thanks for joining me on season two of brunch with Brent. I really appreciate having you well, thanks
It's great to be here
Tim for those who don't know you joined us early last year on Linux unplugged
could you give us a little bit of an introduction of who you are and
What you do? Well, I am a software engineer at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory
In Southern California and for those who might not know you have NASA as a whole
but then there are centers around the country that have various responsibilities and
The Jet Propulsion Lab their responsibility has always been robotic spacecraft. You know, we don't have a pilot
It's not where you don't do man launches. So all these spacecraft. You've read about over the years like Voyager and Cassini and
the Mars Rovers those were all built and
Launched and operated by the Jet Propulsion Lab. And so I started there in 1991 coming out of school and I've been there ever since
Except for one brief trip out to industry in the mid-90s, but I've been back and doing that ever since and
My background is I'm an electrical engineer
but I during my studies I also studied computer architectures and
Software so I might much of my career spent living in that
straddling that world between
software and hardware and
So over the years I worked on a number of projects at JPL. I worked on when I first came out of school that worked in their deep space network for those who
who may not be familiar JPL has three sites around the globe so that as a globe rotates all these deep space
Spacecraft can be in view of the earth. So there are these gigantic antennas. One of them is 70 meters across if you can imagine antenna
That's most most of the width of a football field wide
So when I early in my career, I worked writing software to operate those systems
And then as my career went on I switched to the flight side worked on Cassini for a while worked on the Curiosity rover
The one that's on that's been on the surface for 10 years now much of that software was brought forward to the Perseverance rover
So I have software running on that rover as well. But obviously the most in the last
Five years or so. I've been working on the Mars helicopter, which is a small semi autonomous helicopter
That is a companion to the Perseverance rover
And so we operate the helicopter via the rover and it does flights around in the vicinity of the rover doing scouting
Taking pictures getting a lot of great flight data
And so that project launched with the rover last year
We landed in February so we're almost coming up on a year of the rover being on the surface
And then during April we did a series of primary flights to prove the concept of flying on Mars
And then they went so well and we got so many awesome pictures that they decided to extend our our mission
So we've been doing an extended mission of flying around and doing scouting for the rover ever since
And it sounds like you were in part let's say in part
But you can you can accept the whole thing if you like in part responsible for some of the Linux adoption
That went into you know, I think this was a deep project where you it's kind of experimental
And you were telling me earlier how Linux was a natural progression from things like Solaris back in the day
How was that transition for you from one to the other?
And why was Linux interesting to you back then? And why is it interesting to you again today?
Well coming from the Linux angle about 15 years ago when we were when JPL was very much a Solaris house was
I saw kind of the democratization of the platform as a good thing
Because with Solaris, you know, it was this big corporate package and you bought their hardware with it
And it was very much a silo
But the hardware with the software with the services all together and they were also extremely expensive
To rewind like the internal clock, but you know back in the 2002-2003 era
You know one of the one of the standard Sun workstations was anywhere between 15 and 20 thousand dollars a pop
They were very expensive
Back then that was actually even more money than we think about these days, right?
Exactly
And as I mentioned in I think it was this podcast, you know our previous the Linux unplugged one was
I discovered Linux and I put together a system out of basic parts you can buy from Fry's electronics
May it rest in peace, you know
I was thinking you were gonna say Radio Shack
But I put together a PC for a couple grand at work and ran Linux on it
And it compiled our code at the time twice as fast as the Sun machine did that cost seven to eight times more
But I'm surprised that that experiment hadn't been done before in a sense like that the Solaris guys weren't like
Oh, we kind of really keep track of of what else is out there
And and so what was the incentive for you to even give that a try?
Well, I was trying to you know, I saw some of these tool environments that I kind of like that were in Linux
you know build build environments and things like that and not pilers and and
I saw it as a way to take advantage of them and also just trying to be a good if you will a good steward of JPL's money
Right if we could have a project where we could sometimes the developers would have to share machines because they were just so expensive
And you know the idea that you could you could have more machines that were more powerful and more people's desks
just kind of was a multiplier of people's efficiency and a better use of JPL's money
And so I that's why I started looking into it for my project
And we essentially turned on a dime at that point and we would switch from Solaris to Linux
And then when I was hired on to do curiosity the rover project
They were still using or were planning on using Sun boxes from the previous project
And I just said, well, let's try this, you know, let's switch and use these Linux machines instead
because they're much more powerful and they're cheaper so we can buy more of them and for more developers
And you know, they were skeptical at first
But once I made you know, I showed from my trade study that we did that it worked better
They pretty much switched to and now it's very pervasive on the flight side of the house of JPL to use Linux for not only development
but the ground systems themselves, they run on Linux
And so back 15 years ago and I don't want to claim sole credit for this because there's other people that were advocating for it
I was just in a position where I could actually do it
But what's happened in the last five or 10 years is that there's been a big switch to containerization and cloud tools
Right, so I was able to get us to we're actually using Linux on physical boxes, which was a big change
And then in recent years, they've switched to, you know, running a big giant VMware instances
Now they're starting to transition to doing everything on the cloud
So there's like this AWS government cloud where the AWS provides services to run containers
And so JPL switching a lot of their infrastructure to use them instead of physical machines
But it's still all living within a Linux world
And so I'm glad I played a part in that
I don't want to overstate my role, but I think it was it happened at the right time to kind of catch the trend
Well, in many ways, it sounds like you're really just taking the attitude that, you know, new technologies need to be looked at
and considered and implemented if they really make sense
And that I would imagine at a place like JPL is kind of it should be the way to go
And and OK, we rely on what we know
But we need to still stay very current because some of the new technologies allow things like, you know
the Mars helicopter to be as small as it is and to do some of the things it's doing
So I would say kudos to you for keeping your thumb on new technologies
and not being afraid to continue to dive in
Even, you know, even even this far into your experience with with all that stuff to not stagnate is no small thing I'd say
And I don't think it's overt, but it's very likely that JPL getting a lot of institutional experience with Linux
to the point where they trusted it for some of their critical tools for the ground systems or for development
and even some of the enterprise tools that they use, you know, that are business related
When it came time just to proffer up the helicopter as a platform running Linux
You know, they at least had some institutional comfort with Linux as an idea
Because back when I was first doing it, it was kind of viewed as this
How do I put it? Like the crazy uncle who's got everything wired up in his basement
You know, the people that were pushing Linux were kind of fringe
You know, that's how they were viewed because they didn't have these enterprise solutions like Sun offered at the time
And so if we had come completely out of the cold and just said, hey, we're going to fly Linux on a helicopter
You know, they there could have been a lot more resistance to it had we already not made the transition
Linode.com slash unplugged
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account and you go there to support the show
Let them know you heard about it here
Linode is how we've built everything
A couple of days ago, we were working on an outage of our own making
And it was really nice to have Linode in there as our co-pilot, if you will
You know, I could go into the dashboard
I could get all the disk information I needed so we could sort things out
And I was able to quickly resize the disk which gave us the breathing room we needed to get things back online
It's nice not having to fight Linode's interface or Linode's capabilities
Or having to like trick their customer service into helping
They have just the best support too
And that's always kind of in the back of our mind if we ever get really stuck
And their S3 compatible object storage has been such a useful tool for us
I think once you wrap your head around it, you're going to love it
Even just for your backups
Of course, I've got cloud firewalls
VLAN support, a powerful DNS manager
Super fast networking
They've got 11 data centers around the world
They've been doing MVME PCIe upgrades for their hard drives, AMD EPYC CPUs for their big CPU rigs
And they've got pricing that's going to work for an individual or for a business
It's 30-50% cheaper than those hyperscalers that want to lock you into their crazy esoteric platform
And Linode has just recently rolled out Kali Linux support
I kid you not guys, at one point when I was back in the quote unquote industry
I almost just laugh at myself just saying it now
But I kid you not, we were seriously investigating building a solution like this ourselves and selling it to clients
Because there's real utility in installing Kali Linux in a remote, safe cloud location
And then checking your network
You know, even if it's just a couple machines or it's an entire business network
It's such an incredible tool
And they have it in their app marketplace too, so you can get it up and going in just seconds
That's Linode, it's powerful, it's fast
It's Linux to the core
And they support some of your favorite shows and some of your favorite community projects and events too
So go say hello, get $100 in 60-day credit and support the show
Go sign up and see why we love it so much
Linode.com slash unplugged
Brent, that was a fantastic talk with Tim
And the entire conversation is available at extras.show
We've already published it, so we'll drop a link in the show notes for that as well
But one of the reasons we wanted to play that chat
Is because it ties in with an announcement that we have here on the show
So, let's start this off because there's a lot to it
We have a very special meetup that we're planning at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory
On September 29th at 12.30pm
It's a special tour from our friends at JPL
They do have some restrictions in notes, so we'll link to their public tours page
And it's going to be limited to 20 audience members
So it's going to be a little bit tricky to figure out how we do this
Now don't worry, this is not the only meetup that we'll be doing
Oh no
No, we're going all the way in and we're doing a west coast tour
And so we'll probably do something like half a dozen meetups in that route
But we need to know where you're at
And we need to be able to plan and be smart about our fuel usage
So we have spun up a west coast crew matrix room
Where we're hoping that if you are on the west coast
And you'd be interested in a JB meetup in your area
You'll let us know you're out there so we can start getting some data
So we can start planning this route
We're also going to need some local experts to help us pick out locations
That we could go for a meetup or maybe a spot JOOPS could park
Especially, I know immediately we're going to need to know a dinner place near JPL
Since we can only fit 20 audience members at JPL for the tour
We want to do a meetup nearby maybe like the next day or something like that
Where we can all sit down and do dinner
So if you're in the area that could be really helpful if you get in that matrix chat room
We'll have that linked in the chat room
I also made a short URL out of it to make it easy
It's just bit.ly slash west coast crew
And that'll take you to our matrix chat room
Tips via email and boosts are great too
But we're hoping really to build a long term community in that matrix chat room
So if you join us in there we'll have a link for that in the show notes
But this is something very awesome that we are very excited about
And very grateful that Tim has extended this opportunity to us
No kidding
And we're huge space nerds so to be able to go down to JPL
And see all of it down there is going to be
Well it's an opportunity of a lifetime for us
Linode is on board for another Linode on the road road trip to help us get down there
So we're going to make a whole tour out of it
And we're just getting it all figured out right now
We will have meetup details and locations as we figure them out at meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting
But phase one is really we're just trying to get some signal of if you're out there
So if you're out there and you want to do a meetup in your area on the west coast
And I include basically Idaho, Oregon, Washington, California that general area
We almost never stop in the Portland area
We almost always just blast right on through
So if you're out there let us know
You can send us a boost and say you're in the area
Or you could join that matrix chat room that'd be great
Or send us an email and we can start figuring it out
But we know ultimately our end destination will be the jet propulsion laboratory
Where we will meet up do a small tour there
And then we'll have you know subsequent meetups
It's just super exciting it's a great opportunity
And it's really nice because there's not a lot of events going on
We're starting to see more starting to come back
But there still hasn't been like the full return of events
And we've been missing it we've been missing the audience you know
Especially after what a great time we had in Raleigh recently
Yeah which
And we're feeling a little jealous we don't get to go to the London meetup I know I am
We may have a Raleigh matrix chat room soon as well
Because Brent's going to be in the area
And maybe doing some micro meetups
It's true while Alex is in London I'm going to be at his place
That West Coast crew matrix room
That again is bit.ly slash west coast crew
And we'd just like to get an idea if you're out there where you're at
If you've got any suggestions that could hold
You know 30 40 people or something like that
And the near JPL too would be really helpful
Super excited about that
We'll have more details to share as well as planning that will happen in office hours
So stay tuned
Just a quick spot of housekeeping I want to mention that you can become a member
You get an ad free copy of all of the shows at Jupiter.party
Of course you can become just an unplugged core contributor at unpluggedcore.com
You also get access as an option to the live show feed which is like twice the show
Usually it's a lot of Brent cussing but other than that
Mostly
But you got to listen to find out really
Yeah Brent you potty mouth
But yeah Jupiter.party to become a network member and support the independent podcast here
I mean the reality is guys we do a niche you know
We're never going to we're never going to get like a million views on YouTube
Or go viral on Twitter talking about
No matter how many ridiculous faces you make I mean you keep trying
I try yeah I try
We really really thrive on direct audience support
And so your membership is a great way to do that at Jupiter.party
All right we have a bit of a tale of woe this week
Here here I was 10 p.m. Thursday minding my own business
Making myself a snack before kind of getting ready for bed you know the usual usual evening
I see a message on my phone from Brent nothing nothing too unusual you know he
We've been chatting a lot lately
And we tend to stay up late too
We sure do but there was something about this message
Sounded simple
Hey is Matrix down for you
But I had a sinking feeling that was going to change the course of my evening
I even paused for a moment because I was like surely it's me
You know I have I have pretty terrible Internet over here and stuff
So usually the problem is just like I gotta wait a half an hour
And so I did and things didn't change and I just thought is it too late
No I'll just try it'll be fine it'll be fine
And so well I asked and the answer kind of surprised me
I didn't go figure
We all were kind of doing something different in the Matrix rooms at different times
So one of us would inevitably going to notice but it's always Brent
You know I was sitting down to contribute again
I've gotten this routine this week of sitting down late at night and contributing to our new website
Which has been really great
And so I sat down as usual as I had the last you know four nights before then
And I was just kind of looking at my phone
Four nights before then and I was just going to check our little Matrix chat room
We have a little website Matrix chat room
Everybody keeps in tabs of what's happening there
And I couldn't update people
And that's really how it started
I sat down just to get started
And then I couldn't I couldn't do step number one
And so I looped both of you guys
And I mean we can't have a sad Brent
No and of course there I am right
By this point I got one kid down
I'm managing two other kids
My wife Adia is out that evening
She's hanging out with her lady friends
I'm literally just like trying to get everything settled down for the night
And well we decide we all got to jump on a call
I'm just doing dishes while we take care of the Matrix server
Oh that's nice
Yeah
So I'm sitting there doing that stuff
One kid falls asleep while we're on the phone
Two other kids still missing
We got to track them down because it's way past the time they're supposed to be out
But of course now the Matrix server is down
And Wes like the pro that he is
He kind of gives us like a good solid like stand up meeting recap of the situation
Before we ended up down this route of you know dumping our entire database
And restoring it somewhere else
We realized that our Matrix server had gone offline
And then it turned out that we had eaten up all the extra disk space that we'd given it just a few months ago
Oh yeah okay
We were able to allocate a little extra disk space by reclaiming the stuff that ext4 auto reserves for root
Which is quite handy
And that was enough to allow us to bring the database back online
And Postgres is pretty good about you know it's got its write ahead log and stuff
So it can restore itself pretty well from that kind of failure usually
And it seemed to restore just fine in our case
But we did have enough room to do a preliminary run of this Rust program
That compresses the state groups
So we did get that to run
They hopefully provide a repo that has a Docker file
So you could just if you already have Docker compose going for Synapse
You can just tell it to go build this and then run it
And then they the first time I used it they only had that like a manual tool
Which we can look at and maybe see like that might be a way to figure out how to do more
What it auto did wasn't sufficient
But now they have an auto tool that will go through all of your all the state groups for the various rooms and stuff
And compress the ones that thinks it needs to compress
So we can do future rounds of that as well
Assuming it works
But once again our matrix server was down
And we just a couple of months ago scrambled and really upgraded this box
But what gets us is the database growth
And it's the state tables too which is not what you'd expect right
You'd think it'd be people's conversations or you think it'd be images
But it's the state's table that's growing and growing and growing
And you came across a cool little utility that actually helps us do some proper maintenance on this thing
And what was that written in there?
Oh it's written in Rust
This is great I wish this was built in to be honest with you
Yeah that would be nice perhaps in a future version some someday
But yeah it kind of goes in and it looks at some of this the state group cache that they're using
To be able to quickly answer questions about the state of various rooms
And then you can just compress some of those entries so they don't need as many individual rows
And kind of shrink that giant table
Because I think right now that's by far the biggest table in the database
And it's something like a hundred gigs
More than that
Maybe now it's a hundred gigs
Yeah it was more before
It didn't start that way
So we had to get the box back up online
I mean you fill up your disk, services crash, things go offline
And then you kind of sit there with options
Like do we want to migrate this to Linode's managed Postgres
So we're just not worried about a Postgres server anymore
We've been tempted I mean it's a recent offering
We've been hoping to see it and it's great that they offer that now
Do we want to maybe change data centers
Because maybe this isn't in the best location
Because we kind of spun it up on a lark
So maybe we should do you know like all these questions kind of came up
And we had to answer which technical debt are we going to solve
To get this system back up and online
And can we play around with the storage sizes to give us a little flexibility
So once we had that conversation
Of course as things are going on
As you know Wes's dogs need to go out
And I'm doing dishes
We kind of sort all of this out
And so Wes gives us a recap, again
Not some professional
I see, so are you thinking of moving it to a disk that has more room
Or can we avoid doing that?
So I think first things first
We shut off the server
Then we do a dump of the database to a file
And then from that
We can import it into our new shiny hosted database
But we want to get that process started because that's probably going to take some time
Because we have a painfully large database at the moment
And even just moving it to that hosted system would take forever at its current size
Which was one of the issues right
This thing was like nearly 300 gigabytes when you included all the different tables and everything in there
So like moving it around
Not necessarily an easy job
Most of the rest of the database was a reasonable size though
Templates are built in
Postgres is the internal one
And Synapse
So yeah Synapse is the only thing we care about
And as we see here with 223 gigs
Right that's the one
That's the problem child
I think the 7000 KB is probably not too big of a deal
At one time it was
At one time it was indeed
Actually it looks like kind of like a minimum
Because they all seem to have that
There's really a lot to this
And most people wouldn't run into this
If you didn't have thousands of users that were coming in from all these different matrix servers across the federation
Right if you just set up yourself a home server
With a small community
You'd be fine
Yeah we've gotten ourselves in a somewhat particular situation
Yeah and as we were debating like how do we want to do this
Do we want to move rigs
Do we want to change things up
We kind of realized this is all our own fault
So I suppose the thing to do would be to put it in the same data center
At the
Yeah it looks like we've got everything in Fremont
At the moment
California
That doesn't seem like the best place
No that's probably a consequence of us
Spinning this up on Alarc a few years ago
And we're like well we should make it close to us
Wes I feel like this very call
Right now is the consequence
Of us spinning it up on Alarc
A couple years ago
Touche, touche
One crazy night and we're still paying the consequences
For it
And speaking of crazy nights
I'm literally like
Trying to figure out where my kids are at
Because I know they're at a birthday party but they were supposed to be home already
This is crazy over here
As we're talking on another device
I'm getting a call from my daughter letting me know
That there's being cake served over at a friend's house
For a birthday party
And you're not there?
Wow
Don't they know we have a matrix server issue
Well they're just trying to make you feel better
Well they weren't offering cake
Oh I see, I got it all wrong
I don't know exactly what went wrong but I guess the mom went out
9 hours ago to pick up the cake
And just got back now at 10 o'clock at night
And so now they're serving cake
At 10 o'clock at night
My kids are supposed to be asleep
They're supposed to be over there having a sleepover and now they're getting
And of course my daughter thinks this is so great
She's gotta call me to let me know
Dylan wants to get out of bed
And walk over there in the dark
Aww, cake at 10 o'clock at night
I think it's cute that you think people
Sleep at sleepovers
Gosh darn serving cake at 10 o'clock at night
That's just crazy
Save it for the morning
Yeah breakfast cake right?
So we realize okay I gotta go take care of kids stuff
Wes has gotta walk his dogs
Brent's gotta get back to watching Star Trek Discovery
That's the most important one
So really clearly the thing to do
Is for Brent and I to piss off and leave Wes
With all of the work
And so we left the call
Not knowing how things were going to go
Alright well I don't know that we need to hang around
It seems it's gonna keep going on both fronts
For a little while
It is compressing this? I don't know how big it's gonna be compressed
But
Well I guess we could
I guess
I guess we could leave it as a cliffhanger for Brent and I
And then you could tell us
Oh true
Yeah you have to set up and then
Should I close my Matrix client then?
Oh that's right
Yeah I guess you'll see
We'll know if it's online
But we won't necessarily know if it's on its own server
Or if it's on
The hosted thing
Or how late Wes stayed out
I know a little bit because I increased the disk size
For the Linode
Bless you
And then we upgraded it for our Matrix server
Mostly because we're still figuring out how to optimize it
And then we're planning to shrink it back down
When we upgraded
An additional amount of storage
Was allocated to us
That we could actually resize our disk to
That we never took advantage of
When we upgraded the RAM and the CPU cores
And we didn't realize that at first because
In the previous setup we were using all of the
Fast disk we had available to us
Yeah and so when that part clicked
It was like oh man
I need to bring the database
Get the database back online
And then that's where I
That's all I know
So what happened after we resized the disk?
And what did you do to get the server back online?
I mean not much really
At that point we just had to bring the database
We just kind of had to start things up again
We had thought about much more
Dramatic migration plans
But once we realized that we just had more
Fast disk right there
Locally
That's just how it came to us so we just sort of
Resized that file system on the now
Much bigger partition and
Spun things back up. That was one thing you did have to do
After we did the resize in the Linux dashboard
You have to go in and resize the file system but
I was actually giving you an opportunity to mention
That you can run that tool
And we were actually able to get the database down
About 150 gigs in size
After running that. I think there's more we could
Do. Oh definitely yeah yeah
And we're in a better position now. We've actually been planning
Sort of a little matrix
Sprint to shore up some of the matrix stuff that's been on our
Bucket list. We just weren't planning it for
This week. You and I was
It the day before two days before we're just
Like yeah we better get that matrix sprint scheduled
We really got to get some of that taken care of and
Then like the next day this happened
In a part it's like every time something
Like this happens we learn there's a new set
Of tooling that we can take advantage of
And I think our matrix
Instance is the size where it's not
It's not considered like a huge instance
So there are people just
Ahead of us that are discovering these
Problems and creating solutions
Like this rust tool or like the synapse
Admin interface or you know
Trying out workers at scale
And then our instance being a little
Bit smaller we kind of we eventually
Get to these problems after they have
And so we're taking advantage of
All of the upstream work that's being done to solve
These problems before we hit them
And then when we hit them there's almost
Always a tool available now like that's been
The upshot or there's almost always a solution
Or legitimately like twice in a row
They've just added
That feature or just changed that
Default in the synapse server like a release
Or two before we needed it yeah
Really that keeps happening the docs
Have also gotten a lot better for like the administration
Side of running a synapse server so
It's really nice to see I think that's one of
The benefits of all the pain that we do put
Ourselves through the benefits we get to watch
That growth and how the community is developed
And I think you know each time we kind of dive back
In like this time we you know we know
Way more about sort of the internals of
The database schemas and how that's working
And so I think we have more confidence in that side of things
Even if you know it took a late night
Another thing about it is it's a bit of practicing
What we preach like I really have been on this
Whole decentralization I think
Is key for free software long term
Matrix is part of that
And there are upsides and downsides to decentralization
And choosing to self host
And it would be unfair
For us to come on here and only ever
Represent the good things and never
Represent the bad things and
If anything I think maybe we could represent
Some of the better things probably
A little more often because one of the reasons
We're willing to go through this is there's a really great
Community on there and there's a growing
Network effect with other free software projects
And communities that are happening all the time
And it's getting better and you know the various
Clients are getting better over time as well
And so in one sense it's quite impressive what
You know what they've built there and all the capabilities
Especially compared to other platforms like
It's getting much closer. I have
A final question for you both. We
We seem to kind of dive into the Matrix server
Either by choice or not every
What was it? Every two months
Or so? Yeah it was right before Raleigh
So it's been a bit. Do you have any predictions
On what will happen in the next two months
And what will bring us to doing another
Late night session? Well maybe
Migrating out of Fremont perhaps. Maybe
I know something else we want to do is we want to
Get the Synapse admin backend up and running
I don't think that will cause an outage other than
Us restarting services and stuff
I know that's next. Some more database optimizations
Are next. We definitely have some more
Performance gains to get. It's a lot better
But there's clearly more work to be done
I think that's sort of
Going to be the target of the next sprint and now that we have
Some disk space and we've reduced the size of the database
We can focus more on maybe
Some of the performance side of things and less
On the keeping things running side of things
Which would be nice. Also shout out
You know we've been getting various tips both on the Matrix
Server itself but then also very from boosts
And feedback from audience members who
Have way more experience and understanding
Of Matrix and Synapse than we do and that is always
Super helpful. Yeah we get tips in and that is
Super great. Thank you everybody.
Bitwarden.com
Slash Linux. Get started with a free
Trial at Bitwarden.com slash
Linux. A team, an enterprise
Or an individual. It's Bitwarden.com
Slash Linux. This is
The easiest way to store and share and sync
Sensitive data.
Bitwarden is open source and trusted by millions
Of individuals, teams and organizations.
It's a tool you've got
To have. And a good password manager
That's great but Bitwarden is more
Than that. It's really a secrets manager.
It'll help generate user names.
It'll store one time authorization tokens
For two factor.
And of course if you're in the enterprise it's fully
Customizable. You can turn features on
And off using enterprise policies
To adapt it to your business needs.
And if you're an individual user like me who
Likes to know there's a
Self hosted option as well.
Well Bitwarden contributes upstream
To the Vaultwarden project to help make
Sure they stick around and help that community
Thrive. And they've got incredible
Support in their apps for just all kinds of great
Power user features and
User friendly features for people
That are just learning how to use software like this.
Some of my favorites are
Like the fast user account switching.
It's so easy now to switch between maybe
Like a personal account or
Your business account or maybe you have an account for
An open source project you're working with.
When you're auto filling now
It'll just let you switch between
User accounts. And on iOS
The face ID integration
Is killer. It's like
You're living in the future. It just scans
Your face opens up the password database gets the
Right password auto fills it.
The reason why I think that's super critical
Is it means maybe I signed up on a website
Or maybe I signed up using the app. But I can take
That sensitive data across
My desktop and my mobile
And I can use complex
Rich passwords on mobile and
Stay safe using Bitwarden.
And with the username generator too now I'm using a unique
Username at every site and service
I sign up for. I should have always been doing that.
Bitwarden's always thinking of that
Kind of stuff. That's their job.
So go try it out.
It's easy to get started. Visit Bitwarden.com
Slash Linux. Try it for yourself or
Your business. Maybe you know someone
A friend, a family, a colleague
That could use a little bit of help in this
Department. Send them over there.
Nudge them in the right direction.
Bitwarden.com slash
Linux.
We got some amazing
Feedback again this week. Thank you everyone. We did get
A few songs in
For our pump up song.
What would you call that?
We're trying to find a great pump up song.
Our pre pre show starter song.
It's true.
You can hear those if you're a
Member and you get the extra long feed
Or on PeerTube. You can check it out there. It's a lot of fun.
Pre show mantra maybe?
Hey! I like that.
And so thank you Justin and Andrew
And Jeff sent one in as well.
Keep them coming. I think we'll
We'll find one in time. Right guys?
I think. Yeah I think
So. That implies there's a dead
Loan. Which I'm not sure we have.
I don't want to put like a time on this. I feel like a song
Commitment is a big commitment. It's a long term
Relationship and I don't want you to rush things.
It might be the most important relationship any of us have.
It might be. Well Levi.
Yeah.
But we also got other feedback which
Has been really great. And I think Wes
This one's right up your alley.
Well maybe both of us since we've been talking about it.
Casey wrote in and says
I heard on office hours
That Wes was giving Brent some
Python tips. A specific
Example Brent gave was a Python REPL.
I know Wes does some Clojure
Which has one of the best REPL
Experiences. So if he's recommending
A REPL for Python that's something I want to
Know about. As much as
I wish I could write Clojure all day
Python still pays more of the bills.
Care to spill the beans on this
REPL recommendation?
Yeah. Okay. I think a REPL
Is just super handy because it
Recreates this feeling of being really
Connected immediately with the computer. It's much
Like using a command prompt. Right? Like
Bash. It's like having a conversation with the machine
Where you sort of you can you can touch the data
Structures. You can feel them right there. You don't have to construct
An artificial test environment or something.
Not that that's bad but it's just I think when you're
Especially when you're exploring a new API or you're trying
To learn and you know you don't have a lot of previous
Understanding on how a new mechanism works
Or something. It's just it's a great way to learn.
Totally true Casey that
Clojure has an amazing REPL experience. Python
Can't quite compete for a lot of reasons.
One of them being sort of the culture
Isn't there as much. Especially now with
Type hinting and stuff. There's been more focus
On the static analysis side of things
Which don't get me wrong it's also great and wonderful and
There's a lot of good tools around that now.
But there's less interest in
Building APIs that are REPL friendly necessarily.
That said B Python is
A nice one. It doesn't have as many
Fancy features but it's got great tab complete
And a nice little pop up menu.
So it's friendly to interact with and then
IPython or
Jupyter notebooks as well. It can be one thing but if you just
Want it in like a terminal IPython works great.
They've also got a auto reload
Extension which is one way to get a decent REPL
Experience anytime you input
A new expression or statement on the command line
It'll load reload all the
Stuff that you've imported. I also
Have rigged up with an
Async file watching library
To kind of do the same thing and just do like a hot
Reload anytime I rewrite
Any of the files on my disk.
It's not perfect but it works pretty well and then if you
Kind of design things stay
Away from classes and objects if you can and just have
Sort of functions and pass
In all of your state explicitly so
That you don't have to like rebuild your classes you
Just have some dictionaries and other things like that data
Classes etc. That makes things
A little bit better in the REPL environment.
This is super super fascinating.
Wes I got to say thank you for
Having long late night
Conversations with me about all of this stuff.
If someone was just learning
Python would you recommend just diving
Into this right away or is this more of an experts tool?
I mean it could certainly be both
But yeah I think
Having a REPL available you can just use the built
In Python one but if you use something like
IPython you get just a lot more of a friendly environment
With things like auto complete and tab complete and
Read line support and
Yeah it can be a way to just sort of type in stuff you see
From tutorials without having to set up a complicated
Environment to get it all to run.
I mean you will need to figure that out too and you'll want to figure out how to get
A test runner going and all those things but
Just be able to type IPython
On the command line and start playing is super nice
And also shout out here
Gigatexel in the IRC room mentions
PT Python which is another great choice.
And of course I'm sure the next thing Gigatexel
Was going to mention that coder.show
For Coderadio where we talk about Python quite a bit.
Casey mentions too yeah
Jupiter notebooks are a fantastic way because
They're quite visual and interactive
And there's plenty of places to go use
Those for free online so
Yeah check out Jupiter notebooks if you haven't.
And of course we're not going to get out of the feedback section
Without a little discussion about Merkle trees.
Of course seems like a popular
Topic around here these days.
Joe wrote in was great
To hear you talk about Merkle trees on the last
Linux Unplugged. They're my favorite most
Underrated data structure.
They're incredibly simple to implement since
It's basically just a big key value store
And they're great for syncing because
You can just rsync the key value stores around
And then atomically update a few
References or branches.
I once also wrote a minimal
Implementation of git in about
300 lines of code which he links
To. That sounds fascinating.
Awesome.
And now
It is time for the boost.
Well our first boost of the day
Is from Purple Hummingbird
5 days ago with
2222 sets.
I'm a duck. D-U-K Duck.
Loaded with talent.
Hey guys I just got my steam deck.
Sending you a row of ducks for your coverage
So far. Is there a gadget or new tech
Each of you are looking forward to?
Thanks for the show. Hmm I bet this is a hard
Question for you to answer. You're not really
You don't covet much in terms of tech.
You're very practical when it comes to this stuff.
I'm really curious to see what like the next generation
Framework stuff. Oh yeah
The framework laptop. Yes.
It's a little nebulous but that's on my
Radar. I think that would be a really good work machine
For you. Right.
What about you Brent? You got a gadget or a device?
Maybe the dev one?
The new dev one waiting for you?
Oh yeah I almost forgot about that.
Apparently it's being
Held hot sausage somewhere. I gotta figure that out.
I'm gonna get to that soon I'm sure. But yeah
I'm sure. You'll enjoy that.
I think almost immediately on my list is actually
Some hardware that Jeff sent me.
Thank you very much again. He sent me some
Equipment to boost my local
Wireless network here. From one building
To another. And I
It's been a great cat pillow so far.
I hesitate to remove it from that
Use but I'm
Looking forward to setting it up real soon and
Jumping into iperf and giving it
A bunch of testing and seeing how
Optimized I can get it. Yeah I am
Looking forward to hearing how that goes too.
Purple I
I just got my confirmation
And I said yes to the
Steam Deck. So like I've done the
Payment thing now. I got
My your things coming soon email.
So I think I'm gonna answer Steam Deck
Because I had a realization last
Week even I was kind of on
The fence about oh
Do I really want one anymore?
You know maybe I'd rather have a dev one
But I realized in my
Situation in the RV
Having a portable gaming
Device is freaking perfect
Because I sometimes need to be up front or sometimes I need
To be in the back or sometimes I want to be outside
A console hasn't
Served me super well because of that
And I just realized that that's exactly
What I've been needing and I've been wanting to game at
Home in the evenings but
It just hasn't worked out because maybe like that's the evening
I have my ThinkPad and that just has an Intel graphics
Card in it or whatever and you know so I've never
Gotten around to it I think I will now
I'm actually pretty excited about the Steam Deck coming in
And of course I'll share my thoughts and
What nots on it when I
Have a chance to look at it and play around
With it for a bit. Gene Bean wrote in
Three days ago with a thousand sats thank you
Very much. Boost
They wrote don't forget the newer
Raspberry Pi imaging tool will also
Let you set all of your Wi-Fi info
And user info on the GUI
So Wes I think that's
A little shout out to your adventures
There last week. Yeah hey that does
Sound handy. Yeah that is actually
Something that I forget because I don't use it
Very often but when you're trying to get people introduced
To the Raspberry Pi the Raspberry Pi
Imaging tool is very legitimate
Try it probably will do
What they need. Don't do it the hard way like I do
For some reason. Quantum
Boosted in with 500 sats
And I wanted to
Read this because well
First of all I think it's important this gets
Talked about. Second of all
I think there's a little bit of shenanigans going on here
They write when trying to order the dev
One machine for my dev team
Last week we were told by HP that
The dev one is not for quote professional developers
And available only in their consumer
Division. We were also told by
HP they have no plan to offer a similar experience
For professionals in their
Commercial line. Why do you
Think they would make a developer laptop and then not
Offer to developers where they work. First
Of all that does sound really silly and
Anybody who's ever worked in a medium to large
Company can probably already do the math
In their head and go oh yeah
Yeah you got the enterprise sales team and this
Has been marked as a consumer laptop
So those two shall not pass right like
You already know where this is going
What's weird and it's silly right
Maybe HP should take care of that
So that's why I wanted to read the boost but what's
Interesting about Quantum's boost here
Is this exact
Message for Betam was sent to Coda Radio
Maybe three weeks ago only I note
That they don't say three weeks ago in this boost they
Say last week this email was
Also sent into Destination Linux
And now it has been boosted into us
All verbatim somebody
Has a bit of a mission
Out there to try to
Take things down a
Notch not
Necessarily an invalid point
But just saying that I've noticed this
Go around and I want the listeners to be
Aware somebody is trying
To manipulate an emotional reaction from
People on this subject should
They fix it yeah HP should probably fix
That is it surprising that there's
Divisions between enterprise sales business
Sales and consumer sales no
Not at all
Welcome to corporate America
I think what is surprising to me
In a way is that system 76
They really pride themselves
On on on building all of their stuff
For professional developers
And so it's kind of
Odd to me that this happened I hope it's not
Happening more often but
Maybe they got a fix for it it
Seems like a great laptop I haven't touched it yet
You guys would definitely know
But would you would you say it's
Ready for the kind of quote unquote
Professional developers Chris
I mean I could see maybe
HP only views enterprise sales
As maybe laptops that have
Like the HP pro management stuff in it
I mean there's probably some sort of division
Where they check yes this is an
Enterprise box or not but yeah right it's
Got to be more like that or the how the support contracts
Work out or how they you know they get you parts
Or whatever it's not it's not about the actual experience
Of the laptop in the hands of the developer and
Also I will point out
It's it's also
It's a commentary on the company
That this person supposedly works for that they
Are so inconceivably inflexible
That they can't come up with another way to order these
Laptops like that stuff's also
Very typical for companies but so
Annoying because you know like the finance guy
Could put it on the credit card or maybe they you
Know like there's a way they can
Fix this and they could order these laptops
As you know anyone
Else can but their company
Is also super inflexible apparently
Was this just a I called my rep
He looked in his catalog it wasn't there sorry
Sorry if we can't do the PO process we can't
Order the machine right and meanwhile they're angry HP
Is like sorry this isn't a consumer machine we can't
Sell it to business it's like both companies
Are being typical companies
And it's really silly
I just want to give you money for your laptop
Right and it's like this is one of the things I really appreciate
About being a small business is this just you go to the website
And you order the laptop it's not really a big
Deal
Another boost from DL
0 7 0 2 days ago
10,000 sets
Boost just wanted to
Say hi from Australia and
Thanks for all your hard work you chose to give me
Many ideas to try and further my Linux
Knowledge hey that's great
Thanks for the boost and that's exactly what we're going
And I love the check in from Australia and
It really is great because also
Lightning is a global network
Sats are
Sats here in Washington and there in Australia
A sat is a sat yeah once you like
Get the onboarding stuff it doesn't matter where you are
Right the internet has needed its own native
Money and it's just really cool so thank you
An Australian boost it's great
Exception boosted
In as well two days ago with one two three
Seven sets that must
Mean that must mean something
You got me with all this next
Stuff looking for a spare laptop
To play around kind of remind
You of the arch challenge from forever ago oh
Yeah it does
Little bit or gosh that weird gentoo experiment
Where we had that long tail of like
Well all right I'll give it a go okay I'll give it
A go talking about it for so long now I
Guess I have to and to be fair we are
Trying to like dial it down because we know
Not everybody cares about Nix but we
Are really it's probably the most excited I've
Been about Linux in a few years
Right it's really very impressive stuff
And what's also so fun about it
Is it's a major rethinking
Of the way a distro works so it's
Like a it's like you got to be willing to go for a big
Shift right yeah that's just it it's like a whole
New paradigm in some ways but if you're willing to
And you've got nothing really on the line so why not try like
It has been my last thing then I'll stop
Because I could just go on and on I have
Been surprised how great it has been
On my ThinkPad I thought when we started
This thing okay this is great
For servers but I'm never going to want to have
A prescribed laptop like this
No man like it's now
Made me rethink like how I want to do the studio systems
Because I want them rock solid right
So one of the great things I love about using
Nix as a workstation or perhaps
Studio equipment is the
Updates all have to like pass
And everything has to be good before it gets applied
So you do a build
And it checks everything and then you make sure
There's no like weird conflicts
Or any crazy config changes
And if something like you know your bootloader breaks
Or something like that it airs out
And you don't switch to a broken
System you only switch to
That new updated system after
It's passed all the tests
And then you reboot into this new clean
Environment and it's just it's
So solid it's so solid for a
Workstation or for a production system
I loves it so much yeah because
We got another boost in here
This is something of a special boost though
It's from su cd two days
Ago twenty nine thousand
Two hundred and eighty seven
That's our baller boost
That's a baller in our parts
Yeah especially because this was a manual
Boost sent via the blockchain and then a
Message to you via matrix yeah
Hello from Portland I've been
Listening to Jupiter broadcasting for about
Ten years well you were asking for a Portland
Check-in and we've got one yeah
All right well there's one
Now we need to know if there are more
The Portland signal is up y'all
But as you check out the West
Coast crew we do have a West Coast
Crew matrix room now jump in there
And maybe give us some hot tips
On where we should take things we have a couple of
Thank you boost to get into or at least one
Five hundred stats from 412
Linux wishing Brent safe travels Brent's going
To be traveling to Alex's house
In the near future and then eventually
At some point he'll be making
The trek to the studio either by
Car train or something we don't
Know yet but we have Brent's
Node now online he has
Participating in the split
For the next we were doing it for the
Month of July so far I guess three more
Episodes we're gonna do a 50-50
Split of the boosts with
Brent so that way we can build up
A little bit of a fuel travel fund
So when he's done at Alex's he's gonna come
Here he's gonna he's gonna do it he's gonna
Do it he's threatening me no we'll just guilt
You into it'll be real easy you know can we use some of that
Fun to like get a tracker we can put on them to verify
He's oh that's a great idea it's
Built into the dev one I think
But really you know what it was it was fun setting
All that up that node in the community opening up
Channels it's just yeah you were impressed
Too by how much liquidity
Came in on the node
In a very very short amount of time
I can you speak a little bit more to that well
About 400,000 stats of it came from
Me so a lot of that liquidity was me
Sending you some stats but then
Yeah we definitely had some community community members
Step up and open up channels and so the way it works
And lightning is you have people who
Put some stats on each end of the channel and then you can
Move Bitcoin or sats in between
They're really super quick and that's why it's so
Dang quick and then it only really has to settle
On the blockchain when you close those channels and
So you get super fast lightning payments
And so people open up the channels and it's a peer to peer
Network and
You think about it you just kind of peer with
With who you're gonna be getting boosts from
But necessarily or lightning messages from so like
I appeared that node
With the fountain app and with the podcast
Index and with Jupiter Broadcasting's node
And then if you are a peer with
One of those nodes the clients can find routes
To you it's so much fun
To work with and watch it kind of the network
Discover itself and build out
So it's online and we'll be
Doing the boost splits for a bit to help with the travel fund
For Brentley so we can come to the studio and we can engage
In projects and now prepare
For our September road trip too because I think it'll be getting close
To that oh yeah you know Chris
I have also been keeping helipad
Up so I can watch the boos come in as they
People send them in that is so fun
You've been talking about
How that like
Basically drives your
Your mood all day and
Just pumps it up whenever you need it and
I gotta totally agree it's really great
It's yeah it's my it's exactly
It's my top off when I'm feeling kind of like
Frustrated I'll be like I'll open up I'll open up
Helipad and it is so great for that
You gotta get on that let's put you in there too
If you'd like to send in a boost
Go go just go get a new podcast app
Go do it why not try it out for a little bit
I've been using fountain pod
Versus great as well cast-o-matic if you're on
IOS and if you don't want to switch podcast
Apps breeze b-r-e-e-z
Dot technology or boost
CLI you can boost from the command line
They're all listed new podcast apps dot com
Hey you know looks like the most recent antenna
Pod update added podcasting
2.0 chapter support so yeah that's
Come on along nicely as well that's
That's a number now that's a several
Several pack I don't know how many but I think
It's a handful of the podcasting 2.0 features
That have been added to antenna pod now it's
Really great to see that because we've got about a 30
Percent audience share with antenna
Pod probably one of the more popular ones
And it's a it's a great client and
You can combo that with breeze
So you can keep using antenna pod
And then you can use breeze to send the boost in
And then there are some patches out there
Already to kind of integrate those two apps
It's not done yet
I also want to say we did
Get a postcard in the mailbag this
Week mentioning that
Hey we shouldn't forget about those
Who are members we talk
About boost a heck of a lot and
Sometimes we forget to thank the members so
I just want to say to all the members
Thank you for continuing to support us
I know you guys are getting tons of benefits over
There too so I just want to say
Thank you thank you for
Being a friend
Yeah unplugged core dot com
You get an ad free version you get the live stream
Hey what do you say we do a little pick skis
This is fun what did you find Wes
Well you know as we were having some disk
Space problems you need some
Disk space tools sometimes
And see do is an old favor of mine that
I use all the time but I thought
We love rust picks what else was
Out there right surely someone's made some of this stuff
In rust and oh yeah
Dua dash CLI
Disk usage analyzer
As a tool to conveniently
Learn about the usage of disk space of a given
Directory and yes it's parallel by default
And will max out your SSD
Awesome it's also got that nice little
Support to optionally just delete right from
That interface which I like about and see do as well
Oh that is super
Handy but you know what there's
A few more links in there and we have a very
Special bonus pick that Brent threw in
Yeah this is maybe a really
Nerdy pick but from
The brunch that I did with
Tim he
A long time ago
Wrote a framework
That has been open source for a long time
Now and it's a flight
Software and embedded systems
Framework called F prime
And it's directly straight from
NASA and is
Available to anybody it even runs on
The Raspberry Pi they have it
They have it tested on the Raspberry Pi
Their nightly build is
Is piped into a Raspberry Pi so they can
Test it every night it's really it's super
Fascinating so it's so great
Okay what what if we built
A really janky
Drone I mean right like
Like a Linux unblocked it won't work very well
Probably crash immediately but
I mean I'm down can we just
Absorb for like a hot
Second here this thing is a
Linux copter right
And then on top of that the framework
It's using to be semi-autonomous is
Also open source
And we're about
To go down and meet the folks that put
All this together and we're going to
Get a tour that's all about
To happen right now how great
Is that my head is going to explode it's so neat
Sony it's worth even if you're never going to
Use it go check it out we'll have a link in the show notes right
Because it's pretty cool
Yeah I know Tim's a fan of the show
He's probably listening so thank you Tim for all that wonderful
Insight and it's actually his brother
That got him hooked
On to listening to Linux unplugged so
Thank you to Tim's brother too
We owe his brother a serious couple of beers
Right it's a reminder too of just
The power of word of mouth it's very true that's
What I really that's that is what makes
Podcasts grow it's not you know
It's not really like
Practical for somebody to invest an hour
Of their life into something that
Nobody's recommended to them it just doesn't happen
Very often so it's a great example and then the
Connections that that creates right
The second order effects of your recommendations
You never know where it's going to go
It helps that we just have a really badass audience
That's exactly it that's exactly it
So let's wrap it up
But I am so excited
About this West Coast meetup I
Have missed you guys I love doing these meetups
It really recharges us it's a great opportunity
To connect with the audience to get a sense of what people
Out there are thinking about that isn't from the social
Media bubble
It's just so intensely valuable for
Us in terms of just like
Getting signal from the audience and it really
Is yeah getting an idea of what's on people's minds
And getting a really good picture
I'm just getting a different slice and
Yeah verse info from y'all
So right now we have
The matrix room link for that's in the show notes
Bit.ly slash
West Coast crew and
We will then begin
To build out the meetup page as we start
To get signal from the audience and we start to get
An idea of where we're going to go and we'll start talking
About that in office hours as well so
It's a lot there but it's
Going to be so much fun and of course we're
Extremely grateful to Linode to helping make
All of this road trip stuff possible
It's not like this is a cheap time
To do a road trip on the West Coast
In fact you could not figure
Out of more expensive time to do a road
Trip on the West Coast like we should be like
Taking a road trip to like Central America
To the plane because it's a lot
Cheaper to drive but
You know we just did an East Coast meetup
We just did a Denver meetup
We have a London meetup coming up in just a few
Weeks it just seems like it's time
To revisit the West Coast
And what an opportunity to go to JPL
So we're going to do it
So we'd love to hear from you
Send us in a boost or go to linuxunplug.com
Slash contact and then don't forget
We do this show live that's like
The high bandwidth way to interact
See you next week same bad time
Same bad station
Every single Sunday noon pacific
3pm eastern over at
Jupiter.tube that's the pure tube instance
We stream on there's no python bot
Taking us down usually it's just
Me and if you want an audio
Only version jplive.fm
And of course linuxunplug.com
Slash subscribe for the fully edited
Fully produced version because
We want you to get it every single week and Drew just does
A fantastic job on the show that's
Linuxunplug.com slash subscribe for that and links
To everything we talked about today
Well that's at linuxunplug.com slash
466 we try to make sure that's just
Full of goodies for you let's go take a look
At that thanks so much for joining us on this
Week's episode of the unplugged program
See you right back here next Sunday
You know Chris you made me so happy just there because it's taken six months and I've been pretty quiet about this but you're starting to say next Sunday the way you used to say next Tuesday and I have been waiting for that for so long you know
I understand it had to like settle in
For a bit but I'm
Encouraging it yeah it had to be its
Own thing you mourn the loss
And yeah right too early I
Loved saying see you next Tuesday that
Was the highlight of the end of the show
For me right there right and you
Know we switched to some days and it just didn't feel
The same I felt like I had to give it time before I moved
On and started you know
Building relationships with new
Ways of ending the show but I felt like that
Was one of our better endings you know
Mostly also you notice
I switched to just I'm just gonna start mentioning the
Jupiter tube in fact I think maybe
At some point we should just redirect jblive.tv
To Jupiter tube
I know that's crazy but we got big
Things in the works we talked
To Alex Gates the podcasting to do
Consulting consultant on office
Hours this last week and
Chatted with how he's modifying
PeerTube to make it work with podcasting
To those standards but also to make it work
With more live streaming options build a few
Things that are just really small things that are missing
Like in the RSS XML file
And whatnot to make it like totally
Usable for podcasters and it's
All just it's all coming
Together it's so freaking exciting
There's like work being done by
Dozens of different community members
Adding these different features
At different areas of the podcasting stack
And it's really impressive to see it all kind of
Come together and so that was
That's why I reached out to Alex is like will you come on
So we can just geek out about this because I'm back
Into PeerTube again and I know you're making these changes
And I wanted to find out is he planning
To upstream them and all that stuff yeah
It's a good interview there was a well thank you
Thank you I thought
Brent really made it though it was it was a good Brent
Episode oh well on average
Yeah well thanks I mean
It takes two doesn't it well
At least a tango it's been neat seeing
PeerTube you know developing
To like looks like there was a release just 12 days
Ago oh oh
Well it's time to upgrade that yeah
We should also there's some important upgrade notes
I note here so let's uh well it's not even
Let's just skip that Wes what
Could go wrong is one of the
Upgrades like maybe the view counts I know
I know Chris you've had some
Yeah I can't don't get his hopes
I try not to grouse about that but it is
Slightly annoying that the view counts aren't accurate
Because it's like under representing
The views and the other thing that's kind of
Annoying is like when you drop when you stop
Live streaming it loses
Those numbers too and then you start all over
And like but I but I
Okay but you know then you're not
Supposed to care right because there's no algorithm
Right it doesn't really matter
We don't even have comments it's true
So we don't put those numbers anywhere
The whole thing is supposed to be a practice in me
Not caring right so I try not to
But as like as a
But as a content creator who
Wants a signal on what's working and not
Working it would also be nice if
It was accurate that's all yeah that's fair
Can I ask you gentlemen since
It's kind of on point for this episode how
Is the PeerTube server doing do we know
Is it performing fine is it
Oh yeah yeah because
We're doing the so right now we're doing the minimum
Viable PeerTube where we're just using it for
Our live stream archive and we're not like
Creating channels for every show and
Uploading the edited versions and we're not
Having community members contribute videos
It is a really solid little rock
Solid instance the only thing we got to do is make sure
That we got the storage back end all tied up
But that's pretty quick change
Yeah we should do that yeah well I'm sure once it runs
Out of disk space we will obviously
It'll be an unplanned sprint
That's how we do it