You know, well, hmm, okay.
You sound unsure, Chris.
Don't tell those jerks over at the Linux Action Show,
but I think I'm gonna steal one of their Runs Linux.
Let's spot the Runs Linux.
Are you ready, Runs?
Unset in D minus five minutes.
To do something as ambitious as making a car drive itself,
you need lots of testing and lots of places
so that you can cover all the scenarios
you might ever expect to see.
All right, so a couple of interesting things about this.
You notice there's not a whole bunch of cameras
hanging off this car here.
And, you know, one of the things I have honestly wondered,
and I know they use LiDAR to some extent,
but how well do the Google self-driving cars
work in the dark with no lights?
I've wondered about that.
And, you know, so far, all of these self-driving cars
seem to run Linux, but I bet we spot some in this one.
It's my kind of bet.
NVG check.
So they're putting on helmets with cameras.
Fusion Niner One Two, prepare to go dark.
They're covering the steering dash column stuff with a...
Fusion Niner One Two, are all personnel in place?
Some sort of blackout.
This is Gold Leader, I'm in position.
Okay, you ready, Wes?
Fusion Niner One Two, could we get a systems check, please?
These guys.
LiDAR is go.
IMU is go.
Radar is go.
Camera is go.
All systems are functioning.
We are ready to go at once.
Oh, look at that.
Wow, wow, we are getting a lot of stuff here.
So they're using the system sentry log message interface.
Don't reckon that's probably something to them.
But over here, I'm noticing Wireshark over here.
MBV player, there's Java, there's hardware info,
VLC, screen capture program.
They have a update manager running in the background.
Wow, look at all that stuff on that Linux box.
They're just like you, they do updates
right before they have to do something.
Yeah, they totally are, aren't they?
All right, guys, we're gonna go.
Now watch this.
We are autonomous.
They're using a camera that captures the LiDAR lasers.
That's awesome.
Or whatever, I guess it's not lasers or whatever.
It's whatever, oh no, I guess it would be.
But look at that, look how it blankets the area,
surveying the ground as they say.
It's an odd feeling to be looking at the viewer
and seeing exactly what I expected.
But as soon as I looked out the window,
all I saw was blackness.
Through the S's again, everything is stable.
That was Linux again there.
It's breaking into the hairpin.
And accelerating out of the corner.
Pull back in here, complete the mission,
and then we'll restart again just to do it on the full lap.
It's going good.
Car is functioning just as it should.
Car is driving by itself in the middle of the night.
You know, I have yet to see one of these
that isn't powered by Linux.
And isn't that something, Wes?
Yeah, that is something.
Because this is going to be a huge deal.
This is going to change our culture forever.
This is how they should have made the, what is it, Kinect.
Because Kinect shows a bunch of dots in infrared
and maps the depth perception throughout the room.
This is doing it in a 3D area.
This is how Kinect should have been.
And they're using Linux end to end.
They're using Linux in the computer in the car.
They're using Linux for the reviewing of the data.
And then when they were playing back the 3D map
of the thing driving, they're using Linux.
End to end, using Linux to create something
that's going to fundamentally change the world.
And probably kill the podcasting audience
because people won't be sitting in traffic anymore.
Dang it.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 140 for April 12th, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that didn't force Wes to reload his laptop this week.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hey there, Wes.
I think this is like the first week in like five episodes.
I think so.
I'm still running apricity.
How's it going over there?
Not bad.
Nice.
It's like you get to just enjoy it for a little while.
Maybe install some things I forget from the episode.
I bet we'll break it next week.
There's going to be something we'll have to try out.
But this week we have a huge show.
We have so much stuff to get into.
We have an interesting follow up from something
that happened about 106 weeks ago in Unplugged history.
We'll get to that coming up a little bit in the show.
I went and installed myself a tracker
so I could track myself as I move about the world.
Not on Google, in my own cloud.
Something I wanted to use for Lady Joops
as we take the rover over to pick up Mr. Ham radio.
So I installed the open source track car server.
And I'll give you my experiences with setting up
a tracker that uses your smartphone for yourself
or whatever you need.
For me, it's so you guys can follow me
because why not be creepy.
Also, we have some really big updates
for some pretty important projects
that we've been following.
Some interesting Scuttlebutt and news,
as well as a quick Linux Fest Northwest update
coming up towards the end of the show.
It is a bunch of stuff to get into, Wes.
So we should probably start with my favorite thing.
One of my, I think, one of my favorite beers
probably in the last couple of weeks, maybe.
Yeah, I mean you've been bringing
some really good local brews.
Another brewed in Seattle beer.
Now this one stands out because it's gluten-free.
That's right, no gluten here.
Which you didn't even realize.
And also, on the bottle they want you
to transcend your limits.
That stands out.
Do you do that every week here?
Yeah, we do, we do.
So it's Ghost Fish Brewing Company we're drinking this week
and maybe some of you in our virtual log will be as well.
And how do you suppose, I was gonna say,
how do you suppose, Wes,
but I was gonna say, watchstander.
I believe so, watchstander stout.
Yeah, I like that, the watchstander stout.
We got a pint here, we'll be drinking on the show.
An additional six fluid ounces after that one pint,
six fluid ounces.
Oh, you're right, I didn't even see that.
I had my thumb right there.
So thanks, Wes, these are some nice brewskis.
I'm glad you enjoy it.
We'll be enjoying them.
So let's get into some of the updates for the week.
Let's bring in our virtual log first.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello, hello, hello, hello, hello.
It is good to see all of you, or at least, well, hear you.
One of the stories that people seem to be kind of jacked up
about today is, well, it's a Valve story.
We're gonna do a little Valve update right here
at the top of the show.
An open source driver, an open source contender has emerged,
at least early development has, for the Steam Controller.
You might not have realized this,
but to get the actual full Steam Controller driver
on your rig, on your Linux rig,
you had to have Steam installed.
You had to have, you had to have all the Steam installed.
Yeah, and so-
It's not very Linux-y.
The final purpose is to have a custom mapping ability
created for this controller, also some others.
The initial target is for GNU slash Linux,
but there are welcoming contributors to port it to.
Ox, what is this, Ox 10?
No, Os 10, Windows, BSD, or even perhaps Android.
Whoa.
Android, I think, would be really awesome to have.
Yeah. Yeah.
So there you go.
You have to check it out.
It's on GitHub right now if you want it,
but it will mess up your current driver if you do load it.
What do you think, Wes?
Is this important?
Rodden Corp seems to think so.
Why do you, what do you think?
Yeah, I mean, it seems like good hardware.
We already enjoy good support for things
like the Xbox 360 controller.
I'm sure people want to use this with weird niche games
or games that really have no place on Steam
or don't support Steam,
or for gamers that just don't want to have anything
to do with Steam, but enjoy the hardware.
Yeah, I could definitely see it also as a pretty cool,
a pretty cool, like, just as an example,
something we were talking about before the show,
is if you just had a standard open source driver,
then maybe you could integrate it
with other kinds of open source projects,
and all of a sudden you could have
a really cool controller for those.
Who knows what those could be?
Maybe it could be something to brew beer.
Speaking of the Valve,
we talked about this itch app store on Linux Action Show.
That's right.
Yeah, it's already been pulled.
They pulled it. Of course.
So quick update on that.
Yeah, Valve has pulled the itch or itch.io desktop app.
It was in violation of their terms and service.
So there's a quick one there,
and they were clear about what categories they do allow in,
and your own frickin' app store is not one of them.
So sorry, guys, sorry about that.
Now, that was sort of just a real quick update.
That ends our Valve section of the show.
And now it brings our Richard Stallman section of the show.
I've never installed GNU slash Linux.
Into the focus. Your favorite.
Yeah, it is.
So Richard Stallman has spoken out about
Popey's attempt to get ZFS working on Linux.
And now, as we all know,
Popey is personally involved in getting ZFS
to run on Ubuntu 16.04,
and is personally responsible for the legal fights
that will be, I mean, we all know this.
It's obvious.
He's the one loading the kernel engine.
He might downplay it.
But remember, if he tries to downplay it, Wes,
his denial is actually a confirmation.
Absolutely.
On advice of counsel, I decline to answer.
Very well.
So Richard Stallman has spoken out about ZFS,
as Mr. Jude would say, shipping on Ubuntu.
And he said,
the code under GPL incompatible licenses cannot be added,
neither in source nor binary form,
without violating the GPL.
If you distribute modules meant to be linked together
by the user, you have made them into a combined work,
and you must release the entire combined work
under the GNU GPL.
He says it's therefore impossible to release ZFS
alongside the GNU GPL license code,
because ZFS is licensed under the CCDL version one.
And Richard Stallman points out,
and the value of this is negative,
that Oracle could just simply relicense ZFS
under the GPL and solve everybody's problem.
It would make it possible to combine that version
with Linux without violating the license of Linux.
This would be the ideal resolution,
and we urge the copyright holders of ZFS to do this,
is what he said.
That ain't gonna happen ever.
No, no.
No, have you noticed that both the Software Conservancy
and now the Free Software Foundation
are taking this tact of, well, it's not Canonical's fault,
and it's not the GPL's fault,
it's Oracle's fault.
To me, that seems, and I'll ask you, Wimpy,
what you think of that, but that seems ridiculous,
because what you're doing is, hey,
that thing that you made and you own,
I want it so bad that I think you should change it to this.
That seems like a childish argument.
And Oracle didn't make it either.
They acquired it from Sun Microsystems,
and they acquired the license it was under.
So, you know, I'm no fan of Oracle,
quite the opposite in fact,
but they are not at all motivated to change the licensing
of ZFS, unless of course they want to start shipping it
in their, do they call it unbreakable Linux or something?
So the only time the license will change
is if Oracle decide they want to ship it in their own.
And haven't they, no, there was components of D-Trace
that they've shipped in unbreakable.
Oh, okay. Yeah.
Which has sort of put some of this in question,
and it'd be interesting to take that
as a trial balloon and see what happens.
But yeah, to me-
If Oracle relicense it, it will be under some license
that suits them and no one else.
Exactly.
Well, and they're not gonna do something
I wouldn't think, I mean, maybe I'm wrong on this,
but if they relicense ZFS to GPL,
wouldn't that screw over the BSDs?
Well, no, because they can fork it
from the last CDL-licensed version, can't they?
Not ideal though, is it?
Well, no, not ideal.
So they're not gonna do that.
They're not gonna do that.
Well, Oracle will do whatever they see fit
without any regard for the BSD or the Linux community.
Yeah.
OS writer says that this is actually
just a passive aggressive threat against canonical.
I wonder if that's, I wonder if that's true.
You know, they also, Mr. Mogen, even Eben,
just wrote a really long piece on understanding
the Linux Foundation's role in arbitrating these issues,
basically saying it's not their role to do these.
They did a good job of explaining their tax structure.
Right, yeah, exactly.
Yeah, and when I read that, to me it said
that they're gonna make their own decision
and take some sort of action.
These two things are not being talked about
in isolation, right?
Eben is making this blog post.
At the same time, Richard Stallman
is making these statements,
and within a short time after the software conservancy
has made their statements,
all of which are sort of like limp-handedly,
sort of passively aggressively
throwing some dirt on canonical,
but most of them are trying to say,
but it's really Oracle that's really the bad guy
because everybody loves to hate Oracle, I think.
But in this case, I mean, I'm no Oracle fan,
but in this case, they now are the rightful owners of ZFS,
and it seems strange to me that we have the nuts
to just come up and say, well, we want it so much
that you should have to do this thing,
and that's the good guy thing to do.
Well, no, it's not good or bad.
It's their code.
Right, they do have the right to do what that exactly is.
Yeah, and you know what?
They have chosen not to license it that way,
and so we've made the clown shoe file system butter FS,
which is, you know.
At least it sounds like butter.
It pales in comparison.
Well, actually, they made it, oddly enough.
Yeah, that's true, actually.
True, very good point.
Thank you, that is true, but yeah.
But they got the license.
Yeah.
But as soon as they got ZFS, they dumped it, basically.
Yeah, and now the community maintains a lot,
and there's developers from a lot of large companies
that now contribute code to it,
which we've talked about before.
Kitson, you wanted to make a point, though.
Realizer's point's good, too,
that it's different. Yeah.
Do you think that RMS is just pitching a fit
because he wants to have his absolute way
and is unwilling to compromise about the issue,
even though compromise is sometimes the best solution
in the short term?
Hmm.
You know, well, he doesn't compromise.
I will grant you that.
When has he ever?
Yeah.
That's the thing he never has.
But he's.
So it makes sense that he wouldn't hear.
I'm sure he gets tons of email about this,
and so he has to release a statement
so that people stop emailing him about it.
I'm sure he does, too, actually.
But the fact of the matter is it's,
to me, his argument doesn't sound passionate.
It sounds cold and legal.
I mean, he's clearly quoting the confines
of what the GPL code is allowed and not allowed to do,
and he's not talking about crushing our freedom.
He's not calling it the swindle.
You know, he's saying you're just legally
not allowed to do this thing.
I mean, it sounds like a very cognizant argument.
Right, it's not his usual rhetoric.
It's not like he's okay with software piracy, right?
Because that's kind of the same.
Like, it's in a similar boat.
You're doing something against
Oracle's terms of their license.
The difference here is that he's not talking
about free software and non-free software.
He's actually talking about
two free software license bits of code
and incompatibilities between those free software licenses.
So there's really not much room for passion here
because his passionate subject is being addressed.
It's a legal issue now.
That's a good way to put it.
May I ask a question to clarify the issue?
Mm-hmm, yeah.
Okay, Poppy.
Does the kernel module for ZFS
actually contain ZFS code?
Or is the issue having any similar
compatible implementation of ZFS?
Whose issue?
Stallman's and this whole general hubbub about ZFS.
The problem is mixing Cuddle code with GPL code
and linking them together.
Right.
It has nothing to do with implementation.
The kernel module.
Or it does, I guess.
The kernel code doesn't have any non-GPL code in it.
That's not the issue.
The issue is that fully GPLed kernel code
connects to a binary blob.
But as we've discussed before,
boy, we are really getting to the weeds on this.
Do we care that much about this?
Final thoughts.
Poppy, did you have any final thoughts
on that question before we move on?
No, it's one of those technical legal arguments
where you have two people who have differing opinions
and the only way to settle it is for one of them
to take the other one to court, usually.
We need the fun animation for this.
You know, this is no different than any other
legal disagreement.
It's just the fact that it's all very public and out there.
Because we're in this, these are personalities
that we listen to and people align themselves
with one side or the other.
Yeah.
Very well said.
I would like to say, though.
Yeah, go ahead.
If RMS does want his license to stand up legally,
he should try and defend it and make sure
that it's legally enforced where possible.
Why allow this one case, which may be against license,
because then that allows all sorts of other cases
in the future.
If people want to just disagree with the license
and do what they want.
Well, we will continue to watch this.
I don't want to spend too much time because I remember
when I was new to Linux and I heard Linux users
talking about this kind of crap, it just melted my head.
I didn't care at all.
And then later I realized why I should care,
but it took me a while to get there
and so I don't want to scare off people
that are tuning in going,
God, is this what these guys talk about?
So I think we should probably move on,
but it is interesting to follow.
You know what else is a big public disappointment?
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
The HTC Vive and Valve's Steam VR
will not be getting Linux and SteamOS support
at least, well, at least not anytime soon,
which is a total go figure.
I mean, a real bummer too,
but just as a follow up to last week's episode,
it doesn't look like they're gonna have SteamOS support,
at least not for now.
There's also been no official statement,
so really, not much news.
Chris takes a deep breath, he takes a deep breath.
Do you think, Wes, this is,
I mean, here's why I think it's a disappointment.
If it requires something real crazy
in the operating system, you're doing it wrong.
It should be something I hook up to HDMI and USB
and then it shows up as a display device
and that should really be it.
And I realize that this is sometimes
not a super awesome area for Linux,
multiple display devices and whatnot.
Let me worry about that part.
If you developers who get paid so much money
and companies who are backed by Facebook
worth billions just can't find it within yourself
to learn how to use SDL properly,
just release it and let the community work on it.
For God's sakes, how many times
do you have to be told this lesson?
If you can't figure it out yourself,
there's probably a community out there
that is passionate enough to,
yeah, especially when it's something hot like this.
It just, it boggles the mind that companies
still fail to figure this out in 2016.
How many times do we have to learn this lesson
and how many different industries
have to figure this crap out?
There's just nothing else to say, I suppose.
All right, Wes, do you have any thoughts on that
before we move on?
Because I got something I got thoughts on.
Are you ready?
Because it's our friends over at DigitalOcean.
That's right, DigitalOcean.com.
Go there and check out DigitalOcean,
sponsor of the Linux Unplugged program.
You can get your own Linux rig up in that cloud
like in no time, less than 55 seconds
and for only $5 a month,
you'll get a rig with 512 megabytes of RAM.
Boom.
A 20 gigabyte SSD, you know why, Wes?
Because they all SSD.
Yes, they are.
Which, if you think about it,
when DigitalOcean got started,
that was kinda ballsy, I'm really impressed.
They were brave, you know, they took command.
They said, we're gonna go out there,
we're gonna build the best servers with SSDs,
with Linux, using KVM, tier one connections
in our data centers.
Use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED, one word, lowercase,
put it all together and get yourself a $10 credit.
They got Ubuntu rigs, FreeBSD, Fedora, Debian,
Core OS, CentOS, what's up?
Of course they're gonna have 16.04 just about immediately.
They've already got guides on how to set stuff up on it.
They got data centers in New York, San Francisco,
Singapore, Amsterdam, London, Germany.
Have you seen those pictures, too?
Their data centers are pretty.
Dude, they are seriously pretty.
Which is a weird thing to say, but they are.
But they are.
They are.
The interface, though, also speaking of pretty,
that interface, very nice interface
that allows you to do simple things
to very advanced things.
With an HTML5 console, so you get access from post
all the way to login.
And DigitalOcean's got a few tricks up their sleeve.
They launched early access to sign up
for their new block storage service,
which I am super stoked about.
If you wanna try that, go to digitalocean.com
slash features slash storage.
Remember, when you're spinning up a DigitalOcean droplet,
or if you have one spun up already,
you can apply the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
Give yourself credit and support this show.
And then, go check out DOCTL, or TI.
What do you think that is, Wes?
What do you think that is?
Oh, I'll tell you what it is.
DO control.
It's a command line utility
for managing your DigitalOcean droplets.
And it is slick.
It takes advantage of their straightforward API.
Again, another great tool that uses their API.
This.
You should just throw that in the IRC right now.
Oh, I will.
I will drop it in the internet relay chat right now.
Go check them out at digitalocean.com.
Use the promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
And then, when you need to create something up in the cloud,
or AKA on somebody else's computer
that's way more badass than yours,
go to digitalocean.com and use that promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
I'm gonna be talking about track car later today
on the show.
Of course, I have it running on a DigitalOcean droplet.
I just got a Yuba key.
Got my own validation server
on a DigitalOcean droplet.
Boom.
You can do anything with them.
I'll give that a ding, Wes.
I agree.
DigitalOcean.com, please use that promo code DOUNPLUGGED
to support this here show.
And a big thank you to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring Unplugged.
And don't forget,
they do have that block storage early access.
Ooh, I'm excited.
And Naomi, too.
All right, so.
Hey, everybody.
I'm Ryan Sipes,
CTO and community manager at Mycroft AI.
We got ourselves a Mycroft AI update virtual lug.
And I'm sure probably a lot of you
have seen this video already.
Maybe some of you haven't.
And I wanna go through something here.
First of all, I really think it's great
that the Mycroft project
is continuing to do these video updates
because they really are working on something unique here.
Now, Ryan is gonna do a demonstration of the Mycroft.
And Ryan decided not to edit it, I think.
And I wanna continue to play it
because I think he's being very honest
with the performance of the device and how it works.
And so I wanna play a little bit of it.
Today, I have an early developer's kit unit of Mycroft.
And I'm going to be demoing some of the features for you.
Remember that this is an alpha build.
And so you may see some bugs,
but I'm really excited to get to share
what we're working on with you, the internet.
So here we go.
Hey, Mycroft, what time is it?
It is currently 2047, Sunday, April 3rd, 2016.
That is super cool.
And the first thing I noticed
is it didn't sound like Popeye.
What happened there?
I thought it was gonna sound like you, Popeye.
Was that just you showing off the voice emulation stuff?
So the one that it ships with at the moment
is, yeah, whatever their prototype default voice is.
And I finished recording the audio yesterday, day before.
No.
So, yeah.
Yes, that is so cool.
They'll start mushing that.
Somehow, some cloud somewhere
will start turning that into words.
And then I think that'll be an update.
That's a-
You'll be able to read yourself to sleep at night?
That is a fascinating process.
I would like him, you know what?
I would love to somehow be able to document that,
like how they put it all together now.
Boy, isn't that neat?
I can tell you my bit.
Oh yeah, I would, yeah.
Which was, right, so picture the scene,
my son's bedroom with blankets covering all the walls
and all the other hard surfaces.
You mean you don't already have that set up
for recording your podcast, Popeye?
No, not at all, not at all.
But I thought I'd do something half decent for them.
Me sat on the floor with a table with a laptop
and a microphone and me speaking
three and a half thousand sentences into this laptop.
Wow.
So was it tedious or was it fun?
Or it had to be tedious?
Oh my God, it's tedious, yes.
Yes.
Yeah, and the weird thing is,
the phrases, they're snippets from books.
Well, there are bits of The Wizard of Oz,
but in order to not have me linearly,
could you have to read it flat,
like the she-wolf saw the thing?
Like you can't put any intonation in the voice at all.
You have to read it flat.
And every, like you read a line and you think,
oh, he's talking about the scarecrow,
that's from The Wizard of Oz.
And then the very next thing you read
is not from The Wizard of Oz,
it's from a completely different book,
so that you don't start getting into a flow, I think.
Right, you can't tell even any kind of story
with your voice.
Huh.
Right.
Oh, interesting.
And you read all these different phrases
and then once you've read all of the phrases,
they've captured every possible word.
And they don't have you,
they don't have you, like,
so, you know, one of the things.
I don't say, hello, my name is Mycroft,
or anything like that.
I say a whole load of words
that have nothing to do with Mycroft.
At no point did I say the word Mycroft.
But they will be able to generate.
I say a whole bunch of other words.
Yeah, they synthesize.
So I'm interested to find out
when my bank wants to do voice print analysis
for, like, authenticating,
because I'm just gonna say no,
because I know that there are computers out there
that have my voice on them,
so someone could fake my voice.
So I wanna show you, as an example,
I'm gonna do, let's try this.
Hey, Siri.
How many days ago,
or what was the question,
wait, hold on, I should ask Siri.
Well, I can't just remember, okay.
So we tried this on the pre-show.
The reason I wanna bring it up
is because there's, like, a inflection
that the modern voice assistants use
to end a sentence.
So, hey, Siri.
Hey, Siri.
What was the date 106 weeks ago?
It was Tuesday, April 1st, 2014.
April Fools' Day.
You see how she kind of does different, like.
Fools' Day.
Yeah, and then she sort of ends,
there is a way she ends the sentence.
Now, were there, like, did you make clear, like,
punctuations and things like that,
that they would, okay.
Yes, there were bits where I had to ask a question,
and a question mark is one of the sounds
that they capture.
They capture all of them, every sound you make,
and then they synthesize a word out of that.
That is really something.
I have no idea how much it will sound.
It may not ever actually sound like me at all.
Well, the demo they did sounded like you.
Yeah, that was me recorded.
Oh, yeah, that's true.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Right, yeah.
You sounded very robotic, good job.
Wow, so what do you think about
being the voice of Skynet?
Does that weird you out at all?
No, not really.
It's weirded out my coworkers and my friends,
who say it's gonna be really weird
having you talking to me in my house.
I'm like, well, you know.
My thought is, talking to their wife.
As all of the AIs, all of the AIs come online,
because AIs will create more AIs.
Naturally.
Obviously, and they will need to bring
all to their own distinct voices,
and so they will go out into the web,
and they will download all of the podcasts of humanity,
within days, and have listened to all of them.
So all of us that have been in podcasts
will eventually probably be a voice of an AI out there.
Robots are stealing our voices.
Yeah, exactly, in the future.
Future robots are stealing.
Thanks, archive.org.
Anyways, so Ryan continues on,
and I want you to notice how he interacts with it,
and sort of how he chooses not to edit out
some of these things, which I think is great.
Hey, Microp, what's the weather?
Right now, it's clear sky and 73 degrees,
for a high of 75 and a low of 70 in Lawrence, Kansas.
It's going to be a lovely day.
Aw, it smiled after that.
That isn't all that impressive,
but let's see what is going to be the case tomorrow.
Hey, Microp, what's the weather in Kansas City tomorrow?
Tomorrow, Kansas City will have a high of 67
and a low of 49, with clear sky conditions.
A general query.
The unit can also answer various questions
using sources like Wikipedia and Wolfram Alpha.
Let's ask him a question.
Hey, Microp, tell me about Mozilla.
Not as fast as the Echo or Siri or Google, but...
I am looking for Mozilla.
Still looking.
And those eyes are so cute.
Mozilla is a free software community
created in 1998 by members of Netscape.
The Mozilla community uses, develops,
spreads, and supports Mozilla products,
thereby promoting exclusively free software
and opens standards with only minor exceptions.
Uh-oh, future podcaster right there.
So kind of, and I like that Ryan left in
how long it takes to do the things.
If you guys want to watch the whole video,
you can in the show notes.
And obviously that's going to improve
as the hardware gets more powerful
and as the backend services grow.
Right. That'll get faster and faster.
I've been hearing a lot of people talk about their Echo.
Have you tried one?
I haven't, no.
Anybody in the Mumber Room have that Amazon Echo?
Or something like it?
I've been hearing a lot of people talk about it,
but, or reading a lot of people talk about it
and watching on YouTube, but.
I guess I would consider trying the Pi one.
Yeah, where you can load the Alexia service
or whatever on a Pi.
Yeah, that is pretty neat, actually.
Then you can at least kind of sandbox it
or have some control.
Yeah. All right, well I know,
okay, I know we're going to have
at least somebody that is interested in XFCE.
We got an update on XFCE 4.14 is going to go,
are you ready for this, Wes?
GTK 3.
What?
They're going to replace their D-Bus implementation
with GD-Bus.
They're going to go new icon names across the boards.
They're going to replace old widgets.
They're going to replace core components
like their compositor.
They're going to update their compositor
to actually use OpenGL and GLX for compositing
instead of XRender.
Sweet.
They're going to redo their panel
to support GTK 3 across the board.
Now they've already shown an example of their,
some of their work.
One of those is a GTK 3 app
and one of them is their old GTK 2 app.
And you really can't tell the difference.
The one on the left is GTK 3.
They're probably going to try to keep it
as close as possible, I would guess.
Hey.
Yeah.
That'll keep people happy anyway.
I'm kind of actually,
I'm kind of curious about Wimpy's thoughts on this,
just having spent a lot of effort and energy
having people working on Mate getting GTK 3 support going.
Is this, what do you think, Wimpy?
Is this an obvious step for them
and will it actually happen?
I think it'll happen.
The X, well, the lines are blurred a bit for me
between Xfce and Xubuntu.
Okay.
It seems to me that the lead developer for Xubuntu
is doing most of the Xfce development now.
So if his advancements are anything to be taken as well,
anything to be taken as reference,
then yes, it's likely to happen.
And it's a big job.
So again, I don't know Xfce very well.
I know it sort of pulls in other components,
you know, like open box and stuff like that.
And some of the underlying bits are different,
although it uses its own window energy now, doesn't it, Xfwm.
So it's taken us ages and we've only got a small team.
I don't know how big the Xfce team
and how far along they are,
but like what the Marte team have done,
I think Xfce really have to do this,
need to do it to stay relevant
with the rest of the desktop components.
Well, even just to support Wayland,
don't you have to eventually get here?
Well, Wayland and Mir, because both of those have got-
Right, Mir's a thing too, yeah.
Yeah, Mir's totally a thing.
And from my point of view,
the most important thing that GTK brings to the table
is high DPI.
Yes, absolutely.
More than Wayland, more than Mir,
more than, you know, composited desktops,
the most important thing is high DPI.
I think we're just,
we're not quite at the tipping point yet,
but I think in a year from now,
high DPI is going to be,
if you're not doing high DPI,
if you can't support it, that's gonna be an issue.
Well said.
Richard, if you wanted to jump in on this,
I'd be curious to know your thoughts on,
what do you think, just your personal opinion,
XFCE could do to make itself more attractive to distros?
We kind of talked about this last week
in regards to the Plasma desktop.
Using that same kind of lens,
what are your thoughts about XFCE?
I don't think it needs to make itself more attractive.
I mean, it is, on openSUSE,
the most popular lightweight desktop we've got.
So, I mean, I'm really interested to see them jump to GTK 3,
because like for us, the pain point has often been
like keeping all this GTK 2.2 stuff about.
As long as it's relatively easy for us to package
and live with.
Right, that could make it a lot.
Bring it on.
Yeah, because now you only have to worry about GTK 3
for a majority of your install base.
I didn't think about that.
Yeah.
That's a great point.
Yeah, this reduces the GTK 2 dependency
for a ton of people once they get there.
I mean, it's probably gonna take a while
to get to that point, to be honest with you.
Yes.
But that-
But it's on the roadmap.
Yeah.
There's an awful lot of GTK 2 desktop applications
out there that-
Right.
What are you using, Wimpy, that's still GTK 2?
GIMP?
Firefox.
Oh yeah, Firefox.
I don't use Firefox.
Firefox.
Yeah, yeah.
Firefox has GTK 3, though.
It's pretty good at this point.
I do use GIMP.
I forgot about GIMP.
There's so many.
Yeah.
How can GIMP still be on?
How can GIMP not be on the new GIMP toolkit?
I told you.
How can GIMP not be on GTK 3 at this point?
I mean, obviously it's huge, but that's-
It's to stop being the GIMP toolkit long ago.
Yeah, I know.
I know.
I'm just making-
Toolkit.
Just taking a shot,
because it does seem a little crazy that GIMP isn't-
Are they working on this now?
There's a port in progress.
Yeah.
You're saying GIMP is taking a long time to do things?
No.
No way.
Rodden, did you have any thoughts on the XFCE roadmap
before we move on from the topic?
Well, I think it's funny that it's on there,
because it's like, yeah, okay,
it was on there like three years ago as well.
So, we'll see.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean, it takes a while, especially for them.
It does take a while.
Derek Delvin, you want to jump in about GIMP.
Go ahead.
I just wanted to say that it's a good opportunity
for GIMP to revamp their UI again
and actually make something decent.
Hmm.
Just a hint to say,
take the chance you're putting into GTK 3,
the part of building UI components is there,
not take the chance to make better UI.
I'll make a proposal for you.
Maybe they should go the route of starting
with Google Photos, or Google, I mean, GNOME Photos.
Start with GNOME Photos and go from there.
Sort of recently, this affected Ange.
Apple just totally dropped the ball
on their iPhoto program, which was like,
a key part of the switch to Mac iLife suite
is this iPhoto, and so she puts, you know,
I like, you know, terabyte or something,
I don't know, just a crap ton of pictures in there.
And then they come along and say,
oh yeah, we're no longer gonna make iPhoto,
but we're gonna take our iOS app
and we're going to scale it up for the desktop.
And I thought this was gonna be a horrible train wreck
for her, but so far, it's gone fine.
And the idea might be sort of the same for GIMP,
maybe you, because GNOME Photos is in way better shape
and it's already a desktop application with great features.
And so, why not just start with that?
Well, I don't know.
I guess there is somebody, RealAzure out there,
RealAzure out there says he likes the GIMP UI.
Kitson, you wanted to jump in about GTK apps
being unmaintainable in the long run.
Go ahead.
Yeah, it just may be that they are unmaintainable
in the long run when you are talking about
going from version two to three, et cetera.
And I wonder if somebody could maybe do a comparison
between QT and KDE apps and how they fared
from version to version and see if there's similar issues.
Because this is something that I have noticed
between major desktop shifts.
There's differences, but there's never been
a catastrophic, like, massive bug
that's between QT4 and QT5.
There were a few things that were harder to port,
like Dolphin took longer than expected.
But the majority of the stuff moved over very quickly.
Yeah, I know, it's because every tool change stack
is gonna have some kind of pain at some point.
Like, we've got QT5.6 in Tumbleweed staging right now,
and it just seems to be randomly breaking keyboard shortcuts.
But that's true of, like, every major upgrade.
Apart from 320 for GTK, it was pretty smooth.
Really, yeah, I mean, I feel like that's a valid concern
when GTK3 first came out, and maybe until,
maybe even till 3.10, 3.12.
Yeah, 3.12, maybe.
Yeah, I mean, maybe, but I mean,
if that's, even 3.12 was really pushing it,
and that's years into it at that point.
Right.
Keeping pace with the development
momentum that's going on in GTK3
when you're not part of that core team is really hard.
We've tried really hard to align the Marte release
with the GTK3 releases, and we managed it to.
The releases, Marte 1.12 and Marte 1.14,
they've been released alongside GTK 3.2,
but almost the whole five-month cycle for Marte 1.14
was accommodating the changes in GTK3.20,
which is significantly different from 3.18 under the hood.
Is it wimpy, in your opinion, that GTK3
is still just so busy catching up
that they have to be this aggressive,
or is it perhaps legitimately time to reconsider
either A, the six-month cycle,
or B, switching to a different release style?
And there could be release styles
that accommodate a six-month cycle,
but yet, if you use something like a feature flag set,
just like Open ZFS does, where you have feature flags,
and you just don't, if you don't support those flags,
then you're not incompatible,
you just can't use those features.
I think the actual solution to this problem
are things like XDG app, and Snappy, and AppImage,
and that we can start to focus on building a runtime
for a desktop environment, and we can just say,
we are going to target this and the next two versions
of Marte against these libraries,
and it doesn't matter what the development momentum is.
That really does make the most sense.
We've got a platform that we can build against,
and I'm not sure when that's going to be a reality for us,
but when I see, I mean, the GNOME team are innovating,
they're taking things forward,
they're developing very quickly,
but it's very, very difficult for other projects
to keep pace with that, because they've got
a lot of full-time developers, and we simply don't.
So I think the solution to this problem
for smaller projects like ours
is to start to exploit these container-based,
these isolated runtimes and application environments,
and start to leverage those, so we can say,
we're going to put a flag in the ground here.
This is our tool set version we're going to target,
and we can just build against that for whatever period.
Interesting, that really seems like what that would do
is it relieves the pressure off of the downstream projects
to sort of, like you said, exactly say,
we're going to stabilize around this for a while,
and then because the end users remain unaffected
with XGG app, and although I would imagine XGG app
is going to be the most tied to GTK features
as of all of them, but that would probably solve
the problem and allow each project
to work at their own rational pace.
Odyssey, you have some experience
with a drawing application that's making the transition.
How did that go?
So far, when we first ported MyPay over to GK,
when MyPay was ported to GTK 3,
it actually broke a lot of our cross-platform builds
for Mac and Windows.
And even with the update to GLib,
they may have changed the way it handles GLib,
it ended up breaking builds for Integra or Arch builds.
No!
So are you saying software development breaks things?
Now, is this a matter of hours to resolve,
days, months, unresolved?
What is the process when something like this happens?
Usually, it comes down to just trying to get the person
who first reported the issue on their GitHub page
to just kind of submit the debug reports on Python stuff.
And then our only developer actually opens up the ticket
on the actual GTK to get it fixed.
See, I haven't asked the obvious question.
What was the catalyst to go to GTK 3?
I don't exactly remember,
it's why we've been using it since it came out.
Because it's awesome!
All right.
Embracing the future.
I think it was just trying to keep up with GNOME.
Yeah.
The problem with GTK 3 on Windows and Mac
is because the pace for GTK is still being,
it's still being the GNOME pace of six months,
but the pace for the Windows and Mac builds
are actually like two versions behind.
Right, yeah.
Yeah, and the major problems with us,
with the GTK part, is the fact that the tablet support,
even though our Wacom tablets worked okay,
a lot of the Opera ads will not.
Well, I guess I appreciate the insights there, honestly,
because I hadn't really, I hadn't heard about it
from that kind of breakage standpoint.
The other kind of things I've usually heard
are more on the desktop level.
So.
Just to point out one thing, though,
is that the speed of a toolkit does not necessarily
mean there's going to be a lot of breakage.
Because if you pay attention to the release dates
of KDE and QT, it's actually like every four months,
three to four months.
So they're doing double pace,
and they're not breaking stuff.
Okay.
All right, so there you go.
There's Rotten's obligatory plug of the week.
I'll make my obligatory plug of the week.
Now, that's Ting, everybody.
Go to last, no, linux.ting.com.
I'm gonna go to linux.ting.com.
Those guys are jerks.
Go to linux.
Careful now, Chris.
Linux.com.
I'm at war with the Linux action show.
Me too.
Yeah, that one guy that's on the show all the time,
he's always wearing red.
It's obnoxious.
I don't like it.
So if you would like to save a little cash
on your next mobile service provider,
and you want to put the power back in your pocket
in your relationship with your service provider,
and you would like to disrupt the duopoly a bit
and vote with your wallet,
go to linux.ting.com.
You get yourself a discount off your first Ting device,
or if you bring a Ting compatible device,
and you likely will because they got two networks.
You're kidding.
Well, then you're gonna get $25 in service credit.
Your first month, probably gonna be about 23 bucks
if you're an average user.
They got great customer service.
You get to speak to a real human being.
GSM and CDMA services,
you get to pick whichever is better in your area.
And I found this to be extremely useful
when I go on the road trip.
They have enough, I mean,
I was gonna say an ANFAD metanisable or something.
I was trying to come up with a new word,
something like my kids would think of
for something that's so mind-bendingly awesome.
One of the first things that really,
I mean, there's a ton of things.
You can set up thresholds and alerts
and all these kinds of things,
but when I realized,
geez, it's only $6 a month for a Ting line,
I was like, I'm gonna give our nanny a line.
We had a nanny, and I wanted her to have a phone
so she could always contact us,
and I want it to be a smartphone
so that way she could send us pictures of the kids
and we could, you know,
because she had just this,
I won't even, it was just a garbage feature phone.
Six bucks a month, right?
So then I go into Ting,
and I label this as the nanny's line.
And so I can see how much data she's using specifically,
and I can set thresholds,
and I can be like, really?
Really?
Don't need 10 gigs of data this time.
Right, or I can just turn it off or anything like that.
So when we no longer have a nanny,
just turn that line off and no longer,
I'm just not paying for it.
It's really, it's a super nice control panel.
And that's just, I'm just scratching the surface.
They have companion apps and all kinds of stuff.
It's a really, really great service.
They have everything from feature phones,
just the bare SIM cards,
all the way up to the best smart devices.
You can bring them yourself or grab one from Ting.
And they're doing the great Ting mobile data experiment.
They have information over at their blog.
If you'd like to get involved,
they have a great blog with tons of good info,
including a recent review of the Roku 3
and the Roku streaming stick.
Check them out.
You start by going to linux.ting.com.
That supports this show.
You can try out their savings calculator.
This is kind of cool too.
Because you know, I'd say if you're a listener
to our audience, you're already kind of by default
a pretty good target for the Ting service.
But you can just sort of verify
where things would line up for you
by seeing how your rates and plan
would stack up to what Ting would do.
You go over to.
And they're so transparent about it.
Yeah, it is nice.
Because you know, if you're not gonna save money,
then just don't switch.
But you likely are gonna save money,
especially if you're Wi-Fi savvy.
Just start by going to linux.ting.com
and use the savings calculator.
Plug in your current usage and just get an idea.
And like for me, because I got Wi-Fi everywhere I'm at.
I used, I actually, even when I don't have Wi-Fi,
I still, you know, I don't really worry about it that much.
And it's still, everything works out just fine.
Plus, I don't, this is the one thing where I do save.
I almost, I probably haven't received a text message
since New Year's.
Wow.
Everything else is Telegram.
Right. Yeah.
Or Hangouts.
Speak of the devil.
Wow, that is some crazy timing right there.
There's Telegram.
I love it.
Yeah, and it's, that right there has been like,
because I don't use the phone much,
because I use Telegram or Hangouts for everything,
and because I've got pretty much Wi-Fi everywhere,
except for when I'm on the road,
my Ting bill, even with three lines,
is usually under 40 bucks.
Nice. Yeah.
I've saved a ton of money by switching to Ting.
Linux.ting.com and a big thank you to Ting
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
Okay, so I've been teasing it,
but 106 weeks ago on April 1st, 2014,
we talked about nationally syndicated
Premier Radio Network's host,
Leo Laporte. My good friend.
The tech guy who we, from time to time, play.
It's for people who like to mess with computers.
If you're, and you know who you are.
If you're somebody who doesn't wanna mess with,
I just wanna surf the,
just wanna buy something on Amazon,
send an email to my kids,
look at some websites.
If that's you, you don't wanna mess with it,
probably not a good choice.
I think Chromebooks are a good choice.
I think a new version of Windows would be fine.
Windows 8, if you can afford it.
A Macintosh, if you've got even more money,
that's a good choice.
It's only for the enthusiasts that I'd recommend Ubuntu.
So that was on his radio show,
and we were just very displeased.
And the reason why Leo had made that recommendation was
is he'd gotten some bad advice from his chat room.
I don't know, did you ever hear this episode?
Do you remember this?
Do you recall this?
You know, I think I did listen to it,
but it's been a while.
Yeah, yeah.
And we were like, oh man.
And it was also, it was at the peak of some other bad press
that Linux had recently gotten.
And it was sort of all, it was like,
oh, this is just another blow.
Well, I felt after 106 weeks, it took a little while.
But I felt recently, Leo really got it right.
And props to the subreddit for pointing this out.
But Leo stopped, he did his homework,
and at the end of this week in Google episode 347,
he talked about his experiences studying Linux.
And I thought as, I thought for us,
because a lot of us are always thinking about
the new users that are coming to Linux,
which just drives me crazy.
It's like, let's focus on the geeks for a while
and get that right.
But all of us here.
Anyways, we're always talking about, you know,
the new user, the defaults, all that kind of stuff.
And so it's really interesting to listen to Leo's
journey into Linux, because it reminds me very much
in some ways of Chase's journey into Linux a little bit.
And he actually did his homework here.
And so it's sort of, it's kind of educational
to listen to this.
So I'm gonna play a bit of this, just a little bit of it,
as sort of a follow up from our coverage
on April 1st, 2014.
Has kind of made me think, I really probably
should start looking at another operating system.
You know, the best desktop, without anybody knowing it,
the year of desktop Linux happened with Chrome OS.
That is Linux.
And it's a-
You can't really install anything on it.
No, but it's really gets you most of the way there.
It is Linux, and a lot of the merits of it
are based on the fact that it's based on Linux.
So people, and Android is Linux as well.
So Google's done a lot to put Linux in the mainstream,
but I thought, I wouldn't mind finding a desktop Linux
that would give me all of the stuff I get
from OS X or Windows.
Now actually, just as I start engaged in this process,
Microsoft announced that they're gonna put
the Bash shell in Windows.
God damn it.
Which is really good news for web developers,
anybody who's used to the Unix tool chain,
and most developers want some sort of Unix tool chain.
That means Windows is no longer out of the question.
I was pretty impressed so far, what I was hearing.
Are you impressed so far?
Yeah.
I also want that chair.
A lot of web developers use Macs just because of that.
Because they have the Bash shell,
they have a command line.
So I've been shopping around,
and with lots of help from our chat room,
I've tried a lot of different distributions.
Of course, your first one you go to is Ubuntu.
A lot of people say Linux Mint,
that's the most popular distribution right now
on DistroWatch.
But there's security reasons.
Now I thought, when he mentioned the security reasons,
what do you think he's gonna say?
I always think he's gonna talk about
the website hack, right?
Not sure I wanna go with Linux Mint,
they blocked some of the upstream updates and so forth
for compatibility reasons.
Ubuntu, also in a way, kind of gets out of date fast.
If you do the stable release,
you're gonna be out of date on a lot of stuff.
I then I looked at Debian,
which is what Ubuntu and Mint are based on.
And that's a pretty nice operating system
if you use the Debian stretch version.
Debian has it right, they have a stable version
that tends to be older, but is very rock solid.
And then somebody told me,
oh, you should use Arch Linux,
that's a build it yourself Linux.
And I did build an Arch system.
You have to be a Linux guru to do it.
And finally, somebody told me about this.
This is-
What?
It's also like a backhanded compliment there.
I did build it.
You have to be a guru.
Yeah, yeah, that's typical Leo.
But then he discovers, Wes,
I've done it across.
You're out of date on a lot of stuff.
And then I looked at Debian,
which is what Ubuntu and Mint are based on.
And that's a pretty nice operating system
if you use the Debian stretch version.
They have, Debian has it right,
they have a stable version that tends to be older,
but is very rock solid.
And then somebody told me,
oh, you should use Arch Linux,
that's a build it yourself Linux.
And I did build an Arch system.
You have to be a Linux guru to do it.
And finally, somebody told me about this.
This is Antergos.
Antergos is from Spain.
And it is a Linux distribution that is Arch,
but it's pre-configured to be very easy
and friendly to use.
And actually, I really, really like it.
I put it on two machines now.
And I think anybody looking to get both
a rolling updated Linux,
a Linux like Arch that is constantly up to date,
but a user interface that is agreeable, easy to use.
And remember, you've got a full,
you know, free office suite, LibreOffice.
You've got a lot of the tools that you use.
If you put Chromium on it,
that's identical to Google Chrome.
In fact, you log in with Google and you sync it.
Okay, NorthRanger.
I think NorthRanger has the best comment on all of this.
Will you share it with the class real quick?
Cause that's, that's gorgeous.
Yeah, this, yeah, go ahead.
I am totally buying a lottery ticket right now.
Yeah.
Hell is freezing over.
I don't know what's going on.
What like, what bizarre alternate universe
do we live in right now?
I know, Microsoft's releasing Bash on Windows,
Leo Leport's running Arch Linux on two computers.
And loving it.
Yeah, I mean, previously he said.
Most of the web runs on servers powered by Linux.
That's how reliable it is.
Android phones are based on Linux.
All Android phones run Linux.
That's the operating system.
You're probably using Linux all the time.
Maybe you don't even know it.
So you can get a free version of Linux.
There are many, as I mentioned.
So he's talked about it before.
Not like he's new to Linux, but this is a big development.
So I wanted to give him props for not only,
not only trying it, but he apparently, you know,
it sounds like I get the impression at least
he's done his homework.
He really does sound like he's curious
and wants to use it.
Yeah.
He's dug in before.
This is actually like probably his third update.
That's, you know, impressive.
My favorite one was when he first started
really getting into, started doing it.
It was an episode where he talked about Linux Mint
when he was using it and he was talking about
how Cinnamon was great and he was showing,
this was really early on before he realized
there was, you know, the security issues.
But he was looking at it and saying like,
this is great and the best part about when he was doing it
is that he was showing Paul Therot on Windows Weekly.
Nice.
There you go.
So props to Mr. Laporte.
Now, Mr. Laporte, if you want to stop taking advice
from your chat room and would like to learn more,
I invite you to go to linuxacademy.com slash unplug.
Be the real expert.
Maybe you should tweet that to Leo.
Leo, take your Linux skills,
which apparently he's got some,
and take them to the next level, right?
I bet that next website could run on a system
built by Leo Laporte if he goes over
to linuxacademy.com slash unplug.
Leo, they've got 2,364 video courses that you could take.
I'm talking good stuff with downloadable,
comprehensive study guides.
You can take that and listen to it in the shower, Leo,
which is really, according to my audience,
the best time to do it.
Scenario-based labs put you with hands-on experience
in an environment just like the real world,
so that way you walk away with real-world experience,
and that would really help inform
your commentary on the subject.
Instructor mentoring is available,
which if you think about it,
from some of the competitors out there,
not even really a serious offering,
and they have instructor mentoring.
Live streams, too, where you can do Q&A.
A community that is stacked full
of Jupiter Broadcasting members.
Graded server exercises give you grades in real time.
The entire Red Hat course,
well, most of the Red Hat,
and they're working on more all the time.
Yes, they are. It is really cool.
And I just recently heard from them
that the OpenStack stuff is blowing up right now for them.
The courseware is on OpenStack. Blowing up!
Really, some of the best Amazon Web Service courseware, too.
Now, that is legit. You should check that out.
They are blowing the doors off of that.
And if you want to go investigate
that dark, murky world of DevOps,
well, guess what? Linux Academy has courseware on that as well.
They have a really cool system as well if you're busy.
Say you're like Leo and you're recording
like a dozen podcasts a week and you're on the air all the time.
You don't have a lot of time to do all these courses.
I understand that. Shoot, I'm busy, too, son.
You know how many kids I got, Wes?
Three.
Yeah, Wes. That's a lot of kids.
That's a lot of kids. Not enough time for Linux.
No. So you know what I do?
I use their availability planner to customize my coursework.
Nice. I know. It is real nice.
And plus, with their practice exams,
I can feel like I can go in there and try something
and make sure I got it right, which is good for me
because I got that test anxiety.
You know, except for an STD test because I don't feel like...
Then you need to know.
Yeah. And I don't feel like that's like a cue.
That's not like when I got to get the question right or wrong.
I should be pretty solid. They judge you either way.
But I just, you know, they just prick me and it's done.
But with this where I got to answer questions,
I need a practice exam.
Maybe I need...anyways.
Enhanced learning plans are also available,
which are really great because you can get a detailed learning plan
with reminders and daily assignments, labs,
quizzes that are doing things like that.
It's a really awesome place built by people
who are crazy passionate about Linux, linuxacademy.com.
Go check them out, linuxacademy.com, slash, Unplugged,
to save some money and support this here show.
Okay. Odyssey Wester is going to be at Linux Fest Northwest to see who else.
Blaster, are you still in there?
Blaster is going to be at Linux Fest Northwest.
Blaster gets here on Tuesday evening, actually.
Oh, sweet.
Yeah. So you're going to just have missed him
because, yeah, he'll be in here after the show.
Anybody else that I've missed that's going to be at Linux Fest Northwest
in the Mamba Room? Hammer, you're in there.
I'm going to be there.
Who's that? Who's this?
Richard.
Oh, Richard, you're going to be there.
Oh, great. Cool.
Well, you should stop by the booth and say hi.
That'd be really cool.
Oh, I plan to.
Oh, good. Good.
And if you guys have Sousa beer koozies,
you should bring one of those with you.
Or bring one for Wes because he doesn't have one.
I have one. But if you have them this year.
Anybody else in the Mamba Room going to make it to Linux Fest?
That's sad.
If the network was crazy rich, I'd just like,
you're all coming. That'd be so fun.
Well, if you're going to make it.
If North Ranger wins the lotto.
Right. Yeah, maybe. Maybe.
If you're going to make it, meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting
and you'll find the event there.
I have it linked directly in the show notes.
Oh, I should sign up right now.
That'd be cool. That'd be cool.
This is where I think we'll eventually coordinate some of our game plan,
which I'm a little hesitant because Emma could technically just sign up herself
and then get access to everything.
Don't tell her.
I'm sure she's thought of that.
Aye, she's smart, yeah.
Yeah, so I don't know exactly, but I feel like at the same time,
we have to do in a way that is approachable to the audience.
You know, this is a real conundrum for me.
My need for absolutely dominating this contest is interfering with my need
to share with the audience of where to be at.
You see what I mean?
I do. Yeah. Yeah.
But anyways, meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting,
at least this is the starting point.
And then maybe once we'll...
I got it.
We use this to coordinate the in-person meetup place
and then from then on, everything's in person.
Right. Then you can tell if she's there or not.
Yeah, that's how we're going to do it.
Just don't tell her the secrets.
There you go.
And plus, you know, you could also, if you're just going to make it to Linux Fest,
even if you're not going to make it for anything else,
if you're just going to go there, let us know.
I know more than 22 of you are going because here's a funny thing
that the audience always does to me.
It's a nice joke they play on Chris and it's super funny
because it happens every year.
30, 40, 50, 60 people will sign up for the meetup page.
500 people will come and shake my hand.
So where were the rest of you?
Why didn't the rest of you...
Now, I know you're busy.
I understand.
But seriously, like...
He's very friendly.
I do this every year and like 60, 70 people sign up on the meetup page
and we're like, oh, we're going to have 60 or 70 people.
So we get like, you know, a hundred things of a swag item just in case.
Right.
And then 500 people show up and it's like, OK, all right.
Nice.
And literally last year, it might have literally been a thousand people.
And I don't know how many people it was anyways.
My point is, if you could take a moment out of your busy day
and go over to meetup.com as you put a broadcasting.
Let us know that we're going to see you.
Yeah, I'd like to know.
It'd be nice.
I'm not trying to give you a hard time here, but I'm just saying it'd be nice.
So in preparation for Linux Fest Northwest,
we're going to go pick up Mr. Ham Radio.
And I'm kind of I'm looking forward to this because it's been a little while
since I got to spend any time at all in Idaho.
And so nice ham radio here, who is often in the Mamba room with us.
He's often in the chat room as well.
He he is one of our newer editors.
And he kind of does some of the extra stuff you guys will be seen in the future,
some stuff you've seen in the past, and he's going to help us
and Rekai go through a lot of our footage from Linux Fest.
And so we're in the chat room right now.
And so, yeah, like Blaster just said,
Operation Ham Holland will take place very soon.
We're going to Noah and I and my lady got the ham.
Oh, that's a really great idea, actually, and bring it with us.
So Noah is going to arrive next Saturday.
Yeah, probably late in the night.
He's going to stay up.
Probably do that thing he always does where he travels,
where he stays up for 24 hours like a jerk.
Oh, fun.
Yeah, he likes to do that.
But then, you know, the nice thing is he gets to go here's his logic is then
he gets to sleep in a hotel room where he has where there's no kids.
It's just him.
And he just sleeps like he's never slept in like close the blinds.
Yeah, he's out, too.
So he actually has a he actually has a bit of a plan there.
But he's going to fly in super late Saturday.
Next Sunday is a big episode for the Linux action.
He'll be in.
Not only will he be in studio, which means I might need rotten.
I don't know if we need to think about frame changes for that or not.
We might.
He's going to be in studio and we're going to do a very special episode of Linux
action show.
And then after that episode jumping in Lady Jupiter and we're driving over to
Idaho to go pick up Ham would be a couple day trip.
Going to get back late Monday.
Hopefully be able to do tech talk today on Tuesday morning and then we'll have
Noah here in studio for Linux unplugged on next Tuesday and Ham will be around
as well.
So I thought, boy, wouldn't it be nice if on our on our when Noah and I head off
to go pick up Ham if people could watch our progress like last time at
Jupiter broadcasting dot com slash Rover.
So I have been talking about for a while setting up a track car server.
And so I did just that.
I went I went and I downloaded track car T R A C car dot org and they have
downloads for Windows and Linux and even Linux arm and the Mac.
And the installation West is it's pretty interesting.
It's not your typical Linux software installation.
When you download it you download their zip file.
Right.
And you need to have you need to have open JD key said I have for mine at
least I don't know what you need.
I don't want to tell you for what I did tell you what to do.
I installed open JDK seven Jerry headless.
That's the package on Ubuntu.
I have it in the show notes and then I installed unzip.
I unzip the package and then you run like they just have a little dot run
file little script.
So you run the track card at run file and it just goes off right in all of
your file system.
You know.
Oh you got a package manager screw you screw you and your package manager.
Let me just put the oh I see you have you have an old style in it system.
Let me stuff these right here.
I'll stuff these in your net system.
Oh good you have an op directory.
Well I'm think thanks for running me as root.
I'll go right on my stuff to your to your op directory.
And then if you don't have of course because it's not using your package
manager if you don't have the Java packages installed there's no air right.
Well no no no air until you try to start the day man and by and their website
instructions tell you to just reboot your machine like I'm going to reboot my
entire server so that way I can start your day man which you don't need to do
that.
There is a day man in just your op directory you can just go run it
yourself and then it creates it creates a website for you with really poor
security that you can access from any computer in the world.
Show us Chris.
I will.
Because why not Wes because who cares about security.
So right now I have it running on my digital ocean droplet and I have a
car called L.J. tracker for lady jubes and it's running on my Internet phone
six and you can see I can zoom in right here and it's right here in the studio
and here's that.
So here's the Internet phone West.
I'll just show you the UI so you can see it and it's kind of neat because it
keeps a log of when it's pinged to see on the phone here.
It keeps a log of when it's pinged the server.
Oh neat.
And the settings to set it up are.
That's all you have to do.
It's like five lines you fill in.
Beautiful.
That's beautiful.
Thank you.
All right.
So I so that just runs now in the background on the Internet phone and it
updates the track car server which is really a job app and you can add as many
devices you want and you can have as many users as you want with their own
device list.
Oh wow.
And you can set some server defaults a couple of things I really like about it
right off the bat is by default can keep track of everyone at Linux fest your
crew make sure you know right where they could.
Yeah if we will actually we could if we wanted to do that which may be helpful
for people get lost but one of the things I like right off the bat is it's
using open street maps for the for the map and at least in my area the open
street map stuff is just real beautiful well labeled.
It looks nice.
Yeah it really does.
Wes and the other thing is you can.
This has this.
This has a server API so you could also overlay it with Bing Maps or Google
Maps or whatever you want if you prefer those and their satellite data or
something like that.
It gives me extremely accurate longitude and latitude positioning.
So yes that is the longitude and latitude of the studio.
Yes that is public information.
I know it's on the stream right now and it tells you how fast the tracking
device is moving which right now is zero miles per hour and it gives you the
address there but that's actually that's funny that's actually not the address
of the studio the I would imagine the longitude latitude coordinates are
correct but that is that is not actually the address of the studio but that
would just be open.
That's just its guess based on the open street map data.
Now here's something that I'm majorly bummed about because all of that's
really cool and it took me about you know 30 minutes to get it all set up and
it works for Android too you don't have to have an internet phone from
Apple.
Nice.
Yeah.
Here's the major bummer and I just did not expect this.
They don't have any facility for embedding the map in your own web page.
No easy link.
No.
As Popey knows is like the entire intention of why I'm doing this and he
had he wrote you see he did it correctly as he wrote his own because he's so
fancy with it with the Ubuntu touch over there right and I just wanted I wanted
to use track car because it just seemed like a nice easy straightforward
solution.
Someone's already done the hard work for you.
Yeah and so doing a little research I've discovered there is a way to I guess
and I don't really understand how this works but you can embed a Google map on
your own website and then you can overlay data on top of it okay and the
track car server can act as that API source for the data my track car server
has an API now and if I knew how to embed a Google map and overlay data from
an external API I could embed that on the Jupiter broadcasting comm slash
rover page okay so do it basically I'm gonna punt that to the audience to know
if anybody knows what the hell I'm talking about and you know how to do that
I would please let me know telegram me at Chris LAS on telegram I can't
telegram you because one of you bastards trolled my account but you can tell me
and then if you I think if you telegram me like I knew I wanted to say something
to wimpy like a couple of weeks ago like super bad I wanted to relay something to
wimpy and I can't I can't message him I can only I can only message wimpy when
he messages me first and then I can reply to wimpy but I can't met I can't
initiate the conversation I totally yeah yeah it does suck it does really suck
because I had something I really wanted to tell you but not and I've completely
forgotten what it was now but my point is if you know let me let me know either
hit me up in the chat room or actually ping Rekai in the chat room if you're
gonna do it via the IRC or hit me up on telegram because I'm just because of
everything that's going on Twitter would actually be fine too but I'm not checking
email very much for the next few days because I'm running around like crazy I
would love to get that set up those who people could watch and then because I've
wanted what I've been using in the meantime is a proprietary solution that
uses a dedicated piece of hardware and a monthly service fee that's a couple
hundred dollars for like three months or something like that there's no open
source anywhere no and I want every component of lady Jupiter to be as open
source as possible and I've even to some extent had to put things in and roll them
back to try to accomplish that and then eventually I mean this is like it
probably a 2017 thing but eventually I'd love to do an episode on a fully you
know open source setup that I've set up and I feel like this I shouldn't open
rover I should write and I shouldn't implement anything that isn't open source
today if I'm trying to get it all right so I bought this thing this tracker for
the first road trip and then it because I'd prepaid for the service at all and I
knew this at the time it also covered the scale road trip so that worked out
perfectly so I just used the same proprietary thingy because I had paid
for the service but now my service is done and it's like it's like several
hundred dollars if you guys want it's silver cloud tracker if you're
interested if you want the thing that was appealing to me is it's a dedicated
hardware device you know and then you can embed their web app and they had
really pretty decent support too anyways but now I'm done with that and I'd
rather just have an app that runs on the background on my phone and and then just
have something I could embed on the website so if you have any any idea on
how the hell I could actually accomplish that just just let me know and and
blaster and ham radio I got good news for you guys while you guys are out here
we're gonna have a big turkey feed what yeah we did Thanksgiving for Dylan's
birthday last week because that's his favorite meal and so we and I just got
this huge turkey because we had a whole bunch of people over but people snacked
and stuff so there's a whole bunch of turkey leftover and we're gonna have
like turkey enchiladas we're gonna have all kinds of stuff while the crews out
here so yeah we're gonna have a good time when everybody's out here and I'll
be on the road and hopefully you guys have built a track that so if you tune
it for next week's unplugged it should be quite the show I would I would try to
catch that one lives probably gonna be a lot of shenanigans going on in the
studio that day it'll probably simmer down by the time the show's on the air
but if you could make a live next week would be a good when you go to Jupiter
broadcasting comm slash calendar for your lifetime but I got I got a feeling
like what I'll probably do is I'll probably jump out for a little bit for
like a segment or two and let Noah sit in or something you know we can rotate
out or something I know we'll figure it out we can tag team we'll tag team the
hosting or something like that yeah all right guys is it any mumble room is
there anything else from the virtual lug we want to cover before we wrap up on
this week's episode of the unplugged program I turn over you guys for one a
two a three no that's how many licks it takes to get to the center of the
unplugged lollipop you ever seen that commercial oh yeah all right
all right so I'm really I'm really looking forward to next week I'm super
excited Sunday's a big show I hope you guys can catch Sunday's episode of the
Linux action show if you're turning in live on Thursday we got the double tech
snaps coming up a lots going on it's crazy and it's a lot a lot of good
content even if you can't make it in these events it's we're gonna make them
we're gonna put the very best stuff I want anything but JB it's crazy West
there's not time no time no no all right you were broadcasting comm slash calendar
for our lifetimes Linux action show dot reddit comm for feedback Jupiter
broadcasting comm slash contact for email and we'll see you right back here
next Tuesday
And with that, I say get it out of here.
Because that is the end of the show.
All right.
Thank you, Mumbroom.
Yeah, guys.
You're welcome.
Thank you.
JimmyTaylors.com.
Boop-a-doop-a-doop-a-doop-a-doop-do-do-do-do-do-do.
Wimpy, your Mate edition of the Ubuntu distribution, I'm not sure if you're familiar with this,
but this is-
Something you've been doing for a while now.
The hype is strong with the 16.04 release.
I can't believe how many websites I'm seeing right about it.
Probably from basically Network World, Matt, you got Softpedia, you got-
Network World?
Yeah.
Or maybe it was PC World, maybe?
One of them.
Somebody wrote some from-
Oh, okay.
I'll miss that one.
I know.
I blare all the World ones together, but I tell you what.
The-
It's awesome.
Yeah.
It's like, I mean, I almost wonder if it's overshadowing the other main release.
I think the reason it gets so much hype is because, really, in my experience of actually
using Ubuntu Mate, it really feels like what Ubuntu should have been had it stuck with
its original path.
All right, all right.
But what about handy Linux, right?
The distro that gives you-
Get handy with handy Linux.
Yeah, get handy with-
Okay, so it's a Debian without the headaches, right?
Based on Debian GNU slash Linux, you heard of that, lightweight and stable XFC desktop
environment.
Handy Linux is safe, convenient, and free of charge.
Now that's a distro with a name.
That's a brand right there.
Yes, it is.
And look, it even has a hand as its logo.
Yeah, I was reading today on Google Plus that the Fedora project is working on it, and I
guess there's just certain syscalls that maybe aren't even implemented yet.
So it might be a more narrow range that the Ubuntu user line is using than we suspected.
So it sounds like OpenSUSE guys are thinking about it, but it's like a trial and error
stage right now.
So no art show in there yet?
Yeah, because I'm wondering, like, who's the next distro?
You know it's going to be some distro that's going to be the one that announces, we got
it running on the Windows Linux subsystem.
Well, if there's some choice, I'll be more excited to try it.
We've been able to retask the build service to basically pump out what should be viable
images because we have similar use cases we've already been playing with for that.
So like, dump out an OpenSUSE user space, we build our docker images that way, all that
kind of stuff.
Ah, yeah, brilliant.
Yeah.
So that's been the final easy part.
So yeah, it's just figuring out those syscalls and poking around those parts.
I would like to see it.
The same stage as Fedora, but we've managed to get bits and pieces of Tumbleweed and bits
of pieces of Gleap on that.
Huh.
Well, that's a start.
That's exciting.
That's great.
Yeah, that'll be fun.
That could be like, I don't know, like, the next time I ever have to install Windows 10,
that might be something I'd like to play with it.
Right.
So you got a while.
WinArch 10.
I kind of wonder if it'll be Arch, but see, I don't think so.
I think this is probably not going to be Arch's strong suit unless a really savvy developer
out there does it for the distro, right?
But see, some of the more structured distros sort of have an advantage here, I should think.
Yeah, you need a way of getting your root file system deployed on there.
Yeah.
Well, you see-
What is an Arch root file system?
You see examples of people reloading DigitalOcean droplets to different distributions while
it's loaded.
Right.
The BSD guys on BSD now have talked about doing that too, swapping between BSDs.
They could learn about Linux too.
And so you wonder if it could be done from within.
In fact, you almost would have to do it from within the Ubuntu environment, is sort of
replace it from within.
Package your own Windows app.
Well, because you can't get into the App Store.
And when you install the subsystem, I believe it pulls it down as soon as you try to run
it or something.
It's not really coming from an App Store.
It says it is, but it's lying and coming from a plain old website.
So you can man in the middle of that.
Yeah, just on an Azure server.
You can man in the middle of that, no problem.
That's true.
Oh, that's a good point.
You could just do a little DNS trick or something.
Add this line to your host file.
That's what I've guys did, yeah.
Blaster.
If I could just inject for a moment, what you've been referring to as Windows NT is
actually GNU-slash-Windows-NT.
Very good, sir.
Very good.
I've been corrected.
Windows NT.
Yeah, that's an interesting point.
You can fire up Yast from some pretty peculiar angles.
I did that before with some host.
It wasn't DigitalOcean, but yeah, they didn't provide an open SUSE image, so I took their
Debian image, hacked around with it, grew up without it, booted into Yast and nothing
else.
Yeah.
That's good.
I'm sure it's been said a number of times, but isn't it amazing how much of a proof
this is that Linux has won when the Linux API system is used in Linux, it's used in
VSD, and now it's used in Windows.
It's kind of like the universal app platform.
Yeah, I think so.
That or it makes it extremely easy for its competitors to integrate, embrace, and extend.
I don't know.
Come on, glass half full, Chris.
You're right.
I don't think I know anyone who's tried it yet.
Actually I've installed the Ubuntu bash on Windows 10 to try it out.
How'd that go?
Well, I installed Clang and built a C binary just to try it out.
It actually worked.
Pretty sweet.
I can update and upgrade, not dist-upgrade, but just upgrade.
And is it a 15.10 environment?
No, 14.04 at the moment.
Oh, right, right, right, right.
And so will you be doing a dist-upgrade to go to 16.04?
How does that work?
I'll give it a shot.
I'm not messing around with it too much because, you know.
Well, okay, I had to kind of use the latest snapshot image in order to actually update
the Windows 10 laptop that I've got because it just didn't want to do the upgrade to the
actual build.
So I just kind of overrode it to get the bash on Windows thing.
So it actually does work.
I've upgraded, just tried a few binaries or at least compiling a few things.
I haven't done too much beyond that, but it works apparently.
I'm getting really, you know, for me personally, I just couldn't care less about Windows 10
in so many ways.
It's still, it's so Windows still.
It doesn't matter.
You know, I was thinking about this recently.
Microsoft will have truly changed when they have one version of Windows for all systems.
If you want to run it on a server, you want to run it on a desktop, they don't have enterprise
and data center because look at the way the market's going.
Microsoft, when they started as a company, they were one of the first companies to figure
out you could take the same exact code and if you're just a smart enough business major,
you could sell that same code to people who will pay $3,000 for it because they're in
a business and they depend on it and you can sell it to people who will pay $100 for it
because they're a consumer and they don't require it as much and it's the same damn
stuff with artificial limitations.
And they were some of the people that just brilliantly made obviously a lot of money
off that.
And now they are in an era where things are in the cloud and those kinds of little divisions
and things are on mobile and that little artificial limitation seems trivial and obvious now.
And the rest of the world has realized it.
Apple realized it for God's sakes before Microsoft did.
And Apple is the company that charged their beta users to do upgrades originally and then
Steve Jobs came out and claimed, well, we have to do it.
It's an accounting rule.
We have to charge you.
And then two years later, they dropped the charging.
So Apple figures it out before Microsoft does.
And so Microsoft is still trying to sell this differentiator product.
But you know, at the end of the day, it's still the same crap product.
I have a close family member.
I didn't even know this.
I'm actually very sort of upset about it.
Their parent went out and bought them a Windows 10 laptop at Best Buy.
And they're all excited.
They came over for Dylan's birthday party and they're like, hey, Chris, look, it's my
laptop.
It's got the new Windows 10 on it.
Isn't that great?
It's got the new Windows 10.
I'm like, wow, they really got sold.
So how's it been going?
And so Dylan, you know, he brings down his elementary OS Sputnik and he fires it up.
And you know, this is the same exact install that Dylan's had since I gave it to him for
his last birthday.
So it's now over a year old.
And he fires up Minecraft and he's got all his mods installed.
He's like, come on, let's play.
And he's like, oh, I can't.
And Dylan's like, why not?
Well, I got a virus a few days ago and we took it in a geek squad to replace it.
And they had to format my computer and they lost all my worlds.
And we haven't been able to get Minecraft reinstalled since then.
But I got a geek squad shirt.
It's the same.
Wow.
And it looks just like the round reflect, but they actually add it for the game as
well.
I just love this thing.
It looks pretty cool.