So today's a special day you guys may have saw the link in the subreddit but
if you look at the numbers now in the Steam store there are 1700 Linux games
Wowee that's a series of games or does that include movies and DLC it includes
anything that when you search by the Linux or Steam OS plus Linux tag so
whatever they classify anything which includes oh look at this though hey hold
on hold on hold on stop there stop there they've filtered it just based on games
they're filtering just based on games so it is 1700 games that is pretty
impressive considering it's not been that long and the Steam machines are not
that established two years ago what was that that's gone up 700 just since
January yes yeah yeah and you know what else I recalled from our discussion
about the performance of the first generation Steam machines we were
discussing you know their frame rate and we were discussing the benchmarks and
how the Steam machines were a little disappointing and we were kind of bummed
about that and then I realized they still are benchmarking better than
consoles like the like so you know because their competitors right are the
other consoles the PlayStation and the Xbox one and the Nintendo and and in
terms of raw performance they can push higher resolution with higher frame
rates than any of those consoles can so as far as consoles go it actually is a
higher performer which when you think about like how the fact they put a
spinning rust drive in there and all that kind of stuff when you realize that
the real competitor is other consoles it kind of makes more sense another thing
to consider is it's just been released right what other console or anything in
history has had that many titles upon release that's pretty amazing yeah
really yeah wow wow really 1700 if you figure only 800 of them are any good
yeah right that's still a crap ratio yeah but not just that the big issue
that consoles have is that you can't take your console game to your PC right
yeah and well actually I think the bigger issue with consoles is next
generation bye-bye all your money that you spent on all those games where some
steam machine more likely than not your games are gonna be portable to your new
hardware fair point I do want to point out though you're talking about 1700
titles the NES I believe only had about seven hundred and eighty something
titles you know yes and yes actually had 385 right right I mean it is a huge yeah
it is it is a huge amount of titles really well what are you laughing at
what are you just just playing over here with with a with a little thing we'll be
reviewing later in the show yeah nice tease there Wes isn't that funny looking
there it really is yeah you guys will see what Wes is talking about I have your
screen capture setup too so we can show it to the video version yeah I just
thought see it you can already see it it's too late they've seen everything so
yeah I thought that was interesting 1700 titles congratulations something else
that came up this week I never even really thought about it but you guys may
or may not recall that I have been using spider oak on one of my machines so all
of my sync thing and my bit torrent sync and my Dropbox on one computer in my in
my office I have them all installed and on that computer I also have spider oak
installed and it backups all it backs up all of those peer-to-peer or non cloud
like storage based sync services to spider oak and so I'm and I'm like my
photos go to spider oak so spider oaks like one more off-site it's my final
destination that yeah sure there might be a few several copies here and there
but spider oaks like the master backup well today they ran a blog post post
yeah we ditched Google they say we gave it some thought and we realized we were
hypocrites since inception spider oak has been an advocate for online privacy
unlike others in our market we strive to be very clear about how our product
design truly delivers zero knowledge privacy for our users so for the past
five years we have been using Google Analytics for monitoring our web traffic
innocent enough decision right then we asked ourselves are we contributing to
mass surveillance of the web by using a feature-rich yet free service that
tracks web visitors sadly we didn't like the answer to that question yes by using
Google Analytics we are furthering the erosion of privacy on the web wow wow I
you know Google Analytics really I guess I guess it is a really great tracking
system for Google isn't it I mean let's them it's a little you know a little
insight into every little website that uses it man now I have to think about
this I got a wimpy what do you use for a buntum at a on the website are using any
kind of analytics package I am are you using Google I am I did I did I did look
into using P wick but the simple fact is I haven't had the time to actually you
know sit down and set it up right the other nice thing about it is that there
you know it's fairly quick and they're using real-time features so it's getting
more and more competitive too so how do you also it's great it's more than what
Google Analytics does and and recently I was reading about it I've got the tabs
open now I was reading about it as a means of effectively tracking podcast
downloads I looked into that as well yeah and it seems to be very good at
that mm-hmm so that's that's potentially we use it it's like nifty features JB in
the past I don't anymore but for a period of time and I used a really nice
wordpress press plug-in that just did this for me and it would append the
tracking code information I needed to be able to track downloads through analytics
and I would use that to verify the pod track numbers and what I discovered is
that the pod track numbers are crazy conservative pod track is what was sort
of the sort of the industry standard that advertisers respect and now I am
understand it's because they screw you on and downloads massively you know like
it's really interesting yeah like if it is it is they'll take out entire SWAT
like Wi-Fi downloads they'll take those out you know things whoa all kinds of
stuff yeah so it is really users yeah they're the worst they don't not all not
all Wi-Fi users but like public Wi-Fi and things like that they just cut it all
out anyways so analytics was a really nice third party way to sort of see the
gap there but I don't know you know I over the last couple of years have
started to think more and more about the long-term ramifications of Google
collecting this information not just oh they know where I've been this year but
what does it mean when they know after ten years of my web browsing history or
five years and am I contributing that to my audience am I you know am I am I
subjecting my audience to that so I've been thinking about it more and more so
to see spider oak come out with this post I don't know I also have not found
an open source solution that is compelling to me right it would be
interesting if there's wasn't so niche you know like they say here like like
lots of other companies with high traffic websites we are technology
company one with a deep team of software developer expertise so like they you know
they have people on payroll they can just spin this up it'd be interesting to
see that open source yeah you know more competitive and for me it's nice because
I can see okay what topics maybe we're a little more popular what topics do
people share a little bit more the other thing I have used analytics for is when
looking at 2016 and going okay well where should I take the rover and what
areas are likely to have you know enough people to meet up kind of get an insight
into where your base analytics gives me that so I just wanted to put the put it
out there to the audience if you know of a better replacement Linux action show
dot reddit.com I would consider you know I very much would consider replacing
Google Analytics if it was something that was fast maybe something I could
host on a droplet or or somewhere that would give really good response times
because I don't want it to cause my website to slow down and P wick is
really the only really those game in town yeah and you found it's good it's
good but I've not I've not set it up in anger I've only I've only played with
the demos but you know from what I've looked at it's the only option. This is
Linux Unplugged episode 122 for December 8th 2015
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's already feeling
a little bit of that holiday cheer aka booze my name is Chris my name is Wes
hey Wes guess what we got a pretty big show today we sure do
episode 122 of the Linux Unplugged show is here to put it in your face that's
right coming up we're gonna talk about Mozilla Thunderbird all of that
shenanigans what's going on with Thunderbird what does our virtual lug
think about it and then today today like salt in the wound Mozilla has a big
announcement and I'm gonna ask just what the hell's going on with Mozilla
and I want to see what people in our virtual lug think I want to see what you
think it is really something Wes we're gonna do a big expanded double segment
conversation on the state of Firefox Mozilla and Thunderbird it's a massive
massive project with major importance for the Linux desktop so we're gonna
dedicate a lot of time to it today then later on in the show new release today
crossover version 15 just came out now this is the application that made it
possible for me to switch to Linux years ago years and years and years ago and
they have their 15th version today I installed it on Wes's computer I'm gonna
give him a first hands-on boom dropping it why am I excited see what your
impressions are so we'll do that we'll go through and also I'll do the
installation live right here on my machine because I think it's actually
it's it's it's all kind of like no other version of any kind of Linux desktop app
it is really a unique installation process maybe a little more familiar to
Windows users I want to just show it to you guys to document kind of a slick
thing that they've developed for getting software installed on Linux and then you
can see what you can do with it so coming up later in the show we'll be
talking about all of that stuff and it is actually really cool what it can do
play on Linux is a thing I you know wine obviously you could run wine on the
command line but there is something that crossover brings to the table and we
also have a discount so you can save some money on it coming up later in the
show so we got a lot to talk about plus a bunch of other things some feedback
and follow-up so let's bring in that mumble room time appropriate greetings
mumble room hello hey everybody hey everybody welcome here it is you know I
feel like it is maybe gonna be one of those shows where we get cut off in the
middle because it is extremely windy and rainy here today it is it has been very
stormy and last time that happened we literally lost power in the last few
seconds of the show remember that it was like a lot of fun just stay tuned
everyone if we disappear we will do everything we can to go right right so
we have a couple of things I wanted to just follow up on before we get into
the main show because there is a topic that every now and then I feel like this
show is perfect to discuss because we've got you and I who are both big podcast
listeners and we've got our virtual log and a lot of them they got opinions man
and they are big podcast as well and so there was a question that was submitted
to the subreddit and I wanted to kind of kick it around it's not extremely Linux
related although I would be curious to hear people's Linux solution but it came
in from I'm gonna say Vinci but henchies how you say it he says I'm looking for
solutions to sync podcast between Android and my Linux desktop he says I
guess the title kind of explains it all but I'm curious as to what others
elegant or maybe not so elegant solutions to sync podcast between their
Android and Linux desktop my goal is to be able to listen to a podcast on my
drive to work and then sit down at work and continue where I left off and vice
versa now Wes do you have any solutions for this I'll go to you first I know
somebody the mumber must they must you know not in my own life I'm just only
listen in the car no you know I do listen I do listen kind of both places I
usually end up using something on the back end to sync sync thing what have you
to get the file and then do you just jump ahead I just jump you know it's not
usually not too many things at once that is enough to be like oh 42 53 all right
that's fine but I do wonder if something like Plex or MB I know MB will do
interesting and that's kind of already already has the multiple device you know
I'll tell you so my use case is I I drive a lot now it's ridiculous you
don't say and so I but but then like I really get into the show and I want to
finish it up as I get to the studio or as I get to the rover yeah and so things
setting up yeah and so I have or you know the other thing which has been
really nice is Hadid and I have been sharing some pockets like 99% invisible
invisibility and cereal which are great shows but like we only listen them while
we're in the vehicle together and sometimes we're in her vehicle sometimes
we're in my vehicle so it's really nice to bring the sync state between us and
and I love this as a podcaster because like the idea that we are like we're
almost saving up podcasts and watching them like you would a Netflix series or
something like that sharing them together so yeah I'm like this I want to
encourage this is great this is really exciting as a content creator that this
is happening so I wanted to find a system that would work kind of in all of
these different scenarios and wimpy I'm gonna go to you first because I know
you're a big podcast listener and a podcaster what are you doing right now
to kind of solve this problem because this must be something you face well
just recently I've been using pocket casts on Android for a long long time
and just recently I've discovered that they've now got a web player that stays
in sync with what you've been listening to on your mobile device so you can stop
listening on your mobile device go to your Linux computer login to the web
service which you have to pay another fee for so you pay once for the Android
client right and once for the web player but then you can switch between them
seamlessly and it keeps all of your podcast playback in sync plus you're
given you're given a great you're given a great podcast application a little bit
of money which I I don't think there is a better podcast playing platform out
there yeah especially to have something like this that's not tied with a bigger
corporation right in you know Apple's environment they're gonna have to get
bought up eventually I would imagine but maybe not they've got a decent sized
team they're making decent revenue right now they make a really good app on
Android iOS and and I really really appreciate this the the the tablet
version is really first rate and really tablets make for great podcast listeners
because not only they have a great battery life but they have usually
better speakers in your phone so you don't need to hook up any additional
speaker so just for going around the house a tablets a great podcast
listening machine and the pocket cast tablet version is great it's great in
fact to try that out we've talked about a lot we went in depth on Kota radio on
the design of pocket cast because they took a lot of what's great about
material and then went their own direction with it and it is really a
fantastic app so I it's like five bucks or look they even have the Windows store
good good we're covered guys that problem solved so it is it is really
quite fantastic and it'll also sync between iOS so like if you have an iPad
and an Android phone nice right and then the web player like wimpy saying this is
my go-to solution wimpy just just basically covered mine because it does
have sync it has continuous playback it also has server-side feed checking which
is very nice so server-side feed checking means that essentially they
check remotely for you so your phone isn't wasting battery life going out and
checking all these different RSS feeds then you only get the push when you get
the right you get the push when they found something new and I think that is
a fantastic way to do it because early on podcast catchers I'm looking at you
dog catcher and others on Android we're just battery vampires and so this is a
great way to do it you don't even need to have Android you can have iOS and
just a web player anybody else in the moment room have like a podcast sync
solution because this is a good one but you got to spend some money and it's
closed source and I'm looking for something free and open something that
could sync playback location maybe if possible you know and of course there's
things like subsonic and the thing that replaced subsonic the project that
replaced that but madsonic whatever yeah whatever yeah we talked about it yeah
we did a podcast addict is what is being mentioned alright so pocketcast I think
that's sort of the go-to as long as you're okay with spending a little bit
of in fact maybe I can show you guys the do you use do you use about you don't
use a podcast catcher at all I don't know what do you how do you listen to
and do podcasts on your phone do I just use VLC you're you're kidding me make
playlists if it's a long drive you're kidding me no really I'm old-school I
guess I was just about to say another option for something's like if you have
something that streaming player like if you have VLC on your at home and you
have that web interface or a console interface you can pause it and then just
attach to your if you if you have it you know port forwarded or on a digital
ocean droplet perhaps and you can just use do that way to keep things in sync
okay so it's play.pocketcast.com for the web version so like say I go here to
Tom's you know you go here to Tom's a daily tech show well I've got some
really crazy subscriptions and can't anyways these are not my current
subscriptions but let's say whatever the sex with Emily right have you ever
listened to sex with Emily no I haven't well it's not a good show but let's just
say you want to listen to sex with Emily and you were several minutes into it now
I'm not but it would sync up right here in the web I'm gonna hit play just to
get an idea what that looks like. Hey everyone thanks for listening to sex with Emily you know how much I love
sharing the best sex toys and products with you well on today's show I've got
not one but two lovey ladies whose entire business is helping people pick
the right toys for them and ways to enhance a relationship they'll be sure.
There you go ways to enhance your relationship Wes. Is the relationship with the toy or is
it with the human? I think it's probably with the human and the toy together but I'm
not sure I you know what that's probably that I'd have to listen to that really
great episode of sex with Emily to check that out but so say you want to listen
to sex with Emily I'm trying to show you here in the web version you have like 10
seconds back 30 seconds skip forward but the other thing that's really cool let's
keep listening to sex with Emily let's let's keep listening we'll go a little
bit further in oh it's nation it is today now watch this I love it I can speed up
playback right here in the web browser that is really nice now I can listen to
Emily in fast 2x speed. Shipmunk sex what could be better?
but you know hey you can customize it it comes with 7 vibration modes according to mashable the izzyvibe plans to launch in june 2016 so it's basically just attachment you just pull on it.
It's not so bad. No that's probably the best way to listen to sex with Emily.
So there you go there's Pocket Cast and uh yes I was playing with that and also
I the other thing I was playing with uh before the show because I thought I'd
be a little funny is um I fed in a custom AR RSS so check what
check this out Wes this was my little solution
because I was just playing around with different things on Pocket Cast and
uh I brought in are you familiar with Pinboard? So Pinboard's a great
bookmarking service that kind of replaces delicious and others
and Pinboard allows you to bookmark things with tags
and each tag can actually have its own RSS feed
so what I've started doing is I have started
tagging things with Pocket Cast in Pinboard
and then I can pull them in to a Pocket Cast RSS feed
already set up in Pocket Cast so when I jump in the car I can listen to that
I'm just starting to mess with that because my my main podcast catcher of
choice is Overcast which also has a web client
yes I've played with Overcast a little bit before yeah uh but Pocket so one of
the things that's been fun with Pocket Cast is I
so I have my own custom feed and the other thing that's nice about Pocket
Cast is it has a really good discovery that's how I found
uh sex with Emily there which uh of course had to put that in the podcast
see this sounds like a really good way if you wanted to share with someone else
who maybe wasn't up to like making that custom but if you
sort of picked podcast you wanted to share and they could just tune in and
listen that was actually what I was thinking
uh is I'm so uh I have a couple of different cousins
that at Thanksgiving were like all right let's talk about podcast
and I'm like all right let's talk about podcast let's do it and so
now I'm just going to be able to give them a feed and I'm going to put in a
bitly I'll just say subscribe to this feed
and I'll just start putting really good shows in there for you I'm going to do
like my own playlist for them using I mean only throwing in a few JB
you know now and again right and of course episodes with sex with Emily
of course yes and I'm going to throw them in there like you know some 99s and
some some other things in there that I just think are really good shows
and put them in there and they'll just have a nice curated feed and it's a
really nice way to send media to your phone in an RSS feed and
because pocketcast does that remote refresh
as soon as you open up pocketcast they're ready to go I gotta say that's
pretty that's pretty killer I mean that's
that's making me interested maybe my single mp3 files aren't enough
so uh Kitson you're a podcast listener what are you what's your solution for
listening on the go I just use my smartphone old school yeah
and what are you doing like Wes and using VLC on there or what what were you
using an app are you an animal what's going on
pretty much I just use the media player on my phone uh which
right now is uh dead beef oh I didn't realize they had a phone
version that dead beef is a thing on the phone like
it is uh you have to pay for the extra codex if you
listen to anything uh too fancy uh like uh
SNES rips and whatnot so if you're into like chiptunes
but I just use a uh I use a feed reader uh to get the uh podcasts and then I
just uh upload them on my phone and put them
in my playlist and it's interesting how many people do
that that is actually uh huh yeah that is uh G Potter is a great
one for the desktop being mentioned yeah all right any other thoughts in the
mumble room before we move on from this topic uh I don't oh okay uh hold on
whoever had the really great voice go first and then uh
who was that I think that was me is that hey citizen hey citizen what's going on
hey um yeah I was just gonna mention uh I use antenna pod
which uh also works uh with G Potter it doesn't sync location but at least
you'll have the same podcasts oh good tip thank you that is really
great so it just shares like your subscription
list essentially yeah oh that is nice yeah it uses your
G Potter account thank you okay so yeah yeah so G Potter
which is great one if you listen on the desktop now who was right after uh hey
citizen there that was me okay go ahead so uh I was
just gonna kind of extrapolate on what Wes was saying the same thing
um as other people are saying they have their desktop feeders that they like
so you just take your desktop feeder and you have it download whatever the
podcast is have syncing sync it to your phone
and then you can have automatic syncing over to your phone from your desktop and
have the same files wherever you go and then whatever
media you like to open those files with on your phone you can use that
you know what I would really like to be honest with you and and
there are some things that uh I would just like to be able to have and
I think it's so close but I just haven't connected all the dots yet
is I honestly would just love to be able to send the audio
from my phone to my desktop and just keep playing everything from the phone
yes and just walk in and be like okay remote audio send to my desktop and
because I have for editing purposes here at the studio I have nice
studio monitor quality speakers right and so if I can listen to a podcast on
that I'm going to right and I would love to just be able to
sit down and be like send a pulse audio server and then the audio from my
like kind of like apple airplay only only apple airplay lets you send to
machines you can send like devices we can't send
like a desktop I would like to be able to set or bluetooth audio or something
you know there might that might I know you can do the reverse I'm thinking so
I yeah there must be way to get pulls just to do it that way yeah
uh all right Mr. Blaster I'll let you have the last word on this one
so um I don't know if the first thing that comes to mind is maybe getting
like a google chromecast emulator or something yeah yeah receive
on on the pc but I have looked a little bit for like chromecast type servers but
google has actually been killing the project so I've been
so it's funny you say that because I have specifically like well maybe I
could make my machine pretend like it's a chromecast because well fuck it's
linux yep so I'll just put it on yeah no no no
which is a good topic I mean google I know we talk about google so
positively I wanted to make I wanted to make I wanted to make a whole segment
out of it and google keeps killing these projects and like
with lawsuit all kinds of threats it's it's not good stuff
but uh if you know of a way to do this blaster
so um I don't know of a way to do it with googlecast
however uh there is a product called air server
which emulates a uh an apple airplay um receiver and that works it is paid
it is proprietary and and commercial so you do have to pay for it but so
you're saying it would be easier to use my iphone to send audio to the linux
desktop than is my android that's the thing though I
think you can use anything I think I think it supports anything we
used it we used it in the office actually um we
installed it on the pc there is a windows version of air server
uh we had a windows pc running in the in the conference room
and then anytime we wanted to uh cast something with our laptops instead of
dragging out the old hdmi cable we just use this air server
but you're saying they have a linux version they do have a linux server
because they say mac pc i don't i don't think they have a linux
version i'd imagine it runs well in crossover
yeah i would give that a shot right yeah exactly that might be something to try
yeah in the same same vein upnp dlna there might be something there like
right there's already like bubble cast i think that's where your best bet would
be under android is to have a playback client that supports dlna
or some other streaming protocol and then find a dlna server
or some other streaming server on linux that it could connect to just send it as
a receiver and queue it up yeah that's what i think maybe the best
bet is but i don't i don't have all that put together
is that essentially what you were going to say kitson yes i was actually just
going to suggest uh putting a dla uh
server on your phone and just streaming it to your computer or vice versa
i have lc will play dla so i haven't looked too much into it i just did a
quick search on like pulse audio on android and it looks like there is pulse
audio on android so you could uh do the
audio stream so when you get home you connect to the audio stream and then
i would you have it i would like to try this i think this is worth playing with
so and i see rikai has got a couple of links in there he's busticating out too
he's the best yeah well rikai's got that google food like you wouldn't believe
uh okay huh so there's a couple different ways to scan so allcast is
what uh rikai is what is this
hey allcast is the new app that plays photos music and videos
all from your phone right to your tv watch this
it's like magic you know kitties are complicated what's
not he's holding an iphone he sure is complicated is the allcast app
it's so simple i'll play you a video
get off my lawn you yeah you with the ears i do love kids
but you know what how simple is that that's as simple as pie
hillbillies with mullets it's as simple as air or blinking
there's no more crowding around your phone it's the ultimate slideshow you
just throw it up on your big beautiful high definition television it's great
all right i'll check it out i'll check it out that is worth checking out so it's
called allcast and you can find it in the play store
there there's got to be something to it here but uh yeah interesting
all right anybody else have any last thoughts on syncing podcasts between your
mobile device and your desktop device before we get out of this segment
and and really i would love to hear what people do
that are listening too because i yes that's you know those these are the
people that are listening on in their commute right now are exactly the people
i'm talking to what are you doing linux action show at
reddit.com go find 122 and let me know because i want to i have one okay yeah
oh give it to me so i used to listen to a lot of podcasts
when i used to commute a lot probably about seven years ago when i
first studied listening to podcasts and back then i used to have it
synchronizing between uh you know my phone and um
my desktop and everything and it worked and it has continued to work since then
and unfortunately it's on ios they have nailed this and we still
haven't and it's frustrating and depressing
but it has worked for a very long time and we still haven't caught up
it's very sad and i actually and maybe you know
my perspective is perhaps you could suggest a bit skewed but i feel like
this is an area that is maybe more more relevant than ever on-demand
media is becoming the norm even for mainstream media right and to not
have a super great solution here is is kind of embarrassing because apple
has their crappy podcast client you've got uh of course google google play is
getting to the podcast scene there's going to be a lot of
proprietary solutions here for this or they're already here today
i'm looking at stitcher i'm looking at apple podcast i'm looking at you know
all those things that are already existing
and this is one more time on the linux desktop where it's like
you can do it but you have to hobble together your own solution
hobble together and how many times have we heard that phrase oh yeah you can do
it just have to hobble it together it is i hate that i hate that it's not a
good it's not a good answer surprising when you know when apple own you know
top to bottom the entire stack every platform that they're on they can do
that kind of tight integration across every device
across two different operating systems you know for a long time and keep that
integration working for a long time whereas we're constantly replacing our
stacks and replacing our frameworks and i would
argue actually no i have to disagree i have to i have to
disagree uh apple is constantly screwing up their
cloud-based solutions uh their cloud syncing stuff barely works
after all these years in fact for a company that's as rich as
they are it's embarrassing how bad their cloud infrastructure is and
they still don't have it working and they are
they are always changing even as a sorry one last point it's even as
recently as ios 8 they completely redid the back-end
storage infrastructure for how their cloud system works
i mean they're constantly making changes and and that
that may all be true but the only question you're asking about syncing
podcasts and that has worked reliably forever right damn it i don't
care about any of that other stuff but i'm just pointing out like
but they're they're fairly they're fairly a mess here and yet that's
they still manage to make it work i think that's actually my point right
which is like a bizarre yeah now wimpy what were you gonna say
uh well poppy was making the point that everyone keeps changing their stacks all
the time and i was saying that there's some people that uh are not basking in
the glamour of all the new and shiny but just you know
staying with tried and true yeah i i look at this now and i think
this has got to be something that we will figure out and there's
projects out there like uh vocal have you seen vocal i have not vocal
is it's under the umbrella of the elementary project there's things out
there that have been out there for a long time like g potter
and bash potter but none of them none of them
really have solved this problem g potter was ahead of it if you think about it g
potter created the g potter accounts yeah they've been they've been ahead of
this but they still haven't quite sealed the deal yet
maybe it's because they don't feature jp content is pretty i will say
yeah they have a nice kind of yeah yeah vocal is nice popcorn time-ish interface
yeah they do yeah they and the problem is is are you going to bet
on an elementary os project i don't know i don't know
i mean i don't know yeah i mean if you're i'm not saying it won't but i just
don't know about the staying power as yet
imagine imagine where you're you know the use case being you want to keep in
sync between you know your commute to work and then
when you arrive at work what if it's one device and you're on
your way to work with your phone you get to work and plug it in it's
not you're not changing application it's the same app you just unpause it
hold on you mean instead of remote sending audio or
syncing to files between two systems using some sort of third-party
proprietary service i just have one computer that does it all
that i already carry with me in my pocket every day everywhere couldn't be
done couldn't be who could ever dream up
something crazy like that uh i still well done papi half an hour
before you mentioned a window touch yeah that was actually not too bad
but this did have a point on that of why not to do that or why
to do the multiple setup system and that you have a nicer sound quality from your
desktop than you do your phone yeah absolutely yeah do android support
like usb audio devices could i if i already had
like a usb dac setup can you do that from a phone no but
you know what i have i don't think that i don't think you well
i don't actually yeah yes be on the go well because then there you go if
you've got a decent one that supports modular you know
devices yeah in fact uh uh noah's dad is trying to record his band using his s6
on ting we should probably feature that i'd like
to hear that uh so uh i think it's it's an interesting
point because there are we should mention physical solutions you
could also get a headphone jack you know you could hook up your your
your uh your speakers with a headphone jack to your phone
and the podcast that way and that would also work
so there are hardware solutions but i'm just curious what other linux users
uh do for this and this is probably a good um platform to ask that question
all right uh let us know your thoughts linuxactionshow.reddit.com or
jupyterbroadcasting.com slash contact speaking of mobile devices let's talk
about ting my secret weapon to actually giving my
small business real connectivity i couldn't actually
afford like the uh duopoly carriers uh prices no way
no you don't have like 200 a month just to throw away it's too on data you don't
i think 200 i let's so let's you know i actually think for so we have three
lines we're using right now on a cellular i think 200 is generous i
think that would actually i think it would be probably
boy i bet you couldn't get under 195 uh then you do taxes and i bet you're over
oh yeah that's tax 220 something like that yeah
uh you know it's great because my bill through ting like 40 45 bucks
wow yeah so go to linux.ting.com to support this show but also get your
get a 25 get yourself a 25 discount just off any device or if you've got a
compatible device with ting 25 in service credit because they've got a
gsm and cdma network probably going to work with a device or
you can get one of their sims which are right there on their on their
website or where else amazon amazon oh man i saw that that is
amazing that all of these things just go together to make it so easy to switch
someone to take you're like well you know they'll help pay your etf yes
get the sim card in like a day or two you know you have prime already yeah and
your phone already works so just switch there's no excuse and then there's no
contract so you have no early termination fees or anything like that
you just pay for your usage it's six dollars for your line and then your
usage on top of that and because they have the cdma or the gsm networks you
can kind of just plan where do i have better coverage
or you know like this was a legit thing on the road trip
where cdma is stronger in some areas and and gsm is stronger in other areas
so basically and my my observations kind of
show this to be true a lot of hills and trees
cdma a lot of flats or not a lot of big hills between you and the towers gsm
and and if you can do gsm you're going to get like i'm getting 21 megabits
just like you know uh four out of five bars
21 megabits rocking and that's the thing with ting as you know
they don't throttle you you pay for what you use so they have no incentive the
other thing i like about it is they don't get in the way of the updates
they're not you know how so many times the carrier is the blocker for you
actually getting the update yeah ting ting has zero incentive to ever
block the update ever they and in fact in most cases the
devices the the android devices you get from the ting store
are just the pure google experience they're not branding them they don't
have a ting store they don't have a ting cast
service they don't have any like a ting home phone service
they don't have that stuff right they want all integrate in one package and
the nice thing is they give you tools to really control this they have an
incredible online dashboard they have companion apps
for ios and android and these dashboards are legit
they actually work they give you full control it lets you set up names
and manage it it is a very nice experience and then they back it all
with fanatical support you can call it 1855 ting ftw
and human beings actually solve your problem they have incredible online
resources they have an active youtube channel twitter account and reddit
subreddit it is very nice it's basically mobile for anybody who's a little bit
technically savvy if you if you're a little technical set if you have a
little bit of technical cred and you're just sick of the duopoly
screwing you around and their crappy contracts and basically
screwing you for anything they can you could check out ting that's not part
of the ad read that's just my personal advice after
over two years of using ting if you're tired of taking it in the butt
go to ting go to linux.ting.com linux.ting.com
you'll save 25 off your first device they really do it right
and it's not just me that's been saying that uh consumer reports and this is a
really big deal just put out their annual report for
2015 and you weren't kidding they this is an
in-depth report i mean 90,000 cellular customers
surveyed 90,000 think about the work to do a survey of 90,000 people
like three people i don't know i'm done exactly dude i don't even
like people that much i'm done no this is really great so it
was like it was the choice of cdma and gsm that pushed them over
and you know their incredible customer service and the great dashboard
and the no hassling you uh when i was on the road trip i just i i had to call in
one time for my mi-fi device and i i just i kept expecting her to bail
on me like i kept it because like it was a very complicated problem
it was very complex and i just thought it like it got to a certain point i was
like it is okay if she doesn't want to help me anymore i understand she has
done everything she can and she she stuck with
me and she and we i mean it really was a 45
minute call it was it was it was longer than i was expecting
but i was so impressed that she really stuck with it so
you combine that with uh the fact that they have all the tools to manage your
account they have devices that are you own them
outright they're not locked down you get them off contract and then with
their with their with the rest of the ting service it really
it's obvious why they would rank so well but it is really cool to actually see
them get the recognition they deserve by consumer
reports annual cell phone service report so go to linux.ting.com
linux.ting.com and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring linux unplugged show
you guys rock all right so uh i think this is something that we
started to cover we we we started the conversation on linux
action show and i want to continue the conversation
here on linux unplugged and that is the conversation around
thunderbird and what the mozilla foundation wants to
do with thunderbird some of the ideas that are being kicked around
and i don't know if you saw this idea wes but there has been an idea suggested
that perhaps the libre office project would
take over stewardship of thunderbird and they list some
really nice benefits over on the libre office document foundation.org
wiki what are your thoughts on that you know it seems like there are at least
some people inside that strongly are against this idea or you know at
least think it's not the right time but it is a little interesting just
given how much microsoft has tied in outlook and their kind of email identity
solutions into their platform yeah yeah from the outlook angle it does make a
lot of sense right and and i would say that mozilla as we're
going to talk about has been floundering i don't know if
that's right i'm a big mozilla fan myself but
they've made some interesting moves uh we see a lot of their standard user base
kind of has moved moved to chrome or is questioning
staying with firefox they don't they don't seem as strong as they did and i
think libre office is an example of a huge success on the wiki they document
several advantages you could possibly even use libre office
as the writer for thunderbird like you can do an outlook
which a lot of my clients actually liked you can enable contact notes to support
complex formatting and pictures you can provide a theme for thunderbird to
make it look more familiar to libre office
all of that does have a i mean there's a web element
but that's kind of the worst part of email whereas the kind of like the
document the management the like it is note-taking it is record it that's
where it seems a little more libre office now as many of you probably
listening right now already know at this point
the libre office project has said they don't want it
no hard to blame them but don't want it one of the reasons behind the success of
libre office they say is our sharp focus on a single
application which side note was going to be my exact
criticism if this wasn't news by the time we went on air i was going to say
that is ridiculous and libre office needs to focus
this is exactly what they're saying they need to focus on a single application
just going to say i was going to get on a big old noisy rant about it but
they totally preempted that rant which is not going to change anytime soon
preach it they say we are already working on the android and cloud versions of
libre office and that is more than enough oh my god preach it in terms of
global effort for a community-based project we are tapped out they're saying
thank you oh my god this is this is this is great
they say they go on to say so please avoid any speculation based on rumors
as they might be intentionally created by our competitors
that's quite a statement it really is maybe a competitor put that rumor out
there like microsoft but it is really nice to see them at
least saying like no you know like we we have enough on our
plate we do i think you do already see a lot of
open source projects that are stretched thinly or
have a lot of ambitious goals which is great but limited development time and
i don't want libre office to suffer so i want to ask the mumble room and
we're going to get into the state of the mozilla foundation and what they're
focusing on later i want to save that for the
conversation i want to break this up but i will i do want to start with you
poppy because i know you have been commenting about this online so save
your thoughts on their current focus on what they're choosing to work on now
instead of thunderbird let's talk about that later
and and i would like your opinion on who would be a good shepherd to take in
this thunderbird project and perhaps would that person or project
need to be willing to completely scrap some of the base and start over or
or maybe they would be would they be somebody who just keeps it going i'd
like to hear your thoughts on that i'll start with poppy and then i'll open up
the rest of the mumble room i i don't know i have mixed feelings
because i i i use thunderbird and i feel that it's it's a great
product and it does exactly what you know it needs to do it's great for
you know personal cons and mailing lists and having large volumes of emails and
you know it does the job right and okay it might not be ready for the
next generation of devices it's not mobile ready for example but
you know as a desktop mail client it does the job and many people have used
it for many years and it seems okay so does this really need a huge amount of
work that necessitates being owned by and run by a foundation
or a company or some corporation or could this be
a community project that you know throw the code on github
put a ci system in place to gate all the merges to make sure reliability is high
and there's qa yeah and do regular releases it almost
sounds why does why do you have to have libre office or
apache foundation or colabra or any other company look after here's the
thing it it almost i mean it almost sounds like
you're talking down to thunderbird it sounds like you're kind of
essentially saying well if you don't have any aspirations to move forward
into the future why don't we just stick your code up on github
and and and let the luddites that want to continue to use
their old desktop paradigm poke at you and keep you good enough
while the rest of us go forward and create our new convergent desktop it
almost sounds like that's what you're saying
to some degree yeah because other people other people are making
mail clients you know there are the geary guys you know we've got
deco in ubuntu and there are there are other email clients around that are
being worked on yeah that maybe are because they're starting
later they can not have all the craft that
thunderbird has that people like i'm not saying it's bad
craft i'm saying it's good craft right right
maybe they maybe you don't need that and and maybe i'm wrong west but to me it
seems like uh to do a email is something we have had
now for a very long time and to get the basic
fundamentals of a good email client right it isn't it isn't the world's
largest software project anymore well just
just given the number of webmail apps that people actually do use on a daily
basis right i think that's a big part of this conversation too is
what exactly audience does thunderbird target yeah
yeah i i still feel like thunderbird has relevancy i mean i think noah is a great
example of that yeah or myself i like thunderbird too i i do
too uh i uh i wonder uh okay kids and i'll go to you and
then if anybody else in the mummer room wants to comment on this uh tag me i'm
curious to hear your thoughts on it and also
at some point i want to get to wimpy on somebody who's you know thinking about
the desktop experience and and and what fits that but kids and i'll
start with you go ahead uh what are your thoughts yeah i think the
big problem with uh all these uh newer applications such as
gary they're they're lovely lovely applications if you have basic email
needs but you can't use this in an enterprise uh someone that has like a
journalist or an activist wouldn't be able to use it because it doesn't have
features like encryption it's a security nightmare well the real problem with
gary is that yobra has shut down and there's nobody developing gary anymore
that's the real problem with gary so close and then yeah gary's dead
unfortunately at least it's a zombie right now um
and so that is a part of this is i have been burned by evolution and its
instability i've used i've literally used evolution
since it was something that was developed for the linux desktop
i mean i cannot i mean there has not there is not
there is not i i have i can't i cannot sit here and tell you in any confidence
that evolution is something you can use at scale
because i have seriously used it its entire lifespan it has never held up to
my inbox ever and i'm not trying to brag i'm just saying i have a lot of email
and this thing can't handle it okay so evolution and if you have minimal
uh email needs it's actually really great has a good ui and i love
love love that it ties in with the gnome calendar right that is a great feature
and so i actually set up evolution today still just to get that functionality
and there are other projects out there like like they're considering taking
gary and making it use the evolution back end for elementary os that might be
nice right so there is something there uh i've
tried kmail uh i've tried claws i i have tried so many
different but i've tried so many different mail clients and thunderbird
is fundamentally what i keep going coming back to lightning is a great
plugin enigma is a great plugin and thunderbird
has the ability to be connected to both my personal
inbox and my jb inbox and not dump its pants and and it can
do search all of these things like nothing
after all of these years has been able to compete with
thunderbird at just some core functionality that i need
and i think thunderbird has so much in that there are kind of like disparate
groups of email users right there's like the person who uses webmail and it's
fine for their personal correspondence and looking at
the new shopping ads or whatever and then you have people that need
outlook compatibility for work and thunderbird can work there in a lot
of situations you know or or are kind of a power user
and then you have the very power users who are using mutt in a terminal
and without thunderbird there there's not a lot in the middle yeah
in fact that's sort of i want to ask wimpy about the elephant in the room and
that is with gmail and yahoo mail and hotmail and
all these really nice webmail solutions like
mail pile you know that we're working on right yeah yeah but there are so many
that are closed source there are so many that are locked down that users don't
have access to the source code doesn't that almost make thunderbird
even more important wimpy and doesn't that make other open source mail clients
even that more relevant i think so i think that having um
open free desktop email clients is as important as having open
web browsers in particular when you look at something you know
as only what two months ago a month ago we were talking about nihilus
which is a very pretty looking desktop email client
but the way that it works is to abstract the email handling
to yet another back-end server so now your
email lives in two right um you know siloed data centers rather
rather than on your computer and i just think you know
with all that's going on in the world we really need to focus on
an email you know despite its flaws and despite how
things are sort of overtaking it is still
the main way that commerce communicate you know commercial
communication is conducted yeah can i pause you right there just for
a second just because i want to i want to just take a
moment to zoom out and appreciate the fact that what email is
is sort of like a federated network of social networks because
so you have a jupiter broadcasting server and say there's 35 people on that
server that i'll communicate but then we can send out to another
server that is completely different but it has a whole other network of users
we have agreed upon protocols in which we exchange messages back and forth and
though you can even be get ready for this encrypted which is
really remarkable and we have systems that automatically
scan and detect any spam communications between these
federated networks and what we have if you were to look at it from the web 2.0
social networking system is like this incredible distributed
social network that isn't controlled by any single company
and it is literally like nothing that would enter the market today
it's what i think it's what we would hope would right like we would love more
federated services like that email you it's a lot of work but you can stand up
your own email server and interrupt completely and and here's i know and
here's where wimpy's point to me really strikes a nerve is there are
companies like google who have introduced the gmail api the
gmail api is the appropriate way for mail clients to interact with your
google inbox not through imap not through pop3 but now through the
gmail api and they've taken the functionality of
gmail and they've exposed it as an api and you know what guess what it's better
than imap because it's newer it's more modern and it's more secure
obviously so there's a lot of advantages to using this new gmail api
but if you think about what that really is is that is taking something that is
this free open network and locking it down to an api
and so i think your point wimpy is is well taken
that these open mail clients are just as important as
an open web browser is for an open web and so i'm curious you know as somebody
who's looking at putting together a desktop
how does that influence your decision on maybe would you include a mail client
what would you want from that and does the state of thunderbird
really make an impact there i think it's too
early to say what decisions i might take regarding email clients
certainly in the short term i i won't be moving away from thunderbird and i shall
just have to be a spectator and watching
how things develop there are as you've said
there are other open source email clients
few can hold a light to thunderbird yeah i agree and so and i think
thunderbird's one of those projects that's important enough
that uh it's always there's there's always going to be a solution for
thunderbird users it's too important and too many users for
too long have used it it's been here forever i mean
yeah and businesses use it i mean it's it's it's going to be one of those
technologies that you're lucky it's open source i
wonder what red hat uses i mean they're such
you know big users of libre office bra what was it they use what they use
zimbra oh oh right yes zimbra of course i see
yeah yeah there is zimbra there is zimbra
all right well now i want to sort of shift the conversation
into let's talk about mozilla and let's talk about why
they can't manage a project like thunderbird even though it has
massive relevance and it is extremely important to the open internet
let's talk about what they are choosing to focus on
uh their brand new app that just hit the ios app store today
that only works with safari so let's talk about that and
let's talk about some of the other options and where we might see things
end up but first i want to talk about linux academy go
over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged go check out linux academy
this is a platform to train you about the systems that use linux
or the technology that rides on linux or the basics of linux
it is really nice and they they understand that you are probably
fairly busy so they have a lot of different features that work around your
schedule availability planners nuggets hands-on
answers by actual instructors things like that that make it possible for
even those of us who are very busy even in the holiday season
to take advantage of linux academy i think this would be a great gift to
yourself linux academy is something that when i
first started working in it uh the kind of courses i wanted to learn
from linux academy were some of the basics i was self-taught in linux and i
felt pretty confident but i began to realize as i worked with
other administrators as system administrators that
maybe there was a few shortcuts i could learn maybe i could learn to use things
a little bit better so i enrolled in a local community college
and i went to local community college to learn these things
and i was very very very happy to pick up a few
small things here and there but the time investment just
didn't really add up if i had something like linux academy
where you have scenario based labs where you'll receive
access to these labs over ssh that put you in the middle of task common to
everyday environments you work in these advanced lab
environments complete these scenarios from beginning to end
on live servers through your favorite ssh client and remember instructor help
is available the community is full of jupyter broadcasting members
and linux academy is constantly adding not only new courseware but features to
the entire platform itself like the new html5 player and their new
cdn and the update of the red hat certified
courseware and the stuff in the aws category that is
really really nice if you end up wanting to play around with s3
check out linux academy one of the other things i think is kind of nice about
linux academies because they're so passionate about
this community is they understand some of the things you might face
when you are trying to get out into the workplace or maybe
when you are trying to just upgrade your lifestyle a bit
it's hard to get that next job they actually have courseware on that
and one of the things that's really inspiring is when you log into your
dashboard you can see announcements from people
who have had success and it is it is it is very motivational i have to say one
of the things that i found about that is two things i love seeing the people
that try and do some of the same things that i am
have success doing it because you realize it is actually attainable to you
that is very encouraging but the other thing that i found that
works really well for me is the way it breaks it down in hours
things that were massive concepts like learning open stack
or python development we were talking about ruby and python on the pre-show
these are things that are broken down into hours on linux academy and i know
that they really care about this stuff this is what they focus on it's not just
a checkbox of a feature it's what they focus on that's such a huge deal i mean
even just listening to ads on the radio you hear like
three different services that do you know online learning kind of
oh they have all kinds of different services but this is focused on linux
yeah and and and and i know because i have spoken to the people that run
linux academy now for a while we've established a relationship
because they've been advertisers for a while now
and i i know what they tell me about stuff they're working on
and i know the back end tech they're using to develop that and it's all
linux it's all open source it's like they start there
and then they work with their educators and the developers to build it out the
platform it is it is seriously inspiring from one
content creator to watch them work on because because for them it's not
just the content that they're creating it's not just the courses they are also
building the back end infrastructure to manage it and deploy it all at the same
time not just like spin up a server and you have their
seven plus distros you get to choose from you choose that distribution
the vm automatically adjust to that distro and all the courseware adjust to
that distro that's a neat feature like to roll out as
an end user thing but think about the infrastructure they had to create and
develop to make that possible and and like when you're doing aws stuff
they manage like local uh virtual servers versus aws instances like
on all behind the scenes automatically for you
they really figured this stuff out because this is what they live
and breathe that's that's the human angle that really gets me like
can't i feel like many people in our audience you can imagine like oh i love
linux i'd love to teach people how to use linux for a job spread the
word guys have done it yeah and it's awesome and you should check
it out that is why i picked them as an advertiser so you go to linux academy
dot com slash unplugged you get our great discount
and it is a good value and it also looks good on a on a review or a resume
it is a good it is really a good service too by great people so go to linux
academy dot com slash unplugged and a big thank you to linux academy for
sponsoring the unplugged program you guys are
really had a great 2015 you guys are rocking it really good stuff
okay so uh today a couple of big things were announced uh
number one it was announced that mozilla will stop developing
firefox os smartphones they're done they're getting out of that market i
mean we don't have to talk about it anymore well i don't know about that
farewell firefox os smartphones mozilla today announced an end to the smartphone
os experiment and said it will stop developing and
selling firefox os smartphones it will continue the experiment on how
it might work on other connected devices and the internet of things
networks like tvs little things etc maybe i
hope so actually the announcement was made earlier
today at mozilla's developer event in orlando
and uh a lot of people you got to say mo's lando mo's right there
mo's lando what is that i see the reason why i didn't is because people
think i mispronounce stuff so often now that i avoid stuff like that there's no
other way i have mo's lando thank you thank you so uh that is a huge
bombshell and also uh poppy uh noticed uh via twitter and
also on google plus uh i like how poppy actually summarized
this he said goodbye popular desktop email client thunderbird
and hello ios ad blocker that only works with safari
so today they announced they're dropping the smartphone initiative
they also launched a ad blocker for the iphone that only works with safari and
they're spinning off thunderbird poppy you have the tweet so i'm
going to go to you first but i open this up to the whole number room but i'll go
to you first poppy uh has mozilla freaking lost it
i think they're they're having a bit of pain and
trying to rationalize the work that they're doing and i think they were
spread a bit too thin across a bunch of projects
and i i think it's sad that they're one of the very few
free software uh phone platforms is not going to be available in retail
stores but the way i understand it is they're going to carry on
developing it or it will still be available on github and people can still
contribute of course yeah um and you can still flash your own
device right i did this evening i updated my firefox
flame tonight so you know that i don't think it's it's
you know it sounds like a bad monty python sketch it's not dead it's resting
yeah it's not completely dead yeah i think it
it's just a bit of a shame that it's had to end
you know retail wise in this way because that that
that really doesn't mean it has much in the way of longevity if there's if
there's no and are you also worried about the
narrative that it now adds to for these you know third part these these these
uh up and coming smartphone os operating systems or these free
operating systems do you think it adds to a negative narrative now
so it depends who you read you know if you read
uh some of the comments on reddit they are you know
well you know what with uh y'all are having financial problems over the last
couple of months we don't know how that's going to pan out and
now this vague dropping of firefox os that puts all the pressure on canonical
for a bunch of os or the flip side is well look at those
two going down the pan canonicals next you know it depends who
you are yeah you can find plenty of arguments either way really and it uh it
is um it does sort of add a little more
scrutiny now to canonicals efforts because there
there's two less big contenders in the game now and
and so people are probably going to be watching what canonical does even closer
now don't you think well i wouldn't i wouldn't write selfish
off yet uh you know i i realize you know they're
under some financial pressure there's no other ones
but there's been two big contenders removed from the field
no but it would be very arrogant i'm not so sure it'd be very arrogant of us to
say hey you know we're still here and look at those guys they've gone
i i don't think it's that i don't think that's the the narrative that i would
i would read into it i think you know both of those projects are having
troubles you know we haven't exactly got you know
handsets in every market you know you can't buy a handset in the u.s
so you know we're not exactly trailblazing ahead of everyone here so
you know we wouldn't be arrogant enough to do that so no no i think it's
troubling i didn't mean to imply that i just meant to
i meant to suggest that perhaps every move now will even
be more watched because there's less contenders now to to comment just that
there are perhaps perhaps within within a certain set of
interested you know geeks and phone
aficionados and free software people yeah sure i wonder that i wonder i think
there's plenty of people who've never heard of any of them i wonder if that
means pragmatic open source evangelists will now start throwing more support
behind uh a bunch of bubble but uh i want to
give wizard jet a chance to jump in here yeah we can he says uh that mozilla's
been floundering for a while and he thinks this is part of it
wizard jump in and kind of expand on that what do you mean
yeah so for a while mozilla's been kind of
kind of like it's flopping all over the place i guess is the right thing like
i've been i i've had a firefox west flame since you
know kind of day one ever since it shipped
and i've been using it as a daily as my daily driver for
quite a while i stopped using it a couple weeks ago because i broke the
screen uh no it it's one of those things when
you start sitting in the community and you
really watch it you see all kinds of people
that kind of are saying you know everything that
all the resources that they have are spread so thin like they're trying to
attack a mobile operating system and a browser and you know and an email
client and they had instant bird which was
another project which is you know a chat client
and then they were also integrating the chat client into you know into
mail now so thunderbird does that too now so like
they have so much resources that are spread over such a huge
area that they're trying to attack and then you
just have all the chaos that's been going on you know like
for example that the whole thing with with ike leaving
um mazilla you know i'm not going to get into you know the whole controversy
behind that but you know like this all came down and
like it's just been hit after hit after hit
and i don't think they've ever gotten the chance to kind of stand up and say
okay i gotta find my footing now where do i
step next yeah and i think this is them trying
but you know it's here's the thing that i the whole thing so poorly
here's my here's what i take issue with if that is the case if they're
refocusing you know what's the brand let's figure this out
let's double down uh uh and and i don't i don't quite
understand then where this ios ad blocker thing is coming from it's
a little weird they're they're trying they're trying right now
because and they say it again and again like if you if you go to their their
subreddit or firefox they always everyone the whole
narrative now is we're attacking general users we care
about the general users we don't care about power users they'll figure their
own thing out all we want is the regular people and
regular people have ios devices and regular people have android devices
you don't have yeah you know what else though regular people use safari
and chrome exactly how much regular people have to choose their web browser
right like they don't think it was regular people that spread firefox to
begin with exactly not at first anyway now when it
counted yeah regular i agree with blockers either
no no they watch all the ads that's true i mean we should be thankful for that
that's what let us get away with blocking all the ads but
that's true well on on ios i think there's a lot of um uh publicity
around the integrated ad blocking on ios now because
people have noticed that there's a significant performance gain to be had
by blocking all of this stuff on a on a on a mobile
device yeah yeah you know people don't notice it so
much on a desktop because your desktop isn't
like so constrained resource-wise but on a mobile device there's a lot of
advantage to blockings not you're not downloading stuff
over your 4g or 3g or gprs connection and not
using those precious cpu cycles to render an animated
video or an advert or something that's bad exactly so
you know this is a compelling product there's there's a there's a market there
the guy who created one of the first ones you know
went gangbusters and you know people were all over it and
paying him you know wanting to throw money at the screen to get an ad block
for ios so there there certainly is a market for it and i think they've been
quite canny in creating a product a positive product
when all the other mozilla news today has been negative
so you think them having a let's let's just give them the benefit of the doubt
and let's say the mozilla or whatever whatever brand they're putting on that
sort of helps it move to the top you think that that maybe will give them
that that's sort of like a way to introduce them to new users as like a
it yeah it feels weird that they'd be making an ios ad blocker but the it's
really more subversive the long-term goal is to introduce them to the mozilla name
and then maybe they'll switch perhaps yeah and the fact that it's called
focus you know the whole it seems like their
whole all hands meeting is about focus is about getting rid of the
the products that they're they don't need to focus on and focusing on things
that are going to potentially keep the company going and keep revenue coming in
and keep their um their mission statement
alive you know the the open web and and keeping things
um you know right for the users how are mozilla going to make money off an ad
blocker when so much of my question you is advert
right generated yeah and and wimpy too aren't they then like
damaging potential future revenue sources that could keep them alive
well you'd have thought so it's a difficult conversation to have with your
ad networks isn't it yeah maybe it's hey we'll block your competitors
well annoying ad networks well this i don't know this is also
a trend at the moment isn't it to have an ad blocker that doesn't
right yep so you would like to have some views
yeah and they come down like boy if that's the case that feels dirty though
that doesn't feel very good it also could very well be that they're just
going to try and to live off of their whole you know we're going to
set your search provider to yahoo and then we're going to get money from yahoo
or whatever they choose which by the way is horrible
that yeah that's the biggest thing running linux mint this week
yes that is the biggest thing is i was trying to use firefox but just the
fact that they defaulted to yeah they were unusable yeah yeah no uh
it's for people who like to mess with computers that was the biggest thing
that i noticed and i completely failed to mention it in my
review on on last because it didn't seem like in
comparison everything else worth mentioning but
the search results on mint suck so bad because you just you come to expect
as it as somebody if you've been on the internet before and never
searched on google you expect things to look a certain way and work a certain
way and so you got two options on the mint
desktop your first option is to use the built-in search in firefox
which uses that horrible yahoo search which it's so bad it really is bad i
mean i tried it like i kept trying to use it but i was trying to set up
linux containers other technical things yes i think for regular google
you know regular searches i think it's terrible okay probably it's terrible
especially for the technical linux specific
questions like but then but then so then your second option is when when you
launch firefox on the mint their desktop right there it
brings a mint start page up and what uh clam or some of the folks
at the mint project have done has gone ahead and embedded one of those
sponsored google searches yes right there and so you start
searching in that but the thing is that also looks like a
clown show and there are links all over the place
theme yeah it is it so so so what so what i'm trying to tell you is the out
of the box experience on linux mint is your web searches feel and look
horrible and and result like there it is the worst out of the box
web search and experience ever and it's a weird thing to say but it's true
isn't it wes yep and i think even just going with like
duck to go even would be like way better 50% better at least yeah no
there's bang g and you're it would actually look right so and
something i something i think you have to understand
is it it doesn't look it looks like scam search results
they all look like ads or they all yeah right it looks like
phony crap and so it all i don't i don't trust
i don't want to like my my instincts are i don't want to click any of that i
don't want to click that i don't know what that is i don't know if that's a
legit research result or if that's a sponsored search result
and and uh i find myself actually having to go to google.com
and then so here so i'm going to pull it up there so wes has got it there on his
machine and there you can see there's the firefox
page uh so wes go back to the home page there
and do a search for like linux or something in there i don't know just
search for something just because i want to show people
like you see how they all look like ad results they all look like ads don't
they they really do it is no good it is no
now okay so go back uh and now search for linux in the firefox
search box go up to the search box there and search for linux
and yeah you see uh oh you switch it to google you already switched it to google
yeah you said here here you go this is what you see yeah there you go and
that's actually not so bad but it's still not that good there's too much
going on there and i gotta say just just the i don't know it really speaks to the
quality of google is and i hate to say it but yeah the
search results that you get are a lot more meaningful
and it's a lot easier to decipher what's meaningful and what's not it is really
like you so you know you sat down and within 20
seconds you had it changed you already fixed it i don't think i i
think you changed it oh maybe rika i changed it rika
thanks rika he's got everything here yeah well you know it works in the
studio rika did it rika knows what drives me crazy uh
so yeah he probably fixed it but uh it is it is not a hard fix but uh
defaults do reign supreme and so it was and it really bad out of the box
experience that i just neglected to mention
because uh it made me feel it made me feel unsafe
and i think it's one of those things where mint has so many other defaults
out of the box that do are are better than other competitors
it sucks that this one is worse also it's using
firefox uh anyways
uh just kidding i love firefox uh i found this whole
mozilla conversation to be rather fruitless though i don't really know
i guess i like poppy's take on it that maybe this is their way to try to
introduce mozilla to the masses uh it seems like honestly perhaps giving
up on firefox os and focusing a little more is actually a very
reasonable thing to do um i had some hopes pinned on the project
so that's why i'm a little disappointed i am as well
but i to be honest with you uh if i am looking at it objectively it makes a lot
of sense if you have limited resources limited funds and limited time and
compared to like canonical they have a lot less experience
packaging and operating system which is different than a web browser it's true
that's a good point i just i just would love now to see where
this new philosophy takes firefox itself and i think
yeah exactly because mozilla has been a good bastion for
the open web like they say you know it's a little cliched but
it's true and i think we do i hope that they succeed because i would like there
to continue to be an organization that represents that that's exactly it that's
exactly it uh kids and i'll let you take it out
because i know you've been wanting to touch a point on the
identity thing so go ahead expand on that yeah i think that uh
mozilla is uh basically you know they're they're a company with a history they've
been around uh for almost 15 years now they have
uh an identity crisis right now because they're trying to figure out where the
market's going to go next then you're just
unable to do it so they're just sticking their finger in the wind seeing which
way it goes that's why they uh you know want to
abandon uh thunderbird and that's why they've
abandoned uh uh nightingale which is their music
player they've also abandoned uh their standalone chat client
i don't think anybody's doing much development on chatzilla
either uh and the other thing is is firefox is such a huge product there's
all this technical debt that goes along with it
uh like zuul and all of that kind of stuff that they need to
maintain yeah it's a difficult position and
uh thunderbird has inherited a lot of that technical debt
yep and so there are there is a very honest discussion going on right now of
maybe it's time to rebase and that would be basically a reset
qt thunderbird anyone yeah i'd be down for that i would
actually think that'd be right i think that'd be really good that sounds
wonderful yeah i i'd like to see a no native uh
yeah sure sure oh man of course this how it's gonna go
there'll be a thunderbird core right and then there'll be a
thunderbird qt and a thunderbird gtk and a thunderbird etc
thunderbird there'll be a thunderbird web of course and then we'll still
complain about the dependencies it pulls in when you try to install it
and it's going to run the thunderbird backend is going to run on top of node js
you just wait of course you wait it's going to happen
oh man we've called it here we need our own red book yeah we do we do
that's a good that's a good end of 2015 prediction right there i think that could
happen actually hey you know what else could happen you
could have your own cloud server in less than 55 seconds go to digitalocean.com
and use our promo code dio unplugged one of these days we should demo that
we should just spin it up on the air because it is a hundred percent true
how come 55 seconds i don't know we could like and we could like you know
each time we could do like a different kind of server
it is that's a great idea west because it is a really easy way to get going with
your own linux rig up in the cloud that is super fast
their entire infrastructure is linux based ssds for their
for their hard drives 40 gigabit e connections to each hypervisor you can
get started in less than 55 seconds and pricing plan start at only five
dollars a month use our promo code dio unplugged one
word lowercase you get a ten dollar credit try that five
dollar rig out two months for free you get 512 megabytes of ram
20 gigabyte ssd because like i said they're all ssds one cpu
and a terabyte a terabyte of transfer and they've got data center locations in
new york san francisco singapore amsterdam london germany
and choronto that's the funsa data center
i'm just putting that out there they don't say that but i mean come on
yep uh and also it's that interface dat interface is so simple yet you get
everything done you can create your machines
you have an acml5 console to watch your machine from the bios post all the way
up to when the operating system starts i do too very nice very nice no flash
needed nothing like no java of course not you don't need that java runtime
that won't even work in today's modern browsers don't get me started about
mustaches and java i have rants for both the number of load
balancers that have never updated it just drives me wild
also one of the things that's really great about digital oceans is they've
digital oceans digital oceans has got lots of linuxes
in their ocean uh obviously they're going to have your abuntus why not
you got your latest abuntus you got your ltss they also have sent os
ah oh now that's starting to make sense yeah or debian you know you want to go
old school just good old tried and true debian they have that available as well
but one of the things they did that was really cool
is they worked upstream with core os and freebsd to make sure that they're just
boom right in with the channels from those
projects to get updates directly they got the latest fedora up there
because yeah fedora is making progress and especially with dnf upgrade
i've got a fedora 23 digital ocean droplet that i'm continue to upgrade
from release release and just see how it goes yep you can see how that goes
but one of the things that's really nice about their interface is their one
click deployment of applications i tell you what you can get something
deployed that's super fancy in no time you go to digital ocean.com you use the
promo code do unplugged and i tell you what you'll love it in
two months now poppy you just created a droplet
right now yep during the show i was uh while you
while you were talking about ting i noticed there was an advert
or a an article about um a daily show with uh
john stewart had been on it and uh i clicked the link and it didn't work
because i'm in the uk and it says no you can't use that
right so i thought i'll screw you so i spun up a digital ocean droplet
brilliant grabbed youtube dl on my droplet
grabbed the video and then pulled it down to my local machine and i'll watch
it later i tell you what it's handy down done it's rather handy they have they
have data centers in london and they have data centers in san francisco
and new york so depending on your preference
and that api right like so what poppy just did
that could be one shell script it's up ansible installs everything it's done
right i mean it's beautiful it really is pretty slick and you know the great
thing is is because honestly i would never write that code
the code's already up on github there's a lot of good code yeah you pull it down
you run it you're done you're done bob bob is indeed your uncle and you can
say hi and merry christmas to bob so go over to digital ocean dot com
and use the promo code do unplug there's so many things you can use it for just
like we have and i think uh that do unplug code will
give you a little opportunity to try it and see what you can do you'll be pretty
impressed you'll after your first package upgrade
or update you'll be sold oh it's so fast so it's
awesome it's awesome plus what you spent five dollars oh man
so i want to try something kind of never done before here on the unplugged show
are you ready there wes probably not but let's do it anyway i
want to talk about crossover 15 crossover 15 came out today
and uh it is um their release that includes
wine 1.8 the latest wine 8 which you know brings like
tons and tons and tons and tons of improvements they have experimental
early support for like directx 11 in this 11
11 that's impressive yeah and also crossover now uses pulse
audio as the back end sound system and they've completely
redone the user interface completely redone the user interface
uh for uh for linux so crossover office if you're if you're not if you're not
familiar with it is a linux desktop application that
takes wine and really repackages it and if you're watching the video version
here i'm installing it right now on my computer and i wanted to go through this
installation with you because it's kind of familiar but not for the
linux desktop and and and this is really this is
really where crossover begins is if you have come from the windows
world to the linux world this immediately feels familiar it's a
setup wizard so chris how did you start this
oh you know the story but the long version is the short version of the long
story is i had to have exchange compatibility in
order to use the linux desktop at work and evolution wasn't doing the job i had
to be able to use outlook and and and i was kind of new to linux
desktop and what crossover gives you is a really
sort of out of the box simple and back then
everything was installed from cd like so it managed all of that right
so it would tell you when to insert new cds
and out of the box with a wizard i could install office have full outlook
and be ready to go license it like normal yeah oh yeah oh yeah so anyways
i'm going through the installation right now so it installs an opt
cx office which is where all the best stuff goes you know
puts itself aside in the file system that actually is really
kind of handy because you can you can have crossover wine and you can have
regular upstream wine installed like separate bottles and the whole plan and
so that's very nice so now it's installed here on the desktop
and i can hit finish and when i go to my menu there will be a crossover entry
that was that is created and i will launch crossover here
and you'll immediately notice the uh if it launches oh
so this is actually kind of nice it doesn't do this on all distributions but
on ubuntu based distributions or debian based distros it does do this
and it says there are several uh dependencies that i need
in order to make wine applications work correctly so it immediately launches
the terminal ask me for my pseudo password that's the big part right there
gets it in there and then installs the dependent packages
that are necessary to make sure that you're out of the box experience
actually is pretty nice and so this is something that you wouldn't
starting right here when you're trying to run your own application under wine
you would need to go google well why isn't my wine application running yes
and maybe this is your first time on linux you're trying it out seeing if you
can make it work yeah or or really even if you've been
using it for a while like do you okay just it's so instead of having
to do this i try to launch the application it fails
and then okay i go get this dependency now i need this dependency and
each one is a google search before you even try to do anything this says hey
this environment's never going to work you need to install a few packages
and then it goes out and gets those packages for you automatically so you
never get into that game of trying to figure out what dependencies
need to be installed to run this properly it just manages that for you so
i i actually think that is worth some value
right there but then once you have once it does that it brings you up to
their brand new interface this this doesn't look anything like
crossover has looked under linux for for a decade now
and you click install software one of the first things that happens
is it says hey for better results i could go out and get a new update of all of
the available applications that will work under crossover
would you like me to do that and i always say yes so i say always update
and it has a ui for telling you it's sort of like going out and getting a new
list of packages and then after it's done i
will have a category of app i will have broken down by categories
different applications i can install so i can just search for something like
quicken i hit search and it will quicken uh basically
every version of quicken is on here although i don't know why the search
isn't working oh there it goes quicken and so you can see even up to
quicken 2016 is on here so if you need to use more quicken than i would ever
want to run i know right but if you if you want to if you need
to if you need to use quicken under linux and uh
this is something the crossover development team
specifically focuses on to make sure this application works even got a star
rating yeah exactly yeah and there's other things in there that don't
necessarily have such a good star rating
you can also just browse the available applications so uh you can go and you
know go to games and you can go to uh online games and a
good thing here is like this installer doesn't look horribly
unnative right like it it fits right into what your desktop experience
yeah and so say i wanted to play star trek online because uh
well you do well it's star trek and i do actually want to play it
you click it here it gives you the rating and when i say continue one of
the nice things is is there's several installation options for the installer
source it can get the star trek online installer
for steam we also did this with a batman arkham city
earlier before we started the show it can download the installer directly from
their website or if i have the installer locally i can
just point it at that i don't so i'll just say i can choose
download the installer now when i continue
it will create the english version uh it will it will go and get the english
version of star trek online it will download the file it will create
a windows xp bottle named star trek online and then it will
begin to install the additional dependencies that it needs like directx
internet explorer because the launcher uses internet explorer to render
right so it installs internet explorer it gets the minimum versions of those
that it requires to function and then it locks it all down into a
static bottle that is isolated from all of the other wine
applications i use so their changes will never affect my
ability to play star trek on you randomly
right it'll just work so that is the go ahead uh i've used uh play on linux
quite a bit yeah now i've i've resorted to
saying i will only accept native linux content because i always seem to hit
one issue is we use cdns now we use steam to
get our games and our games that may be windows based but use steam
whenever that updates you hit wine regression
does crossover have a particular way of dealing with this to where your games
and your save files don't just break because that's my main issue with play
on linux i can't really answer that because that is
always a possibility but so the way crossover so we before the
show did batman arkham city and arkham asylum and uh
what what crossover does is it creates a bottle for each game so that's like an
isolated container to use today's parlance
and it actually installs directx in that bottle it installs steam
windows version in that bottle you log into steam
it then downloads batman arkham asylum into that bottle
and here i'm gonna pull your screen up west and it installs steam then steam
goes out and gets the game and it uses the steam game
to actually use it so i uh the answer is it's it installs windows steam it
installs it uses that client so that's kind of
the usage paradigm and then crossover seems to be built for that so there you
go west just lost windows steam here yeah windows steam which is kind of
weird because it looks a lot like linux team it really does which i mean
testament of out there so west why don't you okay so minimize steam there and uh
why don't you launch like uh this is an example uh the excel viewer
there just you can double click on that as an
application and uh it will it will look like the regular
old version of excel viewer and i want to then what we'll do
is and you have to do the trial you have to acknowledge the trial because i
didn't register it on there there you go so look it's got the nice new uh what do
they call that a beautiful what do they call that i forget the ribbon the ribbon
it's got the ribbon that is the excel viewer now west go ahead and close that
uh and get it out of here get it out of here west and click on install windows
software there and let's just walk through that it's
the bottom of the ui there uh and why don't you search for word
viewer in the search box there because this is free
it'll just automatically download it off the web it could install full-fledged
office as well but you would actually have to have
the installation media i see which we do not have here at jb1 studios no of
course not so okay so search for word or or you
can you could probably just put word in there or something like that
and it will come up and and it has it here we go
would you like 2003 or 2007 so this is the nice thing too
it is sometimes you want older versions of windows software for compatibility
testing you're getting from your client etc
and so this bottle environment makes it possible to have different versions of
windows software on your linux box so which one did you choose 2007
yeah because that'll do the the docx so then you say continue
and what's it say there it's going to go out and get those files english version
you'll download the installer install into a new windows xp bottle named
microsoft word viewer 2007 so even if you're just looking at the bottle you
know what's in there and what's nice so you see how they did windows xp
is what they do for windows software is the lowest common denominator
that way it's not going to try to do something super fancy it's not going to
work under linux all the updates all the patches right and and the software goes
oh i'm on xp i'll just give you this and it's just
honestly functional right it's just basic okay so hit next there whatever it
is install whatever your option is and now it goes out and it's going to go
out and pull out each individual dependency and say trial there because
we're just doing the trial version now this is going to walk you through all
of the software you would need to install before you could run the viewer
chris i have to ask do you accept the license agreement
hold on wes i'm not so sure uh
yes i'll accept all right let's do it live on air you can just hit next you
don't have to put anything in there and just yep next next next all right so
you're going through it's it's bringing you through
each type of dependency package like the redistributed files libraries the real
experience installing microsoft software
yeah it's a real msi installation you're going to choose your so there you go now
you just now hit ok and now hit ok there and you'll see in
the background crossover will finish things up it'll get any of the last
things that need to be done is downloading these off of microsoft site
right now for you you don't have to go get these files yourself
and now it's done and now it's been added as an icon there
and also wes it adds those lamo yeah and it also go into your menu there you
can close this go ahead and close this uh and then go into your menu there and
if you look around like i think if you go into crossover anyways or maybe an
office category yeah an office it i think go to your office or did it add
them to your office category you know i don't i'd only see libre
office right now okay yeah i'm not yeah i'm not sure if it
does with the viewers it will it can integrate them oh here we go windows
application there's a whole separate category oh yeah yeah yeah yeah it can
integrate them in with the desktop menuing system as well
that's really nice it is really nice and so this
especially for you're trying to migrate your friend to linux right you install
this you set it up and they're right in their start menu i
say with quotation marks quote unquote it looks you know right like they can
just load word if that's what they need for work or whatever yeah
so it is uh it's a pretty nice ui and oh uh if you go go here wes
to uh let's see i think it's a view i'm not sure what the
menu option is there there's a way to view bottles or so
bottles show bottles here we go yeah so there on the left there it has broken
out each container environment in a so you can have different service
packs dot net installs if you right click on like one of them
you have different options like you can shut down all of the running processes
in that bottle so if you've got like a windows app that's being we can run a
command install software into bottle that's awesome
yeah and you can also launch control panel applets you can manage like
your different control panel settings you can open the c drive right there you
can modify it yourself if you need to which
is something you need to do if you're going to use if you're going to play star
star wars old republic through crossover you need to be able to right click on it
and go edit one of the launcher dot settings
wow files and it's it just makes it really easy to do all of that
so uh anyways it's crossover office version 15 now here's the thing wes
uh and us linux users we're not used to paying very much for software no we're
not it's 60 bucks it's 60 bucks uh
but they do have a promo code going right now i got info in the show notes
and uh you can get it if you use like the promo code what is it here um
cx 15 you get 50 you get 25 off for their new religion and i will say if
you are a user of wine you know these people contribute yeah
like all this goes back upstream that's the other thing to mention
so and so you are helping uh future development of the wine project and it's
a lot of work can you imagine being a wine developer like
that's a lot of thankless just like oh how do i make this microsoft crap
work on the linux desktop yeah right that's a lot of work so
it's kind of cool that there's a commercial effort to help support that
effort yeah and the 60 bucks is for this version but they usually do
many updates and like when the new versions of ubuntu or fedora or open
suso when major versions come out they generally issue a new update and
your purchase covers those updates for this version nice
so i always buy every major version and then i just get all of the updates for
like a year or whatever it is and i end up installing it on any serious
workstation where i want to be able to run any windows application
because you know i almost prefer to use things with regular straight out
wine because i just drop to the command line wine the executable name i'm good
to go right yeah but if it's ever more advanced
that there's dependencies or i want to be able to revert or take snapshots or
something that's going to be installed like appliance life long term or
like my game like star trek online i just want it to work
and that's where i use crossover and i i don't know exactly how long i've been
using it but i think i've i think i think since
2003 but i'm not i'm i'm not quite sure it's been a long
long time and i've bought every single version
they've never ever paid me to promote it they've never paid me to talk about it
and i almost don't even know you exist yeah no they don't exist
uh we actually might talk to them on friday
uh before uh the linux action show they were going to join us today but the
scheduling just didn't work out because their
ceo is on vacation but he may come back on friday and if he is back we'll talk
to him and maybe we get that in the linux
action show so uh anyways yeah go check it out we'll
have links in the show notes it's just a really great piece of commercial
software that's managed to be around for a long
time um and i i like that about it and it's
available it's been available for the linux desktop and it's made switching
possible and if quicken or something like that
is one of those few applications you need to get and that's a big deal for a
lot of small businesses huge huge huge actually it's a huge deal
i've used i've had to use it myself in the past
it's i think it's up there with auto cad and photoshop
definitely i think it's a big deal they make it work oh also photoshop
i think with starting with cs which isn't the latest
but cs and earlier um work beautifully under crossover just give
you all of the stuff you need to get it going
you just point it at the installation file and it sets everything up for you
integrates photoshopping with your desktop it can you can even associate
you know file extensions with photoshop it's like having adobe photoshop on your
linux desktop full full full-fledged and if you're okay
with things like version 7 of photoshop which really is
fine really it is flawless under crossover
there is like nothing that doesn't work it's amazing
and and it i mean it is good enough under crossover that i think you could
use it full time as your daily driver and it just that's a
big deal so they take they make quicken and adobe photoshop
very easy for non-experienced users to get going under linux and i just don't
think the project and the company gets enough attention
and the other thing that burns me is they make way more money on their mac
product which is total shit wow because they've been around for linux
way longer and if linux users would just step up a
little bit and buy something from time to time
uh then we wouldn't yeah we don't pay any license fees so yeah and then they
release cash in your pocket and then they release something for the mac and that's
what sustains the business after all these it's just it drives me crazy
so we go out there and buy something and uh yes that is true uh it is uh it is a
proprietary which is negative in the freedom
dimension but it is a commercial product that contributes upstream
right i mean i think we see similar things with valve
with netflix right these are all kind of areas that are
open source ish in some ways yeah they're not quite at the end user
perspective but they might help our cause in the long run
yeah uh all right so i wanted to mention something
so now we're talking about stuff you can pay for let's talk about stuff you get
for free uh we are doing swag for the holidays we
just gave away a really really cool linux action show
glass coaster which was neat it was a thick piece of
glass with the linux action show logo in there
uh we gave if we were giving away all kinds of swag
if you have successful patreon payments in november or december for the
patreon.com today or patreon.com on filter
patrons pages patreon pages paid i'm confused patron pages
uh then you just have to watch for swag links in the show notes of any show
sometime in december like kota radio or other shows text
snap shows like that there's swag link wait just
click it there's just a link in there just swag links in there
and then you get entered to draw and if you think about this
the pool is not that big so you have to be a successful patron
so you can just go which means you love jb a whole lot and you're helping us you
keep us going patreon.com today you have to be a successful so that so
you know the total number of people that is because that number is right on the
patreon page and then there is only a subset of those
people who are going to click the link and enter
to get the swag so i'm just saying is a hatched the chances of actually
winning something are extremely high and uh wes you saw
when you got here it's beautiful this is badass is what this is
full christmas fever yeah so and and legitimately so
each one of those boxes has wrapped swag for each show
whoa each show has its own individual swag that is unique to that show that
is a callback to the show that when you enter the swag drawing
we'll be giving out through december and and maybe january depending on how many
people say no way uh and they're all extremely cool uh
that that lamp you can see the lamp there oh the lamp
is so cool it's great angela is amazing yeah it is and
each ornament has a uh has a special show saying on the back of
it so you can see the front of the ornaments there
but each ornament on the back of it has something unique to the show looking at
that after the show yeah and each each box there has a unique swag
item related to each individual jb show so here's how you get in go to patreon
dot com slash today or unfiltered depending on where you want to invest
and then you will be entered for the drawing once one more thing
you find the link in the show notes for the shows that you got to pay attention
here and once you go in there you have those
two things bada boom bada bing bada boom bada boom bob's your uncle
say hi to richard you're entered and that's all you got to do it's it's
it's really quite easy that's just a false belief
get him out of here get him out of here all right so there you go i just wanted
to mention that patreon.com today also helps
all of the shows wes was there anything else we wanted to cover before we get
out of here i don't think so no all right mama room
is there any final thoughts you wanted to have before we get out here anything
that doesn't go into the post show going once going twice
all right they have spoken west that brings us to the end of 122
now i would invite you to join us live next week
because it is the last live show before the holidays we'll be back the week
after christmas but the christmas week there's going to be no unplugged live
that's crazy we do have something very special that will be going out
so please watch please tune in but it won't be live
so why don't you join us next week for 123 hang out with us for the live show
jvlive.tv everyone's welcome yeah and also submit content linux action
show at reddit.com we also have feedback go over there give us your thoughts
all right everybody well thank you so much for tuning this week's episode of
linux unplugged and we'll see you right back here next
tuesday
oh wait wait wait wait wait wait wait wait you said commercial software
all right jbtitles.com now we have to name this beast i just like to say that
crossover has age of empires 3 patch 114 up in here
now does it have a web installer because that's the real sweet spot when it just
goes and gets the setup off of the web for you
that's the it does aom.zone.com i have no idea do it hit install oh my god
that's amazing i've been wanting to play that game so
that's what i love is sometimes these scripts like sometimes you have to
supply your own executable but sometimes they just go get the
executable it's like if if there's an ex if there's an exe on the web somewhere
they will stick it in there in true windows style i love it
so now we're gonna be playing some age of empires here in a little bit we won't
even have time for future shows no no screw that so um
my new machine has got has got some fancy brand new technology in it this is
the first time it's my first computer that i've bought
that's new as a new computer that's new to me
yeah that is not behind the times it's like
bang up to specification right now so i've got one
rock in the painting enjoy it yeah yeah yeah
i've got to it's a dual pentium 3 128 megabytes of nano
it's uh it's the uh the tippity top um i7 intel knuck
really which uh generation congratulations sir the
broadwell cool whatever the whatever the one with iris
6100 oh yeah oh yeah okay all right we've got those at work those are nice
that's legit that's and and uh i did some research and i found out you can
actually buy the memory for the haswell um boxes and this will work in this
particular generation so i've got the faster clock
ram but um and i'm also going to have to eat some humble pie and take everything
bad i said about black friday because this wouldn't have happened had it been
the black friday deals in the uk this year
saved i got about a 60 discount on all of the items i bought oh that's nice
one of one of which is one of these new
fancy nvme um ssds which is
amazing oh yeah oh yeah read read performance is 2000 megabytes a
second and write performance oh my gosh oh 500
megabytes per second so if you've ever booted a knuck
and you've seen that intel knuck logo you know the big
nuc appears in the center of the screen and that disappears
i've got a slightly old monitor which i'm also going to sort out maybe in the new
year but in the refresh cycle for the monitor
to fade that out the system has booted and i'm at the
login screen that is amazing it's like are you running what i
assume you're running of course yes of course it's the fastest
booting operating system planet now that's right that's right
um so yeah that's made um that's made a huge difference it's quite amazing
actually those those new uh quad channel nvmes are um are
amazing yeah yeah wow it makes me want to build
a new rig yep do you have uh a is
system d on this rig so you can run like system d analyze and tell us like your
boot speed on this that would be very nice
yeah yeah yeah
uh huh give me a minute how do you oh link to post that's what
you do a link to post but you can't you can't open that the uh boot the boot
time was uh 1.15 seconds wow
that is hmm whoa probably faster than a resume from
suspend would be yeah really yeah who needs power management
anymore this is what i'm saying you know by the time the screen has realized it
needs to go from black to something else it's it's up and up
and round what were the specs again it's uh i'll tell you what i'll find
the exact model and i will paste the details you know what i'll see
you know what i've i've i've realized that i i
if i build a really nice computer i think it gets me two three years
like if i build a really nice one and if i if i go cheap it's a year
it actually i think saves me money long term to buy nicer computers it probably
does invest in the nice stuff now and look at
this this is officially three years old here
right and so as yeah no you disagree well yeah my my the computer that it's
replacing um is was purchased in 2008
and that was a it's um dual quad core xeon
with 32 gigs of ram and nvidia stuff and all the rest of it
and it's got a sas raid and what have you
and that machine is still very very usable today um and more so because
because of black friday i've got four 250 gig
ssds striped raid zero in it now that sounds lovely lovely no kidding
yeah the wimpy you you you upgraded yeah yeah i didn't about us being in the
dark ages yeah yeah well the black friday really came
through for me this year it was um it was really terrific