So Dan, how's it working now?
I think it's working.
You sound awesome.
Good job. Well done, sir.
Are you using that newfangled elementary OS I've heard so much about?
Okay, so I was
on the experimental
artful build that is super
unstable, and so every time I opened
Mumble, it would just destroy my session.
It would just crash. Oh, man.
Oh, dear. Yeah, so I came back to stable
and everything works.
So is that a yes?
Yes.
I'm glad we sorted that.
I'd just like to point out
one week away from release, and I'm using
Ubuntu Mate 17.10. Oh, boom!
It's fine.
This is
Linux Unplugged, episode 218
for Tuesday, October 10th, 2017.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly
Linux talk show that's been carrying around
multiple laptops for weeks.
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. And hello,
Beardsley. Hey, how's it going?
So guys, we have a pretty great show today.
Finally gonna get
to sit down and review the
Librem 15, the latest
and greatest from Purism,
which kind of the timing's sort of
perfect, because also
there's some big news around the funding for Librem 5.
So we'll be taking a look at one
of their products that initially was a crowd
funder at just the moment
that the Librem 5 hit its crowdfunding
goal. Very interesting to see where something
like this they've worked on a couple years, where are they at?
How far did they get if they had a couple years to work
on something? Also,
really, really big community news
that I want to cover this week, and we're gonna
roll out an experimental new segment as
part of that community news. Controversial,
the beard tells me. Prepare to be
flamed, the beard warns me.
Didn't you? He did. I did.
So we will roll out a new corner
of the show this week to talk
about something that's here, it's real,
and we're all dealing with it.
And it's spelled with a lowercase d. That'll
be coming up in a little bit. And then
after all of that, if
time permits,
this show is in a special moment
right now. It is
32 episodes away from
250. And why
do you say that matters? Why does that matter? Is that what you might be wondering?
Why does that matter, right? Isn't that just a number?
Yeah, well it is, and I couldn't wait till 300,
that's why it mattered. So 250
is just 32 episodes
away, and it is time
for
some changes. We're switching
to Haiku. Boom.
So if you're a fan of this show, following
the show for a while, I encourage you to stick around towards
the end of the show. We'll talk a little bit
about some of the changes that could be coming down the road
around 250, around
episode 250, so we'll give you a long time
to digest it all. But never fear,
I think it's all for the better.
Before we go any further, we gotta cover some community
news, and there is one order of business
that we must take care of before we go there.
And that's bringing in our virtual
log. Time appropriate greetings!
Mamba room! Hello!
Hello!
Well I'm like William Shatner getting thrown
across his bridge right now with that one.
We got some excited people. They're fired up and ready
to go. There you go. I'll tell you what I'm fired
up about. One of the projects
that has one of the worst names in recent history
but is so damn useful, FW
Update.
Firmware update, FWupd, just hit
version 1.0. Now this is
that special little bit of magic
that's a lot of good software
but also a lot of really great
partnerships and relationships
that have resulted in Linux
users getting firmware
updates to critical pieces of hardware in their
machine via software updates
like any
modern desktop system does in 2017.
And they just hit version
1.0. Since they've
started the project, they've basically re-architected
the way the entire daemon works. They've re-imagined
how the metadata is downloaded and managed.
They've changed core ways of the way
things themselves are done with the upgrades.
They now support 72 different kinds of
hardware with support for another
dozen or so currently being worked
on. And lots
of vendors are now using the LVFS
project to distribute firmware.
Now LVFS project stands for
the Linux Vendor Firmware Project.
Every month
165,000 plus
devices get updated using
FWupdate.
Now that is some good progress.
Yeah, yeah. Del, as you
might know if you've followed some of our coverage here
on this network, has been a huge supporter, they write,
since the early days. Now smaller
companies like Logitech are also supporting the
project. And he also gives a shout out to his
employer Red Hat who's given him the
resources and infrastructure and some of the
political handshaking that
has been needed that he said literally no one else would have given
him. And he's extremely grateful.
So this is huge.
This is one of those little bits of software
that doesn't have a really flashy name.
You know, if this was something that like Max didn't
have and then all of a sudden
they got this feature, they would give
it some sort of great name like
Active Firmware Updates or something. Like it would have
some sort of publicity name and
it would be a feature in the OS that this
version of the OS finally supports.
But in Linux land,
it just slowly gets rolled out
and one day when you're on a Linux machine
and you're on Gnome Software Center
and you go to updates, you see there's a firmware update.
And you click it and you just installed your firmware update
and you don't think about the fact that you didn't have
to go download an exe from their horrible
driver's website. You didn't have to go find
some weird version of FreeDOS or something like that.
Like it just worked.
And that's why this project's so great.
And it's really great to see them hit version 1.0.
And there's a lot of devices on that
list. You should go check. Tons of Dell things.
The Color Hug, the Logitech Unifying
Receiver, which a lot of people probably use.
Like that's awesome. I'm hopeful
that Dell gets support for this
on some of their servers at some point because I think that would
be handy. Sure, there's usually like
TMI or other ways to do it, but it'd be awesome to be able to do it
just from your regular old
operating system. Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
So I have a segment that I want to
roll out. A corner, if you will. It's for people who like
to mess with computers. Now I'm going to call this
the System D Corner and
the value of this is negative.
I apologize if you're not a System D
fan. I understand. It is a bit
of a complex beast.
But it is the reality in which we
find ourselves today. And there have been some
interesting developments in System D land.
And I thought since most of us are going to be
running a version of Linux that uses it,
maybe we should know what those things are.
So we now dive
into the complex and
inspired world of System D.
And there's some new features, Wes.
There's some really nice new features. I
highlighted a few. Like one I thought that was
particularly neat was
dynamic users,
which is coming to System D 2.35.
And you can now configure
System D to dynamically allocate
Unix user IDs for service
processes when they start.
And then they release the user ID
when it stops them. It's pretty secure and it mixes well
with transient services. It works with
socket activated services and
with service templating.
So instead of having to have user accounts sitting
around that could be exploited, user accounts
created. The UID that is
necessary is created. When the service
is done, it's destroyed. The other part I like about this
is not necessarily just the dynamic users
thing, but they talk a lot about the methods
that you have available with System D, like
it runs as a dynamic user and then you can
pick and choose either temporary or permanent
places on the file system to give it write access
to. And it won't be able to write outside of that,
which there's a ton of things I can think like, you know,
much like snaps do in some ways where you're just like
you need to save your data in your
spot. I will go fetch it when I need it.
Don't touch anything else in my home.
Now there's something else that they've
added that I didn't really think about until
I saw it as a feature and I'm like, oh, geez, I can't believe we
didn't have this. So System D analyzes
gain new verbs like get log level
and get log target,
which will print the logging level
and the target of the system manager,
which is if you think about what they're saying
here is now you can ask the system what
level in which are you logging at?
And you could not ask the system that before
this necessarily, but more so
than that, they're going to be able to expose this
to like GNOME logs up in the GUI
level. So you'll be able to open up your local desktop
log manager and see
your system is currently
logging at this level right now, which
that is kind of like one of those
I'm surprised we didn't have those features.
And then here's another one in that category
for each service unit
for each time a service is restarted
there'll be a counter that is now
kept so you can keep track of
how often the service restarts. It's
increased each time the service is restarted
and you'll be able to
query like systemctl show
dash P number of restarts for
service X and you can see if your
nginx daemon is restarting
constantly and you get an idea of how many times that's
happened, which I think is just going to be really great
information. Then last
but not least, before we get out of the corner
you notice a little something
about kind of a clever way
that systemd murders people's system
processes and
murders them good. It really does
because it does it in a way where they don't make
a big fuss and then it can just go
and clean house after that because
and so
I don't mean I don't want to steal your thunder because you
found this one but I thought
this is pretty great the way they I guess they use sig stop
before a real signal completely
before it gets any other signals the
process gets any other signals that would prevent it
from closing like so before it can lock up
because it got another signal they sent it a sig
stop. The process suspends
and then you can
go in and you can just tell it all to die right
there on the spot and the ones that don't
die they'll come back they'll get
woken up and then you can generally go back and
clean them up in a loop and kill them again.
It seems like it was just a really simple kind
of way to sort of kill processes and
I thought okay well that was you put it in the slack
so I don't I didn't mean to steal it but what did you
no no I think just just it's just good
to see the implementation of
something simple for a common problem
like that I'm sorry I'm doing it again
but that's what it was is it was
something simple for system where otherwise we
give we attribute systemd as this huge
monster and this is just a really
clean plain simple way to do something right
like there's plenty of things systemd does wrong I
will not try to say that it's this perfect piece of
software anything like that but when they do things
right or if there's something interesting
it's interesting to see and I have not
dived that deep into the internals
so it's cool to see like a filtered version
a look inside yeah
yeah so something that
I've noticed that you guys didn't mention
there's also systemd
run gain support for a new pipe
command which allows you
to invoke arbitrary
processes as systemd services
so you get all the benefits of systemd like the systemd
logging while still allowing
to be integrated into the classic unix
shell pipeline fascinating
that is a good catch yeah right yeah
so you can like spin up a pipeline give it
a give it like a temporary working
to store all of its stuff logs
to the journal and then have it all disappear
as a user that no longer exists there you go
there you go so okay everybody okay
did everybody make it did you did you survive
I'm in a cold sweat now but let's
just carry on
all right and that concludes our systemd
corner I just I thought we were going to need
a theme for this I know music
I'm just hacking it together as we go right now
but I thought somebody screaming about doing only
one job sort of was appropriate for systemd
because sort of you know
okay so it's too appropriate yeah
well it's kind of ironically appropriate
so before we run Mr. West
Payne and I had a chance to go to seagull
this week last week actually
and Wes even had
a talk there which
I attended and this was my first time
going to seagull it's in Seattle
at the Seattle Central College
and it ran this last weekend and
a lot of our friends are there
oh yeah Valerie from
the Ubuntu
in Oregon and Katie I think she
actually probably with Katie she was there
Ian from
System76 was there
as well and he gave a talk as well
as he sat in a booth and
yeah it was
not a huge event in fact it sort of
hit that sweet spot if you want something
that's not a very very large production
but still has really interesting informative
talks it sort of nails
that like I'll give you an example like
so while Wes was giving a talk on
Clojure
there was also a talk on
on how to
set up like a key
pass set up with your own private
sync and encrypted backup
and in another room there was a talk about
how to wire an automated chicken
door using a Raspberry Pi
and like those were
the talks that were all going on at once
and it gives you sort of a it is like that all day
and almost every
talk there was something like I would really like to go to that
and so you gave one
what did you think what was that process like for you
was that your first talk at a Linux event
at a Linux event yes I've given others
other talks but at a Linux event yes it was a lot of
fun it was super easy when I was
submitting and preparing and saying like oh do I
want to try to give one here all the
people in their IRC room the people volunteers
people running it super nice super helpful
really it's just a great conference
I'm glad to have been a part I'm glad to have gone
to gone this year and I hope
you're right it wasn't super huge but
I thought they got a good array like there's a lot of speakers
from not in this area Microsoft
was represented IBM had several people
there as you said system 76
so I think it's it's an up
newcomer hopefully something to watch and it
feels like you know Seattle's a big enough
tech hub with enough tech people
and companies there that it makes sense
for a Linux type event
like this to exist so
it sounds like this year went great
I hope that keeps going yeah
I found
it to be a little
smaller scale than like a Linux fest it was
more like a more like
a probably a crowd of like four or five hundred
yeah probably yeah and
it was at the venue was
a school Seattle Central College
and it was in session
so at certain times
you were walking around the hallways with college
students going between rooms
which not quite
my thing but not bad
either a little chaotic but not bad
I guess they had to do some rescheduling too
there was like an HVAC problem so they had to change some
of the rooms that they were using at the last
minute I don't know if that played a role there's always
complications like that but either way
nice group of people nice group of
talks definitely worth the travel
if you're in the area so yeah
I'll probably go back for a bit next year too
I got to meet up with a few Jupiter broadcasting
listeners so that was cool I like that
and then the year I went the fire
alarm went off so you guys lucked out
ouch
and then after it was all done
Wes and I went to Angela's
Angela's family diner oh
that was a ton of fun yeah so we went down to Planet Java
diner and we got chicken strips Wes and I
were adorable and got chicken strips to get twinsies
we totally went twinsies on lunch
and then and then you know what
we went and got cookies so it was actually
all around a pretty good time did you guys share
a milkshake no
no but those cookies
are worth getting they were super super
good so yeah it was Segal was a good event the Seattle
area is good if you can make it out
maybe go next year maybe
maybe and now and now we look forward my friends
now we look forward so there's
many things to chat about so let's take a moment
and thank Ting for sponsoring the unplugged
program go to linux.ting.com
to sign up and that's where you'll get $25
off a device or $25
in service credit if you bring a device
check their BYOD page
because over there they'll list all the devices
that are compatible and you'll be impressed with the list
because they have a CDMA network and
a GSM network they have a really
well designed dashboard where it
gives you a quick access to
your minutes your messages or
your megabytes whatever you've used or you could turn
a line off or you could turn a line
on and just use only text
or only use data or only use phone like
you have all these really different granular
levels of control you can
say usage alerts you can name
the line so you don't have to go by the numbers but you can go
by like a easy to know alias
and then that shows up across like the mobile
apps too it's really sophisticated
now here's the nice thing
about a $25 service credit
you see your average Ting line is going
to be around $23 $24
a month and that's after your minutes
and your messages and your megabytes are added up and the $6
for the line you're still going to be around
this pretty low price point
so if you get a $25 service credit it's going to
pay for more than your first month I really
really like that because that's what happened to me
and that that experience that
that made me a Ting customer for life
and of course they've got devices you can buy directly
like I said you can bring your own and if you're
watching their Twitter page and
you can find that at Ting FTW on Twitter
you'll see that they're giving away 2 gigabytes
of data right now if you add a line
to your Ting account you'll get 2 gigs
of free data so if you're
already a Ting customer check that out
if you're not go to
linux.ting.com linux.ting.com
and a big thank you
to Ting for sponsoring the Linux
Unplugged program linux.ting.com nationwide
coverage with no contracts and no
early termination fees whoa
linux.ting.com
so you found this really great
I think you found this this really great
unless the beard found it I'm sorry if I'm misattributing
but this really great app called
Tor Proxy which uses net filter
hooks in the Linux kernel to route all
of your network traffic to the Tor
network it uses net filter
hooks and then it just
makes sure that all of your outbound
traffic that of course the kernel would be
responsible for anyways gets routed to
the Tor network now here's a major
limitation it only supports IP
4 traffic and it's TCP IP
4 so no UDP
fancy shenanigans no
IP v6 and no pings
no ICMP pings get those
out of here yeah get those out of here but this is
a pretty neat thing could you
could give me a use case for this West
give me your best spy use case for this
like what do you got like an always secure
Linux box as soon as you turn it on the kernel
routes all your traffic to Tor like listen what's
going on yeah I mean that or
yeah maybe you're using a you have a virtual machine or
you have like a you know a laptop with no
OS that you boot this up you load the module
you make sure that you know at no time
are you going to be able to send
packets out there except
through Tor yeah or you want
to run an application over Tor that doesn't
support proxies inside of
the application sure yeah yeah that's
good I bet you that'd be a big use case yeah
Tor proxy and it's a kernel
module which who doesn't love a load in a good
kernel module I like how
I like how simple it is it only has four arguments
oh really good
I like I was gonna say I like
that they tested against kernel 3.16
so I'm like oh okay
but what are they what are the arguments
well you have dash S which is to insert the module
and start the proxy you have
dash I which is just to insert the module
you have dash R which is to remove
the module and you have dash T which is
to refresh the relay tables
that's pretty simple
that's it I can get I can get behind
that that's how you build your ultimate secure box
somebody make a live CD that
does that the the downside is the proxy
must be run as root and Tor
must be running so
you are putting
something network enabled
on root yeah
yeah that is a downside
I also noticed like if you want to get to any hidden
services you're still gonna have to use a Tor browser to
do that yeah but I guess that's kind of expected
so I saw a question
on our Linux and I
I know I've had offline conversations
with Wimpy about this but I
figured it might be on the minds of
a lot of listeners out there and
I did show I did see it show up on our Linux so I
thought well let's let's talk about this for a moment and
maybe Wimpy you could chime in
and share as much as you'd like
I just want to find a game
I think is or a name I think
is the person's handle on
Reddit why did comp is die
I don't understand people like
people act like comp is archaic or
maybe it's gimmicky and buggy that hasn't
been my experience at all I don't really understand
why it's gone away I like gnome shell
but I like comp is much much
more I'm actually going to jump to
XFCE and load
comp is and I don't understand why more people
and more distros haven't done this so
Wimpy how did
comp is and why is comp is dead and is it dead
well no comp is
isn't dead there's there's effectively
two strands of comp is that
are being actively maintained right
now there is comp is not
point nine which is the comp is you'll
find in Ubuntu
for example and that's
the C++ re-implementation
so it was forked from
the 0.8 branch
a whole load of stuff was reworked
and all of the plugins that
are available there were
also made to work with
EGL so they work on
things like ARM devices and what have
you and then you have
comp is reloaded
which is based on the 0.8 branch
so pre the C++
re-implementation and
has a wider selection of plugins
available but not all of those
are available for EGL
and both of those projects are alive and
well Ubuntu
Marte ships comp is 0.9
by default obviously Ubuntu
16.04 is shipping comp is because that's
where a lot of the Unity functionality
is
exposed
and I
think I'm right in saying that the Fedora
Marte spin comes with
comp is reloaded
so you know it's funny because
Veritunda makes the obvious joke
in the room and you're right Veritunda everybody
when you say comp is you think of things like
cubes or
the aquarium
my windows don't wiggle anymore wiggly windows
wobbly windows
yeah I mean if you've got no taste
then
those things are turned on by default
then Linux is the place to be
if you're actually using comp is for
you know feature enhancement then
maybe comp is
used a little bit more sensibly and
tastefully yeah that's always why I've liked
it is because it always gave my system
this feeling like it
was keeping up with me like the
smoothness to the window draws
and movements to the windows and
the fact that maybe my disk
might be busy but the windows would still
render rather cleanly and smoothly
to me that was always the
draw to comp is I think my
favorite comp is feature was actually
it was my first experience with
live previews
in your alt tab menu oh yeah
yeah and also like hover over
the icon and see like a
preview of your minimized window window
peaking yeah yeah there
is some genuinely useful functionality
in comp is and you know if you're
using a desktop environment which is
using X then
it's a great way to get
in most cases a tear-free
experience and also in
my experience I've been working on comp
is for just over two and a half
years now I don't find it
to be buggy or crashy you often see
throwaway comments you know in the various
or it steals a lot of frames per second
or memory oh it's you know it's crashy
and it's buggy well I don't
see that I use it all day
all the live long day for years
and I don't think I've ever seen
comp is actually crash
on me it's usually something else
yeah that causes you know
a disastrous failure it's not comp is
I'm inclined to agree my
my main machine
is a 1604 machine so it's Unity
7 comp is based but
comp is I don't even think
about comp is on a daily basis
I don't really think about Unity 7
on a daily basis it's just the
thing that puts windows on my screen and I tend
to leave my machine on all the time
and I get quite decent uptime
without my desktop
dying in any way shape or form
so yeah that might have been the case
some time ago and there may have been some instability
when comp is
0.8 transitioned over
to C++ in the 0.9
and the early days of Unity plugin
but these days
I don't see it being anywhere
near as crashy
as people say in fact I
before I joined this hangout
I was playing a
3D accelerated game
via Steam on one display
while displaying other stuff on
two other displays and everything
just worked perfectly and I didn't get any
rendering issues or crashing at all
it's just expected
that it just works and it does in 2017
it does yeah I've really had no problem with it
we have a machine here in the studio running
Unity 7 on the LTS last
LTS release and I never
think about comp is I never give it two
thoughts the only thing I ever think about is the interface
always seems fairly responsive
and I appreciate that aspect
of the computer yeah definitely you know it gives me
it gives me some pause though now
that I think about this because you've
all just made really great points comp is still
maintained it technically does
something superior that we all
enjoy and while we have projects out there like
kwin which are great projects
I still find projects like
comp is to still have a considerable amount of value
specifically for me
and how I use Linux just
you know for me personally I
like using a desktop with comp is
and I wish you
and millions of other people I wish there was a
way to have that with gnome 3
because
that's what I'm going to miss I think the most
about the transition for the
Ubuntu desktop is
I was always one of the things I liked the most is when I would
load up a Unity 7 Ubuntu desktop
which I didn't use very often
but when I loaded it I was always like
gosh this thing is smooth and polished
I think comp has played that role
and I admit I'm a little
biased at the moment because just before we went on air
gnome 3 crashed and we lost audio
on our live stream again and we're back
to having gnome 3 crashes after
weeks of things working great and
we've made no software changes at all
and yet we're now back to
having gnome 3 crashes so I do admit I'm
a little
but let's not get roasted into spectacles
when Ubuntu switched
to Unity it was pretty fraught
and Unity in the early days
and comps in the early days
was pretty unstable
Yeah I guess I feel like I've gone through that though
I don't really feel like doing that again
Right well you don't have to because the
1710 release is an interim release there's no
reason why you
as a normal user I don't mean you Chris as a
podcaster and a tech journalist I mean
a normal user would have to upgrade to
1710 they might do it out of curiosity and they might
run it in a VM or on a spare laptop but there's no
obligation to run it
other than curiosity so wait for
the 1804 release when things are a bit more
stable and the upstream gnome
developers have had a ton of
bugs filed by
quite a few Ubuntu users
who are enthusiastic and do want to
try this stuff early
but I think when you get to 1804
I think
given that Unity 7
has stabilized over the last
like 3 years 4 years or so
you picture where we'll be
with gnome shell in
I don't know the 20
2020 LTS
release just think how rock solid that
2020 release I know that's quite
a hard picture for some people to grasp but
think how stable that's going to be
and that's effectively where we are with Unity 7
That's a good point
and that is the nice aspect
about LTS's and the fact that there's many
other desktops out there that
we do have
there are other islands
we can hop to and
time does seem to heal these wounds
so while we're talking about the march towards
I noticed that the Ubuntu Mate
project has a very interesting
announcement in fact some of my friends on
Twitter seem to be rather excited about this too
Ubuntu Mate will be pioneering
a snap pre-installed
so when you install Ubuntu Mate
17.10 there will be a snap
pre-installed and it looks like
it's going to be the pulse audio mixer
Wimpy can you tell me a bit about this?
Yeah I can so
as of yesterday
I believe that landed so
you were at the Ubuntu rally
and this was one of the outcomes
of the Ubuntu rally which was
how do we
put the last pieces in place so that it's
possible to ship a snap
pre-installed by default
in the ISO images
and I was approached as
Ubuntu Mate
to sort of sound
me out to see if we'd be able to do this
and work on this so that we could
learn some lessons
and feed that back to the
Ubuntu desktop team proper
so they've got sight of
how things have gone and what
we've learned in readiness
for 1804. So
we've chosen to ship
the pulse mixer application
by default which is a
console based mixer for pulse
and in fact when I was
fumbling with my audio earlier
it was actually that that I used to
sort my volume levels out
because it's quite fine grained
in what it can do. So
that's now pre-installed by default
on the daily images so we've got a post
over at community.ubuntu.com
which is a
call for testing for anyone who's
interested in Ubuntu not necessarily
Ubuntu Mate to come and grab
the daily images and test
it and make sure that that pulse
mixer application is working correctly.
So there's a lot to what you just
said and this is
remarkable. So there's a lot
a listener could infer based
on this conversation so I think we should
be pretty clear. You
say you're shipping a snap in Ubuntu Mate
in preparation for 1804.
Now if I were an alarmist
I'd say that means that 1804 everything
is going to be snapped. That's not what's happening here right?
No there's no
plans for everything to be a snap in 1804
although you know
if there was a new flavor
to crop up where everything being
a snap made sense then
that would be possible. You know there could be some
interesting use cases for this sort of
thing like
Ubuntu Kodi for example.
You know you could have an Ubuntu Kodi
distribution where Kodi is
provided as a snap and is
permanently upgraded to the latest
stable release even though that you're
on an LTS that's you know running
for five years you know unchanging
but the core application
moves on top. That would be quite
a nice way to do this.
Or an Ubuntu kiosk
that has just like
the base install and a browser
and that's it and the
networking stack and everything is nicely
confined so someone coming up to use that kiosk
knows that nothing else is going to
infringe upon the data
that they're saving at that time.
So why Pulse Audio Mixer
or Pulse Mixer
and
what does having it installed by
default what kind of
value does that have?
Right well the particular
reason that this application has been
chosen is because until it
was a snap there was no easy way
to install this on Debian and Ubuntu
because this application has never been in the
Debian or Ubuntu archives before
and in fact it was Popey spotted
what's called an ITP
on the Debian mailing list.
An ITP is an intent to package
and that was a request by somebody
to say package this software for Debian
and Ubuntu. So
in the two weeks that have elapsed
since that ITP post
a snap has been created
it's in the snap
store for the appropriate
archives and the necessary support
to embed snaps in ISO
images has been added
to the build infrastructure and now
we're shipping a snap by default.
Which is an interesting story when you
think about what we've heard
about projects like Nextcloud and
you know software that's frozen
in archives and how that causes
maintenance issues for developers
and all the rest of it and that the time
that they have to wait before the next version
gets into the archive.
So there's a very interesting story here
about a fast moving piece of software that
is now being deployed by default
in an ISO image and the
speed at which that's been done.
And this implementation isn't
complete at the moment. So at the moment
it's kind of tightly
coupled with the live
build system
and what we're going to be doing is
exposing this in the usual way
that people that make
Ubuntu flavors
are used to for what's called
seeding packages that go in their live
image. And I see on the
Ubuntu
community hub the Ubuntu
budget team have replied and said you know they
were interested in doing this and they wanted
some more details about how this was done
because they have a number of snaps
that they would be interested in shipping by
default in Ubuntu budget.
And what do you learn by
having something like this installed because it's
not just a matter of making it available to
install which I could do now but there
is got to be value in
a certain amount of user base
having this installed by default.
Yeah so there's a couple of things
there. Oh goodness.
The first is
that you know the build infrastructure has
to be able to install this snap into
the ISO as it's being
constructed. And it's not just the snap
of course because the snap sits on top
of the core snap
as well. So the core snap
is being shipped by default
in Ubuntu Mate 17.10
now. Which normally what
happens is the first time you install a snap
the core snap gets installed
as well.
So the core snap and this
snap are shipped by
default. And what we'll do is
sometime after the release
we'll push out an update
to PulseMixer
and we'll be able to make sure
that all of the backend infrastructure is
geared up appropriately to cope with
that demand for updating
all of those systems. So there's some backend
soak testing being conducted
as well. That makes a lot of sense.
It was super critical that we choose
something nice and small that doesn't
have a super big impact on the
size of the ISO image but also
is a useful utility.
We don't want to just throw shovelware on
the ISO. We wanted to put something on
there that's actually quite useful and
PulseMixer is actually a kind of
useful thing to like open a terminal type
PulseMixer and have a nice little
thing that you can use to adjust the levels
on your microphone and your speakers and your
headset and all that kind of stuff. It's actually a cool tool.
So it fulfills
like all of the requirements for
putting something on the CD.
Think PAVU control but
for the console. I was just wanting
that. I think I'll be snap installing this later
today. We're making an official pic of the show today.
Go check it out. It's PulseMixer and
you can get it as a snap too. Which I guess would be
what? Snap search PulseMixer if you want to see the
entry? Snap install PulseMixer
Snap Info PulseMixer. Both of those work.
There you go. And then
if you look at like the screenshot here
on the Ubuntu community page
you can see that you can individually control
the volume of particular Chrome tabs too
which that's pretty cool.
And then Mumble and individual applications.
Also you'll see that Wimpy has a
Scarlett USB analog which
I approve. I like that.
I love that. It's great audio interface.
That's what we're talking on
right now actually. We are talking on one of those.
It's not the only one we have but that's the one
on this machine. Well fascinating.
So I
suppose this is really early days
but my last question might be
what are your thoughts on sharing
what's discovered?
Well I think that that will
be some months from now before
we see enough users
installing Ubuntu Mate and having
this snap pre-registered on people's
machines and then we'll push an update
out. And what's interesting is
the plan for the update is to push out
a version of the snap that's actually smaller
than the snap that's being deployed
on the ISO image.
Do we talk much about that?
Do we talk much about that on the show?
That was another thing that kind of came up
at the Ubuntu rally that
was a rather impressive piece of
work.
And I don't want to steal the thunder but it sounds like
there could be kind of a big change coming to the size
of snaps.
Yeah, I mean this was
I think actually if Daniel's here
it was actually one of the elementary
applications that saw the biggest
reduction in that whole exercise.
Oh snap!
Tell me.
Well it was really interesting because we're
digging into the idea
of the platform snap, right?
And trying to make sure
that the size of the snaps
were comparable to
their deb package equivalents.
And because we're kind of sticklers
about that kind of stuff and we kept poking
and going, can it get smaller? Can't it get
just a little bit smaller? And Ken
was just furiously typing
you know, okay maybe if we did this and
did that and we finally poked him
enough that he found a hidden
off by default option that just
drastically reduces the size of
snaps. Really?
The really cool thing was Ken found it
via the KDE developers
who were also there at the rally.
It was actually one of the KDE
developers, Scarlett, who's been
going like a machine
snapping all the KDE
apps. There's loads of them been pushed in
the store. And she said, oh yeah you want
this option and this will make your snaps
much smaller. She passed that on to Ken
and then that little word of mouth
thing made all the snaps much smaller.
Not just the elementary ones but all the
known ones as well. It was great.
Yeah, significantly smaller.
I think in the case of, was it
local that was being snapped at the time, Daniel?
No, we were actually just doing the calculator.
We were trying to start simple.
I think it was something like
9 meg and then this change was made
and it was 136k.
That's quite the diet.
That is really good work.
That's
something that should just make it across Mark's
desk at some point. Like if nothing else
we can take that away from the Ubuntu
rally, Mark. We got that.
That's a good
point. Well, good work gentlemen.
Curious to see where this goes
and of course the timeline is rather
obvious I suppose because this is all an effort to collect
data for 1804 in a sense
to determine how far
you go. So I guess in
a sense you're going to have to kind of turn this thing
around in a few months really.
Yeah, I don't know what the
plans of the desktop team are but
you will have seen that
Ken, as we just
discussed, Ken has been snapping a
number of the GNOME desktop
applications and other members of the
desktop team have been doing the same.
It may well be that
some of those applications ship
as snaps in 1804
and you have an LTS with
rolling applications sitting
on top.
And you know
the thing that's interesting
here is there's this popular
meme in the community
that snaps are only for IoT and
server and don't work for desktop
apps and Ken is totally
proving that wrong in
multiple ways like
the Snap Demon that runs
on 1804 next year
is the same Snap Demon that
runs on 1604 that was released
a year ago and that's the same
Snap Demon that was
available for 1404 that
was three years ago.
So he can put one
GNOME application, 3.26
GNOME application in the store
and that same Snap works
on 1804, 1604, and
1404. The exact same
application packaged once
runs on multiple LTSs
and non Ubuntu
systems as well. That is an
epic win. There you go.
I guess we should
probably move forward but
I guess this is all really
you know I'm going to say this.
What the bigger picture is
is that 1710 is now days
away and a lot
of this stuff is falling into place and that's really
the meta story around all
of this and
I'm going to give a plug to the last two
episodes of Ask Noah. You got to
check those out if you are not a routine
listener of his show. First of all he's been
killing it recently and second of all
he has two interviews
that are split across to episode
29 and episode 28
and start with 28
and it's an interview
maybe Martin
or Poppy if you know the name of the developer
that Noah was interviewing but
It's Jerry Boland. Thank you.
He had a great interview with Jerry and
it talks a lot about
Canonical's thoughts around Wayland
and how to implement it correctly where
Mir could still have a very
real role especially for smaller desktop
projects and what
the hell happens if 1710
ships Wayland by default and it blows up
in everybody's face. What happens
then? All of that is in episode
28 and then in episode 29
of the Ask Noah show and so
good additional background information
as we get really close to the 1710
release.
I can hear you wanting to
wrap up this Ubuntu stuff.
I know there's one more thing we want to get to so go ahead.
There is yes. Yeah.
It's all yours. You have the floor.
Well Poppy you've
been doing a lot of the local comments.
Poppy you have the floor.
You have the floor Poppy.
So as you mentioned
Chris it's a few days away from the 1710
release and it turns
out that the Ubuntu project
kicks out a ton
of ISO images. It's not just Ubuntu
with Gnome. There's all
the flavors as well. There's that little
known one called Ubuntu Mate
and then there's all the other really big ones as
well. So Ubuntu, Lubuntu,
Ubuntu Studio.
There's just tons and
we need
some help from our community
to help us test those and
we would really love it if people
could join us on Monday. We're having a
hangout on Monday.
1500 UTC I think
it is where myself and Martin
are going to go through all you need to do
to download the ISO images get
these things booted up on a machine
and a USB stick test that
stuff out report bugs. Let us
know what's busted so that we can
get that stuff fixed. Now we're not saying you'll get fixed
for release which is next
Thursday the 19th of October
but we'll certainly get stuff queued up
for immediately after release if
it's super critical. So yeah
join me and Martin. If you go
to Ubuntu On Air there's a nice
little YouTube video you can
you can watch next Monday
on the 16th of October at
1500 UTC. So that's
the URL to go to is ubuntuonair.com
next Monday.
Yep. You can go to
our community site community.ubuntu.com
and there's a pinned post there
as well and you'll find
a post about this. It's all about
just the easy way to get
a smooth transition into the Ubuntu community
helping people out and
getting stuff tested. If you got a little
bit of spare time it would be super appreciated.
Yeah. You know what I'll put a link in the show notes
because you might not out
I don't always get a chance to file a bug
for every little thing. I don't get to test
every little bit but I can download
an ISO and give it a go and
that's something we can all do.
And that's part of the problem
is you know people find it difficult to do
that. The process of finding
bugs is a little bit abrasive. We want to make that
easier and if it's difficult
you just tell us what the bug is. We'll reproduce
it. We'll file the bug right.
We'll help you through that process.
We want to make it easy. But what we need is
lots of different people to test this stuff on
diverse platforms
lots of different systems. Not just
the same ThinkPad that everyone in the
company has. How about I'll bring
my Macbook that I use for
video editing. How would you like that?
Nobody wants that.
Although I do have a Librem 15 I could
bring to the party.
I'll bring my System76 Lemur guys.
There you go. That's good. Got to make sure that
works because there we go. That's three people.
Yeah.
We've got this Librem 15 here in studio
that we've got to talk about.
I've been using it
now for about three weeks
and I wasn't really quite sure
how to really do
this review until
I went to the Ubuntu rally and I brought this as my
daily driver for the rally. Then it all just sort of
clicked together. Now the timings worked
out really well with them nailing
their crowd funders. We're going to talk about
all of that. We've got to get to this thing. We've got to
discuss this. Although
we're running a little tight I'm hoping we'll still
have time to also talk about
episode 250 and beyond.
But first
DigitalOcean. DigitalOcean.com
Go over there and create your account
and use our promo code DOUNPLUGGED.
It's one word and you get a $10 credit.
Now you can do a lot with this $10 credit.
Traditionally I would say go spin up a
droplet. Go like the $5 a month rig.
Run it for two months for free. Go like a maniac.
Lots of distros, great
dashboard, data centers all over the world.
But now
there's a whole new thing you could
use that $10 credit for.
Wes I've got to recommend
if you haven't had a chance yet you've got to
try out the new DigitalOcean spaces.
It's
remarkable how straightforward
this is. It's simple
reliable object storage.
And if you want to use it with their
crazy great simple API and
programmatically create storage
and transfer stuff
into it and then destroy the storage
you can do that.
If you also just want to upload
some files through a nice web UI
generate a public URL that expires
after a couple of days and can be
downloaded X number of times and send it out
you can do that. And what's
really nice about that is DigitalOcean
has really
great bandwidth. Like their
hypervisors have 40 gigabit connections but the data
centers themselves are nuts.
And that's where these files are hosted.
You're getting the full blast
of the DigitalOcean data center when you share these
links. Right. You don't have to worry. It's not like you
put it on some tiny little server
and then oh whoops I shared
this to so many people.
It's prepared for that. When you're using it to share
files super fast. When you're using it
for crazy back end object storage
it's intensely
fast. And they're giving a two
month trial right now. If you go over to
DigitalOcean.com you create your account
apply our promo code DOUNPLUGGED and you can try
out their new spaces system. Beyond that
though if you want to create a machine on their infrastructure
be it Ubuntu or Fedora or
FreeBSD or Debian they
have the best UI to do
this. They have a system that will
get you going in less than 55 seconds.
And if you want to attach this traditional block
storage that just shows up as like a
Dev SDA device or whatever they
have that too. You don't have to go
with the fancy new object storage
if that ain't how you roll. They have monitoring
alerting. They have load balancing as a service
and tons of pre-built open source applications ready
to go.
Just really all I have to say right there. There's really no
reason like just go sign up get that you know.
Ten dollars. You can
roll with that for quite a while especially with that three cents
an hour which is my favorite rig. Yeah
right. Like there's tons of times there's times where I have no
droplets going for a little while. You know I'm just not I don't have
any. I have some other things going.
But in like less than a minute I just
open my browser bump on over there
several new servers. I did that last night.
It's so helpful. Once you have everything set
up you've got your SSH keys in there.
It just becomes part of your workflow.
Yeah it's a fun way to play with new open source
projects that you've been thinking around with or something you find
on GitHub. It's pretty cool.
It's pretty cool.
DigitalOcean.com use the promo code DO
unplugged all one word you apply to your account
after you get started. And a big thank you to
DigitalOcean for sponsoring the unplugged
program. So yeah let's start
this guys in Mumble Room. Please feel free
to jump in if
you have any questions as we go
along. Now
I want to start this review by talking about the
obvious elephant in the room.
And that is the fact that Purism
reached their crowdfunding goal
for the Librem 5 which is
really kind of remarkable because it's a one point five
million dollar target. Yeah that's
impressive. Yeah. Yeah. And this as you
recall we've talked about this. This is the five inch
privacy focused smartphone
that they're building from the
ground up to use Matrix
for encrypted communications.
They'll have a separate CPU from the baseband.
They're going to have kill switches for the camera.
Hello.
Oh. We have somebody
at the door.
We have the separate kill switches for Wi-Fi
and cellular connectivity
and things like that. And then of
course they're also going to not necessarily
prevent the possibility of connecting to an external
display or keyboard and mouse because the thing's running
basically Debian. It's pure OS
or whatever with
about three gigs of RAM if I
recall. Yeah 32 gigs of storage and
a courage jack aka the headphone port.
And it's reached
its initial goal and now they're shooting
for the milestones I guess or
not the milestones but the what do you call it?
What are they called? Stretch goals.
Yeah.
Congratulations to them I suppose. Yeah that's good.
And so if anybody in the mobile room has anything they want to
comment on that aspect of the story before we
continue feel free.
I say congrats to them and I hope this thing
is a success. Just as a comparison like the
mobile room 15 they had a $250,000
goal they made twice that so
almost $600,000 but this
is a whole new scale of just projects.
Wow it really is. Yeah. Can you explain
to me what a multi-function port is
though? No.
Well do you ever wonder if one of your
ports just didn't do enough you know?
It only did the one thing?
I guess that just means USB-C.
That's what I was thinking. I think the implication
is it's a mobile device so it's only going to have a limited
number of ports. You're not going to have like
tons of ports all around the edges of the device.
You'll have one and everything will connect
to that maybe with a dongle or USB-C like
you say. Yeah.
I've been following
this with some interest because what seems to have
really pushed it over the edge in the final
last couple of days
here was some
people got in at really
significantly high levels like I believe perhaps
the highest levels
which is quite remarkable because it
caused quite the trajectory
and
it was a bit weird actually.
A little while ago, a few
days ago there were two people who
went in at the
$19,999 level and two people
who went in at the $17,999 level
within the same hour
and then again
this morning or earlier on today
the same thing happened.
Two more at $19,999 and two more
at $17,999. Now it
makes me think that when you add those
numbers up it's probably just
one person investing but the only way that they can
invest that significant chunk of money
is to split it between those two
and that totals up to the amount that they
want to invest. There's someone
who wants to invest in this thing and they're
giving that amount of money. That's
the only way it makes sense to me. There's no way
you'd get four people
within one hour
giving that amount of money.
Yeah and you've been following the chart
rather closely so I think you've got actually
a good visualization
of it
and that seems possible
and I suppose good for them.
I think they're running the crowdfunding
site themselves so I don't know if they actually have
to disclose who these people are but I sure
would be interested.
I don't know. As a privacy
focused device I can see them not doing it.
I can see them not wanting to do that
and people who donate not wanting people
to know who they are and that's perfectly
reasonable.
Yeah and
I think it's sort of with this
as the background that I'm
looking now at the
Alibrum 15 which is
their rather high end
laptop that's
fairly competitive. This one is black
it's all metal. It's
15.6 inch screen.
It has a high end i7
processor in it. It has
very fast SSD drives. It has
a sixth generation or
seventh.
If you get a chance over there give me a
give me a read on the graphics
because I think it's actually Intel 600
but
this was something that I didn't actually
order. I didn't actually buy this.
This was something that Purism thought
would be appropriate to replace for me.
So
it's 520. OK. Thank you.
OK. So
I have the very first
Alibrum 15 that they ever shipped that
was slightly below what they
had hoped to originally ship I think.
And I
know that they kind of hummed hot about it
and they decided it was worth trying to make good on that.
And I respect that. That's really nice of
them. And so I wasn't expecting
this when it arrived. I just thought OK
well this is really. So I came
at it with this sort of like
where does this fit. Right. Where does this
fit in my life. And
so I used it. You know I did the standard
things like you know tried to push it to see how
loud it could get and tried to
push the battery and
loaded Soulless and now it's going
loaded Gentoo and yeah
loaded Ubuntu and yeah now it's
undergoing the beard test. And it was
it wasn't until the trip to
New York came up. Is that
right. And I went OK
because the
the physical kill switches
all of a sudden became
a much more practical
option because
I'm going into an area
that I don't normally go into.
And
why not just turn off the Wi-Fi like why not
have that extra level of security. Now
ironically iPhone 7 users
did experience issues with Wi-Fi in
New York so that Wi-Fi attacks
were actually a problem in that very hotel.
Now it wasn't one for this but
I actually kind of I found a
practical purpose and I will say this to
their they are they are implemented in a cleaner
less obvious
way than the old
Librem 15. Is that right. So it's interesting. So we have it
right here the old Librem 15 and they're
like basically there's holes in the aluminum
casing and then there is a
old school electronic black toggle switch
that sticks out of the aluminum.
Yeah. Now with this one it's like
a nice etched
plastic switch and
the hole is sort of cut to the size that
it needs to be for that switch.
Beard you have it right now. Do you agree with that.
Yeah. And they put it in.
Weren't they on the side before. Yeah. Well they
stood out more because they were in a more obvious spot.
Yeah. Now they've put it more
like close to the screen.
And it has a matte display. I'm not
I'm not blown away by the display to be
honest with you. The viewing angles are a little rough from
time. But if you're sitting if you're looking right
at it it's a pretty great display. And the fact that it's
non reflective is a nice
change of pace. I'd say it's at least comparable
or better than Lenovo displays.
Really. You like it. So you like it.
Yeah. Well I don't like Lenovo
displays. So now
the one thing so there's there's one thing that
they're doing differently with the trackpad that I'm having
a hard time adding
a description
to. It's a
decently sized trackpad
and it's it doesn't have like an obvious
right or left side. It's just one big
trackpad and it has some
multi-touch support including like two finger
scrolling and things like that. But it's
it's texturized.
It's texturized in a way that I like though
in a
in sort of a
in a way that gives me
sort of tactile feedback of where
I'm at on the trackpad like how much distance
my finger has traveled. But not
in a way that feels like I'm going
against gunk on the trackpad. Like it doesn't
it doesn't cause friction.
I disagree. Yeah I thought you might
because to me it does feel very frictiony
and I don't like it at all.
Yeah I thought you might. I'm a little more
I'm coming more from the MacBook trackpad which is
like slippery glass and I'm just
like that's the other extreme and I'm like
I think I like a little more traction right now.
Yeah I've definitely had like I don't mind
the amount of friction on this one.
It was pleasant enough. It's still
smooth. I could move as fast as I wanted
to. I've definitely encountered some trackpads where
it feels like you're just dragging your finger
across I don't know solid
sandpaper. Another thing that I've noticed with the trackpad
is if you drag your finger
from the bottom like where the invisible
buttons are
it won't move the mouse
and I haven't run into that with other
trackpads.
So that's a button only
area. Yeah. One of the things I like is it does
have hardware physical toggle right there
you can do FN and toggle the mouse button off
so you don't have to worry about like accidental
when you're doing a lot of typing. Speaking of
typing
I'm all over the map on this keyboard.
I think
when I put the laptop down and pick it
back up I'd like it a lot because
I've been experiencing RSI recently
and so this is one of those laptops where
my fingers aren't being slammed into
like a shallow keyboard hole
there's there's travel
and there's some good give to it
and I like that
aspect of it but my hands don't seem to quite
line up. Yeah.
I think this keyboard
would be perfect if they
didn't include the number pad.
It's funny you say that because I've been really enjoying
having that number pad. Yeah I feel
like you could if you really wanted a number pad
that you could just get an external one and plug it in.
Yeah I suppose so.
The way the keyboard is it feels cramped
and too off center so my
fingers are always on the wrong keys. Yeah I notice
it the most when I'm typing like a complicated password.
Or when you're
going through the Google doc for the show.
Ah yeah.
But what do you think of the feel of the keyboard
like if you're sitting down there because that particular
problem if I'm typing a lot in a day
I can I can generally reset
and I can I can adapt.
I like the feel of the keyboard.
I feel like the
I guess the base that's underneath it
tends to
send vibrations a bit too much.
Makes the whole laptop
vibrate and it bugs me a little
bit. So those are sort
of the unique things that I feel like they've
brought. And the reason why I wanted
to talk about these things is because
all of this feels different than a Clevo.
It doesn't doesn't. I don't.
This is this must not be a Clevo because this
it doesn't feel like a Clevo at all. It feels like
a custom built laptop
and that's something that generally only
get an impression of when I'm holding like an XPX
or a ThinkPad in my hands.
This feels like it
was built for this
purpose and it feels like it's a
unique piece of equipment. It actually
feels a lot like the razor
blade laptops which
I like. Yeah it does.
And they have a they have a purism
key on the super key there. So that's
the aesthetics. And it's I've
mentioned it's a it's a it's like an aluminum all
black. And
now the performance
has been pretty great.
I've been trying to get
fan issues to crop up because that's
what I had original problems with
and been quite happy with. Really.
The acoustics have been quite. I mean I guess if you
took it to New York you used it. Yeah.
And you know in almost
all cases I'd say
battery life was pretty
pretty pretty average. Were you using
any like power top or
you know I don't I wasn't I was
just sort of going with do. Can I get my
work done in the day. Yeah. And I was probably
doing three and a half four hours worth of work and
the battery was I just plugged in every single
night and the battery lasted every day for me just fine.
I'm going to I'm going to run a GPU benchmark and see
if it gets on the fans. Yeah do it. Yeah go
ahead because that is an interesting area to play with.
So you have you have something
that is
notably better than
the first model that I got in
every single way. Obvious
ways like the better CPUs
the better graphics the faster
SSDs the superior screen
all of those ways. But
in some of the ways that are truly
purism to like the way
the toggle switches are implemented or
the obvious
obvious care that went into
the keyboard that
feels uniquely purism
and that actually does
give me a lot of hope for
the Librem 5.
If anybody has ever owned a TiVo
you know
that the engineers of the TiVo
must have spent the majority of their time
developing the TiVo remote
because that's truly the most innovative
aspect of the TiVo was
the perfect peanut remote.
And you
and nobody's ever beat the TiVo remote.
Nobody has ever created a better remote
than the TiVo remote.
And it feels like that's where purism is going with the
keyboard. They're not there yet
but when you sit down and use it it feels
like something unique
to them. It doesn't feel like a ThinkBad
or a MacBook
and I don't think they're quite there yet
but you can tell a lot of thought and care
went into that. And when
you're looking at a lot of vendors out there a lot
of whom I respect who are selling
a repackaged Clevos in a way that
some of those things are sort of standard across
all of the models. It's really nice
to see some differentiation here. I don't
know where they're sourcing it from exactly so don't
quote me on all of that but it generally
somebody who has played with a lot of laptops
it's nice to see a unique trackpad
implementation and a unique keyboard
implementation with
what feels like their own hinge to
on the laptop screen. And then
the performance is as you would expect with
any of this generation of Intel and
and you know SSDs.
It's like yeah it may not be perfect. It may not
be where we want it to end up but
it feels like there's been care and
concern and design choices
made. I opted not to use PureOS
so they shipped it to
me with no OS installed.
And I've tried
Solus. I've tried Gentoo and I've
tried Ubuntu 17.10
proper which is what's on there
right now. And Beard I
kind of wanted to get your thoughts about that too
because
it's like a really great
Ubuntu machine isn't it? Like it's just the new
release and the black casing and
the nice screen and the colors with the
all black system. Like it all just
goes really well together don't you think?
And it says something about like
I didn't even realize that this was Gnome
or Ubuntu 17.10
until you told me because
it looked just like a Unity
desktop. Yeah it does look
a lot like Unity 7 too. Yeah that as
well. So the Librem
15 is actually
a contender. I really think it
is. I don't know for myself
if I would buy one today because what
I need from a system like this today
is Thunderbolt 3 support
in that USB-C port.
And I'd like charging and I'd like external
GPU because what I want to start doing
is I want to start switching over to laptops
that have Intel graphics built in
with external GPU support so I can buy
one GPU maybe once a year
and then I can switch it between
my systems. I
was not able to get this to work
with my external Thunderbolt 3 dock
at all for power or for
any devices external display or anything like that.
That would be something for me
that I would really really want.
Now however because now that I have this
obviously I'm going to be
using it for things so
I'm now going to just make this my
Ubuntu 17.10 system for a while
and it'll be my daily driver at home
running Ubuntu 17.10. Nice.
And yeah I think it's going to make
a great home workstation for me. See for me
I think long term I probably would
not like this. Mostly
because it doesn't have a dedicated GPU
built in. Yeah if you could see
that's why I was thinking like here at work I'm going to want a dedicated
GPU. So if you could hook up an external
eGPU. Yeah but
for someone like me I don't want to
spend an extra five or six hundred dollars
on an external GPU enclosure that I'm only
going to use with one system. Oh yeah
I would use it across a couple systems yeah.
Wimpy sold me on that pretty heavily.
Definitely.
But yeah
good build. I would not
be ashamed to take it into a coffee shop
or conference. No
it looks good and it's clean and
there's no obvious branding on the top.
Yeah kind of like that. On the bottom there's
like a Purism logo but it's just white on black
it's nice and clean. I feel like this is actually
a laptop if you took it to
like a coffee shop or something people would ask you what it is.
Yeah.
It's that good
polish wise. Yeah and I've got
I've got I picked up at Segal
I picked up an all white
circular gnome logo.
And it would look really good in the center of that
laptop. But of course I
may not end up writing gnomes out.
But yeah you're right. Everyone has to know. You just have to have it
installed you know. I feel like we need to do a
hardware hack where we just put a glowing
gnome foot on the back of the laptop.
The next things I would
yeah that'd be cool. The next things I'd really like to see from
laptops like this is no power
dongle needed. No separate power brick
and dongle. I'd like to see everything
being only powered off USB-C. That's an important one
for me. It really simplifies things so we can get there.
I gotta say man when I was editing
off of a car charger of cigarette
adapter in a car off of USB-C
I was like this is really useful.
And this laptop couldn't do that and
it made it not as usable in the car. And that's just
a small thing. It's only really applicable to me.
Hashtag Chris problems. And then
the other thing I'd really really really
love to start seeing
is I'd love to see some other manufacturer
besides Lenovo integrate
LTE modems or some sort of
cellular connectivity into these
sons of bitches. Right but not like not in a
you can add it if you open it up and add
but you know like a just like I can check it on the website.
I just add a SIM. I add a SIM card when I
get it and I can get connectivity because
I would love that. I would pick it all the time.
Having always
on connectivity is such
an important aspect to anybody
that would be getting a machine
like this that we're all
either jumping on insecure Wi-Fi
or we're tethering our devices
in some cockamamie fashion or
we're stopping by Starbucks constantly
and getting on the free Google Wi-Fi and they monitor everything
we do like there's no great option.
And one of the things that drives me crazy about
Noah is him and his
fancy ass Lenovo where the son of a gun
has two batteries and an LTE
modem and it all works under the
same screen. I'm like I want to buy
from a vendor who only builds Linux
systems but has those things.
So they're working on
the keyboard. They're working on the trackpad. They're
working on the matte display and
they've really nailed the 15.6 inch
you know system here.
If the next generation
could have USB-C charging and
Thunderbolt 3 and some sort
of cellular connectivity with another
hardware switch which is there with something
they're great at. I would be
all over that.
You're making me drool Chris. That would be a great system.
By the meantime if you don't need
those things this
system nails it. I was really impressed
and what's your battery at right now
because we've been off battery I don't know for
at least two hours. We still have another
four hours of battery left. Yeah okay there
you go. Is that 67 percent? Okay
so that's after about two hours of and you messing around
on the system checking it out not probably doing
benchmarks. Oh you are running some benchmarks.
Well it's not bad
and no fans yet.
No. Yeah that's really a thing about this one.
When I was running the GPU benchmark I very
slightly heard the fan. Yeah every now and then just a little bit
but I'm pretty particular
about that and I had it on
my desk which is a glass desk so it just
amplifies laptop fan noise
and really no complaints.
And in fact you know what
I had some benchmarks running on it when the room
was way hotter than it should have been because
I didn't leave my window open I left my door
closed and I got in there it was like 85 degrees
in American imperial degrees
and I got in there and it was
it was
ridiculously hot and that laptop
was chugging away and the fan noise was
still pretty respectable it was just like a little
just a little background noise.
Damn. Wow. Just past the hot
box test. Yeah.
So I'm impressed and so I'm going
to be packaging up my old one
my old Librem 15
and they're going to they're going to they're going to take it
and probably put it under some sort of like
quarantine or something I would imagine.
Maybe an honorary sacrifice. Yeah.
Viking funeral. Yeah. And melt it down and
use its parts for the Librem 5. Yep yep.
There we go. From the ashes. Recycling.
Alright
well Mumble Room you guys have been pretty quiet during
our review do you have any questions
about this here
hardware and about the Librem 15 before
we move on or any thoughts too if you have
about the Librem 5 feel free.
Yes I do. Go ahead.
So I was wondering about
I'm sorry about
the kill switches.
So if you
really have the laptop
by your side
are the kill switches soft or hard
and what can we expect if
they just
maybe break or stop
working. Well I
would I guess that have to be a warranty problem.
So there they are hard
plastic slide switches
that slide to the
they come shipped in the on position and
you just pop them over to the off position
sort of like similar to like a mute switch
on a smartphone. It's basically a physical disconnect
I believe. Yeah it is. Yeah that's how they do
it. So it just disappears
to the operating system.
Oh that's OK. Thank you.
Yeah I think that's kind of nice
actually and that's why I think they'd be
one of the best vendors to ship a LTE
motor because boy isn't that something I'd love to just leave
switched off completely. Yes exactly. No
doubts about it. No doubts about
spying. No doubts about accidental data usage.
No doubts about it. Just flip that switch
off and then when I need mobile Internet I flip
it on. I think that I think they'd nail
it. Of course they'd probably say buy a
Liebman 5. Oh no.
All right. Anybody else.
I'm good Chris. I don't really have
anything on top of my head.
Yeah. And yeah. Well there
you go. Beardsley you have any closing thoughts Beardsley
on that before we move on. I just saw something I'm using
the
USB hubs that are inside
the laptop. Apparently the vendor is listed
as the Linux Foundation.
Really. Yeah.
I don't know why. I bet
you we could find out. I bet you there's a good
I bet you there's a good story behind that. Yeah maybe.
All right. So
do you think we could take a little time to talk about
the show or do you think we should wrap it up.
Anything. We can talk about
it. I mean.
All right. So this is a wild west plus we started
a little late. So I'm just excited
that Dan's here from elementary. I know.
That's really cool. It's great to have you here Dan.
It's great to be here.
So Dan
was just featured was it last week in the
show. So check out interview with Dan
that we just had last week.
All right. So 218
right now and
I was you know we've recently had a lot of
changes.
With the end of Lass
and there's changes in the
works in JB already
that you don't know about.
And so I wasn't really going to make any big
changes here on this
show because I felt like you know
we'll just stay here. We'll be set
a rock of the network. Right. Exactly.
Exactly. But
in such then I began to wear
weary worry weird worry
about perhaps some stagnation.
And so I thought OK well
let's let's make changes by episode 300.
And I thought
about you know these things are actually pretty good.
None of them are really a bad thing. So we should make these changes
sooner. And so I think we're going to slowly start working
towards some stuff with episode 250.
So you're going to take a moment
talk about the show.
Which we don't do very often. And
all of this is subject to change as well.
Yeah.
Because things change right. Preliminary and
meta and you know. Yeah.
Yeah. Speaking of things changing maybe
it's time for you to change Linux Academy
dot com slash unplug. That's where you
go to learn more about Linux and all of the critical
technology and the stacks of
technology around. You got to call it a stack.
That's what we get to call it a stack now.
Out of all of the terms we use
stack is one of them we're going to take. Linux
Academy is a full featured training library
with everything you need to know to learn new skills
and advance your career in Linux.
They have hands on scenario based labs
that give you experience on real servers
and they have self paced in-depth
video courses which means when you
have time you can get the work done.
They have course schedulers so you can pick
a time frame and stick to it with certain
learning goals and they have human beings that can
help you when you get stuck and they have learning
passes which are a series of courses and contents
planned by instructors for specific
career tasks and they have practice
exams which you can take before you actually
go take the big test which probably would
have been maybe one of the number one features
I was probably I mean
maybe that maybe that and
maybe the hands on labs for me would have been the two
features when I was trying to get my certs that I could have used
a lot more of as I couldn't
imagine having Linux Academy back in the day
when I was working in IT.
I mean I use it now just to dabble and one of the things
I love about it is you get like hour estimations
of how long learning something is going to take
and you get course where you can download with you
and listen to offline like those are things that
today I can appreciate but
oh man when I was when I was playing
that race of making sure I can get the certifications
so that way I can either get improvements on
the review or I can get that client
I always got to taking the test
and would sort of jam up there
and if I could have taken more practice
exams or I could have taken courses that were
created specifically to prepare you for
the certification exams that
would have been a fundamental enabler for me.
Well and they're like you know you don't
have to bootstrap yourself so especially if you're
new to this can be pretty hard like okay well go set
up your own test server at home figure out how to
do that with Linux Academy like no just
they'll get you right in the environment you need to learn
whatever it is that you're actually working on
and then after like once you've figured it out
you just play with it so you can you know keep
doing it do it again go advanced
on it it's all right there and if you
get stuck human beings are there to help
and they're always adding new content
and retroactively adding and
proving the old content as well so
go to linuxacademy.com slash unplug
to sign up for a free seven day trial and support
the show linuxacademy.com slash
unplugged and a big thank you to
Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged
program so it is time for us to take
bold action Wes bold
action is required upon
us here for the unplugged program turns out
change is a way of life
we're making it into a show about hot sauce
well we are pivoting to a cooking show
no
well although sometimes
we joke we one day we would just
launch a cooking show just to get out of our system
it feels like it's inevitable like it's
gonna happen the beard and I joke about it
all the time so okay
let's talk about I consider them upgrades
so let's talk about why the changes
so right now Linux Unplugged
is Jupiter Broadcasting's largest
podcast which is funny because I don't
think of it as that because I'm so used to
having last be the largest podcast it's true
though so that means it's probably
up there in terms of largest
Linux podcast I don't know if I can't claim it's the
largest although I think if you count video downloads
it's got to be up there but who knows anymore
last was so
huge that it just seemed easy to say yeah
that's obvious now with love it's like I'm
slugging it out and
we don't want to stand still basically
like I said I was gonna wait till 300
but I can't hold back
yeah that's what it's a waste
so what are the changes
here's what I'm thinking now none of this
is set in stone all of this is
subject to change and it's gonna
depend on if we can make it happen
obviously
but I think to keep
Unplugged competitive and to keep people
enjoying the show
we're gonna go to a full video
show that's better produced than
last ever was and we're gonna do that
by making Unplugged an audio only
show
you following me
we're gonna go we're gonna become a video
show that was better produced than
Linux action show ever was
and we're gonna do that by
becoming an audio show
an audio only show
that's more edited
it's closer to Linux action news as polish
but with the chill vibe
of Linux Unplugged and still live
while being a full video show
so that's what we're gonna do
is this before or after we've invented that
time travel
so what we're gonna do is
we're going to buy about a thousand dollars
or more in camera equipment if we can get the support
you know so we'll have a camera for me
a camera for you a camera for a guest
eventually if the beard ever goes on
camera we'll have a camera for him
and my intention is
what I'm thinking is we'll release a full unedited
video version behind the scenes
sort of like if you're gonna watch
like the Howard Stern show behind I don't know that's probably
a bad example but I'm trying to think of some radio
what are you setting us up for here?
you and I will be on camera and we'll
make that feed available to the patrons
because we have the whole pipeline to do that
we just have to add a couple of camera
pieces of equipment and boom boom boom done
and we've got the switcher we've got the
production pipeline we've got the publishing platform
we've got the download CDN everything
we need to do that is in place
but the thing I always hated about the Linux
action show was we had a camera
straight on and it was two people
sitting in front of a table
and not facing each other looking at a camera
with studio lights on and it just creates
a phony environment
and the green screen didn't help and
this would be you and I still sitting here
across the table looking at each other in the eye
doing this show
lights off relaxed but people
could just be here with us and
when you're talking the camera would be on you when I'm talking
camera on me etc. Are we gonna have to
put pants on for this?
No. This is for patrons.
Oh right. So then what we'll do with the wider
audience we'll get a better sounding more polished
product so we'll do multi track recording
of some capacity I'm not there yet we may
make changes in how we produce the virtual
lug so we can improve the audio
quality there.
And that
will be a show and we'll make small
edits to that so that way like if there's
some weird erroneous loud noise
or a click or a clack or
too much talking over each other we'll clean
some of that up.
And publish that as
the standard show
with well produced audio levels
slightly tighter and cleaner production
but not dramatically changed which
would be the main show. And then if you want the
behind the scenes version we'll have that completely
unedited version that we have now.
It'll be like you're just right here in the studio with us.
And I think and so don't
don't jump to conclusions about
will the show change or anything like that because I think
if all of this is implemented right
all the things we like about the show will just be better
and it won't be like
this radical change to the show. In fact
I could have gotten away without saying anything potentially
but the wider audience should get a better
sounding more polished product that's
more competitive I think.
And is easier to listen
to. And the video version will have
better production than the Linux action show ever had
for those that really want it that still miss last.
And the hardware investment would be our
initial upfront cost but then after that we'd be just
utilizing our existing production pipeline we're already
pumped for so
it's a pretty straightforward process
for JB to implement. And I think it would make
for a good show all around because those that want
a really great audio show will get it and people
that want to laid back
sort of low key video show will get that too.
A lot of flexibility. And we'll
make some changes in how we record the
individual microphones and mumble to make this
all happen.
But all of it will be for the better.
So that's we're working towards that towards 250 now.
I think what we're going to do
and we haven't made the official changes yet but I think
what we're going to do is we're going to set a milestone
on our Patreon page at patreon.com
slash Jupiter signal for forty
five hundred dollars.
We have to change some of the milestone stuff right now.
And we're going to work
towards that because we're going to make the initial
purchase for
the cameras but then also
we're going to either hire somebody
or I'm going to or some
somebody is going to be editing
the audio version of the show.
So that way it's a fully fledged
well produced supported product.
And so we're also going to be trying to raise
funds to make that happen. And so that's
why we're hoping that if people like this
idea or just want to help
us improve the production quality of the show they
consider becoming a patron at patreon.com slash
Jupiter signal and then once you become one
later on once the video version is published
you would get access to that.
Which is really not too far
away. It just takes time and cameras.
Yeah. All of which we
can figure out but just
going to take some financing. And
I know that all sounds like a lot
but if you think about all the pieces we have
in place it's actually all quite doable
because the video can be produced
on OBS. Yeah we have that.
And that's that's running all the time.
The audio can be recorded on a separate machine
on a multi-track recorder
that spits out FLAC files
or WAV files or whatever
that goes off to
Rekai or a dedicated audio editor or
myself that then
runs the production on that and publishes
that as an MP3 and AUG or Web
M or whatever crazy ass format people want.
Right. And that's that nothing really
changes there. And
the video version is already done because it's
unedited. Yeah it's just a live OBS
creates the file and then we upload
that to Scale Engine we publish to the patrons
and we're done. And
we don't walk this weird awkward
line anymore.
It just takes us changing some hardware
or actually adding some hardware
and adding some staffing.
Yeah. Contract staffing likely.
So it seems doable. So we're just
we're going to we're going to we're going to try to get
to a new milestone on Patreon
to get there and I'm going to say I'm hoping we get there
by 250.
We'll see. What do you guys think? Am I crazy?
Everybody's good to me. No I like that idea.
I mean. Sounds good. Video
can be fun. I like the like
live unplugged aspect and it's I mean
like we're hanging out here. It's a lot of fun. I think it would be fun to
to kind of share that more.
And also I've been loving land
so there's certainly times
I would. And you've been on the other end of the actual production
aspect of land which that means there's
some there's other things there that we gain
that are sort of like inside baseball but
great from a production standpoint.
Which would be nice. Yeah.
So here's my question.
Yes. You're going to be doing a nice
audio focus show when you can
upgrade me to an RE20. I know.
Maybe we'll do that when we get to the milestone as well.
Upgrade that microphone. Get you off the old stuff.
Yeah. That's people don't know
because we don't have cameras in here. But Rekai's on this weird
old mic that we used to use that
we no longer use. But then when we set up two more
additional chairs in the studio we had to pull out the old stuff.
I missed the sexy bassiness
of my voice. Yeah.
When you do use here you sit on a different mic so it sounds like a
different Rekai.
Well yeah. Then we'll work on that too.
We'll work on that. All right.
So if you have any thoughts
I'd like to hear them. So go over to the usual
places like jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash contact or
you can go to linuxunplug.reddit.com
or if you're a patron
I'd really like to hear your thoughts at patreon.com slash
jupiter signal.
And before we go I want to give
a plug to Mr. Popey's
Ubuntu podcast. Go check that out.
Always a great listen.
See what I'm listening. Hold on. Let me promote my
player right now. I'm listening to
season 10 episode 31
right now. So I just
that's how I love the show. And you know what
after seeing those guys
after seeing those guys in New York
I realized I missed hanging out with them when I got back to
Washington. That's so sweet.
So you want to hear my solution. It's not it's not it's
not bulletproof but it's there it's getting there.
You ready. Hey Siri.
What are beans.
A common name for large seeds
of several genera of the flowering plant family
for bacilli also known as leguminosi
which are used for human or animal
food. I've changed my
Siri voice to be quote unquote
British.
And now it's now I think you
guys when Siri talks to me which is weird
in a lot of ways when I think about it.
I think about it. Yeah. So check out the Ubuntu podcast
and of course Ubuntu
on air dot com on
Monday 1500 UTC
for the ISO testing seems like
a good cause seems like a very good
cause. All right.
Absolutely. Thank you for being here. I think that's going to
bring us to the end of this week. So is there anything else we want to cover.
I was going to try to fit in the Gentoo review this week
but I think we've kind of run out of time.
So I guess we should probably punt that
till next week. And you know who saw that
coming. I didn't know. We don't want to distract
people should be thinking about the show the future getting
excited for it. So that's a perfect note to
well and you know the Libra 15 reviews really the meat
of the show. That was the focus this week. So I hate
to talk about Gentoo and it hasn't been the primary
focus. So I
guess for this week we're going to punt it. I didn't
see it coming. Didn't see it. I apologize.
I'm sure we'll get to it soon
though. I'm sure that's coming up very soon maybe 2 19
in the meantime. Thank you very much for being
here. If you'd like to join us go to Jupiter
broadcasting dot com slash calendar. We have all
of our lifetimes there and then we've got a
Mumble room you can participate in the
Mumble room a Mumble room go to
Mumble dot Jupiter calling dot com for the setup guide
as long as we're still using that we'll see
we'll see
we'll see you can also subscribe to get the show
weekly. And of course we
appreciate any content on the subreddit
that I mentioned just a bit ago. Follow the network
at Jupiter signal on Twitter's
and we'll see you right back here next
Tuesday.
All
right. And it is officially post
show. Good job everybody.
It was great having you all here.
Now let's go pick a title. Let's go see if we
can't name this thing. JB title see if the chat room
came up anything. If you're in the discord room feel
free to drop a few in there right
now. Windows unplugged
foggy transport protocol punting
Gentoo. Who saw that one coming
punting Gentoo again.
She's she's she's
he came. There you go.
I'm back. I'm back. I'm back.
So
make it for that was
cool. Well Chris I just
finished setting up no nice
known to know to. Yes
exactly. You crazy. Now you're going to load
compass or I mean
maybe I'm getting covers on this
son of a compass fusion.
Oh yeah. There we go. That's yeah I'm going to
have the fusion icon baby. Yeah
I got to get the I got to get the control center icon
thing so you can right click this exactly
here.