I am legitimately I think I didn't realize it but I have like some sort of weird Linux
fest sleep hangover happens every year but I sat down and I actually forgot to even get
in the mumble room.
Have we ever even done the show without a mumble room?
Does it make sense even?
It's Linux Unplugged.
You got to cough the mumble rooms here.
That is probably what it is yeah both of you guys are here and so that is it that's a good
portion at least but sounds like sounds like Wes has a pick me up before we get started.
Yes well okay we both been watching the very same show and you've reached something of
an important juncture.
Oh really?
So I just thought you're gonna be done soon it's always hard when you finish a show you
know it's all it's all over you miss the characters.
Here we go.
I got you something to remember it by.
Oh okay all right here we go here we go ladies and gentlemen oh my god no no.
It's all the songs.
It's a CD of Vic Fontaine from D Space Nine.
Absolutely.
The worst thing about D Space Nine now on his own CD oh the only the only thing that's
gonna make this better is you know I'm gonna put this in the car and put this on when I'm
in with Hadia and see how long it takes her to notice.
I would think maybe we could rip it and get some soundboard clips.
I can't believe you found this I can't believe are any of the songs from the show on here?
Yeah that they're all songs from the show.
Oh yeah Saturn doll I'll be seeing you oh wow I'm getting angry just thinking about
it I'm getting there there you go I feel much better now thank you Wes.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 299 for April 30th 2019.
Well hello there and welcome to your weekly Linux talk show that's just made it back from
a huge Linux fest Northwest.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello Mr. Payne how are you feeling?
Oh I'm alive.
Everything but barely.
Did you get some rest?
A little bit I mean I approached a full night's sleep but it's about the only one in the past
week yeah you're even worse yeah but but we did walk away with some great stories so we'll
talk about those today and we've got some great friends joining us in studio some of
some of them that have hung around from the fest thankfully actually to make it on the
show so we'll get to all of that you know in this week's podcast in this little here
show coming right up lots to talk about two plus towards the end of the show a brand new
segment something we're rolling out some of the flicks all of us premiered today first
time first time right here on the show so we'll get to that in just a bit but before
we go any further got to bring in that virtual lug time appropriate greetings mumble room
hello there hello hello hello Brandon Bruce code sections Jeff mini mech well remember
Sony six I can't see remembers only Oh Oh remembers only right of course tech Mav and
turf are in there as well but on the studio line we have the one the only mr. cheese bacon
hello cheese hey what's up guys hey man how you doing doing great good good good well
nobody cares because we have something very important I love you too very excited to welcome
Brent back in studio it's been a while Brent hello almost exactly a year yeah it's tradition
now mm-hmm it's tradition gotta keep it going and joining us in the studio for the first
time mr. ironic Badger it's Alex hello Alex good day pip pip hello hello how are you doing
very well thank you good nice to have you for an extended time in the Pacific Northwest
sounds like he's falling in love it's beautiful I know I think you should move up here dude
yeah one day well okay well we have a lot to talk about today not just Linux vest but
we have some really really big news to start out with fedora 30 is out right now as we
record and we're taking a look at the fedora 30 workstation which ships with gnomes three
dot three two completely refreshed icon themes new consistency across the desktop way snappier
performance the new application panel the control permissions for flat packs and a lot
more of course there's also the silver blue release and the cloud edition release but
I regrettably because of all the Linux fest stuff did not quite get this installed before
the show wanted to take L out to lunch before she had a flat that's nice I know did you
get a chance to give it a look hmm you know it took a while I think their CDNs are pretty
popular a lot of people downloading this release which is a good sign yeah I got it installed
in a virtual machine and booted into the live CD and it's I mean it's nice every time fedora
comes out it's always a little hard because it's not it's not a radical change right it's
a small iterative improvement but I've been looking forward to their release of gnome
three dot three two because I've been enjoying it so much in 1904 and that flicker free boot
oh it's shiny oh man we've been looking forward to that for a while okay I mean it's honestly
I hardly ever reboot my computer except for like a kernel upgrade so I don't see it a
lot it's not something I really care about but as someone who grew up some of the first
hacking I did on a computer you know a wee little lad breaking my windows my parents
windows workstation was changing how the boot screen appeared and finally Linux users get
first class decent looking boot now you need a flicker free kegs yeah maybe someday I tease
there's there's numerous improvements throughout fedora and gnome three three two pretty much
worth it just for that update alone but I'll give you more thoughts later on as I get a
chance to kick the tires congratulations to the team and hopefully we'll get a chance
to do a little comparison and performance did you have any early impressions between
the Ubuntu 1904 implementation of gnome shell and the fedora 31 I mean there's always a
little you know they don't have the Ubuntu style theme but otherwise performance wise
they both just felt really snappy it's always nice to have a fresh fedora installed with
good classic gnome I didn't do any tweaking so it wasn't I would say it doesn't come out
of the box quite as pretty as 1904 but yeah you can style it to your taste yeah yeah exactly
and some people do prefer the more standard-looking no and it's perfectly usable you know like
you may not like the default theme but it works just fine sure sure Alex I'm curious
did you hear any of the purism scuttlebutt while we were at Linux fest Northwest I had
some things I'm not sure I'm allowed to repeat oh I'm going to repeat them I will I wasn't
going to necessarily but then we have a pretty big announcement today from purism and I don't
know if you guys have seen this but it is the era of services and they have launched
the Librem one a quote growing bundle of ethical servers services they have five hundred and
thirty out of five thousand backers yes this is another crowd funder from purism this one
now for services and it includes a range of apps Librem chat Librem social Librem mail
and Librem tunnel yeah chat is an end-to-end encrypted VoIP chat using matrix Librem mail
is a rebadged mail client I understand Librem tunnel is I think private internet access
white label and Librem social I think is also a rebadge of mastodon and things like that
but it's it's self-hosted private labeled privacy first focus as they say no ads no
tracking and quote we respect you have you seen how many options there are on these
packages it's quite a bit yeah there's must be 15 20 different options here what do you
think of the pricing so like the basic pricing is you described it as a as like a crowdfunding
thing but generally I think of a crowdfunding program as something you pay up front of like
a you know you pay one cost here though they're all talking and they say like the full monthly
bundle $7.99 a month they also have a couple of weird ones like a $20 one-time or $5 monthly
donation so there's like different options where you can just and the way they write
it is it's kind of interesting Purism is a social purpose company if you'd like to donate
to the cause of social good and technology and want to see more products and services
from Purism well we welcome it so just send us some money but at this point it's going
to be cheaper in the long run to invest in your own self-hosted thing is it not and just
as privacy focused I do think it's an interesting space to explore because we're all all right
I mean right people people that use Dropbox or other things there are many managed services
that we like to use we have complaints about their the privacy of the implementation of
what's going on behind the scenes and I've been kind of wondering why don't we see more
of this you know taking the open source software that we can run for ourselves and not really
developing it anymore maybe they're adding back to it but just running it for you compare
a digital ocean droplet at five dollars a month running next cloud with this service
for eight dollars a month you know you look at the feature list here you know vpns documents
mail all the rest of it and there's pretty much nothing you can't self-host yourself
for five dollars a month that they're offering here for eight absolutely but for three dollars
more so like I pay I think like two dollars a month for someone to host my mail server
not that I couldn't I just don't want to and I think mail's on the on the other end of
that spectrum mail I would agree because of the whole spam thing but everything else like
next cloud is so good now that's true especially with the with the snap version that they have
it is easy to install I just wonder I mean are there people who like the philosophy but
don't have an admin experience or just don't have the time to want to bother with a digital
ocean droplet yeah I think there is likely a customer base for this kind of stuff or
else things like slack wouldn't be as popular as they are people want convenience of push
button get a service the the scuttlebutt that I heard and what is concerning because if
you just look into it if you know the people involved it is apparently true people received
layoff notices from purism Saturday evening over the weekend some of the people like in
their sales department Sheree from gnome and others were let go Saturday they went home
Friday thinking they had a job on Monday and Saturday evening they got an email saying
you let go and now we are pivoting to services which seems to be the popular brace yourselves
kids because we're gonna get a lot more of this over 2019 and 2020 hey I need a reoccurring
revenue stream turns out selling and shipping to a free software market is hard to monetize
so let's go for reoccurring and let's figure out how we can rebadge some open source services
and do this fundraiser style initiative now my issue here is having been a previous backer
of purism products is the previous products have not necessarily been 100% delivered on
the laptops didn't necessarily meet the original commitments now they have iterated on that
over time the Libram 5 is currently the development edition is slightly delayed unlikely to ship
in July as promised that's also a crowd raise product and now we have services that are
also crowd funded while they're kind of quietly letting staff go on a Saturday night how many
people are involved in this in this project behind the scenes right what's the company
look like well this is what I wanted to get to so purism is an interesting beast because
they're a social purposes company established here in Washington State now they're they're
a corporation in California like they're a business out of California but their social
purposes status is out of Washington State and God bless them I think this is an interesting
idea especially if let's just say things really line up well the Libram 5 ships the Libram
15 and those laptops do well PureOS gets a large user adoption and you start having devices
that are phones laptops and tablets all running PureOS you combine it with this Libram one
service and all of a sudden you're starting to see kind of an Apple iCloud model very
much so you can see the logic in it that does not make it a reality and the thing that really
bothers me as a former sysadmin is just like we've seen with these streaming services like
CBS all access companies that don't have this as their core focus think it's easy to just
stand up a service real quick oh I'll just you know what we'll get into services we'll
build some servers we'll rebadge some software we'll invest in security we'll get a couple
really smart people on our team and we'll really build out a really scalable secure
infrastructure and we'll start offering services to answer Alex's question on their their core
team page there's currently about 22 people listed and that really bothers me because
companies with 22,000 employees can barely provide infrastructure grade reliable services
companies like YouTube and ESPN have invested decades in their streaming infrastructure
and in their storage infrastructure and so for a company that's making laptops and now
attempting to make a phone and topple Android also wanting to get into services while having
a small employee base that's essentially the size of my team to make podcasts nearly is
crazy, it's crazy. Does anybody remember Mobile Me with Apple? That was a hot mess and if
Apple can't do it and you know canonical struggle with Ubuntu Touch with a lot more people and
a lot more money I think this guy's on cloud nine isn't he? Well you know you got to have
a you know you do need to have a visionary somebody who's willing to be bold Todd is
a bold visionary character and that draws a lot of people in. It helps if the vision
is realistic though. Well here's what the issue is and this is see we are I think because
I hear from the audience all the time about this is we're the minority on this issue is
what we're really facing here is I think the limitations of humanity. Seriously the problem
is is that we are all tribal monkeys that want to be signaling constantly to each other
I agree with you I belong in your tribe I agree with what you believe I want to be in
your tribe and so we do that by promoting things that seem great ideas that reflect
our ideals and our beliefs like software freedom like the ability to turn off your webcam the
ability to load your own operating system on your own phone that kind of stuff is things
we believe in and so we want to see that propagate we want to see that continue so we want a
virtue signal that we think that's great so we tend to just talk about this stuff and
lacker over all of the obvious issues because deep down we're all a bunch of optimists and
we want to see this stuff be successful we want to believe there's a big enough market
to buy free software phones we want to believe a company like purism can come around and
change an entire entrenched industry that nearly goes back now a hundred years of legacy
we want to believe that's possible and because we don't have the hands-on experience we have
no idea how complicated of a job it is we frankly don't understand any of the dynamics
involved in carrier agreements and getting something certified for a carrier network
we have no insights into any of that we have no idea what it takes to manufacture a phone
or to stamp out a motherboard or to write drivers for a modem we have no concept of
any of that and so we sit back and go that seems possible yeah that seems like that's
some that should be really easy how hard could it be well I sure hope they can get it well
let's give them another fundraiser let's raise more money because obviously it's gonna go
somewhere because I believe in this idea and god forbid you don't believe in it because
if you don't believe in it then you don't love free software you don't respect privacy
don't do you want the NSA listening to your phone calls West how could you not believe
in five there's something wrong with you because you're skeptical and that propagates
shysters and crazy ideas because we love ourselves a great big moral idea and if you got a company
here like purism who will tell you every three paragraphs that they're the moral authority
in their blog seriously they go here they list out the business models of purism Facebook
Google all of them are horribly evil companies that want to track you and control you except
for purism which quote benefits society then at the bottom of this post there's a bunch
of random quotes that don't really have anything to do with the product like there's quotes
in there from Stallman and other people but the top quote the top quote is from Todd Weaver
and the top quote says society's technology genius is not lacking but it's moral genius
is because Todd's going to be our moral authority and he's going to guide us with
his social purposes company into free software and hardware now if you don't like free software
and if you don't like privacy and you don't respect users control over their computers
then why would you care something about Libra why would you back this but if you do care
if you don't want them privacy if you don't want them spying on you and invading your
junk well then you should probably back this and because I'm saying that they're a tiny
company who isn't built to do something like this and who should be focusing on what they
can do and I'm the lunatic I'm the crazy person I'm the bad person we all know this
to be true gets me crazy I think what you need to do is is fund a much more grassroots
level approach to solving this problem so the talk that I gave at Linux Fest Northwest
for example was about writing your own firmware for your own home home assistant related home
automation stuff if you if you enable people smart people to write their own firmwares
or you know 56k modem firmwares we have no concept of how difficult they are to write
if we make all of the bits that go into a phone open then we've we've seen over the
years that open source will do amazing things with that technology the baseband in the purism
phone I have no idea how that works but the baseband in my Android phone is a completely
separate operating system that is a black box that the NSA probably have a backdoor
right into so my question really is how how can we audit what Libras purism are doing
how can I as a an open source advocate how can I sit here and say yes what they're doing
is actually legit I think this is the problem like I was saying earlier we have no context
we have no concept of like even how hard it is to get the corner plastic pieces of the
phone molded we don't even know we don't how long how long does it take to mold the corner
pieces of Libra and five does anybody know who have they contracted to do that we don't
know any of this information we're just told don't worry I just take care of it we have
a vision I just got my pixel 3 in the mail today so it's sitting at home waiting for
me which I'm excited about but even then right Google just admitted they were having how
all the problems they've been having with that line and they're a huge business who
already has some of these deals in place and they still can't get a phone as cheap as they
want it to be so exactly how are we supposed to yeah now I am curious one option would
be that we just shouldn't fund this sort of thing because it's not realistic well and
this is just gonna be one of many there's gonna be other are there ways that they could
communicate more so maybe you know maybe at some of the issue I think we're having is
the unrealistic expectations and that there are a lot of people who don't know that and
are then funding it right are there ways that a business like this or a project like this
could be a more upfront about that say like listen we want your money do we know we're
doing maybe kind of we want to explore this buyer beware you know what I think I think
no because I think what makes a company like purism successful is by rolling hard into
the freedoms aspect of it and the privacy aspect of it and by positioning themselves
as a moral authority because they they respect and and and try to enable user privacy right
there they're setting themselves as a moral authority leader and when you're coming when
you're when that's your brand there's really no higher ground right there's you there is
no way to talk about this stuff in sort of a humble way because you've already just crossed
that out by the way that you're branding and marketing yourself right so I suspect there
is no going back and I also know from my own personality that I'm the type of person that
when you get rid when you get high on the hyperbole scale when you get rid of you know
what I'm like what's a good way to put that like when you get really high on the lake
PR yeah yeah it's just I start it starts to trigger me it just really does and I but
I also appreciate that to really reach the market they're trying to reach they have to
hit those notes really hard this is going to be a model in a sense yeah I think you're
going to have distributions that try to do things like this to try to monetize the user
base you look at what Apple's doing with iOS they've looked at this okay well we're having
a hard time selling more iPhones but we got a billion active iOS devices let's start monetizing
that user base with services so they're launching TV streaming services they're going to launch
all this crap everybody's going to do that it's all going to be about the reoccurring
eight bucks they can get out of you and we're just this is the beginning of many what kind
of bothers me about this one and this is really petty because this is open source free software
but they've lifted two of the icons for their apps the mail app and the chat app and I'm
I know the mail app the mail app is the Geary icon that's Gary mail straight up they just
straight up lifted it's probably a free it's probably a free icon but I don't know she's
what they like does that bother you like it bothers me I mean you know they have they
could be working with the dev for all we know right maybe it is here and they could leave
her mail is Gary no because if these are all Android apps I should point out these are
all Android iOS apps are not Linux apps right so you know maybe they're working with the
team or maybe they at hopefully they ask the team that'd be really shitty thing to do to
just lift an icon for something else which I mean people do all the time it's not like
it doesn't happen all the time or not like Brent hasn't had a million of his photos taken
in the other stuff right so I mean it happens everywhere whether it's in you know the open
source world or not you know the whole thing man I see it's it's interesting how they're
they're trying to provide a services type plan but you know didn't Google one time say
don't be evil yeah right like where do we where do we draw the line and how do we trust
how do we trust purism to be that company I think there are other companies out there
that are doing similar things the pine guys and they're just here's a piece of hardware
you know this is for the community this is for you guys use it try it out break it you
know it's inexpensive yeah and at this point I feel like to some degree it's a race to
market between these two and so while maybe this was something that purism was going to
do later they decided to drop it earlier to create more buzz before because I really think
these two companies in particular are racing to get out to market with something if anything
just for the the links in the open source community where's that recurring revenue gonna
come from so Apple we just said you know struggling to sell devices I mean that they're putting
things on sale for the first time practically ever all the time if you know like the pine
guys you know here's a piece of hardware like you said what where does where does that upgrade
cycle where does that revenue to sustain the company come from if they don't go into services
that's but I think that's the that's the real question how do you sustain an income and
well I think that's when they they they come up with a with another device they keep iterating
on that product if they can keep it in a in a price range that's reasonable you've got
to finish there would be no yeah there's a smaller scale too right like we might expect
the big guys be able to make a new phone every year every two years but that's gonna that's
gonna be a challenge those big guys those those annual phones are generally only fairly
iterative yeah right or Samsung who throws out just all the all the crap that they possibly
can and you know there's entire youtubers that make careers out of saying is it worth
upgrading if you have to ask that question no it's not right right I think I think what
I come back to is my core concern is I have a fundamental and maybe it's out date but
I have a fundamental belief that if you are going to offer data storage services like
chat like mail and VPN tunneling where you're where you are also either white labeling or
standing up VPN infrastructure it is my outdated belief I guess that you need to be a specialist
in services you need to know how to run servers it needs to be what you do now that said if
I was gonna pay a monthly money for something like this I suppose I like the option of being
able to use stuff that's all based on open source software it's funny if this was the
only thing that they were doing yes I would believe they could started with this yes absolutely
yeah that's what's so weird is if they started with this I would not be nearly as skeptical
but because it seems like it kind of seems like flailing around a little bit we're gonna
do a tablet we're gonna do laptops we're gonna do this they can't even get the SSL set for
their VPN domain right oh is it still screwed up as of now yeah that's been since Saturday
yeah yeah I know I thought maybe I thought maybe by the time they announced it they'd
have it fixed yeah I have not tried that I trust them now is it possible that they're
just really good at selling ideas and not so good at carrying them through that's kind
of what we've seen in the last few years is that their their ideas are are actually quite
sound however the the bringing to market is where things are falling apart a little bit
ideas are sexy and tempting and easy to write on a web page uh-huh it's much easier to say
I'm going to do this than actually doing this right and I think I'm a big believer that
actually shipping is is the difference between professionals and amateurs like actually getting
it shipped out there in a something that you can you can feel good about is harder than
coming up with the idea and the last 10% so cliche but the last 10% is the hardest part
it's like a number of people that say I'm gonna do a podcast and then yeah yeah don't
ship every week like you do yeah or all kinds of things right people get and that's fine
you know for some people it's just uh really it's that they are billed that we are billing
them as this big name with a big project an idea that's really important that we should
support and there are aspects that like you said the philosophy that we agree with but
we just we need to be realistic about yeah the scale and expectations and um given enough
time and given enough resources they may be able to get there but right now I'm just I'm
not I'm not a big fan of the look of the constant fundraiser thing either it's concerning to
me that they're not at a sustainable point now I know you could argue well there are
social purposes company and so blah blah blah they give money back blah blah I don't buy
it simply don't buy it yeah I think it introduces a large amount of uncertainty in their finances
and that I'm sure makes it hard to plan for on their end which only makes it even harder
for us to have any idea what's actually going on yeah so what's the alternative then let's
play devil's advocate for a second if if you were Todd and you wanted to build a sustainable
company around this stuff what other choice does he have well going back to Wes's point
sorry to interrupt but going back to Wes's point I think um I think they would have started
with services I think part of it is I've never really believed the tablet and phone hype
that they've they've had and that has always since they've since they've gone down that
route they've really kind of dropped down in credibility in my book because not only
is it a insurmountable problem it is a problem that is solved we should be figuring out the
next major platform and getting open source and free software there first for once instead
of spending five six years a decade after the fact trying to catch up and even come
barely close to feature comparative it just seems like a fool's errand because even if
you get there the market isn't standing still and it eventually by the time you get a competent
product the next wave be it wearables or VR headsets or implants or whatever it is will
be here will be arrived like that it'll be the people that are working on that or will
have started so we'll just be missing that boat now correct me if I'm wrong isn't that
why Ubuntu Touch ended up in the way it did was that you know that the pace of the market
is such that unless you are Apple or Google it's almost impossible to keep up yeah I heard
this weekend from people who were familiar with the matter that looking at the videos
like the videos that developers have released and that purism is released that there were
canonical was about four years ago which was about two years from like getting deals with
BQ and whatnot so we'll see and so what happens if you've contributed to this this crowdfunding
thing and it doesn't ship well then you can you contributed to a good cause okay I wonder
if a different business model might be helpful and I have an idea to grow on what you were
just talking about so I'm glad you interrupted me because it grew my idea a little bit gave
me a little bit of time I wonder if they might be you know since their their strength is
ideas and vision it seems or at least some moral high ground that is a lot of people
appreciate I wonder if it might be a good idea to instead of concentrating on products
which is where their weak point seems to be on shipping products I wonder if there might
be almost like a patreon style funding for their business if they're gonna be what they're
doing isn't it yeah but they're tying it to a specific product so what if you are instead
funding them to grow ideas and be almost a think tank to try to get open source ahead
of the curve maybe just be more honest like because that's probably I mean probably these
fundraisers do go to keep the company going of course it's pretty obvious crowdsourced
VC funding that's what yeah all right well we spent way too much time it'll be interesting
to see where it goes you know that's this is the ultimate this is one of our this is
one of our more ponderous stories the ultimate pondries ponderous story for the last few
years just last point apparently they've quietly dumped the tablet yeah yeah yeah yeah all
right well few things to talk about looks like L joined us in the mumble room she's
on her way down to docker con right now so if you're gonna be a docker con say hi to
L are you at are you at the airport right now I am if you can hear with all the background
noise how is pain field it's tiny it took five minutes to get through security it was
amazing perfect I love it I love it I love it we have a live we have L on the scene at
pain field right now you guys know how it's awesome I've been talking about pain field
the whole weekend I'm just so jealous all the locals are jealous of you so yeah yeah
totally jealous so L's got to what a couple hour flight down to San Francisco and there's
docker con time yeah decker con party people should join me there absolutely absolutely
how should they find you look for the hair follow you on Twitter yeah just look for the
hair or just ask somebody I hate to say it but somebody will have seen my hair they know
who she is you know the girl with the great hair and also knows all the things about containers
cool that'll be great and there may be a couple of stickers you never know depends supply
walls while supplies last oh my those stickers these hot stuff they're pretty good they're
pretty good well I'm glad you're able to give us a on location pain field report L safe
travels but Wes has dared me to go and preach the gospel of LXD so we shall see if it's
safe travels or not wow I believe in you into the wolf's den with that one did you put her
up to that oh yeah I mean I saw her for all of I don't know 10 seconds while she was hopping
out from the studio to go catch this flight yeah yeah of course yeah good um next week
Red Hat Summit Wes Cheese and I will be at Red Hat Summit Alex are you going to Red Hat
Summit the Red Hatter is not going to Red Hat Summit that's ironic silly isn't it I've
just not found anyone's budget to put the expenses again right yeah yeah you just start
making the expenses and they'll tell you where to put it that's how it works yeah my bank
account probably yeah yeah very very fair I totally understand there's a lot of competition
internally for people to go to Red Hat Summit so I bet you have to submit a talk or you
have to be actually associated with one of the products does anything get done around
Red Hat the weeks before the summit yeah a lot I mean there's a lot of people doing an
awful lot of work to crunch together I mean there's an awful lot of open shift announcements
coming up at the summit this year so there's a lot of work been happening for months if
not years to prepare for this because it's a big release coming up so oh yeah oh well
I'm glad we're going oh yeah yeah one of the reasons I'm sad I'm not is because by open
shifts the products I work most closely with and it's going to be a big big announcement
hmm hmm now one last little bit of housekeeping before we skadoots have you ever heard me
ever say skadoots I just heard you about four times skadoots maybe if it was the name of
a project that you were trying to pronounce yeah yeah and it would be a total mispronunciation
all right so I just wanted to mention that Linux Academy was getting a bunch of great
feedback on the promo of the $2.99 yearly promo normally the price is $4.49 it's $2.99
right now they've extended it for just another five days that's a great deal that's like
a 33% that's actually exactly a 33% discount so Linux Academy calm go take advantage of
that because that's crazy that's crazy that's a mighty fine is a mighty fine deal as someone
who had has paid the full price before being associated at all yeah that seems nice there
you go there right there that was the the keeping of the house we're all done very nice
we got through that nice and quick got that got that through really good well as I said
we're all back from Linux Fest Northwest and cheese just got in last night yeah yeah last
night around 1030 1045 so that's late but dogs went crazy ballistic well cheese what
did you think as your first Linux Fest Northwest was it worth or not that's not the way I want
to put it was it everything we've been talking about for years on the air absolutely yeah
did not disappoint did not disappoint boy because we've been hyping it a lot yeah I
mean it you know I was kind of going into it expecting you know a conference of fest
you know just a kind of a small one but I did not realize how much it just it actually
felt more like a giant family reunion than than anything else even with like that one
crazy aunt like it was still this this giant family reunion yeah who's the crazy aunt that's
why I want to know hmm who was the I don't know Noah I have to think he was he did get
kind of crazy yeah we'll get there we'll get there don't worry oh it's there I got a story
I agree with you cheese by the way family reunion and a lot of these people had never
met Chris once before but I never met wears or like half the crew I'd never met before
and yet because their voices have been such a part of my life for so many years it felt
like a family reunion yeah really nice way to put it this year more so I think than ever
it really did it was like I think it was really interesting too because you could tell especially
at the studio when we had just a you know group of us hanging around just all of the
voices it was super surreal because all the voices that you hear on the podcast everyone's
in a conversation talking here there it was it was definitely interesting with you know
bodies and heads when I met Joe he he looked at me kind of strange when I said oh hey I'm
Brent nice to meet you Joe and he said oh you're not what I expected and I had to ask
him well is that a good thing or a bad thing because you're not what I expected either
I thought that about Joe Joe looked nothing like I expected right yeah he looked nothing
like his picture yeah you have that moment and then and then it passes and then it just
kind of becomes normal because you fuse the voice with the person which is good surprisingly
quickly in almost all cases you know and it is a little different some people are look
very different but geez we had also not met and I feel like meeting you it was it was
just great I mean I had seen your picture but it really was like brothers or something
like hey oh cool yeah you got some beers awesome yeah where else that happens with people you
know maybe people you've known from podcasts but even just other people at Linux fest right
you just strike up conversations you don't have to make awkward small talk you have all
the things you have the same vocabulary you know and like the same things so it's not
just the it's not just us on air it's that's it's like that for everybody it really is
and this year was was our biggest Linux fest in in several ways the one thing that we really
did big time this year there was a massive success that we've never done before and I
think now we have to do it every single year is there was a Jupiter track a room that was
just loaded full of Linux Academy and community members that had talks and Wes had the privilege
of giving the very first talk very early in the Jupiter room as everyone doing today happy
Linux fest Northwest I don't know about you guys but 930 is just about the earliest possible
time I think conference talk should be scheduled yes you had a packed room that was everybody
had a packed room I was it was very humbling the number of people that came to our room
it was just incredible I'm not joking I had two different people tell me they were emotionally
moved by else talk this on the second day I wanted to go see you know like my co-host
Jim I wanted to go see his talk I couldn't know it's full by the time I got there you
couldn't even go into Alan's talk because they just closed the room they put a sign
up that said no more people it's crazy some of us just walked past the sign I sat down
anyway right the live stream wasn't full so I got in there you know that's always open
yeah we did have we did try to get the audio on the live stream we'll try to get the audio
posted up on our site and the slides up on github or something pretty soon once we get
everybody and once everybody's done traveling I know I was really nervous about her talk
and I thought she did a great job I thought you know I thought the feedback are you still
there what do you think how did it go because I thought the feedback for your talk was particularly
good out of all the talks um well I've always loved doing the container talk because that
one's always really fun people get really excited and I love it when people actually
turn in the homework I give them but the mentoring talk was the hardest one this time because
it is telling my story and I was really happy to see how many people came to a community
based talk at a technical conference that was just really heartwarming to me yeah it's
something people are taking seriously that is good to see and I think I think links fest
Northwest in particular has a lot of that vibe I've noticed over the years a number
of talks that that will focus around that you know it is because it is a community driven
event people are thinking about it already I really liked your talk on Linux audio you
got into like even the science of how sound moves around a room and the different microphones
were yeah it was great it was really nerdy and Alex your talk was packed on home automation
people were even sitting on the floor in front of the projectors and stuff it was a bit daunting
yeah somebody told me 83 people or 88 people or something wow yeah we just gotta get a
bigger room in a room for 30 years the class of normal classroom size yeah I think it was
87 in Alex's talk yeah 87 is what I counted that's a lot of people yeah I like how like
toward the end they just had to start putting you know like on Alan's talk no more because
because we were cramming as many people as possible in there and we also got rid of a
ton of the vintage swag in there too yeah we had the old we were given a lot of that
people love that stuff you know I've been most amazed by since the talk is the interactions
on Twitter since people have been actively seeking me out and you know people I've never
met or talked to you are just like hey you know like your talk how do I find out more
information so there is a blog post I wrote about it which I'll get when you throw in
a show notes yeah yeah for the home automation stuff which is so cool yeah the other talks
were there were some other popular ones too I think one that I'll have a link for in the
show notes because it was a great one was mad dogs 50 years it was unbelievable it could
have been 50 but it was a long history of X and you know in fact I have a clip right
here of just the intro where I think he says it you know play a little bit of it welcome
this is talk is the 50 years of X a computer Odyssey and it's not just a rumination of
history about Unix and things like that but I want to explain some things maybe to some
of the younger people and maybe to some of the older ones who keep this information in
the back of their head and I'm gonna bring it back out to the frontal lobes I just didn't
think 50 was possible but it is that whole talks great for the entire talk is linked
in the show notes also in the show notes if you want although I don't know why you would
our entire eight hour stream from Linux vest which kicked off with a bang we are here at
Linux best they just opened the doors about eight minutes ago of course there was a lot
of people waiting to get their badges which this year are plantable did you guys try that
did anybody try planting their badge well not yet no it's recycled paper with seeds
in it I saw Alan's there earlier I'm gonna take it home they these badges look like crumpled
toilet paper yes they were the strangest badges I've ever seen well the first day on the second
day they were looking extra a lot fell apart did they start disintegrating yeah yeah degradable
in a day where the neck like what do you call that the hole the hole punch for yeah yeah
the hole punch where you would clip it in was would just rip out yeah yeah I noticed
on the second day they started taping that before they would give it to the person yeah
like tape over with it to reinforce it a bit yeah then you gotta rip the tape off before
you plant it nice bit of plastic on your biodegradable badge and so I sat down on the stream for
a while with Angela and yourself Chris but then Dylan popped up for a while and that
kid knows his Mario music yeah he does my goodness yeah that was fun I that's about
halfway through the stream chase starts quizzing Dylan on different Mario tunes to see if he
can to nail him that is his specialist subject if ever he goes on a quiz he is all about
that in Minecraft the most fun I mean I'm really trying to trying to think of what it
could be because there was there was great road adventures we went on we went on a hike
to a lake there was sightseeing there was so many good meals but it would be sort of
negligent on my part not to spend a little bit of time talking about our parking lot
barbecue right I got of all the stories I could share yeah this is I think with our
limited time the one I have to share wow well lesson learned we're gonna need more barbecues
we're gonna need a lot more grills sounds like pretty soon you'll need a bigger parking
lot too it was it was unbelievable cheese and the Bruce aka Brandon saved the day it
was a massive scale operation way beyond anything we planned over 300 people showed up to get
fed all of two grills to one I come out yeah no yeah the the the little grill I mean that's
just laughable yeah like so we walk up from that line yeah the Texans Chris would give
me lots of feedback on the size of your grill yeah oh you need a trailer to fit a whole
hog in next time it hasn't been an issue in the years past but this this year it went
big and the beauty thing that happened is cheese and Brandon like fell into this system
the only only way to do this when you're trying to feed 300 people is to have a system I had
no system if I hadn't gotten injured during the cooking process I smacked myself in the
nose with a spatula then we would have been listen to their system here listen this is
great
brought to the front of the line that's cheese right there as it should one more time because
it's it's I got to play that last part because it's so great oh yeah it was good times man
and you know whenever it came down to it and I think if he's in the mobile you should jump
in here too but you know I asked him I was like hey what do you want to do do you want
to cook it or do you want you know you want me to prep it and he's like I'll cook so all
right man I just started busting out of the hamburger patties I was throwing them on the
grill he's flipping them we're cooking as quick as we can yeah we ran out of charcoal
twice like we had to keep going for charcoal runs and then eventually we went for supplementary
pizza runs to like to read to alleviate the lines and then it was good time though as
the party sort of settled you know the people that have been drinking kind of held stayed
back so they could sober up or kept drinking some of us retired into the RV and played
ukulele a little bit and others decided to cross dress like like oh man like Noah Chalaya
and I happened to catch the moment when Noah decided to put on Emma's bathing suit from
system 76 here's what's happening right now is Noah's putting on Emma's bathing suit which
got a little crazy it just got a little and then Noah was running around in a bathing
suit for a little bit it's good times I just feel bad for Emma I mean is she gonna I assume
she'll just throw that one away and get yeah so that's it would never be the same again
will it well if you if you listen to the very the very first of that clip in the background
you can hear Noah say oh I think I just ripped the leg hole yeah yeah yeah yeah that happened
oh we had Jeff up from California the guy that helped do the wiring for your RV and
he was flying some drones around that was fun one of the best moments of the barbecue
actually because Jess what are those called what are those what are those drones called
the Jeff had FPV drones very fast yeah and he had the goggles so you could put on like
VR goggles plus he had an auxiliary display screen so other people could watch and we
were playing around for quite a while and Levi starts to get hip to the fact that there's
a thing flying around that's like an insect and maybe that should get out of my backyard
he starts to think to himself so he spends a couple of hours chasing the drone until
one beautiful moment when Levi manages to catch the drone in his little dog mouth and
he catches it such that the camera faces outwards so you then get a point of view from Levi
as he does a celebratory run around the parking lot just totally pleased with himself for
cap finally capturing this as he should be present dog view and then you look over the
people with the VR headsets on just laughing because they're they're seeing the world from
Levi's point of view and boy does that dog move yeah just booked around it's a big party
he's a cutie that was he loves that he loves that barbecue he loves it because he gets
to get all kinds of scratches and scraps it's perfect for him there's a lot of fun and thank
you to everybody who made it out it was great to see you didn't get a chance to chat a lot
with everybody but tried to shake as many hands as possible I mean it was an amazing
diversity of people I think we got you know lots of regular and lots of people who might
just be now learning about the network Linux Academy and everyone involved yeah I just
saw a great amount of mixing you know like you would you'd have groups that would form
but then new people would come in others would leave yeah there was a lot of that yeah and
people weren't too creepy about lady jupes though this year that was nice it was good
yeah the awkward part is you do have your home here right next door good toilet that's
a kid it didn't work out it worked out other than the fact that the toilet got overflowed
boy that's another story and I just have to drive people's poops down the highway yeah
yeah I am still carrying their poops around it lady jupes that that is also true but I
think thank you to system 76 to me yeah oh jeez wow so so awesome the barbecue would
uh just straight up would not have been possible without them and man when Emma saw the crowds
that we were getting they went out and did another meat run and uh she also set aside
a couple of sirloins for those of us in the crew that were hanging out late so after things
kind of died down a little bit when the coals were still going just a little quick salt
and pepper on the old sirloin threw them on the grill and we had ourselves a little more
a little more meat I ate a bit of cheeses meat and it was delicious yeah yeah he's got
some good meat he really does was there some bacon on there no no it was just steak and
that's all that steak that steak sans bacon was good enough yeah yeah yeah they did they
also grabbed a bunch of chairs and just a ton of stuff so system 76 was just above and
beyond went above and beyond with the barbecue and uh Emma just left the studio a couple
hours ago she went out to breakfast there with Brent and uh they went out and tried
to try to restaurant that I used to go to as a child the Bluebird Cafe Bluebird Cafe
Emma um impressed me because she ordered two very large blueberry pancakes and then proceeded
to order um a cup of ice cream and uh ate all of the pancakes with the ice cream I had
never seen that before she earned it she had a hell of a day I think poppy and wimpy would
have really enjoyed that experience it was so good seeing them so good so good seeing
we have so many stories I want to share on the Friday stream I just I think we some of
like the non-linux related stories we'll put there but I'll wrap up this Linux Vesta review
by saying hell of a year great great talks great crowd great exhibit hall people were
into the raffle this year and we just blew the doors off the barbecue and the Jupiter
track was so much more successful than I would have thought like I thought we'd have attendance
I just didn't think we would have that much attendance it was especially because I mean
there were a lot of other really interesting talks at the conference like it's not like
we had the all the good stuff yeah yeah although we had some pretty great we had some great
stuff oh absolutely the one the only I will I will try to work with as many people as
possible to get um to get those up online we'll have a link to Alex's talk we'll try
to get some of the audio posted I recorded nearly all of them in audio we weren't doing
video but I think we might try to get like a video of the of the slides next year but
we will at least have the source slides up on github eventually in a week or so it was
really lovely actually so my mom and dad were listening in England to the audio stream
and they text me both text me both afterwards saying that was that was fun so thank you
for making that that's great yeah also we heard from people that had to leave the fest
early but got to keep streaming as they're on their way to the airport that's also really
cool definitely I had to chase for making that just make that making oh yeah that was
awesome yeah great great point yeah geekgamer.tv to check out what he's doing and you walked
away with a bit of a plasma success story too that's I mean if that's not something
I mean yeah worth it right worth flying so many people out here oh for that yeah I was
I was attending a really interesting talk about um it was like a live coding demo and
someone was you know my little hobby language of Clojure there's a javascript version they
were making a minesweeper game just like live right there in the browser didn't need any
supplies their laptop wasn't working working so well so some of the some of the other staff
and volunteers had have been trying to get things set up on another laptop I guess that
room had been having projector problems and we should say like there's a lot of rooms
it is a complicated setup especially with the live streaming and the mixing and the
recording so there was another um another district there with the with the green logo
I won't mention by name and you know it just couldn't it just couldn't cut it on the couldn't
cut it on the projector really like it wasn't detecting it yeah what was the desktop environment
was it it was linux mint that's what it was it was actually I'm actually was I thought
it was susa did you think susa when he said green there aren't many with green logo absolutely
I thought yeah I had mint did you okay nothing against it yeah yeah yeah so it's cinnamon
then it was like it wasn't finding it and then eventually it did but have you seen that
where like the it's just shifted so you have like multiple desktops that you can see where
the desktops end to begin wasn't going to cut it for the presentation but I had just
given a presentation that morning so you know it's going to be it's going to work right
I got a laptop I don't need it I was here for the talk anyway so I just go and volunteer
stick my laptop up there plug it in windows key p choose you know mirror the things no
problem worked perfectly and no credit to me it was I was just really glad that plasma
is so dependable it works so well in that sort of setting it does so good with projectors
it really does and that meant I actually got to enjoy the talk oh that's great that is
a nice win I also will say I mean so there's a there's a plasma success story I have a
bit of an XFC success story and it's out Joe I know right yeah don't let don't don't let
anybody else hear this I didn't bring my power cord because I'm lazy I mean I had it because
it's USB-C so lazy about power cords I hate power cords ran my laptop my t480 both days
recording all of the talks except for like the last couple of talks of the Sunday all
from battery the entire time wow I just left it in the room overnight sleeping came in
the next day fired about I mean just all from the XFCE sips my my experience is limited
still but when plasmas on I've got a t480s ThinkPad and you know you can feel that thing
when it's running plasma you can feel it under your fingers is a few degrees warmer than
your hands yes yes XFC is actually cooler and the fan turns off completely yeah it's
for it's a big difference yeah not pushing the GPU as much as I imagine all right well
so I think we have enough time I think we're gonna try to slip in we have a brand new segment
for the show very very excited about this ladies and gentlemen Jason Evangelo and L
Marquez both have commitment issues when it comes to picking a distribution so instead
of suffering they have decided to make a new segment called the distro hoppers and they
kick it off with a new random distribution they've picked and that am I building the
tension yet just get on with it man and that distribution is Linux Lite you know I was
actually really afraid I was gonna I was afraid that we were gonna end up with something really
weird like you know a NAS specific you know Linux distribution so when I click the button
and Linux Lite OS popped up it was it was actually kind of relieving because I was like
okay I can do this I can look at this OS and actually give honest feedback to what it would
be to somebody who's new to Linux I want to start with the minimum recommended specs for
this distro because it's it's billed as really lightweight and all you need for it is a one
gigahertz processor and 768 megabytes of RAM and I think even the recommended requirements
are something like a 1.5 gigahertz processor and two gigs of RAM that's recommended so
that's like when it will really scream Linux Academy recently sent me some USBs to give
away and these things are like two gigs in size they're tiny there's nothing you can
actually do with them so I have a bunch of them sitting around and I put Linux Lite on
it and I put it into the computer and I could actually run off of it like you could have
a functional OS on a 2 gig USB that you can now use that was amazing to me because I can't
even burn most ISOs on something under eight gigs at this point did it run well with the
live USB honestly yeah I did my daughter has this little bitty laptop that we bought on
sell on back Friday that I just regret because that thing runs like mud with you know real
specs to it it's the Lenovo something pad like the oldest version possible Linux Lite
was running off of this USB faster and more user friendly than that laptop has ever run
so did you get around to doing an actual native install on to the hard drive okay so this
one I kind of started getting out of my comfort zone because on that laptop I was running
fedora and because I give it to my kids I like having it as secure as possible so I
ended up leaving you at EUFI actually enabled on it and no problem with fedora but I couldn't
even get it to read the USB or boot up to Linux Lite OS without going back to legacy
boot so I don't know if that is a concern for some people I you know it really goes
back to how much work are you doing that requires security but I ended up going ahead and going
to the legacy going through the boot process you had told me that this was very similar
to the Ubuntu process I haven't gone through that so I can't speak to that but it was really
native it was very simple the English in which it asked how I'd like my install to happen
was very user friendly like somebody off the street who generally doesn't even really mess
with installs or even computers could understand what it was asking you know are you sure that
you actually want to erase everything on this drive and then you click yes and it says specifically
these are the areas that are going to be deleted if you accept this yes and it's like what
keyboard would you like and even gives you a little bar at the bottom so you can test
to make sure that your keyboard is functioning with the option that's chosen so you don't
go through the entire process and then find out later that you made a mistake the fact
that it prompts you to ask you about third-party drivers and Wi-Fi before you even get into
the mix I think eliminates a lot of the issues that people who are brand-new run into when
they kick an OS yeah so it uses the Ubiquiti installer which is the same installer that
Ubuntu uses and it's just as simple it may have some slight language tweaks like you
pointed out but yeah it's basically click next click next click next let's talk about
the first boot let's talk about your first experience did you spend any time in the Linux
Lite OS welcome screen I did and that's because this is kind of interesting so when I was
going through the boot process there was a little option that said you know do you want
to go ahead and install updates so I said yes I do you know why not do it all at one
point then it goes in and the little welcome screen shows up and it's like first thing
it says is to install updates and I'm thinking well I already did that but let's you know
hey I'm test driving this and I click the button and I was really surprised that there
were packages there that needed to be updated so I'm not sure what the disconnect is there
did you happen to see that I didn't actually notice that because I did the same exact thing
but I skipped down because there's like four steps and I basically ignored that because
I had updated already and I went through the remaining steps but then so I was going through
the welcome screen and just kind of looking at all the different options and I do like
how you're picking as you're picking them it actually has information to what it is
that you're doing it doesn't just assume that if you're running updates or that if you're
choosing another one of the options that you are already going to know what that's going
to do does that make sense yeah it does it's very I found the language on this OS to be
very explicit it's very clear and it it assumes that you are new to Linux and I really love
that and this welcome screen probably my favorite welcome screen since Ubuntu Budgie's welcome
app because what this does it just guides you through every step it's you know install
updates install drivers set a restore point that's another cool thing is that it actually
suggests to you hey set a restore point so that you can have a backup down the road it's
like it knows you're going to screw it up at some point and then there's links to you
know all their support pages and forums and social media and they even have this hardware
compatibility database that's just for Linux lite OS there's thousands and thousands of
reports on there from people who have volunteered their their hardware information kind of similar
to what you get with the steam hardware survey so in your case like if you were you know
booting up that live USB you could click that hardware compatibility database and see if
your components or your system is perfectly supported by Linux lite I don't know if you
had a chance to open up the terminal when you did this but I find it interesting that
as soon as you open up the terminal there's actually a link to that same support guide
right there and I saw that throughout like you down the menu and they give you the support
docs so they're making the option of support like first and foremost through your entire
experience in the OS well if my support docs were this good I would want to link them everywhere
too the documentation for Linux lite is so good it's all super detailed and it's really
easy to follow there are visuals actual screenshots of everything you could possibly imagine you
know one of my qualms with so many Linux distros is that there's this lack of education about
all these different drivers that are out there for AMD and Nvidia and this breaks it down
in really simple language and it even has this section where it's like okay if you
want to if you don't know what graphics card you have do you have AMD do you have Nvidia
open up a terminal and type this and then there's tutorials on customizing it how to
use a VM how to use time shift to create and restore backups there's troubleshooting tips
and it's so well done and I flipped over to Zubuntu in a VM because I wanted to see okay
what's kind of the big XFCE based distro that would compete with this so I fired up
Zubuntu and I went into their documentation and it's just it's laid out very cleanly
but it's all text I don't think we can make light or even just kind of glaze over the
fact that how documented there are screenshots are I would argue that you could actually
take the text out of most of those support guides and still be able to know exactly what
you're supposed to be doing by going through those screenshots okay did you did you happen
to dig into the menus and notice something called light tweaks I did and that's because
so I actually went looking for it simply because whenever I opened up settings and configuration
files I don't know if you noticed but there's no minimize bar so I just assumed that I had
to go in and install it the way that I had with elementary OS so I was looking for that
setting and then suddenly realized that my computer and other options do have the minimize
bar it's kind of hit and miss on which ones do but that's how I ended up finding that
option so I really like this it's not the most attractive app but it's super useful
it's got I don't know 12 15 different tweaks that you can run you can fix your boot process
you can locate large files you can clean the Firefox cache it'll show you how much space
you'll clean out if you you know execute this tweak or this tweak what's really neat about
it is it shows you before you execute the tweak would you like to clean out 63 megabytes
of Firefox cache would you like to clear seven recent entries from your favorites menu and
so it's updating that in real time and I think that's really cool because when you're on
Windows you have to you know go into the you know right click the disk and hit properties
and then hit some other thing and and then run it and analyze it until finally it tells
you this is how much space you'll clear the light tweaks menu is the first time that I
saw something on this OS that I'm going okay this is targeted to more than just new people
because I don't know if you notice it actually has some higher level kind of Linux user experience
like installing new kernels removing new kernels things that I would say that I would always
do on the command line because I can't imagine a GUI running for me and then it grades like
how severe is this action is it something safe and I really can't hurt my system or
you know proceed with caution it's possible you're gonna break everything because I can
imagine somebody coming in here just be like oh what's a kernel I don't need it and removing
their kernel yeah so I mean you get the sense that they really thought about both beginners
but also power users I think this would be the first time that I've really thought that
of a Linux distribution that they're just like you know we're gonna include things that'll
be easy and make life easier for all of our users not just a specific category yeah it's
really it's it's a little confusing because when I see the words Linux Lite the image
that forms in my head is this lightweight stripped-down distro not a lot of apps installed
just you know bare minimums right Linux Lite bare minimums that's that's what I get in
my head but there's a lot of software even you know all the stuff that you mentioned
plus there's a lot of software that's pre-installed there's a GIMP and VLC and LibreOffice and
a bunch of other utilities and accessories that as you mentioned power users could really
take advantage of I was told you earlier that I was running pop OS and as much as I've loved
it one of the things that I had to do when I went in was go in and configure Firefox
so that I could actually watch certain videos on sites that I go to for training then in
this one that was one of the first things I did I'm like okay how much configuration
do I have to have on this to make it work out of the box and I clicked Firefox I went
to the site and the video is just loaded everything was already installed which is just confusing
to me on something that says it's a light install yeah it really makes me wonder you
know I don't know anything about Linux Lite's popularity or usage numbers or anything like
that but it may have it may actually suffer the same problem that I think XFCE suffers
is it it doesn't have that first impression that it needs you know with XFCE you get these
gray screenshots and it looks like it's from like the early 2000s and then you have a you
know Linux Lite based on Ubuntu 1804 and so immediately you think well is it is it just
a stripped down Ubuntu why would I want to use this I was imagining something like puppy
OS that's really what I was imagining when we first decided that we're gonna do this
challenge and I'm like okay Linux yeah all right I I'm going to have a hard time being
able to really get this up and running so that I can work off of it so that's kind of
why I went so many different ways trying to figure out how to install it and how to really
provide feedback on it and I was blown out of the water I was really wrong with my first
impressions on it and I have to point out something here regarding the appearance when
you go into the customization options there are like 30 different desktop styles to choose
from built-in I was having fun with that just going down and be like there's XFCE winter
and XFCE purple I'm like all right let's just try all of these yeah that was a lot of fun
and I love that I love that they include that many options without having to you know get
on the internet and download themes and make those tweaks on your own well I think we better
get out of here but we have one more thing to do what is next all right let me get the
screen up don't don't don't I'm gonna cross my fingers the winner is oh you have to stay
tuned to find out what distro they're going to pick next so the whole idea is they run
a rando spinner it picks a distro and then they give it a go oh so try probably trying
some things I would not have tried yeah things you and I were never gonna try on the show
now we get a chance to give them a go now I really hope they get Gentoo right out of
the gate is it is it actually called the rando spinner because if not it should be well we
should yeah I don't know actually don't know if I've gotten the name of it from them but
I like the idea so I think we'll be hearing from them in the future and if you have any
suggestions or feedback go to Linux unplug calm slash contact and let us know in there
let us know what you think I enjoyed it I think I was right I was right along with L
I thought it'd totally be like a puppy small like damn small Linux that's what I was expecting
that's what I was expecting anyways we have reached the end of our program and before
we get out of here I wanted to point you to an article that mr. bacon has worked on over
on the Linux unplugged website we'll have a link for this in the show notes as well
but you can also just go to Linux unplug calm slash articles and it is some behind the scenes
photos of our Linux fest events including the Friday stream in the studio which we had
a great crowd in the studio you can see some pictures of mr. chase who's just looking incredible
these days he's lost 140 pounds I literally did not recognize the man until he opened
his mouth yeah and I heard the voice was like oh that's chase you kidding me amazing look
at that group there's some pictures of Alex in there chase work in the booth and of course
some of the rooms a letter talk Alex at his talk and some behind the scenes photos from
the barbecue as well all up on the website Linux unplug calm slash articles or there'll
be a link in the notes wherever you consume those show notes we usually say the website
URL but then I realized most people listening they're checking on their phone app that's
really where they're looking at the notes is in the phone app because now we have it
in the feed because that's how we do now that's right well gentlemen thank you very much for
making it into studio it was great to have you so good to be here mumble room thank you
guys for making it and mr. bacon is there any parting words we need to give people before
we get out here like a baby a plug for the Friday stream or something yeah Friday Friday
is coming up it's coming up gonna be doing that and we're gonna be going through some
of our travel ventures yes home yes I encourage anyone that was there to show up and maybe
share some of your yeah adventures there or around for the Friday stream yeah people can
jump in mumble share their stories they'll be good they'll be great they'll be great
yeah the Friday stream is a great chance to meet the crew cover a few stories wrap up
a few things here and there guess what we do it on Fridays jblive.tv Jupiter broadcasting
calm slash calendar for that and this show when they're live and Linux unplug calm for
links subscriptions all of that and I hope to see you right back here next Tuesday
get it out of here
for people who like to mess with computers I do like to mess with computers thank you
episode 300 next oh boy whoo I haven't expected yeah I remember 300 or less and that was a
big deal yeah yeah yeah it's it's like you know it's not the first time he's got the
300 so it's like it's getting less of a big deal it's like the third or fourth time I've
gotten to 300 you blink and just sort of burp out 300 like come at me when I get to a thousand
you know burping out podcast there's another one so I next year we're gonna have to uh
race uh our little tiny hawks right oh yes oh yeah definitely Jeff Jeff yes is that what
they're called tiny hawks yeah the model is that specific model is yeah I have to buy
some I mean these just seem aggressive so I warn you now a drug habit will be cheaper
than fpv yeah so the drones themselves are 150 or so okay um then you need the batteries
which can be 10 to 20 bucks a pop and they have a flight time of two to three minutes
so you need five or ten of them geez to have any kind of you know Jeff had three for example
and he had lots of downtime in between yeah which can be annoying um and then you need
the radio which is 200 and then you need the goggles which can be two to five hundred dollars
so you know proper hobby then you need to you need to set aside at least a thousand
to get into it and then you're going to want another quad for when the first one breaks
sure of course or some dog gets it well the uh the emax tiny hawk has a little bundle
it's uh right around 200 bucks comes with everything but it's not uh not a hobby grade
radio not hobby grade goggles but it'll get you started okay I think I probably uh I won't
I won't say I spent more money than I told my wife I spent yeah yeah every every time
but uh yeah so there's the little tiny ones like Jeff had but then there's also the five
inch racing drones which you can build yourself um out of components from China and and that's
for me I learned a lot of my electronic skills through doing that um when you plug a 12 volt
thing into a five volt thing and it goes bang and lets out the magic smoke it stops working
yeah okay that is a good that is a good way to learn if maybe just a little bit expensive
but a point which you made very well in your talk was that's why in your travels you have
found components that you can assemble that you are willing to have blow up on you so
that way instead of losing a 60 dollar part you're losing a six dollar part correct yes
so the most expensive component on an FPV drone is probably at most 30 each you know
each each motor is about 20 the flight control is probably the most expensive at around 30
or 40 dollars at most so if any if any single component goes bang then it's not that annoying
if you fly your drone off into a lake then you've lost three four hundred dollars and
that that is annoying it's like what Alex always says I mean this is he's famous for
saying this uh if you can think it you can do it yeah you just have to know how