Big CES week.
And Michael over at Ferronix said not as big of a deal
for Linux as it was last year,
and he may or may not be right,
but I was sure spotting a lot of Linux
in NVIDIA's live demo.
So NVIDIA today announced the PX2,
which is the second generation of what they call
their computer, their mini supercomputer for a car.
That's what they call it.
And it's a big, massive NVIDIA box that is liquid cooled
for this new version, the PX2.
It's a big box with an ODB2 connector,
and it's meant to go in your computer
and power these self-driving cars.
We talked a little bit about it,
Poppy and I did today, actually, in Tech Talk today.
Like one of the nice things is it can process
2800 images a second.
Wowee.
Yeah, it's got eight teraflops of processing,
12 CPU cores, and it is a pretty neat beast.
And we talked more details in Tech Talk,
but check out the demo here, how cool this is,
and then I wanna show you where the Linux is involved.
Like you were saying, there's millions of points
per second coming in.
We can't just throw all of this at the driver
as they're going down the road.
They won't understand what's happening.
So we need to distill and refine the localization
of where the vehicle is into both the lane.
The Here HD maps help us draw these lanes perfectly.
Every vehicle that's coming past that's noticed
by the LIDAR or by the cameras,
refined and placed properly in their lanes.
So all of these cars that I see around us right now,
they're real cars.
I mean, they're not some kind of imaginary cars.
They're real cars that we've detected.
And we know where they are in 3D space.
We know how fast they're traveling.
We know how fast we're traveling relative to it.
And we know what lanes they're all in now
because we've identified everybody,
we've localized everybody.
And we know the path that we're gonna be taking,
optional paths that we might be taking.
All of this information we can present
in a very refined fashion so that somebody can relax,
have a serene ride down the road.
But how do we know that this isn't just a mock-up,
some kind of a demo?
You know, I think one of the best things that we can see
is actually what it looks like going down the road
with real information.
So if we look at it with the video.
Unfortunately, we don't have a windshield in front of you,
but let's put a virtual windshield up here.
Yeah, so this is the actual information driving down 101
with the vehicles passing.
All of this is being computed in real time.
This is not a video down below.
This is-
Look at that, it's just changed lanes.
The car in front of me has just changed lanes.
Two cars just come up next to us.
We don't need rear view mirrors anymore.
All right, so that's a little bold there.
Just get rid of them.
Yeah, just a little more.
There's no reason to ever have to look around you.
Yeah, you can just loop there
is all it's doing right there.
And because our sensors are so robust
and because we have so many redundant sensors,
it is possible for us to detect
all of these different cars.
And we talked more about the image processing
and recognition in Tech Talk,
but if you look at the presentation,
during the presentations,
one of the things you would have noticed
showing up on screen over and over again,
Popey, do you know what it is?
Did you catch it?
Oh, I know this.
What is it, what is it, what is it?
No, no, I don't.
Oh, you don't?
Oh, well, it's fedora.
No, actually it's a lots of Ubuntu.
There are demos like last year,
we run on Ubuntu, the machines are running Ubuntu.
It's Ubuntu all over the place.
All right, they're up on stage
during the video presentation at CES.
You knew that because they did it last year
and the year before,
but I still think it's pretty damn cool.
It is cool.
This self-driving supercomputer car thingy.
You know it's cool because of that leather jacket.
That leather jacket, it was one of the best investments
that CEO has ever made.
That dude wears it up on stage every single event.
And you know what, I like him.
He seems to kind of actually,
he seems like a CEO that actually knows his stuff.
So you gotta respect that.
Actually, now you come to say it,
I can't think of any car automation demos
that I've seen in the last year or two
that don't have Ubuntu on them somehow.
At some point in the development, right?
Yeah, like either the computers
that are connecting to the in-car system
or the computers that are developing the sensors, yeah.
In fact, I think, you know what?
It's almost, it would be more shocking
if they were doing it on Windows.
Yeah.
That's what we'd be talking about.
Wow, now that is your story right there, everybody.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 126 for January 5th, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's for people who like to mess with computers.
My name is Chris.
And my name is Wes.
Hey there, Wes, happy new year.
Happy new year to you, Chris.
Oh, thank you.
You know, after today's episode,
I'm going to go ride a horse.
Really?
Yeah, happy birthday.
It's my daughter, Abby.
She turned five today.
Happy birthday, Abby.
Yeah, so after this, we're going to go ride horses.
That sounds great.
Hopefully, it's not raining.
Great, it sounds great.
No, it's indoors.
Oh, OK.
I thought, come on.
I thought you were not much of an equestrian there, Chris.
No.
Well, I used to be back in the day, long story.
Make sure someone films this, and I think
it would make great Patreon content.
All right, well, coming up on today's episode,
hopefully, we've got some great content for you.
We're going to get an update on the new Linux
update from the Mycroft project, straight from Ryan's mouth,
a.k.a. the horse's mouth.
Also, later on in the show, every single year,
this chap out there puts out the big list of all of the things
that are super wrong in Linux.
Major Linux problems on the desktop.
The 2016 edition is out, and the list is extensive,
to say the least.
We're going to go through the list.
Wes and I read the whole dang thing.
We picked out the important bits that we need to respond to,
and we're going to do it right here in the show
with the whole virtual lug.
There are some pain points the guys got us on.
Oh, yeah, for sure.
And they're helpful observations.
Yeah, and if you're thinking about switching to Linux,
there are probably things you should know about going in.
So we're going to talk about that.
But there's also a few points.
Kind of misses the mark on.
And then, towards the end of the show, I'm going to do it.
I'm going to own up to what I thought
was going to happen in 2015.
We made our predictions of Linux action show up, so 345.
I hope you look this scared during it.
I know.
And I went through and pulled out
some of the predictions I made, and now I'm
going to play them back and see how I did for 2015.
Yeah.
I just get to watch.
Yeah, it's going to be a little painful for me.
But you know what?
It's on record, so I got to do it.
It's not like I can hide it.
So I'll go through it.
We'll do it.
But, you know, Wes, before we get into all of that stuff,
you and I, just a moment before the lug comes in here,
let's take a moment and talk about this rather outstanding
beer you brought in today.
Oh, do you like it?
I do.
This is like, we're going to call this the beer is tasty
segment, because you brought in a beer last week and this week.
And I think it's worth talking about.
You brought in the Sierra Nevada Celebration.
And it's a fresh, fresh IPA.
And I was looking on Beer Advocate.
It's got a BA score of 93, which is pretty amazing.
6.8% by volume.
Yeah, yeah.
And you know, that 6.8 is kind of high for a beer.
It's kind of high.
I like a little, you know, the higher.
It's definitely hoppy.
It's pretty good.
So what do you think?
I like it.
But you know, it is hoppy, but it
doesn't have too much of the bitter hop finish.
Right.
It has a nice, you know, it's there.
It's tasty, but it's not.
Yeah, there is a bit of a finish that's like.
It's not too cloying.
Yeah, it stays on the tongue, but not too bad.
Yeah, so there you go.
If you're listening to this episode and you have a Sierra,
you should crack one open.
It's a crucial element that makes this show work.
And also makes me a little belchy sometimes.
But I'll try to avoid that.
I got a mute switch right here.
Maybe I can take advantage of that.
Hey, let's get into our updates of the week.
And to do that, let's bring in our virtual log,
time appropriate greetings, Mamba Room.
Hello, world.
Hello.
Hey, everybody.
So it's here, the final episode of The World Without Linux
put out by the Linux Foundation.
It's finally arrived.
And I haven't seen it yet.
I've been saving it.
Oh, I haven't seen it either.
We've watched like three or four of these on the show.
And this is a series to market Linux at the Linux Foundation,
the people behind a lot of great initiatives
and the funders of Linus Torvalds' paycheck and Greg
and others that are super important to Linux kernel.
They have been putting these videos out
to help the average person understand what the world would
be like if Linux didn't exist.
So let's watch it and then do a little Mystery Science Theater
on it.
Hello, and welcome home to Freeburger,
where the message of the day is free, blah, blah, blah, blah.
Oh, hey, Annie.
Sam, what's up?
I didn't know you worked here.
Yeah, I started here in 91 just as a hobby.
Nothing professional, but here I still am.
I do it just for fun.
Anyways, what can I get you?
Wow, this menu is huge.
What's good here?
Well, I like the Sloppy Joe Distro, the Pseudo Menudo,
the Wild Cherry Binary, mm, bomb, the Raspberry Pie,
the Soussai Souffle.
Oh, the Helsinki Drinky, you should get that on the side.
And of course, there is the world famous Freeburger
and Kernel Fries.
What are Kernel Fries?
They're just like regular fries, only monolithic.
So where are your ingredients sourced from?
Actually, thousands of chefs from around the world
contribute ingredients and recipes,
so the menu is constantly evolving and getting better.
Oh, you should try the gooey chocolate chip cookie.
It's brand-gnu to the menu.
You mean brand-new?
No, brand-gnu.
What's gnu?
Beats me.
I thought you gnu.
Just kidding.
I don't know.
They just make me say it.
I'll just have the Freeburger and Kernel Fries.
Oh, and I need that to go.
So you want that in a container?
I guess.
So how much do I owe you?
Nothing.
It's free.
What, seriously?
Yeah.
The owners give everything away for free.
And since so many people around the world contribute,
the recipes are free for everyone to check out, too.
It's pretty cool.
That's why they call it Freeburger, dude.
Oh, right.
Hey, Linus?
Wait, is it Linus?
Anyway, I need you to release the Freeburger and Kernel
Fries, and make it snappy.
Users are so demanding.
Hey, that's really him, isn't it?
And it says I'd rather be diving on his shirt.
Hey, world without Linux is hard to imagine.
Thanks to the hundreds of thousands
of new individuals and companies who support Linux,
we don't have to.
Hashtag world without Linux.
Let's see.
There's also the Bash Sour Mash, the config pig.
Mm, mm, mm.
There's the shells and cheese.
Echo Prosecco, very smooth.
Wow.
Or you can get the seedy paranoia
with a side of chowing down.
Mm-hmm.
If you're thirsty, there's grep juice.
For sweets, we've got gummy boots, jelly beans,
cinnamon buns, yum extenders, ice cream sandwich,
gingerbread.
You could have some Java with gnome foam, if you're into that.
All right, that was a pretty good one.
That was the best one, wasn't it?
That probably was the best one.
They saved the best for last, and they got a Linus.
I wonder, though.
I feel like a lot of those jokes you'd already
have to know and like Linux to understand.
That doesn't seem like a world without Linux, did it?
Well, or at least it doesn't mark as well.
Look at you calling out the premise.
I mean, I'm glad they're making it.
I like the catchy music.
You're right.
That was playing to the base, wasn't it?
Right, which is fine.
I feel played, too, which makes me feel good.
But I don't think I could show that to my parents.
Java with gnome foam could be a title, Jumba.
You should bang suggest that.
I don't know.
What do you guys think in the Mumble Room?
That was a valiant effort, right?
I think they did pretty good.
And I'm imagining how they did this,
and I think it was probably a worthwhile effort.
Yeah, definitely appeals to the Linux old school, doesn't it?
Yeah.
Right.
I think it's the least worst one so far.
Yeah.
That's kind of you.
Reminds me of watching a Quentin Tarantino movie
for all the references.
Oh, just in the sense of making callback references,
or in the sense of Kill Bill cutting off heads?
Oh, OK.
All right.
Yeah, OK.
Yeah, iMacon doesn't like it.
You guys are a bunch of critics.
You know, the Linux crowd is a hard crowd.
It's a hard crowd.
We're not a nice community.
Oh, yes, we are.
We are.
In fact, if you want to prove it, just attend scale.
You'll actually see how nice we are.
It's just we're much nicer in person,
and that's the truth of it.
So we're going to scale, and I'm crapping my pants
as I talk about this.
It is not something I intended to do.
Damn it, Chris.
And I know, I'm sorry about that.
It's kind of smelly.
I have to be here for the rest of the show.
Go on.
You know, I'm not like Mr. Fancy Pants
Popey in the mumble room here, where my company will send me.
You know?
Well, you are your company.
Yeah, exactly.
And I just, the thing is, I have to be there.
I have to go.
And not only because I think it's extremely relevant for two,
at least, of the shows on the network,
if not three shows on the network,
but really, there is something to what Wes just
said, that joke you just made about how we're
kind of a rough community.
I was looking back at some of the stuff
we did to do the last retrospective of 2015,
and it just kept coming up over and over again, like community
drama and community issues.
And then I was doing the retrospective on LUP.
Same thing.
All of this crap about how the kernel mailing list is
handling interacting with people.
There was a period of time in the devian community
during the system D stuff.
Excuse me.
It is like, it is a bad, we have a bad stereotype going now.
It is like, it's kind of getting, it's like,
well, I don't know if I should say this,
but you know how there's communities online that
are known for being kind of a hard community to get into?
That's the Linux community.
We're that community now.
And it's totally unfounded, because I
think there are legitimate problems like there
are in any large scale community.
FreeBSD.
Some people have a bad time, but that doesn't
mean it's the majority.
Even the gentlemen, as they like to call themselves,
over at FreeBSD are going through this right now.
The FreeBSD Foundation just released a statement
about harassment.
There's back and forth going on.
If you want to follow that drama,
you can try to look into it.
No community is isolated from this,
because these are worldwide communities that are,
it's not just gender issues.
It is complete and different culture issues.
There are different cultures working together
that see things completely differently.
And so there are flare ups that happen.
And the thing is they happen out in the public,
because these are open mailing lists, not
behind some closed commercial private meeting
where everybody can yell at each other and nobody ever knows
about it.
I think Greg Cage touched on that very well
in that same retrospective.
Yeah.
And that's why I actually chose one of the reasons
I chose that clip, because I felt like it addressed
that issue at a meta level.
And so I don't know how else to say this,
but if you don't go to these events in person,
you don't get to see the other side of the coin.
You only get to read the online experience, which
is very, very skewed, because there's
some money to be made in the headlines and to generate clicks.
And people love drama.
Yeah.
So if you can, I really think going to an event like this,
it's a special experience.
There's not a lot of things that,
if you're as passionate about Linux,
even half as passionate about Linux as we are,
and it's something you follow.
You're listening to this show, so you probably are.
It is really a unique and fun experience.
And I think Linux Fest Northwest, I just love it.
It feels organic and genuine, and I've never
been to a scale before.
I've literally been avoiding it for the entire run of the show.
But I'm going to go to my first scale,
and I don't know what it's going to feel like.
I'm going to tell you, but I don't want to get there.
But I don't know yet.
But there are a lot of events that go on in the industry,
and these are some of the events that are really the good ones.
And if you're passionate about Linux,
it's a pretty cool opportunity.
And we have a promo code, last40.
We don't get any kickback for that at all.
There's no financial agreement to offer you that.
It's just they know we're going to be talking about scale,
and they want to get more people there,
and they gave us a promo code, last40.
And I guess I get the distinction
of having sent some people if you use that promo code.
So I guess in that sense, it helps the esteem of the show.
But I don't get any money for it.
Last40, you get a 40% discount, and it's
January 21st to the 24th.
And there's a couple of days there
where Ubicon will be overlapping scale.
It's going to be a track at scale that you can attend.
So you can go to both.
Ubicon's free.
They'd like you to register, though.
We'll have links in the show notes to do that.
And we're planning to do a tentative brunch on Friday.
Brunch, you say?
I do an action power brunch, actually.
I've already set up the meetup,
so we're starting to organize now.
I just kind of plugged in a temporary location,
which may or may not be the final location.
So if you want to join us,
go to meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
Here's why.
This is why we're doing this.
There's only going to be a short period of time
where both Noah and I are at scale.
I'm coming in to cover Ubicon
and the first couple of days of scale,
and then I'm leaving on Friday.
And I'm going to try like hell to get back here by Sunday.
I don't know if it's possible.
I'm going to try.
That is a mad dash.
It might not work.
I don't know what's going to happen.
So I'm going to try to get back here by Sunday
and do last from here with Noah doing it live from scale.
So Noah's going to be there from Friday to Sunday
to cover the latter half.
And I think it's going to be big on the weekend.
But the only day both Noah and I are going to be there
is Friday so far, as is planned.
So we're scheduling a meetup
in the kind of morning before scale really kicks off.
The idea being people always got stuff going on
in the evening.
Right.
So anyways, and I'm going to be leaving.
So I just put the meetup link in the chatroom.
It's also in the show notes.
And Mr. Popey, rumor has it there's also
kind of like a little gathering before Ubicon
that kicks off on Wednesday.
Do you know anything about that?
Maybe.
I've kind of messed up.
I'm getting out there really early.
I'm getting on the, I think I'm leaving here on the 18th.
So I'm going to be there around and about like a tourist.
On Tuesday.
Yeah, I think so.
Yeah.
So I may or may not.
So here's what I'm planning to do
is I'm planning to leave on the 16th
and take one of the most beautiful drives
in the United States of America is Highway 101
because from Washington to California,
it's the coast the entire way.
Highly recommend.
Yeah, and I've just been,
I've been reading people talking about it on blogs.
They're just raving about it.
It's beautiful.
Yeah, and lots of like really nice,
you know, small towns and stuff like that.
So I'm planning to take that drive down to California.
So we'll get some more Rover log.
Yeah, oh yeah, oh yeah.
And I'll probably arrive on the night
of the 19th or the 20th, I'm not sure.
I'm not quite sure when I'll arrive
because I'm going to take my time getting down there.
And then I'm going to haul balls getting back.
So.
I mean, you've seen it all before.
Yeah, yeah.
So I'd love to have you guys at the,
anybody that's attending, you too, Popey,
anybody who's attending,
I'd love to have you at the brunch if you can make it.
And we may change all the details.
All the details may change depending on Noah's flight
because he hasn't locked in flights yet
because his wife's birthday is right in there.
But right now it's tentatively scheduled
for Friday the 22nd at 9.30 a.m.
And I just figured we'd do lunch at a cafe right by the,
look, I found a nice cafe right by the event center,
the convention center.
But if people have a better suggestion
that are more familiar with the area, I'm all ears.
So there is a Linux action show subreddit thread
where we're already organizing.
And P4P3R has been kicking ass.
He's been updating it with new details as I release them.
So hopefully he'll update the post
with a link to the meetup.
I would prefer that this be where the discussion is had.
I don't really check the meetup forms very often
because honestly I got to check all these different places
and I'm driving.
So it's not super convenient
to check the crappy meetup page.
So we can organize and discuss right here in the subreddit.
And this is a great thread that's already going.
And if you can attend, just join the meetup.
Otherwise, you get to just watch from afar
as we kill ourselves to get this content to you.
Hey, you know what I should do is I should mention
we have a shirt that we're selling.
Teespring, it's funny, you see I didn't even plan for this,
but teespring.com slash last400.
You're a natural seller, Chris.
Well, it's because this whole scale event
is, well, I mean, really, to be honest with you,
is sort of at the worst time ever
because not only did Christmas just finish up
and not only is my daughter's birthday today,
but on a personal side, I'm just finishing up a divorce,
which-
I've heard those make you more wealthy.
Is that accurate, Chris?
Because I have three kids
and they're staying with Ange in that house,
I'm giving them everything.
So I'm moving out on my own
and I literally am buying everything
from toothbrushes on up.
And so I can't really personally afford to finance this.
Traditionally in the past, whatever the gap is,
I just pay for it personally,
is how I've done it for 10 years now.
I can't really afford to do that anymore
and not for a while.
So the idea is we have a couple of things
that are coming up.
I'd love to celebrate last400 at that power brunch we have.
I'd love to have cameras there.
I'd love to be able to afford to bring the gear there
to record it.
But in order to just get to scale,
we're gonna need to get funding.
And then to be able to do something like last400 video.
I wanna make a video for last400 while we're all at scale.
That's my intention.
And I would like to get all of that funded
as much as we can without it going on my credit card.
That's the base.
I mean, I'm just being 100% honest with you.
The idea was this is something
that we recognize we wanna do.
And I believe there is long-term value
to the open source community by going there
and documenting it the way that our shows do it.
So I think there is value to the open source community
and I think it's also value to the show
to make the show something
that continues to be relevant
and covers relevant Linux things.
And so at the end of it all is what I wanted to do
was once again, when we can, have you guys help us out
but also get something in the process.
And these are all very nice items.
They're not cheap.
We don't make a huge margin on them.
The quality is very good.
We've worked with Teespring now for years.
So we have a relationship with them
that allows us to call them up and say,
hey, this doesn't work for us.
You've gotta fix this.
And they've been very responsive.
I really like the spot we're in now
because now we're able to really do some great stuff.
The one thing we don't have the leverage to do,
which means the guys in the EU get a better deal,
is over at teespring.com slash last400EU.
We have a t-shirt, we have a hoodie,
but they also have a tote bag.
Oh, I want that tote bag.
I think I'm gonna buy one.
Maybe two. I am.
I actually told Ansh today to get me
like three different ones
cause you know, we can order from the EU,
we just have to pay more in shipping.
Right.
So, but the EU guys don't have to.
So at teespring.com slash last400EU,
you get the EU shipping,
cause they have a different,
they have a different, like,
they set up another shop over there,
so they do the printing locally.
Right.
Tote bag.
Tote bag at conferences is a no brainer.
It's a no brainer.
So that is, we are like,
you need to bring that to the US.
So we've been talking to them,
but they're like, yeah, we can't do it for this campaign.
Anyways, I would love to get your support,
and I'd like you to get something too.
These shirts are great.
These hoodies are killer.
We have a bunch of different colors.
You got the ladies fitted tee.
And what we're gonna do is,
so right now we've probably sold 26 or so,
and a few other on the EU side.
We're getting close to covering the gas to get down there,
which is great.
Right.
You know, but we're not really covering any shipping
to get the equipment, the big equipment from NOAA,
and we're not really covering anything
to really do at the party.
But we're getting close to covering the gas,
which is great.
But we definitely are not there,
so we could use a lot more support.
And, you know, really, I appreciate the fact
that I can just sit here and tell you guys,
honestly, why I'm doing it.
I hope that you understand that,
from a business standpoint,
this is sort of our best way to keep doing this
in a way that allows us to sustainably produce these shows.
Because if I overextend for events as they come up,
that's not a sustainable approach.
You could put the network in jeopardy.
Yeah.
But at the same time, I also,
and I am willing to consider,
I am definitely willing to,
and this is not like you have to do this or else,
I am willing to consider that maybe the better option is
to go to a commercial sponsor
and have them just sponsor the hell out of an event.
But I don't know.
I don't know if it is or not,
and I'm willing to experiment with it,
but I also really like the idea of,
as best we can, crowdsourcing it,
because not only does that save me time
when having to line up deals,
but it also just sort of lets you guys know
I'm going there really for you
not to go promote somebody else.
Anyways, teespring.com slash last 400,
or patreon.com slash today.
And don't forget meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting
for the meetup.
And I got a link to the Ubicon stuff
where they say Wednesday, January 20th,
one night before the event,
there'll be a meeting around 1900
for an informal gathering to get to know each other.
And I have a link to the whole Ubicon conference schedule
in the show notes if you guys are gonna be able to attend
both.
And it looks like there's gonna be a Thursday night party.
Which I don't know if I'm registered for.
Poppy, you and I need to talk.
Maybe you can get me in contact with somebody,
make sure I'm already in for all this stuff, okay?
Cause I wanna go to that Thursday party.
Maybe after the show you and I can little wink-wink.
That's nice.
A party, that sounds good.
Get drunk with Mark Shuttleworth, right?
Yep. Right.
Plus you know- Body shots, I think that's-
Plus you know,
Poppy's drinking that watered down beer over there.
So when you're here drinking the Sierra,
the Sierra, what is it here?
The- Celebration.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, you know he's gonna get a little tipsy.
So you're gonna have to coax me off of dry January first,
which won't be that hard to be honest.
Dry January?
Tell us more.
Have you never heard of this?
Oh, it's just like, you know,
stop drinking for a month after the excess of Christmas.
Oh, really?
Oh, well I don't think that'll be too hard.
No, it won't.
It really won't.
It doesn't count if you're in another country.
Yeah, first of all, it's a way different area code.
So that doesn't count.
And second of all, it's like the end of January.
So it's, you pretty much did it.
Just have to make sure nobody tells my wife, all right?
No problem.
As long as she doesn't listen to the show, we're good.
Which I think we're probably good.
Everyone tweet at the real Popey.
I thought you had to drink to recover from Christmas
and the time you spent with the family and everything.
Popey, alls you have to do is just think of a line
that the wife will buy.
I don't know if she has any anti-American sentiment in her,
but just say, honey,
I was down there around all those Yankees.
It was just the worst.
They smell bad.
They don't drink any tea.
And they drive on the wrong side of the road
like a bunch of assholes.
I needed something to soothe my nerves.
And then she doesn't-
Have you been listening in to my conversations
with my wife?
That's exactly what I would say.
So there you go.
So you just say you got problem solved.
I'm a problem solver.
People ought to consult me for relationship counseling
as somebody who's going through divorce.
I think I could make some money at that.
Let me tell you something.
All right, let me tell you another way.
Maybe it's not the counseling.
Here's a way you could save some money.
Switch to Ting.
That would probably be a better way.
Maybe my counseling skills should wait
and you should just switch to Ting.
And this would be a good time to do it
at the beginning of the year.
Linux.ting.com.
That's where you go to support this here show.
Also get yourself a discount off some Ting gear,
which is all unlocked and you own.
Or get a credit if you bring a device.
And they have a lot of devices
because they have a CDMA and GSM network
that you get to pick from.
And some of these devices like the Nexus Eye devices
and some of the nicer ones,
they have the capability of running on CDMA or GSM.
Now that's cool.
Now you can get kinda picky.
Now you can sort of say, well,
I mean, for me, when I'm out in the Rover
and I go somewhere over the weekend,
sometimes I have better CDMA coverage
and sometimes I have better GSM coverage.
It just depends on the location.
So I can be kinda savvy about that.
And Ting has an incredible dashboard
that lets you manage all of this stuff.
It works on all of your devices.
But it's actually good.
It's actually useful.
I don't really know how else to describe it.
It is, you know, you can go in there
and you can set nicknames for your devices.
You can go in there and set alerts
and you can set maximum thresholds.
You can turn off individual level services
that allows you to really get granular control
over your account.
You can do things like transfer to another line
from the control panel itself.
You don't even have to call customer service.
But it's not to get you to avoid using customer service
because they have fanatical customer service
that sticks with you until the problem is solved.
So it's a really nice setup.
So go to linux.ting.com to see more.
They have great devices at great prices.
And they also have a great blog.
We covered this in Linux Action Show this Sunday.
Kyra just posted her top five apps
over the last 12 months.
Pretty good video.
And they also have done some recent holiday cord cutter
posts that are really useful if you need to cut the cord.
And they've also even got the sports.
Which I know, Wes, you're a big sports guy.
You're a huge.
It's hard to find those college football.
Playoff games on the internet.
Sports ball.
You know, I actually got a couple good ideas
from reading the blog post even though I'm not a sports guy.
Because I just am really interested in getting live TV
on the internet and things like that.
And that was actually, it was a good post.
IPTV the future.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
You know, Ting really seems like they're made up
of people like us.
They really are.
Which is awesome.
It is kind of cool.
And you know, so because they're owned by Two Cows,
which has been around forever,
and they're like one of the original internet companies
that figured out how to survive the dot com boom
and do things right.
So there's certain things that they just really,
like they just follow by law.
It's just like their own personal law.
Linux.ting.com.
Go there, support the show and get $25
off your first unlocked device and go own it.
Linux.ting.com.
And a big thank you to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
I love it.
All right, Ryan, I hope you are back here, sir.
Because I would love to talk to you
about what's going on at the MyCraft project.
Ryan?
Did he make it back?
No.
Oh yeah, oh sorry.
There you go.
Okay, Ryan, go ahead.
Well, I'm here and I've got a lot to talk about.
Well, now hold on, let's tease it a little bit.
So Ryan emails me and we're talking back and forth
about a couple things that you guys probably hear about
more down the road.
And there was a tease that there might be something
landing that people, a tangible thing people
can go get their hands on online and look at
and sort of maybe even contribute to.
I don't wanna say anymore.
I'm excited already.
But I'm just saying something interesting
could be dropping very soon from the MyCraft project.
You think I have teased properly, Ryan?
Yeah, that's perfect.
Okay, so what's going on?
Tomorrow at three o'clock PM, central standard time.
I don't know what it is in UTC.
Ha ha ha.
Okay.
We are releasing the Adapt Intent Parser.
Hey!
Which is our software library that we use
to convert natural language into machine
readable data structures.
So what that means, yeah.
So it's the Intent Parser you said?
Yeah, that's right.
Okay.
And this is kind of some of the secret sauce of MyCraft.
So we're really releasing probably one of our
most powerful tools right out of the gate.
That's high.
Ryan, I might have you check your input a little bit
because you're clipping a little bit.
I think this sounds like, and I'm gonna ask you
if I'm right or not, but this sounds like this is
sort of like the critical decision maker piece
that once I've been given input, I have to decide
what the intent of that input was.
Are they looking to do a thing?
Are they asking about a thing?
Do I have that right?
That's exactly correct.
What it does is it looks at your sentence or your query
and parses it and it decides what the person is trying to do
and then turns it into an action.
Or turns it into at least a JSON little data set
that an application can use to take an action.
That kind of seems like that's a core thing
that makes Siri and Google Now useful is they know
when I say, what's the weather like today?
They're able to grab the context out of that and say,
well today is this, like they get the intent
of what I'm doing, like that seems like the thing
that makes these things actually smart.
Yeah, that's right.
And since we had, actually when we began
after the Kickstarter, we had received a lot of attention.
And Josh and I, the founders had, we had a,
what we call Mycroft Legacy now.
And we were using a variety of tools
in order to perform this action.
And then Sean Fitzgerald, who was formerly
one of the developers at Siri and on the Amazon Echo,
came over and he brought this with him.
Oh wow.
An earlier version of this.
And he was like, hey, I've been working on this,
I was gonna open source it, but it seemed like
it would be a good fit for your guys' project
considering I had spoken on multiple occasions
about wishing that I didn't have to rely on outside APIs
to do this type of task.
Ah, so this is huge in the sense too
that you're now less reliant on third-party services?
Yeah, that's right.
And so we immediately, once I realized
what he'd brought with him, I was like,
we need to put some resources into this
and get this as polished as we can
and then share it with the world.
And so we've put some polish on it.
It's still early days, but our release is in July
of everything.
And so we're just opening it up now
so the community can get in there and hack it
and use it for other things other than
what we've used it for.
I actually got some ideas laid out here
because I wanted to share them with your audience
because I'm really excited for people to use it.
Yeah.
What is, could you tell us what's the license gonna be?
What is it written in?
Oh yeah.
It's gonna be, it's Python, it's all written in Python.
Oh great.
It's being released under the LGPL version three.
Wow.
We were originally going to release it
under the GPL version three,
but we realized that some people wouldn't be able
to use it in their applications
because of the nature of the GPL.
So the one limited sort of negated that.
Yeah.
And so the LGPL can be used with other licenses
a lot easier.
And that was a conversation that I had
with the community on mostly on Google Plus.
I just asked, I was like, hey,
we're gonna release this new project.
I want to know what you guys think we should release it
under and the overwhelmingly they said LGPL.
So not to get too down into the weeds, Ryan,
but does this intent parser kick in before
or after a call out to a remote service?
Where is this fall in sort of the decision chain
that a MyCraft device follows?
So right now what happens is it kind of depends
on the device because adapt sometimes has to live
on our servers with our testing with really small
embedded devices that don't have any processing,
real processing power on board, but it's super lightweight.
We've run it on the original Raspberry Pi and the B plus.
And it was just fine.
It was fast and responsive.
And it lives on our current MyCraft stack.
If you're using the embedded device,
so if you're using the MyCraft unit
that we raise money for in the Kickstarter,
it actually does live locally.
So the query goes out, the STT,
whatever we're using for STT in this case would be with AI
or Google STT would come back with the text.
So what you said, and then the adapt intent parser
sitting on the unit would look at it
and turn it into actionable data,
which then MyCraft would take the next action,
whether that be calling out to an API to get the weather
or casting something to the Chromecast.
So now this piece is sort of been pre-developed.
Are you concerned at all about anybody
that's gonna claim things like intellectual property patents
or anything like that?
Is this a minefield for you guys?
Or are you feeling safe?
We're feeling pretty safe.
It's a different approach than...
So there's two things.
There's nothing like this out there
that's open source right now,
which is just a giant hole that's missing in the world.
And it could be used for so many other things
than what we're using it for, like chat bots, IRC bots.
I actually keep thinking of studio automation tasks
that I could use.
And robots and video games.
Video games would be so cool
if you could type something to a character
and have them understand your intent, or like a phone system
or analysis of large amounts of data.
Like if you were analyzing a whole bunch of tweets,
this could pick out.
Really?
Various things about what they're doing and things like that.
You mean there's wide applications
outside of even AI devices like this?
You mean there could be server-side
background analysis applications for something like this?
That's exactly right.
And to answer your question,
because I kind of sidestepped there,
we're not worried about copyright infringing
or anything like that,
because we kind of have so many people now from backgrounds
who have worked on projects like this before
that a lot of people say that our approach
is a lot different than those of the other existing companies
and that they don't think that it's really necessarily
going to be a problem.
But we'll see.
I mean, we'll see.
It seems like, it seems,
one of the things, Ryan,
that has always struck me about these personal assistants,
be it Amazon Echo and today,
I talked about it in Tech Talk today, Ford announced,
they're looking to integrate with the Amazon Echo,
so that way you can give it commands from your car.
It seems like what you really need for these things
to ever be useful is ubiquity.
So like I would need one in my home,
I would need one in my office,
I might need one in my car,
and I would maybe need one in different areas of my house.
And I think the only way to truly make that possible
is to have the device be different types of devices
for different scenarios.
Maybe in my studio, it's all running on a computer.
Maybe in my RV, it's on a little Mycroft appliance box,
and in my kitchen, it's a Mycroft appliance box.
But maybe in my studio,
it's something that's on just a Raspberry Pi
that I've implemented myself.
It seems like the ability to have the stuff behind this,
the open source software behind this,
run on a server in a different form of implementation,
actually gives the possibility of true ubiquity
in this kind of artificial assistant.
So I don't have to have just my phone.
I don't have to have just the Mycroft device.
I don't have to be in just this room.
And if I have even a little a DIY inspiration,
I could roll it myself,
or somebody could make a product that does it.
I could even have it running on my server
that's checking my email in some degree.
It seems to me that open source isn't just a licensing thing,
but it actually makes like this truly
an Internet of Things capable device or set of software.
Yeah, you nailed it on the head.
The idea where a lot of people are too siloed
and they're thinking about what this type of technology means
and where it's going to live.
Mycroft, the thing that I keep saying in interviews
is Mycroft is not just going to live on the Mycroft unit.
Mycroft in the world that we envision lives on the computer,
it lives on the phone, it lives on the freaking dishwasher.
Maybe it's on a droplet working on something I gave it.
Yeah, exactly.
And these parts, and the thing that was the most frustrating
when we took up this task was none of this was there.
There were some projects that were kind of, you know,
tackling maybe a little bit of one part of what we're doing.
But the thing is, in order for us to actually make a dent
and compete with the proprietary applications
that are coming out, we have to,
we've found ourselves having to tackle various parts
of this project, which is fine.
They need to be tackled.
And so this is one part, you know, the adapt engine
is one part.
So I guess in day to day, here's to bring it all
to a sort of like a point, a relevant point,
is I could see myself having a Mycroft AI unit
in my kitchen and then I go upstairs to work in my office
and instead of having another hardware that I spent 100
or 200 or whatever it is, I have Mycroft on the desktop.
And it also is using my desktop mic and it is also aware
of the same things my kitchen version is,
but in the kitchen I have in a self-contained appliance unit
and up in my office where I have my nice powerful desktop,
I'm just running the Mycroft software.
Does that seem like a feasible implementation to you?
Yes, it does.
In fact, I'm running it on my desktop right now.
Yes, earlier.
What else can you tell us about that?
Well, we did release a video just a couple days ago
about Mycroft on the desktop.
But the other thing is, I, yesterday,
or was it the day before, I don't know,
Aaron's sitting next to me, he knows, I'm sure,
I launched every application I could on my computer
via Mycroft and my fan was kicking up
and making all sorts of noise
because I didn't close any of them,
I just kept asking him to open more and more and more.
And it was crazy what accuracy was and I realized,
yes, you could just go and pick through your applications
and open that random one, but it is so convenient.
Are you using Mycroft on an Oryx Pro?
There is, yeah, there's an Oryx Pro next to me
that has it on it.
What's a mitochondria?
Mitochondria, an organelle containing enzymes
responsible for producing energy.
Hey Mycroft, what is 31 divided by six?
5.16 repeating.
It kind of sounds like Wimpy.
Are you telling me, are you telling me
that System76 gave you Oryx Pros for this video?
Are you telling me that?
Because I wanted an Oryx Pro real bad.
They didn't give us one.
You bought it?
That's Aaron's, yeah.
They're always, okay.
I got back from System76 and I was talking about
what the nice build quality was and everything
and he broke down and bought it and a frenzy.
I want one so bad I was about to get super jelly
because you know what, I got to say,
I want to be first in line if they're giving them away.
All right.
I want to say one thing about the Oryx Pro real quick.
Okay.
The keyboard on that is the best keyboard I've ever used.
Yeah.
I just put, yeah, I got to use it for one night
and I fell in love.
So I'm inferring from the video here
that this is a working thing.
Is this something I can get my hands on yet?
Not yet, April.
April is when, I mean, you,
maybe we can work something out, but.
But like I keep saying, we're really just trying
to ensure that our first,
each of these projects around Mycroft,
we're trying to make as solid as possible
before we release it to be contributed to
because part of that is not does this run well,
but it's how, what's the,
what's it look like when someone wants to contribute
back to this project?
Are they able to do that in an easy way?
Are they able to, do they have the documentation they need?
Do they have the tools they need in order to develop for it?
And so people just want me,
a lot of people ask me like to just throw everything
out there in one big release party,
but I'm like, if I throw it out there
without enough documentation,
this is actually a problem that people aren't used
to dealing with this artificial intelligence
or in the event of like natural language processing.
And so I've tried, I've set people in front of it
and said like, hey, look at this.
And they're like, I'm not familiar with any of these terms.
I don't know how any of this works.
And it's because we're used to creating applications
where you point and grunt.
You know, you're not used to parsing what people say
and turning that into actionable.
Is this your way of letting me know
that you're not gonna bring a demo unit to scale?
I am bringing a demo unit to scale.
Oh, all right, nice.
Yes, I was hoping so, I wanna see it.
Yeah, I've heard you're giving out demos
and I'm hoping to see one at scale.
Watch Chris's hands, he will steal it.
Ryan, what is your hope?
I mean, aren't you at least a little concerned
that the noise of the convention floor
will make the audio interaction impossible with the thing?
So I'm concerned about that, but I'm also planning on,
I already talked to Jono
cause I gave him a demo earlier today.
And we talked about stealing a side room
in order to show people so that we weren't,
cause yes, just like when you're talking to a person,
if lots of people are yelling around it,
sometimes it picks you up, sometimes it's like hey,
I don't know what you said.
That's gotta be the worst case scenario
is a convention floor for a device.
So if it even works at all,
then you're probably good.
Make sure you grab me or Noah
and let's get a little video of it
cause that'd be amazing when we're down there.
So Ryan, what else do we need to talk about today?
Cause I feel like there's other things,
but I don't, nothing comes to the top of my head.
Well, I just really wanna remind people
that what's coming out tomorrow, Adapt and Temp Parcer,
and we are so excited to see
what people will be using Adapt for,
what ideas they have,
where right now I've been spending all day
working on the documentation,
trying to make it as easy as possible
for people to get up and use it for something.
And this, if you start with this
and you really gain an understanding of this,
you'll be able to, on day one,
probably write various skills from Mycroft.
So it's not a waste of time to pop in
and learn a little bit about this.
And what I want to see
are really, really intelligent IRC bots.
Like that seems like a perfect match for this.
It does, it really does.
And JBot gets an upgrade in 2016.
Yeah, and you know, like I said,
robots would be a really good match for this.
And video games, video games are the clearest one to me
because you could have characters who understand
the simplest of phrases.
This very well may be the originator
of the intended parser for the frickin' holodeck.
Yeah. That could be, right?
Oh, I know what we should talk about, Chris.
Yeah.
And I haven't committed to this, but-
It's in the back of your mind,
something you got kicking around?
Yeah, I keep, I shouldn't commit to things on here.
No, this isn't a commitment.
This is a brainstorming session.
Oh, a brainstorming session.
So I told Chris this so everybody knows,
that we should totally pimp the RV with Mycroft units.
Oh yeah. Oh yeah.
The Rover's gotta be upgraded with Mycroft AI.
I'm not kidding, that's gotta happen.
I just don't-
Not just one, not just one.
You don't want the unit at the front of the RV.
No, you gotta have one in the back
where the business is too, because-
In the bathroom too.
Oh, oh yeah, yeah.
Just everywhere.
That's a good point.
You basically nailed the three sound isolation zones
where I would need mic coverage.
Yeah, yeah.
So can you hook Mycroft up to accelerometers
and things like that?
So it can say to Chris in the middle of the night,
stay calm, it's just an earthquake.
Well, you know, this is something
that we don't talk about enough anymore,
but remember the actual units themselves
are with the exception of the Raspberry Pi,
which, you know, some people are like,
that's not open hardware,
but the unit itself is completely open.
You can pop it open, there's a Raspberry Pi in there,
and there's an Arduinos, and there's, you know,
everything's exposed, all the ports are exposed.
So you can hack on it if you want to
and add whatever it is that you-
That actually in the rover could be a useful feature.
That could be a very useful feature.
Somebody asked in chat, and I just wanted to tell them,
you do not need a Mycroft unit
in order to use Mycroft on the desktop.
Right.
Yeah, but I would still encourage anybody
who's been on the edge to order a Mycroft unit
because it supports the development effort.
Yeah.
But no, you know, anyone who has the ability
to install Debian packages should be able
to run Mycroft on their desktop.
Cool.
Now, Wimby usually had a question, go ahead.
Yeah, we've obviously heard quite a lot about Mycroft
over the last sort of six to nine months.
I was just curious how much time you'd been working on it
prior to the Kickstarter.
I started working on Mycroft.
Mycroft probably was born in January of 2015.
I think that sounds right.
And then that was Josh Montgomery, the CEO, at the time.
Him and I, I actually hung out at his makerspace
and what had happened is he'd seen a really simple AI
at another makerspace.
It was all like, you just said a specific word
and it just had a pre-selected action that it took.
And so we started geeking out about geek things.
And he started telling me about this
and we were like, you know, maybe we can make this.
That would be so awesome if the makerspace
that we hang out in had this in every room
and you could say like, hey, Mycroft, where's this?
Do this, play this music.
And so it was originally named Scarlett, though,
after Scarlett Johansson.
Now I'm in love.
Now you've sold me.
And then over time, when we started playing
with our early code, we were like,
this is actually really awesome.
We should make a product out of this.
And that's where that was kind of born.
So I got on around March or April.
And so it's been worked on since January, 2015.
And then the Kickstarter was, of course,
I think around September.
I kind of, that was so,
there was so much going on at that point with Mycroft
that my mind has kind of like blocked out all of that.
But yeah, anybody who thinks you just throw up
a Kickstarter and money rolls in is just wrong.
Anyway.
Are you saying the device was inspired by the movie Her?
No, not necessarily.
Have you seen that movie, the AI,
voiced by Scarlett Johansson?
It was inspired by many things.
Yeah, I know, I'm just teasing.
Well, you know the namesake, right?
Of Mycroft?
No, I don't.
Oh, you did, I think you told me, but I don't remember.
It's named after the AI in The Moon is a Harsh Mistress.
Right, okay.
It's also the name of Sherlock Holmes' brother, but.
Yeah, right, right, right.
Anyway, but yeah, so yeah, we've been working on it for,
well, it's January now, so a full year.
That's remarkable progress.
Yeah, it's actually pretty neat to see.
Yeah, really good momentum.
Yeah, and I mean, especially if you're ready
to show a device at scale.
That's pretty cool.
I'm excited to see that footage.
Yeah, yeah, I'm really excited to share it, you know.
So where do I go right now?
I know I go to Mycroft AI for the project
but if I wanted to jump in with the funding,
where else could I go?
Let me post a link.
It's Indiegogo, you can pre-order on Indiegogo.
They have a nice pre-order system.
I'm gonna post a link in the chat.
Sure.
And if you can post it in the show notes,
that would be awesome.
No problemo.
Yeah, I think this is really neat
and one of the things I like about it is,
I would like to have a hardware device.
I genuinely think that's neat.
But I also love the idea of just turning
all of my Linux desktops into something
that contributes to this thing.
Like if they could all be tied into the same
information sources and I have the same
kind of functionality on my desktop
that I could have and say my kitchen
or the rover would really be pretty unique.
And like VR and other things that are really
kind of developing right now,
I would love to see Linux really have
something here for this.
And what Mycroft to me, in my estimation,
is it's putting us kind of ahead
of the overall competition.
Because the competition can't offer
what Mycroft can offer and it's powered by Linux.
So this is the one to get behind in my opinion.
Yeah, and let me tell you guys
something that's really exciting.
I, we updated, so everything that Mycroft can do
is called a skill.
And we updated our skill framework right before Christmas.
And so on December 24th, we're getting ready
to head up to my parents' house
and I've got the Mycroft code base open
and I said I'm just going to see with the new,
because it looked really simple, the new skill framework.
I'm like, I'm going to see how quickly I can create a skill.
I created a skill in 15 minutes.
And that was with me having not touched the skill,
the new skill framework.
Like I'm granted, I'm somewhat familiar with, you know,
how these things are developed and everything.
But Sean and Jonathan, two of our developers,
had really headed up the new skill framework.
And I just sat down, looked at another skill
that was based on the new framework
and wrote one in 15 minutes.
That's great.
It was a Pokedex.
So if any of you have played Pokemon,
you could say like, what does a Pokedex say
about this Pokemon and it would tell you.
And so it seemed like an easy target.
And so, and I was going up to visit
my little brother-in-law, he's like 13.
And so it was nice to be able to show him that.
But just when I did that, I thought,
holy crap, like that my own,
like our own project surprised me.
Cause I thought if I could do this in 15 minutes,
people can do amazing things.
There's so much out there that can be done.
And that's why we're so excited.
We're trying to get this stuff ready as quickly
as we can to get it out there and get people,
you know, having fun with it.
It's probably worth mentioning too.
If you go to the Indiegogo page,
you can also just get in,
you can just chip in at five bucks or 10 bucks.
You know, you get a sticker, 30 bucks
and you get the dev kit.
You don't have to go all the way in.
If you can't afford to get a hardware device,
but you still think this is a great idea,
there's a $5 and $10 and $35 or $30.
We don't want the open source desktop to be,
you know, left in the wayside with Cortana and Siri.
Yeah, screw Cortana, screw Cortana.
Yeah, really.
Can I share something else that was really awesome?
There's so much, I just need like,
we need a Mycroft action show, but anyway.
We very well might one day.
Yeah, okay.
So the other thing that we got running really well
was up until just last week,
I think of the week before,
we had run Mycroft on a Ubuntu phone emulator.
And so we finally got two Ubuntu phones
and we threw, and we got Mycroft running
on the Ubuntu phones.
Cool, wow.
So I was, but I was getting upset
because I knew it could text
because the other phone was able to text people
by saying, hey, Mycroft, text so-and-so, this is awesome.
You know, text that message to them.
Yeah.
So I was sitting there and I was like,
hey Mycroft, text Aaron, you know, this is awesome.
And then I didn't do anything and I was like,
hey Mycroft, text Aaron, this is awesome.
And so I was getting really pissed.
And so I looked in the logs and it's like,
you haven't put any contacts in the phone.
I don't have anybody named Aaron to send a message to.
And so, but it was, it's just so awesome
that the tech is, it's so awesome using Ubuntu
with like, whether it be on the desktop or on the phone,
with a personal assistant.
I mean, it's just.
Yeah, absolutely.
It's just, I think that a lot of people
are going to appreciate having that option
on the Linux desktop and also having the ability
to add things that are specific to you.
Right, and if it got really crazy big one day,
so you know, somebody could make an Android app,
somebody could, you know, I mean,
it could be on all the platforms.
Yeah, Aaron's writing an in-map skill.
Nice, there you go.
So I think Northranger sort of summarizes it a lot.
And it really, for me, Northranger, I don't know about you,
but it comes down to the fact that
Mycroft doesn't have sort of an overall
multinational corporate strategy tax,
where Cortana has the tax of whatever Microsoft
intends to do with their Bing and Azure
and the entire Microsoft Windows ecosystem.
And Google obviously wants to keep using Google search.
They want to be able to mine your data for advertising.
Siri locks you into the Apple platform.
Mycroft doesn't have that baggage.
And I don't know about you, Northranger,
but I think that's maybe its most attractive feature.
What do you think?
I totally agree.
Having something that both individuals
who'd want to add their own skills, you know,
and it's attractive, Mycroft is an attractive system
for that, and you know, if it takes off,
I'd love to see, you know, outside companies,
you know, publishing their own Mycroft skills,
you know, and not have to feel like they're giving away
their secret sauce to Google or Amazon or whoever.
Yeah, exactly.
Em Hall wants help, Ryan, installing it at scale.
So you're gonna be doing a little tech support
while you're down at scale with Mr. Hall.
That sounds good.
Yeah, so anyway, keep your eyes peeled
for Adapt getting released tomorrow.
If you are not already following us on Twitter,
it's at Mycroft underscore AI.
And if you're on Google+, it's plus Mycroft A dot I.
Yeah.
And you can find us.
If you search, you can find us,
and maybe we can get into the show notes.
Yep, yep, I'll have it linked.
I'll have that linked up in the show notes for you
because I think it's worth checking out.
And you know, Ryan, I really appreciate you
coming on the show and sharing this with us.
It is extremely fascinating to follow this
as you're working on it, so it really means a lot
to come in and chat about it with us.
I love coming in, chatting about this stuff.
Well, thank you, sir.
So thanks.
Stick around if you want to,
because after I go through and own up
to my 2015 predictions later on in the show,
I'm gonna open up the floor to some predictions,
and I'd like to hear some of yours.
So stick around if you can.
And before we get into the rest of the show,
I'm gonna take a moment and thank Linux Academy,
sponsors of the Unplugged show now, for a long time.
And I think that's because this is an obvious fit.
Right?
It's kind of a no-brainer, actually.
This is a resource created for Linux users,
by Linux users, who give a shit about open source.
And if that sounds like somebody that
sort of is in line with the things that you care about,
that might be why it's such a great fit.
Maybe that just has something to do with it.
I don't quite know.
But go over to LinuxAcademy.com slash Unplugged
and take advantage of our discount,
and go check out the Linux Academy.
They really, I mean, I joke.
I'm having fun with you here, but let's be serious.
This Linux enthusiast got together with educators
and developers, and they made the Linux Academy platform
for people who know what Linux is,
know what all of the different stuff in the stack is
that you need to learn, and they know they needed
a good place to go to learn it
from people who actually care.
So they've got over 2,000 video courses you can take,
with instructor help when you need it,
downloadable comprehensive study guides,
seven plus Linux distributions you get to choose from.
It automatically adjusts the courseware
and the virtual machines that you can SSH into
from your favorite SSH client and do it like a boost,
which is nice, right in with your existing workflow.
They have the entire AWS stack.
If you want to get into the Red Hat certified courseware,
they've got that.
If you want to learn the Ubuntu LAMP stack,
If you want to go into NGINX or Python or Ruby,
if you want to go into Android development,
if you want to go into virtualization
and containerization, they have all of it.
This is something that they've been really good at
is they watch what's going on
because they're into it just like we are,
and then they pull the trigger on the stuff
they know that's really gonna be the long-term stuff
that's gonna add value to your life to learn.
They have scenario-based labs
so you get real hands-on experience.
So you're actually working with the stuff
so when you go to do it in person,
it's not the first time you've ever done it.
When you're actually doing it, getting paid for it,
gives you that kind of confidence in their lab servers.
And then they have that instructor help.
That to me, that to me seems like the big differentiator.
Because these topics are not like learning After Effects
where there's tens and thousands of After Effects guys
out there that they could go contract.
It's not tightening the bolts on your sink
that there's tons and tons and tons of ways
to get instructions and help on that
with experts that can help you.
It is working with a Red Hat server.
It's setting up AWS and working with S3.
These are a little more esoteric,
more complicated types of questions,
and they have instructor help when you need it.
They have graded server exercises.
You log into a lab, you perform a specific task,
and then they'll automatically grade your actions
so you can see how well you did.
This is really nice.
Talk about the kind of experience you get
from something like that.
And remember, it's choosing from the distro
that you've selected.
That's pretty cool too.
And imagine the amount of work they have to do
to make that work.
That's the thing.
That's the thing that we thought about doing
for How To Linux and we're like,
whoo, we don't have a staff of a bajillion.
We could never do it.
You have to pick one.
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
Go check them out.
They just recently revamped
their backend distribution infrastructure.
Whole new CDN, HTML5 players throughout
so it works on all your good devices.
It really is a great resource.
You can support the show
by going to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
And a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring.
Thank you.
The unplugged program.
Okay, Wes, so every year this guy comes along now
with his big old list of crap that don't work
on the Linux desktop,
and this is the major Linux problems for 2016 edition.
And this is as put a regularly updated article
of all of the things that are wrong
with Linux distributions.
Now, Wes, did you get a chance by any chance
to go through this long list of items?
And did you get a sense of this person's intent
when you went through this list?
Yes, I think the intent is good.
I think it's a helpful catalog.
I think there are some items
where it reads more emotionally
or more heat of the moment than it could.
I think there are some items that are either dated
or I think a lot of it also draws attention
to this fails in some cases.
And it's important that we note that, right?
Because any failure is important,
but it also kind of I think highlights some things
where it's like, well, you may have that problem,
but 90% of people do not.
I think what it really lacks is a real sense
of any statistics and the larger context.
Do you have a sense if this person is experienced
with Linux or with other operating systems?
Do you have a sense if they have a good technical capability?
Yes, I would say it sounds like someone
who's been in the trenches using a Linux desktop
for a long time and continues to do so.
I know a lot of people who have jumped that ship,
now they're on the Mac, now they use Windows
because they have games.
This person sounds like someone who's put up with a lot
and who's run the full gamut of working or not.
He says here, I want to make one thing crystal clear,
Windows in some regards is even worse than Linux
and it's definitely not ready for the desktop either.
Right, and I think a lot of these too are
how you define that ready for the desktop
because there's some of these where it's like,
well, if ready for the desktop is you need it
to work reliably, 100% production machine
with this specific equipment, maybe it won't.
Is it ready for your grandmother's computer
to browse the web and write up a word,
you know, or maybe it is.
Right, and those are two different interpretations
of the desktop.
So here's where he starts.
Open source Nvidia driver is much slower,
up to five times than its proprietary counterpart
due to improperly working power management
and the AMD and Intel graphic drivers
can significantly be slower than the proprietary
counterparts.
This is a huge issue, he says.
And I think this is a prime example
of what you were just saying.
Those of us that would be using, in my estimation,
the open source Nvidia driver could give really
no crap about the performance.
We just really want to be able to hook up a projector
or hook up an external monitor, hook up our TV
or just run our single monitor
and as long as the windows render properly
and if there is some sort of desktop effect,
it is within appropriate response time,
they're happy, that's the baseline,
all they need from the open source driver.
Those of us who want every bit of performance
out of our GPU we can, we're already compelled
to run the proprietary driver for other reasons.
So this right off the surface is,
it's not taking into context this complaint.
And I would also, I could take a moment
and mention that the graphic situation
is not necessarily much better on the Mac.
The Mac has horrible GPU drivers.
So.
And in some cases the open source,
like I know the open source AMD graphics,
while they may not be great currently for 3D,
the 2D stuff is great,
they support multiple monitors flawlessly.
So I think his first complaint sort of puts it
in the context of what you're saying
with the overall issue we take with the article
is it sort of, it blurs the lines
between different use cases and it just tries to take,
Linux is a very flexible operating system
that can work on a lot of different scenarios
and some scenarios have different requirements.
Right, some of those requirements are directly at odds.
If it works well in one scenario, maybe it can't.
Yeah.
All right, so Mumble Room, as we go through these,
feel free to chime in as you like.
That was our first one.
But here's some other ones in here that,
you know what, they ring a little true.
Let's talk about the audio subsystem.
Let's start with my favorite one
because it affects the Mumble Room.
No reliable echo cancellation.
If you use a normal microphone and speakers,
in many cases you won't be able to use Skype
and VoIP services normally.
Windows, Android, and Mac OS all implemented
voice cancel echo cancellation on a system level.
There's a solution for pulse audio
and hopefully be enabled by default in the future.
This is legitimately something that is kind of
a pain in the ass on Linux.
Are you familiar with that solution?
I am not.
The solution is don't use speakers, use headphones.
That's the solution.
Because even voice cancellation, echo cancellation
isn't that great on the other platforms either.
Just don't use Hangouts or Mumble
with a microphone and open speakers.
Use a headset or something like that.
Which is what many professional broadcasters
would be doing anyway.
Yeah.
All right, no reliable sound system.
No reliable unified audio mixing implemented
in all modern OSes except for Linux.
Many old and or proprietary applications
still open audio output exclusively,
causing major user problems and headache.
Too many layers of abstraction lead to situations
where the user cannot determine why audio input output
doesn't work.
Also kernel drivers, also library connected to DMX
connected to the pulse audio server,
then the also library, then the pulse backend,
then the application.
That's six layers of redirection.
And then you add the seventh layer in the case of KDE
because they have phonon.
That seventh layer really is killer sometimes too.
Yeah.
It really is.
That seventh.
Six seems to work.
It's like a dip, man.
The seventh layer dip, nothing bothers my gut
except for the cheese on the top.
It's that seventh layer that actually bothers my gut.
Dammit.
You know, it's funny because as somebody
who is sitting in front of two Linux computers right now
doing an audio podcast,
I'm not really having a lot of audio issues
with these machines.
It really is only under KDE that I ever have problems.
Otherwise I really like pulse audio actually.
Yeah, I used it to as like an RTP source
to play to some other speakers.
Yeah.
And it was two clicks of the config
and it just was playing.
So as an end user,
if you remove Plasma Desktop from the equation,
I actually don't feel like these are legitimate complaints
because they're not,
they don't really impact the end user.
And there are definitely people
who have weird pulse situations,
especially on older districts.
Yeah, Mumble Room, feel free to disagree.
But in my estimation,
this is kind of a non-issue for the average user.
Unless you got three or four sound cards.
Or you need it to not be mixed at the end.
You know, you need direct output to the card.
Then you might have to do some work around.
Yeah.
But for people who just want to listen
to their YouTube video
and have it play at the same time as another sound.
Yeah.
Works great.
We got no disagreement from the lug.
So we move on.
I would say a unified control panel
for all distros of letters would be better.
Yeah, proof of control.
Because.
Proof of control.
Because like there's sometimes when we have issues
staging people and sometimes, you know,
they don't know their own control panel
and you're on a different distro
and then you have to try to find some example.
Yeah, that is.
And it really doesn't help.
Yeah, that is a good point.
That is a good point.
That is kind of a.
Even here on my little Mint laptop
they have a native sound settings.
You know.
Yeah.
Cinnamon.
Which is different than.
Yep.
I like Pava control more.
So that's what I use but.
Yeah, that's a good point.
That is well received.
Okay, so.
And I don't really have a response to it
other than it makes remote support scenarios
a little more difficult.
Right.
This was a point that he made it
almost five times in the article over and over again.
And I'm really curious to see what the mumble room
says about this one.
As he puts it, an insane number of regressions
in the Linux kernel when with every new Linux kernel release
hardware can stop working inexplicitly.
Incomplete drivers, playback regressions on audio,
all kinds of problems.
He points, he pounds this issue
throughout the entire article.
Kernel regressions all the time.
Insane amounts of bugs introduced
with every kernel version.
It really happens.
No, that happens all the time for me.
All the time.
Really, okay.
In what use case scenario are you experiencing
regressions all the time?
Tell me.
Typically the AMD open source driver
because it seems like they rewrite significant parts of it
every single major release.
But that's not really the Linux kernel, right?
That's the driver.
But it's shipped with the kernel, right?
It's the open source driver that ships with the kernel.
It's a module that ships with it.
So are most of the other devices
that he could talk about here.
Okay, all right.
I think he's, by reading this entire article,
I grok he's kind of talking about audio devices.
I almost get the sense that he's an audio engineer
that works with some Linux systems by reading this article
because he gets into the specifics about the bit rates
on Linux audio and stuff that I do kind of agree with.
It seems like you would only know of
unless you professionally work with it.
And so I could see sound devices breaking on him.
I guess I was just surprised
because I pretty much, I am running current Linux kernels
on four out of six machines I use regularly.
And it also seems like another one where,
at least the one you were just reading there,
like if you follow the link,
it's a DataMation article
that has some other people talking about a few.
Yeah, the source is weak.
Hand-picked quotes from some kernel developers.
And it doesn't even talk about regressions
for like the majority of that article.
So I'm willing to believe that there are regressions,
but to say that so strongly
and then not have any sort of like,
what are the numbers?
How many companies are affected by it?
And here's where I think this blog post
goes way down into the weeds
because if you just back up for a second,
you realize that's why there's things like Ubuntu 14.04
that Mint 17.3 that you are running your laptop on
right now is based on.
It is not experiencing these regressions
because this is being managed at the distribution level.
And if you're in the enterprise
where these things really matter,
you're likely running Red Hat Enterprise Linux,
Ubuntu LTS, or CentOS.
You also couldn't afford to have QA teams
that can review these things.
True, but even if you didn't have a single tester
before you just randomly installed a kernel update
on a production machine,
if you're running it in a business scenario,
in most cases, you're using an LTS-style release.
Hell, there's even Arch machines have,
you can have an LTS kernel on an Arch machine.
So this, it feels like a false argument
because if the scenario in which you are so dependent
on the kernel support of your hardware,
that scenario is not one in which you would be
also installing every single kernel update that comes up.
The two just things are completely incongruent.
It doesn't match up.
No, I don't think so.
I think you should be able to expect Upstream
does a decent job testing the software they write.
You shouldn't have to rely on a distribution
to test all your software.
You shouldn't rely on Red Hat to test that the kernel works.
I agree.
Because I've had a lot of esoteric hardware
where it just does not work correctly with a major update.
And I mean, even on point releases, they break things
like the ButterFS bug that they introduced
in like 3.19.1 or something that wasn't even in 3.19.0.
Yeah, but my point is that these things do happen.
It is a reality.
And anybody that is administering these systems
is aware of the reality because these are people
that their jobs are on the line for managing these systems.
And so they have to work in the reality
of the context of the situation.
So they're not deploying these kernel updates
on these massively critical machines.
It's just not something that's commonly done.
It's not a shortcoming, right?
It sucks when you're going to test these things
and you have to weed through all these weird issues
in your lab. I agree.
I agree. It sucks.
It's one of the main points of his articles
as the drawback to Linux.
I don't think it's a drawback because the fundamental way
that Linux is deployed and distributed
is essentially built to mitigate these potential issues.
No, I don't think it's a drawback,
but I think it's something that needs to be worked on
because I don't think they do enough regression testing.
And I think it can be a lot better.
Yeah, I know.
I agree there too.
But the thing is, that is...
Well, I mean...
I guess that's what I was saying
is that there's a lot of nuance there
that is covered in that point.
Well, maybe instead of funding a blockchain replacement,
they should be funding more kernel testing
over at the Linux Foundation.
And there's the Hacker News article,
our discussion, which maybe we should link to.
They have some good discussions
about what current test frameworks are used by the kernel
and what they do.
Anything to jump out at you?
I just remember seeing a lot of the...
Because that Hacker News thread
seemed overly hostile to me.
There are some hostile sentiments in there for sure.
There's some nice ones too, but yeah,
it was just like a whole bunch of people
like, yeah, that's why I switched to the Mac.
And I was like, I don't want to read that.
Just, it's getting disappointing.
And you know what?
They're all gonna come back.
They're all, they'll all be back.
The Mac is...
They switch to the Mac,
but they find they have the same regressions, right?
Like I think I updated to a minor point release
on Yosemite or something,
and my Wi-Fi driver broke pretty horribly.
This Mac, this...
And this is their hardware.
This expensive Mac Pro,
that is not the trashcan model,
but it was the last one they released before the trashcan.
Right.
It's actually a decent desktop.
Big metal.
Kind of sexy.
The one that actually has PCI Express slots
that you can use and stuff and drive slides.
It's kernel panic before the last two Linux unplugs.
Maybe it's when I come over.
Alls I'm saying is,
anybody who actually uses Mac OS X
under production load,
where your CPUs are running at higher than 70%
for more than say 90% of the machine's day,
anybody who uses a Mac under those conditions
knows that it is one of the weakest
operating systems out there.
It eats itself constantly.
It has one of the worst file systems
in the history of desktop computing.
And on top of all of that,
the expensive hardware has such a premium around it
that all of the accessory manufacturers
also get to add a premium
to hook crap up to these expensive machines.
It is infuriating.
The Mac platform,
this is what gets me about this hacker news thread,
and we should link to it now that I'm ranting about this.
You can go read it and see why I'm ranting about this.
The arrogance of these people,
the supposed superiority of their operating system,
it makes me laugh because it is all about
what the different work cases
and how there's just simply some tools
that work for some people better
and other tools that work for other people better.
And that's really what it comes down to.
And when you read this guy's article,
every single one of these issues that we highlighted here
is a use case that is edge.
And there are legitimate ones like Xorg allows applications
to exclusively grab keyboard and mouse input.
If such applications misbehave,
you're left with a system you cannot manage.
A lot of us have experienced this at some point or another.
But again, it is an edge use case.
And so when I read these things, I read these rants,
I just, I walk away from something that doesn't feel
productive, it feels more,
it feels more nitpicky for nitpick's sake.
What I would like to see from this article in 2017
is a refinement of what we argue about.
Because there are issues in here that, in my case,
are worth highlighting.
Like I've run into this one.
In most cases, kernel crashes are invisible
if you're running an X session.
Moreover, KMS prevents the kernel from switching
to plain 640 by 480 or 80 by 25 text in VGA mode
to give you an error message.
Because KMS is all locked up.
Very incomplete hardware support for sensors, too.
Yeah, I've seen that.
You know, you might have a machine on a modern laptop
that has 50 sensors.
And HWinfo is only detecting maybe 20 of them,
maybe 12 of them.
It's a weak point of Linux.
Power management.
This isn't in his article, but Feronix took a look
at power management for Linux.
For 2014 versus 2015.
And we are worse at power management at the end of 2015
than we were at the end of 2014.
We use more battery power.
So there are obvious areas.
But what he ends up doing is nitpicking in a way
that feels unproductive and also so esoteric and specific
that it doesn't feel like there's any action
that we can take on these.
And I think part of it, too, is where it lacks context.
Like with the regressions.
Like, regressions are bad, but how do the rates
of the Linux kernel versus other kernels
that are updated as much, that make as much project,
that support as much new hardware as that does.
Sure, that's a great question.
Yeah, yeah, and almost in all of these,
through this whole thing, I have to resist the urge to say,
well, but Windows does it this way.
Well, but the Mac does it this way.
Because there's nothing perfect out there.
Not at all.
And I think we could all agree that no desktop is perfect.
And basically, whatever desktop you spend the most time on
sucks.
And I think this just needs a little bit more context
so that we, like, a lot of those are completely legitimate
points that should be fixed.
But we have limited work, you know, hours.
And so I think that maybe this article needs a little bit
context of which are the most important,
which one of these should we really be pushing towards
in the next year.
That would be more helpful.
And also, it also needs to not be so contradictory
at the top of the article he bangs on about
not bringing Android into the equation.
Right.
Then winds on about how Android UI becomes unresponsive
if you do certain IO intensive operations.
Good point.
It's like, okay, well, you can't say,
you can't talk about Android as a plus point
and then draw on it as, by the way, Android.
Yeah, that's nuts.
There's another interesting one in here.
I quite like this one, which I agree with.
Xorg is largely outdated, unsuitable,
and even terribly insecure for modern PCs and applications.
And you could change one word in that sentence.
Windows is largely outdated, unsuitable,
and even terribly insecure for modern PCs and applications.
That's true.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Yeah, you could also say the same about-
That's comparing the display server
with fundamentals of the operating system design.
You could also say that about Mac OS X.
Somebody just ran the numbers, right?
And in 2015, the Mac OS X had the most vulnerabilities
out of any desktop operating system.
Now, sure, some of that was open source packages.
Some of it wasn't.
But you can pick and choose this data any way you want.
You could then say the Mac OS
was the most insecure operating system of 2015.
It'd be kind of be a bullshit statement,
but you could say that based on the data.
You could say Xorg's architecture is inherently insecure.
You could also claim that Windows architecture
is inherently insecure.
Yeah, that's a great point, Wimpy.
Did anybody else in the Mamba Room
have any points they wanted to make from this article
before we wrap up?
And we'll have the full thing linked in the show notes
if you guys at home want to read it.
Can we not do this one next year?
Maybe not, you know?
I kind of like, the thing I like doing is,
the reason why I like covering it
is this article manages to get quite a bit of traction
online and every year it's gotten more and it's less-
Don't you think that's his agenda though?
Don't you think he just loves trolling the Linux community?
I mean, some of the hyperlinks in this article
are links to bugs that he's raised on the LKML
and have been closed and then he reopens every year
and he's beginning to wind up people with every year
these things being reopened.
So some of his citations are his own bullshit bugs.
See, this is the inevitable problem,
is as this gets more attention,
it almost feels like we are ignoring it
if we don't respond to it because essentially,
the way it is written and structured,
that almost just gives it credibility
right there unfortunately.
Like when you read something like this online
and then you see something that's sourced like this,
you don't even start clicking links,
you go, oh, this guy's really sourced his stuff,
he really knows what he's talking about.
And so it generates a 100-common deep hacker news thread
that's an entire attack on Linux, right?
And it gets linked all over the hell over Twitter
and Reddit and Facebook and it starts generating this buzz
of this is why it's still not the year of the desktop Linux
and then that's the headline that runs it.
It's not the year of the desktop Linux,
it's got all of these issues and I just feel like...
And it really hits that crowd of people too
who use Linux on the server,
but just don't think that they can use it on the desktop.
And I feel like that rubs at least me
and some people in our community just like...
So I kind of feel like it is sort of our duty
to sort of respond to it and say, no, no,
this guy's blowing some of these things out of proportion,
he's citing himself as Wimpy just pointed out,
he's citing datamation articles
that kind of refer to regressions in the Linux kernel
and some of these are extremely niche use cases
that don't affect regular day-to-day users,
which he's supposedly writing this for.
So I think that's worth mentioning.
I don't want to give it necessarily any more credibility
than it deserves though.
So I don't, like we didn't cover it in last as news,
for example, you know, just as we almost did
and I thought, eh, we had a discussion behind the scenes
about running it as news in the Linux action show
and we decided that this is more of something
we feel like as a community we should respond to
in Unplugged and so we moved it down to the Unplugged show
in the sense of, not to demote the status of it,
but just to recognize what it really is.
Right.
It's really kind of a conversation piece.
I actually feel like it's a more honest Linux sucks.
Blaster Sissy feels like it's a less honest,
I feel like it's a more because it is at least,
it is appropriately updated and it is also cited,
which is really nice.
Yeah, there's a difference.
The siting often is himself or the animation articles,
but the siting is done.
So it seems like it's sort of, it's a different spin
on that sort of this is what's wrong
and that's what plays well on the internet.
Right.
And I think.
I think it's at all ironic that that website
is running on Linux.
Well, the guy obviously uses Linux, right?
I mean, you read the article,
the guy obviously is a Linux user, that's the thing.
And so these continue to generate discussion
and he managed this year and last year
to get a hell of a lot of traffic to discuss it.
So yeah, I find it to be fascinating.
I find it to be fascinating because it is like,
geeks can argue about this kind of thing forever.
The edge cases are, I guess, where all of the discussion is.
And it's a lot of work, but you find these articles,
it really gets your blood boiling
and you know you're engaged and it's like,
you have to put in some thought,
like why is that so wrong?
Well, like the stuff, like I think his PowerPoint,
or his PowerPoint, I think his PowerPoints were really,
where he goes into Xorg.
Right.
That is kind of Xorg.
We all acknowledge that.
Yeah, and then at the same time we all know
we've got our solutions in the works too, so.
And he harps on Flash.
Right.
It is kind of getting tiring, actually,
now that I think about it.
It is, the whole thing is just getting kind of old.
And it's getting less and less relevant
as the strategy tax of the big platforms
becomes more and more apparent on the Mac and Windows.
Right.
So yeah, maybe next year we don't cover it.
I don't know.
Let's hope we don't even have to.
Yeah, it does feel like it's sort of,
it does feel like it's something of a bygone era.
I'll tell you what's not of a bygone era,
that's our friends over at DigitalOcean.
Head over to DigitalOcean.com
and get yourself a Linux rig up on their awesome servers,
all running KVM, sitting on top of Linux boxes
with SSD drives, 40 gigabit E connectors,
and guess what, a $10 promo code
when you use DO Unplugged, one word, lowercase.
One word, lowercase, that'll get you hooked up
over at DigitalOcean for two months
to try out their $5 rig.
You can get started in less than 55 seconds.
And at $5 a month, you get 512 megabytes of RAM,
a 20 gigabyte SSD, one CPU, and a terabyte.
Did you see my old terabyte dance I just did there?
That was a beautiful dance.
That's my terabyte transfer dance.
That's a big deal.
Do the terabyte transfer.
There you go, I just did it again.
You get a terabyte of transfer with a $5 rig,
it just, I just don't even.
That's insane.
That's great, I just, as somebody who used to have
to do coload servers, I just, that really blows my mind.
And they got data center locations in New York,
San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam, London,
Germany, and Toronto, so you can go have your server
chill with Alan Jude.
Hey hey.
Yeah, Netflix and chill with Alan Jude.
That's what I hear you do up in Toronto.
They have a great interface, it's very simple and intuitive.
And that's kind of my nice way of saying it's better
than any other virtualization management platform.
Way, way better than anything VMware could ever dream of,
which is pathetic.
It is really good.
It's better than any other service provider out there.
And then to just sort of put a little sprinkling
on top of that tasty muffin.
You know, because muffins with sprinkles are better.
Ooh, they are.
Just ask my five-year-old.
They gave you a great API.
Really straightforward.
They've just recently updated it, well not,
they updated it last year now, because this is 2016.
That allows you to replicate the functionality
of the control panel on a larger scale.
And so there's a bunch of really nice open source code
written around that API to manage droplets.
It's nice.
They got an HTML5 dashboard, so you can see it
from boot all the way up to login.
It's a great system.
Digitalocean.com.
Use the promo code DOUNPLUG, get $10 credit.
Also, go check out their documentation
and their one-click deployment.
You got Ubuntu, CentOS, Debian, Fedora, CoreOS, FreeBizzle.
Is that what I see?
FreeBSD right in the corner there?
Yeah, yeah, that Alan Jude.
That Alan, he's a campaigner.
He's a campaigner.
Let's see what we've got him,
because it's running under KVM.
Yeah, that's true.
That's true.
Oh, that gives me a nice jolly.
You can also deploy applications with a single click.
They use DoCo in the background.
They're big fans at Docker.
They work upstream with the projects.
It's pretty good.
Digitalocean.com.
Use the promo code DOUNPLUG.
And a big thank you to Digitalocean
for sponsoring the Unplugged program.
And thanks, you guys out there, for keeping the show going
into 2016, and keep us going.
Everyone get more droplets for 2016.
DOUNPLUGED.
All right, so in episode 3, Hyundai,
and 45 of the Linux Action Show,
I busted out my predictions.
Now, traditionally, in the big show,
what we do is we own up to our predictions from last year,
and we make our new predictions.
But since we had a host change up from Matt to Noah,
I decided it wasn't really fair
to make Noah own up to Matt's predictions, and vice versa.
That would have been funny, though.
What I did is I pulled out a few of my predictions,
and I'm gonna own up to them in this episode.
We start with a clean slate on last week,
and then we'll do this own up thing in next year.
I'm watching this, you know what?
I came away realizing I didn't like
the way I did this format last time.
It really sucks to watch yourself,
and then be like, you know what?
I don't like the way I did that.
So having watched this again, I decided
I probably wouldn't do the format like this.
So now I'm gonna, now I know, now I know.
You know what I mean?
Like, going forward, I'm gonna do this right.
But what I will do here is I'm gonna play,
I pulled out one, two, three, four predictions
that I made, and I'm gonna see how I did.
And I'll link to the full episode
if you wanna watch all of them.
But I wanna start with this one
that I think I got half right.
I kinda made the mistake of making
like two predictions in one here,
but I'm gonna play it for you.
And this is about Debian, and how I thought
that in 2015 they'd have a new feature come to Debian
that would be a big hit.
Hold on, that was my cue, but then I don't hear nothing.
I hear nothing, hold on.
See, Debian come up with a PPA-like solution for 2015.
You know, like, honestly, one of the reasons
I will go with Ubuntu over Debian is for PPAs.
Yeah, yeah, but I would like them
to not just, you know, carve and copy the concept.
Because it's not a great system.
It's not, I mean, even with PPA Manager,
while that, god, that's a huge help,
it's more of a Pac-Man-like situation would be ideal.
I would love, so obviously the Debian PPA thing,
that didn't work out.
That didn't happen.
I thought for sure it would, too.
And then there was even discussions in the mailing list
about implementing a PPA-like system.
Yeah, there was a lot of news about it.
It got close, my prediction got real close.
But it didn't quite work out.
And then I kinda threw in like this other prediction.
Love, love to see more distros work
with the openSUSE build service in 2015.
That would be cool.
Although, open, yeah, it's a good idea,
but their stuff is-
It's not gonna happen, is it?
There's still misses stuff.
When I tried using it in the past,
it does still miss some things.
So, yeah, it's the right idea.
I wanna put a stake in the ground right here.
My prediction for openSUSE build service
and for Copper is more of the same.
And I think that was kind of true.
I mean, they grew more, but it was just sort of more steady,
more of the same.
Nothing really broke through as like a big,
like, oh, we're switching over to this.
You think I kinda got that one, that last part right?
I definitely didn't get the PPA thing right.
Unfortunately, no.
But the, yeah, I mean, I do think at least marginally more
are using the build service.
It's a great resource.
I wish that more people would use it.
I hope that's another repeat, let's just say.
I hope that continues.
All right, so then I made a prediction about Docker
and how it might affect the Linux action show.
I think containers will continue to see huge adoption.
It's gonna blow up.
Docker's gonna do great.
Rocket's gonna do great.
We're gonna come up with a lot of great new uses.
You're gonna see probably your humble host
here on the Linux action show say,
here is a project, it's super cool,
and you can do it in a container
on your distribution right now.
And we'll stop saying things like,
this only works on Ubuntu.
This only works on SUSE.
This only works on Arch.
That is gonna go away a little bit towards, but...
So you know what?
And it did kind of work out that way.
Not completely as I thought,
but I know off the top of my head,
we talked about Smokeping and MB last year
that at the end of the episode were like,
all right, go get this Docker container
and you can use it.
It came up a couple of times.
But I saw you kind of go iffy.
What was that iffy on, do you think?
Oh, just don't know.
I feel like Rocket from CoreOS.
Oh yeah.
It's not delivered as much as...
Yeah, you're right.
It really hasn't, has it?
Rocket hasn't been like huge.
It's, yeah.
They're there.
I mean, I appreciate it.
I like CoreOS, but...
Yeah, yeah.
Pocket Casey points out that ownCloud
is using the openSUSE build service.
In fact, I was gonna talk about that today in the episode.
I just forgot.
MB was for a while.
Yeah, Joss Blog is like,
don't use your native distro repo packages.
You know, use the build service packages.
So there's been some movement there,
but I just attribute it at the same steady pace.
I don't think the openSUSE build service
or Copper has had a breakout.
Like when I install Fedora,
I still find Copper not nearly competitive at all
with the AUR.
And that's kind of my benchmark for both those things.
All right.
So I have one I'm saving towards the end,
but I got one more.
And I'm curious, I think this one is iffy.
I wanna know what you think, Wes.
I made a prediction about freeBSD
kicking Linux in the bools.
Is in large scale production, enterprise grade.
People are gonna look at the Linux stack as a whole
and look at virtualization.
They're gonna look at containerization
and they're gonna look at the file system.
And I predict that Linux over 2015
will lose a lot of installations to freeBSD.
I think 2015 will be the year
that the Linux community recognizes the amount of heat
that the freeBSD project
and all of the people around freeBSD are bringing.
So I was supposing that freeBSD
would see a lot more market adoption.
I don't know how to measure that now in looking back at it,
but it does seem like a lot more VPS providers
have started offering freeBSD.
Free NAS has gotten a lot more mindshare
and a lot more market.
Noah just shared a story on Linux Action Show this Sunday
about a client that wasn't even willing
to consider Linux anymore.
They wanted free NAS and CFS.
So what do you think?
Do you think?
I think a lot of the system D stuff,
I think there's a certain set of,
well, on the Linux side,
I think some of the system D fallout,
there have been more Linux power users
who have been exploring freeBSD.
I think it still is the king
in terms of easy, open source, secure data storage.
But I'm not sure.
I know from our emails that come into TechSnap,
a lot of people have been switching in our audience.
So I know, and the BSD Now show
has grown a ton in the last year.
The BSD Now show really grew a lot last year.
It was a big year for the BSD Now show.
So yeah, I kind of think that did actually happen.
If I go by those metrics.
I think it does deserve to be recognized
because freeBSD is a great open source project.
I don't know, I feel like it deserves more recognition
in the container space for jails.
And I feel like there's the privileged admins
and developers who do use it.
But I feel like there's been so much further hype
in the Linux community that that shift has not happened.
Go ahead, Ryan.
So I'm not really sure that even though there
is a lot of interest in BSD, and especially
among those who are really technical
and like to explore this technology as far as they can
and be kind of on the cutting edge,
I think that we have to ask, at what expense?
Is it at Linux's expense?
No, I mean, Linux may be losing these users,
but many are coming to take their place.
That's a great way to put it.
There's so much momentum behind Linux and people
that want to be creators and people that
want to be on the cutting edge.
There's so much momentum there that it's
a drop in the bucket, right?
Yeah, and I was just going to say,
I got the opportunity to talk to somebody who works for one
of my former employers.
And when I worked there, it was completely a Microsoft shop.
They were a Microsoft Platinum partner,
whatever the highest was, and they would not really
deploy anything.
I maintained three Linux servers that I
had to beg to get in there.
And I just had a conversation with one of the guys who
works there, and now they have OpenStack deployed.
It's pretty much all Linux where Windows was king before.
And so I think about that, and I think,
yeah, people might be moving over to BSD
to try some of these technologies
that they're interested in.
But there are so many people continuing
to come to Linux because it's becoming the de facto.
The part that jumps out at me at the prediction
is at the end there I said, by the end of 2015,
we're going to recognize the heat that FreeBSD is bringing.
And I think now if you look back at canonical preemptively
announcing planned support for ZFS,
I think that is sort of a recognition of the demand
for some of the feature set there.
Wimpy, you say more it's like you see FreeBSD going in
for specific tasks, not really replacing Linux,
but more like complementing it.
Tell me more about that.
Yeah, well, yes, replacing Linux, but not entirely.
So the things that I do, I've been deploying
PFSense for firewalls because if you're
going for a full-on open source solution, in my opinion,
there isn't a Linux-based firewall that
can compete with PFSense.
And in terms of doing big file servers,
if you're not doing clustered storage like Ceph or GlusterFS,
then ZFS is really the only game in town
unless you really pay through the nose from something
from EMC, for example.
So I've been deploying BSD in those scenarios for file
servers and for firewalls, but the rest of the Linux
infrastructure has remained.
So all of the big compute and data science stuff
still runs on Linux.
It's now just using TrueNAS in this case, or FreeNAS.
As the back end.
And ZFS as the back end, and then PF in front of it all.
But I think you're right.
I think with Ubuntu adopting ZFS in 16.04,
and also some of the Debian derivatives,
so Open Media Vault, for example, where ZFS is now
an option, I think you were right in your predictions
that this year is the year that Linux is going
to sort of embrace ZFS, and ZFS will
be the future of enterprise scale storage on Linux.
And then you can layer all of the clustering file
systems on top of that.
So don't go away, because this last prediction,
I think I kind of got it right.
And I think what I got wrong was Ubuntu Mate edition
wasn't at the forefront of my vocabulary at the time.
But it's essentially, I think, what
I was trying to say in my last prediction for 2015.
Right.
Here's what I think.
I think 2015 will be the year that the bet that Mint took
with their multi-year release, and that Ubuntu is taking
with the let's not focus on a Unity 7,
let's just make it better.
I think 2015 is the year that that check is due.
Like that payment needs to be made.
And 2015 is going to come along.
And I'm not trying to brag, but guys
like me on Arch, and Gnome 3, and the rolling releases,
like KDE 5, SUSE Tumbleweed, Fedora,
we are going to have such awesome desktops that's
so much far and above what the commercial competitors are
going to do, that I suspect that where Linux's genuine gains are
is in that geek, that enthusiast.
That when we did how-to Linux in 2014,
and Chase was sort of like the ideal Windows switcher.
He was a Windows power user.
He liked to tweak Windows.
He was ready to do more.
And what he found was, those old desktops
were not very appealing to him.
They weren't customizable enough.
They weren't new enough.
And I think in reality, you have more people switching
to Linux that are savvy than you do that new mythical user.
Over 2015, I think it's still going to be more of us,
more geeks, more enthusiasts switching to Linux.
And because of that, I think things like Plasma 5 and Gnome
3 will be way better received, because you're
getting a modern experience, you can still customize it.
You don't feel like you're taking a step back.
But I think in terms of raw numbers and organic adoption,
things like the Matei project or Trinity,
other classic desktop paradigms, I
think that's where the most growth will happen.
I think a lot of it's still going to be Ubuntu-based.
Last year, I thought it was going to be Arch-based.
I think this year it's going to be Ubuntu-based.
Maybe I'll be wrong.
Maybe it's going to be Fedora-based.
I think a lot of it's going to be traditional Matei edition
style, Ubuntu-based growth.
But I think for power users, enthusiasts,
the people that are watching this show, those of us who
work in IT, those of us who are just like Windows power users
that are switching to something else.
I would agree.
We're going to look for the more modern stuff.
And a lot of the power user growth is going to happen there.
So I think I got it right.
The base usage growth, the granite growth,
was in the Ubuntu Matei.
And then people had to go with the Raspberry Pi grabbing
the Ubuntu Matei edition.
And then the people with powerful computers,
more of us adopted Plasma 5 and Gnome 3 this year.
That's sort of the long version of,
that's a short version of a long thing I just said.
But I think, I don't know, Wimpy,
your thoughts being Mr. Ubuntu Matei over there?
What do you think?
I don't know.
I know.
It was a long way to get to it, watching that back.
But I think essentially, it seems like Ubuntu Matei really,
really came into its own in 2015.
It really became recognized.
It existed in 2014.
But 2015, I mean, it became a serious contender.
April, when the official version came,
the official, when it became part of the Ubuntu family,
that really did jump on quite considerably.
Things have calmed down a bit now.
People are used to the fact that it's there
and it's part of the furniture.
So it's a bit more calm.
I don't really know how to gauge,
because I've got no insight to how popular
the other distributions are.
I'm just pleased that I've made something
that's so many people.
And there are a lot of people that are downloading it.
Yeah, but you can just tell, as somebody
who's been in the Linux community for a while,
when a distribution moves up to the forefront
and sort of gains mindshare.
And yours has very quickly.
Yeah.
Yeah, maybe.
I think, yes, it's clearly popular.
I can't gauge how popular exactly versus the others.
That's very difficult to do.
But generally, there's a lot of interest
around it, and that's very pleasing for me.
You know, it started off as a bit of fun,
and it's become a bit more than that.
But yeah, it's been a very enjoyable journey
and I'll make it continue.
Now, Ryan is a crazy SOB, and he thinks
that those blokes over at Canonical
are going to actually make an Ubuntu vanilla desktop that's
going to get all the buzz.
Ryan, share your wisdom with me.
So as somebody who spent a considerable amount of time
using the Ubuntu phone here in the last,
I don't know, probably month and a half,
and just played around with Unity 8 a bit,
I got to say that if the desktop, Unity 8 desktop,
doesn't make a big splash, then the apps
that the community has created for that desktop that
seem to fit in so well in that desktop
and scale as your screen size does, that I think
will swing the pendulum back the other way.
Because if you think about it, the Unity 7
was just really iterative, almost for the past like two
years.
You know, it's just been bug fixes and the occasional,
I would consider, minor feature.
And I'm sure somebody could debate me on that.
But especially this year, it kind of,
it just kind of polished and fixed bugs.
And I was using Gnome 3 quite a lot
until I played around with the Ubuntu phone
and then Unity 8 some.
And I realized that they've actually
got something really interesting there.
And if I were going to predict, I
would say that there's going to be some renewed interest when
they really push that to the forefront.
So is this an official Ryan prediction for 2016?
Because we've been writing it down.
I'm willing to put my stamp on that.
I've got another one if I can share it.
Yeah, go ahead.
So I've been saying this forever.
And I know I'm sure Canonical doesn't like this
when I spread these rumors.
But I really think that we will see
some Canonical partnerships.
And I don't have any privileged information or anything.
But I just think that I was looking
at the stats of their cloud, how many deployments Ubuntu
has in the cloud.
And I don't feel like somebody who has so many,
even on their competitors, like, well, not really,
they would say not a competitor.
But Azure, on the Microsoft platform,
they have significant market share.
I don't think that's a play.
I think what you want about Canonical,
but that's not something they can ignore,
these companies like Amazon and Microsoft.
And so I would be really interested to see
what happens with that company, Canonical,
and their partnerships with these traditional big players
in that space.
So this Sunday on the Linux Action Show,
we're doing what we wish happens in 2016.
And one of my wishes, and I'll just give one of them away,
I guess, is my wish is that Ubuntu's adoption
in these cloud platforms encourages a desktop adoption
after Unity 8 stabilizes, like Unity 8.5, Unity 8.7,
something like that, is I really hope that.
Can I?
Go ahead.
Sorry, go ahead.
No, I was just going to say, the thing that I think about
is this year, it wasn't just Ubuntu, but people who,
and we talk about the year of the Linux desktop every year.
And I'm not saying it's the year of the Linux desktop,
but the barriers to get there, every year,
I think it's impossible for it to drop down again.
I think this Linux, the desktop is
going to remain this niche thing.
And we've kind of got the users we're going to have.
And it's just going to be the tinkerers, the hackers,
and the really explorative, curious power users.
But then something like Steam drops, or even more
applications go to the web, or somebody implements,
for instance, I've got Spotify on my Linux rig.
And each time one of these things happen,
somebody else can be talking to me.
A new category of user can move over, yeah.
Exactly.
Months ago, I put my lay friend on the Ubuntu Mate desktop.
And really, Spotify was probably the final app
that made it doable.
Not a single functionality or feature
is missing anymore for her.
Not a single thing.
There's nothing that she needs her computer for
that the Ubuntu Mate desktop is not providing.
And maybe a stable Unity 8 could provide something
of the reference platform that Ubuntu kind of already is,
but in better form.
I like it, Ryan.
It's good stuff.
I talked about this at System76, but I have a Yoga 2 laptop
that I take around with me.
And Unity 8 would be so cool if, when
I flip it back to tablet mode right now,
it just kills the keyboard and switches
to pulling up the online keyboard, which is fine.
It allows me to just sit there and read a web page
or something.
But wouldn't it be so cool, since they
have the tablet interface and the phone interface
versus the desktop interface, if, when I did that,
it actually switched to a complete touch-centric experience?
Because when I want to read, I want
to just be able to flip through the stuff with my hands,
sitting there relaxed on the couch or whatever.
And consolidating that device seems pretty nice,
because I have all my files, and I
wouldn't be using some kind of sync service to go to tablet.
I agree.
That's the dream.
That's the dream, Ryan.
And then you tie it all together with a little Mycroft here
and there.
And boy, that's a happy world after all.
Yeah, then I don't even have to touch it anymore.
I can just say things to it.
Yeah, yeah, I love it.
I love the fact that you're talking about the opposite way
that whenever we talk about convergence at Canonica,
we talk about how you take a phone out of your pocket,
and you plug your keyboard and mouse,
and it turns into a desktop.
You want to go the other way.
You want to take a desktop and turn it into a tablet.
Oh, for me too, yeah.
It should be able to do both of those.
Yeah, I would say I fall in that category too.
That's exactly how I think about it.
Well, guys, I look forward to seeing both of you at Scale.
Don't forget, if you're curious about Scale,
we got links in the show notes.
We also got links to all the Mycroft stuff that's
going on, including the Indiegogo campaign
and the community.
As well, we have links to that episode of the Linux Action
Show if you want to see all of the predictions of Matt
and mine.
It's a whole bunch of stuff in the show notes this week.
A whole bunch of stuff.
Don't miss it.
That's right.
And you know, you could be here live to take in all of it
and actually get even more show.
You get some of it.
Way more show.
We could include some of it, but not all of it,
especially the really dirty parts.
What?
Whoa.
Let's just say pants were involved.
Yes.
All right.
So that brings us to the end of this week's episode
of Linux Unplugged.
We do this live on Tuesdays over at jblive.tv.
Go to jubilabroadcasting.com slash calendar
to get that in your local time zone.
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com for topics and feedback
into this here show.
I'd love to get your feedback there.
And of course, join us live next week
so you can be in the Mumble Room and take
part of our virtual lug.
Thanks so much for tuning in.
We'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
Good day.
Now we're all done.
I think it's time for a little Mycroft and Chili.
We can just do this.
That's a good show.
Thank you, everybody, for making it out.
That was an awesome show, guys.
Did you see my BSD and Chill image?
Yeah, I did.
That's perfect.
Yeah, that's great.
BSD and Chill.
I guess it's like now that I did
the whole, now that I totally didn't
get the whole Netflix and Chill reference,
now I'm seeing even Ted Cruz is making references
to Netflix and Chill.
I am an old man when Ted Cruz has got a meme faster
than I do.
All right, jbtitles.com.
Let's go vote.
Speaking of which, my wife is actually chilling here.
I had the headphones unplugged for a little bit,
and she was listening to you.
What'd she think?
She liked the show?
And hold on.
Java with Gnome Phone was kind of good.
Oh, right, titles.
Minecraft Action Show, that's not bad.
Master Clickbaiting, that's good, too.
Here she is.
I'm going to let her tell you in her own words.
Hello, Ryan's wife.
Hello.
Ryan, hello.
What's your name?
Hello.
Hi.
Misha.
So what'd you think of the show today?
I actually didn't hear the show today.
I was working.
But I actually hear your various shows quite often
because Ryan listens while he's in the shower
and has it over a big speaker.
How considerate.
That's nice.
That's good.
Yes.
So I stay quite informed on Linux news.
Oh, good.
I listen in my fortress of solitude.
Right.
So while you're having shower thoughts, I understand.
That's pretty good.
Yeah, it's the best time.
All right, so give me your feedback.
This is your chance to give me any feedback, any improvements
you'd like me to make.
Go ahead.
I'll note them down right here.
I got a piece of paper.
Oh, OK.
OK.
Maybe more, I don't know.
I don't know.
Really?
I guess that's good.
Something complementary.
Yeah, something involving magic would be great.
More magic.
OK, I'll write magic.
Yeah.
All right, magic and sparkles.
Yeah, OK, I got this.
Purple elephants.
Purple.
OK, these are all things I can work on.
Purple elephants.
Good.
OK, thank you.
Yeah.
That's solid feedback.
The thing that I wonder about, Chris,
because she gets to listen to you on Linux Action Show,
Linux Unplugged, and Coder Radio mostly.
My question is, I know you have the women's,
I'm blanking on the name, but I have the Women's Tech Radio.
And I'm curious, do you know how much of your audience
as maybe a percentage or as a number is women?
Do you have any idea on that?
I don't think I have any current numbers,
but I don't think it's a huge, I don't think it's more than about 6%
or 7%, but I'm not sure.
And how many of them are forced to listen
by their showering husbands?
Yeah.
I'm going to have to try that.
Do those count?
Maybe that could be a new marketing approach.
Spread the word via the shower.
Get those, tell those sponsors, if you're trying
to hit this demographic, women who are forced to listen
to their husband's podcast, then you never know.
We could have Ting, and then we could have, I don't know,
what's a brand that wouldn't offend every woman that
listens to this, if I said it?
I feel like I could focus on shower-related products, too.
That could be a new category.
I could focus on soap.
Yeah, oh, yeah.
It's a video show, just chest up, Chris showering,
shampooing his hair.
No more.
No more shower talk.
Actually, I would like to know what hair products he uses.
He says he doesn't.
Cut you guys off.
This is ridiculous.
This is Washington water.
End of discussion right there.
End of discussion.
Just had my first day at my new job today, and I'm super excited.
Oh, congratulations.
How did it go?
Yeah, great.
Like-minded people.
Fabulous.
All the right things.
Lots of Debian, lots of Ubuntu, lots of open source.
Yeah, really?
That sounds wonderful.
So are you saying Ubuntu and Debian on the desktop?
What are you saying?
I'm saying Debian for server infrastructure and Ubuntu on the desktop.
Nice.
Mm-hmm.
Get in.
Get in?
What the heck?
That's such an old man thing to say.
No, it's not.
It's a very British thing to say.
Oh, okay.
It sounds old.
Yeah.