The heck does this really mean Netflix at Netflix tweets to the 53 people who have watched A Christmas Prince
every day for the past 18 days who hurt you and
And then people are like Netflix. Why are you watching me and Netflix responds with well? We just care about you
We're just worried about you and like Netflix has been outing people's crazy watching habits over Twitter for the last couple of days
Have you seen this? It's bizarre. I like it though. It is good. It's like it's funny
But then it's also a reminder how these hosted platforms are constantly monitoring everything we do and even when I like them
It's still a little gentle reminder every time you hit that play button. They know you're watching someone is silently judging you
My buddy, but I'm gonna be at the same time exactly exactly
My buddy got hit with it. They checked in on him
Really?
Yeah, he binge watched. I can't even remember what it was but nutshell he binge watched like eight
Seasons of something within like four days or and they're just like oh your patterns look different. Are you good?
You know what? I heard from somebody else
This is not the first time I've heard the story that and the person was legitimately depressed and they were in a funk and they watched
They watched like a whole bunch of shows back-to-back-to-back-to-back and Netflix support emailed them and asked them if they were okay Wow
Netflix is kind of a crazy company. That's really crazy
I mean, it's good that somebody cares right even if it's just some anonymous support person at Netflix. It's nice that somebody cares at the
Stock you right?
Like do they have like some sort of dashboard where they're like somebody's having a bad day like alert comes up
It's probably a piracy thing. It's probably like a somebody is downloading a whole bunch of content off our servers
Let's flag them and then they look at it go. No, it looks legit. They're just depressed. Yeah
Oh, yeah, but that's their job. All they're doing now is watching Netflix. Oh, gosh
This is Linux unplugged episode
227 for December 12 2017
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show
That is so fired up about today's episode it might just strike a little too close to home. My name is Chris
My name is Wes. Hello, mr. Wes today on the show. We're gonna tackle a few big topics
first we'll bust through some community news things you need to know about and
I'm not gonna lie the system to you debate rages on still
This time you're never died
Your humble hosts are taking a flamethrower to the idiots that won't stop this once and for all
We're going to take a flamethrower to this particular discussion and then let's get in to replacing YouTube
Let's get in to replacing patreon. Let's get in to replacing Twitter. That's right on this week's episode
We're going to attack
centralized platforms and services and tell you how it's nearly
Within your grasp to replace all of these with p2p
Decentralized no single point of failure or control systems. The internet is falling apart
And there's been a couple of things that have happened just this last week
That honestly as a Linux user
Get a little like throw up in my throat, you know
Like we need to throw up a little bit and you gotta swallow it down. You're like, hmm. That was horrible
Yeah, that's how these things make me feel. I've been throwing up in my throat all week
Okay, well proverbial not really the proverbial throw up in my throat
I'll tell you why and we'll bust through all of this and the solutions that are emerging that are all open source
They're all peer-to-peer and that are all decentralized. How about that?
So it's not quite there yet, but who better than Linux users to push this crap over the edge speaking of Linux users
Let's bring in our virtual lug time appropriate greetings mobile room
Hello
Hey, oh, hey. Hey. Oh everybody. Thank you for joining me. I know everybody's busy as the
Freaking holidays approach and I appreciate everybody taking a moment of their busy day to join us in the lug
It's nice. It just wouldn't be the same without you. It wouldn't the beards not here this week. I should mention lonely
We need you mumble room. He sends his regrets, but he's out on assignment assignment being moving. Yeah, which
Do not envy that rather be here. Do you remember dev one?
Yeah, yeah, the the Ubuntu fork or no the I'm sorry the Debian fork that doesn't have system D. No
System D in dev one and we've we've had some things here to there to say about dev one
But nobody's had something to say about dev one
like
The owner of a server hosting company not inside the US his name is Nico
I think is how you pronounce it doesn't write an ICO. I'm sorry Nico if I'm if I'm mispronouncing your name
and he takes to the internet this week to defend dev one and to
Silence the system D lovers once and for all with his empirical data his hard-learned evidence
And of course his links that are indisputable which would be all the studies that he references in his I'm sorry what?
Mm-hmm. He doesn't have any of those things. He doesn't have any any studies. Mm-hmm. This is all anecdotal evidence. Uh-huh
I'm just been informed that my producer says that we're good to go with the story. So here we go. We carry right
So I'll dig into some of the most important parts. So this is a defense of dev one. He opens up
He says I understand that some of you may think that dev one a fork of Debian is an infinite waste of resources
The problem is that you're small-minded and you don't understand how the world works you see because it's saving the world
It's saving resources and I'm gonna explain to you why and if you don't understand and disagree
Then you're just not obviously a server person. So they tried to build a data center light, you know
Like a thin compact study version of a data center on Debian and Ubuntu
But you see there's a fundamental problem with servers that run system D. They don't boot
they don't boot and they don't reboot and
System D resolve D that constantly interferes with core network configurations made it very expensive for them to run Debian or Ubuntu their words not mine
And while they're using flowery words, they say the reason to use dev one is the hard calculated costs
They're a small team and they simply don't have the time to fix problems caused by system D on a daily basis
Did you know that you're having problems with system D on a daily basis with the systems you run?
Did you know that every day? Did you know that? Yeah, I see
I was under the I was under the mistaken impression that all of my systems with system D have been running fine now for about
a year
That might just be you I'm an idiot
Their objective is to create a great easy-to-use platform for virtual machine hosting not to walk a fucking tightrope
So don't get it wrong. Okay, because I don't want to you want to walk a tightrope. That's a different business
That's somewhere else not in a day. That's where Debian's at. That's where Ubuntu is at not that type
Oh the devil in community creates infinite economic costs. Sure, but that's not their fault
Creating dev one is simply a counter reaction to ensure that Linux
remains stable
Which is of high importance to a lot of people because everybody in IT management
Everyone who's built a data center and anyone who's ever managed at a server is completely aware that if you can run a minority
Operating system that is tested by a very very few fraction of the users that doesn't have wide use in production
That's the definition of a production ready system. If you can have a system that only a couple handful of tens
maybe at most
15,000 users are using versus a system that's literally deployed by millions of users by the largest enterprise companies in the entire world
You don't want to use that system because their systems don't boot
see what you want to do is you want to stick with the esoteric fork that's only used by a very small minority of people who
Aren't likely to bitch in the first place because it's confirmation bias and they don't want to validate confirmation bias
So you got to stick with that system
Yeah, you read it, right dev one developers are creating stability. Think about it
If not for a few repeating system system debugs or the insecurity caused by a huge
monolithic piece of software running and Ruth root privileges then system do you be okay see what we much prefer are
tens of thousands of tiny programs that are no longer maintained that diffract our
vulnerability landscape across
Thousands of lines of entry points in code so you don't want to have one active project being maintained by the most important people in
The industry who have their entire revenue model on the line to make sure this thing works. That's the last thing you want
That's the last thing you want what you want
What you want to make sure you have on your data center servers is something that is no longer maintained
something that is done by thousands of different pieces of software instead of one maintained code base and
Something that's simply too large for one any one individual to fully understand
That's you got to have something like that when you run in production and system D
Not that
That's a problem. You see when you're running servers. You got to make sure
Keep it as diffracted keep it as just deferred as possible really the key thing there
And then and then you're getting as close to old Linux as possible and everybody's happy. There's no problems. It's not too complex
It's nothing like Windows and it's stable. Remember how much fun we had when we tried out slackware the other month. It was great
Yeah, old-school Linux with system D. The main advantages to use Linux
Are obsolete. So what is the importance of Devon?
it's not only crucial to Linux users, but to everyone running servers or rockets or
watches
Or anything that actually depends on a stable operating system
support to have one
support
That's
This is a this is the shit that we deal with and it's so funny because
You know what really people who care have switched to free BSD or another BS and another BSD like people that really care about system
D on their servers. They're just I'm working on gentoo right here, man. No, that's right. We got to talk about that
so, you know the thing that I guess what I'm coming back to here is
If you if you see this as they do then you need to reevaluate why you're in the industry and you need to think about the
Fact that you may be a risk to your business your personal stubborn views on the way computers should run
probably make you a risk not because you're even necessarily wrong about system D or the reason it was deployed or the fact that one
piece of code base is a singular target versus thousands of scattered applications
You could be right on all of that, but there's a fundamental fact of the network effect testing user testing and enterprise
deployment that makes system D
Inevitable if you want to run Linux in a major installation and anything that's actually production important in the next few years
If you're not on system D, you're not going to be on Linux and I I'm sorry
I'm sorry, it's that way but it's time for you to either quit your job or switch to BSD
Not because you're wrong about system D. You might be right you might be right
But it's just for the same reason that I think man Jaro is a chicken shit reason to not use arch
It's literally the same thing, right?
But you see the whole thing that people like to pretend is great about man Jaro is that theoretically there's millions of users
Using man Jaro testing and the man Jaro makes arch, right? It is it you could only have that when you have
millions
Millions of users using your software and all the different esoteric edge cases that find bugs that have
Unprecedented load on the network stack or unprecedented load on the disk IO or attackers hitting this thing remotely over
From Iran over the internet like until you are in those positions with your software. You're not production ready
That's why you have something like ZFS and you have something like butter FS
There's clear differences in which one's production ready one has massive enterprise deployment where people are making millions of dollars off of product
A year and one has a few enthusiasts that are trying out and losing data, but it is made of butter
So there's that it is it is is a common thread that we see and I totally understand where they're coming from
And you know, it would be great. It would be great if using Linux was a better way to do it
It would be great if using Linux without system D was going to be a viable option
But if you're in production if you're accepting real internet connections if it's a customer facing environment
It's time to step up and learn how to use your computer
And in this case, it means learn how to use system D
All of your complaints you have in there about system D resolve D and all this stuff
It's you not knowing how to use your computer anymore
You are now one of those people that doesn't know how to use their computer and you're blaming it on system D
Think about that for a second
You're no better off than all of those users who blame something because they just simply don't know how to use it
That's you now
And if that's how that's maybe you're right, maybe you're right. I'm not saying you're not right. I'm saying go use something else now
Because you shouldn't be running some crazy ass fork like this that isn't being properly maintained
Okay, I'm almost done I'm just gonna wrap it up
The reason why system D was launched is because some of the things that system D replaced are no longer maintained by anyone
You understand that right you understand that
System D started not because they're like, hey, here's a random ass idea. Maybe we should just do X
It was because they were sitting around going well fuck
Nobody's maintaining these super important open source projects anymore and this stuff's falling behind. We got to do something
That's why system D came about
And when you understand that or that origin and then you look at people saying well don't let's not use system D
What they're saying is let's use software that's no longer maintained
That's dangerous people packaging it for your distribution your dev one or your gen two doesn't make it maintained
That just means it's packaged. There's a big difference there and you have to understand that if you're running servers in production
especially customer facing
You got some desktop. You got some laptop. You got some personal home machine. I don't care right doesn't make any difference
But if you're selling to customers and you got a responsibility here to keep these things secure and patched
That's how I feel about it for me
The biggest problem I had it was mostly tone like I'm not gonna say they can't run a production grade facility on this operating system
Maybe they're very skilled admins
Give it a go. Absolutely. And if this had been a case study in hey, look we tried out dev one
We it scaled super well. We had no, you know, here's a here's an example of how this really worked for us
And we're it's successful in production. I would not have a problem with that. That's right, right
But to imply that you can't do that with system or to say that
Servers with system d don't boot or reboot. Yeah, right that which which is just insane hyperbole
And maybe you did have problems that it's not like system d is perfect
No one is claiming that in a real discussion, right?
It's just and it's fine if you want to run something else and you can do it in a maintainable sustainable secure way fine
Talk about that. Let's make that the story. I would love to learn more about that
That's not where we're at
That's how I feel and then it just gets me all fired up and i'm like well
Now you're just digging your head down and being a turd about it. Yeah, exactly that article is
riddled
Riddled with confirmation bias. Yeah, he's accusing others of having confirmation bias. That's true too. Good point
um
Yeah, yeah anyways, uh, I just can't believe it, you know before the show started we were talking about uh,
The stuff in 2017 that's really left a mark on us and linux. Well, we're gonna talk about it more in a future episode
so we were just sort of brainstorming and
Looking, you know, you could almost flip it around say what kind of things can you just not believe?
We're not done talking about in 2017. Yes freaking system d
Right. I mean, oh my gosh. Yeah things that should have been over with in 2017. Yeah
Yeah, also things that should be over with is frivolous lawsuits and trademark disputes
So the software conservancy
Has a trademark dispute, uh put against them from the software freedom law center
We talked about this on a previous linux action news and on this show in the past
And now we have some additional clarifications by bradley kuhn the president of the software conservancy the the group
that has the trademark action being taken against them from the law center law center being run by even moglen and
the conservancy being run by bradley m kuhn and then you have the
Executive director karen sandler. I forget her exact title
Um, and they uh, they started a blog post that sort of blew this thing out into the public a couple of about a month
ago that they were being shut down by the law center for their for trademark infringement of their name, even though the law center
was their
Law council for seven years and helped establish the software conservancy. So it was pretty weird
and uh
What's happened now is they've actually filed their motion to have this entire case dismissed and as part of that
In this judgment motion, they've had to put it all out there. They have the full filing. I have it linked in the show notes
It's long. It's 120 pages and I read it this morning
Oh, and uh, i've never read um so much legalese in one sitting
I usually have to take it in spurts, but I wanted to get it all in before the show
It was uh, who that explains the gray hair, okay, oh I tell you and um
There's there is nothing that we didn't speculate in there it uh, if you read the conservancy's filings
you'll see various examples of personal vendettas between even and
Or evan and bradley and karen
There is bad blood there. I think would be a way you could put it and uh,
It's all laid out in the legal filing in a very matter of fact way
and um this software freedom law center
Which are the aggressors here have a history of complaining to the conservancy complaints about the organization's name
We're never among them though in the years that they have been complaining each time the
The conservancy took the complaint seriously and each time discovered that they were generally
Just sort of over the top threats
And the conservancy says bradley specifically says I hesitated for years to talk publicly about this bad blood historically
I concluded that you know
Unilaterally exposing privately made specious claims interferes with the essential jobs of promoting and defending software freedom
Um, despite our differences the law center is a fellow charity and I have no wish for them to cease to exist
Only did they stop attacking us a year ago
Morgan publicly described certain gpl enforcement work to which I have contributed since the 90s as a jihad
I was offended because I have dedicated my life to non-violent principled activism for social justice causes
Even so I did not likewise assail in response. I sought to keep the discussion about policy
And not her not her uh hyperbolic rhetoric
But on finally on a meta issue and this is the point that I tried to make last time we covered this story
I've seen a lot of stories blogs stories and comments on linux or on lwn.net
And other venues in the last few weeks about this matter
It seems to have burned more electricity and time than it warrants
I do appreciate the statements of support that so many of you have made but I have a request
While I understand that this kind of situation generates an intriguing distraction and seemingly endless discussion
I encourage those of you who are otherwise software freedom contributors to temper your time investment
Faced with the petition to cancel our trademark conservancy must defend ourselves before the trademark board
But I loathe the idea the time wasted damage of the law center's action may extend to other software freedom
Contributors and activities in particular. I ask those of you who are conservancy project volunteers to avoid distraction
by this
The work of the conservancy member projects in the work is the work that the software freedom law center's actions seek to impede
So, please don't allow them to break your focus and succeed even just for a little bit
I completely agree that I hate when all of this um
Lawyer stanky bullshit distracts from actually creating code. I hate it
And what I respect about bradley and karen is they haven't been airing their dirty laundry with the law center
When even's been contacting them saying hey, I don't think you're doing this right. Hey, I think you ripped off some of our material
Hey, I don't think that's properly creative commons
Hey, and every time they have they've been pretty receptive and they haven't come out and said
Yeah, these guys over at the law center keep giving us a hard time
They've never done that until this came up and they clearly state
In their legal filing that they never received any kind of preemptive warning that this was coming. No tweet. No email
No text message no phone call, right?
They didn't receive any kind of preemptive warning of this trademark dispute that was heading their way
And they clearly think and they position it
so in their legal filing that this is a vendetta a personal vendetta and the conservancy is
Is taking the heat for what is a personal vendetta between the people running the conservancy and the people running the software law center freedom
Anyways, the names are hard to say. Yes, and um, it's kind of hard to watch because it is creating behind the scenes
I guess the meta story here is behind the scenes. There's a lot of connections
The software freedom law center has connections to the linux foundation
There's obvious contributors that have their software projects that are being managed by either of these entities
People that have worked with both these entities together when they were partners on a middle ground here
There's a lot and it's it's awkward because it's filled with landmines and it's one of these things when you read the headline
You're like, oh lawyers are making money and then you realize well, one of these is an umbrella organization
That is essentially home to about 30 open source projects. And if they shut down those open source projects are screwed
So there's real ramifications to projects that we all use and at the end of the day. We just want to see them do well
Oh, man, we can't have nice things. Let's just this is why we can't have nice things
Wes, this is why right here. It's really extremely frustrating. Let's distract ourselves with a little gen 2 challenge. Just open up the challenge
Fascinating
It's gen 2 challenge time. Wes. How you feeling about today's gen 2 challenge?
Oh boy feeling system d right out of my life. Are you uh, how's your kernel build going?
That's where we left off last week. Oh, it's finished now. We got a kernel. So now we're doing our bootloader
You're doing grub? What are you doing? What's where you at right now? What's going on?
Yeah, well, we're setting up we're setting up uh network some f-stab all that fun. Oh, yeah
Uh, then we'll do the bootloader and then maybe maybe a little later today
We're gonna see if this whole thing will reboot
Fascinating. All right. I look forward to it. We will check back in just a little bit the gen 2 challenge continues on
Yes, it does. This is week two. I think so
Oh wow, so I wonder if within within two episodes if you're gonna get a graphical environment now, I wonder I bet you'll get booting
Yeah, that's what I bet you won't get x until next week next week. We'll get some x
Then we're gonna try to get some remote screen caps going and all kinds of stuff. So that's gonna be good
That is really gonna be good. So, um bashful. You're not running gen 2, right? I mean you're not running system d right now. Are you uh,
How are you doing this? How are you pulling this magnificent feat of engineering off?
I don't know. I was making a joke. I said you're about to reboot gen 2 and I said not if it's running system
Yeah, that's right. You can't you can't so
No, you can't or reboot eric or configure your network feature
I am using the wrong system then I know I have been for months. I'm an idiot. I didn't even know
And here I thought I was rebooting booting and having networking. I am such an idiot to me
I'm, sorry guys. I apologize. Well wes you continue on the good work. We'll check back in with you
Uh towards the end of the show. We do have much much much to get into including some community news
Let's take a moment and talk about the perfect holiday gift ting
Go to linux.ting.com support the show and get 25 off a device
or
25 in service credits and here's why I say that because if you bring a device that's the way to go
They got cdma and gsm. This is how I got into ting
You following me? See I brought over an old evo 4g cdma phone
I got 25 in ting credit when I did that
25 I was like, okay. I'll play with this. I'll play with this right? What's 25 gonna get me like 15 minutes
You know paid for more than my first month paid
Yeah
The average ting bill is just 23 dollars per phone per month because it's six dollars for the line
And then just your usage on top of that your minutes your messages and your megabytes and then whatever uncle sam's gonna cut
That's sort of unique to your area, but you just pay for what you use
It's a fair price however much you talk however much text or data you use nationwide coverage. No contracts
No determination fees linux.ting.com you're in control you get to see usage you get to take uh alerts
You can set like hey, i'm you've used 15 megabytes
Send alert or hey, you've used 20 gigabytes send an alert. You've used 15 messages
You've used 15 000 messages. Whatever is your mark you can start generating alerts for you
They have a great dashboard to manage all of it fantastic customer service and a ton of good devices
I'm gonna give a shout out though to the motorola moto g5 s plus
Ting's got it in stock and you can get it unlocked no contract nor the termination fee pay for what you use
Not interrupting your experience if there's an update you get it
254 dollars from ting
Pay for what you use nice now the stock thing the thing the downside like the downside to the g5
To me isn't that big of a downside?
So it where they save their money on the g5 s is the storage it comes with 32 gigabytes of built-in storage
But you can put up to 128 gigabytes of additional storage with the micro sd slot
And one of my favorite things about this series of phone is it has the turbo power charging
So you can get up to six hours of power in 15 minutes when you plug your phone in
So like just driving somewhere you get six hours of battery life and and it has a 401 ppi screen
and gorilla glass 3
This is a serious. Oh and uh fingerprint unlock. This is a really nice phone with a really clean android experience
under
300 unlocked pay for what you use motorola gs g5 s plus
254 dollars when you go to linux.com because you're gonna take 25 off the device that'll knock it down from 280
You need a new phone. Maybe you think a little present for the holidays. This is perfect
The other thing is is well, I don't know why the trend is is going in the wrong direction
This has a physical button just one physical button to take you back to the home screen and has headphone jack
Which uh, so you got you got micro sd
401 ppi screen gorilla glass 3 and you get six hours of battery life in a 15 minute charge all metal design and a fingerprint unlock
For 254 dollars pay for what you use. This is a great phone
This is and or you just bring your own just start by going to linux.ting.com
Linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program linux.ting.com
Go there go there and check out the blog, too
I want to give a shout out to mail spring
I'm I've installed it this week on all of my systems and if you remember Nileus, I know you turned me on Nileus
Yeah, so thank you to that because this is the continuation of Nileus. I'm yet to try it
But we've talked about it
Yeah
You and I have talked about it for weeks and a mail spring works with all IMAP providers works with the mail and a lot of the
other online ones the thing that's that's nice about mail spring is
First of all, they have a pretty decent Linux user base over 10,000 active Linux users
So it actually matters to the developer
I like that but the other thing that's really nice about it is they've just this week patched it up as a snap
So check this out. Hey, you know, we can see it
I don't they have a see if you go to their website right now if you go to mail suit go to their mail spring website
They're with you go to the mail spring website
I know you're in the middle of installing gentoo
but if you go to get mail spring comm and then you go to
Download mail spring and you click on the gunu slash Linux option. Their first option here is Linux auto updating snap
Yeah, wow, look at that. How great is that?
I've got the traditional dab and RPM if that's for you. Yes. Yes. Yes, they do
Yes, an arch over here. So right snap sounds great
Well, and so here's what's so nice about mail spring
If you're using Thunderbird and you've been looking for another a local email client
Give it a look because it's it works super well with multiple accounts
So that for me is a killer feature and it supports unified inbox for searches. I like that a lot now
I don't have experience with mail spring
But I assume this is similar to the way in the latest did but the real frickin creepy magic that I love is
The read receipts link tracking and more it's like genuine
It's read receipts if you could redo the way read receipts worked in 2017 and it I don't know how they do it
But it's great because it gives me push notifications when somebody's opened my email to my desktop and it uses the gnome
Notifications systems and so it integrates in with my desktop or in this case unity and it's a
Brilliant way to know right before somebody's gonna email me because everybody opens up their last email that they got from you before they send
You another email. Yeah, right
So I get a good 30 to 30 second to 15 minute heads up before I get an email and I can just sort of mentally
Prepare myself for it. It's got great shortcuts super nice search
and it's got a dark theme that looks good on on Linux and
It it'll tie in with like it'll look at people's like LinkedIn profiles and it has
Multiple theme support it has a pro version
And the reason I mentioned that is because it actually has a monetization strategy that isn't like advertising or tracking you I was about to
Say I think you do need the pro to get some of those things like link tracking and the quick reply templates
Which is also great for somebody gets a lot of emails, but like you said like it's nice to see this this open-source project
Yeah, they've got they've got some you know some long-term stuff going out. They can actually get some good revenue exactly
So Ben is one of the lead developers of the project and I invited Ben on the show next week if it works out for him
It's crazy with the holidays and all that but I just I want to talk to him and say hey
did you did you expect such a big Linux reaction and
Does it change the way you're developing this and why why build it in the technologies you have?
And why are you continuing this when there's something like Thunderbird out there? Why not just contribute to Thunderbird and
I've got I've got my
Assumptions to those answers, but I'd really like to hear Ben's absolutely and so I sent him an invite
He was gonna try to make it today
but he had something come up couldn't make it today because it was kind of a last-minute thing and
Might be able to make it next week really any time. Yeah, really excited. I've been using it now
I've got it installed on all of my systems, so I'll just keep using it to have more things to ask him about it
now
You know every now and then Wes the mainstream media tries to cover something. That's our wheelhouse
This is CNN breaking news, and they just really blow it they really
So
Afronaut Mark Shuttleworth has become a billionaire from his bet on Ubuntu Linux software according to Bloomberg and
They have one of these pictures of mark where if if you have if you've seen mark in the last few years
Mark doesn't look a lot. I mean
Mark looks fine, but mark doesn't look like this anymore. This is an old picture, right?
So it's like always funny when people go to like ten years ago and get like these really old 2002
Like what I know so
spaceman mark shuttleworth
Was interviewed by Bloomberg not a boom to creator not canonical CEO. No no spaceman spaceman mark shuttleworth
Is that like where you've served in a political office once and then you get that title as an honorific forever?
What do you go to space?
I guess kind of cuz like how many people have gone to space it's a handful of people so yeah
So the headline on Bloomberg comm is literally
spaceman shuttleworth finds earthly riches with Ubuntu software
Not the editor's best day oh
man, so
Why why such a why such a ham-fisted headline and why Bloomberg why Bloomberg well?
This is a messaging piece you see kids. This is canonical positioning themselves for a little investment
This is mark
Communicating to the investment community. That's what Bloomberg's all about. They're all about the investment community
So it's been written for that audience, so I'm gonna read a little bit of it keep it in mind though
This isn't really for us. This is this is for the investing audience and
It's it's pretty bad, so they say he's best known for being the world's first afro not but since returning to earth from his
2002 trip on the Russian Soyuz TM 34 rocket ship
Cape Town native Mark Shuttleworth set about with the conquest of much more lucrative universe the Internet of Things as
If in 2002 the Internet of Things was even some stupid term we were using back all over the place
Shuttleworth created a boon to an open source Linux operating system that helps connect everything from drones to thermostats to the Internet his company
canonical group makes money from about
800 paying customers
Which is the first time we've ever gotten a number publicly including Netflix Tesla
Deutsche Telekom they all pay for support services, of course
They don't mention HP Dell, you know any of those know its success has helped boost the network his network marks net worth to
$1,000,000,000, but mark says it is destructive to focus on that
It's just a distraction and you have to keep your finger on what's the pulse for next now?
It's funny how they position this
So they use terms again, you have to keep the market audience in mind here they use terms that are
Rough so marks marks Shuttleworth in this interview, which is the sort of the pull quote is the industry term for this
He has a pull quote that is pretty good
He did a really good job actually and the pull quote is
Open source is defining innovation in
2017 and or today he says it is the defining innovation of today
It says he could went on to say that it gives me the luxury of being able to focus on things that I thought were
Really meaningful and interesting and deep open source software is deep
You have to get under the hood a little bit then you realize it's everywhere. It's defining innovation today
What do you think of that?
Because I think if you ask the average Bloomberg consumer who's defining innovation today, they'd say Apple or Google. Yeah, or Amazon
It'd be a big
proprietary company of some sort
But I think this actually while obvious gives you the insight to the layer that Mark Shuttleworth works on
Because mark knows because he's an intelligent man that all of these companies that are making their billions of dollars right now are doing it
Essentially on the backs of open source. Do you agree? Oh, yeah, absolutely, right?
I mean these are these are the underpinnings in the engine house of a lot of these companies, right?
And it's always this like where you see about that
Yeah, the big managed services the things that the everyday consumer uses you hear a lot about those
But you don't hear about back-end infrastructure, right?
So you've got Google obviously very very dependent on Linux for everything from their ad platform to Android
You've got Amazon the entire EC2 infrastructure and the echo infrastructure and all of the things that support their e-commerce infrastructure
Linux you've got Apple everything that's in iOS and macOS is
BSD based it comes from so many open source developed applications and libraries
But you also don't hear about it, but you know what their cloud runs a bunch on Linux servers. Yeah
Yeah, so I guess he's kind of right. And so this is the area where I think investors read this and they go
Oh, yeah, so this is what shell worth is working on. Oh, okay
Now they also talk about how shuttleworth started programming Ubuntu years ago and stuff like that
So it's it's pretty bad. Mm-hmm, but there is one other quote in here that I thought
Well, what the hell does that mean?
And I kind of want to get the mumbles take on this
The vision for canonical is to provide the platform that you see everywhere other than the personal domain
Other than the personal domain we won't make a dent in phone or PCs
But pretty much your entire data center runs Linux and every other thing in the room is running Linux
What do you think of that bashful
I mean you're working on a Linux desktop distro right now and Mark says we won't make a dent in phones or PCs
Is he talking just investor speak there? Or do you think he actually believes it? I
Think it's a bit of both. He's looking at what's profitable which I mean running a business
You can't really blame them but where they're making their dollars and cents is not on you know, the desktop and things like that
it's all you know server support or
The data center stuff there kubernetes, you know all of that stuff's where they're pushing hard as a quote-unquote company
You know and even the snap initiative really drives
That as well, you know, it's like availability of software their snappy core stuff for the IOT the desktop
You know, they obviously haven't bailed on it, but it's not their focus as a company. They're still heralding it, you know being a
Curator of sorts if you think about it, but isn't isn't the server a PC?
Well, is it no I suppose not in terms it is in terms of platform and you know architecture
But I suppose not in the way the market talks about a personal computer. Yeah, right. It's not a personal computer
because he all right said it's not like
The consumer front right? He didn't say PC is in servers and underlying infrastructure
He's just talking about like, you know what Apple's doing or even to a degree some of the other vendors
You mean those guys are out in front in your home? Yeah, that's true. Yeah. Yeah. That's good point
I wonder if there's any signal into maybe more of some savvy investors that have followed the company for a while and were perhaps
Worried about some of their direction. Is this you know, a little bit like hmm reassuring that like, you know
This is this is our new this is our focus trimmed. We're not gonna be silly. Yeah, we're not gonna be trying any more phones
We're not really pushing to compete with Windows or Mac OS. I want to hear so. Hey citizen
What is your take on Mark's on Mark's quote here? Is it disingenuous?
I don't know. Do you feel like I really don't know. I mean to me it feels a little disingenuous
I'm gonna be honest. It feels disingenuous to me. It feels like well
I have these staff members and I know what they're working on and I know what they're working on
and I know what they're working on and I have these contracts with Dell and
HP
Lenovo and others and I'm I'm making a pretty good profit off them, but I don't want to talk about it
Doesn't that give you pause a little bit? Mr. Citizen?
I mean to me it does just as just a slight degree
Like I'm a little worried that I've just sort of switched everything over to a bunch of desktop. Just a tad
Should I know it's hard to know
Like what the agenda is? Yeah, if there's the audience something not being told right something is being told that maybe
May or may not be true, right? I
I I kind of sit back and go. Well, you're right from a revenue standpoint
You probably never will and there's probably no other company that's gonna get in on this game at this point. It's not like
Samson is not gonna come along and launch the Samsung desktop
The Chromebook is the closest we've gotten to cracking the desktop duopoly in decades
But we're also like you and I we're in a different position in that like you maybe aren't looking to the same extent
For like this complete like a Windows 10 style desktop
I think like as we've seen maybe with Fedora and Red Hat as a parallel
There is enough like I think incentive to maintain the developer or power user focused desktop just in terms of like I
Want to use Ubuntu to develop Ubuntu
Yeah, fair enough and that's all part of your ecosystem, right?
It's all part of your eco, but it is not the big thing that you're really pushing to the market. Mm-hmm
Mm-hmm. Well speaking of ecosystems
Well speaking of ecosystems steam has made an adjustment that I think Linux users should be made aware of just so that way they can
Vote a little bit to get developers to support more Linux
Development you may be hurt. Yeah, so valve has made a change to the developer side of steam that actually gives them more information
It gives developers a breakdown of the different platforms that people are choosing when they add a game to their wish list
You know, you might think that this is a small
Change, but I happen to know from a Netflix developer that this is how Netflix science
multibillion-dollar
content deals is
they they actually look at what's in your wish list what's in your queue versus what you're watching and
If they have if they have tens of thousands of users that have a show or a movie in their wish list
They work way harder to get that content provider to license it for Netflix
steam
developers can now take the same tact
See now platforms that don't currently or games that don't currently support the Linux platform
will at least get a vote to let the developer know that hey, there's some interest here to get your port over to that platform that
might not be Windows and
You know, it's also gonna be the same for Mac users
But now when you add something you say I want the Linux version
They're gonna get that metric back which may actually end up in getting us a few more Linux games
Yeah, who knows but from the developer perspective, it's pretty hard to be motivated
If you just have a big question mark, right?
Like maybe you don't even use Linux you've heard about it
Maybe some people emailed you saying they want it but right I don't get a couple of tweets
What percentage is there really any revenue here? I don't know and it means as Linux users
We need to start adding this stuff to our wish list. Yes, right. That's the thing we can do and
And then maybe the developers
Will sneeze
Maybe they'll sneeze and then when they sneeze lucky and they'll make a game
Yeah, they'll actually hit the export option for Linux. Yes
I'm gonna give a quick mention for Linux fest Northwest 2018 April 28th through the 29th West and I'll be there with our pants on
I'm so excited and we invite you to be there with your pants on as well. It's gonna be a good Linux fest
19 freaking years of Linux fest. That's that's stupid. Hey boy Wow Wow Wow, that's really something, huh?
And rumor has it and I thought Linux was just a fad
Rumor has it that Alan Jew that free BSD love and Alan Jude might make it again
I'm trying to talk a couple other people into making it out here a few of our other friends from other shows that we do
I like that trying to get that all worked out. We'll lay the peer pressure on them
Yeah, and we're also already discussing party options
So if you could make it out of Linux fest Northwest 2018, I highly encourage it and go to Linux fest Northwest org for more information
I'm giving them a little plug because we're gonna be there and we're doing something totally different this year
I hope it's gonna be good. But now that we're not doing last like it's our opportunity
Yep to totally refactor the way we do Linux fest even more reasons for you to come
I remember I there used to be a time West when I used to go to Linux fest before I actually did any shows
and I would sit there with my notebook and
Sometimes Angela would come with me and she'd take notes, too
And then I would sit there and I would go back and I would do all the cool stuff
That I'd learned at Linux fest at work nice and then I sat down and I did all that stuff and I went shit
This is so awesome. I got to do a podcast about this and that's how we got last here
We are today so I let express Northwest has a real special heart a real special place in my heart
Also, I guess while I'm sharing all
one of the cool things about Linux fest Northwest for me is that it was I
Had a I had a I had a teacher in high school. Mr. Bassett
Who made some really cool open-source software by the way this guy he helped me get into Debian and he wrote some really great
open-source attendance management and grade management software and
He and I used to drive up to Linux fest Northwest when I was you know
20 years ago when Linux fest Northwest was brand new and I was a young pup
I I was I was out of school, but not by much back then Jesus. I'm old
And I would go with my old teacher my old high school teacher
We go to Linux fest Northwest. Yeah, and so then it's just over the years. It's it's it's it's it's really
I mean think about the number of people even if even counting people have only been there once or you know
But just especially having been there and seen people who've just kind of wandered in from the community or weren't that big into it or came
Down from the local or just trying out Linux. They've heard this thing or hey, there's some event going on here
What is this? What are all these people doing? It's really touched a huge number of people
Speaking of touching people let's go over and touch our servers a little bit of touching servers right now
Nothing's better than touching servers getting getting your hands-on experience with some open-source software and West
You hear right here, you know what I have right here. Well, you got secrets. I got fresh secrets
I've got pages and pages of secrets. You want me to share them with you?
Oh, please you otherwise I'll have to steal them after the show understood understood digital ocean calm you go over there and
Learn about all of the secrets use our promo code do unplugged do unplugged
It's one word you get a $10 credit at digital ocean comm you get started in less than 55 seconds and spin up a system
on their awesome
Infrastructure everything's SSDs. They got a buntu fedora centOS core OS
I mean, they probably have uncle Joe OS and they even have free BSD. They got block storage. They got object storage now
What's the difference? What's the difference? How would you describe the difference between block storage?
I guess I would describe block storage as hey
You know how you can hook up a storage device to your Linux box and it shows up as like a dev slash SD device
That's block storage
object storage
It sounds it sounds too meta, but I would describe it as programmable storage. Yeah, right
It's a it's a higher level of abstraction where instead of thinking about blocks and having to format a file system
Yes, you're just saying hey
I want this file
Put it somewhere and the back end just manages all that stuff and generates the storage for you puts it somewhere on all those
And then you can destroy you can set time expirations. It's great. They got team support if you're an open source group
Are you working by yourself and want to bring somebody else and eventually and everything is super fast networking 40 gigabit connections coming into the hypervisors
Monitoring and metrics to tell you how things are doing load balancing as a service
Firewall at the network level and an API that is simple and easy to use with tons of open source applications
Love that API. It is nice and the nice thing about it so much stuff's already built around it, too
You just use it. There's a ton of apps use scripts. It's supported with a bunch of things
You know all the tools terraform vacant all the stuff. You're already using yeah, yeah
But when I'm sitting by the fire at night West, and I'm rocking in my chair and sipping on a little whiskey I think to myself
Nothing's like that dashboard. They got a dashboard for days. It's simple. It's easy to use it's fast
It works on your tablet. It works on your phone. It works on your web browser
I don't care what you use and they don't either and they got apps on top of it. It's
It's so nice. It is it is so damn nice
I am so appreciative that they have really done this well, and I think that their interface is actually an API client
I'm not positive about that
But it seems to it seems to be as soon as they added something to the API the interface has it as soon as they
Add something interface the API has it so I think they're super good UI is actually an API client
Which is it's all dog food mind-blowing digital ocean calm create your account use the promo code do unplugged and
Go look at a couple of their different tutorials right now
I like this one
I mentioned this on Kota radio recently how to create a highly available setup with heartbeat and floating IPs on a boom to 1604
LTS
That's boss level right there and in look at this guide like even if you're not a digital ocean customer
Just shut up and go over here. Look at this thing. Look at this freaking chart. Yeah this diagram with animations, dude
Oh, and then you notice when you click on it to get a bigger version of the animations
It doesn't like take over the full screen. It just pushes the content below down a little bit
So considerate look how nice that is like this is so well formatted that if you
Literally had no idea what failover and heartbeat was you could read this and understand it
And if you'd set it up before and just need a refresher, you could jump around and set it up. It's
It's it's freaking magic West. It just kind of brings a tear to me
I digital ocean calm go over there create your account do unplugged is the promo code you get the $10 credit
You can try out their $5 rig two months for free. It's magic. I assume
I don't know. There's no other way to explain it ponies and fairies
It's the only way digital ocean calm promo code do unplugged and maybe a little Linux and open source in there as well
Maybe maybe
No devil on though. Let's talk about platforms. Um, I
Actually
This this paper I was making noises with here earlier I printed my statement out actually
I got a printed statement for you West. I got a printed statement laid on me
Mmm, a couple of things have happened this week that have pushed this topic. I think to the front of my mind
It's all about platforms. It's all about commercial proprietary lockdown closed source pain in my ass platforms pain in your ass, too
Audience, let's talk about it for a second. So this is this is on the backs of a new YouTube and Amazon and Google War
This is on the backs of big leaks coming out about YouTube
Demonetization policies and the way they walk people through it. It's all about platforms
It's about building the biggest platform with the most engaged users with the most control over what they can and can't do
YouTube is a
platform
iPhone iOS platform
Patreon is a platform Libre pay is also a platform
It feels like the walls on all of these platforms are closing in tighter and tighter than ever before it's and then you combine
The the weight of net neutrality on top of all this as if it's about to lock all of these new regimes in all
of these platform regimes into place
early Linux users watch this as Microsoft used the position of their platform the Windows desktop to keep
Linux off the desktop to keep Linux off of hardware and
Now these platform wars that used to be the defining thing about the technology industry the Microsoft platform war now
They happen every single day at an exponential rate across every tech category
Just just recently Google has started blocking YouTube on the echo shows
Because Amazon doesn't sell nest cameras in Chromecast on amazon.com
So everybody who's bought a Amazon echo show to watch YouTube videos. Yeah, screw you too bad
It's always the users who lose on these platform wars
the creators the users and a large corporation they don't care
There there's no there's no cost to the collateral damage for them the collateral damage being the end users
And we're starting to see some cracks. I think in these platforms
There's a couple of open source solutions coming, but they're not quite there yet
So I want to talk about where which ones we do have where they're at and how we could start using them as linux users
Now if you're watching the video version right now
You're going to see women bending over and showing their asses
You're going to see a guy's junk in tight underwear, and you're going to see an Asian woman showing her breasts
What not Chris's background? No, I know it's tempting not yet, but what it what it is is
the YouTube guide on
How people should decide how they should flag sex nudity or other controversial topics?
And it's all very fucking subjective what they consider inappropriate and these heroes of YouTube who are answering these things
And this is a real problem
It really shuts down speech and that's the antithesis of what open source is about so I want to look at
solutions that we can take on as a group
to get rid of these platforms
What can we start using in place of YouTube for example?
I mean, there's nothing quite locked in yet, but there are some options on the horizon
And I think for a moment here
I want to talk about peer tube which I'm pretty excited about it's a federated video streaming platform using bit torrent
directly in the web browser with web torrent and angular and
Its early days is definitely a work in progress, but if you think about it legitimately guys
We have zero chance of some other commercial company coming along and offering streaming alternatives that are commercially viable to YouTube
Or daily motion or vimeo. It's not going to happen
They can't it's just the peering agreements in place and net neutrality rules that are about to change a huge backers involved
The massive amount of money the corporate interest
One organization alone doesn't have enough money to pay the bandwidth and the storage for something like this
It has to be peer-to-peer the next replacement for Facebook and Twitter and YouTube have to be peer-to-peer and decentralized
so we have to get this working and
you need something like
peer tube which is using peer-to-peer software on the back end and
Web torrent makes all the stuff. They actually have a demo
I'll link to it in the show notes and
They have a github page, but you can go to peer tube dot cpy dot re and you can actually start to watch
Demos and it's pretty nice
So I'm watching right now a video on peer tube and it shows how many peers are seeding it shows me my quality
All of that and you've got comments down here just like you would on you actually I don't see comments
But you it looks just like YouTube and it's streaming over web torrent in my browser. I
Mean the nice things about this is that they don't get they don't get punished if somebody's video goes viral or somebody gets popular because
The more people watching the more people distributing so it's an obvious replacement and there could be something else that comes along
I'd like to hear the audience's recommendations, but peer tube seems like a pretty pretty good replacement for YouTube who is
They allow these creepy like
Elsa videos have you seen this stuff like spider-man has sex with Elsa kind of stuff meanwhile
BSD now and Linux action news on and ask Noah on a weekly basis get demonetized
We're pretty extreme over here on JV. Yeah, we're super extreme
But meanwhile spider-man can dry hump Elsa and it's totally fine
It can make millions of dollars, but just good old-fashioned fun. God forbid Alan's you'd talk about ZFS
And we can't have that he does get pretty excited. Yeah, he gets oh yeah
He gets really excited, but this week the real cluster bomb has been patreon they
Really pissed off a bunch of people they changed the way the fee structure worked
They essentially raised rates on all of our patrons
They communicate in a way that was slightly disingenuous and it caused of as one would expect an internet outrage mob
Seeking justice and I I mean I can't I can't even tell you how many times it was demanded that I give a response
Immediately to what patreon has done as I record this I checked a day ago
We've had 17 people cancel their patreon accounts
No longer supporting Jupiter broadcast Wow because of a change patreon has made nothing something completely out of my control and
Ultimately a change that gives the creators more money
But people are pissed because they they were already at the line
They couldn't really afford more and something just changed on them
Now one of the number one solutions that I have had suggested to me is Libre pay
Libre pay is a reoccurring donations platform
Now the thing with Libre pay is it suffers the same problem that Facebook and YouTube and patreon and
Twitter all suffer
It's a centralized platform in fact in fact because of all the attention
They've been receiving recently it wasn't until today that I could even load their web page
Couldn't even people have been telling me demanding screaming at me all week to switch to Libre pay I couldn't even get
Ian dot Libre pay comm to load until today in fact
I wasn't even sure if it would load for this show so I could show it to you on the screen
That's how there's they just aren't there yet
It's a centralized server that is that is kicking out a few hundred bucks a month to creators
There's nothing that's fundamentally different here. They still have to go through the banking system
They still have to do clearing of credit card transactions
It suffers all of the same damn problems as a centralized platform. Yeah, the server codes open source
But it doesn't solve the problem right there's still this middleman between you and the people you don't have any control as long as they
Do what's in your interest okay?
But as we see yeah, that is not always the case and sure you know I'm some podcaster, but what about the developer of your?
Favorite file system. What about the developer of your favorite Linux desktop application? What about the creator of your favorite distribution?
How do we fund open source software in a world where a platform can make a change that pisses off a huge percentage of your?
Users and in a world where the internet is ready to go to mob justice mode in two seconds flat
They go from zero to mob justice in two seconds the one it takes one tweet one Facebook post
One link in IRC full mob justice mode so how can a content creator or an open source developer?
Secure reliable development. I mean holy shit am I glad I'm not Ikey-Dorty right now am I so glad
I'm not Ikey trying to develop the soulless project right now because people are pissed off about patreon
He just went full frickin time off of patreon and people are pulling off. Yeah, I think he's I think he's something like on late night
Linux I think he said he had 22 people cancel their subscriptions
That's stressful. That is true. Yeah, right absolutely
We've got to build in a way to prevent this problem because as long as one central authority has control over the platform
They're gonna make changes users don't like especially as patreon begins to get more profitable
They start looking at larger creators who have people that are maybe donating more money
Ten thousand dollars more a month the creators. That's their real. That's the sweet spot for them
Yes, there's less incentive to work with people that are supporting one or two creators
So everybody says go to Libre pay but Libre pay has some of the same limitations and essentially has the same fee structure as patreon
What do you do? Yeah? You know it's other contexts. We talk about like with these services
Yeah, you just like you know you know you might have to move and that works okay for the personal use base
But when you're trying to run a small business
Or you're trying to write an independent creator that kind of churn
And ruins it the only long-term solution. I can think is you have to get rid of a centralized platform a
central point of failure
And you see it's it's funny that we're having all these conversations about YouTube demonetization or YouTube censorship net neutrality
or
Twitter being shit all of these conversations are happening at once and there's another big conversation. That's happening right now
They may actually be giving us the answer to the Libre play problem
To the patreon problem to the PayPal problem to the credit card transaction processing problem
Like I could build my own system for Jupiter broadcasting
Donation page a subscription model and just get rid of patreon
You know have somebody write something that uses stripe for the back end with a custom page
And all of it is managed by us internally maybe even hire another person to actually stay on top of all that like Philip
DiPranco has
But I'm still using stripe, I'm still using a central clearinghouse and stripe is still trying to do batch processing with banks
I'm still
Stuck to a platform that doesn't have my best interests
Or my users best interests at heart
But for weeks and months and years we've been talking about something that solves this problem today, it's free
It's open source
It's available to anyone on the internet
It's cryptocurrency
See cryptocurrency solves this problem. There's no bank. There's no central clearinghouse. There's no processor
There's no middleman you have your cryptocurrency and you send it to your creator now
I know it's too early days for this to actually take off and replace patreon
But again, a lot of this stuff is so is peer tube this early days and we've all talked about Bitcoin
But not a lot of discussions been had on these shows about dash now dash just as an example
I'm not saying everybody should go buy dash
But dash is an example of something that one day could replace PayPal could replace patreon could replace Libra pay
And they've done a couple of things that are better than Bitcoin
You know, do you remember do you remember one of the cool things about Skype before Microsoft bought them was they had this really nice
Peer-to-peer network that the FBI bitched that they couldn't get access to. Yes, I do. That was a big deal back. Yeah
Yeah, right and then as the Skype network grew
You had this problem over the peer-to-peer network was so large that you didn't know who was online
You couldn't really coordinate at all. So then you had these master nodes develop
which was still part of the peer-to-peer network and then and then that was sort of
That would sort of be like the master repository of information Dash sort of launches with that concept
They call it a next-generation p2p network at dash at dash
Its core is a unique fully incentivized peer-to-peer network where miners are rewarded for securing the blockchain and
Masternodes are rewarded for validating storing and serving the blockchain to users now. What does that mean?
What does any of that shit mean? It means they have a
Reliable fast transactions that don't have a huge transaction fee and a huge leg like Bitcoin and it's anonymous as shit
That's the thing masternodes represent a new layer of network servers that work in the highly secure cluster called
quorums to provide a variety of decentralized services like
instant transactions
privacy and self-governance and
Eliminating the threat of localization
Privacy and self-governance and eliminating the threat of low-cost network attacks
So this is an area. It's a self-governing
self-funding protocol
that's anonymous it had it solved some of the
Tracking problems that Bitcoin has it solved some of the transaction
validation problems that Bitcoin has and
Currently as we record this episode the dash coin is at eight hundred dollars a coin
So it's it's also a pretty high functioning high value crypto. Yeah last year
That was that was big money in the cryptocurrency game. It still is really it really is
It's open source. It's it's fully open source. It has a
masternode system for fast transactions
And you could see how open source developers and content creators could potentially build a funding model around something like this
It's gonna have guys. I know some of you out there hate cryptocurrencies. It's gonna have to be something like this
It has to be because anytime you come back to a clearing house
Anytime you come back to the banks you end up with your PayPal your square your patreon situations every damn time
There's no way around it and in particular in some of these cases
You're you're uniquely tied to US institutions as well
Which for 30% of you out there listen to this show is not applicable to you, right?
And we've seen a ton of problems with like maybe there's different laws
You're developing open source that's legal in your country, but not in the US. There's all kinds of things. Jeez that could
Think about this for a second think about all of the talk recently about installing backdoors into encryption and secure protocols
right about how all of that could change when if you are a
open-source rogue developer making software that doesn't have backdoor encryption I
Could see the federal government pressuring PayPal to discontinue your donation. We have seen that with WikiLeaks. Yep
Once it becomes political, I mean all things are out the window and again
The idea of this segment here is how do we create something that's truly decentralized that it's platform-free
That if you were today to have all of the time in the world to build all these different like a peer tube system
And it and a dash power donation system. You could really divorce yourself from these
Information silos on the internet, but there's one last piece that I think is fairly important
Not a big fan of social networking, but I can't deny the value it is useful and
This is another area
Where we have a pretty hard lock right now with Twitter and Facebook now we all know about mastodon
It's the world's largest free open-source decentralized microblogging network
Where you can really build a custom community, so now we're talking peer-to-peer
Peer-to-peer torrent based YouTube
Now we're talking dash peer-to-peer
decentralized funding models and
Now mastodon peer-to-peer decentralized federated
microblogging for communities
All kinds of aspect or or maybe instead of mastodon if mastodons because it's not my thing
It's not my thing if mastodons not your thing. Maybe something like matrix
Rocket chat something like these where we have individual components now that are getting pretty damn good
I've come a long way. Yeah, especially
Mastodon and matrix and rocket chat they could truly replace slack and Twitter and Facebook and Skype
Decentralized federated ready to go
open-source code
Nobody owns it. These components are coming together
Cryptocurrencies play a piece in this
Mastodon plays a piece in this web torrents and peer tube could play a piece. I don't know if a peer tube is gonna be it
But surely some of you thought around sat around and gone what the hell is it gonna take to
To replace Facebook. What's it gonna take to myspace Facebook? What's it gonna take to replace YouTube?
What's it gonna take to replace Google Docs?
it
seems like an in track like when we at the heart when Windows 98 second edition released and
Windows 2000 released I
Couldn't foresee a world where the entire industry wasn't completely dominated by Microsoft. Yeah, that was the future then
It was impossible to see it because Microsoft owned the entire landscape at that moment
That's what serious people did to get work done. Yes to make money
We're at the we're at the same point now where there's these open-source initiatives these p2p initiatives these decentralized initiatives
That are making cracks in these platforms
Nobody's giving you one solution that ties it all together
Nobody's just gonna give you a package where you can go create an account and link it with your Facebook account and get going
It's not there yet
But if you know how to spin up a few servers, you know how to set up a few systems
You could replace a lot of these information empires now with open-source software
I and I I don't know if it's yeah
I don't think any of it's quite there for JB because the the core problem
With people that are creating a lot of content or people that are writing a lot of code and open-source is
That's what you have time for that's what you have passion for and that's what you have time for
You don't have time to go build this stuff at the end of the day. We've tried to use matrix
We ended up back on slack
Because we don't have time to run matrix
But I feel good that it's close like it's so close that I could almost taste it
Like I could almost launch a podcasting network based on these technologies today
Almost and get somewhere with it. I wonder too does that open any room for you know small businesses, right?
Can you could you have a local IT firm that runs it for you?
But then you still have the option should they go out of business or whatever else
You could you could take that infrastructure and bring it in-house if you absolutely need I can't I can't say who but I was just
talking to a commercial
Company that wants to go they want to take something they've been developing for 20 years and they want to make it open source
And it's they're trying to avoid the whole throw it over the wall and now all of a sudden
Here's a huge open source code dump right because they want people to actually engage with them and improve it and maintain it and so
They're there at this stage right now like how do we build a community around this in a way?
That's genuine that gets them engaged that isn't tied to these these platforms people can just pull the rug out from underneath us
This is conversations. I've been having with them, and I'll talk about more when they go public
But it's it's a real problem, and it's something I've been thinking about in the context of Jupiter broadcasting recently
especially with all the patreon stuff going on
I'd really like to hear what the audience thinks is best what works best for them out of these solutions
We talked about right because that they're the other really important half of this whole puzzle totally
That's the whole point of this is that we don't want middlemen
We can't have these these kinds of fluctuations that really hurt the communication and the relationship between us and the audience
I want to build a business and I want to sit down here
And I want to work and I want to make shows and I don't want to be sitting here worrying about jumping funding
Platforms every two years or that just is not sustainable. It's dangerous
It's risky and that's in the way of you making making this awesome content at the same time
I got to be where the audience is
and I
The none of these answer the whole network effect problem other than perhaps people just understand
This is the way things have to go, but boy Wes
Look at this stuff. You know peer tube and whatnot. I am very excited about the future
It's not quite there yet
But geez if I'm not gonna be watching it every single week to see where it gets right and there are a lot of issues
as you as you just pointed out right that there's not that level of polish that level of integration the level of
Constantly everything wants you to use this account. It's tied in everywhere. If you have it, it's easy, right?
Or it's apps on every device, etc
There are a lot of those blockers and sometimes especially running a business. Those are enough where you're just like
I don't have time for this. It's not important enough
But a lot of those are ultimately I think surmountable problem
It doesn't isn't that and isn't that why it also has to start with the technical elite the the open source crowd like it
Needs some early adopters to start shaving down these rough edges and making this shit usable and productizable
like somebody has to do where we need to do better as a
Technological elite doing better interface with with people in design and we've talked about some of this on this show and other shows on the
Network, but bringing those people in, you know an open source version of a of the whole product manager design UX UI consultant
And so we can have this start with yes
It works for the technological elite something that ultimately can be palatable to to everyone
What do you think bashful is the network effect too much to get over?
You know cuz if if I build these things, it doesn't actually mean anybody will come
Well, that's always gonna be the challenge
I mean look at the same thing like even with the chat program if you break it down like unless your people are there
You're not going anywhere. So something something it's a chicken and egg. Something's got to be there first
That's gonna draw people over there whether it's people whether it's content. Maybe it's exclusivity
I mean a little hard to tell right I agree and and Eric the IT guy you were pointing out that yeah
This is all good. But then once you do all of this now, you're maintaining servers
You're like next cloud like if I go set up next cloud
I'm maintaining next cloud instead of just using Dropbox and that's that's a that's a split of my focus, isn't it?
Right and and I'm really torn on this particular issue
Because I've spent the last year separating myself from the from the Apple
The Apple walled garden. I've given up iCloud Drive and moved to next cloud
That's that's all well and good for myself
But what about what about my spouse who is right tied?
Very very concretely to her to our iOS and to our macOS devices
much less the rest of my family who are very tech illiterate and
And so do I just start walking over to them and animal Linux laptop with next cloud
And become like the IT guy for the whole family. You may have to be the admin and you're not getting paid for this
Yeah, that's a great point. And the thing is they don't have your moral convictions or your motivations, right?
So while they care about their technology working well, and they care about having power over it, you know
They just want their shit to work. Can I cast beer tube to my TV in the living room? It's time to watch TV
exactly exactly and
You're completely right
is it you sort of take the burden on as the as the advocate and that's why I feel like
Some places will be able to be early at like Jupiter broadcasting can be an early adopter of this before say
PewDiePie or some other large youtuber can because they're sort of tied down by the popularity of their YouTube platform
Where we have a technical audience
We've always just you viewed YouTube as one of the many publishing platform not our only publishing platform
Like maybe Linus tech tips does you know, they were they're all in on YouTube. We're like, yeah, we'll send our videos there
But really we're all in on our RSS doesn't define go subscribe to the RSS if you want the canonical versions of our show
without getting censored
But we'll publish we'll publish there because they got apps for days
They got every single platform if you got shitty balance situations like I do
YouTube's one of the few things that actually works like there's reasons to be there, right?
But yeah, it's really hard to sell it unless people understand the technical reasons
So Eric I take your point completely because it would be
Essentially our job to make all that happen
And then you have the fact that really it's a huge overhead for all of the projects or other content creators
It's it's not an easy solution yet
Do you have any follow-up thoughts Eric before we move on?
Well, I mean my family I could pull it off with but what about my neighbors and what about their family someone who doesn't have
An open-source enthusiast like a lot of us here at JB. Yeah, I
I don't know
Maybe they're unsavable just like the normals won't use encryption ever unless it's done for them automatically
I don't know. I wonder if there's any room for like
Local government or like small community run services, especially in some sort of mesh system, right?
You know your your community association perhaps has a few of these services maybe just for intra community communication
But possibly providing more, you know more actual services wouldn't that be something like a like a community mesh network? Yeah
I like that that connects out to a greater Internet at that point potentially to like retrieve other broader things
Yeah, and maybe maybe you pay a little bit
Maybe you've hired a local admin to help keep everything running
I don't know
I feel like I want to punt to the audience and ask them what they think about
solutions to replace these information silos these proprietary platforms and
What do you think about?
Linux users brunting this a little bit
you know like
You've got to go to a special website. Maybe you got to go create a mastodon account
Um, and I don't know not a big mastodon fan, but you know what I'm saying?
Like just from like a from a theoretical standpoint
should we should we be the ones to brunt this to help the rest of the web or
Do should we just get to sit back and enjoy just like everybody else?
Like why does that to be our fucking job? Why does it gotta be us that does this?
Why is it our burden that you know, I'm not Batman. I'd answer you but I'm busy watching YouTube over here
Haha liar you're busy building gentoo right now. Actually, mr. West. Why don't we do a little gentoo checking?
How is it going over there got a thumbs up or a thumbs down right now? What are you thinking?
Well, it's going pretty well right now
We're emerging XFS frogs because I know how much you love XFS
I do but I couldn't build this thing on ext4 with you around. I mean, I would quietly judge you
I mean, I don't know if I would have vocalized it. I would have seen the look in your eyes
So we're doing that then we're gonna get some bootloading going and then later we're gonna see will it come back online?
All right, that's pretty good. So is that what I'm hearing in the back right now is XFS building. Oh, yeah, absolutely
It's nice. I didn't realize that if you output the terminal to the sound card, we could actually hear it right there
Yeah, that's nice. Wes. I think I could fall asleep to this
West building software you wake up. You feel really productive
All right, well speaking of feeling really productive
Linux academy comm slash unplugged you go there to sign up for a free seven-day trial
It's a platform to learn more about Linux
But more importantly it's a platform for you to feel secure about your knowledge and how to manage all of this stuff
You get a hands-on experience
It gives you the real confidence self-paced in-depth video courses on every Linux cloud and DevOps topic
And if you get stuck, you got a question something doesn't make sense
They got real human beings that are happy to help you and answer your questions. They'll spin up cloud servers on demand
They'll match the distribution you've chosen for your courseware. You're busy
I understand that and they got course schedulers for that and they got learning paths to go in deep right on a specific
like a series of content
Time to get up to speed on open stack
Let's say just as an example
They got learning paths that will do that for you
You you got you got a couple of days to get up to speed they got that for you
They got certification training if that's what your goal and they have practice exams and quizzes to help you get ready for all of that
so when you go in to take the big test, you kind of feel like it's old hat and
That's invaluable. They also have nuggets. We're
Again with the holidays family
I understand you're busy a little bit of nuggets here and there you go in there
You a little sparkly bit of wisdom deep dive for 10 minutes 15 minutes 45 minutes
I don't care depends on the topic and then you walk away like damn. I just got some value damn learn one single topic
Linux academy comm slash unplug sign up for a free seven-day trial community stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members
iOS and Android apps you can study on the go
Tools to listen to like lesson audio or read stuff offline
No internet connection required and then public profiles to make sure you can show your employer your contractor
Or just yourself all of the great things you've accomplished
It's gotten so easy to to sell Linux Academy
Like if you have if you're trying to learn some new stuff on the job sure
They have a ton of good materials
You can send to your boss or just like walk them around
They've got a great site and it's really useful and it does have all those tools so that your boss or others can check in and
Make sure that people are actually learning. Yeah, and they have team training too, which is nice
Yeah, if you do have a group of people Linux Academy comm slash unplugged you go there you get the free seven-day trial and
Support the show Linux Academy comm slash unplugged in a big
Thank you to Lynx Academy and as we record this here episode just two hours ago. They have announced new courseware
They're always adding new courseware you constantly getting value out of the subscription
but they've just added a whole bunch of new stuff on AWS on
Serverless applications all of that stuff, so if you're hearing that stuff thrown around a lot definitely go check out Linux Academy Linux Academy comm
Unplugged and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program so mr.
Wes as we sit here today
Many many of people have asked us about gentoo so it's time for us to do a little gentoo
And we've been covering gentoo now for weeks on the show
Building up to it some people thought it would never happen, but I'm happy to report for the last two weeks now going on three weeks
Mr.. Wes Payne has been building a gentoo install
And we've been checking in on that gentoo install now
So mr.. Wes
That's me
Last week we decided going on sway this week you've decided on XFS oh
Oh also last week you picked your kernel build options as well damn
This is going pretty good kinds of fun unique options here, so what is next on your horizon?
So you did a stage three install let's recap so you did a stage three install after we decide well
What's the audience most likely to do so you did a stage three?
Which is all pretty good, so what's next after we get XFS built?
After that we're gonna make sure that it actually reboots. That'll be that's a that's a big step right there really
Really, you know you never know I've been running it from the install environment
So we've been a little privileged in that respect
I'm pretty confident will I think the kernels pretty nice
So it should just come right up a little mount all the file system now
Have you have you done gentoo install before or is this your first is this your first year on the show?
I wasn't like one not my first ever
But the last time was probably like six years ago, and I was also building it to run on a Wii
So it was a little bit different. I'm sorry what yeah, I'm so it was a little bit of a different environment
Let me check up back checking here
I
Yeah, I just got a note from my producers here
You can't install Linux on a Wii so turns out you can what that's right you put gentoo on it
Yeah, and it worked super well. What did you do?
We just like hooked up to the whole at the time
I didn't have like a really good up it
This is before like the Raspberry Pi was super popular or anything like that
So it wasn't a great like streaming option
But I got into that I installed M player and I could just like stream stuff right to it playing all around my house
You it was awesome to see just a to the Nintendo. We did it have internal storage. You could write to like you got axe
Like so you could put an SD card and and you're using this to watch videos on your TV watch
Yeah, watch some videos play a lot of audio play live streams from the Internet
Okay, I just I'm having a hard time understanding the use case where somebody goes to themselves
Hey, you know what?
I'm gonna do is I'm gonna take a Wii and I'm gonna put Linux on this thing and then I'm gonna use MPV
To watch videos when you could just get a Roku or something like I just was before those days
I mean, all right, it was maybe pretty primitive and I had an additional Wii sitting around so
So I've never done like a full traditional PC based gentoo install. So it's been actually a lot of a lot of fun
I gotta say I've been walking through the handbook
It's really quite nice. I'm used to the a little more barren version of like the arch wiki style
I've also installed oh, yeah thousand times. So I'm pretty familiar gentoo wiki does feel a little more verbose
Yeah, it's not a bad thing. They've got they've got some it's a little harder for the like
Hundred-foot view over you like quick like I know what this what's the key that I really need?
Cuz I don't need to like I'm not configuring this one for all I can emerge plenty of stuff later
If I need to I just want to know like what do I need? Yeah, there's a lot of really well commented configuration files
There's obviously a lot of hair has been put into this in certain terms of just getting you start
There's a lot. I think I still need to learn
I'm excited to have the system around to play with it
But so far it's been a pretty good experience
Hmm, especially considering that I'm doing this while also trying to do the show now
Have you there is a configuration file like the central configuration file in a jet in a gentoo install
Which I don't remember if you get to at a stage three where you go in there and you add your use flags
Oh, yeah. Have you done this already? Yes. I didn't configure them too much at this time
I was trying to keep it pretty simple. Yeah, that is kind of like the
the
Maybe the best thing about you is it?
Yeah
After this thing is a little work because because you can put a couple things in there that everything you build on your system
follows
those build rules so maybe it's like certain optimizations for your processor or
Your video card or or multiple cores or whatever it could be right?
And then you add all that in there and then everything you build gets a slight
Advantage just a little advantage and the idea is, you know, you do it for all of the things on the system from the
most basic tools all the way up to your graphical environment and
Every time maybe you get like a two to five percent edge
You can actually target the architecture instruction set that you're actually running on
Yeah
and you get all that flexibility where like maybe you don't like that they've
Configured this software with all the optional dependencies or maybe right, right, right
You can start to choose those things like I really like this lean and mean or I like it really fat
so that's the thing about
Linux distributions, right is they're built for
they're built for an Intel 64-bit compatible system and that's sort of the
overall
Large target that they go for but in Gentoo you can say well, yeah
but I have this specific version of Intel processor with these specific features and I want you to build optimally for that or
Or or close to it and some people believe it makes a big difference overall in your performance because every little thing has that edge
I don't know if it's true or not, you know in my experience
You almost don't notice it
But one of the things that brought me to Gentoo early on and the reason why I ended up putting on a ton of servers
Even though it doesn't seem like a good server OS
Is those those use flags and those build time options?
Allowed me to install versions of Samba and cups
They could do stuff that none of the other distributions could do at the time. And so there is a place for that with Gentoo
So I'll be really curious to see maybe we'll talk about that more like a future episode when you've gotten a little bit further down
The road right and there's more things that you know, especially when you're getting your graphical environment applications
That's really where it matters. There's the basic command line tools like how fast can they be?
I will say that that's your point though
Like, you know, it may not be it's not the server OS that you'd want to run just like hey
I'm running a server but but if you're a large organization or you have very specific needs or you're targeting specific hardware
It gives you this middle ground of control between I'm rolling my own full distribution and using whatever they've provided right you have this
Ability that for some people is like is the right choice and it does kind of feel like your OS when you're all done
Like cuz it's you know, like it's been built. Oh, yeah, that's right
It's been built with this in mind because I always wanted to build with this
Sorry, and if you're doing it on the server, you can probably also have you know
Build farms and other things you can produce one big tarball artifact that gets pushed to server. So there's a lot of options
Yeah, sure. All right, Wes. Well, it's been good to follow bringing back the old memories
the day is when I
actually bought
Two Apple excerpts. Did you ever see the Apple excerpt? Yeah, you know about the Apple excerpt really actually
Oh my gosh, nobody knows about the Apple excerpt
I swear cuz they don't you know, they they didn't sell a lot and they don't make them anymore
No, but the cool got right out of that market
So in full disclosure, I came into I came into a shop that had two of these rigs
and
They were neat
It was right when Apple switched over to Intel and one of the cool things that gen 2 supported about the Apple excerpt
Was the CPU of meters right on the front? Did you do you see these?
Did you ever actually see Apple excerpts in production? No, I've used them at SSH to them
I didn't actually get to see him wrecked
well
okay
so one of the great things about the Apple excerpts and I wish more servers would do this today because
Go figure Apple did it is they had on the front LED indicators
of
CPU load so you could look just at your rack and see how hard all of your yeah
And then they had this disk called the XServe raid
Which you could manage the raid at a hardware level and then they would just show up to the operating system
Linux included and so I walk in there and they had they had two XServes and an x-ray and the x-ray
Also had a CPU meter on so you could see how hard your disks were working. That's awesome
And I walked in there and I saw one day I saw these silver Apple servers in Iraq and I was like, what the fuck?
Yeah, I see these little LED lights bouncing and I'm like what is going on?
And of course they were crashing like crazy because they were running
Something called Mac OS 10 never heard of it
but I put Linux on there and I put gen 2 on there and it supported the LED indicators and
Boy, did they start they stopped having problems and then I attached the x-rayed storage. It was pretty pretty neat actually
I I went in thinking there's no way in hell
I'm gonna get gen 2 working on this custom-ass Apple hardware and
Sure enough it was it ran for three years in production
I wish I had done that because because mine was running OS X and I was at the time I was writing C programs to run
Like physics simulations and I had to like really carefully recompile them or get them ready because I was developing on Linux
Yeah, of course. That's awesome. Yeah, it was pretty great
It was pretty great because they were ready to toss these
Machines out because the max just kept failing and the XServes were decently built to like
One of the things that was it was kind of nice about them back in the day was that they they have these removable storage
Drives that were actually pretty convenient now. This is pretty common stuff, but it was kind of nice back then
Yeah, and so to be able to put gen 2 on them such gen 2 and then I believe I had 700 users
That were printing daily at least sometimes multiple often often multiple times a day
Through these two XServe printers or servers running gen 2 as CUPS servers
just so these two XServes running gen 2 would run CUPS and Samba and they would provide all
of the printing services to a
700 user bank and every time you came in and you got it like a balance statement or you made a deposit and they gave
You a receipt or anything like that?
It was all being generated through these Apple XServes running gen 2 for a bank
That's fast and it was one of those things where they would
They would have customers that were sitting there waiting for the printouts and the printouts weren't coming. Oh, I'm sorry ma'am, you know
Maybe if you come back tomorrow, we can give you a printout like stuff
You just can't do in banking. No, you don't do that in banking
You're a business and that was when they ran Mac OS and when we switched them over to gen 2 those problems went away
It was pretty pretty good pretty good and then eventually having a little gen 2 love affair right here
Eventually CUPS came to Mac OS, but it was that was much much much
Much later. Anyways, keep up the good work to us. I'm glad you're going with XFS. And that is the little gentoo challenge update
I'm having a ton of fun. So if anyone else has never installed gentoo
You just want something fun to do play around with Linux. I recommend it
yeah, I know we got a couple of people that are doing it along at home let us know how it's going and
Let's see. I think now now is the time for people to start betting on if Wes is gonna have to reload at some point
You
So you start taking your wages on that right now
Well, Wes Payne have to reload his gentoo installation stay tuned and find out but in the meantime, we're gonna leave you with that
We'll be back next week. We got lots of stuff in store
The year isn't over yet and neither is your unplugged program if you'd like to join us live next week, in fact
Come a little early next week because I think we're gonna be recording some of our holiday episodes
Next Tuesday over jblive.tv go to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash counter to get this show and all of the shows you may want to catch
Live converted to your local times on time zone by robots
That are likely paid in litecoin
Let's go with that litecoin also the subreddit Linux unplugged at reddit comm
Thanks so much for joining us and we'll see you right back here. Not tomorrow. Not the next day, but next Tuesday
Oh
Get it out of here
Believe I did pretty good. Didn't he? He's good studio, but it great. Yeah. Yeah
I forgot I was like wasn't even sure where he was up. You just see just so sleeping behind me the whole time
What a good dog. What a good dog. Alright, let's see if we can get a title for this thing mumble room
Thank you guys. You were excellent as always tight and concise
Appreciate it jvtitles.com
What do you think West? What should we name the son of a bitch? Well, I got a look at that titles first
Got some good suggestions here saving the world one pit at a time
Nice kid one at a time. I do like that. That's pretty good
I
Let's see if we can see if we can get let's see kill all system D platforming war zones. Look at you
So yeah, something about open source alternatives would be good
Open source options options for open source
My nose it just today. I was I was having some allergies
I've had some of those too. It's been rough this year. I don't know
Oh, I got a picture of the new dog on the Twitter's if you want to see
Levi do you want to be my new best friend? He does he does he really does. Perfect. He's
Rejection was gonna be pretty hard. Yeah. No, he wants to be your best friend badly
My nose itches and I'm sick and tired of having allergies all episode
I was basically rubbing scratching my nose and trying not to sneeze. You did a pretty good job. I had one sneeze
I did have one sneeze. It was unavoidable. I couldn't I couldn't help it. What about long live the excerpt? There we go
Yeah, right. I'm good. That'd be good
It's like it. It's almost like it. It's like I don't know how to describe it
It's like it it buzzes my nose is buzzing with itching right now
And like no matter how much you touch it. It's not it's not gonna change. It's just more it doesn't matter
It just constantly itches more and it's driving me crazy. I'm sorry. I'm sorry for about the sniffing and sneezing in the show guys
Punishing content creators. That's not bad. Where was that? Somebody submitted punishing content creators. That's not bad
What do you think Wes what do you think
Oh, that's perfect bashful. You had four excerpts. I didn't see any special. Nice. Yeah
Yeah, it's quite a while ago, but we had them around
Yeah, they ran OS 10 for a while and then they got repurposed to Linux and became a cluster. So yeah. Yes
Yeah, which version of links do you remember?
What were we running at the time I thought it was like yellow dot
Yeah, pretty much I don't think there were any other were they Intel or were they actually powered PC now
They think about it power PC. Yeah, the ones I had work. Yeah, no mine worked
I don't even think they ever made them as x86. No, they think about it
I think they were all power PC servers, which was what was so cool about them now that I recall
Yeah, first thought when he asked me about the distro is gonna say oh it must be right at because I was thinking yum
But yeah, no yellow dog
Yeah, exactly gotta get that yellow dog update manager from somewhere after all. Yeah, that's right