OK, so we have some pretty spooky audio.
All right, I'm going to play this.
This is a real thing observed by scientists.
See if you can figure out what it is while you're listening.
All right, Brent or Alex, do you have a guess as to what we're listening to?
Well, I have a guess.
I don't know that I know what it is, but it sounds to me like, let's say you're in Miami
right now and you might be at the, you know, the racetrack where they have the boats sitting
in the false water.
If you were underwater watching watching the race, that's what it would sound like.
Hmm.
Right.
Because not only is today Mother's Day, but it's also Formula One day.
So happy Mother's Day, everybody.
But go ahead.
What do you think it is, Alex?
I think it sounds a bit like plate reverb where they have the big metal plate in like
the basement of a recording studio, and that's how they create reverb.
I like that idea.
I think that makes it a lot less spooky.
When you find out what it is, it's extremely creepy.
This is the sonifications from a black hole that NASA has observed.
Right, Wes?
Yeah, that's right.
The black hole at the center of the Perseus galaxy cluster.
That's what it sounds like.
And it sounds like to me, thousands, maybe millions or billions of souls.
This is so cool because, OK, there's a lot of different sonifications, right, where you
take some data and you map it to sound.
But this is actually measuring pressure waves in hot gas in this galaxy cluster.
It's actually sound.
It's just, you know, 57 octaves below middle C.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
My name is Brent.
My name is Alex.
Hello, gentlemen.
I love these episodes.
It's one of these weeks where I can't tell you what we're about to talk about.
I got no idea.
We're each bringing a topic to the show and we're going to find out live with you what
each of us has to say.
But then, of course, we'll get into the traditional steaks and eggs and sides, I guess.
Hey, I brought biscuits.
Great.
You know, I was hoping.
But all I have over here is cider.
Anyways.
Are they sous-vided biscuits?
They are.
Are they sous-vided biscuits, really, we'll find out.
And then, of course, along with them biscuits, we'll have picks, some boasts, and a whole
lot more.
Well, let's just get right into it.
Wes, what did you bring to class today?
I thought I'd revisit a tool that I've been playing with more again, but I used to use
a lot.
And that's Canonical's LexD.
Oh, yeah.
Obviously, we use containers for basically all the things here.
But most of the time, we're running something like Podman or Docker.
I was thinking back on this, and it was when 1604 first came out, if you remember those
heady days, and Canonical had just started shipping ZFS.
Just built in, no fuss, no DKMS, like you just got ZFS.
I wanted to play with that because, you know, I dabble with ZFS, but mostly like from Freeness
on a free BSD system or similar.
So I rented a dedicated server, you know, had a couple of TB of storage, had a couple
of hard drives, nothing super fancy, but it was enough to start playing with like a, you
know, physical system I didn't have to run in my actual home lab.
And I got it all set up, had ZFS, had LexD on top, it was routed up with IPv6.
And it was really neat because it was almost like running my own little VPS setup because
you could just spin up all these like system containers, which is one of the things that
LexD does that's a little bit different than Docker, you know, it's almost like a virtual
machine, but it uses all the cool container tech.
And so I could spin up Bastion hosts, I could spin up whatever OS I wanted to play with.
It was a great way to just run like the latest version of Arch on a server.
What do you mean when you say it's almost like a virtual machine, like does it have
virtual devices?
What do you mean by that?
At least the way that you see containers run a lot, at least with the docker is these sort
of application containers, you know, where it's focused on one particular piece, right?
It's I'm running this process, a single thing, it's all, you know, declarative, you set it
out.
LexD runs what they call system containers, which is pretty much just like what you might
be used to when you run a full Linux operating system.
So it starts up system D, you can run multiple processes, but it isn't a virtual machine.
It's you know, it's using the container technology of, you know, C groups and namespaces and
that sort of thing to isolate it.
So you get all the nice bare metal performance, there's no overhead involved, but it's designed
to work as if you have a full system access.
Now this isn't for anything, it's not to compete necessarily with docker, I find it has a particular
sweet spot in the home lab for times where you don't need to scale things arbitrarily
horizontally.
Your end goal with this, it's not that how you're going to run the system, but you want
to be able to run multiple things and have a nice REST API on top to orchestrate it.
So how does the kernel model work with this, Wes, with containers, like typical like docker
containers, you would have one kernel shared amongst multiple processes with LexD.
How does that work?
Yeah, same thing.
So that in the container model, you get the host kernel in that case, I haven't really
used it for a while.
And it's been in the back of my mind, but it just hasn't been the thing that I've been
playing with.
We covered last month, LexD 5.0 in Linux action news.
And that's what kind of triggered me to think I should play with this again, because one
of the things they've added now is they also do virtual machines.
So you can do system containers, if you know you're okay with relying on the host kernel,
you want that density or just you know, that if that works for you.
But you now have basically feature parity on the VM side, including stuff like migrations
and snapshots, also clustering.
And they've added this whole overlay virtual networking.
It's powered by OVN, which then sits on top of like open vSwitch.
Okay, so this is like the networking layer.
So you've got this overlay network on top, but it can do some pretty wild stuff, including
if you've got like nice a nice Nick, like a Mellanox Nick can do offload hardware offload.
So it gets processed.
No, cool.
It can also talk BGP.
So you can, you can spin up new containers or virtual machines.
And it will do all the BGP peer with your routers and announce them.
So you don't have to worry about like, dealing with any of those routes, man, this seems
like really nice.
If you're an organization using this, and you just want to spin up some infrastructure
real quick.
That's great.
I wonder how deep we could take that rabbit hole, could we put Docker inside an LXD, and
then run libver inside the Docker that's inside the LXD.
So use that to run Docker inside the libver.
You see where I'm going?
Like how deep does the rabbit hole go here?
I think we have to find out I know it does at least support running itself inside of
itself because they've got to try it online and that's what it does.
That'd be fun.
That's a little inception right there.
That's pretty great.
And so my question to you is, are you looking at moving any workloads over to this?
I think I'm going to dabble, you know, I don't know.
It doesn't fit every use case and, you know, at work and I'm already quite comfortable
with both with Docker and dabbling with Podman.
But you know, it takes a different approach where sort of the, you know, the Docker and
Podman doing a lot of it kind of breaks things out and you're kind of assembling it or maybe
you're going to go run it on Kubernetes or Swarm or some other, you know, system doesn't
really care.
You get the pieces and you can go put it together.
LexD it's almost like ZFS in a sense where it presents more of a holistic, like I can
set this up on a server and it's going to go figure out all these things, including
fancy PCI pass through.
It's got all kinds of acceleration if you want.
So I think if you had some hardware and you wanted to get, you know, just wanted to manage
that and you maybe weren't a particular fan of say the libvert API, which I'm really not,
LexD might be an interesting thing to try.
I wondered, Wes, do you remember why past Wes got less interested and let this technology
fade for you?
That was a time where I was kind of just running more things.
Maybe I was a less busy version of myself or it was just, you know, containerization
was new.
Virtual machines were new.
I was also at a stage in my career where those were things that I was learning for the first
time.
Not quite the first, but you know, kind of first really trying to both learn them so
I could apply them at work, which we hadn't quite migrated that far.
So I was trying to, you know, get on the cutting edge.
I'm not running as many things these days.
I've tried to minimalize some of my personal infrastructure just to keep things simple,
especially I've just moved a lot in the past few years.
So I haven't wanted a big home lab that I've been dragging around.
And there is the employability of having a really solid understanding of Docker because
that is such a normal standard deployment now in the business world.
So if you're looking to build out like an employable skillset, I mean, not that LexD
isn't used widely, but Docker is probably more widely used.
As we've shown for better or worse, you can get quite far with, you know, just a Docker
compose file these days.
There's a lot of community momentum behind that.
But I think if you wanted to get more complicated or perhaps, you know, your VPS bill was getting
high and you wanted to like get a couple of bigger boxes that you were going to handle
on your own or something like that, you know, there's a lot of use cases where I just hadn't
really thought about LexD.
You know, I wonder if we're not going to discover a theme accidentally.
I almost can sense it because my story is about figuring out maybe I'm not using the
right tool for the job.
Your story is about the right tool for the for the job.
Mine definitely is.
Is it?
All right, Brent.
So, all right.
OK, here we go.
So tell us, Brent, what's been going on for you this week?
Well, as listeners might remember, I'm still sitting here with Alex.
Yeah, he's still here, people.
Will he ever leave?
Send us your feedback.
Raleigh's awful nice.
Alex has got a great place.
They're both very nice people.
You know, so I can understand, Brent.
I can understand.
I'd probably be in the same.
I'd probably be there if I were you, too.
You know, just before the show, he did make me an account on his Mac.
So.
Wow.
It finally happened.
You got a you got a local account.
That is a big step.
Probably means he expects you to come back to.
Yeah, I think he probably wants me to do a bunch of projects, it seems.
So being here has been a real opportunity because I've been able to sort of tap into
Alex's expertise a little bit and learn some things that I've had in mind for the last
few years, and this might be quite topical after our NixOS challenge.
Turns out Alex knows a thing or two about Ansible, and one of the main things I wanted
to learn while I was here was sinking my teeth into that a little bit and to see the differences
that I could at least grok so far between Ansible's advantages and those of NixOS, for
instance.
And I gotta say, it's been super fun.
For the last few days, Alex and I have been sort of diving in.
I think I'm pretty lucky because he's got all the shortcuts.
He basically said in a day and a half, he showed me everything he's learned in five
years.
So, right.
It's like you got sent to one of those expert courses, you know, you're at you're at the
Ansible boot camp, basically, except one on one.
Yeah.
And it's been a real treat.
I gotta say thank you, Alex.
I mean, that's the thing about Ansible that I always thought in the in the early days
was the learning curve is actually quite short.
And the complexity can ramp as quickly or as slowly as you need it to.
Like the basics of just installing a package or something like that.
We did that in, what, an hour or two?
Yeah, I think once you sort of describe the main structure underneath, installing packages
are super simple, which is really similar to the NixOS process.
Like wrapping your head around the concepts is kind of a big part of the hard part.
While you were doing that, did you have moments where you felt like, oh, this seems like a
lot of work to get something kind of fairly basic done?
I think had I not had the NixOS challenge that we did last month, I would have certainly
thought that.
But knowing that the work you put in has many advantages and is a real investment, then
it made looking at Ansible just make a lot of sense from that perspective.
I think probably the biggest thing that we struggled with, certainly me as the air quotes
instructor struggled with, was Ansible is a collection of a lot of little files all
glued together to build this configuration management structure.
I kind of struggled explaining, well, you need this directory, and then you need this
one, and then you need that.
I do open source all of my code on my GitHub at ironicbadger, if anybody's interested.
The number of times it said, well, if you look at my code on GitHub.
That repo is used to deploy all of my personal infrastructure, and that's Ansible as I understand
it.
In my defense, that's kind of like my living and breathing encyclopedia.
Alex, you touched on something that I found a little bit more difficult compared to NixOS,
for instance.
In NixOS, you can start with just a Nix config that has a default location.
One of the things with Ansible that you sort of have to get over a little bit is there's
a directory structure and expected files in certain places and an equally thick nomenclature
to go with the naming of those files and those, I don't want to say roles because that's actually
one of the names of something and don't want to confuse people too much, but that nomenclature
was a little tricky, and I think you saw me struggle with that.
Yeah, so there's a lot of domain specific language to learn, so you got to learn what
a playbook is, what a role is, what a task is.
Those are the three basic fundamental building blocks, and once you've got your head around
how those three different things kind of link together, I saw your progress kind of skyrocket,
and you went from how does this connect to that to being, oh, well, I just do this.
That's exciting.
Yeah, when it all clicks.
It's been fun, and Alex discovered a reason for me to also use some other pieces of software,
which was really great.
I think Proxmox was a thing that you threw me at to get a VM going so that we can play
on this.
Second mention of the show this week.
Yeah, because we could use snapshots on Proxmox because the VM storage is just backed by ZFS,
so it's really easy just to create a snapshot and run some Ansible, break some things, and
then roll back the snapshot.
This has been a really, really good sesh for you at Alex's place because you got your first
hands-on with the Raspberry Pi, which we talked about in Office Hours 3.
You've now got your first taste of Ansible and Proxmox, like Brent, this is major milestone
stuff.
Yeah, I got to say, it feels like a whole new world has opened up for me in a way.
The reason I wanted to bring that as my topic today was I hope I can encourage some other
people to even sink their teeth in a little bit and feel some of that excitement, especially
those who have joined us in the NixOS challenge because I feel like that was a part of the
conversation that came up often was, hey, what's the difference between the two?
Which one's more suited for me?
And I think it's worth diving in even just for an afternoon or something and seeing what
it might be able to do.
So I want to take a sidebar conversation that you and I had off air and bring it into this
conversation because I think it applies.
And that was, you were talking about how you had just deployed Umbral for yourself and
you felt like it didn't really work well with this new Ansible paradigm where you're kind
of prescribing a system because Umbral itself is essentially a small little orchestration
system in a box.
But I think what we realized there is there's a fundamental shift perhaps in the way you
look at how to build things now.
Can you expand on that a little bit?
It's true.
Yeah.
So to give a little context, the last time you and I, Chris, talked about Umbral, I believe
is here on the Linux Unplugged actually, it was maybe a month or two ago.
Which I should say is like this, you can set it up yourself as a self-hosting platform
to install lots of really awesome self-hosting apps and it's a Bitcoin node, although I guess
they're going to make that optional in the future.
It's a platform that sort of showcases some premier self-hosting apps and it manages all
of it as Docker containers with its UI.
So it itself is a platform in a sense.
Yeah.
And it can also manage a few Docker containers for you in sort of their, I don't know, Umbral
store if you will, which is actually really nice for people running this, I don't know,
on a Pi or something like that who don't necessarily have that much Docker experience.
So that's kind of neat.
So back then I sort of installed it, I think we did it in a VPS, Chris, do you remember?
Probably yeah.
Probably on Linode.
Yeah.
And I kind of followed their documentation, you know, note for note.
This time around, I thought, Alex and I are playing with this Ansible stuff.
Maybe this is a nice way I can just sort of integrate that into Ansible and have a little
tiny project to, you know, learn a thing or two outside of having Alex help me.
So you know, got up nice and early this morning to do that.
And I did discover a difference in how I understand how software is delivered.
Help me maybe explain it if I don't get it quite right, Chris, but it seemed to me that
Umbral, the way it's been packaged, you know, it uses Docker under the hood, but it kind
of tries to obfuscate that for me a little bit.
The way they package it is for those who don't necessarily have that expertise or that experience
with some of this containerization, you know, tool, toolkits, and they're trying to make
it as simple as possible.
You know, their default is to run this on a pie.
They have a pie image, which they call, I think they call it an Umbral OS, something
like that.
That's really great because you can kind of get up and running with the defaults pretty
quickly.
What I discovered trying to integrate this into my Ansible setup, the way Ansible works
is that you can use a few, Alex, help me with the wording here, but you can use a few modules
that are predefined in sort of the underlying Python code to do tasks that are really common.
So let's just say you want to install htop while there's a package module that will just
sort of know how to handle things.
So you just pass it a few little variables like the package you want.
I want htop and what state you want it in.
I want it to be present and then it just goes and figures out the rest.
What I ran into trying to get Umbral into my Ansible sort of setup was that they want
you to just kind of curl a script and most of what you do with Umbral is based on scripting
that they've included when you download, you know, their tarball.
And that's great because it's super simple to get up and running just by running one
script.
You don't necessarily understand the underlying technology in there.
Exactly.
Yeah.
But I was trying to use it as a way to understand the underlying technology, which I think is
going a little bit outside of what they were hoping someone would do.
You kind of jumped to a hundred, too, right?
Like you're getting started with this thing.
You chose a system that's like fighting against you and not designed to play nice with exactly.
So what you really what you've really come across, but now from the other side of it,
is the difference between something that's designed for consumer use and something that's
designed for production grade use and not that Umbral can't be used in production.
I mean, I'm using it in production and I like that because this is a one off isolated system
that isn't part of the overall JB infrastructure or anything like that.
I like that Umbral manages and orchestrates all of this for me.
I didn't use their OS, but I'm running some of their scripts.
I could also see a future where like this probably is not likely, but say we had a future
where boosts were representing like a third of our revenue or something like that.
Well, then I would probably want to migrate that to an infrastructure that was a lot more
managed and a lot more reproducible because it would be a real serious endeavor, right?
Like right now, I'm in the very early, very early stages where beta testing, all of that
kind of stuff.
It's a couple of years down the road before I really expect this to really gain traction.
And so it's not a quote unquote production grade setup yet.
And you know, some people probably would probably say that's not a great idea, but it has the
advantage of letting you get started fast.
Yeah, I would say Chris, when you and I in January wanted to play with this when I was
at the studio, we were able to relatively quickly get up and started with it.
I think most of our time was spent understanding all the concepts around it, but getting the
software up and running was super straightforward, wasn't it?
I find it interesting how the Umbral project provide all these scripts and they're essentially
an opinionated set of scripts that say this is how we think the world should be.
And Chris, I know that you with Home Assistant don't like it when they do that.
So what's different with Umbral versus Home Assistant?
Well, the key difference is they did let me deploy my own OS.
So I am managing the OS the way I traditionally manage an Ubuntu base, right?
So I still am applying all of that at that layer.
And then the stuff that runs in the container with the orchestration script, I just let
them manage.
But the underlying OS and storage and all of that is under my control.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Linode makes it simple, affordable and accessible to deploy and manage a system for yourself,
or maybe for your customers in the cloud.
And they do it at a better price and better performance in those large hyperscalers that
have just endless options and want to basically lock you into their platform.
Linode is how we run everything that we've built in the cloud for the last few years.
And you can tell when you use it, if you're a long time Linux user, you can smell this
kind of stuff.
You can tell they love Linux.
That's where the whole inspiration for the product came from.
They started 19 years ago when this stuff was just getting baked into the kernel.
They learned along the way that customer support is critical.
So they've invested in having the best support in the business.
And this is probably the number one signal I get back from the audience.
Number two is definitely performance.
But I often hear like that because somebody just like had some sort of disaster happen,
they blew something up or I don't know.
And they contact me like, you wouldn't believe how they saved me.
And they stayed on the phone.
It was the first person that answered.
But on top of that, they really just have some of the best options.
And they have 11 data centers for you to choose from.
Each one is screaming fast because they are their own ISP.
They've invested in MVME storage.
They've invested in Epic AMD processors.
So they've really, really made sure these things perform.
And then they have a bunch of great backend features like firewalls and object storage
and a powerful DNS manager, Kubernetes and Terraform support, and of course Ansible support.
So they really, really make it a compelling option if you're doing infrastructure as code.
And along those lines, and I'll put a link in the show note, they have released a white
paper, I guess you could call it as such.
It's really an ebook, I guess.
It's about infrastructure as code.
And it goes through things like Terraform, Ansible, Puppet, Chef, and Salt.
And it kind of explains all of it through the entire book.
And it gives you a sense of what each technology is about and how it might fit into what you
do.
It's just a really good resource.
And I've mentioned it on one other show, and I got really great feedback from the audience
on it.
So go check the show notes for that.
Or you can just Google Linode infrastructure as code ebook, and you'll see what I'm talking
about.
But go get $100.
Go kick the tires.
Go build something.
Go learn something.
It's a great opportunity.
And they have a bunch of one-click app deployments too.
You can get things like a Minecraft server, Nextcloud, GitLab, lots of stuff, one click.
Go check it out.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
One question I did run into coming back to Ansible was how to install non-repo software.
Because the way Ansible, at least I understand, is the straightforward method for installing
software uses your auto-detected distributions package manager to install software.
And one of the questions I ran into pretty quickly was, well, how do I install software?
What's not in the package manager's repos?
And Alex, you had a pretty good answer that I think is worth sharing.
There's a few ways.
And you're quite right.
The default package module will auto-detect whether it's running on YUM or DNF or APT
or YAST or Pacman, whatever it might be.
And that's one of the beauties of Ansible versus, say, the Nix approach, is it transposes
across Linux as a whole, the entire ecosystem, pretty much.
Where Nix OS is, they have their own packaging system that you're pulling software from.
And you learn the Nix OS thing, and you now know Nix OS.
But if you get a new job at somewhere that's running Suzy, you've got to learn Suzy now.
So that's one of the key things.
But coming back to your question, there's a few different ways.
Ansible has the concept of Ansible Galaxy, which is a bit like Docker Hub.
So you specify a remote repo, a remote source that you can pull in.
In the case of your question originally last night, it was Docker.
How do I install Docker?
You can pull Docker from your repo in your package manager.
But quite often, the version of Docker that's in there is out of date or it's not packaged
very well or it has a weird name.
And so what I tend to do is I tend to rely on Ansible Galaxy roles for that.
And Jeff Geerling, who was on Self-Hosted a little while ago, he writes a metric S ton
of different roles that he uploads to Ansible Galaxy.
One of them is Docker.
And so you can reuse Jeff's expertise to install those sorts of packages by specifying a couple
of lines in your Ansible, and I do mean only a couple, which is geerling-guide.docker.
Install that role from Ansible Galaxy and just magically Docker will be installed.
Yeah, it is sort of magic.
And you can do that for a bunch of other services.
Tailscale was another one that we did.
So we went away on Ansible Galaxy and found a role that installs Tailscale.
And it actually did some really neat stuff.
We ended up having to go and grab an authentication key from the Tailscale admin console.
And two minutes later, not only was Tailscale installed, but also this role had authenticated
that server with my Tailscale account without me even really realizing that's what it was
doing.
And I just found that really cool.
I'm reusing this Tailscale expert's knowledge that I didn't even know I could do that.
Yeah, they're like these little, as far as I understand it so far in my little mental
model, they're like templates to use in your Ansible roles.
And you asked me a question last night about how do I know that these Galaxy roles are
safe to run.
The beauty of all of them is that they're all open source.
So the Jeff Geerling stuff, for example, if you go to Ansible Galaxy and search for Jeff
Geerling, there's a GitHub repo link in every single Galaxy role.
You can go and look at the code.
And one of the things I truly love about Ansible over any other configuration management software
is that it executes tasks in a linear fashion.
So if you write task one, do this, task two, do that, it won't try and be clever and cute
and do these things in the order that it thinks is the most sensible.
It will execute them like a bash script would, line one, then line two, then line three.
And so it's very easy to understand that this task happens here, and then it does this.
And for me, as a layman at the beginning when I was learning Ansible, I found that so helpful
because there's a whole extra layer of complexity that I don't have to wade through.
And in terms of reading open source code, we often say this in the community of, I'll
just go and audit the code.
It's open source, go audit it, and you'll be fine.
But with Ansible, you actually can.
You can see that this five line task does this, this five line task does that.
Yeah, it's quite human readable, I would say.
Yeah, for sure.
And for me, that's one of the huge, huge benefits of it.
So you've got code reuse out of the box, that's a massive DevOps checkbox facilitated there.
You've also then inadvertently created a source of truth, which is your source code repository,
which you then should be putting into Git or something like that to manage the version
controlling there.
The only real pitfall really is if you start using Ansible and then decide, oh, I just
want to quickly install a package on the command line natively, like, you know, want to do
sudo apt-get install htop, right?
And you don't put that then into your Ansible repo.
And if you do that over a week, you've got a very small amount of configuration drift.
If you do that over a month, it gets a bit bigger, but very quickly after a year or so,
you end up in the way the fact that your desired state in Ansible is nowhere near what reality
is on that server.
And so once you commit to doing it with configuration management, you've really got to go all in
and try and do it completely forever that way.
I've been really enjoying this journey and I hope to continue it.
Oh, right.
I go now.
I go now and I just realized that my topic is encrypted in the show notes again.
I like to do that.
Create a little problem for yourself, eh?
I have, but...
Do you remember the password?
No, but you know what I have is I have this handy little app right here.
It's a Rust app and it will basically encrypt text as AES, whatever you choose.
I chose 8-bit AES.
I love security.
I don't really care, but I thought I'd start with a story that was sent in to me by a whole
bunch of you out there and it's about something I haven't talked about very much and it's
one of my absolute favorite Linux boxes, my little Starlink Dishy.
And there is this week a new announcement for Starlink owners about a portability option
coming.
So you can now take your Starlink with you, you're not locked to the region that you signed
up for.
And I had noticed they were beta testing this because I got bit by this region availability
thing.
I moved out of my region.
Oh no.
Set up at a new place.
Just no internet.
And there was no capacity for me.
But then a couple of days later, it just started working.
And the thing about the Starlink setup is if you use their app with their router, you
can open up the app and go into debug mode.
You'd like this, Wes.
You go in there and it just tells you like all the raw log information that the little
Dishy has.
And I could be wrong, but I think there's either one or two different Linux boxes inside
that little Dish that talks to the satellites.
And you can see what it's doing.
And in there, there was this little flag about portability or roaming or something like that
that had flipped to true.
And it turns out they were beta testing this and I was benefiting for free.
And now they're rolling out for a $20 add on.
I had that.
I mean, so many people sent that in to me and it is really cool.
But unfortunately, I got a bit of a tale to tell you.
You see, I was packing up my Starlink the other day.
Yeah, that's right, Wes.
I don't like how this starts.
No, it's not good.
You see, I was getting ready for our trip out into the woods.
I put little Dishy into stow mode, as they call it, and I packed it up.
And a few days ago, i.e. Friday, I decided it was time to hook it up, get some additional
tubes into the home because we needed more internets, little kids, you know.
I get it all set up, I put it out in the grass field, I power it up because it's on a smart
plug.
This is one of the ways I control it during the night is I sometimes turn it off and it
just sort of sat there limp, dead, never looking up at the stars, never asking what else is
out there.
Can I be more than just what I am?
It just sits there limp in stow mode.
And I'm watching the app and all of a sudden this little red air comes up and it says Starlink
motors are stuck.
And I walk up to it and I can hear like a weird buzzing, but nothing else is happening.
I rebooted.
I mean, I went through.
Oh, no.
I probably went through six hours of trying to get this thing to come back to life, just
like refusing to accept my harsh reality.
I mean, I was bummed, bummed, Wes, crushed, because, you know, you go from cellular to
Starlink and it's a pretty big upgrade.
And I was so crushed.
And so I just refused to accept.
I thought maybe I could move it just right and get the motor.
What if I smash it a bit or jiggle it or toss it up in the air?
Plus, this is the round dishy, which is reportedly overbuilt and more robust and has more antennae
in it.
So you broke the strong one?
Yeah.
And the new square one, which is smaller, is supposedly not quite as robust.
It's more like...
Quite svelte.
Yeah, it is smaller.
That is nice.
So I opened up a support ticket and now I understand why Starlink business is five hundred
dollars a month and the number one feature is prioritize support because I have heard
nothing back.
One automated reply and that's it, right?
And I'm trying to get all my ducks in a row.
I'm trying to like pre-upload the debug info, but I look like an idiot because when you
use the app, it has like this copy debug info option.
Really handy, I thought.
I'll get a jump on this because in the debug info, it clearly shows that the motors aren't
working, right?
And it shows that it's not obstructed otherwise.
It's incredible what it knows about itself, actually.
It's remarkable when you hit copy in the app.
It just seems to be copying the debug info for the app and the router, but not the Dishy.
So I realize that.
I'm like, oh, my bad.
So I re-upload it again thinking, well, this time I was to captured it.
Nope.
So now I have two tickets where I have like bad debug info in there and I look like a
total new.
But so I've done like three responses to this ticket and I've heard nothing back yet.
I can kind of take a guess because I've been in this this spot before.
I can kind of guess where the satellites are like during the day.
So I kind of like, you know, like weekend at Bernie's style, kind of like positioned
it in the direction of the satellites or like, you know, if you're old enough, you might
remember like having to tune in rabbit ears on your television.
Yeah, I would do.
I'm doing that trying to point this thing up into space.
Right.
And it gets a bit of a connection.
And so I can download stuff for a bit and I'm getting like 100 megabit connection and
everything's good.
But then as the satellites move, it doesn't adjust and I lose connection.
You might need like a home assistant integration that can automate retuning.
I need like a motor.
I looked into like used dishes, but they go for like a thousand bucks on eBay.
And it's not even clear how you even associate that with your account because these dishes,
you know, they connect to your account like a fifth support ticket for that.
Yeah, I'm going to definitely support tickets so I can get like temporary connection.
But then I lose it.
But I've heard like when when support does engage with you, it tends to be really good.
But I was looking at the option.
So they have this ridiculous five hundred dollars a month Starlink service that they're
going to roll out.
Have you seen this?
It's their business version.
And supposedly it's a more robust antenna and you get more like 300 megabits instead
of like one hundred and fifty megabits.
It's nice about the same latency.
OK, but the number one feature they list on their support and I it dawned on me right
now, like I could almost see the utility of it for the business because without I realize
without Starlink, I'm S.O.L. on remote broadcasts, really, or I go back to cellular, which was
always so horrible.
It could be pretty great, you know, like if you drug it with you into the studio studio
has Internet outages.
That'd be a solid backup.
Sometimes I mean, it's just I can't justify the price now.
But if I canceled all my all my cellular data plans, which I have three different cellular
data plans, I'd probably almost pay for it.
Connectivity is a big deal, right?
I mean, this is what my whole job's online.
So when I'm broadcasting remotely, which I'm going to be in a couple of weeks because I'm
taking Jups in to get it ready for a summer road trip, I'm going to need to do, I think,
at least Coder from southern Oregon.
And I was planning to rely on Starlink to do that.
And I don't really know what happened.
I'm thinking either it fell or something in transport, like I tried to set it, but it's
in a storage base.
I couldn't see what happened.
Right.
But I just took it out and it wasn't working.
I guess would be the snails got in there again.
Might have been there were there were a surprising amount of snails living in the in the pole.
But when I took it down, I looked in the pole and there's like a half a dozen snails all
over the thing.
The good news is that it seems like SpaceX is serious about supporting hashtag vanlifers
and RVs.
In fact, Elon Musk tweeted that Starlink is awesome for RVs camping or any activity away
from cities.
Yeah, I mean, it definitely is right.
So I would describe it as life changing.
I really would.
I mean, imagine going somewhere where there is nobody around for a dozen miles.
You don't have any other connectivity.
And you put this little dish up in a field and you're getting 150 megabits down.
I can't I can't even with that.
It's and it's, you know, sometimes 20 milliseconds or so, which is fine for VoIP and stuff.
It works.
I'd love lower, but it gets the job done.
So it really is a life changing kind of thing.
And I just am always, always happy to see use cases like this for Linux, too.
Like that's always in the back of my mind that I'm using Linux to talk to space.
Now that I've gone through this experience, I can kind of see, like, say I was doing the
shows out of the RV on the regular and not out of the studio.
I think I'd see I could see the logic in getting a business grade tool, right?
Using the right tool for the job kind of thing, you know, in the meantime, I'm hoping to get
a good support experience.
If anybody at Starlink is listening, look up my ticket for me, help a brother out.
He's been waiting a couple of days.
I'd really like to get connected back to the Internet again.
Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Get started with a free trial for teams or enterprise or even a personal plan at Bitwarden.com
slash Linux.
Bitwarden is the easiest way for an individual or a business to store, share and sync all
kinds of sensitive data.
We use it here for our passwords, of course, and we love that Bitwarden is open source.
It's trusted by millions in their community.
And of course, businesses are using it worldwide.
Our business, Jupiter Broadcasting uses it.
It's a really handy way to work with teams of people when you have common resources you
need to sign into.
And that's really where the password hygiene can fall down.
And now recently, Bitwarden has also rolled out username generators, which, man, oh, man,
I can't believe I hadn't thought of this earlier.
So now not only will each one of my sign ins for these different services I use, especially
when it's not like a public profile, it's just something I'm using to manage an account
or something like that.
I'm not sure why I was ever using the same username for all of them.
And if your email provider supports it, like Gmail, where you can do the plus in the address,
Bitwarden figures that out, too.
And it will support that.
The username generator is such a great idea.
And then you save it all in Bitwarden.
Using a good password manager to keep different passwords for different websites is probably
one of the number one things you can do for your security online.
You know, it takes sometimes a hard lesson to figure it out, but I bet a lot of you already
know this.
If there's somebody out there who's maybe doing things a little less than ideal, point
them to bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Get them started.
And then for our community, one of the things that gives us peace of mind is that if you
want, you can self-host.
I've opted to use a Bitwarden cloud.
I feel like they're probably going to do a better job of managing that than I will.
But I know some of you out there just prefer to run it all on your own infrastructure.
I like that Bitwarden gives you that flexibility.
And then I think the other thing that's key to it is that there's actually a really large
active community on their forum and on Reddit to help with all that kind of stuff.
So you're not just off on an island by yourself either.
It's really nice and it gives me the confidence to use Bitwarden and it gives me the confidence
to recommend it to our audience.
So go get started for free at bitwarden.com slash Linux.
That's a great way to get started, make your online security better, and you support the
show and recommend it to somebody who needs this advice.
You know they're out there, bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Majid wrote in and he pleaded with us, could you read my feedback on your lovely show?
That would make my year.
So I thought we could do that.
And there's also a question here.
If you are in contact with the NixOS devs, could you ask how accessibility is going with
the installation?
I'm blind and would like to try out NixOS and the NixOS challenge if possible.
All right, we'll put feelers out there and if we hear anything back, we'll relay it here
on the show.
That's a great question.
And I wonder too if, and maybe somebody could let me know for my own edification, is this
something that a VM software could help solve, like a VM that supports screen reading?
I wonder too there.
I don't really understand how that works.
So I'd love to know for my own education if that is indeed in the works and if there is
another solution our listener could employ.
And now it is time for Le Boost.
Our first boost is from the Golden Dragon with 4500 sats.
How'd this Linux time machine get here?
Oh well, on my journey, I would have stuck out the pain points I had in college with
my Wi-Fi drivers not working and just figured it out.
Back then, I didn't have the same patience I have now and that would have made all the
difference.
I love the idea that the audience took this idea of the time machine and sent us a few
of their own ideas.
Marcel wrote in with a similar kind of theme for 2000 sats.
He said, I wish I could say my biggest Linux regret was rising i3 gaps instead of paying
attention to my undergrad classes.
Probably my biggest regret was not learning NixOS and Docker back when those things were
just coming out.
Thanks for taking us along on the time machine.
It was fun.
Another great boost came in from the Muzo 2000 sats.
Thank you very much.
Regarding ARM hardware, there are the SBBR and EBBR specifications that are supported
by recent single board computers and ARM server hardware, which allows generic ISO images
to be booted on compliant hardware.
Been listening since early 2020.
Keep up the great work.
Well, thank you.
The amazing rain sent in a boost and caught us.
Did you guys announce the results of the Nix server poll?
So in our NixOS challenge results, we asked the audience if we should consider nuking
and paving our local server setup here, going from OpenSUSE Tumbleweed as the base OS and
going for more like a Proxmox Nix kind of setup.
I'm feeling nervous.
So we did get the results and we had almost 300 respondents, which I've actually found
even that low can still be representative.
I think people didn't vote on it as much because it was buried in what was our most show notes
we had ever had for links.
Of course.
So we asked, should we use NixOS as our cloud and local server OS going forward?
And with 57.44% of the vote, the audience said, yes, keep us posted with 42% of the
vote going to stick with SUSE.
It was a 57% vote for yes.
Go with Nix.
That feels like a really close result.
Yeah, I don't know.
Should we do both?
What do you think, Wes?
How do you how do you feel about this, Wes?
I think we have some work to do.
I could see also kind of having our cake and eating it too.
Like if we do VMs.
Wait, you brought cake?
I should have.
I should have said that.
But if we did VMs, we could do Nix base and then open SUSE tumbleweed VMs or something,
right?
Like there's still maybe a role for tumbleweed here, right?
All right.
We install open SUSE and then we install LexD and then we run Nix.
Right.
This again, this election is being called into question.
You see, we had some meddling with the last election.
There was lizard meddling and now it is called into doubt this election.
I don't know what to do.
We'll have to keep you posted because clearly we have not figured out this controversy yet.
We should never have left Arch.
You know what?
Maybe that's the lesson.
All right.
Our last boost 1200 SATs from the Computer Guy.
I absolutely love the shows.
They inspired me to revive my own podcast.
Oh, that's great.
JB is my favorite thing to tune into online.
Well, thank you, the Computer Guy.
Also thank you to some boosts from the Spherical Cow.
He sent a couple of thank you boosts.
We also have a few of you out there that are streaming in SATs while you listen.
Of course, thank you to our members.
We are actually working on boosts for the member feed because that's a frequently requested
feature, but we have to build out a lot of other infrastructure first.
So it's not going to be anytime soon, but it is on our radar.
We are detailing out like those new website plans, things that will be new member features,
stuff that we're building out over the summer.
We are detailing that out in office hours.hair, starting with episode three and then kind
of doing it fortnightly from there.
So join in.
Listen to that if you're curious about where all that's going.
We have a pic.
I think you found this one, Wes.
Yeah, but you, you tried it out.
I think it's called Liar Bird.
It's a voice changing app, simple and powerful voice changer for Linux written in GTK three,
and it takes your microphone input, whatever it might be, and then it creates a virtual
output that you can record in any app that you use to record your audio.
And the idea is that it's supposed to make you sound kind of, kind of fun.
You can make yourself sound like you're on a sketchy radio connection from far away.
And it has like a Darth Vader mode and it has a gender changer mode and it has like
a megaphone mode, just random stuff like that.
And it's a nice looking app, simple.
You didn't try the Darth Vader mode?
Oh, I tried them all.
I just could have, you know, I didn't want to be obnoxious with all of the different
clips, but yeah, before the show we were playing around quite a bit.
It's fun.
If you've got a great pic idea or something that you're like, why have these guys never
talked about X on the show, send it in to us.
Go to linuxunplug.com slash contact.
We got the contact form there.
And of course you can always boost it in by getting a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com.
And the great thing about those apps is it's not just boosts, it's the entire podcasting
2.0 spec.
And the more people that use those apps, the more podcasts will adopt things like transcripts
and chapters, embedded image and all kinds of nice things that podcasting has needed
for a long time.
So go get a new podcast app at newpodcastapps.com.
And of course you can always grab linuxactionnews.com in one of those apps.
Well at least Linux Action News podcast at linuxactionnews.com.
I think that's how it works.
Anyways, it's our weekly news podcast, and if you're not getting that, then you're missing
out on what's going on in the world of Linux.
And we welcome you to join us live.
Come on in.
Wes sets up some chips and dip for the live members.
They're virtual chips and dip.
Could you imagine sending out chips to everybody?
We don't want to make a mess.
Maybe when we make it big time, big time, we'll send out chips to everybody.
But in the meantime, you get some virtual chips and dip when you come over to jblive.tv.
We do it on noon, around noon, right around noon or we start getting started.
Sometimes there's virtual tacos.
Sometimes there are indeed.
And you can hang out in our chat room or our mumble room and participate here in this podcast.
We like it when you do that.
That's real great.
We also just like it when you listen in the chair with a friend, just like all that kind
of stuff.
We should also mention, Chris, I think we're recording in a new office hours this week,
aren't we?
It'll be live on Tuesday, Brent.
All right.
Noon air.
Noon air again.
That's right.
Yeah.
Let's let's let's talk website stuff.
Let's talk project stuff.
Let's talk podcast stuff.
All of that on Tuesday, office hours.
The mumble room will be open as well.
See you next week.
Same bat time.
Same bat station.
In the meantime, links to what we talked about today at Linux Unplugged dot com slash four
five seven.
Let's see.
You can go find.
Where are you on Twitter, Wes?
At Wes Payne.
Yeah.
There you go.
The network's at Jupiter Signaled.
Catch more Alex on the self-hosted podcast at self-hosted dot show.
And I think that's all the plugin we have.
I'll just spend the last few seconds thanking you for listening.
If you've written in or thinking about it, do it.
It's a big part of the show.
It helps us think of what you want to hear.
Make a new pop.
Make new show content.
All that stuff.
It's really useful.
We like your feedback.
We're making the show for you.
Yeah.
Linux Unplugged dot com slash content.
All right.
Thanks for being here.
We'll be right back here next week.