Now, Chris, I know you're an animal lover, but mostly just on the outside.
You ever been curious about the inside?
No, no, that sounds like that would be something a psychopath would want to do,
like cut open a cat or something.
It sure does.
Why are you asking me this?
Oh, well, I've got a link for you.
A kind of cute, kind of disturbing new VR cat demo.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, right.
This one from Leap Motion.
Yeah, I've I heard about it.
I had not seen it.
I don't think I need to go inside a cat, Wes.
This is Linux Unplugged Episode 253 for June 12th, 2018.
Oh, welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show
that's definitely not going to talk about Microsoft buying GitHub this week.
Well, I mean, I mean anymore.
And yes, I'm still live from the road.
I'm just outside of Dallas, Texas, parked at the Linux Academy headquarters.
I'll tell you more about that.
But let's bring in everybody.
My name is Chris.
And that right there over there is my name is Wes.
Hello, Wes, you and your wonderful Seattle weather.
Oh, I know, right?
It's overcast right now.
Can you even imagine that, Chris?
No, no, no, no, I cannot.
Wes, we're going to try something a little different today.
Going to reformat the show a little bit.
This is the Unplugged program after all.
And we're going to do things in blocks.
This is an idea I came up while I'm on the road, totally 100% open to feedback.
So here's what's going to happen for the first time.
We're going to bust through a community update block of news.
Then I'm going to block all of the sponsors together in one easy to navigate
spot in the show with all the links of the stuff I'm going to talk about this
week, because they're all launching stuff, some big stuff.
I'll tell you about that.
Then towards the end of the show, we're going to kick back.
I'm going to tell you about Texas Linux Fest, what the event was like, about
the parties that we attended and all of those kinds of stories, and then we'll
wrap it up with an app pick that is extremely useful and our own Mr.
Wes Payne will tell us all about it.
But Wes, before we go any fervor, there is one duty that we must perform.
We must.
We must holla at that mumble room.
Time appropriate greetings, Virtual Lug.
What's up?
Hello.
Hello, everybody.
So wonderful to hear you.
I, uh, I'm, I'm feeling pretty good right now.
You know, I've started to acclimate to the Texas heat.
You're Texan through and through.
Yeah, I'm not doing too bad.
It's 97 degrees here every single day in Keller, Texas, but, uh, I don't know.
You kind of get used to it after a while, if that makes any sense.
And it's a little less humid here than it was down in Austin.
So that helps a lot too.
And, uh, I got to, uh, I, I, Anthony, the CEO of Linux Academy, picked me up
Friday morning out, uh, from the campground to take me to Linux Fest.
And while we were driving, I chatted with him.
I said, yeah, you know, we're, we're a little concerned about the heat because,
uh, it's going to be 97 degrees.
And of course I'm going to have to run my generator to be able to run the AC.
And that's going to be loud and it's going to be limited.
I'm only going to run it for, you know, it's just kind of like, it was just kind
of convincing as I'm sometimes known to do.
It's only sometimes.
Yeah.
It's almost like I've made a living out of it or something.
And so, uh, you know, super cool guy.
He, he gets ahold of his facilities guy Friday morning.
And by Sunday, when I got here, they had a power hookup for the RV.
So I could hook up and get full service.
Yep.
So I got AC, I got full power.
It's great.
Even, I'm even in the shade a little bit by the, by this time, it's, uh, it's,
um, almost about three o'clock, uh, uh, about Chicago time zone area.
Um, about this time, the, uh, building starts to shade the RV too.
So it's, it's, it's actually downright comfortable.
I couldn't believe it.
How did you get such a sweet spot?
I don't know, man.
I was worried about it the entire time before I left.
I was worried.
Like I was, I was, I almost went out and got like this whole reflectix kit that I
was going to put out all over the windows.
And I was going to, I remember I was really upset when my awning got busted
because that was like a key part of, and that still would have been very useful.
Uh, but it was a key part of my shade strategy.
Like I was very concerned about this particular aspect and it's gone way
better than I could have imagined.
And on top of that, we're right next to like a little pond crick thing.
I don't know.
They're not like what we have in Washington because there it's just like
any old average, like basically big ditch, but it's a natural thing and it's full
of fish and turtles.
I have a turtle pond next to the RV and so far I've counted four turtles and I'm
told there's some turtles in there.
They're as large as hubcaps, like big turtles.
So you brought one on as a guest on the show today?
Yeah, yeah.
He's sitting right there.
He's, uh, he just hasn't had much to say yet.
So last night I'm working out by the pond, watching the turtles, Levi and I.
So that was pretty cool.
Yeah.
And then, and then do you found this tour app?
I'm not sure if I'm pronouncing it right, but it's tour or something like that.
Have you seen this?
It's Airbnb for cars.
No, I have not.
And they specialize in sort of fancy cars, like, you know, so Mercedes, BMWs,
Teslas, or like really souped up Jeep Jeep wranglers and trucks for Texas.
And so for 60 bucks, we rented today a Mercedes with great air conditioning, a
white Mercedes with air conditioning that we can bop around for a couple of days.
Bopping around in Texas in style, no less.
Look at you.
You really know what you're doing.
Hmm.
It's been pretty good.
I mean, I'm getting there.
I've got to walk through the Linux Academy office too, and got to see some
of their studio space that they have here.
And, uh, I've got the OBS rig, um, loaded.
It's got OBS on it.
It's got Kubuntu 1804 loaded.
It got the capture cards of the audio interface all hooked up to it.
And, um, I'm going to try doing a Chromebook HDMI capture on it after the
show.
So they're, they're interesting.
Yeah.
Their transition to Linux, uh, from the Mac is, uh, is well underway.
So it's been a great visit and, um, I now, I now have a new term for air
conditioning and that term is life support.
I now understand that it's life support.
Yeah.
So it was, it was a great, it was a, it was a, it was a great trip to get here.
It was hot.
It was 104 degrees on the drive up here and there was construction in Waco.
So, yeah, it took a while.
It took me five hours to get from Austin to Dallas and, uh, 104 degrees in that
drive, but so, so are you, are you homesick yet?
Are you, are you?
Are you missing the comforts of the JV one studio?
You know, actually today's kind of the day that I wasn't like some days I am
right, but today isn't one of those days today.
I'm really kind of digging it.
I'm kind of, I'm comfortable, you know, uh, I got the car, so I was able to go
out and I was able to get some babes, uh, fried chicken, which, uh, yeah, which
was described to me as, as fried chicken.
That's better than grandma's fried chicken when grandma grew up making fried
chicken.
Yeah.
That's incredible.
It was actually pretty good.
So it's been a great trip.
There's been so much cool, like, uh, people to meet.
There's some people that are visiting the Linux Academy offices that are out
like writing software and doing startup stuff and they're building on top of
Linux and they're here talking to people.
So the thing about the thing that I'm starting to appreciate is there's like a
bench of people here that are like, uh, like Red Hat experts and Azure experts
and like expert experts, like really, like really like I shouldn't give anybody
ideas, but like Amazon and Microsoft and Red Hat are poaching people from here
constantly.
Like these people really, so they're, so Linux Academy has people out here.
They're just, uh, you know, getting questions answered and stuff like that.
They've got this new meetup space they're building to, uh, bring people in
from the community and so they can get questions answered.
And it's just really cool thing there.
So I got to see all of that that they're building out right now.
It's pretty neat.
That is really neat.
Yeah.
So there's probably going to be some more Linux community things going on in this
area, uh, later on down the road once they get all that stuff rolling.
But, uh, what do you say?
What do you, should we get into some, some, uh, larger open source free
software community news updates?
That's what we're here for, right?
Let's do it.
Yeah.
We'll talk about Texas Linux Fest later, but let's talk about some news items that
people should probably know about this week as we're, uh, it's only Tuesday and
there's things you should probably know about if you're a Copperhead OS user,
especially now, Copperhead OS is a security enhanced Android distribution
started in 2016, but it looks like the company behind Copperhead OS appears to
have run into some internal trouble.
Now I don't really know the specifics at this point, but the situation seems to be
devolving and there's clearly some kind of dispute between the founders.
You guys know how much I hate drama, so I don't really care to get into it, but
there is a Reddit post that we'll have linked in the show notes where
apparently one of the co-founders essentially is kicking out the other
co-founder from the company.
So that does tend to cause drama, Wes.
Absolutely.
Especially, you know, at these really, these really small distributions or
companies where that makes up a lot of the culture, a lot of the history and
a lot of the people, you know, trying to do work and organizing things.
So yikes.
Yeah.
And my thoughts are with the users.
I know it almost sounds cliche to say, but it's like, okay, well now what?
Because, uh, you know, you have a user base who's using this because they
have very certain kinds of considerations.
A Copperhead OS appeals to a certain kind of user base.
Well, now what?
I don't know.
I honestly don't know where they go cause I don't follow this very carefully.
I see Mr.
Popey has entered in the room.
Hello, Popey.
Good to see you.
Hello.
And Tyler's here too.
Tyler, welcome back.
It's been good.
I haven't seen you for a little bit.
Taking the night off.
I just got back in from, uh, driving home from Southeast Linux Fest.
Well, maybe we can pick your brain about that a little bit in the show.
What do you say?
Do a little Texas Linux Fest update and a little Southeast Linux Fest update.
Both were going on this weekend.
So I'd love to pick your brain about that.
Stick around.
I'm glad you're here.
Uh, yeah.
So this weekend was huge.
It was full spectrum for Jupiter broadcasting.
So we had BSD can going on in Canada and Alan Jude, uh, was there and it was live
streamed Tyler and Noah were at self and they were live streaming the hell out of
self I was at Texas Linux Fest doing no work at all, just hobnobbing with
everybody and, uh, uh, Joe and Popey were at a floss talk this weekend.
This weekend, so all of that was happening this weekend.
So, Popey, if you want to talk about floss talking a little bit too, we could
just do kind of a whole kind of roundabout about some of the events we
were at this weekend and, uh, that'd be awesome.
All right.
So yeah, Copperhead OS, uh, back to the news.
So Copperhead OS, uh, is, uh, perhaps in trouble and it might be
time to look for an alternative.
I don't know if I'm in the Mamba room has any alternative suggestions or if you do
West, but, uh, I'd love to hear what the audience thinks on that.
It's kind of a shame to see these projects.
Maybe things will work out fine, but it's a shame to see things go this way.
Especially in a security focused project where you sort of hope that calmer heads
will prevail as it's, you know, serious attention to details sort of work.
But as always, personalities, they happen.
That's exactly, basically just summed it up.
Personalities happen.
Uh, that's a title.
Somebody said, bang, suggest that.
That's a good title suggestion.
Uh, open source personalities happen.
So Plasma 5.3, speaking of refinement and working away on stuff, Plasma 5.13
launched today, and I think the big headline feature for most users is going
to be the browser integration.
It's a new set of features for Firefox, Chrome and Chromium based browsers.
They integrate in with plasma notification, pop-ups, transferring
files with dolphin notifications, media controls can now mute and skip videos
playing from within the browser.
And you can send a link to your phone with KDE connect now, and, uh, you can
also choose browser tabs.
I've not tried this at all, but I, I understand that you can try, you can try
to choose browser tabs somehow from K runner with an old space keyboard
shortcut.
That's blowing my mind.
I got to try that at some point.
So that's probably the biggest user facing new feature in Plasma 5.13.
The one that I have been anticipating the longest is the redesigned for system
settings and the new look for the lock-in for the lock screen and login screen,
which I think looks really slick.
There's also graphics, compositor updates.
Kaywin gain a much improved effects for blurring and desktop switching.
And of course, as all these updates go, there's been continued work on making
Wayland awesome, including the return of windows rules now on Wayland, which is
a fantastic plasma desktop feature and the use of high priority EGL context, as
well as initial support for screencast and desktop sharing.
Whoa, huge one, plus something that's not really just like a bullet point
feature.
Here's tons of performance improvements, memory usage improvements, lots of
improvements on the system setting stuff and a tech preview.
That's what they're calling it of the GTK global menu integration.
So if you're a fan of global menus, there has been a hack available on Plasma.
I call it a hack, but there's been a way to get it working on Plasma for a
while.
This is official stuff.
There's going to be official stuff.
So that's really nice.
And then a small one.
It's kind of funny they're even put this in here, but I legit like it.
The digital clock widget allows you now to copy the current date and time to
the clipboard.
Hallelujah.
Wes, it's those small little usability things that when they're there, it just
makes sense.
Right.
So new users to me like, oh, hey, look, this is handy.
And when you want it or you're just trying to just trying to copy the things
you need to send it to someone right now and then it works and you're just
like, yes, great, perfect.
And now I think I think I'll leave I'll leave it as an exercise to the user.
But producer Michael and I work together on a video for the Plasma 513
introduction.
So I'll have that linked in the show notes if you guys want to watch that.
That covers more stuff and shows screencasts and whatnot of all of that.
But big news for you, Popey, now that you're a big Plasma desktop user, you
must be looking forward to this.
Yeah, always.
I love just getting the fire hose of updates that come on KDE Neon because
because it's different for me because I'm used to Ubuntu where we have our six
monthly releases.
So I have to upgrade every six months in order to get new crack at the platform
level with KDE Neon.
I've got their PPA enabled or their repo enabled.
So I just get new stuff all the time and it's great.
I love it.
It kind of is because it's like it's the desktop stuff.
But your core OS is pretty much not changing much unless there's been some
upstream change from Ubuntu.
So it's kind of just the right balance in a weird way and surprisingly has not
broken yet for me.
You know, that's the other thing.
Sweet.
Always a bonus.
Has it broke for you at all?
Um, no.
Oh, I was going to say it did right back at the start.
There was a, well, Kwin has crashed once, maybe twice, I think, but everything
carried on working.
All the applications are still running.
It's just the window decorations died and I just went to a TTY rerun Kwin and
carried on running.
And I carried on running for about a week with Kwin running in a TTY.
It was fine.
And it worked.
Yeah.
That's a testament right there.
The Neon updates will probably be flowing.
I have not tried to update my box yet because I'm doing the show right now, but
I think I will after the show.
Oh, you've learned.
Good job.
I'm proud.
I am a little extra conservative about it when I'm on the road because like if
it breaks at the studio, well, I could probably just go grab another machine.
If it breaks while I'm on the road, I really am going to be in a, like, it'd
be kind of embarrassing to walk into Linux Academy with like my laptop in hand
and be like, uh, anybody have a thumb drive I can use?
That's, uh, it's not the direction I want that to go.
Poby, did you hear about these wine packs?
It reminds me just last week we talked about a couple of snaps that were quote
soaked in wine and now we have wine packs, which, uh, are just like the name sounds.
Uh, it's a packaging up of wine applications, a flat pack bundle, and
they have, um, Fortnite, Overwatch, and World of Warcraft as well as Internet
Explorer 8, everyone's favorite browser.
Um, as, uh, I guess you could call it, uh, what do they call them?
Wine packs as a wine pack.
What are your thoughts?
I think these, um, these various, uh, tools for making containerized
applications are suited perfectly to this use case of having wine plus something.
And the reason why is often you want to have, um, a specific build of wine or a
specific tweaked set of additional libraries that you might install with
wine tricks, plus the application and that, that delicate balancing of all
those things someone needs to figure out and then get it all right and package it
all up and it works, but then you don't ever want to touch it and you don't want
to then, you know, update the version of wine or screw around with what's inside
that, that, um, that, you know, fake C drive as it were.
Um, and that's exactly what these containerized applications that you do,
you end up having the right version of wine and the right config for Fortnite
or whatever, the right version of wine and the right config for whatever other
game and they don't interfere with each other.
It's a great idea.
I like that.
And I wonder if this could be something that, um, that maybe crossover office
could jump on top of and, uh, bundle it with, uh, you know, bundle their
applications in a way or bundle wine applications in a way that make it even
easier for end users to install those.
That could be kind of a neat thing.
Yeah.
It really seems like it could open up this.
I'm thinking about the number of people I've sort of, you know, uh, softly
pushed on the Linux.
Some of them are playing more games or trying to use some more, you know,
they're just doing more and sometimes that involves Windows programs.
I don't want to teach them how to use wine.
So if I can point them at these things, that's so much better.
It makes it easier for them to get at, it's just, you know, click an icon or,
you know, download a flat pack or whatever, and just make it easy for
people to get all the necessary bits and pieces that make it work.
I'm going to be curious to watch how many more of these we get with snaps too.
And, uh, I think, I think, uh, the, the whole concept is, is also potentially
a huge boom for piracy.
It could be, um, you know, you could go, you could, you could go pirate all
kinds of Windows applications.
If you can get it working right and get it in one of these, uh, containerized
application delivery mechanisms.
Well, that's already been done.
There are on pirate bay, there are a whole bunch of flat packs for
commercial, uh, Windows applications that have been bundled with wine.
That was done probably about eight months ago.
Um, but, you know, people will always bend technology to their will, even if
it's nefarious uses, unfortunately.
Yeah.
Um, and some ways maybe that's a way we can preserve software to way, way down
the road, so that'll be something interesting to watch.
Yeah.
I mean, uh, there's a, there's a mosaic snap in the store, so you can get the
original mosaic browser if you really, really, really want to, uh, yeah, just
do snap install mosaic and you can run the mosaic window, not a lot of websites
work with it because it's a very old web browser, but the original homepage for
the mosaic web browser does work.
And that's what it is, the homepage for that, that web browser.
So yeah, it is a great way to preserve software.
You can have it in a little container is not going to break out of that container.
And, um, you've got a little runtime environment that it will work in for, you
know, forever and for always.
No, hold on.
I got to do this.
This is too great right now.
I mean, I'm sorry if my connection gets a little shaky cause I'm going to, I'm
actually legitimately installing this right now as we go.
Well, we could use this mosaic browser isn't particularly large.
It's like 1.4 megs.
Yeah.
Right.
Oh, this is great.
Oh my, oh boy.
It's also a train wreck on high DPI.
Uh, surprise, surprise everybody.
Oh yeah, it will be.
Yeah, yeah.
I wonder if there's any webpage you can actually open on that.
There are a few.
You know what?
One of my favorite sites, one of the things that, uh, one of the great things
that I think GDPR brought us us citizens is a whole bunch of news websites,
can't figure out what to do, so they just threw their arms up and made text
versions of their websites, which is nothing on it, but the text NPR has done
this, CNN has done this, and it's the best thing ever.
In fact, if you want to try it, go to text.npr.org and it's just an all text
version.
Um, and I also, I tweeted a couple of days ago, this is what the CNN one is.
I want to try it in text.npr.org.
Let's try it in the mosaic browser and see if it works.
Are we going to fail on an SSL server?
I'd imagine.
Oh, it is.
Yep.
It's SSL.
Damn.
That seemed like if anything was going to work, that would have worked.
But yeah, it's, you know, I hear that SSL can't be trusted, so they should
probably drop that cause I hear it's bad.
Oh, it's the worst.
Just stay away from it.
I'll try out more.
Are you familiar with Gopher, Chris?
Cause that it's making a research.
So let me tell you.
Oh man.
Geez.
You, you just really showed your age there.
You want to talk about BBS's too while we're at it?
Oh, I thought that was on the docket already.
We always on the lookout.
For old crusty software that we can put in a stamp for a bit of a lull.
So yeah, if you have any ideas to, you know, where to find me.
Yeah, I love the idea too.
Cause it is in a way preserving old, old work.
We've been following this slow March to Linux apps landing on Chromebooks.
And last week we talked about how the Samsung Chromebook is getting Linux apps
support, even though it's an ARM based Chromebook.
That's a, that's just great news, but now it looks like a new Chromebook that's on
the market soon. Two actually that were introduced by Acer, the Chromebook 13
and the Chromebook Spin 13 are going to ship with this Linux app support.
So you guys recall Google revealed back at Google IO, we'd be covering it before
that even that Chrome OS would be adding support for running Linux apps within
Chrome OS's environment on certain select hardware because it involves as either
a certain modern version of the kernel or back porting certain kernel modules
and features to older versions.
Which is what's happening in some cases or in some cases like the Pixelbook, it
just has the newest version of the kernel and you're good to go if you get the
dev channel. Last week we discovered that if you subscribe to the dev channel on
the Samsung Chromebook Plus, you could get Linux apps.
And now, according to a commit that was spotted by the XDA developers, Acer's
new machines are going to support Linux apps at launch.
That's kind of a big deal.
So they're going to start from day one with Linux apps.
This is actually happening faster than I thought it would, Wes.
What are your thoughts? Does it seem like this is happening faster or is this about
what you thought it was going to be pace wise?
No, I agree with you.
It sort of felt like, OK, yeah, you know, the high end, high end stuff, the developer
focused stuff that's going to get this right away, the things that are already out
there and people are already using this sort of experimental machines on the bleeding
edge. Not something we'll see like launch right away or that people marketing
Chromebooks would necessarily think that a wide array of people, potential customers
might want. But, boy, this seems like, you know, the couple of news items we've
covered about this, it does seem to have some real momentum and like it's a feature
that's well designed enough or stable enough that they feel like they can ship it, not
have to worry about it. Sure, probably not a huge amount of people will use it right
away or at least won't know that they're using it.
But for the rest of us weird Linux nerds over here, it's awesome.
Yes, weirdos. Eric, do you have a Chromebook?
And if you do or don't, would you consider getting one that has this Linux app support?
Yeah, I would definitely consider one.
I've been pricing out like XPS 13s and that kind of thing, but that's a little pricey
for my position right now. So a Chromebook might be a good way to get Linux, but not
at, you know, at a Cadillac price.
That's a good way to put it. I was thinking, too, it works well as sort of like my backup
Linux rig. You know, I can have I can have I can have maybe I can have a 15 inch laptop
and then I have a smaller Chromebook. That's sort of like my backup portable Linux rig.
You know, that'd be pretty nice. I think this might be the year that I buy a new
Chromebook. I've never, never have never bought a Chromebook. I've I've bought a used
Chromebook once. Of course, I played with my kids Chromebook, but I've never bought
a Chromebook. And so this might be the year that I finally break down and I do it.
What about you, Bobby? Would this put you over the edge for getting a Chromebook or
or a new one?
I actually picked up a Chromebook just last week. It was in amongst a bunch of stuff that
was being thrown out from the canonical offices. They were clearing out some some
cupboards. So I grabbed it and it's, it's quite neat, but it's out of support because
unfortunately, it's the very, very first Chromebook, the CR 48. So there's no chance
it's ever going to run Linux apps unless I wipe it and put something like Ubuntu, like
1310 on there or something really old and crusty.
I think that was the Chromebook I had. I think that was the same one. That was a
popular one. I don't remember why it was so popular. So yeah, I think I think I'm
going to I think I'm going to shop a little bit and I'm going to try it. Yes.
Check that out. Acer Chromebook. Yay. All right. So let's talk about something a
little sad, just a little bit. The Mars Opportunity Rover, which does have a Linux
angle, we'll talk about here in a second, is in danger of dying right now this week
from a dust storm. And engineers are delicately balancing the remaining battery
power. It's caught in a pretty significant dust storm. In fact, the most significant
I believe that it's ever been in. And if not, it's the second most significant and
the craft is hunkered down, trying to survive the intensifying weather. The storm
was first detected on Friday, June 1 by the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter, at which
point the rover's team was notified because whenever there's a large storm
near one of the rovers, they they page the team. The rover uses solar panels. So
a dust storm is going to have an extremely negative impact on the rover
opportunities, power levels and its batteries. I feel like I understand its
pain. You know, I feel like my rover also has suffered from similar situations.
Just a harsh universe out there and you got to protect yourself. And then on
June 6, Wednesday, June 6, opportunity was in minimal operations mode because of
the sharply decreasing power levels. Now, the brave little rover is continuing to
weather the storm. In fact, it sent a transmission to Earth Sunday morning. We
last heard from it, which is a good sign. So that means there's still enough
charge left in the batteries to communicate with home, despite the fact
that the storm is continuing to worsen. But the main concern isn't really the
dust storm itself. It's the need to keep the rover's heaters operating at a
minimum while maintaining minimal power levels in the batteries because it's so
cold. Opportunity, though, is a pretty hard little rover and maybe Linux has
contributed this a little bit. It's continually defied everyone's
expectations for 15 years. It was only designed to last for 90 days and it's
still going. So this, I mean, this is why it's such a kind of a big deal because
not only is it represent just a massive technological breakthrough for NASA and
it's just an incredible accomplishment, it's also representative of when NASA
and the Jet Propulsion Labs made the change to using Linux as their
development and control systems. Really? Yeah, it represents a really cool story
behind, the long term behind, the development story behind this rover was.
This wasn't going to be the rover initially. It was going to be a different
rover, completely going to be designed, controlled, managed, developed for using
all SGI systems. SGI top and bottom, SGI everything. But that mission took a
turning point and in the background, JPL and others had been experimenting with
Linux here and there. A Debian laptop had gone up on the space shuttle STS-83 in
97. So Debian went up into space in 97. But internally, they just weren't there
yet. But they had sort of like this skunk works project to move things off of
the SGI's and onto Linux box, onto a Linux box. And I've got the full story
from Linux journal from years ago linked in the show notes, but I'll just give
you the highlights of this piece. So they say, Linux originally was not intended
to be the primary development platform. Our software initially was intended for
use on the Mars 01 mission, which essentially would have been a repeat of
JPL's 97 Mars Pathfinder mission. The plan was to do all rover commanding on a
single Silicon Graphics workstation, as had been done on the Mars Pathfinder.
Our Linux support was, at that time, mainly a hedge against SGI's fortunes.
Wow. After the failure of JPL's Mars 98 missions, however, JPL replanned its
Mars strategy. The Mars 01 plans were scrapped in favor of a later launch. That
mission later on became the MER mission, M-E-R. The upshot was that we got two
years of development time that we hadn't planned on. Although it was for a
different spacecraft than we had planned, we had two years. In those two years,
Linux and the generic x86 hardware it runs on made enormous strides in both
CPU and graphics speeds, thanks in no small part to the graphics shipmaker
NVIDIA and its strong support for Linux on the enterprise systems. As a result,
we increasingly came to favor the faster, better, cheaper solution that was Linux.
We eventually purchased two high-end SGI's to add to our Linux boxes during
flight operations, but it's unclear whether we ended up using them. The Linux
boxes now give us equal, if not better, performance. And as a result, the MER
rovers are being commanded by multiple teams working in parallel on dozens of
Linux systems that we purchased for the mission. And now that's for 17 years
they've been doing this. Our software suite of applications called the Rover
Sequencing and Visualization Program, RSVP for short, was developed, tested,
and deployed on Linux. RSVP gives MER engineers and scientists sophisticated
tools for commanding Mars rovers. Because of the lengthy light time delays,
which amount to nearly 20 minutes round trip, it's not possible to control the
rovers interactively. RSVP provides an immersive environment that accurately
displays the rover's environment and simulates its behavior. Throughout the
Martian night, we Earthlings use RSVP to plan a days of activities at the
command level and then uplink the resulting commands to the rover. The
rover then executes those commands during the following Martian day. So
there's two main components of RSVP. The Rover Sequencing Editor, which provides
text oriented commanding for all spacecraft commands, and Hyperdrive, which
provides an advanced three dimensional graphics for driving, arm motion, and
imaging commands. I think we call that AR these days, Wes.
We sure do.
And they say also the messages is based on RML, an XML based specification
designed specifically for representing rover commands and sequences. And they
have so much more detail in the article. But they say the automation friendly
Linux environment contributed greatly to the whole system's reliability. Early on
we wrote extensive self-tests to code, to test our code, and then set up a simple
cron job to run the tests every night. If any self-test failed, they were
reported an email message to the developer the next morning. This helped
us catch bugs early, while the changes that it caused them were still fresh in
our minds. Our aggressive self-testing was something of an experiment, and it
paid off handsomely. How about that?
This is an incredible article, and what a story. I think you really hit on it.
It's like the rovers have been so cool and given us such a new understanding of
this, you know, this neighbor in our solar system, and that you can make it all
happen with the technology we already think is great and use and love. And it
just sells Linux so well, right? You don't have to make sure that you've
budgeted accurately for the number of machines that you hope that you actually
need and all the licenses to run them. If you can get commodity parts, you can
just stick more Linux on it, have multiple people working on the same
thing, not a problem. And it's so interesting that it kind of started as
like this little side skunkworks hedge, and then as time went on, it's like,
wait a minute, this thing has just surpassed what we originally hedging
against. That's so Linux. That's such a Linux thing to do.
It is a Linux thing to do, right? You're like, well, it's free, so you can kind of
sneak it in. Oh, we're just running the test server on it. Oh, yeah, the backup
system, it's fine. And then you realize it's just easier to work with.
I met some Linux journal people at Texas Linux Fest, actually.
Is that right? Yeah, speaking of Texas Fest, they had a booth. They were
giving away posters and things like that. We'll talk about that in a minute.
So what we just did there is kind of a new format. We just did everything just
all back together, no stopping, no interruptions. We just did all of the
news right there. And now I want to stop and I want to do a sponsor block
because our sponsors are doing a lot of cool things this week, and you're going
to need links for some of this stuff. And so what we're going to do is we're
going to do all of them right here. And then the rest of the show, we just
continue on. And I want to get your feedback on if you like this because I
know, A, some of you have heard this before. So that makes it a little easier
to navigate. And B, when we talk about some of the stuff our sponsors are
doing, there's no clear place where in the show you go get those links.
So let's start by thanking Linux Academy because that's where I'm parked at
right now. Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged is where you go to sign up
for a free seven day trial. Linux Academy can help change your life through
affordable, high quality online cloud training. You can learn new skills, get
certified and train your team and advance your career. We heard from
several people at Texas Linux Fest who said their whole IT department has an
account. And a lot of people said, I just got one because I'm learning to go
somewhere. I'm trying to get into security. I'm trying to get into cloud
computing. I'm trying to wrap my head around how the Google Cloud works. It's
really fascinating all the different reasons people get into it. But the one
thing that remains true is that it's extremely valuable, extremely valuable
resource. It's a training platform to learn everything about Linux and
whatever Linux runs on. And back in April, they launched 70 new courses,
challenges and learning activities. And I mentioned it here on the show. And
that was a big deal. 70 is huge. It's a lot of content. And now that I'm here,
I have learned, little bird, I won't say much, but little birdies have been
telling me they are all focused on July. They have, they have a lot of content
coming out in July. Their biggest ever. It's going to be a ton of stuff. They've
already kind of been teasing it a little bit, including their newest pillar,
security. They're going to be launching a bunch of security courses and they're
doing a giveaway to celebrate all of it. So I'm going to put a link in the blog,
I'm going to put a link to their blog in our show notes at linuxunplug.com
slash 253. So you can get in on the swag giveaway and find out about the new
content that's coming out. It's massive. And to watch the whole team work on it
as they are from, from art people to developers, to the course authors, to the
executives and the admins, to the marketing folks and to the community
people that are trying to get the word out there. Like everybody's focused on
this because it's just a huge launch. It's massive. It'll blow your mind away
and they're really proud of it. So go to Linux Academy right now. You can sign up
for a free seven day trial. Try out the platform and then next month a whole
bunch of stuff is going to land. Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged. That's
where you go to support the show and get a free seven day trial. Now Ting, Ting
has been providing my connectivity on this entire trip from the moment I left
Washington to right now. They have been a rock solid mobile carrier. They're smarter
than unlimited. If you use less, you pay less. You can go to linux.ting.com and
get $25 in Ting service credit or $25 off a phone. That's linux.ting.com. The
average bill is $23 per month per phone. You pay for what you use. A fair price
for however much you talk, however much you text, and however much data you use.
So this month my data bill is going to be more. But for the other 11 months of
the year, I pay hardly anything for data because I have Wi-Fi everywhere I go and
they have nationwide coverage. I've been able to use CDMA and GSM. Where I'm at
right now is a GSM town. It's a GSM town. It's been working just fine. But
sometimes CDMA works a little better, especially when I was in Utah. I found
that CDMA just worked a lot better. No contracts, nor the termination fees. You
can try Ting risk free and you can support the show. Linux.ting.com. They
give you a control panel where you can manage everything, see your usage at a
glance, take complete control, set usage alerts. Oh, oh, and they're doing some
giveaways. They have a lot of things going on. But the thing I'm going to
direct you to, because you've heard me do these ads before. You could probably do
this ad and you could make some money. Ting is doing a $100 Amazon gift card.
If you refer a friend or family member, you know, whoever, maybe a child.
You know, convince your eight-year-old. No, I'm kidding. You can't do that. Yeah.
Refer a friend to Ting and you win a chance to win. You get a chance to win
$100 in Ting gift card, Amazon cards from Ting. And you just take all the things
I've told you about Ting. You pay for what you use. Take your ministry message,
your megabytes, whatever you use. That's what you pay. $6 a month for the line. No
contract, nor the termination fee. Great company. Fanatical customer support.
CDMA and GSM. You can bring your own device or you can buy one directly. They
got no agenda. They don't necessarily care what you do with your device. Just
use it. They're not going to try to push some sort of Ting experience down on
your device. You say all those things and then you give them a link and you're
probably going to get this $100 card because you're going to sell it. You're
going to sell it. I know you. Start by going to linux.ting.com, either for
yourself or a friend or a family or if you're visiting the States. I've met
people traveling. They come here, they get themselves Ting and they use it while
they're here because it's $6 a month. Why not? It's great. I love having it. I
love having it. I have a CDMA and GSM now just to make it easy. I'm not
activating devices or nothing. They're just ready to go. linux.ting.com.
And finally today, big thank you to DigitalOcean. Making changes everywhere
in the open source community and they're making it possible for you to build
better applications and get things deployed in incredible speeds at
industry leading price performance and predictable costs. Start by going to
do.co.plugged. You get a $100 credit. You can apply that to your DigitalOcean
account and you can mess around with a new account for 60 days with a $100
credit. My favorite rig is $0.03 an hour. So a $100 credit is going to get you
far and they have incredibly fast infrastructure, enterprise grade SSDs on
everything from like the $5 a month rig up to the big mama jamas that have
hundreds of gigs of RAM and Xeons for days. Oh, and they now have flexible
droplets. You can mix and match the resources you need. I've got a Fedora 28
box running up on DigitalOcean using 250 gigs-ish of block storage. It's so
smooth the way all of this works. When you set up a Fedora 28 cloud instance,
you immediately connect your SSH key. You get the DNS all set up if you do it
like I do and you just log right in and get working. It's so straightforward
because of this dashboard. They make managing all this stuff simple even if
you've never done it before or if you've done it for a decade. So check it out by
going to do.co.plugged. Cloud firewalls that block traffic at the network level,
monitoring and alerting to keep you on top of what your rig is doing. Easy to
use, well-documented API and tons and tons of documentation. Speaking of that
documentation, I've told you in the past that DigitalOcean is willing to pay
folks that write really good documentation for DigitalOcean. Well, now
they're introducing something different. So I'm going to put this link in the
show notes as well. You can now write for DO-nations, for DO-nations. Okay,
sorry, but that's the joke. You can actually now write for DigitalOcean and
then what they were going to pay you contribute to an open source project or
a charity. For example, there's an article I have linked in the show notes,
how to verify downloaded files that you download on your Linux box like an
ISO. That was written by Michael Holly and he donated his $300 writer's fee to
the Electronic Frontier Foundation. So you can go write up something that you're
a technical expert on and then contribute out to a charitable donation.
And they're going to match too. I think they'll match up to $400, something like
I can't remember. So if you want to, anyways, the details I'll have linked in
the show notes. I think this is a super cool program. It's definitely worth
reading if that's something that you could possibly be good at. It could be a
great way to contribute documentation to a community and contribute to a charity
or an open source project that you like. So I'll have that linked in the show
notes as well. Everybody's got something going on. It's just a big, great week.
Check it all out and get started by going to do.co.pl and get that free $100
credit for 60 days, do.co.pl. Unplugged and a big thank you to DigitalOcean, to
Ting, and of course to Linux Academy for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged program.
Okay, moving on now. Let's talk about Texas Linux Fest. What a hell of a party.
So it looks like Omnipotent had to leave. He joined me there along with a whole
bunch of people. We had such a great time. So let me tell you a little bit about
it. We won't spend too long on it, but it'll be real quick. Texas Linux Fest
2018 was held at the AT&T Conference Center in Austin, Texas on Friday, June
8th to Saturday, June 9th. And it was a hell of a party. Oh, Ironic Badger. Oh,
where are you? Hello. Hello. I'm in Denver today. You are? Well, you're good
to see you. Good to see you. How are you doing? How's the road been? How's the
trip been? Are you recovered? Are you still hung over? How has it all gone?
2,000 miles in two days for a British man. That's all I'll say.
Yeah, that is a lot for you. Yeah, you've done a ton of driving. Welcome to the
States. Yeah. Yeah. Well, that's awesome. Alex, Mr. Badger there, has been
traveling around looking for reasons for places perhaps. And he joined us at
Texas Linux Fest. He made quite, I think you win for probably making the
furthest track to Texas Linux Fest. Thank you. Is there a prize?
Um, no. The barbecue, I guess. It was, it was so, yeah, bragging rights. How good
was that barbecue? Life changing barbecue. Life changing. Like people talk
about barbecue a lot, about Texas and barbecue. It's next level. You agree? Well,
I wrote a blog post about it and I used the same phrase, life changingly good. So
yeah, I do agree. Okay, good. It was, it was amazing. It was incredible. And it's
one of the funny things about Austin is if you're hanging out with Austin locals,
they're really passionate about discussing the best place to get food. And
that might just be a Texas thing because we were in the hallway here at Linux
Academy talking about where to get lunch and people stopped by to give us their
two on where we should go. It seems to be food is important in Texas and I can
respect that. I really can. About 500 people made it out to Texas Linux Fest.
There was roughly about like three to five tracks going on at the same time.
Really good talks. In fact, I heard a lot of people saying they're having a hard
time choosing which one they wanted to go to. I attended a few. Wes, I went to
a talk about how BPF is being used to do like Linux kernel tracing and stuff
like that. Oh, that sounds fascinating. Yeah, the BPF talk was probably my
favorite. Yeah, I was kind of creeping on the whole you guys down at the fest.
I looked like there were a ton of great talks. I would have had the same problem.
And that's always a good sign when you're at a conference, right? I mean,
it's a little upsetting because you can't go to every single one of them, but you
know it's packed. There's no filler content. Yeah, yeah, that's a good way to
put it. And I liked also the talk. So you've been home. So you've been pwned
like what to do in the next 30 minutes or something like that. I can't remember
what it was. It was a it was a good one. You could text nappy kind of
absolutely talk. Lots of lots of lots of tech snap fans there. Tons and tons of
Linux unplugged and Linux action news fans. That was so awesome. Every night we
had probably about three parties. Really, it was one of those things where you'd
go out and then you go out again and then the group would break off again and
they'd be like three separate parties. The first night we went out, it was I
mean, we probably had a group of 40. I don't know. I'm guessing it was huge and
it was because Linux Academy bought out the hotel bar and paid an obscene amount
of money and drinks for everybody were on Linux Academy, which was amazing.
So generous. There's no way I was going to cover that tab. And then and then we
went out to like another place. Alex, you don't remember the name of the place
that was on the lake, do you? It was the Hula Hut. The Hula Hut. What a place the
Hula Hut was. Great drinks, great atmosphere, right on a lake. And so we
hung out at the Hula Hut for a bit with the Linux Academy crew and another
group of the Jupiter Broadcasting Group. And then then from there we went to a
brewery where we got a little minor brewery tourie tourie and drank some
great ciders and shut that place down and then went home. And Saturday night
was the barbecue shenanigans, which were just life changing. My first thought
after I ate that barbecue and I'm 100% serious and I did not expect this
reaction was a shit. Now what am I going to do now? I have to come up with some
excuse to come down here soon so I can eat this barbecue again because it was
like I have to be back here. There's just no no question about it. So that was
Saturday. We did a bunch of festing and then we went out. Oh man, I can't even
remember. Oh Saturday we went and got some horrible pizza I think and fried
food. That was pretty awful. But then a few of us like Alex, we went back and
hung out at Lady Jupes for a while. That was pretty great. That was a lot of fun.
It was good to see Lady Jupes in person that's for sure.
Now I think it was a total blast. People take their food very seriously and so do
I. The whole thing was so much fun. I've adapted to the heat. I'm damn near ready
to move to Texas at this point. I really had a great time. It's definitely hot,
but for some reason it doesn't matter. You know what I mean? It's because you're
having such a good time you don't care. That first cafe we walked to for like 30
minutes Friday was the most brutal of the whole trip really. That was rough.
Yeah, exercising in that heat is not a good idea. No, Alex and I are both used
to around Seattle and London style climates so walking around in 100
degree sun beating right on you was quite intense. But everybody takes their
AC very seriously so once you get inside there is some sweet, sweet relief.
There was a thread on our Linux. Your favorite. I attended Texas Linux Fest.
Where's the Linux? And they're calling out people for being at Texas Linux Fest
and not using Linux to present, including they call it somebody from Linux Academy,
although I don't know who it is, and several others for using Macs and whatnot.
And it's got a decent amount of upvotes, 529 votes. It's got something like damn near
345 comments. And it's this old boogeyman that we have in the Linux community
where we'll collapse an entire person or an entire company down to a single
variable and we'll say anyone at company X is not using Linux, therefore that
company is disingenuous. Or that presenter isn't using Linux, they're using a Mac,
so therefore they're not a very good presenter for a Linux event. And it's
almost bigoted in a way if you think about it. Because say you take away Mac
user and say they're because they're white or because they're bald. Now all
of a sudden that's a real asshole thing to do. Now you're a dick. But when you
replace that variable with Linux, that's a perfectly fine thing to do apparently.
And it's kind of sick. It's kind of gross. It's something that I think if you
were coming into the Linux community and you saw that, it would kind of disgust
you a little bit. And I think it's because of insecurity. I think people are
looking to those people to be validated, to have their choices validated. And
when they don't have their choices validated, they're looking for, well,
what's wrong with this person? Why wasn't that what I expected? Why am I not
wrong and they are right? That's of course me playing armchair podcast therapist.
If you look at one of the comments, Chris, it says Linux Academy have invited
Chris from JB to come and convert their broadcasting workflow. The next comment
says, but they are an academy, so why do they need help from somebody else? Isn't
that the point of the open source community to share ideas and collaborate?
Yeah, help each other.
I just don't understand the hate. I don't get it.
Yeah. And, you know, it doesn't make you an expert on every topic, does it Wes?
But no, no, not at all. Right. And I think we Linux desktop users obviously
like that, want to promote it. And that does usually get, or at least historically
has gotten a fair amount of time at these, these Linux meetups and events.
But especially if you just have, you know, Texas Linux fest, that doesn't
necessarily mean it has to be desktop Linux. It doesn't really have to mean
anything else. And shouldn't we try to be an inclusive community of, hey,
we want whatever you like. Maybe you, maybe you started on the server. You
love using your Mac on a desktop. It works really well, especially with the
corporate provided PowerPoint that you're required to use or, or whatever else.
And just try to show that, Hey, look at all these, you know, if you come to the
conference and see a bunch of other people presenting on ThinkPads or see
people with ThinkPads showing you how great they are, that's one way to do it.
And complaining about it probably won't get very far.
Well said. Good point. And what do you think about this idea that if we bury
our heads in the sand and say, none of us ever use a Mac or nobody ever tries
Adobe premier, they only use Katie and live or they, they never try anything
on windows. They've never even booted windows. Are they an expert that you
want to hear their opinion on topics from? I mean, like, aren't they missing a
huge data point? Can they be trusted? What do you think of that, Wes?
You do need to be aware of what alternative workflows actually exist. If
you're going to speak to them, especially if you're coming from a world where
people are already using those workflows, it's much easier, especially in the open
source side. If you just have never touched the proprietary stuff. And sometimes,
honestly, I've had it in my life where I just avoid it. You know, I don't need
that. I know that if I try it, I'll probably get hooked and I'll start wanting to
use that service instead of whatever open source tool I'm using.
Yeah, that's the slippery slope.
It really is. And that can be fine, right? We've talked a lot on the show about
sometimes it makes sense to pay for things, even if they're proprietary for
your own personal life. Be pure when you can support open source when you can.
But none of us are perfect. And then especially going the other way, once
you've established a workflow, especially if you're using it for some sort of
commercial endeavor for your business at your workplace, you can't just change
because you want to. You have to be able to change because it actually works or
maybe is even better. Yeah. Yeah, true that. Eric, you have to use what you use
a Mac or Windows for your day job. Do you find that gives you a good contrast
of point of comparison?
So when I first started this job, I was issued a Dell laptop running Windows
7. They announced shortly thereafter that they moved moving to Windows 10,
which is OK for the two games I played twice a month here at home. But as far
as a work system, Windows 10 just isn't isn't there at all as a Linux server
engineer. So I was able to request a MacBook Pro, which I liked my 2015
MacBook, but they issued me one of the one of the one of the touchpad
MacBooks with the new keyboards that feel like you're just pounding on
concrete. But having having all three operating systems around me, I'm a
Linux server engineer and then I'm actually talking to you guys from my
from my custom built arch PC at home. So I feel like at least having some
exposure to all three platforms really gives me an appreciation and really
gives me a drive to work on what what tools can I port over to my Linux
system? Because yeah, I hear I may be I may be running arch, but it's still
the most stable platform of all three operating systems I work on.
Yeah, OK, that makes sense. It sort of drives you to keep pushing it forward.
So Poby, I'd love to hear your perspective on this because rumor has it
there may be a Mac user to a canonical. Someone may be using arch even at
canonical. So this is a controversy that you've witnessed not just a canonical,
but all over the place. What are your thoughts on a don't you kind of isn't
it isn't it good every now and then to like look at a Mac and see how they do
it when you're when you're working on, say, creating software for the Linux
desktop? Because that's good, valuable experience. And B, what about this
whole attitude around the whole thing? So it's not controversial at canonical
because we've never had a policy where you have to run Ubuntu. You run
whatever you need to run because actually the computer is your own. The
company doesn't provide you with a computer. You get a
chunk of money periodically and you go buy whatever you want. Soon as you
do your job, nobody cares what you're running on your desktop. And so that
means some people are running Ubuntu. Some people actually aren't running
Ubuntu. And that might mean they're running some other Linux distro. It
might be in there running a different desktop or it might be in there running
a Mac. And many of those people who are using Macs are using Macs because the
software they need to use to do their job is not available on Linux. End of
story. And no, GIMP and Inkscape are not alternatives. So yes, those people,
some of those people work in design, but some of them aren't. Some of them are
server people or DevOps people and they run OS 10 on a on a Mac because they
prefer that laptop and they do all their Linuxy stuff in VMs or on remote
machines. They're not part of the desktop team. So there's no real reason
why they should have to run Ubuntu desktop. So you may see someone who
works for Canonical on the server side or the cloud side who uses OS 10,
but it's their laptop. It's their choice. They can do whatever they want with it
so long as they get the job done. Personally, I can see why people have
this need to point out that if you're an ambassador of a distro or an
ambassador of a product, it makes sense for you to use it. You would never see
someone who works for Coke on stage drinking Pepsi. It's no different than
that, really. But if your role is in PR, you're making a massive faux pas by
doing that Coke Pepsi thing. But if that's not your job, if your job is
working on something that's completely unrelated to the Linux desktop and is
like a server component or an application that runs on a server, then
all bets are off. It's up to you what you run on it. So I think it's a little
ridiculous that people go hunting down people who are running something other
than the thing they want to run, right? And these same people are the people
who will reboot into Windows in order to run Steam and they're allowed to do
it, but you're not. And I don't like that attitude.
That's a good point too. Yeah, I think my wrapping thoughts are really around
this whole thing is it just makes really good practical sense to stick with
free and open source software. And it isn't necessarily worth like going to
the pitchforks when somebody is talking about Linux from a Mac because there
were other presenters that were using, I don't even know what kind of hardware
it was. It was ARM-based eclectic self-built small batch computers that
were like you had wires running to an HDMI port. And I didn't see a Reddit
thread started about that, but those are running Linux. So it's I think
important to keep in mind that you want to have an informed opinion,
especially if you're going to have a strong one. I have a strong preference,
for example, for iOS over Android. Not a big fan of it. Just think iOS is
slightly better. Think Android slightly worse. I think there's also serious
privacy trade-offs with Android versus iOS. That's a position I'm perfectly
comfortable defending because I've owned an Android device. I still own
Android devices. I've bought many many Android devices. I know how to use
Android very well. I'm a very competent Android user. So my preference for
iOS is based on my direct experience using Android. I feel like that's a good
thing because at least you know I've tried it. I'm not sitting here espousing
how great Siri is without trying the Echo. I'm not telling you that I think
iOS is better without ever trying an Android device. That would make me an
idiot. It's important that we don't lose sight, that we can't just white watch
the world and have everyone on Chromebooks or everyone on a Linux
desktop and pretend like Windows and Macs don't exist. Because the reality is
they do exist. So we have to know how to interact with them. We have to know how
to support them. And we have to know where we're deficient so we can make up
our deficiencies. And when you're committing, when you're trying to
convince someone to switch over to a free or open source software product,
and if it has deficiencies, if it does not have equivalent functionality to the
proprietary thing you're switching them to, you're going to lose credibility if
you don't tell people that. If they get over and then they discover, it's going
to leave a bad taste in their mouth and it's probably going to push them back
into the arms of commercial software harder and probably forever.
Exactly. Yeah, right. And it's the wrong perspective. Especially if you're
trying to convince someone, the nice thing to do is have a conversation. So
maybe we can have a conversation about this topic as like, why did we not see
more Linux laptops in presentations? And instead of being antagonistic or
an interrogation, it can be a conversation. And if you start from the
place of, hey, what are your workflows? I'm curious if maybe Linux could do
those better instead of, or just try to understand why they think a Mac works
well from them. That's very different. Is it a projector thing? Is it a slide
software thing? What is it? What are we not, what are we not proficient enough
in? We don't know. We don't know. It's a great point, Wes. Okay. So Tyler,
if you're at the mic, I'd love to hear how self went about maybe, do you
know about how many people were there? Yeah, I couldn't give an exact number,
but definitely a healthy crowd. Pretty much filled the room during the keynote
talk that Jeremy gave. And that was a good talk going over the last 10 years
itself. He had plenty of funny anecdotes, especially stories about, including a
story about a wedding that went on one of the years that they had the
conference at a hotel. That's great. And was there a fair amount of vendors?
From what I understand, there were fewer than there was last year from what I
was told. And I think that's probably due to the overlapping in schedules with
the conferences like Texas Linux Fest. So he didn't want to step on too many
toes on that one. Yeah, I think that costs Texas Linux Fest a few vendors as
well. And that really, I think the reason why it was going down at the same time
came down to like venue scheduling or something really benign that ends up
just totally being like, what was everybody thinking? It's really kind of
a shame. So now do you regret skipping Linux Fest Northwest or do you think it
was good to balance it out this week or this year? I think it was definitely
good to balance it out this year. But having experienced both now, I am
definitely returning to Self next year. Really? Yeah. Okay. Good plug for Self.
Very nice. Maybe I'll go. So Mr. Popey, how was Floss Talk? A good get together
of Linux podcasters drinking beer in a small, intimate venue. Must've been fun.
Yes. Actually, it's Foss Talk. Oh yeah, thank you. Yeah. Foss Talk Live. It's
organized by the internet's Joe Ressington. And this is a third one, I think.
We went along as in the people who run Ubuntu podcast, Joe and the guys from
Late Light Linux, and there's the guys from Linux Voice go along. And also
there's a drunken mashup show at the end of the evening, which is variable
quality, but was excellent this year, much better than they've redeemed
themselves from last year. And there's a podcast recording then a break and
a podcast recording then a break. So everyone gets to clear out and go and
get another beer and then come back down into the very small cozy basement
where we record the shows. And it's very intimate. There's some familiar faces
that turn up in the audience and also some new people each time. It's lovely.
It's really, really good fun. It's a really nice way to just have an evening
out with some friends and record some silly podcasts. It's good fun.
Yes, that does sound like good fun. And yes, Floss Talk, of course, is
Randall Schwartz's show that I get stuck in my head because my brain does
not have enough room for words. Now, I know that Joe's already put out
his Late Night Linux of the talk there, and it was good. I won't lie.
It made me a little bummed because the topics they chose were all the guys
had very, I thought, clear analysis of challenges facing Linux. And it
actually kind of motivated me to kind of want to try to fix it. Some of the
things they talked about around marketing and all of that. So anyways,
their episode was out. I'm assuming an Ubuntu podcast must be coming soon.
Yep. Ours will go out at 3pm UK time on Thursday. We were on immediately
after them. They were our warm up act. And we were a lot more upbeat, I think.
You bring the mood up? Good. I should have known.
We lifted the mood a little bit. So yeah, look out for that on our website on
Thursday.
I should have stacked them. That would have been better to stack them in my
podcast player if I had known because I was like, oh, all right, we can fix
this. It was kind of motivating, though. So it was good. I'm really glad that
that happened. One of these days, although they're at Texas Linux Fest,
there were several people saying, go to Fosdom, go to Fosdom, go to Fosdom.
That's the thing to go to. So that may be in my future as well.
Yes, go to Fosdom. It's amazing.
So this must be your first US Fest, Alex.
First time I've been to anything outside Europe, yeah. But Fosdom,
you should definitely go to Fosdom.
All right. There you go. Another plug for Fosdom. It might just happen.
I'll go with you. You and I will both go, Wes. We'll go over there. We'll do
like a Wes and Chris tour of London.
Or Storm Europe.
So start drinking your water now because we're probably going to be
drinking a lot of beer. Yeah. Wes and Chris, Storm Europe.
Fosdom's in Brussels, so you get great beer and great waffles.
Ooh. Oh my, oh my.
Yep. So I'll be fasting pretty soon to make up for the tons and tons and tons of eating
because there has just been... I mean, what else are you going to do when you're in Texas?
Yeah. I think you're 90% barbecue. Did you manage to steal any recipes to sneak back
up here to the Pacific Northwest?
I tried to bring back a few samples so that we could study them and then derive.
Yeah. But somehow it all got eaten. I don't know what happened.
It's some mysterious thing. Oh, Levi.
I think the secret's in the cows, Wes. That's what I think it is.
Oh. The secret's in the cows.
Actually, speaking of secrets though, after our really great barbecue that we had at Terry Black's
barbecue, we got to tour where they cook it all.
No way.
It's like behind the restaurant. Yeah. We just casually asked and they're like,
yeah, man, come on in. Mind you, it was like 98 degrees outside
and a humidity of like 80% or something.
And so you go inside this barbecue pit, which is like a large greenhouse,
almost only it's full of barbecue cookers, temperature shoots up to like 110 degrees.
It's dry heat, but it's just incredibly hot in there where they were smoking tomorrow's meat.
And the guy works in there in that Texas heat all day long.
And when you step out, when you step back outside, it feels like you're stepping into
air conditioning because the temperature is so hot in there.
So I did try to grok a few secrets. They converted old propane tanks,
like big propane tanks, like on the side of a house.
They converted big propane tanks into barbecue tanks.
Really?
Yeah. Yeah. It was a good time. It was a really good time.
And I'm going to have to do it again.
So let's talk about our app pick this week, and then we're going to wrap this sucker up.
It's FERP, F-R-P, a fast reversible proxy.
And I like the way they described this, Wes, because it will help you do one of two things.
It'll expose any HTTP and HTTPS service behind a NAT, or number two, expose any TCP or UDP service
behind a NAT, which would seem to include HTTP.
So what is FERP, Wes, and how is it doing it?
It is a fast reverse proxy, and it's a Go application that's got just pretty simple
I and I based command file.
You run one instance on some server with a public IP address.
So I've got one up on our dear friends digital ocean, and then you connect to it.
It also has a client program.
Both of them have a configuration file.
The server just sort of like sets up, opens its port for clients to connect to.
There is token based authentication if you have security in mind, and you probably should.
Then you configure your client and sort of configure on the client side,
what services you want to export.
You then get that running with that client config, connects up to the server,
and then they do a little magic mumbo jumbo talking to each other.
Then your services are, that's it, your services are exposed.
You can reach them from the public internet.
It does the reverse proxy back to whatever computer is behind the NAT.
It doesn't really have to care.
You don't have to open anything on your firewall as long as the client can reach out.
And then the stateful firewall does its job and lets the server talk back through.
You're good to go.
That's pretty cool.
And I could think of all kinds of fun ways to use and abuse that.
The other nice thing is it's also got a dashboard that comes with it, and the dashboard's pretty,
it's a little more full feature than I really expected it to be,
especially for something that is probably just thrown together.
So there is a link that'll exist at least for a little while in the IRC room.
You can go check it out.
The password's admin.
The username is admin.
Just yeah, simple little view.
It shows you all the proxies that you've set up so you can get a good idea of what's actually running,
if they're online or not.
Cool.
Plus it's Go, so it's just like a little, you know, it's a little static binary.
They've got it for different architectures, whether you're on ARM or AMD or whatever else.
Have you moused over one of these pie charts for the network traffic yet?
Have you seen that little bounce effect that it does?
It's pretty cute.
It's really neat, actually.
I did not expect the dashboard part of this.
That surprises me.
Oh, this is really cool.
And it's actually still responding even though myself and others in the chat room are banging
on it right now.
Yeah, no, I haven't used this a ton.
It just caught my eye this week, and I thought it would be neat.
In other situations, you'd probably set up some sort of a version of it.
A reverse or dedicated tunnel.
But for, you know, if you're just moving around a lot, you don't really know what you need,
or you just need something for short term, this could be super handy.
And I like how minimal the config is.
So instead of having a generic VPN tunnel that you have to really carefully firewall,
you know with this program that you're really only setting up a few exported services,
and you can see them right there in your config.
Absolutely.
So that's pretty cool.
Again, it's FERP, and we'll have a link to that in the show notes at linuxunplugged.com.
Slash 253.
Mr. Payne, before we go, you should probably tell people where they can get a little more
West in their life.
Oh, yeah.
Well, one, techsnap.systems.
Stay tuned.
There'll be another one coming out sometime this week.
Or if you're just impatient, I'm at West Payne over on the Twittersphere.
Heyo, I'm at Chris LAS.
The whole network is at Jupiter Signal.
I'll be down in Texas for about four more days, three more days or so.
And then I'm starting the long journey back up to the Pacific Northwest.
Man, do I miss those kids.
I'm excited about getting home.
I'm almost tempted just to fly home and see them.
Aw.
Leave Joob's behind.
We all miss you, too.
Don't worry.
Go get more episodes at linuxunplugged.com slash subscribe.
Go check out the Ubuntu podcast.
They're going to have their episode.
And Joe put out Late Night Linux.
So go grab more Linux content over there at our friend sites.
And of course, join us next week live over at jblive.tv.
We do this show on Tuesdays.
And if we don't see you then, I'll see you on the download next Tuesday.
Oh, and the boss is away, Wes.
The bots will play.
I thought J-Bot took the afternoon off, but it looks like the title page is actually loading.
Oh, it is?
Oh, good.
I thought it was down, too.
Yeah.
Personalities happens not bad.
That's pretty good.
That's not perfect, but it's pretty, pretty good.
It's close.
Pretty good.
Hey, Mumba Room.
Thanks, guys.
It's great to have some of you in there for the first time.
You're welcome.
You guys are the best.
Where did you get FRP from?
This graph thing.
Wes found that.
Yeah, Wes found that this week.
He is a sleuther, Popey.
It's true.
I don't actually quite remember where I saw it from.
Kind of neat, huh?
Eric and I are wondering if we need to try Kansas City barbecue.
Yeah, that's what everybody says.
Although, man, do the people in Austin talk shit about Kansas City barbecue.
You know what else they say is that you guys think it's good because you don't know any
better.
That's what they say.
Multiple people say.
People tell me.
People tell me, Tyler.
Don't they also BS about Carolina barbecue?
Hey, look, I have tried all the barbecues on this trip.
I've tried North Carolina, South Carolina, Memphis, Arkansas catfish barbecue, Texas
barbecue.
And hell, if Texas barbecue didn't win, hands down.
Yeah, only one got the life changing title.
Only one.
I didn't hear no memo in there.
Does anybody want to visit Alabama?