You know what, screw the pre-show.
It's not the boss of us.
Yeah.
Or you could make the pre-show just you saying,
I think we're going to skip the pre-show.
Yeah, but that's so cliche.
We shouldn't do that.
We've got to stop doing that.
Just admit you're failing, Chris.
No, I could.
I could.
I could come up with a pre-show if I wanted to.
If I wanted to.
I'm sure I could, you know?
But I figure, why bother?
You know what, who needs a pre-show?
Nobody needs a pre-show.
You know, pre-show, it's not even the actual show.
So if it was, we'd put it in the show.
So we might as well just get rid of it.
These folks just want extra free show.
That's not fair.
I know.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Guess what?
What?
Big news.
This episode's brought to you by the all new Cloud
Guru, the leader in learning for Cloud Linux
and other modern tech skills.
Hundreds of courses, thousands of hands-on labs.
Get certified, get hired, get learning
at acloudguru.com.
Coming up on today's episode, this is one of those episodes.
This is one of those.
It's one of those, really.
You know what?
I don't even need to say more than that, but I'm going to.
It might just be one of the most exciting releases
in a long time.
Fedora 34 is out today as we record.
And we have a comprehensive review coming up.
But loads of new tech are packed into this Fedora release
beyond just GNOME 40, which is big on its own.
And basically, all of it that we're
going to talk about today will be coming to a distribution
near you very soon.
Plus, as always, we've got some community news,
some pics, and more.
So before I get into any of that,
I got to holla at that virtual lug.
Time appropriate greetings, Mumble Room.
Hello.
How's it going?
We've got a strong group today.
Yeah.
Look at that.
Jeez, how'd you all fit in here?
Wow.
You know, this is why we had to get the mega studio.
Because all the social distancing and whatnot,
we needed the 40,000 square feet.
And the room for the grills.
Right, of course.
Let's get into some community news.
And this week, we wanted to talk a little bit
about this University of Minnesota kernel ban story.
Please do check out Linux Action News 186, where we
went into some details there.
But if you didn't know, I want to make
sure we cover some of this in this here episode.
Because this is a very thick and complicated story
with a lot of finger pointing and mail list posts to read.
And if you didn't know the details,
you might not fully understand and appreciate
the scale of this problem.
You might maybe just sort of brush it off as drama
or just sort of not even really pay attention.
But there is a real problem here.
Three hypocrite patches, as they are called by the researchers,
made it into the Linux kernel around August of 2020.
If you didn't know that, you should be listening to LAN.
Because I think a lot of people right now
think that nothing made it, that a maintainer caught something
in April and rejected it, and these patches never made it in.
But that's actually not the case.
In fact, there's really no evidence
that indicates the patch in April
is linked to these hypocrite patches at all.
So it's a great example of why Wes and I go above and beyond
to really try to get the facts right.
I contacted Greg KH directly to try
to get some of the details as accurate as possible
for the story.
And one thing that I feel like hasn't been properly talked
about is a pretty valid concern that was going
to be raised by the research.
Super quick recap, Wes, you totally correct me
if I'm wrong, just jump right in.
But if you're not familiar with the story, back in August
of 2020, some researchers at the University of Minnesota
around that time submitted a series of stealthy fixes
that weren't really fixes that when combined actually
sort of created a vulnerability, but not necessarily
each individually on their own.
And three of those patches were accepted
by the maintainer of that particular subsystem
into the Linux kernel in August of 2020-ish time.
We don't actually have all the details yet.
That's one of the things the Linux Foundation is asking for.
And it is a little nuanced because it sort of relied
on the workflow of the maintainers.
They weren't looking for the code
to actually make it into a git tree.
They were just looking for the maintainer
to sign off on it saying, like, yeah, this looks good.
Right.
They never shipped like a distro or even making it
a Linus's tree, right?
It wasn't like it never made it that far.
And I think it's also worth mentioning just as a side note
here, my understanding is, again,
the university has not given us all the details yet.
But my understanding is when the maintainer accepted
the patches, the university actually reached out and went,
oh, oh, actually, we just caught the mistake.
Here's the actual patch instead, and then sent them
working code.
That's their claim.
I don't know how true that is.
But that is important to understand.
So then we fast forward to April of 2021
when a PhD student submitted a patch,
and it was rejected by the maintainer
for being just crap code.
And not really fixing anything, right?
Well, you're saying you're fixing
this use after free thing, but we've already
taken care of that elsewhere.
This doesn't do anything.
Right.
And so there was a little bit of suspicion about,
like, why did you submit this?
Because your university has a history here
of kind of screwing with the kernel for your own research,
and now you submit me this patch that
looks kind of like garbage.
This is either just you not knowing what you're doing,
or malicious.
And so that triggered a series of events
that eventually led to the University of Minnesota
from being banned to contribute to the kernel,
and the kernel team going through and reviewing
any patch they've ever made, and the Linux Foundation
sending the university a letter saying,
you need to tell us about every patch you've ever
committed to open source projects, period,
and you need to kill that paper.
Essentially, you need to shut that paper down
that you are about to announce in less than a month
at the IEEE convention that happens virtually
on May 23rd through the 25th.
You got to shut that paper down.
Because the researchers were writing a paper essentially
about doing these hypocrite patches,
about how they could gain the trust of open source
developers, and then trick them into accepting bogus code
to build a vulnerability via multiple patches.
And they were going to write a paper, and they did,
and they were going to publish it.
It's all done.
It's written.
That's not what the recent news is about.
The recent news is just sort of perfectly timed
so that when that paper does announce,
or they're going to have to kill it,
that paper is dead, basically.
The news is perfectly timed to kill the news story that
was about to be landing as a bit of a bombshell,
potentially, around the end of May.
And the question that I think the researchers
were trying to raise is, in one part, no duh.
If you trick somebody for a while
and then you stealthily slip in bogus code that
builds to a vulnerability, I think
even without doing any studies, pretty good guess,
you could probably get that pass to maintainer.
But what about that problem?
It's truly possible it could happen at Microsoft, or Apple,
or Oracle, or some other proprietary organization.
Absolutely.
But it's not as easy, because there's
going to be, in the case of the Mac OS kernel,
about four people at Apple that are allowed to actually commit
that code.
And so you'd have to compromise one of those four people,
at least their GPG key.
And on top of that, there is a clear repercussion system
in place if somebody were to make a compromise like that.
It's not impossible.
But it's much harder to happen with a Windows kernel
or the Mac OS kernel.
And then imagine for a moment if this was something higher up
in the stack, if this wasn't a kernel,
if this was maybe NGINX, or something even higher up
in the stack in the user land that really
doesn't have as many eyes.
Could it be just a common library that you have, right?
Who really cares what gets merged into left pad?
And so what do we do about this problem, Wes?
Because it's there.
It's probably not super critical,
because in reality, it would eventually be caught.
It would be worked out.
The way the systems and tools work,
we'd know when it was committed and who committed it
and every commit they'd ever made.
So there are tools in place in that regard.
But doesn't it seem like there should be something in place,
screening or doing some kind of automated checking
at best we can to see if what they claim it does,
it even does?
Well, to some degree, there are some automated tooling.
I think the question of can we have more things that help,
that's always true.
We have to think about it.
There's just bugs that get merged,
both malicious and accidental.
That's a problem that happens in all software
and in the kernel as well.
I think we need some more research to help understand,
what's the scope of this problem?
And how does the maintainership process really work?
I think scholarship around that and what's happening there
is worthwhile, just clearly not in the way
these researchers did it.
No kidding.
Talk about messing around with a development team
that has very limited time and resources
and messing around with software that literally
ships in mission-critical, life-critical applications.
There is satisfying intellectual curiosity,
and then there is crossing the line.
And I agree with the kernel team that from the evidence
that's available to us at this time, in my opinion,
they definitely crossed the line.
And they are right to ban future development
until they sort this whole thing out.
They've been sent a letter.
The Linux Foundation has made reasonable requests,
in my opinion.
And now it's really kind of the balls in the university's court.
They released on the 24th of April an apology.
But the apology sort of just says, well,
if I'd asked you for the cookie, you would have said no,
so I just took the cookie.
And so I know I shouldn't have taken the cookie,
but I really wanted the cookie, is essentially
what their apology says.
Not good enough.
No, and a lot of folks pointed out
that, well, you could have tried to come up
with other methodologies.
And then there's just sort of the arrogance or isolation
of researchers in academia who need to publish.
They have an idea.
They think they just want to go about it.
Clearly, they didn't give that much thought
to how to get the institutional review or what level
or really what the potential consequences of that work
might be.
And I think there's also sort of a trust between academia
and open source, because there's a lot of principles shared
there and a lot of shared history.
So that's just even more rude.
Yeah, and not to bang this drum too much,
but the details are in Linux Action News 186.
And the reason why I'm hitting that drum so hard
is Wes and I spent our entire Sunday
getting the details of that story as accurate as we could.
Listening back, I'm pretty happy with it.
I think I would have likened maybe one more
crack at covering it, but we spent all day on it
on a Sunday to get that story right.
And so the details, I think, matter in this one,
because there's multiple timelines.
There's multiple he said, she said.
And so it is a fascinating topic, and the bigger question
it raises, I think, is worth considering.
And we should say, I think that question is being considered,
maybe not as much as it showed or not as publicly.
But you did see in the mailing list,
there were even conversations around people asking,
how much review do you give to these folks?
Some maintainers saying, oh, someone like that,
I'd be very skeptical.
And others saying, well, we have to admit many of us
are very busy maintainers, and if the code looks good,
we might just merge it.
So I think there's also a cultural thing at play
beyond tooling, and that conversation
should happen too.
And while all of this is going on, of course,
business still is normal, usual.
Development continues for the Linux kernel,
and version 5.12 was released this weekend.
And Linux can now run as a root partition on Hyper-V.
There's also more support for that lightweight hypervisor
Acorn, as well as some RISC-V support landing.
Broadcom's VK video accelerators, instead of CPU
load, can now be chip-based.
Support for the PlayStation controller for PS5,
Nintendo 64, and more all land.
Nintendo 64 console's in there too,
which we noted on LAN as well, but just hilarious.
That thing runs at like 94 megahertz.
You could just swap it in for a couple of your pies, right?
You don't need more than eight megs of RAM.
You know what I found fascinating, though,
around 5.12, Wes, was actually just some of the details
of what make up a kernel.
So if you look at it, in some senses,
Linux 5.12 was one of the slowest development cycles
we have seen in the kernel since version 5.6, which was not
released that long ago, about a year ago.
But there's still plenty of things that landed,
like we mentioned.
And you still have some serious numbers here.
1,873 developers contributed to Linux 5.12.
262 of those were first-time contributors.
That's about an average number, but it's
pretty neat to see that.
Oh, yeah.
No, that is nice to see.
Of course, on the other side, there's some heavy hitters.
Folks like Lee Jones, who was the most active chainset
contributor this time around, working on compiler stuff,
docs, and warnings throughout the tree.
Chris Wilson doing a lot of work on the Intel i915 graphics
driver, which, hey, as an Intel user, I appreciate that.
And Christopher Helwig continues to clean up
the code in the block layer and file systems.
Also important work.
Yeah, that looks really good.
And it's nice to see the IOU ring subsystem
get some improvements.
The network subsystem is in there,
as well as some cleanup code in the block layer and file
systems.
So it's a good, solid kernel in there.
It's a handsome kernel, you might say.
And it was supported by 211 different employers
that LWN was able to identify.
So LWN went in and looked at this stat.
They say it's a small decrease, but the top contributor
by chainsets in 5.12 is Intel at 10.9% of the changes.
Interestingly, though, by lines changed,
Lonaro is at the top with 17.4%.
When you go by the pure number of lines of code change,
Lonaro was really crushing it this time.
I guess just due to a flurry of code removal patches
that they sent out this time.
All right, keeping things clean, I like that.
That counts, man.
That counts.
Unknown represents 7.7% of changes
by just looking at chainsets.
And then in the number three slot
is Red Hat with 872 chainsets.
Red Hat's also in the number three slot
when you look at just lines changed,
with 38,000 lines of code changed just in this kernel.
Oh my god.
Wow, that's just the scale, Wes.
The scale of this project and the fact
that they managed to ship and ship reliably
and produce something usable is, well, it needs to be,
it's going to have to be studied by historians at some point.
Well, yeah, right?
That's kind of why some scholarship is warranted here,
because they incorporate a huge number of changes
in a reliable way, in a predictable way.
I mean, we're going to be running a pretty new kernel
with 5.11 here on Fedora.
And I'm not worried about that at all,
and I wouldn't really be worried about switching
to 5.12 today either.
Yeah, in fact, 5.13 is shaping up to be a big boy.
Torvalds wrapped up the announcement of 5.12
by kind of prepping people for the size and scale of 5.13.
He says, quote, please spend a bit of time
running and checking out 5.12 before we start sending
a merge request for 5.13.
Because despite the extra week, this 5.12
was actually a fairly small release overall.
And judging by the Linux Dash next tree,
5.13 is going to be making up for it.
And in 5.13, as just a reminder, we're
going to get initial support for Apple's M1 chips,
the addition of a new wireless WAN
subsystem, more RISC-V support, and Intel's standalone GPUs,
if they ever ship.
Well, 5.13 will have support for them.
Just can't wait.
Yeah, you know what, Wes?
You look at this and you go, there
is so much happening in kernel land
that by the time you could actually get caught up,
by the time you get to a distro, it's
like a whole other generation of hardware is out.
The kernel team, though, just continues to just crush it.
And to get, again, some of this RISC-V stuff and Intel stuff
in and the M1 stuff in, years maybe, in some cases,
before anybody needs it, is going to lay some groundwork
for the future.
Can't stop, won't stop.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Head over there and check out Linode.
They're our hosting provider, and everything
we've built in the last couple of years is on Linode.
So you go to linode.com slash unplugged
to get a $100, 60-day credit towards your new account.
And of course, you support the show at linode.com slash
unplugged.
Unlike entry-level hosting providers or the big clouds
like AWS that try to tie your hands and lock you down,
Linode gives you the tools to get the most out
of their crazy fast systems.
You get 11 data centers to choose from,
and every service level is backed by the best customer
support in the business.
And that really matters.
I mean, that really matters.
It makes all of the difference when you're in a tight spot.
And it's not just like one great thing
like the support that makes Linode fantastic
and our go-to choice for anything we're building.
It's all of the great things about Linode coming together
that make them special.
And at every step of the way since 2003,
Linode has asked themselves, how can we
use Linux to accomplish this next task?
How can we use Linux to do what we want in a way
that people are not yet using it?
Their love and dedication to that is baked into the product.
And as a long-timer, I can tell it.
And that's something I really love about Linode.
And if you're not catching Linode's new tutorials
by HackerSploit, you're missing out on something great,
some chances to learn.
I'll put a link in the show notes
to a video on learning the various tools and commands
for logging and monitoring.
These are some great basics.
And if you can learn that from a YouTube video in like 15
minutes, well, that's going to change your server game.
So get started by going over to linode.com slash unplugged.
Get that $100 for your new account.
And try this stuff out.
Try out the object storage.
This could be an amazing way to get
your configs, your server stuff, off-site
in a system that's in the cloud, that's reliable, that's fast,
but doesn't require running an entire server in front of it.
Go build something, or maybe learn something.
With that $100, there's a lot you can get access to.
So go to linode.com slash unplugged.
There's a lot of ways to host something.
And there's a lot of various companies
that will do it for you.
Go see why we choose Linode every time.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
So Flatpak has a new version that's in the works.
So you have an interim release as they develop stuff.
And then we're going to have the final release that
is the actual stable version for end users.
And the development version is 1.1.1.1.
And the release version that we'll actually
get our hands on eventually is going to be 1.1.2.
And why am I telling you about this?
Because this is actually the first time
we've ever covered a Flatpak interim release on the show.
But this time, they're taking a few steps
towards something kind of cool.
Yeah, they have some notable feature changes already
in just 0.1 here, one of which that's worth mentioning
is allowing sub-sandboxes to have
a different slash user or slash app.
Why would you want that?
Well, right now, initially, it's being
used by the Flatpak Steam effort to launch games
within its own container runtime showing up
with a replaced slash user.
That's why they need the new feature.
Basically, the goal is to be able to handle the Steam Linux
runtime within a Flatpak sandboxed environment
and sort of merge those two systems together.
Whoa.
My mind is blown by this.
And it's not just that, too.
Flatpak's also working on support for better command line
text user interface type programs,
like the Nano Text Editor was specifically mentioned.
So that's pretty great.
To make it clear here, they're making
it possible to support Steam's pressure vessel.
They're not using pressure vessel.
They're making it possible.
And that's Valve's project to put Linux runtimes
in containers to make old libraries and whatnot available
to games, even on newer OS releases.
And unlike certain other use cases for containers,
that one, the pressure vessel, the pressure vessel stuff
is just for compatibility with old games.
They're not really trying to get security right.
They're not really bothering about sandboxing.
The idea is that you could ship this stuff inside a Steam
Flatpak and have support for these containers
and do all of it with bubble wrap and a universal package,
I suppose.
The idea is pretty neat.
It feels a bit like turtles all the way down to me.
But I understand that it's necessary for compatibility.
Really, it's just exciting to see these technologies both
working.
And I mean, I'm already using a lot of the Flatpak stuff anyway.
Seems like this is a good test of using it in anger,
making it work for more and more use cases,
and just ironing out the whole setup.
OK, Wes, this next one here, it's
kind of one for the virtual lug a bit.
I think we've kind of got it wrong.
I think we've all been worried about WSL, especially now
WSLG, which supports GUI Linux applications.
Right, yeah, everyone's a little worried about that.
Yeah, we're all worried about it.
But if you look at Linux's true successes in the market
at scale, it's the server, right?
Like, the desktop, as much as we love it,
the desktop doesn't even really show up on the radar, right?
It's just a teeny, teeny, tiny blip.
But the server is like this.
It's this massive worldwide phenomenon.
So even if WSL were to rob all of the Linux desktop market,
every single Linux desktop user, which is never going to happen,
but just for the sake of argument, if WSL with WSLG now
on Windows 10, or Windows 11, or whatever,
one day were to take every single Linux user
and get them to convert somehow, it wouldn't actually
radically change the market dynamics
of where Linux is a powerhouse, really.
It wouldn't really change the server dynamics.
So WSL can't really harm Linux.
In fact, if anything, it's probably
just going to mean more Windows developers are writing
server-side Linux applications.
It's probably going to actually further the Linux
server dominance.
Maybe it's not great for the desktop, but overall,
it's going to be good for Linux.
But AWS and companies like them, like other companies
that have these app platforms.
These sneaky cloud services, huh?
Right, or these serverless services
that are working to essentially abstract Linux away.
I think they take this argument that we
used to worry about with WebMint or services like Cockpit,
that, oh, the GUI makes it so you don't even
have to learn Linux.
And you don't even know how your system works.
Well, that seems like a quaint concern compared
to how things like serverless application platforms
work now, where everything is simply
an implementation detail behind the scenes,
and the user and the developer never have to know any Linux.
They never have to know a single command line.
They don't have to know the name of any
of the open source applications under the hood,
making it possible.
And this continues to be what all of these platforms push.
It's the primary marketing point of DigitalOcean.
It's the primary marketing point of AWS to small to medium
business segments.
It really is true.
At the day job, same thing.
There's a lot of rigmarole I have
to even get something close to Docker exec
into the container, despite all of it
being running on Linux and powered by Container Tech.
Right.
And so I think while we are kind of looking over at WSL,
worried that it's going to eat our lunch,
it really would only take companies
like Amazon and one or two others to flip a switch
and start changing the implementations
behind the scenes.
As long as they're still executing the code that end
users are expecting, the customers are expecting,
I don't think they're going to care if it's a Mac
on a power PC chip, executing the code as long as it
runs fast enough and gives them the output they want
at the price they want.
The fuchsia subsystem for Linux, right.
So I actually think that these companies that
are abstracting Linux away are more dangerous than WSL is.
They're more of a risk to Linux's actual core strength
and position in the market, because you can kind of come in
and sell on compatibility and ease,
and then over time, Amazon could switch it on the back end
to whatever they want, or Azure, or Digital Ocean.
It could be any one of them.
They could just flip a switch one day.
And now it's running on their new platform,
but all of the compatibility for the end user is still there.
And so I wonder if Amazon is essentially
over time in a position more and more
to kill server Linux, which is actually
the market of Linux that matters.
And I wonder if anybody in the Mumble Room has thoughts.
I don't think that they're going to do that.
If you want to talk about anyone who
would have any incentive to do that sort of thing,
it'd be Google.
AWS, I know AWS is often the boogeyman here,
and I don't have much skin in this game at all.
But AWS actually makes their own Linux distribution derived
from Red Hat Enterprise Linux.
They actively contribute to Fedora and the Fedora
ecosystem and other distribution ecosystems.
There's folks involved in SUSE Linux distributions, Debian
and so on.
And they even work with FreeBSD people.
I think of the big cloud providers,
AWS is actually the most open source friendly
and the least likely to screw over the Linux ecosystem.
I think few people remember how critical it
was that Fedora supported Zen properly for them
to even launch EC2.
Fedora was the first Linux distribution
that was available there.
And there's a strong relationship
between AWS and the Linux community as a whole.
I don't think we have the similar strength
of that relationship with the other cloud providers.
And that's where I tend to be more worried.
Microsoft has every incentive to do that,
because they build an operating systems platform that
is directly competing against Linux on all fronts.
And they're winning on one out of three fronts.
And the stuff that they're doing with Wizzle
makes it a lot easier to chip away at it with Google.
They're making Fuchsia.
That is their project.
Fuchsia has the ability to, if not now,
will eventually have the ability to emulate enough
of the user syscall interface to be
able to run Linux applications in the same way WSL1 did.
But in server workloads, the scale of syscalls and stuff
that's being used is considerably more limited.
And with containers, you already have so much filtering going
on that you kind of have a good idea of what kind of surface
you need to cover to be able to make stuff work.
And so if you target it that way,
you can do exactly what you're talking about.
So AWS isn't the one I'm worried about.
I'm worried about the other two.
Carpino, you think you agree because Google's Fuchsia
project could be this bait and switch swap?
Yeah, I think so.
I think it's not likely to happen anytime soon.
But because Fuchsia is offered under a different license that
is not GPL, it could provide a different kind of value
for some companies.
Therefore, the idea of investing in it
may sound attractive for some people.
There's kind of two things going on.
There are maybe some competitors to Linux like Fuchsia coming up.
But then also, I think the abstraction layer
is just continuing to raise like it does, right?
Like we are programming to higher standards.
And so Linux is just becoming more and more truly
of infrastructure, as it always has been.
It's just that the infrastructure is just
getting farther away from us as we go up the stack.
Yeah, and somebody has to set up those systems
to host those applications serverlessly.
Yeah, right.
There'll still be a lot of cloud providers
using them at least for a while until it makes sense not to.
And if they don't have to do that,
and Linux means they don't have to reinvent the real,
that seems like a good idea.
Hey, Wes, let's duck over here.
A little production side meeting.
I think we should probably do this privately, though.
The cone of silence.
All right, this is a little awkward.
So before we mention this on the show, you know, in the past,
I've promoted a lot of the humble bundles.
And they seem like a pretty good cause.
Yeah, I mean, I've definitely bought a few.
Yeah, yeah, I've bought more than a few.
But I think they got like bought out.
And I think they're making like weird, awkward changes.
And like they don't allow you to contribute your payments
to only devs who supported Linux anymore.
And they're kind of like restricting how much you
can give to charity now.
And like no more than 15% now.
They got a cap.
I don't know, it's awkward, man.
Do I say something on the show?
Think you might have to?
We should observe it at least anyway, you know?
They've been pretty consistent over the years.
So this is a big change.
Yeah, it's awkward.
It's definitely awkward.
OK, all right.
The cone of silence.
Oh, dang it, I left my keys in the cone.
Oh, Wes, dang it.
Well, we'll have to go back in later.
We have, because we have, first we
have a public service announcement.
The humble bundle pricing situation's
getting a little weird.
If you know what's going on, go to linuxunplug.com
slash contact to let us know.
Yeah, it seems like they've forced a certain set
of default splits.
And you just kind of go with that.
And you don't have any choices, which
was all the fun before, really.
And so I don't know why.
Maybe they just, it wasn't sustainable.
Maybe the new owners need some different revenue goals.
I don't know what it is, but I wanted
to let you guys know that they have capped the amount you
can give to charities at 15%, and they have changed it
so that you can no longer adjust your payments so that only
developers who supported Linux would get paid,
which I understand that everybody should get
some value for their product.
But I really liked trying to give
the bulk of my contribution to Linux developers
to kind of vote with my wallet.
So Wes didn't want to let you guys know.
He said don't tell you, but I thought you should know.
Well, I thought it would really get them down.
You know, there's enough bad news these days already.
That's true.
I have some good news.
MailRoute.net slash Linux.
Try out MailRoute today and get 10%
off the lifetime of your account and start
with a 30-day free trial, no credit card required.
That's right, MailRoute's back for another episode
because it just is such a great fit.
We heard from a bunch of you last week
that tried out MailRoute.
They've been doing MailRoute for 24 years.
Yeah, they've been focused on one thing,
providing cutting-edge email security.
And you know I respect that.
MailRoute protects your email server
with a suite of services designed
to remove spam, prevent viruses, and debilitating downtime.
And with our audience who likes to host stuff on their own,
you guys know sometimes it's tricky with your ISP
or for your own security.
Maybe you want to run SMTP on a different port.
Or maybe for some stupid reason, your perfectly legitimate email
server has ended up on a blacklist
that you are constantly fighting.
Oh, no more.
MailRoute solves all of those problems and more.
And they make it super easy for your business
to migrate if you use Google Apps or Office 365.
It's like one click.
But really, even if you don't, I just
set it up with our mail server that we
built over the last couple of weeks.
And it's crazy straightforward.
If you know anything about managing a mail server,
you can make this work.
It's probably, you're probably done in 10 minutes,
assuming you know the logins to your DNS
and to your MailRoute account.
But the one click migration is really sweet.
And they do have API level integration
for getting information in and out of MailRoute, which
I really appreciate, especially if you want to make sure
that you only allow mail from certain accounts
and you want to sync it with your master mail server.
Their API is great.
If you do business with the federal government
or you're a contractor where you have
to meet certain types of requirements,
well, they got you covered there as well.
And as an admin, you're going to love the fact
that they have real time log searches, which
was super useful when we were setting up our mail server.
And you also can queue mail up at MailRoute for up to 15 days
or whenever you release it, which
is perfect for covering you during an outage
or maybe just a window for some maintenance.
Like before that, I don't know what I would have done.
Like what, just take the mail server down and hope nobody
emails us during that time?
It's so silly.
So having something just in front of your mail server,
it's just a higher quality, higher production grade.
And of course, they know how to do this stuff.
So go try out MailRoute today and get 10%
off the lifetime of your account and get a 30-day free trial
by visiting mailroute.net slash linux
to protect your business and your email server.
MailRoute makes email better.
mailroute.net slash linux.
Fedora 34 is a big release.
It's huge.
And there's a lot to talk about in here.
So much to cover from both the desktop side,
but also in the other Spains and Core technology.
Whew, Wes.
I don't even know where we start.
Well, before we get too far along,
maybe we should take a moment to address the long-term future
of Fedora.
I think it's safe and probably more secure than ever.
Even after those recent CentOS changes.
But I know there's a lot of people
that have been worried about that, thinking maybe,
well, look at the changes happening to CentOS.
Could something like that happen to Fedora?
But I mean, I don't see it.
I don't think it really makes sense.
It seems like Fedora's role really is needed.
It's the place where everything happens first,
where these things get integrated and tested
and tried out.
And the needed development can actually happen.
Packages come in and they're ready to go.
They happen, packages can be tweaked, bugs fixed.
Core system stuff.
Yeah, new approaches to both the server and the desktop,
they all happen there.
And Red Hat needs that.
Right, they want it to happen there.
It seems like it's now sort of integrated
to the process of development in a way that is,
I think you'd say it's codified.
It's clear that for RHEL to be a successful product,
when you look at it from a corporate org chart
standpoint, Fedora is square one.
It's like you start at Fedora.
And for the end product that they make all the money
from to be successful, Fedora has to be successful.
And this new arrangement with CentOS Stream sort of codifies
that, I think.
Yeah, exactly.
I mean, it makes it more clear, at least,
to some of the stuff that was happening internally.
Now you can just see it laid out in this pipeline of how things
get created and how those changes eventually make
themselves into a Red Hat release.
But regardless of the details, I think we can just not worry.
Don't be scared to try out Fedora 34.
It's great.
We should probably just highlight
all the awesome things going on and maybe a few
of the things we don't love.
Yeah, and I think it's worth mentioning that there
are many spins of Fedora.
So we're going to talk at first a lot about the workstation
version, which ships with GNOME Shell.
But there's a plasma spin.
There's a server spin.
There's a lot of different versions here.
And some of it is core technology
that applies to all of them.
If you want us to cover another one specifically,
like a specific spin, totally let us know at the contact page.
I would love to.
I just don't want to overdo it.
So if there's something you'd like
us to look at specifically in this realm,
please let us know, because otherwise, we
are just sort of restraining ourselves
and trying not to overdo it.
Like the server spin, I think that's
particularly interesting this release, potentially,
because I believe, correct me if I'm wrong, guys,
but I believe that the next rel is ultimately
going to be based on Fedora 34.
So what happens here is particularly interesting
for several reasons beyond the immediate reasons.
And no matter what variant of Fedora you use,
you're going to get the latest in what the open source
world has to offer.
And really, all of what we're about to cover
will show up in just about every distro near you soon,
at least most of it.
So let's start with the big headline feature
in the workstation spin, which is GNOME 40, which we've
talked about a little bit before.
Yeah, I mean, it's not new in the sense
that it was already released.
But the first time it ships in a big name distro,
that's something of a milestone.
It is.
And it's the first time you're going
to really see it land in front of a lot of end users.
And it's predominantly recognized for the change
to horizontal workspace layouts, which
is similar to how elementary OS has already been doing it.
It's how I actually have my plasma setup configured most
commonly.
And it's a lot how Mac OS has done it for several releases.
And I think how Windows 10 does it
if you enable virtual workspaces, where everything
is left to right, essentially.
And once you learn it, it feels fast and natural.
And actually, because it is so common with the other desktop
platforms, it makes moving between all of those
a little less frictiony, a little smoother on the brain.
I like that a lot.
But I think the other thing that hasn't really
gotten a ton of appreciation in GNOME 40 is GTK 4.
And GTK 4 is like at step one of getting awesome.
And each inner release we're about to get,
it gets even more awesome.
And the awesome that I'm talking about is performance.
I'm talking Vulkan rendering performance.
And it's looking real good.
And GTK 4 apps, snap.
They really do.
Yeah, man.
And when you combine that with GNOME Shell 40 itself,
that's a nice little package, right?
I mean, I've just been playing with 2104 for a while
and was thinking about keeping it around.
It already felt much faster than the plasma desktop
I'd been using before.
But GNOME 40 is just the next level.
Yeah, and I've been impressed at how fast extension developers
are updating to support GNOME 40.
They have to implicitly update their extension.
Now, there are a few cons that I've noticed.
And I want to preface these cons with I
suspect they're all going to be addressed in future releases.
But the reality is it's not as easy
to get a quick overview of what apps are on which workspaces.
In the vertical layout, you would have a right there,
like a film strip on the side of your screen.
And you would see all the different application windows
across all of your desktops at once.
With the horizontal layout, you see like 1.3 of a desktop
at a time.
It's just not quite as efficient.
But it's so quick to slide through them.
And they do have little tiny, tiny, tiny previews
at the top that kind of give you an indication.
Right, that where did I put that terminal problem?
Yeah, that app I launched two days ago.
Also, it's kind of hard to move the workspaces
around themselves.
Say you start a chat app.
Maybe you've got two chat apps on one screen.
And on the second desktop, I open up my browser.
And then I decide I want to swap those two things.
So the browser's on desktop one.
And my two separate chat applications are on desktop two.
The only way to do that right now in GNOME 40,
instead of just being able to grab the virtual workspace,
the whole workspace itself, and move it,
you have to reshuffle all of the applications.
So move all the apps over to one screen.
And then move the other apps over to the other screen.
And these tiny little boxes at the top of the screen
in this little bitty, bitty preview,
you just can't swap the workspaces around easily.
But when you do get that layout right,
after you've spent the day with it,
and you figured out, OK, I like these apps on these screens
and all of that, man, it rocks.
And it rocks, really.
It rocks in a way that feels super polished.
And the only thing it leaves me wishing
is that I could then somehow save and restore that layout.
So I just log into GNOME Shell.
And my applications always open up on those virtual desktops.
Right, something that Plasma makes pretty easy.
Yeah, but man, is it smooth.
It feels very, very professional.
So that's GNOME Shell 40.
Really, overall, pretty much a positive take.
I'd like to see some work with additional external monitors,
but I know that stuff's coming.
I do think you hit on something that I noticed as well.
It is really great, but it is clearly
the start of a development chain.
There's some new ideas that are being explored and have
been recently implemented that are still getting worked out,
and that changes will happen too.
And that really felt contrasted to 2104,
sticking with the previous release, which, you know,
they'd polished out a little more of those things.
So depending on which way you like
to interact with your desktop, that
might be one way to sort of choose,
which of these new distros do I stick with?
In 2007, Fedora 8 was released.
And one of the headline features of Fedora 8,
I listened to my review this morning from Linux action show
like 67 or something.
Amazing.
Yeah, was Pulse Audio.
That was the release of Fedora that they
switched to Pulse Audio.
And I think everybody knows how that went.
In Fedora 34, this is the release
where they switched to PipeWire by default,
and it is a completely different migration.
Seems to be far more successful.
I mean, it's only just started, but at least in my testing,
you basically don't notice anything's different,
unless you use some, you know, there are picky apps.
There's still some Pulse modules that are getting
implemented here and there.
But by and large, it just works.
Not only does it just work from an end user experience,
but the project has been much more successful in reaching out
to the individual, quote unquote, stakeholders,
if you will, and getting them on board.
And even making changes, like I think in particular,
there was a lot of feedback from the Jack community
that influenced some of the design decisions
with PipeWire that meant that as PipeWire went along,
instead of turning people off and pissing them off
and kind of creating a divisive atmosphere,
it created this momentum of support.
And we started picking up application support
and library support and distribution support
and Linux media support.
And it all kind of really worked well.
Like, it was a good community management and code management.
Which is what you need if you're going
to try to be the unifier, right?
I mean, that's part of the promise of PipeWire,
is all of this stuff happening in one go, your Pulse
and your Jack, and you're also all happy together.
And in particular, one thing you get out of this now
if you're using Jack is way better and easier access
to Bluetooth devices, thanks to PipeWire.
Yeah, and really just, I think, an easier time
kind of getting up and going and configuring
Jack applications.
It sort of solves some of the fundamental plumbing
that you used to have to worry about
and makes it just all of a sudden,
like these applications that have been around for a while,
even easier to use in some respects.
It is neat as a moment right now of PipeWire happening.
I think we all had a lot of confidence in the project just
because of the folks developing it and their history and skill
and just sort of the previews we'd seen along the way.
And we've certainly covered it a lot on this show.
But the fact that it is not used for audio yet,
but deployed in 2104 and now shipping
with audio in Fedora 34, I don't know.
If this goes well, it seems like PipeWire
is here to stay after this.
I think this is the part of the technology stack of this release
that you and I are the most excited about.
And we don't know what the line is.
Should we talk about it a lot?
Or is it like inside baseball podcaster stuff
and so we just cover the high details and move on?
So let us know.
That's another area we'd like feedback.
But something that's a bit of peace of mind for me
in this release is that this version of Fedora
ships with ExWayland standalone.
This is nice because you've probably
heard that Xorg releases are a bit unmaintained.
The current upstream release has stuck to the 120 branch
for years with no real foreseeable major update,
at least.
But what they've done with this standalone ExWayland session
is they've built it from the Git snapshots of current code
upstream rather than the stable branch,
so where the fixes have kind of landed.
And they've broken it off out from Wayland itself.
It's nice to see that.
And it could probably even, I mean,
not only could it result in better performance,
but maybe even in some use cases better battery life
if you're not running any X applications now,
this won't be running at all.
Yeah, definitely.
And it just sort of wasn't accessible.
There were fixes going in, and that
was the main part of the sort of X repo
actually seeing any development.
But when they weren't being shipped,
no one had access to them.
You don't want to just pull from that without having tested it.
So it's nice to see that there was enough developer
effort to sort of bootstrap this, keep it alive,
and functioning nicely.
Yeah, I bet you'll see other distributions
follow this particular suit.
Another nicety, and for several reasons,
is that Wayland is now the default for the plasma spin.
So you know, Plasma's Wayland support
has been getting pretty good and pretty much daily
drivable in 5.20, and even better in 5.21,
which is what's shipping with Fedora 34.
And so it's a great kind of milestone that was set.
Because when the Fedora project said,
we're switching to Wayland by default for our plasma spin,
the Plasma project saw that and realized,
we've got to double down on this code.
We've got to get this shippable and working.
And not in a bad way, like in a very kind of cooperative,
well, this project set a goal, and we're
going to work hard to help them succeed at that goal,
and it's going to be good for our project, too.
And it was a good example of how Fedora 34
played a role in a wider ecosystem improvement
for Wayland support.
Yeah, you can really see that even just in the change here
and on their post about it on the Fedora Wiki,
where they write, Fedora has long
been a leader in advancing the adoption of the Wayland
protocol.
Much of the quality of Wayland for GNOME
can be attributed to the work done by the Fedora Workstation
working group.
It's now the KDE special interest group's turn
to do the same for the KDE platform.
So I think there really is this sort of shared responsibility
and help and goal to sort of push things over the hill
and get it nicely working now that we've
got stuff like NVIDIA proprietary support working,
screencasting, middle click paste,
all the sort of 90% little paper cut
stuff that needed to be in there before you
could really ship it.
Yeah, there's still edge cases.
The other day I had this problem where for whatever reason
until I rebooted, my Wayland applications could not
copy and paste to my ex-Wayland applications.
It's a problem that's been solved,
but it just started hitting me the other day.
And so it's not all there.
But I am such a performance nut that I
will live with those paper cuts to get
the smoothness of Wayland.
On my X1 Carbon with the full Fedora stack,
it's so damn good that I think you could hold that up
as an example of a premier Linux experience.
And it makes me really excited for this technology
to land in other distributions as well.
I also decided to give it a spin on something a little different,
Wes.
I tried out the ARM64 image on my Raspberry Pi 400.
Oh, yeah, right.
There's a new ARM64 KDE Plasma desktop image
available this time around.
Yep.
What did you think?
You know, it's not super fast, Wes.
It's a little bit faster, I felt like, than the GNOME Shell
images, which is probably not too surprising.
But not fast enough for daily use.
Not fast enough at all.
The command line interface, perfectly fine.
If you wanted to use this thing to host some file services
for yourself or make it a LAN server, fine, great.
It'd be good.
But as a desktop environment, Wes, it's just not quite there.
We're not there yet, huh?
Or maybe you needed something more lightweight, I guess.
And I was running it from a SSD over USB 3, not from an SD card.
So I was kind of giving it a performance advantage.
You were trying, yeah.
And the Pi 400 is slightly faster than the Raspberry Pi
4 vanilla.
Someday, those things will be a regular desktop.
What I really want, actually, my goal,
and I think they're going to get there eventually,
my goal is to have a Pi device of some kind that is on 24-7
that's logged into all my stuff.
So if my desktop ever breaks, or an update goes haywire,
or I want to reload for a day for some crazy thing
we're doing on the show, I want to have an appliance that
has my chat apps, my email, and my web browser ready to go
for me all the time, just like a mission-critical console that's
in my office that takes up very little space.
And the great thing about the Pi 400 for this job
is that it's the keyboard and the computer in one.
And as silly as that sounds, it means
it takes up a lot less space, because I just
have an HDMI cable, and a USB-C cable, and a mouse.
It's simple.
It's great.
I actually do ethernet too, but it's really nice.
So I'm hoping, and I honestly just,
I think maybe Manjaro has invested more in this area.
They've spent more time here.
But the Manjaro versions on the Pi 400
are significantly better, like absolutely I
can do that job with Manjaro or Ubuntu 20.04.
OK, so maybe there just needs to be a little more tuning.
That's hopeful.
Could be, could be.
I learned a valuable lesson, though,
thanks to Neil, who responded to a quick question I
had during the week.
To make it work, you need to really, for the best time,
I mean, there's probably 1,000 ways to do it,
but you really should use the Fedora media
writer to make the whole thing actually bootable.
And there's some cool options it gives you, some nice-to-haves,
like turn off the boot splash so you can see all of the output,
or turn on SSH, or some options you
might use if you didn't have a monitor hooked up.
So it's a really nice tool.
Also nice to see that you can use it from the Mac and Windows
too, if you need.
Oh, really?
They have, oh, well, OK, I did not know that.
So they have Mac and Windows versions
of the Fedora media writer?
That's great.
Good for them.
All right, well, moving down the stack a little bit,
another kind of headline feature here
is ButterFS transparent compression.
And if you're like me, and you are around
during the drive-doubler days of the DOS era,
this is a totally different beast,
and it could be particularly great for SSD users.
So where do you want to start, Wes?
Well, maybe we should start and say,
this isn't a new feature for ButterFS,
but what's new here is Fedora adding it on by default.
You could add it if you'd like, but I don't even
think it's a default. Just when you make a ButterFS file
system, you have to manually go in there and add the mount
flags to say, hey, do compression.
So like with a lot of things in Fedora,
this is some trust in saying, this makes sense.
It works in enough use cases that we think all of our users
should have it, at least if they're using ButterFS.
I'm going to use this.
Totally think this is a great feature.
But it did cross my mind, like, what if something goes wrong?
Am I risking my data here?
Sounds like they checked that out as part of this change.
And as far as we know, known compression-related
bugs are just kind of cosmetic, nothing that is data loss.
And this has been in the file system for a while.
Seems like it just works.
OK.
Yeah, I know it's been in ButterFS for a while.
The change here is they're turning it on.
And I say good on them.
I say, too, if you're in CFS, you
should consider doing the same.
And they went with this compression algorithm
because I assume they must have looked at the impact on the CPU
and disk straight off and decided, OK,
this is the right one to use.
Yeah, they're using the Z standard.
Then they picked a specific default compression level
because it's tunable here, and you
can kind of choose different parameters, you know,
speed and how well does it compress and kind of pick
the one that made the most sense in terms of CPU usage
and memory and disk space savings.
What do you actually get out of it?
It's just so neat that because of the way our architectures
are and how fast CPUs are and how slow it can be sometimes
to talk to the disk, even a fast disk just
makes sense to compress things first.
And you don't ever have to worry about it.
Right, just get it to the CPU.
Just get that data to the CPU, then let it do its thing.
And this is probably available on the disk
you're using now.
You could make a partition and use compression today,
and you probably should consider it.
There's just one thing to remember.
It's kind of tricky when you're checking your free disk
space going forward due to the nature
of transparent compression.
It's transparent.
So utilities like DU are only going
to report the exact uncompressed file space
usage, which is not the actual space that they take up
on the disk.
So it gets a little tricky.
I assume there must be tools, Wes.
Yeah, the Fedora magazine had a good write-up about this feature,
and they recommend that they comp size utility.
If you're curious, of course, that'll be in the show notes.
And they've also got a good tip if you
want to go back and retroactively compress
older files if you've just added this mount option now,
because it only applies to future files.
Now a little bit further up in the stacks,
on the systemd layer, I thought we talked about this feature
in episode 351, but we're getting
systemd out of memory daemon now, which I guess
is different than the early OOM we've talked about before.
Yeah, it turns out there's a lot of options here.
Yeah, so last year at this time, I guess Fedora 32,
it would have been early OOM shipped in Fedora.
And that was a big change, and we talked about it.
Of course, there's also Facebook has some work,
which we talked about in this space.
They were interested and also helped
get new statistics like memory pressure, PSI metrics
into the kernel.
So they've got a tool that uses that,
also kind of enabled cgroups, and now systemd is in play.
Because if you have a daemon, it's
doing something on your Linux system,
you better just do it in systemd.
It's going to work out better.
Managing processes does make sense, right?
It does.
It does make sense to have that in systemd.
Yeah, and it's nice and smart and integrated.
It can do stuff per cgroup, lots of cleverness
with fancy new kernel features to try to get this right,
and do a better job of not killing stuff that
doesn't need to be killed, but also trying
to kill things early enough that it actually
helps save your system.
And I actually, I have not looked at this myself,
but I have been led to believe this
is simpler than, at least from a configuration standpoint,
than the previous stuff made by Facebook.
Yeah, sounds like it.
And it's neat that it's using that memory pressure indicator.
And so what it does, audience, I don't
think we've clearly explained this,
is it's monitoring applications and processes and whatever,
and it's checking for memory pressure and availability.
And if it has to, before your system gets really
crappy in a low memory situation, which
Linux is famous for, this thing will
kick in and essentially kill it to save the overall system.
Yeah, this systemd OOMD, I guess,
can also monitor similar stuff for swap
and act there to try to free up swap.
And according to Neil in the IRC room just now,
I guess early OOM was really just something of a stop gap
to try to get this feature out there while systemd OOMD was
in the works.
OK, and then there's one last thing
that I was waiting for you to kind of explain to me.
And that is, I think I must be mistaken,
but I guess it looks like they've
removed support for disabling the SELinux runtime.
What is this outrageous thing, Wes?
Oh, yeah, so people might be kind of confused by this.
So we should probably note upfront that by disabling SELinux,
what they mean is that the kernel doesn't call
into the SELinux subsystem at all.
Switching SELinux between permissive and enforcing,
using set enforce, that's not affected.
That's fully functional.
You can still set it to permissive mode.
What's changing here is kind of subtle.
You may never have used it.
Right now, SELinux can be disabled
by passing SELinux equals 0 on the command line
as you're booting, or in user space by a config file
in etsy SELinux slash config.
And then there's a library in user space lib SELinux
that reads that file.
And during boot, if you've told it to disable SELinux,
then that user space library actually
writes into the kernel unmount slash sys slash fs
slash SELinux and sort of disables it.
But doing it that way, while very flexible
and sort of helped out distros that had a harder time
or environments systems that had a harder time changing
or adding on to kernel parameters,
it did make some security trade-offs
when you're trying to use Linux security modules
like SELinux.
So now that's getting ripped out.
The only way to do it,
you can't use that config file anymore.
You have to pass SELinux equals 0 on the command line.
Ah, man, I polished this pitchfork and everything.
It was really shiny.
That sounds perfectly reasonable.
Yeah, it sure is.
You'll have to look elsewhere for drama today.
I'm also really, really liking what I see
for the future of grub configuration.
It looks like it could be a lot simpler
regardless of what platform you're on.
Fedora 34 uses unified grub config.
So the grub configuration file layouts
depend on the platform you're using.
So if you've got an old bio system or an open firmware
or an EFI system, it's gonna be different.
And that's confusing for your old podcast host here.
So the proposal,
and I don't know if it's actually shipping yet,
is to always store the grub config
and grub environment files in the same place,
slash boot, slash grub2 directory,
that place right there.
And then making small tweaks in another directory
and it always being consistent across all platforms.
Seems like it has some obvious benefits.
Yeah, it's just kind of more of what you'd expect.
And I don't know about you,
maybe there's a lot of users
who hopefully don't ever have to mess around with grub
or what goes on in slash boot.
But for whatever reason,
I'm fascinated by booting the kernel.
So I'm always mucking around in there,
even when I don't need to or just checking things out.
And on EFI systems in particular,
there's been a lot of variants around
how does the EFI partition get managed?
How does it get mounted and where?
And then what things go in there
versus go on like a slash boot partition
that's not the fat one, but like an ext4 version.
So now that's being simplified.
Everything's gonna be consistent
no matter where you're running Fedora.
And it's gonna be under slash boot slash grub
slash grub.cfg, like you'd expect.
And Neil says it has shipped.
That is so brilliant.
You know, and it's kind of thankless work.
Sure, it's like it doesn't really change anything.
It's not a new feature or anything.
I mean, there are benefits,
but it's just that kind of nice cleanup and maintenance
that is really nice to see.
Oh, 34 is such a solid release.
There's so much we could dig into.
If you have any specific questions or area of interest
that you found that you think maybe Wes
and I could geek out on,
let us know at linuxunplug.com slash contact
and congratulations to the entire team.
It is yet another fantastic release.
And it's, I think maybe an extra special one
with GNOME 40 and plasma switching to Wayland
and pipe wire landing and this unified grub stuff.
Wow, just really just very impressed.
Good work everybody.
Now, before we wrap up today,
we do just have a spot of housekeeping around here
because Minimac has a special Luplug announcement.
Yeah, thank you, Chris.
You know, Chris, I had a dream.
I always wanted to do a talk
about the MyCraft voice assistant project
and guess what, my dream will come true.
I'm in contact with Chris Gessling,
the community manager of the MyCraft project.
And we both hope to be able
to put together a cool talk for you.
The talk will be scheduled the 9th of May,
but we'll be already be playing around
with MyCraft next Sunday during Luplug.
So in case you want to give MyCraft a try,
we will give you a hand next Sunday.
Chris himself, so Chris Gessling himself
might not be available for the talk
because he is living in Down Under.
So I mean, for him,
the talk will be in the midst of the night.
So this is a call for participation
for our MyCraft talk of the 9th of May
and even for next Sunday.
Of course, we will also invite
the MyCraft community for that talk.
I don't understand, but I'm learning new things every day.
And now I was interrupted by MyCraft.
That will be our special guest.
Hey, MyCraft.
Sing a song for us.
I would be happy to sing for you.
She packed my bags last night, pre-flight.
Hey, MyCraft.
Stop.
So Chris, I'm sure we will have a lot of fun
and that's all from me.
Thank you.
Thank you, Mini Mac.
Check out the Luplug every Sunday.
It's noon Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern,
or get it in your time zone
at jupiterbroadcasting.com slash calendar.
That sounds like that's going to be a really great one.
And it's always fun to hang out in the lounge
in our Mumble server and just chat with people
that think like you do.
Information for the Mumble server is at linuxunplugged.com.
And thank you to our Unplugged Core contributors
at unpluggedcore.com.
I have a special note for you.
So check your feeds.
It's also in the member download area
for a very special exclusive deal to get 15%
off an item I have created for our members
in the Jupiter Garage at jupitergarage.com.
So go check your feed or the download area.
You'll see it there.
And then you can take 15% off for something,
which is the reason why it's 15% off
is really because that's the cost.
That's our, so you just get it at cost.
And it's a very limited item.
But our members make this show really possible
at the end of the day.
So we thank them at unpluggedcore.com
and a discount on something like that
is just one of the ways we can thank them.
But I also get two feed options,
a limited ad version of the show, same full production,
all the Joe Lovin, just less ads,
or the full live stream, which is like
another 1.5 shows really.
All our screw ups, which is a lot this week.
I had a liquid lunch.
On my way into the studio,
I grabbed me a See Ya Next Tuesday
because I just missed lunch.
So I grabbed a See Ya Next Tuesday
on the way into the studio and popped it open
and chugged it before I started the stream.
And I'm paying the price.
But you know what?
Joe cleans it all up.
If you'd like to see all of the hard work he does,
you can get the full live stream version
where you hear all of it
and you get all the extra content as well.
So thanks to our members at unpluggedcore.com
and make sure you go look for that special message.
It's like a phone call between me and you
and it's a discount and more information
on what I'm hinting at right now.
So thank you everybody.
We do appreciate you.
Couple of quick bits of feedback.
Jim wrote in after hosting email for six plus years.
You wanna take this one, Mr. Payne?
Jim wrote, I've hosted my own email server
for six plus years with almost all that time
performing minimal maintenance.
There's hope for us yet, Chris.
Servers pretty much remain the same
except for maybe compiling Dovecot a couple of times
to get new versions.
Originally, I'd followed a guide
and installed the email server on dedicated hardware.
But as I evolved in my Linux experience,
I actually implemented Proxmox
and was able to move that dedicated install
into a container without reinstalling.
Nice.
Interesting.
Here's another part that I had missed out on.
I guess two years ago,
Jim implemented Proxmox mail gateway container
which sets up a backend post effect server
while still using the web UI
of this Proxmox mail gateway to access it.
So you can still keep this existing setup
but just get a nice web GUI for free.
Awesome.
That is nice.
You know what?
That's the second mention I've heard
of this Proxmox mail gateway.
So that seems pretty, pretty good.
He said he has had some blacklist issues
but he just tries to ignore those ones.
He's lucky because I've had a lot worse.
But we also got a neat trick
for another self-hosted mail solution.
One that may be a solid replacement for mail in the box
if that doesn't work for you.
It's from Sir Lurksalot.
He says, apparently having been dropped
on my head at some point,
I also run my own mail server.
And I thought I would mention a neat feature of doing so
that I take advantage of.
So here's a reason why you might wanna
host your own mail server.
We also heard, by the way,
side note, Wes, we also heard
from a lot of people out there.
They're just like, hell yeah,
I'm still running my own mail server.
Good on you guys.
Go for it.
That's awesome.
Which I appreciate.
Yeah.
But he says that he uses this wildcard feature
which are aliases that any non-existing email address
that gets sent, like somebody emails something
at Bob at his server that doesn't exist,
it'll just forward to his main email account.
The reason why that's nice is he can easily make up
an email box name on the spot
when registering for an online service,
like make something specific for them.
And then never really have to worry about it
because it'll just show up in his mailbox.
And then if he ever wants to reply to it,
he just goes and creates a quick alias first
and then sends it off.
But he also wanted to recommend this tool
that's called Modoba.
Modoba.
M-O-D-O-B-O-A.org.
And it is an easy way to get up and running with mail,
perhaps a mail-in-a-box replacement.
It gives you Python and Django-based front-end interface
to manage Postfix, Dovecot,
and all of the related components.
We'll put a link to that in the show notes.
Wow, yeah, it looks like it's got web mail,
calendars, address book, filtering rules, auto response.
Fancy.
And you know, I love that first tip there
because it's kind of like what you can do
with Pluses and Gmail or Outlook,
but way more flexible,
especially for those picky websites that won't take a Plus.
["Pomp and Circumstance"]
And we have a Rust pick, not just any pick,
a Rust pick, and this one's a workspace
that's aimed at developers.
I think they call it like a terminal
with all batteries included.
Tell us about this little discovery, Wes.
Yeah, it's called Zelj, Zelj, I don't know.
Z-E-L-L-I-J, and of course, yes, it's written in Rust.
And while that part is exciting,
I think what's most exciting to me
is just sort of this new approach
at a terminal multiplexer.
And that's what it is at its core,
but that's just the infrastructure layer
because it also includes a layout system
and a plugin system allowing you to create plugins
in any language that compiles to WebAssembly.
Yeah, Rust and WebAssembly,
that's double hype for this project.
That's right, that is pretty great, and it looks good too.
And of course, because it's Rust,
there's a sketchy, just pre-compiled,
Musal-linked binary you can go download
to give it a try with minimal friction.
What could go wrong?
I would run it with pseudo privileges.
I would just do pseudo,
and then I'd run the binary directly.
It looks nice, though, I will say.
Like, I've got it up, and it's got fancy fonts
and a really nice banner at the bottom by default.
It might stick around.
Yeah, no, I tease.
It does look really great.
And don't run random binaries from the internet as pseudo.
Do I even have to disclaim that?
Should be obvious, I'm kidding.
Jeez, jeez.
Anyways, that looks really good.
It's Z-E-L-L-I-J?
Link in the show notes at linuxunplugged.com slash 403.
You can find a lot there.
Also, you can find our sponsor, Cloud Guru, on social media.
They're just slash a Cloud Guru just about everywhere.
That's a social media website.
It's really easy.
Slash a Cloud Guru about everywhere.
The Jupiter Garage is rocking.
We have a little more Linux action show retro merch
in there, including the beloved zip-up hoodie.
One left is in there,
as well as a couple of brand new low-code items,
all in the garage sale at jupitergarage.com.
Wes, I know you already know this,
but I'm very proud.
We have shipped damn near 300 items from the garage sale.
Two NASs in the last week.
That really is something.
And it shows, just if you take a look at the studio,
which is now definitely more of a packing and shipping place
than it is an audio recording studio.
We have got, I'm very proud of it, actually.
Took those lessons from that robe,
and we have really gotten our game together.
And we had so much old merch that I was hanging onto
because of these emotional attachments
that I realized we could be sharing with our audience.
And it's going, it's going out the door.
And we still have more gear and more stuff,
so check out jupitergarage.com for all of that.
If you do the Twitter thing,
you can follow this show at Linux Unplugged.
The network is at Jupiter Signal.
And we have a whole network of shows, fantastic shows,
over at jupiterbroadcasting.com.
Lots of great shows.
Go check those out, including Linux Action News,
where we break down lots of stories in the Linux world
that you need to know about every single week.
See you next week.
Same bad time, same bad station.
Keep the Linux rolling, and make it a Linux Tuesday,
and join us live, 12 p.m. Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern,
at jblive.tv.
Links to everything we talked about today,
how to contact us, the Mumble Room, Matrix Info,
probably even the garage sale.
We link it up at linuxunplugged.com.
Isn't that a great idea?
It's like one website.
You just go to that one website
for all the crap we talk about.
How easy is that?
We do that because we love you, linuxunplugged.com.
Thanks so much for joining us
on this week's episode of the Unplugged program.
And we will see you right back here, next Tuesday.
Tuesday!
How to Get Rid of the Linux
All right, JBtitles.com. Let's title this here show. It's a long one, and we cover it
a lot. I mean, obviously, mostly the focus is Fedora 34, but there's a lot of ground.
There's a lot of ground to cover.
No kidding.
Uh, Fedora 34, the worst release ever. Oh, that would be a good idea. Yeah, get him clicking
with that one.
Oh, jeez.
Clicks!