Wes can I interest you in snakeware? It's a free Linux distribution with a full Python user space
Inspired by the Commodore 64. Oh boy, you had me at Python and well the creepy name snakeware
This looks pretty cool though. You're booted directly into a Python interpreter and you can do whatever you want
Now you should also note that snakeware. Yeah, it doesn't use x11. Definitely not Wayland. It just writes directly to the frame buffer
Hello friends and welcome into 356 of your weekly Linux talk show. My name is Chris. My name is Wes
Hello, Wes. I've been looking forward to hearing your take on the XPS 13 for a couple of weeks now and in my hot little hands
I have the Pinebook Pro. We'll tell you more about our hardware extravaganza
But of course, we have some community news in 356
I got a little clarification on what's going down with the GNOME patent suit as
Well as some great features landing in the latest Linux kernel. We have some feedback
We may even have some pics who knows but before I can get to any of that
I got to say hi to the guys over there in the red chairs. Hello cheese Andrew. Hello
Hello, thanks for bringing your own chairs guys. Mm-hmm. Yeah, of course. Yeah, I mean after what happened last week
I don't blame you, right? Right
What was so sticky there? I never figured that out. It's the honey Wes
I told you we shouldn't use the honey and also of course our virtual lug is here time appropriate. Greetings mumble room. Stay a while
Hello mumble room good to have you along had a fun virtual lug over the weekend
We'll tell you more about that and a little bit but let's start with GNOME getting a big open source
patent win now you might remember back in 2019 the dome foundation was sued by Rothschild patent imaging for violating its wireless image distribution system and
method patent, of course
Rothschild a non-practicing entity, which is
business speak for a patent troll has filed
714 lawsuits over the past six years
But now in a surprising move GNOME has won not only a release and covenant not to be sued for any Rothschild
Specific patent but a release and covenant to any software that is released under an existing open source initiative
Approved license, right? So they're essentially not going after anyone who is covered by an OSI approved license
So it's not completely a green light
But it's a green light for tons and tons of projects dozens many projects the Shotwell open source image organizer
infringed on a 2008 patent because it used an image capturing device to import and
Filter photographic images from cameras and then it would allow users to organize those photos and share them on social media
Yeah, nothing does that right right that patent would apply to just about every kind of software
Fortunately for no they had friends including the open invention network
Which we've mentioned before and is a pro Linux patent non-aggression consortium
Faced with opposition like that and the possibility of losing their patents in the lawsuit. Well Rothschild backed off
Making the best of it. Well, I Rothschild managing member of Rothschild Trust Holdings said
I'm pleased that we've managed to settle this issue
Amicably, I've always supported the innovation of open source software maintenance developers and encourage its innovation and adoption
Yeah, uh-huh. It sounds genuine. So Wes I had a bunch of questions about this because
We talked about this aspect on the show the genome
Foundation took some funding to fight this but then at the end of it
It looked like they didn't have any settlement to pay out
They didn't have any legal fees to necessarily pay seemed because some of that was also going to be covered
So I wasn't really clear on where the money it went
So I emailed Neil McGovern the executive director of the Gnome Foundation and I asked him, you know
What's happening with the money what happened with the money that was contributed and as you would expect he writes as with any court case
Things get expensive really fast. Although our lawyers were working on pro bono
There's a large number of other expenses
We have from court filing fees and prior art searches to even flights and hotels
Which I think is the aspect of these court cases
We don't talk a lot about and it was pretty awesome that they had lawyers working pro bono for them. I mean, that's incredible
No kidding. It really doesn't it show you unity there? Yeah, definitely right that you've got this, you know
You're all you're all working together and that we can defend the cause of open source software
The important thing he says he continues is I want people to know that we didn't pay RPI
That's the Rothschild patent imaging folks for the settlement agreement
They didn't receive any money from us
Now there is more to this settlement that wasn't
publicly available and Neil kind of hinted to that that there was more details and if you had a project that is
Covered by an OSI compliant license you can email him to get these details
But they're not otherwise publicly available. So I said, what can you tell me? What what about these things?
Can you share with me and he writes? I'm a little restrained here. Usually a settlement agreement is confidential in this particular case
I wanted to ensure that those affected by the Covenant not to sue was able to inspect the protections we had gained for them
Also, it shows that we didn't pay them any money
He goes on to say this means that I can pass on the full and unedited agreement to those who are arguably covered by the CNS
This means that anyone who has authored a non-trivial bit of free software can request a copy
But I can't just put it on a website
However, if you have any extra particular questions about the agreement, I can probably answer those Neil isn't that great?
So they didn't pay any money to RPI
They had the lawyers that were there pro bono and the community funding covered all of those extras like prior art searches flights
hotels all of the admin stuff for this case and the walkaway win here is an
Agreement that if you have an OSI compliant license, which is a lot of them
You're not gonna get sued by this patent troll. It didn't invalidate the patent which would have been the ultimate win
But it's pretty darn close West. Yeah, it is now the weird amount of secrecy
All the lawyer lawyer Lee goings on still a little disappointing and I'm not quite clear
What non-trivial piece of free software really means but it's definitely a win. Yeah, and
It's nice to see this happen for Shotwell who I I'm not positive
But I don't even believe Shotwell is part of like the default gnome core. I
Mean, I don't know if it necessarily was the gnome foundations obligation here to help, but I think they did anyway
I I'm not positive on that. I say this to the patent trolls
Leave our free software alone. Yeah, I'm flushing them down the studio toilet
That's where a lot of things go around here. So thank you Neal for answering those questions because you know
I asked him was like so what did the money go for where did the money go Neal and I gave me a very straight
Answer and I really appreciate that. Maybe let us know if you've got further questions and you know, we can drill down a little bit deeper
Yeah, absolutely. He left that line of communication open so I'd be willing to do that
but I'm very pleased to see it and
This is a way that larger software projects and foundations can contribute beyond
organizational and financial stability and it's great to see it a new kernel landed West
version five dot seven since we all gathered together and
There's many many many things in this kernel release including the new official
ExFAT file system driver that is the code from Samsung the good one a good one
Yes, but I wanted to talk about
The thermal pressure in the task scheduler support now because this opened my eye to a problem that I didn't fully appreciate on Linux
That kind of seems obvious on its face
When a CPU is overheating probably a common scenario for my Raspberry Pi's or for your laptop the thermal governor
Will usually cap the maximum CPU frequency. We're all familiar with that
however
This decreases the maximum available compute capacity of the CPU
Obviously, if a task scheduler is not immediately aware of those frequency changes
IE Linux is task scheduler
It will take the wrong scheduling decisions assuming that the CPU has greater computing capacity
Than it actually has
Never really thought about this, but the scheduler is looking at it going. This is a CPU at this speed
It's not aware that the governor's kicker is at this speed
A CPU at this speed it's not aware that the governor's kicked in and it keeps scheduling stuff as if that
CPU is at full capacity
So this release in 5.7 introduces the notion of thermal pressure
Which makes the task scheduler more aware of frequency capping and leads to better task placement among available CPUs in the event of overheating
Which then in turn leads to better CPU performance numbers. This is just so cool
I mean, we've already worked some on memory pressure getting added to the kernel
You know just to better understand what that's like and now that we have thermal pressure added
I think this is gonna be huge when at least eventually
I mean, you know, no one's running 5.7 at least not very many just yet
But once it makes its way to the distros, this is gotta be good for laptop users
Yeah, I think so
I think although it could be wrong because I'm not super familiar with the bowels of Mac OS
But I think this is similar to how the kernel task scheduler process works in Mac OS
Where it is monitoring the temperature sensors even including the ports where you plug in your power adapters
They have temperature sensors there and it's monitoring the overall chassis temperature of your laptops
And then this kernel task process
Will start eating more CPU to make the CPU is look busier to the scheduler
But doesn't actually reduce the frequency and keeps the thermal load lower
They don't expose the thermal pressure information though
Like this Linux API will like this is going to be a kernel level thing that also exposes that metric as information
So you can monitor that thermal pressure and that is an example of where Linux once once it gets a feature like this
It's always so much cooler. Yeah, you know, there is definitely a little bit of a barrier to get things into the kernel
But once they're there you've got this amazing community of folks who can all work to make it better
Right before we move on from new kernel features. There's a patch that is being discussed right now
So that's the phase this one's in just in the discussion phase
That is necessary to land in the Linux kernel
for newer
Windows games on wine to work properly. Wait, this is kernel stuff about Windows games
Yes for wine stuff, which you can maybe get a feel for why the conversations a bit awkward
But newer Windows games and even applications are making use of system call instructions from the application code without
resorting to the win API
Which is wines mega tricks and it's breaking that wine emulation support
Which is not an emulator a Linux kernel patch that it's being worked on would address this issue in the form of a system call
isolation
based on memory areas while having a smaller performance hit than say some alternatives where you do it all in user space and
That's pretty important when you're talking about games
So with newer Windows software, they're basically just executing system call instructions directly without going through the Windows API
So that means wine isn't able to intercept those with their implementation of the Windows API and then emulate those system calls
And that means those games just don't work under wine
Wine can't really rework its handling of every single system call. That was just trash performance
So that's why you basically need a Linux kernel based solution for this
Gabrielle Chrisman Burtazi of
Collabora the consulting firm that has helped valve in all kinds of these, you know
Linux gaming efforts posted an initial patch to the kernels sec comp mailing list implementing a system call isolation mechanism
based on memory areas
Sec comp which is short for a secure computing is traditionally used for Linux security matters
And this really isn't for security in this implementation
But sec comp already has all these mechanisms in the kernel for filtering system calls
So basically with this patch
Set comp gains an ability to sort of filter things in this new virtual memory attribute
That's used for tracking where in memory these calls are coming from
So since wine can set this up and basically say like yes, I know that I've set the program up with this virtual memory area
It can then use if accepted this patch and sec comp to filter all those calls and then do the patching
Filtering and adjustments that wine needs to do to make sure that those system calls get translated correctly
Wow, now they did look into using the existing sec comp filtering
But that's like a 10% performance penalty and if you just do it with isolation based on memory areas like their proposed plan
That's 1.5 percent and that's a lot better. Isn't it interesting to see
Windows and Linux making changes to bring each other slightly closer together in some ways and that is fascinating
I mean, it's no longer a you know
Not quite the Cold War of old anymore and you know
So many people especially with proton are using wine for playing games on Linux. So hopefully that you know with that sort of momentum
The kernel developers won't object too much. I guess we'll see but you know, this change is under a hundred lines of code
So it's not like it's muddy enough the kernel too much. Yeah, we're not talking like a huge change to Linux kernel here
I like to think about this from like 2002 Chris where I was really in the prime of my everything must be Linux
This would be heresy to even suggest such a thing
But if you look at this, it's it's not a major change
It opens the door to bringing even more application could bit of compatibility to Linux. It's not something we'll see immediately
It's not gonna land in 5-8. That's kind of too late
It may may end up in 5-9 if they go ahead with it later this year, but we'll see only a time
We'll tell but yeah, you're right at some point things just get tricky, especially when you're emulating
I mean not really emulating but you know, you're trying to pretend that you're a Windows system
And there's just so much going on there. And of course, that's a target that doesn't stand still
Wes I am excited to say that I have received my Pinebook Pro. Oh, no way awesome
Yep, it's a nice nice rig. I
Love it already. I open it up. I took it out of the box
I didn't have a strong immediate reaction to it because it's it just looks nice
It's not striking any particular way, but it's also not like ugly in any particular way. So I took out. Okay, that's great
Take it out of the box
Booted it up as I started to use it over the next few minutes. I started to realize
Oh, this is gonna be one of those devices one of those that's in my bag all the time that I carry with me
I was hoping in the back of my mind
That this would be a solid alternative something like an iPad Pro with a keyboard. That's a big ask right there
Well, if you look at what I use an iPad for not really because I use it for a web browser
I use it for a terminal a lot and
Telegram and chat apps. I haven't tried all the different chat apps yet, but
Man, is it really great? It's light
The keyboard is solid. It has way more travel to the keys than I expected for a keyboard in 2020. It's
so far
Performing very well battery wise. It's probably been off battery for
Um, uh, does it tell me no it doesn't tell me but it tells me I have eight hours of runtime left
So that's pretty good night. I would guesstimate that it's been off for about an hour
Maybe even slightly more than that. Maybe an hour and a half boy. Am I impressed now?
I know cheese you traveled with yours to system 76. So this is sort of a unit that you have
Extended hands-on with at this point. Are you still using it on a semi daily basis? Yeah
I mean I use it mainly for all of my 3d printing needs so slicing and you know checking out models
adjusting models and stuff like that and then of course, you know telegram and
Browsing and just general kind of couchsurfing
Computing, you know, so that's it seems to fit that and that niche really well
And yeah, you know whenever I ran it at the system 76 event for a week
Yeah, I was using it primarily as as a device just for that writing up some reviews
And you should have held it up and said guys you could just build one of these you could just well
You know, I did put it in Carl's hands
Good. I've showed him, you know the machine and he was actually really really surprised by the machine and
You know big up to Dan and and all the guys over at Manjaro that have put a bunch of work into this machine as well
Yeah, Manjaro really really sings on this thing and it makes it feel like a powerful workstation
It doesn't just seem like a toy. I think it seems like I've got
Nearly the entire Linux universe of software available to me
Dan is joining us today Dan. Welcome to the unplug program
Thank you, and then explain your role with the project before we go too far because sometimes I'm horrible at that
Well, I'm the you can call it lead developer of the Manjaro arm branch
So you are the perfect gentleman to have on the show as we are talking about this
I'd love to know a little bit of the background of the work
It went into if you anything you do know about the work
It went into getting this thing singing like it does on the Pine Book Pro
The main thing is probably the main line of the kernel
Oh, I bet that went into five dot seven now, but we've been running our own
Kernel repo branch for a while since five dot four five dot five on the Pine Book Pro
And so what aspects of Pine Book Pro hardware have been mainlined almost everything?
except the battery that's going into five dot eight and the
Display port alternate mode. It's also missing and suspend is missing. This is why I think
Manjaro is such a great candidate for these ARM platform devices because it's not all there yet
And you need something that's going to be really fresh because the stuff is inbound right now
We are living in the era where these fixes and the support is landing
But if you use a distribution that doesn't update very often its hardware support
You basically end up with a machine that isn't fully functional. Yeah. Well the previous OS was Debian and that was using a
Very specific kernel built on 4.4, which was specific for the Pine Book Pro
So that had most of the things working. So do you have a bunch of ARM?
SBCs around your place to I do I have a lot
How many do you roughly would you guesstimate I guess about 15 Wow, oh
Okay, are they mostly all one type or all different kinds?
Like I'm curious what you're finding to be your favorite all that like for me mine are obviously
I love the pi 4 and I love the rock pro 64. Yeah, those are my favorites as well
I have a lot of the
Love the pies. I have all the way back to the Raspberry Pi 2 and 3 then 4 and
I have lots of the pine 64 devices because of our partnership. They shipped them out to me, which is nice. Yeah, no kidding
I see you invited Dan on just to normalize your Raspberry Pi collection Chris, right?
Absolutely. I just got to clip this out and send it to Alex now because he's giving me a hard time
Yeah, the rock pro 64 for me was sort of a the next level of these SBCs because of that PCI Express slot and then I
When I threw the MV me drive in there and I'm sitting there getting performance that seems
Well, it seems absolutely comparable to an x86 system
Yeah, it's really great device and the Pine Book Pro is really close if I understand to the rock pro 64
Is there any any major deviations that you're aware of other than different ports the different ports?
And of course the displays and stuff, but otherwise, it's basically the same
Stock and board that's in it. So it also has the PCI
slot inside it kind of feels like the plasma desktop is
Sort of at the edge of what the device is comfortable performing it works for sure
But like I get the I get the I get kind of the chunkiness when I'm resizing windows
So why plasma as the version to ship? I love it. I'm gonna keep it, but I'm just curious what the what the thinking was
well, I'm a plasma guy myself, so I I was pretty hooked on getting that to work pretty good and the
GPU drivers also pretty far ahead now so they can actually run plasma. So the plasma you're running on the device
It's actually hardware accelerated
it's awesome and the login screen and lock screen looks super sharp and clean and
The when I'm logging into the desktop the progress bar. It sort of fades up from the bottom very nice and smooth
It's it's a pretty tight experience and I wouldn't have thought it'd be possible a couple of years ago. So it's it's great
I'm glad it it feels like that that
addition of plasma and of course the repositories available to mangero and
The the work that you've put into it to make it all really sing
It made it feel like full-fledged product not a hobby toy
That came with a cool arch install on it
But it made it feel like a full-fledged product that is actually competitive for what I would use a thousand dollar tablet for
Yeah, we were even for giving it a pretty much a desktop feel
It's it's remarkable for the price and and and for the and for the board
So as we get into the XPS 13 here in just a few moments
It's got I think a higher bar it has to hit now because this for what you get for around
$300 the Pine Book Pro gives you a great terminal experience gives you a great browser experience
I watched some live stream videos and Firefox on it worked just fine
I brought the whole thing up to date installed a ton of packages on it
Yeah, I mean, I'm not gonna say it felt like it was some super performing I 732 gigs of RAM system
But when I look at the relative price points and the fact that you could save a thousand dollars
And you're still getting in your terminal web browser email chat work done still feels like a real laptop with a good keyboard
To Wes that was the other thing that surprised me. I don't love the trackpad
That's my main criticism of the overall hardware
How have you felt she's using that trackpad for an extended period of time is that you get used to it?
Mmm. I'm not a huge fan of it. I would imagine that the version that you have
Has been flashed to have the new firmware for the trackpad
the early first
Shipment of those devices. It was pretty horrible. The palm rejection was really bad. I
Usually just hook up a little USB mouse to it and I'm fine rock and roll that way, you know
And it should be said too. I think Dan and you can correct me if I'm wrong here
You guys have already got the latest
Pi 8 gig working with man jar as well, right? Yeah, we have awesome
My 8 gig supposed to arrive tomorrow my my gig pie. So I'm looking forward to that
Yeah, there's that caveat cheese that if you got the Pine Book Pro in 2019
You need to reflash your trackpad
But they have instructions on their wiki and then the other caveat is that if you got one of the more recent batches of pine
Books like mine it came with the Wi-Fi and microphone turned off
This is actually one of the cool features of the Pine Book is you can turn these off and then there is a LED
Indicator to let you know if they're off or on and they ship with all of those things off in that they tested them in
The factory and they left them in the off configuration. So your Wi-Fi won't work out of the box
it's just you hold down the pine key and I think it's f11 and
Then if you get the two flashes of the LED your Wi-Fi is on if you get three flashes
Your Wi-Fi is off. Did I get that right Dan? Yeah, you just need to reboot in between them. Yes, and that too
Yes, thank you. You also have to reboot because I hit it and I'm like, well, where are they? I
Thought it'd be like airplane mode. No, no, it's hardware physically
Reconnecting to your OS, you know
I actually mentioned to Lucas as well that maybe that's something they should ship turned off and include
You know kind of an instructional pamphlet so that people actually know that those features are baked in
I mean the majority of us do right but secure by default. Yeah, exactly and then opt to turn them on
I actually I didn't turn on the others just turned the Wi-Fi back on. Oh
Yeah, left there left leave the camera off. I don't need the camera right now
I thought I should probably try it. So I'll keep using it. I'm gonna take it on the trip with me
it'll be kind of like my go-to
you know just checking up checking in on stuff machine and
I'll give you my thoughts after an extended review today
Really? We're gonna talk more about the XPS 13, which is the most recent 10th gen Intel a
developer workstation from Dell and it's
Gorgeous. I have been watching Wes use it as we've recorded the shows with a lot of envy
usually I get to review the machines, but we thought
Let's change it up. It's fair that West get not only get a shake at it
But he's got a new gig where he's setting up new machines and he had to give back his ThinkPad
So he's kind of in a sense. He's in the market. So before we get there
How about a little housekeeping
We'd love to have you join us live just as a disclaimer though. We will not be live next Tuesday
We have a special episode already recorded and waiting to release
We will each get assigned a lightweight distribution
We're going to review it and then we'll have to meet a certain set of requirements
We'll score it based on those requirements and then we're going to try to convince each other all of the co-hosts
That our distribution is the best
It's a really fun episode. Yeah, that's for the June 9th
So we won't be here June 9th
But pay attention to your feed because they'll still be a new show. Exactly Linux Unplugged.com
Linux Unplugged.com slash subscribe also check it out. Go pay it forward cloud
Learners can now empower others to gain the knowledge needed for a career in the cloud
Just by getting your own certs for every cloud certification a cloud guru and Linux Academy users earn between May and June 2020
They're awarding an annual subscription to a person applying to receive a free a cloud guru subscription
So you get a cert somebody else gets a subscription. That's a nice thing to do right now
So I wanted to pass that along the luck plug goes on every single Sunday, even when I'm on the road
I'm by the way guys, I am gonna try to connect from the phone
I suppose the only variable will be if I have signal or not
Or if I have children climbing all over me, but the luck plug happens every Sunday noon Pacific
So that's when we do this show on Tuesdays the same bat time
Different bat day in the same mumble room. We just do it up in the lobby
to help figure out when all this is going we will soon be adding it to the calendar and
also
you can join the chat room on IRC that get shed net where the
Hashtag Jupiter broadcasting chat room is there's now a new room
Hashtag lup lug you join that you can chat in there. That's also the room everyone uses
During the lug so lup lug happens every single Sunday
Sometimes we may even commandeer it into a surprise show recording which may or may not have happened recently
But I can't say because that's in the future and that is also all of the housekeeping
The XPS 13 Dell's
2020 developer edition with 10th generation Intel CPUs
Super edge-to-edge screening keyboard this nice new fingerprint reader
I mean, it's definitely one of the fanciest machines we've ever had in studio
We're drooling all over it and those drill marks are easy to clean off though. So don't worry. I
Just kind of want to mention this because we often will just pass right over it. But the aesthetics of this thing
Are I think worth noting because to me it's striking
I mean you're sitting there with this thing and I look at it with these chamfered edges and I look at it with this gorgeous
keyboard and I think to myself that is a very high-end machine I
Legitimately one time glanced at it and I thought Wes is using a Mac. Oh, no. No, it's in several ways
They've exceeded what the Mac books do with the edge-to-edge screen and keyboard and the chamfered edges
I mean aesthetically it's it's very nice
I don't know if you had did you have a chance to show it to anybody else and get any reaction? Yeah, you know
Everyone I sent pictures to and the few folks that saw it in person from afar
But they were all impressed like it's in the Linux community, especially we're we're used to sort of settling a little bit
You know trying to find the right hardware that we know will work well with our you know
Out there operating system at times
There's no settling with this new XPS 13. Like it's just it feels great in the hand
It's it's definitely a lot more dense than some laptops like especially the leave me with a pro
But it feels so solid, you know, you can just really tell that it was they've been refining
Building these things over the years now that they've been working on them. Yeah, I agree with that assessment and
It kind of shows in a lot of ways. Yeah, boy. So it's a 10th generation
10 nanometer chipset here ice-like
It can be hard to get your hands on ice like get the 10 nanometer process from Intel because a lot of their stuff these days
It's still Comet Lake and 14 nanometer
It's a nice CPU. I was especially pleased with the Iris graphics installed
One of the first things I did was just get steam going
So no that wasn't job work, but it was a lot of fun
And I was pretty impressed with the wide range of games. I was able to play now
Not all of them are on the settings that I was used to from using a desktop
But they worked like there there weren't problems and they were definitely playable
which is nice because I think I think one thing that this XPS excels at is
Sort of being a jack-of-all-trades
It's small enough to fit in your bag very comfortably
You hardly notice it's there even though it's not the lightest of all laptops
But at the same time if you've got the right dock set up, which we'll get more into
It can be almost a desktop replacement. All right, let's talk about that because I know this sounds kind of silly
But if I'm gonna spend I don't know maybe it's not silly
Maybe not
But if I'm gonna spend a good chunk of change nearly two grand or something on a laptop or maybe even 2200 after it's all
configured and shipped I
Want to be able to play a little bit of games and I want to be able to do a little bit of work
I've heard good things about the 10th generation graphics if my expectations are
Moderately low, but not too low. I'm gonna you think I'll be happy with the results
So this is the Intel Iris plus
G7 with three gigs of a dedicated memory there now one caveat here is by default
You know, it's it's a 4k screen on this laptop and it is beautiful
But the higher resolution has some cost so that will depend a lot on how far you push things in terms of the in-game
resolution and honestly
that was one of the factors I think that
Showed up a lot in several of the benchmarks from performance to battery life is just it's a big beautiful display that
Takes a lot of power just that's just how it works
you know and it's it's worth it if it's it's not gonna be the laptop that has the longest battery life on the field or
is the fastest but it's it's in a very special middle ground between those where it's fast enough and
It lasts long enough. So we have the benchmark data for the limo room. We have the benchmark data for the previous XPS
Generation the one just before this did it stack up decently in those results?
You know, we'll have to dive more into the graphs to really tell but it's a it's a four core eight thread laptop
now you do have to do a little bit of tweaking to make sure that it's in in the performance mode in terms of the
CPU performance and you as well as you might want to do some battery tweaking to get it there
But I've been pretty impressed with the general overall performance in terms of you know
Running a workload spinning up a bunch of virtual machines
I also did just some some various benchmarks out of the Phronics test suite to you know
See how the system would perform under load. I did notice a couple times the desktop freezing
That was a little concerning, but it didn't take the whole computer down. I was able to just pop over to you know another term
Restart GDM and get back into my desktop and it wasn't that big of a deal but
I've heard from some other folks who've been testing out these that they've had similar experiences and that was a little concerning
Would it do that only in a load scenario or would it do that even under like idle conditions?
No, you know during normal use I didn't run into that at all
Yeah, that's a tricky one because even on my on my fairly powerful workstation upstairs. I would I would get desktop freezing
Until I switched to profile sync demon for my browser
Overall impressions on the way the work applications all that kind of stuff pretty good
It sounds like the battery life not quite what you'd want but acceptable charging all USB C
I assume all of that kind of standard stuff. In fact, it's only USB C, isn't it?
It is only USB C and that is something we should definitely talking to is just what ports do you got?
And you've got a micro SD to USB C that are you know Thunderbolt as well full full featured both able to charge from
So that's really nice. That's nice to see so you got you've got Thunderbolt 3 on those ports and micro SD which feels like
Is just an obvious
Easy addition for any laptop at this point and it's got one of those legacy 3.5 millimeter headphone ports on there
Wow legacy ports indeed. I know right
So if you if you pick up one of these, you're just gonna need some docks and some dongles basically
There's just there's no getting around it
I think for folks that have a newer laptop, you know before this already or maybe some setups from from various work
Configurations not that big of a deal
But if you've been lucky enough to hang around and just using manual, you know USB a style ports or you like physical Ethernet
Maybe not the configuration for you. Mm-hmm
Yeah, one big thing though in this line is you can get it with up to 32 gigs of RAM
And that is a huge change for the XPS line
It's great to see that especially for those of us that have a few VMs kicking around
Let's talk about what it feels like to actually use it seems like it has a pretty sizable trackpad that keyboard layout
I'm wondering about like I noticed that the arrow keys look like the bad version of the MacBook keyboard
How's the how's the overall like experience using that? Are you triggering the mouse more than you mean to with a trackpad that big?
Is that an issue, you know? No, honestly, I've been decently impressed with you know
Some of the rejection from the trackpad no no complaints and I like it a lot better than I liked the ThinkPad trackpad
That's for sure. Oh, really? Okay. Oh, yeah, definitely and it's not quite MacBook level
But in terms of like the actual material the build quality of the trackpad a lot of laptops use the trackpad
Especially if you're using it a lot. It just starts to wear out really quick
You know that it loses whatever surface that they put on there to make it smooth and nice for your fingers. I
Took the XPS on a little tour around Seattle. We'll have a photo gallery in the show notes
So I you know, I set it up
I couldn't go to coffee shops
Unfortunately
But I went to several different parks and locations around and set it up to just use it try to get some work done tethered
To my phone using the trackpad the whole time
Really one of the better trackpads I've used on Linux. It wasn't again
It's not like Mac level with tons of fancy gestures and all that
But really just solid basic trackpad and I've got to say the same for the keyboard
It's not quite ThinkPad level in that written in that term
But for just regular day-to-day use a little light programming catching up on emails sending slack messages
It was good enough that I just didn't think about it
Do you think that keyboard would bother you a year out from now? No, I don't think so
There are times it feels like maybe a little bit flimsy and the travels not super deep
But it's good enough that when you're using it, you just you just forget about it. It's totally fine
And once you've got it docked for a real workstation setup, I'm just gonna use a regular keyboard anyway
But that's true for basically all laptops that I use so you went the dock route. I assume, you know limited ports
It's kind of easier if you just shunt it all off into a dock. Yeah, I think you have to in the USB C lifestyle
Right you guys just you just you're gonna need a nice dock setup so that you can actually have all the peripherals you want
especially if you've got like a
Desktop microphone and maybe you've still got a non bluetooth mouse in play like I do at my current work from home setup
So it just seemed like the easiest route
Go plug everything in that way
So there were some times especially when I was I was trying to do some testing
As maybe you know
Like a recording workstation the lack of parts was kind of annoying because I've run Ethernet up into my recording location or I am now
I've got it all set up. And of course my audio interface is a USB a so if you're not prepared for the USB C lifestyle
There are times that you sort of forget that your computer can't cannot connect to things and can't talk to
Most of your gadgets, but if you're used to it, it's just not that big of a deal. I love your pictures
I'm looking at some of these pictures. I was showing them on the live stream
They're really cool. And it really does show you what a nice looking machine is. You get a good idea of that keyboard
But the thing that I'm not I'm not blown away by the results in the Ferronix benchmarks
They're good, but I'm not I'm not blown away by them. They didn't super surprise me
It doesn't seem like it's a a substantial performance increase
But it other than the RAM area where if you need more memory, it's an obvious an obvious choice
yeah, and this isn't some you know, it's not like the
The the real desktop replacement lines the precision series. It's it's not to that level, right?
Yeah, but you know, I was testing it out with a ton of containers running and some virtual machines
tons of electron apps and chrome tabs and let me tell you plenty of tabs open and
Compared to any of the other sort of day-to-day laptops I've used for the past couple of years
Wasn't breaking a sweat. What about fan noise? I was gonna get to that
When you're playing a game or spinning up a whole bunch of stuff, you will hear the fans, but it's not a bad fan
It's not shrill. It's not too, you know, whooshie. It will be there in the background, especially if you are playing a game
It's basically there all the time
But if you're listening to any of the game audio or you're you know chatting with friends on discord
They didn't hear it and I couldn't hear it once I put headphones in. Yeah, okay
I mean, that's that's how it works on a laptop
I did notice it right away, but I wasn't really put off by it and it wasn't wasn't anything like those laptops that you know
Have the world's tiniest fans spin up and are just screaming in your ear
I want to take a moment to talk about Thunderbolt 3 here because
This is something that really has gotten a bad rap. You know, everybody
Probably is aware that recently there was yet another
Security story that mentions that oh by the way, it's it's dangerous to have external access to the PCI bus Wow shocker
shocker
but yeah, it also is external access to the PCI bus and that makes it amazing and I have
some
Docs in the studio and in my RV that I can move between
Linux I can move between
MacBooks I can move between anything that supports Thunderbolt and it's it's so great because they're not
Gimped devices that require a bunch of CPU usage to sort out messages on the USB bus
It is really PCI wired in and that means multiple monitors and GPUs and and sound cards
And it really gives you a lot of power that you can hook up into a laptop with one
Single cord and if you're willing to invest in that it I think tremendously expands
what these laptops are capable of like I just really think it's
It's gotten a bad rap and I know as part of a review
It's hard to go out and buy a whole bunch of Thunderbolt accessories because they're not cheap
Unfortunately, they're not but I think did you get a sense of like it's nice
You can hook up the monitor
You can hook up your mouse and keyboard to one thing the power if you have power pass through and then it's just that
Single cord that goes into the laptop. Yeah, you know that actually that was really nice
and I got myself a little Bluetooth mouse to play with too and that combination
Really made for a seamless sort of docking and undocking experience where I could throw it in my bag
Go run around and do stuff show back up at the house
You know when I was using the ThinkPad for better or worse
There were like three or four things because I actually had ports
so I was using the ports that I had to unplug and replug in even with USB C on there and
And with the XPS 13, yeah, it's just one cable and you're done and then you're instantly back at your legitimate setup
And you don't have to feel like it's some really flaky setup
Like I know I've had in the past some docks that especially with like display port pass-through for multiple monitors
And like they just would never wake up correctly after you know after sleeping none of those problems
Yeah, and you could even if it is say you're going all-in you could eventually decide
I really actually want to game on this thing fairly seriously and then you could go spend the ridiculous amount of money
It is on an eGPU and have a real powerful GPU you hook up
Maybe it's not 16x PCI, but it's still plenty fast to play your video game
I do it all the time and it means that you can have this tiny machine that has almost no
Bag debt and you know what I mean?
Like it just doesn't really affect your bag in terms of size it takes or weight and because it's USB C
You're charging it with the same charger. You're charging all of your other devices on your trip and it matters a lot
So if that's a situation that a rock that comes up for you from time to time or you want to have a grab-and-go
Situation where you just take the bag and get out and work somewhere
I think it really makes a big difference and I think we're now in a world where
The Linux version is a superior product to the Windows version
Friend of the show Jim Salter had a review of the XPS 13 and on the Windows side
There's software it comes with to manage the killer wireless card and all of this that has some trade-offs
that make it maybe an experience that I don't think the developer market would be interested in and
It shows you how when you buy the developer edition of this laptop. Not only do you get a great operating system, but you also
don't have these silly like gimmicky killer wireless management features that take a bunch of
CPU overhead and whatnot and I think that's also worth considering now is like these products are in some ways better on the Linux side
They are I mean you also get that 4k screen, which you know, I could go back and forth on it. It is so beautiful
It's a little bit much in a 13 inch laptop. I think and it definitely has some as we talked about
complications for the battery life and some other issues, but
It's just it's so nice to see the Sputnik program have gotten this far that we have this developer focused machine
that really does feel like it with 32 gigs of RAM and a first-class experience all around and
Up on to shipping on it right out of the box. Was it 1804 that it shipped with do you recall?
I know we kind of we nuked and paved fairly quick. We very quickly got rid of that
It did ship with 1804 and that worked fine
But I wanted to own to try 2004 on it because that's that's the new hotness and it works great now
One thing people been asking about with this machine is the fingerprint reader. Yeah, that doesn't work quite yet
I haven't found any official updates about when that will be available. If you look at the Dell website and Barton
George's original post on his blog. They mentioned that that will come out sometime mid 2020
So I think we're in that range anytime. It should be an over-the-air update
Just some firmware that gets added support and a new driver available for Linux. Not there yet, though
maybe a combination of an FW up D and
a point release of
2004 yeah, I think so because you can see it there, you know if you do LS USB
It shows right up and you get all the driver information and they have promised that you know
They've been working with the hardware vendor. This should be coming down the pipe, but so far not there yet
Which is a little disappointing because I was excited because in 24
They've got the the genome changes in that you can you can add fingerprint support just right there in the genome settings
Which is pretty cool. It's a nice fingerprint reader. It's a it's like a big padded button
It's not your old swipey fingerprint reader. No, it is not and it actually doubles
It's the power button which feels a little modern
Maybe too modern takes a little bit to get used to but is pretty cool. Don't change West Pains power button
It spooks them now this thing doesn't it?
Technically have support for the Windows. Hello style face ID style login. Yes, it does
So it has the infrared
Sensors needed to do that right next to the webcam and we should note
Unlike the old days of staring up your nose on a webcam call
This XPS has the camera in the usual spot on the top of the display
It is only 720p, but honestly, it's fine. You know, I did so I did some work calls
Did some gaming with friends some zoom calls. No one complained. No one said anything. The webcam is good enough
I can't believe they managed to fit a webcam up there. Oh, I know it's it's shockingly small
You hardly believe it
It was I tried to take a picture of it
But that was hard to because it's just it's just a tiny little bezel
You could kind of see it in your picture
So I do you got to check this out go check out the photo gallery because it's it's remarkable
They fit it in there along with the IR sensor
Also, it's it's it gives you a better concept of what we're saying when it's edge to edge screen and edge to edge keyboard it
It really feels like every scrap of space in that machine is used
Nothing has gone to waste on the design and space of that machine. So you were mentioning the Windows style. Hello
So this gave me a good opportunity to try some open source software called howdy
Oh, really and howdy provides Windows Hello style
Authentication for Linux and it's actually pretty cool because it ties into PAM
So if you want to do pseudo you can use your face to do it now
I'm not saying you should do this is probably not a good security posture
But it was really neat to see this actually work on Linux. There's a PPA out there if you want to go install it
They've got packages available for Ubuntu add that install it and then it's got a handy little guy that will guide you through
Registering your face getting that enrolled and then it downloads all the necessary machine learning models sets things up for you
You're done. Say you were going to buy this thing you get there's two base models. They start with a
$1,000 model and a $1,400 model they both come with the 10th gen processors ones and I five and I seven
I want to price this out and see if you'd actually buy it now that you've used it
Would you get the i5 model for Westpain or would you get the i7 model?
You know, that's a tough one. I might be tempted to just stick with the i5
I could see it's reasonable and in a laptop. You're probably not gonna see a huge difference. That's just it
I mean if you're using this thing, you're gonna throw it in the closet never be around it
It's gonna have its fan going and it'll be cooled and you're busy on the CPU all the time
Then okay, maybe you want the i7 but I don't think you'll notice just what the i5 for whatever reason
I think when you get the i5 you cannot do 32 gigs of RAM with a Dell configurator at this time
So are you okay with 16 gigs or would you stick with eight?
What's your choice be I don't think I could buy a new laptop that only had eight gigs in 2020
It's $100 to go up to 16. So the display has two options
Now the one we got in-house to review is the UHD plus 4k infinity edge touch
Anti-reflective 500 nit display. I mean it's like
Gorgeous on a laptop. However, you can get that same chassis
with the infinity edge display at
1920 by 1200 and it's actually
$400 cheaper that I would be tempted for I mean the 4k is beautiful
But honestly just for like simple Linux desktop stuff and since I'm not, you know
I wasn't using it for doing any sort of like content creation in terms of photo or video work
The smaller resolution would be fine for just when I'm in the terminal
1920 by 1200 is a great resolution. It's a great resolution and it'll save you some battery life
I'd love to see a 2k option, but they have an anti-reflective
Version of that 1920 by 1200 for an additional $100. I don't know
That's a tough call but at the storage level by base. It's 256. I'd kind of advise you bump it to a terabyte for 250 bucks
I don't know what your thoughts are though. Maybe 512 or 256 is enough for Wes 256
Not not anymore. I think that that fits in the 8 512
I can live with especially if it's you know, you build your workflow around it
You just know that you're gonna need a scratch disk attack to your dock somewhere or you're doing everything in the cloud
Anyway, those are all workable. You've got Thunderbolt. You've got you've got cloud storage. You can always build the NAS
So ok 512 m.2 for 100 bucks more. All right, Wes
Are you ready for your final price this by the way is with the base warranty one-year pro support
And no additional damage and at any kind of like office software. No office software. No antivirus, please
your grand total comes to
1249 dollars and 99 cents. So let's just say maybe 13
14 hundred dollars after sales tax or whatnots shipping is free
Let's round up just to make it a little easier. Would you pay 14 hundred dollars all-in?
For the laptop you have right now. Yeah, you know, I really think that I would it's just it has fallen into my lifestyle
So well, you know, it doesn't do really any one thing
Better than anything else necessarily, but it is remarkably well rounded
I feels comfortable just throwing it on the couch and using it while you're watching TV and it feels comfortable
It's like a primary development workstation. That's a hard thing to get right and
Make it a laptop that I'm proud to show off as I'm walking around and I gotta say you and I both having been
XPS owners, I think we both have some very old XPS is that still boot up and run
And they have no right to be doing so at this point. Yes
Now unfortunately, you do kind of have to make the the Mac style calculus of how much more am I gonna spend to try?
To future-proof this thing, but you're right
I have no doubt that this will still be especially given the build quality of the thing a
Great laptop in four years time. So before tax this thing came out to essentially
Thousand two hundred fifty dollars and for that it was a 10th gen i5 up to three point six gigahertz boost
It came with Ubuntu pre-installed
16 gigabytes of DDR4 low-power RAM a
1920 by 1200
FHD plus edge-to-edge
500 nit display a
512 gigabyte PCI MVME solid-state disk the killer Wi-Fi ATX 1650 which is legitimately
Supposedly a very good Wi-Fi chip
I poked fun earlier and also those Intel UHD graphics that come with that 10th gen Intel i5 and
on the mid-range area a 4-cell 52 watt-hour battery in the
fully nice shiny platinum silver with black carbon fiber
design
You get all that for
1250 plus tax that does seem like a pretty strong value
I don't know if it's the end-all machine for everybody because they have made some very
Serious decisions and how you can use the machine and and that I think is where the compromise lies
But outside of that, I think it's very compelling now
It'd be another $400 to go with the 4k display, but I like your build a little bit better Wes
yeah, I do too, honestly, that's very
tempting because it's just
It fits it does what you need and I love that Dell is making these with Linux just pre-installed
I think that it's it's great to be able to support that if you can and send that signal like
Yes, keep doing that. Yeah, the team's got to be super proud of this machine looking backwards come, you know, it's funny to you
you mentioned the Wi-Fi there and
All of Jim's problems with the Wi-Fi was on Windows and it turns out
It's a totally fine Wi-Fi chip with Wi-Fi 6 support and when you just use the in kernel driver for it
I mean kernel 5.1 or later you won't notice the thing
I think that's another way in which it is a superior product using Linux for people that just want to get their work done
Well, that means we have to box it back up and send it back to Dell now
But it was it was neat to see it. And this is really prompt
I mean we say it every time but
They really just keep iterating on this product
and so if you buy in at a certain generation there is a
Really good indication that when you're ready to rebuy in how many years has it been for us seven years since you bought your XPS?
Whoo. Yes
you know though that you can now go back to that same product line and
There's continuity there and that there's very likely at this point that if say you bought another laptop and four to seven years
There could be another one in that product line and there's something to that. That's just it as I think they've shown
Excellent stewardship of the line, you know, it hasn't really betrayed us yet
It hasn't just really sacrificed quality
If anything they've continued to invest in the quality of this of the hardware of the setup of thinking thoughtfully about how to configure these
Machines with things like adding 32 gig support with finally working on drivers for fingerprint readers for Linux
Those are all good things and I expect we'll see them to continue
Yeah, and you really can't argue with that price
$1,300 or if you want to round up $1,400 all-in for decent hardware
But what is not in that price but is included is the design of the chassis that edge-to-edge screen that huge trackpad
I think it's I think I agree with Wes. I think it's likely the best trackpad shipping on a Linux pre-installed laptop right now
We've talked about the beauty and niceness of sort of the machining and the build of the chassis
But it also just feels very sturdy and reliable as I was walking around with it using it around like I wasn't worried about damaging
It had a great feel in the hand and the hinges were really solid
Which is one thing that I really bugs me on a lot of laptops
Even if it's a good laptop supports Linux
Well, you can just tell that those hinges are really gonna wear out and after a year or two
You're just gonna have a floppy screen that you have to prop up. Yep. Absolutely. Well, thank you Wes now
before we run out of time I wanted to do a little follow-up on my data loss crisis and
Answer I'm a question that I'm sure was common in a lot of listeners minds Jameson wrote in and he said
Why not build all of what you just tried to do with butter FS on LVM and XFS?
I know it requires a bit of stacking of technology and different tools to manage
But there isn't much you can do on LVM that you can do on butter FS and ZFS these days
And I think that was probably everyone's probably wondering why I didn't go with XFS. I was I was specifically trying to
Use butter FS. That was a choice. I made there was a couple of things that played into it
Number one is I do like to do it as low-level to the system as possible
So that's bias number one is I don't like a lot of tools stacked on top of it
I love the concept of an all-inclusive file system that's built into my operating system kernel
That has the tools to do these things for me all about that monolith
Yeah, man, and these things being I want drobo like capacity to just add
Dis so I have production discs that we may retire out of production
This is not an actual scenario that exists right now
but in the future we will have
discs that will want to retire out of production and I could take some of those and just add them to an existing
Group storage pool with butter FS very simply for just scratch projects. I have I have no concern if the data loss occurs
there's a very simple butter FS add volume command that just grows a mount point and
That's a very appealing technology
so I wanted to learn and experiment with that as well if I was building something that I wanted absolute stability and
predictability and that I never touched again, I
Probably would have gone with LVM and XFS
That's that's generally my go-to strategy for like a server setup
or if it was a more powerful x86 system probably would have gone with a
Isolated OS and then ZFS pool approach like we do here in the studio, you know
But it is a good point by Jameson here writing in which thank you LVM, especially with thin provisioning and the snapshot capabilities
As a lot of these features and XFS 2 is growing copy-on-write abilities as well
So they have not stood still and I think we've seen too with things like project Stratus that there are a lot of those
capabilities
But you're right to my mind a lot of the big wins with things like butter fast and CFS
You you just have the one interface for it
You don't have to manage multiple different projects and how they interact and really understand it
You just got to rely on using the one tool correctly, even if sometimes with butter FS. That's tricky. Yeah, that's it and
On a Raspberry Pi there is less overhead available
so I really want to do something as low level as possible the other thing that I find appealing about butter FS is
Besides its SSD trim support and things like that is I can individually turn off copy-on-write for a directory of things
There's some compelling reasons perhaps on a docker container to turn off copy-on-write
Although there's advantages to for snaps
There's advantages of having butter first for snapshotting there too
but anyways actually where I where I don't really intend to use copy-on-write is these
five
Plus gigabyte media files that can be you know up to 20 25 gigabyte MKV files
I don't really want copy-on-write on USB media for those and I can turn that off just with a
Directory attribute with butter FS. Yeah, that's pretty nice
But you can you know, you can still get some of the other nice features of butter FS at the same time
Yeah, exactly and I can do this drobo style mismatch disk sizes
over time which is probably a recipe for horrible disaster unless I bring some kind of raid into the mix which
I'm not super inclined to do with butter FS
But I'm also doing it with files that assuming my backups are working correctly are all
Restorable the applications are all in containers. The data is all backed up here at the studio
So it's all recoverable and I am happy to say it is all back up and running and like what happens anytime one of these
Catastrophes happen and you rebuild you rebuild with lessons learned and so now I like the new setup
Even more than I liked the old setup
So I'm feeling pretty good at this point all about it all I am using the crazy butter FS setup
I after I rebuilt everything I went back to butter FS from the start this time
No file system conversion shenanigans and I did the volume add so I have now combined two
1TB
MVME SSDs as a
a
2TB storage pool that is available for my media and I love solid-state media in the RV because I'm going down the road
you know, it's it's a they say it's like a
4 on the Richter scale for an earthquake for everything in the RV as you're going down the road
So obviously spinning rust is out mind those platters. Yeah, and so my kids are watching TV
Well, I'm going down the road and I'm serving up media and doing the encoding I'm streaming it and I don't want to be running
off of platters so that's where this kind of technology where I'm adding fairly reliable disks and
The use case scenario is our media server goes out or I can't get to my notes
Makes the stakes low enough that I'm comfortable experimenting with raspberry pies and with butter FS
Because it's a great learning opportunity and nothing truly teaches you like actually using something in a scenario where you kind of depend on it
That's why I was glad to see you picked butter FS. Honestly, is it it's just nice to use some of these times because we've
Deployed it a little bit at the studio
I've still got a storage pool at my house that's using it and I haven't sent seem to need to replace and
It's good to remember that it's in the kernel. It's being updated and maintained. It hasn't stood still
So it's good for us to keep a rest of the changes and for me
It's like okay if I was gonna rebuild say the file server here in the studio again something god forbid happened
I'd go ZFS again. I wouldn't be experimenting with butter FS there, but at the same time
I don't want to be ignorant to what it's capable of and because I have been critical of it in the past
I think it's important that I check in on it from time to time and update my
understanding of what it's capable of because otherwise I just become one of those
jackasses on the internet that
Criticizes things for 15 years and never updates their opinions and never tries things out and that's just annoying. We wouldn't want that
All right, mr. Payne. Well, I think that wraps us up this week Linux unplug calm slash three five six
You can go to Linux unplug calm slash contact to send us your feedback
Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar if you want to find out when we'll be here alive could mention the Twitter handle at Linux unplug
The network is at Jupiter signal. I'm at Chris glass. He's at West Payne and thank you for being here
That's what really matters and we'll see you back here next Tuesday
You
Know I was looking at the specs for that XPS. It was pretty surprised
2.6 pounds. Yeah, it's definitely dense because it's you know, so just small in a 13 inch platform
But it feel it just feels very sturdy. And yeah, I threw it up through my bag
Didn't feel different than having an empty bag. It kind of feels like it's all one solid device
It does feel like that
Could you open it with just one finger or did you have to hold the base down as well?
So that I found depends a little bit on what surface they've got some pretty good little grippies on the bottom there
So on most normal surfaces, yes
Holding it in my hand also
Yes
but the the hardest part is just like the angle on the screen and it's like at the ends of the screen is thicker than
Like the taper on the bottom part of the laptop. So the hardest part is just getting that first crack going
They don't have the little cutout like the older MacBooks did got you but once it's open a little bit then it works really nice
Yeah, that's the tricky thing. I tried that probably too much
I was just playing with it because the hinge is so smooth. It was fun to mess with