All right, Wes Payne, I want you to take a guess.
What is the average miles per hour in which you exhale air?
So the speed at which it leaves your hot bod?
Fourteen? Fourteen. What do you say, Cheese?
Is it sneeze or is that just regular exhale?
I think a sneeze is probably, like, pedal to the metal.
So I say regular.
That's a special case, yeah.
Okay, so I'm gonna say 27 miles an hour.
Whoa, okay. All right, what about you, Drew?
I'm gonna go way lower.
I'm gonna say, like, three miles per hour.
He's a real slow breather, that's true.
He's a smoker, maybe.
Yeah. Anybody in the Mumble Room have a guess?
Fifteen.
Jill says 15.
All right, are you ready for the big reveal?
Are you ready? Are you ready?
I've never wanted anything more.
It is 15 miles per hour!
Whoo!
Hello, friends, and welcome into a very special edition of 357.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
I don't know how we got into this, Wes,
but we are here on a Sunday with our virtual lug
recording a special edition of the show
while I am on the road.
It's a bake-off, which we don't tend
to get into, but on this episode,
we each went off and took a lightweight Linux distribution
with us, and we're gonna come back and, A,
tell you what we thought about it,
but, B, we created a point system,
which I'll tell you about here in a moment,
in which to score them, and we'll see who walks away
with the ultimate lightweight distribution.
So to help Wes and I do that, of course,
is our two Robins.
It's Drew and Cheese. Hello, gentlemen.
Hello.
I think that Drew, you went for the more retro Robin,
and Cheese went for the more modern movie Robin.
Skimpy, that's for sure.
Yeah, Cheese, I'm not sure.
I think that was a Robin costume for ladies.
Hey, you don't be dissin' my cute-ass Robin costume.
It looks good.
It looks good, you know?
I just gotta say, it looks good.
And then, of course, all-wearing costume
is our virtual lug.
Hello, Mumble Room.
Time-appropriate greetings.
Hello.
Happy Linux Tuesday recorded on a Sunday.
Happy Sunday.
Yeah, this is a special one.
We just took over the virtual lug today with no heads up,
because this is the last MINNA idea we had.
Sorry, MINNY.
Sorry, guys.
But we wanted to get you in on this as well.
We thought, why not?
Let's have some fun talking about
lightweight distributions.
I think lightweight distributions hold a special part
in all of our hearts.
I think the first one that I really took seriously
was probably back in the Lubuntu 1010 days, which back then
included LXDE and was really nice for systems
that were single-core processors before the domination
of multi-core and tons and tons of RAM.
I ran it on a system with 128 megabytes of RAM.
And I think it was a Pentium 3.
It was a really old system at the time.
I mean, it just brings back some of that magic of, yeah,
you can make Linux work on that when whatever proprietary OS
came on it is no longer supported.
There's that.
It's like bringing life into a system, which feels incredible.
But it's also a special challenge
that not every distribution decides to take on,
because it's not necessarily an easy goal to fit
within these tiny constraints.
Mind those dependencies.
Especially when you want yourself a modern desktop.
So we set off to define a few rules around the game
and award some points.
Now, because this is a special edition, gentlemen,
the floor is open for you to ask any questions about the rules
or make any suggestions, because we're doing this as we go.
But we had some minimum requirements that will
earn your distribution a point.
So you need to be responsible for tracking your points here.
Do you guys have something?
I got paper right here.
What, are you asking us to tally our own points?
Because I'm going to give myself a winning number, so.
Bring your own tally.
The audience will be keeping count,
and they will hold you accountable.
So you'll get one point if you can run it on a single CPU
core, if you can run it with one gig of RAM,
you get a point for each of these, I think.
What do you think?
You like doing it that way?
Or do you think you should just get one point for all of them?
No, I like splitting them up.
All right, so these are one pointers.
One CPU, one gigabyte of RAM, within a gigabyte
of hard drive space, easy dark mode, and easy to install.
And you must be able to run a web browser that
can play any episode of LUP in the browser.
So that is for one point.
If you get one point for each of those.
All right.
Now, the bonus round, where each one of these
is awarded five points, if you can get a modern GTK
or cute theme on there, and I define that in here as ARK,
YARU, POP, or Breeze, if you can install software that is not
in the distribution's repos, so somehow get software
from outside the repos running on the box,
that is also worth five points.
Another five points if you can play YouTube or Netflix
in your browser.
And if you can boot to the desktop within 20 seconds,
another five points.
And if any video game at all plays, five points.
All right.
Not a lot of points, but some of these
are slightly challenging.
Some of these distros, it may be harder to get ARK or YARU
or POP on there.
Sure.
The modern GTK theme, is that out of the box?
Or is that something that you can install after?
I think it's fair if you can get it after.
I think that's fair.
Do you guys agree with that?
Agreed.
Yeah.
OK, all right.
Because I mean, honestly, at this level,
you're the type of user that's OK doing that.
All right, then we have the illumination round,
which is 10 points for each one of these.
You get 10 points if you can get it to run Visual Studio code.
Just thought that'd be a fun one.
And 10 points if you can get it to install
a different kernel than the one that it shipped with,
and it still boots.
So 10 points for that.
And then we have the will of the people round.
An additional 10 points will be awarded just for one thing.
If you convince a co-host, each co-host
you convince that your distro is the best,
you can be awarded 10 points.
Yeah, OK.
Y'all turncoats.
I mean, this is, I think, a chance
where if your distribution can't meet
some of these other minimums, you
could make it up in the will of the people round.
It's the personality factor.
So we hit the randomize button, and we're
each distributed a distribution, which
I now am, of course, a main advocate for.
Drew was distributed Bunsen Labs, Cheese, Puppy Linux,
Wes, FreeBSD, and what was the other one, Wes?
Well, this was a late contender I added to the race
because it was just too fun.
OK, so FreeBSD is going to be my main contender.
But Calibri OS is written in pure assembly
and needs only something like eight megs of RAM.
So I thought, why not go super tiny?
Now, it's not going to score very well,
but I thought it deserved an amendment.
Yeah, I'm really looking forward to hearing about that,
and FreeBSD.
And then I was assigned Sparky Linux,
which I'm looking forward to telling you about because
obviously, it is the best Linux out of all of these
and should clearly be the winner.
And by the end of this, you'll all want to run it.
So we'll talk about that.
These are the ground rules.
It's a little complicated, but it's essentially
there is a one-point category, a five-point category,
and a 10-point category.
And then there is that final will of the people category
that's also 10 points, just one item.
And that is convince a co-host.
So what do you say we start with Bunsen Labs?
Drew, I'm curious to know about Bunsen Labs
and why we should all be using it.
First of all, it is so Debian that you can switch to it
from a base Debian system.
Oh, wow.
OK.
Bunsen Labs Helium, you can get as a PPA
and convert your current Debian system into Bunsen Labs.
So what does that mean?
First of all, you have the full power of Debian behind you.
So this is going to score very, very, very highly
on this test.
Talk's a big game.
Oh, I do.
And rightly so.
I ran it on one core and one gig of RAM.
No problem whatsoever.
Yeah, but this thing's based on Debian 9.
Snore.
Wah, wah, wah.
Oh, well.
If I'm deploying systems all over left and right,
I want something modern.
I want like Debian 10.
Yeah, but I can still get back ports through PPAs.
OK, all right.
I was not really able to get it to install
with one gigabyte of disk.
Just to get it to properly install and be
able to run updates afterwards, I had to go to five gigabytes.
But I would recommend going to 10 gig
for a fully functional system.
So losing a point there, but.
OK, did anybody else get in within the one gig?
Did anybody get the one gig point?
Not quite.
Not with the GUI, although Calibri OS totally does.
Yeah, I got to admit, I did not quite get there either.
I got really close.
And none of us got the one gig point.
But Drew, did you get the one CPU core?
Oh, absolutely.
All right, so mark yourself a point down for that.
What about how much RAM?
One gig.
All right, so you get a point for that.
How was the install to disk?
Install to disk was fine as soon as I had a big enough disk.
Right, OK, tell us about that.
Super easy.
So it has an install to disk option in the grub menu.
And it launches into a nice, easy installer.
It explains everything as you're going,
and tells you exactly what it's doing,
and asks you simple questions that you
can decide on how to proceed.
It is fine with just the default options.
I didn't change a single thing, and had
zero problems going through the entire installation.
OK, I got to admit, early on, I'm feeling a little concerned.
Are you feeling competitive right now, Cheese?
Nah.
Yeah, OK, all right, OK.
Damn it, Debian.
So what about easy dark mode?
No, there was no dark mode out of the box.
I'm not going to give myself a point for that.
I could get a dark mode going to the repos
and downloading something, but I feel
like the easy dark mode should be out of the box.
So I'm going to say no.
OK, I think we all agree on that.
I am curious, is there any special sauce
you really liked about it to keep things light?
I mean, if you've got the full power of Debian,
are they doing anything different about how
they set up defaults, or just tune things to keep it small?
Aside from just using Openbox as the window manager,
I don't know what special things they're doing on the back end
to make it run so light.
But the default install is literally
it's just Openbox on a Debian-based system
with kernel 4.9 and it has Firefox ESR instead
of the latest stable.
Aside from that, it doesn't appear
that there's any specific kernel tuning or anything
like that that is really making it so light.
I think it's just the fact that Debian
doesn't need much to begin with.
And neither does Openbox.
Really, it doesn't, yeah.
So did you get a rough idea of what you're just sort
of sitting idle RAM usage was?
Very, very low.
I didn't specifically calculate it,
but it wasn't even really showing up
in my virtual machine manager.
I know.
That's what's so funny about this, huh?
These things are so lightweight,
you don't even really notice them.
All right, well, let's get into the bonus round here.
So did it have a modern theme?
Not out of the box, but it's Debian.
So any theme you could, OK.
I think you get five points for that then.
I do.
Were you able to install any software that
wasn't in the repos?
I installed software from PPAs, and I also
compiled from source.
Oh, snap.
All right, total five points.
Were you able to play YouTube or Netflix?
I was able to play YouTube on the live CD version,
and I was able to get into Netflix after installing
the DRM in Firefox.
But unfortunately, it crashed while I
was trying to play Netflix.
However, after I installed it to disk, no problems whatsoever.
Netflix worked without even skipping a beat.
Now, I'm betting, because it is Debian-based,
you probably didn't get to the desktop in under 20 seconds.
Actually, on the very first boot,
I got to the desktop in 26.8 seconds.
However, after that, on any subsequent boot,
seven seconds on the dot.
Whoa.
Really?
All right, I think you get five points for that.
Any video games?
Yeah, I loaded up a few simple games,
because I was running in a virtual machine,
and I didn't have any kind of real DRM
or any kind of access to the video card.
I wasn't going to try anything like super snazzy,
but I was playing Xtron, I'll Riot, Xboard.
Stuff's in Debian, so.
So you got every category.
You got every one of those in the five points category.
All right, now to the elimination round.
Each one of these is 10 points.
Does it run Visual Studio Code?
I'm assuming, yes.
Yes, I did have to pull Flatpak
from the squeeze back ports PPA.
But as soon as I did that, no problems whatsoever,
came right up.
What about installing a different kernel?
Did you go for that one?
I installed the Licorix kernel.
Oh, true.
Whoa.
Oh, no, guys.
Kernel 5.6, and that booted in 8.67.
OK, wow, OK.
So I think we'll hold the convince till the end,
which will be the extra, but you're doing really well there.
Bunsen Lab sounds like a serious contender.
What was the final disk size?
That's what I'm curious about.
Yeah, good question.
I went with 10 gig because Flatpak is a little heavier
as far as disk space.
And that was the only way I was able to really get
VS Code going.
OK, all right, fair enough.
All right, well, standby, Drew, I'll have a few more questions,
but we got to go to cheese now on Puppy
and see how Puppy stacks up and how many points.
Drew, do you have a rough back of the napkin calculation
so far of how many points you got there?
Oh, let's take a look here, 1, 2.
So let's see, I got 5 for that, 10, 15, 20, 25, 35, 45, so 47.
Ouch.
OK, so cheesy.
Let's see if we can beat 47.
How was Puppy Linux?
Puppy Linux is great.
It's real great.
Convince me now.
You're not really convincing me.
Yeah, I'm definitely not going to win
that portion of the 10 points.
So I did run it on a single core with a single gig of RAM,
as you would expect.
Normally, Puppy's meant to just boot and load into RAM.
I'm using boxes here for this, so I
ran into an issue with boxes where I could only
go down to 10 gigs in size.
Final install size, though, was 1.4 gigabyte.
I definitely hit all of those marks.
That's impressive.
I guess, except for the hard drive, it was 1.4 gigabyte.
I was able to run a browser, their Pale Moon browser,
and play an episode of Love.
There is an easy dark mode, kind of.
How do you figure?
What do you mean?
Yeah, let's get into that.
It's JWM, and there are different themes for JWM,
GTK2-based themes.
So I was able to install, out of the box, Nox, the Nox theme, which
is their version of a dark theme.
While maybe not extremely pretty, it is a dark mode.
So I was able to get a dark mode out of the box.
Easy to install the disk is kind of, I mean, it is.
It's stupid simple to install to disk, but.
You sound a little, I don't know, not confident.
Well, the way the Puppy is kind of set up, right,
is that it's the root user.
Like, everything defaults as root.
Now, you can go through settings to kind of adjust that to,
I think there's three different levels, FIDO being basically
a guest user type of thing.
So it's really a different kind of Linux.
It's not really your typical install.
The prompts are ridiculous.
You're not convincing me at all.
You know, I'm putting it all out there on the table, right?
It's one of those things where there's just a ton of these
prompts that are just lengthy and don't make a ton of sense.
There are three different networking applications
to choose from by default.
How do you want to connect to your network sort of thing?
Like, if this one doesn't work, try this one.
If that one doesn't work, try this one.
If you need a NDIS wrapper or something, try this one.
So it's kind of silly, right?
But you see, this is where you have an advantage.
Because for this, we're scoring it by the rules of the game.
So if you got this thing to play YouTube or any video game at all,
you're getting five points for either one of those things.
I think maybe at the end, we should consider too, like,
which one has the least space, since it sounds like we're all
kind of going over a little bit.
And I would mention too, BiteBitten points out
in the Mumble Room that this is available for some other
platforms where the minimal size really matters.
Right, like the Pi.
If you wanted to run it on the Pi, it'd be great for that.
I don't like running stuff as root,
so it's kind of weird for me, but yeah.
So what about things like VS Code or getting a different kernel
on there, how did that go?
So I kind of combined this two in one.
I installed software, which wasn't in the repos.
I installed VS Code or VS Codeium via an app image.
All right, OK, OK, hold on, hold on, hold on, hold on.
We got to have a quorum on this.
See, I was thinking specifically it needs to be VS Code, not VS Codeium,
because VS Codeium is easier.
And I was thinking VS Code makes it actually a little harder
because it's the quote unquote, you know, official version,
which is slightly hard to get your hands on.
But I'm open to what Drew and Wes think on this issue.
Half credit.
All right, I'll agree with that.
Cheese, are you OK with that compromise?
Yes.
All right, all right.
Because there is that element of like, you have to use proprietary X,
can't you?
Yes, that's what that was going for there.
OK, OK.
Because obviously in this situation,
you would just use VS Codeium.
I agree, that's the right way to go.
But OK, we'll do five points.
Continue on.
I'm sorry, I just wanted to clarify that.
I was able to install that app image.
It doesn't have a modern GTK theme, so no five there.
I was able to play YouTube, so a five point there.
OK, good.
It booted in 12 seconds consistently.
Oh.
So not bad.
As far as any video game, they have a section in Puppy called Fun.
And I was able to play a Sudoku clone.
Did you have fun?
Yes.
Good.
I am glad you had fun.
Ha, ha, ha, ha.
Have you tallied up your score yet?
Not quite.
I was not able to install a different kernel
by the default install, to be honest.
I just didn't go down that route.
You can easily switch kernels if you're
booting it off of a flash drive or something like that.
You're not actually installing it to disk.
So yeah, not really on that.
But if I tallied it up, that would be, what is it?
5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30.
So I'm looking at 30 points.
All right, 30 points.
All right, 30 points for cheese.
I'm going to write that down.
That's not bad cheese, especially
because Puppy Linux is a longtime contender.
All right, Mr. Payne, we move on to you.
And let's start with your free BSD.
What do you say, let's try to score free BSD
against the board, and then you just
tell us a little bit about your side fling there.
Yeah, all right.
Because I really, that's kind of what I'm most interested in.
But I am interested also in how free BSD is stacked up.
What was the experience?
You know, honestly, nice.
I always enjoy free BSD, but it had been a little bit
since I really tried to shape it into something.
And I thought, how lean is it?
I mean, I've always found it to be just well organized,
not necessarily aimed towards being lean.
But why not give it a shot?
It has some good, I mean, some very good base requirements,
minimum hardware requirements, 96 megs of RAM.
So that was a no brainer at passing a whole gig of RAM.
Yeah, there's a point.
I think when I just installed base, it was under a gig.
But with like everything necessary, it was about 2.5.
That was to get XFCE on the desktop.
Fair enough.
I think we all went over the one gig disk limit.
When we were sitting around dreaming up these requirements,
I think maybe we were being a little over nostalgic.
It's interesting to see.
And I mean, Colibri definitely gets there.
But you're right, at some point, the applications
that we want to use these days, regardless of even just the OS
part of it, there's a lot of dependencies
because we have a lot of expectations
about richly featured software.
You know, it's just funny because I don't know,
does anybody remember making like special DOS
or even Mac boot disk to play video games
where you'd have just a minimal OS and the game
all on one disk?
Oh, absolutely.
Yep.
What a time.
A simpler time.
FreeBSD Handbook is, of course, excellent.
So, you know, walked me basically through like,
all right, how do I get X up and going?
How do I install XFCE?
And then from there, I had it on Firefox.
So listening back to an episode of Linux Unplugged,
that was also pretty easy to do.
You really took the build it up from the ground approach.
And that means things like dark mode and whatnot
are themes that you just install from the package manager
or whatever.
And so in a way, it's sort of easy to get these points
because you built the system towards it.
However, I don't, and I'm totally open to Drew
and Cheez's interpretation to this.
I think it still qualifies because our listeners
could do that if they were so interested.
And it was all very, you know, I mean, the installer
was very helpful to get me started with what did I
want to get set up with.
And then the Handbook gave you lots of options.
It didn't say you had to, but you know,
just like if you want to go down the route
to a graphical interface, here you go.
So the initial install, it's all still in Curses?
Yeah. Wow.
But it's very efficient. You know, it was a pleasant experience.
Yeah. No, it is. All right.
So I think you're probably going to qualify for the one points
except for the one gigabyte hard drive.
But I don't think any of us are getting that.
So you might take that off your list if you have it.
But would you classify that as a pretty easy to install OS
if you were just generally fairly comfortable
using computers and whatnot?
Yeah, I think so. You know what it also had
that most operating systems don't.
Just an easy automatic ZFS installer option.
Oh, really?
So I went with UFS for this little test,
but I mean, it works really nicely.
Okay. I was going to say, I think our buddy Allen Jude
had a hand in that.
Right.
Okay. So let's get to the five point bonus round,
which is modern GTK theme, installing something
that's not in the repos,
which I'm really interested in that one.
And then obviously playing YouTube or Netflix,
booting to the desktop in 20 seconds
or any video game at all.
Did you have challenges with any of those?
Okay, so GTK theme, that was fine.
The Arc theme is in the ports tree,
so that was easy to get, which the ports tree is awesome.
Maybe second only to the AUR.
You know, honestly, configuring FreeBSD up
and getting it all running,
it does, Arch and FreeBSD seem like they are sort of
two sides of the same coin in some respects.
Obviously, there's a ton of philosophical differences
between them, but just from my end user experience of them,
and I like both of them.
I absolutely have felt that way too.
I am interested that you have had that same observation.
I think what happened is FreeBSD users just said,
you know what, I'm gonna go do this on Linux.
Right, exactly.
I really liked what I had, but I want this random piece
of hardware that Linux has support for to work,
so I guess I'll use their bastard kernel.
Okay, so what went less well?
I did get YouTube to work in Firefox, no Netflix.
Oh, yeah, yeah, that's okay.
If you get one of them, you still get the point.
Oh, okay, really?
Yeah, I'm not gonna let DRM hold us back.
I like it.
I feel like, you know, and Firefox is doing
a lot of the heavy lifting there, I suppose.
Feel free to push back, but I mean,
I think to make that work, we should have made Netflix
its own point item.
That's right, there's a slash in there.
Yeah, all right, how about that desktop boot time?
Just under the wire at 18 seconds.
Ha, spoiler alert, that's what mine was too.
Okay, what about any video game at all?
Super Tux Cart was in the ports tree,
so I gave that an install.
Classic.
Okay, now we get to the ten points.
Can you get VS Code going on FreeBSD?
VS Codium, yes, that is, I believe that's what's
in the ports tree, that's what I gave it an install,
that seemed to work.
I didn't edit anything really in it,
but it's the open source version.
So five points, I think, to you for that.
So adjust your accounting.
Oh, I did install some software, not in the repos,
because I didn't even check, I don't know why,
but I just downloaded RIPGrip, that handy,
super fast, Rust-implemented grip alternative
and so it gave the Rust stuff an install on FreeBSD
so I could compile it.
Huh, okay, that counts.
Does the kernel, so we have, this is a tough one.
I was gonna, yeah.
For ten points, we have install a different kernel,
but you kinda could choose your own kernel in a way, right?
I mean, I'm not super familiar with the way FreeBSD works,
but I assume you had some governance.
Well, and I mean, should I at least get half points
just because I'm using a non-Linux kernel for this one?
Yeah, I think maybe you could get five.
You guys okay with that, what do you think?
Yeah, sure.
Giving him points now, come on.
Well, no, I mean, we don't have to, but it seems like.
He's bringing BSD to a Linux challenge.
I mean, we could not.
I think Cheese is just butt-hurt because he scored so low.
Hey, don't you be hatin' on the woof-woof.
Hey, you brought the jalopy, bro, I'm sorry.
Okay, so, Wes, you're looking pretty good there.
Do you have a grand total for FreeBSD on our Linux podcast?
Oh, no, what have we done?
Forty.
Well, he beat Puppy.
That wasn't surprising that that was gonna happen.
So far, though, we got Drew in the lead at 47.
Yeah, well, we'll see.
I'm hoping to convince you all.
I didn't even bother doing the kernel
because I think I'm gonna win the Convince Your Co-Host round here
because Sparky Linux was something special that I came across.
I wasn't expecting to fall in love,
but I definitely have.
It's a Linux distribution that's on top of Debian.
And boy, do I now appreciate what that means.
When you're looking for a minimal Linux distro,
having a Debian base means you have access to everything.
And Sparky is a fast, lightweight, fully customizable OS
that has a couple of different versions
that I'll get into here in a moment.
But something else that I think,
as somebody who has used a distribution on and off
a couple of times, as a guy who has used Linux
every now and then for a couple of years,
one of the things I have learned is a active community
makes the difference between a living distribution
and a dead one.
Sparky Linux has a very healthy Linux community around it
and also very active developers who are laying out
near-term and long-term roadmaps.
This month, I mean, it's not a huge goal,
but this month, they are 210% funded by their community.
That's great. Wow.
This is something special here.
Sparky Linux is something really special.
And I think it's targeted at those of us
who have been around for a little while,
tried a couple of desktops, and we know what we like.
The main features of Sparky, obviously, is that it's Debian.
But it has two branches, stable and semi-rolling,
which is awesome.
And of course, I obviously went with semi-rolling.
Lightweight, fast, simple.
It has lots of desktops to choose from,
and it has a command line edition that has no X,
where you can just build up from the ground up.
Oh, fancy that.
Mm-hmm. This is the FreeBSD guy.
And I really like their three special editions
that they focus on.
So they have a Game Over edition, which is great.
I'll talk more about that in a minute.
They have a multimedia edition for audio and video.
They have a rescue edition for going in
and fixing broken Linux systems.
Oh, I called right out. That's handy.
Yeah. And a minimal command line edition,
which is really nice.
But I chose to go with the rolling LX cute version
of their distribution.
They also offer XFCE and MATE.
But I went LX cute.
And they also have a, I should add,
a minimal GUI version, which is Openbox.
Oh, nice.
Which I also checked out,
because I was really enjoying this distribution.
So I just kind of, I ate it all up.
I just tried out all the different spins
because it was so great.
But for my main testing, I focused on the LX cute version.
Now let's go down the points, because I got an issue
with the starting line, and I got to ask you guys about this.
So it technically fits within a system
within one gigabyte of RAM.
Okay.
With a major caveat.
How much swap are we talking?
Actually, by default, it does not have the swap enabled.
And when you only have one gig of RAM on a system
with no swap, let me tell you
about the careful dance you learned to take.
Yeah, I mean, I turned swap off on the systems I installed.
Yeah, I did not have swap, and it was something.
Firefox was really great until it wasn't, let me tell you.
I think you just got it treated as a single tab browser.
Yes, very much.
So the installer, I think it's a bug,
and that's why I think maybe we should allow this.
So it technically runs on systems
with one gigabyte of free RAM.
But when you boot a live environment...
Well, that takes some RAM.
And then you technically do not have a gigabyte of free RAM.
The installer does a check, is one gigabyte free, yes or no?
And when it's no, it puts up an error message
and does not allow you to continue.
However, if you go with the minimal GUI
or the minimal CLI version, and you do it on the same box,
and it doesn't do that check, or it does the check
and you're using so little RAM, it's okay, it continues.
And then you can use the system just fine.
Right, so if you, right, you can even boost the RAM,
install, and then shrink it down.
And it would work fine, I did exactly that test
for the gaming edition.
Yeah, I think you should get that point then.
So what did it idle around on RAM usage?
So good question, I did take a note of that.
Let me pull up my notes here, cheese.
You know, honestly, that just feels like experiences
I've had installing operating systems on Mac hardware
after they said, no, they won't support this.
But if you edit that P list...
Yes, yeah.
I don't know, I kind of take issue with this.
Okay.
If there's a bug in the installer
that causes you not to be able to install on one gig of RAM,
that is problematic.
However, there is a case to be said for the fact
that you were able to do it on another edition.
So I don't know, I could go either way.
That does seem like a savior right there.
Yeah, it's sort of a tricky one
because you could just do the CLI
and then apt-get install the desktop and you'd be fine.
Sounds like a half point to me.
Yeah, that's what I was thinking, half point.
But then I'm in like a 0.5 situation
because this is only a one pointer.
Yeah, half point, round up to one, give it to you.
All right, all right, okay.
So half a point, I'll take half a point
if you guys are okay with that.
I think that's fair because there is that issue.
So you'd have to, yeah, all right, I think it's fair.
So yeah, so cheese, you asked what was the base run rate?
Just with the LXQt version, which I checked the most,
with it just running and everything kind of like sitting
there for 10 minutes, I was using 398 megabytes of RAM.
Okay.
Not bad.
So I mean, you're still within that threshold of one gig,
right?
Here's what surprised me.
I mean, this is kind of horrible,
but also is not the end of the world.
I, spoiler alert, was able to install third party apps
because it's Debian-based.
Chrome, watching the SpaceX live stream,
750 megabytes of RAM usage, not horrible.
I mean, really close to my limit, right?
So I was able to launch a terminal and do htop.
So that was in that mix, but I don't have much room
for anything else, like another Chrome tab.
What was interesting about this is
Firefox ran really, really well in this one core
limited memory environment until it didn't.
And then it just drug my whole system down,
where Chrome was just consistently slow.
Interesting.
Yeah, I just thought that was one thing.
But just an aside here, guys, as somebody
who has been around and using the Linux desktop
since single core computers were a common thing,
holy crap is single core Linux painfully slow.
I did not fully appreciate or understand
how much my Linux desktop has taken advantage
of multi-core progress because it just
was like the boiling frog thing.
It just sort of happened slowly as the technology built out.
So did the desktop, and the developers
took advantage of it.
I know it sounds silly to say this, but back in my day,
there was a real push to try to convince developers
that multi-core development was worth their time.
I even attended an Intel event where
they tried to make a pitch to open source developers
that it was worth their effort to support multi-core
processors.
And they said that the days of CPU megahertz increasing
year after year were over.
This is an Intel event.
They fed us, they brought us in, they put up this video,
the whole thing about Moore's law and all that,
and they showed like a progression of the Pentium line
from the 286 to the 386 to the 486 to the Pentium
to the Pentium 2 to the Pentium 3 to the Pentium 4
and just this increase, increase, increase of megahertz
that was so impressive.
And you have to understand that for a period of time,
it was just assumed that this was just the law of computing,
that this megahertz increase was just
going to continue at infinitum until we were piling starships.
And Intel sat us all down and said, no, no, no, no.
We're kind of done with that.
The megahertz race is over.
We're going to have some gradual increments,
but what it's all about now is cores.
We're going to have multiple cores.
This is before they did like the core series and all of that.
There was a line of Intel processors
that I actually have in the machine here that
was before the core series, but still multi-core.
And it was right around this time.
And they were trying to make the case to developers
to go with multi-processing and multi-core development.
Yeah, right.
I mean, it is extra work.
You've got to sell them.
If you want to take advantage of the hardware that's
going to be out there in your customer's hands,
this is what you have to do.
Yeah, and so now from an end user's perspective,
I just didn't really appreciate how well the Linux desktop had
adapted to the multi-core CPU world
because it just sort of happened organically over time.
But by doing this challenge and going back in time
and limiting myself to one gigabyte of RAM
and one CPU core, even if it was like a 2.3 gigahertz CPU
core or whatever, is painfully slow.
It's striking how better it is now.
We really have it good.
Well, and I wonder how much of that
is due to you using LXQt because I did not have the same
experience under Openbox.
Everything was snappy and fast for me,
even with one core and one gig of RAM.
I wouldn't say that the desktop was necessarily slow.
It was just if I was installing software
and I was trying to watch the SpaceX video stream,
I definitely was waiting on stuff.
Like, I would click on a new tab,
and it would be a few beats before.
I mean, I was definitely I felt like I was pushing it.
There's also a question of what your backing store was.
I was running on an NVMe.
It's a WD Blue NVMe M.2 drive.
And that could play a big part of it too.
Also, I did have swap.
So yeah, I don't know.
Cheater.
I honestly, I felt like the one thing
that Sparky Linux was missing for me
after all the spins that they have
was this would be so perfect on the Raspberry Pi.
It would have been like the ideal desktop environment.
Because everything else in this list I had,
I had easy access to dark mode.
They just have it right there built in.
That was absolutely no problem.
VS Code, Chrome, fine.
That all worked.
Easy installation.
Yeah, the installer, the GUI installer,
it felt like maybe I'd done it 1,000 times.
It's obviously some installer I've used before.
I just don't know what it's called.
All that worked fine.
I played Extreme Tax Cart Racer flawlessly.
It worked just great.
And if you use their game mode, which
is really cool, it comes loaded with games,
but it also has Steam installed.
It has Steam installed?
Yeah, or it's that, you know, I actually didn't run it.
I just saw it on the menu.
So it's possible it is that script that just downloads
Steam and runs it.
But it's right there in the menu, already set to go.
They call it the Game Over Edition.
And it loads XFCE.
And it's great.
It is really fun.
And the gaming on it is just basically one click
to get things started.
I was really impressed with Sparky.
Their Openbox edition, also really well done.
But I think, ultimately, what I really liked about it
was the way the developers were communicating
with the community.
They have forum posts, which are, I mean,
they're even active today.
I checked it before the show, and there's
topics that are going today.
But they have forum posts about their next milestones
for the distribution and where they see it going.
They're very transparent about the development.
That's really neat.
They're basing it on Debian, which
means you have access to any deb file, so Chrome or VS code.
We're just a deb download away.
A bunch of really smart defaults, so things
that I like to use out of the box, like gdebi,
were already installed and ready to go.
It was simple to install Chrome.
The base installation is tiny.
It's not one gig, but it's just around just a little bit
over two gigs.
Yeah, OK.
And I like that it's a modern Debian, too.
Their, quote unquote, rolling is essentially Debian testing
or whatever.
Or SID, is that what it's called in Debian?
And because I'm old, I don't remember anymore.
It's called Bullseye.
And I think it's totally usable as a desktop.
Everything was simple.
Everything worked.
And the community had a lot of interesting discussions
going on about future directions.
And I felt like, at the end of it,
this is a distribution.
And I don't often say this.
This is something I'm going to keep using.
This is now my go-to clean Debian environment in a VM.
That does sound very minimal and just.
And because they're semi-rolling,
it's an apt update, apt get update, whatever.
Follow along with Debian.
And I'm essentially current.
And because it's so minimal, there's
not a lot that's going to break.
So I can leave this in a VM, park it for months at a time,
fire it back up, do an update upgrade, and I'm good to go.
Really, the only thing I didn't do
was bother installing a different kernel
because everything was working really great.
I think, really, when you look at it,
Sparky Linux is that thing we didn't really
know was possible anymore, is a new community based
around a Debian distro cropping up that really actually kind
of fills a few niches and isn't just barking into the wind.
A community has actually shown up
and is funding this thing at the tune that is,
I'm very happy to say, 210% of the monthly goal, right?
Like, there's a real response here.
Barking into the wind, was that a stab at puppy?
Also, what kind of boot time did you get?
18 seconds.
I got 18 seconds on that there boot time, which just barely
under it.
And I felt like maybe could have been a little better.
I tell you, there's that.
I felt like the boot time could have been slightly faster,
although I'll take it.
I would have loved to have seen the Arc theme installed
by default, obviously, in the repo.
Why not have it by default?
And boy, howdy, would I love an ARM version.
This would be such a solid candidate for a Pi 4 desktop.
Well, you know, Chris, I just looked,
and there actually is on, if you go to sparkylinux.org
slash tag slash Raspberry Pi, they actually
do have builds ready to go.
I think Chris should be minus points for not finding that.
I mean, I don't want to speak here for all of you,
but clearly this is a contender now
because the active community, the Debian rolling base,
or stable, whichever you prefer, the several editions
that scratch different itches, and an ARM edition.
How are you going to beat this in a lightweight distro, guys?
How are you going to beat that?
So I mean, that's why I'm going for that additional 10 points
of convincing your co-hosts.
I didn't even bother with the kernel
because I think if you just look at the facts here,
you add it all up, I have 39.5 points base.
But if you add that 10 point convince a co-host,
if any one of you agree with me that this is a solid
lightweight distro with a great community available
for multiple platforms and different types of uses,
then I get 10 additional points.
And that puts me at 49.5, which is ahead of Drew at 47.
I'm just putting that out there.
I think that your whole display there
was the convincing the co-host.
I think you started with convincing your co-hosts,
and then you went into the specs.
And let's not forget that Chris added the convincing
the co-host 10 point round today, today, hours ago.
Moments before the show.
Yes, that's true.
However, he looked at it.
He saw what I was posting in Slack and said,
oh my god, I'm going to lose this thing.
I need something.
Yep.
No, I just feel like, I just thought, you know what?
At the end of the day, you got to have
an inclusive understanding of a distribution.
It can't just be a by the numbers thing.
It's got to be about the community too.
And we needed a way to factor that.
And I thought if one of us could truly advocate because we
love something, we fell in love with it,
that should be worth something.
Well, let me just tell you, Calibri OS,
I added up the points for it.
Oh, shoot.
And it got 19.
Hold on, hold on, I forgot all about that.
If three of us vote that it's our favorite.
I got so obsessed with Winnie, and I completely
forgot to talk about that.
So give us your thoughts on Calibri OS.
Well, it's a small open source x86 only,
so I'm losing out there.
But hey, FreeBSD runs on all kinds of stuff.
It's forked off a Menuet OS, if you remember that.
And it's just coded completely in assembly.
And all right, if you thought what you were using
was a throwback, this thing is amazing.
Not only does it have primo floppy support,
it's got read-only NTFS, it can do ext2, 3, and 4.
But it comes with a whole bunch of games,
including Doom, let me just say.
And a ton of just handy from all this compile chain,
a lot of nice tools for doing development in assembly.
And then an IRC client that you can use to connect up to,
some other chat stuff, its own web browser.
Now, I wasn't able to play the MP3.
It does include an audio player, and sound does work.
But the web browser didn't want to.
I tried to download it, but our MP3s are hosted on HTTPS,
and I think that's what things went wrong.
Are you serious?
I didn't verify.
It did load the page, so like linuxunplugged.com loaded,
and it got to the download link,
but I tried to use the built-in.
Yeah, HTTPS is hard.
I think if I had done it and pulled up a terminal,
downloaded it that way, and I could have played it back
on the operating system.
Using like WGIT or something, curl or something.
It does have a bunch of Unix built-ins,
and it comes with a compiler tool chain,
so you can install stuff from an outside operating system,
and it boots wicked fast, so it should get extra points there.
I love this, because this is one of those OSs
that you didn't even know existed,
and now you just want to go check it out.
I just searched for this online,
and one of the things that came up was,
my mom tries it out.
But Wikipedia says, Wes,
that they haven't had a release for a year.
For a year, but hey, we were talking about XFCE,
so we all know that that's okay sometimes.
Fair enough, fair enough, fair enough.
You only need an i586 compatible CPU, so.
All right, so I think what we have here
is a bit of a standstill, and we need to bring in
our virtual lug to help us sort this out a little bit.
I know some of you have been listening along
and have your own considerations.
Jill, you've heard the arrangement.
I know that you've been around.
You've seen these distros.
What do you think is the winner here?
Who should get the Convince the Co-host 10 points?
Definitely Sparky Linux. I love it too.
And it's just so flexible.
Hey, really?
That was not planned. That was not planned.
Okay, Jill, please go into detail.
Checks in the mail, Jill.
It's a beautiful-looking desktop and minimal,
and you can run Steam games on it.
So for me, that was, that's huge.
And this is a really, really great challenge.
There's another distro that's kind of similar to Sparky
called AntiX, or Antics.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, and so that one was based on originally MeePis
with my group, the Linux Checks of Los Angeles.
We used that to install on old Pentium II
and Pentium III laptops that went to third world countries.
Oh, that's great.
And it's still running great on those machines,
and they're still actively updating it.
And it's a wonderful little Debian distro
that does all the things.
That is a bit of what we're talking about here.
And we get so caught up in vulnerabilities
about Intel CPUs and old machines
that are just discarded now.
But the reality is you can put a distribution
on these things, and if it's the right one,
that machine could run until the components fail,
which is a surprisingly long time.
At this rate, it seems to be long after the world ends.
Yeah, definitely.
And another suggestion I had,
and it's one of my favorite distros of all time,
is Tiny Core Linux, which was a spinoff
of damn small Linux.
And it actually runs on my thin clients,
my four megabytes of RAM thin clients.
Wow.
And it'll run in a DOS loopback, on ARM,
you know, on all the things.
Holy smokes. Wow. Yeah.
This wasn't an extensive list of tiny distributions
or like lightweight, but that's what we got.
And MiniMecha, I wanted to get your take
on which distribution here should be assigned
the Convince a Co-Host award.
The thing is, it looks like the Debian-based systems
seem to be the winner because they are really,
really flexible, and you can basically do whatever you want.
You can have a full-fledged system,
you can strict them down to the basics,
but you're really flexible with Flatpak,
Steam, everything you want.
I think that's the takeaway from this episode,
is when you do a lightweight, if you can afford it,
it does require a little bit more disk space,
but go Debian-based if you can,
because that just opens up so, so much more software.
It comes down now, I think, in my estimation,
to Bunsen Labs and Sparky, if we go by the points
and nobody assigns the Convince a Co-Host,
then I think Drew has it at 47, and I'm coming in at 39.5.
Cheese, you got 30 points. Wes, you got 40.
I'm quite compelled, especially by Jill's testimony here today,
about Sparky Linux.
I'll admit, as much as I really have had fun with FreeBSD.
Okay, I like what you're saying.
But I think you've had the pulpit for a while,
and Drew should get to go to bat, maybe,
for some of the community or other aspects around his show.
Yeah, I would like to hear more about the community around Bunsen.
That's actually the thing that's gonna make me say
that my vote actually will go to Sparky.
Oh, no way!
What?
How dare you?
As much as I love Bunsen Labs
and really enjoyed my time with Helium,
the pitch that you gave for the community around Sparky Linux
really makes me appreciate it.
It's not a distro that I had really checked out.
I'm not familiar with Sparky at all,
but I am curious, especially if the community is that driven.
Community is such an important part to me,
especially after everything that I went through
with all of the investigations that I did for Choose Linux.
Community is huge.
And if the Sparky community is that involved,
then it deserves my attention,
just hands down.
Now, I will say that between the two,
Bunsen Labs and Sparky,
do seem like they're on a fairly even playing field.
I think you would have clinched it
without any of the co-host points
if you had installed the kernel.
Yeah.
Because, running Debian,
you could have gotten Liquorix installed in five minutes.
You could have done it.
No, you're right. I should have.
I just, I thought going into it,
I was so impressed by how, because, skeptical Chris,
I went into it thinking, you know,
this must be one of those ego projects
where nobody's paying attention,
and boy, did I have that opinion corrected.
And so I was so, I was so impressed by that
because you just don't see it anymore.
And I really thought to myself,
this seems like something that will stick around for a while.
Okay, now with that all said,
does anyone in the mumble room want to chime in for Puppy?
Because I know we have some advocates in there.
Maybe we could do some convincing.
Cheese could use a solid 10 points
because right now he's at the bottom at 30.
That would bring him up at least two tie with Wes.
That depends on what kernel does Sparky come with.
Puppy comes with 4.7 out of the box
on the Bionic Pup version.
Four seven?
You know what you can say about that.
It's not three.
Mm, I can't even get that to boot on my system, man.
But, you know, I mean, something that we need to consider too,
right, is portability.
So if you wanted to just throw this on a flash drive
and say you had an old netbook kicking around,
it would be a great distro for that.
Dude, it doesn't matter if you can't boot it.
Okay, it's really coming down to it.
So Drew has thrown in behind Sparky Linux.
That adds 10 points to me.
Here's our current point lineup.
I'm in the lead at 49.5 points.
Drew has 47 points, Cheese has 30, Wes has 40.
Mr. Cheese Bacon, which distribution would you like
to consolidate behind?
I'm definitely gonna go with Bunsen.
Oh!
And a lot of the reason behind that
is because I was a huge Crunch Bang fan
and the community around Crunch Bang was awesome
back in the day and evolved into Bunsen.
And I'm a huge fan of Openbox because, look,
you got Openbox.
You are so fired, man.
You are so fired.
You got Openbox, you got Trayer, you got Tint2.
Everything is configurable by just a comp file.
So just restart X and you're back.
It's super easy, super extensible, modifiable.
But I think in the future that we need to add
to this points list.
We need to add community and we also need to add
documentation because there's a lot to be said
about both of those things and how well distros
implement those.
Very true.
Okay, all right.
I think that is completely fair for future versions
if we do this again, if we do the great bake-off.
I think we have to bring pies for the next bake-off also.
Ooh, I like that.
I'll just talk about it.
All right, okay, I need to brace myself.
Westpain, you currently sit at 40 points.
You're not gonna beat this thing.
So you gotta, I think, you just gotta throw in
behind a distribution.
Drew currently sits at 57 points in the lead.
I'm coming in the rear at 49.5.
I thought maybe you were making a good case for
getting behind the old Sparky, but I gotta admit
there's a good case for Bunsen too.
Westpain, where are you throwing your host endorsement?
Well, what I want to do is give it to CalibriOS
to get it to 29 points, so it's a little more respectable.
But, I mean, I think having listened to Jill
and just a ton of stuff I see over there on the IRC,
yeah, all right, I have to go with Sparky.
Oh, my goodness, are you serious right now?
Are you serious?
Is that your final answer there, Westpain?
That is my final support.
Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha, ha.
That barely puts me in the lead at 59.5.
I take the win there, just barely for Sparky Linux.
Not for me, but for the developers of Sparky Linux
who have worked so hard to make a great distribution
with a strong community following.
It is that community, not me, that put it over the edge here.
And I also want to thank my mom and my kids.
You know, I saw you booting it up a little, really.
It's only because it had a nice looking boot animation.
I saw that across the room and I was like,
ah, that's going to have to be.
And also, the dark mode is slick looking, isn't it?
Isn't that nice?
Yeah, they really nailed it.
Now, the only thing that kept us from being a blowout
was that you had a gambit to not do the alternate kernel
and instead rely solely on your last minute
addition of a points entry for convincing your co-host.
You know, the thing is, I am a natural salesman,
so I thought that could be a strength.
But also, I knew you guys, because you all
are long-term Linux users, you know that a strong community
is vital to make a distribution successful.
And I knew I'd get you on that point.
Dammit.
Ah.
If I was a co-host, I would have actually thrown it
towards Bunsen because it's actually
outlasted a distribution now.
That's fair.
You know, longevity does count.
And Cheese did, I think to Cheese's credit,
he did throw in his 10 points.
Drew, you really almost got it at 57.
And I think with the takeaway there is Bunsen or Sparky
is actually really great.
They're both worth giving a try after you listen to this episode.
And they both have great names.
There's that.
And the really thing to take away from it
is that they're Debian-based.
And that really seems to be the winning recipe.
And what a rich ecosystem has spawned from Debian, you know?
I mean, like, it itself is great,
and then you've just got this whole world
of other creative, interesting options that are useful.
Well, let's begin to wrap it up right here.
If you've got any show ideas or feedback or concerns,
considerations, or anything else,
go to linuxunplugged.com slash contact.
For links to the distributions we talked about and whatnot
today, you can go to linuxunplugged.com slash 357.
The show is at Linux Unplugged on Twitter.
The network is at Jupiter Signal.
Mr. Payne, where can they find you?
At Westpane.
How about that? That's easy.
Easy to remember.
Drew, Cheese, where can they find you guys?
I'm at DrewofDoom on Twitter, at Cheese Bacon.
God, I can't believe that, Cheese Bacon.
That's so good.
You know what, you could build an empire around that name.
All right, we are live on Tuesdays,
except for when I'm on the road.
That calendar is JupiterBroadcasting.com
slash calendar.
We appreciate you joining us live.
Thanks so much for tuning in to this week's episode
of the Unplugged program.
And we'll see you right back here next Tuesday.
So this whole challenge was flawed
because there was no Arch involved in this conversation.
And there was no Fedora either.
Yeah, Arch is the smallest.
Well, you know, we just kind of, we had a list of distributions
and we just tumbled them all up and assigned them.
It wasn't like a comprehensive, but you're right.
Something Arch-based would probably do very well.
And I could see something Fedora-based.
I don't think that is, I don't think that's a good idea.
Something Fedora-based, I don't think that is so much
as oversight as it is an opportunity for future content.
More backups.
Yep, yep.