This is Linux Unplugged, Episode 15, for November 19th, 2013.
Hi everyone and welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's applying
all its updates before we do our online banking every single week. My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
Hey Matt, welcome to Episode 15, buddy.
Thanks for having me.
Now, I might not be, um, I might not be giving the whole situation enough of its due, but
I felt like that line right there was all we needed to say about this whole mint canonical
controversy that erupted over the last couple of days.
No kidding.
You and I, here we go. We put out a nice Linux action show talking about OpenSUSE 13.1. Meanwhile,
the whole interwebs blows up because somebody three weeks ago on a mailing list said something
and then some other blog picks that up and then Slashdot picks it up and then it goes
crazy, Matt.
Well, it's almost like someone peed someone's Cheerios. I mean, really, it's like, come
on people.
That actually would have been more newsworthy.
It would have been, right.
That would have been a more interesting topic. Uh, so, you know, this week, this week, it's
interesting. I, every now and then I'm a bit of a slow man and it takes me a while to realize
that there's trends that happen in my inbox. We get lots of email from the Linux action
show and now this show as well. And a lot of new users that are looking to switch over
to Linux and trying to, trying to do their investigation, right? Trying to suss out the
situation before they move over, they'll tune into the Linux action show, watch our how
tos, watch, watch the news, just kind of get a feel for it, which totally makes sense because
if I was switching to Linux back in the day when podcasts, there weren't any podcasts
really. I mean, I think there was some podcasts, but there wasn't really any major Linux podcasts
and I would have totally loved that. So it totally makes sense. But what I, what I failed
to really notice is we've been getting a lot of emails about people switching from Windows
to Linux and for a lot of the reasons you might suspect, but there's a catch. The switching
is not going very well.
No, no. There's definitely some bumps in the road, some hurdles along the way and whatnot.
Yeah. And, and some people are, are, um, I think sometimes they're sold a bit of, a bit
of bag of goods as it were. And they're kind of told all switch one-to-one replacements
for your applications, stability, security, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. And then they
switch over and they're in, they ended up maybe a little disappointed or something doesn't
work the way they want. They end up in the end disenfranchised and they go back to their
Windows and they huddle down and they stay there even longer. And they say, well, I'll
just live it out. I'll just make it work over here on Windows. And so this week we're going
to pull in our mumble room. That's our online Linux users group. Matt and I are going to
kick around as long time Linux users and people who've, you know, run multiple OSs and helped
lots of people switch over to Linux.
Oh yeah.
I want to just, you know, we're just going to have a frank discussion about the legitimate
downsides. If you are a full fledged alternative operating system user and you're going to
move over to Linux, there's some things that might not go very smooth. And I don't feel
like there's enough places out there that are talking about that stuff, frankly.
That's true. Actually, you know, I think you nailed the nailed it on the head there because
I think the big piece of it with any distribution out there, especially the ones targeting newbies
because they're the worst offenders and that they have this great experience waiting for
people. But there's things that folks need to be aware of and it's not always attractive
from a visual standpoint or even from an experience standpoint to spend a lot of time talking
about it because then you're detracting from the value of that particular decision. And
that's where it gets funky for. And I can see where they're coming from, but still.
It is hard. It is hard. You know what? Essentially what you're saying is that sometimes it's
hard to talk about this kind of stuff.
It is.
Because, I don't know, you know, you got a little skin in the game.
I mean, we can talk about it, but at the same time, I think if I'm running, you know, Jim
Bob's, you know, virtual Linux thing or whatever it is and they're trying to switch to my distro,
I'm a little gun shy about saying, oh, hey, by the way, here's a list of things that might
stop you. That's a funky spot to be.
Well, and I'll be honest, I'm a Linux advocate, right? So I like talking about all of the
stuff Linux does really well, right? And all the stuff that's really cool in Linux. I don't
like to so much talk. I don't even like to focus on the stuff it does really bad. So
I've brought a third co-host to the show this week. His name is Woodinville Whiskey Bourbon.
And actually, I figured I picked up this bourbon whiskey from, you know, the alcohol store,
whatever you call it. And it is a local brew. Micro Barreled, they call it, Matt. Have you
ever heard of that?
Micro Barreled.
This is batch number eight and bottle 115 handwritten on the bottle too, I might add.
I mean, I lived in a state with drive through liquor stores once, but I've not experienced
a Micro Barreled.
So, wow.
I mean, you know, for when you're too drunk to get out of your car.
Yeah, right. Yeah. This is crafted entirely by hand in a small batches and aged to maturity
in a new charred American oak barrel. The demanding process results in extremely rich
and full bodied bourbon whiskey. So I'm going to be drinking that today to help bring out
the honesty. That'll be my, that's my honesty gateway this week.
That works. That works.
Still fighting through some of the tech issues we talked about last week on the show. I feel
like I actually haven't really solved any of them, but I've learned like the new way
to mitigate them to just create a new normal, which is a lot more work, takes about 45 minutes
more, which I've whittled down from two hours. It takes about 45 minutes per show. I'm going
to do some more work tonight. So there's not going to be a live side by tonight, but it'll
be on her, she's going to do a hangout on her Google Plus page if you search for Heather
on Google Plus.
So you know, still going through a lot of, a lot of troubleshooting there. Had some great
suggestions from folks that have heard of different solutions to try it on Linux. You
know, all of them I've heard of so far, but I still love getting those because you know,
if I could do, if I could do the bulk of this on Linux, man, even if I had to do a bunch
of work at this point, I'm already doing a whole bunch of work.
So exactly. There may be that eventual update to where, you know, blurb comes out and you're
like, oh hey, that wasn't there before.
You know what, they just released an update today. I haven't tried it obviously cause
I didn't want to mess with the show, but I'm going to install it tonight. So we'll see
how it goes.
All right. Well I wanted to, I wanted to get to some emails. We like to do the, we like
to do some followup emails that are sort of continuing threads that we've had in previous
shows here at the top of Unplugged. That way every show is, we're not like Star Trek here
on Unplugged and I love me some Star Trek, but Star Trek did the monster of the week
and that way they could syndicate. We don't have, we don't have those pressures here on
the Unplugged show. We like to do a continuing thread. So the Unplugged show is an evolving
storyline that takes place across a whole series of episodes. That way we make you listen
to all of them. And so going back a ways in our threads is OwnCloud. We talked about OwnCloud
a lot. Big OwnCloud fan. I don't actually have an OwnCloud installation in production
cause I'm kind of waiting for a few things to kind of work themselves out, waiting for
the next version. However, I know a lot of you out there have it and we also have the
JB Cloud that people are experimenting with. So Richard wrote in and this one was a little
bit of a warning to any of you running your OwnCloud installation on an SSD with Trim
enabled. He said, I had an existing home server running an established OwnCloud setup with
a laptop running an OwnCloud client on my SSD. I upgraded my home server to Mint 15,
reformatted my drives and did a full reinstall of everything including OwnCloud. No issues.
On my laptop client, I tried to reestablish the OwnCloud sync and push my files back up
to the server. It briefly showed a screen with two options, which I seem to remember
asking which way to sync. It defaulted to the one where the local files would push to
the server. The other option had a warning about data loss. Since I defaulted to the
right value, I clicked next. I sat back with a smile thinking that was easy until I got
a notification.
That's your first mistake right there is you sat back, you got all cocky, your big old
smile and you thought that was easy.
Pulled the staples right there. All right. Until I got a notification that it was unable
to delete a file that I was editing. What the F, he said. I quickly looked at my document
structure and it was gone. It synced my laptop to match the empty OwnCloud installation.
Even if I did pick the wrong option, would a are you sure you want to do this prompt
have been that hard? He's a little burned there. He said, I killed the power and booted
up on a live disk and proceeded to try to get the data back. I had all my favorite go
tos for the data recovery, such as test disk said it was unrecoverable. Then as I dug deeper
with Google's researching, undelete on extended for became clear. SSD with trim support means
deleted files are unrecoverable.
While this isn't a little side effect ever talked about and why isn't this ever talked
about in SSD conversations. I've never heard of this fact stated in last or text out discussions
with SSDs either. I would have have been a little more careful had I known this when
I switched to SSDs. I was using OwnCloud with its versioning as a backup strategy for
documents not safe for Dropbox, consulting documents, uh-huh, and accepted some short
term risk to rebuild the server knowing that I had another copy on the laptop. This is
exactly why the data must reside in three locations or else it doesn't exist. Two is
not enough. I had an older outdated backup on a Windows home server share, but about
two months of documents that were not safe to sync to Dropbox were lost. Please remind
users that switching SSD means you lose the option of data recovery undelete with them.
And you know, Richard, I've also heard the opposite side of that where because the way
an SSD can kind of randomize the way it writes to a file, to a disk, in some cases when you
try to do like an overwrite, sometimes it doesn't necessarily overwrite all the files.
So we're still kind of learning really some of the challenges of SSDs because not everybody
switched over yet. So they don't have the mass adoption that, you know, a spinning disk
does.
That's true.
But this is a hard thing because like you want to have the master authority generally
be the central server. That's generally how you avoid all these sync conflicts.
But at the same time, and this of course there's exceptions to this rule, large media files,
things like that obviously are in limit. But for the most part, you know, they were talking
about backing up in three locations. One of those three locations needs to be offsite,
whether that's physically in a physical drive in another location or in the cloud or whatever
you're comfortable with. But, you know, for something like this to happen, that's kind
of the whole thing of it.
As far as something like this happening, yeah, I think that we need more SSD action taking
place out there so we can kind of gauge what other little surprises are out there.
Yeah, and this is stuff we'll hit. You know, I'm pretty much all SSDs these days as I can.
And so I'll experiment more with this. You know, his point is well taken. And this is
why I've – so here's – we had an email this week. So Chris, you know, you talked
about your backups but you'd never really said what you've landed on.
And I really haven't landed on a good one except for anything that's important I store
in either BitTorrent Sync or directly on my Synology. Now, if I put it in BitTorrent Sync,
it syncs to my Synology. And then everything that's in this important data area on my
Synology NAS goes to Spyderoak. And that's how I'm doing my back – I'm not doing
like nightly backups on my laptop, right? I just don't – I don't have time. And
to be completely honest, setting up a new installation is kind of like playing a video
game for me. So, you know, if I got to set aside an evening and stay up super late and
have a few too many drinks to get my KDE configuration rocking, that's a sacrifice I'm willing
to take. So then it's just a matter of moving my data back in. And, you know, to his point,
you got to have multiple copies.
And I want to go back to one point in his email. Mint on a server, that's a bad time.
I can't even fathom that. I'm not sure I understand what the – what the advantage
would be.
I'm not sure either.
On the desktop, okay, arguably that's fine.
Maybe it's also a desktop?
Yeah, that could be.
Maybe it's doing dual duty or something? Because otherwise, go Ubuntu LTS, if you like
the Ubuntu underlying system, go Debian, go Cent, whatever. I like Mint, but, you know,
the inherent disadvantage that Mint's always going to have – and Lunteli changed this
– is you need to reinstall to go to the next version. And eventually, if you want
to get security updates, you're going to have to reinstall. And this is the problem
with reloading servers. You know, my approach to a server installation is I'm really hands
off as much as I can be. And that kind of plays into the whole stability thing.
But sorry to hear about that, Richard. I wanted to pass that along to folks out there. You
know, just be careful when you're doing that kind of stuff. It's –
And I agree with him, though, on the whole being prompted. I mean, I totally am on board
with that, that you should be prompted for something like that. I mean, it's kind of
a –
Yeah. I feel like the old cloud desktop program is still early days a little bit. And it just
doesn't have the deployment level that Dropbox does. So it – you know, things like that
just don't get quite as – identified as much, I guess. So yeah. Bummer, Richard.
All right. Well, next email comes in from Tim. And he's positive in the pragmatic dimension.
Pulling off of last week's title, he said, I hear you guys. I believe in support free
software. However, there is a lot in my life I have to get done and a lot of people who
depend on me and I will use whatever tools available to get it done.
And I remember last week we were saying, even as Linux advocates, we can understand how
sometimes there's reasons not to use Linux if an application you just got to have –
Right.
You got to have it. So he says, I'm beholden to Windows for work. Proprietary software
enterprise applications I have to access and use from home. Yet, I have a free NAS box,
an Ubuntu server, a Roku and a digital ocean droplet for a VPN as well as an Android tablet.
Not to mention a laptop with whatever distro I'm currently learning about. But again,
I have an iPhone from work and I use Windows for my sCrypt miners. It's an economic decision.
I could get better hash rates in plain and simple. And I've noticed this too, sCrypt
and also mining Bitcoin, it is much easier to get up and running under Windows. I actually
haven't noticed better hash rates under Windows, but it is easier to get running under
Windows.
He said, I may get bashed by free software proponents, but this is the world I live in
and I got to get it done every day. Cheers, Tim.
I think he's basically looking at this as there's effective behavior and then there's
ineffective behavior. And that really removes the argument of, well, you can't do it because
that's just not supporting blankety blank. At the end of the day, you have to decide
what's going to provide the most effective outcome that you're seeking. And for him,
that's what's working.
Yeah, I think so. I think so. We got an email about switching over to Linux and we got a
lot of these and one of them was quite long. And so I want to read his email to set us
up and kind of set the tone of the discussion because we've talked before about switching
to Linux from primarily Windows. I think maybe now we should start talking about switching
from Mac too, because I think there's more and more Macs out there. And I think a lot
of times the way we've kind of just come out and say, yeah, it's going to be great. It's
going to be awesome.
Sure. It's awesome. Yeah. Just load it up. You'll figure it out.
Yeah. Yeah. So we have an email as a great example of what somebody runs into when they
take that advice. So that'll be a good spot I think for us to kind of frame this conversation
plus or you just did a great piece over on Datamation about Linux desktop's missed opportunities.
So we might even just want to start there. So before we dig into that, I want to thank
our first sponsor this week and that my friends is Ting.com. Now Ting is mobile that makes
sense. My service provider and Matt's service provider for mobile. You can get started by
going to linux.ting.com. That'll take $25 off your first month of service or $25 off
your first device if you don't already have a device. Now, one of the things that really
makes Ting stand out is to pay for what you use system. And I want to talk about this
for a little bit. Actually, I'd say there's a few things that really make Ting stand out,
but the pay for what you use system is pretty unique. I don't really know anybody else that's
doing that. So they take your messages, your megabytes and your minutes, and they add it
all up at the end of the month, whatever bucket you fall into. That's all you got to pay.
It's pretty reasonable pricing. It's not like it's going to surprise you because they've
got a very active dashboard. This is where I want to change gears. This dashboard is
really something. So not only do you get a snapshot of where you're at, what your usage
is, what your bills have been, you can manage all of that. You can activate and deactivate
devices. You can manage your voicemail settings. You can manage your call forwarding settings.
You can manage what happens when you get X amount of calls. You can manage all of this
from the most intuitive dashboard I have ever seen to do any of this. And as a long-term
Ting customer, this is the kind of stuff that down the road, other than the amazing savings
you're going to get because each device is just $6 per month. Yeah, $6 per month for
a phone. That's it you guys. That's all you have to pay. And then you just pay for your
usage fairly on top of that. When you combine that with the awesome management of their
dashboard, it really has a long-term solution. It really is awesome. And if you go over to
Ting.com and you're kind of checking things out, you're not quite sure if it's going to
work for you, they have a savings calculator. You can get an idea of what kind of money
savings you're going to see. And if you're worried about your contract with your current
mobile provider, they also have an early termination relief program. Up to 75 bones per line. It's
super easy. You get your phone from Ting. You port your number to Ting. And then you
submit your early termination relief claim to Ting. Now the other great thing about Ting
is they are riding the wave of the investment the Sprint Network is making in LTE right
now. They are trying to roll out LTE. They are on a mad dash right now to roll LTE out
to all major nations, all major areas in the United States. So you're going to see a lot
more areas turn up. I happen to be particularly lucky and you might be as well. You can go
check out their coverage map on their website. I live in an area where I get great 3G. I
get great LTE and I also get awesome WiMAX. So I'm sort of benefiting from like all the
major available types of connectivity and that for me is great because I'm a heavy ways
user. So every moment I spend in the car I have a data connection. It's up. It's pulling
down information. The state troopers on our Interstate 5 here are absolutely maniacs.
I went up to the, seriously, I went up to the meat store today up in Arlington and four
or five cops on just that between three exits. Waze flags all that stuff for me. So Waze
is an absolute must. And I don't want to have to sit there and worry about am I going to
reach my two gigabyte cap or am I going to, you know, or if I, do I need to, do I need
to make a slightly less phone calls this month? That, all of that honestly feels like a scam.
It all feels like a scam to get my money when I'm just using the service the way I want
to use it and Ting just nukes all of it. They give you control and they give you the tools
to keep control and monitor all of it. Plus they have fantastic Android apps that really
work in concert with all of this stuff. If you're in a small business or if you're in
a family, that six dollars per line from the pooled minutes and you just pay for what you
use really works amazingly well. And then to top it all off, Ting has incredible support.
You can call them and somebody answers. You can go to their support forums. They've got
people there discussing stuff. You know, as they're working through the Nexus 5, there's
some awesome threads in there right now about getting Nexus 5 working on Ting. And to see
that just, not only just to see the community kind of take on that, but to see Ting embrace
it, right? Not to try to stamp it down, no, no, don't, don't try to port some unauthorized
device onto our network. Oh, no, they're not about that at all. They embrace the community.
They work with them. And by working with their community, they've come up to have a working
solution to get the Nexus 5 on Ting. You can go buy the Nexus 5 from the Google Play Store.
Like you should be able to just buy a computing device directly from the manufacturer and
you can put it on a network where you only pay for what you use and you're in no contract.
There's no early termination fee. That's exactly how it should be. We're finally starting to
see the smartphone market shape into the version of the future we want and we can all make
that happen. So go over to linux.ting.com, sign up, you'll get $25 off your first month
of service and I think you're going to be pretty happy. So a huge thanks to Ting for
sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
Thank you. That's awesome.
All right, Matt. So you wrote a good piece over at DataMation that said Linux desktops
missed opportunities. And you said if Windows users consider migrating, or this was the
sub headline I guess, does the Linux desktop offer a clear and easy choice? And one of
the areas you said, well, right now Linux definitely has a leg up and some people might
be surprised by this, but it hasn't a leg up on old peripherals.
This is something that's a misnomer with most people. You ask even experienced Linux people,
I've actually had some of them actually be misinformed on this, you know, what's the
hardware support look between Windows and Linux? With peripherals dating back to even
some modern ones, but especially with older ones.
Like scanners and printers?
Scanners and printers are the big ones. But even other stuff, Bluetooth dongles, certain
headsets, you'd be surprised. In certain, depending on the age, in certain instances
you will find that the support is crap under Windows. Even if you try and find a driver.
I remember when Windows 7 came out, it had been out for, I don't know, a year at the
time, and I was setting my mom up with her printer. Okay, I'll go get a driver for
it. HP has no reason to do a driver for that.
Oh, what a nightmare.
This is an old printer.
Yeah.
What a nightmare.
I mean, no, granted, I managed to hack it together, I think, with something later on
and then eventually switched her anyway over to Linux. But at the time it was just like
it was really appalling. Okay, same thing with Bluetooth. Try the Bluetooth dongle.
No love. Okay, maybe there's drivers for it. Nope, Bluetooth dongle is too old.
You know what, I found this is, this is kind of my enterprise background coming through,
but Ethernet adapters, which is such a linchpin because if you don't have network connectivity,
you can't get drivers for all the other stuff, right? And Linux, you know, because the stuff's
at the kernel level, man, you just, you plug it in and you turn it on and it just works.
And the experience there, if you really want to personify it, is you take a mouse on a
Windows box, it's never seen that mouse before, and you plug it in. And then you do that wait,
call it, and it goes out, it downloads the updates, it installs the driver. And then
the case, well, ironically, the worst offender are the actual Microsoft mouse and keyboard
where then they download an installer and a wizard you have to run through.
Is there some extra software you didn't ask for?
Right, and same with scanners, right? But on Linux, you plug it in and the software
detects it or it doesn't. It's very one or zero, right, for most basic users. And I think
this is a good point as Linux has sort of got a bad rap from the past because vendors
couldn't give a crap about supporting it, but that really has started to change. But
the other point you make for switchers is the security issues, right? Windows historically
and to this day remains massively targeted by hackers.
It's horrible.
Windows XP, obviously worst offender, and you look at the end of Windows XP, seems like
an opportunity to make a case here.
It's absolutely, and the big picture here is that, and of course Windows XP actually
ties into my peripheral argument earlier because a lot of people running XP are still running
those peripherals that were working with XP. So then you have the peripheral argument and
then on top of that, from the security standpoint, you had a Swiss cheese operating system that
now what little basic security you had is going to be yanked out from underneath you.
And people are going to run it blind. They have no idea. They have no clue. They don't
know that what they're running is essentially like riding a motorcycle down a bobsled track
in ice and snow. I mean, they have no idea. It's just incredibly dangerous and they don't
realize they're doing it because of the marketing problem.
Yeah. Yeah, you're right. And I recommend people go read Matt's piece here, but you
also made, and on this one, I kind of want to push on you a little bit here because you
say, well, you know, vendor lock-in is totally not a problem under Linux, but I wonder if
that really resonates with Windows users. I don't know if they recognize the fact they're
in vendor lock-in.
It's application specific. In most instances, it's maybe some random thing they created,
maybe let's say a greeting card maker or some random, you know, Podunk-y piece of software
they don't really think twice about.
Gosh, or yeah, like the holiday card maker. That's such a great example. That's totally
what I've seen happen too.
And it's the consumer stuff. It's usually some Podunk software consumer thing they bought
at Best Buy at one point or whatever it is. And they don't really think twice about it
until they go to, I don't know, maybe they're trying to upgrade to the next version of Windows
and they realize, okay, it's no longer compatible or there's even compatibility modes not working
for them or go to Windows 8 or whatever it may be. And then of course, going to Linux
though, it's not always a straight shot. I mean, there are tools that make it easier.
Scribus, for example, has worked on their publisher support, but it's not quite a hundred
percent yet. But it's one to watch and that helps. But that's the danger of vendor lock-in
even at a consumer level. It does exist. It's a problem.
So do you think there is an option here that average, you know, I'm thinking, you know,
the people that would want to make a greeting card software that want to buy that to make
a card, they put their kids on it and they send that out to the family as the family
holiday card. Do you think there is a solution for that type of user under Linux or is that
type of user going to be better served by the Mac?
If I was in PC repair still, first thing I'd do is I'd get up to an affiliate program to
want it for one of the cloud-based alternatives for that same program. And there's lots of
them. Then you're not only saying, oh, by the way, you know, your app is no longer compatible
with my upgrade, you know, they're upgrading them to Windows 8 or whatever it is, but you
can go this route. Same thing if you're moving into Linux.
Yeah, I think that's a huge part of the conversation we're about to have is like the cloud, I hate
calling it the cloud. I wish I could. Should we just call it the butt solutions? I don't
know what we should call it.
You can call it the butt solutions. I mean, I was in Best Buy here recently and I remember
some woman asking the Geek Squad person, I want to make sure I get the computer with
cloud.
Oh, no.
Not the cloud, but just cloud.
I want cloud. I want cloud.
I got to get some cloud.
Well, yeah.
This is the people you're dealing with.
Well, and look at Microsoft. Well, we've integrated SkyDrive into the Windows operating system.
That way you have cloud storage built in.
Because they get marketing. I mean, as much as I hate to say it, I'm not a fan of saying
that, but it's true, you know.
I look at this and I think this conversation, even two years ago, would be more like, yeah,
if you kind of want that, you kind of have to go to the Mac. But now we're looking at
a new generation, really, of web apps that do a lot. A great example is that greeting
card thing could probably completely be done on some greeting card maker's website. They
probably have an HTML5 or, God forbid, Flash-based wizard you run through, and then they just
submit it and print it right there.
So the cloud now offers a whole new set of apps, because it's itself an application.
Let's just call them web apps. We won't call them cloud apps. Web apps. They're web applications.
They run on an NGINX or Apache server. They have a SQL backend or something, right?
And so this sort of relieves some of that pressure. Now, as we talk about this, it brings
me to an email we got. And I really felt for this guy, because the subject was, please,
help me switch from Windows. And his name is Milan. And he says, hello, good people.
I've been watching you for a bit, about less than two years, and you're the only nudgers
I have helping me switch from the glory whose symbol is inspired by a carpenter's design.
Yes, I am struggling to switch to Linux, simply because of the non-existing Linux community
in my area. Out of laziness or comfort, one seems to want more and better. So here's my
frustrations.
Also, my parents have a lot of issues with Windows. Getting them on the Mint world would
never happen. But I've decided to get Mint with Cinnamon 2, as it seems to be stable.
I've settled on Mint 13 for now, Cinnamon Edition, eight months ago, on my old 80-gigabyte
hard drive. I used Matt's guide to do it. Big thank you, Matt. And it was a breeze.
The reasons I didn't use it now. So here's what happened. He ended up reinstalling Windows
7. That process removed the boot choice as an option when he booted up, so he could no
longer boot into Mint. Obviously, Windows overwrote the boot motor. Now I have a drive.
Now I have to dive inside the cable world and unplug my main hard drive to power up
Mint, and that annoys me. So I'm going to have Linux on its own machine all by itself
and be Windows-free.
Second problem I have. No power programs I like to use on Mint. Things like Photoshop,
Premiere. There's also a lack of audio players, such as Awesome or AMP. And yes, one can run
some of these things under Wine, but I do not see that as a viable option. Everyone
praises Clementine. I haven't tried it, but it seems fine. It just seems a little bloated.
I noticed a couple episodes ago that you set up a service for monitoring resources. He
says, I went and found a parallel. I can set that up, but he says, I don't like the way
it works. There's some things that lack compared to the commercial versions. He says, some
of these things seem like silly stuff, but you had a little quarrel a couple episodes
ago in the IRC on the same topic, and he says, I share your same point of view. Windows is
just too comfortable. Everything works for me in Windows. I spent a lot of resources
to get under people's skin. It's made us weak and comfortable seeking fools, thinking that
data security is an issue that is nonexistent and unimportant. He says, I'm also a bit fed
up with Google, mainly about mail safety, but also forcing the way it uses some of their
products onto us. So he says, here's the essentials I need in order for Linux to get
some traction. In a nutshell, I need Photoshop, Premiere, a good audio player, and system
resource monitoring, and a mail service.
So the long and short of this is right off the bat. The first mistake he's making is
this is someone who obviously is using computers in his professional life, and so a one-size-fits-all
tool is probably a bit naive. He probably does need to consider a multi-platform experience
because that sounds like he's got a lot of stuff. Music player thing, I definitely argue
with that. I think there's minimalist music players. You just got to spend a little time
at SourceForge or whatnot.
As far as the other part of it, I today actually had to do a multi-Skype thing for work, and
I plugged in my headset with Skype open, and boy, you betcha, it went ahead and just froze
the entire desktop for me because that's a feature. So I reboot with the device detected.
It sees the device, but I can't get any sound to happen. So this belief that one operating
system is somehow easier to use, honestly, I think it proves to me it's really what
you spend the most time in.
So because I spend so much time in Linux, I pull my hair out trying to do the most basic
stuff in Windows. I can't. I spend all my time in the device manager going, okay, no,
it's not working.
Yeah, I think you're right, too. So another email we got this week was somebody who tried
to switch to Linux and just was not happy with any CAD solutions.
And that's a fair point, actually.
I guess, too, part of me feels like you've got to do a little research before you make
the switch.
You would think, yeah. There are a number of program areas where-
Is that asking too much?
The research, no, but at the same time, the expectation has been set. See, Microsoft and
even to a certain extent Apple has made people complacent in whatever you do, don't think.
We're going to do, especially Apple, we're going to do the thinking for you and we're
going to-
But look at Windows, right? Windows is so popular that you're guaranteed to probably
find an application that'll do what you expect.
Just based on market share, it's a given. The market has spoken in that space.
Could be a shit app.
It could be completely crap. You have to be off some shareware site. But yeah, it's interesting.
I think with Linux, that's again, going back to what I was saying as far as Joe Bob's distro.
When they're promoting these distributions, they need a section that is painfully clear.
Your experience is going to be completely different than anything you've had before.
This is not a Windows experience.
Yeah. And I think you're kind of getting to-
Honestly, I think when it comes to that, Ubuntu does a great job. It says right up front,
this is not Windows. Do not expect it to be Windows.
I've yet to find that page.
It's in the download page.
Is it? Okay.
I've not experienced that because everybody I've ever talked to that frustrates with it,
it's like, well, I don't understand why it's little. And I think also that you're also,
even if it's a paragraph or even a whole page, you're expecting people to unlearn a lot of
that too. Again, Windows made people lazy and complacent.
I think it's not that Ubuntu is trying to say it's, we're not Windows. They're trying
to say we're OS X.
That was a slam. But yeah, no, I think Ubuntu does a good job, but I mean, their documentation
is a great example. Horribly, horribly out of date. I can point to example after example
of just, and again, it's all volunteers and I get that. I understand that. But compared
to say like large or some of these other distros, it's like, obviously it's not impossible.
Well Don Thornton Jr. in the chat room says, why switch? Why does it have to be all or
nothing?
That's what I was saying. There's different tools for different jobs. That's why I live
in a multi-platform universe.
Yeah. I mean, even here, I've got a couple of Macs. I don't have any Windows anymore,
but I did for a long time.
I've got to be honest on my end, my desktop, my main entertainment machine runs Windows,
but my laptop is 100% Linux.
Is that that Netflix?
That's how I started out actually back in the day.
My suggestion is to just use something like Mint that has already a good base of applications
installed and just use the IRC. Don't be afraid to ask questions in the IRC because, I mean,
the problem with the Ubuntu IRC is there's a ton of people in there and oftentimes I
want to see it squatted like after like two or three seconds and then Mint IRC is a little
bit more stable in that regard too. Plus they'll help you most of the time in there too.
But people don't know about IRC, right? I mean, see here's what we are going to be encountering
is the Steam generation. The Call of Duty players or whatever it's going to be who,
you know, I'm trying not to be stereotypical here, but let's just go worst case scenario.
Mom and Dad won't pay for a new version of Windows. I need Steam OS, so I load it on
a box. I have no idea what I'm getting into or I try out Ubuntu. I have no idea what I'm
getting into, but I know it can play Steam games. I know it can browse the web. So I'm
just going to jump whole hog into it because here's what I'm noticing, you guys, and this
is not, I'm not, I don't mean to like shame anybody who's emailed in because, you know,
because you emailed in, we have this topic, but a lot of, a lot of people don't even,
don't even look beyond their nose. They just jump, man. They just, they just, they have
a certain expectation of sort of appliance like functionality because their previous
operating system provided them appliance like functionality in a sense and they just switch
like whole hog like I got to open up an AutoCAD file tomorrow. I'm going to switch to Linux
today and they just do it and I, I feel like I want to, I want to, I want to put up a red
flag here and say if you're listening to our content and, and you think that's possible,
it is not. It is, you know, you are switching, you are switching to a different philosophy
of computing and one that I argue is better. It is worth that switch. It is worth that
effort, but it is a transition, my friends. It is. It'd be a good chunk of time to get
rid of my Windows partition, but I still have Windows programs I have to run, so I run them
in a virtual machine.
Yeah.
Another thought, you know, is this next couple of days, I'm actually going to play with open
SUSE 13.1 and try to get pipeline working on that and I might try to spend some full
time Linux experience on my desktop again for the first time in a while and see how
that runs.
That should be fun.
Chris, I think that, I think you're talking about awareness here, really. There's not
enough awareness of what Linux is all about and that's why some people, they fire up,
we always pick on Ubuntu because it's the easiest one to install or mint a variation,
although Debian soon. So, they fire it up and they think it's going to work out of the
box. It does, more or less, until you start installing proprietary drivers and there's
a kernel update, for example, and things like that.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah, that can be really tricky. You know, we were just talking on the pre-show
on the live stream about the need to sometimes update your kernel to get some piece of hardware
working correctly.
Well, not only that, but with new computers as well, there's a new hurdle that, you know,
with traditional BIOS, really wasn't that big of a deal as far as...
UEFI?
Yeah. I mean, you know, that new hurdle there is really, for us, it's like, okay, whatever,
you just find stuff in a different place.
No, you nailed it. People have been emailing in and they've been talking about it.
Every one of them is different.
Yeah, they've been talking about it. It's a problem.
You know, if I can bring something up about the codecs, on Windows and OS X, people expect
those codecs to be there out of the box these days. The idea of having to install codecs
is in the last decade.
It seems like a deficiency in the functionality of my desktop operating system to them. And
I think that's why a lot of them are going mint.
The old-school mindset is when someone buys a computer, it's an appliance, like a toaster.
And that is what they've been growing up in, when they actually switch the internals of
the toaster. Our system is dynamic. It's more dynamic.
Well, yeah.
Yeah, it's not static, like they bought, when they bought the appliance.
My biggest suggestion is you have to search about these things. Google is your best friend
in these situations.
What if we just said Linux is computing without the training wheels, and it's just not for
the absolute beginner user. It is, Linux is for somebody who is comfortable with Googling
things. Linux is for somebody who's comfortable with, you know, having to maybe set a few
settings that they wouldn't normally have to set under these up there. Is that really
that bad to say?
I wouldn't even agree with that, though.
I think yes, it does.
Because they're not too old of a dog to learn a new trick.
Well, I disagree, too.
I don't agree with that, just because, for example, my mom is a person who doesn't want
to learn how to do anything like that, and I have a neighbor who has no intention of
ever learning how to install anything. They don't even know what an EXE file is on Windows.
So what I would suggest is if there's people like that that you want to have try Linux,
don't just tell them to try Linux. Give them an out-of-the-box situation where you take
their computer, put everything up, set it exactly how they're going to use their computer,
and then let them go at it, and they will never have a problem.
Exactly.
I consider it's a little bit harder than that.
My wife is running Linux on her computer. It's an Arch install that I made for her,
because I know what she's going to use it for. I know that she's not going to tinker
around with it and muck it up at all. She's not even going to touch the command line.
She's just going to do word processing and web browsing for school. That's all she's
going to do.
So why Arch?
Why Arch? Because I can custom make it for her.
Because you're managing it.
But you have to manage it. You have to manage it for her.
But it's different, though, too, because you know that you can update it and never have
to worry about reinstalling. You're only doing those things if you're not trying to add five
different desktops doing stuff like that.
And that was the major motivating factor, to be honest.
Exactly.
For many people, their operating system is like a religion. You're not going to be able
to change their way of thought. There's some cases which cannot be fixed. They cannot change.
They're stuck.
It's true, because you're trying to retrain the brain. You're trying to retrain how people
think. And I go back to what I said about the Ubuntu page. I've looked back and forth
both on slash download and slash download slash desktop. You couldn't be, you know,
it says nothing.
Yeah, you almost wonder, you almost think like there should be a legal disclaimer warning.
Your Windows applications will not work under Ubuntu.
Honestly, it has a lot of great details here, but it's missing that core, hey, by the way,
we have a great operating system experience for you, but understand it's different.
Yeah.
Honestly, I think this is why this whole discussion is why Canonical is partnering up with these
manufacturers to push out computers in markets where people don't have that established bias.
Yeah, it doesn't look like it's in Africa.
And that's actually from Firefox OS.
Yeah, I actually have a great wallpaper for that, too. It's a little hitchhiker's guide,
a little robot thing, and it says, don't panic, it's not Windows.
Yeah, right, exactly.
All right, well, I tell you, you got to send that, like put it in the room or something.
I think Microsoft has built this regime where we have all learned to ride the bike, and
we all know to ride the bike, we pedal forwards, and we start moving forwards.
And for somebody to say, hold on, you can start pedaling with your arms, they're like,
no, that's not what Microsoft taught us to do. Do you see what I mean?
Not at all.
Well, no, I think it goes deeper than Microsoft. I think it goes deeper into how many people
will actually truly cook a meal versus do whatever is quick and easy. How many people
truly change their own oil versus go to the Quicky Lube. How many people truly go and
go to their own cow. So Microsoft catered to an audience of people that wanted that
anyway.
Yeah, I mean, the Windows environment is just as much of a sandbox as the Mac is. It's just
a way bigger sandbox. And to me...
It's becoming more closed and closed as it keeps going.
Oh, yeah. The advantages of the Windows desktop are diminishing, and the advantages of the
Linux desktop are increasing, especially as we get to HTML5-based applications, especially
as Qt comes around and we get a lot more cross-platform applications. As all of these things mature,
the advantage is that Linux inherently advantages from cross-platform development, from web
standards, from all of this stuff, and Windows inherently is disadvantaged by those things
because they take away the Windows advantage, right? They take away the monopoly.
So it's almost like this problem we are struggling with today, we are heading... I truly believe
we are heading... And I couldn't put a time and date on it. We are heading to a point
where just like Linux has completely dominated every area of computing, the desktop eventually,
like Steve Ballmer said, almost like a cancer, will be consumed by Linux because as these
top-tier vendors begin to focus on their new areas of revenue, mobile, they will recede
and they will offer less and less advantages to running on those platforms, and as Linux
will continue to just grow as it has, it will benefit from standardization, it will benefit
from all of these things that weaken these other guys, and it will become the dominant
desktop platform. I don't know what that's going to look like or what form factor it's
going to take place in, but I got to believe these problems we are talking about right
now, these are solvable problems, and I do not believe the problems that Windows faces
are solvable. I believe they are the eventual outcome of a maturing market.
Well, Windows is also killing Windows intentionally.
I think that people when changing from Windows because they don't like it or whatever the
reason, they have to know that in Linux, you don't use the same program as in Windows because
you don't have them, and you use alternatives like LibreOffice. You don't use Winamp, you
use WrittenBox or Clementine. You use different programs, and you need to know that before
you switch.
I guess I feel like we've always hung our hat on games are the barrier to desktop Linux,
and man, if we just had games, dude, if we just had games, people would be switching
to Linux, and now I feel like we're starting to get games and I'm realizing actually it's
more than that.
And another thing I kind of want to mention is the whole thing about the word Linux sometimes
being dirty in people's mind. You ever wonder, like back in 2010 when Canonical changed their
branding of Ubuntu, they started removing a lot of references to the word Linux.
Yeah, I mean, I think that's kind of understandable. Cars aren't manufactured as gasoline anymore.
This is a gasoline engine. Everybody just kind of assumes it's a gasoline engine.
Yeah, people think too that, Linus has said this before, people do not install OSes. They
just don't.
Right.
Yeah, that's right.
So, like, you're having Joe is not going to download like an ISO of the Bluetooth and
put it on a flash drive and install it. That's just not going to happen. It's got to be somebody
like us to show him that.
Or it's mobile.
I think that most people don't even know what is Linux. When my mom came to my room and
said, what's that Ubuntu thing? What's that?
Yeah, I think the Linux branding right now. So here's what it is. It's a deficient brand.
There isn't enough there to bank on it. Brands are like a commodity that could literally
be traded on the stock market. And they are so much amazing amount of value. You guys
don't even realize how manipulated you are by brands, but brands are everything. And
Linux right now doesn't have a super strong brand. Windows actually has the opposite problem.
It had a great brand. It had a very strong brand. Shit, you bought something because
it supported Windows or because Windows ran on that. And that's why you bought it. But
now it is a debt. It is a problem. Things that are in the marketplace do not succeed
when they are branded with Windows. So they have crossed that lexicon. They have moved
into a territory where Windows now is a problem.
The branding of Linux is not yet like, oh shit, that's Linux. Oh, I'm going to buy that.
But it could get there.
I think it suffers from a lot of old stereotypes where it was the, quote, hacker's OS where
you required more knowledge to use it.
You could have made that same argument. If you take it, so one of the things that I think
you can draw parallels to, to watch what happens in a compressed timeframe. The commercial
industry, in my opinion, operates in a much more compressed timeframe than the open source
organic evolved market, which is the Linux market. If you look at the Apple branding,
Apple was a joke in the late 90s. I don't know how old you guys are, but in the 90s
they were terrible.
It was awful.
Right? Yeah. Now they're almost like at a, you know, their brand is like the number one
brand in the world or some crap. Like they're competing with Coke. It's ridiculous, right?
And so you can see how you, as long as, I feel like the brand can cross from, I feel
like you can have a brand that people understand isn't there yet. And then down the road, they'll
acknowledge, okay, it's reached that point where it's refined enough that now it's good.
It's a good thing. And I know about this and it's good. Whereas a brand like windows can
also be, can, can travel that whole lifespan and then enter that period that it's in now.
I don't feel like Linux has crossed that. What's that?
I wonder, you know, how close we're going to achieve that when distributions like Ubuntu
would rather focus on the Ubuntu brand rather than saying, Oh, Hey, we're Linux.
But aren't you glad?
It will never be that brand. It will never be that brand because it's an, it's impossible
for the quiz. The people who own the brand of Linux and own the trademark won't do that
themselves and a company won't want to put money behind it to advertise someone else.
It doesn't make sense.
It is more empowering to the user. And in this case, the user could be the manufacturer
that they don't have to live on that brand that they can build their own. The fact that
Ubuntu can build a respected brand by using Linux makes Linux more important. Like I go
back to my gasoline comparison, like GM doesn't say this is the gasoline powered Chevy Volt
or whatever. Volt's probably a bad example. Chevy truck or whatever, right? They don't,
they don't advertise the fact that it's powered by gasoline. I mean, everybody just knows
it.
Well, I guess an electric car would have different advertising and branding. I mean, the same
thing goes for like Chrome OS or Android. You don't, it's more about the Android focus
or the Chrome OS focus and not so much on the Linux aspect, which I definitely understand.
Well, I kind of like to say like the Chevy Lithium.
Chevy Lithium is one. A big piece of what we've got to remember is what makes or breaks
a brand is the experience that they are selling and or otherwise offering. If they're selling
an experience that you want to participate in or emulate in some fashion, whether it
be Apple or whatever it may be, it's like, wow, I like what they're doing. I want to
do that or I want to try that or I want to experience that. That's what will make a brand
successful. Even if it's past, even if you're watching something.
When it comes to the business side of things or the Quicken or the, you know, it's always
the business apps.
And I think that's why Ubuntu focus on changing, I'm sorry. I think that's why Ubuntu focus
on changing their branding three, four years ago because rather than being Linux for human
beings, they were just Ubuntu.
Yeah, it is. That is a good point. And so I guess the way to kind of bring this back
to the switching conversation is people will be, people definitely, I mean, based on my
inbox. So here's the trend I've noticed when I started doing the Linux action show is Fedora
that people were finding because they were finding the link from Red Hat and then they
would follow that down to Fedora and then they would try out Fedora and then they'd
be burned.
And you would see it, you would see that reflected in my reviews. Like I'd be like, why the F
are they doing this? Don't they understand they're making, I mean, literally you go back
to my early Fedora reviews, I'd be like, don't they understand they're making the Linux community
look bad by shipping a volume app that doesn't actually change the volume. Like I, but now,
I would say the vast majority, the vast majority of emails are people that are trying Mint
or Ubuntu.
Yeah.
Mint or Ubuntu. What's interesting, it seems to be older versions of Mint too. I don't,
where's that coming from? Magazines? I don't know what that's about.
I found Ubuntu back in 2006. That was my first experience with Linux. And now when I use
Linux, I go right for OpenSUSE. So just because of the tools it offers.
I think this is part of the problem is like to understand what makes a successful long-term
viable desktop. And it's based on like, well, what do you need? For me, I want community
and I want modern software. So that's art, right? But for a lot of folks, it's, I want
to know this is going to be around forever. I want to, I want to know it's enticing to
commercial software creators. And in that definition, Fedora, Ubuntu and OpenSUSE fit
that definition a lot better. But how is a Windows user supposed to know that?
Exactly. And if you go back to early days of Lin Spire, Xandros and some of the other
guys, we've seen people try and take this concept without any disclaimer, disclosure
or what their people are getting into, put it into storefronts or in some cases, online
shopping. People will buy these machines not realizing what they're actually getting.
So they get it home and they say, great, I'm going to go ahead and install my, let's
say, you know, the greeting card maker software. They put the CD in the tray, they close the
tray, they go to install it, nothing happens. Okay, what's going on? Well, okay, I'm
going to, I got to get Microsoft Office on here. I got Microsoft this. Okay, that's
fine. Got my, I got my product key. I had to, you know, dig it out from under in the
drawer, got it, good to go, entered it in, nothing. And so it's like, okay, well, especially
with Xandros, which actually, believe it or not, for a while required a product key, which
was weird, but you know, which really sent a mixed message. But these guys, you know,
this was the early days. And what was worse is if you look back at the time, they were,
I won't use the brand names, but they were using very low end hardware. So you had a
double pronged sword of misinformation, really bad experience, a misunderstanding on OS and
bad to make it more confusing, at least under Xandros business edition, business edition
came bundled with crossover, which I like, I like crossover was fine, but they didn't
really explain what you'd put. If you put the office CD in your CD drive, like it would
auto mount it and it would actually start the office installation process like right
there. It's very confusing because like some applications, so what you got was some applications
automatically installed when I put in the disk and some don't do anything. I don't understand
what's going on, right?
And then you had Lenspire, which on the consumer side of it, automatically worked with DVDs,
encrypted or otherwise. It actually even went so far as to allow you to purchase weird stuff
like hang on to your hats kids, parental controls. We don't have that now, but we had that back
then and they did a really good job with it actually. And then of course you had a variety
of other tools, but even with all that stuff, because of the legacy concerns and questions
and things that people would have and no real support system, they didn't really understand
what they were getting into.
But I would say, I guess our tips to new switchers to kind of put a bow on this whole thing is
just spend some weekends, spend some late nights doing your research, find all of the
programs you think you would use for the stuff you need before you switch. So you know going
in what programs you're going to try, right?
I would also suggest dual booting.
Oh yeah, or virtualization.
USB.
Yeah, I would say USB is one. Dual booting at one time I was a big proponent of at one
time. I used to think it was great. These days I'm absolutely shaking my head, jumping
up and down no.
Yeah, with the UEFI it seems to be kind of hit and miss. One of the things I've been
noticing in the emails is UEFI sometimes people booting up their machines and they're just
getting different results even.
So who's to say a Microsoft update won't break something, you know, MBR wise? You don't know.
I mean you're putting a lot of trust in that.
Is when I dual boot, you know, I find one week I'll spend 90% of my time in one of us
and then put it together and feel alien so I go spend a week in that and then vice versa.
Absolutely a depressing conversation because a lot of times if you're willing to learn
and try something new Linux is a good option. If you're not willing to learn and try something
new you have to stay with Windows. It's unfortunate and sad.
Well Windows 7, which is the last good version of Windows, hear ye, this is the last version
of Windows that will ever be acceptable as far as I'm concerned.
It really wasn't terrible. To me Windows is actually going to die. Microsoft themselves
are going to kill Windows.
So you have time though. I mean they're not going to pull the plug on it next year. It's
got years of support left. So it's not like somebody can't find the time to try this stuff
out eventually. Buy a new machine, set up your new machine, so then see how it works.
And if it doesn't work with Linux then put Windows on it. You know there's a lot of different
ways to approach it. Virtualization, dual boot, whatever works for you.
Usually whatever they buy they're going to use. They don't care to change it. It comes
as it is.
I feel like if you're going to take this on yourself, wait until you're going to buy
a new computer. And when you buy that new computer put Linux on it. And just try it
like that for a little bit because then you have your old computer if something should
go wrong.
Here's what I don't like about the dual boot. The dual boot, the problem with that is you
immediately will reboot your computer after 30 seconds of not being able to do whatever
it is you know you could do within 10 seconds on the other operating system. So the problem
is that temptation to hit that restart button and now you've got an SSD so it's going to
reboot into Windows super fast. It's not like you've got to wait that long. You're going
to reboot back into Windows and you're just going to get the job done under Windows. And
the problem is lesson will never be learned. You'll never have learned how to do that.
If you have it on its own machine it's just that much more of a barrier where you're going
to stick with it and try it for a little bit and you know you've got plan B. You can go
over to the other computer if you can't get it working on that new computer. And I'm envisioning
like you've got a desktop for years and you buy a new laptop. Maybe you try that new laptop
with Linux and you keep Windows on that desktop for a month or two until you've decided you
can switch over right. I mean and other things like Dropbox and BitTorrent Sync by the way
make this a lot easier. Set up a synchronization between your two machines. Open the same files
on both machines and if you're working on a GIMP file and you just can't get it to work
the way you want after you've tried it enough go open up on Photoshop right and do it there.
But you can avoid the dual boot. There are solutions where you can avoid the dual boot
now. With UEFI I think it might be time to start considering at least for a little while
not doing the dual boot solution. And that Chris is kind of why I have a different machine
for different purposes and run a different OS on different machines. Yeah. Yeah totally.
Yeah I think you really nailed it there because I think at the end of the day I generally
recommend to people that if you have an older computer and you're wanting to try Linux and
you're going to buy a new computer anyway whatever your new computer is I generally
recommend using the operating system it comes with. If you're not sure get it with whatever
you're going to do whatever you're at. But with older computers you have a little more
flexibility in that you know the compatibility is going to be more likely especially with
people that tend to buy a brand new Windows machine and then they go I'm going to go put
Ubuntu on it and then five minutes later they're in the forums whining about how Ubuntu sucks
because it doesn't work with this thing that has a Microsoft sticker on it I might add.
So that's my pick. That's one of my pick describes. Well said. And also maybe a little bit is
be willing to be your own teacher like Bullet Freak is saying in the chat room is like we
are living in a time where information is so abundantly available to us it's kind of
ridiculous like to not take advantage of that is almost negligence on our part so be willing
to be your own teacher do the investigation that you need to do. So yeah I think that's
remember trying to learn stuff pre-internet. I was having this conversation with my nephew
earlier you know what we used to do. It's kind of fun when I you know in the enterprise
what we would do is about once every quarter we would a couple of guys a couple guys would
jump in the car and we could take a super long lunch and we go down to the most closest
Barnes and Noble and we would just buy a crap ton of books. We would just buy a bunch of
books right because we didn't have Google. We didn't have Google. I mean come on. I mean
maybe we had Alta Vista back then maybe but that sucked. Well that was a joke. Yeah. So
we bought books. Now you just Google. I mean everybody knows HotBot won right. I mean you
know. Yeah good times. I kind of miss some of that a little bit. I miss HotBot. I don't
know why. Maybe it's the logo. I don't know what it was. Yeah. All right. Well I want
to shift gears and kind of bring us into the end of this week's show but first I had an
email I wanted to get to and that was from No Need to Pronounce My Name Correctly. Hey that's
one I think I can get. I think I can manage that one. They just won the internet. What
do you think? You think I can. I think you nailed it. But before we do I want to talk
about our sponsor this week. Now Matt did you know that DigitalOcean is sponsoring
this week's episode of Linux Unplugged. Oh that's awesome. Yeah DigitalOcean is cloud
hosting made simple. Now cloud hosting like somebody like Ray Ramey and our audience pointed
out cloud hosting might not be the best way to put it. Think of it as hosting you completely
control on your own. It is a brand new way of getting your own server under 55 seconds
and pricing starts at just five dollars per month. DigitalOcean has data centers in New
York San Francisco and Amsterdam. Interface is super simple. It's intuitive with the control
panel. They call it intuitive. I would say the control panel is inspired. It is so easy
to deploy a new machine whether you want a lamp stack, you want something that supports
Docker or you want to go cray cray like I did and deploy a Linux machine you can. It's
all click click and you've got it. 55 seconds if you're slow. Here's what you can get in
under 55 seconds for only five dollars per month. 512 megabytes of RAM, 20 gigabytes
of SSD storage, one CPU and a terabyte of transfer. Now you might think oh SSD that's
interesting. You know what? It is interesting and when you combine it with their super fast
network speeds, oh boy does that sucker sing let me tell you. So here's what I want you
to do. Go over to DigitalOcean.com and use the promo code Linux13. That's going to get
you a ten dollar credit. Now if you buy their lower end machine for five bucks, their beginning
machine, that's the machine, I've been using it now. Five dollars a month when you combine
SSD storage with their crazy awesome network performance and the fact that Linux has amazing
memory management so 512 megs of RAM is plenty for what I'm using it for. I have been so
happy and I got the first two months for free because I used the code Linux13. They'll give
you a ten dollar credit. Five dollar machine means you get it for two months. They've also
got servers by the hour. If you want to toss up a machine, now here's what's great is they
have droplets and these can be the pre-configured droplets like I was talking about, LAMP, Docker
or you can make your own image like I've done of my Arch installation and then if I want
to test something and I don't want to spend a couple of hours setting up Arch, I just
deploy that image, I do an update and then I've got a fully current Arch machine with
all the installations I need and I can pay by the hour if I like. I think it's really
nice too because you can also resize on demand so if I want to really throw something at
it, I can add more memory, more CPU. I can get web console access if I don't want to
fire up SSH. You can also SSH into it later. You get backups, you get snapshots, you get
one click application installs. It is really awesome. Plus they have a 99.99 percent uptime
SLA. So go over to DigitalOcean.com and use the promo code LINUX13 and oh by the way DigitalOcean
offers a vast collection of tutorials for their community. Yeah, they're big on community.
You know I'm a fan of that too. Here's the great part though. If you want to contribute
to the articles that community has, you know reference stuff, if they decide something
they want to publish to the community, you can get $50 per published piece. That is awesome.
We'll have a link to that in the show notes too as well as a link to get this deal. Use
the promo code LINUX13 when you're checking out over at DigitalOcean. You're going to
love it. I've been using it for all kinds of things. It's a fixed cost so I know what
it's going to be every single month, not like some of the other stuff where it varies depending
on CPU and bandwidth and you get a surprise. It's got a great, amazing, awesome interface.
I get root access to my box and the performance is incredible and on the back end I love the
technology they're using. They're using Linux. They're using KVM. They're using industry
standard security technologies and I love it. So go over to DigitalOcean.com and use
the promo code LINUX13 to get a $10 credit on your account and thanks to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring Linux Unplugged. You know what's awesome about that? You got the promo. You
walk in, right? You get started essentially for free really and then by the time you're
done and you want to continue with it, it's like a Starbucks coffee. I mean that's crazy.
Yeah, it's no bigs, right? Right? Yeah, it's great. I love it. All right, no need to pronounce
my name sis. First off, thanks for lasting all the shows on Jupiter Broadcasting. I've
been an avid listener ever since installing Ubuntu 9.10 and experienced Linux for the
first time back then. Oh man, oh man, did I freaking fall in love. Now after all these
long years, I have been mainly staying in Ubuntu. In particular, 1204 LTS has been treating
me well. I'm not much worried about having the bleeding edge like an Arch, but with all
these news and all of these recent privacy issues in Ubuntu, I have thought about switching
to a different distro. I know Chris, you use Linux Mint. Actually, I use Arch these days,
but I do like Cinnamon quite a bit and it caught his eye as well. He said, I've used
Unity starting in 1204 and I'm looking at the next LTS release and I really feel like
maybe after looking at what their plans are for the next LTS, maybe I should try Linux
Mint. But at the same time, I kind of want to know how Manjaro works. It's rolling release
instead of LTS, so I kind of want to test it out. I know Matt likes Manjaro. I do. So
here's the long and short of it. I would say, is it as easy as Ubuntu? Not exactly.
It's close, but there's a couple of little snags that you might run into along the way.
The good news is that their forums probably have already covered it. So if you're willing
to check that out, you're probably fine. Like setting just little things. On the bonus
side of it, yeah, most of the stuff you expect to be set up like in Ubuntu will be set up
for you automatically and you want to fool with it. That is nice. If you're wanting
to actually step out a little further and try something a little more hands-on, you
can actually go full-on Arch with what we're using now, Integros. Integros has kind of
been a hit in the JB community. It has. Totally based on straight up Arch. So one of the things
I'm not totally sold on with Manjaro is their approach to stability is having a repo that
they just kind of held back for a little bit. But I do not believe, and I could be wrong
and maybe time will fix this, but I do not believe their testing base, it's not big enough
to really suss out problems. So what you really just get is delayed packages. Now that's a
bit of a, that's a, I'm sure Manjaro camp hates hearing that criticism, but the reality
is that's, that's how I see it. They're not Debian, right? They don't have a Debian deployed
base where they literally have thousands and thousands of people running the testing branch.
That is true. They probably have hundreds of people using the testing branch, maybe
500, who knows, right? Whereas with Integros, you stayed more married to the mainline Arch.
So when Arch pushes out that security fix, you get it right away.
But I would also point out that, and that's true, and you know, I definitely would agree
with that, but I would also say the difference between setup is, oh, there's no question
Manjaro is easier. I mean, it's, it's not, it's, oh yeah, it's not, it's not hard for
Integros just because I mean, I've done Arch. So for me doing Arch, it was no big deal.
I mean, Integros has a very Ubuntu like installation.
It's real, the install is fine, but as far as like getting some of the niceties set up,
first of all, if you don't know what Pac-Man is from Space Invaders and you're coming into
this, okay, then what are you doing? That, you know, the tool they provide is a little,
you know, you might want to actually, you'll either want to study up ahead of time and
learn what the hell it is, or if you go with, you go with Manjaro, they provide an app where
you don't really care.
Do you think maybe, do you think maybe he should go Mint?
Ah, you know, because he's kind of coming from a, you know, an Ubuntu Debian kind of
space and he's kind of doing the whole app scene, you know,
Elementary OS?
Yeah, I'd say probably Elementary OS over Mint. Mint is making me kind of nervous lately.
So Elementary OS is probably a good choice. Manjaro's cool if you want to try something
cool or new. And Tegros is awesome as well. But if you want something you can just slide
in directly, probably Elementary. Mint, I don't know. I just lately, they're just, not
because of all the other stuff that's been going on as far as the back and forth, but
more just from stability. I'm not really feeling it. I've always had, I've always had nothing
but problems getting it to work right.
Oh snap. You talking about Cinnamon?
Yeah, or no, not just Cinnamon, but just the later versions of Mint. It's like, there's
always some little thing that pops up that, yeah, I can work with it, but it's just kind
of like, look, if I want to work with it, I'll use a more advanced operating system.
He also asked, how would you compare rolling releases to LTS? And I would say apples and
oranges, right? So the LTS is you get all of your updates in one big go. And I mean,
one really big go, like you moved to a whole new OS. Whereas rolling is a lot of little
changes frequently.
Absolutely. And no matter what distro you choose to go with, first and foremost, say
it with me, a dedicated home. You'll thank me later because you will forget to back something
up and kick yourself. But by having dedicated home, your life's going to suck a whole lot
less.
Hey, hey, hey, hey, maybe we should be recommending OpenSUSE 13.1. It's got, it's never been
released, three years of support. It automatically recommends a home partition for software availability.
You've got software.opensuse.org. I mean, seriously, maybe this is an opportunity for
no need.
I think I agree.
Yeah, no need to pronounce my name correctly. Go check out OpenSUSE 13.1. I actually think
this is your perfect solution.
I think I'm going to agree with that because it's kind of a balance of both, the best of
both worlds. You can actually try something new and cool, but at the same time, it's really,
really easy to use.
Yeah. And Yast is a pleasure if you're not super comfortable with Linux.
You're going to discover things you didn't even know you could do.
Just go check out the one click installs for the software you need, and I think you'll
be pretty happy. And because they got three years support, I think that's just right.
For somebody who doesn't want something that changes that often, but you don't want to
get too stale, I think that's the sweet spot.
And you got your package access, which you got to love that.
And you got your sugar daddy who's keeping the project alive long term.
That's right.
So there's advantages there too.
Uh-huh. Uh-huh.
So very good.
Yes.
All right, Matt. Well, I think that'll bring us to the end of this week's Linux Unplugged.
Now you know, sir, of course, we love to get people's feedback.
Yes.
So they can go over to jubilabroadcasting.com. They can pop that contact link and then choose
Linux Unplugged or Linux Action Show. We'll take them both. Send that in to us and we'll
read it on the next week's show. And of course, we want you to join us live. You can go to
jblive.tv on a Tuesday afternoon. You can also join our mumble room if you go over there.
We put all the details in our live chat room over at jblive.tv or jblive.info. Timing for
that can be found over at jubilabroadcasting.com slash calendar. So you can go over there and
get it updated in your neck of the woods.
Well, Matt, I'll see you on Sunday for the big show, okay?
See you Sunday.
All right, everyone. Well, thank you so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged.
We'll see you right back here next week.