Well, first and foremost, it is great to have you back, Wes.
Thank you.
It is awesome to be back.
I missed the show while I was away.
We missed you.
And now you're like a well-traveled man.
I can be like, oh, yeah, my buddy Wes,
he goes to Bali for vacations.
Hey, you know it.
Yeah, you can increase your coolness factor.
Just latch right on.
You're always welcome.
Now, in your wild world travels, Wes,
have you ever seen anything as wild as a Commodore 64 running
Slack?
Oh, my.
No, I have not.
Brent found this and sent it to me during the week.
And he's like, you've got to see this.
This is Slack running on a Commodore 64.
And you've got to think, how is that even possible?
Well, a Raspberry Pi is involved with a little bit of Linux,
of course.
You see, the C64 has an extension port
called the, quote, user port, which via an adapter
can communicate over RS232 serial.
So this guy connected that user port to an RS232 serial USB
adapter connected to, well, a Raspberry Pi.
But the part that I like is the cable description.
This is the cable that he used.
And I think it's great.
It was an artisanal, locally sourced, homemade cable
with a user port connector on one end
and a USB TTL RS232 converter on the other.
He says the fastest he got this thing to communicate,
the fastest you could use Slack, was 1,200 baud,
or 150 bytes per second.
That should be enough for anyone.
This is Linux Unplugged, episode 257 for July 10, 2018.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk
show that, unbelievably, is already live again from Texas.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
Oh my gosh, it's good to have you back,
you world-traveling suave man, you.
Good to have you here.
It's amazing.
And I get back, and suddenly you're not here?
What is going on?
I know.
We're just two podcasters passing in the night.
As my plane is taking off, your plane is landing.
It's been like that since my first Texas trip.
Just kind of the way it worked out.
But I'm glad, after all that, we're back together again.
Someday we'll see each other again in the real world.
But we have the magic of technology,
so we're here anyway.
One day.
And that event may be barbecue that brings us together.
But coming up on this week's episode of the Unplugged
program, a great bunch of community news you can use,
including a really popular open source app that's
asking for your attention.
We have a couple of Firefox fast takes
that you probably need to know about.
And then we'll get into the Ubuntu corner.
A couple of new announcements coming out of the Ubuntu
project, as well as some things around them.
And then holy crap.
Holy crap.
Wine is so old, but like in an awesome way.
Now it's also going to get cheaper car insurance.
We'll tell you about some new milestones for wine
and some big changes that are coming to the project.
New architectures, et cetera.
And then, later on in the show, we now
have the results from the recent Gentoo hack.
We know what happened.
We know what went wrong.
They've posted an entire postmortem.
And it's in-depth.
It's detailed.
And I think it's educational.
So we'll cover that.
We'll describe what happened.
And then maybe talk about the bigger picture
about Linux distributions maintaining infrastructure.
Now, I will admit I may have some sysadmin bias
in this particular segment.
But I'm really looking forward to hearing everyone's thoughts.
Like our mumble room, let's bring them in.
Time appropriate greetings, virtual lug.
What's up?
Hello.
And you may have noticed in that,
I don't know what you call that, those series of voices there,
there is one Mr. Brent in there.
Brent is joining us via the mumble room this week.
Brent, so glad to have you here as well.
Hey, it's great to be with both of you this week.
Absolutely.
Yeah, all of us need to get together in the studio.
How fun would that be?
The three of us in studio doing a show, eating some barbecue.
I'm salivating already.
Yeah.
This needs to happen, doesn't it?
Didn't that happen already?
Wasn't that the first experience on the show for me?
That's why we know it needs to happen again, Brent.
We know it works.
Obviously.
Every single week it should happen, I think.
That'd be great.
Yeah, we'll just get this huge budget,
and we'll just fly you out every single week for the show,
like some sort of high end radio show or something.
You know, I could stay for more than a week.
There you go.
Now you're thinking, yeah, we could just set you up
a little room in the studio.
I've got the space.
Decent connection, decent Wi-Fi, all the things you need.
I did sleep in the studio last time, if you remember.
That's right.
Yeah, that's how our barbecues go.
And if you're lucky, a little Levi comes and snuggles
with you.
Man, I tell you what.
That is the hardest part about traveling is that dog.
I miss that dog already.
All right, well, let's get into the community news
that you can use.
Let's start with KDN Live's significant refactoring
that they're doing that they're asking for testing.
I feel like this is a really big deal because this,
at least in my view, is open source's most
potential Final Cut killer.
Let's put it that way.
It's really coming along.
And they've added a couple of new features
that I think are really handy, including
proper slow motion video support, massive improvements
to their timeline, the ability to automatically separate
clips that have both video and audio tracks, which
is very handy when you're trying to remove what we have is
what we call is scratch audio on the camera.
So you record scratch audio on the camera, and then you
record the actual source audio using a professional microphone
going into a professional recorder.
And it's really handy to be able to just drop
the audio from the video, separate it out,
and then get rid of your scratch audio.
So that's coming in there now.
Support for generating lower resolution video
in the timeline preview, which means
it makes it easier to work with something like 4K
video on a machine that maybe can't render 4K in real time.
They're changing the layout of the keyboard.
Yeah, and it's a lot of stuff.
And just a bunch of other enhancements.
So it's available now as an app image
if you want to help them test it.
And they're trying to get the word out there.
They've been contacting a few media outlets
and saying, hey, can you spread the word
that we need people to test this?
We really need people to test this.
Time to bring back the video version of Last Then,
isn't it?
Just kidding.
You know what's funny is when I saw this story,
I'm like, oh, that's so nice.
I'm glad that this is really improving.
And there was a version of me that
would have been almost hyperventilating with excitement.
But since we've spun down some of the video stuff,
I've really taken a break from video editing.
It's been easier on my body.
My RSI issues have started to clear up a little bit.
And it's just.
You've been less depressed, happier,
and maybe if you're lucky, by the time
you come back around and are doing video again,
Linux will be the best of the lot.
I would be amazing because it sure is for audio production.
I tell you what, it really is.
And that's the thing about where I'm at with audio production
is I enjoy it.
I like it.
I feel good about it on Linux.
I want to do it on Linux.
I don't have to force myself to do the audio production
stuff on Linux.
I want to do it on Linux because it's, in my opinion, the best.
It's just actually a good tool set.
Yes.
And so that's where I would love to see video get to.
And part of what's really helped me switch my workflow over
is also at the same time switching my workflow
on the desktop over to the Plasma desktop.
And so I've been following the desktop's developments
pretty closely.
And there's some new features that
are coming to future versions of Dolphin
that I think are really slick, especially
if you're a Telegram user.
And it's built around this new framework called Purpose.
And it's got its own dedicated blog post.
I'll try to put a link in the show notes
if you guys want to know more about it.
But the idea is it's an extensible framework
to fulfill the developer's purpose
while providing abstraction.
Yeah, I know.
Right now, they really don't have much going on other
than this new Share menu that's coming to Dolphin.
And if you've been following the weekly usability posts,
there has been some talk about this new Share menu.
When you right click on a file, it
does a lot like you would expect to do, say, on a mobile device.
You can share it to KDE Connect.
You could share it to a Bluetooth device.
And they're collapsing some of the stuff that's
in the menu into this new Share menu.
But you could also do things like Telegram
because the system will detect what applications you
have installed, or like Nextcloud, another example,
or maybe Imgur or Twitter.
There's a lot of extensions you could put in there.
And then you can right click on a file.
There'll be a built-in Share menu, built-in Plasma.
Anything that uses that framework can get access to it.
So soon, on your Linux desktop, if you're
using the Plasma desktop, you could right
click on the document, select Telegram,
then choose the contact, just like you
do on your mobile device.
And right now, it's in development.
And they just put up a blog post answering
some of the questions about, like, what
about adding more clutter?
Or what about accidentally sharing a file and all
of that kind of stuff?
He has answered all of those questions.
And it's worth calling out, if nothing other than to talk
about the rapid improvement that we're
seeing on the Plasma desktop, even though there's recently
been some complaints about communication
between developers and the visual design group.
Actual Plasma itself is progressing extremely fast.
And we've really now entered a flip-flop situation
where, generally, GNOME is considered the slower, heavier,
more less stable, I'll put it nicely, desktop.
And Plasma has become the fast, lean, efficient desktop
that has all these new things coming to it.
I feel like they've flip-flopped in a bit.
And you really see that the Plasma desktop is moving
forward fast with some of these new features.
The Share menu is great.
And I recommend reading the link in the show notes
if you're curious about the implementation.
It's one of these small things that really, I think,
draws a contrast between Plasma and Gnome Shell.
Files over the years has gotten simpler.
For better or for worse, it's gotten simpler and simpler.
Whereas Dolphin has managed to get simpler by default
but more powerful when you need it.
And that is the balance that I find myself to prefer.
They do seem to sometimes err on the side of features,
but they get back to that usability balance over time.
I love this kind of stuff and this kind of communication.
That's part of it, Wes, like this clear communication
about this is why the project is doing this,
this is how it's going to work, it's coming down the road,
prepare yourself.
I love that kind of stuff.
I think that's huge.
And it really seems like Plasma team
has done a lot of slower efforts over the years
that we're now seeing with solid foundations laid
with some clear purpose, if I can say that.
They can iterate fast, they can change things,
and as long as they communicate clearly,
we're not left in the dark.
So we don't have to speculate, oh,
which feature is going to disappear next?
What horrible thing are they going to add?
They've thought about it.
It's clear that they're thinking about a wide range of users.
So you and I might love all these features.
But as you say, there's tons of ways
to disable it if you're never going to use it.
And it doesn't add a whole bunch of clutter for everyone.
Yeah, it's interesting that they're
including the option to disable it.
Like, oh, you don't ever just want this at all to show up?
All right, you can just turn it off.
Instead of just, no, it's baked in now.
You can just use it.
I do think I have gotten really used to doing that on Android,
you know, just be able to send it right to an app
and have that all work after I've installed it.
So I will be using this in Telegram probably from day one.
Yeah, Telegram, Slack, Imgur too.
I mean, how handy would it be to quick screenshot,
right click, upload to Imgur, although you can actually
do it within Plasma's screenshot tool.
But the whole point, right, is that maybe you
started a new image hosting platform.
You're not as popular as Imgur, and this can work for you too.
Yeah, that is very nice.
So let's talk about the AUR for a moment.
We've recently had stories about a crypto miner
that made it into the Snap store.
We also talked about some crypto miners
that made it onto Docker Hub for quite a while.
It was really pretty embarrassing.
And now, almost as if we could just check them off a list,
we now have a story about the Arch Linux AUR repository
containing malware.
Don't panic.
It's already been resolved, and it's already been cleaned up.
But it is interesting.
It seems to be a trend we see.
Now, the thing about the Arch user repository
is from the very beginning, they warn you
that it is user-submitted software,
that you should double check all of it.
And when you follow the Arch guide,
like the first time you're getting started with Arch,
they have you build things from the AUR by hand.
So that way, you learn how the package build files work.
You can see what URLs it's calling, things like that.
So in Arch's defense, they do warn the user
as much as possible.
But I'm surprised this almost hasn't happened before.
There's been a full investigation now
that shows that a malicious user with the nickname Xactor
modified, on June 7, an orphan package that
didn't have an active maintainer, something called
AcroRead, hmm, Acrobat, I don't know, never heard of it.
The changes included a curl script
that downloads and runs a script from a remote site.
It then installs persistent software
and configures systemd to start it up from time to time.
I love it when systemd is involved.
Now, there was two packages total that were modified.
They were both modified by the same person.
And the investigation reveals that the executed scripts were
just doing data harvesting about your machine, your machine ID,
the output of uname a, the CPU information, the PacMan
output of information, and the output of systemctl list units.
The harvested information was then
transferred to a pastebin document.
And the AUR team discovered that the scripts contained
a private API key, which shows this was probably
done by an inexperienced hacker, because you can track that down
to somebody.
But the purpose of gathering that system information
remains unknown.
Just doing like a system scan, you know?
Isn't that funny?
And using systemd, too, to make sure it starts.
I really do kind of wonder what, well, I mean,
systemd is just so reliable, Chris.
That's a natural choice.
It does definitely seem like sort of inexperienced
in that if you wanted to do damage,
you could do a lot more damage.
You could also probably get more sensitive information
if that's also what you wanted.
So it is kind of peculiar.
And you're also right that we all use helpers, or at least
most of us, but to the AUR's credit,
package builds are actually pretty simple.
And so if you do have the time, especially if you don't use
that much AUR software, it's pretty reasonable to go look
at least before installing something.
Just go scan the package build.
It's pretty easy to see, does this
point to the real Git sources?
Does this point to an HTTPS website hosted
by the organization that maintains this project?
That will help a lot.
Yeah, especially for the system you're putting in production.
I think there's a definite room for improvement around GPG key
handling, though.
So I can't remember what the package was,
but sometimes you see these pinned comments
at the top of the AUR that say, oh, just copy paste this key
into your key ring, and it will be fine.
Yeah.
That's a great point, Alex.
There is some room for improvement there, isn't there?
It was caught pretty quickly, it seems, and taken care of,
and a full investigation was done.
So on the other end of this, it's pretty well handled.
What are your thoughts on it, Brent?
Well, I have to say I'm a relatively new AUR user,
so it's amazing.
I call myself relatively new, but there's
a surprising number of packages I'm pulling from there.
But I was taught very early on in the process
from some forums and things like that,
that actually you should really look at the package builds.
And they're super simple, I've been looking at them.
And I did catch actually something
last week that was a little bit curious to me,
and so it just allows you to do a little bit of extra homework.
And in this case, it was my lack of maybe technical knowledge,
and it allowed me to learn a little bit more
about how it all worked.
But I really think that's essential for everyone
to be extra cautious, let's put it.
Yeah, really, the rule of thumb is
if it's user-submitted software, well, really, hell.
I mean, even the stuff that's, quote unquote,
curated by Fortune 500 companies or whatever they are,
it still has crap in it, so it's tricky.
But definitely more caution is needed
when it's a user-curated or user-submitted, quote unquote,
app store.
Yeah, it's a good reminder.
Yeah.
All right, let's do a couple of Firefox fast takes,
just a couple of little things to know about.
Firefox for Android is entering a maintenance phase
as the team is preparing to completely replace it.
So if you're a user of Firefox and Android,
which I have been for a little bit,
it's entered a maintenance phase,
meaning that they're not going to give
any updates for the foreseeable future except for major bug
fixes and security updates will still come down.
That's according to Emily Kager, the mobile engineer at Mozilla.
It sounds like Mozilla is working
on an entirely new browser based on open source
components in Android.
And Android components, quote, is the actual name of it,
is a collection of Android libraries
that can be used to build browsers or browser-like
applications.
Something tells me they're probably not going
to be using Gecko, though, they'll probably
be using the Chromium backend stuff in WebKit.
What do you think, Wes?
Is that a bit of a loss to have another?
I mean, this has kind of been the way
it's been going for Firefox and mobile for a long time,
though, so I suppose not.
I suppose it's not really much of a loss.
I mean, in a historical sense, it might be.
I get that.
I mean, Gecko's been rendering my things
for so long now on a number of platforms.
But it does seem like this is also maybe a sign of them
taking Android as more of a primary platform.
I think so many people use Chrome or other browsers there.
I, too, have been using Firefox and Android,
and honestly, I really like it.
It's one of my favorite mobile browsers,
and if they can make something even better,
even more tightly integrated and focused on that platform,
I'm excited to see it.
Yeah, you know, I started using it
to sync bookmarks and passwords, but for iOS users,
there seems to be another solution.
And I think they just launched this.
You found this, Wes.
It's the Firefox Lockbox.
And this is the password management component
of Firefox broken out as a standalone mobile application.
The idea, I would assume, the use case idea
is you have all of your websites and passwords saved
on Firefox on your desktop.
And then you go to your mobile device,
and you don't have access to any of them.
So Lockbox gives you access to those passwords.
It uses their back-end sync.
It's 256-bit encrypted, it says.
And you sync down your usernames and passwords
using this Lockbox app.
And I was talking with Wes about this,
and I was like, Wes, what do you think the use case is
for this, which is when you point out for people
using it on their desktop.
And I remembered that Noah used to do this.
I don't know if you recall, but he used to use Firefox
as his primary password manager for a long time.
Yeah, he was looking at us kind of funny.
He was like, what are you guys doing?
My browser has all my passwords.
It's already right there.
I think he was sort of eventually had
to replace it with a Homeworld solution,
just in part because mobile.
So Lockbox is only for iOS today,
and they just launched it today.
They may be rolling out an Android version soon.
But it's kind of interesting to see where all this is going.
And then one last Firefox fact for you.
A little fast take here.
There is a big update for you Ubuntu users running Firefox.
Firefox 61 is now available today,
as we're recording, in the repo.
Now, that's a nice update.
And it's even available for you LTS users, I believe.
So go out there and get your upgraded Firefox.
So you'll get Firefox 61, which includes several new features.
And it's nice to see that the LTS is
getting the latest versions.
It is actually really nice, because the latest versions
are great.
Now, if you do want to stay a little more up to date,
I will say just downloading the tarball of Firefox
and sticking it somewhere in your home
here and adding that to your path also works very nicely.
Yeah, that is a good way to do it, isn't it?
Yeah, that's what I do on most of my platforms.
And no failures yet.
I kind of stopped getting all worried about the version
after Quantum shipped.
Then I kind of was like, OK, well,
I got the major version once I got to 60.
But it'd be nice to get to 61.
It's good to see.
All right, well, if that's the Firefox fast takes,
is what I was calling them.
You like that?
Fast takes, Firefox fast takes.
It's so fast now, right?
Quantum fast.
Yeah, exactly.
You got it.
Let's do the Ubuntu corner.
Speaking of Ubuntu, they launched this week
the minimal Ubuntu, which is not the same thing
as the minimal install or the server install.
It's minimal Ubuntu.
I don't understand why you're confused on what
the problem is.
But the idea is pretty slick.
It's a small footprint of Ubuntu that's
meant for fast virtual machine provisioning.
So imagine an AWS infrastructure that
has to spin up 1,000 instances at once.
You think I'm exaggerating.
I'm not.
They really, really care about the spin up time.
I heard this from an AWS engineer directly.
They are constantly pushing back on Canonical and Red Hat
to shave down the boot time.
Because you multiply that by 1,000 in some cases.
And so if you can shave down the boot time
and shave down the image size, it really matters.
It might not matter for us on our laptops,
but it really matters for really large cloud deployments.
And that's exactly what these are for.
This is really Ubuntu designed to be
deployed by machines, not humans.
So think of it in that context.
Yeah, exactly.
I'm really excited for this.
Just because for many cases, Ubuntu server is great,
but it's still kind of stuck in the era of bare metal servers.
I remember the argument when system B came out
and everyone was like, well, why do we
need servers to start fast?
You start it once and you reboot it, maybe never.
But in the days of clouds and functions
as a service and all the different sorts of containerized
options we have today, you're starting stopping
immutable deployments.
Everything moves very quickly.
And if you can get this down in an image everywhere,
it really scales.
Plus, I don't know about you, but when I'm making images
for other people to use, I want to customize that.
And I want to start with as lean a base as possible.
I don't have to go in and remove or disable services
that I don't need or no one knows what they do.
This just starts as a super lean core,
add on everything you want, do some customization,
make a new AMI, and you're good to go.
Yeah, especially in the context of quote, unquote,
serverless computing.
Serverless computing, it just means
they're taking care of the server.
They're standing up an entire Linux instance
and then tearing it down once the processing's done.
They need that to be fast.
But Brent, you're pointing out there's
other aspects besides the speed of the boot
when you minimize like this.
There's other advantages.
Yeah, I had, I guess, kind of a little bit of a question.
There's a section there that says minimal security
cross-section comes with this minimal Ubuntu.
And I just wondered if anybody from the community
or maybe Wes has any thoughts on that.
Yeah, well, less attack surface means
it's by default less likely to get exploited.
Now, it's still something you attach to the network, right?
It's still running a full Linux stack.
I mean, it is Ubuntu.
You can install any package you want on it.
I think that's it right there.
It's not some magic layer of security.
It's just that when you install the default Ubuntu server,
there are a lot of things which are super handy
and make it really easy for users
to get started with that are just enabled by default, right?
So the Snap service is running.
LXD might be running.
But if you don't use those things, you don't need it.
And unfortunately, not everyone, even some sysadmins,
know enough to go how to go prune that,
how to disable the services, how to check for those things.
So if you can just start from a really clean minimal base,
it's better for everyone.
There's some real numbers here, too.
They say that the images are less than 50%
of the size of a standard Ubuntu server image.
And they boot up to 40% faster than standard Ubuntu.
But that doesn't mean they're necessarily the fastest.
Does it, 10-bit?
No, I was checking for Onyx.
And Michael did some tests.
And Clear Linux was the big winner.
Minimal Ubuntu is definitely better.
But Clear Linux was still four times.
That's a great point.
There's still other.
Many people are still going to run Docker containers
with Alpine.
Or if you have particular needs, there are a lot.
What I think Ubuntu makes a special impact here
is that you still get all of the comfort of using Ubuntu
like you do on any other platform.
All the things are there.
You can still install devs that you need to.
It'll just work.
Whatever happened to unikennels?
Do you remember them?
Yeah, that's a good question.
I haven't heard as.
I mean, they're interesting.
I haven't heard very much.
There's been less buzz these past two years.
I don't know if that's just because serverless and Lambda,
et cetera, have taken over that space.
Or maybe it's just incubating in the background.
Now, Badger, weren't you thinking
that maybe Atomic from Fedora makes this a bit less relevant?
Yeah, I think so startup time is one thing.
And I guess I hadn't really thought about the scale
Amazon run at.
I go around to a lot of different customer sites.
And I see people with 400, 500 EC2 instances in just
their test environment alone.
It's pretty crazy.
And you multiply that across all the different companies
across the world.
The scale that Amazon are running at is mind boggling.
But then for me, I think if you look at an Atomic OS
has a read-only file system.
And so there's a lot less tinkering
needs to actually occur.
So you can almost basically boot from a known state.
And it's kind of like how Apple deal with hardware.
So they know exactly what's under the hood.
So they don't have to do a whole bunch of checks
like a PC BIOS would or something.
So it's that similar sort of principle.
Yeah, yeah, just if you don't have
to worry about the drive changing at all,
you could launch as fast as you can
initialize the hardware support you can launch.
That's right, yeah.
Yeah, that is a good point.
I feel like the broader context for this, too, is containers.
Because this isn't just for spinning up VMs.
It's also for spinning up an Ubuntu inside it
a container so you can start with something minimal
and build your container environment around it, I think.
There's other solutions for that,
but I feel like this would be a pretty good one.
And because it's just an app getaway,
you can get anything else loaded in there that you need,
which is really convenient.
Yeah, I think you hit it on the head right there, right?
Like that you don't, it may not be the best
if you have particular needs, then maybe look elsewhere.
But if you were just already using Ubuntu,
it got a little bit better today.
Yeah.
Now they just got to work on the branding
because there's too many minimals at this point.
And you know, it's tough when you have an OS that
runs on IoT devices, it runs on cloud devices,
it runs on laptops and desktops, and now apparently
on floating AIs that will go up into space.
Ubuntu is also running on an astronaut AI.
It's called Simon, C-I-M-O-N, and Joey has a great write up
over at OMG Ubuntu all about it.
And it's one of six experiments.
It was recently launched to the International Space Station
as part of the ESA's International Space Station
program, the Horizon Mission.
It's not science fiction though.
It is an autonomous AI powered assistant
that can see, hear, and understand and speak
with the astronauts.
And it's got a touch screen on it.
When you minimize the Simon application,
there is an Ubuntu desktop.
It's just like right there.
And you can open up files and browse the file system
on this floating robot.
And it's really cool.
It's about the size of a beach ball with one side of it
flat that has an LCD screen and a somewhat freaky face,
I'll be honest.
And I just love the concept of this.
There's so many things they can use it for.
As we go out deep into space, it's
much easier to send robots than it is humans.
But the other thing you have to consider
is this isn't something that's going
to turn on your smart lights.
This can be very, very purpose built
to know very, very deep knowledge
about the particular experiments they're working on.
It's not going to answer when Walmart down the road opens up.
It's not going to know that.
But if you need to know the molecular structure
of this rock, it's going to know that in and out
and be able to display that on the screen.
If you think about how useful having a smart home with data
about your house or about your car is,
you take that to the next level here, wow.
You're right about the face, though.
The face is creepy.
And I'm just imagining a Hal-style moment there.
And the face, you know, the smile turns into a frown.
And oh, Podbe Dois, whoops.
Yeah.
Yeah, uh-oh, yeah, it gets angry all of a sudden.
All right, well, here is one of the scientists
who's been working on it, explaining how
this works better than I can.
My name is Till Eisenberg.
I'm from Friedrichshafen, the project manager
of the project Simon.
Simon weighs about five kilograms
and has a diameter of 32 centimeters.
He has a velocity of about one meter per second,
which is rather slow.
But it's quite comparable with the normal movement
of a crew member.
He's equipped with a display of eight inches, which
was chosen because this gives the ability
to display a complete face.
Simon stands for Crew Interactive Mobile Companion.
And it's meant to be a social interactive free-flying object
who shall assist the crew during extensive tasks
and to reduce stress.
Simon will assist Alexander Guest during his next mission.
He will assist him during two different tasks.
So we will be able to provide him
with the good advices during complex procedures,
as well as assist him in social interaction
or by social interaction, and will provide additional data
to the science group, like video data,
or during complex tasks to validate the exact process.
They go on, too, to talk about how
if they're working somewhere where
they have decent connectivity, they're
going to still use offloaded cloud processing to help
with Simon's intelligence.
And when they're somewhere where they don't have connectivity,
which I guess there is connectivity in parts of space,
but when they're somewhere where they don't have connectivity,
it can work offline.
The majority, though, right now, of the AI work
is taking place on IBM's Watson Cloud Service.
And the language comprehension is being done by that,
although they're working on some local language processing,
but they don't talk about what technology
they're using for that.
And they say the earthly link may
seem antiquated by comparison, but it has its upsides.
He can download new software, and they can improve things
in batch processing.
So he can come up with solutions like offload it to the cloud.
It'll chew on it, and then they'll
send it back to him, depending on the bandwidth.
And then he can give the results to the astronauts
working at the station.
I know this is early days, but I will be very curious to see,
after six months or a year, or however
long this project runs, how useful is it?
Do they get real benefits?
Because if so, I assume this will
be the first of a long line of AI assistants in space.
Yeah, the first AI assistant in space is pretty, pretty neat.
Let's bring it down to Earth, though,
and talk a moment about the Gnome desktop.
A lot of love these days from us for plasma.
But things over in the Gnome camp
are slowly but surely getting better.
A lad on Twitter tweeted that we could look forward
to some serious performance improvements
and included a picture of a slide
from Gwadek, which just wrapped up the Gnome conference.
And there was a lot of talk about improving
the performance in Gnome.
And in the slide, too, I noticed they specifically
call out those jerks at Canonical
for all the good work they're doing to actually help
get really deep into the performance issue and solve it.
So it looks like the kumbaya of Canonical and Gnome
continues because they give them a particular call out
of thanks in this slide.
And it seems that we may see even more performance
improvement announcements soon coming from the Gnome project
because they're touting them at Gwadek this year, which
I am very happy to see.
So don't become a plasma user just yet, Wes.
Yeah, I know, right?
I think this is also just another good case of a bunch
who is used in so many ways.
And I think it's pretty easy.
The way I use Gnome, I don't care as much
about the performance for 90% of them
because I have a web browser, and I have a terminal,
and maybe I'm developing something,
and the rest doesn't matter too much.
But let's say you're a video editing professional using
Ubuntu on your powerful workstation.
Suddenly, that matters a lot.
So I think the focus of end user deliverables
that Ubuntu can bring is just going
to keep these improvements coming.
Well, I look forward to it.
And it's a whole group effort now.
There's so many major distributions
that are shipping Gnome that hopefully we
will start to see some.
That's what we've all been hoping,
is that when everybody kind of focuses on it, not everybody,
but when so many desktops focus on it,
maybe we'll get real results.
That might be what we're seeing now.
And it's a whole group effort, but it's
really great to see Canonical sticking with it.
Now, I got to tell you, we had a story
that I decided not to include, but now I kind of
wish we did because it was about setting up
enterprise-grade Wi-Fi.
Holy smokes.
If anybody out there has solutions for like home,
what am I looking for here?
Not like a DDWRT solution, but what
is the latest in Linux solutions for Wi-Fi?
This isn't a question for the audience.
What is the latest in firmware replacement on a router device
or even better, ones you build with like a PC or something?
I'd love to know.
I've been living in Wi-Fi hell for about three days.
Things are looking better now.
I was so worried today because I'm down here at Linux Academy.
And today was the first of several, I think,
five live streams they're doing to announce
all this new content that they're launching in July.
And I got here on Saturday, had a nice chill morning,
got in here around 9 AM Sunday morning,
started setting up for Linux Action News.
And I pretty quickly discovered that I was dropping packets.
And it was really hard for Joe to even understand
a word I was saying.
I mean, harder than normal, right?
Not just because you're mispronouncing things.
Yes, exactly.
I didn't know what it was.
Was it Wi-Fi?
Was it something on the network?
You know, on a Sunday, 9 AM, 10 AM, I'm the only one here.
So it's not like it's somebody torrenting stuff.
Nobody's here.
Most of the machines aren't even here.
Most of them are laptops.
So I started going through all of these old school
troubleshooting processes that I used to go through.
Can I ping the router?
Am I dropping packets here?
Am I dropping packets when I go here?
Can I do all these trace paths and all that kind of stuff?
Started running around with a dongle and a spool of ethernet,
trying different jacks to see if anything was live.
But the folks here at Linux Academy, about a year ago,
refurbed the building a bit.
And at that time, they deployed what's called, like,
a common generic term, enterprise-grade Wi-Fi,
as if there's some committee that reviews and measures Wi-Fi
to determine if it's enterprise-grade or not,
stamps it, like the USDA-grade beef.
I assume it's one of those things where that's
what the vendor says, and you pay enough for it
that that's the title you get.
Yeah.
I think that's exactly what it is.
Everybody you pay said it's enterprise-grade,
so therefore it is enterprise-grade.
I mean, that's what you tell the boss, right?
And they're like, oh, yeah, good work, IT.
Yeah, and that is true.
I tell you, that is so true.
And I'm sitting here going, well, Wi-Fi is still Wi-Fi,
and I'm doing VoIP.
And any kind of disruption really
messes with the VoIP call.
And so we did a bunch of troubleshooting.
Stefan, their network engineer, he helped me out, too.
At least I assume he's their network engineer,
because the man really knows his stuff.
And we actually still haven't tracked it down.
I don't know exactly what it is, and of course,
I'm the only jerk that's having an issue,
because I'm the only jerk trying to do
a live, high-quality, high-bitrate VoIP call.
Everybody else is browsing the web, doing email,
and they're all on Wi-Fi, because they're just
on laptops.
And most laptops that they buy now
don't even have ethernet ports.
So everybody's on Wi-Fi.
The Wi-Fi network's just got all of these machines on it.
So I'm like, no, I want to go ethernet.
Did you see the post on Ars Technica over the weekend
about Wi-Fi?
Is that what you're talking about?
Yes, yes, that's the one.
I thought it was a great read.
It's like six pages long and doesn't
have a huge amount of detail.
Well, it has some detail, but yeah, I've
used ubiquity gear at home for the last two or three years,
and it's been genuinely pretty flawless.
You just set it and forget it, which is exactly what you want
from Wi-Fi.
And they have PS Sense on the front end.
That's great.
See, I think that's what they have here, but not the PS
Sense on the monitor at all.
But Stephanie's coming out.
He's going to bring a spool.
We're going to wire me in a jack,
because there's no jacks that are hot,
because everything's on enterprise ethernet,
or Wi-Fi ethernet.
You still can't beat a cable, can you?
No, no.
But ironically, the solution was, really,
the only solution was I had to get outside the network.
It's a particular challenge, too,
because normally when I come down,
when I go places to do the shows, I always take the RV.
And I've done it so many times, and it's kind of expensive.
So I was starting to really question
the practicalness of that.
Really, do I need to take an RV, a 40-foot-long RV,
every time I go somewhere?
That is too much.
It is way more efficient to fly down there and just
do the shows from one of the recording booths for a week,
or more, maybe.
Potentially, actually, two weeks.
So whatever I could fit in my backpack
is what I brought with me.
And then everything else got ordered from Amazon
by Linux Academy.
And all of the gear that Wes and I use and Noah
use in our mobile setups, they pre-bought and had it
here for me.
I get everything all hooked up, got all my gear,
same exact software setup, same software
I used on the last trip with my XPS 13.
Really, I thought I had it all dialed in,
and I started having these issues.
And I start thinking, you know, if I was in the RV,
I would have three cellular networks.
I would have three laptops I could switch between.
I have Wi-Fi I could connect to.
And plus, I have a booster on the top of my RV
that can pick up Wi-Fi signals from two miles away.
It's insane.
It has this little tiny device that
is just this incredible booster.
So there's a lot of flexibility.
Plus, I can move, and I can just go somewhere else
that has better connectivity.
That has saved your butts a number of times.
Yeah, and so this trip, I'm like, oh, boy.
So what can I do?
Because I don't have the RV.
I don't have any other equipment with me.
And I need to get outside the network.
So I went and I got a MiFi.
I went and got a MiFi.
I might return it within 14 days.
But you know, it's another device
with another payment and all that kind of stuff.
But it was what you have to do to do the show.
And so now, it seems to be holding up mostly.
Do you guys not have tethering over there?
Because over here, I just switched my phone
into a hotspot, and off I go.
Yeah, the issue is the room I'm in,
which is in the center of a very large building,
and then it's a thick wall with sound insulation.
And so the only thing that gets signal in here is Verizon.
So I had to get a Verizon MiFi.
Otherwise, I would just use my, that's what I've done before,
is I just turn on tethering on my Nexus.
But that's the way it goes sometimes.
Maybe can we buy like a second one of those boosters
and just sort of strap it to your back.
You can walk around with that at all times.
Dude, a podcasting backpack.
Yeah, right?
Right?
Yeah, and just put like a Linux box in there.
So that way, we can say it runs Linux.
Yeah, a little nook sitting at the bottom.
It'll be perfect.
Then you're going to look like the guys in Silicon Valley
walking around the convention and trying to hack everyone.
Oh, yeah.
Oh, I already do.
I have been out on the street, and it's
like if I'm with a couple of people,
this has happened a few times.
I think it's even happened when I've been around you, Wes.
People will stop and go, hey, what are you guys doing?
What's going on?
Is there a computer convention?
Is there some sort of computer convention in town?
Yeah, exactly.
But you just get enough of us in one room,
and I guess it is a computer convention.
I guess we just look it.
So yeah, it's been a bit of an interesting problem.
But man, if the guys here haven't been awesome to work
with trying to track it down and troubleshooting stuff
and turning off all the packet inspection
to make sure if that's not it and that kind of thing.
So the live stream went pretty well.
It didn't disrupt the live stream much.
There's a couple of dropouts because of it,
but it was a little more tolerant.
So that was nice.
And the big launch, we had lots of people
show up and watch the live stream, so that was cool.
You can probably find it on Linux Academy's YouTube channel
if you want to check it out.
We had a fun little bit in the beginning,
and I was there for the whole stream, so that was fun too.
And now I'm just kind of hanging out here
for a couple of days.
They have one more on Thursday.
I haven't booked a return flight,
so I'm thinking about hanging out until the weekend
and then being here for the Thursday stream too.
Oh yeah, you should, just a little week in Texas, why not?
It's nice.
Plus it's like, I just have this total nightmare vision
of me flying out of town,
and then that's when something goes wrong with the Linux box
or the OBS machine.
Something's gonna happen
because I just got them all switched over.
You need to protect the reputation of Linux, Chris.
If there's one point to your entire existence, this is it.
Well, the thing too is the guy that's in charge here
of the live stream, he's a photographer
and a videographer and a good one too,
but he's never used OBS before.
So it's been of a training process and all of that.
So I may be here till at least then,
but pretty happy the first one went through pretty well.
And if we track down this network issue,
I think the next one will be really smooth.
And it's a process.
It reminds me when you're the one person
having issues with the network,
it is what you were asking for is a leap of faith
by the people that you were asking for their time
to troubleshoot it.
Like I felt constantly like I had to continue to prove
that really I know what I'm doing,
there really is an issue here.
Do you know what I mean?
Like when it comes to the network.
It's up to you to prove that it's not just your problem,
that it's actually a systemic network wide problem.
And of course, because network engineers
are bothered all the time, right?
Everyone loves to blame the network.
So of course, that's a natural defensive position.
Plus from what it sounds like,
if you're just browsing the web
or doing various office related tasks,
that is so different than any sort of real time
video streaming protocol.
So it's just a different use case too.
Yeah, so true.
And it's like way more intolerant of outages and breakups
where like a web browsing session or Slack chat
won't even notice a, I'll give you an example.
So it's not that bad.
I would say, so I'll ping Google DNS, say 800 times.
And in that 800 times, I may drop 0.5% of the packets.
You know, it's really small.
It's like a very small amount.
But what it equates to is about every minute or so,
maybe every 30 seconds or so,
there is about a second or so of my speech
that's completely lost.
And you have no idea what I'm saying.
We just had to kind of grind through land
and code a radio the last couple of days.
So I knew it had to get fixed.
But tracking that down has sent me like down
the old Google's searching for like tools on Linux
to like send bandwidth checks and like try to figure out
where I might have a lot of latency
or try to figure out where something's dropping packets.
Like it's kind of been a fun adventure again.
And getting to talk to lingo to the network guy,
talking to him about drop packets
and going to the patch panel,
seeing if I can't patch in my ethernet to the switch.
You're back on the front lines.
The whole lingo has been fun.
All right, let's keep going though.
A lot of you, at some point,
have tried to get something working with wine.
And maybe you were successful, maybe you weren't.
But the 4th of July marked wine's 25th frigging birthday.
25 years since the first stable, not a Windows emulator.
The first year brought the all-important support
for Microsoft Solitaire.
And by 1996, the wine developers managed to get Word
and Excel to run.
It, however, would be another 12 years
before the software was declared stable.
Version 1.0 was released in 2008.
And in the intervening years, the wine team bounced around
to several different licensing models for code,
starting with BSD style,
before eventually landing on a limited GPL,
followed by a number of flame wars
that lasted for a long time,
which you can still find archives of.
As wine slogged its way towards its first stable release,
a brief period of commercial support from Corel propped up
for a bit that eventually faded away
when the Canadian company departed from it all in 2001
to focus on its slow decline.
Windows came around,
which promised to offer easy Windows applications
while switching over to Linux.
Microsoft noticed that the name was close to Windows,
took issue with that,
and started the process of suing them.
They went to court in 2002.
Lindos lost.
But Microsoft did something interesting.
They opted for a retrial
and ended up paying Lindos $20 million
to purchase the trademark.
And then Lindos was renamed to Linspire,
which has actually just recently come back to life
when it launched under new ownership earlier this year.
I did a review of their release, one release ago.
You may remember Transgaming got in the mix for a while.
And Transgaming did something interesting.
They really got a fork of wine that focused on DirectX.
And that ended up kind of really pushing forward
wine as a project in the direction of DirectX,
which has been huge for wine.
And has developed in its current form
for wine and has developed and has continued.
They've just recently released 3.11, which is stable.
Yesterday, they released 3.14 testing,
or I'm sorry, 3.12 testing.
And they have also big news from WineConf.
They're beginning progress on arm support.
What?
For wine.
Yeah.
That's, it's like using, I don't, I mean,
this is really something,
but this is actually what Microsoft is doing too.
It's using x86 on arm emulation
to run 32 bit and 64 bit binaries on arm.
So I don't even, not only do I not need
to actually run that operating system,
I don't even need that architecture.
What a world.
Yeah, that's hilarious.
In fact, it really makes me just respect wine even more.
It may be slow, but as arm CPUs get faster,
it may, you never know.
Also, it looks like there has been some solid progress
on wine on the Tegra-based Shield,
which is running Android as well.
On the NVIDIA Shield running Android,
they showed Notepad++ and Age of Empires
running under wine on Android on the NVIDIA Shield,
which I love the NVIDIA Shield, it's been pretty great.
And they also talk about Vulkan support and whatnot.
We'll have a link in the show notes
if you guys want to read up about that.
And one other little note in there,
and I've been a long time advocate of crossover office,
they mentioned that CodeWeavers is still,
for a long time now I believe, employing about 50%
of all of the wine developers.
Wow.
It's a big deal, yeah.
And I just noticed they had a new version out
that I haven't bought yet, that I was kind of on the fence
because I don't really need it anymore,
but I think I'm going to do it.
I mean, it's almost been worth it just to support this,
right, like this is awesome.
You know, I've talked to Jeremy, their CEO, a long time ago.
I had a lot of respect for him when I talked to him.
And then when I saw that now for a long time
they've been employing over, not only do they employ 50%
of the wine developers, but then they kick that stuff
upstream too.
It's not like they're locking it behind some sort
of proprietary re-license and then
you have to buy it to get it.
They're still kicking that stuff upstream.
They're just so confident in their product
that they feel like they can sell it too.
And it's a great UI that sits on top of wine
that if you need business-grade wine that
is really easy to walk through, it
has specific profiles for each application,
it sets up bottles so that way each wine configuration
doesn't disrupt the other, or you
can install multiple applications
in a single bottle, and it has step-through wizards
that will pull down installers off the internet
if they're out there, it's great.
And I really think that CodeWeavers is a solid company,
so I think after the show I'm going to go buy myself
a copy of Crossover Office.
I think it's worth it.
And man, more power to the wine projects.
25 years in, we might not be running all of the Windows apps
we thought we would 25 years into it, maybe not,
but it's still pretty cool what they're pulling off.
All right, we have to keep going because I
want to get to the Gen 2 stuff, and we've been catching up,
so we've taken a little bit extra time here.
But it's just good to chat.
Now it's like the old shows back together again.
It's just so much fun.
It's beautiful.
Let's talk about Ting, though.
Let's talk about Ting.
Go to linux.ting.com.
This is, boy, do I miss having my multiple Ting access points.
This is how I do it because I have a phone on Ting,
and I have two MiFi devices, a CDMA device and a GSM device.
The reason why I can afford to do that,
it's not because I'm some big baller here.
It's because it's $6 a month for the line,
and then just my usage on top of that.
That's a pretty understandable business expense for what I do.
$6 a month, and if I don't use them, I don't pay.
Just pay for the line.
That's it.
That's easy.
It's really simple, and that's why the average Ting bill is just $23
per phone per month.
It's a fair price for how much you talk, text, and data you use.
And when you go to linux.ting.com, they'll
take $25 off a device if you want to get one from Ting directly.
If you bring one, and remember, it's CDMA and GSM.
So if you want to bring a device, and there's
a lot that are supported, just check their BYOD page.
They'll give you $25 in service credit,
which will probably cover more than your first month
potentially.
They have a fantastic control panel
where you can see your usage at a glance
and take complete control.
You can set alerts.
You can turn services off.
You can activate devices through their website.
And if you ever get stuck, they just really
have great customer service, the best customer
service in the industry.
And that's something that Ting can focus on
in a really particular kind of way.
So not only do they have great prices,
not only do they have a great device selection,
but they make flexible usage, like the kind that I use,
where I have one phone and then two different MIFIs, possible.
It means that when I'm trying to do a show,
I can switch between those devices
just by changing my Wi-Fi network on my laptop.
I love it.
They also have a great blog.
They just did a tiny home post a little bit ago,
which I'm partial to, being that I live in one.
And it's pretty cool.
They really get this stuff.
And that's what I love about Ting.
And I'd love you to get some Ting.
So go to linux.ting.com and check them out.
They're a great service.
Also, thanks to Linux Academy for sponsoring
this episode of the Unplugged program,
linuxacademy.com slash unplugged.
You go there, you sign up for a free seven-day trial,
and you support the show.
It's a platform to learn more about Linux, anything
that runs Linux or that Linux runs on top of.
And today, they just launched new Azure courseware,
some Linux Essentials courseware,
and, man, Wes, it's a perfect courseware for the TechSnap
audience.
It's a full deep dive into continuous integration
and deployment.
And on top of that, when you're all done with the courseware,
you actually set up a whole system.
You really go through and implement every aspect of it.
And they've broken it out into different areas.
And the thing that I learned today
that I didn't know before is, so say they've
itemized continuous integration and deployment courseware
into eight major sections.
If you just needed to brush up on the Kubernetes aspect,
you could jump right to step six.
It will fill in all of the required stuff
and build the server infrastructure
that you would have had to go through to get there,
just so you can deep dive on that single topic,
take it, and learn more.
That is the difference when you use Linux Academy, right?
Who else has thought about this this seriously?
They're trying to do so many different things
that they just can't have this level of polish and attention
to detail.
And if you want to get the next promotion,
you really want to prove that you've learned something,
I can think of nowhere better.
That's right.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplug.
They're going to have another live stream
on Thursday, July 12 at 10.30 Chicago time.
That's central.
And the word on the street, although I
haven't seen the deets, but the word on the street
is they have a bunch of Red Hat related announcements
on the Thursday show.
So check that out.
And they're also hiring.
I wanted to make a little mention of this.
They are looking for a full stack node developer,
if that's something that you might be interested in.
They also are looking for a senior Ruby developer,
as well as a customer support manager,
Ruby on Rails developer, and a Microsoft Azure training
architect.
Now that's a lot of positions.
So I would say there's an email address I gave out last week.
And I think that's the same one.
I don't remember what it was.
I'm sorry.
I can't recall.
Brent, do you happen to remember randomly
what email address I randomly said last week in the show?
I'm sorry, I have no idea.
No, I can't recall either.
But if anybody in the chat room knows either,
maybe put it in there.
Because there is a lot of positions here.
And it's a really cool company.
I've been down there hanging out with them for a while.
And I totally think that if you are in this area
and you listen to the show, some of these actually,
all of the ones I just listed, except for the customer support
manager, are all telecommute jobs.
So you don't even have to be in Texas.
You can be wherever you're at.
That's pretty awesome.
So check it out.
Go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged to get the deal.
And you know what, do this.
If you want to apply for the positions,
I have a special email address that's
set up just for the Jupyter Broadcasting audience.
So you kind of get the hotline treatment.
So if you really are interested, it
may be worth listening to the sponsor section
of last week's episode.
But otherwise, I'll give you a little hot tip.
linuxacademy.workable.com.
I have them all listed there.
I think if you're a listener of this show, that
might put you ahead of the list.
So go check that out.
And if you really want the fast line,
go listen to last week's episode and grab the email address.
And then maybe remind me what it was.
Also, a big thank you to DigitalOcean.
deo.co slash unplugged.
Go there to get a $100 credit at DigitalOcean when you sign up.
You've got to use that URL, though, to get that.
deo.co slash unplugged.
You can build applications super fast
on DigitalOcean's crazy quick infrastructure.
Enterprise-grade SSDs, 40 gigabit connections
coming into the hypervisors.
Of course, they're running Linux, KVM,
to virtualize it all.
And they have industry-leading price
to performance, predictable cost and billing.
And I love these optimized compute types.
While you were out, Wes, we set up a PeerTube instance
on a DigitalOcean droplet using their super crazy fast,
high-end Xeon CPUs, where you get two dedicated.
Oh.
So cool, Wes.
Because I've encoded these exact videos many times.
So I really get into a sense of the speed up on DigitalOcean.
And it's so nice.
It's just right there.
They also have these mix-and-match droplets
now, where you can set the different, like,
maybe you want more RAM.
Or you can say, you know what, I just
want all in SSD, as well as block storage.
It's so slick.
And the whole thing is easy to manage
with their fantastic dashboard.
And they're easy to use API.
If you just want to do it via script
or use your favorite language, it's
really easy to get started.
And they got great documentation, data centers
all over the world.
This is the bar, you understand, right?
DigitalOcean is the bar that everybody else in this game
is trying to catch up to.
The problem is, when you're ahead,
you just got to stay hungry.
And you can stay competitive.
And that's exactly what DigitalOcean's done.
Now they're offering $100 credits to try it out.
That's insane.
Take advantage of that before they stop doing it,
because that's insane.
It's so great.
do.co.co.co.co and a big thank you to DigitalOcean
for sponsoring the unplugged program, do.co.co.co.
All right, well, last week we talked about Gen2's GitHub
repo getting owned.
It wasn't a massive, massive blunder,
because they weren't really anything more than mirrors.
But now it turns out that it was a bit of a rookie mistake.
And I say that with love, much respect
to some of the very, very technical people
over in the Gen2 community.
In fact, yeah, there's some people in the security industry
that only use Gen2 because of some of the people involved
with the project.
So I say this with no disparity to the people involved with Gen2,
but it helps me make a larger point.
And that is, after looking through this
and thinking about some of the other recent distro snafus,
things like expiring SSL certifications,
project leaders randomly quitting,
leaving nobody with access to any of the infrastructure,
there's just been example after example
after example this year of projects
getting this stuff wrong.
And in the case of Gen2, they just
owned up to it on their own Wiki page.
They say the attacker gained access
to a password of an organization administrator.
Evidence suggested a password schemes
was used to disclose on one site made
it easy to guess the password for unrelated web pages,
i.e. using the same password on multiple websites.
The Wiki page also reveals that the project got lucky.
The attack was loud.
Removing all of the developers caused everyone
to get emailed if they had been more careful and more
selective, like figured out somebody
that hadn't been active for a while and just removed them
and then got in, it would have taken much longer for the Gen2
project to notice.
But the credentials were taken, and they did a noisy attack
where they did something that notified all of the developers,
and so it alerted them to it.
And those are the things that really kind of,
that was the thing that saved them.
But the thing that caused the issue
is a shared password as well as GitHub failing
to block access to repositories via Git,
resulting in malicious commits being extremely accessible.
So Gen2 had to force push over as soon as these things were
discovered, and credential revoking procedures
were incomplete for them.
And they also didn't have a backup copy of the Gen2 GitHub
organization details.
So that made it particularly hard.
And the systemd repo turned out not to be mirrored.
It was stored directly on GitHub.
So there was a couple of things, oh, as well
as some communication snafus.
But my core point that I'm trying to make
is this is clearly not the stuff that distros
are super strong at, as it probably shouldn't be.
You know, they're developers.
They're maintainers.
They're organizers.
But they're not necessarily sysadmins,
or maybe some of them are.
But that isn't what they're spending their time doing.
And I'm not trying to make a case for putting everything
in the cloud here, Wes.
But do you kind of follow my logic?
Like, I kind of come from the school of thought
that developers should develop software,
and sysadmins should manage servers.
And recently, the Gnome Foundation
just launched new positions specifically
to take off the server administrative burden
from the developers and people in the foundation.
What's the compromise here?
Because obviously, projects don't have unlimited budgets.
They can't hire people full time to do this.
And there's only so many people to do the work.
But yet, there's obviously a certain amount
of neglect that goes when you have too many hats on.
What's the solution for this?
Solve it, Wes.
Yeah, I'll solve the whole thing, and maybe world peace
while I'm at it.
I do think you're right.
Like, when we talk about the split between developers
and admins, it's not about even skill sets
or anything like that.
It's really what you're saying.
Too many hats, when you have too many jobs
and you're thinking about too much
and too many responsibilities, you get sloppy.
I'm sure the people involved here,
they probably even knew somewhere in the back of their mind
that this wasn't the best password policy.
And you know what, I'll fix it next weekend
when I finally have an ounce of time.
I'll sit down, and I'll get this right,
and I'll finally install that password manager
that I've been meaning to.
But that's never going to work.
And so whether you're a developer or anything else,
you really do need people that your job
is maintaining infrastructure.
And it's not sexy, and it might not even be fun,
especially when, as you say, right,
a lot of these people, these are volunteers.
You're trying to contribute to open source
for the benefit of everyone.
And you're excited about scratching the itch
or improving the awesomeness of the build system
or whatever else it is you're interested in.
And if you try to take on too many things,
it's just gonna fail.
So if you can find people who are willing to be humble
and just say like, yes, I'm gonna administer.
I'm gonna be an administrator.
I'm gonna be an overseer.
I'm just gonna make sure that all the central parts
that no one else thinks of,
and it just has to run in the background,
will actually work.
And ideally, if you could have some sort of funding
to make sure that happened,
because that's probably especially hard
to find volunteers for, that would be even better.
Yeah, yeah.
Brandon, what do you think of the idea
of the free and open source software community
coming together with essentially
like an open best practices,
like a comprehensive best practices
that many, many, many projects could contribute to?
What about something like that?
Yeah, it seems to me like these are the types of problems
that would exist with almost any project, right?
So I think because we have such strong community,
even if you're making quasi-competitive products,
everyone needs this infrastructure
to make their work happen, right?
So what if we can maybe all get together
and create some kind of, this might be a dream,
but some kind of best practices,
I don't know if it's a document or some kind of,
maybe it's a conference or something
where everybody can just be up to date on this,
and some of the developers can maybe lean
on some of the projects who are a bit more expert.
Or maybe what about some sort of donated auditing time,
where you could get in security experts
to go into an organization and do periodic assessments
to say like, hey, where are you at?
What can you improve?
Yeah, you would think there would be people
in the community that have that particular skill set
that could be a way they contribute,
but there would need to be some structure around it,
because otherwise you could get people
just banging on doors they shouldn't.
Eric, you think maybe I'm just a DevOps hater?
You say DevOps aims to solve this.
I say DevOps is the problem.
DevOps is a philosophy, first and foremost.
It's not a position, it's not supposed to be click-baity.
It's a philosophy, it's a way of doing work.
It's with the way that the founding team folks,
it was just a bunch of people that were at a conference
that were sitting down talking over drinks
and basically came up with this entire philosophy.
It's a way of doing work.
You break things down into one or two week sprints.
You take tasks one at a time.
You sit down with the developers,
with the security people, with the network people,
with the business, with the systems administrators.
Everybody sits down at a table and prioritizes work
and what can I get done this week?
What needs to get pushed to next week?
And that's where a lot of these tool sets have come in.
The CI, CD, continuous integration,
continuous deployment type of an approach
comes from this DevOps philosophy.
So if you've got all of your code for your infrastructure,
for your network, for your applications
in a GitLab instance,
and that's managed by a tool like Jenkins
that will automatically set up new builds
that talks to a tool like SaltStack
that automatically provisions and monitors
your infrastructure to make sure that,
well, the server crashed so I'm gonna rebuild another one
and tell the load balancer to point to this IP address
instead of the bad IP address.
It's a philosophy and it only works well
as the people that are implementing that philosophy.
Yeah, and it does seem like the tools are getting better
and they're getting more complicated too,
but it seems like the tools around this,
what has been a philosophy for years now,
are actually starting to catch up with the philosophy.
Would you agree with that, Wes?
Yeah, I mean, it's really like anything else.
I think when you can have better communication,
better communication around shared goals in particular
and have stakeholders working closer together,
that's a benefit.
Now, it's not a silver bullet, right?
So anytime you have more things to do
than you actually have manpower or time to do,
you're trying to do too much,
you'll still face the same problems.
Yeah, I like that you got the word stakeholders
that worked in there, that's well done.
Now, Brent has an idea, maybe we just simplify this.
Something a little easier than a comprehensive guide,
right, Brent?
Yeah, I remember, I wish I could remember
what it was called, and maybe someone in the community
can help me out on this, but I remember Noah talking,
it might have been like even six weeks ago on Ask Noah
about exactly this, a type of checklist
that you could look at your own systems
and see if they were secure with basically,
you didn't have to be creative to come up with a checklist.
It was right there and it was being distributed
by one of the organizations, I forget what it was.
A checklist isn't a bad way to go,
even if it was something that was sort of generic
that you could at least say we followed
this community checklist.
I feel like there is something here.
Yeah, I mean, a checklist is good,
I think you need, a checklist is helpful,
it's a start, right, but you still do need that person
who has enough time and focus and skill
to run through the checklist and know
which ones are actually checked or not.
Yeah, that is a really fair point.
And maybe the checklist is a little bit too surface,
you know, you need to understand
what's happening below the checklist.
Yeah, and that is sometimes what I worry is happening,
and this is just me being a curmudgeon,
is we have, what DevOps to me really is,
is it's getting software developers more empowered
to just deploy things that they need to do their job
and not have to sit around and wait for the sysadmins
to set the system up and then this tedious back and forth
where something isn't configured quite right,
and you know, the sysadmin has no idea
how the software works, and the software developer
has no idea what the sysadmin's doing,
and the whole momentum there really caught,
and I guess another way to put that is
the demands to speed up software development
have sort of put us down this path
where developers are deploying infrastructure.
And when I started in the IT industry,
those two lines were never crossed,
and they generally didn't get along super well either,
either sides of the camp were always grousing
about the other side of the camp,
so it wasn't an ideal solution.
And Linux really is an operating system
designed for system administrators, it really is.
If you think about it, you have to be root
to install software, well, who's root?
The system administrator, and if you think about the repo,
what is the repo?
The repo is an all-knowing person
who has blessed this package
as being possible to install on your system.
That's the mindset of a sysadmin,
and snaps and Docker and AppImage and Flatpaks and DevOps
are all about collapsing that resistance down
to the developer can publish and the user can install it.
And sometimes the user is the developer.
And that mind shift has been good
for the pace of software development,
and it's led to things like incredible cloud infrastructure
and things like AWS Lambda and DigitalOcean
one-click deployments, which I use the hell out of.
So it's not all negative,
but my core issue has always been
as we go down this path is you become less
and less of an expert.
You are required to be less and less of an expert
to set up really complicated systems.
Whereas in the past, your level of knowledge
basically had to match the level of complication
of those systems.
It was a one-for-one thing.
To get that sucker working,
you knew exactly how it worked in and out intimately.
That is no longer the case.
There is now a massive gap between knowledge and complexity.
And that's not necessarily a bad thing,
but I think it does lead us down this path
where you can over-deploy an infrastructure.
You can build yourself a kingdom that traps you.
And then it's a lot to manage.
You've got multiple people trying to get the stuff.
You start sharing passwords.
You're using three different things
to coordinate the team's communication.
Nothing is super solid
because there's not one really uptight person
who is worrying about all of that stuff constantly,
saying, we need to be doing this.
We need to be fixing this.
And if you don't have a team or a person
or whatever to do that,
and you leave it up to just the developers
or the distributions or the projects
who are busy doing other things to maintain it,
I feel like this is going to be a systemic issue
that constantly plagues busy,
overtaxed open-source projects
and could even, over time,
lead to a bit of a reputation as amateur
and that a lot of these projects
don't have their shit together
and that they constantly are having issues.
I mean, going all the way back to Mint breaches,
I mean, we can just sit here and rattle off
mistake after mistake after mistake
that has really just boiled down to,
oops, we missed that, or we didn't really know,
or something changed that we weren't aware of,
or the project lead who had all the access left.
And every time you just go,
you smack your head and you go,
God, that's amateur hour.
It's a gray area in many ways,
because you're right, we have so many tools.
And in many ways, that's good
because a lot of times, if they're done well,
it means it's easier to get it right, right?
So if you're on Amazon
and you're deploying a load balancer,
it will handle all, you know,
if you have SSL on there and you have it provisioned,
you know, it will have the best ciphers,
they take care of it.
It gets upgraded automatically.
So that's nice.
You don't have to go learn the horrible world of SSL.
At the same time, you're right that if it's so easy
to build yourself this giant, complicated mountain
and no one really understands how it works,
that will fall down.
And that's where I think maybe sometimes
it's a little bit of a fallacy that,
just because you've, you know,
you've quote unquote gone DevOps or whatever else,
that doesn't mean you can't have individual experts
and you can't have people that happen to know more
about a part of the system than others
or are specific domain experts.
And at the same time, it reminds me of sort of unit tests
for software development and all the safeguards
and everything else, there's really no substitute
for attention to detail and caring about the software
or systems that you're crafting.
Yeah.
Well, there you have it.
I'm just putting out there that would be great
if somehow we could really come together on,
even if it was a checklist, that'd be fine,
that'd be a great starting point
or a guide, a Wiki of best practices.
The problem would be anything like this ever getting traction
and it would take a lot of buy-off,
but it really seems like if we could give these folks
that are too busy to, if you think,
if you have the mindset ever
when you're managing your infrastructure,
that, oh man, this is this tedious thing
that I just have to get done so that way we can do X,
you're probably not the person that should be managing that.
You should be the person that's looking forward
to setting that stuff up so that way you can do X.
And if you're in that position where like,
oh man, this thing again, all right,
well, we gotta go get that thing set up on GitHub
so we can just do this, please,
so that way we can get back to work.
If that's how you feel about it,
it's probably a sign that your team
needs somebody else doing that work.
And so if we could make that person's job,
because that's not always an option,
if we can make that person's job and life
a little bit easier with a checklist or a guide
or some sort of community resource that says,
these are at least the minimums that you should be doing,
I think that would be extremely valuable.
So I hope we see it, who knows?
You never know, you never know, you never know.
Maybe I'll travel around in my RV
and I'll advocate it on every Linux event I go
and one day something will happen, maybe.
In the meantime, where should folks
get more Westpain in their life?
Oh, you can find me on Twitter at Westpain
or stay tuned from some exciting new TechSnap episodes
coming to a podcast near you.
Ooh, TechSnap.Systems slash subscribe.
Brent, do you have anywhere you'd like to send
the good folks any tips, tricks
to get more Brent in their life?
Yeah, sure, you can either come to Northern Ontario
and I'll tour you around or you can hit me up on Twitter,
Brent, at Brent Gervais, B-R-E-N-T-G-E-R-V-A-I-S
or BrentGervais.com.
That's great, that's great.
Now I know if I ever go there, I'm gonna contact you.
If I ever go back to New York City, I'm gonna contact XMN
and if I ever go down to Seattle, I contact Wes.
I am really covered now, at least on the major coast.
You can follow me, I'm at Chris Ellis.
The whole network is at Jupiter Signal.
Links to build the community.
Well, you know what, really, if you think about it,
we have a very wide ranging network of experts,
probably in every major city.
So anywhere we wanna go,
there's probably gonna be somebody there.
If you'd like to join us or get links
to anything we talked about,
we have all that stuff detailed at linuxunplug.com,
linuxunplug.com slash 257.
The live show is at jblive.tv on a Tuesday
and I may be still down in Texas
by the time you hear us again.
I just don't know, but thanks so much for joining us
and we will see you right back here next week.
is
Thank you, guys. That was a lot of fun. Thank you, Mumble Room. You guys were great as always.
Stars, as always, that Mumble Room. Brent, the mumble worked pretty good. You sounded
pretty good during the whole show, too, so I'm glad that worked.
That's kind of unbelievable. It's great. We kind of pulled that together last minute,
didn't we?
Yeah, yeah. And, Eric, it's good to hear that whatever was wrong with your mixer last week,
the highs are a little better this week.
Yeah, that was fun to find out after the fact.
Yeah, the kids love the knobs on the mixer, man. They love the knobs on the mixer. Look
at that, Daddy. Security amateur hour coming in by Architect right now. The Traveling LUP
Roadshow, we need up-tights. That's funny. Do you have any hot travel tips to leave us
with, Wes, before we part?
Buy a Kindle and spend your whole time using it.
Oh, did you get a Kindle?
I did. I don't know how I didn't have one already in that I'm a pretty big reader. I've
just been stubborn and sticking to the old dead tree matter.
But it's an Amazon product.
Yeah, I was conflicted, but, boy, I was glad I had it on that 12-hour flight.
I got a Switch for this trip.
Oh, really? Oh, nice.
Yep. Yep, I got Odyssey and Mario Kart. Man, those games at 60 bucks a pop, though, that
is outrageous. So I'm going to wait a little bit for the others, but so much fun. Much
better than I expected. It has a kickstand on the back, so you can take the handles off
and it's just so much fun to play with the kids. It has been great. It is better than
expected. And the fact that it uses USB-C to charge is an absolute perk.
Loved it.
Mm-hmm. Yeah. So I'll have some Switch time while I'm on this trip. So by the time I get
back, I'll probably have a pretty good take on the device and might be ready to try to
put Linux on it.
Oh, do it. Yes.