anybody in the mumble room using something besides just the default
terminal for their desktop like I love I love console so that's almost always the
one I go to but anybody using something besides the default like term X
terminator terminator yeah yeah oh really okay I I recommend hyper
Pokemon this is something that dark crack team here at Linux unplugged has
discovered and I just want you to give it a consideration it's wondrous
tailor-made Pokemon themes for hyper terminal okay so just give that a
consideration while the link in the show notes it's for all you Pokemon
enthusiasts this is Linux unplugged episode 202 for June 20th 2017
Oh welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show where your host
is being bombarded by BSD enthusiasts it's a full-on attack I'll tell you more
about that later out of the show mr. West is in route right now battling
Seattle traffic but the show goes on he'll be slipstreaming himself into the
show he'll be live patching himself into the podcast in a little bit in the
meantime we have some community updates to get through including some really
important security news for Kmail users up front huge update from the fedora
project we're gonna dig into some shenanigans going on out there we'll
tell you about that there's a mystery afoot and some mess what I know it's
very confusing and then mr. Michael Hall joins us formally from canonical now at
endless to tell us what he and endless is up to and then towards the very end
of the show we have a random grab bag I have some updates on something we talked
about last week and if time permits although we have so much stuff to get to
this week I have an interview from the floor of self that we haven't had a
chance to play yet in the show now it's not super time-critical so if time
doesn't permit never fear we could always sneak it into later time but if
the show permits we'll get to that so before we jump into all of our community
updates for episode 202 before I start talking about the barbecue coming up in
a couple of weeks before we get to our follow-up let's bring in our mumble room
time-approved screening mumble room Wow I feel like I feel like if I was in a
room and we were in a physical room and you all did that I would nearly go into
an anxiety attack but for some reason you're all coming into my headphones I
maybe it's even more intense but thank you guys for being here I'm looking
forward to chatting about all this stuff Michael welcome back to the show mr.
Hall it's good to have you like this is your third time I think you might be a
record holder yeah do you do like the SNL like five-timer jacket or something
I think I should get one of those I think we should I think we should
probably you could be the person that starts that tradition you never know and
it would be a good jacket too like not one of these WWDC jeans jacket but all
really nice materials I'm afraid you'd have to give Alan and Martin like a full
wardrobe though yeah there'd have to be a line between like occasional guests
and frequent contributor because those guys basically would have not just the
wardrobe but they'd also have to have like a whole line of like swag just for
them of them for their attendance although although to be fair if you keep
it up at this rate you might beat them because they've been very busy on
Tuesdays recently so they haven't been able to join us of course it is
obviously I mean what else you got going on so we do have a few really positive
stories to get into but I wanted to cover one that's I don't know if I don't
know if negative is the right way to describe it but I did want to cover one
that is pretty important for Kmail users Kmail send later feature when combined
with K K mails PGP support didn't work and so if you were scheduling emails
with the understanding that they'd be encrypted when they were sent later
those emails were getting sent in the clear text they were just getting sent
plain text no encryption applied at all even though the UI would suggest
encryption was being applied to that email the back-end scheduler that
actually grabbed that queue and sent the emails off didn't go through the open
PGP system and so those routines were completely bypassed leading to the email
being sent in plain text without being signed or encrypted which is even just
getting not not getting signed is a big deal and so the bug would lead to
unintentional information disclosure of private messages and it's CVE 2017 96 04
how about that and the KD project is aware of it versions 4.11 that's when
the send later feature was introduced and 1704.1 are vulnerable Kmail version
so it's versions between 4.11 guys to 1704 Kmail version 1704.2 released on
June 8th of this year contains a fix for the problem and so this is one of those
where I'm not sure what distros are patching I haven't I didn't look into
that but I'm not sure if it's getting back ported to older desktop versions by
the distro maintainers or what there is there is several there are several links
that more information about it but that just is one of those things you know
it's just like you you're using a tool you think you're using encryption and
maybe you have a reason why you especially like when you're doing this
type of communications you had very limited amounts of doing some of our
work for some of our other shows timing is sometimes kind of an important thing
about it because like you're writing somebody something and you want to send
it off after something after a piece of news breaks or after after a story comes
out then you want the email so the timing thing of really sensitive
communication turns out to be pretty pretty important so this is a this is
one of those where if I have I ran a Linux critics blog I would be extremely
harsh about this because it's an example I think of a vulnerability and I don't
need to harp on this too hardly but I do think it's an example of a
vulnerability that if say
Gmail had this problem or even say Apple Mail on the iPhone had this problem it
would be there would be mobs in the streets there would be mobs in the
streets about about this lack of security and this simple obvious amateur
mistake by these companies but when it's K mail and we all love the the K mail
folks I mean it's not like we want to blame shame anybody here but when it's K
mail we're all just like oh okay good I'll go and get those patches installed
and then we don't really even talk about I mean this is this is a story from June
and I was like nobody's talking about this so I think it's an I think it's
worth mentioning
a HRS points out they don't you says it's a Gmail doesn't support GPG but you
get my drift right if there was a critical vulnerability in something like
this in a in a commercial product we how we hold it to a different standard
WW do you agree do you I mean you see what I'm saying here at least like if
this was Gmail that had a flaw of this magnitude I feel like there would be a
totally different level not just because the users are larger but because the
expectations are different or do you think oh yeah yeah I think if this was
happening on Gmail and I like I'm a Gmail user even though I'm going through
Thunderbird I would probably demand a fence you know you would have want to be
left out of this you know former bro Levy and have your stuff out and open
and to their credit you know they when they found out about it they hustled to
get it fixed and they've been really clear on their communication about it's
not like they're trying to like snuff the story out it just doesn't seem to
get maybe I mean I'm sure user base size must be part of it I don't know feels
like more than that though one of the stories getting a lot of traction is
this post by Christian Shaler on the future of fedora just even beyond
workstation 26 and there's a couple of things I pulled out in here that have me
super excited about just long term fedora not not a lot of stuff we get our
hands on immediately but long term they're working on improving integration
of the NVIDIA binary driver which is kind of remarkable talking about the
fedora project here but they think they have a salute they're gonna have a
solution in place where you can use the NVIDIA driver when you want the extra
graphics and graphics power and they think that it's going to be a pretty
smooth installation and they're also working on a fleet commander which will
allow which will be a tool essentially to allow you to manage fedora and red
hat enterprise desktop centrally it's a tool that's really targeted more like
universities and large installations but I don't know it could be pretty cool and
the the other thing is they're gonna help you integrate it with their free
IPA suite of tools so it's essentially going to give you an LDAP active
directory style like active directory support but the one that I really want
to talk about in this post and I think this is probably why this post is
getting the most attention is pipewire we've talked about it before on the show
when it was called pinnows and now it's been renamed to pipewire and they're
increasing the scope of what pipewire is going to accomplish so think of it maybe
at first pass as pulse audio for everything video and audio it aims at
unifying Linux audio and video the long-term goal is for pipewire to not
only provide handling of video streams but also handle all kinds of audio
wow I got to stop right there that if they pull that off that's the homefield
advantage Mac OS has for media production because they they have that
whole quick time and core audio and core video system worked out where there's
just API's available and Final Cut 10 just sits on top of that technology so
they're spending a lot of time to make sure that pipewire can handle audio in a
way that not only addresses pulse audio use cases but also the ones that are
handled by Jack today wow a big part of motivation for this is they want to make
fedora workstation the best place to create content and we want the pro audio
crowd to be first-class citizens of our desktop oh my god wow so this is huge
this is really really huge is if they can if they can get this even close it's
gonna be it's gonna be a phenomenal phenomenal groundwork for multimedia
applications also flat packs so they expect to start shipping pipewire in
fedora workstation 27 which is pretty soon if you think about it but it it's
only gonna be sort of like the first version the really early stuff it's gonna
handle video and they say one of the reasons they need to do that is to
handle video for flat back applications because I got a they got to give it like
up they got a poke a portal for video and so they're gonna also provide an API
for flat packs and get ready for this
an API for screen capture under Wayland this is one of the number one questions
I get about Wayland I had one just just it came into the show 45 minutes before
I went on air what about what about remote access to Wayland what about
screen capture software in Wayland this is gonna be huge for desktop users of
Wayland that wanted to screen capture that that want to maybe have a remote
desktop system this could lead to all of that potentially so pipewire to the
rescue for more for media production and also for the Wayland transition then
there was this moment oh man I wish Wes was in here so I could see his face in
this one so they make a post and they make a part in here little section here
about fractional scaling for high DPI systems fractional scaling a lot of talk
about that recently we've been talking about that recently because there was
that hack fest between canonical and gnome developers at canonicals what was
it Taipei offices well it turns out fedora workstation has been leading the
charge in supporting high DPI on Linux they write and they hope to build on
that current work to enable fractional scaling support where they link to the
gnome.org blog post about the fractional scaling hack fest and he goes on to talk
about the importance of fractional scaling now they're gonna be there to
support that when it's ready and some great work also going into just the
general performance of gnome shell all this almost feels like a direct
criticism response of mine recently and I'm happy to see this they are closing
bugs on small little performance issues in mutter and gnome shell it's coming on
top of earlier work that they've done and while it's a real you know subjective
thing they are working on quote-unquote gnomes performance and quote-unquote
gnomes overhead to make gnome shell even more performant in future versions of
fedora which of course is going to benefit everyone using the gnome desktop
then there's a little note in here about flat packs they say essentially what
we're doing is making it very simple for a fedora maintainer to build a flat pack
of an application they maintain through the fedora package building
infrastructure and push that flat back into a central flat pack registry hmm so
they're gonna make it easier for people to ship flat packs as well good stuff
overall about about about firmware updates they're getting closer to
shipping codecs just as everybody's streaming things and it doesn't matter
anymore yeah we're glad we fought that and this is a big one I will end on this
I think yeah we'll end on this yeah this will be good battery life they're
looking into hopefully making a dent here they say for a while now we've been
digging into this and we'll hopefully share information soon on which laptops
users should buy that will have good battery life under fedora hmm they also
have a they they have a point Christian Kellner or Kellner is the main point on
battery life and taking up improving battery life benchmark tools that they
use so hopefully we'll see a distribution taking battery life very
seriously one that's very gnome focused again pretty good because it turns out a
lot of districts are shipping something based on no shell these days that's a
lot of that's a lot of stuff coming for fedora after just last week I said it's
fine it's fine it's all right is anybody in the mumble room have any
reactions or responses to any of that stuff that I just rambled on about go
ahead no only the Western already does a spawn RTP back end so oh oh okay I I
guess I think you may have heard that yeah do you just put in the term I'd
love to know more about that so it's like a full-on RDP like Microsoft
remote desktop protocol back end for Weston basically using free RDP and
using those libraries as well so there is an implementation of it for wayland
but only in Western for some reason I don't know why the desktop something up
hmm yeah well and Weston is sort of like the reference right so if they just they
don't have to necessarily choose to use that part of the reference of limitation
I suppose no I mean they could use their own interface for the libraries they
could but they just see the talk is there so I think part of it is to like a
lot of them are adapting their existing compositors or existing systems to use
wayland instead of creating something from scratch so maybe some of that might
be belted on later I don't know that's interesting that you know I'm gonna I'm
gonna take a look at that more thanks for attuned it for for linking that
that's pretty cool that's pretty cool anyways we'll have a link to the fedora
26 workstation post I go ahead sorry I think the flat back thing is rather
interesting tell me does that could some kind of replace the PPAs of Ubuntu if
you have a build server that can build some flag packs out of the sources you
imagine the same thing as snap packages with to get service like some kind of
open build service yeah that would be rather cool I think that you that would
be really cool you guys know about flat hub right so this is I think separate
than flat hub but no go tell go on about flat that's cuz it's pretty interesting
so flat hub is this kind of centralized flat pack repository it spun out of the
gnome work it's independent of gnome now and trying to get buy-in from app
developers and platform developers and it's really just to ease discovery and
distribution of flat packs by having one place where you know distros can set up
by default users can just go there and find whatever apps are available yeah
they're there they were last week we talked a little bit about they're
looking to raise some funding and I like that they're I like that they're trying
to set something up that's independent which is great and whenever you're
trying to figure out like what software is available it's nice to have a central
place to go to go see what applications so if you go to flat pack org slash apps
dot HTML you can get all the GUI or command-line apps there's quite a bit of
stuff really I mean there's some good stuff in here like core bird is pretty
nice and discord and gnome mpv shoot shoot yeah so there's some good stuff in
there and yeah flat pack flat pack org slash apps dot HTML for that yeah I I
think that's fascinating so speaking of competing technologies that's kind of a
similar similar trend everybody's everybody's friend Lenart Pottering has
a new tool new a new project and it's ca-sync casa-sync I'm not sure ca-sync
I'm gonna call it and it's it's it's a tool for distributing file system images
it combines the idea of the our sync algorithm with the idea of git style
content addressable file systems and creates a new system for efficiently
storing and delivering file system images and for optimizing for high
frequency update cycles over the internet with a focus on delivering to
IOT devices containers VMs applications portable services or entire OS images
but he hopes to extend it to later in later on down the road to more of a
generic way a fashion to become useful for backups and home directory
synchronization as well and he goes through his blog post here and says he
took a look at the different approaches out there he says he wanted something
that made updates cheap he wanted something that respected boundaries on
disk space and usage on servers something that was friendly to content
distribution networks something that was simple and he does specifically in here
address systems that operate on block layer and replace squash FS images you
know I don't updates and they just right over the squash FS image and then mount
it he seems to not like that approach which I think is kind of the I could be
wrong on the details but I think it's kind of the Ubuntu core approach and he
wants to he goes on to say later on delivering direct squash FS or other
file system images is almost beautifully simple but of course it means every
update requires a full download of the newest image which is both bad for disk
usage and for generated traffic even though you can try to hack it with z-sync
and things like that he says besides the issues I pointed out already I just
wasn't happy with the security and root reproducibility properties of these
systems either so this isn't like a flat pack snap packages alternative but it is
like a whole new way to distribute OS updates and images I think he was
working on something in the past that use butter FS to accomplish something
kind of similar to this but this is different than like say are just using
our sink or OS tree or similar tools because those tools he is doing
something where he's removing all of the file boundaries and then he chunks
things up small files get lumped together with their siblings large files
get chopped into pieces and then he can recognize similarities between all of
those files beyond just there you know beyond the file boundaries make sure all
the chunks are distributed and then send them around and the chunking algorithm
is based on buzz hash which is a rolling hash function and shaw 256 is used to
store the hash functions to generate the digits of the chunks I know it's super
complicated it's all up on its blog up on his blog post what do you think
www you loving this no I'm not loving it because it reminds me of how I'm
recovering files and I can't even use any of hash functionality or anything to
double-check files and I have one files merged with other files and compressed
containers and all kinds of junk so no this just does not sound appealing to
me at all I I feel like it is complicated to understand and this
diagram isn't doing any benefits but there are other operating systems out
there like plan 9 and there's other systems out there that have this
functionality at an OS level and it's it's really nice because you can
essentially send a system from one system to the other system booted up and
it's live you can clone it you can you can send an update over the internet and
if it fails you know you have recourse you can slowly trickle something to a
device when you have a limited bandwidth connection and then have it assemble the
updates on its side and then do itself you know screw itself over in the
upgrade process so I I totally recognize on the surface of it a need that it
seems to be addressing just like I did with system D when when system D was
announced then I was like oh yeah like the network socket stuff and some of
these other things are really pretty useful in the server space this is one
of those where when you have systems that have all kinds of random ass
containers or dozens of containers running on it you do kind of need a way
to manage all of it that sort of standardized at the OS level that goes
just beyond beyond just software delivery but actually addresses
delivering and managing the operating system and you do want something that's
sort of almost like the plumbing level and he's pretty good at that kind of
stuff but I do wonder if it's competing with other solutions that have already
been created I got to learn more I'm gonna study more into it but if anybody
else has done a deep dive and can help me figure it out I'd appreciate it whole
thing is really fascinating he talks about where it could go down the road
talks about how you can operate at the block level or the file system level
anyways there's there's he's already I mean he's already got essentially this
is what's crazy about Lenart he's already essentially built the whole damn
basics here he's got functional code you can use right now I really I just find
this to be one of those one of those things where it's he creates something
that's slightly slightly thought-provoking and sometimes causes a
strong reaction and it's so ca-sync and we'll have a link in the show notes if
you want to see more about that ca-sync by Lenart quite the quite the transition
he's made over the years anybody else have any thoughts on it before we move on
I'll throw in a quick related story I guess I have I guess I have a thought
then if nobody else does just a quick update canonical has released a new
stable version of the snap craft utility for creating snap packages and this one
supports resuming downloads of the core snap when a building them like a when
building a classic snap or an air occurs or something like that the package can't
be if you know this just happens sometimes you can't fetch do you can't
fetch and this is going to be very handy for anybody that's trying to do that or
people that are doing continuous integration they will continually be
downloading pulling things down and sometimes the snap just fails to grab
something and this is gonna help that maybe the connection resets cuz like for
me I'm on a my file lot this can be really cool so good for them everything
is continuing to move forward I say it's it's good to see all kinds you've got
flat we got news on flat packs we got news on snap packages Katie and live
today just announced that they're shipping the next test version of Katie
and live via app image for the first time or like they said something about
the first time we're shipping this an app image so they're still doubling
they've been talking about it before but they're doubling down an app image it is
and now let notes got see a sink so welcome to Linux everybody it's a party
hey and you're welcome to join it and just bring your own booze now I don't
know what to make of it I don't I don't care it's just as long as I can install
software if I could pick one I'd probably go with snaps or app images but
I'm happy with flat packs do I'll take PPA 2.0 just get it to me just just yeah
BYO packaging exactly you know let's talk about digital ocean for a second
let's take a moment and talk about something that's really simple and
straightforward it's an easy way to spin up a Linux rig on their super powerful
infrastructure in just seconds and probably less than a minute you could
have a Linux system up on one of their many data centers all over the world
with a 40 gigabit connection coming into that hypervisor they got SSD storage for
everything an interface that is so easy to use if you're a total noob or a long
time expert you're gonna have a good time and then when you're ready to grow
it's easy to increase your memory attach highly available block storage it's also
all SSD based a simple I API when you start having multiple systems monitoring
alerting to make you look like a boss and you're on top of things load
balancing as a service and ladies and gentlemen a brand new baby coming soon
object storage yeah yeah and if you sign up for early access you can receive one
terabyte for free through October 31st oh my gosh they don't they don't like
they don't ever rest like they don't do they just never take a vacation over a
digital ocean they're wrong like they just rolled out the new cloud firewall
which is such a brilliant thing now this object storage a simple easy cost
effective way man this is brilliant digital ocean is just killing it go to
digital ocean calm use our promo code do unplugged apply that after you create
your account you get a $10 credit and you can start messing around build a
system put it in production learn more digital ocean calm and use our promo code
do unplugged it's all one word you just apply it to your account digital ocean
calm promo code do unplugged so you heard mr. Michael Hall just a little bit
ago chatting with us and he joins us today but not from canonical anymore but
from now now flying the endless flag is the is the flag is it sort of is it is
it like really well rounded on the corners and with beautiful
translucencies and what's that flag look like Michael welcome back to the color
scheme I'm I'm picking up the whole thing it's a big change and yet not a
whole big change so I was talking about endless a few weeks ago on the show when
I was talking about how I think the future for gnome is extremely bright
beyond just the fact that more people are working on it and everybody just a
lot of things are lining up for gnome right now and on my list of things that
are lining up for gnome in the positive direction was endless and endless OS
which I believe is based on gnome shell am I right it is yeah it's got a
modified version of gnome shell so what is the what is endless about what is
sort of the elevator pitch on to endless for people that aren't familiar so the
company's mission summed up in a single sentence is the whole world empowered
and it's basically there are about three billion people who want a desktop but
don't have access to one for one reason or another and the company's mission is
to make a desktop that works for them price point they have the internet that
they have because a lot of desktops right now if you don't have internet
access or you've got very unreliable or very expensive internet access a lot of
the stuff that you know regular PCs will do but yeah are not available yeah when
they when the internet goes out which happens from time to time my smartphone
and my PC like I I have it happened recently I sat there Michael and I
thought to myself well what the hell did I do with my computer before I had the
internet like I doubt there was a time mean very long time before I was
regularly connected to the internet and now when it's out I it feels like
everything I can't search I can't reference Wikipedia I can't really pull
down my email it's it feels extremely limited so how does how does endless
address that specifically so there's a couple ways we go about it one is
preloading content like you said you go to Wikipedia a lot but how many pages of
Wikipedia do you actually go and see at any given time you can fit thousands and
thousands of these pages onto a few gigabytes of hard drive space so we'll
preload a whole bunch of Wikipedia content onto the hard drive of these
computers that go out so that all that information is there whether they have
internet access or not and then the second thing that we're working on is
what we call asynchronous internet and that's ways to deliver content in either
times where internet is cheap or when in the brief periods where they are
connected so sort of batching up like updates exactly so like if you've got a
newsreader app or something you've got an app for your local newspaper it
doesn't need to go and download the content every time you open the app it
can go download it overnight and get you you know the next day's stories already
there for you and a lot of the the bandwidth expense in a lot of the areas
of the world that we're targeting is really cheap at night when everybody's
asleep so people can download content when it's cheap use it offline when it's
expensive so why not why not a few apps on top of
Ubuntu why why a whole OS why why a complete solution because it feels like
it's more than just a desktop it feels like it's a whole integrated product and
solution it is it's actually it's built off of OS tree and flat packs oh okay
so the OS image is delivered through OS tree we can do transactional updates of
that and then you add apps to it via flat packs from GNOME software that's
some edge that's some cutting-edge stuff there yep and you know part of what
we're doing is we're working on a way now where you can load apps or OS
updates or even like application content updates onto a USB stick from a computer
that has internet access and then take it to a whole bunch of these computers
that don't have it and they can use what's on that USB stick just like they
would connecting to a remote server so they can get their OS updates they can
install applications they can refresh you know their news app whatever hmm and
so are they are they focused it's only on like the the markets that have like
occasional internet and and things like that or are they looking at also the
broader Linux desktop market that is the the specific market and it's kind of a
vague definition because it's not just like you know in Africa or parts of South
America but there's work being done right now in prison systems where those
computers are not connected to the internet ever for obvious reasons sure
but they still need a way to put updates on there get new content on there make
them useful without putting them actually on the internet absolutely gosh
that may avoid there must be there must be so many use cases for that and
there's really nobody that's rushing to fill that void because everybody wants
to integrate their OS is with their cloud product exactly but you know a lot
of these technologies that you were just talking about with flat pack and you
know like see async and everything they're all again make it easier to do
all of this offline or asynchronously so why um why also hardware because it's
pretty unique stuff it's got a unique look a unique design is this is this
part of the we don't just give out an image but is this part of the whole it's
one product thing so that to give it a little bit of history the the original
attempt that the company made was to use mobile hardware like tablets or phones
oh interesting they were gonna have them plug into a TV for a monitor you know
you might call like a convergence type experience yeah similar to what you know
a bunch of was going for but that that wasn't working out for them and they
tried some variations on that before settling on actually doing a desktop OS
based on Linux so once they started getting the the OS going they needed a
way to actually put this OS out there and give it a run make sure it works
show investors that it works so they did this line of hardware they did the
mission mini the mission one a couple others the devices that you've probably
seen the little white yeah which did their job of letting the company test
the OS in these markets with hardware that they knew it would work on since
then though they've been partnering with a sir and ASUS and HP and now those though
we I'm sorry the ones who are making hardware with endless OS running on it
and putting that out into those market no kidding so we're in Brazil and Mexico
and Guatemala right now and we are just about to launch in Indonesia wow
congratulations that's really great and so I guess as part of this growth they
brought you on and are you are you on there as is your official role like Lord
and dictator of endless or where do they fit you in there same role that I had at
canonical actually I'm a community manager and going to be working on
growing their community and helping the the users get in touch with the company
make sure we're getting good feedback into the company and vice versa cool so
I guess what excites me about endless is first of all brilliant idea seems like
that's a pretty good market to go after because even outside of developing
nations there is a lot of installations just in the West that sounds like they
could benefit from a system that's intentionally designed to be offline with
ways to update it via thumb drives and whatnot that's just I love all of it so
it to me when I heard this and thanks for filling in some of the gaps to me
the reason why I thought this is gonna be great for gnome was now you have a
company who's who's gonna have who's gonna have something based on gnome in
front of a lot of users that are truly that quote-unquote new user people that
really expect different things from their computer like it's gonna bring in
a whole new set of of users that are gonna drive finding more bugs they're
gonna drive future upstream development of gnome like I think that even more
deployments are going to increase the eyes on the bugs in the code like all
these things are going to stack up but what are some other ways that endless is
involved with the gnome project outside of just what seemed to me to be obvious
benefits so I mentioned flat hub already one of the endless employees Rob McQueen
is the one who's getting that set up he did the crowdfunding that you mentioned
and endless is already planning on shipping flat hub enabled by default in
future versions so that people who want to put apps available to endless users
submit them to flat hub they're automatically going to be available
that's awesome and that that is a just that would be great for hall clinics in
general really is just getting just getting a universal package format more
accepted and why flat packs and you know the history and the decision there was
it just because it's the whole gnome ecosystem I don't know the history of it
I think it's because there were a bunch of known people that started the
original engineering around this that's what was there at the start it was
available it worked so they went with it can you fill in any details around that
because that was the other thing I remember hearing about endless is that
there was some known people behind it right so I don't know all of them but I
know cosimo who I think he's been on your show before I'm not I can't
remember he's been on some show cosimo cos it yes yes the gnome director is an
engineer here at endless yeah it was Linux action show ages ago I think yeah
and I know we've got some others too I just don't know who's yeah I'm still
yeah I've been here for less than a month now so I'm still learning
everybody and what their past connections were so what are so what are
some of the secret future projects that you can you can tell us about and then
blame on the fact that you were new to the gig and didn't understand all the
rules like give us like give us a hint so if you go to community dot endless m
comm I'm gonna start posting some kind of teaser videos about what's coming in
the next version so endless 3.2 has got some really big changes we fell behind
in our sync with gnome so we were a few versions behind that's being caught back
up a lot of new flat pack improvements have landed a lot of OS and shell
changes have landed that makes it a lot better so I'm gonna start dropping some
short little videos showing off the changes you can check them out there
that's our forum site community dot endless m comm awesome I will link that
in the show notes to to make it easy for anybody that wants to lazy web that link
it looks like that's a that's a pretty cool resource so if I was if I was
looking to switch distros is this something that would be in is this
something you say yeah Chris is a long time desktop Linux user I think you
should give this a consideration or is it more for totally new users who are
coming into Linux and and want something just just something that's more met for
their expectations I would tell you to give it a try but if you're like a
hardcore tinkerer you're probably not gonna like the fact that it's got this
read-only OS tree system image oh interesting but you know if you've got
you know like a guest computer or something anywhere you've got Chrome OS
being run it would be a great replacement for that I actually just
gave I gave a laptop with it to my grandmother to let her try it out
because her windows well she's only had it for a little while now she played a
lot of online games so that's been some issues with flash but I put Chrome on
there and that seemed to have helped stuff I love it but he makes got some
some tough questions for you Michael see if you've managed to grok this stuff yet
go ahead mini yeah Michael do you have some upgrade priorities for your system
I imagine if you have bad internet so let's say you have priority call bug
fixes and other bug fixes and then at the end only application updates I don't
know yet I know the whole offline upgrade with a USB stick is still being
developed and I would imagine it uses just OS tree images so like the kernel
and the system libraries and stuff would all be in one update but if you have
some if you have normal online connectivity could the system just
decide okay I have online connectivity I have new kernels first I do a kernel
update if I have a connection I continue with the upgrades oh like like the like
the oh wow oh that is a neat idea so the update system itself says okay well now
that I've got a moment of data these are the most high priority but you know what
would be tricky about that is you also have to figure out dependency resolution
somehow right in fact so the OS tree models like it's like getting that it
has checksums for individual files right so you can check to make sure every
files legit so if there's a bad file you can you could abort the update so that's
pretty solid so you have a good chance the updates gonna work and it uses hard
links I think so I'm rough on my understanding but the OS tree is like
sort of it does the entire thing in one go and then it goes through and does a
full check of all the files to make sure that everything is solid and that there
aren't any corrupt files and then it flips the bit and says this is now the
live file system that kind of right and I think it keeps that old one around too
so if you go to reboot and something's wrong you just flip back to that old set
right which is sort of going back to what Lenart was saying like here's a
different way to do it Lenart's has CA sync now which is totally different thing
which I'm sure we'll learn more about in the future but this is another way to
deliver this feature set so sounds like maybe CA sync is going to deliver these
differences to OS tree images maybe I don't know I'll have to look more into
that interesting hmm so you do you do you I guess I want to make sure I
understand the the your answer to the hardware stuff sounds like sort of the
implication and your answer was is that endless might pull back a bit from
producing hardware now that they kind of have some momentum going and feature
more so it sounds like you're gonna focus more on working with upstream OEMs
did I did I just grok that yeah yeah I mean we don't we don't want to be the
hardware provider for endless OS that was a way to bootstrap things to get it
out into the market but we really want to work with hardware partners to get it
out there oh okay all right well you know what that seems to make a lot of
sense like I'm really excited about just something just something really focused
on that market focused on on it's so refreshing to hear here's somebody that's
building something that's not all about integrating their cloud solution and
it's more about building a system for people where they could be offline for
long periods of time because that happens to me quite a bit and it's gonna
happen to me in in in about a month I'll be offline for a large period of time
and so it'd be a great time to give something like endless a spin so I'm
considering throwing it on a on an XPS how's the high dpi support um I don't
actually have a high dpi monitor to test it on so I'm not sure I might give it a
go it's a gnome shell so yeah yeah you know and you got all that fractional
scaling well played sir well played well Michael is there anything else you want
to mention or tell us about endless before yeah if you want to get it the
the latest stable version is available at endless OS comm slash download we're
pushing bit torrent so if you could help us out by seeding it that would be
awesome we'd love you for it very good and then keep an eye out in about a
month the next major version should be coming out oh very well we will keep our
ear to the ground and I keep everybody updated and feel free to join us in the
future and tell us what's going on with the project I'm I'm excited I'm really
excited by it look forward to it yeah give it a try I want to see what you
think okay I might just time it perfectly with my offline trip and we
will report back now I before we go I wanted to just mention also really
quickly another bit of community news just sort of a quick aside our friends
over at elementary OS have announced their move over to github oh there he is
ladies and gentlemen mr. West Payne hello I'm late no problem been holding
the fort down though it's been an awkward show but now that you're back
everything's right so I just think I just mentioned that really quickly
because I think that's gonna be great for elementary OS yeah hopefully that
makes it easy to people to contribute exactly you get more people in there
it's exactly that's exactly what I was thinking you read my mind mr. West you
know what let's take a moment and thank ting go to linux.ting.com to sign up and
get $25 off a device if you want to grab one directly or if you bring one and
they have a CD main and they got a GSM network so you might just want to bring
one check out their BYOD page if you bring it you get $25 in service credit
son I'll tell you what girl it's $23 per phone per month on average for a ting
customer so you see why that $25 credits nice it's really simple in fact it's
it's the way mobile would work a lot of times outside the states my audience
tells me you mean this isn't how you guys do it it's it's obvious it's so
simple and obvious I guess it took two cows to figure it out and they launched
ting and now they have a simple smart way to do mobile you just pay for what
you use $6 for each line so if you want one line at $6 a month if you want two
lines at $6 a month if you got a phone that you occasionally use that's a
really really nice thing because you can have your main line like I do and then
you can have a standby line that's only six dollars if you don't use anything on
it and when you do need it you just pay for what you use your minutes your
messages your megabytes it's all clearly laid out on ting's website there's no
hidden charges or surprises you get a great dashboard to manage it incredible
customer service all the stuff you'd expect with a standard plan nationwide
coverage no contracts you can see your usage at a glance so you're on top of it
all the time bring a device or grab one from ting like check this one out Wes I
gotta scoot up here for this guy scoot up gotta get in get I gonna get yeah I
gotta zoom in here zoom in enhance this is the ANS h450r say that again the ANS
h450r Wes I'm sure you've heard of it right you might notice it's a it's it's
a bit rugged look I was gonna say it quite handsome it's rugged yeah it
looks like the fridge that Harrison Ford jumped in to survive yes you get it so
this is I bring this up because this son-of-a-gun is in the sub 70 market
when you use our code oh yeah go to linux.ting.com $65 Android phone now you
know it's not gonna be the S8 here it's not got the it doesn't have like the eye
tracking it does look like I could drop it and have a decent chance of not
scratch that is ruining yes that is exactly you get an Android 5.1 device
with a quad-core 1.3 gigahertz processor that does stand that could stand a nuke
test it's got Corning Gorilla Glass display that takes a punch it's got wet
touch technology yes you can laugh at a maniac during rainstorms while you're
using your phone like a boost yeah it's also apparently dust resistant
waterproof dust proof and get ready for this West is why I picked it for you
shockproof oh perfect yeah you're not getting it for its 2 megapixel front
facing camera though that is not but you know that's gonna catch you when you're
jumping out maybe I really prefer the lo-fi selfies yeah exactly yeah it's
like a learning that much it's retro yeah it's like a 70s so you can get it
with like you know 8 gigs or whatever internal but here's the thing West micro
SD and the son of a gun and if that okay if this wasn't enough for this truck
size Cadillac get this the son of a gun has a 2 sim slot well guess what guess
what that's pretty handy I don't know why does it have CD man GSM antennas in
it let me see no I just think it has CDMA all right no I mean I think it just
has GSM so I don't know why you would want two Sims it's a good question
maybe one goes bad on you it's like eyes it's like your eyeballs or your ears who
is better than somehow I'm sure Noah could tell us why we want want to he
probably has to yeah you're right he probably could Linux dot ting calm
that's where you go to get started you could go get yourself Cadillac phone
maybe just go get yourself that phone I mean I'm not judging to be honest with
you I'm not judging you I'm jealous I'm super jealous so we have ourselves a
barbecue coming up I should probably mention really quick because it's
getting not next week but the week after the 4th of July America's birthday go to
meetup calm slash Jupiter broadcasting if you're anywhere in the Pacific
Northwest if you're within I'd say six hours you should come because seeing
West's in a skirts worth it alone I would say I mean they usually on show
days wear skirts that's true yeah cuz you know we have to cut it off at the
table now I won't even now I'm not pretending like I'm not wearing a skirt
cuz I'm just not wearing any pants so if you want to see that yeah it's warm in
the studio it really does there's a lot of equipment and you want some flow you
do yeah you need otherwise you're getting distracted and if you're
thinking about other things you can't do a good show so meetup calm slash
Jupiter broadcasting that we'd really like to have you join us hang out maybe
help my chair does this squeak on you during text nap like this or is it just
do I just move around more than you do I mean it does squeak I think the latter
yeah yeah I do I'm conscious that it's it's funny cuz I'm not on camera I'm
just sitting here I could just sit here like a lump but instead I'm like moving
around constantly meetup calm slash Jupiter broadcasting I don't know what's
happening other than we're gonna be cooking a lot we're gonna be hanging out
I wonder if we'll have the VR set up or if we can enlist somebody set up the VR
we could have the VR go and that could be pretty fun and then we're gonna do
Linux unplug live we're gonna invite everybody to stay and hang out with us
and we'll have it going on the TV in the living room and we also have a couple of
chairs here in studio so if we get a couple of brave souls who might want to
go from a virtual lug member to an actual physical take it to the next
level right so meetup comm slash Jupiter broadcasting if you can make it just so
we kind of know how many people are coming as we can plan food wise and then
we probably are gonna stream it somehow I mean if nothing else we'll have the
studio cameras on who love the mics open so people come in and talk to the chat
room and I don't know they will have like a barbecue cam or something it could
be a lot of fun so it's we're gonna celebrate episode 200 of the unplugged
program there we go I got that out of my system I feel like we can do the show
now breathing room it was do you see that do you see that box behind you do
you see that there's a box back there is a box what's in that box these started
showing up around the around the around the web and they are they're hand
painted I believe tux mass sort of like a guy Fox mass but it's a guy this is
adorable isn't that pretty cool it's a system 76 been sending out these these
guys here I'll turn on do I have the do we have studio cam yeah there we do it's
not a very clear picture but here you can kind of see if you're watching the
video version you can kind of see the guy tux mask here and it comes in a
nice envelope with a wax stamp straps right to your face and so they have they
have quite a big they're making something something's going on there's
like a hashtag involved and there's a I also notice on the website there's a
countdown going on so I suspect if you go to the system 76 calm website and
look around for their revolution or look so it's either revolution of 76 or
hashtag revolution revolutionist 76 if you're on Twitter I think there's
probably some sales coming down the road but they're making look at this I don't
know what it is it could be something bigger though because I mean at first I
thought okay it's gonna be a big sale but then they start talking about the
people have forgotten what real freedom means to have the possibility of
attaining anything you can imagine rather than allowing limits to define
your greatest potential don't like to allow limits to define my potential
that's true on June 27th which is soon hashtag revolution is 76 commences for
which I have a grand surprise in store for our community this shall be the day
the day that we reveal to the world a global society of creators today we will
remind the people how to access freedom from surveillance from limitations from
restrictions so I so I don't know I don't know what this means access to
freedom sounds good though yeah so I don't know it could be at first I was
like well this sounds like open hardware almost like maybe they're gonna launch
does that was that what you were thinking something like that but it also
could just be a sale it could just be a sale I think it does go to show that
those system 76 keyboards the caps lock key definitely works it's very effective
yeah that smooth travel yeah that is a takeaway you can make and there's also
it's happening here in the tweet to look see see there's a lot of there's a lot
of caps in that tweet there too well what it feels that good why not you
pretty pumped up yeah hey so if you want to play with the it's pretty nice see oh
and then they have a website inside the mask open source revolution org let's go
there let's see what that open source revolution you know I'm having a hard
time typing today is a weird you're not wearing your mask it's because I all
they've had today is a is of is a smoothie oh it just goes to the website
I was already alright so you can go to if you want to check it out and so you
know you people people always say like oh let me put my sys admin hat on now
you can put your sys admin mask on yeah and you're ready to do some do some
penguin eating right all right do you think it would look good it might
the smells alright so I could wear that it's kind of loud though when we set
around on the table you know I mean it's not a good show prop yeah it'd be good
if this was more if we had a camera if we had a camera straight on to us but
anyways yeah so you can we'll have a link in the actually I hopefully I'll
have the image embedded if you want to see it in the show notes so duder linux
says that there's going they're gonna be launching new cases and stuff wow oh my
god West holy crap that was freaky man hello I'm gonna take a picture I just I
just I just turned over and Wes was wearing the mask I looked over at Wes
and he's wearing the mask and I I just about had a heart attack that is uh I'm
gonna tweet that so people can see what I'm talking about cuz that is some
creepy stuff yeah so duder says that he says that they're gonna be launching new
cases and stuff that could be it I'd like to see something I mean there's a
yeah there's a lot of there's a lot of there's a lot of caps and there's a lot
of promotion for freedom and open source so we'll see what's we'll see what it
comes out to be anyway so I'll post that later cuz I'm getting distracted by it I
wanted to cover something that I think is just really important anybody who
likes minecraft or and like in my case is a parent of a minecraft user two of
them as a matter of fact minecraft is going to this new back end this new
fancy bedrock back end that's gonna be a common core for minecraft on Windows 10
minecraft on Xbox and Android and console versions like that and tablets
and there is currently no back end for the Linux what yeah and there currently
is a they drop in Java yes exactly they're moving away now they're gonna
can't they're gonna maintain the Java version so it's not like Java the Java
versions going away forever but the issue is that if you want to if you want
to multi-play or if you want to download any of the new texture packs or any of
the new levels or skins you have to be in this new back end I see so if you
want it's the Java users will probably just be able to keep playing amongst
each other forever and I just never get any of the new cool stuff yeah my yeah
exactly my son Dylan says he's fine with that but I have it see what I'm worried
about is this eventually leads to dad I want Windows 10 and then that's this is
this we cannot have so they have this feedback dot minecraft dot net site where
there is currently a petition yes I know it's a petition there's currently a
petition going on for Linux support and it also is for Mac support but there
are more like radical approaches kidnapping developers children it's just
these petitions so so often fail to work because the developers themselves bring
in a certain bias to the market so this guy his name is mojang to toto MMO and
he's got a Windows icon you know he's got mojang in front of his name and he's
responding on the reddit post about this feedback thread and he says he talks in
here he says well one of the reasons we're not shipping for Linux is there's
there's no store there's no Xbox Live but they probably just have to build that
in there's no update mechanism for closed-source stuff so you would need to
make our own store and then we'd have to sell the launcher there and it's just a
massive amount of work for us and probably more than just porting issues
so he's saying the reason why one of the most highly played games in history
isn't getting ported to Linux is because they can't figure out a way to ship it
for Linux is what he's saying yeah ouch I would like I would like somebody to
tell him about flat packs and snap packages and app images yeah and then of
course they so somebody says what about using the distro third-party repositories
Google does this for Chrome and Debian you could set up your own repo and then
send updates that way and he says but how do you plug that into a store so
then people can buy it and if they don't buy it they don't get it you can't use
repo for paid updates out of the box also each distro can choose different
package managers so instead of one you have to support two and a lot more than
that really or go steam which is gonna be unlikely for Microsoft yeah that's
that part which is he totally acknowledges in this post he says I
ported a game to Linux before and the fragmentation of the and the
non-existence of the ecosystem makes Linux easily the most expensive platform
to support for developers which crossed them which crossed with minimal sales
makes it a really tough idea actually getting the game to run is almost the
easiest part and we're already there because they got working on Android to
the game I've ported sold something like 56 copies in the first month on Linux
this guy's a mojang a place everything theory or a former mojang employee he
might be an MS employee now I'm not sure but the anyways we'll have the thread
all that linked in the show notes if you would like to see it ported maybe it's
worth throwing in there because if it gets enough attention they'll learn
about ways to distribute software on Linux it's a solvable problem it's
actually problem we've already solved so I would love to see that because man
wouldn't it suck if Linux missed out on one of the most important games simply
because it was too freaking hard to figure out how to ship software on it
especially for you for so long when people were running like Minecraft
servers on Linux and I mean you know it feels like there's been we've kind of
been at least somewhat connected to it or it's been a part of our community or
at least on the edges of it for so long yeah architect points out I'm gonna I'm
gonna do this respond to this because they probably get this in the comments
to architect points out well you know Chris you could run you could run the
new bedrock or whatever it's called version in in wine you know maybe
crossover will build a build a nice easy installer and put in a bottle but the
the thing is is like my kids and all of my kids friends aren't gonna install
Linux to then install wine to then install Minecraft the might see the
thing is is right now there's the and this is kind of what this is what muddies
the water is there is a quote-unquote Minecraft launcher which is kind of
recent might still actually be in beta and is native and available for Linux
this is a native Minecraft launcher for Linux and that's been available for a
while now and then there's this new bedrock core version of Minecraft which
is only at present in terms of desktop computers available for Windows 10 there
is a port like a small educational version that they have forked off that
is available for Mac OS that is also based on the bedrock core there is
nothing for Linux and that's really depressing so links in the show notes
I'm gonna I'm gonna try to get in there I'm gonna try to pass around this
information to folks and maybe get the folks over there in touch with people
that know more about how to package up software deliver it and maybe get them
communicating with the folks that are developing the new Minecraft version so
that way they can get educated on what's available maybe we can help them so we
are working on it already behind the scenes it is tough though when you kind
of you you know you're relying on you know other games bigger games or things
where you weren't so assuming that there would be the store infrastructure you
know like a lot of games they'll just do it in game or that kind of thing it's
tough when we don't you know we have kind of those but we don't have great
set of primitives for hey here's your private DRM paywalled app it's just not
yeah yeah yeah yeah and it's one of those things where like the old version
is not gonna die necessarily so maybe it'll be just fine for a while but you
don't also want to be on the road yeah yeah there's yeah there's always there's
always the possibility that mine test could take off yeah well GB mine test
server that's what you're saying no I don't think late at the barbecue I don't
think so man you know I got you know I you know what I gotta do I gotta quit
playing video games takes up a lot of time but just never I never I never have
time for for anything because I'm just playing all these little race the Sun
here and there okay you're right just to wake up with okay you're right okay I
was teasing I I don't actually play video but I you're right I do play some
race the Sun from time to time you know what I you know what I would do if I had
some spare spare time I would lay seeds in my mind and I would then pour stinky
stinky fertilizer over those seeds I would then water it and maybe every now
and then splash in a dash of coffee grinds have you heard this coffee grinds
in your garden have you heard oh yeah sure you have uh-huh yeah I haven't done
it but I've done it don't do too much did you grow me some more coffee no I
grew tomatoes but this is supposed to be an analogy about your mind Linux
Academy comm slash unplugged see I was I was I got off on the I'm being excited
about coffee but the thing is is you could lay the seeds for your mind and
then Linux Academy that's the fertilizer you go in there you get some self-paced
in-depth video courses on every single Linux cloud DevOps topic the big stuff
too like Azure and AWS and your open stacks and oh my goodness oh my goodness
if you didn't if you don't have all of the basics of networking don't feel like
you're don't don't don't feel bad don't sit there and hide it from everybody
don't keep it your big secret just go to Linux Academy they got great courses all
that stuff hands-on scenario based labs to give you experience on real servers
human beings instructors that are happy to advise you and answer questions when
you get stuck course scheduler which is nice to work with your biz a schedule
learning paths with your series of courses and content plan by Linux
Academy's instructors iOS and Android for when you're on the go like West hey
oh and study guides like lesson audio and notebooks that you can take with you
and study offline and flashcards that are maintained forked and made even
better by a community stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members what's not
to love go there and try it out for seven days for free Linux Academy comm
slash unplugged this is a tool and a platform built by Linux enthusiasts
wanting to spread Linux to more people and make it more accessible and this was
their mission they combined up with developers and educators and now more
and more people's Linux Academy is just growing like crazy and they're build out
a team that keeps that content fresh builds in new stuff all the time they
have virtual labs that they really have nailed because you can pick the course
where distro click that and then it'll match up with the lab server and spin
that up for you that stuff is magic and I was involved in some of the
conversations on how they were putting it together super impressed with their
team really smart people running Linux Academy go to Linux Academy comm slash
unplugged and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged
program so I want to do a little follow we got a comment in last so we got a
couple of things so the first one I want to address is like just what it's like a
like a question I'd like to get people's comments that listen to the show
after the fact and the last week's show was like an hour and 27 minutes almost an
hour and 30 and the comment that came into the show was too short shows not
long enough that seems like it was probably and see in my world about an
hour is about probably just right for most commuters maybe hour and 45 for the
longer commuters 30 minutes is even a good time that's what we try to do with
Linux action news is about 30 minutes and it's you know so I was like I what
are your thoughts was I feel like an hour and a half was probably too long
last week I think like we went too long and so I'm kind of curious who you
think and I want to toss it out there for people listening on like the
YouTube's or and they're in their cars when they commute and can maybe tweet me
some feedback and let me know what they think or leave in the comments but your
thoughts what do you think I mean I I do agree that an hour it's a very
tractable time kind of understand it you know how to budget for it maybe an
hour and a half is less so it does bring up a good question about like how do we
want to manage that what do we shoot for and when do we break you know what's our
flex there in terms of like what we're having a really good discussion it makes
sense to go that longer or that deep dive made sense but hmm so maybe the
content should decide yeah I think that's why we went long is like that's
just what the content called for yeah but I mean we should think about how
it's distributed how people can listen to it I know that like you know I don't
want to get in position where it's always just a little too long and then
people aren't finishing it or feel like they don't get to enjoy it the right way
yeah or I don't want people not listening because it's too long right
like I got other shows I gotta listen to too I can't spend an hour and a half on
one show it could be a thing I would like to think that we would be high on
their list but you never know so give us your feedback either in the YouTube
comments or at Chris Elias let me know speaking of at Chris Elias Paul tweeted
me on some moonlight follow-up from last week this is really cool so remember we
talked about moonlight is an open source project that allows you to take
advantage of NVIDIA's proprietary lockdown only to Windows on chip GPU
accelerated network streaming moonlight opens that up for Linux users tablet
users Raspberry Pi users like it just opens that whole thing up and it's
really slick and you and I speculated we thought well could you use this to
stream a Windows desktop to a Linux PC yeah and this would be sort of like
screw wine screw VMs I'll just put a Windows box in the corner and just
stream the whole damn desktop using moonlight yeah well Paul tweeted me and
he said at Chris Elias you can use moonlight on the entire desktop by
pointing it at explore dot exe and it doesn't work on grid cloud so like it
won't work on AWS because it requires a hardware GTX we also said well shoot put
this up on a cloud exactly yeah but it needs a physical GTX card for that which
we know we knew that actually and then Alder wrote into the unplug subreddit at
unplug dot reddit comm he said sometime last year I had a grand plan of putting
a Windows PC in a corner and using it as a gaming appliance yeah yeah he said so
the idea was run Linux on a laptop with a clean-looking office space with
moonlight helping to bridge the gap of missing games for Linux but suffice to
say I ran into a few problems I tried every version available of moonlight on
the iPad 3 on the Nexus 5x on an Android TV box Linux laptop Windows laptop
chromium extension and the Java client they all performed amazingly up to 720p
at 60 frames per second but there is some input lag but it's mostly workable
especially with a single-player game where the where twitch or a frame twitch
FPS or competition isn't the goal as in you know it's not super twitchy but
rather the experience of enjoying the game in that use case it's fantastic
however once I try to push it up to 1080p the leg became very bad the H to
see the h254 which I don't know if that's typo or maybe it is h254 stream
freaks out at times you have to wait for it to come back it does reconnect but it
does freak out from time to time he was running on an Intel for a four core
Intel rig with an NVIDIA 970 and then later he put a 1080 in there and he had
it connected to a gigabit LAN as far as you could see there wasn't a bottleneck
in the setup but he just thought maybe it wasn't up to snuff he also mentioned
messed around with Wi-Fi and things like that so he says you make sure we have
some network stuff but he says he's happy to report the video drivers didn't
really seem to make a big difference same performance with different video
drivers he says I don't I'm not sure anyways he says I just wanted you guys
to know that if you dig into it it's pretty close just needs a little more
work and give a little forgiveness on the performance from time to time but if
you're doing a 720p stream you're gonna be pretty happy up to 60 frames per
second that's reasonable yeah especially if you're just trying to pull you know
pull down a Windows desktop application like I mean after we talked about is
like well this could be a great way to do Photoshop or maybe even premiere
that 720p would be pretty limiting or for me you know you might even like I
remember using this plane with the steam streaming stuff yeah I just wanted to be
hanging out with my roommates in the living room but I didn't want to like
drag my tower and hook it up to the TV but they just like said I could play on
this little laptop and yeah kind of a similar thing kind of a similar thing
so thank you guys for I got a couple other people that wrote about moonlight
and they were similar in tone so I thought that would probably be a good
summation but I was we actually got a few bites on that moonlight topic I was
surprised maybe I should go try it so yeah if you do let me know let me know
let me know how it goes let me know how it goes if you'd like to join us here in
the show we'd love to have you with the we have a decent see how many people
right now we have if you expand the window here hold on let me see I'm gonna
tell you we have eight people have joined us this week which is pretty good
we love each and every one of you they're not super talkative this week but
we love having them here and that's nice but we have had sort of like in the past
we've had up to like 40 50 people in that room it's been a park and I think
the summertime is here and people are out out and about enjoying yes so there
is an opening for a new opportunity for new voices and new opinions come talk
about Linux yeah the opportunity is there it's not as crowded as it has been
and the you could take advantage of the summertime exodus just I think we have a
just go to the go to the chat room really because we you can find out about
the guide that we have you can find out about the mumble room so really the best
resource is to go to jblive.tv and just go to the embedded chat room there you
can do bang mumble to get the mumble server information and then we'd love to
have you join us next week and if you don't make it to mumble the IRC is fun
too yeah yeah you can definitely hang out in the IRC we're watching that
during the show as well we we do try to this is you know we have less less stuff
live than we did because Linux action is to be live right so this is you know
we're kind of moving more towards this is the big live show that we do for our
Linux community so we'd like to see more people get involved I know it's during
the day and that makes it rough for a lot of people right but it's just kind
of the way it's worked out for us I you know it's another option we just do it
even earlier in the day and that's gonna be good for anybody involved it's not a
good idea but we'd love to have you if you can make it so go to jblive.tv
you'll find the chat room or go to irc.geekshed.net and it's a hashtag
Jupiter Broadcast and you don't have to be here the whole show you know you can
chime come in chime in on a couple issues hang out and disappear yeah like
like mr. Hall today you know he came in and we would wish we kind of had to get
out of here by six o'clock East Coast time and so we just kind of you know
make sure we chatted to him before then and then he's chatted a bit with us then
he was out and I think that works too if you can't make it for the whole show
we're just happy to have you for a bit sometimes same with poppy and wimpy
they'll pop in when they're when they're not podcasting themselves yeah also I
guess Mozilla has a new podcast coming I saw that that's an interesting little
headline before we get out of here yeah there's there's been a lot going on in
the Linux community this week and so one of the things that I've been doing is
I've been transitioning Linux unplugged a bit to more about the community stuff
so you know talking with Michael Hall about endless and talking about the
elementary project moving over to github and I'm trying to get more community
stuff that isn't necessarily headline grabbing it's still good discussion here
in this show because every Monday we have Linux action news now it's about a
half hour long it ranges depending on the news and a hell if if our most
recent episode maybe it wasn't our best yet episode oh man because you know what
it was and I don't mean it too I wouldn't I really wouldn't tell my own
horn unless or whatever that's a phrase was it it's definitely not tooting my
horn actually kind of like it's I'm tooting my own horn here it's pretty
good I like that well the skirt makes it real easy so I'm not wearing a skirt I'm
not wearing anything you know I was looking at the news in Linux action news
6 Linux action news episode 6 we covered Debian 9 getting released tales 3
Firefox 54 free nose 11 open media vault 3 plus we did follow-up from the
previous week's episode and Joe gave a boon to touch on his phone a spin and we
managed to get all of that in 30 minutes and I I swear I'll stand by it it's all
of the most important things about all of those releases you need to know and
then we just get through it and it doesn't feel super rushed it just it's I
think because Joe and I have been doing Linux news coverage ourselves for so
long that we really come into it and we really it's just I really like the way
that episode worked so if you haven't checked it out yet or if you checked it
out and haven't come back check out Linux action news episode 6 I thought it
turned out great and speaking of that Debian 9 story there's something I just
wanted to mention before we get out of here Debian 9 did come out this week
congratulations to the project it is always a big big deal when Debian 9
comes out and this release is dedicated to the projects founder Ian Murdock who
did pass away on December 28th 2015 so Debian 9 is dedicated to Ian and I
thought that was pretty cool I thought it was worth mentioning it's really kind
of classy of the project to do that too all right that'll bring us to an end of
this week's unplugged program steaming right towards rushing at a mad pace
towards our VLUG barbecue meetup.com slash Jupiter broadcasting go there
check it out if you want more Wes Payne check out the tech snap program yeah I'm
gonna be listening this week cuz there's a story that didn't make it into this
show that I think you guys are gonna cover in typical fantastic tech snap
fashion don't forget our mumble room we'd love to have you participate with
us live follow the network at Jupiter signal thanks for being here and we'll
see you right back here next Tuesday. Say goodbye Wes. Goodbye.
And the value of this is negative. So go figure I don't have my co-pilot this
week and right before the show starts like I was already on the air it was
actually I think 1.55 something like that the OBS machine lost all of our so I
couldn't grab like my screen and stuff like it lost all the capture yeah yeah
so I had to had to fix that super quick and then got that all solid and then I
started the show and realized into the show that in fact it's it's happened
again it happened again my my browser highlighting extension that I use that I
was just using before the show started that I went through and highlighted like
this this fedora 26 blog post because it was thick and long and it was meaty and
I was like I like I don't need to put I don't need to read all of this in the
show because this would be an hour-long show of me just reading this post so let
me highlight these sections I highlight upstairs I come downstairs and using
Chrome upstairs and I come downstairs and my extensions gone and so I
installed it I stopped the show I stopped recording explicitly to install
because I guess like there's no way I can do this next story without this and
without you here to fill dead air time like I can't sit here and search through
a thing right so I'm like I got to stop the recording which I never do unless we
have a crash I stop recording then I go and I install the extension and now it's
gone again and I did that mid show and so there's no way I'd install the
extension during the show and I was using it to read up to our last story I
was using the highlight function and now it is actually gone from Chrome again I
really can't I can't fathom like shareware extension where you get like
six highlights and then it uninstalls itself it's actually you know Diago or
di GGO it's it's actually a paid service that I've been using for yeah
it's disabled this extension may have been corrupted it says oh what the hell
is repair extension okay so I just okay can I just if I can if I can click a
button and say repair extension and then another screen comes up and says would
you like to repair extension and I click repair extension why doesn't it just
automatically repair extension yeah and then is it is corrupt yes repair and why
is it corrupt on this I wonder if I'm having a mismatch in versions I wonder
if I have a newer version of Chrome here or something that I do upstairs I wonder
if that's what's going on wonder if this is a side because I didn't update on
this computer yesterday so I'm on Chrome 59 here need a script that'll just
update all of your workstations yeah all right JB titles calm we got to get out
of here for mr. West JB title leave you high and dry it's all right it's all
right it just is so I had like that hardware thing so I was it was just a
weird start it was a weird start for the show it was that's all right hi it's too
bad I was actually really excited about I mean I'm always excited about love but
I was especially excited about this one yeah we it I think at all it all shook
out in the end Wes it all shook out all right Jimmy titles calm everybody go
boat so it sounds like the way land is going it should really just be called
like I don't know it's basically like Pac-Man
syu but just for all of your yeah yeah yeah when we got done afterwards we're
because you don't when you're recording you don't know how long the length of
the episode is because you know you're recording for a while before you start
you record for a little bit after you end plus you know you might stop midway
during the show or something like that and so we didn't know because we had a
quite a bit more than a half hour in the recording so when it published and it
came in around a half hour I was like damn like that's amazing that not only
did we not like watch a clock but with all of that stuff we still managed to
nail it I mean I was a editing machine yeah things yeah yeah don't forget the
door knocker oh oh yeah oh that's actually what threw me off wow thanks
MN that's what threw me off super bad is so I was actually I actually had a good
groove going I got I bounced back from the technical failures I hadn't ran into
the gnome extension issue yet right so I hadn't hit that flaw so I didn't know
what was down the road but at 202 201 so this I'm starting up I'm spinning
everything up where I've already hit record we're getting ready to go the
doorbell rings oh no and five minutes before the doorbell ring I got a
telegram from Angela said by the way there's somebody coming to work on the
roof guys having his friends over yeah right at least though she says by the
way somebody's coming to work on the roof don't worry I've pre-briefed him
not to ring the doorbell not to knock on the door I told him you are in there
recording it says I know shit yeah cuz it it always happens yeah there's no way
right cuz like it's instinct especially for people doing roof work like they you
know they they want you to know what that noise is they want you to know why
there's somebody in your yard so they feel obligated to talk to you right for
the like regardless of what they've been instructed like they feel for their own
personal reasons they have to so it always happens and so so but what threw
me off was like all of it like we this guy we went out of our way to tell him
not to do it and so that was kind of frustrating and then also like he took a
long time like he was just talking to me about something like I'm like I'm doing
I'm like I'm on the air right now I didn't say that to him I'm like like
but that frustration builds up in the back of your mind you're like okay I got
a clock ticking I'm I've got a sound clip you should just had him come right
in you kind of had that I know right I should have I'm like could you come in
here and talk to me yeah I had like a sound clip of for like a certain amount
of time that was playing so I didn't have dead air I'm like okay well I've
got this amount of time to talk to this guy before they before we have dead air
so then I sat down and I was totally flustered by it all because we just
really went out of our way to make sure that didn't happen and then I started
thinking like well god can we just never ever schedule stuff on show days but we
always have a show to sell a lot of show today yeah yeah and people don't want to
come out on Saturday yeah yeah so it's the after that and that really did throw
me off this it was a it was a weird episode you know it's just weird weird