Speaking of how great Windows is
There is a new subreddit that it chronicles the most public blue screens of death ever and at first I was like oh, haha
That's old joke, but actually some of these are really good really really good like hey Wes check out
Take a look at this picture here
I don't even know what this is but look how fancy that is that's in a mall
Where they have like a twisted display and the twisted display blue screen
I'd be really curious to see what that looks like when it works. Yeah, right every fifth
Look at this guy sitting there and a massive blue screen right there on that screen. It's almost like art
It is kind of like art. It is kind of beautiful in a way
Yeah, giant giant blue screens giant blue screens, so there is a subreddit now
Dedicated to the most epic blue screens ever and if you check it out
I'll have a link in the show notes some of these are kind of artistic in their own way
The blue screen of death is in its own way gotten its own
Its own status in popular culture so in fairness. Do we need to spin up a Linux kernel crash?
subreddit right right
No, it's not the blue screen. We don't have the blue. Yeah, yeah, although something went something went wrong with your computer
Is the new error message?
Yes, there's my poster photo that said it was just a big word that said error you have an error
Thanks
This is really this is really I love the caption for this Ars Technica photo
So this is the mall one again. We have these wrap displays, and it says malls can they get any more soulless
Yes, thanks to the blue screen of death
Yeah, that's pretty awful mmm. That's pretty gross
You know what I want an ARM powered Linux laptop Linus says it's gonna happen, but maybe not in 2016
He's looking for it though. He said that at Linux con in Europe
He said that I'm happy to see that arm is making progress one of these days
I will actually have a machine with ARM that they said it would be this year
Maybe it'll be next year 2016 will be the year of the ARM laptop
I don't know actually that's a good question. I don't think so
I think when Linus says that he's talking about something kind of along the lines of the MacBook Air that you just buy yeah
And it runs consumer easy-peasy
We're starting to see a higher end Chromebooks now. I mean yeah, yeah
You know who's gonna try to compete with a $500 Chromebook with an arm chip instead of an Intel CPU
You know I was on
Yeah, I would rather have it run the Linux really I mean much much rather I was on tech talk today
I was talking about these high-tech nomadic
That are are living off the grid quote-unquote they're staying connected to the internet
But living off the grid and one of them is you guys may know of him as Joey Hess
He is a Debian software developer. He I'm not sure if he's currently with the Debian project
But he did help develop the Debian installer. He created git annex. He's nice. Yeah
He's working on a software that uses Dropbox
Git and a few other things to sync all of your dot files between all of your Linux machines right like wouldn't that be nice?
So Joey he is an interesting individual because he pines
He says he pines for an ARM based Linux laptop because he's using a Dell Mini 9. He's been using it since 2008
He's worn out two keyboards. He's gone through two SSDs. He's upgraded it to two gigabytes of RAM and
He lives
Totally off the grid he has solar power on a good day
he says he gets 50 amp hours, but on most days he gets 15 amp hour 15 amp hours and
He says he's when power is low he often hacks in the evenings by lantern light
That's adorable, and he says he would kill
Kill for a powerful ARM based laptop something that would you know use way less power?
Right exactly that was what I was gonna say is when I say ARM laptop. I want something that's significantly fast
You know yeah, well you could you do you have your average everyday expectations met yeah?
I mean it doesn't have to be doesn't have to be a screamer
But you know here
I am a few months into this XPS 13 that I have and it's got a core i7 quote-unquote mobile processor
Which is actually a dual core processor with hyper threading that makes it look like four cores
I don't know why that's called an i7, but apparently in laptop jargon that qualifies as an i7 and you know I notice it I
notice I it's been a while since I've you know use a dual core as my daily driver and I
I don't know. It's still a really nice performing machine. Yep, but it's also my newest computer, and it's not my fastest computer
That's a little disappointing. It's a but it's a bummer. It's a bummer
That's precisely because Intel's been focusing on power management last couple of and I I appreciate I get four or five hours of battery life
I do appreciate that that makes a difference
But the reality is if I can if I'm sitting here with a quote-unquote i7 and an SSD
And I'm going not fast enough. There's no way arm
Failed that yeah, the arms just arms not gonna be fast enough for me for a while
I don't think I yeah, you want you do have higher expectations than
Terminal based probably I mean I would claim that Intel has maintained a lead because of their manufacturing prowess
And now they've stumbled with the latest you know process node
So is this the point where arm catches up maybe and if you go like West saying you know if you're doing terminal development
Maybe you have a web browser and email, and that's just about it
If you can tell me here's an arm computer that doesn't need to be charged for 10 13 hours, so that runs Linux
That would be very very tempting when I'm off-grid that would be very very tempting
Yeah, or your arm computer is well not for off-grid, but your arm computer is your interface to a droplet in the cloud
Yeah, exactly he so Joey says I seem to live half the time out of range of broadband and still use dial-up
He uses dial-up two gigs of RAM dial-up. Yeah, so I'm fully adapted to asynchronous communication
I download my mail with offline IMAP as well as blogs get converted to RSS to email
I use a distributed version control
Extensively and use my git annex to maintain large quantities of local data and cube large files to transfer in rare times
When I'm around fast internet, that's really neat. That's really neat
This is Linux unplugged episode 114 for October 13th 2015
Welcome to Linux unplugged your
Weekly Linux talk show that is drinking dawn of the red and Indian style pale ale. That's right
My name is Chris and my name is Wes. Hey, Wes. You are the you're the good soldier here that brought these dawn of the
Red I've never even seen this before I hadn't either
What do you think coming out of Eugene, Oregon a local brewery and look at that a 7% alcohol?
Whoo, this will be a fun one guys. Is this my second or third?
Better not tell yeah, okay
I will cover it up on this week's episode of Linux unplugged
There is a KD elephant in the room a big plasma monster
we're gonna talk about that today and some accusations being thrown around some new application updates coming out and all of that goodness from
the plasma folks as well as
What I believe is the one true
The one true ring no
I'm kidding the one true form of integration or whatever you want to call it canonical calls it convergence
Microsoft calls it. I think continuity or continuity or something like that. I
Actually think there's something here today that we all could install you don't even have to be a KDE desktop user
To take advantage of a really slick integration between your phone and your desktop. You don't need a dock
You don't need any special set it already. We'll tell you about it. Yeah, and then later on in the show
I've been looking at options
Something easy to recommend to people that is an open source to drop in set and forget it a router for the home
That gets updates that stays secure that uses software. We can trust we're gonna talk about that today in the show as well and then
Then we're gonna see if we can end curses all of the things
King Looper put us to the challenge and wants us to end curses all of the things every last thing every last damn thing damn
Yeah, we're gonna do it with the help of the mumble room. That's right
Well, actually with soul reliance on the mumble room
We have a couple of suggestions, but this is a mumble room app pick segment that we'll be getting to which was requested by the mumble
Well, there you go. They get what they want
Yeah, now it's coming to you. All right, and speaking of the mumble room, let's bring them in time appropriate greetings virtual log
Zombies don't run Linux. It's good to have you there Danica's in there too. That's good. I love guys
So I just really quickly a bit of Katie follow-up, you know
The guys over at the Katie project are doing things in an interesting way
You got the plasma desktop and you got the Katie applications and all this different stuff
It's a whole set of applications and the Katie applications 1508 just got a release today
as we are recording this release contains bug fixes translation updates a
Nice update a good safe update for everybody if you use arc or Kate or Katie PIM or localize any of that stuff
This is a great update. Plus this release also includes long-term support versions of the KD development platform for dot 14 dot
13 and I'm gonna underscore that Katie 4.14 dot 13 is still getting updates
The reason I'm going to underscore that is because that brings us to our first bit of feedback from KN RO in the Linux action
Show subreddit does lass hate Katie
Some strong words. Yeah, so I just listened episode 386 of lass and while they were covering Linux usage at the very large array
Chris noted that it's probably red hat with Katie and then no it just couldn't help himself but claiming the Katie is a strange desktop
For such an environment. I mean what the hell laughs. This is not the first anti Katie sentiment that I have heard on the show
I mean, I know you're narrow your gnome fanboys
But can you just try to stray a little bit towards neutral if the Linux action show not the gnome?
action show and this is a this is a
this is a charge that has been lobbied our way directly and
I
Just got off of reviewing netrunner and netrunner came with the netrunner rolling release came with the plasma 5 desktop
And I did have some critical things walking away from there
And I'll just give you a couple of things that happened to me and these are just my experiences
so I'm trying this on a system 76 bonobo and
Traditionally these have been extremely reliable Linux computers without any hardware issues
It's a really safe platform to test a distribution on they've seen a lot of distributions yes
And I had weird things just in the last couple of days for example
I would go click on the menu and then shut down and nothing happens
and then I would click on the menu again and click shut down and
Nothing happens, and then I would click on the menu again and click shut down and it would shut down
Oh, that's almost worse than it never working. Yeah, right
It's just very strange or there was another time where I was thinking about something
I wanted to try and I was just sitting here looking at the screen not even doing anything and
plasma 5 just crashed it just crashed like the desktop just crashed didn't even touch it and then I
Put a thumb drive in which is actually still in the machine
I put a thumb drive in and the little notification box comes up says hey you put a thumb drive in and I click open
And file manager the entire desktop session freezes the entire desktop freezes
I can still alt tab control tab over to my other virtual consoles
totally frozen
All right, so I restart everything and I restart relaunch get all my thing we get everything reloaded again
It's whatever I bounced back. It's not a big deal, but it's one after one after one like this
There's a lot of little things that we ran into during the testing that I walked away thinking
This is unpredictably unreliable to me like I can't I can't even fathom
What's gonna cause it to crash like I can't even wrap my head around and then just avoid that behavior and avoid it if you
Wanted to and this is generally the point
Where rotten corpse would jump in and tell me that kde 5 has not been declared stable
Do you want to make that point now rotten?
Yeah, thank you, and so very much so
It's something you have to understand is that there is a long-term support development platform
Which I just told you about the version 4.14 that's out
And if you're actually gonna run kitty as a daily driver
I think you might want to consider that do you agree with that rotten and isn't that your daily driver right now? It is my daily
driver and why not plasma 5
Because it's not stable. Well, but they haven't declared it stable. It is pretty stable in the sense of
Most people who's been testing it and with 5.4. So and also it matters what distro you're using it on because
The net runner is not a good example of
well
Quality in my opinion. Yeah, I mean you take issue with the managerial base and things like that, right?
right, I take I don't like men draw it in any way whatsoever and
I think that's a terrible base
But I also think that a lot of the decisions that netrunner made are nothing to talk, you know right home about
Like the fact that they have stuff pre-installed. Okay, so that takes 10 seconds to install something. That's yeah
Yeah, and actually to that point one of the things I like the most actually the fact that they had steam library
System libraries and clear all clear all whatever it was. That's actually from managerial. They inherited that from manager
Yeah, so okay. There's there's different weird things that
they did that they just decided that wouldn't really work well and
They even decided to rip out some of the plasma 5 stuff and go back to some for stuff which makes really no sense
but
Like if you look at kabuntu, there are a lot of people who are talking about kabuntu 1510 and using beta
Wnsx is one of them
another person in the mumble
Frequently fretsil is one of them and they've been using it for the beta for a long time and had no problems at all
So it doesn't matter what distro is implementing the plasma 5. So rotten. Do you think it's a little?
Inappropriate and maybe a little premature for certain distributions to be shipping the plasma 5 desktop
I think it used to be now. It's understandable like
5.4 is very close to being a solid release and even production ready
But you have to have the latest version of 5.4. So the latest good quality version is 5.4 point 2
Netrunner s 5.5 point 4.1, which is not as
as
Polished right because they make new releases all the time and if you don't keep up with it
But the odd thing is that of all distros kabuntu is keeping up with it
because they're they were they're currently their beta is currently 5.4 point 2 and
How much they're keeping to keep up with a PPA or whatever who knows? Yeah, but I think 5.4 is good enough
I think 5.5 is going to be like the first solid
Production ready everything. This is what I've been hoping about 5.5 and and Wes. I'm almost virtually positive
You're not a plasma desktop user. Have you experimented with it since the 5.0 releases come out?
And since then have you looked at it? Uh, yes, I have installed a preview of it when it was very new
I have not used it since maybe
5152 I don't quite remember which version it was and I like a lot of what they're doing
I have I do not have personal experience that with is in production ready
And that's you know, a lot of these what is the threshold for you before you would be willing to try it out?
Is it just your workflow is is good enough now or is it you've heard enough horror stories that you're not even interested
I think I fall in the I tolerate crashes and setbacks a little better than a lot of people
Yeah, I have a little more. Yeah flow in my workflows than some so that's not a huge deal to me
So maybe now maybe now is the perfect time for me to give it a shot
Yeah, and I so my takeaway was is I actually for a long time. It was a KDE user. I actually really
Really there's elements of the plasma 5 desktop
I like a lot and I have found different iterations of the 5 desktop to be more stable than other right?
yeah, and so for me I just I
Can't help but take a I when I start having these problems
I can't help but take a step back and go wow
What if I was an average user and I didn't know to expect this or I didn't know this was beta
Or I didn't know how to solve this problem
This some of these things I run into would to me be fundamentally unsolvable problems that make them
Unusable and a lot of times when I get the when I get the feedback about you hate KDE. It's I
Think it's misinterpreted as I think there's a lot of use cases where plasma 5 doesn't make sense
And there's somewhere plasma 5 does make sense
And I just think there's a lot fewer use cases where plasma 5 makes sense than even
plasma 4
So anyways, I I it is getting there
I'm not but I hate I hate the idea that if we if we critique a few things we come across as anti KDE
That's not really my intention. You're still interested in a succeeding it absolutely developing. That's why I can
Check it out. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, no actually is an interesting issue because when
I'm a known fanboy and I have been for like a decade and
When I used KDE 4, I noticed some problems that were fixed in 5
So plasma 5 had all like 99% of what I hated about 4 was in 5
So I was like, I'm I'm excited for 5 and it helped me kind of pull back from critiquing
4 and saying look how this is crap. This is crap
You realize that it's going to be better
But right now just look at the different pieces what makes KDE good
So it's a weird approach like if I had done this test that I did later earlier this year if I had transitioned
Two years ago, it'd be completely different. I would have hated KDE. Hmm, but now
Since I had the perspective that the stuff that I hate is going to be fixed or is already fixed, you know
They're working on it, right?
Well, I like there's here's here's the biggest problem that I have with KDE 4 is that if you like people who like dark themes
Which is a lot of people now
I'm one of them. I have a dark theme
Globally associated to my KDE and I'm a big fan of that
but if
You do a KDE 4 dark theme it will destroy the look of Firefox
Yeah, it fixes it actually makes improvements on some applications like if you for example just load up file filezilla
Well silly is hideous by default, but KDE will fix it and make it look good, which is weird
but it makes it look good, but it takes Firefox and just like
It's Firefox and Thunderbird and makes them just completely crap that you have to stop and fix it or not use it
Well, that's interesting because Firefox and Thunderbird have their own theming things that you think would override that anyway
It's because they're based on GTK 2, right?
Yeah, and that's that's the fundamental problem of the UI, but if you
Run Thunderbird and Firefox in plasma 5 that problem is gone. They fixed it completely
Hmm, so that that problem that I originally go. Holy crap. This is awful
I'm not really pissed off about it because I know it's been fixed and I'm going to get a better version
Yeah, it does help when you know, they're working on it. That is very true. And actually Alan since you're here
I guess I kick it over to you
It is KDE a better
BSD citizen than gnome or has known been pretty good about when they when they build something that say requires login D
They work with well other projects to make sure that so at BSD can this year one of the gnome developers presented?
A talk at our conference. Oh, yeah, I mean how they actually have free BSD in their continuous integration system
Okay, so that they because the problem before was, you know KD's developers make a commit that breaks free BSD
six months later, they do a release on that and then eventually that shortly after that gets ported to free BSD and
Eventually a user gets it and tries it and finds a problem by then the developer that made the change
It's been eight months and he's moved on to something else. Yeah, for sure
So by integrating previously into their continuous iteration system, they find these bugs within 24 hours and
So it's helped them ensure that gnome runs properly on on free BSD
That's good by actually doing that and we're glad to be able to try them to help they needed to get that going and to see
That they actually have an interest in doing that. Yeah, for sure
Heaven's revenge you think you've got it figured out why people think I am anti KD take it sir. Oh
Yes, but one quick thing on the previous D usage. Yeah, that's considering free BSD uses clang is its default compiler
It can also use a lot of static analysis and find a bunch of crazy corner case bugs that the Linux distribution
Choose GCC is default but not fine. So it might help the stability on the BSD platform versus
Hmm that's an interesting point
Alright, so that helps definitely in the back end in the background. So is it something I've been saying?
Is it the way I talk about it? What is it?
Well, we used to love on KDE, but then you know how gnome had a very rocky start. Yeah
Yeah, yeah. Yes, sir. Well, we started seeing it improve. We were trying to give it
Props and have people not be scared to try it. So we're giving a lot of positivity to warm usage
So that might be why people are thinking that you're being negative about KDE by ink
By encouraging the areas that need fixing and things like that. So, you know, such or at least attempt. Yeah, I actually we did some episodes
I actually we did some episodes dedicated to the issues with gnome 3 it was in fact, I remember I remember being
If I took it took years, in fact, it wasn't until January 5th
2014 a season 30 episode 4 of the Linux action show so it has been a while now back in the seasons
Yeah back to the seasons where we said gnomes getting good enough now knew like it wasn't until January 5th
2014 that we said
Now gnome is turning the corner and it's worth checking out and until then we were not of that opinion
Yep, and it's it's just there is a threshold like you were saying and I think maybe this is something worth exploring a little bit
You're willing to live with a few extra bugs assuming it's something I'm interested in and it's makes it worthwhile to check out and Rodden
It was kind of saying the same thing
He's willing to live with a few extra bugs if he knows they're working on it
And I think it is interesting that people were very critical of gnome and now there's a lot of people who that's all been
You know, it's gone now people people. Yeah base their whole work now. There's nothing to fear. It was of what it used to be
Yeah, yeah true true
Yeah, so what was it the real problem was your comment was you know, why is this was a scientific project was it?
Wait, what you know the VLA? Oh, oh, I that I was surprised that there you know as common
I was surprised that they were using KD because it was an old Red Hat installation
Which means it was a very old KD installation, right?
but the reason to use KD in that setting is
because your
Scientists are Windows users and they're coming over and I agree the same
I think I the reason why I use KD boy, but if you're a KD advocate
That's not the number one reason you want people using KD. I wouldn't think it's because it makes switching easier
Yeah, yeah, and and as far as deploying something for scientists to use that's the main thing. Yeah, I agree
I think that's why they were using it too
It was just a it was a throwaway comment that didn't leave a lot of room for I mean
I didn't feel like going into a five-minute explanation about it. But that was that was essentially it. I
Agree Kitson. You have a comment you want to make about combativeness
Yeah, I've noticed that the KDE devs for the most part like on the forums and even an IRC
Can tend to be a little bit combative about their decisions and whatnot when they do receive criticisms or suggestions?
Just like what you have mentioned time and time again about like the sound module and whatnot
And it still hasn't remained changed and it still is a problem
Yeah, it's kind of funny how much of a problem it is too
If you have if you have a computer that has built-in speakers and a headphone jack
HDMI out and like say maybe like a USB audio device. I understand
This is maybe not a super common setup
But I am describing the setup of anybody that has a laptop and hooks up a USB sound card can't be that uncommon, right?
Because most laptops have HDMI that does audio most laptops have a headphone jack and if you hook up a USB sound device
It's not that weird now you got three
And so what we discovered in the latest version that we detested was the way you make sure that sound goes out the right
sound card because in a lot of applications like mumble and Skype they just say
We're gonna use whatever the pulse audio default is you can't you can't specify
What the default sound card is you can just choose default pulse audio device?
So you have to mandate and pulse what your default device is system-wide
Okay, I can roll with that not a big deal
So I go I go in there and the only way to make sure that the sound is going out the right sound card is
By actually turning off all the other sound cards so instead of selecting your sound card
It is a process of elimination you go to the HDMI adapter you turn it off
You go to the built-in headphone jack you turn it off you go to the built-in speakers you turn it off
And then you go to your your USB audio device, and you choose from five different options in the drop-down
Analog stereo duplex, I don't know why it has to have all those different options
I don't know why it has to be a process of elimination
And I actually had to have so I had to have Rekai come down here and verify with his own eyes that I was doing
The right thing because the UI is so odd and so weird now is that a big deal once you learn it
No, but when you pick it up. It is very very strange, and I think these are legitimate points that we make all right
All right
Hardware you have to use is higher-end using different connections
You're gonna have you're gonna deal with stuff like that, but if you're like a regular consumer user who has a USB headset for example
We'll not have a problem with that because the USB headset will show up in mumble
But they still have to you would actually still have to go into the settings and
That's pulse pulses set that as your default sound device you got you got lucky
I mean you got lucky maybe because my my USB audio device didn't get set as the default audio device
I'm not using
Anyways I
I felt like I feel like I guess the core point is I feel like every time we try to say these things need to
Be improved we get we get a lot of criticism for hating something
I don't know why we have to hate just to be able to criticize
Criticism does not equal hate criticism equals caring enough about something to say hey this could be improved upon
I don't know like it's it kind of goes back to the episode from last week of the conversation of if there's a technical problem
It's okay to perform up to point it out. Yeah, pretty much what you were doing right? Yeah
Yeah, in fact speaking of technical stuff that first of all the plasma desktop is filled with awesome technical stuff
But there is a really cool piece of software
That rotten corpse actually had a chance to do a write-up on called Katie connect
And you can sync your Android device with your Linux computer, and this is really really nice in fact
You don't even really have to be a KD desktop user take advantage of it
But this is an example of some really cool technology so before we get into that
I'm going to tell you about our friends over at ting my mobile service provider
Linux dot ting dot-com the internet service provider of the JB rover as well ting is pay for what you use mobile service
How cool is that it's a flat six dollars for the line, and then you just pay for what you use
I'm not even joking that's seriously how it's structured. It's six dollars for the line
Cellphone my fi ting don't care their honey badger about it
It's just six dollars and your usage your minutes your messages your megabytes
No BS charges no extra stuff. No early termination like charges because there's no contract
Nothing like that in fact not only is there no contract, but they have an early termination relief program
I love it. They have an aggressively awesome customer service department
I'd love for you to try them out at one eight five five ting FTW
They have fantastic online communities and because ting is so cool
And they're kind of changing things up a little bit
There are some uber passionate community members that definitely want to help you out is really really cool
What I love about ting is that I'm able to go at it with a little bit of intelligence a little bit of flexibility
So I know that I have X amount of devices. I want to put them all on one plan
I don't want to have to sit here and nickel and dime myself either
I want to have up three or four devices, and I just want to pay a pool of minutes across them for whatever they use
So if I got a couple of phones
I don't use very much or a mi-fi device that I don't use very much
I only pay for the device that is actually using the service and here's another thing. I love about ting
GSM service and CDMA service bumsies
So that way you got a compatible device almost guaranteed in your house because guess what cell phones have been around for a while
You bring it over to ting and when you go to Linux dot ting comm you're gonna get the discount off a phone
But if you got a phone that's working on these GSM or CDMA networks, and you probably do
$25 service credit that paid for more than my first month of ting here's another nice thing about ting
Excellent excellent dashboard really good. It really solves all the problems
I have been a ting customer for over two years
And I've had to call them for a grand total of twice and the first time I called them
I was like yeah, might as well just call them and see what it's like second time
I called them it was totally legit and man
They were like a dog with a bone when it came to my problem. They I
Honestly, it was 20 minutes into the issue
And I thought for sure the customer service rep was gonna start wrapping me up and apologizing and just letting me go man
She stuck with the issue like it was super impressive
It felt really good because I could tell that my time was valuable to ting. I love their dashboard
I love their customer service Linux dot ting comm I want you to check them out six dollars a month for your phone and yes
You can go pick up the Nexus 5x and the Nexus 6p and bring them over to ting
That's right
You can officially bring the Nexus 5 or Nexus pay to ting
Powerful well price you can get the Google edition if you're gonna get yourself a Google phone
You can check it out ting is gonna be doing an unboxing very soon, but here's the power user tip
Just go get a SIM card. We got GSM and CDMA SIM cards for nine dollars
And when you go to linux.ting.com you get a $25 discount if you have a device that needs to do
Updating over text messages check in for stats
Update any kind of remote information like a I mean for example my buddy chase. I thought was
Brilliant about this he went and got one of these home security systems that just
Transmits an image when it detects motion and and and a condition has been triggered very nice
And when that happens it just sends him an image over the ting CDMA network just sends it to him
I think he's using GSM
And I just get he gets the push notification on his phone and he can bring it up and then if he wants to he can
Initiate a real-time stream now when chase was first looking at building that he's like well
I could go get a $30 $40 and $60 a month different
These are like my different plan options, or I can go to ting six dollars a month pay for what I use Noah
Buys like a batch of these GSM SIM cards and then as he gets the devices he pops them in there and boom he's got
Ting service on it now. That's really cool. It is really really cool
You can go to linux.ting.com to get our discount and also go check out their blog to find out details about the new Nexus devices
with that USB C connector
You know what I like about the 5x and the 6p Nexus devices not only are they Google edition devices?
But they have GSM and CDMA antennas in them
And if you combine that I mean just think about this for a second so you can be on ting you pay for what you?
Use you getting all the devices are unlocked, so it's like you really own the device
And then with like the Nexus line of devices you can pick between
CDMA and GSM depending on what you need where you're going all that stuff
That is awesome really slick really really slick linux.ting.com to support the show and a big thanks to ting for sponsoring the Linux
Unplugged program that is very awesome
All right, Mr.. Rotten corpse
Now tell me about Kde connect because it promises to sync my Android device with my linux desktop
And I'm thinking to myself man wouldn't this be nice to finally if I mark something is red somewhere
It's marked as red on both devices if I get a notification
or maybe if I just want to check basic connectivity and so this kind of sounds like it's right up my alley and
When you from what you were telling me on the pre show I don't necessarily even have to be a Kde user do I?
Nope, you don't there's a app indicator, and there's also a shell extension for
For gnome to use the app indicator or to use this Kde connect daemon
Not all of the features are available to like
There's actually only one problem if you're not a Kde user and that is you can't send the connection from the phone to
accept on the computer because the Kde notifications are the only ones that have that functionality built in okay
It will display, but the functionality doesn't work any other de's all right you send the connection from the applet, and it's fine
But the reason why Kde connect is awesome is not like a lot of people look at it is it notification system and
Originally, that's what it was, but there's it's beyond that ridiculous now
You can you sync it notifications. Yes, that's cool, but it has
a wireless mounting of your Android device to your phone wow oh, that's cool. Yeah, it has
Multi-device clipboard synchronization, so yeah, so you have used you copy something on your desktop it will
Then copy it to your phone and then Kde connect will handle it sending it to every other device that is currently connected at that time
And I've tested it through like five different computers, and it all syncs immediately, and there's no lag whatsoever
You just move to the next when it's there. That's cool. That is really slick then it also has a remote input controls, which
Ridiculously awesome, and I don't you know I never thought I would do it until I trusted on a tablet
It's amazing you basically turn your tablet into a touchpad. Oh like a mouse
Yeah
You have a mouse so you have a remote mouse that you can use and you can also have do keyboard your kit your Android
Keyboard can be your keyboard for your computer
Yeah, I know Chris Moore to do PCB SD or
BSD now with uses his Android cell phone to control his media center really pause and play and scrub through videos
Yeah, and this is another cool thing about that is that you it'll work it doesn't work for every player
but it works for like VLC and
Clementine and a lot of applications work, so the ones I use
Yeah, pretty much, so it works with the only guy the only two player
I couldn't find I could find that would not work was mpv, and that's just because they haven't built the functionality in but
There's there's another cool thing about the media player is
It is not only you know controlling media from
Your phone to your computer it also allows you to get to use your your computer your phone as a reference to when to
Lower the volume or mute it so if you get a phone call it will mute your music on your computer
So that is like yeah, and then as soon as you hang up the phone call the music is back up Wow
Okay, that almost tells me on it right there. I
Mean the VLC thing so I have been using I can't remember it. Oh shoot uh
Rekha I might know if he's if he's watching live, but I've been using a Linux an Android app. Oh
Unified remote unified remote I've been using unified remote for a while to essentially accomplish a tiny
Fraction of what you're talking about unified remote it has a little daemon that you install on your Linux box
That makes your your your remote touch device act like a keyboard input device or a mouse and you can control VLC and stuff like
That but you don't get like the pausing and the muting I mean that is genuinely slick the level of integration here seems
Yeah, almost unbelievable. It's more than that too
You also can like make it where it'll display your battery percentage of your phone on your computer
That's nice. You can easily switch, and that's just that's not a little nicety, but there's
Other things you can send files back and forth from the phone to the computer
So if you send a file from your phone, it will go with your downloads folder in your computer
And it like it does
This is not even everything I've mentioned like there's not everything I've mentioned is not all what it does
What is it using on the back end is it using like to transfer the files is it using SSHFS is it using yes?
Uh-huh does the file so does the phone and the app on the phone have like a login to your computer. How does that work?
Yeah, you you essentially you
use SSH to share keys between the devices so that your
Like it will remember your devices and what like your names and things like that based on the SSH key, okay?
That is nice. I love that. It's doing over SSH and does that
How possible is it to do some of this stuff?
Outside your LAN like say if you have a port forwarding setup right now
It's not technically well actually over your LAN if you have if you go through the process of port forwarding you could probably you can
Make it work or you probably need a dynamic DNS or something like yeah, yeah
But if you but another cool thing is that they're working on currently like the next release are two features that are coming
That are even more awesome
That makes this is actually one of the KDE Connect is one of the tools that makes me love KDE project
Because of like all the amazing stuff. They're building for it
and then two things that are coming now is replying to SMS from your yeah Wow and
Bluetooth support so instead of Wi-Fi. It's Bluetooth that handles the yeah
I agree with heavens this stuff kind of thing is much better over the LAN the only thing is is
When I'm out and about and I know this is stupid, but they keep putting better and better cameras and mobile phones
And so I can't help but use it for stuff, and then I'm like okay now
I want to immediately send that back to the studio
Yeah, so that could be really cool, so
Now I don't not to jump a hot not to jump ahead
But I kind of wanted to have a caveat in here for the mint users because apparently you ran into some issues there
Yeah, I did so I like the mean
Yeah, mint does the I don't know why they do this
I I kind of get it, but it's also doesn't make sense because it's just based on the hierarchy of where you put the new source
It's that's all you need to do, but for some reason the mint team decided to put the priority of
Their packages on their repos higher than Ubuntu
But the PPAs del fault lower than the proprietary that mint does so if you put your PPA on
Top of the list on Ubuntu it uses that PPA
But because they're both 500 level priority, but mint for some reason does a 700 priority
So even if you install that PPA. It's going to completely ignore it
So you have to change the policy of mint on your computer, or you have to install with a deb file
So I assume if I install this on my pretty much known pure system
There's going to be a quite a bit of dependencies that it's going to pull down
Yeah, it'll it will have been it will bring in some KD libraries like I've had there was a people a couple people ask me
Questions on the article and in reddit like what they were confused by because a lot of people consider like the KD dependency is
Like a horrible thing
But it brings in packages, and if you're long as you're you know not in 1998
You don't really have to care about the size
That's true
And then the honest the honest truth is is a lot of times with the QT stuff once you pull it in once pretty much
They're going forward all the other QT apps you need are gonna rely you just shocked that first time yeah exactly like well
You know and I pretty much got over that the first time. It's old quazzle. Yep exactly
It's not the disk space so much though because with with the KD connect stuff. It requires the KD base
Yeah, so you've got a quiet bit more. That's running in the background
Okay, it's not it's not like it's running
It's not running QT in the background for anything
And it's not running like plasma or anything like that you're pulling those packages in right you're pulling in the KD base packages
Which is quite a bit of stuff?
But yeah, I agree. It's probably in most the times not all that of avoid
I mean, it's not it's not all avoidable because there's a lot of apps that require that
I mean even on a gnome system. There's a lot of apps that you end up still pulling that down, so yeah
That's not it's not it's not a big deal
It used to be a big deal
But now that it's kind of like one of those legacy issues that people complain about ten years ago
That was relevant then that isn't now, but people still complain about I bet you though
I bet wimpy's to wimpy's point. I bet you it's enough that it won't ship by default in any non KD distros
Right this is gonna be this is gonna be a bit of a leg up
This is a nice advantage this KD connect is really nice. I know it once I hope it works
I'm excited to try it when I go home well and and Wes I kind of you know when you when I think about
Convergence this to me feels a little more like a lot my speed like it's a you know
I'm being able to send files back and forth using SHFS the notifications things like that
It's a little more like I'm I'm
What I like about this is two things number one is it gets sort of two devices
They're weren't really communicating before but doing a lot of the same jobs talking you love that number two is it's essentially Apple's
Handjob, I mean handoff or whatever they call it
But but for Apple you have to have a really new Mac that has bluetooth 4o le and you have to have it like at least
An iPhone 5 or something or better for any of this stuff to work and here Linux comes along
It's like oh, yeah, you got Bluetooth and Wi-Fi and Android and KDE or KD dependencies. You're good to go
No special hardware required. I also like that it lets you kind of separate things
Maybe you like different programs on your phone versus you know or different different workload styles on your phone versus your full-size computer
Yeah, so here you can just share the data without right sharing the app
so also to point out another important thing about KD connect is it
Pertains to the you know, they actually adopt the whole
Customization thing as well in KD connect so every plug-in that is available to KD connect can be turned off on any device that you
Want it to be?
So for some reason if you don't like the clipboard synchronization you can turn it off and
so what's the what's the advantage over something like this so versus like say push bullet or
air droid
They like well push build only does the like well air droid
I hate air droid like there's a lot of people who talk about air droids business great
But you have to activate the login connection every single time you use it like awful
Anyway, well this one KD connect stores the connections and they work consistently regardless
I have never had a connection drop. Oh really like even with Wi-Fi mounting of the file system. I never have a problem
I don't have to worry about losing access while I'm moving files over or anything. It it's I've never had a problem and
It allows me to control every aspect to it and it has features that push bullet for example only has like
Notification in a file connection it push bullet does have SMS
Response, but that's coming soon and KD connect and but another good thing is
None of those are open source. Oh, that's exactly that's a good point, so I had boy. It's been
Holy crap. Oh my god. It's been a year almost and it's been a year and about a week about a year and a week ago
I met the developer of KD connect when he first started working on this and he I'm gonna get it wrong
But I can't remember what country he moved from let's just say let's just pretend like it's Germany
But he just moved to country a yeah
But what what actually matters is he had just moved to Seattle hey?
Yeah, so he was in Seattle, and I went to a KD users group because I hate KD so much
I go to KD users group, and I was right on everyone. Yeah, right. Yeah, just cuz I could
Yeah, that's what I do when I go to KD users groups
And I went down there and I talked to him and I told him like how awesome it is and talked to him
Also, there's some other there was designers there and things like that and I was asking him where where it was going next and he's
Like well, you know just gonna keep working on it, and so here. We are a year later, and it is slick
Yeah, it is really slick
Very nice run and they need to work on their marketing more because they they don't that's one of the reasons
I wanted to write an article about it is because it is
When I never used it because I didn't use Katie then I used
Wow this this is this would make me want to use Katie, but because I don't have to use Katie
It makes it even better and another thing is it doesn't require Android
It also works on BlackBerry oh
They're working on iOS version as well what
What?
No, that one's that'll no way no way how can that even work?
iOS
Does iOS support networking? I don't think I was
They probably have absolutely everything yeah, it'll still it'll still give something that
You know at least it doesn't leave them out completely or anything
But there is there is one thing that should be mentioned that as as far as a versioning caveat mm-hmm
You need
0.7 point three or higher to use the cleat keyboard remote keyboard feature
That's pretty much it everything else works
With that regardless of the version okay, but so like the 1404 and stuff based on that has
0 7 3 or 0 7 1 so you would need to add a PPA to get the functionality for that
But everything else works great
Yeah, yeah alright, so this is something. I'm gonna play with I think I you know after looking at a while ago
I think I definitely have to check it out again, and you can too mr.
Rotten corpse has a write-up at make use of calm
We'll have a link to that in the show notes where he goes through all of this
Which is very handy, so I have a link to that. Thank you rotten corpse
I am my appetite has been whetted as they say is that what they say I believe so
I think that's that's the right next week. We'll have tried it and we'll be better synchronized
So just wait for that
I think so
Whimpy I know you're still around don't go anywhere
I got a question for you about your connectivity and the key point to that connectivity your router
But before we get to that I want to thank our next sponsor, and that's the great folks over at
Digital ocean check out digital ocean comm a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way
For you to spin up your own cloud server. That's what they say I say a
Really fast Linux rig that's how I would say it spin up your own fast Linux rig up in the cloud one that is
Damn, fast is connected to the super fast SSDs a great connection
And it's sitting in a rockin data center
And you can start in less than 55 seconds and pricing plans start at only five dollars a month
Five dollars a month to get your 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte of transfer
But if you use the promo code now get ready for this because it's completely brilliant
Do unplugged do unplug no way one word lowercase you put that thing into the digital ocean thingy there
And it's like some sort of magic. It's like I'm gonna do so much
You know what it's like Donald Trump walks up to you, and he says you know what first of all
I do wine because I want to win and here's ten dollars
It's like Donald Trump gives you ten dollars for digital ocean boom you put it in your digital ocean droplet
You could try it out for two months for free when you do the $5 rig now digital ocean has data center locations in New York
San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam London, Germany
a
Brand new one in Toronto
Yeah, when you want to avoid the NSA. That's where you go. I digital ocean didn't write that
I'm just saying if you want to have your day
I'm Chris's man if you want to have your day in the North America region
And you don't want the NSA reading all of it you could go check out through the Toronto data center
Hashtag just saying now also their interface
Let's talk about that holy moly if I can legally get married to an interface that would be the one I tell you what I?
Would go into the courthouse. I would say I'm going to marry digital oceans interface for the rest of my life. I will
Appreciate that and I would then go home
I would consummate that marriage with digital
Interface that part I will not be there for but here's what I'll do West cuz you know
I'm real slick as I'm gonna use their API because they have a straightforward API and let me tell you something if you want to scale
Up the API is the way to go you want to go deploy on-demand
Maybe you want to scale your infrastructure because I got hourly pricing. Did you know they have hourly pricing?
It's true. They got hourly pricing and you plug into something like chef or puppet
Just scale up on-demand or whatever you want. I'm not gonna judge tons of code out there
You can already take advantage of digital ocean takes these platform features seriously
Here's a few ten poles of digital ocean that I like a lot all based on Linux
Yeah, that rocks KVM for the backend virtualization what you've got SSDs throughout tier one data connections
great interface and last but not least
Really good community documentation tutorials that they've paid for they've hired full-time editors to make sure that they rock
I mean really good stuff that makes taking advantage of digital ocean droplet really straightforward
So you get it deployed you use the one-click application to get your basic stack up
Maybe you want to also throw ghosts on top of that or get lab or whatever it is
And then you're like well geez this $5 rig. It's still got a ton of horsepower left
I should use it for something else trust me
This is gonna cross your mind because you're gonna be blown away with how powerful these things are so then you go to the community
Section that's really where they take it up a notch go over to digital ocean comm remember that promo code do unplugged and take a
Look at the community section three ways to securely browse the internet with an open VPN on
Debian 8 now that is a handy handy tutorial for digital ocean imagine turning your do droplet into an open VPN server I
Love that how to mitigate a denial of service attack against your website with cloudflare. Let's go look at like that one
That's got to be fairly interesting
I would imagine because I'm not a huge cloudflare fan, but you know what I've never really had an opportunity to integrate it properly
I love this kind of stuff so many good apps so many good
Documentation so many so much good tutorials all this stuff is available for free
And I'm gonna be honest some of it's not even specific to digital
You could go use that stuff regardless a reference
Yeah, exactly and you know what then when you are ready to use digital ocean
Just use that promo code do unplugged get the $5 credit for two months try it out absolutely free no credit card required
It's insanely great digital ocean comm promo code do unplugged also
You could probably get paid for doing a write-up
They pay anywhere between a hundred to two hundred dollars for technical tutorials potential writers can submit a writing sample to become a tutorial writer
Just find out more by going digital oceans community website digital ocean comm slash community slash get dash paid dash to dash right
they have
Positions available right now you go do that you write a few tutorials a month you could live out of an RV
Digital ocean comm use the promo code do unplugged and a real big
Thank you digital ocean for sponsoring Linux unplug guys go check it out is a really cool system if you were gonna build a hosting
System around Linux. This is what you'd make you know and that that KVM part cannot be oversold
I've been fighting with a provider on a less than capable virtualization platform recently that I'd already paid for and yes
I'm quite inspired right yes, and trying to get some IP tables modules loaded
You don't need that on digital ocean you know KVM. You've got full control. That's right. Load them yourself
That's right digital ocean comm use the promo code do unplugged and a big thanks to digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged program
You guys are rocking it. I love seeing that so I want to talk about
Something that's more than just an open source router. It's an open source center of your home a home router
They say is necessary to connect you to the internet
But that's just sitting there idle most the time when you're not using internet eating electricity and boy have I noticed that recently
So why not use your home router to do more things?
More powerful hardware can handle gigabit traffic
maybe could act as a home NAS a print server, maybe even a
Virtual server now before I get into how crazy this is I wanted to bring in wimpy because I
Know that if I recall wimpy has some sort of eccentric setup
But it involves like antennae wave
Transmissions and all kinds of stuff and wimpy if you could remind me about your setup, and how do you actually bring that into your house?
Like what is the router you're using and all of that stuff?
I'm really curious because I'm looking at different solutions to bring internet connectivity into the rover
And I keep hitting up against once you have like an antenna you have to bring that into something and that seems to be
Where things fall apart?
Okay, well, I'm speaking to you now over the power of shortwave radio broad band. I love it. You sound good wimpy. You do sound good. You always sound good.
Yeah
so yeah
my
Backhaul is about four miles from here over the other side of the trees
So there's um it's a microtech. You know no one has spoken about these in the past
So running up the side of the house. Okay. There's an aerial with a directional microtech
Radio which is the the piece that actually does the connection between?
the house and the backhaul
That's capable of sustaining a hundred megabits
But I'm only paying for 12. Oh, so I have a 12 12 megabit connection 12
12 down 4 up. Do you mind like roughly giving me an idea of what that costs you?
That costs about 45 pounds a month. Okay, that's not bad $60. Yeah, I'm like that seems pretty reasonable
Well, I mean for 12, and that's unmetered us. Okay, that's on me. Okay, I'll take it
And and I know it's unmetered because one month I kind of got carried away with my radar analysis
And I pulled one and a half terabytes across the the network. That's an excellent test
Yeah, they contacted me to say have you got a virus, but they weren't at all bothered
It's not malware
So the the aerial and the radio that's connected via power over ethernet
So the cable comes down the side of the house through a you know, a small hole in the wall
runs along the back of the skirting board behind me here and
into a little
adapter and POE
converter
nice and
That's plugged into a UPS
So if the power in the house goes down
The internet doesn't nice and then also plugged into the same UPS
I did used to have a micro tech router doing you know, the home LAN and Wi-Fi, but I've now got a TP link
router okay that I flashed
gargoyle router onto which is a
open
wrt
derivative and in my opinion is the best of the
Open-source router project really and you know
What's interesting is the TP link seem to be very very popular for this particular type of activity
Gargoyle
Gargoyle dash router comms that sound right? That's that's the one
Yeah, and the model that I've got I flashed myself
But they have a number of models that you can actually buy from them pre flashed
So if you're at all
Concerned about being a warranty voider, they will they'll do the hard work for you and send you one pre-configured
Interesting. I have not heard of gargoyle before maybe because this is I've a lot of a lot of people that are looking at the
TP links are still doing
ddr
ddwrt and
Yeah, those but I don't think they're getting updated as much anymore
These are this is really good. This gets an update. Well, whenever there's a security exploit this gets an update
Really? It's under active development. I'm actually a version behind at the moment
There's a new stable release out that I need to update to. Rodden have you heard of this before?
Yeah, I could be wrong, but I think it's a fork of either openwrt or ddwrt. It's openwrt
Yeah, it's openwrt with a really nice UI UI on top
Okay
And the reason I found this is because I wanted to put new routers into my family
My extended family's houses after those big netgear exploits a couple of years ago, right?
So I bought cheap TP link routers for like 20 quid a go
Put gargoyle on the on it and pre-configured them and then sent them all out to everyone's houses. I
Like this because the UI on this is really easy to use. Yeah, it's not
Honestly, this seems like a great
Christmas gift idea for my family to do a few of these for like my mother have a good setup
Yeah, be confident that it'll last it won't degrade and and and and and what I did is, you know
I set up the second wireless LAN. Yeah to be common for everybody
Ah, so when we all move between each other's houses, we could all get on each other's guest LAN. Oh
That's looking ahead that is thinking so when you go over to visit you get on their Wi-Fi
Yeah, and everyone else now because I only have to set their phones up once it doesn't matter where they go
They get on the Wi-Fi and there's an analyst. Oh Martin. Can you just configure, you know eight phones?
Right. Yes, you know, what's funny is
Years and years and years ago. In fact, there's a YouTube video about this. I
bought a bunch of Wi-Fi routers for my family and
Because I wanted to get them all digital picture frames to show the pictures of our newborn son
And I thought here you go Kodak has a good deal
I got I got like four or five digital picture frames, but they all required wireless internet connectivity
Of course, there's a long enough ago now, but six before that was coming six years ago
It just wasn't all that common that they had Wi-Fi
And so I bought them the linksys models that you could replace the firmware on and did that and now they all sit there
And some of my I still come over six years later like Oh Christopher
We just want to thank you for that Wi-Fi router now that we have our new tablets
It is so nice to get online and check the Facebook to see the pictures of the grandchildren relative said charming
Yeah, they are quite charming and and I didn't even think about like I it hasn't even crossed my mind
What I'm gonna do to replace their particular setup, but wimpy
This is this is brilliant and you find the software is powerful enough for you as a as a Linux power user quote-unquote
Yeah, so I originally used this, you know for my family for a low-tech solution. Yeah, actually I found it
So nice. I use it for yourself myself
seal of approval
And so you have your wireless wave whatever it is broadband shortwave whatever magic
Radio broadband coming into this and it just acts like a WAN port. I assume. Yeah, it just looks like an Ethernet one port to this
router and
Yeah, you just configure a PPO
It seems like to me the biggest
Challenge with this is you got to get you got to get in the right groove at the right time when it comes to hardware
So you've landed on these TP TP link routers
which work pretty well and it seemed to be pretty popular amongst people that are equipping their RVs that I've been doing research for
different internet options and
The problem I have with that is that's a pretty solid recommendation for a year
But it's not like from a year from now like somebody that's listening to episode 114 in a year from now
We could say go get TP link model blah blah blah blah and maybe you know
It is do you know what it is off the top of your head the TP link model that you're using?
Yeah, mine's it's still being sold. It's a TL WR 10 0 4 3 N
Mine's about I've had mine for about a good while
now over two years don't you find though that the kind of the biggest challenge here is that
In a year from now that won't necessarily be the right router to recommend to people
Like this is the issue I have with the custom firmware's is that you can say you can you can give a recommendation today
but it doesn't necessarily mean that
Like in a six months or even three months from now. It's the right one
Well when when I did this there was two models that I used the model that I've got and a smaller model both of which
Are still available are still either 20 or 30 pounds depending on which model you get
The the revision of the board has changed. It's like a v1 v2 v3
But they're all supported by this and they've got
When you download the firmware, you know from this website, it says, you know, this is for the fee one boards
This is for the v2. Okay, and so on. Okay, so they're sitting on top of the model
The model I'm using is the model that the company still sells pre-flashed
also, the
TP link is not just replacing
like functionality stuff there they're creating new versions of the same model so like
Yeah compatibility still exists like my the router I have I
Bought I went to buy another one of that, but they made a new version of it
So it's still compatible with gargoyle. That's cool
You can you can even though they're making new versions of their hardware. It's pretty pretty much still compatible
Anyway, so let me introduce to you the tourist omnia, which is trying to solve this particular problem
They say it's more than just a router. It's an open source center of your home
I don't know if that's necessarily true or not, but it's open or something you want, right?
It's open heart feature open hardware running
In OS based on open wrt. It has a dual core arm processor running at 1.6. Gigahertz
they say with PC like performance in here and
It has so here's one point six one point six gigahertz dual core arm CPU
Honestly, that does sound fast enough to be a router up to a gigabyte of RAM four gigabytes of flash
five
gigabit ports for the LAN
One gigabit port for the WAN it supports USB 3.0
It has two mini PCI Express one M SATA connector. It has three
MIMO 8 or 211 AC ports and two 8 or 211 BGN ports
starting at a hundred USD for this thing and
I'm looking I'm showing them live on the video version here a
little schematics of it has it has M SATA like I mentioned mini PCI USB 3 and processor a Marvell processor and
and a
Sim card slot for backup internet connectivity how cool is this little thing of this?
I don't I don't know if this is actually practical or not
But and I don't think of this could replace the TP links today wimpy
But I look at this and I think maybe a year from now something like this might be
The direction we're pointing people for something like gargoyle then a TP link. What do you think?
Do you think something like this ARM based could be the solution?
What is your hardware right now? And when you look at this does it sound like reasonable a reasonable option?
Okay, so the box that I've got now the the router I was just describing
Yeah
And it's a few years old that's got five gigabit ethernet ports one one for the WAN and four for the LAN
And I just take one of those
Gigabit LAN ports into a switch and then yeah
Gigabit that makes switch. Yeah, that makes sense
So then you know you minimize how much of your local traffic is actually, you know routing up. Yes to the to the router
I would probably do it that way too. And
Then I've got two HP micro servers
As my you know media servers for the house one one is the server and one is the backup
And I have it. Oh, yeah, that's beautiful. Gotta have that high
Can I do a last cribs episode I'm coming yeah, yeah by all means I'll have to clear out the spare room, but you're welcome
and I have experimented with so
Went way back before I had shortwave radio broadband
I used to use 3g to get on the internet and that was with a router with you know
It had a WAN port and a USB port where you could plug in your 3g dongle
So I've done that, you know high availability thing
briefly
But I've always been nervous about using these
More powerful home routers that you can plug USB do a whole bunch of things
Yeah, because what because they're they're not very robust bits of kit and if they fail then you've lost everything
You haven't just lost internet connectivity. You've lost your LAN as well. So I sort of adopt the same
approach
to
to my kit
That I do with the home cinema, you know one device one job that makes sense
and and it's definitely been my approach for a really really long time because it just means that
you know troubleshooting is much easier updates are much straightforward a lot less to break, but I
Have to admit I have a new perspective now and that new perspective is
how many how much power does something draw and and
how much room does something take and the two things that are real premium for me right now our power draw and
The room that it takes up in and I'm talking like, you know
I'm trying to fit stuff like under a chair like it is really like under a bench seat. It is
really tight
So the the routers obviously don't take up much because they're arm powered and that they don't they don't
Take up much space and they don't draw much power. Yeah, true, but I would still separate things, you know on my father-in-law's barge
Had a wireless router with 3g and the file server there was a Raspberry Pi
This is back a couple of years now. Of course, I'd recommend using a Raspberry Pi 2
Doesn't draw much power. And in fact if you get one of those routers with the USB port on it
Check the specs carefully, but there are some you can actually power a Raspberry Pi off the USB port. Yeah, the router
Yeah, and then instead of you know, instead of going for
huge amounts of spinning storage on the Raspberry Pi
go for a bit less storage use an SSD connected to the USB port and
Then you don't need additional power to drive the SSD attached to the Raspberry Pi
Yeah, I agree. I even even in with limited space and limited power
I still think it's probably better to break them up and Wes got this. I can't remember the brand name of it now Wes
but you got me this
Router that it like it allows for different types of 3g connections. Yeah, how did that work?
Did you use it? No, I haven't yet because I'm waiting to connect it to a machine
But now actually probably over the next week or so
I probably will hook it up because I'm kind of now that I'm back in part with the rover
I'm kind of like working on like the technology land stuff because some of that stuff was like just too much to deal with
before the road drive and yeah, well it was like the my fives
Kind of act as routers and Wi-Fi access points. So for the for out for two weeks
They say solved a problem and I could make it work
But the biggest challenge was I was a minimum
It was either two different my fives or a cell phone that I was jumping between
Yep, and every time on every device I'd have to go to each device and say okay now join this Wi-Fi Network that gets super
Old that router you got me totally solves that problem
so I think I'm gonna try that for a while and see how that shapes out and I'm gonna keep an eye on
this project and just kind of see if the
if did I think it's pronounced tourist you are our
is
Omnia if this results in something of substance, you know, it's kind of try this. It's kind of interesting
I was looking down at the bottom about us and they aren't responsible for some more enterprise-grade software. Yes
That's what gives me some hope. Yeah, go ahead
Yeah, like if you look here, they're talking about bird which is the an internet routing Damon open source that supports BSD's Linux
Yeah, you know, they do BGP OSPF. So it makes me think that this organization at least knows a little bit
It has experience about routing. Yes, exactly. That's it. That is a good point because that's what gave me hope
It made me okay
These have they have some credentials here
But I I'm trying to remember I don't know if you remember the name of it because I'm just I'm drawing a blank right now
But it is it was recommended by someone in the it was yeah
it is a unit that is essentially trying to accomplish this and then I
Agree with Wimpy's approach is whenever it's possible make
Make your your your edge of land device as
Single purpose as possible very much, right?
Because then it's if for security updates and reliability and troubleshooting and and really honestly from your own mistakes
It is much more isolated. And so the way I work is the further out to the edge of the land
I get the less and less stuff. I try to have that machine do and and a big a big
Big trend I have noticed from the tech snap audience is a lot of them want to virtualize their firewalls
Yeah, that is very more and more common. Yeah, it is like, you know, can I run my firewall my pf sense firewall as a VM?
You know, I'll give it a dedicated. I'll give it a dedicated Nick or whatever
They say or the vertio driver and it just so goes. Yeah. Yeah, it just so goes against my like minimal like no
This is a router. That's all it's supposed to it kind of sounds like what wouldn't be saying too
It's like I don't like having it be a file server running Samba running SSH running all this different stuff
I don't want that and so
I'm gonna try scaling it back a bit, but I am definitely kind of relooking at some of the stuff now
I'm going oh, but I could save a lot of watts and a lot of space if I had one device doing it all
I also wouldn't mind just having a really beefy router like that's fine. Even if it's just as little
So I'm not quite sure where I'm gonna fall down on yet, but this is pretty neat and it's available for pre-order right now
I I you know, I'm you know what I'm gonna do
I'm gonna go and put myself down as a as a pos as a possibility and the pre-order right now
I'm just signing up for it. I'm joining you. Yeah
Yeah, cuz I'm curious to see where they go with this and I like that they're yeah. Yeah, there we go
So they I just I just went in and I just had I added myself to the pre-order list
I'm gonna give the Omni a try but my philosophy is more in line with yours and wimpy's
I think it's a I think it's a little safer to say this router is dedicated to do this thing
But we'll see wimpy any any other thoughts before we wrap up
Yeah, open media vaults available for the Raspberry Pi 2 now, so you really know
Oh
Yeah, the Raspberry Pi 2 and open media vault could be perfect
That could be perfect. Can I run MB on it? Cuz that's you know, I'm using MB in the rover
I want to do a little MB follow-up if I could actually because people been asking me about this
I bet that hasn't been I bet that hasn't been ported to the Raspberry Pi, but who knows?
I mean, I'm really enjoying MB. I've been using Plex still at the house in the studio, but in the rover
I am using MB. Well, look at me. I got three different places. I'm trying stuff and MB is really great
Are you are you using the Android client at all? No, no, I'm only using only using the web client at the moment
Why what have you run into issues with the Android version? Yeah. Yeah, it's a bit stuttery and you know
I've noticed some of the similar the most recent version that I don't remember when I last updated
It seemed to be doing a lot better
But I have noticed a little occasional slow really once it gets up and running when you're streaming from your house on your Android
Device for me. It's more than like that the interface the actual stream has been fine
but kind of just like the startup and and those
Transitions have been a little slow you guys are not encouraging me to keep on with my MB exploration
But I mean I've been using it as well and the rest of it has been I've been can I mean I can you know
You can put a fully tight. I I mean that my use for MB is I want to build a small
Network in the rover and I want some I want a component of that network to be media on-demand
I'm not married to MB though. I will say I've been experimenting with the open and external player. Yeah. Yeah
Yeah, and I've got it configured right now. It seems to only want to detect VLC, but with a little XDG
You know like configuring your default apps. Yeah, I've got it one click opening in MPV
Are you telling me in the web browser?
You just click it it opens MPV and it that if you ever had a little like a little slowness when you're changing places
When you're using an MPV, of course, all of these amazing
Yeah, and it seems to be streaming the original quality just just beautiful doesn't market as read or as watched in MB
Yes that part. I haven't updated
Very recently. I think it's been a week or so. So they may have fixed it
There was like a recent little bug in that man, but the actual playback is flawless and they have a UI there
It just isn't quite fixed to have to have I'm gonna talk about that after air how well tell me right now
How do you make MB use MPV as your default player? What do you do?
Well, it has it has a I don't know if it's a plug-in or an option somewhere to enable external players
So you do lose like it doesn't track your progress, but you can enter it
You can't resume right so you lose your resume
But if you're if you're just watching an hour-long and I can remember if I remember a jump in a half hour
Right and then we be makes only gives that up to use MPV, right?
Or you can use Cody and not give up anything
Excellent point I
Would open a leg will work on the pies. Yes
I'm trying to keep it simple
I've got an MB server and I just want to go to the web page in the rover and watch stuff
That's all I want. I don't want to have to do too much more than that. But the MPV thing that is
You can send it to
Cody as well because Cody has an API that I'm actually working on a script to send stuff to Cody
Oh, and it will play through Cody and it will really to the server really won't be sending signals
It'll actually just send the it'll say here's what I want to play and then Cody will connect to it directly and you will
Keep all your sinking and everything. That's awesome. Oh, I think I think you guys are selling me on the rover setup
I mean the rover set up so early now that if I could have Cody look at MB and have all get it. Oh
Anyways, if you guys are not familiar with MB, we did an episode of Linux action show about MB vs. Plex. These are
Really really amazing home theater management solutions. They'll go out. They'll scan your directory. They'll go get all the metadata
They'll build a nice directory. They'll give you watch status pull an additional context. It's really cool
You can find it
MB dot media an open source solution to Plex and we dedicated an episode of the Linux action show to this particular topic
Because in the rover I wanted something that could completely work offline and not the Plex doesn't Plex works great offline
but Plex also assumes you have an internet connection all the time and
So MB allowed me to have a little bit of flexibility there and say, you know
I'm gonna be offline the majority of the time and when I am connected go fetch the metadata and those kinds of things MB
Allows me to have some flexibility there in the rover specifically that are really nice
I will say at least according to a forum post
It does look like there's an open media vault plug-in available the last the last post on the thread here was from July 2015
So hopefully it's updated in real. Oh my gosh. Love to try that. It's more about the architecture support, isn't it?
Yeah, right MB supported by open media vault. Yeah, so if you took an
You took not a NUC with open media vault and MB
Yeah, this is starting to look pretty nice. Yeah connected over what I scuzzy or an NFS maybe to a storage array. Oh
I have a few episodes in mind when I think of that. That's really cool
So anyways, if you want to check out this router
It is the tourist omnia and I signed up for a pre-order. I'll be I'm going to give it a I'm going to give it a go
I'm willing to give it a go. I like that. They have a built-in LAN switch. That's nice. I might not fiber right in there
That's interesting. Yes. Oh, yes, by the way. Yeah, that was that's that one right that little connector right there
Which is just at the bottom of the screen is a little a G bit connector, which is okay
All right. I'm not saying I'm would I would use this as my main switch, but it's definitely tempting and it might be tempting for you
To so go check it out and we'll have a link in the show notes
And if I do manage to get the pre-order, I'll let you know how it goes
So before we move on I want to thank our friends over at Linux Academy
There's something really cool going on at Linux Academy
And I want to tell you about it
But first if you're new to Linux Academy
I want to sort of set up the framework what I really like about Linux Academy is I see a lot of common ground between them
And Jupiter broadcasting they care a hell of a lot about content
They care a hell of a lot about Linux and open source and they really want to deliver that to the people and so my approach
Was let's go make podcasts about it. Their approach was let's go make educational content about it
so they paired up with developers and content creators and
Educators to make sure this could happen Linux enthusiasts the sat around and said we want to bring this to more people and that is
Really truly unique about Linux Academy Linux and open source. It's not a checkbox
They don't have a whole range of tutorials from fixing your sync and after effects tutorials
What they have is stuff that is hyper focused on Linux and all of the technology stack around there
I invite you to go check them out by going to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and get our really really great discount
In fact, I will have I am now I am now very pleased to say our very exclusive
Discount is the only way to get this pricing structure. It is exclusive to Linux unplugged show Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
Go check that out go tour their features. They have almost 1,900 videos for the self-paced courses
Downloadable comprehensive study guides and instructor help is available to you when you need it
that is a really big deal and a huge differentiator between the other online learning courses and
On October 15th. Oh my gosh, that's really soon
Actually, they have some major major major features. They are rolling out really big things are coming on October 15th
They say and this is their words not mine
They're working on their biggest new tool for the last four months and they're gonna be releasing it on October 15th
It's the result of a dream. They had this time a year ago. It's going to change
Self-paced and hands-on training as we know it
Also, they just updated their CDN
So the content is even faster than before and the players have a new version of their HTML 5 player with speed controls
So you can speed up or slow down the videos, which is really cool
And there has been actually some studies as a podcaster. I looked into this when you listen to podcasts at double speed
You actually retain the data more Wow
Didn't know that but the brain because it's working a little bit harder to listen at a faster pace
Retains the information faster. How cool is that for your training and now their new HTML 5 player supports that that's really great
But something else has just come out at Linux Academy that I think you need to know about. This is a huge deal
practice exams
Practice exams are the secret weapon to actually beating the test. I
For whatever reason get a little weird about taking tests
I don't know. I don't know what it is, but I just get a little weird about taking tests
It's just like I'm being put on the spot next week on linux and plugged we give we
We've got a quiz or two. It'll be great fun. Submit your questions online guys. Actually, that would be really cool. That'd be really good
We should do that as an episode if anybody has suggestions out there for an online Linux quiz that we could take
We should do it. We should do it. You can hear me
I'll get totally worked up like I'm not kidding you guys I freak out over our rock-paper-scissors session
Okay, so I'm not kidding. So the idea of taking a test it really overwhelms me
And so that's Linux Academy recognizes that and they have a solution. So in the past and and and still available today
In fact better than ever you have regular mode exams
This is where Linux Academy loads in a preset of number of questions in a preset amount of time
You go through the exam, you know
Like for example, you could take the AWS CSA associates in regular mode
It'll load 60 questions in 80 minutes and you complete the exam like a real exam
That's cool and gives you a very very real-world like experience
However, if that to you would stress you out like it would me check out practice mode
Now you can select your time limit and the number of questions up to a maximum amount of potential questions from the pool and then
Just take the practice exam
This helps you prepare in a different way than you would normally for the exam and it puts flexibility in the practice exam system
Based on your current needs. So here's a summary of what you get
You get to display the total number of questions in exam questions
All practice exams are now timed if time runs out it automatically submits the questions
you're currently going for and grades them practice mode allows you to define the number of questions and time limits for an exam sessions and
the question order is randomized and
Answers associated with the question are also randomized and each new practice exam is started
This is such a cool way for you to be able to go in and find out the questions that are on the test
Try them learn them do your studying see how you did
So that way when you sit down to actually get your certification, it is a slam dunk this right here
I'm telling you is worth the price alone of admission to Linux Academy go to linuxacademy.com
Unplugged to get our discount and try that out a lot of new features. Check out their big presentation, October 15th
So much is coming
I love to see this company continue to grow because you know why they're promoting Linux at the same time Linux Academy comm slash
Unplugged and a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program
All right, so guys as we wrap up today on the unplugged show
It was actually I think it was West's fault. I think this is totally your fault
Again way to go West jerk
So you think you made an offhand comment about why don't we just end curses everything?
Everything should be an end curses UI. Well, you know what King Looper was paying attention when you said that
He said an episode going in depth on cursors to available links would be a great idea
There are so many anchors of programs out there
I think an episode on it really could be interesting not only anchors of programs for everything in true Linux fashion
There are at least four of them with programs from CMUS to H top
There is a lot of content to cover this episode could show off a lot of new useful tools to viewers to exact for example
CMUS makes great media player, especially when paired with drop-down
terminal
Now this happens to coincide perfectly with the end of tech talk today
It was suggested that we have a mumble app picks segment in the Linux unplugged show
So I wanted to turn it over to the mumble room now Wes and I have a couple to go to's
But I wanted to turn it over to the mumble room if anyone in there has any suggestions
For really really great and curses based applications now for those of you not familiar
I don't know how this is possible
But think of end curses as the best interface ever created that never needs to be replaced and never should be superseded and curses
applications are console applications that essentially have a UI I
You know I'd look at this Wes and curses actually even has an entry on Wikipedia. Here's a great example of
Configuring the Linux kernel I believe the BSD installer is end curses based
I believe a lot of things are in curses based Alan is am I right is is anchors is still a thing on BSD as well? Yeah
So well, uh, the tool is called dialog and then it uses anchors is to draw the stuff
So yeah now do you Alan I while I have you do you have any anchors is apps that you've used from time to time?
Or the biggest one is dialog, which is a way to write to use anchors interfaces from a shell script
Yeah, so the entire installer is written in shell script
But it just asks you the questions and present you the menus by calling the dialog command which draws an anchors is menu for you
There's a good one and and it is universally like, you know
When it is universally like if you have a terminal you've probably at some point in time
Seeing an anchors application and Steve jerbs in the chat room
Steve jerbs has a has a recommendation called a T IG and
He says in the chat room is one of my favorite dev tools. It's a text mode interface for get how cool is that Wes?
How about that? Oh, I'm excited already. Yeah, that is really neat
So if anybody the mumble room wants to chime in with their favorite anchors application, the floor is open to you
I'm saving mine to see if anybody else guesses them
Torrent is also quite nice, which is when you're trying to do stuff service our tour. Yeah, that's a great one
If you're trying to see it from a server, it's just be able to pop it up over SSH. Yeah
Yeah, our torrent is killer our torrent and I think like version 9 0.9 is the current version or something like that
I'll put a link to our torrent our torrent is great
In fact our torrent just a little tip is a great resource to put on your digital ocean drop
You pop that in the BSD license team us and away you go
Our turn I'm gonna put a link there because honestly our turns one of the more common things that I hear people are using on
Their digital ocean droplets we chat we chat is has a and curses based interface. Is that real?
Elman elman coming in from the chat room. How about that?
Your see
Oh, yeah, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yep. Oh my gosh. Yeah. Look at this. Look at elman
Oh, I'm installing elman this might grab this might become a last pick. Look at these guys. Oh, that's me. Hi. Hi
Here it is. Here's the shot
Look at that
Wow
That is really really nice and wimpy you got to mention my favorite. Come on wimpy. Give me a plug for nano. Let's hear it
Yeah, I love nano. Yeah, and a great example of it anchors is based a full application
Yeah, I like that one a lot. All right, any other guy any other? Yeah, there's a the new architect installer
Architect Linux is in curses installer for arch architect Linux our
Linux, all right. I'm putting a link to that
If you've ever heard of evolution Linux, it's it's a yes successor to evolution evolution is gone
But it was been it was it was turned into architect
The live installer for Linux brought to you by Karl Duff and yeah, there it is that gorgeous
Ode to ode to end curses. You know what? I don't know what it is, but I
Love it. I love the little outline. I love the lines. I love the ok button
I love the title at the top with the line underneath it. It's so clear. It's so it's so
Obvious, it's like a nice latex formatted scientific. Yes that same kind of let you know where everything's gonna be
Yes, just right where you expect. Yes, and my keyboard hotkeys work. I mean it is I don't mean to sound like an old man
But I think it is truly one of the best interfaces ever rain before my eyes here guys. I think if you if you're interested in using in curses and you also want good UI like design look
Yes, not now not now no no no no it's been for a very long time which is awesome
Right. I'm saying now as in everything that their installer is. Yes. So it's all in curses. Everything they do is now
Yes, every everything that they have so much now into yes, and now yes is completely in curses
No, it's a good-looking in curses as in design and everything
So it doesn't even necessarily look like in curses, but it's reliable just like it was. Yeah
Yeah
And I I love that about openSUSE of because when you're installing a machine a server remotely
That particular feature is extremely extremely valuable
It's very very nice to have that because also one of the things that the openSUSE installer has supported for a very long time is
You can spin up a VNC server over the network and install the system headless using VNC
Which is extremely cool and of course, I got to give a plug Corky beta is pointed out in the chat room
You got to love midnight commander one of the old-school and curses based file managers for the command like a classic
Midnight commander is very awesome a network manager
There's a hold on hold on network manager has a has a and curses interface
No way is that a thing I'd be really interested. I used to use wick d or wicked
Yes, but I guess that's not maintained anymore. No, I would love another curses based Wi-Fi manager
Yeah, look at this on December 2013. I'm apparently this is old-school news
Network manager gets a new text interface while network manager already has a great integration with Nome and KD desktops
There's now a command line interface
It's an open source network management program has the end curses based interface. Look at that
So we eat that is very cool and then colonel panic. Is that how you say that one West?
What do you think colonel colonel panic, but a little bit? It's not spelled with a K. It's colonel
See with that see I'm saying they see oh and yes, but that's a military
Colonel, okay. All right. All right fine. He goes with it. He's got I think a python debugger here
Which is an end curses interface? Oh interesting. Look at that
I'm really surprised that nobody has said our two end curses picks yet
You and I have two really good ones, and I'm surprised
This is colonel panic. Oh my god Chris, but colonel's panic is spelled with a K. I know he's already taken that one
All right
Are you anybody else in the mumber and want to throw out their favorite end curses app before?
Noah and Arab Noah before Wes and I give away the
The best I think we have some really good ones. I think so. All right, nobody's chiming in Wes
You mentioned this one last week
ncdu
Love ncdu a super fast utility you go into a directory
You can say like ncdu and you can give it a directory you can give it the root and it goes through and scans your disk
Usage in real time. It is so so nice. In fact, I should probably just install it right now. It's so nice
I'm gonna install it right now now. I like as well that you can have it export so like we at work
We've got some scripts that all that'll run that as well
So when it has a disk, you know, a host has disk space that's above above what we've said is warning
It'll have saved already on the back end really you can just pop that up. You don't have to rescan it
You can just explore visually
I went to go show it I went to go show ncdu on the live stream and it worked so fast that I couldn't actually
Show you it processing my directories. It's way faster than any graphical tool is way faster and here you can say you can see
I'm I'm wasting a ridiculous
fifty one point seven gigabytes on this bonobo to the Dropbox
That is and you know what's crazy about that. That is a fraction of what is actually in the Dropbox
Let's see here. Does it what is this Dropbox tell you how much space you're using now? Yeah, I'm using that. Oh my god
Oh my god. Do you have a guess how much space I'm using in Dropbox?
Just take just a rough guess just one guess I'll just take one guess
Because here you go. Here you go with 51 gigs are just on this bonobo just on the bonobo on this bonobo alone
So you can assume this is probably just the files. I need just us them just for the show production. I'm gonna guess
700 gigabytes. Oh, that's pretty good. That's pretty good. That's pretty good two terabytes. Oh
Terabytes up in that Dropbox so any enterprise
It's ridiculous. So ncdu is a really really really nice tool that West mentioned last week
That is a very nice straightforward way to go through and so you can see like so say I wasn't gonna go
Delete stuff out of my Dropbox folder, but I wanted to go look at some my other big offenders here downloads
I go into there you can see look and look at all look at five gigs going to gunsmoke old-time radio right worth it
Don't get rid. I know I'm not
1.3 gigabytes is going to X minus one another old-time radio show and then another
337 is going to Superman
But I can easily see where a lot of my storage space is going to in my downloads folder
Which is really really nice and the other really nice thing about this is it works great through an SSH connection
So when you're remote it into that system, you know a hegemon eight in the IRC
He's got a great point also mixer something we take for granted. That's that's curses. What is it?
Awesome. Yeah. Yeah, and there's also there's a pulse audio controller. That's also in curses based, which is really cool and thin
There's another app that I I love two things now telegram is an end curses base
But there is a telegram command-line client, which is really cool for drop-down menu. I haven't tried. Yeah. Yeah
Talks to X now you're familiar with talks. It's kind of like a Skype killer open source
Yeah in the shadow of Edward Snowden that kind of came out right and it grows it blossoms in the shadow of Edward Snowden and
There is toxic
toxic is a tox based instant messaging client and
You guessed it has an end curses interface so you can use talks
In the command-line like say association to a droplet or something like that using end curses. This is my pick
This is I think a really I'm like
Super remiss for not mentioning pipe cut. Oh, yeah. Oh
So pipe cut is this tool to allow you to like when you're when you're dealing with data on Unix, right?
You do like some file cat file pipe grep for something and then sort and then unique minus C
And then sort numerically by the results of that to get and then pipe tail or something like that
Right to get the lab the top ten most popular IP addresses in your web server log or something
this allows you to build those interactively and surf back and forth through your pipe and like when you're
Applying a grep filter it will highlight on the screen
What things you're going to match and what things aren't as you're writing the regular so really stands out
That is so nice. Yeah, I'm looking at their site website right now pipe cut at pipe cut dot org
This is really a presentation. We interviewed the author and did a presentation about it at meet PSD. It is really cool
Yeah, it is. Holy crap. I'm saving this one to go grab after the show
It seems like a great tool to help. I mean one professionals the two people trying to learn. Yeah pipes
Yes, it's like the best teaching tool ever. Yeah. Well, it really illustrates what you're doing, which is really cool
All right. So how about this one this one coming in from Corky our TV our TV?
No, it's not something for your trailer. It's an end curses
reddit client a
reddit terminal viewer right there our TV is an application allows you to view and interact with reddit from your terminal. Oh
I love it. That is so cool. That makes reddit so much better
That makes it so you know getting something like reddit out of the web is I don't know
It's pretty cool. Our TV is built on Python using as you guessed it the curses library
Really really neat. That's a good one
IP traf is another great one. I agree
LFTP something if top yes H top was which was mentioned earlier in the show
I'm gonna put a links to as many of these as that were mentioning as possible in the show notes
So that way you get you guys can check this out. I here's what I love about it. What's that?
A callback to earlier in the show up in WRT has in curses. Mm-hmm. Nice. That is really here's what I here's what?
Here's the point. I want to make I don't think end curses interfaces are out of date or old-school at all
I think there's still a very practical application for a text-based GUI. Yep, and
With VPS is and and cloud computing and becoming more and more common
I think they have a better place than ever like I think these are really really good stuff
So Linux actually showed our reddit.com, please
Please tell me about your favorite end curses based application for episode 114 find the feedback thread
I would really like to hear about them. I want to try them out
I'm all in like I'm like screw gooey's right now and just speaking of gooey's though
If you write your shell script thing in dialogue, you can substitute dialogue for X dialog
Get the gooey version too. Very nice. Very nice. What we gonna say with I just say it's nice that you know
It's just like a terminal away. Yeah, you already have your terminal open. Yeah, someone listening to this show. Yeah
You don't have to learn a new GUI you're already familiar with that right as applications work and
Corky beta says if you give it a good color scheme and curses can be the most modern UI ever
I was just gonna make that joke. All right rotten corpse. You want to take us out with our last end curses pick here
Yeah, see us music player. Yes. Yes. See us music player at I I'm familiar
They have there's an arch wiki entry on it
but I think they're just on a CMUS CMUS that github.io and
It's a small fast powerful concert music player for Unix like operating systems
So even you Mac users can get a little something out of that one CMUS. That's a good one rotten
Man, I'm really for some reason all of a sudden. I'm sitting here. I'm getting super
Foreclamped over end curses based applications like anything I could run out of a terminal. I'm all about these days
So those are really good ones. Thank you guys
And if you want to submit any others
Linux action show dot reddit comm also a good place to go to submit content for this show or the Linux action show
To spotlight open source projects to give something a little of attention, you know, it turns out it's also just a popular Linux subreddit
Regardless of our shows it's also just a popular way for people to talk about cool open source projects and that helps the show
As well Linux action show to reddit comm and also you can contribute directly by going to Jupiter broadcasting comm slash
Contact and sending in some feedback right there. We have a drop-down
You just choose Linux unplugged and send it in and of course
I would be remiss if I didn't mention
patreon comm slash today if you'd like to invest in this show allow us to be flexible with the sponsors that we choose and
Make sure that we can continue to predict to pay our production staff and all those goodies patreon comm slash today
It's a great way for you to get involved with the financial end of this show. I'd love to get more submissions
Yeah, I'm excited to see the final list I know maybe we'll do a follow-up next week
Yeah, like for some reason like these really are hitting like a sweet spot with you. I think these are really sweet Wes sir
Thank you for being here. Thanks for bringing any time
Thank you to the mumble room jblive.tv if you'd like to join us live Jupiter broadcasting comm slash counter to get those live time zones
Our virtual lug is open. We just got to check your mic, and then you get to join us alright everybody
Thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux unplugged see you right back here next week
All
Right that show moved on do you feel like that show moved yeah, whoo yeah, all right all right very good very good
All right, so we go to JB titles. We pick our title, and then we all feel like we accomplished something doesn't that feel good
Yes, it does
Good stuff and curses apps are fun for me for some reason. I'm an old man. It's just fun
Yeah, I like this title suggesting Katie connect all the things I
Look at Microsoft and all of their company resources all of their employees all of their money
And then they ship a product that looks like this
Right and makes noises like that. I don't want to make it noises like that. I don't even know why it made that noise
It didn't tell me anything. Why did it make that noise? Why does it do these things?
Why is there so much contrast in the in the Explorer Windows? Why are the fonts so small is with this menu?
It's like transparent, so you can't you can't even read it. You can't even read it and the thing is nobody talks about this
Nobody talks about it. It's fine now
You know Katie he's got a funky font or gnomes got a corn that's not perfectly rounded or the Mac does something
That's not perfect, and it's all it's all we talked about a freaking. It's a huge deal Windows is a complete and total
presentation crap show with three different types of interfaces built into it three different uis built into it and
Nobody gives it a hard time everybody gives it a pass even we do this is
Disgusting look at that. You can't even read that it's gross and and yet not nobody says anything. I can explain that completely
Let's hear it
Standards I agree standards that are not using Windows and everybody knows Windows is complete. I agree
I think I think we collectively just been like oh well Windows is the challenge kid in the classroom
And so we don't expect as much from Windows. Oh look Windows. How's that? It has the start menu that slides up real nice?
Oh look what a good job Windows is done
Windows has done such a great job. Yeah, exactly yeah, the Windows gets its trophy. They had a release
They couldn't even get their numbering right they couldn't even count correctly I
Just think yeah, I can't stand it as an operating system
It is so awful it is so awful and then so the thing the line
I have to walk is and how do you not judge people who want to use Windows people who choose to use Windows?
How do you know because they have their own valid reasons?
And they probably spend a lot of time making Windows suck a lot less
They probably don't even realize how much energy they put into making Windows suck less over like they set up a Windows box
And they probably spend three months getting it not sucking a lot of work. Yeah, it's the worst dude Windows is the worst