Sometimes there's these news stories that come across
and you're like, what is going on?
Like, what must be happening behind the scenes
to make this story a reality?
So Microsoft is working on AMD GPU hot plugging
for the Linux kernel, not AMD, but Microsoft.
Yeah, I guess this is targeted at the data center.
Microsoft said in a quote that,
we believe the support of hot plug of GPU devices
can open doors for many advanced applications
in the data center for the next few years.
So data center use, maybe for like,
adding GPUs to virtual machines and then removing it?
Yeah, Michael Larbo from Onyx kind of speculates
that this is for Azure hot adding and removing
of AMD accelerators for VMs, exactly.
What a wild, wild world.
And this, you know, wouldn't be possible
unless AMD was contributing their code to the Linux kernel.
And so now they get to benefit from the developers
at Microsoft improving the capabilities
of their hardware product.
I mean, it's for their own interest, but.
Well, on the flip side, right?
Like Microsoft doesn't necessarily have to work directly
with AMD, as long as they can get it reviewed
and accepted upstream of the kernel,
no one's stopping them.
Hello friends, and welcome into your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
My name is Brent.
And my name is Alex.
Hello guys.
How great it is to be in the same room with you.
Coming up on the show today,
we just got back from our big East Coast meetup.
We've got some great stories,
some observations about our fellow Linux users,
and a lot more.
Plus we're going to round it out with some boosts,
some picks, and much, much more.
I would normally introduce the lug right here,
but we had technical issues because we're on live location.
So we're not going to have a virtual lug today.
I apologize ahead of time.
It's heartbreaking.
Wes stayed up all night,
creating some sort of great, powerful contraption
to make this happen.
But unfortunately I came in here this morning
and I tore it all down, didn't know what it was.
And so we just don't have a mumbling.
Well, it had become sentient.
So I think that was the responsible move.
Yeah, it was a tough choice, but the show must go on.
But we do have so much to get to,
and you're going to hear from a ton of audience members
anyways that perhaps it's okay.
I hope so.
We're all hanging out here at Alex's house today.
It's pretty great.
So thanks for hosting us, Alex.
You're very welcome.
That is until my neighbor starts shoveling gravel
from his truck.
Well, it is a nice day out.
So, you know, we've got to get yard work done.
That is the only thing.
But I've been here since Thursday.
Brent, I think you've been here since Thursday.
Do we all come in on Thursday?
No, you came in on Wednesday.
Yeah, I came in on Wednesday.
Yeah, yeah.
I did come in on Wednesday,
but I stayed at a hotel the first night
just because we came in so late.
But it was Thursday that the team really assembled.
Yeah, yeah.
So yeah, I came in, I decided,
wouldn't it be nice not to do like a red-eye flight,
to just do like a midday flight?
How reasonable.
So in the Pacific Northwest, we flew out like 3 p.m.
on Wednesday last week.
And then we landed in Raleigh around 11.50 midnight.
And we didn't want to like wake Alex and his wife
and the baby up.
And we thought, we'll just land and do one of those
like right next to the airport hotels.
Just, you know, wham bam, quick and easy.
Yeah.
So we roll up to this place called a Microtel.
They call it a Microtel.
Which is like, really guys, what are we doing?
It's just like a cheap crappy hotel
that's been refurbed three times.
That's like a step above a nanotel though.
It's better than a nanotel.
So we go in there.
And as I'm opening the door, this guy rushes past me.
And he's like in a panic.
And he just like kind of brushes us out of the way.
And you know, we got our luggage and everything.
So we're kind of like taking up some space.
And he like kind of slams in past us.
Doesn't speak a lick of English.
So he takes forever to get his room booked.
Even like leaves for part of it.
And then the guy tries to like book us.
And then he comes back and he's even more in a panic.
And anyways, so then I'm like, that's not a great sign,
right, but we're starving and we're tired.
So I figured.
Get to your room, get some food, go to bed.
Yeah, let's just get this over with.
I'm excited about getting over to Alex's.
That's gonna be a lot nicer.
Let's just do this.
So I reinstalled the damn Uber Eats app on my phone,
which I just deleted because I was swearing off Uber Eats,
right, because it's so crappy usually.
But I figured, you know, the wife's hungry.
She's got diabetes.
She's got the low blood sugars.
I'm gonna take care of the situation.
Oh, look, the only thing nearby is a McDonald's
for a $4 freaking delivery charge.
Okay, fine, fine, it's 1 a.m., right?
So the moment we get the room,
like the moment we get the room number,
I place this order on Uber Eats, right?
And I'm a little kind of apprehensive about doing this
because I'm like committing to be in this place
for an hour, at least if I do this.
And I'm not sure this is the hotel we want to be in
because my initial impressions is maybe like
they're cooking something in the lobby,
but I don't see anything being cooked.
But it sure smells like something's being cooked.
But I think to myself, maybe in the back room,
like I made himself a meal, you know,
just ran the microwave.
What kind of smells are we talking about here?
Ethnic?
That's it, like all I can say is like smells of food,
clearly food, but not food I could identify.
I couldn't like, it were all like meals
I've never personally eaten, but I'm like,
oh, that's what food smells like.
Strong, unknown food.
Yeah, very strong.
But you know, the lobby, maybe they have a kitchen, right?
I don't know.
So after we get all checked in,
after I place my order, we get in the elevator
and the elevator smells like burnt rubber, real bad.
And what do you think about?
Like you get in an elevator and it smells like burnt rubber.
Doesn't sound like what you want.
You're thinking maybe like the tracks are bad,
like the little wheels it might have are bad.
If there's one vehicle you would really rather
didn't smell at all, it would be a Lyft.
Yeah, right, right?
And okay, so we get up to the second floor
and we step out and it's a whole new set of food smells.
Totally separate, totally different.
Maybe that's like a part of their brand, you know,
you get like a themed smell per floor.
Right, and then as you walk down this floor, second floor,
you walk through different zones of stink.
And I would actually probably describe it as stench.
And you would think that every single hotel room
had a kitchenette where they were making
their own individual meals,
although there are no kitchenettes in this entire hotel.
And it's like probably three or four different phases
of smell as we go to the very end of this hallway.
Cause of course you're walking down this torturous stench.
And of course our rooms at the very end of the hallway.
So you gotta walk past all of the stench.
My wife described it as a bouquet of stench.
So then you get to the door, you open the door up
and boom, you're hit with a totally different smell.
Oh, you finally learned what your rooms customs smell is.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And it's been sitting all day
and it was a humid day in Raleigh.
So it is moist in our bedroom, right?
And we're from the Pacific Northwest
where you don't really have that kind of like
hanging humidity.
And so like, it smells horrible.
We are damp, it's 1 a.m.
And I'm already on my second Uber Eats driver.
Like the first Uber Eats driver is already noped out.
And I'm on my second Uber,
I'm looking at the tracking screen,
like where's my damn burger, right?
So we look at the bed, we pull back the sheet,
the cover, you know, there's like a big liquid stain
and then like hair on the stain.
And then it's just sort of like artfully placed
at the tip of the stain, a cigarette hole.
Like I'm serious, I'm so serious right now.
Did you take a picture for Instagram?
I did not because I was in a bad place at this time.
I just wanted to eat.
So we're sitting there on the bed,
kind of like huddling together,
like on one edge of the bed on this like queen mattress
or whatever because like the other one's
just completely like a no-go zone now.
And this second Uber Eats driver just like nopes out.
And I'm like, two Uber Eats drivers have noped out.
We got a third one at this point.
I'm like, okay, well, what's going on?
This driver has been sitting at McDonald's
for like 45 minutes.
It's almost 2 a.m.
My wife's got, you know, low blood sugar.
I'm trying to get her fed.
Like let's figure out what's going on here.
So I text this guy and say, you know,
everything okay?
I send him the text message.
Two seconds later, food's on the way.
The guy's driving, right?
Doesn't text anything back.
Shows up at the old hotel.
Drops it off at our door.
Doesn't knock on the door.
Then sends me a text message saying,
your food's been gently placed by your door.
So I open it up.
It's somebody else's order.
It's not my order.
Oh no.
It's not my food.
It's a totally different set of food.
It's all cold.
It's all totally cold.
Like to the touch cold, right?
And then, so I'm like,
I slammed down some really bad burger
because I'm starving.
My wife slams down some really cold fries
because her meal wasn't even in there.
And then I go to bed, right?
But I've picked a place close to the airport.
So it's like legitimately in the path of the takeoff.
So as the planes take off,
they are flying over my room.
I got a nice view of the plane taking off.
And that's fine.
I started to get used to that,
but around 4.30 a.m. or so,
a plane came in for like a hard landing
and I swear to God,
I thought they were gonna hit the building.
It was shaking the bed.
I thought we were gonna die.
It was rough.
So I didn't sleep so good that night.
So it's really nice to be over here at Alex's.
Maybe you would have been better with the red eye.
Yeah, I know, right?
The moral of the story is,
don't try to save money on a hotel room near the airport.
We went for the cheapest.
It was 90 bucks a night.
This is not that cheap, but these days it is.
You gotta remember, sleep is like a superpower.
I know, it really is.
It was a touch and go there for a little bit.
So it's been nice.
Alex has made us,
it's like at Alex's bed and breakfast here, you know?
So we got rooms, we got a kitchen.
You know, we should charge 90 bucks a night on Airbnb.
You could.
I think, I feel like you could actually.
And you got the cute dog,
so people are gonna wanna stay.
That's true.
Oh yeah, yeah.
With Airbnb, it would be a dog fee, $9,000.
Right. Exactly.
Now I know, so my,
like a lot of my bumpiness was after the flight,
like my flight and stuff,
that all went smooth, obviously,
cause I'm not complaining about it.
But Brent, didn't you end up in some sort of weird,
like multi-flight situation?
I know Wes did too.
So how was your trip in?
Actually, surprisingly,
usually I have a really great story to tell,
but this time it was really bland and boring.
That's good.
Which I think is what you're looking for
in terms of flights.
So I, the only thing I went wrong
was I spilled my Thai food under my seat
after they forced me to put my luggage up on the rack
instead of down there.
So I was a little.
Pad Thai down.
Yeah, Pad Thai down.
That's too bad.
And that went quite well.
And Wes?
I did take the red eye path this time,
just figuring, you know,
I'd seen your flight
and you were gonna get in pretty late.
I thought, okay, I'm still young enough, right?
I can handle a red eye.
I sleep. I love it.
It's about age.
I sleep decently most of the time.
I feel lucky in that regard.
And yeah, that part of it went just fine.
But, you know, as I land on the ground,
I had a layover in JFK.
As I land kind of groggy,
it's like five in the morning,
I'm waking up,
reconnect to LTE and get my notifications.
Your flight has been canceled.
I was like, wait, what?
Which flight?
The flight of mud?
No, that doesn't make sense.
My next flight?
I guess I'm in New York now.
No, thankfully not.
JetBlue had figured it out.
So by the time, you know,
by the time I'm off the plane,
I didn't have to go talk to anyone.
They'd already emailed me like an updated itinerary.
The only catch was the,
it added an extra flight.
And the first stop I had to do
was go from JFK up to Boston,
which is a 38 minute flight.
Oh, that's such a weird flight.
And because they were kind of having to reschedule things
after the cancellation,
of course it was delayed,
it took a while to get off,
but we still arrived earlier than expected.
So there was another plane already in our spot.
So it was probably like an hour and a half
or a two hour fare from like learning about it
to actually getting to Boston
for 40 minutes of air time.
Wow.
A 40 minute flight,
it feels like you're gonna spend more time
just getting on board,
sitting on the tarmac and getting off.
That was exactly it.
Yeah.
We were on the, we took Delta on the way out from Seattle
and you sit down, right?
And they're booting up all of the in seat displays and stuff.
And I'm like, look, look, honey, this is Linux.
Isn't that cool?
These displays all run Linux.
Oh yeah, that's neat.
You know, that's cool.
We're going on Linux event.
We're on Linux airplane.
Yeah, that's great.
Then we're on the flight
and the thing is so dog slow.
She's like, so this is your Linux, huh?
This is great.
This is.
Probably like a two point something kernel still.
Yeah, oh man.
Well, they're all doing like, they're doing like this weird
like shared display when they can.
I'd be really curious how this works
if anybody out there knows,
but like when you use the flight tracker,
all of the displays on the flight tracker screen
are all updating at the same time.
They're all in sync.
So is it one video feed
or are they actually running instances
of that flight tracker at, you know,
whatever amount of seats that are running it
and somehow they're still staying in sync.
I don't know, but it was a two core Linux system
cause it had two of the tuxes at the top of the screen.
Oh, I know, right?
I love walking through the airport
and like trying to observe like what devices people
are using, if they're using Bluetooth,
if they're using an Apple product or an Android product.
Saw a lot of laptops,
a lot of people using laptops in the airport.
Did you try any new tech on this trip?
Hmm, no, but it is the first time
I've used the Plex downloads feature
since they've introduced the Plex sync versus Plex downloads
and I don't really see a much difference.
It's kind of wonky because it recreates
the directory structure of your online server.
So because I pulled it down from two different servers,
I had two different like libraries I had to manage
instead of just all my downloaded videos,
but it worked nice.
We got the new season of The Expanse
and also Enterprise, season one.
And the nice thing is, is you can just say,
just sync down the stuff I haven't watched yet.
Hmm, that's killer.
And now the thing will be is how well does it do
syncing back what we watched?
So then when I go back to my,
are you starting fresh?
We'll see, we'll see, but that was nice.
But I think that was the only new tech
did either one of you guys do anything new tech wise
for this trip?
Oh, you did.
Yeah, I picked up some of those
Sony noise canceling headphones
and I haven't really had a good pair
of active noise canceling headphones before.
So that was sort of my trial run on the flight this time.
And it was nice, I think especially
because I was taking a red eye,
you know, just let me tune things out.
That extra flight from Boston too, it started off,
I was right at the very back,
like the last row of the plane.
And there was a pretty loud mechanical noise
like until it really got to cruising speed.
So that was handy.
And thankfully I hadn't really even,
this was sort of a last minute,
like, oh yeah, I'm flying,
I really need some new headphones.
Let's just get it, pull the trigger.
Hadn't tested it, but it works beautifully with PipeWire.
Ah, that's great.
You didn't do any new tech for you, Brent?
Or did you have it all dialed in?
I tend to not wanna try new things
because you know, if it's gonna fail,
it'll be when you need it the most.
Look at this guy, the reasonable one over here.
I was tempted to move to a new phone.
As you know, my sort of tried and true phone
is about to explode.
The battery is about twice the thickness
that it should be, so.
Legitimately, I keep telling him it's a fire hazard.
We just think it's definitely a fire hazard.
So about like three days before the trip,
I thought, oh, I gotta change.
I can't bring this thing.
This is just a hazard to everybody.
And, but I never got there
because the other phone I was gonna switch to
doesn't have an audio jack and.
Oh, the audio headphone jack.
Yeah, I got one of those little dongles,
but it was a cheap one like from the grocery store.
It was like the day before I was leaving,
so I couldn't order anything reasonable.
And it sounded awful, so I didn't even bring it.
Well, you know, when you got a phone
where the battery is grown outside the case,
where it's popped the back of the case off,
I'd probably say the best thing to do
would be taking it up on an airplane.
That's probably.
Yeah.
I like that his, you know, audio snobbery too,
is he's willing to put his own personal self at risk
just for that.
Yeah, cause you know, you put it in your pocket, right?
You know what's near your pocket, right?
Like.
Yeah, it's nice and warm.
I like it.
Oh, man.
I guess as long as it's keeping you comfortable.
Well, we have a lot to talk about today.
We had a hell of a meetup yesterday
and I tried to talk to people about
what Linux stuff they're doing,
what's not working for them with Linux,
what is working for them, what distros they're using.
And we try to get a flavor of who's out there.
And I think we did a pretty decent job.
You know, we always kind of evolve every meetup
and try to learn and adapt.
But before we get started today,
I have kind of a special announcement
I want to start the show with
cause I'm very excited about this.
And you guys know that we've been talking about
the future of podcasting in general
and JB shows in particular.
And you know about how particular we are
and how careful we are with the sponsors we pick.
And so I'm super excited to welcome Bitwarden
on board for Linux Unplugged.
They're on board for a little bit
and round of applause, right?
Because we're all Bitwarden users in here.
Yeah, we are.
And I think it's just an absolute great sponsor.
Now I'm not sure the landing page is live yet.
So the background here is Bitwarden has really made an effort
to support independent Linux content.
And so this is all kind of getting set up right now.
So bitwarden.com slash Linux is gonna be the landing page.
If it's not live when you hear this,
let them know maybe via support or some other way
that that's how you heard about it.
Because I'd love for them to stick around for a bit
because I think this is a great sponsor for the show.
So it's bitwarden.com slash Linux.
And you go there, you get started with a free trial
for a team or enterprise account
or for your personal account for an individual user as well.
And it really is, Bitwarden is just the easiest way
for businesses and individuals to store, share,
and sync sensitive data.
And it's not just passwords,
although that's the primary use case
I think a lot of us have for it.
But you can also store your two factor authentication
tokens in there, things like recovery passwords
for maybe like element.
And maybe your Bitwarden certificate
is what I realized I should be putting in there.
I use it to store secure notes.
So I have like WireGuard configs in there too.
Ah, that's a good idea.
Yeah, the attachments feature is pretty darn convenient.
Yeah, I like the idea of putting
my WireGuard config in there.
Yeah, so it's more than just passwords really,
but that is what's great.
And like the support for two factor authentication
is so nice because if you use it on mobile,
it really streamlines the whole process
of good passwords on mobile.
And I think that is really key.
The other thing they have now is account switching support.
How great is this?
So it's super easy to switch between your personal
and a business account or maybe a personal account
and an open source project that you're working with.
And one of the things that's given me confidence
to use Bitwarden is that I know they have
a self-hosted option available if I want it.
I can get that up and running if I need to.
I prefer to just get things up and going really fast
with Bitwarden Cloud.
I trust the security they have around that
and it just got me going immediately
and it made it super easy to share stuff.
And the other nice thing is either route,
they have a very large and active community
in both their forums and on Reddit
and really everywhere online.
Bitwarden just has millions of users.
So you get a lot of community support
if that's the kind of route you prefer to go.
A couple of years into using Bitwarden,
I think what I've really learned to appreciate
is how simple it makes bringing on team members.
Like Alex, you have a way where you use it
where you don't share all of your passwords with somebody,
you just share a few of your passwords.
That's right, yeah.
So my wife and I, I created an organization
and let's say there's a password to log into daycare
to pay the daycare bill or something like that.
We can both share that password
as part of the KTZ organization
that I've created in my Bitwarden kind of universe.
And we both have access to those passwords,
but it's on a need to know basis.
Yeah, I like that.
That's really nice.
And I've been able to do that with team members
when they come on or just like somebody
who's working on a project for us.
And it has made just keeping really good passwords
and safe passwords straightforward and simple.
And I think we all probably know this,
but it's a good reminder that just a good password
and good password hygiene is one of the few things
you can really do to notably improve your online
account security and your safety.
You probably already knew that,
but maybe somebody in your life needs to hear that.
So send them to bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Go try it for yourself, for your business,
and you'll support the show.
It's a great way to get started.
If you're an enterprise or if you're an individual user,
you can go there and get a free trial
at bitwarden.com slash Linux.
And it's free for an individual user.
You may find you don't need the cloud service.
I added it for the two factor support alone,
but there's a lot you can get out of Bitwarden.
Just go try it, go see it for yourself.
It's bitwarden.com slash Linux.
And a big welcome aboard to Bitwarden
for joining us on the show.
It's just super, super great to get support like that,
especially right now.
And you can support the show
by visiting bitwarden.com slash Linux.
All right, let's talk about our meetup.
I feel like there's a lot to talk about
and it's an exciting time.
I think we should,
maybe we should start with like the behind the scenes moment.
We did capture a little bit of like the sitting down
at the kitchen table and us having a conversation
before we left to the event to go like pick up food
and do all the things we had to do
before the event started.
So I'll take you back to like two hours before showtime.
We're sitting in Alex's kitchen.
It's about 15 minutes before we got to leave for the meetup.
Saturday morning on April 9th.
We've been here for a couple of days.
Yesterday was all about eating a lot of food.
And today it's not like we're,
we're not nervous or anxious,
but there's just so many things we still have to pull off
in the next two hours.
I think we're just anticipating,
we're just ready to get this thing started.
But also, super exciting that it's Wes's birthday today.
Happy birthday, Wes.
Wes.
Aw, thank you.
I really can't imagine anything better than,
I mean, being with the team in person.
Happy birthday to you.
With these amazing fools.
I mean, what could really be better?
And Alex's beautiful home,
which he has been so gracious hosting us at.
And yeah, you know, there's just been a lot of,
a lot of excitement and work to get here.
Alex scouting locations,
actually being willing to host us
and the community here in Raleigh.
And then just the small details,
things like rolling up t-shirts.
Rolling up t-shirts seems to be like the key
to a good event, doesn't it?
Well, you gotta have all the little pieces in place
so you're not distracted and you can actually, you know,
do the thing we're excited about,
which is interacting with our amazing audience.
Alex, how's it been having the whole crew
in your house, basically?
It's been a lot of fun.
I really, we're all just guests in Archie's house, my dog.
You know, but you know, to celebrate Wes's birthday,
Chris's iPhone just showed him a montage of past events
and 90% of the pictures were him and Wes recording audio.
One of those pictures was a beer picture.
So I think this afternoon at the brewery,
perhaps we need to, we need to fix that ratio.
We did do better.
I had a couple, I got a couple of ciders down the hatch.
You got a beer too?
Oh yes, I did.
So that, that worked out pretty good.
And even the line at the brewery was helpful
because it was a bit chilly yesterday, let's be honest.
And the brewery was nice and warm.
Everybody was troopers because the standing temperature
was like 55, 60 degrees.
But then you bring in that, you know,
15, 20 mile per hour wind chill and it was really cold.
So after three or so hours, maybe three and a half,
four hours, we actually got the whole crowd
migrate to the brewery.
I think that was some excellent foresight on Alex's part
to pick a spot that had an adjacent brewery.
Yeah, and a barbecue place.
And you know, there was all types.
So let's dig into that a little bit at this event.
I think we all got a chance to at least see the deck
floating around.
Listener Jeff brought his steam deck to the event.
And of course I had to go hands on.
Yeah, I have a steam deck.
I love it.
It's been a lot of fun.
I love it for being, picking it up and being able to play,
you know, five, 10 minutes of a game and put it down
and not have to worry about it.
And have you tried anything else with it at all?
Like poking around, exploring?
Yeah, I haven't had a whole lot of time to do that.
I did have this whole thing where
I was going to run Ansible and get everything figured out.
But with the Immutable OS, apparently
Flatpak's the way to go.
So I haven't exactly had a whole lot of time to play with it.
I do have KDE Connect on it so I can move things back and forth.
But that's about it.
It does look nice, new, and shiny.
Do you want to show Chris how it works?
Sure.
All right, OK.
Oh, we've got a game going too already.
Hades.
Hades, and it looks good.
Any tips or tricks for him?
Kill the skeleton.
I'm good at killing skeletons.
But you know, of course, the first thing I want to do
is I want to get on the desktop.
How do you get on the desktop?
Little trigger action or?
Yeah, so you've got to go down to this one.
Go down to power, A, and then desktop mode.
Switch to desktop.
All right, switching to desktop.
I'm going to bust out the track pads here.
Oh, it's kind of almost doing like a whole new loading thing.
There we go.
I got plasma.
That's fun.
That was easy.
Yeah, they've got to return to gaming mode.
They've got a virtual keyboard here.
It felt pretty good in the hand too.
You know, it felt pretty solid.
What did you think weight-wise?
Did you expect it to be heavier?
I expected a denser, heavier thing.
Yeah, me too.
It was about as light as a.
As a game, like a controller, like an Xbox controller.
Yeah, like an Xbox controller.
Like there wasn't a whole computer in there.
Yeah, it's crazy.
Yeah, I think the size would be more of the limiting factor,
just for portability and really the weight.
I thought the screen was great too.
We were in direct sun for a few little bits outside.
That's where it's going to be at its worst.
And it was fine.
Also, I mean, just I think this speaks to our audience.
He didn't quite get there, but I love the idea
of running Ansible on your gamepad.
I know, I know.
I know.
He also brought a pretty tricked out electric car too
that you got to ride in, Alex.
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
So this is Fuzzy Mistborn on the self-hosted Discord channel.
He brought the Hyundai IONIQ 5.
Hyundai, sorry, for the Americans.
This thing is a fully electric car,
and he just drove it down from Pennsylvania.
So he was a bit worried about the charging situation,
getting into town and stuff like that.
No problem.
No problem at all.
That's pretty slick.
And you got to go for a ride, and that's pretty great.
I did, yeah.
And he put this thing in sport mode,
and it pinned me back in my seat.
To get a petrol car that would do that,
you'd have to spend a lot of money.
Yeah.
I mean, we didn't really get a super official account,
because we didn't have a door, an entrance where we had
somebody counting and clicking.
No, we were just in a lovely park
where people were coming at us from every angle.
But we did buy 90 name tags, and they all disappeared.
So I think over the course of the afternoon,
about 100 people showed up.
I think so.
I think about exactly we asked, if you were going to go,
please try to sign up for the meetup, and people did it.
It was great, and it helped us plan for that.
I didn't sign up for the meetup, I'm sorry.
Great.
Sorry.
Somehow he snuck in anyway.
Yes, who led that guy in?
Party crusher.
So I don't know really how to describe it without saying we
just had all types there.
I mean, when I say that, I mean people who were longtime Linux
users, people who were brand new users to Linux,
people who were 11 years old, people who were 70 years old.
The whole range was there.
And one of the interesting couples that were there
was Jason and Kelly.
And they had come from Virginia.
So here we are at the meetup.
Tell us your names and where you came from.
I'm Jason.
I'm Kelly.
And we came from Alexandria, Virginia.
And for someone like me who has no idea how far that is,
how long would you have drove or?
It was a really long journey.
No, it's just about a four hour drive without traffic.
It's not bad at all.
And we actually have family in the Raleigh area,
so we were able to see them, multitask, and come here.
She graciously agreed to come with me to my Linux Nerdfest
meetup.
And what does the Nerdfest feel like for you?
Is it very inviting?
Oh, you know, I feel right at home here.
I have very nerdy brothers.
I have my own brand of nerdiness,
like Star Wars, fantasy, and sci-fi related.
You fit right in.
But not necessarily IT related.
But yeah, so no, it's great.
And how's the meetup for you?
Is this the first time you go to something like this?
This is the first time I've been to anything quite like this.
Closest I think before would be something like MAGFest,
which is like a music and gaming festival years and years ago,
because it's in the area that we live in.
But yeah, no, it's great.
It's so nice to finally put names
to faces from all the voices you hear on us and meet everybody.
Yeah, Jason and Kelly were really great.
And I would say that is true of most people.
But Jason was, I don't know, he stood out for me.
He told me that he worked at the Department of Defense
in the Office of the Inspector General.
I don't even, it sounds really interesting.
I don't know exactly what that is.
But he was the kind of person, and I saw this repeatedly.
You guys might agree with me, is that he was just
like insatiably curious about all the technologies
that he could get his hands on.
And so for instance, he said he learned Ansible recently,
which came up a lot.
And he said it just changed his world,
but also really made a really nice stride in his career.
He said that took him to a whole new level.
So I thought that was really interesting.
He said the Department of Defense, where he is,
runs all their stuff on Red Hat 7.9, which is interesting.
He was a little nervous about that.
Yeah, he was.
So I thought that was funny.
But he also said he works with a whole lot of data scientists
on some data analytics stuff, which sounded fascinating.
I love that there's Linux users everywhere.
So great.
This kind of lets us get a real sense of just
every weird little niche that Linux has found itself
over the years.
Yeah, yeah.
There's also those moments where you
meet people that you either click with right away,
or you share something in common with.
And we had those kinds of moments.
Of course, when you're named Chris,
you always meet another Chris at these events.
But Brent, you had a chance to meet another Brent.
My name's Arturo, and I drove here from Roanoke, Virginia.
So I had a six-hour drive yesterday
and a three-plus-hour drive today.
How about you?
I think we have something in common.
Yeah, we do.
Actually, I didn't have to drive that far.
It was all the way on the other side, actually,
over by the airport.
Did you fly into RDU?
Yep.
So that was my drive in.
And my name is Brent.
And you didn't have a name tag, did you?
No, I didn't have a name tag.
But I found another guy named Brent.
And it was good enough that he was able to share.
So it worked out pretty well.
I happened to put two layers on, and I put a name tag
on each layer.
And I was able to donate my name tag, which I think
is the first time that ever happens.
The Brents were so inseparable.
I mean, it was adorable.
They were great.
Well, you don't find them that often.
So they're all great people, I've got to say.
Now, if you're wondering, why did Brent have two name tags?
I'll tell you why, listener.
Because Brent is a damn pro.
That's why.
Because Brent had multiple layers of clothing
and had a name tag for each layer of clothing,
so that way he could remove his jacket
and he would still have his name tag on.
Not my first event.
Come on, gentlemen.
Say nothing else about Brent.
He's easily identifiable.
It reminds me of there's an episode of TNG, Star Trek TNG.
I don't know if it's Picard or who,
but somebody takes their jacket off, their uniform,
where they have their combat.
They take their jacket off, and there's
a combat on underneath.
That was Brent.
You know, the thing, too, that's really nice.
So you get people that they deal with Linux users
and they deal with Linux and other admins all day,
every day.
That's totally their thing.
That's the world they live in, right?
But then you also have people that are listening to the show
or maybe they're participating in the Mumble Room
or they come to these meetups because it's
the only place they hear anyone else talking about Linux.
Yeah, so the strange thing is I actually don't, aside from,
you know, we have a lovely gathering here,
I don't actually know anybody else who runs Linux.
What?
Yeah, no, I am a chemist in a factory.
Cool.
So I do industrial chemistry.
It's got nothing to do with Linux,
although there are some mighty fun apps for it.
But it's always just been kind of a thing
I've been interested in.
The local group is the Try Lug.
They're pretty good folks, so I kind of
fell in with them a little bit, and here we are.
I heard you guys were coming all the way over here.
I couldn't not make the 20-mile drive over, so.
We have a good crowd here, like a really good crowd.
I mean, people came from New York and Pennsylvania
and Virginia and Florida, too, but a lot of locals
here in Raleigh.
Yeah, I was impressed.
I mean, Alex, you've got a good crew.
Yeah.
Home of the Red Hat, I mean, it's perhaps not too surprising.
Red Hat, there's a, what's the other largest tech company
here, too?
I don't think there's as big as Red Hat.
There's all sorts.
So Raleigh is actually a conglomerate
of three different cities, and we call it the Triangle.
There's Raleigh, there's Durham, and there's Chapel Hill.
And in the middle of these things
is about where the airport is.
And just over the road from the airport,
pretty much by your crappy hotel,
is RTP, Research Triangle Park.
And in there, you've got IBM, Microsoft.
You've got Pfizer.
There's dozens of big pharma things in there.
Lots of big tech, too.
Yeah, some other tech companies as well.
Yeah, so I mean, it makes sense in retrospect.
It makes a lot of sense in retrospect.
I feel like, though, we had such a good turnout.
And that was, you know, also what
has taught me is the first one you do is when you get
the smallest turnout.
And if you do another one, you get an even larger turnout.
And so we're already talking about,
how are we going to do this on a yearly basis
now, because this is awesome.
You know, coming out here to see the people on the East Coast.
Clearly, we've been neglecting a very serious audience base.
I agree.
And we can get a nice cadence going.
If we have Linux Fest Northwest in the spring in Seattle
on the West Coast, and then something on the East Coast
in the fall, maybe.
And Denver every now and then to sprinkle it in.
And the other thing, of course, don't worry across the pond
if you're listening thinking, what about over here?
What about?
Alex is already campaigning.
I'm working the room.
I'm working.
I'm lobbying.
So it's going to happen.
But every now and then, you run into somebody.
And I think sometimes they have like a message
they want to relay to us.
Like, they've been listening to the show,
and there's something they want us to consider.
All right.
Hi.
I'm Elaine Fu.
In my day job, I'm a cloud and DevOps consultant.
At night, I am deeply involved in the Armbian project.
I've been involved for several years,
working either with CI or just advocating,
liaising between Eastern European folks and native English
speakers, and mostly just fighting the good fight
to let everybody know that there's a lot of stuff
out there besides Raspberry Pi on ARM.
I take that one personally.
I feel like he's dragging that comment to me.
Yes, Lane, I realize.
And Armbian is a great project.
We should probably do more work around that.
Yeah.
I think it just means that if you ever
want to try some more interesting boards out there,
other types of little tiny projects,
you've got a support system out there.
People like Lane Fu are working hard
to make it run decently on other things besides the Raspberry
Pi.
And they're just like, pay attention, would you?
We're working really hard to do this.
Message received.
We'll consider.
We will consider.
See, you come out to these events,
you get us to think about these things.
A lot of Python and Ansible love at the meetup.
And how about you?
My name's Sam.
I'm from Richmond, Virginia.
I'm a Python programmer.
That's my day job.
I was an Ansible core maintainer for about five years.
So long time Linux user.
Just love everything about Linux, open source,
and automation in Python.
That's basically my wheelhouse.
Sam's all about it.
And he had a lot to say.
And the thing is a lot of people had good things
to say about Python and about Ansible.
And Nix, there was some Nix love as well.
There was also some Nix shame.
Dusty came out, and Dusty made a hard pitch
for trying out the Fedora core stuff, the core OS stuff.
I think we've got to give that a fair shot too.
It's only fair.
I mean, you come to a meetup.
Dusty made a good case.
So Dusty said, automatic updates.
I know how you like that.
But also, they have these tracks you can subscribe to.
And one of them is a testing channel
that you can subscribe to.
And you'll get your, I think you said a week or two weeks?
You get two weeks heads up of all changes.
So you throw one machine in this testing channel,
and you get a good solid week heads up of changes.
Because they're all automatic updates.
You see where it goes.
And if that system doesn't break,
then your production system is going to be OK.
But hey, who are you kidding?
We're going to run testing on all our production machines.
Sure.
Yeah, I'll believe that when it happens.
So the nice thing about core OS in particular
is how it boots from one image or partition at a time.
So you can update the image you're not booted into
currently whilst you're booted into the previous one.
Then you reboot into the new image.
And if that's broken somehow, you just
fall back to the old image.
Like a kernel in grub.
Yeah.
Yeah, that does sound good.
And that also sounds consumer friendly for a device.
You can see where you could build in a system where
if the user is power cycling or something,
there's a little bit of logic that just says,
use the last image.
Well, I mean, isn't that some of the stuff
that Valve have had to invent for the way
they're deploying Arch on the Steam Deck?
Yeah, I actually kind of wonder.
I mean, I know we're hyped right now.
And I'm saying this before we've gotten our hands
on Steam OS 3.
Acknowledged and kind of wish we had already
seen this Steam OS 3 stuff.
But wouldn't it be interesting if in like five years
we look back at this and go, Valve was on the right path,
but they just totally implemented
like their own thing when they could have used something
like Nix or something like CoreOS
or anything that uses OS 3.
I wonder if we'll feel like good idea, bad implementation.
Kind of like Munich.
When Munich first did their own thing, we were like, oh, man.
The whole state is switching to Linux?
And then we found out their own custom distribution thing.
And they spent like six, seven years flailing around
trying to make that work.
And the whole time we were all just going,
why didn't you just use Ubuntu?
Maybe that's what's happening right now with the Deck.
But we're too early in the cycle.
We're all too hyped right now to realize it.
So you're saying just skip Steam OS 3.0 and wait till 4.0.
That'll be the good one.
Maybe.
Then again, maybe Linus was right.
Maybe Valve is going to start with Steam OS 3.0.
And they're going to build a consumer product that
is following some of these best practices.
And it ends up being the leading largest desktop use
of this kind of technology.
Linus said that it was going to be Valve that brought Linux
to the desktop masses.
So maybe this is the start of it.
And so maybe we'll look back at it
and think they were geniuses.
Does this mean that this is the year of the Linux desktop?
Oh, Alex.
You know, I was seeing a conversation about this online
recently, and I'm curious to know what you guys think.
But the basic premise is that whole concept
of the year of Linux desktop is harmful,
because it creates this set of expectations.
And the reality is that it's a slow march,
and that it becomes the year of the Linux desktop for each one
of us individually.
And by having this idea, we are doing the whole movement harm
and not recognizing the actual successes we're seeing.
What do you think of that idea?
Yeah, I mean, I think there's probably
a lot of truth in that.
But partially, I also think, does anyone
take the year of the Linux desktop seriously anymore
anyway?
No, it's a total joke, right?
I think everyone might already recognize that already.
I think we do.
I think the Linux community realizes
it's a meme at this point.
But I also hear people outside the Linux community
still throw it in our face as like, oh, yeah,
how's that year of the Linux desktop coming?
It's a very valid point.
I think my year of the Linux desktop
was about five or six, seven years ago when I was first
getting into Linux.
And since then, it's become a tool
I used to do various tasks.
Right.
And kind of assuming that there's
this minimum benchmark it must meet,
it's not really how computers work, is it?
Because Windows and Mac aren't great for everybody either.
It also sort of tries to assume an audience or a certain scale
that tries to say, like, that's what makes it matter when,
especially these days with the relevance of desktops
in general, it doesn't seem like maybe it's
the right concept.
Yeah, you don't really want to be
the winner of the thing that's kind of already on the out.
I mean, I'm going to use a desktop for as long as I can.
I'm not saying it's gone forever, but let's look
at the sales numbers.
It sort of tells its own story.
So we also had a special moment here.
In fact, I honestly wouldn't have been offended or surprised
if you said, sorry, guys, I'm talking to Wes.
Sorry, guys, I'm not going to be able to make it to this event.
I got stuff going on because it was Wes's birthday.
So we wanted to make it special since Wes decided
to spend his birthday with us.
We wanted to acknowledge that at the meetup.
And Alex, like a pro, seized the moment.
All right, where's Wes?
Hello.
Wes, come here.
Chris, come up here, too.
All right.
It's not my birthday.
Thank you all for coming so much.
Oh, yes.
Yes.
JP Fam, thank you.
This is really, really cool.
I think we're all here, pretty much.
I think people are coming, but.
This was a completely unplanned, accidental thing.
But today is Wes's birthday.
Hey!
Happy birthday, Wes.
I didn't know until yesterday.
So we bought him a birthday cake.
You're all welcome to have some.
There's one proviso.
Happy birthday to you.
Boop, boop, boop.
Handsome.
Happy birthday, dear Wes.
Wes, happy birthday to you.
Hey!
Woo!
Thank you, everyone.
All right.
There's a cake.
You have to come cut it.
Yeah, there is cake.
There was way too much cake.
What do we do with all that cake?
We've still got half the damn thing in my kitchen.
Both of them?
Yes.
I think we'll be packing on the pounds this trip.
Yeah.
But thank you for spending your birthday with us, Wes.
I can't imagine anything better.
Aw, geez.
That was pretty nice, though.
And everybody just was totally, immediately in on it.
Like, there was no convincing.
The whole crowd just immediately got in on it.
It was great.
Which I was very relieved of, because my singing voice is not
the best.
No.
If it was just you and I up there singing,
it would have been very embarrassing.
That's what stands out so much about these meetups, you know?
It's total strangers.
We've never seen 90% of these people.
Some of you, unfortunately, we may never see again.
But it's like an instant community.
We all know why we're there.
We're there for the same reasons.
We have the same interests and hobbies
and generally the same philosophies.
And so there's just like a weird and wonderful amount
of implicit trust that just kind of happens.
Yeah, like a lot of the basic social fabric
exists, because you can immediately talk about, well,
so how far away?
Where'd you come from?
Because everybody has that in common.
And you can talk about anything in Linux.
Anything you feel like talking about.
You want to talk about Wayland?
Go ahead.
It's so much simpler from a social interaction standpoint.
And so what you see happen every single time we do these events
is at first, it's sort of about us.
And people kind of cluster around us.
And then about an hour into it, everybody's
talking to each other.
Like people even who maybe don't have great social skills,
maybe they don't interact with people a lot.
But because we all have this in common,
and we all understand these terms,
like if somebody is out there talking about HTOP,
people know what HTOP is.
Like how common is that?
That's not very common in your real life.
My favorite thing was to come up to a bunch of complete
strangers and just hear the word Tasmota.
I'm like, hey, we can talk about that.
That's fun.
Let's go.
Right.
I was impressed with some of the audience members
just being so kind and generous too.
You know, we had people offering to show other folks around.
Or the number of times I saw someone,
they were kind of standing outside the circle a little bit,
maybe not sure where they wanted to go next.
People are just always offering, expanding the circle,
and welcome you right in.
Yeah, very true.
Then I also had a special moment.
So we had Wes's moment, and I had a special moment
which was totally unexpected.
So Nixie, everybody out there is probably familiar with Nixie.
She's been in the Linux community forever.
And she's got a YouTube channel that she does a lot of security
content on.
And they have, her and her crew, have this amazing 70s era GMC
RV.
And if you're an RVer at all that has
any kind of historical RV background,
you know these GMCs were like peak RV.
And I had a chance to actually see one of these
that was in full operation.
20 years I've wanted to see one of these.
20 years?
Really?
Yeah.
So this is actually how I got it.
It was actually set up as a desk like this, and it was a?
Server rack.
It was a server rack, yeah.
It is a server rack.
Yeah.
And he had closed circuit TV systems that he could plug in
and had monitors up here to monitor
some sort of security thing.
An RV with a server rack.
How cool is this?
I finally see a GMC and it's got a damn server rack in it.
Yeah.
Where are you?
Why haven't you done this?
I can't believe this.
So I don't know if this rig, I don't
know if they pull up at clients and hook up
to the security system or what they were doing,
but this thing was like a mobile RV security system.
I'm imagining some ethernet that you've
plumbed through on the outside and you just
sort of plug it into the building.
Yeah, yeah.
It's pretty neat.
Very cool rig.
You guys should Google this thing, the GMC RV.
They only made this.
So it's the only one they ever made.
So you're not going to have any problems finding it.
And it is very special.
And Nixie was talking a bit about that.
I mean, I just think it's really amazing how it handles.
Oh, yeah.
So it doesn't handle like a Greyhound bus.
It handles more like a limousine.
Like a limousine, baby.
That's great.
Yeah.
It is such a cool rig because it has
a super low center of gravity and air suspension in the back.
And it has dually tires.
And it's just the whole thing is just so friggin' awesome.
Real treat for me.
And also just like I love that there's
people in my audience who show up
at an event like this in their RV, right?
That's amazing for me.
So that was a good time.
Beautiful rig.
I think if the Jetsons designed an RV,
that's the design language that we had here.
This thing was just so cool.
Yeah, Chris, how did you describe it?
You said it was like retro future or something?
Yeah, it is.
Is that a weird design?
But that's the thing.
It's like future retro.
So it is also retro.
But it is also kind of how we're designing things now.
Well, yeah.
It was the idea from the past of what
the future could be in a direction
we unfortunately haven't quite taken.
Because as you also said, that thing
had a very Star Trek shuttle pod feel.
There's this curved glass in the cockpit.
Just seeing photon torpedoes.
They don't make them like that no more, I'll tell you what.
They don't.
But at that time, they wanted to build an RV where
they followed what the airline builders followed.
So when you're building a traveling jet,
like a 747 or something like that, all the building
policies, and even down to the paint.
The paint they chose was airplane paint.
And so as a result, the paint, it needs polished.
But the RV's paint still is on and holds up
after all these years.
And meanwhile, modern RVs just disintegrate
after 10, 15, 20 years.
You know something a little bit about that.
And they also don't make it out of corn wire.
So that also is a very good thing.
I also thought the suspension system
was like a whole weird, brand new, crazy thing.
Like that the wheels were able to turn slightly a little bit.
Just a little.
And it sounded like both sides of the rear suspension
worked in concert.
So that let's say, unfortunately, you
were driving into Denver, for instance,
and you found a large bump in the road,
maybe a pothole on one side.
And you hit that.
They were explaining how that would actually only shift
the suspension by about half of that distance,
because each side can independently kind of absorb
that and kind of cantilever back and forth.
It was really fascinating.
I would say, if that sounds interesting in any way,
go check this thing out.
I'm sure there are lots of videos
of people explaining the suspension.
It was really neat.
I'm just picturing one day I pick one of these things up,
and I build a mobile studio.
Come on.
In a GMC from the 70s, how cool would that be?
You have to store it here, though.
Totally, dude.
Yeah, we'd probably have to build it here, let's be honest.
If you inspire us like that, I think we might all need one.
Because what?
We can't all record in yours.
The sound isolation is just not going to be good enough.
Yeah, that's true.
lino.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 in 60-day credit on a new account.
And you go there to support the show.
I mean, let's just be honest about it, right?
lino.com slash unplugged.
Linode is fast, reliable cloud hosting.
If you've got something you want for your next project,
something you want to deploy up in the public,
I'd be embarrassed not to put it on Linode.
And I legitimately mean that.
It's not just that it's super fast and has great performance,
but if anything goes wrong, they also have fantastic support.
I pinged their support recently.
So I have a recent story to share with you,
because I decided to go full baller on our matrix
server before we left.
I didn't want to be over here and have the matrix server
fall down.
So I pinged Linode, and I'm like, hey, guys, how's it going?
So I know how I have this $15 a month Linode here.
Here's what I want to do.
And I kind of just ran them through what
I'm thinking about.
And they sent me back kind of a response
and gave us a few ideas and gave us the green light.
So I turned this thing up to 11.
Our matrix box, we went from 16 gigs of RAM.
We now have 96 gigs of RAM.
We now have 96 gigs of RAM in that thing.
We went from six CPU cores to 48 CPU cores.
We now have 48 CPU cores.
Going to need a lot of workers.
My god.
Yeah.
We are cooking with gas on our matrix server now.
It is so slick.
It's not the final solution.
But you know what?
When you can throw hardware at it, why not?
And isn't this the nice flexibility
I have as a business?
Because the last thing I want is this thing
crashing while I'm on a trip.
But you don't have to commit to some giant new server thing
that we would have had to take a couple of weeks
to get provisioned and set up before we left, right?
You can just do it now.
And if we figure out a solution that
means we need to scale back down later, that's easy to do too.
Click of a button.
That's the thing.
Is it resized an existing system we already had in production.
And it resized it in minutes.
And now the box has like infinite power.
So I love that kind of stuff.
And it's just the sort of thing I could never
do with a physical box or even some janky VM setup
that I'm running on my machine.
So if you're a performance hound,
if you're a reliability hound, if you
want to be like in like slim with good support,
Linode is the way to go.
They got 11 data centers around the world.
You're going to find something near you or your customers.
They've been doing this for nearly 19 years.
And they just keep making it better and better and better.
I love it.
I think you're going to love it.
I would suggest you try something.
Go kick the tires and see it for yourself.
That $100 means you can really try something.
And make your own decision.
And trying it out supports the show.
So go to linode.com slash unplugged.
Get that $100 on a new account and support the show.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
We have a little bit of feedback this week.
Rafael wrote in about NexOS.
We've been getting a lot of those.
And I thought it would be a great question
to put to all of you since we're in the same room.
They write, my dream is to be able to access
a mostly persistent single version of my development
environment on any machine in my local network.
I do hobby app development on Flutter,
which has a relatively complex install procedure in Linux.
Rarely do I get enough time between dad duties
to update, run git pull, and do a system update
if I haven't used a particular laptop in a while.
What I'd like to do is somehow host
a persistent configuration of my workflow and OS
that's always up to date and ready to work on my development
project with minimal interruptions,
such as the changes from one system to the other.
He says he has a small home server that
might be useful in the mix.
And he wondered, is this possible with Nix,
or are there any other solutions?
You know, Nix does have a fair amount of facilities
for setting up a development environment.
And if you're using something like Vim and Emacs,
I know they've got a lot of support
for including configuration for those types of editors
in there as well.
I think if Nix is the right fit might depend on, well, one,
if you like using Nix, but then two,
kind of what tools you're using for development
and how well that fits in the next ecosystem.
Because some ecosystems, I think Go is pretty well supported,
MPM, there's some new exciting stuff for Clojure
I just happened to notice.
Those work well, but there's other ecosystems.
I think Ruby sometimes could be painful from what
I've heard that just maybe fewer of those packages
have made it into the Nix package store.
So those are the things I would check out.
But there might be a lot of ways to skin this cat.
Containers can be a nice way to set up development
environments.
Or if it's just on your local network,
I know you guys really love the remote VS code set up over SSH.
So maybe you don't need to copy the environment everywhere,
and you can have one master install that's
able to reach out to the other systems.
That's a good idea.
I hadn't thought about that.
Yeah, if that's truly what you're looking for,
you probably could get a minimum viable version with that.
I was thinking you could solve this with WebTop
with the container solution, where essentially it's
a Docker container that creates a desktop Linux environment
that you connect to over your web.
It's like a self-hosted version of shells.com.
Oh, very nice.
So you could do something like WebTop.
But you don't want to hear this.
What I hear, I mean, maybe it's because I'm old,
but I hear VM.
I hear VM with free RDP server running on it
that you just RDP into.
And now that GNOME 42 has exposed options
to set up an RDP server, you could set up a Fedora
workstation in a VM with free RDP server running,
and then you could just RDP from any machine on your network.
And honestly, I'd recommend using
one of the higher end RDP clients,
because if you use the actual Microsoft RDP client,
you get a pretty performance session.
It's not bad with the new GNOME server.
That's an option.
I mean, I hear VM.
I do get what he's trying to get at, right?
Raphael wants to just sit down and get to work, right?
It's like when I go to play a Steam game
and I end up spending 15, 20 minutes just
getting my machine capable of playing that game.
Less of a problem these days, but still happens sometimes.
I get it.
Raphael wants to just sit down and get to work.
And I'm trying to think of what would be simpler and quicker
than RDP.
I mean, Alex, do you have any ideas of like,
maybe is this another option?
Maybe just a dedicated laptop?
I'm a big fan of the Westpane VS Code remote suggestion.
I do that for a lot of my development, actually.
And I think perhaps the one thing that
makes this more difficult is the Flutter element, where you
actually need some UI elements on screen.
That potentially makes this more difficult,
because a lot of my development is for infrastructure as code
type stuff, more DevOps-y type things.
So UI development, really, you need the environment locally.
But if you can capture all of these requirements
as to what makes your development environment yours
and get that into an Ansible playbook,
you should play the bell whenever
I mention the word Ansible, I think.
Maybe a Badger sound effect?
We need an Ansible sound effect, guys.
A quick stinger.
We do, yeah.
Now, for me, if you can capture all that into a nice playbook,
that then becomes your repeatable deployment thing
that you sync between machines.
And in fact, you don't even really
need to sync the Ansible itself.
You just commit that to a local Git repo,
sync that between the machines, and then
run Ansible against all of these machines
whenever you sit down.
Have it as a cron job, if you like,
to get more into that kind of GitOps kind
of style of operation.
That's a great idea.
Greg Hellings also wrote in onto our GitHub.
I kind of grabbed this because I thought it was fascinating.
This is the GitHub for the NixOS challenge that we set up.
If you want to check that out, github.com
slash jupyterbroadcasting.
And he writes, about four months ago for a day job,
I began experimenting with the Nix package manager
in order to enable developer tooling to run in Linux,
as well as Mac OS.
Currently, we officially only support Mac OS.
Having come here from Red Hat, this task
was naturally assigned to me.
Nix packages will allow us to eventually unify
the same packaging system across Mac and Linux.
He says, bonus, it also allows us to run under the WSL2
on Windows.
The same package manager in all three systems.
I thought that was pretty brilliant.
That is something I've been hearing a couple of times
from people.
Yeah, it's pretty nice.
I've been trying out using Nix lately on my work Mac.
And yeah, so far, it's going pretty well.
I've been impressed with the number of packages
that are supported.
It sounds like from talking with some of the folks
on our Nix matrix channel that the Darwin support,
as they call it, has gotten a lot better just
in the past couple of years.
So if you tried it before, it might be worth checking out.
And it's really easy and light on the system.
So if you just want an alternative,
if you're already using something like Brew,
I know before the show, we were kind of messing around
and wanted to brew package update one of our machines.
Of course, that takes a while.
And when you're trying to do a live stream, it's not great.
But Nix is pretty fast, and it's a nice alternative.
Yeah, I actually feel like the time
is right for the Nix packager to strike on macOS.
I know it's been around for a while.
But Brew has a lot of people that are not happy with it.
And what is the new project that one of the Brew founders?
I mean, it seems like there's some perhaps weakening
in Brew's dominance in macOS package management.
I feel quite the opposite.
I actually install everything on my Mac using Brew.
So I install Chrome, Spotify, Mumble.
There's a package for literally everything in Brew these days.
And that's where it really wins.
And I have a question for you, Wes.
I haven't done anything with the Nix package manager yet.
But I've heard this promise before with Terraform
as the example, where you write one script
or you define one configuration.
And then that becomes your golden configuration
for all your things, except for the fact that's never true,
because package names are actually slightly different
on different OSes and stuff like that.
Is that a solved problem with the Nix package manager?
That's a good question.
I don't know if I'd say that it's quite solved.
And admittedly, I'm kind of just starting off
on this road myself.
But I have been impressed with the flexibility of overrides.
I haven't quite got it dialed in.
But one thing I was trying out was building cross-compiled
Docker images from Mac without having
to use any of the Docker tools that would spit out
like a Linux container with all the right Linux binaries
and stuff.
And for the most part, that was just
one little change at the top of the file that was like, hey,
here I want to pull in packages that run on the Mac side.
So these are the native packages to run.
And then for the stuff that's going inside the container,
I want you to pull from the x86 part of the Nix package cache.
Really?
So I think that there's some promise.
Now, of course, as you're right, abstractions are leaky.
I'm sure there are some edge cases
that are going to bite you.
But at least for the simple stuff,
like in getting an htop and things like that going,
yeah, just kind of install it by name and go have fun.
I feel like at the meetup, it was a pretty good mix
of people who thought we were crazy for this Nix stuff
and people who were like right on board with us doing
the challenge.
I feel like that's about the split in this room, too.
Yeah.
And now, as the French say, it is time for le boost.
We got a bunch of boosts in.
And for 5,000 sats, bhh32 wrote, thanks for the fountain app
recommendation.
I've been listening to you guys for a few years now.
I've never had an opportunity to attend a live show.
And this is a great way for me to support you and participate.
Here are 5,000 sats for you, easily funded
from my Exodus wallet, since it has its own lightning wallet
that I can deposit from my mining efforts.
And I mine exclusively on Linux, open source funding
for open source shows.
That's rad.
Pretty crazy to think he's using open source software
to mine something that generates value that he can then
send in with a message to a podcast that
talks about open source software,
using all open source self-hosted software
on the back end for every single piece of it, right?
You can't say that about a Visa transaction.
Not a Windows box in sight.
No, no.
Michael B wrote in yesterday with 3,000 sats, hey, guys.
I'm so glad that you're banging on things like Matrix
to help us all getting all of this sorted out.
Keep up the great work.
Michael, you know, the Matrix community continues to grow.
And was it, I don't know if we really
touched on this last week.
Like, it was implicit in the conversation,
but there was like a hot minute like three months ago
where I'm like, screw this.
I don't want to host this.
Discord is way easier.
Why am I bothering with this?
And I was like, let's kill the Matrix server.
Yeah, we really, I mean, we thought about it.
But then all these damn bastards started joining the server,
and they're all so great.
I want to talk to them all.
And now I'm all in.
Like, we've got to keep this thing.
And also, I think the other thing that's
been sort of building over 2022 for me
is I have really started taking a look at centralization
in the Linux community and the negative effects.
I think that centralization has brought
Linux and Linux innovation.
And then I started using that perspective
to look at how we do messaging and look at how we communicate
as a community.
And I realized that there's value long term
in helping build the Matrix ecosystem because
of its decentralized nature.
And that's sort of where I decided
I'm going to double down on it.
So that's why we now have a 48-core box
with 96 gigs of RAM running our Matrix server.
Fingers crossed.
We decided to go crazy.
Well, Marcus boosted in with 10,000 sets.
I hope these boosts and streaming sets
help allow JB to grow.
And hey, by the way, Chris, I was the person that sent you
a 3DS a few years ago.
That was so awesome when Marcus did that.
Thank you, Marcus.
Because my son and I really got into some of the 3DS games
for a little bit.
And so we both had one and made for a nice moment.
User 183 also sent in two days ago 12,000 sets.
That seems impressive to me.
Great live stream last week.
Thanks for the 2,000 sets.
We were sending sets to people, which I think
they really enjoyed, clearly.
Yeah.
I guess they sent it back and then some.
Now have BTC on Blue Wallet and SATs on Fountain.
So here are yours returned and a few more.
If you've not mentioned it before,
worth highlighting Flat Seal, which, among other settings,
allows confined Flatpak apps access to NFS shares
and mounted partitions.
Martin?
Yeah, Flat Seal is a solid Flatpak companion.
Just one of those things, quality of life,
is you try to do more complicated workflows
in your Flatpak apps.
All right, so Wes, I think you probably found this one.
Based on the functionality for our pick this week,
it's called BORE.
Yeah, a modern, simple TCP tunnel that's written in Rust.
Yes!
Yeah, you might wonder, OK, why would I need this?
Aren't there already things like ngrok?
And yeah, they acknowledge that right in the readme.
It's similar to a local tunnel in ngrok,
and there's a lot of tools for this.
But BORE is intended to be a highly efficient, unopinionated
tool for forwarding TCP traffic that's
simple to install, simple to self-host,
with no frills attached.
And yeah, it's true.
I was able to take a look.
It's less than 400 lines of safe, asynchronous Rust.
So you can read through the code if you like.
And because it's Rust, it's easy to get started.
You just run BORE server on maybe a Linode system
out there.
And then you can use your own to forward reports.
So if you're behind some firewall,
you've got NAT in the mix.
It's just really easy and simple.
So let's say you're a guy who's maybe on a flight,
and they're locking down what you can get to on this flight.
Is there a way I could use this to get access
to more things without pain?
I mean, I'm not saying I'm doing that, but I'm asking for Brent.
You know, that's a use case I hadn't considered.
Could a guy do that with this?
Or like, I'm trying to picture what
I would use this in the day-to-day.
Well, I think it's just a nice way,
if you don't have a fancier setup,
or you don't want to invest in other persistent tooling,
you just need sort of an ephemeral port forward.
That sounds like me.
Yeah, right?
You haven't got your firewall configured.
You don't even know how the firewall works.
Who can bother?
Mm-hmm.
Who can?
And so that's where this is really nice, because one, you
can self-host it, or they run what
seems like a pretty beefy server on their own.
And so you just run this on your local machine,
tell it what ports you want to forward,
and then instead of having to set up a reverse proxy
or open that port on your firewall, it's done for you.
Isn't it interesting how we talk about these picks sometimes,
and you dig into it, and you discover
the open source project is also running a server component
to help make it work better?
Like, you don't have to use it, but Magic Wormhole, Jitsi,
Bore, the list goes on and on.
Like, it's very common these days
to have that little kind of server-side component.
And so that's an aspect you've got to take into consideration.
Absolutely.
Maybe, if you find it useful, you
want to support those kinds of projects.
That's right.
I think that's probably true, and we
don't want them monetizing that aspect of it,
because that's not good for any of us.
All right, you know, it's a shorter show today,
because we didn't have a Mumble Room.
Yeah, I mean, we're going to try to do something
in the post-show, so if you're a member at unpluggedcore.com
or at jupiter.party, yeah, then you get to hear the post-show,
and you're going to see if we get it to work or not.
And not to mention the rather not safe for work conversation
we had today.
This is why you show up live, folks, all the extra show.
You're going to hear Chris rant and rave about technical
setups.
That's always fun, you know?
You get the full perspective and the spectrum of emotions.
I'm a little worried about that guy.
You know, you can get that whole thing.
That's always fun.
Who doesn't want that, right?
So check that out.
You can join us on Sundays.
We do the show at noon Pacific, 3 PM Eastern,
over at jblive.tv.
We'd love to have you join our virtual lug,
because it's almost like it's like 99% of the time,
99.5% of the time, it makes its way into the show.
It's just when something gets broken,
then it doesn't make it in here.
But you can always watch live.
See you next week.
Same bat time, same bat station.
All right, that's it.
That's our live show, all hanging out.
Is this considered a living room?
What is this considered, a bonus room?
Officially, I think it's a bonus room.
Yeah, the room above the garage.
Yeah, hanging out in the bonus room.
In this case, bonus means a totally capable for recording
a podcast.
I think it's now a podcast room.
I don't think I've ever seen anybody
look quite so comfortable as Wes Payne, who's
recording from my La-Z-Boy today.
Yeah, this is amazing.
We had to really put it in the studio to share this.
That is a nice spot.
All right, thank you so much for tuning in.
Keep the Linux rolling at linuxunplugged.com
and linuxunplugged.com slash contact.
And send in your boost, get your message on the show,
and get it in front of us.
We read them all.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode
of the Unplugged program.
See you back here next Sunday.
And remember, the Unplugged program,
the new show, is brought to you by Linux.
So don't forget to check us out.
And hopefully, you're all enjoying it,
and we'll see you next week.
Bye.
Alright, JBtitles.com, let's go pick our title.
I like, like, the chatroom's asking, like, what's the deal with the Rust love?
Seriously, why does everybody love Rust so much?
Yeah, maybe I got a little defensive there, whoops.
Does it feel like, I mean, I mean, besides the fact that we are getting some awesome
applications and it's making people rethink stuff, I think in part it's just sort of,
sort of a show trope.
WestPain loves Rust, that's why we love Rust.
Yeah, maybe a little bit, plus, like, we kind of get to pick up on some of the legitimate
enthusiasm out there for, you know, devs who are just finding and falling in love with
Rust.
When's the last time you've seen something like this, where, like, a language like this
wins the hearts and minds of developers like this?
Michael Dominic would tell you Objective C, but I don't know if I believe him.