What do you guys think Nokia jumps in with an Android tablet are you surprised also I hear the optics on the camera quite nice
No key is that if they didn't put their Nokia's ed launcher thingy on there
I'd find it more appealing hmm 200. He's all about the hardware. I mean it's Android so yeah, it's Android Android
Yeah, yeah, well, and you could always stall it you can always put a different launcher on there
Mm-hmm Wow that does look like a look at the hardware. It does look like a great tablet doesn't it yeah
I'm looking at the n1 250. Yeah 250 is what it says on a gadget. Oh really yeah
That could be pretty compelling I was trying to find that information about the camera though because I heard people talking about it
But I don't see the details on that on their page there
Two hundred fifty dollars seven point nine inch and one tablet it'll be on sale in China first for the Chinese New Year which is February 19th
So it's gonna be a little bit
So we won't see it here in the u.s.
probably
Isn't this interesting
Boy, they break up with Microsoft just for a little bit. It's gonna have a 2048 by 1536 resolution
I predicted this when they when they sold off the mobile business to
It's a Microsoft because there was a clause in the contract that said that they could start reusing the Nokia brand
In 2015 like yep, they'll definitely have something ready for them. Did you catch that? It's also using that new type-c USB connector
Which is that new you?
Reversible connector that's not out in the market yet the very first USB can't do that doesn't suck
Yeah
2.4 gigahertz quad-core Intel Atom Z 3580 processor 2 gigabytes of RAM and a 32 gigabytes storage
8 megapixel rear shooter and a 5 megapixel on the front not bad. Hey, we got a little video
Should we watch the video this this looks pretty awesome. Oh
Yeah, it's already cool. Go Nokia go oh
Yeah, look at them holes there I guess that stereo speakers possibly
Yeah, if you hold it wow it looks a lot like an iPad doesn't it it does yeah, I
Didn't really see it until I saw it in the video, and oh, I like it though. I like that a lot
That is I think an extremely compelling tablet. Oh
Man, yeah, it does have that z1 launcher Android 5.0. Hey, oh it's coming with L. There's another check in the box
damn
Well, I think they nailed it didn't they?
Good for Nokia boy. That's great. I I love Nokia hardware really love Nokia hardware, so that's yeah
I like the it clearly shows that they really aren't in bed all that much in with Microsoft
Because different part of the company's a different company. No I understand that but that whole philosophy is sticking with Windows related stuff
I'm ready for my me go based on Nokia tablet. Hey, did you guys see that yeah, okay? People are warning that
Doing something new tomorrow what they're announcing something tomorrow as well. Oh, okay, hold on all right screw the BitTorrent thing
Tell me about this go to yolo.com yolo.com
Yes, I'm really hoping for a yolo too, but I mean I heard about this. That's right
I saw you know what I saw this. I think before last started, but I forgot to put it in the show that's right
This is a
So you think it's a tablet poppy I'm coming hmm if you go to review yola
Blogspot.com they actually have a good write-up on it where they show
the corner that yola shows compared to a like a tablet a generic tablet and
the
Ui is almost similar wow so there's people who are like oh
I see a corner of the device. I have the picture up on the video stream if you're watching
Yeah, interesting you guys we could have some cool hardware coming soon some cool hardware
I'm really happy with my yola one except for the camera and screen, but
Wow
I'm right. You know what I'm really hoping that we get something interesting out of them boy. Oh, man
I don't know what I'm hoping for
I'm right. You know what I'm really hoping that we get something interesting out of them boy. Oh, maybe they'd have in time shipping for Christmas
I could put it on Santa's list
So I was gonna say there was there was a story about these hackers claiming. I don't quote-unquote hackers
Claiming that bit torrent sync should not be trusted for sensitive data. I haven't read through the story has anybody read through this yet
Well, it shouldn't be trusted anyway, and we've been telling you that right ages right because it's proprietary. It's negative in the freedom
Exactly that's something that negative in the freedom right dimension. That's something that our friend
Over our friends over at pulse definitely have going for them is that it's open source now
We've also discussed many times the benefits of bit torrent sync so I think a lot of people understand
There's pros and cons to both
but I think it's pretty obvious at this point if it's not open source don't trust it with your data, and you know it's
funny is I don't necessarily because
Spider oak isn't fully open source. I think the client is I think I think a lot of the protocols document
I don't remember that where the line is with spider oak, but I have more trust there
So if you can't use pulse, and you don't want to use bit torrent sync you got to use something check out spider oak
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's celebrating its cheat day. My name is Chris. And my name is Matt.
Hey Matt, so it's been a few weeks almost a month that I just have been kind of going like really light on the breads and stuff
Not like a hundred percent cut it out, but really light. You know just really going back to that getting back to that
And it's always been great Matt. It's been great, but today before the show
We're working on something huge for tomorrow, and I don't you know it's like in this it's like in this last stage where it's the most work
And you don't know if you're gonna make it in time, but we have something really big for the Jupiter broadcasting network tomorrow that we're working on today
But I'm like starving and like okay. I gotta order a Jimmy John's sandwich
I got I can't leave
You've been listening to the radio
I know I gotta get the gift. I gotta get the gift
I gotta get the gift
I gotta get this work done, and then I gotta go do the unplugged show. I gotta go do the unplugged show
So I figure I'll order Jimmy John's, but I'm gonna be a good boy lettuce wrap that sandwich
I'm gonna get a lettuce wrap right yeah, yeah
Sure, so I order Rekai sandwich cuz you know he's working on this project with me
And I order myself a nice big lettuce wrap double up on that meat Matt
I get double up on that meat, and it shows up at the front door
I grab the bag I go upstairs. We get all situated in our offices
We sit down and we start working again, and you know what?
They put it on bread and at that point Matt. I was so hungry. I and I've been wanting a sandwich so bad man
I've been wanting a sandwich so bad. I ate the whole sandwich Matt, and I got a little bit
I think if I went to the doctor right now
They would say Chris you are clinically diagnosed with food coma you are currently in a state of food coma and so
We're gonna get through today's episode. It's gonna be kind of a thick episode
There's a lot of things going on with the Debian project
You've probably seen some of it, and I want to I want to walk away from today's episode after we talk about what's happened
And and I want to walk away with a clear action plan that Jupiter broadcasting can take to help
Change the tone of the discussion in the discourse and encourage merit-based discussion again
And a sort of back away from sort of the tribal war even though it's a natural tendency
What we're trying to do is we're trying to make sure that we're trying to make sure that we're making sure that we're
Sort of back away from sort of the tribal war even though it's a natural tendency. What can we do?
What could Jupiter broadcasting foster to promote that like more like a you know at a base level and I think there's a few possibilities there
So we're gonna recap what's been going on with Debian then transition into that
We've also got a few other interesting follow-up things we had a big system D survey done producer q5 sis put that together
We had almost 5,000 respondents
And we're gonna go over some of those responses in regards to system D in today's episode
And then when we have a chance we're gonna get to
Something that might sound like it's pondering a negative in reality
I think we're gonna find a few strengths of desktop Linux that we can promote to future switchers
So we're gonna have a lot to accomplish plus the feedback in today's episode
Let me so let me bring on our panel of experts our mumble room a time-appropriate greetings mumble room
Hello hello hello
I'm excited because I think we're gonna accomplish something big today
We're gonna. We're gonna. I feel like if we can pull off what even a little bit of what I want to discuss
I'm gonna be really proud of the unplugged show
But before we get to that we got a follow-up on probably what everybody else actually cares about
That was the whole chromium Firefox thing we got a couple of emails Colton wrote sent one in about the chromium challenge
He decided after last week's show. He's a Firefox user. He says you know what?
I'm gonna take that chromium challenge. I'm gonna take that chromium challenge so after watching your Firefox challenge
I decided to take it. I'm now on chromium, and I'm really amazed at what a difference there is between the two bugs
I once attributed to Linux. I now attribute to Firefox for instance
I had some weird full-screen flash video issues in Firefox that are completely gone now that I'm using chromium
No special config required it also makes much more sense to use chromium since I have a chromecast however
I didn't realize that I don't know
It clicks with me now anyways. Thanks for the great show Colton now. We've got some emails that said oh, yeah
I had a few problems, but Lionhead here in the Mamba room actually took the chromium challenge and
His story isn't quite as positive as Colton's Lionhead. How was your chromium challenge week?
Well for me it was
Thrilled with several minor annoyances that when repeated a thousand times will make you go mad
Like what what happened man? What happened because I felt that way about Firefox, so that's interesting
Well one of the things I do is that I dark theme everything and that is a serious thing for me
And when I browse reddit, which I do quite frequently
It loads the white page right before it goes dark and when you do that a lot of times
It flashes
Yeah
So one of your one of your favorite little modifications
Didn't work under chromium probably in a difference in the way they render the web page
Probably another thing I also like to have is the way that Firefox handles pin tabs
Which was just adding an extension, but again the whole thing
But why should I use something that needs an extension when it's built into your other browser?
The problem I had was for some reason
In the last three days. I had the random tab crashes all the time
Oh, do you think it was a plug-in or just something else?
I have no idea, but even empty tabs just said oh snap crashed
Didn't you feel great that aw snap air though?
Yes, but still
No, that's fair. That's fair. So you're switching back obviously you have you already switched back to Firefox?
I'm back on Firefox now
You made it the week though
Yep
Wow I'm impressed
Well, yeah that goes to show you different strokes for different browsers
I don't think I have that quite right man. We need to refine that what do you
You and I think we come up with a slogan there though
Something something
I don't know we'll have to work it out
Alright so
Different trousers for different browsers
Okay that's good
Oh I like that
That really hits home
I would love to do something if there was something that could work in a gecko
You know for the for the gecko render like different different. I got nothing though. I'm not that quick
I need I need you know some time and then then I got it
Hey so
Are we talking gecko the lizard or Gordon gecko?
I was thinking gecko no I was thinking gecko the rendering engine
Oh okay cool
So a producer q5 sis ran this what he calls a quote-unquote simple systemd survey
And he's now he's now published the results and so he had four thousand seven hundred and fifty five individuals who responded
The survey responses show that forty seven of the respondents are in favor of systemd
But I want to dig into this because I have some questions about this survey
And what it shows about desktop usage versus server usage and all these kinds of things I think are a little fascinating
So before we do that why don't I thank our first sponsor and that's DigitalOcean
Head over to DigitalOcean right now and start checking them out while I talk about it
DigitalOcean.com it's worth a visit I think you're gonna be pretty impressed
So what is DigitalOcean?
It's a simple cloud hosting provider
And they're dedicated to offering the most intuitive and easy way to spin up your own cloud server
And if you go over there right now DigitalOcean.com check them out you can create an account in just seconds
It's pretty impressive
And we also have a promo code that you can use unplug November to get a ten dollar credit
You apply that to the balance of your account no credit card required
You can get started with a droplet for two months for free
Because DigitalOcean droplet started only five dollars a month
And you can get a droplet spun up in seconds
Pricing plans at five dollars means you could easily afford your own own cloud instance or a WordPress install or a GitLab
Or several different things or BitTorrent Sync, Pulse, maybe you want an offsite Pulse server
A DigitalOcean droplet could be a great way to do it
And you'll get a 512 megabyte RAM rig
You'll get a 20 gigabyte SSD all SSD
You'll get one blazing fast CPU on that droplet
And a terabyte of dedicated transfer just to you
And they have DigitalOcean has data center locations in New York, San Francisco, Singapore, Amsterdam and London
I had an email from someone on Coder Radio on Monday
Who said that he was taking part of a competition
And it was a programming competition where your response had to come in in under a minute
And that meant you coded the response
You actually wrote up the code for the response
And then had to deploy it and that would be your answer
And he kept kind of just under, just like barely missing the minute mark
Just like a minute five seconds, a minute three seconds
You know all these, like what am I doing, a minute one second
And then he realized the server was located in France
So he deployed a DigitalOcean droplet over in Amsterdam
Cut down that latency time and now he's in the top leaderboards
Nice
And DigitalOcean, you've seen the power right here on Linux Unplugged
Last week when Wimpy deployed the brand new version of Ubuntu Mate edition live on the show
He used DigitalOcean's resources to do that
And their interface to do all of it is crazy simple and intuitive
And they have an API where you can get started on your own and write some code
And interact with this stuff automatically
Or integrate it in with your management infrastructure
Or take advantage of some of the things the community has already written
It's really slick
And they're paying for tutorials
Because they're trying to get that up to a really high level
So if you've got some experience with something
Go work with DigitalOcean, we have a link in our show notes
And write up a tutorial, they might pay up to $200 for that
And that might be worth your time
They've also got a position open right now for an editor
So that could be an opportunity as well
DigitalOcean.com, Unplugged November
Go create a droplet, try it out
Maybe play with CoreOS for a little bit and see what all the buzz is about
Experience Docker, try out GitLab
You might be able to tie in your own local machine configs
To a GitLab deployment in a DigitalOcean droplet that you have full root control over
That'd be pretty cool, I'd love to hear about it if you do something like that
DigitalOcean.com, Unplugged November
Big thank you to DigitalOcean for sponsoring the Linux Unplugged show
Okay, so Q5 broke out the stats in a pretty digestible way
But he also published the raw data if you want to play with this yourself
And I know some of you do, I've seen some of the comments
So first he asked, do you consider yourself in favor or against SystemD?
47%, 2,247 people responded in favor
22% responded against, 30% undecided
In the age range, 52% are 20-30 or 20-29
And 28% are 30-39, 7% 40-49
Which is interesting, that particular number there doesn't really reflect other demographics I've seen
But who really knows
How many years have you used Linux?
40% responded 6-10 years, 23 responded 11-15 years
And 16-20 years said 10%
And 27% said 0-5
What was your first Linux distro?
OpenSUSE came in at 6%, Debian 41%, Fedora 18%, Arch Linux 3%
Current distro, Arch Linux 37%, Fedora Red Hat 11%, Debian 28%
Which I assume also includes Ubuntu
And where do you live? 46% North America, 42% Europe and the others fall in
Primary use, web server 44%, desktop 90% of the people that took the survey are using it as a desktop, Linux
What's more important, stability or bleeding edge?
32% said stability, 20% said bleeding edge, 47% said flexibility
So flexibility was 47% of the response
And who would win in a face-off, Linus Torvalds, Richard Stallman, Leonard Potter, or Captain Jean-Luc Picard?
Captain Jean-Luc Picard won with 39% of the vote
So there you go, and the raw data is in the notes
One thing I wanted to ask you guys about
What do you think about this number here, System D in favor, 47%
Rotten Corps, is that in line with what you'd expect from the survey?
Actually yes, pretty much
I thought it might be, and why is that?
I like System D, and I don't see, most of the technical issues that people have problems with System D are fixable
And have already been fixed, most of them
Roger that, yeah, I could see that too
And it seems like maybe the people that are in favor of desktops might be more in favor of System D too
And there's a lot of desktop users in the survey, that's kind of what jumped out at me
The desktop thing is the most interesting, and I think it's also
Because of the different districts that have jumped to System D as the default
Is probably a big aspect to that
It's worth noting too, that once Ubuntu makes their full switch to System D
That number's going to be significantly higher as well
Yeah, and that could happen in 1504
That could be the next big release
And I know that this is just one survey, and you can't make all of your consumptions off of this
So we're going to get into this Debian stuff, right Matt?
And I'm looking at this and I'm thinking, geez, when you get these surveys it seems like the majority are actually okay with what's going on with System D
So as we get into this, are we talking about people that are say, harassing maintainers and stuff?
Are these people on the fringe?
I don't think it's necessarily that they're on the fringe
I think it's that they're so passionate about their belief that
And a lot of times when you're not in the largest of numbers
You tend to be a little louder to make your voice heard
And sometimes that's done with eloquence, and sometimes that's done like a raging chimp
It really depends on the person
And I've seen both from all sides
I've seen raging chumps on all sides, and I've seen some really eloquent blog posts from all groups as well
So it's kind of hit and miss
That's a good point
And I encourage you, if you have any questions or anything like that
I have a link in the show notes to Q5Sys' blog post
You can download the, he put it in an ODT file or something
One of them open formats, I believe it was not text, however
It was not text
It was one of them other formats
And you can download that and you can plug it into your spreadsheet of choice
So Andreas writes in, and he has a question for our panel
And I'd like to hear what you guys think about this
He says, hello Chris and Matt, I have a thought that
I have a question that I think all of you could maybe discuss
And have maybe a good round table
He says, what could we do as a community to improve Linux?
What is it, like if you could have a magic wand today
And just improve it to make it more approachable to the mainstream
Would it be something like an app store?
More integration between distributions?
Industry support, etc, etc
What could be done to Linux just to kind of spruce it up a little bit
And make it more palatable?
And Matt, I wanted to go to you first because I think this is along the line you write about a lot
And the space you think about is make it more approachable to users
If you could give somebody a Linux box and remove just a couple of immediate pain points
What would those points be?
Ooh, I think the first thing I would do is make sure that if it's not necessary
Or it's likely to just create new problems
I would do my best to hide it
With the asterisk that I would like to show them how to use it properly later on
But I think giving them immediate access to like say
A more advanced package manager versus a simple one
Do you think like an amazing app store is necessary or is that just a nice to have?
Well, you know, I think it is only from the sense of discovery
I think once, if you know the application you're going to get
And you're willing to do whatever you want to do to get it
I don't think it's critical
But I do think for just Joe average
It definitely is a bigger selling point
It's a little bit like the spinning cube stuff we were talking about
You know, a little bit of wow goes a long way
Yeah, good point
And it grabs their attention
In fact, our next note's coming up
And then you can kind of settle them down and get them grounded as you go
But you know
Josh, in the mumble room there, how much is a really key hardware OEM a part of this?
Like somebody that would have like a storefront filled with Linux machines
Is this an important piece? Is that a pain point you would resolve?
Yeah, definitely
I mean, a key issue with Linux is
Well, I'll put this way
A key issue for end users is hardware compatibility
Because they want to be able to boot up their computer and know everything works
They don't have to go on Ask a Boon 2 and see
Oh, I have to download some weird drivers in order to get something to work
If we point users to OEMs like System76
Then they know immediately things are going to work out of the box
And that's pretty powerful
Inagogo, you think what we need is some good advertising
Yeah, because Windows has a ton more advertising than Linux
And what we need is advertising
So people can hear about it
But it also needs a bit of fixing in some circumstances
So, Daredevil, do you think it's a problem with software quality?
No
Okay
I'm thinking more of a problem
I'm sorry
I'm thinking more it's a problem of actually making developers happy on the platform
I mean, we have all the tools and all the languages
But distributions, like Ubuntu right now is doing a great effort on that department
But it's pretty much almost the only one doing it
We need standardized protocol to develop an app and ship it
Once we have that, we have developers
Developers that are approaching the platform being Linux for the first time say
Alright, what SDK do I download to start making applications for this?
And then the answer is
Yeah
And usually it all wraps around what tool we want to use
And we don't support one tool really well
And the problem is if developers are making the app that users want
OEMs look at that and they say
There's no reason to support the platform
I mean, there's no one writing apps for it
Rotten Corps, do you want to expand on that a little bit?
Yeah, I think the actual developer thing is more than just the SDK
It's also the repos
As the community of Linux, people just talk about
Use your official repo because that's the safest
And it is true, but it's also the most annoying part for developers
Because every single repo is going to have a different version of your project
And then you have to contact these people
You beg them to update, beg the next one to update
And it just continues and continues
And you have no control
Frank from OEMcloud when we were at the Ohio Linux Fest said
We have this very problem
The issue is, is that in Debian, stable today
A very, very old version of OEMcloud ships
That is no longer supported by the OEMcloud project
And it is a poor representation of what their project is about today
It doesn't represent their quality of code
It doesn't represent anything about them
But yet if you apt-get install OEMcloud, you get this
And to them it's a major problem and it is a disincentive for them
Now, their options are to, and I think very wisely
They have utilized the openSUSE build service
And they generate repositories
If you just did a, you know, a monocule of research on the OEMcloud website
You'd know that would be the more appropriate way to install it
But not everybody does that
Because you expect that functionality from your distribution
And you should be able to
So I think the rotten corpse, I think the point about repositories is a very good one
It's like, it's one of the best strengths
But it can also be a disincentive to some developers
The other thing is, is they lose some download stats
So it's hard for them to quantify how many Linux users they have
Like the, you know, we all hear this about the LibreOffice project
They're not exactly sure how many Linux users they have
Because most people get LibreOffice from their distro
They don't download it from the website
But most Windows users and Mac users do download it from the website
So they get most of those counts
So that, you know, when you look at that data right there
The Linux users are massively underrepresented
And it's, in a business sometimes, hard to really wrap their brains around that
Yeah, I think it's, the download stuff is very important
Because there's basically no way to find out
The repos don't provide the information
Like the different package managers don't do anything
You can't find out anything on any distro
You just have to hope that people use it
Right, and some applications, you know, they work around this by
And this is not necessarily a good thing
By pinging home
Maybe it's to check for an update
Or, you know, just whatever to the servers
Just send one ping off, one ping only
And then, hey, bang suggest chatroom by the way
Don't forget to bang suggest today
One ping only, and you go out there and you ping the server
And yeah, okay, now we know we have LibreOffice user 1151157892 on a Linux box
I don't know
But then you get people who hate you for doing that
And then it just creates a bigger issue that you don't want to deal with
So you don't do it
And there's really no practical way
It's just, you have to rely on the distros to give you information
And they don't do it
So those would be some areas I think we'd probably improve
And this is one of the things that are
It's the kind of the good end result of some standardization on SystemD
Is it does normalize some of that middle section of Linux across all the distributions
It is something that developers will be able to wrap their heads around
That is a cross distribution commonality
That is a positive thing for software coming to Linux
SystemD controversy aside
And so as we get closer to this discussion
That's one thing to kind of keep in mind
But before we go there, MJC6370
Rolls right off the tongue
Submitted to the subreddit 23 hours ago
He says he gave a presentation
And this is so cool
He says everyone in the group uses Macbooks
Except for me
I've got a Lenovo Ultrabook and I run Linux
What was a little nerve-wracking about it though
Is I had to go hook up the HDMI to the projector
He was a little worried because those Mac users are walking up
They're plugging in their Macbooks with them HDMI ports
And they're getting up on the projector
He's like okay here I go
I've got to show up these Mac users
He goes up there with the Lenovo
He plugs it in
Works, no problem
After the presentation
Four of the thirteen people came up to say
Hey, what are you running on your PC?
It looks amazing
One even asked what version of Windows it was
Anyways, it makes me smile
And he says the Numix icons seem to be catching people's eye
I thought that was neat in light of our interview with the Numix guys
That it seems to be
And we always talk about oh yeah like Compiz grabs eyes and things like that
But them Numix icons are grabbing some eyes too
They're not for everybody
But I thought that was a great story
It's pretty cool
And as a fanboy
I would point out that in his article he mentioned that
A big point of getting people's eye is GNOME
Yeah, I think it's pretty smexy
I think it is really smexy
Cinnamon is good looking too
But GNOME has that
It has that modern look to it
It looks like something a little bit different
But you immediately know what it is
Of course my GNOME is different than most people's GNOME
I think his too
I think a lot of times people have docs on the side
And in my case I have a full screen doc that kind of makes it look like Unity
Or I mean a full sidebar doc
Hey, okay, alright
So we've got to get to this Debian stuff
We've been talking about it on and off
Before we do that
Let me give a mention here for Linux Academy
Linux Academy is a great service
And it's a great opportunity if you haven't checked it out
Start by going over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
And take a look at what they have to offer
What I love about Linux Academy
Is unlike some of the general online learning courses and sites that are out there
And there seems to be more and more all the time
People seem to figure out some sort of CMS
They throw up a bunch of content on there
Maybe they throw some things on YouTube
Or maybe they have something really high end
Where they just have so many videos that sit there and rot
You know there's a whole range of services
But none of them are built by Linux enthusiasts and advocates
They've teamed up with friends that are educators and developers
And they've created Linux Academy for you
For Linux users
By Linux users
And they cover the whole spectrum of stuff
And when you go over to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
You're going to get a discount on your tuition
A great discount, it's like 33% discount
It's an amazing resource
You get step-by-step video courses
When you log into their dashboard
You see all of the courses outlined
All the different options you have
And they're adding new stuff all the time
They just added a whole bunch of Puppet stuff
You can go check out Introduction to Puppet
If you've been thinking about getting into that
If you have more than a few servers
You should probably think about it
And they've got courseware on it now
And they're adding more stuff all the time
You log in, you say okay I'm going to do this Puppet course
And then it opens it up
It shows you all the different sections
How long each section is going to take
Where you can download audio and PDFs and videos
It's so nice
And if you get to a point where now it's time to do some
Puppet configuration and deployments
They'll automatically spin up a virtual server for you
On demand
They give you logins to it
Now you're working in a production environment
You're actually using the tools
Along with the courseware
Along with the video guides
And they have live stream events
Where you can ask the educators questions directly too
They also have communities
Kind of give you that boost when you're feeling a little down
Or bottoming out a little bit
And need some encouragement
Or need some direction
That's a great resource
And they've expanded so much on their AWS and OpenStack stuff too
It's pretty cool
And I think one of the courses I like to recommend from time to time
Is their R-Sync backup course
So if you want to get a nice solid backup system
With the holidays coming up
You've got all these photos you're taking
Why not back them up
R-Sync is a great tool to do that
Take it from your rig
It's maybe your desktop or your laptop
Send it off to your NAS
Or move it just between devices
Or send it over the internet
Move it up to a droplet
R-Sync is such an incredible tool
And they have a great course on it
It'll really make you an R-Sync expert
But that's just the beginning
They've got courseware on DevOps
Python, OpenStack, Android, Ruby, AWS
I mean the list goes on and on
And new stuff all the time
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
Go find out what courseware by Linux users
For Linux users is actually like
You know that makes all the difference
And that's why you want to go there
Linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
And a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring
The unplugged program
You guys rock
Okay so we don't need to dwell on the Debian stuff that much
It's kind of a bummer
Oh you know I should mention now before
I'm sorry I keep doing this
A couple of brief bits of business next week
Linux unplugged is going to be an hour earlier
At 1pm Pacific
So you can get that in your local time
At jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar
Please join us
It's the 25th
So that's not a great day
And I apologize about that
But we're going to do it one hour earlier
So hopefully we can get a decent turnout
Because after the show
And this is why we're doing it one hour earlier
We're going to team up with the mumble room
We're going to try to recruit as many people
In the mumble room as possible
And we're going to hunt for the best moments
Of Jupiter Broadcasting throughout 2014
Because our idea is
Our hope is to give all of the hosts
Everyone the week of Christmas off
And the only way to do that
Is if we can generate some best of content now
And the only way to go through that
Is if we all work together as a team
We'll sit down
We'll divide up the work
We'll communicate
We'll get a real time doc and form
That you'll be able to fill out
So we'll all be collaborating off the same set of notes
We'll work together as a team
Rekai will be joining us to go through
So he can be here for editing notes
And we're going to try to go through
And discover some of the greatest moments
So if you've got some in your head
We'll have the form available
Probably later in the week
I'll try to make it available during
The Linux Action Show
Or something like that
So keep an eye out for that
I'll probably tweet it out when we have it done
But it'd be great if you could join us next Tuesday
At 1pm Pacific
And help us hunt for all of that stuff
Also, I should probably mention at this point too
There is a Jupiter Broadcasting Polo
A lot of you have asked for it
And this is the one to get
This is something that we worked tirelessly with Teespring
To make sure it's going to be perfect
It's an embroidered Jupiter Broadcasting Polo
And you can find it at teespring.com slash jbpolo
There's a couple of different colors
And they've also added now the Ladies Tea
Which is nice
It's really nice
So you can check that out
Teespring.com slash jbpolo
Oh, I like that grey a lot
That is slick
Snazzy
Yes, very snazzy
Oh my gosh, it's going to look so good
With the white embroidered logo
Teespring.com slash jbpolo
Get your polo on
Or give away some as a gift
We've got more at jupiter.gift
More shirts and stuff too
But yeah, so a little bit of business
J.B. Polo's out
And also our early next week
And we're going to need your help
We will be recruiting as many of you as possible
Okay, so now on to the Debian stuff
This week we've seen some more resignations
From some pretty important folks
In the Debian project
And this isn't the first round we've seen either
And they all seem to be generally
And anybody, if you disagree with me, speak up
No hard feelings
But they all seem to be related to the tone
Of the System D discussion
But not because of System D
Would everybody kind of agree with that?
Yeah
Yeah, I think it's mostly the bureaucracy around Debian
Yeah, so we've had resignations
From the Debian technical committee
We've had resignations from one of the
System D package maintainers
From the package maintaining team for System D
We've had a resignation there
Bruce Perins, a former Debian project leader
Commented on LWN about System D
And about the hostile politics around it
And it's been
What appears to be in most cases
People are sort of re-evaluating
Their life priorities
And deciding
I am not putting up with this anymore
They're being harassed
They're being attacked
Because of their position
Or involvement with either
Whatever aspect of this process
And it's really kind of a sad thing to see happen
Watching people who are contributing
Their time and their energy
To free software
Be attacked
For working on free software
And I don't know what the levels of attacks are
But it's such a hard thing to watch
And I think it represents
Sort of this really hostile tone
That our conversations in the community
Have taken over these things
And it
I don't know
I don't think you could blame System D
System D seems to be the catalyst around it
Matt, are you seeing what I'm seeing?
I'm seeing bits and pieces of it
It's a little bit like
When you're walking through a war zone
And little bits of shrapnel
Are buzzing by your head
So that's been more my experience of it
I don't know the deep details
But it does seem like
That it has been escalating
And at the end of the day
I feel badly for these guys
But I think it is going to be a matter of
Finally, they're going to end up
With an echo chamber of like-minded people
To keep this up
All the people that disagree
See things differently
Alright, Dare Devlin
So you specifically
Focusing on the Debian aspect
Of these latest fallouts
You think it's maybe a symptom
Of getting too big?
Too bureaucratic?
No, I actually think
It's particularly
To the tone
So the bureaucracy
I guess these people were fine with it
So far they've been able to get
Through situations
Through this bureaucratic process
It seems to me that it's rather
The tone that was passed on
The bureaucratic systems lately
Like, you should do this
Which was never the case
It was up to the maintainers
And suddenly there's decisions being made
And the maintainers are just taking
Quote-unquote orders
And in a position of
If you don't like it
Just drop it
One of the more poignant comments
That I saw was Bruce's
The former Debian project leader
And really what he said is
Internally inside Debian
They've lost empathy
Towards the end user
He said that it's sort of like this
It's sort of become this
Cold, calculated system
And it doesn't take into account
The fact that there are certain things
That end users care about
And there are certain things
That end users couldn't care less about
And I wonder if
If this is
And I hate to think about it like this
But is this the result when
You sort of have a
Quote-unquote democracy-type style
Leadership for a distribution
So let me explain why I think this
Before I dig myself too deep into a hole
Arch
Here's how Arch made the transition
To System D
Hey guys, we're thinking about doing this
There was some turmoil
They said okay, well here's what we'll do
We'll support both systems
As long as there's somebody that maintains
The init scripts and all the stuff
For each system
And then when that ends
Then we'll just transition to one system
And that's exactly what happened
People stopped making scripts
For the old system
And they transitioned entirely
Over to System D
And it happened fairly soon
And in fact, because they did it so orderly
I don't know the details on this
But I think
Unless maybe someone in the Mumba Room
Has told me this, I think
One of the guys at Arch
Now works on System D
For his full-time gig
Because they really did such a professional
Job of transitioning over to this
And I think that might be because
Arch essentially is controlled
By a small group of developers
And they just make a decision
And they go for it, right?
And other distributions have people
That just make, you know
Mark Shuttleworth makes a blog post
And says alright, yep
Well now we're going to System D
And I'm sure there was
Internal discussions about it
But once it's declared
It's declared
And I know I've raised this point before
But it seems like every few years
And this is the worst one
I think I've ever seen
Debian goes through these many implosions
And I look at this and I think
This has to just be
Because as human beings
We're just not very good
At this kind of thing
Boy, you know
The more I think about it
I think really when you compare
Arch and the Debian communities
I honestly think back to the
Introduction to Buck Rogers
The intro that showed
Where it has all the things
Happening through time
That's how I see Debian
In a lot of ways
I feel like that, as you said
They have many implosions
But I also think the fact is
That there's a lot of ego
That floats around in that circle
Arch users honestly like Arch
Or go away
They don't care
You know, I've never really
Got a sense of ego
From the Arch community
That I've gotten
From other distributions
And so that may play a part too
To where, you know
Yes, it was just stated
This is what we're doing
Like it, lump it, or leave
And the Debian people are like
Well, you know
We've got to have this big community
Think about it
And blah, blah, blah, blah, blah
But I do feel like there's a lot
Of ego stroking
Going back and forth
I don't know
Am I wrong?
Well, Derrick Delvin
Do you think it could be
That it's more of a
Hey, I didn't sign up
For this kind of mentality?
Yes, I didn't sign up
For doing the work
For that particular thing
And now suddenly
There is that expectation
In the past
That's not how it was done
In Debian
It was up to the maintainers
And now this is being moved up
To the who's ever leading
And the folks are just saying
Okay, I'm going to drop it
So it is a little
It's like
It's egos combined
With a bureaucratic structure
Mixed with people
Who are like
Well, this isn't what I signed up for
I don't want to do this
And all of these things
Come together
And you have a toxic situation
Now here is the
Here's where I want to move
The discussion towards
I still maintain
That I think
A fanning of the flames
And I think that's putting it
Very generously
I would almost say
Throwing fuel on the fire
Is a more inapt analogy
Is the quote, unquote
Open source tech press
Who has fueled these battles
To drive clicks
And I still believe
That it's sort of like
This secular cycle
Where the news
The tech, quote, unquote
Bloggers and press
Write about this
That almost sort of
Becomes reality
And what it does is
It moves the goal post
Of the conversation
So it changes the tone
To be much more dramatic
Much more decisive
Much more amped up
It makes these community discussions
Turned into reality
Television shows
For the web
Is what it does
And when it does that
It moves the tone of the dialogue
In that community
It moves that forward
Into a more aggressive tone
And it begins to reflect
The very thing
They are writing about
Have we not all seen this?
And so once again
Don't we come back to
The tech press
Has a responsibility here
To get the story right
And to stop over blowing
All of these things
That fan these problems
And now
I think you could attribute
Some of that
To causing major strife
Inside a critically important
Linux distribution
What do you think
Dear Devlin?
I think that
That does have an influence
And perhaps we could
I'm not saying like
It's just a suggestion
Try to invite
When we see something
Instead of the first thing
Be comment about it
Just actually invite someone
That is participating
On the actual process
Right so
If they're willing
To come up with that
This was my thought
Is like
There must be something
We could just do ourselves
Something that has to be done
That could be
Our contribution
Something that we could
Figure out
To move the tone back
Into a more
Merit-based conversation
Where it's technicalities
And there is room
For philosophy
But it's not a war
It's not a holy war
It needs to be a space
Where it's perfectly fine
That I think plasma TVs
Are better than LCD TVs
And you think LCD TVs
Are better than plasma TVs
And that's great
And we're both happy
With our choices
And that's fine
Like we need to be able
To have those kinds
Of conversations
Where when somebody says
I think chrome
Is better than Firefox
Instead of having a battle
And calling somebody
Uneducated or saying
They don't know how
To use computers
It's like oh that's interesting
Now I find that
Chrome might be better
For me because of this
Kind of like we've started
Now do you know
Lionhead today
He reported on his
Chromium experiment
We didn't jump on him
Those of us who think
Chromium is better
We're like okay great
Glad you gave it a shot
Thanks man
Thanks for the feedback
And that I think
Is more valuable discussion
So the question is
Is what can we do
To sort of encourage
That everywhere
What can we do
With the base level
And my thought was that too
Is like maybe we could
Bring more people on
But the thing is
That's easier said
Than done to be honest
These are people
That are working
They're in different time zones
Sometimes they don't
Speak English
There's a lot of problems
In that
But I agree
That could be one thing
We could do
We could also
Actually reporting it
To get more context
Let it run first
Then report it
And actually have a comment
And I think we do actually
Here on this show
I think we do do that
Fairly well
And so I want to make sure
It's like
What I was thinking
So I wrote down a couple ideas
And you guys tell me
What you think of this
Maybe we could utilize
Something like Hangouts
And do round table discussions
Where we'd bring on
Several people
Like a counter point
Point counter point discussion
And you know
We try to keep it civil
I don't know how exactly
We'd pull that off
In timing wise
But it could just be like
People we could make
We could send out invitations
Say hey we'd like to have
A nice civil discussion
About this
And then people
And then
What would be the ideal
Output of that
Would be a video
That when the
When the debate comes up
On Reddit or on some form
Or in an IRC room
Or wherever these debates happen
You could send somebody
That YouTube link
And be like yeah
These guys
Discuss this here
And you know
This is a pretty good
Point counter point discussion
So that was one idea
I had
But it
That is not an easy thing
To do
To schedule these people
In the different time zones
And organize all of that
So it's
It might be a little pie
In the sky
Go ahead
What I think
What's fueling this
What's it called
System D debate
Is prejudiced
People
People don't think
System D before actually
Using it
Sure
I'm sure there's a little
Prejudice and predetermination
In it
But it's
It's a mix of stuff
And there's
Because scheduling
Sorry I was just going to say
Besides scheduling
Scheduling things live
Is very difficult
Especially with multiple individuals
Why not have like
A group email thread
Where those people can reply
To each other in a timely fashion
And that can be summarized
On say Linux unplugged
It's pretty boring
For the end
For the listener
But it's definitely
Something
It's already happening
It's yeah
Yeah
And that might be
Chris has not mentioned something
Yes
So
So I have a different view
On the matter
Okay
Actually not everything is
Technical
And of course
System D is superior
And it does things better
And so on
And we can praise it
All day long
But it's not only about that
There's also a philosophical
Or a belief based
Right
Opinion here
And this is actually
This is the same with
Chrome versus Firefox as well
This is why
But
Not to interrupt
Before you go too much further
I just want to say
This is actually
You're making the point
This is why
And skookiesbrights also
Mentioned the chat room
This is why I was thinking
Instead of an email thread
A hangout or whatever
It would be web RTC session
Or whatever is better
Because what we have
Happen a lot
Is people start talking
Philosophies across
Each other's faces
They're not talking
To each other
They talk across
About philosophy
And things like that
And the conversations
Go totally on
To deaf ears
And so if they talk
Then that would be something
When people engage directly
With each other
They're more civil
And they listen
A little bit better
Instead of having to
Read a wall of text
What do you think?
Of course
I absolutely agree with this
But my point was actually
About
You know
Attacking developers
Due to
Or developers essentially
Resigning from their positions
Because of
A problem like that
Of debates going on
Like that
And what I wanted to mention
Was
It's the same
You experienced
That
When you say you know
I prefer Chrome
Because it works
So much better
And so on
You're right
Chrome does work
Much better
In a lot of cases
A lot more than Firefox
And systemd does a lot better
Than sysv
And its scripts
But
There is
The philosophical side
When
I get upset
When you
When I see somebody
Like you
Who really praises
Chrome
That publicly
And
Because
There is
Something called
Market share
And market share is
Information and power
And
We should not be putting
All of our eggs
In one basket
And
So
I personally
I never touch
Chrome
Even if Firefox crashes on me
I just tolerate that
I try to report bugs
I do
Everything I can
Just
Not because it's Firefox
It's not about open web
It's not about
Anything like that
It's just about
Preventing a monoculture
Right
You don't want a monoculture
In web browsers
Yeah absolutely
That's why I took the
So this
Sort of segues
To my next thought
Is maybe
Instead of
Trying to
House discussions
Maybe what we should
Try to do
Is hyper focus on ways
To get people more involved
With open source
So there's more people
Coming in
Instead of
Shouting from the
Stadium
At these developers
Let's get more people
In there
Contributing
And maybe instead of
Being commentators
In peanut gallery
They'll actually have
Some skin in the game
And so my thought
On that was
Let's take a project
And say
This
I don't know
Let's just pick
Because I love it
Let's pick the
Geary project
This is the Geary
Email client
This is how you get
Involved specifically
With the Geary project
Maybe we bring on
One of their developers
And ask them
What would be the most
Helpful type of contribution
What would be the way
People can get a hold of you
How do they start
Submitting code
Where should they go to
Submit patches
And things like that
And really give people
Concrete
Like if you want to walk
Away from this episode
Of the open source project
And maybe we can sort of
Get more people involved
In that aspect of it
And get people
Out of the
Playing
You know
Sports commentator
And actually running the ball
Huh?
Look at that analogy
I see what you did there
Sports ball
I don't know
But would that
Actually be appealing though?
I am already
Doing it
It's just
That thing
Like bringing
More people to develop
You need the
One stop shop
That I've been
Talking about
Yeah
If the developers
Don't have that
One stop shop
It's really hard
To introduce someone
Because they have to
Detach from their tools
Or their ways
And there's also like
These
Floating guidance
Right
It's
There's no channel
For them just to get in
And from end to end
This is how you do it
This is something
We've talked about
On Coda Radio
Is when Mike was looking
At writing one of his apps
You know
He's like
Well do I
Go grab the Ubuntu SDK
Do I just go start writing
You know
And he's looking for
Sort of a
This is the path you take
And it doesn't have to be
The only path
But it's sort of like
Here's a pretty solid path
That you're probably
Going to be able to make
A pretty decent app using
And it's not too intimidating
It's well supported
And it's going to get you
On most modern distributions
Like that's really
All we need
We just need something
Kind of like that
There's different things out there
You can absolutely
Put together yourself
No doubt about it
But what the guys
In the Mumbler are saying
And what Michael Dominic
Was saying
Is they don't even know
Where to start there
Because they don't even know
Those things exist
Yeah
I'm actually already
Doing some work
I'm not going to
Advance much about it
But I'm already
Doing some work
And I'm actually
Going to propose
To all the distributions
See if we can get
Some consensus
On getting something going
See this is
A major area
If we could get
More people contributing
Instead of just
Being on the sidelines
I feel like
If we got the right
I don't know
Like that could be
A great way to really
Sort of move things forward
And hopefully
Make a positive impact
So low level
That it
I don't know if it'd be
Community changing
But it would at least
Be putting things
In the right direction
I don't know
It's something I think
We should think more about
And I'd like to get
The audience's thoughts on it
To expand upon that
Go over to
Jupiterbroadcasting.com
Click the contact link
Choose Linux Unplugged
From the drop down
Or we have that
Feedback thread
In the subreddit
Linuxactionshow.reddit.com
You can submit your thoughts there
Any closing thoughts
Mumble room on that topic
Before we move on
Yeah I still
I mentioned
The
Firefox and Chrome thing
And I just wanted to
Like clarify
Why I mentioned
This point
It's
Like you can make
The analogy with
System D and Debian
And Debian is about
You know
It has a history
Of being careful
And doing things slowly
And taking their time
And doing things right
And not screwing up users
And now that you introduce
System D
Which is essentially
Turning most of Linux
Into a monoculture
Because
Even if you want to do something
That is not
System D
You then have to
Do a lot of work
Such as
You can
You can do so much
Work to the extent
That you're actually
Forking parts of
Desktop environments
Just to make things
Work without System D
And
I think
People in the
Debian project
Are really worried about this
And I think
They should be
Because
Essentially System D
Is not a community project
It's a Red Hat project
And Red Hat can be
Exercising political power
Using technical
Manipulation
Alright
Okay
Let's get on the topic
Because I don't agree
With half of what you said
But I really don't want
To debate it anymore
And it's not a Red Hat project
Yes, Red Hat's involved in it
I think that's one of the reasons
It's been as successful as it has
And yes, I would be also concerned
If I was a big competitor
Of Red Hat
About that
But to be truthfully
To call it a Red Hat project
That's sort of disrespectful
To all of the engineers
At Intel
And all of the engineers
At SUSE
That are developing on it
Every single day
The developers at Arch
That are writing code on it
Every single day
I mean
That's disrespectful to all
Of the people outside of Red Hat
That are contributing to it
We don't need to be this extreme
When we talk about it
Yes, it has its downsides
The monoculture can be bad
But we don't
You don't have to exaggerate it either
It is what it is
But I don't want to discuss it
You're right
Okay
We're done
The system, do you think
To be honest with you
Until something more changes
I feel like
It's
As a community
We've talked it to death
I mean
I talk about stuff for a living
And I'm done talking about it
It's just
You know
I really think
It's an interesting
It's an interesting topic
I do
I do too
But I also have to respect
A lot of the audience
Doesn't care anymore
So
And I really don't understand
Why we make this more complicated
Than it needs to be
It's like look
Okay
We get a kiddie swimming pool
Loaded up with mud
Maybe a little salsa
And mud wrestle
Whoever wins
Wins
You know what
If we could solve it that way
I'd be all for it
I mean
Honestly
I could continue to debate it
I agree
And I think it's a fascinating thing
But at a point
The conversation starts getting into
A lot of
A lot of different areas
That I just
I just don't think
We've tried it too many times
Absolutely
Maybe
You know what
I'm not saying
I'm not shutting the conversation
Down forever
I just want to give it some time
To breathe
And develop more
Yeah
Before we obsess on it
Put it on the windowsill
For a bit
Sure
Yeah
All right
So you know what
Let's take a break
To sort of change gears
And then
We're going to work on
This is
There's sort of a theme
To today's episode
And we're going to round it off
With a final topic
And I think we'll have
A lot more to come
And you'll save $25
Off your first Ting device
If you already have
A Ting compatible device
You'll get $25
Of credits
And because Ting is only
Paid for what you use
It's a flat $6 for the line
And it's just your minutes
Your messages
Your megabytes
That $25
Might carry you through
More than your first month
It did for me
And I still haven't forgotten that
That was my
That was I think
A pretty awesome
First impression of Ting
Now I'm coming in
On my second year almost
I think it will be
Towards the end of December
And it's amazing
I've got the Nexus 5
The iPhone 5
$6 each
Only paying for what I use
And Ting has no
Whole customer service
Which is crazy great
Ting FTW
Any time between 8 AM
Or 8 PM
And a human being
Answers the phone
And they solve your problems
They have a great dashboard
I mean it really is great
It's better than any
Mobile carrier's dashboard
And I know
Because I've tried them all
You can activate
Deactivate lines
Transfer devices
Set nicknames
Alerts
Thresholds
All kinds of really
Crazy stuff
You wouldn't believe
You could even pay for your
Ting account
Nexus 6
You know that big old
Well it's coming real soon
To Ting
So now is the time
To grab your Sim
If you're looking for
The Nexus 6
On Ting
Which would be an awesome
Combo
Nexus 6
Android L
Ting
Only pay for what you use
No contract
No early termination fee
Kind of awesome
So go order a Ting
Nexus to Sim card
Go get that
Then you grab your Nexus 6
Pop your Ting card in there
Then you go over to their website
Bob's your uncle
Now you got Ting service
On your Nexus 6
Woowee
Linux.ting.com
That lets them know
You appreciate them supporting
The Linux Unplugged Show
Linux.ting.com
And it gets you that
$25 credit
And a big thank you to Ting
For sponsoring
The Linux Unplugged Show
Okay, alright, okay, okay
Alright, shake it off guys
Everybody's good
We're good, we're good
Cause I don't want this
To be a negative thing
Because I've seen this
Kicked around a couple of times
And I saw it land
On Reddit today
And he said
Oh I'm sorry
It was yesterday
He says what are the
Drawbacks of Linux
Considering moving
From Windows
To Linux
I use my computer
A lot at work
And unfortunately
The business world
Is riddled with Windows
I'm currently on a Mac
Oh, I misread that
And the good thing with that
Has been
There's Office
For OS X
I don't like Office
But it makes life easier
But more importantly
Besides the small things
Like MS Office
What other drawbacks
Should I take into
Consideration about Linux
I'm fully aware of how awesome
Some software is
But he wants to know
From the perspective
Of long time users
So
I read some of these comments
And I thought to myself
I think coming out of it
That the most complicated
Thing about Linux
Is also the strongest
And best thing about Linux
And that is
There's a lot of diversity
There's a lot of things
Going on
There's a lot of different
Projects
Efforts underway
All at once
And when you step back
From the big picture
That's a great thing
But when you get down
Into the weeds
It looks like insanity
Or maybe that's vice versa
I'm not so sure
Okay
So I know everybody
Probably has a few ideas
I saw that
Wizard Jed
Tossed his hat in the ring
So Wizard Jed
What's your take on this?
So there's a lot of
Really really high level
Software out there right now
That is extremely complicated
And things like
High end parts of Libre Office
And high end parts of
Specifically Microsoft
Style products like SSMS
It's the pieces of software
That aren't necessarily
Really nice
And it's not that
They don't have an alternative
So this is your drawback
Well these are just
General things
They'll just be
Something that will
Be there
And people will say
You have to use this
And you're using this
Because there's no training
For the other things
So we're not even
Going to look at it
It's not even an option
Hmm
Alright
So my drawback was
Sort of like
It can be a mess
A little bit
But you can avoid that
And when you say
Software support
You're coming out from
The things like
Large management suites
Like from Microsoft
Maybe the AutoCAD
That's a popular one
But I feel like
Those are like
Well known drawbacks
That if you are
Working maybe
On a Mac now
Maybe it's not a problem
Right
Because you're probably
Not plugged into an SMS
Management infrastructure
Or using AutoCAD
That's on Windows
Right
So that might not be
As much of an issue
I'm trying to think of
Drawbacks that
Would smack you more
In the face
But I could see
Definitely software
Availability being one
That if you didn't
Research first
Then another thing
Would be
One is just
The package
You know
Just discovering
The different packages
And applications
You can get
Then also discovering
Which one works
For your distro
And then also
To find out which version
That you want to use
Because you
You know
There's a lot of the time
The stuff that's in
The official repo
Is out of date
And you have no idea
So people who are
Coming into Linux
And are expecting
To be able to
Like search Google
Or something
They're probably
Not expecting
That
Now what do you think
How important is that
Like that local
Tech support angle
You know
If you got
A Windows or a Mac
There's a good chance
You can either go
Talk to the Geek Squad
Or there's somebody
In your local
Social group
That probably knows
How to troubleshoot
The problem
Maybe not the case
If you got a
Linux box, right
Don't you think
Go ahead
I know
All right
Go ahead
Matt
You take it
Okay
So that's
That's a big thing
Because you know
I used to do
A lot of home repair
Way, way back in the day
And that's one thing
That I ran into
Is if I was going to
Switch someone over to Linux
I had better not retire
Because I'm going to be
The one supporting it
No one else is
I think that's definitely
A problem
Because for whatever reason
Local techs just don't
Seem to think
That there's any money in it
Or they're not able to learn
Or whatever their individual
Vices may be against it
But that is definitely
A problem
Yeah
And people get confused
By choice
But I feel like
This is a problem
That us geeks
Obsess about
Way
See okay
Here's my final thought on this
And then mumble and I'll let
Anybody else that has
Any closing thoughts
But here's my final thought
Is this is a problem
That us geeks worry about
Way more than end users
Worry about
They don't think about it
See they don't think
Software first
They think
I got to buy a device first
That's how they go
And they don't
You know
I mean
So it's
There's all this choice
All this complexity
Or randomness
Whatever you want to call it
It doesn't matter to them
They get somebody
And they say okay
I've decided I want to do
This Windows thing
And Mac isn't for me
And they go say
Grab a
System 76 Ultra Pro
They they will never really
Have to worry
That there's
A dozen different desktop
Environments if they want
You know
They don't
They don't ever have to
Consider it
So I think it's a problem
That really exists
In the minds of geeks
And not so much in a problem
Of end users
And then of course
Then you get into
The gray area where you have
Your more advanced users
That want to be able to go out
And grab a piece of hardware
Or something like that
And the end users
We're really talking about here
I don't think it's
A big of a problem
Anybody disagree?
No
That's particularly right
Yeah
If they have
If they have something like
Access to something like that
That'd be great
If they're just trying
To find Linux
Because they've heard about it
Then it's really hard to find
People to help you
Like there's lugs
But they're hard to
Yeah
Find themselves
And sometimes the lugs
Aren't very organized
So it's
You know
They might show up one day
And then change it the next week
And you know
You can't do that
But yet that survey shows
That so many of the people
In that survey were using
Linux on their desktop
So it happens
It doesn't happen very easily
But it gets out there
And it's really
I think
I don't know
I think once you discover it
If you are technically inclined
It's pretty attractive
And I think that's more
Of our user base
I think if we're true
To ourselves
Because of these barriers
We've talked about
In today's episode
The problem of discovering it
And the problem of
You know
All these little issues
That we've just talked about
I think it's more practical
To expect that it's
Going to be finding
And discovering
And implementing it
And that's why we're all
Obsessed about this stuff
Because that's
That's all who we are
It's a big echo chamber
And if you step outside
The echo chamber
It's not that big of a deal
That's my thoughts
Hey
I'll give a plug
For your Runs Linux
Send it into the show
Won't you?
We want to see
Your Runs Linux
Like a picture of your setup
Maybe a video of your setup
Send it to
LinuxActionShowJupiterBroadcasting.com
And put Runs Linux
In the subject line
And we'll feature it
In a future episode
Of the Linux Action Show
And don't forget too
To check out our
Tech Talk today
Monday through Thursday
jblive.tv 9 a.m.
Noon Eastern
And then available for download
A little bit after that
Tech Talk today
General tech news
From an open source
Advocate Linux perspective
And we have an open
Mumble room too
It's cool to join
So there you go
And one last final reminder
An hour early next week
So prepare yourself
For 1 p.m. Pacific
Go over to jblive.tv
And join us in there
And help us maybe even
Dig out some of the best
From last year
And you can go to
JupiterBroadcasting.com
Slash calendar
To get it converted
To your local time
JupiterBroadcasting.com
Slash contact
For feedback to the show
All right, Matt
Well, I'll see you on Sunday
Have a great rest
Of your week, okay?
All right, I'll see you then
Okay, everybody
Well, thank you so much
For tuning this week's
Episode of Linux Unplugged
Hope to see you live
An hour early next week
And don't forget
If you do join us live
You get to not only
Participate in our chat room
And suggest titles
You can also join us
In our Mumble room
It's our open virtual log
We just check to make sure
Your mic's working
And then you can come on in
Okay, everybody
That's the episode
Of Linux Unplugged
We'll see you right back here
Next Tuesday
Thank you so much
All right, everybody
Go to JBtitles.com
We got a boat on this thing
See, I don't know if we're
Going to get something
Out of this
It's a mess
What a mess
JBtitles.com
Hey, I had a question
I wanted to ask everybody
Twitch chat room
Anybody listening
I'm doing some improvements
In my Twitter feed
My Twitter feed
And I'm wondering
If there's
If anybody could toss links
In the IRC
For interesting folks
In the Linux community
That you follow
That maybe I should follow
So put links in the chat room
All right, JBtitles.com
Did we get any titles at all?
Anybody suggesting titles?
We got a lot
Yeah, there are some titles
There
Oh, good
Good
Oh, yeah, we did
Okay, all right
Debbie and Disintegration
Ouch, that's
Ouch
Beating the system
Dehorst
Ouch
Debbie and Community Divided
System D
Shiny
Disaster D
Oh, that's not bad
The System D
Tobacco
Ayo
Naked Linux dating
No, you know
I got to tell you
Yikes
System D
Gate
And also
If you happen to be listening
At home
And have anybody you follow
Send it in to the show
And
Yeah
Get that Twitter feed
It's also
Yeah
I think it's worth remembering
That it's just you guys
It's
In the end of the day
It's just you guys
The project's still awesome
Sure, sure
JBtitles.com
It's just you guys
That'd make a good title
Right there
It's just you guys
Two guys in a podcast
The real issues
I'm biting my tongue
I'm not saying a word
The real issues of Linux
How do you like that?
Yeah, well
The real issues of Linux
I still like Debbie and Community Divided
Because it's not inaccurate
Yeah
It really isn't
And that's not
Yeah
Necessarily negative
It's just factual
Yeah
I mean, you say Community Divided
And that's true
For all of it
Yeah, I mean
Really, I mean
What Community isn't
It has division
At some point
The drawbacks of Linux
Because I feel like
The Debian part
Was more of an overall
Discussion
Okay
I mean, it could be
Just about Debian
I mean, that's not bad
But
I think that's
I hate to say it
But there was so much of it
That was
Yeah
That it would feel disingenuous
To try and like
Spin some happy little
Bunny time thing in there
I don't know
Yeah
All right
Well, we'll let democracy decide
JBTitles.com
The vote is on
Democracy
Mm-hmm
I think it's wasted effort
Hmm
Beating the System D horse
Debbie and Community Divided
Is still rising
Two sides
One System D
That's not bad
It's a little dirty though
Okay
I think Debbie and
I think Debbie and Community Divided
Is our winner
Ladies and gentlemen
I think we're going to go that way
All right
So, hour early everybody
See you next week
Thanks everybody
Bye
See you