This is Linux Unplugged, episode 17 for December 3rd, 2013.
Hi everyone, and hello planet Earth! Your weekly Linux talk show welcomes you to the
closing act of 2013, pour yourself a cold one, and join us around the penguin-shaped
table. My name is Chris. My name is Matt. Hey Matt, here we are, episode 17, it's the
final hours of 2013, and it's been a big year, Matt. Oh, it's been huge. I guess this
is supposed to be the year of Steam, but now that we're coming to an end, the only thing
I can think about is Bitcoin. Oddly enough, yeah, I can understand. Yeah, well, yeah,
recently Bitcoin has been sitting above $1,000 right now on Bitstamp, which is where you
could actually cash out today if you wanted to. The price is $10.45. Other exchanges have
it higher. Those exchanges are full of crap, and I think it's interesting because I have
to hold myself back. I don't want to talk about it in the Linux Unplugged show, Matt.
That's all I'm thinking about. Oh yeah? Alright, so you know this week, Matt, I had a grab
bag called a Dev Random, because I'm funny like that, and I had several topics I wanted
to dig into, sort of suss out, and I wanted to start with some of our follow-up this week,
but before we get into that follow-up, I wanted to ask you, have you opened the boxes yet,
Matt? I have. I did my, usually when I get a review item, and this is something I've
done for probably over 10 years, is I get a review item, I pop it out of the box, I
plug it in, make sure everything's working, looks good, drool for a while, then I cry
myself to sleep when I put it back in the box. Yesterday, Matt got three boxes from
System76 on his doorstep. You got the Leopard Extreme in there, and you got two laptops.
You got the new Kudu laptop and their Ultra Pro laptop. Can't wait to try those things
out. Oh, they're just gorgeous, gorgeous machines. Is the Leopard Extreme heavy? What's it look
like, Matt? Is it nice? I remember carrying it in the last time, and yeah, it has some
weight to it. That is solid hardware. You're going to be shown up on Sunday with a car
full of gear. That's going to be awesome. Can't wait to try that out. And we even got
a little bit of extra time to try these things out. I'm going to be banging on the Leopard
Extreme for like a week solid, so we'll have like an extended report on how that thing
performs on the big show. Well, speaking of the big show, so this week I want to talk
about Sailfish OS and the YoloPhone as sort of a follow-up. I don't know how many of you
out there, if any of you out there listen to Unplugged and don't listen to the Linux
Action Show, you're a crazy son of a bitch if you do that. What's the matter with you?
But one of the things that happened, the biggest thing that happened, we talked about Mint
16, mate and cinnamon edition, of the latest release from the Linux Mint project. You would
think that would be the thing that dominates the dialogue from the Linux Action Show audience.
No. No, pretty much everybody was talking about our coverage of YoloOS, or the YoloPhone
and Sailfish OS, and so Kyle wrote in to the Linux Action Show, and I broke into the Linux
Action Show's house, I ripped open their little sack they have hanging on their refrigerator
that holds the Linux Action Show feedback, and I stole it for this show, and so we're
going to read Kyle's email, even though it was directed to the Linux Action Show, we're
going to break all the rules and tie the knots together and cover it here. He writes, Hi
Chris, I'm sure you got more than a few of these emails this week, but hear me out. I
was interested to hear what you and Matt might have had to say about Yolo's launch of their
new phone and OS on this week's show, and I was disappointed to see you dismiss it out
of hand. You spent numerous segments and even a whole Linux Unplugged and Koda Radio talking
about Canonical's dismal mobile efforts, and when similar small groups of devs not
only creates a 1.0 version of their Linux-based OS, but actually ships it on non-vaporware
phone, you blow it off like it's no big deal and don't even bother to research some basic
facts about it. Sailfish OS does run Android apps. In fact, he linked us to some demos
online that show that, and it will run on Android hardware in the future. This is actually
one of their main strategies for expansion into China. The device has only been out for
a few days, and already community members have got Google Play Store support up and
running on it. This is exciting and just the sort of thing to expect from an enthusiastic
Linux community. In fact, smacks the table, Yolo's efforts to provide open source compatibility
for Android hardware helped out Ubuntu Mobile's efforts and represent a real contribution
to the open source community. Furthermore, the MakePlay Live project you got so excited
about is using Mer, which Sailfish OS is also based on, and which Jala is dedicated to supporting
in a similar way to how the Linux kernel gets contributions. There was a developer-oriented
talk by one of the Jala devs on a subreddit a while back that outlined how Sailfish OS
is just one aspect of their broader plans for Mer, which sounds very exciting in terms
of spreading Linux adoption through devices like the improv. Sorry if I came across as
a bit of a fanboy that Matt's always telling to settle down. I know you've probably been
in damage control since Amazon dropped their bomb on you, and you haven't had much time
to research the topic, but I think you might want to give Jala's a second look. At the
very least, I hope you review Sailfish OS once it hits the Nexus 5. On another note,
I can't afford to buy a new t-shirt with the cost of the international shipping, but
I will start a subscription on filter next week. I hope you get over the financial problems
on Amazon that they've dumped on you and continue making great content for the community.
Thanks, best, Kyle. So interesting points, Matt. What are your thoughts?
So here's the deal. We never said, and it's interesting how if you're not really enthusiastic
in a positive way, you're automatically negative. There can never be a gray area, and I noticed
that, because that's not what happened. What actually did happen is that, as he pointed
out, it's very early on, so at this moment in time, until I have something in front of
me that I can really hold on to, like say, I don't know, a Firefox OS, that I can actually
have an opinion on, we're at a meh moment right now, because there's nothing to really
judge. It sounds cool, but Firefox OS actually addresses a specific need. It brings low-end
smartphones, accessible smartphones to people that might not otherwise be in the Android
market.
If I understand the other side of this argument, what their point is, here's what they would
say to that. They would say, hey, dude, look, Sailfish OS is coming from the folks that
made me go, Nokia, we've got industry ties, we've got a proven track record, we've got
a community that's already built, we are here, we are the proven recipe, and we've just shipped,
and meanwhile, you're talking about Firefox OS and Ubuntu Touch.
I'm talking about something I can install on a phone and see right now. Now, again,
I've not researched this heavily, so if I can do that today, I'm excited. If I can't,
I will be excited tomorrow.
When Kyle says, yo, dawg, you're going to be able to install it on Nexus 5, I think
to myself, actually, that's when it crosses the line from interesting concept to practical
product.
Bingo.
It might be a limitation in just the fact that there's a lot of things to focus on these
days. Unless you can actually play with it, it just maybe doesn't spark that interest
internally. But I go back to that I think my senses from the Linux action show audience
and the Linux unplugged audience is there's just straight up mobile exhaustion.
Android didn't just kind of pull ahead, Android dominated everybody in a major way.
And not necessarily in a positive way, it just kind of happened. It's kind of like when
you spill something all over your keyboard, it's there.
You know what I mean?
It makes the deployment and the adoption rate of Windows look quaint.
Oh, yeah.
And so I think in that shadow, it's hard to conjure up any genuine excitement because
it just seems like, it honestly seems like cavemen going up against the United States
government.
Oh, I wouldn't go that far. I think that once we, again, going back to, as you pointed
out, once we have something tangible in our hands, I can experience the performance of
those Android apps running on this. I can experience the flow of the phone, then I can
make an educated judgment based on that experience, but we're not there yet.
I guess.
He's asking me to be excited about nothing.
Okay.
But okay, let's say six months down the road, I can buy a Nexus 5 and guaranteed I hook
it up to the USB port of my computer, I flip a few buttons and I can install Sailfish OS
on it.
Sure.
I'm still probably not going to do it. I mean, I might do it in the sense of try it out,
give it my, you know, give it a go, try it for a couple of weeks, but the reality is
I want applications that are on Android.
I want, if I'm going to have a mobile device, I want badass mapping. I want Waze, right?
I want to have all of these things that are just now come to be expected on a mobile device.
I want Netflix on a mobile device. For that 15 minutes where, you know, we have to wait
for something and I, oh my God, I got to do something to occupy my two kids who are running
around like crazy, let's put SpongeBob on the phone for 15 minutes and it gives me a better
piece of mind.
I want that on my mobile device. Can they offer that? I don't think so. And if they
can, how long do they can?
But do we know? But do we know yet? I mean, that's just it. I mean, and I'm not defending
the email, but I'm just saying, I honestly don't know. I mean, perhaps, possibly, maybe
it addresses something in a fashion we haven't experienced yet. If it does, that's cool.
But yeah, I mean, for myself, I just, because I think those are valid points, but I think
at the end of the day, until it's in my hands, in my universe, in my world, it's theory.
That doesn't mean it's theory for the developer, it just means for the end user it is.
Here's what they have to do. They have to make it good enough. And I think they're actually,
I think this is why people are really excited about Yala and Sailfish OS is I think they
are on the verge, like out of the gate, out of all the projects out of the gate. Because
Ubuntu Touch has a bunch of phony icons that don't do anything and they're relying on their
community who-
Doesn't really care.
Right, to make core functions of their operating system, right? So Yala comes along and they
have Sailfish OS and it's a 1.0. It's a straight up respectable 1.0. And they're like, and
I think these people are like, hey, you assholes, this is almost getting good enough. And I'm
not saying you have to replace Android one to one for somebody like me to switch, because
I will jump when it's, when it's all they got to do is I just got to change a few habits.
You know, I got to, I mean, I got to twist my arm a little bit, but man, I'll switch
to get off of Android. I, Android's doable, but I, you guys, I've documented the copious
amount of problems I had with Android.
Well, and see, that's just it. And I'm holding out hope and I would love to see this. I would
love to see it to where it provides me the same seamless experience, potentially even
a better experience than what Android does. And that includes, not only it runs Android
apps, but if it runs them at native speeds, performance, feel, I don't want to feel like
I'm running wine or something. I want it to feel good. If it does that, it very well may,
I don't know if it does, that's awesome. But until I see it, I have no opinion because
I can't judge it, you know?
So we, we, I want to, I want to make sure I may, I stress that I do believe we need
something like this. So I got the Nexus five. It's an amazing piece of hardware. It really
is great, but it, there's a creepy factor to every time I get a new Android device more
and more is a proprietary, it's closed up. Like now the photo management application
that shipped with the Nexus five is, is, is Google plus photos. Your, your, your photo
gallery is now integrated in with Google plus and they've deprecated the original gallery
app, right? And it's just abandoned where it's just totally abandoned. It totally sucks.
And so I, as, as somebody who is cognizant of these types of deficiencies, this bothers
me and it makes me want to switch. I don't think it ever make Joe user want to switch.
And this is where, this is where the fundamental lack of enthusiasm comes from for me is how
can I get excited about something that 70% of our audience will likely never use?
The same could be said for desktop Linux five years ago though. And so I would say that,
you know, that, that was the argument of, well, it's just a hobby operating system.
When obviously it's not, it's, it's a very core experience for a number of people, myself
included, yourself included. So I, I'm going to be, I'm going to go out on the optimistic
level of if it can in fact provide me with what I'm looking for, I will be its biggest
advocate. If it doesn't, I won't care.
So you're in a wait and see approach.
I'm a wait and see guy. Yeah. I'm very, and I look at that. It's like, I don't get too
bent into licensing. I prefer open source licensing, but I don't, it's not a lifestyle
for me. I'm not a developer. I just, I have a preference, but I'm not married to it.
Right. You have more security in products that use an open source license.
Right. Absolutely. I would prefer that. Absolutely. Hands down. We'll even take a hit on, you
know, user experience to a degree within reason.
Yeah.
Certainly.
Or the amount of hoops you might have to jump.
Oh yeah.
Yeah. I, that's where I fall down too. And I will see, we'll see, you know, all companies
go through their rockstar moment and then they fade and, and, and maybe as that happens
to Google, Android, more and more people look for alternatives. And, and by that point,
these operating systems and these devices will be at a stage where they've had enough
to R and D and development and progress for that. They're ready to pick up that slack
and that would be amazing. So, you know, as, as sailfish OS comes out for other, for other
devices that I can get my hands on, I'm totally going to check it out. I'm keeping my mind
open, but I'll be honest. Um, I couldn't, I couldn't push myself to research the Yala
announcement enough to like know it in and out. Like I researched it enough to know what
the important moments were and, and, and highlight some of those important stories in the show
notes. So folks wanted to go look in the show notes of last week's last, they could go get
that info. However, you know, myself, I was like, I, I more like wanted to cover it in
the show just to document the important moment for the, for the project itself and not much
more than that. And, and that really seemed to bother people.
Well, and they, it's comical because again, it's, we're victims of a, you know, we as
the Linux community tend to, we're almost religious about things and sometimes that's
not okay. I'm going to be brutally honest. It's, it's stupid. It's really annoying.
And quite frankly, it's, it's a real turnoff to people that aren't Linux people. I'm
calloused enough to where I, it's fine. Whatever. But, but regular people are looking at this
thinking, wow, you people are nuts. So, I mean, you know, for me, I need something tangible.
I'm about a user experiences and that includes the benefits of the open source licensing
because there are, there are tangible benefits to that. So, I mean, I put that in the same
bucket, but a great analogy is looking at the difference between the steam box. We're
all really excited about that. You ask my 17 year old nephew what he's excited about
who was really excited about steam box last week until he saw a trailer for kill zone
for the PlayStation four. Right. He couldn't give a rat's butt about the box anymore because
something visually tangible is in front of them that he'd be like, Ooh, drool. And that's
what Androids got over these other operating systems. So I think we're going to have to
overcome that. Yeah. So yeah. Good point. All right. Well, so Kyle, when he wrote in
mentioned the the shirt drive with the problems we've been having with Amazon. So I got a
little update. We had a lot of people say, Hey guys, love the shirt. Don't want a long
sleeve t-shirt. I want a hoodie. So we added a hoodie. So if you go to teespring.com slash
Jupiter 2014, you can grab a hoodie. This is helping us get to our 2014 goal or at least
helping us get through 2013. This is a logo we'll be rolling out in 2014. So now we got
a hoodie available. We've got a woman's tee. Also, if you want to get one for your lady
or maybe that's all in the same, same, same addresses before just in the pull down or
pull down. And now it all goes towards to go all 319 out of 499. That's a great there.
Oh, it just went up to 319. Do you see change? You know what? You know what? I'll tell you
something, Matt. I'll tell you something. The bulk of that is the Linux action show
audience. Now there's a good mix of Coder radio in there too. Sure. But the bulk of
it is is a Linux unplugged and Linux action show audience that have right here alone have
almost got us to 320 shirts. I'd love to see that flip over to 320, 325 during the show
the goal here is is we have we have commissioned a new logo for the Jupiter Broadcasting Network.
We were planning to roll this out in about March of 2014. Yeah, you know, it's one of
those things like we're really proud of ourselves because like we were working like way ahead
of the game. Like we had secrets we were going to roll out in months. And I was like, yeah,
this is awesome. We're just like we're ruling. And then we had a falling out with Amazon
and the way that a lot of people contribute and support our network was removed. Now what
we're trying to do is close that financial gap. I sold some Bitcoin so that way we can
stay we can keep the lights on. But we are definitely still hurting. And this shirt we've
launched over at Teespring.com slash Jupiter 14. This is an effort for us to continue to
fund the network through the remainder of 2013. And also, oops, hi there to get you
guys a little bit of swag. So that way you got yourself something. Maybe you want to
give it up for the holidays or something like that. And that new logo is so gorgeous. Display
it, right? Just display it.
No, totally.
So based on your popular demand, we now have a hoodie. How awesome is that?
That is fantastic. No, it's definitely been very popular. And I think it makes sense.
I think people see the value in not only participating in the program itself by helping to support
it through buying this, but I think they also value the fact that, hey, I get to represent.
Yeah, dude.
Yeah.
You know what? That new logo looks good on black like that.
Oh, it looks excellent. It pops like crazy. It's awesome.
So thank you, everybody who has already picked up a shirt. And if you haven't gotten one
yet, go to teespring.com slash Jupiter 2014. We're trying to get to 500 shirts. We're not
there yet. And if we don't get to 500 shirts, none of them will ship. You won't get charged.
Don't worry. You won't get billed. But none of them will ship. So hopefully we can. And
that'll help us fund the remainder of the year. And thank you, everybody.
All right, man.
Yeah, I think it's also worth mentioning, too. A lot of people have the mindset of,
well, I might do it later, but someone undoubtedly will buy it. Every single purchase helps make
this happen. So definitely jump on.
We have an email. So there's a few recurring topics that we've talked about. Like on Tech
Snap, one of them is drive fragmentation. On this show, it's the whole philosophy of
to swap or not to swap. I've got an email about that that I want to touch on here in
just a second. But first, we should probably thank our first sponsor of The Unplugged Show.
And that, my friends, is Ting. Ting is mobile that makes sense. My mobile service provider
and Matt's mobile service provider, and they freaking rock. So Ting, what's great about
them? No contracts, no early termination fees, and pay for what you use. Pay for what you
use. Messages, megabytes, minutes, they all get added up at the end of the month. Whatever
you just use, that's what you pay for. Flat dollars, six months per line, and just whatever
you need on top of that. That's great if you sometimes use the phone, sometimes you don't
use the phone. And every Ting service includes hotspot and tethering, caller ID, voicemail,
and their amazing Ting dashboard. But something that was pointed out to me in the Linux Action
Show subreddit this week that we don't mention is Ting also doesn't have roaming charges.
There's no additional charges for voice roaming within the US as long as you have a CDMA signal,
you should be fine. The Ting network has agreements in place with Verizon that allows you to just
roam over to the Verizon network and use that service, and you don't get dinged for it.
It's one of the really nice little perks among the many other things with Ting. Now, of course,
the average Ting bill is around $33 per month. Think about that. $33 per month is the average
Ting bill, and that's your smartphone with data, text messaging, all of that contract
free with no early termination fees. Now, I just got my Nexus 5 on the Ting network.
Ting has a bunch of really great devices at all ranges of prices. Right now, if you go
to linux.ting.com, that's right, linux.ting.com, that'll take $25 off your first month of service
if you already have a Sprint compatible device. If you don't have a Sprint compatible device,
they'll give you $25 off your first device. When you buy this device, you own this device.
They're not leasing it to you on like a house on a mortgage where you pay into it every
single month and after two years, you now own a completely out of date smartphone. No,
like a computer, when you buy it, you own it. As an active consumer, as people out there
who are aware of the differences in that kind of setup, this is something I think we can
all elect to be involved in is let's change the dynamic of the mobile market because it's
obvious the mobile devices, even if you don't think they're that hot, are going to play
a huge role in the computing platform going forward. The problem is the cards are stacked
against us right now. Ting is changing all of that and they're doing it in a very dynamic
way. It's starting with no contract, starting with no early termination fees and starting
with the fact that you own your phone and then they price it at a rate that is absolutely
reasonable and not only that, but if you're in a contract right now and you want to get
out of that contract, Ting has an early termination relief program where they will pay up to $75
per line that you need to cancel. That's huge people because you can start saving right
now if you switch to Ting and you can get started by going to linux.ting.com. Man, I
love Ting. I've been using them for a while and as a long time customer now, I've got
to tell you, that dashboard, that dashboard, Matt, it's like nothing anybody else has.
I know that as a Ting customer, when you signed up, when I handed that note to you and said,
Matt, have at it, tell me what you think, that dashboard was it, wasn't it? That was
awesome.
It was really the big point for me and I still use it frequently because there are times
to where if I'm not going to be using the phone for a while or maybe I just don't need
any, I know I'm not going to be getting any important calls, I'll literally just go ahead
and toggle it off. I can keep the phone calls from coming in completely by using the dashboard.
This is a great point. So as you know, back when I was in IT, I would have several different
Blackberry devices and one Windows mobile device and I never used the Windows mobile
device. I was down with Blackberry, man. I was a Blackberry guy. But I only needed one,
right? But the company I worked for, they had to pay for all three lines all the time,
every single month. And then when like another tech needed to try something out for their
client, there's no transferring. Like unless you want to call the Verizon rep and ask them
after you explain to them what it is you're even trying to do, Ting does it all through
their dashboard with a couple of clicks unless you get right back to work. It's so awesome.
So we'll get started by linux.ting.com. And by the way, you need to order your device
by December 13th if you just want to get FedEx Ground or December 19th for FedEx Express
in order to guarantee delivery by December 23rd. So if you're giving somebody the gift
of Ting for the holidays, get your order in before December 13th for the cheap shipping
or December 19th for the express shipping to get that guaranteed by December 23rd. So
a huge thank you to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged. Love those guys. Okay, Matt. So
I want to cover this email that came in from Bab because it's a topic that we talk about
a lot. No, it's all good. Oh, it's good. It's good. I thought where this is going. I'm about
to get... Actually, I think we do have one of those at the end of the show. Oh, no. We
have to have at least one because otherwise, what's the point? I tell you what, we got
one that's going to get people really fired up next. Yeah. Okay, but this one comes in
from Bob. It's safe territory. We're not going to get anybody too upset. He says, hi, guys.
Just a quick note. Chris mused that maybe the day is near that you could run with a
machine without a swap partition. Well, this intrigued me. And for the last year, I've
been running my 8 gigabyte laptop with no swap partition and have not noticed any issues
even when giving it a pretty thorough workout. In fact, it worked so well that I honestly
forgot about it. One thing that had bugged me though was that the Hibernate hasn't been
an option on Ubuntu for me. I just assumed it was a config issue or the hardware not
being supported. I found out I could run pm-hibernate command, but it would just simply not Hibernate.
My frustration boiled over today and I went digging for clues. It looks like it may just
simply be a case that a swap partition is required for Hibernate to work as where the
memory image is written out before the machine shuts down. I goled, that's groaned out loud,
when I found this out. I cannot yet confirm this is an issue, but I thought I'd share
experiences for the benefit of all. Bab. Yeah, that is true. That is true. Interesting. That
is the downside to running without swap. All my machines have swap right now. Do you do
swap partitions still? I do. Honestly, it's just a legacy habit. It's almost like building
machines and putting a floppy drive in it. You do something out of habit. It's like,
why the hell am I putting this thing in here? Actually, Matt, I don't mean to age you, but
it's now CD-ROMs, Matt. It's not floppy drives anymore. What? It's CD-ROMs now, yeah. I've
got my cassette tape drive sitting right here. It works. Magnetic media is the future. God.
Why hibernate when you can just either suspend or boot? What kind of system takes that long
to boot anymore? I don't know. I'd put it out to the mumble room if anybody in here
has a strong feeling on swap partitions. Anybody in the mumble room running swap free these
days? Yes, kind of. I use swap files instead. Can I jump in quickly? You only need swap
if you're using a laptop and you want to put it into hibernate. If you've got more than
two gigs of RAM, you do not need swap. Swap is only used for hibernation. Well, what about
crashing? That's not true. Yeah. That's completely incorrect. Here we go. And it's on. Basically,
I actually need a swap partition. Let's say you've got three gigs of RAM. What is swap
used for? I use a swap partition in order to compile my kernel. Usually, I don't have
a five or six gigs partitioned or put on my rig, so I use a swap file. I knew this would
be a hot topic. I have 12 gigs of swap. Even on machines, I have 144 gigs of RAM. Yeah,
I do too. If you have no swap at all, the only negative thing I had is you can't hibernate.
That's it. No, there's no negative things. First of all, if you don't have any swap space,
as soon as you're out of memory, the kernel either has to start killing random processes
or panic. There's no other option. Okay, but you've got four gigs of RAM. It's not an
issue anymore. Yes, it is. Five or two gigs of swap, I think, should be enough. Just as
a safety, I mean, it's five or two gigs. You already have a good partition or a swap file.
Yeah, exactly. Oftentimes, you will make the swap only 512 megabytes or something, which
is just enough so that really inactive stuff can get out of your way because free RAM is
wasted RAM. You use as much of your RAM as you can for your file system cache and things
like that. If a program is completely idle, why have it wasting memory that could be being
used for cache if you could swap it out? This is my philosophy too. Just to be safe.
Having even just that little bit means that a program can be swapped out. Right, but if
the program is always idle and its memory is not in use, then it's even worse than just
wasting it. You may as well just write it to the disk even if it's slow. It's not being
used. Who cares if it's slow? The important thing is that a lot of applications will adjust
their behavior based on memory pressure. For example, the ZFS file system will free up
some RAM when there's memory pressure, but for those couple of seconds while that's happening,
there's nowhere for the program to go.
If you have even just a little bit of swap, most of the time if you need swap, you'll
know that you'll need a swap partition. Why do we need a swap if you've got more than
four gigs of RAM? Because it's using more than four gigs of RAM. All right, there you
go. So you can see, I did that as a pure demonstration that this is not a cut and dry topic, right?
That was Chris making a point right there. I think there's no total right answer other
than you should use some swap unless you're somebody who thinks you shouldn't, and that's
really the way to leave it. It's so funny because you can see how fired up people are,
which moves us perfectly to our next email from Michael who says, it's time to move on.
Get ready for this. This is going to play right into Alan's cards, Matt. If any of those
BSD guys are listening, maybe they could just skip ahead a couple of minutes. He says, hi
Chris and Matt. Long time viewer of the Linux Action Show and a short time viewer of Linux
Unplugs since it's, well, new. Put both of your flame suits on boys because I'm about
to get some backlash from the listeners about this. I'm done with Linux. I'm done with the
Linux community especially. I found Slackware in 2002 and I immediately fell in love. I
was an everyday Windows user and thought of a virus-free system and that seemed amazing
to me. I learned that right away more learning was required. No problem. I'm a math geek
so I should be able to figure out all of this Linux stuff with no problem, right? Well,
long story short, I've been on Linux for about 10 years. I loved it at first, but there were
always little things that bothered me. I didn't think that there was anywhere else to go though.
I didn't want to get a Mac and I certainly didn't want to go to Windows again. The community
of Linux users was driving me crazy with their irrational views and immature ways of expressing
those views. I have yet to meet a chill Linux guy. Now hold on. I think you and I are pretty
chill Linux guys. I'm literally the most... Oh, man. I mean, yeah. Not only do I run every
operating system there is in my office, but yeah, go ahead. Keep going. Okay. All right.
Funny enough, I found out about an alternative through Jupyter broadcasting. Hearing Alan
talk about BSD on TechSnap made me very curious as I'm sure it has a lot of other Linux guys.
I tried it out and everything seemed basically the same. I didn't even have to learn much
of anything except a different device name or something. He says, I use the system to
build and install ports. I explore it and get actively involved in the mailing list
and forms. Studying and passing on my own limited knowledge to those who could benefit
from it. I pursued my new journey in other open source software world, learned the differences
in BSD and GNU licensing and the fragmented nature of Linux distributions realizing the
free BSD community was more mature and well distributed about industry, education and
research. Everything steered me towards working with and on BSD, even though I expect some
of the listeners to get upset about this email and typical Linux fashion.
Well, so here's the thing. I've actually had fair dealings with both communities, mostly
with Linux community, but with the BSD community as well. And I'm going to go out on a limb
and actually agree them that truth be told, at the end of the day, when you look at hard
numbers of my own personal experiences, I can't speak for other people out there. There
is a vast maturity difference. It's pretty, it's pretty significant. I don't get as much
monkey poop slinging with the BSD guys.
Is it that?
Oh yeah, it's ridiculous.
Is it that it's a more narrow, narrow, more narrow spectrum on the conversation?
The BSD guys, they didn't, the ones I dealt with, they don't give a flying crap if I'm
on board or not. They're just there to answer questions to be polite about it. They're not
fanboys.
You don't think it's a factor of a smaller community that's more focused. Do you think
it's the fact that the people there are there to get some work done?
Yeah. I mean, that was, again, everybody's experience is going to vary. I'm going to
get flamed no matter how I put this, but my, my personal experience is just that when I
asked stupid BSD questions as a newbie, I didn't feel like I was going to be punished like
you do with the arch forms.
Oh, okay. That is interesting. Yeah. Sometimes like, when you mentioned, I'm using your
to install a VLC and then like 10 people pound on you. Oh, you should be using.
The BSD guys didn't drop links in a post. That was my, that's my number one pet peeve.
It's like, look, they're asking a dumb question. That's fair. Answer the question, then mention,
Hey, by the way, use the search feature. Don't, don't be a douchebag and put a link.
Oh my gosh. All right. Mumble room. So let me ask you, what do you think? Mumble room.
Why is the BSD community generally considered more civil and calm than the Linux community?
Anybody have any, the average age of a free BSD developer is 10 years older than a Linux
developer.
Yeah, that's there too. I'm not saying that's a good thing or a bad thing or whatever, but
I think that shows that BSD, yeah, it does help. I think that shows that free BSD has
a more technical, technically oriented, more server oriented user base than Linux, which
obviously is on the desktop.
I don't know. I don't know. It might be a wash there, but I definitely think the, the
age thing probably plays component. I'm 40 years old. The guys I'm dealing with are probably
40 and up. You know,
Popey, what do you think? So you're sitting, you're sitting from the perspective of canonical
who's, you know, sees a huge Linux user base. What do you think?
Right. I don't speak for all of canonical.
I know, but I'm curious because you have a unique perspective on this as somebody who's
involved in a very large Linux project.
Personal experience.
So yeah, we have like, you know, a fairly significant community and like any community,
we have people who are objectionable and say things that are unsavory and are unpleasant
to people. Same as any other community, same as Windows and OS X fans and yeah, iPad fans
and whoever.
I don't think it's necessarily unique to the Linux community that you get doofuses that
make other people feel uncomfortable. I think that's just people being dicks and their dicks
wherever they are.
Yeah.
See, that's the thing.
Hold on here. I'd like to point out too that he felt a need to write a letter saying that
we're all a bunch of dicks because he's switching to previous dicks. It's exactly the same thing.
He's doing it too.
It's all anecdotal at this point anyway that this is true. The claim is all anecdotal.
It's not like we actually have data for this.
And everybody's mileage is going to vary.
Also, when you look at the documentation, the Arch forums, sorry, just one thing. The
Arch forums are not representative of the entire Linux community. Neither are the Ubuntu
forums.
I was using polar opposite ends of the spectrum. I was comparing Ubuntu community to the Arch
forum community. It runs hot and cold. It depends on the time of day, the time of year,
what it looks like outside, what the weather is, whether someone's pissed off or whatever.
Yeah. I've always assumed it's been a volume because there's more people in a community.
There's more chances for jackasses.
But I was looking at like if I was like literally take a checkbox and go yes and no for everyone,
it was awesome and everyone was no. I was running averages. And so for my averages,
that was my experience.
I think the problem is you get people who leave a community feel so angry that they
have to, in the same way that when someone unfollows a celebrity on Twitter, they'll
announce to the world, that's it, I'm unfollowing you. Or they'll leave a post on a blog saying,
you know, that's it, I'm switching to Arch. Or people feel the need to have their voice
heard even if it's a negative one. And yeah, and declare when they're leaving and they're
going away and throwing their tongues at the pan.
That's a good point.
In a way, I think it's a way of natural progression. All of us usually start upon Linux because
it's the largest and most common to start on. Most of the time, it's usually a choice
to change to a BSD base based on what we know and what we consider to be what rubs us right
and what floats our boat. That might be why the way of uniting together under the BSD
umbrella will be a little bit more civil versus the Linux.
Yeah, there's just as much fanboyism over there because they always, because I mean,
they just like pretty BSD, right? Or PC BSD. But then at the same time, they talk a bunch
of crap and whatever about people who use Linux or whatever.
Yeah, I've seen some.
It's the same exact thing.
Yeah, they do that.
Well, I look at it like this, is I think guys like Alan who have a very set of practical
expectations from the software they use. Okay, here's my background. Before I was even doing
the Linux action show, I was using Linux, of course, but I definitely experimented with
some free BSD file servers because at the time, there was a bug that dramatically affected
Linux's performance with AdaptX SCSI cards and free BSD did not suffer from this same
bug. I got massive better multi-user performance from a free BSD server than I did a Linux
server. So I started deploying free BSD in quite a bit, actually. I think about seven
or eight servers over the span of a six-month period that would have each of them having
300, 400, 500, 700 users hanging off of each server.
And in my experience doing that, free BSD was excellent. It definitely got the job done.
But where for me, I started to have some problems, it started to fall down, was this was really
early on in the Sombud project developing their WinBind technology where you could actually
bind to an Active Directory, import the Active Directory NTIDs as UIDs and actually set file
permissions based on entries in the Active Directory. And this became an absolutely mission
critical function of our file servers because this was during the transition from NT4 to
Active Directory. And the only place I could get that initially was on SUSE Enterprise
Linux and so we ended up going that route. And I found it interesting though that I was
very happy with free BSD, but then as I needed something that was really kind of emerging,
I ended up having to go back to Linux and that's always kind of kept me there.
That's weird because Samba would be in the ports tree, so it'd be just as updated on
free BSD as it is anywhere else, unless you're talking about development that is only happening
on SUSE because of their corporate package.
I don't remember what the details were, actually, to be honest with you, because it was so early
on that there were so many bugs, but I find it to be more like one-
Because Samba is actually developed on free BSD.
Here's what I find it to be like. There is a definite range of crossover where both operating
systems can do the same tasks, serve a web page, handle a print job, whatever it is.
And there's other-
I can't think of anything that either of them can't do.
Right. And well, there's other ranges. Come on, let's be fair. There's other ranges where
you start to get more into the desktop spectrum where there is some rationale behind using
Linux and there's other areas where there's some rationale behind using BSD. And I think
what happens is, as people make the transition and whatever kind of requirements they have,
when BSD fills those, they're kind of surprised all of a sudden.
They're like, wait a minute. This whole thing's been out there this whole time and it has-
It's this one cohesive system that's done by this group and it all makes sense and it's
well-documented. It's rational. This is so awesome. And people are like, holy shit, this
has been here the whole time and there's this massive realization about it.
And I think as a lot of people out there, they come to this realization, they're like,
holy crap, and they make this move just like our writer here has done, Michael. But at
the same time, I've been that person who's made that switch like on my router and on
my file server, and I've been like, it's awesome. But I haven't been able to make that switch
in other areas that I use.
So at the end of the day, I think Linux is a little more diverse in the sense that you
have a larger range of users from people who just want to play Minecraft to people like
Alan who are building these crazy, amazing infrastructures on Scale Engine. And there's
just this crazy range of users. And that sometimes leads to all this public drama and there's
all of this... I think the GPL also adds to a little bit more of this advocate mindset.
I think the BSD license is a little more practical in some senses and the GPL is a little more
advocate-based. And I think that also is a base of some of the attitude maybe?
Well, I think that the GPL is great. I think it's awesome. But there are headaches with
it at times as well. It really just depends on what your goals are. From an idealistic
point of view, it's wonderful. It's great. But it's not always the most practical thing
in the world. And I guess the best examples of that is you don't really ever see a whole
ton of monetized open source desktop applications for home users. I know it's like a niche within
the niche within a niche, but I'm kind of putting that out there with a closed source
license that's readily possible because no one is going to take your code and run with
it unless they've hired it. So I think there's facets like that. But where it's like you
have maybe the BSDs to where maybe people would see that as more of a  it's just
less  well, quite frankly, it's less verbiage in the license itself really. It's
almost  I hate to say it, but it's almost easier to understand. You pretty much know
where you stand. So there are advantages there. I'm not saying one is better than another.
I'm just saying I think they serve different purposes and so they probably appeal to different
people. As far as BSD itself, I don't have a ton of experience using it. I just had good
experiences with the community.
Have you ever tried out PC BSD?
I have. I was actually an early tester way back in the day. I love the PBIs. I still
do.
Oh, yeah. We've talked about that.
Yeah, I really, really do. I still think that's  I think they nailed it. The port system
is awesome on its own anyway. But that's just a no-brainer. But no, I mean it has its
advantages. It definitely interacts with your hardware differently as far as detection.
It's less about bleeding edge, more about stability. Yeah, it definitely kind of feels
like an old comfy chair that you know how it's going to work. You don't have to like
cross your fingers. It has some certain advantages, but it doesn't mean that PC BSD was perfect.
It definitely had some challenges along the way. But I think it's interesting to watch
and it's a hell of a great alternative. If Linux isn't your bag and you want to try
something else, I really  I recommend checking it out, certainly.
You know, if this is just  we're just scratching the surface.
We're all over the place.
I just want to get in deep on BSD. Go listen to BSD Now. It comes out every Friday on the
Jupiter Broadcasting Network. You heard from Alan. He's on there. He's my co-host on
TechSnap. He's the host of TechSnap. And also Chris Moore, the creator of PC BSD. He co-hosts
that with Alan and they do it every week live on Wednesdays. It comes out for download on
Fridays over at JupiterBroadcasting.com. They just  BSD Now just had an interview with
this guy, he's not only one of the founders of the FreeBSD Project. I believe he also
was one of the co-creators  Alan's probably going to yell at me. I believe he was one
of the co-creators of SysInstall but also the inventor of ports, which is amazing. His
name is Jordan Hubbard and they did an interview with him on last week's BSD Now if you guys
want to go check that out.
All right, Alan. Boy, see, now I'm in TechSnap mode.
Do what happens.
Hey, I've been upgraded.
So look, I thought we'd  last week when we were gearing up for our Linux Mint review,
one of the things  because people always kick around, like, Linux Mint is the perfect
distro for new users, right? So I brought the wife in and I said, okay, honey, here's
Linux Mint. Have at it. So I'm going to bring her in in just a second to get her opinion
on Linux Mint and kind of share some of her thoughts on some of the things she ran into.
But before we get to that, I want to say thank our second sponsor this week and that is Digital
Ocean.
Digital Ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider dedicated to offering the most intuitive and
easy to spin up cloud server. And it is crazy easy. Users can create a cloud server in 55
seconds and pricing plans start only $5 per month for 512 megs of RAM, a 20 gigabyte SSD,
one CPU, and one terabyte of transfer.
Digital Ocean has data centers in New York, San Francisco, and Amsterdam. The interface
is simple. They've got a control panel that is amazing. Power users can replicate at a
large scale and they even have a straightforward API.
I've got an Archbox running over on Digital Ocean at $5 per month that distributes all
of the content for Unfilter supporters and also some additional content for just fans
of the Unfilter show. I have all of that running through a $5 a month Digital Ocean instance
and I'm looking at this Archbox. I'm like, damn, son, I got more resources available
to me. And I'll tell you, that SSD, it really actually, even on a system that's up in the
cloud, makes a big difference. Not only do the updates just rock on that thing, but anytime
I'm interacting with it, IO contention is never a problem for me.
Maybe I sound a bit like a jerk here, but I hate waiting on my disk. I do not spend
time getting memory and CPU to only wait on the damn disk. And SSDs solve that problem.
You combine that with Digital Ocean's incredible connection, it has been rocking. I downloaded
the Unfilter supporters show using BitTorrent Sync at two megabytes a second from my Digital
Ocean VPS. And I got to tell you, that's just the peak of it. I've seen 10 megabytes a second.
I've seen more coming out of that thing. It's awesome. And by the way, Digital Ocean is
offering a fantastic deal for listeners of Linux Unplugged. If you'd like to try out
Digital Ocean for two months, because they're going to give you a $10 credit, and if you
get the $5 server like I've got, it's going to get you two months, when you use our special
promo code Linux Unplugged December. Linux Unplugged December will get you a $10 credit
on a Digital Ocean account that you can go try out. Digital Ocean has these droplets.
It's all based on KVM virtualization. They deploy to these SSD drives with their amazing
hardware that's all backed up by RAID storage, ECC RAM, and these droplets let you spin up
a server in no time. You can pre-pick from Fedora, CentOS, Ubuntu, several others. You
can have them pre-configured with the LAMP stack. You can have them pre-configured with
Docker. You're ready to go. They've got a flexible API, and they even have, if you can
believe this, hourly pricing. So if you just need to test something for a little bit on
the public web, you can throw it up on a Digital Ocean VPS, take advantage of their hourly
pricing, bang on it for a while, because it's up on the web. It's public. It's got one terabyte
of transfer. It's got these SSD storage, so you can have hundreds of people bang on it
to actually get real world testing and only pay what you use for like, you know, what,
a half hour? That's nothing. In fact, I was just talking with Michael Dominic from our
Coda Radio program. He had a project over the last week where he spun up 10 Digital
Ocean servers for a little while. He didn't spend like 17 cents. It's crazy. Their web
administration panel is awesome, but Digital Ocean also offers a vast collection of tutorials
in their community section on their website. Users can submit articles to that section,
and if Digital Ocean publishes it, you'll get paid $50 per published piece. So I'll
have a link for that in the show notes. Go check out Digital Ocean. We have a brand new
promo code. It's going to get you a $10 credit on Digital Ocean service. That's Linux Unplugged
December. Brand new code. Go over there. Try it out. You guys are so many things. Here's
like a little taste of, I've been thinking about setting up an XMPP server on Digital
Ocean, a Zimbra server on Digital Ocean. I've already got BitTorrent Sync and a web server
on Digital Ocean. I'm even thinking about taking, I don't know, maybe Asygo in the chat
room could help me on the pronunciation. Quazl, the KDE, the awesome KDE IRC client, and putting
the Quazl client on my Digital Ocean VPS. That way I'm just always logged into the Jupiter
Broadcasting IRC chat and I can connect from my front end on my KDE desktop. It's just
so many things you can do and at $5 per month to have an awesome Linux powered VPS in the
cloud that you get root access to, oh man, go check out Digital Ocean and use the promo
code Linux Unplugged December and take advantage of that two month offer. It's so great. A
lot of people out there have been trying this out and their support is fantastic. So go
try it out. DigitalOcean.com, Linux Unplugged December and thanks to Digital Unplugged for
sponsoring Linux Unplugged. When I say Digital Ocean Unplugged, it kind of fits.
Hey, that works for me. These guys are awesome.
So Matt, let's bring the wife in here. Andrew, are you with us? Are you here there, Andrews?
All right, so over the last week I had you try out Mint here and there, Spotty, and I
wanted to bring you into the show. Did you get a completely new Linux user's perspective
on Mint? Did you think was Linux Mint the distro like if you were going to switch, could
I put a Linux Mint computer in front of you and have you actually be successful?
Well, only if you actually like set it up for everything that I would use it for first.
Yeah.
Because I tried their App Store and it just really didn't do it for me.
Yeah, so what was the problem? Because I mentioned a little bit on last, but I don't know if
I gave it its due.
Well, basically, I mean, it's great that it's broken down into like five or six main
categories I think, or maybe there are like 10. Anyway, it was good the way they had internet,
photo, whatever. But after looking at like the photo things, that's where I went first
since I'm so photo centered, I was really discouraged. It looked like I would need to
have like minimum five programs just to import a picture or try out a lot of different programs
just to see what would be the best to import pictures.
Yeah, you kind of felt like there was like you could string several programs together
to get what you wanted, but you wanted like plug the camera in, one program comes up and
takes care of all of the things you needed.
Yeah.
And it's not that that wasn't there, but you just didn't find it in the App Store.
Well, I definitely didn't. The descriptions are very technical and I think I'm a little
better than the average user, but I'm still an average user. So, having that it says I
know what a GUI is, that's great. That's kind of what I would expect as a typical user.
Yeah, they all kind of advertise the GUI aspect. Now, there was a little bit of a bumpy road.
So, when I'm testing out a distro and I want to try it on full hardware acceleration, I
don't want to use virtualization, I have this external USB 3 hybrid drive. It's like SSD,
it's like a 32GB SSD and a 1TB hard drive, spinning drive. And that's what I load the
distros on and then the Bonobo lets you choose what device you want to boot from. So, I just
choose the external USB device and I boot from that. And so, here I am, I'm like, here
you go wife, I'm going to give you this Bonobo and you just sit down here and you use Linux
Mint and Ange is like, oh cool, I'm going to get to use your System76. And then what
happened Ange?
Okay, so this is great. So, he's like, all right, here you go and he turns it around
and I'm sitting pretty much where Chase does when they do unfilter, so they face each other.
And I go to click on something and nothing happens. So, I try the corners.
And I'm not watching because the screen isn't facing me at this point. So, I'm just like,
I'm figuring like she's making mistakes.
Yeah, and I like double click the computer icon and the whole screen like freaks out
and I don't know what's going on. And I was asking him like, how do I do anything because
I didn't have a, oh gosh, all I can think of is calling it a start bar. What is it called
when it's on Linux?
Well, you can call it the start menu. Everybody knows what you're talking about.
Okay, well that menu wasn't even there. And so, when I asked what do I do and what do
I even do, he scoffed. I was like, well, okay. So, then I turned it towards him and he was
like, what did you do? And he's like, oh, he had unplugged the hard drive before he
turned around the laptop.
Her first experience with Linux Mint 16 was total crash fest because me being the dumbass,
I'm turning around the laptop and I'm like, well, we don't need to have all these things
connected as I'm moving the machine. So, I unplugged the USB devices. And then of course,
the USB device was the actual operating system's hard drive.
So, then he got it up and running and I was like, oh good, it's a start bar. That's a
good start. And he said, well, do something. So, I went to digitalblastforme.com from the
suggestions on Twitter. I got a new background, which surprisingly felt just normal. I did
that without any problems. Just right-click the right resolution, set his background just
like Windows, just like Mac. Super easy.
And then, let's see, what was the other thing I tried? Oh, I did the sticky note. That was
good.
Oh yeah, you liked that. In fact, you wanted me to add that to your Mac. I remember that.
Yeah, because I never  Okay, well, on my Mac, I have a really old version of Office
for Mac. And it's slower than Molasses. And I don't like TextEdit because of the lack
of formatting. So, I need something where I can just throw stuff temporarily so that
I can keep it there and then get it later.
Yeah. Well, so your overall, I guess, to encapsulate it, it was, yeah, I could use it, but you
didn't feel like  Now, do you feel like that would be the case if I gave you Windows
today? I have to completely set it up for you. Is that any different than if you were
switching to Windows?
No. No. I mean, the answer is, I think I could be just fine on Windows, surprisingly.
Do you think you could be just fine on Mint?
No, because I don't know if you recall, but you're like, go find a program. So,
I went to Firefox and I typed photo programs for Mint.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. Well, Windows 7 versus Windows 8, which one would you feel more comfortable
with?
Oh, I don't even want to look at Windows 8.
Good answer.
I don't know.
Yeah.
I was a big fan of Windows 2000. I didn't even like XP. So, no, I don't even want
to try 8. No.
It's pretty bad.
Yeah. Well, thank you for trying that. You were a good guinea pig, and I think in the
future I might have you try elementary OS and see what you think about it, and maybe
we'll have you come back on Linux Unplugged and share your thoughts.
Yeah.
That would make Ryan 516 happy.
Yeah. Well, you're a Mac user, and elementary OS is the closest Mac OS experience, I think,
on Linux right now, without being just a rip-off theme. They really try.
I think pair OS might be fun, just to see how different it is.
Pair OS. Yeah.
Yeah.
That would be my choice.
Okay. All right. Well, thanks, Ange.
Yep. No problem.
All righty.
Thank you.
So, Matt, we got one more little bit of email I wanted to get to before we go. Actually,
it wasn't even email. I keep calling that because we've gotten so much email recently,
but this was actually a subreddit post, and I'll read it, and then we'll jump into the
mumble group and see what the guys think. But he says, hello, I got a show idea for
you. Tiling window manager roundup. I feel the Linux action show has not showcased many
tiling window managers. They can be really customizable and, in turn, boost your productivity
when it comes to certain tasks. I personally run an i3wm setup, and although I sometimes
use KDE No Man's Cinnamon, I always keep coming back to good old i3. My main suggestion is
go over to reddit.com slash r slash Unix Porn. They regularly will show off how beautiful
a tiling window manager can be, both new and old. So he wanted us to take the tiling window
manager challenge. And I got to say, Matt, I just-
Are you as excited as I am?
Yeah. I think so. Like, for me, I've been actually-
I think it's worth doing. I think, in fairness, despite what we might feel, that we need,
we need, because remember the Arch thing? Oh, that stupid Arch crap. That was me. I
was Mr. Oh, Arch is stupid. I will never use Arch, and now I'm basically using Arch. So
based on that, even though I've tried it and I was never impressed with it, I have to eat
my own dog food and actually at least try it. Then I can dog on it intelligently.
But Matt, KDE is so nice. I'm liking KDE these days. All right, so I got to, let's jump in
the Mumba room. Let's ask the Mumba room, guys, what do you think? Do Matt and Chris
have to take the tiling window manager challenge?
It would definitely be interesting.
If you do it, you got to do all of them and there's about 11.
I don't want to do all of them. I want to narrow it down to one or two.
I'm sure there's more than 11.
We've talked about Awesome and Window End, and we've done Awesome and Exnomad on the
show before. At both times, I felt like I was just doing a fan service because to me,
I feel like I'm compromising a modern desktop experience. I come from the 80s, people, where
we didn't have desktops. God damn it, we finally have desktops and I want the best possible
desktop possible. Why the hell would I go back to a tiling window manager?
Windows 1.0 was a tiling window manager.
Yeah, exactly. That puts it in perspective.
I think if you're going to do it, you don't need to do all 25,000 of them. You only really
need to do a dynamic tiling window manager, which would be i3.
And then you need to do, because most of the others, they're all forks of DWM. Even Awesome
is just a fork of DWM. I'd probably do i3, Awesome and Exmonad because those three seem
to be the three main ones.
Well, the one I hear the most about-
You need to do-
It's been at least a month or two with each one to really learn them.
A month?
Yeah.
That's not going to happen.
No.
You need to just use the right poison.
I use my- I have my fling with Exmonad and i3.
And then I'll go surf YouTube with links and, you know, I mean, it's just kind of like
clickbait.
To me, tiling windows managers are just not-
TTY4, TTY4.
Tiling window managers are for pretentious idiots who just want to feel cool about using
and can be-
Ouch.
Not at all.
That is exactly-
I completely agree.
Okay. All right. So there we go.
The links and YouTube thing may have been a little much.
I think we got to try out i3. I think we got to try out i3.
That would be fair because we can settle on one and really put it through its paces.
This is the one that we always- Everybody keeps coming back to i3. This is the one we
hear the most about these days. And we've done Exmonad, we've done Awesome window manager
on the last show. Maybe it's time to try out i3. Now, I'm not saying immediately because
we've got a lot of stuff lined up on the big show, but maybe the end of the year.
I'd say that once we get through our big stuff, I think once we're looking for topics, I think
it's a great- I think it's a fair thing. I mean, we tried Arch, it worked out. Who knows?
Maybe we'll have a passing affinity, maybe.
You know what, Matt? You're right. You're right. I said the same thing about Arch and
now here I am running Arch everywhere.
It just allows us to at least- For myself, I can speak intelligently and be like, you
know what? I really love it because of Blank or I really hate it because of Blank. I can
actually point to something directly versus just saying, no, I don't want to try it. That
kind of thing.
Although, I'm going to tell you one of the reasons I like Arch is because I get the most
current KDE anywhere.
Right? Yeah, yeah. And that's a benefit we weren't even aware, really fully rationalizing
that we missed. We heard it, but we never really materialized in front of us, I guess.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to set up an i3 desktop that is powered on the backend
by Kaywin, right?
Oh, there you go.
There you go.
I see where you're going with this.
I will have wobbly windows, although I will never get wobbly windows, but I know it's
there. I know it's there. If I ever needed it, I know it's there. Look, before we run
this week, it is getting close to the holiday season, and I've gotten a lot of crap from
our very own mumble room about talking about Steam and Humble too much, but I don't know.
If you're like me, every now and then around the holiday season, I get the gaming itch.
Even if I don't have the time, it's baked into my brain. It's time to game, and there's
a new Humble bundle, which we will probably talk about on the last, but it'll be several
days into it. Now it's just launched. There's a new Humble bundle out, and there's a couple
of games on there that make the entire thing worth it. Serious Sam 3, BFE, and Natural
Selection 2, which Natural Selection 2 is that game where you get to play as the human
or the alien?
That's the one I like, yeah.
Thirteen days left on this Humble bundle. Alls I'm saying is I want all of you to go
over there and dominate this thing for Linux again. Let's just go over there and remind
them why they go through all the effort on porting some of this S to Linux, because if
you look at this lineup, one, two, three of the games are not available for Linux. This
is not a trend we can allow, my friends, and the trend must be our friend, so therefore
we must go over to Humble Bundle and use our Linux dollars, or Linux Bitcoins as it were,
to own this chart so we can show them that it's still worth their effort to port to Linux,
and the entire damn thing is worth it for Natural Selection 2. Sanctum 2 is also in
there, Magica, plus all the DLC for Magica is in there. Orcs Must Die 2 is a community
favorite, but it is not available to Linux, and those bastards must fix that. So go over
there and buy that sucker, so that way the next time a developer gets in there without
a Linux version, Humble Bundle kicks them in the nuts.
The only way it's going to happen is if we vote with our wallet, and I don't know, I
get a little fired up. Let's see how we're doing right now. Let's see. Okay, okay, man,
are you ready? Average purchase price, $3.89. Okay, okay. Average Windows price, $3.92.
Average Mac price, $4.29. Average Linux price, are you ready for it?
I'm ready.
$4.85.
Hello, everybody.
That's right.
I don't know. I'm just thinking, those are some good games. Too bad I own all of them
already.
Right? It's like, oh wow.
Yeah, that's the only thing. It's Humble Bundle, it's getting a little harder for them to have
the exclusive, but that's understandable.
That's okay.
That's totally cool. All right, man. Well, we have a really big Linux action show coming
up on Sunday. Man, I got more stuff we could dig through, but I wanted to just, before
we run, I wanted to give people a little heads up. The holidays are coming, so Matt and I
are going to do a little double recording on Tuesday the 17th, so not next week, but
the following week, we're going to do two Linux unplugs back to back, starting at 12
p.m. Pacific, and that will probably go from about 12 p.m. Pacific to about 3.30 p.m. Pacific,
and that'll be our live show for the 24th, too, so we won't have a live show. That second
episode will be released on the 24th. That way we can take the holiday week off, so if
you'd like to join us for a special long edition, we're going to need your help out there, too.
We're going to need you in the mumble room. We're going to need your emails, so if you've
been waiting to email Linux Unplug, now's the time. Go over to Jupyter Broadcasting,
click that contact link, and choose Linux Unplug from the dropdown, because we need
your emails. We need your feedback. You fuel the show, and on Tuesday the 17th, without
you, we will have no show, so we need your feedback, and we need you in the mumble room.
Join us live. Normally we're live at 2 p.m. on Pacific, but on that Tuesday the 17th,
we'll be starting at 12 p.m. Pacific over at jblive.tv. Don't forget, you can always
get a hold of us on the subreddit over at linuxactionshow.reddit.com. We check that
out for stories we should follow for the show, your feedback, threads, and all that kind
of stuff. Hey, Matt, have a great week. I'll see you on Sunday for some hardware reviews,
all right?
All right. See you then.
All right, everyone. Well, thank you so much for tuning in to this week's episode of
Linux Unplugged. We'll see you right back here next week.