This is Linux Unplugged Episode 43 for June 3rd, 2014.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that has that fresh, minty flavor.
My name is Chris.
My name is Matt.
Hey, Matt.
So we're going to talk about Linux Mint 17 today.
It was a release that came out over the weekend, and it's an interesting release because this
one is the version that will be supported until 2016.
And technically it will continue to get updates until 2019.
Wow.
Yeah.
So that's a huge, like, they're going to base and continue to push, like, all new versions
of Linux Mint until 2016 off this platform.
This is maybe the biggest release they've ever had.
I don't know.
I don't know if that's maybe overstated.
It might not be, actually.
It feels that way.
I think that's a safe bet.
Yeah.
And so I've had it running here.
I've also been trying out Cinnamon on some of my Arch boxes, and the Mumble Room's got
it installed, so we'll talk with those guys about it.
And then also, if we have time after that, and I think we probably will, Matt wrote up
an article on DataMation about, you know, essentially asking, are Ubuntu derivatives
possibly a bad thing?
And Aaron Saigo on Google Plus today asked the question, what has Mint accomplished in,
you know, in terms of furthering desktop adoption and things like that?
And the two questions are kind of being raised at the same time.
Both are valid points, and I think we'll have a conversation on that.
And then last but not least, developers have been complaining about something that I hold
dearly on the desktop, and that's OpenGL.
And I feel like this is one of those cases where sometimes developers just complain and
complain and complain, and they jump on a bandwagon where they're not fully informed
on a topic, and then it just turns into a giant circle jerk.
And right now, OpenGL's in the crosshairs of apparently every developer out there.
So if we have time, we'll get to that towards the end of the show.
But Matt, I want to start with some feedback.
We got something kind of neat going on.
This is more of an FYI heads up for folks in the Jupyter broadcasting community.
If you're going to Southeast Linux Fest, we have a thread in the Linux Action Show subreddit
where we'd like you to check in.
Our crew is going to be down there, Q5 Sis and Noah and some others.
I don't know who all is going, officially, I think Blaster might be going too and a few
others.
Nice.
And they'll be taking interviews and getting clips for Jupyter broadcasting shows at Southeast
Linux Fest.
So if you're going to go and want to meet up with the guys and say hi, go over to the
LinuxActionShow.reddit.com subreddit and check in in the Southeast Linux Fest 2014 sign-in
sheet.
That way they can kind of coordinate.
That's how they're kind of getting everything put together.
So that should be fun.
I kind of wish I was going.
We won't be making it to that one ourselves.
Matt and I, we had a good time at Linux Fest, but we can only go to so many in a year.
So true.
Okay, Matt.
So speaking of Linux Fest, Jared writes in about Texas Linux Fest.
He says, hey, Chris and Matt.
I'll soon be attending my first Linux Fest right here in Austin.
After watching your coverage up north, I decided to look for one near me.
I'm new to the Linux fun and I want to have the most enjoyable time possible while I go.
My brother and father will be along for the ride as I've come from a long line of thinkers.
Please check out the link if you have some time and let me know of any recommendations
on talks.
Additionally, I just started watching a few months ago and I'm hooked on the Jupyter
broadcasting program.
This network is a real treat.
Thank you.
And he said he's got his four-year-old daughter on Edubuntu for her first machine and it totally
rocks.
So let's go take a look over at texaslinuxfest.org.
And they have it in slash content slash event dash schedule.
And I'm looking at this right now.
This looks like a pretty good lineup.
They've got Wellware and Red Hat and Golden Frog and HP and Linux Foundation as sponsors.
Yeah.
I don't know, man.
The graphical ZFS tools would be one for my interest.
And also Linux shaping the future of network file systems would also be one that I would
find to be pretty interesting.
This looks like a pretty solid lineup.
OpenStack for beginners might be good if you've heard a lot about OpenStack but you
don't know where it is, what it is.
This is one of the things that fests are great for is you can go in and sit in on talk that
you might not have originally gone to but since you're there and it's got a good time
and you can always get up and leave.
But I have done that a few times where I'm like I think I might be kind of interested
in this but I'm not sure and I'll go sit in and it's always been a good experience.
So go through that list and check it out.
And if you're going to be at Texas Linux Fest, say hi to Jared, a fellow Linux Unplugged
listener.
We got a few people that wrote in about Manjaro again, defending it.
We talked about Manjaro last week and a little bit the week before.
And I got to say, hats off to pretty much everybody who wrote in some really well-stated,
well-reasoned emails defending Manjaro and why it works for them.
Sam wrote in one of them.
It's a bit long but I'll go through some of these.
Hey, Chris and Matt, just a quick response to the conversation about Manjaro in Unplugged
42.
I use and enjoy Manjaro on all of my laptops and I've installed it for new Linux users.
I think that the benefits of Manjaro's delayed release scheme have recently been proven with
the release of Cinnamon 2.2.
And see, the reason why I wanted to read this one is because Sam, I specifically called
out can anybody tell me a use case where these delayed packages have actually saved anybody
any trouble.
He says, both Arch and Manjaro update their versions of the UPower package to a new version
that changed its API from the typical OSS fashion.
A consequence of that is a lot of Cinnamon's features relating to power management stopped
working.
It was an easy fix for Arch packagers and it took a long time to get Cinnamon 2.2 in
a usable place.
Oh, I'm sorry, it wasn't an easy fix.
During almost a month, Cinnamon 2.2 under Arch was in a really rough shape.
Manjaro, on the other hand, pushed Cinnamon 2.2 and the new UPower package into its unstable
branch and later to its testing repos, where testers did find lots of issues and even worked
with Arch packagers who were quite helpful at fixing them.
But Manjaro users on the stable branch never had to suffer through that.
Even more significantly, at the time, there was no problem with NDM, the default Manjaro
display manager.
That made it completely, there was a problem that made it completely stop working again.
Manjaro and stable branch users saw the bugs and stable users of Manjaro were never affected.
As major security patches, Manjaro occasionally releases out of band off package updates if
security issue is big enough to warrant it.
So please be kind to Manjaro.
It's providing a great service to its users.
What a great response, Sam.
What do you think about that?
Yeah, I think that really nails it because, I mean, you know, most of my computers are
actually, you know, are Arch based.
I mean, they're based, essentially it's just Arch.
However, the machine I call you each week when we do Linux unplugged is a Manjaro machine
because quite honestly, I don't want to roll the dice with Skype every week.
I don't need to, you know, or not just Skype, but any of the backend stuff as well.
I don't need to have an audio library update and potentially have a bug that I didn't catch
when I was combing through various, you know, files and updates and whatnot.
So you know, I like to keep one machine very, very segmented, you know, to where it's like
group updates, nice and clean.
And then everything else I just let roll on Arch.
It's great.
Yeah, very, very well said.
Now speaking of bugs, I know we are actually currently suffering from a little bug in Arch
that's affecting some of us.
Willie, did you have an update about that X cursor bug?
Yeah.
No, right now I'm not actually logged into my Arch box.
I just rolled it back for the mint thing.
But this is a perfect example of where they have the opportunity to fix something that
affects the rest of Arch.
So Matt, you kind of were playing on the pre-show.
You were discovering, we were talking, hey, I just did updates on Arch, Chrome isn't launching
for me, VLC isn't launching for me.
You saw a suggestion in the chatroom about a certain package and you rolled back what
and it did solve the problem?
Yeah, I actually rolled back a libx cursor from dash two to dash one, rather than reading
off the entire version number.
And surprisingly, instantly, no reboot needed.
Everything worked.
Everything was fine.
And so being able to do so, of course, any Arch based distro makes rolling back really
easy.
But I'm pretty sure this probably won't happen on Monjaro.
Right.
And this is a good example.
So if you're on Arch today and you're having problems with your Chromium launching or your
VLC crashing on you or SMP, whatever, whatever is crashing on you, SMPlayer has done it to
faint in our mumble room.
I haven't, I've had, I actually had Nautilus lock, I'm sorry, files lock up, I don't know
if it was related.
So yeah.
It might be.
It was like, it was making everything difficult to use there for a few minutes.
I was pretty frustrated.
Hey Matt, before we jump into the Mint 17 discussion, actually, well, no, we'll start
with Mint 17 before we get to the derivative things.
I want to mention today, episode two of Tech Talk today was out.
I announced it last week on Linux Unplugged.
Second episode's out today.
And I took a few shots at Apple for essentially blatantly ripping off Gnome and Gnome client
side direct.
I don't know if you've seen the new OS 10 theme, Matt, but it looked exactly like my
Gnome box.
I purposely avoid as much news as possible, but that did leak into my gates and I laughed
and made some comments on it for sure.
I mean, Safari looks identical to Gnome Web.
It's just a little uglier, but it's almost identical.
It's got those Mac OS 10 color buttons that I'm not a big fan of.
And other than that, it looks like Gnome Web.
And Xcode looks like a Gnome app and the Maps app looks like a Gnome app.
So I went off on it on episode two of Tech Talk today, which by the way, Tech Talk today
is on the air.
So check it out over at JupiterPodcasting.com.
Okay, well before we get into Mint, I want to thank our first sponsor this week and that
is Ting.
It's linux.ting.com, linux.ting.com will take $25 off your first device.
If you already got a device that works on the Ting network, check out their BYOD page
because they're going to give you a $25 credit and if you're like me, that'll pay for your
first month of service, linux.ting.com.
Now why Ting?
Because it's mobile, that makes sense.
No contract, no early termination fee.
Let that sink in for a second.
And you only pay for what you use.
It's a flat $6 plus whatever taxes are applicable.
And then your usage, your messages, your minutes, and your megabytes.
Ting just adds them up at the end of the month and whatever bucket you fall into, baller,
that's what you pay.
You're not paying into like a $120 contract that maybe this month you got $40 worth of
your minutes and maybe $50 of megabytes.
I don't even, how does that even break down?
How do they even decide what to charge you for that?
Whereas Ting is just flat rate and it's all listed out right on their website.
And they have so many great devices now, so many great devices.
But if you go to linux.ting.com, go check out the Nexus 5, $350 shipped from Ting.
This is such a great Android phone.
This is the Android phone where if you're like somebody, either you want the fanciest,
one of the fanciest phones out there right now, this is still a great phone.
But I actually think if you bought this phone, this would be a phone that would last you
for several years.
And I was talking with Fate earlier today and we were talking like one of the reasons
I bought it and one of the reasons he's going to be buying the Nexus 5 is this is also the
phone that all of our favorite alternative mobile operating systems are starting to target.
There's essentially, if you've heard of that operating system, there's either an image
or about to be an image for the Nexus 5.
And why not pair that with a great network who respects you as a customer, linux.ting.com,
go check them out.
They've got no hold customer service, an incredible dashboard to manage your account.
And when you only pay for what you use, the value is incredible.
You might pay a little more upfront for that Nexus 5, although I don't think so.
I mean, that's just what Nexus 5s go for, but you get the example.
You might pay a little bit more upfront for a phone, but because you're not subsidizing
that cost over two years, it's such a great value.
And Rotten Corpse in our mumble room would save almost $4,000 by switching his two lines
over.
So as you add more lines, because again, so if you say you got the nephew on the Ting
plan over there, well, that's just $6 a month.
That's all it's going to cost.
And then whatever he uses, and if he's mostly a texter, that's going to be dirt cheap for
you.
Or if he's on Wi-Fi a lot.
If he's using the Wi-Fi a lot, absolutely.
And a great part of it is that if he gets twitchy and needs to be schooled, hey, you
know what?
I can go to the control panel.
That's right.
I can pull things down a little bit.
You got the dashboard hammer.
That's right.
Linux.ting.com.
And a big thanks to Ting for sponsoring Linux Unplugged.
I love my Ting phone.
All right.
So I've got Mint 17 installed here.
I went the Cinnamon route, and I got to say, I think Cinnamon's looking really good.
The new Cinnamon's pretty awesome.
I'll run down a couple of new features, and then we'll talk about it.
So starting with Linux Mint 17, we mentioned this on the Linux Action Show, big updates
to the Update Manager.
It still holds kernel updates back.
I'll get to that in a little bit.
But it makes it really clear if you're a little twitchy about what you're updating, Mint's
kind of there to hold your hand.
So that's good.
The other thing that I thought was pretty nice is they've really taken MDM, which the
rest of the community has just kind of abandoned, and they've made it a really nice display
manager.
System monitor support, animated backgrounds using HTML, high DPI support, all have been
added to MDM, lots of language support, the new welcome screen, which we talked about
in the last.
They've really kind of made the system settings more refined.
The graphical interface for system settings was refined, and settings now look more consistent.
Settings are better categorized and separated into subsections, which make a lot of sense.
I was able to flow through it really easy.
I also have worked on Cinnamon's snapping functionality, which Cinnamon right now has
one of the best snapping systems out of any desktop environment.
Now they admit that they are a bit challenging, so they cleaned up the hot corners UI, which
I have used a little bit, and I think it's really well done.
So again, another where Cinnamon has taken a power user feature, wrapped a pretty good
UI in it, and not made it overly complicated for basic users.
The hot corner module is also less confusing now, and it's more easier to find than before.
That allowed them to disable top left hot corners by default, which had screwed a lot
of people up.
So you can go in there and just turn it right on.
And last but not least, you can now shade windows just by scrolling them with your scroll
wheel on the title bar, which is always important.
And they have better integration with GNOME, so if you have GNOME on the same system, your
system settings won't be bumping heads and conflicting with each other like they had
in the past.
Linux Mint 17, in summary, features Cinnamon 2.2, MDM 1.6, Linux Kernel 3.13, and it's
all based on Ubuntu 14.04.
Linux Mint 17 will receive security updates until 2019.
Until 2016, future version of Linux Mint will be based on the same package base as 17 is.
So that's a huge one, in my opinion.
And until 2016, the development team won't start working on a new base, and will be fully
focused on this as the base.
I don't know of any other Linux distribution that really does it quite like this at this
point.
Matt, why don't we start there?
What do you think of them saying, you know, we're going to be releasing future versions,
but all of the main base packages are essentially going to stay relatively the same.
Is that a good idea?
I think for what they're trying to do and who they're trying to go after, yes, but with
an asterisk.
The asterisk I would put on that is for people that are going straight across from like,
say, you know, the more bleeding edge Ubuntu, specifically to where it's not an LTS release,
they may not find it so awesome.
But I think for casual users that are used to upgrading their Windows install, you know,
every 10 years or whatever it is, I think it's fine.
I think it's an interesting approach.
And if nothing else, even if you're not a fan of it, you got to admit that it does differentiate
them from other alternatives.
So PCWiz, you consider yourself a power user, but you also like this static base, don't
you?
I like not having to worry about my system.
I like code.
I like my system to stay the same.
I don't want to have to worry about updating my system or wake up one day and VLC won't
start or whatever.
Bromium.
Yeah.
It just needs to work for me.
Okay, Rod and Corpse, tell me, it's all about the implementation.
What do you mean?
Well, there's two potentially massive problems with Mint sticking to an LTS.
The first is the package management.
They said they're going to stick to one package base, but are they going to update like the
actual applications or is it just the core structure that's being stuck?
Like how are they...
They've never addressed that.
Yeah, and like when 14.0.1 or 14.0.1 and 0.2.3 and et cetera, et cetera come out, will they
match that?
Will they follow that or will they stay at 14.0?
They'd more than likely match that in the sense of like the kernel and the structure,
but 14.0.4 Ubuntu doesn't update applications either.
So that's the problem.
They'd have to do it themselves and they haven't mentioned whether they're going to do that
or not.
Well, I assume they're going to do user land applications like Firefox and Chrome and VLC,
right?
Yeah, well, I mean the massive packages that Ubuntu does, then they'll bring those in,
but like packages that are just open source apps like MyApp or HTOP or TMUX or something
like that.
That's not...
That's widely used, but not super popular.
So if they have a system that would compensate for that, that'd be great, but they haven't
mentioned whether they do or not.
And the other bigger problem is potentially, you know, Cinnamon is built and they release
it two months before Mint ever comes out because the Arch users are going to beat on it and
make sure that it's good.
And then they kind of get like a, I don't know, not a sneaky, but an easier way to test
their stuff.
The problem with it is that the core system of any LTS is going to stay on one version
of GTK and maybe update a little bit, but not a massive version.
And this is 3.10, right?
Right.
Because if Cinnamon is stuck on a particular GTK base, then the next time it's updated,
it might break in Arch and stuff like that because Arch will always be up to date in
GTK.
Well, and it's not just Arch.
Eventually it will be Fedora.
It'll be all the other distributions too.
True.
Right.
Everybody.
Yes.
How will that...
Wimpy, do you have any insights on that?
A little.
I spoke to Clem about all of this some months ago when he first sort of fielded the idea,
but specifically around GTK.
For example, today I've just built and installed Unity on Arch to do some benchmarking and
that's using GTK 3.12 and I'm not sure what version Unity or rather the Ubuntu desktop
is targeting at the moment, but I think it's either 3.10 or 3.8.
But surprisingly 3.12 with a few patches works really well.
Looks a bit odd in places like other desktops that are moving to the common versions of
GTK 3, but it's not awful and I think one of the reasons why Clem is choosing to put
a line in the sand here is so that he can just target a stable base so that all of those
little features you've just mentioned that are nice evolutions and improvements are what
the Mint team can focus on rather than having to deal with regressions.
Now Heaven's Revenge points out this is already becoming a problem with elementary OS.
Can you elaborate?
Well, only by third-party instances.
Most people or most articles always complain that elementary OS's base is an LTS release
and it diverges from the cutting edge or the leading Ubuntu release.
1204 at that.
1204.
And there's a lot of incompatibilities in why Pantheon won't work on almost anything
else because it's based on the LTS release of so long ago.
Yeah, I mean and a lot could change.
We see within a few years the entire technological landscape can change and especially in the
open source world where things like GTK get updated and a lot of you know quote-unquote
breaking changes happen all the time.
Is it really a good idea to have say a Linux Mint would be based on GTK 3.10 and someone
decides to do some GTK application development on Linux Mint 17 and then they want to deploy
it to say Ubuntu 14.10 at that point or 15.04 or whatever.
There's going to be substantial breakages between those GTK versions.
I mean there would be a problem with just using Ubuntu first place with the Unity compatibility
with Cinnamon because they use different versions of GTK.
The thing about elementary though is that they have only been around for two years so
they've only technically released one time.
Mint's not doing what elementary does.
They release once every two years every LTS whereas Mint plans to use an LTS base to release
consistently.
So if they consistently update the necessary packages there shouldn't be a problem.
Wimpy do you think we're worrying about nothing when it comes to GTK changes?
Well yeah I think the whole point of what Mint is setting out to do here is to pick
an LTS release which has a GTK version and they will target that GTK version for the
next four years so they don't care about the GTK changes that are happening.
When I discussed this with Clem he did make the point that yes you know the Arch users
and the Cinnamon package maintainers for Arch may well find regressions and issues and the
Mint team will address those as it's brought to their attention as they have done for some
time now but it isn't their primary focus.
Their primary focus is going to be revving the Cinnamon desktop environment and bringing
new features and improvements to what is a stable underlying platform.
Well and I could see if there's a transition taking place between traditional Unity desktop
and the new Unity 8 desktop and maybe that's not whatever.
Maybe some people won't like some of the new apps or whatever it is and Mint could come
along and say look we've been here for years we're super rock solid and we've just been
polishing and polishing and polishing the Cinnamon desktop.
I mean they could be in a really really good position and plus like the chat room is pointing
out it's not like Clem can't re-evaluate plans if things don't go swimmingly two years down
the road.
He can look at his outline and go well you know what maybe it's time to re-evaluate or
maybe the Linux Mint Debian edition because that continues on.
Maybe that gets to a point where that's particularly interesting.
Riley I wanted to let you get your point in about Mir.
How do you think that plays in?
Yes because a lot of people a while back were worried about what's going to happen when
14.10 and 15.04 goes Mir.
So like what is like all the other issues based off of what you are going to do.
Maybe that's what Clem's thinking is like you know what I'm going to do?
I'm going to sit down for a couple of years.
A lot of people thought they would just stick like they shouldn't stick with Debian and
do that way and it's focused on that but this keeps the user base.
So there's just two downsides that I see that I think are primarily worrying.
Number one I still believe the number one users of the Linux desktop are of a technical
variety so package currentness is important to what I believe to be the vast majority
of actual people who use Linux on the desktop.
There's probably lots of people there's probably a great percentage of people who drone-lessly
use their machine and don't even realize what operating system it's running.
But people who are actively engaged and want the latest and greatest I believe represent
the majority of the Linux desktop.
So I don't know if Mint's going to be appealing to those people but there is always that the
people who don't care there there's always people from that really technical crowd who
move themselves into that group as life gets busy or for whatever reason so there you can
still you can still satisfy that niche and that user base is always growing as new users
come in.
So I'm not saying it's a failed strategy but I'm just saying it probably won't appeal
to overly advanced Linux users.
The other thing I'm worried about is it seems like the long-term success of Cinnamon would
be dependent on the adoption of Cinnamon in other Linux distributions.
Now maybe that's crazy to me but it seems like if you don't have a relevant desktop
that at least has a large enough user size application developers will never be compelled
to make their applications integrate with your desktop where if you can have like KDE,
Gnome and Unity and these guys are managing to suck out most of the air in the room that's
what's going to have a developer's customization attention and they have limited time so they're
only going to spend their time on the desktops that will really net them the most rewards
and I don't see how Cinnamon can achieve that status unless Cinnamon works on lots of distributions.
Am I wrong?
Well I mean Cinnamon technically has a the extension based system for Gnome so most of
the stuff that's in the Gnome extensions could be pretty much easily ported to Cinnamon like
there's been it there's already been about 40 that been ported and they work perfectly
fine.
All right.
To that point what doesn't work?
Oh okay go ahead Noah and then Dave go after Noah.
Well my question was what doesn't work in in Cinnamon that works on for example Gnome?
Well nothing I mean everything's fine today but as as the GTK desktops move forward and
I mean not that Cinnamon won't be moving forward but if it stays pinned to one version of GTK
eventually you won't it just won't be worth the effort to run it on anything but Mint
it might be possible but it just won't be worth it.
Sure.
Okay.
There's extensions that for example Gpaste that wouldn't that the Gnome extension would
not work in Cinnamon but it was ported to Cinnamon so that works now.
Oh so Dave now you go ahead you were kind of going to challenge the general base that
I was making the argument from right?
Yes you said that Linux is still used by a more technical audience people who want package
currentness and people who are technically inclined to invest in their desktop but I've
been finding that that may not be true.
I mean I went on on a trip a couple of weeks ago and I saw that a lot of people knew what
Linux was and a lot of people had seen Linux desktops people who don't know anything about
computers but they knew what Linux was and they were really impressed they had seen this
before and there are a lot of people that it's easy to install Linux now they use Linux
they know Linux and so I don't think Cinnamon and Mint together are targeting the Arch users
or the hardcore Linux users I think they're targeting Ubuntu's place in the desktop Linux
world because Linux now has a place there I mean I'm in India and people know this people
know that there's something called Linux and it has it has these issues and whatnot but
it works and people have asked me my sister who's a dentist asked me if I if she could
install Linux yeah so yeah I mean it's the world is different now and I think Cinnamon
is trying to make a place in this world by targeting a stable reliable desktop for people
who can install an OS but not do much beyond that.
Well and Wimpy you've noticed at your local Lug that a lot of folks there are using Linux
and it's out-of-date versions at that?
Yeah I was really really surprised by this so at the last Lug meet which is predominantly
populated by Silver Surfers let's say who are finding Linux as an alternative to Windows
mostly because they've heard that it doesn't have the virus problem but they just want
something to install that works that means they can read their email that they can get
on the web and most importantly that they can play solitaire because that seemed to
be the preserve of what they are up to the versions of the Linux distributions they were
running I was kind of amazed what three or four of them were running a version of Mint
and I don't know what the Mint code name was but it was the one that was derived from Ubuntu
Karmic so this is getting on for a five-year-old you know Ubuntu distribution and they're perfectly
fine with it well they installed it and it's got all of the stuff they need and it works
and I can't get my head round that they're satisfied with this but that works it's like
a TV you know what in a sense the TV turns on and the channels come on doesn't matter
if it doesn't have a Netflix app built in exactly and and they were talking about you
know upgrading on what version they were going to move to next and I was explaining well
Mint 17s you know just around the corner oh no no no there's this Mint 13 and that's the
long-term support release version and I think that's the one I'm going to use and I'm like
but that's two years old and they just don't care it doesn't resonate right and Popey
I know you want to look into the crystal ball and talk a little about future desktops go
ahead well it just seems to me that the the the whole rationale for some of these desktops
existing like Cinnamon and Marte is there was a movement some time ago that a lot of
the technical users and existing Linux desktop users didn't like the way the desktop was
going they didn't like Gnome Shell they didn't like Unity that they didn't they may not have
liked KDE 4 as well and it seems that I know I know Mark as Mark Shelterworth has said
before that you know we tried the Gnome 2 way we tried the the two panel traditional
Linux desktop and it didn't work and for our market which is mass adoption you know everyone
buying it in stores and so that's part of the reason why we forwarded ahead with a different
desktop and Gnome have got their own desktop and KDE are working with their new user interface
and it's funny that you know you've mentioned that the Apple announcement at WWDC reflects
some of the changes that Gnome Shell have done it seems that that there's a in the future
there's these desktops that are moving forward and then there's the ones that are holding
back and the ones that are holding back are servicing a requirement from Refuse Nix people
who just flat out don't like that new interface which is fine but they're never ever gonna
get mass market adoption if you're sitting there with something that looks like Solaris
from 19 whatever I can see that I mean definitely one of the things that gives me a little bit
of a chub is the fact that my Gnome 3 desktop looks like it's from the future I used to
KDE looks fine with the proper icon themes and everything KDE looks fine you should tweak
it a bit oh yeah for sure yeah what were you gonna say no okay I was I was just gonna
say I was a CD developer at Sun Microsystems in the late 1990s so Alan I hate you
Myself and Wimpy we're in the same Linux user group so I know I know this group of
people and the Silver Surfers are you know semi-technical and they're the they're the main people who
are still in the Linux user group yeah they're the people who are contributing to the mailing
list and going along because everyone else has moved on and they've got desktops that
work and they don't have to futz around with libfu and you know as some SO file in a directory
somewhere that doesn't match so I can't run my desktop that stuff is just the past let's
move forward I that's kind of how I mean I respect like I guess I'm of two minds because
I've worked with so many just basic staff who really the use of the computer is part
of the job requirement but it's not what they're there to do and so you know you start changing
UI on them and to them it seems it doesn't even seem like annoying it just seems literally
unneeded and it's frustrating for them because like well this is for them it's a hammer it's
a hammer with a lot more buttons and you know and why make why change the hammer if I'm
just nailing the same nail every day and so I understand where there's where there is
room for cinnamon and things like that rotten corpus why don't you take us out and you said
there might be a way for power users to stay on mint and these and and the same mint base
but keep their packages up to date lay it on us right well I was saying because I as
a you know package or a project manager there's a lot of you have to deal with a lot of packaging
for different different distros and one of the easiest thing to do is to build a PPA
so you have support for anything based on Ubuntu and with a PPA you can keep up to date
and the the only problem with the PPA is that when as soon as a Ubuntu release is no longer
being supported the PPAs are killed by launchpad itself but for the LTS as long as they're
they're being supported you can just continuously get updates and updates so if if mint did
some kind of PPA management solution for their packages they could just do that instead of
having to have a completely separate repo well they do have a PPA manager built into
their software sources management it's pretty good I think no I don't I don't mean I don't
I mean I don't mean the user manages oh because that's I mean like the project themselves
the team of men managed what is like like they could go in and see this PPA is trusted
this is an official PPA from the project they're they're good to use that we can put it in
our our default repo have you guys ever noticed and I'm pretty sure I have not downloaded
Chrome from the Google website on a in a very long time but always just get Chromium from
the package manager but on Ubuntu if you download Chrome from like the Google website doesn't
it add a repo to your sources list to get future Chrome updates through the app system
but also Firefox and Chromium have an exception to the package update system in Ubuntu so
they're always up to date unlike you know some other random application that doesn't
get updated they have exceptions so why don't more packages do that though why why why don't
why don't they all do that when I download handbrake overhead someone someone has to
actually update those packages well that's true yes well I'm asking them to get somebody
to volunteer the problem is there's people who would happily like as a project manager
I would happily update my app to be continuously you know recognized as an up-to-date feature
but I have to wait until Ubuntu has the time to do it for one of the maintainers and I
can my testing is not is not enough I think it's wasted effort well that's what he thinks
so I want to pause right here and then let's talk about the whole derivatives thing and
because that kind of dovetails well with our mint discussion and first I want to thank
another sponsor of the unplugged show and that's the awesome folks over at digital ocean
are you familiar with digital ocean head over to digital ocean.com right now and go get
started because we've got a brand new promo code for the month of June which is unplugged
June unplugged you'll get you a $10 credit so what is digital ocean my friends I would
be happy to tell you a little about digital ocean I've been using them for quite a while
now and I've had absolutely rock-solid performance digital ocean is a simple cloud hosting provider
dedicated offering the most intuitive and easy way to spin up a cloud server users can
create a cloud server well often I say about 55 seconds but the it ranges our audience
I think it's actually dipped down down to the 37 second range and I swear that's without
scripting that's without scripting 37 something before boy that's crazy I know I know I think
it's even like at 43 seconds when somebody was doing it from their Android phone and
here's what you get for $5 a month 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD a blazing fast CPU
and one terabyte of transfer for $5 and it's all locked in right there you know exactly
how much it's gonna cost and if you want to upgrade it you can if you want to shut it
off you can and the best thing is a digital ocean has data center locations in New York
San Francisco Singapore and Amsterdam so I've been able to strategically place a droplet
in San Francisco and a droplet in New York spin up bit torrent sync on both of them and
then seed content from both sides of the United States and it made a noticeable difference
in performance and I think the great thing about digital ocean is that awesome simple
and intuitive control panel which power users can replicate on a much larger scale with
their straightforward API I have to say if you haven't tried out digital ocean yet you're
really missing something unplug June to get a $10 credit then you can try it out for two
months on your own to see what you think fire up a bit torrent sync an own cloud set up
a website over there and try out their backup systems with their droplet create a system
get it all configured just the way you want and then deploy it again and again and again
digital ocean makes so many of these functions that used to be really challenging I used
to be able to charge my clients hundreds of dollars an hour to do they now let you do
it in their awesome dashboard all sitting on top of KVM powered by SSD drives connected
to tier one bandwidth digital ocean.com use the promo code unplugged June and a really
big thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring the Linux unplugged show I have I have endless
uses for this you guys and you can too you'll be surprised once you get it running even
in the first two months how necessary to your life it becomes it's like if you've ever gone
from like not having a car to then getting a car and you're always like how did I live
but or the cell phone like like do you ever remember a time with or yeah Wi-Fi like there's
like these exactly there's these technologies that come around like wait a minute how did
I ever get any work done without this that's digital ocean for me digital ocean.com unplugged
June okay Matt you had a piece that you wrote for a data mation and you said our drew our
Ubuntu derivatives a bad idea that's the headline and it starts out with when most people think
of Ubuntu derivatives they usually categorize them into Ubuntu with a different with a different
desktop environment than unity category however according to Ubuntu they refer to Ubuntu
based distros with different desktop environments as derivatives as well as distros using their
own tools apps goals and customizations I think that's a great point in fact later on
you mentioned that that a lot of times mint users will go seek help in Ubuntu forms and
the Ubuntu for necessarily very receptive to that so did you kind of make the argument
here that maybe derivatives aren't a good recommendation for new users I think it's
very case-by-case and probably the best use case scenario I have for something is if you
have someone that's let's say they're a Windows XP user and they're looking to make the switch
they're very set in their ways they don't give a flying rip about what's bleeding edge
they want their launcher where their launchers supposed to be they want their Firefox and
they want to get it done that's probably a Linux mint person however if you have a Windows
7 user who is fluent in all desktops been using you know Windows forever doesn't really
care about how the desktop looks want something a little more a little more bleeding edge
a little more robust I guess you might say Ubuntu is probably a better option simply
because of better compatibility a bigger user base and they're able to drill down a little
deeper that is really my underpinnings of it is that if you're looking at PPAs mint
isn't always going to be your best experience I've based that on my own experience and based
that on my own research so on G Plus on G Plus this morning like literally like at 4
a.m. in the morning Aaron Saigo posted on G Plus in the comment threads of one of his
posts he said that you know he does feel like sometimes these derivatives sometimes are
good in some cases and in some cases what they actually do is dilute the talent pool
and reduce our focus as a community and slow us down as a whole from moving forward and
I wonder too if maybe derivatives aren't a bit like that if people instead of working
on the derivatives were working on the main upstream distribution would that not have
made that upstream distribution that much better I think it depends on the viewpoint
I think from a developer's viewpoint I agree with him I think from an end user's viewpoint
I completely disagree so so I think because from an end user's point of view they want
to be able to have choice they want maybe maybe they want to go with the KDE is desktop
in that case you would actually go with a derivative not a customization the customization
would be like elementary OS or Linux Mint with an actual derivative you're looking at
like a XBoon2, LBoon2, KBoon2 whatever it may be that way you're getting that true Aboon2
base you know a much more pure Aboon2 base without all the extra stuff put over the top
of it so Rotten do you think people show up first as a contributor to a distro and then
get put off and go start their own I wouldn't say always but there's a lot of people I've
talked to that I asked them why they'd made their their derivative of whatever base it
was and they said it was too hard to get the people who were in charge to pay attention
to their contributions and then to test them and get them applied for Aboon2 for example
it's very hard to put any kind of community contribution to any core systems like if somebody
wanted to do to fork the USC and then make it better and improve it in any way they can
it's pretty much going to be ignored and Dave I think I agree with you too it's sort of
hard to pin down what exactly is a respin versus a derivative or even a distro right
exactly see Runcops and I have this conversation often and we'll see when you say it's a different
distro like for example say elementary or Pingai is it actually a different distro
is there a very I'm asking is there a core difference between the libraries they use
or is it just Aboon2 with it is it just Aboon2 with a different desktop because that's not
true for Cinnamon, Mint and Cinnamon work very well on a machine where Aboon2 wouldn't
but I think if I put elementary on a machine and Aboon2 on a machine there wouldn't be
too much of a difference except maybe in the Pantheon in how many resources the Pantheon
desktop uses so we need to say that okay this is a derivative and this is its own this is
just Aboon2 with a respin there's a difference between the two is what I'm saying.
So Hopi I want to pick on you because I'm sure coming from the Aboon2 side of things
you guys must see this come up quite a bit folks are running a derivative of Aboon2 and
they come to get support is it a problem do you think it's maybe and I know you're not
speaking on behalf of Aboon2 or Canonical but do you think maybe it's detracted resources
from the upstream project in this case Aboon2 or something like that?
It's tricky.
Because I mean Aboon2 itself is a Debian derivative right?
Yeah absolutely and we're very grateful for the base that Debian have given us to build
upon and just to pick up a tiny nitpick the Kubuntu, Aboon2 and so on are flavors so we
consider those blessed derivatives they're called flavors a derivative is something that
is separate from Aboon2 and you can usually recognize that by the fact that the packages
that they come pre-installed with don't come from the Aboon2 archive so for example Mint
has its own repository with their desktop in it whereas Lubuntu everything that ships
on the ISO image came from the Aboon2 archive.
I don't want to get stuck in the weeds but let me ask you this if I install...
The reason why that's important is because the people who work on those flavors work
together they work together for a common goal even though they're working on separate desktops
so you've got the Aboon2 guys who are working on their KDE desktop and Lubuntu working on
the LXDE desktop but they're contributing to the commons in the archive rather than
creating silos and PPAs all over the place.
So there's some collaboration happening between the projects and notes being passed back and
forth and things like that?
Yeah and they collaborate in team meetings and so on but there is a certainly I would
agree that sometimes you do get people who come along and say I would like to contribute
in this way and the project whatever it might be and in this case yeah okay it might be
Aboon2 might say well actually we don't need that contribution that bit's done we'd like
if you could to contribute in this other way and they say well no and walk away and that
has manifested itself in derivatives appearing and then dying and other derivatives appearing
and then dying so yeah there is a problem that people want to contribute in their own
way and you know their contribution may not be wanted or their eagerness to contribute
might be wanted but not in the way that they think they can contribute if that makes sense.
But don't you think I mean then we'll go back to the main topic but don't you think man
if Aboon2 touch it takes off and a lot of people like it isn't this going to be like
such a bigger problem with that because there's so many crazy phones and different carriers
and manufacturers there could be derivative after derivative after derivative of Aboon2
touch right?
I'm not sure that would happen I mean it's entirely it's entirely possible for someone
to take the code because it's you know it's free software and you could fork it and create
your own your own phone OS but you know is anyone going to run it you know why why would
you run random you know let's say there's a mint touch for example why would you run
mint touch if you've got to look at the motivation for why mint existed it's in large part as
I said earlier there are a few NICs who don't like unity and and so on so if if mint wanted
to make a touch device an OS for touch devices they're gonna have to create a UI that fits
on a five inch device.
I don't know if it's the the USENIX or if it was maybe theming in codecs originally
I mean it might have been drivers and codecs or ironically the early adherence to strict
free software policies might have actually been what was the original spark for mint
in some ways.
Right and I can't remember the last time I had to even bother about codecs.
Yeah yeah it's yeah not it used to be a thing yeah it used to be a thing it's not a thing
yeah remember those days old man?
Automatics remember that?
Seven years ago.
Wimpy you wanted to touch on the the android when it comes android when it comes to forking.
Well yeah only only with what poppy was just saying about who would fork Ubuntu touch.
We just have to look at all of the OEMs that have effectively forked or customized android
with their own skins themes UI enhancements I mean just about everyone releases with their
own take on the android user interface so why why would Canonical think that the OEMs
aren't going to do that again?
Yeah forking and OEMs that's why all of our mobile carriers just suck for updating android
they are its own fork.
It's very difficult for anyone to contribute to android anyone outside of google to contribute
to android so it whereas you know we've got people from all around the world contributing
to Ubuntu it's very open everything's free software it's not like android where they
throw it over the wall when when there's a release ours is ongoing all the time so there's
certainly it's a lot easier for OEMs to get involved.
Also sometimes some of the android forking like and I would say probably Amazon's case
is also a competitive fork they don't want Google to be in control because of the size
of Google and Google's already existing monopoly base which is not really in fact that's sort
of Canonical's advantage we're not Google but we can still pull this off and that's
sort of like that's not a lot of the people gonna answer that so alright but going getting
back to the derivative things moving us back I kind of here's the way I look at derivatives
is to me it seems like like cars like bicycles like cell phone cases there's not one answer
for one person in most cases and so the reason why derivatives come up is because you know
like for me let's look at enter gross I I personally prefer installing enter gross rather
than regular arch even though at the end I accomplished the same task essentially but
for me I prefer going that route because it saves me essentially two days overall set
up as I would slowly poke away at installing packages and I'm I'm I don't know if you would
consider enter gross a derivative but I'm damn happy it's there and you know I'll tell
you a little behind the scenes thing is Chase and I are you know getting ready to shoot
some some of his first episodes of how to Linux and there's just been this discussion
about what distribution does he go with and we've been kicking around a lot of stuff we're
gonna make our announcement of the distribution he picked in the first episode and it is not
been an easy process it has not been an easy process at all and should he go mint came
up several times and we would start at a conversation thread where we'd start at one place and we'd
end up again at mint and I thought that was particularly interesting and I and I think
that kind of got this derivatives things churning in the back of my head because they're kept
we kept coming up with scenarios where maybe mint would be more preferable for Chase and
I don't know I'm not gonna say if we chose mint in the end but to me it does it did illustrate
that when you are genuinely switching somebody over to a new desktop operating system mint
does offer a few nice things and I I think in some ways it's sort of showing Ubuntu hey
if you did it like this it's might be a little bit better like it's not quite competition
it's like hey here's another way to think about deploying this and in some ways having
that having having that to look over their shoulder and go oh that's how these guys are
doing it maybe we'll like the PPA management wouldn't that be great if one day we just
saw something like that kind of show up in in a future version of Ubuntu wouldn't that
be nice update or two yeah and and maybe that code would just come from the mint repos like
wouldn't that be nice and so I could see how there is a solid argument for derivatives
I do think they do create a bit of a support issue but if you look at the industry at a
whole really in most cases there's lots of different derivatives of PCs there's lots
of different derivatives of Android handhelds and and monitors and peripherals I mean we
just live in a world full of derivatives and you know I think it's just something that
it's just the nature of this beast and it seems to be the nature of open source for
better or for worse I think it could be one of our biggest strengths and maybe one of
our biggest weaknesses too though because of the time loss well and one thing I wanted
to touch on just stick and I'm not trying to split hairs with this by any stretch but
I think it's important to mention we were talking a little bit about derivatives versus
customizations my information is based on the derivative team wiki from from Ubuntu
and according to them it's a it's a customization of it's a derivative customization more accurately
so that's where the where the differentiation comes from and then reverting back to what
you were talking about as to whether or not you want to go with just another desktop or
whether you want to actually go a mint direction or now elementary direction I think it really
comes down to the tools that are offered by each option and which set of tools is going
to work best for you yeah and I think too you can't undersell like the the old way of
doing things paradigm you know when you give a Windows user a computer with Linux one of
the first things they decide to do is well I need to go install some of my favorite apps
and they go down they go to their websites they'd like they look for the downloaders
and there's a whole process that they have to become accustomed to and I don't know I've
been using Suniman now for for at least just over a week and I think it's I kind of been
really enjoying it I I like that it I I honestly like how familiar and fast that old I don't
want to call it a start menu but that start menu and taskbar interface is I I don't want
to I don't want Popey to yell at me but honestly sometimes I go back and then I realized oh
geez when I needed to get data from this window to that window this just made it so much easier
to have these right here and not have to zoom out to a full overview of my entire desktop
or switch virtual desktops if I didn't you know I just I'm just saying I just even even
though using known for a long time and using unity for a long time when I sat down and
got in traditional UI I kind of went oh yeah yeah there were some nice things about this
and then it starts to feel a little old after a while Christian you sound like you sound
like the daughter in Jurassic Park this going back to a system that they know and they recognize
and they recognize this yeah I know this it's also very easy to theme cinnamon I couldn't
see or yeah it's fun there's several menus you can get okay you know what I had one more
topic I wanted to cover before we get and this one's about gnome and this one just caught
my eye because it turns out the gnome foundation board elections are going on and there is
a candidate that has caught my attention I want to see what you guys think so here's
the headline a candidate vined to become one of the directors of the gnome foundation has
raised issues of red hats domination of development of the gnome desktop project claiming that
for the last several years this is a direct quote red hat wants slash needs have trumped
what anyone else wants slash needs including the larger user base of gnome this is Emily
and I think you pronounce her last name Goyner I'm not quite sure this was in an email thread
where she was declaring her candidacy voting for the voting for this board of directors
with its 11 people there's eight posts that are open it's ongoing and will continue until
June 8th and then they will declare the elections on June 10th and there's a couple of choice
quotes from this in her candidacy statement she wrote it is my opinion that gnome has
strode too far towards a corporate driven project and away from its community led roots
as of now gnome is in my opinion to beholden to a small handful of large corporations and
forces with the project and forces which forces the project to ignore large swaths of users
preferences to them the end result being that gnome has lost a tremendous portion of respect
and goodwill in the wire free software community as a member of the gnome board of directors
I will actively work against this tide and towards the more open community driven project
that gnome once was and I hope will be again I have been a gnome I have been a long time
user of gnome since the 1.x days and an active contributor for the last two years now how
about that she goes on to say yes you are part of the community but you are being paid
by a large corporation to work on it and as a result you are beholden to them as least
as much to the rest of the community red hat is not the only thing that matters in the
gnome world or it shouldn't be but for the last several years red hats wants and needs
have trumped what anyone else wants or needs including the larger user base of gnome which
is what I believe has driven it to fracture into so many desktops over the last four years
we need to make sure that the people who aren't working for red hat have a say make sure that
people who aren't being paid to work on free software have a voice sure those of us who
are not currently paid to speak up on mailing lists but we are those of us who are not currently
paid do speak up on mailing lists but we're mostly ignored this was driven so many so
much of the community apart this is the problem wow I completely agree actually that was really
well said she's got my vote so how I mean is is is gnome is known being ran into the
ground by the by the red hat why would why would red hat do that is that really what's
going on I would say that happens with most projects yeah does red hat care about a desktop
well they have a corporate desktop that they make a good amount of money on that's you
know a lot of times like when you see people using linux and hollywood production those
are sitting on top of red hat desktops so it's a potential issue right when if a company
gets involved to the point where their needs come before users but it and some would argue
it's a real issue but in the open source community as long as all their code is open
source that you can fork and I don't think forks are a bad thing because in any project
when you get too many developers working on the same thing they have different ideas about
what you should do so having she argues that having known fracture into I'm guessing she
means cinnamon cinnamon is a bad bad thing but I don't think it's a bad thing they're
they're trying to accomplish two different goals that meets two different types of people's
needs and quite frankly love it or hate it gnome does something that none of the other
desktops really do a way of doing things that they just don't accomplish and there is a
set of users like myself that really enjoys it so to say that they're screwing the pooch
on this one just seems a little arrogant like I mean leave some room for some creativity
if they're really trying to brandish their corporate might at this issue then that's
when you start arguing about it but not until then mm-hmm and we wouldn't have gnome shell
if it wasn't for a large part of the efforts done by gnome developers that are backed monetarily
by companies like red hat true exactly and that's I that's what I was going to point
out as well as that if before you can before we harp on red hat too much for saying well
their interests come before the users yet they're also contributing a lot more I most
users contribute to the development and like it or not developers cost money right I mean
we're talking about the same kind of companies that invest you know multi-million sometimes
billions of dollars into funding the Linux kernel development we're not talking about
you know Microsoft sticking its greedy hands in somewhere and screwing with the UI wimpy
you wanted to point out though that it's not just cinnamon that she's probably referring
to right no there's there's a number of candidates in these known foundation elections that have
got similar sort of messages in their manifestos and a common theme is talking about potentially
unifying the traditional desktops so Marte's being thrown in there along with cinnamon
and to some extent XFC also gets mentioned as well and and one of the candidates is talking
about using gnome 3 as sort of the the skunk works they let's go crazy with the design
ideas throw it all at the wall and see what sticks and whilst everyone's over there experimenting
with new design philosophies then have a something more stable and traditional for the corporate
an enterprise market and this is this is really what the discussions about is what's the desktop
that you're going to put in front of enterprise customers going to be what are they expecting
and I think that you know last time around when they they put the the classic extensions
into gnome 3 for rel it was kind of a vote of no confidence in a new and shiny that everything
has been done in gnome 3 in terms of the enterprise market well Willie what do you think do you
think the fact that Apple just pretty wholesaly ripped off gnome 3 design might give a little
extra credibility to those pushing the gnome design forward I mean it's not the most used
desktop for no reason people like it and if people like it is it really that bad well
I don't know if I don't know if I agree that Apple copying the design validates it but
I think it does give those designers another quiver as these right as these elections are
coming up and there's this hey let's integrate more traditional functionality back into gnome
right as all that's reaching a peak boom Apple drops Yosemite on everybody's face and they're
ripping gnome off and it to me seems like a signal that that is probably a good UI design
direction at least another another shop that is well known for its design aesthetics think
so and I think that is a at least a quiver in their cap or whatever you call it and I
think to them it sort of came just at the right time I think it's just an unfair representation
of the break from 2 to 3 and then everybody in 3 is so much better no shell 3.8 was was
getting so much better and then now at 312 it's quite awesome but people are still with
the stigma of when it broke at the first time yeah exactly it feels like it's the unity
thing all over again like you wrong them once and there's no going back from that well it's
not well the weird thing is there's basically every D has done that like a KDE for example
when it switched to 4 and so it hate me and so many people hated it and now everybody
loves yeah I but they they very carefully manage that over time and I unity I feel like
that I'm same amount of time now has passed and unity hasn't fully recovered from the
public perception I'm not saying whether it's right or not but the put the perception of
it I think they should like if they could figure out a way to make the extensions universal
to not break between updates yeah then unity work nobody would be the best that stop yeah
there's still a design phase right now so as soon as they have that that the global
aspect is they're changing so much between every version that that global aspect can't
really work yet but when they get the foundation solid to where they want it to be they their
goal is to have those global right yeah I'm not really hearing anything from board members
about you know having some sort of plan of like introducing some sort of compatibility
layers for you know extension developers and you know widening it to you know a wider developer
community it just seems to be you know shame or monetary backers and the people that you
know pay us money to work on this desktop environment so is it weird that I kind of
feel like that the manifesto was more like a politician style no I mean yeah it does
kind of feel like it and I kind of agree with the chat room to I I don't follow it super
closely I I haven't I haven't been there to witness the you know the push that red hat
might give I I don't doubt that that is a real thing though I just I'm not totally sure
if it's a bad thing if it is a real thing and how and how bad it is it does feel like
maybe it's a little bit of a politician spin too I mean hey politicians got a spin that's
their job and something I'll be watching so they'll announce the elections on June 10th
it would be interesting a if the elections happen and some of these folks calling for
let's call it a more conservative desktop do get elected will gnome change or will it
continue on its current course and if what depending on what we see that might be the
long answer to this question is red hat really behind what the gnome desktop is doing because
if nothing really changes and things continue on even though these folks get elected then
it probably would indicate the red hats really the ones pulling the strings we'll just have
to watch and see what happens right Matt like everything else I think so I think so and
I mean if you actually have like a Star Wars moment where you know the democracy falls
to a sound of applause or something then I might be more concerned about it yeah but
I think at this point it's too early to tell I think at this point we're basically armchair
quarterbacking what we don't really know I think there's some strong candidates that
are going for it and we'll just have to wait and see absolutely and that music means it's
time for us to go right there Matt I think I think we'll put a put a feather in our cap
right there oh boy oh boy listen to that it's getting us out of here fast it's like the
Oscars like hey guys get off the stage it's time for you to go go get out of here all
right well listen we want you to show up on Sunday we've got a great Linux action show
planned we got another interview lined up so show up on our chat room so you can ask
questions live and don't forget the Linux unplugged show itself is live on a Tuesday
at 2 p.m. Pacific over at jblive.tv go over to jupyterbroadcasting.com slash calendar
to get that converted in your local time zone and don't forget to go grab yourself a little
tech talk today where I dug into that whole Apple ripping off the gnome guys hey Matt
have a great week I'll see you on Sunday okay all right see you then all right everyone
thanks so much for tuning this week's episode of Linux Unplugged see you right back here
next Tuesday.
You