Oh, I'm glad I'm glad you're comfortable poppy. I'm glad you're comfortable shall we relay his best wishes so Barton
Popey says hello
True supporter and I and I appreciate that
Just not enough to get off his butt and join us
This is Linux Unplugged episode 179 for January 10th, 2017
Welcome to Linux Unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's looking at some new rigs and thinking I could spend some Bitcoin on that
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hello, Wes
Are y'all warmed up for today's episode? I think so. It's just a wonderful day filled with podcasting
It's it's on it's very unusual that I'm sitting at the mic with
Co-host who's already recorded one more show than I have for the day. So you're ahead of me right now
You're gonna beat me today. You're gonna let me even well, that's right
Yeah, cuz that you never saw coming doing a double but that's not we're here to talk about today coming up on this week's episode of
The unplugged program you may be familiar with a name out there Barton George
Perhaps that rings a bell he comes from Dell and he's specifically in the Sputnik project and they have some new hard world
We'll be chatting with him very soon about some of the new things coming up and yeah
Yeah, we're gonna get our drool on and then later on in the show
Raspberry Pi wants to be your new Linux distro. Yeah, I mean the Raspberry Pi folks. They have a distro
They want you to run me on your PC not your high your desktop
Well, we'll tell you about that plus the new Linux ransomware that not only is insanely expensive
But then apparently it's just deleting your data anyways
Everybody's freaking out about kill disk
So we'll see the grill disk is a big issue and then because the universe likes to reward me
Not one but two predictions of 2017 are already gonna get checked off that I made on Sunday's Linux action show later on the show
We're gonna talk more about Mac exodus. Yes. I know that terms obnoxious and
Some market details that bode very very very well for Linux
Before we go any further though. We can't really start the show without bringing in our mumble room time appropriate greetings mumble room
Doesn't it just fill your heart
I feel like we can still officially say happy new year to the mobile room. Happy new year. Happy new year again
Well, let's start off right
Thank you. Let's start right off the top by welcoming Barton to the show Barton. Welcome to Linux unplug
Thanks so much for having me now Barton
You work down there at this company that some folks may have heard of before called Dell and there is love
There's the skunkworks operation down there where these crazy kids are doing Linux machines and it's it's really developed into quite a
Well what now appears to be an ecosystem of hardware?
So Barton I am I am really really excited because this is the big story of the week in my estimation
Today Dell is announcing some machines that are coming soon or recently has announced machines that are coming soon and a new workstation
I think it's like a mobile workstation like a big old laptop or something
Tell me all about the new hardware and what you're excited about Barton. Well, thank you very much
So anyway, this is Barton George from Dell as you said, it's really great to be here. I know back on
Episode 136 you talked about some of the previous generations
so it's great to actually be here to talk about on myself and so the news you're talking about now is the
Announcement of the precision lineup and those are our mobile workstations and it's actually the second generation of those that have been
enabled with
Ubuntu and the other the
The thing that we're adding to the pie this time is the all-in-one
So that's something that we had not had before the 5720 for those of you who are keeping count
And so that will be that's new
and then just to if I just take us a trip down memory lane to begin with as you
You alluded to this is a skunkworks project that started about four and a half years ago
and what this was
There was an incubation fund in the company trying to get
Wacky ideas out of people's heads. So
What I did was I said, hey someone had this idea of let's do a Linux laptop. I thought originally great idea
It'll never fly in Dell given the the low volumes relative
What sort of precipice there is there Linux users within Dell that just was sort of side loading Linux on to Dell hardware and thought boy
We could make this great. So there was some enthusiasm the company what what kicked that off? No, it was really if any
You know Steven O'Grady from Red Monk
he was the one we were chatting with him about hey, how can Dell do a better job of
Reaching out to the developer audience because that's one of the we had done well in
From a server point of view outfitting the all the big companies that you're familiar with with servers
but as servers become commoditized how else might we look to to add value and and the idea there was let's let's appeal to
Developers and so that's where the idea came about. Well, why don't we try and do?
Linux based laptop
And and so is when Steven mentioned it. I thought you know great idea. It'll never happen
twofold one is because
That the volume they're gonna ask it for is gonna say hey
That's what we do and you know in Belgium on Tuesday between three and four in the afternoon, right?
And that's not really how how we're geared as a company to do
The other thing is we didn't have very good-looking hardware at that point
So I didn't know if that would be something that the developers would would cotton to so
As I've mentioned there was this incubation program. I came and
Presented to them said here's this idea of let's doing a do a Linux laptop. And in the meantime
Also, we started with the new real good-looking XPS 13s. So the two of them together
I got the the green green light and was given a tiny pot of money and six months
To see with this thing fly would anyone be interested in in getting one of these?
So the the idea from the beginning too was let's do this all out in the open
And so made the initial announcement of our our plan on my blog saying hey, you know what?
We don't even know if this will ever become
a real product
But if you tell us what you want and maybe if we get enough positive feedback
It really will become a real boy. And that's that's how we we went about it. And then we got so much positive feedback
We ended up turning this into a real product and we launched first with the XPS 13
developer edition
It was now four years ago back in November
So the timing on that the timing on that seems to be extremely fortuitous because it's position Dell
In a way where you've been able to iterate on this thing for four years
Expand out the range of what you're doing and what you're doing
We've been able to iterate on this thing for four years expand out the range of hardware and it's sort of all coming to it
At least to me it feels like it's all kind of coming together
When there are certain other market condition factors that are making people look for this type of hardware more than ever and if Dell
Was starting this endeavor today you would be too far behind the ball to be ready for the customers
They're looking for a replacement and it if this wasn't necessarily going to this there was no real clear indicators of these market conditions
ie
The total lackluster updates to Macbooks there was no real clear indication that this was gonna happen
Like these things seem like they were really nailing what developers wanted for a long time. Maybe I'll be a little expensive
So Dell really really got I mean in some ways it seems very lucky that they play it's right time
Yeah, and now now I wonder Barton
Are you experiencing a different set of customers than you originally anticipated is it pretty much exactly what you guys?
It thought it's sustainable. How can you give me a sense of what that looks like?
Well, I think what the the main thing here is is that we're pretty much a grassroots organization
So we don't have a huge marketing
budget
Basically, it's my blog and then doing things like this, which is one of the reasons why I'm so excited to be doing this
but lots of folks
Learn about this after we've been around for a few years
and so it's I would just say it's more of the types of customers that
We've been seeing from the beginning and I think one of the neat things here is we've actually built up some credibility
In the beginning, of course, you can imagine people thinking. Yeah, you guys are just
Dilettante you're gonna dabble in this and then you're gonna kill it after a generation or two
and then we've stuck with it and you know, they told two friends and they told two friends and so now we've
We've got a much bigger group that were that were
Targeting or who are aware of it. I should say. Yeah, I would say too that the hardware has
Has has proven itself West. How old is your Sputnik right there that you have?
Well, this has got to be one of the first or second. Yeah, and I have the first XPS 13 that had the
touchscreen for display
So these I mean the hardware itself has proven to be very sturdy and reliable
So that's had it's had a time to develop a track record. I I guess what are one of the things I kind of curious
I always like to try to
Try to ask the OEMs these these kinds of questions because I feel like a lot of our audience the first thing they want to
Do when they buy a machine is they want to format it install whatever and so I'm sure you must get constant requests for
XYZ distro from everything from things we've heard of two ones
We've never heard of how how important is it when developing a product like this to focus on a single distro?
Or could Dell foresee?
Multiple distros or maybe you personally foresee testing multiple distros because I to me my sense is
The scope of work is much smaller. If you just choose to optimize for Ubuntu
But I'm could you kind of give us a better understanding from somebody who's actually working in this field how critical that is or isn't
Sure, and I think that's the the beauty of open source in the community because as you're saying given our resources
We're gonna we're gonna focus on Ubuntu and and qualify on that
but there was an article that just came out about the review of the XPS 13 and ours technica and
He ran also fedora on and he also ran
Arch on it. So while we ourselves are only installing
Ubuntu as you say lots of folks first thing they're gonna do is is wipe it and put their distro of choice
So when we try and we work with we write drivers
The whole idea is then to push these upstream into the kernel so that people who who are not
Working with a boon to or that's not what their first choice is that they can they can benefit from that as well
So you've got this new Dell precision five or 5720 all-in-one
and one of the things I noticed about it is it's gonna come with a
4k optional display and
My XPS 13 has a 4k display. It also has things like Thunderbolt 3
Are you are you guys running up against any rough edges is okay
Can you could you kind of tell me a little bit the the process of going from?
Developing for focusing on laptops or I guess I shouldn't say developing but really getting getting the whole product ready with laptops is the main
focus and then transitioning over to desktop where their new challenges or is it pretty much business as usual and
Can you give us a little bit of like what it is like to work with with maybe canonical if there are challenges you run
into
Sure, so a bunch of questions there. I'll try and tackle them
I think in reality the the desktop one really isn't that much different than what we've been working on with the mobile workstations, right?
so the the precision line is the mobile workstation and then the okay the all the all-in-one is that is the desktop version of
It obviously but it really isn't that much different
And I then when you start talking about working with canonical the the other leg of the stool
It's it's Dell canonical and then it's whatever third party device driver. I'm sorry
Who's making things like touchpads, etc. And so the three have to work together then to actually get these things written
So it's it's rather than a what shall I say a duo?
It's a trio in in trying to get this stuff done. And that's that's where where it really separates
The the Ubuntu versions from the other ones obviously is you got to write the device drivers and actually make sure it works. So
that feels like that's always been sort of the
challenge to developing a Linux based product that
For the desktop or for the laptop is you're constantly you want to push the edge to meet market demands and you want to get
Like better trackpads in there or better Wi-Fi chips in there, etc, etc
And so there's always seems like there's always just writes out right outside our grasp
This totally open system that doesn't have to have a distro with this specific driver or this proprietary blob to work
It feels like we're always just outside of that because the market itself is always pushing so far forward
when when Dell works on these kinds of things how
How much of a priority is it to build a system one day where it doesn't matter if?
Which distro I load or which if I or I never will need to load a proprietary driver or a proprietary blob
How close do you think Dell could get a system to that ideal state that a lot of Linux users fantasize about?
And I think that's something we would we would push for but we don't have I would love to say we've got an army
Of folks working on that and we do have a fair amount of people working on Linux distros
So we will keep trying to get closer and closer to that
But it still would be a while. Do you feel Barton though?
Like the customers you're targeting right now
Is that a high concern for them or is if you what's your sense of that with the current customer base?
you know, I think is that there was and this is if I take a step back to my
Initial blog that that launched that announced this there was such a pent-up desire for anything like this
that
There was people were just doing what we're doing now
It's got people sort of over the moon not that it can't be done a lot better, but I think the existing
What was out there at that point was was lacking and I think that's where
People have just been so excited with having something that that just works
I think that was if you if you look at Mac they didn't set out to target developers
the reason why they developers picked it up is because
a it just work and be you had a Unix slash
Linux
underpinners
Those two together that's a for a lot of people even the the free software crowd. We're willing to
Put aside their
What shall I say some of their values and and go for mm-hmm?
I would say traditionally Apple to has been sort of
Developer hostile with the exception of unless you're developing for iOS or the Mac and you need access to Xcode
yeah, the whereas these Dell's is positioning these as tools for developers and to kind of play off what you just said Barton I
I'm wondering and I know
Wimpy is wondering
Wimpy do you want to ask the question?
Because it's a it's a really plays off of Barton was just saying so my question is is if the poor
Reception of the recent MacBooks was considered when adding the high-end
Configuration options to the new lineup of right? I mean I'm seeing 32 gigs of RAM here
I'm seeing even Xeon processors available as an option. I mean that seems like a beast. I
Think in general when we talk about our client group is they're basically looking at what is what are the customers gonna want?
And what are they gonna want next?
and I've been at Dell for seven years now and it's just amazing how much better-looking and
All the awards were winning for our systems now that you know
We first started out when I looked at this. I said had the original idea put to me. We had a very
utilitarian
Laptop that did the job at a decent price, but it wasn't gonna win any beauty contest
And so now you've got things that we ourselves we're not looking to follow what what Apple's doing, but we're trying to figure out
how might we
We get ahead and and read what what is going to be next and needed in the market. I
think I think definitely for developers that are looking for a platform that
Matches what they run in production or doesn't necessarily get drug around by market strategy and and things like that
I think it's it's a very compelling option. I
I guess I I guess I would sort of I have just one last question and then I'll open up the mumble room if they
Have questions for you Barton, but I like to do this. It's it's the beginning of the new year
and I would be really curious to know if if
Barton could write one blog post and all of a sudden everything would change in open source that he was concerned about what would that one?
But if you could change one thing to improve
Maybe Linux on on the type of hardware that Dell ships or something in the open source community
Do you think that would help make it this more approachable?
I would love to know your thoughts on if by the end of 2017 something could change that would make Barton's life better
What would it be? What would that wave of the wand be? I?
Think what it would be and this is I started mentioning it before but it's it's the people beyond ourselves
And the canonical who are working to to support things like the touchpad drivers people who do that at different
Places that need to have drivers written if we can get more people to more seriously consider
Linux as as one of their their top targets and obviously with the volumes that Windows
Delivers, it's not going to be something that they're gonna put on exactly equal footing
But the more that we can get people to prioritize that and make it
Make a good show out of it. The the easier it is for for all of us
Barton, what do you suppose? What is your sense of?
How long this effort may continue? Do you have a sense that this has got good momentum?
You're talking about the Sputnik. Yes, sir. I
Think what I'm trying to do is is keep expanding it and not just on
the
client side as we call the the lap the
laptops and the desktops but tying it to other
things that Dell provides and when I say Dell now, I should switch Dell is what we call the the client
Side of the business Dell EMC is the broader company
Okay, and so and so that the more that we can tie it to things like
Cloud Foundry if you're aware, so one of the things I'm getting a system out
Tomorrow if I get if I can do it to someone who's going to see if they can get PCF dev
Which is the pivotal Cloud Foundry
Working natively on a Sputnik. So the more that we can get things tied to it then the the more that this
program
Continues to go on integrates with the rest of the strategy
Exactly. And so and I think in general I've just been extremely excited how we started with one config and now we've got
One config one system. We've now got multiple configs of the XPS 13. We've now got five
Systems in the precision side and because precision is configured to order
Unlimited permutations of of what's offered there. That's great
So so I'm very excited and I think the other thing too is we keep getting more visibility within the company
The fact that Linus Torvalds picked the XPS 13 as his laptop
Was actually something that went over pretty big within within that a lot of people were excited about
That even though we do a ton of stuff on Windows people understand the the value of somebody like Linus
and so
We're getting more
As I said within the company we're getting more visibility as well and that that helps quite a bit
That's great. And you know, I think if if the Sputnik project can stick around
You really are positioned to take advantage of some really great market conditions
They're gonna that they're not only just what was going on with Apple but also just as computing in general moves more towards
Cloud and the web blah blah blah and the general computing device you're using to access
It doesn't need to run a specific operating system
companies that sell
Specific expensive operating systems are going to be doing less less business and a company like Dell that could be positioned to already know
How to interact with the upstream community the individual vendors?
That's a that's a huge advantage potentially Wimpy's reading my mind though
And I wanted to give him a chance to jump in about the XPS. Go ahead movie
So Barton, do you know if there are any plans to introduce an XPS 15 developer edition at some point?
Yes, I just got that on Twitter before I got on the
On the call we get that every so often. So mr. Shuttleworth himself does the uses the XPS. He does
15 that being said at this point. We don't have any plans
But if you get enough positive customer input we do
so for example, the whole way we got into the precision line was because
Customers were saying we need a bigger beefier system. Hmm. We launched on the XPS 13 and we just all of a sudden
People kept saying hey, we need some more XPS. We need a better XPS system
All of a sudden people kept saying hey, we need something bigger
We need something more powerful and then just a quick trip through memory let memory Lane
That's where Jared Dominguez who's on the call and part of the Sputnik team went and just got it running
Ubuntu running on the the M 3800 which is the precision system at the time and he put those that information out for folks
And then that got so much positive feedback that the year after that
We made it a real boy and we had that was once again started with the M
3800 that year then we went to the four and now we're doing the four plus
plus the five so
All that being said to the XPS
15 is very similar to the
fifth not 57 to in the 55 20
So that's for for the right now. That's where we would we would steer people
but as they say just like many times we get enough positive customer feedback and we actually
Just like the program itself it becomes a we can productize it
It's hardening to hear that there's that kind of internal flexibility in the you know
There's you've built that trust up over the years to do that
so we will have a link to Barton's blog if you're curious Barton George dot IO is where you go if you want to visit directly and
We have the post linked where he talks about all the new hardware because for me
I just got really excited about the new all-in-one and the new laptops, but the names matter
So if you want to make sure you get the names, right like a precision versus things that are not laptops
Check all of that out in Barton's blog where he's outlined at Barton
Is there anything else you want to add before I would let you run?
We're gonna update it soon but Dell comm
Sputnik or Dell comm slash developers will have the the list of all the systems. That's work in progress
so if you go today, you'll you'll see the new the
3520 which is available now, but that that'll have more information
we'll have links as as we go forward, but you know other than that, I'd just like to say thank you so much and
The great thing about this and it can only happen with something like this
Is that the whole fact is that this is open source and this is community driven and that's been since day one
What has made this which a lot of people at at Dell looked at skeptically?
Viable that people actually said no this we really do want this
And we want to pay for a nice system as opposed to what Dell had before which is let's put a free
Operating system like canonical on a low-end system and we get a low-end price point
This is the idea here was let's put it on a really good system. So people have a quality system
So anyway, I love that once again. Thanks so much. Thank you Barton. Thank you for making it work
We appreciate it that keep up the great work
we keep advocating Linux there at Dell and feel free to drop us a line whenever something interesting is going on because
2017 I it's funny Barton yesterday on the Linux action show I had I
This is crazy day
I had no idea you and I'd be having this conversation today or I guess it was two days ago on the Linux action show
I predicted the 2017 would be the year that Dell really steps up with Linux and I start taking them seriously and I think two
Days into 2017 s prediction. It's coming true already. I'm gonna be watching this closely for the rest of the year. So
Thanks for once again proving me right Barton
Yeah, thanks for all the great hard work and we will we'll definitely be following with interest and like I said chat room if you
Guys want to see that post you can find the link in the show notes to Barton's blog now before we go
Any further and get into the rest of the updates of the week?
I want to thank ting for sponsoring this episode of the unplugged program best URL in the business
Linux dot ting dot-com
Linux dot ting dot-com is where you go to save $25 off your first ting device or if you bring a device and you just
Might be able to do that because they got CDMA and the GSM's
What does the GSM stand for global?
Come on chat room global
Systems muckery as I think yeah. Yeah, it's a technical term
Yeah, I don't even give me started on CDMA, but they got both of them cuz ting be crazy like that
Here's what I love. There's no contract nor the termination fee and you only pay for what you use you only pay for what you use
How brilliant is that? That's impossible. It's how it works. It's six dollars for the line and then you pay for what you use
Crazy ting is crazy. I know and I love it because I get to choose whichever network works better
I only pay for what I use I use Wi-Fi like a boost and then to top it all off you get to speak to
a real human when you need customer service
And they have a fantastic dashboard to choose from you can bring your own cheapo phone or they'll sell you one with no
Contract no get in the way of updates. No termination fees
Man, everybody ought to do it like this and they just might one day if you vote with your wallet at Linux dot ting
dot-com
And I've had a big thank you to ting for sponsoring the unplugged program Linux dot ting dot-com also. Hey the rest of the industry
Go learn how to do a dashboard. It's only gonna cost you six dollars a month
Go create a ting account and just learn how to make a good dashboard. It's
2017 already linux dot ting dot-com big thanks to ting for sponsoring the unplugged shenanigans all right, Wes, so I
Don't know what to make of this. I really don't know what to make of this
I
Feel like the Raspberry Pi folks some of them want us to run pixel on all of the things
Oh, yeah, and this is a step too far. I can't take it
I can't take it at all, but they have made the pixel linux desktop environment available for x86 PCs
You can download an ISO with it all ready to go
That's a by the way pixel is their backronym for PI improved xwindows environment lightweight. Yeah, just kind of shake me
I'm just confused. It's a jacked up version of LXD. I mean a modified version of LXDE for the x11 desktop environment
That's the new cool desktop environment x11 desktop environment. That's that that's what says it right there
New hot says it right there the x11 a desktop environment
And you know that's the good hotness because it's not transparency Chris is that they're not talking about a display server
No, no, they're talking about an excellent anyways moving on it was originally released in September for the Raspberry Pi
We covered it back then but now it's been packaged up for your x86 PC. They say pixel
This is a ebbin says pixel is our best guess our best guess as to what the majority of Linux users are looking for in a
Desktop environment put simply it's the GNU slash Linux. We would want to use they say
It's clean has a modern user interface curated suite of productivity software and programming tools and by curated. They made 1.3 gigabytes
I wonder what their definition of curated mean
yeah, so it's Debbie and Jesse with a pixel on top and you can burn it to a DVD they say if you like or
Write it to a to a thumb drive
Optional persistence West is this a shot at
The standard Linux distribution desktop environments like I I feel like this
I I feel like I I would say this if wimpy wasn't here
So I'm just gonna say it anyways
I feel like this is a shot at a buntum ate because a buntum ate is kicking a ton of ass on the Raspberry Pis
It makes it makes the Raspberry Pi a completely usable real computer with a no compromises traditional desktop environment
And I think the Raspberry Pi folks are seeing that going. Oh crap. There's this other distribution
That's getting more dominance on our own platform than our own software
Why are they successful? Oh, well, it must be because you can run on x86 PCs ergo. We will make we'll reverse it
We'll flip the script and we'll release our desktop environment in distro for x86 and that will stop the problem
We'll stop the bleeding
What do you think?
You know, I was really confused when we saw this we put it in the show notes. I
I guess to me it feels like they're going there
It's like a like an attempted dominance play where I don't know cuz it's kind of it feels weird from our perspective
Like I'm not interested in this, you know, we have a wonderful community here of like longtime Linux users some new people
But anyway people who are of experience you can shop around I can't imagine installing this
But I wonder if it's something that with the fact that it comes with a pi store icon on the desktop
I wonder if that has anything to do it might but I could see that like, you know
You're new to the pie
Maybe you get into Linux using high software if this is the default if this is what you're comfortable with it could be
You know an easy way to extend it like okay now we can run it on my desktop
I guess I mean at least is Debian wimpy. I have to ask you what you think of this
Well, I'll tell you what I've got two I've got two things to say about this the first is
You know my thoughts about this pixel initiative and if you want them
reinforcing then
Listen to episode 1 of late-night Linux where Aiki Doherty is now a
Presenter on a podcast you just see now you're totally spoiling my end of show plug. Oh, I'm
Do it now now, I don't know what I'm gonna do it the end of the show, but it's fine
Aiki launched a new show. I think it's brilliant called late-night Linux is episode 1
We'll have it linked in the show notes. You guys got to go check it out. It sounds like
Something irrelevant or interest is on there continue
Okay
So you want to listen to Aiki's little spiel about the Raspberry Pi pixel?
Desktop environment his thoughts and my thoughts are completely aligned now to your point about
Did the Raspberry Pi Foundation?
Respond to Ubuntu Marte on the Raspberry Pi. I believe it's the insurgency of Ubuntu
Yeah, whatever you want to call it if if the only thing
Ubuntu Marte achieved is to make a better default operating system for the Raspberry Pi
Then that's a fine legacy as far as I'm concerned
Wow, I couldn't I couldn't have written a better response if I had an hour to come up with it with you
That is some smooth as butter response right there. I love it
Well, I suppose that's one brilliant and wonderful way that leaves my heart feeling warm to look at it
So I choose to move on and not ask further questions. Do you have a thought? Okay, so
Let's go from that heartwarming story to kill disk ransomware that's targeting Linux machines demands
250,000 u.s. Greenbacks ones converted from Bitcoin depending on the rate and then doesn't decrypt your files
after you give it the
$250,000 greenbacks
That is the lowest of the low crazy
You're undermining the whole ransomware industry when you do this because people are gonna stop paying if this becomes a trend a whole trust
Thing here. I mean no one liked it
But yeah, at least you can get your phone that you're really gonna you're gonna undermine the industry when you do this ransomware authors
I'm telling you I don't really know how big of a deal is I'm having this really weird
I mean, it's not unusual
but it's extremely strong with this one a lot of hype logs a
Lot of like end of the world that the sky is falling
All your files will be destroyed and and no good really technical analysis of what this thing is
but it it I don't really cuz you mean like I would love to know a
Great example of how it's getting on people's machines how they're executing it
Has anybody the mumble room come across the story that covers it on that sense?
Yeah, I'm taking that science to me know that I haven't seen it either and I've been I've been looking people are too scared killed
There's been anything though two hundred twenty two bitcoins really I know that's pretty
Yeah, that that is a lot, but doesn't like some businesses have been paying them. I mean yeah, I yeah
Yeah, that's how we found out well
No, we found out because someone reversed
He said did a random key he said did the research on this thing?
So he said went in and did the research on it on December 6th
And they say there's even variants out in the wild too
They say things like we are so sorry, but the encryption of your data has been successfully completed
so you could lose your data or
Pay two hundred and twenty two BTC like people even know what BTC is
Like you imagine if you got that and you don't have any you don't you're just starting from like wow
That's rough, then they put the address on there. You know what we could do if anybody in the chat room wants to screenshot this
Screenshot that and then go look up and see if any bitcoins were sent to that address. That's publicly available
Yeah, so that's how William. That's how we could find out if anybody paid it
Cuz are you true, so I'll leave that up there on the screen for a moment while we do this
So I guess there's only one address oh
Right because there's variants too. Yeah, I don't know necessarily
That's the only address, but you could at least look at that one and see if anyone paid to that one
I don't know if it changes not getting as much attention
But there's also a version for Windows called win 32 kill disk, so it's not just a platform everyone
Yeah, all your favorite side at least they're sorry about it. Yeah
They're so sorry actually we are so sorry, but the encryption
I like the cadence of it, too
We are so sorry comma, but the encryption of your data has been successfully completed comma
So you can lose your data or pay, and there's no commas or periods right there
It's all just like mixed messaging of sorry, but successful also
It's also nice that they have a contact email on maybe if we email them we can ask if anyone's paid
It's interesting look at this and then in grub on the lid on the on Linux
They rewrite grub so that the menu entries in grub are the error message so frustrating look at that. That's it so right there
It's in grub
We are so sorry
But the encryption of your data has been successfully completed so you can lose your data or pay and then it goes on
In and each line of the sentence is a grub menu entry for boot
That is that's a whole kind of awful
That's a kind of they have the they do have a technical analysis on the ESET blog
And it doesn't really go into though how they how they launch it though. What's kind of areas
Is that the one they do they reference the the telebot?
Infection that they reference in the
description of this one
There's an infection vector listed there
But the one that they're now talking about getting a lot of press for knowing no vector
Yeah, I mean I would assume under Linux you are somehow getting this on the machine now
Maybe it's getting put on there remotely through another vulnerability
But it would seem like more like a phishing attempt or something downloading it and then getting the user to execute it
Which for better or for worse is not as easy it is on Windows right? No, it's not
I mean, where are you because you would also likely have to market as executable because what what are you downloading from your browser?
Doesn't automatically mark things as executable. So are you getting people to plus X these things as well? How is this working exactly idea?
Yeah, you've got it's got to be
Distribute what I find interesting is they're seeding the key based on the time of the system and that's it
And so I wonder if based on the modification type of the file you couldn't like and guess what the key might be
Oh, yeah, so Rekai looked it up on blockchain. They've received one transaction
It looks like a test transaction because it's just zero point zero zero zero one BTC
Well, let's hope so they don't get any either
They haven't gotten any money that or they have lots of addresses or something
But yeah, so no one's paid that one at least which is the one that's all over news articles
So don't get tricked audience. Do not send your BTC. It's funny somebody sent it on December 30th
I
Might be might just be I wonder if you could trace this back if it was someone trolling them
What would be really funny is if you could trace that transaction back and then figure out who it is based on blockchain
So I don't really think anybody actually has to worry about this
But what really struck me was the amount of panic is at a whole new level
All kinds of all kinds of blogs about it. Like there was I don't know three or four
different articles by this weekend and now there's like a dozen articles written by today and none of them have any real substance and I
Don't know if anyone that's actually been affected in the wild
I mean it sounds the article implies like somebody was infected in the wild and their screenshots of it
So it's likely been run in testing, but I don't know. I don't know right? It's like there's no
Qualifications or evidence is to like is this any you know dramatically more popular than any of the other
I wonder if they found the Linux variant by first getting the Windows variant
Like I wonder if there's some connection that makes it easy to find the Linux one
After having the Windows one as a sample
Do you guys know I used to work in an antivirus company and they had a yeah
They had a whole isolated research division where they were trying to get infections and stuff all the time
Yeah, it was pretty cool. It was a real scam of an antivirus company, but
It was a bad one
It was I didn't really know at the time because like what did I know about Windows antivirus back then?
but I was in the IT department they ran all Linux and they ran asterix for their phone and
It's where I learned to use bacula. Oh, that's awesome
And I there's a wire I also learned a very I had a very quick crash course in network
Segmentation because they had like this they had this cool setup like they were off in this
Second half of the building where they didn't have their overhead lights on and they had lamps at their deaths
And and and they have their own network with its own internet connection. It was like this
It was like this truly cool and squadrant. Yeah. Yeah, very much. Oh, yeah
So that was my first experience with that kind of thing and it's that's how they do it right they get systems
I have lots of VMs and they would get infections and then they would go track that back. They would reverse the path and
Like William says a lot of times they'd start with a with a Windows one and they'd find that there's a Linux variant just by
Beginning the research of it not because it's necessarily getting actively excellent
It's very it feels like a million years ago
And I would have killed for a resource like Linux Academy back then Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
Go there to support the show and sign up for a seven-day free trial. That's madness
You could really just dive in and you really get it really get a sense of it engage with some of the live instructors
Enjoy the community stacked full of Jupiter broadcasting members
Have yourselves a little hands-on scenario based lab or an in-depth video or maybe use the core scheduler to match your busy schedule
We get lots of emails about certs
Lots of emails and they have courses created specifically to prepare you for exams
And they have this public profile section that I think is ideal for those of us that need to either
Prove to an employer that you're using your education time
Like I I for a long time worked at companies that gave me a budget every year to for education and this boom again
Perfect for that and you can use the public profiles to demonstrate the work
You've done also great to help clients understand what you're capable of or just to prove to yourself
I also appreciate the fact that they understand you don't always have hours and hours and hours to commit to this stuff
They give you the study tools you can download and take with you. That's awesome
They have mobile apps that you can take advantage of when you're on the go
They have nuggets with a little tiny bits of sparkly wisdom. Just a deep dive into a single topic
They have the learning paths and course schedulers to help work around your busy schedule
No cards to help you study up really quick. It is incredible
Incredible and to top it all off. They have that instructor mentoring and they're constantly adding new content
I just got an email from Anthony yesterday about a whole new slew of stuff going into Linux Academy
Check it out at Linux Academy comm
Slash unplugged Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and a big. Thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring this unplugged program
Talking about hardware. I mean Barton's really got me thinking about it. All right, and
I
Have this I have this sort of
kind of kind of
Casual eye on where Intel is going with these really small
x86 PCs and they've tried they keep trying to dip their toe in here
They've totally missed the boat on the mobile stuff and they keep trying to dip their toe in here kind of compete with the Raspberry
Pi and I think they might have something kind of interesting now this came up at CES and it's Intel's compute card
It's a PC that can fit in your wallet. It's intended to be a more versatile replacement for the compute stick
That hasn't really gotten a lot of traction
And I was I was kind of interested in the compute stick
But it really was a bear to put Linux on in fact
I think we bought one and tried and couldn't even get I can't remember but we don't have the specifics on the specs yet
But Intel reps say that it will have the performance of high-end fanless laptops like some MacBooks
The processors have a TDP of up to six watts, which could fit in these things, which is pretty nice
That's like a low-powered atom or even the M and Y series core i5 and i7 CPUs
So that's actually an i5 in my pocket. Yeah, they're gonna enough this
I'm not so sure of I guess this would have to take off but because it's Intel
They could probably just rev it into a chipset
Intel says that the card uses a variant of the USB C port called
USB C plus extension
Oh, it allows you to connect the system right in so you connect this to like say another PC
It allows you to connect right into the PCIe bus as well as the HDMI and DisplayPort video outputs
so they feel like it could be like a like a way to like really juice it up and
They estimate the compute stick will drop off their roadmap in 2018. Okay, and this will be what replaces it
It's an x86 based PC. It'll be available to run something called Windows
That sounds like something you put in your house and then also Linux
Basically any operating system you kind of put on the low-end PC in mid 2017 the Intel compute stick
It's interesting that they felt limited by the the connections available on the compute stick
I think that was one of their motivations to to move to this weird new USB. There's a new USB C era
I wonder if that hopefully it seems like they'll need that. They're a USB C plus extension to be compatible with other things
Because I could see it working if like, you know
The dong we really do start living in the dongle universe where there's dongles and docks and USB C things everywhere
Then yeah, sure
If you've got this thing in your wallet, then you show up and you plug in your one cord
Maybe this is the conversions device
Yeah
Anybody in the mummer room have thoughts on this particular type of form factor before we jump from this one's really cool as like a
smart card type thing
You could be your smart card was like your identity type information and like core information
You want to carry around your smart card could be your entire PC on that. Yeah. Well, not so much
But why not? It's not powerful enough for me. Yeah, I mean, I think some people could live with this
Yeah, I think that's a very small market right now. I think this is up to get more powerful
Yeah before most people can live with it. I agree. Yeah, it's still worse performing than even like the ARM Chromebooks
yeah, and I so I I I think I I think I'm like
I think I need at least a four core I
seven
As a minimum like 50 watt TDP process
Like a 50 watt TDP GPU, yeah, I look at those two core ones
I'm like, you know, you know Chris you could probably slum it and get away with an i5. Yeah, I maybe maybe I don't know
I don't know. I'm back to that precision line then one of the big trends out of CES this year is these
huge
Laptops, have you seen some of these? Yeah. Yeah, they're meant to be fancy crazy. Yeah with like dual power supplies and
22 inch curved screens in some cases and they're just that seems like a lot to look around
I feel like almost like 1820 pounds, which is ridiculous. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Is there a market like a briefcase?
Well, is this is this a huge is this a huge response to is this like a big backlash to?
the MacBook thing I
Know that you know, this was sort of in the making for years. That's what I feel like too. Yeah push this in any way
But they're not making these things as a folly, right?
They must they must believe that there is a customer base out there for these things. I'm thinking maybe
You know on set editing machines for you know, big productions and what have you could have er I know wimpy
You probably would doubt this
It's not gonna not gonna be for VR is it? I mean you blundering around
blinkered
wearing your nose bag
possibly running into
It's just not gonna happen but now I'm thinking I'm thinking, you know high-end editing machines
3d video creation tools that sort of stuff
I think with gaming GPUs being possible to integrate into laptops now
It's becoming more prevalent like your 1080s and your 1070s the desktop variants can be directly integrated into laptops and even water cooled
And that's yeah, I know so it's a crazy
Yeah
well
The 1080 series with the CPU slowing down and being fast enough and the GPUs sort of catching up in the mobile segment
Gamers are really interested in these devices and Asus makes one where you can dock it and it's water-cooled
So like the GPUs and everything are hooked up to water blocks and there are two outlets on the back
That hook up into a dock to give you more cooling when you're docked at your desk. Yeah
That is are you are you saying that there's a potential market there for pro gamers for these? Absolutely. Yeah
Wow, well, there you go. See at least that's a merging as a market
It may be that of course becoming a thing, of course
You're gonna be taking your rig anyway, and you know that that you know, and I've recently
I've recently been working with
4k footage that is it's it's compressed but it's a hundred megabits and
It makes my machine
chug
Just crying and as I'm you know
My my SSD gets like it's like eight nine hundred megabytes a second read and it's still when I'm skimming in the editor
100 megs a second. It can't keep up when I'm really jumping around
And then of course rendering that and all of that. It's becoming a it's big
I'm pushing that I'm pushing the limits of it and I could
Honestly, I don't need portability in my main editing machine other than I need to be able to edit
somewhere wherever I'm at right and I will you know, I can set up and I can plug in and I don't need hours of
Battery life, but I need unlimited disk and CPU and it doesn't make sense to have like a big desktop in the rig
Or anything that you could just have this and then still take it to this video
The other problem is when you're dealing with files like this is a day's worth of shooting now is 70 80 gigs
You probably need your fastest and then like a second disk at least with I'm every night
I have to offload to the NAS to make room for the next day's editing
Oh Chris a minute. Take a look at those laptops with the curved screens. Come on
I think that would be kind of cool Chris. Take a look at the link I son in the where's
Gx800 or the YouTube video. That's some that I gotta go go linked. Oh, jeez. I know yeah
That's what I was thinking about from Linus. Yeah, I don't I think they probably have a content
I did so yeah, they've actually had a similar model out in the past
There was a previous iteration that is very similar
I hope they don't content ID this but I think he actually says right here has to put it down because it's too heavy to
Hold yeah, it's super heavy
My arms tired yeah, it's
It has been funny watching that too bad. They all run Windows. Yeah, Bart needs to go talk to all those people
Tell them what's up?
To get one of these and then integrate Linux into it. Yeah, yeah, maybe I wonder if they would do
I wonder if they'd be up for something like I think these are from a clevo line like I think they could actually
Take these and fix them up these feel like this is a pretty bit like this feels like unless I'm misunderstanding
I understand professional gamers is a huge growing area which kind of blows my mind in its own right, but could they I just seems nuts
Okay, I guess just here's what I'm trying to go with this
Could there really be enough of a market that this many vendors are building machines this extreme and that there's like a gamble
I really don't think so. I think what Dale needs to make is really the thing that Razer is doing with a three monitor laptop
Days where you'd like to slide out monitors. Yeah, that's what I thought of when I saw that
Yep, although I don't think razor has any intention of actually ever shipping that at the moment
Oh, I have to get him bad. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, there's nine thousand dollars for some of those machines
Uni you want to jump in go ahead
Uni go on once are you muted uni? Sorry? Sorry? Oh, there you go. No, you're it's okay. Go ahead. Go ahead
All right, so I got Mario grip over on telegram here
He just wanted to let everyone know that no Ubuntu touch is not dead
Oh, yeah, the guy that runs you be ports. Yeah, we covered that on last
I don't know if anybody in here hint hint has any comments on it
But yeah, essentially it sounds like it's hiatus why we transition from or they
Transition from click packages to snap packages and then integrate it with the rest of the overall strategy fair
Fair I think I've said that before right? Yeah, it just makes sense to and it feels like the right time to do it
Yes, I was I almost made a prediction that canonical will drop mirror in
2017 but then I just decide now they're too far. They're too far
But wouldn't that wouldn't that make everybody's mouth drop if they just said I you know what?
We think we can get what we need to weigh land for us. Yeah, that would be a great news week for us
Yeah, I almost made that prediction but yeah
I know that a lot of people are reacting about Ubuntu phone a lot of what I'm seeing is hope saw that common
you know real armchair kind of stuff, but I think it's extremely practical at this stage and
It it would be it would be awkward to have this division with click packages and snap packages
Especially with so much momentum in the company behind snap packages
And if you wanted to make the case for like Linux users to move over
Here's the whole little bit different of an ecosystem that you have to learn
Sorry, it's not just a bunch of on your phone that you're used to. Yeah, it's
It is it's too bad that it hasn't gotten more traction
I would have liked to have seen a few solid US options. I I
really, you know, I've I've I've exhausted myself talking about about about mobile at this point, but I think
long-term it just seems to make the most sense anyways, like if if you're not afraid to be a little embarrassed in the short term and
you have the
Fortitude to stick with it over the long term seems like the better route to go. Yeah, just my
Estimation. All right, Wes. Well, I want to talk about a couple of things
I said I was gonna I said I said I would confirm two predictions
I've only confirmed one prediction this one more to go. I got one more to I know I know
So before we get into that, I want to thank digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged program
Did you know that digital ocean is a thing and it's a thing that will change your life
That's true. Yeah unplugged
Do unplug it a $10 credit it go create the account then you apply it do unplugged
It is it is really something I guess I probably if you've heard these spots and you've never gone and actually pulled the trigger
I don't really need to tell you something you haven't heard before you probably are aware that it's a simple easy way to get started
To create a Linux rig up in the cloud and their data centers all over the world all SSD based super fast great UI
super nice API
Solid set of documentation some of the best on the web really straightforward pricing and our release available
That's oh and basically any distro you'd ever want to choose from and if they don't have the one you'd want
You know, which one I'm talking about
There's a little birdie that tells me with that HTML 5 console you can make it happen
I'm not saying that and I'm definitely not putting that in the spot
So cut all that out, but I'm just saying there's a thing you can do. They have an HTML 5 console
It's a powerful thing from post to boot check it out at digital ocean comm use the promo code deal and plug now
You know where you know, you know how you can use digital ocean if there is any tasks you can do
That doesn't require a GUI if there's anything you can do on the command line
You could use a digital ocean droplet for it pretty much
You got something you need to download in the background. You want to host some torrents?
I mean I'm talking simple stuff for average everyday users
Digital ocean works for you
If you want to build the back end infrastructure for your business or in our case for your live streaming infrastructure to send it off
To scale engine and YouTube and you stream and bippity bops and records here's and maybe a Twitter account
Maybe a twitch channel one day you gotta use, you know
I could assure I guess I could have a big old rack that I'm running hardware out of all the time like an animal
Or I take advantage of their entire Linux infrastructure using KVM for the virtualizer SSDs for the storage
Oh, and did I mention 40 gigabit e connections right into them hyper visors? They're doing it, right? I
Mean, yeah, I guess I could spend all of my time building that and get like one per not even 1% of what they got
I mean, it's really come on. It's a as the Borg would say it is a futile maneuver
Go over to digital ocean comm use the promo code do unplugged. It's one word
it's lowercase smack your leg when you're saying it apply it to your account and
Thank you to digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged program. I
Am not proclaiming that the Mac is dead
I'm not proclaiming that Linux is going to become the champion of 2017. I am simply saying
That a lot of long time Mac users developers
technical workers are abandoning the platform and
We have yet another blog this week. And these are one of many examples
we have one last week to the title is from OS 10 to Ubuntu and
It's a fascinating read. It's good. If you're looking to switch yourself
I won't go through all of it
But I did highlight a couple of the interesting bits and then I want to talk a little bit more about some of the data
We have so he says I was a Linux user ten years ago, but moved to a Mac one
Mainly because I was tired of maintaining an often broken system looking at X org
Yeah, man
And all Apple had a quite appealing offer at the time a well-maintained Unix platform with beautiful hardware good UX and access to editor
apps I like like Photoshop and
office
The trigger was pulled when Apple though for him to switch when Apple announced the 2015 MacBook line with strange
Connectivity decisions like having unique ports for everything and using strange dongles
You know if they're if their top-notch hardware started to turn weird
It was probably time to look elsewhere and now I've seen the latest MacBook Pro line escape key was removed
I'm kind of comforted in my decision
He's also recently joined Mozilla at the storage team and saw lots of colleagues happily using Linux
They weren't struggling with anything in particular oddly enough. It seemed like they were capable working efficiently both at work and for their personal stuff
so in this case our author buys a Lenovo x1 carbon and
Started transitioning over to Linux chose Ubuntu right away because previously that's what the developer used and stuck with the unity desktop
Everything worked right away
Nothing really needed to be messed with including Bluetooth and external display unity is going fine
The last batch of OS 10 apps are that he really liked are not available on Linux
But so far most equivalents have been found
For the most part the web is your app store. That was an interesting observation
I mean, I think we've talked about that before but he's he's definitely right that ten years ago today
There's a lot more that you can do online. You just don't have to worry about on Linux
Yeah
And this is there's still some web apps than error that don't you know don't live up to the app and up to snuff and so
There's some type of specific tasks and native apps that are still more efficient or better integrated than what the web has
finds a unity launcher to be sufficient and
Has looked at to Albert and synapse file managers talk, you know talks about all that
but I guess I'll end it with the conclusion because you can read the rest talks in here about using
Dark table and and all of that gaming music. It's a really fantastic video editing password management
It's a fantastic
Post but so is Linux ready for the desktop for me?
The answer is yes, the author concludes and will be sticking with Linux
And Nicola's I believe is how you say his first name
This is like I guess we could I am I won't I won't keep doing this
I won't keep reading all of these blog posts every year or I mean every week as these come out
But I wanted to read it this week because it goes in combination with another report that's come out
Greg over at computer world is reporting on this that according to net applications who constantly reports on this stuff all the time
Apple's mac OS is
Is beginning to decline from seven percent actually actually peaked at nine point six percent
But now it's down to six point one percent
Yeah, so I guess it was down seven percent from a year ago. That's actually a decent drop-off
Now you're wondering about Linux Linux user share is at two point two percent
It peaked at two point three percent in November in those new MacBooks came out
And a Linux first cracked the two percent barrier back in June of 2016 and now we're sitting at two point two percent
So nice little growth curve for little there Linux. So um, I
Present you a case West in my am I looking for evidence of
upset in the Mac community and then coming to Linux or do you think we are witnessing the
Slow new trickle of Mac exodus users coming over Linux. Am I right or am I looking for trouble?
No, I think you're right
I mean if anything I think you've been a little bit cautious in that there are always those people who are doing that switch
There's always you know, and there's a lot of for a lot of people who it's kind of easy to be like well
Yeah, it works for me. I think what's unique now is that we're seeing people who had a lot of them were previously unit Linux users
They've dabbled in it
Some of them have tried over the years to switch or you know have one Linux system and then have to use
Their OS X so I think what the difference is we're seeing people who you know, this is like their main workstation
This is their main work laptop that kind of thing
And now the kind of folks Barton is targeting exactly and it does feel like there's like a a zeitgeist changed where now
Linux is a real option for in their minds again
Yeah, and I think it there's there's also sort of this sort of belay setting in over the situation with some of the previous vendors
Mm-hmm. I think it's a whole interesting storm. All right, that's it. I'm done. I'm just saying I think this is a good trend
For Linux in general. I think maybe I've beaten this horse now. We'll check back in in some months. Yeah
Yeah, simmer and exactly exactly because for all I know in a couple of weeks. They'll all realize they hate Linux
Yeah
They all can start writing post Linux is the worst
How I tried to switch to Linux and it blew up in my face and I came rounding back to the Mac like that could be
The post and they all end up buying Mac Pro trash cans
We'll really eat our words. Yeah, that's right. Ww you want to jump in go ahead. Yeah, I'm thinking that maybe
Professionals and the people who really use those big machines that are tired and they're they're moving away from it
They're moving away from it because as work
workloads get you know bigger like
Video professionals and photography professionals are gonna be dealing with higher and higher images
They need something that's cutting edge that can do the work that they need to do it
No work on two-year three-year old hardware. That's last generation
and
That could be pushing them to move to you know, besides openness of Linux, which is yeah much better
I I so I think too when it comes to business, you know, they specifically like predictability to a degree as well
I mean, there's there's there's obviously constraints on that
but you know as a business you you you sometimes build a workflow around certain hardware features and
For a lot of professionals the loss of the SD card reader, even though the thing doesn't doesn't it's not required
It's not necessitated by thickness requirements because the reader is tiny and then it's as thin as an SD card
it is but that's that one thing is a major blow to the digital video workflow because
essentially a lot of like the the Canon cameras and even Sony cameras and Nikon cameras have standardized on SD, right so when you're shooting it with
Photography or shooting video on these cameras and then you go to sit down and import it
You always have SD cards you need to work with and you don't want one more dongle that you're dragging around
You already have the giant camera bag and the laptop this seems like a small example
but this on this unknown quantity with when it comes to Apple hardware where
One one line of one line has this feature and then the next iteration on it all of a sudden removes it and now that's
in a dongle it's this unpredictability of when it's gonna get updated and how much that's gonna cost and
There's also just the fact that businesses are looking at these things and going well, what am I getting from my purchase here?
This is an $8,000 computer when I when I build it. What am I getting out of this?
I think all of those things add up
All right, anything else from the mumble room before we officially consider this closed top unless something interesting develops
We're gonna consider this topic closed for the unplugged program going once
Going twice and poppy. I secretly use Arch Linux. Thank you on a macbook though, so it's fine. Yeah, ha ha ha ha
He doesn't actually, he secretly uses Ubuntu Mate, but we'll just call it that
Yeah, it's not so secret anymore
Alright, that'll bring us to the end of this week's unplugged. We're gonna get out here a little early this week
because once this show ends we redress the set and
And the next episode of tech snaps getting recorded check out Wes on the new tech snap what?
Yeah, also recording on Tuesdays after unplugged at least for now
So you can show up listen to the unplugged program live hang out stick around and catch a live tech snap
How about that for a double ender?
Thank you for joining us this week
You can find all of our live times at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar our subreddit at Linux action show at reddit comm our contact
Page at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact and follow the network on Twitter at Jupiter signal. Thanks for being here
We'll see you next week
You