I don't love this like your discords out of date
I won't I know that shit is and especially especially why so that hit me on arch
And here's what happened
I was I was on air and I asked the discord room a question and then
Went down to my second desktop realized discord wasn't open which it normally is like oh crap well
Let me just go launch that really quick. Oh nope. Sorry you must update well, okay
It can't auto-update because I installed it using pac-man, so let me update it via the packer
Yeah, and nope can't do because of course dependencies are missing well
Let me install that dependency real quick nope can't do that because that conflicts is something else you have installed
So here I am on air doing a show trying to get discord installed on arch, and I'm like
Yeah, I'm gonna install solace hey
Well speaking about the one on solace
And we got basically a warning on reddit from someone who's like there's a new discord out the one that you have
It's just stopped working. We're like wait. Well if you pull the Skype. Yeah, so you just can't get into any words all right
Yeah, we'll go update it this needs libc++. Okay. Oh, we don't have that
Which normally wouldn't be a problem, but libc++ is part of LLVM, and if you know anything about LLVM
It takes hours to build
Like it literally takes hours like you the way that we do the build it also has clang it has LLVM
Now has a libc++ LLDB
LLD all of that in a single tree, and it's also got to build it to 32-bit as well
All because I was like yeah, we're gonna use libc++ now
Why so just why the the quick fix on solace these days, which is a sudo snap install discord
Oh, it is a snap. Yeah, very good. I should have done that on arch. We didn't have snap either
We were screwed this is Linux unplugged episode 210 for August 15th 2017
Oh
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's literally reloading its Linux right before the show starts
My name is Chris. My name is Wes and hello Beardsley welcome back. Hello guys
We got a really good show lined up today
We have of course a few things to follow up on from last week, but before I address those
We've got to talk about a big birthday today. We got a big big birthday in the community
We have not one not two
But three awesome app picks for you guys in this week's episode just some really cool open source projects that need a little attention
And then the Internet's buddy I key has stopped by the program today to chat about solace 3
snap and flat pack support in solace and I might have a little thing or two to say about it as well
Then we're gonna do a little follow-up on the slack wear challenge. It turns out it turns out
I've been using slack wear a little more since the show and I have a couple of more things to say about it
This is probably the point of which we should say this week. We decided we are going to we're gonna punt the gen 2 challenge
Just because neither one of us felt like we spent enough time with it
There's a lot there and I and and part of my part of my problems
I kept using slack wear for a little while and then I'm doing good
I was like, okay, I'm ready to I'm ready to just really get into gen 2 and then that son of a gun I key
Hashtag blame. I key goes and releases a brand new version of solace. Oh, which I I immediately I immediately this morning
I'm how down on all of your USB drives automatically. I have it right here on this thumb stick, right?
That's the thumb stick right there and I I loaded it up on my main
Airmaster machine that we use to send every every all the images and play all the clips and stuff out to the stream
So I loaded solace 3 and I'll tell you about it why I decided to go with solace for my arch
Replacement on this machine and all of that
So I think we just have a ton of really good stuff to get into really excited about the community news the app picks and haven't wimpy
Here and I key are both back. I can't wait to chat with those guys. So let's start right there time-appropriate greetings virtual lug
greetings
Hello, it's good to see everybody. I guess it's probably pretty well known by now
I sort of snuck up on me. But today is gnomes 20th
birthday
Happy frickin 20th birthday gnome. That's impressive. There have been 33 stable releases since gnome 1.0 in
1999 god damn, I am old. Holy crap. You mean I was using Linux. I was using Linux before gnome
I guess that's that's Wow, that really makes me feel old
Anyways, 20 years 20 years of gnome is being celebrated right now and a website's been set up
Happy birthday gnome org and they also have a handy donate to gnome button there and they have a timeline where the project really got
Started in 1997 which is about when I started become a and they've got that handy-dandy gnome 1.0 virtual machine if you want to relive
Yes, Lori. Look at this screenshot, too
You know, I remember I remember thinking how badass it was that the icons and the menus had textures like the gnome foot and the toolbox
They had like textured backgrounds. I thought that was so cool
I
Mean I would look just fine on your slack wear red Chris and isn't that isn't that don't they call that that?
That theme on the control bars there. Don't they call that crux? Isn't that called?
I mean, that's where that's what I think of when people say crux
Anyways, they have a nice nice timeline at happy birthday gnome org
So yeah, so what's interesting about that is there are other projects that I use today
That are older than no like wine wine for example is older than gnome
Isn't that something and of course Gwadek just wrapped up and you can find all of the videos from Gwadek up on YouTube
there's probably a couple that would be worth watching probably a couple that aren't and I
Don't know. It's just a it's kind of a big milestone. Of course today's the day. I also switched off no
But I'm still using the hell out of GTK so there you go
I also I just before we go any further wanted to say next week might be might be just in studio Bearden West
I'm not sure everything should be fine
But I am going down to that to the solar eclipse in Oregon and I'm starting to like a little bit
Get worried about the amount of people that are going to that thing. Yeah, so it could be a different show next week
I may be here
I may not meet up comm slash Jupiter broadcasting if you're gonna get your butt out to the Eclipse in the Oregon area and want
To meet up with us. That's that should be pretty good meet up comm slash Jupiter broadcasting
And then if nothing else, I should make it back in time
To the show, but what I'm worried about is because I'll be traveling
I still might not really get enough time to fully deep dive into gentoo. Okay, so I'm like me
No, I'm like worried that we might need to do a double punt which I feel bad about but at the same time like the audience
Has been asking for a gentoo challenge
So long deserves to be a good one right that's what I figure it's like if I so this week I ended up I ended
Up playing around with slack wear and then jumped over to solace and like well, wait a minute
I was supposed to I didn't really gentoo like I got gentoo started
I got a machine cleared off and I got like that process all started
But I didn't really go much further than just getting started. I'm like, well, I need to run it as a desktop
No long compiles. Yeah, it's okay
It's gonna take you about two weeks to compile Katie. I'm gonna put it
I'm gonna put it on that $10,000 Dell laptop and I'm just gonna let that thing rip through the
If it does half as good as it does as an encoding video, I think I think I'm gonna be fine
So anyways, that'll be so that could be maybe we're gonna punt then the gentoo challenge for two weeks
But then I was thinking that's not necessarily a hundred percent bad because that gives people time to try it out, too
Yeah, like what do you think beer you want you want to do it?
Yeah, I don't even in a little virtual machine I like using my
I just asked to have a good laugh cuz I knew what you were gonna say
I didn't even need to really ask I knew what the answer was
Anybody in the mumble room want to do a gentoo challenge with us?
Can I claim to be above it
Everybody else is busy getting things done
You bastard West you brought this upon us you brought this upon me you dirty dog you dirty dog
You called me out it during the outro music of last week's episode. The music was already playing. I mean I had to say yes
actually, it's kind of a good it's kind of a perfect timing to because
it's gonna be in a way going back to my roots and
That's kind of ideal when I'm sort of I'm distro shopping right now and right now
I'm seriously considering leaving solace on the air master machine doesn't necessarily mean that's where I want to use like that's that
LTS Ubuntu has been working great for that and this just it could work great for OBS. So
Times they are a change. So yeah, happy birthday to gnome
Sorry, you guys know gentoo challenge
But we got plenty of other stuff to talk to with I key here and all of that
Did you also see beard that there is a new release of OBS today OBS 20? I think it is came out today
I just saw the download come. I just saw the update come down
Yeah, it's OBS 20 just come down and one of the things they're adding is like a totally dynamic
Re-shuffable UI
It's just really it's really they're really that is an open source project that is getting it must be huge in the twitch
Yeah, it's just getting huge. Yeah, it's like every point release adds like a bunch of useful new things
yeah, and I was just looking again for a new webcam and
Like a Logitech webcam and on the box now, they're listing OBS support. Oh, that's that's really cool
That's big for the OBS project like Logitech's putting that on the box like so congrats to them
So OBS 20 came out today
Lots of new features if you're looking for a way to do a screen cap and live stream it or even just record it to
A file and maybe also attach a mic into a voiceover the lower third
You know if you just want to even produce an instructional video for work
You could do it in real time and OBS
Instead of instead of putting it together slowly in an editor just do it live
Go through the process like say you're you know
You want to you want to convey some to another another co-worker how to do something on a server?
Just screen cap it with OBS and record the whole thing with attach your mic
And then you have an mp4 file and give it to them and you don't have to use it to live stream your podcast network
You can use it for all kinds of things. Yeah, that's a great point be the next big twitch streamer and
And it's it's really gotten to be super competitive as somebody who's followed, you know these applications for years now and pay thousands and thousands
And thousands of dollars into alternative software
Wirecast um, I mean you can remember back when like you
Couldn't quite switch yet. And now oh, yeah come so far and now here there with version 20. Yeah, we've come so far
I'm so proud of them. So anyways, you can check that out too. So lots of good stuff, but we do have some apps
I thought maybe we get into some of these so let's
Let's take a moment to thank Linux Academy for sponsoring the program Linux Academy comm slash unplugged
It's a platform to learn about Linux built by Linux enthusiasts and it's it really shines because it's all they do
It's what they focus on is Linux and everything around it from the low-level stuff up to the big topic stuff
They have all kinds of different courseware
Depending on what you're going for if you want something that's self-paced and in-depth
This is perfect
If you want something that can automatically nudge you a little bit to meet your goals
They've got that too. If you just want to get some certifications
They have courses created specifically for that and check out this thing. They've recently posted. I don't know if you saw this Wes
build your own
Linux.com. Oh, it's a site that Linux Academy's put up. I don't know exactly when it's new to me
so I think it's kind of new and it is a rundown of how to completely build Linux from scratch using just
the tools that come with the operating system and it's just a
Fantastic way to learn what all this stuff does how it's all put together
It's just it's I mean, it's brilliant. You could go, you know, you could go
Do Linux from scratch or got to Gentoo? That's also an extremely really educational process
But the nice thing about this is that it's recent. It's up-to-date. It's well formatted. It's well written and it's extensive
Yeah, it's long. It's you'll spend a while doing this
Yeah, and they and they have it in they've broken it down into what our major sections
So they have six major sections and then they have individual
Like subcategories in there. This is really this is a massive post so you can find it at buildyourownlinux.com
I mean these guys and cows are really really just intensely passionate about Linux
That's why they started Linux Academy and you can sign up at linuxacademy.com
Slash unplugged sign up for a free seven-day trial and support the show linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
Thank you everybody for visiting there even just go in there and read it more about Linux Academy
You know, let's him know you heard about it here linuxacademy.com slash unplugged
Everybody loves KDE connect even gnome users are cut KDE connect, right?
So this is why I was kind of interested to see M connect integration and KDE connect integration for gnome shell V and extension. Ah
Yes, very very good the KDE connect is a
Great app met the developer just really smart guy and just a really handy application
We just talked about it recently as a way to dictate text into your into your Linux box
Of course, it allows file sharing notification sharing sending of text messages all other kinds of features
like media playback control and whatnot and
there is now an extension that takes all those features of KDE connect and builds them in in a real gnome like way and
It it does all the other kind of stuff you'd expect like if you send files
I'll use Nautilus to do the file transfers. It'll mount the share the phone in Nautilus and
It can use if you have your online account connected to Google it can use your Google account contacts to autocomplete SMS messages
This is so cool. This is a full-fledged KDE connect integration with gnome shell first. No musers
Well, I'm you know musers going to have to try that
I'll have a link in the show notes Wes if you would like to indulge you can check it out
And then well now we're getting to some of these app picks here. So that was the first one now
How about one for everybody Windows users?
Well
You gotta wait a little bit, but everybody else Linux and Mac users you're good
You are good. If you would like to try out alacrity
Alacrity Wes. It's got a powerful name alacrity
It is it is the fastest terminal emulator in existence
It uses all claim it uses the GPU for rendering and why wouldn't it Wes?
I mean you're sitting there with your terminal just wasting your GPU away
Why wouldn't it Wes so alacrity is everyone has videos to render Chris?
They just want to use their GPUs for something. It makes sense. Yeah. Yeah, you got me just sitting there doing nothing
It's a cross-platform. I suppose if you have the free stuff to it work. It's a cross-platform
Terminal based on simplicity and performance you got all you got a leg out like a thousand lines of text scrolling across your screen
leg no more my friends it
It's also available for a solace users and Ubuntu arched fedora. So can I watch a movie in this terminal now?
Wait now do you want it to be ASCII?
No
It's GPU accelerated. Why can't it paint an image over the terminal?
Maybe you could submit a suggestion is a written in rust to kind of looks like yeah
I believe in mention, you know what? You're right. I should always mention when it's right
Should everything I don't know if you should but you see by default, but I oh really? Yeah
Yeah, maybe I just love pushing buttons of rust lovers and if you sudo snap install alacrity dash dash edge
You can install it
Look at that fan to waste this thing has solace build instructions. Yeah, that's what I was interested before then
But no tell me more isn't that something right there? Isn't that somehow?
Yeah, they thought I mean, I knew it had to be roast because that first line. Mm-hmm
They maybe maybe they just figure solace users are the type that might want a GPU
Accelerated terminal because you know, that's gonna be triggering some some listeners out there what I'm sorry
What a GPU accelerated terminal? What is it written in an electron? No, it's rust. Calm down
Well, I might just have to package it
Reading the the about here. It sounds like they're taking the the gnome approach of
removing
features though
Because it says the simple tab goal means that it has no tabs. Yeah, and
It doesn't have such niceties as like a GUI
Configuration editor. Nope. Nope, it doesn't. However, it does have a nice yaml file
It's easy to follow and with good saying defaults once your GPU accelerated
Why would I want a GUI when I just use my super fast terminal to edit my text file configs?
Yeah, I mean it's obvious. This is this is the way I mean
Shh, why else this is alacrity and it's up on github if you'd like to check it out. I actually think it's
It's kind of cool. It's kind of it's actually building it. Are you?
Man, it's even available on BSD. Oh
Really?
Well, I mean they are dead west so they kind of put themselves in the crapper
Anyway, I did I didn't know they had 3d acceleration on BSD now
They must be doing that to the Linux emulation layer probably I would imagine I
I was I was I
Was just teasing BSD guys. You don't have to write me
All right
So that's alacrity and we'll have a link to that in the show notes and then are you ready for your third?
Look how fast we're going through these you guys amazing. We are really doing a good clip
You heard in the show out. So I was uh, I was I started a journey. I
Mentioned I would mentioned I stuck around on slack where I was trying out trying out the plasma desktop. I was trying out
I also tried installing the latest plasma desktop packages on arch before I reloaded air master from arch
so then I've been thinking about
What producer Michael has been saying to me for four months now is he talks about how he has a plasma desktop setup
That's it's actually very kind of gnomish, but it it's plasma
And so I was thinking about like toying with that idea
Is that something I could really do is that something I could sit down and get a nice clean minimal plasma desktop
But still have you know that the performance of kwin and the the the tools and of like I like ksnapshot a lot
Console is one of my favorite terminals and you know like a lean kind of run and config. Yeah, so
during this process which eventually
Completely backfired on me, but we'll get to that in a moment. But during this process I landed on
Latte doc now I have become a doc denier. I am a doc denier these days. I
I I've got my gnome favorites, you know that come up and that's a doc I suppose but I'm just I'm overdocs
They're an awkward use of screen real estate
They they often are dumb like they hide even even even though they call them tele hide and stuff like that
They hide when I don't want them to hide and you know
They're just dumb and it's like we've kind of half all gravitated to just you could mash the super key and then you know
Yeah application. Yeah, you know really these days I all what I wanted what I want is I want something that lists
What my running applications are graphically and lets me click between them and I want something that kind of outlines what virtual desktops
I have and bonus points if I can tell what applications are in those virtual desktops, and I really just need something that
Stays out of my way because I'm not really using it to launch new applications
I'm not even gonna probably except for a core set of applications
I don't need anything even pinned in it because it like you said I searched I you know, just run it
So anyways in this process, I came across latte doc and it's a doc based on plasma frameworks
That is pretty nice. It is it's it's animated a little heavily for me by default, but you can turn that down and it has
a
Pretty good tweak system that lets you set things that you would normally want to set for a doc and a really smart intuitive
Way like what what edge it's on
How it behaves how you add separators it it was nice and you can right-click and you can lock things
It it's not one of these docs that prevents you from getting to the action items of a doc
So like if I right-click on Chrome
I still see open new instance opening cognito window from the dock you can somehow put applets down there
Although I didn't figure that out. It has really kind of a smooth feel to it. I was able to crash it a couple of times
So I inevitably ended up to not to decide not to use it on my machine
It's on the air, but I really felt like if I was gonna go back to a doc
Latte doc would be the one
It really felt like a it felt like a it wasn't like too compromised it but it wasn't
Overly done. It wasn't it wasn't overly built
It was just it was just really kind of smooth and straightforward
It has a couple of really nice features in the version that just came out four days ago version 0.7
Oh, it has a wayland support preview, which is probably a good direction to go
It has a new layout editor, which I liked quite a bit. There is a new dynamic background
option that dynamically switches when a window is maximized versus
Windowed which just makes it look really nice. And that's pretty sounds like yeah, there's there's all little things. They've added that
Oh, oh, oh, I should probably mention this because my favorite one an audio streams indicator is now built into the dock
Oh, yes, you could increase decrease volume or even mute volume right from the top
Yeah that I really appreciate it. Maybe ducks are making their way back
That's latte doc latte doc for you plasma desktop users. I
Think it's pretty good. And so I
got plasma desktop install and I got it configured and I got a latte doc set up but
You know
It just doesn't it doesn't quite click with me
It doesn't there's something about the cute
applications the complicated aspect of them that a lot of the little tweaking that I was gonna have to do and I was doing this an
hour before the show started
Not in your tweekiest mood. I
Yeah, yeah, I ended up I ended up
deciding to just take the solace plunge and I
I went and grabbed the budgie ISO and I etched that to a to a thumb drive put it in the machine installed it
just just cleared out my old partitions and left my data partitions alone and
Just went all-in on budgie right now. So we're set up. I'm on the live stream. I'm on Firefox 55, too
So it's not only that I switched to solace, but I switched to Firefox
Why would you want to stay still that's just no
You know for me it was it was sort of the best of both worlds because I like the GTK applications
I I am very familiar with gnome settings and those settings applets. So they for me
It's just sort of a nice sort of familiarity
I like the new art and and look that we're gonna talk about a little bit in the new version of soul
So that's the other thing. Of course. It's a new release as well came out today
So those all kind of played a role but for me what it finally was is it just seemed like
Well, I'm gonna take a I'm gonna take a little bit of a gnome breather
But this is a good stepping stone because it's it's all of the GTK apps that I know and love
It's all of the themes and icon sets that I know and love comfortable with
Yeah, super comfortable with the terminal comfortable with all that stuff. I'm I've even learned to use current Nautilus
files
But it's it's things like it's mutter and it seems like the the size of gnome shell and all of these things that I've just added
To it over time. It's not even necessarily all gnomes fault
and so but the budgie desktop was sort of this nice sort of stepping stone to not completely switching away from GTK, but
Because sort of stepping away from some of the things have been causing me issues recently to wean you off of it
Yeah, and so latte doc doesn't really have a spot on on a GTK desktop so much
But if you were if I was gonna go to a plasma desktop
I think I would I would consider replacing the main panel that the plasma desktop uses
Yeah, but so we do need to talk about solace though. That's the way I think we have
We've talked enough about community updates and app picks
but if you want to see any of those things we talked about today, we have links in the show notes latte doc also kind of
cool is one of those
Useful plasma applications that you can actually just install from the from the plasma store quote-unquote
And I and it's kind of sort of distro agnostic
Which is which is pretty cool
So you can just you don't necessarily have to go find the show notes
You could just search around in the plasma desktop or whatever. They call it store and install it there
How about that was that so easy? How's your build going? It's still building. Is it? Well, I think I'm installing
I'm still a bunch of rust dependencies now. It's a wild ride
Good good. Well, I'm glad see I got I have installs going in the background right now. You've got installs
This is one of those episodes where we're all users. Damn it. Yeah, we're installing our software while we do the show today
And y'all hey, that's what's part of the fun
That's why we do it fresh open-source software right at our love. We love drunk on the power
We love it
and you know what there's more and more software coming and some of them are getting wrapped up now in these universal package formats and
Aiki and the souls project just announced support for snaps along with flat packs which already existed
But it's not just like baby support. It's full grown-up proper sandboxed support
So we're gonna talk about that with him and we're gonna pick mr
Whippers whimpers his brain as well because I believe there was a little cross collab involved to get some of that stuff working
So I want to figure out what all of that was and get the scoop on that
So let's take a moment and thank digital ocean digital ocean comm go over there
Create your account and then use our promo code of ultimate power do unplugged do
Unplugged one word will give you a ten dollar credit over that digital ocean comm now
They got a five dollar rig five dollar rig for five dollars
You could run that rig two months for free with our promo code do unplug cuz I got a five dollar rig
That's nuts. I can't even get a burger for five dollars. I might be able to get the fish sandwich for five dollars
But what you know you want to?
Exactly, but you know what that five dollars much better spent over digital ocean premium
You can spin up a droplet in less than 55 seconds all SSDs for the hard drives 40 gigabit connections coming to the hypervisor
Linux for the server they have KVM for that hypervisor, which is brilliant
They have a dashboard for days
That's super easy to use they have an API that straightforward brilliant
And it's so well developed that they use it themselves to build their own
Systems on top of digital ocean then they have all kinds of really crazy advanced features like block storage
And they're working on object storage right now
They have firewalls that deploy at the network level so the traffic you want to reject never even reaches your system
They have load balancing as a service
Monitoring alerting where you get metrics and alerts when things go down and of course they have entire stacks of pre-built
Open-source applications ready to go with a single click or you know you just build it from scratch yourself
I was gonna say does that sound too easy. Don't worry. Just install free
What you're doing and you'll have it
Yeah, if you get stuck you just email those BSD now guys
This is the way I go is when I'm just trying out something like either for the show
Or I want to play with something or a new release of a distro comes out that I want to throw on a server
They have a three cents an hour machine three cents an hour machine easy to justify that is that is and then find some
Spare change in your couch. Yeah, throw it on the floor well deal unplugged
Yeah, you get the $10 credit you could run that three cents an hour you get that for quite a while
And you know you could you could destroy and create a couple of machines in that time. It's great
It's just so much fun to play around with to or to put it in production
They got data centers all over the world so you get something nice and fast wherever you your users are at
DigitalOcean.com use the promo code do unplugged big
Thank you digital ocean also while you're over there go over to their community section and look at the open source projects
Built around digital ocean digital ocean calm use the promo code do unplug
So I key welcome back to the show sir it is really good to talk to you
And I don't think you've been on the show since you've gone full-time either although
We talked right before you did go full-time, but congrats on the transition. It looks like time has been well spent
Congratulations
Solus 3 is out, and I got it loaded right here on my machine
And we look it is looking really great, so I I guess let's start there cuz that's like the big
That's like the big story. I noticed that you got Firefox 55 in the sucker and man is that fast, but
I didn't realize this before and I guess last time I tried souls
I just maybe didn't notice or I forgot but Solus 3 is using the Linux LTS kernel and
That was actually what pushed me over the edge because I've been thinking more and more about using
LTS core stuff for our production machines
but having faster moving applications like Chrome and OBS and
So when I saw the fact that I could pin it to LTS, which is the default
I could use current, but it was it was pinned to LTS. It's default on the existing ones
So so in the new ones it's so we have two kernel branches
I mean back in the old days pre-clear bit manager
We just had one kernel and it sucked and if you updated you were screwed
And then we spent ages. I mean basically it updated the same way as our trying
We know how that goes. My modules are gone. It was that same story
But nowadays we have the next current Linux LTS the next LTS basically follows a great branch
So that's gonna update again in September to 4.14 and then it's gonna stay on that for a long time
Yeah, and then it'll update again
So users can now freely have them both installed and then they can go between them
We've got all the Nvidia drivers for both of them as well. So you can quite happily you don't have to build them
There's no DKMS none of this
You know pixie blood crap, dude. You haven't got to go through that so you can just pick every one of them
This new ISO is defaulting to the Linux current branch
Which is basically the stable kernel most of the time, right?
But there might be times when we say and we don't want to update it. So we're not gonna call it Linux
So are you saying with clear root manager you made the switch from shipping LTS is default to shipping current is default
No
Yes, I know so the the ISO itself is now using the Linux current package
Which means it's on four point twelve point seven, right?
But because we now use clear boot manager you can use either we can have any current
What I opted to do which I think is great because and then all the envy of the you have the appropriate Nvidia packages to
Match up. So it was just really easy. Yeah, it was really straightforward
Nice, so okay. So I just that was something I really like okay now, you know what?
I'm gonna do the LTS kernel. I'm gonna go with that
So let's talk about some of the stuff that's in that kernel that that made snap packages possible
Let's start there
Maybe because I think didn't you have to make some pretty low-level changes for the sandboxing support must have required at least app armor
Yeah, so that basically there are there are app armor patches that have gone up for four point thirteen and four point fourteen
The canonical guys are very diligent in getting all that stuff upstream
But you know that that stuff does take time a fair amount of it has gone upstream
But it's it's not all there. So for the two kernels, I've back parted from
Zesty and artful. I've basically back parted their implementations of app armor, which are the future upstream ones
Which means that solace is now using the exact same implementation of app armor that a bunch of is using that's bad
Which also means that we're the only over dish at the time of saying this
I want to be very specific about that at the time of saying this we're the only non-abundant to the next distribution to have
full snap confinement
Like as a like for like with a bun too, right? That's awesome. Well, there'd be a nine has it as well
Well shipped
How did this come about so
Um, okay. Well, it's his fault. Well, I thought so but I mean you're also
You have your position has evolved on this but for some people listening to this show though
They'll remember you as the anti flat pack anti snap guy
Yeah, I mean
I'm you know, like a whole thing about having the angel and devil in your ears, right? Sure
Wimpy has become the the angel in the air and I've got about four of my own devils in here the whole time, but
When we first decided on it
I mean
it was it was a long time ago when the whole debate started coming about and it took a long time for facts to
Change and facts have changed, you know, and there's certain things would have accelerated it, you know
But now snap is looking to be the agnostic agnostic platform that everyone
Needs to support now from the solos perspective when we first went for a flat pack
It was basically replaced the aging crappy third party, which you had the pleasure of enjoying recently
Yeah, that is a bit of a it is a bit of an uncomfortable. It sucks. It sucks. So you want something that you know
Something just works for the users, you know, like minimal friction and when we first said, oh, you know
We're gonna go for flat back
It was we wanted the least invasive change and I guess it was basically bang for buck at the time with least amount of
You're essentially getting it with GTK to
Known world, wasn't it? You know, you bring in OS tree. Well that depends on GLib world
We have all this stuff, you know, that would have been easy enough and it's a C known library essentially
But I mean since that time and it's got to be six plus months eight months or something like that now
It's it's changed a lot and then nowadays flat pack is more about these runtimes very much about these runtimes
But as a vendor, I mean, we're effectively an OS V. We have no say
We have no influence there and there are times when we're gonna want to add value
So you can imagine to draw a parallel if you're a Samsung and you're manufacturing Chromebooks
You're gonna want to add value on for your customers, right?
You're gonna want that value at not just shipping that we want the opportunity of we're doing things with third-party
applications to actually enhance that and
Do cool things today with the solace room. I want to pause you there. So because I think that
Comparison will probably make a lot of people sort of wretch a little bit because it sounds
Value add right? Yeah, right
What about using discord as an example there because I think discord is an example where a lot of distributions sort of just got
Screwed a little bit. Mm-hmm. And I think I think if you are like this is what I was thinking
I key is the thing about solace is you guys are really on top of packaging when you do decide to package something like you
Really think it through and it's you commit to it. So discord was pretty quickly fixed and
There was a dependency that discord all of a sudden required
And of course it also required to be running on a current version
This is you know, this is the way these things go
especially new applications, especially for vendors that are still learning how to support Linux and
In my experience solace handled that pretty much the best and was able to get the additional dependencies
Bundled in there and shipped and pushed down to the end-users and fix the problem pretty quickly, but
It does kind of raise the argument for I mean there is the whole thing if you're an application developer
I mean, we all like to give them a lot of problems, you know
Like they're not bringing this stuff over to Linux, but there is the whole part of which Linux do you target?
It's like the joke I made about solace. Which arm would we target?
Well, it's kind of the same for which Linux would you go for so?
You given them a common target that they can all go for that just happens to run on all the Linux distributions
It makes a lot of sense
So I'm not interested in in terms so much of the open-source software because well you can distribute that anyway
Sure, but stuff that we can't distribute and to give an example I can now
Well bad example, but I can run next cloud on my local box for testing for snap. That's all fully managed
That's not something we're ever gonna package in solace
How would it change in Chrome like if there was an official Google Chrome snap or flat pack?
How would that change distributing that for you? So I mean it comes straight from the vendor
Which is a great thing and in many ways snap operates a little bit like a package manager
Anyway, in terms of there are indexes and there are updates and there are these blobs that it goes to fetch when we do it
Now we've got to go to our third-party repo and effectively mark the new URL for the original deb file
And then put the hash in there. That's you know, we basically some said I try to install Chrome it failed
That's how we know that sucks. Yeah, I mean I really really suck. So there's no update
There's no automatic update for snap kind of takes that away in the the software vendors can be responsible
I mean regardless of the application they can be responsible for when their stuff goes out
They can test it themselves before it actually gets to the distributions and there are built-in update mechanisms as well
So being able to swap out the hacky I was tracking it stuff versus
These vendors would want to put out their own software and say well
This is what you're getting then it takes the pressure off of everyone in that circle
So what going back to flat pack and snap one of the things that does sort of stand out is it sounds like to do
full-fledged proper big boy matching Ubuntu snap support
It was a bit more work than flat pack because you just sort of you sort of just got flat pack
Reflecting on that did did snaps
Focus on not just desktop, but also including server software. Was that a motivating factor here?
Because well traditionally that'd be a weaker area for solace, right? So if snap, yeah, we're desktop
yeah, but this could sort of fill in gaps that
Solace has right now that you know
If some user wanted to run say sab NZB on their solar system, and there's a snap for that
I
Mean a lot of it's Martin's fault
I mean there's stuff that we can't distribute but not only that
There's stuff that we won't distribute and that was the angle that Martin was taking this like
There's gonna be stuff that your inclusion policy is just not gonna go for but some people are gonna need and from the solace
Perspective, it's sometimes it's gonna be a bit like a get out of jail free card instead of just saying to people
No, no, we're not putting this in and then everyone's unhappy
it's like however, you know, there is this over approach that you can go that you can go the snap route and
the the other part of it is that basically
the the snap craft and the Ubuntu teams have
Very much been there over the last few days and I think we started on something like the Thursday or Friday or something like that
But in the end we wanted the first day I got back from holiday
Yeah, and it was like two days later. We got to the point where we actually had the first kernel patched
So it was the next current kernel and we had the full confinement and on the next morning
We then had compatibility with classic confinement as well
What is so without that help?
When be can you explain the difference between confinement and classic confinement?
Okay, so there's three confinement models
now there's dev mode which is what you start with when you're creating your snap at the beginning and that tears down much of the
Confinement and then when you actually want to publish your snap, you've got two confinement options. There's strict confinement
Which means the application is entirely sandboxed and only has access to the things that you define
Via the snap craft yaml. So think of it like a firewall. You've got this application in a sandbox
This application needs access to your webcam
so in the yaml you tell it it can access the webcam and there are
Dozens of interfaces to give applications discrete access to different things on the host operating system
usually hardware devices
And so when it's strictly confined it can only access those things that you've prescribed it can access
and it can also only access files within its snap or if you add a home interface to a
Sandboxed portion of your home directory. So even if you have the home interface enabled you can't see
files and dot folders
From the snap and that's to prevent the snap being used to maliciously get it, you know
GPG keys and things of that nature
so so what was so what was required sort of
On a back end. What is missing? What is missing it for Linux distributions to support this?
Well to support what exactly this confinement
Well
That you need a palmer basically. That's sort of the more controversial thing about this
Is that some people don't want to roll out so much? I mean openSUSE are using app armor
Yeah, I keep us in the position where he hadn't chosen an LSM at this point
So I see Linux
What then I say they make great software
But some part of the problem is that classic confinement is
basically
Allowing a snap to run pretty much without any confinement whatsoever
So there are specific use cases for classic confinement. So for example
a liquidity that we mentioned earlier is a classic snap because it's a terminal and it needs to execute
Shell commands from arbitrary locations on your hard drive. So that means no confinement has
So well
It has to have no confinement over what it can see on your hard disk because it has to be able to execute arbitrary things
And compilers, you know
If you want to snap a language or a compiler that almost certainly has to be classic for the same reasons. So
But then the the trick here is the way that snapd works is that
snaps and everything to do with snap sit under
snap in the root of the file system and
some
distros have elected to not follow that
requirement and
Relocate snaps elsewhere on the file system and at that point it breaks the opportunity to run classic snaps at all
Okay, so this to me to me it seems like it's maybe just a little it's it's a little bit
It's a little confusing because there's a lot. There's a lot of parts there, but it sounds like pretty simply
Simply put if it's done if it's done properly
You can have you could still have a you can have a system that fully fully supports confined snaps
But the snap if set up could not be confined
Yes, okay, I think I got it. Okay interesting. So what was behind the scenes?
What was the work between say yourself and I key to get this working on solace?
Well, I am I've really been a glorified cheerleader in this whole process
And a go-between so I think I heard I key say on
Late night Linux a few weeks ago that he was open to
Using snaps and my ears pricked up and I thought
So I immediately got on telegram
And we started to have a conversation and then I
Had a chat with some of the guys at work and we identified a few people who would have some time to assist and
We waited for I key to
Make his transition to working on solace as his full-time
Endeavor and then I key got busy doing his release business and then last week
We made the introductions with I key and the other guys in the team
And I was basically just standing on the sidelines applauding and cheering enthusiastically at that point. I
Loved how it came out I key, you know
Starts with that it started the Google plus post and I just sit there and I go this this son of a bitch
Well, I did drop hints to it on the last time I was sort of dropped hints that it yeah
It was sort of in the back of my head. But yeah, well, I've a habit of doing this as an end user now
Is there really anything I do? Do I just snap a snap installed on the you have a stop installed already? Yeah
Okay. Well, there you go. So you can just do pseudo snap installed brave dash dash beta. Oh brave really?
Yeah, so we wasn't really looking forward to packaging brave results. It's another thing. It's electronic
So the syntax is pseudo snap installed
Mm-hmm. Yeah, brave brave and then dash beta dash dash. It's a dash. Yeah, that's right
I'm a noob
Sold a couple of snaps, but not many
There we go. It's downloading right now. It's a good example because it's fully confined. Oh
And it will also use the open GL interface as well
Which means that we've actually got a couple of fixes going in at the moment now
We're going back and forth from the polar crates but some of the stuff like the way that we have the open gel libraries on
Solos is laid out basically the same as they would be on arts Linux
So the stuff that we're doing now because we have the full confinement
We're finding books that arts Linux will have by the time it gets full confinement
So we're fixing their books before they happen, which is kind of cool
Yeah, this is another advantage of getting
What is probably and I mean this with love I keep the most foreign Linux distribution
Yeah running snaps because you're you are trailblazing in many ways
It's a very opinionated Linux. Yeah, you're going to bump into things. Yeah, well it will it show up now in my
How does that show up in your menu does it now fight, but I do brave. I see nothing. I see nothing
I see nothing, but if I can if budgie menu is being an idiot, then you can use another feature of budgie all an f2. Oh
alt
f2
Aha, I see. Yes. I need to learn that that's gonna be my new favorite feature. I do need that
That's Brian from the solos team told me that I had to tell you that
So I've been looking to slip that one in that is really good. I really do like that. All right, so I'm waiting
I'm waiting. I'm not seeing all so it's alt f2. Oh, there we go
Yeah, just type in brave and it should be there. Yeah, it just it just it just popped up
Yeah, the first time you launch any snap it takes slightly longer
Because it's setting everything up in the back end, you know, like for the next time it runs
It's got all these policies and everything. But the next time you run it should basically be instant. Yeah, and that that first run
Latency is something we're addressing as well. So that will go away in time
What a perfect way to play with something like brave this is because you just if you have snap support
you can you can do that same command and you can be messing around with it and it's
This is this is probably you know, a browser is a perfect example of an application
That should be you can test the sandbox in though
So if you go on right click on something and was to do like a save as to get the file dialog pop up
Try navigating to one of the folders that you're not allowed to go to
So like your root folder or back into your real home folder. Sure. So we'll go let's try going to
Other locations computer. Oh
Yeah, no, it's basically this is screw you you can't go there
interesting
Interesting. In fact, yeah now this is this is an interesting
Notion this sandboxing of browsers because if you've ever run s trace whilst
You have what if you've had you got
Firefox installed and you start Chrome for the first time and you have s trace on the Chrome process
You will see Chrome going grubbing around all over Firefox looking for stuff really and if they
Know if you've got these in set each of them as sandboxed
Snaps, then you can't have that happen. So I know if you're that's interesting
Sorry to interrupt. I noticed though. So
What about theming support guys? What is the what is the story there?
I went finish your thought if you were if you're gonna finish something
But just after you do finish it, I'd be curious to know what the what the story is with theming
No, no, I've made my point about you know stopping applications from you know snooping on that is really nice. Yeah
But in terms of theme support that was something so a few weeks ago
we had a sprint in London a snap sprint in London and there a number of people from the
community invited to that from you know, KDE and elementary and
gnome and all sorts and one of the
Tracks we did there was how we're going to improve the theme support and that's currently being worked on
So we did the design there and that's that's in progress seems like a challenge
That seems like a real challenge if it's supposed to be isolated and all of that. I mean that seems yeah
There's there's a number of cool new bits of tech coming to make all of this magic happen
But we fleshed out how to handle
themes fonts and icons in a way that you can
Interconnect them and what?
and
So something that I can I've discussed and so what you need to know is I key knows things
He can't talk about at the moment and I heard him so hard podcast a couple of days ago
And I could tell that I key wasn't sure if this thing that he knew he could talk about or not
No, as it happens he can so I key was interviewed on oven to fun
Podcast which is a German language podcast, but fortunately I key was interviewed in English, which I can just about hope with
Yes, and one of the things that I key was alluding to is just talking about how solace could add value to the snap
ecosystem
And he wasn't able to articulate what he meant exactly and I'll explain
so at the moment when you install a snap for the first time a core snap gets installed and that core snap is a
Very thin Ubuntu runtime so a very small shim of user space
Which also has snap D
Embedded inside it. So when you're running brave at the moment, you actually have this very thin Ubuntu
Layer and then the snap sits on top of that. So effectively it's an Ubuntu runtime that you're using
alongside
solace
But what we're doing is we're going to introduce this concept of base snaps
So the core snap would just become snap D and the bits that it needs
Not that will be the new core
So very very small and then the base snap will be that thin shim of runtime
So the default will be the Ubuntu runtime the default the default
Yeah, but we're going to add a facility in the yaml to say base
colon
solace and if Aiki creates a base snap based on the solace runtime
somebody
Somebody could create a snap which is built on top of that solace runtime
and when that snap is installed on Ubuntu you would get that solace base underneath and
Then the application sitting on top and this will be something that you know
Any of the distros can do to create their own base snaps and Aiki can explain why he thinks this will be a useful feature
Optimized optimized libraries. It's gonna be awesome games and stuff. It's gonna be great
Interesting. I just wanted to get that out
I mean it could mean you know, we could also mean a lot of Ubuntu users now can have better libraries
Thanks to solace in a way, you know
I mean like doing a reverse, but now I don't need to switch. I don't need to switch to solace. Yeah
It is a reverse team. It's exactly a reverse team
Revengeous suite. Yeah, that's good. I can see I can see it
And it could you could also see for the fedora project if there was something
It made the most sense to build on top of or you're there's a great angle for this as well. I mean
It's all Travis actually Martin. I'll let you talk about though
Well, what what what do I know about Travis?
I'm just saying Travis like tools are say
What's the other one coveralls and things like that?
Invariably you end up with older stuff
But say like at the moment
I'm having to use Docker to build some of my stuff in tree
Because I don't want to use some of the online services because they're using like a bunch of maverick and stuff like that
So instead of having like a heavyweight Docker image
Which is gonna take me about 10 to 15 minutes to build from a tarball of something
I would then be able to use my solace devel
Kind of snap locally to build budgie and then I could use like the Ubuntu one to build it
So I can do all of my local tests without then having to go through VMs and heavyweight Docker and stuff
So yeah, yeah, that's something I'm very much looking forward to
Yeah, especially for something like budgie as well where you're using like four or five different GTK versions. It's gonna be a godsend
Yeah, and you know, yeah, I've I've I've installed solace on my intro where Apollo
And I'm able to do my day job on solace now
Because I can snap install Docker and I can snap install snap craft and I can snap install Lex D
And although I'm sitting on top of solace now
I can use all of the tools that I need from the you know, the Ubuntu world on this solar system
Just fine. Yeah, that's awesome
We're converging. Yeah, and in
and I suppose in some ways at the end and you know
When I look what I think about a lot of these applications with some of the exceptions that wimpy just put out there
I a lot of the things that I would be using these for
Are applications that never have any interest in being in anybody's repo?
They're never gonna be an OBS there then it's just not what they're interested in
They they develop in a paradigm that is Windows and Mac and on Windows and Mac you have your base OS
And then you just drop your application down on top of it
If you needed your own libraries, you just include them screw with the OS ships. Here's your library link to it
You're good to go
It's all in a bundle and you drop it on the file system
and then when you do a new update you just drop new versions of all that crap right over the old crap on the
file system and this is how they've done it for
going on almost 30 years now and
And there's some applications that even though that's changing
That's that's the culture in which they are created
That's where they come from and they're never going to they're never going to work with the solace
Maintainers to package it up, you know
Like look at look at just all the applications out there that people are using these days
When you look at a desktop with Skype and slack and all these different applications people use
these are just
this
This is just what happens when that kind of application starts coming to the Linux desktop
They're not going to just change their philosophy and start going to each distribution and say please sir
Could you please distribute slack for me? Could you please distribute this to your users this new update?
Could you please distribute it soon? Because it's a vulnerability and we need it fixed and we had to fix something on server side
So if you don't get this client code out there, we can't flip the server side
So could you please work over the weekend and push that out to all of your users? Mr. Debbie and maintainer?
Like that's just that's it's never ever going to happen
So I fix that yeah, so that's why you know, I don't think it's I
Agree with Ikea. I don't think it's I don't think it's the biggest problem facing Linux right now
I really don't but I I do think it's where we are converging
It's making it easier for people to use Linux as a platform to get their shit done. And I think that's really important
I think that's the important part. There is now an emergent platform something that hasn't happened for a long time
Yeah, if you look at any of the over operating systems, I mean you look at the stack that's evolved on Mac OS
There's a very much an emergent platform there
Linux hasn't had one you've had all these disconnected targets and toolkits and libraries and the API's and standards
And now all of a sudden this thing is just starting to bubble up to the surface
it's like a common target a common set of runtimes a common set of expectations and
You know like where does the kernel end the word is distro begin? That's becoming very very clearly defined now
So it's it's getting to a point now where we could say
Okay, if we added more stuff to bring these developers across it's it the deployment issue is basically gone
We have something to resolve one problem. Here's what you can target. Here's the world that you can live in
You have reasonable expectations or any expectation and I could yeah
I mean now we can actually bend over for them, you know bend over backwards for the software
Developers because before it's like oh, well, we can't have your application in because then that means we got to go patch QT
But that version of Q is needed by that thing. We couldn't possibly do that because our users unit
It's like now they can just say well, I'm just gonna do what I do on Windows and ship this patch version to keep with it
We were never gonna stop these people from doing up and now they got away doing that
Yeah, well and you know what sounds like these proposed changes to sort of separate out the the snap processes versus the base
Runtime area means it's not even it's not even an Ubuntu solution anymore
It can just be a Linux solution. And if your Linux is solace or your Linux is SUSE, you're good
So that's pretty great too. So before we go before we wrap up I key, you know
I got a you got a because you've just released a new version. My favorite question to always ask
Is well now what's next
You know you now that you've just spent all of that time and effort getting that out the door
Next what's next? Come on. Give me what's next?
Um, so there's a few things. Okay, so there's an immediate work list to be done after we call it the
It's the meta list the post release blues
One of the first things we got to do is slightly improve our
Basically our pipeline to make us go more faster. That's one of the primary goals going forward
Dropping some standard stuff like the older web kits and rebasing system D, you know the the boring stuff sure
But it's now it's the sort of the time where for solace for we're going to be focusing on the OEM enabling
We're talking to people already and the installer is going to get split up to support an OEM workflow
Which would be very very good
Linux driver manager is actually going back into active development
Which doesn't mean the dynamic optimus GPU support will be coming this year. Hurrah
I'm supposed to drop a bombshell aren't I?
We're all gonna put weight behind the KD plasma stack this year as well. Really? So that's getting brought up
I am willing to permit an out-of-band release for our kitty. Yes that I'm looking forward to seeing that
I really am. I mean, I mean lots of stuff coming this year. Not just
Yeah, I saw you put you basically put a chart up online that says these are a lot of the things we're working on
Right now and there's a lot of core infrastructure stuff you're working on
Yeah, I mean one of the things that's kind of been bugging me like as a distribution
We say these are the rules for things that can come into our repos, you know
And sometimes not everyone has agreed with our reasons for things going into the repos
But one of the things that's interested me is building the best-in-class pipeline
I am interested in building something that's effectively a source to deployment
Pipeline so once that tarball or sources or that stuff goes into the distribution
We're scanning at that level first before it goes anywhere else. So we're gonna be doing static analysis
We even like license calculations once it goes in and then that's gonna be tracking those build out our facts all the way through the repositories
To the final image so that we can basically track the entire distribution and we can say anywhere, you know
These are the problems
These are the things that we have to target so that we can actually say to people using solace, you know
Well, here's a bit of peace of mind, you know
so that's one of the things I personally want to be focusing on but
Yeah
But 11 at some stage, that's what everybody that's what's on everyone's mind
But it sounds like there's a lot of good core stuff getting worked on right now
I mean, that's why I did budget 10.4
But not I there was actually a load of us and a lot of it was a Stefan helping me there
Like the new workspaces stuff the new animations window. That was all Stefan
10.4 was kind of
At LTS I would say because there was a lot of problems in the existing 10.3 release
Like if you had a bottom panel and you click the budget menu
Sometimes it would appear down the bottom
Sometimes it would start at the top
So every row that put new budget popovers in so the idea was to give me more time
So that we didn't have to worry about budget lever a little bit longer, you know
So the people have a stable desktop to use day to day. Yeah, and I'll put you lovingly start that bit later
Yeah, I think that probably played I think I that's kind of what I was like thinking to myself
It's like this is this is getting sort of refined now
I could probably throw this on a production machine and be comfortable for a while. So that's what I did
I would yeah, I mean, it's kind of our goal, you know get to the point where we can say, you know
This is a world-class OS that we're shipping and that's why I'm again too. So it's a bit of a journey
Lots of things are coming into place with the Software Center improvements
And I mean some of the most important things we're doing right now is collaborating with other projects and working outside of solace
And I think that's very very important to us and the rest of the Linux community. Yeah
And it sounds like it's all been going pretty good and been kicking some ass. Mr. Wimpy speaking of some of that cross collab
Speaking across collab. You're gonna be at odd camp this coming weekend, correct? I
Am yes, and you are doing a bit of a mashup show down there, aren't you?
We are yeah
I think
so
We're gonna do a live show on I think the Saturday evening and Joe Ressington is organizing that so it's a mashup of
Some of the late-night Linux podcasters and some of the Ubuntu podcasters
We we're gonna do a live podcast with a Q&A section
In fact, I'll have a link in the show notes. Joe's just put a call out for questions for odd camp
they have a Google form that you can fill out with your question or
You can go to their late night linux.com slash contact page and probably email it in
or
URL is late night linux.com
Forward slash ask. Oh, yeah or hashtag ask. Oh, that's a good. I like that
Yes, we have we're using hashtag ask error right now for for user error
Ask August that's good. We should have asked lup
All right. So yeah, there you go
So there with that you can find links in the show notes to that stuff. Also check out wimpy on the Ubuntu podcast
I'm gonna be looking forward to that episode. Are you guys gonna put a bout out in both of your feeds? How does that work?
In the past we have done I think we don't do these sort of cross distro cross podcasting
But yeah, I did one with the guys at ubu con last year and we put that out on the Ubuntu podcast feed
So probably yes
So long as we don't make her Horlicks off it and it goes well then yeah, we'll publish it. Yeah, I hope it's fun
I hope it's fun. Well guys great work. Thank you very much for chatting with us about that
I have just a little slack wear follow-up to do and the best bug I've ever seen submitted
Simon sent it into the show and we got to talk about it really quickly. I want to thank ting though
Just full stop right here. This is one of these sponsors
I've been using now for years and it's made a real difference. It's it's so simple
I really don't have time to deal with complicated wireless stuff or really pay out the nose for stuff
I don't use and that's why I like ting it's six dollars a month for your wireless and then whatever you use you just pay for
So a few minutes and your messages and your megabytes, that's just what I don't use minutes
Really? In fact, there's been months where I've not used a minute not a minute now there are months
There are months where I use minutes and I may use many of those minutes
But I got to tell you it really averages out. I'm saving about two thousand dollars a year every two years
So about a thousand dollars a year Wow, you know average ting bills about twenty three dollars per phone
but what's what's the reason why it's such a huge savings for me is I had two lines and
I was paying I was paying probably after-tax a hundred and forty dollars a month for two phones
Um now we have three phones and I'm usually paying around thirty seven forty bucks a month
That's crazy. Yeah, it's crazy
Linux dot ting comm I love it
You pay for what you use nationwide coverage GSM and CDMA and a dashboard that guess what goes for days
They also have apps for your device and fantastic customer support Linux dot ting comm
You got to go there to support the show and you get twenty five dollars in service credit
If you bring a GSM or a CDMA they got yep
They got a BYOD page check or if you just want to buy a new one from them
They'll give it twenty five dollars off the phone Linux dot ting comm
Damn, you know you're excited if you use the service you're excited if you don't use the service Linux dot ting comm so slack wear thoughts
You know I I didn't really expect to use it much after the show West to be honest with you
But me you know I sat down and it was on the machine that I was gonna load with gen 2 and I thought well
You know I never really got all the way like I never felt like I didn't you know
I was I just I didn't have I didn't get to that point where I'm just using it to screw around
I was always in that mode
For like reviewing it for the show yeah, yeah, and you know I thought about it a little bit
I thought to myself if
If you go into slack wear, and you don't you know you're not expecting it to be a boon to you know
You're not expecting it to to be soulless you go in you go in with that kind of mindset
It was a lot of fun to get my nostalgia on but after after I got over the nostalgia aspect of it
Which is kind of what I talked about the most last week
I
realized that it reminded me of a of a different time where Linux was simpler in and a lot easier to just
straight up
Understand just like I can see it how it's all laid out right here. It makes a lot of sense to me and
There's something else about it. It's it's it's not that it's like raw Linux. It's
For better or for worse like if you're comfortable with the versions of software that slack where has available
And there's like slack scripts and stuff to get newer stuff like you know newer versions of Firefox
but like say you wanted like Apache and
You know a mail program like post fix and maybe a database, and it just didn't need to be super super current stuff
It's just something you wanted in your house to like serve your favorite links up
And you wanted a mysql database for the back end for your photo management program or whatever
Slack where is kind of perfect because
It's it's an era of Linux where you could install it
It's like it's so much like arch except for without nothing like ours
I
Struggled to relate that because you can install it
And then you can literally not come back to it for two years
And if in two years after not even touching this box you log in and all of a sudden you want to install a new
Package it's fine
It's it's totally fine
It's not a big deal if you wanted if you even and you maybe maybe
Maybe been some updates to slack where like maybe a point release maybe an update to slack where but probably not
Like it's it's the it's like it's a kind of computing
We no longer have access to because all of our devices either constantly are getting abandoned by the vendor or need to be updated
It's either or
My Chromecast I use it so rarely that I swear every damn time I turn it on I have to wait ten minutes while
It updates every single time you know my set-top box on my TV updates every single month it is
It's just this
non-stop
Let us improve that experience for you and often the experience is not improved and there really is something to be said
For this time and I remember it in Linux where there was just so much time between releases software moved
slower
it just moved slower and and you could install a Debian box and let it just sit in a closet and
Nothing had really changed on it
And that's what slackware represents that time that we have lost access to in almost all aspects of our life
And and I wouldn't necessarily want to live there right, but I could see like if I just had a utility box sitting in the corner
Hosting up some websites for my LAN, and I didn't need to be a big deal
It's and you didn't want to make it a big old project or like you know like you set it up once you got involved
With it you understood how everything worked, and yeah, you come back to it
There wasn't a whole lot of extra stuff that will suddenly show up or change or there's a real sense of ownership there
Yeah, exactly so I could I could totally see the long-term
But you get the fun of like an arch system where you're piecing it together yourself
But you don't have to that's what it is constantly
Yeah, read a blog to make sure that you're not gonna break your system. That is what it is
So here's this was sent into the show by Simon, and this is my favorite
this is my favorite bug of the week it was submitted to Dimitri by Dimitri and
It's over on the Ubuntu mailing list as a bug and he has a question. He says the subject is y2k 100 bug is
Is it reasonable to expect the below that the Ubuntu version numbers below will be accurate in?
in April
2100 it's going to be Ubuntu 100 dot 04 LTS
but in
April of the year 3000
It's going to be 1000 dot 04 dot LTS which obviously wouldn't make any sense since it's the year 3000 so you have you know
Obviously there's a there's a numbering problem here
a very important problem that Dimitri brings up and so the Ubuntu development team took a
Long hard look at this bug and they came back with what I think is a pretty solid answer
And I'm imagining they're gonna just go ahead and consider this one resolved
The answer from the Ubuntu team is the world will have been obliterated by nuclear war and biochemical warfare by then
So no need to worry about it
I feel way more assured. You know you sometimes. There's this little things you don't have to worry about
Does make you wonder how they know about that ahead of time?
I wonder if it's like the Apple stuff where they don't you know at Apple
They have like you can't use iTunes we at a nuke base like I wonder if I went to has that in the terms of
Service maybe they don't install
Anyways, thank you everybody for coming in the moment, but specifically
Thank you to wimpy and I key for being there. Thank you to our regulars for making it this week
Even though there wasn't a lot of time for everybody. I see you I appreciate you guys making it the mumble room, too
I hope you can join us next week. I may or may not be here
Depending on how crazy that Eclipse is that could be it could be the at the lost episode for me
We'll see but if I do make it why don't you join us?
We'll do it live over JB live TV at 2 p.m.. Pacific
You can get that converted from JB time to your time at Jupiter broadcasting comm slash calendar Linux unplug dot reddit comm is the sub
Reddit Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contacts the way to get us and the network's at Jupiter signal at Jupiter signal. That's where you find it
Thanks for joining us
You
Okay, let's unleash the hounds JB titles comm let's pick our title before we go
Did you want to toss anything else development wise going on? We're thinking about having reoccurring development meetings
We should maybe mention that so and discord dot is a discord emmy slash Jupiter colony
Yeah, that'll be getting set up over there for more developer participation
But was there anything else we want to mention development wise, right?
So so what is it Beardsley?
We have a
Jupiter dev channel on the discord now
And I was talking with one of the developers that's helped out in JB in the past and he's he's kind of thinking about
leading a
We haven't decided how often maybe weekly maybe monthly
Like a development meetup for the JB community really to work on on JB projects in in discord
uh, yeah, so probably some mix of voice chat and text chat sweet and
It was partially spurred on by the fact that we're kind of
Toying with the idea of maybe completely rewriting
Of course every open source project eventually gets to this point. Yeah. Well, there's a lot of inherited crap and
And
We kind of need to just dump all of that to be able to expand what we want JB to do
So you're saying it's gonna be rebuilt better than ever yeah, you have the technology I heard we're gonna rebuild it better faster and stronger
What are you gonna build it with?
Probably still gonna be Ruby
If you would have said rust, I think you would have had a lot of people excited. Maybe we'll go crazy
Maybe we'll do elixir. I was gonna say yeah elixir. I think you should I hear great things
Yeah, there you go. Yeah, I noticed that a new bug was opened
I think it was new bug was open up on the soundboard. We're getting it
We're trying to get a few more things fixed on the soundboard. I want to get
basically
State saving per action for the sound. Oh, yes. Yes. Yes that way if it crashes
You don't lose all your or the machine. Yeah, or the machines were running on crashes. Yeah in the case
I love you guys. Thank you guys speaking of the the soundboard
Since you have snap on solace now, you can install the soundboard. Oh, yeah, that's right. I might is your soundboard not portable
It is an a you are