I got a rumor you guys ready for a little for a little hardware rumor
Totally I bet Pope he's not here because he knows and he doesn't want to get cornered on it
But rumor has it that you may the you know, the big guy Chinese phone manufacturers plan to release a svelte
laptop that runs Linux
Manifest manufacturing sources speaking to the tiny site DigiTimes which has by the way a horrible track record just in my personal opinion
says that the company is developing a 15-inch notebook with partners in the tech who also makes notebooks for HP Acer and Toshiba and
Foxconn where the manufacturing happens for Apple's iPhones iPads and the PlayStation and
Xbox and Nintendo the I'm a laptop or probably feature a high price performance ratio and the target retail price of around
470 US greenbacks
Yeah, I may make some good stuff. They're often known as an Apple ripoff. Are you familiar with their stuff?
Yes, I've enviously looked at some of theirs. Yeah, I might achieve Android phone. That looks pretty this would be running not Android
This would be running Linux. Yes, this would be even better
Yeah, this would this would be full-on and you wouldn't have to worry about installing Linux
I've never installed you know slash Linux because it would come pre-installed with it. That's awesome
Yeah, now it could be a hoax though
They have had it they have had a hoax in the past
But I don't know anybody the mumbo-jumbo you guys would anybody check this out if you had a sub $500 nice looking laptop from Yao
May now it's not gonna be like a super freedom respecting
It's probably gonna be something that's more similar to a Chromebook
Anybody in the mobile room jumping on it? I might give it a thought what distro is it going to be running?
Well, the rumor is a custom version of Linux
Yeah, exactly, but they say DigiTimes is not always as they point out on OMG Ubuntu not always that reliable I agree I
Agree, but it could make sense. It could go into a nice lineup of products. So actually I
Could see it. I could see this really happening
You know
It doesn't seem like a big jump if you're making cell phones to go into a portable laptop market that maybe includes a data chip
A decent CPU you can install, you know, maybe your own version of Linux on there. This could be kind of a neat thing
Exciting to see a new hardware manufacturer at least. Yeah, or you know what? Here's a way. I got another tip for you
This is this is your pro tip. You ready for this? I got pro tips
Actually, let me think about this. Maybe we should save this for the show because this is good. This is really good
Maybe we'll save it in the show
Now let's talk about it. Now. Let's talk about it right now. So did you guys see did you guys see that the Linux foundation?
Is a giving away Chromebooks?
The Linux foundation is giving away Chromebooks when you sign up for some classes. So here I'm gonna here
Here's the detail. This is from from our buddy over at IT world a swamp swamp Lee. How do you how do you say his name?
I met him at Linux con nice guy nice guy. He took a selfie with his huge nexus 6 and
Now he's using an iPhone 5s as it to test Android where so Linux foundation is giving away
Chromebooks when you enroll in a training course in the month of September
What do you think about this the Linux foundation giving away Chromebooks? Interesting
Well, that's a bummer. I've only just enrolled for a course in like the 30th of August
Well, I wouldn't be does it make you uncomfortable to give me away Chromebooks as I seem perfectly fine
Well, I'm not surprised because
The course that I've enrolled for says that in order to do the course where you have to be running chromium or Google Chrome
Oh, really? Oh, really? Huh? I at first my first gut reaction was like
I wasn't super comfortable because this doesn't feel like real Linux
But here's here's what made me sort of change my tune. I feel a little bit better when I read this
Jim the Jim Zimlin. He's the executive director of the Linux foundation
He said we want students of Linux to experience a Linux desktop and Chromebooks are a great way to do that
Either through Google's Linux based OS or by investing in a Linux based OS
Either through Google's Linux based OS or by installing one of the many Linux distros available
Alright, that's not bad. He says we hope this offer can provide freedom
The freedom Linux developers and IT professionals value and spark new ideas and discoveries as they embark on our Linux training program
So he's right there saying in the announcement that they're pretty much
Okay, if you'd wipe Chrome OS off there and put any Linux distro on there and that I'm all about and by the way
They're not bad Chromebooks. They look like they're these these Dell Chromebooks that we've talked about in the past
Yeah, the I don't the Dell Chromebook 11 the 299 Chromebook features one or probably an 11.6 inch display
1.4 gigahertz processor and 4 gigabytes 4 gigabytes of RAM
So there you go. That's not a bad giveaway
No, it could be pretty fun for people get it to play with as they're learning Linux
Yeah, absolutely
That could be a great way for people to get their start and it's not a big investment for them to see that's actually really
Clever because if it's not a huge expense
Then maybe you're not so worried about trying out and seeing how things go and if things don't go well well
It was a Chromebook you got for free
You don't mind if you erase your hard drive a couple times while you're installing it
This is Linux unplugged episode 108 for September 1st
You
Welcome to Linux unplugged your weekly Linux talk show that's learning how to dump its black tank. Oh
My name is Chris. My name is Wes. Hey Wes. Hey, guess what big show today, Wes
I know I know surprise surprise surprise that so I had I had been I've been pondering this question
I realized maybe I actually have the best group to possibly ask it to because I need to get an international
perspective on this one, so we're gonna bring in our virtual lug on one of our
Quandaries top law for enforcement officials in the US want backdoors into all types of encryption technology
This is something that's been they've been debating since early in the year and it's picking up a lot of steam
What would the ramifications be for open source?
Especially code that's developed outside the US if the US were to make this the land of the law
What responsibilities does open source have distro makers and things like that?
So I want to talk about that and just pontificate on the subject also some details on the upcoming roadshow
Kubuntu's new look and saying goodbye
To an old friend plus we have some really awesome go powered retro feedback coming up in today's episode
So since that's so much to get into no more delaying is is allowed
I say we bring in that virtual lug time appropriate greetings mumble room
Hello, it's good. It's good to have you all here. Yes. Good evening. Hello all so let's start with a little follow-up
I I know some of us may have seen that Kubuntu
Has a brand new look they have a brand new look for a brand new well for a brand new season
I guess it's fall after all it's becoming fall and I want West your first takes on Kubuntu
Dot orgs brand new look one of the big stories today going around. What do you think nice and clean? Yeah?
I don't like it. No. I like I think it represents plasma 5 pretty well
Oh, yeah, it does actually front and center represents some really nice aspects of the haven't used it too much
So the usability that's a separate question, but it's at least visually appealing
Yeah, it really does kind of highlight some of the nice things like here's the productivity suite and the multimedia playback good point
Yeah, it does draw a lot of us make me want to use Kubuntu
And it does yeah, you know it's really nice
Not in your face and like a yeah like a big windows way and like if you're wondering like how do I do media playback?
They have a button right there that we show you that
I've actually heard some grumbling about it, but when I look at it myself
I'm pretty impressed. I like how they've broken out long-term
They also make it really clear of here on which one is the latest instead of release on their download page
And then the the page I haven't looked at yet is their community one. Oh, yeah, there we go
They got a way they got a web chat set up right here. I don't know
I think it's pretty nice anybody in the mumble room have any reactions the new kabuntu org
It's okay. It's
Like I'm on the full desktop, so I don't have windows full screen all the time
So when it's not you got the when your browser like half the screen
It's pretty much hamburger menu and icons are fairly large even on the 1080p desktop
So I still think it needs some work
Chai room thinks it should be kde.org. I kind of agree. This would be a great kde.org site. Yeah, definitely
Should help out. Well, I just props to those guys
It looks like a lot of work and effort went into that if anybody else has comments going once
Oh, did you just shrink it down and see what he's saying? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, it's not great
They should work on their mobile design, but it does work though when you shrink it down at least
I mean definitely I can grab the download right here. Yeah
Well, it does look like they just bought a theme. So I mean looks like they'll need some tweaking after that
Yeah, maybe that's the case. Maybe that's the case
All right
I I wanted to just note because we've been following this story and unplugged now for a little while another death in
Flash is caught another nail and thought flashes death coffin. Is that is that the right turn of phrase?
He'll in the coffin. Yep. Yeah, something like that. Something like is dying. That's important. Yeah, that is the important
That is the thing to pull from that and I think this is a big one because Chrome is gonna block like those obnoxious
Like flashing ads and then one of them in one of the next updates
This is huge for us Linux users because this begins to finally die off
And then what I'm looking forward to is eventually somebody's gonna have to come up with a really good solution for live streaming in HTML 5
Hopefully this will put more pressure in that wouldn't be are you skeptical?
Well, it was just that it was last week or the week before that there was this big brouhaha about Hulu
Not that I can use it, but Hulu has switched to flash. Is that right?
So Hulu switch to flash what were they before
Did they switch or have they always been flashed but they were I saw a load
Maybe from Silverlight or something, huh?
Maybe maybe pardon there
Yeah, and then
over here
I've got Amazon Prime
Yeah, so prime I've now got access to prime music because that's just arrived a couple of weeks ago
and prime instant video and the only way I can access those services on Linux is with with flash so
There's still some sort of premium content
Providers out there using flash. So I'm bring it where heralded heralding in flashes death
prematurely
To me, it's like the slow end of a distribution, right? We're getting there. I think eventually I
Don't know about right now. I mean
Yeah, you're right wimpy I think it's it's years off isn't it because
hmm
Yeah, cuz Google itself distributes quite a bit of ads over flash. I
Flash is gonna end up dying the death of XP
Yeah, is that is that we in the in the sense that like it gets relegated to like a whole bunch of people are still using
It kind of thing or what do you mean there?
Like just it drags on forever before it actually gets, you know put away
The same sort of things where you need XP for that one piece of hardware. Yeah, but your business can't upgrade
That's what happens to flash. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, I could see it. Yeah, I don't actually I know I
People you guys are such a bunch of pessimists
I think this is actually starting to happen though to a degree and you guys are every charm is like, come on
No, come on. This is act when you have auto pause happening you have I don't know
I think this is actually people are starting to finally turn the tide. I think this is really happening plus
I think at the same time this is happening where I think it's gonna be a big deal that well, maybe not
We'll see but a lot of iOS devices starting in the fall are gonna automatically start blocking ads Safari on iOS 9 is coming
with a built-in ad blocker
You combine that with the auto pausing of flash ads and online advertising is about to take a big hit. I
Mean display ads. Yeah, definitely. That'll be interesting
Do we know anything about how Google decides what the main content is versus?
Well, yeah a little bit. So, you know what Google is doing is they're looking at ads that loop fast
So if you have like a very short video play loop loop loop loop loop loop
It'll it'll count that after a certain amount and then it will detect that and then pause it
and you can go to advanced settings and select the content settings for privacy and then you can deselect and
Say deselect and run important plug-in content or something like that is the wording. I can't quite remember it
But yeah, got it. Oh here. I think they specified actually here's the link. I have it in the show notes
Here it is from Google and they have some of the details and they also talk about how to convert your each year
Oh, this is interesting. This is okay. So this here's the back end now and this is gonna work
So starting on September 1st, that's today
Most flash ads uploaded to AdWords
That's Google's ad platform are automatically going to be converted to HTML 5 to ensure your ads continue to show up on Google's display network very
nice
So that's so that's how Google's getting around the fact that so many of their ads are in flash is they're converting them to HTML
I wonder they must just be breaking them out and then
And then transcoding them if necessary
Yeah, that's kind of interesting technology. Yeah
Yeah, and then they give people instructions like to me perhaps it's not perfect though because they say you need to identify flash ads in
Your content that aren't eligible for automatic conversion and then convert these and they give you steps to do that
Yeah, so
I think online advertising is about to
For display ads is about to get a big shakeup. Yeah, what are they gonna do about that? I don't know
That's a huge market. I think they ought to convert to podcast advertisers personally
Yeah
Yeah, well, yes, apparently there are HTML 5 to I mean so flash video for the most part is really just an h264 video
And sometimes an mp3 audio stream wrapped up in an FLV container
And then the flash player is simply just playing it like our live stream right now is an h264 stream and an mp3
Audio stream that is then wrapped up in FLV and sent to the player that just happens to be a very good container for delivering
live content
If you have the technology you could have like for example, there is an open source tool out there called live streamer and live streamer
Will break h264 and the audio stream out of the FLV container
I'm probably butchering the real technicals of how this works, but this is layman understanding
it'll break it out of the FLV container and
Then repackage it up for you and display it on your Linux box without any need for flash and so you could take something like the live
Streamer app and point it at the Jupiter broadcasting backup stream on ustream and it will pull it will break the stream out of
It'll break the h264 video out and the mp3 video out and repackage it for you
Automatically right now, so it's obviously possible because really all flash video is is h264 video with a flash container
so that's why it's that's why it's not that hard, but it's it's
Fascinating and this is on the verge of we were just kind of talking about in the pre-show
But there's a bunch of industry people coming together to hopefully work on a non patent-encumbered video codec
Oh, and I'm my hopes up, but that's happening at least we'll see yeah
All right, so let's move on to something else and something
I've been thinking a lot about right now is mobile data
And I'm gonna tell you why in a little bit coming up on the show and so of course that gets me thinking about our
Friends over at ting I'd like you to think about them to go to linux.ting.com and check them out
It's mobile that makes sense ting is on a mission to change up mobile I say
People follow ting for a while
You've known that some of the things they've been pioneering have now been showing up in other ways and sort of a watered-down
Fashion in the industry. It's kind of a
A little disappointing that can't ever quite get it right
But I guess that's kind of how it goes when you're an imitator ting is great because it's no contracts
No early termination fees, and you only pay for what you use
They just take your minutes your messages in your megabytes, and they add them up
It's six dollars for the line, and then it's just your usage on top of that
It's a really slick system and in fact if you go over to linux.ting.com
You're gonna save fifty dollars off your first ting device or fifty dollars in ting service credit
We have a special promo for the month of September to give you fifty dollars of service credit or off your first device and so
You think about that you only paying for what you use well
I my first month of ting service was less than twenty five dollars
So you might be able to get a couple of months in there or do what I'm doing
I'm picking up the ting netgear zing at least I think this is the one I'm gonna get my hands on this is a nice
Wi-Fi hotspot that connects to the ting network has a nice LCD or I think it's OLED screen on it touchscreen
So you can see your signal how many users you have connected your battery life
And then you only pay for what you use so once you buy this and it's unlocked
You own it
It's just six dollars a month for the line and then your data usage and you can turn it on and off and and with a
fifty dollar service credit
Well, I mean you might be able to use this for a few months and not have to pay a dime
And there's no contract after you're done. It's just a six dollar hotspot in your pocket go to a
Linux dot ting comm get that discount also check out their savings calculator. See why ting is really really great
They have a CDMA and GSM network. So I'm gonna be using it
I'm gonna actually I'm hoping to end up with a CDMA and GSM ting device
So that way wherever the signals the best that's the one I'll use for broadcasting on the road
That's slick
I'm still looking into all of that still but I think it's gonna be really great and if I ever have any troubles or if you
Ever have any troubles ting has no hold customer service
You can call them at 1 8 5 5 ting FTW anytime between 8 a.m. Or 8 p.m. East Coast and a real human answers the phone
And they can actually solve your problems and if you're a small business
Definitely definitely definitely look into ting because it is an incredible way to save money
essentially, this has been verified by there's a couple of third parties if you have
Guaranteed if you have between like 11 and 20 employees, you're probably gonna save on ting. It's almost guaranteed
It's it's impossible not to and it goes from there too. It's because it's six dollars
There's no early termination for you can move the phones around. It's easy to manage the lines
You can turn them on and off you can add and remove devices with no penalties
It's so slick and then all the features you'd expect like hotspot and tethering and caller ID and all that stuff with no crazy
Mysterious line items it's and and a really easy to manage dashboard
Go to linux.ting.com and a big thanks to ting ago get that $50 credit or $50 off a ting device and they have a they
Have the whole range of devices GSM and CDMA linux.ting.com and a big thank you to ting for sponsoring Linux unplugged you guys rock
That $50 promo is awesome
Wanted to do a little follow-up from this Sunday's a Linux action show
we talked about go TTY a way to share your your terminal as a web page and
Halifax submitted his use of go TTY after that episode of Linux action. I thought that was so cool
Because he said there's a there's you know a lot of different things you use with go TTY
So I was delighted to see you guys covered it in the last episode
I recently it's just about a week ago started experimenting with go TTY as a bridge between my telnet
SSH BBS and the web and
It's been pretty sweet the author was very responsive on his github page and walking me through a handful of issues
I was having getting the font set up correctly so he has connected his freaking BBS to the web
Using go TTY and if you're watching the video version right now. I'm I'm I'm amazed look at that. That's amazing
It's awesome. That is that is incredible. We have a link in the show notes if you guys want to check it out
But I love this as this is a super solid follow-up
I thought to look at that so I'm gonna type in let's type in Chris LAS
Chris LAS or maybe I should put new in there
Create an account yes, okay, my username is gonna be Chris LAS my origin is Jupiter that seems like that should be good, right?
Only my email. This is Chris at Jupiter broadcasting calm. That's a secret. Don't tell anybody that okay West and my password
I better not I better not say what my password is
Super secret JB password. Yeah, it's super super secret create account. Yes create account boom now. I I'm done now
I'm in his BBS
Using cheese, this is a really nice system look at this. Here's here's the bulletins. Here's rumors. Who's online who else is online right now?
Let's take a look
Just me just Chris LAS. Yeah, I'm a little lonely hmm. That's too bad
This is slick though odd network org slash BBS if anybody else wants to get online
Yeah, I I agree and so spacebar. Yeah, so everybody go go there. We go now
We got somebody else on line. We got anonymous is logging in cool
We're rocking his BBS and look it's moving around my screen because it's you know cuz I don't you cuz you had a CRT monitor
Back in BBS that you see wouldn't want to burn in so every time you refresh. It's awesome
I guess or maybe it's I'm not sure why it's moving around, but
That is really cool. That is that is really great. Thank you Halifax for submitting that into the subreddit
That is some awesome feedback and that going from flash. That's it. That's not flash at all right, so that's yeah
That's a great. That's such a great use of
HTML 5 I guess what you call it I suppose
Okay, I want to talk about this story
Just because I've been trying to contemplate in my head like how exactly would open source a deal if this actually happened
so a couple of different really important people James Comey the director of the FBI and
Admiral Mike Rogers the director of the NSA
and are are both petitioning industry the technology industry specifically Silicon Valley and Congress as well and
They've remained adamant that companies need to install government-friendly backdoors into their encryption products
And I've played some clips quite a few clips actually on our own filter show about this
But this continues to be a trend that legislators are actively considering
because of threat of terrorism and
They're worried that terrorists are using what's happened what not to communicate and so they want to have backdoors
and I I could really care less if they work with Skype or what's apt or
Instagram or Facebook to build in the backdoor that almost seems like a given
But when I start thinking about what if it became a requirement that if this is a communications piece
This is how the legislation is currently sort of being proposed
Communications enabling technology has to have backdoors
Well, there's a lot of things that fall under that category a lot of open source products and projects fall under communications enabling technology
And so I'm I I don't really understand how if law is passed in the US that mandates this
But software is created outside the US by open source developers
how do we reconcile that difference and
Does that software have to comply with the US law to be used in the US West
Do you have any thoughts on the insights on this?
I don't know, but it sounds very negative for I mean
We've seen how much open source is important to business interest these sure and already you see
You know some programs developed outside of the US open BSD comes to mind almost explicitly because they don't want things like this meddling with software
So I don't think would be in our interest to have this. Yeah, I agree and of course
Building and back doors by design is not as a silly as we've seen import restrictions exactly
I wonder if it's to come across as import restrictions anybody in the mumble room have any thoughts as
As we start to talk about this
My first thought is no this should not exist in any way shape or form
In the entire world because it's just gonna compromise everybody in the end
Yeah building in basically making the product insecure by design
My biggest beef on this one from an economic standpoint is don't they realize that this is going to kill
US businesses. Yeah, exactly. I
Also wonder how they think I mean it depends on if it's at the service level
But if the NSA can use a back door into something owner why they're so you know if they're arrogant enough to think that the Chinese
Intelligent service wouldn't be able to find such a back door. Absolutely. Yeah. Yeah, especially as we've seen that, you know
Documentation and information can leak secrets get stolen and source code can be stolen
And then once that gets out there then that then that any anybody that's implemented that product is compromised
that's so that's a
and it seems it seems like extremely dangerous seems like an extremely slippery slope because
What I would worry about is it would force
large
Large companies that work with the government as contractors or the government itself to buy proprietary software and and not
Longer be able to include an open-source option because they don't have these mandated requirements and they would just look at it as they are
Not up to whatever the spec requirements are and they would just simply be disqualified on those grounds
And so they would have to go to vendors like Oracle and Microsoft and Apple or whoever
Cisco whoever instead of implementing an open-source solution because those open boards open-source solutions
Can't be guaranteed to have that and they're not going to be bothered to patch it themselves or whatever. It's probably impractical, right?
It's probably impractical right? They'll just get a bid from one of those companies and that'll be that. Yeah
Oh, yeah, it just makes me really uncomfortable. I think about it and I was specifically I was specifically wimpy outside the US
I'd be really curious what your thoughts are when we make changes like this and how we can mess with people outside the US
Any insight there?
The UK so in bed with the US that
it's pretty much the same or similar legislation and
activities end up being
Adopted over here. So in fact Cameron himself has been making a lot of rumblings about about this very same issue at the same time
Yes, yeah, it's very interesting that both sides of the pond are talking about the same thing at the same time
There's obviously a push behind the scenes here for this
And I mean not to say here and fry conspiracy bacon in a linux show
But it seems pretty obvious on the face of it that they're all talking about at the same time
and it seems like we're surrounded it really does and
And and in the case where open source might be our salvation as users
I feel like it could also that any companies that have to follow these standards and requirements any private companies or any government
Departments they can't use open source. Just I don't like the way it's going
So it's a good thing
The good thing is is the battle isn't over yet
And there's actually a lot of agencies in the government that are also taking opposite stances
the I think the FCC just published something actually today saying that
Solid encryption is is fundamental to protecting us commerce. Yeah, definitely so
Obviously, there's a lot of different angles on this if you are curious about this topic at all
It's something we've been following for for since about April
Pretty pretty consistently in the unfiltered show and you can check out some of our episodes on that
I've played some clips
I think I oh I did actually in the show notes to if you really actually are really concerned about this and I kind of
Would I like to believe that some of you out there actually are even if I even if it's just a fantasy if not us
Then yeah, I linked in the show notes a hearing back in
Jeez, where was it? I'm looking for it right now. It was a hearing back in April
I think about about this topic and about about all of this and it's a very long boring C-Span capture
but it covers the reasons why they want this and how they want it done and it's
They're really working on it. And I just I always I always curious when one when one major nation makes a big decision like that
How it impacts Linux and open source, maybe the audience has some insights on this to Linux action show dot reddit.com and look for episode
Raymond in there a ramen in general
Hammons in the chat room says if it went through wouldn't that mean that fedora and Debbie et cetera would stop shipping security software as
Non-free on the same grounds as things like patent encumbered codecs. That's exactly what I was thinking, too. Is
It all of a sudden. Yeah, I mean, yeah
Cuz the fedora projects and Debian project isn't gonna want to ship stuff that's compromised by design, right? No, it doesn't protect the user. Oh
Boy, you see what a slippery slope this could be
This is something I've been thinking about it just don't I don't quite have an answer to it
And maybe we're overthinking it, but I don't think so. I think it's something that the kids and what are your thoughts? I
Think that the rest of world is smarter. I don't think they'll go along with it
I mean the US could only go so far with with bullying and with
Legislation before the rest of world just says stop it. You're only 5% of the population
You don't get to dictate what they rest in 95% of the world does. Oh
Maybe
Yeah, maybe but a lot of the industry and influences is where they where they're making those decisions right now
So this is probably for their point of time the time to do it. Well, they still have that position
Well, I don't know this is let's let's move on let's this kind of got us down, isn't it?
I'm a little depressing. I'm sorry. I don't want to be I don't yeah, I agree
It is it is very and the value of this is negative. No more with that. So no more with this
Let's actually move on to something. I'm really crazy super excited about I want to talk about
The the road show that we're gonna be doing here in just a little bit
But first, why don't we pick it up? Let's pick up the pace. Let's talk about something that makes me excited
Let's talk about digital ocean
Let's talk about our friends at digital ocean just for a second because you could go over there and create something that makes you feel
Good doesn't make me think about James Comey or Admiral Rogers or whatever
It makes me think about creating Linux servers on-demand because digital ocean is dedicated to offering the most
Simple and intuitive way for you to do that
If you use the promo code do unplugged you get a $10 credit you can get started in less than 55 seconds
You get a machine with 512 megabytes of RAM a 20 gigabyte SSD one CPU and a terabyte of transfer for $5 a month
And if you use our promo code do unplugged you get the $10 credit try that $5 rig for two months
It's pretty nice and digital ocean is data some locations in New York San Francisco Singapore Amsterdam London and a nice one
I mean a really they're all nice, but a really brand new one in Germany
I say that because I drool a drool at the pictures they post online and I love digital oceans interface
It's simple. It's intuitive and you can replicate it on a larger scale with their API
Go over digital ocean just play around with them a little bit create some machines
Destroy some machines update some software feel like a boss and use the promo code you unplugged you can do it all for free
And while you're there, why not follow one of their great tutorials? They're posting new ones all the time
Like here's one that just went up how to automate installing WordPress on Ubuntu 1404 using ansible
how to set up Apache virtual hosts on Ubuntu 1404 now that is
You know every time you do it you get better and better at it
But if you only done it a couple of times boy, this is a really great guy
first of all, a 1404 LTS is a great machine to deploy Apache on and
This is super super nice. It's all the steps you need and it's been gone. It's gone through by technical editor
Look at this. I mean, I'm sorry Arch wiki, but this is this they're quickly becoming like, you know
Go to place. Look at this. This is I mean, you know what?
The thing is is this is just like scratching the surface. They have tons of them
So not only do they have all of these great tutorials
But they also have one click deployment of many many applications that you might want to install ghost WordPress Ruby on rails
Git lab, I mean the list goes on and on in fact, there's we have wave way more now
So just use the promo code do you unplug it a $10 credit and you know speaking of the road trip when I'm on the road?
You know, you know, I'm gonna be using digital ocean and move stuff around bounce our live signal off of it
Did you lotion calm you can get started right now do unplug?
They also have core OS and go check that shenanigans out. It's a pretty cool system
They get updates right from the upstream distro digital ocean calm use the promo code do unplugged big
Thank you digital ocean for sponsoring the unplugged program
So I've been trying to come up with a name for the road show. So Wes Eubanks current on the shows
I'm impressed. I just watched the latest last this morning
Look at you. I doing your homework for you
You were you weren't we honeymooning or moving last week?
I can't remember is I get them all mixed up kind of both got back from my honeymoon and
Then I had to move out of my previous house
So you get married then and then you and then you go on a honeymoon and then you move like all like back to back
To back. Oh, yeah, why didn't you I mean, I mean, I'm not why didn't you either schedule the move or the marriage?
Further apart probably should have there was some yeah, let's just say operational constraints. Okay. I'm very familiar with that
No, I'll be more stable. I understand. I'm very familiar with operational constraints. Let me tell you
Yeah, yeah, that's my world these days. So this road show so I guess I don't have to fully update you
You're pretty current. I'd like to hear it from okay. Oh, well, all right
So well, I'll give you I'll give that I'll get everybody super up-to-date on where we're at
So right now I am planning to go on the road and this is all
Semi lockdown but also as anything that's production-oriented could change at the last minute. So I make that disclaimer, but right now
tentatively planning to get on the road September 19th and
and and and and make the drive from
Everett Washington to Grand Forks, North Dakota
Taking us to know it tells me that we can leave from Everett Washington and make it to his house without taking more than like
Four or five turns off of us to now we're going to but wow, that's a pretty cool concept
So we're gonna see if it's we're gonna that was the basic core concept we get there and then we've committed to doing a last
Cribs edition where I want to go through and tour Noah's house
No, that's a Google glass and take some video of how he automates his house
See if I can find it where he's snuck in some windows or max
Wouldn't that be something? Yes
Scandal exactly and then but the idea is the journey between Everett and Grand Forks, North Dakota
That itself is going to be content. We're going to be recording along the way
We're gonna be trying to produce shows along the way doing meetups along us, too
Between Everett and Grand Forks and starting in Spokane with I'm a con and crew if anybody wants to meet up at that
I'm a come put the brewery in there again, if you would add the roaming penguin. Yeah, that's oh, that's a good name
Yeah, so we're kind of we're trying to come up with a name for the road trip because I should back up
I'm very excited. I'm very excited
So that was the core concept. We started with
months ago when I mean months and months ago when we had a goal on patreon and
And
So we've been trying to figure out how to really do this in a way that's sustainable and
My initial thought was in order to continue to do shows so the shows can continue. I should rent an RV
Because it would be madness to buy an RV just crazy
That would be what the hell am I gonna do with an RV?
So I will rent an RV and it turns out that's like a lot of money
Like I don't normally really sit there and budget and plan things out
It's not my style, but in this one particular case like Noah was here and we had the crew we had the whole crew here
We all we were going down or broke down all the numbers and we looked at it. It's like it's gonna cost us
Over six thousand dollars just to rent an RV to do this road trip Wow. Yeah
and so because they also have to pay for like like 38 cents a mile for gas and stuff like that, so it's very expensive and
that was like, oh, I totally took the wind out of the sails and
Then I started the search process just to see what it would cost to just get a lightweight trailer to pull with my truck
that I have already and
Like I looked at like teardrop
units and because you know, I'm telling you price range is low here because we don't have a lot to work with and
I found a unit that
Folks were selling because the owner was having some health issues and he only taken on three trips
he did twice down to California once to the Oregon coast and they live here in Washington and
I
Go through it's a 25-foot trailer and it was just about right, you know, it's not quite like
like like an Airstream or something like that, but it's still it's a it's a fine trailer and
The deal was all getting finalized and I was about ready to like I thought maybe we could even do a show out of it
But the gentleman selling to me had a heart attack last week. Oh, that's terrible. Yeah, it's awful
It's awful. And so it completely derailed the deal for a couple of days, but more important things on their mind
Yeah, sure. So we managed but things are picking back up this week. So that's good
So I managed to get a fantastic deal because they needed to get rid of this RV pretty bad
And so I got a fantastic deal on a trailer that I'm gonna load up on September 19th
ideally and hit the road and then meet up with people along the way do broadcasts and
We'll see where I have connectivity and I don't yeah, and I'm gonna take it over the Stevens Pass
I've never pulled a trailer over Stevens Pass. I don't have an engine break
But I'm gonna take it over the pass. It should be fine
And yeah
And and meet up with people and I on the other side and I'm really really looking forward to it
And so this so a zero con 34 had a couple ideas to name the road show
I'm trying to come up with a good name for this road
So we're gonna be doing you know many of the shows from the road including last and unplugged and so he wrote says Chris mentioned
He was looking for a silly name for the new mobile studio in his RV
And he says here was an idea for the show name the whole enchilada show
a whole enchilada show I don't know about that one the other suggestions that
Other suggestions came in the mobile oriented broadcast and Linux entertainment, which the acronym without for that would be mobile
That's pretty clever good JB tube was is not is also available
The the free bird I like that that's not bad actually at the free bird the roaming penguin again comes up
So anyways that mummer if you guys have any ideas from what we should name the road trip the Linux action show road show
That's not bad Chatham's throwing some at us right now shuttle pod 5. I
Don't know why I like that what I do
That's pretty good too free birds not bad, and it's a JCO trailer, too
So it has birds on it already, and we could put a penguin on there. Oh, yeah, I get the J
I like the free bird. I'm gonna write that one down. I'm writing that down
We've got a couple of votes for free bird. That's not bad. He's actually writing it on paper guys. Yeah, I stressingly old-school
Yeah, that's actually how I commit things to memory. I find if I actually write them down
So I don't know exactly how we're gonna do this. We're gonna try to power the broadcast from the rig using Linux
Oh, this is exciting. Yeah. Yeah, we're gonna try to actually make everything DC powered, too
Which should be an interesting challenge, so we'll have a couple a couple of Linux laptops
Probably one of them running nice cast or ice cast or whatever
But there's actually a problem called, but I mean there's a lot of different ones we could use
That well, I don't know
We're gonna use something to send a signal back and Skype and and then we're gonna do local recording so with audio quality should be pretty
Good, so it shouldn't shouldn't be that bad unless there's a bunch of background noise or something like that
And I wonder if I wonder if it's this real stretch goal of mine would be to be actually able to broadcast
While the rig is moving. Oh, that would be amazing
I don't know where that'd be possible that I have to make sure I have really good signal
But I think it'd be amazing to a show while the moosh while the rigs actually going down the road live stream
You just quietly drive for hours. No, I wouldn't be driving doing show at the same time. That's way too distracting
so if you would like to help out with our effort, I would more than appreciate that because I'm the the wish list is
Posted and the list is long right now the big thing the big thing that I'm really thinking
I'm probably not gonna be able to purchase and so if somebody out there is in a position to be able to afford it is
the
Cell phone booster kit which boosts all 4g LTE signals
Oh really from all the networks you press you put an antenna up on a metal plate on top of the
Traylor and then it has a plate that it connects to inside the rig and then it rebroadcast all LTE signals
So some people in the reviews I've read say maybe if you have one bar
This thing will transform it into four bars
And I'm thinking that's the difference between doing a show and not doing a show
however
the problem is it's 380 bucks and
The installation is probably gonna be another 400 bucks
Which just paying for the installation loans about all I can afford right plus I'm getting other things installed on the rig as well and getting
some things removed
That would be one that it could make the difference between being able to do show and not be able to do a show and it's
One that I don't think I can buy
So that would be high on my list if somebody could afford that we have the wish list linked in the show notes
There's also other things on there like
Everything like toilet paper. I mean anything you can do to help would be greatly appreciated because tomorrow
I'm taking the truck in and I'm getting it sort of ready
You know there's a lot of small things on your vehicle when you drive five ten miles a day
You don't really care that it's out of alignment or the tires need rotation
or that you're a 1500 miles over on your oil or that your mirror is shaking or that your e-brake hasn't worked for three years or
The niceties you know or that you've never had your cooling system flush
You don't care about these things when you're just driving five ten miles a day, but then we're gonna be towing a
25-foot trailer
3,000 miles
Plus then these are things you need to look into so tomorrow
I'm taking the truck in and getting all that work done on it
Which pretty much soaks up pretty much any all the free spending yeah, yeah, so if anybody does want to help out
We have the wish link linked in the show notes and as I go along
I'll be posting videos and things like that, too
So hopefully it's gonna be a ton of fun, and if something blows up in my face
I plan to record that too. I'm not just gonna repost the good stuff. Oh
Yeah, yeah, if I end up with a flat on the side of the road
I'm gonna turn it into content. I am bound to determine to make the best out of it
It's all you'll be doing while you wait for the tow truck. Yeah, yeah, and so I don't know
I'll have the mumble room with me or Wes potentially you could be here in studio
And I could be you know you'd be here
Maybe jumping and getting them pulling the mumble room in because the show's got to go on I'd love to help that'd be great
So you so and then we'll still have somebody local in studio when I'm out on the road
Somebody says get triple-a. That's probably not a bad idea there. I should look into the cost triple-a
Yeah, maybe you can do it for just a month or whatever yeah
I'm like I wonder if they have like a limited thing and I'm getting insurance too for the trailer
They're these business things you have to do for a road trip anybody in the mumble room have an RV
I'm screwed. I got nobody get advice from I'm all out on my own on this
I've been watching YouTube videos and reading how to's and I think I actually might have made a good move not ending up with an
Airstream, maybe I was reading about wireless signals and getting wireless in and out of oh
it looks like those airstreams sometimes are a little difficult on that and
Also also
I'm like pre marking down like areas along us to where I think I can might be able to get Wi-Fi if there's no cellular
Signal and I got an email from somebody's like hey Chris. Why don't we meet up here?
This is probably your last best place to get good internet in Montana
And I'm looking at the map, and it's like way way way way way way way east
All right way west on Montana, so it's way early in the trip
And I'm looking at going you mean I don't have good internet for like the rest of Montana
I'm gonna go crazy space. I'm gonna go crazy
So I probably download those coverage maps before you leave yeah, yeah, yeah, I wouldn't picture any Wi-Fi signal either coming out of there
So yeah there you go. I'm pretty excited. That's the latest try to think there's any other up
Yeah, so I'm gonna be posting more videos to our patrons to that for people to check that out
But it doesn't be an interesting challenge a live mobile Linux power broadcast
And I don't know there's anybody else done that. I don't know of anyone
Is this first is this first? I don't know it could be a first. You should probably just start calling it
Actually that's what I was thinking token rings is in the chat room said it might do me some good to disconnect from time to
time
Yeah, especially in the mountains and
Yeah, like a glacier National Park and stuff. Yeah, I know Darren. I know I'm not saying it's the first mobile Roadshow
I'm saying I think it's the first
Linux powered Linux powered mobile Roadshow that's the important part. I think so
I think that's it's the first Linux powered mobile Roadshow. Oh, and you know what speaking of the wish list I
Almost moved on and completely forgot to mention this the first item off the wish list did arrive because I mentioned it on last
On Sunday and it came from Noah and it is the black tank empty kit, which is the poop hose
so this is the poop hose I'll be using on the road trip to empty the
Piss and poo from the RV and Noah got it from me off the wish list. Isn't that great?
So that was his special contribution right there to the road trip. No, I'm that's not his only contribution, but he got me a nice 15 foot
Was it rhino flex sewer kit rhino flex sewer kit and
Do you know why you want a clear swivel connector right there?
I do not so that way when you flush out your black tank
You can see the water turn from brown to clear. Oh, so, you know, you know, it's clear, you know, it's clean
I think this means you might not be welcome to use Noah's bathroom when you get there
You think that's some subtle? Yeah, maybe you're probably right. Yeah. Well, you know, it's funny is I liked it
Cuz this was Noah's real nice way of saying you're not welcome to stay at the house as you said to me
He's like have all the facilities. He's like hey, man
So would you just prefer that I just arrange a hotel for you and when you get here and I'm like, right?
They're like I was planning to stay in the RV. He's like, oh, okay
I think he was just trying to make sure I wasn't planning to stay in the house
Right, like you can come in and do the last Cribs tour, but you can't stay in the house
That's what I please mark a mile away from the property. Yeah, give us a good 15 minutes notice before you come over
yeah, we'll see I and and then if something really dramatically goes wrong and
Like I don't I can't do any I can't get any connectivity
So like like I can't show up for unplugged or something like that Noah's offered to stand in and do the broadcast from his studio
using OBS and Linux and
Probably Skype to do the shows so he can stand in as an emergency host if for some reason on the road trip
I'm completely unavailable which means I'll allow myself also to just if that happens
I'll just take the day off and let Noah handle it which is
which I think would be really nice and then like
For tech snap we're pre-recording because Alan's going to be traveling of course so we're not even gonna be doing tech snap on the weeks
That I'm gonna be gone anyways, so that shows taken care of so it's really a perfect time. It's just all working out
I'm looking forward to it
I'm really looking forward to it, but we could use your help if anybody does want to help us out
I'll have a link in the show notes, so I have I
Want to say goodbye to an old friend?
I maybe I don't know. I don't know if software has a has a sex or a gender, but oh just pot
pot-kettle I just suggested the fecal matters of Chris lass as as
No, no that is not a title suggestion
Okay, so we have an old friend to say goodbye to somebody who's brought us through good times and bad times somebody who's really brought
us up
I'll tell you more about that here in just a second first
I want to tell you about our friends at Linux Academy go to linuxacademy.com slash unplugged and check out Linux Academy
It's a great resource to learn more
About anything around Linux and open source they have a great set of guides
Comprehensive study guides you can pull down scenario based labs they have instructor help available and nuggets to deep-dive into singular topics
I love it. You've heard me talk about them before but something new is happening at Linux Academy. They're hiring
They're looking for great new content creators who want to join a high quality and fast-paced team
Long-term contract part-time potentially full-time for the right candidates
They have a few opportunities are looking to fill with DevOps professionals and developers
They're looking for Linux and C++ development bash pearl and Python instructions
I'm sorry instructors
They want instructors who are seeking to share their knowledge and have a passion for teaching others
If this is something that sort of pushes a button for you
I want you to consider getting paid for by Linux Academy
They're looking also for big data machine learning developers who would love to share their knowledge with a passionate community inside Linux Academy. I
Love I love that our sponsors are coming to us and saying we want to hire your audience because they're that great
This is this is such an awesome trend. This is such a great way for these sponsorships to go to be to
In multiple cases now our sponsors come so we'd like to hire from your audience
This is this is such a great opportunity because you've you've heard me talk about what a great company
They are and why why we work with them and need now you have a chance to join their team
Also, if you're not interested in video creation
They're also looking for certified professionals to help increase the practice exams database Linux Academy
Is going to be paying between a dollar to twenty five dollars for practice exam questions depending on the quality depth and accuracy of the questions
So if you're interested give them like your cover letter your resume and info about you
Send it to career at Linux Academy dot com
career at Linux Academy comm and if you want to go get a job over there check them out if you're interested in signing up for
Linux Academy learning more about Amazon Web Services or learning something like Python or Ruby on rails or how to manage a Linux system properly
Go to Linux Academy and get our special discount when you go to Linux Academy comm slash unplugged you get a 33% discount
Linux Academy comm slash unplugged and career no s career at Linux Academy comm if you are interested in getting a job
I think it's so cool. They're hired from our audience. It's just
It's because there's smart people out there smart people. I love you guys. Alright, so let's talk about our old friend
You guys probably saw the news
Lilo is
going to
cease development on
December
Lilo comes to an end the old Linux loader the development of Lido Lilo as a classic bootloader
was restarted in
2010 Lilo has some advantages because it's super simple and a lot of people liked it over grub and grub 2
But the developer says that because of limitations with butter fs GPT partition tables and even rate itself
He's kind of done. If someone wants to develop this further
He's willing to take submissions
Bye bye Lilo. What do you think Wes? What's uh, are you sad when things like this happen, you know?
It definitely had its place in history
Personally, I've never relied on it, you know between grub and sis Linux and now you know EFI does it itself?
I actually think it's good thing. Yeah, I think so too. I mean we only need so many solutions
It's good to have more than one. Yeah, and this is the natural cycle of software something gets created
It's useful for a long time something new comes along and we make room for the for the new stuff and this service purpose
So well and because the codes open it never goes fully away. Yeah, you want to use it for your own custom solution
Go ahead. I actually think Lilo is a perfect example of how open source code started
It was created to solve a problem people thought it was no longer useful
It was kind of put away and then in 2010
They came back out and he said actually we can take this code that already exists and we can make it relevant again and people
it got a whole new resurgence and
I don't think you'd ever have seen that with a commercial product because you can't do it because the light stuck
Yeah, I actually think it's a great example of the open source life cycle
I'm trying to think of other projects that I'm familiar with in mobile room
If you guys have any suggestions of projects that have been really big and then just so sort of faded away over time
You know, obviously there's been distros like mandrake and mandriva
But individual projects I was trying to think of besides Lilo that have been so important to us at one point
And now have sort of faded away
Doom
Doom no cork, you know not doom. Yeah, I don't know. I think that's it's an interesting
It's it makes me appreciate the contribution that they do make while they're here and you kind of make me realize not everything's gonna
Last forever and it is a lot of work to keep up with the you know changing file systems and XMMS not maybe XM
Yeah, you know some old old old X desktop applications sis Linux sis Linux open office
I don't I think open office is still around for the most part. Yeah
It's an it's an interesting way to look at those kinds of kind of projects in that
DOS
No, no, I can't I look at this to the history of this thing version 23.0 came out in 2010 and then version
24 was released in 21 in 2013. So it's three years between major major releases. So it's not like it was super rapid rapid
Rekha says gnome to star office. Yeah
Yeah, star office is yes still sis Linux is still used broadly. Yes
Star office was was a big one mumble room. Do you guys have any projects that have faded away that you used to?
No, okay. Nobody's very talkative in there today
Yeah, don't even get me started on BOS that yeah, oh boy, yeah, I my BOS experience was really solid
I've talked about we've talked about it before we did
Heroku, is that what replaced it? Is that what came along there open-source? Oh, thank you. Thank you. Yeah
Yeah, we did a haiku episode years ago. You guys remember that
Thank you action show
That's what people call it. Yeah, the haiku action show
We didn't actually we didn't I don't think I don't think we actually named it that but yeah
At the haiku is a pretty fun operating system to check out you guys too. Anyways
Lilo coming to an end you guys can see the announcement in the show in December
Maybe we'll throw a little party for it. Maybe maybe I'll give it a try before it goes
Wait forever, give it one more boot up a couple things. Yeah, I
Like that West that's nice. Good way to send it out. We should do like a boy. That would be really interesting
It's just like a classic Linux distro. That's old kernel using Lilo. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah system D. What? No, no
Hey guys
If you have any any projects any submissions for that kind of thing Linux action show dot reddit dot com go find episode 100
Nate and submit it there or any stories or submissions for this year show
you can go over there Linux action show dot reddit dot com and
Submit that to us. I'd really like to hear your thoughts on the whole NSA stuff, too
Kind of you know
What's going on there with the how would open source respond to that if backdoor encryption?
Was like mandated having backdoors in the interesting to hear from some people from other countries. Yes, exactly
Yes, exactly
And then also with the the debate continues on over over at the Linux action show if Richard Stallman ever needs to have actually installed
I've never installed Gnu slash Linux that debate continues to to rant to age on as well as the combo to site revamp and
A thread about diehard keystroke
Keystroke launcher folks and I have a quick I have a quick one that I'd like to throw to the audience and he runs down
By the way, gnome do and synapse and others I at some point, you know in gnome 3
When you hit the meta key or the super key or the Windows key
Whatever you want to call it it brings over the activities overview and then you can start searching immediately. I love that me too
That's that's pretty much how I use it as a launcher
Some point sometime my main machine upstairs. I accidentally remapped that super key
Yeah
And I have no idea how to undo that like I cannot I cannot use super key anymore
And I've gone in I've gone into gnome settings and keyboard and shortcuts and I don't see anything wrong there
I just can't set it anymore and it's driving me crazy
If anybody knows how to revert that back like if there's some G comp file like and I don't know what I could do
I I missed be able to hit the meta key and launch my oh, that's confusing. Yeah, and because it's upstairs
I can't ever troubleshoot on there. Otherwise, I would try that a little bit go TT wine
We can get the mobile room right on your machine. Yeah. Yeah, that's true, right?
I actually I was thinking if I if I can't figure it out
I might just switch over to one of these
To one of these other ones that were just linked to the subreddit
Cooper is one looks like it's QT. You have gnome do synapse Albert
Albert how about that mutate? Let me look at that one, too
This is a really pretty solid lineup including the built-in krunner unity and gnome shell launchers
I'm looking at mutate the award-winning productivity application. Hmm. Okay, it's in the AUR that meant that meets my requirements
Albert's looking good though. Look at Albert Wes. Look at this Albert an amazing desktop environment agnostic omni launcher
The back end will be written at the end of February. Oh, well, okay, it's after February
So these launchers are super look he's doing math in the launcher. He's doing Google searches in there, huh?
I think that's I might Albert might be want to check out
That might be one to look at. I don't know. I see it looks like it has looks like 27 days ago
It was last ice pretty active looks like it's using qt5
So you need to have qt5 installed on your system. That's Albert. So he has I'll link to this in the in the show notes
He's gone through and done a really good job
SB 5 6 6 3 7 in the subreddit and really summarize the current state
Like one of the things I like here is like he when he's separating out the different launchers
He mentions that gnome do had his last released in January 22nd 2014. Yeah
Yeah, so that's that is the issue with gnome do is that it doesn't have a lot of active elements
So he's done a really really superb job. In fact, that's
That is really great work that he took he spent some serious time writing this up
So I'll link to that if you guys are curious about this if you haven't tried to have you ever tried to launch your West
Yeah, I used to use gnome do pretty heavily. Yeah, why'd you stop? I just launched everything from the terminal now. Yeah
Oh, really? Yeah, mostly really well, I use fish like you do a lot of things on my machine anyway
Yeah, and and and what's your main desktop environment?
No, no, I use awesome. Okay, so that makes sense. Yeah, so they have a yeah that
Oh boy, well then we should have you do a segment on here one day one week about why you use awesome
Oh, yeah, that'd be fun. Yeah, and what did you switch from?
Well, would you use before awesome? Oh, no three, how we certainly did you make this transition? Uh, it's been
No, probably better part of a year. Really? Yeah, really and so you went from gnome
What that would have been what gnome 312 ish timeline 360 now 312 ish timeline 312
Yeah, and you and you went to awesome. Yeah, and I still I mean I still love no, you know
I put it on friends. You're blowing my mind. I use cinnamon at work, which not the Italian window managers are so so crazy. It's just
For some reason I pegged you as a gnome 3 gun. I can't remember what we had said. Well, I do I do really like it
Yeah, yeah for you know when I want to show off Linux and make it look really feel violated now
Everybody tells me I should try it and we did do one episode on awesome at one point
And it just for me it and I wonder why if you don't feel it feel it feels for me like going back in time
You know, I do understand that from time to time I do
You know like integros has a beautifully configured gnome 3. Yeah. So like yeah, I use that as my go-to live CD for a lot of things
Yeah, so I really appreciate it or if I want to just like show off slick shiny Linux. Mm-hmm
Mostly I just don't need I prefer to mount things myself and you know a lot of the little things where I yeah
I'd rather I have my own set up for it already and
You crazy you crazy. Yeah, we should okay. We should do an unplugged episode on tiling window managers
Anybody in the mumble room on a tiling window manager? I three is pretty great, too
Yeah, that's the one I was thinking about trying actually was I three
No, I'm so playing with plasma five. Yeah, how's that been going?
Well, I'm on the beta one now and it's it's getting there. It's getting better
So I'm hoping looking forward to 1510 maybe even put all my new desktop finally. Hmm
Fascinating. Well if you guys want to see us do a tiling window manager episode in love
I'm not quite sure how I think we would need people in the mumble room that
Are involved or that are running it? That's how I would like to do it. I think
Yeah, sounds like okay that sounds like that might be a good idea I suppose I could try it I
Just don't want to waste a week of productivity doing something
I don't love but if people if we had a few people in the mumble room
So because I mean maybe it'd be okay
But if we had a few other people maybe long timers plus you'd be here that might
There might be a decent product could be a good segment. It could be a good segment
All right
I had to I wanted to answer one question before we left the show today because we've talked on and off about running
Linux on Macbooks on unplugged from we tried it with Angela's laptop and some other folks went out and pop MacBooks and try it
Well Jose writes in with a question
That I think a lot of you are probably gonna run into if you have if you've ever tried Linux on a MacBook or you know
Anybody out there who is and he says a year back
I wrote an asking for help getting links on my HP notebook
After a lot of research, I finally got arch running flawlessly. However, I need some help again about six six months ago
I really wanted a new laptop and I was looking at getting the Dell XPS 13
But my mother and girlfriend got me a MacBook Pro retina
with with the iris pro graphics
2014 edition as a gift for finishing my PhD. Well, congratulations Jose says I won't lie. I really like the build quality or it's Josie
I'm not sure
But all but not all that crazy about OS 10, right?
About a month ago. I installed anti-gross, but I have two huge problems
Number one the battery life drops from seven hours to three hours and number two the temperature on the laptop goes way up just by
Watching a simple video and the fan goes crazy. I wonder if you guys have any ideas
I've tried to browse the arch wiki, but it hasn't been all that helpful
I really like to run Linux full-time, but I can't solve these issues if I can't solve these issues. I'm going back to OS 10
So the first issue
Seven hours or three hours. I think partially might be which graphics card you're using. So if you're using say the built-in
Dedicated graphics versus the iris graphics that's going to use way more power
But the major problem you have in my opinion with Linux on MacBooks is that SMC controller you familiar with this only broadly
Yeah, the SMC controller is really responsible for a lot of the thermal management and probably I don't know a lot of other
Regulative things towards power and whatnot in the MacBook. It's custom. It's a custom Mac thing. There's no driver for Linux available. So
The fans and temperature management are all done proactively under OS 10
In fact OS 10 even is aware of CPU load and GPU load and how that relates to potential heat increase and will preemptively
increase the fans to cool the machine and
All of that is done in software inside the OS 10 operating system
And the reality is that what you get when you don't run OS 10 on a MacBook is
You get essentially the hard limit thermal controls that keeps the hardware alive. So you get these weird
swings from
Low thermal management to extreme thermal management where the fans kick up and he says I'm watching a video and my fans go crazy
I don't have a great fix for this and I'm wondering if people in the subreddit or in the mumble room or in the IRC do
But here's uh, oh look here is the air is saying there's a thermal daemon on github. You might build a search for
Not specifically for max thermal D is not specifically for max
But so so the thermal D I'll put a link to that in the show notes
I don't know about that specifically but
What I do know has worked and it's a little hokey and it does require that you have a little OS 10 install on the
Machine and itsy bitsy in OS 10 install which I actually do recommend anyways
Because it's the only way you can do important you if I and other firmware updates that would help protect you against things like Thunder
Strike
So I recommend you do keep a little OS 10 on there despite the hard drive space that comes at a premium on those Mac SSDs
If you boot into OS 10 before you boot into Linux and don't shut off
But just reboot don't power the machine off
But just reboot boot into OS 10 first and install an app called SMC fan controller now
SMC fan controller has been around for a really really long time. And what it does is it controls?
Statically the fans under OS 10 so you can go in there and what you can do is build different fan controller profiles
medium high sound low sound and
If you're going to be gaming you would set it to the higher profile
If you're not going to be gaming you would set it to the lower profile and if you're gonna be watching videos
Maybe you set to a medium profile and then you boot into Linux now
It's not ideal
But what it does is it sets a new baseline for the fan RPMs
So you could say instead of having them spin at 800 rpm
You could have a baseline of 15 or 2,000 rpm with the max about 6,000 where you actually start to hear them
So you could go in and say set your baseline level RPMs at a thousand RPMs or 2,000 RPMs
It's slightly louder than it would be under OS 10 just slightly
But it can run much longer that way before it has to kick into the crazy thermal management
This is a really hokey workaround. There's got to be a better way to do this
But if you do have a mini OS 10 install, that's one way to do it. This is Nate says
There is some Mac fan CTL D. I use it with Ubuntu. No, we never have any problems
So check out Mac fan CTL D. That could be another very nice. Yeah
That's really cool. Thank you Nate Mac
See Mac fan CTL D. I have not I don't I don't I don't have any any more Mac books with Linux on them at the moment
So it's like one of those things to you where it's so specific to you know, the different models and versions
Yeah, it does change right and then Apple can just get it just right and then the next version when you go buy a Mac
Book with one port and it has completely different stuff. So
Yeah, that's a rough way to go. But I know the people like those Mac books. We get a lot of emails about it
So if somebody has some solid solid links like Nate there
I would love it if you'd add it to episode 108 over at the subreddit Linux action show
Dot-reddit dot-com and then other people could benefit from that as well
So Linux unplugged is live on Tuesdays 2 p.m. Pacific can go to jblive.tv to join us
We have the chat room there. We also have a mumble room info so you can hang out in our virtual lug
If you're not quite sure what 2 p.m
Pacific is I don't blame you because I realize now I'm gonna have to try to figure out time zones as I go across the US
I'm like, ah crap. What am I gonna do? And then it was pointed out to me Chris. Just go to do a broadcasting comm
So that's calendar. I'm smart guy already set that up. Yeah, I too will be using the calendar on the road trip
I will be feeling your pain audience. So no judgment
also
we love feedback Jupiter broadcasting comm slash contact choose unplugged from the drop-down and
Send in your emails Linux actually reddit comm West. Thanks for joining me. My pleasure. Thanks for having me
All right, buddy. See you right back here next Tuesday
All
Right now we both JB titles calm JB titles calm only grab this one second. There you go. All right. There we go
Hello coming on the possibility of unfiltered Colorado high note
Haha, if I'm gonna be in car, I don't think I'm gonna be in Colorado. I'm taking us to I
Don't think I'll be there a high note from Colorado. Although I Colorado could happen on the return trip
We're gonna break from us to on the road on the return trip and take in more of an indulgent route home
So it's always possible. Oh that new Google logo. Oh, look at that. Look at that. Oh
I kind of missed the serifs honestly, really
Backdoors for the clueless. Do you have a lot a list of plan stops on us to know Billy?
I'm hoping people want to do meetups and contact me. I need I need meet it
I can if you do meetups, is there a way to do like meetup suggestions on meetup calm?
I don't I don't know. That's I don't know
Yeah
What highly window manager should we force Chris to use for a week?
I do remember that now that we do this see the results were i3 by 54 percent. So apparently we've discussed this
Yes, I do recall discussing this now
Oh boy, see I I was I was see Matt Matt was Matt had my back on the anti
He was an anti Tyler too. So it was easier for me to avoid having to deal with the tiling issue on the show
However now that you're here and you've got tiling preferences now and now got the mumbo-mumbo. Look at this
I 380 votes on it. I look at this. Look at this at a 148 votes. This is no good. This is I
I think you should wait till after the road trip that way you don't get too many things going on
That's probably a good point or maybe we do it on the road trip
Really everything up. Yeah, just like uphaul everything in my life
Why not back doors for the Calusa isn't bad the fecal matters of Chris last while in security by design back door complaint
Lilo bought a boom luxury furry road open source back doors
Hmm smoky on the penguin. That's not bad either. Man. These are some good ones JB titles calm
Dude you're getting shot by a machine gun. Watch out you're getting shot by a machine gun. You better be careful
Keep the bummer room safe everyone. Yeah, it kind of reminds me of how like the original Phil Zimmer
Like the 90s with PGP encryption how that was like you can't export this encryption and stuff like that
And they were fighting for that back then
Yeah, yeah, I know right use Windows for a week. I
Actually wouldn't do that. I
Have some pride
We just drive me crazy the fecal matters of Chris last cannot be our title
I don't think that's a very good title for Linux unplugged. I don't really think that's not accurate
I mean if that's what the episode was about. Yeah, that's true. I mean I could I could definitely do an episode about that. Trust me
Trust me. I was surprised nobody had any nice parting words in the mumble room to say about Lilo, you know is solid
Let's really be ready for death. I guess it's just we've all moved on right? We have all moved on it is time
And jalapeno ale. Yeah, I do need to do that. You're right. I'm a con you're right
So I'm a con I'm gonna have a camera when we're at our meetup
So I should probably get this I kind of get this figured out. I need a meetup on demand
So so basically I'll be I'll just be spawning meetups as I go
So sign up at meetup comm slash Jupiter broadcasting spawning them was spawning them coming out everywhere
just I'll just awash in meetups, I don't actually know if that's true or not because
Us too has long spots where there's nobody around we got to like share your location to you like a where's Chris?
Hmm like a beacon. Yeah, exactly like a JB Road beacon. Yeah
Get up at 2 in the morning and check where Chris is
I wonder how I would actually practically do that in a way that would actually be doable
I saw something that used open street maps and like you could set it up that would be amazing
You could plot where you were going if there's a way to do that and it doesn't cost a bunch of money
I'll see oh totes do it. That'd be fun. I'm a room you see too
Yeah
Don't find out and then you can wallow you can follow me as I go and then if I get stuck on the side of the road
You can alert somebody cuz I might be somewhere. There's no cell so cuz how's that gonna work if it doesn't have Celsius?
Yeah, I assume there'll be some big hole. Yeah, that's true. Yeah. Yeah car tracker thing
Hmm Lila was two letters ago. That's funny Rick guy. That's good way to put it. Yeah, low jack Chris last low jack