Did you share those notes today there, Mr. Chris?
Now, okay.
What?
There are no notes?
Oh, beautiful.
Beautiful.
That's a good part to start the show right there then.
This is Linux Unplugged episode 176 for December 20th, 2016.
Welcome to Linux Unplugged, your weekly Linux talk show that's currently celebrating its
last live production of the year.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Hello, Wes.
There is a tradition on the Jupiter Broadcasting Network that we don't always choose to take
advantage of, but from time to time, and I feel like this is the year we're going to
do it.
Oh, yeah.
No rules shows, the last live show.
Anything could happen.
These are probably going to be awful, and so it's why we never do it like this.
We never do it like this, but if there was any show to go, no rules, no prep, it's this
show.
And it kind of worked out, because I have this debilitating carpal tunnel in both my
hands right now.
Oh, no.
I don't mean to be laughing.
It's the worst thing ever.
The only way to deal.
Yeah, it is.
I can't even lift up the bowl of cereal or put my seatbelt on.
So I thought, well, what a great day not to have to put a dock together.
Yeah, right?
No typing.
What a great excuse to just not worry about it.
So coming up on this week's episode, we're going to throw out the playbook.
We're going to look at the worst of 2016.
What was the worst in Linux in 2016?
We're going to talk about some of that.
Then we're going to look forward to 2017.
Jack Wallins got an article that actually got me thinking about what might be coming
down the pipe.
Not a full-fledged predictions episode, but I want to give the virtual lug a chance to
chime in before we sail into 2017.
And then, at the end of the show, like a maniac, I'm going to hand the reins over to Noah,
and he's going to answer some calls and chat small business and GNU slash Linux.
I've heard of that.
Yeah, it's new.
And they're going to talk about it on the phone.
You can just get in there and take calls.
So why don't we get started by bringing in that virtual lug?
Hello, Mama Robe.
Hello, hello.
Hello, hello, hello.
And hey, guys, thanks for being here on our last episode of the year.
It's not really the last one, because tomorrow or next Tuesday, we'll have a clip show of
all the different stuff throughout the year, which is a great one, by the way.
If you want to spread Linux Unplugged for the holidays, toss them a clip show.
You know it's going to be good.
It's all your favorite moments.
It's going to be passable, though.
I'm kidding.
It's going to be good.
You won't hate yourself after.
The beard's been sprinkling his beard magic all over it.
Yeah, so I didn't want to have any rules.
I wanted to let the mumble room and the conversation go any direction it goes.
So I thought I'd kind of cue us up with a couple of things.
And then I'm going to do the reads for all the sponsors here in a minute.
Just do them all right here at the top of the show.
All right.
And we're just going to do them.
And then however long the show goes, it goes.
And we're going to call it good.
We're going to call it good.
Hey, check in with Grand Forks, North Dakota.
Noah, are you on the line?
Are you there?
Yes, sir.
Over.
Mr. Chris.
That might be a bit excessive.
I may be on my phone, but I don't think we have to I don't think we have to have like
a transition of speaking and thinking.
I think we can handle that.
Over.
10-4 good, buddy.
Yeah.
10-4, Noah.
Get out the telegraph.
Come on, Noah.
So what's going on over there?
Are you are you getting set up to take calls here in a little bit on the show?
Well, I spent I spent a little bit of time getting some levels tweaked and getting some
equipment set up.
I'm actually on my phone because I've used up all of my audio interfaces in the studio
and I don't want to monkey with any of the levels, but.
Oh, my God.
Okay.
All right.
Good.
Well, it's setting the bar high.
So what we're going to do is we're going to shut down production at some point and then
do a quick little swap-a-roo and bring up Grand Forks.
Hold on a second.
Where's my here?
Let's this is just something that I just so we have the context in which Noah is working
right now.
I feel like it'd be useful for us to know what's the temperature in Grand Forks, North
Dakota right now.
It's twenty nine degrees in Grand Forks right now.
Not bad.
No.
Geez.
Congratulations.
No, I'm really happy for you, man.
That's some good news.
So, yeah.
Okay.
Good.
I feel like we got a good show.
We got a good show on our hands here today.
I'm ready to dive into the worst of 2016.
And I thought I had I had like I think what I want to do is I wanted I want to set the
bar as to what I think was the worst thing that could have happened to a tech company
in 2016.
And then we want to talk within the context of Linux about that.
So I've got a couple of ideas, but I feel like once we really get the ball rolling,
that's when we're going to get some stuff.
So that'll probably be thanks to the Mumble Room.
They'll probably be doing some of the heavy lifting there.
But why don't we.
So let's do this.
Are you ready, Wes?
Oh, I'm ready.
Do you feel like you've bought you prepared your body for this?
Well, we'll see.
Well, there's only one way to find out.
That's by doing.
So let's thank the folks that sponsored this show all year long.
And I really appreciate Linux Academy and I appreciate those of you who visited Linux
Academy dot com slash unplugged this year or those of you who plan to soon Linux Academy
dot com slash unplugged.
That's where you go to sign up for a platform to train you all about Linux.
And when you go to Linux Academy dot com slash unplugged, you can get a seven day free trial.
Courseware is great.
It's constantly being improved.
The virtualization system is slick.
They spin up these systems on demand when you need them.
The servers match the distributions you've chosen for the courseware automatically.
They have content availability planning.
They have instructors you can speak to when you need actual human help.
But hot off the presses right here, Wes.
This week, got an email.
I mean, I got a press announcement.
No, it's just an email I got here from Anthony and he says, here's a couple of new courses
we've got working on over at Linux Academy.
Machine learning with Azure, PowerShell Essentials.
Now this, these two first ones right here are fascinating to me because they are on
Linux Academy's Linux platform.
It's using these tools in combination with Linux, which that really, if that doesn't
tell you 2016, right?
It doesn't that the fact that Linux Academy.
PowerShell on Linux.
On Linux Academy.
This is really, I mean, when I saw this, I thought, wow, Linux.
And it also tells you how they stay up to date with what stuff people are actually looking
for to learn.
Right on the bulls.
They also have launched their iOS and Android apps this year, which is a great way to train
when you're on the go.
And they're launching serverless concepts, which was cool because they started with a
live stream where you can join the instructors from Linux Academy, a couple of different
ones, as they discuss serverless concepts and get you started with that.
They have new live labs to get you started with AWS.
This is one of the things I think is really great because it's not just the essentials.
It's like the stuff that is really big high level services stuff like AWS and Azure and
OpenStack and Docker and the things that, you know, look really great on a resume too.
And they help you get those certifications you might need as well.
LinuxAcademy.com slash unplugged.
And a big thank you to Linux Academy for sponsoring the unplugged program.
Also thank you to Ting for sponsoring the show this year.
Wow.
Linux.ting.com.
I love being able to say that.
Go there and save.
You know, the reason why Ting has been a sponsor for so long on the show now is really simple
economics.
This kind of mobile model makes a lot of sense and our audience gets it.
And so they keep going to Ting because it saves them money.
And so because Ting keeps getting customers, they keep sponsoring us.
Linux.ting.com.
It's a great relationship because what we're trying to tell you about here isn't something
that's some big scam.
It's not some big complicated system or it's not some sort of incentive program where I
undermine net neutrality but I do it with a leather jacket so I tell you it's cool.
It is a really good mobile carrier that has CDMA and GSM networks.
You pick which one works better for you and you pay for what you use.
Minutes, messages, megabytes.
Whatever you use, that's all you owe.
And six dollars for the line plus Uncle Sam's take.
Uncle Sam's got to have a little percentage.
It varies in your area.
He's got his hands in your pockets.
But for me, it's usually almost always under 40 bucks.
Almost always.
Every now and then, like when I'm on the road or something like that, it might go up to
55, 60 bucks for three phones.
For three phones with no contract.
I love it.
You can bring a device or you can go grab one.
Go to Linux.ting.com and a big thanks to Ting for sponsoring.
You see, when I say it like that, it changes it up.
It's like a fresh new code.
And if you weren't a long time listener, you might not have any idea what I'm saying.
So it's only for the people in the know.
Alright, and then our last sponsor and one that's also been with us all year and I'm
super, super thankful to DigitalOcean.
Now DigitalOcean, the one thing that you can really tell about DigitalOcean is it's just
about everybody in our audience has a reason to use DigitalOcean.
Charem's always talking about it.
People write in the emails.
We're not only reading the emails that talk about DigitalOcean or something like that.
It's just what people are using because it's such a simple and fast and easy way to spin
up a Linux system on their great infrastructure in less than 55 seconds.
All SSDs for the storage, 40 gigabit e-connections to the hypervisors.
They run Linux, of course.
It's KVM for the virtualizer.
I love that.
And if you've ever wanted to see what a real nice web application can be to manage actual
really high end server type things, DigitalOcean's got the proto example.
You go there, it's like, oh, oh, they managed to put Johnny Ive in a box.
They put Johnny Ive in a box and he spit out this interface and that's why Apple hasn't
gotten anything for years now out of him because he's too busy working for DigitalOcean.
It's the only thing that makes sense.
Plus their API is built for humans.
They really did something good here and there's so much crazy great open source built around
that.
Go check them out.
DigitalOcean.com, just use a promo code from us for you.
D-O-Unplugged.
One word, lowercase, apply to your account after you get started or even if you had an
account for a while, you get $10 credit.
DigitalOcean.com, thanks for using the promo code D-O-Unplugged.
Okay, now the rest of the show is open for however the conversation goes.
So let's start talking about the worst of 2016.
Now this next example is not Linux specific but I thought it set such a good benchmark.
Like it can't get worse than this.
So this is the worst, this is the very worst of 2016.
Now the what?
Go.
I said go.
Frightening headline about your smartphone.
Samsung delaying shipments of its Galaxy Note 7 amid reports of exploding batteries and
that announcement sending their stock plummeting.
ABC's Rebecca Jarvis is here with the latest.
Good morning, Rebecca.
Good morning, Amy.
Multiple consumers have now complained of explosions of their Galaxy Note 7 devices.
Take a look at this.
Some are sharing these pictures of their burnt out phones online.
Samsung says that shipments are being delayed due to additional tests being conducted for
product quality and there's no word on exactly what caused the problems.
When you go to the airport today still, you hear warnings about how you can't bring a
Note 7, a Samsung Galaxy Note 7 on the plane and it's played over the loudspeaker at the
entire airport.
That is embarrassing.
There's no, I mean, Apple had a bad MacBook.
There's a lot of stuff that hasn't come out of Google that we were hoping for.
But nobody really had products that were blown up in your pockets like Samsung did.
And what's interesting now is we do have kind of a picture of what happened.
Did you hear about this?
No.
I'm behind the times.
A third party contractor was brought in by Samsung to investigate what was causing the
explosions and their analysis was is that Samsung left insufficient room for battery
growth when the battery heats up, it expands and when the battery cools, it contracts.
But when it's doing that super fast charging, it expands because it gets hot.
And when it, I guess, part of what caused the problem is it would expand, breach, some
sort of rupture happened and then I don't know, maybe, I don't know what happens from
there that causes it to explode, but that was the core issue.
Undefined behavior.
Woo.
And you know, Samsung, they just really didn't have a response out of the gate.
No.
It really did not feel like they were, you know, they didn't embrace it.
They weren't out there already with the report.
It took a long time to feel like they were really responding or trying to respond.
Yeah.
I tell you, that is, that is a, that is the worst case for a company like Samsung.
And it, it allowed for like the Apple iPhone to essentially be totally lackluster without
a headphone jack and still do very well because people are like, well, I'm done.
I'm done with this.
I'm sure Google was happy about that.
Yeah.
The Pixel release.
William just randomly wanted to jump in there and say hi, I think.
So are you there, William?
Are you good?
Are you okay?
Are you all right?
I think something happened.
We need you in 2017.
Don't hurt yourself.
I think something happened.
I think somebody just busted in William's house.
Are you okay?
Are you all right?
It was a Samsung Galaxy, though.
I think so.
Yep.
Just exploded right there.
Jeez.
What a shame.
So I want to transition from general technology and I want to, I don't really, it's not, I'm
not here to talk about Samsung.
You killed that show this year.
Remember?
That's right.
Hey, where's the bell?
Where are you?
Come on, Wes.
That's a...
You're right.
Bell worthy.
That was bell worthy.
Okay, I thought maybe we'd stop, we'd just stop right there and just talk Linux and talk
worst of 2016.
And I don't, I don't want this to be a bitch fest.
This is just like, you know, this is in, this is kind of in good fun, really.
It's in good fun.
And there's, there are a few that we could start with.
And I thought maybe to do that, we'd look at the 2017 list that Jack Wallen put together.
Because this one jumped out at me right at the top.
Canonical finally exits the phone market.
He just went right for it.
Wow.
He says, I give Canonical credit.
They tried hard.
Unfortunately, Ubuntu phone missed the mark on nearly every possible level.
The idea for interface was the idea for the interface was doomed from the beginning, speaking
in past tense.
Wow, yeah.
In past tense here.
And it couldn't gain any traction in the already saturated market.
However, I do believe their dream of convergence can be fixed.
And it begins with Android instead of focusing so much effort on getting Ubuntu phone in
a position where it can make the convergence between desktop and mobile.
Canonical might well sell their sites or I'm sorry, set their sites on integrating this
functionality into Android.
Regardless of what happens with convergence in 2017, we will see Canonical return their
focus to what they do best the desktop and server market.
What do you think of that?
Is that too strong?
Or do you?
Boy, I don't know.
It's not original, is it?
This is not the first journalist in the Linux and open source.
I think I saw these written in 2015.
About 2016 to definitely, yeah.
And I've seen other journalists say it for next year as well.
And to some extent, it's true, because it's been announced that, you know, Canonical are
stepping back from working on mobile devices to consolidate all of the work that's been
done on unity eight around the desktop.
So that will take some time.
Whether or not there's another device this year, I don't know for mobile.
But it's now bringing all of that work that happened in unit unity eight to the desktop.
And everyone's working on that right now.
Yeah.
So to me, it feels a bit hollow, it feels to actually, here's a better way.
But to me, it feels a bit cookie cutter.
Like it's a it's a it's a cookie cutter argument that somebody else has already made a stencil
for and you can stamp it out and you can mold it into your project or your article pretty
easily.
But what I'm trying to get at here is it feels like it sort of it sort of misses the mark
on a couple of things in its analysis.
First of all, it sort of seems to not acknowledge the work that mobile force canonical to think
about like transactional updates, right and snap packages made a lot of the reason for
for mirror right was involved with their mobile stuff.
And also, I think the other thing that if canonical Oh, hold on, I'll come back to that
because that mirror thing is a great point.
I want to the other thing that I think that sort of it underplays is their their total
refocusing and retooling around cutie are cute, which is going to long term make a huge,
huge differentiator for the Unity desktop.
Like it's going to be a it's going to be its own thing that developers will go after.
It's going to be the Unity desktop is going to stand out from gnome and plasma, not because
of the toolkit that it's using, but because it will not be like any other desktop.
Unity seven already stands out as its own unique thing.
But in most cases, it feels like a gnome desktop.
It feels like a GTK environment.
I believe once Unity eight is in a good usable spot on the desktop, and I don't know when
that'll be.
But when it arrives, I believe it will stand out as a completely, totally differentiating
product.
canonical going their own way.
Yeah.
And not in a bad way.
No, not in a bad way.
I think it really undersells the massive tide change that is happening, that it's only happening
because of the work and investment in mobile.
And I don't even think you necessarily kill off mobile, you just make it as part of a
wider strategy.
So you take the crap you've built to support that, and you integrate it with the wider
product strategy.
So that rather than pushing mobile mobile first, it's a hey, also mobile.
It's a it's it's it's this tool set, this platform will work across this device range
this it's because don't even think of it in hardware terms, think of it more in terms
of screen size.
That's what what do you think of that wimpy that way off the mark?
Nope, no, it's not way off the mark at all.
Yeah.
Okay.
So that's so that's the I think it's possible we could say they're exiting the phone market
in terms of additional partnerships with your aggressive making a continuing aggressive
partnerships with hardware.
What to expect in the next I don't know if you can even say that all I know is that engineering
is focused around putting everything that's happened in unity eight to the desktop right
now.
And as far as I know, the work on mobile has just been paused to allow that to happen.
As in mobile software development has been paused.
Yeah, but that doesn't mean that another device manufacturer couldn't come along, want to
do a device and the platforms there and ready to use.
There's been there's been an interesting shift happening.
And I wonder where the market is going to be once unity eight arrives for end users
because in the background, there is there's a big shift happening with the popularity
of Ubuntu Mate.
There is a lot of energy around projects like solace right now and elementary OS.
There is a lot of energy and discussion there where there is some especially in the case
of elementary OS and in the case of Mate there is some there is definitely some direct connections
to Ubuntu.
So they're not totally their own things, but they're kind of gaining speed and popularity
and size as the more more and more the desktops people are interested in what the things people
are talking about things with high momentum.
So where's that going to be once unity eight actually arrives?
Is it going to be too late?
Are people going to have moved on or will it will we all be ready for something fresh
again?
I don't know.
I think it's interesting, too, because last year we were talking about this.
Sorry.
Go on.
I think the community talks about not liking unity, but I think a lot more people actually
use unity than don't overall in the grand scheme of how many people use Ubuntu and don't
care enough to change their D or even if they could.
I think I would argue that I would I would argue that unity has the best multi monitor
sport of any desktop operating system out there.
And this is coming from somebody who just dumped unity for no.
Yeah, there's that.
I would say the only people who don't like unity are fussy Linux users because every
regular person I've ever given it to, they have two impressions.
Yeah, this is great.
It works fine.
Why are you asking?
It's fine.
Right.
They don't have the concept of that.
They really have a choice.
Right.
No, I've had that exact same experience.
Yeah, I just know.
And I just put a Linux box in for Hadia at her clinic and she has an employee that sits
down there.
She sits down there, uses it, literally did not even did not even say anything to her.
She just sits down and uses it.
She sees the icons on the side.
She could do the printing.
She can do the scanning.
She does it.
It's fine.
All the buttons are in the right place.
We've literally never had a conversation.
And then when I finally asked her, how's the computer working?
She's good.
She looks at me like I'm crazy.
It's fine.
Should I do something wrong with it?
Why are you asking?
Yeah.
You know what did not come out of her mouth?
Well, I really can't stand unity.
I really I wish it was known three Katie.
Yeah, that was not what came out of her mouth.
So we definitely live in a bubble when when it comes to these things just a little bit.
The original argument about the guy saying that it's there, it's an exit from it.
You could just say that it's a they're developing a convergence concept because they already
had a desktop environment built and they already had the server infrastructure built.
So in order to do the convergence, they needed to work on the mobile.
So now that they're getting closer and closer to the convergence, they can work less on
mobile and more on the other stuff.
So just make just changing slight direction doesn't mean that they're going to completely
abandon it.
Yeah, I think so.
Interesting, I think we would have talked last year about, you know, how we saw them
focusing on mobile and how we liked what they were doing on the desktop, but they wanted
to see more focus in that area.
So it's almost kind of like an old Intel tick tock kind of thing where, hey, now we're back
on the desktop.
Maybe that means, you know, if it's a bad thing for 2016, maybe it means there'll be
some good things in 2017 to be excited about, you know, and also, we've just watched so
many different vendors or hardware makers or whoever just lose their ass in mobile.
So it just doesn't look as awesome of a market as it used to.
So as a company, they're probably going, well, maybe we'll just let them eat each other.
We've got this cloud thing, desktop thing, enterprise thing.
So what do you think of Jack's next point then?
You ready for this one?
Let's hear it.
Yeah, so I think because, you know, we kind of were hard on that one.
So this one might be a little different.
Elementary OS will gain significant ground.
He says, I'm not trying to be partial here, but I believe partially due to Canonical's
failed foray into the phone space, Elementary OS will become a much bigger player by the
end of 2017.
There's a good reason for that.
Elementary OS has an amazing flavor of Linux.
It's very user friendly.
It's beautifully designed, and it makes working with Linux very easy.
He goes on also to say that Elementary OS currently stands at number five on DistroWatch
with the ranking.
And he says by the end of the year, he believes it will just be a bit number two under Mint.
It's interesting.
I just read another article today too that thinks that part of the reason they... People
were speculating about... Where did I see this?
People were speculating about what will take Linux to get to 5% desktop market share, and
one of the things in that speculation was that Elementary OS would play a significant
part in growth.
This is two people now saying Elementary OS is going to play a significant role in 2017
for growth.
I don't think just Elementary OS either.
I think Elementary OS are doing great things, and they are very squarely focused on the
Windows and Mac users who are looking to switch to Linux.
But I think the other two distributions that will also grow in popularity are going to
be Solus and KDE Neon, but specifically its LTS version that they've just announced.
Really?
You think that?
You think so?
Tell me more why.
Well, those three projects all have something in common.
They've all... Well, Elementary has been around for a long time, but it's really come
of age in this last release that they've put out.
It really felt like it was the whole thing.
But there's a lot of buzz around Solus and KDE Neon, and I think that people are tempted
to those to try them.
And I think what I've seen is a lot of Arch Linux users who are tired of curating their
own system moving to more cutting edge curated desktop operating systems.
So I think Elementary for those people that just want something that works and is stylish
and has got familiar workflows, and Solus and KDE Neon for the enthusiasts, probably
most of our audience, who are looking for something new and shiny that's got all the
bells and whistles.
That's interesting because Neon's been tugging at my distro hopping gene, or whatever it
is in me that makes me want to constantly move around.
It's tugging on that note again saying, hey, come over here to KDE Neon land.
X-Metal in the chat room says, well, what's the difference between Neon LTS and Kibuntu?
Where's the line there?
What do you think, Ron?
Oh, well, the biggest thing about the difference between Kibuntu and Neon is Kibuntu does the
six month thing with Ubuntu.
Neon is based only on the LTS 16.04.
So that's the biggest difference, but also the Plasma desktop updates in Neon the day
it releases.
Kibuntu is months behind, usually.
There was a post recently about how you can get the latest Plasma 5.8 in Ubuntu with
the Kibuntu backports.
If you had Neon, you'd already have it months ago.
The difference between the LTS of Neon, it's kind of weird that they use that term because
Neon LTS, they're both using Ubuntu LTS.
It's just that the Neon version is like Plasma 5.8 is the LTS of Plasma.
So Neon LTS is 5.8 Plasma on top of the LTS Ubuntu.
So if you use the regular Neon and not the LTS Neon, you're going to continue to get
updates to Plasma.
So like 5.9.
Right.
But in theory, if you have an LTS desktop environment, an LTS based distro, that could
be a pretty sweet setup for those that are looking for a powerful workstation that lasts
a long time.
And you wanted to add something to that discussion.
Go ahead.
I've heard that kicked around of which one, what's the difference between Kibuntu and
Neon?
Well, Kibuntu is Ubuntu's way of doing KDE and Neon is KDE's way of doing Ubuntu.
And it's much better.
No, because they're both separate.
They're both different community projects.
Canonical and Ubuntu does not work on Kibuntu.
So that's I mean, that's like Kibuntu is more of a full service distro.
It's got all the applications like ocular, PDF viewers and things like that.
And it's all built in for you and it's got like email clients and all this other stuff.
KDE Neon is just the fundamentals of what makes the distro work.
And that's it.
You add everything else yourself.
So it's more of a minimalistic with a rolling on top.
But there's the one thing I would say is that if you want if you want a KDE Ubuntu base
and you don't want to do all the effort of having to like set up things up, Kibuntu is
going to do it more for you.
OK, so it depends on like your preference.
I think what would be said about the enthusiast, Neon is definitely more for the enthusiasts
rather than just give it to me and let it go.
So Wimby, you say you notice a lot of buzz, I have to notice about about Neon, about Solus.
But of course, you're being humble and not mentioning Matei, but I see a lot of buzz
around that, too.
That's interesting.
So elementary OS, in my estimation, is probably going to be an important distribution.
Is it going to be a game changer distribution, though?
And something like what Wimby said, you know, they have been around a while and I feel like
they, you know, it's not that they're not moving, they're doing a lot of cool stuff.
It's just feels like it's a slower wave, a longer period, you know, that like it feels
like it was a long time since I was excited about their last release.
And now there's the newest release.
And I think there's a lot of good things.
But at least in our circles, maybe there's less because it changes slower.
There's less that we have to think about.
I think it's because they feel like they're it feels like they're playing catch up when
other DEs already have like everything you expect.
Like Pantheon for a for a long time, maybe even still, had had no ability to always on
top for a window, which seems like a fundamental in every other DE.
So like but when you when the reason why it's going to be very popular is because it's kind
of like a full cohesive unit of a system.
Right.
So I guess I wanted to double down on something that Wimpy said that Rotten seemed to jump
in on and it kind of made my head nod, too, was that Wimpy said, I think one of the targets
for Neon will be ARCH users who are sick of curating their own desktop.
And that hit me because I see that sometimes.
And Antigros definitely tries to serve that niche.
But I wonder if that might be a thing over 2017.
Will there be a as these other distributions stand up and get more popular and get more
software available to them and get more momentum?
Will there be a bit of a migration, do you think, Wes?
And like as as rolling becomes more than just the ARCH Gentoo crowd, right.
So it's like suddenly you have options.
If you before, it felt like it was more like, yes, you rolled and you put everything together
yourself and you got this great system.
But it could be there's an audience there that they want the new packages, they want
the fresh stuff, but they don't necessarily need to put it all together if someone else
is glued it in a good way.
You know, so let's talk about that for a second.
So rolling has has changed or not changed, but has seen it sort of become like the buzzword
in some cases for distributions like, yeah, we're going to go rolling, we're going to
go rolling.
We've seen some major refactorings, like on the case of OpenSUSE, you know, not this year,
but just recently.
And Fedora is now talking about that.
It definitely seems to have done something really good for SUSE because it feels like
in our audience, there's more people using it now than there used to be.
It still doesn't feel like one of the major big players that has a lot of the community
excited about it and hasn't taken over the enterprise.
But it feels like it's carving out this this group of users that use it that really like
it.
And that's a good sign that they got they're doing something right there and that they
could be on the precipice of tipping that over.
So that's been interesting to watch SUSE.
I wonder if I wonder if as we go through 2017, if we'll see that them across the door rumors.
And then, my friends, we have Microsoft, oh, oh, Microsoft, oh, Microsoft, you just you
never know what they're going to do anymore.
And Jack thinks they're going to open up Windows.
I wonder if he I wonder if he's bold enough.
Oh, man, I know I wonder if he's bold enough to predict the license.
This might sound crazy, he says, but for this Jack, man, I like you.
But this is almost making me want to throw out this whole list.
He says this might sound crazy, but I think it makes sense.
Microsoft stands to gain far more leverage by opening up the source for their Windows
platform.
Not only would this be a boon for the enterprise, it would also enable a lot of enterprise level
systems and services to better integrate with Windows.
Yeah, because that's well, he says I don't suspect suspect we'll actually see an open
source version of Windows release.
What I do believe is that Microsoft will finally become open to this idea and begin to see
a certain validity to handling over source to their platform specific entities.
I don't I don't follow that at all, even I don't even think they could because of IP
reasons.
Exactly.
This doesn't seem possible.
If you remember the whole open Solaris project and how long it took them to rewrite the parts
they needed to that were, you know, written by some contractor that they couldn't give
out because they didn't have permission.
I can't imagine Microsoft is any different with Windows.
Like I'm sure there's tons of the Windows core that they just didn't even write a permission
to use.
Yeah.
I think that the recent Microsoft partnership with Qualcomm will have more to do with Microsoft's
resurgence than opening up Windows.
So you familiar with this new new arrangement?
No, talk about it.
Please tell us.
So Microsoft and Qualcomm are partnering so that Qualcomm are going to provide chips for
Windows to run on ARM, but it's full blooded Windows desktop on ARM.
And also the ability to run Windows 32 bit Intel binaries.
I was going to say I have seen that platform.
So they're going to do x86 32 bit binary emulation on ARM chips.
Yeah, so that opens up the entire back catalogue of Windows software on this platform on mobile,
which could or could not be either phones, but more likely probably surface type devices.
There's no reason they're going to open up Windows to do that.
No, I can see them doing more open things in their cloud environments and that focus,
you know, new products being open.
But yeah, there's just no reason to go back and do that.
Historically, we can now look back over sort of, you know, 18 months, two years of Microsoft's
behaviour and it's about server and enabling technologies that they've open sourced.
It hasn't been core core products and it certainly hasn't been Windows.
Right.
So this is this has been my thought is if we watch Microsoft specifically now in 2017,
I don't I think them doing much more with Windows.
They're just going to do I think do business as usual with Windows as businesses need Windows
and people they're doing business want Windows.
It's just going to be what they've always done.
I think what we need to watch for is the new Microsoft hardware that comes out in 2017.
Their surface books, their home devices, the stuff that they're really kind of putting
a lot of their intention and energy behind.
How does that interact with Linux?
How locked down is that?
What is this built out of?
What what can I do with this if I don't want to run Windows?
Like what what are the answers to those questions?
And depending on how close it is to well, pretty much whatever you want or anything
that can use the API or well, if you just grab this, if the answer is getting closer
to that, then that shows you what Microsoft's real intent.
If the answer is, well, you need Windows 10 and it has to be activated, then that shows
you where their where their intentions at.
I would predict it's going to be the more open Microsoft.
It's going to be the more.
Oh, they don't really care what the OS is Microsoft.
And I feel like that's the direction they're going in.
And I would just expect more of that for to go as far as open sourcing Windows.
Right.
I think they're playing they're playing making a strong play towards developers, trying to
be friendly towards developers and not put up roadblocks.
And I don't think the Windows angle helps them with that in the same way as the open
cloud API stuff does.
Yeah.
So we've just finished recording the last two episodes of Ubuntu podcast for the year
and also for season nine.
So we now take a break.
So if you're an Ubuntu podcast listener, we're we're off air for two or three months.
That sounds so nice.
And you want to you want to have a listen to what will be episode 44, which is our predictions
episode and what Poppy has to say about Microsoft in 2017.
So there's a tease for you.
I will definitely check that out.
I wonder if you have any thoughts on Chrome OS and Android merging in 2017 and if this
is going to be a problem for Linux desktop.
I don't I hate to be like chicken little.
But when I think about actual competition to Linux, I don't think about Mac OS or Windows.
Not long, long term, not really long term.
When I think of general desktop computing and business computing, people that are task
oriented that are that need this type of interface for the type of work they do, software development,
production, the all there's so many categories of work that will never really work on touch.
Maybe a lot of them always require local applications.
And I just I just really believe that one day these types of computers, these roles
will go towards a more general computing platform like Linux is always what I've hoped.
But I feel like it's very probably going to be Android.
Very likely because the industry is capable of wrapping its head around Android as a thing
that it can build towards.
They understand how to do product testing against it.
They understand how to image and flash gets put in every little place you can imagine.
And if they play ball, they get to take advantage of Google's APIs and services.
And that makes it nice for end users because they don't have to worry about shipping software
that actually is any good because they can just include Google stuff.
So and they can integrate with their Android of things.
Right.
Of course.
I really kind of wonder if they're targeting.
Are they really targeting the same audience, though?
I mean, Android is targeting your everyday, you know, person.
I don't see many guys that are their heart, their developers, their their, you know, web
designers, whatever.
I don't see those guys going over to Android.
And I think that's I think that's a large target audience that Linux could hit pretty
heavily.
If you can get the dev community, you can get the.
Those guys aren't using Chrome OS either.
Yeah.
I know.
That's what I'm saying.
No, I agree.
To be fair, I actually do it work and I use Chrome OS really regularly, but I'm mostly
just SSH ing into a real machine.
So right.
I was just going to say and you also have your company has built you tools that specifically
allow you to use Chrome OS, you know, as as as a method of production.
Most people would not have those resources available.
That's correct.
That could just become a thing, though.
But that could absolutely become a thing.
Yeah, right.
Like Chrome OS is actually really usable because I'm mostly as a staging through it.
And I have a couple of web portals I use in the mail client, the browser and all that
stuff.
Yeah, I can see that unreasonable for a modern company, especially if you use exchange.
You get Office 365 potentially, and that satisfies all your browser needs.
Or you use the Google apps for business or use Google apps for business.
Those two things are so popular now.
Yeah, it seems fairly possible that if your other work can be ported somehow, whatever
it is, you basically just describe the entire computing setup for my kids school.
That's how they do it.
Oh, no, that's not surprising at all.
That would actually be the most poignant case to make is for school.
It's really easy to go with a Chromebook these days.
And that's what schools are going for because they're cheap.
That's what they have done.
Every kid in Dylan's second grade class gets a Chromebook.
Oh, hey.
The teachers are on Chromebooks.
They're on Google apps for business.
It's the whole shebang.
And it's not just his class.
That's how it is for the students there.
And I don't know.
I don't know who's getting that big fat check.
Somebody got a big fat check.
Yeah, definitely.
Wow.
So I could just I just to me this seems like this is going to spread.
They can jump in real quick.
It's free.
I was actually just working with a client and Google actually you can work on a deal
with Google.
They will give you access to the console and Google apps for G Suite.
G Suite is what they're calling it.
But they give it to you for free if you're a school or education institute.
Yeah, you need to be very careful about your definition of free here, because free is basically
hooking a generation of children into the Google ecosystem.
That becomes the new normal.
That becomes what you expect to do.
You thought it was bad when they were given a Macs.
I mean, yeah.
Or Windows computers and you're bringing them up on a closed source operating system.
Now you're bringing them up into, you know, a whole online life.
A privatized spine apparatus.
Yeah, it's just it's just worrying.
But that aside, you know, Chrome Android blended together for, you know, casual desktop use
or maybe most, you know, office based jobs is very compelling.
But like you say, for developer stuff, maybe not so much.
And also Android have just announced their IoT thing, which is kind of just Android at
the moment.
They haven't seemed to announce anything specifically to target it at IoT.
But because of the juggernaut of Android, you can see that that's going to sort of probably
pick up some traction over the over the coming year.
And it'll be interesting to see how people decide to build their IoT devices and platforms
in the backdrop of 2016, which frankly has been a miserable year for IoT in terms of
appalling security and carefree attitude by device manufacturers.
I just want to quickly address kind of what, you know, I agree that there is definitely
some concern and I definitely think that there is that we are paying a price, you know, for
the Google infrastructure.
But I got to tell you, Wimpy, I mean, I sat on the other end of a conference call with
three adults that had no idea what they were going to do for this infrastructure problem
because they didn't have the budget, they didn't have the resources, they didn't have
the money.
And when we got a hold of Google and they said, hey, we'll just give you everything
for free.
We'll give you the we'll give you the way to manage the devices and we'll give you email
and we'll give you the software.
Everything when you get all of that.
And then on top of that, on top of that, you have to understand when these kids leave the
education institute, they are not tied to it.
It's not like all of a sudden, like with what Microsoft is doing with their office suite,
after you left the student and teacher version for one hundred and forty dollars, you wanted
to write a resume, then they ding those students because they didn't have the professional
version for five hundred dollars.
It's not it's not like that.
I mean, those students can go create a regular Google account and have access to all of those
same tools.
So, yeah.
Is it in Google's best interest?
Of course.
Is Google taking that information and making money off of it while they say they're not?
But they probably are.
And there is so there is a cost there that's being paid.
But I would think that I would say the real cost is that there's a huge benefit.
I agree.
There's a huge benefit to put computing in the hands of young children and enable students
to have access to technology that didn't have it before.
And I don't think that it is too expensive of a cost.
I think that is probably the better good overall, especially if a certain percentage of them
become intellectually curious about how it works.
But the thing that does make me concerned is it's essentially the death of desktop software.
What student is going to come up on Google Docs on Google Docs and ever, ever once they
go start a business or they go into school, install LibreOffice and use that?
That is never going to happen.
It is it is guaranteed lock into the Google ecosystem because it'll simply be how they
expect things to work, how they share information using their social network attached to Google.
The way Google Docs works with links and all that you just you will become to depend on
that infrastructure and those expectations and LibreOffice will never have a shot.
In much the same way that Microsoft encouraged students to use Windows products from an early
age throughout their education, all around the world.
And people consequently know that as the de facto standard.
And if you're not studying computer science or software engineering, it's unlikely that
you will ever consider that there is anything else out there available, although most mostly
because of iPhone and iPod, they're aware that Mac exists.
So what do you think?
Be careful what you wish for to two lines from a popular children's novel, eat me, drink
me.
I still think that Windows is so ingrained in the business world before kids get out
of school using it.
Maybe there may be more similar cycle.
It was only what, like 15, 20 years of a life cycle of that stuff.
I don't know.
Microsoft, I don't know.
You know, because it's getting chewed away at both ends because Microsoft themselves
isn't exactly pushing Windows platforms too hard.
They're moving people over to Azure and Office 365 on their end.
So it's kind of getting chewed out from both ends.
I just don't think any of these things last long enough that it's really ever a lock-in
because they end up kind of fading and dying and things change.
And that is good for us running Linux, right?
Yeah.
I mean, on the flip side.
Not the native apps, but at least the base OS.
The platform agnostic aspect that comes as a result of it is good for Linux.
But that might not make Stolman very happy.
Not much does.
And the value of this is negative.
So we're going to switch over to Ask Noah in a bit.
So I probably, before we wrap up, should give you guys a heads up.
I'll plug the phone number right now if you want to call in.
And if you want to talk business, you want to talk Linux with Mr. Noah.
One eight eight three four seven zero zero one one.
If you're watching live right now, the last unplugged of the year, at least the last live
one.
And then next Tuesday is the Beard Spectacular Clip Show.
But if you want to call in right now, if you're watching live, if you got a question for Mr.
Noah, do it.
And you should.
One eight eight three four seven zero zero one one.
OK.
So there's one more thing.
And this was sort of the worst of 2016.
So I'm going to get to my what I think was the worst thing in Linux for 2016.
And it was the vulnerabilities.
Because we were.
Oh yeah.
Sorry.
Not only were we not hit with.
I'm sorry.
How should I say this?
Not only did we have a fair amount of vulnerabilities, right?
Fair statement.
But they were like super embarrassing, had been around a really long time and really
hollowed out the argument that thousands of eyes make all bugs shallow.
It really like we took a blow to one of our biggest mantras this year.
And we had dirty cow.
We had we had shell shock and we had just I think all the botnets, right?
They're all made of Linux.
Yeah.
I was just I was gonna say I think we also had what was the was that LibreVault or not
LibreVault?
I can't remember.
So I was was that this year?
I can't remember if the heart bleed if it was heart bleed this year.
Yeah.
I can't call.
It was 2014, man.
Okay.
All right.
It's almost been three years.
It feels like it feels like we had that's that's the reason.
Okay.
This is why because it feels like we had three or four heart bleeds this year.
Like one year we had heart bleed and that was like, God, that was a bad one.
And we all remember it.
But it feels like this year we had like three of them.
And it feels like we're on that we're that bad part of the slope where like we're finding
a lot of these things, but they're we're getting them fixed.
And it's just it's we're so big now.
I'll tell you what the worst thing is.
I mean, it's good.
And I'm very thankful for it.
But the worst thing is, you know, why all of these vulnerabilities are being found because
either somebody is exploiting them or because a huge company that makes a ton of money off
commercial software or stealing people's information and making ad money is doing projects because
they have so much extra cash sitting around.
They have a project to better their own interest in this field and are researching these look
at like Google's Project Zero, Cisco's others, others have things just like this that only
they could sustain because they make so much money that they can fund these things.
It's not the millions of free software developers all around the world.
Now hopefully some of these companies have snatched up some of the best software developers
and that's they just happen to be there.
But that's the other thing I don't really I really kind of wish we hadn't hit that so
hard this year and I really kind of wish that we that it would have been more from the community
would have I would have loved to have been like independent hacker groups on the Internet
that have self-organized as a community and are doing this and solving these problems
and have a name for themselves and are not Project Zero from Google.
It's like just a group of real people that are just out there.
I don't know.
The community making itself better rather than something that feels kind of like outsiders,
even if those people do heavily use open source themselves.
And I'm always very thankful that these companies have these projects and it's like, OK, great.
We found another one.
At the same time, I'm like, I wish we could have caught it ourselves.
Boy, it sure is stressing the no press is bad press, right?
Yeah, just kind of not what the open source developers necessarily want to do.
Right.
Like these people who exist to find these vulnerabilities who love doing this are going
to try to get paid to do it.
And so they're going to join, you know, Project Zero and whatnot.
So if you try if you're going to try to call Talos or whoever they call it, if you're going
to try to call Noah, it's one eight seven seven.
Not eight eight.
I don't know why he said eight eight.
Noah, what the hell, man?
What the hell?
Are you in there?
Are you still in there, Noah?
This guy was about to ask about this.
Look at this.
What does it say?
Can you read that on my screen?
What's that first telegram say?
What was that first?
It says eight seven seven.
Uh huh.
Well, OK.
Now, are you going to make me take a screenshot?
Really?
See, look.
What does that first number say, Wes?
What does it say?
That's all eights.
That's all eights, baby.
And then he sends me a correction.
Hey, jerk.
It's eight seven seven three four seven zero zero one one.
Eight seven seven.
We need an API call to return this.
Three four seven zero zero one one.
That I just can't even with this guy.
I can't even with this guy right now.
We don't know.
But we're going to find out today on Ask Noah.
I said just take Skype calls.
That's what I said.
I just take Skype calls.
That's that's all.
The other thing that I think did kind of start to develop this year is Apple did kind of
have a rough year for the desktops and laptops and enthusiasts, the same people we're just
kind of talking about in some regard are actually there is an uptick.
I think the switch is real based on the feedback we've been getting on Koda radio from Mike
switch.
I feel like people have been following along with him because they're doing it, too.
And they're coming from Max.
And I think that's that's that's been a bigger trend this year than we expected.
Oh, definitely.
I mean, I don't I don't think we expected Apple the alienation to be that real.
Right.
Like there's always going to be some people switching.
There's like that small little right little flow of people.
But I have a lot of people who just there was not the computer that they wanted.
They were really, you know, obviously they had been waiting a long time to buy a new
Apple computer.
It was it was it was an event that I guess what I expected was I expected a slow burn
of boredom and dissatisfaction with a platform that wasn't really serving their needs anymore
or being innovated.
And what Apple did was they dropped this huge doubt bomb.
This this massive doubt bomb that said to the hardcore enthusiasts, I'm not sure there's
actually going to be any better Max.
In fact, this is a Mark Gurman.
For those of you that don't follow Apple News, Mark Gurman is probably the guy that has the
best Apple sources in the tech press.
Mark Gurman is he's he helped start a nine to five Mac.
And then because his sourcing became so good, he was able to build a name for himself.
He's been hired by Bloomberg.
And now he writes for Bloomberg, who is trying to focus even more on technology because it's
a huge part of the stock market.
And that's why Bloomberg cares.
So now Mark Gurman writes for Bloomberg.
And today he wrote to to diehard fans, Apple's Macintosh sometimes seems like an afterthought
these days.
Mac upgrades once frequent frequent ritual are few and far between the Mac Pro.
The Apple's marquee computer hasn't been refreshed since 2013.
That's embarrassing.
Yeah, it is embarrassing.
The affordable and flexible Mac Mini was last upgraded in 2014.
And the new machine when the me and when a new machine does roll out, the results are
sometimes underwhelming, if not infuriating to the devotees.
So he says that he's been interviewing people familiar with Apple's inner workings, and
reveals that the Mac is getting far and far less attention than it once did.
Confirming all these diversities, Gurman sources that the Mac team has lost clout within the
famed industrial design group led by Johnny Ive and the company software team.
They also describe a lack of clear direction from senior management, departures of key
people working on Mac Mac hardware and technical challenges that have delayed the rollout of
new computers.
So there is a real actual lack of focus on the Mac in Apple.
It's true.
The Mac is actually dying in Apple.
Now Tim Cook, they leaked a for an internal forum posting saying they have some great
desktops in the line.
But who knows?
To them, the Mac, the new MacBook Pro is a great machine.
They say it all the time.
It's a great new machine.
So their definition is great.
It varies.
And the Mac generates about 10 percent of Apple sales, which is legitimately big.
That's billions.
So it's bigger than some companies make.
But yeah, that is not good.
That is not good for the for those that are out there hoping to make their living on a
Mac.
I wonder how much this window, the bash on Windows 10 will play into that.
You know, the divergence that we see come into Linux users versus how many developers
will be more happy to stick with Windows if they can get a real Unix shell going.
Yeah.
This is this could be good for Linux, too.
Go ahead.
It could be.
I was saying that I think the Windows people, the people who would stay on Windows because
of the access to Linux are the people who are are you OK with Windows in the first place?
I don't think they're going to leave to go to Mac and instead of going to Mac because
of the new releases of the out of touch bar, they could go to Linux instead.
Here's here's actually what I'm thinking.
I think a lot of high end technical users that switch to Mac did it as a refuge from
Windows.
I think a lot of them were pissed off at Windows at the time and they wanted something else.
And the thing is, is Windows 10 is not good enough.
It is especially if you want like if you have any standards, if you want to have high DPI,
if you want to have consistent interface, if you want normal power management settings,
if you have any like sort of like particular esoteric, you know, hipster standards that
a lot of people like to make fun of as as quaint and not necessary, but things that
people pay attention to stuff notice.
If you are a person that is it pays attention to detail, Windows 10 is infuriating to use.
I mean, it's just it is just an absolute train wreck of a mismatch of UI and a lack of high
DPI support and old routing and typical Windows.
It is everything Windows always has been with some nice stuff on top.
So it's not going to attract Mac users.
They're going to look at Linux.
It's just it's I just I think maybe the reason I feel the most fired up about this because
I've gotten the most emails about this.
We've had people following this.
There's podcasters I listen to that are making a transition right now because it was recommended
to me by audience members like, hey, listen to this guy.
He's doing the same thing.
And it's this person has never heard of the Linux action show.
He doesn't know who I am.
And he is going through a process of switching from a Mac to Linux because he didn't want
to go back to Windows.
And it's it's I tell it is I get enough input now that I feel like this is a thing that
is happening, not saying it's billions of people, but I'm saying it's a category of
users now.
And I love it.
I love it.
It's funny, too.
You kind of see this like like they knew they always knew they could they could do Linux,
you know, but they just didn't.
It wasn't they knew it didn't have the polish they wanted or they didn't think it had the
polish they wanted.
And so now there's this like, well, I'm forced to look and oh, hey, it's really not as bad
or it's better than I thought elementary exists.
You know, you're starting to watch you starting to watch some of the cracks in Mac OS.
You know, the new battery life on the MacBook Pro sucks.
And of course, one of the ways Apple fixes it is they just remove the time estimate from
the battery menu on Mac OS now.
You're starting to see the cracks.
And so it's like, well, yeah, OK, Linux has some problems, but so does Windows and so
does Mac OS.
So which which ones do I want to work with this time?
And then you know, the grass is always greener.
It's right.
Oh, yeah.
So, W.W., you were you were just saying that you knew somebody who made the switch because
of Windows 10 to a Mac.
What happened?
Well, it's actually a family member of mine because all all PCs come with a 5400 RPM drive
and that's what's causing part of it because Windows 10 is so heavy that you're sending
people laptops with a 5400 RPM drive in like 2016 when you should be sending them out with
SSDs and people are having such a poor experience, or at least the people I know, that they rather
go to a Mac, pay the extra money, not have the hassle of the average user and having
to put up with Windows stuff and just have a smooth experience.
They're willing to pay for that smooth experience that they get with Mac.
Now, mind you, they're not the most technical person, but they just want a good UI, stuff
that works and, you know, maybe they'll spend more because of it.
I like that theory.
I think I'm going to just sort of sit back and just sort of keep watching Mike and watch
others.
Mike's also considering doing it now.
He's been doing it on Linux.
He's considering doing a stint on Windows and see if he can get Bash on Windows to work
for him and do that just to give it a fair shake, too.
Yeah, no, that would be actually quite interesting.
You know, I'm not going to do it, but it feels like it's worth looking into.
I did want to just sort of conjecture about one other category that I'm getting sort of
my opinions beginning to change from this is a toy to maybe this is something that's
worth taking seriously, and it's not Linux-related specifically, though I do hope open source
and Linux and the entire ecosystem isn't locked out from this next category in 2017, and I
think it's going to be a tight line.
I really think Amazon's nailed something with the Alexa.
I thought, so I do something with the news is I notice when a new product comes out,
there's a hype cycle.
Oh, yeah.
You know, it starts before the product comes out.
It starts.
Then there's the announcement.
Then there's hype till the release.
Then there's release.
Then there's selective review hype where certain people release the reviews.
Then there's the limited release to the public where you start to actually get the people
that are using it begin to review and comment on it, and then there's folks like me who
like to use it for a while and then give you a review, so those start to pop up for a while,
and then it just sort of drops down, and there's not a lot of people that usually keep talking
about a product after that if it's not successful.
We don't get exact numbers from Amazon, but we know they just kind of churn them out as
they can.
Well, one of the things that I find to be really fascinating when it comes to the Alexa
is there is still a good flow of posts about people talking about things you can do with
it, ways you can integrate it, what an interesting device it is, how reliable it is.
Those things are still being written on a daily basis about the Alexa right now, and
Google's obviously interested in this area.
Microsoft's interested in this area, who knows about Apple, but they've got Siri on the devices.
I wonder if in 2017 if we will be able to be somewhat of a player in this field.
I'm not really even talking Mycroft, I mean just our stuff isn't off on its own island.
We're not completely left out.
We're not completely excluded from playing.
I wonder where this is going to go, and what do you think, Wes?
When I look at things like the Alexa, it seems to be more open.
It seems to be the more successful device.
So I guess I'd say, what do you mean by we, when you ask that question?
Well, when I'm using things like... Well, I like to use Telegram instead of WhatsApp.
I like to use this podcast player instead of... What's the one, the streaming one that
combines all the shows and makes it sound worse?
It's the really popular podcast player that I should know off the top of my head.
I should too, but I don't know.
It's a podcast... Oh, damn it.
It's like it basically makes... Anyways, there is software, there are radio and streaming
services that just work with Alexa.
Work with Alexa, right.
There's stuff that when you're in their ecosystems, you work, but... I guess what I'm talking
about, the things I choose to use.
I choose to use Telegram instead of WhatsApp, or I choose to use...
If you've made niche decisions about the products, maybe they're more open source friendly.
Maybe they're more... Whatever, but they're not the... Yeah.
Or maybe I have my calendar on own cloud instead of Google Calendar, or Nextcloud.
It really does come down to how well do these things play with different APIs.
Is there interop?
Is that the focus?
Because if it is just the three big... And you see that with a lot of things where it's
like, hey, we integrate with your favorite clouds, that means you have Dropbox and iCloud,
and that's it.
But if it's like, hey, you can add whatever here, add your custom drop in a URL for your
calendar files, and here you go, that's a whole different story.
Have you thought about picking up on Alexa?
Or a Google Home?
The Google Home looked a little more interesting.
When Alexa first came out, it was interesting.
I'm very interested in their... It seems like they've done a lot of good work with
the microphones, with actually making it so that it can hear you and process your voice
well, which is interesting.
And I did notice-
Slash creepy.
It did also seem that, at least with Alexa, they've kind of... And maybe because it was
from Amazon, who... I think on Coder you were talking about, it's kind of like the
big four.
They kind of get grouped in differently now.
So maybe it was a little more friendly.
But it seemed a lot of people who do value open source or free software had been playing
with the Alexa in a way.
So it does seem like it has some developer mindshare in that respect that maybe other
devices don't.
That's a good way... I think that's what I was trying to say, is the developer mindshare
aspect of it.
Yeah, that's a good way to put it.
I don't suppose... I'm going to roll the dice.
I don't know why I'm betting no for some reason.
It's not that I think that you guys are all a bunch of haters, but I just... I'm going
to guess... Does anybody in the Mamba Room have an Alexa or a Google Home?
Nope.
No.
Yeah.
Anybody considering getting one?
No.
Maybe.
Oh, okay.
So there is a wide range.
So Wimpy, did you jump in on the IM?
Yeah.
Oh, all right.
Tell me about this.
I'm tempted to get an Amazon Echo.
So am I.
Why are you?
Because friends of mine that have experimented with it and reading that I've done on the
API, I can see how I can integrate it into projects that I'm working on trivially, more
trivially than the other systems out there of a similar nature.
I've been thinking about getting it because there are four... I'm sorry.
No.
There are one, two, three, four, five, six lights in the studio that are Hughes lights
that are used now in production.
And also there's certain timer aspects that could be really handy and certain other functions
like J-Bot functions that could be really cool with Alexa.
So I was thinking about maybe not necessarily for my house or my RV.
But for the studio.
For the studs.
Hey, that could be fun.
Yeah.
What about... Now, Rod and I hear you jump in.
So you were thinking about it too?
Yeah.
I'm thinking about it as well.
Mainly because they have the multi-tier options.
So it's not just like one device that you purchase that's $100 or something.
The default Echo is $150.
Oh.
So then if you found it useful, you could slip it in in other places for cheaper.
Yeah.
The Echo Dot, they also have the Echo, the Tap, and the Echo Dot.
The Echo is like $150, the Tap is like $90, and the Dot is only like $50 or $40 depending
on if it's a discount or not.
Like right now it's only $40.
Yeah.
You could get them in a three pack on special offer right now.
Oh.
What?
The deal.
Oh no.
Oh, you know, Chris hasn't gotten a Christmas present for himself.
Oh.
You deserve it.
You've been a good boy.
Now, does anybody know, will the devices work together?
Can I set a reminder, say, at home and then show up at the office and have the Echo at
the office help me?
Anybody know?
Yeah.
See, I think it's time I do need to figure these things out.
I hate not knowing.
That would be a good point.
Well, so anyways, I think that's going to be an interesting category.
I know there is integration.
I saw a video explaining that the integration exists, but I don't know in different locations
how well it works.
Fascinating.
So I think this is going to be, I think it's going to be a really interesting category.
And the thing is, I don't think all of the big players that are going to get in have
gotten in yet.
I think there's still going to be some interesting entries.
So check it out.
Check it out.
It's, we'll have the links to the Echo in the show notes and the DOT if you guys are
curious.
And if you have one, let me know, let me know how that works.
There's another thing that you might want people who are like paranoid about and always
listening.
The tap version doesn't listen to you until you hit the button.
Right.
The DOT is 90 bucks.
The DOT is 40 bucks and the big Echo is 140 bucks.
So the DOT and I don't think the DOT is not always listening either, right?
The DOT is.
Yeah.
Oh, it is?
You're telling me the DOT does everything the big Echo does.
It's just not a huge speaker.
Yeah.
It doesn't have as big speaker and it doesn't have as like the microphone.
That seems obvious then that seems like that for 40 bucks, that's an obvious way to try
it out.
Try it out.
Yeah.
See that starts tempting me too.
Like I don't need it in my life.
I don't need those things.
But for 40 bucks, I can-
It seems like a lot of fun to do it.
The category is interesting enough.
No, it's better because it has the aux out and everything so you can hook it up to like
a decent speaker system.
No.
That's great.
Yeah.
That's the draw to the ones that don't have the speakers is they can be hooked up.
That's pretty clever.
Yeah.
Actually, if you go look on Amazon, go look at the advertising material, it shows it hooked
up to a receiver.
Yeah.
I see that.
To like a Pioneer or something.
Also it will-
That's what I've done.
Yeah.
It will also connect to the speakers using Bluetooth so I could just pair it to the Bose
Bluetooth speaker.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So at the Makerspace, we paired an Echo Dot to a Bluetooth speaker to improve its speakers.
And during Cyber Dark Black Tuesday, Friday, whatever it's called, they were doing three
Echo Dots for a combined discounted price of like $60 or something.
Wow.
This is a very...
That's a very compelling that they're having that-
Are they sending it to the Hue lights?
Oh, man.
Yeah.
They're sending it to the studio.
So that just seems like a-
I just want this in my room so I can be like, hey, turn on my lights when I wake up or hey,
turn them off at night without having to go hit the switch, which is really far away.
That's what I'm interested in because I've identified as a lights project as something
that is going to have wife acceptance factor and also sort of in-law acceptance factor
because they've already got a sort of a lighting system.
And I want to experiment with the Dot to do control of lighting.
Yes, for sure.
And I wonder, you know, if I got just a couple of smart plugs, I could make all of these
lights controllable.
One thing I noticed in discussion of this is that it seems like busy people or people
with children are very interested in these products, just in the kind of direct accessibility,
the kind of a lot of times in busy situations, you can use your voice when you can't use
your hands or sit down to do something more complicated.
Like I'm coming in the door at home and my hands are full of my bag for the day and my
groceries.
It'd be nice to just-
But you still need information or you want to turn-
Turn on the lights.
For those of you, for those of you that want to do like IoT stuff, but without the development,
Alexa was recently added to IFTTT so you can do if this, then that rules and hook Alexa
up to all the other pipes that IFTTT supports.
You know, the only thing I wish, does anybody know-
Which includes Hue lights and all the rest of it.
So the Echo runs on what, Fire OS?
What does it do?
Do we know what the underlying operating system is to the Echo?
Is it Linux?
You would have to think so.
Probably broken.
It's probably not BSD.
It's probably Linux.
So it's-
Just based on their other-
Who knows?
It's safe to put in LadyJuice.
It's safe.
Well, it's only Linux and LadyJuice.
Right.
So that's the thing.
Well, okay.
Maybe you have to take it down and see what you can find out.
Well, now that we've all made Chris, boy, I can actually see a pretty cool episode out
of this too.
I could-
Oh, yeah.
And specifically talking about how to make it work with Linux.
Oh my gosh.
Now I'm going to sell it to myself.
I got to stop.
It's happening.
It's happening, everyone.
Well, I hope you enjoyed this half of the show.
I don't know how much more show we have, but I want to now get us ready to transition over
to Grand Forks, North Dakota.
I want to also let you know that coming up on the Linux Action Show, and probably this
show too, we'll be doing our 2017 predictions soon.
So I'd love to get the conversation rolling on that, linuxactionshow.reddit.com, if you
have thoughts about 2017, you can leave in the comments here, or start a thread, I don't
give an S, or just tweet them at me, at Chris L-A-S, and we'll start talking about that
very soon.
So what we're going to do now is a little internet magic.
We'll hit pause on our end, and when it comes back, you'll be hearing from Mr. Colonel Linux.
Something a little different.
Live from Grand Forks, North Dakota, the show that puts you, the listener, in the driver's
seat because you are the content.
The phone lines are open to be a part of the program.
Give us a call.
It's toll free, 1-877-347-0011, and we'll talk about your tech problems, or your business
and tech problems.
Linux advocate, above all else, small business owner, and now host of the only show that
centered around you, the audience, welcome to Ask Noah.
And as you might have guessed, I am Noah.
Now this show, well this particular episode really, was born right at the end of LASS.
Basically Chris said, I want to see, can we get a show up and running in 48 hours?
And so this is the test of that.
The job looks much easier from the outside than it actually is.
To actually get all of the equipment set up, get everything tested, get levels right, get
the recording set up, get the graphics rolling, all of that, it takes time.
And so I don't have all of the equipment I want.
I don't have things set up the way I want it to.
But we're going to try this and see if we can take calls, if this works.
So you call in 1-877-347-0011 and we'll talk.
Ask any question you want, ask it about Linux, ask it about technology in general, or ask
it about business.
We're going to start going out to the phones and let's see here, who do we have?
We're going to start with Justin from Boston, Massachusetts.
So there's a little bit of a delay right now for the way that our call system is set up.
Justin will be here with us in a second and I'll take his questions.
I made a post on Reddit a while back about business and how we set everything up and
how we got things rolling here at AltaSpeed and that post got so many likes and so many
other follow-up questions.
People sent me emails.
People went online and sent in contact forms and got a hold of me.
All sorts of different ways.
So if you have a business question, you can answer that as well.
So Justin, you're with us and you're here from Boston, Massachusetts I believe.
Hello.
Welcome to Ask Noah.
Hey Noah.
How's it going?
So it's a bit of a complicated setup but it comes down to this.
I am looking at building a personal infrastructure for a replacement Google Drive.
After some price hikes with Google Drive, some file manipulations on Amazon Drive and
other cloud services, I've gotten really, really tired of trying to put terabytes of
data somewhere that is not physically at my home.
Gotcha.
Okay.
So I've got this idea of putting together a few boxes, putting NextCloud on these boxes
and sort of replacing Google Drive with that.
However, I've heard you and Chris, among others, have some issues with large amounts of data
with own cloud and NextCloud being a successor.
I have that same worry but I also wonder about multi-user support and if you guys have had
experience with that because this is a solution for tens of people and the ability to scale
this up if need be.
Currently, the plan is two or three machines that are going to be targeted from the desktop
client and then these two or three machines would be essentially their own redundancy.
If one goes down, the others pick up the slack and so forth.
Gotcha.
So I'll tell you what my experience has been.
I was one of the early adopters of own cloud, Chris was as well, and we used own cloud extensively
and what we found was it worked fine for syncing documents, for syncing pictures.
Large amount of files weren't a problem but when you took a 20 or 30 or 40 gigabyte file
and tried to sync that across multiple machines, what we found was you'd get files that were
corrupted and occasionally you'd have some files that were missed entirely altogether.
I have found that most of those problems have been resolved.
I was on the last version of own cloud before the split and I tried it with some test data
and ran that for a while and that seemed to work pretty well.
If you watched the last week's episode of the Linux Action Show, we actually talked
to Joss from the NextCloud project and they have continued to approve upon the technology
and feature set that own cloud left behind.
I have some lingering concerns.
First of all, I have some concerns with the database that they're using.
It is possible to swap it out, it's possible to point it to something other than SQLite.
The other thing I have a concern with is with the syncing application, it's using CSYNC
on the backend and the entire workhorse is essentially written in PHP and I'm not a coder
and I don't necessarily claim to understand some of the underpinnings of this but everyone
that is in the know tells me that the choices of technology that they have used are not
the best.
I'm going between two different options right now.
My first option is I'm looking at C file for doing file syncing but I'm actually also looking
at building a file server for our company to sync all of our files and we're still considering
NextCloud.
Joss actually talks about how they actually have deployments of large users, universities
so to speak.
If you haven't seen it, I'd suggest you go check out that episode because it does a very
good job of explaining how NextCloud does scale.
I would be willing to give it a shot I think if I were you as in fact I'm going to do the
same.
With that in mind, with your experience, how reliable is it in its rescanning I guess?
One of my concerns is I've, albeit in a virtual machine network, I have set up a few instances
of on cloud and it's nice to start out by just throwing data into the data directory
itself and letting NextCloud rescan and everything appears really nicely in the web interface
but that isn't always super viable and I've noticed that with the desktop client certain
folder names will just be ignored.
For example, I have a folder called archives and I have to explicitly rescan with that
folder being an exception list to get that folder to appear in the web archive or pulled
down by other users.
Are these the kind of problems that you've had experience with?
Yep, I've experienced almost all of those.
I have found that the way to make own cloud the happiest is to install the client, point
it towards whatever directory you're going to use and then give it a couple of minutes
to kind of sync itself up and then start adding data to that directory.
The worst possible thing you can do is climb in under the hood and start moving data around
on the server.
I have destroyed my entire own cloud instance, well my user account anyway, all of my data.
I've erased all of my data by doing stuff like that.
So I would encourage you to be pretty cautious in that regard but I think it's pretty much
ready for prime time.
I think I would go ahead and give it a shot.
And again, I'll be able to tell you more as time goes on because I'm going to be implementing
this myself.
I'm going to try Nextcloud and see if it works.
I looked into the commercial alternatives like Dropbox and that's kind of the go-to
if you're in the business world is you sign up for Dropbox for business.
But they're charging, I think it's something like $9 a user or something.
We have a small team and file syncing is not a central part of our business so the idea
that I would be able to afford that kind of capital stream for the return on the investment
just isn't there.
We're going to head back over to Washington State right where Chris came from.
Sean's joining us.
Hi Sean, how are you?
Hey Noah.
Hey, thanks for joining us.
How can we help today?
So me and a couple of my friends are looking at starting a podcast, just us sitting around
shooting the breeze about technology and we got some mics, we got some computers and not
really sure where to go there from next.
Are you guys doing audio only or are you doing audio and video?
Audio only.
Awesome.
So never do video.
If you go talk to anyone that's doing video in the podcast, they'll tell you that they
would give, they'd trade their soul to the devil to go back in time and never do video.
Audio is actually pretty easy to do.
I have tried, I've used Skype and Mumble side by side and there's a lot of people that will
tell you that Skype is a very high quality piece of software.
I think Skype works okay.
I found that conference calling in Skype can be difficult at best and also I believe it's
Silk, the Kodak or a modified version of Silk that is the Kodak that's being used in Skype.
My understanding is that a future version of that or a built upon version of that is
the Opus Kodak which is what can be used in Mumble and also there is a growing number
of people that are using G.722 or 729, one of the two.
I can double check and get back to you but the G.722 is basically what they've done is
they have built upon what was a phone standard and built it out and so if you look at, I
actually had the opportunity to try some inter-price grade audio connection tools that were basically
designed to facilitate remote studio connections and they were using the G.722 Kodak.
That Kodak is available in software like Zoiper and so you can set up a conference call between
three or four participants or five participants and you could actually use the exact same
Kodak as the industry professionals were using.
If you have mics and you have audio interfaces and you're just looking for the connection
piece, that's an option.
If you want something simpler, Mumble is a great way to go too.
Yeah, because I'll be doing everything on Linux but the other two guys have, one uses
Linux and Windows and one uses just Windows, so.
Okay, great.
Well, I really appreciate you taking the time to call in again, 1-877-347-0011.
That's the number and we'll take your calls, we'll answer your questions.
It is really fun to be able to actually do this.
Every day I'm solving problems on Linux.
I'm going through and trying this stuff.
This Kodak thing was one thing that I was looking at doing because obviously we're looking
at implementing something like this on JB and so as I have gone through and kind of experimented
with this, I can't really make an episode about it but Sean calls in from Washington
and says that he wants to facilitate remote connection between him and his friends to
do a podcast.
Well, now we're talking, right?
Now that's something that we can do.
James, North Carolina, you're calling in about System D. How can we help?
Oh, yes, I was calling about some, I guess, more general recommendations with Ubuntu and
I primarily use Linux myself.
Switching over to System D from Upstart, a lot of programs that I had used for programming
things like automatic triggers for like green dimming when power disconnects from a laptop
or things like that no longer work with System D. So I was just curious if you guys have
any recommendations of like programs that you can interact with those System D triggers
to do things.
That's interesting.
So I have done a number of different upgrades in the last couple of years moving from  to
the latest version of RHEL which of course uses System D and it's interesting.
I have worked with some pretty esoteric pieces of software and I've not run into that issue.
Most of those calls are set up so that it just translates any of those Upstart commands
right to System D. It seems like it's pretty smoother, RedSK, System D, but do you have
some custom stuff that is written in there, custom stuff that it's calling or custom
things that it's doing?
No.
Oh, I just remembered the name of it.
It's called Cuttlefish.
It was a program that would essentially tie into some of the triggers for things like
when you log on, if you I guess disconnect from your session, if you put the laptop to
sleep, wake it up, that kind of deal.
So you could basically connect that to any type of bash script and you could have it
run as triggered or you could have it do a few preset actions as well.
Yeah, so I guess I'll tell you what I'll do.
If you head over to jupyterbroadcasting.com, click on the contact link, click on Ask Noah.
I don't have any great recommendations for you but I know a guy that knows everything
there is to know about moving older init systems to System D and if you send me a contact form,
I'll put you in contact with him and I'll see if you guys can get together and see if
you guys can work something out because I'm sure there's somebody that has run through
this.
For me, it has been a marvelous experience.
Moving to System D has been flawless.
In fact, the only thing that I've really noticed is my boot times have gone from like a minute,
minute and a half down to mere seconds.
That's the big difference for me from moving from the older init systems to System D. So
I really don't have any complaints and like I said, I worked with some pretty esoteric
pieces of software.
I worked with the university on some chemical calculation software that I mean, it was just
a tiny little company and it's a very, very limited use case and all of that stuff worked
perfectly right out of the box.
Angela is calling from Washington.
I have a feeling I might have talked to you before.
Yeah, it may be possibly.
I don't actually have a question but I thought it would be cool to let you know that back
in 2015 at Linux Fest Northwest, my friend Jenny gave you her Mac laptop and asked you
to fix it, which is laughable in its own and you gave her a Linux laptop.
She has been using that for the last year and a half but not like super well and she's
trying to finish up her AA degree, which she only needs about three or four classes to
complete and she is choosing to go back to school and taking CIS 105 intro to Linux with
that laptop.
I thought that you should be able to have that credit and know that she is dabbling
now in Linux to a deeper level.
That's outstanding.
You know what's funny about that is I think I was the only one participating in that conversation.
I'll leave this out for you guys.
So we're at dinner and her friend Jenny is telling me about how her laptop is having
some troubles not working.
Turns out like the motherboard was like totally dead and so I said, if I send you a Linux
computer would you use it?
She kind of looks at me like I'm crazy, two eyes, one eye and she's like yeah, I guess
and so I got back to Grand Forks and I set a computer up and I shipped it off to her
and I get a message from, I think it was, I think you Angela actually sent me a message
and here's a picture of this computer and she's like why did a laptop just arrive at
our house and what is it for?
I'm like well, it's for Jenny, it's for Jenny and so yeah, so anyway, so that's how she
wound up with that computer.
It's not a, it's not a, it's not a, you know, any terribly nice computer but it's something
that if you're just using daily stuff I think it gets you along, it gets her along just
fine, right?
Yep, it does.
It does and now she's just going to be more confident in it and gosh, I feel like she's
going to know more about Linux than I will after taking this course.
Well that's awesome.
Thank you very much for the update and please make sure to give Jenny the number 1-877-3400-11.
I have to memorize my own number.
That would be good, 1-877-3400-11, 1-877-3400-11, someday I'll have that totally memorized and
I won't have that issue.
I love giving Linux to people that don't have a predisposition to it.
I love giving Linux to people that don't already have it made up in their mind that
they're going to like Linux or they're going to hate Linux, Linux is going to work, Linux
is not going to work.
The people that can just evaluate it from the standpoint of I have a need, I have a
task, I want to get that task done, how do I do that task?
That's where Linux is going to succeed.
Really that's where any operating system succeeds because if you take me as a Linux
user and put me on a Windows environment or a Mac environment, I'm going to have a tough
time too.
The inspiration for this show is pretty simple.
My company, AltaSpeed Technologies, we've spent the last couple of years perfecting
providing creative cost saving solutions to our customers without sacrificing quality
using open source software.
We go into a place, to a business that their budget is they spend $500 per workstation
for an office week.
We tell them we're going to provide that to them at nothing.
They're just going to pay us for their time.
They say that they're paying X amount of thousands of dollars to hire this in-house mail administrator
guy that is going to work on this crappy exchange server that works less than 50% of the time.
We show them other solutions and we're going to take that knowledge and we are going to
morph that into a show and provide those answers to you not at our billing rate of $75 an hour
but we're going to give that to you for free just by calling the number.
I think this has the potential to morph into a really successful show.
I hope it morphs into a really successful show and so I want to thank everyone for taking
the time to be here, for being on the phone lines, waiting on hold, particularly those
of you that are calling internationally.
It is a toll free call though, 1-877-347-0011 so I would never be worried about calling.
It won't cost you anything.
That will bring us to the end of this week's test episode.
Keep that number guys, 1-877-347-0011.
We'll be back with you soon for another couple of test episodes and of course finally the
official launch of the YAS NOAH program.
Now if you want to support this program as well as the rest of the network, head over
to patreon.com slash today.
You can directly participate in getting this program off the ground.
Special thanks to Sarah, our producer, Ham Radio, our call screener and of course Rekai,
our editor and resident wizard.
To keep up to date with what the network's doing, head over to jupiterbroadcasting.com
slash calendar and a big thank you to Chris and Wes for giving us this time slot.
Make sure to tune in next week for their clip segment.
Have a merry Christmas, a happy new year and I'll see all of you guys on Sunday for our
predictions episode in the next two weeks.
You guys have a great night.
We have, who do we have here, Ryan, Portland, Port Orchard, Washington.
Welcome to YAS NOAH.
Hey, how's it going?
Excellent.
How can we help today?
So you mentioned on an episode of last recently that you switched over to ARCH on all your
boxes because you're kind of like little things like functioning network manager and all.
Right, yeah, I'm weird like that.
I really prefer my wireless to work, yeah.
What are you trying to live in the future or something?
Come on, man.
I know it's crazy.
I'm a whore for the details.
So I was wondering what made you choose ARCH specifically over something like Ubuntu Mate
which doesn't seem to have all the same issues as standard Ubuntu.
A couple of things.
The first and foremost factor that really led me to ARCH was these days I move more
and I'm spending more and more time doing things for Jupiter Broadcasting and so it
makes a lot of sense to use the same environment stuff that the other people you're interfacing
with do, right?
And that was one of the reasons that drew me to Fedora early on is because I was dealing
with so much Red Hat that it just made sense to have Fedora on my desktop and these days
every Sunday at least I'm doing something and if there's an app pic that we're doing
that week it's really nice to be able to have access to the same applications as everyone
else.
The other side of it too is that I have some ground to step up on and say, okay, I tried
ARCH.
I ran it for X amount of months.
Here's why it didn't end up working for me and then I can put that baby to rest and I
don't have to constantly  because right now or at least prior to that it was always
well, I'm using Ubuntu and there's all these people out there telling me that there's
this better Linux experience available.
Really what I found is I have probably the same amount of problems.
I just  they are more solvable, number one.
Number two, I expect to have to solve them and number three is they're not  well
that's not entirely true.
Some of them are kind of show stopping problems but so far they've all mostly been solvable
or tolerable and not having wireless in Ubuntu was not that way.
Now as for why I didn't choose Ubuntu Mate, the Mate desktop does not offer the ability
at least out of the box, I think they're including it, to launch an application by
hitting the super key and I have  it is so ingrained in my mind when I want Firefox,
I hit super key, F-I-R-E, enter and then I expect Firefox to be on my screen or super
key, T-H-U-N, enter and I expect Thunderbird to be on my screen.
Without those  it's a difference in how I use the computer and I'm really not willing
to make that change.
Other things you can do, you can use Synapsys, in fact I think they're including Elantra
by default but it's  I see Ubuntu Mate as my utilitarian type distro.
So the computer I'm on right now for example is running Ubuntu Mate because it's just
an appliance, it's a computer that needs to sit there and it doesn't need to be pretty,
it doesn't need to switch desktops, I just need to open OBS for example and just have
it run.
That was not the case, that is not the case with my desktop, on my laptop.
So that's the short answer why I wound up on Arch.
Mostly happy  the latest thing that really bit me that I was super upset about was I
went to open Lightworks to edit a  or not Lightworks, Inkscape to edit a graphic and
Inkscape just wouldn't load.
Like I would click on the icon, nothing would happen.
So I had to drop to the terminal and then I ran the Inkscape command and then it gave
me some error that I didn't entirely understand, I had to Google the error and then I'm going
through and I'm going around and somewhere through there I was like, you know, I have
some tolerance when it's TeamViewer or some other non-proprietary piece of software but
like Inkscape, Inkscape is like a huge vector graphic, open source vector graphic editing
suite for Linux.
How in the world do you get to a point where you can't  where that doesn't work?
How is that a thing?
It doesn't even make sense to me.
So I was a little upset by that but got it to work and I guess it's worked now so far.