How's the packing going, Brent?
You on track to make it tonight?
I think actually the packing is the easy part.
No, I'm not going to make it tonight.
There's no way.
With the postal up crash and all the things
that I'm hoping to do, I am going to fail you.
I think it's going to be a morning thing.
I like that you're just scheduling in the post-show crash.
Like, that's a good idea.
That shows he's an experienced podcaster.
Oh, yeah.
I mean, you know how real that is, right?
It's essential.
So I don't know.
So the plan originally was we'd do the show.
This is always how these planning sessions go,
is we're planning.
And it's like, so yeah, then you could just
head out like after the show and then hit the road.
Should be no big deal, right?
And because I'm always, this always happens to me too.
It's like, oh, yeah, no problem.
Yeah, that's fine.
And then you get to the day of and you're like,
there's no effing way I'm leaving after the show.
Even though I've been prepping all week, there's no way.
I mean, one, it means you have to have everything packed,
right?
Yeah, right.
Oh, I'm sorry, Brent.
But you know what?
What you got to do is set yourself
like a timed windows to pack.
And then you just, you know, you take breaks.
You'll get through it.
You'll make it.
Or just don't bring anything.
You know, just go freestyle.
Just throw caution to the wind.
I did give my car a car wash, so there's that at least.
Hey, you'll come in style.
Hello, friends, and welcome back to your weekly Linux talk show.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
And my name is Brent.
Hello, gentlemen.
I'm talking like this today because it's a very exciting
show.
Hello, perhaps.
We have some desktop woes that we're
going to share with you today.
And we're going to be talking about some of the things
that we're going to be talking about today.
Some desktop woes that we're going to share with you
that have struck recently, we'll just say.
And we have some thoughts on some new hardware that's
going to get drafted for some space work.
We have some bugs to file.
There's a lot to do today.
And we're going to round it all out with some great boosts,
some pics, and more.
So before we get any further, let's
say time-appropriate greetings to our virtual lug.
Hello, Mumble Room.
Hello, hello.
Hey, Chris.
Hey, Wes, and hey, Brent.
Time-appropriate greetings, everybody.
Hello, hello.
Thank you for joining us.
Thank you to everybody watching over at jupyter.tube
as we stream it live.
And a good morning to our friends over at TailScale.
TailScale is a mesh VPN protected by WireGuard's noise
protocol.
Noise?
It's a noise protocol.
I just think that's so great.
We love it.
We use it every single day.
I think it's going to change your game.
I think it's up there with R-Sync and SSH.
Go check out TailScale, tailscale.com.
Get it for free on 20 devices.
And tell them the Unplugged program sent you.
So we have an interesting story to talk about this week.
It seems that NASA has selected SciFive,
makers of RISC-V systems, as maybe the potential go-to
ecosystem for future space hardware.
And of course, that's obviously going to be running Linux.
And SciFive, they're like over the moon on this one.
They say that their devices are going
to offer a 100x increase in computational capacity.
Well, yeah, if you remember when we were talking with Tim,
he was mentioning where Linux was kind of running
on this off-the-shelf hardware, but they
had these pretty much ancient PowerPC processors
that were all radiation-hardened.
But those are getting pretty old, and we need something new.
And so yeah, kind of the customizability
of the RISC-V platform, they can make something
that's a huge speed improvement, but also still
meet all of the strenuous needs of interplanetary travel.
There's a lot I like about this.
First of all, I think this is just a great platform
for them to pick.
It's something that'll be around a long time,
and it's an open platform.
And it's going to encourage driver development for Linux
and all those things, which is really great.
And it's one of the things that when an organization like NASA
selects a hardware platform, it kind of just
it means we're going to see a base level of support
for a very long time.
So that's really great.
I think the other thing that's really kind of excellent
about this is I would expect it's
going to bring more developers into RISC-V. It's going to mean
they're going to have more people that are learning how
to write RISC-V of applications and systems.
Like I think, I don't know if the halo effect of this
is the right term, but I think just the effect,
the second order effects of NASA doing this
and requiring software developed for it
means that there's just going to be more of an ecosystem
investment in RISC now.
Seems like nice timing too, just as they're
sort of gaining confidence in deploying Linux
in some of these environments, plus now deploying RISC-V.
And we know Linux has been putting in,
there's been many developers putting in some time
to get Linux's RISC-V support up and going.
I think you're right, that's only going to accelerate.
Wouldn't it be interesting if the story of RISC-V
is like this slow one?
You know, you start seeing it in these rovers, helicopters,
or whatever they might use it on, moon buggies.
But wouldn't it be funny if it takes like 20 years,
I mean not funny, but wouldn't it just figure
it takes like 10, 20 years of using RISC-V in this capacity,
starts as hard drive controllers,
and then it kind of works its way up.
And you know, by now we're starting to see
those single board computers, but not very many of them,
and they're very specialized.
And it's just the slowest of the slow burns,
but it does actually seem to be going
in the upwards direction.
It seems like it's kind of, you know,
the hardware world, CPUs, it just takes time.
Devices have, you know, they age in place to some extent,
and then just to get the adoption to meet the standards.
You know, ARM's dominating the world now,
but there were times where just like,
oh, that's that funny embedded CPU.
I mean, don't do anything serious with that.
Yeah, maybe so, you're right.
And I wonder if it isn't even a longer,
upper hill battle now, because there is so much momentum
around X86, and ARM, and PowerPC.
There's so much already established momentum development
ecosystem that for something to come along
and truly get widespread adoption,
it takes some of that stuff aging out.
It takes some of that stuff just kind of fading away.
The developer talent leaving,
it's not like they have an incentive
to switch to RISC-V right away.
So it would make sense that as these trends
and these technologies become more entrenched over time,
that something new coming along is gonna have
a much longer road before it really gets
significant market share.
It's gonna be a while, but this is a huge first step.
I wonder if Tim will have any thoughts
when we get down to JPL and talk to him about it.
We'll have to bend his ear on this one.
We are gonna be there soon.
We have not left the road for the road yet,
but we do leave soon after next week's episode.
So we're doing a double next Sunday over at jupyter.tube.
We're recording two Linux unplugs,
so that way we have one recorded while we're on the road.
Just give us a little drive time.
Yeah, you know, if you're not always able to make it live,
that's one not to miss.
Yeah, and then after that,
we're gonna do the shows live from the road.
September 18th.
I think what's lucky about next week is
three of us are gonna be in the studio together, I think.
That's true, right, Wes?
You're gonna make it too?
Mm-hmm, I sure will.
Assuming you get all your stuff packed.
Hey, now.
I think I can make it there in seven days.
I think we can do that.
Ha ha ha.
But that also doesn't happen too often.
You know, only what, like a couple times a year?
So that is a pretty special thing,
or at least it is for me.
So I would say if you wanna catch one,
that's one to catch.
Two to catch, two to catch.
We've been looking forward to this.
The audience has helped make it possible
with the splits to the boost of the show.
Mm, my tank is overfilled.
Brent's gonna make it down,
even though now, of course, we have wildfires,
of course, in the area.
So he'll get a nice kind of a smoked Brent flavor
when he arrives.
We lit off the fireworks to welcome him.
Yeah, that's what we do.
Smokey welcome.
Although we thought he's gonna be on time,
so we let them off a little early,
and so that's all an embarrassing thing, but yeah.
Then, so Brent gets here a couple of days
from when we're recording.
Then we're gonna record some content.
We'll do that double up,
and then we're hitting the road for our west coast tour.
And we have dates at meetup.com slash Jupiter Broadcasting.
You never know, things can always change,
so be sure you're following that.
Even if you're already signed up,
just keep an eye on things.
We also have that matrix room, West Coast Crew,
bit.ly slash West Coast Crew.
And we're gonna have some special Linode swag,
because of course, Linode is making this possible.
They're once again partnering with us
to make it doable from a financial standpoint
and from a operational standpoint
and from a logistics standpoint,
to go do these meetups and to go see the community,
to help invest in that community.
It's a real kind of like, you know, high level thing.
And they get it, and they support it,
and we're really grateful.
So we'll have some special swag from them too
that we'll be giving out.
And we'll also have some geocaches
that we'll be stashing along the way.
I'd also like to say if you're planning on joining us
to one of the meetups,
it is pretty important for us to know that you're attending.
So if you can RSVP at the meetup page,
that just helps us suss out some of the numbers
and be able to let the events spaces,
the restaurants know ahead of time
so that we're not surprising them.
So if you can make sure to RSVP, that'd be great.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
Go there to get $100 in 60 day credit on a new account.
And that's a great way to support the show.
You know, you're getting yourself
some really great experience.
You're getting a hundred bucks to go play with,
I think the best cloud hosting platform out there.
And it's a great way to support the show.
You're supporting the show.
How great is that?
And Linode is really the Linux geeks cloud.
They've got 11 data centers worldwide.
They've been doing this for nearly 19 years.
So they really know what they're doing.
They've had to build the best in class experience
to beat out and compete with everybody else who came along,
not to mention the hyperscalers now,
who seem to have unlimited budgets because let's face it,
their data center operations are funded
by like a completely unrelated business.
So they just had the capacity,
but Linode has had to survive
on the merits of their business.
And their performance is incredible.
They have 11 data centers around the world.
They have a ton of great services too,
stuff you can just one click deploy.
I was just looking recently
because I was setting myself up a new Linode.
And I noticed they just added the Unified Network
application, which is a control panel
that simplifies network management.
If you have Unified Gear, you can throw it up on Linode.
They've always, always been innovating.
Every time I go there, there's like new stuff they've added.
In fact, now they even have a better UI
for displaying it all.
I'm looking at it right now.
I've stopped doing the read,
and now I'm just looking at the different rigs
I want to deploy.
I love Linode, and I think you will too.
The performance, the ease of just getting things up
and running.
And some days I'm feeling like I just want
a push button solution.
Some days I want to build it up from the ground.
And Linode lets me do whichever I prefer.
And if I ever make a mistake, if I ever get stuck,
if I ever need help, they've got 24 seven support.
Because the business, again, has had to actually survive
on the merits of being a really good cloud provider.
And so part of that is having, well,
the best customer support.
So go try them out.
Super fast rigs and networking,
11 data centers around the world,
a Linux culture that runs deep, and 24 seven support.
Plus, it's a great way to support the show.
So go get that hundred bucks.
Linode.com slash unplugged.
One more time, it's Linode.com slash unplugged.
We got some baller boosts, the big supporters
for the show this week.
And just a reminder, we have a link in the show notes
to an open issue to help us source a new baller boost
and sound bite, I should say.
And there's some really good ones in there.
So do keep them coming.
I think what we have three or four people,
it's mostly Brent.
Yeah, Brent laid the seeds here and did a good job.
I figured I would like, you know, warm things up
and leave a sort of template for those to follow.
And I've been pretty happy with the extra submissions.
So I think keep them rolling in.
I'd like to see more people do it though,
because right now this is feeling like one of those issues
where like I bring up, hey, what color should this thing be?
And everybody has an opinion on the color,
but then I ask, okay, who's gonna write the code
to set that to be that color?
And then like, nobody steps up.
It's like, oh, so nobody really cares.
I do.
They have an opinion until the work comes to,
yeah, right, I know you do.
Yeah, so we'll have a link in the show notes
and we'll get a new baller boost.
But in the meantime, I do wanna thank Jade Lion
for their 111,111 SATs.
They boosted in for my long podcasting 2.0 rant support
last week.
Thank you very much for that, Jade.
And I wanted to say, you know,
something interesting happened in the last week.
Fountain has made a new discovery mechanism.
They've built a new discovery mechanism
into the Fountain podcast player.
And one of the tabs when you're looking for podcasts
to find now is some of the most boosted shows on Fountain.
They call it hot on Fountain in there.
And this exposes shows that are getting some big boosts.
And as a result, we've had thousands of people
find the show in the last week.
What people are doing is these boosts act as signal.
When people see a show that gets boosted a lot,
it's a good indication there's high quality there.
It's better than any kind of algorithm from Google.
It's real people sending real value to that podcaster.
It's a real signal.
So Fountain is now exposing that
and showing you which ones are getting the boosts.
And what's incredible now is not only can you support
the show by boosting and get a message onto the show,
but you can also make it possible for other people
to discover the show by putting this on these lists.
So when we get a boost from Jade, that's 111,000 SATs,
that puts us up there on that list.
That makes a difference to the show,
not just in a monetary sense,
but in a way that helps other people find the show.
So thank you very much for that.
And Fountain, keep on rocking it.
Check out the Hot on Fountain
and their new lightning podcast section,
helping really spread value for value
and podcasting 2.0 and decentralized podcast financing.
You know, Chris, I would imagine
that's an unintended consequence.
Like that's not something we could have really predicted
when we kind of kicked all this off in January.
And I totally think it makes sense.
I hadn't thought about it, but it absolutely makes sense
is I've discovered shows by,
so one of the big things in Fountain,
not to go on and on about it,
because I think Podverse is really great too.
But one of the great things in Fountain
is that they have this clips section
that is really well done.
And I have added three weekly listens now,
three weekly listens to my podcast collection
through this clips mechanism on here.
And boy, isn't that something like,
how did this not get thought of earlier?
It's a perfect thing for highlighting and sharing podcasts.
It totally is.
Because how often are you listening to one,
you're like, that was a great little thing.
They summarized X or they explained that well.
I'd love to share that with someone
who I might not be able to convince offhand
to listen to the whole darn podcast.
Or me.
Like, I don't know if I want to listen
to the whole darn podcast,
but a lot of times people will clip
some of the best moments in the show.
And I'm like, that was good.
And I go and I subscribe.
And then the other thing that's in here
is the individual clips can get boosts.
So you can like a clip with 10 sats.
And so then you can start looking at the most boosted clips.
And so there's a lot of ways you can sort by it.
And it's a signal that works.
I think it's fascinating.
It's better than I think than Google putting their hands
on that algorithm and promoting things
like NBC News as a podcast.
Anyways, moving on.
John A boosted in with 30,000 sats.
We asked how far behind folks are.
He says, wait, you mean people aren't listening
and boosting the moment a new episode releases?
30,000 sats from John A.
And here's what's incredible about that.
John A's first boost was last week.
Second week, he's now a baller booster.
So thank you, John, for the support.
That is really great.
And then, of course, a frequent baller booster
comes into the show.
And that is, of course, Optimus Gray
coming in with a row of McDucks, 22,222 sats.
Thank you kindly.
He's on board with the Golden Dragon as the LUP mascot.
So we have second approval from an audience member.
I think that means it's official.
Yes, you have the deal right there.
But Golden Dragon needs to make sure he gets a hype song.
He needs a hype song.
So I think that's understandable.
Maybe he gets a licensed hype song.
Maybe something that goes up on the soundboard for when
he boosts in, something like that.
So we'll have to work that out.
But I think it's a great suggestion.
Thank you, Optimus.
And thank you for the support.
If you would like to be a baller and boost into the show
and get your message read in this section,
please send us a baller boost with a new podcast app
at newpodcastapps.com.
And we want to transition into something
that is hard to talk about on the show,
because it often sounds like we're being just critical.
And we're just kind of complaining about something.
But that is not the case.
We love this stuff, right?
But we're invested in it.
And we want to make sure that it's
meeting the needs of users, that it's growing,
that it's adapting for the future, all of those things
that the projects we use are healthy.
If you don't talk about problems,
how can that be the case?
And that's the lens in which we are going
to look at today's segment.
Well, today's segment has been on my mind for, I think,
about a year and a half, maybe more.
And again, it comes from an absolute place of love.
And today, we're talking about some struggles with plasma,
KD's plasma.
I've been a plasma user for, I think,
it's something like five years now.
First started on Anturgos and moved on to Kubuntu.
And gentlemen, I mean, there's some in the studio as well,
some plasma.
And where does it fit in your lives?
Oh, yeah, we use it here in production.
I use it for my main recording OS.
I don't always use it as my sit-on-the-couch OS,
but I definitely put it in places
where I care if it breaks.
Yeah, I think that laptop you're using there is probably
I'm running plasma as we're doing the show right now.
This machine right here is plasma
that I'm sitting in front of.
And then, of course, our OBS machine is plasma.
It's been a really good production work desktop.
Yeah, so clearly lots of plasma love going around here.
And for good reason.
I think it's a desktop environment that
has a ton of features that we love.
It's kind of extensible.
You can modify it to your own needs.
But what I've noticed, and I haven't quite
been able to put my finger on it until just about this last week
or so, what I've noticed for this last year and a half
is some changes or maybe some rough edges
that I've noticed in Kubuntu at first, especially around 2204.
But also, that caused me to go looking elsewhere
for some great plasma integrations.
And I got to say, it's been a little rough road for me.
So I wanted to explore, I think, the history of Kubuntu
and the history of other spins, like Fedora's spin,
and plasma, where it's come from the mid-2000s to now.
And I think there's been some major changes
in how it's been integrated in various distributions.
And we start to ask some big questions like, well, why?
Where's it headed, I think, is really what I want to know.
Because I want it to stick around and be the best it can
be.
So that's an interesting question.
If I think back into the past, I can definitely,
some distributions really stand out.
Soos had a really strong KDE desktop experience.
I seem to recall Mandrake and Mandriva
having a pretty good plasma desktop or KDE desktop
experience at the time.
So I'm curious when you say you've seen a shift over time.
Maybe let's start there.
What do you mean specifically?
Well, I did a little research.
And back in 2007, which if some of you were heavy Linux users,
you may remember this.
But it seems that for the most important distributions,
Red Hat and Fedora had GNOME, Debian, Ubuntu also.
But OpenSUSE, like you said, had KDE as a default desktop.
Mandriva certainly did.
PC Linux OS as well.
And Slackware and Mepis as well.
So that is round five, five or so for KDE
as the top contenders with three or so going to GNOME.
And these days, that's not quite the case.
Some distributions have gone to desktop agnostic,
I think I'll call it.
So now you see OpenSUSE just kind of offering KDE or GNOME
or Xfce right in the installer, which is actually
a really nice way to do it.
But you have some popular distributions like Mint,
for instance, that doesn't even offer, well,
either GNOME or KDE.
They've got Cinnamon, Mate, or Xfce as their sort of choices.
But then Ubuntu and Debian has the default.
Well, I think Ubuntu is a special case.
Debian offers choices, but sort of pre-selects a default
as GNOME for you.
But in the corporate arena these days,
I think GNOME is really the contender.
Red Hat, RHEL, CentOS, they've all
had GNOME as sort of the main thrust, and that makes sense.
I mean, they put a lot of work into that development, right?
They're one of the main funders of development, would you say?
There was a time where Unity had made some serious inroads
there, but after Canonical chose to switch back to GNOME,
I think it's really taken the day.
And even when Unity was strong there,
GTK was still kind of the king.
Exactly, yeah.
That's the underlying theme, is GTK has
done really well in that space.
Honestly, I know a few folks who use Linux at work.
I bet they don't even know Plasma exists.
Yeah, and of course, of course, we're
talking a slice of the market.
Obviously, Qt is extremely successful.
It's huge in the enterprise.
We're talking about desktop here.
Yeah, desktop specifically, I think, is pretty accurate.
I think my question then that we're trying to answer
is, are the spins and the flavors just kind
of second-rate citizens, and are they getting enough attention?
Because my sort of anecdotal experience
in the last several weeks, even months, of trying
to suss out this space, trying Neon, for instance,
which is promising.
It offers the latest Plasma on top of really stable Ubuntu
base, which is kind of a nice combination.
So trying that when I was at Alex's place
for the last few months, trying Fedora's spin of KDE
has been an interesting journey.
And then just kind of retesting my own assumptions
about what 2204 might offer me, I sort of come
into some struggles, actually, which I don't love.
And I haven't heard that much from either of you.
Have you tried sort of, I think, Chris, you have Neon in front
of you, is that correct?
Yeah, you got it.
You know, when I'm listening, what I'm hearing
is you kind of started going from tried and true
stable LTS Plasma to more like modern rolling current Plasma.
And I wonder if what you're seeing
is the difference between kind of these milestone releases.
Carefully gated, kind of curated, right?
Had some time to get that level of polish
and those things ironed out before moving on.
Yeah, although I do run Neon, and I don't really
run into any particular problems,
although my NVIDIA driver is broken at the moment.
So those things do happen.
I feel like my Neon experiences, I
don't know if I'd call them problems, but things kind of
change and go back, right?
Or maybe there's a thing where you notice something crashes
a little bit for a week, but then by the time you've updated
again, it's gone.
So those things show up, but they're not always static.
Yeah, and none of them have been like deal breakers yet.
There's that.
They're more like curiosities, like, oh, that's different,
right?
Right, but I can still get to what I need to get to,
so I'll continue on, and then I'll update in a couple of days.
You also touched on something there, Brent,
that I think could almost be a show topic on its own,
and that is do these spins get the same level of attention
that the main like distro version?
You have Ubuntu proper, right?
You've got Fedora workstation, and then you've got Kubuntu,
and you've got the Fedora KDE spin.
And just like we know the answer.
We know that those spins have less users and less developers,
and KDE is now often relegated to spin status or flavor status.
And so I think that means it's often not
getting a complete like all of distro implementation focus.
And that's not to take anything away
from the Kubuntu team or any of the other distro
makers who are making the plasma version of that distro,
but I do think there might be something
to your underlying observation in that over time,
the main spin of all of these distros
really is, for the most part, their GNOME spin,
with some exceptions.
And maybe that has altered the implementation
to be less perfect.
I don't know, though.
I really don't know.
I mean, it sort of necessarily does, right?
I mean, KDE feels a little bit now
like it's mainly a community project from what
I've been able to research.
And I'm happy to be wrong about that if someone
has some inside information.
I think they proudly are a community project.
I think that's, you know.
Oh, oh, oh, I don't mean to take away from that.
I think as a community project, it
does some amazing, amazing, amazing things.
But I think because it's not the default of some
of these larger enterprise entities,
it maybe doesn't always get maybe the funding
for the kind of work that we would all love to see it get,
even though it's still a super impressive piece of software.
I think I come at this from the most loving place possible,
which is like, I want this thing to keep being as successful as
it has been.
And I hope that my observations are only
a shift in my own perspective.
You mentioned very astutely that maybe I'm just
looking at sort of more leading edge KDE.
And so I'm finding, of course, as I do,
finding more rough edges in the software.
I hope that's the case, is that I'm the one who has changed.
And KDE is not at all changing and just continuing
to do its wonderful thing.
I hope that's the answer because that
would make me quite happy.
But I just have some worries, I guess is the way to put it.
You know, it's hard to say.
I'd like to get into some of the specifics of what you run into.
Maybe we can kick that around a little bit.
For myself, I have definitely struggled
with plasma implementations when I have different monitors,
different resolutions, and different refresh rates.
And I struggle with that with GNOME as well.
It's just an area where, for me, I'm always
hitting bugs in Linux with.
And I wish that experience was better.
But on the whole, I feel like things are collectively just
getting better overall.
Then there's all these edge cases,
like, well, are you using an NVIDIA card?
Are you on Wayland?
Are you on X11?
Are you on an Intel machine or an AMD machine?
And then things get a little weird.
But I want to know specifically what problems you had.
Yeah, and I think my data isn't necessarily empirical.
And I should have taken a more scientific approach.
However, we've had discussions back and forth
for a few months now about the kinds of problems
I've run into.
And I think some of this was pretty clear
when I was at Alex's place.
He has some pretty new hardware.
I think it was a 3080 or something
he's running over there that had some video issues, especially
with Wayland.
It ended up being nearly unusable.
And I had to switch X11, still had some issues there.
So I think that is partly explained
by some hardware, for sure.
And like you mentioned, I was constantly
having monitor issues.
He has multiple relatively state-of-the-art monitors
and relatively state-of-the-art GPUs as well.
And so I can't point the finger only
at the display manager or anything like that.
I think hardware still does play a huge factor there.
So it's not fair to point the finger only
at one of the things in the pipeline here.
So kudos to you for checking me on that.
Well, no, no.
I mean, it's all like the end user experience, right?
I mean, everyone runs into these problems.
So video monitor issues, anything in particular?
Two out of three times, it would work fine.
The third time, it would wake from sleep, for instance.
One of the monitors would just never turn on.
So I'd have to put it back to sleep
and then hope for the next two out of three.
That was a thing that was occurring specifically
on Alex's system over at his office,
where I would adjust the chair quite frequently.
So that was a slightly annoying one.
But you know what is interesting,
which is sort of moving away from the hardware a little bit
and more some of the Plasma-specific features,
something I got into before that trip,
so before headed to Alex's, here on my local computers
that I've been running Kubuntu on for quite a while
is Plasma has this wonderful concept
of something called activities, which is almost like,
but don't call it this, it's almost like virtual desktops.
But it just is a bit more powerful and more sort
of context-specific, I think it's worth reading into
because it's a great idea.
But I tried it for a few weeks and found a few bugs in it
to the point where it was a little clumsy to use.
And I thought, okay, well, I'm gonna try neon
at Alex's place and we'll try it there again.
And it was even more problematic in the sense
that it's almost like it was this great feature
that got implemented years and years ago that worked great.
But then it just hasn't, it's one of those features
that's a little hidden and not everybody uses it.
And so I feel like maybe there's a little bit
of entropy there.
And I think that adds to my like, oh, well,
what, how can we fix this?
And I think submitting bugs is certainly a way to do that.
And yep, I can do that and yep, I have done that.
We'll come up with a list in a little bit.
But I admittedly haven't submitted bugs
for every single issue that I ran into
because sometimes it was like two, three, four things piling
on top of each other in the span of trying to get work done
in an hour sort of thing.
So it started getting a little worrisome, I suppose.
But in the studio, Chris, it sounds like you don't run
into any of this.
So I don't know, is it just me?
This'll derail a little bit perhaps,
but I wanted to give voice, Casey in our chat room
had a thought that I'd kind of wondered a little bit as well.
He's wondering how much of some of this might be Brent
becoming more technically knowledgeable and experienced.
The more you sort of learn what's going on under the covers,
the more you take deeper looks at things,
the more cracks you discover.
And he also here calls out that it's not,
this is mostly just saying,
Brent, you've learned a lot and we all see it.
Oh, thanks.
And I think that's a possibility,
like I'm evolving and that's fine, that's fine.
I wonder, and I didn't want this to be my answer,
but I can't help but feel like maybe this is part of it.
Is those of us who have been schlepping for Linux
for a really long time are maybe willing
to forgive a lot of things.
And like also when things break,
I tend to just move forward and like work around it.
Like I don't stop and I barely even acknowledge the breakage
other than maybe like, ah, this goddamn thing, ah, shit.
And then I'll just move right on.
And it's not, what am I trying to say?
You know what I'm trying to say, Wes?
It's like this mentality of-
I think we're calloused in a way.
Yeah.
Like we're just, we're used to that thing.
We know we're getting this stuff for free.
We don't expect, there's not that,
I mean, some people maybe there is,
but you might get upset about these things,
especially if you've paid an exorbitant amount for software,
but when you just got it gratis and you appreciate how much
and you kind of know what's happening on the backend,
I think, yeah, I'm fairly willing,
if it's not a totally derailing issue,
I'm fairly willing to just say like,
all right, well, I appreciate that.
I could have made that mistake,
or maybe you're trying to improve this,
but it's no longer working for me.
Or it's like you've seen how the sausage is made
so many times that you know how long of a shot it is
that some of these fringe issues
are ever gonna get taken care of.
Like that's not really gonna get fixed
until the entire stack is replaced.
And how often some of the stuff
that looks shallow on the surface
is actually due to like very deep,
complicated interactions between different subsystems.
And you're like, oh, I thought that was just a simple toggle.
And it's like, well, no, these things have long histories
and we gotta maintain compatibility
and it's gonna take mountains of work to fix that.
And sometimes, and I don't like this answer
because I think you always,
everything has to be evaluated on its own.
But sometimes I think to myself,
some of these compromises,
like when I wake my machine up upstairs
and my monitor's just totally all screwed up
and one of them is flickering like it's having a seizure
and the other one, all my windows are rotated
and completely messed up in the wrong spot.
And I do get frustrated and I think,
it's still a better option than running Windows.
I still trust this system more
than I'll ever trust Windows or the Mac.
And I don't deal with some of the other things
on these proprietary systems that drive me crazy.
Like I might get a 99% accuracy hit on the Mac
when I wake it up with multiple monitors
and where all the screens are and everything like that.
It might be like 98, 99% accurate almost every time.
But man, is it a nightmare to deal with Mac OS updates.
And does it just waste an entire two hours sometimes
for some unconceivable reason doing some update
that I don't even know what it's actually doing.
And what a hot mess are all the different
self-implemented updaters on Mac OS
and all these little things about the OS
that I never have to deal with on a Linux box.
And it's stuff that slows me down and takes my time.
It's like, I went on a website this morning.
I was looking up some of the smoke conditions around here
and I got this big pop-up that says we value your time.
And they had all these questions for me.
And I'm like, you lying bastard.
If you valued my time, you wouldn't be putting this pop-up
in front of my face and stopping me, right?
That's Windows.
Windows is like that, we value your time.
Your answer, your call will be answered in 15 minutes.
Like that's Windows, right?
Where Linux is like there's no call waiting,
there's no hold, you just get on, you get your answer,
you get the job done.
And so I weigh those things higher
than I weigh the niggling issues
that I run into from time to time.
And generally, they're never issues
that prevent me from working, right?
Whereas like the deal with Mac OS updates
and its silly long update process,
that'll stop you from working.
You can't work while the machine's doing that.
Where I can choose a Linux distro
that does updates very quick and very efficiently.
And there's also so many more knobs as well as insight,
like I have a lot more faith that there will be
like a bug report that I'll be able to see at least
that can document or I can contribute
to acknowledge this issue.
You can go look at the source code
and to some extent I feel kind of like a guest in a hotel
on some of those other desktops.
I expect to be catered to because I don't have any options.
Whereas with Linux, it's like your own tool,
it's your own house and sometimes you're pretty upset
because well, you really didn't paint that wall very well
or whatever.
You didn't finish that over there.
You know?
But you can then customize it if you need to.
Or like you could compile your own build to Plasma
if you really wanted to.
I don't think you do, but you could, right?
Or you could just stop updating.
You could stick to a stable branch if you wanted to.
I think we, I don't know, you guys may know,
but I used to work with a PHP developer who did just that.
He would get like whatever the previous LTS was
and he would only use that and only use the software
from that repo and he refused to use anything newer
because of the problems you're having.
And Brent, that was almost a decade ago.
It was like, it's always kind of been the case.
And I think that's where the distros still play a role.
And you've just happened to choose a desktop environment
that maybe some of the major distros aren't focusing on
that are doing the polishing.
Now, I really don't want to take anything away from Plasma
because I think in some ways it's great
that we have something like Plasma out there
that isn't tied to any particular distro
that isn't being led around by Red Hat
or something like that, right?
Like, that's a good thing.
That's also an advantage, yeah, absolutely.
You have been trying to effect change, right?
You have submitted bugs for some of the things.
I mean, and that isn't something you have to do,
but it is an option we have with free software
that we don't necessarily have with the commercial stuff.
Well, and actually what's been great about that process,
and it first started a few months ago
when we were participating in the Ubuntu beta testing,
or at least I did.
Some listeners may have as well, hopefully.
And I did find some bugs doing upgrades
between LTS versions.
And it was actually really refreshing to be like,
hey, I found this thing and I think no one else has found it
or other people have,
but I can share some extra information about it
on my particular steps.
And that was a refreshing perspective
into the way that open source functions.
And what's been really neat is watching,
you automatically get tagged
and track those conversations via email or whatever it is.
And it's been fascinating to watch the discussions
and the progress on some of these bugs throughout the months,
both in a, I think in a good and bad way,
I hesitate to use those words,
but like some of the bugs are deemed,
oh yeah, this is very serious,
needs to be fixed before the release.
And it gets all the attention and it gets solved,
sometimes within a few hours or a few days.
But then some bugs that seem at least to me from,
let's say a slightly technically proficient end user,
some bugs that seem super serious to me
have gone months and months and months and months
without any attention.
Well, some people are paying attention,
but without a fix, I'll say.
So one in particular was,
Kubuntu had a bug where you couldn't enter
like their K-D-E-S-U function.
So where you type in your pseudo password
to bring up, to change some repos or something
in the GUI, for instance.
Yeah, that does seem like a bad one.
Yeah, it would present a dialogue to you
to put in your password, which is all good,
but it would never ever accept any of your passwords,
either the pseudo password or your known good password
as the acceptable answer.
It would just never ever let you in, basically.
And it was just changed some fairly important functions.
So you had to find ways around it.
So I guess seasoned enough that I knew ways around it,
but that seemed like a pretty big issue to me.
And I was like, oh, this definitely needs some attention.
Like this is very serious.
And a potential fix to be tested was only sent out,
I think last week, which really surprised me
because we found these back in March, I think it was,
and I'm not the only one to have found this bug.
So it's been really fascinating to watch
sort of the internals of the teams
that are working on these things as well.
So if anyone's interested in getting to learn
the Linux desktop environment on a different level,
I very highly recommend, you know,
go find some bugs and submit some,
or at least go look at some bug reports.
It's an amazing thing.
I'm getting excited.
I'm getting so excited for you, Brent.
This is such an exciting period
you're going through right now.
Oh, this is good.
Well, have you been through this?
It sounds like.
Oh, sure, yeah.
You're gonna get a whole new understanding
of how free software is put together.
And I think this is a super valuable understanding.
Watching this process, what you talked about there,
watching how the team works,
seeing what things they go after,
kind of see who some of the superstars are.
How do you balance all the competing demands
and bugs and issues and new features maybe?
Yeah, yeah.
Well, what's been even more interesting
is from our website project,
where now I've been sort of playing the person
of the triaging bugs that we get in
and priorities and stuff like that.
Now I'm seeing, because of our own open source project
with a bunch of listeners putting in their time
and effort when they can on their specialty
to make our website an amazing thing.
Now I have the perspective of that other chair
and that other hat of trying to organize
all these competing priorities and stuff.
So it has been a really fascinating time for me personally.
And I think that's what I wanted to share here today
is like, there's a lot of different ways
of having perspective on the software that we're using.
And that's kind of a beautiful thing
in this open source environment.
I wanna also take your point to the audience,
maybe have them boost in with their thoughts.
Is Plasma maybe getting a second rate implementation
because it's on these spins and flavors
and not the primary distro focus so often.
And again, not to take anything away
from like Kubuntu teams or Fedora spin team
because we all use it.
We love that project.
We are so thankful for anything.
We just wish they had more developers.
And I'm wondering, are we off?
Just somehow does the free software model
and the development model for free software,
does it kind of avoid this problem
since it's all upstream development?
Let us know your thoughts, boost it in
or go to linuxunplug.com slash contact.
Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Go get started with a free trial of teams
or for an individual right now
by going to bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Bitwarden is the easiest way for yourself,
an individual, a team, an open source project
to share and sync sensitive data.
It's fully customizable.
There's all kinds of things that you can tweak,
you can set, especially for those of you
in the enterprise environment.
And of course we love that Bitwarden is open source,
trusted by millions in the community.
It's of course what Wes and I use every single day
for managing our passwords.
You can manage your two factor authentication there
and have it all in one spot.
And it just syncs beautifully across the desktop
and across mobile devices.
And one of the very first things I install now
when I set up a new Linux box is the Bitwarden Flatpak.
Then I can get logged into all of my services
and my sites and I can use secure,
individual unique passwords for all of them.
I just kept thinking to myself,
how much more could Bitwarden do in 2022?
How much more could they really do?
They've done so much.
They've added so many features,
especially on mobile for both Android and iOS this year.
And for the enterprise,
cross domain identity management was huge.
They just got to that.
This week they're announcing fast mail alias generation.
So if you're a fast mail user,
fast mail has been added to the list of available options
for generating an email address along Firefox relay
and on Addy and simple login.
So now you can have a unique username,
a unique password and a unique email address
for every site and service you use.
That is ultimate security
and Bitwarden just manages all of it for you.
They just do it all for you.
They generate it, they auto fill it, they sync it
and they do it securely and it's all open source.
And if you're a fast mail user, this just got real for you.
I mean, how great is this?
If you're an existing Bitwarden user, you just get this.
I love this and I hear from you guys out there all the time,
how much you love fast mail.
So I'm super psyched for all of you.
Bitwarden just keeps getting better.
If you haven't switched yet or if a friend, a family member
or maybe your workplace, your school place,
if you see some practices
that maybe Bitwarden could help with,
you know what I'm talking about,
passwords under the keyboard.
We've all seen it.
Give them bitwarden.com slash Linux.
It's just a great way to support the show
and get them on the straight and narrow
to good password management,
which is probably the number one thing they could do online
to protect themselves.
So go to bitwarden.com slash Linux, go try it out.
The easiest way to sync, store and share sensitive data.
Bitwarden.com slash Linux.
Tater boosts in this week with 2049 cents.
I'm curious, what did you come up with on the photo front?
I'm in the exact same boat.
I have been testing out Synology Photos lately,
but it really just doesn't cut it.
The wife is especially unhappy with the lack of AI features
that allow her to search for things like dog
or Disney's Animal Kingdom.
I've been using photo sync on iOS
to at least get my pictures onto my unread NAS,
albeit unorganized.
You know, Tater, we got a lot of feedback about that.
So what we're gonna do is a kind of roundup
of some of the stuff that was sent in in the pics.
And then we'll give you a little more information about it.
We're gonna try some stuff ourselves
and then give you like our official final
like definitive setups for photo sync.
But yeah, a lot of people had recommended NextCloud
or they'd recommended PhotoPrism.
And I did get a few people that said Synology Photos
actually works well for them.
So there's, you know, for those of you
that do have a Synology, there's something to consider.
Well, we've got a double boost from Tater
with 2,048 SATs.
Started off with a question there,
but this one I think is a little pro tip.
You mentioned the struggles of getting SATs
into lightning wallets like Fountain.
And I thought I'd share my recent discovery.
No, it's not private like RoboSATs, but I like it anyway.
It's the Cash app.
I've been a user for years now.
And I recently found out that their Bitcoin wallet
in the app supports lightning.
So sending SATs to Fountain was a piece of cake.
Cash app's actually a great tip.
And like right now, they got a boost in there.
You get 5% back in Bitcoin on any food you buy
in the Cash app.
So you could, you know, buy yourself dinner
and then boost those SATs in.
You know, I'm constantly having to buy food for some reason.
I know, it gets old, doesn't it?
Okay, well, next up is a boost from our beloved Elray.
Hey Elray, or is it Elry?
Elry, you're right. Elray, Elry.
I've just been saying Elray this whole time, so.
See, I got it, I'm blaming Brett.
But a solid contributor to our new website.
Boost in and let us know.
Oh yeah, absolutely.
Elray boosts in with a row of ducks.
Working in the offensive security field,
I think I mostly agree with Chris's sentiment.
A lot of antivirus software sucks.
But there are a few AV or endpoint protection products
that are actually really awesome, at least for Windows.
They're working on making Linux better.
All right.
Here's a specific example.
If I see CrowdStrike or a box
with an updated Windows Defender,
I know I have to change my attack pattern
to try and not get caught while I'm on that machine.
All right, that actually is, you know, I remember that.
When you see a piece of software, you're like,
oh, all right, this is gonna be a little harder
than I expected.
That probably is the highest praise you could get
for something like that.
He kind of sums it up with, you know,
AV isn't the best, but it's catching low-hanging fruit,
which is pretty important for non-technical users.
Sure, sure, that makes sense.
Along these same lines, Entropic Ninja boosts in
with a elite number of sets.
Just listening to the discussion about malware
and how Mac have integrated it at the OS level.
To Chris's point about how scanning can tax a system,
made me think about all those co-processors
on Apple Silicon.
Perhaps there might be some specific antivirus co-processors
introduced in the near future.
You know, I thought about this while we were talking
about it in the show last week,
but I didn't wanna derail us.
But wouldn't that be the total Apple move,
is to pretend like your platform was immune
from malware forever, right?
And oh, yeah, it's not us.
Then, when you start to have a malware problem,
you build it in at the system level, the protection,
and build in co-processors after that,
and be like, what, well, yeah, we have malware,
but it doesn't impact the performance of your system.
That is exactly what they're gonna do, right?
Oh, boy, yeah, and you know, you gotta pay
for those fancy co-processors.
You get a co-processor, I get a co-processor,
just all adds to the price.
Neve boosted in with 2016 SATs.
Coming in hot with the boost.
You always get me with that one.
It's our favorite.
2016 was when we first heard the phrase,
the year of the Linux desktop,
which coincides with when Canonical was at the peak
of its convergence hype train.
Do you remember that?
Ubuntu made the switch to the first LTS with SystemD,
and had an ongoing phone and smart TV project.
Manjaro also finally got popular.
GNOME Shell finally reached usable,
and Steam proved the test of time,
lasting the four-year test,
and showed the community Valve was in the long run
with the Steam Machine and SteamOS 1.0.
My last bit of history boosts, by the way.
Neve, I loved your history boosts.
What a wild year the 2016 was.
I'm gonna miss the history boosts.
I want more history boosts.
Yeah, keep those coming.
That was really fascinating.
Steam 1.0 2016 seems like both,
like Steam for Linux just happened yesterday,
and I also feel like it was a decade ago.
The thing for me, the personal story about Steam on Linux
is that I heard it from Michael Larble
and somebody else that I won't name,
six months to nine months before it came to Linux,
but I didn't know when.
I just knew they were working on it,
and I'd seen some really solid evidence.
I didn't know if it was shipping,
but I knew they had a client.
I had seen screenshots.
I had seen source code.
I knew it was real.
I just never knew if we were gonna get a product.
I didn't know when or anything like that,
so to me, so much of my experience
about Steam coming to Linux
was the anticipation of when,
and trying to do that math and keep my mouth shut,
but then also drop hints on air.
So it feels like it was a real time.
2016 was a solid year for Linux.
That's all I know.
Eric Pardee boosted in with 15,000 sats.
B-O-O-S-T.
Chris, I think this one's for you on some documentation.
They write, readme.md, Chris,
and todo.md, saves my bacon
when I write ansible, terraform,
future nix, ooh, I like that.
Comments are great, good commit messages are also great,
but a readme.md with how does this all work again notes
that gets the overall gist is invaluable.
Yeah, that is good advice.
Readme.mds and todo.mds, always really invaluable.
What about, but hold on, we gotta back up.
What is, what is Pulumi?
The next Nix.
Is this like an ansible meets Nix meets something else?
Ooh, a little sneaky.
Oh, I think those are separate items, I believe.
It's Pulumi, which is an existing thing,
and then I think future Nix may be to imply
that Eric will be trying out Nix soon.
Well, Eric.
That's how I understood it.
Okay, thank you for the sage advice.
I will take that to heart.
I will try, I will write future Chris readmes.
You know, like, and I'll put in there like,
you really actually need to read this.
You know, I'll put it in the title so I know it's from me
and not some jerk.
Be kind to yourself, Chris.
It's kind of like the difference between like,
you know, having a reference where you need
the specific detail, which is where those comments are,
like, oh, don't forget, you don't need to do it this way
or it'll break.
And then the readme is that high level thing
where you're just like, what's the intention
from the user, the human view?
And then you can get into the specifics later.
That's good to know.
All right, thank you, Eric, and thank you
for that healthy boost of 15,000 sats.
The Muso, the Muso boosted in with 5,000 sats.
Talking about Unity got me thinking
about the one thing I miss, the menu bar.
I love GNOME, but the move away from the menu bar saddens me.
As a keyboard heavy user, the menu bar allowed me
to quickly access functions that did not have
a keyboard shortcut assigned.
A simple Alt plus key and another key later,
I could use a function.
My opinion, the hamburger menus are not the answer.
Sure, I could probably use KDE, but for various reasons,
I prefer GNOME and the GTK ecosystem.
I do not like the hamburger menu still.
The overflow menu, as it's called now,
and Apple's all in on it.
The Home Assistant project just redesigned
their automations UI in Home Assistant,
and they've helpfully added many things
to the overflow menu.
It just feels like the ultimate UI lazy button.
Ah, well, we couldn't figure out where to put these things,
so one giant menu.
You know, what's unfortunate is our website has one.
Yeah, sure, of course, of course.
This everything does.
It's so handy.
Everything it does, everything does.
Everything has the hamburger menu now,
and I just can't even with it.
And I think part of it is because you can't put everything
on the toolbar or whatever, right, for this stuff.
You gotta, but there's still functions they wanna add.
Ah, I feel that one.
I'm just always struck whenever I go and use
like old school Windows, you know,
and like the Alt plus key is everywhere.
I mean, you could just keyboard drive
so many of those apps that way,
and it's actually quite nice.
That's my one good thing of Windows for the years.
Okay, okay, I'll stop.
I do agree, and consistently too,
like the Windows keyboard shortcuts I learned years ago,
I think for the most part are still valid, right?
Most plasma apps too.
It's really the Gnome stuff.
Yeah.
Ha, ha, ha, ha.
All right, Gene being boosted with 15,000 SATs.
He has two thoughts on open sourcing sound bites.
Number one, be sure to use Git Elfs.
What's a Git Elf, guys?
Pardon?
Hey guys, hey Brent, you're a GitHub guy now.
You're a big GitHub guy now, Brent.
Hey Brent, Brent, what's a Git Elf?
What's a Git Elf, Brent?
What is that?
I think it's like, sort of like the paperclip guy in the.
Huh?
It's sort of like the paperclip guy.
Clippy, yeah, that's the one.
It just like, whenever you need help,
you just hit the button,
and it comes out and tries to help you.
It's a little Linus Torvalds, but it looks like an elf.
Ha, ha, ha, ha.
You're right, I should be using that.
That's a great tip, Gene being, thank you.
I should be using that.
Okay, so reading between the lines here.
It's LFS, and that's large file support,
which is a sort of add-on to Git,
because it's not really designed to support
giant binary files necessarily.
So there's ways to integrate those in,
a little better handling into the mix.
Oh, links.
You just use a link.
You just link it.
But can I get this Linus Elf thing?
Because that sounds great.
Number two, should be careful
about the copyright side of things.
Yes, that's true.
It's a balance.
It's been a balance between the fun of it all
and the copyright of it all.
So I feel like we need to find the right balance.
So far, we've been leaning heavily on the fun side.
Gene Bean had a few extra boosts.
I love it.
Gene Bean's a great supporter of the show,
and I read some of those in the pre-show.
Alex Gates, the podcasting 2.0 consultant,
boosted with $15,000.
We got some $15,000s, woo!
That is great.
You know what you all are?
You're all back home ballers,
but I'm not gonna play it.
Okay, one more time for you all together.
But that's it.
That's it.
Never again.
But we had some solid $15,000 boosts.
I felt like they deserved it.
Alex says that we're working on podcasting 2.0 playlists
that anyone can make and share,
and then shows up as an RSS feed.
What?
That's a great idea.
Frickin' love it.
You know, I would love to do all of our episodes
where we talk about managing and owning your own data,
just like a whole self-sovereign data series
of living some life.
I mean, tags could just be playlists in that way, right?
You just blew my mind.
Keep us posted, Alex.
Please do.
Thor 502 boosted in.
I think we screwed up with the 2048 stats.
Just a heads up, guys.
Wooden, who boosted in last week,
is another way to say Odin.
Yeah, you know the Allfather?
It's Wo-Din.
My dad didn't hang upside down in Yagisal.
How do you say that?
Ictrazil?
Ictrazil.
For nine days and nine nights to be referred to as lumber,
as funny as that might be to you.
Oh.
Sorry, Thor.
You got us wrong.
I'm glad Thor has a podcasting 2.0 app.
You know, Thor's going to new podcast apps.
He's got himself a podcasting 2.0 app.
You know, if he doesn't want to switch apps,
he's sticking with Breeze or Boost CLI.
Maybe he's using Albee, you know?
I don't know what Thor's doing.
Let us know, Thor.
What's worked for you?
Thor's pretty hip.
That's what I hear.
I wouldn't have thought.
But you know, I suppose it makes sense
when you think about it from like a math standpoint.
He knows about newpodcastapps.com.
He knows about that.
Thank you everybody who did boost in.
We got 11,000 stats from Forged Foe,
but he didn't have a message.
But we also wanted to thank Patrick
for sending a row of ducks into the show,
as well as everybody else who boosted in.
We read all of your messages,
and we're just kind of selectively picking the ones
that really float our boat to put in the show,
some make into the pre-show,
then of course those baller boosts
make it to the top of the show.
And all of them help keep podcasting independent.
Thank you everybody.
Guys, we got an over-packed pick segment.
We got a pop and picks segment over here.
We wanted to kind of run through some of the ideas
that were sent in for getting your photos
off of your mobile device and onto your own system
so you can back them up and display them.
Number one with a bullet, Photosync came in,
which is an app for iOS and Android.
Thornbill, amongst others, sent them in to let us know,
hey, you gotta try these out.
And this is definitely one that you'll be hearing more about
from us, I think, in the future.
Photosync lets you transfer your photos
and your videos from your machine, cross-platform,
and it supports all kinds of backend network services.
So pretty much anything you're doing,
WebDAV, SMB, DropBizzle, I don't know what you're using,
but it supports it, it's ridiculous.
So that was sent in by a lot of folks.
iDrive also was sent in.
Another one of the kind of the same dealios,
multi-computer cloud backup, get it off your device.
The pricing is there.
It's kind of expensive, but people were using it,
so I thought I would mention it.
Hey, photos are important.
Same thing was mentioned, was boosted in by iBookie.
He said, I have a server with PhotoPrism and SyncThing.
SyncThing copies the photos from the phone to the server,
and PhotoPrism imports and displays them
from the SyncThing directory.
I like that a lot.
Yeah.
SyncThing is not available for iOS.
I have had good luck in the past using it
to sync my photos on Android, though.
Foldersync was also sent in.
Purple Dog using Breeze sent that in with a row of ducks.
It says, I'm using Foldersync on Android
and then PhotoPrism as the progressive web app.
What I'm really missing, though,
is the ability to share an album.
So Foldersync is an Android option.
Photosync is an iOS and Android option.
And PhotoPrism is the app that a lot of people
are using to display them, but not everybody.
There's a lot here, and we got a lot of emails about this.
Here's what I'd like to know.
We'd like some hands-on experience examples.
We want to take in a lot of the feedback,
kind of have the audience give us
their reports on using things like Photosync
and Foldersync and PhotoPrism.
Yeah, what worked well,
what let you down in a critical moment.
Yeah, what went wrong, how did you recover,
those kinds of stories.
You can boost them in or go to linuxunplug.com slash contact.
We want to try to collate as much of that
so we can kind of get some meta observations
that we can use to inform our commentary,
and then we want to come back to you guys
and tell you what apps we picked for our photo solutions
and what worked, what didn't work,
and if we can, give as much step-by-step instruction
as we can on a podcast.
So that's kind of where we want to take this segment
ultimately, and just kind of gonna be driven
by how much input we get from you guys.
We have some, we've gotten some good stuff.
I'd like a little bit more in terms of actual
hands-on usage and some horror stories.
And also if you ended up going back to Google Photos,
tell us what went wrong and why and that kind of stuff.
All that would be really valuable
because that's all experience that we can then use
to inform our commentary and relate to the audience
because we'd like to create a definitive
take control of your photos,
get away from Google Photos episode
that people can get referred to.
Because we gotta do it, we gotta do it.
We gotta do it.
I mean, if not us, who?
Who?
It's just time.
I think it's time.
We waited too long and now we gotta double down on it.
So let us know how it's worked, how it hasn't worked,
the good and the bad.
And of course, don't forget next Sunday
is our last live stream in the studio
before we hit the road.
Brent's gonna be here.
We should think about food.
Oh, I think we must feast.
Yeah, we're gonna have to feast.
We're gonna be putting on quite the show.
Maybe we just live stream all day, I don't know.
It's gonna be weird, you know?
I mean, you're gonna be up here in Seattle.
We're gonna be gone.
We're gonna be having a great time, you know?
I'm already feeling that.
You're gonna be stuck here at the studio.
You know, it's gonna be weird.
But I'll have full control of the soundboard.
No, no, no, no, no, no, no.
We finally fired your soundboard guy.
You're cut off.
It's been a lot better.
Been noticing a lot less rust sound bites, that's why.
That soundboard guy brought the rust clip
and that was it, and that's all he ever did.
I don't know what kind of hire that was.
He's worth the salary, let me tell you.
I don't know about that.
But we'd love to see you next week.
We do it at noon Pacific, 3 p.m. Eastern
over at jupyter.tube.
That is our self-hosted Peertube instance.
See you next week.
Same bad time, same bad station.
And don't miss Linux Action News.
We covered some underwater Linux data centers
that are going live in our backyard
here in the Pacific Northwest,
and everything else going on in the world
of Linux and free software.
There's a whole other companion to this show.
It's tight, concise, just the information you need.
LinuxActionNews.com.
Links to what we talked about today,
that's at LinuxUnplugged.com, slash, 475,
and of course, at the new website, too.
Over at jupyterbroadcasting.com.
Go check that sucker out.
It's a doozy.
Thanks so much for joining us on this week's episode
of the Unplugged program.
I think we're gonna see you right back here next Sunday.
Hey.
I think we should spread the love just a little bit.
You did try out Gnome after having some plasma frustrations.
Ooh, that could be a good title.
Plasma frustrations.
And so we said, all right, okay, Brent.
Okay then, Brent.
All right, Brent.
Go try out Gnome.
See how that goes for you, Brent.
How did it go for you, Brent?
Yeah, I think we decided that was it last Sunday when we were thinking about this episode
and we thought, okay, well, it's only fair to go try the dark side.
You know, I haven't actually, here's, here's something, I've never actually spent much
time in Gnome because I've been so happy with, with plasma.
So I only have like, at most hours in Gnome before this.
But Chris, you put it to me and you, I know, I know.
But Chris, you put it to me and you said, well, give it a shot for like a week and see
what happens.
And I did, and it was enlightening so far.
Unfortunately it wasn't, I was expecting it to be a polished, wonderful experience.
Now I did choose Fedora's Gnome implementation because I figured, okay, at the time on my
main laptop here, I've got Fedora's implementation of KDE, so I thought, okay, well, let's change
the fewest things possible and just switch to, you know, the Gnome desktop environment.
All right.
That makes sense.
Maybe than my previous experiences trying to change only one variable.
And I ran into a lot of problems, a ton of problems, many, many, many, many bugs that
helpfully the Gnome bug reporter helped me file a whole bunch of them.
But one of the ones that was worrying was the kernel core had 15 occurrences of problems,
system failures, it called it, that were just kept getting collected and collected.
I had some random abrupt black screens that would just happen in the middle of, you know,
I'm in the middle of working on the website and all of a sudden, you know, I've written
this whole like a reply to someone or a new issue and it's like paragraphs long.
And all of a sudden my system just like vanished before my eyes and I couldn't do anything
to, you know, I couldn't use the keyboard to get to a terminal.
I couldn't even put it to sleep or anything to try to like.
That sounds like Mudder or Wayland is crashing on you.
Yeah, it was Wayland and I had some extra issues with Wayland, which I've experienced
on other Wayland systems, which is poor video playback.
But you were primarily X11 before, right?
On your Plasma, in your Plasma days?
Yeah.
So this is always, this is also a little bit new Wayland territory for me as well.
But I've been disappointed, to be honest.
That's kind of what I was getting at in the show is what I think makes this tricky is
if you look back over the last five, six years of Linux, you've gone through so many transitions
that like it's hard to say where in the stack you're actually bumping problems that maybe
on an older system, you know, you didn't.
Although I got to tell you, like if I ever, if I ever had what you're going through happen
to me more than once, I would not use any of these systems.
Like that would be it.
I don't got time for that.
I know that's, and that's how I started feeling this week was like, I almost put up my hands
and just said, you know, it's, it's only Thursday.
I didn't even make it to Sunday again.
And I can't do this anymore.
I wonder how this is going to go on the dev one.
Well that I'm interested.
Could this be hardware?
Could some of this be hardware?
Like potentially I, so one of the main systems I'm using here is an X250 and okay, Alex and
I like Frankenstein this thing, but it's been pretty stable.
And then my workstation as well was what I was using gnome on because I didn't quite
want to wipe this.
I was really hesitant to do that, uh, especially with the travels coming up.
And so I ran it on a completely different system and uh, so yeah, it could be hardware.
They're both old dish.
They don't have that much cat hair in them, but it could be, you know, that's a possibility.
I was just wondering if you'd like the, I mean, not that pops totally made for that,
but you know, in the, in a system that's sort of a little more integrated and not coupled
together, it might be something up your alley.
You mean the pop gnome experience?
Yeah.
I was thinking he might like the pop gnome or the Ubuntu gnome experience.
Cause the thing about Fedora is it's a real upstream experience, right?
So you're getting basically factory gnome.
And I like that because then I know I add these 17 extensions and everything's fine,
but you don't have, you know, literally six years or so of playing around with various
extensions to know which ones just to go to, right?
That to me is just built in knowledge now, um, where something like, you should publish
a feed of the extensions you're currently using.
I wish that's where something like pop and Ubuntu, you know, they've done a little curation
in that experience.
Well, that's, what's really fascinating to me is I feel like, at least for me personally,
when I jump on a plasma machine, I'm, I don't really need to add anything.
It's got most of the things I want, but it's got more than any desktop environment has.
It's got everything.
Yeah.
Fair enough.
And also I'm aware that I have, you know, five years worth of experience with it.
So of course I'm going to lean towards preferring the thing that's familiar, right?
That I have in mind as well.
But you know, you have sort of convinced me that you've been happier with gnome more now
than ever.
Yeah.
Yeah, I have.
That's sort of why I lean towards using the fedora implementation was that you seem really
happy with it.
You did hesitate with like wanting to give me the, the preset up version, which is sort
of what pop pop is doing and what, you know, who Bunty is doing.
Uh, I just went crazy and figured, okay, well I'm just going to try it just the way it is
cause I want to see it from the ground up.
And that I did that I did.
Yeah.
I wonder if you saw my set up, what you'd think of it.
You might soon.
Yeah, you will.
Yeah.
I'm curious what you're going to throw on the dev one for me.
Well, we have, we have a little something to start with, don't we have that USB here
today.
This should be entertaining, so I think we have a whole episode dedicated to these shenanigans.
Is that how it's going?