Are you tired of your Raspberry Pi sounding like this?
Well, the Raspberry Pi Foundation has got some good news for you.
It seems like the thermal performance on the old Pi Fourski is way better these days.
Yeah, they've got a great blog post detailing it with some really neat thermal imaging images
out there, so you can go take a look and see just where the hotspots are.
And how they tested it, and what you could do to test it yourself.
One thing I found humorous though is at the very end, despite all the great improvements
that the recent firmware updates have indeed provided, their best recommendation is still
to just turn the Raspberry Pi 4 on its side.
You're stacking it wrong.
Well, hello friends, and welcome in to the Unplugged program.
This is episode 330.
My name is Chris.
My name is Wes.
Almost forgot the number.
There's too many.
Too many to count.
It's a lot of numbers, Wes.
Hello to Cheese and Alex too, hey gentlemen.
Hello, hello.
Hello.
Well, hello.
We have a really fun show.
I'm excited to be joined by not just you, but also our virtual lug, time appropriate
greetings Mumble Room.
Hello.
Hello, hello.
Hi there.
Mumble Overload.
That's right.
Happy Linux Tuesday.
Happy Linux Tuesday to you too, Jill.
And Ace Nomad, Byte, Cassidy, Dan, DM, and I'm going to say Jensen Gruck.
Wow.
Okay, so we have a lot coming up in the show today.
We have some community news, but this episode is the one we've been waiting to do all year.
We get to celebrate Linux as an implementation detail with the family.
That's right.
I mean, we already know Linux is everywhere, but it can be a few more places, especially
in your family's home.
Now, if you're like me or Wes or Cheesy or Alex or pretty much anyone in the virtual
world, like you've likely got a small board computer of some type or you've thought about
getting one, well, how cool would it be if you could make some great holiday gifts out
of these suckers?
So we're going to talk about ways to do that, but also just some really good projects.
If you want to set up backup for yourself this year, if you want to build some mini
projects for people yourself or maybe strangers, there's a lot of good ideas in here.
This is basically all the things we love and what we're doing with them for the holidays.
Really some great projects we're going to get to.
Now, Mr. Payne, some really, really good news for the backers of the Librem 5 this week.
It seems that backers have begun receiving their Linux phones, some mostly working, but
exciting nonetheless to see this.
And we all expected when people actually started receiving their devices, it would be all over
the internet.
And it has.
Of course.
I mean, who wouldn't be excited?
Yeah.
And these are geeks, right?
That are passionate about the mission.
They want to process it and it's here and it's great.
And it mostly works.
For the most part, things are exactly what you would expect, a little rough around the
edges or completely rough around the edges.
Stability issues have been mentioned.
Charging issues doesn't charge when the device is powered up, essentially is a current problem.
And battery only lasts about an hour.
But there is in almost all of these reviews being posted, a thread of what seems to be
genuine potential, like they see the potential here.
These people are not, they're not ripping it up.
They're just setting expectations, I think.
Right.
I mean, you have to view this as a work in progress and experiment, right?
When you're on the cutting edge of freezing open source hardware.
Yeah.
You can't initiate a call.
You can receive a call, I believe.
But I think there's something working where like they can't hear you, like the audio isn't
routing properly or something to that effect.
And of course, the phone app tends to crash.
It does seem like it's a pretty nice web browser.
And while it is thicker than most phones, so far, the reviewers seem to think that it's
actually quite comfortable to hold.
You can get around the actual Linux underpinnings, too.
So if you know really what you want is a Linux box, I mean, it's there for that.
Pretty neat to see people receiving them.
It's early, early, early, like some of these are not fully functional.
Some of them are very much prototypes.
They seem to vary a lot in quality, more than I think we were led to believe.
But it is nice to see it out there, and kind of along the same lines, while we're talking
about these phones, there's an early look at the PinePhone Developer Edition, which
is the one that I preordered.
Yeah, Lucas, who we've had on the show recently, did a video, which we'll have linked.
It's posted as well over at OMG Ubuntu.
And I mean, you're only getting like a 10-minute look at this thing, so it's pretty hard to
really come away with a firm opinion.
But it feels a lot further along, and I think a big part of that is they're leveraging an
existing software stack.
Yes.
Right.
I mean, from a purism perspective, there's a lot of stuff that needs to get invented,
and a lot of work they've done is things that aren't at that fit and finish layer, at least
not yet.
And something that I only recently come to appreciate, thanks to Cheese's conversations
with Pine, is that they have some genuine experience with smaller systems based around
these components.
And the Popcorn Hour is a shipping commercial product that exists today and has existed
for a very long time.
Right.
And that seems to be a lot of the challenges here, right?
It's a unique space with its own constraints and a lot of difficulty getting the right
components.
Good video, though.
So we'll have that linked in the show notes if you want to see the status of the PinePhone.
For those that are still waiting, which I don't know if I consider myself anymore, but
for those of you that are still waiting for that free Linux phone, it's getting closer.
It's getting closer.
Yeah, really, wherever we're at, it's exciting to see progress.
And for all the folks that are interested in it, we're getting closer.
What'll be the threshold for you?
So you've got a Pixel 3, right?
Yeah, Pixel 3.
Pretty nice phone.
Yes.
Pretty good camera.
I'm honestly using my phone more and more as an appliance, so I think that angle is
a little easier to replace.
I need a few apps, mostly for work.
The camera's the kicker for me, though, because I just love having a decent camera in my pocket
all day long.
Yeah, the camera's really good, too, on the Pixel line.
I wouldn't mind having a little full Linux device in my pocket, though, maybe not for
using as a traditional phone, but just for sitting on the couch or carrying with me as
a mobile workstation.
Would it be more appealing if it was a foldable device with an actual physical QWERTY keyboard?
Yeah, probably.
I know.
Isn't that funny?
We've already built these.
You know that they're actually working on a keyboard for the PinePhone 2.
Oh, buddy.
See, that's what I'm talking about.
They get me.
All right.
Well, thanks if you guys want to read more about that, but we have some big news to talk
about.
A brand shiny, fancy, fantastic release of elementary OS.
Elementary OS 5.1, Cassidy and Dan, congratulations on the new release, gentlemen.
Thank you.
I have been kicking the tires on this one for the weekend, and I am so impressed with
what you guys have accomplished with this release.
You are truly crossing that uncanny valley that we have struggled to really fully cross
for so long with desktop Linux.
And now in some areas, I think you guys are exceeding the quality of experience that you
get on commercial platforms in multiple categories now.
So that's like a huge achievement on its own.
And there is so much in this release that I guess I'll start with you, Dan.
Why is this a.1 release?
This seems like this should be like 5.5, 5.8, maybe even 6.
Like there is new login screens.
There's a new greeter that's the best greeter.
The new onboarding app is the best onboarding app on any desktop.
Incredible.
It's so good.
It's nice, clean.
The only thing I would add is maybe like a little boutique style couple of apps.
But other than that, it's so perfect.
The Flatpak integration, you nailed it.
It's great.
I love the dialogues I get when I'm installing Flatpaks.
So why is this not just a whole new version?
So Dan's internet is actually dropping out.
So it's just me right now.
Cassidy, answer why is this just not a whole new version?
So the big thing is that it's still based on the same solid core of Juno, which means
it's Ubuntu 18.04 LTS based with the Ubuntu 18.04 repositories under the hood.
So it didn't feel right to say that it's a whole new like 6.0 version.
But at the same time, we wanted to like give it a new name and point release because there
is just so much new stuff in this release.
There's also, if I'm understanding correctly, all of the hardware enablement stuff from
the underlying 18.04 updates that have come along.
Exactly.
So it's basically the same core as Ubuntu 18.04.3 with Linux 5.
Whatever the latest is and all the hardware enablement stuff that comes along with that.
That's thanks to Canonical for all that awesome work.
And that's why we enjoy building off the LTS because we get this really solid foundational
platform, but we can have a more rolling release style on top of it.
Right.
You know, things aren't going to change out from under you.
Exactly.
This is starting to address what my experience as somebody who's just a Linux desktop enthusiast
and just enjoys all the different new things that are constantly being developed.
My experience with elementary in the past had been it's sort of a tease.
Like I see all these other great things like do not disturb mode and night color shifting
coming to other desktops.
And I think, oh, man, I really would love to have this on elementary.
In the past, I would have waited quite a bit longer.
But now these things are coming at a much faster clip.
And when they do land, they're like the best implementation period.
The recent, do you call it night light?
The recent tone shifting that people can turn on for nighttime color?
Yeah.
Night light.
So it's just a great implementation where once you turn it on, there's a little icon
up in the beautiful toolbar that I don't know what you call that, the pantheon, that top
bar.
Top panel.
It's gorgeous.
Up there, a little sun icon shows up.
And you can click that.
And you can snooze it with one button.
There's a couple of quick options.
It's so slick.
It's so well done that when these features do land, they seem to be one of the best implementations
of them.
Right.
It's like a microcosm maybe of the whole philosophy of elementary.
So what has been the enabler that's meant that, I feel like this is maybe the third
time we've had a version of this conversation with this release, like they're landing faster
and they're landing in the current releases.
What's been the big shift that's happened?
Is it a philosophical thing?
Is it a resources thing?
I think it's partially philosophical.
We've kind of always had this mentality, but I think we've really kind of hit our stride
with it now where we don't hold back features from the current release.
As much and often as we can, we push out updates to the current release.
It adds features, improves features.
Maybe even redesigns entire apps or parts of the settings because it gives our users
a better experience.
So it's more of that rolling release mentality.
And we've had that for the last few releases, but what's enabled it for us now is that we
have so much automation going into our release process that it means somebody can report
a bug or somebody can design a new feature and then the next day that can be hitting
users.
So it's so fast now and it's really, really great.
Wow.
And that has come online between the previous release and this release?
Yeah.
So that's been a lot of our work over the last month or two probably for kind of preparing
for this 5.1 release to help enable that.
And so it's automating the app releases and automating the ISO building and that all kind
of came together for 5.1.
It's got to feel like almost a new superpower.
You've been upgraded.
Yeah.
It's so awesome.
It's really just in the last couple of weeks we've been seeing like literally somebody
will report a bug and then it gets approved and merged and fixed and out the next day
and it's like, oh, that feels so good.
That's where software should be.
It's more continuous instead of waiting.
In some cases, in some operating systems, you'd be waiting months for that update.
Sure.
Yeah.
I think too, the overall experience I get is I use that uncanny valley analogy.
It's like there's so many little areas that have been smoothed out that make it a more
comprehensive product.
I really, really like Pantheon.
It is at first, not everything is super obvious, but it is pretty easy to discover.
Like if you hit the super key, a menu comes up and it's very clear on what you can do.
And within minutes I was, oh, so this is how I do multiple desktops.
This is how I move stuff around and it's slick, it's smooth.
Why is Pantheon so much smoother than some other projects that are based around similar
technologies?
What is it in there?
Is it the way you guys are hitting the GPU?
Is it magic?
I mean, maybe a little bit of magic, but no, I think we've been working at like a decade
now on UX focused development and all of our features are UX first.
We don't think about, oh, here's a new technology.
Now let's find a way to implement it in the UI.
We think what do we actually want the UI to do and how do we want it to feel and work
for the user?
And then we build the technology to support that.
So I think that's a big part of it.
I mean, honestly, another big part is that we are building off of really solid technologies.
A lot of stuff that's enabled from the gnome upstream projects.
So we're not using gnome shell, but we're using Mudder, which is the window manager.
So improvements there trickle down into elementary OS.
So we have these really solid technologies and can kind of mold them and shape them how
we want to create our own experience.
I see.
So that's great.
I didn't quite appreciate that upstream Mudder improvements benefited the Pantheon desktop
and that kind of maybe explained some of the performance improvements that I'm noticing.
Okay.
So now I have a couple of questions for you that are more like, why aren't you doing this
questions?
You're sort of one of the leading voices of a desktop standard, like a free desktop standard
dark mode.
I note though that dark mode is notably absent from elementary 5.1.
Yes, it's not perfect yet.
So we're doing a lot of work under the hood and behind the scenes and working with other
projects to help standardize this.
But it actually hasn't been standardized yet in GTK or a free desktop spec yet.
So while we could just throw in like a hammer to smash dark mode onto your desktop, it still
can cause breakage in certain areas.
So we don't feel comfortable enabling that because it's not as good of an experience
as it can be, but we are definitely working in that direction.
That makes sense.
I mean, it kind of hits on what you're talking about earlier, right?
Other distributions might not make that choice, but that's the way you guys are doing things.
Yeah.
It's part of the philosophical difference I think of elementary OS compared to other
projects is we really, really, really, and not to say other desktops don't care about
the UX, but we were kind of fanatical about it.
And so we'll be willing to not ship a feature early so that we can get it right and then
ship it to users when it feels really good.
Yeah.
I mean, and at this point where we're sitting, I mean, that's clearly working.
You can't argue with like early on as I don't know, guys, who are you to decide?
But now I'm like, oh yeah, they've got this figured out.
Okay.
So the second question is, and this kind of plays off what you were saying earlier about
how you don't just go and build something once the underlying tech is there.
I was surprised I installed one of the flat packs I decided to sideload just to experiment
with this flat pack and support was Nome firmware, which installs, but then complains excessively
that there's no LVFS support on the system, but that doesn't come from Ubuntu automatically.
Is there plans down the road to integrate that into app center?
Have you guys looked at LVFS firmware updates for like laptops and whatnot?
Yeah.
So that's a feature that we've looked at.
I've prototyped some stuff actually related to that.
I think we plan to support FWEPT, you know, the firmware update Daemon and LVFS.
It's just, we haven't built that out quite yet.
There's still, I think, an open question too of do firmware updates belong in your app
store or in your system settings?
And so we kind of have to figure out what we want that experience to actually feel like
and look like before we start building it.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Yeah.
So the firmware is good, but I don't know if the display and the way it gives out information
is really up to standard.
Yeah.
And it feels pretty Nomi, which Nome and elementary, we share a lot of technologies, but we have
different human interface guidelines and styles.
So it feels a little weird to shove a Nome thing into elementary or an elementary thing
into Nome.
So I think, I mean, right today you can do it from the command line.
You can install FWEPT and use it from the command line.
Obviously that's not the best experience.
So we're looking at how we want to integrate it into the desktop itself.
But there's a means.
Should somebody need to, you know, update a thing bad or something like that that they've
recently got?
Yeah.
I've got a Dell precision and I've run my updates from that and a eight bit dough controller
and gotten updates for that, my watch tech keyboard and stuff.
So it's, it's definitely there and working.
We just got to integrate it into the UI.
There's just a one other thing I thought we should touch on because you guys do such a
great job at it.
But I, I didn't really know when this started happening, but I definitely noticed it because
of the new onboarding process that in the background, elementary OS is doing a bit of
housekeeping and keeping temp files clean and logs.
Like it's, is that, is that a newish feature?
Cause that seems pretty cool.
Yeah.
I think that launched with Juno with 5.0, but a lot of people didn't know about it.
And that's, that's a big reason.
Onboarding is really nice.
We've had people tweeting at us like in the past couple of weeks leading up to 5.1 about
things are like, Oh, I got this new 5.1 feature.
It's like, well, it's actually been in elementary OS for a while, but now that you have onboarding,
you can say, Oh, a nightlight's a cool feature that I didn't know about or, you know, housekeeping
to clean up that stuff.
So I think that's been there since 5.0 and it's enabled by the gnome settings daemon,
but it's just, we've found a way to better expose it to users.
It makes all the difference.
And that's, what's so good about that new onboarding thing is you get, you expose really
good features in a totally non-obnoxious way.
So I really appreciate that.
But the one last thing I wanted to touch on is because I think you guys are doing kind
of a special job at this is constant iteration and improvements on accessibility features.
It's not something I personally follow, but I know that it matters a lot to certain people.
And I know there's been some improvements in 5.1 in that regard.
Yeah.
So actually I recently gave a talk at the Linux app summit about this.
Our philosophy, we kind of shifted our philosophy in the last year or two that accessibility
features are just features rather than kind of putting these features away in a little
closet called universal access where only people who, you know, have severe physical
disabilities find them.
We've decided that it's better and it's, features get better tested and more well supported
if we actually just support them as a standard feature of the operating system and more people
who might not think they need an accessibility feature actually end up using and benefiting
from these.
So that's been the focus.
A lot of that has been in system settings.
So things like text scaling, instead of being under an accessibility setting, it's just
in the desktop settings now.
Yeah.
I think that's a brilliant outlook on it because I'm one of those people, right?
And it fits with the sort of Linux world, right?
We want to be able to tinker with and modify these things.
I really liked the text size one specifically.
That was the one I played with on this latest install just to see how do I feel about it
because I'm on a 2K display and having slightly larger text size was nice.
You know me, Wes.
I love the 2K resolution.
You love those 2K.
So I really thought that was a great idea and I think that's a perfect outlook to have
on it.
Yeah.
And the analogy I like to use is curb cuts.
It's like where a sidewalk meets a road and you have the curb that is like a little ramp
up to the sidewalk.
Uh-huh.
Those were designed for wheelchair users originally, but like those are, those are useful features
for anybody to take advantage of.
So we like to, we have this effort we call curb cuts around elementary OS of things that
help access accessibility, but actually can be useful to everybody.
And I think it's starting to show.
That's a good insight into the project.
And you know, I use those curb cuts when I'm rolling around in my blades.
Cheese, I know.
Exactly.
You had something too you wanted to touch on.
Yeah.
So I have a question for you, Cassidy.
First of all, I, you know, I've been running the latest 5.1 here for, I don't know, a couple
of hours and just tinkering with it.
One thing that you guys do that's really different from anyone else with the App Center is that
you give people the opportunity to donate to these projects, to their favorite pieces
of software.
But one thing that I've noticed is across installs, there's no real say elementary account
based system like maybe you would have with Mac OS or something like that where you can
continue to log in.
And so if I reload my laptop, I can log back in and all the software that I've previously
purchased is available for me to download again.
Are there any plans to maybe put some sort of feature into the App Center like that so
that users who have purchased software can log back into the App Center and redownload
the software that they've already purchased?
Yeah, definitely.
Today, there's actually a way to do it from the terminal to like export your purchases
and then re-import them.
And it's kind of hidden, not super easy.
So we don't expose that for everybody to do because it's not the greatest experience,
but it's possible.
Kind of the hold up there today is we're very, very fanatic about not having a server where
we have user accounts and store user information.
But we do have a way we can do that in the future using actually our payment processor
Stripe has a customer's feature where we're not actually like storing any data about users
on our infrastructure, but we could have a restore purchases option.
So that's definitely something we're working on and looking into.
And alongside that, actually, we're working with the folks at Flatpak and FlatHub to enable
payments for Flatpaks themselves.
So Alexander Larson is doing some awesome work there.
There's a new release of Flatpak coming out soon that should support that.
And a lot of our work will be focused on enabling payments and payment restoration with Flatpaks.
Yeah, I'm looking forward to see where they go with that.
That is coming soon to Flatpaks.
And I think that's going to make a huge difference over at FlatHub, even if it's just for donations
initially, to just say thank you for making this.
Right, having it built right in.
Yeah.
Well, Cassidy, thank you for coming.
Sorry, Dan, that your internet connection was cutting out.
But Cassidy, you covered it great and really enjoying the new release.
I encourage everyone, check the link out in the show notes, read the release notes, because
they're the best.
And then grab an ISO, because it's the best.
Just such a solid release every time.
I can't remember the last time we've been like, boy, that new elementary OS sure is
crap.
I really blew it this time, didn't I?
You guys nail it every single time.
Every single time.
So the wait is worth it.
I say congratulations.
Thank you.
Go get 5.1.
It's killer.
With that said, it's time for a little housekeeping.
First and foremost, gonna mention right here at the top of the housekeeping, Linux headlines
are daily, every weekday, Linux podcast in three minutes or less, everything is happening
in Linux and open source.
And this thing is packed full of information.
We've got a dedicated research person on there, plus our editors review the content, plus
often multiple hosts review every single episode before it gets published.
We're doing like our real best on this thing.
Every single episode is a team effort.
It's damn impressive.
And you can grab it at linuxheadlines.show slash subscribe.
While we're recording this here episode, another one's about to get posted.
I love it.
I mean, it just helps me stay up to date.
And that means less time I have to spend on Linux subreddit or Hacker News or any place
searching for news.
We took our news pipeline collection and just grew it and expanded it.
And it's really meant that everyone on the team is staying very up to date now.
And it's easy to listen to, right?
There's some support on a little smart speaker near you.
Yeah, it's true.
You can get it in your daily briefing if you got one of them echo tubes.
And you can just subscribe at linuxheadlines.show slash subscribe, three minutes or less.
And we aim for your afternoon commute if you're a commuter too.
So you can just pop it on before you listen to anything else and get an update.
That's what I do.
Just pop it on.
I pop it on.
That's what I do, Wes.
There's something I'm thinking about doing this Friday.
This could be a really bad idea, especially since it's like the holidays and I already
do enough as it is and you all have enough going on as it is and nobody needs one more
thing.
But I thought if you're around this Friday afternoon, as of when this episode's airing,
maybe we do a little get together, some distros and drinks.
Something I'm thinking about doing.
Are you supplying the drinks?
Nope.
Ah.
BYOD on that one.
Got it.
I'll probably be sipping on a Red Bull myself, but maybe a beer ski.
We'll see if, if enough people take me up on this, I might go get some beer ski.
You will be providing some tips though, right?
Yeah.
So here's the deal.
Uh, I don't know if this is something I want to do all the time, but I thought I'd give
it a try.
And so for this week I thought let's do a little live setting up plasma session.
How I configure my plasma desktop.
Now that I've been back on plasma for a few weeks, I got some things to share.
So tweak your plasma set up along with me from basic to brilliant.
I will back him up.
He tweaked my plasma install and I've been loving it.
You just left it.
It's great.
Um, and I'll have the mumble room going.
I'll have the IRC going, the live stream going.
You can just watch along as I go from zero to hero with my plasma set up and maybe take
a few of those suggestions yourself.
I'll do a screen cap of it.
I'll be on mic and walking you through it.
I also thought this would be a good time to try out some meetup alternatives because meetups
going in a bad direction.
Meetup.com has been a go to resource, but they're charging coming and going these days.
So I'm trying out get together.
Dot community.
I'll have a link in the show notes.
Get together.
Dot community.
Distros and drinks with me on Friday at one PM Pacific to three 30 PM Pacific.
So translate that to your local time and then they just go to jblive.tv there.
Find all the links.
Yep.
We'll have the, we'll have all the streams up if you want to do, I don't, this might
be a dumb idea.
I know nobody uses get together dot community, so I'm probably not going to get people to
register so then I won't know if anybody's going to be there and because it's Friday
before the holidays, nobody's going to show up.
But if you do show up and it becomes a thing, I'll probably start doing like distro reviews
from time to time.
Try out different distros on the live stream cause I got the capture all set up.
So link for the get together page.
I know it means like you got to create another account somewhere.
It's easy though.
I've tried it.
Yeah.
They got single sign on too, so that's not so bad.
And go check out Jupiter extras extras dot show brunch with Brent episode 36 of Jupiter
extras.
Wow.
We've done 36 of these things, but this one's a special one.
He sat down with Rocco, big daddy Linux, great little chat brunch with Brent at extras dot
show and you know, rumor has it if you fiddle around with the categories on that their site,
there's a way you can get a feed just for brunch with Brent or some sort of magical
tags.
Confirm that.
How would I know?
I can't confirm that, but check that out.
Extras dot show.
Jupiter extras is, is up on YouTube and Hey look, after our call out, we got 76 subscribers.
Thanks guys.
Yeah.
If you'd like to be notified of new brunches or any other extra, that's probably the easiest
way.
We're gonna need more though.
Cause I think you need a hundred at least to get a name.
We believe in you community.
So I have a link to that.
We need you to go over to our extras YouTube channel and subscribe for us so we can name
our YouTube channel.
It's really a team effort.
It's so dumb the way YouTube works, but we would appreciate it.
We'll have a link to that.
And last but not least, you know what I'm going to mention West cause I can Jupiter
broadcasting.com slash telegram boom.
Our telegram group is going seven days a week, 24 hours.
Amazing.
I try to stop in there several times a day, minimum.
A lot of us are in there.
So if you want to chat with us, get some in front of us or just talk about a show episode,
the community is always roaring at Jupiter broadcasting.com slash telegram and um, big
shout out because I often will bounce things off of people in there to get their take on
it.
Uh, people will give me followup ideas to shows in there.
So just shout out to that room over a thousand strong and just a bunch of awesome individuals
at Jupiter broadcasting.com slash telegram.
We don't mention it enough for how great it is.
So go check that out.
Anything else for the housekeeping there, mr.
Payne?
I think that does it.
Alrighty then.
So giving the gift of Linux this year, it really is true that for most of the world,
Linux is an implementation detail.
We don't like it.
It drives us crazy.
Hey, that Android device.
Hey, that's got Linux on it.
You know, they don't.
They don't care.
I mean, most they give you that.
Oh yeah.
Nice.
Huh?
Oh yeah.
Isn't that the thing on the cloud?
Yeah.
That's what the cloud's made of.
So I thought this time, let's just embrace it and let's give friends and family little
trinkets and gadgets and gifts.
Right.
The gift to ourselves is we get to play with this stuff and then the gift to them is some
sort of working device that they don't have to know runs on it.
This is a little cheesy, but when you're, ha cheese.
But when you're giving gifts to friends and family that you've known for a while or acquaintances,
you know, work people, whatevs, there is something about getting a custom made gift.
I know that sounds sort of cliche, but it is true.
Like if somebody gave you something they made, I like, I did a thing where I gave out, I've
talked about this.
I gave out wifi access points and picture frames one year, the family loved it.
It really was like it was a little kid I put together.
Everything was all set up.
The access ID, the WPA password, the photo frame was all good to go.
Well that's just it, right?
I mean most of the time the gifts are just something to show that you're thinking and
have care for those people and what's better than spending some time working on a project.
Well this really got kicked off into high gear when Michael wrote into the show.
This is what happens when we start reading the feedback more, Wes.
He wrote in and said, I recall back in episode 230 that Wes was setting up a NAS for his
family.
Well, fast forward and now I've decided that in 2020 it's my goal to do the same thing.
He's wondering also if you have any updates, but wants to know how would you do it today
if you're going to go about it and what would you build?
He also says thanks for the amazing podcast, Michael subscribing from Germany.
So he wants to know if we were going to do the same thing, give the family or a gift
of like a Linux box or something that solves a problem out of the box, what would our approach
be today?
And I think it's pretty different than it was a couple of years ago.
A couple of years ago, I wouldn't have had as nearly as many small board computer type
projects.
No.
They use raspberry pies or, or the pine 64, right?
I ended up deploying a NUC at my folks house kind of for that reason, but in those situations
it's several hundreds of dollars.
And now this year it's like, well, this is 35 bucks to do this.
This one's going to be 60 bucks to do that.
That's gift category right there.
Exactly.
So I am not doing this one, but I almost pulled this one off from my mom this year.
It just didn't quite work out.
I'm really going to recommend people consider giving the gift of network backups and you
can make it really easy.
There is a piece of open source software that has saved my bacon a few times and it's called
backup PC.
It's a brilliant, brilliant backup software that works over SSH and Samba and NFS and
various other networking protocols.
You can support all operating systems.
It's easy to deploy as a Docker image.
It's a little challenging to deploy on your system itself, but you can.
And I think backup PC, even if it's just one or two computers and a USB hard drive plugged
into a PI would be a fantastic gift.
And if they already have a computer on the network that would be capable of this, you
can load backup PC on that for them.
And it's backup PC gives you a nice web UI to backup and restore files.
And one of the things that's really smart about is eliminating duplicate images by looking
at the block hash, I don't actually recall how it does it, but I'm going, I assume it
hashes the files, looks at each, it does a hash for all the files and then it compares
the hashes.
And when there's duplicate hashes, it sets up hard links instead of actually copying
the file a bunch of times.
And so you end up using a surprising little amount of disk space, having backed up.
So network servers and ZFS, we could have it all stored on ZFS.
And then one other is just don't do, I'm not doing, but I think you could do.
And I almost did for my dad this year, Pi-hole.
We talk about it a lot.
Pi-hole is a black hole for internet advertisements.
You throw it on a device, you set it up for the family members, you tweak their DHCP.
And now on every device they own forever, they've got ad blocking.
What I like about that is ad blocking is fairly easy if you know what you're doing, but that's
not always where your family members are, right?
So this is something you can put in place.
They don't have to think about it.
You should probably tell them about it, I suppose, otherwise you won't get credit.
But after that, it just works.
DM, you have a backup solution for people?
It's called Veeam Agent.
They have Veeam Agent for Linux, Veeam Agent for Windows.
It's not open source, but it's really good because you can backup the system and then
you can do bare metal restore.
So you can pretty much restore the whole system or restore a single file.
That's nice.
When you install the app, it lets you create like a recovery media.
And it's really good for, especially for people that, it's kind of like you backup everything
and then you pick whatever you want to restore after.
Which most of the time people even, they don't know what they want until it's too late.
And they don't know how valuable it is and how much they appreciate it until they need
it.
It really is a thing.
It also does deduplication on the backup level, so you also kind of like save a lot of space
on the backups and stuff.
So I've been using it on a large enterprise scale, but it's also free for home users and
stuff like that.
So it's open source, but it's great.
Veeam gets a plus one from me.
I use it all the time in my network.
Also worth an honorable mention in the PyHole category is the newer AdGuard Home, which
can also run on a Pi as well, which does much the same thing, but I find generally I prefer
the interface to AdGuard.
Yeah, I've been meaning to try that.
That does look really good.
That's a good mention.
And I thought maybe there's still a chance I might do one of these.
So I wanted to put them on this list.
Wes and I have two particular projects we are doing for our family this year, which
we'll tell you about.
But I want to take a moment to talk about the obvious elephant in the room.
It is so easy these days to build a tiny little retro arcade machine.
It's so easy that you could even gift it in a tiny retro NES case for 30 bucks.
I have it linked in the show notes.
You get an NES case built to hold the Raspberry Pi.
Look at that handsome thing.
You get a cooling fan.
You get two USB Super Nintendo ripoff controllers that plug into the ports in the front that
are USB.
It's not just mix and match, why that controller doesn't make sense with the case.
But that's fine.
If somebody were to open this and you tell them, yeah, it does HDMI out, you can plug
it into your current TV and play all your old favorite games, they would love this little
thing.
I mean, it is adorable.
Right, great for kids or just old farts who still love video games.
I'm going on a holiday shopping trip with my dad, I do it every year.
And I always try to drop a few hints to see like what he bites on.
And this is definitely on the possibilities list.
Because it's just a presentation of the whole thing where it's in a retro Nintendo case.
And you can load it with something called, I'm going to say, Laka, L-A-K-K-A, Laka.
It's a DIY open source retro gaming console distro that you can flash on a device or you
can load on even on an x86 machine.
And it's got a sort of a PlayStation inspired UI.
So if you like the PS3 UI style and the PS4.
Oh, nice.
A little more PS3, PS2.
But it's nice.
It's a classic side scrolling UI.
Something very easy.
Looks really good.
And of course, cheese, you love RetroArch.
Yeah, RetroArch is fantastic.
And you can extend that, which is basically what Laka uses on the back end.
But you can extend that to all of the consoles that are out there right now.
Apparently, even it supports iOS and Apple TV.
So if you're really into retro gaming, that's probably a great solution for you as well
to look at.
Maybe, although you built me a little Odroid Go Game Boy like thing that is also one of
those like perfect kind of gifts at the holidays.
Tell me a little bit about this because I've got it in my hands right now and it looks
slick.
It's got a transparent case so you can see the board in there and you can see the battery,
which is super cool.
And it's shaped like an old Game Boy.
Yeah, so the Odroid Go is very similar to Adafruit's Pie Girl, which it's kind of a
Game Boy sort of handheld console, retro handheld console.
But what differs from the Pie Girl and Odroid Go, first off, Odroid makes single board computers
as well.
But this uses the ESP32 microcontroller instead of a Raspberry Pi.
So you're going to get a lot more battery, you're going to get a lot more playtime out
of it.
It also has a header on top so you can break out that header.
I think they have, there you go, I think that header will allow you to expand it and do
some other things.
They have some attachments for it, I'm not sure exactly what attachments are available
for it right now.
I think there's a microphone or something like that available for it.
And you can also just, since it's a microcontroller, you can play with it and you can have it do
just about anything you want.
So if you wanted to turn it into a portable weather station or a tricorder of sorts, you
could do that with this little device.
A tricorder?
I don't know.
Pool holder?
It's really, it's super simple, right?
So instead of having to solder it all together, it comes as a kit and you can assemble it,
but it's really easy to assemble, really easy to put together.
So it's something that you could hand your kid and say, hey, you know, put this together,
build something.
And they would have this, you know, sense of accomplishment once they put it together
and fired it up and got their first games going on it, for sure.
Yeah, I love it.
It's one of my favorite little things.
And I love also just showing it to my kids and be like, here, this is what video games
was like when I was your age, you know, I do one of those moves with it, which is extremely
satisfying because I can be like, see if you can beat that kid.
It's a really nice little gift.
And I think anybody new or old gamer would be very, very happy with this thing.
So we have links to this stuff, the Odre Go and the kit in the show notes.
You got to check that out.
But I love some of the ideas that came in from the audience.
Dennis sent me an idea.
He says, when you have a Raspberry Pi around a 3B plus somewhere level or better, if you
have endless options, you have all kinds of things you can do.
He built, we'll have a link to this to check this out in the show notes, a beautiful wood
case around this thing.
Look at that.
I mean, I don't know if he hand built this or if he assembled it from various parts or
what he did, but he put an LCD screen inside a, like a maple stained case.
It's a gorgeous little computer right there.
Just got a little little wireless keyboard and mouse connected.
That's all you need.
And he can put it in photo frame mode if he wants when he's not using it.
So he's also got a little photo frame there.
That's so slick.
It's a great idea.
So you can get a little inspiration by checking out the pictures there.
But it's also worth mentioning, you could set somebody up a Kodi jellyfin setup on
a Raspberry Pi and give it to him and say, here, plug this into your television.
This is set up now to connect to my jellyfin library.
Yeah, I had that set up with MB for a while, but I'm going to try it out with jellyfin,
I think, over this holidays.
And I just like that it makes it easy to share anything I'm watching with my family.
And they don't have to learn any sort of new interface.
They've been using Kodi before.
So once the database backends plugged right in and you can do the same thing with Plex,
they just keep on going and magically new content appears.
Yeah, it's nice to see.
I'd like figures that it would exist, but it's nice to see a jellyfin plugin for Kodi's
or jellyfin app in Kodi so you can keep using the Kodi player and all of that.
But you can get that jellyfin database.
What a great way to share family movies, too, even if it's just for that kind of stuff.
So that's an obvious one.
But Wes, you're going like a whole other level with this one.
For this year, you're building essentially Sonos in a box.
It's not Sonos speakers.
No, it's speakers powered by the Raspberry Pi.
It turns out there's a whole bunch of high-end audio file gear that's made for the Raspberry
Pi, all kinds of different hats and attachments and DACs that you can get so that if you want
to drive speakers of basically any kind, you can use a Pi properly configured to do that.
And there's a whole bunch, almost too many options for Linux of synchronizing audio to
multiple devices.
So if you can marry those two things, I think you're set.
I haven't decided quite on the stack I want.
A new one I saw was Strobe Audio, which if people remember from the Kodi radio days,
I'm a lover of things hipsters like Elm and Elixir, and both of those technologies are
in Strobe.
But there's also an old favorite, Snapcast, which will do the same sort of thing.
Okay.
I really think Strobe Audio is worth a go.
It looks really solid.
And the thing that this does that I think is worth just wrapping your noodle around for
a second is it allows you to get synchronized audio from any speaker.
You got some old computer speakers sitting around or you've got great home entertainment
speakers.
You've got a whole range of options, which means you can fill audio in anywhere in your
home.
Like everybody probably has an old computer speaker somewhere and you want just a little
bit of mid somewhere, just add it to that.
So Strobe Audio, amongst the others, looks like a great option to handle all of that
math over the network, make sure everybody's talking the same lingo at the same time.
Right.
I mean, you know, Sonos and similar products are definitely out there, but not only are
they expensive, they have their own way of operating.
And I don't, I just don't think that that's right for the people in my life and people
that they know and something that can integrate with their existing systems and maybe even
just take input from, say, a CD player, it's going to be a lot more flexible.
I like this a lot because I was gifted an old set of theater speakers by my dad when
he upgraded to like a Sonos sound bar, of course, he's like, here, you want all these
old speakers?
And I'm like, dad, these are great speakers, but he doesn't want to deal with all the hassle
of wiring them all up.
This I could easily use, especially with some of these DACs you link, that's really cool.
So strobe audio on a Raspberry Pi, and then audio out.
So what I was thinking you could do is just a really simple, cheap, just USB sound card.
Yeah, it doesn't have to be, you don't even have to go fancy DAC unless you're really
aiming at high end speakers.
But you're right.
Yeah, especially for things you just want something in the bathroom or a kitchen device
while you're cooking.
I mean, like 70% of what I would use this would be podcasts.
I just want, I want to walk around everywhere and hear the podcast.
So here's another project.
I didn't include it in the doc, I'd like to extend some Wi Fi from from the main house
that my folks have down to their sheds.
Yeah.
Oh, and then if I could get this going to write, you could have same music, both places.
Sonos, but not quite.
I like that.
All right.
So here's what I'm doing.
This is kind of on theme for me in the last year, especially now that Alex is the devil
on my shoulder.
I'm giving the gift of self hosted automation for Christmas.
I'm not sure how I feel about that.
Why?
I thought you'd love the idea.
I've got this picture of a little me, me, me, me, me, me in your shoulder.
Oh, that part.
Yeah, I know.
Tell me about it.
Right.
Hey, Chris, buy this.
No, I thought, you know what?
I've got two Raspberry Pi threes and I'm going to put has IO on those suckers, which we talk
more about in self-hosted.
So check out selfhosted.show and I'm going to buy it with a cost of smart plug because
home assistant has a built in integration to work over the land with the cost of smart
plugs, which are made by TP link and I like a one pack is I think $20 you can get it or
something like that.
You can get a two pack for 35 bucks.
Oh, we should talk.
We should talk.
We should get you a better plug than that.
I know.
But see, this isn't for me.
This is for the family.
So I, you know, I can get them this as a built in integration and I'm going to give them
the gift of an automated smart tree because we just want something that's running Tasmota.
That's what we want.
I know.
If you want to send me a plug to use, you got a couple of weeks.
I can do that.
But others, I'm going to link the TP link in there.
It's all explained in self-hosted, but I think automating the Christmas tree is a great way
to make it click for people and I'm just going to set it up for the smart plug to just have
a sunrise sunset automation.
So it's an hour before sunset, turn the tree on.
All right.
I'm stealing this because there's also great for like outside lights that you don't have
to go out in the cold.
Absolutely.
Yes, if that's a, that'd be, that would be a killer angle.
I hadn't even considered the outside.
And if you combine it, I know I have got some, uh, some family members, a little skeptical
of all these smart devices and just what's happening with their data.
So you can also add in the gift of like, look, this is all offline.
Yes.
Yeah.
Uh, TP link also makes an outdoor smart plug that has been weatherized with like perfect
rubber covers and whatnot.
Um, and I just think that's such a great way to be like, look, this is that for me, it's
like, this is that thing I talk about all the time, you know, and I'm always talking
about this thing and you know, it is useful and here it is.
And when you put them and I have, I have an old flirt case for the raspberry PI three
that I never used and I've got a raspberry PI three in the box still, and I'm just going
to open them both up, put this together.
I think I'll do Raspbian and then I'll do has IO.
Well, I'm either going to do homocystin or has IO, I'm not sure which is has IO is like,
it's a whole distro itself.
So I could go that route.
I'm going to decide what, because I do like the idea of being able to put other things
on there.
Are you wanting to run this as an appliance?
Cause that's what it boils down to.
That's what I got.
That's the, do I want to run this as an appliance or do I also want to do other things for them?
And I think the appliance angle is the way to go.
Pitch it as a complete product.
It does this.
Yep.
And uh, I think that's, I think I'll go has IO.
And that's easier with all these small board computers, right?
Cause if you need another appliance, you don't have to combine them, you just get another
one.
Something we're going to touch on before we wrap up is a super crazy, dead, easy, Nat
busting way to remote support all of these things we're giving out.
I am setting up remote access on everything this year.
I am backdooring every box or I'm sorry, I'm setting up a service login on everything I
give away this year.
And we'll tell you how we're both West and I are doing that, but she's had a really great
idea for a possible another take on the backup solution outside of my kind of half baked
idea.
I've been running open media vault on, uh, orange pie zero now for a little bit.
Um, and it's, it's a great little easy to use backup solution.
Um, so what I did is over black Friday, they had the Samsung Evo, uh, one terabyte SSDs
on sale for a hundred bucks.
Right.
So for my brother and his entire family, immediate family, um, I'm setting up an orange pie zero,
which is about a $10 single board computer paired with a little external, um, SSD case,
uh, with that one terabyte drive set up in there and they have iPads and just some various
little different, you know, laptops and odds and ends, um, that I wanted to be able for
him to use to easily back up the whole household and still have access to, uh, in case they
need it.
So, you know, all in, I'm looking at about 120 bucks, but for me, this is going to cover
a gift for four people.
So, um, I felt it was a really reasonable, uh, amount of money to be spent for, you know,
everyone to get their backup solution on.
So that's, that's what I'm using.
I like that.
I like, see, the reason why I say mine's a half solution and yours is a complete solution
is because you're going with open media vault.
So it's an appliance, there's a web UI, you could even give them the URL and the login
and they could, they could futz with it, whereas mine is like, I think I'd load Debbie in and
then I harass me and then I think I'd do like, mine's a half baked idea, but that's a fully
formed one.
So I think that's really nice and good call on the orange pie zero.
That's a nice little device for this.
It's questionable if I'll give them the URL to log into, but I may just put a service
door in there for myself as well.
It's these white lies that keep families together.
That's right.
Everybody stays happy.
So there is also a solution that's along all of these same lines that makes it really easy
to one click install things like a wiki and mumble and next cloud, but it's not quite
as DIY as everything we've been talking about.
I've never tried the freedom box before, but it looks like a really cool project.
Each freedom box includes a single board computer with an arm cortex, a seven processor running
a gigahertz.
It's got a gig of Ram, two USB, two ports, it's got gigabit, one native SATA drive and
an HDMI port.
And it comes with a 32 gigabyte micro SD card that has the freedom box software pre-installed.
A couple of other neat things though, inside it's a little case, it has a built in battery.
It sits inside the case.
So the freedom box doesn't lose power if you lose electricity.
Nice.
I really like that.
And it's running Debian under the hood.
It's all running on top of Debian.
So it's kind of a, it's a darling project of Debian, worth checking out the freedom
box.
I think it ran for 80 something dollars, 85 something dollars.
And it's, it's got a platform that lets you just choose these massive open source software
stacks as like a one click deployment at like, like VPS is do only it's on this little tiny
freedom box that you put in your own network.
It seems like a great way to introduce people who are interested in playing with the software
but maybe aren't the most technical to get some of those benefits.
All right.
So let's talk about giving the gift of remote support with SSH.
This is something you and I decided to do just for our own convenience and it's working
out really well.
So we thought we'd share it with the audience.
We may have mentioned it maybe even one episode before, but Wes and I love the self healing
reverse SSH tunnels that you set up using systemd.
Oh yeah, it's so easy.
And it's great because systemd is aware of your network state and all of these things
that make it an ideal way to keep a persistent reverse connection.
We'll have a link in the show notes.
In short, you create a systemd unit file.
It just sort of spells out how to do this SSH connection using the right command line
flags and the right user information.
And then you enable it and start it.
And then there is a persistent, always on SSH connection to whatever you tell it to.
In my case, it's a VPS.
You will need some sort of publicly accessible bastion host out there to make this work really
well.
But I mean, come on, a lot of us already have one of these running somewhere.
You could also get by with something forwarded on your own network if you needed to.
If you have a public IP and you want to open the port, you could even have it connect back
to an SSH, I mean, I'm sorry, you could have it connect back to a DNS address.
I've hardcoded IP and no, actually, I did use DNS.
So yeah, even if my IP changes, it's fine.
If you have dynamic DNS, you'd be fine.
And the idea here, really, you're just going to forward the port of your local SSH connection
up onto that easily accessible server.
And then you can use SSH's great support for jump hosts to just immediately jump right
on through the bastion and get to whatever system you need, no matter how many levels
of NAT are involved.
Okay.
All right.
We got to explain this just a little bit more, because this is such a fricking cool thing
that SSH does that it's worth just everybody understanding what a jump host is.
Right.
So you used to be able to do this in all kinds of ways, including super hacky ones involving
Netcat.
But these days with modern SSH, the proxy jump feature is baked right in.
And so you can just tell, you know, you tell SSH, hey, I want to go to this host.
But you can tell it it needs a jump host.
So it'll first establish an connection to the jump host.
And then on that box using its DNS settings, whatever you need, it'll then go make the
request to the host that you actually want to get to.
So you can chain this.
You can go many levels deep if you want to.
But two is usually enough.
My SSH config file is maybe 100 lines long because I just chain multiple boxes together.
So I use proxy jump every day and it's wonderful.
You can also specify nonstandard ports, users, all that kind of stuff in there.
So, you know, the SSH config file is probably one of the most important, you know, second
probably only to my SSH keys on my systems.
Right.
And that way, when, you know, when the person you're supporting gives you a call and says,
hey, this isn't working, you don't have to worry about it.
You can just type SSH, whatever name you've given it and you're in.
And what I've done is I've made little notes to myself.
So this computer is this jump address.
This computer is this jump address.
And when they say, hey, I need help, I'll just open up that text document, highlight,
paste in my terminal and go.
And I'll be on their system.
I really set up the keys and everything.
So I really, really strongly recommend either for yourself, if you need to get access to
your machine, that's like even even my RV machines, which are behind double carrier
grade gnats.
Bob's your uncle, man.
Works just fine.
Richard is indeed my uncle now.
We'll have links to that.
We'll have links to explain the jump post.
I've mentioned links a lot.
So I realize I've been throwing that out there a ton this episode and I haven't said where
you get those.
And I apologize.
It's just an old habit.
Linux Unplugged dot com slash three three zero.
And we'll have all of that stuff there.
So you can you can get there, man.
All of this really started because Michael sent in an email.
So thank you, Michael.
We would like more of that.
If you're doing any of these or have similar projects in the works or know some great open
source software we should be using to facilitate gift ideas, Linux Unplugged dot com slash
contact.
Yeah.
There's a lot of fun stuff out there.
And if you're just even making it a project for yourself, I think it's worth checking
out some of that stuff.
We had something sort of amazing happen in the community that they didn't even know what
happened.
In my Linux Unplugged inbox came an email asking a question and then not even an hour
later another email came into my inbox answering the previous question.
So this is amazing because I was like, OK, we'll answer this.
And then the next email that came in just did it beautifully.
So let's start with Malik from Germany.
Malik.
We by the way, Germany has been representing hard working over there, Germany.
I think we're proud of you.
I think we got like four emails from Germany in this last week.
And so Malik writes and he says, hey, Chris, happy listening and enjoy the Linux podcast
quite a lot after listening to some interesting episodes on self hosted and also your episodes
on VPNs.
I came to the conclusion that you might have some ideas to solve my very specific networking
problem.
You see, I'm a web developer by trade and I like to tinker a bit in my home network
from time to time.
But there's one problem.
I just can't get my head around yet when I'm out and about.
I would like to VPN to all my machines, my Linux notebook, my Apple mobile devices back
in my home from any of my devices.
Why?
Well, I love Pi-Hole, of course.
And well, I'd like to access through Pi-Hole when I'm out on public Internet.
And I'd also like to get access to my file servers and that kind of stuff.
But what's the problem?
You might ask.
I've got no public IP for address since my Internet provider is using something called
DS Lite.
OK, I did quite a bit of research and I can't find a way to connect to my home, but it seems
there may be a way to do it because I have an IP six address available.
I don't know how to use this right.
So here's my question.
Do you know of a specific guide or tutorial that discusses a multi-platform approach to
connecting home with only an IP V6 public address available?
I say, yes, we do.
But then Lucas writes and he says, hey, there, I heard you had problems with carrier grade
now and I felt the urge to write in.
I also sit behind a carrier grade at my German ISP and I took it took me a while to find
a solution that works for me.
See, we're bringing Germans together on this podcast.
At least with my ISP, the carrier grade net is only active for IP for addresses.
So what I did is I rented a super small VPS at I O N O S dot D E and I installed a tool
called six tunnel, which allows you to tunnel IP for traffic through an IP six connection.
And this has worked brilliantly for him.
He's able to get back to his home network.
I don't know if you really consider it a VPN, he says, but it sure has solved my problem.
Wes, educate me a little bit about six tunnel, because I believe there's other solutions
as well.
But six tunnel looks pretty straightforward.
Looks pretty nice.
Yeah, I'd actually never used it before.
It is kept up to date.
You see project over on GitHub if you want to check it out.
It'll be in the show notes and it allows you to use services provided by IP V6 hosts with
IP V4 only applications and vice versa.
So it's really just a little flexible little connector you can put in between things.
If you're on one end and you can't talk quite what you need to stick six tunnel in the middle
and it'll figure things out for you.
Yeah, it can be used as a tunnel for all combinations IP for traffic so you could pretty much run
anything through it.
And it looks like it also has a lot of flexibility.
I have a link to the man page in the notes and I'm reading through it right now.
Okay, this is something I'm going to look into.
I had also you and I at one point had talked about other solutions using IP V6.
So it seems like the audience is sort of clicked into something that you and I were also kind
of orbiting around.
And I want to also mention that I had a follow up email from Ryan, the developer of Nebula.
And he gave me the suggestion of configuring both of my Nebula clients behind that with
ports of zero.
So they randomly select ports when they're trying to break through the net.
Sounds like we've got some more testing to do.
Yep, so I will test that indeed.
And hopefully that answered some questions if you've got some follow up or feedback or
ideas for the show, like Wes mentioned earlier, Linux unpluged.com slash contact.
That's how you get into the show.
We're trying to do just a little bit more of that towards the end of the year just to
hear from everybody.
Get some different stuff on the air because we always read the emails, but we don't always
feature them on air.
But I thought something about this time of year feels like the right time.
Right.
And that's one of the best ways we get to hear directly from you and we love that now.
Check out user error.
Dan wasn't able to make it on because of internet connections, but error.show.
So good.
User error.
One of my favorite podcasts of all time.
Go check it out.
And if there's one of our podcasts to share with your friends and family over this upcoming
holidays, it's user error.
For sure.
It is.
It's the one I listened to with the lady and she loves it.
It makes me laugh every time.
Techsnap.systems for more Wes Payne with Jim Salter talking about things over there and
check out Alex and I on self hosted self hosted dot show.
New episode is coming out this week and it's packed.
It's packed.
And don't forget about my Friday stream.
I don't know if it's a good idea or not and I need you to like go to that get together
thing so I know if I should even bother.
I know I'm very needy.
We listen to you, but I thought this would be a good thing.
Distros and drinks.
What could go wrong?
See you back here next Tuesday.
All right.
Now we need them titles.
JBtitles.com.
We all go vote something.
Something fun.
You know, I enjoyed this episode.
I think it should be a fun one.
The gift of Linux is not I think it's a little too on the nose.
Have you looked to see what's trending?
All right.
Let's go check it out.
JBtitles.com.
Let's investigate, you know.
Just the gift of Germans.
I don't think we don't have enough votes.
So everybody go vote.
It's urgent.
I've been keeping an eye on that Gnome Shell and Mudder development blog.
Yes.
They're working on something really cool that is going to make Mudder even better.
So one of the areas they've tried to focus on is just the general improvements of Mudder
like we touched on with Cassidy, right?
Well now they're working on really, really specific update areas.
So Mudder only has to update small little bits of the screen.
Much quicker, less work, less overhead.
Way better.
Way, way better.
Right.
And that's exactly the kind of change that will stumble I think very far downstream.
So as the way they put it, Mudder has received the ability to update multiple regions independently
without using bounding rectangles.
I love developers.
And they have some screenshots that actually make it a little more obvious.
There's a lot of other highlights on there.
But like I said, like I promised, I'm keeping an eye on this Gnome Shell and Mudder development
blog because it's so inspiring to see what they're working on and have a better appreciation
as to I can feel the desktop getting better, but why is it getting better?
And what are the hard parts of this that otherwise we would have no idea about?
I can't help but respect their work even more when they do this.
And it's a really well done post with, like I said, screenshots, but also tons of links
properly laid out.
There's real thought to the organization of it.
There's an embedded video of the app grid improvements.
I think you really have to call out how much work that is, right?
You've already done all the code change.
That's a lot of work in and of itself.
But then to go write up a blog post, that's also a significant amount of work.
Yeah, it takes a long time and they're nailing it.
They've really stuck to it.
So really impressed with it.
I'll have a link to that as well because it's worth following.
I just put it in my feed reader and I'm just going to see what they're doing.